<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Allied naval bombardments of Japan during World War II</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30319330</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750521786</id>
      <parentid>740803965</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-20T07:37:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whoop whoop pull up</username>
        <id>13157623</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Submarine attacks */ Fixing link.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34713">{{featured article}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2014}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict = Allied naval bombardments of Japan
|partof = the [[Pacific War]], World War II
|image = [[File:USS Indiana bombarding Kamaishi 14 July 1945.jpg|300px|alt=Color photo of a warship at sea. Smoke is rising from the bow of the ship, and land is visible in the background.|USS Indiana bombarding Kamaishi, Japan, 14 July 1945]]
|caption = USS ''Indiana'' bombarding Kamaishi, Japan on 14 July 1945
|date = July–August 1945
|place = Four Japanese cities, and several military facilities and towns
|coordinates =
|map_type =
|latitude =
|longitude =
|map_size =
|map_caption =
|map_label =
|territory =
|result = Allied victory
|status =
|combatant1 = {{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|New Zealand}}
|combatant2 = {{flag|Empire of Japan}}
|commander1 =
|commander2 = 
|strength1 =
|strength2 =
|casualties1 = 32 (POWs killed in the bombardments of Kamaishi)
|casualties2 = Up to 1,739 killed&lt;br /&gt;Up to 1,497 wounded&lt;br /&gt;Damage to industrial facilities&lt;br /&gt;Damage to urban areas
|notes =
}}
{{Campaignbox Japan}}

During the last weeks of World War II, warships of the [[United States Navy]], the British [[Royal Navy]], and the [[Royal New Zealand Navy]] bombarded industrial and military facilities in Japan. Most of these [[bombardments]] involved [[battleship]]s and caused heavy damage to several of the factories targeted, as well as nearby [[civilian]] areas. A major goal of the attacks was to provoke the Japanese military into committing some of its reserve force of aircraft into battle. However, the Japanese did not attempt to attack the Allied bombardment forces, and none of the involved warships suffered any damage.

The major bombardments began on 14 and 15 July 1945, when US Navy warships attacked the cities of [[Kamaishi, Iwate|Kamaishi]] and [[Muroran, Hokkaido|Muroran]]. The next attack was made by a joint American and British force against the city of [[Hitachi, Ibaraki|Hitachi]] during the night of 17/18 July. Groups of [[cruiser]]s and [[destroyer]]s subsequently shelled the Nojima Saki and Shionomisaki areas on 18 July and the night of 24/25 July, respectively. On 29 July, American and British warships attacked [[Hamamatsu]], and on the night of 30/31 several American destroyers shelled [[Shimizu-ku, Shizuoka|Shimizu]]. The final bombardment took place on 9 August, when Kamaishi was attacked again by American, British and New Zealand warships. Two US Navy submarines conducted small-scale attacks during June and July 1945; one of the submarines also landed a small raiding party.

The Allied naval bombardments disrupted industrial production in the cities targeted, and convinced many Japanese civilians that the war was lost. As many as 1,739 Japanese were killed in the attacks, and up to 1,497 were wounded. The only Allied casualties were 32 [[prisoners of war]], who were killed in the bombardments of Kamaishi.

==Background==

By mid-1945, cities and industrial facilities in the Japanese [[Japanese archipelago|home islands]] were [[Air raids on Japan|under sustained attack]] from [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) [[Boeing B-29 Superfortress|B-29 Superfortress]] heavy bombers based in the [[Mariana Islands]]. Attacks by [[Allied submarines in the Pacific War|Allied submarines]] and surface ships had also cut most of the country's trade routes, and US Navy aircraft carrier task groups had raided locations in the home islands on several occasions. Shortages of fuel had confined most of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]]'s surviving ships to port and forced them and the [[Imperial Japanese Army Air Service]] to hold its air units in reserve against the [[Operation Downfall|Allied invasion]] that was expected to be launched late in the year.&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga (2010), pp. 4–6, 53–54&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the war, the Japanese military had assessed that [[coastal artillery]] was no longer suited to the country's circumstances. As a result, only a few strategic ports were protected by artillery capable of engaging enemy warships, and most of these guns were of relatively small [[Caliber (artillery)|calibers]].&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga (2010), pp. 8–13&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Pacific War]], the US Navy's [[fast battleship]]s had mainly been used to escort the groups of [[aircraft carrier]]s that formed the [[United States Pacific Fleet]]'s main striking force. They had also occasionally bombarded Japanese positions near the shore, and had fought some actions with Japanese warships.&lt;ref&gt;Whitley (1998), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Willmott (2002), pp. 193–194&lt;/ref&gt;

Allied naval commanders decided to use battleships to conduct a series of attacks against Japanese coastal cities in mid-1945. It was hoped that the Japanese military would respond to these bombardments by attacking the Allied forces with the aircraft that were being held in reserve to respond to the planned invasion of Japan, thereby exposing these aircraft to destruction by Allied fighter aircraft. However, the Japanese [[Imperial General Headquarters]] had anticipated that the Allies would conduct bombardments and other operations with this goal, and decided to not attack naval forces operating off Japan. Instead, the aircraft would remain in reserve until Allied landing operations in the home islands began.&lt;ref name=&quot;Giangreco_88&quot;&gt;Giangreco (2009), p. 88&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bombardments==

===First attack on Kamaishi===
On 1 July 1945, the [[United States Third Fleet]] sortied from [[Leyte Gulf]] in the Philippines under the command of Admiral [[William Halsey, Jr.|William Halsey]] to attack the Japanese home islands. Halsey's plans included the use of battleships and [[cruiser]]s to bombard military facilities and factories. To prepare for these attacks, US Navy [[submarine]]s sailed into Japan's inshore waters to search for [[naval mine]]s. USAAF B-29 Superfortress and [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator|B-24 Liberator]] aircraft also conducted photo reconnaissance flights over much of Japan in search of airfields and facilities which could be attacked by the Third Fleet.&lt;ref&gt;Hoyt (1982), pp. 37–38&lt;/ref&gt;

The Third Fleet's main component, [[Fast Carrier Task Force|Task Force 38]] (TF&amp;nbsp;38), began striking targets in Japan on 10 July under the command of Vice Admiral [[John S. McCain Sr.|John S. McCain]]. On this day, aircraft flying from the Task Force's aircraft carriers attacked facilities around Tokyo. Task Force 38 sailed north, and on 14 July began raids on [[Hokkaido]] and northern [[Honshu]]. These areas were outside the range of the B-29 Superfortress bombers, and had at that point not been attacked in the war. The American aircraft met little opposition, and sank 11 warships and 20 merchant ships. A further eight warships and 21 merchant ships were damaged, and the carrier aviators claimed to have destroyed 25 Japanese aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (1960), pp. 310–312&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bombardment of Kamaishi, Japan, 14 July 1945 - 80-G-490143.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Black and white photo of four warships sailing together|Ships of Task Unit 34.8.1 approaching Kamaishi on 14 July 1945]]

The first Allied bombardment of a Japanese coastal town was conducted on 14 July in conjunction with the air attacks on Hokkaido and northern Honshu. A bombardment group commanded by Rear Admiral John F. Shafroth designated Task Unit 34.8.1 (TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.1) was detached from TF&amp;nbsp;38 to attack the iron works at [[Kamaishi, Iwate|Kamaishi]] in northern Honshu. At the time the city had a population of 40,000 and the iron works was among the largest in Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morison_312&quot;&gt;Morison (1960), p. 312&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_218&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; However, due to shortages of [[Coke (fuel)|coking coal]] and other raw materials, the iron works was running at less than half its capacity. TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.1 comprised the battleships {{USS|South Dakota|BB-57|6}}, {{USS|Indiana|BB-58|2}} and {{USS|Massachusetts|BB-59|2}} as well as the [[heavy cruiser]]s {{USS|Quincy|CA-71|6}} and {{USS|Chicago|CA-136|2}} and nine [[destroyer]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morison_313&quot;&gt;Morison (1960), p. 313&lt;/ref&gt; Allied [[prisoners of war]] had been assigned to work at the Nippon Steel Company, and were housed in two camps in Kamaishi.&lt;ref&gt;Banham (2009), p. 262&lt;/ref&gt;

The bombardment group opened fire on the ironworks at 12:10{{nbsp}}p.m. from a range of {{convert|29000|yd|m|abbr=on}}. The ships then moved closer to the city, but did not cross the 100-[[fathom]] line as no [[minesweeper (ship)|minesweepers]] were available to clear the area of mines. The bombardment lasted for over two hours, during which time the force made six passes across the mouth of Kamaishi's harbor and fired 802 {{convert|16|in|mm|adj=on}} shells, 728 {{convert|8|in|mm|adj=on}} shells and 825 {{convert|5|in|mm|adj=on}} shells. While most of the shells landed within the grounds of the ironworks, the concussion from their explosions caused kitchen fires to break out across Kamaishi. The resulting smoke prevented US Navy aircraft from being able to support or spot for the warships, which continued to fire accurately on predetermined targets. No Japanese aircraft or coastal guns responded to this bombardment.&lt;ref name=RN_218/&gt;&lt;ref name=Morison_313/&gt; Allied aircraft photographed the ironworks following the attack, but photo interpreters underestimated the extent to which they had been damaged. This was one of the first times that photographic intelligence had been used to determine the extent of damage from a naval bombardment, and the interpreters placed too much weight on the fact that none of the ironworks' buildings had been destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy (1995), pp. 218–219&lt;/ref&gt; The Allies learned after the war that the ironworks had been extensively damaged and forced to cease production for a period. This resulted in a loss of the equivalent of four weeks of [[pig iron]] production and two-and-a-half months of coke production.&lt;ref name=Morison_313/&gt; Five Allied prisoners of war were killed by the bombardment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Banham_207&quot;&gt;Banham (2009), p. 207&lt;/ref&gt;

===Muroran===
[[File:Allied naval operations off Japan during July and August 1945 (edit 1).svg|thumb|300px|alt=Color map of the Japanese home islands marked with the locations and dates of the air raids and bombardments described in this article.|Major Allied naval air attacks and bombardments of targets in Japan in July–August 1945]]
On the night of 14/15 July, another bombardment unit—TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.2—was detached from TF&amp;nbsp;38 to attack the town of [[Muroran, Hokkaidō|Muroran]] on the south-east coast of Hokkaido. TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.2 was commanded by Rear Admiral [[Oscar C. Badger II|Oscar C. Badger]] and comprised the battleships {{USS|Iowa|BB-61|2}}, {{USS|Missouri|BB-63|2}} and {{USS|Wisconsin|BB-64|2}}, the [[light cruiser]]s {{USS|Atlanta|CL-104|2}} and {{USS|Dayton|CL-105|2}}, and eight destroyers.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (1960), pp. 313–314&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=RN_219/&gt; Admiral Halsey accompanied this force on board ''Missouri''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter_343&quot;&gt;Potter (1985), p. 343&lt;/ref&gt; The targets of this attack were the [[Japan Steel Works|Japan Steel Company]]'s facilities and the Wanishi Iron Works.&lt;ref name=RN_219/&gt; Also that night, a force of four cruisers and six destroyers cruised along the east coast of Honshu seeking to attack Japanese shipping but did not locate any targets.&lt;ref&gt;Hoyt (1982), pp. 43–44&lt;/ref&gt;

TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.2's bombardment began at dawn on 15 July. The three battleships fired 860 {{convert|16|in|mm|adj=on}} shells at the city from a range of {{convert|28000|-|32000|yd|m|abbr=on}}. Aerial observation and spotting of damage was made difficult by hazy conditions, and only 170 shells landed within the grounds of the two plants. Nevertheless, considerable damage was inflicted on the industrial facilities, resulting in the loss of two-and-a-half months of coke production and slightly less pig iron production. Damage to buildings across the city was also extensive. As with the bombardment of Kamaishi, photo interpreters underestimated the scale of the damage.&lt;ref name=RN_219/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Morison_314&quot;&gt;Morison (1960), p. 314&lt;/ref&gt; TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.2 was highly vulnerable to air attack throughout the more-than-six-hour period in which it was visible from the shore of Hokkaido, and Halsey later wrote that these were the longest hours of his life. The failure of the Japanese to attack his ships convinced Halsey that they were preserving aircraft for use against the Allied invasion force.&lt;ref name= Potter_343/&gt; On 15 July, aircraft flying from TF&amp;nbsp;38's aircraft carriers struck again at Hokkaido and northern Honshu, devastating the fleet of ships that carried coal between the two islands.&lt;ref name=Morison_312/&gt;

===Hitachi===
The attacks on Hokkaido and northern Honshu ended on 15 July, and TF&amp;nbsp;38 sailed away from the Japanese coast to refuel and rendezvous with the main body of the [[British Pacific Fleet]], which was designated Task Force 37 (TF&amp;nbsp;37).&lt;ref name=Morison_314/&gt; On the morning of 17 July, the British and American carriers attacked targets to the north of Tokyo. Later that day, TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.2 detached from the carrier force to bombard targets around the city of [[Hitachi, Ibaraki|Hitachi]], which is located about {{convert|80|mi|km|abbr=on}} northeast of Tokyo. This force was commanded by Rear Admiral Badger and comprised the battleships ''Iowa'', ''Missouri'', ''Wisconsin'', {{USS|North Carolina|BB-55|2}}, {{USS|Alabama|BB-60|2}}, and {{HMS|King George V|41|6}}, light cruisers ''Atlanta'' and ''Dayton'', and eight American and two British destroyers. ''King George V'' and her two escorts sailed astern of the American force, and operated independently.&lt;ref name=Morison_314/&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;RN_220&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 220&lt;/ref&gt; Halsey again accompanied this force on board ''Missouri''.&lt;ref&gt;Hoyt (1982), p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;

The bombardment of the Hitachi area took place on the night of 17/18 July. Rain and fog made locating the targets difficult and prevented spotting aircraft from flying, but several carrier aircraft flew protective patrols over the bombardment force.&lt;ref name=RN_220/&gt; The Allied warships opened fire at 11:10{{nbsp}}p.m., and aimed at their targets using radar and [[LORAN]].&lt;ref name= &quot;RN_220-221&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), pp. 220–221&lt;/ref&gt; The attackers targeted nine industrial facilities, and ''King George V'' was assigned similar targets to those engaged by the American battleships. By the time the bombardment ceased at about 1:10{{nbsp}}a.m., the American battleships had fired 1,238 {{convert|16|in|mm|adj=on}} shells, and the British battleship 267 {{convert|14|in|mm|adj=on}} shells. The two light cruisers also fired 292 {{convert|6|in|mm|adj=on}} shells at radar and electronics installations south of Hitachi. All firing was conducted at a range of {{convert|23000|-|35000|yd|m|abbr=on}} from the targets.&lt;ref name=RN_220-221/&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Morison_316&quot;&gt;Morison (1960), p. 316&lt;/ref&gt;

The attack on Hitachi had mixed results. Only three of the bombardment's nine targets were hit, and the overall damage to the city's industrial area was assessed as &quot;slight&quot;. However, the attack inflicted considerable damage on the city's urban area and essential services. This damage was greatly increased by a B-29 raid on Hitachi on the night of 18/19 July that destroyed or damaged 79 percent of the city's urban area.&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_221&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 221&lt;/ref&gt; The [[official history]] of the US Navy in World War II states that &quot;individual Japanese&quot; considered the naval bombardment to have been more terrifying than the air attack.&lt;ref name=Morison_316/&gt;

===Nojima Saki and Shionomisaki===
On 18 July, TFs&amp;nbsp;37 and 38 conducted further air strikes in the Tokyo area, with the American force's main effort being [[Attack on Yokosuka|an attempt to sink]] the Japanese battleship {{Ship|Japanese battleship|Nagato||2}} at [[Yokosuka Naval District|Yokosuka Naval Base]].&lt;ref name=RN_221/&gt; That night, Cruiser Division 17 (CruDiv&amp;nbsp;17), which comprised the light cruisers {{USS|Astoria|CL-90|6}}, {{USS|Pasadena|CL-65|2}}, {{USS|Springfield|CL-66|2}} and {{USS|Wilkes-Barre|CL-103|2}} and six destroyers under the command of Rear Admiral J. Cary Jones, fired 240 {{convert|6|in|mm|adj=on}} shells at a radar station on [[Cape Nojima]] over a five-minute period but did not score any hits.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (1960), pp. 313, 316&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_222&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 222&lt;/ref&gt;

After completing its strikes on the Tokyo region, the Allied fleet conducted an at-sea replenishment from 21 to 23 July before attacking [[Bombing of Kure (July 1945)|Kure and the Inland Sea]] from the 24th to the 28th of the month.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy (1995), pp. 222–223&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of 24/25 July, CruDiv&amp;nbsp;17 patrolled the [[Kii Channel]] and bombarded the naval [[seaplane]] base at [[Kushimoto, Wakayama|Kushimoto]], a landing field near [[Cape Shionomisaki]], and a radio station. This attack lasted for only four minutes and caused little damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morison_331&quot;&gt;Morison (1960), p. 331&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy (1995), pp. 221–222&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hamamatsu===
On 29 July, a group of warships was detached from the main body of the Allied fleet to bombard the city of [[Hamamatsu]], which lies on the south coast of Honshu between [[Nagoya]] and Tokyo. This force comprised the same ships which had attacked Kamaishi on 14 July with the addition of ''King George V'' and the destroyers {{HMS|Ulysses|R69|6}}, {{HMS|Undine|R42|2}} and {{HMS|Urania|R05|2}}; the four British ships were designated Task Unit 37.1.2 (TU&amp;nbsp;37.1.2). The city had previously suffered extensive damage from air attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_224&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 224&lt;/ref&gt;

The British and American ships engaged their targets independently. ''King George V'' opened fire at the Japan Musical Instrument Company's Plant No. 2 (which was being used to manufacture aircraft propellers) at 11:19 p.m. from a range of {{convert|20075|yd|m|abbr=on}}. The battleship fired 265 {{convert|14|in|mm|adj=on}} rounds at the plant in 27 minutes and was able to make use of artillery spotting aircraft, with visibility being good. Even so, little damage was inflicted on the facility. ''Massachusetts'' fired at Plant No. 1 but scored only a small number of hits. Despite the limited physical damage, the shelling caused increased labor absenteeism and disruption to vital services that caused the factory to cease production. The American ships also shelled the [[Japanese Government Railways|Imperial Government Railway]] locomotive works and three other industrial facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_1995_224-225&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), pp. 224–225&lt;/ref&gt;

Of these targets, the locomotive works ceased operations for about three months due to damage, but two of the other facilities had almost ceased production before the attack and the third was not damaged. Two bridges on the important [[Tōkaidō Main Line]] were fired upon but not hit, though damage to rail infrastructure in Hamamatsu closed the line for 66 hours. During the bombardment ''Undine'' twice opened fire on small groups of ships that were probably fishing boats. No Japanese aircraft or shore batteries responded to the Allied attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_1995_224-225&quot; /&gt; The bombardment of Hamamatsu was the last time a British battleship [[wikt:fire in anger|fired its guns in anger]].&lt;ref&gt;Willmott (2002), pp. 194–195&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shimizu===
The next bombardment of Japan took place on the night of 30/31 July. On that night Destroyer Squadron 25 (DesRon&amp;nbsp;25), which was commanded by Captain J.W. Ludewig aboard {{USS|John Rodgers|DD-574|6}}, searched the Suruga Gulf for Japanese shipping to attack. No ships were located, and in the early hours of 31 July the squadron sailed deep into the gulf and fired 1,100 rounds of {{convert|5|in|mm|adj=on}} shells during seven minutes at a railway yard and aluminum plant in the town of [[Shimizu-ku, Shizuoka|Shimizu]]. While the aluminum plant was hit, this was of little importance as it had almost ceased production due to a shortage of raw materials. No damage was caused to the rail yard.&lt;ref name=RN_222/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Morison_322&quot;&gt;Morison (1960), p. 322&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second attack on Kamaishi===
[[File:USS Massachusetts (BB-59) opens fire on Kaimaishi on 9 August 1945.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photo with part of a ship in the foreground and flames and smoke risking from the left of a warship in the background. Several other ships are visible on the horizon at the rear of the photo.|USS ''Massachusetts'' firing at Kamaishi on 9 August 1945]]

During the last days of July and into early August, the Allied fleet sailed away from the Japanese coast to avoid a [[typhoon]] and allow the ships to replenish their stocks of fuel and ammunition. The fleet then sailed north and, on both 9 and 10 August, the carrier aircraft attacked a large concentration of Japanese aircraft on airfields in northern Honshu. The carrier pilots claimed the destruction of 720 Japanese aircraft in this operation.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (1960), pp. 331–332&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_226&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 226&lt;/ref&gt;

As part of these operations off northern Japan, Kamaishi was bombarded again on 9 August in the mistaken belief that the iron works had not been badly damaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_219&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; TU&amp;nbsp;34.8.1 conducted this attack, and comprised the ships that had bombarded the city in July with the addition of the heavy cruisers {{USS|Boston|CA-69|6}} and {{USS|Saint Paul|CA-73|2}}, British light cruiser {{HMS|Newfoundland|59|6}}, [[Royal New Zealand Navy]] light cruiser [[HMS Gambia (48)|HMNZS ''Gambia'']] and destroyers {{HMS|Terpsichore|R33|6}}, {{HMS|Termagant|R89|2}} and {{HMS|Tenacious|R45|2}}.&lt;ref name=Morison_313/&gt;&lt;ref name=RN_226/&gt; ''King George V'' did not participate in this action as mechanical problems affecting two of her propeller shafts meant that she was unable to sail at the speed specified for the bombardment force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hobbs_285&quot;&gt;Hobbs (2011), p. 285&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allied ships opened fire on the iron works and docks in Kamaishi at 12:54{{nbsp}}p.m. The bombardment was conducted from an average range of {{convert|14000|yd|m|abbr=on}} and lasted for almost two hours. During this time, the ships made four passes across Kamaishi harbor and fired 803 {{convert|16|in|mm|adj=on}} shells, 1,383 {{convert|8|in|mm|adj=on}} shells and 733 {{convert|6|in|mm|adj=on}} shells. ''Gambia'' fired the final shots of the attack. During the bombardment, several Japanese aircraft approached the Allied ships and two were shot down by Allied naval fighters. This bombardment caused more damage than the attack conducted in July, and large quantities of pig iron were destroyed.&lt;ref name=Morison_313/&gt;&lt;ref name=RN_226/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wright (2003), p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; The sounds of this bombardment were broadcast live on radio in the United States via a radio relay on board ''Iowa''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter_346&quot;&gt;Potter (1985), p. 346&lt;/ref&gt; One of the prisoner of war camps in Kamaishi was destroyed by the Allied attack, resulting in the deaths of 27 Allied prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;Banham (2009), pp. 209, 262.&lt;/ref&gt;

A further bombardment by ''King George V'', three light cruisers and escorting destroyers was planned to be conducted against an unspecified Japanese target on 13 August. This attack was cancelled due both to the battleship's mechanical problems and the [[atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1994), p. 184&lt;/ref&gt; The Allied fleet did not conduct any other bombardments as Japan surrendered on 15 August.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy (1995), pp. 227–228&lt;/ref&gt;

===Submarine attacks===
[[File:USS Barb crew 1945 i03570.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photo of eight men in military uniforms holding a large banner with the word &quot;BARB&quot; in the center surrounded by Japanese and Nazi flags, symbols designating military medals and symbols signifying bombardments|The members of USS ''Barb''{{'}}s crew who were landed in Japan on 23 July 1945 posing with the submarine's battle flag. It includes symbols marking the destruction of a train in this operation, as well as the submarine's shore bombardments.]]
Two US Navy submarines attacked locations in the Japanese home islands during June and July 1945. On 20 June {{USS|Barb|SS-220|6}} arrived off Japan's northern islands under the command of Commander [[Eugene B. Fluckey|Gene Fluckey]]. For this patrol the submarine had been fitted with an experimental {{convert|5|in|mm|adj=on}} rocket launcher intended for shore bombardments. Shortly after midnight on 22 June the submarine fired 12 rockets at the town of [[Shari, Hokkaido|Shari]] in north-east Hokkaido.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blair_866&quot;&gt;Blair (2001), p. 866&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DANFS_Barb&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Barb I|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/b/barb-i.html|website=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships|publisher=Naval History and Heritage Command|accessdate=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Barb'' then proceeded north, and on 2 July bombarded the town of Kaiyo in south-east [[Sakhalin]] with its [[deck gun]]. This attack destroyed three [[sampan]]s docked in the town, damaged a seal rookery and caused several fires to break out. The next day the submarine fired more rockets at the town of [[Poronaysk|Shisuka]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Blair_866&quot; /&gt; A party of eight men from ''Barb'' was landed on the east coast of Sakhalin on 23 July and planted demolition charges on a railroad track. Shortly after the men began rowing back to the submarine the charges were triggered by a passing train; 150 people, including civilians, were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Goldstein|first1=Richard|authorlink=Richard Goldstein (writer born 1942)|title=Eugene B. Fluckey, Daring Submarine Skipper, Dies at 93|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/01/obituaries/01cnd-fluckey.html|accessdate=7 February 2016|work=The New York Times|date=1 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), pp. 866–867&lt;/ref&gt; On 24 July, ''Barb'' fired 32 rockets at the town of Shiritori and 12 rockets at Kashiho. As the submarine returned to base it shelled the towns of Chiri on 25 July and Shibertoro the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;DANFS_Barb&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Blair_867&quot;&gt;Blair (2001), p. 867&lt;/ref&gt; The attack on Shibertoro targeted a shipyard building sampans, and destroyed 35 newly built vessels.&lt;ref&gt;Sturma (2011), p. 118&lt;/ref&gt;

The other submarine bombardment took place during the morning of 24 June, when {{USS|Trutta|SS-421|6}} fired some shells at the island of [[Hirado, Nagasaki|Hirado Shima]] in the [[Tsushima Strait]] between Japan and Korea. This attack sought to convince the Japanese that a force of American submarines that had been operating in the [[Sea of Japan]] would attempt to depart via the Tsushima Strait, instead of their actual route far to the north through the [[La Pérouse Strait]] between Honshu and Sakhalin.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), p. 864&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Trutta|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/t/trutta.html|website=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships|publisher=Naval History and Heritage Command|accessdate=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Results==
[[File:Allied battleships in Sagami Bay 28 Aug 1945.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photo depicting 13 World War II-era warships anchored close together near the coast of a body of water. Steep mountains are visible in the background.|Battleships USS ''Missouri'', HMS ''Duke of York'', HMS ''King George V'', and USS ''Colorado'' and other Allied warships in [[Sagami Bay]] on 28 August 1945]]
Although the naval bombardments did not result in the reaction the Allies were hoping for from the Japanese military, they disrupted the country's steel industry. While several of the factories attacked were operating at reduced capacity, the important Kamaishi and Wanishi Iron Works suffered heavy damage when they were bombarded in July and August. During both these attacks, the Allied gunnery was accurate and focused on the factories' coke batteries, which were critical to continued production.&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_231&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; Post-war assessments found that the damage caused to industrial buildings by even {{convert|16|in|mm|adj=on}} naval shells was less than that which could be inflicted by the {{convert|2000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} and {{convert|1000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} [[general-purpose bomb]]s that were used by Allied naval aircraft. While this supported a view put forward by Vice Admiral McCain that the aircraft assigned to protect the bombardment forces could have caused more damage than the ships themselves, the post-war [[United States Strategic Bombing Survey]] judged that the naval bombardments were justified as there had been little risk to the ships involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;RN_229&quot;&gt;Royal Navy (1995), p. 229&lt;/ref&gt;

The bombardments also affected Japanese morale. Japanese civilians who experienced both air and naval bombardment found the naval attacks to be more terrifying due to their unpredictability and longer duration. Several of the industrial facilities that suffered little damage in bombardments incurred a significant loss in production due to absenteeism and reduced productivity. This was not the case for all facilities that were attacked though, and the morale among workers in two of the bombarded factories was reported to have increased.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy (1995), pp. 229–330&lt;/ref&gt; The appearance of Allied warships just off the coast also convinced many Japanese that the war had been lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank_158&quot;&gt;Frank (1999), p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; However, such attitudes did not contribute to bringing the war to an end as the views of civilians had little influence on the Japanese Government's [[Surrender of Japan|decision to surrender]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Morison_333&quot;&gt;Morison (1960), p. 333&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1949, the Japanese Economic Stabilization Agency calculated that the Allied naval bombardments and other forms of attack other than bombing had caused 3,282 casualties, representing 0.5 percent of all casualties inflicted by the Allies in the Japanese home islands. The casualties attributed to naval bombardments and other causes included 1,739 fatalities, 46 persons who were still classified as missing and 1,497 people who were wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Economic Stabilization Agency (1949), pp. 1–2&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist|25em}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite book|last=Banham|first=Tony|authorlink=Tony Banham|title=We Shall Suffer There: Hong Kong's Defenders Imprisoned, 1942–45|year=2009|publisher=Hong Kong University Press|location=Hong Kong|isbn=9622099602}}
* {{cite book|last=Blair|first=Clay|authorlink=Clay Blair|title=Silent Victory: The U.S. Submarine War Against Japan| publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|year=2001|isbn=155750217X}}
* {{cite web |authors=Economic Stabilization Agency, Planning Department, Office of the Secretary General|title=Overall Report of Damage Sustained by the Nation During the Pacific War|url= http://www.japanairraids.org/?page_id=1664|publisher=Japan Air Raids.org|accessdate=22 February 2011|year=1949}}
* {{cite book|last=Frank|first=Richard B.|authorlink=Richard B. Frank|title=Downfall: The End of the Imperial Japanese Empire| publisher=Penguin Books|location=New York|year=1999|isbn=9780141001463}}
* {{cite book|last=Giangreco|first=D.M.|title=Hell to Pay: Operation Downfall and the Invasion of Japan, 1945–47|year=2009|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=9781591143161}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hobbs|first1=David|title=The British Pacific Fleet: The Royal Navy's Most Powerful Strike Force|date=2011|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=9781591140443}}
* {{cite book|last=Hoyt|first=Edwin P.|authorlink=Edwin Palmer Hoyt|title=Closing the Circle: War in the Pacific: 1945|year=1982| publisher=Van Nostrand Reinhold Company|location=New York|isbn=0442247516}}
* {{cite book|last=Morison|first=Samuel Eliot|authorlink=Samuel Eliot Morison|title=Victory in the Pacific|year=1960|publisher= University of Illinois Press|isbn=0252070658|location=Champaign, Illinois|series=History of United States Naval Operations in World War II. Volume Fourteen}}
* {{cite book|last=Potter|first=E.B.|authorlink=E. B. Potter|title=Bull Halsey|year=1985|publisher=Naval Institute Press| isbn=0870211463|location=Annapolis, Maryland}}
* {{cite book|last=Royal Navy|title=War with Japan: Volume VI Advance to Japan|publisher=HMSO| location=London|year=1995|isbn=0117728217}}
* {{cite book|last=Smith|first=Peter C.|authorlink=Peter C. Smith|title=Task Force 57|year=1994|publisher=Crécy Books|isbn= 0947554459|location=Manchester}}
* {{cite book|last1=Sturma|first1=Michael|title=Surface and Destroy : The Submarine Gun War in the Pacific|date=2011|publisher=University Press of Kentucky|location=Lexington, Kentucky|isbn=0813129990}}
* {{cite book|last=Whitley|first=M.J.|authorlink=Michael J. Whitley|title=Battleships of World War Two: An International Encyclopedia|year=1998|publisher=Arms and Armour|location=London|isbn=185409386X}}
* {{cite book|last=Willmott|first=H.P.|title=Battleship|year=2002|publisher=Cassell Military|location=London|isbn=030435810X}}
* {{cite book|last=Wright|first=Matthew|title=Pacific War: New Zealand and Japan 1941–45|year=2003|publisher=Reed|location=Auckland|isbn=0790009080}}
* {{cite book|last=Zaloga|first=Steven J.|authorlink=Steven Zaloga|title=Defense of Japan 1945|year=2010|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=1846036879|location=Oxford|series=Fortress}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last=Halsey|first=William F.|author2=Bryan, Joseph|title=Admiral Halsey's Story|publisher=Whittlesey House|location=London|year=1947|oclc=747307493}}
* {{cite book|last=United States Strategic Bombing Survey Naval Analysis Division|title=Report of Ships Bombardment Survey Party–Foreword, Introduction, Conclusions, and General Summary|year=1946|url=http://www.japanairraids.org/?page_id=3975|publisher=Japan Air Raids.org}}

{{subject bar
| portal1=Japan
| portal2=Royal Navy
| portal3=United States Navy
| portal4=World War II
| commons=y
| commons-search=Category:Allied naval bombardments of Japan during World War II
}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:1945 in Japan]]
[[Category:Japanese home islands campaign|naval bombardments]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving New Zealand]]</text>
      <sha1>13u1ddacl12uf2ho12up0xolippu2gd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
