<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anglo-Zanzibar War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1738794</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744651721</id>
      <parentid>736463961</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-16T16:25:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.145.235.206</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37704">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict    = Anglo-Zanzibar War
|partof      = the [[Scramble for Africa]]
|image       = [[File:AngloZanzibarWar.jpg|300px]]
|caption     = ''The Sultan's [[harem]] after the bombardment''
|date        = 09:02–09:40 [[East Africa Time|EAT]] (06:02–06:40 [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]]), 27 August 1896&lt;br&gt;(38 minutes)
|place       = [[Zanzibar Town]], [[Zanzibar Sultanate]]
|casus       =
|territory   =
|result      = British victory
|combatant1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]
|combatant2  = {{flagicon image|Flag of the Sultanate of Zanzibar.svg}} [[Zanzibar Sultanate|Zanzibar]]
|commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Harry Rawson]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Sultanate of Zanzibar.svg}} [[Lloyd Mathews]]
|commander2  = {{flagicon image|Flag of the Sultanate of Zanzibar.svg}} [[Khalid bin Barghash of Zanzibar|Khalid bin Bargash]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Sultanate of Zanzibar.svg}} Captain Saleh
|strength1   = '''Land:'''&lt;br /&gt;1,050&lt;br /&gt;'''Sea:'''&lt;br /&gt;3 [[cruiser]]s&lt;br /&gt;2 [[gunboat]]s
|strength2='''Land:'''&lt;br /&gt;2,800&lt;br /&gt;4 [[artillery|artillery pieces]]&lt;br&gt;1 [[shore battery]]&lt;br&gt;'''Sea:'''&lt;br /&gt;[[HHS Glasgow|HHS ''Glasgow'']], the [[royal yacht]]&lt;br /&gt;2 [[launch (boat)|boats]]
|casualties1=1 wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt;
|casualties2=500 killed or wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett179&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Bennett|1978|p=179}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[HHS Glasgow|HHS ''Glasgow'']] sunk&lt;br /&gt;2 boats sunk&lt;br&gt;1 shore battery destroyed
}}
{{Scramble for Africa}}

The '''Anglo-Zanzibar War''' was a military conflict fought between the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]] and the [[Zanzibar Sultanate]] on 27 August 1896. The conflict lasted between 38 and 45 minutes, marking it as the shortest recorded war in history.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title= Guinness World Records 2008 |year=2007 |publisher= [[Guinness World Records]] |location= London |isbn= 978-1-904994-19-0 |page=118|author= Editor-in-chief, Craig Glenday}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The immediate cause of the war was the death of the pro-British [[Sultan]] [[Hamad bin Thuwaini of Zanzibar|Hamad bin Thuwaini]] on 25 August 1896 and the subsequent succession of [[Khalid bin Barghash of Zanzibar|Sultan Khalid bin Barghash]]. The British authorities preferred [[Hamud bin Muhammed of Zanzibar|Hamud bin Muhammed]], who was more favourable to British interests, as sultan. In accordance with a treaty signed in 1886, a condition for [[Enthronement|accession]] to the sultanate was that the candidate obtain the permission of the British [[consul (representative)|consul]], and Khalid had not fulfilled this requirement. The British considered this a ''[[casus belli]]'' and sent an [[ultimatum]] to Khalid demanding that he order his forces to stand down and leave the palace. In response, Khalid called up his palace guard and barricaded himself inside the palace.

The ultimatum expired at 09:00 [[East Africa Time]] (EAT) on 27 August, by which time the British had gathered three [[cruisers]], two [[gunboat]]s, 150 [[Royal Marines|marines]] and sailors, and 900 Zanzibaris in the harbour area. The Royal Navy contingent were under the command of [[Rear-Admiral]] [[Harry Rawson]] while their Zanzibaris were commanded by [[Brigadier-General]] [[Lloyd Mathews]] of the Zanzibar army (who was also the [[First Minister]] of Zanzibar). Around 2,800 Zanzibaris defended the palace; most were recruited from the civilian population, but they also included the sultan's palace guard and several hundred of his servants and slaves. The defenders had several artillery pieces and [[machine gun]]s, which were set in front of the palace sighted at the British ships. A bombardment opened at 09:02 set the palace on fire and disabled the defending artillery. A small naval action took place, with the British sinking the Zanzibari [[royal yacht]] [[HHS Glasgow|HHS ''Glasgow'']] and two smaller vessels, and some shots were fired ineffectually at the pro-British Zanzibari troops as they approached the palace. The flag at the palace was shot down and fire ceased at 09:40.

The sultan's forces sustained roughly 500 casualties, while only one British sailor was injured. Sultan Khalid received asylum in the German consulate before escaping to [[German East Africa]] (in the mainland part of present [[Tanzania]]). The British quickly placed Sultan Hamud in power at the head of a [[puppet government]]. The war marked the end of the [[Sultanate of Zanzibar|Zanzibar Sultanate]] as a [[sovereign state]] and the start of a period of heavy British influence.

== Background ==
[[File:Anglo-Zanzibar war map.png|thumb|250px|The islands of Zanzibar and the [[Africa|African mainland]]]]

Zanzibar was an island country in the [[Indian Ocean]], off the coast of Tanganyika; today it forms part of [[Tanzania]]. The main island, [[Unguja]] (or Zanzibar Island), had been under the nominal control of the [[Sultan of Oman|Sultans of Oman]] since 1698 when they expelled the [[Portugal|Portuguese]] settlers who had claimed it in 1499.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon397&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=397}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Sultan [[Majid bin Said of Zanzibar|Majid bin Said]] declared the island independent of Oman in 1858, which was recognised by Great Britain, and split the sultanate from that of Oman.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon397&quot;/&gt; The subsequent sultans established their capital and seat of government at [[Zanzibar Town]] where a palace complex was built on the sea front. By 1896, this consisted of the palace itself; the Beit al-Hukm, an attached [[harem]]; and the [[Beit al-Ajaib]] or &quot;House of Wonders&quot;—a ceremonial palace said to be the first building in East Africa to be provided with electricity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hoyle|2002|pp=156–157}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The complex was mostly constructed of local timber and was not designed as a defensive structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon402&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=402}}.&lt;/ref&gt; All three main buildings were adjacent to one another in a line, and linked by wooden covered bridges above street height.&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle160&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hoyle|2002|p=160}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Britain had recognised Zanzibar's [[sovereignty]] and its sultanate in 1886, after a long period of friendly interaction, and generally maintained good relations with the country and its sultans.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon397&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon397&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bennett|1978|pp=131–132}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2000|pp=146–147}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Germany]] was also interested in East Africa, and the two powers vied for control of trade rights and territory in the area throughout the late 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bennett|1978|pp=124–131}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Sultan [[Khalifah bin Said of Zanzibar|Khalifah]] had granted rights to the land of [[Kenya]] to Britain and that of Tanganyika to Germany, a process resulting in the prohibition of slavery in those lands.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon397&quot;/&gt; Many of the [[Arab]] ruling classes were upset by this interruption of a valuable trade, which [[Abushiri Revolt|resulted in some unrest]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon397&quot;/&gt; In addition, the German authorities in Tanganyika refused to fly the [[flag of the Zanzibar Sultanate]], which led to armed clashes between German troops and the local population.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon398&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=398}}.&lt;/ref&gt; One such conflict in [[Tanga, Tanzania|Tanga]] claimed the lives of 20 Arabs.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon398&quot;/&gt;

Sultan Khalifah sent Zanzibari troops led by Brigadier-General [[Lloyd Mathews]], a former [[Lieutenant]] of the [[Royal Navy]], to restore order in Tanganyika.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernon147&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2000|p=147}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The operation was largely successful, but anti-German feeling among the Zanzibari people remained strong.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon398&quot;/&gt; Further conflicts erupted at [[Bagamoyo]], where 150 natives were killed by German military forces, and at [[Ketwa]], where German officials and their servants were murdered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernon147&quot;/&gt; Khalifah then granted extensive trade rights to the [[Imperial British East Africa Company]] (IBEAC) who, with German assistance, ran a naval blockade to halt the continuing domestic slave trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernon147&quot;/&gt; Upon Khalifah's death in 1890 [[Ali bin Said of Zanzibar|Ali bin Said]] ascended to the sultanate.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bennett|1978|p=165}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Sultan Ali banned the domestic slave trade (but not slave ownership), declared Zanzibar a British protectorate and appointed Lloyd Mathews as [[First Minister]] to lead his [[Cabinet (government)|cabinet]]. The British were also guaranteed a veto over the future appointment of sultans.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon399&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=399}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The year of Ali's ascension also saw the signing of the [[Heligoland-Zanzibar Treaty]] between Britain and Germany. This treaty officially [[demarcation line|demarcated]] the [[sphere of interest|spheres of interest]] in East Africa and ceded Germany's rights in Zanzibar to the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | publisher=German History in Documents and Images| title = Text of the Heligoland-Zanzibar Treaty |date= 1 July 1890 |url= http://germanhistorydocs.ghi-dc.org/pdf/eng/606_Anglo-German%20Treaty_110.pdf |format=PDF|accessdate= 2008-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; This granted the [[British government]] more influence in Zanzibar, which they intended to use to eradicate slavery there, an objective they had held as early as 1804.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite hansard | url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1890/aug/01/the-anglo-german-agreement | house= [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]]| date=1 August 1890 | column_start=1530 | column_end=1533 | title = The Anglo-German Agreement}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite hansard | url= http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1804/aug/22/class-v#S4V0029P0-01165| house=House of Commons | date= 22 August 1804| column_start= 324| column_end=337 | title = Class V}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sultan Ali's successor was [[Hamad bin Thuwaini of Zanzibar|Hamad bin Thuwaini]], who became sultan in 1893. Hamad maintained a close relationship with the British, but there was dissent among his subjects over the increasing British control over the country, the British-led army and the abolition of the valuable slave trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon399&quot;/&gt; In order to control this dissent, the British authorities authorised the sultan to raise a Zanzibari palace bodyguard of 1,000 men, but these troops were soon involved in clashes with the British-led police.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernon148&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2000|p=148}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett178&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Bennett|1978|p=178}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Complaints about the bodyguards' activities were also received from the European residents in Zanzibar Town.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon399&quot;/&gt;

== 25 August ==

Sultan Hamad died suddenly at 11:40 EAT (08:40 [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]]) on 25 August 1896.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon399&quot;/&gt; His 29-year-old nephew [[Khalid bin Barghash of Zanzibar|Khalid bin Bargash]], who was suspected by some of his assassination,&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon399&quot;/&gt; moved into the palace complex at Zanzibar Town without British approval, in contravention of the treaty agreed with Ali.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon399&quot;/&gt; The British government preferred an alternative candidate, Hamud bin Muhammed, who was more favourably disposed towards them. Khalid was warned by the consul and diplomatic agent to Zanzibar, [[Basil Cave]], and General Mathews to think carefully about his actions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett178&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=400}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This course of action had proved successful three years earlier when Khalid had tried to claim the sultanate after the death of Ali, and the British consul-general, Rennell Rodd, had persuaded him of the dangers of such an action.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker194&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Tucker|1970|p=194}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Khalid ignored Cave's warning, and his forces began mustering in the Palace Square under the command of Captain Saleh of the palace bodyguard. By the end of the day, they numbered 2,800 men armed with rifles and muskets.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt; The majority were civilians, but the force included 700 Zanzibari [[Askari]] soldiers who had sided with Khalid.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT warning&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=|first=|title=A Warning to Said Khalid|newspaper=The New York Times|date=27 August 1896|page=5|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9405E2D91E3AE533A25754C2A96E9C94679ED7CF| accessdate = 2008-10-16}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The sultan's artillery, which consisted of several [[Maxim machine gun]]s, a [[Gatling gun]], a 17th-century bronze cannon and two 12-pounder [[field guns]], was aimed at the British ships in the harbour.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT warning&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;patience9&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=9}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The 12-pounders had been presented to the sultan by [[Wilhelm II, German Emperor|Wilhelm II]], the German emperor.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt; The sultan's troops also took possession of the Zanzibari Navy, which consisted of one wooden sloop, the [[HHS Glasgow|HHS ''Glasgow'']], built as a [[royal yacht]] for the sultan in 1878 based on the British frigate [[HMS Glasgow (1861)|''Glasgow'']].&lt;ref name=&quot;patience5&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Mathews and Cave also began to muster their forces, already commanding 900 Zanzibari [[askari]]s under Lieutenant [[Arthur Edward Harington Raikes]] of the [[Wiltshire Regiment]] who was seconded to the Zanzibar Army and held the rank of [[brigadier-general]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt; 150 sailors and marines were landed from the [[Pearl class cruiser|''Pearl''-class]] [[protected cruiser]] [[HMS Philomel (1890)|''Philomel'']] and the [[gunboat]] [[HMS Thrush (1889)|''Thrush'']], which were anchored in the harbour.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt; The naval contingent, under the command of Captain O'Callaghan, came ashore within fifteen minutes of being requested to deal with any rioting caused by the general population.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=|first=|title=Zanzibar's Sultan Dead|newspaper=The New York Times|date=26 August 1896|page=5| url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9C0CE5D91E3AE533A25755C2A96E9C94679ED7CF| accessdate=2008-10-16}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A smaller contingent of sailors under Lieutenant Watson of ''Thrush'' were put ashore to guard the British consulate, where British citizens were requested to gather for protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt; [[HMS Sparrow (1889)|HMS ''Sparrow'']], another gunboat, entered the harbour and was anchored opposite the palace next to ''Thrush''.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt;

Some concerns were raised among the British diplomats as to the reliability of Raikes' askaris, but they proved to be steady and professional troops hardened by [[military drill]] and several expeditions to East Africa. They would later become the only land troops to be fired upon by the defenders.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt; Raikes' troops were armed with two Maxim guns and a nine pounder cannon, and were stationed at the nearby customs house.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience8&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The sultan attempted to have the US consul, [[Richard Dorsey Mohun]], recognise his accession, but the messenger was told that &quot;as his accession had not been verified by Her Majesty's government, it is impossible to reply.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;patience9&quot;/&gt;

Cave continued to send messages to Khalid requesting that he stand down his troops, leave the palace and return home, but these were ignored, and Khalid replied that he would proclaim himself sultan at 15:00. Cave stated that this would constitute an act of rebellion and that Khalid's sultancy would not be recognised by the British government.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon400&quot;/&gt; At 14:30, Sultan Hamad was buried, and exactly 30 minutes later a [[21-gun salute|royal salute]] from the palace guns proclaimed Khalid's succession. Cave could not open hostilities without government approval and telegraphed the following message to the [[Foreign Office]] of [[Lord Salisbury|Lord Salisbury's]] administration in London: &quot;Are we authorised in the event of all attempts at a peaceful solution proving useless, to fire on the Palace from the men-of-war?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Owens2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Owens|2007|p=2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, Cave informed all other foreign consuls that all flags were to remain at half mast in honour of the late Hamad. The only one that did not was a large red flag flying from Khalid's palace. Cave also informed the consuls not to recognise Khalid as sultan, to which they agreed.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=|first=|title=Sultan of Zanzibar Dead|newspaper=The New York Times|date=19 July 1902|page=9|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9B06EFD71E3BEE33A2575AC1A9619C946397D6CF|accessdate=2008-10-16}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== 26 August ==

At 10:00 on 26 August, the [[Archer-class cruiser|''Archer''-class]] protected cruiser [[HMS Racoon (1887)|''Racoon'']] arrived at Zanzibar Town and was anchored in line with ''Thrush'' and ''Sparrow''. At 14:00, the [[Edgar class cruiser|''Edgar''-class]] protected cruiser [[HMS St George (1892)|''St George'']], [[flagship]] of the Cape and East Africa Station, steamed into the harbour. On board were [[Rear-Admiral]] [[Harry Rawson]] and further British marines and sailors. At around the same time Lord Salisbury's reply arrived authorising Cave and Rawson to use the resources at their disposal to remove Khalid from power.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon401&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=401}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The telegraph read: &quot;You are authorised to adopt whatever measures you may consider necessary, and will be supported in your action by Her Majesty's Government. Do not, however, attempt to take any action which you are not certain of being able to accomplish successfully.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Owens2&quot;/&gt;

Cave attempted further negotiations with Khalid, but these failed and Rawson sent an [[ultimatum]], requiring him to haul down his flag and leave the palace by 09:00 on 27 August or he would open fire. During the afternoon, all merchant vessels were cleared from the harbour and the British women and children removed to ''St. George'' and a [[British-India Steam Navigation Company]] vessel for their safety. That night, Consul Mohun noted that: &quot;The silence which hung over Zanzibar was appalling. Usually drums were beating or babies cried but that night there was absolutely not a sound.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;patience11&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=11}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== 27 August ==

At 08:00 on the morning of 27 August, after a messenger sent by Khalid requested [[parley]] from Cave, the consul replied that he would only have salvation if he agreed to the terms of the ultimatum.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon402&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lyne200&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lyne|1905|p=200}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At 08:30 a further messenger from Khalid declared that &quot;We have no intention of hauling down our flag and we do not believe you would open fire on us&quot;; Cave replied that &quot;We do not want to open fire, but unless you do as you are told we shall certainly do so.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;patience11&quot;/&gt; At 08:55, having received no further word from the palace, aboard ''St George'' Rawson hoisted the signal &quot;prepare for action&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lyne201&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lyne|1905|p=201}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

At exactly 09:00, General Lloyd Mathews ordered the British ships to commence the bombardment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Owens2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Thompson|1984|p=64}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At 09:02 Her Majesty's Ships ''Racoon'', ''Thrush'' and ''Sparrow'' opened fire at the palace simultaneously, ''Thrush's'' first shot immediately dismounted an Arab 12-pounder cannon. Three thousand defenders, servants and slaves were present in the largely wooden palace, and even with barricades of crates, bales and rubber, there were many casualties from the [[high explosive]] shells. Despite initial reports that he had been captured and was to be exiled to [[India]], Sultan Khalid escaped from the palace.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon402&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=|first=|title= Bombarded by the British |newspaper= The New York Times |date=28 August 1896 |page=1 |url= http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9800E0D91E3AE533A2575BC2A96E9C94679ED7CF |accessdate= 2008-10-16}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Reuters]] news correspondent reported that the sultan had &quot;fled at the first shot with all the leading Arabs, who left their slaves and followers to carry on the fighting&quot;, but other sources state that he remained in the palace for longer.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon402&quot;/&gt; The shelling ceased at around 09:40, by which time the palace and attached harem had caught fire, the Sultan's artillery had been silenced and his flag cut down.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt;

During the bombardment a small naval engagement occurred when, at 09:05, the obsolete ''Glasgow'' fired upon the ''St George'' using her armament of 7 nine-pounder guns and a Gatling gun, which had been a present from Queen Victoria to the sultan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Patience6&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=6}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The return fire caused ''Glasgow'' to sink, though the shallow harbour meant that her masts remained out of the water.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt; ''Glasgow''{{'}}s crew hoisted a British flag as a token of their surrender, and they were all rescued by British sailors in [[launch (boat)|launches]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt; ''Thrush'' also sank two steam launches whose Zanzibari crews shot at her with rifles. Some land fighting occurred when Khalid's men fired on Raikes' askaris, with little effect, as they approached the palace.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt; The fighting ceased with the end of the shelling. The British controlled the town and the palace, and by the afternoon Hamud bin Muhammed, an Arab favourable to the British, had been installed as sultan with much reduced powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon404&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=404}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The British ships and crews had fired around 500 shells, 4,100 machine gun rounds and 1,000 rifle rounds during the engagement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Patience14&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=14}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{multiple image
| align = center
| direction = horizontal
| header =
| image1 = HMS Thrush.jpg
| width1 = 330
| alt1 = HMS Thrush, a gun boat with sails, at sea
| caption1 = [[HMS Thrush (1889)|HMS ''Thrush'']]
| image2 = St George and Philomel.jpg
| width2 = 180
| alt2 = Armoured ships, HMS St George and HMS Philomel in the harbour
| caption2 = [[HMS St George (1892)|HMS ''St George'']] and [[HMS Philomel (1890)|HMS ''Philomel'']]
| image3 = Anglo-Zanzibar War without gunfire.svg
| width3 = 332
| alt3 = Map of battle ships' positions at 09.00, before battle
| caption3 = Dispositions of naval forces at 09.00
}}

== Aftermath ==
Around 500 Zanzibari men and women were killed or wounded during the bombardment, most of the dead a result of the fire that engulfed the palace.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett179&quot;/&gt; It is unknown how many of these casualties were combatants, but Khalid's gun crews were said to have been &quot;decimated&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience12&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=12}}.&lt;/ref&gt; British casualties amounted to one [[Petty Officer]] severely wounded aboard ''Thrush'' who later recovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;/&gt; Although the majority of the Zanzibari townspeople sided with the British, the town's [[India]]n quarter suffered from opportunistic looting, and around twenty inhabitants lost their lives in the chaos.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience15&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=15}}.&lt;/ref&gt; To restore order, 150 British [[Sikh]] troops were transferred from [[Mombasa]] to patrol the streets.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon404&quot;/&gt; Sailors from ''St George'' and ''Philomel'' were landed to form a [[fire brigade]] to contain the fire, which had spread from the palace to the nearby customs sheds.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience20-22&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|pp=20–22}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There was some concern about the fire at the customs sheds as they contained a sizeable store of explosives, but no explosion occurred.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience12&quot;/&gt;

Sultan Khalid, Captain Saleh and around forty followers sought refuge in the German consulate following their flight from the palace,&lt;ref name=&quot;patience12&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=|first=|title=Will Not Surrender Khalid|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=30 August 1896|page=5|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=980CE3D81E3AE533A25753C3A96E9C94679ED7CF|accessdate=2008-10-16}}.&lt;/ref&gt; where they were guarded by ten armed German sailors and marines while Mathews stationed men outside to arrest them if they tried to leave.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frankl163&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Frankl|2006|p=163}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite [[extradition]] requests, the German consul refused to surrender Khalid to the British as his country's extradition treaty with Britain specifically excluded political prisoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon404&quot;/&gt; Instead, the German consul promised to remove Khalid to [[German East Africa]] without him &quot;setting foot on the soil of Zanzibar&quot;. At 10:00 on 2 October, [[SMS Seeadler|SMS ''Seeadler'']] of the [[Kaiserliche Marine|German Navy]] arrived in port; at high tide, one of Seeadler's boats made it up to the consulate's garden gate, and Khalid stepped directly from consular grounds to a German war vessel and hence was free from arrest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frankl163&quot;/&gt; He was transferred from the boat onto the ''Seeadler'' and was then taken to [[Dar es Salaam]] in German East Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Ingrams|1967|pp=174–175}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Khalid was captured by British forces in 1916, during the [[East African Campaign (World War I)|East African Campaign]] of [[World War I]], and exiled to [[Seychelles]] and [[Saint Helena]] before being allowed to return to East Africa, where he died at [[Mombasa]] in 1927.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frankl161&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Frankl|2006|p=161}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The British punished Khalid's supporters by forcing them to pay reparations to cover the cost of shells fired against them and for damages caused by the looting, which amounted to 300,000 [[Indian rupee|rupees]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon404&quot;/&gt;

Sultan Hamud was loyal to the British and acted as a [[puppet ruler|figurehead]] for an essentially British-run government, the sultanate only being retained to avoid the costs involved with running Zanzibar directly as a [[crown colony]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon404&quot;/&gt; Several months after the war, Hamud, with British prompting, abolished slavery in all its forms.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon404&quot;/&gt; The emancipation of slaves required them to present themselves to a government office and proved a slow process—within ten years only 17,293 slaves had been freed, from an estimated population of 60,000 in 1891.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bakari|2001|pp=49–50}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The badly damaged palace complex was completely changed by the war. The harem, lighthouse and palace were demolished as the bombardment had left them unsafe.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience15&quot;/&gt; The palace site became an area of gardens, while a new palace was erected on the site of the harem.&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle160&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;archnet&quot;&gt;{{Citation | last = Aga Khan Trust for Culture | first = | author-link = Aga Khan Trust for Culture| title = Sultan's Palace at Zanzibar | url = http://archnet.org/library/sites/one-site.jsp?site_id=8208 | accessdate = 2008-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The House of Wonders was almost undamaged and would later become the main [[wikt:secretariat|secretariat]] for the British governing authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience12&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle156&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hoyle|2002|p=156}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During renovation work on the House of Wonders in 1897, a clocktower was added to its frontage to replace the lighthouse lost to the shelling.&lt;ref name=&quot;archnet&quot;/&gt; The wreck of the ''Glasgow'' remained in the harbour in front of the palace, where the shallow waters ensured that her masts would remain visible for several years to come; it was eventually broken up for scrap in 1912.&lt;ref name=&quot;patience16&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|p=16}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The British protagonists were highly regarded by the governments in London and Zanzibar for their actions leading up to and during the war, and many were rewarded with appointments and honours. General Raikes, leader of the askaris, was appointed a First Class (Second Grade) member of the [[Order of the Brilliant Star of Zanzibar]] on 24 September 1896, a First Class member of the Zanzibari [[Order of Hamondieh]] on 25 August 1897 and later promoted to Commander of the Zanzibar armies.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=26780|startpage=5320|date=25 September 1896|accessdate=16 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ham&quot;&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=26886|startpage=4812|date=27 August 1897|accessdate=16 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; General Mathews, the Zanzibari army commander, was appointed a member of the [[Grand Order of Hamondieh]] on 25 August 1897 and became First Minister and Treasurer to the Zanzibari government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ham&quot;/&gt; Basil Cave, the consul, was appointed a [[Companion of the Order of the Bath]] on 1 January 1897&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=26810|startpage=65|date=1 January 1897|accessdate=10 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and promoted to consul-general on 9 July 1903.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=27588|startpage=5150|date=14 August 1903|accessdate=10 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harry Rawson was appointed a [[Knight Commander of the Order of the Bath]] for his work in Zanzibar and would later be [[Governor of New South Wales]] in [[Australia]] and receive promotion to [[Admiral (Royal Navy)|admiral]].&lt;ref name=&quot;rawson&quot;&gt;{{Citation | title = Obituary: Admiral Sir Harry H. Rawson | newspaper = The Times | date = November 4, 1910 | url =http://members.cox.net/ggtext/harryrawson1843_obit.html | accessdate=2008-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rawson was also appointed a first class member of the Order of the Brilliant Star of Zanzibar on 8 February 1897 and the Order of Hamondieh on 18 June 1898.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=26821|startpage=758|date=9 February 1897|accessdate=10 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=26979|startpage=3769|date=21 June 1898|accessdate=10 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Perhaps due to the effectiveness shown by the Royal Navy during the bombardment, there were no further rebellions against British influence during the remaining 67 years of the protectorate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett179&quot;/&gt;
{{multiple image
| align = center
| direction = horizontal
| header =
| image1 = Marines in zanzibar.jpg
| width1 = 195
| alt1 = British sailors pose with a captured cannon outside the sultan's palace
| caption1 = British sailors pose with a captured cannon outside the sultan's palace
| image2 = Zanzibar palace after low.JPG
| width2 = 223
| alt2 = The palace complex following the bombardment
| caption2 = The palace complex following the bombardment
}}
[[File:A. C. Gomes Panorama Zanzibar 1902.jpg|center|700px|thumb |The masts of the sunken ''[[HHS Glasgow|Glasgow]]'' can be seen in this panorama of Zanzibar Town harbour taken in 1902, looking east. The House of Wonders is the white building with a tower and many balconies in the middle of the photograph; the [[harem]] and palace stood to the left. The consulate buildings are to the right.
|The masts of the sunken ''[[HHS Glasgow|Glasgow]]'' can be seen in this panorama of Zanzibar Town harbour taken in 1902, looking east. The House of Wonders is the white building with a tower and many balconies in the middle of the photograph; the [[harem]] and palace stood to the left. The consulate buildings are to the right.]]

==Duration==

The war, lasting less than three quarters of an hour, is considered the shortest in recorded history.&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon396&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=396}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Several durations are given by sources, including 38,&lt;ref name=&quot;hernon403&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hernon|2003|p=403}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haws|Hurst|1985|p=74}}.&lt;/ref&gt; 40&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Cohen|Jacopetti|Prosperi|1966|p=137}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and 45&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Gordon|2007|p=146}}.&lt;/ref&gt; minutes, but the 38-minute duration is the most often quoted. The variation is due to confusion over what actually constitutes the start and end of a war. Some sources take the start of the war as the order to open fire at 09:00 and some with the start of actual firing at 09:02. The end of the war is usually put at 09:40, when the last shots were fired and the palace flag struck, but some sources place it at 09:45. The logbooks of the British ships also suffer from this with ''St George'' indicating that cease-fire was called and Khalid entered the German consulate at 09:35, ''Thrush'' at 09:40, ''Racoon'' at 09:41, and ''Philomel'' and ''Sparrow'' at 09:45.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Patience|1994|pp=20–26}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{citation|last=Bakari|first=Mohammed Ali |title= The Democratisation Process in Zanzibar: A Retarded Transition |year=2001 |publisher= [[German Institute of Global and Area Studies|Institut für Afrika-Kunde]] |location= Hamburg |isbn= 978-3-928049-71-9 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=9yCSamtUeiAC }}.
* {{citation|last=Bennett|first=Norman Robert |title= A History of the Arab State of Zanzibar |publisher= [[Methuen Publishing]] |location= London |year=1978|isbn= 978-0-416-55080-1 }}.
* {{Citation|last= Cohen |first= John |last2= Jacopetti |first2= Gualtiero |last3= Prosperi |first3= Franco |title= Africa Addio |location= New York |publisher= [[Ballantine Books]] |year= 1966 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=vR9BAAAAIAAJ |oclc= 230433}}.
* {{citation|last= Frankl |first= P.J.L. |title= The Exile of Sayyid Khalid bin Barghash Al-BuSa'idi |journal= British Journal of Middle Eastern Studies |year= 2006 |volume= 33 |issue= 2 |pages= 161–177 |issn= 1469-3542 |oclc= |doi= 10.1080/13530190600603675}}.
* {{citation|last=Gordon|first=Philip H. |title= Winning the Right War: The Path to Security for America and the World |publisher= Times Books |year= 2007 |location= New York |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=YUm142jq6F8C|isbn= 978-0-8050-8657-7 }}.
* {{Citation|last= Haws|first= Duncan |last2= Hurst |first2= Alexander Anthony |title= The Maritime History of the World: A Chronological Survey of Maritime Events from 5,000 B.C. until the Present Day |location= Brighton, Sussex |publisher= Teredo Books |year= 1985 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=4iFUAAAAMAAJ |isbn= 978-0-903662-10-9 }}.
* {{citation|last=Hernon |first= Ian |title= Britain's Forgotten Wars: Colonial Campaigns of the 19th Century |publisher= [[Sutton Publishing]] |year= 2003 |location= Stroud, Gloucestershire |isbn= 978-0-7509-3162-5 }}.
* {{citation|last= Hernon |first= Ian |title= The Savage Empire: Forgotten Wars of the 19th Century |publisher=[[Sutton Publishing]] |year= 2000 |location= Stroud, Gloucestershire |url= |isbn= 978-0-7509-2480-1 }}.
* {{citation|last=Hoyle|first=Brian |title=Urban Waterfront Revitalization in Developing Countries: The Example of Zanzibar's Stone Town |journal= Geographical Journal |year= 2002 |volume= 168 |issue= 2 |pages= 141–162 |issn= |oclc= |doi=10.1111/1475-4959.00044}}.
* {{citation|last= Ingrams |first= William H. |title= Zanzibar: Its History and Its People |publisher= Cass |location= London |year= 1967 |oclc= 722777 }}.
* {{citation|last= Lyne |first= Robert Nunez |title= Zanzibar in Contemporary Times |year= 1905 |publisher= Hurst and Blackett |location= London |url= https://books.google.com/?id=Z9sLAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage&amp;dq= |oclc= 251506750 }}.
* {{citation|last=Owens|first=Geoffrey R.|title= Exploring the Articulation of Governmentality and Sovereignty: The Chwaka Road and the Bombardment of Zanzibar, 1895–1896 |publisher=[[Johns Hopkins University Press]] |journal= [[Journal of Colonialism and Colonial History]] |year= 2007 |volume= 7 |issue= 2 |pages= 1–55 |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/journal_of_colonialism_and_colonial_history/v008/8.2owens.html |issn=1532-5768|oclc=45037899|doi=10.1353/cch.2007.0036}}.
* {{citation|last= Patience |first= Kevin |title= Zanzibar and the Shortest War in History |publisher= Kevin Patience |location= Bahrain |year= 1994 |oclc= 37843635 }}.
* {{citation|last= Thompson |first= Cecil |title= The Sultans of Zanzibar |journal= Tanzania Notes and Records |issue= 94 |year= 1984}}.
* {{citation|last= Tucker |first= Alfred R. |title= Eighteen Years in Uganda and East Africa |year= 1970 |publisher= [[Negro Universities Press]] |location=Westport, Connecticut |url= http://ia360925.us.archive.org/2/items/eighteenyearsinu00tuck/eighteenyearsinu00tuck.pdf |format=PDF|edition= New |isbn= 978-0-8371-3280-8 }}.

==Further reading==
* {{citation|editor1-last=Appiah |editor1-first= K. Anthony |editor1-link=Kwame Anthony Appiah |editor2-last=Gates|editor2-first=Henry Louis, Jr.|editor2-link= Henry Louis Gates, Jr.|year=1999 |title=Africana: The Encyclopedia of the African and African American Experience |publisher= [[Basic Books]] |location= New York |isbn= 978-0-465-00071-5}}.
* {{citation|last=Ayany |first=Samuel G.|title=A History of Zanzibar: A Study in Constitutional Development, 1934–1964 |publisher= [[East African Literature Bureau]] |location= Nairobi |year= 1970 |oclc= 201465}}.
* {{citation|last=Keane |first= Augustus H. |authorlink= Augustus Henry Keane |title= Africa |publisher= [[Edward Stanford]] |location= London |year= 1907 |edition= 2nd |volume= 1
|url= https://books.google.com/?id=NrgBAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage |oclc= 27707159 }}.
* {{citation|last= Scientific American |title= Zanzibar |journal= [[Scientific American]] |volume= 42 |issue= 1082 |pages= 17287–17292 |date= 26 September 1896 | url= http://www.gutenberg.org/files/24323/24323-h/24323-h.htm#art06 }}.

{{featured article}}
{{British colonial campaigns}}

[[Category:19th century in Africa]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1896]]
[[Category:Wars involving Zanzibar]]
[[Category:Wars involving the United Kingdom|Zanzibar]]
[[Category:19th-century military history of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1896 in Zanzibar]]
[[Category:1896 in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Punitive expeditions of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:19th century in Zanzibar]]
[[Category:Sultanate of Zanzibar]]</text>
      <sha1>dnl7gn1l3thgtvb8h2vd1hb60c91e76</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
