<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anna of East Anglia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>544577</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747165862</id>
      <parentid>747165853</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-31T20:28:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/66.244.41.38|66.244.41.38]] to version by Nikkimaria. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (2818357) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34104">{{EngvarB|date=April 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}
{{Infobox royalty
| type         = monarch
| name         = Anna
| image        = 
| caption      = 
| succession   = [[List of monarchs of East Anglia|King of the East Angles]]
| reign        = c. 636&amp;nbsp;– 654 AD
| predecessor  = [[Ecgric of East Anglia|Ecgric]]
| successor    = [[Æthelhere of East Anglia|Æthelhere]]
| spouse       = Sæwara
| issue        = [[Jurmin]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Seaxburh of Ely|Seaxburh]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Æthelthryth]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Æthelburh of Faremoutiers|Æthelburh]]&lt;br /&gt;possibly [[Wihtburh]]
| house        = [[Wuffingas]]
| father       = [[Eni of East Anglia|Eni]]
| mother       = 
| birth_date   =
| birth_place  =
| death_date   = 653 or 654 AD
| death_place  = [[Battle of Bulcamp]]
| burial_place = probably [[Blythburgh]], Suffolk, now lost
| religion     = Christian
}}

'''Anna''' (or '''Onna'''; killed 653 or 654) was [[List of monarchs of East Anglia|king of East Anglia]] from the early 640s until his death.  He was a member of the [[Wuffingas]] family, the ruling dynasty of the East Angles. He was one of the three sons of [[Eni of East Anglia|Eni]] who ruled the [[kingdom of East Anglia]], succeeding some time after [[Ecgric of East Anglia|Ecgric]] was killed in battle by [[Penda of Mercia]]. Anna was praised by [[Bede]] for his devotion to Christianity and was renowned for the saintliness of his family: his son [[Jurmin]] and all his daughters&amp;nbsp;– [[Seaxburh of Ely|Seaxburh]], [[Æthelthryth]], [[Æthelburh of Faremoutiers|Æthelburh]] and possibly a fourth, [[Wihtburh]]&amp;nbsp;– were canonised.

Little is known of Anna's life or his reign, as few records have survived from this period. In 631 he may have been at [[Exning]], close to the [[Devil's Dyke, Cambridgeshire|Devil's Dyke]]. In 645 [[Cenwalh of Wessex]] was driven from his kingdom by Penda and, due to Anna's influence, he was converted to Christianity while living as an exile at the East Anglian court. Upon his return from exile, Cenwalh re-established Christianity in his own kingdom and the people of Wessex then remained firmly Christian.

Around 651 the land around [[Isle of Ely|Ely]] was absorbed into East Anglia, following the marriage of Anna's daughter Æthelthryth.  Anna richly endowed the monastery at [[Cnobheresburg]]. In 651, in the aftermath of an attack by Penda on Cnobheresburg, Anna was forced to flee into exile, perhaps to the western kingdom of the [[Magonsæte]]. He returned to East Anglia in about 653, but soon afterwards the kingdom was attacked again by Penda and at the Battle of Bulcamp the East Anglian army, led by Anna, was defeated by the Mercians, and Anna and his son Jurmin were both killed. Anna was succeeded by his brother, [[Æthelhere of East Anglia|Æthelhere]]. [[Botwulf of Thorney|Botolph]]'s monastery at [[Iken]] may have been built in commemoration of the king. After Anna's reign, East Anglia seems to have been eclipsed by its more powerful neighbour, [[Mercia]].

==Sources==
The kingdom of East Anglia ({{lang-ang|Ēast Engla Rīce}}) was a small independent [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] kingdom that comprised what are now the English counties of [[Norfolk]] and [[Suffolk]] and perhaps the eastern part of the Cambridgeshire [[Fens]].&lt;ref name=eb11&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=East Anglia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to the kingdoms of [[Northumbria]], Mercia and [[Wessex]], little reliable evidence about the kingdom of the East Angles has survived, because of the destruction of its monasteries and the disappearance of the two East Anglian [[Episcopal see|sees]] that occurred as the result of [[Viking]] raids and settlement.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; The main primary sources for information about Anna's life and reign are the ''[[Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum]]'' (''Ecclesiastical History of the English People''), completed in Northumbria by Bede in 731, and the ''[[Anglo-Saxon Chronicle]]'', initially written in the ninth century, which mentions Anna's death. The mediaeval work known as the ''[[Liber Eliensis]]'', written in [[Ely Cathedral|Ely]] in the twelfth century, is a source of information about Anna's daughters Æthelthryth and Seaxburh, and also describes Anna's death and burial.&lt;ref&gt;Fairweather, ''Liber Eliensis'', pp.&amp;nbsp;8–10.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life and marriage==
[[File:Devil's Dyke Cambs.jpg|thumb|upright|right|alt=Colour photograph|The Devil's Dyke, near Exning. Anna may have been at Exning in 631.]]

Anna was the son of Eni, a member of the ruling Wuffingas family, and nephew of [[Rædwald of East Anglia|Rædwald]], king of the East Angles from 600 to 625.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford DNB&quot;&gt;Kelly, ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography: Anna (d. 654?), king of the East Angles''.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kingdom of East Anglia|East Anglia]] was an early and long-lived [[Anglo-Saxon England|Anglo-Saxon]] kingdom in which a duality of a northern and a southern part existed, corresponding with the modern English counties of [[Norfolk]] and [[Suffolk]].&lt;ref&gt;Lapidge, ''Blackwell Encyclopaedia of Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;

Anna was married, according to Bede, who refers to the saint [[Sæthryth]] as &quot;daughter of the wife of Anna, king of the East Angles&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bede, (edition by Colgrave and Mynors), ''Ecclesiastical History of the English People'', (Book III, Chapter 8), pp. 238–9, &quot;''...&amp;nbsp;inter quas erat Saethryd, filia uxoris Annae regis Orientalium Anglorum''&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Folcard|Abbott Folcard]]'s ''Life of St Botolph'', written in the 11th century, Botolph is described as having been at one time the chaplain to the sisters of a king, Æthelmund, whose mother was named Sæwara. Folcard names two of Sæwara's kinsmen as Æthelhere and Æthelwold. Since these are the names of two of Anna's brothers, Steven Plunkett suggests that it is &quot;tempting&quot; to consider that Sæwara was married to Anna, and that Æthelmund might either be Anna's full name, or the name of an otherwise unknown East Anglian sub-king.&lt;ref&gt;Plunkett, ''Suffolk in Anglo-Saxon Times'', pp. 116–17.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Liber Eliensis'' names [[Hereswith]], the sister of [[Hilda of Whitby|Hild, abbess of Whitby]], as Anna's wife and the mother of Sæthryth, Seaxburh of Ely and Æthelthryth.&lt;ref&gt;Fairweather, ''Liber Eliensis: A History of the Isle of Ely from the Seventh Century to the Twelfth, compiled by a Monk of Ely in the Twelfth Century'', pp. 14–15.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the ''Liber Eliensis'' is regarded with caution by historians: Rosalind Love says that the mediaeval writers who interpreted Bede's information about Hereswith made an &quot;erroneous assumption&quot; regarding her connection with Anna and his family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford DNB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Love, ''Goscelin of Saint-Bertin: the Hagiography of the Female Saints of Ely'', p. lxxxviii.&lt;/ref&gt; Historians now  believe that Hereswith was Anna's sister-in-law and that around the time that she married into the East Anglian royal family, Anna had already been king for a decade.&lt;ref&gt;Hunter Blair, in ''Learning and Literature in Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 631 Anna was probably at the Suffolk village of Exning, an important settlement with royal connections,&lt;ref&gt;Warner, ''The Origins of Suffolk'', p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; and, according to the ''Liber Eliensis'', the birthplace of his daughter Æthelthryth.&lt;ref&gt;Fairweather, ''Liber Eliensis: A History of the Isle of Ely from the Seventh Century to the Twelfth, compiled by a Monk of Ely in the Twelfth Century'', pp. 15–16.&lt;/ref&gt; By tradition, Æthelthryth is said to have been baptised at Exning in a pool known as St Mindred's Well.&lt;ref&gt;James, ''Suffolk and Norfolk'', p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; Exning was an important place strategically, as it stood just on the East Anglian side of the Devil's Dyke, a major earthwork stretching between the [[Fen]] edge and the headwaters of the [[River Stour, Suffolk|River Stour]], built at an earlier date to defend the East Anglian region from attack. An early Anglo-Saxon cemetery discovered there suggests the existence of an important site nearby, possibly a royal estate or regio.&lt;ref&gt;Warner, ''The Origins of Suffolk'', pp. 119–20.&lt;/ref&gt;

==King of the East Angles==

===Accession and rule===
[[File:England green top.svg|thumb|250px|right|upright|alt=Map of Anglo-Saxon Britain|Anglo-Saxon England|The main Anglo-Saxon kingdoms]]

During 632 or 633 [[Edwin of Northumbria]], with his centre of Christian power north of the River [[Humber]], was overthrown. Edwin was slain and Northumbria was ravaged by [[Cadwallon ap Cadfan]], supported by the Mercian king, [[Penda of Mercia|Penda]].&lt;ref&gt;Stenton, ''Anglo-Saxon England'', pp. 80–81.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mercians then turned on the kingdom of the East Angles and their king, [[Ecgric of East Anglia|Ecgric]]. At an unknown date (possibly in the early 640s),&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; they routed the East Anglian army and Ecgric and his predecessor [[Sigeberht of East Anglia|Sigeberht]] were both slain.&lt;ref name=&quot;W110-13&quot;/&gt; D. P. Kirby has suggested that as Sigeberht was alive when the Irish monk [[Saint Fursey|Fursey]] left for Gaul and found [[Erchinoald]], (which happened after Erchinoald became [[Mayor of the Palace|Mayor of the Neustrian palace]] in 641), Sigeberht was probably killed around 640 or 641.&lt;ref&gt;Kirby, ''The Earliest English Kings'', pp. 207–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Penda's victory marked the end of the line of kings of the East Angles who were directly descended from Rædwald.&lt;ref&gt;Kirby, ''The Earliest English Kings'', p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; Some time after Penda's victory, Anna became king of the East Angles, though the date of his accession is quite uncertain.  The ''Liber Eliensis'' says that Anna died in the nineteenth year of his reign, and since he died in the mid-650s this would indicate a date around 635.&lt;ref name=K1_108-9&gt;Kirby, ''The Earliest English Kings'', p.&amp;nbsp;208 (note 26).&lt;/ref&gt; However, the ''Liber Eliensis'' is regarded by some historians as unreliable on this point,&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford DNB&quot;/&gt; and [[Barbara Yorke]] suggests a possible date in the early 640s for Anna's accession, noting that it could not have been after 645 as Anna is recorded as giving refuge to Cenwalh of Wessex in that year.&lt;ref name=Y63/&gt;{{refn|1=Bede gives the story without dates, but makes it clear that Anna was king when Cenwalh came to East Anglia; the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'' gives the date as 645 or 646 but does not specify that Anna was king at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Bede (ed. Colgrave and Mynors), ''Ecclesiastical History of the English People'', (Book III, Chapter 7), p. 235.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Swanton, ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', pp.&amp;nbsp;28–29.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} It is probable that Anna became king with the assistance of the northern Angles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kirby, p.79&quot;&gt;Kirby, ''The Earliest English Kings'', p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout his reign he was the victim of Mercian aggression under Penda, but he also seems to have challenged the rise of Penda's power.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of early Anglo-Saxon-England'', pp. 62–3.&lt;/ref&gt; The British medievalist [[David Dumville]] has written that due to their rivalry for control over the [[Middle Angles|Middle Anglian]] people, Mercia and East Anglia probably became hereditary enemies and Penda repeatedly attacked the East Angles from the mid-630s to 654.&lt;ref&gt;Dumville, ''Essex, Middle Anglia, and the Expansion of Mercia in the South-East Midlands'', p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;

Anna arranged an important diplomatic marriage between his daughter Seaxburh and [[Eorcenberht of Kent]], cementing an alliance between the two kingdoms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Y65-6&quot;&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', pp. 65–66.&lt;/ref&gt; It was by means of marriages such as this that the [[List of monarchs of Kent|kings of Kent]] could become well-connected to other royal dynasties.&lt;ref&gt;Kirby, ''The Earliest English Kings'', p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; Not all of Anna's daughters were married into other royal families. During the 640s Anna's daughter Æthelburg and his stepdaughter Sæthryth entered [[Faremoutiers Abbey]] in [[Gaul]] to live religious lives under abbess [[Saint Fara|Fara]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Y65-6&quot;/&gt; The first royal Anglo-Saxons to become nuns, they made religious seclusion &quot;an acceptable and desirable vocation for ex-queens and royal princesses&quot;, according to Barbara Yorke.{{refn|1=A Christian king like Anna would have made a priority of demonstrating his commitment to his kingdom's new faith by acting in a way that would mark them out as holy, and the patronage of nunneries would have been of concern to him.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Nunneries and the Anglo-Saxon Royal Houses'', pp. 17, 30.&lt;/ref&gt; It is not recorded why Anna's daughters took the veil. Yorke comments on the paucity of written documents regarding the princesses of East Anglia, considering the important role they played in the foundation of Anglo-Saxon royal nunneries.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Nunneries and the Anglo-Saxon Royal Houses'', pp. 18, 27.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}}

D. P. Kirby uses the presence of East Anglian princesses living under the veil in Gaul as evidence of the Frankish orientation of Anna's kingdom at this time, continued since the reign of his predecessor Rædwald.&lt;ref&gt;Kirby, ''The Earliest English Kings'', pp. 55, 74.&lt;/ref&gt; The Wuffingas dynasty may have been connected with monastic foundations in the area around Faramoutiers through Anna's predecessor Sigeberht, who had spent several years as an exile in Gaul and had become a devout and learned Christian due to his experiences of monastic life.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Nunneries and the Anglo-Saxon Royal Houses'', p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Williamson p16 3.svg|thumb|right|upright|250px|The kingdom of East Anglia during the reign of Anna]]
In 641 [[Oswald of Northumbria|Oswald]] of [[Northumbria]] was slain in battle by Penda (probably at [[Oswestry]] in Shropshire). Due to his death, Northumbria was split into two. The northern part, [[Bernicia]], accepted Oswald's brother [[Oswiu of Northumbria|Oswiu]] as their new king, but the southern [[Deira]]ns refused to accept him and were ruled instead by a king of the original Deiran house, [[Oswine of Deira|Oswine]].&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon afterwards [[Cenwalh of Wessex]], the brother of Oswald's widow and himself married to Penda's sister, renounced his wife.&lt;ref&gt;Stenton, ''Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; In 645, according to the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', Penda drove Cenwalh from his kingdom and into exile. During the following year, while a refugee at Anna's court, he was converted to Christianity,&lt;ref&gt;Swanton, ''The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; returning in 648 to rule Wessex as a Christian king.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford DNB&quot;/&gt; Anna probably provided military support for Cenwalh's return to his throne.&lt;ref&gt;Plunkett, ''Suffolk in Anglo-Saxon Times'', p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;

Anna's hold on the western limits of his kingdom, which bordered on the Fen lands that surrounded the Isle of Ely, was strengthened by the marriage in 651 (or slightly later) of his daughter Æthelthryth to Tondberht, a prince of the South [[Gyrwas|Gyrwe]], a people living in the fens who may have been settled in the area around Ely.&lt;ref name=Y63&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', pp. 63, 65.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|1=A [http://www.anglo-saxons.net/hwaet/?do=get&amp;type=map&amp;id=map8c map] of southern England in the 8th century (drawn by [[Reginald Piggott]]) gives an indication of where the Gyrwe people lived&amp;nbsp;– between East Anglia and the land of the Middle Angles.&lt;ref&gt;University of Cambridge (Department of ASNC), online map: ''Southern England in the Eighth Century''.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} Æthelthryth, accompanied by her minister Owine, travelled from Ely to Northumbria when she married for the second time, to [[Ecgfrith of Northumbria|Ecgfrith]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Y70-1&quot;/&gt;

===Exile===
[[File:Wall-of-Burgh-Castle-England-UK.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Monochrome drawing|The ruins of [[Burgh Castle]], the possible site of the monastery at Cnobheresburg, as depicted in 1845]]

During his reign Anna endowed the monastery at [[Burgh Castle|Cnobheresburg]] with rich buildings and objects.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', pp. 62–63, 70.&lt;/ref&gt; The monastery was built in about 633 by Fursey after he arrived in East Anglia. In time, weary of attacks on the kingdom, Fursey left East Anglia for good, leaving the monastery to his brother [[Foillan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;W110-13&quot;&gt;Warner, ''The Origins of Suffolk'', pp. 110–13.&lt;/ref&gt; When in 651 Penda attacked the monastery, Anna and his men arrived and held the Mercians back.  This gave Foillan and his monks enough time to escape with their books and valuables, but Penda defeated Anna and drove him into exile, possibly to the kingdom of [[Merewalh]] of the [[Magonsæte|Magonsætan]], in western [[Shropshire]].&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', pp. 62–63.&lt;/ref&gt; He returned to East Anglia in about 654.&lt;ref&gt;West, et al., ''Iken, St Botolph, and the Coming of East Anglian Christianity'', p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death, burial place and successors===
Soon after 653, when Penda made his son [[Peada of Mercia|Peada]] the ruler of the Middle Angles (but still continued to rule his own country),&lt;ref&gt;According to Bede (Yorke,  ''Kings and Kingdoms'', p. 63).&lt;/ref&gt; the Mercian assault on East Anglia was repeated. The opposing armies of Penda and Anna met at Bulcamp, near [[Blythburgh]] in Suffolk. The East Anglians were defeated and many were slain, including King Anna and his son [[Jurmin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;W110-13&quot;/&gt; Anna's death is mentioned in the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'' in the entry for 653 or 654, '' &quot;Her Anna cining werð ofslagen&amp;nbsp;...&quot; ''&amp;nbsp;– 'Here Anna was killed'&amp;nbsp;– but no other details of the battle in which he died are given.&lt;ref&gt;Earle, ''Two of the Saxon Chronicles Parallel'', p.&amp;nbsp;27.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|1=Manuscript A of the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'' dates ''Onna's'' death at 654; ''Anna's'' demise is dated by Manuscript E at 653. See Swanton, ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', pp. xv–xvi for a discussion of some of the discrepancies between the different manuscripts and possible reasons for these.&lt;ref&gt;Earle, ''Two of the Saxon Chronicles Parallel'', pp. 27–28.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}}

[[File:Marshland near Blythburgh - geograph.org.uk - 192171.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Colour photograph|Marshland around Blythburgh, near where Anna met his death]]
[[File:Blythburgh writing tablet.jpg|thumb|right|alt=drawing|A drawing of the writing-tablet found near a possible monastic site at Blythburgh]]
Blythburgh, a mile from Bulcamp and situated near the fordable headwaters of the [[River Blyth, Suffolk|Blyth]] estuary, was afterwards believed to be the location of the tombs of Anna and Jurmin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford DNB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Y70-1&quot;/&gt; It is a candidate for a monastic site or a royal regio (estate). According to Peter Warner, the Latin derivation of part of the nearby place-name 'Bulcamp' indicates its ancient origins, and mediaeval sources which claim continuous Christian worship at Blythburgh throughout the Anglo-Saxon period provide circumstantial evidence of its connections with East Anglian royalty and Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;Warner, ''The Origins of Suffolk'', pp. 115, 120.&lt;/ref&gt; Part of an 8th-century whalebone [[diptych]] or writing-tablet, used for liturgical purposes, has been found near the site.&lt;ref&gt;Wessex Archaeology.&lt;/ref&gt;

Saint Botolph began to build his monastery at Icanho, now conclusively identified as [[Iken]], Suffolk,&lt;ref&gt;Blair, ''Oxford Dictionary of Nationary Biography: Botwulf (fl. 654 &amp;nbsp;– c. 670), abbot of Iken''.&lt;/ref&gt; in the year that Anna was killed, possibly to commemorate the king.&lt;ref name=&quot;Y70-1&quot;/&gt; Anna was succeeded in turn by his two brothers Æthelhere and [[Æthelwold of East Anglia|Æthelwold]], who may have ruled jointly.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; It is possible that Æthelhere was set up as a puppet ruler by Penda or was his ally, as he was one of the 30 ''duces'' that accompanied Penda when he attacked Oswiu of Northumbria at an unidentified location called the [[Battle of the Winwæd|Winwæd]] in 655 or 656. Penda himself was killed at the Winwæd, after having steadily increased his power over a period of 13 years.&lt;ref&gt;Kirby, ''The Earliest English Kings'', pp. 40, 89.&lt;/ref&gt; Æthelhere (who was also slain at the Battle of the Winwæd) and Æthelwold were succeeded by the descendants of Anna's youngest brother, Æthelric.&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', pp. 68, 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bede praised Anna's piety in his ''Ecclesiastical History of the English People'',&lt;ref&gt;Bede, (edition by Colgrave and Mynors), ''Ecclesiastical History of the English People'', (Book IV, Chapter 19), p. 391.&lt;/ref&gt; and modern historians have since regarded Anna as a devout king,&lt;ref&gt;See for example Fox and Dickens, ''The early cultures of north-west Europe: (H. M. Chadwick memorial studies)'', p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; but his reputation as a devoted Christian is mainly because he produced a son and four daughters who were all made into [[List of Anglo-Saxon saints|Anglo-Saxon saints]].&lt;ref&gt;Hollis, ''Anglo-Saxon Women and the Church'', p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Five hundred years after his death, his tomb at Blythburgh was (according to the ''Liber Eliensis'') still &quot;venerated by the pious devotion of faithful people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fairweather, ''Liber Eliensis: A History of the Isle of Ely from the Seventh Century to the Twelfth, compiled by a Monk of Ely in the Twelfth Century'', p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Descendants==
Anna's children were all canonised.  The eldest, Seaxburh, was the wife of Eorcenberht of Kent. She ruled Kent from 664 until her son [[Ecgberht of Kent|Ecgberht]] came of age. [[Æthelthryth]], according to the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', founded the [[Ely Cathedral|monastery at Ely]] in 673. Another daughter, [[Æthelburh of Faremoutiers|Æthelburh]], spent her life at the nunnery of Faremoutiers. Anna's son, [[Jurmin]], was of warrior age in 653 when he was killed in battle.

By tradition, Anna is said to have had a fourth daughter, [[Wihtburh]], an abbess at [[Dereham]] (or possibly [[West Dereham]]), where there was a royal [[double monastery]].&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Nunneries and the Anglo-Saxon Royal Houses'', p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; She may never have existed: Bede fails to mention her and she first appears in a calendar in the late 10th century ''Bosworth Psalter''.&lt;ref&gt;Bishop and Gaquet, ''The Bosworth Psalter'', p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; She may have been a character specifically created by the religious community at Ely, where her remains were supposed to have been taken after being stolen from Dereham&lt;ref name=&quot;Y70-1&quot;&gt;Yorke, ''Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England'', pp. 70–71.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fryde, et al., ''Handbook of British Chronology'', p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; and subsequently used as visual proof of the incorruptibility of a saint's body, a substitute for her sister Æthelthryth, whose body had to remain unexamined in her tomb.&lt;ref&gt;Raguin and Stanbury, ''Women's Space: Patronage, Place, and Gender in the Medieval Church'', p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; Manuscript F of the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', which dates from about 1100, mentions Wihtburh's death when it records that her body was found uncorrupted in 798, 55 years after she died. The resulting date for her death of 743 is too far too late for her to have been a sister of Æthelthryth, who was born in 636.&lt;ref&gt;Swanton, ''The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', pp. xxvii–xxviii, 56.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Yorke, ''Nunneries and the Anglo-Saxon Royal Houses'', p. 37 (note 11).&lt;/ref&gt;

{{familytree/start |summary=Tytila's descent}}
{{familytree |border=1| | | | | | | | TYT |                  TYT= Tytila of East Anglia}}
{{familytree | | | | | | | | |!| |}}
{{familytree |border=1| | | | | | | | ENI |                  ENI=[[Eni of East Anglia]]|QU3=(?)}}
{{familytree | | | | | | | | |!| | }}
{{familytree | | | | | | |,|-|^|-|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|.|}}
{{familytree |border=1| | | | | |ANN|v|~|SAE| |AEE| |AED| |AEC|             ANN=Anna of East Anglia|SAE=Sæwara|AEE= [[Æthelhere of East Anglia]]|AED= [[Æthelwold of East Anglia]]|AEC=Æthelric
|boxstyle_ANN=background-color: #afa;
}}
{{familytree | | | | | | | | |!| }}
{{familytree | | | | | | |,|-|^|-|v|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|v|~|~|7}}
{{familytree |border=1| |EOR|v|SEA| |AET|-|TON| |AEB| |JUR| |WIH|          SEA=[[Seaxburh of Ely]]|EOR=[[Eorcenberht of Kent]]|TON=1.  Tondberht|AET=[[Æthelthryth]]|AEB=[[Æthelburh of Faremoutiers|Æthelburh]]|JUR=[[Jurmin]]|WIH=[[Wihtburh]]
 }}
{{familytree |border=1| | | | |!| | | | | | | | |ECF| ECF=2. [[Ecgfrith of Northumbria]]}}
{{familytree | | | | |!|}}
{{familytree | | |,|-|^|-|-|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|.|}}
{{familytree |border=1| |ERM|-|WUL| |ERC| |ECG| |HLO|                  ECG= [[Ecgberht of Kent]]|HLO= [[Hlothhere of Kent]]|ERM= [[Ermenilda of Ely|Ermenilda]]|WUL= [[Wulfhere of Mercia]]|ERC= Ercongota}}
{{familytree/end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
'''Primary sources'''
*{{cite book
  | author = Bede
  | authorlink = Bede
  |author2=Bertram Colgrave |author3=R. A. B. Mynors
   | title = Bede: Ecclesiastical History of the English People
  | publisher = Clarendon Press
  | location = Cambridge
  | year = 1992
}}
*{{cite book
  | author = Earle, John
  | authorlink = John Earle (professor)
  | title = Two of the Saxon Chronicles Parallel
  | year = 1865
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=_FUJAAAAQAAJ
  | publisher = Clarendon Press
  | location = Oxford
  | language  = Old English
}}
*{{cite book
  | author = Gaskett, G. A.
  |author2=Bishop, Edmund
  | title = The Bosworth Psalter
  | publisher = George Bell and Sons
  | location = London
  | year = 1908
}}
*{{cite book
  | title = Liber Eliensis: A History of the Isle of Ely from the Seventh Century to the Twelfth, compiled by a Monk of Ely in the Twelfth Century
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=fh5OozghywIC
  | editor = Fairweather, Janet (trans.)
  | publisher = Boydell
  | location = Woodbridge
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 978-1-84383-015-3}}
*{{cite book
  | last = Swanton
  | first = Michael
  | title = The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle
  | year = 1997
  | location = London
  | publisher = Routledge
  | isbn = 0-415-92129-5
}}

'''Secondary sources'''
*{{cite book
  |author=Bishop, Edmund
  |author2=Gasquet, F. A.
  |title=The Bosworth Psalter
  |publisher=George Bell &amp; Sons
  |location=London
  |year=1908
  |url=https://archive.org/stream/bosworthpsalter01tokegoog#page/n116/mode/2up
  }}
*{{cite encyclopedia
 | last = Blair
 | first = John
 | editor-first = Lawrence
 | editor-last = Goldman
 | editor-link = Lawrence Goldman
 | encyclopedia = [[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]]
 | title = Botwulf (fl. 654&amp;nbsp;– c. 670), abbot of Iken
 |date=September 2004
 | publisher = Oxford University Press
 | volume = 10
 | location = Oxford
}}
*{{Cite book
 | last = Dumville
 | first = David
 | author-link = David Dumville
 | year = 1989
 | chapter = Essex, Middle Anglia, and the Expansion of Mercia in the South-East Midlands
 | editor-first = Steven
 | editor-last = Basset
 | title = The Origins of Anglo-Saxon Kingdoms
 | location = London
 | publisher = Leicester University Press
 | pages =123–140
 | isbn = 0-7185-1317-7
}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Fox, Sir Cyril
  |author2=Dickens, Bruce
  |title=The Early Cultures of North-West Europe: (H. M. Chadwick memorial studies)
  |publisher=Cambridge University Press
  |location=Cambridge
  |year=1950
  |authorlink=
  Cyril Fox
}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Fryde, E. B.
  |author2=Greenway, D. E.|author3= Porter, S.|author4= Roy, I.
  |title=Handbook of British Chronology
  |edition=3rd
  |publisher=Cambridge University Press
  |location=Cambridge
  |year=1986
  |isbn=0-521-56350-X
  |page=216
}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Gransden, Antonia
  |authorlink= Antonia Gransden
  |title=Historical Writing in England: c. 500 to c. 1307
  |publisher=Cornell University Press
  |location=Ithaca, New York State
  |year=1974
  |isbn=0-8014-0770-2
  |page=270
}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Hollis
  | first = Stephanie
  | title = Anglo-Saxon Women and the Church
  | publisher = The Boydell Press
  | location = Woodbridge
  | year = 1992
  | isbn = 0-85115-317-8}}
*{{cite book
  |last=Hunter Blair
  |first=Peter
  |editor1-last = Lapidge
  |editor1-first = Michael
  |editor2-last = Gneuss
  |editor2-first = Helmut
  |title=Learning and Literature in Anglo-Saxon England: Studies Presented to Peter Clemoes on the Occasion of his Sixty-Fifth Birthday
  |year=2010
  |publisher=Cambridge University Press
  |location=Cambridge
  |isbn=978-0-521-12871-1
  |chapter=Whitby as a centre of learning in the seventh century}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = James
  | first = M. R.
  | authorlink = M. R. James
  | title = Suffolk and Norfolk: A Perambulation of the Two Counties with Notices of Their History and Their Ancient Buildings
  | publisher = Alastair Press
  | location = Bury St. Edmunds
  | year = 1987
  | origyear = 1930
  | isbn = 1-870567-10-2}}
*{{cite encyclopedia
 | last = Kelly
 | first = S. E.
 | editor = Goldman, Lawrence
 | encyclopedia = [[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]]
 | title = Anna (d. 654?), king of the East Angles
 |date=September 2004
 | publisher = Oxford University Press
 | volume = 1
 | location = Oxford
 | editor-link = Lawrence Goldman
}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Kirby
  | first = D. P.
  | title = The Earliest English Kings
  | publisher = Routledge
  | location = London and New York
  | year = 2000
  | isbn = 0-415-24211-8
}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Lapidge
  | first = Michael
  | title = The Blackwell Encyclopaedia of Anglo-Saxon England
  | publisher = Blackwell
  | location = Oxford
  | year = 2001
  | isbn = 978-0-631-22492-1}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Love
  | first = Rosalind C.
  | title = Goscelin of Saint-Bertin: the Hagiography of the Female Saints of Ely
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location = Oxford
  | year = 2004
  | isbn = 0-19-820815-4}}
*{{Cite book
  | editor = Matthew, Colin
  | editor-link = Colin Matthew
  | title = Oxford Dictionary of National Biography
  | url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/
  | accessdate = 12 March 2011
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location = Oxford
  | year = 2004
  }}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Plunkett
  | first = Steven
  | title = Suffolk in Anglo-Saxon Times
  | publisher = Tempus
  | location = Stroud
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 0-7524-3139-0 }}
*{{Cite book
  | editor1-last  = Raguin
  | editor1-first = Virginia Chieffo
  | editor2-last  = Stanbury
  | editor2-first = Sarah
  | title = Women's Space: Patronage, Place, and Gender in the Medieval Church
  | publisher = State University of New York
  | year = 2005
  | page = 49
  | isbn = 0-7914-6365-6}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Stenton
  | first = Sir Frank
  | authorlink = Frank Stenton
  | title = Anglo-Saxon England
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location = New York
  | year = 1988
  | isbn = 0-19-821716-1}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Warner
  | first = Peter
  | title = The Origins of Suffolk
  | publisher = Manchester University Press
  | location = Manchester and New York
  | year = 1996
  | isbn = 0-7190-3817-0}}
*{{Cite web
  | last = Wessex Archaeology
  | title = ''Blythburgh Priory, Blythburgh, Suffolk, Archaeological Evaluation and Assessment of Results''
  | url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/22056818/Blythburgh-Priory
  | accessdate = 31 May 2010}}
*{{cite journal |last1=West |first1=S. E. |last2=Scarfe  |first2=N. |last3=Cramp |first3=R. J. |year=1984 |title=Iken, St Botolph, and the Coming of East Anglian Christianity |journal=Proc. Suffolk Institute of Archaeology  |volume=15 |pages=279–301 |url=http://www.freightmatters.co.uk/suffolkarch/biblio.html }}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Yorke
  | first = Barbara
  | authorlink = Barbara Yorke
  | title = Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England
  | publisher = Routledge
  | location = London and New York
  | year = 2002
  | isbn = 0-415-16639-X}}
*{{Cite book
  | last = Yorke
  | first = Barbara
  | authorlink = Barbara Yorke
  | title = Nunneries and the Anglo-Saxon Royal Houses
  | publisher = Continuum
  | location = London and New York
  | year = 2003
  | isbn = 0-8264-6040-2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Anglo-Saxon England}}
* {{PASE|10527|Anna 1}}
* [http://www.channel4.com/programmes/time-team/4od#2926753 An episode of ''Time Team'' (Series 16, Episode 13&amp;nbsp;– ''Skeletons in the Shed: Blythburgh, Suffolk'', first broadcast on 29 March 2009)], at http://www.channel4.com, in which the historical association of the village of Blythburgh with Anna is explored.
* {{cite map
 |publisher  = University of Cambridge (Department of Anglo-Saxon, Norse &amp; Celtic)
 |title      = Southern England in the Eighth Century
 |url        = http://www.trin.cam.ac.uk/sdk13/RPMaps/mapOffa.JPG
 ||series     = Maps of Anglo-Saxon England
 |accessdate = 6 June 2011
 }}
*Information about the Blythburgh writing-tablet, now at the British Museum (in London), can be found at the [https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/search_the_collection_database/search_object_details.aspx?objectid=89470&amp;partid=1&amp;output=Places%2f!!%2fOR%2f!!%2f29205%2f!%2f29205-3-2%2f!%2fFound%2fAcquired+Blythburgh%2f!%2f%2f!!%2f%2f!!!%2f&amp;orig=%2fresearch%2fsearch_the_collection_database%2fadvanced_search.aspx&amp;currentPage=1&amp;numpages=10 museum's website].

{{s-start}}
{{s-roy|en}}
{{succession box |
 before=[[Ecgric of East Anglia|Ecgric]] | 
 title=[[Kings of East Anglia|King of East Anglia]] |
 years= possibly early 640s&amp;nbsp;– 653 or 654|
 after=[[Æthelhere of East Anglia|Æthelhere]]
}}
{{s-end}}
{{Kings of East Anglia}}

{{featured article}}

[[Category:650s deaths]]
[[Category:7th-century English monarchs]]
[[Category:Anglo-Saxons killed in battle]]
[[Category:East Anglian monarchs]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:Monarchs killed in action]]
[[Category:House of Wuffingas]]</text>
      <sha1>st2ov1lqe6b9m6kr2x31s3tp90zcedl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
