<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Sio</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20874221</id>
    <revision>
      <id>715737195</id>
      <parentid>709645236</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-17T18:02:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chris the speller</username>
        <id>525927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Sio */replaced: high ranking → high-ranking using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33548">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Sio
|partof=[[World War II]], [[Pacific War]]
|image=[[File:Sio AWM070302.jpeg|300px|alt=Ten men walking in single file though the jungle wearing slouch hats and carrying rifles.]]
|caption=Australian troops of B Company, [[30th Battalion (Australia)|30th Infantry Battalion]] crossing a shallow creek between Weber Point and Malalamai. They have been advancing from Roinji over muddy swamps, Kunai grass and innumerable rivers to link up with American troops at Yagomai.
|date=5 December 1943 – 1 March 1944
|place=[[Sio, Papua New Guinea]]
|result=Allied victory
|combatant1={{flag|Australia}}
*{{flagicon image|Flag of the Territory of Papua.svg}} [[Territory of Papua|Papua]]
{{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flag|Empire of Japan}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Douglas MacArthur]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Australia}} [[Leslie Morshead]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Australia}} [[Frank Berryman]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} [[Hatazō Adachi]]
|strength1=~15,000&lt;ref&gt;9th Division strength returns, December 1943, {{cite web |accessdate=21 November 2015 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1024885--77-.pdf |title=War Diary 9th Division AG Branch, December 1943, Australian War Memorial: AWM52 1/5/21 |page=88}} Includes 1,066 Americans of the 532nd EBSR and 1,712 Papuans. Does not include the 8th Infantry Brigade, or the Finschhafen Base Sub Area.&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2=~8,000&lt;ref&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', p. 228&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1=83 killed, 186 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps&quot;&gt;{{cite web |accessdate=21 November 2015 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1026059--18-.pdf |title=II Corps Report on Operations: October 1943 – March 1944, Australian War Memorial: AWM52 1/4/8 |pages=44, 51–52, 56–57}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=1,421 killed, 2,198 found dead, 76 captured.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps&quot; /&gt;
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Huon Peninsula}}
{{Campaignbox New Guinea}}
}}

The '''Battle of Sio''', fought between December 1943 and March 1944, was the [[Breakout (military)|break-out]] and [[Breakthrough (military)|pursuit]] phase of [[General (United States)|General]] [[Douglas MacArthur]]'s [[Huon Peninsula campaign]], part of the [[New Guinea campaign]] of [[World War II]].

After the defeat of the [[Imperial Japanese Army|Japanese]] in the [[Battle of Sattelberg]], [[Australian Army]] forces broke through the Japanese positions around [[Finschhafen]]. Constant pressure from [[US Navy]] [[PT boats]], Australian land forces and Allied aircraft brought the Japanese logistical system to the brink of collapse, resulting in disease, malnutrition and privation for the Japanese soldiers. Meanwhile, the Allied supply system grappled with the problems of terrain and climate, particularly inclement weather and rough monsoonal seas that hampered and occasionally prevented delivery of supplies by sea.

Australian and Papuan troops advanced along the coast of the [[Huon Peninsula]], using infantry, tanks, and air strikes against the Japanese positions, which were generally sited at creek crossings in the jungle. The advancing infantry kept strictly within range of the supporting artillery, which was liberally employed in the early stages of the operation. Using tactics that exploited the firepower of Australian artillery and armour, the Australian and Papuan troops inflicted heavy and disproportionate casualties on the Japanese as they advanced, ultimately linking up with the American forces at [[Landing at Saidor|Saidor]]. Hundreds of Japanese soldiers were killed; thousands more died from disease, malnutrition, exhaustion and [[suicide]]. The Allies failed to seize the opportunity to completely destroy the Japanese forces.

During the advance, Australian troops captured Japanese [[cryptographic]] materials. This had an important effect on the subsequent course of the war against Japan in the South West Pacific, as it permitted [[cryptanalysis|codebreakers]] in Australia and the United States to read Japanese Army messages on a much greater scale than previously.

==Background==
[[File:The Envelopment of the Huon Peninsula 1943-44.jpg|thumb|right|The Envelopment of the Huon Peninsula 1943–44|alt=map indicating the Allied advance along the coast of New Guinea]]

General Douglas MacArthur's [[Operation Cartwheel]] began with spectacular victories in the [[landing at Lae]] and the [[landing at Nadzab]] but then faltered in the face of inclement weather, unfavourable terrain, and—above all—tenacious and aggressive Japanese opposition on land and in the air.&lt;ref&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', p. 148&lt;/ref&gt; The initiative passed to Major General [[Hatazō Adachi]]'s [[Eighteenth Army (Japan)|Eighteenth Army]] which launched a series of counter-attacks against [[Major General (Australia)|Major General]] [[George Wootten]]'s [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]] in the [[Battle of Finschhafen]].&lt;ref&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', pp. 149–177&lt;/ref&gt; At the [[Battle of Sattelberg]], Wootten finally inflicted a crushing defeat on Adachi.&lt;ref&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;

Although beaten, the Japanese did not leave the area. [[Lieutenant General]] [[Shigeru Katagiri]], the commander of the [[20th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 20th Division]], ordered the [[80th Infantry Regiment (Imperial Japanese Army)|80th Infantry Regiment]] to hold the Wareo area to protect the withdrawal of the [[79th Infantry Regiment (Imperial Japanese Army)|79th Infantry Regiment]] and other units. The 2nd Battalion, [[238th Infantry Regiment (Imperial Japanese Army)|238th Infantry Regiment]] was to act as a rearguard on the coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coates, p. 236&quot;&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lieutenant General (Australia)|Lieutenant General]] [[Frank Berryman]], the commander of [[II Corps (Australia)|Australian II Corps]], now urged Wootten to commence a coastal advance to cut the Japanese supply lines and force Adachi to retreat from the [[Huon Peninsula]] if he were not already doing so. Wootten took a more cautious approach.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coates, pp. 228-229&quot;&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', pp. 228–229&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Battle of Wareo]] proved that the Japanese intended to defend the area. After a fierce fight, Wootten managed to drive the Japanese from the high ground around Sattelberg and Gusika. In early December, Adachi ordered all his troops to withdraw to [[Sio, Papua New Guinea|Sio]]. Wareo was captured by the Australians on 8 December and the last Japanese rearguards left the area on 15 December.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', pp. 675–679&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, Berryman's coastal advance had commenced on 5 December.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coates, pp. 228-229&quot;/&gt;

==Prelude==

===Offensive against the Japanese supply system===
Early in October 1943, a special staff was established at II Corps Headquarters to study the Japanese supply system. It did not include an officer with experience in maintaining a large force over a native [[Porter (carrier)|carrier]] line, and therefore took time to realise that the Japanese force could not be maintained over an inland track, as was first assumed. Operations soon confirmed that the Japanese were dependent on a coastal supply line. During the [[Battle of Sattelberg]], the Allies set out to cut this supply line.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps, pp. 59-60&quot;&gt;{{cite web |accessdate=21 November 2015 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1026059--18-.pdf |title=II Corps Report on Operations: October 1943 – March 1944, Australian War Memorial: AWM52 1/4/8 |pages=59–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; A three-pronged approach was taken:
# Collecting centres for native foodstuffs and tracks leading from the coast were bombed by the US [[Fifth Air Force]]. This reduced food stocks available to the Japanese, and also drove away the native carriers that the Japanese depended on to carry their supplies up from the coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps, pp. 59-60&quot;/&gt;
# [[PT boat]]s of Task Group 70.1 attempted to interdict barge traffic along the coast by night, while Fifth Air Force fighters conducted sweeps for barges by day.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps, pp. 59-60&quot;/&gt;
# The land forces attempted to physically cut the Japanese supply lines. The 9th Division captured Pabu, thereby cutting the most convenient inland track,&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps, pp. 59-60&quot;/&gt; while the [[landing at Long Island]] occupied an important barge staging area.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 731&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:PT boat New Guinea 1943.jpg|thumb|left|A PT boat patrols off New Guinea, 1943|alt=Silhouette of a boat moving at speed across the water.]]
By December, the pitiful condition of Japanese prisoners confirmed for the Australians that &quot;the Japanese logistic system was in the final stages of breakdown&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coates, p. 236&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps, pp. 59-60&quot;/&gt; Between 9 and 13 December, PT boats sank 23 barges, most of them south of Sio.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p727&quot; /&gt; On 7 January, the PT boats also attacked a submarine. No less than twelve barges were destroyed on the night of 8 January, one of which was loaded with ammunition and another with around 70 troops. On 9 January, PT boats attacked a group of six barges, which attempted to fight back. One barge was seen to sink. Another patrol engaged eight barges and destroyed two. A third patrol found six barges on a beach and destroyed them. Then on 10 January, three PT boats sank three troop-carrying barges, taking one Japanese prisoner. The same night, two barges were also sunk north of Sio Island.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p734&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 734&lt;/ref&gt; When General Berryman saw [[Vice admiral (United States)|Vice Admiral]] [[Thomas C. Kinkaid]], the commander of the Allied Naval Forces, on 14 December, he made a point of congratulating him on the work his PT boats were doing.&lt;ref&gt;Berryman diary, 14 December 1943, Australian War Memorial: AWM93 50/2/23/331&lt;/ref&gt;

Lieutenant General Tsutomu Yoshihara, Chief of Staff of the Japanese Eighteenth Army recalled:
{{quote|At this time the air at 20th Division H.Q. was one of fatigue. The troops, short of food and ammunition, were searching for vegetables left in the native gardens around them and were so hungry they were eating banana and pawpaw roots. Since these abandoned gardens were right in the front line or inside the enemy's positions, the troops penetrated the enemy positions to obtain vegetables. And they fought exposed to the enemy shells, committing their bodies to trenches in which the rain of days after days had accumulated.

So the fact that 20th Division was not able to fulfil the idea of its activities were not 20th Division's fault, but ours. With this poverty of supply it made no difference how brave they were; it was a case of &quot;An army marches on its stomach&quot;.

Hereupon, as an emergency measure, the Army began to use auxiliary fishing boats from Hansa for transport round the coast of New Guinea; from Hansa, via Karka, Bagubagu, Long [Island...] the transport began and so a direct supply line to Sio was established.

This daring transport was conspicuously successful and brought great rejoicing to the officers and men of 20th Division. It was amazing the courageous deeds these fishing fleets did in the skilful hands of the shipping engineers. With no training, no equipment the captains and crews of these fishing boats braved the front line of the fighting and all the dangerous places, saying, &quot;We are immortal. Bring on your arrows or your guns.&quot; When attacked by enemy aircraft, they bravely engaged them and miraculously shot them down. However, this secret transport did not long remain hidden from enemy eyes. With the passage of time they were spotted, and their bases were demolished by bombing and the transport unfortunately ceased.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yoshihara&quot;&gt;{{citation |last=Yoshihara |first=Kane |url=http://ajrp.awm.gov.au/ajrp/AJRP2.nsf/pages/NT00007E8E?openDocument |title=Southern Cross |accessdate=16 December 2010 |publisher=Australian War Memorial }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Tactics and logistics===
[[File:Matilda AWM071377.jpeg|thumb|right|A [[Matilda II|Matilda tank]] of A Squadron, 1st Tank Battalion, fires at a Japanese foxhole.|alt=A tank fires into the jungle.]]
The main Australian advance was by [[infantry]]-[[tank]]-[[Military engineer|engineer]] teams moving along the coastal tracks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coates_p243&quot;&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', p. 243&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese positions were generally sited at creek crossings in the [[jungle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;9Div&quot;&gt;{{cite web |accessdate=21 November 2015 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1023730--43-.pdf |title=Report on Operations – 9 Aust Div: Operations from December 1943 – January 1944, Australian War Memorial: AWM52 1/5/20 |pages=25–30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The advancing infantry kept strictly within range of the supporting artillery, except for short periods during the latter stages of the operation when Japanese opposition was negligible and the difficulty of moving the artillery forward quickly was too great.&lt;ref name=&quot;5Div&quot;&gt;''Report on Operations – 5 Aust Div: Operations from Sio to Saidor 20 January – 29 February 1944'', Australian War Memorial: AWM54 519/6/48&lt;/ref&gt; A secondary outflanking movement was made inland, over the higher ground, which was usually [[coral]] cliffs covered by [[Imperata cylindrica|kunai grass]] and rising as high as {{convert|4000|ft|m}}. Since the Japanese intent was to delay rather than fight to the death, a threat to their escape route usually prompted a withdrawal. When this did not occur, the position was reduced by a combination of manoeuvre and tank, mortar, and artillery fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coates_p243&quot; /&gt; During the early part of the advance, 4,700 rounds were fired in one day;&lt;ref name=&quot;9Div&quot; /&gt; but during the entire 5th Division advance from Sio to Saidor, only 30 rounds were fired. The advance was made in a series of bounds, the objective of which was usually to secure sheltered beachheads.&lt;ref name=&quot;5Div&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Sio AWM070049.jpeg|thumb|left|An LCM of the 532nd EBSR ferries men of the 30th Infantry Battalion from Kelanoa to Sio|alt=About forty troops wearing slouch hats and carrying rifles packed into a landing craft travelling across open water, viewed from the stern towards the bow ramp.]]
Allied supply was entirely by sea. Amphibian scouts from the US 532nd Engineer Boat and Shore Regiment (EBSR) of the [[Engineer Special Brigade (United States)|US 2nd Engineer Special Brigade]], wearing Australian uniforms,&lt;ref&gt;Casey, ''Amphibian Engineer Operations'', p. 97&lt;/ref&gt; advanced with the infantry and reconnoitred beaches from the landward side as they were secured. If a beach looked suitable, a second reconnaissance was made from the sea. Once a beach was selected, a shore party was brought in by landing craft to set up an administrative area. Engineers improved the coastal track to enable supplies to units moving along it to be brought up by [[jeep]]s but supplies for units moving inland over the high ground had to be brought by native carriers. Artillery guns were brought forward over the tracks, or else were moved by [[Landing Craft Mechanised]] (LCMs) of the 532nd EBSR. Tanks normally moved along the tracks but used LCMs to bypass obstacles. As the advance continued, new beachheads were opened up while rearward ones were closed. The advance was halted on occasion to allow for the guns to be brought forward or sufficient supplies to be accumulated at the forward beachhead.&lt;ref name=&quot;9Div&quot; /&gt;

The major problem was the weather. The [[monsoon]] caused rough seas that precluded the use of the small [[Landing Craft, Vehicle, Personnel]] (LCVPs) and restricted the operations of the larger LCMs. Because of the extremely rough seas—the most difficult that the 532nd EBSR had ever encountered—most supply missions were by night when tidal conditions were most favourable.&lt;ref&gt;''Monthly Historical Report of Operations – 2d ESB, January 1944'', [[U.S. Army Corps of Engineers]]: X-78 E-20-1&lt;/ref&gt; Wootten insisted that at least seven days' supplies be available in forward areas in case the weather prevented the LCMs from running. II Corps made available two trawlers, manned by the 1st Water Transport Group, to deliver rations. The Australian Army also moved supplies by [[DUKW]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;9Div&quot; /&gt;

==Battle==

===Fortification Point===
[[File:Fortification Point.PNG|thumb|4th Infantry Brigade advance to Fortification Point, 5–20 December 1943|alt=map of New Guinea coast with arrows indicating route taken by the Australian advance.]]
Wootten designated [[Brigadier]] C. R. V. Edgar's [[4th Brigade (Australia)|4th Infantry Brigade]], a [[Australian Army Reserve|Militia]] formation, for the initial phase of the coastal advance, reserving his veteran [[Second Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] brigades for the [[Battle of Wareo]]. The brigade consisted of the [[22nd Battalion (Australia)|22nd]] and [[29th/46th Battalion (Australia)|29th/46th]] Infantry Battalions from [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] and the [[37th/52nd Battalion (Australia)|37th/52nd Infantry Battalion]] from [[Tasmania]].&lt;ref&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', p. 241&lt;/ref&gt; Each battalion was allotted a team of advisors from the 9th Division.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coates_p243&quot;/&gt; Under Edgar's command was C Squadron, 1st Tank Battalion, with seven [[Matilda II|Matilda tank]]s, 9th Platoon, C Company, [[Royal Pacific Islands Regiment|Papuan Infantry Battalion]], and detachments from the 532nd EBSR, [[Australian New Guinea Administrative Unit]] (ANGAU), [[Royal Australian Army Service Corps|Australian Army Service Corps]] (AASC) and [[Royal Australian Army Medical Corps|Australian Army Medical Corps]] (AAMC). In support were the [[sappers]] of the 2/7th Field Company and the 24 [[25-pounder]]s of the 2/6th Field Regiment. In case Edgar got into trouble, the [[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Infantry Brigade]] was in reserve, on six hours notice.&lt;ref name=&quot;9Div&quot; /&gt;

To support the advance, a beach maintenance area was prepared at a beach at the mouth of the Kalueng River, which involved removing underwater and landward obstacles. So that the tanks and jeeps could immediately support the advance, a bridge was required over the Kalueng River. A preliminary operation by the 22nd Infantry Battalion on 3 December 1943 secured a crossing area and a log bridge was constructed.&lt;ref name=&quot;9Div&quot; /&gt; The operation jumped off on 5 December, with the 29th/46th Infantry Battalion passing through the bridgehead established by the 22nd. It soon came under sporadic enemy fire, and a tank was disabled by a land mine.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 714&lt;/ref&gt; In the face of mounting opposition, the advance was halted near the lagoon. It resumed the next day, and the Japanese withdrew after an artillery bombardment, their orders being &quot;while avoiding any decisive engagement&quot; to &quot;carry out successful resistance to try to delay the enemy advance&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p715&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 715&lt;/ref&gt; This became the pattern, with the Japanese preferring to withdraw rather than suffer heavy casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p718&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 718&lt;/ref&gt; On 10 December, Edgar brought all three of his battalions into the line and by 14 December they were closing in on Lakona, a key position on the 20th Division's retreat route.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p722&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 722&lt;/ref&gt;

The tanks had difficulty keeping up with the advance. One obstacle was mines. On the first day, the 2/7th Field Company lifted fourteen mines but a tractor broke a track running over a mine. On 7 December, two more tanks were damaged by mines, one beyond repair. The sappers then cut a new track which they [[Corduroy road|corduroyed]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p716&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 716&lt;/ref&gt; To support the attack on Lakona, the tanks had to cross a creek with steep coral banks, swollen by a torrential downpour. While efforts were made to bring up a compressor, tanks fired into banks and holes were packed with explosives and detonated. On the evening of 16 December, the infantry were joined by five Matilda tanks, and overran the Japanese positions. They counted 47 Japanese dead; and killed another 17 in mopping-up operations the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p722–724&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', pp. 722–724&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 December, aided by four Matilda tanks and 750 rounds from the 25-pounders, the 4th Infantry Brigade occupied the Fortification Point area. Between 5 and 20 December, the&amp;nbsp;4th Infantry Brigade reported 65 killed and 136 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p725&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 725&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese casualties were 420 killed and 136 found dead, victims of disease, malnutrition and suicide. Only six Japanese prisoners were taken.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps&quot; /&gt;

===Sio===
On 21 December 1943, the 20th Infantry Brigade passed through the 4th Infantry Brigade and initiated the second stage of the pursuit. Generals [[Thomas Blamey|Blamey]], Berryman and Wootten visited the acting brigade commander, [[Lieutenant Colonel]] N. W. Simpson, and emphasised that the brigade was to minimise casualties where possible by employing artillery and tanks. That afternoon, the lead company of the 2/13th Infantry Battalion reached Hubika.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p727&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 727&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion diarist recorded: {{quote|Hubika Creek was an indescribable scene. Naked enemy dead everywhere. Evidently used as a dressing station. Forty dead in one small cave. None had been buried. The area was foul and nauseating.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p728&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 728&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Map Fortification Pt - Sio.PNG|thumb|left|Coastal Advance 21 December 1943 – 15 January 1944|alt=map of New Guinea coast with arrows indicating route taken by the Australian advance.]]
A halt was called for Christmas while supplies were brought up. Units had a rest day. Most dined on turkey, ham, roast potatoes and [[Christmas pudding]], and Christmas services were held. General Blamey insisted that Christmas fare be available to all units, and extraordinary efforts were made to carry out his directive. In one instance, a [[Piper J-3|Piper Cub]] of [[No. 4 Squadron RAAF]] dropped Christmas fare to a Papuan Company on a long range patrol.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p729&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 729&lt;/ref&gt; The advance resumed on 27 December, preceded by air strikes by 18 [[B-25 Mitchell]] and 12 [[Douglas A-20 Havoc|Boston]] bombers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p729&quot; /&gt; The [[2/15th Battalion (Australia)|2/15th Infantry Battalion]] and tanks of A Squadron, 1st Tank Battalion took the lead on 31 December; they reached Sialum on 2 January 1944. This had a sheltered beach which served as a maintenance area. That day, the American [[landing at Saidor]] placed a large force across the Japanese escape route.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p730&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 730&lt;/ref&gt;

Before moving over the mountains, the 20th Division headquarters elected to destroy its cryptographic materials rather than carry them. As the wet weather made burning them page by page a slow and difficult process, and a fire might attract the attention of the Allied Air Forces, someone decided to simply bury them in a steel trunk in a stream bed. An Australian [[sapper]] checking the stream bed for booby traps with a [[metal detector]] discovered it, and it was dug up in the belief that it was a mine. An intelligence officer recognised the contents as code books and soon it was on its way to the [[Central Bureau]] in [[Brisbane]]. There, the pages were carefully dried out and photographed. On 4 February 1944, Central Bureau codebreakers decrypted a thirteen-part message that laid out the decisions reached at a conference of high-ranking Japanese officers. Copies of the material were quickly sent to [[Arlington Hall]]. In January 1944, Arlington Hall had decrypted 1,846 Japanese army messages. In March 1944, with the Sio code books in hand, it decrypted 36,000 messages.&lt;ref&gt;Drea, ''MacArthur's Ultra'', pp. 92–93&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 January a platoon of the [[2/17th Battalion (Australia)|2/17th Infantry Battalion]] replaced a rope ladder, and after climbing it and two wooden ladders reached an area atop a cliff which had once been a Japanese headquarters. It would have been a formidable position if defended, but it was not. The main body of the battalion followed the next day. The Goaling River was crossed in small boats left behind by the Japanese on 13 January and it entered Nambariwa, where one prisoner was taken, six Japanese were shot, and nine found dead. On 15 January, Sio was taken. The Sio-Nambariwa area was found to have been the principal Japanese supply area, and a large number of fuel, supply, and stores dumps were found.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', pp. 735–736&lt;/ref&gt; During the advance from Fortification Point to Sio, 303 Japanese had been killed or found dead, and 22 captured. The 20th Infantry Brigade had lost 3 killed and 13 wounded, but 958 had been evacuated sick, mostly with [[malaria]], and an epidemic of [[dengue]] had also taken its toll. Large quantities of Japanese equipment had been captured, including six [[Type 41 75 mm Mountain Gun|75 mm guns]], three [[Type 11 37 mm Infantry Gun|37 mm guns]] and three [[Type 2 20 mm AA Machine Cannon|20 mm guns]].&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 736&lt;/ref&gt;

===Saidor===
[[File:Bengari AWM075165.jpeg|thumb|right|upright|Sergeant Bengari, MM of A Company, Papuan Infantry Battalion. He is carrying an [[Owen gun]].|alt=A bare-footed man with a short back and sides haircut wearing an army shirt and short skirt, carrying a weapon on a shoulder strap.]]
At 1800 on 20 January 1944, the headquarters of Major General A. H. Ramsay's [[5th Division (Australia)|5th Division]], which had come up from [[Lae]], replaced that of the 9th Division. At the same time the [[8th Brigade (Australia)|8th Infantry Brigade]] replaced the 20th.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps&quot; /&gt; The 8th Infantry Brigade, which had spent much of the war on garrison duty in Western Australia, began departing [[Cairns]] on 10 January.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/bundled/RCDIG1021526.pdf |title=War Diary, 8th Infantry Brigade, 10 January 1944, AWM52 8/2/8 |accessdate=21 November 2015|publisher=Australian War Memorial |page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original intention had been for it to go to Lae to relieve the 29th Infantry Brigade, which had fought in the [[Salamaua-Lae campaign]], but in December it was decided to ship it directly to Finschhafen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |accessdate=21 November 2015 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1026254--46-.pdf |title=War Diary, New Guinea Force, 6 December 1943, AWM52 1/5/51|publisher=Australian War Memorial |page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade contained three infantry battalions, the [[4th Battalion (Australia)|4th]], [[30th Battalion (Australia)|30th]] and [[35th Battalion (Australia)|35th]], all from [[New South Wales]]. It also still had the support of the 2/12th Field Regiment, 532nd EBSR, and A Company, Papuan Infantry Battalion. The brigade suffered its first casualties on the night of 21/22 January in a [[friendly fire]] incident, which was a common occurrence with units inexperienced in [[jungle warfare]]. Two Australians were killed and two wounded by their own comrades.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 764&lt;/ref&gt;

On 22 January a native reported seeing seven Japanese in the hills south west of Sio and a patrol was sent out under [[Corporal]] Bengari to investigate. On arriving in the vicinity on 24 January, a local reported that another 22 Japanese had arrived. The next morning, Bengari and his five companions ambushed the Japanese and killed them all before they could fire a shot.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 765&lt;/ref&gt; [[CAC Wirraway|Wirraway]] and [[CAC Boomerang|Boomerang]] aircraft of No. 4 Squadron RAAF scouted ahead of the advance. Its aerial reconnaissance work let the Australians and Papuans know where opposition could be expected, thereby speeding up the advance. The pilots noted Japanese parachutes, signs that the Japanese were receiving supplies by air.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p766&quot;&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 766&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 February, the Australians were also forced onto air supply, as swollen rivers washed out a number of bridges.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 767&lt;/ref&gt;

Each day the Papuans killed 12 to 15 Japanese,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dexter_p766&quot; /&gt; but not until 8 February was the Japanese rearguard encountered at Weber Point and a formal attack made. Five Japanese were killed. In all, 53 Japanese were killed and four captured that day. Two Australians were wounded. The next day another 61 Japanese were killed and 9 captured, this time without any Australian casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/bundled/RCDIG1021526.pdf |accessdate=21 November 2015 |title=8th Infantry Brigade Report on Operations, 21 February 1944, War Diary, 8th Infantry Brigade, January 1944, AWM52 8/2/8|publisher=Australian War Memorial |page=78}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 10 February, the 30th Infantry Battalion encountered two American soldiers at Yagomai, thereby linking up with the American force at Saidor.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 769&lt;/ref&gt;

The 8th Infantry Brigade now began to mop up the area. On 18 February, the 35th Infantry Battalion attacked a Japanese force near Gabutamon, killing 40. Finding a force of about 100 Japanese at nearby Tapen, they attacked, killing another 52 Japanese for the loss of one man wounded, while the Papuans on their flanks killed another 51, of whom 43 were accounted for by Corporal Bengari and two other Papuans. The next day, the Papuans found and killed another 39 Japanese in the vicinity. At Tapen, the Australians and Papuans also found evidence that the Japanese had resorted to [[cannibalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', p. 770&lt;/ref&gt; In the period of 20 January – 1 March 1944, 734 Japanese were killed, 1,775 found dead and 48 were captured. Australian casualties came to four killed and six wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;II Corps&quot; /&gt;

==Aftermath==
Both sides managed to accomplish their objectives; the Japanese withdrew, while the Australians exacted a terrible toll. The balance of losses was overwhelmingly against the Japanese, both in terms of men and equipment. It seems that only about 4,300 of the 7,000 troops under the command of the [[20th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 20th Division]] who had originally been forward of Sio survived the withdrawal, and many of them were rendered ineffective through wounds, sickness, malnutrition and exhaustion.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter, ''The New Guinea Offensives'', pp. 732–737&lt;/ref&gt; The opportunity to destroy the [[51st Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 51st Division]] was not seized. These troops lived to fight the Americans at the [[Battle of Driniumor River]] later in the year, and the Australians in the [[Aitape–Wewak campaign]] in 1945. On the other hand, the new base at Finschhafen was no longer threatened by the Japanese, and became an important staging point for the [[Western New Guinea campaign]]. The capture of the Japanese ciphers at Sio allowed General MacArthur to carry out [[Operations Reckless and Persecution]] with a plan based upon sound intelligence rather than just his own intuition.&lt;ref&gt;Coates, ''Bravery Above Blunder'', pp. 254–255&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |editor-last=Casey |editor-first=H. J. |editor-link=Hugh John Casey |series=Engineers of the Southwest Pacific 1941–1945 |title=Volume IV: Amphibian Engineer Operations |location=Washington, DC |publisher=Government Printing Office |year=1959 |isbn= |oclc=220327009}}
* {{cite book |last=Coates |first=John |authorlink=John Coates (general)|title=Bravery Above Blunder: The 9th Division at Finschhafen, Sattelberg and Sio |location=Singapore |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1999 |isbn= 0-19-550837-8 |oclc=43736921}}
* {{cite book|last=Dexter|first=David|title=The New Guinea Offensives| series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1—Army. Volume VI|year=1961|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070205/|oclc=2028994}}
* {{cite book |last=Drea |first=Edward J. |title=MacArthur's Ultra: Codebreaking and the War Against Japan 1942–1945 |location=Lawrence, Kansas |publisher=University Press of Kansas |year=1992 |isbn= 0-7006-0504-5 |oclc=23651196}}
{{Refend}}

{{featured article}}
{{Coord|5|55|S|147|19|E|type:city|name=Sio|display=title}}
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Use Australian English|date=September 2013}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Sio, Battle Of}}
[[Category:1943 in Papua New Guinea]]
[[Category:1944 in Papua New Guinea]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Papua New Guinea]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Australia]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1943]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Operation Cartwheel]]
[[Category:South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]</text>
      <sha1>liz0hmrj0buy2hcqvr9gsqiqeijhovz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
