<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Radzymin (1920)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33386061</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746668770</id>
      <parentid>729398321</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T20:20:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="60525">{{infobox military conflict
|conflict    =Battle of Radzymin
|partof      =the [[Polish–Soviet War]]
|image       =[[File:The fighting near Radzymin.jpg|300px|alt=A group of six soldiers in Polish Army's uniforms in a trench | Polish infantry in a trench near Radzymin]]
|caption     =Polish infantry in a trench outside Radzymin. The soldier in the centre wears an [[Adrian helmet]], while the rest have [[maciejówka (cap)|maciejówka]] caps inherited from the [[Polish Legions in First World War|Polish Legions]]
|date        =August 13–16, 1920
|place       =Near [[Radzymin]], Poland
|coordinates ={{coord|52|25|0|N|21|11|0|E|region:PL_type:event|display=inline,title}}
|territory   =
|result      =Polish victory
|status      =
|combatant1  ={{flag|Russian SFSR|1918}}
|combatant2  ={{flag|Poland|1918}}
|commander1  =[[Vitovt Putna]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ivan Smolin]]
|commander2  =[[Jan Rządkowski]]&lt;br&gt;[[Józef Haller]]&lt;br&gt;[[Franciszek Latinik]]
|units1      =[[21st Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|21st Rifle Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[27th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|27th Rifle Division]]
|units2      =[[10th Infantry Division (Poland)|10th Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[11th Infantry Division (Poland)|11th Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[1st Lithuanian–Belarusian Division|1st Lithuanian-Belarusian Division]]{{cref2|a|1}}
|strength1   =15,000 soldiers&lt;br&gt;91 artillery pieces&lt;br&gt;390 machine guns&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-ros&quot;/&gt;
|strength2   =17,000 soldiers&lt;br&gt;109 artillery pieces&lt;br&gt;220 machine guns&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-pol&quot;/&gt;
|casualties1 =Heavy&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski&quot;/&gt;
|casualties2 =ca. 3,040 killed and wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski&quot;/&gt;
|notes       =
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Battle of Warsaw (1920)}}&lt;br&gt;{{Campaignbox Polish–Soviet War}}
}}
The '''Battle of Radzymin''' ({{lang-pl|Bitwa pod Radzyminem}}) took place during the [[Polish–Soviet War]] (1919–21). The battle occurred near the town of [[Radzymin]], some {{convert|20|km|mi}} north-east of [[Warsaw]], between August 13 and 16, 1920. Along with the [[Battle of Ossów]] and the Polish counteroffensive from the [[Wieprz River]] area, this engagement was a key part of what later became known as the [[Battle of Warsaw (1920)|Battle of Warsaw]]. It also proved to be one of the bloodiest and most intense battles of the [[Polish-Soviet War]].

The first phase of the battle began on August 13 with a frontal assault by the [[Red Army]] on the [[Praga]] bridgehead. The Soviet forces captured Radzymin on August 14 and breached the lines of the [[First Polish Army (1920)|1st Polish Army]], which was defending Warsaw from the east. Radzymin changed hands several times in heavy combat. Foreign [[diplomat]]s, with the exception of the [[United Kingdom|British]] and [[Holy See|Vatican]] ambassadors, hastily left Warsaw.

The plan for the battle was straightforward for both sides. The Russians wanted to break through the Polish defences to Warsaw, while the Polish aim was to defend the area long enough for a two-pronged counteroffensive from the south, led by [[generał|General]] [[Józef Piłsudski]], and north, led by General [[Władysław Sikorski]], to outflank the attacking forces.

After three days of intense fighting, the [[corps]]-sized 1st Polish Army under General [[Franciszek Latinik]] managed to repel a direct assault by six Red Army rifle [[infantry division|division]]s at Radzymin and Ossów. The struggle for control of Radzymin forced General [[Józef Haller]], commander of the [[Polish Northern Front (1920)|Polish Northern Front]], to start the 5th Army's counterattack earlier than planned. Radzymin was recaptured on August 15, and this victory proved to be one of the turning points of the battle of Warsaw. The strategic counteroffensive was successful, pushing Soviet forces away from Radzymin and Warsaw and eventually crippling four Soviet armies.

== Background ==
{{main article|Battle of Warsaw (1920)}}
Following the failure of the [[Kiev Offensive]], the Polish armies retreated westwards from central Belarus and Ukraine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski-1999-235&quot;/&gt; Although the Bolshevik forces failed to surround or destroy the bulk of the [[Polish Army]], most Polish units were in dire need of fresh reinforcements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski-1999-235&quot;/&gt; The Polish command hoped to halt the advancing Russian forces in front of Warsaw, the capital of Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-zadanie&quot;/&gt; At the same time General (later [[Marshal of Poland]]) Józef Piłsudski was to lead a flanking manoeuvre from the area of the [[Wieprz]] River, while General Władysław Sikorski's 5th Army was to leave the [[Modlin Fortress]] and head north-east, to cut off the Soviet forces heading westwards, to the north of the bend of the [[Vistula]] and [[Bugonarew]] and on towards [[Pomerania]]. However, for this plan to succeed, it was vital that Polish forces hold Warsaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jędrzejewicz&quot;/&gt;

=== Prelude ===
The defence of Warsaw was organised by the 1st Polish Army under General Franciszek Latinik and by a part of the Northern Front under General [[Józef Haller de Hallenburg|Józef Haller]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-sklad&quot;/&gt; The army consisted of four understrength infantry divisions: the [[8th Infantry Division (Poland)|8th]], [[11th Infantry Division (Poland)|11th]], and [[15th Infantry Division (Poland)|15th]], with the [[1st Lithuanian-Belarusian Division]] in reserve.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-sklad&quot;/&gt; In addition, it had at its disposal the battle-weary [[10th Infantry Division (Poland)|10th Infantry Division]], two Air Groups (four [[escadrille]]s in total), 293 pieces of artillery and three [[armoured train]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-sklad&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Battle of Warsaw - Phase 1 - en.svg|thumb|left|upright=1.4|alt=Map showing Central Poland and southern part of East Prussia, with arrows showing main Russian and Polish attacks | First phase of the [[Battle of Warsaw (1920)|Russian assault on Warsaw]]]]
The city was to be surrounded by four lines of defence. The outermost ran some {{convert|24|km|mi}} to the east of Warsaw: to the east of [[Zegrze Fortress]], then along the river [[Rządza]] to [[Stary Dybów|Dybów]] and south through Helenów, Nowa Czarna and the Białe Błota [[marshes]] east of [[Wołomin]]. From there it ran through [[Leśniakowizna]], dense forests occupied by artillery training grounds, and then along the [[Okuniew]]–[[Wiązowna]]&amp;ndash;Vistula line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-pierwsze&quot;/&gt;

The second line ran a mile closer to Warsaw, along the lines of partially preserved [[First World War]]-era trenches built by German and Russian armies in 1915, separated by a [[no man's land]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski-72&quot;/&gt; It ran from the banks of the river Bugonarew at [[Fort Beniaminów]], along the [[Struga]]&amp;ndash;[[Zielonka]]&amp;ndash;[[Rembertów]]-[[Zakręt, Otwock County|Zakręt]]&amp;ndash;[[Falenica]] line. The two most prominent pivots of this line were the towns of Radzymin and Wołomin. The third line of defence ran in the immediate vicinity of the right-bank borough of Praga, while the Vistula River [[bridgehead]]s formed the final fourth line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-1-55&quot;/&gt;

The [[11th Infantry Division (Poland)|11th Polish Infantry Division]] was dispatched to Radzymin  on August 8 in order to prepare the city's defences for the expected arrival of Bolshevik forces. While the unit's core was formed around veterans of the 2nd Polish Rifle Division of the French-equipped and trained [[Blue Army (Poland)|Blue Army]], it had been recently reinforced with fresh, but raw, recruits. The Poles set up defences in front of the town, utilising some earlier German and Russian First World War trenches and digging new positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski-72&quot;/&gt; The Polish line ran some {{convert|2|km|mi}} in front of the town, from the unfinished 1909 Fort Beniaminów at the banks of the river Bugonarew through [[Mokre, Masovian Voivodeship|Mokre]] to Dybów. The following day the [[6th Rifle Division (Russia)|6th Russian Rifle Division]] captured [[Wyszków]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski-17&quot;/&gt; some {{convert|30|km|mi}} to the north-east. On August 12 the Polish [[1st Lithuanian–Belarusian Division]] abandoned the first line of defence and withdrew through Radzymin towards Warsaw. Radzymin now found itself at the front line; by nightfall the first Russian forces appeared in front of [[Ruda, Wołomin County|Ruda]] and [[Zawady, Wołomin County|Zawady]], two villages manned by the Polish 48th Infantry Regiment, and Russian artillery shelled Radzymin for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolatorski-12&quot;/&gt;

=== Battlefield ===
From the north, Warsaw, which spans the Vistula, was effectively shielded by the Vistula, [[Bug River|Bug]] and [[Narew]] rivers. The Red Army's lack of modern engineering equipment for the river crossings inhibited a flanking attack of Warsaw from the west, which had been Russia's historical path of attack,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wandycz-116&quot;/&gt; towards [[Płock]], [[Włocławek]] and [[Toruń]], where their forces could cross the Vistula and strike Warsaw from the west and north-west over permanent bridges there. While a ring of 19th- and early 20th-century Russian-built forts, part of the [[Warsaw Fortress]], ran mostly along the western side of the Vistula,&lt;ref name=&quot;Królikowski-36&quot;/&gt; these fortifications lay in ruins; Russian forces began demolition in 1909 and had destroyed most by the time of [[Great Retreat (Russian)|their withdrawal from Warsaw]] in 1915, during the [[First World War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Królikowski-36&quot;/&gt;{{cref2|g|1}}

The most expedient approach for a large-scale assault on Warsaw was from the east. Terrain was mostly flat; numerous roads converged radially along an arc from the [[Modlin Fortress]] to the north (where the Narew flows into the Vistula), to [[Legionowo]], Radzymin, and [[Mińsk Mazowiecki]] directly to the east.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikorski-2&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, the only permanent defences in the area of Radzymin were the incomplete Fort Beniaminów and a line of First World War trenches west of Radzymin, neglected since their construction by Russians and Germans in 1915.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski-72&quot;/&gt;

=== Opposing forces ===
[[File:Kosynierzy 1920.JPG|thumb|right|300px|alt=A black and white picture of a large group of men marching towards the camera, most of them dressed in civilian clothes and armbands, presumably in colours of the Polish national flag. The men carry long war scythes. To their right a large crowd of civilians.|Although 105,714 people joined the ''[[Volunteer Army (Poland)|Volunteer Army]]'' in the summer of 1920,&lt;ref name=&quot;Manteuffel-370&quot;/&gt; there were barely any weapons for the regular Polish Army units. Thus many regular regiments received reinforcements armed with nothing more than [[war scythe]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pruszynski-238&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolikowski-66&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradziński-156&quot;/&gt;]]
The first and second lines of Polish defences were manned by regular forces. These included three Polish infantry divisions: the 11th (from the Bug River to [[Leśniakowizna]]), the 8th (Leśniakowizna to Okuniew) and the 15th (Okuniew to the Vistula River). The 1st Army also held the newly arrived 1st Lithuanian-Belarusian Division in reserve ([[Marki]]–[[Kobyłka]]),{{cref2|a|1}} while the Northern Front's headquarters reserves consisted of the 10th Infantry Division and some smaller units. The third line was manned by units of mobilised [[Policja|State Police]] and a variety of volunteer units of low combat value. Out of those units, initially only the 11th Division under Colonel Bolesław Jaźwiński took part in the fight. Its 48th ''Kresy Rifles'' Regiment (Colonel Łukowski) manned the Bugonarew-Mokre line, the 46th ''Kaniów Rifles'' Regiment (Colonel Krzywobłocki) manned the Mokre-Czarna perimeter, and the 47th ''Kresy Rifles'' Regiment ([[podpułkownik|Lt. Colonel]] Szczepan) manned the [[Czarna, Lublin Voivodeship|Czarna]]–[[Leśniakowizna]] line. To the south of the 11th Division were positions around Wołomin manned by the 8th Infantry Division, consisting of the 36th, 21st and 33rd Infantry Regiments, as well as the 13th Infantry Regiment held in reserve, which later took part in the Battle of Ossów.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kowalski&quot;/&gt;

The combat value of Polish units is difficult to assess as they included fresh recruits of the so-called Volunteer Army, veterans of First World War, battle-hardened soldiers who fought in earlier stages of the Polish-Bolshevik War, and civilians with virtually no combat training. Prior to the battle the 46th Regiment received 700 reinforcements: mostly [[deserter]]s from various formations, a battalion of volunteer [[sentry guard]]s and [[march battalion|march companies]] of [[sapper]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tarczynski&quot;/&gt; The 11th Infantry Division, nominally 9000 men strong, in practice had only 1500 soldiers in first-line units.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-atak&quot;/&gt; The situation for the Polish Army was so dire that some of the soldiers sent as reinforcements had reportedly &quot;never seen a rifle in their lives&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pruszynski&quot;/&gt; In addition, most units to make a stand at Radzymin were exhausted after surviving a {{convert|600|km|mi|adj=on}} retreat from Belarus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-21&quot;/&gt; However, the Polish side had superior intelligence and [[Air supremacy|aerial superiority]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gałęzowski-27&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-24&quot;/&gt;{{cref2|d|1}}

The two Russian divisions assaulting Radzymin were battle-hardened Siberian divisions led by experienced front-line commanders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Suchcitz&quot;/&gt; Both divisions were as exhausted as their opponents, whom they had chased all the way from Belarus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradziński-212&quot;/&gt; However, prior to the battle both divisions received reinforcements from other units, instead of fresh recruits, and were much superior in manpower to other Russian units on the Polish front.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradziński-212&quot;/&gt; Later, in his monograph on the war, Marshal of Poland Józef Piłsudski remarked that the commanding officer of the 27th Rifle Division had achieved what was unheard of in the Polish Army despite numerous attempts: putting rear echelons and stragglers of his division into front-line service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pilsudski&quot;/&gt; This was indeed a problem for both armies, as the number of &quot;bayonets and sabres&quot;, or soldiers fighting in the first line, was at all times smaller than the number of second echelon troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pruszynski&quot;/&gt; On August 15 Polish intelligence reported the strength of the Russian forces as &quot;three to four standard Russian divisions&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jędrzejewicz&quot;&gt;Jędrzejewicz &amp; Cisek, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; Even post-war memoirs by General Żeligowski mention &quot;[t]hree Russian infantry divisions, that is 27 battalions, though admittedly understrength, against one of our own&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;/&gt; though in fact the Russian forces only had two divisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski-2006-255&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;/&gt;

== Battle ==

=== August 13 ===
&lt;!-- removed due to concerns at Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Radzymin (1920)/archive1 [[File:Polish–Soviet War 1920 Polish defences near Milosna, August.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.4|alt=A group of eight soldiers in Polish uniforms in a shallow trench. The soldier in the centre is looking through the sights of a M1895 Colt-Browning machine gun, surrounded by three soldiers, one of them holding a munitions box in his hands. Behind them a group of four soldiers, two of them sitting on the rear edge of the trench, two of them leaning against it.|Polish [[machine gun]] nest in Miłosna, August 1920. During the Battle of Warsaw both sides were more or less equal in numbers of guns, but the Russians had more modern artillery pieces and more machine guns, while Poland successfully deployed [[FT-17]] tanks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gałęzowski-21&quot;/&gt;]] --&gt;

Both Polish and Russian planners expected an attack on Warsaw—and Radzymin in particular—from the east. Yet the first fights started to the north-east of the Polish capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wierzbicki&quot;/&gt; Warsaw was to be assaulted from the east by the 16th Red Army. At the same time the 14th Red Army (under [[Ieronim Uborevich]]) captured Wyszków and started a fast march westwards,&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski-17&quot;/&gt; towards [[Toruń]]. It was then to cross the lower Vistula and assault Warsaw from the north-west. However, its 21st Rifle Division remained on the south side of the Bug River and headed for Warsaw directly, under orders from Russia's [[Commissar|Commissar of War]] [[Leon Trotsky]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiddick&quot;/&gt; Aided by the Russian 27th Rifle Division, it came into contact with the Polish forces at Radzymin on August 12, and prepared for an assault the following morning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;/&gt;

The Soviet probing attack began at 07:00 hours, but the 21st Rifle Division achieved no breakthrough. After the Soviets had been repelled, the defending 11th Infantry Division received some artillery reinforcements. The artillery commanders wanted to use the church tower of Radzymin as an observation post and to move the batteries forward, closer to the front line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;/&gt; However, before the relocation of the artillery was complete, a new Soviet attack began at around 17:00, this time carried out by four brigades of the 21st and 27th Rifle Divisions,{{cref2|e|1}} reinforced with 59 artillery pieces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-22&quot;/&gt; The Russians achieved a 3:1 superiority in firepower.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-atak&quot;/&gt; Deprived of artillery support, the inexperienced and overstretched&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wierzbicki&quot;/&gt; 1/[[46th Infantry Regiment (Poland)|46th Infantry Regiment]], defending the village of Kraszew, broke, and the Soviets gained entry to Radzymin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tarczynski&quot;/&gt; The Polish unit withdrew in panic,&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-22&quot;/&gt; and soldiers left their arms and backpacks behind.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pobóg&quot;/&gt; One of the artillery officers noted that the Russians achieved complete tactical surprise: &quot;I ordered my dinner prepared when my aide came shouting 'Lieutenant Sir, the Reds are in the city{{' &quot;}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt;

The retreat was made even more serious by the fact that the [[Military Police|gendarmes]], tasked with stabilising the front and catching deserters, also fled in panic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski&quot;/&gt; The town itself was badly damaged, and the commanding officer of the 46th Regiment, Colonel [[Bronisław Krzywobłocki]], was forced to order the retreat of the remainder of his forces south-west from the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski&quot;/&gt; The rest of the division had no option but to fall back to the line of First World War trenches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;/&gt; During the chaotic withdrawal all the artillery sub-units got lost. By 19:00 hours the town was in Russian hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-pierwsze&quot;/&gt;

Although the Polish division was defeated, the Russian forces did not pursue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski&quot;/&gt; This allowed the Poles to mount a night counterattack. A single [[machine gun]] battalion attacked a position behind Radzymin. While ultimately unsuccessful, the battalion forced the Russian troops to remain stationary overnight, giving the Poles badly needed time to regroup and receive reinforcements, which came in the form of a single regiment from the 1st Lithuanian-Belarusian Division. Instead of retreating to the third line of defences, the Poles remained outside the town, hoping to retake it the following day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolatorski-54&quot;/&gt;

[[File:POL Radzymin 9.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.2|alt=Colour picture of a road intersection, with a large neo-classical church in the background|The church of Radzymin was used by both sides as an artillery observation post]]
News of the defeat at Radzymin reached Warsaw the same day,&lt;ref name=&quot;D'Abernon&quot;/&gt; causing panic among both the government and ordinary people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Suchcitz&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wierzbicki&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;D'Abernon&quot;/&gt; The following day the battlefield was visited by, among others, Prime Minister [[Wincenty Witos]], papal [[nuncio]] [[Achille Ratti]] (the future [[Pope Pius XI]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies-213&quot;/&gt; [[Maciej Rataj]] and General Józef Haller, the commanding officer of the Northern Front. General Haller's dispatch of 01:00 hours the same night called the Polish defeat at Radzymin &quot;ignominious&quot;, and ordered the commanding officers of the 46th Infantry Regiment and divisional artillery to be immediately [[court-martial]]led.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;/&gt; The commanding officer of the 46th Regiment was immediately relieved of command and replaced with [[Major]] Józef Liwacz.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-22&quot;/&gt;{{cref2|b|1}}

The gravity of the situation was well-understood by the Polish Commander-in-Chief Józef Piłsudski, who remarked that all the battle plans for his counteroffensive were based on the assumption that Warsaw would hold,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wierzbicki&quot;/&gt; and suggested to General [[Tadeusz Rozwadowski]] that he reinforce the Radzymin area with any forces available, including an &quot;en masse tank attack&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jędrzejewicz&quot;/&gt; Despite this suggestion, out of 49 tanks of the 1st Tank Regiment available in Warsaw at that time, only about six took part in the battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski-89&quot;/&gt;{{cref2|c|1}} The loss of Radzymin also forced General Władysław Sikorski's 5th Army, fighting north of the Bug River and along the Vistula, to start a counteroffensive from the Modlin Fortress earlier than planned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wierzbicki&quot;/&gt; Rozwadowski and General [[Maxime Weygand]], a member of the [[French Military Mission to Poland]], even suggested that Piłsudski also hasten his preparations for a counteroffensive, but he refused and decided to follow the original plans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;/&gt;{{cref2|f|1}}

The Russians considered the capture of Radzymin a crucial accomplishment. The Polish intelligence intercepted and decrypted a euphoric, but completely untrue, report by the Revolutionary Military Committee of the 3rd Army dispatched to Moscow, informing the Russian government that &quot;the brave units of the 3rd Army have captured the town of Radzymin on August 13th, at 23:00 hours. In pursuit of the enemy, they are not further than 15 [[verst]]s from Praga. (...) The workers of Warsaw can already sense that their liberation is near. The revolution in Warsaw is ripe. Workers demand that the city be handed over to the Red Army without a fight, threatening to prevent armed soldiers from leaving the city [for the front]. The [[White movement|White Poland]] is dying&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski&quot;/&gt; The commanding officer of the Russian 3rd Army, Vladimir Lazarevich, informed [[Mikhail Tukhachevsky|Tukhachevsky]] that &quot;Poland is now on fire. Only one more push is needed and the Polish fracas will be over&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-22&quot;/&gt;

To counter the threat of a Russian breakthrough, General Latinik ordered General [[Jan Rządkowski]] to assault the town the following day with all available forces. To strengthen the assault, the 11th Infantry Division (under Colonel Bolesław Jaźwiński) was drawn from the reserves and dispatched to join the assault which was scheduled for 05:00 hours the following morning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski&quot;/&gt; However, the Polish forces were far  from sufficient for the task. Rządkowski argued that he had been promised substantial reinforcements which did not arrive. The battle-hardened [[5th Rifle Division (Poland)|Siberian Brigade]] was at that time tied down in the Modlin Fortress, although the promised cavalry units did arrive—but without their ammunition trains.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski-86&quot;/&gt;

=== August 14 ===
[[File:Warsaw 1920 battlefield.svg|thumb||alt=Map of the area north-east of Warsaw, south-west of Modlin, with Radzymin and Wołomin in the centre. Main Russian attacks of August 14 marked with arrows.|On August 14 the Red Army broke through Polish lines and reached the villages of Ossów and [[Izabelin, Legionowo County|Izabelin]], some {{convert|13|km|mi}} from Warsaw, but this was the closest that Russian forces would come]]
The plans for the Polish assault had to be changed due to unexpected Russian actions. The Polish forces expected heavy opposition from at least two Russian divisions. However, in the morning the Russian 21st Division resumed its advance along the [[Białystok]]–Warsaw road towards Marki and Warsaw, while the 27th started its march towards [[Jabłonna, Legionowo County|Jabłonna]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt; The 21st Division achieved some early successes when its 5th and 6th Rifle Brigades pushed the Poles back from the Czarna River some {{convert|3|km|mi}} to the west.&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolikowski&quot;/&gt; However, at the same time it was advancing right in front of Polish forces which were preparing to assault Radzymin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt; At 10:15 hours the Polish 81st and 85th Infantry Regiments from the 1st Lithuanian-Belarusian Division assaulted the left flank of the unsuspecting Russians,&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt; continued along the Warsaw–Białystok road, and broke through to the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolikowski&quot;/&gt; The attack was led by Lieutenant Colonel Kazimierz Rybicki, who had personally witnessed the defeat of the 46th Regiment the previous day, on his day off.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt; This time spirits were high and the Polish infantry advanced in order, with officers in the first line and the soldiers singing [[Dąbrowski's Mazurka]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt; By noon the town was liberated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt;

The success did not last long, as the Russian 27th Rifle Division turned around and arrived at Radzymin just in time for its 81st Brigade to push the exhausted Polish forces back towards the village of Słupno.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikorski-13&quot;/&gt; Threatened by further attacks from Słupno and Wieliszew, the 85th Regiment retreated after suffering heavy casualties, including the commanding officer of the 1st Battalion, Captain Ryszard Downar-Zapolski.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;&gt;Żeligowski, pp. 89–98, 142–143&lt;/ref&gt; This time the Soviet 81st Rifle Brigade (27th Rifle Division) pursued the Poles and managed to pierce Polish defences near [[Wólka Radzymińska]] and [[Dąbkowizna]], breaking through the second line of defences, which were the last before the city limits. The Polish headquarters at Warsaw was &quot;petrified to hear of the complete destruction of the 19th [Lithuanian-Belarusian] Division&quot;, a report that fortunately for the Poles proved to be false.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikorski-2&quot;/&gt; The threat to the northern flank was halted, with heavy casualties on both sides, thanks to the intervention of the division's commanding officer Jan Rządkowski, as well as Front commanding officer Józef Haller, who arrived on the battlefield to personally organise an ad-hoc line of defence west of Wólka Radzymińska,&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt; with Polish artillery units shelling the advancing Russians with direct fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolatorski-64&quot;/&gt; The Soviet advance was halted, and this time chaos in the Polish ranks was avoided, but again lack of reinforcements behind the main line of defences proved a serious problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- Removed due to concerns at Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Radzymin (1920)/archive1 [[File:Polish machine gunners at Radzymin.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.2|alt=A group of five soldiers in Polish uniforms, manning a M1917 Browning machine gun. In front of their trench, to the left, an open field. |A Polish machine gun nest during the battle]] --&gt;
In the evening Generals [[Lucjan Żeligowski]], Józef Haller, Jan Rządkowski and Franciszek Latinik met in Jabłonna and again in Struga to prepare a plan for retaking Radzymin once again. It was decided that, since the Soviet 27th Division was bogged down around Radzymin and had not resumed its march towards Jabłonna, the Polish 10th Infantry Division was no longer needed in that sector, and instead could be used to achieve a breakthrough at Radzymin. The division was relocated to [[Nieporęt]], where General Rządkowski discovered the artillery units that were believed to have been destroyed by the Russians the previous day. A single battalion from the 28th ''Kaniów Rifles'' Regiment from the 10th Division, led by [[porucznik|1st Lieutenant]] [[Stefan Pogonowski]], was ordered to entrench in a forest near Wólka Radzymińska and organise an ambush. The rest of the Polish forces were to start an all-out assault at 05:00 hours the following morning, with General Żeligowski in command over the ad-hoc corps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-dowództwo&quot;/&gt; The forces amassed for the assault had a nominal strength of 17,000 infantry, 109 artillery pieces, and 220 machine guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-dowództwo&quot;/&gt;

In the evening the 5th Army, operating north of the Bug and Narew rivers with its base of operations in the Modlin Fortress, started a limited counteroffensive with the aim of lessening the pressure on the Polish forces at Radzymin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;/&gt; Grossly outnumbered, the 5th Army could not break through the Russian lines, and got bogged down in intense fights along the [[Wkra]] river.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski&quot;/&gt; However, although initially unsuccessful, the Polish attack prevented the Soviet 5th, 15th and 16th Armies from reinforcing the two divisions already committed to Radzymin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;/&gt; Only the 4th Red Army, the furthest from the battlefield, operating in the north along the [[East Prussia]]n border and moving towards Toruń, kept advancing almost unopposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;/&gt; This however did not pose an immediate threat to the defenders of Warsaw, as its advance was finally halted at the outskirts of [[Włocławek]], and it was forced to start a hasty retreat eastwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pilsudski-134&quot;/&gt;

=== August 15 ===
In the early hours of August 15 the Russian forces resumed their attacks on the Polish lines, intending to break through the second line of defences to the area of Nieporęt and Jabłonna.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt; However, as they bypassed a small forest outside Wólka Radzymińska, they were assaulted from the rear by the 1st Battalion of the 28th Infantry Regiment, which had been concealed there earlier. Simultaneously, the remainder of the 28th Regiment began a badly coordinated and half-hearted attack from Nieporęt. Both Polish assaults were bloodily repelled, with the casualties including Lieutenant Pogonowski who was posthumously awarded the [[Virtuti Militari]] medal for his bravery leading the charge, but they did force the Russians to retreat to their initial positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt;

When the front-line stabilised, the Polish headquarters threw all its reserves into a counterattack. Beniaminów was reinforced with the 29th Infantry Regiment. The Polish attack began around 05:30, after a 20-minute [[artillery barrage]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolikowski&quot;/&gt; Soon the entire 10th Infantry Division started a push along the southern bank of the Bugonarew river in order to outflank the Russian forces from the north, while the 1st Lithuanian-Belarusian Division pushed directly towards the town. Although the Russian side had superior artillery and brought several [[Austin Armoured Car|Austin-Putilov armoured cars]], this time the Polish assault was supported by five [[Renault FT]] tanks and numerous aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski&quot;/&gt; Despite suffering from mechanical failures, the tanks successfully broke through the Russian lines, and the infantry of the 85th &quot;Wilno Rifles&quot; Regiment from the 1st Lithuanian-Belarusian Division followed them into the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt; After a short struggle the Polish forces once again controlled the town. However, as soon as it was taken, General Żeligowski decided to reorganise his division and could not support the 85th Regiment with fresh forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt; Yet another successful counterattack by the Russian 61st and 62nd Infantry Brigades forced the Polish 1st Division to retreat back to its initial positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- Removed due to concerns at Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Radzymin (1920)/archive1[[File:Radzymin 1920.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.5|alt=A black and white picture showing a large artillery crater filled with water. In the background a number of ruined burnt-out houses.|The town of Radzymin was badly damaged during the fighting]] --&gt;
At the same time, on the northern flank, the 10th Division was much more successful. Instead of waiting for orders from General Żeligowski, the commanding officer of the 10th Division, Lieutenant Colonel [[Wiktor Thommée]], started a push along the southern bank of the Bugonarew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;/&gt; The 28th and 29th ''Kaniów Rifles'' Infantry Regiments managed to reach the village of Mokre, on a small hill overlooking Radzymin and the Białystok-Warsaw road, directly behind the Russian lines. The Russians tried to push the Poles back from that position, but ultimately failed. Their assault on the village of Wiktorów also ended in failure. Soon the Polish positions in Mokre were secured, and further reinforced with the remainder of the 1st Battalion, 28th Regiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt;

With the northern flank safely in Polish hands, General Lucjan Żeligowski ordered his Lithuanian-Belarusian Division to complete the encirclement of Radzymin. The division reached a position a few hundred metres from Radzymin by way of the village of Ciemne to the south of the town. Fearing envelopment, the Soviets abandoned the town and withdrew east. A single company from the 30th ''Kaniów Rifles'' Regiment entered Radzymin unopposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;/&gt; The town was completely empty; both the civilians and the Russian soldiers had fled, and one officer remarked that &quot;not a stray dog was left behind in the ruined city&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt;

=== Aftermath: August 16 and the following days ===
[[File:Cemetery Chapel commemorating battle of Radzymin 1920.JPG|thumb|right|upright=1.0|Cemetery Chapel - monument commemorating battle of Radzymin 1920]]
Although the battle was over and Radzymin was secure, the Soviet forces continued to threaten the Polish northern flank. In the early hours of August 16 the Russians mounted yet another assault on Radzymin, reinforced by several armoured cars and led personally by the commanding officer of the 27th Rifle Division, Vitovt Putna. However, by this time the morale of the 27th Division was already broken, and the assault was easily thwarted by the Polish infantry and the three remaining operational FT tanks. The armoured cars withdrew as soon as the Polish tanks opened fire, and the Russian infantry followed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-25&quot;/&gt;

Other Russian forces were more successful to the north of the town, where they managed to capture the village of Mokre from the 28th Regiment. The regiment counter-charged the village, but was initially driven off. However, approximately 80 pieces of emplaced Polish artillery laid a 30-minute barrage on the village. It was the greatest concentration of artillery fire in the war up to that point, and had a tremendous effect on the morale of the Russian defenders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-25&quot;/&gt; After the barrage ended Lieutenant Colonel Wiktor Thommée personally led his forces in a bayonet charge; the regiment re-entered Mokre at noon and the Russians fled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-25&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Mogiła żołnierzy poległych w 1920.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.0|alt=A large group of people, many of them in Polish Army winter uniforms, surround a monument. The monument consists of a concrete base and a 5-metre-high cross, with a large stone tablet in front of it. The text on the tablet reads (in Polish): Brotherly grave of heroes fallen in defence of the fatherland in 1920; the monument was funded by workers of the Polish Bank in Warsaw. In the background a tall factory chimney.|A monument to the fallen at Radzymin was erected soon after the war]]
The entire 13th Red Army stalled because of its defeat at Radzymin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis&quot;/&gt; After that success the Poles slowly but steadily pushed the Soviets back beyond the first line of defences that had been overrun several days before. By the end of 16 August, the 28th and 30th Infantry Regiments manned most of the trench line along the Rządza River, near the village of Dybów.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-25&quot;/&gt; Although initially the Russian command wanted to use the outskirts of Radzymin as a pivot for a tactical withdrawal to the Radzymin–[[Brześć]] line, the following day the Soviet commander ordered a full retreat towards Wyszków and later [[Grodno]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, Piłsudski's 4th Army outflanked the surprised Russians and went as far north as the left wing of [[Nikolai Sollogub]]'s 16th Red Army, which at that time was constantly pressured from the front by the 10th and 15th divisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski&quot;/&gt; This made existing Russian plans obsolete, and Polish forces started a pursuit that ended with the victorious [[Battle of the Niemen River]] in September. On the day of Polish victory the Soviets issued a [[Soviet propaganda|propaganda]] poster in Moscow proclaiming: &quot;Warsaw has fallen. With it the Poland of yesterday became history. It is nothing but a legend now while the truth of today is the red reality. Long live the Soviets! Long live the invincible Red Army!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-25&quot;/&gt;

== Result and assessment ==
The battle was a success for the Poles at both the tactical level (the battle of Radzymin itself) and the strategic level (its role in the battle of Warsaw). After several days of constant fighting for the town of Radzymin and its immediate vicinity, the Russian attack was repelled and the Poles were able to mount a successful counteroffensive, forcing the Russian armies out of Poland and in the end destroying them completely.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski-2006&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- Removed due to concerns at Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Radzymin (1920)/archive1 [[File:Soviet prisoners taken near Radzymin.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A group of several dozen men in various military uniforms, standing, sitting and laying on an open field surrounded by a low fence. To the right a single Polish soldier in winter uniform, holding a rifle. In the background, a long line of railway cars.|The Polish Army took several hundred Russians [[prisoner of war|into captivity]]]] --&gt;
However, the conduct of the Polish forces and their commanders at Radzymin in the early part of the battle has been criticised by historians since the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski&quot;/&gt; It was noted by General Lucjan Żeligowski that the importance of the northern approach to Warsaw was poorly understood by the Polish commanders prior to the battle, and that the untested and relatively weak 10th Division was chosen for the task of defending Radzymin &quot;out of sheer incompetence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;/&gt; In his memoirs he also heavily criticised the commanding officers of the division, whose &quot;military prowess and punctuality in carrying out orders was little more than irony&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski&quot;/&gt; Other post-war authors argued&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt; that on August 13, when the first Russian forces appeared in front of Radzymin, the 1st Army had more than enough time to reinforce the weak Polish forces there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt; Instead, it took several days to recapture what could have been held from the start.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;/&gt;

Despite the lack of strategic flair in the Polish defence of Radzymin, it was one of the cornerstones of the overall success in the Battle of Warsaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gieleciński&quot;&gt;Gieleciński, Izdebski et al., p. 104&lt;/ref&gt; Although it was Piłsudski's Assault Group that defeated the Russians, the forces at Radzymin and Sikorski's 5th Army were responsible for stopping them at the gates of Warsaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiddick&quot;/&gt; Żeligowski noted in his memoirs that &quot;Warsaw was saved thanks to Polish successes at Mokra, Wólka Radzymińska and Radzymin&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pruszynski&quot;/&gt;

== The battle in popular culture and the media ==
As one of the crucial battles of the war of 1920, the battle for Radzymin has been featured in novels, memoirs and historical monographs. It was also portrayed in the 2011 film ''[[Battle of Warsaw 1920]]'', although the battle of Radzymin sequence was shot mostly in [[Piotrków Trybunalski]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dobroni&quot;/&gt; Since 1998 a [[re-enactment]] of the battle has been held annually on August 15 in Ossów and Radzymin,&lt;ref name=&quot;GW-ins&quot;/&gt; organised  by various re-enactment groups and a local [[powiat]] administration.&lt;ref name=&quot;PAP-DGP&quot;/&gt;

== Notes ==
* {{Cnote2|a|The division was originally called the Lithuanian-Belarusian Division ({{lang-pl|Dywizja Litewsko-Białoruska}}). In the early summer of 1920 it was renamed the [[19th Infantry Division (Poland)|19th Infantry Division]], in line with other Polish units of the time. Soon after the battle General Piłsudski reversed his decision and the division was renamed to its former name. Soon afterwards it was split into two divisions, the 1st and 2nd Lithuanian-Belarusian Divisions.}}
* {{cnote2|b|The defeat of the 46th Regiment was considered so great that the entire unit was disgraced. After the battle it was struck from the registers of the Polish Army, and its remnants were incorporated into the [[5th Podhale Rifles Infantry Regiment]]. Even the number of the original regiment was considered disgraced, and thus the post-war Polish Army had 85 infantry regiments numbered from 1 to 86, with the exception of 46th. As described in  Odziemkowski (2000), p. 22.}}
* {{cnote2|c|The use of Polish tanks in the war of 1920 is further discussed in Michał Piwoszczuk's 1935 monograph on the 1st Tank Regiment.}}
* {{cnote2|d|The Polish [[Biuro Szyfrów|Cipher Section]] had managed to break Russian codes and ciphers by 1919.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ścieżyński&quot;/&gt; In the crucial months of 1920, it was able to decode most if not all Russian radio messages easily. Discussed in Nowik, pp. 25–26.}}
* {{cnote2|e|Russian rifle [[brigade]]s were roughly similar in size to Polish [[regiment]]s, while Russian regiments were, at least nominally, similar in size to Polish [[battalion]]s.}}
* {{cnote2|f|Piłsudski claimed in his post-war memoirs that he had hastened his counteroffensive by one day, but then postponed it back to August 16, the day the attack eventually started. Piłsudski, pp. 125–126.}}
* {{cnote2|g|In their drive for Warsaw, Bolshevik forces did briefly reach Włocławek and Płock, and some cavalry patrols crossed the Vistula near Bobrowniki, but not in sufficient time or numbers to affect the outcome of the battle.}}

== Citations ==
{{reflist|20em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;D'Abernon&quot;&gt;D'Abernon, pp. 83, 144&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies-213&quot;&gt;Davies, p. 213&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis&quot;&gt;Davis, p. 371&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dobroni&quot;&gt;Jaczyński, ¶ &quot;W rolę Radzymina wcielił się Piotrków...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fiddick&quot;&gt;Fiddick, pp. 196–219&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- removed as the image is removed as well &lt;ref name=&quot;Gałęzowski-21&quot;&gt;Gałęzowski, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gałęzowski-27&quot;&gt;Gałęzowski, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;GW-ins&quot;&gt;PAP, ¶ &quot;Inscenizacją Bitwy Warszawskiej 1920 r...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolatorski-12&quot;&gt;Kolatorski, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolatorski-54&quot;&gt;Kolatorski, pp. 54–60&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolatorski-64&quot;&gt;Kolatorski, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kowalski&quot;&gt;Kowalski, pp. 98–112&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolikowski&quot;&gt;Królikowski (1991), pp. 17–55&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Królikowski-36&quot;&gt;Królikowski (2002), pp. 31–36&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolikowski-66&quot;&gt;Królikowski (1991), p. 66&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Manteuffel-370&quot;&gt;Manteuffel, p. 370&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-atak&quot;&gt;Najczuk, ¶ &quot;Atak na przedmoście warszawskie podjęło...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-dowództwo&quot;&gt;Najczuk, ¶ &quot;Dowództwo na całością sił wydzielonych...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-ros&quot;&gt;Najczuk, ¶ &quot;Rosjanie dysponowali...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-pierwsze&quot;&gt;Najczuk, ¶ &quot;Pierwsze natarcie rosyjskie z rana 13 sierpnia...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-pol&quot;&gt;Najczuk, ¶ &quot;W dniu 14 sierpnia w godzinach popołudniowych...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-sklad&quot;&gt;Najczuk, ¶ &quot;Ciągły odwrót wojsk polskich spod Kijowa wymuszał...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Najczuk-zadanie&quot;&gt;Najczuk, ¶ &quot;Ogólnie należy stwierdzić, że głównym zadaniem przedmościa...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-1-55&quot;&gt;Odziemkowski (1990), p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski&quot;&gt;Odziemkowski (1990), p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-21&quot;&gt;Odziemkowski (2000), p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-22&quot;&gt;Odziemkowski (2000), p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-23&quot;&gt;Odziemkowski (2000), p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-24&quot;&gt;Odziemkowski (2000), p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Odziemkowski-2-25&quot;&gt;Odziemkowski (2000), p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PAP-DGP&quot;&gt;AW &amp; PAP, ¶ &quot;Organizatorami rekonstrukcji było Starostwo Powiatowe...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pilsudski&quot;&gt;Piłsudski, p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pilsudski-134&quot;&gt;Piłsudski, pp. 134–137&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pobóg&quot;&gt;Pobóg-Malinowski, p. 453&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pruszynski&quot;&gt;Pruszyński &amp; Giedroyć, pp. 32–36&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pruszynski-238&quot;&gt;Pruszyński &amp; Giedroyć, p. 238&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikorski-13&quot;&gt;Sikorski, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikorski-2&quot;&gt;Sikorski, pp. 109–134&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradzinski&quot;&gt;Skaradziński, pp. 185–192, 215&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradziński-156&quot;&gt;Skaradziński, p. 156&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaradziński-212&quot;&gt;Skaradziński, pp. 212–216&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Suchcitz&quot;&gt;Suchcitz, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski&quot;&gt;Szczepański (2002), pp. 30–38&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Szczepanski-17&quot;&gt;Szczepański (1990), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Ścieżyński&quot;&gt;Ścieżyński, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wandycz-116&quot;&gt;Wandycz, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wierzbicki&quot;&gt;Wierzbicki, pp. 594–595&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski&quot;&gt;Wyszczelski (2005), pp. 147–148&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski-1999-235&quot;&gt;Wyszczelski (1999), pp. 235–293&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski2&quot;&gt;Wyszczelski (2008), pp. 17–22&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski-2006&quot;&gt;Wyszczelski (2006), p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyszczelski-2006-255&quot;&gt;Wyszczelski (2006), pp. 255–259&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski&quot;&gt;Zamoyski, pp. 86–102&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski-86&quot;&gt;Zamoyski, p. 86&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski-89&quot;&gt;Zamoyski, p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Żeligowski-72&quot;&gt;Żeligowski, pp. 72–74&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Tarczynski&quot;&gt;Tarczyński, pp. 141–142&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== References ==
{{refbegin|30em}}
;Articles
* {{cite web|url=http://www.wojsko-polskie.pl/articles/view/15467/obchody-90-rocznicy-bitwy-pod-radzyminem.html |title=Bitwa pod Radzyminem (13–15 VIII 1920 r.) |trans_title=Battle of Radzymin (13–15 of August 1920) |author=Lt.Col. Ryszard Najczuk |date=2010-08-16 |work=wojsko-polskie.pl |publisher=[[Polish Army]] |accessdate=2011-10-29 |language=pl |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120403025849/http://www.wojsko-polskie.pl/articles/view/15467/obchody-90-rocznicy-bitwy-pod-radzyminem.html |archivedate=2012-04-03 |df= }}
* {{cite journal | author = Janusz Odziemkowski | editor1 =Janusz Kuligowski | editor2 =Krzysztof Szczypiorski | year = 2000 | title = Walki na przedmościu warszawskim i ofensywa znad Wieprza 1920 roku | trans_title  = Fights for the Warsaw bridgehead and the Wieprz River offensive of 1920 | journal = Rocznik Mińsko-Mazowiecki | volume = 6 | pages = 17–28 | location = [[Mińsk Mazowiecki]] | publisher = Towarzystwo Przyjaciół Mińska Mazowieckiego | format = PDF | issn = 1232-633X | accessdate = 2011-10-24 | url = http://mazowsze.hist.pl/files/Rocznik_Minsko-Mazowiecki/Rocznik_Minsko-Mazowiecki-r2000-t6/Rocznik_Minsko-Mazowiecki-r2000-t6-s17-28/Rocznik_Minsko-Mazowiecki-r2000-t6-s17-28.pdf|language=pl}}
* {{cite journal | archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20110718120235/http://www.mowiawieki.pl/artykul.html?id_artykul=404 | archivedate =2011-07-18 |   author =Janusz Szczepański | year =2002 | title =Kontrowersje Wokół Bitwy Warszanskiej 1920 Roku | trans_title=Controversies surrounding the Battle of Warsaw in 1920 | journal =[[Mówią Wieki]] | volume = | issue =8 | pages =30–38  | url =http://www.mowiawieki.pl/artykul.html?id_artykul=404 | accessdate =2011-10-04|language=pl}}

;Books
* {{cite book | author =[[Edgar Vincent, 1st Viscount D'Abernon|Edgar Vincent D'Abernon]] | title =The Eighteenth Decisive Battle of the World: Warsaw, 1920 | year =1977 | page =178 | publisher =[[Hyperion Books|Hyperion Press]] | location = | isbn=0-88355-429-1 }}
* {{cite book | author =[[Norman Davies]] | title =[[God's Playground]] | year =1981 | page =672 | publisher =Oxford University Press | volume=2 | location =Oxford | isbn=978-0-19-822592-8 }}
* {{cite book | author =[[Paul K. Davis (historian)|Paul K. Davis]] | title=100 decisive battles: from ancient times to the present | year=2001 | page=480 | publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] | location=Oxford | isbn=978-0-19-514366-9}}
* {{cite book | author =Thomas C. Fiddick | title =Russia's retreat from Poland, 1920: from permanent revolution to peaceful coexistence | year =1990 | pages =196–219 | volume=2 | publisher =[[Palgrave Macmillan]] | location = Basingstoke | isbn=978-0-312-03998-1}}
* {{cite book | author =Marek Gałęzowski | title =Bitwa Warszawska 1920 | trans_title=Battle of Warsaw 1920 | year =2011 | editor =Andrzej Dusiewicz | page =39 | publisher =Nowa Era | location =Warsaw | isbn=978-83-267-0322-5 | url =http://www.bitwawarszawska1920film.pl/dopobrania/BitwaW1920.pdf | format =PDF | accessdate =2011-11-10 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author1 =Marek Gieleciński | author2 = Jerzy Izdebski | author3 = Zofia Krasicka | author4=[[University of Warsaw|Uniwersytet Warszawski]]. Instytut Historyczny (corporate author)| title =Wieś, chłopi, ruch ludowy, państwo | trans_title=The Village, The Popular Movements, the State | year =1996 | editor1 =Józef Ryszard Szaflik | editor2 = Arkadiusz Kołodziejczyk | page =104 | chapter =Bój o Radzymin | trans_chapter= Battle for Radzymin | chapterurl = | publisher =Warsaw University Press | location =Warsaw | isbn=|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =[[Wacław Jędrzejewicz]] |author2=Janusz Cisek | title =Kalendarium życia Józefa Piłsudskiego 1867–1935 | trans_title=Chronological biography of Józef Piłsudski | year =1998 | volume = II | pages = | publisher =LTW | location =Warsaw | isbn=978-83-88736-92-6|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Władysław Kolatorski |author2=Jan Wnuk | title =Bitwa pod Radzyminem w 1920 roku | trans_title=Battle at Radzymin in 1920 | year =1995 | page =107 | publisher =Volumen | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-902669-1-1 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book |author1=Tadeusz Kowalski |author2=Janusz Szczepański |editor1=Adam Dobroński |others=preface by Adam Koseski |title=Dzieje 13 pułku piechoty |trans_title=History of the 13th Infantry Regiment|edition= |series= |volume= |year=1996 |publisher=[[Pułtusk Academy of Humanities|Wyższa Szkoła Humanistyczna w Pułtusku]], USKOR |location=Pułtusk |isbn=83-906458-1-5 |oclc= |page=329 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Lech Królikowski | title =Bitwa warszawska 1920 roku; działania wojenne, zachowane pamiątki | trans_title=Battle of Warsaw of 1920; armed actions, surviving sites | year =1991 | pages =17–55 | publisher =[[Państwowe Wydawnictwo Naukowe]] | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-01-10316-7 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Lech Królikowski | title =Twierdza Warszawa | trans_title=Warsaw Fortress | year =2002 | editor = | page =383 | chapter = | chapterurl = | publisher =[[Bellona Publishing House|Bellona]] | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-11-09356-3 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book |author1=Various authors|author2=[[Tadeusz Manteuffel]]  |editor1=Tadeusz Manteuffel |editor2=[[Andrzej Ajnenkiel]] | editor3=Stanisław Arnold |title=Historia Polski |trans_title=History of Poland |edition= |series= |volume=4 | year=1966 |publisher=Państwowe Wydawnictwo Naukowe |location=Warsaw |id=PB 3944/66|page=525 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Grzegorz Nowik | title =Zanim złamano Enigmę...; polski radiowywiad podczas wojny z bolszewicką Rosją 1918–1920 | trans_title=Before Enigma Was Broken: Polish Radio Intelligence during the War with Bolshevik Russia, 1918–1920 | year =2004 | page =1054 | publisher =Rytm | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-7399-099-2 |language=pl}} Excerpt published as: {{cite journal | author =Grzegorz Nowik | date =2005-08-13 | title =Szyfrołamacze | trans_title=Code-breakers | journal =[[Polityka]] | volume =32 | issue =2516 | pages =68–70 | issn =0032-3500 | oclc=6547308 | url =http://archiwum.polityka.pl/art/szyfrolamacze,399934.html | accessdate =2011-11-10 }}
* {{cite book | author =Janusz Odziemkowski | title =Bitwa Warszawska 1920 roku | trans_title=Battle of Warsaw of 1920 | year =1990 | page =56 | publisher =Mazowiecki Ośrodek Badań Naukowych im Stanisława Herbsta | location =Warsaw | isbn= |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =[[Józef Piłsudski]] | editor =[[Julian Stachiewicz]], [[Władysław Pobóg-Malinowski]] | title =Rok 1920 | trans_title=Year 1920 | series=Pisma zbiorowe | volume=VII | year =1937 | page =217 | publisher =Instytut Józefa Piłsudskiego | location =Warsaw|language=pl}} 2nd edition: {{cite book |author=Józef Piłsudski |editor1=Julian Stachiewicz |editor2=[[Władysław Pobóg-Malinowski]] |others=Józef Moszczeński (preface) |title=Rok 1920 |trans_title=Year 1920|edition=reprint |series=Pisma zbiorowe |volume=VII |year=1990 |origyear=1937 |publisher=Krajowa Agencja Wydawnicza |location=Warsaw |isbn=83-03-03056-6|page=217 |chapter=VIII }}
* {{cite book| author = Lt.Col. Michał Piwoszczuk| title = Zarys historii wojennej 1 pułku czołgów| trans_title = Concise wartime history of the 1st Tank Regiment| edition = 2| origyear = 1935| year = 1964| publisher = Taurus| location = London| oclc = 27102801| page = 135|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =[[Władysław Pobóg-Malinowski]] | title =Najnowsza historia polityczna Polski | trans_title = Modern political history of Poland | year =1990 | volume=II | page =453 | publisher =Graf | location =Gdańsk | isbn= |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Mieczysław Pruszyński |author2=[[Jerzy Giedroyć]]  | title =Wojna 1920: dramat Piłsudskiego | trans_title=War of 1920; Piłsudski's drama | year =1995 | pages =32–36, 157, 190–196 | publisher =BGW | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-7066-560-8|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =[[Władysław Sikorski]] | title =Nad Wisłą i Wkrą; studjum z polsko-rosyjskiej wojny 1920 roku | trans_title=By the Vistula and Wkra Rivers; study on the Polish-Russian war of 1920 | volume=1 | year =1928 | pages =13, 109–134 | publisher =[[Ossolineum]] | location =Lwów |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Bohdan Skaradziński | title =Polskie lata 1919–1920 | trans_title=Polish years 1919–1920 | year =1993 | volume =2 | pages =185–192, 215 | publisher =Volumen | location =Warsaw | isbn=978-83-85218-47-0|language=pl}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |author=Andrzej Suchcitz |editor= |encyclopedia=Generałowie wojny polsko-sowieckiej, 1919–1920 |title=Putna, Witold |edition= |year=1993 |publisher=Muzeum Wojska w Białymstoku |volume= |location=Białystok  |page=59 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book|publisher = Stacja Naukowa MOBN w Pułtusku|publication-place = Pułtusk|author = Janusz Szczepański|url = https://openlibrary.org/books/OL18742942M/Wojna_1920_roku_w_powiecie_Pułtuskim|title = Wojna 1920 roku w powiecie Pułtuskim|trans_title=War of 1920 in the powiat of Pułtusk |publication-date = 1990|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Col. Mieczysław Ścieżyński | title =Radjotelegrafja jako źródło wiadomości o nieprzyjacielu | trans_title=Radiotelegraphy as a Source of Intelligence on the Enemy | year =1928 | page =49 | publisher =Dowództwo Okręgu Korpusu X | location =Przemyśl |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Various authors | title =Bitwa warszawska 13–28 VIII 1920; dokumenty operacyjne | trans_title=Battle of Warsaw of August 13–28th, 1920; operational documents | volume=2 | year =1996 | editor =Marek Tarczyński | page =935 | publisher =Rytm | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-86678-37-2 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book |author1=[[Piotr S. Wandycz]] |title=The Lands of Partitioned Poland, 1795-1918 |edition= |series=A History of East Central Europe |volume=7 |year=1974 |publisher=[[University of Washington Press]] |location=Washington |isbn=978-0-295-95358-8|pages= }}
* {{cite book | author =Andrzej Wierzbicki | title =Wspomnienia i dokumenty, 1877–1920 | trans_title=Memories and documents; 1877–1920 | year =1957 | pages =594–595 | publisher =[[Państwowe Wydawnictwo Naukowe]] | location =Warsaw | isbn= |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author = [[Lech Wyszczelski]] | title = Kijów 1920 | trans_title=Kiev 1920 | location= Warsaw | publisher=Bellona | year = 1999 | isbn = 83-11-08963-9|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Lech Wyszczelski | title =Warszawa 1920 | trans_title=Warsaw 1920 | year =2005 | pages =147–148 | publisher =Bellona | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-11-10227-9|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Lech Wyszczelski | title =Operacja warszawska; sierpień 1920 | trans_title=Warsaw Operation, August 1920 | year =2006 | page =534 | publisher =Bellona | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-11-10179-5 |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =Lech Wyszczelski | title =Niemen 1920 | trans_title=Neman 1920 | year =2008 | pages =17–22 | publisher =Bellona | location =Warsaw | isbn=978-83-11-11324-4|language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =[[Adam Zamoyski]] | title =Warsaw 1920: Lenin's failed conquest of Europe | year =2008 | pages =86–102 | publisher =HarperPress | location = | isbn=978-0-00-725786-7}}
* {{cite book | author =[[Lucjan Żeligowski]] | title =Wojna w roku 1920 | trans_title = War of 1920 | year =2005 | pages =89–98, 142–143 | publisher =De Facto | location =Warsaw | isbn=83-89667-49-5 |language=pl}}

;News
* {{cite journal |author1=AW | author2=PAP| date=2011-08-14 |title=Żywa lekcja historii - inscenizacja Bitwy Warszawskiej 1920 r. w Ossowie |trans_title=Lesson of live history - reenactment of the Battle of Warsaw in Ossów |journal=[[Dziennik Polska-Europa-Świat|Dziennik Gazeta Prawna]] |volume= |series= |issue= |page= |location=Warsaw |publisher=INFOR PL | issn=2080-6744 |authorlink2=Polish Press Agency|language=pl}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.dobroni.pl/rekonstrukcje,bitwa-warszawska-1920-roku-walki-o-radzymin-w-piotrkowie-trybunalskim,4858 |title=Bitwa Warszawska 1920 roku – walki o Radzymin w Piotrkowie Trybunalskim | trans_title=Battle of Warsaw 1920 – fights for Radzymin in Piotrków Trybunalski |author=Grzegorz Jaczyński |date=2010-07-24 |work=dobroni.pl |publisher=Fundacja Wojskowości Polskiej | location=Warsaw |accessdate=24 November 2011|language=pl}}
* {{cite journal |author=[[Polish Press Agency|PAP]] (corporate author)| date=1998-08-13 |title=Inscenizacja Bitwy Warszawskiej |trans_title=Battle of Warsaw Re-enactment |journal=[[Gazeta Wyborcza]] |volume= |series= |issue=189 |page=3|location=Warsaw |publisher=Agora | issn=0860-908X|language=pl}}

{{refend}}

== External links ==
* {{cite web | editor=Wojciech Zalewski | title=Warszawa (Wołomin) 1920 | publisher=Taktyka i Strategia | year=2005 | work=taktykaistrategia.pl | url=http://www.taktykaistrategia.pl/?topic=wydanegry&amp;content=wolomin1920 | accessdate= |language=pl}}
* [http://derela.republika.pl/en/ft17.htm Renault FT-17 in the Polish service]
* {{cite web | author=Władysław Kolatorski | title=Bitwa Warszawska | trans_title=Battle of Warsaw | publisher=Urząd Miasta Radzymin | work=radzymin.pl | url=http://www.radzymin.pl/asp/pl_start.asp?typ=14&amp;menu=195&amp;strona=1 |accessdate=2011-10-06|language=pl}}
* [http://www.radzymin.pl/asp/pl_start.asp?typ=6&amp;katalog=Bitwa_Warszawska&amp;tytul= Gallery of historical pictures of the battle]
* [https://picasaweb.google.com/darda01/BitwaWarszawska1920RekonstruktorzyIStatysciNaPlanieII Gallery of stills from the 2011 film featuring the battle]
* [http://www.museumoffamilyhistory.com/warszawa.rt.1915.1922.jpg 1915/1922 staff map of Radzymin and its surroundings]

{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Radzymin 1920, Battle of}}
[[Category:1920 in Poland]]
[[Category:Battles involving Poland]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Battles of the Polish–Soviet War]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1920]]
[[Category:Wołomin County]]</text>
      <sha1>05bgzogsg28wl67pg4sq28hodc2i7so</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
