<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Agua Dulce</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2108091</id>
    <revision>
      <id>731689132</id>
      <parentid>722005527</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-26T22:09:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr Stephen</username>
        <id>863017</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>clean up, ISBN format using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21947">{{featured article}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict    =Battle of Agua Dulce
|partof      =the [[Texas Revolution]]
|date        =March 2, 1836
|place       ={{convert|25|mi|km}} southwest of [[San Patricio, Texas|San Patricio]]
|coordinates ={{coord|27|50|51|N|97|50|59|W|type:event_region:US-TX|display=inline,title}}
| map_type    =  Texas
| map_relief  = yes
| map_size    = 275
 | map_mark = Red triangle with thick white border.svg
 | map_marksize =14
| latitude    = 27.8475
| longitude   = -97.849722
| map_label   = approximate location of the battle
|territory   =
|result      =Mexican victory
|status      =
|combatant1  = [[Mexico]]
|combatant2  = [[Texians|Texian rebels]]
|commander1  =[[José de Urrea]]
|commander2  =[[James Grant (Texas)|James Grant]] {{KIA}}
|units1      =
|units2      =
|strength1   =150 men
|strength2   =53 men
|casualties1 =1 killed&lt;br/&gt;unknown wounded
|casualties2 =12–15 killed&lt;br/&gt;6 captured
|notes       =
|campaignbox ={{campaignbox Texas Revolution}}
}}
{{Campaignbox Goliad Campaign}}

The '''Battle of Agua Dulce Creek''' was a skirmish during the [[Texas Revolution]] between Mexican troops and rebellious immigrants to the [[Mexican Texas|Mexican province of Texas]], known as [[Texians]].  As part of the [[Goliad Campaign]] to retake the Texas [[Gulf Coast]], Mexican troops ambushed a group of Texians on March 2, 1836.  The skirmish began approximately {{convert|26|mi|km}} south of [[San Patricio, Texas|San Patricio]], in territory belonging to the Mexican state of [[Tamaulipas]].

When Mexico transitioned to a [[centralized government]] in 1835, supporters of [[federalism]] took up arms.  Colonists in Texas, primarily immigrants from the United States, revolted in October 1835 and by the end of the year had  expelled all Mexican troops from their province.  With hostilities temporarily suspended, [[Frank W. Johnson]], the commander of the volunteer army in Texas, and [[James Grant (Texas)|James Grant]] gathered volunteers for a planned invasion of the Mexican port town of [[Matamoros, Tamaulipas|Matamoros]].  In late February 1836, Johnson and half of the volunteers drove a herd of horses to San Patricio, while Grant took the remaining men to gather more horses and to attempt contact with federalist sympathizers near Matamoros.

Unknown to the Texians, on February 18, Mexican General [[José de Urrea]] led a large contingent of troops from Matamoros into Texas to neutralize the rebels gathered along the coast.  His troops easily defeated Johnson's small force on February 26.  Several days later, informants revealed Grant's location, and on the morning of March&amp;nbsp;2, Urrea sent 150 troops to ambush the rebels. After a brief battle, the main body of the Texian and Tejano troops were defeated. Grant and two others escaped the battle and were pursued for {{convert|7|mi|km}}. Grant was killed, as were 11 men under his command. Six Texians were taken prisoner; contrary to Santa Anna's orders, Urrea did not execute them, but instead sent them to a jail in Matamoros. An additional six Texians escaped; five of them later died in the [[Goliad massacre]].

== Background ==
Under President [[Antonio López de Santa Anna]], the Mexican government began to shift away from a [[federalism|federalist]] model to a more [[centralized government]]. His increasingly dictatorial policies, including the revocation of the [[Constitution of 1824]] in early 1835, incited federalists throughout the nation to revolt.&lt;ref name=davis121&gt;Davis (2006), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mexican Army quickly put down revolts throughout the country's interior, including a brutal suppression of militias in [[Oaxaca]] and [[Zacatecas]].&lt;ref name=davis121&gt;Davis (2006), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin7&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; Unrest continued in the Mexican state of [[Coahuila y Tejas]].  The area that bordered the United States, known as [[Mexican Texas|Texas]], was populated primarily by English-speaking settlers, known as [[Texians]].  In October, the Texians took up arms in what became known as the [[Texas Revolution]].&lt;ref name=davis142&gt;Davis (2006), p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt; The following month, Texians declared themselves part of a Mexican state independent from Coahuila and created a provisional state government based on the principles of the Constitution of 1824.&lt;ref name=davis168&gt;Davis (2006), p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt;  By the end of the year, all Mexican troops had been expelled from Texas.&lt;ref name=davis183&gt;Davis (2006), p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;

Leading federalists in Mexico advocated a plan to attack centralist troops in [[Matamoros, Tamaulipas|Matamoros]], a major Mexican port.&lt;ref&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 187–9.&lt;/ref&gt;  Members of the [[Consultation (Texas)|General Council]], the interim Texas governing body, were enamored with the idea of a [[Matamoros Expedition]].  They hoped it would inspire other federalist states to revolt and keep the bored Texian troops from deserting the army.  Most importantly, it would move the war zone outside Texas.&lt;ref name=stuart60&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; The Council officially approved the plan on December 25, and on December 30 [[Frank W. Johnson]], the commander of the volunteer army, and his aide [[James Grant (Texas)|James Grant]] took the bulk of the army and almost all of the supplies to [[Goliad, Texas|Goliad]] to prepare for the expedition.&lt;ref&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 107–8.&lt;/ref&gt;  Historian Stuart Reid posits that Grant was a British secret agent and that his efforts were an unofficial scheme to advance British interests in the region.  Britain did not welcome the idea of an independent Texas, and the invasion of Matamoros was a way to tie Texas more tightly to Mexico.&lt;ref name=reid70&gt;Reid (2007), p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;

Determined to quash the rebellion, Santa Anna began assembling a large force to restore order.&lt;ref name=hardin102&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt;   In late December, at Santa Anna's behest, the [[Congress of the Union|Mexican Congress]] passed the [[Tornel Decree]], declaring that any foreigners fighting against Mexican troops &quot;will be deemed pirates and dealt with as such, being citizens of no nation presently at war with the Republic and fighting under no recognized flag.&quot; In the early nineteenth century, captured pirates were executed immediately. The resolution thus gave the Mexican Army permission to take no prisoners in the war against the Texians.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Historians Jack Jackson and John Wheat in their research of Mexican government records believe that although the wording of the December 30, 1835 Tornel Decree specified &quot;foreigners&quot;, the document was a mere formality to green-light Santa Anna's broader plan of dealing with opposition both foreign and domestic. In a letter to General Joaquín Ramírez y Sesma on February 29, 1836, Santa Anna wrote &quot;in this war there are no prisoners&quot;. At the [[Battle of the Alamo]] prior to the final siege, he offered a three-day amnesty to allow Tejanos inside the mission to leave unharmed. At other skirmishes in the war, there is no indication either he or his generals made that distinction. Jackson and Wheat stated, &quot;When he learned that Urrea had taken several hundred prisoners near Goliad, Santa Anna expressed his amazement that they had not been treated as pirates and swiftly executed as Tornel's decree specified. He sent more letters until the tragic deed was done.&quot; Jackson, Wheat (2005), p. 374, 377, 386–7, 390; Poyo (1996), p. 53, 58 Efficient in the Cause (Stephen L. Harden); Lindley (2003), p. 94, 134; Todish et al. (1998), pp. 137–8; Castañeda (1970), pp. 55–56; Scott (2000), p. 71&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Anna personally led the bulk of his troops inland to [[San Antonio de Béxar]], and ordered General [[José de Urrea]] to lead 550 troops along the [[Atascocita Road]] toward Goliad.  Urrea's efforts to quell the rebellion along the [[Texas Gulf Coast]] have become known as the [[Goliad Campaign]].&lt;ref name=hardin120&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin121&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prelude ==
[[File:JOSE COSME URREA.jpg|thumb|[[José de Urrea]], commanding officer, Mexican Army]]
[[File:JamesWFannin.jpg|thumb|[[James Fannin]], second-in-command to [[Sam Houston]]]]
The Texas provisional government had named [[Sam Houston]] the commander of a new [[regular army]] in Texas, but without authority over the volunteers who reported to Johnson.&lt;ref name=davis171&gt;Davis (2006), p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt;  The provisional governor, [[Henry Smith (Texas governor)|Henry Smith]], opposed the Matamoros Expedition and ordered Houston to find a way to disband it.&lt;ref name=davis191&gt;Davis (2006), p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;  In a rousing speech to the volunteers, Houston dissuaded the bulk of the men from continuing their mission.  Many left the army.  Others joined the troops stationed under Houston's second-in-command, [[James Fannin]], at [[Presidio La Bahía]] in Goliad.  By the end of January 1836, only 70&amp;nbsp;men remained with Johnson and Grant.&lt;ref name=hardin111&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;  Most of these volunteers were Americans or Europeans who had arrived in Texas after fighting had commenced.&lt;ref name=reid107&gt;Reid (2007), p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt;

Urrea reached Matamoros on January 31.  A committed federalist himself, he soon convinced other federalists in the area that the Texians' ultimate goal was secession and their attempt to spark a federalist revolt in Matamoros was just a method of diverting attention from themselves.&lt;ref name=reid122&gt;Reid (2007), pp. 122, 128.&lt;/ref&gt;  Meanwhile, Mexican double agents continued to assure Johnson and Grant that they would be able to take Matamoros easily.&lt;ref name=reid131&gt;Reid (2007), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; Urrea's force crossed into Texas on February 18.&lt;ref name=stuart71&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite hearing rumors that the Mexican Army was approaching, Grant and Johnson chose to take their men south of the [[Nueces River]], into territory belonging to the state of [[Tamaulipas]], to search for horses to buy, steal, or otherwise gather.  About February 21, Johnson and a small group began herding approximately 100 horses back into Texas.  The rest of the men remained with Grant, ostensibly to look for more horses.  In actuality, he was attempting to rendezvous with his allies near Matamoros to determine whether federalists were still willing to rise up against the Mexican Army.&lt;ref&gt;Reid (2007), pp. 130–3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Mexican troops arrived in San Patricio in the early hours of February 26.  After a [[Battle of San Patricio|fifteen-minute battle]], Johnson's men were defeated; six Texians, including Johnson, escaped, and the remainder were killed or captured.&lt;ref name=scott110&gt;Scott (2000), p. 110–3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=stuart84&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt;  While Urrea waited for reinforcements before beginning his march towards Goliad, his advance party searched for Grant and the remaining Texians.&lt;ref name=reid140&gt;Reid (2007), p. 140.&lt;/ref&gt;  Unaware of Johnson's fate, on February 27 Grant and his party began their march northward to San Patricio, driving a herd of several hundred horses he had purchased.&lt;ref name=reid141&gt;Reid (2007), p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt;  The men camped along [[San Fernando Creek]] on March 1.  Local ranchers welcomed them, but that night sent a messenger to Urrea with Grant's location and plans.&lt;ref name=reid142&gt;Reid (2007), p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle ==
Mexican troops marched overnight towards El Puerto de los Cuates de Agua Dulce, a well-known crossing point on Agua Dulce Creek.&lt;ref name=reid142&gt;Reid (2007), p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;  Approximately {{convert|26|mi|km}} south of San Patricio,&lt;ref name=hardin159/&gt; about {{convert|1|mi|km}} from [[Banquete, Texas|Banquete]],&lt;ref name=roell17&gt;Roell (2013), p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; and just north of modern-day [[Kingsville, Texas|Kingsville]],&lt;ref name=scott115&gt;Scott (2000), p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; Mexican soldiers took cover in two groves of trees.&lt;ref name=hardin159&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;  Urrea had approximately 150 troops, including 80 [[dragoon]]s.&lt;ref name=reid142/&gt;

Grant's company comprised about 53 men, including a large contingent of ''Tejanos'' (Mexican-born residents of Texas) under the command of [[Plácido Benavides]].  The men were in good spirits and rode at an easy pace towards San Patricio.&lt;ref name=reid143&gt;Reid (2007), p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; Grant, Benavides, and Ruben Brown rode {{convert|0.5|mi|km}} ahead of the main body of Texians and saw no signs of Mexican soldiers.&lt;ref name=hardin159&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 10 and 11 am,&lt;ref name=scott117&gt;Scott (2000), p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; as the bulk of the Texians reached the trees, the Mexican cavalry attacked.&lt;ref name=hardin159/&gt;  Taken completely unaware, many of the Texians were shot before they were able to raise their guns.&lt;ref name=scott115&gt;Scott (2000), p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; As they tried to flee, dragoons chased them down and lanced them off their horses.&lt;ref name=reid143/&gt;  Five Texians dismounted and made a run for a small village nearby, hoping to gain cover so they could use their rifles. Urrea sent the infantry after them.  Two of those Texians were captured and the rest escaped.&lt;ref&gt;Reid (2007), pp. 143–4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Grant, Benavides, and Brown turned back to join the other Texians.  Once in the battle, Brown dismounted, either to reload his rifle or because his horse was killed.  Seeing that the battle was lost, Grant pulled Brown onto another horse, and the two of them and Benavides turned to flee.  Mexican cavalry attempted to stop them; Grant shot one officer and he and Benavides then galloped past that officer's horse.  At this point, the herd stampeded, forcing the Mexican cavalry aside.  The three Texians followed the horses.&lt;ref name=reid144&gt;Reid (2007), p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt;   Mexican soldiers promptly gave chase.&lt;ref name=hardin159/&gt;  According to Brown's later recollection, both his and Grant's horses were wounded as Mexican soldiers fired after them.&lt;ref name=scott116&gt;Scott (2000), p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt;

The three Texians ran for {{convert|6|-|7|mi|km}}, occasionally firing their pistols to force Mexican dragoons to stay back.  Mexican soldiers yelled that the men would be spared if they surrendered, but none of the Texians believed them.&lt;ref name=reid145&gt;Reid (2007), p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt;  Benavides had the strongest mount, and Grant ordered him to go ahead to warn Fannin that the Mexican Army was close to Goliad.&lt;ref name=hardin159/&gt;&lt;ref name=reid146&gt;Reid (2007), p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;  Grant and Brown were surrounded and forced to stop. Grant killed a Mexican soldier who drove a lance through Brown's arm. Between ten and twelve Mexican soldiers then surrounded Grant, and he died after being pierced multiple times.&lt;ref name=hardin159/&gt;&lt;ref name=reid146/&gt;  Historian Stuart Reid theorizes that Mexican soldiers were eager to ensure Grant did not survive the battle.  Grant could identify federalist sympathizers in Matamoros and the surrounding areas, and his knowledge potentially put Urrea and some of his federalist-sympathizing troops at risk.&lt;ref name=reid146&gt;Reid (2007), p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

Brown threw his empty pistol at one Mexican officer, then grabbed the lance from the man Grant had shot and used it to defend himself.&lt;ref name=reid146/&gt; After soldiers [[lasso]]ed him, Brown surrendered and was taken captive.&lt;ref name=hardin159/&gt;  Brown was then brought back to the site of the ambush.  He recalled that one severely injured Texian, Joseph Carpenter, was lying in the dirt, begging for his life.  Brown then saw a Mexican soldier shoot him.&lt;ref name=reid157&gt;Reid (2007), p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
Although Urrea reported that 42 Texians were killed,&lt;ref&gt;Scott (2000), pp. 116–7.&lt;/ref&gt; early 20th century historians generally only list 12 Texians as killed.&lt;ref name=stuart87&gt;Stuart (2007), p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; Tejano involvement in the revolution had been notably absent from textbooks until the 1970s, so it is likely that historians were not including the ''Tejanos'' under Benavides.&lt;ref name=reid143/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Graham (1985), pp. 62–3.&lt;/ref&gt;  Six Texians were taken prisoner. In defiance of the Tornel Decree, Urrea spared those who surrendered and sent them to a prison in Matamoros.&lt;ref&gt;Stuart (2007), pp. 87–8.&lt;/ref&gt;  Reports indicated that Urrea offered clemency after the intervention of [[Francita Alavez]], the mistress of one of Urrea's soldiers.&lt;ref name=scott117&gt;Scott (2000), p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;
Six Texians escaped. Five of these joined Fannin's garrison at Goliad and were later killed in the [[Goliad massacre]]. No reports of Mexican losses have been found, although at least one Mexican soldier is thought to have died. After the battle, Mexican soldiers rounded up the horses that the Texians had been herding and kept them.&lt;ref name=groneman47&gt;Groneman (1998), p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; The battle marked the end of the Matamoros Expedition.&lt;ref name=stuart88&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although it occurred on the same day that Texas [[Texas Declaration of Independence|declared independence]], Grant and his men did not know that they were fighting for the new [[Republic of Texas]].&lt;ref name=ried148&gt;Reid (2007), p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to historian [[Stephen Hardin]], this battle proved that the Texians did not fight well on open prairies.&lt;ref name=hardin160/&gt;  News of the battle reached Fannin on March 4.&lt;ref name=scott118&gt;Scott (2000), p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt;  Urrea's imminent arrival worried Fannin, who feared that Santa Anna would lead his troops from San Antonio de Béxar towards Goliad, essentially trapping Fannin and his men between the two branches of the Mexican Army.&lt;ref name=hardin160&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt; Fannin wrote to the Acting Governor, [[James W. Robinson (Texas and California)|James Robinson]], &quot;I am a better judge of my military abilities than others, and if I am qualified to command an Army, I have not found it out.&quot;&lt;ref name=hardin160and161&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 160–1.&lt;/ref&gt;   The [[Convention of 1836|acting Texas government]] nonetheless left Fannin in charge of the fort at Goliad, instructing him to determine whether it was best to retreat or make a stand.&lt;ref name=scott121&gt;Scott (2000), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;  Fannin delayed making a decision, finally choosing to leave Goliad on March 19.  Urrea's troops trapped Fannin's men on an open prairie.  The Texians surrendered after the [[Battle of Coleto]] and most, including Colonel Fannin, were executed a week later in the [[Goliad massacre]].&lt;ref&gt;Stuart (2008), pp. 123, 154.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Timeline of the Texas Revolution]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

== References ==
{{reflist|15em}}

== Bibliography ==
*{{cite book|last1=Castañeda|first1=Carlos E|title=The Mexican Side of the Texan revolution, 1836, by the Chief Mexican Participants|date=1970|publisher=Graphic Ideas, Inc.|location=Austin, TX|oclc=695593957}}
*{{cite book|last=Davis|first=William C.|author-link=William C. Davis (historian)|title=Lone Star Rising|date=2006|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|isbn=978-1-58544-532-5}} originally published 2004 by New York: Free Press
*{{cite journal|last=Graham|first=Don|title=Remembering the Alamo: The Story of the Texas Revolution in Popular Culture|journal=The Southwestern Historical Quarterly|volume=89|date=July 1985|pages=35–67|url=http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metapth117151/m1/61/|accessdate=January 21, 2015}}
*{{cite book|last=Groneman|first=Bill|title=Battlefields of Texas|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|location=Plano, TX|year=1998|isbn=978-1-55622-571-0|oclc=37935129}}.
*{{cite book|last=Hardin|first=Stephen L.|authorlink=Stephen L. Hardin|year=1994|title=Texian Iliad – A Military History of the Texas Revolution|location=Austin, TX|publisher=University of Texas Press|isbn=0-292-73086-1|oclc=29704011}}.
*{{cite book|last1=Jackson|first1=Jack|last2=Wheat|first2=John|url=http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metapth296837/m1/1/ |title=Almonte's Texas: Juan N. Almonte's 1834 Inspection, Secret Report &amp; Role in the 1836 Campaign|date=2005|publisher=[[Texas State Historical Association]]|isbn=978-0-87611-207-6|location=Denton, TX}}
*{{cite book|last=Lack|first=Paul D.|title=The Texas Revolutionary Experience: A Political and Social History 1835–1836|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|date=1992|isbn=0-89096-497-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Lindley|first=Thomas Ricks|title=Alamo Traces: New Evidence and New Conclusions|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|location=Plano, TX|year=2003|isbn=1-55622-983-6}}
*{{cite book|last1=Poyo|first1=Gerald Eugene|title=Tejano Journey, 1770–1850|date=1996|publisher=University of Texas Press|isbn=978-0-292-76570-2|location=Austin, TX}}
*{{cite book|last=Reid|first=Stuart|title=The Secret War for Texas|series=Elma Dill Russell Spencer Series in the West and Southwest|number=28|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|year=2007|isbn=978-1-58544-565-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Roell|first=Craig H|title=Matamoros and the Texas Revolution|publisher=Texas State Historical Association|year=2013|place=Denton, TX|isbn=978-0-87611-260-1|via=[[Questia]]}}
*{{cite book|last=Scott|first=Robert|title=After the Alamo|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|date=2000|location=Plano, TX|isbn=978-1-55622-691-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Stuart|first=Jay|title=Slaughter at Goliad: The Mexican Massacre of 400 Texas Volunteers|publisher=Naval Institute Press|place=Annapolis, MD|year=2008|isbn=978-1-59114-843-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Todish|first=Timothy J.|last2=Todish|first2=Terry|last3=Spring|first3=Ted|title=Alamo Sourcebook, 1836: A Comprehensive Guide to the Battle of the Alamo and the Texas Revolution|publisher=Eakin Press|year=1998|location=Austin, TX|isbn=978-1-57168-152-2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Agua Dulce, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1836]]
[[Category:1836 in the Republic of Texas]]
[[Category:Battles of the Texas Revolution]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Republic of Texas|Agua Dulce]]
[[Category:Battles involving Mexico]]</text>
      <sha1>28ldmunib3wnmvbzm6caj64nt8v23g5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
