<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Valcour Island</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>88383</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751053325</id>
      <parentid>747841339</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T02:39:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RockDrummerQ</username>
        <id>10510515</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44371">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Valcour Island
| partof      = the [[American Revolutionary War]]
| image       = [[File:BattleOfValcourIsland watercolor.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = ''Royal Savage'' is shown run aground and burning, while British ships fire on her (watercolor by unknown artist, ca. 1925)
| date        = October 11, 1776
| place       = near [[Valcour Bay]], [[Lake Champlain]],&lt;br&gt;[[Peru, New York|Town of Peru]] / [[Plattsburgh (town), New York|Town of Plattsburgh]],&lt;br&gt;[[Clinton County, New York]]
| coordinates = {{coord|44|36|37.84|N|73|25|49.39|W|type:isle_scale:100000_region:US|display=title}}
| result      = Tactical British victory&lt;br&gt;Strategic American victory.
| combatant1  = {{flag|United States|1776}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Great Britain}}
| commander1  = [[Benedict Arnold]]
| commander2  = [[Guy Carleton, 1st Baron Dorchester|Guy Carleton]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Thomas Pringle (admiral)|Thomas Pringle]]
| strength1   = 15 armed ships&lt;ref name=&quot;Silverstone15_6&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;500 sailors&lt;ref name=&quot;AmericanForces&quot; group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Arnold writes in a dispatch ([[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 53) that he has about 500 &quot;half naked&quot; sailors.  An analysis of his fleet ([[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 57) indicates that ideal strength to fully man it was closer to 800, another figure that is sometimes cited.&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 25 armed ships&lt;ref name=&quot;Silverstone15&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;697 sailors&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten59&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;1,000 soldiers&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten58&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 58&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;650 Indians&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten58&quot;/&gt;
| casualties1 = 80 killed or wounded&lt;br/&gt;120 captured&lt;br&gt;11 ships lost&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller178&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 178&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 40 killed or wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;Allen176&quot;&gt;[[#Allen|Allen (1913)]], p. 176&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3 small gunboats lost
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox American Revolutionary War: Canada}}
}}

The naval '''Battle of Valcour Island''', also known as the '''Battle of Valcour Bay''', took place on October 11, 1776, on [[Lake Champlain]]. The main action took place in [[Valcour Bay]], a narrow [[strait]] between the [[Province of New York|New York]] mainland and [[Valcour Island]]. The battle is generally regarded as one of the first [[naval battle]]s of the [[American Revolutionary War]], and one of the first fought by the [[United States Navy]]. Most of the ships in the American fleet under the command of [[Benedict Arnold]] were captured or destroyed by a [[Kingdom of Great Britain|British]] force under the overall direction of General [[Guy Carleton, 1st Baron Dorchester|Guy Carleton]]. However, the American defense of Lake Champlain stalled British plans to reach the upper [[Hudson River]] valley.

The [[Continental Army]] had retreated from [[Province of Quebec (1763-1791)|Quebec]] to [[Fort Ticonderoga]] and [[Fort Crown Point]] in June 1776 after British forces were massively reinforced. They spent the summer of 1776 fortifying those forts, and building additional ships to augment the small American fleet already on the lake. General Carleton had a 9,000 man army at [[Fort Saint-Jean (Quebec)|Fort Saint-Jean]], but needed to build a fleet to carry it on the lake. The Americans, during their retreat, had either taken or destroyed most of the ships on the lake. By early October, the British fleet, which significantly outgunned the American fleet, was ready for launch.

On October 11, Arnold drew the British fleet to a position he had carefully chosen to limit their advantages. In the battle that followed, many of the American ships were damaged or destroyed. That night, Arnold sneaked the American fleet past the British one, beginning a retreat toward Crown Point and Ticonderoga. Unfavorable weather hampered the American retreat, and more of the fleet was either captured or grounded and burned before it could reach Crown Point. Upon reaching Crown Point Arnold had the fort's buildings burned and retreated to Ticonderoga.

The British fleet included four officers who later became admirals in the [[Royal Navy]]: [[Thomas Pringle (admiral)|Thomas Pringle]], [[James Richard Dacres (1749–1810)|James Dacres]], [[Edward Pellew, 1st Viscount Exmouth|Edward Pellew]] and [[John Schank]]. Valcour Bay, the site of the battle, is now a [[National Historic Landmark]], as is {{USS|Philadelphia|1776|2}}, which sank shortly after the October 11 battle, and was raised in 1935. The underwater site of {{USS|Spitfire|1776 gunboat|2}}, located in 1997, is on the [[National Register of Historic Places]].

==Background==
{{main article|Invasion of Canada (1775)}}
[[File:General-Sir-Guy-Carleton 2.jpg|thumb|upright|Quebec's Governor, General [[Guy Carleton, 1st Baron Dorchester|Guy Carleton]]|alt=A half-height portrait of Carleton.  He wears a red coat with vest, over a white shirt with ruffles.  His white hair is drawn back, and he faces front with a neutral expression.]]
The [[American Revolutionary War]], which began in April 1775 with the [[Battles of Lexington and Concord]], widened in September 1775 when the [[Continental Army]] embarked on [[Invasion of Canada (1775)|an invasion]] of the British [[Province of Quebec (1763-1791)|Province of Quebec]]. The province was viewed by the [[Second Continental Congress]] as a potential avenue for British forces to attack and divide the rebellious colonies, and was at the time lightly defended. The invasion reached a peak on December 31, 1775, when the [[Battle of Quebec (1775)|Battle of Quebec]] ended in disaster for the Americans. In the spring of 1776, 10,000&amp;nbsp;British and German troops arrived in Quebec, and General [[Guy Carleton, 1st Baron Dorchester|Guy Carleton]], the provincial governor, drove the Continental Army out of Quebec and back to [[Fort Ticonderoga]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Background&quot;&gt;For detailed treatment of the background, see e.g. [[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]] or [[#Morrissey|Morrissey (2003)]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Carleton then launched his own offensive intended to reach the [[Hudson River]], whose navigable length begins south of Lake Champlain and extends down to [[New York City]]. Control of the upper Hudson would enable the British to link their forces in Quebec with those in New York, recently [[New York and New Jersey campaign|captured in the New York campaign]] by Major General [[William Howe, 5th Viscount Howe|William Howe]]. This strategy would separate the American colonies of [[New England]] from those farther south and potentially quash the rebellion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hamilton17_8&quot;&gt;[[#Hamilton|Hamilton (1964)]] pp. 17–18&lt;/ref&gt; Lake Champlain, a long and relatively narrow lake formed by the action of glaciers during the [[Quaternary glaciation|last ice age]], separates the [[Green Mountains]] of [[Vermont]] from the [[Adirondack Mountains]] of [[New York (state)|New York]].  Its {{convert|120|mi|sp=us|adj=on}} length and {{convert|12|mi|sp=us|adj=on}} maximum width creates more than {{convert|550|mi|sp=us}} of shoreline, with many bays, inlets and promontories. More than 70&amp;nbsp;islands dot the {{convert|435|mi2|sp=us|adj=on}} surface, although during periods of low and high water, these numbers can change.  The lake is relatively shallow, with an average depth of {{convert|64|ft|sp=us}}.&lt;ref&gt;[[#LCPB_FactSheet|Lake Champlain Basin Fact Sheet #3]]&lt;/ref&gt; Running roughly from south to north, the lake's waters empty into the [[Richelieu River]], where waterfalls at [[Saint-Jean-sur-Richelieu|Saint-Jean]] in Quebec mark the northernmost point of navigation.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ketchum|Ketchum (1997)]], pp. 29–31&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:ChamplainValley1777.jpg|thumb|upright|Detail of a 1777 French map showing Lake Champlain. Valcour Island is below and to the left of ''La Grand Isle''.|alt=Lake Champlain lies in northeastern New York, and is a relatively narrow lake running north to south. Key features of Lake Champlain from north to south include Isle La Motte, Grand Isle (with Valcour Island to its west, near the shore), Button Mould Bay, Crown Point, Ticonderoga, and South Bay, where Skenesborough is located.]]
The American strongholds of [[Fort Crown Point]] and Fort Ticonderoga near the lake's southern end protected access to [[wikt:head of navigation|uppermost navigable reaches]] of the Hudson River. Elimination of these defenses required the transportation of troops and supplies from the British-controlled [[St. Lawrence Valley]] {{convert|90|mi}} to the north. Roads were either impassable or nonexistent, making water transport on the lake the only viable option.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hamilton7_8_18&quot;&gt;[[#Hamilton|Hamilton (1964)]], pp. 7,8,18&lt;/ref&gt;  The only ships on the lake following the American retreat from Quebec were a small fleet of lightly armed ships that Benedict Arnold had assembled following the [[capture of Fort Ticonderoga]] in May 1775. This fleet, even if it had been in British hands, was too small to transport the large [[British Army during the American War of Independence|British Army]] to Fort Ticonderoga.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malcolmson26&quot;&gt;[[#Malcolmson|Malcolmson (2001)]], p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
During their retreat from Quebec, the Americans carefully took or destroyed all ships on Lake Champlain that might prove useful to the British. When Arnold and his troops, making up the rear guard of the army, abandoned [[Fort Saint-Jean (Quebec)|Fort Saint-Jean]], they burned or sank all the boats they could not use, and set fire to the sawmill and the fort. These actions effectively denied the British any hope of immediately moving onto the lake.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley131_2&quot;&gt;[[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]], pp. 131–132&lt;/ref&gt;

The two sides set about building fleets: the British at Saint-Jean and the Americans at the other end of the lake in Skenesborough (present-day [[Whitehall (village), New York|Whitehall, New York]]). While planning Quebec's defenses in 1775, General Carleton had anticipated the problem of transportation on Lake Champlain, and had requested the provisioning of prefabricated ships from Europe. By the time Carleton's army reached Saint-Jean, ten such ships had arrived. These ships and more were assembled by skilled shipwrights on the upper Richelieu River. Also assembled there was {{HMS|Inflexible|1776|6}}, an 180-ton warship they disassembled at Quebec City and transported upriver in pieces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Silverstone15&quot;&gt;[[#Silverstone|Silverstone (2006)]], p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley133_6&quot;&gt;[[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]], pp. 133–136&lt;/ref&gt; In total, the British fleet (25&amp;nbsp;armed vessels) had more firepower than the Americans' 15&amp;nbsp;vessels, with more than 80&amp;nbsp;guns outweighing the 74&amp;nbsp;smaller American guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Silverstone15_6&quot;&gt;[[#Silverstone|Silverstone (2006)]], pp. 15–16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley137_8&quot;&gt;[[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]], pp. 137–138&lt;/ref&gt; Two of Carleton's ships, ''Inflexible'' (18&amp;nbsp;12-pounders) and {{HMS|Thunderer|1776|6}} (six 24-pound guns, six 12-pound guns, and two howitzers), by themselves outgunned the combined firepower of the American fleet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller170&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 170&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to ''Inflexible'' and ''Thunderer'', the fleet included the [[schooner]]s {{HMS|Maria|1776|6}} (14&amp;nbsp;guns), {{HMS|Carleton|1776|6}} (12&amp;nbsp;guns), and {{HMS|Loyal Convert||6}} (6&amp;nbsp;guns), and 20&amp;nbsp;single-masted gunboats each armed with two cannons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Silverstone15&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley137_8&quot;/&gt;

The American generals leading their shipbuilding effort encountered a variety of challenges. [[Shipwright]] was not a common occupation in the relative wilderness of upstate New York, and the [[Continental Navy]] had to pay extremely high wages to lure skilled craftsmen away from the coast. The carpenters hired to build boats on Lake Champlain were the best-paid employees of the navy, excepting only the Navy's Commodore, [[Esek Hopkins]].&lt;ref name=Nelson231&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of July there were more than 200&amp;nbsp;shipwrights at Skenesborough.&lt;ref name=Nelson241&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 241&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to skilled help, materials and supplies specific to maritime use needed to be brought to Skenesborough, where the ships were constructed, or Fort Ticonderoga, where they were fitted out for use.&lt;ref name=Nelson239&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 239&lt;/ref&gt;

The shipbuilding at Skenesborough was overseen by Hermanus Schuyler (possibly a relation of Major General [[Philip Schuyler]]), and the outfitting was managed by military engineer [[Jeduthan Baldwin]]. Schuyler began work in April to produce boats larger and more suitable for combat than the small shallow-draft boats known as [[bateaux]] that were used for transport on the lake. The process eventually came to involve General Arnold, who was an experienced ship's captain, and [[David Waterbury]], a Connecticut militia leader with maritime experience. Major General [[Horatio Gates]], in charge of the entire shipbuilding effort, eventually asked Arnold to take more responsibility in the effort, because &quot;I am intirely uninform'd as to Marine Affairs.&quot;&lt;ref name=Nelson243&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 243&lt;/ref&gt;

Arnold took up the task with relish, and Gates rewarded him with command of the fleet, writing that &quot;[Arnold] has a perfect knowledge in maritime affairs, and is, besides, a most gallant and deserving officer.&quot;&lt;ref name=Nelson245&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 245&lt;/ref&gt; Arnold's appointment was not without trouble; [[Jacobus Wynkoop]], who had been in command of the fleet, refused to accept that Gates had authority over him, and had to be arrested.&lt;ref name=Nelson261&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 261&lt;/ref&gt; The shipbuilding was significantly slowed in mid-August by an outbreak of disease among the shipwrights. Although the army leadership had been scrupulous about keeping [[smallpox]] sufferers segregated from others, the disease that slowed the shipbuilding for several weeks was some kind of fever.&lt;ref name=Nelson252_3&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], pp. 252–253&lt;/ref&gt;

While both sides busied themselves with shipbuilding, the growing American fleet patrolled the waters of Lake Champlain. At one point in August, Arnold sailed part of the fleet to the northernmost end of the lake, within {{convert|20|mi|km}} of Saint-Jean, and formed a battle line. A British outpost, well out of range, fired a few shots at the line without effect. On September 30, expecting the British to sail soon, Arnold retreated to the shelter of [[Valcour Island]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller171&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 171&lt;/ref&gt; During his patrols of the lake Arnold had commanded the fleet from the [[schooner]] {{USS|Royal Savage|1775|2}}, carrying 12&amp;nbsp;guns and captained by [[Captain David Hawley|David Hawley]]. When it came time for the battle, Arnold transferred his flag to {{USS|Congress|1776|2}}, a [[row galley]]. Other ships in the fleet included {{USS|Revenge|1776|2}} and {{USS|Liberty|1775|2}}, also two-masted schooners carrying 8 guns, as well as {{USS|Enterprise|1775|2}}, a [[sloop]] (12 guns), and 8 [[gundalow]]s outfitted as [[gunboats]] (each with three guns): {{USS|New Haven|1776|2}}, {{USS|Providence|1776 gundalow|2}}, {{USS|Boston|1776|2}}, {{USS|Spitfire|1776 gunboat|2}}, {{USS|Philadelphia|1776|2}}, {{USS|Connecticut|1776|2}}, {{USS|Jersey|1776|2}}, {{USS|New York|1776|2}}, the [[Cutter (boat)|cutter]] ''Lee'', and the row galleys {{USS|Trumbull|1776 row galley|2}} and {{USS|Washington|1776 row galley|2}}. ''Liberty'' was not present at the battle, having been sent to Ticonderoga for provisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malcolmson29_33&quot;&gt;[[#Malcolmson|Malcolmson (2001)]], pp. 29–33&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller169_172&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], pp. 169, 172&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten57&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 57&lt;/ref&gt;

Arnold, whose business activities before the war had included sailing ships to Europe and the [[West Indies]], carefully chose the site where he wanted to meet the British fleet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller166_171&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], pp. 166,171&lt;/ref&gt; Reliable intelligence he received on October 1 indicated that the British had a force significantly more powerful than his.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten56&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; Because his force was inferior, he chose the narrow, rocky body of water between the western shore of Lake Champlain and Valcour Island (near modern [[Plattsburgh, New York]]), where the British fleet would have difficulty bringing its superior firepower to bear, and where the inferior seamanship of his relatively unskilled sailors would have a minimal negative effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley141&quot;&gt;[[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]], p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; Some of Arnold's captains wanted to fight in open waters where they might be able to retreat to the shelter of Fort Crown Point, but Arnold argued that the primary purpose of the fleet was not survival but the delay of a British advance on Crown Point and Ticonderoga until the following spring.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller172&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 172&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
[[File:ValcourIslandMap1776Detail.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.35|alt=The American ships are shown lined up between the western shore and Valcour Island. Near the southern tip of the island lies ''Royal Savage'', which has run aground. ''Carleton'' is nearby, and twenty British gunboats are lined up from there to the shore, facing the American line. Further south are the British ships ''Inflexible'', ''Maria'', and ''Thunderer''. Lines indicate the path taken by the Americans when they escape the night after the battle, hugging the western shore, while the British ships are lined up across the opening of the bay.|Detail from the map shown below highlighting the scene of the action]]
Carleton's fleet, commanded by Captain [[Thomas Pringle (Royal Navy officer)|Thomas Pringle]] and including 50&amp;nbsp;unarmed support vessels, sailed onto Lake Champlain on October 9.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley137&quot;&gt;[[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]], p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;  They cautiously advanced southward, searching for signs of Arnold's fleet.  On the night of October 10, the fleet anchored about {{convert|15|mi|km}} to the north of Arnold's position, still unaware of his location.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley141&quot;/&gt; The next day, they continued to sail south, assisted by favorable winds.  After they passed the northern tip of Valcour Island, Arnold sent out ''Congress'' and ''Royal Savage'' to draw the attention of the British. Following an inconsequential exchange of fire with the British, the two ships tried to return to Arnold's crescent-shaped firing line.  However, ''Royal Savage'' was unable to fight the headwinds, and ran aground on the southern tip of Valcour Island.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller173&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 173&lt;/ref&gt;  Some of the British gunboats swarmed toward her, as Captain Hawley and his men hastily abandoned ship. Men from ''Loyal Convert'' boarded her, capturing 20&amp;nbsp;men in the process, but were then forced to abandon her under heavy fire from the Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten60_1&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], pp. 60–61&lt;/ref&gt; Many of Arnold's papers were lost with the destruction of ''Royal Savage'', which was burned by the British.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller173&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley142&quot;&gt;[[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]], p. 142&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:ValcourIslandMap1776Overview.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.35|1776 map of Northern [[Lake Champlain]]; detail shown above is outlined in red.|alt=See previous maps for geography.]]
The British gunboats and ''Carleton'' then maneuvered within range of the American line. ''Thunderer'' and ''Maria'' were unable to make headway against the winds, and did not participate in the battle, while ''Inflexible'' eventually came far enough up the strait to participate in the action.  Around 12:30&amp;nbsp;pm, the battle began in earnest, with both sides firing broadsides and cannonades at each other, and continued all afternoon. ''Revenge'' was heavily hit; ''Philadelphia'' was also heavily damaged and eventually sank around 6:30&amp;nbsp;pm. ''Carleton'', whose guns wrought havoc against the smaller American [[gundalow]]s, became a focus of attention.  A lucky shot eventually snapped the line holding her broadside in position, and she was seriously damaged before she could be towed out of range of the American line. Her casualties were significant; eight men were killed and another eight wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller174&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 174&lt;/ref&gt; The young [[Edward Pellew, 1st Viscount Exmouth|Edward Pellew]], serving as a [[midshipman]] aboard ''Carleton'', distinguished himself by ably commanding the vessel to safety when its senior officers, including its captain, Lieutenant [[James Richard Dacres (1749–1810)|James Dacres]], were injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hamilton157&quot;&gt;[[#Hamilton|Hamilton (1964)]], p. 157&lt;/ref&gt; Another lucky American shot hit a British gunboat's magazine and the vessel exploded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller175&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 175&lt;/ref&gt;

Toward sunset, ''Inflexible'' finally reached the action. Her big guns quickly silenced most of Arnold's fleet.  The British also began landing [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada|Indian]]s on both Valcour Island and the lakeshore, in order to deny the Americans the possibility of retreating to land. As darkness fell, the American fleet retreated, and the British called off the attack, in part because some boats had run out of ammunition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller175&quot;/&gt; Lieutenant James Hadden, commanding one of the British gunboats, noted that &quot;little more than one third of the British Fleet&quot; saw much action that day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley142&quot;/&gt;

==Retreat==
When the sun set on October 11, the battle had clearly gone against the Americans. Most of the American ships were damaged or sinking, and the crews reported around 60&amp;nbsp;casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller175&quot;/&gt; The British reported around 40&amp;nbsp;casualties on their ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allen176&quot;/&gt;  Aware that he could not defeat the British fleet, Arnold decided to try reaching the cover of Fort Crown Point, about {{convert|35|mi|km}} to the south. Under the cover of a dark and foggy night, the fleet, with muffled oars and minimal illumination, threaded its way through a gap about one mile (1.6&amp;nbsp;km) wide between the British ships and the western shore, where Indian campfires burned.&lt;ref name=Nelson307_9&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], pp. 307–309&lt;/ref&gt; By morning, they had reached [[Schuyler Island]], about {{convert|8|mi|km}} up the lake.  Carleton, upset that the Americans had escaped him, immediately sent his fleet around Valcour Island to find them. Realizing the Americans were not there, he regrouped his fleet and sent scouts to find Arnold.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller176&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 176&lt;/ref&gt;

Adverse winds as well as damaged and leaky boats slowed the American fleet's progress. At Schuyler Island, ''Providence'' and ''Jersey'' were sunk or burned, and crude repairs were effected to other vessels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller177&quot;/&gt; The cutter ''Lee'' was also abandoned on the western shore and eventually taken by the British.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten67&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; Around 2:00&amp;nbsp;pm, the fleet sailed again, trying to make headway against biting winds, rain, and sleet. By the following morning, the ships were still more than {{convert|20|mi|km}} from Crown Point, and the British fleet's masts were visible on the horizon. When the wind finally changed, the British had its advantage first. They closed once again, opening fire on ''Congress'' and ''Washington'', which were in the rear of the American fleet. Arnold first decided to attempt grounding the slower gunboats at Split Rock, {{convert|18|mi|km}} short of Crown Point. ''Washington'', however, was too badly damaged and too slow to make it, and she was forced to [[striking the colors|strike her colors]] and surrender; 110 men were taken prisoner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller177&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 177&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Benedict arnold illustration.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Benedict Arnold]]|alt=A head and shoulders profile engraving of Arnold.  He is facing left, wearing a uniform with two stars on the shoulder epaulet. His hair is tied back.]]
Arnold then led many of the remaining smaller craft into a small bay on the Vermont shore now named Arnold's Bay 2 miles south of [[Buttonmold Bay]], where the waters were too shallow for the larger British vessels to follow. These boats were then run aground, stripped, and set on fire, with their flags still flying. Arnold, the last to land, personally torched his flagship ''Congress''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten69&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; The surviving ships' crews, numbering about 200, then made their way overland to Crown Point, narrowly escaping an Indian ambush. There they found ''Trumbull'', ''New York'', ''Enterprise'', and ''Revenge'', all of which had escaped the British fleet, as well as ''Liberty'', which had just arrived with supplies from Ticonderoga.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten70&quot;&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Arnold, convinced that Crown Point was no longer viable as a point of defense against the large British force, destroyed and abandoned the fort, moving the forces stationed there to Ticonderoga. General Carleton, rather than shipping his prisoners back to Quebec, returned them to Ticonderoga under a flag of truce. On their arrival, the released men were so effusive in their praise of Carleton that they were sent home to prevent the desertion of other troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller178&quot;/&gt;

With control of the lake, the British landed troops and occupied Crown Point the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratten70&quot;/&gt; They remained for two weeks, pushing scouting parties to within three miles (4.8&amp;nbsp;km) of Ticonderoga.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley144&quot;&gt;[[#Stanley|Stanley (1973)]], p. 144&lt;/ref&gt; The battle-season was getting late as the first snow began to fall on October 20 and his supply line would be difficult to manage in winter, so Carleton decided to withdraw north to winter quarters; Arnold's plan of delay had succeeded. [[Friedrich Adolf Riedesel|Baron Riedesel]], commanding the [[Hessian (soldiers)|Hessian]]s in Carleton's army, noted that, &quot;If we could have begun our expedition four weeks earlier, I am satisfied that everything could have ended this year.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller179&quot;&gt;[[#Miller|Miller (1974)]], p. 179&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Saratoga campaign|1777 British campaign]], led by General [[John Burgoyne]], was halted by Continental forces, some led with vigor by General Arnold, in the [[Battles of Saratoga]].  Burgoyne's subsequent surrender paved the way for the entry of [[France]] into the war as [[Franco-American alliance|an American ally]].&lt;ref&gt;See e.g. [[#Ketchum|Ketchum (1997)]] for a treatment of Burgoyne's campaign.&lt;/ref&gt;

The captains of ''Maria'', ''Inflexible'', and ''Loyal Convert'' wrote a letter criticizing Captain Pringle for making Arnold's escape possible by failing to properly blockade the channel, and for not being more aggressive in directing the battle.  Apparently the letter did not cause any career problems for Pringle or its authors; he and [[John Schank]], captain of ''Inflexible'', became admirals, as did midshipman Pellew and Lieutenant Dacres.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hamilton160&quot;&gt;[[#Hamilton|Hamilton (1964)]], p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; Carleton was awarded the [[Order of the Bath]] by [[George III of Great Britain|King George III]] for his success at Valcour Island.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller178&quot;/&gt; On December 31, 1776 one year after the Battle of Quebec, a [[mass (liturgy)|mass]] was held in celebration of the British success, and Carleton threw a grand ball.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley144&quot;/&gt;

The loss of Benedict Arnold's papers aboard ''Royal Savage'' was to have important consequences later in his career. For a variety of reasons, Congress ordered an inquiry into his conduct of the Quebec campaign, which included a detailed look at his claims for compensation. The inquiry took place in late 1779, when Arnold was in military command of [[Philadelphia]] and recuperating from serious wounds received at Saratoga. Congress found that he owed it money since he could not produce receipts for expenses he claimed to have paid from his own funds.&lt;ref&gt;Randall (1990), pp. 497–499&lt;/ref&gt; Although Arnold had already been secretly negotiating with the British over a change of allegiance since May 1779, this news contributed to his decision to resign the command of Philadelphia.&lt;ref&gt;Randall (1990), pp. 456–457,499&lt;/ref&gt; His next command was [[West Point]], which he sought with the intention of facilitating its surrender to the British.&lt;ref&gt;Randall (1990), pp. 508–509&lt;/ref&gt;  His plot was however exposed in September 1780, at which time he fled to the British in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;Martin (1997), pp. 1–4&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:GunboatPhiladelphia.jpg|thumb|upright|''[[USS Philadelphia (1776)|Philadelphia]]'' was raised in 1935. It is on display at the [[National Museum of American History]]|alt=The ship is shown in a museum installation, mounted on a wooden framework. The ship's woodwork has been discolored, and the ship sports a short mast, a single cannon facing forward near the bow, and two cannons facing port and starboard respectively near the stern.]]
In the 1930s, Lorenzo Hagglund, a veteran of [[World War I]] and a history buff, began searching the strait for remains of the battle. In 1932 he found the remains of ''Royal Savage''{{'}}s hull, which he successfully raised in 1934.&lt;ref name=Bratten75&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=uN4DAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA803&amp;dq=Popular+Science+1933+plane+%22Popular+Mechanics%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ajQdTvrsPKbksQKlm8m7CA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwBjgK#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true  &quot;Arnold's Flagship Raised On Old Tar Drums&quot;] ''Popular Mechanics'', June 1935&lt;/ref&gt; Stored for more than fifty years, the remains were sold by his son to the [[National Civil War Museum]].&lt;ref name=Bratten76&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WHTM/&gt; As of March 2009, the remains were in a city garage in [[Harrisburg, Pennsylvania]]. The city of [[Plattsburgh, New York]], has claimed ownership of the remains and would like them returned to upstate New York.&lt;ref name=WHTM&gt;[[#WHTM|&quot;War Ship Remains Piled in City Garage&quot;]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1935 Hagglund followed up his discovery of ''Royal Savage'' with the discovery of ''Philadelphia''{{'}}s remains, sitting upright on the lake bottom.&lt;ref name=Bratten77&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; He raised her that year; she is now on display at the [[Smithsonian Institution]]'s [[National Museum of American History]] in Washington, D.C.,&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller175&quot;/&gt; and is listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]] and is designated a [[National Historic Landmark]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsumPhil&quot;&gt;[[#nhlsumPhil|NHL Description of USS Philadelphia]]&lt;/ref&gt;  The site of the battle, [[Valcour Bay]], was declared a National Historic Landmark on January 1, 1961, and added to the National Register on October 15, 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;[[#|National Register Information System]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsumBay&quot;&gt;[[#nhlsumBay|NHL Description of Valcour Bay]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997 another pristine underwater wreck was located during a survey by the [[Lake Champlain Maritime Museum]]. Two years later it was conclusively identified as the gundalow ''Spitfire''; this site was listed on the National Register in 2008, and it has been named as part of the U.S. government's [[Save America's Treasures]] program.&lt;ref name=LCMM_Spitfire&gt;[[#LCMM_Spitfire|Shipwrecks of Lake Champlain: Gunboat Spitfire]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of battle==
[[File:Valcour canadianarchive c013202k.jpg|thumb|center|400px|Contemporary watercolor drawing of the American line of battle by Charles Randle. Drawing is titled as follows: New England Armed Vessels in Valcure Bay, Lake Champlain [including ''Royal Savage'', ''Revenge'', ''Lee'', ''Trumble'', ''Washington'', ''Congress'', ''Philadelphia'', ''New York'', ''Jersey'', ''Connecticut'', ''Providence'', ''New Haven'', ''Spitfire'', ''Boston'', and ''Liberty''] commanded by Benedict Arnold.]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%&quot;
|-
|+ American fleet
|-
! style=&quot;width: 20%&quot; | Ship (type, guns)
! style=&quot;width: 25%&quot; | Commander
! style=&quot;width: 30%&quot; | Notes
|-
| {{USS|Enterprise|1775|2}} ([[sloop]], 12)
| [[James Smith (American Revolution)|James Smith]]&lt;ref name=N70&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;
| Hospital ship, escaped
|-
| {{USS|Royal Savage|1775|2}} ([[schooner]], 12)
| [[David Hawley]]&lt;ref name=N297&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 297&lt;/ref&gt;
| Ran aground and burned October 11
|-
| {{USS|Trumbull|1776 row galley|2}} ([[row galley]], 10)
| [[Seth Warner (sea captain)|Seth Warner]] (left flag, [[Edward Wigglesworth (American Revolution)|Wigglesworth]])&lt;ref name=N258&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 258&lt;/ref&gt;
| Escaped&lt;br&gt;Called ''Schuyler'' prior to launch&lt;br&gt;Also referred to as ''Trumble''
|-
| {{USS|Washington|1776 lateen-rigged galley|2}} (row galley, 10)
| John Thatcher (right flag, [[David Waterbury|Waterbury]])&lt;ref name=N284&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 284&lt;/ref&gt;
| Damaged October 11&lt;br&gt;Captured October 13
|-
| {{USS|Revenge|1776|2}} ([[schooner]], 8) 
| Isaac Seamon&lt;ref name=N256&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 256&lt;/ref&gt;
| Escaped
|-
| {{USS|Congress|1776|2}} (row galley, 8)
| James Arnold (flagship, [[Benedict Arnold]])&lt;ref name=Bratten204&gt;[[#Bratten|Bratten (2002)]], p. 204&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=N295&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 295&lt;/ref&gt;
| Ran aground and burned October 13
|-
| {{USS|Lee|1776|2}} (row galley, 6)
| Captain Daviss&lt;ref&gt;[[#NYSM313|Bulletin of the New York State Museum, Issue 313 (1937)]], p. 135&lt;/ref&gt;
| Ran aground October 13&lt;br&gt;Recovered by British
|-
| {{USS|Boston|1776|2}} ([[gundalow]], 3)
| Captain Sumner&lt;ref name=N263&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 263&lt;/ref&gt;
| Ran aground and burned October 13
|-
| {{USS|Connecticut|1776|2}} (gundalow, 3)
| [[Joshua Grant (American Revolution)|Joshua Grant]]&lt;ref name=N263/&gt;
| Ran aground and burned October 13
|-
| {{USS|Jersey|1776|2}} (gundalow, 3)
| Captain Grimes&lt;ref name=N312&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 312&lt;/ref&gt;
| Abandoned October 13&lt;br&gt;Recovered by British&lt;br&gt;Also referred to as ''New Jersey''
|-
| {{USS|New Haven|1776|2}} (gundalow, 3)
| [[Samuel Mansfield (American Revolution)|Samuel Mansfield]]&lt;ref name=N263/&gt;
| Ran aground and burned October 13
|-
| {{USS|New York|1776|2}} (gundalow, 3)
| Captain Lee&lt;ref name=N279&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 279&lt;/ref&gt;
| Cannon exploded&lt;ref name=Cohn&gt;[[#Cohn|Cohn et al. (2007)]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AHL&gt;[[#AHL_cannon|America's Historic Lakes]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;Escaped&lt;br&gt;Called ''[[USS Success|Success]]'' prior to launch
|-
| {{USS|Philadelphia|1776|2}} (gundalow, 3)
| Benjamin Rue&lt;ref name=N262&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 262&lt;/ref&gt;
| Sank October 11&lt;br&gt;Raised 1935
|-
| {{USS|Providence|1776 gundalow|2}} (gundalow, 3)
| Isaiah Simonds&lt;ref name=N255&gt;[[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p. 255&lt;/ref&gt;
| Sank October 13
|-
| {{USS|Spitfire|1776 gunboat|2}} (gundalow, 3)
| Philip Ulmer&lt;ref name=N263/&gt;
| Sank October 12 near Schuyler Island; wreck located in 1997&lt;ref name=LCMM_Spitfire/&gt;
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; |Ship descriptions and dispositions (but not captains) provided by [[#Silverstone|Silverstone (2006)]], pp.&amp;nbsp;15–16, unless otherwise cited. Ship captains are all as cited.
|}
[[File:Valcour canadianarchive c013203k.jpg|thumb|center|400px|Contemporary watercolor drawing of the British line of battle by Charles Randle. Title of the painting: His Majesty's Vessels on Lake Champlain commanded by Commodore Thomas Pringle, R.N., including the ships ''Carleton'', ''Inflexible'', ''Maria'', ''Convert'', ''Thunderer'', as well as a long boat and some gun boats.]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot;
|-
|+ British fleet
|-
! style=&quot;width=20%&quot; | Ship (type, guns)
! style=&quot;width=25%&quot; | Commander
! style=&quot;width=30%&quot; | Notes
|-
| {{HMS|Inflexible|1776|2}} (square-rigged ship, 22)
| [[John Schank]]
| Participated in later stages of battle
|-
| {{HMS|Thunderer|1776|2}} ([[ketch]]-radeau, 18)&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;''Thunderer'' was basically a keelless raft rigged as a ketch.&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[George Scott (Royal Navy officer)|George Scott]]
| Did not participate in main action
|-
| {{HMS|Maria|1776|2}} (schooner, 14)
| John Starke (flagship, [[Thomas Pringle|Pringle]] and [[Guy Carleton, 1st Baron Dorchester|Carleton]])
| Did not participate in main action
|-
| {{HMS|Carleton|1776|2}} (schooner, 12)
| [[James Richard Dacres (1749–1810)|James Dacres]]
| Heavily damaged October 11
|-
| {{HMS|Loyal Convert||2}} ([[gundalow]], 7)
| Edward Longcroft
| Also called ''Royal Convert'' or ''Loyal Consort''&lt;ref name=&quot;malcolmson27note&quot; group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;[[#Malcolmson|Malcolmson (2001)]], on page 27 shows an image of a contemporary British draft document describing the ''Loyal Convert'', where it is clearly readable by that name.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 28 unnamed gunboats (gunboat, 1)
| unknown
| One destroyed October 11; many others damaged, two lost after action
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; |Ship descriptions and dispositions are from [[#Nelson|Nelson (2006)]], p.&amp;nbsp;33. Note that from the early beginnings of the U.S. Navy there had been no standard method of referring to U.S. Navy ships until 1907, when President [[Theodore Roosevelt]] issued [[Executive Order]] 549 on 8 January stating that all US Navy ships were to be referred to as &quot;The name of such vessel, preceded by the words, United States Ship, or the letters U.S.S., and by no other words or letters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=USN Ship Naming|publisher=[[Naval History &amp; Heritage Command]]|date=29 September 1997|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/faqs/faq63-1.htm
|accessdate=12 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|American Revolutionary War}}
* [[List of American Revolutionary War battles]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=Note|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==Bibliography==
{{colbegin|2}}
*{{cite book|first=Gardner W|last=Allen|title=A Naval History of the American Revolution|volume=Volume 1|location=Cambridge, Massachusetts|publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin]]|year=1913|ref=Allen|url=https://books.google.com/?id=hFsSAAAAYAAJ|oclc=2613121}}
*{{cite book|title=The Gondola Philadelphia and the Battle of Lake Champlain|first=John R|last=Bratten|publisher=Texas A&amp;amp;M University Press|year=2002|isbn=978-1-58544-147-1|ref=Bratten|oclc=48003125|location=College Station, Texas}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.lcmm.org/shipwrecks_history/Valcour_Bay_Research_Project.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120416192436/http://www.lcmm.org/shipwrecks_history/Valcour_Bay_Research_Project.pdf |archivedate=April 16, 2012 |title=Valcour Bay Research Project: 1999-2004 Results from the Archaeological Investigation of a Revolutionary War Battlefield in Lake Champlain, Clinton County, New York |publisher=[[Lake Champlain Maritime Museum]] |date=March 2007 |author1=Cohn, Arthur B. |author2=Kane, Adam I. |author3=Sabick, Christopher R. |author4=Scollon, Edwin R. |author5=Clement, Justin B. |accessdate=2016-04-17 |ref=Cohn}}
*{{cite book|first=Edward|last=Hamilton|title=Fort Ticonderoga, Key to a Continent|ref=Hamilton|publisher=Little, Brown|location=Boston|year=1964|oclc=965281}}
*{{cite book|title=Saratoga: Turning Point of America's Revolutionary War|first=Richard M|last=Ketchum|publisher=Henry Holt|year=1997|isbn=978-0-8050-6123-9|ref=Ketchum|location=New York|oclc=41397623}}
*{{cite book|last=Martin|first=James Kirby|year=1997|title=Benedict Arnold: Revolutionary Hero (An American Warrior Reconsidered)|publisher=New York University Press|isbn=0-8147-5560-7|ref=martin}} (This book is primarily about Arnold's service on the American side in the Revolution, giving overviews of the periods before the war and after he changes sides.)
*{{cite book|title=Benedict Arnold's Navy|first=James L|last=Nelson|publisher=McGraw Hill|year=2006|location=New York|isbn=978-0-07-146806-0|oclc=255396879|ref=Nelson}}
*{{cite book|title=Warships of the Great Lakes 1754–1834|first=Robert|last=Malcolmson|ref=Malcolmson|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=2001|isbn=1-55750-910-7|oclc=47213837|location=Annapolis, Maryland}} (This work contains detailed specifications for most of the watercraft used in this action, as well as copies of draft documents for some of them.)
*{{cite book|title=Sea of Glory: The Continental Navy fights for Independence|first=Nathan|last=Miller|publisher=David McKay|year=1974|isbn=0-679-50392-7|ref=Miller|oclc=844299|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|title=Quebec 1775: The American Invasion of Canada|first=Brendan|last=Morrissey|others=Hook, Adam [translator]|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2003|isbn=978-1-84176-681-2|ref=Morrissey|oclc=52359702|location=Oxford}}
*{{cite book|first=Willard Sterne|last=Randall|year=1990|title=Benedict Arnold: Patriot and Traitor|publisher=William Morrow and Inc|isbn=1-55710-034-9|ref=Randall}}
*{{cite book|title=The Sailing Navy, 1775–1854: 1775–1854|first=Paul H|last=Silverstone|ref=Silverstone|publisher=CRC Press|year=2006|isbn=978-0-415-97872-9|oclc=63178925|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Justin H|title=Our Struggle for the Fourteenth Colony|volume=Volume 2|year=1907|url=https://books.google.com/?id=19VBAAAAIAAJ|location=New York|publisher=G.P. Putnam's Sons|ref=Smith14II|oclc=259236}}
*{{cite book|title=Canada Invaded 1775–1776|first=George|last=Stanley|year=1973|publisher=Hakkert|ref=Stanley|isbn=978-0-88866-578-2|location=Toronto|oclc=4807930}}
*{{cite book|title=Bulletin of the New York State Museum, Issue 313|publisher=New York State Museum|year=1937|location=Albany|oclc=1476727|ref=NYSM313}}
*{{cite news|title=War Ship Remains Piled in City Garage|newspaper=WHTM Television|date=2009-03-03|ref=WHTM}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.lcbp.org/factsht/basinfs2006.pdf |accessdate=2010-04-27 |publisher=Lake Champlain Basin Program |title=Fact Sheet #3 |ref=LCPB_FactSheet |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100926223311/http://lcbp.org/factsht/Basinfs2006.pdf |archivedate=2010-09-26 |df= }}
*{{cite web|url=http://tps.cr.nps.gov/nhl/detail.cfm?ResourceId=648&amp;ResourceType=Structure
| title = National Historic Landmark summary listing – Philadelphia (gundelo) |accessdate=2010-05-17|publisher=National Park Service|ref=nhlsumPhil}}
*{{cite web|url=http://tps.cr.nps.gov/nhl/detail.cfm?ResourceId=364&amp;ResourceType=Site
| title = National Historic Landmark summary listing – Valcour Bay|accessdate=2010-05-17|publisher=National Park Service|ref=nhlsumBay}}
*{{NRISref|version=2010a}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.lcmm.org/shipwrecks_history/shipwrecks/spitfire.htm|accessdate=2010-05-13|title=Shipwrecks of Lake Champlain: Gunboat Spitfire|publisher=Lake Champlain Maritime Museum|ref=LCMM_Spitfire}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.historiclakes.org/pdf/cannon_in_time.pdf |title=The Battle of Valcour Island: A Burst Cannon Reflects a Moment in Time |publisher=America's Historic Lakes |ref=AHL_cannon |accessdate=2016-04-17}}
{{colend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|first=William M|last=Fowler, Jr.|authorlink=William M. Fowler, Jr.|title=Rebels Under Sail: The American Navy During the Revolution|publisher=[[Charles Scribner's Sons]]|year=1976|ref=Fowler|isbn=978-0-684-14583-9|oclc=1863602|location=New York}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090215064229/http://www.nps.gov:80/maritime/nhl/nmieval.html Other maritime landmarks] from the National Park Service
*[http://www.historiclakes.org/Valcour/valcour_chart.htm James P. Millard's detailed historical charts, list of ships, period images, and modern photographs]
**[http://historiclakes.org/Valcour/Valcour.html Battle of Valcour Island with pictures]
**[http://historiclakes.org/Valcour/valcour_island.htm The Story of Lake Champlain's Valcour Island]
*[http://www.lcmm.org/mri/projects/vbrp.htm Valcour Bay Research Project] of the [http://www.lcmm.org/index.htm Lake Champlain Maritime Museum]

{{New York in the American Revolutionary War}}
{{featured article}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Valcour Island, Battle of}}

[[Category:1776 in the United States]]
[[Category:Clinton County, New York]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1776]]
[[Category:Naval battles of the American Revolutionary War]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving the United States]]
[[Category:New York in the American Revolution]]
[[Category:Lake Champlain]]
[[Category:1776 in New York]]</text>
      <sha1>1xlr58hal4jkxukfgdrkfs8uii6r9ns</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
