<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Barnet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>50072</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729398266</id>
      <parentid>728793951</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-11T22:47:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender235</username>
        <id>88026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up; http-&gt;https (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51115">{{Use British English|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Barnet
|partof=the [[Wars of the Roses]]
|image=[[File:MS Ghent - Battle of Barnet retouched.jpg|256px|alt=Two groups of black armoured knights, mounted and on foot, charge at each other, fighting with swords and lances.]]
|caption=Late 15th-century artistic portrayal of the battle: Edward IV (left), wearing a circlet and mounted on a horse, leads the Yorkist charge and pierces the Earl of Warwick (right) with his lance; in reality, Warwick was not killed by Edward.
|date=14 April 1471
|place=North of [[Chipping Barnet|Barnet]], England
|result=Yorkist victory
|combatant1=[[File:Yorkshire rose.svg|20px|alt=White rose]] [[House of York]]
|combatant2=[[File:Lancashire rose.svg|20px|alt=Red rose]] [[House of Lancaster]]
|commander1=[[File:Royal Arms of England (1399-1603).svg|20px]] [[Edward IV of England|Edward IV]]&lt;br&gt; [[File:Arms of Richard, 1st Duke of Gloucester.svg|20px]] [[Richard III of England|Richard, Duke of Gloucester]]&lt;br&gt; [[File:Coat of Arms of Sir William Hastings, 1st Baron Hastings, KG.png|20px]] [[William Hastings, 1st Baron Hastings|William, Lord Hastings]]
|commander2=[[File:Neville Warwick Arms.svg|20px]] [[Richard Neville, 16th Earl of Warwick|Richard Neville, Earl of Warwick]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt; [[File:Neville.svg|20px]] [[John Neville, 1st Marquess of Montagu|John Neville, Marquess of Montagu]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt; [[File:Arms of John Holland, 2nd Duke of Exeter.svg|20px]] [[Henry Holland, 3rd Duke of Exeter|Henry Holland, Duke of Exeter]]&lt;br&gt; [[File:Coat of arms of Sir John de Vere, 13th Earl of Oxford.png|20px]] [[John de Vere, 13th Earl of Oxford|John de Vere, Earl of Oxford]]
|strength1=7,000&amp;ndash;15,000
|strength2=10,000&amp;ndash;30,000
|casualties1=Approx. 500
|casualties2=Approx. 1,000
}}
{{Campaignbox Wars of the Roses}}

The '''Battle of Barnet''' was a decisive engagement in the [[Wars of the Roses]], a dynastic conflict of [[England in the Middle Ages|15th-century England]]. The military action, along with the subsequent [[Battle of Tewkesbury]], secured the throne for [[Edward IV of England|Edward IV]]. On 14 April 1471 near [[Chipping Barnet|Barnet]], then a small Hertfordshire town north of London, Edward led the [[House of York]] in a fight against the [[House of Lancaster]], which backed [[Henry VI of England|Henry VI]] for the throne. Leading the Lancastrian army was [[Richard Neville, 16th Earl of Warwick]], who played a crucial role in the fate of each king. Historians regard the battle as one of the most important clashes in the Wars of the Roses, since it brought about a decisive turn in the fortunes of the two houses. Edward's victory was followed by fourteen years of Yorkist rule over England.

Formerly a key figure in the Yorkist cause, Warwick defected to the Lancastrians over disagreements about Edward's [[nepotism]], secret marriage, and foreign policy. Leading a Lancastrian army, the earl defeated his former allies, forcing Edward to flee to [[Burgundian Netherlands|Burgundy]]. The Yorkist king persuaded his host, [[Charles the Bold]], to help him regain the English throne. Leading an army raised with Burgundian money, Edward launched his invasion of England, which culminated at the fields north of Barnet. Under cover of darkness, the Yorkists moved close to the Lancastrians, and clashed in a thick fog at dawn. As both armies fought, the [[John de Vere, 13th Earl of Oxford|Earl of Oxford]] on the Lancastrian right routed the Yorkists opposite under [[William Hastings, 1st Baron Hastings|Lord Hastings]], chasing them back to Barnet. On their return to the battlefield, Oxford's men were [[Friendly fire|erroneously shot at]] by the Lancastrian centre commanded by [[John Neville, 1st Marquess of Montagu|Lord Montague]].  As cries of treason (always a possibility in that chaotic period) spread through their line, Lancastrian morale was disrupted and many abandoned the fight. While retreating, Warwick was killed by Yorkist soldiers.

Warwick had been such an influential figure in 15th-century English politics that, on his death, no one matched him in terms of power and popularity. Deprived of Warwick's support, the Lancastrians suffered their final defeat at the Battle of Tewkesbury on 4 May 1471, which marked the downfall of the House of Lancaster and the ascendancy of the House of York. Three centuries after the Battle of Barnet, a stone obelisk was raised on the spot where Warwick purportedly died.

==Background==
{{further|Wars of the Roses}}
The Wars of the Roses were a series of conflicts between various English lords and nobles in support of two different royal families. In 1461, the conflict reached a milestone when the [[House of York]] supplanted its rival, the [[House of Lancaster]], as the ruling royal house in England. [[Edward IV of England|Edward IV]], leader of the Yorkists, seized the throne from the Lancastrian king, [[Henry VI of England|Henry VI]],{{Sfn|Ross|1997|pp=37&amp;ndash;38}} who was captured in 1465 and imprisoned in the [[Tower of London]].{{Sfn|Carpenter|2002|p=162}} The Lancastrian queen, [[Margaret of Anjou]], and her son, [[Edward of Westminster, Prince of Wales|Edward of Lancaster]], fled to Scotland and organised resistance.{{Sfn|Carpenter|2002|p=149}} Edward IV crushed the uprisings, and pressured the Scottish government to force Margaret out; the House of Lancaster went into exile in France.{{Sfn|Carpenter|2002|p=161}} As the Yorkists tightened their hold over England, Edward rewarded his supporters, including his chief adviser, [[Richard Neville, 16th Earl of Warwick]], elevating them to higher titles and awarding them land confiscated from their defeated foes.{{Sfn|Carpenter|2002|pp=157&amp;ndash;158}} The Earl grew to disapprove of the King's rule, however, and their relationship later became strained.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=104}}

Warwick had planned for Edward to marry a French princess&amp;mdash;[[Bona of Savoy]]&amp;mdash;to create an alliance between the two countries.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=91}} The young king, however, favoured ties with [[County of Burgundy|Burgundy]], and, in 1464, further angered the Earl by secretly marrying [[Elizabeth Woodville]]; as an impoverished Lancastrian widow, she was regarded by the Yorkists as an unsuitable queen.{{Sfn|Ross|1999|p=11}} At her request, Edward bestowed gifts of land and titles on her relations and arranged marriages to rich and powerful families. Eligible bachelors were paired with the Woodville females, narrowing the marriage prospects for Warwick's daughters. Furthermore, the Earl was offended by two matches involving his kin. The first was the marriage of his aunt, [[Lady Katherine Neville]], over 60&amp;nbsp;years old, to Elizabeth's 20-year-old brother, [[John Woodville]], a pairing considered outside of normal wedlock by many people. The other was his nephew's fiancée, the daughter of [[Henry Holland, 3rd Duke of Exeter]], who was taken as a bride by the Queen's son, [[Thomas Grey, 1st Marquess of Dorset|Thomas Grey]], with Edward's approval.{{Sfn|Carpenter|2002|pp=170&amp;ndash;171}} Exasperated by these acts, Warwick decided the Woodvilles were a malignant influence on his liege.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=99}} He felt marginalized: his influence over the young king was failing, and he decided to take drastic action to force Edward's compliance.{{Sfn|Ross|1999|pp=11&amp;ndash;12}} Warwick's alternative plan was to replace the King with his fellow conspirator, the [[George Plantagenet, 1st Duke of Clarence|Duke of Clarence]], Edward's younger brother.{{Sfn|Ross|1999|pp=12&amp;ndash;14}}

Instigating several rebellions in the north, Warwick lured the King away from his main bastion of support in the south. Edward found himself outnumbered; while retreating, he learned that Warwick and Clarence had called for open support of the rebellion. After winning the [[Battle of Edgecote Moor]] on 26 July 1469, the Earl found the Yorkist king deserted by his followers, and brought him to [[Warwick Castle]] for &quot;protection&quot;.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=103}} Lancastrian supporters took advantage of Edward's imprisonment to stage uprisings. Because most Yorkist-aligned warlords refused to rally to Warwick's call, the Earl was pressured to release the King.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|pp=69&amp;ndash;70}} Back in power, Edward did not openly pursue Warwick's transgressions against him, but the Earl suspected that the King held a grudge. Warwick engineered another rebellion, this time to replace Edward with Clarence.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|pp=279&amp;ndash;282}} The two conspirators, however, had to flee to France when Edward crushed the uprising&amp;mdash;the [[Battle of Losecoat Field]]&amp;mdash;on 12 March 1470. Through letters in the rebels' possession and confessions from the leaders, the King uncovered the Earl's betrayal.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|p=285}} In a deal brokered by the French king, [[Louis XI of France|Louis XI]], the Earl agreed to serve Margaret and the Lancastrian cause. Warwick invaded England at the head of a Lancastrian army and, in October 1470, forced Edward to seek refuge in Burgundy, then ruled by the King's brother-in-law [[Charles the Bold]]. The throne of England was temporarily restored to Henry VI;{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|pp=74&amp;ndash;75}} on 14 March 1471, Edward brought an army back across the English Channel, precipitating the Battle of Barnet a month later.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=76}}

==Commanders==

===Yorkist===
Edward IV was normally at the forefront of his armies. Standing {{convert|6|ft|3|in|m|abbr=on}}, he was an inspiring figure in combat, attacking foes while wearing a suit of gilded armour. Medieval texts describe the King as handsome, finely muscled and with a broad chest.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=10}} He was personable and charismatic, easily winning people to his cause. Edward was a capable tactician and leader in battles. He frequently spotted and exploited defensive frailties in enemy lines, often with decisive results.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=20}} By 1471, the young king was a highly respected field commander.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=77}} He received some criticism, however; after winning the throne in 1461, he proved indecisive about putting down rebellions.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=20}} Historian [[Charles Ross (historian)|Charles Ross]] praises Edward's leadership and skill in close combat rather than his strategies and tactics.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=176}} With his good looks and capable leadership, Edward was popular among the common people, especially compared to Henry VI.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|pp=9&amp;ndash;11}} His trade policies, which aimed to expand and protect markets for English commerce, pleased local merchants, who were also won over by the Yorkist king's personality.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|pp=353&amp;ndash;360}} By 1469, Edward's groundswell of popular support had eroded away. The euphoria of a change in government had ebbed and the people blamed Edward for failing to &quot;bring the realm of England in[to] great popularity and rest&quot; and allowing Yorkist nobles to go unpunished for abuses.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|pp=124&amp;ndash;125}} When Edward invaded England in 1471, not many common people openly celebrated his return.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=158}}

Edward was joined at Barnet by his brothers, [[Richard III of England|Richard, Duke of Gloucester]], and George, Duke of Clarence. Unlike his eldest brother, Gloucester was slender and seemingly delicate.{{Sfn|Ross|1999|p=139}} He was 18 years old at the Battle of Barnet, his first major engagement. His military prowess, however, was well respected; many historians judge him a capable warrior and military leader.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=20}} Clarence was not as well regarded as his brothers, especially in matters of loyalty. When Edward became king, Clarence was chosen as his heir; however, the births of [[Elizabeth of York]] (1466) and [[Edward V of England|Edward V]] (1470) displaced the Duke in the line of succession to the throne.{{Sfn|Ross|1999|p=13}}  Hence, Clarence participated in Warwick's schemes, marrying the Earl's daughter [[Isabel Neville, Duchess of Clarence|Isabella]], believing he could gain his brother's throne. Clarence lost faith in the Earl when Warwick defected to the Lancastrians and married off his other daughter, [[Anne Neville|Anne]], to their prince in order to cement his new allegiance. When Edward launched his campaign to retake England, Clarence accepted his brother's offer of pardon and rejoined the Yorkists at Coventry on 2 April 1471.{{Sfn|Royle|2008|pp=227&amp;ndash;228}} The last of the Yorkist commanders was [[William Hastings, 1st Baron Hastings|William, Lord Hastings]], a loyal subject since the start of the wars. Hastings had accompanied the young king in exile and supported his return. The courtier was rewarded for his faithfulness, gaining the [[lieutenancy of Calais]] in 1471, and becoming Edward's lord chamberlain and primary confidant.{{Sfn|Richmond|2000|pp=144, 146}}

===Lancastrian===
Warwick had fought for the House of York since the early stages of the Wars of the Roses and alongside his cousin, Edward IV, in many of the battles. His years of loyalty earned him the trust of the Yorkists, and his victories&amp;mdash;both political and military&amp;mdash;and popularity with the common people made him an important figure.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|pp=1&amp;ndash;6}} He had powerful influence over the line of succession, earning him the nickname &quot;the Kingmaker&quot;. Early historians described him as a military genius, but by the 20th century his tactical acumen was reconsidered; [[Philip A. Haigh|Philip Haigh]] suspects that the Earl largely owed some of his victories, such as the [[First Battle of St Albans]], to being in the right place at the right time.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=13}} [[Christopher Gravett]] believes the Earl was too defensive and lacked mental flexibility.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=21}}

[[File:Warwick prepping for Barnet.jpg|thumb|upright|left|alt=A wax figure of a man stands, preparing for battle. The figure sports a bowl cut and wears a khaki doublet and dark brown breeches. At its legs is the wax figure of a kneeling squire.|The Earl of Warwick prepares for the battle in this [[diorama]] at [[Warwick Castle]].]]

[[John Neville, 1st Marquess of Montagu]], was less ambitious than his brother Warwick, but a more capable warrior and tactician. In 1464, he commanded a Yorkist force that turned the tables on a Lancastrian ambush at the [[Battle of Hedgeley Moor]], and launched a surprise attack at the [[Battle of Hexham]].{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=21}} These victories capped Neville's extensive service in the north, and Edward rewarded him with the Earldom of [[Northumberland]], which bore substantial income.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|p=61}} The gift was particularly gratifying for Neville; his family had experienced a [[Percy–Neville feud|deep feud]] with the former [[Earl of Northumberland|earls of Northumberland]], the Percys, who supported the House of Lancaster. However, in March 1470, Edward, trying to win over the Percys' support, reinstated [[Henry Percy, 4th Earl of Northumberland|Henry Percy]] to the earldom. As recompense, Neville received the grander title of Marquess of Montagu; however, the lands accompanying this rank were much poorer than the estate he had lost.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|pp=144&amp;ndash;145}} The new marquess saw it as an insult&amp;mdash;an insubstantial title that was inadequate recognition for his years of faithful service.{{Sfn|Royle|2008|p=216}}  Montagu did not immediately join Warwick's rebellion, however; he defected later in the year when his brother invaded England.{{Sfn|Carpenter|2002|p=177}}

Not much is known about the early history of [[John de Vere, 13th Earl of Oxford]], another Lancastrian commander; the chronicles mention little about him until the Battle of Losecoat Field. His father, the previous earl and a loyal Lancastrian, was executed for a failed plot to assassinate Edward IV. The Yorkist king tried to secure the loyalty of Oxford by knighting him and pardoning his transgressions. This tactic failed; Oxford remained true to the Lancastrian crown and participated in Warwick's effort to dethrone Edward.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=65}} Historians describe the young Oxford as a decent military leader, exemplified by his conduct in the Battle of Barnet.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=22}}

Although Henry Holland, 3rd Duke of Exeter, was of royal blood,{{Sfn|Wolffe|2001|p=274}} he was commonly viewed as a criminal,{{Sfn|Harriss|2007|p=206}} prone to violence and stupidity.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=17}} A proven enemy of the Nevilles,{{Sfn|Wolffe|2001|p=289}} Exeter bore a grudge particularly against Warwick for displacing him from his hereditary role of [[Admiralty|Lord High Admiral]] in 1457.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|p=133}} Nonetheless, when Warwick joined the Lancastrians, Exeter obeyed Margaret and served under the Earl during the invasion of England.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|pp=302&amp;ndash;303}} Although he supported the Lancastrian cause, Exeter had family ties to the House of York; he was husband to [[Anne of York, Duchess of Exeter|Anne of York]], Edward's sister.{{Sfn|Ross|1999|p=336}}

[[Edmund Beaufort, 4th Duke of Somerset]], was a prominent Lancastrian and one of Margaret's trusted men. Interactions between Somerset and Warwick were less than cordial; the Nevilles and Beauforts had been feuding over estates since the early 1450s.{{Sfn|Wolffe|2001|p=269}} Adding to their animosity was the death of Somerset's father, the [[Edmund Beaufort, 2nd Duke of Somerset|2nd Duke]], at the First Battle of St Albans. The Yorkists won the engagement, after Warwick slipped his force past the Lancastrian defence and attacked from behind.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|pp=11&amp;ndash;12}} The Beauforts largely blamed the Earl for the Duke's death. Somerset is listed in early chronicles as a participant in the Battle of Barnet; however, this has been disputed. When the Lancastrians retook England, Warwick ordered the duke to watch over Henry VI in London. Several historians, such as Ross and [[Anthony Goodman (historian)|Anthony Goodman]], agree that Somerset left London to welcome Margaret in the south.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|p=164}}{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=78}} Michael Jones points out that the Duke is recorded as having been in [[Salisbury]] on the day of the battle, trying to recruit townsmen for the Lancastrian cause.{{Sfn|Jones|Underwood|1993|p=55}} Trevor Royle suggests that due to Somerset's distrust of Warwick, the Duke would rather await his queen and her army than voluntarily aid the Earl.{{Sfn|Royle|2008|p=227}} Therefore, it is unlikely that he fought at [[Chipping Barnet|Barnet]].{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=22}}

==Prelude==
On 14 March 1471, Edward's army landed at [[Ravenspurn]]. Gathering more men as they went, the Yorkists moved inland towards York. Edward's march was unopposed at the beginning because he was moving through lands that belonged to the Percys, and the Earl of Northumberland was indebted to the Yorkist king for the return of his northern territory. Furthermore, Edward announced that he was returning only to claim his father's title of Duke of York and not to contest the English crown.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|pp=115&amp;ndash;117}} The ruse was successful: Montagu, who was monitoring Edward's march, could not convince his men to move against the Yorkist king.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|p=307}}

Once Edward's force had gathered sufficient strength, he dropped the ruse and headed south towards London. Fighting off Exeter's and Oxford's attacks, he besieged Warwick at [[Coventry]], hoping to engage the earl in battle. Although Warwick's force had more men than Edward's army, the earl refused the challenge. He was waiting for the arrival of Clarence, who wanted to use their combined strength to overwhelm the Yorkists. When he learned of this, Edward sent Gloucester to entreat Clarence to return to the House of York, an offer that Clarence readily accepted. Reconciled, the royal brothers moved towards Coventry, and Clarence urged Warwick's surrender.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|pp=164&amp;ndash;165}} Infuriated with his son-in-law's treachery, Warwick refused to speak to Clarence. Unable to fight the earl at this time, Edward turned again towards London.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|pp=117&amp;ndash;118}}

[[File:Late 15th-century armour.jpg|alt=An dummy wearing 15th-century armour and holding a mace in its right hand|thumb|right|Nobles in the Battle of Barnet wore [[Plate armour|composite field armour]] like this suit exhibited at the [[Royal Armouries Museum]].{{Sfn|Wise|1983|pp=21, 39&amp;ndash;40}}]]

Reinforced by Montagu, Oxford, and Exeter a few days later, Warwick followed the Yorkists' trail.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|pp=308&amp;ndash;309}} He hoped that London, under Somerset's control, would close its gates to Edward, allowing him to catch the Yorkist army in the open. The city, however, welcomed Edward warmly; Somerset had left the city, and the London populace preferred the young Yorkist king to Henry VI.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|pp=118&amp;ndash;119}}{{Sfn|Royle|2008|p=229}} The old king greeted his usurper warmly and offered himself into custody, trusting &quot;[his] life to be in no danger in [Edward's] hands.&quot;{{Sfn|Wolffe|2001|p=345}} Lancastrian scouts probed Barnet, which lay {{convert|19|km|mi}} north of London, but were beaten off. On 13 April their main army took up positions on a ridge of high ground north of Barnet to prepare for battle the next day. Warwick arrayed his army in a line from east to west, on either side of the [[A1 road (Great Britain)#Origins and history|Great North Road]] running through Barnet.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=119}} Oxford held the right flank and Exeter the left. Montagu commanded the centre, and Warwick readied himself to command from among the reserves.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=120}} The earl displaced his entire line slightly to the west; a depression at the rear of his left flank could impede Exeter's group if they had to fall back.{{Sfn|English Heritage|1995|p=3}}

Warwick's army heavily outnumbered Edward's, although sources differ on exact numbers. Lancastrian strength ranges from 10,000 to 30,000 men, with 7,000 to 15,000 on the Yorkist side.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=79}}{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=28}}{{Sfn|Royle|2008|p=230}} Facing this disadvantage, Edward hurried to meet the Lancastrians with a surprise attack.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=79}} He brought Henry VI along to prevent the Lancastrians from retaking their king. Edward reached Barnet in the evening, and without knowing the precise location of his foes, prepared the battle line.{{Sfn|Burne|1950|p=109}} The Yorkist king deployed Hastings on the left and entrusted Gloucester to lead the right flank. Clarence would fight alongside Edward in the centre, although this was not due to faith in his ability&amp;mdash;it was easier for the Yorkists to keep an eye on their twice-defected prince there. A contingent of reserves was kept at the rear, ready to deploy at Edward's call.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=121}} As night fell, Edward put his plan for surprise morning attack in motion. Under a strict order of silence, the Yorkist army crept closer to the Lancastrians.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|pp=34, 36}} During the night, neither commander spotted the opposing army, an event that proved crucial in the battle the next day.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=119}}{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|pp=78&amp;ndash;79}}

During the night, Warwick ordered his cannons to continually bombard the estimated position of the Yorkists' encampment. The Yorkists, however, had sneaked in close, and the Lancastrian artillery overshot their enemies. The Yorkist cannon, meanwhile, kept quiet to avoid betraying their location.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=119}} As the armies settled down to rest, Montagu approached his brother and advised him of the troops' low morale. He suggested that, as the highest-ranking commanders, the brothers should fight on foot throughout the battle instead of riding on horse. The soldiers believed that mounted commanders tended to abandon them when the situation deteriorated. By staying on foot, the Nevilles would show that they were prepared to fight to the death with the men, inspiring the troops to stand and fight harder. Warwick agreed and the horses were tethered to the rear, near Wrotham Wood.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=123}}

==Fighting in the mist==
[[File:Battle of Barnet, early-battle.svg|thumb|upright|left|alt=Map of the battlefield: in the middle, four red boxes, depicting the Lancastrians, are above four white boxes, denoting the Yorkists. Arrows extend from the boxes on the right flanks of each force, showing their movements.|Early battle: Oxford led the Lancastrian (red) right wing to outflank the Yorkists' (white) left and routed it southwards. Gloucester, likewise, advanced through [[Monken Hadley]] to attack the Lancastrians' left.]]

On 14 April 1471, at around 4&amp;nbsp;o'clock in the morning, both armies woke. Edward had planned for an early attack, however, and quickly roused his men to engage the Lancastrians.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=79}} Both sides fired their cannon and arrows before laying into each other with polearms. The morning fog was thick and the night movements of the two forces had displaced them laterally with each other. Neither group was facing the other; each was offset slightly to the right. This displacement meant that the right end of either army could outflank the other by wrapping around the opposing left end. The Lancastrians were the first to exploit this advantage; Oxford's group quickly overwhelmed Hastings'. Yorkist soldiers fled towards Barnet, chased by the Lancastrians. Some of Hastings' men even reached London, spreading tales of the fall of York and a Lancastrian victory. Oxford's group disintegrated as they split off to loot the fallen enemies and plunder Barnet.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|pp=121&amp;ndash;122}} Yelling and chasing after his men, Oxford rallied 800 of them and led them back to the battle.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=79}}

Due to the fog, visibility was low and the two main forces failed to notice Oxford's victory over Hastings. As such, the collapse of the Yorkist left wing had little (if any) effect on morale of either side.{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=79}} The fighting between Montagu's and Edward's groups was evenly matched and intense. The Lancastrian left wing, however, was suffering treatment similar to that Oxford had inflicted on its counterpart; Gloucester exploited the misaligned forces and beat Exeter back.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=121}} Progress for Edward's brother was slow because his group was fighting up a slight slope.{{Sfn|Seymour|1997|p=158}} Nonetheless, the pressure he exerted on the Lancastrian left wing rotated the entire battle line. Warwick, seeing the shift, ordered most of his reserves to help ease the pressure on Exeter, and took the rest into fighting at the centre.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=121}} Gradually, the battle line settled to an orientation that slanted north-east to south-west.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=41}}

Oxford retraced his steps through the fog back to the fight. His group arrived, unexpectedly, at Montagu's rear.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=40}} Obscured by the fog, Oxford's &quot;[[Star (heraldry)|star with rays]]&quot; badge was mistaken by Montagu's men, who believed it was Edward's &quot;[[sun in splendour]]&quot;.{{Sfn|Brooke|1857|p=208}}  They assumed their allies were Edward's reserves and unleashed a volley of arrows. Oxford and his men immediately cried treachery; as staunch Lancastrians, they were wary of Montagu's recent defection. They struck back and began withdrawing from the battle. Their shouts of treason were taken up and spread quickly throughout the Lancastrian line, breaking it apart as men fled in anger, panic, and confusion. As the fog started to dissipate, Edward saw the Lancastrian centre in disarray and sent in his reserves, hastening its collapse. Cries of Exeter's demise from a Yorkist axe resounded across the battlefield from the Lancastrian left, and amidst the confusion, Montagu was struck in his back and killed by either a Yorkist or one of Oxford's men.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=122}}

[[File:Battle of Barnet, late-battle.svg|thumb|upright|right|alt=Map of the battlefield in the late stage: the boxes that represent Hastings' and Oxford's forces are at the bottom. Their arrows show Hasting's retreat and Oxford's return to the main battle just above the middle of the map.|Late battle: as the fighting continued, the battle line rotated, and Oxford returned to a line that was oriented mostly north-east to south-west.]]

Witnessing his brother's death, Warwick knew the battle was lost. He made for the horses in an attempt to retreat. Edward recognised his victory was at hand, and&amp;mdash;deciding that Warwick was more valuable alive than dead&amp;mdash;sent the order and dispatched his guards to bring back the earl alive.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|pp=122&amp;ndash;123}} Several chroniclers have suggested that the king thought Warwick would again be a valuable ally if persuaded back to the Yorkist cause. Historian [[Michael Hicks (historian)|Michael Hicks]], on the other hand, suggests that Edward wanted to capture the earl for public execution, rather than as a gesture of mercy.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|p=310}} Regardless of the king's intent, Warwick died in the Lancastrian rout.
A miniature model reproduction of the Battle of Barnet can be found at the Battle's natural interpretive centre, [[Barnet Museum#Collections|The Barnet Museum]].{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=123}}

==Post-battle==
The battle lasted from two to three hours, and was over by the time the fog lifted in the early morning. As usual in most battles of the time, the routed army suffered the most casualties; fleeing men were cut down from behind. Contemporary sources give various casualty figures; the 'Great Chronicle of London' reports 1,500&amp;nbsp;dead, whereas 'Warkworth's Chronicle' states 4,000.  [[Edward Hall]] and [[Raphael Holinshed]], both 16th century chroniclers, say that at least 10,000&amp;nbsp;men died in the battle.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|pp=47&amp;ndash;48}} The Yorkists suffered half as many casualties as the Lancastrians. Royle favours the recorded approximate figures of 500&amp;nbsp;Yorkists and 1,000&amp;nbsp;Lancastrians dead.{{Sfn|Royle|2008|p=231}}

The bodies of the two Neville brothers were brought back to London. They did not suffer the customary fate accorded to traitors&amp;mdash;[[Hanged, drawn and quartered|quartering]] and display at the city gates. Edward exhibited the brothers' naked corpses in [[St. Paul's Cathedral]] for three days to quell any rumours that they had survived, before allowing them to be laid to rest in the family vault at [[Bisham Abbey]].{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=124}}

[[File:Battle of Barnet lithograph.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Mounted knights chase their enemies off to the right, across a river.|1885 lithograph portraying the rout of Warwick's forces in the manner of [[The Battle of San Romano|Paolo Uccello]]]]

Although he had defeated the Neville brothers, Edward had little time to rest; Margaret landed at [[Weymouth, Dorset|Weymouth]] on the day of the battle. She feigned a march to London while augmenting her army with recruits from Wales and the [[Welsh Marches]].{{Sfn|Goodman|1990|p=80}} The Lancastrian queen was disheartened by the news of Warwick's demise, but Somerset suggested that they were better off without the earl.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=125}} Despite the defeat at Barnet, Lancastrians who fled from the battle looked to the queen to restore their house to the throne.{{Sfn|Richmond|2000|p=143}} Alerted by his spies to the Lancastrians' true route, Edward intercepted and defeated them at the [[Battle of Tewkesbury]] on 4 May 1471. Gloucester, Clarence, and Hastings again fought to defend the Yorkist crown.{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|pp=128&amp;ndash;129}}

Exeter had been stripped of his armour and left for dead on the battlefield at Barnet, but he was alive&amp;mdash;though gravely injured. His followers found him and took him to [[Westminster Abbey]]. On his recovery, he was imprisoned in the Tower of London for four years before submitting to Edward's rule.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=46}} Exeter did not participate in the later battles of the Wars of the Roses. Edward sent him on a Yorkist expedition to France in 1475, and the duke was reported to have fallen overboard and drowned without any witnesses.&lt;ref&gt;Griffiths, R A. &quot;Foreword to the Yale Edition&quot; in {{Harvnb|Ross|1997|p=xvi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After withdrawing from the battle, Oxford fled to France and participated in piracy of English ships, continuing his campaign against Yorkist reign. He was eventually captured in 1473 after conquering [[St Michael's Mount]], an island off the south-west coast of England. Twelve years later, Oxford escaped from prison and joined [[Henry VII of England|Henry Tudor]]'s fight against the Yorkists, commanding the Lancastrian army at the [[Battle of Bosworth Field]] in 1485.{{Sfn|Britnell|1997|p=101}}

==Legacy==
The Battle of Barnet was an important engagement in the Wars of the Roses: it brought about the death of a prominent figure and secured the throne for another.{{refn|Warwick Castle was classified as a national monument and converted to a tourist attraction in the 20th century. One of its major exhibits, &quot;Kingmaker&amp;mdash;A Preparation for Battle&quot;, features [[diorama]]s displaying preparations by the earl and his household for the Battle of Barnet.{{Sfn|Kettler|Trimble|2003|pp=163&amp;ndash;164}}|group=nb}} Despite its importance to history, contemporary records about the battle are rare.{{Sfn|Burne|1950|p=108}} The sole [[chronicle]] based on an eyewitness account&amp;mdash;''[[Historie of the arrivall of Edward IV|The Arrivall of Edward IV]]''&amp;mdash;was written by someone within Edward's council, which presents a biased account of the battle.{{Sfn|Hicks|1995|pp=21&amp;ndash;22}}{{refn|''The Arrivall'' was written to promote and celebrate Edward's superiority. Besides presenting supernatural approvals of Edward's venture&amp;mdash;the miracle of St Anne, it approved Edward's violation of [[sanctuary]] after the Battle of Tewkesbury and claimed that Henry VI died just after Tewkesbury, where his sole heir had been killed, due to &quot;pure displeasure and melancoly&quot;.{{Sfn|Hicks|1995|pp=21&amp;ndash;22}}|group=nb}} Another first-hand observation was found in the [[Paston Letters]], written by the Lancastrian Sir John Paston.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|p=9}} Other records, such as ''The Warkworth Chronicle'', offer only bits and pieces about the battle. Therefore, deficits in historical understanding must be filled through field research and discoveries of mediaeval documents.{{Sfn|Hicks|1995|pp=21&amp;ndash;22}}

Historians theorise that had Warwick's force joined Margaret's before challenging Edward, the combined Lancastrian army would have overwhelmed the Yorkists. Instead, Warwick's defeat gave the Yorkists a victory so decisive that it, along with the Battle of Tewkesbury, secured the English throne for Edward IV.{{Sfn|Ross|1997|pp=172, 175&amp;ndash;176}} Historian Colin Richmond believes that Edward's return to power was assured at Barnet&amp;mdash;Tewkesbury was &quot;merely an epilogue&quot;.{{Sfn|Richmond|2000|p=143}} Without having to contend with Warwick's popularity and political influence, the young Yorkist king could fully exert his will and rule the land unchallenged. Ballads composed during Edward's reign celebrated his victory as sanctioned by God: &quot;Man proposes, oftimes in veyn, But God disposes, the boke telleth pleyn&quot;.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|p=311}} Barnet was a disaster for the Nevilles; their lands given away and their offices reduced. The family never again reached the prominence in English politics that they had enjoyed before the battle.{{Sfn|Hicks|2002|p=312}}

===Shakespearian dramatisation===
[[File:The Death of the Earl of Warwick (frame, bw).jpg|thumb|upright|alt=A man, wearing armour and a surcoat, lies on the ground. His helmet is off, and his face is turned towards a kneeling knight, who is supporting him. Standing behind the two is another knight, whose sword and shield are held at the ready.|''[[Henry VI, Part 3]]'': Warwick, dying at the Battle of Barnet, speaks his last words.]]

The battle is alluded to in [[William Shakespeare]]'s ''[[Henry VI, Part 3]]'' (1595).{{Sfn|Martin|Shakespeare|2001|pp=9&amp;ndash;10}} The end of Act V, scene one depicts the events leading up to the battle; scenes two and three portray the conclusion, in which the characters discuss the combat and the fates of its participants. Shakespeare uses few details reported by contemporary chroniclers and ignores notable incidents, such as the confusion over Oxford's and Edward's badges.{{Sfn|Goy-Blanquet|2003|p=131}} His play is based mostly on poetic and dramatic sources. In the play, Montagu is killed while trying to save his brother (Shakespeare's source material included Hall's 1548 ''The Union of the Two Noble and Illustrate Famelies of Lancastre and Yorke''),{{Sfn|Ross|1999|p=xlvi}}{{Sfn|Goy-Blanquet|2003|p=169}} and Warwick is dragged in by Edward IV and left to speak his dying words to Oxford and Somerset.{{Sfn|Goy-Blanquet|2003|p=124}} Warwick's death dominates the scenes, reflecting Hall's vivid portrayal of the earl's passing as a valiant death.{{Sfn|Edelman|1992|p=78}} Furthermore, whereas several chronicles mention Edward's desire to capture Warwick, Shakespeare has the Yorkist king lustily demand Warwick's skin.{{Sfn|Goy-Blanquet|2003|p=169}}

Shakespeare presents the Nevilles as brothers who are willing to die for each other, whereas the three sons of York&amp;mdash;Edward, Gloucester, and Clarence&amp;mdash;are slowly driven apart by their own goals and ideas.{{Sfn|Martin|Shakespeare|2001|pp=51&amp;ndash;63}} Professor of English John Cox suggests that Shakespeare did not share the impression given in post-battle ballads that Edward's triumph was divinely ordained. He argues that Shakespeare's placement of Clarence's last act of betrayal immediately before the battle suggests that Edward's rule stems from his military aggression, luck, and &quot;policy&quot;.{{Sfn|Cox|2007|p=112}} Shakespeare also explicitly excludes Edward from action sequences, a departure from Hall's depictions.{{Sfn|Edelman|1992|p=79}}

===Battlefield===
[[File:Hadley Highstone cropped.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=A column of stone stands on a square base.|Hadley Highstone, [[Monken Hadley]]: an obelisk erected to mark the battle and the spot where Warwick the Kingmaker died]]

[[English Heritage]], a government body in charge of conservation of historic sites, roughly locates the battlefield in an area 800 to 1600&amp;nbsp;metres (0.5 to 1.0 mile) north of the town of Barnet. Over the centuries, much of the terrain has changed, and records of the town's boundaries and geography are not detailed enough for English Heritage or historians to conclude the exact location of the battle. Geographical features corresponding to contemporary descriptions allow approximations of where the fighting took place.{{refn|Gravett, however, states that due to the extensive build-up and remodelling of the town, even these elements are suspect and may not correlate to 15th-century features.{{Sfn|Gravett|2003|pp=89&amp;ndash;90}}|group=nb}}

English Heritage suggests that a 15th-century letter from a [[Hanseatic League|Hanseatic]] merchant, Gerhard von Wessel, helps to identify the battlefield via geological features. It mentions a &quot;broad green&quot; which corresponds to [[Hadley Green]], and the marsh on the right flank of the Yorkist line is likely to be in the valley of the Monken Mead brook. The letter also mentions St Albans road, which has remained largely the same, winding through the fields. Urbanisation over the 18th and 19th centuries, however, has populated much of the area with buildings. By the 20th century, the suburb of [[Monken Hadley]] covered part of the fields where the Battle of Barnet was fought.{{Sfn|English Heritage|1995|pp=1&amp;ndash;2}} A hedge in the local golf course, as suggested by Lieutenant-Colonel [[Alfred Burne|Alfred H. Burne]], is likely the row of shrubs behind which Oxford's men lined up and took cover.{{Sfn|English Heritage|1995|p=7}}

In 1740, Sir Jeremy Sambroke erected an obelisk to commemorate the battle about {{convert|200|m|ft}} south of the junction between the Great North Road and Kitts End Road. It was later moved just north of the junction on the grass between the two roads. Known as Hadley Highstone, it stands {{convert|5.5|m|ft}} tall and marks its location with the inscription:{{Sfn|Brooke|1857|p=211}}
{{quote|&quot;Here was fought the Famous Battle Between Edward the 4th and the Earl of Warwick April the 14th ANNO 1471 in which the Earl was Defeated And Slain.&quot;{{Sfn|Haigh|1995|p=120}}}}

The battle is referred to in the [[coat of arms of the London Borough of Barnet]] which display a red and a silver rose in the top of the shield and two crossed swords in the crest.

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=nb}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth = 40em}}

== Bibliography ==
'''Books'''
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book |last=Britnell |first=Richard |title=The Closing of the Middle Ages?: England, 1471&amp;ndash;1529 |year=1997 |publisher=[[Blackwell Publishing|Blackwell Publishers]] |location=Oxford |isbn=0-631-16598-3 |chapter=Country Politics |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Brooke |first=Richard |title=Visits to Fields of Battle, in England, of the Fifteenth Century: To which are Added Some Miscellaneous Tracts and Papers Upon Archaeological Subjects |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vwAHAAAAQAAJ |accessdate=28 January 2009 |year=1857 |publisher=John Russell Smith |location=London |oclc=43406489 |chapter=The Field of the Battle of Barnet |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=vwAHAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA205 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Burne |first=Alfred |authorlink=Alfred Burne |title=The Battlefields of England |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IzwOAAAAQAAJ |accessdate=8 February 2009 |year=1950 |publisher=[[Methuen Publishing|Methuen and Company]] |location=London |oclc=3010941 |chapter=The Battle of Barnet, April&amp;nbsp;14th, 1471 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=IzwOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA108 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Carpenter |first=Christine |title=The Wars of the Roses: Politics and the Constitution in England, c. 1437&amp;ndash;1509 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z0A9frbkU0MC |accessdate=16 March 2009 |series=Cambridge Medieval Textbooks |year=2002 |origyear=1997 |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |location=New York |isbn=0-521-31874-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Cox |first=John |title=Seeming Knowledge: Shakespeare and Skeptical Faith |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fxXDYBc7BesC |accessdate=8 February 2009 |year=2007 |publisher=[[Baylor University|Baylor University Press]] |location=Texas |isbn=1-932792-95-3 |chapter=History and Guilt |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=fxXDYBc7BesC&amp;pg=PA112  |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Edelman |first=Charles |title=Brawl Ridiculous: Swordfighting in Shakespeare's Plays |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SNnYAAAAIAAJ |accessdate=12 April 2009 |year=1992 |publisher=[[Manchester University Press]] |location=Manchester |isbn=0-7190-3507-4 |chapter=The Wars of the Roses: 2 and 3 Henry VI, Richard III |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=SNnYAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA69 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Goodman |first=Anthony |authorlink=Anthony Goodman (historian) |title=The Wars of the Roses: Military Activity and English Society, 1452&amp;ndash;97 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=F8wOAAAAQAAJ |accessdate=6 March 2009 |year=1990 |origyear=1981 |publisher=[[Taylor and Francis]] |location=London |isbn=0-415-05264-5 |chapter=Local Revolts and Nobles' Struggles, 1469&amp;ndash;71 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=F8wOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA66 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Goy-Blanquet |first=Dominique |title=Shakespeare's Early History Plays: From Chronicle to Stage |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=K_8hd8MEthIC |accessdate=8 February 2009 |year=2003 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-811987-9 |chapter=Unhappy Families |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=K_8hd8MEthIC&amp;pg=PA120 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Gravett |first=Christopher |authorlink=Christopher Gravett |title=Tewkesbury 1471: The Last Yorkist Victory |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ok1Ql8fCLKAC |accessdate=16 January 2009 |series=Campaign |volume=131 |year=2003 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |location=Oxford |isbn=1-84176-514-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Haigh |first=Philip |authorlink=Philip A. Haigh |title=The Military Campaigns of the Wars of the Roses |edition=Hardcover |year=1995 |publisher=[[The History Press|Sutton Publishing]] |location=Gloucestershire, United Kingdom |isbn=1-85833-770-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Harriss |first=Gerald |authorlink=G. L. Harriss |title=Shaping the Nation: England 1360&amp;ndash;1461 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Wd5tzn3krsC |accessdate=5 April 2009 |year=2007 |origyear=2005 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-921119-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Hicks |first=Michael |authorlink=Michael Hicks (historian)|editor-last=Pollard |editor-first=Anthony |title=The Wars of the Roses |series=Problems in Focus |year=1995 |publisher=MacMillan Press |location=London |isbn=0-333-60166-1 |chapter=The Sources |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Hicks |first=Michael |title=Warwick the Kingmaker |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vfCqZl_7ZDwC |accessdate=12 February 2009 |year=2002 |origyear=1998 |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |location=Oxford |isbn=0-631-23593-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last1=Jones |first1=Michael |last2=Underwood |first2=Malcolm |title=The King's Mother: Lady Margaret Beaufort, Countess of Richmond and Derby |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dV4NDnis7yQC |accessdate=8 March 2009 |year=1993 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-44794-1 |chapter=The Wars of the Roses |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=dV4NDnis7yQC&amp;pg=PA35 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last1=Kettler |first1=Sarah |last2=Trimble |first2=Carole |title=The Amateur Historian's Guide to the Heart of England: Nearly 200 Medieval and Tudor Sites Two Hours or Less from London |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8a86j9YqOzgC |accessdate=9 March 2009 |year=2003 |publisher=Capital Books |location=Virginia, United States |isbn=1-892123-65-7 |chapter=Warwickshire |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=8a86j9YqOzgC&amp;pg=PA155 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last1=Martin |first1=Randall |last2=Shakespeare |first2=William |authorlink2=William Shakespeare |title=Henry VI: Part Three |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Gaq66XrJU60C |accessdate=8 February 2009 |series=Oxford World's Classics |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-283141-0 |chapter=Introduction |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=Gaq66XrJU60C&amp;pg=PA1 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Richmond |first=Colin |title=The Paston Family in the Fifteenth Century: Endings |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ni4pNh87eo4C |accessdate=18 March 2009 |series=The Paston Family in the Fifteenth Century |volume=3 |year=2000 |publisher=Manchester University Press |location=Manchester |isbn=0-7190-5990-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Ross |first=Charles |authorlink=Charles Ross (historian) |title=Edward IV |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m8Ojo6VI8KUC |accessdate=16 March 2009 |edition=revised |series=Yale English Monarchs |year=1997 |origyear=1974 |publisher=[[Yale University Press]] |location=[[New Haven, Connecticut]]; and London |isbn=0-300-07372-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Ross |first=Charles |title=Richard III |series=Yale English Monarchs |origyear=1981 |year=1999 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven, Connecticut; and London |isbn=0-300-07979-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Royle |first=Trevor |title=Lancaster Against York: The Wars of the Roses and the Foundation of Modern Britain |year=2008 |publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] |location=Hampshire, United Kingdom |isbn=1-4039-6672-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Seymour |first=William |title=Battles in Britain and Their Political Background, 1066&amp;ndash;1746 |year=1997 |origyear=1975 |publisher=Wordsworth Editions |location=Hertfordshire, United Kingdom |isbn=1-85326-672-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Wise |first=Terence |title=The Wars of the Roses |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=E_Akk9YPgOMC |accessdate=16 January 2009 |series=Men-at-Arms Series |volume=145 |year=1983 |publisher=Osprey Publishing |location=Oxford |isbn=0-85045-520-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Wolffe |first=Bertram |title=Henry VI |series=Yale English Monarchs |year=2001 |origyear=1981 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven, Connecticut; and London |isbn=0-300-08926-0 |ref=harv}}
{{Refend}}

'''Online sources'''
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/content/imported-docs/a-e/barnet.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131127034056/http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/content/imported-docs/a-e/barnet.pdf |archivedate=2013-11-27 |title=English Heritage Battlefield Report: Barnet 1471 |accessdate=2 February 2009 |year=1995 |format=PDF |work= |publisher=[[English Heritage]] |location=Swindon, United Kingdom |ref=CITEREFEnglish_Heritage1995}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of Barnet}}
* {{Cite book |editor1-last=Bruce |editor1-first=John |title=Historie of the Arrivall of Edward IV, in England and the Finall Recouerye of His Kingdomes from Henry VI. A.D. M.CCCC.LXXI |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091014194842/http://www.r3.org/bookcase/arrival1.html |accessdate=13 February 2009 |year=1838 |publisher=John Bowyer Nichols, and Son |location=London |oclc=602067 }}
* {{Cite book |last1=de Commynes |first1=Philippe |editor1-last=Scoble |editor1-first=Andrew |title=The Memoirs of Philip de Commines, Lord of Argenton: Containing the Histories of Louis XI, and Charles VIII, Kings of France, and of Charles the Bold, Duke of Burgundy. To which is Added the Scandalous Chronicle, Or, Secret History of Louis XI |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sstnAAAAMAAJ |pages=199&amp;ndash;203 |accessdate=13 March 2009 |year=1855 |publisher=Henry G. Boyn |location=London |oclc=13897813 }}
* {{Cite book |last1=Warkworth |first1=John |editor1-last=Halliwell |editor1-first=James Orchard |title=The Warkworth Chronicle: Part VI |url=http://www.r3.org/bookcase/warkwort/worthvi.html |accessdate=27 February 2009 |year=1839 |publisher=John Bowyer Nichols, and Son |location=London |oclc=916993 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090326002135/http://www.r3.org/bookcase/warkwort/worthvi.html| archivedate= 26 March 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}
* [http://www.barnetsociety.org.uk/ The Barnet Society] 
{{Wars of the Roses}}

{{Coord|51|39|44|N|0|12|00|W|type:event_region:GB_source:enwiki|display=title}}
{{Featured article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Barnet}}
[[Category:1471 in England]]
[[Category:Battles of the Wars of the Roses|Barnet 1471]]
[[Category:History of Barnet]]
[[Category:Battles and military actions in London]]
[[Category:Registered historic battlefields in England]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1471]]</text>
      <sha1>heat9dx89piebe1bctrh8kmc47qd9zr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
