<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bert T. Combs</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6036140</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749671978</id>
      <parentid>747659143</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-15T16:33:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acdixon</username>
        <id>2133469</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early life */ link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="54237">{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name = Bert T. Combs
|image = Bert-Combs.jpg
|caption = Combs in 1960
|office = Judge of the [[Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals]]
|term_start = April 5, 1967
|term_end = June 5, 1970
|nominator = [[Lyndon B. Johnson]]
|predecessor = [[Shackelford Miller, Jr.]]
|successor = [[W. Wallace Kent]]
|order2 = 50th
|office2 = Governor of Kentucky
|lieutenant2 = [[Wilson W. Wyatt]]
|term_start2 = December 8, 1959
|term_end2 = December 10, 1963
|predecessor2 = [[Happy Chandler|A. B. &quot;Happy&quot; Chandler]]
|successor2 = [[Edward T. Breathitt]]
|birth_name=Bertram Thomas Combs
|birth_date = August 13, 1911
|birth_place = [[Manchester, Kentucky]]
|death_date = {{death date and age|1991|12|4|1911|8|13}}
|death_place = [[Powell County, Kentucky]]
|restingplace = Beech Creek Cemetery
|party = [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]]
|spouse = {{marriage|Mabel Hall|1937|1969|divorce}}&lt;br/&gt;{{marriage|Helen Clark Rechtin|1969|1986|divorce}}&lt;br/&gt;{{marriage|[[Sara Walter Combs|Sara Walter]]|1988|1991}}
|religion = [[Baptist]]
|alma_mater = [[University of Kentucky]]
|profession = Lawyer
|branch       = [[United States Army|U.S. Army]]
|serviceyears = 1943–1946
|rank         = [[Captain (United States)|Captain]]
|unit         = 
|commands     = 
|battles      = World War II
|awards       = [[Bronze Star Medal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Military Merit Medal of Philippines]]
}}

'''Bertram &quot;Bert&quot; Thomas Combs''' (August 13, 1911{{spaced ndash}}December 4, 1991) was a [[judge|jurist]] and politician from the [[U.S. state]] of [[Kentucky]]. After serving on the [[Kentucky Court of Appeals]], he was elected the [[List of Governors of Kentucky|50th]] [[Governor of Kentucky]] in 1959 on his second run for the office. Following his gubernatorial term, he was appointed to the [[Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals]] by [[President of the United States|President]] [[Lyndon B. Johnson]], serving from 1967 to 1970.

Combs rose from poverty in his native [[Clay County, Kentucky]], to obtain a law degree from the [[University of Kentucky]] and open a law practice in [[Prestonsburg, Kentucky|Prestonsburg]]. He was [[Awards and decorations of the United States military|decorated]] for prosecuting [[Japan]]ese war criminals before military tribunals during [[World War II]], then returned to Kentucky and his law practice. In 1951, Governor [[Lawrence Wetherby]] appointed him to fill a vacancy on the Kentucky Court of Appeals. Later that year, he was elected to a full term on the court, defeating former governor and judge [[Simeon S. Willis]]. Kentucky's [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] had split into two factions by 1955 when [[Earle C. Clements]], the leader of one faction, chose Combs to challenge [[Happy Chandler|A. B. &quot;Happy&quot; Chandler]], who headed the other, in the upcoming gubernatorial primary. Combs' uninspiring speeches and candidness about the need for more state revenue cost him the [[primary election]]. Chandler, who went on to win the governorship, had promised that he would not need to raise taxes to meet the state's financial obligations, but, ultimately, he did so. This damaged Chandler's credibility and left Combs looking courageous and honest in the eyes of the electorate. Consequently, in 1959, Combs was elected governor, defeating [[Harry Lee Waterfield]], Chandler's choice to succeed him in office, in the primary. Early in his term, Combs secured passage of a three percent [[sales tax]] to pay a bonus to the state's military veterans. Knowing a tax of one percent would have been sufficient, he used the excess revenue to enact a system of reforms including expansion of the state's highway and [[List of Kentucky state parks|state park]] systems. He also devoted much of the surplus to education.

Following his term in office, Combs was appointed to the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals by President Johnson. He served for three years before resigning and running for governor again in 1971. He lost in the Democratic primary to [[Wendell H. Ford]], his former executive secretary. In 1984, Combs agreed to represent sixty-six of the state's poor school districts in a lawsuit challenging the state's system of financing public education. The suit, ''Rose v. Council for Better Education'', resulted in the [[Kentucky Supreme Court]] declaring the state's entire system of public schools unconstitutional. In response, the [[Kentucky General Assembly]] drafted a sweeping education measure known as the [[Kentucky Education Reform Act#Kentucky Education Reform Act (KERA)|Kentucky Education Reform Act]] in 1991. On December 3, 1991, Combs was caught in a [[flash flood]] while driving home from his law office. His body was found in the [[Red River (Kentucky)|Red River]] near [[Rosslyn, Kentucky|Rosslyn]], in [[Powell County, Kentucky|Powell County]], the following morning. The coroner determined that he died of [[hypothermia]].

==Early life==
The Combs family was one of the oldest European families in the United States. John Combs, the family patriarch, arrived in [[Jamestown, Virginia]], in 1619, and in 1775, Benjamin John Combs came westward from [[Virginia]] into [[Clark County, Kentucky]]. He was followed into Kentucky in 1790 by two of his brothers, including Jack Combs, Bert Combs' great-grandfather.&lt;ref name=pearce56&gt;Pearce, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;

Bert Combs was born in the Town Branch section of [[Manchester, Kentucky]], on August 13, 1911; he was one of seven children of Stephen Gibson and Martha (Jones) Combs.&lt;ref name=lhl&gt;&quot;Combs Rose to Pinnacle From Plain Beginnings&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Combs' father Stephen, a part-time [[logging|logger]] and farmer, was active in local politics, despite being a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]] in a county where a large majority of residents were [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]s.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; His mother was a teacher, and she impressed upon her children the importance of a good education.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; Bert's first school was the two-room Beech Creek [[grade school]].&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; When he reached the [[seventh grade]], his parents sent him and his sister to [[Oneida Baptist Institute]] in nearby [[Oneida, Kentucky]] because its school term was 8 to 9 months long, as opposed to the 5- to 6-month terms at Beech Creek.&lt;ref name=robinson9&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; Later, Combs and his sister began riding a donkey every day to [[Clay County High School]].&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; Combs excelled academically and skipped some grades, graduating as [[valedictorian]] of his class in 1927 at age 15.&lt;ref name=robinson10&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

Unable to afford college tuition, Combs worked at a local drug store and did small jobs for various residents of his community.&lt;ref name=&quot;robinson10&quot; /&gt; In 1929, his mother arranged for him to work at a coal company in [[Williamsburg, Kentucky]], and attend [[University of the Cumberlands|Cumberland College]] (then a [[junior college#United States|junior college]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;robinson10&quot; /&gt; The coal company job did not materialize, but Combs was able to afford three semesters at Cumberland by sweeping floors and firing furnaces in campus buildings.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt;&lt;ref name=robinson11&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-1930, he began working as a clerk for the state highway department.&lt;ref name=ukaa&gt;&quot;Bert T. Combs&quot;. Hall of Distinguished Alumni.&lt;/ref&gt; This was one of several patronage jobs that were usually awarded by the governor, but the Democratically controlled [[Kentucky General Assembly|state legislature]] had stripped Republican Governor [[Flem D. Sampson]] of his statutory appointment powers, giving them instead to a three-man highway commission composed of Democratic [[Lieutenant Governor of Kentucky|Lieutenant Governor]] [[James Breathitt, Jr.|James Breathitt]], Democratic Highway Commissioner [[Ben Johnson (politician)|Ben Johnson]], and Dan Talbott.&lt;ref name=robinson12&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; This allowed Combs, a Democrat, to secure the position.&lt;ref name=robinson8&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

Combs worked for the highway department for three years in order to earn enough money to attend the [[University of Kentucky College of Law]] in [[Lexington, Kentucky|Lexington]].&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt; While at the university, he was managing editor of the ''Kentucky Law Journal''.&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt; In 1937, he graduated second in his class, earning a [[Bachelor of Laws]] degree and qualifying for the [[Order of the Coif]], a national [[honor society]] for the top ten percent of graduating law students.&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt;&lt;ref name=nga&gt;&quot;Kentucky Governor Bert Thomas Combs&quot;. National Governors Association.&lt;/ref&gt; He was [[Admission to the bar in the United States|admitted to the bar]], and returned to Manchester to begin practicing law.&lt;ref name=ho6&gt;&quot;Bertram Thomas Combs (1911–1991)&quot;. History of the Sixth Circuit&lt;/ref&gt; It was also in 1937 that Combs married Mabel Hall, with whom he had two children, [[Lois Combs Weinberg|Lois Ann Combs]] and Thomas &quot;Tommy&quot; George Combs.&lt;ref name=kye217&gt;Harrison, p. 217&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early legal career and service in World War II==
Of his law practice in Manchester, Combs later noted: &quot;I had too many kinfolks and friends in Manchester, and they all expected me to handle things as a favor&amp;nbsp;... Then they'd get their feelings hurt if I charged them. I was taking in a lot of cases, but not sending out many bills.&quot;&lt;ref name=pearce58&gt;Pearce, p. 58&lt;/ref&gt; In 1938, Combs accepted an offer from a law school classmate named LeRoy Combs (no relation) to join his father and uncle's law firm in [[Prestonsburg, Kentucky|Prestonsburg]].&lt;ref name=robinson16&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; Prestonsburg was closer to his wife's home in [[Knott County, Kentucky|Knott County]].&lt;ref name=robinson16 /&gt; Combs' son Tommy suffered from a form of [[mental retardation]], the result of an injury sustained at birth.&lt;ref name=kypost&gt;&quot;Bert Combs Missing, Feared Dead&quot;. ''The Kentucky Post''&lt;/ref&gt; After moving to Prestonsburg, Combs started a class for individuals with mental retardation, in part so Tommy could attend the class.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt;

On December 22, 1943, Combs enlisted as a [[private (rank)|private]] in the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] for service in [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=harmon27&gt;Harmon, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; He received his basic training at [[Fort Knox]] and participated in the Volunteer Officer Candidate Program, which would have allowed him to attend [[Officer Candidate School (U.S. Army)|Officer Candidate School]] (OCS) immediately after basic training.&lt;ref name=robinson16 /&gt;&lt;ref name=harmon27 /&gt; Instead, he was briefly assigned to teach [[cartography]] at the [[Aberdeen Proving Ground]] in [[Aberdeen, Maryland]] before completing OCS in [[Ann Arbor, Michigan]], joining the [[Judge Advocate General's Corps]], and attaining the rank of [[Captain (United States)|captain]].&lt;ref name=nga /&gt;&lt;ref name=harmon27 /&gt; On July 1, 1945, he was sent to the [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|South Pacific]].&lt;ref name=harmon27 /&gt; He served as chief of the War Crimes Investigating Department under General [[Douglas MacArthur]] in the [[Philippine Islands]], conducting tribunals for Japanese [[war crimes|war criminals]].&lt;ref name=nga /&gt; Upon his discharge in 1946, he was awarded the [[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]] and the [[Military Merit Medal (Philippines)|Military Merit Medal of the Philippines]].&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt;&lt;ref name=ho6 /&gt;

After the war, Combs returned to Prestonsburg, forming the law firm of Howard and Combs with J. Woodford Howard as his partner.&lt;ref name=ho6 /&gt;&lt;ref name=kygovs196&gt;Robinson in ''Kentucky's Governors'', p. 196&lt;/ref&gt; He served as president of the Junior Bar Association of Kentucky in 1946 and 1947.&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt; Combs often represented coal companies in [[workers' compensation]] cases against [[Carl D. Perkins]], later a [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. Representative]], who served as legal counsel for the mine workers.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt;

==Political career==
Combs began his political career with his election to the office of [[city attorney]] in Prestonsburg in 1950.&lt;ref name=jusc&gt;&quot;Combs, Bertram Thomas&quot;. ''History of the Sixth Circuit''&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, Governor [[Lawrence Wetherby]] appointed him to fill a vacancy in the office of [[Commonwealth's Attorney]] for Kentucky's 31st Judicial District.&lt;ref name=jusc /&gt;&lt;ref name=robinson20&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; Combs announced, however, that he would serve only until a new election could be held.&lt;ref name=robinson20 /&gt; In April 1951, Governor Wetherby appointed Combs to fill a vacancy on the [[Kentucky Court of Appeals]] caused by the death of Judge Roy Helm.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; Later that year, he sought a full eight-year term on the court.&lt;ref name=pearce59&gt;Pearce, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; His opponent was [[Simeon S. Willis]], a popular former Republican governor who had previously sat on the court.&lt;ref name=pearce59 /&gt; Combs won the election by a vote of 73,298 to 69,379.&lt;ref name=pearce59 /&gt; In George Robinson's oral history, Combs attributed his victory to Willis's advanced age (68) and the fact that many of Willis' supporters assumed that their candidate would win and did not vote.&lt;ref name=robinson22&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;

===1955 gubernatorial race===
[[Happy Chandler|A.B. &quot;Happy&quot; Chandler]], who had served as Kentucky's governor from 1935 to 1939 and was a leader of a faction of the state's Democratic Party, announced his intention to seek a second term in 1955. Members of the anti-Chandler faction scrambled to find a candidate to oppose him. The most likely candidate was [[Emerson Beauchamp|Emerson &quot;Doc&quot; Beauchamp]], the sitting lieutenant governor, but Beauchamp was not a good campaigner and his ties to [[Logan County, Kentucky|Logan County]] &amp;ndash; where politics were dominated by sometimes-corrupt [[political boss]]es &amp;ndash; gave the anti-Chandler faction pause. Instead, the leader of the faction, former governor and sitting [[United States Senate|U.S. Senator]] [[Earle C. Clements]], selected Combs as the faction's nominee, and Combs resigned from his position on the Court of Appeals to enter the race.&lt;ref name=nhok403&gt;Harrison and Klotter, p. 403&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Happy Chandler - Harris and Ewing Crop.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Happy Chandler]], Combs' opponent in the 1955 gubernatorial race|alt=A black-and-white photo of a man in his fifties wearing a suit]]
In Combs' first speech of the [[primary election|primary]] campaign, he admitted that the state needed to raise $25&amp;nbsp;million (${{Inflation|US|25|1955}} million in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars) in new revenue and that a [[sales tax]] should be considered.&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt;&lt;ref name=nhok403 /&gt; Chandler, the more experienced politician, attacked Combs for this suggestion, maintaining that an experienced governor like himself would not need to raise taxes to meet the state's obligations.&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt; Combs' speech was also attacked as dry and uninspiring, partly because he read it verbatim from prepared notes.&lt;ref name=nhok403 /&gt; &quot;And you said ''I'' couldn't give a speech,&quot; Doc Beauchamp later complained to Clements.&lt;ref name=nhok403 /&gt; Hugh Morris, chief of the ''[[Louisville Courier-Journal]]'''s [[Frankfort, Kentucky|Frankfort]] bureau, commented that &quot;Combs opened and closed his campaign on the same night&quot;.&lt;ref name=pearce64&gt;Pearce, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt;

With little but Combs' inexperience to run against, Chandler portrayed Combs as a pawn of former governors Clements and Wetherby, whom he derisively nicknamed &quot;Clementine&quot; and &quot;Wetherbine&quot;.&lt;ref name=nhok403 /&gt; He accused both administrations of wasteful spending, specifically attacking the construction of the [[Kentucky Turnpike]] and [[Freedom Hall]] as unnecessary expenditures.&lt;ref name=nhok403 /&gt; Some of Chandler's attacks were more personal in nature; he charged that when Clements was governor, he spent $20,000 (${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|20000|1955}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars) on a new rug for his office, and that Wetherby had used African [[mahogany]] to panel his office, instead of &quot;good, honest Kentucky wood&quot;.&lt;ref name=nhok403 /&gt;&lt;ref name=pearce6162&gt;Pearce, pp. 61–62&lt;/ref&gt; Though receipts later showed that carpeting for the entire first floor of the [[Kentucky State Capitol|capitol]] had cost only $2,700 and that Wetherby's paneling had been purchased from and installed by a Kentucky contractor, Chandler's charges remained effective at keeping the Combs campaign on the defensive.&lt;ref name=pearce6162 /&gt;

Two weeks before the primary, Combs was endorsed by former [[Vice-President of the United States|Vice-President]] and native Kentuckian [[Alben W. Barkley]], but Combs felt the endorsement came too late to be much help.&lt;ref name=pearce65&gt;Pearce, p. 65&lt;/ref&gt; Chandler defeated Combs in the primary by a vote of 259,875 to 241,754 and went on to win his second term as governor.&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt; Combs returned to Prestonsburg, set up a [[savings and loan]] company, and re-established his law practice.&lt;ref name=pearce65 /&gt; During the four years of Chandler's term, Combs accepted a number of speaking engagements, but otherwise remained out of the public eye.&lt;ref name=pearce66&gt;Pearce, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the state's need for funds compelled Chandler to raise the state sales tax and other taxes, despite his campaign promises not to do so.&lt;ref name=kygovs197&gt;Robinson in ''Kentucky's Governors'', p. 197&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, Chandler lost credibility and Combs gained a reputation as a courageous, forthright, and honest politician for having acknowledged the state's financial need during the campaign.&lt;ref name=kygovs197 /&gt;

===1959 gubernatorial race===
Barred by the [[Kentucky Constitution|state constitution]] from seeking consecutive terms, Chandler endorsed his lieutenant governor, [[Harry Lee Waterfield]], to succeed him.&lt;ref name=nhok406&gt;Harrison and Klotter, p. 406&lt;/ref&gt; [[Wilson Wyatt]], who had managed [[Adlai Stevenson II|Adlai Stevenson]]'s [[United States presidential election, 1952|presidential campaign in 1952]], was the first anti-Chandler candidate to declare his intention to seek the governorship in the 1959 election, doing so on April 9, 1958.&lt;ref name=robinson72&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; Wyatt received several endorsements from leaders in [[Jefferson County, Kentucky|Jefferson County]], which contained his home city of [[Louisville, Kentucky|Louisville]] and was vehemently anti-Chandler.&lt;ref name=robinson72 /&gt; Four days after Wyatt's announcement, Combs declared that he would again seek the office, and he was endorsed by Clements a week later.&lt;ref name=robinson72 /&gt; For the remainder of 1958, the anti-Chandler faction's support remained split between Wyatt and Combs.&lt;ref name=robinson73&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1959, Clements held an all-night meeting at the Standiford Airport Hotel in Louisville in which he brokered a deal whereby Combs would run for governor and Wyatt for lieutenant governor.&lt;ref name=nhok407&gt;Harrison and Klotter, p. 407&lt;/ref&gt; Clements promised Wyatt his support in future political races.&lt;ref name=nhok407 /&gt;

In the primary campaign against Waterfield, Combs attacked the Chandler administration.&lt;ref name=nhok407 /&gt; He was especially critical of a rumor which held that Chandler had placed a two-percent assessment on state employees' salaries and had stored the funds in a [[Cuba]]n bank so they could not be traced.&lt;ref name=nhok407 /&gt; According to the rumor, when [[Fidel Castro]] seized power during the [[Cuban Revolution]], the funds Chandler had deposited in Cuba were lost.&lt;ref name=nhok407 /&gt; Chandler countered on Waterfield's behalf with charges that Combs was a &quot;Clements parrot&quot;.&lt;ref name=nhok407 /&gt; Combs succeeded in uniting the anti-Chandler base, and defeated Waterfield by 25,000 votes; he went on to win the governorship that fall, defeating Republican nominee [[John M. Robsion, Jr.]] by 180,093 votes.&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt; The victory margin was a record for a governor's race in Kentucky, and was the second highest margin of victory for any election in the state, trailing only [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]'s 185,858-vote victory over [[Herbert Hoover]] in [[United States presidential election, 1932|1932]].&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt;&lt;ref name=pearce97&gt;Pearce, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt; Combs was the first governor elected from [[Eastern Mountain Coal Fields|Eastern Kentucky]] since Flem D. Sampson in 1927 and was the first veteran of World War II to hold the office.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt;&lt;ref name=powell104&gt;Powell, p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;

===Governor of Kentucky===
One of Combs' first official actions as governor was to call a special session of the legislature on December 19, 1959, to consider revising the state's constitution, which had been in effect since 1891. Calling a constitutional convention required that the General Assembly approve putting the issue of a convention on the ballot in two consecutive legislative sessions. The call then had to be approved by Kentucky voters. Despite near-universal agreement by legal scholars that the constitution was badly in need of updating, Kentucky voters had rejected calls for a constitutional convention in 1931 and 1947 and had only approved 19 amendments since 1891. Combs wanted to address the issue during his four-year term, hence the haste in calling the special legislative session. The General Assembly easily approved the call for a convention during the special legislative session and again during the subsequent regular legislative session in 1960. Combs signed the measure and the question of a constitutional revision was put on the ballot in November 1960, when Kentucky voters defeated it by a margin of almost 18,000 votes. This was the closest Kentucky has come to replacing the 1891 constitution, which remains in effect today.&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, pp. 102–103, 117, 157, 159&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;History of the Kentucky Unified Court System&quot;. Kentucky Court of Justice&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kentucky's first billion-dollar budget===
During the campaign, Combs had advocated a [[Progressivism in the United States|progressive platform]] that included increased funding for education, highways, parks, industry, and airports.&lt;ref name=kygovs198&gt;Robinson in ''Kentucky's Governors'', p. 198&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after his election, he won approval for a three-percent sales tax to pay a bonus to military veterans, although he could have funded the bonuses with a one-percent tax.&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt; He had asked for the larger tax in order to fund his other priorities.&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt; As a result of the sales tax, Combs presided over the state's first billion-dollar budget.&lt;ref name=nhok408 /&gt; One study showed that Kentucky doubled its per capita expenditures between 1957 and 1962, growing its appropriations faster than any other state.&lt;ref name=nhok408 /&gt; Combs held large public relations events for each tax-funded project that was completed, declaring in dedication speeches that the sales tax had made the project possible.&lt;ref name=kygovs198 /&gt;

[[File:Albert B. Chandler Hospital.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A red, four-story building with two eight-story towers rising above it|The Albert B. Chandler Hospital was completed with funds from Combs' first biennial budget.]]
In 1960, Kentucky had one of the highest dropout rates in the nation, and ranked second only to [[Arkansas]] in the number of one-room schools.&lt;ref name=pearce106&gt;Pearce, p. 106&lt;/ref&gt; Fewer than half of the state's high school graduates attended college.&lt;ref name=pearce106 /&gt; Many teachers educated in Kentucky sought higher salaries available in other states.&lt;ref name=pearce106 /&gt; Combs' biennial budget, passed by the General Assembly in 1960, used money from the new sales tax to increase school funds by fifty percent and establish the state community college system (now the [[Kentucky Community and Technical College System]]).&lt;ref name=nhok408 /&gt; It also increased funding for free textbooks by more than $3&amp;nbsp;million and allocated another $2&amp;nbsp;million to vocational education.&lt;ref name=pearce121&gt;Pearce, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt; It allocated over $5&amp;nbsp;million to the state universities for new buildings and another $10.5&amp;nbsp;million to fund completion of the [[Albert B. Chandler Hospital]], a facility at the [[University of Kentucky]] named in honor of Combs' political foe.&lt;ref name=pearce120&gt;Pearce, p. 120&lt;/ref&gt;

The state's roads were in poor condition when Combs became governor. The [[Automotive Safety Foundation]] found that two-thirds of Kentucky's federal roads were below standards for existing traffic demands.&lt;ref name=pearce106 /&gt; It further found that twenty percent of the state's major city streets were inadequate, that another fifty-five percent would soon be inadequate due to increasing traffic, and that half of the state's secondary roads were unfit for modern industrial traffic.&lt;ref name=pearce106 /&gt; To address these problems, Combs issued $100&amp;nbsp;million in bonds to increase funding for highways, appointing Earle Clements as state highway commissioner to oversee the correction of the road issues.&lt;ref name=nhok408 /&gt;&lt;ref name=pearce106 /&gt; One of the new roads, the [[Bert T. Combs Mountain Parkway|Mountain Parkway]], which connected Combs' native Eastern Kentucky to [[Central Kentucky]], was later renamed the Bert T. Combs Mountain Parkway in Combs' honor.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; Because of generous funding in Combs' budget, Kentucky finished its portions of the [[Interstate Highway System]] much sooner than surrounding states such as Virginia and [[Tennessee]].&lt;ref name=pearce111&gt;Pearce, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt;

Combs also won approval of a $10&amp;nbsp;million bond issue to benefit the [[List of Kentucky state parks|state parks]], which had poor lodging and few amenities. Combs combined the bond issue with $10&amp;nbsp;million in revenue bonds and effected major renovations at all 26 of the state's parks. Though his dreams of seeing privately owned tourist facilities spring up around the parks did not come to fruition, out-of-state tourism to Kentucky more than doubled during his administration, accounting for about sixty percent of state park visitors and fifty-three percent of the overnight visitations to the parks. Journalist John Ed Pearce recounts that Kentucky natives began to complain that they could not get reservations in the parks during peak seasons and called for limitations on the number of out-of-state visitors or a reservation system that favored Kentuckians, although nothing was done to address these complaints.&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, pp. 117–118&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Floral Clock Frankfort KY.png|thumb|right|300px|alt=A large clock with flowers on the face that reads &quot;Kentucky&quot; and has an outline of the state in the middle|The [[Floral clock (Frankfort, Kentucky)|floral clock in Frankfort]]]]
On April 10, 1961, Combs appropriated $50,000 from the governor's contingency fund to construct a [[Floral clock (Frankfort, Kentucky)|floral clock]] on the lawn of the state capitol.&lt;ref name=pearce135&gt;Pearce, p. 135&lt;/ref&gt; Combs had seen a similar clock in [[Edinburgh]], Scotland, and believed it would be a colorful addition to the capitol grounds.&lt;ref name=pearce135 /&gt; In a subsequent gubernatorial campaign, Happy Chandler mocked the clock, declaring &quot;Well, they don't say it's half past 2 in Frankfort anymore. They say it's two [[petunia]]s past the [[jimson weed]].&quot;&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; Chandler's derision became the minority view in time, however; according to John Ed Pearce, the clock became one of the most talked-about and visited tourist attractions in the state and the most visited place in Frankfort.&lt;ref name=pearce135 /&gt;

===Ethical reforms===
Combs created a [[merit system]] for state government workers, ensuring that officials could not be hired or fired for political reasons.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; This provision attracted more well-qualified individuals to public service careers.&lt;ref name=kygovs198 /&gt; Such careers were made even more attractive when, in 1962, the state courts declared that the salaries of state employees, the amounts of which were specified in the state constitution, could be adjusted for inflation.&lt;ref name=nhok408 /&gt; Combs demanded that state employees stick strictly to the rules governing their offices.&lt;ref name=kygovs199&gt;Robinson in ''Kentucky's Governors'', p. 199&lt;/ref&gt; In one instance, Combs ordered a state audit of [[Carter County, Kentucky|Carter County]] superintendent Heman McGuire, who was known to use his office for political gain.&lt;ref name=pearce131&gt;Pearce, p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; While Combs did not have the authority to remove McGuire directly, the audit showed McGuire's misappropriation of funds and abuse of power.&lt;ref name=pearce132&gt;Pearce, p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; The state school board investigated these findings and removed the county school board members from office; the replacement board members then ousted McGuire.&lt;ref name=pearce132 /&gt;

In 1961, a group of citizens from [[Newport, Kentucky]], asked Combs for help in cracking down on crime in their city. Just across the [[Ohio River]] from [[Cincinnati]], Newport had gained a reputation as a haven for prostitution, gambling, and illegal alcohol. After receiving an [[affidavit]] from the citizens, Combs sent agents from the department of Alcoholic Beverage Control to the city. They cited six bars for violating laws governing liquor sales, and instructed [[Attorney General of Kentucky|Attorney General]] [[John B. Breckinridge]] to prosecute four local officials for failure to enforce the laws. When allegations of civil rights violations in a related trial surfaced, [[United States Attorney General|U.S. Attorney General]] [[Robert Kennedy]] sent federal [[United States Department of Justice|Justice Department]] officials to Newport, prompting the resignation of the sheriff and a circuit judge. Two other local officials were barred from office for four years.&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, pp. 165, 167, 171&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of Combs' crackdowns on corruption were politically damaging, including the so-called &quot;truck deal&quot;. In 1961, Kyle Vance, a reporter for the ''Louisville Courier-Journal'' reported that the state was about to purchase some [[dump truck]]s from one of Combs' former campaign officials for $346,800, far more than they were worth, according to the report.&lt;ref name=robinson121&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 121&lt;/ref&gt; The newspaper, long antagonistic toward Highway Commissioner Clements, painted the deal as a political payoff orchestrated by the highway commissioner.&lt;ref name=robinson121 /&gt; In the interest of preserving his reputation as an honest governor, Combs canceled the proposed deal.&lt;ref name=nhok409&gt;Harrison and Klotter, p. 409&lt;/ref&gt; This angered Clements, who took Combs' action as a public rebuke.&lt;ref name=nhok409 /&gt; The incident caused a rift between him and Combs that never fully healed; Clements later resigned, ostensibly to work on the presidential campaign of his friend and former Senate colleague, [[Lyndon B. Johnson]].&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, pp. 138, 150&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter, he worked against Combs at every opportunity, even joining with Happy Chandler to ensure Wilson Wyatt's defeat in his [[United States Senate elections, 1962|1962 race for the Senate]], in a reversal of his previous promise to support Wyatt.&lt;ref name=nhok409 /&gt;

Combs also formed the state's first Human Rights Commission and ordered the [[desegregation]] of all public accommodations in Kentucky.&lt;ref name=nga /&gt; The latter action was commended in a letter to Combs from [[President of the United States|President]] [[John F. Kennedy]].&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; In 1961, Combs was awarded an [[Honorary degree|honorary]] [[Doctor of Laws]] degree from the University of Kentucky, and on February 17, 1962, he received an award from [[Keep America Beautiful]] for his work on cleaning up Kentucky's highways, including securing passage of a bill requiring that auto junkyards near major roadways be screened from view by fences.&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt;&lt;ref name=pearce193&gt;Pearce, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;

Among Combs' other accomplishments as governor were requiring [[voting machine]]s in state elections and passage of a law making the assessment of state employees for political campaign funds a [[felony]].&lt;ref name=nhok408&gt;Harrison and Klotter, p. 408&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of his term, Combs backed [[Edward T. Breathitt]] to succeed him as governor.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; Breathitt defeated Happy Chandler in the Democratic primary, then went on to defeat Republican [[Louie B. Nunn]] in the general election.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; It was the only time in the 20th century that a Kentucky governor's preferred successor won election.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt;

===Later political career===
Following his term as governor, Combs returned to his legal practice. He was a charter member and chairman of the Eastern Kentucky Historical Society and a trustee at [[Campbellsville University|Campbellsville College]].&lt;ref name=powell104 /&gt; In 1963, he was awarded the Joseph P. Kennedy International Award for &quot;outstanding contributions and leadership in the field of mental retardations.&quot;&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt; He was named Kentucky's outstanding attorney in 1964, and in the spring of that year, he served as a visiting professor in the Political Science Department at the [[University of Massachusetts Amherst|University of Massachusetts]].&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt; In 1965, he was inducted into the University of Kentucky's Hall of Distinguished Alumni.&lt;ref name=ukaa /&gt;

In August 1964, Combs declined a nomination to the bench of the [[United States District Court for the Western District of Kentucky]].&lt;ref name=robinson172&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 172&lt;/ref&gt; During the administration of Combs' successor, Ned Breathitt, Republicans gained strength within the state behind the leadership of Louie Nunn, [[Marlow Cook]], and [[William O. Cowger]].&lt;ref name=robinson172 /&gt; The Republican rise, coupled with Democratic factionalism, prompted many prominent state Democrats to approach Combs about seeking another term as governor.&lt;ref name=robinson172 /&gt; Combs wavered on whether to seek the Democratic nomination until October 1966, when he publicly declared his support for [[Henry Ward (Kentucky politician)|Henry Ward]].&lt;ref name=robinson173&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 173&lt;/ref&gt; In a later interview with historian George W. Robinson, Combs recounted that he &quot;would have run at that time except for a personal family situation&quot;.&lt;ref name=robinson177&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 177&lt;/ref&gt; Ward handily defeated his primary opponents, Happy Chandler and Harry Lee Waterfield, but lost in the general election to Louie Nunn.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', pp. 173, 181&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 16, 1967, President Lyndon Johnson nominated Combs to the [[Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals]], replacing the deceased [[Shackelford Miller, Jr.]], and the Senate [[Advice and consent|confirmed]] the nomination on April 5, 1967.&lt;ref name=jusc /&gt; Because of the rules of the federal judiciary, Combs had to liquidate his business and banking assets and severely restrict contact with many of his political acquaintances to avoid potential [[conflict of interest|conflicts of interest]] with cases he might adjudicate on the Court of Appeals.&lt;ref name=robinson181&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; He expressed frustration that the cases that came before the court were frequently appealed to the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]], which often gave little weight to the opinions rendered by the Court of Appeals.&lt;ref name=robinson181 /&gt; Consequently, he resigned from the court on June 5, 1970, and joined the Louisville law firm of Tarrant, Combs, and Bullitt (later Wyatt, Tarrant, and Combs).&lt;ref name=kygovs199 /&gt;

[[File:Wendell-H-Ford.jpg|thumb|right|upright|alt=A man with receding, gray hair and glasses wearing a white shirt with a black tie and jacket|Wendell Ford defeated Combs in the 1971 Democratic gubernatorial primary.]]
With the end of Governor Nunn's term approaching, a rivalry for leadership of the state Democratic party developed between Lieutenant Governor [[Wendell H. Ford]], who had served as Combs' chief administrative assistant during his gubernatorial term, and [[Julian M. Carroll]], speaker of the [[Kentucky House of Representatives|state House of Representatives]].&lt;ref name=robinson182&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; As soon as Combs resigned from the Court of Appeals, Democratic leaders began asking him to seek the party's gubernatorial nomination in 1971, uniting the party behind him rather than splintering it between Ford and Carroll.&lt;ref name=robinson182 /&gt; In June 1970, Carroll announced his intent to run for lieutenant governor, indicating that he would like to serve under Combs as governor.&lt;ref name=robinson182 /&gt; While Combs considered whether or not to seek the nomination, Ford declared his candidacy.&lt;ref name=robinson182 /&gt; Days later, Combs also entered the race.&lt;ref name=robinson187&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 187&lt;/ref&gt;

Combs and Ford proclaimed advocated platforms, but Combs encouraged the state's teachers to become more politically active, negotiating higher salaries and better benefits for themselves, while Ford was critical of educators becoming involved in politics and only advocated more spending on education if the state could afford it.&lt;ref name=robinson188&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 188&lt;/ref&gt; In his oral history of Combs, Robinson noted that Ford, thirteen years Combs' junior, &quot;came across better on television&quot; and that many voters in the state felt that Combs must have ulterior motives in leaving a judgeship that paid a salary of $42,500 for the governorship, which paid only $30,000 annually.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', pp. 188–189&lt;/ref&gt; [[Catholicism|Catholics]] were also upset that Combs had married his second wife, Helen Clark Rechtin, just forty-three days after his divorce from Mabel Hall was finalized on July 18, 1969.&lt;ref name=robinson188 /&gt; (Combs and Hall had been separated for five years prior to finalizing the divorce.)&lt;ref name=kypost /&gt;&lt;ref name=powell104 /&gt; Despite these handicaps, many Democrats assumed that Combs, the proven candidate, would easily defeat the newcomer Ford, and fewer than one-third of registered Democrats voted in the primary.&lt;ref name=robinson189&gt;Robinson in ''Bert Combs The Politician'', p. 189&lt;/ref&gt; In what the ''Courier-Journal'' called a &quot;stunning defeat&quot;, Ford defeated Combs in the Democratic primary and went on to win the governorship.&lt;ref name=robinson189 /&gt;

==Later life==
After the 1971 primary, Combs retired from politics and resumed his law practice, maintaining an office in Frankfort. He continued to represent large coal companies, drawing the ire of local environmentalist and author [[Harry M. Caudill]], who asserted that Combs claimed to represent the powerless while actually representing the powerful.&lt;ref name=lhl /&gt; He was active in the formation of the Rural Housing and Development Corporation and served on the [[Kentucky Council on Postsecondary Education|Council on Higher Education]].&lt;ref name=kye217 /&gt; He also served on President [[Jimmy Carter]]'s General Advisory Committee on Arms Control and Disarmament.&lt;ref name=obit /&gt;

Combs' second marriage ended in divorce on May 19, 1986.&lt;ref&gt;Kentucky Divorce Index 1973–1993 Search Result&lt;/ref&gt; On December 30, 1988, he married his law assistant, [[Sara Walter Combs|Sara M. Walter]].&lt;ref name=ho6 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kentucky Marriage Index 1973–1993 Search Result&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rose v. Council for Better Education===
On October 3, 1984, leaders of the [[Council for Better Education]] asked Combs to represent them in a legal challenge to Kentucky's school financing system, which it claimed unfairly discriminated against poorer school systems in the state.&lt;ref name=dove12&gt;Dove, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; Combs felt the lawsuit would be difficult to win and could cause retaliation against his other clients by state government officials.&lt;ref name=dove12 /&gt; He needed this lawsuit &quot;about like a hog needs a side saddle&quot;, he would later claim; nevertheless, he agreed to take the case if the Council could convince thirty to forty percent of the state's school boards to join it.&lt;ref name=dove12 /&gt;&lt;ref name=bosworth116&gt;Bosworth, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; The Council eventually persuaded 66 of the 177 school boards to join.&lt;ref name=dove13&gt;Dove, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; Working [[pro bono]], Combs assembled a legal team that included [[Kern Alexander]], a Kentucky native and education law expert who was named president of [[Western Kentucky University]] in November 1985.&lt;ref name=dove13 /&gt;

[[File:Martha Layne Collins, governor of Kentucky, Nov 8, 1986.jpg|thumb|left|upright|alt=A woman with dark, shoulder-length hair wearing a light scarf and trench coat, speaking into microphones|Gov. Martha Layne Collins' education reforms were not enough to prevent the Council for Better Education from suing the state.]]
Combs first attempted to gain legislative concessions that might preclude the need for a lawsuit.&lt;ref name=dove15&gt;Dove, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; Governor [[Martha Layne Collins]] proposed an education reform agenda and called the legislature into special session in mid-1985 to consider it.&lt;ref name=dove15 /&gt; The legislature enacted a corporate [[income tax]] to raise $300&amp;nbsp;million aimed at reducing class sizes, but the Council was seeking more fundamental structural changes to the system and deemed the increased funds insufficient to equalize its members' standing with that of more affluent school districts.&lt;ref name=bosworth118&gt;Bosworth, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dove16&gt;Dove, p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; Dissatisfied with the results of the special session, Combs and the Council filed their suit, ''Rose v. Council for Better Education'', on November 20, 1985.&lt;ref name=dove16 /&gt; The governor, state superintendent, state treasurer, leaders of both houses of the state legislature, and every member of the state board of education were named as defendants in the case.&lt;ref name=dove16 /&gt;

The defendants' request for a [[summary judgment]] dismissing the case was not granted, and the trial began in [[Franklin County, Kentucky|Franklin]] circuit court on August 4, 1987. During the trial, a new state superintendent was elected. The new superintendent, John Brock, announced that his office would drop its defense and side with the Council, a major blow to the defense. On May 31, 1988, Judge Ray Corns found in favor of the plaintiffs, declaring that the school finance system was &quot;unconstitutional and discriminatory&quot;.&lt;ref name=dove21&gt;Dove, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; Two days later, the defense announced that it would appeal the ruling to the [[Kentucky Supreme Court]], but recently elected governor [[Wallace G. Wilkinson]] refused to join the appeal and supported Judge Corns' ruling.&lt;ref&gt;Dove, pp. 18, 20–22&lt;/ref&gt;

Opening arguments in the appeal began December 7, 1988.&lt;ref name=dove24&gt;Dove, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; The defense argued that the Council lacked standing to bring the suit; Combs rebuffed this argument and cited statistics that ranked Kentucky as the most illiterate state in the nation to show how inequitable financing had adversely affected the state's students.&lt;ref name=dove24 /&gt; On June 8, 1989, the court handed down a 3–2 ruling declaring Kentucky's entire public school system unconstitutional and giving the General Assembly until the end of their next legislative session, which would convene in January 1990, to create a replacement.&lt;ref name=dove25&gt;Dove, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bosworth127&gt;Bosworth, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;790 S.W.2d 186 (Kentucky, 1989)&lt;/ref&gt; Commenting on the ruling, Combs said &quot;My clients asked for a thimble-full, and [instead] they got a bucket-full&quot;.&lt;ref name=dove25 /&gt;

The court set out nine minimum standards. In response to the court's ruling, the General Assembly passed the 1990 [[Kentucky Education Reform Act]], which radically altered Kentucky's school system, providing mechanisms to equalize funding among school districts and implementing some of the toughest accountability standards in the United States. Of the legislature's actions, Combs opined &quot;Kentucky has now, by reason of this legislation, decided to become educated—and we have embarked on a crusade for that purpose. Don't be surprised if we should within the next decade develop a first class, world-wide educational system.&quot;&lt;ref name=dove31&gt;Dove, p. 25, 30–31&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death and legacy===
On December 3, 1991, Combs left his law office during a [[flash flood]] about 5:30&amp;nbsp;pm.&lt;ref name=obit&gt;Saxon, &quot;Bert T. Combs, 80, Dies in Flood&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; He was reported missing hours later, and the following day, he was found dead of [[hypothermia]] just downstream from his car in the [[Red River (Kentucky)|Red River]] near [[Rosslyn, Kentucky|Rosslyn]], in [[Powell County, Kentucky|Powell County]].&lt;ref name=obit /&gt; He was buried in the Beech Creek Cemetery in Manchester.&lt;ref name=nga /&gt;

In addition to the Bert T. Combs Mountain Parkway, Bert T. Combs Lake, an [[artificial lake]] constructed in 1963 in Clay County, is named in Combs' honor.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Bert T. Combs Lake&quot;. Kentucky Department of Fish and Wildlife Resources&lt;/ref&gt; On April 20, 2007, two life-sized statues of Combs were dedicated—one in [[Stanton, Kentucky]], near the parkway that bears his name and another in the county courthouse in Prestonsburg.&lt;ref name=statue&gt;&quot;Governor Bert T. Combs Statue Project&quot;. Appalachian Heritage Alliance&lt;/ref&gt; Combs' widow, Sara Walter Combs, became the first woman to serve on the Kentucky Supreme Court in 1993 and currently sits on the Kentucky Court of Appeals, where she was chief judge from 2004 to 2010, also a first for a woman.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Judge Sara Walter Combs&quot;. Kentucky Court of Justice&lt;/ref&gt; Combs' daughter, Lois (Combs) Weinberg, unsuccessfully challenged incumbent [[Mitch McConnell]] for his Senate seat in [[United States Senate election in Kentucky, 2002|2002]].&lt;ref&gt;Report of &quot;Official&quot; Election Night Tally Results. Kentucky Board of Elections&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===
*{{cite news |title=Bert Combs Missing, Feared Dead |newspaper=The Kentucky Post |date=1991-12-04 |page=1K}}
*{{cite web |title=Bert T. Combs |url=http://www.ukalumni.net/s/1052/index-no-right.aspx?sid=1052&amp;gid=1&amp;pgid=671 |publisher=University of Kentucky Alumni Association |work=Hall of Distinguished Alumni |accessdate=2009-11-04}}
*{{cite web |title=Bert T. Combs Lake |url=http://fw.ky.gov/pdf/berttcombslake.pdf |publisher=Kentucky Department of Fish and Wildlife Resources |accessdate=2009-12-15 |format=PDF}}
*{{cite web |title=Bertram Thomas Combs (1911–1991) |url=http://www.ca6.uscourts.gov/lib_hist/Courts/circuit/judges/combs/btc-bio.html |publisher=U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit |work=History of the Sixth Circuit |accessdate=2009-11-04 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090827024735/http://www.ca6.uscourts.gov/lib_hist/Courts/circuit/judges/combs/btc-bio.html &lt;!--Added by H3llBot--&gt; |archivedate=2009-08-27}}
*{{cite book |last=Bosworth |first=Matthew H. |title=Courts As Catalysts: State Supreme Courts and Public School Finance Equity |publisher=Albany State University of New York Press |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-7914-5013-0}}
{{FJC Bio|484|Combs, Bertram Thomas}}
*{{cite news |title=Combs Rose to Pinnacle From Plain Beginnings |agency=Knight-Ridder News Service |newspaper=Lexington Herald-Leader |date=1991-12-05 |page=A1}}
*{{cite journal |last=Dove, Jr. |first=Ronald G. |title=Acorns in a Mountain Pool: The Role of Litigation, Law, and Lawyers in Kentucky Education Reform |volume=17 |journal=Journal of Education Finance |year=1991 |url=http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/contentdelivery/servlet/ERICServlet?accno=ED336812 |accessdate=2012-11-05}}
*{{cite web |url=http://bertcombs.com/bertcombs.html |title=Governor Bert T. Combs Statue Project |publisher=Appalachian Heritage Alliance |accessdate=2009-12-07}}
* Day, Richard E., &quot;Bert Combs and the Council for Better Education: Catalysts for School Reform,&quot; ''Register of the Kentucky Historical Society'' 109 (Winter 2011), 27–62
*{{cite book |last=Harmon |first=David G. |title=A Tribute to Clay County Veterans |publisher=Turner Publishing Company |year=2001 |isbn=1-56311-773-8 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qK3xqlkjJyYC |accessdate=2009-11-04}}
*{{cite book |last=Harrison |first=Lowell H. |authorlink=Lowell H. Harrison |chapter=Combs, Bert T. |editor=Kleber, John E |others=Associate editors: [[Thomas D. Clark]], Lowell H. Harrison, and [[James C. Klotter]] |title=The Kentucky Encyclopedia |year=1992 |publisher=The [[University Press of Kentucky]] |location=Lexington, Kentucky |isbn=0-8131-1772-0 |page=217}}
*{{cite book |last=Harrison |first=Lowell H. |authorlink=Lowell H. Harrison |author2=James C. Klotter |title=A New History of Kentucky |publisher=University Press of Kentucky |year=1997 |isbn=0-8131-2008-X |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=63GqvIN3l3wC |accessdate=2009-06-26|authorlink2=James C. Klotter }}
*{{cite web |title=History of the Kentucky Unified Court System |publisher=Kentucky Court of Justice |url=http://courts.ky.gov/research/history.htm |date=2006-08-17 |accessdate=2010-01-25|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090703062053/http://courts.ky.gov/research/history.htm|archivedate=2009-07-03}}
*{{cite web |title=Judge Sara Walter Combs|publisher=Kentucky Court of Justice |url=http://courts.ky.gov/courts/coa/Pages/combs.aspx |accessdate=2012-12-31}}
*{{cite web |url=http://ukcc.uky.edu/cgi-bin/phq?def=vrdivo&amp;field=name&amp;value=bert+t.+combs&amp;Search=Search |title=Kentucky Divorce Index 1973–1993 Search Result |publisher=University of Kentucky |work=Kentucky Vital Records Index |accessdate=2010-05-19}}
*{{cite web |title=Kentucky Governor Bert Thomas Combs |url=http://www.nga.org/cms/home/governors/past-governors-bios/page_kentucky/col2-content/main-content-list/title_combs_bert.html |publisher=National Governors Association |accessdate=2012-04-03}}
*{{cite web |url=http://ukcc.uky.edu/cgi-bin/phq?def=vrmarr&amp;field=bride&amp;value=Sara+M.+Walter&amp;Search=Search |title=Kentucky Marriage Index 1973–1993 Search Result |publisher=University of Kentucky |work=Kentucky Vital Records Index |accessdate=2010-05-19}}
*{{cite book |last=Pearce |first=John Ed |title=Divide and Dissent: Kentucky Politics 1930–1963 |publisher=The University Press of Kentucky |location=Lexington, Kentucky |year=1987 |isbn=0-8131-1613-9}}
*{{cite book |last=Powell |first=Robert A. |title=Kentucky Governors |publisher=Bluegrass Printing Company |location=Danville, Kentucky |year=1976 |oclc=2690774}}
*{{cite web |url=http://elect.ky.gov/SiteCollectionDocuments/Election%20Results/2000-2009/2002/General%20Election/2002statebyoffice.txt |title=Report of &quot;Official&quot; Election Night Tally Results |publisher=Kentucky Board of Elections |accessdate=2012-12-31}}
*{{cite book |last=Robinson |first=George William |title=Bert Combs the Politician: An Oral History |publisher=The University Press of Kentucky |location=Lexington, Kentucky |year=1991 |isbn=0-8131-1740-2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ntD0Typcn98C |accessdate=2009-11-04}}
*{{cite book |last=Robinson |first=George William |chapter=Bert T. Combs |title=Kentucky's Governors |editor=Lowell Hayes Harrison |publisher=The University Press of Kentucky |location=Lexington, Kentucky |year=2004 |isbn=0-8131-2326-7 |pages=196–199}}
*{{cite news |last=Saxon |first=Wolfgang |title=Bert T. Combs, 80, Dies in Flood; Was Kentucky Governor in 60's |work=The New York Times |date=1991-12-05 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/12/05/us/bert-t-combs-80-dies-in-flood-was-kentucky-governor-in-60-s.html |accessdate=2009-11-04}}

==Further reading==
{{Portal|Biography|Kentucky}}
*{{cite journal |last=Combs |first=Bert |title=Creative constitutional law: the Kentucky School Reform Law |journal=Harvard Journal on Legislation |volume=28 |issue=2 |year=1991 |pages=367–378}}
*{{cite book |last=Robinson |first=George William |title=The Public Papers of Governor Bert T. Combs, 1959–1963 |publisher=The University Press of Kentucky |location=[[Lexington, Kentucky]] |year=1979 |isbn=0-8131-0604-4}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Governor of Kentucky]]|before=[[Happy Chandler]]|after=[[Edward T. Breathitt]]|years=1959–1963}}
{{S-ppo}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Democratic nominee for Governor of Kentucky]]|before=[[Happy Chandler]]|after=[[Edward T. Breathitt]]|years=1959}}
{{s-legal}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Shackelford Miller, Jr.]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Judge of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit]]|years=1967–1970}}
{{s-aft|after=[[W. Wallace Kent]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Governors of Kentucky}}

{{Authority control}}

{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Combs, Bert T.}}
[[Category:1911 births]]
[[Category:1991 deaths]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:American prosecutors]]
[[Category:Deaths from hypothermia]]
[[Category:Deaths in floods]]
[[Category:Governors of Kentucky]]
[[Category:Judges of the Kentucky Court of Appeals]]
[[Category:Judges of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit]]
[[Category:Kentucky Commonwealth's Attorneys]]
[[Category:Kentucky Democrats]]
[[Category:Kentucky lawyers]]
[[Category:Kentucky state court judges]]
[[Category:Natural disaster deaths in Kentucky]]
[[Category:People from Prestonburg, Kentucky]]
[[Category:People from Manchester, Kentucky]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Star Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Merit Medal (Philippines)]]
[[Category:United States court of appeals judges appointed by Lyndon B. Johnson]]
[[Category:20th-century American judges]]
[[Category:University of Kentucky College of Law alumni]]
[[Category:University of Massachusetts Amherst faculty]]
[[Category:Democratic Party state governors of the United States]]
[[Category:20th-century American lawyers]]</text>
      <sha1>gysg4xb4jdmmsyupevmp2ux7v36elkv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
