<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>CFM International CFM56</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>437326</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749059361</id>
      <parentid>748623603</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T03:44:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 2 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="66703">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, and guidelines. --&gt;
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2012}}
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
 |name= CFM56
 |image= File:CFM56 P1220759.jpg
 |caption= Rear view of a CFM56-5
 |alt=An exposed jet engine at a trade show. The rear of the polished metal fan case is visible on the left. The outer casing of the compressor section, covered in fuel lines and electrical wires is to the right of the fan case. The right of the image shows the back of the engine, the exhaust area of the turbine section.
}}{{Infobox aircraft engine
 |type= [[Turbofan]]
 |national origin= France and United States
 |manufacturer= [[CFM International]]
 |first run= June 1974
 |major applications= [[Airbus A320 family]] &lt;br&gt;[[Airbus A340]] &lt;br&gt;[[Boeing 737 Classic]] / [[Boeing 737 Next Generation|Next Gen.]] &lt;br&gt;[[Douglas DC-8#Super seventies|McDonnell Douglas DC-8-70 series]] &lt;br&gt;[[Boeing KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135R Stratotanker]]
 |number built= 30,000 (as of July 2016)
 |program cost=
 |unit cost= US${{#expr:100/5/2}} million (list price)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url= http://www.cfmaeroengines.com/press/cit-selects-cfm56-5b-for-new-a321-aircraft/791 |date= 12 March 2015 |publisher= [[CFM International]] |title= CIT Selects CFM56-5B for new A321 aircraft}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |developed from= [[General Electric F101]]
 |variants with their own articles =
 |developed into= [[CFM International LEAP]]
}}
|}

The '''CFM International CFM56''' (U.S. military designation '''F108''') series is a family of [[bypass ratio|high-bypass]] [[turbofan]] [[aircraft engine]]s made by [[CFM International]] (CFMI), with a thrust range of {{convert|18500|to|34000|lbf|kN|abbr=off|lk=on|sigfig=2}}. CFMI is a 50–50 joint-owned company of [[Safran Aircraft Engines]] (formerly known as [[Snecma|SNECMA]]), France and [[GE Aviation]] (GE), United States. Both companies are responsible for producing components and each has its own final assembly line. GE produces the high-pressure [[axial compressor|compressor]], [[combustor]], and high-pressure [[Components of jet engines#Turbines|turbine]], and SNECMA manufactures the fan, [[Transmission (mechanics)|gearbox]], exhaust and the low-pressure turbine, and some components are made by [[Avio]] of Italy. The engines are assembled by GE in [[Evendale, Ohio]], and by SNECMA in [[Melun Villaroche Aerodrome|Villaroche]] in France. The completed engines are marketed by CFMI. Despite initial export restrictions, it is one of the most common [[turbofan]] [[aircraft engine]]s in the world, in four major variants.

The CFM56 first ran in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;&gt;Bilien, J. and Matta, R. (1989). ''The CFM56 Venture''. AIAA/AHS/ASEE Aircraft Design, Systems, and Operations Conference. Seattle, WA, 31 July – 2 August 1989. AIAA-89-2038&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1979, the [[joint venture]] had not received a single order in five years and was two weeks away from being dissolved.&lt;ref name=160712PR/&gt; The program was saved when [[Delta Airlines]], [[United Airlines]], and [[Flying Tiger Line|Flying Tigers]] chose the CFM56 to re-engine their [[DC-8]]s and shortly thereafter it was chosen to re-engine the [[KC-135 Stratotanker]] fleet of the [[U.S. Air Force]] – still its biggest customer.&lt;ref name=160712PR/&gt; The first engines entered service in 1982.&lt;ref name=160602PR/&gt; Several fan blade [[turbine engine failure|failure]] incidents were experienced during the CFM56's early service, including one failure that was a cause of the [[Kegworth air disaster]], and some engine variants experienced problems caused by flight through rain and hail. Both these issues were resolved with engine modifications.

==History==

===Origins===
Research into the next generation of commercial jet engines, [[Bypass ratio|high-bypass ratio]] turbofans in the &quot;10-ton&quot; (20,000&amp;nbsp;lbf; 89&amp;nbsp;kN) thrust class, began in the late 1960s. [[Snecma|SNECMA]], who had mostly built military engines until then, was the first company to seek entrance into the market by searching for a partner with commercial experience to design and build an engine in this class. They considered [[Pratt &amp; Whitney]], [[Rolls-Royce plc|Rolls-Royce]], and [[GE Aviation]] as potential partners, and after two company executives, [[Gerhard Neumann]] from GE and René Ravaud from SNECMA, introduced themselves at the 1971 [[Paris Air Show]] a decision was made. The two companies saw mutual benefit in the collaboration and met several more times, fleshing out the basics of the joint project.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;&gt;Norris, Guy (1999). CFM56: Engine of Change. ''Flight International''. 19–25 May 1999. Online at [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1999/1999%20-%201385.html CFM56: Engine of Change].&lt;/ref&gt;

Pratt &amp; Whitney dominated the commercial market at this point in time. GE needed an engine in this market class, and SNECMA had previous experience of working with them, collaborating on the production of the [[General Electric CF6#CF6-50|CF6-50]] turbofan for the [[Airbus A300]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt; Pratt &amp; Whitney was considering upgrading their [[Pratt &amp; Whitney JT8D|JT8D]] to compete in the same class as the CFM56 as a sole venture, while Rolls-Royce dealt with financial issues that precluded them from starting new projects; this situation caused GE to gain the title of best partner for the program.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt;

A major reason for GE's interest in the collaboration, rather than building a 10-ton engine on their own, was that the SNECMA project was the only source of development funds for an engine in this class at this particular time. GE was initially considering only contributing technology from its CF6 engine rather than its much more advanced [[General Electric F101|F101]] engine, developed for the [[B-1 Lancer]] supersonic bomber. The company was faced with a dilemma when the [[United States Air Force]] (USAF) announced its [[Advanced Medium STOL Transport]] (AMST) project in 1972 which included funding for the development of a 10-ton engine – either to build a &quot;limited&quot; technology 10-ton engine with SNECMA, or a similar engine with &quot;advanced&quot; technology on their own. Concerned that the company would be left with only the &quot;limited&quot; engine in its portfolio if it did not win the Air Force contract (for which it was competing with Pratt &amp; Whitney and a [[General Motors]] division with its &quot;advanced&quot; engine), GE decided to apply for an export license for the F101 core technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;wpost&quot;&gt;Samuelson, Robert (1972). &quot;Commerce, Security and the &quot;Ten Ton Engine&quot;&quot;. ''The Washington Post''. 8 October 1972, p. H7.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Export issues===
GE applied for the export license in 1972 as their primary contribution to the 10-ton engine project. The [[United States Department of State|United States Department of State's]] Office of Munitions Control recommended the rejection of the application on national security grounds; specifically because the core technology was an aspect of a strategic national defense system (the B-1 bomber), it was built with [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] (and therefore American taxpayer) money, and that exporting the technology to France would limit the number of American workers on the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;stpete&quot;&gt;Farnsworth, Clyde (1973). &quot;GE, French To Make Jet Engine&quot;. ''St. Petersburg Times'', 23 June 1973, p. 11-A.&lt;/ref&gt; The official decision was made in a National Security Decision Memorandum signed by the National Security Advisor [[Henry Kissinger]] on 19 September 1972.&lt;ref&gt;GE-SNECMA Jet Engine Joint Venture (1972). &lt;u&gt;National Security Decision Memorandum 189&lt;/u&gt;. 19 September 1972. [http://nixon.archives.gov/virtuallibrary/documents/nsdm/nsdm_189.pdf NSDM 189 (pdf)]. Retrieved 9 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

While national security concerns were cited as the grounds for rejection, politics played an important role as well. The project, and the export issue associated with it, was considered so important that French President [[Georges Pompidou]] appealed directly to U.S. President [[Richard Nixon]] in 1971 to approve the deal, and Henry Kissinger brought the issue up with President Pompidou in a 1972 meeting. GE reportedly argued at the highest levels that having half of the market was better than having none of it, which they believed would happen if SNECMA pursued the engine on their own without GE's contribution. Nixon administration officials feared that this project could be the beginning of the end of American aerospace leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytreject&quot;&gt;&quot;A Rebuff to Pompidou on Engine&quot; (1972). ''The New York Times''. 30 September 1972, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

There was also speculation that the rejection may have been, in part, retaliation for French involvement in convincing the Swiss not to purchase American-made [[A-7 Corsair II]] aircraft that had been competing against a French design,&lt;ref name=&quot;nytreject&quot;/&gt; the [[Dassault Mirage III#Derivatives|Dassault Milan]]. In the end, the Swiss did not purchase either aircraft, opting for the [[Northrop F-5|Northrop F-5E Tiger II]] instead.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1978/1978%20-%200008.html Tooling up for Tiger]&quot;. ''FLIGHT International''. 7 January 1978, p. 8. Retrieved 9 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

====1973 Nixon–Pompidou meeting====
[[File:Nixon-Pompidou.JPG|thumb|alt=Two men in suits stand to the right, with uniformed military officers nearby. Both men are waving and smiling.|right|U.S. [[Richard Nixon|President Nixon]] (left) and French President [[Georges Pompidou]] (right) prior to the 1973 U.S.–French summit in Reykjavík, Iceland]]

Despite the export license being rejected, both the French and GE continued to push the Nixon Administration for permission to export the F101 technology. Efforts continued throughout the months following the rejection, culminating in the engine becoming an agenda topic during the 1973 meeting of Presidents Nixon and Pompidou in [[Reykjavík]]. Discussions at this meeting resulted in an agreement that allowed the development of the CFM56 to proceed. Contemporary reports state that the agreement was based on assurances that the core of the engine, the part that GE was developing from the military F101, would be built in the U.S. and then transported to France in order to protect the sensitive technologies.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytlifted&quot;&gt;Farnsworth, Clyde (1973). &quot;U.S. Ban Lifted on G. E. Plan&quot;. ''The New York Times''. 23 June 1973, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; The joint venture also agreed to pay the U.S. an $80&amp;nbsp;million royalty fee (calculated at $20,000 per engine predicted to be built) as repayment for the development money provided by the government for the F101 engine core.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt; Documents declassified in 2007 revealed that a key aspect of the CFM56 export agreement was that the French government agreed not to seek tariffs against American aircraft being imported into Europe.&lt;ref&gt;GE-SNECMA. CFM-56 Jet Engine Joint Development (1973). &lt;u&gt;National Security Decision Memorandum 220&lt;/u&gt;. 4 June 1973. [http://nixon.archives.gov/virtuallibrary/documents/nsdm/nsdm_220.pdf NSDM 220 (pdf)]. Retrieved 9 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===CFM International===
With the export issue settled, GE and SNECMA finalized the agreement that formed [[CFM International]] (CFMI), a 50–50 joint company that would be responsible for producing and marketing the 10-ton engine, the CFM56. The venture was officially founded in 1974.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100323063956/http://www.cfm56.com/company/timeline CFM Timeline]. CFM International. Retrieved 10 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The two primary roles for CFMI were to manage the program between GE and SNECMA, and to market, sell and service the engine at a single point of contact for the customer. CFMI was made responsible for the day-to-day decision making for the project, while major decisions (developing a new variant, for example) required the go-ahead from GE and SNECMA management.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt;

The CFMI board of directors is currently split evenly between SNECMA and GE (five members each). There are two vice presidents, one from each company, who support the President of CFMI. The president tends to be drawn from SNECMA and sits at CFMI's headquarters near GE in Cincinnati, Ohio.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt;

The work split between the two companies gave GE responsibility for the high-pressure [[Axial compressor|compressor]] (HPC), the [[combustor]], and the high-pressure [[turbine]] (HPT); SNECMA was responsible for the fan, the low-pressure compressor (LPC), and the low-pressure turbine (LPT).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100519130743/http://www.cfm56.com/company/work-split Work Split]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; SNECMA was also responsible for the initial airframe integration engineering, mostly involving the [[nacelle]] design, and was initially responsible for the [[Transmission (mechanics)|gearbox]], but shifted that work to GE when it became apparent that it would be more efficient for GE to assemble that component along with their other parts.&lt;ref name=&quot;av1975&quot;&gt;Yaffee, Michael (1975). &quot;Developers Face 1975 CFM56 Decision&quot;. ''Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology''. 24 February 1975, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==

===Overview===
Development work on the CFM56 began before CFMI was formally created. While work proceeded smoothly, the international arrangement led to unique working conditions. For example, both companies had assembly lines, some engines were assembled and tested in the U.S. and others in France. Engines assembled in France were subject to the initially strict export agreement, which meant that GE's core was built in the U.S., then shipped to the SNECMA plant in France where it was placed in a locked room into which even the President of SNECMA was not allowed. The SNECMA components (the fore and aft sections of the engine) were brought into the room, GE employees mounted them to the core, and then the assembled engine was taken out to be finished.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytobs&quot;&gt;Lewis, Flora (1975). &quot;G.E.-SNECMA Deal: U.S.-French Dispute Is Obscured&quot;. ''The New York Times''. 5 March 1975, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first completed CFM56 engine first ran at GE in June 1974 with the second running in October 1974. The second engine was then shipped to France and first ran there on 13 December 1974. These first engines were considered &quot;production hardware&quot; as opposed to test examples and were designated as the CFM56-2, the first variant of the CFM56.&lt;ref name=&quot;av1975&quot;/&gt;

The engine flew for the first time in February 1977 when it replaced one of the four [[Pratt &amp; Whitney JT8D]] engines on the [[McDonnell Douglas YC-15]], an entrant in the Air Force's [[Advanced Medium STOL Transport]] (AMST) competition.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;YC-15 Enters New Flight Test Series&quot;. ''Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology''. 21 February 1977, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, the second CFM56 was mounted on a [[Sud Aviation Caravelle]] at the SNECMA flight test center in France. This engine had a slightly different configuration with a long bypass duct and [[Bypass duct|mixed exhaust]] flow,&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot; name=&quot;e1&quot;&gt;''Mixed Exhaust Flow'' refers to turbofan engines (both low and high bypass) that exhaust both the hot core flow and the cool bypass flow through a single exit nozzle. The core and bypass flows are &quot;mixed&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; rather than a short bypass duct with [[Bypass duct|unmixed exhaust]] flow.&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot; name=&quot;e2&quot;&gt;''Unmixed Exhaust Flow'' refers to turbofan engines (usually, but not exclusively high-bypass) that exhaust cool bypass air separately from their hot core flow. This arrangement is visually distinctive as the outer, wider, bypass section usually ends mid-way along the nacelle and the core protrudes to the rear. With two separate exhaust points, the flow is &quot;unmixed&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first to include a &quot;Thrust Management System&quot; to maintain engine trim.&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;''Engine Trim'' generally refers to keeping the components of an engine in synchronisation with each other. For example, maintaining proper engine trim could mean adjusting the airflow to keep the proper amount of air flowing through the high-pressure compressor for a particular flight condition.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;flighttest&quot;&gt;Shivaram, Malur (1988). ''A Survey of the Flight Testing, and Evaluation of CFM56 Series Turbofan''. 4th AIAA Flight Test Conference, San Diego, CA.  18–20 May 1988. Technical Papers AIAA-1988-2078.&lt;/ref&gt;

===First customers===
After testing the engine for several years, both in the air and on the ground, CFMI searched for customers outside of a possible AMST contract. The main targets were re-engine contracts for the [[Douglas DC-8]] and the [[Boeing 707]] airliners, including the related military tanker, the [[KC-135 Stratotanker]]. There was little initial interest in the engine, but Boeing realized that the CFM56 might be a solution to upcoming noise regulations.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt; After announcing that a 707 would be configured with the CFM56 engine for flight tests in 1977, Boeing officially offered the 707-320 with the CFM56 engine as an option in 1978. The new variant was listed as the 707-700.&lt;ref&gt;O'Lone, Richard (1978). Boeing to Offer 707-320 Re-engined with CFM56s. ''Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology''. 14 August 1978, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to limited interest from the airlines in a re-engined 707, Boeing ended the 707-700 program in 1980 without selling any aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Plan to Reengine 707 With CFM56 Suspended&quot;. ''Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology''. 28 April 1980. p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the lack of sales, having the commercial 707 available with the CFM56 helped the engine's competitiveness for the KC-135 re-engine contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;kc135&quot;/&gt;

====KC-135R====
[[File:KC-135R-Taxi.JPG|alt=The front of several gray aircraft are centered in the image.|thumb|A nose-on view of several re-engined [[KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135R]] aircraft taxiing prior to takeoff. The new engines are CFM56-2 high-bypass turbofans.]]

Winning the contract to re-engine the KC-135 tanker fleet for the USAF would be a huge boon to the CFM56 project (with more than 600 aircraft available to re-engine), and CFMI aggressively pursued that goal as soon as the Request For Proposals (RFP) was announced in 1977. Like other aspects of the program, international politics played their part in this contract. In efforts to boost the CFM56's chances versus its competitors, the [[Pratt &amp; Whitney JT3D|Pratt &amp; Whitney TF33]] and an updated [[Pratt &amp; Whitney JT8D]], the French government announced in 1978 that they would upgrade their 11 KC-135s with the CFM56, providing one of the first orders for the engine.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;GE, French Firm Get Jet Engines Contract&quot;. ''The Wall Street Journal''. 8 November 1978, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

The USAF announced the CFM56 as the winner of the re-engine contract in January 1980. Officials indicated that they were excited at the prospect of replacing the [[Pratt &amp; Whitney J57]] engines currently flying on the KC-135A aircraft, calling them &quot;...the noisiest, dirtiest, [and] most fuel inefficient powerplant still flying&quot; at the time.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;CFM56 Selected for KC-135 Re-engining&quot;. ''Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology''. 28 January 1980, p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; The re-engined aircraft was designated the KC-135R. The CFM56 brought many benefits to the KC-135, decreasing [[takeoff]] distance by as much as 3,500&amp;nbsp;ft (1,100&amp;nbsp;m), decreasing overall fuel usage by 25%, greatly reducing noise (24&amp;nbsp;dB lower) and lowering total life cycle cost. With those benefits in mind, the [[United States Navy]] selected the CFM56-2 to power their variant of the Boeing&amp;nbsp;707, the [[E-6 Mercury]], in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;kc135&quot;&gt;Kazin, S (1983). ''KC-135/CFM56 Re-engine, The Best Solution''. 19th AIAA/SAE/ASME Joint Propulsion Conference, 27–29 June 1983. Seattle, Washington. AIAA-1983-1374.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1984 the [[Royal Saudi Air Force]] selected the CFM56-2 to power their [[E-3 Sentry]] aircraft (also related to the 707 [[airframe]]). The CFM56-2-powered E-3 also became the standard configuration for aircraft purchased by the British and French.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt;

====DC-8====
By the end of the 1970s, airlines were considering upgrading their aging [[Douglas DC-8]] aircraft as an alternative to buying new quieter and more efficient aircraft. Following the French KC-135 order in 1978, the April 1979 decision by [[United Airlines]] to upgrade 30 of their DC-8-61 aircraft with the CFM56-2 was important for securing the development of the CFM56;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;United Picks CFM56 for DC-8-60s&quot;. ''Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology''. 9 April 1979, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; GE and SNECMA were two weeks away from freezing development had that order not materialized.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt; This decision marked the first commercial purchase (rather than government/military) of the engine, and [[Delta Air Lines]] and [[Flying Tiger Line]] soon followed suit, giving the CFM56 a firm footing in both the military and commercial realms.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt;

====Boeing 737====
[[File:Boeing 737-400 Engine.JPG|thumb|Engine inlet of a CFM56-3 engine on a Boeing&amp;nbsp;737-400 series showing the non-circular design|alt=A zoomed-in view of the front of an engine nacelle. The fan blades of the engine are in the middle of the image. They are surrounded by the engine nacelle, which is seemingly circular on the top half, and flattened on the bottom half.]]

In the early 1980s Boeing selected the CFM56-3 to exclusively power the [[Boeing 737 Classic|Boeing 737-300]] variant. The 737 wings were closer to the ground than previous applications for the CFM56, necessitating several modifications to the engine. The fan diameter was reduced, which reduced the bypass ratio, and the engine accessory gearbox was moved from the bottom of the engine (the 6&amp;nbsp;o'clock position) to the 9&amp;nbsp;o'clock position, giving the engine nacelle its distinctive flat-bottomed shape. The overall thrust was also reduced, from {{convert|24000|to|20000|lbf|kN|abbr=on}}, mostly due to the reduction in bypass ratio.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-3&quot;&gt;Epstein, N (1981). &quot;CFM56-3 High By-Pass Technology for Single Aisle Twins&quot;. 1981 AIAA/SAE/ASCE/ATRIF/TRB International Air Transportation Conference, 26–28 May 1981, Atlantic City, New Jersey. AIAA-1981-0808.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the small initial launch order for twenty 737-300s split between two airlines,&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt; over 5,000 Boeing 737 aircraft had been delivered with CFM56 turbofans by April 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://active.boeing.com/commercial/orders/displaystandardreport.cfm?cboCurrentModel=737&amp;optReportType=AllModels&amp;cboAllModel=737&amp;ViewReportF=View+Report Boeing 737 Deliveries]. The Boeing Company. Retrieved 19 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Continued development===

====Tech56 and Tech Insertion====
In 1998, CFMI launched the &quot;Tech56&quot; development and demonstration program to create an engine for the new single-aisle aircraft that were expected to be built by Airbus and Boeing. The program focused on developing a large number of new technologies for the theoretical future engine, not necessarily creating an all-new design.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.sae.org/aeromag/features/aircraftengines/01.htm Preparing for the future of aircraft engines – TECH56]&quot;. Aerospace Engineering and Manufacturing Online. Retrieved 23 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56son&quot;&gt;Morris, John (2000). &quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20010703030446/http://www.aviationweek.com/shownews/00farn1/hardwr05.htm &quot;Son of CFM56&quot; – TECH56]&quot;. Aviation Week's Show News Online. 24 July 2000. Retrieved 23 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; When it became clear that Boeing and Airbus were not going to build all-new aircraft to replace the 737 and A320, CFMI decided to apply some of those Tech56 technologies to the CFM56 in the form of the &quot;Tech Insertion&quot; program which focused on three areas: fuel efficiency, maintenance costs and emissions. Launched in 2004, the package included redesigned high-pressure compressor blades, an improved combustor, and improved high- and low-pressure turbine components&lt;ref name=&quot;safran&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cfm56.com/press/news/cfm+certifies+tech+insertion+compressor+upgrade+brings+lower+fuel+burn+longer+on-wing+life+to+mature+fleet/448?page_index=5 CFM Certifies Tech Insertion Compressor Upgrade; Brings Lower Fuel Burn, Longer On-Wing Life to Mature Fleet]&quot;. CFM International Press Release. 14 July 2008. Retrieved 23 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; which resulted in better fuel efficiency and lower [[NOx|nitrogen oxides]] (NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;) emissions. The new components also reduced engine wear, lowering maintenance costs by about 5%. The engines entered service in 2007, and all new CFM56-5B and CFM56-7B engines are being built with the Tech Insertion components. CFMI also offers the components as an upgrade kit for existing engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;safran&quot;&gt;Angrand, A. (2007). &quot;[http://www.webcitation.org/5ory01ylE?url=http://www.safran-na.com/IMG/pdf/SAFRAN2UKp26-27.pdf Tech Insertion: Eternal youth for the CFM56 (pdf)]&quot;. ''SAFRAN magazine''. November 2007. Retrieved 23 March 2010. pp. 26–7.&lt;/ref&gt;

====CFM56-7B &quot;Evolution&quot;====
In 2009, CFMI announced the latest upgrade to the CFM56 engine, the &quot;CFM56-7B Evolution&quot; or CFM56-7BE. This upgrade, announced with improvements to Boeing's 737 Next Generation, further enhances the high- and low-pressure turbines with better aerodynamics, as well as improving engine cooling, and aims to reduce overall part count.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.geae.com/aboutgeae/presscenter/cfm56/cfm56-7/cfm56-7_20090428.html &quot;CFM Launches CFM56-7B Evolution Engine Program to Power Enhanced Boeing Next-Generation 737&quot;]. GE Aviation Press Release. 28 April 2009. Retrieved 19 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; CFMI expected the changes to result in a 4% reduction in maintenance costs and a 1% improvement in fuel consumption (2% improvement including the airframe changes for the new 737); flight and ground tests completed in May 2010 revealed that the fuel burn improvement was better than expected at 1.6%.&lt;ref name=&quot;7BE&quot;&gt;Norris, Guy (2010). [http://aviationweek.com/awin/airbus-weighs-modified-cfm56-5-upgrade-options Airbus Weighs Modified CFM56-5 Upgrade Options]. ''Aviation Week''. 12 May 2010. Retrieved 19 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Following 450 hours of testing, the CFM56-7BE engine was certified by FAA and EASA on 30 July 2010&lt;ref&gt;Ostrower, Jon. [http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100809225816/http://www.flightglobal.com/Articles/2010/08/02/345667/cfm56-7be-achieves-faa-and-easa-certification.html &quot;CFM56-7BE achieves FAA and EASA certification&quot;]. Air Transport Intelligence news via Flightglobal.com. 2 August 2010. Retrieved 2 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and delivered since mid-2011.

The CFM56-5B/3 PIP (Performance Improvement Package) engine include these new technologies and hardware changes to lower fuel burn and lower maintenance cost.  Airbus A320s were to use this engine version starting in late 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/cfm-brings-elements-of-evolution-upgrade-to-a320-powerplant-355775/ CFM brings elements of Evolution upgrade to A320 powerplant]&lt;/ref&gt;

====LEAP====
{{Main article|CFM International LEAP}}
The LEAP is a new engine design based on and designed to replace the CFM56 series, with 16% efficiency savings by using more composite materials and achieving higher bypass ratios of over 10:1. LEAP is expected to enter service in 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/new-engines-flurry-of-activity-despite-downturn-332998/|title=New engines: flurry of activity despite downturn|author=Croft, John|date=6 October 2009|publisher=Flight Global}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational History==

As of June 2016, as the most used [[high bypass turbofan]], it achieved more than 800 million engine flight hours, and at a rate of one million flight hours every eight days it will achieve one billion flight hours by 2020.&lt;ref name=160602PR/&gt; It has more than 550 operators and more than 2,400 CFM56-powered [[jet aircraft]] are in the air at any moment.&lt;ref name=160602PR/&gt; It is known for its [[dependability]]: its average time on wing is 30,000 hours before a first [[Aircraft maintenance|shop visit]], with the current fleet record at 50,000 hours.&lt;ref name=160602PR&gt;{{cite press release |url= https://www.cfmaeroengines.com/press-articles/cfm56-fleet-surpasses-800-million-flight-hours/ |title= CFM56 fleet surpasses 800 million flight hours |publisher= CFM international |date= 2 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of July 2016, 30,000 engines have been built: 9,860 CFM56-5 engines for the [[Airbus A320ceo]] and [[A340]]-200/300 and more than 17,300 CFM56-3/-7B engines for the [[Boeing 737 Classic]] and [[737NG]].&lt;ref name=160712PR/&gt; CFM plans to produce 1,700 engines in 2016, the highest production rate in the industry, and there are 3,000 engines in backlog.&lt;ref name=160712PR&gt;{{cite press release |url= https://www.cfmaeroengines.com/press-articles/cfm-news-release-30000th-cfm56-engine-comes-production-line/ |title= 30,000th CFM56 engine comes off the production-line |publisher= CFM international |date= 12 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lufthansa]], launch customer for the CFM56-5C-powered A340, have an engine with more than 100,000 flight hours, having entered commercial service on November 16, 1993 [[overhaul]]ed four times since.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url= https://www.cfmaeroengines.com/press-articles/lufthansa-cfm56-5c-engine-achieves-100000-flight-hours/ |title= Lufthansa CFM56-5C engine achieves 100,000 flight hours |publisher= CFM International |date= 8 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==

===Summary===
The CFM56 is a high-bypass turbofan engine (most of the air accelerated by the fan bypasses the core of the engine and is exhausted out of the fan case) with several variants having [[bypass ratio]]s ranging from 5:1 to 6:1, generating 18,500 to 34,000&amp;nbsp;lbf (80&amp;nbsp;kN to 150&amp;nbsp;kN) of thrust. The variants share a common design, but the details differ. The CFM56 is a two-shaft (or two-spool) engine, meaning that there are two rotating shafts, one high-pressure and one low-pressure. Each is powered by its own turbine section (the high-pressure and low-pressure turbines, respectively). The fan and booster (low-pressure compressor) evolved over the different iterations of the engine, as did the compressor, combustor and turbine sections.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt;

===Combustor===
[[File:CFM56 Combustion Chamber Dome Detail.JPG|thumb|Swirl fuel nozzles of a CFM56 annular combustor]]

Most variants of the CFM56 feature a [[Annular combustor|single-annular combustor]]. An annular combustor is a continuous ring where fuel is injected into the airflow and ignited, raising the pressure and temperature of the flow. Other types of combustors include [[Combustor#Can type|can combustors]], where each combustion chamber is separate, and [[Cannular|canannular]] which is a hybrid of the two. Fuel injection is regulated by a Hydromechanical Unit (HMU), built by [[Honeywell]]. The HMU regulates the amount of fuel delivered to the engine by means of an [[electrohydraulic servo valve]] that, in turn, drives a fuel metering valve, that provides information to the [[FADEC|full authority digital engine controller]] (FADEC).&lt;ref&gt;Croft, John. &quot;Fueling fears&quot;, ''Aviation Week and Space Technology'', 18 February 2013, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1989, CFMI began work on a new, double-annular combustor. Instead of having just one combustion zone, the double-annular combustor has a second combustion zone that is used at high thrust levels. This design lowers the emissions of both [[NOx|nitrogen oxides]] (NO&lt;sub&gt;''x''&lt;/sub&gt;) and [[carbon dioxide]] (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;). The first CFM56 engine with the double-annular combustor entered service in 1995, and the combustor is used on &quot;Tech Insertion&quot; CFM56-5B and CFM56-7B variants.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cfm56.com/press/news/cfms+advanced+double+annular+combustor+technology/198?page_index=23 CFM'S Advanced Double Annular Combustor Technology]&quot;. CFM International Press Release. 9 July 1998. Retrieved 16 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

GE started developing and testing a new type of combustor called the [[Twin Annular Premixing Swirler]] combustor, or &quot;TAPS&quot;, during the Tech&amp;nbsp;56 program.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56son&quot;/&gt; This design is similar to the double-annular combustor in that it has two combustion zones; this combustor &quot;swirls&quot; the flow, creating an ideal fuel–air mixture. This difference allows the combustor to generate much less NO&lt;sub&gt;''x''&lt;/sub&gt; than other combustors. Tests on a CFM56-7B engine demonstrated an improvement of 46% over single-annular combustors and 22% over double-annular combustors.&lt;ref name=&quot;TAPS&quot;&gt;Mongia, Hukam (2003). ''TAPS –A 4th Generation Propulsion Combustor Technology for Low Emissions''. AIAA/ICAS International Air and Space Symposium and Exposition: The Next 100 Years, 14–17 July 2003, Dayton, Ohio. AIAA 2003-2657.&lt;/ref&gt; The analytical tools developed for TAPS have also been used to improve other combustors, notably the single-annular combustors in some CFM56-5B and -7B engines.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cfm56.com/press/news/cfm56-5b/-7b+tech+insertion+package+on+schedule+for+2007+eis/135?sort=2&amp;advanced=1&amp;channel_id=&amp;searchkey=taps&amp;datefrom=1/1/2006&amp;dateto=mm/dd/yyyy&amp;sortcheck=2 CFM56-5B/-7B Tech Insertion Package On Schedule For 2007 EIS]&quot;. CFM International Press Release. 13 June 2005. Retrieved 16 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Compressor===
[[File:Cfm56-3-turbofan.jpeg|thumb|alt=An engine public show at national museum, with the front aft facing left. Sections of the casing are trimmed out and replaced with clear plastic revealing booster vane, compressor and turbine blades, from left to right.|right|CFM56-3 casing, high-pressure compressor revealed.]]

The high-pressure compressor-HPC, that was at the center of the original export controversy, features nine stages in each variant of the CFM56. The compressor stages have been developed from [[General Electric|GE]]'s &quot;GE&lt;sup&gt;1/9&lt;/sup&gt; core&quot; (namely a single-turbine, nine-compressor stage design) which was designed in a compact core rotor. The small span of the compressor radius meant that the entire engine could be lighter and smaller, as the [[accessory unit]]s in the system ([[Bearing (mechanical)|bearings]], oiling systems) could be merged to the main fueling system running on aviation fuel.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt; As design evolved ''HPC'' design improved through better airfoil design. As part of the [[Tech-56 improvement program]] CFMI has tested the new CFM-56 model with six-stage high-pressure [[compressor stage]]s (discs that make up the compressor system) that was designed to deliver same pressure ratios (pressure gain 30) similar to the old nine-stages compressor design. The new one was not fully replacing the old one, but it offered an upgrade in HPC, thanks to improved [[blade (disambiguation)|blade]] dynamics, as a part of their &quot;Tech Insertion&quot; management plan from 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56son&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Norris, Guy [http://wayback.archive.org/web/20121102231320/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/cfmi-details-insertion-plan-for-tech-56-185357/ &quot;CFMI details insertion plan for Tech 56&quot;]. ''Flight International'', 4 August 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Flight International''. 3 August 2004. Retrieved 17 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exhaust===
CFMI tested both a mixed and unmixed exhaust design at the beginning of development;&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAA-Venture&quot;/&gt; most variants of the engine have an unmixed exhaust nozzle.&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot; name=&quot;e2&quot;/&gt; Only the high-power CFM56-5C, designed for the Airbus A340, has a mixed-flow exhaust nozzle.&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot; name=&quot;e1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56rise&quot;/&gt;

GE and SNECMA also tested the effectiveness of [[Chevron (aerospace)|chevrons]] on reducing jet noise.&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;''Chevron'' is the name for sawtooth cutouts that are sometimes applied to the exhaust nozzles of jet engines to reduce the jet noise. An example can be seen here [http://www.sti.nasa.gov/tto/Spinoff2008/images/asa-20.gif]. (The pictured engine is not a CFM56.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brausch, John F. et al (2002). [http://www.google.com/patents/about?id=UAAJAAAAEBAJ US Patent number: 6360528, &quot;Chevron exhaust nozzle for a gas turbine engine&quot;]. Retrieved 22 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; After examining configurations in the [[wind tunnel]], CFMI chose to flight-test chevrons built into the core exhaust nozzle. The chevrons reduced jet noise by 1.3 perceived loudness [[decibel]]s during takeoff conditions, and are now offered as an option with the CFM56 for the [[Airbus A321]].&lt;ref&gt;Loheac, Pierre, Julliard, Jacques, Dravet, Alain (May 2004). &quot;''[http://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2004-3044|CFM56 Jet Noise Reduction with the Chevron Nozzle]''&quot;. 10th AIAA([[American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics]])/CEAS Aeroacoustics Conference (Manchester, Great Britain). AIAA 2004-3044, doi:10.2514/6.2004-3044 {{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fan and booster===
[[File:CFM56 dsc04641.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=The front fan of a jet engine facing the left of the image, surrounded by its metal casing. The conical inlet in seen right in front of the metal fan blades. The fan casing is seen in three distinct (but attached) sections from left to right, first a silver-colored section, then a golden-colored section, then another silver-colored section.|Fan and fan case of a CFM56-5]]

The CFM56 features a single-stage fan, and most variants have a three-stage booster on the low-pressure shaft,&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;The ''Low-Pressure Shaft'', in a two-shaft engine, is the shaft that is turned by the low-pressure [[Components of jet engines#Turbines|turbine]] (LPT). Generally the fan section(s) and the booster section(s) (also known as the &quot;low-pressure compressor&quot;) are located on the low-pressure shaft.&lt;/ref&gt; with four stages in the -5B and -5C variants.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-5B&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100307035338/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-5b CFM56-5B Technology]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The booster is also commonly called the &quot;low-pressure compressor&quot; (LPC) as it sits on the low-pressure shaft and compresses the flow initially before reaching the high-pressure compressor. The original CFM56-2 variant featured 44 tip-[[Shroud (turbine)|shrouded]] fan blades,&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56-2&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100530091327/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-2/cfm56-2-technology CFM56-2 Technology]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;''Shrouds'' are plates that are a part of a fan (or compressor, or turbine) blade. Generally, the shroud of one blade rests on the shroud of the adjacent blade, forming a continuous ring. Shrouds in the middle of blades are often used to damp [[vibration]]s. Shrouds at the tips of fan blades are often used to minimize air leakage around the tips. A midspan shroud is visible on the fan blades here [http://wayback.archive.org/web/20110125193219/http://enginehistory.org/GasTurbines/Blades/PaoloPisani/Comparisons/comp_4.JPG]. (Note that these fan blades are not from a CFM56.) (Gunston, Bill (2004). ''Cambridge Aerospace Dictionary''. Cambridge University Press. 2004. p.558-9.)&lt;/ref&gt; although the number of fan blades was reduced in later variants as wide-chord blade technology developed, down to 22 blades in the latest variant, the CFM56-7.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-7&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100412142134/http://www.cfm56.com/press/news/cfm56-7+an+in-depth+look+at+the+new+industry+leader/63? CFM56-7: An In-Depth Look At The New Industry Leader]&quot;. CFM International, 12 June 1996. Retrieved 13 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The CFM56 fan features [[Dovetail joint|dovetailed]] fan blades which allows them to be replaced without removing the entire engine, and GE/SNECMA claim that the CFM56 was the first engine to have that capability. This attachment method is useful for circumstances where only a few fan blades need to be repaired or replaced, such as following [[bird strike]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56age&quot;&gt;Velupillai, David (1981). [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1981/1981%20-%201100.html CFM56 Comes of Age]. ''Flight International''. 18 April 1981. Retrieved 1 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The fan diameter varies with the different models of the CFM56, and that change has a direct impact on the engine performance. For example, the low-pressure shaft rotates at the same speed for both the CFM56-2 and the CFM56-3 models; the fan diameter is smaller on the -3, which lowers the tip speed of the fan blades. The lower speed allows the fan blades to operate more efficiently (5.5% more in this case), which increases the overall fuel efficiency of the engine (improving [[Thrust specific fuel consumption|specific fuel consumption]] nearly 3%).&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-3&quot;/&gt;

===Reverse thrust===
[[File:F-GTAR Air France (3698209485).jpg|thumb|Pivoting-door thrust reversers are installed on the CFM56-5. Noise-reducing [[Chevron (aerospace)|chevrons]] can also be seen at the engine's rear. |alt=A turbofan engine is shown on an aircraft decelerating on a runway. Small doors on the rear half engine are open.]]

The CFM56 is designed to support several [[Thrust reversal|reverse thrust]] systems which help slow and stop the aircraft after landing. The variants built for the Boeing&amp;nbsp;737, the CFM56-3 and the CFM56-7, use a cascade type of thrust reverser. This type of thrust reverse consists of sleeves that slide back to expose mesh-like cascades and blocker doors that block the bypass air flow. The blocked bypass air is forced through the cascades, reducing the thrust of the engine and slowing the aircraft down.&lt;ref&gt;Brady, Chris. [http://www.b737.org.uk/powerplant.htm#Reverse_Thrust Reverse Thrust]. The 737 Technical Site. Updated: 23 May 2010. Retrieved 28 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;NTSB No: DCA-06-MA-009. [http://wayback.archive.org/web/20061008164354/http://www.ntsb.gov/Events/2006/ChicagoIL%20SW/Exhibits/347284.pdf Section D.1.3 Thrust Reverser Description (pdf)]. National Transportation Safety Board. 10 April 2006. Retrieved 28 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The CFM56 also supports pivoting-door type thrust reversers. This type is used on the CFM56-5 engines that power many Airbus aircraft. They work by actuating a door that pivots down into the bypass duct, both blocking the bypass air and deflecting the flow outward, creating the reverse thrust.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |last = Linke-Diesinger
 |first = Andreas
 |title = Systems of Commercial Turbofan Engines: An Introduction to Systems Functions
 |publisher = Springer Berlin Heidelberg
 |year = 2008
 |chapter = Chapter 8: Thrust Reverser Systems
 |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/u120828176525781/
 |doi = 10.1007/978-3-540-73619-6_8
 |isbn = 978-3-540-73618-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Turbine===
[[File:CFM International CFM56-7B26 fitted to Qantas (VH-VZY) Boeing 737-838 (WL) at the Canberra Airport open day (5).jpg|thumb|Stator vane cooling air ducts circle the iridescent shroud of a CFM56-7B26 turbine]]

All variants of the CFM56 feature a single-stage high-pressure turbine (HPT). In some variants, the HPT [[Turbine blade|blades]] are &quot;grown&quot; from a [[single crystal]] [[superalloy]], giving them high strength and [[Creep (deformation)|creep]] resistance. The low-pressure turbine (LPT) features four stages in most variants of the engine, but the CFM56-5C has a five-stage LPT. This change was implemented to drive the larger fan on this variant.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56rise&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1991/1991%20-%201456.html CFM56 rises to challenge]&quot;. ''Flight International''. 11 June 1991. Retrieved 17 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Improvements to the turbine section were examined during the Tech56 program, and one development was an [[Aerodynamics|aerodynamically]] optimized low-pressure turbine blade design, which would have used 20% fewer blades for the whole low-pressure turbine, saving weight. Some of those Tech56 improvements made their way into the Tech Insertion package, where the turbine section was updated.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56son&quot;/&gt; The turbine section was updated again in the &quot;Evolution&quot; upgrade.&lt;ref name=&quot;safran&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;7BE&quot;/&gt;

The high-pressure turbine stages in the CFM56 are internally cooled by air from the high-pressure compressor. The air passes through internal channels in each blade and ejects at the leading and trailing edges.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56age&quot;/&gt;

==Variants==

===CFM56-2 series===
The CFM56-2 series is the original variant of the CFM56. It is most widely used in military applications where it is known as the F108; specifically in the [[KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135]], the [[E-6 Mercury]] and some [[Boeing E-3 Sentry|E-3 Sentry]] aircraft. The CFM56-2 comprises a single-stage fan with 44 blades, with a three-stage LP compressor driven by a four-stage LP turbine, and a nine-stage HP compressor driven by a single-stage HP turbine. The combustor is annular.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56-2&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; color:black;&quot;
|-
!class=&quot;unsortable&quot;| Model !! [[Thrust]] !! [[Bypass ratio]] !! [[Overall pressure ratio|Pressure ratio]] !! Dry weight&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;''Dry Weight'' is the weight of an engine without any fluids in it, such as fuel, oil, hydraulic fluid, etc. Very similar to the [[Dry weight (automobile)|dry weight of an automobile]]&lt;/ref&gt; !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;| Applications
|-
| CFM56-2A-2 (-3)|| {{convert|24000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}} ||5.9||31.8|| {{convert|4820|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Boeing E-3 Sentry|E-3 Sentry]], [[E-6 Mercury]]
|-
| CFM56-2B1|| {{convert|22000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}} ||6.0||30.5|| {{convert|4671|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135R Stratotanker]], [[Boeing RC-135|RC-135]]
|-
| CFM56-2C1|| {{convert|22000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}} ||6.0||31.3|| {{convert|4653|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Douglas DC-8#Super seventies|Douglas DC-8-70]]
|}

===CFM56-3 series===
[[File:AirBaltic Boeing 737-500 turbine.jpg|thumb|A CFM56-3 series engine mounted on a [[Boeing 737 Classic|Boeing 737-300]] airliner showing flattening of the nacelle at the bottom of the inlet lip. |alt= A close-up view of a CFM56-3 series engine mounted on a Boeing 737-300 showing flattening of the nacelle at the bottom of the inlet lip.]]

The first derivative of the CFM56 series, the CFM56-3 is designed for [[Boeing 737 Classic]] series (737-300/-400/-500), with static thrust ratings from {{convert|18500|to|23500|lbf|kN|abbr=on|sigfig=3}}. A &quot;cropped fan&quot; derivative of the -2, the -3 engine has a smaller fan diameter at 60&amp;nbsp;in (1.5&amp;nbsp;m) but retains the original basic engine layout. The new fan is primarily derived from GE's [[CF6#CF6-80|CF6-80]] turbofan rather than the CFM56-2, and the booster was redesigned to match the new fan.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-3&quot;/&gt;

A significant challenge for this series was achieving ground clearance for the wing-mounted engine. This was overcome by reducing the intake fan diameter and relocating the gearbox and other accessories from beneath the engine to the sides.  The resulting flattened nacelle bottom and intake lip yielded the distinctive appearance of the Boeing&amp;nbsp;737 with CFM56 engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-3web&quot;&gt;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20080920144013/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-3 &quot;CFM56-3 Technology&quot;]. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; color:black;&quot;
|-
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Model !! Thrust !! Bypass ratio !! Pressure ratio !! Dry weight !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Applications
|-
| CFM56-3B-1||{{convert|20000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||6.0||27.5||{{convert|4276|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}} ||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Boeing 737-300]], [[Boeing 737-500]]
|-
| CFM56-3B-2||{{convert|22000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.9||28.8||{{convert|4301|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Boeing 737-300, [[Boeing 737-400]]
|-
| CFM56-3C-1||{{convert|23500|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||6.0||30.6||{{convert|4301|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Boeing 737-300, Boeing 737-400, Boeing 737-500
|}

===CFM56-4 series===
The CFM56-4 series was a proposed improved version of the CFM56-2 designed for the [[Airbus A320 family|Airbus A320]] family of aircraft. Competing with the [[Rolls-Royce/JAEC RJ500|RJ500]] engine being developed by Rolls-Royce, the -4 series was designed to produce 25,000&amp;nbsp;lbf (110&amp;nbsp;kN) and was to feature a new 68&amp;nbsp;in (1.73&amp;nbsp;m) fan, a new low-pressure compressor and a full authority digital engine controller (FADEC). Soon after the upgrade project was launched in 1984, International Aero Engines offered their new [[IAE V2500|V2500]] engine for the A320. CFMI realized that the CFM56-4 did not compare favorably with the new engine and scrapped the project to begin working on the CFM56-5 series.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt;

===CFM56-5 series===
[[File:CFM56 engine of a Hamburg Airways Airbus A319.jpg|thumb|CFM56-5B on an [[Airbus A319]]]]

The CFM56-5 series is designed for the [[Airbus]] aircraft and has a very wide thrust rating of between {{convert|22000|and|34000|lbf|kN|abbr=on|sigfig=3}}. It has three distinct sub-variants; the CFM56-5A, CFM56-5B and CFM56-5C,&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt; and differs from its Boeing-fitted cousins by featuring a FADEC and incorporating further aerodynamic design improvements.

====CFM56-5A series====
The CFM56-5A series is the initial CFM56-5 series, designed to power the short-to-medium range [[Airbus A320 family]]. Derived from the CFM56-2 and CFM56-3 families, the -5A series produces thrusts between 22,000 and 26,500&amp;nbsp;lbf (98&amp;nbsp;kN and 118&amp;nbsp;kN). Aerodynamic improvements such as an updated fan, low-pressure compressor, high-pressure compressor and combustor make this variant 10–11% more fuel efficient than its predecessors.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100530091448/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-5a/cfm56-5a-history CFM56-5A History]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100530091453/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-5a/cfm56-5a-technology CFM56-5A Technology]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; color:black;&quot;
|-
!class=&quot;unsortable&quot;| Model !! Thrust !! Bypass ratio !! Pressure ratio !! Dry weight !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Applications
|-
| CFM56-5A1||{{convert|25000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||6.0||31.3||{{convert|4995|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Airbus A320 family|Airbus A320]]
|-
| CFM56-5A3||{{convert|26500|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||6.0||31.3||{{convert|4995|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A320
|-
| CFM56-5A4||{{convert|22000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||6.2||31.3||{{convert|4995|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A319
|-
| CFM56-5A5||{{convert|23500|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||6.2||31.3||{{convert|4995|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A319
|}

====CFM56-5B series====
[[File:CFM56-5B9P on A319.jpg|thumb|Front view of an A319-112 CFM56-5B6 with its fan removed]]

An improvement of the CFM56-5A series, it was originally designed to power the A321. With a thrust range between 22,000 and 33,000&amp;nbsp;lbf (98&amp;nbsp;kN and 147&amp;nbsp;kN) it can power every model in the A320 family (A318/A319/A320/A321) and has superseded the CFM56-5A series. Among the changes from the CFM56-5A is the option of a double-annular combustor that reduces emissions (particularly NO&lt;sub&gt;''x''&lt;/sub&gt;), a new fan in a longer fan case, and a new low-pressure compressor with a fourth stage (up from three in earlier variants). It is the most numerous engine supplied to Airbus.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-5B&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100530091458/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-5b/cfm56-5b-history CFM56-5B History]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 20 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; color:black;&quot;
|-
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Model !! Thrust !! Bypass ratio !! Pressure ratio !! Dry weight !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Applications
|-
| CFM56-5B1||{{convert|30000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.5||35.4||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Airbus A321]]
|-
| CFM56-5B2||{{convert|31000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.5||35.4||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A321
|-
| CFM56-5B3||{{convert|33000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.4||35.5||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A321
|-
| CFM56-5B4||{{convert|27000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.7||32.6||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A320
|-
| CFM56-5B5||{{convert|22000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||6.0||32.6||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Airbus A319]]
|-
| CFM56-5B6||{{convert|23500|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.9||32.6||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A319, A320
|-
| CFM56-5B7||{{convert|27000|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.7||35.5||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A319, [[Airbus A319CJ|A319CJ]]
|-
| CFM56-5B8||{{convert|21600|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||6.0||32.6||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Airbus A318]]
|-
| CFM56-5B9||{{convert|23300|lbf|kN|sigfig=2|abbr=on}}||5.9||32.6||{{convert|5250|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Airbus A318
|}

====CFM56-5C series====
[[File:2010-10-01 17-47-08 South Africa - Bonaero Park HB-JMO.jpg|thumb|Two of four CFM56-5C installed on an [[Airbus A340-300]].]]

With a thrust rating of between 31,200 and 34,000&amp;nbsp;lbf (139&amp;nbsp;kN and 151&amp;nbsp;kN), the CFM56-5C series is the most powerful of the CFM56 family. It powers Airbus' long-range [[Airbus A340|A340-200 and -300]] airliners, and entered service in 1993. The major changes are a larger fan, a fifth low-pressure turbine stage, and the same four-stage low-pressure compressor found in the -5B variant.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100530091524/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-5c/cfm56-5c-technology CFM56-5C Technology]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike every other variant of the CFM56, the -5C features a mixed-exhaust nozzle,&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot; name=&quot;e1&quot;/&gt; which offers slightly higher efficiency.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfm56rise&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; color:black;&quot;
|-
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Model !! Thrust !! Bypass ratio !! Pressure ratio !! Dry weight !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Applications
|-
| CFM56-5C2||{{convert|31200|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||6.6||37.4||{{convert|8796|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Airbus A340|Airbus A340-200/-300]]
|-
| CFM56-5C3||{{convert|32500|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||6.5||37.4||{{convert|8796|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;| Airbus A340-200/-300
|-
| CFM56-5C4||{{convert|34000|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||6.4||38.3||{{convert|8796|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;| Airbus A340-200/-300
|}

===CFM56-7 series===
[[File:CFM 56 Lauda 737.jpg|thumb|CFM56-7 of a [[Boeing 737 Next Generation|Boeing 737-800]]]]

The CFM56-7 powers the [[Boeing 737 Next Generation]] series (737-600/-700/-800/-900). The CFM56-7 first ran on 21 April 1995&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cfmaeroengines.com/press/first-cfm56-7-engine-to-test-runs-on-schedule/12 First CFM56-7 Engine to Test Runs on Schedule]&quot;. CFM International, 22 May 1995. Retrieved 30 April 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; is rated with takeoff thrust from 19,500 to 27,300&amp;nbsp;lbf (86.7&amp;nbsp;kN to 121&amp;nbsp;kN). It has higher thrust ranges, improved efficiency, and lower maintenance costs than its predecessor, the CFM56-3 series. It incorporates features from the CFM56-5 series such as [[FADEC]], double-annular combustor (as an option), and improved internal design. The basic mechanical arrangement is as the -3 series, but all aspects were aerodynamically improved from that model. For example, the improved wide-chord fan blades allowed the total number of fan blades to be reduced from 38 to 24. Other improvements came from material advances, such as the use of [[single crystal|single-crystal]] turbine blades in the high-pressure turbine.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-7B&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100505122814/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-7b/cfm56-7b-technology CFM56-7B Technology]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The CFM56-7-powered 737 is granted 180-minute [[ETOPS|Extended-Range, Twin-Engine Operations]] (ETOPS) approval by the U.S. [[Federal Aviation Administration]]. It also powers the military versions of the Next-Generation 737, the [[C-40 Clipper]], the [[P-8 Poseidon]], and [[Boeing 737 AEW&amp;C]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100505122724/http://www.cfm56.com/products/cfm56-7b/cfm56-7b-history CFM56-7B History]&quot;. CFM International. Retrieved 12 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; color:black;&quot;
|-
! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Model !! Thrust !! Bypass ratio !! Pressure ratio !! Dry weight !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|Applications
|-
| CFM56-7B18||{{convert|19500|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||5.5||32.8||{{convert|5216|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Boeing 737-600]]
|-
| CFM56-7B20||{{convert|20600|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||5.5||32.8||{{convert|5216|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Boeing 737-600, [[Boeing 737-700]]
|-
| CFM56-7B22||{{convert|22700|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||5.3||32.8||{{convert|5216|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Boeing 737-600, Boeing 737-700
|-
| CFM56-7B24||{{convert|24200|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||5.3||32.8||{{convert|5216|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Boeing 737-700, [[Boeing 737-800]], [[Boeing 737-900]]
|-
| CFM56-7B26||{{convert|26300|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||5.1||32.8||{{convert|5216|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Boeing 737-700, Boeing 737-800, Boeing 737-900
|-
| CFM56-7B27||{{convert|27300|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||5.1||32.8||{{convert|5216|lb|kg|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}||align=&quot;left&quot;|Boeing 737-800, Boeing 737-900, [[Boeing Business Jet]]
|}

==Reliability==

The CFM56 have an in-flight shutdown rate of 1 incident per 333,333 hours.&lt;ref name=960902PR&gt;{{cite press release |url= http://www.geaviation.com/press/cfm56/cfm56-x/cfm56-x_19960902b.html |title= CFM56 Engines: The Standard To Which Others Are Judged |publisher= CFM International |date= September 2, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; Record time on wing before the first shop visit was 30,000 hours in 1996,&lt;ref name=960902PR/&gt; to 40,729 hours in 2003&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.smartcockpit.com/docs/CFM_Flight_Ops_Support_B737.pdf |title= Flight Operations Support |date= 13 December 2005 |publisher= CFM International}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 50,000 hours in 2016.&lt;ref name=160602PR/&gt;

There have been several engine failures in the early service of the CFM56 family which were serious enough to either ground the fleet or require aspects of the engine to be redesigned.  The engines have also suffered, periodically, from thrust instability events tentatively traced to Honeywell's hydromechanical unit.

===Rain and hail ingestion===
There are several recorded incidents of CFM56 engines [[Flameout|flaming out]] in heavy rain and/or hail conditions, beginning early in the CFM56's career. In 1987, a double flameout occurred in hail conditions (the pilots managed to relight the engines), followed by the [[TACA Flight 110]] incident in 1988. Both CFM56 engines on the TACA 737 flamed out while passing through hail and heavy rain, and the crew was forced to land without engines on a grassy [[levee]] near New Orleans, Louisiana. CFMI modified the engines by adding a sensor to force the [[combustor]] to continuously ignite under these conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt;

In 2002, [[Garuda Indonesia Flight 421]] had to [[Water landing#In distress|ditch]] in a river because of hail-induced engine flameouts, killing a flight attendant and injuring dozens of passengers. Prior to this accident, there were several other incidents of single or dual flameouts due to these weather conditions. After three incidents through 1998, CFMI made modifications to the engine to improve the way in which the engine handled hail ingestion. The major changes included a modification to the fan/booster splitter (making it more difficult for hail to be ingested by the core of the engine) and the use of an elliptical, rather than conical, spinner at the intake. These changes did not prevent the 2002 accident, and the investigation board found that the pilots did not follow the proper procedures for attempting to restart the engine, which contributed to the final result. Recommendations were made to better educate pilots on how to handle these conditions, as well as to revisit [[FAA]] rain and hail testing procedures. No further engine modifications were recommended.&lt;ref name=&quot;hail&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.webcitation.org/5m4AuYDuG?url=http://www.ntsb.gov/Recs/letters/2005/A05_19_20.pdf Safety Recommendation A-05-19 and 20 (pdf)]&quot;. [NTSB Recommendations]. National Transportation Safety Board, 31 August 2005. Retrieved 4 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fan blade failure===
One issue that led to accidents with the CFM56-3C engine was the failure of fan blades. This mode of failure led to the [[Kegworth air disaster]] in 1989, which killed 47 people and injured 74 more. After the fan blade failed, the pilots mistakenly shut down the wrong engine, resulting in the damaged engine failing completely when powered up for the final approach. Following the Kegworth accident, CFM56 engines fitted to a [[Dan-Air]] 737-400 and a [[BMI (airline)|British Midland]] 737-400 suffered fan blade failures under similar conditions; neither incident resulted in a crash or injuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaw&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.aaib.gov.uk/publications/formal_reports/4_1990_g_obme.cfm Report on the accident to Boeing&amp;nbsp;737-400, G-OBME, near Kegworth, Leicestershire on 8 January 1989]&quot; (1990). Report No: 4/1990. Air Investigations Branch. 25 August 1990. Retrieved 22 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; After the second incident, the 737-400 fleet was grounded.

At the time it was not mandatory to flight test new variants of existing engines, and certification testing failed to reveal vibration modes that the fan experienced during the regularly performed power climbs at high altitude. Analysis revealed that the fan was being subjected to [[high-cycle fatigue]] stresses worse than expected and also more severe than tested for certification; these higher stresses caused the blade to fracture. Less than a month after grounding, the fleet was allowed to resume operations once the fan blades and fan disc were replaced and the electronic engine controls were modified to reduce maximum engine thrust to 22,000&amp;nbsp;lbf (98&amp;nbsp;kN) from 23,500&amp;nbsp;lbf (105&amp;nbsp;kN).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1989/1989%20-%202046.html Derating Clears CFM56-3Cs to Fly]&quot; (1989). ''Flight International''. 1 July 1989. Retrieved 11 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The redesigned fan blades were installed on all CFM56-3C1 and CFM56-3B2 engines, including over 1,800 engines that had already been delivered to customers.&lt;ref name=&quot;cfmstory&quot;/&gt;

===Fuel flow problems===
Airlines have reported 32 events involving sudden instability of thrust, at various points during flight, including high thrust settings during climb to altitude.  The problem has been long-standing. In 1998, two 737 pilots reported that their engine throttles suddenly increased to full thrust during flight. A very recent investigation has led to the tentative conclusion that the problem originates in the Hydromechanical unit, and may involve an unacceptable level of fuel contamination (with water, or particulate matter, including biodegradable material that create solids in the fuel), or overuse of biocides to reduce bacterial growth.  Boeing told [[Aviation Week and Space Technology]] that CFM International had revised its FADEC software.  The new software &quot;...'reduces the duration and degree of thrust-instability events' by cycling the fuel monitoring valve (FMV) and the EHSV (electrohydraulic servo unit) to clean the EHSV spool.&quot; This software fix is not intended to be a definitive solution to the problem; CFM claimed that no further reports have reached it after this change was made.&lt;ref&gt;Croft, John. &quot;Fueling fears&quot;, Aviation Week and Space Technology, 18 February 2013, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Applications==
* [[Airbus A320 family]]
**[[Airbus A318]]
* [[Airbus A340]]
* [[Boeing 707#Variants|Boeing 707-700]] (prototype only)
* [[Boeing 737 Classic]]
* [[Boeing 737 Next Generation]]
** [[Boeing 737 AEW&amp;C]]
** [[Boeing C-40 Clipper]]
** [[Boeing P-8 Poseidon]]
* [[Boeing Business Jet]]
* [[Boeing E-3 Sentry|Boeing E-3D Sentry]]
* [[Boeing E-6 Mercury]]
* [[Boeing KC-135 Stratotanker|Boeing KC-135R Stratotanker]]
** [[Boeing RC-135]]
* [[Douglas DC-8#Super seventies|Douglas DC-8 Super 70]]

==Specifications (CFM56-7B18)==
{{jetspecs
&lt;!-- If you do not understand how to use this template, please ask at [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Aircraft]]
     Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses). If data are missing, leave the parameter blank (do not delete it). For additional lines, end your alt units with )&lt;/li&gt; and start a new, fully formatted line with &lt;li&gt; --&gt;
|ref= ''CFM International''&lt;ref name=&quot;CFM56-7B&quot;/&gt;
|type=Twin-spool, high-bypass [[turbofan]]
|length=98.7&amp;nbsp;in (2.5&amp;nbsp;m)
|diameter=61&amp;nbsp;in (1.55&amp;nbsp;m) (fan)
|weight=5,216&amp;nbsp;lb (2,366&amp;nbsp;kg) (dry)
|compressor=Single-stage fan, 3-stage low-pressure compressor, 9-stage high-pressure compressor
|combustion=annular
|turbine=Single-stage high-pressure turbine, 4-stage low-pressure turbine
|fueltype=
|oilsystem=
|power=
|thrust= {{convert|19500|lbf|kN|sigfig=3|abbr=on}}
|compression=32.8:1
|bypass=5.5:1
|aircon=677&amp;nbsp;lb/s (307&amp;nbsp;kg/s)
|turbinetemp=
|fuelcon=
|specfuelcon=
|power/weight=
|thrust/weight=3.7:1
}}

==See also==
{{Aircontent
|see also=
|related=
* [[CFM International LEAP-X]]
* [[General Electric F101]]
* [[PowerJet SaM146]]
* [[Shenyang WS-10]]
|similar engines=
* [[IAE V2500]]
* [[Pratt &amp; Whitney PW6000]]
|lists=
* [[List of aircraft engines]]
}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=nb|45em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{official website|https://www.cfmaeroengines.com/engines/cfm56/}}
* {{cite news |url= http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1981/1981%20-%201841.html |title= CFM56 Rejuvenates the DC-8 |date= 6 June 1981 |work= Flight International }}
* {{cite web |url= https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/736x/24/12/b1/2412b146afe9366fc93377b74493ff52.jpg |title= CFM56-5C2 Cutaway |work= Flight Global |date= 2006}}

{{Joint development aeroengines}}
{{USAF gas turbine engines}}
{{featured article}}

[[Category:High-bypass turbofan engines]]
[[Category:Turbofan engines 1970–1979]]</text>
      <sha1>2rs368r6az6nka034d0iwen1c2wvf0m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
