<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Charles Domery</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27723127</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736622845</id>
      <parentid>736589225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-28T19:17:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EEng</username>
        <id>6484069</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>(pretty smart eating the cat, as that increased the population of available rats) ce, lead doesn't need to say who did the experiment; I actually do think we need to see if the modern source really treats this as fact or fable</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16547">'''Charles Domery''' ({{circa}}&amp;nbsp;1778&amp;nbsp;– after 1800), later also known as '''Charles Domerz''', was a Polish{{refn|Most sources attribute Polish nationality to him, but his name and that of his birthplace are almost certainly corrupted. It is also likely that while he might have indeed been of Polish ethnicity, he was born under Prussian administration, in the [[Prussian partition|Polish lands recently annexed by Prussia]] under [[First Partition of Poland]], and as such was not a Polish, but a Prussian citizen.|group=note}} soldier serving in the [[Prussian Army|Prussian]] and [[French Revolutionary Army|French]] armies, noted for his [[polyphagia|unusually large appetite]]. Serving in the Prussian Army against France during the [[War of the First Coalition]], he found that the rations of the Prussians were insufficient and deserted to the French Army in return for food. Although generally healthy, he was voraciously hungry during his time in the French service, and ate any available food. While stationed near Paris, he was recorded as having eaten 174 cats in a year, and although he disliked vegetables, he would eat {{convert|4|to|5|lb}} of grass each day if he could not find other food. During service on the French ship ''[[HMS Donegal (1798)|Hoche]]'', he attempted to eat the severed leg of a crew member hit by cannon fire, before other members of the crew wrestled it from him.

In February 1799, the ''Hoche'' was captured by British forces and the crew, including Domery, were interned in [[Liverpool]], where he shocked his captors with his voracious appetite: despite being put on ten times the usual rations, he ate the prison cat and at least 20 rats, and would often eat the prison candles. In one experiment, over the course of a day he ate {{convert|16|lb}} of raw cow's udder, raw beef and [[tallow]] candles and four bottles of [[porter (beer)|porter]], all of which he ate and drank without defecating, urinating, or vomiting.

Almost everything known about Domery comes from a 1799 account by Dr. J. Johnston in the ''[[Medical and Physical Journal]]'', based largely upon information provided by Dr. Thomas Cochrane.{{sfn|Johnston|1800}}

==Appearance and behaviour==
Charles Domery (later also known as Charles Domerz){{sfn|Dickens|1852|p=547}} was born in Benche, Poland&lt;!-- Don't link [[Benche]]. Although &quot;Benche&quot; is what every source gives for his birthplace, no town by that name exists or existed in Poland. Domery was illiterate, and it is almost certainly a mis-transcription by French officials or British interrogators; it's impossible to know what he meant. --&gt;, in around 1778.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=26}}{{refn|Domery's exact date of birth is not recorded. He gave his age as 21 on his capture by the British in February 1799.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=26}} His birthplace is given as &quot;Benche&quot; in all sources, but no town of that name exists in Poland, and it may be a misspelling in an early report which has been perpetuated.|group=note}} From the age of 13, Domery had an unusually large appetite.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=26}} He was one of nine brothers, all of whom Domery said suffered from the same condition.{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=303}} Domery recalled that his father was a hearty eater and generally ate his meat half-boiled, but was too young to recall the quantity.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=31}} The only illness Domery was aware of in the family was an outbreak of smallpox in his youth, which was survived by all the family.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=31}}

Despite his unusual diet and behaviour in the presence of food, doctors described Domery as of a normal build,{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=303}} and tall for the period at {{convert|6|ft|3|in}}.{{sfn|Dickens|1852|p=547}}{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=29}} He had long, brown hair and grey eyes,{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=30}} was smooth-skinned,{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=31}} and was described as having a &quot;pleasant countenance&quot;.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=30}} Doctors observing Domery saw no signs of mental illness and although illiterate, he was considered of normal intelligence by his crewmates and by the prison doctors who studied him.{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=303}}{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=32}} Despite eating vast amounts of food, it was noted by the doctors studying him that he never vomited,{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=28}} other than when fed large amounts of roasted or boiled meat.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=32}} He showed no outward signs of ill health, and doctors observing him noted that his eyes were lively and his tongue clean.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=29}} His pulse was regular at around 84&amp;nbsp;BPM, and his body temperature normal.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=31}} His muscles were normally formed, but observed by doctors to be weaker than usual, although during his time in the army he had marched 14&amp;nbsp;French leagues (approximately 25&amp;nbsp;mi/42&amp;nbsp;km) in a day with no ill effects.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=32}}{{refn|The [[French units of measurement|''lieue'']], or French league, varied in meaning around the country. The commonest usages were 10,000&amp;nbsp;feet (3&amp;nbsp;km) or 2,000&amp;nbsp;[[toise]] (4&amp;nbsp;km).{{sfn|Zupko|1990|p=10}}{{sfn|Zupko|1990|p=10}}|group=note}}

{{Quote box|width=25em|salign=right|quote=In one year [Domery] devoured 174 cats (not their skins) dead or alive; and says, he had several severe conflicts of interest in the act of destroying them, by feeling the effects of their torments on his face and hands: sometimes he killed them before eating, but when very hungry, did not wait to perform this humane office.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=26}}|source=Testimony of M.&amp;nbsp;Picard, who served with Domery throughout his service in the French Army and was interned with him in Liverpool}}
It was observed that immediately after going to bed, generally at about 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm, Domery would begin to sweat profusely.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=30}} After one to two hours lying awake and perspiring, he would fall asleep before waking at around 1:00&amp;nbsp;am extremely hungry, regardless of what he had eaten before going to bed.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=30}} At this time, he would eat any available food, or if no food was available would smoke tobacco.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=30}} At around 2:00&amp;nbsp;am he would go back to sleep, and wake again at between 5:00 and 6:00&amp;nbsp;am, sweating heavily; as soon as he got out of bed, the sweating would cease, starting again whenever he ate.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=31}}

==Military service==
By the age of 13, Domery had enlisted in the [[Prussian Army]], and became part of an army besieging [[Thionville]] during the [[War of the First Coalition]].{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=32}} The Prussian Army was suffering from food shortages which Domery found intolerable; he entered the town and surrendered to the French commander who rewarded him with a large melon, which Domery immediately ate, including the rind.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=32}} He was then given a wide variety of other foodstuffs by the French general, all of which he ate straight away.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=32}}

Domery then enlisted with the [[French Revolutionary Army]],{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=32}} and shocked his new comrades with his unusual eating habits and voracious appetite.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=26}} Granted double rations, and using his pay to buy additional food whenever possible,{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=26}} he nonetheless suffered from extreme hunger; while based in an army camp near Paris, Domery ate 174 cats in a single year, leaving only the skins and bones, and ate {{convert|4|to|5|lb}} of grass each day if other food was unavailable.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=26}}{{sfn|Bondeson|2004|p=273}}

[[File:HMS Donegal engaging Jupiter at San Domingo.png|right|thumb|The ''Hoche'', on which Domery was captured|alt=Painting showing a large sailing ship engaged in battle with another similar ship]]
He preferred raw meat to cooked; while his favourite dish was a raw [[bull]]ock's [[Liver (food)|liver]], he would eat any available meat.{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=303}} While in service on board the French ship [[HMS Donegal (1798)|''Hoche'']],{{sfn|Nicholson|1818|loc=§ Bulimy}} a sailor's leg was shot off by cannon fire, and Domery grabbed the severed limb and began to eat it until a crew member wrestled it from him and threw it into the sea.{{sfn|Bondeson|2004|p=273}}{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=27}}{{refn|The descriptions of Domery's background and diet prior to his capture by the British derive mainly from testimony obtained during the interrogation of the ''Hoche'' crew, and cannot be verified. In light of Domery's subsequent behaviour in the internment camp, their testimony was accepted by the British doctors examining Domery as accurate.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=25}}|group=note}}

==Capture==
In October 1798 a [[Royal Navy]] squadron under the command of [[Sir John Borlase Warren, 1st Baronet|Sir John Borlase Warren]] captured the ''Hoche'' off the coast of Ireland,{{sfn|Nicholson|1818|loc=§ Bulimy}} and those on board, including Domery, were interned in a prison camp near Liverpool.{{sfn|Dickens|1852|p=547}}{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=302}} The British guards were shocked by Domery's appetite, and agreed to place him on double rations.{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=303}} These were insufficient, and his rations were increased until eventually he was granted the rations of ten men each day.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=27}} Rations for prisoners of war in this period were paid for by the country in whose army the prisoners had served. The standard daily ration for a French prisoner of war was {{convert|26|oz}} of bread, half a pound (230&amp;nbsp;g) of vegetables and {{convert|2|oz}} of butter or {{convert|6|oz}} of cheese.&lt;ref name=&quot;Register&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=Natural History|journal=The Annual Register|publisher=J. Dodsley|location=London|year=1801|volume=42|issue=The Annual Register for the year 1800|page=365}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Domery remained hungry, and was recorded as having eaten the prison cat and at least 20 rats which had strayed into his cell.{{sfn|Dickens|1852|p=547}} Domery also ate the medicines of those prisoners in the camp's infirmary who refused to take them, suffering no apparent adverse effects as a result.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=27}} It was also recorded that he would regularly eat the prison's candles, and that if his ration of beer was exhausted, he would resort to drinking water to wash down his food.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=27}} (To reduce the risk of water-borne disease, troops were issued rations of mildly alcoholic beverages such as [[small beer]] and diluted rum, and drinks such as tea and coffee which involved boiling water before drinking.{{sfn|Neiberg|2006|p=64}})

==Experimental subject==
{{Quote box|width=25em|salign=right|quote=The eagerness with which he attacks his beef when his stomach is not gorged, resembles the voracity of a hungry wolf, tearing off and swallowing it with canine greediness. When his throat is dry from continued exercise, he lubricates it by stripping the grease off the candles between his teeth, which he generally finishes at three mouthfuls, and wrapping the wick like a ball, string and all, sends it after at a swallow. He can, when no choice is left, make shift to dine on immense quantities of raw potatoes or turnips; but, from choice, would never desire to taste bread or vegetables.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=29}}|source=Dr J. Johnston}}
The prison commander brought his unusual captive to the attention of [[Sick and Hurt Commissioners|The Commissioners for taking Care of Sick and Wounded Seamen and for the Care and Treatment of Prisoners of War]], the body then responsible for all medical services in the Royal Navy and for overseeing the welfare of [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]]. {{nowrap|Dr J. Johnston}}, a member of the Commission, and Dr Cochrane, [[Fellow]] of the [[Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh]], performed an experiment to test Domery's eating capacity and tolerance for unusual foods.{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=303}}{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=28}} At 4:00&amp;nbsp;am, Domery was awakened and fed 4&amp;nbsp;lbs (1.8&amp;nbsp;kg) of raw cow's [[udder]], which was eaten without hesitation.{{sfn|Bondeson|2004|p=273}} At 9:30&amp;nbsp;am he was given a meal of 5&amp;nbsp;lbs (2.3&amp;nbsp;kg) of raw beef, twelve large [[tallow]] candles totalling one&amp;nbsp;pound (453&amp;nbsp;g), and a bottle of [[porter (beer)|porter]], all of which were consumed.{{sfn|Dickens|1852|p=547}}{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=28}} At 1:00&amp;nbsp;pm Domery was given another meal of a further 5&amp;nbsp;lbs of beef, a pound (453&amp;nbsp;g) of candles, and three large bottles of porter, all of which were also eaten and drunk.{{sfn|Bondeson|2004|p=273}} During the course of the experiment he did not [[defecation|defecate]], [[urination|urinate]] or [[vomiting|vomit]] at any point, his pulse remained regular and his skin did not change temperature.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=28}} Upon Domery's return to his quarters at 6:15&amp;nbsp;pm following the conclusion of the experiment, he was recorded as being of &quot;particularly good cheer&quot;, and danced, smoked his pipe and drank a further bottle of porter.{{sfn|Wilson|1807|p=28}}

The cause of Domery's appetite is not known. While there are other documented cases of similar behaviour from this period none of the subjects other than Domery's contemporary [[Tarrare]] were autopsied, and there have been no modern documented cases of [[polyphagia]] (excessive appetite) as extreme as Domery.{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=312}} [[Hyperthyroidism]] can induce an extreme appetite and rapid weight loss, while Bondeson&amp;nbsp;(2006) speculates that Domery possibly suffered from a damaged [[amygdala]] or [[ventromedial nucleus]];{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=313}} it is known that injuries to the amygdala or ventromedial nucleus in animals can induce polyphagia.{{sfn|Bondeson|2006|p=313}}

==Later life and legacy==
It is not recorded what became of Domery, or of the other ''Hoche'' captives, following their internment, and it is not known if he returned to France or Poland or remained in Liverpool. The case of Charles Domery briefly returned to public notice in 1852 when it came to the attention of [[Charles Dickens]], who wrote of Domery that &quot;Now, it is my opinion, that a man like this, dining in public on the stage of [[Drury Lane]], would draw much better than a mere [[tragedian]], who chews unsubstantial words instead of wholesome beef&quot;.{{sfn|Dickens|1852|p=547}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=note|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=27em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Bondeson|first=Jan|title=The Two-Headed Boy|year=2004|publisher=Cornell University Press|location=Ithaca, NY|isbn=0-8014-8958-X|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Bondeson|first=Jan|title=Freaks: The Pig-Faced Lady of Manchester Square &amp; Other Medical Marvels|year=2006|publisher=Tempus Publishing|location=Stroud|isbn=0-7524-3662-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Dickens|first=Charles|authorlink=Charles Dickens|date=21 August 1852|title=A Great Idea|journal=Household Words|location=London|volume=5|issue=126|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Johnston|first=J.|date=March 1800|title=Account of a Man who lives upon large Quantities of raw Flesh|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=An-we0KnG78C&amp;pg=PA209|journal=Medical and Physical Journal|location=London|volume=3|issue=13|pages=209–14|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Neiberg|first=Michael|title=The Nineteenth Century|series=''Soldiers' Lives Through History''|volume=4|year=2006|publisher=Greenwood Publishing|location=Westport, CT|isbn=0-313-33269-X|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Nicholson|first=William|title=''The British Encyclopedia, or, Dictionary of arts and sciences''|edition=2|volume=3|year=1818|publisher=Mitchell, Ames and White|location=Philadelphia|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Wilson|first=G. H.|title=''The Eccentric Mirror''|volume=2|issue=16|year=1807|publisher=James Cundee|location=London|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Zupko|first=Ronald Edward|authorlink=Ronald Edward Zupko|title=Revolution in Measurement: Western European weights and measures since the age of science|year=1990|publisher=American Philosophical Society|location=Philadelphia|isbn=0-87169-186-8|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

{{featured article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Domery, Charles}}
[[Category:1770s births]]
[[Category:French military personnel of the French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:Napoleonic Wars prisoners of war held by the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Polish cannibals]]
[[Category:Polish prisoners of war]]
[[Category:Polish soldiers]]
[[Category:Polyphagia]]
[[Category:Prussian Army personnel]]
[[Category:Year of death unknown]]
[[Category:Place of death unknown]]</text>
      <sha1>b8uakbix43smmdn6m0yjiuhe4t0z94x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
