<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Fortress of Mimoyecques</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30321125</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729569076</id>
      <parentid>724097889</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-13T03:15:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender235</username>
        <id>88026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up; http-&gt;https (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48179">{{Infobox military structure
| name              = Fortress of Mimoyecques &lt;br /&gt; ''Wiese'' &lt;br /&gt;''Bauvorhaben 711'' &lt;br /&gt; ''Marquise-Mimoyecques''
| partof            = 
| location          = Mimoyecques, near [[Landrethun-le-Nord]] ([[France]])
| map_type          = France
| pushpin_label     = Fortress of Mimoyecques
| latitude          = 50.854
| longitude         = 1.759
| coordinates_type = landmark
| coordinates_region = FR-O
| coordinates_display = inline,title
| image             = [[File:Mimoyecques eastern site reconstruction.jpg|alt=Artist's impression of the Mimoyecques installation showing a railway tunnel, vertical and horizontal shafts, and the angled shafts in which the guns were to be installed|300px]]
| caption           = Reconstructed view of the installation as originally planned
| type              = [[Bunker]]
| code              = 
| built             = September 1943&amp;nbsp;– July 1944
| builder           = [[Organisation Todt]]
| materials         = 150,000 cubic metres [[concrete]]
| height            = 
| used              = Never completed, captured 1944
| demolished        = 
| condition         = 
| ownership         = {{lang|fr|Conservatoire d'espaces naturels du Nord et du Pas-de-Calais}}
| open_to_public    = Yes
| controlledby      = 
| garrison          = ''Abteilung 705'' ({{lang-en|firing detachment}} 705) &lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Zaloga|Johnson|Taylor|2008|p=17}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
| current_commander = 
| commanders        = 
| occupants         = 
| battles           = [[Operation Crossbow]]
| events            = Critically damaged 6 July 1944;&lt;br /&gt;Captured 5 September 1944;&lt;br /&gt;Opened as museum 1984, reopened 1 July 2010
| website           = {{url|www.mimoyecques.com}}
}}

The '''Fortress of Mimoyecques''' is the modern name for a [[Second World War]] underground military complex built by the forces of [[Nazi Germany]] between 1943 and 1944. It was intended to house a [[Artillery battery|battery]] of [[V-3 cannon]]s aimed at London, {{convert|165|km|mi}} away. Originally codenamed '''''Wiese''''' (&quot;Meadow&quot;) or '''''Bauvorhaben 711''''' (&quot;Construction Project 711&quot;),&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga16&quot; /&gt; it is located in the [[Communes of France|commune]] of [[Landrethun-le-Nord]] in the [[Pas-de-Calais]] region of northern [[France]], near the hamlet of [[Mimoyecques]] about {{convert|20|km|mi}} from [[Boulogne-sur-Mer]]. It was constructed by a mostly German workforce recruited from major engineering and mining concerns, augmented by prisoner-of-war slave labour.

The complex consists of a network of tunnels dug under a chalk hill, linked to five inclined shafts in which 25 V-3 guns would have been installed, all targeted on [[London]]. The guns would have been able to fire ten dart-like explosive projectiles a minute&amp;nbsp;– 600 rounds every hour&amp;nbsp;– into the British capital, which [[Winston Churchill]] later commented would have constituted &quot;the most devastating attack of all&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Churchill&quot; /&gt; The Allies knew nothing about the V-3 but identified the site as a possible launching base for [[V-2]] ballistic missiles, based on reconnaissance photographs and fragmentary intelligence from French sources.

Mimoyecques was targeted for intensive bombardment by the Allied air forces from late 1943 onwards. Construction work was seriously disrupted, forcing the Germans to abandon work on part of the complex. The rest was partly destroyed on 6 July 1944 by [[No. 617 Squadron RAF]], which used ground-penetrating {{convert|5400|kg|lb|adj=on}} &quot;[[Tallboy (bomb)|Tallboy]]&quot; [[earthquake bomb]]s to collapse tunnels and shafts, entombing hundreds of slave workers underground.

The Germans halted construction work at Mimoyecques as the Allies advanced up the coast following the [[Normandy landings]]. It fell to the [[3rd Canadian Infantry Division|Canadian 3rd Infantry Division]] on 5 September 1944 without resistance, a few days after the Germans withdrew from the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga14&quot; /&gt;

The complex was partly demolished just after the war on Churchill's direct orders (and to the great annoyance of the French, who were not consulted), as it was still seen as a threat to the United Kingdom. It was later reopened by private owners, first in 1969 to serve as a [[mushroom farm]] and subsequently as a museum in 1984. A nature conservation organisation acquired the Fortress of Mimoyecques in 2010 and [[La Coupole]], a former V-2 rocket base turned museum near [[Saint-Omer]], took over its management. It continues to be open to the public as a vast underground museum complex.&lt;ref name=&quot;VDN-22042010&quot; /&gt;

==Background==
{{Details|V-3 cannon}}
[[File:Mimoyecques-Eperlecques-Wizernes map.png|left|thumb|Map of the Pas-de-Calais and south-eastern England showing the location of Mimoyecques and other major V-weapons sites]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1981-147-30A, Hochdruckpumpe V-3.jpg|right|thumb|upright|alt=A single Hochdruckpumpe barrel mounted on the side of a steep wooded hill, with flights of steps on each side of it and machinery in the foreground|The prototype ''Hochdruckpumpe'' gun in 1942 at {{lang|de|Laatziger Ablage}} ({{lang|de|Misdroy}}), today [[Zalesie, Kamień County|Zalesie]] ([[Międzyzdroje]]), Poland. Site location: {{coord|53|53|53.91|N|14|26|18.92|E|type:landmark_scale:1000_region:PL|display=inline|name=Central V-3 installation (Laatziger Ablage, Misdroy)}}.]]

In May 1943 [[Albert Speer]], the Reich's Minister of Armaments and War Production, informed [[Adolf Hitler]] of work that was being carried out to produce a [[supergun]] capable of firing hundreds of shells an hour over long distances. The newly designed gun, codenamed the ''Hochdruckpumpe'' (&quot;High Pressure Pump&quot;, HDP for short) and later designated as the [[V-3 cannon|V-3]], was one of the [[V-weapons]]&amp;nbsp;– ''Vergeltungswaffen'' (&quot;retaliation weapons&quot;)&amp;nbsp;– developed by Nazi Germany in the later stages of the war to attack Allied targets. Long-range guns were not a new development, but the high-pressure detonations used to fire shells from previous such weapons, including the [[Paris gun]], rapidly wore out their barrels.

In 1942, [[August Coenders]], inspired by previous designs of multi-chamber guns, suggested that the gradual acceleration of the shell by a series of small charges spread over the length of the barrel might be the solution to the problem of designing very long-range guns. Coenders proposed the use of electrically activated charges to eliminate the problem of the premature ignition of the subsidiary charges experienced by previous multi-chamber guns. The HDP would have a smooth barrel over {{convert|100|m|ft}} long, along which a {{convert|97|kg|lb|adj=on}} finned shell (known as the ''Sprenggranate 4481'') would be accelerated by numerous small low-pressure detonations from charges in branches off the barrel, each fired electrically in sequence.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|After the Battle|1974}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Each barrel would be {{convert|15|cm|abbr=on}} in diameter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;

The gun was still in its prototype stages, but Hitler was an enthusiastic supporter of the idea and ordered that maximum support be given to its development and deployment. In August 1943 he approved the construction of a battery of HDP guns in France to supplement the planned [[V-1 (flying bomb)|V-1]] and [[V-2]] missile campaigns against London and the south-east of England.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Johnson|Taylor|2008|p=6}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Speer noted afterwards:

{{quote|On my suggestion, the Führer has decided that the risk must be stood to award contracts at once for the &quot;high-pressure pump,&quot; without waiting for the results of firing trials. Maximum support is to be accorded to the experimental ranges at [[Hillersleben]] and [[Misdroy]], and especially to the completion of the actual battery.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Boelcke|1969|p=290}}.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

To reach England, the weapon needed barrels {{convert|127|m|ft}} long, so it could not be moved; it would have to be deployed from a fixed site.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga13&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Johnson|Taylor|2008|p=13}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A study carried out in early 1943 had shown that the optimal location for its deployment would be within a hill with a rock core into which inclined [[Drift mining|drifts]] could be tunneled to support the barrels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga16&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Johnson|Taylor|2008|p=16}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The site was identified by a fortification expert, Major Bock of the ''Festungs-Pionier-Stab 27''&lt;ref group=notes&gt;Literal translation &quot;Fortress Pioneer Staff&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fifteenth Army]] [[LVII Corps]] based in the [[Dieppe, Seine-Maritime|Dieppe]] area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga14&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Johnson|Taylor|2008|p=14}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A limestone hill near the hamlet of [[Mimoyecques]], {{convert|158|m|ft}} high and {{convert|165|km|mi}} from London, was chosen to house the gun. It had been selected with care; the hill in which the facility was built is primarily chalk with very little topsoil cover, and the chalk layer extends several hundred metres below the surface, providing a deep but easily tunnelled rock layer. The chalk is easy to excavate and strong enough to dig tunnels without using timber supports. Although the site's road links were poor, it was only a few kilometres west of the main railway line between [[Calais]] and [[Boulogne-sur-Mer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders5&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|loc=''Technical details&amp;nbsp;– Wizernes''; Vol III, p. 5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The area was already heavily militarised; as well as the fortifications of the [[Atlantic Wall]] on the cliffs of [[Cap Gris Nez]] to the northwest, there was a firing base for at least one&lt;ref name=&quot;chalm&quot;/&gt; conventional [[Krupp K5]] [[railway gun]] about {{convert|5|km|mi}} to the south in the nearby quarries of [[Rinxent|Hidrequent-Rinxent]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Powys-Lybbe 1983 210&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Powys-Lybbe|1983|p=210}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design and construction==
Construction began in September 1943 with the building of railway lines to support the work, and excavation of the gun shafts began in October. The initial layout comprised two parallel complexes approximately {{convert|1000|m|ft}} apart, each with five drifts which were to hold a stacked cluster of five HDP gun tubes, for a total of 25 guns. The [[smoothbore]] design of the HDP would enable a much higher rate of fire than was possible with conventional guns. The entire battery would be able to fire up to 10 shots a minute, capable in theory of hitting London with 600 projectiles every hour. Both facilities were to be served by an underground railway tunnel of standard gauge,&lt;ref group=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;North entrance of railway tunnel: {{coord|50|51|32.15|N|1|45|49.75|E|type:landmark_scale:1000_region:FR|display=inline|name=North entrance of the railway tunnel of the Fortress of Mimoyecques.}}. South exit: {{coord|50|51|9.66|N|1|45|32.62|E|type:landmark_scale:1000_region:FR|display=inline|name=South exit of the railway tunnel of the Fortress of Mimoyecques.}}&lt;/ref&gt; connected to the Calais-Boulogne main line,&lt;ref group=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;The branch line to Mimoyecques connected with the main line here: {{coord|50|51|33.63|N|1|45|52.01|E|type:landmark_scale:1000_region:FR|display=inline|name=Connection of railway of the Fortress of Mimoyecques with the main line.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and underground ammunition storage galleries which were tunneled at a depth of about {{convert|33|m|ft|abbr=on}}. The western site was abandoned at an early stage after being disrupted by Allied bombing, and only the eastern complex was built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga16&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bates|1994|p=158}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The drifts were angled at 50 degrees, reaching a depth of {{convert|105|m|ft|abbr=on}}. Owing to technical problems with the gun prototype, the scope of the project was reduced;&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga16&quot; /&gt; drifts I and II were abandoned at an early date and only III, IV and V were taken forward. They came to the surface at a concrete slab or ''Platte'' {{convert|30|m|ft|abbr=on}} wide and {{convert|5.5|m|ft|abbr=on}} thick, in which there were narrow openings to allow the projectiles to pass through. The openings in the slab were protected by large steel plates, and the railway tunnel entrances were further protected by armoured steel doors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders7&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=7}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Each drift was oriented on a bearing of 299°, to the nearest degree – a direct line on [[Westminster Bridge]]. Although the elevation and direction of the guns could not be changed, it would have been possible to alter the range by varying the amount of propellant used in each shot. This would have brought much of London within range.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders9&quot; /&gt;

The railway tunnel ran in a straight line for a distance of about {{convert|630|m|ft|abbr=on}} . Along its west side was an unloading platform which gave access to ten cross galleries (numbered 3–13 by the Germans), driven at right angles to the main tunnel at intervals of {{convert|24|m|ft}}. Each gallery was fitted with a {{RailGauge|600mm|lk=on}} gauge railway track. On the east side of the tunnel were chambers intended to be used as store rooms, offices and quarters for the garrison. Trains would have entered the facility and unloaded shells and propellant for the guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders6&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Gallery
| title = Maps and plans of the Mimoyecques site
| lines = 2
| width = 200
| align = center
|File:Mimoyecques eastern site cross section.png|alt1=Diagram of the eastern site showing a series of galleries, shafts and chambers in the shape of an inverted A|Cross-section of the Mimoyecques eastern site
|File:Mimoyecques eastern site plan.png|alt2=Top-down diagram of the eastern site showing the railway tunnel proceeding laterally and a series of galleries branching off the railway tunnel|Plan of the Mimoyecques eastern site
|File:Mimoyecques local map.jpg|alt3=Annotated aerial photograph of the Mimoyecques complex showing railway lines overlaid on fields, with roads also marked |Photo map of the area around the two Mimoyecques sites
}}

Galleries 6–10, the central group, gave access to the guns, while galleries 3–5 and 11–13 were intended for use as access tunnels and perhaps also storage areas. They were all connected by Gallery No. 2, which ran parallel to the main railway tunnel at a distance of {{convert|100|m|ft}}. Galleries 6–10 were additionally connected by a second passageway, designated Gallery No. 1, running parallel to the main tunnel at a distance of {{convert|24.5|m|ft}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders6&quot; /&gt; Further workings existed at depths of {{convert|62|m|ft|abbr=on}}, {{convert|47|m|ft|abbr=on}} and {{convert|30|m|ft|abbr=on}}, each serving different purposes associated with the drifts and the guns. The 62 m workings were constructed to facilitate the removal of spoil from the drifts, while those at 47 m were connected with the handling of exhaust gases from the guns and those at 30 m gave access to the breeches of the guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders7&quot; /&gt; The lower levels of the workings were accessed via lift shafts, and mining cages were used during construction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders9&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=9}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The construction work was carried out by over 5,000 workers, mostly German engineers drafted in from several companies including [[Mannesmann]], [[MAN SE|Gute Hoffnungshütte]], [[Krupp]] and the [[Vereinigte Stahlwerke]], supplemented by 430 miners recruited from the [[Ruhr]] and Soviet prisoners of war who were used as slave labourers.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hölsken|1994|p=178}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The intensive Allied bombing campaign caused delays, but construction work continued nonetheless at a high pace underground. The original plans had envisaged having the first battery of five guns ready by March 1944 and the full complement of 25 guns by 1 October 1944, but these target dates were not met.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga16&quot; /&gt;

==Discovery and destruction==
[[File:Overlordheavybombing.jpg|right|thumb|alt=A British bomber aircraft flies over a heavily bombed agricultural landscape with many craters and plumes of smoke visible immediately below|An RAF [[Handley Page Halifax]] flies over Mimoyecques on 6 July 1944 as exploding bombs send smoke and clouds of dust into the air.]]
[[File:Sprenggranate4481.jpg|right|thumb|upright|alt=Two soldiers in US Army uniforms hold between them a long, slim projectile that is somewhat taller than them, with a finned tail|Two US Army soldiers with a captured ''Sprenggranate 4481'' projectile, which would have been fired from the V-3 at a rate of  1 every 6 seconds.]]

In 1943 French agents reported that the Germans were planning to mount an offensive against the United Kingdom that would involve the use of secret weapons resembling giant mortars sunk in the ground and served by rail links.&lt;ref name=&quot;Henshall&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Henshall|2002|p=41}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The first signs of abnormal activity at Mimoyecques were spotted by analysts at the [[RAF Medmenham|Allied Central Interpretation Unit]] in September 1943, when aerial reconnaissance revealed that the Germans were building railway loops leading to the tunnels into the eastern and western sites. Further reconnaissance flights in October 1943 photographed large-scale activity around the tunnels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders p.5&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

An analyst named André Kenny discovered a series of shafts when he saw from a reconnaissance photograph that a haystack concealing one of them had disintegrated, perhaps through the effects of a gale, revealing the entrance, a [[windlass]] and [[pulley]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Powys-Lybbe 1983 210&quot;/&gt; The purpose of the site was unclear, but it was thought to be some kind of shelter for launching rockets or flying bombs. An [[MI6]] agent reported that &quot;a concrete chamber was to be built near one of the tunnels for the installation of a tube, 40 to 50 metres long, which he referred to as a 'rocket launching cannon{{' &quot;}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsey&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hinsley|1984|page=435}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The shafts were interpreted as &quot;air holes to allow for the expansion of the gases released by the explosion of the launching charge.&quot;

The Allies were unaware of the HDP gun and therefore of the Mimoyecques site's true purpose. Allied intelligence believed at the time that the V-2 rocket had to be launched from tubes or &quot;projectors&quot;, so it was assumed that the inclined shafts at Mimoyecques were intended to house such devices.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsey&quot; /&gt;

The lack of intelligence on Mimoyecques was frustrating for those involved in [[Operation Crossbow]], the Allied effort to counter the V-weapons. On 21 March 1944 the British [[Chiefs of Staff Committee|Chiefs of Staff]] discussed the shortage of intelligence but were told by [[Reginald Victor Jones]], one of the &quot;Crossbow Committee&quot; members, that little information was leaking out because the workforce was predominantly German. The Committee's head, [[Duncan Sandys]], pressed for greater efforts and proposed that the [[Special Operations Executive]] be tasked to kidnap a German technician who could be interrogated for information. The suggestion was approved, but was never put into effect.

In the end the Chiefs of Staff instructed General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|Eisenhower]] to begin intensive attacks on the so-called &quot;Heavy Crossbow&quot; sites, including Mimoyecques, which was still believed to be intended for use as a rocket-launching site.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsey&quot; /&gt;

The Allied air forces carried out several bombing raids on Mimoyecques between November 1943 and June 1944 but caused little damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga13&quot; /&gt; The bombing disrupted the construction project and the initial raids of 5 and 8 November 1943 caused work to be delayed for about a month. The Germans subsequently decided to abandon the western site, where work had not progressed very far, and concentrated on the eastern site.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga14&quot; /&gt; On 6 July 1944 the [[Royal Air Force]] began bombing the site with ground-penetrating [[Tallboy bomb]]s. One Tallboy hit the concrete slab on top of Drift IV, collapsing the drift. Three others penetrated the tunnels below and substantially damaged the facility, causing several of the galleries to collapse in places.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga13&quot; /&gt;

Around 300 Germans and forced labourers were buried alive by the collapses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bat78&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bateman|2009|p=78}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Adding to the Germans' difficulties, major technical problems were discovered with the HDP gun projectiles. They had been designed to exit the barrels at a speed of about {{convert|1500|m|abbr=on}} per second, but the Germans found that a design fault caused the projectiles to begin &quot;tumbling&quot; in flight at speeds above {{convert|1000|m|abbr=on}} per second, causing them to fall well short of the target. This was not discovered until over 20,000 projectiles had already been manufactured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot; /&gt;

After the devastating raid of 6 July, the Germans held a high-level meeting on the site's future at which Hitler ordered major changes to the site's development. On 12 July 1944 he signed an order instructing that only five HDP guns were to be installed in a single drift. The two others were to be reused to house a pair of Krupp K5 artillery pieces, reamed out to a smooth bore with a diameter of {{convert|310|mm|in}}, which were to use a new type of long-range rocket-propelled shell. A pair of [[Rheinbote]] missile launchers were to be installed at the tunnel entrances. These plans were soon abandoned as Allied ground forces advanced towards Mimoyecques, and on 30 July the Organisation Todt engineers were ordered to end construction work.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Henshall|2002|p=176}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allies were unaware of this and mounted further attacks on the site as part of the [[United States Army Air Forces]] experimental [[Operation Aphrodite]], involving radio-controlled [[B-24 Liberator]]s packed with explosives. Two such attacks were mounted but failed; in the second such attack, on 12 August, Lt [[Joseph P. Kennedy, Jr.]]&amp;nbsp;– the elder brother of future US President [[John F. Kennedy]]&amp;nbsp;– was killed when the drone aircraft exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bat78&quot;/&gt; By the end of the bombing campaign, over 4,100 tons of bombs had been dropped on Mimoyecques, more than on any other V-weapons site.&lt;ref name=&quot;Henshall&quot; /&gt;

The Mimoyecques site was never formally abandoned, but German forces left it at the start of September 1944 as the Allies advanced northeast from [[Normandy]] towards the Pas de Calais. It was captured on 5 September by the Canadian 3rd Infantry Division.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga16&quot; /&gt;

==Subsequent investigations and attempted demolition==
[[File:Mimoyecques concrete slab.jpg|right|thumb|alt=A rubble-strewn rectangular concrete opening with a long thin slot in the middle. More rubble can be seen at the bottom of the shaft in the bottom centre of the photograph|One of the concrete slabs through which the V-3 guns would have been fired. It was demolished in May 1945 by the Royal Engineers.]]
In September 1944, Duncan Sandys ordered the constitution of a Technical Inter-Services Mission under Colonel [[Terence Sanders|T.R.B. Sanders]]. It was given the task of investigating the V-weapons sites at Mimoyecques, [[Siracourt V-1 bunker|Siracourt]], [[Blockhaus d'Éperlecques|Watten]], and [[La Coupole|Wizernes]], collectively known to the Allies as the &quot;Heavy Crossbow&quot; sites. Sanders' report was submitted to the War Cabinet on 19 March 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sandys&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sandys|1945}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Even at this stage the true purpose of the site was unclear. Claims that it had been intended to be used for &quot;electro-magnetic projectors&quot; ([[railguns]]), firing huge shells at London,  were debunked by [[Frederick Lindemann, 1st Viscount Cherwell|Lord Cherwell]], [[Winston Churchill]]'s scientific adviser, who calculated that it would take sixty times the output of [[Battersea Power Station]] to fire a one-ton shell. Sanders' investigation brought to light the V-3 project for the first time, to the alarm of the British government. He concluded that although the site had been damaged it &quot;could be completed or adapted for offensive action against this country at some future date, and [its] destruction is a matter of importance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Moench|1999|p=93}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Sandys brought the matter to the attention of Churchill and advised: &quot;Since this installation constitutes a potential threat to London, it would be wise to ensure that it is demolished whilst our forces are still in France.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sandys&quot; /&gt; Churchill later commented that the V-3 installation at Mimoyecques &quot;might well have launched the most devastating attack of all on London.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Churchill&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Churchill|first=Winston|title=Churchill's War Time Speeches|url=http://www.churchill-society-london.org.uk/13May45.html|authorlink=Winston Churchill|accessdate=26 June 2011|chapter=Forward, Till the Whole Task is Done|date=13 May 1945|quote=...&amp;nbsp;when all the preparations being made on the coasts of France and Holland could be examined in detail, in scientific detail, that we knew how grave had been the peril, not only from rockets and flying-bombs but from multiple long range artillery which was being prepared against London. Only just in time did the Allied armies blast the viper in his nest. Otherwise the autumn of 1944, to say nothing of 1945, might well have seen London as shattered as Berlin.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The discovery of the site's true purpose produced some recriminations in London, as – unlike the V-1 and V-2 projects – the V-3 had not been uncovered by Allied intelligence  before the war's end. The British scientist and military intelligence expert Reginald Victor Jones later commented that &quot;techniques that had been used against the flying bomb and the rocket appeared to have failed against HDP [V-3], and there had to be a reason. Basically it was that with our limited effort we had to concentrate on the most urgent problem, and thus on catching weapons not so much at the research stage (although we sometimes achieved this) as in the development stage – which usually meant when trials were showing promise.&quot; He concluded at the time, in April 1945, that the intelligence failure had not made much practical difference given the fact that the Germans had failed to develop the HDP into an effective weapon: &quot;there was little warning; [but] there was little danger.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Jones|1978|p=463}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the recommendation that the site should be destroyed, the [[Royal Engineers]] stacked ten tons of British {{convert|500|lb|kg|abbr=on}} bombs and captured German plastic explosive in the tunnels at Mimoyecques and detonated them on 9 May. This failed to achieve the desired effect, and on 14 May, a further 25 tons of explosives were used to bring down the north and south entrances to the railway tunnel into the site. A subsequent investigation by the British Bombing Research Mission concluded that the entrances had been heavily blocked and that it would be a very difficult and lengthy engineering task to reinstate them.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot; /&gt; The British action was taken without informing the French beforehand and infuriated [[Charles de Gaulle]], who considered it a violation of France's national sovereignty.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dejonge|Le Maner|1999|p=378}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reopening as a museum==
After the war, the Mimoyecques site lay abandoned. Much of the equipment left by the Germans was disposed of as scrap metal. A complete set of four steel plates,&lt;ref name=&quot;chalm&quot;/&gt; weighing 60 tons, that were intended to protect the entrances to the drifts were bought by the manager of the Hidrequent-Rixent quarries to be cut up for use in rock-crushing machinery.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot; /&gt; Rediscovered by local historians in the 1990s,&lt;ref name=&quot;chalm&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Richely|Neve|1991}}.&lt;/ref&gt; they remained at the quarries until 2010, when the surviving plates were returned to Mimoyecques, where they are now on display.&lt;ref name=&quot;VDN-22062010&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Le retour de pièces historiques à la forteresse de Mimoyecques|url=http://www.lavoixdunord.fr/Region/actualite/Secteur_Region/2010/07/15/article_le-retour-de-pieces-historiques-a-la-for.shtml|work=La Voix du Nord|language=French|date=15 July 2010|accessdate=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Gallery
| title = The Mimoyecques site today
| lines = 3
| width = 220
| align = center
|File:Mimoyecques6.jpg|alt1=A partly overgrown concrete entrance leads into a dark tunnel under a grass—covered hillside, with a gravel path in the foreground|Entrance to the railway tunnel at the Mimoyecques eastern site
|File:Mimoyecques2.jpg|alt2=A long view down a lit gravel—paved concrete tunnel which has a series of openings on the left-hand side|Inside the tunnel, which is now open to visitors
|File:London Gun V-3 replica at Mimoyeques.jpg|alt3=A replica Hochdruckpumpe barrel, which looks like a large drainpipe with a series of short angled pipes branching off it at regular intervals|Replica of one of the ''Hochdruckpumpe'' (V-3) gun barrels in Drift IV at Mimoyecques.
}}

Despite the closure of the railway tunnel entrances it was still possible for many years to get into the complex by climbing down one of the inclined drifts.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot; /&gt; In 1969, Marie-Madeleine Vasseur, a farmer from Landrethun, had the southern entrance excavated so that the tunnels could be used as a mushroom farm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=P.|first=M.|title=Forteresse V3 de Mimoyecques&amp;nbsp;– La base secrète d'Hitler change de propriétaire|journal=La Semaine dans le Boulonnais|date=3 December 2008|url=http://www.lasemainedansleboulonnais.fr/Dossiers/articles_globaux/2008/12/03/article_la_base_secrete_d_hitler_change_de_propr.shtml|accessdate=25 June 2011|trans_title=Fortress V3 of Mimoyecques&amp;nbsp;– Hitler's secret base changes hands|language=French|quote= Forty years after the destruction of the building, Marie-Madeleine Vasseur opened the site to the public as a museum and a mausoleum. By 1969, this farmer from Landrethun proposed to reopen the tunnel for growing mushrooms.&amp;nbsp;... Twenty-five years later, Marie-Madeilene Vasseur take a well-deserved retirement. (transl.)}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{convert|30|m|ft}} of the southern tunnel had to be removed to clear the blockage; the entrance now visible is not the original one built by the Germans.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB114&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Pallud|2001|p=11}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The southern entrance had been bricked up again by the 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot; /&gt; Moved to discover this forgotten construction, Vasseur, helped by family and friends, cleared the tunnels and installed an electricity supply. The ''[[société à responsabilité limitée]] &quot;La Forteresse de Mimoyecques&quot;'' was constituted in 1984 to operate the site as a museum under the name of ''Forteresse de Mimoyecques&amp;nbsp;— Un Mémorial International''.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Middlebrook|1991|p=33}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The museum closed at the end of the 2008 season when the owner retired. Subsequently, the [[nonprofit organisation]] ''Conservatoire d'espaces naturels du Nord et Pas-de-Calais''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Conservatoire d'espaces naturels du Nord et du Pas-de-Calais|accessdate=24 June 2011|url=http://www.conservatoiresitesnpc.org/|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Conservatory of natural sites of the Nord and Pas-de-Calais) purchased it at a cost of [[euro|€]]330,000, with funding provided by the Nord-Pas-de-Calais regional council, the European Union and a private benefactor.&lt;ref name=&quot;VDN-22042010&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=La forteresse de Mimoyecques devrait rouvrir le 1er juillet|url=http://www.lavoixdunord.fr/Locales/Calais/actualite/Secteur_Calais/2010/04/10/article_la-forteresse-de-mimoyecques-devrait-rou.shtml|work=La Voix du Nord|date=10 April 2010|accessdate=22 June 2011|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Conservatory's interest was due to the presence on the site of a large bat colony&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Évolution des populations de chauves-souris en hibernation entre 2000 et 2011&amp;nbsp;– Forteresse de Mimoyecques|accessdate=25 June 2011|author=Conservatoire d'espaces naturels du Nord et du Pas-de-Calais|year=2011|url=http://www.cen-npdc.org/fichiers/AFF_chiros2012%281%29.pdf|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt; that included rare species, such as the [[Greater Horseshoe Bat]], [[Geoffroy's Bat]] and the [[Pond Bat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Un site d'hibernation de chauves-souris|url=http://www.lavoixdunord.fr/Locales/Calais/actualite/Secteur_Calais/2010/04/10/article_un-site-d-hibernation-de-chauves-souris.shtml|work=La Voix du Nord|language=French|date=10 April 2010|accessdate=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Forteresse de Mimoyecques&amp;nbsp;– Quand histoire et nature ne font qu'un|accessdate=25 June 2011|author=Conservatoire d'espaces naturels du Nord et du Pas-de-Calais|language=French|year=2010|url=http://www.conservatoiresitesnpc.org/sites-proteges/site-protege.html?protar_id=9f4rqbY}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Communes of France|intercommunality]] of the [[Communauté de communes de la Terre des Deux Caps|Terre des Deux Caps]] and the authorities in nearly Landrethun set up a partnership to operate the site under the management of the existing museum of La Coupole near Saint-Omer. The director of the latter, historian Yves le Maner, designed the contents of a new museum that was constructed at a cost of €360,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;VDN-22042010&quot; /&gt;

The site reopened to the public on 1 July 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;VDN-22062010&quot; /&gt; As well as presenting a history of the V-weapons and of the site, the museum enables visitors to see some of the tunnels and a mock-up of the HDP gun. The tunnels also house memorials to Joseph Kennedy, the other bomber crew members killed during raids on the site, and the forced labourers who lost their lives during construction.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB114&quot; /&gt; In 2011, the museum had about 11,000 visitors, of whom 53% were French, 18% Belgian and 16% British.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Rapport d'activités 2011|year=2012|author=Conservatoire d'espaces naturels du Nord et du Pas-de-Calais|page=39|language=French|chapter=Les chiffres de la saison touristique à Mimoyecques|url=http://www.cen-npdc.org/pdf/rapportactivites2011_bd.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Air raids on the Mimoyecques site==
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+valign=top| Attacks on Mimoyecques site
!width=11% | Date
!| Notes
|- valign=top
|-
| {{nowrap|5 November 1943}}
| [[File:Patch9thusaaf.png|12px]] More than 150 [[B-26 Marauder]]s of the USAAF [[Ninth Air Force#Ninth Air Force units during World War II|Ninth Air Force]] bombed &quot;construction works&quot; at Mimoyecques, but poor visibility and bad weather caused one group to miss the primary target and numerous other aircraft to abort their attacks.&lt;ref name=Carter&gt;{{harvnb|Carter|Mueller|1991}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hammel&gt;{{harvnb|Hammel|2009|pp=204–5, 265, 268, 283, 287–8, 290, 299, 301, 353}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 8 November 1943
| [[File:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] [[No. 2 Group RAF|No. 2 Group]] of the [[RAF Second Tactical Air Force]] attacked Mimoyecques with three waves each of 24 [[Douglas Boston]] medium bombers. The first two waves (24 aircraft of [[No. 88 Squadron RAF|Nos. 88]] and [[No. 342 Squadron RAF|342 Squadrons]] and 24 of [[No. 98 Squadron RAF|Nos. 98]] and [[No. 180 Squadron RAF|180 Squadrons]]) reported bursts on the railway, in the target area, and on the tunnel entrance. The third wave (19 aircraft of [[No. 226 Squadron RAF|Nos. 226]] and [[No. 305 Squadron RAF|305 Squadrons]]) reported bomb bursts near the north aiming point. Six [[B-25 Mitchell|North American Mitchell]]s of [[No. 320 Squadron RAF|No. 320 Squadron]] also attacked. In the course of the raid one Mitchell was shot down and 12 bombers were damaged by flak.&lt;ref&gt;11 Group ORB Appendix, 8 Nov 1944, TNA AIR 25/207.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 19 March 1944
| [[File:Patch9thusaaf.png|12px]] 173 [[B-17 Flying Fortress]]es of the Ninth Air Force 1st and 3d Bombardment Divisions, escorted by [[P-47 Thunderbolt]]s, bombed V-weapons sites including Mimoyecques.&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 26 March 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 500 heavy bombers of the USAAF [[Eighth Air Force]] attacked a total of 16 V-weapon sites in northern France, including Mimoyecques, dropping 1,271 tons of bombs. Allied losses were four B-17s and one [[B-24 Liberator]]; a further 236 bombers were damaged by enemy fire.&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 10 April 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] Bombers of the USAAF Eighth Air Force attacked Mimoyecques.&lt;ref name=Carter/&gt;
|-
| 20 April 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 375 B-17s and 174 B-24s of the Eighth Air Force attacked V-weapon sites in the Pas-de-Calais and [[Cherbourg]] areas, for the loss of nine bombers.&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 27 April 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 307 B-17s of the Eighth Air Force 1st and 3d Bombardment Division and 169 2d Bombardment Division B-24s attacked V-weapons sites in the Pas-de-Calais and Cherbourg areas, for the loss of four bombers.&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 28 April 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 47 B-24s of the Eighth Air Force, escorted by 50 P-47s of the 361st Fighter Group, bombed Mimoyecques. One B-24 was lost.&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 1 May 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] Over 500 Eighth Air Force heavy bombers carried out an early morning raid on V-weapon sites in northern France. Owing to bad weather only 129 heavy bombers were able to attack the V-weapon sites at Mimoyecques, Watten, and [[V-1 flying bomb (facilities)|Bois de l'Enfer]], and three airfields.&lt;ref name=Carter/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 15 May 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 38 of 58 B-17s of the 1st Bombardment Division bombed Mimoyecques.&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 21 May 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 25 B-17s of the Eighth Air Force&lt;ref name=Carter/&gt; bombed Mimoyecques; 13 aircraft were damaged by enemy fire.&lt;ref name=Hammel/&gt;
|-
| 22 June 1944
| [[File:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 234 aircraft&amp;nbsp;– 119 [[Avro Lancaster]]s, 102 [[Handley Page Halifax]]es and 13 [[de Havilland Mosquito]]s&amp;nbsp;– of [[No. 1 Group RAF|Nos. 1]], [[No. 4 Group RAF|4]], [[No. 5 Group RAF|5]] and  [[No. 8 Group RAF|8 Groups]] attacked a number of V-weapon sites and stores, bombing the sites at Mimoyecques and Siracourt with the aid of [[Pathfinder (RAF)|Pathfinder]] marking.&lt;ref name=&quot;JuneDiary&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 27 June 1944
| [[File:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 104 Halifaxes from No. 4 Group with 5 Mosquitos and 2 Lancasters of the Pathfinders attacked Mimoyecques in good weather without sustaining any losses.&lt;ref name=&quot;JuneDiary&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=|first= |work=Royal Air Force Bomber Command 60th Anniversary|accessdate=24 May 2007|publisher=UK Crown |url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/bombercommand/jun44.html |title=Campaign diary June 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 6 July 1944
| [[File:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] [[No. 617 Squadron RAF]] attacked with [[Tallboy (bomb)|Tallboys]]. The target was marked by the squadron's commanding officer, [[Leonard Cheshire]], from his [[North American P-51 Mustang#Non-US service|Mustang III]] fighter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bat&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bateman|2009|pp=77–78}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The bombers hit one of the shafts with a Tallboy that bored into the earth and exploded underground, leaving an enormous crater.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hogg|1999|p=48}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This was Cheshire's last operation leading No. 617 Squadron, completing his 100th mission.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bat78&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 4 August 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] The first [[Operation Aphrodite]] mission was flown using four radio-controlled B-17s as flying bombs. None of the targets, including Mimoyecques, were hit.&lt;ref name=Hammel /&gt;
|-
| 12 August 1944
|  An [[Operation Aphrodite|Operation Anvil]] drone targeted on Mimoyecques detonated prematurely over the Blyth Estuary, killing the US Navy crew, Lieutenants [[Joseph P. Kennedy, Jr.]] and Wilford J. Willy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bat78&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 27 August 1944
| [[File:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 176 Halifaxes, 40 Lancasters and 10 Mosquitos attacked Mimoyecques without loss.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=|first= |work=Royal Air Force Bomber Command 60th Anniversary|accessdate=24 May 2007|publisher=UK Crown |url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/bombercommand/aug44.html |title=Campaign diary August 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|}

==See also==
* [[Blockhaus d'Éperlecques]]
* [[La Coupole]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=notes|38em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin|38em}}
* {{cite book|first=Alex |last=Bateman|title=No 617 'Dambusters' Sqn|year=2009|publisher=Osprey|location=Oxford|isbn=1-84603-429-9|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Bates|first=Herbert Ernest |title=Flying Bombs over England|year=1994|publisher=Froglets|location=Westerham|isbn=978-1-872337-04-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Boelcke|first=Willi|title=Deutschlands Rüstung im Zweiten Weltkrieg: Hitlers Konferenzen mit Albert Speer 1942–1945|year=1969|language=German|location=Frankfurt am Main|publisher=Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft Athenaion|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Carter |first=Kit C. |last2=Mueller|first2=Robert |title=US Army Air Forces in World War II: Combat Chronology 1941–1945 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=RjzLqxg6KlAC&amp;pg=PT530 |publisher=Center for Air Force History |year=1991 |quote=[citing:]Long-Range Rockets, in Plans file 8090-71; 9th AF Hist. Sec., CROSSBOW Operations Against Ski Sites, 5 December 1943-18 March 1944 (hereinafter cited as 9th AF CB Opns.); AAF Operations Against CROSSBOW and Ski Site Installations, in AC/AS, Plans file 8090-69.|isbn=978-1-4289-1543-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=Le Nord-Pas-de-Calais dans la main allemande|last1=Dejonge|first1=Étienne|last2=Le Maner|first2=Yves|publisher=Le Voix du Nord|location=Lille|language=French|year=1999|isbn=978-2-84393-015-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Hammel|first=Eric|title=Air War Europa: Chronology|publisher=Pacifica Military History|location=Pacifica, CA|year=2009|isbn=978-0-935553-65-9|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Henshall|first=Philip|title=Hitler's V-Weapon Sites|publisher=Strutton Publishing|location=Stroud|year=2002|isbn=0-7509-2607-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Hinsley|first=Francis H.|title=British Intelligence in the Second World War: Its Influence on Strategy and Operations|year=1984|publisher=H.M.S.O. |location=London|isbn=978-0-11-630935-8|page=380|volume=3|authorlink=Francis Harry Hinsley|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=German Secret Weapons of the Second World War|last=Hogg|first=Ian V.|location=London|publisher=Greenhill Books|year=1999|isbn=978-1-85367-325-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=V-Missiles of the Third Reich, the V-1 and V-2|last=Hölsken|first=Dieter|publisher=Monogram Aviation Publications|year=1994|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=The Wizard War: British Scientific Intelligence, 1939–1945|last=Jones|first=Raymond Victor|publisher=Coward, McCann &amp; Geoghegan|location=New York|year=1978|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=The Somme Battlefields: a comprehensive guide from Crécy to the two world wars|last=Middlebrook|first=Mary|publisher=Viking|location=London|year=1991|isbn=978-0-670-83083-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Moench|first=John O.|title=Marauder Men: an account of the Martin B-26 Marauder|location=Longwood, FL|publisher=Malia Enterprises|year=1999|isbn=978-1-877597-06-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Pallud|first=Jean-Paul|title=The Secret Weapons: V3 and V4|journal=[[After the Battle]]|year=2001|volume=114|pages=2–29|issn=0306-154X|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=|first=|title=The V-Weapons|journal=[[After the Battle]]|year=1974|volume=6|pages=23–24|issn=0306-154X|ref={{harvid|After the Battle|1974}}}}
* {{cite book|last=Powys-Lybbe |first=Ursula|title=The eye of intelligence|year=1983|publisher=Kimber|location=London|isbn=978-0-7183-0468-3|edition=1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Richely|first1=Paul|first2=André |last2=Neve|title=Où sont les plaques cuirassées de Mimoyecques?|trans_title=Where are the armor plates of Mimoyecques?|journal=Bulletin d'information du CLHAM|date=September 1991|volume=IV|issue=11|url=http://www.clham.org/050470.htm#Mimoyecques|accessdate=21 June 2011|publisher=Centre Liégeois d'Histoire et d'Archéologie Militaires|language=French|quote=Three times we got a permit to visit the quarry. Our original intention was to photograph the Dom Bunker and the entrance to the gun tunnel. The unexpected and emotions were at the end of the road: a motley mass of steel plates. Our guide knew nothing about it and had no objection to photography of this bizarre material. Examination of the photographs confirmed our initial hypothesis : it could be the Mimoyecques plates. (transl.)|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Richely|first1=Paul|first2=André |last2=Neve|title=Les péripéties du site d'Hydrequent-Rinxent|trans_title=The adventures of the Hydrequent-Rinxent site|journal=Bulletin d'information du CLHAM|date=September 1991|volume=IV|issue=11|url=http://www.clham.org/050502.htm|accessdate=21 June 2011|publisher=Centre Liégeois d'Histoire et d'Archéologie Militaires|quote=The OKW refuses to renounce to the HDP gun originally planned in Mimoyecques, it will be transferred to the site Rinxent which, in turn, finds a new role at the time of abandonment. The choice of Rinxent is based on several considerations: the absence of any bombing of the site that apparently has not worried the Allies, tunnels allowing to work within with virtually ensured safety, nature of the soil (marble), location. (transl.)|language=French|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Sanders|first=Terence R. B. |authorlink=Terence Sanders|year=1945|title=Investigation of the &quot;Heavy&quot; Crossbow installations in Northern France. Report by the Sanders Mission to the Chairman of the Crossbow Committee|location=London|publisher=War Office|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Sandys|first=Duncan |authorlink=Duncan Sandys|date=19 March 1945|ref={{harvid|Sandys|1945}}|title=Report on 'Large' Crossbow Sites in Northern France|series=Memo C.O.S. (45) 177 (O)|location=London|publisher=War Office}}
* {{cite book|last=Zaloga|first=Steven J.| authorlink = Steven Zaloga | last2 = Johnson|first2=Hugh | last3 = Taylor|first3=Chris |title=German V-Weapon Sites 1943–45|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford|year=2008|isbn=978-1-84603-247-9|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|title=Le retour de pièces historiques à la forteresse de Mimoyecques|url=http://www.lavoixdunord.fr/Region/actualite/Secteur_Region/2010/07/15/article_le-retour-de-pieces-historiques-a-la-for.shtml|trans_title=The return of the historic pieces to the Fortress of Mimoyecques|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[La Voix du Nord (daily)|La Voix du Nord]]|date=15 July 2010|language=French|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==

* {{cite book|last=Hautefeuille|first=Roland|title=Constructions spéciales : histoire de la construction par l'&quot;Organisation Todt&quot;, dans le Pas-de-Calais et la Cotentin, des neufs grands sites protégés pour le tir des V1, V2, V3, et la production d'oxygène liquide, (1943–1944) |year=1995|location=Paris| isbn=2-9500899-0-9 |edition=2|publisher=Cerin|language=French}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Mimoyecques}}
* [http://www.mimoyecques.com/ Fortress of Mimoyecques]&amp;nbsp;– museum website
* {{fr icon}} [http://html2.free.fr/canons/basev3.htm Une base pour bombarder Londres]
* {{fr icon}} [http://www.cyanopale.org/ch/chronique13.htm Chroniques Historiques&amp;nbsp;– Les tunnels de Mimoyecques: la Base V3]
* {{fr icon}} [http://www.conservatoiresitesnpc.org/sites-proteges/site-protege.html?protar_id=9f4rqbY Forteresse de Mimoyecques&amp;nbsp;– Quand histoire et nature ne font qu'un]

{{V-weapons}}
{{WWII Operation Crossbow}}
{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mimoyecques Fortress}}
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Pas-de-Calais]]
[[Category:Infrastructure completed in 1944]]
[[Category:Museums in Pas-de-Calais]]
[[Category:Ruins in Hauts-de-France]]
[[Category:V-weapon subterranea]]
[[Category:World War II museums in France]]
[[Category:World War II sites in France]]</text>
      <sha1>816s2d9vxg2omv3gadobvci4quxc6iq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
