<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hasan al-Kharrat</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39024575</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751307312</id>
      <parentid>745074598</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-24T19:41:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Narky Blert</username>
        <id>22041646</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Link to DAB page repaired</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26270">{{featured article}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2013}}
{{Infobox person
|name        = Hasan al-Kharrat &lt;br/&gt; حسن الخراط
|image       = Hasan Kharrat cropped 1925.jpg
|caption     = Portrait of al-Kharrat
|alt         = A man in traditional Levantine Arab dress
|birth_date  = 1861
|birth_place = [[Damascus]], [[Syria Vilayet]], [[Ottoman Empire]]
|death_date  = 25 December {{Death year and age|1925|1861}}
|death_place = Damascus, [[French Mandate of Syria]]
|other_names = 
|known_for   = Commander of Damascus and [[Ghouta]] rebels during the [[Great Syrian Revolt]]
|occupation  = Night watchman and ''qabaday'' (local youths boss) of [[al-Shaghour]]
|children = Fakhri
|nationality = [[Syria]]n
}}
'''Abu Muhammad Hasan al-Kharrat''' ({{lang-ar|حسن الخراط}} 1861{{#tag:ref|Syrian historian Sami Moubayed and Palestinian historian Hanna Batatu list al-Kharrat's birth year as 1861&lt;ref&gt;Moubayed 2006, p. 381&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Batatu 1999, p. 368.&lt;/ref&gt; while American historian Michael Provence asserts that al-Kharrat was 50 years old in late 1925, suggesting that he was born in 1875.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence100&quot;/&gt;|group=note}}–25 December 1925) was one of the principal [[Syrian people|Syria]]n rebel commanders of the [[Great Syrian Revolt]] against the [[French Mandate of Syria|French Mandate]]. His main area of operations was in [[Damascus]] and its [[Ghouta]] countryside. He was killed in the struggle and is considered a hero by Syrians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence119&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
As the ''qabaday'' (local youths boss) of the [[al-Shaghour]] quarter of Damascus, al-Kharrat was connected with [[Nasib al-Bakri]], a nationalist from the quarter's most influential family. At al-Bakri's invitation, al-Kharrat joined the revolt in August 1925 and formed a group of fighters from al-Shaghour and other neighborhoods in the vicinity. He led the rebel assault against Damascus, briefly capturing the residence of French High-Commissioner [[Maurice Sarrail]] before withdrawing amid heavy French bombardment.

After his aborted operation in Damascus, al-Kharrat continued to lead forays against French forces in and around the city. Towards the end of 1925, relations grew tense between al-Kharrat and other rebel leaders, particularly [[Sa'id al-'As]] and Ramadan al-Shallash, as they traded accusations of plundering villages or extorting local inhabitants. Al-Kharrat was killed in a French ambush in the Ghouta, and the revolt dissipated by 1927, but he gained a lasting reputation as a martyr of the Syrian resistance to French rule.

==Early life and career==
[[File:Shaghour 1910.jpg|thumb|right|A street scene in the [[al-Shaghour]] quarter of [[Damascus]], 1910. Al-Kharrat lived in al-Shaghour and served as its ''qabaday'' (local youths boss) and the night watchman of its orchards.|alt=From left to right: A boy staring out from a store's window sill beneath which a lamb is walking by; three fully veiled women are conversing on the street; beneath an olive grove jutting out of a large stone archway and beside a fountain, a man is walking, a woman is collecting water from the fountain, and two young boys are standing and smiling; a young girl walking on the street]]

Al-Kharrat was born to a [[Sunni Muslim]] family in [[Damascus]] in 1861, during [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] rule in [[Syria (region)|Syria]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Syria Opposition Leader Interview Transcript |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970203833104577071960384240668.html |work=[[Wall Street Journal]] |date=2011-12-02 |accessdate=2013-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed381&quot;&gt;Moubayed 2006, p. 381.&lt;/ref&gt; He served as the night watchman of the city's [[al-Shaghour]] quarter and as a guard for the neighborhood's orchards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed381&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Batatu117&quot;&gt;Batatu 1999, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;&gt;Neep 2012, pp. 79–80.&lt;/ref&gt; Damascus was captured by [[Arab Revolt|Arab rebels]] in October 1918. Afterward, the Arab Club, an [[Arab nationalism|Arab nationalist]] organization, emerged in the city to raise support for the rebels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gelvin69-70&quot;&gt;Gelvin 1998, pp. 69–70.&lt;/ref&gt; The club assisted the rebels' leader, Emir [[Faisal I of Iraq|Faisal]], who formed a rudimentary government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gelvin69-70&quot;/&gt; Al-Kharrat became an affiliate of the Arab Club and raised support for Faisal in al-Shaghour.&lt;ref&gt;Gelvin 1998, p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1920, Faisal's government collapsed after its motley forces were defeated by the French at the [[Battle of Maysalun]].&lt;ref&gt;Khoury 1987, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; Afterward, the French ruled Syria under the aegis of their [[French Mandate of Syria|League of Nations mandate]].

In the early years of French rule, al-Kharrat was al-Shaghour's ''qabaday'' (pl. ''qabadayat''),&lt;ref name=&quot;Batatu117&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury157&quot;&gt;Khoury 2006, p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt; the traditional leader of a neighborhood's local toughs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury152&quot;&gt;Khoury 2006, p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''qabaday'' was informally charged with redressing grievances and defending a neighborhood's honor against local criminals or the encroachments of ''qabadayat'' from other neighborhoods.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury152&quot;/&gt; He was popularly characterized as an honorable man, noted for his personal strength,&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury152&quot;/&gt; and protection of minorities and the poor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury154&quot;&gt;Khoury 2006, p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''qabaday'' was considered an &quot;upholder of Arab traditions and customs, the guardian of popular culture&quot;, according to historian [[Philip S. Khoury]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury152&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury154&quot;/&gt; Khoury asserts that al-Kharrat was &quot;probably the most respected and esteemed ''qabaday'' of his day&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury157&quot;/&gt; ''Qabadayat'' normally shunned formal education,&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury152&quot;/&gt; and historian Michael Provence maintains that al-Kharrat was likely illiterate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence118&quot;/&gt; ''Qabadayat'' were normally linked with particular city notables and could secure them political support in their neighborhoods.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury152&quot;/&gt; Al-Kharrat was allied with [[Nasib al-Bakri]], a Damascene politician and landowner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt; The al-Bakri family was the most influential in al-Shaghour, and al-Kharrat served as the family's principal connection and enforcer in the quarter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commander in the Great Syrian Revolt==

===Recruitment and early confrontations===
A [[Great Syrian Revolt|revolt against French rule]] was launched in the mid-summer of 1925 by the Druze [[sheikh]] (chieftain), [[Sultan Pasha al-Atrash]], in the southern mountains of [[Jabal al-Druze]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt; As al-Atrash's men scored decisive victories against the French [[Army of the Levant]], [[Syrian nationalism|Syrian nationalist]]s were inspired and the revolt spread northward to the countryside of Damascus and beyond.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt; Al-Bakri was the chief liaison between al-Atrash and the emerging rebel movement in Damascus and the [[Ghouta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt; The Ghouta is the fertile plain surrounding Damascus,&lt;ref&gt;Neep 2012, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Glassé|first1=Cyril|title=The New Encyclopedia of Islam|date=1989|publisher=Stacey International|location=London|isbn=0-7591-0190-6|page=110|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=focLrox-frUC&amp;pg=PA110|chapter=Damascus}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its orchard groves and extensive waterways provided cover for the rebels and a base from which they could raid Damascus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Baer|first1=Gabriel|title=Fellah and Townsman in the Middle East: Studies in Social History|date=1982|publisher=Frank Cass and Company Limited|location=[[Abingdon-on-Thames|Abingdon]]|isbn=0-7146-3126-4|page=302|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=myoYuye0dS4C&amp;pg=PA302}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August, al-Bakri convinced al-Kharrat to join the uprising.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed381&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101&quot;/&gt; According to Provence, al-Kharrat was &quot;ideal&quot; for the job, possessing &quot;a local following of young men, notoriety outside the quarter, good connections and a reputation for toughness&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101&quot;/&gt; The group of fighters he commanded was known as ''′isabat al-Shawaghirah'' (the band of al-Shaghour).&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt; Though named after al-Kharrat's quarter, the band included twenty ''qabadayat'' and their armed retinues from other Damascus neighborhoods and nearby villages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury174&quot;&gt;Khoury 1987, p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Among the other villages and Damascus neighborhoods that contributed fighters to al-Kharrat's rebel band were [[Jaramana]], [[Kafr Batna]], [[Beit Sahem]], [[al-Malihah]], [[Al-Hariqa|Sidi Amud]], [[Sarouja|Suq Saruja]] and [[al-Amara]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt;|group=note}} His main areas of operation were in the vicinity of al-Shaghour and the al-Zur forest in the eastern Ghouta.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence118&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt; Through his alliance with a [[Sufi]] religious leader, al-Kharrat brought an Islamic holy war dimension to the largely secular revolt, something that was not welcomed by some involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Ghouta rebels in 1925.jpg|thumb|Rebels in the [[Ghouta]] commanded by Druze sheikh Izz al-Din al-Halabi (standing fifth from left), 1925. Al-Kharrat's rebels mainly operated in the Ghouta.|alt=A group of rebels in traditional Arab dress posing with rifles with date palms in the background]]

Al-Kharrat commenced guerrilla operations in September, targeting French forces posted in the eastern and southern Ghouta.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury174&quot;/&gt; His prominence rose as he led nighttime raids against the French in Damascus, during which he disarmed army patrols and took soldiers hostage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed381&quot;/&gt; In al-Shaghour, [[Sarouja|Souk Saruja]] and Jazmatiyya, al-Kharrat and his band burnt down all French-held buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed381&quot;/&gt; In the first week of October, sixty French [[Gendarmerie|gendarme]]s were dispatched to the Ghouta to apprehend al-Kharrat and his fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence100&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt; The gendarmes were quartered in the home of [[al-Malihah]]'s ''[[mukhtar]]'' (village headman).&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence100&quot;/&gt; In the evening, the rebels attacked the residence, killing one gendarme and capturing the rest; the prisoners were eventually all returned unharmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence100&quot;/&gt;

On 12 October, French troops backed by tanks, artillery and aerial support launched an operation to surround and eliminate al-Kharrat's rebels in the al-Zur forest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101-102&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, pp. 101–102.&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Kharrat's men were forewarned of the French deployment by the peasants of al-Malihah.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101-102&quot; /&gt; Positioned among the trees, the rebels used sniper fire against the French troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101-102&quot; /&gt; The latter were unable to lure the rebels out and retreated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101-102&quot; /&gt;

As the French withdrew toward al-Malihah, they looted the village and set it on fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101-102&quot;/&gt; French intelligence officials justified the collective punishment of al-Malihah as retaliation for the rebels' capture and humiliation of the gendarmes during the previous week; the French claimed a young boy from al-Malihah had notified al-Kharrat's men of the French presence in the village.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence102&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; Though they were unable to engage al-Kharrat and his forces directly, French troops executed around 100 civilians from Ghouta villages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence102&quot;/&gt; Their corpses were brought to Damascus, and the bodies of sixteen men described by the French as &quot;[[brigandage|brigand]]s&quot; were put on display.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence102&quot;/&gt;

===Battle of Damascus and operations in Ghouta===
[[File:Maurice Sarrail.jpg|thumb|right|General [[Maurice Sarrail]], the High-Commissioner of the [[French Mandate of Syria]]|alt=a close up of French High Commissioner of Syria, Maurice Sarrail]]

Spurred by French army actions in the Ghouta, al-Bakri planned to capture the [[Citadel of Damascus]], where French forces were concentrated, and the [[Azm Palace]], where General [[Maurice Sarrail]], the French [[High Commissioner of the Levant|high commissioner of Syria]], would be residing on 17–18 October (Sarrail was typically headquartered in [[Beirut]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence102&quot;/&gt; The high commissioner functioned as the overall administrator of Syria on behalf of France and  exercised practically absolute power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Peretz |first=Don |title=The Middle East Today |edition=Sixth |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |location=[[Westport, Connecticut|Westport]] |year=1994 |isbn=0-275-94575-8 |pages=365–366 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-WYVCxd_losC&amp;pg=PA365}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rebel units active in Damascus at the time were al-Kharrat's ''′isabat'' and a mixed force of Druze fighters and rebels from the [[al-Midan]] quarter and the Ghouta.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; To compensate for the lack of rebel strength, al-Bakri sent a letter to Sultan al-Atrash requesting reinforcements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence102&quot;/&gt; Al-Atrash replied that he was currently occupied with operations in the [[Hauran]], but would dispatch his entire force to back the Damascus rebels as soon as affairs there were settled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence102&quot;/&gt; Before he received al-Atrash's reply, al-Bakri decided to move ahead with the operation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt;

On 18 October, al-Kharrat led forty rebels into al-Shaghour from the old cemeteries adjacent to the [[Bab al-Saghir|southern gate of Damascus]], announcing that the Druze had arrived to relieve the city from French occupation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt; Crowds of residents enthusiastically welcomed the rebels and many took up arms alongside them. Al-Kharrat's men captured the quarter's police station, disarming its garrison.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt; They were joined by [[Ramadan al-Shallash]], a rebel commander from [[Deir ez-Zor]], and twenty of his [[Bedouin]] fighters. The joint forces proceeded to the [[Al-Hamidiyah Souq|Hamidiyya Market]] and captured the Azm Palace,&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed382&quot;&gt;Moubayed 2006, p. 382.&lt;/ref&gt; but Sarrail was not present, having already left to attend a meeting in the Hauran town of [[Daraa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt; The rebels plundered the palace and set it on fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt; Provence asserts that capturing the palace without Sarrail &quot;held no tactical importance&quot; but was a highly symbolic achievement for the rebels because of the Azm Palace's &quot;importance as the historical seat of economic and political power in Damascus, now usurped by the French and totally undefended&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt;

While al-Kharrat captured the Azm Palace, al-Bakri and 200 rebels under his command rode through the city and were joined by civilians in increasing numbers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence103&quot;/&gt; After sealing the Old City to prevent the entry of enemy reinforcements, al-Kharrat issued an order to kill anyone linked to the French army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed382&quot;/&gt; About 180 French soldiers were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed382&quot;/&gt; Sarrail ordered the shelling and [[Aerial bombardment of cities|aerial bombardment]] of the city, which lasted two days and killed about 1,500 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence104&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt; Chaos and scattered fighting ensued as whole neighborhoods, mosques and churches were leveled, French forces moved in, and hundreds of leading figures in the Syrian national movement were arrested,&lt;ref name=&quot;Moubayed382&quot;/&gt; including al-Kharrat's son Fakhri.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt; The latter was captured on 22 October during a botched nighttime raid by the rebels against the French, who had by then retaken Damascus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence118&quot;/&gt; Al-Kharrat was offered the release of his son in exchange for his own surrender, but refused.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=MacCallum|first1=Elizabeth Pauline|title=The Nationalist Crusade in Syria|date=1928|publisher=The Foreign Policy Association|location=[[New York City|New York]]|page=132|url=https://books.google.com/?id=dGptAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=editions%3ADr3nEi3knpkC&amp;q=%22Hasan+Kharrat%27s+reputation%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The rebels withdrew from Damascus as a meeting was held between French army commander [[Maurice Gamelin]] and a delegation of Damascene notables.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury177&quot;&gt;Khoury 1987, p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the meeting, the French agreed to end their bombardment in return for a payment of 100,000 Turkish gold liras by 24 October.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence104&quot;/&gt; The fine was not paid by the French deadline, but the bombardment was not renewed, likely as a result of orders from the French government in Paris.&lt;ref&gt;Provence 2005, pp. 104–105.&lt;/ref&gt; International condemnation of Sarrail's bombardment of Damascus and growing criticism in France of his mishandling of the revolt led to his dismissal on 30 October.&lt;ref&gt;Provence 2005, p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; He was replaced by politician [[Henry de Jouvenel]],&lt;ref&gt;Khoury 1987, pp. 181–182.&lt;/ref&gt; who arrived in Syria in December.&lt;ref&gt;Provence 2005, p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt; On 22 November, al-Kharrat commanded 700 rebels in a battle with about 500 French soldiers outside of Damascus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Syrian Revolt: Hassan Kharrat Killed|url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/67628990|accessdate=2013-04-07|newspaper=The Advocate|date=1 January 1926|author=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Kharrat's men inflicted &quot;trifling&quot; losses on the French, but experienced heavy casualties themselves, with thirty dead and forty wounded according to ''[[Reuters]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters&quot;/&gt; On 5 December, al-Kharrat was one of the commanders of a 2,000-strong force uniting rebels from disparate backgrounds, which assaulted the French Army barracks in [[Qadam|al-Qadam]], south of Damascus. The French claimed to have inflicted significant casualties, but rebel activity continued.&lt;ref&gt;Provence 2005, p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tensions with rebel leaders===
Centralized order and oversight among the revolt's armed participants was difficult to establish because of the diversity and independence of the rebel factions. A meeting of rebel leaders was held in the Ghouta village of [[Saqba]] on 26 November.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence134-5&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, pp. 134–135.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sa'id al-'As]] accused al-Kharrat and others of plundering in the Ghouta,&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep81&quot;&gt;Neep 2012, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; while al-Kharrat alleged that al-Shallash extorted the residents of al-Midan and the Ghouta town of [[Douma, Syria|Douma]].&lt;ref&gt;Neep 2012, p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt; The meeting concluded with an agreement to elect a government to replace the French authorities, increase recruitment of the Ghouta's inhabitants, coordinate military operations under a central command, and establish a revolutionary court to execute spies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep81&quot;/&gt; The meeting also designated the area between the village of [[Zabdin]] and north of the Douma-Damascus road as being part of al-Kharrat's zone of operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep81&quot;/&gt; Despite his leading role in the rebels' military efforts, al-Kharrat was not included in the newly formed rebel leadership council, nor were any of al-Bakri's allies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep81&quot;/&gt; Instead, al-'As served as the rebels' overall head.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep81&quot;/&gt;

Sharp divisions among rebel factions became apparent during a second meeting in Saqba on 5 December. According to Syrian journalist [[Munir al-Rayyes]], hostility between al-Kharrat and al-Shallash was well-known among the rebels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence134-5&quot;/&gt; Because al-Shallash had levied war taxes on the major landlords and city elites of the Ghouta, al-Kharrat's benefactor al-Bakri viewed him as a threat to the traditional landowning class to which al-Bakri belonged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence134&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Rayyis claimed the meeting was called for by al-Kharrat,&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence135&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt; who ordered his fighters to capture and bring al-Shallash to Saqba.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence137&quot;&gt;Provence 2005, p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to al-'As, the summit was called by al-Shallash, and once the latter arrived in the village, al-Kharrat personally detained him and confiscated his horse, weapons and money.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence137&quot;/&gt;

After his detention, al-Shallash was given a brief trial during which al-Kharrat accused him of making &quot;impositions and ransoms and financial collections in the name of the revolt&quot;, while al-Bakri condemned him specifically for extorting the residents of Douma for 1,000 ''[[Pound (currency)|giney]]'' (Ottoman pounds),&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence134-5&quot;/&gt; and imposing large fines on the inhabitants of [[Harran al-Awamid]], [[al-Qisa]] and [[Maydaa]] for his own personal enrichment.&lt;ref&gt;Provence 2005, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Kharrat and al-Bakri decided al-Shallash's verdict, and dismissed him from the revolt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence134&quot;/&gt; While many rebels with officer backgrounds similar to al-Shallash disapproved of the judgement, they did not intervene.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence134-5&quot;/&gt; In his account of the meeting, al-Rayyis condemned the rebel commanders for complacency in the &quot;ridiculous trial&quot; and accused al-Kharrat of being motivated solely by personal animosity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence135&quot;/&gt; Al-Shallash was able to escape—or was released by al-'As—when French planes bombed the meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence137&quot;/&gt; Al-Shallash would later surrender to Jouvenel and collaborate with French authorities.&lt;ref&gt;Provence 2005, pp. 138–139.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and legacy==
[[File:Fakhri Kharrat execution, 1925.jpg|thumb||upright|right|Al-Kharrat's son and rebel commander, Fakhri, hanged by French authorities in [[Marjeh Square]], Damascus, January 1926|alt=A man executed by hanging with onlookers in the background.]]

Al-Kharrat was killed in an ambush by French troops in the Ghouta on 25 December 1925.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence135&quot;/&gt; He was succeeded as ''qabaday'' of al-Shaghour and commander of the ''′isabat al-Shawaghirah'' by Mahmud Khaddam al-Srija.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khoury157&quot;/&gt; Al-Kharrat's men continued to fight the French until the revolt ended in 1927,&lt;ref&gt;Provence 2005, p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; though historian Thomas Philipp states that al-Kharrat's group dissipated after his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor-last1=Philipp|editor-first1=Thomas|editor-last2=Schumann|editor-first2=Christoph|title=From the Syrian Land to the States of Syria and Lebanon|date=2004|publisher=Orient Institut der DMG Beirut|location=[[Würzburg]]|isbn=3-89913-353-6|page=281|url=https://books.google.com/?id=3FRtAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=%22Hasan+Kharrat%22&amp;q=%22group+broke+up%22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1926, al-Kharrat's son Fakhri was sentenced to death and publicly executed with two other rebels in [[Marjeh Square]], Damascus.&lt;ref&gt;Neep 2012, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; The French had previously implored Fakhri to persuade his father to surrender in return for his release, but Fakhri refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence118&quot;/&gt;

[[Abd al-Rahman Shahbandar]], a prominent Syrian nationalist leader, described al-Kharrat as having played &quot;the preeminent role&quot; in the battle against the French in the Ghouta and Damascus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batatu117&quot;/&gt; Historian Daniel Neep wrote that al-Kharrat was the &quot;best-known&quot; of all of the Damascus-based rebel leaders,&lt;ref name=&quot;Neep79-80&quot;/&gt; although other leaders of the rebel movement attributed the publicity and praise of al-Kharrat to the efforts of the [[Cairo]]-based [[Syrian-Palestinian Congress|Syrian-Palestinian Committee]], with which al-Bakri was closely affiliated. Al-Kharrat and his son Fakhri are today considered &quot;martyred heroes&quot; by Syrians for their nationalist efforts and their deaths in the Syrian struggle for independence from France.&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence101&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Provence135&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last=Batatu |first=Hanna|title=Syria's Peasantry, the Descendants of Its Lesser Rural Notables, and Their Politics |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=[[Princeton, New Jersey|Princeton]] |year=1999 |isbn=0-691-00254-1 |url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=4_Cvhg3YHIoC&amp;pg=PA368}}
*{{cite book|last1=Khoury|first1=Philip S.|title=Syria and the French Mandate: The Politics of Arab Nationalism, 1920–1945|date=1987|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=0-691-05486-X|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tvP_AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA97}}
*{{cite book |last=Khoury |first=Philip S. |title=Struggle And Survival in the Modern Middle East |edition=Second |chapter=Abu Ali al-Kilawi, A Damascus Qabaday |editor-last1=Burke |editor-first1=Edmund III |editor-last2=Yaghoubian |editor-first2=David N. |publisher=University of California Press |location=[[London]] |year=2006|isbn=0-520-24661-6 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fwjEHoCBO0cC&amp;pg=PA157}}
*{{cite book |last1=Gelvin |first1=James L. |title=Divided Loyalties: Nationalism and Mass Politics in Syria at the Close of Empire |date=1998 |publisher=University of California Press |location=London |isbn=0-520-21069-7 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=D4Us4_x8M4kC&amp;pg=PA75}}
*{{cite book |last=Moubayed |first=Sami |title=Steel and Silk: Men and Women who Shaped Syria 1900–2000 |publisher=Cune Press |location=[[Seattle]] |year=2006 |isbn=1-885942-41-9 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GF51Sml5WpcC&amp;pg=PA381}}
*{{cite book |last=Neep |first=Daniel |title=Occupying Syria Under the French Mandate: Insurgency, Space and State Formation |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=[[New York City|New York]] |year=2012 |isbn=1-107-00006-8 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XU4hAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA79}}
*{{cite book |last1=Provence |first1=Michael |title=The Great Syrian Revolt and the Rise of Arab Nationalism |edition=First |year=2005 |publisher=University of Texas Press |location=[[Austin, Texas|Austin]] |isbn=0-292-70635-9 |url=http://m.friendfeed-media.com/99b18b89a44867df19209accdba69dc1abc13ccb}}
{{refend}}

{{Portal bar|Syria}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kharrat, Hasan}}
[[Category:1861 births]]
[[Category:1925 deaths]]
[[Category:Guerrillas killed in action]]
[[Category:Ottoman Arabs]]
[[Category:Ottoman Arab nationalists]]
[[Category:People from Damascus]]
[[Category:People of the Great Syrian Revolt]]
[[Category:Syrian Arab nationalists]]
[[Category:Syrian Sunni Muslims]]</text>
      <sha1>bjrsjr5obmvvdcx1ualjtix2vlyvku5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
