<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>La Coupole</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>801691</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739403143</id>
      <parentid>739399151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-14T13:44:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Andy Dingley</username>
        <id>3606755</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Design and location */ fix dab</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39764">{{Infobox Military Structure
|name             = La Coupole
|native_name = Bauvorhaben 21&lt;br /&gt;Schotterwerk Nordwest&lt;br /&gt;Coupole d'Helfaut
|partof           = 
|location         = close to [[Wizernes]] &amp; [[Helfaut]], [[Nord-Pas-de-Calais]], [[France]]
|coordinates      =  
|map_type= France
|latitude= 50.70583
|longitude=  2.243889
|image            = [[File:La Coupole, Helfaut-Wizernes.jpg|300px]]
|caption          = View of the dome of La Coupole
|type             = [[Bunker]]
|code=
|built            = October 1943&amp;nbsp;– July 1944
|builder          = [[Organisation Todt]]
|materials        = [[Concrete]]
|height           = 
|used             = Never completed
|demolished=
|condition=
|controlledby     = France
|open_to_public   = History and Remembrance Centre&lt;ref name=lacoupole-france&gt;{{cite web|last=|first=|url=http://www.lacoupole-france.com/en/default.asp|title=History and Remembrance Centre, La Coupole|work=|accessdate=24 May 2007|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|ownership= Conseil Général du Pas-de-Calais&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB97&quot; /&gt;
|garrison         = ''Abteilungen'' ({{lang-en|firing detachment}}) comprising one technical and two operational batteries
|current_commander=
|commanders=
|occupants=
|battles          = 1944: [[Operation Crossbow]] campaign
|events           = September 1944: Captured by Allies&lt;br /&gt;May 1997: Reopened as a museum
}}

'''La Coupole''' ({{lang-en|The Dome}}), also known as the '''Coupole d'Helfaut-Wizernes''' and originally [[codename]]d '''Bauvorhaben 21''' (''Building Project 21'') or '''Schotterwerk Nordwest''' (''Northwest Gravel Works''),&lt;ref name=Zaloga2008&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|pp=13, 41}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[Second World War]] bunker complex in the [[Pas-de-Calais]] ''[[Departments of France|department]]'' of northern France, about {{convert|5|km|mi}} from [[Saint-Omer]], and some 14.4 kilometers (8.9 miles) south-southeast from the less developed [[Blockhaus d'Eperlecques]] V-2 launch installation in the same area. It was built by the forces of [[Nazi Germany]] between 1943 and 1944 to serve as a launch base for [[V-2 rocket]]s directed against London and southern England, and is the earliest known precursor to modern [[Missile launch facility|underground missile silo]]s still in existence.

Constructed in the side of a disused chalk quarry, the most prominent feature of the complex is an immense concrete dome, to which its modern name refers. It was built above a network of tunnels housing storage areas, launch facilities and crew quarters. The facility was designed to store a large stockpile of V-2s, warheads and fuel and was intended to launch V-2s on an industrial scale. Dozens of missiles a day were to be fuelled, prepared and launched in rapid sequence against London and southern England.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga2008a&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|p=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following repeated heavy bombing by Allied forces during [[Operation Crossbow]], the Germans were unable to complete the construction works and the complex never entered service. It was captured by the Allies in September 1944, partially demolished on the orders of [[Winston Churchill]] to prevent its reuse as a military base, and then abandoned. It remained derelict until the mid-1990s. In 1997 it opened to the public for the first time, as a museum. Exhibits in the tunnels and under the dome tell the story of the [[German occupation of France during World War II]], the [[V-weapons]] and the history of [[space exploration]].

==Background==
The V-2 rocket was one of several innovative long-range weapons developed by the Germans after the failure of the [[Luftwaffe]] to strike a decisive blow against Britain. It was a revolutionary weapon – the world's first operational [[SRBM]] – that had been developed in a secret programme begun in 1936. The German leadership hoped that a barrage of rockets unleashed against London would force Britain out of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although [[Adolf Hitler]] was at first ambivalent, he eventually became an enthusiastic supporter of the V-2 programme as Allied air forces carried out increasingly devastating attacks on German cities.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|p=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 12.5-ton missile, standing {{convert|14|m|ft}} high on its launch pad, was fuelled primarily by [[liquid oxygen]] (LOX) and [[methyl alcohol]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ZalogaCalow28&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Calow|2003|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deploying the V-2 on a large scale required far more LOX than was available from existing production sites in Germany and the occupied countries. New sources of LOX were required, situated close to the missile launching sites to reduce as far as possible the loss of propellant through evaporation. The missile's operational range of {{convert|320|km|mi}} meant that the launch sites had to be fairly close to the [[English Channel]] or southern [[North Sea]] coasts, in northern France, [[Belgium]] or the western [[Netherlands]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ZalogaCalow10&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Calow|2003|p=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the complexity of the missile and the need for extensive testing prior to launch, the V-2's designers at the [[Peenemünde Army Research Center]] favoured using heavily defended fixed sites where the missiles could be stored, armed, and fuelled from an on-site LOX production plant before launching. But the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]] and the V-2 project's head, Major-General [[Walter Dornberger]], were concerned that the sites would be vulnerable to aerial attack by the Allies. The Army's preferred option was to use ''[[Meillerwagen]]s'', mobile firing batteries, which presented a much smaller target for the Allied air forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZalogaCalow10&quot; /&gt;

The Army was nonetheless overruled by Hitler, who had a long-standing preference for huge, grandiose constructions. He preferred fixed installations along the lines of the virtually impregnable [[submarine pen|U-boat pens]] that had been built to protect Germany's [[U-boat]] fleet. In March 1943,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Longmate|2009|p=105}}&lt;/ref&gt; he ordered the construction of a massive bunker (now known as the [[Blockhaus d'Éperlecques]]) in the [[Forest of Éperlecques]] near [[Watten, Nord|Watten]], north of Saint-Omer. The bunker was soon spotted by Allied reconnaissance, and on 27 August 1943, a raid by 187 [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress]] bombers wrecked the construction site before it could be completed. A surviving portion was reused by the Germans as a LOX production facility.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZalogaCalow10&quot; /&gt;

==Design and location==
[[File:Mimoyecques-Eperlecques-Wizernes map.png|right|thumb|Map of the Pas-de-Calais and south-eastern England showing the location of Wizernes and other major V-weapons sites]]
The successful attack against the Watten bunker forced the German Army to find an alternative location for a launch site nearby. They had already taken possession of an old quarry between the villages of Helfaut and [[Wizernes]], south-west of Saint-Omer and some {{convert|12|km|mi}} south of the Watten bunker, near the [[Aa River (France)|Aa river]] alongside the [[Boulogne]]–Saint-Omer railway line, about three-quarters of a mile (1&amp;nbsp;km) from Wizernes station. The quarry had been designated for use as a missile storage depot where V-2s would be housed in tunnels bored into the chalk hillside before being transported for launching.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dungan&quot; /&gt;  The Germans undertook major work in August 1943 to lay extensive railway sidings to connect the quarry to the main line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders3&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 30 September 1943, Hitler met with [[Albert Speer]], the Minister of Armaments and War Production, and [[Franz Xaver Dorsch]], the chief engineer of the [[Todt Organisation]], to discuss plans for a replacement for the out-of-commission Watten facility.  Dorsch proposed to transform the Wizernes depot into a vast bomb-proof underground complex that would require a million tons of concrete to build. It would be constructed within a network of tunnels to be dug inside the hillside at the edge of the quarry. A concrete dome, {{convert|16.7|ft|m}} thick, {{convert|71|m|ft}} in diameter and weighing 55,000 tons, would be built over the top of the central part of the facility to protect it from Allied bombing. Beneath it, about {{convert|7|km|mi}} of tunnels were to be dug into the chalk hillside to accommodate workshops, storerooms, fuel supplies, a LOX manufacturing plant, generators, barracks and a hospital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dungan&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Dungan|2005|p=75}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Gallery|align=center
| title = Maps and plans of the Wizernes site
| lines = 4
| width = 230
|File:Wizernes site local map.jpg|Photo map of the area around the site before the bombing campaign
|File:Wizernes site diagram.png|Plan of the Wizernes complex as built by September 1944&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders1945&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|File:Wizernes site octagon.jpg|1944 conjectural reconstruction of the rocket preparation chamber and tunnels  (on the assumption that A4 rockets were to be handled)&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders1945&quot; /&gt;
}}
[[File:Ida railway tunnel La Coupole Flickr 1392294854 e3001919ce o.jpg|right|thumb|The ''Ida'' railway tunnel, where V-2s and supplies would be brought in by train and unloaded]]
A standard gauge railway tunnel, codenamed ''Ida'', was to be built on a curving path that would connect it with both the east- and west-bound main line railway, allowing trains to run straight through the complex without needing to reverse or be turned around. This would serve as the main unloading station, where missiles and supplies would be offloaded onto trolleys that would transport them into the connecting galleries ''Mathilde'' and ''Hugo''. ''Hugo'' connected in turn with ''Sophie'', a dead-end railway tunnel branching from the main line into ''Ida''. Each of the main tunnels had a number of unnamed side tunnels of the same dimensions as the main tunnels and up to {{convert|90|m|ft}} long. The central feature of the complex was a huge octagonal rocket-preparation chamber directly under the dome. It was never completed but would have been {{convert|41|m|ft}} in diameter and up to {{convert|33|m|ft}} high. A number of intermediate floors, possibly as many as ten, would have been built up the sides of the chamber.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders4-7&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|pp=4–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The western side of the chamber opened onto two tall passageways, opening onto two tracks to the outdoor launchpads, with the tracked passages and launchpads named ''Gustav'' (the southerly-located pad) and ''Gretchen'' (the northerly-located pad), both on the western side of the domed complex. Each was to have been protected by bomb-proof doors made of steel and concrete. The passageways were to be {{convert|4|m|ft}} wide and at least {{convert|17|m|ft}} high and were angled in a Y-shape, generally exiting westwards into the quarry. The outdoor launchpads for the V-2 rockets would have been at the end of each passageway. The two passageways were angled at 64° 50' and 99° 50' west of north respectively&amp;nbsp;– not aligned with any probable target but merely permitting the rockets to be transported to sufficiently widely separated launch pads.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders8&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The facility was designed, as was its predecessor at Watten, to receive, process and launch V-2 rockets at a high rate. Trains carrying V-2s would enter the heart of the complex through the ''Ida'' rail tunnel, where they would be unloaded. A large number of V-2s could be stored in the side tunnels; LOX would also be produced on-site ready for use. When the time came, the rockets would be moved into the octagonal preparation chamber where they would be lifted to a vertical position for fuelling and arming. From there they would be transported on motorised launch carriages, still in a vertical position, through the ''Gustav'' and ''Gretchen'' passageways. The launch pads were located at the end of the track on the floor of the quarry, from where the missiles would be fired.&lt;ref name=&quot;Longmate-106&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Longmate|2009|p=106}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The priority target for the V-2s was {{convert|188|km|mi}} away: London, which Hitler wanted to see pulverised by the end of 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga2008a&quot; /&gt; The Allies were alarmed when an analyst found that part of the complex was aligned within half a degree of the [[Great Circle]] bearing on [[New York City|New York]], and its equipment was large enough to accommodate a rocket twice the size of the V-2: the &quot;America Rocket&quot;, the proposed [[Aggregate (rocket family)#A9.2FA10|A10]] [[intercontinental ballistic missile]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Piszkiewicz&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Piszkiewicz|2007|p=176}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although physically separate, another facility built in nearby [[Roquetoire]] was an integral part of the Wizernes complex. ''Umspannwerk C'' was built to house a [[Leitstrahl]] radio command guidance system which could be used to send course corrections to missiles launched from Wizernes to fine-tune their trajectory during the launch phase.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga41&quot;/&gt;

==Construction==

[[File:Wizernes site dome cross-section.jpg|right|thumb|Cross-section of the dome]]
[[File:Wizernes tunnel door.jpg|right|thumb|Section of one of the bomb-proof doors for either ''Gustav'' or ''Gretchen'' tunnels. Segments of the doors were found by Allied troops at a storage dump near the Watten railway station.]]
The Allies first noticed construction activity at Wizernes in mid-August 1943 when the Germans began building railway track and the offloading stores into the old quarry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley593&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hinsley|Thomas|1990|p=593}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Hitler authorised the decision to turn the depot into a missile launch site, construction was stepped up. Work on the dome began in November 1943&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga40&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt; and tunnelling in the cliff face below began in December. At the start of January, Allied reconnaissance aircraft observed an elaborate system of camouflage on the hill top, installed to conceal the dome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley593&quot; /&gt; The building works were greatly hindered by the constant air-raid warnings, which stopped work 229 times in May 1944 alone. In response to Hitler's desire to see the site completed the workforce was expanded substantially from 1,100 in April 1944 to nearly 1,400 by June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Longmate-107&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Longmate|2009|p=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 60% of the workers were Germans; skilled workers, such as miners from [[Westphalia]], were recruited to excavate the tunnels and build the dome.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Seller|Neufeld|2003|page=52}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remainder were principally Frenchmen conscripted by the [[Service du travail obligatoire]] (STO), plus Soviet prisoners of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dungan&quot; /&gt; The project was overseen by several large German construction companies, with [[Philipp Holzmann|Philipp Holzman A.G.]] of [[Frankfurt am Main]] and the Grossdeutsche Schachtbau and Tiefbohr GmbH serving as the chief contractors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders12&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the most difficult challenges faced by the Germans was constructing the great dome while under regular air attack. The dome's designer, Todt Organisation engineer Werner Flos, devised a plan under which the dome would be built first, flat upon the ground, and the soil underneath it would be excavated so that the construction works below would be protected against aerial attacks. A circular trench was excavated on the top of the hill above the quarry to an outside diameter of {{convert|84|m|ft}}. The dome was built within this trench and the galleries and octagonal preparation chamber were excavated below.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders3&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB57&quot;&gt;&quot;An Engineer Returns&amp;nbsp;... And A Museum Is Born&quot;, ''After the Battle'' 57:49–53.&lt;/ref&gt;

As an additional bomb-proofing method, the dome was surrounded by a bomb-proof &quot;skirt&quot; or ''Zerschellerplatte'' of steel-reinforced concrete, {{convert|14|m|ft}} wide and {{convert|2|m|ft}} thick. This was supported by a series of buttresses, which were not tied into the dome itself, above the entrances to the ''Gustav'' and ''Gretchen'' tunnels. Another concrete structure was tied into the skirt to the north-west of the dome, which was perhaps intended for use as an observation and control tower. A separate underground building was constructed on the western side of the quarry to serve as a hospital and as offices for the engineers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders9&quot;/&gt; A [[Decauville]] narrow-gauge railway was installed on the quarry floor to transport supplies from the main line to the construction site.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot;&gt;&quot;The V-Weapons&quot;. ''After the Battle'', 6:23–24&lt;/ref&gt;

A cube-shaped concrete building was constructed on the top of the hill, next to the dome. This was intended to be used as the bomb-proof outlet for a ventilation and air conditioning shaft. It was an essential component of a facility where dangerous and explosive gases were expected to be used in large quantities on a daily basis. It was never finished, and the Allies found when they captured the site that the ventilation shaft had not been fully excavated. The building survived the bombing intact and is still prominently visible today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders9&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike its sister site at Watten, there was no on-site power plant. Electricity at Wizernes was provided by a connection to the main electric grid, with power consumption estimated at between 5,000 and 6,000 [[Volt-ampere|kVA]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders12&quot; /&gt;

==Discovery and Allied attacks==
[[File:Royal Air Force Bomber Command, 1942-1945. CH15363.jpg|thumb|right|RAF ground crew handling one of the Tallboy bombs that was dropped on Wizernes during an attack by [[No. 617 Squadron RAF|617 Squadron]] (1944)]][[File:Wizernes low level 6 July 1944.jpg|right|thumb|A photograph taken by a British Mosquito aircraft flying only {{convert|20|m|ft}} above the ground shows the dome, still intact, sitting at the centre of the wrecked construction site on 6 July 1944, shortly before its abandonment]]
The Allies became aware of the Wizernes site in August 1943 when the Germans began laying extensive new rail sidings which were spotted by RAF reconnaissance flights.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders3&quot; /&gt; Late 1943, a Belgian, Jacques de Duve, supported by German opponents, informed MI5 about the existence of a rocket production site in Saint-Omer. MI5 did not believe Jacques de Duve, who was interned for the rest of the war in Latchmere House.&lt;ref&gt;De Duve Jacques, file KV2/1314 (PF 66116/V1), National Archives (UK). Interim Report, February 1944, p. 23 : « ''A secret factory somewhere in St. Omer, engaged on the production of rocket guns. These were apparently capable of firing shells 16 tons in weight, and could reach London. This factory was supposed to be so secret that its employees were never allowed to leave it.'' » Sent back in Belgium by MI5, beginning 1945, the patriotic intentions of Jacques de Duve have been confirmed by several concordant witnesses (Dossier répressif 45/5487 de l’Auditorat militaire, en cause de Duve, Jacques). He quickly benefited from a dismissal of the prosecution and has been awarded the Escapees’ Cross 1940 -1945 (Arr. du Régent May 10, 1947, Moniteur Belge May 17, 1947).&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1943, the [[RAF Medmenham|Allied Central Interpretation Unit]] reported that the Germans had begun constructing the concrete dome and were undertaking tunnelling works in the east face of the quarry. However, it was not until the following March that the Allies added the site to the list of targets for [[Operation Crossbow]], the ongoing bombing campaign against V-weapon sites that had already wrecked the Watten bunker and numerous [[V-1 flying bomb|V-1]] launching sites. Over the next few months, the USAAF and RAF carried out 16 air raids involving 811 bombers that dropped some 4,260 tons of bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga41&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bombing caused destruction across a wide area, killing 55 residents of the nearby village of Helfault.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Traa|first=Mark|title=Onderdak voor een Wonderwapen|work=Trouw|date=3 December 1997|language=Dutch|url=http://www.trouw.nl/tr/nl/5009/Archief/archief/article/detail/2755747/1997/12/03/ONDERDAK-VOOR-EEN-WONDERWAPEN.dhtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conventional bombing raids only achieved a single bomb hit on the dome itself, causing negligible damage. However, in June and July 1944 the RAF began attacking the site with {{convert|12000|lb|kg}}, [[Bunker buster#World War II|ground-penetrating]] [[Tallboy (bomb)|Tallboy bombs]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga41&quot; /&gt;  The external construction works were completely wrecked by the bombing and one Tallboy landed just beside the dome, blowing out the entire quarry cliff face and burying the entrances to the ''Gustav'' and ''Gretchen'' tunnels. The entrance to ''Sophie'' was also buried, leaving ''Ida'' as the only entrance to the facility. The dome was unscathed but the buttresses supporting the protective ''Zerschellerplatte'' were dislodged and slid partway down into the quarry. Serious damage was also caused to the tunnels beneath the dome. The damage made it impossible to continue work on the site. Dornberger complained: &quot;Persistent air attack with heavy and super-heavy bombs so battered the rock all around that in the spring of 1944 landslides made further work impossible.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Longmate-147&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Longmate|2009|p=147}}&lt;/ref&gt; His staff reported on 28 July 1944 that, although the dome had not been hit by the Tallboys, &quot;the whole area around has been so churned up that it is unapproachable, and the bunker is jeopardised from underneath.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Longmate-147&quot; /&gt;

Although three launch battalions were formed by the Germans in late 1943,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Calow|2003|p=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; they never got the chance to deploy to the V-weapons launch sites at Watten and Wizernes. On 3 July 1944, the [[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|Oberkommando West]] authorised the cessation of construction at the heavily damaged sites. On 18 July 1944, Hitler abandoned plans for launching V-2s from bunkers&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ordway|Sharpe|1979|p=193}}&lt;/ref&gt; and authorized the downgrading of the Wizernes bunker to make it a LOX production facility.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|Calow|2003|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, these plans were overtaken by the Allied liberation of Northern France following the [[Normandy landings]]. The site was finally abandoned a few days before the Allies reached it at the start of September during the rapid liberation of the area by British, American, Canadian and Polish troops.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Le Maner|1997|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; British engineers inspected it on 5 September.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Reference points|url=http://www.lacoupole-france.com/en/historique/reperes.asp|publisher=Museum La Coupole|accessdate=23 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post war investigations==
[[File:La Coupole exhibition V-2 rocket.jpg|right|thumb|upright|Original V-2 rocket and engine on display under the dome of La Coupole]]
Shortly after the Wizernes site had been captured in September 1944, [[Duncan Sandys]], the head of the British &quot;Crossbow Committee&quot; investigating the V-weapons programme, ordered the constitution of a Technical Inter-Services Mission under Colonel [[Terence Sanders|T.R.B. Sanders]]. It was given the task of investigating the sites at [[Fortress of Mimoyecques|Mimoyecques]], [[Siracourt V-1 bunker|Siracourt]], Watten, and Wizernes, collectively known to the Allies as the &quot;Heavy Crossbow&quot; sites. Sanders' report was submitted to the War Cabinet on 19 March 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Sandys|1945}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The purpose of the Wizernes site had been unclear prior to its capture but Sanders was able to deduce its connection with the V-2 from the dimensions of the complex and some intelligence information that his team had been able to retrieve. Sanders' report concluded that it was &quot;an assembly site for long projectiles most conveniently handled and prepared in a vertical position&quot;. He conjectured the approximate length of the projectiles from the height of the ''Gustav'' and ''Gretchen'' tunnels, though he noted that there was some doubt about the height of the doors at the tunnel entrances. Segments of the doors had been recovered from a storage dump near Watten railway station, but were incomplete. Judging from the size of the tunnel entrance, the maximum size of the projectile could have been between {{convert|17|m|ft}} and {{convert|24|m|ft}} in length and {{convert|4|m|ft}} in breadth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders11&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sanders|1945|p=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; (This was substantially larger than the V-2, which measured {{convert|14|m|ft}} long and {{convert|3.55|m|ft}} wide.) Two witnesses interviewed by the Sanders team reported &quot;an intention of firing a projectile 18 metres long&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders12&quot; /&gt; Sanders noted that &quot;the dimensions of the site make it suitable for the A.4 (V-2) rocket, but the possibility of a new rocket up to half as long again as the A.4 and twice the weight cannot be ruled out.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanders12&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref group=Notes&gt;Although the [[V-2 rocket]] at {{convert|14|m|ft}} long could have been carried by a car through the Sanders-identified height, the [[Aggregate series#A10|A10]] New York rocket design was too tall—even without a rail carrier—at {{Convert|26|m|ft|abbr=on}}.&lt;/ref&gt;    He concluded that much of the site was becoming unsafe due to the progressive collapse of timbering and recommended that the tunnels and workings under the dome should be destroyed to prevent subsequent accidents or misuse.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot; /&gt;

The site reverted to private ownership after the war. As the quarry had long since been worked out, it was abandoned.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB57&quot; /&gt; The tunnels were not destroyed but were sealed off, though at some point they were reopened by local people and could be entered; the octagon remained sealed off with a ceiling-to-floor barricade. The quarry itself remained in almost the same condition as it had been in 1944, with sections of railway track still in place on the quarry floor. The hospital section remained relatively intact and was used by the local gendarmes as a shooting range.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB6&quot; /&gt;

==Museum of La Coupole==
[[File:La Coupole museum.jpg|left|thumb|Entrance to the museum of La Coupole]]
In 1986, the Espace Naturel Régional in [[Lille]] earmarked 10 million [[French franc|francs]] to develop the site as a tourist attraction for the Nord-Pas-de-Calais region with the intention of establishing a World War II museum there. The plan was publicised in a special open weekend on 20–21 June 1987, attended by over 20,000 people, in which the dome's designer Werner Flos met Professor [[Reginald Victor Jones]], a surviving member of the &quot;Crossbow Committee&quot;, at Wizernes. The ''Ida'' tunnel and side chambers were opened to the public and used for an audio-visual exhibition of the site's history.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB57&quot; /&gt;

Local historian Yves le Maner was charged with the task of developing the project while a feasibility study was conducted into the possibility of completing some of the original excavation work to make the site safe for public access. The plans were approved in 1993 and the site was purchased by the Commune de Helfaut. The following year, the Conseil Général du Pas-de-Calais acquired the site. The 69-million-franc project (£7.5 million at 1997 prices) was largely underwritten by the Conseil Général, which provided 35 million francs, with another 17 million coming from the regional council. The European taxpayer provided a further 12 million, the French State provided 3 million and the Saint-Omer municipal administration funded the remaining 1 million francs; a number of private shareholders were also involved. The Societé d'Equipement du Pas-de-Calais was contracted to carry out the development work, which involved excavating a further two metres (six feet) beneath the dome, clearing out and completing the unfinished concreting of some of the tunnels, building an exhibition centre and car park in the quarry floor and installing a lift to carry visitors up from the octagon to the dome.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB97&quot;&gt;&quot;Wizernes opens to the public&quot;. ''After the Battle'', 97:34–37. London: After the Battle Magazine.&lt;/ref&gt;

The museum opened in May 1997. Visitors enter and leave through the ''Ida'' railway tunnel, though the rails have been removed and the floor levelled. Short branch tunnels lead off on either side; originally used for storage, they now display wartime objects. Headphone stands along the way present multi-lingual accounts of the construction and purpose of the facility. The tour continues along the ''Mathilde'' tunnel to reach a lift that has been installed to bring visitors up to the space beneath the dome, where the main exhibition area is located.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Henshall|2002|pages=135–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Focusing on the story of the V-weapons, life in occupied France, and the conquest of space after the war, the tour presents audio-visual displays in English, French, Dutch and German. The museum houses a large number of original artifacts including a V-1 provided by London's [[Science Museum (London)|Science Museum]] and a V-2 provided by the [[Smithsonian Institution]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ATB97&quot; /&gt; and incorporates a memorial to the 8,000 people who were shot in or deported from the Nord-Pas-de-Calais region during the war; computer terminals track the paths of several hundred of the deportees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lacoupole-france.com/decouvrir-la-coupole/le-memorial-des-deportes.html|title=Le mémorial des déportés|publisher=La Coupole|language=French|accessdate=13 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the museum welcomed 120,000 visitors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Hervé |last=Vaughan |title=Yves Le Maner s'apprête à refermer la porte de son histoire avec la Coupole|journal=[[La Voix du Nord (daily)|La Voix du Nord]]|date=17 February 2011|url=http://www.lavoixdunord.fr/Locales/Saint_Omer/actualite/Secteur_Saint_Omer/2011/02/17/article_yves-le-maner-s-apprete-a-refermer-la-po.shtml|accessdate=20 June 2011|language=French|quote=|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2012, the museum opened a planetarium as part of Cerendac, a newly established ''Centre de ressources numériques pour le développement de l'accès à la connaissance'' (Resource Centre for the development of digital access to knowledge). The €6 million centre is funded by the Pas-de-Calais ''department'', the Nord-Pas-de-Calais region, the French state, the European taxpayer and the [[Communes of France#Intercommunality|intercommunality]] of Saint-Omer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pasdecalais.fr/Actualites/Culture/Planetarium-de-la-Coupole-On-n-y-regarde-pas-les-etoiles-on-les-touche-!|title=Planétarium de la Coupole : &quot;On n'y regarde pas les étoiles, on les touche !&quot;|language=French|publisher=Conseil Général du Pas-de-Calais|accessdate=13 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2010, the museum has also managed the [[V-3 cannon|V-3]] site of the [[Fortress of Mimoyecques]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mimoyecques.com/ Official website of the fortress of Mimoyecques]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Air raids on the Wizernes site==

{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+valign=top| Wizernes World War II bombings
!style=&quot;background:silver&quot; width=11%         | Date
!style=&quot;background:silver&quot; | 
|- valign=top
| 11 March 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 34 of 51 [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator]]s of the [[2d Bombardment Division]]'s 44th and 93d Heavy Bombardment groups attacked Wizernes using blind-bombing techniques due to thick overcast, dropping 127 tons of bombs.&lt;ref name=usaaf&gt;{{harvnb|Hammel|2009|pp=261, 265, 268, 281, 286, 291}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 19 March 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 152 [[Martin B-26 Marauder]]s of [[IX Bomber Command]] attacked V-weapon sites around Saint-Omer.&lt;ref name=usaaf/&gt;
|-
| 26 March 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 500 heavy bombers of the [[8th Air Force]] attacked a total of 16 V-weapon sites in northern France, including Wizernes, dropping 1,271 tons of bombs. Allied losses were four [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress]]es and one B-24; a further 236 bombers were damaged by enemy fire.&lt;ref name=usaaf/&gt;
|-
| 17 April 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 14 B-24 Liberators and five pathfinder aircraft used an experimental bombing technique to attack Wizernes.&lt;ref name=usaaf /&gt;
|-
| 25 April 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 27 B-24 Liberators from 2d Bombardment Division bombed Wizernes in a special test of new pathfinding equipment.&lt;ref name=usaaf/&gt;
|-
| 3 May 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] 47 B-24 Liberators escorted by 101 fighters from VIII Fighter Command attacked Wizernes using blind-bombing techniques.&lt;ref name=usaaf/&gt;
|-
| 20 June 1944
| [[Image:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 17 [[Avro Lancasters]] and 3 [[De Havilland Mosquito]] of No 617 Squadron attempted to attack Wizernes but were forced to abort by cloud cover over the target.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiaryJun44&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Royal Air Force Campaign Diary&amp;nbsp;– June 1944|url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/bombercommand/jun44.html|accessdate=19 June 2011|publisher=UK Crown}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 22 June 1944
| [[Image:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] A second 617 Squadron attack on Wizernes was again thwarted by cloud cover.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiaryJun44&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 24 June 1944
| [[Image:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 617 Squadron returned to Wizernes with 16 Lancasters and 2 Mosquitos, losing one Lancaster to anti-aircraft fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiaryJun44&quot; /&gt; Several Tallboy bombs were dropped but failed to cause much damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|p=43}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 28 June 1944
| [[Image:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 103 [[Handley Page Halifax]]es and 5 Mosquitos from [[No. 4 Group RAF|No. 4 Group]] and 2 Lancasters of the [[Pathfinder Force]] attacked Wizernes without loss.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiaryJun44&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 17 July 1944
| [[Image:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 72 Halifaxes, 28 [[Short Stirling|Stirlings]], 20 Lancasters, 11 Mosquitos and 1 [[North American P-51 Mustang|North American Mustang]] attacked three V-weapons sites including Wizernes, which was attacked with a dozen Tallboys.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiaryJul44&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Royal Air Force Campaign Diary&amp;nbsp;– July 1944|url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/bombercommand/jul44.html|accessdate=19 June 2011|publisher=UK Crown}}&lt;/ref&gt; The attack caused severe damage to the site and buried the entrances to the launch tunnels ''Gustav'' and ''Gretchen''. The site was abandoned a few weeks later.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaloga|2008|p=44}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 20 July 1944
| [[Image:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 174 Lancasters, 165 Halifaxes and 30 Mosquitos attacked V-1 launching sites and the Wizernes site.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiaryJul44&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 20/21 July 1944
| [[Image:RAF roundel.svg|12px]] 54 Halifaxes, 23 Lancasters and 10 Mosquitos attacked V-weapon sites at [[Ardouval]] and Wizernes, but no bombs were dropped at Wizernes due to bad weather.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiaryJul44&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 4 August 1944
| [[File:Eighth Air Force - Emblem (World War II).png|12px]] An experimental [[Operation Aphrodite]] attack using remotely controlled B-17 Flying Fortress drones packed with explosives failed when they overshot Wizernes by 2,000 feet.&lt;ref name=Dwiggins&gt;{{harvnb|Dwiggins|1965|p=112}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|}

==See also==
* [[Blockhaus d'Éperlecques]]
* [[Fortress of Mimoyecques]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=Notes}}

==References==
;Citations
{{reflist|30em}}
;Bibliography
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite book|last=Dungan|first=Tracy|title=V-2|year=2005|publisher=Westholme Publishing|location=Yardley, PA|isbn=1-59416-012-0|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Dwiggins|first=Don|editor1-first=Phil |editor1-last= Hirsch |editor2-first=Edward | editor2-last=Hymoff |title=The Kennedy Courage|url=http://www.orwelltoday.com/jfkbrother.shtml |year=1965 |publisher=Pyramid Publications, Inc|location=New York |oclc=2800703|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Hammel|first=Eric|title=Air War Europa: Chronology|publisher=Pacifica Military History|location=Pacifica, CA|year=2009|isbn=978-0-935553-07-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Henshall|first=Philip|title=Hitler's V-Weapon Sites|year=2002|publisher=Sutton Publishing Ltd|location=Stroud, Glos|isbn=0-7509-2607-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Hinsley|first1=Francis Harry|last2=Thomas|first2=Edward Eastaway|title=British intelligence in the Second World War: its influence on strategy and operations, Volume 3, Part 1|publisher=H.M. Stationery Office|location=London|year=1990|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Le Maner|first=Yves|title=War, Rockets, Memory: La Coupole|publisher=La Coupole Editions|location=Helfaut-Wizernes|year=1997|isbn=2-9514152-2-2|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Longmate|first=Norman|title=Hitler's Rockets|publisher=Frontline Books|location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire|year=2009|isbn=978-1-84832-546-3|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Ordway |first1=Frederick I. III|authorlink=Frederick I. Ordway III |last2=Sharpe|first2=Mitchell R. |year=1979 |title=The Rocket Team|series= Apogee Books Space Series 36 |publisher=Thomas Y. Crowell|location=New York|isbn=1-894959-00-0|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Piszkiewicz|first=Dennis|title=The Nazi Rocketeers: Dreams of Space and Crimes of War|publisher=Stackpole Books|location=Mechanicsburg, PA|year=2007|isbn=978-0-8117-3387-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Sanders|first=Terence R. B. |authorlink=Terence Sanders|year=1945|title=Investigation of the &quot;Heavy&quot; Crossbow Installations in Northern France. Report by the Sanders Mission to the Chairman of the Crossbow Committee|chapter=Wizernes|volume= III. Technical details|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Sandys|first=Duncan |authorlink=Duncan Sandys|date=19 March 1945|ref={{harvid|Sandys|1945}}|title=Report on 'Large' Crossbow Sites in Northern France|series=Memo C.O.S. (45) 177 (O)|work=Memorandum|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;}}
*{{cite book|last1=Seller|first1=Andre|last2=Neufeld|first2= Michael|title=A History of the Dora Camp|page=52|publisher=I.R. Dee|location=Chicago|year=2003|isbn=978-1-56663-511-0|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Zaloga|first=Steven J.|title=German V-Weapon Sites 1943–45|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford|year=2008|isbn=978-1-84603-247-9|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=V-2 Ballistic Missile 1942–52|last1=Zaloga|first1=Steven J.|last2=Calow|first2=Robert|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford|year=2003|isbn=978-1-84176-541-9|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Hautefeuille|first=Roland|title=Constructions spéciales : histoire de la construction par l'&quot;Organisation Todt&quot;, dans le Pas-de-Calais et la Cotentin, des neufs grands sites protégés pour le tir des V1, V2, V3, et la production d'oxygène liquide, (1943–1944) |year=1995|location=Paris| isbn=2-9500899-0-9 |edition=2 |language=French}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Coupole d'Helfaut|La Coupole}} 
* [http://www.lacoupole-france.com La Coupole] – museum website
* [http://www.v2rocket.com/start/deployment/wizernes.html V2ROCKET.COM Wizernes Bunker – La Coupole] – virtual tour
* {{fr}} [http://coupole-wizernes.e-monsite.com/pages/temoignages.html La Coupole d'Helfaut-Wizernes] - background information

{{V-weapons|state=collapsed}}
{{WWII Operation Crossbow|state=collapsed}}

{{featured article}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures in Pas-de-Calais]]
[[Category:Domes]]
[[Category:Museums established in 1997]]
[[Category:Museums in Pas-de-Calais]]
[[Category:Ruins in Hauts-de-France]]
[[Category:World War II in the Pas-de-Calais]]
[[Category:V-weapon subterranea]]
[[Category:World War II museums in France]]</text>
      <sha1>ks9lmdykocwdoci0laapfdsbcc38dhj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
