<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lady Saigō</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30268493</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737305605</id>
      <parentid>737301420</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-01T23:10:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CAPTAIN RAJU</username>
        <id>25523690</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/40.140.38.202|40.140.38.202]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34117">{{Infobox person
| honorific_prefix          =
| name                      = 西郷の局
| honorific_suffix          = Saigō-no-Tsubone
| image                     = Saigo-no-Tsubone2.JPG
| image_size                = 300
| alt                       = 
| caption                   = Portrait of Lady Saigō, Hōdai-in, [[Shizuoka, Shizuoka|Shizuoka]], Japan
| birth_name                = Tozuka Masako (戸塚昌子)
| birth_date                = 1552
| birth_place               = [[Nishikawa Castle]], [[Mikawa Province|Mikawa]], Japan
| death_date                = July 1, 1589 (aged ~37 years)
| death_place               = [[Sunpu Castle]], [[Suruga province|Suruga]], Japan
| death_cause = unknown
| resting_place             = Hōdai-in, [[Shizuoka, Shizuoka|Shizuoka city]]
| resting_place_coordinates = {{Coord|34.970102|138.383158|display=inline}}
| monuments                 = 
| residence                 = 
| known_for                 = 
| notable_works             = 
| religion                  = [[Buddhism]]
| partner                   = [[Tokugawa Ieyasu]]
| children                  = ''Sons'': Saigō Katsutada, [[Tokugawa Hidetada]], Matsudaira Tadayoshi &lt;br /&gt;
''Daughter'': Tokuhime
| parents                   = Tozuka Tadaharu and mother
| relatives                 = Saigō clan, [[Tokugawa clan]]
| box_width                 = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Lady Saigō'''|西郷の局{{lang|en| or }}西郷局|Saigō-no-Tsubone}} (1552&amp;nbsp;– 1 July 1589), also known as '''Oai''', was the first [[wikt:consort|consort]] and trusted confidante of [[Tokugawa Ieyasu]], the [[samurai]] lord who unified [[Japan]] at the end of the sixteenth century and then ruled as ''[[Shogun]]''. She was also the mother of the second Tokugawa shogun, [[Tokugawa Hidetada]].

During their relationship, Lady Saigō influenced Ieyasu's philosophies, choice of allies, and policies as he rose to power during the late [[Sengoku period]], and she thus had an indirect effect on the organization and composition of the [[Tokugawa shogunate]]. Although less is known of her than some other figures of the era, she is generally regarded as the &quot;power behind the throne&quot;, and her life has been compared to a &quot;[[Cinderella]] story&quot; of [[feudal Japan]].&lt;ref&gt;Mochida (2000–2013).&lt;/ref&gt; Her contributions were considered so significant that she was posthumously inducted to the Senior First Rank of the Imperial Court, the highest honor that could be conferred by the [[Emperor of Japan]].

Once she was in a respected and secure position as first consort and mother to Ieyasu's heir, Lady Saigō used her influence and wealth for charitable purposes. A devout Buddhist, she donated money to temples in [[Suruga Province]], where she resided as the consort of Ieyasu, first in [[Hamamatsu Castle]] and later in [[Sunpu Castle]]. As she was quite [[near-sighted]], she also established a charitable organization that assisted visually impaired women with no other means of support. Lady Saigō died at a fairly young age, under somewhat mysterious circumstances. Although murder was suspected, no culprit was identified.

Lady Saigō bore four children: she had a son and a daughter (Saigō Katsutada and Tokuhime) while married, and she later bore two sons as the consort of Tokugawa Ieyasu: Tokugawa Hidetada and Matsudaira Tadayoshi. Among the descendants of Lady Saigō was the [[Empress Meishō]] (1624–1696), one of very few women to accede to the [[Chrysanthemum Throne]] as [[empress regnant]].

==Name==
The term &quot;Saigō-no-Tsubone&quot;, used in most historical texts, is an official title rather than a name. As an adult she was adopted into the Saigō clan, so she was permitted to use the surname. Later, when she was named first consort of Tokugawa Ieyasu, the title &quot;tsubone&quot; (pronounced {{IPAc-ja|tsu|bo|ne}}) was appended to the surname. The title was one of several titular [[suffix]]es conferred on high-ranking women (others include ''-kata'' and ''-dono''). The bestowal of a title depended on social class and the relationship with her samurai lord, such as whether she was a legitimate wife or a concubine, and whether or not she had had children by him.&lt;ref name=downer&gt;[http://www.lesleydowner.com/journalism/secrets-of-the-shoguns-harem/ Downer (2008)].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hata (2008), pp. 172–190, pp. 175–8.&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''tsubone'' indicates the living quarters reserved for ladies of a court,&lt;ref name=griffis1588&gt;Griffis (1915), p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; and it became the title for those who had been granted private quarters, such as high-ranking concubines with children.&lt;ref name=downer/&gt; This title, ''tsubone'', was in use for concubines from the [[Heian Period]] until the [[Meiji Period]] (from the eighth century to the early twentieth century),&lt;ref name=griffis1588/&gt;&lt;ref name=akiyama&gt;Akiyama (1990)&lt;/ref&gt; and is commonly translated to the English title &quot;Lady&quot;.&lt;ref name=akiyama/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Murdoch (1996), p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Though Lady Saigō's [[given name]] does not appear in surviving documents from the time, there is good evidence it was Masako (昌子), but this name is very rarely used. Her most commonly used name was Oai (お愛 or 於愛, meaning &quot;love&quot;) and most sources agree this was a nickname she gained as a child.&lt;ref name=houdai&gt;Hōdai-in (2010).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=km392&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 392.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hyodo&gt;Hyodo ''et al.'' (2007), p. 546.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=naka1&gt;Nakashima (1999), p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nihon&gt;Nihon (2007), pp. 78–79.&lt;/ref&gt; Intimate friends and family would call her Oai throughout her life, and it is the name most often used in modern popular cultural references. Following death, she was bestowed with a Buddhist [[posthumous name]], and an abbreviation of that name, Hōdai-in (宝台院), is sometimes used out of pious respect.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;&lt;ref name=km392/&gt;

==Background==
The Saigō family was one branch of the distinguished [[Kikuchi clan]] of [[Kyushu]] that had migrated northward to [[Mikawa Province]] in the fifteenth&amp;nbsp;century. In 1524, the forces of [[Matsudaira Kiyoyasu]] (1511–1536), the grandfather of [[Tokugawa Ieyasu]], stormed and took the Saigō clan's headquarters at Yamanaka Castle during his conquest of the Mikawa region. Shortly after the battle, Saigō Nobusada, the third head of the Saigō, submitted to the [[Matsudaira clan]].&lt;ref name=km610&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 610.&lt;/ref&gt;  Following the untimely death of Kiyoyasu in 1536, and the ineffectual leadership and early death of [[Matsudaira Hirotada]] (1526–1549), the leaderless Matsudaira clan finally submitted to [[Imagawa Yoshimoto]] (1519–1560) of [[Suruga Province]], east of Mikawa. When the Matsudaira fell to the Imagawa, the clans of their retainers, which included the Saigō, likewise submitted to the Imagawa.&lt;ref name=km610/&gt;  Following the [[Battle of Okehazama]] (1560), Saigō Masakatsu attempted to re-assert the independence of the clan while yielding some land concessions to the Imagawa. In response, [[Imagawa Ujizane]] arrested thirteen Saigō men, and had them vertically [[impalement|impaled]] near [[Yoshida Castle]].&lt;ref name=km612&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 612.&lt;/ref&gt; The executions did not deter the Saigō, and in 1562 the Imagawa launched punitive invasions of east Mikawa and attacked the two main Saigō castles. Masakatsu was killed in the battle of Gohonmatsu Castle; his eldest son Motomasa was killed during the battle for Wachigaya Castle.&lt;ref name=km612/&gt; Clan leadership passed to Masakatsu's son, Saigō Kiyokazu (1533–1594), who pledged his loyalty to the Matsudaira clan, under the leadership of Tokugawa Ieyasu, in their mutual struggle against the Imagawa. In 1569, the power of the Imagawa ended with the [[Siege of Kakegawa|Siege of Kakegawa Castle]].&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zenkoku (2000), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt;

Neither the name of Lady Saigō's mother nor her dates of birth or death are recorded in any existing documents, although it is known that she was the elder sister of Saigō Kiyokazu.&lt;ref name=km394&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 394.&lt;/ref&gt; Lady Saigō's father was Tozuka Tadaharu of [[Tōtōmi Province]], under direct control of the Imagawa clan. The marriage between Tadaharu and his wife was very likely arranged by the Imagawa clan.&lt;ref name=km392/&gt;

==Biography==

===Early life===
Lady Saigō was born in 1552 at [[Nishikawa Castle]], a branch castle of the Saigō clan,&lt;ref&gt;Aichi (1998), p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; and very likely given the name of Masako soon after birth.&lt;ref name=hyodo/&gt;&lt;ref name=km612/&gt;  Japanese marriages are not usually [[matrilocal]],&lt;ref&gt;Ueno (2009), pp. 199–201.&lt;/ref&gt; but Tadaharu may have been assigned to Nishikawa Castle as an agent of the Imagawa.  Masako spent her childhood with her two siblings in [[bucolic]] eastern Mikawa Province, and at some point gained the nickname Oai.  In 1554, her father Tadaharu died in the Battle of Enshu-Omori, between the Imagawa and the [[Late Hōjō clan|Hōjō clan]].&lt;ref name=km399&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 399.&lt;/ref&gt;  Two years later her mother married Hattori Masanao; the union resulted in four children, though only two survived to adulthood.&lt;ref name=km393&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p .393.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=km395&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 395.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some sources state that upon reaching &quot;adulthood&quot; Oai married,{{ref|a|Note a}} but was widowed soon afterward.&lt;ref name=hyodo/&gt;&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt;  The husband's name is not mentioned and there were apparently no children.  Other sources do not mention the marriage, or suggest that there never was an earlier &quot;first&quot; marriage.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;&lt;ref name=km393/&gt;  It is known with certainty that in 1567, Oai married Saigō Yoshikatsu, her cousin and the son of Motomasa, who had already had two children by his late wife.&lt;ref name=km393/&gt;&lt;ref name=km395/&gt;&lt;ref name=km398&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 398.&lt;/ref&gt;  Oai bore two children by Yoshikatsu: their son, Saigō Katsutada, was born about 1570; they also had a daughter, possibly named Tokuhime.{{ref|b|Note b}}&lt;ref name=km398/&gt;&lt;ref name=km373&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 373.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nakashima (1999), p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1571, Saigō Yoshikatsu was killed at the Battle of Takehiro, fighting the invading forces of the [[Takeda clan]] led by [[Akiyama Nobutomo]].&lt;ref&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 372.&lt;/ref&gt;  Soon after Yoshikatsu's death, Oai was formally adopted by her uncle, Saigō Kiyokazu, then the head of the Saigō clan, though she chose to live with her mother in the house of her stepfather.&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt;&lt;ref name=km393/&gt;

===Tokugawa Ieyasu===
[[File:Tokugawa Ieyasu2.JPG|thumb|[[Tokugawa Ieyasu]]]]
Oai first met Tokugawa Ieyasu at about the age of 17 or 18, when he visited the Saigō family and Oai served him tea.&lt;ref name=naka2&gt;Nakashima (1999), p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt;  It is believed she caught his eye on that occasion, but as she was still married, nothing came of it at the time.  Later, during the 1570s, it is believed that friendship and genuine affection developed between the two.&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt;  This view contradicts a common impression which maintains that Ieyasu was a ruthless leader who treated all the women in his life, and all of his offspring, as commodities to be used as needed to serve the clan or his own ambitions.&lt;ref name=sadler284&gt;Sadler (1937), p. 284.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, it is also known that he valued personal merit over bloodlines.  During this time, Ieyasu had a house built in eastern [[Mikawa province|Mikawa]], far from the residence of his wife, the [[Lady Tsukiyama]], in [[Okazaki, Aichi|Okazaki]].&lt;ref name=km400&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 400.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;  The marriage between Ieyasu and Lady Tsukiyama had been arranged by her uncle, Imagawa Yoshimoto, ostensibly to help cement ties between the two clans, though Ieyasu found it difficult to live with his wife's jealousy, tempestuous moods, and eccentric habits.&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), pp. 75, 92.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Totman (1983), p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting around the time of the [[Battle of Mikatagahara]] (1573), perhaps in its aftermath, Ieyasu began to confide in Oai and sought her counsel on various matters.  It may have been during this period that the two commenced an amorous relationship.  Oai is credited with advising Ieyasu as the [[Battle of Nagashino]] (1575) approached, a major turning point in both Ieyasu's career and the history of Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt;  It is also thought that Ieyasu continued to seek her advice concerning other battles and alliances, even as late as the [[Battle of Komaki and Nagakute|Komaki-Nagakute Campaign]] (1584).&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;

In the spring of 1578, Oai moved to [[Hamamatsu Castle]], where she took over management of the kitchen. She became very popular with the unit of warriors from her native province, who not only admired her beauty, but regarded her as a gentle and virtuous example of the women of Mikawa.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;  While her manners and gentility were exemplary, she could, when the occasion warranted, be outspoken or sarcastic in speech, the probable result of growing up around rustic warriors in a remote castle outpost.&lt;ref name=km392/&gt;  With her move to the court of Ieyasu, Oai entered a bitter arena where prospective concubines schemed and competed with each other for a chance to bear Ieyasu's child.&lt;ref name=nihon/&gt;&lt;ref name=naka2/&gt;  Bearing the child of a powerful samurai, especially a son, was one way an ambitious young woman of the period could elevate her status, ensure a comfortable life, and guarantee the prosperity of her family.&lt;ref name=downer/&gt;&lt;ref name=beard&gt;Beard (1953), p.4 8.&lt;/ref&gt;  These women usually relied on their physical attributes and sexual prowess to keep their lord's attention, and some resorted to the use of aphrodisiacs.&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt;  Unlike these courtesans, Oai already had the attention of Ieyasu, which would have undermined the ambitions of some and very likely made her a target of resentment, hostility, and the intrigues that were common in Japanese harems.&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt;&lt;ref name=beard/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Levy (1971), p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Hidetada.jpg|thumb|right|[[Tokugawa Hidetada]], son of Ieyasu and Lady Saigō]]
While Ieyasu's marriage was arranged for political reasons, and many of his later concubines were chosen in the same spirit, it is thought that he chose his relationship with Lady Saigō.&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt;  Despite the image of Ieyasu as a calculating and stoic warlord,&lt;ref name=sadler284/&gt; there was no new political advantage to the match, as the Saigō were already loyal vassals,&lt;ref name=km610/&gt; and thus texts about Lady Saigō refer to her as the &quot;most beloved&quot; of Ieyasu's women.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;&lt;ref name=km392/&gt;&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt; Moreover, Ieyasu valued her for her intelligence and sound advice and it is believed that he enjoyed her company and calm demeanor as well as their common background in Mikawa province.&lt;ref name=naka1/&gt; On May&amp;nbsp;2, 1579, Oai gave birth to Ieyasu's third son, who would become known as [[Tokugawa Hidetada]].  The news was probably a shock to all who had an interest in Ieyasu, but with the event, Oai's position became more secure and she was accepted as the first consort of Ieyasu.&lt;ref name=km392/&gt;&lt;ref name=naka2/&gt;  Based on this relationship, and out of respect for her gentle manner and devotion to Ieyasu, she became known by the respectful title of ''Saigō-no-Tsubone'', or Lady Saigō.&lt;ref name=km392/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 614.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same year, Oda Nobunaga was informed that Lady Tsukiyama had conspired against him with the Takeda clan.  Although evidence was weak, Ieyasu re-assured his ally by having his wife executed by the shore of Lake Sanaru in Hamamatsu.&lt;ref name=naka2/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Tokugawa Nobuyasu]], Ieyasu's first son by Lady Tsukiyama, was held in confinement until Ieyasu ordered him to commit ''[[seppuku]]''.  With their deaths, Lady Saigō's position at court was unassailable.  With the death of Nobuyasu, Hidetada became Ieyasu's heir apparent.{{ref|c|Note c}}&lt;ref&gt;Griffis (1883), p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ieyasu's fourth son, the second by Lady Saigō, was born on October&amp;nbsp;18, 1580.  He would become known as Matsudaira Tadayoshi, after he was adopted by [[Matsudaira Ietada (Fukōzu)|Matsudaira Ietada]], the head of the [[Matsudaira clan#Branches of the Matsudaira clan|Fukōzu branch]] of the [[Matsudaira clan]].&lt;ref&gt;Totman (1983), p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the same year, Lady Saigō had a temple founded in her mother's memory, indicating she had died by that point.&lt;ref name=km400/&gt;  In 1586, Lady Saigō was at the side of Ieyasu when he entered the newly reconstructed [[Sunpu Castle]] in triumph.  This was a highly symbolic celebration of his victories over his enemies and the subjugation of the region, but it was also a visible and symbolic gesture to Lady Saigō, a way that Ieyasu could credit her for her assistance, and publicly demonstrate the esteem in which he regarded her.&lt;ref name=km400/&gt;

===Charity===
While at Sunpu Castle, Lady Saigō worshipped at a [[Buddhist temples in Japan|Buddhist temple]] called Ryusen-ji.  She became devoted to the teachings of the [[Jōdo shū|Pure Land sect]] and was known for her piety and charity.&lt;ref name=km400/&gt;  Because she suffered a high degree of [[myopia]], she often donated money, clothing, food, and other necessities to blind women and organizations that assisted them.&lt;ref name=km401/&gt;  She eventually founded a co-operative school with living quarters near Ryusen-ji that assisted indigent blind women by teaching them how to play the ''[[shamisen]]'' (traditional stringed instrument) as a vocation, and helped them to find employment.  These women were known as ''[[goze]]'', and were akin to traveling [[minstrel]]s in Edo period Japan.&lt;ref name=fri&gt;Fritsch (2002).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gro&gt;Groemer (2001).&lt;/ref&gt;  The women were granted membership to the [[guild]]-like organization, and musicians with apprentices were dispatched to various destinations.  They played pieces from a sanctioned [[repertoire]], and operated under a strict code of rules on behavior and permissible business transactions intended to maintain an upstanding reputation.&lt;ref name=fri/&gt;&lt;ref name=gro/&gt;  On her deathbed, Lady Saigō wrote a letter pleading for the continued maintenance of the organization.&lt;ref name=km402&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p.402.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death===
[[File:Saigo-no-Tsubone-grave.JPG|thumb|Grave of Lady Saigō]]
Within a short time after taking up residence in Sunpu Castle, Lady Saigō's health began to deteriorate.  It was said that &quot;physical and emotional hardships&quot; were taking their toll on her health, but nothing could be done to help her.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt; Lady Saigō died on July&amp;nbsp;1, 1589, at the age of 37.&lt;ref name=km400/&gt; The cause of her early death was never determined, and while murder was suspected at the time, no culprit was identified.&lt;!--were there other suspicious circumstances? clues?--&gt;  There were later rumors that she was poisoned by a maidservant devoted to Ieyasu's late wife, the Lady Tsukiyama.&lt;ref&gt;Nakashima (1999), p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time of her death, Lady Saigō was treated as Ieyasu's wife in deed if not in word.&lt;ref&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 411.&lt;/ref&gt;  The remains of Lady Saigō were interred at Ryusen-ji.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;  At her death, a number of blind women reportedly gathered in front of the temple and prayed.&lt;ref&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 408.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Tokugawa Ieyasu continued his campaigns allied with [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]].  After their victory at the [[Siege of Odawara (1590)|Siege of Odawara Castle]] in 1590, Ieyasu agreed to relinquish all of his domains to Hideyoshi in exchange for the [[Kantō region]] to the east.&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;  Hideyoshi died in 1598. By 1603, Ieyasu had recovered Sunpu Castle and completed his unification of Japan, and had been named ''shogun'' by the Emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Titsingh (1834), pp.  405, 409.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), pp. 226–7.&lt;/ref&gt;  The following year, he had Ryusen-ji moved from Yunoki to Koyamachi{{ref|d|Note d}} near Sunpu Castle and attended Buddhist funeral rites conducted in honor of the late Lady Saigō on the anniversary of her death.  To mark the occasion, Ieyasu presented the temple priests with the ''[[katana]]'' he inherited from his father, and a portrait of himself as he looked at the time.  These items can still be viewed at the temple in [[Shizuoka, Shizuoka|Shizuoka city]].&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;

In 1628, Tokugawa Hidetada, by then the retired second ''shogun'', attended ceremonies conducted in honor of his late mother on the anniversary of her death.&lt;ref name=km401&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 401.&lt;/ref&gt;  These ceremonies were meant to help her spirit achieve [[Buddhahood|buddha status]].  He also saw to it that she was made the honored [[Tutelary deity|tutelary patron]] of the temple by having her posthumous name changed and the first three characters appended to the name of the temple.  Today, the temple Ryusen-ji is known mainly by that appellation, Hōdai-in (宝台院).&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;  At the same time, the [[Emperor Go-Mizunoo]] conferred the name Minamoto Masako (源 晶子) upon Lady Saigō, in effect posthumously adopting her into the [[Minamoto clan]], the extended family of the Imperial line.&lt;ref name=ito&gt;Ito (2003), p. 445.&lt;/ref&gt;  The new name was then inducted into the Lower First Rank of the Imperial Court.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;&lt;ref name=km401/&gt;  Her status was later upgraded to Senior First Rank, the highest and most prominent award, then or now, bestowed by the Emperor to a few subjects outside the Imperial family who had significantly and positively affected the history of Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Kobayashi and Makino (1994), p. 617.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1938, the mausoleum of Lady Saigō at Hōdai-in, which consisted of a [[Gorintō|five-tiered stupa]] over her grave and a sanctuary for the veneration of her spirit, was designated an [[Important Cultural Property (Japan)|Important Cultural Property]].  The designation was rescinded after the entire temple complex was destroyed in the Great Shizuoka Fire on January&amp;nbsp;15, 1940.&lt;ref name=ito/&gt;  The stupa remains, though evidence of the damage suffered when it toppled over is plainly visible.  Many of the treasures of the temple, including a portrait of Lady Saigō and the sword and portrait bequeathed by Tokugawa Ieyasu in 1604, were saved by the priests who flung the objects out of windows and doorways before fleeing the burning temple.  The temple was rebuilt using steel-reinforced concrete in 1970.  Historical artifacts saved from the fire of 1940 are on display at the new Hōdai-in temple in Shizuoka city.&lt;ref name=houdai/&gt;

==Notable descendants==
Lady Saigō was the ancestral mother to the line of ''shoguns'' that began with the second [[Edo period]] ''shogun'', Tokugawa Hidetada, and ended with the seventh, [[Tokugawa Ietsugu]] (1709–1716).&lt;ref&gt;Screech (2006), pp. 97–98.&lt;/ref&gt;  Aside from this, Lady Saigō also became connected to the Imperial line.  In 1620, Hidetada's daughter, [[Tokugawa Masako]] (1607–1678), married Emperor Go-Mizunoo and entered the Imperial palace.&lt;ref&gt;Ponsonby-Fane (1959), pp. 113–4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Titsingh (1834), p. 410.&lt;/ref&gt;  As [[empress consort]], Masako helped maintain the Imperial Court, supported the arts, and significantly influenced the next three monarchs: the first was her daughter, and the two that followed, [[Emperor Go-Kōmyō|Emperors Go-Kōmyō]] and [[Emperor Go-Sai|Go-Sai]], were sons of Emperor Go-Mizunoo by different concubines.&lt;ref&gt;Ponsonby-Fane (1959), pp. 115–6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lillehoj (1996).&lt;/ref&gt;  The daughter of Masako, and thus great-granddaughter of Lady Saigō, was Princess Okiko (1624–1696),&lt;ref&gt;Ponsonby-Fane (1959), p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; who acceded to the [[Chrysanthemum Throne]] in 1629 as [[Empress Meishō]].&lt;ref&gt;Frederic and Roth (2002), pp. 256–7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Titsingh (1834), p. 411.&lt;/ref&gt;  She reigned for fifteen years as the 109th&amp;nbsp;monarch of Japan, the seventh of only eight [[empress regnant|empresses regnant]] in the history of Japan, until she abdicated in 1643.&lt;ref&gt;Titsingh (1834), pp. 411–2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Imperial Household Agency (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Azuchi–Momoyama period]]

==Notes==
:a.{{note|a}} For women of [[feudal Japan]], &quot;adulthood&quot; was attained at an individual's ''[[genpuku]]'' ceremony, held sometime between the ages of 13 and 15.  Upon reaching the state of adulthood, the young woman shaved her eyebrows for the first time, colored her teeth black, and was considered eligible for marriage.&lt;ref&gt;Bryant (1994), pp. 10–11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lin (2002), p. 403.&lt;/ref&gt;
:b.{{note|b}} Oai's daughter Tokuhime should not to be confused with either [[Toku-hime]], daughter of Ieyasu and Lady Nishigori, or [[Tokuhime]], daughter of Oda Nobunaga.
:c.{{note|c}} Ieyasu's [[Yūki Hideyasu|second son]] was born in 1574 by his wife's [[lady-in-waiting]]; he was shunned by his father and later given in adoption to [[Hashiba Hideyoshi|an ally]].&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (1937), p. 333.&lt;/ref&gt;
:d.{{note|d}} Both Yunoki and Koyamachi are now part of [[Aoi-ku, Shizuoka|Aoi Ward]], [[Shizuoka, Shizuoka|Shizuoka City]].

==References==
{{reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{Cite book |author= Aichi Board of Education |title= 愛知県中世城館跡調査報告 | language=Japanese |trans_title= Survey Report of Castle Hall Sites from the Medieval Period of Aichi Prefecture| volume =Volume 3: East Mikawa Region | year= 1998 |publisher= Association for the Diffusion of Books and Maps of Cultural Assets |place=[[Nagoya]], [[Japan]] }}
* {{Cite book|last=Akiyama |first= Terukazu|chapter= Women Painters at the Heian Court |title= Flowering in the Shadows: Women in the History of Chinese and Japanese Painting| editor= Marsha Weider|year= 1990|publisher= University of Hawaii Press|place=[[Honolulu]], [[Hawaii]]|pages=159–184 |isbn= 978-0-8248-1149-5|others= Meribeth Graybill}}
* {{Cite book|last=Beard|first= Mary Ritter |title= The Force of Women in Japanese History |year= 1953| publisher= Public Affairs Press |place= [[Washington, D.C.]]|isbn= 978-0-8183-0167-4 }}
* {{Cite book |last= Bryant|first = Anthony J. |authorlink=Anthony J. Bryant|title= Samurai 1550–1600 |publisher =Osprey Publishing |place= Oxford |isbn= 978-1-85532-345-2}}
* {{Cite web|last= Downer|first = Lesley|title= Secrets of the Shogun's Harem|url= http://www.lesleydowner.com/journalism/secrets-of-the-shoguns-harem/ |year=2008|accessdate= 16 December 2012}}
* {{Cite book|last= Frederic |first= Louis |title= Japan Encyclopedia |year= 2002| publisher= Harvard University Press |place= Cambridge, USA |isbn= 978-0-674-01753-5|others= Kathe Roth}}
* {{Cite journal|last= Fritsch |first= Ingrid |title= Blind Female Musicians on the Road: The Social Organization of ''Goze'' in Japan |journal= CHIME Journal |year= 1992 |volume= 5 |issue=Spring |issn = 0926-7263|pages= 58–64 }}
* {{Cite book |last= Griffis |first= William |title= The Mikado's Empire |volume= Volume I |year= 1883 |publisher= Harper &amp; Brothers |place=New York}}
* {{Cite book |last= Griffis |first= William |title= The Mikado: Institution and Person |url= https://books.google.com/?id=w_kbAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA88&amp;dq=tsubone+concubine#v=onepage&amp;q=tsubone%20concubine&amp;f=false |year= 1915 |publisher= Princeton University Press |place=Princeton, New Jersey|isbn= 978-1-279-41346-3}}
* {{Cite journal|last= Groemer |first=Gerald |title= The Guild of the Blind in Tokugawa Japan |journal= Monumenta Nipponica |year=2001 |volume= 56 |issue= 3 |pages= 349–80|doi= 10.2307/3096791 }}
* {{Cite book|last= Hata |first=Hisako |title= Servants of the Dynasty: Palace Women in World History|editor= Anne Walthall|  chapter= 9: Servants of the Inner Quarters: The Women of the Shogun's Great Interior |publisher= University of California Press|place =Berkeley and Los Angeles, California |isbn= 978-0-520-25443-5| pages= 172–190 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=QXHbhsfaJAYC&amp;pg=PA173&amp;dq=Life+in+the+Women%E2%80%99s+Palace+of+Edo+Castle#v=onepage&amp;q=Life%20in%20the%20Women%E2%80%99s%20Palace%20of%20Edo%20Castle&amp;f=false|date= 2008-06-23}}
* {{Cite web|author= Hōdai-in |title= 宝台院の由来|language=Japanese |trans_title=History of Hōdai-in |year=2010 |url= http://www.houdaiin.jp/history.html |work= Hōdai-in: Konpei-san, Jodo sect | accessdate= 1 January 2011 }}
* {{Cite book |editor1-first= Masao |editor1-last= Hyodo |editor2-last= Fujii |editor2-first=Takashi| editor3-last= Fujita |editor3-first= Shizuyo |editor4-last= Yoshikawa |editor4-first= Toshiaki |title= 豊橋百科事典 |trans_title= Toyohashi Encyclopedia |edition= |series= |volume= |date= |year= 2007 |month= |origyear= |publisher= Toyohashi City Department of Citizens' Culture, Culture Section |location= [[Toyohashi]], Japan |language= Japanese |isbn= |page=  }}
* {{Cite web|last= Imperial Household Agency |title=明正天皇　月輪陵 |language=Japanese |trans_title= Empress Meisho, Tsukinowanomisasagi |work= 天皇陵 [The Imperial Tombs] |url= http://www.kunaicho.go.jp/ryobo/guide/109/index.html |publisher= Imperial Household Agency| year=2004 |accessdate= 7 May 2011}}
* {{Cite book |last= Ito |first= Mitsuyoshi |title=  戦災等による焼先文化財 |language= Japanese |trans_title= List of Registered Important Cultural Properties which were Removed from the Official File because of Damage caused by Fires and Other Causes |year=2003 |publisher= Ebisu-Kosoyo Publication Co., Ltd | place= [[Tokyo]] }}
* {{Cite book |last1= Kobayashi |first1=Sadayoshi |last2= Makino |first2 =Noboru |title= 西郷氏興亡全史 |language=Japanese |trans_title= Complete History of the Rise and Fall of the Saigō Clan |year=1994 |publisher= Rekishi Chosakenkyu-jo |place=Tokyo }}
* {{Cite book|last = Levy|first= Howard Seymour|title= Sex, Love, and the Japanese |year=1971|publisher=Warm-Soft Village Press |place=Tokyo}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Lillehoj |first= Elizabeth |title= Tōfukumon'in: Empress, Patron and Artist |journal= Women's Art Journal |volume= 17 |year=1996 |pages= 28–34 |doi=10.2307/1358526 }}
* {{Cite journal|last= Lin|first= Irene H. |title= The Ideology of Imagination: The Tale of Shuten Dōji as a ''Kenmon'' Discourse |url= http://www.persee.fr/web/revues/home/prescript/article/asie_0766-1177_2002_num_13_1_1188?_Prescripts_Search_tabs1=standard&amp;| journal = L'Cahiers d'Extrěme-Asie |pages= 379–410 |year= 2002 |volume = 13 |issue= 13|doi= 10.3406/asie.2002.1188}}
* {{Cite web|last= Mochida |first= Shinzaemon| work= よろパラ 文学歴史の10 |year= 2000–2013| title= 日本史人物列伝: 西郷局(お愛の方) |trans_title= Series of Biographies on Japanese Historical Figures |language= Japanese |url= http://www5b.biglobe.ne.jp/~yoropara/retuden/retu00305.htm | accessdate= 19 January 2013}}
* {{Cite book |last= Murdoch |first= James |title=  A History of Japan |volume=Volume III |year= 1996 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=32HnwxdP4pMC&amp;dq=Kasuga+no+Tsubone |place= London  |publisher=Routledge |isbn = 978-0-415-15417-8 }}
* {{Cite book|last= Nakashima |first= Michiko |title= 徳川三代と女房たち |language= Japanese |trans_title= Three Generations of the Tokugawa and their Women |year=1999 | publisher= Ritsubu |place= [[Kyoto]], Japan }}
* {{Cite book |editor= Nihon Hakugaku Kurabu |title= 大奥のすべてがわかる本: 知られざる徳川250年の裏面史 |trans_title= Book about the Great Interior: Understanding the Tokugawa through 250 Years of Hidden Historical Background |year= 2007 |publisher= PHP Research Institute |place=Kyoto |isbn= 978-4-569-69475-7 }}
* {{Cite book|last= Ponsonby-Fane |first= Richard Arthur Brabazon |authorlink=Richard Ponsonby-Fane| title= The Imperial House of Japan |year= 1959 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=SLAeAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=The+Imperial+House+of+Japan&amp;dq=The+Imperial+House+of+Japan  |place=Kyoto |publisher= Ponsonby Memorial Society }}
* {{Cite book |last = Sadler | first= A.L. | title= The Maker of Modern Japan: The Life of Shogun Tokugawa Ieyasu | year= 1937 |place= London | publisher= George Allen and Unwin, Ltd |isbn=978-0-8048-1297-9}}
* {{Cite book|last= Screech |first= Timon |authorlink=Timon Screech |title=Secret Memoirs of the Shoguns:  Isaac Titsingh and Japan, 1779–1822 |year=2006|place= London |publisher= RoutledgeCurzon |isbn= 978-0-7007-1720-0 }}
* {{Cite book |last= Titsingh |first= Isaac |title= Annales des empereurs du Japon |year = 1834 | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=18oNAAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=nipon+o+dai+itsi+ran |place= Paris |publisher= Oriental Translation Fund of Great Britain and Ireland }}
* {{Cite book |last=Totman| first=Conrad |title= Tokugawa Ieyasu: Shogun |year=1983 |publisher= Heian International, Inc |place= [[San Francisco]] |isbn= 978-0-89346-210-9 }}
* {{Cite book|last= Ueno |first= Chizuko |title= The Modern Family in Japan: Its Rise and Fall |year=2009 |publisher=Trans Pacific Press|place=[[Balwyn North, Victoria|Balwyn North]], [[Australia]] |isbn=978-1-876843-62-5}}
* {{Cite book|editor= Zenkoku Rekishi Kyoiku Kenkyu Kyogitai |title= 日本史用語集 |trans_title= Glossary of Japanese History |volume=Volume B |publisher= Yamagawa Publishers |place= Tokyo}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://members2.jcom.home.ne.jp/sengokubusyou/takaie1.htm 隆家流藤原氏 (Takaiie branch, Fujiwara clan)], with [[genealogy]] of the main line of the Mikawa-Saigo family.

{{People of the Sengoku period|state=autocollapse}}

{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Saigo-No-Tsubone}}
[[Category:1552 births]]
[[Category:1589 deaths]]
[[Category:16th-century Japanese people]]
[[Category:Concubines]]
[[Category:Japanese nobility]]
[[Category:Japanese women]]
[[Category:People of Azuchi–Momoyama-period Japan]]
[[Category:People of Sengoku-period Japan]]
[[Category:Samurai]]
[[Category:Tokugawa clan]]
[[Category:16th-century women]]
[[Category:Women of medieval Japan]]</text>
      <sha1>cwszzylo39gnxwhvauy0fc1i671m0uu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
