<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Leningrad première of Shostakovich's Symphony No. 7</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37854530</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717713994</id>
      <parentid>716643711</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-29T09:00:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>P0mbal</username>
        <id>5151728</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>all Kuibyshev - &gt; Kuybyshev, see article on Samara</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23896">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2015}}
{{featured article}}
[[File:Dmitri Shostakovich credit Deutsche Fotothek adjusted.jpg|thumb|upright|220px|Dmitri Shostakovich in 1950.]]
The '''Leningrad première of Shostakovich's Symphony No. 7''' occurred on 9 August 1942 during the [[World War II|Second World War]], while the city of [[Saint Petersburg|Leningrad]] (now St. Petersburg) was [[Siege of Leningrad|under siege]] by [[Nazi Germany|Nazi German]] forces.

[[Dmitri Shostakovich]] had intended for the piece to be premièred by the Leningrad Philharmonic Orchestra, but because of the siege that group was evacuated from the city, as was the composer himself. The world première of the symphony was held in [[Samara, Russia|Kuybyshev]] with the [[Bolshoi Theatre|Bolshoi Theatre Orchestra]]. The Leningrad première was performed by the surviving musicians of the [[Leningrad Radio Orchestra]], supplemented with military performers. Most of the musicians were starving, which made rehearsing difficult: musicians frequently collapsed during rehearsals, and three died. The orchestra was able to play the symphony all the way through only once before the concert.

Despite the poor condition of the performers and many of the audience members, the concert was highly successful, prompting an hour-long ovation. The concert was supported by a Soviet military offensive, code-named Squall, intended to silence German forces during the performance. The symphony was broadcast to the German lines by loudspeaker as a form of [[psychological warfare]]. The Leningrad première was considered by music critics to be one of the most important artistic performances of the war because of its psychological and political effects. The conductor concluded that &quot;in that moment, we triumphed over the soulless Nazi war machine&quot;.{{sfn|Jones|2008|p=261}} Reunion concerts featuring surviving musicians were convened in 1964 and 1992 to commemorate the event.

==Background==
[[File:RIAN archive 216 The Volkovo cemetery.jpg|thumb|The siege caused mass casualties via cold and starvation.]]
Soviet composer [[Dmitri Shostakovich]] (1906–75) completed his [[Symphony No. 7 (Shostakovich)|Symphony No. 7]] on 27 December 1941 and dedicated it to his native [[Saint Petersburg|Leningrad]]. At the time Leningrad was [[Siege of Leningrad|under a 900-day siege]] by [[Nazi Germany|Nazi German]] forces, which would kill about a third of the city's pre-war population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/january/27/newsid_3498000/3498330.stm|accessdate=13 December 2012|publisher=BBC|title=1944: Leningrad siege ends after 900 days|year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shostakovich wanted the [[Saint Petersburg Philharmonic Orchestra|Leningrad Philharmonic Orchestra]] to première the symphony, but that group had been evacuated to [[Novosibirsk]] as part of the government-led cultural exodus.&lt;ref name=lso&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shostakovich.com/may2002.html|accessdate=13 December 2012|date=May 2002|title=Programme notes: Saturday 18th May 2002|publisher=London Shostakovich Orchestra}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, the world première was held in [[Samara, Russia|Kuybyshev]] on 5 March 1942, performed by the [[Bolshoi Theatre|Bolshoi Theatre Orchestra]] under conductor [[Samuil Samosud]].&lt;ref name=lso/&gt; The Moscow première was given by a combination of the Bolshoi and the [[Tchaikovsky Symphony Orchestra of Moscow Radio|All-Union Radio]] orchestras on 29 March in the [[House of the Unions|Columned Hall of the House of Unions]].{{sfn|Fay|1989|p=131}}{{sfn|Robinson|1995|p=69}}

The microfilmed score of the symphony was flown to Tehran in April to allow its promulgation to the West.{{sfn|Fay|1989|p=132}} It received its radio première in Western Europe on 22 June, in a performance broadcast by [[Henry Wood]] and the [[London Philharmonic Orchestra]], and its concert première at a [[The Proms|Promenade]] concert at London's [[Royal Albert Hall]] on 29 June.&lt;ref name=lso/&gt; The North American première was broadcast from New York City on 19 July 1942 by the [[NBC Symphony Orchestra]] under [[Arturo Toscanini]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=Chicago Tribune|title=Shostakovich: Symphonies Nos. 1, 5 and 7|author=von Rein, John|date=31 October 1993|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1993-10-31/entertainment/9310310264_1_leopold-stokowski-toscanini-symphonies-nos|accessdate=14 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Preparation==
The Leningrad Radio Orchestra under [[Karl Eliasberg]] was the only remaining symphonic ensemble in Leningrad after the Philharmonic was evacuated.{{sfn|Ford|2011|p=103}} The Radio Orchestra's last performance had taken place on 14 December 1941 and its final broadcast on 1 January 1942.{{sfn|Reid|2011|pages=360&amp;ndash;361}} A log note from the next scheduled rehearsal reads &quot;Rehearsal did not take place. Srabian is dead. Petrov is sick. Borishev is dead. Orchestra not working&quot;.&lt;ref name=ed1/&gt;

On 2 April 1942, Boris Zagorsky and Yasha Babushkin of the Leningrad city arts department announced preparations for the symphony's performance.&lt;ref name=ed2&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Guardian|title=Orchestral manoeuvres (part 2)|author=Vulliamy, Ed|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/theobserver/2001/nov/25/features.magazine57|accessdate=13 December 2012|date=25 November 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; The hiatus in musical broadcasts was quickly ended by [[Andrei Zhdanov]], a Soviet politician involved in the defence of Leningrad, to allow for rehearsals and provide a morale boost for the city.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt; Performing the symphony &quot;became a matter of civic, even military, pride&quot;.{{sfn|Fay|1989|p=133}} According to an orchestra member, &quot;the Leningrad authorities wanted to give the people some emotional stimulation so that they could feel cared for&quot;.&lt;ref name=galina&gt;{{cite journal|journal=The St. Petersburg Times|author=Stolyarova, Galina|date=23 January 2004|volume=937|issue=5|title=Music played on as artists died|url=http://sptimes.ru/index.php?action_id=2&amp;story_id=12054|accessdate=15 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was considered an important political act because of its potential value as propaganda.{{sfn|Volkov|1997|p=440}}

Of the original 40-member Leningrad Radio Orchestra, only 14 or 15 still lived in the city; the others had either starved to death or left to fight the enemy.{{sfn|Sollertinsky|1980|p=107}}&lt;ref name=bath&gt;{{cite news|work=The Observer|title=''The Conductor'' by Sarah Quigley &amp;ndash; review|author=Bathurst, Bella|date=15 July 2012|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2012/jul/15/conductor-sarah-quigley-review|accessdate=18 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tum&gt;{{cite news|work=Glasgow Herald|date=7 October 2009|page=16|title=The musical monster that defied Nazi invaders|author=Tumelty, Michael}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shostakovich's symphony required an expanded orchestra of 100 players, meaning the remaining personnel were grossly insufficient.&lt;ref name=tum/&gt; Eliasberg, at the time being treated for &quot;dystrophy&quot;,{{sfn|Salisbury|2003|p=512}} went door to door to seek out those musicians who had not responded to the orchestra's reassembly due to starvation or weakness.{{sfn|Reid|2011|pages=360&amp;ndash;361}} &quot;My God, how thin many of them were,&quot; one of the organizers remembered. &quot;How those people livened up when we started to ferret them out of their dark apartments. We were moved to tears when they brought out their concert clothes, their violins and cellos and flutes, and rehearsals began under the icy canopy of the studio.&quot;{{sfn|Sollertinsky|1980|p=108}} A plane carrying supplies from Kuybyshev airlifted the symphony's 252-page conductor's score into Leningrad.&lt;ref name=mhq&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Quarterly Journal of Military History|volume=17|issue=3|date=Spring 2005|author=Trudeau, Noah Andre|title=A Symphony of War|pages=24&amp;ndash;31}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Lincoln|2009|p=293}}

The first rehearsal in March 1942 was intended to be three hours long, but had to be stopped after 15 minutes because the 30 musicians present were too weak to play their instruments.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;{{sfn|Salisbury|2003|p=512}} They frequently collapsed during rehearsals, especially those playing [[brass instrument]]s.&lt;ref name=bath/&gt; Eliasberg himself had to be dragged to rehearsals on a sledge, and was eventually moved by Communist officials to an apartment nearby and given a bicycle for transport. His first attempts at conducting were like a &quot;wounded bird with wings that are going to drop at any moment&quot;.&lt;ref name=tum/&gt;&lt;ref name=voice&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ruvr.ru/2012_08_09/Victory-day-in-war-torn-Leningrad/|accessdate=13 December 2012|date=9 August 2012|publisher=Voice of Russia|title=Victory day in war-torn Leningrad|author=Viktorova, Natalia}}&lt;/ref&gt; A report by Babushkin noted that &quot;the first violin is dying, the drum died on his way to work, the French horn is at death's door&amp;nbsp;...&quot;.{{sfn|Axell|2002|p=94}} Orchestral players were given additional rations (donated by civilian music enthusiasts) in an effort to combat starvation, and hot bricks were used to radiate heat; nevertheless, three performers died during rehearsals.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;&lt;ref name=voice/&gt;{{sfn|Robinson|1995|p=70}}{{sfn|Jones|2008|p=257}} Posters went up around the city requesting all musicians to report to the Radio Committee for incorporation into the orchestra. Performers were also recalled from the front or reassigned from Soviet military bands with the support of the Soviet commander of the Leningrad front, [[Leonid Govorov]].&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;

In addition to the Seventh Symphony, the makeshift orchestra also rehearsed traditional symphonic works by [[Ludwig van Beethoven|Beethoven]], [[Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky|Tchaikovsky]] and [[Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov|Rimsky-Korsakov]]. A concert of Tchaikovsky excerpts was held on 5 April.{{sfn|Salisbury|2003|p=512}}{{sfn|Reid|2011|p=361}}{{sfn|Volkov|2004|pp=179&amp;ndash;180}} Some players protested the decision to perform Shostakovich's symphony, not wanting to expend their little strength on an &quot;intricate and not very accessible&quot; work. Eliasberg threatened to rescind the additional rations, quelling any dissent.{{sfn|Volkov|2004|pp=179&amp;ndash;180}} During the rehearsals, Eliasberg was criticized for his harsh demeanour: musicians who missed rehearsals, were late, or did not perform to expectations lost their rations. One performer lost rations because he had attended his wife's burial and was late for rehearsal.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt; Although some sources suggest a team of copyists was employed, according to other sources musicians were made to copy out their individual parts by hand from the score.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;{{sfn|Fay|1989|p=133}}

Rehearsals were held six days a week at the Pushkin Theatre, usually from 10 am to 1 pm. However, they were frequently interrupted by air-raid sirens, and some musicians were required to undertake anti-aircraft or firefighting duties. To enable them to attend rehearsals, performers were granted orchestral ID cards to show at checkpoints. Members of the military orchestra (and some ordinary troops) were dispatched to the rehearsals to supplement the performers. Rehearsals were moved to the Philharmonia Hall in June, and in late July were increased to 5–6 hours a day.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;{{sfn|Robinson|1995|p=70}}{{sfn|Simmons &amp; Perlina|2005|pp=148&amp;ndash;149}} Instruments were in poor condition and few repairmen were available; one oboist was asked for a cat in exchange for a repair, as the starving repairman had already eaten several.&lt;ref name=galina/&gt;{{sfn|Simmons &amp; Perlina|2005|p=147}}

The orchestra played the entire symphony all the way through only once before the première, at a dress rehearsal on 6 August.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;

==Performance==
[[File:Питерская Филармония Зал.jpg|upright|thumb|The modern stage of the Grand Philharmonia Hall where the concert was performed]]
The concert was given in the Grand Philharmonia Hall on 9 August 1942. This was the day Hitler had previously designated to celebrate the fall of the city with a lavish banquet at Leningrad's Astoria Hotel.&lt;ref name=ed1&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Guardian|title=Orchestral manoeuvres (part 1)|author=Vulliamy, Ed|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/theobserver/2001/nov/25/features.magazine27|accessdate=13 December 2012|date=25 November 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; The performance was preceded by a pre-recorded radio address by Eliasberg, aired at 6 pm:&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;{{sfn|Jones|2008|p=260}}

{{quote|Comrades &amp;ndash; a great occurrence in the cultural history of our city is about to take place. In a few minutes, you will hear for the first time the Seventh Symphony of Dmitri Shostakovich, our outstanding fellow citizen. He wrote this great composition in the city during the days when the enemy was, insanely, trying to enter Leningrad. When the fascist swine were bombing and shelling all Europe, and Europe believed the days of Leningrad were over. But this performance is witness to our spirit, courage and readiness to fight. Listen, Comrades!}}

Lieutenant-General Govorov ordered a bombardment of German artillery positions in advance of the concert in a special operation, code-named &quot;Squall&quot;.{{sfn|Sollertinsky|1980|p=108}} Soviet intelligence personnel had located the German batteries and observation posts a few weeks before, in preparation for the attack.{{sfn|Volkov|1997|p=440}} Three thousand high-caliber shells were lobbed onto the enemy.{{sfn|Volkov|2004|p=180}} The purpose of the operation was to prevent the Germans from targeting the concert hall and to ensure that it would be quiet enough to hear the music over speakers he ordered to be set up. He also encouraged Soviet soldiers to listen to the concert via radio.{{sfn|Jones|2008|pp=265&amp;ndash;266}} Musicologist [[Andrei Krukov]] later praised Govorov's actions as providing the &quot;incentive&quot; for the concert, adding that his choice to allow soldiers to participate was &quot;a quite exceptional decision&quot;.{{sfn|Jones|2008|p=295}} Govorov himself later remarked to Eliasberg that &quot;we played our instrument in the symphony, too, you know,&quot; in reference to the artillery fire.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt; The military contribution to the affair was not widely known until well after the war ended.&lt;ref name=galina/&gt;

There was a large audience for the concert, comprising party leaders, military personnel, and civilians. Leningrad citizens who could not fit into the hall gathered around open windows and loudspeakers. The musicians onstage were &quot;dressed like cabbages&quot; in multiple layers to prevent starvation-induced shivering.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;{{sfn|Robinson|1995|p=70}} Shortly before the concert started, the electric lights above the stage were turned on for the first time since rehearsals had commenced.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt; As the hall fell silent, Eliasberg began conducting. The performance was of poor artistic quality, but was notable for the emotions raised in the audience and for its finale: when some musicians &quot;faltered&quot; due to exhaustion, the audience stood up &quot;in a remarkable, spontaneous gesture&amp;nbsp;... willing them to keep going&quot;.{{sfn|Robinson|1995|p=70}}{{sfn|Jones|2008|p=260}}

The performance received an hour-long standing ovation, with Eliasberg being given a symbolic bouquet of Leningrad-grown flowers by a young girl.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;&lt;ref name=voice/&gt; Many in the audience were in tears due to the emotional impact of the concert, which was seen as a &quot;musical biography of suffering Leningrad&quot;.{{sfn|Robinson|1995|p=71}} The musicians were invited to a banquet with Party officials to celebrate.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;

Loudspeakers broadcast the performance throughout the city as well as to the German forces in a move of psychological warfare, a &quot;tactical strike against German morale&quot;.{{sfn|Fay|1989|p=133}}{{sfn|Ross|2008|p=269}} One German soldier recalled how his squadron &quot;listened to the symphony of heroes&quot;.{{sfn|Dimbleby|2010|loc=&quot;Siege of Leningrad&quot;}} Eliasberg later met with some of the Germans who camped outside Leningrad during the performance, who told him that it had made them believe they would never capture the city: &quot;Who are we bombing? We will never be able to take Leningrad because the people here are selfless&quot;.&lt;ref name=galina/&gt;&lt;ref name=hour&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyinanhour.com/2011/08/09/the-leningrad-symphony-summary/|date=9 August 2011|accessdate=13 December 2012|title=The Leningrad Symphony|publisher=History in an Hour|author=Colley, Rupert}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception and legacy==
Shostakovich scholar [[Laurel Fay]] suggests that this concert was &quot;an event of legendary import all by itself&quot;.{{sfn|Fay|1989|p=132}} Journalist Michael Tumely calls it &quot;a legendary moment in Soviet political and military history&quot;.&lt;ref name=tum/&gt; Critic U.S. Dhuga suggests that this performance &quot;was popularly &amp;ndash; and, of course, officially &amp;ndash; recognized as the prelude to actual victory over the Germans&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Dhuga, U. S.|title=Music Chronicle|journal=The Hudson Review|volume=57|issue=1|year=2004|pages=125&amp;ndash;132}}&lt;/ref&gt; The blockade was breached in early 1943 and ended in 1944. Eliasberg concurred with Dhuga's assessment, saying that &quot;the whole city had found its humanity&amp;nbsp;... in that moment, we triumphed over the soulless Nazi war machine&quot;.{{sfn|Jones|2008|p=261}} There was no official recognition of the significance of the concert: one musician noted that afterwards &quot;there was no feedback, nothing until 1945&quot;.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;

Shostakovich's Symphony No. 7 enjoyed a measure of popularity throughout the Western world during the war, but from 1945 it largely stopped being performed outside the Soviet Union. It became a point of controversy in the 1980s after [[Solomon Volkov]]'s ''[[Testimony (book)|Testimony]]'' suggested it was a critique not of the Nazis, but of the Soviet government.{{sfn|Robinson|1995|p=71}} The veracity of Volkov's account, which he claims is rooted in interviews with Shostakovich, has been debated.&lt;ref name=whose&gt;{{cite journal|author=Fay, Laurel|journal=Russian Review|volume=39|issue=40|title=Shostakovich versus Volkov: Whose ''Testimony''?|pages=484&amp;ndash;493|doi=10.2307/128813|jstor=128813|year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other issues of contention about the symphony include whether it was inspired by the attack on Leningrad (as Soviet authorities and official accounts had asserted) or planned earlier and repurposed for propaganda, as well as its artistic merit in reference to Shostakovich's other works.&lt;ref name=whose/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fairclough|first=P|title=The 'Old Shostakovich': Reception in the British Press|journal=Music and Letters|date=May 2007|volume=88|issue=2|pages=266–296|doi=10.1093/ml/gcm002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The première made Eliasberg a &quot;hero of the city&quot;. Shortly after the concert, he married Nina Bronnikova, who had played the piano part. But once the siege ended and the Philharmonic returned to Leningrad, he fell from favour. The conductor of the Philharmonic, [[Yevgeny Mravinsky]], had him fired in 1950 because he envied Eliasberg's popular acclaim. Eliasberg was a &quot;poor and largely forgotten&quot; travelling conductor when he died in 1978. However, at the fifty-year anniversary of the première his remains were moved to the prestigious Volkovskoye or Alexander Nevsky Cemetery, the result of a campaign by orchestra archivist [[Galina Retrovskaya]], conductor [[Yuri Temirkanov]], and St. Petersburg mayor [[Anatoly Sobchak]].&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt;&lt;ref name=hour2/&gt; Sarah Quigley fictionalized Eliasberg's wartime career in her historical novel ''The Conductor''.&lt;ref name=bath/&gt;

Surviving performers participated in reunion concerts in 1964 and 1992, playing &quot;from the same seats in the same hall&quot;.&lt;ref name=ed1/&gt; Shostakovich attended the first reunion concert on 27 January 1964.&lt;ref name=ed2/&gt; Twenty-two musicians and Eliasberg performed the symphony, and instruments were placed on the other chairs to represent those participants who had died since the première.&lt;ref name=hour2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyinanhour.com/2012/06/10/karl-eliasberg-summary/|accessdate=13 December 2012|publisher=History in an Hour|title=Karl Eliasberg|date=10 June 2012|author=Colley, Rupert}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1992 performance featured the 14 remaining survivors.&lt;ref name=ed1/&gt; The 1942 concert was also commemorated in the 1997 film ''[[The War Symphonies: Shostakovich Against Stalin]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.albany.edu/jmmh/vol2no1/warsymphonies.html|journal=Journal for Multimedia History|volume=2|year=1999|title=The War Symphonies: Shostakovich Against Stalin|author=McCannon, John}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is a small museum dedicated to the event at School No. 235 in St. Petersburg, which includes a statue of Shostakovich and artifacts from the performance.{{sfn|Jones|2008|p=7}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

;Bibliography
*{{cite book|last=Axell|first=Albert|title=Russia's heroes|year=2002|publisher=Carrol &amp; Graf|isbn=978-0-7867-1011-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Dimbleby|first=Jonathan| authorlink = Jonathan Dimbleby|title=Russia: A Journey to the Heart of a Land and Its People|year=2010|publisher=Random House|isbn=978-1-4090-7346-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Fay|first=Laurel|title=Shostakovich: A Life|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1989|isbn=0-19-513438-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Ford|first=Andrew| authorlink = Andrew Ford (composer)|title=Illegal harmonies: music in the modern age|publisher=Black Inc|isbn=978-1-86395-528-7|edition=3rd|year=2011|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Jones|first=Michael|title=Leningrad: State of Siege|publisher=Basic Books|year=2008|isbn=978-0-465-01153-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Lincoln|first=Bruce| authorlink = W. Bruce Lincoln|title=Sunlight at Midnight|year=2009|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=978-0-7867-3089-6|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|title=Leningrad|last=Reid|first=Anna| authorlink = Anna Reid|isbn=978-0-14-318574-1|year=2011|publisher=Penguin Canada|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Robinson|first=Harlow|pages=62–76|chapter=Composing for Victory|title=Culture and Entertainment in Wartime Russia|editor=[[Stites, Richard]]|year=1995|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=0-253-20949-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Ross|first=Alex| authorlink = Alex Ross (music critic)|title=The Rest is Noise: Listening to the Twentieth Century|year=2008|publisher=Picador|isbn=978-0-312-42771-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Salisbury|first=Harrison| authorlink = Harrison Salisbury|title=The 900 Days: the siege of Leningrad|year=2003|publisher=Da Capo Press|isbn=978-0-7867-3024-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editors=Simmons, Cynthia; Perlina, Nina|year=2005|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press|title=Writing the Siege of Leningrad|isbn=978-0-8229-7274-7|ref={{harvid|Simmons &amp; Perlina|2005}}}}
*{{cite book|last=Sollertinsky|first=Dmitri &amp; Ludmilla|editors=Hobbs, Graham; Midgley, Charles|title=Pages from the Life of Dmitri Shostakovich|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|year=1980|isbn=0-15-170730-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Volkov|first=Solomon| authorlink = Solomon Volkov|title=St. Petersburg: a cultural history|year=1997|publisher=Free Press Paperbacks|isbn=978-0-684-83296-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Volkov|first=Solomon|year=2004|title=Shostakovich and Stalin: The Extraordinary Relationship Between the Great Composer and the Brutal Dictator|publisher=Knopf|isbn=0-375-41082-1|ref=harv}}

==External links==
*''[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=irYM2VcBv4A Shostakovich Against Stalin]'' &amp;ndash; segment on concert begins at 35 minutes
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SG_KJI6sOwc 1941 Toscanini performance]

{{Dmitri Shostakovich}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Leningrad premiere of Shostakovich's Symphony No. 7}}
[[Category:1942 in Russia]]
[[Category:Concerts]]
[[Category:History of Saint Petersburg]]
[[Category:Symphonies by Dmitri Shostakovich]]
[[Category:Soviet Union in World War II]]
[[Category:Music in Saint Petersburg]]
[[Category:1942 in music]]
[[Category:20th century in Saint Petersburg]]</text>
      <sha1>iu62y51fg6fk5f9k9oexav26enedqv0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
