<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>McDonnell XF-85 Goblin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>307179</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735605423</id>
      <parentid>729134343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-21T21:57:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LilHelpa</username>
        <id>8024439</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */ typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29051">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name= XF-85 Goblin
  |image= File:McDonnell XF-85 Goblin USAF (Cropped).jpg
  |caption= XF-85 serial number ''46-523'' in the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]]
  |alt=Small egg-shaped aircraft with three vertical stabilizers, resting on yellow movable rig
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type =[[Parasite fighter]]
  |manufacturer =[[McDonnell Aircraft]]
  |national origin= United States
  |designer=
  |first flight=23 August [[1948 in aviation|1948]]
  |introduced=
  |retired=
  |status= Canceled, [[1949 in aviation|1949]]
  |primary user=
  |more users=
  |produced=
  |number built= Two
  |unit cost=
  |program cost={{US$|link=yes}}3.1 million&lt;ref name=&quot;knaack&quot;&gt;Knaack 1978, p.&amp;nbsp;312.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 85&quot;/&gt;
  |variants with their own articles=
}}
|}

The '''McDonnell XF-85 Goblin''' was an American prototype [[fighter aircraft]] conceived during [[World War II]] by [[McDonnell Aircraft]]. It was intended to be deployed from the [[bomb bay]] of the giant [[Convair B-36]] bomber as a [[parasite fighter]]. The XF-85's intended role was to defend bombers from hostile [[interceptor aircraft]], a need demonstrated during World War II. Two prototypes were constructed before the program was terminated.

The XF-85 was a response to a [[United States Army Air Forces]]' (USAAF) requirement for a fighter to be carried within the [[Northrop YB-35|Northrop XB-35]] and B-36, then under development. This was to address the limited range of existing interceptor aircraft compared to the greater range of new bomber designs. The XF-85 was a diminutive jet aircraft featuring a distinctive egg-shaped [[fuselage]] and a forked-tail [[Stabilizer (aircraft)|stabilizer]] design. The prototypes were built and underwent testing and evaluation in 1948. Flight tests showed promise in the design, but the aircraft's performance was inferior to the jet fighters it would have faced in combat, and there were difficulties in docking. The XF-85 was swiftly canceled, and the prototypes were thereafter relegated to museum exhibits. The 1947 successor to the USAAF, the [[United States Air Force]] (USAF), continued to examine the concept of parasite aircraft under [[FICON project|Project MX-106 &quot;Tip Tow&quot;]], [[FICON project|Project FICON]] and [[FICON project|Project &quot;Tom-Tom&quot;]] following the cancellation.

==Design and development==
During World War II, American bombers such as the [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress]], [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator]] and [[Boeing B-29 Superfortress]] were protected by long-range escort fighters such as the [[Republic P-47 Thunderbolt]] and [[North American P-51 Mustang]]. These fighters could not match the range of the Northrop B-35 or Convair B-36, the next generation of bombers developed by the United States Army Air Forces (USAAF). The development cost for longer-ranged fighters was high, while [[aerial refueling]] was still considered risky and technologically difficult.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 37&quot;&gt;O'Leary 1974, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; Pilot fatigue had also been a problem during long fighter escort missions in Europe and the Pacific, giving further impetus to innovative approaches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 483&quot;&gt;Gunston 1975, p. 483.&lt;/ref&gt;

The USAAF considered a number of different options including the use of remotely piloted vehicles before choosing [[parasite fighter]]s as the most viable B-36 defense.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sundey p. 10&quot;&gt;Sundey 1985, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; The concept of a parasite fighter had its origins in 1918, when the [[Royal Air Force]] examined the viability of [[Sopwith Camel]] parasite fighters operating from [[23 class airship|''R23'']] airships.{{#tag:ref|This is apparently a mis-identification of the airship involved.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzsimons 1978, p. 521.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} In the 1930s, the U.S. Navy had a short-lived operational parasite fighter, the [[Curtiss F9C Sparrowhawk]], aboard the airships {{USS|Akron|ZRS-4|2}} and {{USS|Macon|ZRS-5|2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 81&quot;&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; Starting in 1931, aircraft designer [[Vladimir Vakhmistrov]] conducted experiments in the [[Soviet Union]] as part of the [[Zveno project]] during which up to five fighters of various types were carried by [[Polikarpov TB-2]] and [[Tupolev TB-3]] bombers. In August 1941, these combinations flew the only combat missions ever undertaken by parasite fighters – TB-3s carrying [[Polikarpov I-16|Polikarpov I-16SPB]] [[dive bomber]]s attacked the [[King Carol I Bridge|Cernavodă bridge]] and [[Constantsa]] docks, in [[Romania]]. After that attack, the squadron, based in the Crimea, carried out a tactical attack on a bridge over the river [[Dnieper]] at [[Zaporizhia|Zaporozhye]], which had been captured by advancing German troops.&lt;ref&gt;Lesnitchenko 1999, pp. 4–21.&lt;/ref&gt; Later in World War II, the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' experimented with the [[Messerschmitt Me 328]] as a parasite fighter, but problems with its [[pulsejet]] engines could not be overcome.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 37&quot;/&gt; Other late-war [[rocket]]-powered parasite fighter projects such as the [[Arado E.381]] and [[List of German aircraft projects, 1939-1945|Sombold So 344]] were unrealized &quot;paper projects&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lepage 2009, pp. 257, 258.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 December 1942, the USAAF sent out a Request for Proposals (RfP) for a diminutive piston-engined fighter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin p. 36&quot;&gt;Cowin 2011, p.&amp;nbsp;36.&lt;/ref&gt; By January 1944, the [[Air Force Logistics Command|Air Technical Service Command]] refined the RfP and in January&amp;nbsp;1945, the specifications were further revised in MX-472 to specify a jet-powered aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 81&quot;/&gt; Although a number of aerospace companies studied the feasibility of such aircraft, McDonnell was the only company to submit a proposal to the original 1942 request and later revised requirements.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 81&quot;/&gt; The company's Model 27 proposal was completely reworked to meet the new specifications.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin p. 36&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Mcdonnell XF-85.jpg|thumb|Top view of the XF-85, with the hook extended over top of the canopy|alt=Black-and-white top view of egg-shaped aircraft, with a hook extended over top of canopy]]

The initial concept for the Model 27 was for the fighter to be carried half-exposed under the B-29, B-35 or B-36. The USAAF rejected this proposal, citing increased drag, and hence reduced range for the composite bomber-fighter configuration.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 81&quot;/&gt; On 19&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;1945, McDonnell's design team led by Herman D. Barkey,&lt;ref&gt;Pace 1991, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; submitted a revised proposal, the extensively redesigned Model 27D.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 485&quot;&gt;Gunston 1975, p. 485.&lt;/ref&gt; The smaller aircraft had an egg-shaped fuselage, three fork-shaped vertical stabilizers, horizontal stabilizers with a significant [[Dihedral (aircraft)|dihedral]], and 37° swept-back folding wings to allow it to fit in the confines of a bomb bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 484&quot;&gt;Gunston 1975, p. 484.&lt;/ref&gt; The diminutive aircraft measured {{convert|14|ft|10|in|m|2|abbr=on}} long; the folding wings spanned {{convert|21|ft|m|abbr=on}}. Only a limited fuel supply of {{convert|112|usgal|impgal l|abbr=on}} was deemed necessary for the specified 30-minute combat endurance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 484&quot; /&gt; A hook was installed along the aircraft's center of gravity; in flight, it retracted to lie flat in the upper part of the nose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 484&quot;/&gt; The aircraft had an empty weight just short of {{Convert|4,000|lb|t}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winchester p. 151&quot;&gt;Winchester 2005, p.&amp;nbsp;151.&lt;/ref&gt; To save weight, the fighter had no landing gear.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 485&quot;/&gt;{{#tag:ref|A fixed tricycle landing gear was considered for the flight tests but was discarded as the drag was excessive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sundey p. 12&quot;&gt;Sundey 1985, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} During the testing program, a fixed steel skid under the fuselage and spring-steel &quot;runners&quot; at the underside of the wingtips were installed in case of an emergency landing.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 81&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boeing XF-85&quot;&gt;[http://www.boeing.com/history/mdc/goblin.htm &quot;McDonnell XF-85 Goblin Parasite Fighter.&quot;] ''Boeing''. Retrieved: 29 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the cramped quarters, a pilot was provided with a cordite ejection seat, bail-out oxygen bottle and high-speed ribbon parachute.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 38&quot;/&gt; Four {{convert|.50|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} machine guns in the nose made up the aircraft's armament.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L pp. 82–83&quot;&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;82–83.&lt;/ref&gt;

In service, the parasite fighter would be launched and retrieved by a [[trapeze]]. With the trapeze fully extended, the engine would be airstarted and the release from the [[mother ship]] was accomplished by the pilot pulling the nose back to disengage from the hook.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 38&quot;/&gt; In recovery, the aircraft would approach the mother ship from underneath and link up with the trapeze using the retractable hook in the aircraft's nose.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 38&quot;&gt;O'Leary 1974, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; The anticipated production shift would see a mixed B-36 fleet with both &quot;fighter carriers&quot; and bombers&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 487&quot;/&gt; employed on missions.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L pp. 80–81&quot;&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;80–81.&lt;/ref&gt; There were plans that, from the 24th B-36 onward, provisions would be made to accommodate one XF-85, with a maximum of four per bomber envisioned.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L pp. 82–83&quot;/&gt;{{#tag:ref|The initial specification called for the B-36 carrier aircraft to be able to carry either one F-85 and one atomic bomb or three F-85s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 485&quot;/&gt;|group=N}} Up to 10 percent of the B-36s on order were to be converted to fighter carriers with three or four F-85s instead of a bomb load.{{#tag:ref|The modifications included a structurally reinforced bomb bay that included the trapeze apparatus and an &quot;umbilical&quot; fueling station. In operational use, provisions for repair of oxygen and other mechanical systems, as well as replenishing ammunition were contemplated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 487&quot;&gt;Gunston 1975, p. 487.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}

[[File:McDonnell XF-85 trapese.jpg|thumb|upright|Hangar test of recovery trapeze, with wings folded in stowed configuration|alt=Black-and-white photograph of small egg-shaped fighter aircraft hoisted by a lifting mechanism underneath a large bomber.]]
On 9 October 1945, the USAAF signed a letter of intent covering the engineering development for two prototypes ([[United States military aircraft serials|US serial numbers]] ''46-523/4''), although the contract was not finalized until February 1947.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 82&quot;&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, p.&amp;nbsp;82.&lt;/ref&gt; After the successful conclusion of two reviews of a wooden mock-up in 1946 and 1947 by USAAF engineering staff,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sundey p. 10&quot;/&gt; McDonnell constructed two prototypes in late 1947.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 485&quot;/&gt; The Model 27D was re-designated XP-85, but by June&amp;nbsp;1948, it was changed to XF-85 and given the name &quot;Goblin&quot;.{{#tag:ref|This name does not follow McDonnell practice and is the name that the USAAF gave to the aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L pp. 82–83&quot;/&gt; McDonnell personnel nicknamed the aircraft &quot;Bumble Bee.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pace 1991, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} There were plans to acquire 30 production P-85s, but the USAAF took the cautious approach&amp;nbsp;– if test results from the two prototypes were positive, production orders for more than 100 Goblins would be finalized later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 487&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 82&quot;/&gt;

==Operational history==
During [[wind tunnel]] testing at [[Moffett Field]], California, the first prototype XF-85 was accidentally dropped from a crane at a height of {{convert|40|ft|m|abbr=on}}, causing substantial damage to the forward fuselage, air intake and lower fuselage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 485&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin pp. 37–38&quot;&gt;Cowin 2011, pp. 37–38.&lt;/ref&gt; The second prototype had to be substituted for the remainder of the wind tunnel tests and the initial flight tests.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 85&quot;&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

As a production series B-36 was unavailable, all XF-85 flight tests were carried out using a converted [[Boeing B-29 Superfortress|EB-29B Superfortress]] mother ship that had a modified, &quot;cutaway&quot; bomb bay complete with trapeze, front airflow deflector and an array of camera equipment and instrumentation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 485&quot;/&gt; Since the EB-29B, named ''Monstro'', was smaller than the B-36, the XF-85 would be flight tested, half-exposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 85&quot;/&gt; In order to carry the XF-85, a special &quot;loading pit&quot; was dug into the tarmac at South Base, [[Edwards Air Force Base|Muroc Field]], where all the flight tests originated.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;/&gt;{{#tag:ref|The XF-85 would be hooked onto fully extended trapeze before being hoisted into the mother ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;/&gt;|group=N}} On 23&amp;nbsp;July 1948, the XF-85 flew the first of five captive flights, designed to test whether the EB-29B and its parasite fighter could fly &quot;mated&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boeing XF-85&quot;/&gt; The XF-85 was carried in a stowed position, but was sometimes tethered and extended into the airstream with the engine off, for the pilot to gain some feel for the aircraft in flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin p. 38&quot;&gt;Cowin 2011, p.&amp;nbsp;38.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:McDonnell XF-85 Goblin and EB-29 mothership.jpg|left|thumb|XF-85 suspended from an EB-29 via a trapeze|alt=Black-and-white photograph shows diminutive jet fighter suspended from a large aircraft in flight, through a trapeze.]]
McDonnell test pilot Edwin Schoch was assigned to the project, riding in the XF-85 while it was stowed aboard the EB-29B, before attempting a &quot;free&quot; flight on 23 August 1948. After Schoch was released from the bomber at a height of 20,000&amp;nbsp;ft (6,000 m), he completed a 10-minute proving flight at speeds between 180 and 250&amp;nbsp;mph (290–400&amp;nbsp;km/h), testing controls and maneuverability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith p. 1061&quot;&gt;Smith 1967, p. 1061.&lt;/ref&gt; When he attempted a hook-up, it became obvious the Goblin was extremely sensitive to the bomber's [[wake turbulence|turbulence]], as well as being affected by the [[Ground effect (aircraft)|air cushion]] created by the two aircraft operating in close proximity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith p. 1061&quot;/&gt;  Constant but gentle adjustments of throttle and trim were necessary to overcome the cushioning effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;/&gt; After three attempts to hook onto the trapeze, Schoch miscalculated his approach and struck the trapeze so violently that the canopy was smashed and ripped free and his helmet and mask were torn off.&lt;ref&gt;Gunston 1981, pp. 127–128.&lt;/ref&gt; He saved the prototype by making a [[belly landing]] on the reinforced skid at the dry lake bed at [[Edwards Air Force Base|Muroc]].{{#tag:ref|[[Rogers Dry Lake]] and [[Rosamond Dry Lake]] made up emergency landing areas at Muroc.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasa.gov/centers/dryden/pdf/120328main_FS-086-DFRC.pdf &quot;The Lake Beds: Edwards Air Force Base.&quot;] ''NASA Dryden Flight Research Center.'' Retrieved: 2 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}  All flight testing was suspended for seven weeks while the XF-85 was repaired and modified. Schoch used the down period to undertake a series of problem-free dummy dockings with a [[Lockheed P-80 Shooting Star]] fighter.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;/&gt;

After boosting the trim power by 50 percent, adjusting the aerodynamics, and other modifications,&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;/&gt; two further mated test flights were carried out before Schoch was able to make a successful release and hookup on 14 October 1948.&lt;ref&gt;Gunston 1981, p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt; During the fifth free flight on 22 October 1948, Schoch again found it difficult to hook the Goblin to the bomber's trapeze, aborting four attempts before hitting the trapeze bar and breaking the hook on the XF-85's nose. Again, a forced landing was successfully carried out at Muroc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin p. 38&quot;/&gt;

With the first prototype's repairs completed, it also joined the flight test program, completing captive flights. While in flight, the Goblin was stable, easy to fly, and recoverable from spins, although initial estimates of a 648&amp;nbsp;mph (1,043&amp;nbsp;km/h) top speed proved optimistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 85&quot;/&gt; The first test flights revealed that turbulence during approach to the B-29 was significant, leading to the addition of upper and lower fins at the extreme rear fuselage, as well as two wingtip fins to compensate for the increased directional instability in docking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 485&quot;/&gt; All the initial flights had the hook secured in a fixed position, but when the hook was stowed and later raised, the resulting buffeting added to the difficulty in attempting a hookup. To address the problem, small aerodynamic [[fairing (aircraft)|fairings]] were added to the hook well that reduced the buffeting when the hook was extended and retracted.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;&gt;O'Leary 1974, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;  When testing resumed, on the 18 March 1948 test flight, Schoch continued to have difficulty in hooking up, striking and damaging the trapeze's nose-stabilizing section, before resorting to another emergency belly landing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin p. 38&quot;/&gt; After repairs to the trapeze, Schoch flew the first prototype on 8 April 1949, completing a 30-minute free flight test, but after three attempts, abandoned his efforts and resorted to another belly landing at Muroc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin p. 39&quot;&gt;Cowin 2011, p.&amp;nbsp;39.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|On the last XF-85 flight, after completing a lengthy flight test, due to the limited fuel on board, Schoch was forced to abandon further attempts to dock.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;/&gt;|group=N}}

Aware of the problems revealed in flight tests, McDonnell reviewed the program and proposed a new development based on a more conventional design promising a Mach 0.9 capability, using alternatively a 35° swept wing and delta wing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith p. 1062&quot;&gt;Smith 1967, p. 1,062.&lt;/ref&gt; McDonnell also considered adding a telescoping extension to the docking trapeze that would extend the device below the turbulent air under the mother ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowin p. 39&quot;/&gt; Before any further work on the trapeze, other modifications to the XF-85, or continued design studies on its follow-up could be carried out, the [[United States Air Force|USAF]]{{#tag:ref|The USAF was formed as a separate branch of the military on 18 September 1947 under the United States [[National Security Act of 1947]].&lt;ref name=Factsheet2&gt;[http://archive.is/20120527094032/http://www.af.mil/information/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=2 &quot;United States Air Force.&quot;] ''United States Air Force'', September 2009. Retrieved: 6 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} canceled the XF-85 program on 24 October 1949.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yeager&quot;&gt;Yeager and Janos 1986, p.&amp;nbsp;179.&lt;/ref&gt;

Two main reasons contributed to the cancellation. The XF-85's deficiencies revealed in flight testing included a lackluster performance in relation to contemporary jet fighters, and the high demands on pilot skill experienced during docking revealed a critical shortcoming that was never fully corrected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith p. 1062&quot;/&gt; The development of practical aerial refueling for conventional fighters used as bomber escort was also a factor in the cancellation.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 85&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boeing XF-85&quot;/&gt; The two Goblins flew seven times, with a total flight time of 2 hours and 19 minutes with only three of the free flights ending in a successful hookup.&lt;ref name=&quot;J&amp;L p. 85&quot;/&gt; Schoch was the only pilot who ever flew the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Dorr 1997, p.&amp;nbsp;101.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Further developments==
Despite the cancellation of the XF-85, the USAF continued to examine the concept of parasite aircraft as defensive fighters through a series of projects including [[FICON project|Project MX-106 &quot;Tip Tow&quot;, Project FICON, and Project &quot;Tom-Tom&quot;]] which involved fighter aircraft attached to bomber aircraft by their wingtips.&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1977, p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt; Project FICON (&quot;fighter conveyor&quot;) emerged as an effective [[Convair B-36|Convair GRB-36D]] and [[Republic F-84F Thunderstreak|Republic RF-84K Thunderflash]] combined bomber-reconnaissance-fighter, although the role was changed to that of strategic reconnaissance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunston p. 487&quot;/&gt; Project FICON drew heavily on data from the abortive XF-85 project and closely followed McDonnell's recommendations in designing a more refined trapeze.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sundey p. 19&quot;&gt;Sundey 1985, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 10 converted B-36s and 25 reconnaissance fighters saw limited service with the [[Strategic Air Command]] in 1955–1956, before being supplemented by more effective aircraft and satellite systems.&lt;ref&gt;Davis and Menard 1983, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aircraft on display==
[[File:McDonnell XF-85 Goblin on display.jpg|thumb|upright|McDonnell XF-85 Goblin on display at the USAF Museum at Wright-Patterson AFB in Dayton, OH.|alt=McDonnell XF-85 Goblin on display at the USAF Museum at Wright-Patterson AFB in Dayton, OH.]]

After the program's termination, the two XF-85 prototypes were stored, before being surplussed and relegated to museum display in 1950.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith p. 1062&quot;/&gt;
*46-0523 - [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] at [[Wright-Patterson Air Force Base]] near [[Dayton, Ohio]]. Following the cancellation of the program, the aircraft was transferred to the museum on 23 August 1950 and was one of the first experimental aircraft to be displayed at the new Air Force Museum. For several decades, the aircraft was displayed alongside the museum's Convair B-36. In 2000, the aircraft was moved to the museum's Experimental Aircraft Hangar. Museum staff and visitors objected to this move, believing the aircraft should be displayed alongside the B-36 to properly represent its original design intentions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=586 &quot;XF-85 Goblin/46-523.&quot;] ''National Museum of the USAF.'' Retrieved: 10 May 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
*46-0524 - [[Strategic Air and Space Museum]] in [[Ashland, Nebraska]]. It was originally transferred to the [[Norton Air Force Base]] (near [[San Bernardino, California]]) in 1950, still in a damaged state after its last emergency landing. When the base museum was closed and its collection dispersed, the second XF-85 prototype languished in an unrestored condition as part of the [[Frank Tallman|Tallmantz]] private collection in California, until being acquired by [[Offutt Air Force Base|Offutt AFB]]. It is now refurbished and displayed on its ground-handling trestle, nestled under the wing of a B-36J bomber (serial number ''52-2217'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sasmuseum.com/aircraft/xf-8f-goblin/ &quot;XF-85 Goblin/46-0524.&quot;] ''Strategic Air and Space Museum.'' Retrieved: 10 May 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Specifications==
[[File:McDonnell XF-85 Goblin.svg|thumb|right|300px|Three-view image of XF-85 Goblin]]

{{aircraft specifications
&lt;!-- If you do not understand how to use this template, please ask at [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Aircraft]]
     Please answer the following questions --&gt;
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=jet
&lt;!-- Now, fill out the specs. Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses). If an item doesn't apply, like capacity, leave it blank. For additional lines, end your alt units with )&lt;/li&gt; and start a new, fully formatted line with &lt;li&gt; --&gt;
|ref=''Experimental &amp; Prototype U.S. Air Force Jet Fighters'',&lt;ref&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;81–82.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Boeing'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Boeing XF-85&quot;/&gt; ''National Museum of the United States Air Force''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=586 &quot;McDonnell XF-85 Goblin.&quot;] ''National Museum of the United States Air Force'', 18 March 2010. Retrieved: 29 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
|crew=1
|length main=14 ft 10 in
|length alt=4.5 m
|span main=21 ft 1 in
|span alt=6.4 m
|height main=8 ft 3 in
|height alt=2.5 m
|area main=90 sq&amp;nbsp;ft
|area alt=8.3 m²
|empty weight main=3,740 lb
|empty weight alt=1,700 kg
|loaded weight main=4,550 lb
|loaded weight alt=2,050 kg
|max takeoff weight main= 5,600 lb
|max takeoff weight alt= 2,500 kg
|engine (jet)= [[Westinghouse J34|Westinghouse XJ34-WE-22]]
|type of jet= turbojet
|number of jets= 1
|thrust main=3,000 [[pound-force|lbf]]
|thrust alt=13.3 kN
|max speed main=650 mph (estimated){{#tag:ref| No speed trials were attempted and the highest speed reached during any of the flights was 362 mph (582 km/h).&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Leary p. 40&quot;/&gt;|group=N}}
|max speed alt=565 knots; 1,069 km/h
|flight endurance=1 hr 20 min
|range alt= km
|ceiling main=48,000 ft
|ceiling alt=14,600 m
|climb rate main=12,500 ft/min
|climb rate alt=3,800 m/min
|loading main= 51 lb/sq&amp;nbsp;ft
|loading alt= 247 kg/m²
|thrust/weight= 0.66
|armament=
*4 x .50 cal in (12.7 mm) [[M3 Browning machine gun]]s
}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Military of the United States|Aviation}}
{{aircontent|
|related=&lt;!-- related developments --&gt;
|similar aircraft=
* [[Republic F-84F Thunderstreak|Republic RF-84K Thunderflash]]
&lt;!-- similar or comparable aircraft --&gt;
|lists=
*[[List of military aircraft of the United States]]
*[[List of fighter aircraft]]
|see also=&lt;!-- other relevant information --&gt;
}}
&lt;!---neither mentions appear to be significant---
==Notable appearances in media==
* The XF-85 Goblin was featured in episode 11, &quot;Fly&quot; of [[Pinky and the Brain]] where it is stolen from the National Air and Space Museum and flown to Cape Canaveral. In the episode, it is referred to as the experimental G-4 Ziggy.
* The XF-85 Goblin is one of the vehicles in Battlefield 1942: Secret Weapons of WWII, which is an expansion pack to the popular Battlefield 1942 combat game.---looks like cruft submissions----&gt;

==References==
===Notes===
{{reflist|group=N}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin|45em}}
* Cowin, Hugh W. &quot;McDonnell's unmanageable Goblin.&quot; ''Aviation News,'' June 2011.
* Davis, Larry and David Menard. ''F-84 Thunderjet in Action'' (Aircraft No. 61). Carrollton, Texas: Squadron/Signal Publications, 1983. ISBN 978-0-89747-147-3.
* Dorr, Robert F. &quot;Beyond the frontiers: McDonnell XF-85 Goblin: The built-in fighter.&quot; ''Wings Of Fame'', Volume 7, 1997.
* Fitzsimons, Bernard, ed. ''The Illustrated Encyclopedia of 20th Century Weapons and Warfare, Volume 5.'' London: Phoebus, 1978. ISBN 978-0-8393-6175-6.
* [[Bill Gunston|Gunston, Bill]]. &quot;McDonnell XF-85 Goblin.&quot; ''Fighters of the Fifties''. North Branch, Minnesota: Specialty Press, 1981. ISBN 0-933424-32-9.
* Gunston, Bill. &quot;Parasitic Protectors.&quot; ''Aeroplane Monthly,'' Volume 3, No. 10, October 1975.
* Jenkins, Dennis R. and Tony R. Landis. ''Experimental &amp; Prototype U.S. Air Force Jet Fighters.'' North Branch, Minnesota: Specialty Press, 2008. ISBN 978-1-58007-111-6.
* Knaack, Marcelle Size. ''Encyclopedia of US Air Force Aircraft and Missile Systems: Volume 1 Post-World War II Fighters 1945–1973''. Washington, DC: Office of Air Force History, 1978. ISBN 0-912799-59-5.
* Lepage, Jean-Denis G. G. ''Aircraft of the Luftwaffe, 1935–1945: An Illustrated Guide.'' Jefferson, North Carolina: McFarland &amp; Company, 2009. ISBN 978-0-7864-3937-9.
* Lesnitchenko, Vladimir. &quot;Combat Composites: Soviet Use of 'Mother-Ships' to Carry Fighters, 1931–1941.&quot; ''[[Air Enthusiast]]'', No. 84, November/December 1999.
* Miller, Jay. &quot;Project Tom-Tom.&quot; ''Aerophile,'' Volume 1, No. 3, December 1977.
* O'Leary, Michael. &quot;McDonnell's parasite.&quot; ''Air Combat,'' Volume 2, No. 2, Summer 1974.
* Pace, Steve. ''X-Fighters: USAF Experimental and Prototype Fighters, XP-59 to YF-23.'' St. Paul, Minnesota: Motorbooks International, 1991. ISBN 0-87938-540-5.
* Smith, Richard K. &quot;An Escort Appended... The Story of the McDonnell XF-85 Goblin.&quot; ''Flying Review International,'' Volume 22, No. 16, December 1967.
* Sundey, Terry L. &quot;Built-in Escort: The story of McDonnell's  XF-85 'Goblin' parasite fighter.&quot; ''Airpower,'' Volume 15, No. 1, January 1985.
* [[Chuck Yeager|Yeager, Chuck]] and Leo Janos. ''Yeager: An Autobiography''. New York: Bantam Books, 1986. ISBN 0-553-25674-2.
* ''United States Air Force Museum Guidebook''. Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, Dayton, Ohio: Air Force Association, 1975 edition.
* Winchester, Jim. &quot;McDonnell XF-85 Goblin&quot;. ''Concept Aircraft: Prototypes, X-Planes and Experimental Aircraft''. San Diego, California: Thunder Bay Press, 2005. ISBN 1-59223-480-1.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|XF-85 Goblin}}
* [http://www.sr-71.org/museums/usaf/research/index.php?aircraft=XF-85 SR-71 Online – XF-85 Goblin on Display]
* [http://www.air-and-space.com/goblins.htm Goleta Air and Space Museum: Flying Aircraft Carriers of the USAF: McDonnell XF-85 Goblin]

{{McDD aircraft}}
{{USAF fighters}}

{{featured article}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cancelled military aircraft projects of the United States]]
[[Category:McDonnell aircraft|F-085 Goblin]]
[[Category:Parasite aircraft]]
[[Category:Single-engined jet aircraft]]
[[Category:United States fighter aircraft 1940–1949|McDonnell F-85]]</text>
      <sha1>i3pxfxfak41j1r7c8pzv36n2b3trg2u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
