<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nicky Barr</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5571803</id>
    <revision>
      <id>694698041</id>
      <parentid>694697975</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-12-10T23:17:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/OskloOno|OskloOno]] ([[User talk:OskloOno|talk]]) to last version by Esrever</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28748">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2014}}
{{Use Australian English|date=September 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|birth_name= Andrew William Barr
|birth_date=10 December 1915
|death_date= {{death date and age|2006|6|12|1915|12|10|df=yes}}
|birth_place= [[Wellington, New Zealand|Wellington]], New Zealand
|death_place= [[Gold Coast, Queensland|Gold Coast]], Queensland, Australia
|image= AWM MEA1372 Nicky Barr.jpg
|caption= Barr during World War II
|allegiance= Australia
|serviceyears= 1940–45&lt;br /&gt;1951–53
|rank= [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]]
|branch= [[Royal Australian Air Force]]
|commands= 
|unit= [[No. 23 Squadron RAAF|No. 23 Squadron]] (1940–41)&lt;br/&gt;[[No. 3 Squadron RAAF|No. 3 Squadron]] (1941–42)&lt;br/&gt;[[No. 2 Operational Conversion Unit RAAF|No. 2 Operational Training Unit]] (1944–45)
|battles= World War II
*[[Mediterranean and Middle East theatre of World War II|Middle Eastern theatre]]
*[[North African Campaign]]
*[[European Theatre of World War II|European theatre]]
*[[Operation Overlord|Normandy Campaign]]
*[[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|South West Pacific theatre]]
|awards= [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Military Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] &amp; [[Medal bar|Bar]]
|laterwork= Company director
}}

'''Andrew William''' &quot;'''Nicky'''&quot; '''Barr''', {{postnominals|country=GBR|size=100%|sep=,|OBE|MC|DFC}} &amp; [[Medal bar|Bar]] (10&amp;nbsp;December 1915&amp;nbsp;– 12&amp;nbsp;June 2006) was a member of the [[Australia national rugby union team|Australian national rugby union team]], who became a [[flying ace|fighter ace]] in the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) during World War&amp;nbsp;II. He was credited with 12 aerial victories, all scored flying the [[Curtiss P-40 Warhawk|Curtiss P-40]] fighter.  Born in New Zealand, Barr was raised in [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] and first represented the state in rugby in 1936. Selected to play for Australia in the United Kingdom in 1939, he had just arrived in England when the tour was cancelled following the outbreak of war. He joined the RAAF in 1940 and was posted to [[North African Campaign|North Africa]] with [[No. 3 Squadron RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron]] in September 1941. The squadron's highest-scoring ace, he attained his first three victories in the P-40D Tomahawk and the remainder in the P-40E Kittyhawk.

Barr's achievements as a combat pilot earned him the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] and [[Medal bar|Bar]]. Shortly after taking command of No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron in May 1942, he was shot down and captured by [[Axis powers|Axis forces]], and incarcerated in Italy. He escaped and assisted other [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] fugitives to safety, receiving for his efforts the [[Military Cross]], a rare honour for an RAAF pilot. Repatriated to England, he saw action during the [[Operation Overlord|invasion of Normandy]] in June 1944 before returning to Australia as chief instructor with [[No. 2 Operational Conversion Unit RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;2 Operational Training Unit]]. After the war he became a company director, and rejoined the RAAF as an active reserve officer from 1951 to 1953. From the early 1960s he was heavily involved in the [[oilseed]] industry, for which he was appointed an [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire]] in 1983. He died in 2006, aged 90.

==Early career==
Andrew Barr was born in [[Wellington, New Zealand|Wellington]], New Zealand, on 10&amp;nbsp;December 1915; he had a twin brother, Jack. The family moved to Australia when the boys were six. Growing up in [[Melbourne]], Andrew attended [[Kew, Victoria|Kew Public School]] and played [[Australian rules football]]. He was also the Victorian Schoolboys' 100 yards athletics champion three years in succession, from 1926 to 1928. In 1931, aged fifteen, he began his association with the [[Lord Somers Camp]] and Power House social and sporting organisations located at [[Western Port]]. After leaving school, Barr studied construction at [[Swinburne University of Technology|Swinburne Technical College]], but later took a diploma course in accountancy and made it his profession. He started playing [[rugby union]] in 1935 through a friend in the Power House club. Weighing {{Convert|80|kg|lbs}} and just under {{Convert|6|ft|cm}} tall, Barr gained selection for Victoria as a [[hooker (rugby union)|hooker]] the following year. In 1939, he was chosen to play in the United Kingdom with the Australian national team, the [[Australia national rugby union team|Wallabies]]. The tour was cancelled less than a day after the team arrived in the UK on 2&amp;nbsp;September, due to the outbreak of World War&amp;nbsp;II.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM 023231&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cas.awm.gov.au/item/023231|title= Item 023231|publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]]|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 5–8&lt;/ref&gt; Keen to serve as a [[fighter pilot]], Barr initially tried to enlist in the [[Royal Air Force]], but withdrew his application when told that it was unlikely he would fly anytime in the near future, and that he could expect only administrative duties in the interim.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 9–10&lt;/ref&gt;

Returning to Australia on the [[RMS Strathaird|RMS ''Strathaird'']], Barr joined the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] as an air cadet on 4&amp;nbsp;March 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/people_1077820.asp|title= Wing Commander Andrew William Barr, MC, DFC &amp; bar|publisher= Australian War Memorial|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;&gt;Barr; Stokes 1990&lt;/ref&gt;  After undergoing instruction on [[Tiger Moth]]s at [[No. 3 Elementary Flying Training School RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;3 Elementary Flying Training School]], [[Essendon, Victoria|Essendon]], and on [[Hawker Demon]]s and [[Avro Anson]]s at [[No. 1 Flying Training School RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;1 Service Flying Training School]], [[RAAF Williams|Point Cook]], he was commissioned as a [[pilot officer]] on 24&amp;nbsp;September.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dornan 10-12&quot;&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 10–12&lt;/ref&gt; He gained a reputation as something of a rebel during training, and became forever known as &quot;Nicky&quot;, for &quot;[[Christian teaching about the Devil|Old Nick]]&quot;, or the Devil.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM 023231&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dornan 10-12&quot;/&gt; In his quest to gain assignment as a fighter pilot, he had deliberately aimed poorly during bombing practice, a stratagem also adopted by at least two of his fellow students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;/&gt;  By November 1940, he had been posted to [[No. 23 Squadron RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;23 (City of Brisbane) Squadron]], flying [[CAC Wirraway]]s on patrol off the [[Queensland]] coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM 023231&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt; The aircraft was, according to Barr, &quot;our front line fighter in those days, but it didn't take too long to realise that the capacity of the Wirraway, compared with the types of planes that we were going to encounter, left much to be desired&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;/&gt; Though his duties frustrated him somewhat, Barr was grateful to have this extensive flight experience under his belt when he eventually saw combat. While based in Queensland, he served as honorary [[aide-de-camp]] to the Governor, [[Leslie Orme Wilson|Sir Leslie Wilson]], and also captained the RAAF rugby union team.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 15–17&lt;/ref&gt; He was promoted to [[flying officer]] on 24&amp;nbsp;March 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt;

==Combat service==
[[File:010233Tomahawk1941.jpg|thumb|upright=1.36|left|RAAF P-40 Tomahawk in North Africa|alt=Underside of single-engined monoplane in flight, with twin machine guns on each wing]]
Barr was posted to [[North African Campaign|North Africa]] on 28&amp;nbsp;September 1941, to fly with [[No. 3 Squadron RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron]] under the command of Squadron Leader [[Peter Jeffrey (RAAF officer)|Peter Jeffrey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;&gt;Garrisson 1999, pp. 113–115&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; He converted to [[Curtiss P-40 Warhawk|P-40D Tomahawk]] fighters at an RAF [[Operational conversion unit|operational training unit]] in [[Khartoum]]. There he also received his &quot;[[goolie chit]]&quot;, a piece of paper to be shown to local tribesmen in the event he was shot down, reading in [[Arabic language|Arabic]]: &quot;don't kill the bearer, feed him and protect him, take him to the English and you will be rewarded. Peace be upon you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 23–25&lt;/ref&gt; Returning to North Africa, Barr achieved his first aerial victory, over a [[Messerschmitt Bf&amp;nbsp;110]], on 12&amp;nbsp;December. He followed this up with a [[Junkers Ju&amp;nbsp;88]] and a [[Messerschmitt Bf&amp;nbsp;109]] the next day. The squadron then re-equipped with P-40E Kittyhawks; Barr was flying the new model when he became an [[Flying ace|ace]] on New Year's Day 1942, shooting down two [[Junkers Ju 87|Junkers Ju&amp;nbsp;87 ''Stukas'']].&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas&quot;&gt;Thomas 2005, pp. 22–23&lt;/ref&gt; On 8&amp;nbsp;March, he led a [[Flight (military unit)|flight]] of six Kittyhawks to intercept a raid on [[Tobruk]] by twelve Ju&amp;nbsp;87s escorted by ten [[Macchi C.&amp;nbsp;202]]s and two Bf&amp;nbsp;109s. The Australians destroyed six Macchis and three Ju&amp;nbsp;87s without loss, Barr personally accounting for one of the Macchis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070683--1-.pdf Herington 1954, pp. 223–224]&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually credited with victories over twelve enemy aircraft, plus two probables and eight damaged, Barr became No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron's highest-scoring member.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Newton&quot;&gt;Newton 1996, pp. 65–66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AirForceNews&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/news/raafnews/editions/4811/features/feature01.htm |title=Goodbye to Aussie great|work=[[Air Force (newspaper)|Air Force News]]|date= 29 June 2006|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He flew a total of eighty-four combat [[sortie]]s, twenty of them in one fortnight, and six on 16&amp;nbsp;June 1942 alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;AirForceNews&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070683--1-.pdf Herington 1954, p. 241]&lt;/ref&gt; His philosophy was that the P-40 was not a top-class fighter, but that its shortcomings &quot;could be offset by unbridled aggression&quot;, so he resolved to treat aerial combat as he would a boxing match and &quot;overcome much better opponents by simply going for them&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas&quot;/&gt; [[Bobby Gibbes]] became No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron's commanding officer in February 1942, and made Barr his senior flight commander.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 80–81&lt;/ref&gt; Promoted to [[flight lieutenant]] on 1&amp;nbsp;April, Barr was raised to acting [[squadron leader]] and appointed to command the unit in May, barely six months after he commenced operations, following Gibbes's hospitalisation with a broken ankle.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas 2005, p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; Barr had never sought leadership of the squadron, and felt that others were just as well qualified for the role.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 94–95&lt;/ref&gt; As a commander he delegated most administrative tasks to his [[adjutant]] but, contrary to normal practice, wrote letters to the next-of-kin of casualties himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;/&gt;

{{Quote box
|width=30%
|align=right
|quote=... it had two guns firing from the cockpit and four&amp;nbsp;– two in each wing&amp;nbsp;– to augment it. And I liked very much indeed the loading of the guns when one took off. There was a closeness to combat which seemed to help me with my make-up, the smell of [[cordite]] in the cockpit was particularly helpful to me; I really felt that I was at a war.
|source=— Nicky Barr on the P-40 Tomahawk, interview, 1990&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;/&gt;
}}
Three times while serving with No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron, Barr was himself shot down. The first occasion was on 11&amp;nbsp;January 1942 when, having destroyed a Bf&amp;nbsp;109 and a [[Fiat G.50]], he was preparing to touch down in the desert to pick up a fellow pilot who had crash landed. He had his undercarriage halfway down when he was &quot;jumped&quot; by two other Bf&amp;nbsp;109s. He immediately engaged both and shot one down before more German fighters arrived and he was hit and forced to land behind enemy lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson&quot;&gt;Wilson 2005, pp. 86–87&lt;/ref&gt; As one of the German planes came in low to strafe the downed Kittyhawk, Barr ran straight at it in an attempt to throw the pilot off his aim, and was injured by fragments of rock sent airborne by impact from cannon shells. A tribe of friendly [[Senussi]] Arabs found him, dressed his wounds, and helped him return to Allied lines.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 67–73&lt;/ref&gt; For this exploit, and his earlier successes, Barr was awarded the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] (DFC), the full citation being published in the ''[[London Gazette]]'' on 20&amp;nbsp;February 1942:&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=35463|startpage=844|date=20 February 1942|accessdate= 20 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/items/ACCNUM_LARGE/RCDIG1068966/RCDIG1068966--320-.JPG|format=PDF|title=Recommendation: Distinguished Flying Cross|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:023231Barr1942a.jpg|left|thumb|upright=1.36|Barr has his temperature taken by a medical officer following his return to base three days after being shot down behind enemy lines, January 1942.|alt=Blond man in bed having his temperature taken by another man wearing a military uniform]]
{{quote|This officer, who commenced operational flying in November, 1941, has displayed the greatest keenness and skill as a fighter pilot. In December, 1941, during a patrol over the Derna area, he shot down a Messerschmitt 110; the next day, in the same area, he destroyed a Messerschmitt 110 and a Junkers 88. One day in January, 1942, his squadron formed part of an escort to bomber aircraft operating over El Agheila. Enemy aircraft were encountered and, in the ensuing engagement, Flying Officer Barr attacked 2 Italian fighters, one of which he shot down. He then observed one of his fellow pilots, who had been shot down, waving to him from the ground but, when preparing to make a landing in an attempt to rescue him, Flying Officer Barr was attacked by 2 Messerschmitt 109s. Although the undercarriage of his aircraft was not fully retracted, he immediately manoeuvred to engage the attackers, only to find that his guns had jammed. Quickly rectifying the fault he delivered an accurate burst of fire which caused one of the Messerschmitts to disintegrate in the air. A further 2 enemy aircraft joined in the combat and Flying Officer Barr was wounded and forced down. While on the ground he was further wounded by the enemy's fire but, despite this, he made his way through the enemy's lines and rejoined our own forces some 3 days later. He brought back much valuable information regarding the disposition of enemy tanks and defences. Flying Officer Barr displayed the greatest courage and tenacity throughout. He has destroyed 8 enemy aircraft.}}

On 25&amp;nbsp;May 1942, Barr had to land in the desert when his engine overheated. Having just taken off the engine [[cowling]], he spotted enemy tanks approaching and immediately took off with the engine exposed to the elements, safely landing back at base.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Newton&quot;/&gt; He was shot down for the second time on 30&amp;nbsp;May,&lt;ref name=&quot;Newton&quot;/&gt; when he engaged eight Bf&amp;nbsp;109s and destroyed one before being hit and forced to crash land at high speed in no-man's land. He came down in a minefield during a fierce tank battle, and was forced to remain where he was as troops of both sides slowly converged on him; British forces managed to reach him first and, after treatment for wounds, he again returned to his squadron.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 106–107&lt;/ref&gt; On 26&amp;nbsp;June, however, after being attacked by two Bf&amp;nbsp;109s and bailing out of his burning Kittyhawk, he was captured by Italian soldiers and taken as a prisoner-of-war, first to [[Tobruk]], and then to Italy, where he received hospital treatment for serious wounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newton&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas 2005, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt; He later learned that the pilot who shot him down was Oberleutnant [[Werner Schröer|Werner Schroer]], a [[Luftwaffe]] ace credited with sixty-one victories in North Africa.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 137–138&lt;/ref&gt; Bobby Gibbes, having recovered from his own injuries, again took command of No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070683--1-.pdf Herington 1954, p. 244]&lt;/ref&gt; During his incarceration, on 5&amp;nbsp;February 1943, Barr was awarded a [[medal bar|Bar]] to his DFC for &quot;destroying further enemy aircraft&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=35891|supp=yes|startpage=653|date=2 February 1943|accessdate= 20 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/items/ACCNUM_LARGE/RCDIG1068966/RCDIG1068966--319-.JPG|format=PDF|title=Recommendation: Bar to the Distinguished Flying Cross|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:UK1197Barr1944.jpg|upright=0.96|thumb|Barr in London, April 1944|alt=Formal head-and-shoulders portrait of man in dark military uniform with pilot's wings on breast pocket, wearing a forage cap]]
Barr tried to escape from his confinement four times.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.abc.net.au/austory/transcripts/s513633.htm |publisher=[[ABC Television]]|title=The Quiet Man|work=Australian Story|date= 1 April 2002|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; By November 1942 he had recovered sufficiently from the injuries received in June to break out of the hospital where he was being held in [[Bergamo]], northern Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 153–155, 158–161&lt;/ref&gt;  He made his way to the Swiss border, but was challenged by an Italian customs official, whom he struck with a rock before being recaptured. Court-martialled on a charge of murder, Barr only avoided a death sentence when the [[Swiss Red Cross]] colonel representing him located the official and proved that he had not died. Barr was instead sentenced to ninety days solitary confinement in Gavi Prison Camp, [[Genoa]].&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 163–171&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1943, with Italy on the verge of surrender, prisoners of war were rounded up for transport to Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, p. 190&lt;/ref&gt; Barr jumped from a moving train bound for the [[Brenner Pass]] and joined a group of Italian partisans in [[Pontremoli]], remaining at large for two months before again being captured. Taken to a transit camp just over the Austrian border, Barr and fourteen other prisoners escaped by tunnelling under the barbed wire.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 196–204&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually he managed to link up with an Allied special operations unit, which was gathering intelligence behind enemy lines, sabotaging Axis infrastructure, and helping Allied prisoners and Italian refugees escape over the [[Apennine Mountains]] along the so-called &quot;Alpine Route&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 210–211&lt;/ref&gt; Barr was recaptured and escaped once more before finally making it through the Alpine crossing himself, leading a group of more than twenty. After reaching friendly lines in March 1944, he was sent to a military hospital in [[Vasto]], weighing only {{convert|55|kg|lb}} and in poor health, suffering [[malaria]], malnutrition, and blood poisoning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 222–224, 231–239&lt;/ref&gt; The assistance he rendered to fellow Allied fugitives earned him the [[Military Cross]] (MC) for &quot;Exceptional courage in organising escapes&quot;; the award was [[gazette#Gazette as a verb|gazetted]] on 1&amp;nbsp;December 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=36820|supp=yes|startpage=5515|date=28 November 1944|accessdate= 20 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/items/ACCNUM_LARGE/RCDIG1068966/RCDIG1068966--318-.JPG|format=PDF|title=Recommendation: Military Cross|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is thought to be one of only five or six RAAF pilots to receive the MC during World War&amp;nbsp;II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt;

Posted to Britain in April 1944, Barr went ashore at [[Omaha Beach]] two days after [[Normandy landings|D-Day]] as part of an air support control unit. During the [[Operation Overlord|campaign in Normandy]], he flew rocket-armed [[Hawker Typhoon]]s on operations against [[V-1 flying bomb]] launch sites.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 247, 253–257&lt;/ref&gt; After his return to Australia on 11&amp;nbsp;September, Barr was promoted to acting [[Wing Commander (rank)|wing commander]] and appointed chief instructor at [[No. 2 Operational Conversion Unit RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;2 Operational Training Unit]] in [[Mildura, Victoria|Mildura]], Victoria, taking over from Bobby Gibbes. He also went to New Guinea and flew some ground-attack missions in the Kittyhawk to gain experience in the [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|South West Pacific theatre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 263–264&lt;/ref&gt; Following the end of hostilities in August 1945, Barr was treated for recurring fever and underwent two operations on his limbs in No.&amp;nbsp;6 RAAF Hospital, [[Heidelberg, Victoria|Heidelberg]]. He was discharged from the Air Force on 8&amp;nbsp;October.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 267–268&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later career==
{{Quote box
|width=30%
|align=left
|quote=I was not very proud of the things that I was called upon to do. Nonetheless, I accepted the fact that some people have to do the killing. But when you are recruited, it's not sold to you that way and you find out that after they teach you to fly they then teach you to kill. And, uh, I didn't like it at all, but I did it&amp;nbsp;– that was my job.
|source=— Nicky Barr, ''Australian Story'', 2002&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC&quot;/&gt;
}}
After leaving the Air Force, Barr remained in Mildura with his wife, Dorothy (Dot). They had met on a blind date in 1938 and been married only a few weeks when Nicky joined the RAAF. During the war she was told on three occasions that her husband was dead.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Age&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://newsstore.fairfax.com.au/apps/viewDocument.ac?multiview=true&amp;sy=age&amp;page=1&amp;kw=nicky+barr&amp;pb=all_ffx&amp;dt=selectRange&amp;dr=10years&amp;so=relevance&amp;sf=article&amp;rc=10&amp;rm=200&amp;sp=nrm&amp;clsPage=1&amp;hids=&amp;sids=AGE0204259OTTT3VOSBU |title=Reluctant Hero|work=[[The Age]]|date=25 April 2002|page=1 (Culture section)|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The couple had two sons, born in 1945 and 1947.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dornan&quot;&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 273–274&lt;/ref&gt; Barr's injuries prevented him from returning to a rugby career, and he took up yachting as a sport. He also briefly assisted fellow No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron veteran Bobby Gibbes in an airline venture in New Guinea, before going into business as a company manager and director with civil engineering and pharmaceutical firms.&lt;ref name=&quot;AirForceNews&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dornan&quot;/&gt; Barr rejoined the RAAF on 20&amp;nbsp;March 1951 as a pilot in the active Citizen Air Force (CAF), with the acting rank of wing commander. On 15&amp;nbsp;April 1953, he transferred to the CAF reserve.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garrisson&quot;/&gt; A member of the [[Royal Air Forces Escaping Society]], Barr began travelling to Italy with his wife on a regular basis in the late 1950s to seek out and offer assistance to those who had helped him during his wartime escape attempts.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 275–276&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1961, Barr became General Manager of Meggitt Ltd, an [[Vegetable fats and oils|oilseed-crushing]] firm; he eventually rose to become Executive Chairman. The firm's board was joined in 1971 by the recently retired [[Chief of Air Force (Australia)|Chief of the Air Staff]], Air Marshal [[Alister Murdoch|Sir Alister Murdoch]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dornan&quot;/&gt; Barr's work in the industry led to his appointment in the 1983 [[New Year Honours]] as an [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire]] (OBE).&lt;ref name=&quot;AirForceNews&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=49213|supp=yes|startpage=42|date=30 December 1982|accessdate= 20 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, he became Australian representative and Chairman of the International Oil Seed Group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dornan&quot;/&gt; In June 1987, Barr accepted an invitation to join [[John Glenn]], [[Chuck Yeager]], and fifteen other famed flyers in a so-called &quot;Gathering of Eagles&quot; for a seminar at the USAF [[Air Command and Staff College]] in [[Montgomery, Alabama|Montgomery]], Alabama.&lt;ref&gt;Dornan 2005, pp. 276–277&lt;/ref&gt; Generally reluctant to talk publicly about the war, he agreed to discuss his experiences during an episode of the television series ''[[Australian Story]]'' in 2002, appearing with his biographer Peter Dornan, and Bobby Gibbes. By this time Barr was said to be receiving daily treatment for the injuries he had suffered in combat.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC&quot;/&gt; He died at the age of ninety on 12&amp;nbsp;June 2006, a few months after his wife. Four [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18 Hornet]] jet fighters from No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron overflew his funeral service on the [[Gold Coast, Queensland|Gold Coast]], Queensland.&lt;ref name=&quot;AirForceNews&quot;/&gt; He was further honoured at a [[2006 mid-year rugby test series|rugby test match between Australia and England]] at [[Docklands Stadium|Telstra Dome]] in Melbourne on 17&amp;nbsp;June, the day after his funeral.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/sport/andrew-nicky-barr-and-the-1939-wallabies-tour/2006/06/16/1149964742758.html |title=Andrew &quot;Nicky&quot; Barr and the 1939 Wallabies tour|work=The Age|date= 17 June 2006|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 September 2006, No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron dedicated a stone memorial in Barr's honour; the unveiling was attended by his sons Bob and Brian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/news/raafnews/editions/4818/topstories/story12.htm |title=Memorial honours a squadron hero|work=Air Force News|date= 5 October 2006|accessdate=26 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{Cite conference | last = Barr | first = Nicky | author2=Stokes, Edward | title = Transcript of oral history recording: Barr, Andrew William 'Nicky' (Squadron Leader) | work=The Keith Murdoch Sound Archive of Australia in the War of 1939–45 | date =3 July 1990 | publisher =[[Australian War Memorial]] | location=Canberra|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/S00939_TRAN.pdf }}
* {{cite book|last=Dornan|first=Peter|title=Nicky Barr: An Australian Air Ace|publisher=[[Allen &amp; Unwin]]|location=Crows Nest, New South Wales|year=2005|origyear=2002|isbn=1-74114-529-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Garrisson|first=A.D.|title=Australian Fighter Aces 1914–1953|url=http://airpower.airforce.gov.au/Publications/Details/220/Australian-Fighter-Aces-1914–1953.aspx|publisher=Air Power Studies Centre|location=Fairbairn, Australian Capital Territory|year=1999|isbn=0-642-26540-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Herington | first=John |year=1954| title=Australia in the War of 1939–1945: Series Three (Air) Volume III&amp;nbsp;– Air War Against Germany and Italy 1939–1943 | location=Canberra| publisher=Australian War Memorial|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070211/|isbn= |oclc=3633363}}
* {{cite book|last=Newton| first=Dennis|year=1996| title=Australian Air Aces| location=Fyshwyck, Australian Capital Territory| publisher=Aerospace Publications|isbn=1-875671-25-0}}
&lt;!---* {{cite book|last= Newton | first=Dennis |year=1996| title= Clash of Eagles | location= Kenthurst, New South Wales | publisher= Kangaroo Press |isbn=0-86417-793-3|oclc=37087446}}--&gt;
* {{cite book|last=Thomas|first=Andrew|title=Tomahawk and Kittyhawk Aces of the RAF and Commonwealth|publisher=[[Osprey Publishing|Osprey]]|location=Oxford|year=2005|isbn=978-1-84176-083-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilson| first=David|year=2005| title=The Brotherhood of Airmen| location=Crows Nest, New South Wales| publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |isbn=1-74114-333-0}}


{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box|
 title=Commanding Officer [[No. 3 Squadron RAAF]]|
 before=Squadron Leader [[Bobby Gibbes]]|
 after=Squadron Leader Bobby Gibbes|
 years=May–June 1942
}}
{{s-end}}

{{featured article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Barr, Nicky}}
[[Category:1915 births]]
[[Category:2006 deaths]]
[[Category:Australian escapees]]
[[Category:Australian prisoners of war]]
[[Category:Australian rugby union players]]
[[Category:Australian World War II flying aces]]
[[Category:Officers of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross and Bar (United Kingdom)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Cross]]
[[Category:Royal Australian Air Force officers]]
[[Category:Royal Australian Air Force personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Rugby union hookers]]</text>
      <sha1>fdt01fhyc3opw1ygsyc9u0aesghdpkz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
