<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>No. 79 Squadron RAAF</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3575929</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745916863</id>
      <parentid>745802486</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T04:14:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian Rose</username>
        <id>502570</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Finetune link; AFAIK RAAF bases were &quot;stations&quot; until 1952</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38550">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2015}}
{{Use Australian English|date=May 2015}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=No. 79 Squadron RAAF
|image=[[File:79SqnRAAFCrest.jpg|120px|No. 79 Squadron's crest|alt= Crest of 79 Squadron, Royal Australian Air Force, featuring a phoenix and the motto &quot;Born for Action&quot;]]
|caption=No. 79 Squadron's crest; the [[Phoenix (mythology)|phoenix]] symbolises the multiple occasions the squadron has been disbanded and re-formed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/About-us/Structure-of-the-RAAF/Air-Command/Air-Combat-Group/No.-78-Wing/No.-79-Squadron/?RAAF-vFul+wi4pA9gHiwBOk+jJ5DiK+zwMuCL|title=No. 79 Squadron history|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|accessdate=23 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|dates=1943–45&lt;br/&gt;1962–68&lt;br/&gt;1986–88&lt;br/&gt;1998–current
|country=Australia
|allegiance=
|branch=[[Royal Australian Air Force]]
|type=
|role=
|size=
|command_structure=[[No. 78 Wing RAAF|No. 78 Wing]]
|garrison=[[RAAF Base Pearce]]
|garrison_label=Current base
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=&quot;Born for Action&quot;
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=World War II
*[[New Britain Campaign]]
*[[Admiralty Islands campaign]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|notable_commanders=[[Alan Rawlinson]] (1943)
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=
&lt;!-- Aircraft --&gt;
|aircraft_fighter=[[Supermarine Spitfire|Spitfire]] (1943–45)&lt;br/&gt;[[CAC Sabre]] (1962–68)&lt;br/&gt;[[Dassault Mirage III|Mirage III]] (1986–88)
|aircraft_trainer=[[Aermacchi MB-326]] (1998–2001)&lt;br/&gt;[[Hawker-Siddeley Hawk|Hawk 127]] (2000–current)
|aircraft_transport=[[De Havilland Canada DHC-4 Caribou|DHC-4 Caribou]] (1986–88)
}}
'''No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron''' is a [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) flight training unit that has been formed on four occasions since 1943. The [[Squadron (aviation)|squadron]] was established in May 1943 as a fighter unit equipped with [[Supermarine Spitfire]]s, and subsequently saw combat in the [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]. Between June 1943 and the end of the war in August 1945 it flew air defence patrols to protect Allied bases and ships, escorted Australian and United States aircraft, and attacked Japanese positions. The squadron was disbanded in November 1945, but was re-formed between 1962 and 1968 to operate [[CAC Sabre]]s from [[Ubon Royal Thai Air Force Base|Ubon Air Base]] in Thailand. In this role it contributed to the defence of Thailand against a feared attack from its neighbouring states and exercised with [[United States Air Force]] units. No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron was active again at [[RMAF  Butterworth|RAAF Base Butterworth]] in Malaysia between 1986 and 1988 where it operated [[Dassault Mirage III|Mirage&amp;nbsp;III]] fighters and a single [[de Havilland Canada DHC-4 Caribou|DHC-4 Caribou]] transport during the period in which the RAAF's fighter squadrons were transitioning to new aircraft.

The squadron was re-formed in its present incarnation during 1998 and is currently stationed at [[RAAF Base Pearce]], where it has operated [[Hawker-Siddeley Hawk|Hawk&amp;nbsp;127]] jet training aircraft since 2000. The unit's main role is to provide introductory jet aircraft training to RAAF pilots as well as refresher training on the Hawk for experienced pilots. No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron also supports [[Australian Army]] and [[Royal Australian Navy]] training exercises in [[Western Australia]] and the [[Northern Territory]].

==History==

===World War II===

No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron was formed at [[RAAF Station Laverton]] in Victoria on 26&amp;nbsp;April 1943 under the command of [[flying ace]] Squadron Leader [[Alan Rawlinson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eather_92&quot;&gt;Eather (1995), p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=RAAF_HS_69 /&gt; The squadron's intended role was to use [[Supermarine Spitfire (early Merlin powered variants)|Spitfire Vc]] fighters to provide 'high cover' escort for the RAAF's [[Curtiss P-40 Warhawk|P-40 Kittyhawk]]-equipped units which were engaging Japanese forces in the [[New Guinea Campaign]]. This requirement was considered urgent, and the [[Chief of Air Force (Australia)|Chief of the Air Staff]], Air Vice Marshal [[George Jones (RAAF officer)|George Jones]], directed that No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron receive priority for the RAAF's limited stock of Spitfires.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cooper&quot;&gt;Cooper (2011)&lt;/ref&gt; The squadron moved to [[Wooloomanata Station|Wooloomanata Aerodrome]] several days after it was formed, and received its first Spitfires on 3&amp;nbsp;May.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_69&quot;&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; While at Wooloomanata No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron undertook training exercises to prepare for combat.&lt;ref name=Thomas_73 /&gt; The allocation of 24 Spitfires to the squadron resulted in [[No. 1 Wing RAAF]], which was stationed near [[Darwin, Northern Territory|Darwin]] and responsible for protecting the town against air attack, suffering a shortage of these aircraft during June and July.&lt;ref name=Cooper /&gt;
[[File:79 Sqn Spitfires Momote.jpg|thumb|left|250px|A No. 79 Squadron Spitfire Mk. VC and ground crew at [[Momote Airport|Momote Airfield]] in April 1944|alt=Black-and-white photo of two single-engined monoplane aircraft and a fuel tanker on a dirt clearing. Tropical palms are visible in the background.]]

No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron began moving to [[Goodenough Island]] in the war zone off the north coast of [[Territory of Papua|Papua]] in mid-May 1943. Its advance party departed Wooloomanata on 17&amp;nbsp;May, followed by the pilots on 4&amp;nbsp;June. The main body of ground crew sailed from [[Sydney]] on 7&amp;nbsp;June.&lt;ref name=RAAF_HS_69 /&gt; The squadron suffered its first fatality on 13&amp;nbsp;June, when Flight Lieutenant [[Virgil Brennan]]—an experienced fighter pilot who had shot down 10 Axis aircraft over [[Malta]]—died from wounds incurred when his Spitfire collided with another while they were landing at [[Cairns, Queensland|Cairns]].&lt;ref name=Thomas_73 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), pp. 69–70&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;&gt;{{Australian Dictionary of Biography|last=Wilson|first=David|year=1993|id=A130284b|title=Brennan, Virgil Paul (1920 – 1943)|accessdate=7 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the unit's transit to Goodenough Island, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron Spitfires were [[Scrambling (military)|scrambled]] from [[Gurney Airport|Gurney Airfield]] at [[Milne Bay]] on several occasions between 19 and 25&amp;nbsp;June to intercept Japanese reconnaissance aircraft, but did not damage these intruders.&lt;ref name=Thomas_73 /&gt;&lt;ref name=RAAF_HS_70 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;No. 79 Squadron (1943–1945), p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Eastern New Guinea and New Britain 1944.jpg|thumb|250px|alt=Map of eastern New Guinea and the Solomon Islands showing the locations mentioned in the article's text|Map of Eastern New Guinea, New Britain and nearby islands]]

The squadron completed its movement to Goodenough Island on 26&amp;nbsp;June and began flying air defence [[sortie]]s from [[Vivigani Airfield]] as part of [[No. 73 Wing RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;73 Wing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas_73&quot;&gt;Thomas (2009), p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_70&quot;&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; It did not intercept any Japanese aircraft while operating from this base, however. The squadron moved to [[Losuia Airport|Kirwina Airfield]] on [[Kiriwina]] between 9 and 18&amp;nbsp;August, from where it operated alongside the P-40 Kittyhawk-equipped [[No. 76 Squadron RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;76 Squadron]].&lt;ref name=Thomas_73 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_70&quot; /&gt; This was the closest Allied airfield to the major Japanese base at [[Rabaul]] and was expected to be regularly attacked. No Japanese raids were made on the airfield during the first weeks of the squadron's deployment there, however, and its pilots were disappointed to not see combat while conducting patrols in support of [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) raids on Rabaul.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (2009), pp. 73–74&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Imperial Japanese Army Air Force]] (IJAAF) began a series of attacks on Goodenough Island and Kiriwina in early October, however, and the squadron claimed its first victory in 31&amp;nbsp;October when one of its Spitfires shot down a [[Kawasaki Ki-61]] fighter {{convert|2|mi|km}} north of Kiriwina (this type of aircraft was [[World War II Allied names for Japanese aircraft|labelled]] the &quot;Tony&quot; by the Allies).&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas_74&quot;&gt;Thomas (2009), p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

After a period of training, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron flew its first sweep over Japanese-held territory on 27&amp;nbsp;November when eight Spitfires were dispatched to [[Gasmata]] on [[New Britain]]. The next day one of its Spitfires shot down a [[Mitsubishi Ki-46]] &quot;Dinah&quot; reconnaissance aircraft south of [[Kitava]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_70&quot; /&gt; As few Japanese attacks were made against Kirwina, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's pilots became restive. The offensive patrols over New Britain improved their morale, however.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odgers_127&quot;&gt;Odgers (1968), p. 127&lt;/ref&gt; Another Ki-61 was intercepted and shot down by a Spitfire on 21&amp;nbsp;December, and an [[Mitsubishi A6M Zero|A6M Mitsubishi A6M]] &quot;Zero&quot; fighter was destroyed on the ground at Gasmata seven days later. A Spitfire was lost during a patrol over New Britain on 31&amp;nbsp;December, however.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_70&quot; /&gt; During January and February 1944 the squadron conducted offensive sweeps over New Britain, strafed Japanese positions and escorted Allied bombers.&lt;ref&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), pp. 70–71&lt;/ref&gt; On 17&amp;nbsp;January, eight No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron Spitfires took part in an attack against a Japanese camp near [[Lindenhafen]] which involved 73 Australian aircraft; this was the largest RAAF operation of the war up to that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Odgers_130&quot;&gt;Odgers (1968), p. 130&lt;/ref&gt; Two Spitfires were lost during the operations in January and February.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_71&quot;&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:79 Squadron Spitfire Morotai Sept 1945.jpg|thumb|left|250px|alt=Black-and-white photo of a man wearing military uniform and two other men wearing only shorts standing on the wing of a single-engined monoplane aircraft|A No. 79 Squadron pilot (wearing uniform) and two members of the squadron's ground crew posing with a Spitfire Mk. VIII at Morotai during September 1945]]

In early 1944 No.&amp;nbsp;73 Wing was selected to support the US Army's [[Admiralty Islands campaign]]. The [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Cavalry Division]] began to land on the islands on 29&amp;nbsp;February, and the wing moved to [[Momote Airport|Momote Airstrip]] on [[Los Negros Island]] in March 1944. No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron became operational there with 24 aircraft on the 29th of the month.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_71&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Odgers_179&quot;&gt;Odgers (1968), p. 179&lt;/ref&gt; From Momote, the squadron flew ground attack sorties in support of US troops until Japanese resistance ceased.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_71&quot; /&gt; No Japanese aircraft were encountered throughout this operation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas_76&quot;&gt;Thomas (2009), p. 76&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of April, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's main role was to escort Allied shipping, though flying was hampered by a shortage of spare parts.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_71&quot; /&gt; The squadron's commanding officer, Squadron Leader M.S. Bott, was killed in an accident on 16&amp;nbsp;April. Shipping escort patrols continued in May, but difficulties maintaining the Spitfires reduced the squadron to just two operational aircraft with another 12 awaiting repair.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_71&quot; /&gt; Due to a shortage of aircraft the squadron's flying activities were limited to training sorties between August and October, and aircraft availability continued to be a problem until late November.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_71&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=Thomas_76 /&gt; On 9&amp;nbsp;November, two Spitfires unsuccessfully attempted to intercept three Japanese A6M fighters which had raided [[Hyane Harbour]]; while the Japanese force had been tracked by Allied radar for 25 minutes prior to the attack, the Spitfires were scrambled only after the raiders had left the area.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (2009), pp. 76–77&lt;/ref&gt; No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron subsequently maintained a three-aircraft patrol over Los Negros during daylight hours until 22&amp;nbsp;November. Two days later the squadron was released from operations ahead of moving to [[Darwin, Northern Territory|Darwin]] in northern Australia to be re-equipped with more modern [[Supermarine Spitfire (late Merlin powered variants)|Mark VIII Spitfires]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_71&quot; /&gt;

No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron arrived at [[Sattler Airfield]] south of Darwin on 12&amp;nbsp;January 1945 and received its new aircraft shortly afterwards. It began to move to [[Morotai]] in the [[Netherlands East Indies]] (NEI) on 6&amp;nbsp;February and became operational there as part of [[No. 80 Wing RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;80 Wing]] at the end of March. The squadron conducted ground attack sorties against Japanese positions on nearby islands until the end of the war and also became responsible for Morotai's air defence from 28&amp;nbsp;May. Although no Japanese aircraft were encountered in this area, several Spitfires were shot down by anti-aircraft fire during ground attack sorties.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_72&quot;&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas_84&quot;&gt;Thomas (2009), p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; Operations were hindered at times by personnel shortages, and many of the airmen who were posted to the unit were judged by the squadron's commander to have been inadequately trained.&lt;ref&gt;Odgers (1968), p. 442&lt;/ref&gt; On 30&amp;nbsp;July No.&amp;nbsp;80 Wing was disbanded and the squadron became the first flying unit  assigned to the newly formed [[No. 11 Group RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;11 Group]]. This group was responsible for garrison duties in much of Borneo and the eastern NEI.&lt;ref&gt;Odgers (1968), pp.  478–479&lt;/ref&gt; No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron dropped leaflets on Japanese positions after Japan agreed to surrender on 15 August and returned to Australia in October 1945. It was disbanded at [[Oakey Army Aviation Centre|Oakey Airfield]] on 12&amp;nbsp;November that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eather_93&quot;&gt;Eather (1995), p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; The unit suffered 13 fatal casualties during the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;79_Sqn_AWM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11109second_world_war.asp|title=79 Squadron RAAF|work=Australian Military Units|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=7 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In late 2010 the squadron was awarded [[battle honour]]s for its World War II service in the Pacific, New Britain and Morotai.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Smith|first=Skye|title=Recognition for 79SQN's 1940s role|url=http://digital.realviewtechnologies.com/default.aspx?xml=defencenews_airforce.xml&amp;iid=42319&amp;startpage=13&amp;crd=0&amp;searchKey=79%20Squadron|accessdate=8 May 2011|newspaper=Air Force|date=11 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ubon===

In May 1962 the Australian Government decided to deploy a squadron of [[CAC Sabre]] fighters to Thailand to bolster that country's defences. This action was undertaken as part of Australia's [[Southeast Asia Treaty Organization]] (SEATO) commitment to defend Thailand against attack from its Communist neighbours, which was thought likely to occur.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens_254&quot;&gt;Stephens (2006), p. 254&lt;/ref&gt; The United States, United Kingdom and New Zealand also deployed forces to Thailand in response to this perceived threat, though Malaysia and several other SEATO members chose not to be involved. On 28&amp;nbsp;May, Minister for Defence [[Athol Townley]] announced that Australia's contribution would be an RAAF squadron equipped with Sabre fighters.&lt;ref&gt;Edwards and Pemberton (1992), pp. 242–243&lt;/ref&gt; The eight aircraft, along with their pilots and ground crew, were drawn from [[No. 77 Squadron RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;77 Squadron]], which formed part of Australia's [[Far East Strategic Reserve|Commonwealth Strategic Reserve]] forces at [[RMAF Butterworth|RAAF Base Butterworth]] in Malaysia. In order to preserve Malaysia's neutrality, the Sabres were flown to Thailand via [[Singapore]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens_254&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Trebilco_108&quot;&gt;Trebilco (1997), p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; This force was designated No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron while at [[Tengah Air Base]] in Singapore on 29&amp;nbsp;May.&lt;ref name=Trebilco_108 /&gt;{{ref|def|(I)}}
[[File:Sabre Mk32s RAAF in Thailand early 1960s.jpg|thumb|250px|No. 79 Squadron Sabres at Ubon|alt=A monoplane aircraft with three men and a fuel tanker truck. One of the men is wearing military uniform and the other two are clad only in shorts. The aircraft is mainly painted grey, but is marked with the Royal Australian Air Force roundel and stripes on its tail. The tail of another aircraft of similar appearance is visible in the background.]]

The squadron arrived at [[Ubon Royal Thai Air Force Base|Ubon Air Base]] in the [[Ubon Ratchathani Province]] of eastern Thailand on 1&amp;nbsp;June 1962 and flew its first operational patrol four days later.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_72&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coulthard-Clark_11&quot;&gt;Coulthard-Clark (1995), p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Facilities at Ubon were initially spartan, and the pilots and ground crew lived in tents. Construction of permanent accommodation began under the supervision of [[No. 5 Airfield Construction Squadron RAAF|No. 5 Airfield Construction Squadron]] in September 1962, however, and facilities were later further improved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens_255&quot;&gt;Stephens (2006), p. 255&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Malaysia's policy of neutrality in regards the conflict in Southeast Asia, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron operated as a detachment of the RAAF force ([[No. 78 Wing RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;78 Wing]]) based at Butterworth throughout its time in Thailand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coulthard-Clark_13&quot;&gt;Coulthard-Clark (1995), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; Aircraft and personnel were regularly transferred between Butterworth and Ubon, and most pilots' nominally six-month-long [[tour of duty|tours of duty]] in Thailand were broken into several shorter periods during which they and their aircraft were illegally rotated between the two bases.&lt;ref name=Stephens_254 /&gt; In March 1963 the Defence Committee, which was the highest decision-making body of the [[Department of Defence (Australia)|Department of Defence]], recommended to [[Cabinet of Australia|Cabinet]] that No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron be withdrawn from Thailand on the grounds that the British and New Zealand contingents had left the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards_Pemberton_272&quot;&gt;Edwards and Pemberton (1992), p. 272&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frühling (2009), p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; The Cabinet's Foreign Affairs and Defence Committee decided against this on 28&amp;nbsp;March as it was believed that maintaining the squadron at Ubon helped maintain good relationships with Thailand and the United States. The Thai Government was discreetly asked if it would prefer a different form of assistance, however.&lt;ref name=Edwards_Pemberton_272 /&gt;

Throughout its period at Ubon, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron formed part of an international force tasked with defending Thailand's air space against intruders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens_255&quot; /&gt; At the start of the deployment, tensions in Thailand were such that the squadron's personnel believed that they were at war.&lt;ref name=Coulthard-Clark_11 /&gt; While the situation became more stable from late July 1962, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron maintained armed aircraft on alert at all times and scrambled Sabres when unidentified aircraft were detected. No air attacks were conducted against Thailand, however, and the unidentified aircraft that were intercepted almost always proved to be from the [[Central Intelligence Agency]]-controlled [[Air America (airline)|Air America]]. In January 1965 two Sabres accidentally overflew [[North Vietnam]] after becoming lost during a training sortie but returned safely to Ubon.&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark (1995), pp. 14–15&lt;/ref&gt;

From early April 1965, Ubon became an important base for [[United States Air Force]] (USAF) attacks on North Vietnam during the [[Vietnam War]], and No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron became part of an integrated air defence system controlled by the USAF on 25&amp;nbsp;June. This changed the status of the squadron's presence in Thailand, and RAAF Headquarters assessed that the North Vietnamese would be justified in regarding it as forming part of the air campaign against their country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens_256&quot;&gt;Stephens (2006), p. 256&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the threat of counter-attacks on Ubon, the base's ground defences were upgraded during 1966; this included the construction of defensive positions for No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's aircraft and personnel as well as the deployment of a detachment of RAAF [[Airfield Defence Guards|airfield defence guards]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Coulthard-Clark_15&quot;&gt;Coulthard-Clark (1995), p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; While the squadron did not play an active role in the war, it supported the US effort by providing air defence for Ubon and taking part in exercises with USAF aircraft in which the Sabres adopted tactics used by North Vietnamese [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-17|MiG-17]] fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_HS_73&quot;&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1965 the commander of the United States [[Pacific Air Forces]], General [[Hunter Harris, Jr.]], wrote to the chief of the RAAF, Air Marshal [[Alister Murdoch]], to suggest that No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron join the USAF operations against the [[Ho Chi Minh trail]] in southern Laos which were being covertly conducted by Ubon-based aircraft. The Thai Government indicated that it would allow the squadron to be used for this purpose as long as the Australian operations were conducted without a formal agreement or any public announcement.&lt;ref&gt;Edwards (1997), p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; On 2&amp;nbsp;March 1966 the Australian Cabinet decided to reinforce the Army and RAAF force in South Vietnam, but rejected the option of expanding the scope of RAAF operations in Thailand. This decision was made on the grounds that the expanded force in South Vietnam and existing deployments to Thailand, Malaysia and Singapore represented the maximum forces Australia could commit to the region.&lt;ref&gt;Edwards (1997), p. 94&lt;/ref&gt;

By mid-1968, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron no longer had a clear role at Ubon. The USAF had sufficient fighters based in Thailand to defend the country and was reluctant to use the Australian fighters—which were now regarded as obsolete—to intercept potentially hostile aircraft, as the squadron's [[rules of engagement]] did not allow it to pursue contacts that left Thai airspace. As a result, the Australian military's chiefs of staff determined that the RAAF presence in Thailand had outlived its political and military usefulness and decided to withdraw the squadron without replacement. No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron was taken off alert status on 26&amp;nbsp;July and disbanded at the end of the month.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eather_93&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens_257&quot;&gt;Stephens (2006), p. 257&lt;/ref&gt; On 31&amp;nbsp;March 2011 it received a battle honour for its deployment to Ubon between May 1962 and August 1968.&lt;ref name=&quot;New battle honours unveiled&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Stackpool|first=Andrew|author2=Solomou, Bill |title=New battle honours unveiled|url=http://airforcenews.realviewdigital.com/?iid=47220&amp;xml=defencenews_airforce.xml&amp;startpage=4|accessdate=14 September 2014|newspaper=Air Force|date=14 April 2011|pages=4–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{ref|def|(II)}}

===Butterworth===

On 31&amp;nbsp;March 1986, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron was re-formed at RAAF Base Butterworth as a temporary measure to cover part of the period while the RAAF's three fighter squadrons were transitioning from [[Dassault Mirage III|Mirage&amp;nbsp;III]]s to [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18 Hornets]].&lt;ref name=Eather_93 /&gt; The squadron inherited all of [[No. 3 Squadron RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron's]] twelve Mirage&amp;nbsp;IIIs fighters and most of its personnel; the remainder of No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron returned to Australia to be re-equipped with Hornets. As well as the Mirage IIIs, the squadron operated a single [[De Havilland Canada DHC-4 Caribou|DHC-4 Caribou]] transport that was also based at Butterworth.&lt;ref&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), pp. 6, 73&lt;/ref&gt;

In its new incarnation, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron continued the air defence and training duties for which No.&amp;nbsp;3 Squadron had been responsible at Butterworth.&lt;ref&gt;Air Power Development Centre (2005), p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; It participated in routine training exercises in Southeast Asia, which included making regular deployments to [[Paya Lebar Air Base]] in Singapore to train with the [[Republic of Singapore Air Force]]. In May 1987 the squadron deployed to [[Clark Air Base|Clarke Air Force Base]] in the Philippines to participate in the annual [[Red Flag – Alaska|Cope Thunder]] exercise with USAF units.&lt;ref&gt;RAAF Historical Section (1995), pp. 73–74&lt;/ref&gt; It also exercised with No. 77 Squadron's new F/A-18 Hornets in April 1988 when that unit visited Butterworth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bomball_110&quot;&gt;Bomball (1990), p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; The Caribou transport was used to support Australian Army units in Malaysia and also flew training sorties to neighbouring countries.&lt;ref name=RAAF_HS_73 /&gt;

By early 1988 both No.&amp;nbsp;3 and No.&amp;nbsp;77 Squadrons had successfully converted to the F/A-18, and No. 79 Squadron was no longer required.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eather_93&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bomball (1990), pp. 90–91&lt;/ref&gt; Preparations to return the unit's Mirages to Australia took place during the first months of 1988, and on 3&amp;nbsp;May they departed Butterworth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bomball_89&quot;&gt;Bomball (1990), p. 89&lt;/ref&gt; As the RAAF's F/A-18 Hornet squadrons were to be based in Australia, this marked the end of the permanent deployment of RAAF fighters to Butterworth that had begun in mid-1958. No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's aircraft commemorated the occasion by conducting a spectacular low-altitude flypast of the base, the first leg of which commenced at [[transonic speed]].&lt;ref&gt;Air Power Development Centre (2005), pp. 1–2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bomball (1990), p. 90&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft were flown to [[Woomera, South Australia|Woomera]] in central Australia to be placed in storage via Paya Lebar, [[Bali]], Darwin and [[RAAF Base Tindal]]. Most of No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's ground crew returned to Australia in late May, and the squadron was formally disbanded at Butterworth on 30&amp;nbsp;June 1988.&lt;ref name=Eather_93 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bomball_110&quot;/&gt;

==Current status==
[[File:RAAF Hawks formation Pearce.jpg|thumb|250px|Four No. 79 Squadron Hawks in formation near RAAF Base Pearce in November 2008|alt=Four monoplane aircraft flying in close formation. The aircraft are painted grey and have been photographed from below.]]

No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron was re-formed a third time on 1&amp;nbsp;July 1998 as a training unit located at RAAF Base Pearce near [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]] in Western Australia. The squadron was re-established by separating [[No. 25 Squadron RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;25 Squadron's]] Permanent Air Force (full-time) component from its Air Force Reserve (part-time reservist) personnel and responsibilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_25_Sqn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/Units/25sqn.aspx|title=No 25 (City of Perth) Squadron|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|accessdate=7 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The squadron initially operated [[Aermacchi MB-326]] aircraft before being re-equipped with Hawk 127 aircraft between 7&amp;nbsp;December 2000 and 4&amp;nbsp;March 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes_47&quot;&gt;Holmes (2005), p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000 No.&amp;nbsp;78 Wing was re-formed and assumed command of No.&amp;nbsp;76 and No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadrons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Liebelt|first=Simone|title=Cloudy day, bright outlook|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/news/raafnews/editions/4512/topstories/story02.htm|accessdate=13 May 2011|newspaper=Air Force|date=17 July 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Hawks experienced serviceability problems during their first 18 months with the squadron, but these were eventually rectified.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes_48&quot;&gt;Holmes (2005), p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; During October 2003 two No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron Hawks conducted a tour of Australia to belatedly commemorate the unit's 60th anniversary. During this tour the aircrew visited Alan Rawlinson at his home at [[Naracoorte, South Australia]], and later conducted a flyover of the town in his honour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Innes|first=Stuart|title=Peter jets in with plenty to celebrate|newspaper=The Advertiser|date=10 October 2003|page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Shand|first=Jenny|title=Squadron roars home for birthday bash|newspaper=Geelong Advertiser|date=14 October 2003|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The squadron made its first overseas deployment in almost twenty years during April 2006 when six Hawks and 52 personnel were dispatched to RMAF Base Butterworth to take part in [[Exercise Bersama Shield]]. This was also the first time RAAF Hawks had operated overseas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hawks make history|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/news/raafnews/editions/4806/topstories/story08.htm|accessdate=7 July 2013|newspaper=Air Force|date=20 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of May 2010, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron was equipped with 15 of the RAAF's 33 Hawks.&lt;ref name=&quot;10 years in the air&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Smith|first=Syke|title=10 years in the air|url=http://digital.realviewtechnologies.com/default.aspx?xml=defencenews_airforce.xml&amp;iid=36510&amp;startpage=8&amp;crd=0&amp;searchKey=79sqn|accessdate=8 May 2011|newspaper=Air Force|date=27 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the squadron was organised into a Training Flight, Operations Flight, and Maintenance Flight.&lt;ref name=RAAF_79_Sqn /&gt; A program to modernise all of the RAAF's Hawks to a similar standard to the Royal Air Force's Hawk T.2 aircraft began in 2014, and No. 79 Squadron is scheduled to begin operations with these aircraft in mid-2017.&lt;ref&gt;Pittaway (2014), pp. 66–67&lt;/ref&gt; The unit's Maintenance Flight was disbanded in July 2016  when responsibility for support services for the Hawks was transferred to BAE Systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Monk|first1=Shannon|title=Best of west|url=http://airforcenews.realviewdigital.com/?iid=142505#folio=16|accessdate=30 May 2016|work=Air Force|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|date=2 June 2016|page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=BAE Systems begins RAAF Hawk flightline maintenance|url=http://australianaviation.com.au/2016/07/bae-systems-begins-raaf-hawk-flightline-maintenance/|accessdate=12 July 2016|work=Australian Aviation|date=5 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In its current role No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's main responsibility is to provide introductory fast jet training to pilots who have recently graduated from [[No. 2 Flying Training School RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;2 Flying Training School]].&lt;ref name=RAAF_79_Sqn /&gt; During this training, new pilots who have been selected to fly jet aircraft are taught to operate Hawks and provided with initial instruction on jet aircraft combat tactics. In 2004, each of No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's training courses lasted for twelve weeks.&lt;ref&gt;Australian National Audit Office (2004), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; After completing their initial jet aircraft training, pilots transfer to No.&amp;nbsp;76 Squadron at [[RAAF Base Williamtown]] for advanced instruction before being posted to one of the RAAF's [[operational conversion unit]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Sadler (2006), p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron also provides introductory training on fast jets for RAAF air combat officers who have been selected to serve on board [[Boeing F/A-18E/F Super Hornet|F/A-18F Super Hornets]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Air Combat Officer Further Training|url=http://www.defencejobs.gov.au/airforce/jobs/AirCombatOfficer/FurtherTraining/?entryTypeId=8|work=Defence Jobs|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=29 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The squadron trained RAAF personnel selected to serve as navigators on board [[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark|F-111]] strike aircraft until these aircraft were replaced with Super Hornets in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;Australian National Audit Office (2004), p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Cornish|first=Murray|title=F-111 farewell: RAAF's 'pigs' no longer fly|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2010/12/03/3084047.htm|accessdate=29 May 2011|newspaper=ABC News|date=3 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron also provides refresher training on the Hawk aircraft for experienced fighter pilots.&lt;ref name=RAAF_79_Sqn /&gt;

In addition to its pilot training responsibilities, No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's Operations Flight provides aircraft to support Navy and Army training exercises.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_79_Sqn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/About_us/Structure_of_the_RAAF/Air_Command/Air_Combat_Group/No._78_Wing/No._79_Squadron/?RAAF-vFul+wi4pA9gHiwBOk+jJ5DiK+zwMuCL|title=No. 79 Squadron|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|accessdate=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These duties are undertaken by experienced pilots who did not successfully complete operational conversion training, and also by new pilots who have completed training with No.&amp;nbsp;76 Squadron and been posted back to No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron until a place becomes available in an operational conversion course. No.&amp;nbsp;76 Squadron has a similar Operations Flight.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes (2005), p. 51&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Australian National Audit Office (2004), p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; Most of No. 79 Squadron's exercises with the Navy take place off the coast of Western Australia, but aircraft are occasionally deployed to Darwin for this task.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes (2005), p. 52&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
{{note|def|(I)}} Coulthard-Clark (1995), p.&amp;nbsp;13 states that the detachment of Sabres was officially designated No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron on 24&amp;nbsp;June 1962.&lt;br&gt;
{{note|def|(II)}} No.&amp;nbsp;79 Squadron's battle honour for its service at Ubon was one of several new battle honours issued on 31&amp;nbsp;March 2011 to mark the 90th anniversary of the RAAF's formation.&lt;ref name=&quot;New battle honours unveiled&quot; /&gt;
{{refend}}

==References==
{{Commons category|No. 79 Squadron RAAF}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===

* {{cite web|last=No. 79 Squadron RAAF|title=NAA A9186, 108: No 79 Squadron April 1943&amp;nbsp;– October 1945 operations record book|url=http://recordsearch.naa.gov.au/scripts/Imagine.asp?B=1158174|work=RecordSearch|publisher=National Archives of Australia|accessdate=6 January 2011|year=1943–1945}}
* {{cite web|last=Air Power Development Centre|title=Butterworth: The RAAF's Only Overseas Base|url=http://airpower.airforce.gov.au/publications/Details/284/35-Butterworth-The-RAAFs-Only-Overseas-Base.aspx|work=Pathfinder, Issue 35, November 2005|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|accessdate=21 May 2011|year=2005}}
* {{cite book|last=Australian National Audit Office|title=Developing Air Force's Combat Aircrew : Department of Defence|year=2004|publisher=Australian National Audit Office|location=Canberra|isbn=0-642-80777-9|url=http://www.anao.gov.au/Publications/Audit-Reports/2003-2004/Developing-Air-Forces-Combat-Aircrew}}
*{{cite book|last=Bomball|first=R.J.|chapter=Roles and Disposition|editor=Susans, M.R.|title=The RAAF Mirage Story|year=1990|publisher=RAAF Museum|location=Point Cook, Victoria|isbn=0-642-14835-X}}
*{{cite web|last=Cooper|first=Anthony|title=Shortages of drop tanks, spares and Spitfires|url=http://www.darwinspitfires.com/index.php?page=shortages-of-drop-tanks-spares-and-spitfires|work=Darwin Spitfires|publisher=Anthony Cooper|year=2011|accessdate=23 October 2016}}
*{{cite book|last=Coulthard-Clark|first=Chris|title=The RAAF in Vietnam : Australian Air Involvement in the Vietnam War 1962–1975|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin in association with the Australian War Memorial|location=Sydney|year=1995|series=The Official History of Australia's Involvement in Southeast Asian Conflicts 1948–1975|isbn=1-86373-305-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Eather|first=Steve|title=Flying Squadrons of the Australian Defence Force|publisher=Aerospace Publications|location=Weston Creek, ACT|year=1995|isbn=1-875671-15-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Edwards|first=Peter|author2=Pemberton, Gregory |title=Crises and Commitments : The Politics and Diplomacy of Australia's Involvement in Southeast Asian Conflicts, 1948–1965|year=1992|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin in association with the Australian War Memorial|location=Sydney|isbn=1-86373-184-9|series=The Official History of Australia's Involvement in Southeast Asian Conflicts 1948–1975}}
* {{cite book|last=Edwards|first=Peter|title=A Nation at War : Australian Politics, Society and Diplomacy During the Vietnam War 1965–1975|year=1997|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin in association with the Australian War Memorial|location=Sydney|isbn=1-86448-282-6|series=The Official History of Australia's Involvement in Southeast Asian Conflicts 1948–1975}}
* {{cite book|last=Frühling|first=Stephan|title=A History of Australian Strategic Policy Since 1945|year=2009|publisher=Department of Defence|location=Canberra|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/strategicbasis/menu.htm|accessdate=21 June 2011}}
* {{cite magazine|last=Holmes|first=Tony|title=Fighter Pilot Nursery|magazine=Australian Aviation|date=April 2005|issue= 215|publisher=Phantom Media|location=Fyshwick|issn=	0813-0876|pages=46–53}}
* {{cite book |last=Odgers |first=George |authorlink=George Odgers |title=Air War Against Japan 1943–1945 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070210/|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 3&amp;nbsp;– Air |year=1968|edition=reprint |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra |oclc=11218821}}
* {{cite magazine|last1=Pittaway|first1=Nigel|title=Upgrading the Hawk|magazine=Aero Australia|date=October–December 2014|issue=44|pages=66–67|issn=1448-8086}}
* {{cite book|last=RAAF Historical Section|title=Units of the Royal Australian Air Force: A Concise History. Volume 2 Fighter Units|publisher=Australian Government Publishing Service|location=Canberra|year=1995|isbn=0-644-42794-9}}
* {{cite magazine|last=Sadler|first=Paul|title=76 Squadron|magazine=Australian Aviation|date=October 2006|issue= 232|publisher=Phantom Media|location=Fyshwick|issn=	0813-0876|pages=68–73}}
* {{cite book|last=Stephens|first=Alan|title=The Royal Australian Air Force: A History|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=South Melbourne|year=2006|edition=Paperback|isbn=978-0-19-555541-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Thomas|first=Andrew|title=Spitfire Aces of Burma and the Pacific|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford|year=2009|series=Osprey Aircraft of the Aces|isbn=978-1-84603-422-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Trebilco|first=R.E.|title=RAAF History Conference 1997: South-East Asian Commitments 1950–1965 |chapter=Ubon|year=1998|publisher=Air Power Studies Centre|isbn= 0-642-26516-X|url=http://airpower.airforce.gov.au/Publications/Details/204/RAAF-History-Conference-1997-South-East-Asian-Commitments-19501965.aspx|editor=Mordike, John|location=Canberra}}

{{List of RAAF Squadrons}}

{{featured article}}

[[Category:RAAF squadrons|79]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1943|79]]
[[Category:Cold War history of Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>d2ctcwdc3rz91otvo7y73vtdluvbo1l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
