<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Northrop YF-23</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>547733</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750232967</id>
      <parentid>750157863</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T14:29:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fnlayson</username>
        <id>1216158</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Partial revert, mostly incorrect and that detail is not really relevant to YF-23.  The B-21 came from the later [[Long Range Strike Bomber program]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22592">{{redirect|YF-23|other uses|YF-23 (disambiguation)}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, and guidelines. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
 |name= YF-23
 |image= Northrop YF-23 DFRC.jpg
 |caption= YF-23, nicknamed ''Gray Ghost'' (foreground), flying with YF-23 ''Black Widow II'' |alt=Gray and black jet fighters overflying rocky and barren terrain with the gray jet in the foreground.
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
 |type= [[Fighter aircraft|Stealth fighter]] technology demonstrator
 |national origin= United States
 |manufacturer= [[Northrop Corporation|Northrop]]/[[McDonnell Douglas]]
 |designer=
 |first flight= 27 August 1990
 |introduced=
 |status= Canceled
 |primary user= [[United States Air Force]]
 |more users=
 |produced= 1989–90
 |number built= 2
 |program cost=
 |unit cost=
 |developed from=
 |variants with their own articles=
}}
|}

The '''Northrop/McDonnell Douglas YF-23''' was an American single-seat, [[twinjet|twin-engine]] [[Stealth aircraft|stealth]] [[fighter aircraft]] technology demonstrator designed for the [[United States Air Force]] (USAF). The design was a finalist in the USAF's [[Advanced Tactical Fighter]] (ATF) competition, battling the [[Lockheed YF-22]] for a production contract. Two YF-23 prototypes were built with the nicknames &quot;Black Widow II&quot; and &quot;Gray Ghost&quot;.

In the 1980s, the USAF began looking for a replacement for its fighter aircraft, especially to counter the USSR's advanced [[Sukhoi Su-27]] and [[Mikoyan MiG-29]]. Several companies submitted design proposals; the USAF selected proposals from [[Northrop Corporation|Northrop]] and [[Lockheed Corporation|Lockheed]]. Northrop teamed with [[McDonnell Douglas]] to develop the YF-23, while Lockheed, [[Boeing]] and [[General Dynamics]] developed the YF-22.

The YF-23 was stealthier and faster, but less agile than its competitor. After a four-year development and evaluation process, the YF-22 was announced the winner in 1991 and entered production as the [[Lockheed Martin F-22 Raptor]]. The U.S. Navy considered using the production version of the ATF as the basis for a replacement to the [[Grumman F-14 Tomcat|F-14]], but these plans were later canceled. The two YF-23 prototypes were museum exhibits as of 2010.

==Development==
American reconnaissance satellites first spotted the advanced Soviet [[Sukhoi Su-27|Su-27]] and [[Mikoyan MiG-29|MiG-29]] fighter prototypes in 1978, which caused concern in the U.S. Both Soviet models were expected to reduce the maneuverability advantage of contemporary US fighter aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Rich, Michael and William Stanley. [https://www.rand.org/pubs/reports/2006/R3113.1.pdf ''Improving U.S. Air Force Readiness and Sustainability'']. Rand Publications, April 1984. p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1981, the USAF requested information from several aerospace companies on possible features for an [[Advanced Tactical Fighter]] (ATF) to replace the [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle|F-15 Eagle]]. After discussions with aerospace companies, the USAF made [[air superiority fighter|air-to-air combat]] the primary role for the ATF.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_p10-3&gt;Sweetman 1991, pp. 10–13.&lt;/ref&gt; The ATF was to take advantage of emerging technologies, including [[composite material]]s, lightweight [[alloy]]s, advanced flight-control systems, more powerful propulsion systems, and [[stealth technology]].&lt;ref name=Miller_p11&gt;Miller 2005, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;  In October 1985, the USAF issued a [[request for proposal]] (RFP) to several aircraft manufacturers. The RFP was modified in May 1986 to include evaluation of prototype air vehicles from the two finalists. At the same time, the U.S. Navy, under the Navalized Advanced Tactical Fighter (NATF) program, announced that it would use a derivative of the ATF winner to replace its [[Grumman F-14 Tomcat|F-14 Tomcat]]. The NATF program called for procurement of 546 aircraft along with the USAF's planned procurement of 750 aircraft.&lt;ref name=Williams_p5&gt;Williams 2002, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:YF-23 top view.jpg|thumb|left|Top view of the YF-23, showing the trapezoidal wings and separation between the forward fuselage and engine nacelles|alt=Top view of black jet aircraft, showing trapezoidal wings, engine nozzle, and two-piece tail. The separation between the forward fuselage and engine nacelles are apparent.]]
In July 1986, proposals were submitted by [[Lockheed Corporation|Lockheed]], [[Boeing]], [[General Dynamics]], McDonnell Douglas, Northrop, [[Grumman Corporation|Grumman]] and [[Rockwell International|Rockwell]]. The latter two dropped out of competition shortly thereafter.&lt;ref&gt;Miller 2005, pp. 13–14, 19.&lt;/ref&gt;  Following proposal submissions, Lockheed, Boeing, and General Dynamics formed a team to develop whichever of their proposed designs was selected, if any. Northrop and McDonnell Douglas formed a team with a similar agreement.&lt;ref&gt;Goodall 1992, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt; The Lockheed and Northrop proposals were selected as finalists on 31 October 1986. Both teams were given 50 months to build and flight-test their prototypes, and they were successful, producing the Lockheed YF-22 and the Northrop YF-23.&lt;ref&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, pp. 233–34.&lt;/ref&gt;

The YF-23 was designed to meet USAF requirements for [[Survivability (military)|survivability]], [[supercruise]], stealth, and ease of maintenance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1986/1986%20-%203004.html &quot;ATF procurement launches new era&quot;]. ''[[Flight International]]'', 15 November 1986. p. 10. Retrieved 25 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Supercruise requirements called for prolonged supersonic flight without the use of [[afterburner]]s.&lt;ref name=Goodall_p91&gt;Goodall 1992, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; Northrop drew on its experience with the [[Northrop Grumman B-2 Spirit|B-2 Spirit]] and [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18 Hornet]] to reduce the model's susceptibility to radar and [[infrared]] detection.&lt;ref name=winchester&gt;Winchester 2005, pp. 198–99.&lt;/ref&gt; The USAF initially required the aircraft to land and stop within {{convert|2000|ft|m|sigfig=3}}, which meant the use of [[thrust reversal|thrust reversers]] on their engines. In 1987, the USAF changed the runway length requirement to {{convert|3000|ft|m|sigfig=3}}, so thrust reversers were no longer needed. This allowed the aircraft to have smaller engine [[nacelle]] housings. The nacelles were not downsized on the prototypes.&lt;ref name=Miller_p23&gt;Miller 2005, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sweetman_p23_43&gt;Sweetman 1991, pp. 23, 43.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first YF-23 ([[United States military aircraft serials|serial number]] ''87-0800''), Prototype Air Vehicle 1 (PAV-1), was rolled out on 22 June 1990;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1990/1990%20-%201803.html &quot;YF-23 roll out marks ATF debut.&quot;] ''[[Flight International]]'', 27 June – 3 July 1990. p. 5. Retrieved 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; PAV-1 took its 50-minute [[maiden flight]] on 27 August with Alfred &quot;Paul&quot; Metz at the controls.&lt;ref name=Goodall_p99&gt;Goodall 1992, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; The second YF-23 (serial number ''87-0801'', PAV-2) made its first flight on 26 October, piloted by Jim Sandberg.&lt;ref name=J-L_p237/&gt; The first YF-23 was painted charcoal gray and was nicknamed &quot;Spider&quot;&lt;ref name=J-L_p237/&gt; and &quot;Black Widow II&quot;, the latter after the [[Northrop P-61 Black Widow]] of [[World War II]]. It briefly had a red hourglass marking resembling the marking on the underside of the [[Latrodectus|black widow spider]] before Northrop management had it removed.&lt;ref name=Goodall_p120&gt;Goodall 1992, p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Miller_p37&gt;Miller 2005, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Sources describe the first YF-23 fighter as being dray gray or black colored.&lt;ref name=Goodall_p120/&gt;&lt;ref name=Miller_p37/&gt;|group=N}} The second prototype was painted in two shades of gray and nicknamed &quot;Gray Ghost&quot;.&lt;ref name=Pace_p50c&gt;Pace 1999, p. 50c.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

==Design==
[[File:YF-23 front.jpg|thumb|A front view of ''87–0801'' showing the curving exterior of the design.|alt=Front view of jet aircraft showing curving exterior. The tail is V-shaped.]]

The YF-23 was an unconventional-looking aircraft, with diamond-shaped wings, a profile with substantial [[area rule|area-ruling]] to reduce [[aerodynamic drag]] at [[transonic]] speeds, and an [[Stabilator|all-moving]] [[V-tail]]. The [[cockpit]] was placed high, near the nose of the aircraft for good visibility for the pilot. The aircraft featured a [[Tricycle gear|tricycle landing gear]] configuration with a nose [[landing gear]] leg and two main landing gear legs. The weapons bay was placed on the underside of the fuselage between the nose and main landing gear.&lt;ref name=Goodall_p108&gt;Goodall 1992, pp. 108–15, 124.&lt;/ref&gt; The cockpit has a center stick and side throttle.&lt;ref name=walkround&gt;[http://www.yf-23.net/galleries/walkaround.html Walkaround]. yf-23.net&lt;/ref&gt;

It was powered by two turbofan engines with each in a separate engine [[nacelle]] with [[S-duct]]s, to shield engine [[axial compressor]]s from radar waves, on either side of the aircraft's spine.&lt;ref&gt;Sweetman 1991, pp. 42–44, 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Of the two aircraft built, the first YF-23 (PAV-1) was fitted with [[Pratt &amp; Whitney F119|Pratt &amp; Whitney YF119]] engines, while the second (PAV-2) was powered by [[General Electric YF120]] engines. The aircraft featured fixed engine nozzles, instead of [[thrust vectoring]] nozzles as on the YF-22.&lt;ref name=Miller_p23/&gt; As on the B-2, the exhaust from the YF-23's engines flowed through troughs lined with heat-[[ablation|ablating]] tiles to dissipate heat and shield the engines from [[infrared homing]] (IR) missile detection from below.&lt;ref name=winchester /&gt;

The [[flight control surfaces]] were controlled by a central management computer system. Raising the [[Flap (aircraft)|wing flaps]] and [[aileron]]s on one side and lowering them on the other provided [[Flight dynamics (aircraft)|roll]]. The V-tail fins were angled 50 degrees from the vertical. [[Flight dynamics (aircraft)|Pitch]] was mainly provided by rotating these V-tail fins in opposite directions so their front edges moved together or apart. Yaw was primarily supplied by rotating the tail fins in the same direction.  Test pilot Paul Metz stated that the YF-23 had superior high [[angle of attack]] (AoA) performance compared to legacy aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;&quot;YF-23 would undergo subtle changes if it wins competition&quot;. ''Defense Daily'' 14 January 1991&lt;/ref&gt; Deflecting the wing flaps down and ailerons up on both sides simultaneously provided for [[Air brake (aircraft)|aerodynamic braking]].&lt;ref&gt;Sweetman 1991, pp.&amp;nbsp;34–35, 43–45.&lt;/ref&gt;  To keep costs low despite the novel design, a number of &quot;[[commercial off-the-shelf]]&quot; components were used, including an F-15 nose wheel, F/A-18 main landing gear parts, and the forward cockpit components of the [[McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagle|F-15E Strike Eagle]].&lt;ref name=winchester/&gt;&lt;ref name=J-L_p237&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==
[[File:YF-22 and YF-23.jpg|thumb|left|A YF-22 in the foreground with a YF-23 in the background]]

===Evaluation===
The first YF-23, with Pratt &amp; Whitney engines, supercruised at Mach&amp;nbsp;1.43 on 18 September 1990, while the second, with General Electric engines, reached Mach&amp;nbsp;1.6 on 29 November 1990. By comparison, the YF-22 achieved Mach 1.58 in supercruise.&lt;ref name=Goodall_p102&gt;Goodall 1992, pp. 102–103.&lt;/ref&gt;  The YF-23 was tested to a top speed of Mach 1.8 with afterburners and achieved a maximum angle-of-attack of 25°.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;  The maximum speed is classified, though sources state a maximum speed greater than Mach 2 at altitude and a supercruise speed greater than Mach 1.6.&lt;ref name=Aronstein_p136&gt;Aronstein 1998, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;  The aircraft's weapons bay was configured for weapons launch, and used for testing weapons bay acoustics, but no missiles were fired; Lockheed fired [[AIM-9 Sidewinder]] and [[AIM-120 AMRAAM]] missiles successfully from its YF-22 demonstration aircraft. PAV-1 performed a fast-paced combat demonstration with six flights over a 10-hour period on 30 November 1990. Flight testing continued into December.&lt;ref name=Miller_p36_9&gt;Miller 2005, pp. 36, 39.&lt;/ref&gt; The two YF-23s flew 50 times for a total of 65.2 hours.&lt;ref&gt;Norris, Guy. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1991/1991%20-%201440.html &quot;NASA could rescue redundant YF-23s.&quot;] ''[[Flight International]]'', 5–11 June 1991. p. 16. Retrieved: 25 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The tests demonstrated Northrop's predicted performance values for the YF-23.&lt;ref name=Miller_p38-9/&gt;  The YF-23 was stealthier and faster, but the YF-22 was more agile.&lt;ref name=Goodall_p110&gt;Goodall 1992, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sweetman 1991, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

The two contractor teams submitted evaluation results with their proposals in December 1990,&lt;ref name=Miller_p38-9&gt;Miller 2005, pp. 38–39.&lt;/ref&gt; and on 23 April 1991, [[United States Secretary of the Air Force|Secretary of the Air Force]] [[Donald Rice]] announced that the YF-22 was the winner.&lt;ref name=J&amp;L_p234&gt;Jenkins and Landis 2008, p. 234.&lt;/ref&gt; The Air Force selected the YF119 engine to power the F-22 production version. The Lockheed and Pratt &amp; Whitney designs were rated higher on technical aspects, were considered lower risks, and were considered to have more effective program management.&lt;ref name=J&amp;L_p234/&gt;&lt;ref name=Miller_p38&gt;Miller 2005, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; It has been speculated in the aviation press that the YF-22 was also seen as more adaptable to the Navy's NATF, but by 1992 the U.S. Navy had abandoned NATF.&lt;ref name=Miller_p76&gt;Miller 2005, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williams 2002, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the competition, both YF-23s were transferred to NASA's [[Dryden Flight Research Center]] at [[Edwards Air Force Base|Edwards AFB]], California, without their engines.&lt;ref name=winchester/&gt;&lt;ref name=NASA_DFRC/&gt; NASA planned to use one of the aircraft to study techniques for the calibration of predicted loads to measured flight results, but this did not take place.&lt;ref name=NASA_DFRC&gt;[http://www.dfrc.nasa.gov/gallery/Photo/YF-23/index.html &quot;YF-23.&quot;] ''[[Dryden Flight Research Center|NASA Dryden Flight Research Center]]'', 20 January 1996. Retrieved: 25 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Possible revival===
In 2004, [[Northrop Grumman]] proposed a YF-23-based bomber to meet a USAF need for an interim bomber, for which the [[Lockheed Martin FB-22|FB-22]] and [[B-1R]] were also competing.&lt;ref&gt;Hebert, Adam J. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2004/November%202004/1104strike.aspx &quot;Long-Range Strike in a Hurry.&quot;] ''Air Force magazine,'' November 2004. Retrieved: 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/2004/2004-09%20-%201169.html &quot;YF-23 re-emerges for surprise bid&quot;]. ''[[Flight International]]'', 13 July 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Northrop modified aircraft PAV-2 to serve as a display model for its proposed interim bomber.&lt;ref name=Miller_p38-9/&gt; The possibility of a YF-23-based interim bomber ended with the 2006 [[Quadrennial Defense Review]], which favored a long-range bomber with much greater range.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/qdr/report/Report20060203.pdf &quot;Quadrennial Defense Review Report.&quot;] ''U.S. Department of Defense'', 6 February 2006. Retrieved 25 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hebert, Adam J. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2006/October%202006/10062018.aspx &quot;The 2018 Bomber and Its Friends.&quot;] ''Air Force magazine,'' October 2006. Retrieved 24 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The USAF has since moved on to the [[Next-Generation Bomber]] program.&lt;ref&gt;Majumdar, Dave. [http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=5520432 &quot;U.S. Air Force May Buy 175 Bombers.&quot;] ''Defense News'', 23 January 2011. Retrieved 29 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aircraft on display==
[[File:YF-23 in the restoration area of the usaf museum.jpg|thumb|Restoration work at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force|USAF Museum]]]]

Both YF-23 airframes remained in storage until mid-1996, when the aircraft were transferred to museums.&lt;ref name=NASA_DFRC/&gt; 
* YF-23A PAV-1, Air Force serial number ''87-0800'', registration number N231YF, was on display as of 2015 in the Research and Development hangar of the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] near [[Dayton, Ohio]].&lt;ref name=Nat_Museum_YF-23&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/Visit/MuseumExhibits/FactSheets/Display/tabid/509/Article/195766/northrop-mcdonnell-douglas-yf-23a-black-widow-ii.aspx &quot;Northrop-McDonnell Douglas YF-23A Black Widow II&quot;]. ''National Museum of the U.S. Air Force'', 6 November 2015.  Retrieved 27 February 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* YF-23A PAV-2, AF ser. no. ''87-0801'', registration number N232YF, was on exhibit at the [[Western Museum of Flight]] until 2004,&lt;ref name=NASA_DFRC/&gt; when it was reclaimed by Northrop Grumman and used as a display model for a YF-23-based bomber.&lt;ref name=Miller_p39&gt;Miller 2005, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; PAV-2 was returned to the Western Museum of Flight and was on display as of 2010 at the museum's new location at [[Torrance Airport]], [[Torrance, California]].&lt;ref name=YF-23_display&gt;[http://www.wmof.com/display.htm &quot;Static Displays&quot;]; [http://www.wmof.com/yf23a.htm &quot;Northrop YF-23A 'Black Widow II'&quot;]. ''[[Western Museum of Flight]]''. Retrieved 31 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Specifications (YF-23)==
[[File:YF-23 exhaust.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.25|A rear view of a YF-23, showing its tile-lined exhaust channels]]

{{Aircraft specifications
&lt;!-- If you do not understand how to use this template, please ask at [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please answer the following questions. --&gt;
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=jet
&lt;!-- Now, fill out the specs. Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses). If an item doesn't apply, like capacity, leave it blank. For additional lines, end your alt units with a right parenthesis &quot;)&quot; and start a new, fully-formatted line --&gt;
|ref= Pace,&lt;ref name=Pace_p14-6&gt;Pace 1999, pp.&amp;nbsp;14–15.&lt;/ref&gt; Sweetman,&lt;ref&gt;Sweetman 1991, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; Winchester,&lt;ref name=winchester/&gt; Aronstein,&lt;ref name=Aronstein_p136/&gt;
&lt;!--  Size and capacity --&gt;
|crew=1 (pilot)
|length main= 67 ft 5 in
|length alt= 20.60 m
|span main= 43 ft 7 in
|span alt= 13.30 m
|height main= 13 ft 11 in
|height alt= 4.30 m
|area main= 900 ft&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|area alt= 88 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|empty weight main= 29,000 lb
|empty weight alt= 13,100 kg
|loaded weight main= 51,320 lb
|loaded weight alt= 23,327 kg
|max takeoff weight main= 62,000 lb
|max takeoff weight alt= 29,000 kg
&lt;!--  Powerplant --&gt;
|engine (jet)= [[Pratt &amp; Whitney F119|Pratt &amp; Whitney YF119]] ''or'' [[General Electric YF120]]
|type of jet= [[afterburner|afterburning]] [[turbofan]] 
|number of jets= 2
|thrust main= 35,000 lbf
|thrust alt= 156 kN
&lt;!-- Not used |afterburning thrust main=
|afterburning thrust alt= --&gt;
&lt;!--  Performance --&gt;
|max speed main=&lt;br&gt;
**'''At altitude:''' [[Mach number|Mach]] 2.2+ (1,450+ mph, 2,335+ km/h)
**'''[[Supercruise]]:''' Mach 1.6+ (1,060+ mph, 1,706+ km/h)
|max speed alt=
|max speed more=
|cruise speed main=
|cruise speed alt=
|cruise speed more=
|range main= over 2,790 mi
|range alt= over 4,500 km
|range more=
|combat radius main= 750–800 nmi
|combat radius alt= 865–920 mi, 1,380–1480 km
|ceiling main= 65,000 ft
|ceiling alt= 19,800 m
|climb rate main=
|climb rate alt=
|loading main= 54 lb/ft&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|loading alt= 265 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|thrust/weight= 1.36
|armament= None as tested but provisions made for:&lt;ref name=winchester /&gt;
* 1 × 20 mm (0.79 in) [[M61 Vulcan]] cannon
* 4 × [[AIM-120 AMRAAM]] or [[AIM-7 Sparrow]] medium-range air-to-air missiles&lt;ref name=winchester/&gt;&lt;ref name=Sweetman_p42-3&gt;Sweetman 1991, pp. 42–43.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2 × [[AIM-9 Sidewinder]] short-range air-to-air missiles&lt;ref name=Sweetman_p42-3 /&gt;}}

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Air Force|Aviation}}
{{Aircontent
|see also=
|related=
|similar aircraft=
*[[Lockheed YF-22]]
|lists=
*[[List of military aircraft of the United States]]
*[[List of fighter aircraft]]
&lt;!-- See [[WP:Air/PC]] for more explanation of these fields. --&gt;
}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|group=N|50em}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* Aronstein, David C. and Michael J. Hirschberg. ''Advanced Tactical Fighter to F-22 Raptor: Origins of the 21st Century Air Dominance Fighter.'' Arlington, Virginia: AIAA (American Institute of Aeronautics &amp; Astronautics), 1998. ISBN 978-1-56347-282-4.
* Goodall, James C. &quot;The Lockheed YF-22 and Northrop YF-23 Advanced Tactical Fighters&quot;. ''America's Stealth Fighters and Bombers, B-2, F-117, YF-22, and YF-23''. St. Paul, Minnesota: Motorbooks International Publishing, 1992. ISBN 0-87938-609-6.
* Jenkins, Dennis R. and Tony R. Landis. ''Experimental &amp; Prototype U.S. Air Force Jet Fighters''. North Branch, Minnesota: Specialty Press, 2008. ISBN 978-1-58007-111-6.
* Miller, Jay. ''Lockheed Martin F/A-22 Raptor, Stealth Fighter''. Hinckley, UK: Midland Publishing, 2005. ISBN 1-85780-158-X.
* Pace, Steve. ''F-22 Raptor''. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1999. ISBN 0-07-134271-0.
* [[Bill Sweetman|Sweetman, Bill]]. ''YF-22 and YF-23 Advanced Tactical Fighters''. St. Paul, Minnesota: Motorbooks International Publishing, 1991. ISBN 0-87938-505-7.
* Williams, Mel, ed. &quot;Lockheed Martin F-22A Raptor&quot;, ''Superfighters: The Next Generation of Combat Aircraft''. London: AIRtime Publishing, 2002. ISBN 1-880588-53-6.
* Winchester, Jim, ed. &quot;Northrop/McDonnell Douglas YF-23&quot;, ''Concept Aircraft''. Rochester, Kent, UK: Grange Books, 2005. ISBN 1-84013-809-2.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons |Northrop YF-23}}
* [http://www.dfrc.nasa.gov/gallery/Photo/YF-23/HTML/EC94-42454-3.html YF-23 photos on DFRC/NASA site]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PYLiMYGBE2Q &quot;YF-23 Black Widow II, Declassified: Web of Secrecy&quot;] - documentary film (2000)
* [http://www.joebaugher.com/usaf_fighters/f23_1.html Northrop/McDonnell Douglas YF-23 page on Joe Baugher's site]
* [http://www.fighter-planes.com/info/yf23.htm YF-23 &quot;Black Widow II&quot;, Northrop/McDonnell Douglas page on fighter-planes.com]
* [http://www.yf-23.net YF-23 Enthusiast's Site, includes details about post-cancellation]

{{Northrop aircraft}}
{{McDD aircraft}}
{{US fighters}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2013}}
{{featured article}}

[[Category:McDonnell Douglas aircraft|F-023]]
[[Category:Northrop aircraft|F-023]]
[[Category:Stealth aircraft]]
[[Category:United States fighter aircraft 1990–1999|Northrop F-23]]
[[Category:V-tail aircraft]]
[[Category:Twinjets]]
[[Category:Monoplanes]]</text>
      <sha1>nuu9f99etm9bqzry13thvfsdo7ok5iz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
