<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nyon Conference</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31950058</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729953792</id>
      <parentid>708562183</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-15T18:47:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender235</username>
        <id>88026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Sources */clean up; http-&gt;https (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27014">{{Infobox summit
| summit_name  = Nyon Conference
| other_titles = 
| image        = British delegation at the Nyon Conference.png
| alt          = &lt;!-- See [[Wikipedia:Alternative text for images]] --&gt;
| caption      = An &quot;informal picture&quot; published in ''The Times'' of members of the British delegation. [[Anthony Eden]] sits to the right, accompanied by [[Lord Chatfield]] and [[Robert Gilbert Vansittart|Robert Vansittart]].
| country      = 
| date         = {{Start date|1937|09|10|df=y}}–&lt;br /&gt;{{End date|1937|09|14|df=y}}
| venues       = 
| cities       = [[Nyon]], Switzerland
| participants = {{Flatlist|
* [[Kingdom of Bulgaria|Bulgaria]]
* [[Kingdom of Egypt|Egypt]]
* [[French Third Republic|France]]
* [[Kingdom of Greece|Greece]]
* [[Kingdom of Romania|Romania]]
* [[Turkey]]
* [[United Kingdom]]
* [[Soviet Union|USSR]]
* [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]}}
| follows      = 
| precedes     = 
| website      = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
}}

The '''Nyon Conference''' was a [[diplomatic conference]] held in [[Nyon]], Switzerland in September 1937 to address attacks on international [[shipping]] in the [[Mediterranean Sea]] during the [[Spanish Civil War]]. The conference was convened in part because [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italy]] had been carrying out [[unrestricted submarine warfare]], although the final conference agreement did not accuse Italy directly; instead, the attacks were referred to as &quot;piracy&quot; by an unidentified body.  Italy was not officially at war, nor did any [[submarine]] identify itself. The conference was designed to strengthen [[non-intervention in the Spanish Civil War]].  The [[United Kingdom]] and [[French Third Republic|France]] led the conference, which was also attended by [[Kingdom of Bulgaria|Bulgaria]], [[Kingdom of Egypt|Egypt]], [[Kingdom of Greece|Greece]], [[Kingdom of Romania|Romania]], [[Turkey]], the [[Soviet Union]] and [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]].

The first agreement, signed on 14 September 1937, included plans to counterattack aggressive submarines. Naval patrols were established; the United Kingdom and France were to patrol most of the western Mediterranean and parts of the east, and the other signatories were to patrol their own waters. Italy was to be allowed to join the agreement and patrol the [[Tyrrhenian Sea]] if it wished. A second agreement followed three days later, applying similar provisions to surface ships. Italy and [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] did not attend, although the former took up naval patrols in November. In marked contrast to the actions of the [[Non-Intervention Committee]] and the [[League of Nations]], this conference succeeded in preventing attacks by submarines.

==Context and organisation==
The [[Non-Intervention Committee]], a group of twenty-four nations set up in 1936 and based in [[London]], had attempted to restrict the flow of weapons to the parties of the Spanish Civil War.&lt;ref name=&quot;review103&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;103.&lt;/ref&gt; For the United Kingdom, it formed part of the policy of appeasement towards [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] and [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italy]] and aimed at preventing a [[proxy war]]&amp;nbsp;– with Italy and Germany supporting [[National Faction (Spanish Civil War)|Franco's Nationalist Coalition]] on one side and the [[Soviet Union]] supporting the [[Republican Faction (Spanish Civil War)|Republican faction]] on the other&amp;nbsp;– from escalating into a major pan-European conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Stone (1997). p.&amp;nbsp;134.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank&quot;&gt;Frank (1987). pp.&amp;nbsp;390–391.&lt;/ref&gt;  An Anglo-Italian &quot;Gentleman's Agreement&quot; had been signed on 2 January 1937, with each party respecting the rights of the other in the Mediterranean and aimed at improving Anglo-Italian relations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank&quot;/&gt; In May 1937, [[Neville Chamberlain]] succeeded [[Stanley Baldwin]] as [[British Prime Minister]], and adopted a new policy of dealing directly with Germany and Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Mills (1993). p.&amp;nbsp;1.&lt;/ref&gt; The British believed they could convince Italy to abandon Germany through appeasement.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). pp.&amp;nbsp;475–476.&lt;/ref&gt;

Under a Non-Intervention Committee plan, neutral observers were posted to Spanish ports and borders.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas394&quot;&gt;Thomas (1961). p.&amp;nbsp;394.&lt;/ref&gt; The plan also assigned zones of patrol to the United Kingdom, France, Germany and Italy, and patrols began in April.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas395&quot;&gt;Thomas (1961). p.&amp;nbsp;395.&lt;/ref&gt; Following attacks on the German cruiser ''[[German cruiser Leipzig|Leipzig]]'' on 15 and 18 June, Germany and Italy withdrew from the patrols.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p.&amp;nbsp;457.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletin of International News'' (August 1937). pp.&amp;nbsp;4–5.&lt;/ref&gt; The United Kingdom and France offered to replace Germany and Italy in patrols of their sections, but the latter powers believed these patrols would be too partial.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin7&quot;&gt;''Bulletin of International News'' (August 1937). p.&amp;nbsp;7.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[British Admiralty]] proposed four plans in response to attacks on British shipping, favouring sending significant naval resources to the Mediterranean as the best solution;&lt;ref name=&quot;review105&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;105.&lt;/ref&gt; previous control measures had been widely evaded.&lt;ref name=&quot;review103&quot;/&gt; As suspected by the other powers, Italy was behind some of these attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;review104&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;104.&lt;/ref&gt; Whilst officially being at peace,&lt;ref name=&quot;review104&quot;/&gt; the Italian leadership had ordered the commencement of [[unrestricted submarine warfare]], referred to in discussion as a campaign of [[piracy]] without mention of Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;review105&quot;/&gt; These plans would be the basis for a Mediterranean meeting, suggested by French Foreign Minister [[Yvon Delbos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;review105&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, on the night of 31 August to 1 September, the Italian submarine [[Italian submarine Iride|''Iride'']] unsuccessfully attacked the British destroyer [[HMS Havock (H43)|''Havock'']] with torpedoes, between the [[Gulf of Valencia]] and the [[Balearic Islands]], strengthening [[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs|British Foreign Secretary]] [[Anthony Eden]]'s sceptical stance towards Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Mills (1993). p.&amp;nbsp;12.&lt;/ref&gt; The attack led the British representative in Rome to protest to the Italian Minister of Foreign Affairs, but without response.&lt;ref name=&quot;review105&quot;/&gt;

Up to 60,000 Italian volunteers were now operating in Spain,&lt;ref&gt;Alpert (1998). p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; and the removal of foreign nationals was discussed by the Non-Intervention Committee.&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletin of International News'' (August 1937). pp.&amp;nbsp;11–12.&lt;/ref&gt; Italy had made a declaration that it would stop Italian volunteers from fighting in Spain on 7 January 1937,&lt;ref&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 340.&lt;/ref&gt; and  put a [[Moratorium (law)|moratorium]] on volunteers on 20 January, also agreeing to support limitations on the number of volunteers on the 25th.&lt;ref&gt;Alpert (1998). p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt; Italy continued to request that [[belligerent rights]] be given to the Nationalists and Republicans, so both would gain the [[Search and seizure|right to search]] vessels for [[contraband]], thus removing the need for naval patrols.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas457&quot;&gt;Thomas (1961). p. 457.&lt;/ref&gt; This request was opposed by the United Kingdom, France and the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletin of International News'' (August 1937). pp.&amp;nbsp;7–8.&lt;/ref&gt; British recognition of Italian sovereignty over [[Ethiopian Empire|Abyssinia]] following the [[Second Italo-Abyssinian War]] was an important issue during Anglo-Italian discussions in August 1937. Following Eden's disagreement with Chamberlain and [[E. F. L. Wood, 1st Earl of Halifax|Lord Halifax]], [[Leader of the House of Lords]] and influential politician, over the issue, any agreement recognising Italian sovereignty was postponed until after the planned shipping conference had taken place.&lt;ref&gt;Mills (1993). p.&amp;nbsp;10–13.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 or 6 September, the British arranged a conference for all parties with a Mediterranean coastline, along with Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;review106&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;106.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas475&quot;&gt;Thomas (1961). p.&amp;nbsp;475.&lt;/ref&gt; The conference was to be held at Nyon, Switzerland&amp;nbsp;– Geneva was avoided because Italians associated it with the actions of the [[League of Nations]] over the [[Abyssinian Crisis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas475&quot;/&gt; The United Kingdom agreed to France's request to extend an invitation to the Soviet Union, but blocked France's attempt to invite a representative from [[Second Spanish Republic|Republican Spain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;review106&quot;/&gt; Portugal expressed surprise at not being invited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Portugal's Claim To A Place At Nyon |newspaper=[[The Times]] |location=London, United Kingdom |page=11 |date=13 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Camille Chautemps]], the new [[French Prime Minister]], opposed direct intervention on the Spanish question.&lt;ref&gt;Mills (1993). p.&amp;nbsp;13.&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union accepted the invitation, indicating that it would use the opportunity to blame Italy for the attacks on shipping.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Soviet Acceptance: Accusation of Italy Demanded |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=8 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Soviet government formally accused the Italians of sinking two Soviet merchant vessels, [[List of foreign ships wrecked or lost in the Spanish Civil War#Soviet flag|the ''Tuniyaev'' and the ''Blageav'']],&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas476&quot;&gt;Thomas (1961). p.&amp;nbsp;476.&lt;/ref&gt; an accusation the Italians described as &quot;aggressive and offensive&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Meeting at Nyon |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=8 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was perhaps an attempt by the Soviet Union to push Italy and Germany away from the conference.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas476&quot;/&gt; Germany rejected the invitation, stating that piracy and other issues the conference was to discuss should be handled only by normal meetings of the Non-Intervention Committee, not a conference like Nyon.&lt;ref name=&quot;times09&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Nyon Plan Declined |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=9 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; The United Kingdom and France rejected this suggestion, and continued to prepare for the conference.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas476&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;times09&quot;/&gt; Soon after, the Italians similarly declined. The Non-Intervention Committee, it said, also had the advantage of including other European powers, notably Poland and Portugal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Italy and Nyon |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=11 |date=10 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Provisions==
[[File:Map of the Nyon Conference 2.jpg|thumb|right|500px|Map of the Mediterranean, showing some of the features referred to at the conference.]] British and French naval staffs rejected the idea of a [[Convoy|convoy system]] in draft proposals. The British wanted to curb submarine activity, on the theory that focusing on covert submarine attacks would help avoid confrontation, whereas the French considered surface vessels and aircraft just as important. The French protested at a plan to create multi-nation squadrons, unhappy at the prospect of French ships coming under foreign command.&lt;ref name=&quot;review106&quot;/&gt;  On 8 September, plans were discussed in the [[British Cabinet]], including the setting up of eight groups of three [[destroyer]]s for the western Mediterranean. Preliminary talks with the French were held on 9 September,&lt;ref name=&quot;review107&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;107.&lt;/ref&gt; and the conference began on the 10th. Proceedings took two forms: discussions between the British and French, and formal meetings of all attending parties. Many of the other nations opposed the participation of the [[Soviet Navy]] in the Mediterranean,&lt;ref name=&quot;review107&quot;/&gt; so the United Kingdom and France agreed to handle [[Aegean sea|Aegean]] patrols. This was, perhaps surprisingly, accepted by the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;review108&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;108.&lt;/ref&gt;

The conference ended on 14 September with the signing of the &quot;Mediterranean Agreement&quot;. Signatories were the countries of Bulgaria, Egypt, France, Greece, Romania, Turkey, the United Kingdom, the USSR and Yugoslavia. The agreement noted attacks on neutral shipping by submarines, in contravention of the [[London Naval Treaty]] (signed in 1930) and the Submarine Protocol, part of the [[Second London Naval Treaty]] (signed in 1936).&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin12&quot;&gt;''Bulletin of International News'' (September 1937). p.&amp;nbsp;12.&lt;/ref&gt;

The agreement provided that any submarine that attacked neutral shipping was to be sunk if possible, including submarines in the vicinity of a recent attack that were determined to be responsible for the attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin12&quot;/&gt; French and British fleets would patrol the seas west of Malta and attack any suspicious submarines,&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas476&quot;/&gt; with the division of patrols between the United Kingdom and France to be decided by their governments. Both countries would patrol the [[high seas]] and territorial waters of signatory countries in the Mediterranean.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin12&quot;/&gt; The British would provide slightly more than half the 60 [[destroyer (ship)|destroyer]]s needed, with the French providing the remainder and most of the accompanying aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Success at Nyon |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=13 |date=13 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was agreed that Italy could participate in patrols of the [[Tyrrhenian Sea]] if it wished to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;review108&quot;/&gt; In the Eastern Mediterranean, British and French ships would patrol up to the [[Dardanelles]], but not in the [[Adriatic Sea]]. In this area, signatory countries would patrol their own territorial waters, and would provide any reasonable assistance to the French and British patrols. The future revision of these provisions, including the way the area had been divided into zones, was specifically allowed.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin12&quot;/&gt; Submarine activity would be banned, subject to two exemptions: travel on the surface accompanied by a [[surface ship]], and activity in certain areas for training purposes. Governments would only allow foreign submarines into each of their territorial waters in extreme situations, such as immediate distress. Merchant shipping would also be advised to stick to particular [[shipping route]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin12&quot;/&gt; The agreement repeated the suggestion that Italy join in the proposal.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin13&quot;&gt;''Bulletin of International News'' (September 1937). p.&amp;nbsp;13.&lt;/ref&gt; Delbos announced that similar proposals about surface craft would be prepared. The provisions of the agreement would come into force on 20 September.&lt;ref name=&quot;review108&quot;/&gt; The British and French knew that the secret Italian submarine operations had already been paused,&lt;ref name=&quot;review107&quot;/&gt; but actions to enforce the conference agreement started at midnight on 19/20 September.&lt;ref name=&quot;review108&quot;/&gt; The delegates to the agreement were happy; ''[[The Times]]'' likened them to [[cricket]]ers, &quot;reviewing their innings, over by over&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;review108&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;times14&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Last touches at Nyon |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=14 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The French and British naval staffs moved to Geneva, where a second agreement was signed on 17 September 1937.&lt;ref name=&quot;review109&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;109.&lt;/ref&gt; It extended the rules governing submarine warfare to surface vessels, and had the same signatories.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas477&quot;&gt;Thomas (1961). pp.&amp;nbsp;476–477.&lt;/ref&gt; Official versions of both agreements were published in French and English.&lt;ref&gt;Schindler, Toman (1988). pp.&amp;nbsp;887, 890.&lt;/ref&gt; Several proposals were not implemented: for instance, the British Admiral [[Ernle Chatfield]] wanted the Spanish parties to be able to verify that the flag a ship was displaying was correct, thereby preventing attacks on British shipping if Republican ships continued to use the British flag as a means of escape. This would have benefited the Nationalists, and the French insisted that this provision be dropped. Greece and Turkey wanted ships with a clear identifying mark to be excluded, so as to avoid being forced to fire on a German or Italian warship. This was rejected, but an amendment was made allowing nations to issue their preferred orders in their own territorial waters.&lt;ref name=&quot;review109&quot;/&gt; A suggestion to fire at any attacking aircraft was easily passed. Another suggestion on surface ships (which incorrectly stated no attack had yet been proven) was eventually toughened with the addition of a clause stating aggressors would be attacked, at the request of the French. A Soviet proposal strengthening the effect of the agreement was made.&lt;ref name=&quot;review109&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H12967, Münchener Abkommen, Chamberlain.jpg|thumb|right|Neville Chamberlain in September 1938]]
Meanwhile, on 13 September, Italy was invited to join in the agreement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Invitation Handed To Italy  |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=14 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; Italy unequivocally rejected it, refusing to patrol the [[Tyrrhenian Sea]]. It demanded &quot;absolute parity&quot; with the United Kingdom and France, meaning the same right of patrol in the Mediterranean.&lt;ref name=&quot;review110&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin14&quot;&gt;''Bulletin of International News'' (September 1937). p.&amp;nbsp;14.&lt;/ref&gt;  Italy subsequently indicated that its refusal would be reversed if such parity was granted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=A Conditional Refusal: 'Absolute Parity' Needed  |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=15 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, on the 15th, [[Benito Mussolini]]'s government sent two submarines to [[Francisco Franco]]'s [[National Faction (Spanish Civil War)|National Faction]].&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas476&quot;/&gt; The Soviet Union refused to use routes patrolled by the Italians; the Turks, Greeks and Yugoslavs refused to let the Italians use their ports.&lt;ref name=&quot;review110&quot;/&gt; A compromise was signed on 30 September,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Mediterranean Patrol: Experts' Agreement Signed  |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=16 |date=1 October 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Italian patrols started on 10 November.&lt;ref name=&quot;review111&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;111.&lt;/ref&gt;  The British government, and in particular [[Neville Chamberlain]], desired better [[Italy-United Kingdom relations|relations with Italy]] and these were achieved with the signing of the [[Anglo-Italian Agreements of 1938]].&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas477&quot;/&gt;

The patrols were a strain on the [[Royal Navy]] and the provisions were relaxed with French agreement, effective from January. Submarine activity soon returned and full patrols were resumed in early February.&lt;ref name=&quot;gretton11112&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). pp.&amp;nbsp;111–112.&lt;/ref&gt; On the whole, submarine activity during this period did not amount to much; patrols were again relaxed in May, and the agreement suspended in August.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buchanan&quot;&gt;Buchanan (1997). pp.&amp;nbsp;59–60.&lt;/ref&gt; The success of the conference was in marked contrast to the failure of the Non-Intervention Committee.&lt;ref&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;112.&lt;/ref&gt; The Nationalists and Italians switched to using air power against shipping;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buchanan&quot;/&gt; at least one ship was sunk off the Spanish coast by aircraft in the final months of 1937.&lt;ref name=&quot;gretton11112&quot;/&gt;

In the United Kingdom, Eden described the submarine attacks as savage. He also noted that attacks on submarines would be restricted to suitably extreme circumstances and that the two parties in the war would still not be able to engage neutral vessels.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin13&quot;/&gt; He was keen to avoid an &quot;Anglo-Franco-Soviet bloc&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lammers (1971). p.&amp;nbsp;173.&lt;/ref&gt; The British press was in favour of the agreement, although ''The Times'' and ''[[The Guardian#Spanish Civil War|The Guardian]]'' expressed some concerns.&lt;ref name=&quot;gretton10910&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). pp.&amp;nbsp;109–110.&lt;/ref&gt; British historians have tended to see the Nyon Conference as an important stand against aggression, with some reservations. [[Christopher Seton-Watson]] describes it as a &quot;diplomatic victory&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;interview3&quot;/&gt; but Jill Edwards points out that it failed to achieve a change in Italian policy.&lt;ref name=&quot;interview4&quot;&gt;Mills (1993). p.&amp;nbsp;4.&lt;/ref&gt; The agreement created further divisions between Eden as foreign minister and Neville Chamberlain as prime minister.&lt;ref name=&quot;interview4&quot;/&gt;

[[Maxim Litvinov]], the Soviet representative, was pleased with the outcome.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas476&quot;/&gt;  The agreement also allowed for greater military resources to be deployed to the Mediterranean as needed. Litvinov, in particular, stressed the Soviet Union's &quot;indisputable right&quot; to commit naval forces to the Mediterranean (something Germany and Italy had opposed in meetings of the Non-Intervention Committee). He also said he regretted that Spanish merchant shipping had been left out&amp;nbsp;– the other nations believed this would have amounted to formal intervention into the civil war.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulletin13&quot;/&gt; [[Aretas Akers-Douglas, 2nd Viscount Chilston|Aretas Akers-Bouglas]], Viscount Chilston and [[List of Ambassadors of the United Kingdom to Russia|British Ambassador to the Soviet Union]], reported that the Soviets considered the conference with &quot;tempered satisfaction&quot;, and that they claimed credit for their delegation's role.&lt;ref&gt;Lammers (1971). p.&amp;nbsp;172.&lt;/ref&gt;

Elsewhere, French public opinion was strongly in favour of the outcome of the conference,&lt;ref name=&quot;gretton10910&quot;/&gt; the only criticism coming from the far left that Republican ships would not receive direct protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Little Criticism |newspaper=[[The Manchester Guardian]] |location=Manchester, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=13 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German mood was restrained, where the press were satisfied by the Soviet exclusion from patrols.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=German Press and Nyon Conference|newspaper=The Manchester Guardian |location=Manchester, United Kingdom |page=12 |date=13 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Spain, the Republicans&amp;nbsp;– on the verge of disaster&amp;nbsp;– were largely in favour, and the Nationalists strongly against.&lt;ref name=&quot;review110&quot;&gt;Gretton (1975). p.&amp;nbsp;110.&lt;/ref&gt; The Republicans praised the improved safety of the shipping routes, but were somewhat unhappy that belligerent rights had not been granted to both sides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Valencia Welcomes The Trade Route Patrol  |newspaper=The Times |location=London, United Kingdom |page=11 |date=15 September 1937}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Nationalists made several complaints, including one over the route recommended to shipping, but none of these resulted in changes to the agreement.&lt;ref name=&quot;review110&quot;/&gt; The agreement was welcomed by other members of the [[League of Nations]].&lt;ref name=&quot;times14&quot;/&gt; Italian historians tend to downplay the importance of the Nyon Conference, often seeing it as a mere extension of the Non-Intervention Committee.&lt;ref name=&quot;interview3&quot;&gt;Mills (1993). p.&amp;nbsp;3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
;Books
*{{cite book |last=Alpert |first=Michael |title=A New International History of the Spanish Civil War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=p0OfRdqQEr4C|year=1998 |location=Basingstoke, United Kingdom |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-0-312-21043-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Buchanan |first=Tom |title=Britain and the Spanish Civil War |year=1997 |location=Cambridge, United Kingdom|publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0-521-45569-3}}
*{{cite book |title=The Laws of Armed Conflicts: a Collection of Conventions, Resolutions, and Other Documents |first1=Dietrich |last1=Schindler |first2=Jiří |last2=Toman |series=Scientific collection of the Henry Dunant Institute |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=k5FqSAX9HyMC |publisher=Martinus Nijhoff |location=Dordrecht, The Netherlands |edition=3rd |year=1988 |isbn=90-247-3306-5}}
*{{cite book |first=Glyn |last=Stone|title=Personalities, war and diplomacy: essays in international history |chapter=Sir Robert Vansittart and Spain, 1931–1941 |editor1-first=Thomas G. |editor1-last=Otte |editor2-first=Constantine A. |editor2-last=Pagedas |year=1997 |location=London, United Kingdom  |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-7146-4818-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Thomas |first=Hugh |title=The Spanish Civil War |authorlink=Hugh Thomas (writer)|year=1961 |location=London, United Kingdom |publisher=Eyre and Spottiswoode |edition=1st}}

;Journals
*{{cite journal|title=Spain: the British Compromise Plan|journal=Bulletin of International News|date=7 August 1937 |volume=14|issue=3|jstor=25639692 |location=London, United Kingdom |publisher=Royal Institute of International Affairs|issn=2044-3986}}
*{{cite journal|title=The Nyon Conference and its Result|journal=Bulletin of International News|date=18 September 1937 |volume=14|issue=6|jstor=25639708 |location=London, United Kingdom |publisher=Royal Institute of International Affairs|issn=2044-3986}}
*{{cite journal|title=The Nyon Conference&amp;nbsp;– The Naval Aspect|journal=The English Historical Review|date=January 1975 |first=Peter|last=Gretton|volume=90|issue=354|jstor=567512 |location=London, United Kingdom |publisher=Oxford University Press|issn=0013-8266|pages=103–112 |doi=10.1093/ehr/xc.cccliv.103}}
*{{cite journal|title=The Spanish Civil War and the Coming of the Second World War |journal=The International History Review |date=August 1987 |first=Willard C. |last=Frank |volume=9 |issue=3 |pages=368–409 |jstor=40105814 |location=Abingdon, Oxfordshire, United Kingdom  |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|issn=0707-5332 |doi=10.1080/07075332.1987.9640449}}
*{{cite journal|title=The Nyon Arrangements of 1937: A success ''sui generis'' |journal=Albion: A Quarterly Journal Concerned with British Studies |date=Winter 1971 |volume=3 |issue=4 |first=Donald N. |last=Lammers |jstor=4048234 |issn=0095-1390 |publisher=The North American Conference on British Studies |location=Denver, Colorado, United States|pages=163–176|doi=10.2307/4048234}}
*{{cite journal|title=The Nyon Conference: Neville Chamberlain, Anthony Eden, and the Appeasement of Italy in 1937|journal=The International History Review|date=February 1993 |first=William C.|last=Mills|volume=15|issue=1|jstor=40107260 |location=Abingdon, Oxfordshire, United Kingdom  |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|issn=0707-5332|pages=1–22|doi=10.1080/07075332.1993.9640636}}

{{Spanish Civil War}}

{{featured article}}

[[Category:1937 conferences]]
[[Category:1937 in international relations]]
[[Category:1937 in Switzerland]]
[[Category:Diplomatic conferences in Switzerland]]
[[Category:Naval conferences]]
[[Category:Nyon]]
[[Category:Piracy in the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:Anti-piracy]]
[[Category:Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Submarine warfare]]</text>
      <sha1>o4mqeodhkthoao9nbm8gxiwz3auif72</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
