<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Oerip Soemohardjo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35742993</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729953864</id>
      <parentid>722416238</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-15T18:47:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender235</username>
        <id>88026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */clean up; http-&gt;https (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39392">{{Infobox military person
| honorific_prefix = 
| name             = Oerip Soemohardjo
| honorific_suffix = 
| native_name      = 
| native_name_lang = 
| image            = Oerip Soemohardjo 5 November 1947 KR.JPG
| alt              = &lt;!-- A primary purpose of alt text is to benefit low-vision users who may be reading this encyclopedia with the help of screen readers. Because of this, text should be evaluated in terms of their listening qualities and not merely in terms of their spelling consistency or adherence to grammatical convention. In the provided alt text, I have used the Perfected Spelling System of the article subject's name because &quot;Oerip Soemohardjo&quot; is pronounced very poorly by my screen reader whereas it has no issues with pronouncing &quot;Urip Sumoharjo&quot;. --&gt; A three-quarter view portrait of General Urip Sumoharjo, the first chief of staff of the Indonesian National Armed Forces. He is wearing a peci hat, also called a songkok, and faces towards the viewer's left. 
| caption          = Oerip in uniform, {{circa}} 1947
| birth_date       = {{birth date|df=yes|1893|02|22}}
| death_date       = {{death date and age|df=yes|1948|11|17|1893|02|22}}
| birth_place      = [[Purworejo]], [[Dutch East Indies]]
| death_place      = [[Yogyakarta]], Indonesia
| placeofburial    = [[Kusumanegara Heroes' Cemetery]]
| placeofburial_label = 
| placeofburial_coordinates = {{coord|7|48|10|S|110|23|2|E|region:ID|display=inline}}
| nickname         = 
| birth_name       = Mohammad Sidik
| allegiance =
  {{plainlist |
* {{flag|Dutch East Indies}} &lt;small&gt;(1914–1939, 1942)&lt;/small&gt;
* {{flag|Indonesia}} &lt;small&gt;(1945–1948)&lt;/small&gt;
  }}
| branch           = 
| serviceyears     = 1914–39, 1942, 1945–48
| rank=
  {{plainlist |
* Lieutenant General
* General &lt;small&gt;(posthumous)&lt;/small&gt;
  }}
| servicenumber    = 
| unit             = 
| commands         = 
| battles          = [[Indonesian National Revolution]]
| battles_label    = 
| awards           = [[National Hero of Indonesia]]
| relations        = 
| laterwork        = 
| signature        = 
| website          = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
}}

{{Indonesian name|patronymic=yes|Soemohardjo}}
'''Oerip Soemohardjo''' ({{IPA-id|uˈrɪp sumoˈhardʒo|}}; [[Perfected Spelling System|Perfected Spelling]]: '''Urip Sumoharjo''', 22 February 1893&amp;nbsp;– 17 November 1948) was an Indonesian general and the first chief of staff of the [[Indonesian National Armed Forces]]. He received several awards from the Indonesian government, including the title [[National Hero of Indonesia]] in 1964.

Born in [[Purworejo]], [[Dutch East Indies]], Oerip exhibited leadership skills from an early age. As his parents wanted him to become a [[Bupati|regent]], after elementary school Oerip was sent to the School for Native Government Employees in [[Magelang]]. His mother died during his second year at the school, and Oerip left to undertake military training in [[Meester Cornelis]], [[Jakarta|Batavia]] (modern-day Jatinegara, Jakarta). Upon graduating in 1914, he became a lieutenant in the [[Royal Netherlands East Indies Army]]; during almost 25 years of service he was stationed on three different islands and promoted several times, eventually becoming the highest-ranking [[Native Indonesians|Native]] officer in the country.

Oerip resigned from his position in about 1938 after a disagreement with the regent of Purworejo, where he had been stationed. He and his wife Rohmah then moved to a village near [[Yogyakarta]], where they established a large garden and villa. After [[Nazi Germany]] [[Battle of the Netherlands|invaded the Netherlands]] in May 1940 Oerip was recalled to active duty. When the [[Empire of Japan]] [[Japanese occupation of Indonesia|occupied the Indies]] less than two years later, Oerip was arrested and detained in a prisoner-of-war camp for three and a half months. He spent the rest of the occupation at his villa.

On 14&amp;nbsp;October 1945, several months after [[Proclamation of Indonesian Independence|Indonesia proclaimed its independence]], Oerip was declared the chief of staff and interim leader of the newly formed army. Working to build a united force from the fractured former military groups in the country, Oerip received little oversight owing to irregularities in the chain of command. On 12&amp;nbsp;November 1945 General [[Sudirman]] was selected as leader of the armed forces, while Oerip remained as chief of staff. The two oversaw almost three years of development during the [[Indonesian National Revolution]], until Oerip resigned in early 1948 because of the political leadership's lack of trust in the army. His health deteriorated; he was already suffering from a weak heart, and he died of a heart attack a few months later. He was posthumously promoted to full general. 
{{TOC limit|2}}

== Early life ==

[[File:Birthplace of Oerip Soemohardjo.JPG|thumb|The Soemohardjo family home in Sindurjan]]
Oerip Soemohardjo was born Moehammad Sidik (&quot;Little [[Muhammad]]&quot;{{sfn|Zoetmulder|Robson|Darusupapta|Supriyitna|2006|p=1085}}) in his family's home in [[Sindurjan]], [[Purworejo]], [[Dutch East Indies]] (a colony of the Netherlands), on 22&amp;nbsp;February 1893.{{sfn|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}} He was the first son born to Soemohardjo, a headmaster and son of a local [[Muslim leader]], and his wife,{{efn|Her name is not recorded.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=3}}}} the daughter of Raden Tumenggung Widjojokoesoemo, the regent of [[Trenggalek]];{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=2}} the family later had two more sons, Iskandar and Soekirno,{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=13–15}} as well as three daughters.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=30–36}} The boys were raised partly by servants, and at a young age Sidik began showing leadership qualities, commanding groups of neighbourhood children in fishing and games of [[association football|football]]. The brothers attended the school for [[Javanese people|Javanese]] headed by their father, and as a result received special treatment; this led to them becoming complacent and frequently misbehaving.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=13–15}}

In his second year of school, Sidik fell from a [[Aleurites moluccanus|candlenut]] tree and lost consciousness.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=18–19}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=7}} After he awoke, his mother sent a letter to Widjojokoesoemo, who decided that Sidik's name was the cause of his misbehaviour.{{efn|The Javanese traditionally believed that a name that showed too high expectations could have negative effects on a child, generally making the child constantly ill.{{sfn|Andayani|2006|p=169}} Brigadier General [[Slamet Rijadi]] had his name changed for the same reason when he was young.{{sfn|Pour|2008|pp=15–16}}}} In reply, Widjojokoesoemo wrote that Sidik should be renamed Oerip, which means &quot;alive&quot;.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=6–7}} When he recovered fully, his family decided that the newly renamed Oerip&amp;nbsp;– who continued to misbehave&amp;nbsp;– should study at the local Dutch School for Girls ({{lang|nl|''Europese Lagere Meisjesschool''}}); the schools for boys were full and they hoped that the girls' school would improve Oerip's skill in Dutch, the language of the regime, as well as his temperament.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=18–19}} After a year in the girls' school, in which Oerip became calmer, he was sent to a Dutch-run school for boys.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=20}} However, his academic results continued to be poor.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=16}} Beginning in his final year of elementary school, he often visited his friend's father, an ex-soldier who had served in [[Aceh]] for twenty years, to listen to the old man's stories, which inspired Oerip to join the [[Royal Netherlands East Indies Army]] ({{lang|nl|''Koninklijk Nederlands Indisch Leger''}}, or KNIL).{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=23–25}}

After passing an exam for would-be state employees{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=21}} and several months of preparations, Oerip moved to [[Magelang]] in 1908 to attend the School for Native Government Employees ({{lang|nl|''Opleidingsschool Voor Inlandse Ambtenaren''}}, or OSVIA);{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=23–26}} his parents intended for him to become a regent like his grandfather.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=14}} The following year his brothers joined him.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=27}} After his mother died in 1909, Oerip sank into a months-long bout of depression{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=30–36}} and became withdrawn.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=20}}

After finishing the year at OSVIA, he decided to enrol at the military academy in [[Meester Cornelis]], [[Jakarta|Batavia]] (modern-day Jatinegara, Jakarta). He went there directly from Magelang, and told his brothers to inform their father, who disapproved of his son's choice.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=30–36}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=21}} Soemohardjo initially attempted to bribe his son with 1,000 [[Netherlands Indies gulden|gulden]] to return to OSVIA, but eventually agreed to pay for Oerip's tuition.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=26}} After his training, during which he found military life enjoyable, Oerip graduated from the academy in October 1914 and became a second lieutenant in the KNIL.{{sfn|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}}{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=37–39}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=27}}

== Royal Netherlands East Indies Army ==
After several days visiting his father in Purworejo, Oerip returned to Meester Cornelis where he took up a posting to Battalion&amp;nbsp;XII.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=39–43}} Even though he was the smallest man in the unit and the only [[native Indonesian|native]],{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=28}} he was placed in a position of leadership.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=39–43}} A year and half later he was sent to [[Banjarmasin]], [[Borneo]].{{sfn|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}}{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=39–43}} After a period patrolling the jungles outside Puruk Cahu and Muara Tewe, he was sent to Tanah Grogot, followed by [[Balikpapan]]. While stationed there Oerip was promoted to first lieutenant but faced discrimination as a native in the Dutch forces. In Banjarmasin he had convinced his commander to strike an ordinance forbidding non-Dutch officers from joining the football team, and by 1917 Oerip had received equal legal status with Dutch officers.{{sfn|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}}{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=44–47}} After Balikpapan Oerip was further sent to [[Samarinda]], [[Tarakan, East Kalimantan|Tarakan]], and ultimately [[Malinau]].{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=44–47}}

In Malinau, Oerip patrolled the border between the Dutch East Indies and the British-controlled [[Kingdom of Sarawak]] (part of modern-day Malaysia); he also worked to prevent conflicts and [[headhunting]] among [[Dayak people|Dayak]] tribes.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=47–48}} One day, seven years after arriving in Borneo, Oerip returned from patrol to find his home had been burned down. Upon the recommendation of a passing doctor, Oerip went back to Java, via Tarakan and [[Surabaya]], to [[Cimahi]], where he spent several months in recovery from fatigue.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=50–52}}

Fully recovered, in 1923 Oerip was stationed in his hometown, Purworejo. In September 1925 Oerip was transferred to Magelang to serve in the {{lang|nl|Maréchaussée te Voet}} (Foot Marshalry), a [[gendarmerie]].{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=53–55}} Initially known to avoid women and under pressure to marry quickly, in Magelang Oerip became involved with Rohmah Soebroto, the daughter of his former [[Javanese language|Javanese]] and [[Malay language|Malay]] language teacher Soebroto and a distant relative of female emancipation figure [[Kartini]]. The pair were engaged on 7&amp;nbsp;May 1926 and married on 30&amp;nbsp;June of the same year.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=57–58}}{{sfn|Tempo 1977, Meninggal Dunia}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=35}} Also in Magelang, Oerip took on his [[Patronymic|father's name]], which he used as a family name for dealing with the Dutch.{{efn|Family names were required by Dutch civil code for things such as land purchase.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=59}}}} Afterwards he began referring to himself by the full name of Oerip Soemohardjo, although others continued to call him Oerip.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=59}}

The year after his marriage, Oerip and his wife were stationed in [[Ambarawa]], where Oerip was tasked with rebuilding a previously disbanded unit.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=59}} While training local recruits in place of the Dutch commander who had yet to arrive, Oerip was promoted to captain.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=36}} After the Dutch commander arrived, in July 1928 Oerip was given a year's leave, which he used to travel throughout Europe on a sightseeing trip with his wife. Upon his return to the Indies, he was stationed at Meester Cornelis.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=60–62}}

In Meester Cornelis, Oerip began running training exercises; while stationed in Batavia, his father died.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=36}} In 1933, he was sent to [[Padang Panjang]] in [[Sumatra]] to deal with unrest that had already killed several Dutch officers. His time in Padang Panjang passed uneventfully, and in July 1935 he was given leave to go to Europe again.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=63–67}} He was also promoted to major at that time, which made him the highest-ranking native officer in the KNIL.{{sfn|Anderson|2005|pp=233–234}} The following year, upon his return to the Indies, he was stationed in Purworejo.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=69}} In mid-1938, after a disagreement with the local regent,{{efn|The regent was refused entry to a gala celebrating the anniversary of Queen [[Wilhelmina of the Netherlands|Wilhelmina]]'s coronation.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=38}}{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=72–73}}}} Oerip was told to transfer to [[Gombong]]; he refused, then left the KNIL and moved to his parents-in-law's home in [[Yogyakarta]].{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=38}}{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=72–73}}

== Civilian life and Japanese occupation ==
In Yogyakarta, the unemployed Oerip took up [[orchid]] gardening. Soon after arriving, he and his wife bought a villa in Gentan, north of the city. Although the villa was small, the couple used its {{convert|2|ha}} of land to open a large flower garden,{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=74–75}} with their income subsidised by Oerip's pension from the KNIL.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=47}} At his villa, named KEM (for {{lang|nl|''Klaarheid en Moed''}}, or &quot;Purity and Bravery&quot;), Oerip often received guests, both military and civilian, from whom he received information about current events and to whom he gave advice regarding military matters and politics.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=76–77}} In 1940, the pair adopted a four-year-old Dutch girl named Abby from an orphanage in [[Semarang]].{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=78–79}}

Shortly thereafter, on 10&amp;nbsp;May 1940, when [[Nazi Germany]] [[Battle of the Netherlands|invaded the Netherlands]], Oerip was recalled to active service. Three days after reporting to Colonel Pik in Magelang, he went to the KNIL headquarters in [[Bandung]],{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=80–81}} where he was the first retired officer to report.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=53}} Afterwards, he and his family&amp;nbsp;– who had joined him&amp;nbsp;– were transferred to Cimahi, where Oerip was tasked with establishing a new battalion depot. Several native officers were stationed in northern parts of the Indies during 1941 in preparation for an expected attack by the [[Empire of Japan]], although Oerip stayed in Cimahi.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=80–81}}

After the [[Japanese occupation of Indonesia|Japanese occupied the Indies]] in early 1942, Oerip was held in a mixed [[prisoner of war]] camp in Cimahi. Upon his release three and a half months later, Oerip refused an offer to form a new, Japanese-backed police force and returned to KEM,{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=83}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=54–55}} where he and his wife rented [[paddy field]]s to grow rice while continuing to operate their flower garden.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=84–87}} To protect their land, they surrounded their property and home with a high bamboo fence.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=58}} Although no longer active in the military, Oerip occasionally received former KNIL members, including [[Abdul Haris Nasution]] and Sunarmo, who brought news of events outside the village. The couple continued their work, harassed and surveilled by the Japanese and pro-Japanese Indonesians, until the [[bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]] in early August 1945 signified that Japan would soon withdraw.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=84–87}} It was during this period that Oerip began having heart problems.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=109}}

== Indonesian National Revolution and death ==

[[File:Dharma Wiratama Museum 04.jpg|350px|thumb|The first dedicated TKR headquarters, in Gondokusuman, Yogyakarta; it is now the [[Dharma Wiratama Museum]].]]
After the [[Proclamation of Indonesian Independence]] on 17&amp;nbsp;August 1945, Oerip and his family left KEM for Rohma's parents' home in Yogyakarta.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=89}} When the People's Safety Body ({{lang|id|''Badan Keamanan Rakjat''}}, or BKR) was formed on 23&amp;nbsp;August, Oerip led a group of military commanders who petitioned for it to be set up as a national military formation;{{sfn|Anderson|2005|pp=103–106}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=63}} a separate group, led by politician [[Oto Iskandar di Nata]], wanted the BKR to fulfil the functions of a police organisation. The political leadership, consisting of [[President of Indonesia|President]] [[Sukarno]] and [[Vice President of Indonesia|Vice President]] [[Mohammad Hatta]], agreed to a compromise: it became a police-style organisation, but most of its members had served in the military, either with the [[Pembela Tanah Air|Defenders of the Homeland]] ({{lang|id|''Pembela Tanah Air''}}, or PETA) or the Heihō.{{sfn|Anderson|2005|pp=103–106}}

On 14&amp;nbsp;October 1945&amp;nbsp;– nine days after the [[Indonesian National Armed Forces]] was formally established&amp;nbsp;– Oerip was declared its Chief of Staff and interim leader, and left immediately for Jakarta.{{efn|Batavia was renamed Jakarta after the Japanese invasion.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=89}} }} In a cabinet meeting the following day,{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=99–100}} he was ordered to build a national army, headquartered in Yogyakarta,{{efn|Oerip had originally suggested using Purwokerto for his headquarters, but ultimately Yogyakarta was chosen as it had better facilities and guaranteed support from the local ruler.{{sfn|Said|1991|p=28}}}} in preparation for an expected assault by Dutch troops coming to reclaim the Indies.{{sfn|Anderson|2005|pp=232–234}} He departed for Yogyakarta on 16&amp;nbsp;October, and arrived the following day. He first established the headquarters in a room at Hotel Merdeka, which he used until the Sultan of Yogyakarta [[Hamengkubuwono&amp;nbsp;IX]] donated land and a building for the army to use.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=67–68}}

With the BKR scattered under independent leadership throughout the country, the newly formed People's Security Army ({{lang|id|''Tentara Keamaanan Rakjat''}} or TKR, now known as the {{lang|id|''Tentara Nasional Indonesia''}}) drew officers mainly from the native members of the former KNIL.{{sfn|Anderson|2005|pp=232–234}} However, these officers were poorly received by Indonesian nationalists, who viewed them as mercenaries for having served in the Dutch forces. Meanwhile, [[wikt:rank and file|rank and file]] members of the TKR were drawn from numerous groups, including former PETA, current Pemuda (young Indonesian revolutionaries), and the BKR.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=99–100}}{{sfn|Anderson|2005|pp=235–237}} Although Oerip set out a command structure, in reality the army's hierarchy was provisional and depended heavily on the strength of local units.{{sfn|Anderson|2005|p=240}}

Following a government decree on 20&amp;nbsp;October Oerip became subordinate to both the acting Minister of Defence Soeljoadikoesoemo and Commander in Chief of the Armed Forces [[Soeprijadi]]. However, neither man showed up to assume his duties. Soeprijadi, a PETA soldier who had led an uprising against Japanese forces in [[Blitar]] in February 1945, was thought dead.{{efn|The historian Amrin Imran suggests that Soeprijadi's appointment may have been a way to see if he was still alive; it may have been thought that he would have certainly contacted the government in Jakarta to take over this post if he were.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=71–72}}}} While Soeljohadikosomo's position remained unfilled, the guerrilla leader [[Moestopo]] declared himself Minister of Defence. As such, Oerip had little oversight and felt pressured to quickly establish a stable command structure.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=71–72}} On 2&amp;nbsp;November, he appointed leaders for military operations in various parts of the country: Didi Kartasasmita for western Java, Soeratman for central Java, Mohammad for eastern Java, and Soehardjo Hardjowardojo for Sumatra; each of these sub-commanders was given the rank of major general.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=101}} Oerip also began appropriating weapons to different TKR commands. He took confiscated Japanese weapons from well-equipped forces and distributed them as needed.{{sfn|Sardiman|2008|p=126}} However, the results were less successful than he had hoped. PETA had been organised locally during the Japanese occupation, and as such its members were unable to accept a centralised leadership.{{sfn|Said|1991|p=31}}

[[File:Sudirman.jpg|thumb|alt=A man in a peci, looking straight forward|General [[Sudirman]] was elected as leader of the TKR on 12&amp;nbsp;November 1945. He kept Oerip as his chief of staff.]]
On 12&amp;nbsp;November 1945, at the first general meeting of army leadership, General [[Sudirman]]&amp;nbsp;– the leader of the Fifth Division in [[Purwokerto]], who had two years military experience and was 23 years younger than Oerip&amp;nbsp;– was elected leader of the army following two deadlocked votes.{{sfn|Nasution|2011|p=196}} In the third round, Oerip had 21&amp;nbsp;votes to Sudirman's 22. Divisional commanders from Sumatra, who had voted unanimously, swayed the vote in Sudirman's favour;{{sfn|Sardiman|2008|p=132}} Oerip had lost votes because some of the division leaders distrusted his history with the KNIL and the oath he had taken to the Dutch motherland upon graduation.{{sfn|Sardiman|2008|p=133}} Although Sudirman was surprised at his selection and offered to surrender the leadership position to Oerip, the meeting did not allow it; Oerip himself was glad to no longer be in charge of the army. Sudirman kept Oerip, by then a lieutenant general, to serve as chief of staff under him.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=74–79}} While Sudirman remained unconfirmed, Oerip remained ''de jure'' leader; however, the Indonesian journalist Salim Said writes that Oerip's orders were at times unintelligible owing to the leader's poor command of Indonesian and often ignored unless approved by Sudirman.{{efn|Oerip was fluent in Dutch and Javanese, but had a poor command of Indonesian, which had gained mainstream currency in the early 20th century.{{sfn|Said|1991|p=50}}}}{{sfn|Said|1991|p=50}}

When General Sudirman was approved on 18&amp;nbsp;December, he began working to consolidate and unite the army.  Meanwhile, Oerip handled day-to-day organisational and technical issues.{{sfn|Anderson|2005|p=245}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=74–79}} Many of the details, such as company uniforms, he left to regional commanders.{{efn|At the time, the Indonesian National Armed Forces did not have the resources to enforce a standard uniform nationwide.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=74–79}} }} However, to deal with more important issues, such as establishing a [[military police]] and preventing enemy [[paratrooper]]s from landing, he passed edicts that applied nationally.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=74–79}}

Together, Sudirman and Oerip were able to address many of the differences between former KNIL and PETA troops. The government also renamed the army twice in January 1946, first to the People's Security Army ({{lang|id|''Tentara Keamanan Rakjat''}}), then to the Army of the Republic of Indonesia ({{lang|id|''Tentara Repoeblik Indonesia''}}, or TRI). On 23&amp;nbsp;February 1946, Oerip was appointed head of the 11-member Committee to Reorganise the Army ({{lang|id|''Panitia Besar Reorganisasi Tentara''}}), formed by presidential decree. After four months of discussion, on 17&amp;nbsp;May the committee gave its recommendations to Sukarno. Oerip was set to handle day-to-day operations of a downsized army, while the Ministry of Defence was given greater bureaucratic power. Sudirman was kept as leader of the army.{{sfn|Anderson|2005|pp=372–373}}{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=80–81}}

As Minister of Defence [[Amir Sjarifuddin]] began establishing pro-leftist groups within the military, Oerip became distrustful of the political leadership{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=82–84}} and vehemently decried the government's attempts to use soldiers' political affiliations to control the military.{{sfn|Said|1991|p=46}} Still, he and Sudirman continued to work to ensure that [[paramilitary]] troops ({{lang|id|''laskar''}}), which had arisen from the general populace, were included in the military. This was realised on 3&amp;nbsp;June 1947, when the government declared the union of the laskar and TRI into a new military organisation, the Indonesian National Armed Forces ({{lang|id|''Tentara Nasional Indonesia''}}, or TNI). Meanwhile, Oerip established a [[military academy]] in Yogyakarta.{{sfn|Imran|1983|pp=82–84}}

[[File:Grave of Oerip Soemohardjo.JPG|thumb|left|Oerip's grave in Yogyakarta]]
To meet the Dutch threat, Oerip intended to attack while the former colonists were still consolidating their forces, a plan that was quashed by the government's attempts at diplomacy. He preferred guerrilla tactics to formal military conflicts, once telling a subordinate that the best attack would be one with a hundred snipers hidden behind enemy lines.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=85}} Oerip was strongly against the [[Renville Agreement]], an ultimately unsuccessful treaty that led to the withdrawal of 35,000&amp;nbsp;troops from western Java and the formalisation of the [[Van Mook Line]] between Dutch and Indonesian forces.{{sfn|Adi|2011|pp=79–80}} He saw the agreement, ratified on 17&amp;nbsp;January 1948, as a stalling tactic, giving the Dutch the chance to strengthen their forces.{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=104}} Meanwhile, Amir Sjarifuddin&amp;nbsp;– by then also serving as prime minister&amp;nbsp;– began culling the army, predominantly keeping leftist-leaning troops.{{sfn|Imran|1980|pp=42–45}} Disgusted with what he perceived as the government's lack of trust in the military, Oerip tendered his resignation,{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=87}} although he continued to serve as an advisor to the Minister of Defence, Vice President Hatta.{{efn|Sjariffudin had been forced to resign over general disapproval of the Renville Agreement.{{sfn|Imran|1980|pp=42–45}}}}{{sfn|KR 1948, Let. Djen. Urip Meninggal}}

After several months of growing steadily weaker and undergoing treatment from Dr Sim Ki Ay,{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=88}} on the evening of 17&amp;nbsp;November 1948 Oerip collapsed and died from a [[heart attack]] in his room in Yogyakarta. After a night-long [[Viewing (funeral)|viewing]] he was buried the next day in [[Kusumanegara Heroes' Cemetery|Semaki Heroes' Cemetery]] and posthumously promoted to general.{{sfn|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}}{{sfn|KR 1948, Let. Djen. Urip Meninggal}}{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=108–111}} When Sudirman threatened to resign in 1949, he blamed Oerip's death&amp;nbsp;– as well as his own [[tuberculosis]]&amp;nbsp;– on the government's inconsistency during the revolution.{{sfn|McGregor|2007|p=129}} Oerip was survived by his wife and adopted daughter. Abby died of malaria in January 1951,{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|p=120}} and Rohmah died on 29&amp;nbsp;October 1977 in Semarang; she was buried in [[Ungaran]].{{sfn|Tempo 1977, Meninggal Dunia}}

== Legacy ==
[[File:Oerip Soemohardjo 1993 Indonesia stamp crop.jpg|thumb|Oerip on a 1993 Indonesian stamp]]
Oerip received numerous [[Orders, decorations, and medals of Indonesia|awards from the national government]] posthumously, including the Bintang Sakti (1959), Bintang Mahaputera (1960),{{sfn|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}} Bintang Republik Indonesia Adipurna (1967),{{sfn|Indonesian State Secretariat, Bintang Republik Indonesia}} and Bintang Kartika Eka Pakçi Utama (1968).{{efn|The Bintang Sakti is a high-level military award for showing bravery above and beyond the call of duty.{{sfn|UU No. 20/2009|pp=4, 10, 23}} The Bintang Mahaputera is a high-level award for persons who have aided Indonesia's development, become experts in a certain field, or are widely recognised for their sacrifices for the country.{{sfn|UU No. 20/2009|pp=4, 9, 23}} The Bintang Republik Indonesia is the highest award available for civilians; only eight persons have received the Adipurna class.{{sfn|Indonesian State Secretariat, Bintang Republik Indonesia}}{{sfn|Saragih 2012, SBY bestows honors}} The Bintang Kartika Eka Pakçi Utama is a low-level military award for aiding the development of the army above and beyond the call of duty; Utama is the highest class.{{sfn|UU No. 20/2009|pp=4, 10, 23}}}}{{sfn|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}} On 10&amp;nbsp;December 1964 he was declared a [[National Hero of Indonesia]] through Presidential Decree 314&amp;nbsp;of 1964. Sudirman was also declared a National Hero by the same decree.{{sfn|Indonesian State Secretariat, Daftar Nama Pahlawan}}

On 22&amp;nbsp;February 1964 the Indonesian military academy in Magelang dedicated a memorial to him, which described the military leader as &quot;a son of Indonesia who valued work over words, who prioritised his Duty over his wants.&quot;{{efn|Original: &quot;''seorang putra Indonesia yang mengagungkan karya daripada kata, yang mengutamakan Dharma daripada minta.''&quot;}}{{sfn|Soemohardjo-Soebroto|1973|pp=135–136}} The academy's Catholic chapel also includes a dedication to him from 1965, prompted by a discussion between Rohmah and a missionary friend of hers.{{sfn|Imran|1983|p=90}} Several streets are named after Oerip, including in his hometown of Purworejo,{{sfn|Google Maps, Purworejo}} nearby Yogyakarta,{{sfn|Google Maps, Yogyakarta}} and the capital at Jakarta.{{sfn|Google Maps, Jakarta}}

== Notes ==

{{notelist}}

== References ==

=== Footnotes ===

{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{refbegin|colwidth=30em}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Adi
  | first = A. Kresna
  | year = 2011
  | language = Indonesian
  | title = Soedirman: Bapak Tentara Indonesia
  | trans_title = Soedirman: Father of the Indonesian Military
  | publisher = Mata Padi Pressindo
  | isbn = 978-602-95337-1-2
  | location = Yogyakarta
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Andayani
  | first = Ria
  | year = 2006
  | language = Indonesian
  | title = Adaptasi Budaya Masyarakat Lampung
  | trans_title = Cultural Adaptations in Lampung Society
  | publisher = Department of Culture and Tourism
  | location = Bandung
  | isbn = 978-979-1142-03-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=YRAr57aGrM0C
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Anderson
  | first = Benedict Richard O'Gorman
  | year = 2005
  | title = Java in a Time of Revolution: Occupation and Resistance, 1944–1946
  | publisher = Equinox
  | location = Jakarta
  | isbn = 978-979-3780-14-6
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=87totx4p3ZcC&amp;vq
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Bintang Republik Indonesia Adipurna
  | language = Indonesian
  | url = http://www.setneg.go.id/index.php?Itemid=43&amp;cat=1&amp;id=1&amp;option=com_tandajasa
  | work = Awards of the Republic of Indonesia
  | publisher = Indonesian State Secretariat
  | accessdate = 9 May 2012
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Indonesian State Secretariat, Bintang Republik Indonesia}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Daftar Nama Pahlawan Nasional Republik Indonesia
  | trans_title = List of Names of National Heroes of the Republic of Indonesia
  | language = Indonesian
  | url = http://www.setneg.go.id/index.php?Itemid=43&amp;cat=1&amp;id=1&amp;option=com_tandajasa
  | work = Awards of the Republic of Indonesia
  | publisher = Indonesian State Secretariat
  | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/67WW7R2g9
  | archivedate = 9 May 2012
  | accessdate = 9 May 2012
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Indonesian State Secretariat, Daftar Nama Pahlawan}}
  }}
* {{wikicite
  |  reference =
    {{google maps
    | title = Jakarta
    | url = http://maps.google.com.sg/maps?ll=-6.213343,106.862093&amp;spn=0.004256,0.006899=m&amp;z=17
    | accessdate = 4 September 2012
    }}
  |  ref = {{sfnRef|Google Maps, Jakarta}}
  }}
* {{wikicite
  |  reference =
    {{google maps
    | title = Purworejo
    | url = http://maps.google.com.sg/?ll=-7.708015,110.012648&amp;spn=0.008484,0.013797&amp;t=m&amp;z=16
    | accessdate = 4 September 2012
    }}
  |  ref = {{sfnRef|Google Maps, Purworejo}}
  }}
* {{wikicite
  |  reference =
    {{google maps
    | title = Yogyakarta
    | url = http://maps.google.com.sg/?ll=-7.783282,110.38305&amp;spn=0.008483,0.013797&amp;t=m&amp;z=16
    | accessdate = 4 September 2012
    }}
  |  ref = {{sfnRef|Google Maps, Yogyakarta}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Imran
  | first = Amrin
  | year = 1980
  | publisher = Mutiara
  | location = Jakarta
  | title = Panglima Besar Jenderal Soedirman
  | trans_title = Commander in Chief General Soedirman
  | language = Indonesian
  | oclc = 220643587
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Imran
  | first = Amrin
  | year = 1983
  | publisher = Department of Education and Culture
  | location = Jakarta
  | title = Urip Sumohardjo
  | trans_title = 
  | language = Indonesian
  | oclc = 10945069
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Let. Djen. Urip Meninggal
  | language = Indonesian
  | trans_title = Lt. Gen. Urip Dies
  | work = Kedaulatan Rakjat
  | date = 18 November 1948
  | ref = {{sfnRef|KR 1948, Let. Djen. Urip Meninggal}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = McGregor
  | first = Katharine E
  | year = 2007
  | title = History in Uniform: Military Ideology and the Construction of Indonesia's Past
  | location = Honolulu
  | publisher = University of Honolulu Press
  | isbn = 978-9971-69-360-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=dVxi2oXZqjkC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Meninggal Dunia
  | language = Indonesian
  | trans_title = Passed Away
  | url = http://majalah.tempointeraktif.com/id/arsip/1977/11/12/PT/mbm.19771112.PT75962.id.html
  | work = Tempo
  | date = 12 November 1977
  | accessdate = 10 May 2012
  | archivedate = 10 May 2012
  | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/67Y3vLxIc
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Tempo 1977, Meninggal Dunia}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=WrkzPcxBnLMC
  | title = Takhta untuk Rakyat: Celah-celah Kehidupan Sultan Hamengku Buwono IX
  | trans_title = Serving the People: The Life Story of Sultan Hamengku Buwono IX
  | isbn = 978-979-22-6767-9
  | editor1-first = Mohamad
  | editor1-last = Roem
  | editor1-link = Mohamad Roem
  | editor2-first = Mochtar
  | editor2-last = Lubis
  | editor2-link = Mochtar Lubis
  | editor3-first = Kustiniyati
  | editor3-last = Mochtar| last = Nasution
  | first = A. H.
  | authorlink = Abdul Haris Nasution
  | publisher = Gramedia Pustaka Utama
  | location = Jakarta
  | year = 2011
  | origyear = 1982
  | edition = Revised
  | ref = harv
  |display-editors=etal}}
* {{cite web
  | title = Oerip Soemohardjo
  | url = http://www.jakarta.go.id/english/encyclopedia/detail/2102
  | work = Encyclopedia of Jakarta
  | publisher = Jakarta City Government
  | accessdate = 9 May 2012
  | archivedate = 9 May 2012
  | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/67WUfhDjl
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Jakarta City Government, Oerip Soemohardjo}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | year = 2008
  | last = Pour
  | first = Julius
  | title = Ign. Slamet Rijadi
  | language = Indonesian
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Ukf9i3uZe7UC
  | isbn = 978-979-22-3850-1
  | publisher = Gramedia
  | location = Jakarta
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Said
  | first = Salim
  | isbn = 978-981-3035-90-4
  | year = 1991
  | title = Genesis of Power: General Sudirman and the Indonesian Military in Politics, 1945–49
  | location = Singapore
  | publisher = Institute of Southeast Asian Studies
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Saragih
  | first = Bagus BT
  | title = SBY bestows honors to late Cabinet members
  | url = http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2012/08/13/sby-bestows-honors-late-cabinet-members.html
  | work = The Jakarta Post
  | date = 13 August 2012
  | archivedate = 26 August 2012
  | accessdate = 26 August 2012
  | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/6AC6OuWK8
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Saragih 2012, SBY bestows honors}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Sardiman
  | title = Guru Bangsa: Sebuah Biografi Jenderal Sudirman
  | trans_title = Teacher of the People: A Biography of General Sudirman
  | publisher = Ombak
  | location = Yogyakarta
  | isbn = 978-979-3472-92-8
  | year = 2008
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Soemohardjo-Soebroto
  | first = Rohmah
  | year = 1973
  | publisher = Gunung Agung
  | location = Jakarta
  | title = Oerip Soemohardjo : Letnen Jenderal TNI (22 Februari 1893&amp;nbsp;– 17 November 1948)
  | trans_title = Oerip Soemohardjo : Lieutenant General of the TNI (22 February 1893&amp;nbsp;– 17 November 1948)
  | language = Indonesian
  | oclc = 13266021
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | title = Undang-Undang Republik Indonesia Nomor 20 Tahun 2009 tentang Gelar, Tanda Jasa, dan Tanda Kehormatan
  | trans_title = Law of the Republic of Indonesia Number 20 of 2009 Regarding Titles, Awards, and Recognition
  | publisher = Government of Indonesia
  | date = 18 June 2009
  | location = Jakarta
  | ref = {{sfnRef|UU No. 20/2009}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Zoetmulder
  | first1 = P. J.
  | authorlink1 = Petrus Josephus Zoetmulder
  | last2 = Robson
  | first2 = S. O.
  | last3 = Darusupapta
  | last4 = Supriyitna
  | first4 = Sumarti
  | year = 2006
  | publisher = Royal Netherlands Institute of Southeast Asian and Caribbean Studies working with Gramedia Pustaka Utama
  | location = Jakarta
  | title = Kamus Jawa Kuno Indonesia
  | trans_title = Old Javanese-Indonesian Dictionary
  | language = Indonesian
  | isbn = 978-979-605-347-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{refend}}
{{Commons category}}
{{National Heroes of Indonesia|state=collapsed}}

{{featured article}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2012}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Oerip Soemohardjo}}
[[Category:1893 births]]
[[Category:1948 deaths]]
[[Category:Indonesian generals]]
[[Category:People from Central Java]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands East Indies Army officers]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands East Indies Army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:World War II prisoners of war held by Japan]]</text>
      <sha1>5xejtd1i2ei12xd88wx703wd87uutzm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
