<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Operation Goodwood (naval)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43116930</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736541088</id>
      <parentid>733052479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-28T06:15:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nick-D</username>
        <id>415269</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Aftermath */ tweak</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40378">{{About||the July 1944 British Army offensive in Normandy|Operation Goodwood|Operation Goodwood (1968–1969)|Battle of Hat Dich}}
{{featured article}}
{{EngvarB|date=July 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Goodwood
| partof      = [[World War II]]
| image       = [[File:Fairey Barracuda and Vought F4U Corsair aircraft being armed on board HMS Formidable.jpg|300px|alt=Black and white photograph of several groups of men bent over bombs on the flight deck of an aircraft carrier at sea. Several monoplane aircraft are parked on the flight deck, and another warship is visible on the sea near the carrier.|[[Fairey Barracuda|Barracuda]] bombers and [[Vought F4U Corsair#Royal Navy|Corsair]] fighters being armed on the flight deck of {{HMS|Formidable|67|6}} during Operation Goodwood]]
| caption     = [[Fairey Barracuda|Barracuda]] bombers and [[Vought F4U Corsair#Royal Navy|Corsair]] fighters being armed on the flight deck of {{HMS|Formidable|67|6}} during Operation Goodwood&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_2009_27&quot;&gt;Brown (2009), p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;
| date        = 22–29 August 1944
| place       = [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]], Norway
| coordinates =
| map_type    =
| map_relief  =
| latitude    =
| longitude   =
| map_size    =
| map_marksize =
| map_caption =
| map_label   =
| territory   =
| result = German victory
| status =
| combatant1 = {{flagu|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany|1935}}
| combatant3  =
| commander1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Henry Ruthven Moore|Henry Moore]]
| commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Wolf Junge]]&lt;ref&gt;Williamson (2003), p. 40&lt;/ref&gt;
| commander3  =
| units1      =
| units2      =
| units3      =
| strength1   =
| strength2   =
| strength3   =
| casualties1 = 17 aircraft&lt;br&gt;1 frigate sunk&lt;br/&gt;1 escort carrier badly damaged
| casualties2 = 12 aircraft&lt;br&gt;1 battleship lightly damaged&lt;br&gt;7 other ships damaged
| casualties3 =
| notes       =
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaigns (1941 - 1945)}}
}}
'''Operation Goodwood''' was a series of unsuccessful British carrier air raids conducted against the [[German battleship Tirpitz|German battleship ''Tirpitz'']] at her anchorage in [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]], Norway, during late August 1944. It formed the last of [[List of Allied attacks on the German battleship Tirpitz|several major attacks]] made by the [[Home Fleet]] during 1944 which sought to eliminate the potential threat ''Tirpitz'' posed to Allied shipping by badly damaging or sinking the warship. While each of the previous raids on Kaafjord conducted by [[Fleet Air Arm]] aircraft had involved only a single air strike, Operation Goodwood involved repeated attacks over a week. The Royal Navy hoped that these raids would wear down the formidable German defences.

The British fleet departed its base on 18 August, and launched the first raid against Kaafjord on the morning of the 22nd. This major attack was unsuccessful, and a small raid that evening inflicted little damage. Two further major strikes were conducted on 24 and 29 August, but without success. ''Tirpitz'' was struck by two bombs during the raid on 24 August, but neither caused significant damage. British losses during Operation Goodwood were 17 aircraft to all causes, and a [[frigate]] sunk by a submarine. An [[escort carrier]] was also badly damaged. German forces suffered the loss of 12 aircraft and damage to 7 ships.

Following Operation Goodwood, responsibility for attacking ''Tirpitz'' was transferred to the [[Royal Air Force]] in late August 1944. In three [[heavy bomber]] raids conducted during September and October 1944, the battleship was first crippled and then sunk. Historians regard Operation Goodwood as a significant failure for the Fleet Air Arm, and attribute its results to shortcomings with the force's aircraft and their armament.

==Background==

From early 1942, ''Tirpitz'' posed a significant threat to the [[Arctic convoys of World War II|Allied convoys]] transporting supplies through the [[Norwegian Sea]] to the Soviet Union. Stationed in [[fjord]]s on the Norwegian coast, the battleship was capable of overwhelming the close-escort forces assigned to the Arctic convoys or breaking out into the North Atlantic.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis (1999), pp. 294–295&lt;/ref&gt; To counter this threat, the Allies needed to keep a powerful force of warships with the British [[Home Fleet]], and [[capital ship]]s accompanied most convoys part of the way to the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_9&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Faulkner_109&quot;&gt;Faulkner and Wilkinson (2012), p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Battleship Tirptiz in Kaafjord during May 1943.JPG|thumb|left|alt=Black and white aerial photo of a body of water surrounded by steep snow-topped mountains. Several ships are anchored in a bay, with the battleship Tirpitz's location being marked with an arrow.|Aerial photo of ''Tirpitz'' moored in Kaafjord]]

Several air and naval attacks were launched against ''Tirpitz'' in 1942 and 1943. On 6 March 1942, [[torpedo bomber]]s flying from the aircraft carrier {{HMS|Victorious|R38|6}} attacked the battleship while she was attempting to intercept [[Convoy PQ 12]] but did not achieve any hits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_11&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 78–83&lt;/ref&gt; Bombers from the Royal Air Force and [[Soviet Air Forces]] also attempted to strike ''Tirpitz'' in her anchorages several times in 1942 and 1943 but failed to inflict any damage.&lt;ref name=Bennett_11 /&gt; On 23 September 1943, two British [[X-class submarine|X-class]] midget submarines penetrated the defences around the battleship's main anchorage at Kaafjord in northern Norway during [[Operation Source]], and placed explosive charges in the water beneath her. This attack caused extensive damage to ''Tirpitz'', putting her out of service for six months.&lt;ref&gt;Woodman (2004), p. 340&lt;/ref&gt;

Following Operation Source, the task of attacking ''Tirpitz'' was assigned to the Home Fleet's aircraft carriers. Following months of preparations, a successful attack ([[Operation Tungsten]]) involving two strike forces of 20 [[Fairey Barracuda]] dive bombers escorted by 40 fighters was conducted on 3 April 1944. While ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s crew suffered heavy casualties during this operation, the battleship was not badly damaged.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett (2012), pp. 14–17&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, she was placed out of action for several additional months while repairs were completed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garzke_267&quot;&gt;Garzke and Dulin (1985), p. 267&lt;/ref&gt;

The Home Fleet initiated a further four raids against ''Tirpitz'' between April and July 1944, though the battleship was only attacked during the last of these operations. These attacks were hindered by the transfer of many of the Home Fleet's airmen to other units following Operation Tungsten, as the replacement aircrew were less experienced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_283&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 283&lt;/ref&gt; The first raid (Operation Planet) began on 21 April but cancelled three days later when agents stationed near Kaafjord reported bad weather over the target area.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_280 /&gt; The Home Fleet put to sea to attack ''Tirpitz'' again in mid-May in what was designated Operation Brawn.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_280&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 280&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_310&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 310&lt;/ref&gt; A strike force of 27 Barracudas escorted by [[Vought F4U Corsair]] and [[Supermarine Seafire]] fighters took off from the carriers {{HMS|Furious|47|6}} and ''Victorious'' on 15 May, but returned to the ships without attacking after they encountered heavy cloud over Kaafjord.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_36&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; The next raid, Operation Tiger Claw, was initiated in late May but cancelled due to bad weather on the 28th of the month.&lt;ref name=Brown_36 /&gt; The subsequent attack ([[Operation Mascot]]) was timed for mid-July, before the resumption of the Arctic convoys, which had been suspended since April 1944 to free up ships for the [[Normandy landings]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tarrant_129&quot;&gt;Tarrant (1994), p. 129&lt;/ref&gt; The strike force of 44 Barracudas and 40 fighters dispatched on 17 July reached the target area, but found ''Tirpitz'' cloaked in a protective smokescreen and the attack failed to inflict any damage on the battleship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_310&quot;/&gt;

==Preparations==
{{location map|Finnmark| lat = 69.9353| long = 23.0454| caption =The location of Kaafjord in northern Norway| label = Kaafjord| float = right |alt= Map of northern Norway showing the location of Kaafjord }}
In the weeks after Operation Mascot, ''Tirpitz'' continued to prepare for potential combat operations. Following trials in the sheltered waters of [[Altafjord]], she put to sea on 31 July and 1 August to train with her protective destroyers. Additional smoke generators were also installed around Kaafjord to improve the area's already strong defences.&lt;ref name=Garzke_267 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_311&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 311&lt;/ref&gt; These activities were reported by spies, and the British [[Admiralty]] interpreted them to mean that ''Tirpitz'' was being readied for a raid against Allied shipping.&lt;ref name=Bishop_311 /&gt; To defend against this threat, it was decided to conduct further attacks against the battleship at her anchorage in Kaafjord at the time of the next series of Arctic convoys.&lt;ref name=Hinsley_277 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweetman_78&quot;&gt;Sweetman (2000), p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; In reality, the German Navy was not planning to use ''Tirpitz'' offensively as she would be very vulnerable to the superior Allied naval and air forces if she put to sea. Instead, the battleship was being maintained in active service to tie down Allied warships and aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 316–317&lt;/ref&gt;

The failure of Operation Mascot convinced the commander of the Home Fleet, Admiral [[Henry Ruthven Moore|Sir Henry Moore]], that the [[Fleet Air Arm|Fleet Air Arm's]] main strike aircraft, the Fairey Barracuda dive bomber, was not suited to operations against Kaafjord. As the dive bombers' slow speed gave the defenders of Kaafjord enough time to cover ''Tirpitz'' in a smoke screen between the time incoming raids were detected and their arrival over the target area, Moore concluded that further attacks using these aircraft would be futile. However, the Admiralty judged that repeatedly striking Kaafjord with Barracudas over a 48-hour period might wear down the German defences and exhaust the supply of fuel for ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s protective smoke generators. Consideration was also given to flying fast and long-ranged [[de Havilland Mosquito]] bombers off the carriers in an attempt to achieve surprise, but none of these land-based aircraft could be spared from supporting the Allied bombing of Germany. Despite his misgivings, Moore agreed to make another attempt to strike ''Tirpitz''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_156&quot;&gt;Roskill (1961), p. 156&lt;/ref&gt;

As proposed by the Admiralty, Moore's plans for the new attack on Kaafjord involved the Home Fleet's aircraft attacking the region over several days. While the fighter aircraft involved in the previous raids had used only their machine guns to [[Strafing|strafe]] German defences in order to reduce the threat they posed to the Barracudas, it was decided to use some of these aircraft as [[dive-bombing|dive bombers]] during Operation Goodwood. In preparation, the two squadrons of Corsairs and single squadron of [[Grumman F6F Hellcat]]s selected to participate in the attack received training in dive-bombing tactics during the period between Operations Mascot and Goodwood. Another new element of the plans was a decision to use Fleet Air Arm aircraft to drop [[Naval mine|mines]] near ''Tirpitz'' and the entrance to Kaafjord. The mines dropped near the battleship were to be fitted with time-delay fuses, and it was hoped that the explosions of these devices would cause ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s captain to try to move the warship into safer waters and pass through the minefield at the fjord's entrance.&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 282–283&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_1977_37&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 37&lt;/ref&gt; During the period before Operation Goodwood, the Home Fleet's flying squadrons conducted training exercises using a target range at [[Loch Eriboll]] in northern Scotland; the terrain in this area is comparable to that around Kaafjord, and the loch had also been used for this purpose as part of the preparations for Operation Tungsten.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweetman_79&quot;&gt;Sweetman (2000), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 297&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposing forces==

The Operation Goodwood attack fleet was divided into three groups. Admiral Moore embarked on board the battleship {{HMS|Duke of York|17|6}}, which sailed with the fleet aircraft carriers {{HMS|Indefatigable|R10|6}} (the flagship of Rear Admiral [[Rhoderick McGrigor]], commander of the 1st Cruiser Squadron), {{HMS|Formidable|67|2}} and ''Furious'' as well as two [[cruiser]]s and fourteen [[destroyer]]s. The second force comprised the escort carriers {{HMS|Nabob|D77|6}} and {{HMS|Trumpeter|D09|2}}, cruiser {{HMS|Kent|54|6}} and a group of frigates. A pair of [[Replenishment oiler|fleet oilers]] escorted by four [[corvette]]s sailed separately to support the two attack groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_159&quot;&gt;Roskill (1961), p. 159&lt;/ref&gt;

The aircraft carriers embarked the largest group of Fleet Air Arm aircraft assembled up to that point in the war.&lt;ref name=Bishop_311 /&gt; Their main striking element was the 35 Barracudas assigned to [[820 Naval Air Squadron|820]], [[826 Naval Air Squadron|826]], [[827 Naval Air Squadron|827]], and [[828 Naval Air Squadron]]s which operated from the three fleet carriers. The two units of 6 Naval Fighter Wing, [[1841 Naval Air Squadron|1841]] and [[1842 Naval Air Squadron|1842 Squadrons]], flew 30 Corsairs from ''Formidable''. A total of 48 Seafires were assigned to [[801 Naval Air Squadron|801]], [[880 Naval Air Squadron|880]], [[887 Naval Air Squadron|887]] and [[894 Naval Air Squadron|894 Squadrons]] on board ''Indefatigable'' and ''Furious''. In addition, [[1770 Naval Air Squadron|1770]] and [[1840 Naval Air Squadron|1840 Squadrons]] operated 12 [[Fairey Firefly]] and 12 Hellcat fighters respectively from ''Indefatigable''. The two escort carriers embarked a total of 20 [[Grumman TBF Avenger]]s (which had responsibility for the mine-dropping element of Operation Goodwood) and 8 [[Grumman F4F Wildcat]] fighters; these aircraft were split between [[846 Naval Air Squadron|846 Squadron]] on board ''Trumpeter'' and [[852 Naval Air Squadron|852 Squadron]] on ''Nabob''.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_283 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_2009_24&quot;&gt;Brown (2009), p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;

''Tirpitz''{{'}}s anchorage at Kaafjord was heavily defended. Prior to Operation Tungsten, eleven batteries of anti-aircraft guns, several anti-aircraft warships and a system of smoke generators capable of hiding ''Tirpitz'' from aircraft were located around the fjord.&lt;ref&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), pp. 135, 151&lt;/ref&gt; After the attack, additional radar stations and observation posts were established and the number of smoke generators was increased.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_37 /&gt; ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s air defences were strengthened by fitting her with additional {{convert|20|mm|in|adj=on}} cannons, modifying the {{convert|150|mm|in|adj=on}} guns so they could be used to attack aircraft, and supplying anti-aircraft shells for her {{convert|380|mm|in|adj=on}} main guns.&lt;ref name=Garzke_267 /&gt; The German Air Force (''[[Luftwaffe]]'') had few fighters stationed at airfields near Kaafjord, and their operations were constrained by a lack of fuel.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 135&lt;/ref&gt;

==Attacks==

===22 August===
[[File:HMS Nabob.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photograph of an aircraft carrier at sea. The stern of the ship is much lower in the water than the bow.|HMS ''Nabob'' after being torpedoed on 22 August]]
The Operation Goodwood attack force sailed on 18 August. The timing of the operation was set to allow the Home Fleet to also protect [[Convoy JW 59]], which had departed from Scotland on 15 August bound for the Soviet Union. After an uneventful journey north, the attack forces arrived off Norway on 20 August. While the first attack against Kaafjord had been planned to take place on 21 August, weather conditions that day were unsuitable for flying operations, and Moore decided upon a 24-hour postponement.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_37 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Roskill_159 /&gt; The Germans were first alerted to the presence of the British fleet on 21 August when radio messages from the carriers were detected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley_277&quot;&gt;Hinsley et al. (1988), p. 277&lt;/ref&gt;

The first strike against Kaafjord was launched on 22 August. While flying conditions were poor due to low cloud, Moore decided to attack that day as some of his ships were starting to run low on fuel and would soon need to move away from Norway to refuel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweetman_80&quot;&gt;Sweetman (2000), p. 80&lt;/ref&gt; At 11:00 am a force comprising 32 Barracudas, 24 Corsairs, 11 Fireflies, 9 Hellcats and 8 Seafires was launched from the three fleet carriers.&lt;ref name=Roskill_159 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_1977_38&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 38&lt;/ref&gt; No Avengers were dispatched as the cloudy conditions were unsuitable for the execution of their task. Because few mines were available and the Avengers could not safely land while still carrying these weapons, the mine-dropping element of the plan would fail if the aircraft were unable to locate ''Tirpitz'' and had to dump their loads into the sea.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_283 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Roskill_159 /&gt;

As the strike force neared the coast, heavy cloud was sighted covering the hills near Kaafjord. Because the clouds prevented accurate bombing, the Barracudas and Corsairs returned to the carriers without attacking. The Hellcat and Firefly fighters continued on, and approached the fjord below the cloud base.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tarrant_134&quot;&gt;Tarrant (1994), p. 134&lt;/ref&gt; These aircraft achieved surprise, and ''Tirpitz'' was not obscured by smoke when they arrived over Kaafjord. The Fireflies initiated the attack at 12:49 pm by strafing German anti-aircraft guns on and around ''Tirpitz''. Two minutes later nine Hellcats attacked the battleship with {{convert|500|lb|kg|adj=on}} bombs but did not achieve any hits.&lt;ref name=Tarrant_134 /&gt; As the strike force returned to the carriers it destroyed two of ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s seaplanes in Bukta harbour and badly damaged the submarine [[German submarine U-965|''U-965'']] at [[Hammerfest (town)|Hammerfest]].&lt;ref name=Sweetman_80 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Tarrant_134 /&gt; At [[Ingøya|Ingøy]], north of Hammerfest, three Hellcats strafed a German radio station. The attack set the station's buildings ablaze and damaged the [[Antenna (radio)|aerials]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Klo |first=Allan |date=23 August 2015 |title=Bombet Ingøy radio for å svekke kommunikasjonen i Barentshavet |url=http://www.nrk.no/finnmark/bombet-ingoy-radio-for-a-svekke-kommunikasjonen-i-barentshavet-1.12510936 |publisher=[[NRK]] |location= |access-date=27 August 2015 |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt; The eight Seafires made diversionary attacks on the [[Banak, Norway|Banak]] area and a nearby seaplane base, destroying five German seaplanes.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_80 /&gt; Three British aircraft were lost during the attack on the morning of 22 August; one Hellcat and a Seafire were shot down, and one of the Barracudas was forced to ditch into the sea during its return flight.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_80 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_38 /&gt;

After the strike force was recovered, much of the Home Fleet sailed away from the Norwegian coast to refuel. A group comprising ''Formidable'', ''Furious'', two cruisers and several destroyers set a course for the two fleet oilers, and the escort carrier group withdrew so that the carriers could refuel their escorts.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_80 /&gt; At 5:25 pm, ''Nabob'' was struck by a torpedo fired from [[German submarine U-354|''U-354'']]. The carrier suffered serious damage and 21 fatalities but was able to continue limited flight operations.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_80 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_2009_28&quot;&gt;Brown (2009), p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wragg (2005), p. 135&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards ''U-354'' torpedoed the frigate {{HMS|Bickerton|K466|6}} as the latter searched for ''Nabob''{{'}}s attacker.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_160&quot;&gt;Roskill (1961), p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; ''Nabob'' was forced to return to the Home Fleet's base at [[Scapa Flow]] that evening, escorted by ''Trumpeter'', a cruiser and several destroyers.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_283 /&gt; ''Formidable'' and ''Furious'' covered their withdrawal; during this period ''Furious'' also refuelled from the Home Fleet's tankers.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_38 /&gt; The departure of both escort carriers meant that the mine-dropping component of Operation Goodwood had to be cancelled.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_283 /&gt; ''Bickerton''{{'}}s stern was wrecked by the torpedo, and she could have potentially been salvaged. However, the force's commander did not want to have to protect two crippled ships, and the frigate was [[Scuttling|scuttled]] at around 8:30 pm on 22 August.&lt;ref&gt;Brown (1990), p. 120&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after the attacks on ''Nabob'' and ''Bickerton'', Seafires from 894 Naval Air Squadron shot down two German [[Blohm &amp; Voss BV 138]] reconnaissance aircraft.&lt;ref name=Brown_2009_28 /&gt;

During the evening of 22 August, a force of eight Fireflies and six bomb-armed Hellcats from ''Indefatigable'' raided Kaafjord again.&lt;ref name=&quot;Polmar_1969_310&quot;&gt;Polmar (1969), p. 310&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first in what was intended to be a series of small harassing attacks conducted to wear down the German defences.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_81 /&gt; German forces did not detect the aircraft before they arrived over Kaafjord at 7:10 pm, and the Fireflies' strafing attacks on German gun positions killed one member of ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s crew and wounded ten. However, the Hellcats' bombs failed to inflict any damage on the battleship. The British fighters also attacked German ships and radar stations on their return flight, damaging two tankers, a supply ship and a patrol boat.&lt;ref name=Tarrant_134 /&gt; No British aircraft were lost during this raid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_171&quot;&gt;Roskill (1961), p. 171&lt;/ref&gt;

===24 August===

Fog cancelled ''Indefatigable''{{'}}s flying operations on 23 August, including a planned diversionary attack against German shipping in [[Langfjorden (Alta)|Langfjord]].&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_38 /&gt; The other two carriers and their escorts rejoined Moore and ''Indefatigable'' off Norway during the morning of 24 August. While conditions that day were initially foggy, the weather cleared enough in the afternoon to permit a strike against Kaafjord.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweetman_81&quot;&gt;Sweetman (2000), p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; The attacking force comprised 33 Barracudas carrying {{convert|1600|lb|kg|adj=on}} [[armor-piercing shot and shell|armour-piecing]] bombs, 24 Corsairs (including 5 armed with a 1,000-pound [450&amp;nbsp;kg] bomb), 10 Hellcats, 10 Fireflies and 8 Seafires. In an attempt to achieve surprise, the aircraft flew off from the carriers from a point further to the south of those used in previous raids. The strike aircraft then flew parallel to the coast, before making landfall and approaching Kaafjord from the south. A German radar station detected the force at 3:41 pm, and immediately alerted ''Tirpitz''.&lt;ref name=Tarrant_134 /&gt;
[[File:A Fairey Barracuda of 827 Squadron, Fleet Air Arm returns to HMS Furious during Operation Goodwood A25423.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Black and white photograph of a single-engined monoplane on the flight deck of a World War II-era aircraft carrier. Large numbers of men are watching the aircraft or running towards it.|A Barracuda landing on HMS ''Furious'' at the conclusion of one of the attacks on ''Tirpitz'' during Operation Goodwood]]

The British attack began at 4:00 pm. It was initiated with attacks on German gun positions by the Hellcats and Fireflies, which were flying five minutes ahead of the Barracudas and Corsairs.&lt;ref name=Tarrant_134 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Sweetman_81 /&gt; ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s protective smokescreen was not fully in place at the start of the raid, but by the time the Barracudas and Corsairs arrived she was completely covered by smoke.&lt;ref name=Tarrant_134 /&gt; As a result, these aircraft had to blind bomb the ship, releasing their weapons from altitudes between {{convert|5000|and|4000|ft|m}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tarrant_135&quot;&gt;Tarrant (1994), p. 135&lt;/ref&gt; Only two bombs hit ''Tirpitz''. The first was a {{convert|500|lb|kg|adj=on}} weapon dropped by a Hellcat that exploded on the roof of her &quot;Bruno&quot; main [[gun turret]]. The explosion destroyed the quadruple {{convert|20|mm|in|adj=on}} anti-aircraft gun mount located on top of the turret, but did not cause any significant damage to the turret itself.&lt;ref name=Tarrant_134 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Garzke_268 /&gt; The second bomb to strike the ship was a {{convert|1600|lb|kg|adj=on}} armour-piercing weapon which penetrated through five decks, killed a sailor in a radio room and lodged near an electrical switch room. This bomb failed to explode, and German bomb disposal experts later determined that it had been only partially filled with explosives. The German report on the attack judged that if the bomb had gone off it would have caused &quot;immeasurable&quot; damage.&lt;ref name=Roskill_160 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Garzke_268&quot;&gt;Garzke and Dulin (1985), p. 268&lt;/ref&gt; British fighters also attacked other German ships and facilities in the Kaafjord area, damaging two patrol boats, a [[minesweeper]] and a radar station, as well as destroying an [[ammunition dump]] and three guns of an anti-aircraft battery. ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s last remaining [[Arado Ar 196]] seaplane was attacked in Bukta harbour and damaged beyond repair.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_1977_39&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; Four Corsairs and two Hellcats were shot down during the raid, and the battleship's crew suffered 8 fatalities and 18 men wounded.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_283 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Tarrant_135 /&gt; Casualties among the anti-aircraft units stationed around Kaafjord were heavy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweetman_83&quot;&gt;Sweetman (2000), p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;

At 7:30 pm on 24 August, a pair of Fireflies conducted a photo-reconnaissance sortie over Kaafjord to gather intelligence on the results of the attack; their presence caused the Germans to generate a smoke screen over the fjord and fire an intensive anti-aircraft barrage.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_39 /&gt; In a separate action that day, ''U-354'' was sunk off [[Bear Island (Norway)|Bear Island]] by [[Fairey Swordfish]] operating from the escort carrier {{HMS|Vindex|D15|6}} which was escorting Convoy JW59.&lt;ref name=Brown_2009_28 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Woodman_401&quot;&gt;Woodman (2004), p. 401&lt;/ref&gt;

The German command at Kaafjord judged that the attacks on 24 August had been &quot;undoubtedly the heaviest and most determined so far&quot;, and requested that fighter units be transferred from northern Finland to bolster the area's defences. Due to the other demands on Germany's fighter force at this time, the request was turned down on 26 August by the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;Sweetman (2000), pp. 82, 84&lt;/ref&gt;

Gales and fog prevented the British from conducting further attacks between 25 and 28 August.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_313&quot;&gt;Bishop (2010), p. 313&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 August ''Indefatigable'', ''Formidable'', two cruisers and seven destroyers refuelled from the oilers. Both of the cruisers later detached from the force and returned to Scapa Flow. ''Duke of York'', ''Furious'', a cruiser and five destroyers also sailed to the [[Faroe Islands]] to load supplies. Before leaving the fleet, ''Furious'' transferred two Barracudas and a pair of Hellcats to ''Indefatigable''.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_83 /&gt; As the elderly ''Furious'' was judged to be no longer capable of combat operations, she proceeded from the Faroe Islands to Scapa Flow with the cruiser and several destroyers.&lt;ref name=Roskill_160 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_39 /&gt; On 29 August ''Duke of York'' and the remaining destroyers rejoined the main body of the Home Fleet off north Norway.&lt;ref name=Sweetman_83 /&gt; During this period, the flying squadrons' maintenance personnel worked to repair aircraft which had been damaged during the 24 August attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweetman_82&quot;&gt;Sweetman (2000), p. 82&lt;/ref&gt;

Convoy JW59 completed its journey on 25 August, with most of its ships docking at [[Kola, Russia|Kola]] in northern Russia. The convoy had been repeatedly attacked by U-boats from 20 to 24 August, and its escorting warships and aircraft sank two submarines. All of the merchant vessels arrived safely, with the only Allied loss being the sloop {{HMS|Kite|U87|6}} which was torpedoed and sunk by [[German submarine U-344|''U-344'']] on 21 August.&lt;ref&gt;Woodman (2004), pp. 400–403&lt;/ref&gt;

===29 August===
[[File:British naval personnel moving bombs before a raid during Operation Goodwood.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photograph of a group of men pushing bombs on trolleys on the deck of an aircraft carrier at sea. A single-engined aircraft is located immediately behind the men.|British sailors moving bombs along the deck of an aircraft carrier prior to &quot;bombing up&quot; Baracudas for one of the raids conducted during Operation Goodwood]]
The final attack of Operation Goodwood was made on 29 August. The strike force comprised 26 Barracudas, 17 Corsairs (of which 2 were armed with 1,000-pound [450&amp;nbsp;kg] bombs), 10 Fireflies and 7 Hellcats. Seven Seafires also conducted a diversionary raid on Hammerfest. In an attempt to give the bombers accurate aiming points once the artificial smokescreen was generated around ''Tirpitz'', four of the Hellcats were armed with [[target indicator]] bombs. The aircraft began launching at 3:30 pm.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_39 /&gt;

The British aircraft failed to achieve surprise. German radar stations had been tracking the Home Fleet's routine anti-submarine and fighter patrols, and the Seafires were detected at 4:40 pm when they were {{convert|54|mi|km}} from Kaafjord.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_39 /&gt; In response to this report, the smoke generators around Kaafjord were activated and the fjord's defenders went to their battle positions.&lt;ref name=Tarrant_135 /&gt; The arrival of the main body of British aircraft over Kaafjord was delayed by stronger than expected winds and a navigational error, and they did not reach the target area until 5:25 pm. By this time ''Tirpitz'' was covered in a very thick smokescreen, and none of the British airmen sighted the ship. The Barracudas and Corsairs were forced to blind-bomb Kaafjord, and while no hits were achieved on the battleship, six members of her crew were wounded by bomb fragments from near misses. German ships and gun positions were once again strafed by the fighters, but no significant damage was inflicted. Heavy anti-aircraft gunfire from ''Tirpitz,'' which was directed by a party of observers stationed on a mountain near Kaafjord, shot down a Corsair and a Firefly.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_39 /&gt;

Following the raid on 29 August, the Home Fleet sailed west to cover [[Convoy RA59A]] which had sailed from northern Russia on 28 August bound from the UK.&lt;ref name=Brown_1977_39 /&gt; Due to fuel shortages, ''Indefatigable'' and three destroyers detached later that day to return to Scapa Flow and ''Formidable'' with two destroyers followed 24 hours later. ''Duke of York'' and six destroyers remained on station in the Arctic Sea until 11:00 am on 1 September when the convoy was judged to be safe from attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweetman_85&quot;&gt;Sweetman (2000), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;

Overall, Fleet Air Arm casualties during Operation Goodwood were 40 airmen killed and 17 aircraft destroyed.&lt;ref name=Bishop_313 /&gt; ''Nabob'' was also judged to be beyond economical repair, and was withdrawn from service.&lt;ref name=Brown_2009_28 /&gt; On the German side, ''Tirpitz'' suffered only superficial damage.&lt;ref name=Brown_2009_28 /&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Commonwealth War Graves gravestone of C. E. Woodward in Tromsø.jpg|thumb|alt=Colour photo of a dark grey gravestone|upright|A New Zealand airman who flew from HMS ''Formidable'' and was killed during Operation Goodwood is interred at the Commonwealth War Graves section of Tromsø's main cemetery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Woodward, Clive Eustace|url=http://www.cwgc.org/find-war-dead/casualty/2186955/WOODWARD,%20CLIVE%20EUSTACE|publisher=Commonwealth War Graves Commission|accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Following the 29 August raid, the British learned from [[Ultra]] signals intelligence that ''Tirpitz'' had not sustained any significant damage during Operation Goodwood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_19&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; In public statements the Royal Navy claimed to have damaged or sunk 19 German warships during the attacks on Kaafjord, but did not report damage to ''Tirpitz''.&lt;ref name=Bennett_19 /&gt;

During the final days of Operation Goodwood Royal Navy planners decided not to order further Fleet Air Arm operations against Kaafjord. The planners accepted that the Germans were now able to cover ''Tirpitz'' in smoke before Barracudas could reach the battleship, and these aircraft could not carry bombs large enough to inflict heavy damage. Further consideration was given to attacking Kaafjord using Mosquitos launched from aircraft carriers, but the light bombers continued to be in short supply and it was judged that they were not well suited to the task. Moreover, there was a growing need to transfer the carriers to the Pacific to strengthen Britain's contribution to the [[Pacific War|war against Japan]].&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 285&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2010), p. 317&lt;/ref&gt;

As ''Tirpitz'' was still considered a threat to shipping, the British [[Chiefs of Staff Committee]] and the Supreme Allied Commander of the Allied Expeditionary Force General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] decided in late August to conduct further attacks against her using Royal Air Force heavy bombers.&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 285–286&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Eisenhower was involved in this decision as RAF Bomber Command was under his command at the time to support the [[Operation Overlord|invasion of Normandy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_316&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 316&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} On 15 September, a force of [[Avro Lancaster]]s [[Operation Paravane|attacked Kaafjord]] after refuelling at bases in northern Russia and inflicted irreparable damage on the battleship. Following this raid she sailed to an anchorage near [[Tromsø]] to be used as an immobile coastal defence battery. [[Operation Obviate|Another heavy bomber attack]] on 29 October caused only minor damage, but in a [[Operation Catechism|third raid]] mounted on 12 November, ''Tirpitz'' was struck by several [[Tallboy bomb]]s and capsized, sinking with heavy loss of life.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett (2012), pp. 19–21&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians have judged Operation Goodwood to have been a failure. Writing in 1961, the British official historian [[Stephen Roskill]] stated that the attacks marked the end of a &quot;series of operations whose results can only be classed as intensely disappointing&quot;, and concluded that the possibility of sinking ''Tirpitz'' had been &quot;remote&quot; due to the shortcomings of the Barracudas and their armament.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill (1961), pp. 160–161&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[Norman Polmar]] argued in 1969 that Operation Goodwood was &quot;perhaps the most striking failure of the F.A.A. [Fleet Air Arm] during World War II and can be directly attributed to the lack of effective aircraft&amp;nbsp;– the Barracudas were too slow and could not carry large enough bombs to make effective attacks&quot;.&lt;ref name=Polmar_1969_310 /&gt; More recently, Mark Llewellyn Evans judged the results of Operation Goodwood to have been &quot;pathetic&quot;, and Mark Bishop concluded that &quot;the Fleet Air Arm's greatest operation of the war ... ended in failure&quot;.&lt;ref name=Bishop_313 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Evans (1999), p. 132&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{commons category|Operation Goodwood (naval)}}
* {{cite book|last=Bennett|first=G.H.|title=Hunting Tirpitz: Naval Operations Against Bismarck's Sister Ship|year=2012|publisher=University of Plymouth Press|location=Plymouth, Devon|isbn=9781841023106|editor=Bennett, G.H.|chapter=Introduction|pages=7–25}}
* {{cite book|last=Bishop|first=Patrick|title=Target Tirpitz|year=2012|publisher=Harper Press|location=London|isbn=9780007431199}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=David|title=Tirpitz: The Floating Fortress|year=1977|publisher=Arms and Armour Press|location=London|isbn=0853683417}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=David|title=Warship Losses of World War Two|date=1990|publisher=Arms and Armour|location=London|isbn=0853688028}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=David|title=Carrier Operations in World War II|year=2009|publisher=Frontline|location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire|isbn=9781848320420|editor=Hobbs, David}}
* {{cite book|last=Ellis|first=John|title=One Day in a Very Long War: Wednesday 25th October 1944|year=1999|publisher=Pimlico|location=London|isbn=0712674659|edition=Pimlico}}
* {{cite book|last=Evans|first=Mark Llewellyn|title=Great World War II Battles in the Arctic|date=1999|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport, Connecticut|isbn=0313308926}}
* {{cite book|last=Faulkner|first=Marcus|title=War at Sea: A Naval Atlas, 1939–1945|year=2012|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=9781591145608|author2=Wilkinson, Peter}}
* {{cite book|last1=Garzke|first1=William H.|last2=Dulin|first2=Robert O.|title=Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II|year=1985|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=9780870211010|oclc=}}
* {{cite book|last=Hinsley|first=F.H.|title=British Intelligence in the Second World War: Its Influence on Strategy and Operations. Volume Three, Part I|year=1984|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|isbn=0116309350|display-authors=etal}}
* {{cite book|last=Polmar|first=Norman|title=Aircraft Carriers: A Graphic History of Carrier Aviation and Its Influence on World Events|date=1969|publisher=Macdonald &amp; Co.|location=London|isbn=1574886630}}
* {{cite book|last=Roskill|first=S.W.|title=The War at Sea 1939–1945. Volume III: The Offensive Part II|year=1961|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|oclc=59005418}}
* {{cite book|last=Sweetman|first=John|title=Tirpitz: Hunting the Beast: Air Attacks on the German Battleship, 1940–44|date=2000|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=1557508224}}
* {{cite book|last=Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section)|title=Hunting Tirpitz: Naval Operations Against Bismarck's Sister Ship|year=2012|publisher=University of Plymouth Press|location=Plymouth, Devon|isbn=9781841023106|editor=Bennett, G.H.|chapter=Naval Aircraft Attack on the Tirpitz (Operation 'Tungsten') 3 April 1944|origyear=1944|pages=133–177}}
* {{cite book|last=Tarrant|first=V.E.|title=The Last Year of the Kriegsmarine: May 1944&amp;nbsp;– May 1945|year=1994|publisher=Arms and Armour Press|location=London|isbn=185409176X}}
* {{cite book|last=Williamson|first=Gordon|title=German Battleships 1939-45|date=2003|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Botley, Oxfordshire|isbn=1841764981}}
* {{cite book|last=Woodman|first=Richard|title=The Arctic Convoys: 1941–1945|year=2004|publisher=John Murray|location=London|isbn=0719566177|edition=Paperback}}
* {{cite book|last=Wragg|first=David|title=The Escort Carrier in World War II: Combustible, Vulnerable, Expendable!|date=2005|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Maritime|location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire|isbn=1844152200}}
* {{cite book|last1=Zetterling|first1=Niklas|last2=Tamelander|first2=Michael|title=Tirpitz: The Life and Death of Germany's Last Super Battleship|year=2009|publisher=Casemate|location=Philadelphia|isbn=9781935149187}}
{{coord|69.9353|23.0454|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Goodwood}}
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1944 in Norway]]
[[Category:Alta, Norway]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Naval aviation operations and battles]]</text>
      <sha1>hdaxnww444czo8hiny29puzixmna81j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
