<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Operation Tungsten</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3282123</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737081568</id>
      <parentid>736515986</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-31T17:07:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chris the speller</username>
        <id>525927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>hyphen</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47940">{{Featured article}}
{{infobox military conflict
| conflict = Operation Tungsten
| partof = the [[World War II|Second World War]]
| image = [[File:HMS Furious armourer with bomb message April 1944 IWM A 22640.jpg|300px|alt=Black and white photograph of a man wearing military uniform crouching under an aircraft. He is holding a piece of chalk in his hand, and is posing next to a bomb which is fixed to the bottom of the aircraft on which &quot;Tirpitz it's yours&quot; has been written.|A Fleet Air Arm crewman chalks a message on the 1,600-pound bomb carried by a Fairey Barracuda of HMS ''Furious'']]
| caption = A [[Fleet Air Arm]] crewman chalks a message on the 1,600-pound bomb carried by a [[Fairey Barracuda]] of HMS ''Furious''
| date = 3 April 1944
| place = [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]], Norway
| coordinates =
| map_type =
| latitude =
| longitude =
| map_size =
| map_caption =
| map_label =
| territory =
| result = Inconclusive
| status =
| combatant1 = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany|1935}}
| combatant3 =
| commander1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Henry Ruthven Moore|Henry Moore]]
| commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} Hans Meyer
| commander3 =
| units1 =
| units2 =
| units3 =
| strength1 = 40 dive bombers&lt;br/&gt;80 fighters
| strength2 = 1 battleship&lt;br/&gt;Anti-aircraft batteries and ships
| strength3 =
| casualties1 = 9 fatalities&lt;br/&gt;4 aircraft lost
| casualties2 = 123 fatalities, 329 wounded&lt;br /&gt;1 battleship and 5 other vessels damaged
| casualties3 =
| notes =
}}
{{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaigns (1941 - 1945)}}

'''Operation Tungsten''' was a Second World War [[Royal Navy]] air raid that targeted the [[German battleship Tirpitz|German battleship ''Tirpitz'']]. The operation sought to damage or destroy ''Tirpitz'' at her base in [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]] in the far north of Norway before she could become fully operational again following a period of repairs.

The British decision to strike Kaafjord was motivated by fears that the battleship, upon re-entering service, would attack strategically important [[convoy]]s carrying supplies to the Soviet Union. Removing the threat posed by ''Tirpitz'' would also allow the Allies to redeploy the [[capital ship]]s which had to be held in the North Sea to counter her. After four months of training and preparations, the British [[Home Fleet]] sailed on 30 March 1944 and aircraft launched from five [[aircraft carrier]]s struck Kaafjord on 3 April. The raid achieved surprise, and the British aircraft met little opposition. Fifteen bombs hit the battleship, and strafing by [[fighter aircraft]] inflicted heavy casualties on her gun crews. Four British aircraft and nine airmen were lost during the operation.

The damage inflicted during the attack was not sufficient to sink or disable ''Tirpitz'', but 122 members of her crew died and 316 were wounded. The German ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' decided to repair the battleship, and works were completed by mid-July. The British conducted further carrier raids against ''Tirpitz'' between April and August 1944 in the hope of prolonging the period she was out of service, but none were successful. ''Tirpitz'' was eventually disabled and then sunk by [[Royal Air Force]] heavy bombers in late 1944.

==Background==
The threat [[German battleship Tirpitz|''Tirpitz'']] had an important influence on British naval strategy during the Second World War. She was commissioned in February 1941 and completed her crew training late that year. At about the same time the German high command decided to station the battleship in Norway; this deployment was intended to deter a feared Allied invasion of Norway and threaten the convoys which regularly sailed through the Arctic Sea to the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_10&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; [[Arctic convoys of World War II|These convoys]] carried large quantities of war material from ports in the UK and Iceland, and were frequently attacked by the German air and naval units stationed in Norway.&lt;ref&gt;Dear and Foot (2005), p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; ''Tirpitz'' arrived in Norway in January 1942 and operated from anchorages located in fjords.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett (2012), pp. 10–11&lt;/ref&gt; While she was operational the Allies had to keep a powerful force of warships with the British [[Home Fleet]] to guard against the possibility of a sortie against the Arctic convoys, and capital ships accompanied most convoys part of the way to the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_9&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Faulkner_109&quot;&gt;Faulkner and Wilkinson (2012), p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;
{{location map|Finnmark| lat = 69.9353| long = 23.0454| caption =The location of Kaafjord in northern Norway| label = Kaafjord| float = left}}

The British attacked ''Tirpitz'' [[List of Allied attacks on the German battleship Tirpitz|several times during 1942 and 1943]]. When the battleship sortied to intercept [[Convoy PQ 12]] on 6 March 1942 {{HMS|Victorious|R38|6}}, which formed part of the convoy's escort, attempted to attack her using [[torpedo bomber]]s. These aircraft launched twenty torpedoes at the battleship but all missed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_11&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 78–83&lt;/ref&gt; On several occasions during 1942 and 1943 bombers from the [[Royal Air Force]] and [[Soviet Air Forces]] attempted to strike ''Tirpitz'' in her anchorages without success.&lt;ref name=Bennett_11 /&gt; On 23 September 1943 two British [[X-class submarine|X-class]] midget submarines succeeded in penetrating the defences around the battleship at her main anchorage at [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]] in northern Norway during [[Operation Source]], and placed explosive charges in the water beneath her. This attack caused extensive damage to ''Tirpitz'', putting her out of service for six months.&lt;ref&gt;Woodman (2004), p. 340&lt;/ref&gt;

Repairs to ''Tirpitz'' were carried out using improvised facilities at Kaafjord as it was considered too risky to attempt to move the damaged warship to Germany. Instead, equipment and work crews were shipped to the fjord from German ports.&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 251&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of 10/11 February 1944, 15 Soviet aircraft attacked the battleship, but did not cause any damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_295&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 295&lt;/ref&gt; By 17 March, the repairs to ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s armament, machinery and hull were complete, but several minor repair tasks were outstanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_265&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 265&lt;/ref&gt; During the period the ship was under repair, [[German battleship Scharnhorst|''Scharnhorst'']], the only remaining operational German battleship, was sunk on 26 December during the [[Battle of the North Cape]].&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 264&lt;/ref&gt; Following this engagement the Royal Navy stopped deploying battleships to cover convoys travelling to and from the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley_269&quot;&gt;Hinsley et al. (1984), p. 269&lt;/ref&gt; By this stage of the war the Allies also had large numbers of anti-submarine and anti-aircraft escort ships available, and were able to assign strong forces to protect all of the Arctic convoys. German submarines operating in the Norwegian Sea were rarely able to evade the convoy escorts, and few merchant vessels suffered damage from enemy attack.&lt;ref&gt;Dear and Foot (2005), p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;

The British Government and Royal Navy were concerned about the threat ''Tirpitz'' posed once she re-entered service. Allied intelligence tracked the progress of work on the battleship using decrypted German radio signals, photo reconnaissance flights and eyewitness reports from agents in Norway.&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 291–293&lt;/ref&gt; It was feared the battleship could sortie and attack convoys in the Norwegian Sea or Atlantic Ocean after the repairs were completed. The need to guard against this possibility would also occupy warships needed to support the planned [[Operation Overlord|invasion of France]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_294&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 294&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, it was decided in late 1943 to make further attempts to sink the battleship.&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 266–267&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite Allied concerns, ''Tirpitz'' posed only a limited danger to Allied shipping. From late 1943 the battleship was unable to put to sea for crew training due to the threat of Allied attack and fuel shortages. These shortages also meant the Germans were unable to move the battleship between anchorages to make her more difficult to locate and attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_14&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

==Preparations==
[[File:The Royal Navy during the Second World War A22634.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photograph of a Second World War-era warship in a small bay with a steep and snow-covered shoreline. Clouds of smoke are being blown from the shoreline towards the ship.|A British aerial reconnaissance photograph of ''Tirpitz'' moored at Kaafjord. The artificial smoke generators on the shores of the fjord have not yet obscured her.]]

The options for attacking ''Tirpitz'' at Kaafjord were limited. Another submarine-borne raid was considered impractical as intelligence gathered from intercepted radio transmissions and field agents indicated that the battleship's underwater defences had been improved and more aerial reconnaissance patrols of the region were being flown.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_265 /&gt; The commander of the Royal Air Force's [[RAF Bomber Command|Bomber Command]], Air Chief Marshal Sir [[Sir Arthur Harris, 1st Baronet|Arthur Harris]], also refused to attempt a [[heavy bomber]] raid on ''Tirpitz'' on the grounds that the Kaafjord area was beyond the effective range of these aircraft and the battleship's guns would cause heavy casualties.&lt;ref name=Bishop_294 /&gt; After these two options were ruled out, the task was assigned to the Home Fleet's aircraft carriers.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_265 /&gt; At this time the large [[fleet carrier]]s {{HMS|Furious|47|6}} and ''Victorious'' and four smaller [[escort carrier]]s were ready.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_267 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 296–297&lt;/ref&gt;

Planning for the raid on Kaafjord began in December 1943. Vice Admiral [[Bruce Fraser, 1st Baron Fraser of North Cape|Bruce Fraser]], the commander of the Home Fleet, was not optimistic about the prospects for success, and had to be persuaded to undertake the operation by First Sea Lord Sir [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_297&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 297&lt;/ref&gt; Fraser gave his second in command, Vice Admiral Sir [[Henry Ruthven Moore|Henry Moore]], responsibility for planning and leading the raid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_267&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 267&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bishop_297 /&gt; The operation was initially designated &quot;Operational Thrustful&quot;, but was later renamed &quot;Operation Tungsten&quot;. The attack was originally scheduled for mid-March 1944, shortly before the time Allied intelligence believed ''Tirpitz'' would become operational.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_267 /&gt; However, it was delayed by two weeks while ''Victorious'' was fitted with new radars.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_299&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 299&lt;/ref&gt; The British considered cancelling Operation Tungsten in February as ''Victorious'' was also needed in the Indian Ocean to counter a build-up of Japanese warships at Singapore. To enable the attack to proceed, the [[United States Navy]] agreed to temporarily transfer {{USS|Saratoga|CV-3|6}} to the [[Eastern Fleet]] so that ''Victorious'' could be retained in the North Sea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley_271&quot;&gt;Hinsley et al. (1984), p. 271&lt;/ref&gt;

The plans for the raid were centred on two dive-bombing attacks by [[Fleet Air Arm]] [[Fairey Barracuda]] aircraft. Each of the attacks was to involve 21 Barracudas escorted by 40 fighters; [[Vought F4U Corsair]]s flying from ''Victorious'' would provide protection against German aircraft while [[Grumman F4F Wildcat]] and [[Grumman F6F Hellcat|F6F Hellcats]] operating from ''Furious'' and the escort carriers {{HMS|Emperor|D98|6}}, {{HMS|Pursuer|D73|2}} and {{HMS|Searcher|D40|2}} were to strafe anti-aircraft [[Artillery battery|batteries]] near ''Tirpitz'', as well as the battleship herself. Further aircraft flying from ''Furious'' and the escort carrier {{HMS|Fencer|D64|6}} would protect the fleet against attack by German aircraft or submarines.&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 295–296, 298&lt;/ref&gt; While carrier aircraft had previously lacked a bomb capable of penetrating a battleship's thick [[Deck (ship)|deck]] armour, it was hoped that the recently developed {{convert|1600|lb|kg|adj=on}} armour-piercing bomb would be able to pierce at least the first layer of ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s armour if they were dropped from an altitude of {{convert|3500|ft|m}} or higher. The damage caused by such hits was expected to put the battleship out of service. Nine of the Barracudas were to be armed with 1,600-pound bombs and a further 22 would each carry three 500-pound semi-armour-piercing bombs that were capable of penetrating the lightly protected upper decks of the ship if dropped from above {{convert|2000|ft|m}}. The remaining ten aircraft would be armed with 500- and 600-pound general-purpose bombs and with anti-submarine bombs intended to inflict casualties among the battleship's crew and cause underwater damage if they exploded in the water near her hull.&lt;ref name=Bishop_299 /&gt; The aircraft carrying high-explosive bombs were to initiate the dive bombing of ''Tirpitz'' as it was hoped that these weapons would knock out at least some of the battleship's anti-aircraft guns before the main attack commenced.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_267 /&gt;
[[File:View down Loch Eriboll - geograph.org.uk - 8211.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Colour photograph of a body of water surrounded by hills viewed from a hill|[[Loch Eriboll]] in Scotland was used to simulate Kaafjord during training exercises]]

The Fleet Air Arm units selected for Operation Tungsten conducted intensive training from February 1944. A high proportion of the airmen were inexperienced, and the captain of ''Victorious'' estimated that 85 per cent of the aircrew embarked on his ship had not previously operated at sea.&lt;ref name=Bishop_300 /&gt; The training program was centred on [[Loch Eriboll]] in northern Scotland which, like Kaafjord, was surrounded by steep hills. Flying from [[RNAS Hatston]] in the Orkney Islands, the aircrew practiced manoeuvring around this terrain to familiarise themselves with the tactics needed to avoid German anti-aircraft guns and successfully attack ''Tirpitz''.&lt;ref name=Bishop_297 /&gt; The Royal Navy drew on intelligence on the defences of Kaafjord to make the exercise range as similar to the conditions around ''Tirpitz'' as was possible, and the aircrew were extensively briefed on the locations of German positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley273-274&quot;&gt;Hinsley et al. (1984), pp. 273–274&lt;/ref&gt; An area the size of the battleship was also marked out on an island in the centre of the loch and repeatedly bombed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_298&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 298&lt;/ref&gt;

While these preparations were under way, the Allies continued to monitor ''Tirpitz''. In late February the escort carrier {{HMS|Chaser|D32|6}} transported photo analysts and the ground crews for a Royal Air Force photo reconnaissance detachment to [[Vaenga airfield]] in northern Russia. These personnel were joined by three [[Supermarine Spitfire]]s fitted for photo reconnaissance work and a single [[Consolidated PBY Catalina]] in March. The Spitfires flew regular sorties over Kaafjord and took very detailed photographs of ''Tirpitz'' and the nearby anti-aircraft batteries on 12 and 13 March; after being developed the Catalina flew these images to the UK. Although the German forces in northern Norway detected the Spitfire flights, the Kaafjord area's defences were not increased or placed on alert.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_274&quot;&gt;Roskill (1960), p. 274&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 March eight British, Dutch and Norwegian submarines were directed to take up positions off the Norwegian coast after decrypted German radio messages indicated that ''Tirpitz'' may have been preparing to depart Kaafjord for Germany to complete her repairs. A further eight British and Dutch submarines were dispatched on 18 March, but two days later it was concluded that ''Tirpitz'' was not about to put to sea and the submarines were diverted to other tasks or ordered back to port.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rohwer_311&quot;&gt;Rohwer (2005), p. 311&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 March British intelligence warned the [[Admiralty]] that due to recent Soviet advances on the Eastern Front, the Germans were placing a strong emphasis on disrupting the flow of supplies to the Soviet Union and could dispatch ''Tirpitz'' to attack any convoys not escorted by capital ships. In response, Fraser was directed to provide battleship protection for the next Arctic Convoy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley_273&quot;&gt;Hinsley et al. (1984), p. 273&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barnett (2000), p. 744&lt;/ref&gt;

The final decision to undertake Operation Tungsten was made in mid-March on the basis of a decrypted radio message that indicated that ''Tirpitz'' was almost ready for combat and would conduct high-speed trials on 1 April.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_267 /&gt; As a result of the delays to the operation, the sailing of the attack force coincided with the departure of [[Convoy JW 58]] for the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=Bishop_299 /&gt; It was hoped that if German forces spotted the British fleet it would be assumed that the warships were supporting the convoy.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_268 /&gt; As part of the final preparations for the attack a full-scale rehearsal was conducted using the training range at Loch Eriboll on 28 March.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_33&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; From 1 April onwards, the Admiralty received hourly weather reports from a group of Norwegian [[Secret Intelligence Service]] agents in [[Alta, Norway|Alta]], near Kaafjord.&lt;ref&gt;Rørholt and Thorsen (1990), p. 254&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposing forces==
[[File:HMS Jamaica tirpitz raid.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photograph of single propeller fighter aircraft on the deck of an aircraft carrier at sea. Several other ships are visible in the background.|Grumman Hellcats on the escort carrier HMS ''Emperor'', with other ships of the British force in the background]]
{{see also|Allied order of battle for Operation Tungsten}}
The Royal Navy assembled a powerful force for Operation Tungsten. The main striking force was made up of two wings of Barracudas: 8 Wing comprising [[827 Naval Air Squadron|827]] and [[830 Naval Air Squadron]]s, and 52 Wing with [[829 Naval Air Squadron|829]] and [[831 Naval Air Squadron]]s. While 8 Wing was normally based on board ''Furious'' and 52 Wing on ''Victorious'', Moore chose to station a squadron from each of the wings on each carrier so they could launch simultaneously and go into battle as formed units.&lt;ref name=Bishop_298 /&gt; The 163 Fleet Air Arm airmen in the attacking units included 28 New Zealanders, three Canadians, two Australians, and one South African;&lt;ref&gt;Army News (Darwin, NT), Wednesday 7 June 1944&lt;/ref&gt; the remainder were British.&lt;ref name=&quot;Navy Today April 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Operation Tungsten — Attacking the Tirpitz, 1944|journal=Navy Today|date=April 2011|issue=160|publisher=Royal New Zealand Navy|accessdate=28 January 2013|url=http://www.navy.mil.nz/know-your-navy/official-documents/navy-today/nt11webformat/nt160/op-tungsten.htm|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130210125126/http://navy.mil.nz/know-your-navy/official-documents/navy-today/nt11webformat/nt160/op-tungsten.htm|archivedate=10 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article78311720 |title=Fights Germans From Sea, Air|newspaper=[[Daily News (Perth, Western Australia)|The Daily News]] |location=Perth, Western Australia |date=21 June 1944 |accessdate=6 July 2015 |page=5|edition=City Final|publisher=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The large number of warships assigned to the operation were initially split into two groups. Force One was personally commanded by Fraser on board the battleship {{HMS|Duke of York|17|6}}, and also included ''Victorious'', the battleship {{HMS|Anson|79|6}} (with Moore and his staff on board), a [[light cruiser]] and five [[destroyer]]s. Force Two was commanded by Rear Admiral [[Arthur La Touche Bisset]] and comprised ''Furious'', the four escort carriers, five destroyers and two [[Tanker (ship)|tankers]]. It was planned that Force One would initially provide support for Convoy JW 58 and Force Two would sail separately and proceed directly to a point off Norway where it would be joined by ''Anson'' and ''Victorious'' on 3 April and conduct the raid the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_268&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 268&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 299–300&lt;/ref&gt;

''Tirpitz''{{'s}} anchorage at Kaafjord was protected by anti-aircraft batteries and fighter aircraft. At the time of Operation Tungsten, four batteries of heavy anti-aircraft guns and seven batteries of light guns were located on the shore near the battleship. Several anti-aircraft vessels and destroyers were also usually moored near ''Tirpitz''.&lt;ref&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; The battleship herself was fitted with 68 anti-aircraft guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnett_745&quot;&gt;Barnett (2000), p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; Equipment capable of generating an artificial smokescreen to hide ''Tirpitz'' from aircraft had also been installed around Kaafjord.&lt;ref name=&quot;TTSDD_135&quot;&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 135&lt;/ref&gt; The German Air Force (''[[Luftwaffe]]'') had only a small number of fighters stationed at bases near Kaafjord, and their operations were constrained by a lack of fuel. British intelligence believed that the German fighter force in the area could be rapidly expanded in the event of an emergency.&lt;ref name=Bennett_14 /&gt;&lt;ref name=TTSDD_135 /&gt; The ''Luftwaffe'' typically conducted three reconnaissance flights into the Arctic Sea each day.&lt;ref name=TTSDD_135 /&gt;

==Attack==
Force One departed the Home Fleet's base at [[Scapa Flow]] in the Orkney Islands on 30 March, three days after [[Convoy JW 58|JW 58]] had sailed from [[Loch Ewe]] in Scotland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_300&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 300&lt;/ref&gt; Force Two departed separately later that day.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_268 /&gt; The convoy comprised 49 merchant ships escorted by a powerful force of 33 warships, including two escort carriers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blair_516&quot;&gt;Blair (2000), p. 516&lt;/ref&gt; German reconnaissance aircraft located JW 58 on 30 March, and all of the [[U-boat]]s in the Norwegian Sea were directed to intercept it. The German aircraft did not conduct wider-ranging sorties in search of the convoy's battleship [[covering force]] or other Allied ships. A total of 17 U-boats attacked JW 58 between 1 and 3 April without success; none of the Allied ships suffered any damage, and the escorts sank four U-boats and shot down six German aircraft during the convoy's voyage from Scotland to the Soviet Union. JW 58 reached its destination at [[Kola Bay]] on 6 April.&lt;ref name=Bishop_300 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2000), pp. 516–517&lt;/ref&gt; While several Allied aircraft were lost during the voyage, mostly to flying accidents, all of the ships arrived unscathed.&lt;ref&gt;Woodman (2004), pp. 390–394&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Fleet Air Arm personnel fusing bombs prior to the 3 April 1944 attack on Tirpitz.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Colour photograph of men wearing military uniform crouching over bombs on the flight deck of an aircraft carrier|Fleet Air Arm personnel arming bombs on HMS ''Victorious''{{'}} flight deck prior to the attack]]

Owing to a combination of favourable factors, Fraser decided on 1 April to bring the raid on Kaafjord forward by 24 hours. Decrypted German signals indicated that ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s trials had been delayed until 3 April, and Fraser hoped that an attack on this date would catch the battleship away from her usual well-protected mooring. Moreover, as JW 58's escorts were performing well and there was no indication that ''Tirpitz'' would sortie into the open sea, Fraser judged that Force One no longer needed to provide support for the transports. Weather conditions were also unusually good for the Norwegian Sea in early Spring and were well suited to flying operations.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_268 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_275&quot;&gt;Roskill (1960), p. 275&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 300–301&lt;/ref&gt; After the decision to attack was made both tankers and two escorting destroyers detached from Force Two and proceeded to a point {{convert|300|mi|km}} north-west of Kaafjord where they remained to supply any destroyers that ran low on fuel. The rest of Force Two altered course to rendezvous with Force One, and this was achieved at 4:20 pm on 2 April.&lt;ref name=&quot;TTSDD_140&quot;&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 140&lt;/ref&gt; After the two forces met ''Duke of York'', with Fraser on board, and two destroyers sailed to the north-west and took up a position where they would be able to intercept ''Tirpitz'' in the event that she had sailed from Kaafjord without being detected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy_144&quot;&gt;Levy (2003), p. 144&lt;/ref&gt; The remainder of the Home Fleet proceeded to the strike's launching point.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_301&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 301&lt;/ref&gt;

The attack was launched during the early hours of 3 April. All the airmen were woken shortly after midnight, and attended a final briefing from 1:15 am. The aircraft to be used in the strike were armed at this time, with all of the bombs being marked with messages for ''Tirpitz'' in chalk. The aircrew began boarding their aircraft at 4:00 am and flying-off operations started 15 minutes later; at this time the warships were {{convert|120|mi|km}} from Kaafjord. Ten Corsairs drawn from [[1834 Naval Air Squadron|1834]] and [[1836 Naval Air Squadron]]s were the first aircraft to be launched and were followed by the 21 Barracudas of 8 Wing; 827 Squadron was launched from ''Victorious'' and 830 Squadron departed from ''Furious''. Seven of the Barracudas were armed with a 1,600-pound bomb, and the remainder carried multiple 500 or 600-pound weapons. Once the Barracudas were airborne the remaining escort fighters&amp;nbsp;– 30 Wildcats and Hellcats from [[800 Naval Air Squadron|800]], [[881 Naval Air Squadron|881]] and [[882 Naval Air Squadron]]s &amp;nbsp;– were launched. All the aircraft of the first wave were dispatched successfully, and the force completed forming up at 4:37 am.&lt;ref name=Roskill_275 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop (2012), pp. 301–302&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 268–269&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_34&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; Flying conditions remained perfect, and German forces had not detected the British fleet during its approach.&lt;ref name=TTSDD_140 /&gt;
[[File:Barracudas flying over a fjord shortly before attacking the battleship Tirpitz during Operation Tunsten IWM A22631.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photograph of a group of aircraft flying in formation above a fjord surrounded by snow-covered mountains|Barracudas flying over a fjord shortly before attacking ''Tirpitz'']]

The first wave headed for Norway at low altitude, flying just {{convert|50|ft|m}} above the sea to avoid detection by German radar. The aircraft began to climb to a higher altitude when they reached a point {{convert|20|mi|km}} from the coast, and had reached {{convert|7000|ft|m}} by the time they made landfall at 5:08 am. The force approached [[Altafjord|Altenfjord]] from the west, passing over the western end of [[Langfjorden (Alta)|Langfjord]] before turning south, then looping to the north and attacking the battleship over the hills on the southern shore of Kaafjord shortly before 5:30 am.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_302&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 302&lt;/ref&gt;

The arrival of the British force caught ''Tirpitz'' by surprise. While the aircraft had first been picked up by a German radar station shortly after they crossed the Norwegian coastline, the battleship was not immediately warned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_270&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 270&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the attack ''Tirpitz'' was preparing to sail for her high-speed trials, and her crew were busy unmooring the vessel. Her five protective destroyers had already departed for the trials area in [[Stjernsundet|Stjern Sound]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_303&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 303&lt;/ref&gt; The warning from the radar station arrived shortly before the British aircraft appeared over Kaafjord, and the battleship's crew were still in the process of moving to their battle stations when the attack commenced; at this time not all of the watertight doors were closed and some damage-control stations were not fully manned.&lt;ref name=Bishop_302 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 271–272&lt;/ref&gt;

As planned, the British raid began with Hellcat and Wildcat fighters strafing ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s anti-aircraft guns and batteries located on the shore; this attack inflicted heavy casualties on the battleship's gunners, disabled her main anti-aircraft control centre and damaged several guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_272&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 272&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TTSDD_144&quot;&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 144&lt;/ref&gt; The fighters also strafed several anti-aircraft ships in Kaafjord.&lt;ref name=TTSDD_144 /&gt; The 21 Barracudas began their attack shortly afterwards, and hit ''Tirpitz'' with a general purpose bomb, three 500-pound [[Armor-piercing shot and shell|semi-armour-piercing]] bombs and three 1,600-pound bombs within 60 seconds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_275&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, ten bombs struck the battleship during the first attack.&lt;ref&gt;Garzke and Dulin (1985), pp. 266–267&lt;/ref&gt; Most of these bombs did not penetrate the ship's armoured deck as they had been dropped from too low an altitude.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_275 /&gt; Hundreds of members of the ship's crew died or were wounded; her commanding officer, Captain Hans Meyer, was among the wounded and another officer assumed command. The battleship also drifted into the western shore of Kaafjord and ran aground, but was quickly refloated.&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 275–277&lt;/ref&gt; One of 830 Squadron's Barracudas crashed following the attack with the loss of all three members of its crew. The surviving aircraft of the first wave began landing on the carriers at 6:19 am, and all were recovered by 6:42.&lt;ref name=TTSDD_144 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_305&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 305&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Fleet Air Arm attack the battleship Tirpitz.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Black and white photograph of a warship moored near a snowy shore viewed from the air. Smoke is issuing from the warship.|Bombs exploding around ''Tirpitz'' during the first attack on the battleship]]

The first aircraft of the second wave took to the air at 5:25 am. One of 829 Squadron's Barracudas crashed shortly after take-off, resulting in the deaths of its crew of three, and another aircraft from this squadron was not launched due to engine problems. Only two of the Barracudas in this wave were armed with 1,600-pound bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_35&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; As with the first strike, 40 fighters accompanied the torpedo bombers; these comprised 10 Corsairs from 1834 and 1836 Naval Air Squadrons, all of the 20 Wildcats assigned to [[896 Naval Air Squadron|896]] and [[898 Naval Air Squadron]]s and 10 Hellcats from [[804 Naval Air Squadron]].&lt;ref name=Brown_35 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TTSDD_158&quot;&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 158&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tillman_74&quot;&gt;Tillman (1996), p. 74&lt;/ref&gt; All aircraft were launched by 5:37 am, and the force had an uneventful flight to the Kaafjord area.&lt;ref name=&quot;TTSDD_145&quot;&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 145&lt;/ref&gt; While the German defences were now alert, the artificial smoke screen being generated around Kaafjord was not yet sufficient to hide ''Tirpitz'' from view.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_277&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 277&lt;/ref&gt;

The second attack on ''Tirpitz'' was similar to the first. It began with Hellcat fighters strafing the anti-aircraft batteries while Wildcats attacked the battleship. The fighters also attacked German ships in Kaafjord and a radio or [[Direction finding|radio direction finding]] station. The Barracudas executed their dive bombing attack at 6:36 am and struck ''Tirpitz'' with a 1,600-pound bomb and four 500-pound bombs within a minute.&lt;ref name=Brown_35 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TTSDD_145&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_306&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 306&lt;/ref&gt; The German defences at Kaafjord received little warning of the incoming raid, and the smokescreen hid the British aircraft from sight. As a result, the gunners had to fire blindly and only shot down one of the Barracudas; all three airmen died.&lt;ref name=Brown_35 /&gt; The second wave landed on the carriers between 7:20 and 7:58 am. A damaged Hellcat had to ditch near the Canadian destroyer {{HMCS|Algonquin|R17|6}} and one of the Corsairs suffered heavy damage as a result of a landing accident; both pilots survived.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_279&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 279&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TTSDD_147&quot;&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), p. 147&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy_145&quot;&gt;Levy (2003), p. 145&lt;/ref&gt;

During the period in which the air strikes were conducted, a force of 25 Wildcat and [[Supermarine Seafire]] fighters from [[801 Naval Air Squadron|801]], [[842 Naval Air Squadron|842]] and [[880 Naval Air Squadron]]s provided air defence for the Home Fleet. Nine [[Fairey Swordfish]] torpedo bombers, which were also operated by 842 Naval Air Squadron, conducted anti-submarine patrols. No threat to the fleet developed, and Corsairs took over air defence duties at the conclusion of the two attacks.&lt;ref name=Levy_145 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section) (2012), pp. 148, 176&lt;/ref&gt;

During the early afternoon of 3 April, Moore considered conducting a further raid on Kaafjord the next day. He decided against doing so as the preliminary assessment of photos taken during the attack had concluded that ''Tirpitz'' was badly damaged. Moore was also aware that his aircrew were fatigued, and was reluctant to expose them to what would now be alert defences.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_279 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_308&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 308&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinsley_275&quot;&gt;Hinsley et al. (1984), p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, he ordered that the fleet return to base, and it arrived at Scapa Flow in the afternoon of 6 April.&lt;ref name=Bishop_306 /&gt; [[George VI|King George VI]] and Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]] sent congratulatory messages to the fleet, but both Churchill and Cunningham were concerned that ''Tirpitz'' could be returned to service. Cunningham also regretted Moore's decision not to launch a further strike on 4 April.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_309&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 309&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:The Royal Navy during the Second World War- Operation Tungsten March-april 1944 A22644.jpg|thumb|alt=Black and white photograph of a single engined monoplane flying just above the deck of an aircraft carrier with its wheels extended. Two other aircraft are visible flying in the background of the photo.|A Barracuda landing on HMS ''Victorious'' during Operation Tungsten]]
The two attacks on ''Tirpitz'' largely went to plan. The airmen found the defences and geography at Kaafjord to be very similar to the Loch Eriboll training range, and one of the post-attack reports stated that the operation had been &quot;almost an exercise which they [the aircrew] had frequently carried out before&quot;.&lt;ref name=Hinsley273-274 /&gt; The official historian of the Royal Navy's role in the Second World War, [[Stephen Roskill]], also judged that the strikes were &quot;beautifully co-ordinated and fearlessly executed&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_276&quot;&gt;Roskill (1960), p. 276&lt;/ref&gt; The most important discrepancy between the plans for the operation and its execution was that many pilots dropped their bombs below the specified minimum altitude of {{convert|3000|ft|m}} in an attempt to improve their chances of hitting ''Tirpitz''. The shorter than optimum flight times may have meant that some of the bombs which struck the battleship lacked the necessary velocity to penetrate her deck armour.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bennett_12&quot;&gt;Bennett (2012), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; Nine Royal Navy airmen died during the raid.&lt;ref name=Zetterling_279 /&gt;

''Tirpitz''{{'}}s crew suffered heavy casualties in the attack, but the battleship was not badly damaged. Overall, 122 sailors died and 316 were wounded; these casualties represented 15 percent of the battleship's crew. Many of the casualties were anti-aircraft gunners who were killed or wounded by machine-gun fire from the British fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop_307&quot;&gt;Bishop (2012), p. 307&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_36&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; While two bombs that exploded in the water near ''Tirpitz'' opened holes in her hull and caused flooding, none of the 15 bombs that struck the battleship penetrated her main deck armour belt. As a result, her guns, magazines, and machinery did not suffer serious damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_281&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 281&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Garzke_265&quot;&gt;Garzke and Dulin (1985), p. 265&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the damaged areas of the battleship were located in her superstructure and between her armoured decks. The starboard aircraft catapult and crane were destroyed, as were both ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s Arado floatplanes. The number two starboard {{convert|150|mm|in|adj=on}} gun turret was knocked out, and the number three port 150&amp;nbsp;mm turret incurred significant damage. The officers' mess and several galleys were wrecked, and the ship was filled with smoke. ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s funnel was also struck by bomb fragments that badly damaged all of the boiler intakes. While the starboard turbine was knocked out by shock damage and two of the boilers were disabled after being contaminated by salt water used for firefighting, the battleship was still capable of steaming within Kaafjord.&lt;ref name=Bishop_307 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Garzke and Dulin (1985), pp. 265–267&lt;/ref&gt; The British fighters also damaged four patrol craft and a large repair ship; the captain of an [[Naval trawler|armed trawler]] died and 13 other sailors on board these vessels suffered wounds.&lt;ref name=Brown_36 /&gt; [[Torstein Raaby]] of the Allied [[Secret Intelligence Service]] group in Alta reported a few hours after the raid, that no civilian casualties had resulted from the attack, and that the local population was &quot;... extremely impressed by the bombing.&quot; A further report six days after the operation relayed that the Germans estimated that it would take months to repair the damage inflicted on ''Tirpitz''.&lt;ref&gt;Rørholt and Thorsen (1990), pp. 255, 257&lt;/ref&gt;

The commander of the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'', Grand Admiral [[Karl Dönitz]], directed that the damage caused to ''Tirpitz'' during Operation Tungsten be repaired. Although the battleship was no longer capable of operating against Allied convoys for lack of air support, it was considered desirable to retain her in service in order to tie down Allied naval resources.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garzke_267&quot;&gt;Garzke and Dulin (1985), p. 267&lt;/ref&gt; Repair work began in early May after a destroyer transported equipment and workmen to Kaafjord from Germany, and ''Tirpitz'' was able to steam under her own power by 2 June. She was capable of undertaking gunnery practice by the end of June, and all repairs were completed in mid-July. During this period the battleship's anti-aircraft armament was augmented by fitting her with additional {{convert|20|mm|in|adj=on}} cannons, modifying the 150&amp;nbsp;mm guns so they could be used to attack aircraft and supplying anti-aircraft shells for her {{convert|380|mm|in|adj=on}} main guns.&lt;ref name=Garzke_267 /&gt; The defences of Kaafjord were also improved during this period. Additional radar stations and observation posts were established, and the number of smoke generators located around ''Tirpitz'' was increased.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown_37&quot;&gt;Brown (1977), p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Commonwealth War Graves section Tromsø cemetery 2013.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Colour photo of a small graveyard with about 40 dark grey gravestones|Five of the British airmen who died during Operation Tungsten are interred at the Commonwealth War Graves section of Tromsø's main cemetery&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Tromso Cemetery|url=http://www.cwgc.org/find-a-cemetery/cemetery/2016262/TROMSO%20CEMETERY|publisher=Commonwealth War Graves Commission|accessdate=20 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Following Operation Tungsten, British intelligence assessed that ''Tirpitz'' would be repaired within six months. Accordingly, Cunningham directed Fraser on 13 April to launch another attack on the battleship.&lt;ref name=Bishop_309 /&gt; While Cunningham did not believe that Barracudas could carry weapons capable of sinking ''Tirpitz'', he hoped that further air strikes would increase the period the battleship was out of service and harm her crew's morale.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_278&quot;&gt;Roskill (1960), p. 278&lt;/ref&gt; Fraser initially resisted Cunningham's order, arguing that the prospects for a successful raid were poor as the Germans would have reinforced the defences around ''Tirpitz'' and weather conditions were likely to be worse than those encountered during Operation Tungsten. He eventually relented, and Moore sailed from Scapa Flow on 21 April to attack Kaafjord again. This raid, designated Operation Planet, was called off on 24 April due to bad weather over the target area. Two other attacks, Operation Brawn and Operation Tiger Claw, also had to be cancelled on 15 and 28 May respectively because of adverse weather.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zetterling_280&quot;&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), p. 280&lt;/ref&gt; Further carrier raids were attempted in July and August after Allied intelligence determined that the repairs to ''Tirpitz'' were nearing completion. During [[Operation Mascot]] a force of 42 Barracudas and 40 fighters attacked ''Tirpitz'' on 17 July, but did not score any hits as the battleship was hidden by a smokescreen. A further four carrier raids were conducted against Kaafjord between 22 and 29 August during [[Operation Goodwood (naval)|Operation Goodwood]], but these caused only light damage to the battleship.&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 282–284&lt;/ref&gt;

In late August it was decided that further Fleet Air Arm attacks should not be attempted as the Germans were now able to cover ''Tirpitz'' in smoke before Barracudas could reach the battleship, and these aircraft could not carry bombs large enough to inflict heavy damage. As it was still seen as desirable to destroy ''Tirpitz'', the task was assigned to Bomber Command.&lt;ref&gt;Zetterling and Tamelander (2009), pp. 285–286&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 September a force of heavy bombers [[Operation Paravane|attacked Kaafjord]] after refuelling at bases in northern Russia and inflicted irreparable damage on the battleship. Following this sailed to an anchorage near [[Tromsø]] to be used as an immobile coastal defence battery. [[Operation Obviate|Another heavy bomber attack]] on 29 October caused only minor damage, and a [[Operation Catechism|third raid]] was mounted on 12 November in which ''Tirpitz'' was struck by several [[Tallboy bomb]]s and capsized with heavy loss of life among her crew.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett (2012), pp. 19–21&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
'''Citations'''
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
'''Works consulted'''
{{Commons category|Operation Tungsten}}
* {{cite book|last=Barnett|first=Correlli|authorlink=Correlli Barnett|title=Engage the Enemy More Closely: The Royal Navy in the Second World War|year=2000|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|isbn=0141390085|edition=Classic Penguin}}
* {{cite book|last=Bennett|first=G.H.|title=Hunting Tirpitz: Naval Operations Against Bismarck's Sister Ship|year=2012|publisher=University of Plymouth Press|location=Plymouth, United Kingdom|isbn=9781841023106|editor=Bennett, G.H.|chapter=Introduction|pages=7–25}}
* {{cite book|last=Bishop|first=Patrick|title=Target Tirpitz|year=2012|publisher=Harper Press|location=London|isbn=9780007431199}}
* {{cite book|last=Blair|first=Clay|authorlink=Clay Blair|title=Hitler's U-boat War: The Hunted, 1942–1945|year=2000|publisher=Modern Library|location=New York|isbn=0679640339}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=David|title=Tirpitz: The Floating Fortress|year=1977|publisher=Arms and Armour Press|location=London|isbn=0853683417}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=[[I. C. B. Dear|Dear, I. C. B.]] |editor2=[[M. R. D. Foot|Foot, M. R. D.]]|title=The Oxford Companion to World War II|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=2005|pages=35–38|chapter=Arctic convoys|isbn=9780192806703}}
* {{cite book|last=Faulkner|first=Marcus|title=War at Sea: A Naval Atlas, 1939–1945|year=2012|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=9781591145608|author2=Wilkinson, Peter }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Garzke | first1 = William H. | last2 = Dulin | first2 = Robert O. | title = Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II
| year = 1985 | publisher = Naval Institute Press | location = Annapolis, Maryland | isbn = 9780870211010 | oclc =}}
* {{cite book|last=Hinsley|first=F.H.|authorlink=Harry Hinsley|title=British Intelligence in the Second World War: Its Influence on Strategy and Operations. Volume Three, Part I|year=1984|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|isbn=0116309350|display-authors=etal}}
* {{cite book|last=Levy|first=James P.|authorlink=James P. Levy|title=The Royal Navy's Home Fleet in World War II|year=2003|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=Houndmills, United Kingdom|isbn=1403917736}}
* {{cite book|last=Rohwer|first=Jürgen|authorlink=Jürgen Rohwer|title=Chronology of the War at Sea: 1939–1945: The Naval History of World War II|year=2005|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=1591141192|edition=Third revised}}
* {{cite book |last1=Rørholt |first1=Bjørn |authorlink=Bjørn Rørholt |last2=Thorsen |first2=Bjarne |authorlink2=Bjarne Thorsen |year=1990 |title=Usynlige soldater: nordmenn i Secret Service forteller  |pages= |publisher=Aschehoug |location=Oslo |isbn=8203160468 |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2007110500050 |language=Norwegian}}
* {{cite book|last=Roskill|first=S.W.|authorlink=Stephen Roskill|title=The War at Sea 1939–1945. Volume III: The Offensive Part I|year=1960|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|oclc=58588186}}
* {{cite book|last=Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section)|title=Hunting Tirpitz: Naval Operations Against Bismarck's Sister Ship|year=2012|publisher=University of Plymouth Press|location=Plymouth, United Kingdom|isbn=9781841023106|editor=Bennett, G.H.|chapter=Naval Aircraft Attack on the Tirpitz (Operation 'Tungsten') 3 April 1944|origyear=1944|pages=133–177}}
* {{cite book|last=Tillman|first=Barrett|authorlink=Barrett Tillman|title=Hellcat Aces of World War 2|year=1996|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=London|isbn=1855325969}}
* {{cite book|last=Woodman|first=Richard|authorlink=Richard Woodman|title=The Arctic Convoys: 1941–1945|year=2004|publisher=John Murray|location=London|isbn=0719566177|edition=Paperback}}
* {{cite book|last1=Zetterling|first1=Niklas|last2=Tamelander|first2=Michael|title=Tirpitz: The Life and Death of Germany's Last Super Battleship|year=2009|publisher=Casemate|location=Philadelphia|isbn=9781935149187}}

{{coord|69.9353|23.0454|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tungsten}}
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1944 in Norway]]
[[Category:Alta, Norway]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]</text>
      <sha1>ju6qdpwykac79mt4gwaugytu00wuqam</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
