<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Operation Kita</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31271813</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733051962</id>
      <parentid>689004780</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-05T01:42:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robert Brukner</username>
        <id>27556976</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26793">{{DISPLAYTITLE:Operation ''Kita''}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict = Operation ''Kita''
|partof = [[Pacific War]], World War II
|image = [[File:Battleship-carrier Ise.jpg|300px|alt=Black and white photograph of a World War II-era warship.|Japanese battleship-carrier ''Ise'' in 1943]]
|caption = Japanese battleship-carrier ''Ise'' in 1943
|date =10–20 February 1945
|place = Waters between Singapore and Japan
|coordinates =
|map_type =
|latitude =
|longitude =
|map_size =
|map_caption =
|map_label =
|territory =
|result =
|status = Japanese victory
|combatant1 = {{flag|Empire of Japan}}
|combatant2 = {{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Australia}}
|commander1 = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} [[Matsuda Chiaki]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|USA|1912}} [[James Fife, Jr.]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|USA|1912}} [[Charles A. Lockwood]]
|units1 =
|units2 =
|strength1 = Two battleship-carriers&lt;br /&gt;One light cruiser&lt;br /&gt;Three destroyers&lt;br&gt;Aircraft
|strength2 = 26 submarines&lt;br&gt;More than 88 aircraft&lt;br&gt;Two destroyers
|casualties1 = Several aircraft
|casualties2 = None
|notes =
}}
{{nihongo|'''Operation ''Kita'''''|北号作戦|Hoku-gō sakusen|&quot;'''North'''&quot;}} was conducted by the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] (IJN) during the [[Pacific War]] in February 1945. Its purpose was to return two [[Ise-class battleship|''Ise''-class]] hybrid [[battleship]]-[[aircraft carrier]]s and four escort ships to [[Japan]] from [[Singapore]], where they had been based since November the previous year. The movement of the Japanese force was detected by the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]], but all attempts to attack it with [[submarine]]s and aircraft failed. Nevertheless, as a result of the intensifying Allied blockade of Japan, the ''Ise''-class battleship-carriers and their escorts were among the last IJN warships to safely reach the country from the [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|Southwest Pacific]] before the end of the war.

Before departing Singapore, the Japanese ships, which were designated the Completion Force, were loaded with supplies of [[oil]] and other important raw materials. This formed part of an effort to run increased quantities of supplies through the Allied [[blockade]] of Japan before the country was cut off from its empire. The Allies had learned of the Completion Force's composition and goals through [[military intelligence|intelligence]] gained from decrypting Japanese radio signals, and plans were developed for coordinated attacks on it by submarines and [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) aircraft. As part of these preparations, 26 submarines were eventually positioned along the ships' expected route.

The Completion Force sailed on 10&amp;nbsp;February 1945 and was sighted leaving port by a [[Royal Navy]] submarine. However, attempts by it and several [[United States Navy]] submarines to attack between 11 and 14&amp;nbsp;February were unsuccessful. More than 88 USAAF aircraft attempted to bomb the Completion Force on 13 and 14&amp;nbsp;February, but were unable to do so because of bad weather. A further submarine attack on 16&amp;nbsp;February did not damage any of the Japanese ships. As a result, the Completion Force reached its destination of [[Kure, Hiroshima|Kure]] in Japan on 20&amp;nbsp;February without having suffered any casualties. Despite this success, the Japanese Government was forced to discontinue its efforts to ship oil from Southeast Asia to Japan in March due to the heavy losses Allied submarines were inflicting on [[oil tanker]]s, and all the ships of the Completion Force were sunk in or near Japanese home waters before the end of the war.

==Background==
During 1944, [[Allied submarines in the Pacific War|Allied submarine attacks]] effectively cut off the supply of oil from Southeast Asia to Japan and greatly reduced Japanese imports of other commodities. By this stage of the war, the oil reserves in Japan had been largely depleted. U.S.&amp;nbsp;Navy submarines sank many Japanese warships during 1944, including the battleship {{Ship|Japanese battleship|Kongō||2}}, seven [[aircraft carrier]]s, two [[heavy cruiser|heavy]] and seven [[light cruiser]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), pp. 816–817&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1945, the Japanese Government assessed that all [[convoy]] routes from the south would eventually be cut, and attempted to supplement the supplies of oil brought in by [[Oil tanker|tankers]] by loading drums of oil on [[Cargo ship|freighters]]. Several IJN [[aircraft carrier]]s were also used to transport drums of oil from [[Singapore]] to Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prados_703&quot;&gt;Prados (1995), p. 703&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;span color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;
On 11&amp;nbsp;November 1944, the two ''Ise''-class hybrid battleship-aircraft carriers—{{Ship|Japanese battleship|Ise||2}} and {{Ship|Japanese battleship|Hyūga||2}}, which were grouped as [[Fourth Carrier Division|Carrier Division&amp;nbsp;4]] and under the command of Rear Admiral [[Matsuda Chiaki]]—sailed from the Japanese home islands to join the main body of the IJN in the Southwest Pacific.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley_199&quot;&gt;Whitley (1998), p. 199&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Hackett&quot;&gt;Hackett ''et al''. (2011)&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn | group = Note | The two ''Ise''-class battleships were fitted with a flight deck and hangar during major modifications which took place between 1942 and 1944. While they were each capable of carrying 22 [[floatplane]]s as hybrid battleship-aircraft carriers, due to a shortage of pilots they never operated as carriers.&lt;ref&gt;Worth (2001), p. 179&lt;/ref&gt;}} This deployment was made to both reinforce the remaining elements of the IJN in the area and place the ships near a source of fuel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Willmott_200&quot;&gt;Willmott (2002), p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; During their voyage from Japan, each of the battleship-carriers was loaded with about {{convert|1000|ST|t|abbr=on}} of munitions for the units defending [[Manila]] in the [[Philippines]]. Due to heavy Allied air attacks on Manila, the two warships unloaded their supplies in the [[Spratly Islands]] from 14&amp;nbsp;November. They sailed for [[Lingga Roads]] near Singapore on the 20th of the month and arrived there two days later.&lt;ref name=Hackett /&gt; The Allies learned from intelligence gained by [[Cryptanalysis|decrypting]] Japanese radio signals that the battleship-carriers had sailed. Allied submarines were ordered to keep watch for the ships, but did not intercept ''Ise'' or ''Hyūga'' during their voyage to Singapore.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prados_701&quot;&gt;Prados (1995), p. 701&lt;/ref&gt; The two battleship-carriers were deployed to [[Cam Ranh Bay]] in Indochina during December and returned to Singapore on 11&amp;nbsp;January 1945. The [[United States Third Fleet|U.S. Third Fleet]] raided the [[South China Sea]] between 10 and 20&amp;nbsp;January in search of the Japanese fleet, but did not locate ''Ise'' or ''Hyūga''.&lt;ref name=Hackett/&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

==Preparations==
In early February 1945, ''Ise'', ''Hyūga'' and an escort of smaller warships received orders to sail to Japan in what was designated Operation ''Kita''. The goal of this operation was to return some of the IJN warships in the Southwest Pacific to Japan loaded with important supplies.&lt;ref name=&quot;L-W_650&quot;&gt;Lacroix and Wells (1997), p. 650&lt;/ref&gt; The ships selected to accompany the battleship-carriers were the light cruiser {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Ōyodo||2}} (which became part of Carrier Division&amp;nbsp;4 from 10&amp;nbsp;February) and destroyers {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Asashimo||2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Hatsushimo||2}} and {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Kasumi|1937|2}}.&lt;ref&gt;Lacroix and Wells (1997), pp. 650–651&lt;/ref&gt; Carrier Division 4 and its escorts was designated the Completion Force.&lt;ref name=Hackett/&gt;

The ships of the Completion Force departed the Lingga Roads on 6&amp;nbsp;February and began loading their cargoes in Singapore the next day. Shortly before docking, ''Ise'' sustained a small amount of  damage when she struck a [[naval mine|mine]] which had been [[Bombing of Singapore (1944–1945)|dropped by Allied aircraft]]. During the Completion Force's period at Singapore all six ships were loaded with supplies and ''Ise'' received temporary repairs.&lt;ref name=Hackett /&gt; ''Hyūga'' embarked 4,944 drums of [[Avgas|aviation gasoline]] as well as 326 drums of standard [[gasoline]] and 440 oil field workers. ''Ise'' was loaded with 5,200 drums of aviation gasoline and 551 oil workers; each of the battleship-carriers also embarked {{convert|1750|ST|t|abbr=on}} of [[rubber]], 1,750&amp;nbsp;short tons of [[tin]] and {{convert|200|ST|t|abbr=on}} of other metals.&lt;ref name=&quot;L-W_651&quot;&gt;Lacroix and Wells (1997), p. 651&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ōyodo'' was loaded with {{convert|120|ST|t|abbr=on}} of tin, {{convert|70|ST|t|abbr=on}} of [[tungsten]], 70&amp;nbsp;tons of aviation gasoline, {{convert|50|ST|t|abbr=on}} of rubber, {{convert|40|ST|t|abbr=on}} of [[zinc]] and {{convert|20|ST|t|abbr=on}} of [[mercury (element)|mercury]]. A further {{convert|140|ST|t|abbr=on}} of rubber and tin was split among the three destroyers.&lt;ref name=L-W_651/&gt;

Through code breaking, Allied intelligence was aware of the Completion Force's composition and objectives. Allied [[signals intelligence]] units carefully monitored radio transmissions in the Singapore region, and the resulting &quot;[[Ultra]]&quot; intelligence provided details of the two battleship-carriers' movements to Singapore, preparations to return to Japan and planned route.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), p. 846&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Holmes_201&quot;&gt;Holmes (1979), p. 201&lt;/ref&gt; The commander of Allied submarines in the South-West Pacific Area ([[Task Force 71]]), Rear Admiral [[James Fife, Jr.]], placed a high priority on stopping ''Ise'' and  ''Hyūga'' from reaching Japan, and stationed 15 submarines along their expected route.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), pp. 846–847&lt;/ref&gt; A plan for coordinated attacks on the ships by the U.S.&amp;nbsp;Navy and USAAF was developed.&lt;ref name= &quot;CC_492&quot;&gt;Craven and Cate (1953), p. 492&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, the [[United States Seventh Fleet|U.S. Seventh Fleet]] was assigned four battleships in  Filipino waters to guard the Allied beachhead at [[Lingayen Gulf]] in [[Luzon]] against attacks by the Japanese forces based at Lingga Roads and the [[Seto Inland Sea|Inland Sea]] until the USAAF forces in the region were strong enough to assume this responsibility.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (1959), pp. 176–178&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn | group = Note | The four battleships were {{USS|Colorado|BB-45|6}}, {{USS|Mississippi|BB-41|2}}, {{USS|Pennsylvania|BB-38|2}} and {{USS|West Virginia|BB-48|2}}.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (1959), pp. 178, 303–304&lt;/ref&gt;}} As of early February, the USAAF units in the Philippines were focused on supporting the [[United States Army]]–led [[Philippines Campaign (1944–45)|Philippines Campaign]] and attacking Japanese facilities in [[Taiwan|Formosa]]. An intensive campaign against Japanese shipping in the South China Sea had been planned, but was yet to begin.&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate (1953), pp. 470, 491–492&lt;/ref&gt;

==Voyage==
[[File:route of operation Kita.svg|thumb|300px|alt=Map of Southeast Asia and East Asia between Singapore and Japan showing the approximate route of the Completion Force as described in the article|The Completion Force's approximate route between Singapore and Japan&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), pp. 826, 848&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The Completion Force sailed from Singapore on the evening of 10&amp;nbsp;February.&lt;ref name=Hackett/&gt; The timing of its departure was set by a long-term forecast of bad weather for the voyage to Japan.&lt;ref name=CC_492/&gt; The British submarine {{HMS|Tantalus|P318|6}} observed the ships leaving port and attempted to attack them on 11&amp;nbsp;February, but was driven off by a Japanese aircraft. Following this action, ''Tantalus'' radioed a contact report to Fife's headquarters.&lt;ref name= &quot;Blair_847&quot;&gt;Blair (2001), p. 847&lt;/ref&gt; The four U.S.&amp;nbsp;Navy battleships at Lingayen Gulf sailed on 10&amp;nbsp;February bound for U.S. bases in the Pacific where they were to receive repairs and undertake preparations ahead of their role supporting the [[Battle of Okinawa|invasion of Okinawa]]. The ships left the Philippines area on 14&amp;nbsp;February without having played any part in efforts to intercept the Completion Force.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (1959), p. 178&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Colorado|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/c11/colorado-iii.htm|work=Dictionary of American Navy Fighting Ships|publisher=United States Navy Naval History &amp; Heritage Command|accessdate=16 July 2011}}, {{cite web|title=Mississippi|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/m12/mississippi-iii.htm|work=Dictionary of American Navy Fighting Ships|publisher=United States Navy Naval History &amp; Heritage Command|accessdate=16 July 2011}}, {{cite web|title=Pennsylvania|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/p4/pennsylvania-ii.htm|work=Dictionary of American Navy Fighting Ships|publisher=United States Navy Naval History &amp; Heritage Command|accessdate=16 July 2011}}, {{cite web|title=West Virginia|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/w6/west_virginia-ii.htm|work=Dictionary of American Navy Fighting Ships|publisher=United States Navy Naval History &amp; Heritage Command|accessdate=16 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

U.S.&amp;nbsp;Navy submarines unsuccessfully attempted to attack the Japanese ships on 12&amp;nbsp;February. At about 1:45&amp;nbsp;pm, {{USS|Charr|SS-328|6}} detected the Completion Force at a distance of {{convert|9|mi|nmi km|lk=on|abbr=on}} using her radar and transmitted a contact report. An hour later, {{USS|Blackfin|SS-322|6}} made radar contact with the Japanese ships at a range of {{convert|15|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=Blair_847/&gt; Over the next 14 hours the submarines ''Blackfin'', ''Charr'', {{USS|Flounder|SS-251|2}}, {{USS|Pargo|SS-264|2}} and {{USS|Tuna|SS-203|2}} attempted to reach a position where they could attack the Japanese ships, but were unable to do so.&lt;ref name=Blair_847/&gt; A group of submarines to the north—comprising {{USS|Guavina|SS-362|6}}, {{USS|Hake|SS-256|2}} and {{USS|Pampanito|SS-383|2}}—was unable to reach a position where they could attack the Completion Force.&lt;ref name=Blair_847/&gt;

USAAF patrols made contact with the Completion Force on 12&amp;nbsp;February; following this, it was tracked almost continuously by radar-equipped Army Air Forces and U.S.&amp;nbsp;Navy aircraft.&lt;ref name=CC_492/&gt; On the morning of 13&amp;nbsp;February, a force of [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator|B-24 Liberator]] heavy bombers and 40 [[North American B-25 Mitchell|B-25 Mitchell]] medium bombers escorted by 48 [[North American P-51 Mustang|P-51 Mustang]] fighters was dispatched from several bases on the islands of [[Leyte]] and [[Mindoro]] to attack the Japanese ships. While the aircraft successfully rendezvoused near the Completion Force, heavy cloud cover kept them from spotting any of the ships. As radar-directed blind bombing was prohibited to avoid accidental attacks on the Allied submarines in the area, the strike force returned to its bases without attacking.&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate (1953), pp. 492–494&lt;/ref&gt; On the same day, the Australian destroyers {{HMAS|Arunta|I30|6}} and {{HMAS|Warramunga|I44|2}} departed Lingayen Gulf and proceeded to a position about {{convert|300|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}} west of Manila where they were held in readiness to rescue the crews of any aircraft downed while attacking the Completion Force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gill_599&quot;&gt;Gill (1968), p. 599&lt;/ref&gt;

More submarines attempted to attack the Japanese force on 13&amp;nbsp;February. A group of three boats—comprising {{USS|Bergall|SS-320|6}}, {{USS|Blower|SS-325|2}} and {{USS|Guitarro|SS-363|2}}—was deployed along its route, and ''Bergall'' sighted the Japanese ships at 12:30&amp;nbsp;pm. The submarine was submerged at the time and attempted to maneuver into a firing position, but could not get any closer to the ships than {{convert|4800|yd|m|abbr=on}}. Nevertheless, it fired six [[torpedo]]es at the Japanese force, all of which missed. ''Blower'' attempted a submerged attack, but the five torpedoes it fired at one of the battleship-carriers and ''Ōyodo'' missed.&lt;ref name=Blair_847/&gt; {{USS|Bashaw|SS-241|6}} and {{USS|Flasher|SS-249|2}}, the northernmost submarines that Rear Admiral Fife had deployed, encountered the Completion Force during the afternoon of 13&amp;nbsp;February. ''Bashaw'' sighted the Japanese ships as they emerged from a rain squall at 3:15&amp;nbsp;pm, but one of the battleship-carriers spotted the submarine and launched an aircraft to attack it. ''Bashaw'' was forced to dive when the battleship-carrier began shelling it with her [[main battery]], and neither it nor ''Flasher'' was able to intercept the Completion Force. During this period the other submarines in the area continued to chase the Japanese ships but did not regain contact with them.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), pp. 847–849&lt;/ref&gt;

An air attack was attempted against the Completion Force on 14&amp;nbsp;February. The number of B-24s, B-25s and escorting P-51s dispatched on this day was smaller than the force which had been used on 13&amp;nbsp;February, as the Japanese ships were now beyond the range of aircraft based at Leyte. Once again, cloud cover over the Completion Force prevented the Allied aircraft from sighting the Japanese ships, and they were unable to attack due to the prohibition on radar-aimed bombing. This was the USAAF's last attempt to bomb the Japanese force. As a result, the only successes gained by the USAAF aircraft involved in the operation were to shoot down a [[Mitsubishi Ki-57]] &quot;Topsy&quot; transport plane near the Completion Force on 13&amp;nbsp;February as well as several fighters in the area of the ships between the 12th and 14th of the month.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC_494&quot;&gt;Craven and Cate (1953), p. 494&lt;/ref&gt; The two Australian destroyers were released for other duties on 15&amp;nbsp;February.&lt;ref name=Gill_599 /&gt;

Vice Admiral [[Charles A. Lockwood]]—the commander of the [[United States Pacific Fleet|U.S. Pacific Fleet's]] submarine force—followed the unsuccessful attempts to intercept the Completion Force in the South China Sea, and stationed a further eleven submarines along its projected route between the [[Luzon Strait]] and Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blair_849&quot;&gt;Blair (2001), p. 849&lt;/ref&gt; The Completion Force reached the [[Matsu Islands]] at the northern end of the [[Taiwan Strait|Formosa Strait]] in the evening of 15&amp;nbsp;February, and anchored there for five hours.&lt;ref name=Hackett /&gt; The Japanese ships resumed their journey to Kure via Korea and the [[Shimonoseki Strait]] at midnight, and the destroyers {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Kamikaze|1922|2}} and {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Nokaze||2}} were attached to the force for part of the day.&lt;ref name=Hackett/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;L-W_652&quot;&gt;Lacroix and Wells (1997), p. 652&lt;/ref&gt; At 5:07&amp;nbsp;am on 16&amp;nbsp;February, {{USS|Rasher|SS-269|6}} intercepted the Completion Force south of the Chinese city of [[Wenzhou|Wenchow]] and fired six torpedoes at one of the escorts, but all missed. At this time the Japanese ships were sailing at a speed of {{convert|18|kn|km/h}}.&lt;ref name= Hackett/&gt; None of the other American submarines made contact with the Japanese force as it sailed to the east of where they had been positioned by Lockwood.&lt;ref name=Blair_849/&gt;

The Completion Force finished its entire voyage in about 10 days; after slipping the Allied patrols it anchored off [[Zhoushan|Chusan Island]] near [[Shanghai]] from 9:06&amp;nbsp;pm on 16&amp;nbsp;February until 7:00&amp;nbsp;am on 18&amp;nbsp;February, when it sailed for Sanzenpo Harbor near [[Sacheon]] on the southern coast of Korea. It arrived there at 4:00&amp;nbsp;pm that day, and anchored overnight. The Completion Force departed Sanzenpo Harbor at 7:00&amp;nbsp;am on 19&amp;nbsp;February and reached the Japanese island of [[Mutsurejima]] at 4:00&amp;nbsp;pm that day. After anchoring overnight, the Completion Force docked at Kure at 10:00&amp;nbsp;am on 20&amp;nbsp;February.&lt;ref name=Hackett/&gt; The ships of the Completion Force were among the last Japanese warships to reach the home islands from the Southwest Pacific.&lt;ref name=Willmott_200 /&gt;

==Aftermath==
The Allied naval commanders were disappointed by the failure of the 26 submarines directed against the Completion Force to inflict any damage on the ships.&lt;ref name=Blair_849/&gt; Fife concluded that this was due to the Completion Force's high speed, the poor weather conditions at the time of the operation and the Japanese ships being fitted with equipment that enabled them to detect submarines' radar signals. In a letter to Lockwood, he wrote that the failure of the submarines under his command &quot;was a bitter pill to take and I make no alibi&quot;.  Lockwood attributed the decision to deploy his submarines too far to the west on faulty intelligence, and told Fife that &quot;our dope certainly went sour at the last moment. Perhaps I depended too much on it&quot;.&lt;ref name=Blair_849/&gt;

The use of freighters and warships to carry oil was successful in increasing Japanese oil imports, and the total level quality of oil which reached the country during the first quarter of 1945 was greater than the amounts achieved in late 1944.&lt;ref name=Prados_703 /&gt; Nevertheless, Allied submarines sank the majority of the merchant tankers that attempted to sail from Southeast Asia to Japan during February, and in March the Japanese ceased attempting to import oil from this source.&lt;ref name=Holmes_201 /&gt; Following the departure of the Completion Force, the only major seaworthy Japanese warships remaining in the Southwest Pacific were the [[heavy cruiser]]s {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Ashigara||2}} and {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Haguro||2}} as well as the light cruiser {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Isuzu||2}}. These three cruisers did not attempt to return to Japan, and all were sunk by Allied submarines and destroyers between April and June.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (2001), pp. 852–855&lt;/ref&gt;

After reaching Japan, ''Ise'' and ''Hyūga'' were assigned to bolster the anti-aircraft defenses of the city of Kure and its naval base. Due to shortages of fuel and aircraft, the ships did not put to sea again, and both were sunk during the U.S.&amp;nbsp;Navy's [[Bombing of Kure (July 1945)|attacks on Kure]] between 24 and 28&amp;nbsp;July 1945.&lt;ref name=Whitley_199/&gt; ''Ōyodo'' became part of the Kure Training Force and remained in port until she was sunk on 28&amp;nbsp;July.&lt;ref name=L-W_652/&gt; The three destroyers also failed to survive the war; ''Asashimo'' and ''Kasumi'' fell victim to American carrier aircraft while escorting the battleship {{Ship|Japanese battleship|Yamato||2}} during [[Operation Ten-Go|Operation ''Ten-Go'']] on 6&amp;nbsp;April, and ''Hatsushimo'' sank after striking a mine near [[Maizuru, Kyoto|Maizuru]] on 30&amp;nbsp;July.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nevitt_Asashimo&quot;&gt;Nevitt (1998), ''IJN Asashimo: Tabular Record of Movement''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nevitt_Hatsushimo&quot;&gt;Nevitt (1998), ''IJN Hatsushimo: Tabular Record of Movement''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nevitt_Kasumi&quot;&gt;Nevitt (1998), ''IJN Kasumi: Tabular Record of Movement''&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* The [[Channel Dash]] was conducted by the German [[Kriegsmarine]] in February 1942; it was a successful operation to return both [[Scharnhorst class battlecruiser|Scharnhorst-class battlecruisers]] along with an escort group including the {{ship |German cruiser|Prinz Eugen||2}}, to German waters from France, using the heavily-patrolled [[English Channel]].

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|group=Note}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|last=Blair|first=Clay|authorlink=Clay Blair|title=Silent Victory: The U.S. Submarine War Against Japan| publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|year=2001|isbn=978-1-55750-217-9}}
* {{cite book|editor1-last=Craven|editor1-first=Wesley|editor2-link=James L. Cate|editor2-last=Cate|editor2-first=James|title=The Pacific: Matterhorn to Nagasaki|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|year=1953|series=The Army Air Forces in World War II|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/V/index.html|isbn=978-0-912799-03-2}}
* {{cite book |last=Gill |first=G. Hermon |title=Royal Australian Navy 1942–1945 |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/second_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67911 |series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945|Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 2&amp;nbsp;– Navy]] |year=1968 |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra |oclc=65475}}
* {{cite web|last=Hackett, Bob; Kingsepp, Sander; Ahlberg, Lars|title=IJN ISE: Tabular Record of Movement|url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/Ise.htm|work=CombinedFleet.com|accessdate=17 July 2011| year=2011}}
* {{cite book|last=Holmes|first=W.J.|title=Double-Edged Secrets: U.S. Naval Intelligence Operations in the Pacific during World War II|year=1979|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=0-87021-162-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Lacroix|first=Eric|title=Japanese Cruisers of the Pacific War|year=1997|publisher =Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=0-87021-311-3|author2=Wells, Linton }}
* {{cite book|last=Morison|first=Samuel Eliot|authorlink=Samuel Eliot Morison|title=The Liberation of the Philippines : Luzon, Mindanao, the Visayas, 1944-1945|year=2002|publisher=University of Illinois Press|location=Urbana, Illinois|isbn=0-252-07064-X|series=[[History of United States Naval Operations in World War II]] |origyear=1959}}
* {{cite web|last=Nevitt|first=Allyn D.|title=IJN Asashimo: Tabular Record of Movement|url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/asashm_t.htm|work=CombinedFleet.com| accessdate=23 March 2011|year=1998}}
* {{cite web|last=Nevitt|first=Allyn D.|title=IJN Hatsushimo: Tabular Record of Movement|url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/hatsus_t.htm|work= CombinedFleet.com|accessdate=23 March 2011|year=1998}}
* {{cite web|last=Nevitt|first=Allyn D.|title=IJN Kasumi: Tabular Record of Movement|url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/kasumi_t.htm|work=CombinedFleet.com|accessdate=23 March 2011|year=1998}}
* {{cite book|last=Prados|first=John|title=Combined Fleet Decoded : The Secret History of American Intelligence and the Japanese Navy in World War II|year=1995|publisher=Random House|location=New York|isbn=0-679-43701-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Whitley|first=M.J.|title=Battleships of World War Two: An International Encyclopedia|year=1998|publisher=Arms and Armour|location=London|isbn=1-85409-386-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Willmott|first=H.P.|title=Battleship|year=2002|publisher=Cassell Military|location=London|isbn=0-304-35810-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Worth|first=Richard|title=Fleets of World War II|publisher=Da Capo Press|year=2001|isbn=0-306-81116-2|location=Cambridge, Massachusetts}}

{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kita, Operation}}
[[Category:1945 in Asia]]
[[Category:Pacific Ocean theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Naval aviation operations and battles]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>nnnkosyj7psr5r8tha36veyjfw8td48</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
