<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Operation Passage to Freedom</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12014603</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733704887</id>
      <parentid>729954039</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-09T15:41:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>100.37.183.60</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Evacuation */changed &quot;unable to provide little more&quot; to &quot;able to provide little more&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="63125">[[Image:030630-N-0000X-001.jpg|thumb|250px|Up to a million refugees left communist [[North Vietnam]] during Operation ''Passage to Freedom'' after the country was partitioned.]]
[[Image:306-ppb-225-2012-001-pr.jpg|thumb|250px|Propaganda poster exhorting Northerners to move South. Title: &quot;Go [[South Vietnam|South]] to avoid Communism&quot;. Bottom caption: &quot;People of Southern Vietnam are welcoming with open arms Northern Vietnamese people.&quot;]]
'''Operation ''Passage to Freedom''''' was a term used by the [[United States Navy]] to describe its assistance in transporting in 1954–55 310,000 [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] civilians, soldiers and non-Vietnamese members of the French Army from communist [[North Vietnam]] (the [[Democratic Republic of Vietnam]]) to [[South Vietnam]] (the [[State of Vietnam]], later to become the [[Republic of Vietnam]]). The French and other countries may have transported a further 500,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frankum&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Operation Passage to Freedom: The United States Navy in Vietnam, 1954–55 |last=Frankum |first=Ronald |year=2007 |publisher=Texas Tech University Press |location= Lubbock, Texas |isbn=978-0-89672-608-6 |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Prados&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | url =http://www.vva.org/TheVeteran/2005_01/feature_numbersGame.htm  | first = John | last = Prados | title = The Numbers Game: How Many Vietnamese Fled South In 1954? | work = The Veteran |date=January 2005 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060527190340/http://www.vva.org/TheVeteran/2005_01/feature_numbersGame.htm |archivedate = 2006-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;l5557&quot;/&gt; In the wake of the French defeat at the [[Battle of Dien Bien Phu]], the [[Geneva Conference (1954)|Geneva Accords of 1954]] decided the fate of [[French Indochina]] after [[First Indochina War|eight years of war]] between [[French Union]] forces and the [[Viet Minh]], which sought [[Vietnam]]ese independence. The accords resulted in the [[partition of Vietnam]] at the [[17th parallel north]], with [[Ho Chi Minh]]'s communist Viet Minh in control of the north and the French-backed State of Vietnam in the south. The agreements allowed a 300-day period of grace, ending on May 18, 1955, in which people could move freely between the two Vietnams before the border was sealed. The partition was intended to be temporary, pending elections in 1956 to reunify the country under a national government.  Between 600,000 and one million northerners moved south, including more than 200,000 French citizens and soldiers in the French army &lt;ref&gt;Lindholm, p. 49; Prados&lt;/ref&gt; while between 14,000 - 45,000 civilians and approximately 100,000 Viet Minh fighters moved in the opposite direction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frankum&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruane&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=War and Revolution in Vietnam |last=Ruane |first=Kevin |year=1998 |publisher=Routledge |location= London |isbn=978-1-85728-323-5 |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tran&quot;/&gt;

The mass emigration of northerners was facilitated primarily by the [[French Air Force]] and [[French Navy|Navy]]. American naval vessels supplemented the French in evacuating northerners to [[Saigon]], the southern capital. The operation was accompanied by a large humanitarian relief effort, bankrolled in the main by the United States government in an attempt to absorb a large tent city of refugees that had sprung up outside Saigon. For the US, the migration was a public relations coup, generating wide coverage of the flight of Vietnamese from the perceived oppression of communism to the &quot;free world&quot; in the southern dictatorship under American auspices. The period was marked by a [[Central Intelligence Agency]]-backed propaganda campaign on behalf of South Vietnam's [[Roman Catholic]] Prime Minister [[Ngo Dinh Diem]]. The campaign exhorted Catholics to flee impending religious persecution under communism, and around 60% of the north's 1 million Catholics obliged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tran&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last=Tran |first=Thi Lien|title = The Catholic Question in North Vietnam| journal = Cold War History| volume = 5 | issue = 4 | pages = 427–49| publisher = Routledge| location = London|date=November 2005 | doi=10.1080/14682740500284747}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 45&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
{{Main article|First Indochina War|Geneva Conference (1954)}}

At the end of World War II, the  [[Viet Minh]] had [[Vietnamese Declaration of Independence|proclaimed independence]] under the [[Democratic Republic of Vietnam]] (DRV) in September 1945. This occurred after the withdrawal of [[Imperial Japan]], which had seized control of the French colony during World War II. The military struggle started in November 1946 when France attempted to reassert control over [[French Indochina|Indochina]] with an attack on the northern port city of [[Haiphong]].&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; The DRV was recognised by the Soviet Union and the [[People's Republic of China]] (PRC). On the other hand, the western powers recognised the French-backed [[State of Vietnam]], nominally led by Emperor [[Bảo Đại]], but with a French-trained [[Vietnamese National Army]] (VNA) which was loyal to the [[French Union]] forces. In May 1954, after eight years of fighting, the French were surrounded and defeated in a mountainous northern fortress at the [[Battle of Dien Bien Phu]].&lt;ref&gt;Karnow, pp. 210–214.&lt;/ref&gt; France's withdrawal from Indochina was finalised in the [[Geneva Conference (1954)|Geneva Accords]] of July 1954, after two months of negotiations between Ho's DRV, France, the PRC and the Soviet Union. Under the terms of the agreement, Vietnam was temporarily divided at the [[17th parallel north]] pending elections in 1956 to choose a national government that would administer a reunified country. The communist Viet Minh were left in control of North Vietnam, while the State of Vietnam controlled the south. French Union forces would gradually withdraw from Vietnam as the situation stabilised.&lt;ref&gt;Karnow, p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt; Both Vietnamese sides were unsatisfied with the outcome at Geneva; [[Ngo Dinh Diem]], Prime Minister of the State of Vietnam, denounced France's agreement and ordered his delegation not to sign. He stated &quot;We cannot recognise the seizure by Soviet China . . . of over half of our national territory&quot; and that &quot;We can neither concur in the brutal enslavement of millions of compatriots&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j412&quot;/&gt; North Vietnamese Prime Minister [[Phạm Văn Đồng]] expressed bitterness after his Soviet and Chinese backers threatened to cut support if he did not agree to the peace terms; Dong had wanted to press home the Viet Minh's military advantage so they could lay claim to more territory at the negotiating table.&lt;ref name=&quot;j412&quot;&gt;Jacobs (2006), pp. 41–42.&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the accords, there was to be a 300-day period in which free civilian movement was allowed between the two zones, whereas military forces were compelled to relocate to their respective sides. All [[French Far East Expeditionary Corps]] and VNA forces in the north were to be evacuated south of the 17th&amp;nbsp;parallel, while all Viet Minh fighters had to relocate to the north. The accords stipulated that civilians were to be given the opportunity to move to their preferred half of Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;jstart&quot;/&gt; Article&amp;nbsp;14(d) of the accords stated that:

{{quote|Any civilians residing in a district controlled by one party who wish to go and live in the zone assigned to the other party shall be permitted and helped to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;jstart&quot;/&gt;}}

Article&amp;nbsp;14(d) allowed for a 300-day period of free movement between the two Vietnams,&lt;ref name=h178&gt;Hansen, p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; ending on May 18, 1955. The parties had given little thought to the logistics of the population resettlement during the negotiations at Geneva, and assumed the matter would be minor. Despite claiming that his northern compatriots had been &quot;enslaved&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;jstart&quot;/&gt; Diem expected no more than 10,000&amp;nbsp;refugees. General [[Paul Ely]], the French Commissioner-General of Indochina, expected that around 30,000&amp;nbsp;landlords and business executives would move south and proclaimed that he would take responsibility for transporting any Vietnamese who wanted to move to territory controlled by the French Union, such as South Vietnam. [[Prime Minister of France|French Prime Minister]] [[Pierre Mendès France]] and his government had planned to provide aid for around 50,000&amp;nbsp;displaced persons.&lt;ref name=jstart/&gt; Mendes-France was sure that the FFEEC would be able to handle the work all by itself.&lt;ref name=j130&gt;Jacobs (2004), p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt; The Americans saw the period as an opportunity to weaken the communist north.&lt;ref name=&quot;jstart&quot;&gt;Jacobs (2006), pp. 43–44.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evacuation==
[[Image:HD-SN-99-02045.JPEG|thumb|Vietnamese refugees move from a French [[List of United States Navy LSMs|landing ship]] to the {{USS|Montague|AKA-98|6}} during Operation ''Passage to Freedom'' in August 1954.]]
The predictions made by Diem and Ely were extremely inaccurate.&lt;ref name=jstart/&gt; There had been heavy fighting in northern Vietnam, where the Vietminh were at their strongest, and many people had been forced to abandon their homes.&lt;ref name=f38&gt;Frankum, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; Although French charities had been operating in the north, the refugee camps were disorganised and were able to provide little more than shelter. As a result, there was a great number of northerners who wanted to leave and start a new life in the south.&lt;ref name=f39&gt;Frankum, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

The French started their evacuation with their pre-conceived notion that few would want to head south. As knowledge of the migration program spread through the communist-controlled north, thousands of predominantly northern Catholic asylum-seekers descended on the capital [[Hanoi]] and the port of [[Haiphong]], both of which were still in French control. This led to anarchy and confusion as the emigrants fought over limited shelter, food, medicine and places on the ships and planes that were bound for the south. By early August, there were over 200,000&amp;nbsp;evacuees waiting in Hanoi and Haiphong.&lt;ref name=&quot;jstart&quot;/&gt; Initially the ad hoc camps had insufficient sanitation and water quality control, leading to the possibility of outbreaks of disease. Some American representatives said that they were the worst conditions they had seen.&lt;ref name=f109&gt;Frankum, p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; The conditions continued to be poor and chaotic after the evacuation got into full swing, and did not improve significantly for a month.&lt;ref name=f114&gt;Frankum, p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; There was no organization infrastructure as far as registration or medical records and immunisation of the waiting evacuees.&lt;ref name=f109/&gt; The communists thus sent their propaganda activists through the camps and said that the lack of organisation proved that life for prospective refugees would be even worse in the south, where they would be completely under the control of South Vietnam.&lt;ref name=f110&gt;Frankum, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[French Navy]] and [[French Air Force|Air Force]] had been depleted during World War II. They were unable to deal with the unexpectedly large number of refugees.&lt;ref name=jstart/&gt; This was exacerbated by their unwillingness to allow civilian evacuees to travel on trains from outlying districts to Hanoi and Haiphong, as their priority was evacuating their military personnel and equipment. France asked Washington for assistance, so the [[United States Department of Defense|US Department of Defense]] ordered the [[United States Navy|US Navy]] to mobilise an evacuation task force.&lt;ref name=jstart/&gt;

The American government saw the evacuation as an opportunity to weaken the communists by providing for and thereby winning the loyalty of the refugees to the anti-communist cause.&lt;ref name=f38/&gt; The [[United States Operation Mission]] proposed that aside from helping to evacuate refugees to the south and thereby draining the communist population base, the Americans should provide healthcare, shelter, food and clothing in order to help the anti-communists win the fidelity of their compatriots.&lt;ref&gt;Frankum, pp. 38–39.&lt;/ref&gt; Another benefit of participating in the evacuation was that American personnel would be on the ground in North Vietnam, allowing them to gather intelligence on communist activities.&lt;ref name=f40&gt;Frankum, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

Accordingly, [[Task Force 90]] (CTF-90) was inaugurated under the command of Rear Admiral [[Lorenzo Sabin]]. US servicemen renovated and transformed cargo vessels and tank carriers to house the thousands of Vietnamese who would be evacuated in them. The repairs were frequently done en route to Haiphong from their bases at [[Subic Bay]] in the [[Philippines]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jstart&quot;/&gt; Sabin had no prior involvement in humanitarian matters, and he and his staff prepared Operation Order 2–54—the 114-page policy framework for the operation—in the space of a week during their sea voyage from Japan to Vietnam.&lt;ref name=f40/&gt;

The first US vessel to participate in the mass evacuation was the {{USS|Menard|APA-201|2}}, which left Haiphong on August 17. It carried 1,924&amp;nbsp;refugees for a 1,600&amp;nbsp;kilometre, three-day journey to the southern capital.&lt;ref name=l63/&gt; By this time, there were already 132,000 people registered at the waiting areas, although very few had any identification.&lt;ref name=&quot;f110&quot; /&gt; As a result, there would be more work to be done in identifying their needs once they arrived in the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;f110&quot;/&gt; The {{USS|Montrose|APA-212|2}} followed on the next day, with 2,100&amp;nbsp;passengers. Both were originally built as attack transport vessels. In August, the US policy was liberalised so that Vietnamese and French military personnel could also be evacuated at the discretion of CTF-90 and the [[Chief Military Assistance Advisory Group]] (CHMAAG).&lt;ref name=l63&gt;Lindholm, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; To cope with the rising volume of southbound sea transport, CHMAAG established a refugee debarkation site at [[Vũng Tàu]], a coastal port at the entrance of the [[Saigon River]]. This site relieved congestion in the Saigon refugee camps and decreased the traffic bottlenecks along the river. A setback occurred when a [[typhoon]] struck the Haiphong area, destroying almost half of the refugee staging area. Despite the problems, by September 3, the US Navy had evacuated 47,000&amp;nbsp;northerners after only two weeks of operations.&lt;ref&gt;Lindholm, p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; The high rate of evacuation caused the South Vietnamese government to order that only one shipment of at most 2,500&amp;nbsp;passengers was to arrive in Saigon or Vũng Tàu per day, until September 25. The population pressure in the south was eased as incoming numbers fell due to Viet Minh propaganda campaigns and forcible detention, combined with the rice harvesting season, which had prompted some to delay their departure.&lt;ref name=l6567/&gt; Some were even waiting to finish all their business deals before moving in the Lunar New Year. On October 10, the Viet Minh were given full control of Hanoi, closing off one point of evacuation for those who wanted out.&lt;ref name=f158&gt;Frankum, p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt; Some also decided to stay behind and see how the Viet Minh would treat the inhabitants of Hanoi before making a decision on whether to leave their ancestral lands.&lt;ref name=f158/&gt; On October 20, the French authorities that were still in control of the ports decided to waive docking fees on US vessels engaged in the evacuation.&lt;ref name=l6567&gt;Lindholm, pp. 65–67.&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the high demand, the naval vessels had to travel quickly; one ship completed one round trip in a record of only six days.&lt;ref name=f193/&gt; The record for the most passengers taken in one journey was set by the USS ''General Black'', which sailed on October 29 with 5,224 Vietnamese aboard.&lt;ref name=f159/&gt; In November, the evacuation was further hampered by another typhoon, while the entire crew of one American vessel were struck down by a [[scabies]] outbreak.&lt;ref name=f172&gt;Frankum, p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; In December, because of Viet Minh obstruction, which prevented people from rural and regional areas from travelling to Hanoi and Haiphong to emigrate, the French Navy sent ships to hover just off the coast near the regional town of [[Vinh]] to evacuate refugees.&lt;ref&gt;Frankum, pp. 188–189.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:USS Menard (APA-201).jpg|{{USS|Menard|APA-201|6}}, the first American ship to participate in the naval evacuation|thumb|left]]
According to COMIGAL,&lt;ref&gt;Formally known as the Commissariat of Refugees, COMIGAL was the acronym in French.&lt;/ref&gt; the South Vietnamese government agency responsible for the migration, French aircraft made 4,280&amp;nbsp;trips, carrying a total of 213,635&amp;nbsp;refugees. A total of 555,037&amp;nbsp;passengers were recorded on 505&amp;nbsp;sea trips. The French Navy accounted for the vast majority of the naval evacuees, with 388&amp;nbsp;voyages, while the US Navy made 109. British, [[Taiwan]]ese and [[Poland|Polish]] ships made two, two and four journeys respectively. The official figures reported that a total of 768,672&amp;nbsp;people had migrated under military supervision.  Of this number around 190,000 were French and Saigon soldiers and returned prisoners; some 43,000 were military dependents, &quot;15,000–25,000 Nung tribesmen who were military auxiliaries, between 25,000 and 40,000 French citizens, and about 45,000 Chinese residents.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Prados&quot;/&gt; It also included several thousand people who had worked for the French and Vietnamese administrations in the North.  The official figures recorded that more than 109,000&amp;nbsp;people journeyed into the south by their own means, some arriving outside the 300-day period. These people typically crossed the river that divided the zones on makeshift rafts, sailed on improvised watercraft into a southern port, or trekked through Laos. As of 1957, the South Vietnamese government claimed a total of 928,152&amp;nbsp;refugees, of whom 98.3% were ethnic Vietnamese. The 1957 report said that 85% were engaged in farming or fishing for their livelihood and 85% were [[Catholic Church|Catholics]], while the remainder were Buddhists or [[Protestant]]s.&lt;ref name=l4850/&gt; However, an October 1955 government report claimed that 76.3% were Catholics, 23.5% were Buddhists and 0.2% Protestants.&lt;ref name=h180&gt;Hansen, p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1959, however, the head of COMIGAL, Bui Van Luong, admitted that the actual number of refugees could have been as low as 600,000. The official data excluded approximately 120,000&amp;nbsp;anti-communist military personnel and claimed that only 4,358&amp;nbsp;people moved north, though no historians consider this number credible. The northward migration was attributed to itinerant workers from [[Plantation#Rubber|rubber plantations]] who returned north for family reasons.&lt;ref name=l4850&gt;Lindholm, pp. 48–50.&lt;/ref&gt;

An independent study by the French historian [[Bernard B. Fall]] determined that the US Navy transported around 310,000&amp;nbsp;refugees. The French were credited with around 214,000&amp;nbsp;airlifted refugees, 270,000&amp;nbsp;seaborne refugees and 120,000 and 80,000 Vietnamese and French military evacuees respectively.&lt;ref name=l5557/&gt; During the US Navy voyages, 54 people died on board, and 111 babies were born.&lt;ref name=f193/&gt; Fall believed that of the 109,000&amp;nbsp;refugees who went south by their own means, a large number hitchhiked on southbound French transport vessels that were not related to the migration operation. Fall felt that the figures were likely to have been overestimated, due to immigration fraud. Some refugees would travel south and register themselves, before smuggling themselves onto vessels returning north for another shipment of humans. They would then return south and re-register to claim another aid package. Likewise, with instances of entire villages moving south, the authorities frequently did not explicitly count the number of villagers, but simply took the word of the village leaders. The chiefs would often inflate the population figures to claim more aid rations. The mass exodus did not disrupt the north largely because whole villages often emigrated, instead of half a village moving and leaving the remainder of the community in disarray. Fall estimated that around 120,000&amp;nbsp;Viet Minh troops and their dependents went north. Most of these evacuations were attributed to Viet Minh military strategy, with some being ordered to stay behind in readiness for future guerrilla activities. The northward movement was facilitated by vessels leaving from assembly areas at [[Qui Nhơn]] and [[Cà Mau]] at the southernmost extremity of Vietnam. The voyages to North Vietnam were provided by empty French ships heading back north to fetch more southbound anti-communists, as well vessels from communist nations such as Poland. The Viet Minh also actively cultivated the [[Montagnard (Vietnam)|Montagnard]] indigenous people of Vietnam, whose land in the [[Central Highlands (Vietnam)|Central Highlands]] was encroached upon by incoming northern settlers. The communists spread propaganda through broadcasts in tribal languages and infiltrated the highland areas. According to a study by the [[Michigan State University Vietnam Advisory Group|Michigan State University Group]], some 6,000&amp;nbsp;tribespeople went north with the communists, accompanied by some Viet Minh who had adopted the indigenous culture.&lt;ref name=l5557&gt;Lindholm, pp. 55–57.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:HMS Warrior 1954Saigon.jpg|300px|thumb|Refugees transfer from a French LCT landing craft to British carrier [[HMS Warrior (R31)|HMS ''Warrior'']] at the port of Haiphong during the operation 4 September 1954]]

The largest numbers of Catholic refugees came from the two northern dioceses with the highest percentage of Catholics in Vietnam.&lt;ref name=h179/&gt; These were [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Phat Diem|Phát Diêm]] and [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Bùi Chu|Bùi Chu]], mainly located in modern-day [[Ninh Bình Province|Ninh Bình]] and [[Nam Định Province]]s respectively. The bishops of the dioceses, had been strident opponents of the communists, and both had organised Catholic paramilitary groups that fought against the Viet Minh, which had long identified Catholics with colonial collaborationism.&lt;ref name=h179&gt;Hansen, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt; When the communists had gained the upper hand in the north, many Catholics had already begun making preparations to move to the south, where the communists were less influential, and large movements began immediately when news of the partition came through.&lt;ref name=h179/&gt; After the defeat of French Union forces at Dien Bien Phu, French officers had evacuated their troops from Bui Chu and Phat Diem to reinforce the area between Hanoi and Haiphong which they still controlled, making it very easy for the communists to progress through the Catholic strongholds.&lt;ref name=h179/&gt;
The French withdrawal was not announced and was supposed to be secret, but the local church leadership found out quickly and the local Catholic community had already begun to move to the ports before end of talks in Geneva. By the time the accords were signed, 45,000 Catholic refugees were already waiting in Hanoi, Haiphong or [[Hải Dương]].&lt;ref name=h179/&gt; According to the records of the Catholic Church, over 70% of Catholics in Bui Chu and Phat Diem left, compared to around 50% in most other areas. The Catholic records claim that only a third of Hanoi Catholics left, and that around 80% of all clergy left.&lt;ref name=h180/&gt; In all areas, a higher proportion of priests left than laypeople, which has been attributed to the communists inflicting heavier punishments on more prominent opposition figures, such as clerics.&lt;ref name=h189&gt;Hansen, p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt; The departure rate was also lower in areas further removed from the coastal areas and departure ports;&lt;ref name=h181/&gt; in [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Hưng Hóa|Hưng Hóa]], only 11.8% of Catholics were recorded by their diocese as have migrated.&lt;ref name=h180/&gt; It has been speculated that the low rate of Hanoi residents choosing to depart may have been because the city was relatively untouched by the decade of fighting,&lt;ref name=h181/&gt; and that the varying and high rate of departures among rural Catholics was due to the influence of the local clergy;&lt;ref name=h182&gt;Hansen, p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt; priests in northern Vietnam were noted to be more theocratic and involved in civic decision-making.&lt;ref name=h187&gt;Hansen, p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; They used a variety of ways to persuade their disciples to migrate; some explained their belief that circumstances would be difficult for people who did not immigrate, some simply gave dogmatic reasons such as &quot;God is not here any more&quot;,&lt;ref name=h187/&gt; while others gave no reason at all and made declarations such as &quot;We are leaving tomorrow&quot; in the expectation that their followers would obey without question.&lt;ref name=h187/&gt; Surveys on the immigrants suggested they were largely content to follow the recommendation of the local priest.&lt;ref name=h187/&gt; In some areas, the bishop in charge of the diocese told Catholics to stay, but laypeople were more likely to leave or stay depending on the stance of the local priest with whom they had regular contact; in many cases, such as in Hanoi, a majority of priests ignored their bishop and left anyway.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen, pp. 188–189.&lt;/ref&gt;

In many cases, families left some members behind in the hope that they would retain land for the family,&lt;ref name=h185&gt;Hansen, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt; while there were reports that a minority of Catholics with links to the communists decided to stay willingly.&lt;ref name=h188&gt;Hansen, p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt;

The US provided emergency food, medical care, clothing and shelter at reception centres in Saigon and elsewhere in the south. American sources donating through the [[Agency for International Development|United States Operations Mission]] (USOM) were responsible for 97% of the aid.&lt;ref name=l50/&gt; The USOM sent public health professionals to help with sanitation in an attempt to prevent the spread of disease. Doctors and nurses were sent to help train local workers in healthcare procedures, so that they would eventually be able to take care of the medical needs refugees.&lt;ref name=f38/&gt; In order of contributions to the aid efforts, the US were followed by France, United Kingdom, Australia, West Germany, New Zealand and the Netherlands.&lt;ref name=&quot;l50&quot;&gt;Lindholm, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Australian sent farming equipment and accompanying technical instructors under the [[Colombo Plan]].&lt;ref name=f193/&gt;

With most of the refugees being Catholic, the voluntary agencies most prominent in helping the US and French governments with humanitarian relief efforts were Catholic. The [[National Catholic Welfare Conference]] and [[Catholic Relief Services]] contributed over US$35 million (${{formatprice|{{inflation|US|35000000|1954|r=-6}}}} as of {{CURRENTYEAR}}) and sent hundreds of aid workers to South Vietnam. US clerics such as [[Joseph Harnett]] spent more than a year supervising the establishment of humanitarian and religious projects in Saigon. These included the establishment and maintenance of orphanages, hospitals, schools and churches. Harnett's volunteers fed rice and warm milk to 100,000&amp;nbsp;refugees on a daily basis. Tens of thousands of blankets donated by the American Catholic organisations served as beds, makeshift roofs against monsoonal downpours and as temporary walls in mass housing facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;j45&quot;&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Nations Children's Fund]] contributed technical assistance and helped to distribute merchandise, foodstuffs and various other gifts.&lt;ref name=&quot;l50&quot;/&gt;

== Propaganda campaign ==
[[Image:Major-general-lansdale.jpg|Colonel [[Edward Lansdale]]|right|thumb|180px|alt=Man with dark hair and moustache in a dress uniform, suit and tie, sitting at a table, with a star indicating his rank, in front of a map on a wall.]]
The US ran a propaganda campaign through the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA) to enhance the size of the southward exodus. The program was directed by Colonel [[Edward Lansdale]], who masqueraded as the assistant US air attaché in Saigon while leading a covert group that specialised in psychological warfare. Lansdale had advised Diem that it was imperative to maximise the population in the south in preparation for the national reunification elections. When Diem noted the limited ability of the south to absorb refugees, Lansdale assured him that the US would bear the burden. Diem thus authorised Lansdale to launch the propaganda campaign. According to the historian Seth Jacobs, the campaign &quot;ranked with the most audacious enterprises in the history of covert action&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j52&quot;&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; Lansdale recollected that &quot;U.S. officials wanted to make sure that as many persons as possible, particularly the strongly anti-communist Catholics, relocated in the South&quot;.&lt;ref name=j133&gt;Jacobs (2004), p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; While many Diem supporters claimed that the mass exodus was proof of the popularity of Diem and the people's hatred of communism, the CIA operative Chester Cooper said &quot;the vast movement of Catholics to South Vietnam was not spontaneous&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs (2004), p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt; However, while Lansdale is often credited by historians—usually those critical of his influence—with the large exodus of refugees due to superstition, he rejected the notion that his campaign had much effect on popular sentiment, saying in later years: &quot;People don’t just pull up their roots and transplant themselves because of slogans. They honestly feared what might happen to them, and their emotion was strong enough to overcome their attachment to their land, their homes, and their ancestral graves. So the initiative was very much theirs—and we mainly made the transportation possible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hansen, pp. 182–183.&lt;/ref&gt; Some northerners who stayed behind and were interviewed half a century later said that they had not come across any pro-migration propaganda and said that their decisions were based on discussions with fellow locals.&lt;ref name=h185/&gt; They said that concerns over the possible effects of communist rule were discussed among themselves independent of outside information.&lt;ref name=h185/&gt;

Lansdale employed a variety of stunts to encourage more northerners to move south. South Vietnamese soldiers in civilian clothing infiltrated the north, spreading rumours of impending doom. One story was that the communists had a deal with Vietnam's traditional enemy China, allowing two communist Chinese divisions to invade the north. The story reported that the Chinese were raping and pillaging with the tacit approval of the communists. Lansdale hired counterfeiters to produce bogus Viet Minh leaflets on how to behave under communist rule, advising them to create a list of their material possessions so that the communists would be able to confiscate them more easily, thereby fomenting peasant discontent.&lt;ref name=j52/&gt;

Lansdale's men forged documents allegedly issued by the Vietminh that promised to seize all private property. He claimed that &quot;The day following distribution of these leatlets, refugee registration tripled&quot;.&lt;ref name=j133/&gt; The Central Evacuation Committee in Haiphong, an American-funded group, issued pamphlets claiming that in South Vietnam, &quot;the cost of living is three times less&quot;,&lt;ref name=j133/&gt; and that there would be welfare payments and free ricelands, the latter two of which were false.&lt;ref name=j133/&gt; It said that &quot;By remaining in the North you will experience famine and will damn your souls. Set out now, brothers and sisters!&quot;&lt;ref name=j133/&gt;

Lansdale's campaign focused on northern Catholics, who were known for their strongly anti-communist tendencies. His staff printed tens of thousands of pamphlets with slogans such as &quot;Christ has gone south&quot; and &quot;the [[Virgin Mary]] has departed from the North&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;j53&quot;&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; alleging anti-Catholic persecution under [[Ho Chi Minh]]. Posters depicting communists closing a cathedral and forcing the congregation to pray in front of Ho, adorned with a caption &quot;make your choice&quot;, were pasted around Hanoi and Haiphong.&lt;ref name=&quot;j53&quot;/&gt; Diem himself went to Hanoi several times in 1954 while the French were still garrisoned there to encourage Catholics to move, portraying himself as a savior of Catholics.&lt;ref name=h186&gt;Hansen, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign resonated with northern Catholic priests, who told their disciples that Ho would end freedom of worship, that sacraments would no longer be given and that anyone who stayed behind would endanger their souls.&lt;ref name=&quot;j53&quot;/&gt; A survey of refugees some five decades later confirmed that they felt their interests would be best served under a Catholic leader and that Diem had substantial personal appeal due to his religion.&lt;ref name=h186/&gt; Some have argued that the Catholics would have left regardless of Lansdale's activities, as they had first-hand experiences of their priests and co-religionists being captured and executed for resisting the communist revolution.&lt;ref name=h184&gt;Hansen, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;

Regardless of the impact of the propaganda campaigns, the Catholic immigrants helped to strengthen Diem's support base. Before the partition, most of Vietnam's Catholic population lived in the north. After the borders were sealed, the majority were now under Diem's rule. The Catholics implicitly trusted Diem due to their common faith and were a source of loyal political support. One of Diem's main objections to the Geneva Accords—which the State of Vietnam refused to sign—was that it deprived him of the Catholic regions of North Vietnam,&lt;ref name=j45/&gt; and he had unsuccessfully called for Bui Chu and Phat Diem to be omitted from the communist zone.&lt;ref name=h203&gt;Hansen, p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt; With entire Catholic provinces moving south en masse, in 1956 the Diocese of Saigon had more Catholics than Paris and Rome. Of Vietnam's 1.45&amp;nbsp;million Catholics, over a million lived in the south, 55% of whom were northern refugees.&lt;ref name=&quot;j45&quot;/&gt; Prior to this, only 520,000 Catholics lived in the Dioceses of Saigon and Huế combined.&lt;ref name=h177&gt;Hansen, p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt;

Apart from anti-communist campaigning, economics was another factor in moving south. The US gave handouts of US$89 (${{formatnum:{{inflation|US|89|1954|r=0}}}} as of {{CURRENTYEAR}}) for each refugee who moved; the per capita income in Vietnam at the time was only $85 per year (${{formatnum:{{inflation|US|85|1954|r=0}}}} per year as of {{CURRENTYEAR}}).&lt;ref name=j133/&gt; Others have pointed to natural geographic factors unrelated to and uncontrollable by political regimes. They point to the fact that the land in the south was seen as being more productive, and memories of the [[Great Vietnamese Famine of 1945]], which killed millions in the north, as reasons independent of politics that motivated migrants.&lt;ref name=h185/&gt; In the mid-1950s, northern Vietnam again suffered food shortages, and some migrants have cited food security as motive for relocation.&lt;ref name=h186/&gt; Adding to this was a general perception that Saigon was a more modern city with more economic vibrancy.&lt;ref name=h186/&gt; Earlier in the 20th century, there had also been instances of campaigns by Catholics to encourage southerly migration to exploit underdeveloped land in the south, so it was not a new concept for them.&lt;ref name=h185/&gt;

The Viet Minh engaged in counter-propaganda campaigns in an attempt to deter the exodus from the north.&lt;ref name=l78/&gt; They moved through the neighbourhoods of Hanoi and Haiphong on a daily basis, passing out their pamphlets.&lt;ref name=f112/&gt; Evacuees reported being ridiculed by the Viet Minh, who claimed that they would be sadistically tortured before being killed by the French and American authorities in Haiphong. The communists depicted the personnel of [[Task Force 90]] as cannibals who would eat their babies, predicting disaster in the jungles, beaches and mountains of South Vietnam.&lt;ref name=l78/&gt; They further said that the Americans would throw them overboard to drown in the ocean.&lt;ref name=f112&gt;Frankum, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; The Viet Minh boasted to the emigrants that it was a high and futile risk, asserting that the 1956 reunification elections would result in a decisive communist victory.&lt;ref name=l78&gt;Lindholm, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; The communist efforts were helped by the fact that many French or State of Vietnam offices in the north evacuated their personnel and sold or otherwise left behind their printing facilities, many of which fell into Viet Minh hands.&lt;ref name=f112/&gt;

== Communist prevention of emigration ==
Along with counter-propaganda, the Viet Minh also sought to detain or otherwise prevent would-be refugees from leaving. As the American and French military personnel were only present in the major cities and at air bases and on the waterfront, the communists tried to stop people from trying to leave through a military presence in the ruralside to interdict the flow of would-be refugees.&lt;ref name=f159&gt;Frankum, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt; The communists were most effective in [[Nghệ An Province|Nghệ An]] and [[Thanh Hóa Province]]s, which they had long controlled;&lt;ref name=h181/&gt; only 20% of Catholics in Thanh Hóa migrated.&lt;ref name=h180/&gt; In parts of the Red River Delta, ferry services and other water traffic were shut down so that refugees would not be able to travel to Haiphong.&lt;ref name=f160&gt;Frankum, p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases there were reports of thousands-strong groups of refugees being forced back by similar numbers of armed communist cadres.&lt;ref name=f160/&gt; The most notorious took place at Tra Ly and Ba Lang. At Tra Ly, Viet Minh troops forcibly dispersed most of a group of about 10,000 refugees. Some villagers who fled to sandbars offshore hoping for sanctuary were trapped by rising tides. The French asked the International Control Commission to dispatch mobile teams to Tra Ly, but the Viet Minh hindered ICC movement and had finished their job before the team arrived. French naval officers on the scene reported that the Viet Minh fired upon villagers in the dunes. At Ba Lang in December, the Viet Minh arrested refugee leaders who had contacted a French ship. This prompted villagers to clash with soldiers, killing one and capturing three, before barricading themselves inside a church. Troops forced their way into the church and dispersed the Vietnamese peasants, arresting several hundred. The village leader and a priest were tried by a kangaroo &quot;People’s Court&quot; and sentenced to prison.&lt;ref name= &quot;Prados&quot;/&gt; As a result, many refugees headed directly for the nearest coastal point to wait for passing vessels.&lt;ref name=f162&gt;Frankum, p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt; In one sweep of the coast near the Catholic stronghold of [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Phat Diem|Phát Diêm]], the French Navy picked up 42,000 stranded refugees in two days.&lt;ref name=f172/&gt; The VNA also swept the area in late 1954 for two days, picking up several thousand refugees, but increasing communist attacks forced them to stop.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hansen, pp. 204–205&quot;&gt;Hansen, pp. 204–205.&lt;/ref&gt; In some rural coastal areas where it was common for refugees to converge before boarding vessels to connect to the long-distance naval vessels taking them south, the Viet Minh installed mortars on the beaches to deter prospective immigrants.&lt;ref name=f190/&gt;

They prohibited mass gatherings in an attempt to stop entire villages or other large groups of people from emigrating together, and also isolated people who sold their water buffalo and other belongings, as this was a clear sign that they intended to end their farming.&lt;ref name=f190&gt;Frankum, p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt; Both the Americans and the South Vietnamese lodged complaints to the [[International Control Commission]] about the violations of the Geneva Accords, but little action was taken.&lt;ref name=f167&gt;Frankum, p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; According to B. S. M. Murti, the Indian representative on the ICC, the communists did not try to stop the refugees at first, but increased their efforts over time as it became clearer that large proportions of the population wanted to emigrate.&lt;ref name=h181&gt;Hansen, p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Media and public relations ==
[[Image:Một người di cư Thiên Chúa giáo, 1954.jpg|thumb|left|A Vietnamese [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] evacuee. Catholics represented approximately 85% of the refugees in South Vietnam.|alt=Wrinkled old man wearing a straw [[Pointed hat|conical hat]], black ''ao baba'', and a large crucifix necklace holds a white cylindrical container with English language writing on it. Behind him is another person, partially obscured, wearing black with straw baskets of luggage on their head.]]

The United States reaped substantial public relations benefits from the mass exodus, which was used to depict the allure of the &quot;free world&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j45&quot;/&gt; This was enhanced by the comparatively negligible number of people who voluntarily moved into the communist north. The event generated unprecedented press coverage of Vietnam.&lt;ref name=j45/&gt; Initially however, the press coverage was scant, and Admiral Sabin bemoaned the lack of promotional work done by the US Navy to publicise the evacuation among the American media.&lt;ref&gt;Frankum, pp. 167–168.&lt;/ref&gt; At one point, a journalist from the [[Associated Press]] travelled from [[Manila]] to Haiphong, but was ordered back by superiors on the grounds that Americans were not interested in the subject.&lt;ref name=f168&gt;Frankum, p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, over time, the media interest grew. Many prominent news agencies sent highly decorated reporters to cover the event. ''[[The New York Times]]'' dispatched [[F. Tillman Durdin|Tillman]] and [[Peggy Durdin|Peggy]] Durdin, while the ''[[New York Herald Tribune]]'' sent the [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning war reporters [[Marguerite Higgins]] and [[Homer Bigart]]. Future US embassy official [[John Mecklin]] covered the event for ''[[Time Life]]''. The press reports presented highly laudatory and emotional accounts of the mass exodus of Vietnamese away from the communist north. ''Time Life'' called the mass migration &quot;a tragedy of almost nightmarish proportions&amp;nbsp;... Many [refugees] went without food or water or medicine for days, sustained only by the faith in their heart.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;j45&quot;/&gt;

In the American Catholic press, the migration was given front page coverage in diocesan newspapers. The accounts were often sensationalist, demonizing the communist Viet Minh as religious persecutors who committed barbaric atrocities against Catholics.&lt;ref name=&quot;j46&quot;/&gt; ''[[Our Sunday Visitor]]'' called the &quot;persecution&quot; in Vietnam &quot;the worst in history&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;j46&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;osv&quot;/&gt; alleging that the Viet Minh engaged in &quot;child murder and cannibalism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j46&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;osv&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Today's Persecution Worst in History |date=1955-03-20| work=[[Our Sunday Visitor]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; San Francisco's ''Monitor'' told of a priest whom the Viet Minh &quot;beat with guns until insensible and then buried alive in a ditch&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j46&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bishops Bare Red Record of Viet Violence |date=1954-12-24| work=Monitor}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Newark, Ohio]]'s ''[[The Advocate (Newark)|The Advocate]]'' posted an editorial cartoon titled &quot;Let Our People Go!&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;j46&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Let Our People Go! |date=1954-12-03| work=[[The Advocate (Newark)|The Advocate]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; depicting mobs of Vietnamese refugees attempting to break through a blood-laced fence of barbed wire. [[Milwaukee]]'s ''Catholic Herald Citizen'' described two priests who had been chained together and &quot;suffered atrocious and endless agony&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j46&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Viet Minh Violence Angers U.S. Bishops |date=1954-11-27| work=Catholic Herald Citizen}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other papers depicted the Viet Minh blowing up churches, torturing children and gunning down elderly Catholics. One paper proclaimed that &quot;the people of Vietnam became a crucified people and their homeland a national Golgotha&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;j46&quot;&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic media also ran stories about Buddhist refugees who converted, hailing it as proof of their religion's superiority.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs (2004), pp. 191–192.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Social integration ==
The mass influx of refugees presented various social issues for South Vietnam. The new arrivals needed to be integrated into society with jobs and housing, as long periods in tents and temporary housing would sap morale and possibly foster pro-communist sympathies. Diem had to devise programs to ease his new citizens into the economic system.&lt;ref name=&quot;j54&quot;&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

Diem appointed [[Bui Van Luong]]—a family friend and devout Catholic—as the head of COMIGAL, the government resettlement agency. COMIGAL worked in cooperation with the United States Operations Mission, the non-military wing of the American presence and the [[Military Assistance Advisory Group]].&lt;ref name=j54/&gt; Although COMIGAL was purely dedicated to refugee issues, there was a constant turnover of public servants through their staff, and the benefits of continuity did not materialize.&lt;ref name=f193/&gt; After only a few months in the job, Luong was replaced by Pham Van Huyen on December 7, 1954.&lt;ref name=f193/&gt; COMIGAL were supplemented by American Catholic aid agencies and an [[Michigan State University Vietnam Advisory Group|advisory group from Michigan State University]], where Diem had stayed while in self-imposed exile in the early 1950s.&lt;ref name=j54/&gt; There were three phases in the resettlement program.&lt;ref name=h193&gt;Hansen, p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt; With more than 4,000&amp;nbsp;new arrivals per day, the northerners were housed in Saigon and Vũng Tàu in 42 makeshift reception centers.&lt;ref name=h193/&gt; These consisted of existing schools, vacated French barracks, churches and tent cities on the grounds of [[Tan Son Nhut Air Base]] and [[Phú Thọ Racecourse]].&lt;ref name=h193/&gt; These could not be used indefinitely as the grounds needed to be used for their preexisting purpose, and furthermore, such ad hoc areas were vulnerable to outbreaks of fire and disease.&lt;ref name=h193/&gt;

The refugees needed buildings such as schools, hospitals, warehouses, places of worship were built for them. As part of the second phase, temporary villages were built and by mid-1955, most of the one million refugees were living in rows of temporary housing settlements, mostly near highways leading out of Saigon, in provinces adjacent to the capital. The largest concentration of housing in this second stage was located to the north of the capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;j54&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=h193/&gt; Only a minority could be sent to the fertile [[Mekong Delta]], as the area was already overcrowded. It was also restive due to the presence of militant religious sects, so the most of the military evacuees were sent there.&lt;ref name=f149/&gt;

Overcrowding was a serious problem in many of the ad hoc secondary camps set up in the Saigon region, and led to public health issues.&lt;ref name=f149/&gt; The [[Biên Hòa]] region on the northeastern outskirts of Saigon was scheduled to have a capacity of 100,000 refugees,&lt;ref name=f149&gt;Frankum, p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; but this was soon exceeded.&lt;ref&gt;Frankum, pp. 180–195.&lt;/ref&gt; In the Ho Nai camp near Bien Hoa, which was supposed to hold only 10,000 refugees, more than 41,000 were present by the end of 1954.&lt;ref name=f192&gt;Frankum, p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt; The area surrounding [[Thủ Dầu Một]] north of the southern capital had initially been allocated a quota of 20,000 even though there was no rice paddies in the area.&lt;ref name=f149/&gt; The area near [[Tây Ninh]] was to accommodate 30,000 people, although the locals thought that 100,000 could fit in.&lt;ref name=f149/&gt; Some large Catholic settlements such as [[Thủ Đức District|Thủ Đức]], [[Bình Thạnh District|Bình Thạnh]] and [[Gò Vấp District|Gò Vấp]] on the outskirts of Saigon have now been subsumed by urban sprawl and are now districts of the city.&lt;ref name=h202&gt;Hansen, p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the excessive number of inhabitants, the infrastructure at many camps could not cope and the promises made to the refugees were not kept.&lt;ref name=f192/&gt; American military doctors travelled around the south in groups of three, and because of the paucity of health professionals, saw around 150–450 patients per day. They were also hampered by customs law, which only allowed charities to bring medicine into the country without taxation. This forced them to turn to charitable organisations as a conduit, creating another layer of bureaucracy.&lt;ref&gt;Frankum, pp. 171–172.&lt;/ref&gt; This was exacerbated by the fact that some corrupt Vietnamese officials pocketed the medical aid.&lt;ref name=f183&gt;Frankum, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;

The organisational ability of the government agencies charged with overseeing the integration of the refugees into society was frequently criticised by American officials.&lt;ref name=f150&gt;Frankum, p. 150.&lt;/ref&gt; In many cases, the individual officials simply made their own decisions and the goal of resettling the northerners without disruption to the existing local economy or social structure was not achieved. In other cases, the northern Catholics formed their own committees and settled and built on areas as they saw fit.&lt;ref name=h194&gt;Hansen, p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of September, the shortage of funds and equipment had eased, but their distribution was not organised or coordinated effectively.&lt;ref name=f150/&gt; At the same time, some Viet Minh cadres who stayed in the south after the partition pretended to be refugees and stirred up trouble inside the camps.&lt;ref name=f183/&gt; Aside from disruption by communists, other non-communist movements such as the [[Việt Nam Quốc Dân Đảng]] were strong in areas of central Vietnam, were opponents of Diem and some of them were military personnel.&lt;ref name=f185&gt;Frankum, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt; This sometimes caused hindrance in civilian-military cooperation in the resettlement program, as some of Diem's public servants were suspicious of the military's reliability as a working partner.&lt;ref name=f185/&gt;

At the time, much of the rural ricelands had been abandoned due to war and lay fallow. The Americans pressured Diem to assume control of such lands and distribute it to the new settlers and to allow them to start their new lives and ease the overcrowding in the camps, but no action was taken in 1954.&lt;ref name=f193&gt;Frankum, p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, there was a severe wastage of personnel due to the placement of refugees in land that was inappropriate to them. Vietnamese officials had resolved to place the settlers in land similar to their northern origins so that they could be productive, but bureaucratic difficulties hampered COMIGAL and no plan was produced. Throughout 1954, 60% of the new arrivals identified themselves as having an agrarian background, but only 20% of the total refugees were placed in arable farming areas, meaning that at least 40% of the northerners were in areas not appropriate for their skill set.&lt;ref name=f192/&gt; There were also severe problems in finding and then distributing farming equipment to the northerners so that they could get to work and resuscitate the agricultural sector that was hindered by the war.&lt;ref name=f192/&gt;

The next objective was to integrate the refugees into South Vietnamese society. At the time, there was a lack of arable land in secure areas. In early 1955, the Viet Minh still controlled much of the [[Mekong Delta]], while other parts were controlled by the private armies of the [[Cao Đài]] and [[Hòa Hảo]] religious sects. The [[Bình Xuyên]] organised crime gang controlled the streets of Saigon, having purchased the operating license for the national police from Emperor [[Bảo Đại]]. The new arrivals could not be safely sent to the countryside until the Viet Minh had moved north and Diem had dispersed the sects and gangs. The urban areas were secured when the VNA defeated the Bình Xuyên in the [[Battle for Saigon]] in late April and early May. Lansdale managed to bribe many of the Hòa Hảo and Cao Đài military commanders to integrate into Diem's VNA, but some commanders fought on. It was not until early 1956 that the last Hoa Hao commander, [[Ba Cụt]], was captured in an [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam]] campaign by General [[Dương Văn Minh]]. This allowed COMIGAL to send expeditions to survey the rural land for settlement.&lt;ref name=&quot;j54&quot;/&gt;

The third phase of the resettlement involved the dispersal of the new arrivals from the temporary villages in regions surrounding the capital and other large cities. The areas where the refugees had initially were over settled, notably Biên Hòa, where the population had doubled during the migration period. In contrast, two thirds of South Vietnamese provinces had taken less than 10,000 refugees, and some of these less than 1,000.&lt;ref name=h195&gt;Hansen, p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt; In the crowded provinces there were fears of social unrest due to a shortage of work.&lt;ref name=h195/&gt;

COMIGAL dispatched inspection teams throughout South Vietnam to identify areas that were suitable for accommodating the new arrivals according to their professional skills. This required a search for arable land for farmers, favourable coastal areas for fishing and areas near large population centres for industrially oriented arrivals. Having identified the relevant areas, COMIGAL would set up plans for settlement subprojects, sending proposals to the USOM or the [[French Technical and Economic Cooperation Bureau]] to gain approval and funding. The bureaucracy was relatively low, with most applications taking less than a fortnight for finalising paperwork and receiving approval. Each subproject was given a nine-month deadline for completion.&lt;ref name=&quot;l51&quot;&gt;Lindholm, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

When suitable areas were found, groups of refugees usually numbering between one and three thousand were trucked to the site and began creating the new settlement. This involved digging wells, building roads and bridges, clearing forests, bushes and swamps and constructing fishing vessels. Village elections were held to select members for committees that would liaise with COMIGAL on behalf of the new settlement.&lt;ref name=&quot;l51&quot;/&gt;

COMIGAL provided the settlers with agrarian implements, fertilisers and farm animals. By mid-1957, 319&amp;nbsp;villages had been built. Of these, 288 were for farmers and 26 for fishermen. The refugees settled predominantly in the [[Mekong Delta]], where 207&amp;nbsp;villages were built.&lt;ref name=l5253/&gt; The most notable scheme in the area was the Cai San Agricultural Resettlement Project, based along a system of canals near [[Long Xuyên]].&lt;ref name=h195/&gt; Another 50 villages were created further north near the border with North Vietnam, while 62 were built in the central highlands.&lt;ref name=l5253/&gt; A 1955 government report claimed that only 2% of the land in the central highlands, mostly inhabited by indigenous tribes were being used for economic purposes, and it was seen as a key area for exploitation and building settlements to block the advance of communism.&lt;ref name=h196&gt;Hansen, p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt; The area was seen as an important means of alleviating overcrowding, fuelling rapid economic development, and the government hoped that the presence of ethnic Vietnamese development would prompt the indigenous tribespeople to abandon their hunter-gatherer lifestyle, thus &quot;guiding them on the path to civilization and progress, so that they might join the ranks of the State's founders and liberators&quot;.&lt;ref name=h196/&gt; In the Central Highlands town of [[Buôn Ma Thuột]], the local sawmill was inundated with lumber to build houses and much of the surrounding forest was cleared for settlements.&lt;ref name=f193/&gt; In total, 92,443&amp;nbsp;housing units were constructed, serviced by 317 and 18 elementary and secondary schools respectively. 38,192&amp;nbsp;hectares of land were cleared and some 2.4&amp;nbsp;million tons of [[potassium sulfate]] fertiliser were distributed.&lt;ref name=l5253&gt;Lindholm, pp. 52–53.&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 1957, Diem dissolved COMIGAL, declaring that its mission had been accomplished.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Difficulties and criticism ==
{{See also|Huế Phật Đản shootings|Xá Lợi Pagoda raids|Arrest and assassination of Ngô Đình Diệm}}
[[Image:Ngo Dinh Diem - Thumbnail - ARC 542189.png|thumb|right|President [[Ngo Dinh Diem]] of South Vietnam saw the predominantly Catholic refugees as his most reliable constituency.|alt=A portrait of a middle-aged man, looking to the left in a half-portrait/profile. He has chubby cheeks, parts his hair to the side and wears a suit and tie.]]
The program had some loose ends that manifested themselves later. Many refugees were not economically integrated and lived from government handouts. Critics noted that the refugees had become a special interest group that fostered resentment. The COMIGAL officials often decided not to split up refugees belonging to the same village, hoping to maintain social continuity.&lt;ref name=j56/&gt; In some cases, Catholic priests refused to obey government directives to settle in certain areas.&lt;ref name=f191&gt;Frankum, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the refugees also refused to relocate from the camps on the outskirts of the capital, wanting to live an urban lifestyle,&lt;ref name=f151&gt;Frankum, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt; and objecting to Diem's desire that they help developed inhospitable frontier territory where disease was more common and the economy less developed.&lt;ref name=h197&gt;Hansen, p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt; On occasions, the reluctance to disperse away from Saigon resulted in protests outside Diem's residence.&lt;ref name=h199&gt;Hansen, p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; Many Catholic villages were effectively transplanted into southern territory. This was efficient in the short run but meant that they would never assimilate into southern society. They had little contact with the Buddhist majority and often held them in contempt, sometimes flying the Vatican flag instead of the national flag.&lt;ref name=j153/&gt; Peter Hansen, an Australian Catholic priest and academic scholar of religion, has added that tensions between northern and southern Catholics were also present, due to issues of regionalism and local traditions. Hansen also said that northern Catholics took a more defensive attitude towards other religions than their southern co-religionists, and were more likely to see non-Catholics as a threat. He further noted that northern Catholics had a more theocratic outlook in that they were more willing to listen to the advice of priests on a wide range of issues, not only spiritual and ecclesiastical matters.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen, pp. 177–178.&lt;/ref&gt; These differences and the sense of segregation persist to the current day.&lt;ref name=h201&gt;Hansen, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt;

Diem, who had a reputation for heavily favouring Catholics, granted his new constituents a disproportionately high number of government and military posts on religious grounds rather than merit.&lt;ref name=j153/&gt; The disproportionate number of northerners who occupied leadership posts also raised tensions among some regional-minded southerners who regarded them as intruders.&lt;ref name=h175&gt;Hansen, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; He continued the French practice of defining Catholicism as a &quot;religion&quot; and Buddhism as an &quot;association&quot;, which restricted their activities. This fostered a social divide between the new arrivals and their compatriots. While on a visit to Saigon in 1955, the British journalist and novelist [[Graham Greene]] reported that Diem's religious favouritism &quot;may well leave his tolerant country a legacy of anti-Catholicism&quot;.&lt;ref name=j56&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1963, simmering discontent over Diem's religious bias exploded into mass civil unrest during the [[Buddhist crisis]]. After the [[Buddhist flag]] was prohibited from public display for the [[Vesak]] celebrations commemorating the birth of [[Gautama Buddha]], Diem's forces opened fire and killed nine protesters.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; As demonstrations continued through the summer, the [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam Special Forces]] ransacked pagodas across the country, killing hundreds and jailing thousands of Buddhists.&lt;ref name=j153&gt;Jacobs (2006), p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt; The tension culminated in Diem being overthrown and [[Arrest and assassination of Ngô Đình Diệm|assassinated]] in a [[1963 South Vietnamese coup|November coup]].&lt;ref&gt;Jones, p. 429.&lt;/ref&gt;

The indigenous population in the central highlands complained bitterly about the settlement of ethnic Vietnamese Catholics in their regions. As a result of their discontent with the southern government, communist propagandists in the highlands found it easier to win them over.&lt;ref&gt;Lindholm, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{reflist|colwidth=25em}}

== References ==
{{commons category}}
* {{cite book |title=Operation Passage to Freedom: The United States Navy in Vietnam, 1954–55 |last=Frankum |first=Ronald |year=2007 |publisher=Texas Tech University Press |location=Lubbock, Texas |isbn=978-0-89672-608-6 |url= }}
* {{cite journal |last= Hansen |first= Peter |date= 2009 |title= Bắc Di Cư: Catholic Refugees from the North of Vietnam, and Their Role in the Southern Republic, 1954–1959 |journal = Journal of Vietnamese Studies |volume= 4 |issue= 3 |pages= 173–211 |publisher= University of California Press |location = Berkeley, California |doi= 10.1525/vs.2009.4.3.173}}
* {{cite book |title=America's Miracle Man in Vietnam: Ngo Dinh Diem, Religion, Race, and U.S. Intervention in Southeast Asia, 1950–1957 |author=Jacobs, Seth |publisher=Duke University Press |year=2004 |isbn=0-8223-3440-2 |location=Durham, North Carolina}}
* {{cite book| first=Seth |last=Jacobs| year=2006| title=Cold War Mandarin: Ngo Dinh Diem and the Origins of America's War in Vietnam, 1950–1963| publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield| isbn=0-7425-4447-8 |location=Lanham, Maryland}}
* {{cite book| first=Howard |last=Jones| year=2003| title= Death of a Generation: How the Assassinations of Diem and JFK Prolonged the Vietnam War | publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]| isbn=0-19-505286-2|location=New York}}
* {{cite book| title=Vietnam: A History| authorlink=Stanley Karnow |first=Stanley |last=Karnow |year=1997 |publisher=Penguin Books |isbn=0-670-84218-4 |location=New York}}
* {{cite book| first=Richard |last=Lindholm| year=1959| title= Viet-nam, The First Five Years: An International Symposium|publisher=Michigan State University Press}}
* {{cite book |title=War and Revolution in Vietnam |last=Ruane |first=Kevin |year=1998 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=978-1-85728-323-5 |url= }}
* {{cite journal |last= Tran |first= Thi Lien |date= November 2005 |title= The Catholic Question in North Vietnam: From Polish Sources, 1954–56 |journal= Cold War History |volume= 5 | issue= 4 |pages= 427–449 |publisher= Routledge |location= London |doi= 10.1080/14682740500284747}}

{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Operation Passage To Freedom}}
[[Category:Vietnamese migration]]
[[Category:Ngo Dinh Diem]]
[[Category:1954 in Vietnam]]
[[Category:1955 in Vietnam]]</text>
      <sha1>15mljlcedublsiznc8sinsz3sb7trhm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
