<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>R. V. C. Bodley</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28018225</id>
    <revision>
      <id>720127361</id>
      <parentid>718511078</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-13T22:15:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bearfoot</username>
        <id>238623</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early life and First World War */ mother's name corrected.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24569">{{featured article}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2014}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
| name          = Ronald Victor Courtenay Bodley
| image         =File:R. V. C. Bodley restoration.jpg
| caption       =R. V. C. Bodley, {{circa}} 1914
| alt              = A black and white portrait photo of R. V. C. Bodley in a military uniform
| birth_date          = {{birth date|1892|03|3|df=yes}}
| death_date          = {{death date and age|1970|05|26|1892|03|3|df=yes}}
| placeofburial_label =
| placeofburial =
| birth_place  = [[Paris]], France
| death_place  =  [[Bramley, Surrey]], United Kingdom
| placeofburial_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
| nickname      =
| allegiance    = United Kingdom
| branch        = United Kingdom
| serviceyears  = 1911–19&lt;br /&gt;1939–43
| rank          = [[Major (United Kingdom)|Major]]
| unit          =
| commands      =
| battles       = [[First World War]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Second World War]]
| awards        = [[Military Cross]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Legion of Honour]] (France)&lt;br /&gt;[[Order of the Black Star]] (France)&lt;br /&gt;[[Order of the Crown (Romania)|Order of the Crown]] (Romania)&lt;br /&gt;[[Order of Wen-Hu]] (China)
| relations     = [[John Edward Courtenay Bodley]] (father)
| laterwork     = Author, screenwriter
}}

'''Ronald Victor Courtenay (R. V. C.) Bodley''', [[Military Cross|MC]] (3 March 1892 – 26 May 1970) was a [[British Army]] officer, author and journalist. Born to English parents in [[Paris]], he lived in [[France]] until he was nine, before attending [[Eton College]] and then the [[Royal Military Academy Sandhurst]]. He was commissioned into the [[King's Royal Rifle Corps]] and served with them during the First World War. After the war he spent seven years in the [[Sahara]] desert, and then travelled through Asia. Bodley wrote several books about his travels. He was considered among the most distinguished British writers on the Sahara, as well as one of the main western sources of information on the [[South Pacific Mandate]]s.

Bodley moved to the United States in 1935, where he worked as a [[screenwriter]]. He re-enlisted in the British Army at the outbreak of the Second World War and was sent to Paris to work for the [[Ministry of Information (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Information]]. He later immigrated to the United States, where he continued to work as a writer and also as an advisor to the [[United States Office of War Information]].

== Early life and First World War ==
Bodley was born in [[Paris]] on 3 March 1892 to civil servant and writer [[John Edward Courtenay Bodley]] and Evelyn Frances Bodley (née Bell). He was the oldest of three children; his brother Josselin and sister Ava were born in 1893 and 1896 respectively.&lt;ref name=keio&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://koara.lib.keio.ac.jp/xoonips/modules/xoonips/download.php/AN10030060-20130930-0017.pdf?file_id=94715 |title=R.V.C. Bodley (&quot;Bodley of Arabia&quot;) at Keio University, 1933 |last=Snell |first=William |year=2013 |journal=The Hiyoshi Review of English studies |publisher=[[Keio University]] |issue=63 |pages=17–49 |format=PDF |accessdate=3 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bodley was a cousin of [[Gertrude Bell]],&lt;ref name=smh /&gt; a writer and archeologist who helped establish the [[Hashemite]] dynasties, and he was also a descendant of diplomat and scholar Sir [[Thomas Bodley]], founder of the [[Bodleian Library]].{{sfn|Carnegie|1981|page=280}} He lived in [[France]] with his parents until he was nine.{{sfn|Carnegie|1981|page=280}} His grandfather owned a Turkish palace in [[Algiers]], which Bodley often visited as a child.&lt;ref name=arabia /&gt;

Bodley was educated at a [[Lycée]]{{sfn|Bodley|1968}} in Paris before he was sent to [[Eton College]] and then to the [[Royal Military Academy Sandhurst]]. Bodley showed interest as a writer during this time, writing poetry at Eton and for a cadet magazine at Sandhurst.&lt;ref name=keio/&gt; From Sandhurst he was commissioned into the [[King's Royal Rifle Corps]] as a [[second lieutenant]] in September 1911.&lt;ref name=smh&gt;{{cite web |url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/27894878 |title=Englishman In The Garden Of Allah |date=9 August 1947 |work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |accessdate=18 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=28532|startpage=6882|endpage=6882|date=19 September 1911|accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He spent three years serving in a regiment in India where he began to write and stage plays. His commanding officer once remarked &quot;The plays are amusing. You're a credit to the regiment and all that, but did you join the army to become a soldier or a comedian?&quot; Shortly thereafter the [[First World War]] commenced,&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt; and Bodley was sent to the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] for four years.{{sfn|Bodley|1945}} He was wounded several times,&lt;ref name=arabia&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/1943/02/27/bodley-of-arabia |title=Bodley of Arabia |last1=Flanner |first1=Janet |last2=Maloney |last3=Kinkead |first3=Eugene |first2=Russell |date=27 February 1943 |work=The New Yorker |accessdate=2 February 2015}} {{subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt; including by [[Chemical weapons in World War I|chemical gas]].&lt;ref name=keio /&gt; At the age of 26 he was given the rank of [[Lieutenant colonel (United Kingdom)|lieutenant colonel]] and command of a battalion.{{sfn|Bodley|1968}} He was appointed assistant [[military attaché]] to Paris&lt;ref name=smh /&gt; on 15 August 1918,{{sfn|Dutton|2001|page=164}} and attended the [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|1919 Paris Peace Conference]]. What he heard there reportedly made him feel that he and the millions of other soldiers had fought for nothing;&lt;ref name=smh /&gt; he wrote later that &quot;selfish politicians [were] laying the groundwork for the Second World War – each country grabbing all it could for itself, creating national antagonisms, and reviving the intrigues of secret.&quot;{{sfn|Carnegie|1981|page=281}} Disillusioned with the military, Bodley considered a career in politics instead,&lt;ref name=smh /&gt; on the advice of [[David Lloyd George]].&lt;ref name=arabia /&gt;

Gertrude Bell introduced Bodley to [[T. E. Lawrence]].&lt;ref name=smh /&gt; Bodley ran into Lawrence one day outside the Paris Peace Conference and told him of his intent to move into politics. Lawrence responded furiously, calling him a moron and a traitor. When he replied that he had no other prospects now that the war was over and asking what he should do, Lawrence suggested &quot;Go live with the Arabs.&quot;&lt;ref name=smh /&gt; Bodley said his conversation with Lawrence, which lasted &quot;less than 200 seconds&quot;, proved to be life-changing.{{sfn|Carnegie|1981|page=281}} He promptly sorted his affairs and went to live in the [[Sahara]]. His bemused friends held him a farewell party. They all agreed he would be back in six weeks; he stayed in the Sahara for seven years.&lt;ref name=smh /&gt;

== Travels through the Sahara and Asia ==
Bodley spent his seven years{{sfn|McDonald|2007|page=33}} in the Sahara desert living with a [[nomad]] [[Bedouin]] tribe. He purchased a herd of sheep and goats and used them as a source of income. He hired 10 shepherds to care for his flock, and consistently earned 120% on his investment.&lt;ref name=arabia /&gt; He wore Arab dress, spoke Arabic, practiced the Muslim faith and abstained from alcohol;&lt;ref name=arabia /&gt; Bodley continued to be a non-drinker after leaving the Sahara.&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt; He left the tribe on the advice of its chief, who told him there was no use in continuing to pretend to be an Arab.&lt;ref name=arabia /&gt; In 1927 he wrote ''Algeria From Within'', after being encouraged to do so by publisher [[Michael Joseph (publisher)|Michael Joseph]].&lt;ref name=keio/&gt; The book is based on his experiences living in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Pond |first=Alonzo |authorlink=Alonzo W. Pond |date=March 1928 |title=Algeria from Within. by R. V. C. Bodley |journal=[[American Journal of Sociology]] |volume=33 |issue=5 |pages=844–845 |doi=10.1086/214565}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= |first= |last2= |first2= |date=October 1927 |title=Algeria from within – R.C. Bodley |journal=[[The Geographical Journal]] |publisher=[[The Royal Geographical Society]] |volume=70 |issue=4 |pages=398–399 |doi=10.2307/1782074}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book's success greatly exceeded his expectations, prompting him to continue writing.&lt;ref name=keio /&gt; His first novel, ''Yasmina'', was published later that year; it sold well and was reprinted. His next novel, ''Opal Fire'', published the following year, was a commercial failure, though this did not discourage him from continuing to write.&lt;ref name=keio /&gt; He regarded his time in the Sahara as &quot;the most peaceful and contented years&quot; of his life.{{sfn|Carnegie|1981|page=280}} He was considered amongst the most distinguished British writers on the Sahara.{{sfn|Speake|2003|page=886}}

{{quote box
|width=35em
|quote=&quot;One of the strongest impressions I had when I lived with the Arabs, was the 'everyday-ness' of God. He ruled their eating, their travelling, their business, their loving. He was their hourly thought, their closest friend, in a way impossible to people whose God is separated from them by the rites of formal worship.&quot;
|source=Ronald Bodley, commenting on life in the Sahara{{sfn|Cranston|1949|page=171}}
}}

After leaving the Sahara, Bodley spent three months in [[Java]] working on a tea plantation, before travelling to China and Japan.&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt; The success of ''Algeria From Within'' made it easy for him to obtain work as a journalist in Asia. He became a foreign correspondent for ''[[The Sphere (newspaper)|The Sphere]]'' in London and ''[[The Advertiser (Adelaide)|The Advertiser]]'' in Australia.&lt;ref name=keio /&gt; Bodley was one of several westerners to be granted access to the [[South Pacific Mandate]]s by Japan in the 1930s,{{sfn|Peattie|1992|page=245}} and he has been cited as one of the main sources of information on the area at the time.{{sfn|Peattie|1992|page=246}} Like other westerners allowed to visit the region, he reported that there was no evidence that Japan was militarising the area. Bodley's movements were &quot;carefully choreographed&quot; by the [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Japan)|Gaimu-shō]].&lt;ref name=keio/&gt; He wrote about his experiences and findings in his 1934 book ''The Drama in the Pacific'', in which he wrote, &quot;having visited practically every island … I am convinced that nothing has been done to convert any place into a naval base&quot;.{{sfn|Peattie|1992|page=246}} In his 1998 book ''Nan'yo: the Rise and Fall of the Japanese in Micronesia, 1885–1945'', [[Mark Peattie]] stated that while it is easy to accuse Bodley and the other writers of naivety, the militarisation of the area was complex and occurred in several stages. Bodley was a passenger aboard the ship ''Shizuoka Maru'' when it was wrecked on a reef north of [[Yap]] in April 1933. The vessel was lost, though there were no injuries.{{sfn|Peattie|1992|pages=333–334}} Bodley was offered a job teaching English at [[Keio University]], and did so for nine months; he wrote about the experience in his 1933 book ''A Japanese Omelette''.&lt;ref name=keio /&gt;  Bodley and Keio university Professor Eishiro Hori provided voluminous notes in the 1934 Japanese textbook version of ''Round the Red Lamp'' by [[Arthur Conan Doyle]],&lt;ref name=keio/&gt; and in 1935 Bodley published a biography of [[Tōgō Heihachirō]].&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt;

== Later life ==
In 1935 Bodley moved to the United States to work as a [[screenwriter]],&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt; leaving Japan aboard the [[Chichibu Maru]].&lt;ref name=keio/&gt; In October 1936 Bodley was hired by [[Charlie Chaplin]]&lt;ref name=fitch&gt;{{cite news |date=26 September 1936 |title=News and Comment of Stage and Screen |newspaper=[[Fitchburg Sentinel]] |page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; to adapt the D.L. Murray novel ''Regency'' into a feature film. It was the first time Chaplin had hired someone to write a script; he had previously written his own scripts.&lt;ref name=fitch /&gt; Bodley had a rough draft ready by January 1937,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Graham |first=Shiela |date=26 January 1937 |title=Nothing to Harlow, Taylor Romancing |url=https://www.newspapers.com/newspage/37818074/ |newspaper=[[Lincoln Evening Journal]]}} {{subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt; and completed his work in March, though in late May that year Chaplin abandoned the script,{{sfn|Flom|1997|page=118}} in favour of another project he was working on.{{sfn|Robinson|1992|pages=482–483}} Bodley also worked on the script for the 1938 film ''[[A Yank at Oxford]]''.&lt;ref name=quiet&gt;{{cite news |last=McCollough |first=Trudy |date=23 July 1944 |title=Writer Bodley Loves His Quietude |newspaper=[[Abilene Reporter-News]] |page=50 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Glancy|1999|page=220}} In the United States Bodley was known to his friends as &quot;Ronnie&quot; and was often referred to in the press as ''Bodley of Arabia''.&lt;ref name=keio/&gt;

When the Second World War commenced, Bodley immediately rejoined the King's Royal Rifle Corps and was given the rank of major,&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt; though according to his book ''The Gay Deserters'' he was regarded as too old for active service in the infantry.{{sfn|Bodley|1945}} He was instead sent to work for the [[Ministry of Information (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Information]] in Paris.&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt; He was in Paris when the [[Battle of France|German army invaded]] in 1940.&lt;ref name=arabia /&gt; According to his book ''The Soundless Sahara'' after Paris fell he went to work behind the German lines until he came under suspicion of the [[Gestapo]], then escaped across the [[Pyrenees]] on foot.{{sfn|Bodley|1968}} He returned to the United States via Portugal.&lt;ref name=arabia /&gt; Upon his return he became a US citizen and an advisor to the Arabic desk of the [[United States Office of War Information|US Office of War Information]],&lt;ref name=quiet /&gt; and focused on a career in writing and lecturing.&lt;ref name=keio/&gt; Bodley would go into complete isolation in order to write a book, spending about 10 weeks to complete his work.&lt;ref name=quiet/&gt; He wrote several of his books in [[York Harbor, Maine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Nickerson |first=Row. W |date=15 February 1948 |title=World Traveler, Author To Speak Tonight At Bowdoin College |newspaper=Portland Sunday Telegram |location=Portland, Maine |page=52}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bodley frequently gave lectures while travelling the United States,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=5 December 1948 |title=News of the Yorks |newspaper=Portland Sunday Telegram |location=Portland, Maine |page=38 }}&lt;/ref&gt; speaking in almost every state and referring to himself as &quot;Colonel&quot; or &quot;Major&quot;.&lt;ref name=keio /&gt; Having reached the mandatory age for retirement, he ceased to be a member of the British Army on 3 March 1943.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=35926|supp=y|startpage=1065 |date=2 March 1943|accessdate=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1944 Bodley published ''Wind in the Sahara''.{{sfn|Bailey|1963|page=326}} By 1949 the book was in its seventh edition and had been translated into eight different languages.&lt;ref name=nomad&gt;{{cite news |date=24 April 1949 |title=Nomad Contracts to Publish Book About Serenity |newspaper=[[Kingsport Times-News]] |page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1945 he wrote the satire novel ''The Gay Deserters'', which was inspired by his flight from the German army,{{sfn|Bodley|1945}} though it was not well received.&lt;ref name=keio/&gt; Robert Pick from the ''[[Saturday Review (U.S. magazine)|Saturday Review]]'' wrote &quot;it isn't even humorous at all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Pick |first=Robert |date=24 November 1945 |title='Tempest Tost' Guests of U.S.A.: The Gay Deserters by R. V. C. Bodley |url= |newspaper=[[Saturday Review (U.S. magazine)|Saturday Review]] |page=32}}&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote an essay entitled ''I Lived in the Garden of Allah'', which was featured in the 1948 book ''[[How to Stop Worrying and Start Living]]''.{{sfn|Carnegie|1981|page=280}} In 1953 he wrote ''The Warrior Saint'', a biography on [[Charles de Foucauld]]. John Cogley from ''[[The New York Times]]'' said Bodley had &quot;written a clean, poetic and frankly admiring account&quot; of Foucauld's life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9A01E1DF143FE03ABC4852DFB3668388649EDE |title=The Saint of the Sahara |last1=Cogley |first1=John |date=10 May 1953 |work=[[The New York Times]]}} {{subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1955 he wrote the partly-autobiographical&lt;ref name=nomad/&gt; [[self-help book]] ''In Search of Serenity''. Elsie Robinson from ''The Index-Journal''  and Phyllis  Battle from the ''Tipton Tribune'' gave favourable reviews, with Robinson calling it &quot;a must for every rasped spirit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Robinson |first=Elsie |date=21 June 1955 |title=Listen, World! |newspaper=The Index-Journal |location=Greenwood, South Carolina |page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Battalle |first=Phyllis |date=15 April 1955 |title=Assignment America |newspaper=Tipton Tribune |location=Tipton, Indiana |page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; His next and final book, ''The Soundless Sahara'', was published in 1968; according to the book's back cover he spent part of his years living in [[Massachusetts]], and the rest in either England or France.{{sfn|Bodley|1968}} He provided information for the book ''The Secret Lives of Lawrence of Arabia'', which was published by [[Thomas Nelson (publisher)|Thomas Nelson]] in 1969.{{sfn|Knightley|1969|page=vii}} He died on 26 May 1970 in a nursing home&lt;ref name=keio /&gt; in [[Bramley, Surrey]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=45238|startpage=13034|date=26 November 1970|accessdate=1 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Personal life ==
Bodley married Ruth Mary Elizabeth Stapleton-Bretherton on 30 April 1917&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=5 May 1917 |title=Marriages |url=http://archive.thetablet.co.uk/article/5th-may-1917/24/marriages |newspaper=[[The Tablet]] |page=24 |access-date=19 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; while on [[furlough]].&lt;ref name=quiet/&gt; They had one son, Mark Courtenay Bodley, born 22 May 1918. His wife filed for divorce on the grounds that Bodley was adulterous and drank excessively. He did not contest the petition and the divorce was finalised on 8 June 1926. In his 1931 memoir ''Indiscretions of a Young Man'', Bodley said the marriage was an &quot;unfortunate action&quot; which &quot;proved the folly of very young people ignoring the advice of their parents.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;keio&quot; /&gt; In 1927 he married Australian Beatrice Claire Lamb, who he met while travelling in North Africa. She filed for divorce around 1939. Bodley's son, who became a lieutenant in the [[Royal Armoured Corps]], was killed in [[Western Desert Campaign|action in Libya in 1942]]; ''Wind in the Sahara'' is dedicated to him. In November 1949 Bodley married American divorcee Harriet Moseley;&lt;ref name=keio /&gt; according to ''The Soundless Sahara'', published in 1968, they were still married.{{sfn|Bodley|1968}}  According to a biographical journal article on Bodley by William Snell from Keio University, there is very little information on his last years, but he believed that Bodley's marriage to Moseley ended in divorce no later than 1969.&lt;ref name=&quot;keio&quot; /&gt;

== Awards ==
Bodley was awarded the [[Military Cross]] in the 1916 [[King's Birthday Honours]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=29608|supp=yes|startpage=5570|endpage=5571|date=2 June 1916|accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was awarded the Croix de Chevalier of the [[Legion d'Honneur]] by the President of France in 1919,&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=31222|supp=yes|startpage=3279|endpage=3280|date=7 March 1919  |accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and appointed Officer of the [[Ordre de l'Etoile Noire]] in 1920,&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=31812|supp=yes|startpage=2868|date=5 March 1920  |accessdate=21 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Knight Officer of [[Order of the Crown (Romania)|The Order of the Crown]] by [[Ferdinand of Romania]] in 1920,&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=31812|supp=yes|startpage=2874|date=5 March 1920  |accessdate=13 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Order of Wen-Hu]] (4th Class) by the [[Republic of China (1912–49)|Republic of China]] in 1921.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=32268|supp=y|startpage=2388 |date=22 March 1921|accessdate=13 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Publications ==
Bodley published 18 books during his career:&lt;ref name=keio /&gt;
{{div col|cols=2}}
*''Algeria from Within'' (1927)
*''Yasmina: A Story of Algeria'' (1927)
*''Opal Fire'' (1928)
*''Indiscretions of a Young Man'' (1931)
*''The Lilac Troll'' (1932)
*''A Japanese Omelette'' (1933)
*''Indiscreet travels East (Java, China and Japan)'' (1934)
*''The Drama of the Pacific'' (1934)
*''Admiral Togo'' (1935)
*''Gertrude Bell'' (1940) with Lorna Hearst
*''Flight into Portugal'' (1941)
*''Wind in the Sahara'' (1944)
*''The Gay Deserters'' (1945)
*''The Messenger'' (1946)
*''The Quest'' (1947)
*''The Warrior Saint'' (1953)
*''In Search of Serenity'' (1955)
*''The Soundless Sahara'' (1968)
{{div col end}}

== References ==

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
*{{cite book |last1=Bailey |first1=Matilda |title=A World Expanding |last2=Leavell |first2=Ullin W. |year=1963 |publisher=American Book Company |url=https://books.google.com/books?ei=Da07TMWnG4zCcbLy1foO&amp;ct=result&amp;id=ql4NAQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=R.V.C.+Bodley+World+War+1&amp;q=R.V.C.+Bodley#search_anchor |oclc=21749342 |ref={{sfnRef|Bailey1963}}
}}
*{{cite book |last=Bodley |first=Ronald Victor Courtenay |title=The Gay Deserters |year=1945 |publisher=Creative Age Press |at=Dust jacket |oclc=2097448 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Bodley |first=Ronald Victor Courtenay |year=1968 |title=The Soundless Sahara |publisher=Robert Hale Limited |at=Back cover |isbn=978-0-7091-0066-9 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Carnegie |first=Dale |authorlink=Dale Carnegie|title=[[How to Stop Worrying and Start Living]] |year=1981 |publisher=Pocket Books |isbn= 978-0-671-44530-0 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Cranston |first=Ruth |authorlink=Ruth Cranston |title=World Faith |year=1949 |publisher=Ayer Co Pub |isbn=978-0-8369-0108-5 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Gjbde7MXbNgC&amp;pg=PA171 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Dutton |first=David |title=Paris 1918: The War Diary of the British Ambassador, the 17th Earl of Derby |year=2001 |publisher= Liverpool University Press |isbn=978-0-85323-517-0 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U5PcxzF-I_0C&amp;pg=PA164 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Flom |first=Eric. L |date=1 April 1997 |title=Chaplin in the Sound Era: An Analysis of the Seven Talkies |url=https://books.google.com.au/books?id=R9NuChpopoAC&amp;pg=PA118  |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company |isbn=978-0-7864-0325-7 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Glancy |first=Mark |date=October 1999 |title=When Hollywood Loved Britain: The Hollywood 'British' Film 1939–1945 |url=https://books.google.com.au/books?id=T_Yryky_eA4C&amp;pg=PA220 |publisher=Manchester University Press |isbn=978-0-7190-4852-4 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1 =Knightley |first1 =Phillip |authorlink1=Phillip Knightley |last2 =Simpson |first2 =Colin |title = The Secret Lives of Lawrence of Arabia |year = 1969 |publisher=Thomas Nelson &amp; Sons |isbn= 978-0-586-03433-0 |ref={{sfnRef|Knightley1969}}
}}
*{{cite book |last=McDonald |first=John W |title=Walt Whitman, Philosopher Poet: Leaves of Grass by Indirection |year=2007 |publisher= McFarland and Company |isbn=978-0-7864-2388-0 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=N_rToyP77-MC&amp;pg=PA33 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Peattie |first=Mark R. |authorlink=Mark Peattie |title=Nan'Yo: The Rise and Fall of the Japanese in Micronesia, 1885–1945 |year=1992 |publisher=University of Hawaii Press |isbn=978-0-8248-1480-9  |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DHxdSkoo4AMC&amp;pg=PA338 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Robinson |first=David |authorlink=David Robinson (film critic) |date=1992 |title=[[Chaplin: His Life and Art]] |publisher=[[Grafton (publisher)|Grafton]] |isbn=978-0-07053-182-6 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Speake |first=Jennifer |title=Literature of Travel and Exploration: An Encyclopedia Volume 2 G to P|year=2003 |publisher=Fitzroy Dearborn Publishers |isbn=978-1-57958-424-5  |ref=harv}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bodley, Ronald}}
[[Category:1892 births]]
[[Category:1970 deaths]]
[[Category:British Army personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:British Army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Graduates of the Royal Military College, Sandhurst]]
[[Category:King's Royal Rifle Corps officers]]
[[Category:Officers of the Order of the Crown (Romania)]]
[[Category:People educated at Eton College]]
[[Category:People from Paris]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Wen-Hu]]</text>
      <sha1>819resg8mdt7qqmbm7ki7xiw7s73o2a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
