<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rivadavia-class battleship</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27568728</id>
    <revision>
      <id>731868679</id>
      <parentid>731867721</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-28T01:17:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The ed17</username>
        <id>1100608</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Service histories */ exact month/year</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45619">{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image = [[File:Rivadavia Battleship LOC 14781u.jpg|400px]]
| Ship caption = ''Rivadavia'' c. 1914–15, possibly on a [[sea trial|speed trial]].
}}{{Collapsed infobox section begin|Specifications}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
| Builders =* [[Fore River Shipyard|Fore River Shipbuilding Company]] (''Rivadavia'')
* [[New York Shipbuilding|New York Shipbuilding Corporation]] (''Moreno'')
  
| Operators = {{Navy|Argentina}}
| Class before = {{sclass-|Independencia|battleship|4}}
| Class after = None
| Subclasses = 
| Cost
  {{plainlist |
* [[United States dollar|$]]12,000,000&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1915-04-27/ed-1/seq-3/ Argentine Pride Outweighs $6,000,000 Profit Greece Offers for Moreno],&quot; ''New-York Tribune'', 27 April 1913.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[pounds sterling|£]]2,214,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Burzaco&quot;&gt;Burzaco and Ortíz, ''Acorazados y Cruceros'', 94.&lt;/ref&gt;
  }}
| Built range = 1910–15
| In commission range = 1914–56
| Total ships completed = 2
| Total ships preserved = 0
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = 1915
| Ship type = [[Dreadnought]] [[battleship]]
| Ship displacement =* {{convert|27500|LT|t}} [[standard displacement|standard]],
* {{convert|30100|LT|t}} [[full-load displacement|full load]]
  
| Ship length =* {{convert|594|ft|9|in|m|abbr=on}} [[length overall|oa]],
* {{convert|585|ft|m|abbr=on}} [[length between perpendiculars|pp]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot;&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 401.&lt;/ref&gt;
  
| Ship beam = {{convert|98|ft|4.5|in|m|abbr=on}}
| Ship draft = {{convert|27|ft|8.5|in|m|abbr=on}}
| Ship propulsion =* 3-shaft, [[John Brown &amp; Company|Curtis]] geared [[steam turbine|turbines]],
* 18 [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] [[boiler]]s;
* 40,000&amp;nbsp;[[shaft horsepower]]
  
| Ship speed = {{convert|22.5|kn|mph km/h}}
| Ship range =* {{convert|7000|nmi|mi km}} at {{convert|15|kn|mph km/h}}
* {{convert|11000|nmi|mi km}} at {{convert|11|kn|mph km/h}}
  
| Ship complement = 
| Ship sensors = 
| Ship EW = 
| Ship armament =* 12 × [[12&quot;/50 caliber gun (Argentina)|12 inch (305 mm)/50]] guns
* 12 × 6 inch (152 mm)/50 guns
* 16 × 4 inch (102 mm) guns
* 2 × 21&amp;nbsp;inch (533&amp;nbsp;mm) [[torpedo tube]]s
  
| Ship armor =* [[Belt armor|Belt]]:&amp;nbsp;12–10&amp;nbsp;inches (300–250&amp;nbsp;mm)
* Turrets:&amp;nbsp;12&amp;nbsp;inches (305&amp;nbsp;mm)
* Casemates: 9&lt;sup&gt;1/3&lt;/sup&gt;–6&lt;sup&gt;1/5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;inches (238–159&amp;nbsp;mm)
* Conning tower: 12&amp;nbsp;inches (300&amp;nbsp;mm)
  
| Ship aircraft = 
| Ship aircraft facilities = 
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}{{Collapsed infobox section end}}
The '''''Rivadavia'' class''' consisted of two [[battleship]]s designed by the American [[Fore River Shipyard|Fore River Shipbuilding Company]] for the [[Argentine Navy]]. Named {{ship|ARA|Rivadavia||2}} and {{ship|ARA|Moreno||2}} after important figures in Argentine history, they were Argentina's entry in the [[South American dreadnought race]] and a counter to Brazil's two {{sclass-|Minas Geraes|battleship}}s.

In 1904, Brazil scrapped a previous naval building program in favor of an order that included three warships of the new &quot;[[dreadnought]]&quot; type, despite signs that such an action would spark a [[South American dreadnought race|South American naval arms race]].{{efn-ua|Three were ordered, but only two were built right away. The third's [[keel]] was laid down and ripped up several times before becoming ''Rio de Janeiro'', later the British {{HMS|Agincourt|1913|6}}.&lt;ref&gt;Topliss, &quot;The Brazilian Dreadnoughts,&quot; 246–249, 284.&lt;/ref&gt;}} To counter this acquisition by a major rival, Argentina began [[call for bids|seeking bids]] for at least two dreadnoughts in 1908. Over the next two years, shipbuilders from five countries vied for the contracts, complemented by efforts from their respective governments. Argentina was able to play this hyper-competitive environment to its own advantage by rejecting all of the initial proposals and calling for new ones that required the best aspects of each. They then repeated this process, despite complaints from shipbuilders that their trade secrets were being given away. The contracts were awarded to the lowest bidder, Fore River, in early 1910. This move shocked the European bidders, but could partly be explained by the American [[Trust (business)|steel trust's]] ability to produce steel at a lower cost than any other country.

With increasing tensions in Europe that would eventually lead to the [[World War I|First World War]], newspapers speculated that the Argentine dreadnoughts would be sold to another country. Under diplomatic pressure, Argentina kept the ships. Throughout their careers, ''Rivadavia'' and ''Moreno'' were based in [[Puerto Belgrano]] and served principally as [[training ship]]s and diplomatic envoys. They were modernized in the United States in 1924 and 1925 and were inactive for much of the [[World War II|Second World War]] due to Argentina's neutrality. [[wikt:stricken|Struck]] from the navy lists on 1 February 1957, ''Rivadavia'' was [[ship breaking|scrapped]] in Italy beginning in 1959. ''Moreno'' was struck on 1 October 1956 and was towed to Japan in 1957 for scrapping in what was then the world's longest tow (96 days).

== Background ==
{{main article|Argentine–Chilean naval arms race}}
The ''raison d'être'' for the ''Rivadavia'' class can be traced back to Argentine–Chilean territorial disputes over the boundary of [[Patagonia]] and control of the [[Beagle Channel]] going back to the 1840s. It nearly led to war in 1878 and kindled a naval arms race from 1887 to 1902 which was only settled via British mediation. As part of [[Treaty of Arbitration Between Chile and Argentina of 1902|the three pacts]] which ended the dispute, restrictions were placed on the navies of both countries. The British [[Royal Navy]] bought two {{sclass-|Swiftsure|battleship|0}} [[pre-dreadnought]] battleships that were being built for Chile, and Argentina sold its two [[Kasuga-class cruiser|''Rivadavia''-class]] [[armored cruiser]]s under construction in Italy to Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Naval History'', 45–52; Garrett, &quot;Beagle Channel Dispute,&quot; 86–88.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, beginning in the late 1880s, Brazil's navy fell into obsolescence after an [[Decline and fall of Pedro II of Brazil#Fall|1889 revolution]], which deposed [[Politics of the Empire of Brazil|Emperor]] [[Dom (title)|Dom]] [[Pedro II of Brazil|Pedro II]], and a [[Revolta da Armada|1893 civil war]].&lt;ref&gt;Topliss, &quot;The Brazilian Dreadnoughts,&quot; 240; Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 32.&lt;/ref&gt; By the turn of the 20th century it was lagging behind the Chilean and Argentine navies in quality and total tonnage,{{efn-ua|Chile's naval tonnage was {{convert|36896|LT|t}}, Argentina's {{convert|34425|LT|t}}, and Brazil's {{convert|27661|LT|t}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore32&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 32.&lt;/ref&gt;}} despite Brazil having nearly three times the population of Argentina and almost five times the population of Chile.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, &quot;Brazil,&quot; 403; Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Brazilian battleship Minas Geraes firing a broadside.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.2|The gun trials of the Brazilian [[dreadnought]] {{ship|Brazilian battleship|Minas Geraes||2}}, the ship that began the dreadnought race. Here, all guns capable of training to the port side were fired, forming what was at that time the heaviest [[broadside]] ever fired off a warship.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Brazilian Battleship 'Minas Geraes',&quot; ''Scientific American'', 241.&lt;/ref&gt; ]]
By 1904, however, Brazil began to seriously consider upgrading its navy to compete with Argentina and Chile.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore32&quot; /&gt; [[Coffee production in Brazil#History|Soaring demand]] for coffee and [[rubber boom|rubber]] brought the Brazilian economy an influx of revenue,&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare'', 216; Scheina, &quot;Brazil,&quot; 403.&lt;/ref&gt; which paid for a US$31.25&amp;nbsp;million{{efn-ua|Argentina uses &quot;$&quot; to represent their [[Argentine peso|peso]] and &quot;US$&quot; or similar for the U.S. dollar; however, &quot;$&quot; generally means &quot;dollar&quot; in English sources and in this article.}} naval repair scheme, a substantial amount for the time period. The bill authorized 28 ships, including three battleships and three armored cruisers.&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, ''Naval Warfare'', 216&lt;/ref&gt; It was not possible to [[keel laying|lay down]] the battleships until 1906, the same year the trend-setting {{HMS|Dreadnought|1906|6}} was constructed. This ship prompted the Brazilians to cancel their battleship plans in favor of two {{sclass-|Minas Geraes|battleship|0}} [[dreadnought]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore32&quot; /&gt; The ordering of these powerful ships—designed to carry the heaviest armament in the world at the time—shocked Argentina and Chile. Historian Robert Scheina comments that the dreadnoughts alone &quot;outclassed the entire [elderly] Argentinian fleet.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 400; &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9E0CE4D9123EE233A2575AC0A96E9C946997D6CF Germany may buy English warships],&quot; ''[[The New York Times]]'', 1 August 1908, C8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Debates raged in Argentina over the wisdom of acquiring dreadnoughts to counter Brazil's. The [[National Autonomist Party]] cabinet was in favor, despite a probable cost of nearly $10&amp;nbsp;million, but a specific plan for two {{convert|14000|LT|t|0|adj=on}} battleships and ten destroyers was not popular with the public. Alarmed, the American ambassador to Brazil sent a [[cablegram]] to his [[United States Department of State|Department of State]], warning them of the destabilizing effects that would occur if the situation devolved into a full naval arms race.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 32–33.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite American entreaties to preclude the naval arms race, Brazil continued development on the ships. This, combined with renewed border disputes, particularly in the [[Río de la Plata|River Plate]] (''Río de la Plata'', literally &quot;Silver River&quot;) area, spurred Argentina to move forward with plans for their own battleships. Inflamed by newspaper editors, the public was now fully supportive of a naval building program. While an early plan called for $35&amp;nbsp;million to be invested—$7&amp;nbsp;million from foreign loans—a $55&amp;nbsp;million plan was adopted in August 1908. Hoping to end the arms race, Argentina made an offer to purchase one of the two Brazilian ships, but the refusal prompted the dispatch of an Argentine naval commission to Europe to acquire dreadnoughts.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bidding ==
[[File:Argentine Rivadavia Class Battleship 1912.jpg|thumb|right|''Rivadavia'' under construction, 2 December 1912.]]
Proposals from shipbuilders for two dreadnoughts (along with a possible third, to match Brazil should a third ship be ordered) and twelve destroyers were solicited in 1908 by [[Call for bids|open tender]].&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 401; Scheina, ''Latin America'', 82; Whitley, ''Battleships'', 18.&lt;/ref&gt; In order to ensure that the designs reflected the most modern practices, the requirements were intentionally vague.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 401; Scheina, ''Latin America'', 83.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fifteen shipyards from the United States, Great Britain, Germany, France, and Italy began bidding on the battleships.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 401; Scheina, ''Latin America'', 83; Whitley, ''Battleships'', 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Diplomatic pressure to give the contracts was brought to bear from all these countries, especially the first three.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore34&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 34.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn-ua|Although the United States had done little to promote American armament interests in Latin America under President [[Theodore Roosevelt]], this was drastically reversed after the election of [[William Howard Taft]] in 1912, most notably demonstrated with the creation of the [[Division of Latin American Affairs]] and the appointment of [[Charles H. Sherrill (ambassador)|Charles H. Sherrill]] to be the [[United States Ambassador to Argentina|American minister to Argentina]]. As part of this, American bankers were persuaded to offer a $10&amp;nbsp;million loan to Argentina to help pay for the dreadnoughts should they be built in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore34&quot; /&gt; From a global perspective, this was a concentrated effort to obtain naval contracts from countries as varied as Spain, Russia, Greece, Turkey, and China, as well as Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;American Navy,&quot; 875–876.&lt;/ref&gt;}} Even with this assistance, industry leaders in the United States believed that they had no chance in the bidding without active cooperation from their government, as Europe was the traditional arms supplier to Argentina (and to all of South America).&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 35–36.&lt;/ref&gt; Even when this was given, including the removal of import tariffs on [[hides]] from Argentina, promises for additional concessions if American shipbuilders were selected,&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore36&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 36.&lt;/ref&gt; and an offer to include the most technologically advanced [[fire-control system]] and [[torpedo tube]]s available on the Argentine battleships, the United States was widely viewed as a non-contender.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scheina83&quot;&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 83.&lt;/ref&gt; Historian [[Seward W. Livermore]] remarked that &quot;opposition to the United States was formidable. The naval commission was pro-British; the vice-president of the republic, [[Roque Sáenz Peña]], favored Italy, where he had been the Argentine envoy for many years; and the minister of war wanted the contracts to go to Germany, so as to standardize the military and naval equipment of the country.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore36&quot;/&gt;

The president of the [[Northrop Grumman Shipbuilding Newport News|Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Company]] believed that the United States would not receive contracts due to what he saw as a large amount of European meddling in Argentina:

{{quote|The political influence of foreign powers is being exerted in a very forceful manner to turn the business to English and Continental firms; the King of Italy, the German Emperor, and the force of English diplomacy are being made use of; and American firms will have very little consideration, I fear, unless our government will exert some very powerful influence in favor of this country.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 35.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The United States, however, found an ally in Buenos Aires' main daily newspaper, ''[[La Prensa (Buenos Aires)|La Prensa]]''. The owner, editor, and naval editor were all in favor of acquiring American-designed dreadnoughts. In addition, the paper found evidence of British wrongdoing in a related naval contract. Under public pressure, the naval commission was forced to reconsider its original list, which had placed Italy first and Britain second. It now featured the United States first, Britain second, and Italy last.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore36&quot; /&gt;

In a surprise move, the Argentine naval commission then threw out all of the opening tenders and called for another round of bidding; they simultaneously updated the specifications to include what were judged to be the best aspects of all the plans.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 83; Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 37.&lt;/ref&gt; The competitors were given three weeks to come up with new designs and cost estimates. After diplomatic protests, this was modified slightly; the original bids were kept, but alterations to attempt to conform to the new desired characteristics were allowed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore37&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 37.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn-ua|While both Scheina and Livermore explicitly state that the commission threw out all the bids twice,&lt;ref name=&quot;Scheina83&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore39&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 39.&lt;/ref&gt; neither makes it clear when this occurred. Livermore only goes into detail about one of these occasions, of which it is not clear if it is the second or third round.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore37&quot; /&gt; Hough states that Armstrong was forced to draw up four designs, which could mean that the bid was thrown out as many as three times.&lt;ref&gt;Hough, ''Big Battleship'', 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:ARA Rivadavia launch.jpg|thumb|left||upright=1.2|''Rivadavia''{{'}}s launch, 16 August 1911.]]
The commission found that the Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Company bid was lowest on one battleship, and the [[Fore River Shipyard|Fore River Shipbuilding Company]] was lowest on the other. Despite a British attempt to allow the [[Armstrong Whitworth]]-[[Vickers Limited|Vickers]] team to lower their price by $570,000, prompt American diplomacy granting various assurances regarding recent events between the United States and Brazil, the upcoming 1910 [[Pan-American Conference]], and a guarantee of American participation in the Argentine centennial celebrations secured the battleship contracts for Fore River on 21 January 1910.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore38&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 38.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn-ua|There were five specific assurances (quoted from Livermore):&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore38&quot;/&gt;
* A denial that the United States contemplated any understanding with Brazil in regard to joint or simultaneous action in reference to Latin-American affairs.
* A statement from Secretary Knox giving that Senor Portela, the Argentine minister, credit for the suggestion of British mediation in the Alsop case—or at least denying that Senor Nabuco, the Brazilian ambassador, was the first to suggest it.
* A specific denial for the benefit of Senor de la Plaza, the foreign minister, that the state department had ever acknowledged the claim of the Brazilian foreign office for credit in the settlement of the Alsop case.
* A substantial congressional appropriation for the Pan-American conference in Buenos Aires in July 1910.
* The dispatch of a squadron of American warships to the Argentine Centennial Celebration in May 1910.
* The United States to discourage Brazil and Uruguay from raising the question of jurisdiction of the waters of the Rio de la Plata.}} The maximum price Fore River tendered, $10.7&amp;nbsp;million, underbid the British by more than $973,000, but their ship's [[displacement (ship)|displacement]] was {{convert|2000|LT|t|-2}} smaller, the [[belt armor]] was {{convert|2|in|mm}} thinner, and the top speed was slightly lower.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alger595&quot;&gt;Alger, &quot;Professional Notes,&quot; 595.&lt;/ref&gt; Orders for the twelve destroyers were divided among Britain, France, and Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 38; &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9803E3D81730E233A25750C2A9679C946196D6CF America to Build Argentine Ships],&quot; ''The New York Times'', 23 January 1910, C4.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Rivadavia'' was built by Fore River at its shipyard in Massachusetts, but they were contractually obligated to [[subcontractor|subcontract]] the second ship to a different shipyard in the hope that both would be completed faster, so ''Moreno'' was constructed by the [[New York Shipbuilding|New York Shipbuilding Corporation]] of Camden, New Jersey.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 83; Sarcone and Rines, ''A History of Shipbuilding''.&lt;/ref&gt; The steel for the ships was largely supplied by the [[Bethlehem Steel Company]] of Pennsylvania,&lt;ref name=&quot;Evening Post&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://paperspast.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/paperspast?a=d&amp;d=EP19100323.2.42 Argentine Navy; Dreadnought Orders],&quot; [[The Evening Post (New Zealand)|''Evening Post'']], 23 March 1910, 4.&lt;/ref&gt; which, due to their ability to produce steel at a lower price than other nations, was an integral cost-saving measure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore39&quot; /&gt; The Secretary of the Argentine Naval Commission, the body which chose the final design, said the reason the American tender was lower than that of the English was that &quot;steel for construction work and armor-plating is a great deal cheaper in the United States than in England. Wages are higher there, but the contractors ... are able to obtain it more cheaply owing to the manipulations of the Steel Trust.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alger595&quot; /&gt;{{efn-ua|The disparity in cost per ton was quite large (units are [[pounds sterling]]): American, 78.3; Italian, 85.9; British, 86.3; French, 87.4; and German, 88.2.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 39; Alger, &quot;Professional Notes,&quot; 595.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A third dreadnought, provided for in the contract, was strongly supported by Argentina and by U.S. diplomats during 1910, while the ''Minas Geraes'' class was still under construction. ''La Prensa'' and one of its rivals, ''[[La Nación|La Argentina]]'', heavily advocated a third ship; the latter even started a petition to raise money for a new battleship. An American diplomat wrote back to the United States that &quot;this newspaper rivalry promises the early conclusion of a movement which means a third battleship whether by public subscription or by Government funds.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore44&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 44.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Brazil's 21–26 November [[Revolt of the Lash]]—in which the three most powerful ships in the fleet (the battleships {{Ship|Brazilian battleship|Minas Geraes||2}}, {{Ship|Brazilian battleship|São Paulo||2}}, and the cruiser {{Ship|Brazilian cruiser|Bahia||2}}) and several smaller warships violently rebelled—crushed the previous sentiment for a new battleship.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 104–107; Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 44.&lt;/ref&gt; About two years later in October 1912, a third dreadnought was authorized by Argentina in case Brazil's [[HMS Agincourt (1913)|''Rio de Janeiro'']] was completed and delivered. The ship was never named or built, as ''Rio de Janeiro'' was sold to the [[Ottoman Empire]] due to monetary issues, and a later planned Brazilian ship ({{Ship|Brazilian battleship|Riachuelo||2}}) was canceled due to the beginning of the [[World War I|First World War]].&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 321; Scheina, &quot;Argentina&quot; and &quot;Brazil,&quot; 402, 405.&lt;/ref&gt;

== International reaction ==
The choice of Fore River came as a complete surprise to the European bidders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scheina83&quot; /&gt; Britain's reaction in particular was scathing: Sir [[John H. Biles]], a professor and well-known [[naval architect]], decried the bidding process as &quot;unethical&quot;:

{{quote|... it may be presumed that everything ... good in the first proposals [was] seized upon by the Argentine authorities and asked for in the new design. This second request went not only to British builders but to all the builders of the world, and in this way it is exceedingly probable that a serious leakage of ideas and practice of our ships was disseminated through the world by the Argentine government.... The third inquiry that was issued showed to all the builders of the world what has been eliminated or modified in the second inquiry; and so the process of leakage went merrily on, and with it that of the education of foreign builders and the Argentine government.&lt;ref&gt;JH Biles, &quot;The Argentine Dreadnoughts,&quot; ''Times'' (London), 25 February 1910, 4c.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

Various British newspapers also cried foul. The ''[[Evening Standard]]'' believed that as &quot;Argentina's greatest creditor and greatest client&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore39&quot;/&gt; Britain ought to have been awarded the two ships. ''[[The Times]]'' took a different track, accusing American shipbuilders of slashing prices to an obscene degree,{{efn-ua|Ironically, the ''[[New York Herald]]'' had previously stated on 17 January 1909 that it believed the British would eventually win the Argentine contracts by slashing prices.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 354.&lt;/ref&gt;}} and accusing the government of exerting undue diplomatic pressure to obtain the contracts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore39&quot; /&gt;

[[File:ARA Rivadavia speed trials 2.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|''Rivadavia'' on its speed trials]]
New Zealand's ''[[The Evening Post (New Zealand)|Evening Post]]'' noted that the United States had previously built major warships for other countries, including Russia, and Britain's ally Japan, and commented, &quot;The severity of the blow to England rests in ... the amount of English capital in [Argentina]&quot;, possibly echoing the ''Evening Standard''{{'}}s argument. They referred to a &quot;startling&quot; fact printed by the ''[[Daily Mail]]'': the steel used for the armor of the American design was obtained for a much lower price. With Bethlehem's ability to produce it at £8 less per ton than British foundries, a cost savings of more than 10% in steel over the British ship could be realized.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evening Post&quot; /&gt;

Germany asserted that the United States was given the opportunity to view the other nations' tenders and lower their price accordingly. Germany also alleged that the United States had secured the deal by pledging to come to Argentina's defense should they become embroiled in a military conflict.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9A00E0DC1E31E233A25755C2A9679D946096D6CF Accuse America of Unfair Competition],&quot; ''The New York Times'', 26 November 1911, C4.&lt;/ref&gt;

''The New York Times'' noted that with Argentina's and Brazil's dreadnought orders, countries in North and South America were building the five biggest [[capital ships]] in the world (Brazil's ''Rio de Janeiro'', Argentina's ''Rivadavia'' and ''Moreno'', and the United States' {{USS|New York|BB-34|2}} and {{USS|Texas|BB-35|2}}) in addition to seven of the ten largest (including the United States' {{USS|Wyoming|BB-32|2}} and {{USS|Arkansas|BB-33|2}}).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9D02E1DD1339E433A25752C1A9649D946196D6CF Our Navy Close to England's Now],&quot; ''The New York Times'', 11 December 1910, 8.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after ''Rivadavia'' had completed its trials, the U.S. Navy's [[Board of Inspection and Survey]] remarked that the ship &quot;handle[d] remarkably well ... with comparatively minor modifications the vessel would practically meet the requirements of our own vessels.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways402&quot;&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 402.&lt;/ref&gt; The Board of Inspection was less pleased with the wing turrets, stating that &quot;while theoretically the ''Rivadavia'' has an ahead and astern fire of six guns, this is not so in reality, as it is almost certain that the blast from the waist turrets would dish in the smokepipes and damage the uptakes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways402&quot; /&gt;

== Possible sale ==
After Brazil sold ''Rio de Janeiro'' to the Ottoman Empire, Argentina began to actively seek a buyer for their two ships so the profits could be invested in education. In the tension that preceded the First World War, there were many suitors. The United States, however, abhorred the idea of their latest technological advances falling into the hands of a possible future combat opponent. While the contract allowed the United States Navy an option to acquire the ships if a deal was reached with a third nation, the Navy did not want the ships; with the rapid advances in dreadnought technology, such as the [[all or nothing (armor)|&quot;all or nothing&quot; armor arrangement]], even new ships like ''Rivadavia'' and ''Moreno'' were seen as outmoded.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 45–46.&lt;/ref&gt;

Three bills directing that the battleships be sold were introduced into the [[Argentine National Congress]] in the summer of 1914, but all were defeated. Still, soon after the beginning of the First World War, the German ambassador to Argentina alleged to the U.S. State Department that Britain's Royal Navy was going to take over the ships as soon as the ships reached the River Plate, and the British put diplomatic pressure on the United States to try to ensure the ships were not sold to any other country (as this new country could in turn sell them to Germany).{{efn-ua|This was possibly referencing an earlier (March 1914) incident where French bankers—given direction by Russia—offered Argentina twice the amount they paid for the ''Rivadavia''-class ships so that the ships could be turned over to Greece.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livermore46&quot;&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 47.&lt;/ref&gt; Scheina mentions a 1913 Russian attempt to purchase both Argentine and both Chilean battleships, but gives no specifics.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 355.&lt;/ref&gt;}} Italy, the Ottomans, and Greece were all reportedly interested in buying both ships, the latter as a counter to the Ottoman purchase of ''Rio de Janeiro''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://paperspast.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/paperspast?a=d&amp;d=PBH19140103.2.48 Turkey and Greece; Purpose of Dreadnoughts],&quot; ''Poverty Bay Herald'', 2 January 1914, 3.&lt;/ref&gt; The United States, worried that its neutrality would not be respected and its technology would be released for study to a foreign competitor, put diplomatic pressure on Argentina to keep the ships, which it eventually did.&lt;ref&gt;Livermore, &quot;Battleship Diplomacy,&quot; 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Design influences ==
The ''Rivadavia'' design was very similar to a 1906 proposal from Fore River for an American dreadnought class.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, ''U.S. Battleships'', 69.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn-ua|The plan from the [[Bureau of Construction and Repair]] was selected over that of Fore River and was used for the two {{sclass-|Delaware|battleship|5}}s, {{USS|Delaware|BB-28|2}} and {{USS|North Dakota|BB-29|2}}.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, ''U.S. Battleships'', 68.&lt;/ref&gt;}} This ship would have mounted a [[main battery]] of fourteen {{convert|12|in|mm|adj=on}} guns in dual turrets (two [[Superfire|superfiring]] fore, two [[wing turret|wing]], and three non-superfiring aft), a secondary battery of twenty 4-inch (102&amp;nbsp;mm) guns and four [[torpedo tube]]s on a hull of {{convert|22000|LT|t|-3|lk=in}} that would be capable of {{convert|21|kn|mph km/h}}.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, ''U.S. Battleships'', 68–69.&lt;/ref&gt; Foreign practices also bore a large influence on the design; most were acquired through the unique design process of rejecting multiple bids and calling for the best aspects of each.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 401; Scheina, Latin America, 83.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the superfiring arrangement of the main battery was an American innovation, while the wing turrets were similar to British designs of the time. The secondary battery of 6-inch (152&amp;nbsp;mm) guns and the three-shaft system were influenced by German design practices, while the engine and boiler layout was reminiscent of the Italian battleship {{Ship|Italian battleship|Dante Alighieri||2}}.&lt;ref&gt;Whitley, ''Battleships'', 19–20.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Service histories ==
[[File:Moreno Battleship LOC 17604.jpg|thumb|right||upright=1.2|''Moreno'' in [[drydock]], October 1914.]]
{{ship|ARA|Rivadavia||2}} was named after [[Bernardino Rivadavia]], the first president of [[Argentina]], and was built by [[Fore River Shipyard]]. The ship was [[keel laying|laid down]] on 25 May 1910, [[ship naming and launching|launched]] on 26 August 1911, and completed in December 1914. {{Ship|ARA|Moreno||2}} was named after [[Mariano Moreno]], a member of the [[Primera Junta|first Argentine government]]; laid down on 10 July 1910 by [[New York Shipbuilding Corporation]], it was launched on 23 September 1911 and completed in February 1915.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9402E4DB163CE633A25757C2A96F9C946096D6CF Moreno Launched For Argentine Navy],&quot; ''The New York Times'', 24 September 1911, 12.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley21&quot;&gt;Whitley, ''Battleships'', 21.&lt;/ref&gt; Both ships had engine trouble soon after completion: ''Rivadavia''{{'}}s completion was delayed due to a damaged turbine,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9506E2D9143EE033A25754C2A96E9C946596D6CF The Rivadavia Delayed],&quot; ''The New York Times'', 24 August 1914, 7.&lt;/ref&gt; while ''Moreno'' had an entire turbine fail while on its trials.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9B05E4DF1738E633A25750C0A9679D946596D6CF New Battleship Disabled],&quot; ''The New York Times'', 3 November 1914, 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ships finally arrived in Argentina in February and May 1915, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley21&quot; /&gt; In the early 1920s, both ships spent time in the reserve fleet due to an [[Depression (economics)|economic depression]],&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 86.&lt;/ref&gt; but enough money was available by 1924 to have the dreadnoughts modernized in the United States. Both refits included a conversion from coal to fuel oil, a new fire-control system,&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley21&quot; /&gt; and other minor improvements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways402405&quot;&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina&quot; and &quot;Brazil,&quot; 402, 405.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1930s they participated in training cruises and diplomatic trips, including:
*''Moreno''{{'}}s 1933 visit to Brazil with Argentine president [[Agustín Pedro Justo]] aboard;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley21-22&quot;&gt;Whitley, ''Battleships'', 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt;
*A second visit in 1934 to mark the centennial of Brazilian independence;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley21-22&quot;/&gt;
*''Rivadavia''{{'}}s and ''Moreno''{{'}}s 1937 voyage to Europe, where they visited [[Brest, France|Brest]] (France), [[Wilhelmshaven]], [[Bremen]], and [[Hamburg]] (Germany);&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley21-22&quot;/&gt;
*''Moreno''{{'}}s additional participation on the same voyage in the British [[Fleet review (Commonwealth realms)|Spithead Naval Review]], where the ''New York Times''{{'}} [[Hanson Baldwin]] described it as a &quot;a strange vestigial sea monster in this company of more modern fighting ships&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Hanson Baldwin, &quot;158 Warships Boom Salute to George in Spithead Review,&quot; ''New York Times'', 21 May 1937, 1, 9.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Rivadavia''{{'}}s and ''Moreno''{{'}}s 1939 training cruise to Brazil with naval cadets embarked; with the beginning of the Second World War in September, destroyers had to be sent from Argentina to escort them home.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitley21-22&quot;/&gt;

During the war, both ships were mainly inactive due to Argentine neutrality. ''Rivadavia'' undertook a last diplomatic cruise to Trinidad, Venezuela, and Colombia in 1946, but both ships were immobile by 1948. ''Moreno'' was stricken from the naval register on 1 October 1956 and was brought to Japan in 1957 for [[ship breaking|scrapping]] in a then-world-record 96-day tow. ''Rivadavia'' was stricken on 1 February 1957 and scrapped in Italy beginning in 1959.&lt;ref&gt;Whitney, ''Battleships'', 21–22; &quot;96 Day Tow,&quot; ''The New York Times'', 18 August 1957, 61.&lt;/ref&gt; The money gained from selling the two dreadnoughts along with an older armored cruiser, {{Ship|ARA|Pueyrredón||2}}, was used to buy an [[aircraft carrier]] from the United Kingdom, [[HMS Warrior (R31)|''Independencia'']] (ex-''Warrior'').&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America'', 194.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Specifications ==
{{multiple image
&lt;!-- Essential parameters --&gt;
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| width     = 260

&lt;!-- Image 1 --&gt;
| image1    = Argentine battleship Rivadavia in 1948.jpg
| width1    = 
| alt1      = 
| caption1  =

&lt;!-- Image 2 --&gt;
| image2    = Argentine battleship Moreno in 1947.jpg
| width2    = 
| alt2      = 
| caption2  =

|footer     = The two battleships near the end of their lives: ''Rivadavia'' in 1948 (top), and ''Moreno'' in 1947 (bottom).
}}

The two ships of the ''Rivadavia'' class were {{convert|594|ft|9|in|m}} [[length overall|overall]] and {{convert|585|ft|m}} [[Length between perpendiculars|between perpendiculars]]. They had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|98|ft|4.5|in|m}}, a normal [[draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|27|ft|8.5|in|m}}, and [[displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|27500|LT|t|lk=in}} [[normal displacement|normally]] and {{convert|30100|LT|t}} [[full-load displacement|at full load]]. The ships were staffed by 130 officers and about 1000 enlisted men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot; /&gt;

For armament, the ''Rivadavia'' class was equipped with a [[main battery]] of twelve [[12&quot;/50 caliber gun (Argentina)|12-inch/50]] [[Caliber (artillery)|caliber]] guns, a secondary battery of twelve 6-inch (155&amp;nbsp;mm)/50 and twelve 4-inch (102&amp;nbsp;mm)/50 [[Quick-firing gun|QF]], and two 21-inch (533&amp;nbsp;mm) [[torpedo tube]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot; /&gt;

The 12&quot;/50 was a [[Bethlehem Steel Company|Bethlehem]] development. It was most likely based on the weapon used in the United States' {{sclass-|Wyoming|battleship|1}}, the [[12&quot;/50 caliber Mark 7 gun]]. The twelve guns were mounted in six dual turrets. Four turrets were [[superfire|superfiring]] fore and aft, while the other two were located ''[[en echelon]]'' in [[wing turret]]s. The latter weapons could, in theory, fire on a {{formatnum:180}}° range on their respective sides of the hull and {{formatnum:100}}° on the other, but in reality this was not possible, as the [[Muzzle flash#Problems caused by muzzle blast|blast damage]] from the weapons would damage the ship. A more reasonable estimate would be {{formatnum:90}}° on their sides.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, &quot;Argentina,&quot; 401; Tony DiGiulian, &quot;[http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNARG_12-50_Bethlehem.htm 12&quot;/50 (30.5 cm) Bethlehem],&quot; NavWeaps, accessed 11 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The 6-inch secondary armament was placed in [[casemate]]s, with six on either side of the ship. For protection, they were provided with 6&amp;nbsp;inches of armor. The 4-inch weaponry, intended for use against marauding [[destroyer]]s, was mounted unarmored in various places around the ship, including the main deck, [[Superstructure (ship)|superstructure]], and far up near the bow. As originally built, there were sixteen 4-inch guns, but four of those were replaced with four 3-inch AA guns and four [[Ordnance QF 3 pounder Vickers|3-pounders]] during the 1924-1926 modernization.&lt;ref&gt;Whitley, ''Battleships of World War II'', 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt; The torpedo tubes were located underneath the waterline and were loaded in a dedicated compartment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot; /&gt;

Full ammunition loads were 1,440 rounds for the 12-inch guns (120 per gun), 3,600 rounds for the 6-inch (300), 5,600 rounds for the 4-inch (350), and 16 torpedoes manufactured by [[Robert Whitehead|Whitehead]]. To assist the main battery with targeting during a battle, the two ships were equipped with two [[Barr &amp; Stroud]] [[rangefinder]]s that were located above the [[conning tower]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot; /&gt;

''Rivadavia'' and ''Moreno'' used [[John Brown &amp; Company|Brown–Curtis]] geared [[steam turbine]]s, powered by 18 [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] [[boiler]]s and connected to three [[propeller]]s. With a total output of about {{convert|40000|shp|lk=in}}, the ships were designed to travel at a maximum speed of {{convert|22.5|kn|lk=in}} and may have been capable of slightly more. At speeds of {{convert|11|to|15|kn}}, their endurance ranged from {{convert|11000|to|7000|nmi|lk=in}}, respectively. Their fuel was a [[coal]]–[[oil]] mix and the ships carried {{convert|3900|LT|t}} of the former and {{convert|590|LT|t}} of the latter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot; /&gt;

Typical of American-designed dreadnoughts at the time, the ''Rivadavia'' class included substantial armor protection. A {{convert|12|in|mm|adj=on}} [[belt armor|belt]] was fitted amidships, covering {{convert|5|ft|m}} above and {{convert|6|ft|m}} below the designed [[waterline]], gradually decreasing towards the bow and stern to {{convert|5|in|mm}} and {{convert|4|in|mm}}, respectively. The gun turrets received heavy armor, including {{convert|12|in|mm}} on the front, {{convert|9|in|mm}} on the sides, {{convert|9.5|in|mm}} on the back, and {{convert|4|in|mm}} on the top. Deck armor consisted of {{convert|.5|in|mm}} [[maraging steel|medium steel]] and {{convert|2|in|mm}} [[carbon steel|nickel steel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Conways&quot; /&gt;
{{clear}}
{{Gallery
| title = South American dreadnoughts &lt;br /&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 85%; font-weight: normal;&quot;&gt;From [[Brassey's Naval Annual|''The Naval Annual'']] (1915)&lt;/span&gt;
| width = 340
| height = 210
| lines = 8
| File:Minas Geraes-class battleships.jpg|The {{sclass-|Minas Geraes|battleship|4}} was designed, constructed, and completed before the other South American dreadnoughts, but they were also smaller and not as well-armed. Two later dreadnoughts, [[Brazilian battleship Rio de Janeiro (1913)|''Rio de Janeiro'']] and [[#Riachuelo|''Riachuelo'']], were planned, but the former was sold to the Ottoman Empire amid falling government revenues, and the other was canceled.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Naval History'', 82; Vanterpool, &quot;The 'Riachuelo',&quot; 140.&lt;/ref&gt;
| File:Rivadavia-class battleships.jpg|The ''Rivadavia'' class were the second dreadnought class purchased by a South American country and the only ones to not be built by a British company. Ordered in response to the ''Minas Geraes'' class, they mounted the same-size [[main battery]] as the Brazilian ships (12-inch), but the Argentine ships were much larger and significantly better-armored.&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, ''Naval History'', 82; Scheina, &quot;Argentina&quot; and &quot;Brazil,&quot; 401, 404.&lt;/ref&gt;
| File:Brassey's HMS Canada Plan (1915).jpg|[[Almirante Latorre-class battleship|''Almirante Latorre'']] was the last South American dreadnought built, and was larger and better armed than its counterparts. The more efficient arrangement of the five 14-inch turrets, with all mounted on the centerline rather than ''[[en echelon]]'', allowed the main battery to fire on a single [[broadside]] without damaging the ship.&lt;ref&gt;Whitley, ''Battleships'', 20; Preston, &quot;Great Britain,&quot; 38.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== See also ==
{{portal|Battleships|Argentina}}
*''[[Dreadnoughtus]]'' – a fossilized dinosaur found in [[Patagonia]], Argentina, named in part because of the ''Rivadavia'' class

== Footnotes ==
{{notelist-ua}}

== Endnotes ==
{{Research help|Mil}}{{reflist|30em}}

== References ==
{{refbegin | indent = yes}}
: Alger, Philip. &quot;[https://books.google.com/books?id=tiJKAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA595 Professional Notes; Ships of War, Budgets and Personnel; Argentine Republic].&quot; ''Proceedings of the United States Naval Institute'' 36, no. 2 (1910): 595–647. {{oclc|2496995}}.
: Burzaco, Ricardo and Patricio Ortíz. ''Acorazados y Cruceros de la Armada Argentina, 1881–1992''. Buenos Aires: Eugenio B. Ediciones, 1997. ISBN 987-96764-0-8. {{oclc|39297360}}.
: Friedman, Norman. ''U.S. Battleships: An Illustrated Design History''. Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press, 1985. ISBN 0-87021-715-1. {{oclc|12214729}}.
: Gardiner, Robert and Randal Gray, eds. ''Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1921''. Annapolis: Naval Institute Press, 1984. ISBN 0-87021-907-3. {{oclc|12119866}}.
: Garrett, James L. &quot;The Beagle Channel Dispute: Confrontation and Negotiation in the Southern Cone.&quot; ''Journal of Interamerican Studies and World Affairs'' 27, no. 3 (1985): 81–109. {{jstor|165601}}. {{issn|0022-1937}}. {{oclc|2239844}}.
: Hough, Richard. ''The Big Battleship''. London: Michael Joseph, 1966. {{oclc|8898108}}.
: Livermore, Seward W. &quot;Battleship Diplomacy in South America: 1905–1925.&quot; ''The Journal of Modern History'' 16, no. 1 (1944): 31–44. {{jstor|1870986}}. {{issn|0022-2801}}. {{oclc|62219150}}.
: ———. &quot;The American Navy as a Factor in World Politics, 1903–1913.&quot; ''The American Historical Review'' 63, no. 4 (1958): 863–879. {{jstor|1848944}}. {{issn|1937-5239}}. {{oclc|35776522}}.
: Preston, Antony. &quot;Great Britain.&quot; In Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's'', 1–104.
: Sarcone, Anthony F. and Lawrence S. Rines. [http://thomascranelibrary.org/shipbuildingheritage/history/historyindex.html ''A History of Shipbuilding at Fore River'']. Quincy, MA: Quincy Junior College, 1975. {{oclc|21584870}}.
: Scheina, Robert L. &quot;Argentina.&quot; In Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's'', 400–403.
: ———. &quot;Brazil.&quot; In Gardiner and Gray, ''Conway's'', 403–407.
: ———. ''Latin America: A Naval History 1810–1987''. Annapolis: Naval Institute Press, 1987. ISBN 0-87021-295-8. {{oclc|15696006}}.
: Sondhaus, Lawrence. ''Naval Warfare, 1815–1914''. London and New York: Routledge, 2001. ISBN 0-415-21478-5. {{oclc|44039349}}.
: Topliss, David. &quot;The Brazilian Dreadnoughts, 1904–1914.&quot; ''Warship International'' 25, no. 3 (1988): 240–289. {{issn|0043-0374}}. {{oclc|1647131}}.
: Vanterpool, Alan. &quot;The Riachuleo.&quot; ''Warship International'' 6, no. 2 (1969): 140–141.
: Whitley, M.J. ''Battleships of World War Two: An International Encyclopedia''. Annapolis: [[Naval Institute Press]], 1998. ISBN 1-55750-184-X. {{oclc|40834665}}.
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Rivadavia class battleship}}
*[http://www.archivesdirect.amdigital.co.uk/CP_LatinAmerica/Introduction British diplomatic documents] relating to the dreadnought race (FO 508/8; [http://www.amdigital.co.uk/ Adam Matthew] subscription required)
* [http://www.histarmar.com.ar/Armada%20Argentina/HistoriaAcorazadosArgentinos.htm &quot;Historia y Arqueología Marítima&quot; (HistArMar) Battleships ARA ''Moreno'' &amp; ''Rivadavia''&amp;nbsp;– History and pictures]
* [http://www.histarmar.com.ar/Armada%20Argentina/Buques1900a1970/AcARARivadavia-Historia.htm &quot;Historia y Arqueología Marítima&quot; (HistArMar) Battleship ARA Rivadavia (1914)&amp;nbsp;– Pictures]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z2CmqPprTBw Acorazado Rivadavia] (YouTube)
* [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1067193/ The Launching of the Battleship Rivadavia] (IMDB)
*[https://secure.flickr.com/photos/library_of_congress/tags/ararivadavia/ ARA ''Rivadavia''] on Flickr (LOC)
* [http://www.histarmar.com.ar/InfHistorica/AntiguaFlotadeMar/EspTec10AcMoreno.htm &quot;Historia y Arqueología Marítima&quot; (HistArMar) – Battleship ARA ''Moreno'' (1915) – Pictures &amp; Specifications]
*[https://secure.flickr.com/photos/library_of_congress/tags/aramoreno/ ARA ''Moreno''] on Flickr (LOC)

&lt;!-- non-breaking space to separate the navbox --&gt;

{{Rivadavia class battleships}}
{{South American dreadnoughts}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{Featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rivadavia-class battleship}}
[[Category:Rivadavia-class battleships| ]]
[[Category:1910s ships]]
[[Category:Battleship classes]]</text>
      <sha1>boj93d7bk64kar5kctgz1zncsszzz2u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
