<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Thüringen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30270385</id>
    <revision>
      <id>688726569</id>
      <parentid>683928070</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-11-02T18:16:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trappist the monk</username>
        <id>10289486</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>|Ship country= fixes; using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33633">{{featured article}}
{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:SMS Thuringen.png|300px]]
| Ship caption = SMS ''Thüringen'', probably before the war
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header = 
| Ship country = [[German Empire]]
| Ship flag = {{shipboxflag|German Empire|naval}}
| Ship name = ''Thüringen''
| Ship ordered = 
| Ship awarded = 
| Ship builder = [[AG Weser]], [[Bremen]]
| Ship original cost = 
| Ship yard number = 
| Ship way number = 
| Ship laid down = 2 November 1908
| Ship launched = 27 November 1909
| Ship sponsor = 
| Ship christened = 
| Ship completed = 
| Ship acquired = 
| Ship commissioned = 1 July 1911
| Ship recommissioned = 
| Ship decommissioned = 
| Ship maiden voyage = 
| Ship in service = 
| Ship out of service = 5 November 1919
| Ship renamed = 
| Ship reclassified = 
| Ship refit = 
| Ship struck = 
| Ship reinstated = 
| Ship homeport = 
| Ship identification = 
| Ship motto = 
| Ship nickname = 
| Ship honours = 
| Ship honors = 
| Ship captured = 
| Ship fate = Broken up for scrap, 1923–33
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = 
| Ship class = {{sclass-|Helgoland|battleship}}
| Ship displacement =* {{convert|22,808|t|LT|sp=us|lk=out}} (designed)
* {{convert|24,700|t|LT|abbr=on}} (full load)
  
| Ship length = {{convert|167.20|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship beam =  {{convert|28.50|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship draft = {{convert|8.94|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship power = {{convert|20,594|kW|ihp|lk=in|abbr=on|order=flip}}
| Ship propulsion =* 3 shaft
* 4-cylinder vertical triple-expansion steam engines
* 15 [[water-tube boiler]]s
  
| Ship speed = {{convert|20.8|kn|lk=in}}
| Ship range = {{convert|5,500|nmi|-1|lk=in}} at {{convert|10|kn}}
| Ship complement =* 42 officers
* 1027 enlisted
  
| Ship armament =* 12 × 30.5&amp;nbsp;cm (12&amp;nbsp;in) guns
* 14 × 15&amp;nbsp;cm (5.9&amp;nbsp;in) guns
* 14 × 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm (3.5&amp;nbsp;in) guns
* 6 × 50&amp;nbsp;cm (19.7&amp;nbsp;in) torpedo tubes
  
| Ship armor =* Belt: {{convert|300|mm|in|abbr=on}}
* Turrets: 300&amp;nbsp;mm
* Deck: {{convert|63.5|mm|in|abbr=on}}
  
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}

'''SMS ''Thüringen'''''{{efn|name=SMS}} was the third vessel of the {{sclass-|Helgoland|battleship|4}} of [[dreadnought]] [[battleship]]s of the German [[Kaiserliche Marine|Imperial Navy]]. ''Thüringen''{{'}}s [[keel]] was laid in November 1908 at the [[AG Weser]] dockyard in [[Bremen]]. She was launched on 27 November 1909 and commissioned into the fleet on 1 July 1911. The ship was equipped with twelve {{convert|30.5|cm|in|sp=us|adj=on}} guns in six twin [[gun turret|turrets]], and had a top speed of {{convert|21|kn}}. ''Thüringen'' was assigned to the I Battle Squadron of the [[High Seas Fleet]] for the majority of her career, including [[World War I]].

Along with her three [[sister ship]]s, {{SMS|Helgoland||2}}, {{SMS|Ostfriesland||2}}, and {{SMS|Oldenburg||2}}, ''Thüringen'' participated in all of the major fleet operations of World War I in the [[North Sea]] against the British [[Grand Fleet]]. This included the [[Battle of Jutland]] on 31 May and 1 June 1916, the largest naval battle of the war. ''Thüringen'' was involved in the heavy night fighting at Jutland, including the destruction of the [[armored cruiser]] {{HMS|Black Prince|1904|6}}.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=44}} The ship also saw action  against the [[Imperial Russian Navy]] in the [[Baltic Sea]], where she participated in the unsuccessful [[Battle of the Gulf of Riga|first incursion into the Gulf of Riga]] in August 1915.

After the German collapse in November 1918, most of the High Seas Fleet was interned in [[Scapa Flow]] during the peace negotiations. The four ''Helgoland''-class ships were allowed to remain in Germany and were therefore spared the [[scuttling of the German fleet in Scapa Flow|destruction of the fleet in Scapa Flow]]. ''Thüringen'' and her sisters were eventually ceded to the victorious [[Allies of World War I|Allied powers]] as [[war reparations]]; ''Thüringen'' was transferred to France in April 1920 and used as a target ship for the French Navy. She was sunk off [[Gavres]] and broken up [[wikt:in situ|''in situ'']] in 1923–1933, though some sections of the ship remain.

== Construction ==
{{main|Helgoland-class battleship}}

''Thüringen'' was ordered by the German Imperial Navy (''Kaiserliche Marine'') under the provisional name ''Ersatz Beowulf'',{{efn|name=provisional names}} as a replacement for the old [[coastal defense ship]] {{SMS|Beowulf||2}}. The contract for the ship was awarded to the [[AG Weser]] dockyard in [[Bremen]] under construction number 166.{{sfn|Gröner|p=24}} Work began on 2 November 1908 with the laying of her [[keel]], and the ship was launched a year later on 27 November 1909.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=36}} She was christened by Duchess [[Adelheid von Sachsen-Altenburg]], and Grand Duke [[William Ernest, Grand Duke of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach|Wilhelm Ernst]] gave the speech.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=231}} [[Fitting-out]], including completion of the superstructure and the installation of armament, lasted until June 1911. Following her completion, six pontoon barges were attached to the new battleship to reduce her draft to allow her to be towed down the [[Weser River]] to the [[North Sea]].{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=44}} ''Thüringen'', named for [[Thuringia]], a state in central Germany, was commissioned into the High Seas Fleet on 1 June 1911, less than three years after work commenced,{{sfn|Gröner|p=25}} at a cost of 46.314&amp;nbsp;million [[German gold mark|gold marks]], the most expensive unit of her class.{{sfn|Gröner|p=24}}

The ship was {{convert|167.2|m|ftin|abbr=on}} [[length overall|long overall]], had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|28.5|m|ftin|abbr=on}} and a [[draft (ship)|draft]] of {{convert|8.94|m|ftin|abbr=on}}, and displaced {{convert|24,700|MT|LT|-1}} at full load. She was powered by three [[Marine steam engine#Triple or multiple expansion|vertical triple expansion steam engines]] and fifteen [[water-tube boiler]]s. The engines were rated at {{convert|20,594|kW|ihp|lk=in|abbr=on|order=flip}} and were capable of producing a top speed of {{convert|21|kn}}. ''Thüringen'' stored up to {{convert|3200|t|LT|sp=us}} of coal, which allowed her to steam for {{convert|5,500|nmi|lk=in}} at a speed of {{convert|10|kn}}. After 1915, the boilers were modified to spray oil on the coal to increase its burn rate; the ship could carry up to {{convert|197|t|LT|sp=us}} of fuel oil.{{sfn|Gröner|p=24}}

''Thüringen'' was armed with a main battery of twelve [[30.5 cm SK L/50 gun|{{convert|30.5|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/50]]{{efn|name=gun nomenclature}} guns in six twin [[gun turret]]s, with one turret fore, one aft, and two on each flank of the ship.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=146}} The ship's secondary armament consisted of fourteen {{convert|15|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/45 guns and fourteen {{convert|8.8|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/45 guns.{{sfn|Gröner|p=24}} After 1914, two of the 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm guns were removed and replaced by 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm anti-aircraft guns. ''Thüringen'' was also armed with six {{convert|50|cm|in|abbr=on}} submerged [[torpedo tube]]s; one was in the bow, one in the stern, and two on each [[broadside]]. Her [[belt armor|main belt]] of armor was {{convert|300|mm|abbr=on}} thick, with the same thickness of armor on her main battery turrets. Her deck was {{convert|63.5|mm|abbr=on}} thick.{{sfn|Gröner|p=25}}

== Service history ==
After her commissioning on 1 July 1911, ''Thüringen'' conducted [[sea trial]]s, which were completed by 10 September. On 19 September, she was assigned to the I Battle Squadron of the [[High Seas Fleet]], alongside her sisters.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=44}} She then went on to conduct individual ship training exercises, which were followed by I Squadron exercises and then fleet maneuvers in November.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}} The annual summer cruise in July and August, which typically went to Norway, was interrupted by the [[Agadir Crisis]]. As a result, the cruise only went into the Baltic.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=8}} ''Thüringen'' and the rest of the fleet then fell into a pattern of individual ship, squadron, and full fleet exercises over the next two years.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=44}} In October 1913, [[William Michaelis]] became the ship's commanding officer; he held the post until February 1915.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=230}}

On 14 July 1914, the annual summer cruise to Norway began.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=11}} During the last peacetime cruise of the Imperial Navy, the fleet conducted drills off [[Skagen]] before proceeding to the Norwegian fjords on 25 July. The following day the fleet began to steam back to Germany, as a result of Austria-Hungary's [[July Ultimatum|ultimatum to Serbia]]. On 27 July, the entire fleet assembled off [[Skudenes|Cape Skudenes]] before returning to port, where they remained at a heightened state of readiness.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 2)|p=14}} War between Austria-Hungary and Serbia broke out the following day, and within a week all the major European powers had joined the conflict.{{sfn|Heyman|p=xix}} By 29 July ''Thüringen'' and the rest of I Squadron were back in [[Wilhelmshaven]].{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=11, 43}} During the first year of the war, the future anti-Nazi [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]] pastor [[Martin Niemöller]] served aboard the ship as an officer.{{sfn|Garland &amp; Garland|p=669}}

=== World War I ===
[[File:Scheer's illustration of I SG disposition 16 Dec. 1916 en.SVG|thumb|The High Seas Fleet's disposition on the morning of 16 December 1914, during the [[raid on Scarborough, Hartlepool and Whitby]]|alt=Map showing the locations of the British and German fleets; the German light cruisers pass between the British battleship and battlecruiser forces while the German battlecruisers steam to the northeast. The German battleships lie to the east of the other ships.]]

''Thüringen'' was present during the first sortie by the German fleet into the North Sea, which took place on 2–3 November 1914. No British forces were encountered during the operation. A second operation followed on 15–16 December.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}} This sortie was the initiation of a strategy adopted by Admiral [[Friedrich von Ingenohl]], the commander of the High Seas Fleet. Admiral von Ingenohl intended to use the [[battlecruiser]]s of ''[[Konteradmiral]]'' (Rear Admiral) [[Franz von Hipper]]'s [[I Scouting Group]] to raid British coastal towns to lure out portions of the Grand Fleet where they could be destroyed by the High Seas Fleet.{{sfn|Herwig|pp=149–150}} Early on 15 December the fleet left port to [[raid on Scarborough, Hartlepool and Whitby|raid the towns of Scarborough, Hartlepool, and Whitby]] on the English coast. That evening, the German battle fleet of some twelve dreadnoughts—including ''Thüringen'' and her three [[sister ship|sisters]]—and eight pre-dreadnoughts came to within {{convert|10|nmi|abbr=on}} of an isolated squadron of six British battleships. Skirmishes between the rival [[destroyer]] screens in the darkness convinced von Ingenohl that he was faced with the entire Grand Fleet. Under orders from [[Kaiser Wilhelm II]] to avoid risking the fleet unnecessarily, von Ingenohl broke off the engagement and turned the battle fleet back toward Germany.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=31–33}}

The [[Battle of Dogger Bank (1915)|Battle of Dogger Bank]], in which Vice Admiral [[David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty|David Beatty's]] [[1st Battlecruiser Squadron (United Kingdom)|1st]] and [[2nd Battlecruiser Squadron (United Kingdom)|2nd Battlecruiser Squadrons]] ambushed the I Scouting Group battlecruisers, occurred on 24 January 1915.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=38}} ''Thüringen'' and the rest of I Squadron were sortied to reinforce the outnumbered German battlecruisers; I Squadron left port at 12:33&amp;nbsp;[[Central European Time|CET]],{{efn|name=CET times}} along with the [[pre-dreadnought]]s of II Squadron. The High Seas Fleet was too late, so it failed to locate any British forces. By 19:05, the fleet had returned to the [[Schillig Roads]] outside Wilhelmshaven.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}} In the meantime, the [[armored cruiser]] {{SMS|Blücher||2}} had been overwhelmed by concentrated British fire and sunk, while the battlecruiser {{SMS|Seydlitz||2}} was severely damaged by an ammunition fire. As a result, Wilhelm II removed von Ingenohl from his post and replaced him with Admiral [[Hugo von Pohl]] on 2 February.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=43}}

[[File:SMS Helgoland illustration.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A large gray warship steams at high speed in choppy water; thick black smoke pours from three tall smoke stacks in the middle of the ship|Recognition drawing of a ''Helgoland''-class battleship]]
The eight I Squadron ships went into the Baltic on 22 February 1915 for unit training, which lasted until 13 March. Following their return to the North Sea, the ships participated in a series of uneventful fleet sorties on 29–30 March, 17–18 April, 21–22 April, 17–18 May, and 29–30 May. ''Thüringen'' and the rest of the fleet then remained in port until 4 August, when the I Squadron returned to the Baltic for another round of training maneuvers. From there, the squadron was attached to the naval force that attempted to sweep the [[Gulf of Riga]] of Russian naval forces in August 1915.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}} The assault force included the eight I Squadron battleships, the battlecruisers {{SMS|Von der Tann||2}}, {{SMS|Moltke||2}}, and ''Seydlitz'', several [[light cruiser]]s, 32 destroyers and 13 [[Minesweeper (ship)|minesweepers]]. The plan called for channels to be swept in Russian minefields so that the Russian naval presence, which included the pre-dreadnought {{ship|Russian battleship|Slava||2}}, could be eliminated. The Germans would then lay minefields of their own to prevent Russian ships from returning to the Gulf.{{sfn|Halpern|p=196}} ''Thüringen'' and the majority of the other big ships of the High Seas Fleet remained outside the Gulf for the entirety of [[Battle of the Gulf of Riga|the operation]]. The dreadnoughts {{SMS|Nassau||2}} and {{SMS|Posen||2}} were detached on 16 August to escort the minesweepers and to destroy ''Slava'', though they failed to sink the old battleship. After three days, the Russian minefields had been cleared, and the flotilla entered the Gulf on 19 August; reports of Allied submarines in the area prompted a German withdrawal from the Gulf the following day.{{sfn|Halpern|pp=197–198}} By 26 August, the I Squadron had returned to Wilhelmshaven.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}}

On 23–24 October, the High Seas Fleet undertook its last major offensive operation under the command of von Pohl, though it ended without contact with British forces.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}} By January 1916 [[hepatic cancer]] had weakened von Pohl to the point where he was no longer able to carry out his duties, and he was replaced by Vice Admiral [[Reinhard Scheer]] in January.{{sfn|Herwig|p=161}} Scheer proposed a more aggressive policy designed to force a confrontation with the British Grand Fleet; he received approval from the Kaiser in February.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=50}} Scheer's first operation was a sweep into the North Sea on 5–7 March, followed by two more on 21–22 March and 25–26 March.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}} During Scheer's next operation, ''Thüringen'' supported [[Bombardment of Yarmouth and Lowestoft|a raid on the English coast]] on 24 April 1916 conducted by the German battlecruiser force. The battlecruisers left the [[Jade Estuary]] at 10:55 and the rest of the High Seas Fleet followed at 13:40. The battlecruiser ''Seydlitz'' struck a mine while en route to the target, and had to withdraw.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=53}} The other battlecruisers bombarded the town of Lowestoft unopposed, but during the approach to Yarmouth, they encountered the British cruisers of the [[Harwich Force]]. A short gun duel ensued before the Harwich Force withdrew. Reports of British submarines in the area prompted the retreat of the I&amp;nbsp;Scouting Group. At this point, Scheer, who had been warned of the sortie of the Grand Fleet from its base in Scapa Flow, also withdrew to safer German waters.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=54}}

==== Battle of Jutland ====
{{main|Battle of Jutland}}
[[File:Map of the Battle of Jutland, 1916.svg|thumb|350px|Maps showing the maneuvers of the British (blue) and German (red) fleets on 31 May&amp;nbsp;– 1 June 1916|alt=The British fleet sailed from northern Britain to the east while the Germans sailed from Germany in the south; the opposing fleets met off the Danish coast]]

''Thüringen'' was present during the fleet operation that resulted in the battle of [[Jutland]] which took place on 31 May and 1 June 1916. The German fleet again sought to draw out and isolate a portion of the Grand Fleet and destroy it before the main British fleet could retaliate. During the operation, ''Thüringen'' was the second ship in the I Division of I Squadron and the tenth ship in the line, directly astern of the squadron flagship ''Ostfriesland'' and ahead of another sister ''Helgoland''. The I Squadron was the center of the German line, behind the eight {{sclass-|König|battleship|5}}- and  {{sclass-|Kaiser|battleship|2}}s of III Squadron. The six elderly pre-dreadnoughts of the III and IV Divisions, II Battle Squadron, formed the rear of the formation.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=286}}

Shortly before 16:00, the battlecruisers of the I Scouting Group encountered the British 1st Battlecruiser Squadron under the command of David Beatty. The opposing ships began an artillery duel that saw the destruction of {{HMS|Indefatigable|1909|2}}, shortly after 17:00,{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=94–95}} and {{HMS|Queen Mary||2}}, less than half an hour later.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=100–101}} By this time, the German battlecruisers were steaming south to draw the British ships toward the main body of the High Seas Fleet. At 17:30, the crew of the leading German battleship, ''König'', spotted both the I&amp;nbsp;Scouting Group and the 1st Battlecruiser Squadron approaching. The German battlecruisers were steaming to starboard, while the British ships steamed to port. At 17:45, Scheer ordered a [[Boxing the compass|two-point]] turn to port to bring his ships closer to the British battlecruisers, and a minute later, the order to open fire was given.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=110}}{{efn|name=compass points}}

While the leading battleships engaged the British battlecruiser squadron, ''Thüringen'' and ten other battleships, too far out of range to attack the British battlecruisers, fired on the British 2nd Light Cruiser Squadron. ''Thüringen'' and {{SMS|Kronprinz||2}} engaged the cruiser {{HMS|Dublin|1912|2}}, though both ships failed to score a hit.{{sfn|Campbell|p=54}} ''Thüringen'' fired for eight minutes at ranges of {{convert|18600|to|20800|yd|m|abbr=on}}, expending twenty-nine 30.5&amp;nbsp;cm shells.{{sfn|Campbell|p=99}} The British destroyers {{HMS|Nestor|1915|2}} and {{HMS|Nomad||2}}, which had been disabled earlier in the engagement, laid directly in the path of the advancing High Seas Fleet.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=114}} ''Thüringen'' and three other battleships destroyed ''Nestor'' with their primary and secondary guns while several III Squadron battleships sank ''Nomad''.{{sfn|Campbell|p=101}} Shortly after 19:15, the British dreadnought {{HMS|Warspite|03|2}} came into range; ''Thüringen'' opened fire at 19:25 with her main and secondary battery guns, at ranges of {{convert|10600|to|11800|yd|m|abbr=on}}. The ship fired twenty-one 30.5&amp;nbsp;cm and thirty-seven 15&amp;nbsp;cm shells in the span of five or six minutes, after which ''Thüringen''{{'}}s gunners lost sight of ''Warspite'', without scoring any hits. They then shifted fire to {{HMS|Malaya||2}}.{{sfn|Campbell|p=154}} ''Thüringen'' fired twenty main battery rounds at ''Malaya'', also unsuccessfully, over seven minutes at a range of {{convert|14100|yd|m|abbr=on}} before conforming to a 180&amp;nbsp;degree turn ordered by Scheer to disengage from the British fleet.{{sfn|Campbell|p=155}}

At around 23:30, the German fleet reorganized into the night-cruising formation. ''Thüringen'' was the seventh ship, stationed toward the front of the 24-ship line.{{sfn|Campbell|p=275}} An hour later, the leading units of the German line encountered British light forces and a violent firefight at close range ensued. Sometime around 01:10, the armored cruiser {{HMS|Black Prince|1904|2}} stumbled into the German line. ''Thüringen'' illuminated the vessel with her spotlights and poured salvos of 30.5&amp;nbsp;cm rounds into the ship at point-blank range. The first salvo struck near ''Black Prince''{{'}}s rear gun turret, which appears to have been blown overboard. ''Thüringen'' fired a total of ten 30.5&amp;nbsp;cm, twenty-seven 15&amp;nbsp;cm, and twenty-four 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm shells. She was joined by three other battleships, and ''Black Prince'' was soon destroyed by a huge ammunition explosion.{{sfn|Campbell|p=290}} Around a half an hour later, ''Thüringen'' spotted what appeared to be a [[Town-class cruiser (1910)#Birkenhead class|''Birkenhead''-class cruiser]]. She fired a [[starshell]] to illuminate the British cruiser and opened fire with her secondary guns. The ship was actually the destroyer {{HMS|Turbulent|1916|2}}. ''Thüringen'' fired eighteen 15&amp;nbsp;cm and six 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm shells before launching another starshell. ''Turbulent'' appeared to be capsized to starboard, though she remained afloat and was dispatched later by the cruiser {{SMS|Regensburg||2}} and the destroyers {{SMS|V71||2}} and {{SMS|V73||2}}.{{sfn|Campbell|p=293}}

Despite the ferocity of the night fighting, the High Seas Fleet punched through the British destroyer forces and reached [[Horns Reef]] by 04:00 on 1&amp;nbsp;June.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=246–247}} A few hours later, the fleet arrived in the Jade; ''Thüringen'', ''Helgoland'', ''Nassau'', and {{SMS|Westfalen||2}} took up defensive positions in the outer [[roadstead]] and four undamaged III Squadron ships anchored just outside the entrance locks to Wilhelmshaven. The remaining eight dreadnoughts entered port, where those that were still in fighting condition restocked ammunition and fuel.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=263}} In the course of the engagement, ''Thüringen'' had fired one-hundred and seven 30.5&amp;nbsp;cm, one-hundred and fifteen 15&amp;nbsp;cm, and twenty-two 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm shells,{{sfn|Tarrant|p=292}} while she and her crew emerged from the battle unscathed.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=44}}

==== Subsequent operations ====
On 18 August, Admiral Scheer attempted to repeat the 31 May operation. The two serviceable German battlecruisers (''Moltke'' and ''Von der Tann''), supported by three dreadnoughts, would bombard [[Sunderland, Tyne and Wear|Sunderland]] in an attempt to draw out and destroy Beatty's battlecruisers.{{efn|name=Derfflinger, Seydlitz &amp; Lützow}} The rest of the fleet, including ''Thüringen'', would trail behind and provide cover. British signals intelligence informed Jellicoe of the German departure later in the day, and he sent the Grand Fleet out to intercept the Germans.{{sfn|Massie|p=682}} On the approach to the English coast, Scheer turned north after receiving a false report from a [[zeppelin]] about a British unit in the area.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 2)|p=15}} As a result, the bombardment was not carried out, and by 14:35 on 19 August, Scheer had been warned of the Grand Fleet's approach and so turned his forces around and retreated to German ports.{{sfn|Massie|p=683}}

On 25–26 September, ''Thüringen'' and the rest of I Squadron covered an advance conducted by the second commander of the torpedo-boat flotillas (II ''Führer der Torpedoboote'') to the [[Terschelling]] Bank.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43, 46}} Scheer conducted another fleet operation on 18–20 October in the direction of the Dogger Bank, though rudder damage prevented ''Thüringen'' from participating.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=46}} For the majority of 1917, ''Thüringen'' was assigned to guard duty in the [[German Bight]]. During [[Operation Albion]], the amphibious assault on the Russian-held islands in the Gulf of Riga, ''Thüringen'' and her three sisters were moved to the [[Danish straits]] to block any possible British attempt to intervene. On 28 October the four ships arrived in [[Bay of Puck|Putzig Wiek]], and from there steamed to [[Kuressaare|Arensburg]] on the 29th. On 2 November the operation was completed and ''Thüringen'' and her sisters began the voyage back to the North Sea. A final abortive fleet sortie took place on 23–24 April 1918.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43, 46}} ''Thüringen'', ''Ostfriesland'', and ''Nassau'' were formed into a special unit for Operation ''Schlußstein'', a planned occupation of [[St. Petersburg]]. The three ships reached the Baltic on 10 August, but the operation was postponed and eventually canceled.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=43–44}} The special unit was dissolved on 21 August and the battleships were back in Wilhelmshaven on the 23rd.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=44, 46}}

=== Fate ===
''Thüringen'' and her three sisters were to have taken part in a [[Naval order of 24 October 1918|final fleet action]] at the end of October 1918, days before the [[Armistice with Germany|Armistice]] was to take effect. The bulk of the High Seas Fleet was to have sortied from their base in Wilhelmshaven to engage the British Grand Fleet; Scheer—by now the [[Grand Admiral]] (''Großadmiral'') of the fleet—intended to inflict as much damage as possible on the British navy, to improve Germany's bargaining position, despite the expected casualties. But many of the war-weary sailors felt that the operation would disrupt the peace process and prolong the war.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=280–281}} On the morning of 29 October 1918, the order was given to sail from Wilhelmshaven the following day. Starting on the night of 29 October, sailors on ''Thüringen'' and then on several other battleships [[Wilhelmshaven mutiny|mutinied]].{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=281–282}} Stokers turned off the boilers and refused to work. The following day, the torpedo boats {{SMS|B110||2}} and {{SMS|B112||2}} came alongside and the [[U-boat]] {{SMU|U-135||2}} pointed her guns at the ship. A significant portion of the crew, 314 sailors and 124 stokers, were arrested and taken off the ship. This was not enough to stop the mutiny, which quickly spread throughout the fleet.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=46}} The unrest ultimately forced Hipper and Scheer to cancel the operation.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=282}} Informed of the situation, the Kaiser stated &quot;I no longer have a navy&quot;.{{sfn|Herwig|p=252}}

Following the capitulation of Germany in November 1918, most of the High Seas Fleet, under the command of Rear Admiral [[Ludwig von Reuter]], was interned in the British naval base in [[Scapa Flow]].{{sfn|Tarrant|p=282}} ''Thüringen'' and her three sisters, along with the four ''Nassau''-class battleships, were permitted to remain in Germany during the peace negotiations.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|pp=26–46}} On the morning of 21 June, the British fleet left Scapa Flow to conduct training maneuvers, and in their absence Reuter ordered the crews to [[scuttling|scuttle]] the ten battleships and five battlecruisers interned at Scapa Flow.{{sfn|Herwig|p=256}} ''Thüringen'' was decommissioned on 16 December 1918 and used as a barracks ship while she remained in Germany.{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=46}} She was stricken from the naval register on 5 November 1919 and placed out of commission.{{sfn|Gröner|p=25}} The fate of the eight remaining German battleships was determined in the [[Treaty of Versailles]], which stated that the ships were to be disarmed and surrendered to the governments of the principal Allied powers.{{r|Article 185}} ''Thüringen'' was surrendered to the French Navy on 29 April 1920 under the name ''&quot;L&quot;''. A skeleton crew took the ship to [[Cherbourg]] for the official transfer.{{sfn|Gröner|p=25}} ''Thüringen'' was briefly used as a target ship by the French Navy before sinking off [[Gavres]]. The ship was partially broken up [[wikt:in situ|''in situ'']] in 1923–1933, though significant portions of the ship remain off the French coast.{{sfn|Gröner|p=25}}{{sfn|Staff (Volume 1)|p=46}}

== Notes ==

{{portal|Battleships}}

'''Footnotes'''

{{notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = SMS
| &quot;SMS&quot; stands for &quot;''[[Seiner Majestät Schiff]]''&quot; ({{lang-de|His Majesty's Ship}}).
}}

{{efn
| name = gun nomenclature
| In Imperial German Navy gun nomenclature, &quot;SK&quot; (Schnelladekanone) denotes that the gun is quick firing, while the L/50 denotes the length of the gun. In this case, the L/50 gun is 50 [[Caliber (artillery)|calibers]], meaning that the gun is 50 times as long as its diameter.
}}

{{efn
| name = CET times
| The Germans were on Central European Time, which is one hour ahead of [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]], the time zone commonly used in British works.
}}

{{efn
| name = compass points
| The compass can be divided into 32 points, each corresponding to 11.25 degrees. A two-point turn to port would alter the ships' course by 22.5 degrees.
}}

{{efn
| name = Derfflinger, Seydlitz &amp; Lützow
| {{SMS|Derfflinger||2}} and {{SMS|Seydlitz||2}} had been seriously damaged at the Battle of Jutland, and {{SMS|Lützow||2}} had been sunk. See {{harvnb|Gröner|pp=56–57}} and {{harvnb|Tarrant|p=277}}.
}}

{{efn
| name = provisional names
| German warships were ordered under provisional names. For new additions to the fleet, they were given a single letter; for those ships intended to replace older or lost vessels, they were ordered as &quot;Ersatz (name of the ship to be replaced)&quot;.
}}

}}

'''Citations'''

{{reflist
| colwidth = 20em
| refs =

&lt;ref name=&quot;Article 185&quot;&gt;
[[s:Treaty of Versailles/Part V#Article 185|Treaty of Versailles]] Section II: Naval Clauses, Article 185.
&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

== References ==

* {{cite book
  | last = Campbell
  | first = John
  | year = 1998
  | title = Jutland: An Analysis of the Fighting
  | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
  | location = London, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-55821-759-1
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Campbell}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | editor1-last = Gardiner
  | editor1-first = Robert
  | editor2-last = Gray
  | editor2-first = Randal
  | year = 1985
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1921
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-907-8
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gardiner &amp; Gray}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Garland
  | first1 = Henry B.
  | last2 = Garland
  | first2 = Mary
  | year = 1986
  | title = The Oxford Companion to German Literature
  | location = Oxford, UK
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | isbn = 978-0-19-866139-9
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Garland &amp; Garland}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Gröner
  | first = Erich
  | editor1-last = Jung
  | editor1-first = Dieter
  | editor2-last = Maass
  | editor2-first = Martin
  | year = 1990
  | title = German Warships: 1815–1945, Major Surface Vessels
  | volume = I
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-790-6
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gröner}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Halpern
  | first = Paul G.
  | year = 1995
  | title = A Naval History of World War I
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-1-55750-352-7
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Halpern}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Herwig
  | first = Holger
  | year = 1998
  | origyear = 1980
  | title = &quot;Luxury&quot; Fleet: The Imperial German Navy 1888–1918
  | publisher = Humanity Books
  | location = Amherst, NY
  | isbn = 978-1-57392-286-9
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Herwig}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Heyman
  | first = Neil M.
  | year = 1997
  | title = World War I
  | publisher = Greenwood Publishing Group
  | location = Westport, CT
  | isbn = 978-0-313-29880-6
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Heyman}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Hildebrand
  | first1 = Hans H.
  | last2 = Röhr
  | first2 = Albert
  | last3 = Steinmetz
  | first3 = Hans-Otto
  | year = 1993
  | title = Die Deutschen Kriegsschiffe
  | volume = 7
  | location = Ratingen, DE
  | publisher = Mundus Verlag
  | isbn = 978-3-8364-9743-5 
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Massie
  | first = Robert K.
  | authorlink = Robert K. Massie
  | year = 2003
  | title = [[Castles of Steel]]
  | publisher = Ballantine Books
  | location = New York City, NY
  | isbn = 978-0-345-40878-5
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Massie}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Staff
  | first = Gary
  | year = 2010
  | title = German Battleships: 1914–1918
  | volume = 1
  | publisher = Osprey Books
  | location = Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-84603-467-1
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Staff (Volume 1)}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Staff
  | first = Gary
  | year = 2010
  | title = German Battleships: 1914–1918
  | volume = 2
  | publisher = Osprey Books
  | location = Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-84603-468-8
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Staff (Volume 2)}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tarrant
  | first = V. E.
  | year = 2001
  | origyear = 1995
  | title = Jutland: The German Perspective, a New View of the Great Battle, 31 May 1916
  | publisher = Cassell Military Paperbacks
  | location = London, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-304-35848-9
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Tarrant}}
  }}

{{Helgoland class battleship}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Thuringen}}
[[Category:Helgoland-class battleships]]
[[Category:Ships built in Bremen (state)]]
[[Category:1911 ships]]
[[Category:World War I battleships of Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>8m640hx9ly0qv1n5jzco7gyldvjp5wz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
