<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Baden</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>571374</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736878530</id>
      <parentid>736153752</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-30T12:35:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mdnavman</username>
        <id>7061136</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */ Added template and category.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24881">{{for|the earlier ironclad warship|SMS Baden (1880)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R17062, Linienschiff &quot;Baden&quot;.jpg|300px|alt=Overhead view of a large battleship; black smoke pours from its smoke stacks as it steams through choppy seas]]
| Ship caption = ''Baden'', with her main battery trained to port
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header = 
| Ship country = [[German Empire]]
| Ship flag = {{shipboxflag|German Empire|naval}}
| Ship name = SMS ''Baden''
| Ship namesake = [[Baden]]
| Ship owner = 
| Ship operator = 
| Ship ordered = 
| Ship awarded = 
| Ship builder = [[Schichau-Werke]]
| Ship original cost = 
| Ship yard number = 
| Ship way number = 
| Ship laid down = 20 December 1913
| Ship launched = 30 October 1915
| Ship sponsor = 
| Ship christened = 
| Ship completed = 
| Ship acquired = 
| Ship commissioned = 14 March 1917
| Ship fate =* Beached in [[Gutter Sound]], [[Scapa Flow]], 21 June 1919
* Sunk as target 16 August 1921
  
| Ship badge = 
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = 
| Ship class = {{sclass-|Bayern|battleship}}
| Ship displacement = {{convert|32,200|t|LT|abbr=on}}
| Ship length = {{convert|180|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship beam = {{convert|30|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship draft = {{convert|9.4|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship propulsion = 3 × Schichau [[steam turbine]]s, three shafts
| Ship speed = {{convert|21|kn|abbr=on}}
| Ship range = {{convert|5,000|nmi|lk=in|abbr=on}} at {{convert|12|kn}}
| Ship power = {{convert|25,742|kW|shp|lk=in|order=flip}} 
| Ship complement =* 42 officers
* 1,129 enlisted men
  
| Ship armament =*  8 × {{convert|38|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns
* 16 × {{convert|15|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns
*  2 × {{convert|8.8|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns
*  5 × {{convert|60|cm|in|abbr=on}} torpedo tubes
  
| Ship armor =* Belt: {{convert|170|to|350|mm|abbr=on|1}}
* Deck: {{convert|60|to|100|mm|abbr=on}}
* Turrets: 350&amp;nbsp;mm
  
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}

'''SMS ''Baden'''''{{efn|name=SMS}} was a {{sclass-|Bayern|battleship|0}} [[dreadnought battleship]] of the German [[Kaiserliche Marine|Imperial Navy]] built during [[World War I]]. Launched in October 1915 and completed in March 1917, she was the last battleship completed for use in the war; two of her [[sister ship|sisters]]—''Sachsen'' and ''Württemberg''—were incomplete when the war ended. The ship mounted eight {{convert|38|cm|sp=us|adj=on}} guns in four twin [[gun turret|turrets]], displaced {{convert|32200|MT|sp=us}} at full combat load, and had a top speed of {{convert|21|kn}}. Along with her sister {{SMS|Bayern||2}}, ''Baden'' was the largest and most powerfully armed battleship built by the Imperial Navy.

Upon commissioning into the [[High Seas Fleet]], ''Baden'' was made the fleet [[flagship]], replacing {{SMS|Friedrich der Grosse|1911|2}}. ''Baden'' saw little action during her short career; the only major sortie in April 1918 ended without any combat. Following the German collapse in November 1918, ''Baden'' was interned with the majority of the High Seas Fleet in [[Scapa Flow]] by the British [[Royal Navy]]. On 21 June 1919, Rear Admiral [[Ludwig von Reuter]] ordered [[Scuttling of the German fleet in Scapa Flow|the scuttling of the fleet]]. However, British sailors in the harbor managed to board ''Baden'' and beach her to prevent her sinking. The ship was refloated, thoroughly examined, and eventually sunk in extensive gunnery testing by the Royal Navy in 1921.

== Construction ==
''Baden'' was ordered under the provisional name ''Ersatz Wörth'' in 1912,{{sfn|Gröner|p=28}}{{efn|name=ersatz}} under the fourth and final [[German Naval Laws|Naval Law]], which was passed that year.{{sfn|Herwig|p=81}} Construction began at the [[Schichau-Werke]] dockyard in [[Danzig]] under construction number 913. The ship was laid down on 20 December 1913 and launched on 30 October 1915.{{sfn|Goodall|p=13}} After [[fitting-out]], sea trials were conducted; the ship was commissioned into service on 14 March 1917.{{sfn|Gröner|p=30}} She had cost the Imperial German Government 49 million [[German gold mark|Goldmarks]]. ''Baden''{{'}}s two sisterships, ''Sachsen'' and ''Württemberg'', both lay incomplete at the end of World War I and were subsequently scrapped, leaving ''Baden'' the last battleship built for the Imperial Navy.{{sfn|Gröner|p=28}}

''Baden'' was {{convert|179.4|m|ftin|abbr=on}} [[length at the waterline|long at the waterline]], and {{convert|180|m|ftin|abbr=on}} [[length overall|long overall]]. She had a [[draft (hull)|draft]] of between {{convert|9.3|-|9.4|m|ftin|abbr=on}}. ''Baden'' [[Displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|28,530|t|LT|sp=us}} at her designed displacement, which did not include a full load of combat supplies, fuel, and other operational necessities; at full combat load, she displaced up to {{convert|32,200|t|LT|sp=us}}.{{sfn|Gröner|p=28}} ''Baden''{{'}}s displacement was more than {{convert|3,000|t|LT|abbr=on}} greater than that of the preceding {{sclass-|König|battleship|0}} ships, making her the largest battleship built by the Imperial Navy.{{sfn|Hore|pp=69–70}} ''Baden'' was powered by three sets of Schichau [[steam turbine]]s, which were rated at {{convert|25,742|kW|shp|lk=in|order=flip}} , and produced a maximum of {{convert|41,390|kW|shp|lk=in|order=flip}}.{{sfn|Staff (''Battleships'')|pp=40, 42}} Designed speed was {{convert|21|kn}}, but ''Baden'' achieved a maximum speed of {{convert|22.1|kn}}.{{sfn|Staff (''Battleships'')|p=40}}

She was armed with eight 38&amp;nbsp;cm (15&amp;nbsp;in) guns arranged in four twin [[gun turret]]s: two [[superfire|superfiring]] turret pairs fore and aft of the [[superstructure]]. ''Baden'' and her sister ''Bayern'' were the first German warships to feature guns of this caliber;{{sfn|Hore|p=70}} earlier battleships carried either 28 or 30.5&amp;nbsp;cm (11 or 12&amp;nbsp;inch) guns.{{sfn|Hore|pp=67–69}} Her secondary armament consisted of sixteen 15&amp;nbsp;cm (5.9&amp;nbsp;in) guns, six 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm (3.45&amp;nbsp;in) guns and five 60&amp;nbsp;cm (23.6&amp;nbsp;in) underwater [[torpedo]] tubes, one in the bow and two on each beam. Upon commissioning, she carried a crew of 42 officers and 1,129 enlisted men.{{sfn|Gröner|p=30}}

== Service history ==
After her commissioning into the [[High Seas Fleet]], ''Baden'' was placed in the role of [[flagship]] for the commander of the fleet, Admiral [[Franz von Hipper]], a position she held until the end of the war.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=81}} At the end of August 1917, ''Baden'' took [[Kaiser Wilhelm II]] to visit the fortified island of [[Helgoland]]; the ship was escorted by the battlecruiser {{SMS|Derfflinger||2}} and the light cruisers {{SMS|Emden|1916|2}} and {{SMS|Karlsruhe|1916|2}}. After the conclusion of the visit, ''Baden'' returned the Kaiser to [[Cuxhaven]].{{sfn|Staff (''Battleships'')|p=43}} The ship struck the sea bottom outside Cuxhaven, though no major damage was done.{{sfn|Staff (''Battleships'')|p=44}}

=== Advance of 23 April 1918 ===
In late 1917, light forces of the High Seas Fleet began [[interdiction|interdicting]] British convoys to Norway.{{efn|name=coal convoys}} On 17 October the light cruisers {{SMS|Brummer||2}} and {{SMS|Bremse||2}} intercepted one of the convoys, sinking nine of the twelve cargo ships and the two escorting destroyers before turning back to Germany. On 12 December, four German destroyers ambushed a second British convoy of five cargo vessels and two British destroyers. All five transports were sunk, as was one of the destroyers.{{sfn|Massie|p=747}} Following these two raids, Admiral [[David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty|David Beatty]], the commander of the [[Grand Fleet]], detached battleships from the battle fleet to protect the convoys.{{sfn|Massie|pp=747–748}} The German Imperial Navy (''Kaiserliche Marine'') was now presented with an opportunity for which it had been waiting the entire war: a portion of the numerically stronger Grand Fleet was separated and could be isolated and destroyed. Vice Admiral [[Franz von Hipper]] planned the operation: the battlecruisers of the [[I Scouting Group]], along with light cruisers and destroyers, would attack one of the large convoys, while the rest of the High Seas Fleet would stand by, ready to attack the British [[dreadnought battleship]] squadron.{{sfn|Massie|p=748}}

At 05:00 on 23 April 1918, the German fleet departed from the Schillig [[roadstead]]. Hipper, aboard ''Baden'', ordered wireless transmissions be kept to a minimum, to prevent radio intercepts by British intelligence.{{sfn|Massie|p=748}} At 06:10 the German battlecruisers had reached a position approximately {{convert|60|km|mi|sp=us}} southwest of [[Bergen]] when the battlecruiser {{SMS|Moltke||2}} lost her inner starboard propeller, which severely damaged the ship's engines.{{sfn|Staff (''Battlecruisers'')|p=17}} The crew effected temporary repairs that allowed the ship to steam at {{convert|4|kn|km/h|abbr=on}}, but it was decided to take the ship under tow. Despite this setback, Hipper continued northward. By 14:00, Hipper's force had crossed the convoy route several times but had found nothing. At 14:10, Hipper turned his ships southward. By 18:37, the German fleet had made it back to the defensive minefields surrounding their bases. It was later discovered that the convoy had left port a day later than expected by the German planning staff.{{sfn|Massie|p=748}}

On 24 May, ''Baden'' again steamed to Helgoland, this time to take the commander in chief of the fleet, Admiral [[Reinhard Scheer]], and Grand Duke [[Frederick II, Grand Duke of Baden|Friedrich von Baden]] to visit the island. Only ''Karlsruhe'' joined the ship on this voyage.{{sfn|Staff (''Battleships'')|p=44}}

=== Wilhelmshaven mutiny ===
{{main|Wilhelmshaven mutiny}}

As the fleet flagship, ''Baden'' was to have taken part in a [[Naval order of 24 October 1918|final fleet action]] days before the [[Armistice with Germany (Compiègne)|Armistice]], an operation which envisioned the bulk of the High Seas Fleet sortieing from their base in Wilhelmshaven to engage the British Grand Fleet. In order to obtain a better bargaining position for Germany, Admirals Hipper and Scheer intended to inflict as much damage as possible on the British navy, whatever the cost to the fleet.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=280–281}} Consequently, on 29 October 1918, the order was given to depart from Wilhelmshaven to consolidate the fleet in the [[Jade Estuary|Jade]] roadstead, with the intention of departing the following morning. However, starting on the night of 29 October, sailors on {{SMS|Thüringen||2}} mutinied.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=281–282}}

Early on the 30th, the crew of ''Helgoland'', which was directly behind ''Thüringen'', joined in the mutiny. Both ships surrendered after two [[torpedo boat]]s arrived and threatened to open fire, and the battleships' crews were taken ashore and incarcerated.{{sfn|New York Times Co.|p=440}} The mood of ''Baden''{{'}}s crew was reported as &quot;dangerous&quot;.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=281}} The rebellion then spread ashore; on 3 November, an estimated 20,000 sailors, dock workers, and civilians fought a battle against the authorities in [[Kiel]] in an attempt to secure the release of the jailed mutineers.{{sfn|Schwartz|p=48}} Meanwhile, on 9 November, the Socialists' [[red flag (politics)|red flag]] was hoisted aboard ''Baden'', which finally convinced Hipper and Scheer to abandon the plan.{{sfn|Schwartz|p=48}}{{sfn|Butler|p=212}}

=== Scapa Flow ===
[[File:Salvage at Scapa Flow.jpg|left|thumb|Salvage work in progress on the ''Baden'' at Scapa Flow. The cruiser {{SMS|Frankfurt||2}} is also in view.]]
''Baden'' was not originally intended to be surrendered under the terms of the Armistice, but was substituted for the battlecruiser ''Mackensen'', which lay incomplete and could not put to sea.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=81}} As a result, instead of joining the High Seas Fleet when it departed for Scapa Flow on 21 November 1918,{{sfn|Herwig|p=254}} ''Baden'' left Germany on 7 January 1919.{{sfn|Staff (''Battleships'')|p=44}} The Royal Navy inspected the ship on 9 January, but many of the technical instruments, including gunnery equipment, had been removed before the ship left Germany.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=82}}

The fleet remained in captivity during the negotiations in Versailles that ultimately produced the [[Versailles Treaty|treaty that ended the war]]. A copy of ''[[The Times]]'' informed Rear Admiral von Reuter that the Armistice was to expire at noon on 21 June 1919, the deadline by which Germany was to have signed the peace treaty. Von Reuter came to the conclusion that the British intended to seize the German ships after the Armistice expired.{{efn|name=armistice expiry}} To prevent this, he decided to [[scuttling|scuttle]] his ships at the first opportunity. On the morning of 21 June, the British fleet left Scapa Flow to conduct training maneuvers; at 11:20 Reuter transmitted the order to his ships.{{sfn|Herwig|p=256}} ''Baden'' was the last major warship to begin the scuttling process, and British forces in the harbor managed to secure the ship and run it aground before it could sink in deeper water. She was the only [[capital ship]] not successfully sunk in the scuttling.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=81}} The ship was refloated in July,{{sfn|Gröner|p=30}} after which she was towed to the British naval base at [[Invergordon]].{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=82}}

=== British service ===
[[File:SMS Baden towed from Scapa.jpg|thumb|''Baden'' being towed from Scapa Flow|alt=Two small boats pull a larger vessel through calm waters.]]

After the ship arrived in Invergordon, ''Baden'' was carefully examined by Royal Navy technicians. Naval engineers inspected the hull, including the screws, [[bilge keel]]s, and rudders, to determine the water resistance of the hull form. The ship was found to have been approximately as efficient as the British {{sclass-|Revenge|battleship|2}}s.{{sfn|Goodall|p=15}} The ship's armor system was extensively investigated; the British team concluded that the ship had not been modified to incorporate the lessons from the [[Battle of Jutland]] of 31 May&amp;nbsp;– 1 June 1916.{{sfn|Goodall|pp=16–17}}

The main battery turrets and ammunition magazines were also the subject of intense scrutiny; among the tests conducted was a trial to see how fast the magazines could be flooded—the result was 12 minutes.{{sfn|Goodall|p=18–19}}{{efn|name=magazine flooding}} The gunnery school [[HMS Excellent (shore establishment)|HMS ''Excellent'']] ran loading trials on the main battery guns. It was found that the guns could be prepared to fire in 23 seconds, 13 seconds faster than in the {{sclass-|Queen Elizabeth|battleship|2}}s.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=82}} The ship's watertight bulkhead and underwater protection systems also particularly interested the inspection team; they paid close attention to the ship's pumping and counter-flooding equipment.{{sfn|Goodall|pp=23–24}} Commander [[W M Phipps Hornby]], who lived on board ''Baden'' for weeks during the examination, wrote to the naval historian [[Arthur Marder]] in 1969 that it was his &quot;considered opinion—which I know coincided with that of others engaged on the same job—that, ''considered as a fighting machine'', anyhow on balance the ''Baden'' was markedly in advance of any comparable ship of the Royal Navy&quot;.{{sfn|Marder|p=311}}

[[File:HMS Erebus I02.jpg|thumb|left|HMS ''Erebus''|alt=A small warship with one large gun turret sits off shore. The vessel is painted with an angular camouflage scheme of alternating light and dark colors.]]

After the inspection was concluded, it was determined to expend ''Baden'' as a gunnery target. In January 1921 the first round of gunnery tests was ordered. The gunners at HMS ''Excellent'' fired the new [[armor-piercing shot and shell|armor-piercing]] (AP) shells that had been introduced after the Battle of Jutland. This round of tests was used to determine the most efficient ratio of explosives in the detonator caps; the shells fired at Jutland had a tendency to fragment when striking heavy armor rather than penetrate. The [[Monitor (warship)|monitor]] {{HMS|Terror|I03|6}} moored some {{convert|500|yd|m|abbr=on}} away from ''Baden'' to fire her {{convert|15|in|cm|abbr=on}} guns from [[point-blank range]]. ''Baden'' was made to list to starboard by the removal of coal and armor from the port side, to simulate the effect of a shell striking armor from a plunging angle.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=83}} The forward-most gun turret had by this time been removed. ''Terror'' fired 17 shells of various types into the ship. The Royal Navy concluded after these tests that the new shells were sufficiently powerful to penetrate heavy armor, and were much more effective than the previous versions that had been employed at Jutland.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=84}} Following the tests, heavy seas caused the ship to sink in the shallow water; after three months she was again raised and docked for repairs. The ship was readied for a second round of testing by August 1921.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=87}}

The second series of tests was scheduled for 16 August 1921. The monitor {{HMS|Erebus|I02|6}} fired a mix of shell types into ''Baden'' with her 15&amp;nbsp;in guns. This time, the shells did not perform as well against ''Baden''{{'}}s heavy armor; one of the AP shells failed to explode and two semi-AP shells appear to have broken up on impact. Six aerial bombs were also detonated on the ship, though they had been placed on board and were detonated remotely. The bombs did not perform as well as had been expected.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=87}} Immediately following the second round of gunnery trials, ''Baden'' was scuttled. The ship sank in [[Hurd Deep]] in a depth of approximately 180&amp;nbsp;m (600&amp;nbsp;ft).{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=81}}

The most important finding of the trials on ''Baden'' was that the {{convert|7|in|cm|adj=on}} thick medium armor was completely useless against large-caliber shells. As a result, the British navy adopted the &quot;[[All or nothing (armor)|all or nothing]]&quot; armor pioneered by the [[United States Navy]].{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=90}} The &quot;all or nothing&quot; armor theory consisted of protecting the ship's vitals with extremely heavy armor, while leaving the rest of the ship completely unprotected.{{sfn|Brown|p=19}} This system was used on Britain's first post-war class of battleships, the {{sclass-|Nelson|battleship|4}}.{{sfn|Schleihauf|p=90}}

== Notes ==

{{portal|Battleships}}
{{Commons category|SMS Baden}}

'''Footnotes'''

{{notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = SMS
| &quot;SMS&quot; stands for &quot;''[[Seiner Majestät Schiff]]''&quot;, or &quot;His Majesty's Ship&quot;.
}}

{{efn
| name = ersatz
| ''Baden'' was ordered as a replacement for the old battleship {{SMS|Wörth}}; [[ersatz]] means &quot;replacement&quot; in German.
}}

{{efn
| name = coal convoys
| Britain had promised to ship {{convert|250000|ST}} of coal to Norway every month. See: {{harvnb|Massie|p=747}}.
}}

{{efn
| name = armistice expiry
| By this time, the Armistice had been extended to 23 June, though there is some contention as to whether von Reuter was aware of this. Admiral [[Sydney Fremantle]] stated that he informed von Reuter on the evening of the 20th, though von Reuter claims he was unaware of the development. For Fremantle's claim, see {{harvnb|Bennett|p=307}}. For von Reuter's statement, see {{harvnb|Herwig|p=256}}.
}}

{{efn
| name = magazine flooding
| In case of an ammunition fire, magazines were fitted to be flooded so as to prevent a catastrophic explosion.
}}

}}

'''Citations'''

{{reflist|20em}}

== References ==

{{Wikipedia books|Bayern class battleships}}

{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Bennett
  | first = Geoffrey
  | authorlink = Geoffrey Bennett
  | year = 2005
  | title = Naval Battles of the First World War
  | publisher = Pen &amp; Sword Military Classics
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1-84415-300-8
  | oclc = 57750267
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Bennett}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Brown
  | first = David Keith
  | year = 2006
  | origyear = 2000
  | title = Nelson to Vanguard: Warship Design and Development, 1923–1945
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 978-1-59114-602-5
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Brown}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Butler
  | first = Daniel Allen
  | year = 2006
  | title = Distant Victory: The Battle of Jutland and the Allied Triumph in the First World War
  | publisher = Greenwood Publishing Group
  | location = Westport, CT
  | isbn = 978-0-275-99073-2
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Butler}}
  }}
* {{cite journal
  | last = Goodall
  | first = Stanley Vernon
  | year = 1921
  | title = The Ex-German Battleship ''Baden''
  | journal = Transactions of the Institution of Naval Architects
  | location = London
  | volume = LXIII
  | pages = 13–32
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Goodall}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Gröner
  | first = Erich
  | year = 1990
  | title = German Warships: 1815–1945
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-790-6
  | oclc = 22101769
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gröner}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Herwig
  | first = Holger
  | year = 1998
  | origyear = 1980
  | title = &quot;Luxury&quot; Fleet: The Imperial German Navy 1888–1918
  | publisher = Humanity Books
  | location = [[Amherst, New York]]
  | isbn = 978-1-57392-286-9
  | oclc = 57239454
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Herwig}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hore
  | first = Peter
  | year = 2006
  | title = Battleships of World War I
  | publisher = Southwater Books
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1-84476-377-1
  | oclc = 77797289
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Hore}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Marder
  | first = Arthur J.
  | authorlink = Arthur Marder
  | year = 1970
  | title = From the Dreadnought to Scapa Flow, Volume 5 1918–1919: Victory and Aftermath
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-19-215187-2
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Marder}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Massie
  | first = Robert K.
  | authorlink = Robert K. Massie
  | year = 2003
  | title = [[Castles of Steel]]
  | publisher = Ballantine Books
  | location = New York City
  | isbn = 978-0-345-40878-5
  | oclc = 57134223
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Massie}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | author = New York Times Co.
  | year = 1919
  | title = The New York Times Current History: Jan.–March, 1919
  | location = New York
  | publisher = The New York Times Company
  | ref = {{sfnRef|New York Times Co.}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Schleihauf
  | first = William
  | year = 2007
  | chapter = The Baden Trials
  | title = Warship 2007
  | editor-last = Preston
  | editor-first = Anthony
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 978-1-84486-041-8
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Schleihauf}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Schwartz
  | first = Stephen
  | year = 1986
  | title = Brotherhood of the Sea: A History of the Sailors' Union of the Pacific, 1885–1985
  | publisher = Transaction Publishers
  | location = New Brunswick
  | isbn = 978-0-88738-121-8
  | oclc = 13792782
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Schwartz}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Staff
  | first = Gary
  | year = 2006
  | title = German Battlecruisers: 1914–1918
  | publisher = Osprey Books
  | location = Oxford
  | isbn = 978-1-84603-009-3
  | oclc = 64555761
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Staff (''Battlecruisers'')}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Staff
  | first = Gary
  | year = 2010
  | title = German Battleships: 1914–1918 (Volume 2)
  | publisher = Osprey Books
  | location = Oxford
  | isbn = 978-1-84603-468-8
  | oclc = 449845203
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Staff (''Battleships'')}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tarrant
  | first = V. E.
  | year = 2001
  | origyear = 1995
  | title = Jutland: The German Perspective
  | publisher = Cassell Military Paperbacks
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-304-35848-9
  | oclc = 48131785
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Tarrant}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Weir
  | first = Gary E.
  | title = Building the Kaiser's Navy: The Imperial Navy Office and German Industry in the Tirpitz Era, 1890–1919
  | year = 1992
  | location = Annapolis
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | isbn = 978-1-55750-929-1
  | oclc = 22665422
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Weir}}
  }}
{{refend}}

{{Bayern class battleship}}
{{1919 shipwrecks}}
{{1921 shipwrecks}}

{{coord|49|49|42|N|2|23|21|W|type:landmark_source:kolossus-dewiki|display=title}}
{{Featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Baden (1915)}}
[[Category:1915 ships]]
[[Category:Bayern-class battleships]]
[[Category:Ships sunk as targets]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1919]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1921]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks in the English Channel]]
[[Category:World War I battleships of Germany]]
[[Category:Ships built in Danzig]]
[[Category:World War I warships scuttled in Scapa Flow]]
[[Category:Ships built by Schichau]]</text>
      <sha1>5f5mt9739xy02qqp1m5anx79q4qzdk8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
