<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Texas Revolution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38711</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749134805</id>
      <parentid>740458354</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T17:02:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tassedethe</username>
        <id>7098284</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>v1.41 - Repaired 1 link to disambiguation page - [[WP:DPL|(You can help)]] - [[James W. Robinson]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="101458">{{pp-protect|small=yes}}
{{featured article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
 | conflict      = Texas Revolution
 | colour_scheme = background:#FFCC00
 | image         = [[File:Campaigns of the Texas Revolution.jpg|300px|upright]]
 | caption       = The campaigns of the Texas Revolution
 | date          = October 2, 1835 – April 21, 1836&lt;br&gt;({{Age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=10|day1=02|year1=1835|month2=04|day2=21|year2=1836}})
 | place         = [[Mexican Texas|Texas]]
 | result        = [[Treaties of Velasco]] and the formation of the [[Republic of Texas]]
 | territory     = ''[[De facto]]'' Texan independence from the centralist Republic of Mexico
 | combatant1    ={{flagdeco|Texas|size=23px}}   [[Republic of Texas]]
 | combatant2    = {{flagdeco|Mexico|1823|size=23px}} [[Centralist Republic of Mexico|Mexico]]
 | commander1    = [[Sam Houston]]{{WIA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[James Fannin]]{{KIA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Frank W. Johnson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Edward Burleson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Stephen F. Austin]]
 | commander2    = [[Antonio López de Santa Anna]]{{POW}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Vicente Filisola]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Martín Perfecto de Cos]]{{POW}}
 | strength1     = c. 2,000
 | strength2     = c. 6,500
 | casualties1   = 700 dead, 100 wounded
 | casualties2   = 1,000 dead, 500 wounded
 }}
{{Campaignbox Texas Revolution}}
{{History of Mexico |First Republic}}
{{Revolution sidebar}}

The '''Texas Revolution''' (October 2, 1835 – April 21, 1836) began when colonists (primarily from the United States) in the [[Mexican Texas|Mexican province of Texas]] rebelled against the increasingly [[centralized government|centralist]] [[Centralist Republic of Mexico|Mexican government]].  After a decade of political and cultural clashes between the Mexican government and the increasingly large population of American settlers in Texas, hostilities erupted in October 1835. [[Texians]] (English-speaking settlers) disagreed on whether the ultimate goal was independence or a return to the [[1824 Constitution of Mexico|Mexican Constitution of 1824]].  While delegates at the [[Consultation (Texas)|Consultation]] (provisional government) debated the war's motives, Texians and a flood of volunteers from the United States defeated the small garrisons of Mexican soldiers by mid-December 1835.

The Consultation declined to declare independence and installed an interim government, whose infighting led to political paralysis and a dearth of effective governance in Texas.  An ill-conceived proposal to [[Matamoros Expedition|invade Matamoros]] siphoned much-needed volunteers and provisions from the fledgling Texas army.  In March 1836, a second [[convention of 1836|political convention]] declared independence and appointed leadership for the new [[Republic of Texas]].

Determined to avenge Mexico's honor, President [[Antonio López de Santa Anna]] vowed to personally retake Texas.  His Army of Operations entered Texas in mid-February 1836 and found the Texians completely unprepared.  Mexican General [[José de Urrea]] led a contingent of troops on the [[Goliad Campaign]] up the Texas coast, defeating all Texian troops in his path and executing most of those who surrendered. Santa Anna led a larger force to [[San Antonio|San Antonio de Béxar]] (or Béxar), where his troops defeated the Texian garrison in the [[Battle of the Alamo]], killing almost all of the defenders.

For the next month, a newly created Texian army under the command of [[Sam Houston]] steadily retreated towards the border with Louisiana; terrified civilians fled with the army, in a melee known as the [[Runaway Scrape]]. On March 31, Houston paused his men at Groce's Landing on the [[Brazos River]], and for the next two weeks, the Texians received rigorous military training. Becoming complacent and underestimating the strength of his foes, Santa Anna further subdivided his troops. On April 21, Houston's army staged a surprise assault on Santa Anna and his vanguard force at the [[Battle of San Jacinto]]. The Mexican troops were quickly routed, and vengeful Texians executed many who tried to surrender.  Santa Anna was taken hostage; in exchange for his life, he ordered the Mexican army to retreat south of the [[Rio Grande]].  Mexico refused to recognize the Republic of Texas, and intermittent conflicts between the two countries continued into the 1840s.  The [[Texas annexation|annexation of Texas]] as the 28th state of the United States, in 1845, led directly to the [[Mexican–American War]].

==Background==
{{Main article|Mexican Texas}}
After a failed attempt by France to [[French colonization of Texas|colonize Texas]] in the late 17th century, Spain developed a plan to settle the region.&lt;ref&gt;Weber (1992), pp. 149–154.&lt;/ref&gt; On its southern edge, along the [[Medina River|Medina]] and [[Nueces River]]s, [[Spanish Texas]] was bordered by the province of [[Coahuila]].&lt;ref name=edmondson6&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;  On the east, Texas bordered [[Louisiana (New France)|Louisiana]].&lt;ref name=edmonson10&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;  Following the [[Louisiana Purchase]] of 1803, the United States also claimed the land west of the [[Sabine River (Texas–Louisiana)|Sabine River]], all the way to the Rio Grande.&lt;ref name=weber291&gt;Weber (1992), p. 291.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the United States officially renounced that claim as part of the [[Transcontinental Treaty]] with Spain in 1819,&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Spain did not ratify the treaty until February 1821, in the hopes that the delay would stop the Americans from recognizing Mexico as an independent country.  Weber (1992), p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt; many Americans continued to believe that Texas should belong to their nation,&lt;ref name=weber299and300&gt;Weber (1992), pp. 299–300.&lt;/ref&gt; and over the next decade the United States made several offers to purchase the region.&lt;ref name=lack5/&gt;

Following the [[Mexican War of Independence]], Texas became part of [[Mexico]].  Under the [[1824 Constitution of Mexico|Constitution of 1824]], which defined the country as a [[federal republic]], the provinces of Texas and Coahuila were combined to become the state [[Coahuila y Tejas]].&lt;ref group=Note&gt;For the purposes of this article, &quot;Texas&quot; refers to the area north of the Medina and Nueces Rivers and west of the Sabine River. &quot;Coahuila y Tejas&quot; comprises both Texas and the province of Coahuila. The &quot;Republic of Texas&quot; includes Texas and the land between the Nueces River and the Rio Grande.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=manchaca161and62&gt;Manchaca (2001), pp. 161–2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=vazquez51&gt;Vazquez (1997), p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; Texas was granted only a single seat in the state legislature, which met in [[Saltillo]], hundreds of miles away.&lt;ref name=davis63&gt;Davis (2006), p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmndson72&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; After months of grumbling by ''[[Tejano]]s'' (Mexican-born residents of Texas) outraged at the loss of their political autonomy, state officials agreed to make Texas a [[Department (country subdivision)|department]] of the new state, with a ''de facto'' capital in [[San Antonio|San Antonio de Béxar]].&lt;ref name=davis63&gt;Davis (2006), p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;

Texas was very sparsely populated, with fewer than 3,500 residents,&lt;ref group=Note&gt;This number excludes native tribes.&lt;/ref&gt; and only about 200 soldiers,&lt;ref name=edmondson75&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=weber162&gt;Weber (1992), p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt;  which made it extremely vulnerable to attacks by native tribes and American [[Filibuster (military)|filibusters]].&lt;ref name=weber161&gt;Weber (1992), p. 161.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the hopes that an influx of settlers could control the Indian raids, the bankrupt Mexican government liberalized immigration policies for the region.  Finally able to settle legally in Texas, [[Anglo#United States|Anglo]]s from the United States soon vastly outnumbered the ''Tejanos''.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;David Weber (1992), p. 166, states that in 1830, there were approximately 7,000 foreign-born residents and 3,000 Mexican-born residents. Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 4, states that there were 16,000 Anglos and only 4,000 Mexican-born residents in Texas in 1830.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=weber166&gt;Weber (1992), p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=manchaca164&gt;Manchaca (2001), p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the immigrants came from the [[southern United States]].  Many were slave owners, and most brought with them significant prejudices against other races, attitudes often applied to the ''Tejanos,''. Mexico's official religion was Roman Catholicism, yet the majority of the immigrants were Protestants who distrusted Catholics.&lt;ref name=&quot;davis60 and 64&quot;&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 60, 64.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mexico 1835-1846 administrative map-en-2.svg|350px|thumb|left|alt=A map of Mexico, showing state and territory divisions as of 1835.  Texas, Coahila, Nuevo León, Tamaulipas, Zacatecas and the Yucatán are shaded, marking them as having separatist movements.|A map of Mexico, 1835–1846, showing administrative divisions. The red areas show regions where separatist movements were active.]]
Mexican authorities became increasingly concerned about the stability of the region.&lt;ref name=lack5&gt;Lack (1992), p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;  The colonies teetered at the brink of revolt in 1829, after Mexico abolished slavery.&lt;ref name=edmondson80&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt;  In response, President [[Anastasio Bustamante]] implemented the [[Law of April 6, 1830|Laws of April 6, 1830]], which, among other things, prohibited further immigration to Texas from the United States, increased taxes, and reiterated the ban on slavery.&lt;ref name=manchaca200&gt;Manchaca (2001), p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; Settlers simply circumvented or ignored the laws. By 1834, an estimated 30,000 Anglos lived in Coahuila y Tejas,&lt;ref name=manchaca201&gt;Manchaca (2001), p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt; compared to only 7,800&amp;nbsp;Mexican-born residents.&lt;ref name=manchaca172&gt;Manchaca (2001), p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1832, [[Antonio López de Santa Anna]] led a revolt to overthrow Bustamante.&lt;ref name=davis78&gt;Davis (2006), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=winders20&gt;Winders (2004), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Texians]], or English-speaking settlers, used the rebellion as an excuse to take up arms.  By mid-August, all Mexican troops had been expelled from east Texas.&lt;ref name=davis89&gt;Davis (2006), p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;  Buoyed by their success, Texians held two political conventions to persuade Mexican authorities to weaken the Laws of April 6, 1830.&lt;ref name=davis92and95&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 92, 95.&lt;/ref&gt;  In November 1833 the Mexican government attempted to address some of the concerns, repealing some sections of the law and granting the colonists further concessions,&lt;ref name=&quot;davis110 and 117&quot;&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 110, 117.&lt;/ref&gt; including increased representation in the state legislature.&lt;ref name=vazquez69&gt;Vazquez (1997), p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Stephen F. Austin]], who had brought the first American settlers to Texas, wrote to a friend that &quot;Every evil complained of has been remedied.&quot;&lt;ref name=davis117&gt;Davis (2006), p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;  Mexican authorities were quietly watchful, concerned that the colonists were maneuvering towards secession.&lt;ref name=vazquez67&gt;Vazquez (1997), p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=davis120&gt;Davis (2006), p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

Santa Anna soon revealed himself to be a centralist, transitioning the Mexican government to a [[centralized government]].  In 1835, the 1824 Constitution was overturned; state legislatures were dismissed, militias disbanded.&lt;ref name=davis121&gt;Davis (2006), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin6&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;  Federalists throughout Mexico were appalled.  Citizens in the states of [[Oaxaca]] and [[Zacatecas]] took up arms.&lt;ref name=davis121/&gt;  After Santa Anna's troops subdued the rebellion in Zacatecas in May, he gave his troops two days to pillage the city; over 2,000 noncombatants were killed.&lt;ref name=hardin7&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;  The governor of Coahuila y Tejas, [[Agustín Viesca]], refused to dissolve the legislature, instead ordering that the session reconvene in Béxar, further from the influence of the Mexican army.&lt;ref name=davis122&gt;Davis (2006), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although prominent ''Tejano'' [[Juan Seguín]] raised a militia company to assist the governor, the Béxar ''ayuntamiento'' (city council) ordered him not to interfere,&lt;ref name=lack21and2&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 21–2.&lt;/ref&gt; and Viesca was arrested before he reached Texas.&lt;ref name=hardin23&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

Public opinion in Texas was divided.&lt;ref name=lack24through6&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 24–6.&lt;/ref&gt; Editorials in the United States began advocating complete independence for Texas.&lt;ref name=davis131&gt;Davis (2006), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; After several men staged a minor revolt against customs duties in [[Anahuac, Texas|Anahuac]] in June,&lt;ref name=lack25&gt;Lack (1992), p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; local leaders began calling for a public meeting to determine whether a majority of settlers favored independence, a return to federalism, or the status quo. Although some leaders worried that Mexican officials would see this type of gathering as a step towards revolution, by the end of August most communities had agreed to send delegates to the [[Consultation (Texas)|Consultation]], scheduled for October 15.&lt;ref name=lack31and32&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 31–2.&lt;/ref&gt;

As early as April 1835, military commanders in Texas began requesting reinforcements, fearing the citizens would revolt.&lt;ref name=lack20&gt;Lack (1992), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;  Mexico was ill-prepared for a large civil war,&lt;ref name=davis198&gt;Davis (2006), p. 198.&lt;/ref&gt; but continued unrest in Texas posed a significant danger to the power of Santa Anna and of Mexico.  If the people of Coahuila also took up arms,   Mexico faced losing a large portion of its territory.  Without the northeastern province to act as a buffer, it was likely that United States influence would spread, and the Mexican territories of [[Santa Fe de Nuevo México|Nuevo Mexico]] and [[Alta California]] would be at risk of future American encroachment.  Santa Anna had no wish to tangle with the United States, and he knew that the unrest needed to be subdued before the United States could be convinced to become involved.&lt;ref name=davis199&gt;Davis (2006), p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; In early September, Santa Anna ordered his brother-in-law, General [[Martín Perfecto de Cos]], to lead 500 soldiers to Texas to quell any potential rebellion. Cos and his men landed at the port of [[Copano, Texas|Copano]] on September 20.&lt;ref name=&quot;davis136and138&quot;&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 136, 138.&lt;/ref&gt;  Austin called on all municipalities to raise militias to defend themselves.&lt;ref name=davis133&gt;Davis (2006), p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Texian offensive: October–December 1835==

===Gonzales===
{{main article|Battle of Gonzales}}
[[File:Gonzales Flag.JPG|thumb|right|200px|alt=A white flag, with a five-pointed-star over the outline of a small cannon, with the words Come and Take It below.  The left corner of the flag has been torn off and sewn back on.|A reproduction of the original [[Come and take it]] flag, which flew during the [[battle of Gonzales]]]]
&lt;!--[[File:Texas Flag Come and Take It.svg|thumb|right|200px|Modern representation of the [[Come and take it]] flag Texians flew during the [[battle of Gonzales]]]] --&gt;

In the early 1830s, the army loaned the citizens of [[Gonzales, Texas|Gonzales]] a small cannon for protection against Indian raids.&lt;ref name=edmondson74&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;  After a Mexican soldier bludgeoned a Gonzales resident on September 10, 1835, tensions rose even further, and Mexican authorities felt it unwise to leave the settlers with a weapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;winders57&quot;&gt;Winders (2004), p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; Colonel [[Domingo de Ugartechea]], commander of all Mexican military forces in Texas, sent a small detachment of troops to retrieve the cannon.&lt;ref name=hardin7/&gt; After settlers escorted the group from town without the cannon, Ugartechea sent 100 [[dragoon]]s with Lieutenant [[Francisco de Castañeda]] to demand compliance, with orders to avoid force if possible.&lt;ref name=hardin7/&gt;&lt;ref name=davis138&gt;Davis (2006), p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the settlers believed Mexican authorities were manufacturing an excuse to attack the town and eliminate the militia.&lt;ref name=davis137&gt;Davis (2006), p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt; Texians stalled Castañeda's attempts to negotiate the cannon's return for several days as they waited for reinforcements from other colonies.&lt;ref name=davis139&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 139–40.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the early hours of October 2, approximately 140 Texian volunteers attacked Castañeda's force. After a brief skirmish, Castañeda requested a meeting with Texian leader [[John Henry Moore (Texas)|John Henry Moore]].  Castañeda revealed that he shared their federalist leanings, but that he was honor-bound to follow orders.  As Moore returned to camp, the Texians raised a homemade white banner with an image of the cannon painted in black in the center, over the words &quot;[[Come and take it|Come and Take It]]&quot;.  Realizing that he was outnumbered and outgunned, Castañeda led his troops back to Béxar.&lt;ref name=hardin12&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;  In this first battle of the revolution, two Mexican soldiers were killed, and one Texian was injured when he fell off his horse.&lt;ref name=davis142&gt;Davis (2006), p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the event was, as characterized by historian [[William C. Davis (historian)|William C. Davis]], &quot;an inconsequential skirmish in which one side did not try to fight&quot;, Texians soon declared it a victory over Mexican troops.&lt;ref name=davis142/&gt;  News of the skirmish spread throughout the United States, encouraging many adventurers to come to Texas to join the fight.&lt;ref name=hardin13&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

Volunteers continued to arrive in Gonzales. On October 11, the troops unanimously elected Austin, who had no official military experience, the leader of the group he had dubbed the [[Texian Army|Army of the People]].&lt;ref name=winders55&gt;Winders (2004), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin26&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;  From the beginning, the volunteer army proved to have little discipline.  Austin's first official order was to remind his men that they were expected to obey their commanding officers.&lt;ref name=winders55/&gt;  Buoyed by their victory, the Texians were determined to drive the Mexican army out of Texas, and they began preparing to march to Béxar.&lt;ref name=&quot;winders57&quot;/&gt;

===Gulf Coast campaign===
After learning that Texian troops had attacked Castañeda at Gonzales, Cos made haste for Béxar. Unaware of his departure, on October 6, Texians in Matagorda marched on [[Presidio La Bahía]] in [[Goliad, Texas|Goliad]] to kidnap him and steal the $50,000 that was rumored to accompany him.&lt;ref name=hardin14&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; On October 10, approximately 125 volunteers, including 30 ''Tejanos'', [[battle of Goliad|stormed the presidio]].  The Mexican garrison surrendered after a thirty-minute battle.&lt;ref name=hardin15thru17&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 15–7.&lt;/ref&gt; One or two Texians were wounded and three Mexican soldiers were killed with seven more wounded.&lt;ref name=davis148&gt;Davis (2006), p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texians established themselves in the presidio, under the command of Captain [[Philip Dimmitt]], who immediately sent all the local ''Tejano'' volunteers to join Austin on the march to Béxar.&lt;ref name=lack190&gt;Lack (1992), p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the month, Dimmitt sent a group of men under [[Ira Westover]] to engage the Mexican garrison at [[Fort Lipantitlán]], near [[San Patricio, Texas|San Patricio]].&lt;ref name=hardin42&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;  Late on November 3, the Texians took the undermanned fort without firing a shot.&lt;ref name=hardin44&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;  After dismantling the fort, they prepared to return to Goliad.  The remainder of the Mexican garrison, which had been out on patrol, approached.&lt;ref name=davis176&gt;Davis (2006), p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mexican troops were accompanied by 15–20 loyal centralists from San Patricio, including all members of the ''ayuntamiento''.&lt;ref name=lack157&gt;Lack (1992), p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt;  After a [[battle of Lipantitlán|thirty-minute skirmish]], the Mexican soldiers and Texian centralists retreated.&lt;ref name=hardin46&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; With their departure, the Texian army controlled the Gulf Coast, forcing Mexican commanders to send all communication with the Mexican interior overland. The slower land journey left Cos unable to quickly request or receive reinforcements or supplies.&lt;ref name=davis176&gt;Davis (2006), p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin17and19&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 17, 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

On their return to Goliad, Westover's group encountered Governor Viesca.  After being freed by sympathetic soldiers, Viesca had immediately traveled to Texas to recreate the state government.  Dimmitt welcomed Viesca but refused to recognize his authority as governor.  This caused an uproar in the garrison, as many supported the governor.  Dimmitt declared martial law and soon alienated most of the local residents.&lt;ref name=lack190and1&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 190–1.&lt;/ref&gt;  Over the next few months, the area between Goliad and [[Refugio, Texas|Refugio]] descended into civil war.  Goliad native [[Carlos de la Garza (Texas)|Carlos de la Garza]] led a guerrilla warfare campaign against the Texian troops.&lt;ref name=lack162to3&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 162–3.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to historian Paul Lack, the Texian &quot;antiguerilla tactics did too little to crush out opposition but quite enough to sway the uncommitted toward the centralists.&quot;&lt;ref name=lack162&gt;Lack (1992), p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Siege of Béxar===
{{main article|Siege of Béxar}}

While Dimmitt supervised the Texian forces along the Gulf Coast, Austin led his men towards Béxar to engage Cos and his troops.&lt;ref name=barr6&gt;Barr (1990), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Confident that they would quickly rout the Mexican troops, many Consultation delegates chose to join the military. Unable to reach a quorum, the Consultation was postponed until November 1.&lt;ref name=lack41&gt;Lack (1992), p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;  On October 16, the Texians paused {{convert|25|mi|km}} from Béxar.  Austin sent a messenger to Cos giving the requirements the Texians would need to lay down their arms and &quot;avoid the sad consequences of the Civil War which unfortunately threatens Texas&quot;.&lt;ref name=davis150and1&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 150–1.&lt;/ref&gt;  Cos replied that Mexico would not &quot;yield to the dictates of foreigners&quot;.&lt;ref name=davis151&gt;Davis (2006), p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Martin perfecto de cos.jpg|left|thumb|upright|alt=Black-and-white drawing of a man, shown from mid-chest up. He is wearing a military jacket with a high collar.|General [[Martín Perfecto de Cos]]]]
The approximately 650 Mexican troops quickly built barricades throughout the town.&lt;ref name=winders57&gt;Winders (2004), p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=davis152&gt;Davis (2006), p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt;  Within days the Texian army, about 450 strong, initiated a [[siege of Béxar]],&lt;ref name=davis152/&gt; and gradually moved their camp nearer Béxar.&lt;ref name=barr19&gt;Barr (1990), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;  On October 27, an advance party led by [[James Bowie]] and [[James Fannin]] chose [[Mission Concepción]] as the next campsite and sent for the rest of the Texian army.&lt;ref name=barr22&gt;Barr (1990), p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;  On learning that the Texians were temporarily divided, Ugartechea led troops to engage Bowie and Fannin's men.&lt;ref name=barr23&gt;Barr (1990), p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mexican cavalry was unable to fight effectively in the wooded, riverbottom terrain, and the weapons of the Mexican infantry had a much shorter range than those of the Texians.&lt;ref name=barr26&gt;Barr (1990), p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;  After three Mexican infantry attacks were repulsed, Ugartechea called for a retreat.&lt;ref name=hardin33&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;  One Texian soldier had died, and between 14 and 76 Mexican soldiers were killed.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Barr (1990), p. 26. claims 14 Mexican soldiers died.  Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 23. estimated 60 Mexican casualties.  Hardin (1994), p. 34. claims 76 Mexican soldiers died.&lt;/ref&gt; Although [[Texas Tech University]] [[professor emeritus]] [[Alwyn Barr]] noted that the [[battle of Concepción]] &quot;should have taught&amp;nbsp;... lessons on Mexican courage and the value of a good defensive position&quot;,&lt;ref name=barr60&gt;Barr (1990), p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; Texas history expert [[Stephen Hardin]] believes that &quot;the relative ease of the victory at Concepción instilled in the Texians a reliance on their long rifles and a contempt for their enemies&quot;.&lt;ref name=hardin35&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the weather turned colder and rations grew smaller, groups of Texians began to leave, most without permission.&lt;ref name=barr29&gt;Barr (1990), p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; Morale was boosted on November 18, when the first group of volunteers from the United States, the [[New Orleans Greys]], joined the Texian army.&lt;ref name=barr35&gt;Barr (1990), p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin60&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the majority of the Texian volunteers, the Greys looked like soldiers, with uniforms, well-maintained rifles, adequate ammunition, and some semblance of discipline.&lt;ref name=hardin60/&gt;

After Austin resigned his command to become a commissioner to the United States, soldiers elected [[Edward Burleson]] as their new commander.&lt;ref name=hardin62&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;  On November 26, Burleson received word that a Mexican [[packhorse|pack train]] of mules and horses, accompanied by 50–100&amp;nbsp;Mexican soldiers, was within {{convert|5|mi|km}} of Béxar.&lt;ref name=barr39&gt;Barr (1990), p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin64&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; After a near mutiny, Burleson sent Bowie and William H. Jack with cavalry and infantry to intercept the supplies.&lt;ref name=hardin64/&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson237&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt; In the subsequent skirmish, the Mexican forces were forced to retreat to Béxar, leaving their cargo behind. To the disappointment of the Texians, the saddlebags contained only fodder for the horses; for this reason the battle was later known as the [[Grass Fight]].&lt;ref name=edmondson238&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 238.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the victory briefly uplifted the Texian troops, morale continued to fall as the weather turned colder and the men grew bored.&lt;ref name=edmondson224&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 224.&lt;/ref&gt;  After several proposals to take Béxar by force were voted down by the Texian troops,&lt;ref name=davis179and181&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 179, 181.&lt;/ref&gt; on December 4 Burleson proposed that the army lift the siege and retreat to Goliad until spring.  In a last effort to avoid a retreat, Colonel [[Ben Milam]] personally recruited units to participate in an attack.  The following morning, Milam and Colonel [[Frank W. Johnson]] led several hundred Texians into the city.  Over the next four days, Texians fought their way from house to house towards the fortified plazas near the center of town.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Milam was killed by a sharpshooter on December 7. Edmondson (2000), p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson243&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt;

Cos received 650 reinforcements on December 8,&lt;ref name=winders64&gt;Winders (2004), p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; but to his dismay most of them were raw recruits, including many convicts still in chains.&lt;ref name=todish26/&gt;  Instead of being helpful, the reinforcements were mainly a drain on the dwindling food supplies.&lt;ref name=winders64/&gt;  Seeing few other options, on December 9, Cos and the bulk of his men withdrew into the [[Alamo Mission]] on the outskirts of Béxar. Cos presented a plan for a counterattack; cavalry officers believed that they would be surrounded by Texians and refused their orders.&lt;ref name=barr55&gt;Barr (1990), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Possibly 175 soldiers from four of the cavalry companies left the mission and rode south; Mexican officers later claimed the men misunderstood their orders and were not deserting.&lt;ref name=todish26&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; The following morning, Cos surrendered.&lt;ref name=barr56&gt;Barr (1990), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;  Under the terms of the surrender, Cos and his men would leave Texas and no longer fight against supporters of the Constitution of 1824.&lt;ref name=barr58&gt;Barr (1990), p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; With his departure, there was no longer an organized garrison of Mexican troops in Texas,&lt;ref name=barr64&gt;Barr (1990), p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; and many of the Texians believed that the war was over.&lt;ref name=hardin91&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; Burleson resigned his leadership of the army on December 15 and returned to his home. Many of the men did likewise, and Johnson assumed command of the 400 soldiers who remained.&lt;ref name=barr58/&gt;&lt;ref name=todish29/&gt;

According to Barr, the large number of American volunteers in Béxar &quot;contributed to the Mexican view that Texan opposition stemmed from outside influences&quot;.&lt;ref name=barr63&gt;Barr (1990), p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; In reality, of the 1,300 men who volunteered to fight for the Texian army in October and November 1835, only 150–200 arrived from the United States after October 2. The rest were residents of Texas with an average immigration date of 1830.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;If those who arrived after the battle of Gonzales are included, the average immigration date is 1832. Lack (1992), pp. 114–5.&lt;/ref&gt; Volunteers came from every municipality, including those that were partially occupied by Mexican forces.&lt;ref name=lack114and5&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 114–5.&lt;/ref&gt; However, as residents returned to their homes following Cos's surrender, the Texian army composition changed dramatically.  Of the volunteers serving from January through March 1836, 78 percent had arrived from the United States after October 2, 1835.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;These numbers are gathered from a combination of surviving muster rolls and veteran applications for land grants.  It is likely that the statistics on the Texian army size in both 1835 and 1836 underestimate the number of ''Tejanos'' who served in the army.  American volunteers who returned to the U.S. without claiming land are also undercounted.  Lack (1992), p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lack122and3&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 122–3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Regrouping: November 1835&amp;nbsp;– February 1836==

===Texas Consultation and the Matamoros Expedition===
The Consultation finally convened on November 3 in [[San Felipe de Austin|San Felipe]] with 58 of the 98 elected delegates.&lt;ref name=lack43and3&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 43–4.&lt;/ref&gt;  After days of bitter debate, the delegates voted to create a provisional government based on the principles of the Constitution of 1824.  Although they did not declare independence, the delegates insisted they would not rejoin Mexico until federalism had been reinstated.&lt;ref name=lack49&gt;Lack (1992), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;  The new government would consist of a governor and a General Council, with one representative from each municipality.  Under the assumption that these two branches would cooperate, there was no [[Separation of powers|system of checks and balances]].&lt;ref name=lack50and1&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 50–1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=todish24&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 13, delegates voted to create a [[regular army]] and named [[Sam Houston]] its commander-in-chief.&lt;ref name=lack51/&gt; In an effort to attract volunteers from the United States, soldiers would be granted land bounties.  This provision was significant, as all public land was owned by the state or the federal government, indicating that the delegates expected Texas to eventually declare independence.&lt;ref name=davis167&gt;Davis (2006), p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt;  Houston was given no authority over the volunteer army led by Austin, which predated the Consultation.&lt;ref name=lack51&gt;Lack (1992), p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;  Houston was also appointed to the Select Committee on Indian Affairs.  Three men, including Austin, were asked to go to the United States to gather money, volunteers, and supplies.&lt;ref name=todish24/&gt;  The delegates elected [[Henry Smith (Texas Governor)|Henry Smith]] as governor.&lt;ref name=winders72&gt;Winders (2004), p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;   On November 14, the Consultation adjourned, leaving Smith and the Council in charge.&lt;ref name=lack52&gt;Lack (1992), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;

The new Texas government had no funds, so the military was granted the authority to impress supplies.  This policy soon resulted in an almost universal hatred of the Council, as food and supplies became scarce, especially in the areas around Goliad and Béxar, where Texian troops were stationed.&lt;ref name=lack54&gt;Lack (1992), p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;  Few of the volunteers agreed to join Houston's regular army.&lt;ref name=lack55&gt;Lack (1992), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;  The ''[[Telegraph and Texas Register]]'' noted that &quot;some are not willing, under the present government, to do any duty ... That our government is bad, all acknowledge, and no one will deny.&quot;&lt;ref name=lack74&gt;Lack (1992), p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

Leaders in Texas continued to debate whether the army was fighting for independence or a return to federalism.&lt;ref name=lack55&gt;Lack (1992), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;  On December 22, Texian soldiers stationed at La Bahía issued the [[Goliad Declaration of Independence]].&lt;ref name=lack56&gt;Lack (1992), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; Unwilling to decide the matter themselves, the Council called for another election, for delegates to the [[Convention of 1836]].  The Council specifically noted that all free white males could vote, as well as Mexicans who did not support centralism.&lt;ref name=lack45and57&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 56–7.&lt;/ref&gt;  Smith tried to veto the latter requirement, as he believed even ''Tejanos'' with federalist leanings should be denied suffrage.&lt;ref name=lack77&gt;Lack (1992), p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;

Leading federalists in Mexico, including former governor Viesca, [[Lorenzo de Zavala]], and [[José Antonio Mexía]], were advocating a plan to attack centralist troops in [[Matamoros, Tamaulipas|Matamoros]].&lt;ref name=todish27&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;  Council members were taken with the idea of a [[Matamoros Expedition]].  They hoped it would inspire other federalist states to revolt and keep the bored Texian troops from deserting the army.  Most importantly, it would move the war zone outside Texas.&lt;ref name=winders78&gt;Winders (2004), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; The Council officially approved the plan on December 25, and on December 30 Johnson and his aide Dr. [[James Grant (Texas)|James Grant]] took the bulk of the army and almost all of the supplies to Goliad to prepare for the expedition.&lt;ref name=todish29&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;  Historian Stuart Reid posits that Grant was a British secret agent, and that his plan to take Matamoros, and thus tie Texas more tightly to Mexico, may have been an unofficial scheme to advance British interests in the region.&lt;ref name=reid70&gt;Reid (2007), p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;As of March 2015, no other historian has examined Reid's theory in detail.  The [[Texas State Historical Association]]'s article on Grant was written by Reid and includes mention of this theory.&lt;/ref&gt;

Petty bickering between Smith and the Council members increased dramatically, and on January 9, 1836, Smith threatened to dismiss the Council unless they agreed to revoke their approval of the Matamoros Expedition.&lt;ref name=lack59to60&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 59–60.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=winders90&gt;Winders (2004), p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;  Two days later the Council voted to impeach Smith and named [[James W. Robinson (Texas and California)|James W. Robinson]] the Acting Governor.&lt;ref name=lack60&gt;Lack (1992), p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; It was unclear whether either side actually had the authority to dismiss the other.&lt;ref name=hardin109&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;  By this point, Texas was essentially in anarchy.&lt;ref name=lack62&gt;Lack (1992), p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

Under orders from Smith, Houston successfully dissuaded all but 70 men from continuing to follow Johnson.&lt;ref name=hardin109through11&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 109–11.&lt;/ref&gt;  With his own authority in question following Smith's impeachment, Houston washed his hands of the army and journeyed to [[Nacogdoches, Texas|Nacogdoches]] to negotiate a treaty with [[Cherokee]] leaders.  Houston vowed that Texas would recognize Cherokee claims to land in East Texas as long as the Indians refrained from attacking settlements or assisting the Mexican army.&lt;ref name=scott68&gt;Scott (2000), p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;  In his absence, Fannin, as the highest-ranking officer active in the regular army, led the men who did not want to go to Matamoros to Goliad.&lt;ref name=stuart68-70&gt;Stuart (2008), pp. 68–70.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Council had neglected to provide specific instructions on how to structure the February vote for convention delegates, leaving it up to each municipality to determine how to balance the desires of the established residents against those of the volunteers newly arrived from the United States.&lt;ref name=lack76and7&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 76–7.&lt;/ref&gt;  Chaos ensued; in Nacogdoches, the election judge turned back a company of 40 volunteers from Kentucky who had arrived that week.  The soldiers drew their weapons; Colonel [[Sidney Sherman]] announced that he &quot;had come to Texas to fight for it and had as soon commence in the town of Nacogdoches as elsewhere&quot;.&lt;ref name=lack79&gt;Lack (1992), p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt;  Eventually, the troops were allowed to vote.&lt;ref name=lack79/&gt; With rumors that Santa Anna was preparing a large army to advance into Texas, rhetoric degenerated into framing the conflict as a race war between Anglos defending their property against, in the words of [[David G. Burnet]], a &quot;mongrel race of degenerate Spaniards and Indians more depraved than they&quot;.&lt;ref name=lack86&gt;Lack (1992), p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mexican Army of Operations===

[[File:Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna 1852.jpg|thumb|right|upright|alt=A lithograph showing the bust of a clean-shaven man.  He is in military dress uniform with one medal around his neck and several others pinned at his shoulder.|[[Antonio López de Santa Anna]]]]
News of the armed uprising at Gonzales reached Santa Anna on October 23.&lt;ref name=davis199/&gt;  Aside from the ruling elite and members of the army, few in Mexico knew or cared about the revolt.  Those with knowledge of the events blamed the Anglos for their unwillingness to conform to the laws and culture of their new country.  Anglo immigrants had forced a war on Mexico, and Mexican honor insisted that the usurpers be defeated.&lt;ref name=davis197&gt;Davis (2006), p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt;  Santa Anna transferred his presidential duties to [[Miguel Barragán]] in order to personally lead troops to put an end to the Texian revolt. Santa Anna and his soldiers believed that the Texians would be quickly cowed.&lt;ref name=hardin98/&gt; The Mexican Secretary of War, [[José María Tornel]], wrote: &quot;The superiority of the Mexican soldier over the mountaineers of Kentucky and the hunters of Missouri is well known. Veterans seasoned by 20&amp;nbsp;years of wars can't be intimidated by the presence of an army ignorant of the art of war, incapable of discipline, and renowned for insubordination.&quot;&lt;ref name=hardin98&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt;

At this time, there were only 2,500 soldiers in the Mexican interior.  This was not enough to crush a rebellion and provide security—from attacks by both Indians and federalists—throughout the rest of the country.&lt;ref name=davis200&gt;Davis (2006), p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt;  With funds loaned by the Roman Catholic Church specifically to finance the war in Texas,&lt;ref name=scott70&gt;Scott (2000), p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Anna began to assemble a new army, which he dubbed the Army of Operations in Texas.  A majority of the troops had been [[conscript]]ed or were convicts who chose service in the military over jail.&lt;ref name=todish20&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mexican officers knew that the [[Brown Bess]] muskets they carried lacked the range of the Texian weapons, but Santa Anna was convinced that his superior planning would nonetheless result in an easy victory. Corruption was rampant, and supplies were not plentiful.  Almost from the beginning, rations were short, and there were no medical supplies or doctors. Few troops were issued heavy coats or blankets for the winter.&lt;ref name=scott73and74&gt;Scott (2000), pp. 73–4.&lt;/ref&gt;

In late December, at Santa Anna's behest, the Mexican Congress passed the [[Tornel Decree]], declaring that any foreigners fighting against Mexican troops &quot;will be deemed pirates and dealt with as such, being citizens of no nation presently at war with the Republic and fighting under no recognized flag.&quot;&lt;ref name=scott71&gt;Scott (2000), p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the early nineteenth century, captured pirates were executed immediately. The resolution thus gave the Mexican army permission to take no prisoners in the war against the Texians.&lt;ref name=scott71/&gt; This information was not widely distributed, and it is unlikely that most of the American recruits serving in the Texian army were aware that there would be no [[prisoner of war|prisoners-of-war]].&lt;ref name=scott75&gt;Scott (2000), p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;

By December 1835, 6,019&amp;nbsp;soldiers had begun their march towards Texas.&lt;ref name=hardin102&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; Progress was slow. There were not enough mules to transport all of the supplies, and many of the [[teamster]]s, all civilians, quit when their pay was delayed. The large number of ''[[soldaderas]]''—women and children who followed the army—reduced the already scarce supplies.&lt;ref name=hardin103&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; In Saltillo, Cos and his men from Béxar joined Santa Anna's forces.&lt;ref name=davis211&gt;Davis (2006), p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt;  Santa Anna regarded Cos's promise not to take up arms in Texas as meaningless because it had been given to rebels.&lt;ref name=hardin120&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

From Saltillo, the army had three choices: advance along the coast on the Atascocita Road from Matamoros to Goliad, or march on Béxar from the south, along the Laredo road, or from the west, along the [[El Camino Real de los Tejas National Historic Trail|Camino Real]].&lt;ref name=davis205and11&gt;Davis (2006), pp. 205, 211.&lt;/ref&gt; Santa Anna ordered General [[José de Urrea]] to lead 550 troops to Goliad.&lt;ref name=hardin120/&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin121&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; Although several of Santa Anna's officers argued that the entire army should advance along the coast, where supplies could be gained via sea,&lt;ref name=hardin102/&gt; Santa Anna instead focused on Béxar, the political center of Texas and the site of Cos's defeat.&lt;ref name=hardin102/&gt;  His brother-in-law's surrender was seen as a blow to the honor of his family and to Mexico; Santa Anna was determined to restore both.&lt;ref name=scott70/&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin102/&gt;  Santa Anna may also have thought Béxar would be easier to defeat, as his spies had informed him that most of the Texian army was along the coast, preparing for the Matamoros Expedition.&lt;ref name=davis212&gt;Davis (2006), p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt;  Santa Anna led the bulk of his men up the Camino Real to approach Béxar from the west, confounding the Texians, who had expected any advancing troops to approach from the south.&lt;ref name=todish34and36&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), pp. 34–6.&lt;/ref&gt;  On February 17, they crossed the Nueces River, officially entering Texas.&lt;ref name=davis212/&gt;

Temperatures reached record lows, and by February 13 an estimated {{convert|15|-|16|in|cm}} of snow had fallen. A large number of the new recruits were from the tropical climate of the [[Yucatán Peninsula|Yucatán]] and had been unable to acclimate to the harsh winter conditions. Some of them died of [[hypothermia]],&lt;ref&gt;Calore (2014), p. 57&lt;/ref&gt; and others contracted [[dysentery]]. Soldiers who fell behind were sometimes killed by [[Comanche]] raiding parties.&lt;ref name=hardin105&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the army continued to march towards Béxar. As they progressed, settlers in their path in [[South Texas]] evacuated northward. The Mexican army ransacked and occasionally burned the vacant homes.&lt;ref name=scott77&gt;Scott (2000), p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;  Santa Anna and his commanders received timely intelligence on Texian troop locations, strengths, and plans, from a network of ''Tejano'' spies organized by de la Garza.&lt;ref name=scott91&gt;Scott (2000), p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Santa Anna's offensive: February–March 1836==

===Alamo===
{{Main article|Battle of the Alamo}}
[[File:1847 watercolor of The Alamo in San Antonio.jpg|left|thumb|alt=The front of a brick building; the top of the building appears torn off.  Around the arched doorway are four niches, now empty.  There are two small square windows.|The [[Alamo Mission]], painted 10 years after the battle]]
&lt;!--[[File:Alamo pano.jpg|left|thumb|The [[Alamo Mission]] in modern times.  The distinctive bell-shaped facade was added decades after the battle.]]--&gt;
Fewer than 100 Texian soldiers remained at the Alamo Mission in Béxar, under the command of Colonel [[James C. Neill]].&lt;ref name=todish29/&gt;  Unable to spare the number of men necessary to mount a successful defense of the sprawling facility,&lt;ref name=edmondson252&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 252.&lt;/ref&gt; in January Houston sent Bowie with 30 men to remove the artillery  and destroy the complex.&lt;ref name=todish31&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Houston's orders to Bowie were vague, and historians disagree on their intent. An alternate interpretation is that Bowie's orders were to destroy only the barricades that the Mexican army had erected around San Antonio de Béxar, and that he should then wait in the Alamo until Governor Henry Smith decided whether the mission should be demolished and the artillery removed. Smith never gave orders on this issue. Edmondson (2000), p. 252.&lt;/ref&gt; In a letter to Governor Smith, Bowie argued that &quot;the salvation of Texas depends in great measure on keeping Béxar out of the hands of the enemy. It serves as the frontier [[picket (military)|picquet]] guard, and if it were in the possession of Santa Anna, there is no stronghold from which to repel him in his march towards the Sabine.&quot;&lt;ref name=todish31/&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The [[Sabine River (Texas-Louisiana)|Sabine River]] marked the eastern border of Mexican Texas.&lt;/ref&gt; The letter to Smith ended, &quot;Colonel Neill and myself have come to the solemn resolution that we will rather die in these ditches than give it up to the enemy.&quot;&lt;ref name=todish31/&gt; Few reinforcements were authorized; cavalry officer [[William B. Travis]] arrived in Béxar with 30&amp;nbsp;men on February 3 and five days later, a small group of volunteers arrived, including the famous frontiersman [[Davy Crockett]].&lt;ref name=hardin117&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; On February 11, Neill left to recruit additional reinforcements and gather supplies.&lt;ref name=todish32&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;  In his absence, Travis and Bowie shared command.&lt;ref name=hardin120&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

When scouts brought word on February 23 that the Mexican advance guard was in sight, the unprepared Texians gathered what food they could find in town and fell back to the Alamo.&lt;ref name=hardin121/&gt;  By late afternoon, Béxar was occupied by about 1,500 Mexican troops, who quickly raised a blood-red flag signifying [[no quarter]].&lt;ref name=todish40&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; For the next 13 days, the Mexican army [[Siege of the Alamo|besieged the Alamo]]. Several small skirmishes gave the defenders much-needed optimism, but had little real impact.&lt;ref name=todish42and43&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), pp. 42–3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edmondson325&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 325.&lt;/ref&gt;  Bowie fell ill on February 24, leaving Travis in sole command of the Texian forces.&lt;ref name=hardin129&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt;  The same day, Travis sent messengers with a letter [[To the People of Texas &amp; All Americans in the World]], begging for reinforcements and vowing &quot;victory or death&quot;; this letter was reprinted throughout the United States and much of Europe.&lt;ref name=todish42and43/&gt;  Texian and American volunteers began to gather in Gonzales, waiting for Fannin to arrive and lead them to reinforce the Alamo.&lt;ref name=hardin133&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt;  After days of indecision, on February 26 Fannin prepared to march his 300 troops to the Alamo; they turned back the next day, having traveled less than {{convert|1|mi|km}}.&lt;ref&gt;Scott (2000), pp. 91–101.&lt;/ref&gt;  Fewer than 100 Texian reinforcements reached the fort.&lt;ref name=edmondson340&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 340.&lt;/ref&gt;

Approximately 1,000 Mexican reinforcements arrived on March 3.&lt;ref name=edmondson349&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 349.&lt;/ref&gt;  The following day, a local woman, likely Bowie's relative [[Juana Navarro Alsbury]], was rebuffed by Santa Anna when she attempted to negotiate a surrender for the Alamo defenders.&lt;ref name=edmondson355&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 355.&lt;/ref&gt; This visit increased Santa Anna's impatience, and he scheduled an assault for early on March 6.&lt;ref name=todish49&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;  Many of his officers were against the plan; they preferred to wait until the artillery had further damaged the Alamo's walls and the defenders were forced to surrender.&lt;ref name=hardin136&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;  Santa Anna was convinced that a decisive victory would improve morale and sound a strong message to those still agitating in the interior and elsewhere in Texas.&lt;ref name=davis220&gt;Davis (2006), p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:FalloftheAlamo.jpg|thumb|''The Fall of the Alamo'' depicts [[Davy Crockett]] swinging his rifle at Mexican troops who have breached the south gate of the mission.]]
In the early hours of March 6, the Mexican army attacked the fort.&lt;ref name=hardin138&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; Troops from Béxar were excused from the front lines, so that they would not be forced to fight their families and friends.&lt;ref name=todish49/&gt;  In the initial moments of the assault the Mexican troops were at a disadvantage. Although their column formation allowed only the front rows of soldiers to fire safely, inexperienced recruits in the back also discharged their weapons; many Mexican soldiers were unintentionally killed by their own comrades.&lt;ref name=todish52&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;  As Mexican soldiers swarmed over the walls, at least 80 Texians fled the Alamo and were cut down by Mexican cavalry.&lt;ref name=davis223&gt;Davis (2006), p. 223.&lt;/ref&gt; Within an hour, almost all of the [[List of Alamo defenders|Texian defenders]], estimated at 182–257 men, were killed.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Brigido Guerrero convinced the Mexican army he had been imprisoned by the Texians. Joe, the slave of Alamo commander [[William B. Travis]], was spared because he was a slave. Some historians also believe that Henry Warnell hid during the battle, although he may have been a courier who left before the battle began. He died several months after the battle of wounds incurred during his escape. See Edmondson (2000), pp. 372, 407.&lt;/ref&gt;  Between four and seven Texians, possibly including Crockett, surrendered.  Although General [[Manuel Fernández Castrillón]] attempted to intercede on their behalf, Santa Anna insisted that the prisoners be executed immediately.&lt;ref name=hardin148&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most Alamo historians agree that 400–600&amp;nbsp;Mexicans were killed or wounded.&lt;ref name=todish55&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin155&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; This would represent about one-third of the Mexican soldiers involved in the final assault, which historian Timothy Todish remarks is &quot;a tremendous casualty rate by any standards&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;todish55&quot;/&gt;  The battle was militarily insignificant, but had an enormous political impact. Travis had succeeded in buying time for the Convention of 1836, scheduled for March 1, to meet.  If Santa Anna had not paused in Béxar for two weeks, he would have reached San Felipe by March 2 and very likely would have captured the delegates or caused them to flee.&lt;ref name=davis229&gt;Davis (2006), p. 229.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[List of Texian survivors of the Battle of the Alamo|The survivors]], primarily women and children, were questioned by Santa Anna and then released.&lt;ref name=todish55/&gt;   [[Susanna Dickinson]] was sent with Travis's slave Joe to Gonzales, where she lived, to spread the news of the Texian defeat.  Santa Anna assumed that knowledge of the disparity in troop numbers and the fate of the Texian soldiers at the Alamo would quell the resistance,&lt;ref name=edmondson378&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 378.&lt;/ref&gt; and that Texian soldiers would quickly leave the territory.&lt;ref name=hardin158&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Goliad Campaign===
{{Main article|Goliad Campaign}}
Urrea reached Matamoros on January 31.  A committed federalist himself, he soon convinced other federalists in the area that the Texians' ultimate goal was secession and their attempt to spark a federalist revolt in Matamoros was just a method of diverting attention from themselves.&lt;ref name=reid122&gt;Reid (2007), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt;  Mexican double agents continued to assure Johnson and Grant that they would be able to take Matamoros easily.&lt;ref name=reid131&gt;Reid (2007), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;  While Johnson waited in San Patricio with a small group of men, Grant and between 26 and 53 others roamed the area between the Nueces River and Matamoros.&lt;ref name=reid141&gt;Reid (2007), pp. 141–3.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although they were ostensibly searching for more horses, it is likely Grant was also attempting to contact his sources in Matamoros to further coordinate an attack.&lt;ref name=reid133&gt;Reid (2007), p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt;

Just after midnight on February 27, Urrea's men [[battle of San Patricio|surprised Johnson's forces]].  Six Texians, including Johnson, escaped; the remainder were captured or killed.&lt;ref name=stuart84&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;  After learning of Grant's whereabouts from local spies,  Mexican dragoons ambushed the Texians [[battle of Agua Dulce|at Agua Dulce Creek]] on March 2.&lt;ref name=reid142&gt;Reid (2007), p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;  Twelve Texians were killed, including Grant, four were captured, and six escaped.&lt;ref name=stuart87&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although Urrea's orders were to execute those captured, he instead sent them to Matamoros as prisoners.&lt;ref name=stuart88&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:La Bahia Presidio Chapel, South on U.S. Route 183, Goliad (Goliad County, Texas).jpg|thumb|right|alt=A large stone complex, several stories high.  Two crosses top the structures in the foreground.|[[Presidio La Bahía]], also known as Fort Defiance, in Goliad]]
On March 11, Fannin sent Captain [[Amon B. King]] to help evacuate settlers from the mission in Refugio. King and his men instead spent a day searching local ranches for centralist sympathizers.  They returned to the mission on March 12 and were soon besieged by Urrea's advance guard and de la Garza's [[Victoriana Guardes]].&lt;ref name=stuart91&gt;Stuart (2008), pp. 91–2.&lt;/ref&gt;  That same day, Fannin received orders from Houston to destroy Presidio La Bahía (by then renamed Fort Defiance) and march to Victoria. Unwilling to leave any of his men behind, Fannin sent [[William Ward (Texas)|William Ward]] with 120 men to help King's company.&lt;ref&gt;Reid (2007), pp. 93–4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Davis (2006), p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;  Ward's men drove off the troops besieging the church, but rather than return to Goliad, they delayed a day to conduct further raids on local ranches.&lt;ref&gt;Stuart (2008), pp. 95–6.&lt;/ref&gt;

Urrea arrived with almost 1,000 troops on March 14.&lt;ref&gt;Reid (2007), p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt;  At the [[battle of Refugio]], an engagement markedly similar to the battle of Concepción, the Texians repulsed several attacks and inflicted heavy casualties, relying on the greater accuracy and range of their rifles.&lt;ref&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 165.&lt;/ref&gt;  By the end of the day, the Texians were hungry, thirsty, tired, and almost out of ammunition.&lt;ref&gt;Reid (2007), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt;  Ward ordered a retreat, and under cover of darkness and rain the Texian soldiers slipped through Mexican lines, leaving several severely wounded men behind.&lt;ref name=stuart103and4&gt;Stuart (2008), pp. 103–4.&lt;/ref&gt;  Over the next several days, Urrea's men, with the help of local centralist supporters, rounded up many of the Texians who had escaped.  Most were executed, although Urrea pardoned a few after their wives begged for their lives, and  Mexican Colonel [[Juan José Holzinger]] insisted that all of the non-Americans be spared.&lt;ref name=stuart103and4/&gt;

By the end of the day on March 16, the bulk of Urrea's forces began marching to Goliad to corner Fannin.&lt;ref&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;  Still waiting for word from King and Ward, Fannin continued to delay his evacuation from Goliad.&lt;ref name=&quot;hardin166&quot;/&gt;  As they prepared to leave on March 18, Urrea's advance guard arrived.  For the rest of the day, the two cavalries skirmished aimlessly, succeeding only in exhausting the Texian oxen, which had remained hitched to their wagons with no food or water throughout the day.&lt;ref&gt;Scott (2000), p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texians began their retreat on March 19.  The pace was unhurried, and after travelling only {{convert|4|mi|km}}, the group stopped for an hour to rest and allow the oxen to graze.&lt;ref name=hardin166&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;  Urrea's troops caught up to the Texians later that afternoon, while Fannin and his force of about 300 men were crossing a prairie.&lt;ref name=stuart122&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt;  Having learned from the fighting at Refugio, Urrea was determined that the Texians would not reach the cover of timber approximately {{convert|1.5|mi|km}} ahead, along Coleto Creek.&lt;ref name=hardin168&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt;  As Mexican forces surrounded them, the Texians formed a tight hollow square for defense.&lt;ref name=stuart122/&gt;  They repulsed three charges during this [[battle of Coleto]], resulting in about nine Texians killed and 51 wounded, including Fannin. Urrea lost 50 men, with another 140 wounded.  Texians had little food, no water, and declining supplies of ammunition, but voted to not try to break for the timber, as they would have had to leave the wounded behind.&lt;ref name=hardin171&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt;

The following morning, March 20, Urrea paraded his men and his newly arrived artillery.&lt;ref name=stuart148&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;  Seeing the hopelessness of their situation, the Texians with Fannin surrendered.  Mexican records show that the Texians [[Unconditional surrender#Surrender at discretion|surrendered at discretion]]; Texian accounts claim that Urrea promised the Texians would be treated as prisoners-of-war and granted passage to the United States.&lt;ref name=stuart143to6&gt;Stuart (2008), pp. 143–6.&lt;/ref&gt;  Two days later, a group of Urrea's men surrounded Ward and the last of his group less than {{convert|1|mi|km}} from Victoria.  Over Ward's vehement objections, his men voted to surrender, later recalling they were told they would be sent back to the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Scott (2000), pp. 164–6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt;

On [[Palm Sunday]], March 27, Fannin, Ward, Westover, and their men were marched out of the presidio and shot.  Mexican cavalry were stationed nearby to chase down any who tried to escape.&lt;ref name=hardin173&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately 342 Texians died,&lt;ref name=hardin174&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt; and 27 either escaped or were spared by Mexican troops.&lt;ref name=stuart188&gt;Stuart (2008), p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt;   Several weeks after the [[Goliad massacre]], the Mexican Congress granted an official reprieve to any Texas prisoners who had incurred capital punishment.&lt;ref name=vazquez314&gt;Vazquez (1985), p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Texas Convention of 1836===
The Convention of 1836 in [[Washington-on-the-Brazos, Texas|Washington-on-the-Brazos]] on March 1 attracted 45 delegates, representing 21 municipalities.&lt;ref name=davis231&gt;Davis (2006), p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt;  Within an hour of the convention's opening, [[George C. Childress]] submitted a proposed [[Texas Declaration of Independence]], which passed overwhelmingly on March 2.&lt;ref name=lack86/&gt;&lt;ref name=lack87&gt;Lack (1992), p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;  On March 6, hours after the Alamo had fallen, Travis's final dispatch arrived.  His distress was evident; delegate [[Robert Potter (U.S. politician)|Robert Potter]] immediately moved that the convention be adjourned and all delegates join the army.&lt;ref name=lack88&gt;Lack (1992), p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;  Houston convinced the delegates to remain, and then left to take charge of the army.  With the backing of the Convention, Houston was now commander-in-chief of all regular, volunteer, and militia forces in Texas.&lt;ref name=davis223&gt;Davis (2006), p. 223.&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the next ten days, delegates prepared a [[Constitution of the Republic of Texas|constitution for the Republic of Texas]].  Parts of the document were copied verbatim from the [[United States Constitution]]; other articles were paraphrased.  The new nation's government was structured similarly to that of the United States, with a bicameral legislature, a chief executive, and a supreme court.&lt;ref name=lack89&gt;Lack (1992), p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; In a sharp departure from its model, the new constitution expressly permitted impressment of goods and forced housing for soldiers.  It also explicitly legalized slavery and recognized the people's right to revolt against government authority.&lt;ref name=lack90&gt;Lack (1992), p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;  After adopting the constitution on March 17, delegates elected interim officers to govern the country and then adjourned.  David G. Burnet, who had not been a delegate, was elected president.&lt;ref name=davis241&gt;Davis (2006), p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; The following day, Burnet announced the government was leaving for [[Harrisburg, Texas|Harrisburg]].&lt;ref name=davis242&gt;Davis (2006), p. 242.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Retreat: March–May 1836==

===Texian retreat: The Runaway Scrape===
{{Further information|Runaway Scrape}}
On March 11, Santa Anna sent one column of troops to join Urrea, with instructions to move to Brazoria once Fannin's men had been neutralized.  A second set of 700 troops under General [[Antonio Gaona]] would advance along the Camino Real to [[Bastrop, Texas|Mina]], and then on to Nacogdoches.  General  [[Joaquín Ramírez y Sesma]] would take an additional 700 men to San Felipe.  The Mexican columns were thus moving northeast on roughly parallel paths, separated by {{convert|40|-|50|mi|km}}.&lt;ref name=davis253&gt;Davis (2006), p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:SHouston.jpg|thumb|right|upright|alt=Black-and-white photograph showing a balding man from the chest up.  He is looking to the side, with a pensive expression.|[[Sam Houston]]]]
The same day that Mexican troops departed Béxar, Houston arrived in Gonzales and informed the 374 volunteers (some without weapons) gathered there that Texas was now an independent republic.&lt;ref name=moore48and52&gt;Moore (2004), pp. 43, 48, 52, 57.&lt;/ref&gt;  Just after {{nowrap|11 p.m.}} on March 13, Susanna Dickinson and Joe brought news that the Alamo garrison had been defeated and the Mexican army was marching towards Texian settlements.  A hastily convened council of war voted to evacuate the area and retreat.  The evacuation commenced at midnight and happened so quickly that many Texian scouts were unaware the army had moved on.  Everything that could not be carried was burned, and the army's only two cannon were thrown into the Guadalupe River.&lt;ref name=moore55through59&gt;Moore (2004), pp. 55–9.&lt;/ref&gt;  When Ramírez y Sesma reached Gonzales the morning of March 14, he found the buildings still smoldering.&lt;ref name=moore71&gt;Moore (2004), p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most citizens fled on foot, many carrying their small children.  A cavalry company led by Seguín and [[Salvador Flores]] were assigned as rear guard to evacuate the more isolated ranches and protect the civilians from attacks by Mexican troops or Indians.&lt;ref name=moore60&gt;Moore (2004), p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; The further the army retreated, the more civilians joined the flight.&lt;ref name=davis243&gt;Davis (2006), p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt; For both armies and the civilians, the pace was slow; torrential rains had flooded the rivers and turned the roads into mud pits.&lt;ref name=hardin182&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;

As news of the Alamo's fall spread, volunteer ranks swelled, reaching about 1,400 men on March 19.&lt;ref name=hardin182/&gt;   Houston learned of Fannin's defeat on March 20 and realized his army was the last hope for an independent Texas.  Concerned that his ill-trained and ill-disciplined force would only be good for one battle and aware that his men could easily be outflanked by Urrea's forces, Houston continued to avoid engagement, to the immense displeasure of his troops.&lt;ref name=hardin183and4&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 183–4.&lt;/ref&gt;  By March 28, the Texian army had retreated {{convert|120|mi|km}} across the [[Navidad River|Navidad]] and [[Colorado River (Texas)|Colorado River]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Moore (2004), pp. 71, 74, 87, 134.&lt;/ref&gt;  Many troops deserted; those who remained grumbled that their commander was a coward.&lt;ref name=&quot;hardin183and4&quot;/&gt;

On March 31, Houston paused his men at Groce's Landing, roughly {{convert|15|mi|km}} north of San Felipe.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Groce's Landing is located roughly {{convert|9|mi|km}} northeast of modern-day [[Bellville, Texas|Bellville]]. Moore (2004), p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt;  Two companies that refused to retreat further than San Felipe were assigned to guard the crossings on the Brazos River.&lt;ref&gt;Moore (2004), pp. 134–7.&lt;/ref&gt;  For the next two weeks, the Texians rested, recovered from illness, and, for the first time, began practicing military drills.  While there, two cannon, known as the Twin Sisters, arrived from [[Cincinnati, Ohio]].&lt;ref name=hardin189&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt;  Interim Secretary of War [[Thomas Rusk]] joined the camp, with orders from Burnet to replace Houston if he refused to fight. Houston quickly persuaded Rusk that his plans were sound.&lt;ref name=hardin189/&gt; Secretary of State [[Samuel P. Carson]] advised Houston to continue retreating all the way to the Sabine River, where more volunteers would likely flock from the United States and allow the army to counterattack.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;After getting inaccurate reports that several thousand Indians had joined the Mexican army to attack Nacogdoches, American General [[Edmund P. Gaines]] and 600 troops crossed into Texas. This would have provoked a war if they had encountered the Mexican army, which might have followed Houston if he continued his retreat. Reid (2007), pp. 152–3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=davis263&gt;Davis (2006), p. 263.&lt;/ref&gt;  Unhappy with everyone involved, Burnet wrote to Houston: &quot;The enemy are laughing you to scorn. You must fight them. You must retreat no further. The country expects you to fight. The salvation of the country depends on your doing so.&quot;&lt;ref name=hardin189/&gt;  Complaints within the camp became so strong that Houston posted notices that anyone attempting to usurp his position would be court-martialed and shot.&lt;ref name=moore185&gt;Moore (2004), p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt;

Santa Anna and a smaller force had remained in Béxar.  After receiving word that the acting president, [[Miguel Barragán]], had died, Santa Anna seriously considered returning to Mexico City to solidify his position.  Fear that Urrea's victories would position him as a political rival convinced Santa Anna to remain in Texas to personally oversee the final phase of the campaign.&lt;ref name=davis254&gt;Davis (2006), p. 254.&lt;/ref&gt;  He left on March 29 to join Ramírez y Sesma, leaving only a small force to hold Béxar.&lt;ref name=moore154&gt;Moore (2004), p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;  At dawn on April 7, their combined force marched into San Felipe and captured a Texian soldier, who informed Santa Anna that the Texians planned to retreat further if the Mexican army crossed the Brazos River.&lt;ref name=moore176&gt;Moore (2004), p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt;  Unable to cross the Brazos due to the small company of Texians barricaded at the river crossing, on April 14 a frustrated Santa Anna led a force of about 700 troops to capture the interim Texas government.&lt;ref name=hardin190&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=moore182&gt;Moore (2004), p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;   Government officials fled mere hours before Mexican troops arrived in Harrisburg, and Santa Anna sent Colonel [[Juan Almonte]] with 50 cavalry to intercept them in New Washington.  Almonte arrived just as Burnet shoved off in a rowboat, bound for [[Galveston, Texas|Galveston Island]].  Although the boat was still within range of their weapons, Almonte ordered his men to hold their fire so as not to endanger Burnet's family.&lt;ref name=hardin191&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;

At this point, Santa Anna believed the rebellion was in its final death throes.  The Texian government had been forced off the mainland, with no way to communicate with its army, which had shown no interest in fighting.  He determined to block the Texian army's retreat and put a decisive end to the war.&lt;ref name=hardin191/&gt;  Almonte's scouts incorrectly reported that Houston's army was going to Lynchburg Crossing, on [[Buffalo Bayou]], in preparation for joining the government in Galveston, so Santa Anna ordered Harrisburg burned and pressed on towards [[Lynchburg, Texas|Lynchburg]].&lt;ref name=hardin191&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texian army had resumed their march eastward.  On April 16, they came to a crossroads; one road led north towards Nacogdoches, the other went to Harrisburg.  Without orders from Houston and with no discussion amongst themselves, the troops in the lead took the road to Harrisburg.  They arrived on April 18, not long after the Mexican army's departure.&lt;ref name=hardin192and3&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 190–3.&lt;/ref&gt;  That same day, [[Deaf Smith]] and [[Henry Karnes]] captured a Mexican courier carrying intelligence on the locations and future plans of all of the Mexican troops in Texas.  Realizing that Santa Anna had only a small force and was not far away, Houston gave a rousing speech to his men, exhorting them to &quot;Remember the Alamo&quot; and &quot;Remember Goliad&quot;.  His army then raced towards Lynchburg.&lt;ref name=hardin199and200&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 199–200.&lt;/ref&gt;  Out of concern that his men might not differentiate between Mexican soldiers and the ''Tejanos'' in Seguín's company, Houston originally ordered Seguín and his men to remain in Harrisburg to guard those who were too ill to travel quickly.  After loud protests from Seguín and [[Antonio Menchaca]], the order was rescinded, provided the ''Tejanos'' wear a piece of cardboard in their hats to identify them as Texian soldiers.&lt;ref name=hardin209&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 209.&lt;/ref&gt;

===San Jacinto===
{{Main article|Battle of San Jacinto}}

The area along Buffalo Bayou had many thick oak groves, separated by marshes.  This type of terrain was familiar to the Texians and quite alien to the Mexican soldiers.&lt;ref name=hardin202/&gt;  Houston's army, comprising 900 men, reached Lynch's Ferry mid-morning on April 20; Santa Anna's 700-man force arrived a few hours later.  The Texians made camp in a wooded area along the bank of Buffalo Bayou; while the location provided good cover and helped hide their full strength, it also left the Texians no room for retreat.&lt;ref name=hardin200and1&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 200–1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=moore258&gt;Moore (2004), p. 258.&lt;/ref&gt;  Over the protests of several of his officers, Santa Anna chose to make camp in a vulnerable location, a plain near the San Jacinto River, bordered by woods on one side, marsh and lake on another.&lt;ref name=hardin202&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=moore283&gt;Moore (2004), p. 283.&lt;/ref&gt;  The two camps were approximately {{convert|500|yd|m}} apart, separated by a grassy area with a slight rise in the middle.&lt;ref name=hardin208&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 208.&lt;/ref&gt;  Colonel Pedro Delgado later wrote that &quot;the camping ground of His Excellency's selection was in all respects, against military rules. Any youngster would have done better.&quot;&lt;ref name=moore287&gt;Moore (2004), p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:The Battle of San Jacinto (1895).jpg|thumb|left|300px|alt=The painting shows many men, some on foot and some on horseback, engaged in hand-to-hand combat.  One man carries the Mexican flag; another carries the flag of the Republic of Texas.  In the background are several tents; behind them is a body of water.|[[Henry Arthur McArdle]]'s 1895 painting, ''The Battle of San Jacinto'']]
Over the next several hours, two brief skirmishes occurred.  Texians won the first, forcing a small group of dragoons and the Mexican artillery to withdraw.&lt;ref name=hardin202/&gt;&lt;ref name=hardin203/&gt;  Mexican dragoons then forced the Texian cavalry to withdraw.  In the melee, Rusk, on foot to reload his rifle, was almost captured by Mexican soldiers, but was rescued by newly arrived Texian volunteer [[Mirabeau B. Lamar]].&lt;ref name=hardin203&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt;  Over Houston's objections, many infantrymen rushed onto the field. As the Texian cavalry fell back, Lamar remained behind to rescue another Texian who had been thrown from his horse; Mexican officers &quot;reportedly applauded&quot; his bravery.&lt;ref name=hardin204&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 204.&lt;/ref&gt; Houston was irate that the infantry had disobeyed his orders and given Santa Anna a better estimate of their strength; the men were equally upset that Houston hadn't allowed a full battle.&lt;ref name=davis267&gt;Davis (2006), p. 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the night, Mexican troops worked to fortify their camp, creating [[breastworks]] out of everything they could find, including saddles and brush.&lt;ref name=hardin205&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 205.&lt;/ref&gt;  At {{nowrap|9 a.m.}} on April 21, Cos arrived with 540 reinforcements, bringing the Mexican force to 1,200 men, which outnumbered the Texians.&lt;ref name=hardin206&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt;  Cos's men were raw recruits rather than experienced soldiers, and they had marched steadily for more than 24 hours, with no rest and no food.&lt;ref name=moore292&gt;Moore (2004), p. 292.&lt;/ref&gt;  As the morning wore on with no Texian attack, Mexican officers lowered their guard.  By afternoon, Santa Anna had given permission for Cos's men to sleep; his own tired troops also took advantage of the time to rest, eat, and bathe.&lt;ref name=moore328&gt;Moore (2004), p. 328.&lt;/ref&gt;

Not long after the Mexican reinforcements arrived, Houston ordered Smith to destroy [[Vince's Bridge]], {{convert|5|mi|km}} away, to slow down any further Mexican reinforcements.&lt;ref name=hardin207&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt;  At {{nowrap|4 p.m.}} the Texians began creeping quietly through the tall grass, pulling the cannon behind them.&lt;ref name=hardin312-8&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 312–8.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Texian cannon fired at 4:30, beginning the [[battle of San Jacinto]].&lt;ref name=moore210&gt;Moore (2004), p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt;  After a single volley, Texians broke ranks and swarmed over the Mexican breastworks to engage in hand-to-hand combat.  Mexican soldiers were taken completely by surprise.  Santa Anna,  Castrillón, and Almonte yelled often conflicting orders, attempting to organize their men into some form of defense.&lt;ref name=moore211&gt;Moore (2004), p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt;  Within 18 minutes, Mexican soldiers abandoned their campsite and fled for their lives.&lt;ref name=davis271&gt;Davis (2006), p. 271.&lt;/ref&gt;  The killing lasted for hours.&lt;ref name=hardin213&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Mexican soldiers retreated through the marsh to Peggy Lake.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Peggy Lake, also called Peggy's Lake, no longer exists. It was located southeast of the Mexican breastworks, which is now the site of the monument. Hardin (2004) pp. 71, 93&lt;/ref&gt; Texian riflemen stationed themselves on the banks and shot at anything that moved.  Many Texian officers, including Houston and Rusk, attempted to stop the slaughter, but they were unable to gain control of the men.  Texians continued to chant &quot;Remember the Alamo! Remember Goliad!&quot; while frightened Mexican infantry yelled &quot;Me no Alamo!&quot; and begged for mercy to no avail.&lt;ref name=hardin211to5&gt;Hardin (1994), pp. 211–5.&lt;/ref&gt;  In what historian Davis called &quot;one of the most one-sided victories in history&quot;,&lt;ref name=davis274&gt;Davis (2006), p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt; 650 Mexican soldiers were killed and 300 captured.&lt;ref name=hardin215&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt;  Eleven Texians died, with 30 others, including Houston, wounded.&lt;ref name=moore364&gt;Moore (2004), p. 364.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Santa Anna's troops had been thoroughly vanquished, they did not represent the bulk of the Mexican army in Texas. An additional 4,000 troops remained under the commands of Urrea and General [[Vicente Filisola]].&lt;ref name=davis272&gt;Davis (2006), p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt;  Texians had won the battle due to mistakes made by Santa Anna, and Houston was well aware that his troops would have little hope of repeating their victory against Urrea or Filisola.&lt;ref name=davis273&gt;Davis (2006), p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt;  As darkness fell, a large group of prisoners were led into camp.  Houston initially mistook the group for Mexican reinforcements and shouted out that all was lost.&lt;ref name=davis276&gt;Davis (2006), p. 276.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mexican retreat===
[[File:SantaAnnaSurrender.jpg|thumb|right|alt=A group of men are gathered under a large tree.  One man lays on the ground under the trees, with his bare foot exposed.|''&quot;Surrender of Santa Anna&quot;'' by [[William Henry Huddle]] shows the Mexican president and general surrendering to a wounded Sam Houston, [[battle of San Jacinto]]]]
Santa Anna had successfully escaped towards Vince's Bridge.&lt;ref name=moore353&gt;Moore (2004), p. 353.&lt;/ref&gt;  Finding the bridge destroyed, he hid in the marsh and was captured the following day.&lt;ref name=hardin215&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt; He was brought before Houston, who had been shot in the ankle&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Lamar thought Houston was deliberately shot by one of his own men.  Moore (2004), p. 339.&lt;/ref&gt; and badly wounded.&lt;ref name=davis272&gt;Davis (2006), p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; Texian soldiers gathered around, calling for the Mexican general's immediate execution.  Bargaining for his life, Santa Anna suggested that he order the remaining Mexican troops to stay away.&lt;ref name=hardin216&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt;  In a letter to Filisola, who was now the senior Mexican official in Texas, Santa Anna wrote that &quot;yesterday evening [we] had an unfortunate encounter&quot; and ordered his troops to retreat to Béxar and await further instructions.&lt;ref name=davis273&gt;Davis (2006), p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt;

Urrea urged Filisola to continue the campaign.  He was confident that he could successfully challenge the Texian troops.  According to Hardin, &quot;Santa Anna had presented Mexico with one military disaster; Filisola did not wish to risk another.&quot;&lt;ref name=hardin245&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 245.&lt;/ref&gt;  Spring rains ruined the ammunition and rendered the roads almost impassable, with troops sinking to their knees in mud.  Mexican troops were soon out of food, and began to fall ill from dysentery and other diseases.&lt;ref name=davis277/&gt;  Their supply lines had completely broken down, leaving no hope of further reinforcements.&lt;ref name=hardin246&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 246.&lt;/ref&gt; Filisola later wrote that &quot;Had the enemy met us under these cruel circumstances, on the only road that was left, no alternative remained but to die or surrender at discretion&quot;.&lt;ref name=davis277&gt;Davis (2006), p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt;

For several weeks after San Jacinto, Santa Anna continued to negotiate with Houston, Rusk, and then Burnet.&lt;ref name=davis279&gt;Davis (2006), p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt;  Santa Anna suggested two treaties, a public version of promises made between the two countries, and a private version that included Santa Anna's personal agreements.  The [[Treaties of Velasco]] required that all Mexican troops retreat south of the Rio Grande and that all private property—code for slaves—be respected and restored.  Prisoners-of-war would be released unharmed, and Santa Anna would be given passage to Veracruz immediately.  He secretly promised to persuade the Mexican Congress to acknowledge the Republic of Texas and to recognize the Rio Grande as the border between the two countries.&lt;ref name=davis282&gt;Davis (2006), p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Urrea began marching south in mid-May, many families from San Patricio who had supported the Mexican army went with him.  When Texian troops arrived in early June, they found only 20 families remaining.  The area around San Patricio and Refugio suffered a &quot;noticeable depopulation&quot; in the Republic of Texas years.&lt;ref name=lack180&gt;Lack (1992), p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the treaty had specified that Urrea and Filisola would return any slaves their armies had sheltered, Urrea refused to comply. Many former slaves followed the army to Mexico, where they could be free.&lt;ref name=lack245&gt;Lack (1992), p. 245.&lt;/ref&gt;  By late May the Mexican troops had crossed the Nueces.&lt;ref name=davis277/&gt;  Filisola fully expected that the defeat was temporary and that a second campaign would be launched to retake Texas.&lt;ref name=hardin246/&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Military===
When Mexican authorities received word of Santa Anna's defeat at San Jacinto, flags across the country were lowered to half staff and draped in mourning.&lt;ref name=henderson103&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt;  Denouncing any agreements signed by a prisoner, Mexican authorities refused to recognize the Republic of Texas.&lt;ref name=davis288/&gt;  Filisola was derided for leading the retreat and quickly replaced by Urrea.  Within months, Urrea gathered 6,000 troops in Matamoros, poised to reconquer Texas.  His army was redirected to address continued federalist rebellions in other regions.&lt;ref name=davis289&gt;Davis (2006), p. 289.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most in Texas assumed the Mexican army would return quickly.&lt;ref name=lack201/&gt;  So many American volunteers flocked to the Texian army in the months after the victory at San Jacinto that the Texian government was unable to maintain an accurate list of enlistments.&lt;ref name=davis291&gt;Davis (2006), p. 291.&lt;/ref&gt;  Out of caution, Béxar remained under martial law throughout 1836.  Rusk ordered that all ''Tejanos'' in the area between the Guadalupe and Nueces Rivers  migrate either to east Texas or to Mexico.&lt;ref name=lack201&gt;Lack (1992), p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt;  Some residents who refused to comply were forcibly removed.  New Anglo settlers moved in and used threats and legal maneuvering to take over the land once owned by ''Tejanos''.&lt;ref name=davis288&gt;Davis (2006), p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lack206&gt;Lack (1992), p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt;  Over the next several years, hundreds of ''Tejano'' families resettled in Mexico.&lt;ref name=davis288/&gt;

For years,  Mexican authorities used the reconquering of Texas as an excuse for implementing new taxes and making the army the budgetary priority of the impoverished nation.&lt;ref name=vazquez315/&gt;  Only sporadic skirmishes resulted.&lt;ref name=henderson125&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt;  Larger expeditions were postponed as military funding was consistently diverted to other rebellions, out of fear that those regions would ally with Texas and further fragment the country.&lt;ref name=vazquez315&gt;Vazquez (1985), p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;New Mexico, Sonora, and California revolted unsuccessfully; their stated goals were a change in government, not independence. Henderson (2008), p. 100. Vazquez (1985), p. 318.&lt;/ref&gt; The northern Mexican states, the focus of the Matamoros Expedition, briefly launched an independent [[Republic of the Rio Grande]] in 1839.&lt;ref name=reid169&gt;Reid (2007), p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, the Mexican Congress considered a law to declare it treasonous to speak positively of Texas.&lt;ref name=henderson123&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 123.&lt;/ref&gt;  In June 1843, leaders of the two nations declared an armistice.&lt;ref name=henderson127&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Republic of Texas===
[[File:Wpdms republic of texas.svg|thumb|right|alt=The land comprising Mexican Texas, between the Red, Sabine, and Nueces Rivers, is shaded yellow.  The land between this boundary and the Rio Grande on the south and the Arkansas River on the north is shaded green and marked as &quot;claimed territory&quot;. |The Republic of Texas, including the disputed territory]]
On June 1, Santa Anna boarded a ship to travel back to Mexico.  For the next two days, crowds of soldiers, many of whom had arrived that week from the United States, gathered to demand his execution.  Lamar, by now promoted to Secretary of War, gave a speech insisting that &quot;Mobs must not intimidate the government. We want no [[French Revolution]] in Texas!&quot;, but on June 4 soldiers seized Santa Anna and put him under military arrest.&lt;ref name=lack104&gt;Lack (1992), p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Lack, &quot;the shock of having its foreign policy overturned by popular rebellion had weakened the interim government irrevocably&quot;.&lt;ref name=lackl105&gt;Lack (1992), p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;  A group of soldiers staged an unsuccessful coup in mid-July.&lt;ref name=lack106&gt;Lack (1992), p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt;  In response, Burnet called for elections to ratify the constitution and elect a Congress,&lt;ref name=lack107&gt;Lack (1992), p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt; the sixth set of leaders for Texas in a twelve-month period.&lt;ref name=lack256&gt;Lack (1992), p. 256.&lt;/ref&gt;  Voters overwhelmingly chose Houston the first [[President of the Republic of Texas|president]], ratified the constitution drawn up by the Convention of 1836, and approved a resolution to request annexation to the United States.&lt;ref name=davis295&gt;Davis (2006), p. 295.&lt;/ref&gt;  Houston issued an executive order sending Santa Anna to [[Washington, D.C.]], and from there he was soon sent home.&lt;ref name=davis301&gt;Davis (2006), p. 301.&lt;/ref&gt;

During his absence, Santa Anna had been deposed.  Upon his arrival, the Mexican press wasted no time in attacking him for his cruelty towards those executed at Goliad.  In May 1837, Santa Anna requested an inquiry into the event.&lt;ref name=vazquez316&gt;Vazquez (1985), p. 316.&lt;/ref&gt;  The judge determined the inquiry was only for fact-finding and took no action; press attacks in both Mexico and the United States continued.&lt;ref name=vazquez317&gt;Vazquez (1985), p. 317.&lt;/ref&gt;  Santa Anna was disgraced until the following year, when he became a hero of the [[Pastry War]].&lt;ref name=henderson116&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first Texas Legislature declined to ratify the treaty Houston had signed with the Cherokee, declaring he had no authority to make any promises.&lt;ref name=scott69&gt;Scott (2000), p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the Texian interim governments had vowed to eventually compensate citizens for goods that were impressed during the war efforts, for the most part livestock and horses were not returned.&lt;ref name=lack232&gt;Lack (1992), p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt;  Veterans were guaranteed land bounties; in 1879, surviving Texian veterans who served more than three months from October 1, 1835 through January 1, 1837 were guaranteed an additional {{convert|1280|acre|ha}} in public lands.&lt;ref name=miller343&gt;Miller (1961), p. 343.&lt;/ref&gt;  Over 1.3 million acres (559 thousand ha) of land were granted; some of this was in [[Greer County, Oklahoma|Greer County]], which was later determined to be part of [[Oklahoma]].&lt;ref name=miller344and6&gt;Miller (1961), pp. 344, 346.&lt;/ref&gt;

Republic of Texas policies changed the status of many living in the region.  The constitution forbade free blacks from living in Texas permanently.  Individual slaves could only be freed by congressional order, and the newly emancipated person would then be forced to leave Texas.&lt;ref name=lackslaves&gt;Lack (1992), pp. 250–1.&lt;/ref&gt;  Women also lost significant legal rights under the new constitution, which substituted English common law practices for the traditional Spanish law system.  Under common law, the idea of [[community property]] was eliminated, and women no longer had the ability to act for themselves legally – to sign contracts, own property, or sue.  Some of these rights were restored in 1845, when Texas added them to the new state constitution.&lt;ref name=stuntz56&gt;Stuntz (2012), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; During the Republic of Texas years, ''Tejanos'' likewise faced much discrimination.&lt;ref name=hardin250&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 250.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Foreign relations===

Mexican authorities blamed the loss of Texas on United States intervention.&lt;ref name=&quot;henderson103&quot;/&gt;  Although the United States remained officially neutral,&lt;ref name=hardin177&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt; 40 percent of the men who enlisted in the Texian army from October 1 through April 21 arrived from the United States after hostilities began.&lt;ref name=lack132&gt;Lack (1992), p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;  More than 200 of the volunteers were members of the [[United States Army]]; none were punished when they returned to their posts.&lt;ref name=hardin177/&gt; American individuals also provided supplies and money to the cause of Texian independence.&lt;ref name=lack254&gt;Lack (1992), p. 254.&lt;/ref&gt;  For the next decade, Mexican politicians frequently denounced the United States for the involvement of its citizens.&lt;ref name=henderson114&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States agreed to recognize the Republic of Texas in March 1837 but declined to annex the territory.&lt;ref name=henderson121&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;  The fledgling republic now attempted to persuade European nations to agree to recognition.&lt;ref name=barker185&gt;Barker (1967), p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt; In late 1839 France recognized the Republic of Texas after being convinced it would make a fine trading partner.&lt;ref name=barker187&gt;Barker (1967), p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt;

For several decades, official British policy was to maintain strong ties with Mexico in the hopes that the country could stop the United States from expanding further.&lt;ref name=reid10&gt;Reid (2007), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;  When the Texas Revolution erupted, Great Britain had declined to become involved, officially expressing confidence that Mexico could handle its own affairs.&lt;ref name=reid76&gt;Reid (2007), p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1840, after years in which the Republic of Texas was neither annexed by the United States nor reabsorbed into Mexico, Britain signed a treaty to recognize the nation and act as a mediator to help Texas gain recognition from Mexico.&lt;ref name=reid157&gt;Reid (2007), p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States voted to [[annexation of Texas|annex Texas]] as the 28th state in March 1845.&lt;ref name=Henderson139&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt;  Two months later, Mexico agreed to recognize the Republic of Texas as long as there was no annexation to the United States.&lt;ref name=Henderson146&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;  On July 4, 1845, Texans voted for annexation.&lt;ref name=henderson147&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;  This prompted the [[Mexican–American War]], in which Mexico lost almost 55 percent of its territory to the United States and formally relinquished its claim on Texas.&lt;ref name=henderson177&gt;Henderson (2008), p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
{{further information|Legacy of the Battle of the Alamo}}
[[File:San Jacinto Monument - Full.jpg|thumb|right|upright|alt=A tall stone column, which widens as it meets the base, a large rectangular building with no windows. |[[San Jacinto Monument|The San Jacinto Monument]] is a memorial to the men who died during the Texas Revolution.]]
Although no new fighting techniques were introduced during the Texas Revolution,&lt;ref name=davis305&gt;Davis (2006), p. 305.&lt;/ref&gt; casualty figures were quite unusual for the time.  Generally in 19th-century warfare, the number of wounded outnumbered those killed by a factor of two or three.  From October 1835 through April 1836, approximately 1,000 Mexican and 700 Texian soldiers died, while the wounded numbered 500 Mexican and 100 Texian.  The deviation from the norm was due to Santa Anna's decision to label Texian rebels as traitors and to the Texian desire for revenge.&lt;ref name=davis302&gt;Davis (2006), p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the revolution, Texian soldiers gained a reputation for courage and militance.&lt;ref name=hardin250/&gt;&lt;ref name=lack132/&gt;   Lack points out that fewer than five percent of the Texian population enrolled in the army during the war, a fairly low rate of participation.&lt;ref name=lack132/&gt;  Texian soldiers recognized that the Mexican cavalry was far superior to their own.  Over the next decade, the [[Texas Ranger Division|Texas Rangers]] borrowed Mexican cavalry tactics and adopted the [[western saddle|Spanish saddle]] and spurs, the [[riata]], and the bandana.&lt;ref name=hardin248&gt;Hardin (1994), p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Texas Veterans Association]], composed solely of revolutionary veterans living in Texas, was active from 1873 through 1901 and played a key role in convincing the legislature to create a monument to honor the San Jacinto veterans.&lt;ref name=moore423&gt;Moore (2004), p. 423.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the late 19th century, the Texas Legislature purchased the San Jacinto battlesite, which is now home to the [[San Jacinto Monument]], the tallest stone column monument in the world.&lt;ref&gt;Moore (2004), pp. 425–6.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the early 20th century, the Texas Legislature purchased the Alamo Mission,&lt;ref name=todish199&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; now an official state shrine.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmondson423&quot;&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 423.&lt;/ref&gt; In front of the church, in the center of Alamo Plaza, stands a [[Alamo Cenotaph|cenotaph]] designed by [[Pompeo Coppini]] which commemorates the defenders who died during the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Edmondson (2000), p. 418.&lt;/ref&gt; More than 2.5 million people visit the Alamo every year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Plan a Visit|publisher=TheAlamo.org|url=http://thealamo.org/plan-a-visit/index.html|accessdate=January 21, 2015|date=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texas Revolution has been the subject of poetry and of many books, plays and films. Most English-language treatments reflect the perspectives of the Anglos and are centered primarily on the battle of the Alamo.&lt;ref name=graham35and42&gt;Graham (1985), pp. 35, 42.&lt;/ref&gt;  From the first novel depicting events of the revolution, 1838's ''Mexico versus Texas'', through the mid-20th century, most works contained  themes of [[anticlericalism]] and racism, depicting the battle as a fight for freedom between good (Anglo Texian) and evil (Mexican).&lt;ref&gt;Graham (1985), pp. 36–9, 44.&lt;/ref&gt; In both English- and Spanish-language literature, the Alamo is often compared to the [[battle of Thermopylae]].&lt;ref&gt;Graham (1985), pp. 41–2.&lt;/ref&gt;  The 1950s [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] miniseries ''[[Davy Crockett (miniseries)|Davy Crockett]]'', which was largely based on myth, created a worldwide craze for everything Alamo-related.&lt;ref name=graham53&gt;Graham (1985), p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; Within several years, [[John Wayne]] directed and starred in one of the best-known and perhaps least historically accurate film versions, ''[[The Alamo (1960 film)|The Alamo]]'' (1960).&lt;ref name=todish188&gt;Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Historians [[James Frank Dobie|J. Frank Dobie]] and [[Lon Tinkle]] requested that they not be listed as historical advisers in the credits of ''The Alamo'' because of its disjunction from recognized history. Todish ''et al.'' (1998), p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt;  Notably, this version made the first attempt to leave behind racial stereotypes; it was still banned in Mexico.&lt;ref name=graham59&gt;Graham (1985), p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the late 1970s, works about the Alamo began to explore ''Tejano'' perspectives, which had been all but extinguished even from textbooks about the revolution, and to explore the revolution's links to slavery.&lt;ref&gt;Graham (1985), pp. 62–3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Texas}}
*[[List of Texas Revolution battles]]
*[[Timeline of the Texas Revolution]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
*{{cite journal|last=Barker|first=Nancy N.|authorlink=Nancy Nichols Barker|title=The Republic of Texas: A French View|journal=[[The Southwestern Historical Quarterly]]|volume=71|date=July 1967|url=http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metapth117145/m1/213/|accessdate=January 21, 2015}}
*{{Cite book|last=Barr|first=Alwyn|authorlink=alwyn Barr|title=Texans in Revolt: the Battle for San Antonio, 1835|publisher=University of Texas Press|location=Austin, TX|year=1990|isbn=0-292-77042-1|oclc=20354408}}
*{{cite book|last1=Calore|first1=Paul|title=The Texas Revolution and the U.S.–Mexican War A Concise History|date=2014|publisher=McFarland|isbn=978-0-7864-7940-5|location=Jefferson, NC}}
*{{cite book|last=Davis|first=William C.|author-link=William C. Davis (historian)|title=Lone Star Rising|date=2006|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|isbn=978-1-58544-532-5}} originally published 2004 by New York: Free Press
*{{Cite book|last=Edmondson|first=J.R.|title=The Alamo Story: From Early History to Current Conflicts|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|location=Plano, TX|isbn=1-55622-678-0|year=2000}}
*{{cite journal|last=Graham|first=Don|title=Remembering the Alamo: The Story of the Texas Revolution in Popular Culture|journal=The Southwestern Historical Quarterly|volume=89|date=July 1985|pages=35–67|url=http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metapth117151/m1/61/|accessdate=January 21, 2015}}
*{{Cite book|last=Hardin|first=Stephen L.|authorlink=Stephen L. Hardin|year=1994|title=Texian Iliad – A Military History of the Texas Revolution|location=Austin, TX|publisher=University of Texas Press|isbn=0-292-73086-1|oclc=29704011}}
*{{Cite book|last=Hardin|first=Stephen |authorlink=Stephen L. Hardin|year=2004|title=The Alamo 1836 : Santa Anna's Texas campaign|location=Westport, CT|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=978-0-275-98460-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Henderson|first=Timothy J.|title=A Glorious Defeat: Mexico and Its War with the United States|publisher=Macmillan|location=New York, NY|year=2008|isbn=1-4299-2279-6}}
*{{Cite book|last=Lack|first=Paul D.|title=The Texas Revolutionary Experience: A Political and Social History 1835–1836|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|year=1992|isbn=0-89096-497-1}}
*{{Cite book|last=Manchaca|first=Martha|title=Recovering History, Constructing Race: The Indian, Black, and White Roots of Mexican Americans|series=The Joe R. and Teresa Lozano Long Series in Latin American and Latino Art and Culture|publisher=University of Texas Press|location=Austin, TX|year=2001|isbn=0-292-75253-9}}
*{{cite journal|last=Miller|first=Thomas|title=Texas Land Grants to Veterans of the Revolution and Signers of the Declaration of Independence|journal=The Southwestern Historical Quarterly|volume=64|date=January 1961|url=http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metapth101190/m1/377/|accessdate=January 21, 2015|pages=342–7}}
*{{cite book|last=Moore|first=Stephen L.|title=Eighteen Minutes: The Battle of San Jacinto and the Texas Independence Campaign|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|location=Plano, TX|year=2004|isbn=1-58907-009-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Reid|first=Stuart|title=The Secret War for Texas|series=Elma Dill Russell Spencer Series in the West and Southwest|number=28|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|location=College Station, TX|year=2007|isbn=978-1-58544-565-3}}
*{{Cite book|last=Scott|first=Robert|title=After the Alamo|year=2000|location=Plano, TX|publisher=Republic of Texas Press|isbn=978-0-585-22788-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Stuart|first=Jay|title=Slaughter at Goliad: The Mexican Massacre of 400 Texas Volunteers|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, MD|year=2008|isbn=978-1-59114-843-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Stuntz|first=Jean A.|chapter=Tejanas: Hispanic Women on the Losing Side of the Texas Revolution|title=Women and the Texas Revolution|editor-last=Scheer|editor-first=Mary L.|publisher=University of North Texas Press|location=Denton, TX|year=2012|isbn=1-57441-469-0}}
*{{Cite book|last=Todish|first=Timothy J.|last2=Todish|first2=Terry|last3=Spring|first3=Ted|title=Alamo Sourcebook, 1836: A Comprehensive Guide to the Battle of the Alamo and the Texas Revolution|publisher=Eakin Press|year=1998|location=Austin, TX|isbn=978-1-57168-152-2}}
*{{cite journal|last=Vazquez|first=Josefina Zoraida|authorlink=Josefina Zoraida Vázquez|title=The Texas Question in Mexican Politics, 1836–1845|journal=The Southwestern Historical Quarterly|volume=89|date=July 1985|url=http://texashistory.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metapth117151/m1/365/|accessdate=January 21, 2015|others=translated by Jésus F. de la Teja}}
*{{Cite book|title=Myths, Misdeeds, and Misunderstandings: The Roots of Conflict in U.S.–Mexican Relations|editor-last=Rodriguez O.|editor-first=Jaime E.|editor2-last=Vincent|editor2-first=Kathryn|location=Wilmington, DE|year=1997|publisher=Scholarly Resources Inc.|isbn=0-8420-2662-2|contribution=The Colonization and Loss of Texas: A Mexican Perspective|last=Vazquez|first=Josefina Zoraida}}
* {{Cite book|last=Weber|first=David J.|authorlink=David J. Weber|title=The Spanish Frontier in North America|publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven, CT|series=Yale Western Americana Series|year=1992|isbn=0-300-05198-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=Winders|first=Richard Bruce|title=Sacrificed at the Alamo: Tragedy and Triumph in the Texas Revolution|publisher=State House Press|location=Austin, TX|year=2004|isbn=1-880510-81-2}}

== External links ==
*[http://omniatlas.com/maps/northamerica/18360421/ Omniatlas.com: Map of North America showing the Texas Revolution]

{{Mexican Texas}}
{{Texas History Navbox}}
{{Use US English|date=April 2015}}
{{Mexico topics}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Texas Revolution| ]]
[[Category:Mexican Texas]]
[[Category:Colonial United States (Mexican)]]
[[Category:Separatism in Mexico]]
[[Category:Wars fought in Texas|Revolution]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1835]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1836]]
[[Category:1835 in Mexico]]
[[Category:1835 in Texas]]
[[Category:1836 in Mexico]]
[[Category:1836 in the Republic of Texas|Revolution]]
[[Category:1836 in Texas]]</text>
      <sha1>0fxgg2l5dnu9kii4w31a7cr1chyvqt3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
