<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Sinking of the Lusitania</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7682623</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751070770</id>
      <parentid>739800164</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T05:41:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WFinch</username>
        <id>2477977</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ update Commons category name</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29275">{{About|the 1918 animated film|the historical event|Sinking of the RMS Lusitania}}
{{featured article}}
{{use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{use American English|date=August 2013}}
{{Infobox film
|name           = The Sinking of the Lusitania
|image          = Winsor McCay - The Sinking of the Lusitania still - Lusitania torpedoed.jpg
|image_size     = 300px
|caption        = A still from the film showing the [[RMS Lusitania|RMS ''Lusitania'']] engulfed in smoke after being torpedoed
|alt            = A black-and-white drawing of a sinking ship, exploding with thick, black smoke.
|director       = [[Winsor McCay]]
&lt;!-- |producer       = Winsor McCay
|writer         = Winsor McCay
|cinematography = 
|editing        = --&gt;&lt;!-- all redundant --&gt;
|distributor    = [[Jewel Productions]]
|released       = {{film date|1918}}&lt;!-- SOURCES CONFLICT -- John Canemaker dates the first showing as July 20; Earl Theisen dates the première as August 15, 1918; an early magazine talks about the film in May 1915 ?!?!? --&gt;
|runtime        = 12 minutes
|country        = United States
|language       = [[Silent film|Silent]] with English [[intertitle]]s
|budget         = 
}}

'''''The Sinking of the Lusitania''''' (1918) is a [[silent film|silent]] animated short [[film]] by American cartoonist [[Winsor McCay]].  It is a work of [[propaganda film|propaganda]] re-creating the never-photographed 1915 [[Sinking of the RMS Lusitania|sinking of the British liner RMS ''Lusitania'']].  At twelve minutes it has been called the longest work of animation at the time of its release.  The film is the earliest surviving [[animated documentary]] and serious, dramatic work of animation.

In 1915 a [[U-boat|German submarine]] torpedoed and sank the [[RMS Lusitania|RMS ''Lusitania'']]; 128 Americans were among the 1,198 dead.  The event outraged McCay, but the newspapers of his employer [[William Randolph Hearst]] downplayed the event, as Hearst was opposed to the [[American entry into World War I|US joining World War&amp;nbsp;I]].  McCay was required to illustrate anti-war and anti-British editorial cartoons for Hearst's papers.  In 1916, McCay rebelled against his employer's stance and began work on the patriotic ''Sinking of the Lusitania'' on his own time with his own money.

The film followed McCay's earlier successes in animation: ''[[Little Nemo (1911 film)|Little Nemo]]'' (1911), ''[[How a Mosquito Operates]]'' (1912), and ''[[Gertie the Dinosaur]]'' (1914).  McCay drew these earlier films on [[rice paper]], onto which backgrounds had to be laboriously traced; ''The Sinking of the Lusitania'' was the first film McCay made using the new, more efficient [[cel]] technology.  McCay and his assistants spent twenty-two months making the film.  His subsequent animation output suffered setbacks, as the film was not as commercially successful as his earlier efforts, and Hearst put increased pressure on McCay to devote his time to editorial drawings.

{{TOC limit|2}}

==Synopsis==

[[File:Winsor McCay (1918) The Sinking of the Lusitania.webm|thumb|alt=Video of the animated film ''The Sinking of the Lusitania''|thumbtime=1:57|''The Sinking of the Lusitania'' (1918)]]

The film opens with a live-action prologue in which McCay busies himself studying a picture of the ''Lusitania'' as a model for his film-in-progress.{{sfn|McKenna|2013|p=17}} [[Intertitle]]s boast of McCay as &quot;the originator and inventor of Animated Cartoons&quot;, and of the 25,000 drawings needed to complete the film.  McCay is shown working with a group of anonymous assistants on &quot;the first record of the sinking of the ''Lusitania''&quot;.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=195}}

The liner passes the [[Statue of Liberty]] and leaves [[New York Harbor]].  After some time, a [[U-boat|German submarine]] cuts through the waters and fires a torpedo at the ''Lusitania'', which billows smoke that builds until it envelops the screen.  Passengers scramble to lower lifeboats, some of which capsize in the confusion.  The liner tilts from one side to the other and passengers are tossed into the ocean.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=196}}

A second blast rocks the ''Lusitania'', which sinks slowly into the deep as more passengers fall off its edges,{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=196}} and the ship submerges amid scenes of drowning bodies.  The liner vanishes from sight,{{sfnm|1a1=Canemaker|1y=2005|1p=196|2a1=Crafton|2y=1993|2p=116}} and the film closes with a mother struggling to keep her baby above the waves.{{sfn|Crafton|1993|p=116}}  An intertitle declares: &quot;The man who fired the shot was decorated for it by the Kaiser!  ''And yet they tell us not to hate the Hun.''&quot;{{sfnm|1a1=Canemaker|1y=2005|1p=196|2a1=Crafton|2y=1993|2p=116}}

==Background==

[[Winsor McCay]] ({{circa|1869}}–1934){{efn|Different accounts have given McCay's birth year as 1867, 1869, and 1871.  His birth records are not extant.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=22}} }} produced prodigiously detailed and accurate drawings since early in life.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=23–24}}  He earned a living as a young man drawing portraits and posters in [[dime museum]]s, and attracted large crowds with his ability to draw quickly in public.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=38, 40, 43–44}}  He began working as a newspaper illustrator full-time in 1898,{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=47}} and in 1903 began drawing comic strips.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=60}}  His greatest comic strip success was the children's fantasy comic strip ''[[Little Nemo|Little Nemo in Slumberland]]'',{{sfnm|1a1=Harvey|1y=1994|1p=21|2a1=Hubbard|2y=2012|3a1=Sabin|3y=1993|3p=134|4a1=Dover editors|4y=1973|4p=vii|5a1=Canwell|5y=2009|5p=19}} which he began in 1905.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=97}}  In 1906, McCay began performing on the vaudeville circuit, doing [[chalk talk]]s—performances during which he drew in front of a live audience.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=131–132}}

[[File:RMS Lusitania coming into port, possibly in New York, 1907-13-crop.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A black-and-white photograph of an ocean liner with four smokestacks.|[[U-boat|German submarine]]s [[Sinking of the RMS Lusitania|torpedoed and sank]] the [[RMS Lusitania|RMS ''Lusitania'']] in 1915; the incident contributed to the [[American entry into World War&amp;nbsp;I|US entry into World War&amp;nbsp;I]].]]

Inspired by the [[flip book]]s his son brought home,{{sfnm|1a1=Beckerman|1y=2003|p=18|2a1=Canemaker|2y=2005|2p=157}} McCay said he &quot;came to see the possibility of making moving pictures&quot; of his cartoons.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=157}}  His first animated film, ''[[Little Nemo (1911 film)|Little Nemo]]'' (1911), was composed of four thousand drawings on [[rice paper]].{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=160}}  His next film, ''[[How a Mosquito Operates]]'' (1912), naturalistically shows a giant mosquito draw blood from a sleeping man until it burst.{{sfnm|1a1=Berenbaum|1y=2009|1p=138|2a1=Telotte|2y=2010|2p=54}}  McCay followed this with a film that became an interactive part of his [[vaudeville]] shows: in ''[[Gertie the Dinosaur]]'' (1914), McCay commanded his animated dinosaur with a whip on stage.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=175}}

The British liner [[RMS Lusitania|RMS ''Lusitania'']] briefly held the record for [[List of world's largest passenger ships|largest passenger ship]] upon its completion in 1906.{{sfn|Ramsay|2001|page=25}}  McCay displayed a fondness for it, and featured it in the episode for September 28, 1907, of his comic strip ''[[Dream of the Rarebit Fiend]]'',{{sfn|McKinney|2015|p=13}} and again in the episode for November 10, 1908, of ''[[A Pilgrim's Progress by Mister Bunion]]'', where Bunion declares it &quot;the monster boat that has smashed the record&quot;.{{sfn|McKinney|2015|pp=7–9}}

The Germans [[U-boat Campaign (World War I)|employed submarines in the North Atlantic]] during World War&amp;nbsp;I, and in April 1915 the German government issued a warning that it would target British civilian ships.  The ''Lusitania'' was [[Sinking of the RMS Lusitania|torpedoed]] on May 7, 1915, during a voyage from New York;{{sfn|Marshall|1964|p=166}}{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=186}} 128 Americans were among the 1,198 who lost their lives.{{sfnm|1a1=Canemaker|1y=2005|1p=186|2a1=Roland|2a2=Bolster|2a3=Keyssar|2y=2008|2p=264}}  Newspapers owned by McCay's employer [[William Randolph Hearst]] downplayed the tragedy, as Hearst was opposed to the [[American entry into World War I|US entering the war]].  His own papers' readers were increasingly pro-war in the aftermath of the ''Lusitania''.  McCay was as well, but was required to illustrate anti-war and anti-British editorials by editor [[Arthur Brisbane]].  In 1916, McCay rebelled against his employer's stance and began to make the patriotic ''Sinking of the Lusitania'' in his own time.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=207, 209}}

The sinking itself was never photographed.{{sfn|DelGaudio|1997|p=190}}  McCay said that he gathered background details on the ''Lusitania'' from Hearst's Berlin correspondent August&amp;nbsp;F. Beach, who was in London at the time of the disaster and was the first reporter at the scene.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=195}}  The film was the first attempt at a serious, dramatic work of animation.{{sfn|Theisen|1933|p=84}}

==Production history==

''The Sinking of the Lusitania'' took twenty-two months to complete.{{sfn|Theisen|1933|p=85}}  McCay had assistance from his neighbor, artist John Fitzsimmons, and from Cincinnati cartoonist William Apthorp &quot;Ap&quot; Adams,{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=188}} who took care of layering the cels in proper sequence for shooting.  Fitzsimmons was responsible for a sequence of waves, sixteen frames to be cycled over McCay's drawings.{{sfn|Hoffer|1976|p=32}}  McCay provided illustrations during the day for the newspapers of William Randolph Hearst, and spent his off hours at home drawing the cels for the film, which he took to [[Vitagraph Studios]] to be photographed.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=188}}

McCay's working methods were laborious.  On ''Gertie the Dinosaur'' an assistant painstakingly traced and retraced the backgrounds thousands of times.  Rival animators developed a number of methods to reduce the workload and speed production to meet the increasing demand for animated films.  Within a few years of ''Nemo''{{'}}s release, it became near-universal practice in animation studios to use American [[Earl Hurd]]'s [[cel]] technology, combined with Canadian [[Raoul Barré]]'s registration pegs, used to keep cels aligned when photographed.{{sfn|Barrier|2003|pp=10–14}}  Hurd had patented the cel method in 1914; it saved work by allowing dynamic drawings to be drawn on one or more layers, which could be laid over a static background layer, relieving animators of the tedium of retracing static images onto drawing after drawing.{{sfn|Kundert-Gibbs|Kundert-Gibbs|2009|p=46}}  McCay adopted the cel method beginning with ''The Sinking of the Lusitania''.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=188, 193}}

[[File:The Sinking of the Lusitania (Winsor McCay, signed cel).jpg|thumb|alt=A black-and-white drawing of a sinking ship, signed &quot;This is one of my original drawings, Winsor McCay&quot;.|An original [[cel]] from ''The Sinking of the Lusitania'', signed by [[Winsor McCay]] ]]

As with all his films, McCay financed ''Lusitania'' himself.  The cels were an added expense, but greatly reduced the amount of drawing necessary in contrast to McCay's earlier methods.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=193}}  The cels used were thicker than those that later became industry standard, and had a &quot;tooth&quot;, or rough surface, that could hold pencil, [[wash (visual arts)|wash]], and crayon, as well as ink lines.  The amount of rendering caused the cels to buckle, which made it difficult to keep them aligned for photographing; Fitzsimmons addressed this problem using a modified loose-leaf binder.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=193}}

McCay said it took him about eight weeks to produce eight seconds worth of film.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=193}}  The claimed 25,000 drawings{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=195}}{{efn|Bill Mikulak notes that at 25,000 frames at 16 [[Frame rate|frames per second]] would make the film 26 minutes long, not 12, assuming that one drawing was produced per frame.{{sfn|Mikulak|1997|p=71}} }} filled 900 feet of film.{{sfn|Bottomore|2000|p=161}}  ''Lusitania'' was registered for copyright on July 19, 1918,{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=195}}{{efn|John Canemaker dates the first showing as July 20;{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=195}} Earl Theisen dates the première as August 15, 1918.{{sfn|Theisen|1933|p=84}} }} and was released by [[Jewel Productions]]{{sfn|Theisen|1933|p=84}} who were reported to have acquired it for the highest price paid for a one-reel film up to that time.{{sfn|Motography staff|1918|p=74}}  It was included as part of a [[Universal Studios]] Weekly [[newsreel]]{{sfn|Crafton|1993|p=116}} and featured on the cover of an issue of Universal's in-house publication ''The Moving Picture Weekly''.{{sfn|Callahan|1988|p=227}}{{efn|The issue of ''The Moving Picture Weekly'' for July 27, 1918.{{sfn|Callahan|1988|p=227}} }}  Its première in England followed in May 1919.{{sfn|Bottomore|2000|p=161}}  Advertisements called it &quot;{{interp|t}}he world's only record of the crime that shocked humanity&quot;.{{sfn|Bottomore|2000|p=161}}

==Style==

[[File:Winsor McCay - The Sinking of the Lusitania still - periscopes.large.jpg|left|thumb|alt=A black-and-white film still.  An ocean scene.  In the distance is an ocean liner.  In the foreground, two periscopes breach the water.|A [[U-boat|German submarine]] spies on the ''Lusitania''.]]

The animation combines editorial cartooning techniques with live-action-like sequences,{{sfn|DelGaudio|1997|p=190}} and is considered McCay's most realistic effort; the intertitles emphasized that the film was a &quot;historical record&quot; of the event.  McCay animated the action in what animation historian Donald Crafton describes as a &quot;realistic graphic style&quot;.{{sfn|Telotte|2010|p=49}}  The film has a dark mood and strong propagandist feel.  It depicts the terrifying fates of the passengers, such as the drowning of children{{sfn|Bottomore|2000|p=161}} and human chains of passengers jumping to their deaths.{{sfn|Crafton|1993|p=117}}  The artwork is highly detailed, the animation fluid and naturalistic.{{sfn|Bottomore|2000|p=161}}  McCay used [[Cross-cutting|alternating shots]] to simulate the feel of a newsreel,{{sfn|Crafton|1993|p=116}} which reinforced the film's realistic feel.{{sfn|Telotte|2010|p=49}}

McCay made stylistic choices to add emotion to the &quot;historical record&quot;, as in the anxiety-inducing shots of the submarines lurking beneath the surface, and abstract styling of the white sheets of sky and sea, vast voids which engorge themselves on the drowning bodies.{{sfn|Telotte|2010|pp=49–50}}  Animation historian Paul Wells suggested the [[negative space]] in the frames filled viewers with anxiety through [[psychological projection]] or [[introjection]], [[Psychoanalysis|Freudian]] ideas that had begun circulating in the years before the film's release.{{sfn|Telotte|2010|p=50}}  Scholar Ulrich Merkl suggests that as a newspaperman, McCay was likely aware of Freud's widely reported work, though McCay never publicly acknowledged such an influence.{{sfn|Taylor|2007|pp=552–553}}

==Reception and legacy==

[[File:HearstAbout1910.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=A black-and-white photograph of a middle-aged man in a business suit.|[[William Randolph Hearst]] curbed McCay's animation work to focus his employee on editorial cartooning.]]

''The Sinking of the Lusitania'' was noted as a work of [[war film|war]] propaganda,{{sfn|Theisen|1933|p=85}} and is often called the longest work of animation of its time.{{sfn|Mikulak|1997|p=71}}{{efn|The running times of surviving copies of McCay's ''[[Gertie the Dinosaur]]'' (1914) and ''Lusitania'' are close in length, but the animated portion in ''Gertie'' is significantly shorter than that of ''Lusitania''.  An Argentine animator, [[Quirino Cristiani]], reportedly produced a [[lost film|now-lost]] 70-minute animated film ''[[El Apóstol]]'', whose first screening was November 9, 1917.{{sfn|Mikulak|1997|p=71}} }}  The film is likely the earliest [[animated documentary]].{{sfn|Wells|2002|p=116}}{{efn|A lost animated film from Britain depicted in animation the sinkings of the ''Lusitania'' and [[SS Aztec|SS ''Aztec'']].  The film was released in 1918 and may have preceded McCay's.{{sfnm|1a1=Bottomore|1y=2000|1p=161|2a1=Wells|2y=2002|2p=116}} }}  McCay's biographer, animator [[John Canemaker]], called ''The Sinking of the Lusitania'' &quot;a monumental work in the history of the animated film&quot;.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=197}}  Admired by his animation contemporaries, Canemaker wrote that it &quot;did not revolutionize the film cartoons of its time&quot;{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=197}} as McCay's skills were beyond what his contemporaries were able to follow.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=197}}  In the era that followed, animation studios made occasional non-fiction films, but most were comedic shorts lasting no more than seven minutes.  Animation continued in its role of supporting feature films rather than as the main attraction,{{sfn|Callahan|1988|pp=227–228}} and rarely received reviews.{{sfn|Hoffer|1976|pp=27–28}}  ''Lusitania'' was not a commercial success; after a few years in theaters, ''Lusitania'' brought McCay about $80,000.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=193}}  McCay made at least seven further films, only three of which are known to have seen commercial release.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=197–198, 254}}

After 1921, when Hearst learned McCay devoted more of his time to animation than to his newspaper illustrations, Hearst required McCay to give up animation.{{sfn|Sito|2006|p=36}}  He had plans for several animation projects that never came to fruition, including a collaboration with ''Jungle Imps'' author [[George Randolph Chester]], a musical film called ''The Barnyard Band'',{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=198}} and a film about the Americans' role in World&amp;nbsp;War&amp;nbsp;I.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=198, 217}}  Later in life, McCay at times publicly expressed his dissatisfaction with the animation industry as it had become—he had envisioned animation as an art, and lamented how it had become a trade.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|pp=199, 239}}  According to Canemaker, it was not until [[Walt Disney Animation Studios|Disney]]'s feature films in the 1930s that the animation industry caught up with McCay's level of technique.{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=197}}

Animation historian Paul Wells described ''Lusitania'' as &quot;a seminal moment in the development of the animated film&quot;{{sfn|Telotte|2010|p=49}} for its combination of documentary style with propagandist elements, and considered it an example of animation as a form of [[Modernism]].{{sfn|Telotte|2010|p=49}}  Steve Bottomore called the film &quot;{{interp|t}}he most significant cinematic version of the {{interp|''Lusitania''}} disaster&quot;.  A review in ''The Cinema'' praised the film, especially the scene in which the first torpedo explodes, which it called &quot;more than reality&quot;.{{sfn|Bottomore|2000|p=161}}

==Notes==

{{Notelist|colwidth=40em}}

==References==

{{Reflist|20em}}

===Works cited===

====Books====

{{Refbegin|colwidth=40em}}

* {{cite book
|last       = Barrier
|first      = Michael
|authorlink = Michael Barrier (historian)
|title      = Hollywood Cartoons: American Animation in Its Golden Age
|url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=zDJXnzMh7bkC
|year       = 2003
|publisher  = Oxford University Press
|isbn       = 978-0-19-516729-0
|ref        = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last      = Beckerman
|first     = Howard
|title     = Animation: The Whole Story
|url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=EjW6cCE4v1QC
|year      = 2003
|publisher = [[Skyhorse Publishing]]
|isbn      = 978-1-58115-301-9
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last       = Berenbaum
|first      = May R.
|authorlink = May Berenbaum
|title      = The Earwig's Tail: A Modern Bestiary of Multi-Legged Legends
|url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=SPxvx0X22XEC
|year       = 2009
|publisher  = [[Harvard University Press]]
|isbn       = 978-0-674-03540-9
|ref        = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last      = Bottomore
|first     = Stephen
|title     = The Titanic and Silent Cinema
|url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=2KGJJsUggtAC
|year      = 2000
|publisher = [[The Projection Box]]
|isbn      = 978-1-903000-00-7
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last        = Canemaker
|first       = John
|author-link = John Canemaker
|title       = Winsor McCay: His Life and Art
|url         = https://books.google.com/books?id=vs82AQAAIAAJ
|edition     = Revised
|year        = 2005
|publisher   = [[Abrams Books]]
|isbn        = 978-0-8109-5941-5
|ref         = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last         = Canwell
|first        = Bruce
|title        = Bringing Up Father: From Sea to Shining Sea the Cross-Country Tour of 1939–1940
|editor-first = Dean
|editor-last  = Mullaney
|editor1-link = Dean Mullaney
|year         = 2009
|publisher    = [[IDW Publishing]]
|isbn         = 978-1-60010-508-1
|ref          = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last      = Crafton
|first     = Donald
|title     = Before Mickey: The Animated Film 1898–1928
|year      = 1993
|publisher = [[University of Chicago Press]]
|url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=yaeJFVTedysC
|isbn      = 978-0-226-11667-9
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite book
|author    = Dover editors
|title     = Dreams of the Rarebit Fiend
|year      = 1973
|publisher = [[Dover Publications]]
|isbn      = 978-0-486-21347-7
|ref       = ref}}
* {{cite book
|last       = Harvey
|first      = Robert C.
|authorlink = R. C. Harvey
|title      = The Art of the Funnies: An Aesthetic History
|url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=vaSHrtEKchoC
|year       = 1994
|publisher  = [[University Press of Mississippi]]
|isbn       = 978-0-87805-612-5
|ref        = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last1     = Kundert-Gibbs
|first1    = John
|last2     = Kundert-Gibbs
|first2    = Kristin
|title     = Action!: Acting Lessons for CG Animators
|url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=UZPr6xvPnokC
|year      = 2009
|publisher = [[John Wiley &amp; Sons]]
|isbn      = 978-0-470-59605-0
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last       = Marshall
|first      = Samuel Lyman Atwood
|authorlink = S. L. A. Marshall
|title      = World War I
|url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=xN7t7DgsclcC
|year       = 1964
|publisher  = [[Houghton Mifflin Harcourt]]
|isbn       = 978-0-618-05686-6
|ref        = harv}}
*{{cite book
|last      = Ramsay
|first     = David
|title     = Lusitania: Saga and Myth
|date      = 2001
|publisher = [[Chatham Publishing]]
|location  = London
|isbn      = 978-1-86176-170-5
|url       = {{google books|BRusY6BF68EC|plainurl=yes}}
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last1       = Roland
|first1      = Alex
|authorlink1 = Alex Roland
|last2       = Bolster
|first2      = W. Jeffrey
|authorlink2 = W. Jeffrey Bolster
|last3       = Keyssar
|first3      = Alexander
|authorlink3 = Alexander Keyssar
|title       = The Way of the Ship: America's Maritime History Reenvisoned, 1600–2000
|url         = https://books.google.com/books?id=Qf2QiRYXcdUC
|year        = 2008
|publisher   = John Wiley &amp; Sons
|isbn        = 978-0-470-13600-3
|ref         = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last       = Sabin
|first      = Roger
|authorlink = Roger Sabin
|title      = Adult Comics: An Introduction
|publisher  = Routledge
|year       = 1993
|isbn       = 978-0-415-04419-6
|ref        = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last       = Sito
|first      = Tom
|authorlink = Tom Sito
|title      = Drawing the Line: The Untold Story of the Animation Unions from Bosko to Bart Simpson
|url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=XZ0PsCWPSZ0C
|year       = 2006
|publisher  = [[University Press of Kentucky]]
|isbn       = 978-0-8131-2407-0
|ref        = harv}}
* {{cite book
|ref          = harv
|first        = Jeremy
|last         = Taylor
|editor-last  = Merkl
|editor-first = Ulrich
|title        = The Complete Dream of the Rarebit Fiend (1904–1913) by Winsor McCay 'Silas'
|location     = Catalog of episodes &amp; text of the book
|chapter      = Some archetypal symbolic aspects of ''Dream of the Rarebit Fiend''
|pages        = 552–561
|type         = .doc
|year         = 2007
|publisher    = Ulrich Merkl
|isbn         = 978-3-00-020751-8}} (on included DVD)
* {{cite book
|last      = Telotte
|first     = J. P.
|title     = Animating Space: From Mickey to Wall-E
|url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=mZ5CfCXl3u4C
|year      = 2010
|publisher = [[University Press of Kentucky]]
|isbn      = 978-0-8131-2586-2
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last         = Theisen
|first        = Earl
|chapter      = The History of the Animated Cartoon
|pages        = 84–87
|editor-last  = Fielding
|editor-first = Raymond
|title        = A Technological History of Motion Pictures and Television
|url          = https://books.google.com/books?id=qn6_5XqRXVsC
|year         = 1967
|origyear     = 1933
|publisher    = University of California Press
|isbn         = 978-0-520-00411-5
|ref          = harv}}
* {{cite book
|last      = Wells
|first     = Paul
|title     = Animation: Genre and Authorship
|url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=Nj3hwD1Sk-QC
|year      = 2002
|publisher = Wallflower Press
|isbn      = 978-1-903364-20-8
|ref       = harv}}

{{Refend}}

====Journals====

{{Refbegin|colwidth=40em}}

* {{cite journal
|last      = Callahan
|first     = David
|title     = Cel Animation: Mass Production and Marginalization in the Animated Film Industry
|journal   = Film History
|volume    = 2
|issue     = 3
|date=September–October 1988
|pages     = 223–228
|publisher = Indiana University Press
|jstor     = 3815119
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite journal
|last      = DelGaudio
|first     = Sybil
|title     = If Truth Be Told, Can 'Toons Tell It? Documentary and Animation
|journal   = Film History
|volume    = 9
|issue     = 2
|year      = 1997
|pages     = 189–199
|publisher = [[Indiana University Press]]
|jstor     = 3815174
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite journal
|last      = Hoffer
|first     = Tom
|title     = From Comic Strips to Animation: Some Perspective on Winsor McCay
|journal   = Journal of the University Film Association
|volume    = 28
|issue     = 2
|date=Spring 1976
|pages     = 23–32
|publisher = University of Illinois Press
|jstor     = 20687319
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite journal
|last    = McKinney
|first   = Kirsten
|title   = The Waking Life of Winsor McCay: Social Commentary in A Pilgrim’s Progress by Mr. Bunion
|date    = July 2015
|url     = http://scholarship.richmond.edu/student-publications/1/
|journal = International Journal of Comic Art
|volume  = 17
|issue   = 1
|ref     = harv}}
* {{cite journal
|last      = Mikulak
|first     = Bill
|title     = Mickey Meets Mondrian: Cartoons Enter the Museum of Modern Art
|journal   = Cinema Journal
|volume    = 36
|issue     = 3
|date=Spring 1997
|pages     = 56–72
|publisher = University of Texas Press on behalf of the Society for Cinema &amp; Media Studies
|jstor     = 1225675
|ref       = harv}}
* {{cite journal
|author  = Motography staff
|title   = Pays Big Price for One-Reeler
|journal = Motography
|volume  = 20
|issue   = 2
|page    = 74
|date    = 1918-07-13
|url     = https://archive.org/stream/motography20elec#page/74/mode/1up
|ref     = harv}}
* {{cite journal
|title   = Impression and Expression: Rethinking the Animated Image Through Winsor McCay
|first   = Daniel
|last    = McKenna
|journal = Synoptique
|volume  = 2
|issue   = 2
|date=Fall 2013
|url     = http://synoptique.hybrid.concordia.ca/index.php/main/article/view/18/25
|ref     = harv}}

{{Refend}}

====Other sources====

{{Refbegin}}&lt;!-- |colwidth=40em}} --&gt;

* {{cite news
|last       = Hubbard
|first      = Amy
|title      = Celebrating Little Nemo by Winsor McCay; his 'demons' made him do it
|date       = 2012-10-15
|newspaper  = [[Los Angeles Times]]
|url        = http://articles.latimes.com/2012/oct/15/nation/la-na-nn-little-nemo-google-doodle-20121015
|accessdate = 2012-12-15
|ref        = {{SfnRef|Hubbard|2012}}
}}

{{Refend}}

==Further reading==

{{Refbegin}}

* {{cite book
|last      = Wells
|first     = Paul
|title     = Animation And America
|url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=jhgXnXaOvlwC
|year      = 2002
|publisher = Edinburgh University Press
|isbn      = 978-1-85331-203-8}}

{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|The Sinking of the Lusitania (film)}}
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0009620 ''The Sinking of the Lusitania'' at IMDB]

{{Winsor McCay}}
{{Portal bar|Animation|Disasters|Film|Nautical|World War I}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sinking Of The Lusitania, The}}
[[Category:1918 films]]
[[Category:1910s American animated films]]
[[Category:1910s animated short films]]
[[Category:1910s documentary films]]
[[Category:Black-and-white documentary films]]
[[Category:American black-and-white films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American silent short films]]
[[Category:American World War I propaganda films]]
[[Category:Animated documentary films]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Documentary films about maritime disasters]]
[[Category:Films directed by Winsor McCay]]
[[Category:Films set in the Atlantic Ocean]]
[[Category:RMS Lusitania]]</text>
      <sha1>45oe0xnyx0zhswftonnr7nmd8xu095o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
