<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>William of Wrotham</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27407062</id>
    <revision>
      <id>720232542</id>
      <parentid>701084165</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-14T15:15:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ealdgyth</username>
        <id>4497767</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */ fix</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21161">{{Infobox Christian leader
| name  = William of Wrotham
| title = [[Archdeacon of Taunton]]
| image = 050715 140 lydford castle.jpg
| imagesize = 250px
| alt         = 
| caption     = Ruins of [[Lydford Castle]], which was in William's custody
| enthroned   = 1204
| ended       = [[circa|c.]] 1217
| predecessor = Robert de Geldford&lt;ref name=BHOArchTaunt/&gt;
| successor   = Peter&lt;ref name=BHOArchTaunt/&gt;
&lt;!---------- Personal details ----------&gt;
| birth_name  = William
| birth_date  = 
| birth_place = 
| death_date  = c. 1217
| death_place = 
| nationality = English
| parents     = Godwin
}}

'''William of Wrotham''' or '''William de Wrotham'''&lt;ref name=Brooks572/&gt; (died [[circa|c.]] 1217) was a medieval English royal administrator and clergyman. Although a late 13th-century source says that William held a royal office under King [[Henry II of England]] (reigned 1154–1189), the first contemporary reference to William is in 1197, when he became responsible among other things for the royal tin mines. He also held ecclesiastical office, eventually becoming [[Archdeacon of Taunton]], and served King [[John of England]] as an administrator of ecclesiastical lands and a collector of taxes.

William's main administrative work was naval. He was in charge of the royal fleet in the south of England in 1205, and was one of those responsible for the development of [[Portsmouth]] as a naval dockyard. He continued to be involved in naval matters until 1214 or later, but by 1215 he had joined the [[First Barons' War]] against John. After John's death in 1216, William returned to the royalist cause. He probably died in late 1217. Known to a contemporary chronicler as one of John's &quot;evil advisers&quot;, William is said by modern historians to have had a &quot;special responsibility for ports, customs, and the navy&quot;,&lt;ref name=Bartlett260/&gt; and was &quot;keeper of ports&quot;, a forerunner of the office of [[First Lord of the Admiralty]].

==Early life==

Little is known of William's background or family, except that his father Godwin [[Feudal land tenure in England|held]] land in [[Shipbourne]], near [[Wrotham]] in Kent, perhaps as a [[vassal]] of the [[Archbishop of Canterbury|Archbishops of Canterbury]]. William's brother Richard was named as William's deputy in 1207.&lt;ref name=DNB&gt;Golding &quot;Wrotham, William of&quot; ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography''&lt;/ref&gt;

According to late 13th-century documents, the [[Hundred Rolls]], King Henry II gave William the office of [[Steward (office)|steward]] of [[Exmoor]], and lands at [[North Petherton]], Somerset.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; William was the [[prebend]] of [[Decuman|St Decumans]] in the [[cathedral chapter]] of [[Bath Abbey|Bath Cathedral]] by 9 May 1204. He claimed to have held the office since 1194 during a later dispute with [[Savaric FitzGeldewin|Savaric fitzGeldewin]], the [[Bishop of Bath]] and another [[canon (priest)|canon]] of the cathedral, Roger Porretanus, who claimed the prebend. By 23 December 1205, William had secured a papal judgement against Roger.&lt;ref name=BHOPreb&gt;Greenway ''[http://british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=34393 Fasti Ecclesiae Anglicanae 1066–1300: Volume 7: Bath and Wells: Prebendaries: St Decumans]''&lt;/ref&gt;

William may have owed his advancement in royal service to [[Geoffrey fitz Peter|Geoffrey fitzPeter]], a royal judge. In 1197 he granted William a [[manor]] at [[Sutton-at-Hone]], Kent, which later was supposed to become a hospital, but instead eventually became a [[preceptory]] for the [[Knights Hospitaller]]. From 1197 William was responsible for the collection of revenues from Geoffrey's lands at [[Lydford]], Devon, and held the office of chief [[forester]] of Somerset; it is unclear to whom he owed that position.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt;

==Royal service==

In 1197, [[Hubert Walter]], who was Archbishop of Canterbury and [[Justiciar]], appointed William to the administration of the royal [[stannary|stannaries]], or tin mines, and in 1198 William was placed in charge of tin production, an office later known as the [[Lord Warden of the Stannaries]]. Under his control the mines became much more lucrative for the king, and accounted for a total of £1100 in William's first year of administration.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; As part of his administrative work he became the first warden of [[Lydford Castle]] after it was constructed in the 1190s.&lt;ref name=Maddicott37&gt;Maddicott &quot;Trade, Industry and the Wealth of King Alfred&quot; ''Past &amp; Present'' p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The castle served as a prison for the administrators of the stannaries besides its other functions.&lt;ref name=Maddicott37/&gt;}} In 1199 he was involved in a dispute over the stannaries with another official, Hugh Bardulf, temporarily losing control of them&amp;nbsp;– along with his office as sheriff&amp;nbsp;– in 1200. The reason for the loss of these offices is uncertain.&lt;ref name=Powell181&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; After restoration to office, he remained as Lord Warden of the Stannaries until 1215.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt;

In 1198 and 1199, William was [[High Sheriff of Devon|Sheriff of Devon]] and [[High Sheriff of Cornwall|Sheriff of Cornwall]], along with another royal servant, and served as a [[royal justice]].&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt;{{efn|His fellow sheriff was [[John de Torrington]].&lt;ref name=Powell179&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 179&lt;/ref&gt;}} In 1200 he was recorded as a receiver of the [[carucage]], a tax on land, in the [[Pipe roll]]; whether this meant that he was a local or a national collector of the tax is unclear.&lt;ref name=tax15&gt;Mitchell ''Taxation'' pp. 15–16&lt;/ref&gt; By 12 September 1204, William was Archdeacon of Taunton in the [[Diocese of Bath]], and he witnessed the election of [[Jocelin of Wells]] as the new bishop of the [[diocese]].&lt;ref name=BHOArchTaunt&gt;Greenway ''[http://british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=34353 Fasti Ecclesiae Anglicanae 1066–1300: Volume 7: Bath and Wells: Archdeacons: Taunton]''&lt;/ref&gt; He was jointly placed in charge of the mints of London and Canterbury in 1205, along with [[Reginald de Cornhill]], with whom he also shared the collection of the [[Taxation in medieval England|tax of a fifteenth on merchants]], a post the two had held since 1202.{{efn|This tax was imposed on the imports and exports of merchants. William and Reginald also shared this office with [[William of Furnell]].&lt;ref name=Powell182&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' pp. 182–183&lt;/ref&gt;}} In May 1205 William, along with de Cornhill, was given custody of one of three [[Coining (mint)|die]]s for the mint at [[Chichester]]; in July the king gave William's custody to [[Simon of Wells]], the [[Bishop of Chichester]].&lt;ref name=Stewartby294&gt;Stewartby &quot;Lichfield and Chichester&quot; ''Numismatic Chronicle'' p. 294&lt;/ref&gt; William was one of the officials in charge of the collection of a tax of a thirteenth in 1207.&lt;ref name=Tax33&gt;Mitchell ''Taxation'' p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|This tax was assessed as a [[shilling]] for each [[mark (currency)|mark]]'s worth of property owned.&lt;ref name=Warren149&gt;Warren ''King John'' p. 149&lt;/ref&gt;}}

William was also placed in charge of vacant ecclesiastical offices, collecting their revenues for the king.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; He performed this office for the [[Anglican Diocese of Worcester|Diocese of Worcester]] around 1200,&lt;ref name=Tax30&gt;Mitchell ''Taxation'' p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Diocese of Winchester]] in 1204, for [[Glastonbury Abbey]] in 1205, and for [[Whitby Abbey]] in 1206 and 1209.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; From his actions it can be assumed that Wrotham was a member of the [[royal household]], probably working in the [[Wardrobe (government)|wardrobe]].&lt;ref name=Brooks572&gt;Brooks &quot;William de Wrotham&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 572&lt;/ref&gt;

==Naval administration==

William's main administrative work concerned the navy.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; In 1204 he, de Cornhill, and William of Furnell were placed in charge of granting wool export licences. William of Wrotham was also one of the officials charged with supervising the ships dispatched to the coasts in 1204,&lt;ref name=Warren124&gt;Warren ''King John'' pp. 124–125&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|His fellow supervisors of the ships in 1204 were Reginald de Cornhill, William Marsh, and [[John la Warr]].&lt;ref name=Warren124/&gt;}} after the loss of Normandy exposed England to invasion by the French.&lt;ref name=Warren121&gt;Warren ''King John'' p. 121&lt;/ref&gt; In 1205 he was again one of the keepers of the royal fleet along the south coast.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; William was in charge of the 17 ships based in [[Romney Island|Romney]], [[Rye, East Sussex|Rye]], [[Shoreham-by-Sea|Shoreham]], [[Southampton]], [[Winchelsea]], and [[Exeter]], while the rest of the fleet came under Cornhill's control.&lt;ref name=Brooks573&gt;Brooks &quot;William de Wrotham&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 573&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The ships under Cornhill numbered 10 and were based in London, [[Newhaven, East Sussex|Newhaven]], and [[Sandwich, Kent|Sandwich]].&lt;ref name=Brooks573/&gt;}} In the same year, he was also in charge of naval spending for the attempted invasion of France,&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; which in June alone totalled over 470 [[pound sterling|pounds]].  William surrendered custody of [[Taunton Castle]] to [[Peter de Taraton]] in July and was in charge of purchasing the royal wine in August. No further naval duties are recorded until November, when along with Cornhill he was responsible for assessing the ports.&lt;ref name=Brooks574&gt;Brooks &quot;William de Wrotham&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 574&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1206 William was in charge of the naval forces in the [[Cinque Ports]] and commanded the fleet that invaded [[Poitou]].&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; Whether he accompanied the fleet or stayed in England after it sailed is unclear; according to two historians&amp;nbsp;– F. W. Brooks and R. W. Powell&amp;nbsp;– it is more likely he stayed.&lt;ref name=Powell184&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 184&lt;/ref&gt; From 1206 until 1215 he was effectively commander of King [[John, King of England|John]]'s navy, and helped to develop [[Portsmouth]] as a royal dockyard.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; In 1208 William was put in charge of ensuring that no ships sailed without royal permission. That year he also oversaw the naval preparations made by the Cinque Ports.&lt;ref name=Brooks576/&gt; The purpose of these preparations is unknown; the ''[[Annals of Dunstable]]'' ascribe to John a desire to oppress the Cinque Ports.&lt;ref name=Powell185&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 185&lt;/ref&gt; During May 1208 a royal order was issued that William's deputies in all the seaports should seize any ships in the ports that were from foreign countries, excluding Denmark, Norway and other countries that did not oppose John's diplomatic efforts. A gap in the governmental records does not allow a detailed view of William's activities for the next years, until 1212, when William is shown performing many of the same duties as earlier.&lt;ref name=Brooks576&gt;Brooks &quot;William de Wrotham&quot; ''English Historical Review'' pp. 576–577&lt;/ref&gt; He was in charge of repair of some ships and the construction of a large new ship, named the ''Deulabenit'', owned by the king.&lt;ref name=Powell186&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 186&lt;/ref&gt; William was also responsible for [[impressment|impressing]] privately owned merchant ships into royal service. These ships were used in the naval action of the [[Battle of Damme]] at [[Zwyn]] in 1213, when a fleet under [[William Longespée, 3rd Earl of Salisbury|William Longespee]], the Earl of Salisbury, destroyed a substantial French naval force and sacked the town of [[Damme]].&lt;ref name=Rose5&gt;Rose &quot;Wall of England&quot; ''Oxford Illustrated History of the Royal Navy'' pp. 5–6&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 1213 William was directing the efforts of the seaports of south-western England and the Cinque Ports in naval affairs.&lt;ref name=Brooks578/&gt; He was also responsible for the setting up of a supply depot for the navy in June 1213, for which he received supplies from the diocese of Chichester.&lt;ref name=Powell187&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 187&lt;/ref&gt; In 1214 William had custody of some royal prisoners.&lt;ref name=Brooks578&gt;Brooks &quot;William de Wrotham&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 578&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, the king ordered him to return a merchant ship if he had indeed seized it from its owner, Joscelin de Hampton.&lt;ref name=Powell188&gt;Powell &quot;Administration of the Navy&quot; ''English Historical Review'' p. 188&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1214, William co-founded the hospital of [[Domus Dei]] in Portsmouth with [[Peter des Roches]], the [[Bishop of Winchester]]. The foundation was confirmed by the king in October 1214.&lt;ref name=Roches114&gt;Vincent ''Peter des Roches'' p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;

John rewarded William for his service with churches in [[Isle of Sheppey|Sheppey]] and [[East Malling]], which were granted in 1207,{{efn|William received the ecclesiastical revenues from these churches, a common practice.&lt;ref name=Moorman28&gt;Moorman ''Church Life'' pp. 28–32&lt;/ref&gt;}} and the right to oversee the [[royal forest]]s in Cornwall and Devon. Other grants included lands in [[Dartford]] and Sutton-at-Hone that had [[escheat]]ed to the crown, lands in Westminster and a prebend in the royal ecclesiastical foundation at Hastings.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt;

==Later years and legacy==

During John's reign, Pope [[Pope Innocent III|Innocent III]] placed an [[interdict]] on England, forbidding public celebration of sacred rites in English churches. William supported John, and remained in England. The medieval chronicler [[Roger of Wendover]] named William as one of John's &quot;evil advisers&quot;,&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; or &quot;most wicked counsellors&quot;. Modern historians argue that Roger's account of John's reign, while containing some truth, was written to defame men who were prominent in the early years of King [[Henry III of England|Henry III]], John's son who had succeeded his father in October 1216.&lt;ref name=Evil&gt;Vincent &quot;King John's evil counsellors&quot; ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Warren255&gt;Warren ''King John'' pp. 255–256&lt;/ref&gt; According to Nicholas Vincent, while Roger's account of the exactions and crimes of the members of his list of evil advisers certainly had a strong basis of truth, it was also greatly exaggerated.&lt;ref name=Evil/&gt; [[W. L. Warren]] agrees and points out that many of the details of Roger's accounts that can be checked with other records are wrong, making the other parts of his stories suspect.&lt;ref name=Warren11&gt;Warren ''King John'' pp. 11–14&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1215 William joined the baronial rebellion against John, and lost his naval offices, the royal forester's office for Somerset, and custody of Lydford Castle.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt; In May 1216 the king offered William a safe conduct, which noted that William had fled overseas. The letters were witnessed by Peter des Roches.&lt;ref name=Roches126&gt;Vincent ''Peter des Roches'' p. 126&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-1217, he rejoined the royalist cause, returning to the side of Henry III.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt;  This action regained him some of his lost lands.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt;

William last appeared in documents on 25 July 1217 and was dead by 16 February 1218, probably before 2 December 1217, when someone else is mentioned as archdeacon.&lt;ref name=BHOArchTaunt/&gt; On 16 February 1218, John Marshall became the guardian of Richard, William's nephew and heir, who was the son of William's brother Richard.&lt;ref name=DNB/&gt;

William has been described as having a &quot;special responsibility for ports, customs, and the navy&quot; by the historian [[Robert Bartlett (historian)|Robert Bartlett]].&lt;ref name=Bartlett260&gt;Bartlett ''England Under the Norman and Angevin Kings'' p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; He is usually given the title of &quot;keeper of ports&quot; or &quot;keeper of galleys&quot;, which Ralph Turner equates with being [[First Lord of the Admiralty]] in later history.&lt;ref name=Evil96&gt;Turner ''King John'' p. 96&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes this would be given as ''&quot;custos portum maris&quot;'' in Latin, or &quot;keeper of the seaports&quot;.&lt;ref name=Joliffe147&gt;Joliffe ''Angevin Kingship'' p. 147 note 1&lt;/ref&gt; At other times he was titled &quot;keeper of the king's ships&quot;.&lt;ref name=Joliffe288&gt;Joliffe ''Angevin Kingship'' p. 288&lt;/ref&gt; Bartlett also called William &quot;one of the king's most important administrators&quot;.&lt;ref name=Bartlett260/&gt; Charles Young said that William's service to King John was a &quot;distinguished administrative career&quot;,&lt;ref name=Young109&gt;Young ''Hubert Walter'' p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; and J. E. A. Joliffe called William one of the &quot;greatest of the king's clerks&quot;.&lt;ref name=Joliffe290&gt;Joliffe ''Angevin Kingship'' p. 290&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{notelist|40em}}

==Citations==
{{reflist|40em}}

==References==
{{refbegin|60em}}
* {{cite book |author=Bartlett, Robert C. |authorlink=Robert Bartlett (historian)|title=England Under the Norman and Angevin Kings: 1075–1225 |publisher=Clarendon Press |location=Oxford, UK |year=2000 |isbn=0-19-822741-8 }}
* {{cite journal|author=Brooks, F. W. |title=William de Wrotham and the Office of Keeper of the King's Ports and Galleys|journal= [[The English Historical Review]] |volume=40 |date=October 1925 |pages=570–579 |doi=10.1093/ehr/xl.clx.570 |jstor= 552525}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |author= Golding, Brian |title=Wrotham, William of (d. 1217/18) |encyclopedia =Oxford Dictionary of National Biography |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2004 |url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/30087 |accessdate= 19 May 2010 |format= {{ODNBsub}}|oclc=66605350}}
* {{cite book |author= Greenway, Diana E. |url=http://british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=34353 |title=Fasti Ecclesiae Anglicanae 1066–1300: Volume 7: Bath and Wells: Archdeacons: Taunton |publisher=Institute of Historical Research |year=2001 |accessdate= 19 May 2010}}
* {{cite book |author= Greenway, Diana E. |url=http://british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=34393 |title=Fasti Ecclesiae Anglicanae 1066–1300: Volume 7: Bath and Wells: Prebendaries: St Decumans |publisher=Institute of Historical Research |year=2001|accessdate= 19 May 2010}}
* {{cite book |author= Joliffe, J. E. A. |title= Angevin Kingship  |year= 1955|publisher= Adam and Charles Black |location=London |oclc= 8936103 }}
* {{cite journal |author=Maddicott, J. R. |authorlink=John Maddicott |title=Trade, Industry and the Wealth of King Alfred |journal= [[Past &amp; Present (journal)|Past &amp; Present]] |volume=123 |number=123 |date=May 1989 |pages=3–51 |jstor= 650989 |doi= 10.1093/past/123.1.3}}
* {{cite book |author=Mitchell, Sydney Knox |title=Taxation in Medieval England |publisher=Archon Books |location=Hamden, CT |year=1971 |isbn=0-208-00956-6 }}
* {{cite book |author=Moorman, John R. H. |authorlink= John Moorman  |title= Church Life in England in the Thirteenth Century  |year=1955|edition=Revised |publisher= Cambridge University Press |location= Cambridge, UK |oclc= 213820968  }}
* {{cite journal |author=Powell, W. R.  |title=The Administration of the Navy and the Stannaries, 1189–1216 |journal=[[The English Historical Review]] |volume= 71 |issue=279 |date= April 1956 |pages=176–188 |jstor=557697 |doi= 10.1093/ehr/LXXI.279.177}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |author=Rose, Susan |title=The Wall of England, to 1500 |encyclopedia = The Oxford Illustrated History of the Royal Navy |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford, UK |year=1995 |isbn=0-19-211675-4 |editor=Hill, R. J. |pages=1–23}}
* {{cite journal |author=Stewartby, Lord |title=Lichfield and Chichester |journal = The Numismatic Chronicle |year=2001 |volume=161 |pages=293–295 |jstor= 42668028}}
* {{cite book |author=Turner, Ralph V. |title=King John: England's Evil King? |publisher=Tempus |location=Stroud, UK |year= 2005 |isbn=0-7524-3385-7}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |author= Vincent, Nicholas |title=King John's evil counsellors (act. 1208–1214) |encyclopedia= Oxford Dictionary of National Biography |publisher=Oxford University Press |url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/theme/95591 |accessdate= 12 January 2015 | format={{ODNBsub}}|oclc=66605350}}
* {{cite book |author= Vincent, Nicholas |title=Peter des Roches: An Alien in English Politics 1205–1238 |origyear=1996  |year=2002|edition=Reprint |publisher= Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, UK |series =Cambridge Series in Medieval Life and Thought |isbn=0-521-52215-3  }}
* {{cite book |author=Warren, W. L. |authorlink=W. L. Warren|title=King John |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley, CA |year=1978 |isbn=0-520-03643-3 }}
* {{cite book |author=Young, Charles R.|title= Hubert Walter: Lord of Canterbury and Lord of England |year=1968 |publisher= Duke University Press |location= Durham, NC |oclc= 443445  }}
{{refend}}

{{Authority control}}
{{featured article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2014}}
{{EngvarB|date=September 2014}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:William Of Wrotham}}
[[Category:13th-century Christian clergy]]
[[Category:13th-century English people]]
[[Category:High Sheriffs of Cornwall]]
[[Category:High Sheriffs of Devon]]
[[Category:English judges]]
[[Category:1210s deaths]]
[[Category:Archdeacons of Taunton]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]</text>
      <sha1>ex1osl3arhp941a7nk0uoqqxx569x19</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
