<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>William Harper (Rhodesian politician)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>40009589</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744807220</id>
      <parentid>729969915</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-17T15:15:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anomalocaris</username>
        <id>299039</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>{{cite -journal+news}}; logical quotes; avoid links in quotes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36355">{{featured article}}

{{Infobox politician
|name               = William Harper
|image              = William Harper 1965.jpg
|imagesize          
|alt                = William Harper at an airport, wearing a hat
|caption            = Harper, photographed in 1965
|birthname          = William John Harper
|birth_date         = {{Birth date|1916|07|22|df=y}}
|birth_place        = [[Kolkata|Calcutta]], [[British Raj|British India]]
|death_date         ={{Death date and age|2006|09|08|1916|07|22|df=y}}
|death_place        = &lt;!-- not given in source --&gt;
|restingplace       =
|restingplacecoordinates =
|citizenship        =
|nationality        =
|party              = {{plainlist|
*[[Dominion Party]] (1958–62)
*[[Rhodesian Front]] (1962–68)
*United Conservative Party (1974–76)}}
|spouse             = Elizabeth{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=473}}
&lt;!--Military service--&gt;
|allegiance         = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
|branch             = {{plainlist|
*[[Royal Air Force]]
*[[Royal Australian Air Force]]}}
|serviceyears       = 1937–49
|rank               = [[Wing commander (rank)|Wing Commander]]
|battles            = Second World War
}}
'''William John Harper''' (22 July 1916&amp;nbsp;– 8 September 2006) was a politician, [[general contractor]] and [[Royal Air Force]] fighter pilot who served as a Cabinet minister in [[Rhodesia]] (or [[Southern Rhodesia]]) from 1962 to 1968, and [[signatories of Rhodesia's Unilateral Declaration of Independence|signed]] that country's [[Rhodesia's Unilateral Declaration of Independence|Unilateral Declaration of Independence]] (UDI) from Britain in 1965. Born into a prominent [[Anglo-Indian]] merchant family in [[Kolkata|Calcutta]], Harper was educated in India and England and joined the RAF in 1937. He served as an officer throughout the Second World War and saw action as one of &quot;[[The Few]]&quot; in the [[Battle of Britain]], during which he was wounded in action. Appalled by Britain's granting of independence to India in 1947, he emigrated to Rhodesia on retiring from the air force two years later.

Harper contended that British rule in the subcontinent should never have ended, and took a similar stance regarding his adopted homeland, reportedly declaring that it, South Africa and the neighbouring Portuguese territories would &quot;be under white rule forever&quot;.&lt;ref name=forever/&gt; He entered politics with the [[Dominion Party]] in 1958 and became Minister of Irrigation, Roads and Road Traffic in the [[Rhodesian Front]] (RF) government in 1962. The head of a far-right group within the RF, he called for Rhodesia to abolish black representation in parliament and adopt &quot;a form of political apartheid&quot;.&lt;ref name=leaderpost68/&gt; When the Prime Minister [[Winston Field]] resigned in 1964, Harper was a front-runner to succeed him, but lost out to [[Ian Smith]], who moved him to the Ministry of Internal Affairs.

Each breakdown or setback during the early years of Smith's premiership prompted press speculation that Harper might replace him. In 1966, when Smith brought a working document back from the [[HMS Tiger (C20)|HMS ''Tiger'']] talks with the British Prime Minister [[Harold Wilson]], Harper led opposition to the terms in Cabinet, contributing to their rejection. Harper resigned from the Rhodesian Front in 1968, soon after Smith dismissed him from the Cabinet, reportedly because Harper had had an extramarital affair with a British agent. He subsequently became a vocal critic of the Prime Minister, greeting each step Smith made towards settlement with black nationalists during the [[Rhodesian Bush War|Bush War]] with public indignation. By the time majority rule began in [[Zimbabwe Rhodesia]] in 1979, following the [[Internal Settlement]] of the previous year, Harper had left for South Africa. He died in 2006 at the age of 90.

==Early life==
William John Harper was born on 22 July 1916 in [[Kolkata|Calcutta]], [[British Raj|British India]],{{sfn|Gillison|1962|p=167}} scion of an old and prominent [[Anglo-Indian]] merchant family that had been based in the subcontinent for generations, working with the [[East India Company]] during the 18th and 19th centuries.{{sfn|Shamuyarira|1966|p=210}} He was educated at [[St. Joseph's School, Darjeeling|North Point]] in [[Darjeeling]], India, and in the English town of [[Windsor, Berkshire|Windsor]].{{sfn|Wynn|2015|p=223}} He grew into a short but tough man who spoke with clipped diction. [[Nathan Shamuyarira]] wrote of him in 1966 that &quot;his tight mouth rarely relaxes into a smile, so&amp;nbsp;... he seems always on the point of losing his temper&quot;.{{sfn|Shamuyarira|1966|p=210}}

==Second World War; Royal Air Force pilot==
[[File:The Battle of Britain HU54414.jpg|thumb|A [[Hawker Hurricane]] of Harper's unit, [[No. 17 Squadron RAF]], during the [[Battle of Britain]]]]
Harper joined the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) in 1937, and was commissioned as an acting [[pilot officer]] on 5 September.&lt;ref name=lg210937&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=34437|startpage=5902|endpage=5903|date=21 September 1937|accessdate=9 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was promoted to [[flying officer]] on 12 February 1940,&lt;ref name=lg200240&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=34794|startpage=1003|endpage=|date=20 February 1940|accessdate=9 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and attached to [[No. 17 Squadron RAF|No. 17 Squadron]].{{sfn|Wynn|2015|p=223}} On 18 May 1940 he shared in the destruction of a [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]] heavy fighter, and a week later he destroyed a [[Junkers Ju 87|Ju&amp;nbsp;87]] &quot;Stuka&quot; [[dive bomber]]. He was appointed B Flight commander, with the rank of acting [[flight lieutenant]], on 26 May. He destroyed another Bf 110 over [[Dunkirk]] three days later, during the [[Dunkirk evacuation|evacuation of Allied forces]], and continued as flight commander until 8 June 1940, reverting to the rank of flying officer. He was again promoted to acting flight lieutenant on 4 July, when he was given command of A Flight.{{sfn|Wynn|2015|p=223}}

From July 1940, still flying with No. 17 Squadron, Harper was one of &quot;[[The Few]]&quot;, the Allied pilots of the [[Battle of Britain]]. On 11 August he shared in the probable destruction of a Bf 110 and damaged a [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] fighter. Four days later, after taking off as part of a group of six [[Hawker Hurricane]]s assigned to intercept more than 20 [[Luftwaffe]] aircraft, Harper contacted the German planes alone and probably destroyed a Bf 109 before being shot down. He crash-landed in a field near the [[Suffolk]] seaside town of [[Felixstowe]], and convalesced in hospital there with wounds to his face and leg.{{sfn|Wynn|2015|p=223}}{{sfn|Collier|2002|pp=134–135}}{{sfn|Young|1969|p=280}} He soon rejoined No. 17 Squadron and continued his command of A Flight from the ground—he returned to the skies on 1 November 1940. A week later he destroyed a Ju 87 and probably another.{{sfn|Wynn|2015|p=223}} Harper received the [[war substantive]] rank of flight lieutenant on 12 February 1941.&lt;ref name=lg300541&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=35176|startpage=3098|endpage=|date=30 May 1941|accessdate=9 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A month later he was posted to No. 57 Operational Training Unit RAF, based at [[Hawarden Airport|RAF Hawarden]] in Wales, as an instructor.{{sfn|Wynn|2015|p=223}}

In September 1941, Harper was seconded to the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) to command [[No. 453 Squadron RAAF]], which was based at Singapore and operated [[Brewster F2A Buffalo|Brewster Buffalo]] fighters.{{sfn|Gillison|1962|p=167}} After suffering heavy losses during the [[Malayan Campaign]] in December, No. 453 Squadron was temporarily amalgamated with another Buffalo unit, [[No. 21 Squadron RAAF]], to form No. 21/453 Squadron under Harper's command.{{sfn|Gillison|1962|p=280}} By February 1942, No. 453 Squadron was denuded of aircraft and its remaining personnel were evacuated to Australia.{{sfn|Gillison|1962|pp=437–438}}  Harper assumed command of [[No. 135 Squadron RAF]] in India in April 1942. In January 1943 he took command of [[No. 92 Squadron RAF|No. 92 (East India) Squadron RAF]] in North Africa,{{sfn|Gillison|1962|p=167}} and was promoted to temporary [[squadron leader]] with seniority backdated to March 1942.&lt;ref name=lg080143&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=35855|startpage=218|endpage=|date=8 January 1943|accessdate=9 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was transferred to England in September 1943 and commanded the [[University Air Squadron]] at [[Leeds]] until 1944. He remained with the RAF following the end of hostilities.{{sfn|Gillison|1962|p=167}}

==Political career==

===Emigration to Rhodesia===
[[File:Federation rhodesia nyasaland.png|thumb|The [[Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland]] (1953–63)|alt=A map. See description]]
Harper was appalled when Britain made India independent in 1947—he held that the British government had unnecessarily caved in to Indian nationalist demands and should have continued in the subcontinent indefinitely. He retained this view for years afterwards.{{sfn|Shamuyarira|1966|p=210}} He retired from the RAF in April 1949 with the rank of [[Wing commander (rank)|wing commander]],&lt;ref name=lg2160&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=38599|supp=yes|startpage=2159|endpage=2160|date=3 May 1949|accessdate=16 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the same year emigrated to [[Southern Rhodesia]], a British colony in southern Africa that had been [[responsible government|self-governing]] since 1923. He settled in the central town of [[Kadoma, Zimbabwe|Gatooma]], where he farmed, mined and set up an earth-moving [[General contractor|contractor]]'s business.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Southern Rhodesian Cabinet: Careers of Ministers
|newspaper=East Africa and Rhodesia
|location=London
|publisher=Africana
|volume=40
|date=23 April 1964
|page=662}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1953, Southern Rhodesia became a territory of the [[Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland]] alongside [[Northern Rhodesia]] and [[Nyasaland]]. Each territory retained its own political status and government, and Southern Rhodesia's constitutional status was unaltered.{{sfn|Gowlland-Debbas|1990|p=46}}

===Dominion Party===
Harper entered politics when he contested the Gatooma seat in the 1958 [[Southern Rhodesian general election, 1958|general election]], running for the opposition [[Dominion Party]] (which called for full &quot;[[dominion]]&quot; or [[Commonwealth realm]] status).{{sfn|Willson|1963|p=182}} The Southern Rhodesian electoral system allowed only those who met certain financial and educational qualifications to vote—the criteria were applied equally regardless of race, but since most black citizens did not meet the set standards, the electoral roll and colonial [[Southern Rhodesian Legislative Assembly|Legislative Assembly]] were overwhelmingly drawn from the [[white people in Zimbabwe|white minority]] (about 5% of the population).{{sfn|Gowlland-Debbas|1990|pp=48–53}}{{sfn|Weinrich|1973|p=15}} Harper won in Gatooma with 717 out of 1,300 votes.{{sfn|Willson|1963|p=182}} Holding strongly conservative views, he soon became seen as the voice of the party's right wing. He was elected president of the Dominion Party's Southern Rhodesian arm in October 1959, and by 1960 he was the official [[Leader of the Opposition]] in the Southern Rhodesian parliament.&lt;ref name=goitalone/&gt;

Amid [[decolonization of Africa|decolonisation]] and the [[Wind of Change (speech)|Wind of Change]], the Federation was looking ever more tenuous and the idea of &quot;[[no independence before majority rule]]&quot; was gaining considerable ground in British political circles.{{sfn|Jackson|1990|pp=96–97}}{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=20}} Harper called for Southern Rhodesia to abandon the Federation and &quot;go it alone&quot;.&lt;ref name=goitalone&gt;{{cite news
|title=Congo Nerves
|last=Creighton
|first=I R M
|url=http://archive.spectator.co.uk/article/29th-july-1960/5/congo-nerves
|newspaper=[[The Spectator]]
|location=London
|date=28 July 1960
|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1960 he and the Southern Rhodesian branch of the Dominion Party adopted the policy of &quot;Southern Rhodesia first&quot;, prompting strong protests from the party's Northern Rhodesian division;{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=39}} the Dominion Party splintered into separate Federal and territorial entities a month later.{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=42}} When black nationalist riots broke out in the townships in October 1960, Harper condemned the Southern Rhodesian Prime Minister [[Edgar Whitehead|Sir Edgar Whitehead]] and the governing [[United Federal Party]] (UFP) as too lenient on the protesters, and argued that giving concessions following political violence would make black Rhodesians believe that &quot;trouble pays dividends&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia Uneasy as More Troops Called Up
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=6K4UAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=e7oDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5415,2852298&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=[[The Age]]
|location=Melbourne
|date=17 October 1960
|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arguing against black representation in the Legislative Assembly, he said that if there were black MPs &quot;they will share the restaurant with us and they will share the bars with us. We will be living cheek by jowl with them, and what sort of legislation can the people of this country expect when we ourselves are being conditioned to living cheek by jowl with Africans?&quot;{{sfn|Good|1973|p=38}}

===Rhodesian Front===
[[File:Ian Smith 1950s.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Ian Smith]] became [[Prime Minister of Rhodesia|Prime Minister]] in 1964. Harper was touted by pressmen as a possible replacement for the next four years.]]
In 1962 Harper was a founding member of the [[Rhodesian Front]] (RF), an alliance of conservative voices centred around the former Dominion Party and defectors from the UFP. The party's declared goal was independence for Southern Rhodesia without radical constitutional change and without any set timetable for the introduction of majority rule. After the RF won a surprise victory in the November 1962 [[Southern Rhodesian general election, 1962|general election]]—Harper comfortably retained his seat in Gatooma,{{sfn|Willson|1963|p=195}} and elsewhere the country's first black MPs were elected—the new Prime Minister [[Winston Field]] made him Minister of Irrigation, Roads and Road Traffic in the new government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=All-White Cabinet Named in S. Rhodesia
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=qTVgAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=ym8NAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2247,2385582&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=[[The StarPhoenix]]
|location=Saskatoon, Saskatchewan
|date=17 December 1962
|pages=1, 5}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=122}} Over the next few years, Harper became one of the main agitators in the Cabinet for a [[unilateral declaration of independence]] (UDI); equating Southern Rhodesia to India, he saw this as a way to prevent a repeat of &quot;the same mistake&quot;.{{sfn|Shamuyarira|1966|p=210}}

The RF grew dissatisfied with Field during late 1963 and early 1964 because of his failure to win independence on Federal dissolution at the end of 1963. Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland, by contrast, were both independent under black majority governments within a year, respectively renamed Zambia and Malawi.{{sfn|Wood|2005|pp=189–190}} Harper, who had been assigned the additional portfolios of Transport and Power in November 1963,{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=186}} was one of two frontrunners to replace Field. The other was the Deputy Prime Minister [[Ian Smith]], formerly of the UFP, who was also Minister of the Treasury. Harper, described in ''[[The Spectator]]'' as &quot;an ambitious politician and single-minded upholder of white supremacy&quot;, was generally considered the more hardline choice, and the man more likely to go through with UDI.&lt;ref name=spectator&gt;{{cite news
|title=Waiting for the Crisis
|first=Keith
|last=Kyle
|url=http://archive.spectator.co.uk/article/10th-january-1964/6/waiting-for-the-crisis
|newspaper=The Spectator
|location=London
|date=10 January 1964
|accessdate=21 November 2013
|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the Cabinet forced Field to resign in April 1964, it was Smith who was nominated by the ministers to become the new Prime Minister. Accepting the premiership, Smith reshuffled the Cabinet a few days later and moved Harper to the Ministry of Internal Affairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia Cabinet Is Reshuffled
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=taFIAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=PQENAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4579,5589278&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=[[Record-Journal|The Morning Record]]
|location=Meriden, Connecticut
|date=16 April 1964
|page=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harper was deeply disappointed not to have succeeded Field.{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=210}}

As Minister of Internal Affairs, Harper oversaw the ''[[indaba]]'' (conference) of chiefs and headmen at [[Domboshawa]] in October 1964, at the end of which the tribal leaders unanimously announced their support for the government's line on independence.{{sfn|Wood|2005|pp=243–246}} He continued to be linked with the premiership. During Smith's negotiations with the British government, each breakdown or setback was accompanied by speculation in Rhodesia (&quot;Southern&quot; was dropped in late 1964) that Harper might step up to take his place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=As You Were
|last=Baron
|first=Leo
|authorlink=Leo Baron
|url=http://archive.spectator.co.uk/article/6th-november-1964/5/as-you-were
|newspaper=The Spectator
|location=London
|date=6 November 1964
|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the dispute with Britain intensified and white Rhodesians clamoured for independence, Harry Franklin reported in ''The Spectator'' in August 1965 that if Smith proved unwilling to go through with UDI, &quot;it is widely believed that&amp;nbsp;... Harper will emerge from the wings, no longer an understudy, to dare what Mr Smith dare not.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia: Coming or Going?
|last=Franklin
|first=Harry
|url=http://archive.spectator.co.uk/article/20th-august-1965/6/rhodesia
|newspaper=The Spectator
|location=London
|date=19 August 1965
|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harper was one of four ministers chosen by Smith to accompany him to London for talks in October 1965, the others being [[John Wrathall]] (Finance), [[Desmond Lardner-Burke]] (Justice) and the Deputy Minister of Information [[P. K. van der Byl|P&amp;nbsp;K van der Byl]].{{sfn|Smith|1997|p=91}} Agreement was not reached and a month later, on 11 November 1965, Smith and his Cabinet [[Rhodesia's Unilateral Declaration of Independence|declared Rhodesia independent]].{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=471}}

At the time of UDI, Harper reportedly kept a map of southern Africa on the wall of his office, on which he had coloured South Africa, South-West Africa, Rhodesia, Mozambique south of the [[Zambezi]] and Angola red; he told visitors that &quot;the red area will be under white rule forever.&quot;&lt;ref name=forever&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia melting pot of white-black troubles
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=vjJVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Hj4NAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1443,1857583&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=[[Leader-Post]]
|location=Regina, Saskatchewan
|date=23 April 1976
|page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; While insisting that Rhodesia would continue regardless of international opinion, he publicly demonised the UK government, describing it in January 1966 as &quot;an enemy&amp;nbsp;... [that] must be brought down&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia 'Holding Her Own'
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=tWtAAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=e6MMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1530,3829506&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=[[The Glasgow Herald]]
|date=26 January 1966
|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also vilified black nationalist guerrilla fighters opposed to the Rhodesian government, calling them &quot;gangs of terrorists&quot; and &quot;criminals&quot;.&lt;ref name=criminals/&gt; Comments such as these helped to cement Harper's reputation as a hardline right-winger and rival to Smith's leadership.&lt;ref name=criminals&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia tightens screw
|last=MacSween
|first=Joseph
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=g9xUAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=WzwNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4958,5277048&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=The Leader-Post
|location=Regina, Saskatchewan
|date=27 August 1966
|page=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Young|1969|p=551}} The strong personalities of Harper and other ministers such as the [[James Graham, 7th Duke of Montrose|Duke of Montrose]] (generally known in Rhodesia by his former title Lord Graham) were perceived by the British Prime Minister [[Harold Wilson]] and his compatriots as a great influence on Smith's political decision-making, an opinion also expressed by Harper himself.{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=472}}

[[File:The 7th Duke of Montrose in 1967.jpg|thumb|upright|The [[James Graham, 7th Duke of Montrose|Duke of Montrose]] (Lord Graham), one of Harper's main allies in Cabinet]]
Although Harper was considered an intelligent and capable minister by peers and reporters—a 1965 report in ''[[The Economist]]'' called him &quot;by far the best brain&quot; in the Rhodesian Cabinet&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia's future
|newspaper=Rhodesian News Summary
|location=New York
|publisher=National Student Christian Federation Committee on Southern Africa
|url=http://kora.matrix.msu.edu/files/50/304/32-130-F75-84-RhodNews%2012%2019%2024%2065.pdf
|date=December 1965
|format=pdf
|page=67}}&lt;/ref&gt;—his views were often perceived as overly reactionary.{{sfn|Young|1969|p=551}} He led a phalanx of far-right voices within the RF calling for &quot;a form of political [[apartheid]]&quot; in Rhodesia,&lt;ref name=leaderpost68&gt;{{cite news
|title=Crisis in Rhodesia
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=uOxUAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=mDwNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5133,2939802&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=The Leader-Post
|location=Regina, Saskatchewan
|date=18 July 1968
|page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and while the party line was gradual advancement of black political representation, Harper called not only for the cessation of such moves, but for the abolition of black MPs altogether.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=472}} He thus became something of an obstacle to an Anglo-Rhodesian settlement. Indeed, when Smith brought a working document back from the [[HMS Tiger (C20)|HMS ''Tiger'']] talks with Wilson in October 1966, it was Harper who led opposition to the terms in Cabinet, contributing to its ultimate rejection.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=472}} Harper considered himself to have been overlooked when Smith gave the office of Deputy Prime Minister (which had been vacant since UDI) to the more moderate Wrathall the month before the ''Tiger'' conference. The South African newspaper ''[[Beeld|Die Beeld]]'' reported in December 1966 that the RF's right wing was poised to oust Smith in favour of Harper,&lt;ref name=spokesman66&gt;{{cite news
|title=Smith Meeting Opposition From Rhodesian Cabinet
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1314&amp;dat=19661212&amp;id=DgdFAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=9-gDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4991,4164269
|newspaper=[[The Spokesman-Review]]
|location=Spokane, Washington
|date=12 December 1966
|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this did not occur.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=472}}

===Resignation===

On 4 July 1968, Harper resigned from the Cabinet at Smith's request. He was the first minister to be dismissed during Smith's premiership.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=472}} The government released a statement explaining that Harper had been removed &quot;for reasons entirely unrelated to differences of opinion over constitutional or other political issues&quot;,{{sfn|Wood|2005|p=472}} and saying simply that Harper had been deemed &quot;a security risk&quot;. Harper publicly claimed that he had been fired for political reasons and because of the threat he posed to Smith's leadership.&lt;ref name=sorrytale&gt;{{cite news
|title=Rhodesia Hit By Guerrillas
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=4BhVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=gJMDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4835,3869007&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=The Age
|location=Melbourne
|date=22 July 1968
|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smith was reticent but told reporters he was prepared to tell &quot;the whole sorry tale&quot; if Harper wished.&lt;ref name=sorrytale/&gt;

According to the memoirs of [[Ken Flower]], then the director of Rhodesia's [[Central Intelligence Organisation]] (CIO), Harper's downfall was the result of an extramarital affair with a young secretary in the Rhodesian civil service who the CIO discovered was an agent for [[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]].{{sfn|Flower|1987|pp=85–86}} Flower informed Smith of this on 3 July and the Prime Minister demanded Harper's resignation that afternoon; Harper acquiesced the next day. Because this was kept secret (presuming it is true), Harper's sudden departure from the Cabinet was interpreted by many observers at the time as the culmination of the personal and political rivalry between Smith and Harper, or the result of disagreements over the new constitution.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=472}}

Harper officially resigned his parliament seat and left the Rhodesian Front on 11 July 1968. Wilson publicly welcomed his departure as a &quot;step in the right direction&quot;,{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=474}} prompting a retort from Smith that he did not appoint or sack ministers to please the British government. Smith said that Harper had been depicted as more extreme than he really was, and denied that he had obstructed a settlement.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=474}} In retrospect, Smith said he had been glad to be rid of Harper, who he considered underhand and devious.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=541}} Harper ignored an approach from the ultra-right-wing Rhodesian National Party, offering the leadership, and for a time withdrew from public affairs.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=472}} Montrose and the ministers A&amp;nbsp;P Smith and Phillip van Heerden briefly threatened to follow Harper out of the government, but backed down within a few days. After a fresh dispute Montrose resigned on 11 September 1968 in protest against Smith's proposed constitutional and racial policies, which he deemed too liberal.{{sfn|Wood|2008|pp=473, 512}} A week later the RF's Albert Mells easily won the by-election to fill Harper's former seat in Gatooma.{{sfn|Wood|2008|p=517}}

===Later career===

By the time of the [[Rhodesian general election, 1974|July 1974 general election]], amid the [[Rhodesian Bush War|Bush War]], Harper had formed a small bloc of [[Independent politician|independents]] called the &quot;Harper Group&quot;. In an attempt to co-ordinate opposition to the Rhodesian Front, the group made an election agreement with the Rhodesia Party (RP), which had been formed two years earlier; according to ''[[The Bulletin]]'' it was &quot;seriously hampered by lack of established leadership&quot; but nevertheless &quot;the only real resistance [to the RF] in the polls&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Cease-fire in Rhodesia as Smith seeks talks
|first=John
|last=Martin
|newspaper=[[The Bulletin]]
|location=Sydney
|volume=96
|year=1974
|page=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly before election day, Harper told a meeting of 300 people that under the present system, which was geared to eventually bring parity between black and white Rhodesians, racial tension would increase and &quot;the white man will be forced out of the country.&quot;&lt;ref name=worldbroadcasts1974/&gt; He said that while he was not prepared to let black Rhodesians take control of the government, he understood that some form of power-sharing between the races was imperative to the country's future.&lt;ref name=worldbroadcasts1974/&gt; The RF won all 50 white roll seats, denying the RP any representation in parliament; Harper himself lost decisively in the southern Salisbury constituency of [[Hatfield, Harare|Hatfield]].&lt;ref name=worldbroadcasts1974&gt;{{cite book
|title=Summary of World Broadcasts: Non-Arab Africa
|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=8wosAQAAIAAJ
|publisher=BBC
|location=London
|volume=4639–4716
|year=1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of 1974, Harper had formed the United Conservative Party,&lt;ref name=usstatedepartment&gt;{{cite news
|title=Review of State Department Trip Through Southern and Central Africa
|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Rd8jAAAAMAAJ&amp;q
|publisher=Committee on Foreign Affairs, United States House of Representatives
|location=Washington, D.C.
|date=12 December 1974
|page=135}}&lt;/ref&gt; which called for separate black and white legislatures.{{sfn|Political Handbook of the World|1978|p=364}} He subsequently reacted with revulsion each time Smith moved towards settlement with black nationalist factions. In December that year he described Smith's announcement of a ceasefire in the run-up to the [[Victoria Falls Conference (1975)|Victoria Falls Conference]] as a &quot;ghastly capitulation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Cease-fire in Rhodesia as Smith seeks talks
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=3Y9AAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=7KQMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5175,2281260&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=[[The Glasgow Herald]]
|date=12 December 1974
|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1976, when Smith announced his acceptance of unconditional majority rule by 1978, Harper accused the Prime Minister of &quot;selling us out&quot;.&lt;ref name=sellout/&gt; &quot;The mind boggles at the enormous impertinence and audacity of this man Smith,&quot; he said.&lt;ref name=sellout&gt;{{cite news
|title=Blacks to Take Over Rhodesian Government Within Two Years
|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=kjtBAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=36gMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4052,4776677&amp;dq=harper+rhodesia&amp;hl=en
|newspaper=Middlesboro Daily News
|location=Middlesboro, Kentucky
|date=25 September 1976
|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1975, two months after the disappearance of the prominent lawyer and black nationalist leader Edison Sithole from the middle of Salisbury, along with his secretary Miriam Mhlanga, Harper stepped forward claiming that the Rhodesian state had kidnapped them.{{sfn|Africa Today|1981|p=1468}} In what became known as the &quot;Harper Memorandum&quot;, the ex-minister stated that [[Special Branch#Rhodesia|Special Branch]] had interrogated Sithole at [[Goromonzi]] prison and then shuttled him between holding points around the country. The Rhodesian government denied that it was holding Sithole, adding that he was not under any form of restriction.{{sfn|Africa Today|1981|p=1468}} Sithole and Mhlanga were never seen again, and their fate has never been explained.{{#tag:ref|In modern Zimbabwe it is generally accepted that they were abducted and killed by agents of the Rhodesian government.&lt;ref name=patriot&gt;{{cite news
|title=40 years on: Search for Edison Sithole continues
|first=Emergency
|last=Mwale
|url=http://www.thepatriot.co.zw/old_posts/40-years-on-search-for-edison-sithole-continues/
|newspaper=The Patriot
|location=Harare
|date=8 October 2015
|accessdate=9 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=heraldsithole&gt;{{cite news
|title=Unisa honours Edison Sithole
|first=Sifelani
|last=Tsiko
|url=http://www.herald.co.zw/unisa-honours-edison-sithole/
|newspaper=The Herald
|publisher=Government of Zimbabwe
|location=Harare
|date=20 March 2015
|accessdate=9 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;n&quot;|name=&quot;opinion&quot;}}

==Emigration to South Africa and death==

Smith and non-militant nationalists agreed what became the [[Internal Settlement]] in March 1978, and in January the following year whites backed the new majority rule constitution by 85% in a national [[Rhodesian constitutional referendum, 1979|referendum]]. [[Zimbabwe Rhodesia general election, 1979|Multiracial elections]] were held in April 1979 with the country due to be reconstituted as [[Zimbabwe Rhodesia]] afterwards.&lt;ref name=alreadysettled&gt;{{cite news
|title=As black rule approaches Smith's warriors begin to withdraw
|last=Ellman
|first=Paul
|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]
|location=London
|date=3 April 1979}}&lt;/ref&gt; By this time Harper had already left the country; ''[[The Guardian]]'' reported shortly before the elections that he was &quot;already settled in South Africa&quot;.&lt;ref name=alreadysettled/&gt; Zimbabwe Rhodesia, with Bishop [[Abel Muzorewa]] as Prime Minister, failed to win international acceptance and following the [[Lancaster House Agreement]] of December 1979, the UK oversaw a process leading to [[Southern Rhodesian general election, 1980|fresh elections]] in which the guerrilla leader [[Robert Mugabe]] was elected Prime Minister. Britain granted independence to the country as Zimbabwe in April 1980.{{sfn|Gowlland-Debbas|1990|pp=89–91}} Harper died on 8 September 2006, at the age of 90.{{sfn|Wynn|2015|p=223}}

==Notes and references==
'''Footnotes'''
{{reflist|group=n}}

'''References'''
{{reflist|30em}}

'''Bibliography'''
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book
|title=The Few: Summer 1940, The Battle of Britain
|last=Collier
|first=Richard
|year=2002
|location=London
|publisher=[[Orion Books]]
|isbn=978-0-297-84345-0
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Serving Secretly: Rhodesia's CIO Chief on Record
|last=Flower
|first=Ken
|authorlink=Ken Flower
|year=1987
|location=Johannesburg
|publisher=Galago Publishing
|isbn=978-0-947020-27-9
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Royal Australian Air Force, 1939–1942
|last=Gillison
|first=Douglas
|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070209/
|year=1962
|location=Canberra
|publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]]
|oclc=480400608
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=UDI: The International Politics of the Rhodesian Rebellion
|last=Good
|first=Robert C
|year=1973
|location=London
|publisher=Faber and Faber
|isbn=978-0-691-05647-0
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Collective Responses to Illegal Acts in International Law: United Nations action in the question of Southern Rhodesia
|last=Gowlland-Debbas
|first=Vera
|publisher=[[Martinus Nijhoff Publishers]]
|location=Leiden and New York
|year=1990
|edition=First
|isbn=0-7923-0811-5
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Quasi-States: Sovereignty, International Relations and the Third World
|last=Jackson
|first=Robert H
|year=1990
|location=Cambridge, England
|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]
|isbn=978-0-521-44783-6
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Crisis in Rhodesia
|last=Shamuyarira
|first=Nathan
|authorlink=Nathan Shamuyarira
|year=1966
|location=New York
|publisher=Transatlantic Arts
|oclc=942260
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=[[The Great Betrayal|The Great Betrayal: The Memoirs of Ian Douglas Smith]]
|last=Smith
|first=Ian
|authorlink=Ian Smith
|year=1997
|location=London
|publisher=John Blake Publishing
|isbn= 1-85782-176-9
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Black and White Elites in Rural Rhodesia
|last=Weinrich
|first=A K H
|year=1973
|location=Manchester
|publisher=Manchester University Press
|isbn=978-0-7190-0533-6
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Source Book of Parliamentary Elections and Referenda in Southern Rhodesia, 1898–1962
|editor-last=Willson
|editor-first=F M G
|publisher=Department of Government, [[University of Zimbabwe|University College of Rhodesia and Nyasaland]]
|location=Salisbury
|year=1963
|oclc=219295658
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=So Far and No Further! Rhodesia's Bid for Independence During the Retreat From Empire 1959–1965
|last=Wood
|first=J R T
|year=2005
|location=Victoria, British Columbia
|publisher=Trafford Publishing
|isbn=978-1-4120-4952-8
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=A Matter of Weeks Rather Than Months: The Impasse Between Harold Wilson and Ian Smith: Sanctions, Aborted Settlements and War 1965–1969
|last=Wood
|first=J R T
|year=2008
|location=Victoria, British Columbia
|publisher=Trafford Publishing
|isbn=978-1-4251-4807-2
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Men of the Battle of Britain: A Biographical Dictionary of the Few
|last=Wynn
|first=Kenneth G
|year=2015
|origyear=1989
|location=Barnsley
|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books
|isbn=978-1-4738-4767-5
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Rhodesia and Independence: A Study in British Colonial Policy
|last=Young
|first=Kenneth
|year=1969
|origyear=1967
|location=London
|publisher=J M Dent &amp; Sons
|oclc=955160
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Africa Today
|location=London
|publisher=Africa Books
|year=1981
|oclc=9334568
|ref={{harvid|Africa Today|1981}}}}
*{{cite book
|title=Political Handbook of the World
|location=New York
|publisher=McGraw-Hill
|year=1978
|isbn=978-0-07-003690-1
|ref={{harvid|Political Handbook of the World|1978}}}}
{{refend}}

{{Signatories of the Unilateral Declaration of Independence}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Use South African English|date=July 2013}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Harper, William John}}
[[Category:1916 births]]
[[Category:2006 deaths]]
[[Category:Anglo-Indian people]]
[[Category:British emigrants to Rhodesia]]
[[Category:Indian emigrants to Rhodesia]]
[[Category:Indian military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:People from Kolkata]]
[[Category:Rhodesian anti-communists]]
[[Category:Rhodesian Front politicians]]
[[Category:Rhodesian politicians]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force officers]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Royal Australian Air Force personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Signatories of Rhodesia's Unilateral Declaration of Independence]]
[[Category:The Few]]
[[Category:White Rhodesian people]]</text>
      <sha1>iw8bysp0egja7v5lkghewvylki1v90l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
