<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Delta Force</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1954748</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746226438</id>
      <parentid>744549431</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-26T01:57:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sephiroth storm</username>
        <id>4175697</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Training section outdated? */ reply ~~~~</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="57626">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProject Military History
|class=Start|US=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= no
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes
}}
{{Archive box|[[/Archive1|Archive 1]]}}
__TOC__
==Page naming?==
Should the page really be named Delta Force? it seems a bit informal and no other military page's are named after their nicknames, i.e 1st infantry division, shouldn't the page rather be named by the detatchemnts actual name, 1st SFOD-D?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/58.174.240.205|58.174.240.205]] ([[User talk:58.174.240.205|talk]]) 01:57, 7 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:That's a good question. It's our policy to name articles based on the name most commonly used and easiest to recognize. In this case, 
that's &quot;Delta Force&quot;. [[User:Rklawton|Rklawton]] ([[User talk:Rklawton|talk]]) 03:25, 7 January 2012 (UTC)

::hmm, okay seems like a decent reson i guess [[Special:Contributions/58.174.240.205|58.174.240.205]] ([[User talk:58.174.240.205|talk]]) 01:49, 8 January 2012 (UTC)

:::I see your &quot;Delta Force&quot; and raise you [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group]], which is most well-known as &quot;SEAL Team Six&quot; and is probably better-known overall than Delta as a result of [[Operation Neptune Spear]], which is ''itself'' better known as &quot;Operation Geronimo&quot;, even though &quot;Geronimo&quot; was merely ''bin Laden's'' code name (edit: and even that isn't true—&quot;Geronimo&quot; was the code name for &quot;step G&quot; of the operation—the step that involved the killing of bin Laden). Situations like these are what redirects are for. [[Special:Contributions/70.172.215.165|70.172.215.165]] ([[User talk:70.172.215.165|talk]]) 06:42, 18 September 2012 (UTC)

::::Maybe I'm missing your point, but what does that have to do with this article? This article's title is based on the [[WP:COMMONNAME|common name]] for the subject.  Other articles may not do so, but that would be a discussion for ''that'' article's talk page, not this one. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 06:47, 18 September 2012 (UTC)

:::::The point is that the policy, like any Wiki policy, ''isn't'' hard and fast and oughtn't be. Common sense and a little research dictate both that the [[Charlie Sheen]] article should not be &quot;Carlos Estévez&quot; ''and'' that the [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group|DEVGRU]] article should not be &quot;SEAL Team Six&quot;. The former is a case of the common name being the ''more'' correct one despite not being &quot;technically&quot; correct, while the latter is an example of the more common name being ''less'' correct than the real one. Why shouldn't we just let the title of DEVGRU be SEAL Team Six if a simple Google count is the only metric we use to determine what an article should be called? The answer is because Wikipedia isn't meant to forge a consensus reality; it's meant to ''reflect'' reality. It should acknowledge inaccuracies and correct them, not perpetuate them. It should provide assistance to users by acknowledging the common names of subjects and re-directing them to the correct articles, but it shouldn't use those names itself as if they were appropriate. [[Special:Contributions/70.172.215.165|70.172.215.165]] ([[User talk:70.172.215.165|talk]]) 10:01, 18 September 2012 (UTC)

::::::&quot;a simple Google count&quot; isn't what we use to determine the common name, it is what reliable sources use to describe the subject.  I took a look through the sources in the article, and most of them clarify the &quot;official name&quot; elsewhere, but they refer to this article's subject as Delta Force, and these sources include government officials.  The sources also say that &quot; Delta Force is an official title commonly used to refer to the unit.&quot;, so it cannot be said that this title is somehow an &quot;inaccuracy&quot;. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 16:03, 18 September 2012 (UTC)

:::::::Of course they say what its most common name is, just as the article does—they (and it) have to, or people might not make the connection. Nowhere in the article does it mention that &quot;Delta Force&quot; is an official title. In fact, the introduction all but explicitly says that it's an informal name. Which source are you referring to? [[Special:Contributions/70.172.215.165|70.172.215.165]] ([[User talk:70.172.215.165|talk]]) 16:46, 21 September 2012 (UTC)
--
Don't worry Hondo most of the information on this article is complete crap. Utter nonsense. Not that civvy's would know any better. Time to change my IP address.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/121.214.135.135|121.214.135.135]] ([[User talk:121.214.135.135|talk]]) 11:14, 9 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

===Proper name===
This ''is'' a case where [[WP:OSE]] applies in the affirmative. Just as the &quot;DEVGRU / SEAL TEAM SIX / ''Guys that killed bin Laden''&quot; page goes by the unit's formal title; [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group]], so should this page. This page's proper title should be &quot;'''1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta'''&quot;. (with redirects from &quot;1st SFOD-D&quot;, &quot;Delta&quot;, &quot;Delta Force&quot;, &quot;Combat Applications Group&quot;, &quot;CAG&quot;, &quot;Army Compartmented Elements&quot; and &quot;ACE&quot;) From what I understand, the operators of this unit, (and the SOF community as a whole) ''don't'' use &quot;Delta Force&quot;... in fact, they hate it. &lt;small&gt;(No, I don't have a source for that)&lt;/small&gt;. The term has largely been propagated by the media and the entertainment and gaming industries (which Wikipedia is not a part of). This is clearly demonstrated by google counts (speaking of...), there are only about 93,000 hits for &quot;1st SFOD-D&quot;, but there is almost 50 million (!) hits for &quot;Delta Force&quot;. Why not respect what the actual operators of this unit want and use, and go by the proper name, which we should've be doing in the first place. - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  21:52, 12 September 2013 (UTC)

===Move===
Anyone object to moving the page to &quot;'''1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta'''&quot;, with a redirect to &quot;Delta Force&quot; (and the others noted above), so ye all speaketh now.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  21:52, 12 September 2013 (UTC)

:This is just a comment and not a !vote but I believe it is &quot;Delta Force&quot; largely due to [[WP:COMMONNAME]]. —&lt;font face=Verdana&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid;border-radius:1.7em 0&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background:#000;border-radius:1.5em 0 0&quot;&gt; -[[User:Dainomite|&lt;font color=#FFF&gt;dain&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;[[User:Dainomite/t|&lt;font color=#000&gt;omite&lt;/font&gt;]] &amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 22:34, 12 September 2013 (UTC)

::WP:COMMONNAME states the name must be accurate and correct. We don't if that is the case here... has the US Army officially named this unit after a Chuck Norris movie? We do know that it's first, official proper name was 1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta (sometimes &quot;Delta&quot;, for short, as well as possibly being subsequently renamed CAG and then ACE).&lt;br&gt;COMMON also calls for precision, that names &quot;unambiguously identify the article's subject and distinguish it from other subjects&quot;. There's a disamb page with a half dozen other Delta Forces on it. 1st SFOD-D is not going to be confused for a movie or a Norwegian Swat team.&lt;br&gt;Furthermore, Common calls for adherence to naming conventions. This is a military article. From what I can see, military articles go by proper names and titles, not popular nicknames. - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  01:33, 13 September 2013 (UTC)

:::From commonname... &quot;''Wikipedia prefers the name that is most commonly used (as determined by its prevalence in reliable English-language sources) as such names will be the most recognizable and the most natural.''&quot; I'm not sure if you checked the page logs but someone already moved [[Delta Force]] to [[1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta]] in December 2012 and it was reverted citing COMMONNAME. If you choose to go about this suggested name change I suggest [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]]. —&lt;font face=Verdana&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid;border-radius:1.7em 0&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background:#000;border-radius:1.5em 0 0&quot;&gt; -[[User:Dainomite|&lt;font color=#FFF&gt;dain&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;[[User:Dainomite/t|&lt;font color=#000&gt;omite&lt;/font&gt;]] &amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 02:18, 13 September 2013 (UTC)

::::[[WP:COMMONNAME]] is Delta Force, and is the [[WP:PRIMARY|primary topic]] for the phrase &quot;Delta Force&quot;.  It's official name is important to include in the lede (and it is), but is not the criteria by which articles are titled.  Just as an example, [[Bill Gates]] is not his birth name or his legal name, and there [[Bill Gates (frontiersman)|are other people by that name]], but he's what people mean when they say &quot;Bill Gates&quot;, and most people refer to him as such.  That's why his article is at that title, and this article is the same situation. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 02:37, 13 September 2013 (UTC)

:::::Well, that's why we have redirects. People looking for &quot;Delta Force&quot;, will still find it, but the article will be appropriately titled, like the rest of the military articles here, just as COMMONNAME demands. By the way, as for examples... you don't see the [[USS Enterprise (CV-6)|USS ''Enterprise'' (CV(N)-6)]] titled '''''Big 'E{{'}}''''', but that was a nick name that it was (and still is) popularly known by. [[Mike Tyson]] isn't titled '''''Iron Mike''''' and the [[Volkswagen Beetle]] isn't titled '''''VW Bug''''', but again, these are popular, COMMON NAMES that these subjects go by. The aspects of COMMONNAME you may be referring to are not carved in stone. In many cases, it is more appropriate that the proper ''confirmed and sourced'' name be used. This is the case here. - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  05:02, 13 September 2013 (UTC)

::::::There is a difference between &quot;''a'' common name&quot; and &quot;''the most'' common name&quot;, and none of your examples are the latter, whereas this article's current title is.  That's why we have [[WP:COMMONNAME]]; redirects are useful and allow [[1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta]] to redirect here, but that's not cause to move the article from the current title, nor does anything currently written at [[WP:COMMONNAME]]. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 05:22, 13 September 2013 (UTC)

:::::::First off, your argument appears to be based on present tense. But whereas it has been years since the WWII aircraft carrier has been referred to much at all, it could be argued that during the 80's and 90's, &quot;Iron Mike&quot; was ''the'' common name for Tyson. Considering his notability is based primarily on his status as a boxer in that era, the example stands up quite well. But, again, if you are indeed focused strictly on the present, then &quot;VW Bug&quot; is arguably &quot;the most&quot; common name for that car today. But another, even more fitting example is another military article, ''and'' 1st SFOD-D's direct naval counterpart, the [[Naval Special Warfare Development Group]]. Really, who calls it ''that'' ? This unit existed in relative obscurity until the bin Laden raid. Now it is known ''primarily'' as &quot;SEAL Team Six&quot;. (And after that, DEVGRU). But, as the '''convention''' is with military articles, the proper unit name is used as the page title. Changing the title, would keep the articles '''consistent'''. And, as I've pointed out, we haven't confirmed that &quot;Delta Force&quot; is a title ever officially used by that unit, therefore, using &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment - Delta&quot;, is ensuring that the '''correct''' name is used. You commented that &quot;''...but that's not cause to move the article from the current title, nor does anything currently written at WP:COMMONNAME''&quot;. Well, &quot;convention&quot;, &quot;consistency&quot; and &quot;correctness&quot; ''are'' currently written into WP:COMMONNAME.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  18:01, 13 September 2013 (UTC)

::::::::It is present tense because the sources still exist.  You could possibly argue that &quot;VW Bug&quot; is the most common name, but if you feel that's the case you're welcome to bring that up at [[Talk:Volkswagen Beetle]], not here.  You're still using the assumption that arguing &quot;proper over [[WP:COMMONNAME]]&quot; means anything, but that's not how Wikipedia articles work.  Articles use [[WP:COMMONNAME]], ''that'' is &quot;consistent&quot;; ignoring that policy in inconsistent with how article titles work on Wikipedia. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 04:09, 14 September 2013 (UTC)

:::::::::Again, your argument appears to be based on present tense. But whereas it has been years since the WWII aircraft carrier has been referred to much at all, it could be argued that during the 80's and 90's, &quot;Iron Mike&quot; was ''the'' common name for Tyson. Considering his notability is based primarily on his status as a boxer in that era, the example stands up quite well. But, again, if you are indeed focused strictly on the present, then &quot;VW Bug&quot; is arguably &quot;the most&quot; common name for that car today. But another, even more fitting example is another military article, ''and'' 1st SFOD-D's direct naval counterpart, the [[Naval Special Warfare Development Group]]. Really, who calls it ''that'' ? This unit existed in relative obscurity until the bin Laden raid. Now it is known ''primarily'' as &quot;SEAL Team Six&quot;. (And after that, DEVGRU). But, as the '''convention''' is with military articles, the proper unit name is used as the page title. Changing the title, would keep the articles '''consistent'''. And, as I've pointed out, we haven't confirmed that &quot;Delta Force&quot; is a title ever officially used by that unit, therefore, using &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment - Delta&quot;, is ensuring that the '''correct''' name is used. You commented that &quot;''...but that's not cause to move the article from the current title, nor does anything currently written at WP:COMMONNAME''&quot;. Well, &quot;convention&quot;, &quot;consistency&quot; and &quot;correctness&quot; ''are'' currently written into WP:COMMONNAME.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  03:16, 16 September 2013 (UTC)
::::::::::I don't know if you meant to copy the same comment, but if that's the only rationale then there's no cause to move the article from its current title. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 05:07, 16 September 2013 (UTC)

:::::::::::I re-posted because your reply did not make sense, and it appeared you hadn't actually read what I wrote. Indeed, you seem to be avoiding or ignoring most of the points I have made. I have shown multiple reasons to move the page, whereas you keep writing &quot;COMMONNAME, COMMONNAME, COMMONNAME&quot;, without it actually supporting your point, or refuting mine.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  17:16, 16 September 2013 (UTC)

{{od}}Copy-pasting the exact same comment because you don't like the response you got isn't going to make your comment somehow more relevant the second time.  Your argument is based on the assumption that articles on Wikipedia use the official name and that this is how titles are determined; it is not.  Wikipedia article use the most common title, '''not''' the official one.  Most of the time the official name is also the most common name, so that's not an issue.  But when they aren't, we use the most commonly used title.  That is Wikipedia policy, so when your argument for renaming the article is that it isn't the official name, that doesn't matter because that [[WP:OFFICIALNAME|is not how articles are titled on Wikipedia]].  Don't confuse my not agreeing with you with avoiding or ignoring you, because that's not the case and it's been explained multiple times now why; because there is a longstanding consensus on Wikipedia written into policy that the most commonly used and recognizable title is used over any official title. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 19:32, 16 September 2013 (UTC)
{{outdent}}
(''see cont'd'')


----
:Aoidh is correct, with minor exceptions that don't apply in this case. [[User:Rklawton|Rklawton]] ([[User talk:Rklawton|talk]]) 19:53, 16 September 2013 (UTC)

::Um, no he's not. And what exceptions are you referring to?  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  23:39, 18 September 2013 (UTC)


----
(''cont'd'')&lt;br&gt;
[[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]], I re-posted my comment because your reply gave no indication that you either read it at all, or read it and understood it. Maybe that is my fault, perhaps I'm not explaining myself clearly enough. You wrote; &quot;''Your argument is based on the assumption that articles on Wikipedia use the official name and that this is how titles are determined; it is not.''&quot; That, is ''not'' my argument. 

My argument is that;
1) You're applying COMMONNAME as a hard and fast rule, which it isn't, it's a guideline. Per COMMONNAME;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;These should be seen as goals, not as rules. For most topics, there is a simple and obvious title that meets these goals satisfactorily. If so, use it as a straightforward choice. ''However, in some cases the choice is not so obvious. It may be necessary to favor one or more of these goals over the others''. This is done by consensus.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

2) The naming of this page is in conflict with several of the ''guidelines'' listed at COMMONNAME;

* '''Precision''' – ''The title is sufficiently precise to unambiguously identify the article's subject and distinguish it from other subjects''.
- This title is based on one that was created for a [[The Delta Force|film]] that heavily fictionalizes 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;SFOD-D, and has since been erroneously applied by the media and others to the actual unit. This is an error that Wikipedia should &lt;u&gt;not&lt;/u&gt; be perpetuating. This title in not ''precise'', as per COMMONNAME. 

* '''Conciseness''' – ''The title is no longer than necessary to identify the article's subject and distinguish it from other subjects.'' 
- The title &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment - Delta&quot; ''does'' distinguish it from the other '[[Delta Force (disambiguation)|Delta Forces]]' found on WP and is exactly the title the unit was created with (confirmed [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/agency/army/sfod-d.htm here] and [http://www.history.army.mil/html/forcestruc/HRC/2011/137-33_20110517_HRCMD_CC.pdf here]). Since then, there have been official revisions such as &quot;Combat Applications Group (CAG)&quot; and &quot;Army Compartmented Elements (ACE)&quot;, but those are covered in the article, just as &quot;Delta&quot;, &quot;D-boys&quot;, and &quot;The Unit&quot; are nicknames and covered under &quot;Nicknames&quot;. That is where &quot;Delta Force&quot; belongs, with the other nicknames. This title is not ''concise'' as per COMMONNAME.

* '''Consistency''' – ''The title is consistent with the pattern of similar articles' titles.''
- All other military articles are titled by their proper name. (see [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group]] (SEAL Team Six) and [[United States Navy Strike Fighter Tactics Instructor program]] (Top Gun). These are two perfect examples. One is a direct counter-part to the article subject in question, the other is a unit of the U.S. military that is also the name of a [[Top Gun|movie]]. Using this current title is ''inconsistent'' with COMMONNAME.  

3) Aditionally;
a) COMMONNAME states;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Ambiguous or inaccurate names for the article subject, as determined in reliable sources, are often avoided even though they may be more frequently used by reliable sources.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
- This title is inaccurate as it comes from a movie, and was applied after the fact. There is not one reference that confirms the U.S. Army (or U.S. Gov't for that matter) as referring to 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; SFOD-D as &quot;Delta Force&quot;. The fact is, they [http://www.neoseeker.com/news/19188-activision-being-sued-over-delta-force-usage-in-modern-warfare-3/ don't]. The current title ''is'' ambiguous. 

b)COMMONNAME states;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Other encyclopedias are among the sources that may be helpful in deciding what titles are in an encyclopedic register as well as what names are most frequently used.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
-For this, I direct you to our [https://de.wikipedia.org sister site], for [https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/1st_Special_Forces_Operational_Detachment-Delta_(Airborne) usage] within another encyclopedia.
 
c)COMMONNAME also has an entire [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:COMMONNAME#Neutrality_in_article_titles section] about neutrality. Again, I believe using a name created to promote a movie, is in violation of this.


In closing, I will ask that if you still disagree that the change should be made, I would ask that you respond on a point-by-point basis with all the points I have presented, instead of just lumping everything together with a singularly generic answer, (such as: &quot;Your argument is ''this'', but COMMONNAME says it isn't). Thanks  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  23:39, 18 September 2013 (UTC)

===sub-section 1===
:The book, ''Delta Force'' by the unit's founder Col Beckwith, predates the movie and gave the unit its common name. And you've not presented significant evidence that ''Delta Force'' isn't the unit's commonly accepted name. [[User:Rklawton|Rklawton]] ([[User talk:Rklawton|talk]]) 00:11, 19 September 2013 (UTC)

::Again, thank you for ignoring all the other points I've made. But as for the book, &quot;Delta Force&quot; is a title of a privately published novel, not an official document of the US Army or US Gov't. It's the same principle as the film - advertising. (It sells better than &quot;1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Special Forces Operational detachment - Delta.&quot; Was the official name even mentioned in the book? Was it allowed to be?) As for your request that I &quot;''presented significant evidence that ''Delta Force'' isn't the unit's commonly accepted name''&quot;, that is putting a reverse onus on me. Actually, it is you that needs to prove that it is an accepted name within US special operations circles and/or the upper echelon of the military, and, (as per COMMONNAME) that the name is ''correct'', for it to be used as the title of the article. As for &quot;commonly accepted name&quot;, please re-read part 2 of my post.&lt;br&gt;
::Also, you still haven't responded to my first reply to you in this thread.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  03:00, 19 September 2013 (UTC)

:::You're welcome. And yes, you want the move. The onus is entirely on you. [[User:Rklawton|Rklawton]] ([[User talk:Rklawton|talk]]) 14:35, 19 September 2013 (UTC)

::::Am I to take it that your reply &quot;''You're welcome''&quot; as confirming your intention to ignore the majority of the points I have made?&lt;br&gt;As for your other comment; &quot;''you want the move''&quot;, well, sure I do, but not so much as a personal preference, but as need to have the correct name, as per wiki-policy, COMMONNAME. There is no reliable sources to confirm that this name is even correct, so, as I've already pointed out, that is a violation of policy, (one of the several). And, on that note, No, ''the onus is entirely on you'' to provide reliable sources that warrant the inclusion/use of the name as a page title. It not policy to force others to try and prove a negative, as a means to avoid the guidelines. - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  22:51, 19 September 2013 (UTC)

===Consensus===
OK, all in favor of moving &quot;Delta Force&quot; to &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta&quot; please read the thread above and make your wishes known. [[User:Rklawton|Rklawton]] ([[User talk:Rklawton|talk]]) 00:31, 20 September 2013 (UTC)
* '''Oppose''' - I believe most people immediately grasp &quot;Delta Force&quot; and wouldn't have a clue what &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta&quot; means. We aren't bound to official names that tend to change with every military re-organization. Folks searching for this unit are more likely to search on &quot;Delta Force&quot; than they are &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta&quot;. The organization's founder referred to them as &quot;Delta Force&quot;. A Google News search on &quot;Delta Force&quot; turns up (at the moment) 184 results. A Google News search on &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta&quot; turns up zero results. I chose Google News because it limits searches to media published within the last 30 days thereby eliminating fansites for the movies and books, and it illustrates which term is in ''current'' use. A regular search shows more than 4:1 favoring &quot;Delta Force&quot;. Either way, it's obvious &quot;Delta Force&quot; is the common name. [[User:Rklawton|Rklawton]] ([[User talk:Rklawton|talk]]) 00:31, 20 September 2013 (UTC)
::&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;*&lt;/font&gt; Right... once ''again'', you ignore every point I made, and instead, jump ahead with a consensus vote. By the way, #redirects invalidate your whole argument. What a joke.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  07:51, 22 September 2013 (UTC)

*'''Oppose''' - The decision of how articles are titled on Wikipedia is based on consensus, and a very large part of that consensus is [[WP:COMMONNAME]] (which is a [[WP:POLICIES|policy, not a guideline]]).  Policies are not hard and fast rules, but that doesn't mean they can be discarded without reason.  The title is overwhelmingly the [[WP:PRIMARYTOPIC|primary topic]] for this subject and is concise and [[WP:PRECISION|precise enough]] without being ''too'' precise.  In short, the current title meets every criteria Wikipedia has when determining an article's title.  The only thing it lacks is that it isn't the official name, and an argument was put forth that this creates inconsistency because some other article do use the official name.  However, those articles use the official name ''because'' of [[WP:COMMONNAME]], not in spite of it.  They use the most commonly used name; that it happens to also be the official name is good, but not why those titles were chosen.  The titles are chosen because they are most commonly used, are concise, and recognizable. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 03:29, 20 September 2013 (UTC)
::&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;*&lt;/font&gt; Guideline, Policy, whatever. Even if you really do think this conforms to commonname, this is a case where it would need to be ignored, for the sake of consistency and respect due a correct name vs. a made up, lay person name. If anything, it should at least just be &quot;Delta&quot;, instead of &quot;Delta force&quot;. Furthermore, please confirm you believe &quot;United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group&quot; is the &quot;''...most commonly used, are concise, and recognizable...''&quot; name, as opposed to &quot;DEVGRU&quot;, or &quot;SEAL Team Six&quot;, because I find that hard to believe.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  07:51, 22 September 2013 (UTC)  
:::Actually, such articles use the most common name, and ''that'' is consistency; ignoring that would not only create an inconsistent naming scheme but would also lose the benefit of being more easily recognizable, which creates multiple reasons why such a move would be a step in the wrong direction. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 13:16, 22 September 2013 (UTC)

*'''Oppose'''. I think COMMONNAME gets misapplied a lot of the time, but in this case, the common name is truly the most recognizable and most likely search term. Even among those knowledgeable on the topic, the term is more commonly used. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 22:05, 20 September 2013 (UTC)
::&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;*&lt;/font&gt; Yes, COMMONNAME ''does'' get misapplied a lot, and right here is a perfect example. &quot;''Even among those knowledgeable on the topic''&quot; will '''know''' that &quot;1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Special Forces Operational Detachment - Delta&quot; was the first official name for the unit, and is still known today. Anyone else looking will still find it thru #redirects.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  07:51, 22 September 2013 (UTC)  

*'''Oppose''', per COMMONNAME since Delta Force is the most recognizable and prevalent term in english-language sources. —&lt;font face=Verdana&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid;border-radius:1.7em 0&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background:#000;border-radius:1.5em 0 0&quot;&gt; -[[User:Dainomite|&lt;font color=#FFF&gt;dain&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;[[User:Dainomite/t|&lt;font color=#000&gt;omite&lt;/font&gt;]] &amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 12:53, 21 September 2013 (UTC)
::&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;*&lt;/font&gt; ''You'' oppose?, that surprises me.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  07:51, 22 September 2013 (UTC)

*'''Abstain''', I'm not going to even bother voting. COMMONNAME has ''no clear'' application if favour the current name, what-so-ever. All of your arguments are completely negated by redirects, and also, completely contradicted by the DEVGRU page, (among others). So, sure, let's keep &quot;Delta ''Force''&quot;. It just sounds so much cooler. Silly me, here I thought WP was an encyclopedia, not a fan-site.  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  07:51, 22 September 2013 (UTC)

:If that's all you take from this, then you've lost an opportunity to learn something. I think you spent so much time trying to make your point that you failed to fully appreciate the views of others. [[User:Rklawton|Rklawton]] ([[User talk:Rklawton|talk]]) 21:08, 22 September 2013 (UTC)
::Oh, the irony...  - '''''[[User:Thewolfchild|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;thewolfchild&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''  00:26, 24 September 2013 (UTC)

== &quot;Operator&quot; section ==

  
This section is in need of rewite/updating  While true that initially the term &quot;operator&quot; was used only to refer to Delta, it has since grown to be used by other special operations forces, and has gained recognition by the pentagon as such.  For instance, SEALs used to be required to test within their MOS for promotion, so a SEAL who was trained, initially, as a sonar technician, would have to test as a sonar tech for promotion, NOT as a SEAL.  That has since changed, and SEALs are now given SEAL specific MOS ratings, as &quot;Special Warfare Operator _____ Class.&quot;  Clearly the term &quot;operator&quot; now, officially, refers to SEALs as well.  The section should reflect that, or be scrapped as outdated. [[Special:Contributions/208.40.242.41|208.40.242.41]] ([[User talk:208.40.242.41|talk]]) 22:54, 24 December 2012 (UTC)

Related Q: If SF Delta members are called Operators, what are non-Delta SF members called?

[[User:Phantom in ca|Phantom in ca]] ([[User talk:Phantom in ca|talk]]) 19:14, 25 July 2013 (UTC)

:&quot;Operator&quot; has become a generic colloquialism for combat roles in the special operations community. It's modern usage is so broad that the Marine Corps even felt the need, for whatever absurd reason, to call their new special operations MOS  [[United States Marine Corps Critical Skills Operator|Critical Skill Operator]]. Some guys in the community hate it, others like it but most are rather indifferent. With the manner in which the term is used it doesn't really delineate anything. Aside from the historical note that the term came out of Delta there is no reason to attempt to catalog the term's contemporary meaning as it doesn't have one.[[User:TomPointTwo|TomPointTwo]] ([[User talk:TomPointTwo|talk]]) 02:56, 26 July 2013 (UTC)
::*I'm not entirely convinvced that the matter deserves a section in the article. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 11:59, 26 July 2013 (UTC)

A CAG Squadron consists of Approximately 50 operators. It is broken into three 16 man Troops; 2 Assault Troops, and 1 Sniper Troop, plus the Squadron HQ. An Assault Troop consists of a four man Head Quarters element, Troop Commander, Troop Sergeant Major, Troop Communications Chief, and Troop Medic, and then 12 Assaulters, which are typically organized into three 4 man teams, or two 6 man team (referred to as &quot;Heavy&quot;), plus any attachments that there might be (i.e. such as CCT). A Sniper Troop, also consists of 16 operators, the same 4 man HQ elements, and then the other 12 Snipers are divided into two 6 man sections, which are further divided into 2 man sniper teams. A sniper team consists of a Sniper and an Observer (who is usually the Team Leader). CAG recruits from ALL of the different service branches (including the Coast Guard) of the Military unlike DEVGRU, which recruits exclusively from within the ranks of the Navy SEALs. They are THREE Operational Squadrons (A,B, and C). It also takes about 2 years to become a full fledged &quot;Operator,&quot; after you complete the 6 month OTC, you also have to complete an 18-month probationary/OTJ period, after which you receive the &quot;T&quot; identifier. In addition, CAG Operators also serve as part of Intelligence Support Activity (also known as &quot;The Activity&quot;, &quot;Task Force Orange&quot;, and the &quot;Army of Northern Virginia&quot;), which conducts SR operations in Sensitive, Denied or Restricted territories, they also do things like Target Acquisition and TTL, using things like Blackbird systems, &quot;Airscan&quot;, and other covert SIGINT. There is also a Tier above this, it is referred to as &quot;PM&quot; (Paramilitary). These are the Operators, who are discharged from the military and then are hired by PMCs and then go to work for groups such as SAD/SOG. &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:96.39.118.245|96.39.118.245]] ([[User talk:96.39.118.245#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/96.39.118.245|contribs]]) &lt;/small&gt;

== &quot;USASOC patch worn by Delta&quot; ==

Is there any verification or reliable source that says &quot;Delta&quot; wear that patch?

Also fair use: &quot;In rare instances, the U.S. Army Special Operations Command (USASOC) may link to websites that are not government-owned or government-sponsored if these websites provide government information and/or services in a way that is not available on an official government website. USASOC provides these non-government websites as a public service only. USASOC neither endorses nor guarantees in any way the external organizations, services, advice, or products included in these website links. Furthermore, USASOC neither controls nor guarantees the accuracy, relevance, timeliness or completeness of the information contained in non-government website links&quot;. Please provide a reference and also a permission slip given out by the US Federal Government.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/120.144.79.213|120.144.79.213]] ([[User talk:120.144.79.213|talk]]) 10:41, 29 December 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I'll take your second question first. I ''think'' you're asking about the fair use of the image, yes? According to US copyright law all images produced by a federal employee in the performance of their duties is in the public domain. If the federal government created it, there is no copyright. As for the first, Delta doesn't have an official Shoulder Sleeve Insignia patch for a couple reasons. As far as the US Army is officially concerned, the unit doesn't exist.  Of course it does exist, everyone knows it exists and everyone in it has to have something on their paperwork and uniform, they don't just fall into an administrative black hole during their tenure in unit. Also, the Army's Shoulder Sleeve Insignia works by parent organization so if you're part of a tactical element that's administratively part of USASOC then you'll wear the USASOC SSI. I'm 99% sure there's a reference for that somewhere in Haney's book or some other well worn place but if you want it taken out until that's found then that's not a big deal for me. [[User:TomPointTwo|TomPointTwo]] ([[User talk:TomPointTwo|talk]]) 19:58, 29 December 2012 (UTC)

Understood, however Special Mission Units such as the CIA SAD as well as many other compartmented SCI units have been known to use a front or cover name and unit. Haney's book is very old and the entire Unit has had radical changes pre 9/11. Just like other Special Operations forces around the globe 'Delta' will use whatever cover they deem necessary, on the article it even states that they were attached to the USMC.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/120.144.79.213|120.144.79.213]] ([[User talk:120.144.79.213|talk]]) 00:07, 30 December 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:For what it's worth the CIA's SAD isn't a Special Mission Unit. &quot;Special Mission Unit&quot; is just a bureaucratic designation used by JSOC for the purposes of funding and tasking, it doesn't really carry any real meaning outside of that world. Guys in SMUs are still in the military, they still have dress uniform regulations, administrative hierarchies and the other mundane organizational stuff that goes along with government work. When a Delta guy gets forced to climb into his pickle suit it still still has to have an SSI. Last I checked that was still the USASOC's patch. Which brings me to the other thing.

:Most of this article is bogus. More than half is outdated, taken out of context, a half truth or just flat out wrong. Even the name, Delta, is just a common colloquialism. The inevitable reality of dealing with subjects that are based on classified and highly perishable information is you will never achieve a broad degree of specific truth. Only [[WP:V|verifiability]]. If some guy wrote it in a book and that guy is deemed to be a subject matter expert or a reliable source by the criteria set forth here then it gets pushed into the article. It's not a fixable dilemma. If you know it's wrong you can't prove it. If you can prove it then it's probably already be in the article. [[User:TomPointTwo|TomPointTwo]] ([[User talk:TomPointTwo|talk]]) 01:59, 30 December 2012 (UTC)
::*The IP editor is missing the point here. Nobody is saying that Delta might not wear other patches to protect identities etc. Of course that happens and of course theiy're allowed to do it. However, the SSI they are assigned is the one in the picture. For example, when they have to take their official file photos, they wear a class A uniform, complete with SSI. If you look at the file photos of [[Randy Shugart]] and [[Gary Gordon]] used in their Wikipedia articles, you'll see both Delta operators wearing that ASOC SSI. I'm restoring it. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 13:35, 31 December 2012 (UTC)

I know, I actually didn't want to give any examples of actual Special Mission Units because some are SCI and examples just help create Wikipedia pages that are not needed, OPSEC has been compromised one time to many. I can see that they would wear it on Class A, however could you at least include a piece to say that the patch is not only worn by Delta? Also what happened to all the other talk on this page?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/121.219.166.54|121.219.166.54]] ([[User talk:121.219.166.54|talk]]) 12:13, 1 January 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::*Why would we say it isn't only worn by Delta? Nobody said it was. It is clearly identified as the USASOC patch, not the Delta patch. The C stand for command, not a single unit. As for the other, outdated talk, those were archived and the link is at the top of the page. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 19:50, 1 January 2013 (UTC)

Because I have seen people talk online about Delta and say it is the official patch, maybe thats for the simple wiki page though. haha.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/58.165.40.52|58.165.40.52]] ([[User talk:58.165.40.52|talk]]) 08:29, 2 January 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:*We can't prevent people from making incorrect assumptions. The patch is clearly, correctly labeled. It is the official patch for Delta....and others USASOC units.[[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 12:09, 2 January 2013 (UTC)

== Green ==

[[Stanley A. McChrystal]]'s memoir, ''My Share of the Task'' consistently refers to &quot;Green&quot; and never mentions &quot;Delta Force.&quot; Is &quot;Green&quot; another name for &quot;Delta Force?&quot;  On page 93 he says
: Although I had served in special operations for much of the previous eighteen years, I was from the Rangers and had never served in either of the other units&amp;mdash;“Green” (the Army's elite commando unit) and “Blue” (the Navy SEAL special mission unit)&amp;mdash;considered the crown jewels of the command and of TF 714.
&quot;Blue&quot; sounds like the [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group]] (SEAL Team Six).  The [[Special Mission Unit]] article needs some TLC but it identifies four Special Mission Units, with one of them being &quot;1st Special Forces Operational Detachment-Delta (1st SFOD-D), or Delta Force.&quot;

In the introduction of his book McChrystal state that he sometimes used pseudonyms to shield operational details from the general public. Is &quot;Green&quot; a standard military term or is that one of McChrystal's pseudonyms? McChrystal used &quot;Green&quot; hundreds of times in the book. I don't think he ever used &quot;Blue&quot; other than on page 93. --[[User:Marc Kupper|Marc Kupper]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Marc Kupper|talk]] 19:46, 7 February 2013 (UTC)
:*Why wouldn't &quot;green&quot; simply refer to Special Forces, commonly called green berets? [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 20:13, 7 February 2013 (UTC)

Sean Naylor reports in &quot;Not a Good Day to Die&quot; that, in the context of JSOC ops, the JSOC units are sometimes designated by color code : 
* Task Force Green = Delta
* Task Force Blue = SEAL Team 6
* Task Force White = 24th STS
* Task Force Red = Rangers
* Task Force Brown = 160th SOAR
* Task Force Orange = the former Intelligence Support Activity

Task Force Green/Blue, depending on context, may be either an alias for a unit (&quot;a Blue guy&quot; = a SEAL Team 6 operator) or the unit detachment deployed in theater (Task Force Blue was the name of the ST-6 detachment in Afghanistan). 

Previously, in Panama (1989) and Haiti (1993), some of these names had already been used for components of a large JSOTF which included JSOC and non-JSOC special units. Task Force White in Panama was then a &quot;white&quot; (non-classified) Navy SOF detachment, while TF Blue was a SEAL Team 6 detachment. [[User:Rob1bureau|Rob1bureau]] ([[User talk:Rob1bureau|talk]]) 15:21, 10 February 2013 (UTC)

Regular SEAL Teams are classified under &quot;Vanilla&quot;, &quot;Blue&quot; is always ST6, and &quot;Green&quot; is always Delta. And to the person asking why Green isn't referred to for Special Forces, it's because SF has no place on the JSOC Task Forces, hence no color designation. - d375  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/65.112.195.186|65.112.195.186]] ([[User talk:65.112.195.186|talk]]) 19:37, 5 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Moved operations to it's own page and created entry al-Liby capture. ==

Operations section was taking up over 2/3rds of the page and looked really bulky imho. I have created it's own page. I have not edited anything from the original section (other than my al-Liby contribution). I assume no one should have much problem with this, if someone does feel free to let me know. Also, at the end of my day so if someone could do a quick once over to make sure everything looks good it'd be much appreciated. Cheers, [[User:Sulfurboy|Sulfurboy]] ([[User talk:Sulfurboy|talk]]) 13:46, 6 October 2013 (UTC)

== Commons photo ==

Since the Nick refuses to discuss the issue here, I'll start the discussion for him. The image is currently in the Commons and has a license. Just because it is your personal opinion that the license isn't correct doesn't mean you get to declare it as fact and everyone has to accept it. Do you have any evidence that the license is incorrect? Why do you refuse to nominate it for deletion? That would instantly solve this issue. There is a current license displayed. It's up to you to either nominate it or show evidence that the license is incorrect (something I've done before). Until then, I have returned it in good faith. It would be nice if you'd assume a little on your end. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 01:47, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
:As the US military almost never releases images of Delta force, and no source is provided for the image uploaded to Commons there's no reason to assume that this is actually a public domain image, and lots of reasons to assume that its a copyright violation (and quite possibly a fake). Per [[WP:COPYLINK]] we don't link to images on Commons which can be reasonably assumed to be copyright violations. I also noted an example of a recent WP:AN discussion on your talk page where there was clear consensus in regards to this principle ([[Wikipedia:Administrators' noticeboard/Archive262#Admin removing content]]). Given that you want to use the image, can you please explain the grounds on which you believe that the image is actually genuine and PD? - the onus is actually on you to establish this if you think it's OK to use given that this isn't currently established by the details in the Commons record. I have in fact nominated the image for deletion, so I'm not sure why you're claiming that I'm refusing to do this. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 02:12, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
::*That discussion you keep linking is mainly you talking and a couple of people finally chiming in. Hardly the big stick you're acting like it was. Why do I say you refused? Well, because your removal was contested and you just edit warred. You '''finally''' nominated it, so this should be over soon. Right now, the contributor asserts it is PD. We AGF and follow the process. The process is to nominate it, allow discussion and then delete it if that is the result. I'm glad that you've finally decided to follow the process. You'll have your way in a few days. So relax. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 02:25, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
::::Do you  have any particular grounds for thinking it's actually PD? Taking the say-so of someone on Commons who's uploaded lots of images which have been deleted as being copyright violations isn't a tenable reasons for keeping a dubious image in an article given that the policy is to remove links to content which can be reasonably be assumed to be copyright violations (see also [[WP:DCV]]), and your understanding of process here isn't correct (what you rudely dismiss as &quot;mainly you talking and a couple of people finally chiming in&quot; was a discussion among experienced editors on this very topic...). Can you please provide a link to a policy or guideline which supports your contention that the norm is to leave questionable Commons images in articles until they are removed from Commons? [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 03:37, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
− ::*So rudely dismiss? Look Nick, I'm sorry that your feelings are hurt because someone doesn't just bow to your little admin icon and let you do what you please. I'm sure it would be easier for you if nobody expected you to use the process, but well, here we are. I see an image that CURRENTLY has a license asserted. There is nothing preventing use. In a few days, it will probably be deleted. I'm not sure why you feel the need to disregard showing some good faith towards the uploader, nor am I sure why you feel this need to shortcut the process. Let the deletion process handle it. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 04:00, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
:As I asked before, can you please provide a link to a guideline or policy which supports your position, or evidence that the image can in fact be reasonably assumed to be PD? It is my understanding, supported by the links I've provided, that the rule is to pre-emptively remove images such as this, and as such your position is not correct. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 04:08, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
:: Niteshift36 - I tried to find anything which backs up the claim that the source of this image is US Army and I couldn't find anything via Google Image search at least [https://www.google.com.au/search?hl=en&amp;site=imghp&amp;tbs=sbi:AMhZZivSwQR3c7gdvQtb-m2OqZo7NBPoff8d9ejeJanblTe0o9ikrWRFAtDEkn51ZbS2bRWCqBkbxJsC8c4qDLwagF_1G772gvDTdZNiQnFu6EzFR7jgWJ4LcbtNoxY2ioQfUCILo9O2f0DIRuaPDmseGfppul0-AdnoJdgD2EyDsYtvqYihiBwQFNUdEmMPwa5zGhGKRRwG0nC4X5U7PY0THMru4lCpPIapDGCgMBe31oqSEvWd8N8Ff3dNvyCJUC4DAV1ihQuORBUNkixsalVhcQDOwo28K6zx5pvjk7peuEJenYGw2tH8IMN0sfcCdF-VG4gHAuTvi1Lzp40mUQj-Phf0Ev6oURaZUBcvz48Ms0pOjKLDQ10KrGaXjP2bO0qSwaBQIllHCu8ptVqT4iU4EI1RUUWftWDI5rEp15YRTBgCvI9sgd8fNW91-rjvJtfezKGiavOq6Pj4nio7WBhme-MIZAK1oezzkuOR5MofiosjjzxLWuTC3MT1YcBDi4l1NEjmYvQRnwu4oJe7f_18mi4uoGrV7DahYoDxWJwZcyR956QEi0ejHFnllmphqvs9OKXTWXjy46rgmr8OMZ4ebHSqjspr85R_1GMwwjBHzxcE7Zas4SeE70U8w80WesrtywaclgKSRMhSu6yvO-MIplo969XDAX7ESaQP4GNbpf69rd7iWnhI_1pi1NN9j5GfFwiGNIuXkNgbAggTY5Dyp7ERZhtupG_1kFfUzQ9fDoueSh1obW2lP64CXotx_1ZmlenCg6OMk9ZaOFSXpxwu1FhWXTNG3ytg2m2kyeBAhZyq0S3QZ5-N7tHAy6jO7d-8sNR0Cg3wXBNrCSSFHImeb5WuKZv3VnSK81uIDrpsJ9hB7L7oYsIBo7GJYnLI_1FmHabTZjLxgfrSYH637zff6EwPtLzCG8yyJUtSXGfq4WiCMbgllDNaSULWpU8Q80IkpR7X2JkU5SWr2OjIrIO8VvgOyVFiEq-Fj7hnziXsySIXL-VXF2xDejlS6YwTyNoRP1abQBDeUest2Q-sT7b2Q4PBBYP8C2r5htmTJMS2QpXmTzL8DzoC7DGDNEqMmvOOxMH4sPaXkv2gQu4wGQfPAL0YZ9V8_1PA31da5Bfi-tyci6nnkbfEWQCUKOyhAs-V4PKBYC9v-mMsAgWMEcWE0cmls-EH-ian_1HTzl4BXgt3_1hwGIf41SoYCagwlmtPm7xm9i8sj8go9L0tkTm7R3EqSIP4tYmVuF-MqR3Fonr2xgsjFH6m6LTbOItGLzSzANvGc0YzGdk4JxeIlevaInzbLiSOVfipGEmNTBdycNk_10gPGsGzGaZ7u2UzYaYklAieX0Wb_1LOtl0h7_1k2fA-fDAu2z-0vMHoQTT9zeXPJgiaE_1E4XsxLPyClme5Iqe35ipkCEqDW1KZcyvh00EDDEUqYPSa9IO2xmCBRydQl_1OvVTfRHmXzQ7sANry3ddqMSv_1z13-r6bKafQOp7e&amp;ei=yKibU6rpE8PNkwWahYDABg&amp;start=20&amp;sa=N&amp;biw=1366&amp;bih=620]. It does seem to be used on a large number of SF-related websites but nothing official so I think the uploader's claim is quite reasonably called into question. Nick has outlined several other reasons above to be dubious about it as well. Regardless, your comment above &quot;In a few days, it will probably be deleted&quot; would seem to indicate to me that you also suspect it doesn't meet the grade. Why then are you insisting on keeping it? Would seem to be more about trying to enforce some perceived process (which I note you have so far failed to provide any policy basis for) or to grind some axe for the sake of it when the ultimate outcome is going to be the same anyway. Surely we all have far better things to do than debate this? If we can all see there is a problem with the image licencing why not just remove it from the article and be done with it? Wikipedia and Commons are completely separate so what they decide to do is up to them but that doesn't mean we should use suspect images just because they are made available by a project which has been shown to be devoid of standards at any rate. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 09:07, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
:::As no evidence has been put forward here or at Commons to demonstrate why the photo is legit and PD (or at least can be reasonably assumed to be such), and no policy/guideline has been referred to here to justify retaining the image in the article in lieu of this evidence, I'd just removed it per the policies/guidelines I've linked to above. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 10:16, 16 June 2014 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Delta Force]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=686298435 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20040117090928/http://www.carson.army.mil:80/pao/MountaineerArchive/2003%20Archive/01-16-03.pdf to http://www.carson.army.mil/pao/MountaineerArchive/2003%20Archive/01-16-03.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090611002659/http://us2.newsmemory.com:80/ee/paraglide/default.php to http://us2.newsmemory.com/ee/paraglide/default.php

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 08:31, 18 October 2015 (UTC)

== E Squadron ==
{{ping|BlackScorpio91}}, {{ping|2601:243:403:df09:19d6:da62:a07c:cd40}} &amp; {{ping|2601:243:403:df09:b815:3560:5686:4822}} - &lt;small&gt;(not sure if all three of you are the same person or not, but...)&lt;/small&gt; - Re; this [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Delta_Force&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=704517881 edit]. You can't just add content based on something you read in a novel. All content must have a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] added in support. Additionally, while ''Strike Back'' may be based on some of [[Chris Ryan]]'s experiences in the military, it is also considered fiction. You also can't re-add content without first discussing it, per [[WP:BRD]]. Just find another, more proper, source and you can re-add your edit. Cheers -  ''[[User: Thewolfchild|&lt;sup&gt;the&lt;/sup&gt;'''&lt;big&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Matisse itc;color:red&quot;&gt;WOLF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/big&gt;'''&lt;small&gt;child&lt;/small&gt;]]'' 01:34, 12 February 2016 (UTC)
:*Agreed. At first glance, I'm not even convinced that the Seaspray article is sourced well enough to establish notability. [[User:Niteshift36|Niteshift36]] ([[User talk:Niteshift36|talk]]) 01:43, 12 February 2016 (UTC)

:::First of, I meant Relentless Strike, not Strike Back, my mistake and second of all, well since you want me to discuss it, here I am. The reason I decided to add some more info was because someone else who clearly read Relentless Strike added some info to it and so I thought I'll contribute. Sean Naylor is a pretty credible guy and it has many details on operations that already happened before and still plenty of details about JSOC that I've never heard of before, doesn't mean it's fiction. Read the book, E Squadron superseded SEASPRAY and G Squadron superseded the Funny Platoon. --[[User:BlackScorpio91|BlackScorpio91]] ([[User talk:BlackScorpio91|talk]]) 02:08, 12 February 2016 (UTC)
::::I never said &quot;Relentless Strike&quot; was fiction, I said that about &quot;Strike Back&quot;, and like you said... that was your mistake. You keep telling people to &quot;go read the book&quot;, but that's not how Wikipedia sourcing works. If {{u|Niteshift36}} feels the source is questionable, you guys may have to take the matter to [[WP:RSN]]. And if he feels there is a problem with the [[SEASPRAY]] article, there are also different avenues to pursue for that as well, to either improve the article or delete it. But that discussion should take place on the SEASPRAY talk page. Cheers. -  ''[[User: Thewolfchild|&lt;sup&gt;the&lt;/sup&gt;'''&lt;big&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Matisse itc;color:red&quot;&gt;WOLF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/big&gt;'''&lt;small&gt;child&lt;/small&gt;]]'' 02:16, 12 February 2016 (UTC)

== Training section outdated? ==

The first bullet point claims Delta trains to &quot; shoot without aiming&quot;. Is there a recent source which backs this up? I'm sure this was the protocol at the time the author was in the unit, but techniques change with time. As far as I know, modern techniques do NOT encourage shooting without acquiring a sight picture, which is easier and quicker now with modern sights (EOTechs and Aimpoints.) [[User:Code16|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white; background:black&quot;&gt;c&lt;span style=&quot;background:white;border-radius:7px;color:black&quot;&gt;Ө&lt;/span&gt;de1+6&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Code16|&lt;i style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;TP &lt;/i&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 14:09, 11 September 2016 (UTC)
:The technique is still taught by individuals and organizations, I don't think you are going to find any recent references for quite some time. In any case the article makes it clear things do change and the information may not be up to date. [[User:Sephiroth storm|Sephiroth storm]] ([[User talk:Sephiroth storm|talk]]) 01:57, 26 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>l3de2q6murqlapcqtboeclafhzacq5c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
