<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Type 93 torpedo</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1877496</id>
    <revision>
      <id>687194952</id>
      <parentid>685793037</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-10-23T22:55:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Diannaa</username>
        <id>10728040</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History and Development section;  Splinters  Typo ? */ mark as answered</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15953">{{WPMILHIST
|class=c|&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=y
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=y
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=y
|Japanese-task-force=yes
|Weaponry-task-force=yes
|Maritime-task-force=yes
|WWII-task-force=yes
}}
{{WPJ|class=c|importance=mid|b1=n|milhist=y}}

==Reloading==
The torpedo reloads turned out not to be very practical in the heat of battle as this article suggests. As far as I can determine the IJN only successfully reloaded (and used those reloads during the same engagment) twice during the entire Second World War - this out of hundreds of torpedo attacks made.
*They don't have to reload during the heat of battle. They can wait until night falls or the battle ends to reload. In fact, the Japanese doctrine seemed to focus on night battles, which makes reloading torpedoes much more useful.
::The Type 93's were very heavy weapons and it did take some time for reloads to be accomplished.  Therefore, there weren't very many battles in which reloads were accomplished before the battle was over.  I'll try to list here later which battles in which reloads were done, but, it's going to take me some time to research it. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] 03:57, 18 July 2006 (UTC)

== Specifications? ==

It would be very nice to have specs for this weapon, such as length, weight, and speed.  What kind of fusing did it use? Did it use single or counter-rotating screws?

==Japanese ships sunk by Type 93 explosions==
The article mentions that several Japanese cruisers and destroyers were sunk or heavily damaged when their Type 93s exploded or burned after being ignited during battle.  Perhaps we can list the ships here that this happened to and eventually add it to the article: 

* [[Japanese cruiser Mikuma|''Mikuma'']] (sunk; [[Battle of Midway]])
* [[Japanese cruiser Furutaka|''Furutaka'']] (sunk; [[Battle of Cape Esperance]])
* [[Japanese cruiser Suzuya|''Suzuya'']] (sunk; [[Battle off Samar]])
* [[Japanese cruiser Aoba|''Aoba'']] (heavily damaged during air attack at [[Kavieng]])
* [[Japanese cruiser Mogami|''Mogami'']] (heavily damaged at [[Battle of Leyte Gulf#The Battle of Surigao Strait (25 October)|Battle of Surigao Strait]]
* [[Japanese destroyer Yamagumo|''Yamagumo'']] (sunk; [[Battle of Surigao Strait]])
* [[Japanese cruiser Chokai|''Chokai'']] (sunk; [[Battle off Samar]])
''add more here''
[[User:Cla68|CLA]] 08:00, 7 June 2007 (UTC)
::Source for the information on the cruisers is:  ''Japanese Cruisers of the Pacific War'', (1997) by Eric Lacroix and Linton Wells II, Naval Institute Press, p. 64. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 12:18, 10 January 2010 (UTC)

:Can somebody clarify '''why''' they tended to explode? IIRC, the pure oxygen fuel was highly volatile, as well as suceptible to reacting to chemicals in common use shipboard, &amp; to some metals (reasons USN resisted &quot;oxygen&quot; fish); also, IIRC, &quot;oxygen&quot; is actually hydrogen peroxide... I'd add it, if I was more certain, &amp; had any clue about a source....  [[User:Trekphiler|Trekphiler]] 15:11, 14 November 2007 (UTC)

::Why they tended to explode: The Type 93 used a very high-pressure O2 tank or flask which was also very thin-walled to save weight. If the O2 tank were as robust as typical commercial O2 tank used in hospitals (these are built to withstand fire and tremendous shock to prevent explosion) then the weapon would have been so heavy that much of the advantge of the design (ie, long range/high speed options) would have been lost. Thin-walls and high pressure equals a high probability of catastrophic (ie, explosive) rupture. Japan accepted the risk to acquire what they hoped would be a war-winning weapon. Night fighting in the Solomons proved that the Type 93 was indeed formidable, but US radar and improved tactics made the opportunities to use the Long Lance more and more scarce. However, the action in Surigao Strait showed that the much safer Mark XV torpedo could be just as deadly to capital ships if used properly.[[User:ENScroggs|ENScroggs]] ([[User talk:ENScroggs|talk]]) 21:09, 16 April 2009 (UTC)

:::The Japanese and several other navies experimented with H2O2 as a torpedo and/or submarine fuel, but found it was too dangerous. The Type 93 used compressed gaseous O2 as an oxyidizer in a fairly conventional internal combustion engine, no hyrogen peroxide was used in the Type 93.[[User:ENScroggs|ENScroggs]] ([[User talk:ENScroggs|talk]]) 21:09, 16 April 2009 (UTC)
::::Your two posts above provide extremely valuable information about the torpedo.  Do you have a source for the information?  If so, we can go ahead and add it to the article. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 23:46, 16 April 2009 (UTC)

::Oxygen is not a fuel, surprisingly enough it is a very efficient oxidizer.[[Special:Contributions/212.188.109.61|212.188.109.61]] ([[User talk:212.188.109.61|talk]]) 01:31, 12 December 2008 (UTC)

==Point blank?==
I deleted
:&quot;but did not have as great an effect on the war as it might have had, owing to the Japanese tactic of using submarines to engage warships rather than merchantmen&quot;
because, while true, it's not relevant to the '''torpedo''' (not even the [[Type 95 torpedo|Type 95]], I'd say).  [[User:Trekphiler|Trekphiler]] 15:11, 14 November 2007 (UTC)

== Impact on postwar torpedo development ==

What about impact of Type 93 on other navies after WWII? Soviet and US development, especially the 65-76 that killed the [[Kursk (submarine) | Kursk]] [[Special:Contributions/212.188.109.61|212.188.109.61]] ([[User talk:212.188.109.61|talk]]) 01:18, 12 December 2008 (UTC)

=='Surviving Examples'==
Added a 'Surviving Examples' section. Please add to it more museum examples you can confirm exist.[[User:Catsmeat|Catsmeat]] ([[User talk:Catsmeat|talk]]) 22:09, 20 December 2008 (UTC)

==Navy zealer==
In the &quot;American, Australian, &amp; New Zealand&quot;, I have a question: shouldn't it be &quot;Zealander&quot;? Since the previous 2 use the (adjectival?) form, IMO, it shouldn't just be &quot;NZ&quot;...  [[User:Trekphiler|&lt;font color=&quot;#1034A6&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;TREKphiler&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Trekphiler|&lt;font color=&quot;#1034A6&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;any time you're ready, Uhura&lt;/small&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 01:40, 17 January 2010 (UTC)
  	
== United States Navy Tactics ==
An editor has removed the following text from this article on the grounds that United States naval tactics are inappropriate for an article on a Japanese weapon.  I rather felt this information illustrated how well the Japanese weapon was designed for a specific mission against an identified antagonist:
	
:Anticipating the possibility of war with Japan, the United States planned to move their battleships across the Pacific with the fleet train. Cruisers and destroyers would be responsible for defending this large formation at night. Fleet exercises held during the 1930s revealed the confusing nature of close range engagements during hours of darkness. &quot;Attacking&quot; destroyers closed to within 500 meters (one third mile) of [[USS Saratoga (CV-3)|USS ''Saratoga'']] before being detected during Fleet Problem XIII in 1932. Fleet Problem XV in 1934 placed the destroyer screen 7 miles (11 km) outside of the battleship formation, but the battleships were unable to differentiate &quot;friend&quot; from &quot;foe&quot; at that distance. Screening destroyers were subsequently stationed at the effective searchlight illumination range of 3 miles (5 km) from the battleships. Recognition improved at that distance, but torpedo hit probability increased as evasive maneuvering of the large, compact fleet was restricted within the closer screen.&lt;ref name=&quot;proceedings&quot;&gt;*{{Citation |last = Hone |first = Thomas C. |year = 1981 |title = The Similarity of Past and Present Standoff Threats |editor-last = |periodical = Proceedings of the U.S. Naval Institute |publication-place = Annapolis, Maryland |issue = Vol. 107, No. 9, September 1981 |publisher = |pages = 113–116 |issn = 0041-798X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
	 
:United States Navy ''War Instructions'' (FTP 143) published in 1934 remained in effect through the initial 1942 engagements in the Solomon Islands. The instructions emphasized defense to avoid the attrition objective of Japanese planning:
:* Cruisers were advised to avoid night action unless conditions were favorable.
:* Destroyers were to attack at once with guns and illumination, but reserve torpedoes for use against capital ships.
:Searchlight illumination range effectively covered launch positions of United States torpedoes, but not the Japanese Type 93 Torpedo. Japanese ships could remain outside of illumination range, launching torpedoes at American ships revealing their position with gunfire and searchlights.&lt;ref name=&quot;proceedings&quot;/&gt;

I would value the opinion of other interested parties in assessing suitability for inclusion.[[User:Thewellman|Thewellman]] ([[User talk:Thewellman|talk]]) 01:01, 16 March 2010 (UTC)

:As noted, this is all USN info, with no direct bearing on the Type 93. Information on the tactical use of the Type 93 ''by IJN'' deserves inclusion, not this, any more than IJN response to the [[Mark 15 torpedo|Mk 15]] belongs there. To add, I'd say similar commentary on IJN tactics would be not only okay but desirable. IIRC, Peattie &amp; Evans had some mention in ''Kaigun'' (including a doctrinal ref, explaining why CCs had TT), plus a diagram of IJN's projected &quot;torpedo cruiser&quot;? IIRC, she had 5x5 TT. 80  [[User:Trekphiler|&lt;font color=&quot;#1034A6&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;TREKphiler&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Trekphiler|&lt;font color=&quot;#1034A6&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;any time you're ready, Uhura&lt;/small&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 02:30 &amp; 09:32, 16 March 2010 (UTC)

== Risk ==
[[Samuel Eliot Morison]]'s vol. 3 states that the ''Long Lances'' effectiveness out weighed it's risks.  Since the above list of sunk IJN warships are the result of those &quot;risks&quot;; it would be appropiate to also list the &quot;effectiveness&quot; of the type 93...how many allied warships were sunk by the Long Lance type 93 torpedo?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.104.160.36|75.104.160.36]] ([[User talk:75.104.160.36|talk]]) 03:23, 2 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:An excellent question.  [[User:Trekphiler|&lt;font color=&quot;#1034A6&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;TREKphiler&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Trekphiler|&lt;font color=&quot;#1034A6&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;any time you're ready, Uhura&lt;/small&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 09:39, 2 November 2010 (UTC)

== history and development section ==

I don't think it would be proper to use the word bioluminesence since there is no living organism creating the light.  I'm not sure what the correct term would be.  Perhaps just drop the bio- prefix?  I believe it has something to do with the cavitation and light refraction.  

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavitation  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/8.20.67.4|8.20.67.4]] ([[User talk:8.20.67.4|talk]]) 18:56, 12 June 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Are you quite certain the effect isn't caused by [[Dinoflagellate]]s?  I recall frequently observing luminescence on the ship's bow wave at night in the absence of cavitation.[[User:Thewellman|Thewellman]] ([[User talk:Thewellman|talk]]) 07:40, 13 June 2012 (UTC)

::Certain, no, but confident. I've always understood it to be the product of the disturbance the wake creates in the ocean surface, not by any creature. I am, however, no expert in bioluminescence...  [[User:Trekphiler|&lt;font face=&quot;cursive&quot; color=&quot;#9400D3&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;TREKphiler&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Trekphiler|&lt;font face=&quot;cursive&quot; color=&quot;#008000&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;any time you're ready, Uhura&lt;/small&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 13:39, 13 June 2012 (UTC)
:::I would have guessed dinoflagellates as well. I note that there is no cite for the claim that all torpedoes produce a luminescent wake at night, so we can't check the original source for clarification. Perhaps I should tag this claim? --[[User:Yaush|Yaush]] ([[User talk:Yaush|talk]]) 14:14, 13 June 2012 (UTC)

::::Air bubbles in the water make for a more visible wake but not for a luminescent one. Air bubbles would need to be highlighted by light from the moon, or some other source of light at night. Bioluminescence is probably the reason for wakes visible during moonless nights. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 16:31, 13 June 2012 (UTC)

:::::I deleted this sentence. The claim is not specific to the Type 93 so there's no need to keep it here, no need to try and support it with a reference. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 16:35, 13 June 2012 (UTC)

== Quotes within the section &quot;Specification&quot; ==

There are many parts of that section that seem to be quotes from particular Japanese personnel. The material is not in quotes nor in block quote. I edited a few parts of the writing as the writing seemed a bit clunky. If those lines are quotes they should be in quotes and the original wording restored. I however do not have access to the original material and can't tell if they are quotes from the sources. 

In addition, there is a general lack of citations provided in the article.[[User:Zedshort|Zedshort]] ([[User talk:Zedshort|talk]]) 20:41, 18 September 2014 (UTC)

What is going on with this, I can't see the edit made that provided the source that is displaying? [[User:Zedshort|Zedshort]] ([[User talk:Zedshort|talk]]) 20:57, 18 September 2014 (UTC)

:On the subject of possibly inaccurate information, it should be noted that the info-box gives the maximum range speed as 34-36 knots whereas the article text mentions a speed of 38 knots to achieve maximum range [[User:Friecode|Friecode]] ([[User talk:Friecode|talk]]) 19:54, 5 October 2014 (UTC)

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

== History and Development section;  Splinters  Typo ?  ==

{{request edit|answered=yes}}

A typo appears to exist in the History and Development section, 4th paragraph.

The sentence;
 &quot;The Type 93 was launched from 61 cm (24 in) torpedo tubes mounted on the decks of IJN destroyers and cruisers; some Japanese destroyers, unlike ships of other navies, mounted their banks of torpedo tubes in turrets offering protection against splinters, and had tube loaders.&quot;


Request remove &quot;offering protection against splinters&quot;
Request creating two sentences from original sentence.

New text;
&quot;The Type 93 was launched from 61 cm (24 in) torpedo tubes mounted on the decks of IJN destroyers and cruisers. 
Some Japanese destroyers, unlike ships of other navies, mounted their banks of torpedo tubes in turrets and had tube loaders.&quot;

Unless there is a explanation why World War II IJN ship crews needed protection against splinters and how torpedo tube turrets would protect against splinters, I believe this is a typo.

The sentence seems to be a run on sentence as well.

The error seems to have been added 22:13 12 Jan 2010
:It's not a typo. Splinter protection is sensible, given it's likely if a tincan is being fired on by a heavy. I'm not clear why you think it doesn't make sense. The qualifier &quot;splinter protection&quot; is necessary to distinguish the tube turrets from ones with armor (such as battleship turrets).  [[User:Trekphiler|&lt;font face=&quot;cursive&quot; color=&quot;#9400D3&quot;&gt;TREKphiler&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Trekphiler|&lt;font face=&quot;cursive&quot; color=&quot;#008000&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;any time you're ready, Uhura&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 00:58, 15 October 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lizq801xpmxhugs0frg81u4bc2i8sbu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
