<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Peshmerga</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2966092</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748935750</id>
      <parentid>745102720</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T08:20:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25549">{{talkheader}}
{{WPKU|class=C|importance=high}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=C|Middle-Eastern=yes
|B-Class-1&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;= no
|B-Class-2&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;= yes
|B-Class-3&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;= yes
|B-Class-4&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;= yes
|B-Class-5&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;= yes
}} 
{{Copied |from=Peshmerga |from_oldid=642035565 |to=History of Peshmerga |diff=https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=History_of_Peshmerga&amp;oldid=642036921 }}

==History==
Made minor grammatical and spelling edits to various mistakes in the history article, but did not change the content. [[Special:Contributions/50.158.229.206|50.158.229.206]] ([[User talk:50.158.229.206|talk]]) 03:43, 19 January 2015 (UTC)

==Etymology==
The origin of the name has become a dispute with some of the people. The origin of the name is clearly Persian and is very evident. There are numerous sources indicating this. It's a good idea to create a section in the article which talks about the origin of the name.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:TheScholar2006|TheScholar2006]] ([[User talk:TheScholar2006|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/TheScholar2006|contribs]]) 17:59, 17 June 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Vehicles==

:This sentence is confusing...
:''&quot;During the American-led invasion the Peshmerga captured the rest of the arms of the Iraqi forces, consisting of more than 2000 armoured vehicles (some hundred of them PT-76s and a smaller number of T-55s) and an unknown number of artillery guns.&quot;''
:Does this mean that the Peshmerga have 2,000 Armoured Vehicles or is that the number the Iraqi Forces had at the time?
:Or is it saying they only have 100 PT-76s and some T-55s? Can someone please clarify?
:--[[User:Hibernian|Hibernian]] 18:47, 28 February 2006 (UTC)

the peshmerga captured about 2000 armored vehicles 
no really a lot of pt-76 but several hundreds tanks t-55 or t-54, in kurdistan they said, that they have 700 of them in their inventory , some apcs and anti aircraft armored vehicles with 23 mm anti aircraft and bigger calibres  cannons on them and even some 2S1 M-1974 122mm Carnation Self-propelled howitzers and a lot of towed artillery

::I saw the tanks this summer, and from what i could see they were T-55. They are stationed in two or more compounds outside Sharazur.

==Kurdish state?==

this doesn't make sense:
&quot;Peshmerga forces do make use of female fighters, making it one of only three states in the Middle East that actively uses female soldiers (others being Israel and Iran).&quot;

Since when is Kurdistan a state? Changed it to &quot;nation,&quot; but may need to be considered further.

:I changed it further to 'entity'. This may turn out to be even worse (POV-wise), since neo-nazis, Hamas and Ahmadinejad likes to refer to Israel as the 'zionist entity'. Though, Iran is never referred to as an 'entity' in this POV way so it shouldn't be a problem. [[User:Joffeloff|Joffeloff]] 15:02, 4 July 2006 (UTC)

http://www.zreportage.com/graphics/KurdishWomen/highres/004.jpg

here is a good picture of a female peshmerga

&lt;br&gt;
*The Iraqi constitution recognizes Kurdistan as a region, not a state or entity. ([[Special:Contributions/214.13.130.100|214.13.130.100]] ([[User talk:214.13.130.100|talk]]) 10:27, 12 September 2008 (UTC))

==PKK?==

&quot;The PKK forces are currently involved in a dispute with the military forces of Turkey. This conflict has resulted in 37,000 deaths since it started in 1984.&quot;

Why is PKK mentioned in the article? It's kind of random just sitting there. Peshmerga is only usually used when referring to the fighters in Northern Iraq, not with the PKK. I'm pretty sure when the PKK entered into the areas where KDP and PUK had influence, it usually resulted in conflict between the PKK and the region's Peshmerga.--[[User:MercZ|MercZ]] 15:44, 10 September 2006 (UTC)


::Peshmerga is a term used by Kurds for their guerrila soldiers, this term is not a political term, so anyone who fights for Kurdistan is considered a Peshmerga wether he/she is fighting with PUK, PDK, PDK-I or the PKK. There is however one criteria for many Kurds to call a guerilla soldier a Peshmerga, that is to fight with Honour - and this could be turned against the PKK (or any other party for that matter), as they have been involved in terrorist actions.

== Peshmerga in ancient times ==

There is proof of that peshmergas or an ancestor of the modern peshmerga was present during ancient times.
In ''The Kurds, a consice handbook'' prof. Izady writes:
&quot;The 1500-year dominance of mesopotamia over the Kurdish highlands (since the fall of the Qutils) was reversed...A crusial element in the succes of this epoch-making event was the Medians' brilliant use of people militias or guerrillas. These are calles Kâra in the Behistun inscription in southern Kurdistan. This is the earliest record of this form of warfare, which since has become the preffered form of defence of Kurdistan up to the present day, in the form of the peshmerga&quot;

He also writes: &quot;A point of interest is the term by which the Kurdish fighters are reffered to in the original text of King Ardashir's battle chronicle, the Kârnâmak. The term Jânspâr, a persian equivalent of the modern Kurdish term for their fighters, i.e., peshmerga, both meaning &quot;self-sacrificer&quot; to the cause.&quot;

== Picture of Peshmerga &quot;Special Forces&quot; ==

Why does this Peshmerga have a US flag on his uniform? &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:69.168.215.196|69.168.215.196]] ([[User talk:69.168.215.196|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/69.168.215.196|contribs]]){{#if:03:56, 3 December 2006 (UTC)|&amp;#32;03:56, 3 December 2006 (UTC)|}}.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:The guy with the American flag on his shoulder is an American soldier, but the other three guys are Kurds.  --[[User:D.Kurdistani|D.Kurdistani]] 01:27, 5 December 2006 (UTC)

I disagree.  He has distinctly Kurdish features, and he may have been working with Americans, as an interpreter or as a liaison with the Peshmerga.  Also, it may have just been a show of support for the American invasion by a Peshmerga.  American flags are proudly displayed by Kurds frequently.  The people in Sulayminiyah treated me as if I were a returning king when I visited there, even 3 years after the invasion.

:How can you tell if he has distinctly Kurdish features, you can’t see his face?  --[[User:D.Kurdistani|D.Kurdistani]] 08:01, 11 March 2007 (UTC)
::Green berets helping?--[[User:CnrFallon|Conor Fallon]] ([[User talk:CnrFallon|talk]]) 02:34, 7 May 2009 (UTC)

== What is the size of peshmerga during the gulf war? ==

===What was the size of the Peshmerga forces during the first Gulf War===
You mean what was the size of the Peshmerga forces during the first Gulf War, I don't know that information. But what I can tell you is there current size is between 100,000 - 150,000.   --[[User:D.Kurdistani|D.Kurdistani]] 00:51, 19 December 2006 (UTC)

now is the size higher because they get more money if they are at the army and and lot 
of teenagers learn it!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/87.150.37.141|87.150.37.141]] ([[User talk:87.150.37.141|talk]]) 14:32, 8 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Need sources for the Israel connection? ==

While I don't really doubt that Israel would have helped the Kurds, there still needs to be some evidence to back it up. --[[User:65.81.26.5|65.81.26.5]] 18:21, 18 April 2007 (UTC)

==Reformatted article==
I've decided to [[Wikipedia:Be_bold_in_updating_pages|be bold]] and reformat the History section into more manageable chunks. I have also commented out the headings with no text until such time as someone adds the text, though I am of the impression that most of these headings are unneccessary and disrupt the flow of the article. --[[User:Admbws|Admbws]] 23:38, 22 April 2007 (UTC)

== Misspelling of source ==

As the author of &quot;Willing to Face Death&quot;, the master's thesis that is used throughout this wiki entry, I ask that someone please correct the spelling of peshmerga in the title to &quot;peshmerga&quot;, not &quot;peshmarga&quot;. I used the spelling as used in David McDowell's &quot;Modern History of the Kurds&quot; for uniformity purposes. I understand the openess of the wiki project and of course do not mind my thesis being used, but please correct the title of my work. Thank you.

[[User:192.31.19.50|192.31.19.50]] 17:10, 2 July 2007 (UTC)

== Female peshmerga ==
{{cquote|Peshmerga forces do make use of female fighters, making Kurdistan one of only three entities in the Middle East that actively uses female soldiers (others being Israel and Iran).}}

I guess Turkey is not considered Mideastern?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Slntssssn|Slntssssn]] ([[User talk:Slntssssn|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Slntssssn|contribs]]) 18:12, 14 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Turkey is actually is Mideast country and wanabee-euro [[Special:Contributions/212.187.1.213|212.187.1.213]] ([[User talk:212.187.1.213|talk]]) 15:38, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

'''Well I think Kurdistan is the only entity using females fighters, other countries might have female soldiers but they are never taken into combat.  However we make sue fo female fighters even in comabat.  E.g. Kirkuk was captured by a full female battilion during the last iraqi war. [[User:Shav4life|Shav4life]] ([[User talk:Shav4life|talk]]) 15:17, 5 March 2008 (UTC)'''

According to this source here, [http://www.nato.int/ims/2004/win/turkey.pdf NATO Report&quot;] &quot;Today, women are assigned only as officers and NCOs in the Turkish Armed Forces and
there are no enlisted personnel.&quot;. The Turkish military does not actively use women in armed combat, it seems, though they do have them serving in the police. --[[User:MercZ|MercZ]] ([[User talk:MercZ|talk]]) 18:20, 26 March 2008 (UTC)
:There are female fighters in Israel in [[MAGAV]], Karakal, [[Artillery Corps (Israel)|artillery]] and in [[Combat Engineering Corps (Israel)|Combat Engineering Corps]], see anti-NBC unit 76 in it. [[User:Lizrael|Lizrael]] ([[User talk:Lizrael|talk]]) 11:04, 27 March 2008 (UTC)

== Kurdish Air Force ==

Kurdish Iraqi pilots perform an outside check on their plane before taking off at an airfield in the Kurdish town of Arbat, 30 kms east of the northern Iraqi city of Sulaimaniayh, 24 January 2008. Eighteen pilots, four of them women, graduated yesterday at the town's agricultural airfield established by the Kurdish autonomous region government.
Kurdish Iraqi pilots fly their planes above an airfield in the Kurdish town of Arbat, 30 kms east of the northern Iraqi city of Sulaimaniayh, 24 January 2008. Eighteen pilots, four of them women, graduated yesterday at the town's agricultural airfield established by the Kurdish autonomous region government. 
A female Kurdish Iraqi pilot performs an outside check on her team's plane before taking off at an airfield in the Kurdish town of Arbat, 30 kms east of the northern Iraqi city of Sulaimaniayh, 24 January 2008. Eighteen pilots, four of them women, graduated yesterday at the town's agricultural airfield established by the Kurdish autonomous region government. AFP PHOTO/SHWAN MOHAMMED (Photo credit should read SHWAN MOHAMMED/AFP/Getty Images) 

&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;gallery&gt;
http://img144.imageshack.us/img144/2705/pilots1mu3.jpg

&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;

== Shaky Sources ==

I just wanted to note that the use of Bob Woodward's Plan of Attack is a highly partisan source that contains more rhetoric than historical facts

== Alleged peshmerga killing of Christians in Mosul ==

This section is now getting  so lengthy and detailed, and so far  removed from the subject of the Peshmerga, that it should maybe be split of as a separate article.--[[User:Vindheim|Vindheim]] ([[User talk:Vindheim|talk]]) 17:23, 2 December 2008 (UTC)

They're a terrorist group who want North Iraq to be a Kurdish zone only.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.99.165.106|2.99.165.106]] ([[User talk:2.99.165.106|talk]]) 20:40, 26 January 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

As it should be!!--[[Special:Contributions/108.36.244.16|108.36.244.16]] ([[User talk:108.36.244.16|talk]]) 10:56, 18 July 2015 (UTC)

== Unrelated Citing ==
Citation 22 has nothing to do with the 
and instead seems to be a link to a model buying site.
Removing.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.232.40.102|74.232.40.102]] ([[User talk:74.232.40.102|talk]]) 10:48, 25 October 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== BM-21 Grad ==

In the &quot;Current Equipment of the Peshmerga&quot; section, the BM-21 Grad is listed as an IFV. It's a fantastic piece of kit, but I doubt it fits that purpose... Don't know whether it's a misclassification (MRL or SPA) or a confusion on the vehicle - or some weird variant I'm not aware of.

Cheers for the article, only nitpicking/wondering.
-- 
Blaise  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/129.12.214.183|129.12.214.183]] ([[User talk:129.12.214.183|talk]]) 13:48, 5 July 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

What is IFV? MRL or SPA BM-21 Grad in Kurdistan-iraq http://img109.imageshack.us/img109/2594/33929610150356334048140.jpg  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/78.34.10.53|78.34.10.53]] ([[User talk:78.34.10.53|talk]]) 17:04, 12 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:An IFV is an Infanty Fighting Vehicle which is a vehicle that supports infantry on the ground much like a tank does. I agree with the 129.12. The MB-21 is more of an artillery than an IFV ~ [[User:Zirguezi|''Zirguezi'']] 19:15, 12 November 2012 (UTC)

== A bit old ==

Maybe the article is a bit old and need some updates regarding troop numbers and the equipments?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Alan khalil|Alan khalil]] ([[User talk:Alan khalil|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Alan khalil|contribs]]) 17:38, 2 December 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Re-formatted ==
I have re-formatted the whole equipment section to better columns.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:TheDulki123|TheDulki123]] ([[User talk:TheDulki123|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/TheDulki123|contribs]]) 19:28, 28 December 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Small Arms ==

The BBC recently broadcast footage of peshmerga snipers battling ISIS. Two snipers were shown. One had an L96 or an Artic warfare and an AS50. Both made by Accuracy International. --[[Special:Contributions/92.232.49.38|92.232.49.38]] ([[User talk:92.232.49.38|talk]]) 21:31, 20 June 2014 (UTC)

:The article also fails to mention that Britain has supplied M2 brownings and ammo. --[[Special:Contributions/92.232.49.38|92.232.49.38]] ([[User talk:92.232.49.38|talk]]) 19:50, 23 September 2014 (UTC)

On a similar subject, the given images as cites for the use of M16A2s all show M16A''4''s. I'm unsure what the 2007 DoD article claims since I can't navigate to it to read it, but since photographic evidence shows A4s rather than A2s, I'm going to change that. [[User:Spartan198|Spartan198]] ([[User talk:Spartan198|talk]]) 00:35, 10 December 2015 (UTC)

Also, the image given for the SPAS-12 isn't a SPAS-12, it looks like a Hawk 97-2 to me. [[User:Spartan198|Spartan198]] ([[User talk:Spartan198|talk]]) 00:42, 10 December 2015 (UTC)

== History bit removed to new article? ==

Does anyone have a problem with this? It does not seem right that the article of the millitary force itself is made up of many pages of history. This should be in an article by itself, with a short version on the millitary article.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mozad655|Mozad655]] ([[User talk:Mozad655|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mozad655|contribs]]) 18:27, 11 January 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I do not have a problem with that, if you would summarize each section of the history, like it is in the article of [[United States Army]]. So we do not completely loose the history of Peshmerga article. Greetings --[[User:Moplayer|Moplayer]] ([[User talk:Moplayer|talk]]) 18:37, 11 January 2015 (UTC)

We have not lost the history of Peshmerga. The deleted bits have been moved to a main article, and a have been replaced with a summary in this article no longer than 10-15 lines (Note  [[Republic of Korea Armed Forces]]). The equivalent of the Peshmerga forces is not the United States Army, but United States Armed Forces. The United States Army is a branch of United States Armed Forces. Peshmerga is not a branch of any other force, it is the main force with branches such as Asyaish and Zeravani. Please redo your edit as the material has not been lost, but simply moved since this page should not be dominated by history. The history section is large enough to have its own article which I have created and pasted into without any editing. no editwar

== Feel free to add pictures ==

Feel free to add pictures where you feel would be good. I don't know how unfortunatelyand there are copyright issues &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mozad655|Mozad655]] ([[User talk:Mozad655|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mozad655|contribs]]) 10:12, 13 January 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Utility and transport helicopters ==

Why are utility and transport helicopters under millitary equipment? They are for civil use and I am not aware of any incident where they were used as part of the peshmerga force.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mozad655|Mozad655]] ([[User talk:Mozad655|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mozad655|contribs]]) 15:56, 15 January 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== KS-30 anti-aircraft gun ==

That anti-aircraft gun (which is more like an artillery piece in this day and age), is extremely uncommon. Its Wikipedia page doesn't mention it having been exported to any country outside of the Warsaw Pact so it is not readily discernible from this wiki where the Peshmerga would be able get a hold of one. In other words you have to have a link, and if there are no pictures it doesn't exist.

== 270,000 troops? ==

The actual sources cited say the Peshmerga has 150,000 to 200,000 troops rather than the 270,000 listed. In-fact, I did a google search on &quot;270,000 Peshmerga&quot; and got no results anywhere so I'm not sure what the original editor got it from. In the meantime though I changed it to &quot;150,000-200,000&quot; since that's what the actual sources give.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/72.84.226.174|72.84.226.174]] ([[User talk:72.84.226.174|talk]]) 02:26, 8 September 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Literally &quot;those who face death&quot; ==

I'd like to get this changed. In Sorani Kurdish pesh actually means before and merga means death. So &quot;literally&quot; peshmerga means before death and not those who face death.

It may be taken to mean those who are before death, but using the word literally is inaccurate. The problem is that so many articles have now used the phrase &quot;literally translates as those who face death&quot; that it ends up everywhere.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/109.127.74.162|109.127.74.162]] ([[User talk:109.127.74.162|talk]]) 09:48, 11 October 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

=== Translation of Peshmurga ===

According to my source 'pesh' means to stand in front of while merga means death.  The title of the article also refers to facing death. ([http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/explainer/2003/03/are_kurdish_soldiers_facing_death_or_seeking_death.html Are Kurdish Soldiers &quot;Facing Death&quot; or &quot;Seeking Death&quot;?]) It occurs to me that this can be translated as to face death and 'face death' is a known English expression.  I have experience translating between German and English and am familiar in general terms with problems when a word does not have an exact literal translation between one language and another.  

Input from experts in the relevant languages (Kurdish and Persian) would be appreciated. [[User:Proxima Centauri|Proxima Centauri]] ([[User talk:Proxima Centauri|talk]]) 08:14, 28 November 2015 (UTC)
:I don't have a source for this but I do speak Sorani and AFAIK it does mean &quot;those who face death&quot;. ~ [[User:Zirguezi|''Zirguezi'']] 21:10, 28 November 2015 (UTC)

==Vehicles==
Germany delivered 40 Semi-trailer trucks &quot;Unimog&quot; (not 20), see http://www.bundeswehr.de/portal/a/bwde/!ut/p/c4/NYo9D4JAEET_0S5H40cnodDCAhuEboEN2Qh3ZFkkMf547wpnklfMG2wx1tNbRjIJniZ8YtPLuduh2wcGFr8S24dBlF5Yp3uc--DZEo29SeSoZEFhCWpTMptqNCADNpkrC3fI_nHfU1td63ueH8tb8cBlni8_qo-YzQ!!/  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2003:43:AE05:A801:85BF:691A:866A:EAA1|2003:43:AE05:A801:85BF:691A:866A:EAA1]] ([[User talk:2003:43:AE05:A801:85BF:691A:866A:EAA1|talk]]) 11:52, 19 December 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Peshmerga]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=698825835 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20140911002330/http://www.hometv2go.com/news/read/category/Europe%20News/article/the_associated_press-merkel_arming_kurds_in_germanys_interest-ap to http://www.hometv2go.com/news/read/category/Europe%20News/article/the_associated_press-merkel_arming_kurds_in_germanys_interest-ap
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20080824014202/http://www.tau.ac.il/jcss/balance/Iraq.pdf to http://www.tau.ac.il/jcss/balance/Iraq.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 13:42, 8 January 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Peshmerga]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=748935743 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20150112042513/http://mope.krg.org/about-e.php?z=8&amp;l=3 to http://mope.krg.org/about-e.php?z=8&amp;l=3
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20150727174333/http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3203&amp;context=etd to http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3203&amp;context=etd
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20140808141133/http://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/land/row/type-63-aaa.htm to https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/land/row/type-63-aaa.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 08:20, 11 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>28d7xe6ed3bcardwhftf95vuukfhskp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
