<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:American Civil War</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>15321468</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750887261</id>
      <parentid>750887181</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T01:45:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/50.102.141.170|50.102.141.170]] - &quot;/* True end of the war 20 August 1866 */&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26983">
{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=April 10, 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/American Civil War/archive2
|action1oldid=47772423

|action2=GAN
|action2date=November 4, 2006
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=85575539

|action3=GAR
|action3date=November 26, 2006
|action3link=Wikipedia:Good articles/Disputes/Archive 8#American Civil War
|action3result=Delisted
|action3oldid=88657348

|action4=GAN
|action4date=December 10, 2006
|action4link=Talk:American Civil War/Archive 5#GA passing
|action4result=Listed
|action4oldid=93373461

|action5=WAR
|action5date=12:10, 22 March 2007
|action5link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/American Civil War/Archive 1
|action5result=not approved
|action5oldid=116915570

|action6=WAR
|action6date=20:03, 28 March 2007
|action6link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/American Civil War/Archive2
|action6result=approved
|action6oldid=118578254

|action7=GAR
|action7date=April 21, 2007
|action7link=Wikipedia:Good article review/Archive 16#American Civil War
|action7result=Kept
|action7oldid=124579787

|action8=GAR
|action8date=October 14, 2007
|action8link=Talk:American Civil War/Archive 6#GA Sweeps Review: Pass
|action8result=Kept
|action8oldid=164618610

|action9=FAC
|action9date=16:20, 5 November 2007
|action9link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/American Civil War/archive1
|action9result=not promoted
|action9oldid=169390768

|action10=GAR
|action10date=23:14, 10 December 2008 (UTC)
|action10link=Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/American Civil War/1
|action10result=kept
|action10oldid=257057790

|action11=PR
|action11date=02:50, 23 March 2011
|action11link=Wikipedia:Peer review/American Civil War/archive3
|action11result=reviewed
|action11oldid=419708507

|action12=GAR
|action12date=01:29, 28 July 2012 (UTC)
|action12link=Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/American Civil War/2
|action12result=delisted
|action12oldid=04035795

|topic=War
|currentstatus=DGA

|action13=WAR
|action13date=21:17, 30 May 2014 (UTC)
|action13link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/American Civil War
|action13result=demoted
|action13oldid=610792959
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|A-Class=fail|class=C
&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|ACW=yes|US=yes|portal1-name=United States|portal1-link=Selected article/11}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=C|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=C|importance=Top|USOldwest=Yes|USOldwest-importance=High
 |UShistory=yes
 |USMIL=yes
 |ACW=yes|portal1-name=United States|portal1-link=Selected article/11}}
{{WikiProject United States history|class=C|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject African diaspora|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=C|category=History|WPCD=yes|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Guild of Copy Editors|user=geraldshields11|date=February 15, 2013}}
}}
{{Banner holder|collapsed=yes|
{{Outline of knowledge coverage|the American Civil War}}
{{press
| title = Who, What, Why: How many soldiers died in the US Civil War?
| author = Daniel Nasaw
| date = 4 April 2012
| month= April
| year = 2012
| url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17604991
| org = [[BBC]]
| section = News Magazine BBC website
|collapsed=no}}
{{On this day|date1=2004-12-20|oldid1=8699678 |date2=2005-12-20|oldid2=32085448 |date3=2006-12-20|oldid3=95320435 }}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=History|class=C}}
{{American English}}
{{old peer review|archive=4}}
}}
{{FAQ}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 18
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:American Civil War/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=2 |units=months }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes |template= 
}}
{{findnote}}
== Casualties discrepancy in sidebar ==
The &quot;Casualties and Losses&quot; section of the side panel lists a total dead that is far in excess of what is said on any other site I have looked at &lt;ref&gt;http://www.historynet.com/civil-war-casualties&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.civilwar.org/education/civil-war-casualties.html&lt;/ref&gt;, and within the breakdown is listed a second &quot;total dead&quot; figure for both sides of the conflict, apparently included in the overall bolded figure at the bottom. Is there someone that can clarify/fix what this? [[Special:Contributions/2600:8805:90F:F100:6C6C:5FF3:BA1A:F7CE|2600:8805:90F:F100:6C6C:5FF3:BA1A:F7CE]] ([[User talk:2600:8805:90F:F100:6C6C:5FF3:BA1A:F7CE|talk]]) 23:12, 11 November 2016 (UTC)


== The States in the war==

Couldn't the article contain some information about the states in the war,information such as the battles fought in the state,the secession,the regiments,etc.

In addition,it could contain the two templates of the states in the war to lead for the articles for more information.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/177.19.122.50|177.19.122.50]] ([[User talk:177.19.122.50|talk]]) 03:57, 24 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I added in See also -- * &quot;*state* in the American Civil War&quot;.  Templates sounds more ambitious. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 23:41, 17 August 2016 (UTC)

== France ==

&lt;i&gt;The Confederacy was never diplomatically recognized by any foreign country. &lt;/i&gt;

Total BS.  France was buying cotton from them like it was going out of style.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.51.217.118|24.51.217.118]] ([[User talk:24.51.217.118#top|talk]]) 11:30, 27 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Trade is not the same thing as formal diplomatic recognition.  Just ask Taiwan.  -[[User:Benwbrum|Ben]] ([[User talk:Benwbrum|talk]]) 17:43, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::It is not true that French businessmen were buying lots of cotton from the Confederacy. The Southerners themselves imposed export embargo and early 1861, and by the time it was lifted the US naval blockade shut down 90+ percent of cotton exports. French businessman purchased more cotton from the United States than from the Confederacy. In any case, the French government bought zero cotton and the French government did not recognize the Confederacy. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 20:37, 27 September 2016 (UTC)

:I think that there was one small state in pre-imperial Germany that recognized the Confederacy. IIRC, it was attributed to the fact that the wife of the (count/Duke/Freiherr???) was a southern belle. My source is the book Battle Cry of Freedom by James McPherson, but I can't find the specific passage that talks about it just now. [[User:Jmland3|Jmland3]] ([[User talk:Jmland3|talk]]) 00:52, 20 October 2016 (UTC)

::No that's a myth. The country was [[Saxe-Coburg and Gotha]] and it never recognized the Confederacy.  The key person was [[Ernst Raven]]. Saxe-Coburg and Gotha strongly supported the Union and Raven did not tell it he was applying to the Confederacy--he was something of a rogue. (He had been appointed by S-C-G back in the 1840s when Texas was an independent country.) see the Raven article for details. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 05:22, 20 October 2016 (UTC)

:::How could Saxe-Coburg-Gotha be a &quot;strong supporter of the Union&quot; by recognizing a state that had just '''seceded''' from the Union?  Consular authority was granted to Raven while Texas had delegates seated in the Confederate Congress.  That authority was never withdrawn.  The Duke of SCG would have been an idiot to '''''not''''' know that the aim of Texas was to become part of a Southern Confederacy. [[User:BorderRuffian|BorderRuffian]] ([[User talk:BorderRuffian|talk]]) 1 November 2016 (UTC)BorderRuffian
::::When the war broke out in April S-C-G supported the Union, hosted &amp; Union hailed diplomats (according to NY Times report), &amp; provided recruits &amp; exports. Prince Albert (husband of Queen Victoria) was part of SCG leadership and supported the Union as well, esp in Trent crisis. SCG never supported the Confederacy and never sent  any diplomat.  It did not appoint Raven to the Confederacy.  Texas was out/in/out/in of USA and Raven provided advice to SCG residents trapped there during the war.  [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 21:37, 1 November 2016 (UTC)

:::::I see a NYT article (24 Aug 1862) about a German-American rifle club that had a meeting in Frankfort, Germany (btw that's not in SCG).  They presented a Union flag to the Duke of SCG (he was president of the German Rifle Club).  It's not clear that the Duke actually attended the meeting or was just in the same city at the time.  No where do I see any &quot;pro-Union&quot; statement by the Duke.  &quot;Provided recruits &amp; exports&quot; - I don't see that in the article.  What is your source?  &quot;SCG never...sent  any diplomat.&quot; - No one has made that claim.  A consul is not a diplomat.[[User:BorderRuffian|BorderRuffian]] ([[User talk:BorderRuffian|talk]]) 2 November 2016 (UTC)BorderRuffian

== States ==

Why not list the States that fought with the Union and the Confederacy?  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/177.158.175.240|177.158.175.240]] ([[User talk:177.158.175.240#top|talk]]) 05:27, 9 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


Would have to specifically describe actions of/in some states, for example- Kentucky or Missouri, State governments for both sides, regiments formed and fighting on both sides, etc. [[User:Jmland3|Jmland3]] ([[User talk:Jmland3|talk]]) 00:44, 20 October 2016 (UTC)

== A &quot;civil war&quot; in fact?   ==

This was probably mentioned before, but I think it is an interesting point.  Although I readily concede that the title “American Civil War” should remain in  place as that is what it is known as by most people, the war simply doesn’t appear to have been a civil war which involves two or more factions fighting for control of a single country.  The Confederates were rebels (as they were/are oft referred to both then and now).  They wished to establish an independent sovereign nation within the territory of the USA and did not express any desire to take control of the national government by force and impose their views on the other states.   I just think that towards the beginning of the article it might be acknowledged that the war would have perhaps been more accurately known as a revolutionary one with the goal to establish a separate nation by the rebels exactly as the USA itself had been established.  (No one refers to that as a British civil war.) Thank you.[[User:HistoryBuff14|HistoryBuff14]] ([[User talk:HistoryBuff14|talk]]) 17:13, 3 November 2016 (UTC)

:There is no scholarship to substantiate your POV. As is noted in the Virginia ratification of the U.S. Constitution, only the “people of the United States” have the right to revolution. The states of the U.S. themselves cannot secede without Constitutional Amendment. 

:Individuals conspired in a rebellion to overthrown the United States Government in several states of the Union, and sought to extend their rebellion into states where they could not control or suspend the legitimate state legislatures where members had taken an oath to uphold the U.S. Constitution. These included Missouri, Kentucky, Maryland and a failed effort to occupy Washington DC at the Battle of Bull Run (read the Richmond newspapers of the day). 

:They failed in a civil war with substantial division in their populations in Tennessee and Virginia (West Virginia). Most of the other“seceding” states did not have referendums among their people to submit to the Confederate military dictatorship, with Texas the only other referendum state. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 09:50, 4 November 2016 (UTC)
::TheVirginiaHistorian has stated the history very well indeed. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 09:56, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

:::Yes, the Confederates would almost doubtlessly liked to have had included in their prospective new nation all the slave states, with the possible exception of Delaware, and would have liked to have had Washington D.C. included, perhaps as their capital.  But still, they did not give any indication that they desired to control the Northern free states. If anything, they seemed to have desired to have as little to do with the people of the North as possible.   In regard to Missouri, the legitimately elected state legislature and its governor voted and approved secession from the USA and were driven out by force of arms.  Your point about only the people of the US having the “right”  to revolution and not the states seems a point without a distinction as the legislatures and the governors of the seceded states had been freely elected by those eligible to vote in those times.  Texas actually belatedly held a referendum, as you stated.  

:::But after I left my note, it occurred to me that even the term “revolution” would not really apply as in revolutions, such as those in France and Russia, the revolutionaries took control of the entire country.  The most accurate term would be, I think, a “war of secession.&quot;[[User:HistoryBuff14|HistoryBuff14]] ([[User talk:HistoryBuff14|talk]]) 16:28, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

:See [[Civil war]], territorial integrity is a hallmark of a nation-state - a civil war is not just what you say it is, it includes a region trying to establish its own independent nation-state out of the territory of an existing nation-state. [[User:Alanscottwalker|Alanscottwalker]] ([[User talk:Alanscottwalker|talk]]) 11:01, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

::Then are you suggesting that the American Revolutionary War is a misnomer?  That war should have been called “The Second British Civil War”?[[User:HistoryBuff14|HistoryBuff14]] ([[User talk:HistoryBuff14|talk]]) 16:28, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

:::: That is a nonserious argument. None of the colonies that rebelled in 1775 were a part of Britain. If the Welsh or Scots had joined us maybe we'd have had to rename the war. [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 16:38, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

:::::''My'' argument is “nonserious”?  Are you honest to God serious?  The American colonies were not part of Britain?  Did anyone tell the British that?  It’s a shame if no one had thought of that as presumably from your POV it would have saved a lot of fuss and bother all around![[User:HistoryBuff14|HistoryBuff14]] ([[User talk:HistoryBuff14|talk]]) 16:44, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

::: I'm pretty sure the British knew the colonies were not little counties of Britain, yes. [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 17:51, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

::::Okay, I’ll play along.  With the issuance of the American Declaration of Independence, whom exactly were the Yanks declaring their independence from, and why did the British send generals and armies to America in response?[[User:HistoryBuff14|HistoryBuff14]] ([[User talk:HistoryBuff14|talk]]) 19:27, 4 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::I don't get why, anyone would have so unuanced and unbalanced a view of history that they would argue 'American Revolution' and 'American Civil War' are the same and should be looked at the same - when they were not the same events, at all, and there is no reason to look at them the same. [[User:Alanscottwalker|Alanscottwalker]] ([[User talk:Alanscottwalker|talk]]) 15:11, 5 November 2016 (UTC)

::::::Well, obviously they were not the same event.  They were, however, two wars of the same type.  In both instances, subjects/citizens of an existing nation wanted to secede from the established nation and form their own within the existing territory of the present government.  I really don’t understand how anyone can fail to note this.  What am I missing, please?[[User:HistoryBuff14|HistoryBuff14]] ([[User talk:HistoryBuff14|talk]]) 16:03, 5 November 2016 (UTC)
::::::::You seem to be missing history.  The American Revolution was the first modern colonial war for independence from a mother country. The American Civil War was a civil war between two groups in a single nation. To the extent you wish to compare and contrast those things, here is not the place. -- [[User:Alanscottwalker|Alanscottwalker]] ([[User talk:Alanscottwalker|talk]]) 23:22, 5 November 2016 (UTC)

::::::::: I agree not a Civil War at all, A Civil by the very name is a, entity with a country trying to take over the government. That entity usually does not have their own treaties, currency, defined borders  etc. Like the confederates did, and that why the civil war is also known as &quot;THE WAR BETWEEN THE STATES and THE WAR OF NORTHERN AGGRESSION. But history is written by the victors. If the Britain won the revolutionary war it would probably be known: The British  Civil War and not the American Revolutionary War.   [[User:Thatwhoiswise|Thatwhoiswise]] ([[User talk:Thatwhoiswise|talk]]) 16:42, 8 November 2016 (UTC)

::: The north american colonies were *colonies*, not little bits of Britain. That's what the (successful) attempt to break away a revolution. All parts of the Confederacy were parts of the USA. That's the obvious distinction. 
::: &quot;war between the states&quot; is a neoconfederate term meant to minimize the fact that there was a legitimate US federal government. It was NOT simply a war between two collections of States. it was the elected federal government against pro-slavery yahoos. [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 18:07, 8 November 2016 (UTC)
::::{{Ping|Thatwhoiswise|HistoryBuff14}} “A civil war, by the very name is an entity with a country [sic] trying to take over the government.” No, it is a conflict with an internal faction trying to overthrow a national government within its sovereign territory, such as those rebels who were U.S. citizens pardoned by the U.S. Congress in a blanket amnesty following the American Civil War. 
::::History is written by victors for triumphalism, or by the losers for triumphalism (see [[Lost Cause of the Confederacy]]). But it is also written by scholars accepted at Wikipedia with an eye to chronologically placed accuracy describing the relationships, ideas and self-proclaimed motives of the actors of the time.  [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 14:31, 9 November 2016 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 6 November 2016 ==

{{edit semi-protected|American Civil War|answered=yes}}



[[Special:Contributions/73.185.143.93|73.185.143.93]] ([[User talk:73.185.143.93|talk]]) 16:01, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
hi
:[[File:Red question icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=|alt=]] '''Not done:''' it's not clear what changes you want to be made. Please mention the specific changes in a &quot;change X to Y&quot; format.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; -- [[User:AntiCompositeNumber|AntiCompositeNumber]] ([[User talk:AntiCompositeNumber|Leave a message]]) 16:32, 6 November 2016 (UTC)


== Stonewall Jackson ==
According to this Wikipedia article: American Civil War, Stone Wall Jackson was &quot;killed in Action&quot;. See the &quot;COW&quot; by his name on the info bar. But according to the Stonewall Jackson Wikipedia article &quot;Jackson died of complications from pneumonia on May 10&quot; most historians and books would agree with the death from pneumonia because his friendly fire injuries did not kill him. He was only hit in the arm and hand. 

[[User:Thatwhoiswise|Thatwhoiswise]] ([[User talk:Thatwhoiswise|talk]]) 16:35, 8 November 2016 (UTC)

== True end of the war 20 August 1866  ==

The Civil war ended on 20 August 1866 by presidential order 157 . Many rebels were still fighting well past your claimed end of the war allegedly May of 1865.  The rebel combat ship CSS Shenandoah was still active and fighting till November of 1865. Major divisions of rebels fought until well into October of 1865. The last of the Texas rebels were fighting till Aug of 1866. After they surrendered the president passed the order that the war was over. No confederate unit took up arms after that date.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/50.102.141.170|50.102.141.170]] ([[User talk:50.102.141.170#top|talk]]) 08:23, 20 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The Civil War was a de facto war, not a declared war. Hence, it had a de facto beginning with the siege of Fort Sumpter, and a de facto end with the surrender of major Confederate forces, and the de facto disintegration of the Confederate government in May, 1865. cf The holdout of various Japanese forces and individuals well beyond the end of the Pacific war in September, 1945; some holdouts remained until the 1980's or even (reportedly) the 1990's. No one claims that WWII extended beyond September, 1945. [[User:Tresmegistus|Tresmegistus]] ([[User talk:Tresmegistus|talk]]) 17:30, 20 November 2016 (UTC)

Under your De facto war theory you would have to consider the end of the Civil war to be June 23,1865. On that day General Stand Waite surrendered 15,000 native Americans and assorted Confederate  soldiers. The May 9,1865 date is a joke as over 110,000 active Confederate combat soldiers were still in the field fighting the Union. At minimum the June 23, 1865 date should be used. Even if you used that date what do you consider the Confederate units that fought on till October not commanded by a General. Or the Navy unit not surrendering till November? The true end of the Civil war was 20 Aug 1866 after the last Texas Confederates  surrendered .  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/50.102.141.170|50.102.141.170]] ([[User talk:50.102.141.170#top|talk]]) 20:12, 20 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Under your de facto theory the war began when South Carolina withdrew from the Union and called up troops to train for war on December 20, 1860.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/50.102.141.170|50.102.141.170]] ([[User talk:50.102.141.170#top|talk]]) 03:03, 21 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::Thank you for your interesting interpretation of my comments, and for your contribution to the topic. I would just like to state that my opinion, expressed above, was in no way a theory (as you have put it), it was a statement of facts from which I drew a conclusion. I think we all can agree that the Civil War commenced with the siege of Fort Sumpter, not with the calling to arms of the South Carolina military. The question is: when did the war end? There is no universally accepted date for that. Many have suggested various dates. None of which fits a universally accepted criteria. You have suggested a date of August 20, 1866. I have suggested sometime in May, 1865. I think the question is still open to debate among scholars.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Tresmegistus|Tresmegistus]] ([[User talk:Tresmegistus#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Tresmegistus|contribs]]) 06:11, 21 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::::Wiki writers are not allowed to fix the date.  Our job is to report what is the consensus among reliable secondary sources.  The textbooks I think all have the war ending in late spring, with Juneteen (Texas) a common date. The historians do not focus on obscure naval units that had not heard the news in months. but rather on the people &amp; territory of the Confederacy, who were all under Union power by June.  [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 11:09, 21 November 2016 (UTC)

The 23 June 1865 is much more accurate accurate date than your made up date of May 9, 1865. At least by then the last Major General surrendered his army of 15,000. After that date small Confederate units were still fighting with small arms but no cannons. If you look at Union records they started discharging troops in July in great numbers after the last major Confederate Army surrendered on June 23,1865. So from the Union Army prospective the war was active at least until then.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/50.102.141.170|50.102.141.170]] ([[User talk:50.102.141.170#top|talk]]) 17:14, 21 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::Made-up?  I doubt it was made-up, at least by Wikipedia but what does the source say? At any rate, there is a whole article on [[Conclusion of the American Civil War]], and the Confederate armies were apparently surrendering all over at the time. So, no need for accusations just discuss sources, and make recommendations for text. [[User:Alanscottwalker|Alanscottwalker]] ([[User talk:Alanscottwalker|talk]]) 17:34, 21 November 2016 (UTC)
::I take it the May 9 date was when the president of the Confederacy surrendered himself causing Johnson to declare the war &quot;virtually&quot; at an end. [http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/the-american-civil-war/american-civil-war-may-1865/] [[User:Alanscottwalker|Alanscottwalker]] ([[User talk:Alanscottwalker|talk]]) 17:46, 21 November 2016 (UTC)

After the made up date of May 9,1865 for the end of the Civil war . A Major battle happened at Palmito ranch in Texas where Col John Salmon Ford won a great Confederate victory on May 13. Confederate General Kirby Smith did not surrender his units until June 2, 1865. Finally on 23 June 1865 the last Confederate General surrendered.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/50.102.141.170|50.102.141.170]] ([[User talk:50.102.141.170#top|talk]]) 01:44, 22 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>3xocb3qhjtuy68oetthcxhlv58zdvd7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
