<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Fedor von Bock</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>450824</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744418900</id>
      <parentid>744408968</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-15T02:48:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>K.e.coffman</username>
        <id>22615369</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Dated source */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8846">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=C|importance=mid|B-Class-1=no|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=yes|B-Class-4=yes|B-Class-5=yes}}
{{WPMILHIST
|class=C
|B-Class-1=no
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|German-task-force=yes
|Maritime-task-force=yes
|WWII-task-force=yes
|WWI-task-force=yes
}}
{{WPBiography
|living=no
|class=C
|military-work-group=yes
|military-priority=high
|listas=Bock, Fedor Von
}}
}}
{{Translated page|de|Fedor von Bock}}

==Untitled==
Somebody's Grandpa one imagines [[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 19:51, 1 Feb 2004 (UTC)

----
Apols for the double rollback, my mistake. -- [[User:Francs2000|Graham  :)]] | [[User talk:Francs2000|Talk]] 23:48, 7 Apr 2004 (UTC)

== Where did he die ==

Does anyone know where von Bock was killed? 
Thanks!

[[User:Oremp|Oremp]] ([[User talk:Oremp|talk]]) 10:52, 24 June 2016 (UTC)06.24.2016

F. von Bock has got under bombardment of the English aircraft on the Kiel highway when he together with the wife and the daughter drove the car to Hamburg on May 3. He has been seriously wounded and has died in hospital next day. Where there was this hospital, I don't know.

== Expansion of article ==

I've started to dramatically expand the article. I added several photos along with Military person infobox. I'm currently working on expanding the sections on von Bock's command of Army Group Center and Army Group South during the Invasion of the Soviet Union. I don't have too many sources on his involvment in the invasions of Poland and France so maybe someone could please work on those sections that has access to more information. [[User:Tzar|Tzar]] 01:18, 18 May 2007 (UTC)

:I also need some help on Bock during WW1 [[User:Tzar|Tzar]] 14:20, 18 May 2007 (UTC)
==Fair use rationale for Image:Bock hitler minsk.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:Bock hitler minsk.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:Bock hitler minsk.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is  other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;

[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 13:49, 26 October 2007 (UTC)

==Ancestry==

&quot;He was born into a Prussian Protestant aristocratic family whose military heritage is traceable to the time of the Hohenzollerns.&quot; Since the &quot;time of the Hohenzollerns&quot; ended only in 1918, this is a rather silly statement. How far back can his family's military heritage actually be traced? If no-one knows, this line should be deleted. [[User:Intelligent Mr Toad|Intelligent Mr Toad]] ([[User talk:Intelligent Mr Toad|talk]]) 03:44, 21 July 2009 (UTC)

== Updating research ==

This article would bear some work to update it, the primary acknowledged source being from 1971 there have been significant advances in the understanding of the war on the eastern front since the 70's with much notable research and new writing, some of the comments for example concerning the relationship between Bock and Hitler are somewhat tendentious. There is now strong evidence that Hitler did not change Army Group Centre's orders when the two panzer groups attached to it were diverted away to support operations on the flanks rather than the drive on Moscow.  There is now strong evidence (e.g. considered in David Stahel's book published in 2009) that Hitler always supported a northward diversion in the pre-war planning and accountability for whether this was faulty decision making might more appropriately rest with, for example, Halder and other senior planners in the army for failing to address this with Hitler, and failings in their overall operational planning.  Halder failed to communicate what he knew was Hitler's preference for the northward diversion down the chain of command (he hoped to persuade Hitler to rethink once operations were under way) further exacerbating the problem by making the diversion away from Moscow appear unexpected to commanders like von Bock.  The same book cites primary sources indicating before the invasion Hitler had also shared his views that Army Group South would receive support from the Army Group Centre panzers in a diversion away from Moscow. I just pick these as examples of how new research may influence improving the quality of these articles.  I'm planning to review a number of the WW2 Eastern Front entries. --[[User:Freagman|Freagman]] ([[User talk:Freagman|talk]]) 21:05, 13 April 2010 (UTC)


--[[User:Oremp|Oremp]] ([[User talk:Oremp|talk]]) 11:29, 24 June 2016 (UTC)Oremp 06.24.2016
Fairy tales about &quot;awful frosts&quot; near Moscow in 1941 have been thought up by Germans to justify the defeat in the Moscow fight. Aryan generals just had no right to lose fight to the Russian generals! Loss to &quot;general Moroz&quot; was more honourable. :) But if to study data of weather reports for winter 1941/1942, then it is possible to be convinced that any record frosts (as it is written in article - - 45C!!! ;) why not -60C? lol ) wasn't. Study data of meteorological stations of Moscow and the surrounding cities and you are convinced of everything.

== &quot;Der Sterber&quot; ==

Whatever Time magazine wrote in 1941, in German &quot;der Sterber&quot; does not mean &quot;the Starver&quot;. It does not imply death by starvation. It is simply a made-up word, turning the verb &quot;sterben&quot; (to die) into a noun. Just like &quot;die-or&quot; or &quot;dier&quot; -- it makes not awfully much sense, but in context you can guess the meaning and feelings the word is supposed to convey. Again, starving has nothing to do with it. Probably the nickname is completely made-up or even WW2 propaganda, anyway.[[Special:Contributions/88.68.51.17|88.68.51.17]] ([[User talk:88.68.51.17|talk]]) 21:49, 19 November 2010 (UTC)

&quot;Der Sterber&quot; is not a German word at all. The Dying one is &quot;der Sterbende&quot;.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/80.86.176.180|80.86.176.180]] ([[User talk:80.86.176.180|talk]]) 10:42, 29 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Problematic sources ==

This article suffers from reliance on outdated (1971, 1941 (!)) or unreliable/potentially unreliable sources (some I already tagged, there's also a ''Battlefield Russia'' documentary(. I plan to look at the article in the next couple of days with a critical eye. Meanwhile, if there are any suggestions, please let me know. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 07:41, 7 March 2016 (UTC)

== Dated source ==

Moving this here for storage:

*As a leader who lectured his soldiers about the honor of dying for the [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[Fatherland]], he was nicknamed &quot;''Der Sterber''&quot; (literally, ambiguously, and ironically: &quot;The Dier&quot;).&lt;ref name= &quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;&quot;Death on the Approaches&quot;, ''TIME'' Magazine, 8 December 1941&lt;/ref&gt;

Some more:
*A lifelong officer in the [[German military]], Bock was considered{{by whom|date=May 2016}} to be a very &quot;by the book&quot; [[General (Germany)|general]]. He also had a reputation for being a fiery lecturer, earning him the nickname &quot;Holy Fire of Küstrin&quot;.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=6}} Bock was not considered to be a brilliant theoretician, but possessed a strong sense of determination, feeling that the greatest glory that could come to a German soldier was to die on the battlefield for the Fatherland.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=6}}

{{reflist-talk}}

[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 01:19, 15 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>t1bhwv7ynz2osfvv5jho9xcbz2xyhbk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
