<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:William Mahone</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1450552</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717894206</id>
      <parentid>683141890</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-30T10:41:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot</username>
        <id>27446209</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>subst /Comments to [[WP:DCS|discontinue comments subpage]]) ([[Project:AWB|AWB]] [12009]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14994">{{Talk header}}
{{Article history
|action1=GAN
|action1date=07:18, 2 February 2006
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=37812018
|action2=GAR
|action2date=June 2, 2009
|action2result=Delisted
|action2oldid=288626762
|action2link=Talk:William Mahone/GA1
|currentstatus=DGA
|topic=History}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=C|politician-work-group=yes|politician-priority=Mid|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=Mid|listas=Mahone, William}}
{{WikiProject Virginia| class=C| importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=C|B1=n|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y
|US-task-force=yes|ACW-task-force=yes|Biography=yes}}
{{WikiProject U.S. Congress|class=C|subject=person}}
{{WikiProject Trains|class=C |importance=mid}}
}}

==Other info==
Other info I found but haven't incorporated yet:

*Name:  William Mahone  
*State Served: Virginia  
*Highest Rank: Major-Gen  
*Birth Date: 1826  
*Death Date: 1895  
*Birth Place: Southhampton County, Virginia 
*Army: Confederacy  
*Promotions: Promoted to Full Colonel (6th VA Inf)
*Promoted to Full Brig-Gen
*Promoted to Full Major-Gen (Temporary Rank (declined))
*Promoted to Full Major-Gen

*Colonel, Sixth Virginia Regiment Infantry, , 1861.
*Brigadier general, P. A. C. S., November 16, 1861.
*Major general, P. A. C. S. (temporary rank), June 1, 1864; declined.
*Major general, P. A. C. S., July 30,1864.

Died at Washington, D. C., October 8, 1895.

Commands.

Brigade composed of the Third Alabama, the Sixth, Twelfth, Sixteenth and Forty-first Virginia, and Second (afterward the Twelfth) North Carolina Regiments Infantry, Anderson's Division, A. P. Hill's Corps, Army of Northern Virginia.

Division composed of Wright's Georgia, Weisiger's Virginia, Saunder's Alabama, Harris' Mississippi and Finegan's Florida Brigades, Army of Northern Virginia, 1864-1865.

Source: Hall, Charles B. ''Military Records of General Officers of the Confederate States of America''. Austin, Texas: The Steck Company, 1963.

== Comments ==
At least one source I have read incorrectly states that he was a Senator when he had the stroke on October 1895. He was not reelected after his first term, but was in Washington when he had the stroke and died a week later. 

I am researching the middle name, although the letter T is well-documented. [[User:Vaoverland|Vaoverland]] 04:17, Jan 31, 2005 (UTC)

==William Mahone references==

If you are able to get to a library with newspapers or other material on microfilm, here is a list of mentions of &quot;William Mahone&quot;:

*The Petersburg Index newspaper
#06 April 1867
#09 April 1867
#10 April 1868
#25 April 1868
#27 April 1868
#28 April 1868
#29 April 1868
#04 May 1868
#07 May 1868
#09 May 1868
#14 May 1868
#16 May 1868
#19 May 1868
#22 May 1868
#28 May 1868
#29 May 1868
#30 May 1868
#02 June 1868
#03 June 1868
#11 June 1868
#18 August 1868
#02 October 1868
#06 October 1868
#10 October 1868
#12 October 1868
#13 October 1868
#14 October 1868
#23 November 1868
#07 December 1868
#28 December 1868
#18 January 1870
#11 February 1870
#19 February 1870
#18 March 1870
#18 July 1870
#02 May 1871
#17 November 1871
#04 January 1873

*Petersburg Daily Index newspaper
#15 April 1868  
#07 August 1868 

*Daily Index newspaper (also of Petersburg)
#20 July 1865

*The Virginia Genealogical Society Quarterly
#Series XXIX, Vol 2, Chapter: 01-MAY-1991, Section: Legislative Petitions from Virginia Counties with Significant Record Losses: 3. James City County
#Series XXX, Vol 4, Chapter: 01-NOV-1992, Legislative Petitions

==Census references==
*1860; Age in 1860: 33; Birthplace: Virginia; Home in 1860: Norfolk, Norfolk, Virginia; Post Office: Norfolk; Roll: M653_1366; Page: 529;  Other members of household: Otelia Mahone (age 22), William Mahone (age 3), Butler Mahone (age 1), Otelia Mahone (age 5/12), Susan Voinard (age 63)
*1870; Age in 1870: 43; Birthplace: Virginia; Home in 1870: Lynchburg Lynch Ward, Lynchburg (Independent City), Virginia; Post Office: Lynchburg; Roll: M593_1638; Page: 530; Other members of househould: A L Mahone (age 8), Butler Mahone (age 9), Otelia Mahone (age 34), Otelice Mahone (age 1), William Mahone (age 15)
*1880; Census Place: Petersburg, Dinwiddie, Virginia; Roll: T9_1363; Family History Film: 1255363; Page: 395B; Enumeration District: 95; Other members of household: Otelia, William, Butler, Otelia.

==Other entries==
MAHONE, WILLIAM, civil engineer, soldier, legislator, United States senator, was born Dec. 1, 1826, in Monroe, Va. In his youth he taught school and then became a civil engineer on the surveys of the Orange and Alexandria railroads. He subsequently built the Fredericksburg Plank road; then was chief engineer of the Norfolk and Petersburg railroad; and became its president. He served as quartermaster in the confederate army, and became major-general. In 1881 he entered the United States senate, and served a full term for six years. It was through his policy that the free school system of his state was rehabilitated; the whipping post abolished; the prerequisite to suffrage removed; a colored normal school and a colored asylum were erected; and the state expenses reduced.
:Source: Herringshaw, Thomas William. ''Herringshaw's Encyclopedia of American Biography of the Nineteenth Century'', Chicago, IL: American Publishers' Association, 1902, page 611.

MAHONE, William, a Senator from Virginia; born in Southampton County, Va., December 1, 1826; was graduated from the Virginia Military Institute at Lexington in 1847; taught two years at the Rappahannock Military Academy; became a civil engineer and constructor of the Norfolk &amp; Petersburg Railroad; participated in the Civil War and took part in the capture of Norfolk Navy Yard; raised and commanded the Sixth Virginia Regiment; was engaged in most of the battles of the Peninsular campaign, those on the Rappahannock, and those around Petersburg; was commissioned brigadier general and major general in 1864 and afterward commanded a corps in Hill's division; at the close of the Civil War returned to railroad engineering, and later became president of a trunk line from Norfolk into Tennessee; served in the State senate 1863-1865; elected to the United States Senate as a Readjuster and served from March 4, 1881, until March 3, 1887; unsuccessful candidate for reelection in 1887; died in Washington, D.C., October 8, 1895; interment in Blandford Cemetery, Petersburg, Dinwiddie County, Va.  
:Source: Biographical Directory of the American Congress, 1774-1949, page 1494

MAHONE, William, senator, was born in Southampton county, Va., Dec. 1, 1826; son of Feilding and Martha (Drew) Mahone. He was graduated at the Virginia Military institute in 1847, became a teacher and subsequently a civil engineer, and was constructor of the Norfolk and Petersburg railroad. He joined the Virginia state troops and took part in the capture of the Norfolk navy yard in April, 1861. He raised the 6th Virginia regiment, was appointed its colonel, was promoted to the command of the 2d brigade, Huger's division, Magruder's command, and took a conspicuous part in the battles of Seven Pines and Malvern Hill. In the Chancellorsville campaign he commanded the 3d brigade, R.H. Anderson's division, 1st corps, Army of Northern Virginia, and he took part in the battle of Petersburg, July 1-3, 1863. At Spottsylvania he commanded Anderson's division, when that officer assumed command of Hill's corps, and he drove Hancock back across the river. At North Anna he drove Warren back, and on the Welden road he again opposed Warren, and his division formed the rear of Longstreet's corps previous to the surrender of Lee. He was promoted major-general in August, 1864. After the surrender he became interested in railroad engineering and was elected president of the Norfolk and Tennessee railroad, which he rebuilt. In 1878 he advocate the nomination of G. C. Walker for governor of Virginia before the Democratic state convention. After the election his views on the question of the payment of the public debt did not meet the approval of the Democratic party, and he organized and became a prominent leader of the Readjuster party, which favored the partial repudiation of the state debt, and secured the control of the state legislature. In 1880 he was elected U.S. senator for the term expiring March 3, 1887, and in the senate acted with the Republican party. He was defeated for re-election in 1886 by J. W. Daniel. He died in Washington, D.C., Oct. 8, 1895.
:Source: The Twentieth Century Biographical Dictionary of Notable Americans: Volume VII

== GA Re-Review and In-line citations ==

Members of the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Good articles]] are in the process of doing a re-review of current [[WP:GA|Good Article]] listings to ensure compliance with the standards of the [[WP:WIAGA|Good Article Criteria]]. (Discussion of the changes and re-review can be found [[Wikipedia talk:Good article candidates|here]]). A significant change to the GA criteria is the mandatory use of some sort of in-line citation (In accordance to [[WP:CITE]]) to be used in order for an article to pass the [[WP:V|verification]] and reference criteria. Currently this article does not include in-line citations. It is recommended that the article's editors take a look at the inclusion of in-line citations as well as how the article stacks up against the rest of the Good Article criteria. GA reviewers will give you at least a week's time from the date of this notice to work on the in-line citations before doing a full re-review and deciding if the article still merits being considered a Good Article or would need to be de-listed. If you have any questions, please don't hesitate to contact us on the Good Article project [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Good articles|talk page]] or you may contact me personally. On behalf of the Good Articles Project, I want to thank you for all the time and effort that you have put into working on this article and improving the overall quality of the Wikipedia project. [[User:Agne27|Agne]] 23:35, 25 September 2006 (UTC)

PS: I would also work on incorporating the Trivia section details into the main article sections. [[User:Agne27|Agne]] 23:35, 25 September 2006 (UTC)

== Link to wrong dis-ambiguation ==
The link to &quot;corduroy&quot; in &quot;Civil Engineer, Railroad Builder, Family&quot; section links to fabric, not road type as it appears it should. As a non-registered user, albeit frequent reader, I have no idea how to fix it or if I should be the one to do so! Can someone please fix the link? Thanks!
: Fixed. Thank you for noticing. [[User:Hlj|Hal Jespersen]] 01:39, 18 January 2007 (UTC)

== Political affiliation ==
We don't need a category for this, but I was curious if anyone knew whether or not he was one of the (if not the only) former general officer in the Confederacy to turn to politics as a Republican - likely as a result of the whole Readjuster party outcome.  Worth adding to the article if my assumption is correct, but if an expert knows that'd be great.  [[User:Old64mb|Old64mb]] 07:14, 13 June 2007 (UTC)

==GA Reassessment==
:''This discussion is [[WP:transclusion|transcluded]] from [[Talk:William Mahone/GA1]]. The edit link for this section can be used to add comments to the reassessment.''
&lt;!-- Please add all reassessment comments below this comment, and do not alter what is above. To keep the discussion within a single section, please do not use level 2 headers (==...==) below to break up the reassessment. Use level 3 (===...===), level 4 and so on.--&gt;

===GA Sweeps: Delisted===
As part of the [[WP:WGA|WikiProject Good Articles]], we're doing [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Good articles/Project quality task force/Sweeps|sweeps]] to go over all of the current GAs and see if they still meet the [[WP:WIAGA|GA criteria]]. I believe the article currently has multiple issues that need to be addressed, and as a result, I have delisted the article. Although several references are listed, there are no inline citations for any of the article's content which is required under the criteria. Add additional citations from a variety of sources to provide a balanced representation of the information present. Perhaps sources can be pulled from the main articles linked to within the article. Look to books, magazines, newspaper articles, other websites, etc. The lead also needs to be expanded to better summarize the article. See [[WP:LEAD]] for guidelines. As a side note, I tagged multiple images for moving over to Wikimedia Commons, so if you have an account there, consider moving them over so other language Wikipedias can use them. Although the article has been delisted, the article can be return to GA status by addressing the above points. Once sources are added and cleanup is done, I recommend renominating the article at [[WP:GAN]] or you can contact me on my talk page and I'll review it for you so you can bypass the month-long backlog. If you need assistance with any of these issues, please contact me on my talk page and I'll do my best to help you out. --Happy editing! [[User:Nehrams2020|Nehrams2020]] ([[User talk:Nehrams2020|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nehrams2020|contrib]]) 01:40, 3 June 2009 (UTC)

== Copyright problem ==
[[File:Copyright-problem.svg|left|50x50px]] This article has been reverted by a bot to {{oldid|page=William Mahone|oldid=399060256|label=this version}} as part of [[WP:CCI|a large-scale clean-up project of multiple article copyright infringement]]. (See [[WP:Contributor copyright investigations/Pohick2|the investigation subpage]]) This has been done to remove [[User:Accotink2]]'s contributions as they have a history of extensive copyright violation and so it is assumed that all of their major contributions are copyright violations. Earlier text must not be restored, ''unless'' it can be verified to be free of infringement. For legal reasons, Wikipedia cannot accept [[Wikipedia:Copyrights|copyrighted]] text or images borrowed from other web sites or printed material; such additions must be deleted. Contributors may use sources as a source of ''information'', but not as a source of ''sentences'' or ''phrases''. Accordingly, the material ''may'' be rewritten, but only if it does not infringe on the copyright of the original ''or'' [[Wikipedia:Plagiarism|plagiarize]] from that source. Please see our [[Wikipedia:NFC#Text|guideline on non-free text]] for how to properly implement limited quotations of copyrighted text. Wikipedia takes copyright violations very seriously. [[User:VWBot|VWBot]] ([[User talk:VWBot|talk]]) 14:31, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=269|lastedit=20061005061240|comment=I have assessed this article as GA-class and identified the following areas for improvement:
* The article would benefit from copyediting (try to work trivia items into prose areas)
* The article needs inline citations
[[User:Plange|plange]] 06:12, 5 October 2006 (UTC)}}
Substituted at 10:41, 30 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8ogz7xw69vtsrs0l62f0qso9f0a4p9m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
