<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Armenian Genocide</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>140377</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749765705</id>
      <parentid>749724614</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T01:56:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chewings72</username>
        <id>12824384</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Revert to revision 747370303 dated 2016-11-02 00:21:42 by Fairchia using [[:en:Wikipedia:Tools/Navigation_popups|popups]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="251816">{{FailedGA|07:05, 5 June 2014 (UTC)|topic=World history|page=1}}
{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|search=no|noarchives=yes}}
{{warning|1=Under the discretionary sanctions imposed at [[Wikipedia:Requests for arbitration/Armenia-Azerbaijan 2]], this article has been placed on a '''one-revert rule'''. Any editor who makes more than one revert in a 24-hour period will be ''blocked''. Please edit cooperatively, and seek consensus and compromise rather than edit-war. [[User:Moreschi|Moreschi]] 22:17, 27 January 2008 (UTC)}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
 |action1date=2006-10-27 |action1result=reviewed |action1oldid=84090069
 |action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Armenian Genocide/archive1
|action2=GAN
 |action2date=2007-11-07 |action2result=failed |action2oldid=169853722
 |action2link=Talk:Armenian Genocide/Archive 18#GA Review
|action3=FAC
 |action3date=18:03, 4 April 2008 |action3result=not promoted |action3oldid=202978830
 |action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Armenian Genocide/archive1
|otddate=2008-04-24
|otdoldid=207729745
|otd2date=2009-04-24
|otd2oldid=285854519
|otd3date=2010-04-24
|otd3oldid=358016170
|otd4date=2011-04-24
|otd4oldid=425605379
|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=History|class=C}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Armenia|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Turkey|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Ottoman Empire|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject European history|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Disaster management|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Discrimination|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=c|B1=n|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|B6=|portal1-name=World War I|portal1-link=Selected event/7|WWI=yes|priority=High}}
{{WikiProject Pritzker-GLAM|class=C|importance=low}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=C|category=History}}}}
{{oldpeerreview|archive=1}}
{{oldpeerreview|archive=2}}
{{oldpeerreview|archive=3}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2013-04-24|oldid1=551978268}}
{{Archive box | auto= long | index= /Archive index| search = yes | bot = MiszaBot I | age = 180|&lt;center&gt;
;Other archives&lt;/center&gt;[[/Arguments|Arguments]], [[/Fadix Analysis|Fadix Analysis]], [[/Proposed Refactor|Proposed Refactor]]}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{Talkarchivenav}}
{{dashboard.wikiedu.org assignment | course = Wikipedia:Wiki_Ed/Canisius_College/EDU122_(Spring_2016) | reviewers = [[User:Fairchia|Fairchia]] }}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 24
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(180d)
|archive = Talk:Armenian Genocide/Archive %(counter)d
}}		
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn|target=Talk:Armenian Genocide/Archive index|mask1=Talk:Armenian Genocide/Archive &lt;#&gt;|mask2=Talk:Armenian Genocide/Arguments|mask3=Talk:Armenian Genocide/Fadix Analysis|mask4=Talk:Armenian Genocide/Proposed Refactor|leading_zeros=0|indexhere=yes
}}

==Discussion on lede imperative==

{{ping|EtienneDolet}}A sweeping change such as the one you just made needs to be fully discussed beforehand. I am prepared to let Massacres and Holocaust go, but I cannot accept eliminating Medz Yeghern from the lede. What do you say? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 22:35, 23 April 2016 (UTC)
:You had earlier agreed to the footnote solution! It is pointless discussing anything with you - the only solution you accept is your own and have edit warred that solution into this article for years. I will give temporary support to the edit by EtienneDolet. Once it is there, I will initiate a RfC regarding its content. Once the content issue has been settled, I suggest a second RfC regarding the return of that content to the lede (as said earlier, I do not think the extent of the content overloads the lede). The issue remains the same: either Medz Yeghern is gone from the lede and placed together with the other alternative names in a footnote, or all the alternative names including Medz Yeghern remain in the lede (along with Aghet and the sourced translations of Medz Yeghern). If you, Diranakir, had the slightest interest in consensus based on sourced content, you would have taken up the offer of moderated discussion and presented your what you are &quot;prepared&quot; to accept at that forum. A position that Medz Yeghern with a mere 75 Google Scholar hits remains but &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot; with 394 Google Scholar hits goes is not sustainable. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 23:00, 23 April 2016 (UTC)
::As an alternative, if EtienneDolet want's to drop ''for now'' the format of alternative terms in a footnote solution, a RfC can be started right away on what content related to alternative terms there should be in the lede (with the understanding that if the decided content is too much it could be moved into a footnote). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 23:06, 23 April 2016 (UTC)
:::I thought Diranakir [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=715019838&amp;oldid=715001715 didn't have any objection] to it being in the note. At any rate, my concerns over having Medz Yeghern in the first sentence of this article are growing. Its definition is vague. Its interpretation has been a topic of debate for almost a decade now. More disconcertingly, however, Medz Yeghern has become synonymous with Armenian Genocide denial. Obama has said it for the eighth year now and we all know that he refuses to classify the events as ''genocide''. Unfortunately, much more people would take Obama's understanding of the word Medz Yeghern than any other Armenian historian or etymologist. Even the Turks have [http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/obama-avoids-using-genocide-opting-for-meds-yeghern-in-april-24-commemoration-.aspx?pageID=238&amp;nID=65514&amp;NewsCatID=359 caught on] and I'm not going to let Turkish denialists have the satisfaction of seeing Medz Yeghern in the first sentence of an article on the Armenian Genocide. Unless, for some strange reason, you guys actually think that Obama means genocide when he employs the term Medz Yeghern. I hardly doubt it. As a matter of fact, the only time it is searched is under the context of its denial thanks to Obama's routine annual statements. For all the google scholar (or google in general) hits of Medz Yeghern, 90% of them come after 2008, the year Obama first used the term to describe the events. Unfortunately, whether it's some sort of cruel joke or whether it's some sort mistake of his behalf shouldn't be a concern anymore. The term Medz Yeghern has become corrupted to such a degree that I think it's utterly useless to use it unless there's a long and elaborate explanation as to the terms traditional and historical use. And that's something that only the body of this article can do for us. However, finding it on the first sentence of this article would confuse our English readers and render Medz Yeghern a convenient term to describe the events. I'd much rather it be disassociated with the Armenian Genocide altogether so we wouldn't have to deal with this issue anymore. I also welcome a RfC. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 03:26, 24 April 2016 (UTC)
::::Yes Obama, that blatant little hypocrite (in a week where he has been accused of being a blatant little hypocrite rather more than usual, re UK EU membership referendum), has done it again: [http://armenianweekly.com/2016/04/22/obama-issues-statement-on-armenian-remembrance-day/]. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:44, 24 April 2016 (UTC)

:::::{{ping|EtienneDolet}} At 19:20 on 11 April 2016 (UTC), ArmenOhanian proposed the following to you: 'I think it may be fairly reasonable to establish a comparison with the opening sentence of the entry &quot;Holocaust&quot; and divide the first sentence into two:&quot;The Armenian Genocide (Armenian: Հայոց ցեղասպանություն Hayots tseghaspanutyun), also known as the Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Մեծ Եղեռն, &quot;Great Crime&quot;), was the systematic extermination by the Ottoman government of its Armenian population. It was carried inside and around their historic homeland, which lies within the present-day Republic of Turkey.&quot; '
:::::To which you replied: 'Armen's proposal looks good to me. Étienne Dolet (talk) 19:45, 11 April 2016 (UTC)' and to which I replied: 'I concur. An admirable resolution by Armen. Diranakir (talk) 20:08, 11 April 2016 (UTC)'
:::::Shortly after that statement you basically disappeared from the discussion. You next made a clean sweep of the lede of the article, throwing out Medz Yeghern which you had previously accepted. Concerning your first sentence, I don't know whom you were addressing: 'I thought Diranakir didn't have any objection to it being in the note.' Was that a response to me, the readership, or someone else? I also don't know why you waited until the eve of this April 24th to decide that Medz Yeghern was 'synonymous with Armenian Genocide denial'. If you felt that way you should have done something much earlier, it seems to me. It is a bit over the top to declare Medz Yeghern a denialist term when it is part of the name of the Armenian Genocide Complex in Yerevan and appears on many genocide memorials around the world, as well as being used interchangeably with Hayotz Tseghaspanutyun in both Armenia and the diaspora. President Obama's use of the word instead of genocide cannot change its Armenian meaning. That is a fallacy.
:::::'Meds Yeghern', per se, is referred to 3 times at the highest level of international law as reflected in the Judgment of the ECHR in the case of Perinçek v. Switzerland on 17 December 2013, Strasbourg. In their Joint Concurring Opinion, judges Raimondi and Sajó state: 'There are occasions when judges of human rights courts have a special moral obligation to account for their position to people affected by the judgment. This is such an occasion. Why do we have a special obligation vis-à-vis the Armenians? Because government-led destruction of a people always commands particular attention and imposes special obligations on all of us. From 1915 to 1917, the Armenian people experienced an unimaginable degree of suffering. This tragedy has had lasting consequences even for the fifth generation that grew up after the Meds Yeghern (Great Crime), in part because that past injustice and suffering has never been fully acknowledged or remedied.' 
:::::In paragraph 10 of their Joint Partly Dissenting Opinion, judges Vucinic and Pinto de Albuquerque add a footnote citing President Obama's use of 'Meds Yeghern' in his 14 April 2012 statement. In paragraph 22 they state: 'And the denial of the HayotsTseghaspanutyun (Հայոց Ցեղասպանութիւն) or Meds Yeghern (Մեծ Եղեռն) is no less dangerous than the denial of the Shoah.' For these and many other reasons, I think you should consider that the purpose of this encyclopedia is to inform the public and not to select what seems to be fit at any given moment based on the shifting perspectives of one editor. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 14:57, 24 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::When an average English speaker consults the word Medz Yeghern, they most likely didn't consult it because of what judges Vucinic and Pinto de Albuquerque had to say about it, they consulted it because of Obama said. This is why that term is such a problem, even though there's valid proof that suggests the term can be equated with Armenian Genocide. For every source you can pull that equates Medz Yeghern with genocide, I could probably pull ten more that says its just Obama's way of denying it. Above all, however, this falls under policy. We must provide a [[WP:COMMONTERM]] when it relates to not only the title of this article, but of the alternative use of the term as well. As WP:COMMONTERM states:
{{Quote box
 |quote  = '''Ambiguous or inaccurate names for the article subject, as determined in reliable sources, are often avoided even though they may be more frequently used by reliable sources.'''
 |width  = 80%
 |align  = right
}}

::::::And it is also noted:
{{quote box
|quote='''Ambiguity as used here is unrelated to whether a title requires disambiguation pages on the English Wikipedia. For example, heart attack is an ambiguous title, because the term can refer to multiple medical conditions, including cardiac arrest, myocardial infarction, and panic attack.'''
 |width  = 80%
 |align  = right
}}
{{clear}}
::::::In this case, not only is Medz Yeghern's meaning ambiguous, it's less cited as a term to equate with genocide, and more cited as a term associated with denial. My main concern is creating an image that presents the former, rather than the latter. If we can place Medz Yeghern in another part of this article, with a comprehensive analysis on its usage, I'd welcome it. But in no way do I suggest Medz Yeghern and Armenian Genocide being used interchangeably, at least not anymore. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 17:01, 24 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::It appears, as it has happened in the past, that whatever Armenians do or think is dictated by what other, non-Armenian people think. As Marc Nichanian has written, &quot;Out of this demented, if also logical in its coherence and persistence, historical situation, it follows that any reference to the catastrophic event within the civilized world today is under the obligation to abide by the logic of the executioner.&quot; When an English reader consults the word Medz Yeghern in Wikipedia, it sends them to Armenian Genocide. So your argument that it is Obama and not the judges is totally irrelevant, even if it were true, which you can't prove. In your reasoning, if Obama uses Medz Yeghern, then we should not use it, because it's a term of denial. This reasoning simply plays into the hands of the denier. Incidentally, who told you that it's a term of denial? In case you don't know it, here's the view of a prominent denialist in an open letter to Obama, six years ago: &quot;Although your statement omitted the highly charged word ‘genocide,’ you twice employed the expression ‘metz yeghern‘ which is the exact translation of ‘genocide’ in the Armenian language. You twice employed the expression ‘metz yeghern’ which is the exact translation of ‘genocide’ in the Armenian language&quot; (Hurriyet Daily News, April 20, 2010). I think I don't need to tell you who Sukru Elekdag is, don't I? The only thing that Obama has consistently done from 2009-2016 is to cite the name Medz Yeghern without using &quot;genocide.&quot; As I mentioned in a previous post, the former Prime Minister of Canada, Stephen Harper, in 2006 used Medz Yeghern and &quot;genocide&quot; in the same sentence. Did he use a term of denial? Of course not, he stated his recognition of the genocide. Today, I heard Senator Chuck Schumer saying &quot;Medz Yeghern, the Armenian Genocide&quot; from Times Square (BTW, he didn't say, &quot;Aghed, the Armenian Genocide&quot;) Did he used a term of denial? Of course not. Last year, Pope Francis used &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; in his message. Did he use a term of denial? Of course not.
::::::::On the same token, besides some other tasks I had suggested to you, you may also want to cleanup all references to Morgenthau in this article. Although the &quot;little hypocrite&quot; spoke about him in 2015 and 2016, don't forget that Morgenthau is nothing else but a liar and a creator of &quot;tall Armenian tales,&quot; according to a former Princeton University professor and a sizable amount of Turkish sources. So, since he's &quot;associated with denial,&quot; Morgenthau must go. (Otherwise, there's the risk that some troll will come and plant those sources for you.) Do you want me to continue with this theater of the absurd?
::::::::Should someone &quot;abide by the logic of the executioner&quot; and allow him to dictate what to do? He or his representatives or imitators must even dictate what to do with the language about which they have no clue? I am sure you have learned long time ago that denial is just a continuous fishing expedition for all possible ambiguities in order to create escape doors. I'm afraid you're unwillingly helping feed the fishermen. 
::::::::You don't suggest Medz Yeghern and Armenian Genocide being used interchangeably. It's your and only your problem. FYI, the facts of language doesn't abide by what you or I think. Here is just one example. The President of Armenia said the following in April 2014 (98th anniversary). Of course, he spoke in Armenian, but there is an English translation (www.president.am) that I assume it's official. For your benefit, I took upon myself to find how he said &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; and I'm putting into brackets what I found:
::::::::&quot;Today we bow to the memory of the innocent victims of the Armenian Genocide [Hayots Medz Yeghern]. One and a half million Armenians fell prey to such a crime which did not have a name at that time.(...) Up until now, all the parts of Armenian people and all generations have known what the outcomes of the Genocide [Medz Yeghern] feel like. (...)The 24th of April is just a symbolic date: it is clear that the Armenian Genocide [Hayots Tseghasbanutiun] was not initiated and put an end in one day. (...)Today, we stand on the threshold of the 100th anniversary of the Armenian Genocide [Hayots Tseghasbanutiun]. (...) We are approaching the 100th anniversary of the Armenian Genocide [Hayots Tseghasbanutiun] with a straightening back, open-faced and having a state whose name is the Republic of Armenia.&quot; [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 23:40, 24 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::To Dolet: The reference to the ECHR judges was to show the international standing of the term Meds Yeghern/Great Crime. It can't just be chucked out of the lede as irrelevant or 'ambiguous'. If an average Anglophone reader runs into the word in the AG article, they are given a simple, unambiguous definition right there in the lede, Great Crime. You can't prove that most people look up the word because of the president's statement. The statement doesn't even get that much circulation. There are all kinds of ways someone might look up the word. And it takes more than your reservations or resentments about the use of a word to make it  'ambiguous'. There must be something inherently unclear in its meaning. That is not the case with Medz Yeghern, unless you subscribe to the fraudulent 'alternate meaning' gambit of your associate in this discussion. The meaning of the word in the lede (Great Crime) is very clear, since it is presented as a synonym or alternate name for the Armenian Genocide. The ECHR judges used the term in very straightforward fashion, not a hint of ambiguity. So, the big problem with the term is not a big problem. Your sentence, 'This is why that term is such a problem, even though there's valid proof that suggests the term can be equated with Armenian Genocide', is not as straightforward as it could have been. You should have said, 'Even though there is proof that the term has been equated with the Armenian Genocide, it is a problem'. That's what your sentence amounts to. So spare me the fancy WP acronyms, they don't help. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 01:08, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::I don't subscribe to that fraudulent view, but this is not about me, nor is it about you. It's about the average English reader who has stumbled upon the term Medz Yeghern when Obama gave his annual denial statement. That English reader, who sees Medz Yeghern in the first sentence of this article, is immediately inclined to feel that Obama's statement is justified, and that the terminology he uses is acceptable. That's just great news for denialists who would love to spread the word Medz Yeghern around rather than genocide. And as I have already mentioned, the Turkish media is loving it. So I'm not going to give them that satisfaction. Also, if the Anglophone reader stumbles upon this article, he will see nothing that will help clarify this for him. All he sees is ''&quot;traditionally by Armenians, as Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Մեծ Եղեռն, &quot;Great Crime&quot;)&quot;'' and it would make matters even more confusing. Hell, it makes matters confusing for Armenians, let alone non-Armenians. So in order to shed light on this matter, it needs to be placed under context. That can only happen in the body of the article, or in a note. But not in the first sentence. Also, if this bargain isn't suitable enough for you two, I will go ahead and start a RfC. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 05:34, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::Since you have clearly forgotten what I have written and what you had agreed before (you're surely familiar with the colloquial term &quot;flip-flopping&quot;), I will remind you a small part of my proposal that I left aside for the sake of space at the end of the previous thread:
::::::::::::&quot;Finally, as I had promised, I would like to go back to your proposal of alleviating the burden in the lead and build up on it. I think it may be fairly reasonable to establish a comparison with the opening sentence of the entry &quot;Holocaust&quot; and divide the first sentence into two:
::::::::::::&quot;The Armenian Genocide (Armenian: Հայոց ցեղասպանություն Hayots tseghaspanutyun), also known as the Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Մեծ Եղեռն, &quot;Great Crime&quot;), was the systematic extermination by the Ottoman government of its Armenian population. It was carried inside and around their historic homeland, which lies within the present-day Republic of Turkey.&quot;
::::::::::::Compare:
::::::::::::&quot;The Holocaust (from the Greek ὁλόκαυστος holókaustos: hólos, &quot;whole&quot; and kaustós, &quot;burnt&quot;), also known as the Shoah (Hebrew: השואה, HaShoah, &quot;the catastrophe&quot;), was a genocide in which Adolf Hitler's Nazi Germany and its collaborators killed about six million Jews&quot; (Wikipedia, &quot;Holocaust&quot;)
::::::::::::What part in the first sentence of the Holocaust entry is &quot;confusing&quot; to you or to any average English reader? Is there anything more &quot;confusing&quot; to any average English reader in the first sentence of my proposal, to which you had agreed? The Holocaust or the Assyrian genocide entries may have their proper names in the language of the victims in the first sentence, but the English average reader is too stupid to be able to read the same in the first sentence of the Armenian genocide entry? If you want to write &quot;the Armenian Genocide (Armenian: Հայոց ցեղասպանություն Hayots tseghaspanutyun), also known as the Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Մեծ Եղեռն, &quot;Great Crime&quot;), was the genocide by the Ottoman government of its Armenian population&quot; to make it even more clear by repeating &quot;genocide&quot; twice, go ahead! The Holocaust Have you ever seen in any of Obama's eight statements a translation for &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot;? Have you ever seen in any of Obama's statements for the Holocaust the translation for &quot;Shoah&quot;? Do you need me to clutter even more this page with citations of English readers who are not daunted or confused by the meaning of Medz Yeghern? Didn't I show you, with '''sources,''' that the terminology that Obama uses is acceptable, except that he has excluded the word &quot;genocide&quot;? (Don't tell me that John Paul II, Stephen Harper, or Francis are less famous than Obama, and that's why you don't take him into consideration.) Didn't I show you, with '''sources,''' what '''denialists''' think of Medz Yeghern? You want to create context? As in the case of the Holocaust, create an article, &quot;Names of the Armenian Genocide,&quot; and feel free to start writing it, or even a subsection in the AG article. You say that this is not about you, or about someone else. In the same way that I deferred to the combination of pov and legalese in the picture matter, you may want to finish this conversation for the extensive series of proofs given in this entire talk. There is absolutely no need of RfC, CfR, fCR, or RCf. There is only need for common sense, i. e., &quot;sometimes, someone else may be right.&quot; [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 14:20, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::{{ping|EtienneDolet}}(05:35 above) I'm very glad to see you openly state you do not subscribe to the fraudulent view that 'great calamity' is an alternative definition of Medz Yeghern. I hope we hear nothing more about that nonsense again. The issue was never about you or me in the first place. I doubt you can speak for the average English or Armenian reader. You may be right. You may be wrong. This is something that requires evidence, not a blanket statement by one person. As for the Turkish media loving it, Armen Ohanian has given you an example of a prominent Turk who sent up flares about it, and as usual the Turkish establishment is making its yearly vigorous objections to the statement. What's just great for denialists is for Armenians to be represented as having had no genuine word for their genocide before Raphael Lemkin supplied them with one 25 or so years later. That goes right along with their idea that there was no genocide before 'genocide', a lie. As I said, there is nothing 'confusing' about the use of Medz Yeghern following on the word Armenian Genocide nor in the ECHR verdict I cited. If necessary, further context can be supplied in the body of the article or a note, as you suggest. But because some readers might get the impression that President Obama came close to the truth should not be a criterion for eliminating a word from the lede which has a long and meaningful history of use among Armenians and corresponds in function if not literal meaning to Shoah as used by Jews. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:24, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::The fundamental difference is that the Shoah is not being used in the context of denying the Holocaust. That's why English readers won't get confused when they see it as part of the first sentence of the Holocaust article. The same cannot be said for Medz Yeghern, which has been used consistently by notorious deniers of the AG such as George W. Bush, Barack Obama, and many Turkish denialist journalists and writers. In fact, the entire [http://www.ozurdiliyoruz.com/ I Apologize campaign] uses that term instead of ''soykırım'' or ''jenosit''. And if you don't remember, the founding members of that campaign aimed specifically at not using the term genocide. Hence, many Turkish sources use that term without any problem now, and these sources continue to deny the Armenian Genocide at the same time. And again, this is not about whether Obama, Bush, and Turkish intellectuals/denialists are right or wrong in their understanding of the term, this is about what the word has become regardless of that. It's for the sake of the average English reader who would be more likely learn about the Medz Yeghern under the context of its denial (i.e. Bush's, Obama's annual denialist statement) than he would under the context of what the ECHR or what Armenian linguists or historians use it as. And no, I'm not picking sides either (i.e. &quot;it's Obama's word over John Paul II's&quot;). My fundamental argument is that the term Medz Yeghern is not being used under a universally applicable context, but rather in many different contexts. Therefore, it's not a black or white picture. And to say that my argument is not backed by sources is to not understand the point of this discussion. What were trying to apply here is [[WP:COMMONTERM]]. Obama's annual denialist statement and the media uproar surrounding it is suffice in relation to that argument. Hence, there's no denying that Medz Yeghern is being used to deny the AG. The sources are there and its use as a euphemism to deny the Armenian Genocide is clear and abundant. The fact that the English, Turkish, and Armenian news media outlets have picked up on the whole: &quot;Obama does not call 1915 events ‘genocide’ '''instead''' calls it Medz Yeghern&quot; can be seen all over the internet. The question is whether it belongs in the first sentence of the AG article. I say no, and for good reason. In fact, unless this term cannot be clarified elsewhere in the article, I say remove it from the article in its entirety. Until then, I strongly suggest that such an expression used to appease the whims of a denialist never be equated with the Armenian Genocide. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 17:31, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::::I will repeat the quote: &quot;&quot;Out of this demented, if also logical in its coherence and persistence, historical situation, it follows that any reference to the catastrophic event within the civilized world today is under the obligation to abide by the logic of the executioner&quot; (Marc Nichanian). Therefore, if a couple of American presidents and Turkish denialist journalists and writers use it (BTW, Bush didn't use it, only its &quot;translation&quot;), then the whole world comes to an end and the clarion of retreat must sound: &quot;Remove it from the article in its entirety!&quot; '''This is exactly what denialists want'''. Period. I already quoted you one. How many do you want me to quote you? If your problem is not to write/say anything to feed denialists (Obama or Bush omitting the use of &quot;genocide&quot; does not make them automatic denialists; for instance, go and read what &quot;mass atrocity&quot; means in current genocide scholarship.), don't you know that genocide and denial were/are born at the same time? 
:::::::::::::::::::What about all the others, Americans and Turks who use Medz Yeghern to affirm the genocide? Nada, zilch, because they don't help your case. I brought you the example: you have to purge the AG article from any reference to or from Morgenthau, because he has been rejected as a trustworthy source by American and Turkish denialists. Absurd? It is as absurd as your insistence in taking out Medz Yeghern, the proper name (did I tell you that &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; is not a proper name?) that was characterized, right and wrong, as &quot;the only definition, the only expression, used until the Armenian Diaspora discovered the PR value of ‘Armenian Genocide.'&quot; Do you remember who said this? Baskin Oran, the one guy in the apology campaign who explicitly rejects using &quot;genocide,&quot; but uses &quot;great massacre.&quot; (Do I need to remind you that Turkish denialists did not, do not even accept the term &quot;massacre&quot;?) By the way, if you don't remember, some of the founding members of that campaign '''did not''' aim specifically at not using the term genocide. Here is one quote when the campaign was still ongoing: &quot;The Armenian Genocide is a common tragedy of Anatolia, and even today what is uttered in the villages of Anatolia as part of the old stories is the tally of an unprecedented catastrophe&quot; (Hurriyet Daily News, February 24, 2009). This was Cengiz Aktar. I don't think that you need me to quote Aktar's articles of 2014, 2015, and 2016 where he uses &quot;genocide&quot; all over the place.  
:::::::::::::::::::No word is used in a universally applicable context. An Ukrainian understands &quot;Holodomor&quot; to be genocide, many Russians probably not. That has not deterred whoever created the entry on the Ukrainian Great Famine to call the entry &quot;Holodomor&quot; and not &quot;Ukrainian Great Famine.&quot;
:::::::::::::::::::&quot;Until then, I strongly suggest that such an expression used to appease the whims of a denialist never be equated with the Armenian Genocide.&quot; You're 40 years late. If you read or speak Armenian, you should know by now that Armenians have been doing that since the 1970s at least. Following your strong suggestion, the words &quot;annihilation,&quot; &quot;mass atrocity,&quot; &quot;tragedy,&quot; &quot;catastrophe,&quot; &quot;disaster,&quot; &quot;mass killing,&quot; &quot;murder,&quot; &quot;exile,&quot; &quot;deportation,&quot; and many others must be banned from the vocabulary used by Armenians, because all those words, one way or another, have been used to &quot;appease the whims of a denialist&quot; by past or present American presidents. I'll repeat what I said yesterday: &quot;FYI, the facts of language doesn't abide by what you or I think.&quot; [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 19:36, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::::::To Dolet: The term 'Medz Yeghern/Great Crime' is out in the public domain now, as the numerous examples that have been cited show. Trying to return to the status quo ante by making it taboo is not a responsible solution to the problem of Turkish denialism. It would be a retreat. [[Special:Contributions/76.102.205.37|76.102.205.37]] ([[User talk:76.102.205.37|talk]]) 20:38, 25 April 2016 (UTC) [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 21:29, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::::::::The point I think that EtienneDolet is making is that properly explaining the issues and ambiguities connected to the alternative terms and their usages is far too complex to be contained in the lead, and to just state the alternative names without such an explanation is to not give the whole picture and in fact give an inaccurate picture. I see validity in this, but there is also a bit of cart-before-the-horse here, since there is no article content dealing with these issues and ambiguities, and the lede's purpose is to summarise article content. For example, while just about everyone agrees it is true, an assertion that President Obama has taken to using Medz Yeghern as a way of avoiding saying &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; can only  be made in the article if a source is found making that assertion (and it has to be an actual article or book source, not one of the many critical comments we find posted in response to an article about Obama mentioning Medz Yeghern). Here is one for the first time he said it [https://www.minnpost.com/eric-black-ink/2009/04/president-obama-breaks-promise-call-armenian-genocide-genocide], here is one for his seventh [http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/promises/obameter/promise/511/recognize-armenian-genocide/]. Oh, and btw, we have in that first source an Armenian spokesperson translating Medz Yeghern as &quot;Great Calamity&quot; - an indication that my assertion that the &quot;Great Crime&quot; translation is a translation coined and propagated in recent years as a response to Obama's insincere usage of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; has substance. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:24, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::::::::As I said, if there is the need to give the picture of the alternative names, an article called &quot;Names of the Armenian Genocide&quot; can be created. I already brought the initial sentences in the entries on Holocaust, Holodomor, and Assyrian Genocide as examples to follow in the construction of the initial sentence of the lead. And, btw, since you feel the need to go back again to the same tired issue, let me tell you something: if someone comes and asks for your opinion or mine, you don't become a spokesperson. The &quot;spokesperson&quot; was &quot;speaking as an individual.&quot; Besides, FYI, she doesn't speak the Armenian language. 
::::::::::::::::::::::::As a bonus, regarding the substance of your assertion, I will copy two sources that may help you assess it (http://armenianweekly.com/2013/01/04/the-great-calamity-hoax-what-medz-yeghern-actually-meant-for-the-survivors/). 
::::::::::::::::::::::::This is the direct translation of a text in Armenian:
::::::::::::::::::::::::“But the Armenian martyrdom lacked principally a voice of conscience and piety, a cry of resistance on the part of the millions who constitute that people who carry the entire responsibility for this horrible '''yeghern'''.&quot;
::::::::::::::::::::::::Here is the English published translation:
::::::::::::::::::::::::&quot;What is principally lacking in the records of Armenia’s martyrdom is the voice of conscience on the part of the millions who constitute the nation that is entirely responsible for this fearful '''crime'''.”
::::::::::::::::::::::::The Armenian text is from Aram Andonian's The Great Crime, Boston, 1921, p. 5. The English is from its translation, The Memoirs of Naim Bey, Newton Sq., Pennsylvania, 1964, p. IX. As you surely know, this is the photographic reproduction of the original edition of 1920.
::::::::::::::::::::::::The translation &quot;crime&quot; in this text is '''eighty-nine years (89)''' older than Obama's first statement. So much for the &quot;substance&quot; of your assertion. Please drop the issue and you will do yourself (and others) a favor. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 00:15, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
Yet, Armen Ohanian still continues to quote people like Marc Nishanian, who no average English reader knows about or cares to know about. An average English reader's chances of encountering ''Medz Yeghern'' is not due to Marc Nishanian, it is due to Obama. It would be insane to suggest otherwise. However, we agree that there's more than one understanding of Medz Yeghern, therefore the term needs some sort of clarification, or else we're left with the reader to decide what its definition and signification is at the risk of outside influences (i.e. Obama, Turkish denialists, and etc.). You see, the first sentence of this article cannot be an appropriate place for us to clarify that for them. But if you feel that we should make an article on the names of the AG, be my guest. Personally, I'd rather just have a section devoted to the topic. But until then, don't add such expressions in the article if you're not willing to express who, what, why its being said and for what reason. Otherwise, it shall go. And it doesn't end with Medz Yeghern. We also have the &quot;Armenian massacres&quot; alternative name. Wonderful. I mean really, is this some sort of joke? Britannica used that term to deny the genocide for nearly a decade. The AG article on Turkish Wikipedia, a notorious outlet to deny the genocide, is called &quot;Ermeni Kırımı&quot;, or Armenian Massacres, for crying out loud. In fact, I remember when they first chose the term &quot;Ermeni Kırımı&quot; for their article title, they used these ridiculous alternative names on the English Wikipedia and Britannica to justify their reasoning to avoid the term genocide ([https://tr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Tart%C4%B1%C5%9Fma:Ermeni_K%C4%B1r%C4%B1m%C4%B1&amp;diff=4222961&amp;oldid=4166676][https://tr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Tart%C4%B1%C5%9Fma:Ermeni_K%C4%B1r%C4%B1m%C4%B1&amp;diff=4062158&amp;oldid=4061508][https://tr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Tart%C4%B1%C5%9Fma:Ermeni_K%C4%B1r%C4%B1m%C4%B1&amp;diff=4826533&amp;oldid=4825756]). Talk about embarrassing. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 01:27, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
:::1) Yet, you continue to conveniently forget what I had suggested as the first two sentences of the lead on April 11 and you agreed with. I have to repeat it for the third time (not my fault):
:::&quot;The Armenian Genocide (Armenian: Հայոց ցեղասպանություն Hayots tseghaspanutyun), also known as the Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Մեծ Եղեռն, &quot;Great Crime&quot;), was the systematic extermination by the Ottoman government of its Armenian population. It was carried inside and around their historic homeland, which lies within the present-day Republic of Turkey.&quot;
:::Along the lines of what you [Etienne Dolet] had proposed, footnote 3 would become:
:::&quot;Spelt Հայոց ցեղասպանութիւն in classical Armenian orthography. In English, the Armenian Genocide is also known as the Armenian Holocaust, and, previously, as the Armenian Massacres.
:::(The last sentence of footnote 3 can even be taken out, if someone thinks that its too &quot;heavy.&quot;).Armen Ohanian (talk) 19:20, 11 April 2016 (UTC)
:::The answers by Diranakir and you, the two agreeing parties, were:
:::Armen's proposal looks good to me. Étienne Dolet (talk) 19:45, 11 April 2016 (UTC)
:::I concur. An admirable resolution by Armen. Diranakir (talk) 20:08, 11 April 2016 (UTC)
:::It seems that your absence afterwards made you forget some things. . Following YOUR proposal, I sent two names to the footnotes and even said that they could be deleted, if someone wanted to. Translation: &quot;I'm not going to delete them by myself, I'm looking for consensus.&quot; What are you still talking about Armenian Massacres and the like? Armenian Massacres existed as a name for decades, until the 60s at least, and neither Britannica nor Ermeni Kırımı had anything to do with it. I even wrote &quot;previously,&quot; in case the name would remain, to indicate that it's no longer the case.
:::I didn't quote Marc Nichanian for the average English reader, but to show the ridiculous predicament where we put ourselves (in this case, you put yourself): whoever says something unfavorable, we bow and fall back. If Obama says &quot;Meds Yeghern,&quot; then we automatically want to take it out, because &quot;it's a term of denial.&quot; I have explained extensively why we don't need to take it out, and you have just clung to the scarecrow of the &quot;average English reader&quot; and repeat it mechanically as the ultimate discovery.
:::Again, I don't need to clarify anything. Did Obama write any translation? NO. What did he use? The name that WE have traditionally used. He used the PROPER name, Medz Yeghern, not the legal qualification of the crime committed by the Ottoman Empire, genocide. What does the lead say? Armenian Genocide, traditionally called Medz Yeghern (&quot;Great Crime&quot;). Period. I don't care where your &quot;English average reader&quot; comes from. He will come there and see the article &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; and the first three words: &quot;The Armenian Genocide...&quot; Period. I don't need to explain why the name is that and why the translation is that. There is a reference for that. The same as there is a reference to why it's called Armenian Genocide. It's enough for the &quot;average English reader.&quot; He can go to those references and find for himself/herself.
:::Since you're in the mood of nitpicking where there is no need for (except to play into the hands of denialists, which I'm sure it isn't your actual intention), let me tell you: everybody says Shoah &quot;Catastrophe&quot;. But I'm sure you know that there four or five different translations for Shoah, &quot;catastrophe,&quot; &quot;destruction,&quot; and so on. Go and find the list. Do they talk about &quot;ambiguities&quot;? No. They write &quot;Shoah&quot; &quot;Catastrophe&quot; and end of story. It doesn't even have a footnote. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 02:07, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
::::{{ping|EtienneDolet}} At 01:08, 25 April, I made the point there must be something inherently unclear about the meaning of a word for it to be called ambiguous (not just your issues with the use of the word), then said &quot;That is not the case with Medz Yeghern, unless you subscribe to the fraudulent 'alternative meaning' gambit of your associate in this discussion&quot; to which you responded at 05:34, &quot;I don't subscribe to that fraudulent view&quot;. The fraudulent view I was referring to was the idea that there is a so-called 'alternative definition' of Medz Yeghern, i. e., 'great calamity'. At 01:27 today you said, &quot;However, we agree that there's more than one understanding of Medz Yeghern&quot;, which forces me to ask in order to clear the confusion:  Do you believe Medz Yeghern has two definitions, Great Crime and Great Calamity? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 03:56, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::Why does that matter? [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 06:21, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::The asking of the question &quot;Do you believe Medz Yeghern has two definitions, Great Crime and Great Calamity?&quot; again reveals that Diranakir and his co-actor Armen Ohanian either fail to accept or fail to understand the premise at the very core of Wikipedia. If this failure continues, they should both be blocked because they are unable or unwilling to follow that core premise. Content on Wikipedia is not about what '''you''' believe, or what '''I''' believe, or what '''they''' believe - it is about what acceptable sources say. Such sources give two translations of Medz Yeghern, &quot;Great Crime&quot; and &quot;Great Calamity&quot;. The question that Diranakir and Armen Ohanian need to answer is &quot;do you dispute that sources exist giving translations of Medz Yeghern as &quot;Great Crime&quot; and as &quot;Great Calamity&quot;? [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:25, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Your &quot;answer&quot; actually does not even deserves the time I'm using to write this one. I have presented you an &quot;acceptable source&quot; from 1920 that substantiates that &quot;yeghern&quot; means &quot;crime&quot; and kills your &quot;substantial assertion.&quot; The &quot;answer&quot; is utter silence and insistence on the same broken music. Sources that give the translation as &quot;Great Calamity&quot; exist. The '''actual''' question that you and anyone else need to answer is: &quot;Are those sources reliable&quot;? I'll give you not one, but two examples of what I mean:
:::::::a) A Princeton professor, when he was not yet a professor, said that Morgenthau's memoirs are &quot;crude half-truths and outright falsehoods.&quot; It is an acceptable source? Of course, the assertion was published in a book, and archival sources were used to substantiate the assertion. By your standards, there should be a sentence in the AG article that disputed whatever is quoted about Morgenthau. However, that assertion has been debunked. Therefore, it has no room there, because there is a difference between acceptable and reliable source, which you seem to ignore.   
:::::::b) By your standards, the source used to say that the roundup of the intellectuals in Constantinople happened on the night of April 23-24 is &quot;acceptable.&quot; It was published in a book by a reputable author. But you will never bother to find out that the source is wrong, and the roundup did not happen on the night of April 23-24, because, for you, acceptability and reliability are the same thing.  
:::::::Anything or anyone that doesn't fit your agenda simply deserves to be ignored or dismissed. You insist with intentionally committed fallacies in debates and reasoning, which an outsider observer would call &quot;intellectual dishonesty&quot; (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intellectual_honesty), repeating things already said and factually debunked for the past four years, while hiding behind your particular (mis)interpretation of what &quot;acceptable&quot; is. If this failure continues, I would suggest that you should be blocked, because you are unable or unwilling to believe that there is a limit to what you can &quot;substantiate,&quot; after which you enter into disruption. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 18:41, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Now that you have affirmed that sources do give two translations of Medz Yeghern: &quot;Great Crime&quot; and &quot;Great Calamity, do you agree that Wikipedia content should be content derived from acceptable sources and presented with a neutral point of view, and that an &quot;acceptable source&quot; is a source that is deemed to be reliable and high-quality using Wikipedia's standards? Will you also confirm that you will follow standard Wikipedia procedures to determine the suitability of a source if the quality or reliability of that source is being questioned by you? This is your '''final''' final warning regarding your relentless personal attacks against me - accusing someone of intellectual dishonesty is a personal attack, accusing someone of lying (as in your weasily worded &quot;intentionally committed fallacies&quot;) is also a personal attack.  [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:43, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::I said: &quot;Sources that give the translation as &quot;Great Calamity&quot; exist.&quot; I have '''not''' &quot;affirmed that sources do give two translations of Medz Yeghern: &quot;Great Crime&quot; and &quot;Great Calamity.&quot; This is you who has said the latter, not me. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 01:12, 27 April 2016 (UTC)

If there is a controversy about the terminology for the event and it is mentioned in several presumably reliable sources, it should be covered and explained in the body of the article. Swiping it under the rug to justify someone's sensibilities seems to violate an important part of [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view]]: &quot;Neutrality assigns weight to viewpoints in proportion to their prominence. However, when reputable sources contradict one another and are relatively equal in prominence, describe both points of view and work for balance. This involves describing the opposing views clearly, drawing on secondary or tertiary sources that describe the disagreement from a disinterested viewpoint.&quot; [[User:Dimadick|Dimadick]] ([[User talk:Dimadick|talk]]) 17:53, 27 April 2016 (UTC)
:::{{ping|Tiptoethrutheminefield}} I am willing to delete our exchange about Google Scholar hits under the 'Discussion' heading below but still insist that they are not a reliable source for determining what key words in the Armenian language mean. I appreciate your informing me about the protocol you follow, but I still get substantial fluctuations in results from one transaction to another, confirming that the method is fundamentally flawed, if not a heady form of original research in which arcane protocol combined with tendentious interpretation achieves a desired result. I explicitly said I depended on my arguments above to support my position and not Google Scholar hits. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 05:06, 28 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::It is not just the protocol I follow, it is the correct protocol, see [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Search_engine_test#Using_search_engines]: &quot;The single most useful search engine tool may be the use of quotation marks to find an exact match for a phrase&quot;. You can't get fluctuating results that vary from person to person or location to location - every identical search will give the same result if searched at the same time. If you click on the urls beside my search results you are making a new search, not getting an archive of my search, and you should get the same results. Of course they will vary over time as new sources are either published or put on Google's database but that changes slowly and the numbers will never go down. Except for when I corrected my 2 errors of a missing inverted comma in a search parameter, the search results I got have not varied from when I first posted them a month ago. If you have got questions about Google Scholar's usefulness or how it should be used there are probably other forums to ask about this - but I know that search results from it are more highly regarded for Wikipedia sourcing purposes that Google internet search results. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:20, 28 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::From the page you recommended, &quot;Wikipedia: Search engine test&quot;. You will of course have a ready explanation.
:::::::&quot;Google Scholar provides evidence of how many times a publication, document, or author has been cited or quoted by others. '''Best for scientific or academic topics'''.&quot; [Philology? I don't think so.]
:::::::&quot;A raw hit count should never be relied upon to prove notability. Attention should instead be paid to what (the books, news articles, scholarly articles, and web pages) is found, and whether they actually do demonstrate notability or non-notability, case by case. '''Hit counts have always been, and very likely always will remain, an extremely erroneous tool for measuring notability, and should not be considered either definitive or conclusive'''.&quot;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Diranakir|contribs]]) 15:03, 28 April 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;[[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:09, 28 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::Which is why I did not quote the &quot;raw hit count&quot; for Aghet in my google scholar results, and why I gave '''actual quotes''' from numerous sources in my  earlier &quot;Sources mentioning &quot;Aghet&quot; as a name for the Armenian Genocide (in addition to the 4 sources cited earlier)&quot; post. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 20:21, 28 April 2016 (UTC)

::::::::::'''For the record'''. The following are my Google Scholar results which differed from those of Tiptoethrutheminefield and Tiptoethrutheminefield's critique of same, both of which had been posted in the now-deleted 'Discussion' section which had followed the RfC and was deleted to facilitate the RfC. The whole content of that section is reproduced below.

::::::::::'''Different Google Scholar results obtained'''

::::::::::Aghet + Armenian Genocide, 66 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=%22Aghet%22+%2B+Armenian+Genocide%22&amp;btnG=&amp;as_sdt=1%2C5&amp;as_sdtp=]&lt;br /&gt;
::::::::::Aghed + Armenian Genocide, 48 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Aghed%22+%2B+Armenian+Genocide%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
::::::::::Medz Yeghern + Armenian Genocide, 127 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Medz+Yeghern+%2B+Armenian+Genocide&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
::::::::::Medz Yeghern + Great Crime, 81 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Medz+Yeghern+%2B+Great+Crime&amp;btnG=&amp;as_sdt=1%2C5&amp;as_sdtp=]&lt;br /&gt;
::::::::::Medz Yeghern + Great Catastrophe, 68 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Medz+Yeghern+%2B+Great+Catastrophe&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
::::::::::Medz Yeghern + Great Calamity, 14 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Mets+Yeghern+%2B+Great+Crime&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt; 
::::::::::Mets Yeghern + Armenian Genocide, 22 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=Mets+Yeghern+%2B+Armenian+Genocide&amp;btnG=&amp;as_sdt=1%2C5&amp;as_sdtp=]&lt;br /&gt; 
::::::::::Mets Yeghern + Great Crime,14 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Mets+Yeghern+%2B+Great+Crime&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
::::::::::Mets Yeghern + Great Catastrophe, 11 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Mets+Yeghern+%2B+Great+Catastrophe&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt; 
::::::::::Mets Yeghern + Great Calamity, 7 results [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Mets+Yeghern+%2B+Great+Calamity&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;

::::::::::Comment: I obtained very different results from Google Scholar than those posted above by Tiptoethrutheminefield. Such wide discrepancies prove Google Scholar hits to be completely unreliable as sourcing for this discussion. They constitute, in fact, the polar opposite of reliable sources. Results that fluctuate according to geographical location, date of transaction, etc., are patently disqualifying in any purported source. But let's suppose for the sake of argument that Google hits is the gold standard of truth that Tiptoethrutheminefield makes it out to be. Then it clearly supports my position, not his: Tiptoethrutheminefield boasts of 114 hits for Aghet/Aghed, compared to 75 for Medz Yeghern/Mets Yeghern. I obtained 149 hits for Medz Yeghern/Mets Yeghern, far exceeding that 114. If, additionally, we do a search under the term 'Meds Yeghern + Armenian Genocide', another 130 hits fall into the Medz Yeghern/Mets Yeghern/Meds Yeghern column. But I am not invoking the fickle Google hits standard to prove my point. I have stated my case without it and, as I tried to tell Tiptoethrutheminefield, it is not dispositive. Aghet, a valid and meaningful term in its own context, is not traditional among Armenians as a name for their genocide. It has no parity with Medz Yeghern as far as inclusion in the lede is concerned, and the majority of knowledgeable contributors to this discussion have agreed it does not belong there. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 21:59, 27 April 2016 (UTC)

::::::::::Your search is invalid because you have not searched for any terms! You need to use inverted commas to define each of the actual terms for each search. Otherwise you are just searching for individual words. See my own search results to understand this. Though it is easy to forget how to do it - I now see that I too omitted the inverted commas in my own searches on two occasions (I have now corrected this) However, I think the very act of trying to duplicate what I have done and then presenting your results as being different exhibits bad faith on your part. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 23:08, 27 April 2016 (UTC)

::::::::::Can we please not get off-topic about the ''Aghed'' stuff and defer the conversation over to section above: [[Talk:Armenian_Genocide#Aghet_inserted_in_the_lede]]. I really don't want to confuse non-involved editors who want to participate in the RfC. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 23:57, 27 April 2016 (UTC)

::::::::::Given that the result of Diranakir's Google Scholar search is invalid due to it being incorrectly done, and that assertions derived from that invalid search must also be invalid, and given that if the search had been dome correctly it would have exactly reproduced the data I have already given in the RfC, I suggest that Diranakir deletes this entire section. I have no objection to my response post being deleted. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:46, 28 April 2016 (UTC) [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 22:33, 29 April 2016 (UTC)

== RfC for Medz Yeghern as an alternative name ==

{{Archive top|result=The consensus here seems to be to exclude the term Medz Yeghern as an alternative name in the lead, although clearly there is no prejudice towards discussing the term in the body of the article. Here the closer notes that if there ends up being extended discussion of the term in the article, then it may become necessary to mention the term in the Lead. However at present the consensus is clearly to exclude, and unless the rest of the article changes substantially to include more discussion of the term this consensus should stand. [[User:Maunus|·maunus]] · [[User talk:Maunus|snunɐɯ·]] 09:33, 7 July 2016 (UTC)}}

Should we include the term 'Medz Yeghern' as an alternative name to the Armenian Genocide in the first sentence of this article? Please comment precisely whether you want to exclude or include the term. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 22:13, 26 April 2016 (UTC)

===Comments===
'''Exclude''' per [[WP:COMMONTERM]] and for reasons I have aforementioned. The expression Medz Yeghern (Great Crime, sometimes called &quot;Great Calamity&quot;) has become a euphemism for genocide deniers to use in place of the more appropriate legal term: ''genocide''. This expression is now less cited as a term to equate with genocide, and more cited as a term associated with its denial. Comparisons between the term Shoah and the Holocaust have been made, but the fundamental difference is that the Shoah is not being used in the context of denying the Holocaust. The same cannot be said for Medz Yeghern, however, which has been consistently used by notorious deniers of the AG such as George W. Bush, Barack Obama, and many Turkish denialist journalists and writers. For example, for those who don’t know, Obama has [http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/news/210865/Obama_fails_to_keep_Genocide_recognition_promise_for_8th_year used the term Medz Yeghern] for the eighth year in a row in his most recent annual denialist statement. And again, this is not about whether Obama, Bush, Armenian linguists, and Turkish intellectuals/denialists are right or wrong in their understanding of the term, this is about what the expression is currently [[WP:RECOGNIZABLE|recognized]] as. This is also not to say that Medz Yeghern is not being used to describe the events of 1915 as genocide either. Indeed, there are those who do so. But it is due to these different meanings and interpretations of this particular expression that ultimately render it [[WP:COMMONTERM|too ambiguous]] to be used as an alternative name. Therefore, as another user mentioned, to just state the alternative names without such an explanation is to not give the whole picture and in fact give an inaccurate picture. The first sentence is simply not a convenient place to provide such a clarification on all these interpretations. And if this isn’t handled properly, we're left with the reader to decide what its definition and signification is at the risk of outside influences (i.e. Obama, Turkish denialists, and etc.). Therefore, I '''propose''' removing the term Medz Yeghern in the first sentence of the article and creating a section in the body of the article that clarifies this for our readers by providing a brief explanation of the term, bearing in mind its historical and contemporary usage. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 22:30, 26 April 2016 (UTC)

'''Keep''' based on the exchanges above and the following. The name Medz Yeghern/ Great Crime was given to the Armenian Genocide by the leading lights of the Armenian nation while it was still underway and was adopted by the people as the principal and most enduring name they gave to the apocalypse they had suffered. It has been used continuously since that time and today lends its name to the Armenian Genocide Memorial Complex in Yerevan as well as genocide memorials around the world. The name embodies much more than tragedy. It conveys outrage at the shocking rupture of every rule of civilized behavior that led to national death and destruction. This is the name that it is being proposed to shut away in a footnote with the reasoning that it is too 'ambiguous', does not justify the space it occupies in the lede, and is a 'euphemism' exploited by 'notorious genocide deniers' such as President Obama. Ignoring the word's historic standing as well as its contemporary recognition and notability as reflected in the 2013 ECHR verdict in Perincek v. Switzerland (as 'Meds Yeghern')[http://hudoc.echr.coe.int/eng?i=001-139724]&lt;br /&gt; it is denied the same standing as Shoah because 'Shoah is not used to deny the Holocaust'. The reason it is not used and cannot be used to deny the Holocaust is because Germany long ago accepted responsibility for the Holocaust whereas Turkey has for 101 years adamantly refused to face up to its historic role in the Armenian Genocide and uses every stratagem to continue doing so. Proposing to exclude the word betrays a reluctance to trust the average reader to judge for themselves and overlooks the fact that trying to rehabilitate the Great Calamity fallacy as an 'alternative meaning' invests the word, now very clearly defined, with the very ambiguity and euphemism found to be so objectionable. This would only be a shot in the arm to genocide deniers and apologists who want to convince the world that Armenians never had a clear-cut legal name for what happened to them and that there was no genocide before the word 'genocide', a complete myth. While an understanding was reached above to drop Armenian Massacres and Armenian Holocaust from the lede, these are the reasons I '''propose''' that Medz Yeghern be kept in the lede. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 17:07, 27 April 2016 (UTC)

'''Exclude'''. It is a compromise solution. There are many different terms and phrases used as alternative terms for the Armenian Genocide, and several different nuances of meaning in the usages of each term, or in their translation. To maintain a neutral point of view these terms and translations would need to be given ''equal status'' in the lede. I am not convinced this is impossible to do, but EtienneDolet has said it will make the lede too complicated. If equal status were to be done, the lede would contain something like ''&quot;...also known as the Armenian Holocaust, the Armenian Massacres and, traditionally by Armenians, as the Aghet (Armenian: Աղետ, usually translated as &quot;Catastrophe&quot;) and Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Մեծ Եղեռն, usually translated as &quot;Great Crime&quot; or &quot;Great Calamity&quot;).'' The bulk of the recent talk page discussions over several weeks reveals the refusal of two editors, Diranakir and Armen Ohanian, to accept the equal status principle. This alternative proposal - to remove them all and instead deal with them in the article's content - was an attempt at reaching a compromise. However, the same two editors also oppose the compromise. What I am certain of is that the issues of usage and meaning cannot be explained in the lede - it is not the appropriate place to do it. To cherrypick for lede content just one term (&quot;Medz Yeghern&quot;) from all of them  and to additionally cherrypick just one translation (&quot;Great Crime&quot;) for that one term '''is unsustainably pov'''. As proof, Google Scholar (see section below this post) indicates that there is an alternative Armenian term, &quot;Aghet&quot; (which, when translated, is almost always translated as &quot;Catastrophe&quot;), that is of equal status (actually slightly higher, based on the number and the age of sources), and alternative English Language terms (such as &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot;) are far more popular than either of the two Armenian ones. Google Scholar also indicated differing English-language translations of Medz Yeghern and the choice of which translation to use is defined as a matter of controversy in some of those sources. In addition, there are nuances of usage with Medz Yeghern: it has been written that politicians have been using Medz Yeghern as an Armenian genocide denialist methodology to avoid mentioning the word &quot;genocide&quot; [https://www.armenianow.com/en/genocide/2016/04/19/armenia-genocide-obama-usa-anca/1471/], [https://www.minnpost.com/eric-black-ink/2009/04/president-obama-breaks-promise-call-armenian-genocide-genocide], [http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/promises/obameter/promise/511/recognize-armenian-genocide/]. The singling out as &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; as alone being fit to be included as an alternative term is simply not justifiable.  Note that Diranakir and Armen Ohanian refused an early request for moderated discussion on this issue [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Dispute_resolution_noticeboard/Archive_136#Talk:Armenian_Genocide.23Aghet_inserted_in_the_lede]. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:00, 27 April 2016 (UTC)
{{Hidden begin
| titlestyle = = background:pink; text-align:right; padding-right:3.0em;
| title = ''Google Scholar results''}}
'''Google Scholar results'''&lt;br /&gt;
Aghet + Armenian Genocide, 61 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Aghet%22+%2B+%22Armenian+Genocide%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Aghet + Armenian Genocide + Catastrophe 19 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Aghet%22+%2B+%22Armenian+Genocide%22+%2B+%22Catastrophe%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Aghed + Armenian Genocide, 38 Results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Aghed%22+%2B+%22Armenian+Genocide%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Aghed + Armenian Genocide + Catastrophe, 28 Results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Aghed%22+%2B+%22Armenian+Genocide%22+%2B+%22Catastrophe%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Medz Yeghern + Armenian Genocide, 60 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Medz+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Armenian+Genocide%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Medz Yeghern + Great Crime, 19 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Medz+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Crime%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Medz Yeghern + Armenian Genocide + Great Crime 19 results[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Medz+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Armenian+Genocide%22+%2B+%22Great+Crime%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Medz Yeghern + Great Catastrophe, 13 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Medz+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Catastrophe%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Medz Yeghern + Great Calamity, 9 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Medz+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Calamity%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Mets Yeghern + Armenian Genocide, 15 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Mets+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Armenian+Genocide%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Mets Yeghern + Great Crime, 3 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Mets+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Crime%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Mets Yeghern + Great Catastrophe, 3 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Mets+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Catastrophe%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;
Mets Yeghern + Great Calamity, 4 results [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Mets+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Calamity%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]&lt;br /&gt;

There seems to be no overlap in the alternative spellings of each phrase. There seems to be a minor overlap in the Medz Yeghern / Mets Yeghern translations, where the same source gives two alternative translations [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Medz+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Crime%22+%2B+%22Great+Calamity%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5] &amp; [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Medz+Yeghern%22+%2B+%22Great+Crime%22+%2B+%22Great+Catastrophe%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5]. The results show that of the two terms, the most common term used in association with the term &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; is &quot;Aghet&quot; or its alternative spelling &quot;Aghed&quot;, with 99 hits in total. &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; and its alternative spelling &quot;Mets Yeghern&quot; used in association with the term &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; get 75 hits in total. &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; searched for on its own gets 81 hits, &quot;Mets Yeghern&quot; on its own gets 19 hits, &quot;Aghet&quot; means something in other languages so raw results for &quot;Aghet&quot; on its own are not usable. &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot; gets 394 results, a low number but probably because it will be mainly older sources that use it, sources that Google Scholar neglect. &quot;Armenian Massacres&quot; gets 2760 but those results will include massacres before 1915. &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; on its own gets 13,000 results, which indicates that all the alternative terms actually rarely get mentioned in sources compared to Armenian Genocide (an argument perhaps for all the alternatives being removed from the lede). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:38, 27 April 2016 (UTC)
:Interestingly, the portmanteau word &quot;Armenocide&quot; gets 166 hits. So it too should definitely be classed as an alternative term. [http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22armenocide%22&amp;btnG=&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C5] [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 23:27, 27 April 2016 (UTC)
{{Hidden end}}

'''Keep''' for reasons I have extensively mentioned in the discussion and the following. A proper name, Medz Yeghern, cannot be equated to a generic expression, ''genocide''. It has and is equated by Armenian political and worldwide leaders (president and church heads) to “Armenian Genocide.” Three world leaders, Pope John Paul II, Stephen Harper (PM of Canada, 2006-2015), and Pope Francis, have used Medz Yeghern and ''genocide''. One world leader, Barack Obama, has used Medz Yeghern without ''genocide'' (George W. Bush never used Medz Yeghern), instead using “mass atrocities” (= “mass atrocity crimes”), which currently designates what is embraced by the description “genocide, war crimes, ethnic cleansing, and crimes against humanity.” No serious commentator or newspaper, whether Armenian or not, has called Obama a “denier” and/or equated him to Turkish denialist journalists and writers for using Medz Yeghern, but he has been repeatedly called out for having “refused to properly acknowledge the Armenian Genocide” due to his failure to use ''genocide''. Notorious Turkish deniers, incidentally, have reproached Obama the use of Medz Yeghern, claiming that it is synonymous with ''genocide''.  (There is good reason why the current Turkish government has never used Medz Yeghern and chided Obama for using it.) Medz Yeghern appears in the lede in the same way as Shoah and Sayfo appear in the lede of the articles “Assyrian genocide” and “The Holocaust”, and Holodomor as the entry name for the Ukrainian genocide. The article is named “Armenian Genocide,” starts with the words “The Armenian Genocide...” and continues with its literal translation in Armenian and the proper name in the same language. No ambiguity is left there, and no further clarification is needed in the lede. The issue revolving around “Great Calamity” and “Aghed” (including the groundless attempt to put the latter before Medz Yeghern with omission of conclusive evidence to the contrary) is the result of the years-long search for anything to debunk the meaning of “Great Crime” that may appear acceptable, with token consideration of scholarly procedures, prominence, reliability, and content of sources, and above all, with no knowledge of the language in question to have a saying on linguistic issues. Here is the reason for the so-called &quot;refusal... to accept the equal status principle.&quot; It does not matter whether something is true or just a good find: hence the renewed attempt to impose a solution at any cost through two pseudo-methods: &quot;Google hits,&quot; which could also be claimed to enter any discredited theory to Wikipedia through the backdoor (say, revisionist views in the Holocaust article), or &quot;Google Scholar,&quot; which assumes that a bunch of hits represents the entire universe of mentions (= if it isn't on the Internet, it doesn't exist). Therefore, I '''propose''', as in the case of the article on the Holocaust, to keep the proper name Medz Yeghern in its current place--along the lines of my proposal previously accepted and then left aside--and to add a section as the first one in the body of the article that explains briefly the historical and current use of the term. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 01:50, 28 April 2016 (UTC)
:But you propose excluding the proper name &quot;Aghet&quot;, and the proper name &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot;, and the proper name &quot;Armenocide&quot;, and the &quot;Great Calamity / Great Catastrophe&quot; translations for &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; from the lede, even though all of them are sourced, and &quot;Aghet&quot;, &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot;, and &quot;Armenocide&quot; all have more sources than &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; has. How does your proposal not break [[WP:neutral point of view]] guidelines? Are you also advocating the exclusion of &quot;Aghet&quot;, &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot;, &quot;Armenocide&quot; and the &quot;Great Calamity / Great Catastrophe&quot; translations for Medz Yeghern from your proposed article section that would explain the historical and current use of the term Medz Yeghern? [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 03:02, 28 April 2016 (UTC)
:::This is not the place to discuss the value of each of those names. The lede is one thing, the proposed article section is a different thing. The article section only needs to explain succinctly what &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; means and what has been its historical and current use of the term. Exactly as it is for &quot;Shoah&quot; in the Holocaust article, which doesn't explain other alternative names in the seven lines of the section &quot;Etymology and use of the term.&quot; For all the other names, you can create an article called &quot;Names of the Armenian Genocide,&quot; in the same way as there is an article called &quot;Names of the Holocaust.&quot; [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 03:50, 28 April 2016 (UTC)
::::You are avoiding responding to my valid question. Please answer the accusation that your desire to exclude all sourced alternative terms '''from the lede''' except &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot;, and exclude all sourced alternative translations of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; '''from the lede''' except &quot;Great Crime&quot;, breaks npov guidelines. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:00, 28 April 2016 (UTC)

'''Exclude''' there's many alternative names to the Armenian Genocide, some of these alternative names have different interpretations than others. Therefore, it needs to be better elaborated on somewhere in the article. I'm ready to help out with the section proposal and we need to keep [[WP:NPOV]] in mind when doing so, as {{u|Dimadick}} pointed out above. --[[User:Yerevantsi|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''Ե'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;րևանցի&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Yerevantsi|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]  18:53, 28 April 2016 (UTC)

'''Comment''' I haven't forgotten about this. The consensus is clearly in favor of its removal. But I'll still wait till more opinions before going ahead with the proposal. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 03:37, 23 May 2016 (UTC)
:::Yes, I too was hoping for more opinions, but it does not look like the subject is interesting enough to attract attention. Maybe some work should be started on what the content section will look like that would contain all the alternative terms. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:36, 23 May 2016 (UTC)
* '''Exclude''' from lead. As it stands, I don't think that there's any point as, by the time you get an uninvolved third party around to responding to closing, Legobot will have removed the RfC template. If editors felt strongly about this, I'm sure more would have spoken up. Personally, I've abstained from !voting so far as I don't like getting involved in every RfC, but I am against its use in the lead, particularly as being presented as if it were an alternative COMMONNAME. There's no parallel between the commonality of usage of &quot;Medz/Mets Yeghern&quot; to, for example, that of &quot;Holodomor&quot;. Should the situation change [[WP:CRYSTAL|at a future point in time]], there's no problem in updating the content of the article as it will be obvious. Until then, per Yerevantsi's observation, it should be elaborated on in an appropriate section within the body of the article. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 04:12, 23 May 2016 (UTC)

'''Comment''' to Iryna Harpy: For the record and as far as it bears on future discussion of this topic, the relevant parallel is not between Holodomor and Medz Yeghern, but between Terror-Famine and Medz Yeghern. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 20:53, 23 May 2016 (UTC)
:I disagree. As it is, there were perpetual arguments over the use of 'Holodomor' because it is not an English language COMMONNAME. It is, in fact, ''already'' the equivalent of 'Medz Yeghern' in that it is the Ukrainian language term for that incident. Holodomor has, however, become the prominent name used in English language scholarship, but 'Terror-Famine' and 'Famine-Genocide in Ukraine' appeared in scholarship (and continue to do so) because English language variants on the terminology pre-date the use of Holodomor in scholarship. By the same token, there is no weight of scholarship demonstrating the use of 'Medz Yeghern' as being a common usage alternative nomenclature for the genocide. I responded as I did because I did not see Armen Ohanian's argument about &quot;The Holocaust&quot; or &quot;Holodomor&quot; as being relevant. Comparing the details between genocides is like comparing apples and oranges: each instance should be accorded due respect and treated on a case by case basis.

:Personally, I've never !voted on whether other terms are appropriate for the lead for the Holodomor article, and I'd be reticent to start a discussion as to their usage because the Holodomor related articles are amongst the most egregious on Wikipedia. The &quot;Holodomor&quot; article alone has not budged from its uncomfortable truce-consensus state for years. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 23:38, 23 May 2016 (UTC)
:::The relevance of the argument is that you have three articles on genocides -- &quot;The Holocaust,&quot; &quot;Holodomor,&quot; and &quot;Assyrian genocide,&quot; -- where the name of the event in each language (Shoah, Holodomor, Sayfo) is mentioned in the first paragraph or as the article name. I didn't compare details between genocides, but between the articles on genocides, which is a comparison between four types of apples. The Armenian genocide has a traditionally used proper name in its own language: it is Medz Yeghern (&quot;Great Crime&quot; / &quot;Great Genocide&quot;), not the calque translation of &quot;Armenian Genocide.&quot; There is a weight of scholarship showing its use as proper name.  I have offered a perfectly reasonable solution that makes the first sentence readable and understandable to any middle English reader, as much as it is readable and understandable in the case of the other three articles on genocides. As I have said previously, whether deniers or euphemistic users exploit it, I don't see a reason to budge to denial and use pov as pretext to eliminate the name from the first paragraph. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 00:25, 24 May 2016 (UTC)

:::::To Iryna Harpy: In relation to the articles on the Armenian Genocide and the Holodomor, we are talking about lead sentences that, in each, begin with the principal name of the article followed by alternative names in the 'also known as' clauses. Holodomor and Armenian Genocide correspond to each other in the roles they play in their respective sentences, and Terror-Famine and Medz Yeghern bear a similar relationship in their respective 'also known as' clauses. That should be self-evident. It therefore remains a complete mystery to me what it is you disagree with and why the inclusion of Medz Yeghern in the lede is such a problem for you, given that it is the most enduring name Armenians have given their genocide. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 05:36, 24 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::As indicated it the Google Scholar results that I have posted in this RfC, and in the numerous quotes and citations I provided in earlier discussions, the weight of scholarship that Armen Ohanian mentions actually indicates that ''Medz Yeghern'' is rather far down the list of common names in terms of its academic usage, lower than that of ''Aghet'', and that the English translation that he and Diranakir have repeatedly insisted Medz Yeghern MUST HAVE is not even the majority translation. The edit warring of their pov into the article, and their inability to make or accept any compromise, has led to an impasse where the only solution available to move forward is the removal of all alternative terms from the lede and instead have them mentioned and explained in the body of the article. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:24, 24 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Your &quot;predecessor&quot; in the same insistence on &quot;Great Calamity&quot; and yourself have been UNABLE for the past four years to bring a single, decent argument that proves that &quot;Great Calamity&quot; is a real translation, except quoting people that say so, but do not prove it, and filling these pages with pov, including the newfangled claim that pretends that Google Books or Google Scholar is the modern equivalent of the library of Alexandria, and everything is there. This is, unfortunately, the risk of Wikipedia rules: to quote some secondary source to prove a point leads to not give any attention to the accuracy of the source. (For instance, the picture of the eight severed heads stayed for years in the main text, because there was a source that said that there were the heads of &quot;eight Armenian professors.&quot; I cleaned up the picture, indicating that the source was inaccurate, since the picture had been first published in 1899. Nobody argued, despite the fact that the same picture and the same inaccuracy had been remarked in 1992 by two researchers from Germany, but alas, that article published in an Armenian scholarly journal in English IS NOT in Google Scholar.) The so-called &quot;repeated&quot; insistence is the consequence of the repeated insistence on anything that may serve to prove your pov. It is akin to the picture that we see every time that a denialist rejects a certain fact and someone upholds the fact. Another denialist comes back with the same denial and someone else upholds the same fact, and the same goes again and again. Here, the difference is that someone rejects a fact (I don't imply that anyone is a denialist here), and when that fact is upheld with stronger proof, the same person comes back with a variation on the same theme, and the vicious circle continues again and again. Now the latest &quot;discovery&quot; is the existence of ''Aghed'' and ''Armenocide'' (Armenocide was invented fifty years ago or so, and neither Aghed nor Armenocide are &quot;more common Common Names,&quot; except in your opinion, which unfortunately rejects referenced opinions) to help clutter the lead and, in this way, create an artificial &quot;impasse&quot; with the aim of imposing the pov by any means. I repeat it: a clean version of the lede had been introduced and won necessary consensus more than a month ago, but unjustifiable pov concerns botched that agreement and led to this unnecessary situation.[[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 20:56, 24 May 2016 (UTC)

::::::::::For the record: The alternative name Medz Yeghern (Մեծ Եղեռն) has been part of the lede for a decade now and it is curious that those who are presently campaigning to have it thrown out have only recently been seized with the urgency of applying the COMMON NAME principle to it. Where were they all that time with the COMMON NAME principle? Or is their real problem with its UNAMBIGUOUS and fully documented translation as Great Crime? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 22:35, 24 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::And the reason it can no longer remain is thanks to your pov edit warring. Past versions of the article lede included Great Calamity as either the main translation of Medz Yeghern, [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;direction=next&amp;oldid=495871173], or its only translation [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;oldid=254356079]. But you and Armen Ohanian have edit warred for years against that referenced content and also against the addition of any additional alternative names even if better sourced, and have insisted that the recently-coined &quot;Great Crime&quot; translation is the only valid one despite numerous sources indicating otherwise. You have been unwilling to accept any compromise. So the only solution is to remove all of the existing alternative terms. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:31, 25 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Unfortunately, your response already shows that you seem to only read what it suits your pov. There was NO referenced content for &quot;Great Calamity&quot; in the lead for the past decade, as I explained to you in my latest posting, except &quot;quoting people that say so, but do not prove it&quot; (apologies for quoting myself), and the source currently referencing &quot;Great Crime,&quot; if your read it outside your edit-warring mind --you're ascribing what you have started to others --, proves with extensive examples that the meaning &quot;crime&quot; for yeghern existed even before the genocide, and it is not &quot;recently-coined&quot; by any means.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Armen Ohanian|contribs]]) 13:46, 25 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
*'''Keep'''. Current name of the page, Armenian Genocide, is fully consistent with WP:Common name. There are also several alternative names. Given that they are sufficiently widely used, keeping them in intro is fine. Even if one of them was frequently used by &quot;denialists&quot;, that does not invalidate mentioning the term in lede. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 15:03, 24 May 2016 (UTC)
::In which case you will agree that the even more common Common Names, such as Aghet and Armenocide, should be there too, and that the alternative translations of ''Medz Yeghern'' should also be there, yes? [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 19:26, 24 May 2016 (UTC)
:::The discussion above shows that Medz Yeghern is rather widely used and even became a matter of controversy (the presentations by Obama, etc.). Is &quot;Armenocide&quot; that significant? I do not know. The number of Google hits is significant, but one should look at actual sources. If it is important, then yes, there is nothing wrong with including it too. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 12:24, 25 May 2016 (UTC)
::::[[User:My very best wishes]], this RfC was started because two editors - Diranakir &amp; Armen Ohanian - have point blank refused to include in the lede anything except Medz Yeghern and anything except &quot;Great Crime&quot; as its translation. This is even after sources and google scholar data has been presented that shows their position is invalid. (Part of that data has been presented in this RfC, so your Armenocide question is easy to answer: 166 hits on Google Scholar, more than Medz Yeghern.) The RfC proposes a compromise solution - remove all alternative names and translations from the lede and instead deal with them all in the article. No content is going to be deleted. Since you are opposing this compromise solution, what alternative solution do you suggest to move forward. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 16:28, 26 May 2016 (UTC) 
:::::Many pages have alternative names in intro. They must be there (in the first phrase) simply for convenience of a reader. Starting an RfC to exclude an alternative name that arguably should be included looks to me something very strange. Just keep the alternative name and move forward. This is very simple.  [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 14:29, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::'''Except that it has been anything than very simple!''' I don't think the RfC was well worded or explained, but its purpose was to resolve the long running issue of two editors refusing any compromise on their opinion that no alternative Armenian names can be inserted into the lede except Meds Yeghern, and no alterantive translation than &quot;Great Crime&quot; is allowed for Meds Yeghern. This is all despite plentiful sources indicating that this opinion is nothing but a pov opinion of those two editors. Showt of getting them banned, there is no way to move forward.  [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 15:28, 28 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::MVBW, you're missing the point that there are a great number of [[WP:OTHERNAMES]]. What is being suggested is that OTHERNAMES take on the same status as the COMMONNAME: in other words, editors are taking it upon themselves to promote other names... which is [[WP:OR]]. If the [[WP:TITLE]] of the article were &quot;Various names used for the Armenian Genocide&quot;, then I would have to agree with the inclusion in the lead. The TITLE is, however, &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot;. Other names belong in the body where/if appropriate, not in the lead. The rationale behind Wikipedia is that we don't run ahead of the ball and make the news (i.e., ''we'' would be facilitating the acceptance of other names as common names). --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 00:43, 28 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::I think having three alternative names in the first phrase right now is fine, just as on [[Holodomor|this page]] and a lot of other pages, and it is consistent with [[WP:OTHERNAMES]]. That would not work with a larger number of names (e.g. generic names of drugs). Once again, this something very minor that does not deserve RfC and this discussion. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 04:15, 28 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::There are MORE than three othernames names. &quot;Aghet&quot; and &quot;Armenocide&quot; have more Google Scholar hits than &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot;. To include Medz Yeghern in the lede and not the other two is a pov decision that is not supported by sources. To state in the lede that &quot;Great Crime&quot; is the only translation of Medz Yeghern is a pov decision that is not supported by sources. So, what exactly are you supporting? [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 15:36, 28 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::While we wait for the response to your question from My very best wishes, it has become quite clear what you are supporting, unfortunately: 1) your own pov agenda, which you continuously try to hide behind your &quot;sources&quot; that have been solidly shown once and again to be a smokescreen, 2) your not-so-veiled menaces to end your four-year-long campaign against Medz Yeghern by having other editors banned because they don't conform to your &quot;my way or highway.&quot; 
:::::::::::The passage &quot;also known (...) traditionally by Armenians, as Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Great Crime)&quot; speaks of the knowledge by Armenians, understandably, in the '''Armenian language''' (hence &quot;TRADITIONALLY&quot;), not in English or any other language, which '''are not the TRADITIONAL language''' of Armenians. Therefore, all Google Scholar/Google Books lucubrations are null and void, because nobody asked about English, German, French (or Chinese, for that matter) mentions of Medz Yeghern, Aghed, Armenocide, or the next name that one can think of in any particular language. They only serve to give a cover to utter ignorance of the Armenian language, because knowing words like Medz Yeghern or Aghed do not give anyone the right to claim knowledge of the language (unless such knowledge is demonstrated otherwise), the same as I don't claim that I know Ukrainian because I know Holodomor. Unfortunately, we have come to the point where people who do not know the Armenian language take upon themselves the right to speak about linguistic issues.   &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Armen Ohanian|contribs]]) 19:49, 28 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::::::::::::You really are Not There in every sense of the term. I doubt anyone else could be so willfully and consistently in error about Wikipedia's insistence on content being sourced. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:06, 29 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::: I don't need any lessons about Wikipedia's insistence on sourced content, since I know very well the value of sources. The insistence of people in exploiting that insistence by Wikipedia for their own purposes is what remains incomprehensible to me. I doubt anyone else could be so willfully and consistently in purposeful disdain of all sorts of evidence that contradicts his views and still repeats those same views.[[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 05:11, 29 May 2016 (UTC)
'''Exclude''' - term has lost its original meaning and is a violation of common name rule. --[[User:Oatitonimly|Oatitonimly]] ([[User talk:Oatitonimly|talk]]) 17:18, 25 May 2016 (UTC)
::[[WP:Common name]] is about title of the article, i.e. &quot;Armenian genocide&quot;, not about alternative, less commonly used names, which can also be included merely for convenience of a reader. Was that alternative name used in important recent publications on the subject? Yes, it was. Hence including it was fine.[[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 17:29, 25 May 2016 (UTC)
:::'''Question''' to Oatitonimly: Please specify what original meaning the term has lost.
:::'''Comment''' to My very best wishes: I appreciate your raising a very important point about the application of the common name 'rule'.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Diranakir|contribs]]) 18:22, 25 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt; [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 18:58, 25 May 2016 (UTC)
::::The fact of the matter is that at this point, there's been an open debate about the current meaning of Medz Yeghern for quite some time. Medz Yeghern has lost its meaning because it is not a term associated with the Armenian Genocide anymore. Rather, it is a term used to deny it. So the ambiguity of this meaning, whether it be in our understanding of [[WP:COMMONNAME]] or [[WP:OTHERNAMES]], should be handled the same way. Ambiguous names should be removed from the lead and further expressed in the article. Wikipedia is pretty clear on this. [[User:Oatitonimly|Oatitonimly]] ([[User talk:Oatitonimly|talk]]) 21:09, 25 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::You didn't answer my simple question. What is the original meaning that was lost? Either you meant something by it or you didn't. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 22:12, 25 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::The original meaning was something that was untranslatable, beyond a precise definition, a name to give something beyond comprehension or encompassment or description or explanation. Now it is mostly a [[euphemism]] that gutless politicians are using to avoid mentioning the word genocide. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 19:17, 26 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Tiptoe, why is it that when I ask another editor a direct question, it is you who jumps in? This is the second time it has happened. Are they not capable of answering for themselves? Apparently not.  It seems they prefer talking through their various hats. Thanks for a perfect description of the muddle in which you propose to bury Medz Yeghern. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 21:00, 26 May 2016 (UTC)
&lt;s&gt;'''Exclude''' from the lead per concerns expressed by ÉtienneDolet and other editors. It seems to be a name preferred by genocide deniers (such as Obama) and I see the situation could be compared to adding notions used by Holocaust deniers to the lead of the article on Holocaust. The problem also is that there are numerous other variants more often used than Medz Yeghern that should then consequently also be added to the lead, for which I see no reason. [[User:Dorpater|Dorpater]] ([[User talk:Dorpater|talk]]) 19:29, 28 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt; (vote by sock of blocked user). 17:41, 29 May 2016 (UTC)
:*This is strange. Last time when I checked Wiktionalry [https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Meds_Yeghern], it was telling: &quot;'''Meds Yeghern''' is used by Armenians refer to [[w:Armenian Genocide|the Armenian Genocide]] the way [[Shoah]] is used by [[Jew]]s to refer to the [[Holocaust]].&quot; Other sources were telling the same. So no, this is not terminology by deniers or Obama, but a terminology by Armenians. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 21:45, 28 May 2016 (UTC)
:::Wiktionary is not a citable source! More seriously, are you saying it is incorrect to say that Obama since becoming president has on numerous occasions said &quot;Meds Yeghern&quot; and has never once said &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; and that there are many sources that state he chooses the former to avoid saying the latter? [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:13, 29 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::So what? It is clear who cares about what Obama said: 1) Those people who ignore the Armenian language and dare to give lessons about it; 2) Those people who supposedly know the Armenian language, but are simply obsessed with the word &quot;genocide&quot; and reject the language that supposedly they know; 3) Those people who are pushing the others to impose their POV. 
:::::Instead, I will quote from a different source that cannot be suspected of denying anything, the President of Armenia, Serzh Sargsyan. John Paul II, Stephen Harper, and Pope Francis are not enough for you, then I have to add a fourth person who is not a &quot;gutless politician&quot; in this issue, the President of Armenia, Serzh Sargsyan. I have FOUR using Medz Yeghern and genocide, you have ONE not using both:
:::::&quot;Today, we commemorate the memory of the holy martyrs of the Armenian Genocide. More than a century has passed since the Meds Yeghern&quot; (April 24, 2016)(www.president.am/en/statements-and-messages/item/2016/04/24/President-Serzh-Sargsyan-speech-April-24/)
:::::&quot;The crimes of genocide – Medz Yeghern, Shoah, those committed in Cambodia, Rwanda, Darfur and elsewhere, shall be commemorated by both the successors of the victims and perpetrators. The path to reconciliation is not paved by denial, but rather by the consciousness of memory&quot; (April 22, 2015)(www.president.am/en/statements-and-messages/item/2015/04/22/President-Serzh-Sargsyan-Genocide-global-forum-April-22-speech/). 
:::::If Wiktionary is not a citable source, it is more than enough to quote the same from a source that has been a darling to source-twisters like you in a different time and name:
:::::&quot;Armenians sometimes still refer to the Armenian Genocide as ‘Medz Yeghern,’ just as the Jews use the Hebrew word Shoah for the Holocaust.” (Harut Sassounian, California Courier, January 5, 2005)
:::::If that is not enough, there one more for you and for everybody else out there who are ignorant of their own language to the point of simply considering &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; just one more about many:  
:::::&quot;When Metz Yeghern is used, Armenians understand genocide&quot; (Sukru Elekdag, former ambassador of Turkey to the United States, December 2008, http://armenians-1915.blogspot.com/2008/12/2680-tv-debate-transcript-32nd-day-on.html).[[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 05:11, 29 May 2016 (UTC)

The consensus is overwhelming in favor of the removal of Medz Yeghern. I've begun working on an alternative names section. I will remove Medz Yeghern bit in the lead and work to make the section in the coming days. Anyone is welcome to work on it with me. This is long overdue. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 17:45, 2 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::With all due respect, the &quot;overwhelming consensus&quot; --do you include, to mention only one case, the sock puppet who almost copied and pasted your opinion and who was blocked a few days ago?-- only exists (and I will repeat myself, since you seem not to have read much of what has been written here) in the imagination of: 1) Those people who ignore the Armenian language and dare to give lessons about it; 2) Those people who supposedly know the Armenian language, but are simply obsessed with the word &quot;genocide&quot; and reject the language that supposedly they know; 3) Those people who are pushing the others to impose their POV. 
:::::Will all due respect again, you unfortunately happened to be the person who broke the consensus reached almost three months ago and opened the floodgates for an endless discussion that has been going on and on since then. (It was an useful experience, however: every time someone's groundless arguments were crushed with facts, these facts were left aside and another groundless argument came forward, and this is how you built the &quot;overwhelming consensus.&quot; It allowed me to see first hand how a denialist would operate in a slightly different context.) It was clearly explained that every COMPARABLE article in Wikipedia has the proper name of the genocide in its first paragraph, and I could not hear a single rational objection, except what amounted to denialism: when you deny your own name on the name of denial, you allow others to deny it too, as it happened. 
:::::&quot;Last April 24, on the 100th anniversary of what Armenians call the Great Crime, the Bundestag postponed voting on a similar resolution to classify the mass killings as genocide. Yet German President Joachim Gauck used the term, drawing criticism from Turkey.&quot; This was written by Deutsche Welle on May 31, 2016 (http://www.dw.com/en/turkeys-erdogan-warns-germany-ahead-of-armenian-genocide-vote/a-19296898). They didn't call it Great Catastrophe/Calamity/Disaster/Tragedy or Aghed. &quot;(...) WHAT ARMENIANS CALL THE GREAT CRIME.&quot; This is the name of the genocide (other than &quot;Armenian Genocide,&quot; which is not the Armenian name), and this is what should remain in the first paragraph of Wikipedia, as the Holocaust, the Holodomor, and the Assyrian genocide do. Afterwards, one could write a full article about the names of the Armenian genocide in good conscience. But now, please do not hide behind &quot;overwhelming consensus,&quot; because that looks like the emperor's new clothes. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 20:49, 2 June 2016 (UTC)

:::::::Six users ([https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=722078298&amp;oldid=722061350][https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=721636379&amp;oldid=721633128][https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=717614193&amp;oldid=717610504][https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=717435108&amp;oldid=717429442][https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=717460445&amp;oldid=717455287] as opposed to three appears to be quite overwhelming. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 03:26, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::::The merits of the word &quot;overwhelming,&quot; as well as of your mathematical source to come to that conclusion are very disputable, but I'll leave them to your conscience, the same as the entire merit of this discussion, for which we are indebted to your previous break of overwhelming consensus (two users opposed to one are as overwhelming as six to three) and the lack of grounded argumentation that followed. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 13:16, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::I stand corrected for the record. Two users opposed to one are as overwhelming as five to three. Banned sock puppets do not count. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 16:39, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::I never &quot;broke a consensus&quot; concerning this Medz Yeghern stuff. I don't get why you keep bringing that up with every comment of yours. My agreement was a temporary solution (the stuff about Aghed) to an otherwise very large problem. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 16:11, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::Here's your agreement as a so-called &quot;temporary solution&quot; to a problem that it has never looked (and it does not) as &quot;otherwise very large.&quot; Indeed, I was addressing you in the comment):

:::::::::::::&quot;d) Finally, as I had promised, I would like to go back to your proposal of alleviating the burden in the lead and build up on it. I think it may be fairly reasonable to establish a comparison with the opening sentence of the entry &quot;Holocaust&quot; and divide the first sentence into two:
:::::::::::::&quot;The Armenian Genocide (Armenian: Հայոց ցեղասպանություն Hayots tseghaspanutyun), also known as the Medz Yeghern (Armenian: Մեծ Եղեռն, &quot;Great Crime&quot;), was the systematic extermination by the Ottoman government of its Armenian population. It was carried inside and around their historic homeland, which lies within the present-day Republic of Turkey.&quot;
:::::::::::::Compare:
:::::::::::::&quot;The Holocaust (from the Greek ὁλόκαυστος holókaustos: hólos, &quot;whole&quot; and kaustós, &quot;burnt&quot;), also known as the Shoah (Hebrew: השואה, HaShoah, &quot;the catastrophe&quot;), was a genocide in which Adolf Hitler's Nazi Germany and its collaborators killed about six million Jews.&quot;
:::::::::::::Along the lines of what you had proposed, footnote 3 would become:
:::::::::::::Spelt Հայոց ցեղասպանութիւն in classical Armenian orthography. In English, the Armenian Genocide is also known as the Armenian Holocaust, and, previously, as the Armenian Massacres.
:::::::::::::(The last sentence of footnote 3 can even be taken out, if someone thinks that its too &quot;heavy.&quot;).Armen Ohanian (talk) 19:20, 11 April 2016 (UTC) 
:::::::::::::Armen's proposal looks good to me. Étienne Dolet (talk) 19:45, 11 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::I concur. An admirable resolution by Armen. Diranakir (talk) 20:08, 11 April 2016 (UTC)&quot;

:::::::::::Your proposal was to alleviate the burden in the lead. I build up on it and I proposed how to alleviate the lead, and I gave a comparative example to another lead. There was no &quot;temporary solution&quot; there. This was a consensus for a final solution. This is what you broke and you don't remember. 
:::::::::::The &quot;stuff about Aghed&quot; was an artificial issue created by someone who has never spoken the word &quot;aghed&quot; or any other Armenian word in his entire life, and who brought the word to muddle the field (including a fair amount of misinterpretation, indeed), as he has tried relentlessly to do for the past four years. This has shown beyond the need of more proof. Unfortunately, you seem to have bought that red herring.[[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 20:42, 3 June 2016 (UTC) 

::::::::::::Yup. It was a temporary solution for Aghed, but not the final solution for Medz Yeghern. I don't know why I need to go back and forth with you on this. It really doesn't matter, even if I did &quot;break&quot; some sort of consensus. After all, a [[WP:CONSENSUSCANCHANGE|consensus can always change]]. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 20:51, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Nobody forces you to go back and forth. Consensus may always change. POV doesn't. This is, unfortunately, the bottom line of this issue: POV based on a subjective perception of denial for Medz Yeghern and the red herring of Aghed bought from someone who didn't know of its existence until he found it in his crusade to impose his own POV. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 22:31, 4 June 2016 (UTC)

:::::::Armen Ohanian, your above is just a continuation of your ignoring of Wikipedia rules regarding sources. What you say you want, what you say you know to be true, what you think is correct, all of that has no place in deciding what Wikipedia content should be. Sources decide content. Also, long-established sources are more important that recent ones when deciding on spellings or translations.  [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 23:21, 2 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::::If you believed in what you said, you would have ended this discussion long ago.  If you think that I say what I want, what I know to be true, what I think it is correct, then look at yourself and your opinions and stop ascribing your own attitude to others. Long-established sources have been shown long ago, but you preferred to ignore them. I have backed what I say and what I think with sources of which you have not the slightest idea, as it has been proved once and again. Your remaining arguments are the repetition of hot air to which readers and editors have been used for the past four years. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 00:18, 3 June 2016 (UTC) 
:::::::::Armen, you seem to be missing the point of this whole discussion. Something true years ago isn't necessarily true in the present day. --[[User:Oatitonimly|Oatitonimly]] ([[User talk:Oatitonimly|talk]]) 21:30, 3 June 2016 (UTC).
:::::::::::That is the point of this discussion? Anything which was true in the past is no longer true? Unless there are sounding facts that prove the contrary -- not speculations based on POV -- a truth remains as such. In this case, the truth of the proper name &quot;Medz Yeghern,&quot; its meaning, and its importance remains there. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 22:31, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::I have cited numerous articles, I have cited the Google search results, I have cited the Google Scholar results. All hot air to Armen Ohanian? However, this &quot;hot air&quot; forms the basis of deciding what Wikipedia article content should consist of.[[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:09, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::Any denialist may cite numerous articles, Google search results, and Google Scholar results, and claim that those &quot;form the basis of deciding what Wikipedia article content should consist of.&quot; In such a case, and in this case, the [[reliability]] of those citations is what is at stake. This is what has been called into question and debunked once and again, and not just with words. But, of course, whoever has one and only one goal in his mind will never renounce to it. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 22:31, 4 June 2016 (UTC)

::::I look forward to seeing your work, EtienneDolet,but could you place the proposed new section here first, rather than going straight into the article with it. So it can be discussed. What do you think about having the origin of the word genocide section combined into this news terminology section, detail when and why it was coined, then detail and explain the various names for the AG that were used before the coining of the term genocide, names that contemporary sources called it or '''described it''' (things like &quot;the murder of a nation&quot; (in the 1915 Toynbee booklet) is more a description than an actual term), and then onto the internalized names Armenians used, like Aghet and Medz Yeghern. And maybe also the terminology found in denialist sources, and the ways that avoid mentioning the word &quot;genocide&quot;. This proposed section can be inserted regardless of any lede content decision, regardless of the AfD (which did have a clear majority to delete but the low numbers participating probably preclude calling it overwhelming). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 23:09, 2 June 2016 (UTC)

:::::{{ping|Tiptoethrutheminefield}} here's my [[User:EtienneDolet/Alternative_names_section|draft]]. Nothing too elaborate so far. You're welcome to work on it with me, as is everybody else here. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 03:26, 3 June 2016 (UTC)

:::::{{ping|Tiptoethrutheminefield}} so what do you think of the draft? Are you willing to work on it? I should I just place what I got so far? [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 23:50, 7 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::Sorry, I have not worked on it yet. I think it could be far more comprehensive. Is reproducing the terms found in denialist sources permissible, or would that be OR unless a third source refers to those phrases (things like &quot;a tragedy&quot;, or &quot;Armenian allegations&quot; or &quot;the events of 1915&quot;, etc.) as phrases found in denialist literature. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:33, 8 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::To Etienne Dolet: 5 to 3 is no overwhelming consensus, especially given an RfC tarnished by sock puppetry.  Your proposal to throw Medz Yeghern out of the lede is based on what you think is appropriate for the reader to see or not see at the top of the page, that is what it comes down to. The name has unique status in Armenian tradition, as Armen Ohanian has made perfectly clear. You choose to ignore that in the interests of your beef with the POTUS. Not very neutral. &quot;Too many words, too confusing for the reader, not a common name&quot;, nonsense. All the other articles on genocides can have their alternative names in the lede but this one? Not very encyclopedic. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 00:32, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Note that one of the three, My very best wishes, said that all alternative names should be inserted into the lede. This is something that the other two of the three refuse to accept (and their refusal was the reason for having this RfC). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:14, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::: My very best wishes said that in reference to the THREE alternative names ALREADY on the lede for the past ten years (but you know this even before I did), not for what you are implying. (This proves my point that you cling to anything that suits your goals.) He said, in reference to Medz Yeghern (May 27): &quot;Many pages have alternative names in intro. They must be there (in the first phrase) simply for convenience of a reader. Starting an RfC to exclude an alternative name that arguably should be included looks to me something very strange. Just keep the alternative name and move forward. This is very simple.&quot; And later (May 28): &quot;I think having three alternative names in the first phrase right now is fine, just as on [[Holodomor|this page]] and a lot of other pages, and it is consistent with [[WP:OTHERNAMES]]. That would not work with a larger number of names (e.g. generic names of drugs). Once again, this something very minor that does not deserve RfC and this discussion.&quot; [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 22:31, 4 June 2016 (UTC)

'''Exclude''' per [[WP:OTHERNAMES]]. ''Medz Yeghern'' has become an euphemistic term mostly used by Armenian Genocide deniers. Denialists and US presidents have employed the term ''Medz Yeghern'' to the point that the term has been perverted of its meaning. There's no denying that ''Medz Yeghern'' was or still is a word for the Armenian Genocide, but this background info needs to be clarified elsewhere in the article in a more appropriate place. [[WP:OTHERNAMES]] for example encourages us to have an alternative names section in the article to handle these kind of problems. [[User:92slim|92slim]] ([[User talk:92slim|talk]]) 17:47, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

::To 92slim: You say 'Exclude per WP:OTHERNAMES' then immediately follow with the comment, 'Medz Yeghern has become an euphemistic term mostly used by Armenian Genocide deniers' , as if that is the reason for applying the 'othernames' principle, when it isn't. Then you say, 'Medz Yeghern '''was or is''' still a word for the Armenian Genocide'. Why the confusion? Why don't you just say '''is'''? With credit to 'My very best wishes', I have to point out that the very fact that we are having this discussion shows that the name has real prominence, far above any of the other alternative names. By the common name/other name principle as interpreted by you, 'Hayots tseghaspanutyun' should also be excluded from the lede. It is far less commonly known than Medz Yeghern. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:57, 8 June 2016 (UTC)
{{od|2}} &lt;s&gt;Has anyone actually submitted this RfC for closure at the [[WP:ANRFC]]? It really needs a neutral admin/experienced user to close it. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 01:42, 9 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt; &lt;small&gt;Striking as it is listed. Just a huge backlog on the board. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 01:45, 9 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

'''OR, Synthesis and Undue Weight issues relating to edits made to the consensus solution''' - This edit [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725247796&amp;oldid=725242096] adds the claim that Obama had acknowledged the AG by using the term Medz Yeghern. This was a clear case of undue weight, and I have removed it. Obama, before becoming president, had used the words &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; - so his acknowledgement predated his use of Medz Yeghern. As soon as he became president he stopped doing that, saying only &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; instead. Six years have passed since the cited source's opinion - an opinion that was about the FIRST instance of Obama having used the term. In those six years Obama has continued each year to decline to say the words &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot; and has continued to only say &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot;. It is his '''continued''' use of Medz Yeghern and '''continued''' refusal to say Armenian Genocide that the sources say amounts to denial (or gives encouragement to and succor for denialists). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:14, 14 June 2016 (UTC)
::Diranakir, without answering any of the points made above, has again inserted this content [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725795362&amp;oldid=725794636]. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:09, 18 June 2016 (UTC)
:::And has edit warred it in yet again [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=725952787], despite being directed to discuss it here.  [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 00:25, 19 June 2016 (UTC)
:This edit [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725299832&amp;oldid=725247796] as well as having an extremely bad faith edit summary that is probably sanctionable, adds OR, Synthesis, and Undue Weight. It is a return by Armen Ohanian to exactly the same edit warring that obliged this RfC. Yet again this editor removes Aghet as an alternative term, despite the Google Scholar results presented during this RfC that indicate it is the most common term used, more common than Medz Yeghern. In order to try to placate this editor I deliberately did not put &quot;Aghet&quot; before &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot;, even though the Google results would suggest it should be - but nothing it seems will stop Armen Ohanian's pov warring. And the alternative translation &quot;Great Calamity&quot; for Medz Yeghern is yet again deleted, despite the Google Scholar results indicating it is quite common, about half as common as the &quot;Great Crime&quot; translation. In this edit we also have a curious use of commas inside quotation marks: &quot;xxx&quot;, &quot;yyy&quot;, (which appears the correct usage to me) becomes &quot;xxx,&quot; &quot;yyy,&quot;, etc. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:26, 14 June 2016 (UTC)
::Ultimately, while the ANRFC may be frustratingly backlogged, there has been no ruling to include Medz Yeghern or any other naming convention... meaning that no editors should be reintroducing the content in any shape or form, much less elaborating on it. Such tactics can only be understood as being [[WP:BATTLEGROUND]], reflecting badly on the editor tampering with what currently stands as the status quo. Please wait until a decision is made. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 22:58, 14 June 2016 (UTC)
:::To be completely correct, the RfC was about lede content and whether particular content should be in the lede or should not. Since these edits concern body content and are thus independent of the lede content I think they do not need to wait for a final RfC decision. The troubling thing is that the same pov exclusion of Aghet and promotion of Medz Yeghern (with &quot;Great Crime&quot; as its only permissible translation) that was edit warred into the lede - to the extent that the only way to progress was the removal of all terms - seems to be being transferred into the article body content. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 00:39, 15 June 2016 (UTC)
::::There's nothing to &quot;close&quot; here. The RfC template expired a long time ago. We can't close a template that doesn't exist. This tends to happen a lot during RfCs. And as for the RfC itself, it's nothing but a method to help get the community further involved, hence why it's called a &quot;request for comment&quot; and it should be treated as such. The discussion has reached a point in which we were able to fix up the lede without any further problems or altercations, so I think we would be [[WP:DROPTHESTICK|beating the dead horse]]. We aren't supposed to view RfC's as something like congress voting over a bill and waiting for the speaker of the house to confirm the result. That's not how RfCs work. The importance given to the discussion and the result of it is what counts. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 00:59, 15 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::Apologies for not checking the edit more thoroughly. I admit that I only took a cursory look. Agreed that no one is interested in closing, just as another RfC trying to overturn a recently adopted guideline RfC is going to be ignored. The give away with whether an RfC is going to have a third party close it is the fact that it ''was'' submitted ''before'' the 30 days were up. If admins and other experienced users are disinclined to close, it becomes an in-house issue. I believe that there was also a DRN submitted and either declined immediately, or within a short period of time (feel free to correct me if I'm wrong). Looking at the edit again, [[WP:DTS]] summarises the situation succinctly. Omission from the lead does not preclude that POV pushing is acceptable for the body. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 04:11, 15 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::Yes there was a Dispute Resolution request some months before the RfC - I submitted it, but the other invited parties declined to accept. At issue was what I saw as the pov exclusion of alternative terms from the lede. Identical issues now seem to be arising in the article body now that there is a section about terminology. However, lede content is meant to summarize body content, so in a way the earlier discussions were doing it the wrong way around because the lede content dealing with terminology summarized nothing that was in the body. This is why having a terminology section is required to move forward, regardless of the content that ends up being in it. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 18:45, 15 June 2016 (UTC)

'''Content allegation that &quot;clamity&quot; is a denialist term.''' It was inserted, I fact tagged it, a source was provided, it was invalid, I have deleted both the tagged claim and the invalid source. [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725934111&amp;oldid=725918893]. The source is a denialist text, but the cited page is actually part of a huge verbatim quotation of many passages from Hovhannes Katchaznouni's &quot;The Armenian Revolutionary Federation Has Nothing To Do Any More&quot;, in which the word &quot;calamity&quot; is used once by Katchaznouni. Katchaznouni is not denying the Armenian Genocide (the word genocide was not coined when he wrote his pamphlet), nor is the source claiming that he was, the source does not even mention anything about Katchaznouni's usage of the word &quot;calamity&quot; - there is nothing in this to even remotely support a claim that &quot;clamity&quot; is a denialist term. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:51, 18 June 2016 (UTC)

{{archive bottom}}

== Numbers ==
I strongly disagree with the way the death toll is portrayed now. The widely agreed upon number of 1.5 million Armenians having been killed should be given in the first sentence. Compare [[The Holocaust]], where in the first sentence the number of 6 million is also immediately given. Nearly every reliable source immediately describes it as the systematic killing of 1.5 million Armenians,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.com/topics/armenian-genocide history.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/ref/timestopics/topics_armeniangenocide.html NY Times]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armenian-genocide.org/genocidefaq.html#How_many Armenian-genocide.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-36433114 BBC News]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/turkey/11373115/Amal-Clooneys-latest-case-Why-Turkey-wont-talk-about-the-Armenian-genocide.html Telegraph]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/why-isnt-the-killing-of-15-million-armenians-officially-called-a-genocide-a6999861.html Independent]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/04/23/armenian-genocide-controversy_n_7121008.html Huffington Post]&lt;/ref&gt; so having the second sentence say &quot;The number of victims is estimated at between 800,000 and 1.5 million.&quot; is straight up disrespectful. Giving equal value to a much rarer estimate that is ''almost half'' of what is generally agreed upon gives credit to deniers and is an insult to the hundreds of thousands that died in it. [[User:Prinsgezinde|Bataaf van Oranje (Prinsgezinde)]] ([[User talk:Prinsgezinde|talk]]) 13:02, 2 June 2016 (UTC)
{{reflist}}
*I agree with you, number of 1.5 million should be highlighted, as it is the most published number. Your sourcing is sufficient.[[User:Jirka.h23|Jirka.h23]] ([[User talk:Jirka.h23|talk]]) 05:08, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
::I do not think it should be in the first sentence. Genocide is not directly connected to the number of victims, it is to do with aims and effects. But, as long as it is made clear in the wording that this is an &quot;around about&quot; figure given in the majority of sources, just having 1.5 million seems acceptable. An maybe a footnote to give other legitimate higher and lower estimates would be useful because the figure for Armenian deaths, unlike the politicized and almost religious dogma that surrounds the Holocaust's &quot;6 million&quot;, is subject to legitimate variations in estimates in legitimate sources that have nothing to do with any attempts to deny the genocide. 13:26, 3 June 2016 (UTC)[[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]])
:::[[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]], to clarify: I'm not trying to say lower estimates are automatically attempts at denial, and you are right in saying that the numbers aren't pivotal to a genocide. I'm saying that giving equal weight (in this case: [[WP:FALSEBALANCE]]) to lower ''and'' rarer estimates has a detrimental effect on an article's accuracy. We may never know the exact numbers, and we may never reach a consensus based on exactly how many people were killed as a result of genocide, but the best thing we can do is [[WP:Verifiability|follow the RS]]. [[User:Prinsgezinde|Bataaf van Oranje (Prinsgezinde)]] ([[User talk:Prinsgezinde|talk]]) 16:12, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::::We use the general consensus number 1.5 million in the lede using words like, up to 1.5 million, as many as 1.5 million, approximately 1.5 million, or just &quot;1.5 million&quot;, whatever editors choose.  Elsewhere in the article we can note scholarly variations while again reiterating the the scholarly consensus number is 1.5 million.  This has been in the news lately because of Turkish anger at Germany for acknowledging the genocide, but anyone denying the Armenian Genocide holds a [[WP:FRINGE]] view and should be treated as such. [[User:Lipsquid|Lipsquid]] ([[User talk:Lipsquid|talk]]) 16:52, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::Concerning the unfortunate phrase used above by Tiptoethrutheminefield, ''the politicized and almost religious dogma that surrounds the Holocaust's &quot;6 million&quot;'', it is in order to directly quote what the WP Holocaust article says so that there are no grounds left for misunderstanding or obfuscation: The Holocaust (from the Greek ὁλόκαυστος holókaustos: hólos, &quot;whole&quot; and kaustós, &quot;burnt&quot;), also known as the Shoah (Hebrew: השואה, HaShoah, &quot;the catastrophe&quot;), was a genocide in which Adolf Hitler's Nazi Germany and its collaborators killed '''about six million Jews'''. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 17:23, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::A timely reminder (to me) about why I oppose Diranakir's editing aims here. Diranakir's promised land of &quot;no grounds left for misunderstanding or obfuscation&quot; is a nightmarish society where truth (and the quest for it) is banished and is replaced by whatever dogma the controlling elite has decided should be final, unalterable, and alone permissible. 19:15, 4 June 2016 (UTC)[[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]])
::::::::&quot;... A nightmarish society where truth (and the quest of it) is banished and is replaced by whatever dogma the controlling elite has decided should be final, unalterable, and alone permissible.&quot; Whether its author wanted it or not, this is another unfortunate phrase that sounds dangerously close to the &quot;Armenian version of this history&quot; expounded by Bernard Lewis in November 1993 and to what Turkish neo-denialists use to push forward their distorted version as an alternative narrative: the &quot;quest of truth.&quot; It is also a timely reminder (to me, at least) about the motive behind its author's relentless and years-long quest to downgrade --ultimately, to exclude-- the name Medz Yeghern from that same first paragraph at any cost, even &quot;giving equal weight... to lower ''and'' rarer estimates&quot; (Prinszgezinde dixit): because it doesn't suit his relativist POV about &quot;the controlling elite&quot; under the guise of the &quot;quest of truth.&quot; [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 23:35, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
It is complete nonsense to quote a figure of 1.5 million having in mind [https://tr.wikipedia.org/wiki/1914_Osmanl%C4%B1_%C4%B0mparatorlu%C4%9Fu_n%C3%BCfus_say%C4%B1m%C4%B1= the Armenian population in Ottoman lands before WW1]]. This topic has become simply mater of politics than historical facts. [[User:Hittit|Hittit]] ([[User talk:Hittit|talk]]) 19:46, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:It certainly is frightening to see the Turkish Wikipedia promoting that myth, as those numbers have been debunked endlessly (see [[Armenian Genocide denial]]), but as described in [[WP:CIRC]] Wikipedia is not a reliable source and we're getting off topic here. I'd hate to straight up accuse you, but alleging that there were far less than 1.5 million Armenians even in the Ottoman regions at the time is a [[WP:FRINGE|fringe view]] often used by deniers that we will never voice for the reason that the scholarly consensus is entirely against it. It's unhelpful to give an argument of &quot;don't include it because it's nonsense&quot; when the factual accuracy of it being possible isn't even up for debate here. We're discussing how and where to present it. [[User:Prinsgezinde|Bataaf van Oranje (Prinsgezinde)]] ([[User talk:Prinsgezinde|talk]]) 20:28, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::It is even more nonsensical to put any faith in Turkish sources regarding this subject. [[User:Lipsquid|Lipsquid]] ([[User talk:Lipsquid|talk]]) 20:34, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
Ottoman archives are the only reliable statistics in this matter, as the population data is available. I can understand if the facts are not liked, the article POV shows it. [[User:Hittit|Hittit]] ([[User talk:Hittit|talk]]) 20:50, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:They are not reliable. See [[Armenian_Genocide_denial#Efforts_at_rebuttal|here]]. Scholars have long been denied access to these archives. And even when they could (under conditions) access it, as stated by [[Taner Akçam]], a significant portion of the documents are missing. [[User:Prinsgezinde|Bataaf van Oranje (Prinsgezinde)]] ([[User talk:Prinsgezinde|talk]]) 21:24, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::For those who think that &quot;Ottoman archives are the only reliable statistics,&quot; Talaat's &quot;Black Book&quot; may give them a surprise. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 23:35, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::::Tiptoethrutheminefield speaking of me and Armen Ohanian: ''Showt of getting them banned, there is no way to move forward''. Tiptoethrutheminefield (talk) 15:28, 28 May 2016. (UTC). So just who is dreaming of a dogmatic, nightmarish society purged of all opposition and ruled by a conspiratorial elite? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 02:22, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::Take it to user pages, not a discussion about Armenian Genocide.  People can have all the arguments they want, keeping it out of the public eye is best for everyone.  I am not picking you out nor negating your right to defend yourself, this is probably just not the right place.  [[User:Lipsquid|Lipsquid]] ([[User talk:Lipsquid|talk]]) 02:54, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::I Agree that the number 1.5 million should be used in the lead, then other numbers from other secondary sources should be included later in the article. [[User:Markewilliams|Markewilliams]] ([[User talk:Markewilliams|talk]]) 14:15, 11 June 2016 (UTC)

== Moving discussions from OWNTALK here ==

These threads were started on my [[WP:OWNTALK]], but I'm moving them here as they are relevant to this article's talk page as a matter of transparency.

;On synth
Regarding the Armenian Genocide article, in your edit summary at 22:08, 17 June 2016 you say &quot;‎There's also a difference between WP:SYNTH &amp; WP:NOTSYNTH&quot;. As far as I can see, the difference is merely that between two different pages or sections of guidelines. I don't get the point. Perhaps you were using shorthand. Please clarify. Thanks. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 12:18, 18 June 2016 (UTC)
:[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725791763&amp;oldid=725786401] - there are numerous sources around concerning the issue of Obama's continuing use of Medz Yeghern. I do not know if that particular citation says it equates to genocide denial, but there are sources that do make that equation. I am not going to be able to look for them as I will be away from Wikipedia for the next 5 weeks and this will probably be my last post here for a while. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:41, 18 June 2016 (UTC)

;False balance

Concerning your edit on the Armenian Genocide article at 00:14, 18 June 2016‎: your suggestion that a statement by a genuine legal body in Armenia concerning President Obama's use of the term Meds Yeghern may be a 'minority view' or falls into the same category as 'flat Earth' theories and other forms of pseudoscience seems a considerable stretch of the WP:GEVAL guidance. If you have 'no idea' as to the quality as an RS in context, how relevant can that suggestion be? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 18:41, 18 June 2016 (UTC)
:It is more than a minority view, it is an off-topic view and it is an outdated view. To have this content next to content concerning the effect of Obama's usage of Medz Yeghgern is editorializing for effect. The article in that source was written as a response to President Obama's '''first''' use of the term &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; in a public statement. Many years have passed since the cited source's opinion, and over those years Obama has used &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; on multiple occasions but has never used the phrase &quot;Armenian genocide&quot; (despite having said it before becoming president). It is the '''repeated''' non-uttering of &quot;Armenian genocide&quot; and the use of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; instead that MULTIPLE sources say is a way of Obama avoiding mentioning the word &quot;genocide&quot;. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:30, 18 June 2016 (UTC)
::{{ping|Diranakir|Tiptoethrutheminefield}} When discussing content matters on highly controversial articles, I prefer not to use my OWNTALK page as a matter of transparency. My apologies for not following up my revert and changes on the article's talk page, but I'm pushing myself for time on Wikipedia with IRL obligations at the moment. To qualify, Diranakir, the GEVAL policy means exactly what the header describes it as being, that is {{tq|&quot;Giving 'equal validity' can create a false balance'}}. The use of extreme examples is merely an indicator of what it encompasses. The use of tit for tat content in order to negate the prominent academic position is precisely that, and is antithetical to NPOV. Requesting multiple references for something that is NOTSYNTH leads to [[WP:CITEOVERKILL]]. There are multiple RS to attest to it as being a denialist position, but forcing other editor's hands into providing these is a BATTLEGROUND position. Finally, my ES saying that 'I don't know' was a polite way of saying that I think that the source is a dud. I should have called it an op-ed piece in from a source that I've never heard of (and have never seen being used as a source anywhere else). If the opinion were attributed to an expert, it may have some merit... but it isn't, so it may as well be from a blog or forum for its reliability. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy#top|talk]]) 23:36, 18 June 2016 (UTC)
::::Calling the source a 'dud' is not academic. It appears that your never having heard of it is what makes it a 'dud'. That does not make the case. Quoting the header also does not make the case. The source is entirely valid. There is nothing extreme about it. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 00:13, 19 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::It's a dud... and I've explained to you in technical terms why it's a dud. It's an op-ed piece from an anonymous writer (probably a staff piece) in a source that only meets with [[WP:BIASED]]. Please stop edit warring this content back. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy#top|talk]]) 00:18, 19 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::It's no more a dud or an op-ed or outdated than the unsigned 1997 statement from the IAGS given in footnote 11 in the lede. Quit edit warring against valid content and defending a lopsided presentation of the matter. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 02:02, 19 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::I fail to see the comparison. IAGS is a scholarly community, and this is their stated, ongoing position (unless you have RS contradicting that it is still their position). How does this [http://news.am/eng/news/15852.html op-ed piece] in an unknown quantity source eliciting its own opinion of what Obama 'meant' the second time he used &quot;Meds Yeghern&quot; rather than calling it the Armenian Genocide compare? Even the title - &quot;Obama lawyer recognized Armenian Genocide: RA Council of Bar Association&quot; - is misleading. It presents as if Obama's lawyer recognised the Armenian Genocide when, in fact, it's drawing on the Obama's being a lawyer... and that he is the lawyer being alluded to. It's badly written and is dependent on the assumption that it can read his mind. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 05:54, 19 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::::I have removed the claim and the source. My point that it is an outdated source, inappropriate for content that relates to the sustained usage of Medz Yeghern by Obama '''long after the source was published''', has not been countered. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:55, 29 July 2016 (UTC)

== Over-elaboration in terminology section ==

Please stop developing the [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=726565650&amp;oldid=726396275 terminology section] without WP:CON. It's [[WP:UNDUE]], protracted [[WP:ITSIMPORTANT]] content. There's more rambling about how many names there were, how often they were used, and when they were used than there is on the use of &quot;genocide&quot;: and Lemkin's use of &quot;genocide&quot; takes precedence for the benefit of the reader. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 00:56, 23 June 2016 (UTC)
::Please stop it with the WP jargon over-kill ([[WP:WL]]) which obscures the fact that the spanking new section (Origins of the word genocide/Terminology) was a sprawling mess to begin with, which you never seemed to notice until some valid points were made to repair the damage done to the article when Medz Yeghern was thrown out of the lede in an aborted RfC, as if it could simply be excised from its proper place without consequence. Editors whom you favor and with whom you 'voted' in the RfC are now to be given an unopposed field day to romp as they wish with a serious matter, which is the actual meaning of the name Medz Yeghern. This is not allowable. By your own admission, the RfC was not duly closed (of course, because of backlog). WP says that an RfC is not simply a 'vote' and that an uninvolved 3rd party is to make an assessment on the merits of the arguments to complement the 'votes'. Nothing like this was remotely done and your repeated efforts to fill that gap do not serve well, no matter how many WP:THIS&amp;THATs you invoke. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:44, 23 June 2016 (UTC)
:::{{re|Diranakir}} I think you ought to read [[WP:PETTIFOG]] carefully, particularly the [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikilawyering#Misuse_of_the_term section on misuse of the terms]. Between yourself and {{u|Armen Ohanian}}, the terminology section has been developed [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=726570265&amp;oldid=726565650 here], [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=726570265 here] (reduces the verbiage?), even further [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=726740301 here] and [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=726940798 here] to create a lengthy paragraph of a multitude of names used before the term 'genocide' was created and employed in any languages. It appears that neither of you see that this does not improve the quality of the article, but is antithetical to the reader's understanding of the 'Armenian genocide': it is [[WP:OFFTOPIC]] and so elaborate as to trivialise the subject of the article which is the ''genocide'' of ''Armenians''. The subject is 'genocide', not: {{talkquote|&quot;The Armenian Genocide happened before the coining of the term 'genocide'. English-language words and phrases used by contemporary accounts to characterise the event include 'massacres', 'atrocities', 'annihilation', 'holocaust', 'the murder of a nation', 'race extermination' and 'a crime against humanity'. 'Yeghern (Crime/Catastrophe), or variants like Medz Yeghern (Great Crime) and Abrilian Yeghern (the April Crime)' were the terms most commonly used. Other terms used by the survivors included Medz Voghperkutyun ('Great Tragedy'), Medz Vogchagez ('Great Holocaust'), Medz Nahadagutyun ('Great Martyrdom'), Aghed ('Catastrophe'), Medz Nakhjir and Medz Sbant (both meaning 'Great Massacre'), Medz Potorig ('Great Storm') and Sev Vojir ('Black Crime'). The common name 'aghed,' usually translated as 'catastrophe,' was, according to Beledian, the term most often used to name the catastrophe of 1915 in Armenian literature. After the coining of genocide, the portmanteau word Armenocide was also used for the Armenian Genocide.&quot;}} I find it disturbing that neither of you seem to understand why other editors think that it's overkill, and that it detracts from the flow of imparting relevant information. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 21:48, 25 June 2016 (UTC)
::::: There was only one Armenian-language name that was enough for any reader for ten years, including many journalists who have used Wikipedia as a source for their information, and its meaning was established with a reliable source until this entirely unnecessary discussion was provoked (I have pointed out its unnecessary nature with plenty of facts) and the present situation of &quot;overkill&quot; was generated. Please go and check who wrote down entire paragraphs about &quot;English-language words and phrases&quot; and &quot;multitude of names&quot; before getting disturbed about overkill and addressing your discomfort to the wrong addresses.[[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 22:30, 25 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::Finger pointing really isn't a constructive method of trying to improve the article content. The escalation of picking over details in the content was far more complicated than a single parsing of COMMONNAME, however I thoroughly commend the elimination of all but the primary terms used in Armenian. I hope that any [[WP:GRUDGE|grudges]] can be put aside, and AGF be adopted again in order to make a positive impact on the quality of the article. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 03:55, 26 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::My request to you is that you communicate your points with common sense, in ordinary English, and in accord with conventional rules of reasoning, rather than habitually putting the focus on sources outside the specific area of discussion (WP:THIS/THAT) which often cut both ways and can be interpreted in a multiplicity of ways. For instance, can you give me an ordinary English translation of the following sentence? &quot;The escalation of picking over details in the content was far more complicated than a single parsing of COMMONNAME.&quot; As far as the verbiage in the section, most of that was installed the day Medz Yeghern was removed from the lede, and I had nothing to do with it. See [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=724839262] I am with you in welcoming the elimination of all but the primary terms used in Armenian. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 05:00, 26 June 2016 (UTC)

== Armenian Massacres and Armenian Holocaust in the lead ==

Should they stay or should they go? [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 17:17, 23 June 2016 (UTC)

:Both [https://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Armenian+holocaust&amp;btnG=&amp;as_sdt=1%2C5&amp;as_sdtp= seem] [https://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=Armenian+massacres&amp;btnG=&amp;as_sdt=1%2C5&amp;as_sdtp= common] (use quotation marks '''&quot; &quot;''' to make sure the two words in the term aren't separated – linking doesn't seem to allow this). I see no reason why they should go. [[User:Prinsgezinde|Bataaf van Oranje (Prinsgezinde)]] ([[User talk:Prinsgezinde|talk]]) 14:37, 26 June 2016 (UTC)

== Sentence adjustment needed ==

The very first sentence of the first alinea of the body states: &quot;Armenia had come largely under Ottoman rule during the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries.&quot;
This is impossible, and unverifiable, given that the Ottomans hadn't even expanded into Eastern Anatolia/Western Armenia/modern-day Eastern Turkey in the fifteenth century. The [[Battle of Chaldiran]], which marked the first Ottoman expansion into the region, only took place in 1514 and was a temporary gain. With the [[Peace of Amasya]] (1555), they secured Western Armenia, which is nevertheless only a part of the historical Armenia meant here. To conclude what I mean; neither in the 15th nor the 16th century, did ''Armenia come largely'' under Ottoman rule. The sentence therefore needs some adjustment. Bests - [[User:LouisAragon|LouisAragon]] ([[User talk:LouisAragon|talk]]) 01:38, 25 June 2016 (UTC)
::A very reasonable suggestion. The sentence should reflect that the Ottoman rule was extended over the western portion of Armenia in the sixteenth and early seventeenth century, following the treaties of Amasya (1555) and Zuhab (1639), with the latter establishing a lasting border between the Ottoman and Persian empire. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 16:05, 25 June 2016 (UTC)
:::{{ping|Armen Ohanian}}, thanks for your constructive response. I just rewrote that part, and added 3 sources to it as well. Bests - [[User:LouisAragon|LouisAragon]] ([[User talk:LouisAragon|talk]]) 15:00, 29 June 2016 (UTC)

==numbers in lead==
The Armenian massacres enjoys a vast array of research which is not monolithic, and at least the lead has to display that. Lets not turn this into the puritanism Holocaust scholarship suffers from. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 02:51, 13 July 2016 (UTC)
:Mr. Dolet do you mind to at the very least support the claim you made in your summary?

:''was the Ottoman government's systematic extermination of about 1.5 million[note 4] of its minority Armenian subjects inside their historic homeland, which lies within the present-day Republic of Turkey.[13][14]''

:There is two controversial statements in the above sentence, while mine actually has none. If the above sentence was to be true, my wording would still stand while the contrary is not necessarily true.

:Your wording excludes large array of published scholarship, while mine includes all including what you'd call denialist, revisionist etc... [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 04:40, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

::Wikipedia consensus sees the Armenian Genocide as a policy of extermination and not some debatable topic. It's been like this ever since the project started. Denialist opinion has always been in the minority. Please don't try to make amends to denialists in this article. That actually leads to sanctions in the [[WP:AA2]] topic area. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 04:59, 13 July 2016 (UTC)
:::Are you Wikipedia? I just randomly checked versions of the article, and found different ranges of figures... but here in talk, I have seen no rational of an absolute number to change ranges.

:::Where does my version suggests it was extermination or not? It simply avoids the term. The way your version is worded, it entirely excludes relevant scholarship, denialists or not, minority or not; this is arbitrary and largely selective. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 05:09, 13 July 2016 (UTC)
::::{{re|Yahya Talatin}} A) Try reading through the archives; B) There is nothing 'arbitrary' about mainstream scholarship and perceptions... and I seriously suspect that you don't understand what the [[WP:NPOV]] policy means. As a further suggestion, beware of [[WP:FRINGE]]. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 05:22, 13 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::I actually did, also the history of the article... this current wording seems to be new when considering the age of the article (check it for yourself). Arbitrary is to divide scholarship into two distinct group or use constructs to assume what is mainstream and what is not. Besides your reply is loaded with perceptions. More like what I assume rather than what I actually have written. You never in fact commented about the accuracy of the wording I proposed. You made different assumptions, even going as far as warning me about WP:FRINGE. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 05:37, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

::::::We actually have sources within this article that clarifies the fact that most genocide scholars and historians view this event as genocide, alongside the fact that 29 countries (as opposed to just one) have recognized the Armenian Genocide. You are pushing a minority position of denial which is disruptive and can lead to sanctioning. I already gave you an AA2 advisory and I suggest you don't edit-war over this again. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 05:47, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

::::::What I was telling you in as polite a manner as I deem to be fit, Yaḥyā, is that you are using this talk page as a [[WP:SOAP|soapbox]]. Take a look at the top of this [[WP:TPNO|talk page]] and read the warning boxes. Now, please desist from your [[WP:ACTIVIST|advocacy]]. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 06:03, 13 July 2016 (UTC)
To Dolet, Your accusation of revert warring doesn't stick scrutiny! Where did I ever write anything about if it was a genocide? I above avoided (and only in the talkpage) the term, because this term is a construct coined for ideological reasons attributed to an author (who holds authority on the word) to be used by authors and jurists, while massacre is an universally known word not attributed to someone and known in every language and nation. I won't take part in this word game which is devoid of any true meaning! But you again failed to tell me where in the wording (you reverted) there is an error! [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 06:12, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

To Iryna, please show me what is the advocacy in question, and where in my above comment, there is any indication that I am using this talkpage as a soapbox, again your reply is irrelevant to the comment it was meant to answer. I am done (made my point)... this alone shows who is the activist. An activist has an ideology to defend, and will never be the one to drop the sword. Actions speak louder than words.&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 13:33, 13 July 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:[[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]], I added that as per the discussion above. False balance is using &quot;above X&quot; when the actual number Y is much, much higher than X. That there were more than hundreds of thousands (which can be as low as 200,000-300,000) is quite uncontroversial. The current number is reported in nearly all prominent media outlets about the subject. That makes it the most accepted. By the way, most languages ''do'' have a word for &quot;genocide&quot;. In Turkish, this is ''soykırım''. I know the Turkish wiki uses just ''kırım'' (&quot;killing&quot;) here, but this is not the Turkish wiki. [[User:Prinsgezinde|Bataaf van Oranje (Prinsgezinde)]] ([[User talk:Prinsgezinde|talk]]) 09:49, 25 July 2016 (UTC)

::Doesn't change the fact that 1.5 million is an absolute number and it would require a form of selection to present it as actual figures representing the number of victims. The little research which has been done to provide any accurate figures were limited because of such things as the way the Ottoman Empire kept its records. Most British academics I've checked provide figures in the range of 600,000 or 800,000 figures. Why aren't they mainstream? You see where I am getting at? As for the term genocide, if I reply to this, I will probably be accused of soapboxing the talkpage. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 18:29, 25 July 2016 (UTC)
::: 'About 1.5 million' is in no way an 'absolute number'.  How could anyone read it as such, let alone push the point? There is no basis for criticism. All the reasoning was duly and patiently presented ahead of time. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 22:11, 25 July 2016 (UTC)
::::You'd prefer a better term? How about, it is the most controversial way the figures could be presented. It isn't even ''up to'' but ''about''! There is no room to variations for a wording like this, therefor it is presented as ''absolute'' truth. Anyone who doesn't see the problem, is just selectively ignoring. I'd like to see the reasoning which was duly and patiently presented. How does it address the fact that it excludes all those ''mainstream'' estimates which aren't 1,5 million? [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 22:46, 25 July 2016 (UTC)

:::::{{ec}} {{re|Yahya Talatin}} As already noted, the precise wording is &quot;...of about 1.5 million&quot;. In light of the fact that the reader is rightly assumed to have reasonable cognitive skills, who is going to read this as an 'absolute' figure. You're clutching at straws. Please [[WP:DEADHORSE|drop it]]. An intelligent and logical consensus has existed here for a long time, so it should be clear that persisting with [[WP:BLUDGEON]] tactics is not going to change this consensus. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 22:52, 25 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::: Iryna, I reworded that (absolute) above (to explain what I have meant by that word), we're not here to find bugs on others writings... I translated that wording (''of about'') in google translate into several languages (to be sure that I am not missing up some English language rules). ex. French ''environ 1.5 million.'' I repeat for the last time, word it the way you want it, but the current wording ignores a large array of estimates which are far away from the ''of about'' and which are considered as mainstream. In all the above replies, I have been accused of advocacy, of edit warring (for ONE revert) etc. but not once anyone has directly answered this. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 23:07, 25 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::::The &quot;large array of estimates... considered as mainstream&quot; have been reflected in a particular section of the article. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 15:24, 27 July 2016 (UTC)

Hi Armen,

One sober estimate (just a proposition, as there could be other sober estimates too) would be to take the highest estimate the Turkish side is willing to concede as minima and then the lowest the Armenian side is willing to concede. And present this as ''probably'' if it happens that the real number lies outside of the range, we won't make a mistake, because we wrote ''probably''.

Checking the articles on the subject published on Wikipedia (in different languages) and their talkpage... here is what we find.

The highest figure I found from the other side were suggested by Justin McCarthy, I chose it because it is published by The Turkish Historical Society For The Council Of Culture, Arts (Publications Of The Grand National Assembly Of Turkey.

It was an estimate by Justin McCarthy based on figures drawn by the parishes, he claims that if the parishes records are genuine, that he would have to raise his previous numbers with 250,000 more deaths (total: over 800,000 deaths). Given that those estimates appeared in a publication of The Grand National Assembly Of Turkey, I guess we can assume that it is the highest figures the Turkish side is ready to concede. From what can be found on Wikipedia, those are similar to the highest figures the Ottoman Empire (and newly created republic of Turkey) were ready to concede (800,000) back then, so they correspond.

Now, coming to the lowest figures the Armenian side is ready to concede.  What I found are those which circulate in France (drafted by the Armenian community), which is 1,2 million. This figure is also what appears in the lede of the French article about the event on Wikipedia.

One is close to a million, the other is over a million.

In this case, it would be something like (feel free to find a better wording) ''probably close to or over a million'' or something like that... by excluding any numerals we subject the article to even less controversy. Any estimates out of the range would be included, but not in the lede.

Again, those are just my propositions, since I have never gone so far to explain the rational behind my position. This kind of estimate is more stable, because it generally takes the most reasonable figures from either sides. There will be several other estimates, but the maximum one side is ready to concede and the minimum to other side is ready to concede are less likely to change. They are also coming from official organs from both sides.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 01:11, 28 July 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Other ranges include 600,000 to 1,500,000, 600,000 to 1,200,000... or 300,000 to 1,500,000, etc. with a higher inclusion criteria...
:We could increase the range by being more permissive but wider estimates are worthless.

:Interestingly, the means aren't much affected... they all revolve around the million (with expected variations).

:I guess we can for all practicable purpose just write ''probably about a million'' and clarifying in the notes. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 02:47, 28 July 2016 (UTC)
::We could also write: ''approximatively a million.''
::Britannica uses of the range: ''Conservative estimates have calculated that some 600,000 to more than 1,000,000 Armenians were slaughtered or died on the marches.'' [[https://www.britannica.com/event/Armenian-Genocide]]
::Encyclopedie Universalis (which is published by Britannica for French readers) uses: '' près d'un million cinq cent mille personnes perdent la vie en 1915-1916, dans des conditions effroyables, victimes du régime jeune-turc.''

::Average between Britannica two versions: Lowest here: 600,000 (English) to highest 1,500,000 (French), again the mean is about a million. 

::I'll search more to see if the approximative figure of a million is confirmed. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 14:05, 28 July 2016 (UTC)

:::Another encyclopedia, this time more specific of the Islamic World uses the term: ''More than a million.'' [https://books.google.ca/books?id=jBBYD2J2oE4C&amp;pg=PA300&amp;dq=#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]
:::An encyclopedia of the middle East and Africa: 600,000 to 1,500,000. [https://books.google.ca/books?id=GN5yv3-U6goC&amp;pg=PA28#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]

:::So seems the consensus are those ranges, with an invariable mean. Encyclopedia's of war crime and genocide are too specific and might be suffering of selection bias, by using the highest estimates.

:::We can therefor not really be wrong with the ''approximatively a million.'' [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 14:24, 28 July 2016 (UTC)

To incite editors to take a more sober stance, just reminding them that if they make the effort with the reasonable concessions, the article could become a ''good article'' and later even a ''featured''. Note that the last time I have checked, there are no genocide article meeting the ''good article'' criteria (not even the [[Holocaust]]). This might be the first. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 03:33, 28 July 2016 (UTC)
:Yaḥyā, I think you are straying into essay writing and OR here. The lede summarizes content. The content being summarized in this case will be the content contained in the Armenian population, deaths, survivors, 1914 to 1918 section. So I think any issues regarding the generally accepted figure should be worked out there first. That section does seem very inadequate at the moment. For example, it has a figure contained in a report compiled on 24 May 1916, and then wording that this report doesn't contains figures after May 1916. Well duh! Talk about stating the bleeding obvious!! There seems also to be too much emphasis on genocide denialist McCarthy's figures in both the amount of content in the section and in his overall position regarding the AG (which is fringe in relation to mainstream AG research). And why only &quot;1914 to 1918&quot;? Surely the section should deal with the entire timespan of the killing phase of the genocide. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:27, 29 July 2016 (UTC)
::I have changed the date in the section title to 1923. Is justified since 1923 is mentioned in the infobox note for the year 1915. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 22:08, 29 July 2016 (UTC)

:::{{ec}} While I think that Yahya's approach to 'discussion' has been acerbic from the onset, the fact is that Prinsgezinde himself described eliminating any range of estimates as being a [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=725506674&amp;oldid=725480780 bold move], therefore I'd suggest that there be an attempt to discuss whether a range is appropriate for the lead in a WP:CIVIL manner. Personally, I see a rationale for presenting reliably sourced lower estimates (and this does not mean the use of denialist figures). 'About' is a terrible qualifier where the discrepancy in estimates is literally tens of thousands of people. 'Up to' is equally ineffectual as it can be construed to be anything from 73 people to 1.''4'' million. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 22:17, 29 July 2016 (UTC)
::::Hi Iryna, thank you for your feedback. Just to clarify that the point in avoiding numerals (like 1.2 etc.) in ranges (or single absolute figure) is that those will be relying on specific sources (which would require exclusion of other figures). New publications are regularly published and references works are regularly updated with different estimates or ranges provided. This was behind the rational of using more stable ways of conveying information. The proposition of taking the highest of one to the lowest of other was to find if there might by overlapping or close to..., with a range which might be less prone to variate in time, and then check if it is confirmed in reference work (tertiary). The mean seems to remain the same (more or less) regardless of the variations. Rounding up numbers with approximations without numerals (such as 0,6, 1,2 etc.) would make the article more stable; less prone to change each time there is a new reference work or notable book published. Just my opinion. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 01:27, 30 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::I think 1.5 million adequately does that, but I think there needs to be better justification for it given within the content of the &quot;Armenian population, deaths, survivors, 1914 to 1918&quot; section of the article. One issue is that figures, including those you have stated, can cover different periods. This article is about the Armenian Genocide, not just about Ottoman Armenian victims of the Armenian Genocide, or Armenian victims of the genocide killed during WW1. So any overall number of victims needs to include all victims in all territories in which the genocide took place and over the full period of its accepted timeline. 02:19, 30 July 2016 (UTC)[[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]])
::::::I see your point, but those dates are too precise (along with selected lede figure), more you add precision more you have to rely on records, which can individually be discarded by further publications. It just isn't stable in time. When you go over the period of 1916/17, then you create even more controversy. You should rather rely on wording such as during World War I (which includes a period from 1914 to late 1918) without specifying dates in category title. Also by widening the range to 1915-23 you downplay the extent of the tragedy... because most victims were reported in the period between 1915 to 17. Also as stated, round numbers which don't require numerals will always remain there.

::::::Besides, precisions of records don't allow to slice more accurately than the million division, and luckily here, this is where the mean lies. A scholar could endorse low figures of victims, he will never be able to reject that the mean of the ranges of estimates is a million, and his own estimates are further from it. In research, the meta-analysis is generally considered the standard rather than one single study, particularly when the study is further from the center. By endorsing the million, you close the door to any later attempt to question it. And by adopting less precise dates, even more. 

::::::The level of sophistication of the revisionist material can only be countered by being fully and wholly neutral. The Turkish government can finance scholars, but those individual scholars will never be able to change the mean (it is Earth which gravitates around the Sun, not the other way around; since Earth's mass is insignificant for the Sun). [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 04:09, 30 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Forgot to add (to clarify the analogy with the Sun) on Turkish government financed and Holocaust uniqueness adherents studies and scholars. For each low new biased estimates there will be, they will be balanced with those new other estimates biased toward Armenian side. This is why the mean is the only invariable figure, no matter what a couple of scholars publish, it will remain there. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 15:49, 30 July 2016 (UTC)
:::Hi Tiptoethrutheminefield, I am just providing different figures and check if they correspond. OR concerns the injection of ones thought in the article itself. On McCarthy figures, the reason this much weight is given on his figures, are because it is through him the Ottoman records were published in length. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 00:06, 30 July 2016 (UTC)

== Heath W. Lowry article ==

For editors interested, there is currently [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Neutral_point_of_view/Noticeboard#Heath_W._Lowry a discussion on the NPOVN] regarding potential POVPUSH issues on Lowry's article. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 00:34, 19 July 2016 (UTC)
:My reply on the noticeboard gives clues on how to treat scholars positions on the issue. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 18:43, 28 July 2016 (UTC)

==Erdogan uses of the word massacre==
Erdogan uses of the term ought to be mentioned in the article. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 04:50, 28 July 2016 (UTC)

==Encyclopædia Britannica references to the research of Arnold J. Toynbee==
The reference to it from the article has to be removed. Britannica does not refer to it anymore, the material was removed from its page. [https://www.britannica.com/topic/Death-toll-from-the-Armenian-deportation-and-massacres-1688531] This is an example of what I was referring to, it was too far from the mean, didn't resist. I just want users to trust me that I will not mislead anyone. There is currently a shift in the way the Turkish population is perceiving this event; here is the time to invite Turkish editors to contribute and provide their feedback. This article internal structure is to be drafted anew. There just are too much arbitrary divisions and inclusions and exclusions, just one example is why this [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian_Genocide#Scandinavian_missionaries_and_diplomats] goes just after the Russian military, and why the Russian military goes there and not elsewhere. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 23:44, 30 July 2016 (UTC)
:You wrote earlier: &quot;Average between Britannica two versions: Lowest here: 600,000 (English) to highest 1,500,000 (French), again the mean is about a million&quot; - I think this is invalid as a starting point. If one source says 1 million and 10 say 1.5 million, the mean is not 1.25. We would use the number (or range of numbers) that the majority of suitable sources use, and describe that number in that way. In fact, any talk of getting a &quot;mean&quot; figure is OR because it means you or I doing research to work out that mean! This is what I meant when I said you were straying into OR. I still think 1.5 million is the figure used in the majority of suitable sources, though I don't have general works to hand to cite. Those that initially advocated stating just 1.5 million as the lede figure need to come in to this discussion, with sources. I'm not sure exactly what you mean by the rest of your post, but this article should not be an exercise in &quot;reconciliation&quot; - it should not be written to reflect the shifting perceptions or sensibilities of sets of ethnicities, nor should its facts be artificially softened to make a catch-up-to-the-truth process by Turks easier for them.  [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 20:14, 31 July 2016 (UTC)

But the thing is that I am not disagreeing with you, I am just disagreeing with your exclusion of some parameters to draw your conclusions. 

For instance, Britannica is a very reputable encyclopedia with hight standards. While in the past it had changed its figures of losses to more conservative numbers reportedly because of pressures from the Turkish diplomacy, it was later compensated with it's French encyclopedia Universalis. It has taken the approach to use both figures to convey the less popular number for both sides (million).

It can be considered as established that we can not just use plurality of published secondary sources to compute means. Thousands might be using the same source and have therefor to be rejected to avoid redundancy. More importantly is that most reference works do have ranges closer to a million. Those are generally never used by those who defend or reject the term genocide, because it satisfies neither sides (too low for one, too high for the other). See how when searching Armenian massacres million on google book [https://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;q=armenian+massacres+million]. All results on top are directly related with the subject of defending the thesis of genocide, and therefor provide the highest ranges (it's selection bias). See Taner Akcam estimates with the others here [https://books.google.ca/books?id=DudJBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT371&amp;dq=armenians+ottoman+million&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=armenians%20ottoman%20million&amp;f=false], footnote 35. While Lewy figures there are further from the range (expected, Ottoman books are generally biased toward the other side so they will tend to include the low estimates), Taner Akcam endorses the mean (800,000 to a million, because of the original Turkish figures), even Vahakn Dadrian doesn't provide explicit figures! Also in the list you will find Fuat Dundar (he has works published in the European Journal of Turkish studies) estimates of 664,000, he was the author of Crime of Numbers: The Role of Statistics in the Armenian Question (1878-1918). Why he is relevant is that here we have a Turkish scholar who use the official Ottoman records and statistics to compute data and finds a number above the 600,000 range. Quite obviously things seem to revolve around a same mean, one way or another. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 23:17, 31 July 2016 (UTC)

My reason to invite Turkish editors is because they will be more critical and they will be the first to point out which wordings are problematic.

Lastly, what I am doing isn't OR (I am not editing mainspace), I am using three different methods which are being used to compute and treat data, and am finding the same results and this systematically and then compare them with tertiary sources to see if they confirm the results, and they do. While any selection process to choose 1,5 million is either entirely undisclosed or rely on incomplete ways of choosing and polling the data.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 21:44, 31 July 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Reintroduction of lawyer claim==
The edit summary here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=732168999&amp;oldid=732138293] is weird, the author of this comment should explain his rational to justify it. Why is this man opinion even relevant? An opinion which we don't even know he still maintain, or why it should make any differences if he does. Will it still remain there after Obama was replaced? [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 19:18, 31 July 2016 (UTC)
:Actually, everyone [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Armenian_Genocide#Moving_discussions_from_OWNTALK_here], except the editor who has repeatedly inserted this content, agrees that it needs to go. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 20:18, 31 July 2016 (UTC)
::I missed that discussion, tks! [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 21:49, 31 July 2016 (UTC)
:::Okay, I've removed it again. The rationale has been discussed at length and reintroducing the content on flimsy pretexts is not an option when the relevance and [[WP:WEIGHT]] of a dated source is dubious. Yes, there is a 'shelf life' as has been explained clearly. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 05:04, 1 August 2016 (UTC)

::::There is no such thing as 'shelf life' of sources. If there were, all of WP would come unraveled. It is a fabricated standard to avoid content the proponents wish to censor. The statement by the ABA speaks for itself, being the carefully weighed position of one of the top civil bodies of Armenian society about President Obama's statement. Nothing has changed. The WH statement has been the same from year to year. The ABA statement still holds. It doesn't need to be issued each year, as seems to be suggested. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:28, 1 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::Hi Diranakir, all the edit warring on Wikipedia are directly or indirectly related with sources ''shelf life''. We can not overemphasis on individuals positions, because those individuals can change minds, discredited or their inclusions or exclusions can sound arbitrary for others (why Mr. X, not Mr. Y?). I can understand why it might be considered as relevant to some as a statment, but a better approach is to concentrate on the event itself rather than it's wording. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 16:22, 1 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::Obama, before becoming president, had used the phrase Armenian Genocide and had stated that the event was a genocide. Thus his &quot;recognition and affirmation of the Armenian Genocide&quot; occurred before his first public use of the phrase Medz Yeghern - so it is deceptive wording to suggest that it had occurred only when he said Medz Yeghern [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=732471062&amp;oldid=732466279]. Many sources have said that Obama's CONTINUED public use of the phrase Meds Yeghern rather than Armenian Genocide was to intentionally avoid repeating his earlier explicit &quot;recognition and affirmation&quot;. It is a case of undue weight to introduce a single source, a source that talks only about (and dates from) Obama's FIRST public use of the phrase, in order to imply that those other MORE RECENT sources are incorrect in their opinions about his REPEATED public use of it. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 12:27, 2 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::::We are here talking about different views of Obama's use of M Y. No one said that his recognition and affirmation occurred only when he used it. The Armenian Bar Association statement (given in the censored source) said that he described 1915 as genocide and used the Armenian name for it the same as Armenians do. What is called a 'single source' is a statement by the highest professional legal body in Armenia. That is giving INSUFFICIENT WEIGHT to the source. Their endorsement of Obama's statement (which has essentially remained the same until today) was based on close analysis and interpretation of the statement. One may disagree with their conclusion, but it is a fact that cannot be left out of the picture without engaging in crude censorship and preventing a presumably mature readership from reaching their own conclusions. M Y is one of the two principal names for 1915 used by Armenians, a full synonym of Hayotz Tseghasbanutyun, used all over the place in Armenia and outside, used completely interchangeably with HT. To pretend otherwise is to stick your head in the sand. You can do so if you wish, but you shouldn't try to force others to do the same. It is a travesty to have an article on the Armenian Genocide that gives virtually no recognition to the name Medz Yeghern which is commensurate with its importance. If you look at the article on the Armenian Genocide in Armenian Wikipedia, you will see otherwise. The same if you look at the official site for the Armenian Genocide Memorial Complex. Enough of contrived excuses and tortured timelines for avoiding the issue. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 03:56, 3 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::::You have admitted it - you have one source that is, contrary to what all the other (later) sources are saying, concluding that Obama's use of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; is not a genocide negating usage. All the other sources of course have the benefit of seeing Obama's continued use of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; (and continued lack of usage of &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot;) as evidence to support their opinion. We do not use sources giving inaccurate reportage of or opinion of events when later, more accurate ones, emerge. Yet you continue to pov war on this issue in order to minimize mention of the fact that sources are saying that Obama and others have been using your dearly-held &quot;Meds Yeghern&quot; term as a way of avoiding saying the word &quot;genocide&quot; when talking about the Armenian Genocide. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 20:26, 3 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::What 'other (later) sources' ? I don't see them. Please specify and don't beat around the bush. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 04:27, 4 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::Ref 201. And cited earlier on this talk page, in discussions you took part in (maybe your conveniently goldfish-like memory fails to remember that) were several more, online media sources such as [http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/news/210865/Obama_fails_to_keep_Genocide_recognition_promise_for_8th_year] and [http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/obama-avoids-using-genocide-opting-for-meds-yeghern-in-april-24-commemoration-.aspx?pageID=238&amp;nID=65514&amp;NewsCatID=359] and [http://armenianweekly.com/2016/04/22/obama-issues-statement-on-armenian-remembrance-day/]. And an additional dozen or so more can easily be found using google. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:33, 5 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::I was wrong: you did not beat around the bush; you faded into the tall grass. In evoking earlier discussions on this talk page, which sources do you mean? Either quote them directly or give me the time and date of prominent examples of what you mean. 
::::::::::::You are making up your own rules as you go and to very unwholesome effect. If you have valid sources for your point, you should make them as inline citations so that they can be fairly assessed and responded to, this in accord with accepted WP practices. What is in your head or what you may tactically scrape together after the fact does not count. If that is allowed, then the whole principle of reliable sources and their proper citation is out the window. You are engaged in an effort to prevent presentation of the fact that not everyone in the world shares your crimped view of Medz Yeghern and its implications. I will repeat: you and those who support your stance are engaging in outright censorship. You have no right or justification for keeping the ABA statement out of the article to push the POV that Medz Yeghern is universally condemned as a 'negating usage', when it is in fact a well-known, full synonym for the Armenian Genocide, as reflected in many quotations from government figures and pontiffs in the previous discussions which you conveniently ignore. You are thereby turning the section in question into an 'opinion piece', at best. A very low standard to set for the encyclopedia. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:22, 6 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Does your goldfish memory not even last two seconds, the time it takes for you to see a link and then decide to click on it? If you can't remember what discussions you took part in, it's your lamentable memory that is at fault. Conveniently lamentable of course, conveniently goldfish-like, since it allows you to resurrect any long settled discussion point you lost and restart it from scratch as if you had never lost the argument and the discussion had never taken place. 21:19, 6 August 2016 (UTC)[[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]])
{{od|13}}Diranakir, please stop pushing the envelope on [[WP:GOAD|goading]] and [[WP:DEADHORSE|drop the stick]]. Your arguments have ceased to be coherent. Take some time to [[WP:COOL|cool your heels]]. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 22:28, 6 August 2016 (UTC)
:To Iryna Harpy: Instead of using provocative labels, you might point out how I have 'ceased to be coherent'. Unless you are willing to do that, there really isn't much to your comment. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 23:41, 6 August 2016 (UTC)
::You've reduced the argument to 'Medz Yeghern' being a full synonym for the Armenian genocide as being a well known 'fact'. Really? Should we put that to the test with an RfC to find out whether the title of the article should be changed to &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; if they're so interchangeable? Instead of being provocative, please stop this [[WP:BLUDGEON]]. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 23:57, 6 August 2016 (UTC)
::Diranakir - the article has content that clearly states that &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; is a term that is used to refer to the Armenian Genocide. So your claim that the article's content expresses the opinion that &quot;Medz Yeghern is universally condemned as a 'negating usage'&quot; is nonsense. The section you are pointlessly warring over details the usage by certain non-Armenians of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot;. Four sources have been presented that give the opinion that President Obama's REPEATED usage of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; is to avoid him having to say the word &quot;genocide&quot;, and many more sources giving an identical opinion are available. Yet you still insist on edit warring into the article a marginal opinion expressed in only a single source, and an obsolete opinion at that, since it was based on Obama's FIRST use of the term. Would you stop flogging this dead horse. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 00:04, 7 August 2016 (UTC)
:::&quot;By admitting the facts and labeling the event as 'Meds Yeghern' Obama de facto acknowledges genocide. But the argumentation is manipulative and he thus avoids admitting it de jure&quot; (Zarine Avetisyan, &quot;Speech Impact Realization via Manipulative Argumentation Techniques in Modern American Political Discourse,&quot; International Journal of Social, Behavioral, Educational, Economic, Business and Industrial Engineering, vol. 9, No. 6, '''2015,''' p. 1787). So much for the &quot;obsolete opinion,&quot; the &quot;dead horse,&quot; and the useless nitpicking about the issue. Opinions about the first and the last use of &quot;Medz Yeghern&quot; are equally valid, since the word is the same, whether in 2009 or in 2016. [[User:Armen Ohanian|Armen Ohanian]] ([[User talk:Armen Ohanian|talk]]) 17:14, 7 August 2016 (UTC)
::::Have you actually given any thought as to what you've reproduced here? {{tq|&quot;But the argumentation is manipulative and he thus avoids admitting it de jure...&quot;}}. You've just contradicted what you're trying to prove in one fell swoop. Could you please try to come up with an RS that doesn't defy your own logic? --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 23:57, 7 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::Incidentally, the PDF of the source you're invoking can be found by Googling it (available at waset.org). I can't paste the URL here because it's blacklisted by Wikipedia. Reading the article will assist other editors to understand the context in which the observation is made. It's a deconstruction of spin-doctoring and, in the context of this article, the complexity of the ''example'' of the Armenian genocide is used within a research paper not even examining the subject. What you are presenting as evidence is pure [[WP:SYNTH]]. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 00:12, 8 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::It's an article worth reading (though a bit badly written because its author is obviously not a native English speaker). Backs up what I have always felt - that Obama's supposedly highly praised oratory skills result in amongst the most deceit-filled productions emanating from any politician. Thankfully there is a two term limit on US presidencies - someone that able to (and that willing to) manipulate the masses could do no end of damage without that limit. There has to be some alternative to either the manipulative snake-oil-salesman speak of Obama and his ilk, or the absence of any reasoned argumentation crudity of Trump's utterances. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 16:58, 8 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::::It's an excellent read for personal interest. What it lacks in eloquence is made up for in content (in spades). --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 22:02, 8 August 2016 (UTC)
::::Armen Ohanian's sources defy his own logic regularly. Here he is trying to uncapitalise &quot;Aghet&quot; [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=733416631&amp;oldid=733387070], but his same French source also does not capitalise &quot;Yeghern&quot;. Is he going to follow the logic of his own argument and argue it should be yeghern? Probably not. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:46, 8 August 2016 (UTC)

==Sarafian==
I changed it, because he applied the undercounting reported by Talaat, the figures used there in the black book (particularly the undercounting) are nothing new, see here [http://www.genocidereality.com/htmlpages/publication1/table2page70.gif] Justin McCarthy had used similar correction values then. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 01:37, 2 August 2016 (UTC)
:If someone disagree in replacing the name, I won't bother if it is changed back, but it should be clarified it's not exactly Sarafian view... even though it seems he did add some undisclosed extra in it (probably assumptions of Protestant Armenians etc.) That's the problem with scholars in such case is that they always seem to add undisclosed stuff, they're like closed source softwares. :) [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 01:48, 2 August 2016 (UTC)
::I'm restoring Sarafian because he is the [[WP:SECONDARY]] source who interprets Talaat's figures. Please familiarise yourself with [[WP:RS]] carefully. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 01:52, 2 August 2016 (UTC)
:::Hi Irnya, I won't disagree, I realized later about that. My language skills are limited but I am under the impression from reading the sentence  that ''he'' thinks there are as much Armenians: '' Therefore, according to the historian Ara Sarafian, the population of Armenians should have been approximately 1,700,000 prior to the start of the war.'' I don't know if a clarification is appropriate to clarify that he is presenting Talaat figures. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 02:07, 2 August 2016 (UTC)
::::There is more, he does not say ''approximatively'' but rather ''close'', won't make much differences but still. The actual wording is: ''based on official figures,  close  to  1,700,000  people.''  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 02:11, 2 August 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::::I think it's clear without further qualifications (i.e., we could get caught up in pedantry over much of the content in various Wikipedia articles), but other editors may deem it relevant to note that Sarafian used state documentation. If so, they're welcome to discuss it here further. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 04:47, 2 August 2016 (UTC)

== Errors in lede sentence ==

The lede sentence contains two very striking errors.

In the first place the historic homeland of Armenia is not contained within the borders of modern day Turkey (possibly an [[Armenian Revolutionary Federation |irredentist claim]]?) The [[Armenian Highlands|historic homelands of the Armenians]] comprise the eastern regions of Turkey as well as all of present day Armenia and parts of Azerbaijan and Georgia. About half the historic homeland is contained within Turkey.

Secondly the figure of 1,500,000 fatalities is not confined to Ottoman-Armenians living within the Ottoman empire, but include some 400,000 fatalities suffered post-1916 by Armenians living outside the Ottoman empire during attempts by the Ottomans to expand their empire.

Of course these errors should be corrected. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 19:21, 28 August 2016 (UTC)
:If you can provide scholar sources for your claim, edit the prose to fit the sources.  if not, the article should remain as is. [[User:Lipsquid|Lipsquid]] ([[User talk:Lipsquid|talk]]) 19:44, 28 August 2016 (UTC)
::Hello Lipsquid. I'm surprized by your response because my understanding is that protected articles like these need consensus on the Talk page before an edit can be made in the article. Perhaps you can clarify and meanwhile I can try and get consensus here in the way you suggest. Do you in fact challenge my assertions above? [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 20:18, 28 August 2016 (UTC)
::First of all, regarding the article's own sources for the assertion that the historic homeland of the Armenians lies within modern day Turkey, these are two in number [http://edition.cnn.com/2015/04/23/world/armenian-mass-killings/index.html 13] [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/04/23/armenian-genocide-controversy_n_7121008.html 14]. These are from CNN and the Huffington Post and while certainly reliable sources, I don't think they would normally be regarded as the scholarly sources you say should be cited. But no matter, because neither in fact supports the assertion that the historic homeland of the Armenians is contained within present day Turkey. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 20:36, 28 August 2016 (UTC)
::It is therefore the duty of the existing editors to provide scholarly sources for their assertion that the historic homeland of the Armenians lies within present day Turkey. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 21:16, 28 August 2016 (UTC)
:: Regarding the 1,500,000 fatalities mentioned by the article, it's quite correct that's the consensus of the sources. But it's important to observe that relates to the whole period 1915 to 1923. The article's sources referenced in its note are newspapers and not scholarly sources and for the most part gloss the situation. Dadrian's standard history, the authoritative source, is perfectly clear on the subject [http://www.armeniansgenocide.am/images/menus/176/The%20history%20of%20Armenian%20Genocide.pdf right at the start of his introduction]: there were some one million fatalities in the Ottoman empire during the war 1915-1917 and several hundred of thousand more as the Ottomans attempted to extend their empire into Russia Armenia. To quote [http://www.armenian-genocide.org/genocidefaq.html#How_many ''armenian-genocide.org'']
:::It is estimated that one and a half million Armenians perished between 1915 and 1923. There were an estimated two million Armenians living in the Ottoman Empire on the eve of W.W.I. Well over a million were deported in 1915. Hundreds of thousands were butchered outright. Many others died of starvation, exhaustion, and epidemics which ravaged the concentration camps. Among the Armenians living along the periphery of the Ottoman Empire many at first escaped the fate of their countrymen in the central provinces of Turkey. Tens of thousands in the east fled to the Russian border to lead a precarious existence as refugees. The majority of the Armenians in Constantinople, the capital city, were spared deportation. In 1918, however, the Young Turk regime took the war into the Caucasus, where approximately 1,800,000 Armenians lived under Russian dominion. Ottoman forces advancing through East Armenia and Azerbaijan here too engaged in systematic massacres. The expulsions and massacres carried by the Nationalist Turks between 1920 and 1922 added tens of thousands of more victims. By 1923 the entire landmass of Asia Minor and historic West Armenia had been expunged of its Armenian population. The destruction of the Armenian communities in this part of the world was total.
:: Of course Russia Armenia was not part of present day Turkey. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 22:22, 28 August 2016 (UTC)
:: It's clear that the lede sentence currently misrepresents the facts. I invite response so that we can build a consensus. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 22:27, 28 August 2016 (UTC)
The issue of the inaccurate (or at the very least, misleading) &quot;historic homeland&quot; lede content has been raised in the past. However, expect a conflict at least as long as the recent Medz Yeghern thing to get rid of it. The victim total should be for the entire period of the Armenian Genocide because this is the subject of the article. So it necessarily will include deaths inside Russian territory and Persian territory and deaths that happened after the year 1918, as long as the events are considered to be part of the Armenian Genocide. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 16:55, 29 August 2016 (UTC)
: That's right about &quot;misleading&quot;. You really have to abuse English quite a lot to construe the sense as talking about the historic homeland of the Ottoman Armenians (as distinct from Armenians in general) as these cannot be said to have an historic homeland as Ottomans. Rather the Ottoman Armenians were an Armenian minority within the Ottoman empire who happened to be Ottoman subjects through conquest. This is how Dadrian describes them in the opening paragraph of his introduction I link in the introduction above.
: That's right also that the victim total should be for the whole 1915-1923 period, cited in multiple sources including Dadrian as 1,500,000 fatalities. But the problem is that if you understand the opening sentence as the editors intend, i.e. as about the Ottoman Armenians, then that's no longer correct because the number of victims among the Ottoman Armenians is cited by Dadrian and multiple other authors as of the order of 1 million. It's the 400,000 or so post-1917 fatalities outside the Ottoman empire that brings the total to 1,500,000. 
: I do think it quite likely irredentist enthusiasm that is at the heart of the matter here. But a reader new to the subject is wholly misled and it should be corrected. I'll wait a few more days to see what established editors here propose. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 20:47, 29 August 2016 (UTC)
::I've gone ahead and reworded it. It is not irredentism, imo. It is just the simplified and simplistic [[sound bite]] material that Armenians have been dishing out to non-Armenians for decades. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 00:42, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
:::Nice edit, certainly a move in the right direction which is as much succinct clarity in the lede as possible.  [[User:Lipsquid|Lipsquid]] ([[User talk:Lipsquid|talk]]) 01:20, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
:::: Yes. It's much better and I thank Tiptoethrutheminefield for that. A remaining concern is the reference to the [[Ottoman government]] because that of course was not in place after 1918 (rather there were two competing governments during the [[Turkish War of Independence]]).I think that needs to be addressed as well.
:::: I'll look back, but I don't really want to get involved editing here. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 01:25, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
::::: Oh, and while I'm here, I would like to see &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot; go. That's a neologism due to Robert Fisk and it hasn't gained currency nor is it especially useful I think, much as I admire Fisk. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 01:40, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::It's not a neologism, it actually dates back to the 1920s. Whether it should be in the lede is a different matter though. If it was the primary term used to refer to the Armenian genocide before the coining of the word &quot;genocide&quot;, then I think it should be there. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:26, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::: Small h holocaust, as a massacre dates from Victorian times developing from Milton's (that great coiner of neologisms) use of it in ''Samson'' to mean a consuming fire. Big H Holocaust (by itself) to mean the Nazi genocide of the Jews was used by historians of the 1950s as a translation of the Jewish term ''shoah'' and took a while to catch on. Small h holocaust does appear in some 1940s sources describing the Nazi genocide and quite possibly appears in earlier texts describing the Armenian genocide. It's strictly incorrect to talk about the &quot;Jewish Holocaust&quot;, but that is what Fisk affects [http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/commentators/fisk/robert-fisk-let-me-denounce-genocide-from-the-dock-6231049.html in his piece] and it really irritates me. However no great matter. The business of [[Ottoman Government]] ''is'' a great matter that ought to be addressed. I note the [[Imperial_Government_(Ottoman_Empire) | article's wikilink for it]] states its end as 1918.
::::::: Nevertheless, as I remarked, I have no plans to edit here, and I am grateful for the attention you gave my original request. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 04:03, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::: Curiously enough &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot; has been there [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;oldid=386442 ever since the article began], so I suppose it had better stay. The Fisk citation needs repairing (the article is still extant on The Independent site so it shouldn't default to its archive) and I shall do that when I have a spare moment. Those early versions of the article have a certain charm :). I'm not sure in the end they're not more informative. I glanced through the Medz Yeghern debate. See what you mean. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 18:29, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::: The article [[Names_of_the_Holocaust#The_Holocaust|Names of the Holocaust]] cites Winston Churchill using &quot;holocaust&quot; writing about the Armenian Genocide in the 1920s. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 00:35, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::::I can't access a copy of Churchill's book, but the quote can be verified via the ''Encyclopedia of Genocide''as, &quot;...whole districts blotted out at one administrative holocaust...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor=Charny, Israel W.|editor-link=Israel Charny|title=Encyclopedia of Genocide|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8Q30HcvCVuIC&amp;pg=PA42|accessdate=31 August 2016|volume=1|year=1999|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-87436-928-1|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

::::::::I can't, however, account for the remainder of the quote in this article (in the &quot;Allied forces in the Middle East&quot; section). I also think one needs to be careful in how the parallel usages of the pre-existing English language word/term 'holocaust' is used as as a descriptor: that is, it is not used in the same way as the later neologism &lt;u&gt;''The'' Holocaust&lt;/u&gt; is used. Per the Charny encyclopaedia, it was evident that 'holocaust' was used to describe wholesale organised destruction of a civilian population before Lemkin's coining of the word 'genocide'. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 01:34, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
{{reflist-talk}}
:::::::: Ah yes, thanks for that. I hadn't realized it was quoted in the article. I used my unlimited Kindle account with a certain internet provider to collect the two sources in full as follows:

:::::::::The conduct of the Bulgarians in Serbia excited the extreme indignation of the investigators. As for Turkish atrocities: marching till they dropped dead the greater part of the garrison at Kut; massacring uncounted thousands of helpless Armenians, men, women, and children together, whole districts blotted out in one administrative holocaust— these were beyond human redress.

:::::::::Churchill, Winston S.. The World Crisis, Vol. 4 (Winston Churchill's World Crisis Collection) (Kindle Locations 2213-2215). RosettaBooks. Kindle Edition. 

:::::::::When Turkey attacked Russian Armenia, the Czar’s Government, fearing that a successful defence of Caucasia by Armenians would dangerously inflame the Nationalist aspirations of the race, conveyed a hundred and fifty thousand Armenian conscripts to the Polish and Galician fronts and brought other Russian troops to defend Armenian hearths and homes in Caucasia. Few of these hundred and fifty thousand Armenian soldiers survived the European battles or were able to return to Caucasia before the end of the War. This was hard measure. But worse remained. The Turkish war plan failed. Their offensive against Caucasia in December, 1914 and January, 1915 was defeated. They recoiled in deep resentment. They accused the Armenians of the Turkish eastern districts of having acted as spies and agents on behalf of Russia, and of having assailed the Turkish lines of communication. These charges were probably true; but true or false, they provoked a vengeance which was also in accord with deliberate policy. In 1915 the Turkish Government began, and ruthlessly carried out, the infamous general massacre and deportation of Armenians in Asia Minor. Three or four hundred thousand men, women, and children escaped into Russian territory and others into Persia or Mesopotamia; but the clearance of the race from Asia Minor was about as complete as such an act, on a scale so great, could well be. It is supposed that about one and a quarter millions of Armenians were involved, of whom more than half perished. There is no reasonable doubt that this crime was planned and executed for political reasons. The opportunity presented itself for clearing Turkish soil of a Christian race opposed to all Turkish ambitions, cherishing National ambitions that could only be satisfied at the expense of Turkey and planted geographically between Turkish and Caucasian Moslems. It may well be that the British attack on the Gallipoli Peninsula stimulated the merciless fury of the Turkish Government. Even, thought the Pan-Turks, if Constantinople were to fall and Turkey lost the war, the clearance would have been effected and a permanent advantage for the future of the Turkish race would be gained.

:::::::::Churchill, Winston S.. The World Crisis, Vol. 4 (Winston Churchill's World Crisis Collection) (Kindle Locations 6099-6101). RosettaBooks. Kindle Edition. 

::::::::The first comes from a section on war crimes investigations. I don't know what the context for the second is (trouble with ebooks is that they're hard to flick through). It's perfectly clear, however, that Churchill was quite clear in his mind that this was genocide as it would later be called (likewise Lloyd George later in that interesting source you cite).

::::::::I'm content to stay with &quot;Armenian Holocaust&quot; in the lede in the circumstances, notwithstanding your reservation. I honestly thought it was an innovation of Fisk's (which I suppose it strictly is from the capital H point of view).

:::::::: Thanks for correcting my Fisk citation edit by the way. Indeed I should have cited the first Wayback archive. [[User:Awen23|Awen23]] ([[User talk:Awen23|talk]]) 03:45, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
Re lede error correction: For a while I thought my &quot;expect a conflict at least as long as the recent Medz Yeghern thing to get rid of it&quot; prediction was going to be surprisingly (but pleasantly) wrong. But now the usual suspect has arrived [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=739143545&amp;oldid=737306935].  [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 19:15, 14 September 2016 (UTC)
::The brilliant historian, author of the previous comment, needs to be asked whether the following statement upholds WP standards and serves the readers: The AG was the Ottoman government's systematic extermination of Armenians within its successor state, the Republic of Turkey. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 21:09, 14 September 2016 (UTC)
:::No, that's definitely ''not'' what the sentence boils down to after parsing it. There appears to have been a hiccup in your spotting &quot;the Ottoman Empire&quot; (and its successor state). Quite a different kettle of fish. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 01:54, 15 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::Homey images of hiccups and kettles of fish do not obscure the fact that my parsing of the sentence is spot on and that you are, either out of obtuseness or willful blindness, defending fraudulent usage to the detriment of the encyclopedia. I would have appreciated a direct response from the author of the defective sentence, rather than from a surrogate. This only adds to the sense that the issue is not being addressed forthrightly, but rather out of [[groupthink]]. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 02:41, 15 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::The obtuseness and willful blindness appears to be all from you, Diranakir. Did you read anything of the start of this thread? It was initiated by an editor validly pointing out two glaring errors in the lede; the edit you reverted was my attempt at correcting those errors. Or maybe you did read it, and perhaps an ignorance of the overall history of the Armenian genocide, or a belief that content should follow the very simplified version of that history presented by certain Armenian activist organizations, does not allow you to acknowledge those errors were there. Are you denying that the Armenian Genocide extended into Armenians living in the Russian-ruled Southern Caucasus (including as far as Baku), and into the Armenia that comprised the territory of the first republic, and into Armenians living in northern Persia? If you are not, what valid reasons can you present to support the old ''&quot;The Armenian Genocide ... was the Ottoman government's systematic extermination of 1.5 million Ottoman-Armenian citizens inside their historic homeland, which lies within the present-day Republic of Turkey&quot;'' wording over the current ''&quot;The Armenian Genocide ... was the Ottoman government's systematic extermination of 1.5 million Armenians, mostly Ottoman citizens within the Ottoman Empire and its successor state, the Republic of Turkey.&quot;'' The current wording is probably not perfect, but it is far better than what existed before. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 13:32, 15 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::In your urgency to avoid 'the simplified version of history presented by certain Armenian activist organizations', you obviously bit off more complexity than you could chew and ended up with a sentence containing an absurd contradiction: that the Ottoman government systematically exterminated Armenians in its successor state, the Republic of Turkey. Why can't you and Harpy just face that fact? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 21:16, 15 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::You answer nothing, you propose nothing, you revert to a flawed version that you refuse to even justify. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 13:25, 16 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::And what is the justification for your contradiction that the Ottoman Empire exterminated Armenians within its successor state, the Republic of Turkey? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 14:59, 16 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::Again, you refuse to actually defend the text version you reverted to, and decline to offer any alternative to either it or my wording. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:25, 16 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::Read the edit summary. I am refusing and declining nothing. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:13, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::To Harpy: I need a rational explanation of why you reverted my latest edit. Your edit summary amounts to zero. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 01:07, 21 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Diranakir, you have been REPEATEDLY asked to justify your edits on the talk page. You have refused to do so, and you have refused to address the issues which the content you have been repeatedly reverting was written to resolve. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 13:49, 21 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::I corrected your error, which was a direct contradiction in the article, I did not revert. You had plenty of time to correct it yourself but didn't, because neither you nor Harpy ever admitted the error. More [[groupthink]]. That is the beginning of the problem.  You and Harpy do not own the article and cannot dictate the conditions under which an edit is made. You had been unresponsive. Address the merits of my edit rather than shouting about process. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:01, 21 September 2016 (UTC) 

:::::::::::::::Whereas you own the article to the extent that you ignore its 1RR and distain to provide even the smallest talk page explanation. Your edits ARE reverts - they are all removing the same content, replacing it with content that is slightly different every time. The content you are deleting is there to explain that the majority of the victims of the Armenian Genocide were Ottoman citizens, and that the event mostly took place inside the territory of the Ottoman Empire. It replaced content that incorrectly claimed that ALL of the victims were Ottoman citizens and that it all took place inside the Ottoman Empire, all of which was also &quot;historic Armenia&quot;. So, for your most recent edit, why are you deleting &quot;citizens&quot; (you seemed happy to have &quot;citizens&quot; rather than &quot;subjects&quot; when it was the old wording) and why are you deleting mention that it mostly occurred within the territory of the Ottoman Empire? There needs to be mention of where the event occurred, and ideally there should also be lede wording found that conveys the fact that the timespan of the AG extended beyond the defacto end of the Ottoman Empire and into its successor state, modern Turkey. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 20:32, 21 September 2016 (UTC)

:::::::::::::::Diranakir, I don't know whether you genuinely don't understand why citizens, Ottoman Empire ''and'' Turkey are being used, but I am sick to death of your aspersions, demands left on my talk asking me to justify something that has been discussed and qualified here for months, but please try to 'get it' this one last time. Tiptoethrutheminefield has now elaborated slightly on the section in order to make it absolutely clear that the genocide may be predominantly associated with 1915, but that year only describes the ''prominent'' year, and the total tally of victims is gleaned from a more protracted period of time, ergo the victims cannot be described as subjects of the Ottoman Empire alone. Do you comprehend now? --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 21:57, 21 September 2016 (UTC)

::::::::::::::::Harpy, you are inventing things. I did not say victims of the OE alone. That is pure fiction. Point one. Point two: you have still not acknowledged that Tiptoe's version contains a direct contradiction by having the OE carrying out Armenian extermination in its successor state, the Republic of Turkey. Apparently such a contradiction is a small matter to you and can reasonably be overlooked, but it is simply not acceptable to any responsible reader of the English language, I don't care what presumed informational burden or issues its author claims to have taken up. A shabby result.  Point three: The Ottoman-Armenian majority of the victims were emphatically 'subjects' of the Ottoman Empire. The term 'citizens' is a completely ahistorical misnomer. 
::::::::::::::::My edit simply removed the contradiction from the sentence. Except for that, the substance is essentially the same. So what's the beef?  Why can't you and Tiptoe deal with the merits of what I actually said in my edit of yesterday?  And, as to your statement, 'Tiptoethrutheminefield has now elaborated slightly on the section in order to make it absolutely clear. . . ', I see nothing new, let alone 'absolutely clear'. It is still the same old contradictory sentence. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 23:22, 21 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::Diranakir, you claim you &quot;did not say victims of the OE alone. That is pure fiction&quot;. But that is '''exactly''' what your edit did here: [ [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=739143545&amp;oldid=737306935]. Regarding &quot;citizens&quot; vs &quot;subjects&quot; - after the 1908 revolution and the empire's resulting new constitution, all the inhabitants of the Ottoman empire became, theoretically at least, &quot;equal citizens without distinction of race or religion&quot; (as one source puts it) and no longer the subjects of the Sultan. So &quot;citizens&quot; is the correct term. You offer no alternative wording to express in the lede that the timespan of the AG extended beyond the defacto end of the Ottoman Empire and into its successor state, modern Turkey. Or are you denying that it did? [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 02:27, 22 September 2016 (UTC)

:::::::::::::::::::Let's try to stay in the present. We are here discussing Harpy's arbitrary and unjustified revert of my edit here[[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Armenian_Genocide&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=740418593]. It is pure fiction that in it I refer to Ottoman Armenian victims alone. 
:::::::::::::::::::You accept at face value the reassuring words of an anonymous Ottoman spokesman that Armenians were 'citizens' after 1908. More dreaming on your part. They were Ottoman subjects until they were no more. &quot;The liquidation of 1 million Armenian subjects of the empire&quot;, is just one phrase out of many in a prominent contemporary work on the Armenian Genocide that uses the word. Using citizens would be laughable. Finally, you still do not acknowledge the contradiction in your sentence, and with Harpy's help will undoubtedly go on trying to cover it up. Groupthink over and over again. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 05:10, 22 September 2016 (UTC)

{{od|:::::::::::::::::::}}{{ec}} I'm at a loss over how to explain this any any further. I've been through multiple sources looking for whether 'subject' is appropriate in context: no, it is not; and neither is suggesting that the genocide stopped when the Ottoman Empire collapsed. I'm not claiming that there's an easy way of conveying the complexities of the period for the purposes of the lead, but creating SYNTH out of the scope it should cover is ''antithetical'' to what needs to be included in the lead. Did the persecution suddenly stop with the birth of the new nation-state known as Turkey? If that is the case, please provide the RS for this being the case and I will be more than happy for your version to be reintroduced. A million? I see, we need to change the current estimates to a million and exclude all of the sources for post-1915. Well, if that's the compromise you're willing to make. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 05:26, 22 September 2016 (UTC)

:Harpy, 'explaining further' assumes having explained at all. There is little sign of that except for the few emaciated straw men you have propped up here and there as roadblocks. Also, your readiness to give me the green light if I agree to one million is very revealing. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 21:18, 22 September 2016 (UTC)
::Oh, seriously! Do you ''really'' think that was an offer?! The [[WP:TITLE]] of this article says it all: it's not an article about the Armenian genocide which did not take place in 1915 alone. The fact that you think that I'm ready to do a deal to present misinformation is indicative of irrational thought processes on your behalf. I'm not prepared to make deals with anyone unless someone can come up with a better way to present the complexities of the entire situation. Subjects of the Ottoman Empire is non-starter, full stop. As has been pointed out to you numerous times (that is, each time you've made the same edit over a period of many weeks), that ''is'' what your edit states. Tell me what your rendition of the lead, being {{tq|&quot;'''The Armenian Genocide''', also known as the '''Armenian Holocaust''', was the Ottoman government's systematic extermination of 1.5 million Armenians, most of them subjects of the Ottoman Empire.&quot;}} means if not a [[WP:SYNTH]] rendition of a longer term genocide that covers a period of turmoil in the structure of political entities at the end of days of empires as sovereign states? I don't know how many more times you need your rendition to be quoted here by editors before you [[WP:NOTGETTINGIT|get it]]. Your change to the content is seriously flawed, and all you're able to muster as an argument in defence of a flawed description is angry accusations levelled at anyone who gets in the way of your [[WP:WIN|winning]] an indefensible piece of lack-of-description. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 04:04, 23 September 2016 (UTC)
:::My rendition in no way implies the genocide took place only in 1915. 'Most of them subjects' covers other victims in other places. This is one of your straw men. Your 'full stops' notwithstanding, the correct term is subjects when we are talking about the Ottoman Armenians. The consensus of historians on that point is obvious.
:::You mention your wish that someone could come up with a 'better way to present the complexities of the entire situation'. Certainly the present version is not the answer to your wish and mine comes closer.
:::The present version has the OE carrying out exterminations in the time of its successor state, the Republic of Turkey (successor state being a very formal term in international law). This is a direct contradiction. The advantage of my rendition is that it contains no such contradiction. 
:::Another question in regard to the present rendition is this: How does saying that the OE carried out exterminations in the time of its successor state further the presentation of 'the complexities of the entire situation'? Is that an effective way to indicate it all didn't happen just in 1915? Not at all.
:::While there may be better ways to convey the complexities of the entire situation, I think mine is better. It should also be brought to your attention that the information box at the top of the page already makes clear that the genocide was not confined to Ottoman territory. For these reasons I urge you to help resolve the serious flaw in the current version. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:48, 23 September 2016 (UTC)

 
The source for &quot;equal citizens without distinction of race or religion&quot; is not &quot;an anonymous Ottoman spokesman&quot;, it is Anahide Ter Minassian, chapter titled &quot;Van 1915&quot;, page 211, in &quot;Armenian Van / Vaspurakan&quot;, edited by Richard Hovhannisian. The same information can be found in many sources. Before the 1908 constitution all inhabitants of the Ottoman Empire were &quot;subject&quot; to an individual (the sultan), so were &quot;subjects&quot;, after 1908 the Sultan lost that status and the inhabitants (foreign nationals excepted) became citizens who were protected by the same laws regardless of race or religion. This of course made the resulting genocide even more monstrous - it was not the whim of a medieval-era despot but the product of a modernizing empire purporting to follow enlightenment ideas of liberty and democracy and the rule of law (just as its successor state, Turkey, continues to claim to follow despite all the evidence that it does not). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 15:37, 22 September 2016 (UTC)

:It is Anahide Ter Minassian describing the ideals of the ARF in the previous century. Subjects is the correct word. Your contradiction remains unresolved and a serious blemish on the article. Try rewriting it if you and Harpy insist on owning the article and blocking anything I do to resolve the problem. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:58, 22 September 2016 (UTC)
::Go take it to a RfC, that is the normal route when an editor genuinely thinks they are right and are being incorrectly opposed by article talk page consensus. Or just drop it and stop wasting everyone's time. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:08, 23 September 2016 (UTC)
::: You complained a few days ago that I had REPEATEDLY been asked to justify my position. Now that I have done so, it is apparently TOO MUCH. More of your contradictions. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 15:28, 24 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Repeatedly stating &quot;I am right&quot; is not justifying your position; repeatedly stating &quot;I want this&quot; is not justifying your position; repeatedly stating &quot;it should be subjects&quot; is not justifying your position, I have presented a source that uses &quot;citizens&quot; and I have explained the political circumstances that mean &quot;citizens&quot; is the correct term to use post-1908. You delete mention of Turkey's involvement in the AG in the lede, criticizing the wording that was used in it; yet you decline to offer any alternative wording that would retain mention of Turkey or, alternatively, explain why you think mention of Turkey should be deleted from the lede. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 15:46, 26 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::I categorically refuted your use of the source for 'citizens' above (re: Anahide Ter Minasian). It pertained to the previous century and was describing the ideals of the ARF. No answer from you. Instead you told me to stop wasting everybody's time. 
:::::Here are a couple of sources on the matter: 'The testimony of the principal authors of these mass crimes, corroborated by the evidence given by high-ranking officials and officers as well as Armenian survivors '''and other Ottoman subjects''', constitute the fullest body of information we have for a single region' (page 471, ''The Armenian Genocide: A Complete History'', Raymond Kévorkian); 'Mehmed Cavid pointed out that in 1917 he had helped restore '''the rights of Ottoman subjects''' who had disappeared more than a year earlier' (page 726, ''The Armenian Genocide: A Complete History'', Raymond Kévorkian). 
:::::Now you're doubling down with nonsense about my deleting mention of Turkey's involvement in the genocide, an absolute absurdity. I did no such thing. I eliminated the obvious contradiction that the Ottoman Empire carried out exterminations under its successor state, the Republic of Turkey. How many times does this have to be presented before you finally get the point and we can move on to a better formulation. Your stonewalling is contributing nothing to the quality of the article. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 22:39, 26 September 2016 (UTC)
Would both of you agree to avoid either terms? Both terms are are state imposed and therefor legal binding, and therefore subject to be disputed in the future. A less controversial term would be ''its Armenian population'' or ''its Armenian inhabitants'' or something of the sort. Both of you have to discuss about this without me though, I return to my long pause. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 00:59, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::Ah,  Yaḥyā, where have you been?! Sounds like a promising direction to go. Now, if we can just convince Tiptoe. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 04:19, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
:::NO, they have to be called something and citizens is sourced and is the correct definition used to define their legal status post-1908 constitution (as opposed to loose wording like &quot;subjects&quot;). Of course I understand where Yahya Talatin is coming from - there is no concept of universal &quot;citizenship&quot; in Islam - you are either a true Muslim, a slave, or to be killed as soon as is convenient. However, given that they do have to be called something, I wonder what strange alternative will be suggested? &quot;Ottomans&quot;, as in a piece of furniture? Again I am asking you, Diranakir, to take it to a RfC - but given your quickly arrived at willingness, expressed above, to drop advocating for the term &quot;subjects&quot;, I think you are just making conflict here for the sake of making conflict. The newly-acquired &quot;citizenship&quot; status of the Christian inhabitants of the Ottoman Empire was a major contributing factor behind the genocide, and was probably the primary one for the ordinary Muslim population (I can cite a Kurdish tribal leader, European educated, speaking in 1914 in an interview in Ararat magazine, stating that the result of this forced equality of status between Kurdish Muslims and Armenian Christians will be the massacre of the latter by the former because they could not live with such an outrage to their honour). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:14, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
Just a last clarification, I was not discussing which of both terms is more appropriate, because to me this is irrelevant. Neither of you two is disagreeing in essence. Reason is that both ''subject'' and ''citizen'' in this particular case convey about the same message (that Armenians were members of the Ottoman family, by force or not), both words mostly diverge on forms only. The concepts of ''citizenship'' or ''subject'' aren't necessarily exclusive. This means that just because it is sourced that they were ''subjects'' does not mean they were not ''citizens'' and vis versa. There is no explicit set of unmovable rules to place them as either exclusively one or the other. Because what is a ''citizen'' or ''subject'' is decided by authors and relies on some set of changing parameters. The controversy exist mostly because after 1908 it was still an Empire, which assumes that there was a group (Muslim-Turks) ruling on others. I think both of you should be presenting what you are willing to concede and someone else has to cut in the middle.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 17:00, 27 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::::But after 1908 the assumption of Muslim Turks ruling (by right of them being Muslim alone) over others was abolished by the 1908 constitution. The Ottoman Empire after this had a constitutional monarchy, the sultan's right to act as an absolutist monarch ended (removing most of his influence as caliph), and all the empire's citizens / subjects were now equal under the law, had voting rights that were not restricted by their religion, were taxed equally, and had the same obligations (such as conscription). So there was a material change. To me I think it is useful to use &quot;subjects&quot; before 1908, and &quot;citizens&quot; after 1908. I also think &quot;citizens&quot; more accurately defines the legal status of Ottoman Armenians in the years running up to the genocide, especially since &quot;subject&quot; carries with it the implication of subjugation.  [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 20:53, 27 September 2016 (UTC)

::::::I'm not disagreeing with you. I'm just stating that there are sources using the term ''subject'' too... with stated reasons. I am not assessing any of either, but I am understanding why each are using one term over others depending on what they are covering and why. Using citizen or subject doesn't affect in anyway the understanding of the article, for most people they mean about the same thing. But it could be argued by some that the notion of Empire contradicts with the concept of citizenship as it is understood, by its modern use and that is what caused the dissolution of the empire. This is contextual and would fit well in a section dealing with the background. But in the lede, we're not yet there because space is lacking to contextualize it.&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 22:00, 27 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:::Yahya, what happened to your idea of using 'Armenian population' or 'Armenian inhabitants'?  That seems to be gone now for some reason. And one more question: Do you find anything wrong with saying the Ottoman Empire carried out exterminations under its successor state, the Republic of Turkey? That is really the central question. [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 19:44, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::Hi Diranakir, I still maintain wordings which are constructs (such as citizens, subjects) will never achieve long term consensus. This is particularly true when those words are in the lede, where we have limited place to put things in context. I prefer not to reply regarding your question on the Republic of Turkey, because the conflict in that case arise from the way articles in general are written. I found a solution, I am working on it and will return once ready. Right now, my replies aren't constructive, because they are still tainted by my opinions. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 21:51, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::You refuse to offer any alternative wording that retains mention of Turkey. AGAIN I ask you - are you disputing that the Armenian Genocide continued after the de facto end of the Ottoman Empire's control over most of its territory. The Ottoman Empire was not responsible for massacres of Armenians in Cilicia in the post WW1 period, nor the massacres that took place during the 1920 invasion of Armenia, nor the many small scale massacres and deportations that took place throughout the territory that was still, de jure, the Ottoman Empire. These were the responsibility of the Turkish nationalist Ankara government that in 1920 had declared itself to be the government of Turkey. Are you disputing that victims of these events are part of the Armenian Genocide. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 21:07, 27 September 2016 (UTC)

:::::To Tiptoe: I asked Yahya two important questions and you jumped in. Why is that? [[User:Diranakir|Diranakir]] ([[User talk:Diranakir|talk]]) 21:32, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::Because it is not a matter of compromise between you and Tiptoethrutheminefield. Yahya Talatin has suggested a compromise and has made it clear that s/he prefers to return to watching from the sidelines. Tiptoethrutheminefield has explained his position on why the choice of citizen is the correct form. I appreciate that Yahya Talatin has tried to find a compromise to suit all, but I don't actually think it's appropriate as it suggests that the Armenians were somehow 'other' within both states, which is not the case. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 21:52, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Hi Iryna, see here [http://www.aber.ac.uk/en/media/departmental/interpol/csrv/nations%26nationalism.pdf] for instance. Fact is that even scholars such as Kamuran Gurun (mouthpiece of the Turkish government in the past) do cover such an ''other''ing. It was the thesis postulated as the reason behind the tragedy which got consensus universally and by every sides (even those who reject the thesis of genocide) since several decades of scholarship. That you interpret the wordings as meaning Armenians being ''others'' between two states further straighten my alternative. The reason I broke silence after months on that particular question is because this element is ''central'', most important point having been raised in the talkpage. I was just attempting to show that by excluding conceptual words which rely on constructs we expose a genuine consensus in the academia, regardless of the sides. Your reply and interpretation of my wording you disagree or not is sufficient.&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 23:22, 27 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
{{od|:::::::}}Hi, {{u|Yahya Talatin}}. Thanks for the link. I've only just taken a quick glimpse at it, but it looks like an interesting read. I'll get to it as I have to head out for a couple of hours. What is evident is that you're reading my use of 'other' too literally as being a postmodern 'self' and 'other' argument. I used the term simplistically to reflect my position on the context in the lead. 'Otherness' can be applied broadly to the non-ruling ethnic groups living under empires/nation-states, etc. in any epoch. In terms of the construct of the lead, such application suggests to the reader that Armenians were an enclave living outside of the laws of the OE and Turkey: that they possibly even were privy to self-governance in some form. I know it would be nice to find a less clumsy way of conveying their status, but I believe that your suggested compromise takes us further away from a satisfactory resolution. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 01:46, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
:Sorry for contaminating my reply with my opinions.
:I am wondering, does everyone agree that:

:*It happened during a transitional period, from subjects to citizens? Can this not be included very shortly, max one phrase in lede? This way the spectrum is included.

:*The major event happened during WWI and within the boundaries of the Ottoman Empire... without having to exclude what might have happened later and beyond the boundaries? 

:Can we not deal with the major-minor (majority vs minority) relationship the way it is done in music, like in a type of Chord substitution, major-minor :) Music isn't biased and it's universal... it follows natural rules, and less subjected to constructs. It has beautifully dealt with the transitioning from the natural tonal to the more human friendly major-minor transition. Beethoven found the solution in the 9th symphony 4th movement with the D minor-D major. As a matter of fact, it wasn't by accident that he chose Schiller's &quot;Ode to Joy&quot;, seems that he really found the solution for ''All men shall become brothers,'' and that ''This kiss is for the whole world!'' :)

:OK now, I really return to my pause before I go off-topic. But the above was a hint to the solution I am working on. :) [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 03:43, 28 September 2016 (UTC)

:

:


::::::::I apologize to everyone with the way I placed my replies. Feel free to move them, I just get lost with all those replies.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yahya Talatin]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yahya Talatin|contribs]]) 21:56, 27 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::::::::I fixed what I could. [[User:Yahya Talatin|Yaḥyā ‎]] ([[User talk:Yahya Talatin|talk]]) 22:00, 27 September 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:4|one external link|4 external links}} on [[Armenian Genocide]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=739369742 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.genocideeducation.org/files/A%20Brief%20History%20of%20the%20Armenian%20Genocide.pdf
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.reuters.com/article/2015/04/24/us-turkey-armenia-germany-parliament-idUSKBN0NF0Y120150424
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070926235019/http://www.freemedia.at/cms/ipi/statements_detail.html?ctxid=CH0055&amp;docid=CMS1169459655335 to http://www.freemedia.at/cms/ipi/statements_detail.html?ctxid=CH0055&amp;docid=CMS1169459655335
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070303055331/http://www.freemedia.at/cms/ipi/statements_detail.html?ctxid=CH0055&amp;docid=CMS1169459655335 to http://www.freemedia.at/cms/ipi/statements_detail.html?ctxid=CH0055&amp;docid=CMS1169459655335

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 08:22, 14 September 2016 (UTC)

== Note repetitiveness  ==

Can someone please explain why we should have '''Note 4''' when we already have '''Note 2'''? It needlessly clutters the first sentence of the article. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 16:49, 22 September 2016 (UTC)
:I'm in agreement with the removal and using the references you've left. The note was [[WP:CITEOVERKILL]]. It was a remnant of edit warring to prove a point and annoying rather than edifying. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 23:44, 23 September 2016 (UTC)
:I also agree, but this is nit picking stuff really (as is most of the recent talk page content dealing with the lede). The lede is not the main problem, I think. '''Barely 20% of this article's content details the event itself''', and we are 20% into the article's body before that small amount of content even starts, and the bulk (60% or more) of the article's content is aftermath-related material. I believe that this article is in urgent need of massive deletions and a lot of forking of content off into other articles. This article, titled as it is &quot;Armenian Genocide&quot;, should be primarily concerned with giving an account of the Armenian Genocide as it happened, of what it consisted of, and not on what peoples, countries, organisations, or individuals have post-event done with the history of, or legacy of, the Armenian Genocide. The actual content detailing the events of the Armenian Genocide is completely inadequate - there is no overall timeline given, no sense of geography, little indication of what exactly happened where and when, overemphasis of certain minor events (such as &quot;Use of poison and drug overdoses&quot;), presentation of certain events as if nobody has challenged them (the alleged mass drownings at Trebizond for example, which modern research suggest may not have happened to that scale), and very little mentioning of what happened in specific places and specific instances (despite plenty of source material being available). The article is so structurally wrong it is hard to know where to begin to start repairing it (maybe that is why most of our attention has been focused on the more easily handled lede) - but I suggest we start by removing or condensing material that is not directly concerned with the core subject. [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 14:44, 24 September 2016 (UTC)

::I'm particularly concerned about the Portrayal in the media section which is unnecessarily long, and filled with trivial stuff that should be deleted. But it should be done in a orderly and systematic fashion. Proposals concerning which part should be deleted must be brought forth and decided upon accordingly. [[User:EtienneDolet|Étienne Dolet]] ([[User talk:EtienneDolet|talk]]) 17:22, 25 September 2016 (UTC)

:::Addressing the lead, I find the elaboration on the death marches to be too protracted and detailed. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 21:23, 27 September 2016 (UTC)

== General Improvements ==

[[User:Fairchia|Fairchia]] ([[User talk:Fairchia|talk]]) 00:21, 2 November 2016 (UTC) This article as a whole is solid, with a multitude of unbiased viewpoints and facts backed by sources on multiple aspects of the genocide. Even the pictures provided assisted in providing a visual aid to the atrocities committed during this time period. An improvement could be to add a segment on Turkey's thought process on being able to commit these crimes under the falsehood of war. Turkey believed that it was justified in the genocide not only in ethical considerations but also that it was war, and certain occurrences happen. Another improvement could be to provide a generalized timeline to put in to reference the major historical events that occurred.</text>
      <sha1>4d6uvcrjsd82w8y7z1a3b8h4y8rkdv3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
