<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Repatriation of Cossacks after World War II</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3922066</id>
    <revision>
      <id>697898476</id>
      <parentid>692303313</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-02T17:45:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RichardBond</username>
        <id>7246295</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>New talk section: Vladimir D'Arbeloff</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52697">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=27 September 2007
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=160578121
|currentstatus=FGAN
|topic=history
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=c|attention=yes
|B-Class-1= no
|B-Class-2= yes
|B-Class-3= yes
|B-Class-4= yes
|B-Class-5= yes
|British=y|Russian=y|WWII=y|German=y}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=C|importance=Mid|hist=yes|mil=yes}}
{{WikiProject Soviet Union|class=C|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class=C|importance=Mid}}}}
{{controversial}}

- This article presents a POV - namely, that British and American allies were at fault for repatriating Cossacks to Russia. It doesn't present any basis for that claim. Moreover, it doesn't substantiate the claim that Cossack civilians who weren't complicit in service for Nazi Germany were prosecuted in Soviet Union. There are other evidence that suggests that, while cossack men (traitors and war criminals) were indeed punished and in many cases exterminated, women and children went through the same filtration system as other Soviet citizens who were repatriated after the war.    &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/79.183.251.198|79.183.251.198]] ([[User talk:79.183.251.198|talk]]) 14:05, 20 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Untitled==
To me it is a story of one particular formation of cossacks who were nothing else but Nazi collaborators [ This is partisan ranting and not helpful - does the author include all the thousands of women and children raped and massacred by the Soviets in this?] . The brutality of Stalin's regime is undisputed, but the story is about the capture and , yes, transfer to Stalin, a group of people who killed Jews, Russians, Bellorusians, Ukrainians, Poles and Slovenians. I have no pitty for them at all. KS 

To be blunt, what you think doesn't matter. 
(1) The sources in question allege that the 'relevant' Cossacks included significant numbers of civilians and non-combatants. 

(2) Decossackization entailed massive pogroms against the Cossack people, and Stalin's campaigns against the Cossacks and peasantry is a history of genocide that rivals--if NOT EXCEEDS--the Shoa. Therefore, even those Cossacks who collaborated with the Nazis have at least *understandable* reasons for doing so. Let us take, in the Western imagination, the most moral state on Earth: Israel, and look at some of its bedfellows, hmm? What if we were to judge it by some of the more sordid allies it has found in its quest for survival (rabid Christian militias, dissident Arab extremists, etc)? Your reasoning is invalid, and your lack of 'pitty'--can be written off as either crass ignorance of the topic or simple callousness towards people you do not understand and have never met. 

(3) Thirdly, your suggestion that the Cossacks at Lienz et al, were involved in ethnic banditry during the chaos of the 10's-20's evinces a shallow understanding of who the Cossacks are, and ideas of 'ethnic culpability' in general. Consider--do I go on articles regarding the Shoa and tell everyone that I have no 'pitty' for the Yidden because of mongrels like Iagoda, Fritz Haber, and Salomen Morel?--no. Decisions, right or wrong, are made by an individual and depend on personal circumstance--if a Cossack is implicated in a pogrom, innocent Cossack emigres that just barely escaped genocide in their own country shouldn't have to suffer for it.

Please understand the material before spewing your contempt all over the internet. 


Let me assure you that I am well-aware of the subject as a grandson of Kuban cossack family half of which was &quot;decossacked&quot; and the other half was fighting nazies on eastern front. I am not being &quot;ignorant&quot; or &quot;spreading contempt&quot; for that matter. Quite to the contrary, I am saying that this is a controversial subject and offering my own view point which anyone has a right to. And it respectuflly remains my opinion that the cossacks who comitted war crimes in Poland, Slovakia, Yugoslavia and Ukraine and collaborated with Nazies deserved no better faith. That said, civilians being killed by Soviet troops is a disgrace. But there is no justification for those who fought against partizans and Warsaw uprisers. There is an article on wikipedia entitled Nazi Collaborators. If you read it, you will know that people had no pitty (and that the word i used) for such collaborators across europe and many were executed by the people on public squares at the time. would you call these mass murders? Also, since you mentioned Israel, let me say (as someone who is intimately familiar with Israel and has a large family over there) that the term &quot;betrayal&quot; of Nazi collaborators does not fly well in that country as there are people who actually suffered from these collaborators and will never change their opinion. Same applies to Polish and former Yugoslavian people's perception and collective memory. Let me suggest that French ressistance fighters would do exactly the same to these cossacks if they got into their hands at the end of the war. I hope you are not suggesting double standards here. Again, the death of the civilians is a different story and reflects Stalin's policy of total extermination of the enemies, which cannot be justified. And to be completely blunt, let me perhaps suggest that what I think does actually matter (as does your point of view as well as the one of others as this is what dispute page is for), even if you may not like it. Sincerely, KS


You're still an idiot who cannot spell 'pity' correctly. Even so, your response is a web of equivocations where you attempt to equate Cossacks fighting for Cossackdom with Nazi purists. Perhaps people didn't have pity for them. Ignorant people are always sparing with their pity, true. But even people who collaborated--from the most vile Kapo (Jews who collaborated by taking jobs in prison camps and occupied ghettos)--deserve to have their point of view understood. We are discussing one of the most extreme periods in human history, and a heavy-handed moralism is not helpful to real historiography.

Would I call them 'mass murders'? Uh, yeah: they were murders en mass, that's pretty much the definition of mass murder. This wouldn't happen anywhere in the civilized world today. Even to the Nuremberg prisoners--the most authentic Nazis in Germany--we gave these people a real trial. 

You're rewriting history by assuming what the French resistance fighters would do, and its incredibly annoying. Editors like you have no place in the wikiverse. CB 

CB, 

Nobody gave you a right to call anyone an &quot;idiot&quot;. I am not even getting angry but the low level of your rethorics make me think you are not worth arguing with. Expressions like &quot;to be blunt what you think doesn't matter&quot; do speak to your level of intelligence, which i will leave to others to comment. Your degrading to personal level is highly, hum, what would be the right word, unprofessional at the best. 

As to my point and your emotions apart, yes, these Cossacks (the active adult part of them, at least) are indeed Nazi collaborators. Like it or not. How they got there is a different story. And yes, they should have deserved a trial. Too bad there was none (fair and open) in Stalin's USSR). Their armed fighting on the side of Hitler does make them Allies' enemies. They are not a friendly force by any measurement.

I am not sure what your analogy with &quot;French resistance fighters&quot; was supposed to mean. Whatever that was, I have high respect for these people, who are forever remembered for their courage and determination in France and elsewhere. So at a minimum I should take your analogy as a compliment. 

May I suggest that yourself, for all your calling me names, ridiculing my arguments and myself personally have no right to be in the wikiverse. And well-redone article as it stands now. Whoever did the final editing, changed the name of the article and re-wrote the content, deserves a credit. 


KS  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.73.27.140|74.73.27.140]] ([[User talk:74.73.27.140|talk]]) 03:47, 15 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

 


&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by 
[[Special:Contributions/72.229.118.156|72.229.118.156]] ([[User talk:72.229.118.156|talk]]) 18:31, 19 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==This article is already neutral and fair - read the research and see for yourself==
The relevant research has been comprehensively undertaken by Count Nikolai Tolstoy-Miloslavksy, a descendant of Count Lev Tolstoy, the famous writer.

Count Tolstoy's research is painstaking and meticulous and cites all sources very extensively and fully, taking them from government files in the West and now from the Soviet Union files. No-one has written a satisfactory rebuttal of his research nor, indeed, any rebuttal at all.

The Libel action brought by Lord Aldington in 1989 against Count Tolstoy and Mr Watts concerned a pamphlet circulated by Mr Watts and did not relate to any of Count Tolstoy's books which have never - repeat never - been challenged in the courts.

It is quite clear that the Cossacks were, indeed, betrayed and that largely by officials of the British government, particularly some in the Foreign Office. It is also quite clear that the Foreign Office illegally ordered the return to the Soviet Union of a very large number of Cossack and other emigres, knowing that they would be shot or imprisoned but also knowing that this would partially appease Stalin. British Special Forces units were tasked with the hand-over and witnessed many Cossacks and emigres being shot by the NKVD.

It is probable that this may have been a secret arrangement concluded at or after Yalta by Soviet-friendly officials in the British government, since British officialdom was, at that time, heavily infiltrated by fellow-travellers and others sympathetic to the Soviet Union, like the spies and traitors, Burgess, Philby and McLean. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:84.71.45.151|84.71.45.151]] ([[User talk:84.71.45.151|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/84.71.45.151|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

These men were serving the enemy of their own state during war. Women and children were non-combatants, but they were Soviet citizens. I fail to see how handing them over to their own state can be considered illegal. On the other hand, according to the laws of virtually any country at the time, defecting to the enemy and fighting against your own state was treason, and punishable by death.
The facts may be accurate, but the whole slant of the article, starting with the title, is one of the most POV I have ever seen. Glad it did not make a good article. I'll consider renaming it to something like &quot;Fate of Cossack Soviet Citizens Serving the Enemy in WWII&quot;.
[[User:212.216.210.234|212.216.210.234]] 07:11, 5 October 2007 (UTC)

:I strongly oppose naming it &quot;Fate of Cossack Soviet Citizens Serving the Enemy in WWII&quot;. For one the title is confusing and misleading.  It implies that all of the Cossacks and other ethnic Russians that were &quot;repatriated&quot; were Soviet Citizens, which many were not according to most, if not all, historians.  Many left before the Russian Revolution and were never Soviet citizens.  Secondly, the phrase &quot;Serving the Enemy&quot; is confusing.  Whose enemy, the Soviets' enemy? (that could be the U.S.) the Allies' enemy? (that could be Japan?) In this situation you have to look at it from a different view than Axis vs. Allies because the Cossacks that  fought against the Soviet Union did not consider themselves as part of the Axis. They did not consider the United States, Great Britain, Canada, and other Allied powers their enemies.  I think if this title is seriously going to be changed, it would need to be something similar to &quot;Cossack Repatriations of World War II&quot;. ~ &lt;font color=&quot;339900&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Joe [[user:Jklin|&lt;small&gt;Jklin&lt;/small&gt;]] '''('''&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jklin|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Jklin|C]]&lt;/small&gt;''')'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 12:58, 5 October 2007 (UTC)

I frankly doubt that most of the Cossacks were not Soviet citizens, and would like to see these &quot;most historians&quot; stating that. We're talking about many thousands of persons. Maybe a handful of the officers had lived for twenty years in France and other countries, certainly not the bulk of the men.
As to who is the enemy, it is not as ambiguous as you think. It's the enemy of their state, pretty much straightforward. Their state was at war with Germany, they served Germany, they served the enemy. That also applies to the other distinctions you make; when one takes orders from Germany in WWII, it's quite pointless that he considers himself &quot;not at war&quot; with Germany's enemies, such as the United States etc. It's a war and there is no halfway point. I suppose it's possible the British volunteers who served in the SS might have not considered themselves at war with their own country, but only with the USSR, for instance; they were still objectively serving the enemy.
Having said that, yes, Cossack Repatrations would still be much much better than the current POV title.
[[User:212.216.210.221|212.216.210.221]] 13:17, 5 October 2007 (UTC)

:Here is good reference to most historians stating that most of the Cossacks were not Soviet citizens [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0037-6779(197512)34%3A4%3C823%3AOKTSOF%3E2.0.CO%3B2-0 JSTOR]. It is a review of two works about the forced repatriations or &quot;Operation Keelhaul&quot;.  One work is &quot;Operation Keelhaul: The Story of Forced Repatriation from 1944 to the Present. by [[Julius Epstein]], Bertram D. Wolfe&quot; Julius Epstein is considered a leading authority on the subject. The other work is &quot;The Last Secret: The Delivery to Stalin of over Two Million Russians by Britain and the United States. by [[Nicholas Bethell]], Hugh Trevor-Roper&quot;. There are many other references to this fact by historians, politicians, and authors.  If many of these people were not Soviet citizens then the enemy question becomes more ambiguous. The Soviet Union was not there state so they could be at war with any number of people.  I am still seeking out a title that is completely NPOV but am having trouble. As is stated below, Cossack Repatriations implies that they were Soviet citizens, which we have discussed.  Lienz cossacks has been considered but it makes it seem as though Lienz was their [[host (Cossack)|host]]. So I am trying to find some scholarly articles using neutral names but it is tough as the author is usually slanted one way. If you were curious, I named the article because that is the name of the famous painting of the event in Lienz and is therefore what I grew up knowing it as.~ &lt;font color=&quot;339900&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Joe [[user:Jklin|&lt;small&gt;Jklin&lt;/small&gt;]] '''('''&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jklin|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Jklin|C]]&lt;/small&gt;''')'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:29, 5 October 2007 (UTC)

Yeah, I saw that. That fact alone should tell you how absurdly steeped in POV the title and the article are. It's like writing an article about the Nazi party and titling it &quot;Triumph of the Will&quot;. Propaganda art seldom is NPOV. But maybe you are too emotionally involved to write a NPOV article about this subject.[[User:212.216.211.250|212.216.211.250]] 08:06, 24 October 2007 (UTC)

'''Tolstoy cannot be used as a reliable historical source for Wikipedia. His claims were found by a court of law to be defamatory.''' 'Having accused Lord Aldington of being a &quot;major war criminal&quot;, responsible for the deaths of up to 70,000 Cossacks and Yugloslavs handed over to the Communists in 1945, Tolstoy was found to have committed defamation. Over the years the trial was in preparation, much new evidence devastating to the Tolstoy &quot;conspiracy&quot; thesis has been gathered.' (Alistair Horne, ''Macmillan'' (1988), p. 285). [[Special:Contributions/129.67.174.46|129.67.174.46]] ([[User talk:129.67.174.46|talk]]) 12:54, 17 September 2008 (UTC)

British defamation laws are totally lame. You can't invalidate a source just because of a British Court. Nation-states do not define the truth. As a Soviet refugee (and a Jew, and an anarchist) I can still say that deporting anyone to the Soviet Union may not be &quot;illegal&quot; but is certainly deeply immoral, namely because it caused death and suffering. Churchill and Roosevelt sold out all of Eastern Europe and if the Cossacks had it bad, how about the Poles! They fought both sides. I am in favor of incorporating this article with Operation Keelhaul  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.239.178.33|128.239.178.33]] ([[User talk:128.239.178.33|talk]]) 01:10, 19 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


I would agree that, as it stands (Dec 2009) the article at least tries to be fair. BUT IT HAS NO REAL SOURCES. If you click on the various footnotes, you generally end up at some webpage or other, whose information is verified by – exactly nothing. One is a book review (in Italian) of a book called, the Cossacks in Italy. Another appears to be a Soviet style source describing the massacre in Krasnodar, with a sidebar on the Cossacks in Italy. Neither source is vouched for by anything. Another, major source for the article seems to be an article posted on the Future of Freedom Foundation, which is itself based on other sources, that is, the writer of this article has chosen an account that accords with his or her ideological prejudices, hence, not a valid source. I would say, this needs to be scrapped and started again, basing its structure on the different points of view. As it stands, though it tries hard, it's basically junk history, not even up to History Channel standards. [[User:Theonemacduff|Theonemacduff]] ([[User talk:Theonemacduff|talk]]) 20:07, 17 December 2009 (UTC)

==POV==

Although to me a cossack, this is a touching piece, I must urge for it to be NPOVed. You must remember that at the same time hunderds of thousands of ethnic Cossacks fought for the Red Army against the nazis whether being in Cossack regiments or in others, and the tone that this article sets for how our motherland is portrayed is unacceptable and if I was more skeptical I would have given this article a thorough filtering. However since it is unfinished, I shall wait for a while and urge the author to NPOV and expand the section... The whole of my family fought for my motherland in Cossack regiments. --[[User:Kuban kazak|Kuban kazak]] 16:23, 1 February 2006 (UTC)

The article needs a new title or should be merged with [[Operation Keelhaul]] article. [[User:Fisenko|Fisenko]] 17:09, 14 February 2006 (UTC)
:This article definitely needs a new title because the word 'betrayal' is strongly pov. --[[User:Tomato|Tomato]] 02:21, 15 June 2006 (UTC)

I agree that this article needs some more NPOVing but am finding it difficult to do myself because of my personal feelings towards these events.  It definetly needs a new title but I can't think of one.  It could be merged with Operation Keelhaul as they are essentially the same thing but from different POV (one from a British, the other from a Soviet refugee).  I thought of adding something about the Red  Army but didn't think it should be added to this article because it was dealing solely with those Cossacks that fought for the White Army, as they were the ones that were handed over.
--[[User:Jklin|Jklin]] 05:27, 21 February 2006 (UTC)

:White army and Red army in sense of the Russian civil war? Then that is rather irrelevant, except for those people who fought twice against the Soviet Union. Now I am talking about those Cossacks who, once their land has been occupied made the choice of collaborating. This article should clearly mention that they only compromised a minority, that most Cossacks fought for the Red Army (athough the majority did not fight in Cossack regiments, that is true). Finally it should also mention the 1950s pardon of the Soviet Govenment.--[[User:Kuban kazak|Kuban Cossack]] 09:50, 21 February 2006 (UTC)

== Not Soviet citizens? ==

Having read [[Pyotr Krasnov]] I suggest the assertion here that he was never a Soviet citizen is incorrect. He was taken prisoner during the Kerensky-Junker plot and was then released after promising &quot;never to do it again&quot;. A promise he broke almost immediately.

On the other hand, the Shkuro case is different. As I suppose will be the case with many others.

Many of these people committed heinous war crimes, not necessarily in the Soviet Union (Yugoslavia comes to mind, and the Warsaw Uprising). Which does not mean that one crime deserves another, but puts things into perspective. --pgp 12:23, 24 March 2006 (UTC)

He was taken prisoner during the Kerensky-Junker plot. And ? Do you suggest that he became a Soviet citizen in the process ? This makes absolutely no sense. You simply don't understand how much people like Pyotr Krasnov hated everything Soviet. He still remained a citizen of the Russian Empire, even though it was no more.
[[User:Mitekphoto|wingedhorse]] ([[User talk:Mitekphoto|talk]]) 01:45, 18 March 2011 (UTC)

== The POV! It's Blinding! ==

Pretty POV. Still, it covers an interesting aspect of the policy of forced soviet repatriation in the aftermath of the second world war. I'd recomend deleting the sensationlist parts, citing sources carefully, and using hard numbers rather than generalizations. I'll try to launch into a little bit of cleanup, but I suspect the  big cleanup guns are going to have to come from our cyrillic reading wikipedians who have more plentiful access to specific sources.

--[[User:Irongaard|Irongaard]] 02:59, 7 April 2006 (UTC)

I agree, the POV is blinding.[[User:212.216.211.250|212.216.211.250]] 08:06, 24 October 2007 (UTC)

== POV ==

: If over one million people of Soviet nationality served with or in the German army one can't speak of a minority. In March 1943 they were numbering already apprx. 430.000 men which joined the German army voluntary. A great part of them were Cossacks. To be read in &quot;Cossacks in the German army&quot; 1991 by Samuel J. Newland, U.S. Army War College:
&quot;When the German 14th Panzer Corps moved into the vicinity of the River Mius, during mid-October 1941, they were surprised to find an engagement in progress behind the Red Army's front line. They found not German troops but a Russian militia unit had attacked the Soviet Army from the rear. The militia group was commanded by 1st Lietenant Nicholas Nazarenko, a Don Cossack..(p.90). On August 22, 1941, with the war only two month old, the entire 436 Soviet Regiment defected to the Germans. The defection was led by Major Ivan Nikitch Kononov, a Don Cossack...(p.92). Kononow was later commanding as Colonel the Plastunbrigade in the XV.-Cossack-Cavallery-Korps in the Wehrmacht. Not to forget about General Vlassov with his Army of Liberation.
All this facts needs to be considered when as suggested the article needs &quot;thourough filtering&quot; and NPOV.--[[User:Bargen|Bargen]] 12:28, 9 April 2006 (UTC)
::''Voluntary''...well the bulk of the collaborators were Vlasovites, Soviet POWs faced with either to die (since Holocaust was not really limited to the Jews, and Soviet POWs were not treated any more humane then they were) or to join the ROA, or wait and be faced with a question:  &quot;Why are you not dead?&quot; by the NKVD. Cossacks read the article 50,000. ... As for the 436th regiment...well if you follow the Soviet order of battle then a regiment can number between 500 up 2000 men depending on what the regiment is. Still quite far away from 430 000. Then if you include Ukrainian, Estonian, Latvian and other nationalist collaborators, those did join voluntary then that is a believable figure... until then please do not feed BS by some random author who lived on a different continet.--[[User:Kuban kazak|Kuban Cossack]] [[Image:Romanov Flag.svg|25px|]] 14:53, 9 April 2006 (UTC)
: Wrong, the bulk were Soviet origin. In the &quot;XV. Cossack Cavalery Corps&quot; apprx. 25.000 Cossacks were serving. Wlassow's so called Army of Liberation only came in action in February 1945 and changed side again already beginning of May in Praque.
::Prague not Praque, and 25 000 is nowhere near 430 000... Which preatty matches the Soviet figures and our Cossack ones. You are forgetting however about the nearlly millions of Cossack descendents who took arms for their motherland and fought in ALL military branches of the Worker Peasent Red Army and Red Fleet. --[[User:Kuban kazak|Kuban Cossack]] [[Image:Romanov Flag.svg|25px|]] 14:48, 14 April 2006 (UTC)
By the way Samuel J. Newland is a member of the US Army War College teaching faculty and the Academic Officer for the Department of Corresponding studies. You should read his book on the Cossacks. --[[User:Bargen|Bargen]] 09:56, 14 April 2006 (UTC)
::Yes...US Army, what makes him an expert--[[User:Kuban kazak|Kuban Cossack]] [[Image:Romanov Flag.svg|25px|]] 14:48, 14 April 2006 (UTC)
:::Kuban, perhaps displaying a bit of respect for non-Soviet sources would be appropriate. [[User:Jtpaladin|Jtpaladin]] 01:13, 13 November 2006 (UTC)

== New Title proposal ==

Since it seems to be agreed that this article needs a new title, how about ''Cossacks after WWII''.  Most of this information could be transferred there and more information about cossacks that fought for the allies could be added.  This would also get rid of the POV title and give an opportunity to further NPOV the article in the move.--&lt;font color=&quot;ff6633&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Joe [[user:Jklin|&lt;small&gt;Jklin&lt;/small&gt;]] '''('''&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jklin|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Jklin|C]]&lt;/small&gt;''')'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 04:07, 15 June 2006 (UTC)
:Strong oppose. Cossacks after WWII is a direct insult to millions of Cossack descendents who fought in the Red Army ranks. This article deals with a single group of those people and should be mentioned. I propose that it be moved to Lienz Cossacks, as that is directely relevant title and has been applied several times in English--[[User:Kuban kazak|Kuban Cossack]] [[Image:Romanov Flag.svg|25px|]] 09:42, 15 June 2006 (UTC)
::: It looks like the word 'betrayal' comes from Tolstoy's book and thus it can't be considered an accepted scholarly name of these events. Other possible variants are &quot;Post-WW2 Cossack repatriations&quot;, &quot;Lienz Cossack repatriation&quot;, &quot;Post-WW2 Cossack transfer&quot; and &quot;Lienz Cossack transfer&quot;. [[User:Alaexis|Alæxis]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User_talk:Alaexis|¿question?]]&lt;/sub&gt; 11:27, 20 July 2007 (UTC)

::That is why I mentioned that information about cossacks that fought for the allies (which includes the Red Army) would need to be included in the article.  Currently the only mention that I can find of cossacks after or during WWII is [[Cossacks#Cossacks after the Russian Revolution|here]]. I just think it's a chance to mention the cossack's parts on both sides of WWII--&lt;font color=&quot;ff6633&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Joe [[user:Jklin|&lt;small&gt;Jklin&lt;/small&gt;]] '''('''&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jklin|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Jklin|C]]&lt;/small&gt;''')'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 18:44, 15 June 2006 (UTC)

:::How about &quot;Forced return of Cossacks after WWII&quot;? &quot;Forced repatriation of Cossacks after WWII&quot; might be clearer, but would tend to imply that they were all Soviet citizens. [[User:Jbhood|Jbhood]] 07:27, 5 October 2007 (UTC)

::::I think that the title is fine.  The problem is the sub-titles.  It seems to me to br wrong to imply that the betrayal was at a single camp, or two camps, and that it was a betrayal by Britain.  Both major allied agreed with the USSR to return all cossacks.  America is as guilty as Britain.  Ultimately we must remember that Uncle Joe was the villain of the piece.[[Special:Contributions/124.197.15.138|124.197.15.138]] ([[User talk:124.197.15.138|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 05:25, 28 May 2009 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

As you can see, this was a difficult article to name when I created it. I took the title from the painting by S.G.Korolkoff for those that are wondering. While the title does appear to be POV it has been used by others, including [[Andrew Roberts]] and [[Colonel Chessernoff]]. I  don't like &quot;Lienz Cossacks&quot; or similar titles because that implies that they were from a Lienz host or something when in actuality they were Don Cossacks and Kuban Cossacks. I'll keep looking for scholarly titles.~ &lt;font color=&quot;339900&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Joe [[user:Jklin|&lt;small&gt;Jklin&lt;/small&gt;]] '''('''&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jklin|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Jklin|C]]&lt;/small&gt;''')'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 13:10, 5 October 2007 (UTC)

==move to Operation Keelhaul?==

Maybe this should be moved to operation keelhaul, just under the sub title of &quot;Cossacks.&quot;

:'''Strong Oppose''' as the Cossack story is far greater than the story of Operation Keelhaul. Also this article is still fairly POV on what is a very sensitive subject. Rgds, - [[User:Trident13|Trident13]] 11:09, 13 November 2006 (UTC)

I consider that this article should be merged with &quot;Operation Keelhaul&quot; and the resulting article should be rewritten in a more NPOV style. The main problem is to determine exactly what was the scope of Operation Keelhaul. Was it just forcible repatriation of cossacks of [[XVth Cossack Cavalry Corps]] who in May 1945 were in a camp near Lienz or was it forcible repatriation of all Soviet (and Yugoslav) citizens from Western Germany ans Austria? 

It seems to me that the former is true. Then the resulting article should be rewritten accordingly and, probably, another article &quot;Forcible Repatriation of Soviet and Yugoslav Citizens in 1945&quot; should be created.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Olegwiki|Olegwiki]] ([[User talk:Olegwiki|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Olegwiki|contribs]]) 12:54, 26 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Actually it was all ethnic Russians that were repatriated, including women, children, and elderly.~ '''&lt;font color=&quot;#800000&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Joe [[user:Jklin|&lt;small&gt;Jklin&lt;/small&gt;]] '''('''&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jklin|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Jklin|C]]&lt;/small&gt;''')'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;
''' 17:50, 30 October 2007 (UTC)

==AndyZ peerreviewer==
The following suggestions were generated by a semi-automatic [[User:AndyZ/peerreviewer|javascript program]], and might not be applicable for the article in question.
*Per [[Wikipedia:Only make links that are relevant to the context|Wikipedia:Context]] and [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (dates and numbers)|Wikipedia:Manual of Style (dates)]], months and days of the week generally should not be linked. Years, decades, and centuries can be linked if they provide [[WP:CONTEXT|context]] for the article.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#contxt|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#contxt|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*Per [[Wikipedia:What is a featured article?]], [[WP:IMAGE|Images]] should have concise captions.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#caption|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#caption|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*&lt;s&gt;There may be an applicable [[WP:INFOBOX|infobox]] for this article. For example, see [[Template:Infobox Biography]], [[Template:Infobox School]], or [[Template:Infobox City]].&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#infobox|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#infobox|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt; (Note that there might not be an applicable infobox; remember that these suggestions are not generated manually)&lt;/s&gt;
*There are a few occurrences of [[weasel word]]s in this article- please observe [[WP:AWT]]. Certain phrases should specify exactly who supports, considers, believes, etc., such a view.
**''is considered''
**might be weasel words, and should be provided with proper [[WP:FOOTNOTE|citations]] (if they already do, or are not weasel terms, please &lt;strike&gt;strike&lt;/strike&gt; this comment).&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#awt|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;!--This javascript cannot determine if a citation is provided; if all weasel terms are covered by citations, please strike this--&gt;
*Watch for [[User:Tony1/How_to_satisfy_Criterion_2a#Redundancy|redundancies]] that make the article too wordy instead of being crisp and concise. (You may wish to try Tony1's [[User:Tony1/How to satisfy Criterion 1a: redundancy exercises|redundancy exercises]].)
**Vague terms of size often are unnecessary and redundant -  “some”, “a variety/number/majority of”, “several”, “a few”, “many”, “any”, and “all”. For example, “&lt;font color='red'&gt;&lt;s&gt;All&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/font&gt; pigs are pink, so we thought of &lt;font color='red'&gt;&lt;s&gt;a number of&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/font&gt; ways to turn them green.”
*This article needs [[WP:FOOTNOTE|footnotes]], preferably in the [http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php cite.php] format recommended by [[WP:WIAFA]]. Simply, enclose inline citations, with [[WP:CITE]] or [[WP:CITE/ES]] information, with &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;THE FOOTNOTE&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;. At the bottom of the article, in a section named “References” or “Footnotes”, add &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;&lt;references/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#foot|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#foot|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*Please ensure that the article has gone through a thorough copyediting so that it exemplifies some of [[WP:WIAFA|Wikipedia's best work]]. See also [[User:Tony1/How to satisfy Criterion 1a]].&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#copyedit|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#copyedit|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
You may wish to browse through [[User:AndyZ/Suggestions]] for further ideas. Thanks, ~ &lt;font color=&quot;339900&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Joe [[user:Jklin|&lt;small&gt;Jklin&lt;/small&gt;]] '''('''&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jklin|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Jklin|C]]&lt;/small&gt;''')'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 22:00, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

== Problem with location ==

This seems inconsistent with the article on [[Andrey Vlaslov]] which does not indicate that he was ever in the United States.

=== Other locations ===

==== Fort Dix, New Jersey, United States ====
While this event is often viewed as occurring only on European soil, it also occurred across the Atlantic Ocean at [[Fort Dix]], New Jersey. [[Andrey Vlasov]], a man who repeatedly voiced objections against Nazism and communism, was one of the men captured by American forces. His conversation with his American captor was described by [[Sven Steenberg]] in his book '' &quot;Wlassow - Verräter oder Patriot?&quot;''&lt;blockquote&gt; He began to speak, at first slowly and dispassionately, but then with growing intensity. For one last time, he spoke of all the prospects, hopes, and disappointments of his countrymen. He summed up everything for which countless Russians had fought and suffered. It was no longer really to the American that he was addressing himself — this was rather a confession, a review of his life, a last protest against the destiny that had brought him to a wretched end.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. Vlasov stated that the leaders of the ROA were ready to appear before an international court, but that it would be a monumental injustice to turn them over to the Soviets and thereby to certain death. It was not a question of volunteers who had served the Germans, but of a political organization, of a broad opposition movement which, in any event, should not be dealt with under military law.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Andrey Vlasov was hanged [[August 2]], [[1946]] for &quot;treason as well as active espionage and terrorist activity against the Soviet Union.&quot;

[[User:Roadrunner|Roadrunner]] 03:34, 21 February 2007 (UTC)


The reference at the end of the section states - Some of this dirty work even took place on American soil. Epstein describes what happened to Russian POWs who were imprisoned at Fort Dix, New Jersey:

:::First, they refused to leave their barracks when ordered to do so...

Andrey Vlasov — the man who hated communism — the man who hated Nazism — carefully explained his position and reasoning to the American generals.

So it seems as though he might have been there, I do not know personally. However, Russian POWs were held at Fort Dix, New Jersey so the section should stay (which I'll add back) the Vlasov issue should be looked further into though.--&lt;font color=&quot;#228B22&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;comic sans MS&quot; size=+1&gt;Iosef &lt;sup&gt;'''[[user:Iosef|&lt;small&gt;U&lt;/small&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Iosef|T]] [[Special:Contributions/Iosef|C]]'''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 14:57, 21 February 2007 (UTC)

==NPOV tag==
Its been there for ages, I see no reason for continuing to hold it... the controversy tag on the talk page is sufficient IMO...--[[User:Kuban kazak|Kuban Cossack]] 12:59, 30 April 2007 (UTC)

== Remove Fort Dix again ==

According to the Vlasov article and every work that I know of, Vlasov was never in the United States.  He was held by the Americans in Europe.

[[User:Roadrunner|Roadrunner]] 21:53, 9 August 2007 (UTC)

==Failed &quot;good article&quot; nomination==
This article failed [[WP:GAN|good article nomination]]. This is how the article, as of September 28, 2007, compares against the  [[Wikipedia:What is a good article?|six good article criteria]]:

:'''1. Well written?:''' [[Image:Symbol unsupport vote.svg|15px]] Alongside a general need to review the article per the [[WP:MOS|Manual of Style]], the [[WP:LEAD|introduction]] is not a concise overview of the entire article. Things such as the simple statistics need to be included, mostly as part of asserting the notability of the event in an obvious way. The article in general does a poor job of [[WP:OBVIOUS|stating the obvious]], and needs better transitions between paragraphs and topics.
:'''2. Factually accurate?:''' [[Image:Symbol unsupport vote.svg|15px]] The article has a common problem, which is that it has a basic modicum of good sources but suffers from proper inline citations to those sources. A cite at the end of each paragraph and for quotations is the bare minimum. Citations to any fact likely to be challenged (see [[WP:V]]) is desirable, especially for a &quot;good article&quot;. Every section now present in the article requires more thorough citations.
:'''3. Broad in coverage?:''' [[Image:Symbol support vote.svg|15px]] The article would seem to cover all of the major points of interest in a focused way. The Aftermath section could do with some expansion however.
:'''4. Neutral point of view?:''' [[Image:Symbol unsupport vote.svg|15px]] This is most egregious violation of the [[WP:QFC|quick-fail criteria]] in the article. Without solid references verifying that the incident is called the &quot;Betrayal of the Cossacks&quot; by a clear-cut majority of significant published sources, it is a clearly non-neutral thing to call the incident a betrayal. I'm not suggesting that this is necessarily impossible or untrue, but without proper attribution it is not kosher. I suggest that if no sources verifying this are provided, then the article be renamed to &quot;Status of the Cossacks following World War II&quot; or the like. This states a little more clearly the &quot;what&quot; and &quot;when&quot; of the event, without making a moral judgment. Other areas where there is also obviously non-neutral treatment are rampant in the introduction and body of the article. Attribution of statements which are similar to &quot;...many innocent people -- ones who never fought against the Allies -- were handed over as well.&quot; might result in a more acceptable article, though toning down the partisan language is still necessary.
:'''5. Article stability?''' [[Image:Symbol support vote.svg|15px]] Not the subject of any major on-going conflicts.
:'''6. Images?:''' [[Image:Symbol support vote.svg|15px]] Present and accounted for with proper licenses and fair-use rationales.

As the article meets one or more of the [[WP:QFC|quick-fail criteria]], I have failed it without a hold period for minor improvements.

When these issues are addressed, the article can be [[Wikipedia:Good article nominations|renominated]].  If you feel that this review is in error, feel free to take it to a [[Wikipedia:Good article reassessment|Good article reassessment]].  Thank you for your work so far.&lt;!-- Template:FGAN --&gt; 
— [[User:VanTucky|'''Van&lt;span style=&quot;color:#FF4F00&quot;&gt;Tucky&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:VanTucky|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:25, 28 September 2007 (UTC)

:I agree with some points. I just tried to remove ''labeling all Cossacks as &quot;pro-Nazi&quot;'' in this article per [[WP:NPOV]], but user Kuban Cosak reverted all my edits at once. It is very unusual that someone who claims to be a Cossack himself wants to describe Cossacks as &quot;pro-Nazi&quot;.[[User:Biophys|Biophys]] ([[User talk:Biophys|talk]]) 20:46, 18 February 2008 (UTC)

==It was not only Lienz==
Cossacs were also in Carinthia (Oderdrauburg), like von Pannwitz himself, in smaller villages such as Tristach, Amlach and Lavant.
-[[User:Phips|Phips]] 00:29, 30 October 2007 (UTC)

== War crimes ==

War crimes of the cossacks in question should be depicted--[[User:Dojarca|Dojarca]] ([[User talk:Dojarca|talk]]) 21:22, 24 September 2008 (UTC)

== Hornberger ==
Notwithstanding the dispute about the POV of the article itself, the use of Hornberger's website is worrying to me - it's hardly NPOV either (and I wonder about the use of almost direct quotes from his site in the article text itself without verification). Also, most of the the parts quoted from his website are originally from Epstein's book - surely better to cite the book in the first place (might involve a trip to the library, though!). &amp;ndash; [[User:SHtev|sHtev]] ([[User talk:SHtev|talk]]) 09:37, 21 April 2009 (UTC)

== Nazi Collaborators ==

If there is an indisputable fact here it's that certain Cossacks were Nazi sympathizers and collaborators as well as actively engaged in combat at times and killed allies.  These were the Allies enemies during the war as well as traitors to the Russians.  We can sit here and cite historical text all day long, but it is undeniable that that group Betrayed the Allied forces during the war.  And they deserved what they got.  Soldiers aren't the only ones who fight wars, civilians do too.  They support the cause.  All traitors...civilian and military alike should burn at the stake. A traitor is like a cancer...you need to eliminate it.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.90.30.203|24.90.30.203]] ([[User talk:24.90.30.203|talk]]) 17:32, 23 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Let me assure you that I am well-aware of the subject as a grandson of Kuban cossack family half of which was &quot;decossacked&quot; and the other half was fighting nazies on eastern front. I am not being &quot;ignorant&quot; or &quot;spreading contempt&quot; for that matter. Quite to the contrary, I am saying that this is a controversial subject and offering my own view point which anyone has a right to. And it respectuflly remains my opinion that the cossacks who comitted war crimes in Poland, Slovakia, Yugoslavia and Ukraine and collaborated with Nazies deserved no better faith. That said, civilians being killed by Soviet troops is a disgrace. But there is no justification for those who fought against partizans and Warsaw uprisers. There is an article on wikipedia entitled Nazi Collaborators. If you read it, you will know that people had no pitty (and that the word i used) for such collaborators across europe and many were executed by the people on public squares at the time. would you call these mass murders? Also, since you mentioned Israel, let me say (as someone who is intimately familiar with Israel and has a large family over there) that the term &quot;betrayal&quot; of Nazi collaborators does not fly well in that country as there are people who actually suffered from these collaborators and will never change their opinion. Same applies to Polish and former Yugoslavian people's perception and collective memory. Let me suggest that French ressistance fighters would do exactly the same to these cossacks if they got into their hands at the end of the war. I hope you are not suggesting double standards here. Again, the death of the civilians is a different story and reflects Stalin's policy of total extermination of the enemies, which cannot be justified. And to be completely blunt, let me perhaps suggest that what I think does actually matter (as does your point of view as well as the one of others as this is what dispute page is for), even if you may not like it. Sincerely, KS   &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.127.122.114|69.127.122.114]] ([[User talk:69.127.122.114|talk]]) 18:36, 25 August 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::&quot;''All traitors...civilian and military alike should burn at the stake. A traitor is like a cancer...you need to eliminate it. &quot;''. So much for someone from New York. This is called a [[collective punishment]] without trial. Executing &quot;by the people on public squares&quot; is known as [[Lynching]]. That's a bad thing. Someone from New Jersey should know.[[User:Biophys|Biophys]] ([[User talk:Biophys|talk]]) 19:39, 25 August 2009 (UTC)

==Move==
Several problems with this article, have been identified, but the biggest is the title.  I propose moving it to &quot;Repatriation of Cossacks after WWII&quot;. [[User:PatGallacher|PatGallacher]] ([[User talk:PatGallacher|talk]]) 20:06, 25 September 2009 (UTC)
:I agree that current title is bad. Most precise title would be [[Extradition of Cossacks]], with different versions like [[Extradition of Cossacks to the Soviet Union]], [[Extradition of Cossacks from Europe]], [[Extradition of Cossacks after WWII]], and so on. &quot;Forceful evacuation&quot; would be probably worse than &quot;Extradition&quot;. More opinions needed.[[User:Biophys|Biophys]] ([[User talk:Biophys|talk]]) 21:57, 25 September 2009 (UTC)
&quot;Repatriation of Cossacks after WWII&quot; is Soviet title.[[User:Xx236|Xx236]] ([[User talk:Xx236|talk]]) 09:56, 19 November 2009 (UTC)

== Warsaw Uprising ==

Cossack units fighting against the Warsaw Uprising:
*Schutzmannschaft 209
*206 (?)
*3 Regiment, Iakov Bondarenko
*IV/57 Regiment
*69 Kosaken Abteilung, Schlachtermund
*572 Infantry Battalion, Zinoviev 
*579 
[http://www.historia.gildia.pl/wiek-xx/wojskowosc/ii-wojna-swiatowa/wlasowcy-w-powstaniu-warszawskim], [http://www.blogi.szkolazklasa.pl/?blog=1717]
If the &quot;repatriated&quot; Cosacks are accused, we should check, if they participated. Certainly women and children didn't participate.
[[User:Xx236|Xx236]] ([[User talk:Xx236|talk]]) 14:11, 26 November 2009 (UTC)

== Still a &quot;Repatriation&quot; ==

People living ouside the SU were also deported. [[User:Xx236|Xx236]] ([[User talk:Xx236|talk]]) 12:11, 16 December 2010 (UTC)

== Allied motivation ==
I do not claim to know the motivation of everyone on the Western Allies' side involved in the repatriation, but some may have seen them as traitors who the Russians were entitled to execute or sentence to lengthy imprisonment.  Several people were executed or imprisoned for lengthy periods by Britain after the war, including [[William Joyce]] who was hanged on a very broad interpretation of who had a duty of loyalty to Britain, so some may have considered that the Ryssians were also entitled to take a broad view of who had a duty of loyalty.  In normal parlance you talk about someone betraying their country, not betraying their state.  These people had chosen to define themselves as Russians by fighting with Russian units, when they could have joined other units fighting on the German side.  It is not clear that even if some of them had left Russia prior to the formation of the USSR in 1922 they were not Soviet citizens, since the USSR was surely the successor state to the [[Russian Soviet Federative Soviet Republic]], formed in 1917, although it may be less clear if the RSFSR was the successor state to the previous Russian state. [[User:PatGallacher|PatGallacher]] ([[User talk:PatGallacher|talk]]) 18:02, 23 July 2011 (UTC)


There is no such ethnic group as Cossacks. 
&quot;Evgenij Tarruski, a Coassack author&quot; - Eugene or Evgenij Tarusski, was not familiar with Southern Russian or Cossack environment, he was an Admiralty officer and later the editor of Le Sentinelle magazine in  Brussels. He did commit suicide at Lienz.  There is even a Russian Wikipedia entry on Tarusski  - http://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A2%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%83%D1%81%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B8%D0%B9,_%D0%95%D0%B2%D0%B3%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B9

The article gets everything wrong, even the names of personages it describes. What a mess. 

Info  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/95.55.29.119|95.55.29.119]] ([[User talk:95.55.29.119|talk]]) 22:11, 4 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==GoldenEye==
There is a citation needed tag on Bond's line - I am certain he said those exact words in the movie in the scene where he meets with Zukovsky, so if I can pinpoint the exact time in the movie would that be enough for a citation? [[Special:Contributions/199.20.117.176|199.20.117.176]] ([[User talk:199.20.117.176|talk]]) 14:41, 10 August 2015 (UTC)

I presume http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0113189/quotes would do? I don't have time to work out how to do a proper reference.

== War crimes against Yugoslav partisans &amp; civilians ==

I believe the reference should be included. It seems very innocuous to say: &quot;so they were deployed to the Balkans to fight the Communist Yugoslav Partisans commanded by Josip Broz Tito.&quot;  

See a 2002 book by [[Jozo Tomasevich]] - [https://books.google.com/books?id=fqUSGevFe5MC&amp;pg=PA306&amp;lpg=PA306&amp;dq=cossack+atrocities+in+yugoslavia,%20Pp%20305-306 War and Revolution in Yugoslavia: 1941 - 1945, Occupation and Collaboration 2. Stanford: Stanford University Press]. The research is well sourced.  . 
--[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 06:14, 5 November 2015 (UTC)

:Further to my note above, I would like to add the following copy and reference to the article. Addition is in bold: 

:Although the Cossack units were formed to fight the Communists in Russia, by the time they formed, the Red Army had already recaptured most of the Nazi-occupied territory, so they were deployed to the Balkans to fight the Communist Yugoslav Partisans commanded by Josip Broz Tito.[6] '''While in Yugoslavia, the division established a reputation for undisciplined and ruthless behavior, not only towards the partisans, but also towards the civilian population, and committed war crimes and atrocities.''' &lt;ref&gt;[[#refTomasevich2001|Tomasevich 2001]], p. 306.&lt;/ref&gt; By the war's end, the Cossack units had come under the command of the Waffen-SS.

:Full source for Tomasevich 

:* {{cite book
|first=Jozo
|last=Tomasevich
|title=War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: Occupation and Collaboration
|volume=2
|publisher=Stanford University Press
|year=2001
|location=San Francisco
|isbn=0-8047-3615-4
|ref=Tomasevich_2001
}}
{{reflist-talk}}

:Please let me know if there are any concerns. --[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 19:56, 24 November 2015 (UTC)

== Vladimir D'Arbeloff ==

There is an account of his fathers life in the autobiography of D'Arbeloff. Among those former Russians sent by the Americans to the Soviet Union was a naturalized citizen. Vladimir D'Arbeloff  a Georgian volunteered for the United States military. Due to his ability to speak Russian he was assigned to guard the Cossack prisoners of war. When the Cossack prisoners were being guarded and negotiated for by the Allies D'Arbeloff was one of the officers who interacted with the Soviets. At the time the Soviets received incarcerated prisoners some of the Soviets and Americans arranged to have D'Arbeloff misdescribed. This was despite his never having served with the Germans at all.[[User:RichardBond|RichardBond]] ([[User talk:RichardBond|talk]]) 17:45, 2 January 2016 (UTC) [[User:RichardBond|RichardBond]] ([[User talk:RichardBond|talk]]) 17:45, 2 January 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jlolqbnln473o8n1wtrnj9pfpzfds7c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
