<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Chris Kyle</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>34272070</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735571096</id>
      <parentid>734748128</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-21T17:20:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Topher385</username>
        <id>4355324</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Semi-protected edit request on 12 August 2016 */ closing request due to lack of response</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34135">{{Discretionary sanctions|ap|brief}}
{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=n|class=C|listas=Kyle, Chris|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=C
&lt;!-- B-Class 5-criteria checklist --&gt;
|B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; =n
|B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; =y
|B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; =y
|B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; =y
|B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; =y
|Biography=y|Maritime=y|US=y}}
{{Pritzker-GLAM|class=C|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=C|importance=Mid|USMIL=y|TX=y|TX-importance=Low}}
}}
{{ITN talk|6 February|2013}}
{{Auto archiving notice|age=30
|index=./Archive index
|bot=MiszaBot}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{tan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 3
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Chris Kyle/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Chris Kyle/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Chris Kyle/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}

== Chris Kyle medals RfC ==
{{archive top|result= {{nac}} From reviewing the comments, consensus was reached to not add the information regarding the subject's personnel records until it is reported on by a reliable source. The current sources are not consider [[WP:RS]], and therefore should not be used. [[User:RickinBaltimore|RickinBaltimore]] ([[User talk:RickinBaltimore|talk]]) 13:08, 7 July 2016 (UTC)}}

How should the current news story regarding the question over Kyle's awards be presented in the article?

*via The Interceptor and news reports mirroring The Interceptor; 
*via the notation in Kyle's autobiography in addition to his [[DD-214]] and news sources reporting interviews with Kyle, quoting his autobiography, and reporting what's contained in his [[DD-214]].
-- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt; 18:07, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
===Option 1===
*'''Comment''' - It took far more time than I expected to figure out what this RfC was about but I think it's about adding a highly controversial allegation that has not been confirmed.  If the latter is the case, I'm of the mind that it shouldn't be included at all based on numerous PAGs.  It's groundless tabloid sensationalism about a person who is deceased and unable to defend his/herself.  I'm a bit confused that the US Navy hasn't actually confirmed either way or that there is not a RS available to verify the information; therefore the only verifiability we can confirm in any source is the fact that there is an unverifiable claim about the man's honors.  Delete it until verifiable information can be cited using more than one, high quality RS.  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;text-shadow:#F8F8FF 0.2em 0.2em 0.4em,#F4BBFF -0.2em -0.3em 0.6em,#BFFF00 0.8em 0.8em 0.6em;color:#A2006D&quot;&gt;[[User:Atsme|Atsme]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User talk:Atsme |📞]][[Special:EmailUser/Atsme|📧]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:20, 29 June 2016 (UTC)

===Option 2===
*'''Support''' Wikipedia is not news and we use reliable sources only.  The Interceptor is not a reliable source and the reporting there, quite biased. The Navy has already stated there will be an investigation into the discrepancy between personnel records and the final authority, the DD214, so this is likely to be cleared up by the end of the month.  I believe the article should remain with the status quo until the issue is settled, with a minor notation regarding the news story, but reflected by major, reliable news sources (preferably the Navy Times), not the Interceptor.   -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  18:07, 3 June 2016 (UTC)[[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  18:07, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
*'''Support''' per [[WP:NOTNEWS]]. Let the news agencies present the news, and when the story has been clarified and verified, we can update our article. [[User:Mr Ernie|Mr Ernie]] ([[User talk:Mr Ernie|talk]]) 18:08, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
&lt;s&gt;*'''Not only oppose, point out that the language of this laughable RfC is completely dishonest and that it's posted in bad faith, per Keri.''' 
::QUOTE:''&quot;it is one of the worst examples of biased push-polling I have ever seen, saying that the choice is between &quot;an online unreliable source&quot; (false) or &quot;the notation in Kyle's autobiography [a primary source, containing several disputed claims] in addition to other reliable sources based on his DD-214&quot; [stated by the Navy as potentially inaccurate].&quot;'' [[User:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz]] ([[User talk:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|talk]]) 00:32, 4 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt; Strike indeffed sock puppet. 09:36, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
*'''Support''' - as noted above, [[WP:NOTNEWS]]. [[User:Meatsgains|Meatsgains]] ([[User talk:Meatsgains|talk]]) 16:12, 18 June 2016 (UTC)

===Discussion===
I started this RfC because the current discussion was going nowhere.  Not to mention all of the bad faith accusations, edit warring, and poor attitudes being bandied about that makes it difficult to weed through and get to the meat of the issue.  This should get more eyes and opinions in an orderly fashion, and hopefully, a true consensus. -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  18:09, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
	
There is a discussion above where consensus is being formed. This RfC is in bad faith and an attempt to ignore that discussion and should be struck. [[User:Keri|Keri]] ([[User talk:Keri|talk]]) 18:12, 3 June 2016 (UTC)

Furthermore, it is one of the worst examples of biased push-polling I have ever seen, saying that the choice is between &quot;an online unreliable source&quot; (false) or &quot;the notation in Kyle's autobiography [a primary source, containing several disputed claims] in addition to other reliable sources based on his DD-214&quot; [stated by the Navy as potentially inaccurate]. [[User:Keri|Keri]] ([[User talk:Keri|talk]]) 18:17, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
:I'm [[WP:AGF|AFGing the hell]] out both sides here. I think the RFC was done in good faith, but needs some work and probably a bit early. Having said that, I tend to agree with Keri. It doesn't matter whether ''The Interceptor'' is a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] or not, because it's reporting has been covered by reliable sources. So, ''The Interceptor'' itself doesn't have to be even mentioned, but the controversy can be mentioned using those other sources. &lt;b&gt;[[User:Jauerback|Jauerback]]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Jauerback|dude?]]&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Jauerback|dude.]]&lt;/sub&gt; 18:32, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
::This is not only a contentious issue, it's a huge issue that needs more eyes and opinions from more editors.  Which is another reason why I started this RfC (see my other reasons above).  And yes, done totally in good faith.  Given the weight of this issue across three separate projects, it needs to be considered and commented on by more than those choosing to edit war, make completely bad faith accusations (including sock puppetry and meat puppetry), and log out to do both as IPs.  It wasn't going to stop (obviously), and I felt an RfC was a good, productive answer to a growing problem, {{U|Jauerback}}. -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  18:39, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
: {{re|Keri}} The Navy did not say that any particular aspect of the two official records they have may be more or less accurate than any other. &quot;The Intercept&quot; formed only the DD214 conclusion but it's not supported by the actual quotes.  It did receive substantial secondary coverage but that coverage was on ''The Intercept'' and the ''The Intercept''s conclusions, not independent coverage.  Second, the published autobiography with a co-author is not a primary source, it is a [[WP:SECONDARY]] secondary as it has been through editorial review and vetting by the publisher, the co-author as well as review for accuracy by the Navy (the Navy forced redactions of details, including the names, places, operations, confirmed kills, etc as some of those details are classified or revealed more information than SEALs wanted revealed- yes, his confirmed kills of 160 or so is understated because the Navy classified some of the missions where he had more.  He carefully states that throughout his book that the number is from the Navy).  The book is not necessarily independent of the subject but it is still a secondary source as the co-author interviewed third parties and formed analysis in addition to the review process above.  --[[User:DHeyward|DHeyward]] ([[User talk:DHeyward|talk]]) 20:38, 3 June 2016 (UTC) 
: Here's a [http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/american-sniper-chris-kyle-medal-898004 new source][http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/american-sniper-chris-kyle-medal-898004]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/american-sniper-chris-kyle-medal-898004&lt;/ref&gt;  [http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/american-sniper-author-defends-chris-899044 and another][http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/american-sniper-author-defends-chris-899044]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/american-sniper-author-defends-chris-899044&lt;/ref&gt; that is an interview with the co-author. 
{{Reflist-talk}}
: The problem with parsing the Navy spokesperson's quotes that are pretty general about the process into a specific argument against Kyles DD214 is lack of knowledge.  If it was the IRS that said &quot;We use Tax Returns and W-2s as our authoritative reference for income&quot; and then said &quot;Form 1040 is filled out by taxpayers and there are people involved.&quot; - Most would understand that &quot;Tax Return&quot; and &quot;1040&quot; are the same thing and it would a far-fetched conclusion to say the &quot;The 1040 Form doesn't match the official Tax Return or the official W-2.&quot;   Also, it doesn't mean the W-2 is not filled out by hand and not prone to similar errors. The meaning of those quotes would lead people familiar with U.S. taxes to conclude the Tax Return is Form 1040 and it does not match the W-2 without a conclusion about which is correct and wouldn't think to separate the Form 1040 from the Tax Return as separate.  Finally, W-2s and tax returns are sent to the IRS so the return and W-2 are centrally located.  The [[DD Form 214]] is not separable from OMPF.  It is centrally filed.  What's missing, without explanation, is a quote from the Navy spokesperson about how personal awards are entered.  The answer is they are locally generated records by the same command that would generate the DD214.  Both are then forwarded to their respective repositories.  People are involved in both processes.  Errors can exist in both award database and OMPF regarding personal awards.  The starting process for correcting is identical: contact the local command to correct it.  The awards database is easy to correct, the DD214 is a pain but that's a process issue as the award database doesn't affect anything.  The SEAL community does not like the awards database because it contains too much operational details unless the citation is heavily redacted.  They don't want their name associated with actions regardless of whether the operation was classified or not.  It's the meaning of &quot;quiet professionals.&quot;  It's why there are 100's of Silver Star awards to Navy SEALs that are not in the database and associated with a service members name. --[[User:DHeyward|DHeyward]] ([[User talk:DHeyward|talk]]) 20:38, 3 June 2016 (UTC)
:: &lt;s&gt;And we get another round of [[WP:IDIDNTHEARTHAT]] and '''not-even-[[WP:OR]]-because-that-would-imply-someone-did-more-than-make-dishonest-stuff-up''' from the one most likely to be involved in [[WP:CANVAS]] activities offsite. This is ridiculous. [[User:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz]] ([[User talk:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|talk]]) 00:33, 4 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt;
:::&lt;s&gt; Also {{yo|DHeyward}} seriously, READ the [[WP:RS]] policy already. An &quot;interview with the co-author&quot; is not a reliable source for claims of supposed facts; neither is something in an opinion column / blogging area published in a [[Gossip magazines|gossip magazine]]. [[User:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz]] ([[User talk:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|talk]]) 00:40, 4 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt;

*'''Comment''' - I would highly suggest you reword the wording of the RfC, as it is [[Wikipedia:Requests_for_comment#Statement_should_be_neutral_and_brief|nowhere close to a neutral wording]]. Your RfC question leaves no doubt of your opinion, [[Wikipedia:Writing_requests_for_comment#Neutrality|which I shouldn't be able to infer from merely reading your RfC question]], and makes it seem like it's a position where one side is wholly unreliable, and the other is reliable. - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 14:16, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::{{U|Aoidh}}, I'm not quite sure what you are getting at, as the Interceptor ''is'' an unreliable source and was being cited to support the non-neutrally worded content.  I certainly never intended for the RfC to be anything but neutral, and thought I achieved neutrality, especially in its simplicity and to-the-point wording.  Can you give me an example of how, in your opinion,the wording could be improved? -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  14:29, 4 June 2016 (UTC)  
:::What I'm getting at is that your RfC is not neutrally worded. There is no doubt what opinion you have, as it is evident in the RfC question. If someone had created the RfC and said &quot;Should we trust the Associated Press's reporting or ignore what those reliable sources say in favor of the subject's own words?&quot; They could likewise argue that such an RfC wording is not factually inaccurate, but it's certainly not neutral and worded in a way to suggest the answer before the question is even asked. The same problem exists for the RfC as worded. A more neutral wording would be something like &quot;Should the article mention the recent controversy/concerns surrounding the medals as reported by various sources?&quot; - [[User:Aoidh|Aoidh]] ([[User talk:Aoidh|talk]]) 22:54, 4 June 2016 (UTC) 
::[[Push poll]]ing sprang immediately to mind. Particularly when the original discussion and consensus veered away from Winkelvi's preferred POV. [[User:Keri|Keri]] ([[User talk:Keri|talk]]) 14:19, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
*I agree with Aoidh, my perception of the question being asked is - should we use an unreliable source or a reliable source, with the obvious answer being, per WP policies and guidelines, we use the reliabe source. I'd also point out that while it is true that some of the media is mirroring The Interceptor article, at least one reliabe source, the Associated Press, has independently confirmed some of the details being reported - [http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/wireStory/documents-show-american-sniper-kyle-embellished-record-39377725 the Navy on Wednesday confirmed the contents of the documents to The Associated Press.] and the AP article goes on to state: ''Lt. Jackie Pau, a Navy spokeswoman, '''told the AP''' that Kyle's military personnel file...'' Therefore we do have a reliable source that has independently confirmed some of the details being reported, so maybe the RfC language should be tweaked to reflect that it's not a choice of &quot;unreliable vs. reliable&quot;. Another option that can be considered is to wait until the Navy is finished with their investigation - [http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/navy-to-probe-american-sniper-chris-kyles-alleged-medal-discrepancies/article/2592310 &quot;As we figure out which route we're going or does a correction need to be made, we'll make that information public&quot;].--[[User:Isaidnoway|&lt;font face=&quot;Times New Roman&quot; color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt; '''''Isaidnoway''''' &lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Isaidnoway|&lt;font face=&quot;Times New Roman&quot; color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;'''''(talk)'''''&lt;/font&gt;]] 18:10, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:** First, I agree we should wait for the Navy. They will file a DD-215 for correction, if necessary. Second, not waiting invites a maligning narrative that we should avoid. The awards mentioned as part of the FOIA were released and can be viewed. There is only 1 silver star and 2 bronze stars. The only reason I can see that they say 3 bronze stars is because the award certificate says it was his third (&quot;gold star in lieu of 3rd award&quot;). The documents for the 2nd bronze star was not there, not even the barebone frameable certificate. Until they track it all down, there is just discrepancy. The biggest issue that I saw, for me, is dates on awards. It takes a while for these very high awards to get approved and I was personally surprised to see he received them all by his separation considering the dates that were on the released awards. There may be lots of reasons why but they all are reasons to wait for the Navy to sort it. The commanding officer that signed the DD-214 and filed it is likely still living. --[[User:DHeyward|DHeyward]] ([[User talk:DHeyward|talk]]) 12:46, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
* '''This RFC should be closed''' and Winkelvi warned that opening an RFC with a biased question is a form of canvassing. No comment on the substance of the dispute. [[User:Hijiri88|Hijiri 88]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Hijiri88|聖]][[Special:Contributions/Hijiri88|やや]]&lt;/small&gt;) 10:21, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
*'''NOTE''' RFC has been reworded per good faith editors and suggestions. -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  13:01, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

*Wording is still biased. What if the RfC was:

:* via news reports
:* via other sources echoing Kyle's own claims.

:Yes, this is biased the other way -- ''equally'' biased.  I consider this RfC invalid, but for the record, I go with news reports.  Personally, I kind of suspect that Kyle was right, and I hope this gets sorted out soon, but no crystal ball, y'know.  If we have an RS that reports the discrepancy, we can note that, but that's all for now.  --[[User:A D Monroe III|A D Monroe III]] ([[User talk:A D Monroe III|talk]]) 20:59, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
::Not trying to be contentious, but I honestly don't see how the wording is still biased.  If anything, the wording you suggest, &quot;echoing Kyle's own claims&quot; is biased as it gives the impression he's the only one making the claims.  He worked with two co-writers on his book, American Sniper, from where the public claims originated.  The book is taking the medal count from his DD214, which reflects those claims, as well.  -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  22:29, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
:::Winkelvi, you just slightly altered the wording of the question (and it is ''still'' clearly biased, as you imply option 1 has only one source and the rest are mirrors, but imply option 2 has multiple sources which you do not name) and heavily altered your own !vote to counterbalance it by inserting a large amount of one-sided commentary immediately below the question. Look at what I did on WT:MOSKOREA: if you want to present your own commentary immediately below an RFC question, please collapse it. [[User:Hijiri88|Hijiri 88]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Hijiri88|聖]][[Special:Contributions/Hijiri88|やや]]&lt;/small&gt;) 23:22, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
::::As far as I'm aware, there's no policy or guideline that states someone !Voting cannot alter their !Vote nor any statements accompanying it.  As well, there is no policy stating that accompanying commentary is disallowed and needs to be collapsed.  Commentary such as mine here happens all the time in RfCs as well as other !Vote discussions. -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  23:39, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::This RfC should have been specific about what source said what. As I understand it &quot;The Intercept&quot; claims 1 Silver Star and 3 Bronze Stars, while the DD-214 and ''American Sniper'' claim 2 Silver Stars and 5 Bronze Stars. Is that what is being discussed here?
There are many rational explanations for why one source might report a different number of medals. One Silver Star is not in dispute, and a person has much to lose and little to gain by lying about a second award; I also have a sense that people who do what is necessary to earn a Silver Star would be unlikely to lie about it. So I do not feel this article should be changed to &quot;reflect the controversy&quot; until a reliable source, preferably a Navy source, is available. I don't really understand why there is such a desire to discredit Kyle; it has to be political, but he was not a political figure. [[User:Roches|Roches]] ([[User talk:Roches|talk]]) 03:41, 12 June 2016 (UTC)
{{archive bottom}}

== Canvassing template ==

I don't know who put it there originally, but a template claiming &quot;There have been attempts to recruit editors of specific viewpoints to this article&quot; has been added to this talk page.  There is no evidence of this happening except for an anonymous IP (that has now been rangeblocked for disruptive editing) trying to out editors by claiming there has been canvassing on Facebook.  There is no evidence that anyone from Wikipedia has done any off-Wiki canvassing, there is no evidence that anyone has been recruited to edit in a non-POV manner.  The template is inappropriate and needs to be removed.  I have attempted to do so twice, and another editor has replaced it both times.  Not sure what to do at this point and I really don't want to have to go to any kind of noticeboard.  Helpful comments, thoughts, advice, action from someone else would be welcomed, from my standpoint.  -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  00:54, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:&lt;s&gt;It was [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AChris_Kyle&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=723349610&amp;oldid=723348948 placed by Keri] and after going away for an afternoon with my girlfriend only to come back and find this crazy mess, I think it needs to stay. It is 100% appropriate given the speed with which IP POV-pushing followed your inappropriate and disruptive editing minutes after the page protection expired. [[User:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz]] ([[User talk:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|talk]]) 01:18, 4 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt;
:: There are no IP editors. It's semi-preotected.  The thinly veiled aspersions you have made on this page as well as the blatant personal attack making spurious allegations in the edit summary[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AChris_Kyle&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=723629614&amp;oldid=723629464] is unwelcome and you should leave the template alone considering your expressed views.  --[[User:DHeyward|DHeyward]] ([[User talk:DHeyward|talk]]) 05:20, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::&lt;s&gt;The history of this page and associated talk page show that you're making a blatantly false statement there, DHeyward. [[User:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz]] ([[User talk:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz|talk]]) 05:24, 4 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt;
There is clear evidence that someone - and I'm not pointing fingers or naming names - has posted a request on Facebook for people to visit this page, specifically the RfC, to &quot;stop the Libtards&quot;. The template stays. Winkelvi, if you &quot;don't know who put it there originally&quot;, try looking in the page history. [[User:Keri|Keri]] ([[User talk:Keri|talk]]) 13:20, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:&quot;Someone&quot;, yes.  Someone who has or is editing Wikipedia?  There is no evidence of it.  There is evidence that people in online groups outside Wikipedia talk about the goings on in Wikipedia.  Does that mean there is evidence Wikipedia and its articles are directly affected editing-wise by what's said in those online groups?  No.  The template is inappropriate and unwarranted since there is zero evidence the alleged off-Wiki talk has affected this article.  -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  13:31, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::I'm not here to witch-hunt whether Editor X or Editor Y or Editor Z has made posts on Facebook. Read the template and show me the part that is incorrect: &quot;There have been attempts to recruit editors of specific viewpoints to this article. If you've come here in response to such recruitment, please review the relevant Wikipedia policy on recruitment of editors, as well as the neutral point of view policy. Disputes on Wikipedia are resolved by consensus, not by majority vote.&quot; It doesn't apportion blame, it doesn't even say that a Wikipedia editor has carried out canvassing. It explains that canvassing has taken place elsewhere and points people to the relevant policies viz consensus and !vote. [[User:Keri|Keri]] ([[User talk:Keri|talk]]) 13:59, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::All that's been produced is a .png screen shot of a comment that could have come from any online page.  Heck, it could have been created with some cut and paste and use of photoshop or other similar software.  There's no link that takes us to where that screenshot was allegedly obtained.  There's no real, empirical evidence that the screenshot is authentic or anyone has been recruiting anyone.  Minus such evidence, there is no legitimate reason I can fathom that makes placement of the template tag appropriate. -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  14:04, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::::Take it to ANI. [[User:Keri|Keri]] ([[User talk:Keri|talk]]) 14:05, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::Discussion was started here and it should stay here.  Unless an administrator specifically asks me a question there, I won't be posting in the ANI report you started.  My personal opinion is that you should be [[WP:TROUT|trouted]] for filing it.  -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  14:11, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::{{re|Winkelvi}} This talk page is for discussion of ways to improve the article, not for accusations about outing, canvassing, abuse of Photoshop, off-wiki impersonation or any other such behavioural issues. [[User:Hijiri88|Hijiri 88]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Hijiri88|聖]][[Special:Contributions/Hijiri88|やや]]&lt;/small&gt;) 10:26, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Look at the comments here and the history, look into what was actually happening, look at who is now blocked/indeffed and why, look at the comments at the ANI, and then make a true assessment of the situation entire.  The discussion Keri took to ANI should never have gone there and your chastisement is misplaced, {{U|Hijiri88}} (if it should be happening at all). -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  12:35, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
::::::::{{ping|Winkelvi}} And all of that stuff you are talking about belongs on a noticeboard like ANI, not here. This page is for discussing improvements to the article, not outing, canvassing, abuse of Photoshop, off-wiki impersonation, sockpuppetry, personal attacks or any other such stuff. You should re-read [[WP:TALK#USE]]. And I don't care who is &quot;right&quot; or &quot;wrong&quot; in the off-topic disputes about user conduct-- ''you'' are wrong in saying that such discussions belong on the article talk page. [[User:Hijiri88|Hijiri 88]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Hijiri88|聖]][[Special:Contributions/Hijiri88|やや]]&lt;/small&gt;) 12:47, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
{{od}}And I disagree with your thoughts on the matter.  You seem to be wanting to start a fight and possibly see me formally sanctioned or chastised?  I'm not interested in the argument, and this article talk page certainly isn't the place for it, anyway.  Please drop it. -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  13:07, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

I've removed it again.  [[User:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz]] has been indeffed for being a sock puppet of [[User:SkepticAnonymous]].  He has a history of creating Joe Jobber accounts falsifying canvassing. See [[User talk:JimWHall#My observation]] where he doctored IRC logs to try and make it appear as if another WP editor canvassed him to join in political discussions. All are indeffed and the template just feeds their goal of disruption through suspicion.  Considering all the accusations and invective thrown at me by User:Prostetnic Vogon Jeltz over the past few days, I'd rather not leave false impressions for anyone. --[[User:DHeyward|DHeyward]] ([[User talk:DHeyward|talk]]) 09:28, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

==Edit request==
{{edit fully-protected|answered=yes}} Under &quot;Death&quot;, I don't think Littlefield's age needs to be mentioned within this section. I personally think it adds undue weight. As such, I am requesting that an administrator change the wording to &quot;Kyle and his friend, Chad Littlefield, were shot and killed...&quot; --&lt;font color= &quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;[[User:Patient Zero|'''Patient''''''''Zero''''']]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;0000FF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Patient Zero|'''talk''']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 14:33, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:Do you really think Littlefield's age in the article is going to impede the reader's understanding of the article subject if it stays until the full protect is lifted, {{U|Patient Zero}}? Could be it's low on the list of immediate changes to be made, eh? ;-) -- &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #0099FF, -4px -4px 15px #99FF00;&quot;&gt;[[User:Winkelvi|WV]]&lt;/span&gt; ● &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow: 4px 4px 15px #FF9900, -4px -4px 15px #FF0099;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Winkelvi|✉]] [[Special:Contributions/Winkelvi|✓]]&lt;/span&gt;  14:40, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
::{{u|Winkelvi}}, the sooner the better though, am I right? :) I agree it's not a major issue though. --&lt;font color= &quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;[[User:Patient Zero|'''Patient''''''''Zero''''']]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;0000FF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Patient Zero|'''talk''']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 14:50, 4 June 2016 (UTC)
:::{{done}}, the requested edit doesn't appear to be part of the contested edits. [[User:Nakon|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#C50;&quot;&gt;'''Nakon'''&lt;/span&gt;]] 00:33, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
::::Thank you {{u|Nakon}}. :) --&lt;font color= &quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;[[User:Patient Zero|'''Patient''''''''Zero''''']]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;0000FF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Patient Zero|'''talk''']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 09:17, 5 June 2016 (UTC)
I disagree with making this change (and I have no involvement with this article). How does this add undue weight, particularly when the article states the type, caliber and owner of the gun that he was killed with? I used 35 in commas; I think &quot;35-year-old Chad Littlefield&quot; would be better. It's almost universal to state the age of a person who has died. [[User:Roches|Roches]] ([[User talk:Roches|talk]]) 12:31, 11 June 2016 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 12 August 2016 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Chris Kyle|answered=yes}}



Hi Chris Kyle was originally interested in becoming a United States Marine Corps Scout Sniper, not USMC MARSOC/RECON etc. Please edit this. 

Directly under ''MILITAIRY CAREER&quot; the sentence ''
After his arm healed, Kyle went to a military recruiting office, interested in joining the U.S. Marine Corps special operations. A U.S. Navy recruiter convinced him to try, instead, for the SEALs. Initially, Kyle was rejected because of the pins in his arm, but he eventually received an invitation to the 24-week Basic Underwater Demolition SEAL school (BUDS), which he joined in 1999.[14]

AND FROM REFERENCE 14 YOU CAN'T MAKE UP HE WAS INTERESTED IN BECOMMING A SOF MARINE, JUST THAT HE WANTED TO JOIN THE USMC AS A MARINE.

EVIDENCE https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7yISEIg1XIg WATCH FIRST PART 0.00-0.15

Thank you very much


[[Special:Contributions/83.86.204.95|83.86.204.95]] ([[User talk:83.86.204.95|talk]]) 16:39, 12 August 2016 (UTC)
:[[File:Pictogram voting comment.svg|20px|link=|alt=]] '''Note:'''&lt;!-- Template:EP --&gt; I was unable to find any remarks by him in the video concerning the type of Marine he wanted to be. However, I have very little knowledge of military matters, so I will leave this open for a more knowledgeable editor. [[User:Topher385|Topher385]] ([[User talk:Topher385|talk]]) 13:01, 16 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>iuoaodz5bn11h4ppjfyvf3ri5n6fwp7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
