<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Tupolev Tu-160</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1498133</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744714295</id>
      <parentid>744710532</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-17T00:34:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BilCat</username>
        <id>2043601</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Phone no. Glitch */ Comments</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14440">{{talk header|search=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=C
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
|B-Class-1=n &lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=y &lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=y &lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=y &lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=y &lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|Aircraft=yes }}
{{WPMILHIST|class=start
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
|B-Class-1=n &lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=y &lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=y &lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=y &lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=y &lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|Aviation=yes |Russian=yes  |Cold-War=y }}
{{WikiProject Soviet Union|class=C |importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=C|importance=high|mil=yes|tech=yes}}
}}
{{notice|{{find}}}}

== Comparing Tu-160 ==
This constant attempts to compare Tu-160 and B1 are getting rather old. Please understand that these two aircraft are in entirely different leagues - Lancer is a low-alt penetrator and Tu-160 is a high-alt supersonic missile carrier, you just can't compare two of them. Just get over the fact that Tu-160 is bigger, faster, delivers a bigger punch and that US today still doesn't has anything comparable.   &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/149.225.130.141|149.225.130.141]] ([[User talk:149.225.130.141|talk]]) 10:46, 14 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

You say people shouldn't compare the two planes, then you end your post by comparing the two planes.  The Tu-160, though a capable aircraft indeed, is a knock-off of the B-1A.  YOU need to get over that fact.  --[[Special:Contributions/203.110.206.180|203.110.206.180]] ([[User talk:203.110.206.180|talk]]) 14:24, 28 January 2011 (UTC)
:It's been very well established that the Tu-160 is ''not'' a &quot;Knock-off of the B-1A&quot;. Stating that it is is [[WP:OPINION]] and [[WP:POV]] that are not supported by the [[WP:RS]]s. - [[User:The Bushranger|The Bushranger]] &lt;sub&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;maroon&quot;&gt;[[User talk:The Bushranger|One ping only]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 19:33, 28 January 2011 (UTC)
::Really?  Because all the period literature I've read states the Tu-160 was HEAVILY based off the B-1A design.  Not to mention the utter ridiculousness of calling reality POV.  (For the love of Pete...one need only LOOK at the planes.)  I wholly respect the Tu-160's capabilities and wonder what it could have been capable of if it was fully fielded prior to the U.S.S.R.'s collapse.  The Tu-160 and B-1B may serve different functions today, but that doesn't change the Blackjack's history.--[[Special:Contributions/203.110.206.180|203.110.206.180]] ([[User talk:203.110.206.180|talk]]) 07:04, 29 January 2011 (UTC)
::::What 'period' is being spoken of? The most recent literature, or the 'period' of the 1980s/early 1990s? - [[User:The Bushranger|The Bushranger]] &lt;sub&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;maroon&quot;&gt;[[User talk:The Bushranger|One ping only]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 07:08, 29 January 2011 (UTC)
:::: Surely influenced by the B-1, but not a simple &quot;[[knock-off]]&quot;. -[[User:Fnlayson|fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 11:16, 29 January 2011 (UTC)

:::::I concur that the Tu-160 is not a simple knock-off, but it's obviously &quot;inspired by&quot; the B-1. The Soviets certainly never had a problem using Western designs as &quot;starting points&quot; for their own. That they could design products completely on their own is without dispute, but they did show a tendecny to &quot;outsource&quot; some initial design work from time to time! - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 11:26, 29 January 2011 (UTC)

::::::If you are going to say that the Tu-160 was based on the B-1, you might as well say that the tank was based from the Chinese cannon made in the 10th Century AD. Why? Because it uses gunpowder and it has a flash when it fires. Yes, that's the similarity that a Tu-160 and B-1 have; they both just drop bombs and happen to have similar shape. [[Special:Contributions/203.213.43.182|203.213.43.182]] ([[User talk:203.213.43.182|talk]]) 12:48, 14 April 2011 (UTC)
:::::::Unless you were actually trying to come up with the dumbest comparison you could, you've failed to demonstrate anything but your own bias.--[[Special:Contributions/172.129.23.158|172.129.23.158]] ([[User talk:172.129.23.158|talk]]) 03:10, 10 April 2014 (UTC)

There is plenty of grey area in between &quot;they copied the design of the B1&quot; and &quot;its a completely different aircraft, they just look the same&quot;. 

The B1-A only existed for a handful of years, they only built 4 and it never entered service, and it was re-developed into the B1B. The original design directive for the TU160 clearly mirrors that of the B1A, however the Russians didn't cancel and repurpose their design, so they ended up with something similar to the B1A, but taken much further, matured and naturally, had its design goals changed and/or modified along the way, ending up with a fully-fledged service aircraft.

You cannot say it is fully a copy of the B1A because the B1A was never even finished.
You cannot say it is fully a copy of the B1B because they are designed for radically different roles, and those differences account for  some of the radical differences between the two aircraft (and yes, there are radical differences, its almost as if not everything is as it meets the eye huh?).

Of course you'd have to be blind not to comment on the similarities, but to affix on it as if the russians just bought a model kit and decided to make one just like it is ridiculous. Its a lot harder to build an aircraft than that.
[[Special:Contributions/94.175.244.252|94.175.244.252]] ([[User talk:94.175.244.252|talk]]) 11:13, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

==Comparison table==
The comparison table was added a couple of weeks ago, but I missed it's addition. Had I seen it then, I would have removed it immediately. It smacks of [[WP:PEACOCK]], and is quite bulky. In additin, we don't usually put theses sort of comparison tables in aircraft articles, while the flags and thumbnail images are also non-standard. Please discuss the table if you believe it should be in the article, and build a consensus to re-add it before doing so. Thanks. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 11:41, 7 October 2010 (UTC)

==Tu-134UBL==
While I concur that the Tu-144 should be placed under the heading&quot;Related&quot;, I believe the Tu-134UBL falls more correctly under the standard heading &quot;Related Development&quot;, as the aircraft was developed exclusively for training Tu-160 pilots, using the cockpit and nose section of the tu-160 - [[User:Kenkeisel|Kenkeisel]] ([[User talk:Kenkeisel|talk]])

: Use for training pilots really has nothing to do with development of the Tu-160 aircraft, which is what that label implies.  This training use is already mentioned in the article and needs to be referenced.  By the way, your signature needs fixing since it does not link to your user page as it should. -[[User:Fnlayson|fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 16:39, 28 November 2010 (UTC)

: 'Related development' is for types developed from, or into, the type in question. Also, looking at pictures of the -134UBL, that really looks more like the nose of a ''Backfire'' to me... - [[User:The Bushranger|The Bushranger]] &lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:The Bushranger|Return fire]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User:The Bushranger/Pages Created|''Flank speed'']]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 16:53, 28 November 2010 (UTC)

:: The Tu-134UBL incorporates a nose containing a complete mock-up of the Tu-160 cockpit, from which the pilots in training are able to fly the Tu-134UBL as if it were a Tu-160 (though under the limitations of the Tu-134UBL's configuration). It was built using Tu-160 cockpit components strictly as a trainer aircraft for Tu-160 aircrews. As such, it certainly qualifies for the catagory &quot;Related Development&quot;. It saved the Soviet's from the cost of constructing a trainer version of the Blackjack. [[User:Ken keisel|Ken keisel]] ([[User talk:Ken keisel|talk]]) 18:26, 29 November 2010 (UTC)

:::Thank you Fnlayson. That looks much better. Wish I had a good photo of the Tu-134UBL to post in the article. [[User:Ken keisel|Ken keisel]] ([[User talk:Ken keisel|talk]]) 19:20, 29 November 2010 (UTC)

::::Ah, that is useful, thanks. I wonder if the pictures of the &quot;UBL&quot; I found were actually showing the variant they stuck a Tu-22M's nose onto (I forget the designation at the moment)? Thanks for the input! - [[User:The Bushranger|The Bushranger]] &lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:The Bushranger|Return fire]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User:The Bushranger/Pages Created|''Flank speed'']]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 20:14, 29 November 2010 (UTC)

== See also ==
I can't see how this article is related to the &quot;2010 Polish Air Force Tu-154 crash&quot;. [[Special:Contributions/89.204.138.129|89.204.138.129]] ([[User talk:89.204.138.129|talk]]) 18:11, 19 October 2012 (UTC)

:I cant see how either, so I've removed it. The link was added by an IP user without explanation. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 18:33, 19 October 2012 (UTC)

: I don't see the connection either.  No mention of Tu-160 anywhere in the crash article. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 18:45, 19 October 2012 (UTC)

== Best / better lead image ==

Objects possess the greatest amount of detail when an even axonometric view is displayed. The previous image is a side view that obscures the plane. The one I propose is an under view that shows full detail of the largest orthographic view of the plane. Please discuss. [[User:Al Khazar|Khazar]] ([[User talk:Al Khazar|talk]]) 04:01, 16 December 2014 (UTC)

:The image you selected is a poor choice as Lead photo. 10 dollar words can make an ugly image look any better. Please present some options here, and get other opinions and a consensus before changing the image again. Thanks. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 04:09, 16 December 2014 (UTC)

::I accept. I'll remove the photo for now. [[User:Al Khazar|Khazar]] ([[User talk:Al Khazar|talk]]) 04:10, 16 December 2014 (UTC)
::I expect a legitimate reason against my proposition rather than referencing &quot;10 dollar words&quot;. Please present valid points rather than the classical argument structure with no policies to sustain it. [[User:Al Khazar|Khazar]] ([[User talk:Al Khazar|talk]]) 04:16, 16 December 2014 (UTC)
:::OK, thanks. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 04:13, 16 December 2014 (UTC)

::::Your &quot;argument&quot; referenced no policies. An orthographic view is generally presented in the Specs section as a 3-view, which we have. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 04:23, 16 December 2014 (UTC)
:::::That's still not a legitimate argument. I point out a major flaw in your opposition and you completely ignored it. You've mentioned so-called &quot;policies&quot; but fail to actually accurately point to them. Policies do not play a major role in this argument and you know tis very well. The current image is a side oriented view of the Tu-160 [almost orthographic] and creates a diminutive appearance unlike a more bottom oriented view. The latter exposes more of the plane due to being situated in a position that makes the larger dimensions more noticeable. [[User:Al Khazar|Khazar]] ([[User talk:Al Khazar|talk]]) 04:31, 16 December 2014 (UTC)

::::::I'm not here to argue. Two editors have nixed your choice, and it's up to you to persuade others to support your choice, ie. build a [[WP:CONSENSUS|consensus]]. Choosing a Lead image in an aircraft article is usually a matter of aesthetics, not geometry. The Lead photo is the first image a reader sees, and in most cases having an aesthetically pleasing image is better than having one that isn't. There are dozens of photos of the aircraft on Commons, so surely we can find one that we can agree on. I asked if you would present some options, meaning other photos to choose from. So pick another image, and we'll see if a consensus.can be built. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 04:49, 16 December 2014 (UTC)
:::::::In case like this, aesthetics is directly related to geometry. The current one had a lower resolution and an inferior orthographic view (side). It's amazing how you still can't back up your argument and claim that you don't have one when you fail to do so. You've already ridiculed my proposition by insults rather than legitimate reasons. [[User:Al Khazar|Khazar]] ([[User talk:Al Khazar|talk]]) 15:16, 16 December 2014 (UTC)

{{outdent}}
These are the images in question:
[[File:Tu-160 at MAKS 2007.jpg|thumb|left|Existing infobox image]]
[[File:2013 Moscow Victory Day Parade (57).jpg|thumb|Proposed new infobox image]]
{{clear}}
The purpose of the Infobox image is show the complete aircraft as best as possible.  The proposed image shows mostly the underside of the aircraft.  This is not good enough, imo.  Discuss the merits of these images, thanks. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 15:30, 16 December 2014 (UTC)

== Russia to start production of TU-160 ==

According to [http://sputniknews.com/military/20150429/1021514706.html Sputnik news], Russia is planning to restart production of Tu-160 again. The news says that Russian Defense Minister Gen. Sergei Shoigu said that Russia should start production of Tu-160 in addition to upgrading existing ones. [[User:Tumsaa|Tumsaa]] ([[User talk:Tumsaa|talk]]) 15:37, 29 April 2015 (UTC)

== Phone no. Glitch ==

In where it was produced it has a phone number can someone edit the template, I couldn't figure it out [[User:Planer 12346578955|Planer 12346578955]] ([[User talk:Planer 12346578955|talk]]) 00:04, 17 October 2016 (UTC)

:Can you be more specific about where it is? I can't find it. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 00:34, 17 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rz11c9zuxvqfwpgpvpi262qd5x8u0g9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
