<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Aleppo (2012–present)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>36494851</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749807706</id>
      <parentid>749803420</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T07:10:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Editor abcdef</username>
        <id>22381518</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Terrorists */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12272">{{Talk header|search=yes }}
{{SCW&amp;ISIL sanctions|brief=yes}} 
{{FailedGA|14:55, 19 November 2015 (UTC)|topic=Warfare|page=1}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=c
| B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; = no
| B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; = yes
| B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; = yes
| B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; = yes
| B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; = yes
|Middle-Eastern=yes}}
{{WikiProject Arab world|class=c|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Syria|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Terrorism|class=c|importance=Low}}
}}
{{Banner holder|collapsed=yes|
{{Old AfD multi|page=Battle of Aleppo(2012)|date=21 July 2012 |result='''withdrawn'''}}
{{ITN talk|30 July|2012}}
}}

{{findnote}}



== ISIS in the infobox ==

I think the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant should be in the infobox because they have played a big role in the battle of Aleppo. They still control the outskirts and surrounding areas of Aleppo and have done for a very long time and still launch attacks/fight against both government and rebel forces near the city and surroundings. So ISIS should be put in the infobox as a belligerent. They have participated throughout!--[[User:PaulPGwiki|PaulPGwiki]] ([[User talk:PaulPGwiki|talk]]) 09:15, 20 April 2016 (UTC)
:It was decided long ago (years ago) on the discussion page to focus this article exclusively only on the battle for the city. ISIS is a littler over a dozen kilometers away from the city in the province's countryside. If they ever do reach the city we would add them. [[User:EkoGraf|EkoGraf]] ([[User talk:EkoGraf|talk]]) 18:17, 20 April 2016 (UTC)
Ah yeah i understand, its the battle for the city itself not including the surrounding area/countryside, that explains it, thankyou. And yeah if they ever do reach the city then they should be added.--[[User:PaulPGwiki|PaulPGwiki]] ([[User talk:PaulPGwiki|talk]]) 10:02, 22 April 2016 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 6 October 2016 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Battle of Aleppo (2012–present)|answered=yes}}
The opening paragraph makes no sense, I want to remove the phrase &quot;and against the Kurdish People's Defence Units&quot; because it makes no sense. I suggest either amending the grammar or removing this altogether. 

[[User:Sammyh2000|Sammyh2000]] ([[User talk:Sammyh2000|talk]]) 06:08, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
:[[File:Pictogram voting question.svg|20px|link=|alt=]] '''Question:'''&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; Can you be more specific about why it makes no sense and what you would like us to change it to? [[User:Topher385|Topher385]] ([[User talk:Topher385|talk]]) 22:02, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
:[[File:Padlock-silver-open.svg|28px|link=|alt=]] '''Not done:''' The page's protection level has changed since this request was placed. You should now be able to [[Help:Editing|edit the page yourself]]. If you still seem to be unable to, please reopen the request with further details.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; —&amp;thinsp;[[User:JJMC89|JJMC89]]&amp;thinsp;&lt;small&gt;([[User talk:JJMC89|T]]'''·'''[[Special:Contributions/JJMC89|C]])&lt;/small&gt; 05:03, 8 October 2016 (UTC)

== I have added UN statements on rebels shelling civilians ==

They come from UN News portal:
[http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=55201#.WAKeM4l5hyY ''The use by armed opposition groups of what is known as a ‘hell-fire cannon,’ a homemade mortar that fires gas cylinders packed with explosives and shrapnel, is also totally unacceptable,” the High Commissioner said, noting that the use of such weapons constitutes indiscriminate attacks, as they are virtually impossible to aim correctly and have frequently killed and maimed civilians in Government-held areas. “As no military advantage can likely be gained from their use due to their inaccuracy, it must be concluded that their primary purpose is to terrorize the inhabitants of western Aleppo,” he added'']

There are other sources confirming that the rebels do indeed shell civilians and terrorize the population.--[[User:MyMoloboaccount|MyMoloboaccount]] ([[User talk:MyMoloboaccount|talk]]) 21:31, 15 October 2016 (UTC)

:The question though is whether or not they purposefully target the civilians, like the Russian and Syrian governments do, as military tactic. You know, like Luftwaffe strafing refugees on the roads in 1939, because that's pretty much what these two governments are doing. That's the difference. [[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 00:34, 16 October 2016 (UTC)

''The question though is whether or not they purposefully target the civilians, like the Russian and Syrian governments do, as military tactic.''
Of course they do, UN says so in the above statement and numerous sources state so as well. Why are you contesting this?  The rebels in Aleppo include internationally recognized terrorist groups.
''That's the difference. Also, this &quot;terrorize the population&quot;, I believe, is your own original, very POV, research and hyperbolic rhetoric which really just evidences your own biases in terms of editing this article''
What ? You realize this is a quote and statement from UN High Commissioner for Human Rights? And the rebels include groups who routinely behead and execute people ?
--[[User:MyMoloboaccount|MyMoloboaccount]] ([[User talk:MyMoloboaccount|talk]]) 00:42, 16 October 2016 (UTC)


Here, report on the groups in Aleppo who you state &quot;The question though is whether or not they purposefully target the civilians&quot; and that &quot;Also, this &quot;terrorize the population&quot;, I believe, is your own original, very POV&quot;

https://www.amnesty.org.uk/press-releases/syria-armed-opposition-group-committing-war-crimes-aleppo-new-evidence
  
''Armed groups surrounding the predominantly Kurdish Sheikh Maqsoud district of Aleppo city have repeatedly carried out indiscriminate attacks - possibly including with chemical weapons - that have struck civilian homes, markets and mosques, killing and injuring civilians, and have displayed a shameful disregard for human life, said Amnesty International today.
Amnesty International’s Middle East and North Africa Deputy Director Magdalena Mughrabi said: 
“The relentless pummelling of Sheikh Maqsoud has devastated the lives of civilians in the area. A wide array of armed groups from the Fatah Halab coalition has launched what appear to be repeated indiscriminate attacks that may amount to war crimes.
“By firing imprecise explosive weapons into civilian neighbourhoods the armed groups attacking Sheikh Maqsoud are flagrantly flouting the principle of distinction between civilian and military targets, a cardinal rule of international humanitarian law.
“The international community must not turn a blind eye to the mounting evidence of war crimes by armed opposition groups in Syria. The fact that the scale of war crimes by government forces is far greater is no excuse for tolerating serious violations by the opposition.” 

 --[[User:MyMoloboaccount|MyMoloboaccount]] ([[User talk:MyMoloboaccount|talk]]) 00:51, 16 October 2016 (UTC)

:It's terrible to realize there are people out here who prefer terrorists close to al-Qaida over Russia and its allies. Some people haven't realized yet the Cold War ended decades ago! [[User:Piotr Ukalev|Piotr Ukalev]] ([[User talk:Piotr Ukalev|talk]]) 22:54, 16 October 2016 (UTC)

*While the text about &quot;hell fire cannons&quot; ''might'' be disputable, [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Aleppo_(2012%E2%80%93present)&amp;diff=744649454&amp;oldid=744593877 this text] is about something different and clearly does not belong to the page because it describes events before this battle even started. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 23:18, 16 October 2016 (UTC)
*No it is not, it is about events during fight for Aleppo. Where did you get this idea?--[[User:MyMoloboaccount|MyMoloboaccount]] ([[User talk:MyMoloboaccount|talk]]) 00:03, 17 October 2016 (UTC)
::OK, but I think all such materials should be combined in a single section entitled as either as &quot;Human right abuses&quot; or &quot;War crimes&quot;. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 01:19, 17 October 2016 (UTC)

:::Thank you [[User:MyMoloboaccount|MyMoloboaccount]], this is very relevant to the article.[[User:GPRamirez5|GPRamirez5]] ([[User talk:GPRamirez5|talk]]) 18:26, 18 October 2016 (UTC)

==&quot;began ... as a part of the Syrian Civil War&quot;==
{{ping|EkoGraf}} Regarding [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Aleppo_(2012–present)&amp;diff=746532901&amp;oldid=746443367 this edit]. I know we are an encyclopedia, and I know historical context is important, but the grammatical structure you restored carries an implication that the battle outlasted the &quot;official end&quot; of the war and so at some point stopped being part of the Syrian Civil War. My wording doesn't take anything away from the context-setting function of the sentence, because no one is going to think it started before the Syrian Civil War and later became part of it. [[User:Hijiri88|Hijiri 88]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Hijiri88|聖]][[Special:Contributions/Hijiri88|やや]]&lt;/small&gt;) 09:43, 28 October 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Battle of Aleppo (2012–present)]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=746607888 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20161005053229/http://www.syriahr.com/en/?p=49141 to http://www.syriahr.com/en/?p=49141
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20161005053225/http://www.syriahr.com/en/?p=49158/ to http://www.syriahr.com/en/?p=49158/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 12:43, 28 October 2016 (UTC)

== US and Russia ==

Why are the US and Russia sectioned off from the rest of the belligerents? There's a line that separates them from the rest, and I'm wondering why. &lt;span style=&quot;background:black;border:1px;border-radius:10px;font-family:'century gothic'&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[User:WikiWinters|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00C9FF&quot;&gt;Wiki&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_talk:WikiWinters#top|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white&quot;&gt;Winters ☯ 韦安智&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt; 09:04, 30 October 2016 (UTC)

== Disputed claims ==

Page says that russisan and syrian forces indiscriminately bomb schools and hospitals. This has been proven to be misrepresentation of the facts, and that these &quot;schools&quot; and &quot;hospitals&quot; aren't used for their intended purpose, but as terrorist strongholds. See Vanessa Beeley reports as example. [[User:Mimosveta|Mimosveta]] ([[User talk:Mimosveta|talk]]) 09:49, 15 November 2016 (UTC)
: Welcome to the world of western propaganda.[[User:DerElektriker|DerElektriker]] ([[User talk:DerElektriker|talk]]) 06:30, 16 November 2016 (UTC)

== Terrorists ==

Why are terrorists in this article still called &quot;rebels&quot; ? There are nor &quot;rebels&quot; in Aleppo. It's a mix of different radical islamic groups. If we call them &quot;rebels&quot; then we need to call ISIL rebels to.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:DerElektriker|DerElektriker]] ([[User talk:DerElektriker#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/DerElektriker|contribs]]) 06:34, 16 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Not even ISIL should be called terrorists. And yes, calling ISIL &quot;rebels&quot; is perfectly legitimate for Wikipedia. It's just unpopular and &quot;militant&quot;, another relatively neutral term, is more commonly used instead. [[User:Editor abcdef|Editor abcdef]] ([[User talk:Editor abcdef|talk]]) 07:10, 16 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>6uxcux96si4ejevkuhq5dqm14a1dixw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
