<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Memorial Day</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>669953</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723331677</id>
      <parentid>723331611</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-02T12:17:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/69.23.47.219|69.23.47.219]] - &quot;/* Memorial Day / Decoration Day */&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17688">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Holidays|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=c|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=c|B-Class-1=no|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=yes|B-Class-4=yes|B-Class-5=yes|US-task-force=yes|ACW=yes|Memorials=y}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=c|importance=low}}}}
{{hightraffic|site=Fark|url=http://forums.fark.com/cgi/fark/comments.pl?IDLink=3627753|date=26 May 2008}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-05-31|oldid1=6717963|date2=2005-05-30|oldid2=16335231|date3=2006-05-29|oldid3=55493034|date4=2007-05-28|oldid4=134183296|date5=2008-05-26|oldid5=214966511|date6=2009-05-25|oldid6=292163546|date7=2010-05-31|oldid7=365278536|date8=2011-05-30|oldid8=431681311|date9=2012-05-28|oldid9=494712040|date10=2013-05-27|oldid10=556823927|date11=2014-05-26|oldid11=610098921|date12=2015-05-25|oldid12=663933593|date13=2016-05-30|oldid13=722805877}}
{{archives}}

== Proposed merge - Decoration Day ==

This article already contains all pertinent information about the origins of Memorial Day as Decoration Day, and continued observances of Decoration Days.  As the holiday is the primary topic for the term Decoration Day, I propose that [[Decoration Day]] be changed to a redirect to [[Memorial Day]].  The other meanings of the term (e.g. the film and Drive-By Truckers album) should be moved to [[Decoration Day (disambiguation)]].  Does anyone have any objections? [[User:Nick Number|Nick Number]] ([[User talk:Nick Number|talk]]) 15:10, 24 March 2015 (UTC)
*'''Support''' the proposed merge, as all other references invoke the holiday. [[User:BD2412|&lt;font style=&quot;background:gold&quot;&gt;'''''bd2412'''''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:BD2412|'''T''']] 15:20, 24 March 2015 (UTC)
* I '''support''' the merge as well for the above reasons. [[User:Wikiisawesome|wia]] ([[User talk:Wikiisawesome|talk]]) 12:12, 25 March 2015 (UTC)

::Merge complete. [[User:Nick Number|Nick Number]] ([[User talk:Nick Number|talk]]) 19:04, 30 March 2015 (UTC)

== Images ==

Two images on the page don't appear to be correct -- showing a picture of a ceiling fan?  Can someone fix this?
[[Special:Contributions/2601:A:5F00:65F:C448:4CC5:8826:D18B|2601:A:5F00:65F:C448:4CC5:8826:D18B]] ([[User talk:2601:A:5F00:65F:C448:4CC5:8826:D18B|talk]]) 04:22, 17 May 2015 (UTC)


Hello! The others noticed the picture, and if you have it, then we would be very grateful for your help. 
[[Special:Contributions/Kulamap]] ([[User talk:Kulamap|talk]]) 19:33, 25 May 2015 (UTC)

:Ok, glad to help. Let's start with a question: What, exactly, are you talking about? which image have you &quot;noticed&quot; and what would you like done about it? [[User:Beeblebrox|Beeblebrox]] ([[User talk:Beeblebrox|talk]]) 19:50, 25 May 2015 (UTC)

::Clicking on the image of the ceiling fan takes you to the wikimedia page which references its source https://catalog.archives.gov/id/558761 that page has the correct image  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.200.246.117|68.200.246.117]] ([[User talk:68.200.246.117|talk]]) 22:59, 25 May 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Picture is Wrong ==
A ceiling fan?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.47.218.100|71.47.218.100]] ([[User talk:71.47.218.100|talk]]) 14:14, 25 May 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:What ceiling fan?? - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 14:22, 25 May 2015 (UTC)

The picture with the caption &quot;Civil War Veterans in Ortonville, Minnesota, on the Fourth of July, 1880—also called &quot;Decoration Day&quot; prior to the Uniform Monday Holiday Act almost a century later.&quot;  Appears as a ceiling fan on my system It is on the right side of the screen in line with the sub Title  &quot;History of the Holiday&quot; 

Is the original picture available. Or should this image and caption be removed.
[[Special:Contributions/71.211.107.60|71.211.107.60]] ([[User talk:71.211.107.60|talk]]) 22:25, 25 May 2015 (UTC)N8Brad

== GregorianCalender/Whit Monday/table formatting ==

I have just removed a few things:
:*A mention in the lead that the date is determined by the [[Gregorian Calender]]
:*Extra formatting int he table of dates that showed when this coresponded with the unrelated [[Whit Monday]] holiday in other countries, again mentioning the Gregorian Calender

The reason I removed these is simple: All dates in prety much all western countries are based ont he Gregorian Calender. It has been in use in the U.S. since colonial times. And the times it coincided with the completely unrelated European religious holiday Whit Monday are utterly meaningless coincidences that do not add to the reader's understanding of either subject. 

That leaves one least thing: the re-formatting of the table of dates. It was vertically aligned, now it is horizontally aligned and if I may say rather confusing to look at. It also runs off the edge of the page, causing formatting that shrinks the text, making this page slightly more difficult to read on smaller screens. I propsoe it be changed back to the former alignment. [[User:Beeblebrox|Beeblebrox]] ([[User talk:Beeblebrox|talk]]) 18:50, 25 May 2015 (UTC)
{{collapse top|comparison of old and new versions}}
'''Old version:'''

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! colspan=5| Year
! Memorial Day
|-
| 1971 || 1999 || 2027 || 2055 || 2083 || May 31
|-
| 1972 || 2000 || 2028 || 2056 || 2084 || May 29
|-
| 1973 || 2001 || 2029 || 2057 || 2085 || May 28
|-
| 1974 || 2002 || 2030 || 2058 || 2086 || May 27
|-
| 1975 || 2003 || 2031 || 2059 || 2087 || May 26
|-
| 1976 || 2004 || 2032 || 2060 || 2088 || May 31
|-
| 1977 || 2005 || 2033 || 2061 || 2089 || May 30
|-
| 1978 || 2006 || 2034 || 2062 || 2090 || May 29
|-
| 1979 || 2007 || 2035 || 2063 || 2091 || May 28
|-
| 1980 || 2008 || 2036 || 2064 || 2092 || May 26
|-
| 1981 || 2009 || 2037 || 2065 || 2093 || May 25
|-
| 1982 || 2010 || 2038 || 2066 || 2094 || May 31
|-
| 1983 || 2011 || 2039 || 2067 || 2095 || May 30
|-
| 1984 || 2012 || 2040 || 2068 || 2096 || May 28
|-
| 1985 || 2013 || 2041 || 2069 || 2097 || May 27
|-
| 1986 || 2014 || 2042 || 2070 || 2098 || May 26
|-
| 1987 || 2015 || 2043 || 2071 || 2099 || May 25
|-
| 1988 || 2016 || 2044 || 2072 ||  || May 30
|-
| 1989 || 2017 || 2045 || 2073 ||  || May 29
|-
| 1990 || 2018 || 2046 || 2074 ||  || May 28
|-
| 1991 || 2019 || 2047 || 2075 ||  || May 27
|-
| 1992 || 2020 || 2048 || 2076 ||  || May 25
|-
| 1993 || 2021 || 2049 || 2077 ||  || May 31
|-
| 1994 || 2022 || 2050 || 2078 ||  || May 30
|-
| 1995 || 2023 || 2051 || 2079 ||  || May 29
|-
| 1996 || 2024 || 2052 || 2080 ||  || May 27
|-
| 1997 || 2025 || 2053 || 2081 ||  || May 26
|-
| 1998 || 2026 || 2054 || 2082 ||  || May 25
|}

'''New version'''

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! colspan=23| Year
! Memorial Day
|-
| 1971 || 1976 || 1982 ||      || 1993 || 1999 || 2004 || 2010 ||      || 2021 || 2027 || 2032 || 2038 ||      || 2049 || 2055 || 2060 || 2066 || 2083 || 2077 || 2083 || 2088 || 2094 || May 31
|-
|      || 1977 || 1983 || 1988 || 1994 ||      || 2005 || 2011 || 2016 || 2022 ||      || 2033 || 2039 || 2044 || 2050 ||      || 2061 || 2067 || 2072 || 2078 ||      || 2089 || 2095 || May 30
|-
| 1972 || 1978 ||      || 1989 || 1995 || 2000 || 2006 ||      || 2017 || 2023 || 2028 || 2034 ||      || 2045 || 2051 || 2056 || 2062 ||      || 2073 || 2079 || 2084 || 2090 ||      || May 29
|-
| 1973 || 1979 || 1984 || 1990 ||      || 2001 || 2007 || 2012 || 2018 ||      || 2029 || 2035 || 2040 || 2046 ||      || 2057 || 2063 || 2068 || 2074 ||      || 2085 || 2091 || 2096 || May 28
|-
| 1974 ||      || 1985 || 1991 || 1996 || 2002 ||     || 2013 || 2019 || 2024 || 2030 ||      || 2041 || 2047 || 2052  || 2058 ||      || 2069 || 2075 || 2080 || 2086 ||      || 2097 || May 27
|-
| 1975 || 1980 || 1986 ||       || 1997 || 2003 || 2008 || 2014 ||     || 2025 || 2031 || 2036 || 2042 ||      || 2053 || 2059 || 2064 || 2070 ||      || 2081 || 2087 || 2092 || 2098 || May 26
|-
|      || 1981 || 1987 || 1992 || 1998 ||       || 2009 || 2015 || 2020 || 2026 ||     || 2037 || 2043 || 2048 || 2054 ||      || 2065 || 2071 || 2076 || 2082 ||      || 2093 || 2099 || May 25
|}
{{collapse bottom}}

:Allright then, {{done}}. [[User:Beeblebrox|Beeblebrox]] ([[User talk:Beeblebrox|talk]]) 19:43, 2 June 2015 (UTC)

== Strange Claims ==

The article says: &quot;n June 28, 1968, the Congress passed the Uniform Monday Holiday Act, which moved four holidays, including Memorial Day, from their traditional dates to a specified Monday in order to create a convenient three-day weekend.[40] The change moved Memorial Day from its traditional May 30 date to the last Monday in May. The law took effect at the federal level in 1971.[40]&quot;

1. It was not moved to a Monday to make a &quot;convenient three-day weekend.&quot; 2. As the article shows, May 30th was only the day for one organization. 3. The source is to the law and does not make these fringe claims. Someone obviously messed around with the article to try to disparage the holiday. [[Special:Contributions/173.153.9.202|173.153.9.202]] ([[User talk:173.153.9.202|talk]]) 21:42, 25 May 2015 (UTC)
&quot;The VFW stated in a 2002 Memorial Day Address:
&quot;Changing the date merely to create three-day weekends has undermined the very meaning of the day. No doubt, this has contributed a lot to the general public's nonchalant observance of Memorial Day.[41]
This is also not in the source. Why are there so many claims like that with faked sources?[[Special:Contributions/173.153.9.202|173.153.9.202]] ([[User talk:173.153.9.202|talk]]) 21:52, 25 May 2015 (UTC)
:It was moved to create more three-day weekends, at least according to the president who signed it into law [http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/?pid=28963]. It's neither a fringe claim nor disparaging to say so. [[User:Calidum|Calidum]] [[User talk:Calidum|T]]&amp;#124;[[Special:Contributions/Calidum|C]] 21:53, 25 May 2015 (UTC)
::[[WP:VERIFIABILITY]] - those aren't cited and yes, it is a negative claim. Your link doesn't say what the article claims and instead says that it was moved to ensure that the Federal Government was not closed in the middle of the week (&quot;he costs will be offset to an important degree by avoiding disruptions of Government business through Monday observance of holidays. &quot;). That is a very different reason. Your link says that fixing the date helps families get together. It also doesn't say that May 30th was the &quot;true&quot; date or make a claim about the VFW wanting May 30th. Wikipedia pages shouldn't be home to false information hidden behind reference notes that don't say what is being claimed. This site has a lot of problems with that. [[Special:Contributions/173.153.7.11|173.153.7.11]] ([[User talk:173.153.7.11|talk]]) 22:43, 25 May 2015 (UTC)
:::I most certainly do see the bit about bringing families together in Johnson's remarks. He also said the bit about saving moey for both governmental and private entities. They are not mutually exclusive. As the text of his remarks are uncopyrightable I am simply going to reproduce the whole thing here so we can all easily see it.
&lt;blockquote&gt;THE BILL that we sign today will help Americans to enjoy more fully the country that is their magnificent heritage. It will also aid the work of Government and bring new efficiency to our economy.

This bill provides that three of our national holidays will be celebrated on Monday:
--Washington's Birthday on the third Monday in February,
--Memorial Day on the last Monday in May,
--Veterans Day on the fourth Monday in October. The bill will take effect on January 1, 1971. State legislatures will thus have time to act for observances in local government offices and in private employment.

This will mean a great deal to our families and our children. It will enable families who live some distance apart to spend more time together. Americans will be able to travel farther and see more of this beautiful land of ours. They will be able to participate in a wider range of recreational and cultural activities.
The bill also establishes Columbus Day as a Federal holiday--to be celebrated on the second Monday in October. Thirty-four of our States have already established a day honoring Christopher Columbus. It is fitting now that we give national expression to our faith in the spirit of discovery embodied by this great adventurer. This new holiday will henceforth honor one of our finest and most cherished national characteristics--our ability to live and work together, men and women of all national origins, as one united and progressive nation.

The provisions of this bill insure a '''minimum of five regularly recurring 3-day weekends''' each year for Federal employees. The costs will be offset to an important degree by avoiding disruptions of Government business through Monday observance of holidays.

The private employer will enjoy similar gains in efficiency. The Monday holiday will stimulate greater industrial and commercial production, sparing business and labor the '''penalty of midweek shutdowns.'''&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[User:Beeblebrox|Beeblebrox]] ([[User talk:Beeblebrox|talk]]) 02:02, 29 May 2015 (UTC)
:::three day weekends was an explicit goal. &amp; LBJ mentions that midweek holidays are disruptive. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 02:13, 29 May 2015 (UTC)

== Initial sentence is wrong. ==

Initial sentence says 
Memorial Day is a federal holiday in the United States for remembering the people who died while serving in the country's armed forces.[1] 

That is false

This is a legal federal holiday that should point to the federal laws informing the article  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2602:306:80A5:90:ADD7:8D2C:9146:B8C8|2602:306:80A5:90:ADD7:8D2C:9146:B8C8]] ([[User talk:2602:306:80A5:90:ADD7:8D2C:9146:B8C8|talk]]) 01:53, 19 November 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Memorial Day / Decoration Day ==

[[Special:Contributions/74.219.48.158|74.219.48.158]] ([[User talk:74.219.48.158|talk]]) 18:07, 26 May 2016 (UTC)current article starts out with a claim in 1868 for Decatur, Il starting Decoration Day.

its looks like Waterloo NY also shares a claim to first Decoration in 1866, supported by Lyndon Johnson and affirmation by senate and house.

only offering.

Dennis

[[Special:Contributions/74.219.48.158|74.219.48.158]] ([[User talk:74.219.48.158|talk]]) 18:07, 26 May 2016 (UTC)

Being that Decoration Day didn't exist as a nationwide day of observance until May 1868, Ironton is most likely laying claim to having the oldest continuously running Memorial Day parade based off of the official start of the federal holiday. Before 1868, any day of observance was local or regional and not nationwide. These parades and celebrations would not be official &quot;Decoration Day&quot; events because Decoration Day didn't yet exist as declared by the federal government. Any events happening before would be more in line with local remembrances rather than national and it is very likely that communities were remembering their fallen as far back as the Revolutionary War. Although the purposes are the same in that fallen soldiers were memorialized, saying an event in 1866 or 1867 is a &quot;Memorial Day event&quot; would be incorrect since there was no official Memorial Day declared yet.  

Ironton held its first Decoration Day parade the very day that John A. Logan, the commander-in-chief of the Grand Army of the Republic called for the national observance of Decoration Day, pulling from a tradition that began in the south. That was May 5, 1868. It has been difficult to find when the other communities held their first parades. What I have found so far are just years and not months or days. It is possible that Ironton's parade is older by days rather than the number of parades after the official declaration that Decoration Day would be observed nationwide. The U.S. Congress has recognized Ironton as having the longest continuously running Memorial Day Parade in the nation. There are some other communities that have laid such claim, but it was found that they skipped a year or two, particularly during wartime. 

-Ginger  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.23.47.219|69.23.47.219]] ([[User talk:69.23.47.219|talk]]) 12:16, 2 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Memorial Day  ==

The source (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memorial_Day#cite_note-6) for the differentiation between Memorial Day and Veteran's Day seems to be a questionable source.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.101.36.181|99.101.36.181]] ([[User talk:99.101.36.181|talk]]) 21:11, 31 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Why is a daily published newspaper, the [[Baltimore Sun]], a questionable source? - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 22:37, 31 May 2016 (UTC)
::The IP's objection to it could be based on it being an opinion piece, but the claim itself (Memorial Day is for those died; Veterans Day is for all veterans) isn't [[WP:EXTRAORDINARY|extraordinary]]. '''&lt;span style=&quot;border: 1px blue solid;background:Cyan&quot;&gt;[[User:Calidum|&lt;font color=&quot;#4863A0&quot;&gt;Calidum&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Calidum|&lt;font color=&quot;#A18648&quot;&gt;¤&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;''' 23:07, 31 May 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lmlirsca7o5ot9qk43td0d8l4klhifr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
