<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Bannockburn</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2662201</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748332069</id>
      <parentid>748331978</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T17:50:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/94.199.236.88|94.199.236.88]] - &quot;&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="121165">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Military History|importance=High
|class=c|B-Class-1=no|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=yes|B-Class-4=yes|B-Class-5=yes
|British-task-force=yes|Middle-Ages-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Scotland|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject England|class=c|importance=mid}}}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-06-24|oldid1=15781459|date2=2006-06-24|oldid2=60371006|date3=2007-06-24|oldid3=140242512|date4=2008-06-24|oldid4=221544532|date5=2009-06-24|oldid5=298268662|date6=2010-06-24|oldid6=369657814|date7=2014-06-24|oldid7=614205676}}

== Casualties. ==

Where on earth did the figure of 4000 Scots casualties at Bannockburn come from?  Such a loss-a casualty rate of close on 50%- would make Bannockburn a pyrrhic victory in every sense of the term.  The truth is we have no precise information on casualty rates for either side; but as the Scottish schiltrons were not penetrated by Edward's cavalry, and as his archers were dispersed at an early stage, King Robert's losses are likely to have been modest.
[[User:Rcpaterson|Rcpaterson]] 06:01, 13 June 2006 (UTC)

Totally agree, but someone else dosen't. I don't know what source is being used for 4,000 casualties. The casualties box previously read, &quot;unknown but light&quot; I'm going to change it to hundreds, but will be perfectly happy to back down if someone provides a source, because 4,000 is absoulute nonsense.  --[[User:Lochheart|Lochheart]] ([[User talk:Lochheart|talk]]) 17:28, 9 December 2009 (UTC)

:Instead of responding to a 3+ yr old post, removing a reference, removing referenced information and simply re-inserting &quot;''Hundreds''&quot; with NO reference, it would have been better to supply a reference to replace what you call ''absolute nonsense''. Here on wikipedia, facts(from 3rd party published sources) are considered [[Wikipedia:Reliable sources|reliable sources]] '''not''' your personal opinion. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 18:57, 9 December 2009 (UTC)

It just so happens that this is the box for discussion on casualties. That is secondary source and therefore an author's opinion. We know,(stated in the article) that the trained soldiers numbered 6,000 - 7,000 and that this was likley nearly all of Bruce's trained infantry, we also know that in 1315, Edward Bruce landed 6,000 trained soldiers in Ireland ([[Edward Bruce]] under invasion of Ireland). If these aren't the same men, (and I'm not saying they are or not), it would have been impossible for Bruce to recruit and train these men with only 2,000 - 3,000 while continueing his campaign. --[[User:Lochheart|Lochheart]] ([[User talk:Lochheart|talk]]) 17:10, 10 December 2009 (UTC)

::FYI, you SERIOUSLY need to read [[Wikipedia:Reliable sources]]. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 02:36, 11 December 2009 (UTC)

:::[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] is right that Wikipedia should rely on published sources, not speculation.  However, [[User:Lochheart|Lochheart]] is right to say there are problems with the figures.  Both numbers of participants estimates come from the same book - Grant.  The casualties come from three different ones - Sadler, Mackenzie and Grant.  There is no reason why they should fit together, because they are all taken out of the author's reasoned context. The text makes different judgements again. It is one of the perils of the Wikipedia colaborative editing philosophy. There are, as I see it, two solutions. We could make the info box consistent with the text by taking the text numbers into the info box. Alternatively, we could have a reasoned discussion on the casualty rates quoted by authors and how they fit with their troop numbers to reach a consensus as collaborating editors - which is why Wikipedia has talk pages. Can I suggest interested editors look at the sources we have used in the article and their rationales and report back? We then seek consensus on the best ranges to place in the info box and thereafter defend it against change not discussed on talk first?[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 08:00, 11 December 2009 (UTC)

===Dryfield or Carse?===

There is no evidence whatsoever of heavy Scottish casualties at Bannockburn, although all of the primary sources state that English losses were heavy. 

Any author guessing at Scottish losses being heavy is using conjecture or mere opinion as no primary source states this or even suggests that this is so.

The reason for the lighter losses of the Scottish army can be gleaned from the sources themselves which show that the English were attacked in their camp at first light (very early in Stirling on June 24th) and were surprised by the rapid ground made by the three schiltrons which eventually spread out to form a narrower band that stretched from the Pelstream to the &quot;great bend&quot; of the Bannockburn. 
Therefore the English army was completely ''unprepared'' to respond, and then further rendered ''unable'' to respond as well; this was due to them being hemmed in by the streams at either side and behind them, the very reason that the camp was an excellent choice the night before as both a place for water and affording protection. 

The protection of the streams the night before thereafter became their prison, the army of England was hemmed in; when attacked at dawn by the Scots, the English cavalry was unable to get up the required speed for a cavalry charge, due to having their field of charge substantially reduced by the Scottish tactics employed rapidly by foot-soldiers alone, (no cavalry in any primary source).

These foot soldiers included the Scottish King himself Robert I,  right at the front according to the primary sources. 

Imagine that fact about the Bruce alone as a king within the European context and the unknown principle of man of the people. 

The pre-planned tactics of the Scots, surprising the English in their camp led to chaos and confusion. The English army, unable to deploy or use thier probable military superiority to good effect as they could have so easily had they been ''allowed'' to choose the battle site, lost the battle. 

The choice of battle site was decided by the Scots. 

The primary sources give ample evidence of this fact; that, at dawn,  the English army was surprised and attacked within the area they had chosen to camp in the night before. There is no primary or secondary source that states otherwise.

One of the reasons for the low casualty rate for the Scots was that they had a plan, they were well drilled, well prepared and ''chose'' the site for a battle. Once the tactics were deployed, the battle was as good as won.

One of the biggest failings in the historical community, at least those that support the Dryfield, is that they dismiss the Carse of Balquhiderock because the English Army &quot;wouldn't have chosen to fight there&quot;, (I have heard at least two historians state this personally) and yet even the Dryfield theorists all agree that the English army camped within the carse. There is no evidence in any source of the English army traipsing up the formidable slopes of the Dryfield (held by the Scots through battle the day before for good reason) or any reason why the Scots would allow them to gain entry to this area the following day; a formidable military endeavour in itself from the carse against a determined Scottish army. 

This military feat, where the Scots allowed the English army to occupy an area the next day, an area they had defended so vigorously and successfully only the day before, would have been noted by the primary sources, mentioned at the very least. It would have been a sight to behold and write about, even without an opponent positioned on higher ground determined to oppose you to the death.


I hope we can work together and improve the Bannockburn article.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kinghob|contribs]]) 20:24, 11 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;--[[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]]) 21:02, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

:: I have taken the opportunity to edit this post into a connected subsection because it is actually a more fundamental point about the battle than the argument on casualty figures.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 11:24, 13 February 2010 (UTC)

I have cut out the part relating to casualties in favour of the larger discussion on the Battle site for the destruction of Edward's cavalry.
At risk of giving proponents of both the Dryfield site and the carse apoplexy I would like to propose a third alternative where Edward camped his cavalry.
 Very few people are aware that the Bannock burn had two tributaries running through the Bannocburn area. There was an upper and a lower tributary that ran roughly parallel to each other. The one everybody knows about is the lower one than ran and still runs through the great ravine from Whins of Milton. That is the burn that today people refer to as the Bannock burn and so it is assumed that when historical references to crossing it are made, this is the burn they are talking about. Is this a safe assumption, or a misconception that has arisen over the passing of centuries and one watercourse gaining more importance than the other as an industrious community grew from a tiny settlement of cot houses in 1314?
As best I can I will argue this is a misconception and not a safe assumption at all. The upper tributary originally ran east from beyond Pirnhall past Corbywood and right past where the small settlement was, entering present day Bannockburn at Stein Square. From there on it ran through a steepening gulley some 350 yards or so parallel to the great ravine and steepening into a ravine itself beyond Ochilmount. From there it ran down to the carse where it intersected with the lower burn not far out on it. What lay between the two burns was a roughly u shaped promontory of high ground with no way up to it or down from it other than the open end of the u. Once a force blocked that open end the only way to try and get out was via the steep gulley of the upper burn. For those mystified why no one can find anything resembling the well known &quot;evil ditch&quot; term along the Bannock on the carse, that is your answer. It was never down there, it was up on the high ground above the mouth of the great ravine and on the upper tributary not the lower one. I say was, because little remains of the gulley now after it was filled in and housing built over it. The burn that ran through it has been diverted buried and obliterated and now there is not much more than a trickle running through where the steeper ravine part still exists. You can still see it on a Google map of Bannockburn. To the right of the obvious blue line of the lower burn a thin unnamed blue line still runs up from where the two burns join on the carse only to stop dead where it says Cowie Rd. The upper burn is the one the settlement drew its water from. It was the important heart and lifeblood of the settlement. To them that was the Bannock burn in 1314. I would argue that in that day it was also likely the larger water course of the two in volume.
Why do I argue this? Over the centuries the tiny settlement slowly grew into a village, particularly with the development of water power. Mills were built down in the great ravine. Some may remember the Wilson tartan textile mill that was once there. Water was diverted from other burns, including the upper tributary to increase the water flow for the mill wheels and dams were built for the same purpose. The size and volume of that burn down in the great ravine today bears no relation to it's size and volume in 1314. It's size is entirely artificial and in 1314 it is quite possible it was no larger a body of water than the burn running through the Dollar glen is today. Due to the development of the local industries in the great ravine, the lower tributary became the important heart and lifeblood of the community. It became the important burn that signified the name Bannockburn and somewhere in that period the lower tributary took on recognition as the Bannock burn and the original bearer of the name above became a forgotten irrelevance. By the time people no longer needed to carry water from a burn, it had no relevance at all. By the early 1960's it was just a nuisance that kept bursting its banks and flooding the adjacent fields, so they diverted even more of it away and buried it in a pipe all the way to Stein Square in Bannockburn. I am well aware it is impossible to prove this happened, but I challenge anyone to disprove what I have said about the artificial altering and reversals in size of the two water courses and the new importance and relevance of the lower tributary with the advent of water power. Impossible to prove yes, but still logical reasoning, backed up by the evidence of alteration. The burn referred to as the Bannock burn in 1314 is not the burn running through the great ravine, its the upper tributary that ran parallel with it on the higher ground. I'm sure many are thinking not nearly enough at this point and they would right, there's more.
In 2001 the then local council archaeologist published an old aerial photograph she'd found in the archives in the Stirling Observer. It showed an extensive honeycomb of circles that she believed were Bruce's pits. What struck me about it was the location. They were in the Pirnhall area. Not north of today's Bannock burn, south of it? In fact they occupied the area between where the upper burn ran and the lower one ran all around the line of the old Roman road. I questioned her on this and she confirmed that was the area shown on the photograph. She was understandably confused how the vanguard could have crossed the Bannock from the south and fell into the pits when the pits were south of the burn not north of it. In fact that confusion has apparently resulted in that location still not being investigated to this day. She also informed me of something else she had found confusing in that they had found remnants of wooden stakes embedded in the north bank of the Bannock suggesting that Bruce had prepared a defensive position on the north bank of the burn. That and the location of the pit circles ran counter to the entire historical account of the vanguard crossing the bannock and falling into the pits before encountering Bruce's line. How could Bruce's defensive line be at the Bannock itself and the pits be south of it? I pointed out that the small length of burn between the end of the great ravine and Milton bog at the ford over that burn was exactly where you would put a defensive line, with the burn itself as a further obstacle in front of you for the cavalry. Why it has to be asked would Bruce not use that ideal defensive position and let Edward cross it unchallenged? The lady agreed but couldn't fathom the discrepancy with the historical account. I put it to her that there used to be another Bannock tributary south of there and that was more likely to be the burn they were referring to. Then there was no contradiction with the accounts, merely a misconception on our part which burn they were talking about. I then offered to show the lady what was left of it and where the lost &quot;evil ditch&quot; actually was. To say she was astonished on seeing the site was putting it mildly, she had no idea the upper ravine existed, but even though a large part of the gulley running to Stein Square had been filled in and built over the depth of it could still be discerned from the large dip down in the old Cowie road as was. She also noted that three schiltrons in close order would entirely block any other avenue of escape but that gulley. It was the worst imaginable trap for cavalry not just hemmed in  between two burns but on a high promontory between two deadly ravines. Unfortunately as she sadly put it at the time however impressive the trap might be, it would not be politically acceptable to her employers. How right she was.
Before anyone explodes because I am not mentioning clues relating to the carse I will come to that, but first I would like to pose a question. It must be remembered that when Edward gave up at Milton re crossed the Bannock and turned east the foot and archers were still hours behind on the road. There was only cavalry when Edward went east and crossed the Bannock burn one last time to camp. Why then would Edward ignore high dry ground, firm safe footing for horses, good grass and accessible water, to go down on the carse and camp on a bog? Why would they do that? You would send the peasants down there when they turned up yes, but the aristocracy with their horses. I think not. There was nothing forcing the cavalry to go down there. They were not being pursued, it did not even occur to them the Scots would leave their positions and attack them. What possible reason is there for going down off the good ground to that bog. The answer is none, and they didn't. The burn they crossed for the third time before camping, was the upper tributary, not the lower one and that put them south of the burn in the great ravine not north of it, because in 1314 the burn they called the Bannock ran through the high ground, not the ravine.
Why do I say it was a bog between the two burns on the carse? 10.000 years ago the entire carse was under water. It was the bed of an inland sea. An excavation up near the university once revealed the skeleton of a long beached whale. Anyone who cares to walk up the slope at Balquhiderock Wood will find at the top edge where the ground under turf is exposed that it's actually sand, because once it was a beach. There is similar evidence of that near Ochilmount at the top end of Bannockburn. That is why there is only a bare foot or so of soil down on that carse and below that if you dig is some 30 feet of blue clay. The houses they built closest to the railway line would shake like a jelly every time a train came past if they hadn't driven steel piles deep down into the clay first to prevent it. That's why water doesn't drain from there, not just because it's low ground, but because the clay that made the whole area a clay bog won't let it. 700 years ago before a system of drainage ditches was dug to run the worst of the water off it was a whole lot worse. It is not a matter of dispute, it is fact that it was a marsh, a bog, call it what you like, but you would not take horses out there. Clifford was unable to bypass Moray and Douglas at the Pelstream ford for two reasons. They could not ride up the ridge on the left on horseback and they could not get past to their right. Not because the Pelstream itself was so impassable away from the foot of the ridge, but because as soon as you left the foot of the ridge you were riding your horses into soft bog and liable to break their legs. These were seasoned horsemen, not fools.
What about the historical references I have ignored, pointing to the carse? Let's get to it. There were campfires seen at night all over the carse. Absolutely. No one is denying that the peasants were sent down to camp in that bog, that's where the foot and the archers were. Good enough for them, not good enough for the nobility and commanders and too dangerous for valuable horses. As ever, the poor bloody infantry.
There were many pools and powys. This has understandably led many people to assume that everybody was down in the carse, but we don't know what's first hand and what's second hand here. We don't know if this is only a reference to the final struggle that did take place on the carse, but only after Edward's cavalry had been slaughtered on higher ground, and the remnants had fled the field with the king. There is no doubt that there was an attempt to rally the still intact if disheartened foot down on that carse. There is also no doubt that it was a long struggle far different from the easy slaughter of the cavalry. Why was it so easy? Why did it take so long to organize the foot and the archers? Why were the cavalry overwhelmed before the foot and most of the archers even got going let alone engaged? The commanders and the low born were not camped in the same place, that is why. That is why the commanders failed to organize them until it was too late for Edward. That is why they took so long to get to the fight. That is why when they finally got there they couldn't help because of the press. Not because they were wedged between two burns, but because when they finally struggled up the slopes of that promontory there was so much press up there right to the back of it, they couldn't do a thing to help. The next thing they saw was the King and some surviving knights fleeing below them along the foot of the ridge and they panicked and ran back themselves until an attempt was made to rally them and save the day. As for the archers Keith dispersed. Those who contend that they were positioned behind Edward between two &quot;impenetrable&quot; burns and were chased off by Keith's cavalry need to consider this obvious question. If there was so much press and no room out there, how on earth did Keith manage to cross one of those &quot;impenetrable burns&quot; with his cavalry to chase them off? Did he just charge through his own schiltrons in the way? Of course not, because it didn't happen there. The archers who managed to get up the slope to enter the fight got up onto the not very elevated Ochilmount. There they were behind and a little south of their own men on the south side of the upper burn and gulley. It was from that position they were doing damage to both sides. From there they were easily chased off by Keith's cavalry, with no press to get through and no &quot;impenetrable&quot; burn to stop them. That left Bruce's archers free to take up the position, from where they could decimate any foot trying to follow the same route up Edward's archers came. One last point I would like to make concerns attempts by people who believe Edward camped down on the carse, to find the &quot;evil ditch&quot; on the course of the Bannock down there. Edward made his escape in the direction of the castle, that is where he went. If Edward was down on the carse, then the direction he surely went trying to escape from there was north towards the castle. That means the burn he escaped across would have been the Pelstream, not the Bannock burn.  It defeats me why people who believe Edward was on the carse insist on looking for the &quot;evil ditch&quot; in the opposite direction to the Castle along the Bannock. There is just no logic in that at all. If there was some terrible ditch there why not head straight for the castle across the Pelstream rather than the opposite direction?
Well I've made my case contentious though it is and doubt it will have pleased anyone. I have done it without being vitriolic, insulting, or abusive to anyone else and I wish more people would do the same. People are not stupid, idiots,or undeniably wrong because they disagree with me. They are just trying to make sense out of scarce information and missing confirmation and will do so in different ways. An open mind can still make errors, but an entrenched mind will never correct them. I expect no praise for this controversial effort and I'm sure I will not be disappointed. My thanks to anyone who got the whole way through without spontaneously combusting[[User:2001perseus|2001perseus]] ([[User talk:2001perseus|talk]]) 22:40, 14 July 2014 (UTC)

:This is too long. No one is going to wade through this to find your point. Please put it briefly and clearly.--&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Black Chancery;text:grey 0.3em 0.3em 0.1em;&quot;&gt;'''[[User:Sabrebd|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;SabreBD&lt;/span&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Sabrebd|talk&lt;/span&gt;]]) 00:12, 15 July 2014 (UTC)

== Headline text ==

Isn't the [[Robert Burns|Robert Burns']] poem Bannockburn [[Scots Wha Hae]]? [[User:Rshu|Rshu]] 14:02, 24 June 2006 (UTC)

I think you are right.  I left this section, though, as it stands.  Please edit as you wish.
[[User:Rcpaterson|Rcpaterson]] 22:52, 24 June 2006 (UTC)

RE: 'The Battle of Bannockburn (Blàr Allt a' Bhonnaich in Gaelic) (June 24, 1314) was a significant Scottish victory in the Wars of Scottish Independence. It was the decisive battle in the First War of Scottish Independence. According to William Wallace, the Scottish fought like &quot;warrior-poets.&quot;' -- Wallace died in 1305, I think you're quoting Mel Gibson....  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/208.57.242.194|208.57.242.194]] ([[User talk:208.57.242.194|talk]]) 22:10, 24 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Lead image. ==

Would it be possible to get a better image? I know this is an ancient battle, but one that we have to label as &quot;fanciful&quot; doens't seem to add much to the understanding of the articel... [[User:68.39.174.238|68.39.174.238]] 03:06, 14 July 2006 (UTC)

It's actually laughable in its silliness.  Bruce's troops would not have worn kilts.  Besides, the kilt shown-the short or small kilt-did not appear in Scotland until the eighteenth century.
[[User:Rcpaterson|Rcpaterson]] 16:29, 14 July 2006 (UTC)
Mr Paterson is absolutely right. Surely a better image can be found.....the Corpus Christi MS, illustration from Bower ?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.166.178.92|86.166.178.92]] ([[User talk:86.166.178.92|talk]]) 17:58, 16 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I just added an alternative. An editor more familiar with the subject may wish to consider moving this (almost contemporaneous) image into the infobox. To replace the romantic/&quot;fanciful&quot; bit of Victorian nostalgia currently extant. [[User:Guliolopez|Guliolopez]] ([[User talk:Guliolopez|talk]]) 23:11, 21 September 2008 (UTC)

::Seeing as there doesn't seem to be any objection or other insights, I'm just going to &quot;swap&quot; the two images. And move the Victorian illustration out of the infobox in favour of the more contemporaneous image. [[User:Guliolopez|Guliolopez]] ([[User talk:Guliolopez|talk]]) 18:06, 8 October 2008 (UTC)

:::Good image but not of Bannockburn (it's a biblical battle - no idea which one).  I've adjusted the caption.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 15:54, 5 July 2009 (UTC)

Ok this has been reverted with a challenge - legitimate, as I hadn't give my reasons..  The problem has arisen because someone in placing the image on commons has said it is an image of Bannockburn, and this has propagated on the web through mirrors.  Interestingly, there is a version on the web called Battle of Berwick, which is equally erroneous.  The Holkham Bible isn't a bible translation but a set of bible stories.  The image is in the Apocalypse section and it's caption translates as &quot;The Great fight each other: Likewise the Commons&quot;.  We see the great at the top, the commons at the bottom.  You can find the image in WO Hassall's facsimile edition here [http://posner.library.cmu.edu/Posner/books/book.cgi?call=741.64_H35H_1954] - it's Folio 40. Caption is listed at the beginning.  Worth taking the time to look at some of the pictures - there are quite a lot of arms &amp; armour pictures here which don't get published much.  Can I recommend to the revision on grounds of accuracy? [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 21:45, 6 July 2009 (UTC)
:I appreciate your response here, [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]], and I defer to your knowledge and judgment on this matter, as you have obviously done your research. ---&lt;font face=&quot;Georgia&quot;&gt;'''[[User:RepublicanJacobite|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#009900&quot;&gt;RepublicanJacobite&lt;/span&gt;]]'''&lt;sub&gt;''[[User talk:RepublicanJacobite|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#006600&quot;&gt;The'FortyFive'&lt;/span&gt;]]''&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 23:47, 6 July 2009 (UTC)

== The King's Rebuke. ==

I realise that this is a page that is going to atttract all sorts of attention, informed or not. The amendments concerning Barbour and the Bruce-Mowbray Pact were both ''very'' clumsy in wording and profoundly ill-informed.  Barbour may have writen in verse but he is first and foremost a chronicler and historian, one of the chief sources we have for the life and campaigns of Robert Bruce.  Like most medieval chroniclers he is far from perfect and prone, on occasion, to considerable exaggeration; but his epic is based on conversations with those who had served and fought with Bruce, and much of the detail stands up to historical scrutiny.  To claim that his rebuke to his brother was an 'invention' without any supporting evidence is intellectually shallow.  Bruce's whole strategy since 1307 had been based on the avoidance of battle with the main English army; Edward's pact now committed him to the defense of a static position, the very opposite of guerilla warfare.  His rebuke was both likely and justified.  Edit wisely and think carefully.
[[User:Rcpaterson|Rcpaterson]] 04:25, 14 July 2006 (UTC)
More complicated than that really....The surrender of castles through pacxts of thia nature was an ordinary aspect of medieval war...it seems probable that Dundee fell to the Scots in 1312 by just such a measure. 

Surely the point of King Robert's rebuke was that Stirling was the premier stronghold of Scotland. Lose it and Edward had lost control of the whole of the kingdom north of the Forth.  The fact that Edward Bruce had allowed him a year and a day to relieve the castle meant that he had time to raise a large army and guaranteed a full scale invasion.  Up to that point the English ruling classes were split, weakening their effort. The challenge (for such it was) meant that they would come together in opposition to Bruce, something he wanted to avoid. [[User:Andygm|Andygm]] ([[User talk:Andygm|talk]]) 15:17, 8 August 2009 (UTC)

'Guerilla' warfare is a challenging term in a medieval context. Most of the fighting, at least from 1308-9,  was conducted by men-a-arms - knights in armour if you like - as was the case in France, Spain, the Low Countries. Also - Barbour was at pains to paint Edward Bruce as rash in order to enhance the reputation of Robert.

:I think it's a mistake to read too much into the use of &quot;men-at-arms.&quot;  While the forces Robert Bruce deployed in this period were made up largely of men who would have corresponded to the &quot;men-at-arms&quot; of other societies of the period in terms of social standing, they were not equipped in the same way that a Continental - or English - force would be.  The armies that Bruce was fielding were a mix of mounted spearmen who rode to battle but fought on foot and lightly mounted cavalry with relatively minimal armor and smaller, more agile horses.  There was no heavy cavalry analog in the Scottish armies of the period, and at the beginning of the 14th century, heavy cavalry remained the primary offensive striking arm in pitched battle.  Clearly, this was not an army built for pitched battle.
''iNTERESTING....BUT IT WOULD BE NICE TO SEE SOME EVIDENCE-BASED SUPPORT FOR THIS SUGGESTION. RECORD MATERIAL MAKES IT VERY CLEAR THAT THERE WAS NO DISTINCTION IN HORSE OR ARMOUR BETWEEN SCOTTISH AND ENGLISH MEN-AT-ARMS', WORTH CHECKING OUT DR. AYTOUN AND DR. KING ON THIS TOPIC, and several Ph.D. theses.......
:Instead, what we see from the Scots of this period, and most of all, from Bruce's armies, are forces built for mobile warfare.  These aren't field armies, they're raiding parties.  Whether they carried out &quot;guerrilla warfare&quot; in the modern sense is open to debate, but it was certainly 'asymmetrical' warfare by the standards of the day.  If we examine Robert Bruce's strategy and tactics over the years leading up to Bannockburn, what emerges is a pattern of mobile warfare that avoids enemy strength and strikes at weakness to achieve an attritional effect.  There are NO pitched battles {HISTORICALLY OF COURSE THERE WERE SEVERAL, THOUGH NONE OF THEM VERY LARGE], just a seemingly endless series of raids, looting expeditions, ambushes and sudden assaults on isolated strongpoints.  It's not just the avoidance of major pitched engagements with English field armies, it's also that Bruce never engaged in the sort of protracted siege warfare that was so typical of medieval conflicts [EXCEPT AT CARLISLE, BERWICK, EDINBURGH,STIRLING, DUNDEE, PERTH,ROXBURGH AND SO ON.....]  The series of events that led to Bannockburn is just so totally out of keeping with the grand strategy Robert Bruce had followed with rigorous discipline for years - events that could have (and would have, if not for the grossly inept handling and deployment of the English army) led to absolute disaster for Bruce's cause - that it is almost inconceivable that the terms given to the Stirling garrison represent anything BUT freelancing on the part of Edward Bruce...UNLESS OF COURSE THE EPISODE IS AN EXAMPLE OF BARBOUR TRYING TO UNDERMINE EDWARD BRUCE...WHICH HE DOES REPEATEDLY. [[Special:Contributions/97.89.158.250|97.89.158.250]] ([[User talk:97.89.158.250|talk]]) 05:58, 24 June 2009 (UTC)

== The Knight and the Poet. ==

Once again I see there has been an attempt to discredit John Barbour and-at the same time-conjure the Black Douglas out of of his place at Bannockburn.  We have four main contemporary, or near contemporary accounts for the battle; Barbour's ''The Bruce''; Sir Thomas Gray's ''Scalicronica''; and the anonymous accounts of the monkish authors of ''The Lanercost Chronicle'' and the ''Vita Edwardi Secundi''-the Life of Edward the Second.  Of the four Barbour is the only Scottish source; he is also by far the most detailed.  One could hardly expect English sources to give a precise description of Scottish dispositions and command arrangements: so why is Barbour's account of four schiltrons to be dismissed and why did he feel the need to magnify artificially the role of Douglas at the battle?  If Douglas was not a major player at Bannockburn when did he become one?  He had fought with Bruce since Methven, and proved himself to be a tough and capable soldier.  It would be astonishing if he had not been given a leading command role.  Barbour is, of course, as I have said in the above, prone to exaggeration; but this is quite different from outright lies.  He was writing at a time when Bannockburn was still a living memory, and informed opinion would have been immediately aware of manipulation and invention.  If we dismiss Barbour then we dismiss all attempt to create a convincing account of Bruce's military career, and such events as the Battle of Inverurie and the Battle of the Pass of Brander might as well never have happened.  I can do no better than quote Professor Geoffrey Barrow on this matter, who says of John Barbour on Bannockburn; &quot;We accept his judgement or abandon any attempt at a detailed account.&quot; (1976, p. 326)
[[User:Rcpaterson|Rcpaterson]] 16:21, 14 July 2006 (UTC)
I am not an accomplished 'Wikipedia'user, so I may be writing this in the wrong place - if so, please accept my apologies. There are a number of useful medieval accounts of this battle, all of which, except Barbour, clearly describe the Scottish army as consisting of three major formations. The reason Barbour gives a fourth formation to Douglas is that from his perspective - half a cenury later - it would seem impossible for Douglas NOT to have had a senior command role, however it was not until after the death of Edward Bruce in Ireland that Douglas became prominent as a political figure. Interested persons might like to consult Dr. Michael Brown's 'The Black Douglases'. Incidentally - although SIr Thomas Grey (Scalacronica) was not present at Bannockburn, he had (while a POW in the 1340s)) access to Scottish chronicles which no longer exist. Finally, Barbours 'Bruce' was probably written as a 'performance piece' for the entertainment of the Scottish nobility. It is an important source, but should not be taken too literally.
Scottish armies of the 14th century invariably consisted of three major infantry divisions - falikirk is the only excpeption.

== Army numbers ==
There have been two recent attempts to amend the figures for the size of the English army at Bannockburn, either making the figure far too low-12000-or far too high-30000 plus.  Anyone who wishes to may take John Barbour, the chronicler, as their point of departure for this, with a figure of 100000, no less, for the English army.  There is, however, no need to guess around this point: we ''know'' from muster roles, pay roles and the like that Edward II gathered some 3000 knights and 17000 infantry.  I am quite prepared to debate this point; but it does no service to the Scots, the English or to simple historical accuracy to produce arbitrary and inaccurate figures.  [[User:Rcpaterson|Rcpaterson]] 22:40, 23 August 2006 (UTC)
:Are there muster rolls/pay rolls for the Englsih army of 1314? There are several documents relating to the conscription of troops, but these are demands for service, not records of actual recruitment. It is perfectly possible that the English army did amount to 20,000 men, but more likely that it was rather smaller than that judging by the strength of Englsih armies in Scotland for which such material has survived - see R. Nicholson 'Edward III and the Scots' and A. Ayton's 'Knights and their Warhorses' for more information on these topics. CB.&lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:86.145.135.72|86.145.135.72]] ([[User talk:86.145.135.72|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/86.145.135.72|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; (17:17, 8 December 2006)&lt;/small&gt;
::Pay Roles are only wholly effective sources if the entire army is professional. As for muster roles are only a survey, not a call-to-arms. Therefore I suggest that we should accept John Barbour's account that there were tens of thousands of peasant infantry on the English side. As for the Scots it is widely accepted that there were 5,000 - 6,000 professional infantry, 500 professional cavalry and 4,000 volenters/irregulars known as 'small folk'. RS 12/07/09.&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.147.140.135|81.147.140.135]] ([[User talk:81.147.140.135|talk]]) 13:44, 12 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::Excuse me, but &quot;widely accepted&quot; by whom.  I have reverted your changes until a source is provided. ---&lt;font face=&quot;Georgia&quot;&gt;'''[[User:RepublicanJacobite|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#009900&quot;&gt;RepublicanJacobite&lt;/span&gt;]]'''&lt;sub&gt;''[[User talk:RepublicanJacobite|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#006600&quot;&gt;The'FortyFive'&lt;/span&gt;]]''&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 16:31, 12 July 2009 (UTC)
Republican jacobite is quite right...there is no reliable information on the size of the Scottish or English armies. The 'volunteers' may never have existed at all beyond the imagination of Barbour.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/217.42.97.59|217.42.97.59]] ([[User talk:217.42.97.59|talk]]) 19:02, 19 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::::I've changed the numbers and gave a reference from Grant's ''Battle'', p 118. Dupuy's ''The Encyclopedia of Military History'', Laffin's ''Dictionary of Battles'' and Bruce's ''Dictionary of Battles'', give no numbers for Bannockburn. I don't expect these numbers to be &quot;written in stone&quot;, merely a base from which to work. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 21:42, 9 September 2009 (UTC)
::::Seymour's ''Battles in Britain'', p.90,92, states the English arrived with just under 20,000 and states it's confidence in Barbour's figure for the Scots at no more than 7,000 but probably nearer to 6,000. Sadler's ''Scottish Battles'', p.46, states as many as 17,000 for the English and perhaps 5000 foot and 500 horse for the Scots. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 21:53, 9 September 2009 (UTC)

I agree more with John Barbour figure of around 100000, Yes perhaps a figure of 3000 knights is on the pay roles, but those knights all have titles and it would be stupid to think that they alone went to a battlefield without their own household troops of knights and infantry not to mention their supply wagons so you can add a further 5-30 men to each of the 3000 English knights. There are also the knights from Germany Netherlands, Scotland and France to take into account. The argument of logistics, 100000 men marching is going to consume allot of food. But Barbour states that the army met up at Berwick which has a port, much of the army that came from the south of England and other distant lands probably sailed there the rest who where closer walked or rode but its not like 100000 set of from London to Stirling. Once they were all assembled the army was broken up into 10 groups which made their way to Edinburgh then Stirling. As for the supplying this large army, it is possible that supply ships where used to sail along the coast to Edinburgh.  This was well in their means todo as it had been done before during the crusades. Scots having 30000 men is also reasonable, its not like 30000 men stayed together in one area for months, an army of that size would stay together for a few days at most then disband due to lack of provisions. I think one should take the fact into account that Barbour was born around 1316-20 and died 1395 he studied in both Scotland and England there is a good possibility he talked to men who where actually at the battle, he was also a part of the clergy, I do not see any point in over exaggerating the numbers by as greatly as 75%. And I take the word of someone who lived closer in time to an event than any historian living today--[[linz2d]] 11 April 2010  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Linz2d|Linz2d]] ([[User talk:Linz2d|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Linz2d|contribs]]) 11:50, 11 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::It is extremely unlikely that the English had 100,000 men at Bannockburn - medieval armies simply didn't have the logistical capability to grow to this size, certainly for the length of a campaign.  As to the 3000 knights and their followers, most of these men didn't have followers, except for pages and servants.  Most were serving more senior nobles.  The infantry weren't followers in the same way - they were raised separately.  Our best guide are the pay rolls of other English expeditions to Scotland in the late 13th./early 14th. centuries, which would be consistent with a 20-30000 figure for the English.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 08:58, 12 April 2010 (UTC)

:::True, but this event could be considered a one off and it is widely believed to be the largest army to have ever assembled on British soil, except for World War II when over a million allied men took part in the invasion of Normandy. One also has to consider the time given to the English to assemble such a force, a whole year. Edward Bruce had besieged the castle from Lent to just before St. Johns day (aka Midsummer's day) in 1313 and made the the agreement (due to no side having the advantage) that if no relief came by midsummer day the following year then he would have the castle without force, Wikipedia has Edward besieging the castle in 1314 and making the agreement for midsummer's day the same year. Which really makes no sense to the story whats so ever, its the fact that Edward Bruce had given such a long time for relief to come that sets the stage for the epic battle. A year is long enough to make the preparation for having an army of 100000 gather at Berwick and for them to be supplied. I do not personally see the logistics as a problem, I acknowledge that its would be highly unlikely that the army of 100000 would stay together for anything longer than a week and a half, but as John Barbour states, a day was set, therefore everyone on the English(and Scot's probably) side had rough idea when the battle would be taking place and the day by which they had to gather at Berwick. If Persians could attack the Spartans with a equal or greater force of 100000 then why cant one of the greatest kingdoms in Europe do the same traveling a shorter distance in greener lands. --[[User:Linz2d|Linz2d]] ([[User talk:Linz2d|talk]]) 11:52, 14 April 2010 (UTC)

There isn't a shred of evidence that Edward's army was the &quot;largest ever assembled on British soil&quot;. England in 1314 was a relatively poor and backward country, and at a low economic ebb. Even in good times, English mediaeval armies rarely exceeded 20,000 men, and were usually much smaller. Edward 111, for example, (a strong and popular king) invaded France (FRANCE!) with between 5000 and 15,000 men, as did Henry V a century later. To maintain a large army (50,000+) in hostile territory requires a level of logistical sophistication which was not achieved in post-Roman Britain until the late eighteenth century. As for Bannockburn: the muster roles suggest a total force of 3000 knights and 17,000 followers (a plausible figure), but this would have been the manpower required to sustain the entire expedition, a proportion of which would have been deployed to secure strongpoints along the invasion route. To put this in perspective: in 1812 Napoleon required a total force of over 500,000 men to place an army of 60,000 men at the gates of Moscow. Common sense suggests that the English army probably fielded between 10,000 and 15,000 men at Bannockburn, a size which fits with the likely geography of the battlefield. These numbers are also consistent with the eventual outcome of the battle; i.e. a comprehensive defeat, but one in which there were 10 named deaths and 10 named hostages. By way of comparison: at Flodden, out of a Scottish army of 30,000, there were 44 named deaths and a similar number of high-ranking prisoners. Both were hard-fought conflicts of similar duration using not-dissimilar weapons and with similar (albeit reversed) outcomes. It seems likely that the respective sizes of the armies were of similar proportions.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/94.199.236.88|94.199.236.88]] ([[User talk:94.199.236.88#top|talk]]) 17:50, 7 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


===Numbers in info box===
After a recent flurry of changes to the numbers in the info box, culminating in their replacement with references to a Braveheart website, I have bitten the bullet and produced an estimate range based on 8 books I have access to.  I am aware that there are a number more of relevance that I don't have but hopefully these 8 give us a good sample of published estimates.  I have then cited the numbers to published sources.  These ranges also encompass the estimates given in the text, leading to greater consistency.  I propose this to fellow editors as the methodology to use on this page - a referenced range in the info box to show uncertainty of historians' estimates and use the opportunity the text provides to make a best guess, with appropriate rationale.  I hope this suggestion finds consensus to allow us to return to the stability required by the importance and quality scale of the article.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 11:26, 26 June 2010 (UTC)

== New research ==

Two books have been written on the subject of this battle in recent years, Bannockburn Revealed and Bannockburn Proved, author William Scott.  This research uncovers information using non traditional historical research and extensively research evidence.  Mr. Scott's book hasw been utterly debunked by a succession of very competent medievalists, but has gathered support from no-one with a credible background in the history of medieval Scotland or England. Surely - as an advert- Mr. Scott's paragraphs in praise of his (own) book should be removed?  

The paragraphs that have now been removed, were entered by [[User:Ewsd02|Ewsd02]] 09:59, 10 May 2007 (UTC), not by the author.  I simply read the books and thought it was worth representation.  Perhaps a link to the website on the main page would be a fair compromise? 

[http://www.elenkus.com New research on the Battle]NB, This link takes the reader to an advertising site fo Mr.Scott's book.


I have removed Scott's insert from the page because it violates Wikipedia policies on a number of levels: it is self-promotion, it represents Scott's original research, contains &lt;i&gt;ad hominem&lt;/i&gt; attacks on other authors and provides no citations to support the assertions being made.[[User:Iain1917|Iain1917]] 07:25, 10 May 2007 (UTC)

If you read the books, there is ample evidence to support the assertions being made.  Whether you agree with it or not, this is well researched material that deserves representation on an open source information site like wikipedia.  Many of Scott's assertions have yet to be accepted by the historical community, however, this may be because his conclusions differ from those of the more established researchers, and indeed invalidate many of their publications if correct.  People should be able to review all available material and decide for themselves, University Lecturers must not have a complete monopoly on how our history is interpreted. 
[[User:Ewsd02|Ewsd02]] 09:57, 10 May 2007 (UTC)

I have read the books, which did nothing to convince me of the author's point of view, but that is not the reason for removing the paragraphs.  The reason was, as stated above, that the removed paragraphs violated Wikipedia standards.  If you wish to provide a link to the books so that readers can access them, that is fine.  However, it is not fine to have material that is original research, nor is it fine to have material that includes ad hominem attacks.  This is an encyclopedia that has particular ways of doing things.  If you wish to draw attention to Scott's work, why not establish your own web pages about it?  You could do a Wiki entry about Scott himself, but remember that Wiki entries need to be neutral and factual, rather than polemical and expressing opinion. [[User:Iain1917|Iain1917]] 07:38, 14 May 2007 (UTC)





There is no need to create a webpage for Mr Scott. That is far from the point, and is merely an opinion that would reduce his work to some secondary status that the actual woeful Bannockburn article displayed for all to see does not actually deserve.

The Wikipedia webpage on Bannockburn should reflect the battle as currently understood in relation to the sources, (primary ones of course, not say, Barbour , who is a secondary source) the topography etc and any latest interpretation of them. It is unfortunate that you believe that because someone has updated the rather tragic wikipedia article based on the work of William Scott, and upset you or somebody else by attacking 'established' historians, you therefore believe his work should not be included.

May I say that although Bannockburn Revealed and Bannockburn Proved are indeed original works, they use all the early sources, fully included in one book for the first time, and examine them thoroughly. The works also utilise the knowledge gained from approximately 18 years of writing, studying and examining the area of Stirling to ascertain how the sources link in to the geography. 

I also note that somebody has claimed that Mr Scott's work:  &quot;has been utterly debunked by a succession of very competent medievalists&quot;-this is not true as far as I am aware and is actually not possible because the work is miles in front of anything ever published with regard to the Battle of Bannockburn on too many levels to mention. If this claim is true, then I would like to see a reference, an article or academic paper which does debunk this work. Any link or title will do and I will purchase or access it myself. I would truly appreciate this.

I feel that some sort of censor is involved in Wikipedia here, because the unsubstantiated claims of 'debunking' (or the other reasons like impoliteness or whatever) appear to have led to the work of William scott being totally ignored and this is of immeasurable loss to anybody who wishes to understand this battle. I see no reason why somebody cannot edit the article on Bannockburn in Wiki, which has an enormous amount of factual errors which are almost beyond belief and the complete opposite to what is inferred by the person who 'removed' any reference to Scott's work.

I would like to edit this article and the errors within, using primary sources (Vita Edwardi Secundi, Lanercost. Scalacronica, Baston's verses etc) but do not wish to waste my time by having it removed for spurious reasons, however the article as it currently stands is not an adequate reflection of what is currently known about the Battle of Bannockburn and that is simply wrong and very sad just four years before the 700th anniversary in 2014.

if the person who is so certain that William Scott is wrong would care to meet me anywhere in scotland, i will buy him lunch and explain not only why William Scott's research is correct, but why most other research is wrong. including the works of Barrow and Duncan-and i have read virtually everything written about this battle including most books in print. I have no idea why anybody could possibly not be convinced of the arguments (plural) research and conclusions of Mr Scot if they have actually read his work and understood it.

Once again, I must reassert that to say that any historians have debunked Mr Scott's work is completely wrong to my knowledge, the best they might have done is to ignore it, probably for the reasons given by the other more supportive commentator above, however i have no interest in the internal politics of the historical community, I wish only to see the truth conquer all.

I see there are some emotive comments about Barbour elsewhere on here. Barbour wrote a seminal piece of Scots prose, beautifully rendered and a joy to read, but he cannot be taken as being historically accurate unless what he states has been confirmed by primary sources. The reason for this is obvious if you consider that he wrote over 60 years after the event (Bannockburn) and that he was commissioned by Robert II to praise his ancestors.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kinghob|contribs]]) 18:36, 11 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::I think  it is perfectly legitimate to seek to edit the article to remove errors.  However, given the obvious controversy over what Mr. Scott wrote (I have not read the books and can offer no personal judgement) I would recommend you discuss those changes here to seek consensus first.  Otherwise, you are going to put in a lot of work to see it reverted, an edit war could easily break out and we could end with a locked page, which doesn't help your cause of offering up alternative viewpoints. [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 19:04, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

I was completely unaware of Mr Scott ever contributing to this article (as there is no mention of his work) though I did read the comment above on here today. However it was hinted at that perhaps this was an over enthusiastic supporter of Scott rather than himself. There is nothing controversial about Mr Scotts work as far as I am aware. However, I can assure you that although I have read and studied all of his works and papers (and virtually everything else written about Bannockburn including all the early sources in full) my goal is exactly the same as your own so obviously is; to allow a better article on the Battle of Bannockburn to be available. I have never attempted to alter an article in Wikipedia before, (though I have wished to!) so please bear with me, but I can assure you that i will discuss every aspect of any proposed changes thoroughly as having others comment on what you might propose is a fantastic facility that I wasn't even aware of until today.

I will feed in comments to see how they are received (or indeed opposed!) and then go to work rereading the sources or evidence that backs up what is stated,  and will hopefully convince the people here that there is much that can be stated and verified about this battle. I use a mac and cannot find 'tildes' (and believed after my first discussion that my name would be added when I clicked save), so apologies for not signing myself properly, but I read the message about clicking the tab and will do that instead.

Thanks for the prompt reply [[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]]) 20:59, 11 February 2010 (UTC)Kinghob

::Looking forward to the input [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 08:06, 12 February 2010 (UTC)

:::I'd like to see some quotes, sourced directly from Scott's book. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 08:11, 12 February 2010 (UTC)

First of all I am embarrassed to say there are indeed tildes on my keyboard. I feel a bit daft having never spotted them before.

Thanks for giving me a chance to put forward some changes and for the support. Having read the vast majority of works, whatever I propose will be cited by stated sources and I would welcome any challenge that might either argue against or hopefully advance an alternate argument, and of course  some consensus when warranted. Especially on here, this discussion board. I have read wiki for years and it has been unbelievably useful and accurate in the main. 

The strong impression you give is that you wish for accuracy and rational reasoning and that is comforting and perhaps challenging, but certainly welcome.

The kansas request for quotes should be ok though i will have to type them directly from the books or papers, I will do that no problem if you ask for a specific part of the battle you have an interest in, or have a dispute between Dryfield and Carse, (the lectures I have attended centre around this issue), and it takes understanding of day 1 and Day 2 to get your head around all of that.
This is a discussion on wikipedia, and my mind was changed by the work of Scott because of the depth he went into and the insight this gives.  That is his work though. 
Any proposed changes I may ask to be included will simply use the original sources, not Scott's work, even though it was by reading his first book (bought for me by my mum in Oban!) 6 or 7 years ago that led me to believe that there was indeed a great deal that could be proven about the site and military tactics related to the Battle of Bannockburn.
--[[Special:Contributions/82.41.194.247|82.41.194.247]] ([[User talk:82.41.194.247|talk]]) 23:45, 12 February 2010 (UTC)--[[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]]) 23:52, 12 February 2010 (UTC)

:: Take care when using quotes from original sources.  This may seem odd, but wiki rules give more weight to published modern sources in some cases.  Wikipedia is a digest of published opinion.  Creating an interpretation based on primary sources is considered original research.  You may therefore find your hard work undone by a zealous editor declaring it original research.  Personally, I prefer to see some quotes from original sources to illustrate points.  If you link them to a published opinion, they are less likely to be reverted.  Apologies if you know all this, but you have said you are just finding your way in editing in a previous post.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 11:13, 13 February 2010 (UTC)

No need to apologise. I did not realise that more weight is lent to published modern sources in some cases. There are plenty of modern published works which cite the Carse of Balquhiderock (from General Christison in the 1950's onward) although a fuller understanding of the primary sources and what they reveal was not known to him. Similarly a very recent book by Chris Brown cites the Carse as the battle site as well, although having read this book, his arrival at the Carse as the site is more related to Barbour's words (a secondary source worthy of note when he agrees with the Primary sources) than the primary sources themselves, although they are quoted/covered to back up other ideas related to the battle.

This would need further explanation perhaps to ensure something isn't erroneously revised, because if I was commenting on the circumstances that led to the creation of the Scottish parliament, or the initial investigation into the Lockerbie atrocity,and wish to edit a page on these matters, then the obvious way to counteract or give an alternate view would be to cite modern works of which there is an abundance, but the issue itself would have to be more than a mere opinion of an author, it would have to be based on facts, or it would carry no credibility. 

In the case of a historical event, multi faceted,  if I am attempting to change the year the Stirling castle truce was made, (cited as 1314 in the wiki article) then one obvious way is to quote a letter from Edward II from 1313 that mentions the date of 24th June the following year, an ancient document. Of course this letter is in modern books where it is translated along with other documents, although not necessarily to substantiate a debate about Bannockburn per se. I am sure it is mentioned in some books, as far as I am aware most historians believe the date of the truce to have begun in 1313, any who do not are in a minority from what I have read, so this could be easily rectified. I would imagine that the source that backs up the wiki date of 1314 for the beginning of the truce would need to be examined as it would be wrong to simply quote a few lines from a book which may be factually incorrect on this matter although correct on other matters.  --[[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]]) 13:03, 13 February 2010 (UTC)

== NATIONALITIES ==

is it correct to talk about the combating Armies in terms of nations when such entities did not exist at this period of History? For example, to talk about &quot;English&quot; armies or &quot;Scottish&quot; armies when these nations did not exist as we know them today? ben 1314
:Well, they do fulfill the criteria which are nowadays used for a country: a territory, a government and a fixed population. &quot;Nationality&quot; and national awareness are indeed 19th century notions but the Kingdom of Scotland and the Kingdom of England were established countries in this timeframe... so to speak of the English army and the Scottish army in the sense of the army of the Kingdom of England or the army of the Kingdom of Scotland is correct. -- [[user:fdewaele|fdewaele]], 14 June 2007, 15:01 (CET).
Medieval Welsh, Scots, English and Irish peole were well aware of their national identities if 13th-14th century record and narrative evidence is to be taken seriously - and if not, why bother with history at all. English records refer to 'The Scots' all the time, check out  Strvenson's 'Documents Illustrative of Scottsh History'  the 'Calendar of Documents Relating to Scotland'  'Rotuli Scotiae' 'The Treaty Rolls' 'Calendar of Inquisitions Post Mortem'. ALso in narrative accounts - Guisborough, Vita Edwardus Secundus, Scalacronica, Barbnour, Foroun, Bower, Barbour, Brut, etc. etc.
The beleif that 'nationalism' was a product of the Napoleonic wars derives from Sociology rather than history and has its origins in Marxist idealism.

In which case wasn't it an English (Bruce, born Writtle) victory over the Welsh (Edward II, born Caernarfon).
Or a [[List_of_people_excommunicated_by_the_Roman_Catholic_Church#14th_century|Accursed]] victory over the Church of Rome.Edward may have been born in Wales, but he was still English. Robert I was most certainly not born in Essex and was most ceratainly Scottish.
&lt;p&gt;
The movie &quot;Braveheart&quot; gets young Robert and his father wrong, according to what I have read. The father, who had extensive lands in England, is played with a guid Scots accent, and Robert with an English.
Besides which, Robert fought for the Scots at Falkirk, and temporarily gave up hope afterwards, to  be re-encouraged by the famous spider.
[[User:DaveyHume|DaveyHume]] ([[User talk:DaveyHume|talk]]) 22:03, 31 October 2014 (UTC)

********************* 

The human mind craves a simple narrative. Therefore Bannockburn becomes a simple 'nasty English' v 'good Scots' fixture. But it was not so simple. James Murray for example describes the whole war of independence as the last and only successful rebellion of Anglo-saxon England against the Norman conquerors. There is some truth in this. 'Scot-land' at this time meant only the Highlands. The Lowlands were (and had been for hundreds of years) inhabited by northern English, and though they may have been under the  jurisdiction of Robert the Bruce it is not clear that he held these lowlands as part of the 'Kingdom of Scotland', or simply as just another Norman baron owing fealty for them to King Edward. Barons' rebellions were of course not uncommon events in the period.  What we now call Scotland was certainly, at least, a two-part entity - and if one is to judge by the savage internal war which he prosecuted in Scot-land prior to Bannockburn the Bruce doesn't  seem to have had much love for the 'Scots' half of his realm. Cassandra.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.5.12.220|92.5.12.220]] ([[User talk:92.5.12.220|talk]]) 11:08, 30 June 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
&lt;br&gt;The Lowlands were northern English? I regard the Scots pronunciation as more accurately Saxon than what the English tongue has become, but I do not think that in the 14th century they'd have thought of themselves as English. However, the American author of &quot;How the Scots Invented the Modern World&quot; holds that even at the time of the Jacobite, ah, Rebellions the Highlands were places of great savagery. &quot;Kidnapped&quot; suggests the same thing. [[User:DaveyHume|DaveyHume]] ([[User talk:DaveyHume|talk]]) 22:03, 31 October 2014 (UTC)
:So Robert the Bruce, just another Norman baron, led with vital support of the MacDonalds and other Gaelic-speaking clans an Anglo-Saxon rebellion, in the course of which he savaged the 'Scots' Comyns, coming from another Norman family... you make my head reel. --[[User:Thrissel|Thrissel]] ([[User talk:Thrissel|talk]]) 19:35, 30 June 2013 (UTC)

::&quot;Cassandra&quot; you are heading ever more firmly back to your OR-posting IP-socking talk page misuse habits, on this and other articles. No doubt you are misrepresenting (or &quot;misunderstanding&quot;) any sources you purport to support your opinions, if your previous pattern is anything to go by. You are making no genuine attempt to improve articles, the purpose of talk pages, but simply floating your own half-baked controversialist OR theses. You have incurred sanctions for this before; please desist. Can I also request, again, that since you informally sign your posts anyway you may as well get a user account to avoid the potential of any other numpty passing themself off as you, to avoid the appearance of IP-socking to escape tracking and avoidance of sanctions and to allow any post regarding your behaviour to go more appropriately on your talk page rather than clutter those of articles. [[User:Mutt Lunker|Mutt Lunker]] ([[User talk:Mutt Lunker|talk]]) 17:14, 2 July 2013 (UTC)


==:: Is it correct to talk in terms of nationalities?==
Yes, for that is how they described themselves. The documentation is not scant or obscure, it runs to many thousands of statements made by many different people who prepared for and/or fought this (and previous) battles. The two kings, the bishops (even the pope) the commanders of the armies, the eyewitness chroniclers who wrote three or four contemporary accounts - they all expressed their view of what they were doing in terms of nationalities, national armies (albeit with contingents from other nations) and nation-states.

::'Scot-land' at this time meant only the Highlands.&quot;
This is provably false. Every single contemporary source from at least Edward i onwards -- a plethora of English and Scottish state and church records concerned with diplomacy, conflict, governance, land ownership, taxation and legal jurisdiction speaks of &quot;Scotland&quot; as the land immediately north of the Tweed. Pick any book of regnal &quot;rolls&quot; from internet archive and read. [[Special:Contributions/86.130.215.140|86.130.215.140]] ([[User talk:86.130.215.140|talk]]) 11:07, 4 November 2015 (UTC)

Yes, I think you're right. The term 'Scotland' seems to have been applied to the whole kingdom from c 1249. Previously Scot-land or 'Scotland proper' was used to refer to the Highlands whilst the Kingdom of Scotland included Scot-land, Lothian and Galloway, each referred to as separate entities within the kingdom. That distinction was emphasised by royal charters up to the time of William the Lyon which expressly addressed subjects as  French (i.e Norman) English, Scots, Galwegians, and Welsh (of Clydesdale). The huge irony of course is that in time the English of the lowlands came to call themselves 'Scots' and for centuries thereafter referred to the original Gaelic-speaking Scots of the Highlands as 'Irish'. At the time of Bannockburn however the multiple ethnic divisions amongst the Scottish king's subject were still clear cut; Robert the Bruce was 'French' and his lowland subjects in the south and east of his kingdom were still 'English in the kingdom of the Scots'. Much of the history of Scotland concerns the disunity and antipathy between Highland and Lowland, a centuries-long conflict between  two 'nationalities' within a single kingdom.  [[User:Cassandrathesceptic|Cassandrathesceptic]] ([[User talk:Cassandrathesceptic|talk]]) 10:43, 6 July 2016 (UTC)

:Er, so you are now supporting someone who is arguing against [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Battle_of_Bannockburn&amp;diff=562232407&amp;oldid=516654882 your very own post] (if under an IP-sock incarnation, nonetheless informally signed), in the section above from 30 June 2013? Must be difficult keeping track. Still the off-topic [[WP:NOTFORUM|forum]] ramblings though I see. [[User:Mutt Lunker|Mutt Lunker]] ([[User talk:Mutt Lunker|talk]]) 14:19, 10 July 2016 (UTC)

== Very confusing ==

The first couple of paragraphs are very confusing. I've read the introduction and first couple paragraphs several times, and I still have no idea about the basic concepts of the battle. For instance: who held the castle? You would think this would actually be stated, but no, of course not! It appears that the Scots were laying a siege against... Scots! What? Doesn't make any sense at all. I guess the English must have held it (though the article, apart from the infobox, never actually names Edward as the leader of the English), but why does it say a Scot held it?

Overall, this whole thing really confused me. [[User:Matt Yeager|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#DF0001&quot;&gt;Matt Yeager&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]] [[Special:Random|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot; color=&quot;#B46611&quot;&gt;♫&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]] [[User_talk:Matt Yeager|&lt;font color=&quot;#00AA88&quot;&gt;(Talk?)&lt;/font&gt;]] 03:51, 5 August 2007 (UTC)

It is not so confusing really.....The English held Stirling Castle, the Scots laid siege to it in the spring of 1314. An agreement was made that the Castle would surrender to the Scots unless it was releived by an English army by midsummer. An English army approached Stirling and was defeated, after which the Castle surrendered.
Moubray was a Scot in Englsih service.
&lt;p&gt; There was an interesting experiment, recorded by the BBC if I've got it right, in which was built a trebuchet of the size and style that they believed was the &quot;War Wolf&quot; that the English used to break down and enter the walls of Stirling Castle. From a bit beyond crossbow range, it did indeed demolish a wall five feet or so wide. That would be how it came to be in English hands.[[User:DaveyHume|DaveyHume]] ([[User talk:DaveyHume|talk]])&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

 : Thank you, but the trebuchet &quot;[[Warwolf]] was used in the 1304 siege of Stirling Castle by Edward I. It played no part in the 1314 Battle of Bannockburn. [[User:Mediatech492|Mediatech492]] ([[User talk:Mediatech492|talk]]) 18:21, 1 November 2014 (UTC)

I think that there is a point in the statement of confusion as to who held Stirling, particularly if you consider those who are not familiar with the battle and are looking for information.

The castle of Stirling was English held (one of only a very few left in English hands in Scotland by 1313) and was supposed to be relieved by an English Army by the Feast of St John 1314 (Midsummers day 24th June). The Scots did not lay siege to Stirling castle in 'spring' 1314, rather than Lent 1313. Therefore the truce lasted over a year.

There are several ways that this can be shown, but since there is no evidence of the alleged shorter period of months referred to within the wiki article and or reasons of simplicity, I will give just one reason at this time for the truce being known about for a longer period than 'spring 1314' and see if anyone objects:

&quot;.....we consider that we must answer you that before the Feast of the Birth of St John the Baptist we have arranged to be at Berwick upon Tweed with our Army to march beyond against our enemies and rebels in those parts&quot;.

By the King's Witness, at Westminster, 28th day of November. By the King himself.
Foedera, Litterae &amp; Acta Publica. A.D. 1313 An. 7 Edw.II. 237

This is the earliest mention of the relief date by the English army after the Stirling castle siege. The letter is addressed to concerned landowners and English supporters in Lothian who were alarmed at the run of the land the Scottish army had by 1313-this latter was to placate them, but it gives a specific date; June 24th 1314, one that was already agreed. This letter only confirms in writing what Edward II knew earlier-it is documentation of a specific date and purpose related to an ''full'' English invasion of Scotland. The reason Edward II would have an assembled army at Berwick ''before'' 24th June 1314  was because this was the expiry date of the truce entered into between Edward Bruce and Philip De Moubray in Lent 1313.

I hope that together we can write a better wiki article about Bannockburn and do Scottish history a service.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kinghob|contribs]]) 19:48, 11 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt; --[[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]]) 21:04, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

The opening lines of the Wiki article on Bannockburn are:

&quot;Prelude

Around Lent of '1314' Edward Bruce, brother of the Scottish king, began the siege of Stirling Castle, which was commanded by Sir Philip Mowbray. Unable to make any headway, Bruce agreed to a pact with Mowbray - if no relief came by midsummer 1314, the castle would surrender to Bruce.&quot;

In view of the Edward II missive of 28 November 1313 cited above; does anybody object to the idea that an earlier date for the relief of Stirling castle was known about in November 1313, and that Edward II is acknowledging this fact by mentioning &quot;the Feast of St John&quot; the following year (24 June 1314) as a timeline at least? We have to bear in mind that this specific date mentioned in November 1313, with hindsight and using the information stated within the primary sources, is known as being the date of the end of a truce that related to the English relief of Stirling castle, and was also the date the actual Battle of Bannockburn was fought. 

--[[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]]) 00:23, 13 February 2010 (UTC)
If Edward gathered his army at Berwick for the feast of St. John, it would not have been able to reach Stirling in time to beat the contracted date...which was the Feast of St. John. In November 1313 there were already plans for an invasion the following summer, but Stirling castle was not yet seen as being 'at risk' to the Scots. Barbour is alone in giving the date of Edward Bruce's siege and compact as 1313. The period from Lent to midsummer 1314 is much the more likely option.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.153.249.167|81.153.249.167]] ([[User talk:81.153.249.167|talk]]) 15:36, 8 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Map image ==

I think it admirable that someone should have gone to the trouble to create a map for the battle, but if it is going to appear on the entry, it must be made clear that it is an interpretation and that it is not an authoritative statement of what happened.  I would suggest that it would be better to remove the image: the location of the fighting, which took place in two separate areas on two successive days, is too uncertain to provide a map.  There are numerous alternative hypotheses for the location, and no valid physical evidence to choose between them.  I will leave it now to allow debate about the retention of the image, but if there has been no convincing argument in favour of it, I will remove it. [[User:Iain1917|Iain1917]] 13:10, 7 September 2007 (UTC)

== Edward, King Edward or Robert the Bruce? Very Confusing and poorly written. ==

The opening sections of this article are very poorly written with regard to the naming/identification of the relevant parties. It is entirely unclear whether Edward Bruce or King Edward is being referred to as much of the piece simply refers to &quot;Edward&quot; or &quot;Bruce&quot; which is ambigious. The ambiguity continues as the remainder of the piece simply refers to &quot;Bruce&quot;, rather than Robert the Bruce, or Edward the Bruce. In an article that mentions both brothers, the surname &quot;Bruce&quot; should not appear in isolation. Equally, reading the opening sections the reader is left in doubt as to who actually led the Scottish army, was it Robert the Bruce or his brother Edward?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Alistairgd|Alistairgd]] ([[User talk:Alistairgd|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Alistairgd|contribs]]) 16:10, 29 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


== 200 Templars ==
Many know the story how 200 Templars rode out to save the day for Scotland and the Bruce
and this twisting of history by apparently English writers of the article is sad indeed.
Many may know the story, but ot is just a story. It was invented by Fr. Hay circa 1700 as part of a romance about the Sinclair familiy. There is not a scrap of medieval evidence to support it, which is why not one of the many reputable scholars (Barrow, Duncan, Boardman,Brown, MacNamee, Duffy, Prestwich etc. )of the period accepts it.     &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.151.162.156|86.151.162.156]] ([[User talk:86.151.162.156|talk]]) 18:40, 3 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

But it is obvious proved that some of the Templars fled to Scotland after 1307 and it is also quite possible they took part in the battle as volunteers without flying any official insignia. Then you would never know them apart from other guys. Moreover Templars used state of the art equipment and looting bodies after battle was a common thing, so it is unlikely that if any has fallen, his body wouldn't be looted.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.190.175.66|81.190.175.66]] ([[User talk:81.190.175.66|talk]]) 13:51, 26 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

GM PS /s CINCU Sr  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.195.75.17|76.195.75.17]] ([[User talk:76.195.75.17|talk]]) 00:04, 6 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

It is all very well to say 'it is obvious that templars fled to Scotlamnd', but it is important to remeber that there is not the slightest bit of evidence to that effect; not one jot or iota. The tale of templar snctuary in Scotland was invented by a Mr. Burnes in the mid -19th century; presumably as part of Masonic romance.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.221.65.117|90.221.65.117]] ([[User talk:90.221.65.117|talk]]) 17:38, 16 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Actually, there is documentary evidence to show that the Templars were given land at Balantrodoch (now known as Temple, oddly enough after the Templars), where they founded a preceptory. Whether they took part in the battles or not is open to speculation, but their presence in Scotland is not. The following quote is taken from the RCAHMS website &quot;The modern 'Temple' is identical with 'Balantrodoch', the principal seat of the Knights Templars in Scotland. There is no record of its foundation, though it is commonly assumed that this was due to David I. The earliest reference is probably in a charter of 1175-99. After the suppression of the Templars, about 1309, &quot;Temphill of Balantrodoch with the kirk&quot; became one of the baronies held by the Hospitallers, while, at an unascertained date, the former Templars' church became parochial.&quot; taken from http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/53261/details/temple+church/  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.41.12.178|82.41.12.178]] ([[User talk:82.41.12.178|talk]]) 17:46, 18 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:: See effigies in round Templar church, London including 7 Templars plus unidentified no. 8 which is marking the spot of burial for the Lord Jesus Christ... JC2 [[Special:Contributions/69.121.221.97|69.121.221.97]] ([[User talk:69.121.221.97|talk]]) 02:31, 11 July 2009 (UTC)

::: Can we please stick to topic and not drift off down the Da Vinci Code route? I think we have the answers we need above - there is no primary or reliable modern evidence for formed bodies of templars, or ex-templars, or templars who became hospitallers, at Bannockburn.  As the fate of all individual templars in Scotland is not known,we cannot state whether individual ex-Templars took part on either side[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 10:52, 11 July 2009 (UTC)

== 700th anniversary - The Gathering II? ==

Please see [http://news.scotsman.com/latestnews/Home-of-Scots-victory-over.5514632.jp article] from today's SoS. --[[User:Mais oui!|Mais oui!]] ([[User talk:Mais oui!|talk]]) 07:25, 1 August 2009 (UTC)

==Composition of Scots armies==

Have removed some material today which attempted to eliminate the role of Scots archers and replace them with pikemen.  To take the last first, the article follows the convention of calling the Scots spearmen.    I recommend we maintain that convention as this avoids confusion with the pikeblocks of 15th-17th. century warfare.  On the archers, it is clear from original sources that there were Scots archers at Bannockburn (Chris Brown suggests maybe 10% IIRC).  There is evidence that Robert I was aware of the potential of military archery and that after Bannockburn sought to build up the numbers of archers available to him.  [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 08:40, 2 August 2009 (UTC)



Hello there.I noticed you had reverted my edit.I have a ref which supports what happend in the battle.When Edwards Knight were engadged the scottish pikemen the English combined attack with archers failed and were pushed to the right flank.Robert the Bruce then engadged his light cavalry to chase down the archers since the archers wernt able to fully mobilise.

http://books.google.com/books?id=6J6-ZD9l6bIC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;dq=the+battle+of+bannockburn+scottish+army&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false


I think this main engagement with the English archers must be mentioned.So what do you think???Goodbye.--[[User:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|HENRY V OF ENGLAND]] ([[User talk:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|talk]]) 08:53, 2 August 2009 (UTC)

Thanks.  I did leave in the part about the English and Welsh longbowmen not having a clear shot, bcause I know it is in several modern accounts of the battle, so thanks for that - maybe you want to put in an in-line citation?  See [[Template:Cite book]] for a copyable template, if you need one.

The issue of Keith's attack on the English archers is a bit controversial.  Kelly de Vries in Fourteenth Century Infantry Warfare doubts it happened at all.  Most accounts seem to accept it though.  There is no reason to believe the Scots cavalry were &quot;light&quot; - Barbour doesn't say this.  Men-at-arms are just as, if not more, likely.  This might raise more discussion, so may need a citation.

I will change pikemen, though, for consistency reasons outlined above.  The statement about Scots archers would work better in a footnote, I think, for the sake of the flow of the piece.  I'll do that too.  Thanks for coming back to discuss [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 09:25, 2 August 2009 (UTC)


Thanks youre a great help.Also I added the fact that the scots used yew stave longbows but gave a further explanation they had largely inferior archer.I got it from that book I mentioned to you.Goodbye and thanks again.--[[User:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|HENRY V OF ENGLAND]] ([[User talk:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|talk]]) 09:34, 2 August 2009 (UTC)

I footnoted it to Strickland and Hardy's The Great Warbow - seemed a pretty definitive source.  OK with you? [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 09:48, 2 August 2009 (UTC)

No problem.Go ahead.--[[User:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|HENRY V OF ENGLAND]] ([[User talk:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|talk]]) 10:29, 2 August 2009 (UTC)

I'm unaware of any source relating to the battle, or indeed any of the battles of the first Scottish war of independence which say or infer that the Scots used yew longbows. Where does the source get his evidence from?  It's usually been accepted by the main writers on the subject (Barrow, Barron, etc.) that the archers from the Ettrick Forest used shorter bows than the Welsh (English) archers. I'm also intrigued by the reference to 500 Scottish archers, as I am not aware of any primary source which mentions Scottish archer numbers.[[User:Andygm|Andygm]] ([[User talk:Andygm|talk]]) 00:09, 4 August 2009 (UTC)

:On the issue of Scottish archery, the idea is taken from Strickland and Hardy as referenced.  They argue strongly that the &quot;short bow&quot; is a Victorian invention for which there is no evidence.  They also argue that the indigenous bow of the British Isles was a long bow from which the longbow would evolve.  While I wouldn't say they prove their case conclusively, there is certainly no evidence that the Scots used an inferior bow to the English or Welsh at this time. Strickland &amp; Hardy produce quite a bit of evidence to rehabilitate the Scots archer , so worth a read.  Chris Brown has also challenged the emphasis on Ettrick archers, showing Robert I had access to a wider range of archers.  HENRY V told me off page that he'd got the 500 archers from Armstrong's book.  Checking, however, I see Armstrong actually gives 1500 out of 7,850 for Scots archers.  It is the source for his comment about Scottish bows though, rather than directly from S &amp; H.  The number of Scots archers is not considered by every author on the battle because of their relatively small role - I've got quite a few accounts I could trawl through to get an estimate but not at the moment.  On your edits, I would suggest the Vita Edwardi might do better as a footnote - I also note the failure to reference the other statement on arms (Robert I's 1318 statute, which I'll try to correct (it's online at the Scottish Parliament site IIRC).  Bastons poem needs at least to be put in the refs.  [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 08:12, 4 August 2009 (UTC)

Regarding the reference to 500 archers (or 1,500) I think that this should be noted as an opinion of Armstrong rather than stated as a fact. I'm also surprised that Armstrong can be so precise about the total numbers of the Scottish army given that there is no contemporary evidence whatsoever as to its size [[User:Andygm|Andygm]] ([[User talk:Andygm|talk]]) 18:20, 4 August 2009 (UTC)

: Fair points both.  I think all writers on the battle feel a need to make an estimate/guess of the size of the two armies (as, of course, does this page).  Armstrong is doubly constrained by the format of the series he is writing for.  In fact, his estimate isn't really precise - he thinks the Scots army had the fairly arbitrary figures of 6000 pikemen,1500 archers and 350 cavalry.  Fits quite well with most mainstream estimates overall, but the breakdown is speculative.  [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 15:19, 5 August 2009 (UTC)


::Greetins to you both.Page 63 in this book called Bannockburn 1314 Robert the Bruce victory suggests that there was only 500 scottish archers present in the main battle but as Monstrelet said Neil Amstrong sugests a total of 1500 archers.The question itself if it is indeed 1500 archers where did the other 1000 archers dissapear from the scence?Scottish Archers carried battle axes and disdained missile and often liked to engadge in a close melee,as said by this book http://books.google.ie/books?id=RHQHAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=Scottish+archers&amp;dq=Scottish+archers.Also the book also states on page 31 that before King Roberts reign scotland had been hugely deficient of archers.There is evidence that Robert I changed the feudal obligation of knight service to archer service.A Knights fee was to supply 10 archers.However a bow(short) is clearly different from a longbow.Most of The archers of scotand were recruited from the Borders and low-lands since they were the most anlicised in manner.I wouldnt expect the scots have such a high amount of archers if there amount of cavalry was pretty little anyway.If they used the longbow it takes in least 10-15 years of practice to gain profficiency and also there skill is completely medicore.This all implyes to those archers because they engaded the English archers on the second day at dawn and were quickly put to flight by the English ones.1500 scottish archers is too high and anyway Amstrong even admits that there is no evidence of the proportion that was meant for the scots concerning pikemen and archers.A scottish ordinniane and parliamiant was held in scone 1318 near Perth adressing many angles of importance but an intresting one is that when it specificly aimed at those second category of men  worth goods to a value of a cow were expected to equip themeselves with either a spear or a bow.The first(spear) was the most favored of that category.Scottish pikemen have been trained by Robert the Bruce to engadge in the move(litterely push them of the battlefield) to makethemselves harder targets for English archers.There is no evidence of trained scottish archers at the time of Bruce.Those very few good archers came from ettirick forest on the Borders as at Falkirk 1298.Unfortunatly I would have to disagree with Monstrelet on the argument that the scots had a wide range of archers since there is no evidence for this as far as I have read.Archery Law as I previously stated wasnt introduced until by King James in 1424 when he returned from English captivity.http://books.google.ie/books?id=x1QCAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA18&amp;dq=The+scottish+archers+had+weak+skill#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false . This here states that English skill with the bow is indisputibly better then that of any scotsmen frenchmen ect.Archery Law was established twice in scotland both were a failuire.The French Francs-Archers formed by Charles VII in 1448 later turned out to be weak archers whom had no intrest in defending France or in archery and were no more a ruthless band of thugs so were quickly disbanded in 1535.Golf and football is propably a main reason for scottish indescisiveness with the bow in archery.Read this book Otterburn 1388.http://books.google.ie/books?id=5wEZgyYnoikC&amp;pg=PA24&amp;dq=Scottish+Archery+in+medievial+times&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false .It says that the scottish archers were drawn from the borders and low-lands but they did not match the English archers in number or in there tactical skil.Scottish corps of archers continued to be a minority in the scottish army.1500 Archers is way to high.http://books.google.ie/books?id=KCl1l35K-IcC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;dq=Scottish+Archery+in+medieval+times&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false .Also Robert the Bruce only stayed because of bad morale in the English camp.Scottish archers were only considerd a minority to Robert I not an accomplishement of victory.Bruce thought of having a sizeable amount of Longbowmen would counter the English ones but he could have never have recruited a huge nuber of them.The scottish archers were a small amount at Bannockburn and Falkirk.Goodbye and hope to see you again.--[[User:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|HENRY V OF ENGLAND]] ([[User talk:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|talk]]) 19:42, 8 August 2009 (UTC)

: My first comment would be to find a copy of The Great Warbow by Strickland &amp; Hardy.  They give a reasonable amount of coverage to Scottish archery.  The idea that Robert I encouraged archery has some reasonable evidence.  But there was certainly an archery tradition before.  Like 13th.-early 14th. century England, forest areas provided the most skilled archers but not the only ones.  Chris Brown is good on this - see his books in the article bibliography. The Highlands and Islands do have a separate archery tradition, with a great deal of Scandinavian influence.  I'm guessing that Langs idea of Scottish archer/axeman comes from later Highland practice and not 14th. century Lowlands - he doesn't seem to give a reference for it.  Although archery laws were introduced in 1424, by this stage mercenary Scots archers were well known on the Continent.  The high watermark was probably the Scots army in France 1418-24, which managed a men-at-arms to archers ratio of 2-1.  Anyway, that is well in the future by the time of Bannockburn.
[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 10:13, 9 August 2009 (UTC)


::Hello Monstrelet thanks for your reply about scottish archery on the Bannockburn talkpage.I would like to explain a few points to you about the difference between the short bow,crossbow and longbow in government records at the time of Edward II.I found a book about the battle of Falkirk(1298) regarding archers.The same as usual n quote that they had hugely deficient archers and that archery was not a strong tradition in scotland.http://books.google.com/books?id=ykx5PcLxu-0C&amp;pg=PA28&amp;dq=Ettrick+Bow+and+lonbow&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false .Of course they had a tradition (as does other countries) but as said in the book far from strong.Certainly the scots fought as mercenairies but they wernt allways archers or in fact had to be.Scottish mercenaries were employed by the french but in large amounts over-time.At the battle of Verniuil(1424),the English were commanded by the regent of France John the Duke of Bedford against the french led by the constable of France.The English archers were thought to have engadged the scottish archers but the scots were also put to flght.The last of Charles VII scottish allies were destroyed in this battle and the very last few fought at Heerings(1429) not as archers but as axemen.They also lost that battle.You might have heard of Edward III Yeamon of the Gaurd which was a 120 archer gaurd for the soveriegn.The French copied this idea and formed the scots gaurd(genndairimie das esscois) in 1418 by John Stewart but rarely fought in open-pitched battle with the exception if the French king as at battle in person like at the battle of Patay during the Italian Years War.Unfortunatly,the name Scots Gaurd became moot over time since Frenchmen started to fill up those ranks.Francs archers formed in 1448 were supposed to exercise the principle of archery at the church parishes.However the principle wasn't at all effective and was never even put to practice.When they went to church at sunday there are accounts of francs-archers plundering and looting goods.Charles de Bold convinced Louis XI after Guingaite (1479) when the french archers were exposed badly that they were not the best solution and started employing swisss pikemen.francs-archers had no exprerince or trainaing at all and during the italian years war they were nothing more then plunderers.They were also exposed really badly at Ravenna 1512 when the Gascon Archers ran off the battlefield.francs archers were said to only kill chickens not soldiors.The french drill with the use of the bow was not proficcient.http://books.google.com/books?id=hdh4Elj-3WEC&amp;pg=PA513&amp;dq=francs+archers+were+bad#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false .Louis XI even if he did not formally disband them let them freeley deterioate.http://books.google.com/books?id=xj8FAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=francs+archers+were+bad&amp;dq=francs+archers+were+bad&amp;lr=
.http://books.google.com/books?id=OJQ9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA120&amp;dq=francs+archers+were+bad&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false .http://books.google.com/books?id=6PyBAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA208&amp;dq=francs+archers+were+bad&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false .Back to archery in general,the difference between short-bows and longbows are given in this government record.The most prominint was the longbow with an average length of two ells(2.3m),a thickness of 4 thumbs(10 cm) and could discharge a clotharrow arrow(1m or 3ft).The next was the turkish bow and was a composite-bow of shorter length(1.5-1.7m) which fired a wolfarrow.It was made of horn.yew and glue and with its two arms bieng bend forward against the way of the recurve.The third was an elm bow(short bow).Its lenght is not mentioned and it dischared a scottish barbed arrow.It would seem therefore the difference between the short bow and the longbow is the constuction of wood.So,as long as the bow has a yew construction and measures 2.3 m approx.Then it could therefore be correct to term it as a longbow.The Normans at Hastings used yew stave bows but were only 4 feet tall so are not taken as bieng longbows.http://books.google.com/books?id=utafxJAR63YC&amp;pg=PA50&amp;dq=Robert+Hardy.Longbow+of+Welsh+origin&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false .Goodbye--[[User:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|HENRY V OF ENGLAND]] ([[User talk:HENRY V OF ENGLAND|talk]]) 16:51, 9 August 2009 (UTC)

:I think it is time to stop this strand here.  Remember, this is the page for the Battle of Bannockburn.  So though while francs archers and their failings are interesting, discussing them under the [[Battle of Guinegate]] may be more appropriate. The Edward II info on the nature of bows is interesting for context but it seems to come from legal cases (bows and arrows were often described in detail in murder or poaching trials, for example).  The elm bow is interesting because, although elm was used for bows in England, the famous quote about elm bows is from Gerald of Wales 12th. century description of Welsh bows. [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 19:27, 9 August 2009 (UTC)

==Co-ordinates==
We now have co-ordinates on the page - the satellite view is particularly impressive.  I do have a query though.  How and why do people use these?  I ask because the co-ordinates centre on the Carse.  This is the main battle area on the second day so that's OK but, unless you know the ground a bit, you won't find the visitors centre, monument or statue if you were using this to navigate.  Should we recentre on the Visitor's Centre, maybe have alternative co-ordinates for that, or a Day 1/Day 2 split (don't know technically if we can have two sets though)? [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 09:57, 21 November 2009 (UTC)

Kinghob: I use the satellite views of Stirling that are within the public domain to review the area prior to going out there and looking for the many features that are only really evident by personal observation. 
The Day 1 and Day 2 co-ordiantes are close enough to each other to allow them to viewed as one whole picture. I have done this myself. There is little dispute about where Day 1 was fought, I believe that only one writer has said that Day 1 was anywhere else except at the Milton Ford (Gloucester) or St Ninian's (Clifford) and the rest agree that the Scots held the wooded New Park and Dryfield on Day 1 and fought within that vicinity to hold on to this, the only route the English army would have taken to Stirling in 1314.
Day 2, most if not all historians believe that the English camped in the Carse-if so then they were attacked there as there is no suggestion that the English Army had the slightest opportunity to travel elsewhere, or that the Scots would have let them move in the case of the Dryfield being where the battle was fought. The evidence appears to point to teh English being attacked in their camp, surprised that the battle was brought to them.

So the satellite would be a useful tool for both those who favour the Carse or the Dryfielders. Some of this might belong to the Carse or Dryfield sub section kindly created. I will leave that to the editor to decide, although I have tried to merely answer his query about satellite imagery in the main this needed explanation. --[[User:Kinghob|Kinghob]] ([[User talk:Kinghob|talk]]) 13:20, 15 February 2010 (UTC)

==Welsh units==
I have reverted the placing of Welsh forces as an independent combatant in the info box, as it is in conflict with [[Template:Infobox military conflict]].  Clearly Welsh units were present and in fact were probably the major formed force to exit the battlefield, but did not form an independent party to the action. They are mentioned in the article text, which can be expanded with further information, if it can be backed with references [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 12:46, 9 January 2010 (UTC)

==Gaelic name of battle==
In recent days, a number of deletions of the Gaelic translation of the name of the battle have taken place.  While clearly it is not the original name of the battle, I am assuming it was inserted because of the place of the battle in later clan tradition.  I have therefore defended it.  However, I personally have no strong view as to it being there.  I therefore leave it to others to make a case for deletion, meanwhile the status quo should stand.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 17:17, 12 April 2010 (UTC)

==MILHIST reassessment==
Looking over the article I couldn't help but notice that it does not reach recent MILHIST B1 criterion and regretably, I've reset that to no.  This means that the article will drop down the quality scale to C class.  The B1 criterion states that all major content should be in line cited and recommends a rule of thumb that there should be at least one in line citation per paragraph.  The article has already got a citation improvement tag but I hope editors will be inclined to imrove the article with a greater degree of citation.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 18:32, 18 June 2011 (UTC)

== Shake up of images ==

I've taken the opportunity to swap the Holkham Bible image for a medieval image of the battle in the info box, as more representative of the subject.  The Holkham image appears lower down - it is still useful as a contemorary image showing what the participants would have been equipped like.  I removed the black &amp; white victorian image - it was highly historically dubious with its 18th century style highlanders.  I've left the image of Bruce v. de Bohun because it is more accurate in its portrayal of costume, even if de Bohun's coat of arms is completely wrong.--[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 10:39, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

== Removal of promotional mention of fringe works ==

I have removed mention of the following book from the list of references:

* Scott, W., &quot;Bannockburn Proved&quot;, 2006

as added without explanation on 13:00, 18 July 2013 [[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Bannockburn&amp;diff=564784682&amp;oldid=564204749]]. I note that Mr Scott's work has been discussed in the past on this talk page, and nothing convinces me here or a quick Google search that these books are anything other that the [[WP:FRINGE|fringe theories]] of one man. Most of the activity involving Mr Scott's work seems to come from one editor, and that editor's edits solely concern adding mention of Mr Scott's work. I have also removed the 2 other remaining mentions of Mr Scott's books on Wikipedia, along with seemingly promotional links to his website, from the articles [[Henry de Beaumont]] and [[John III Comyn, Lord of Badenoch]]. [[User:Rubiscous|Rubiscous]] ([[User talk:Rubiscous|talk]]) 19:28, 9 October 2013 (UTC)

==Moving to GA/FA==
Is there any interest among editors in getting this to GA and perhaps FA status before the centenary in June? It would make a good front page article for that day.--&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Black Chancery;text:grey 0.3em 0.3em 0.1em;&quot;&gt;'''[[User:Sabrebd|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;SabreBD&lt;/span&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Sabrebd|talk&lt;/span&gt;]]) 07:43, 16 January 2014 (UTC)
:Happy to contribute if I can [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 18:03, 16 January 2014 (UTC)
::That is great, thanks. Lets give a bit of time to see if anyone else volunteers and then look at what needs doing.--&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Black Chancery;text:grey 0.3em 0.3em 0.1em;&quot;&gt;'''[[User:Sabrebd|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;SabreBD&lt;/span&gt;]]''' ([[User talk:Sabrebd|talk&lt;/span&gt;]]) 11:53, 17 January 2014 (UTC)
:::I have few credible sources to hand but I am willing to help if I can. For a GA attempt I'd say it needs a couple of dozen or more inline refs, (probably the sources quoted already would do if someone has 'em and can fish out page nos), an expansion of the &quot;Historical significance&quot; section and a good copy edit. Assuming editors with some genuine credentials history-wise are involved in that, getting it to FA is often an exercise in more detailed copy-editing and diplomacy rather than content creation. In the context of the politics of Scotland in 2014, getting agreement on the 'significance' might prove interesting. [[User:Ben MacDui|&lt;font color=&quot;#6495ED&quot;&gt;Ben&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Ben MacDui|&lt;font color=&quot;#C154C1&quot;&gt;Mac&lt;/font&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Ben MacDui|&lt;font color=&quot;#228B22&quot;&gt;Dui&lt;/font&gt;]] 16:58, 26 January 2014 (UTC)

===Article improvements===
I have noticed that there is masses of unsourced information in the article. I have a source that I would like to use to improve the article. Noting that any unsourced info can be removed from Wikipedia. I will of course leave in any existing sourced information. Comments appreciated.[[User:QuintusPetillius|QuintusPetillius]] ([[User talk:QuintusPetillius|talk]]) 15:18, 14 June 2014 (UTC)
::Can I suggest you first add what sources you can, then give time for other editors to assist if possible before removing content?  If all the unsourced content was removed from the article (which is dreadfully undercited), we risk having a patchy sub in place just before the 700th anniversary.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 15:33, 14 June 2014 (UTC)

I feel as if the removal of unsourced content did not change much.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Hannibalcaesar|Hannibalcaesar]] ([[User talk:Hannibalcaesar|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hannibalcaesar|contribs]]) 22:34, 18 September 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:First off, the vast majority of the article was unsourced and was therefore written to a bad standard. Wikipedia is about quoting the sources and reflecting what the sources say. Not just adding any old jargon of whatever you feel like. The &quot;new&quot; article replaced the unsourced info with properly sourced info from a published secondary source.[[User:QuintusPetillius|QuintusPetillius]] ([[User talk:QuintusPetillius|talk]]) 07:49, 19 September 2014 (UTC)

== Battlefield interpretative centre presentations ==

Is anyone able to add something to the heritage centre section on the new interpretative centre displays, which are quite innovative (in the UK at least), so worthy of note.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 15:38, 14 June 2014 (UTC) 
Sadly they're pretty grim, much more to do with an exciting visual experience than the nature of the event...all the Victorian myths recycled and put onto computer screens and digital projections. probably best to ignore them I'm afraid.

== Repeated addition of links to personal website... ==

Leodgunn, you've added an external link to a personal website of what appears to be excerpts from your book &quot;The Bruce, Bannockburn and Beyond&quot; four times now, and been reverted by three different editors. In addition to this being edit-warring, please have a look at [[WP:EXT]], which gives guidance on this, and in particular the line that runs &quot;you should avoid linking to a site that you own, maintain, or represent&quot;. If you've an interest in history, consider editing the article itself, which would be welcomed, rather than adding links to your own websites across the wiki, which isn't. 
[[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 22:02, 12 August 2014 (UTC)

== Recent edits==
I have removed a small number of statements which may w=be sourced, but are not at all reliable. The term schiltrom does not imply any particular shape. It is likely that Moray deployed part of his division (the 'men of his own leding' as Barbour puts it) in a schiltrom to face the English,   cavalry on Day 1, but circular schiltroms would not have been at all practical for the main action on day 2. There is no reason to assume that Scottish men-at-arms were equipped any differently from English ones; if it were the case, surely contemporary material would tell us so. In fact  - pay rolls, restauro, horse and armour purchases and  all the record evidence points to complete interchangeability. The case for 'lighter' Scots depends entirely on one line in Barbour's poem - two generations after the event - which is, in itself, contradicted by the very next line.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.158.135.83|86.158.135.83]] ([[User talk:86.158.135.83|talk]]) 17:18, 24 March 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Are there any secondary sources that you could provide to support your argument? (e.g. an academic article or book etc. that makes these points)  [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:38, 24 March 2015 (UTC)
Pretty much any bit of  scholarship on the subject - Andrew Ayton, Michael Prestwich, Michael Brown,  - but since my Thesis (published as Knights of the Scottish Wars of Independence) was on the subject of the Scottish man-at-arms class in the early 14th C. I 'd suggest ...me - I just would n't feel right about citing myself. There is absolutely no evidence at all (apart from the one line in Barbour's poem) to support the contention that Scottish men-at-arms were equipped at all differently from their English counterparts. The contention has been repeated widely for over 100 years, but it is not evidence-based. Barbour was making a propaganda claim; in the very next line he goes on to tell us that the Scottish cavalry were all well-armoured in steel. By deleting amendments the editor is reinforcing accounts which depend on recycling the inventions of Gardiner and Oman; surely we can do better than that.
I am a bit concerned about the reliance on some rather questionable sources for the main article, but I 'd not want to get into a rammy by making wholesale changes. Even so, if this is to become a good and useful piece - and given the amount of material available there's no reason why it should n't - it could do with some work. C.Brown.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.158.135.83|86.158.135.83]] ([[User talk:86.158.135.83|talk]]) 18:01, 24 March 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::Awkward.  Chris Brown has written one of the best recent works on bannockburn.  If anyone else was referencing his work, it wouldn't be a problem.  Also, we should note that the idea that schiltrons were not always circular is covered by the wikipedia article on the subject [[Sheltron]].[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 21:20, 25 March 2015 (UTC)
:::Provided the interest is declared (as it has been) and we've got the works and page references, there shouldn't be a problem in Chris adding them in. The issues around writers citing their own work only usually emerge if its done anonymously, or if their works don't represent mainstream opinion. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 18:09, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
I've made couple of changes, but I'm not really clear how to adjust the reference numbering. A whole bunch (all numbered '10') refer to Jeremy Black's book, including the unsupportable modern assumption about 'light' Scottish cavalry. As a stop-gap measure I could cite me - Bannockburn 1314, p.129-30, History Press, but I'd feel a bit iffy about that...self-promotion and all that.
The article as a whole really is n't awfully good, but it could be made so given that we have a lot of material to work from and I'd be more than happy to collaborate with others on improving it.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.137.246.79|86.137.246.79]] ([[User talk:86.137.246.79|talk]]) 13:09, 13 April 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
I see that the 'light cavalry' thing has been re-instated despite the evidence to the contrary. What can be done about that?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by Chris Brown. Who  is Sinebot? She/He continually reverts amendments, but offers no justification for doing so.  [[Special:Contributions/86.137.246.79|86.137.246.79]] ([[User talk:86.137.246.79|talk]]) 17:30, 19 April 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:[[User:SineBot|Sinebot]] signs unsigned posts on talk pages when the editor fails to, so it has been signing your posts here with your IP address as you have not been signing them. It does not make changes to articles.

:I reverted your change because, per [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Bannockburn&amp;diff=715055929&amp;oldid=715055403 the edit summary]: &quot;no references given; rv to cited material&quot;. You may be sure that the existing text may be wrong but it is referenced and your changes to the text are not. You may be convinced of your contrary view but even if it is problematic to provide reliable sources for your changes, you must do so. You are correct to be cautious about citing your own works but it isn't outrightly prohibited and may be justified in some cases; see [[Wikipedia:SELFCITE]]. I'm not sure why the other participants above haven't cited the work in question if they regard it as a [[WP:RS|reliable source]], unless they don't have access to a copy. [[User:Mutt Lunker|Mutt Lunker]] ([[User talk:Mutt Lunker|talk]]) 21:58, 19 April 2016 (UTC) 
I would have done so if I had known how to alter the footnote numbering. So what should I do now? How do I alter the referencing? I'd be keen to see a much better article (and it's not as if there's a dearth of valid material rather than re-hashes of Victorian antiquarianism) if only to reduce the amount of time spent explaining to people how bad the article is. CB.

:See [[Wikipedia:Citing sources]] and [[Wikipedia:Signatures]]. [[User:Mutt Lunker|Mutt Lunker]] ([[User talk:Mutt Lunker|talk]]) 16:19, 20 April 2016 (UTC)

:: I'll give it a go - I both have the book and think it is a reliable source.  While I personally am convinced by Chris' arguments (which hinge round a misinterpretation of Barbour which tends to be repeated by authors not going back to sources), I think it will need a conditional statement as reputable historians do repeat the &quot;light cavalry&quot; version.  @ Chris Brown - Chris, you can sign your posts by clicking on those four blue tildes after '''Sign your post''' in the short cuts below.  I'd also advise, for etiquette if nothing else, to sign up as an editor.  IP editors are viewed with suspicion by established editors (because so many are disruptive, I suppose).  You however are a serious historian and should reflect that in a named account.  Best wishes [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 17:49, 21 April 2016 (UTC)

Okey-dokey; how do I sign up as an editor?[[Special:Contributions/86.131.148.57|86.131.148.57]] ([[User talk:86.131.148.57|talk]]) 15:10, 22 April 2016 (UTC)

:[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:UserLogin?type=signup Here]. [[User:Mutt Lunker|Mutt Lunker]] ([[User talk:Mutt Lunker|talk]]) 16:07, 22 April 2016 (UTC)

:: I've edited the bit on Scottish cavalry and referenced same.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 11:03, 23 April 2016 (UTC)
It's still there at the beginning of the article I'm afraid. Don't know if you missed it or if someone is reverting it[[Special:Contributions/86.131.148.57|86.131.148.57]] ([[User talk:86.131.148.57|talk]]) 17:14, 25 April 2016 (UTC)https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Battle_of_Bannockburn&amp;action=edit&amp;section=28#

== Numbers &amp; Losses ==

The correct numbers at the Battle of Bannockburn are - Scotland - 10,000
                                                                                            England - 20,000
The Scottish losses 600-800 Men and the English losses were 7,000 - 9,000 

These numbers a given by the Battle of Bannockburn Heritage members themselves, so they would be very accurate. But when I try to edit the inbox it keeps on resseting to the untrue estimates. So how can I edit the inbox without it resseting?

 [[User:Dragon25920|Dragon25920]] ([[User talk:Dragon25920|talk]]) 20:02, 15 July 2016 (UTC)

:Well, Rowanis12 sockpuppet:
*Nusbacher, Aryeh (2000). The Battle of Bannockburn 1314. Stroud: Tempus. p. 85. ISBN 0-7524-1783-5.
*Oman, Charles (1991) [1924]. A History of the Art of War in the Middle Ages Vol. II. London: Greenhill Books. p. 88. ISBN 1-85367-105-3.
*Armstrong, Pete (2002). Bannockburn. Botley, Oxford: Osprey Publishing. p. 43. ISBN 1-85532-609-4.
*Grant, R.G. (2008), Battle: A visual journey through 5,000 years of combat, DK Publishing,p.118.
*Sadler, John, Scottish Battles, (Biddles Ltd., 1998), 52–54.
*Grant, 118.
*Mackenzie, p.88 referencing Walsingham, p.141
*Reese, p.174
:You appear to be ignoring a few reliable sources. Care to explain your editing? FYI, the &quot;Battle of Bannockburn Heritage members&quot;, do not appear to be [[Wikipedia:RS|reliable sources]]. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 20:27, 15 July 2016 (UTC)

::There are no &quot;correct numbers&quot;, only estimates.  The info box therefore compiles a range of estimates from reliable secondary sources to demonstrate this uncertainty.  This is how wikipedia is supposed to work.  Not knowing the group Battle of Bannockburn Heritage, I have no way of knowing whether their estimates would be any more accurate than any other published author on the subject but I doubt it, as they'd be working from the same evidence.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 11:25, 16 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>76rna6dtqm8pshkz576j2mnnmaw0sux</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
