<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Kurukshetra War</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2415289</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739338826</id>
      <parentid>739326462</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-14T03:37:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ravensfire</username>
        <id>4156945</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sunil Sheoran */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25669">{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Hinduism|class=B|importance=high|myth=yes|vaishnavism=yes|krishna=yes}}
{{WikiProject India|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=C|B1=n|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Classical=yes|South-Asian=yes}}
{{WikiProject Mythology|class=|importance=}}
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archive = Talk:Kurukshetra War/Archive %(counter)d
|algo = old(90d)
|counter = 1
|maxarchivesize = 200K
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
}}

==Date of Occurance==

I hope i dont screw this page up in my contribution, but the date posted &quot;P. V. Vartak calculates a date of October 16, 5561 BCE using planetary positions.&quot; seems highly unlogical, because the number of participants would be greater than half of the world's population at thetime period, as stated in the wikipedia site, 6th century B.C. &quot;World population is essentially stable at circa 5 million people, though some speculate up to 7,000,000.&quot;  I would appreciate some insight here. [[User:Ghost9420|Ghost9420]] ([[User talk:Ghost9420|talk]]) 23:54, 30 April 2010 (UTC)

:Krishna passed away in 3102 BCE which marks the beginning of Kaliyuga. Long after the Kurukshetra war when both Arjuna and Krishna were older men, Arjuna went to Dwarka to see Krishna and Dwarka was about to be run over by the waters of the ocean and all the people including Arjuna and Krishna evacuated Dwarka and were going east. At this time Arjuna was not able to keep his bow and arrow steady because of the old age. And during a conversation Krishna told Arjuna that Dwapara Yuga is coming to an end and Kaliyuga is about to begin. The correct date of Kurukshetra war is 3139 BCE as explained in (note 1) in the main article.
[[User:Kingcircle|Kingcircle]] ([[User talk:Kingcircle|talk]]) 04:18, 22 February 2016 (UTC)

== Historical Evidence ==

I think it would be appropriate to mention that the only evidence of this war is in the Mahabaratha, and maybe some additional information on historical evidence that has shown atleast some of aspects of the event to be true.

I think it may be worth mentioning here about Prof. Rao's findings on Dwaraka City. It may through some light on Mahabharata war date and it seems that the date is close to Prof. Iyngar's prediction that the war could have happened around 15th century BC.

== Dating ==

=== Dating by B. N. Achar ===
An IP [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kurukshetra_War&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=707360086&amp;oldid=707360014 re-inserted] this piece of info at the incorrect place:
:''&quot;Physicist Narahari Achar &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=B. N. Narahari Achar Professor Emeritus|url=http://www.memphis.edu/physics/people/profiles/b-achar.php|website=http://www.memphis.edu/|publisher=University of Memphis|accessdate=28 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; used planetarium software to argue that the Mahabharata War took place in 3067 BCE &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Singh|first1=Bal Ram|title=Origin of Indian civilization|date=2010|publisher=Published by Center for Indic Studies, University of Massachusetts and D.K. Printworld, New Delhi|location=Dartmouth|isbn=8124605602|page=Chapter 7, Pp. 202-252; 302|edition=First|url=http://www.dkprintworld.com/product-detail.php?pid=1280856795|accessdate=28 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;''
{{reflist-talk}}
Stating that Narahari Achar is a physicist is a claim from authority. The fact that he is a Professor Emeritus is irrelevant to the status of his calculations, which depart from the scholarly concencus. This is underscored by the contents of ''[http://www.dkprintworld.com/product-detail.php?pid=1280856795 Origin of Indian civilization]'', which is a fine collection of fringe-theory: ''&quot;The papers examine the events that gave rise to the Aryan invasion theory and debunk the theory as a myth and present evidence and arguments supporting the theory that the Rigveda was composed in its bulk in the fourth millennium bce.&quot;'' Ergo, his dating, which was already included, does not belong in the &quot;Scholarly datings&quot; section. [[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 12:29, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
::You clearly outline the issue with biased western historians and editors on wikipedia trolling around reverting edits by South Asian editors to dates that are dismissed in that article but upheld on Wikipedia removing it is a deliberate act racism and cultural revisionism in my view.--[[Special:Contributions/175.157.204.29|175.157.204.29]] ([[User talk:175.157.204.29|talk]]) 12:37, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
:::[[Wikipedia:Talk page guidelines]]: ''&quot;Talk pages are for improving the encyclopedia, not for expressing personal opinions on a subject or an editor.&quot;'' See also [[WP:TPNO]]: 

::::''&quot;Please note that some of the following are of sufficient importance to be official Wikipedia policy. Violations (and especially repeated violations) may lead to the offender being blocked or banned from editing Wikipedia.
::::''* No personal attacks: A personal attack is saying something negative about another person. This includes:
:::::''* No insults: Do not make ad hominem attacks, such as calling someone an idiot or a fascist. Instead, explain what is wrong with an edit and how to fix it.&quot;''

:::[[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 13:12, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

::::'''Comment''' Looking at that IP address edits he did provide edit summaries and you kept reverting them and you also removed the citation tags when the debate of archaeological evidence (Witzel) is questionable as discussed in this work by Vishal Agarwal, Richard Meadow, Martin Huld, Edwin Bryant, D. P. Agrawal, Asko Parpola, Stefan Zimmer, J. P. Mallory, Elena Kuzmina 11 August 2003 [http://www.jies.org/Discussion/MichaelWitzel.pdf ''A Reply to Michael Witzel’s ‘Ein Fremdling im Rgveda’''] those dates in the scholarly section should be properly cited anyway you chose not to insert citations when you reverted and why should they take you word for it? If you don't agree add the citation and not keep adding fuel to the fire.--[[User:Navops47|Navops47]] ([[User talk:Navops47|talk]]) 14:19, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
{{od}}
Navops47, have you any clue what this is about? 
* The &quot;information&quot; this IP provided was already in the article; the dating by Narahari Achar is not a scholarly dating, and does not belong in the section with scholarly datings. 
* The removal of the citation-tag was a mistake. The intention was to rollback the addition on Narahari Achar; unfortunately I also removed the citation-tag, which was indeed rightfully placed there. Anyway, I provided a citation by Michael Witzel. 
* The pdf you linked to is not by ''&quot;Vishal Agarwal, Richard Meadow, Martin Huld, Edwin Bryant, D. P. Agrawal, Asko Parpola, Stefan Zimmer, J. P. Mallory, Elena Kuzmina&quot;'', but solely by Vishal Agarwal, in response to Michael Witzel, which was a response to Kazanas' original article in the JIES. Please read [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Indigenous_Aryans/Archive_3#RfC:_the_.22Indigenous_Aryans.22_theory_is_fringe-theory RfC: the &quot;Indigenous Aryans&quot; theory is fringe-theory] to get a grip on the value of Kazanas' publication. From that thread:
{{blockquote|
:''&quot;In 2002 Kazanas was allowed to publish in &quot;The Journal of Indo-European Studies&quot;, probably the only publication by an &quot;Indigenist&quot; in the JIES ({{cite journal |last=Mallory |first=J. P. |title=Editor's Note: The Indo-Aryan Migration Debate |journal=[[Journal of Indo-European Studies]] |volume=30 |number=3 &amp; 4 |year=2002 |pp=273-274}}[https://beta.groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/akandabaratam/conversations/messages/46143]) Mallory, editor of the Journal of Indo-European Studies, and emeritus professor at Queen's University, Belfast, and a member of the Royal Irish Academy, introduced this with an explanation, in which he stated:[https://beta.groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/akandabaratam/conversations/messages/46143]
:::''&quot;Many regard the scholarship of the Indigenous Indo-Aryan camp so seriously flawed that it should not be given an airing [...]  I indicated that I thought it would be unlikely that any referee would agree with [Kazanas'] conclusions.&quot;''

:''Michael Witzel, Wales Professor of Sanskrit at Harvard University, commented:
:::''&quot;It is certain that Kazanas, now that he is published in JIES, will be quoted endlessly by Indian fundamentalists and nationalists as &quot;a respected scholar published in major peer-reviewed journals like JIES&quot; -- no matter how absurd his claims are known to be by specialist readers of those journals. It was through means like these that the misperception has taken root in Indian lay sectors that the historical absurdities of Kak, Frawley, and even Rajaram are taken seriously by academic scholars.&quot; (Wiztel (2003), ''Ein Fremdling in Ṛgveda'', JIES vol 312003, p23, §5 end))''}}
[[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 14:59, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

:Oh right, you misread this sentence from [[:Nicholas Kazanas]]: ''&quot;His [Nicholas Kazanas] work was criticized by M Witzel, Richard Meadow, Martin Huld, Edwin Bryant, D. P. Agrawal, Asko Parpola, Stefan Zimmer, J. P. Mallory, Elena Kuzmina and others.&quot;'' [[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 15:14, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
::Also note that ''&quot;(Journal of Indo-European Studies, Vol. 31, No.1-2: pp.107-185, 2003)&quot;'' refers to Witzel's publication, not to Agarwal's reply, which was ''not'' published in the JIES, but only added to the website. [[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 15:18, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

::::The issue they seem to have is being lectured to by westerners as to what is their history and what is not I suggest they have a far better understanding of their own history than either I do you do or Witzel does &quot;The most widely accepted date is 10th century BCE or 950 BCE, according to archeological evidence&quot; says who? Not referenced sufficiently in the section to make that claim and should be there. ''Basham considers the beginning of the 9th century BCE as a more plausible date for the events. Again where is the source link? also your repeated use of scholarly as justification for reverting http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/scholarly. Michael Witzel (born July 18, 1943) is a '''German-American''' philologist and academic. Professor Achar scientist and academic received his early education in '''India''' earned his MS and PhD degrees from the Pennsylvania State University research Ancient Sanskrit texts of India I would suggest he reads its as does Witzel excuse me BOTH are scholars one is no better than the other and what ever they publish is scholarly that's a ridiculous assertion stating one viewpoint matters the other does'nt.--[[User:Navops47|Navops47]] ([[User talk:Navops47|talk]]) 15:35, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

:::::Says who?  [[Upinder Singh]] who is clearly not a Western historian. As the article now states, she has written that &quot;Whether a bitter war between the Pandavas and the Kauravas ever happened cannot be proved or disproved It is possible that there was a small-scale conflict, transformed into a gigantic epic war by bards and poets. Some historians and archaeologists have argued that this conflict may have occurred in about 1000 bce.&quot; It looks as though you haven't read the article carefully. And we should never try to decide that one nationality must be the source for their own history - that's not the way we work at all. In any case it's easy to find examples in most countries of authors, even professionals, who put forward a nationalistic agenda that overrides the evidence. This is a problem in India at the moment, it was a serious problem in Japan where a prominent archaeologist faked finds to make them look older, in happens in the US, the UK, etc. Achar's postgraduate work wasn't in ancient texts - this is outside his speciality. You can be a scholar in one field and an amateur in another. Barry Fell was a prominent US professor of marine biology at Harvard who wrote books of nonsense on Celts, Ogham, etc. He was also both a scholar and an amateur. You ask where the Basham source link is? It's at the first mention of Basham - again you missed it. Maybe we need to condense these but we don't need to source the same statement twice. By the way, I changed the description of Achar to read 'physicist' because the wording before seemed to be an argument from authority, while 'physicist' to me at least suggests he's an amateur when he writes about this. Physics isn't astronomy or history. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 15:54, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
::::::Final word on the matter physics one of the oldest academic disciplines, perhaps the oldest through its inclusion of astronomy (assume then older than philology) that involves the study of matter and its motion through space and time (dates) that's what is important here!. [[Upinder Singh]] wheres the citation I can't see it also states the wide range of views (absolute, sweeping  unconditional, overall, all-inclusive) they still need to be cited when I have made that statement in articles I cite it substantially. I also don't agree with the fact that a scientist who can prove it (date) through mathematical equesions is less important than the study of languages does not stack up in my book. I also looked a lot at Joshua's revert history he appears to revert a dis-proportionate high number of users from South Asia quite a lot whats that all about then?--[[User:Navops47|Navops47]] ([[User talk:Navops47|talk]]) 16:39, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
:::::::I can't help it if you can't find the citation to Singh, I can guarantee it's there. Search for it, it's in the section 'Historical context'. Note that Singh is mentioned twice and the citation is in the first mention. Astronomy is not physics, and what Achar has done isn't really astronomy, it was using texts with planetarium software. Not physics. Achar's work in physics is nothing to do with the physical aspects of astronomy. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 16:58, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
::::::::And you really can't prove the date with just mathematics, you have to interpret the texts for a start. In other words, it's subjective, not objective. So not 'proof', not like carbon14 dating of artifacts and even then there are other issues. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 16:59, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::Mathematics is the absolute study measurement so your wrong there I won't change my opinion and don't agree as for Singhs citation is not exactly in the section were TALKING about its in the lead she also does not state definitely the date  '''&quot;may have occurred in about 1000 bce&quot;''' one view point ONLY not widespread view as stated we have '''6 references ONLY''' not very widespread or substantial in my view when you see articles with 000's  of references that's widespread sourcing I am for a balanced argument from both sides of the debate equally given not one way traffic and I'm sure I could find many Indian academics that would argue against Singh's hypothesis the reverts are being done on the basis of unsubstantiated '''sources''' in that '''section''' we are '''talking about''' and if some other scholar University Researcher does not agree with that hypothesis include it in the scholarly section otherwise that is misleading the average reader.--[[User:Navops47|Navops47]] ([[User talk:Navops47|talk]]) 17:47, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

{{od}}Her citation is not in the lead. I can see where it is and it hasn't been moved. It's clearly given as her opinion. Mathematics an exact science until you start to apply it, then it is no longer exact. &quot;Garbage in garbage out&quot; applies to mathematics as well as computing. It doesn't matter if you don't understand this. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 18:53, 28 February 2016 (UTC)
:How in the world did I let myself get distracted into talking about mathematics. Achar used a computer, so GIGO applies perfectly. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 21:45, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

::Scholars versus fringe theorists is not &quot;a balanced argument.&quot; Unfortunately, as long as there are people who don't know the difference; who think that mythology is the same as history; and who think that the rest of the world has to believe what they believe, and that Wikipedia exists to spread those beliefs; so long will it be necessary to &quot;lecture on history.&quot; Not only by westerners, also by Indians and editors of all other parts of the world. [[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 04:49, 29 February 2016 (UTC)

===References===
The [[:Mahabharata]] article contains the references which are missing here. I bet that some &lt;s&gt;POV-pusher removed them here&lt;/s&gt; one copied plain text from that article. [[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 05:16, 29 February 2016 (UTC)
:As I write, references 1, 4 and 5 in this article are to Singh. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 05:57, 29 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Kurukshetra War]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=713006775 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.ejvs.laurasianacademy.com/ejvs0104/ejvs0104article.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 10:23, 1 April 2016 (UTC)

== Sunil Sheoran ==

An editor has recently been [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kurukshetra_War&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=739155620 adding a claim] about the date by this person sourced to a presentation uploaded to a random site.  It's self-published and I can see no evidence this person a scholar in this area. The phrasing is also extremely POV. Discussion here as the editor has been pushing this repeatedly into the article. &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;darkred&quot;&gt;[[User:Ravensfire|Ravensfire]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Ravensfire|talk]])&lt;/font&gt; 12:39, 13 September 2016 (UTC)

'''Response:''' So, what's the problem with self-published work? This is a research work. If you would have known anything about Mahabharata, you wouldn't have deleted the small dating reference that people may find helpful. Did you even bother to look through the contents of the link provided? 

As far as Mahabharata dating is concerned, this dating is closest to Archaeological dating by BB Lal, an eminent archaeologist of India, and also uses the astronomical parameters stated in Mahabharata. Deleting it without an analysis/evaluation goes to show what kind of ignoramus you are.

And for your information, Slideshare.net is not a RANDOM SITE, it's one of biggest presentations site in the world. Google it.
Do you consider Quora.com also as a random site? If yes, to hell with Wikipedia. Better be in company of few wise people than be in company of fools.
If no, here is his profile: https://www.quora.com/profile/Sunil-Sheoran. Noticed how much he contributes?  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/49.32.56.144|49.32.56.144]] ([[User talk:49.32.56.144|talk]]) 12:59, 13 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:You have to follow our policies. See [[WP:SPS]]. It's also not reliably published, see [[WP:SPS]]. We don't care how much he contributes to open sites such as quora.com, any fool, as you say, can do that. We wouldn't use Wikipedia as a source either or an editor with 200,000 edits here just because they had so many edits. Anyone can contribute to slideshare.net just as they can contribute to YouTube. It doesn't count here. We are an encyclopedia based upon what [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] say about a subject.  You're not going to be happy here taking that attitude. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 14:31, 13 September 2016 (UTC)

'''Response #2:
'''
Oh really? Look at the following extract from this very page:

&quot;Day 1
When the battle was commenced, Bhishma went through the Pandava army wreaking havoc wherever he went but Abhimanyu, Arjuna's son, seeing this went straight at Bhishma, defeated his bodyguards and directly attacked the commander of the Kaurava forces. The Pandavas suffered numerous losses and were defeated at the end of the first day. Virata's sons, Uttara and Sweta, were slain by Shalya and Bhishma. Krishna consoled the distraught Yudhishthira saying that eventually victory would be his.&quot;

Now ask yourself? Where did you get it from? Who put it here? I don't see a reliable source. Where are all these lines written? I don't see any source quoted. Now since there is no quoted reliable source, how do you allow it to continue here?

The problem, my friend, with your approach, is that your approach is robotic and overtly technical rather than a well-versed and intelligent one.

With people like you staffing YOUR Wikipedia.org, I am sure it wouldn't last very long. People who don't know anything history are editing history articles. Best of luck, I say BYE BYE BYE to your website forever. Congratulations for making good the loss of one client to your website !!  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/49.32.56.144|49.32.56.144]] ([[User talk:49.32.56.144|talk]]) 16:12, 13 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:It is sourced, to the ''[[Mahabharata]]'' where the tale of this war comes from.  It is a reliable source for a summary of itself.  Huge difference.  You, however, are not a reliable source.  Nor is your presentation.  You really need to read our page on [[WP:RS|reliable source]]s to get some more information on what is and is not a reliable source.  You also need to dial back your tone a lot.  This is a collaborative website, not combative.  You won't find much help with the tone you've taken. Think about it. &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;darkred&quot;&gt;[[User:Ravensfire|Ravensfire]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Ravensfire|talk]])&lt;/font&gt; 17:35, 13 September 2016 (UTC) 
::{{yo|Ravensfire}} this is a good hook to raise something that's been bothering me. Our policy at [[Wikipedia:What Wikipedia is not]] says &quot; articles on works of non-fiction, including documentaries, research books and papers, religious texts, and the like, should contain more than a recap or summary of the works' contents. Such articles should be expanded to have broader coverage.&quot; This is far too much of a summary of the source to make me comfortable. [[User:Doug Weller|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#070&quot;&gt;Doug Weller&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Doug Weller|talk]] 17:45, 13 September 2016 (UTC)
:::{{replyto|Doug Weller}} I won't disagree with you there, it is a rather long article.  It's part of a rather massive epic (1.8 million words!!) and seems to be a fairly significant part of that epic.  I think the impact of the epic is shown by the passion of various editors, plus several co-workers more familiar with this culture all confirmed the impact of the epic.  The article is really detailed into the story. &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;darkred&quot;&gt;[[User:Ravensfire|Ravensfire]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Ravensfire|talk]])&lt;/font&gt; 03:37, 14 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gxhwzmajf8y2zuib3p60iskcp4k4uyn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
