<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:IWI Tavor</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6973027</id>
    <revision>
      <id>714023128</id>
      <parentid>697965130</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-07T05:08:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avaya1</username>
        <id>1755816</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Avaya1 moved page [[Talk:IMI Tavor TAR-21]] to [[Talk:IWI Tavor]]: the article encompasses different variants and it is IWI now</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18609">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=C|B1=n|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Weaponry-task-force=yes|Middle-Eastern=yes}}
{{WikiProject Firearms|class=start}}
{{WikiProject Israel|class=B|importance=mid}}
}}

==Units in service==
The TAR-21 has just entered service with the Golani Brigade as well as the Givati Brigade as of August 2008.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/89.139.152.16|89.139.152.16]] ([[User talk:89.139.152.16|talk]]) 22:09, 22 August 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I have a friend in Kfir brigade who also has a TAR-21 as his personal weapon - AvihooI.

==Logic Edit==
For anyone who cares, I removed a statement that was logically incorrect about rifles.  The article said, before the edit that the rifle requires partial disassembly to swap from lefty to righty ejection.  That is true.  The article then said that a result of this is that a shooter can not shoulder the weapon to go around a corner on the &quot;wrong&quot; shoulder, and that this problem is unusual among rifles.  Most rifles in the world today are not easily configurable for right-handed or left-handed operation, without disassembly.  The most prolific rifles in the world at the moment (the AK-47 and M-16 families) can not be modified at all, most components must be replaced, including the receiver, to allow left-handed operation.  Even with these &quot;flaws&quot;, either can be fired from either shoulder, with a minor inconvenience to the shooter if it is on the &quot;wrong&quot; shoulder.  So both of those points are incorrect.  [[Special:Contributions/64.102.254.33|64.102.254.33]] ([[User talk:64.102.254.33|talk]]) 17:27, 19 March 2008 (UTC)

:There is no need to reconfigure an M16 or AK-47 to fire from the left shoulder.  Both will function perfectly from the left shoulder, and without any injury to the operator.  Most bullpup designs do not allow for left-shoulder use, without at least partial disassembly and reconfiguration as with the Tavor.  Some can not be reconfigured and are physically dangerous to fire from the left shoulder as the charging handle reciprocates and would strike the shooter in the face, causing serious injury.

:This is not a trivial criticism of bullpups.  Firing only from the right shoulder means that the soldier must expose his entire head and upper torso in order to fire around the left side of cover.  This greatly increases the likelihood of being injured or killed.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/97.127.185.105|97.127.185.105]] ([[User talk:97.127.185.105|talk]]) 09:56, 19 May 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


:It's true that the AK and AR can easily be fired from the opposite shoulder, but they have conventional layouts with the ejection port at least a foot forward of the back of the stock.  Ejected casings will easily clear the shooter's face.  Bullpup rifles like the Tavor are much more difficult to shoot off the opposite shoulder because the ejection port is much closer to the rear of the stock.  When firing a bullpup like this from the opposite shoulder it will eject casings right into the shooter's face.  Some bullpups solve this by ejecting spent cases downward (P90) or forward (Kel-Tec RFB).  The Tavor does neither.  [[User:Blackeagle|Blackeagle]] ([[User talk:Blackeagle|talk]]) 21:32, 9 June 2009 (UTC)

::A Tavor can be fired from the &quot;wrong&quot; shoulder; getting hot cases in the face is uncomfortable, but does not preclude proper operation. [[Special:Contributions/68.146.30.79|68.146.30.79]] ([[User talk:68.146.30.79|talk]]) 10:38, 22 February 2011 (UTC)

:The Tavor is not 100% designed for left-handers but at least it has a design more suitable than Singapore [[SAR-21]]. The SAR-21 cannot be easily shot using the left-hand while even the Micro-Tavor can.
[[Special:Contributions/147.188.254.196|147.188.254.196]] ([[User talk:147.188.254.196|talk]]) 11:36, 4 January 2012 (UTC)

==addition==
on fps creator, there is a weaopn called tavor. should that be included? &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/97.81.109.36|97.81.109.36]] ([[User talk:97.81.109.36|talk]]) 21:02, 29 April 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

No? [[User:Koalorka|Koalorka]] ([[User talk:Koalorka|talk]]) 21:40, 23 March 2008 (UTC)

Why should it be included? [[User:Spartan198|Spartan198]] ([[User talk:Spartan198|talk]]) 01:24, 22 August 2009 (UTC)

== maximum Range ==

On the Maximum range it says 3600m, That is more than a standard issue sniper rifle. Can this be changed to the correct range, and/or does anyone know the correct Maximum range? --[[User:91.105.29.13|91.105.29.13]] 10:55, 13 May 2007 (UTC)

Ithink taht this was made with a some of Isreali prejudice. There seem to be some of mistakes that glorifi the weapon.

I think whoever wrote that meant 360 meters, not 3600.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Zeratul2k|Zeratul2k]] ([[User talk:Zeratul2k|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Zeratul2k|contribs]]) 22:15, 2 September 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The '''maximum''' range is how far the bullet travels if unimpeded, and they often go much, much further than their '''effective''' range. The figure is not a mistake. [[User:Geoff B|Geoff B]] 22:29, 2 September 2007 (UTC)
:: They ALWAYS go further than their effective range. Otherwise, correct (-: --[[Special:Contributions/212.235.85.149|212.235.85.149]] ([[User talk:212.235.85.149|talk]]) 19:21, 2 November 2008 (UTC)

Actually, by my calculations (which do not include air resistance) the max range of a weapon firing at around 3000 feet per second is like twenty-something miles. There's no reason to doubt that a bullet will travel 3.6 kilometers. Hell, the warning label on a box of .22 rimfire ammo says &quot;lethal within five miles&quot; and a 5.56mm cartridge has a lot more ooomph than that stuff. Maximum range is a bogus stat, but if you're just asking &quot;how far it will go,&quot; then 3600 meters is a ''really'' conservative estimate. [[User:Archer884|J.M. Archer]] ([[User talk:Archer884|talk]]) 18:56, 17 March 2010 (UTC)


:Air resistance can not be ignored.  The maximum range of 5.56mm ball is about 3600m.  This is determined by actual testing.  The maximum range of .22LR cartridges is nowhere near &quot;five miles&quot;; it's about 2000m, again from actual testing.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/97.127.185.105|97.127.185.105]] ([[User talk:97.127.185.105|talk]]) 10:00, 19 May 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Issued? ==

has the Tavor been issued to Israeli infantry yet? [[User:82.47.137.100|82.47.137.100]] 19:39, 20 October 2007 (UTC)

AFAIK, no. I suppose it's possible, but not likely, that some of their SOF units have seeing as the SOF units of all nations don't always tell you what they use.[[Special:Contributions/65.54.154.46|65.54.154.46]] ([[User talk:65.54.154.46|talk]]) 05:02, 19 January 2008 (UTC)13tawaazun14

Just read the service section. [[Special:Contributions/86.84.221.109|86.84.221.109]] ([[User talk:86.84.221.109|talk]]) 00:04, 9 March 2008 (UTC)

Both of these comments are older then what is shown. I entered one of them like 2 years before my service changed.[[User:13Tawaazun14|13Tawaazun14]] ([[User talk:13Tawaazun14|talk]]) 23:15, 18 March 2008 (UTC)

== Another country using Tavor that is not mentioned ==

I saw a video by the Croatian army and they seem to use the Tavor.  Would someone with more expertise look this up, and then add it to the page?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/35.11.56.20|35.11.56.20]] ([[User talk:35.11.56.20|talk]]) 01:14, 14 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

You've probably confused the VHS for the TAR-21. I suggest you look at the video again. [[User:Jun Kayama|Jun Kayama]] ([[User talk:Jun Kayama|talk]]) 22:28, 5 October 2009 (UTC)

On this video you can see the TAR-21 in service in the Republic of Macedonia's armed forces (time index 2:57 and onwards):
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S04s40UuHRo&amp;feature=player_embedded
Does anyone have any data on this. This video is just 2 days old and is from the Independence Day parade....  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Captain dalan|Captain dalan]] ([[User talk:Captain dalan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Captain dalan|contribs]]) 17:57, 9 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Folding Stock ==
The article states: '''By 2005, IMI had supplied 350–400 Tavors to India's northern Special Frontier Force (SFF). These were declared to be &quot;operationally unsatisfactory&quot;, however, due to problems with their folding stock''.'

Folding stock? It's a bullpup, the stock categorically does not fold.

== Nahal Brigade ==

I added info about the upcoming switch to Tavor. [[User:PluniAlmoni|PluniAlmoni]] ([[User talk:PluniAlmoni|talk]]) 12:16, 5 April 2009 (UTC)

== Turkey ==

http://birliknet.net/uploads/1/33%5B1%5D.jpg

turkey use it this pohto is from 2008 or 2007  from  EFES Landing Traning

sorry there is no  source becouse  the weapon trades of the special forces  keeped secret

== Azerbaijan and Turkey ==
The Tavor is also in use with Azerbaijani and Turkish special forces, and there are numerous photos of these troops wielding Tavors in parades or exercises. The &quot;owner&quot; of this page seems to insist on having a &quot;credible source&quot; such as newspaper articles as references. Militaries in Turkey and Azerbaijan do not operate with the levels of transparency that Western populations take for granted, and many weapons purchases are simply never reported in the media. This means there probably will never be a &quot;credible source&quot; (by the criteria used in this article) for verifying Tavor's use in these countries. 

I wonder what could be more credible than actual photos showing the weapon in use by these countries' soldiers??

Azerbaijani special forces with Tavors: http://www.murdoconline.net/2008/azerbaijan_tavor.jpg
Turkish special forces with Tavors: http://img337.imageshack.us/img337/4382/pic00941lg2.jpg  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.172.111.123|173.172.111.123]] ([[User talk:173.172.111.123|talk]]) 04:37, 15 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Read [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|Wikipedia's verifiability policy]] or even the note you're shown when you open an edit window. Direct quote: '''Encyclopedic content must be verifiable. The threshold for inclusion in Wikipedia is verifiability, not truth'''. You need to provide either a [[Wikipedia:reliable sources|reliable source]] stating those organizations use the weapon, or else a picture with a caption from a reliable source identifying the organizations that are pictured. [[User:ROG5728|ROG5728]] ([[User talk:ROG5728|talk]]) 05:01, 15 May 2010 (UTC)

::Point taken. I was able to find a reference to Azerbaijan's Tavor purchase in the monthly bulletin of the Turkish Undersecretariat for Defense Industries, which in turn refers to a past issue of Jane's Defense Weekly. I added it as a reliable source and added Azerbaijan as a verifiable Tavor user. I hope to find a source for the Turkish purchase, too.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.172.111.123|173.172.111.123]] ([[User talk:173.172.111.123|talk]]) 06:28, 17 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Cleanup / merge ==

The Users section and the Deployment section should be re-arranged. The Deployment section may contain information about deployment in IDF, in this case the Users section should be called Export (without Israel). [[User:Flayer|Flayer]] ([[User talk:Flayer|talk]]) 16:55, 19 August 2010 (UTC)
:Done. [[User:PluniAlmoni|PluniAlmoni]] ([[User talk:PluniAlmoni|talk]]) 09:30, 25 August 2010 (UTC)
::Thank you! [[User:Flayer|Flayer]] ([[User talk:Flayer|talk]]) 10:37, 25 August 2010 (UTC)

== Fire selector options ==

In this article, it states that the Tavor allows for semi-automatic, Burst, and fully automatic fire, with a &quot;safe&quot; position as well, but, according to numerous sources, IWI's website being one of them, the weapon is not configured for &quot;burst fire&quot;. I do have to say it is not entirely impossible a version which allows two or three round bursts(most likely three)was or is manufactured in small numbers, but to my knowledge there isn't.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.131.101.161|66.131.101.161]] ([[User talk:66.131.101.161|talk]]) 23:50, 12 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Reference site not now available. ==

It seems this reference site is no longer available.

^ &quot;IWI Tavor civilian semi-automatic carbine&quot;. Canadaammo.com. Retrieved 2010-08-31

Please make note!

Regards,
Ronald L. Hughes

[[Special:Contributions/96.19.158.71|96.19.158.71]] ([[User talk:96.19.158.71|talk]]) 22:03, 27 June 2012 (UTC)Ronald L. Hughes

== Problem in design description ==

The article states &quot;The TAR-21 is waterproof&quot; 
What does that even mean, hahahaha, no conventional rifle or bull-pup rifle is &quot;Water proof&quot; lol, makes no sense at all.
It then goes on to say
The weapon has a built in laser and MARS red dot sight; one of the main advantages of having a built in system is that the weapon does not have to be zeroed after each use
Again this statement doesn't make sense, it suggests that other firearms without such a system need to be re-zeroed after each use, this is entirely false, even with aftermarket sights such as the aimpoint, eotech, or acog, when replaced on the same slot of pcatinny rail, no re zero is necessary.

This section should be edited accordingly[[Special:Contributions/96.54.181.40|96.54.181.40]] ([[User talk:96.54.181.40|talk]]) 21:01, 30 December 2012 (UTC)

== IMI or IWI? ==

There are numerous references in this article to IMI and IWI. Are these typos, or are there really two separate entities. If there are, need clarification.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/205.247.207.210|205.247.207.210]] ([[User talk:205.247.207.210|talk]]) 17:12, 14 March 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:IWI used to be the Small Arms Division of IMI, an Israeli government-owned company.  IMI sold the Small Arms Division to a group of private owners who renaed it IWI.

:http://www.israel-weapon.com/default.asp?catid={5C80290A-8823-4F46-9454-675D18629CC1}  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/97.127.185.105|97.127.185.105]] ([[User talk:97.127.185.105|talk]]) 10:07, 19 May 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Why no comparision with Steyr AUG? ==

Another older bullpup, similar and its not worth mentioning?
[[User:Alexmcfire|Alexmcfire]] ([[User talk:Alexmcfire|talk]]) 20:55, 26 August 2013 (UTC)

*...or the FN F2000 -  ''[[User: Thewolfchild|&lt;sup&gt;the&lt;/sup&gt;'''&lt;big&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Matisse itc;color:red&quot;&gt;WOLF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/big&gt;'''&lt;small&gt;child&lt;/small&gt;]]'' 07:25, 31 May 2014 (UTC)

:::Because no reliable sources have made that comparison, and we can not make our own. [[Special:Contributions/217.209.73.224|217.209.73.224]] ([[User talk:217.209.73.224|talk]]) 03:17, 3 January 2016 (UTC)

== Adding this for user reference? ==

Should we add this since the Pennsylvania State Capitol Police adopted the Tavor SAR? [[User:Ominae|Ominae]] ([[User talk:Ominae|talk]]) 07:37, 30 August 2013 (UTC)

[http://www.tactical-life.com/news/pennsylvania-state-capitol-police-adopt-iwi-tavor-sar/ For reference.]

== External Link to American Rifleman ==

I added this external link
* [http://www.americanrifleman.org/article.php?id=13077&amp;cat=3&amp;sub=6 DECIDEDLY DIFFERENT: THE IWI TAVOR], [[American Rifleman]], [[National Rifle Association]], USA
but was reverted with vague reference to [[WP:EL]]. What is wrong with this link? It is informative and contain technical information about the Tavor, including shooting range tests. '''[[User:MathKnight|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;ath&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;K&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;night&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  21:39, 7 January 2014 (UTC)
: Since there was no explanation given what is wrong with this link, I re-add it to the page. '''[[User:MathKnight|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;ath&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;K&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;night&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  20:10, 17 January 2014 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[IMI Tavor TAR-21]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=686422080 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20110717154347/http://unffmm.com/Galerias_AR/Galerias/v/GN/album_011/album/ to http://unffmm.com/Galerias_AR/Galerias/v/GN/album_011/album/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 01:28, 19 October 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qzyq08z35dk4hyev8fr3004ps1ms4ud</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
