<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Remembrance poppy</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>31643269</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747655263</id>
      <parentid>747522790</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T16:15:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Valentina Cardoso</username>
        <id>27351447</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Poppy fascism */ Not forum</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11632">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Death|class=c|importance=mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=C| B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; = n
| B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; = y
| B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; = y
| B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; = y
| B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; = y|Memorials=Yes|British=y|Canadian=y|ANZSP=y|US=y|WWI=Yes|WWII=Yes |Culture-traditions-and-heraldry-task-force=yes }}
{{WikiProject Commonwealth}}
{{WikiProject Canada|class=C |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Holidays|class=C |importance=}}
{{WikiProject Plants|class=C|importance=Low}}
}}

== Wearing a white poppy is also an act of &quot;remembrance&quot; ==

Notice the difference between these two words: 
# &quot;remembrance&quot; - A word with a lower case &quot;r,&quot; and is defined as &quot;the act of remembering&quot; at [http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/remembrance this Wiktionary link]
# &quot;Remembrance&quot; - A word with an upper case &quot;R,&quot; and is used in the name of the official holiday, [[Remembrance Day]].

Wearing a [[white poppy]] is also an act of &quot;remembrance&quot; (with lower case &quot;r&quot;).   Therefore the the white poppy should be mentioned in the lead section -- even if the only purpose of that mention is purely for clarification purposes only.

Clarification is an important function of Wikipedia: See [[Wikipedia:Please_clarify|this Wikipedia information page]]. Because of Wikipedia's clarifying function, the supporting sources that are required on this question need only to establish a need for clarification (to fulfill the clarifying function of Wikipedia) -- they do not need to establish the white poppy as a &quot;Remembrance poppy&quot; (with upper case &quot;R&quot;).

The above discussion raises the following question:

Does society use the upper case &quot;R&quot; or lower case &quot;r&quot; when the word &quot;remembrance poppy&quot; is used?

[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/6133312.stm this source] uses the lower case &quot;r.&quot;

If there are no sources which use the upper case &quot;r,&quot; then the title of this article is technically &quot;remembrance poppy.&quot; and not &quot;Remembrance poppy.&quot;  Even though [[Wikipedia:Article_titles]] stipulates that the first letter of article names should be capitalized, there should be a clarifying sentence in the lead section which displays the word as it is used in society: ie. with a lower case &quot;r.&quot; (Capitalization is important in the article title. Example [[WASP]] vs [[Wasp]]) 

Any thoughts?

Sincerely, [[User:Boyd Reimer|Boyd Reimer]] ([[User talk:Boyd Reimer|talk]]) 12:02, 29 May 2011 (UTC)

== Rosemary instead of poppies in Australia ==

Could some mention be made that in Australia a sprig of rosemary was traditionally worn, even on Remembrance day, and that the wearing of poppies is more recent. The custom dates to Gallipoli - where rosemary grows wild and the smell of that plant would cause anyone who was there to remember.

See:
http://www.warmemorialsnsw.asn.au/traditions/rosemary.cfm
http://www.anzacday.org.au/education/tff/rosemary.html  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/202.129.81.174|202.129.81.174]] ([[User talk:202.129.81.174|talk]]) 00:56, 4 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
== Flanders as a geographical region ==
&quot;ts opening lines refer to the many poppies that were the first flowers to grow in the churned-up earth of soldiers' graves in Flanders, a region of Europe that overlies parts of Belgium, France, and the Netherlands.[1]&quot;

This line refers to Flanders as a geographical region, I doubt that its used in that context these days. Even then, the Flanders used in the poem refers to the region in Belgium, and perhaps hints at a region in France aswell, but since the Netherlands did not participate in WWI I think the poem doesn't refer to any region of the Netherlands. The reference doesn't say anything about what region is ment in the poem, but I doubt the Netherlands were ment... &lt;b&gt;[[User:Sitethief|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Site&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;thief&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;b&gt;~[[User_talk:Sitethief|&lt;sub&gt;talk to me&lt;/sub&gt;]]~&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 09:04, 9 November 2011 (UTC)

== Section arrangements ==

I have placed the sections in the least contentious arrangement possible. 
# All Commonwealth nations placed under a single heading, as it appears other editors do not recognize the validity of the ==== sub-section, though I admit, there is only a slight size difference between the === and the ====. 
# All other countries separated out, as it is hardly balanced to make a group called &quot;Outside the Commonwealth&quot;, as if that makes them lesser. 
# While Commonwealth countries might use the poppy more than other countries, they did not start there, therefore the most balanced way is, alphabetical order. When the &quot;Commonwealth&quot; heading is used, it gets to be first anyway. 
I would be pleased to hear other opinions on the matter. [[User:Boneyard90|Boneyard90]] ([[User talk:Boneyard90|talk]]) 19:03, 13 November 2011 (UTC)

==Text from [[Corn poppy]] article==
The following text from the above article, which properly belongs in this one, was removed and replaced with a summary. Much of the content is already in this article, but there is some that may need to be readded here. 
[[Image:Field poppy (Papaver rhoeas) in meadow.jpg|thumb|left|''Papaver rhoeas'']]
: ...'' In Flanders Fields '' ... It was written by [[Lieutenant Colonel|Lt. Col.]] John McCrae, a doctor serving in the Royal Canadian Army Medical Corps, and appeared for the first time in ''Punch'' magazine on December 8, 1915. McCrae wrote the poem on May 3, 1915, after witnessing the death of his friend, Lt. Alexis Helmer. The opening line of the poem vividly depicts corn poppies blowing in the wind amongst the many crosses that mark the resting places of fallen soldiers. Similarly, the poppy is a symbol of the blood of Polish soldiers killed in the [[Battle of Monte Cassino]] in the [[Polish language|Polish]] [[war song]] &quot;''[[Czerwone maki na Monte Cassino]]''&quot; (&quot;Red Poppies on Monte Cassino&quot;).

: The corn poppy has become a [[cultural icon]] to military [[veteran]]s, especially veterans of World War I, and has become associated with wartime remembrance, especially during [[Remembrance Day]] or [[Anzac Day]] in [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth countries]].  In [[Canada]], where the corn poppy is largely associated with Remembrance Day, the [[Royal Canadian Mint]] in 2004 released into circulation a [[Quarter (Canadian coin)|quarter]] with a [[Commemorative coin|commemorative reverse]] featuring a corn poppy coloured red.

: This poppy is a common [[weed]] in [[Europe]] and is found in many locations, including [[Flanders Fields]]. 

: Inspired by McCrae's poem, in 1915 US professor [[Moina Michael]] published a poem of her own called &quot;[[We Shall Keep the Faith]]&quot;. In tribute to the opening lines of McCrae's poem&amp;mdash;&quot;In Flanders fields the poppies blow / Between the crosses row on row,&quot;&amp;mdash;Michael vowed to always wear a red poppy as a symbol of remembrance for those who served in the war.&lt;ref name=BBC&gt;{{cite news | author = | title =Where did the idea to sell poppies come from?  | publisher =BBC News | date =November 10, 2006 | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/6133312.stm  | accessdate=2009-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: Artificial poppies are used for remembrance, because they do not flower naturally in November in Europe, and because individual flowers are short-lived.  In many [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries, [[paper]] or [[plastic]] corn poppy flowers are worn to commemorate the sacrifice of veterans and civilians in World War I and other wars, during the weeks preceding [[Remembrance Day]] on November 11. In the United States, it is common practice to wear &quot;Buddy Poppies&quot; (artificial, paper or plastic versions distributed by the Veterans of Foreign War) during the weeks preceding [[Memorial Day]], the last Monday in May to commemorate the sacrifice of veterans in the various wars;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vfw.org/index.cfm?fa=cmty.levelc&amp;cid=127 Veterans of Foreign Wars (VFW)]&lt;/ref&gt; whereas Veterans Day on November 11 is used to honor &quot;living&quot; veterans.

: In Canada, poppies are distributed by the [[Royal Canadian Legion]] and the [[Anavets]] organization each fall prior to Remembrance Day. The design of the Canadian poppy consists of petals made of red plastic with a felt lining and black centre held on by a pin. In 1980, the Royal Canadian Legion formed a committee to decide the future of the poppy and it was decided that the centre should be changed to green to represent the green fields of France. In 2002, the poppy centres were switched back to the traditional black.  Those who were unaware or had forgotten that black centres had been used in the design of the poppy from its introduction in 1921 until 1980 found the change somewhat controversial.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}

: In New Zealand and Australia, plastic poppies are widely distributed by the Returned Services Association leading up to [[ANZAC Day|ANZAC]] day (April 25).

: The corn poppy has been adopted as a symbol by [[The Royal British Legion]] in their [[Poppy Appeal]].
[[User:Imc|Imc]] ([[User talk:Imc|talk]]) 17:21, 3 December 2011 (UTC)

== The Linford House Poppy Burning ==

Should be added among the others.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Beingsshepherd|Beingsshepherd]] ([[User talk:Beingsshepherd|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Beingsshepherd|contribs]]) 21:46, 2 February 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Canadian Poppy trademark ==

The poppy design is Canadian Trademark TMA586995  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/213.120.141.254|213.120.141.254]] ([[User talk:213.120.141.254|talk]]) 16:16, 1 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== For remembrance to fashion statement ==
Kleshna is one of two businesses selling its own poppies - ''but only gives 10% of its sales to charity.'' Kleshna sells crystal-clad poppy jewellery which has been worn by celebrities on television. So the poppy is ''not'' in danger of being used as a Fashion Appendage or Marketing Tool?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.20.248.99|92.20.248.99]] ([[User talk:92.20.248.99|talk]]) 10:07, 4 November 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Real or artificial? ==

The article says that the Remembrance poppy is based on a real flower. However, '''every single picture''' on the article shows artificial flowers. As entirely non-British, I have to ask: Is the Remembrance poppy supposed to be a real flower or an artificial one? [[User:JIP|&lt;font color=&quot;#CC0000&quot;&gt;J&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00CC00&quot;&gt;I&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CC&quot;&gt;P&lt;/font&gt;]] &amp;#124; [[User talk:JIP|Talk]] 20:07, 7 April 2016 (UTC)

: I'm not sure about other countries, but here in Canada, most people wear the artifical poppy. There are practical reasons for this, they are less costly and more damage resitant than real poppies; plus the fact that real flowers don't do well in November in Canada. However as far as I know there is no objection to anyone wearing a real poppy if you're willing to take the exta cost and care reqired. [[User:Mediatech492|Mediatech492]] ([[User talk:Mediatech492|talk]]) 20:59, 30 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>iyq0vs961ytc3lo3omb2e7l7w9gs87z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
