<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Osan Air Base</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3999590</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730098926</id>
      <parentid>624282530</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-16T17:40:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10347">{{WPMILHIST|class=C|B1=n|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Aviation=yes|Korean=yes|US=yes}}
{{WikiProject Korea|class=Start}}

== stupid question ==

does anyone know if the gas station at osan, yongsan, or camp humphreys sells Premium Fuel (93 Octane)?

i know it sounds like a dumb questions, but i would like to know before i were to take my car over there.

:Yeah, they have it.

:At Yongsan's AAFES gas station, regular unleaded is 92 octane and premium unleaded is 98 octane.  [[User:Americaninseoul|Americaninseoul]] 07:33, 11 April 2007 (UTC)AmericanInSeoul

==WPMILHIST Assessment==
A nice, lengthy article, and I am happy to see pictures. But there is far too much emphasis on the type of information one would use when visiting or living at Osan, not the kind of information a researcher is looking for. Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a travel guide. [[User:LordAmeth|LordAmeth]] 15:11, 3 January 2007 (UTC)
:LordAmeth - You are correct, but notice that this article is under the Military WikiProject. Most who are interested in this Air Base are looking for exactly this type of information, which often not provided by a servicemember's losing base as the move to Osan AB. Hopefully, others will add more information that you are looking for. [[User:T_geier|Tom Geier]] 23:16, 18 July 2007 (UTC)

Actually, not to contradict anything you say.
But, the Air Force does a nice job of introducing personel to their next duty assignment.
I was &quot;in&quot; more than thirty (30) years ago, and when I rotated from Osan to Hickam, for instance, I was given a brochure with complete information about base facilities, and the local area in general.
By the way.....Osan is full of history from the Korean War, and the cold war as well. I could add factual information if Wikipedia, or the author would allow me to do so. I served there from April of 77 to April of 78.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/167.206.169.66|167.206.169.66]] ([[User talk:167.206.169.66|talk]]) 21:57, 17 March 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Freedom bird flights==
Do they still fly commercial flights to/from the states into Osan, or is this all handled out of Incheon now?  When I was there in the mid-1990s we flew Delta MD-11 from PDX direct to Kimpo, but leaving I was booked on a World MD-11 out of Osan to LAX via Yokota.  The kind of contract flights going in and out of Osan might be worth mentioning in the article.  -[[User:Rolypolyman|Rolypolyman]] ([[User talk:Rolypolyman|talk]]) 20:45, 17 February 2009 (UTC)

It's funny you should mention the &quot;freedom birds.&quot;
I flew all the way from Travis AFB, Ca. to Osan in a &quot;stretch&quot; DC-9 operated by &quot;World Airways.&quot; We stopped in McCord Washington, Anchorage Alaska, and Yakota, Japan. They called it a &quot;military contract&quot; flight because it was operated by a civilian airline, even though it only carried military personel, and a class A uniform was required for all passengers.
The military also ran &quot;contract&quot; flights outbound from Osan back to &quot;the world&quot; as well.
But, I was lucky enough to score a &quot;catagory Y&quot; flight out of Kimpo Airport on the way home when my tour at Osan was over. I took a Korean Airlines 747 to SeaTac airport in Washington State, and flew home to NY via Northwest Orient.
The same circumstances were prevalent when I &quot;rotated&quot; to Hickam Air Force base. I flew on my own to SF, took the bus from the airport to Travis AFB, and was flown (non-stop) via &quot;Trans-American&quot; airlines from Travis to Honolulu International Airport.
Same type of plane (&quot;stretch-nine&quot; or &quot;cattle car&quot; as it was called back then) and everyione on board had to wear a uniform.
Oddly enough, the same thing happened on my way home from Hickam, as did when I left Osan. They flew me in a Pan Am civilian flight from HIA to LAX, and from there I was on my own (with their travel money, of course) to make my way back to NY. It all worked out pretty good, as I recall. The travel pay was enough for a 1st class ticket on a &quot;red-eye&quot; back home. Not a bad way to end a four year hitch!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/167.206.169.66|167.206.169.66]] ([[User talk:167.206.169.66|talk]]) 19:05, 17 March 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Inaccurate Information==
It mentions in the article that the 25th FS and their A-10 aircraft moved to Osan in October 1993. That is incorrect. The 19th Tactical Air Support Squadron (TASS) and their fifteen A-10 aircraft relocated from Suwon AB, South Korea to Osan AB in September 1990. They flew as the 19th TASS until the unit was redesignated the 25th FS in 1993. At some point over the intervening years, they've regained several aircraft. Note: I was with the A-10s in Suwon and Osan form 1988 until 1992 and was in the 19th TASS unit that relocated from Suwon to Osan in 1990. I left Osan in January 1992.[[User:OldMustang|OldMustang]] ([[User talk:OldMustang|talk]]) 20:40, 13 April 2009 (UTC)

As I recall, the 19th TASS had OV-10's back in '77'. The A-10's and the F-15's first came to Osan from the Paris Air Show (where one of them crashed, by the way) in the spring of that year. They were on static display for two or three days. I got a 30mm inert shell with an A-10 stamp on it from one of the crew, and it was taken away from me when I rotated back to the states the following year. I'm sure it's sitting on someone's mantle or in someone's trophy case. The F-4's were still the mainstay of the Air Forces fighter inventory until well after I left Osan in April of '78.'  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/167.206.169.94|167.206.169.94]] ([[User talk:167.206.169.94|talk]]) 12:32, 5 September 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Incentives for an Osan AFB assignment? ==

Wjile reading the article, I got the feeling that there is a great emphasis on incentives for an assignment to this airbase. Why is there such a need? Some more explanation to this point would ne nice. Regards, [[User:Grand-Duc|Grand-Duc]] ([[User talk:Grand-Duc|talk]]) 02:19, 13 August 2011 (UTC)

I can't speak as to what conditions are like over there, now. But, back in 1977 South Korea was the &quot;armpit&quot; of PACAF. The streets off base smelled of human manure because they had open sewage ditches alongside the sidewalk curbs, the nighclubs were filled with rot-gut Korean liquor, and &quot;Yobos&quot; (another word for hookers). V.D. was rampant amoung young troops who sought the overnight company of the nightclub girls. (G.I.s were not allowed, by Korean custom, to be in the company of &quot;good&quot; girls, or they would be labled as prostitutes.) The one (1) year tour over there was what they used to call &quot;isolated&quot; inasmuch as nobody could bring their wives and kids with them under any circumstances. There was no &quot;base of preference&quot; when you left, either. Most of the guys I was stationd with ended up at nothern tier SAC bases when they rotated back to the U.S. SAC was lousy duty for SP's back in the late 70's. Cigarettes, liquor, and foodstuffs were rationed at all the BX's in the ROK. You were issued an 8th Army ration card, and they ran it off everytime you made any type of consumable purchase. It took almost two full weeks to get mail from home through the APO, to Osan. It cost a good $30.00 or so to make a short phone call home (there were no cell phones back then), and there was only one phone on base, at the visiting airman's quarters, that you could use for overseas calls. (Unless you made a &quot;MARS&quot; call, which was limited to three minutes in length.) The conditions on base were okay. Good facilities such as two (2) NCO clubs, a golf course, bowling alley, recreation center, gymn, and pool. But, there wasn't much off-base except for the bars and the hookers. It was a 50-60 minute cab ride if you wanted to go to Seoul, and once you got there, a days worth of sightseeing would last you an entire year. Oh, and the weather....hotter than hell in the summer, and FREEZING cold in the winter. I mean wind chills to sub zero temps that would halt all outside traffic on the base. Guys would start a countdown calendar the very day they arrived in country. Some liked it and &quot;extended&quot; their tours. Most wanted to get the hell out of there and go back to &quot;the world&quot; (The U.S.) ASAP! I would imagine, after the word got out years ago, that it really sucked over there, people stopped wanting to go, and stopped volunteering. Like I said, some guys actually liked it and stayed. But, most wanted to go somewhere else. I'll make a disclaimer here by saying that I hope I have not offended anyone. But, what I'm saying here is all true.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/167.206.169.66|167.206.169.66]] ([[User talk:167.206.169.66|talk]]) 19:23, 6 December 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Osan Air Base]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=730098915 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090130025918/http://home.att.net/~jbaugher/usafserials.html to http://home.att.net/~jbaugher/usafserials.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:40, 16 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7ahl93y6whia3ji24227o0d0l1aam4w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
