<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:CAC CA-15</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5489473</id>
    <revision>
      <id>578796845</id>
      <parentid>554691204</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-10-26T08:18:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Petebutt</username>
        <id>3299145</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8742">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=C|b1=n|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|importance=Mid |Aviation-task-force=yes |Australian-task-force=yes |WWII-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=C
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; =n
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; =y
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; =y
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; =y
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; =y
|Aircraft-project=yes}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=C|importance=low}}
}}

==Photo needed==

This article really needs a photo. Does anyone know of a photo not covered by copyright? The AWM's excellent database doesn't seem to have any photos of the CA-15. --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] 07:24, 9 June 2006 (UTC)
:Hi Nick, I have searched quite a bit myself and had exactly the same experience with the AWM. The RAAF Museum website has a small pic, which looks like it's been scanned from a book or display. If the museum is a government body we could probably get away with using it, but there is no source given. [[User:Grant65|Grant65]] | [[User talk:Grant65|Talk]] 11:28, 9 June 2006 (UTC)
Hi Nick, I'm new to this so apologise in advance if I get something wrong.I have a picture of what could be the CAC 15, I cannot remember where on the web I found it and do not know if it has a copyright on it.  The photo was only identified as &quot;Mystery 0137&quot;  Let me know if you want it, I have put this page on &quot;watch&quot; --[[User:CliffP|CliffP]] 15:02, 22 July 2006 (UTC)

==Image==
The top image looks like a wildcat, and the bottom image looks like a kittyhawk. Have they been verified?--08:49, 24 July 2006 (UTC)

== Specifications ==

The specifications were coming back, it was just taking me a minute to get them into the new template. - [[User:Aerobird|Aerobird]] 01:18, 9 January 2007 (UTC)
:OK sorry. [[User:Grant65|Grant65]] | [[User talk:Grant65|Talk]] 04:12, 9 January 2007 (UTC)
::No prob. - [[User:Aerobird|Aerobird]] 14:23, 9 January 2007 (UTC)
:::I changed the listing of the guns as it seemed very unlikely they would put what was essentially a Russian/Japanese caliber in a prototype. I don't know what they actually were, if anyone does please change it.[[User:Ca 16|Ca 16]] ([[User talk:Ca 16|talk]]) 10:55, 22 September 2009 (UTC)

== First flight ==
4 and 6 March 1946 are both given as date of first flight. Which is correct? [[User:Drutt|Drutt]] ([[User talk:Drutt|talk]]) 09:35, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
The engine which was ultimately specified was in fact the as yet unbuilt RR Griffon 120 (it was never built in any case). The airframe was fitted with a Griffon 61 as an interim fit only.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Wombat40|Wombat40]] ([[User talk:Wombat40|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Wombat40|contribs]]) 00:02, 3 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

&quot;Commonwealth CA-15: The 'Kangaroo' Fighter&quot;  David Donald, WINGS OF FAME, Volume 4 (1996)  gives the date as 4 March 1946, flown by Jim Schofield (see &quot;www.airwaysmuseum.com/Jim Schofield biog.htm&quot;). Two engines supplied were Griffin 61's.
[[User:Ketabatic|Ketabatic]] ([[User talk:Ketabatic|talk]]) 13:09, 2 June 2009 (UTC)

There's considerable debate over the first flight. I knew Jim Schofield in the 70s, as he was my father's boss. He first flew CA-15 and also the CAC P-51.  He left the RAAF in 1945, and worked for CAC when he test flew the CA-15 in MArch 1946. I'm fairly sure he also broke the 500mph barrier. Lee Archer did the first wheels-up landing in a CA-15, and the project was then scrapped, as CAC did not have the money to fix the machine. Both Mk61s were returned to the RAF. Jim later went on to restore VH-USU, at Eagle Farm, before retiring in 1985. He died in 2005, aged 85.[[Special:Contributions/220.244.88.137|220.244.88.137]] ([[User talk:220.244.88.137|talk]]) 09:43, 3 November 2012 (UTC)

== Failed verification tag ==
The Crick webpage does not say that the CA-15 was ''not'' based directly on the P-51 Mustang. It does not say that later stages of development showed it a viable replacement for the P-51. It does not say &quot;shallow dive&quot;, it says 4000-foot dive. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 17:31, 13 February 2011 (UTC)
:&quot;NOTE: This is not true. The fuselage and all flying surfaces are nearly identical in shape to the P-51 Mustang. Comparison of multi-view drawings show this to be true. (In addition, this &quot;fact&quot; uses this very page as it's citation, not an outside source.)&quot; was the section in question, but the caption note: &quot;(Photographed from the rear turret of an [[Avro Lincoln]] bomber.)&quot; was also removed. The following response perhaps clears up the issues. 
&lt;nowiki&gt;== Edit of CA-15 article 13 Feb 2011 (you can't introduce personal opinion) ==&lt;/nowiki&gt;
Hi Bzuk,
I am relatively new to Wikipedia, but I appreciate that the rigour applied to the monitoring of edits is what makes Wikipedia such a useful reference.
I note that you recently removed the statement &quot;(Photographed from the rear turret of an Avro Lincoln bomber.)&quot; from the description of a photograph I contributed to the CA-15 article (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CAC_CA-15), with the comment (you can't introduce personal opinion).
However, it was not my own opinion that the photograph was taken from a Lincoln, it was the opinion of the pilot (my dad). The difficulty I have now is proving it.

If you examine the roundels on the wings of the CA-15 in the photograph I contributed, you will see that the red dot at the centre exists. This dates the photograph to the second series of CA-15 tests (May 1948 - March 1950), carried out by RAAF ARDU (Aircraft Research and Development Unit). There is a brief ARDU history at http://www.airforce.gov.au/raafmuseum/research/units/ardu.htm, which confirms that ARDU was flying both the CA-15, and at least one Lincoln bomber.

My dad's log book has him flying the CA-15 on the 18th, 20th, 21st, 24th and 25th of May 1948. The 25th was the day of the 'gentle' dive over Melbourne at 502.2 mph. It also has him piloting the ARDU Lincoln A73-20 on May 20th and May 26th 1948. It seems extremely like that the photograph was taken from the Lincoln A73-20, but does this constitute sufficient proof?

What do you think?

Regards, John Archer.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:JohnnyOneSpeed|JohnnyOneSpeed]] ([[User talk:JohnnyOneSpeed|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/JohnnyOneSpeed|contribs]]) 12:42, 4 June 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::I have restored the citation to the original submission by [[User:JohnnyOneSpeed|JohnnyOneSpeed]]. FWiW [[User:Bzuk|Bzuk]] ([[User talk:Bzuk|talk]]) 13:42, 4 June 2011 (UTC).
:::The photo is stated to be from the rear turret of a Lincoln in the ''Wings of Fame'' article.[[User:Nigel Ish|Nigel Ish]] ([[User talk:Nigel Ish|talk]]) 15:12, 4 June 2011 (UTC)
::::The entry on commons says it was taken by JohnnyOneSpeed in which case I am confused by the statement &quot;extremely likely&quot; as odds are you would know exactly when you took it? Perhaps the commons category ''Category:P-51 Mustang in Australian service'' needs to be changed as well. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 15:26, 4 June 2011 (UTC)
:::::The photo is credited in the ''Wings of Fame'' to Commonwealth Aircraft Corporation.[[User:Nigel Ish|Nigel Ish]] ([[User talk:Nigel Ish|talk]]) 15:52, 4 June 2011 (UTC)
::::::The licencing of the photo, as PD-Australia is probably OK- however, at it was taken prior to 1955.[[User:Nigel Ish|Nigel Ish]] ([[User talk:Nigel Ish|talk]]) 15:55, 4 June 2011 (UTC)
:::::::Dont have a problem with the PD but I think the image should be correctly credited on commons to CAC. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 15:57, 4 June 2011 (UTC)

==3 View==
Any reason we are not using the 3 view that the italian wikipedia entry uses?
http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:CAC_CA-15_vs_CA-18_(P-51D)_(Greg_Goebel).png
[[User:Yakumo|Yakumo]] ([[User talk:Yakumo|talk]]) 17:35, 27 June 2011 (UTC)

:It shows a comparison with the P-51 which gives the impression of some sort of relationship, which it hasnt. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 18:08, 27 June 2011 (UTC)

::Is there a 3view available without the comparison then? Plus the article clearly states that it was not based on the p51 design. I just like 3views and saw one on the italian article. If one does not exist, one does not exist. cheers mate[[User:Yakumo|Yakumo]] ([[User talk:Yakumo|talk]]) 14:02, 28 June 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8i1dwuv1bdzvrejm29cqcz3rq6m07yt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
