<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Pole weapon</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7252620</id>
    <revision>
      <id>727131631</id>
      <parentid>727130148</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-26T22:16:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Shinobody</username>
        <id>14771695</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16364">{{WikiProject Military history
|class = Start
|B-Class-1=no
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|Weaponry-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Martial arts|class=Start}}

==Linstock==
While the linstock could be used as a weapon, it's primarily a long-match holder for cannons. Thus, I'm cutting the following:
Linstock
A Linstock is a polearm similar to both a Halberd and a Pike (or Spear.) The primary difference is that a Linstock lacks the blade that a halberd has, and has replaced the blade with a (usually ornamental) cats holder for slow matches. The spear point would be used to defend artillery, and the slow-match would be used to fire the cannon.

==&quot;Evolved from&quot;==
Please stop using this phrase. Nevermind that it's mis-using a precise technical term from biology to mean 'change over time', but any 'evolutionary' linkages between weapons is a supposition at best, especially when the period of 'evolution' jumps centuries and cultures without the presence of intermediary forms. I strongly suggest using 'similar to' as an alternate phrasing.   &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Theblindsage|contribs]]) 02:00, 19 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Pole Weapon List ==
# Trident - Three pronged spear. 
# Military Fork - Military version of a pitch fork. Two tines, straightened.
# Fauchard/War-Scythe: Scythe blade on a pole, perpendicular to the pole. Inner edge for slashing.
# Glaive: 18&quot; blade on 6-7 pole. (AKA Naginata) Used for slashing. 
# Guisarme: Pruning hook on a pole. Useful for dismounting horsemen. 
# Voulge: Meat cleaver on a pole. Used for chopping. Later developing a stabbing point. 
# Bardiche: Axe-like voulge. Shorter, with blade extending beyond 2' haft. 
# Lochaber Axe: Midway between Voulge and Bardiche, included a hook on far side for scaling walls.
# Ranseur - Spear head with protrusions for blocking/trapping. Also used for dismounting.
# Ox-Tounge - Wide and heavy spear head for slashing with.
# Spetum - Spear head with forward slanted 'leaves' on the side for slashing. 
# Partisan - Ceremonial. Spetum + Ranseur.

[[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] 01:37, 21 February 2007 (UTC)
: We appear to have forgotten that old English favourite the bill ... unless we're considering it a kind of guisarme, which would be rather backwards. [[Special:Contributions/62.196.17.197|62.196.17.197]] ([[User talk:62.196.17.197|talk]]) 14:28, 12 June 2013 (UTC)

==missing weapon==
There is a weapon similar to the Naginata but with blades on both ends, curved in opposite directions. anyone nkow what it is called?

I formatted the above edit better..

== Pole Arm Links ==

As I'm researching this, thought it might be polite to include some sources.
http://www.retromud.org/weapons/polearms.html (Frighteningly complete)
http://www.shoshone.k12.id.us/medieval/handweap.htm
http://www.salvatorfabris.com/SectionPolearms.shtml
http://hea-www.harvard.edu/~fine/Fun/polearms.html
http://www.knives.com/polearm.html
http://www.retromud.org/weapons/
http://therionarms.com/armor/polearm10.jpg
http://therionarms.com/old_armor_page.shtml
http://www.myarmoury.com/talk/viewtopic.php?t=1403&amp;start=20
http://www.preferredarms.com/Pole%20Arms.htm
http://www.aurorahistoryboutique.com/ahb_poleArms.htm

Perhaps this article ought be organized into &quot;European Pole-arms&quot; and &quot;Asian Pole-Arms&quot;. Traditional kung fu has a baffling variety of its own. 
http://www.wahlum.com/weapons.htm
Japan has not only the naginata, but also the so-called 'monks's spade', and doubtless other undiscovered varieties.

[[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]]) 09:31, 18 November 2007 (UTC)

== More pole arm links. ==

Japanese pole-arms appear limited to the spear (Yari), and the Naginata. China seems to have a much richer tradition. Aside from the excessive variety of kung-fu weapons, the main pole-arm seems to be the pu-dao, or horsecutter, and closely resembles a falcion blade mounted on a pole about the same length of that of the poll-ax. 

----
Rather too many types of pole-arms. 
http://medieval.ucdavis.edu/20C/Weapons.html

----

== Structure and Content ==

We are in danger here of suffering from the curse of bad articles - lack of clear purpose and direction, which leads to lack of clarity of content.  I think we would all agree that this entry is likely to be thrown up by general searches e.g. by internet users not sure what they are looking for.  How does this affect content and structure?  At present, the weapons lists seem quite random.  It mixes weapons from west and east and includes weapons from ancient times, the middle ages and later.  It also does not contain anything on important weapons such as the poleaxe or bill.

Rather launch into a major edit, I want to float this first.  I suggest we attack this from several directions.
* A clear format, divided either chronologically or (simplest) dividing Western and Oriental as has already been suggested.
* Attempt to agree key weapons and add a short entry on each, with links section expanded to cover a wider range of less significant types
* Improve the referencing - there are a load of fantasy weapon lists out there, this one should be factually &amp; historically based[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 13:52, 21 June 2009 (UTC)

OK, in the absence of cries of &quot;Don't do it&quot; I've restructured the page.  I intend to come back with a para on the bill and one on the poleaxe.  I don't have the specialist interest in the Ancient and Oriental sections, but there is more could be done there (Chinese polearms anyone?).  We might need a Rest of the World category (e.g. polynesian warclubs) but we can cross that bridge when we come to it.[[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 11:23, 27 June 2009 (UTC)

Wonder if we might not be better off just organizing this as a list, with links to the resultant articles? I might leave an image for easy and rapid comparison. 
[[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]]) 20:46, 7 June 2016 (UTC)

==Pole-arm&lt;&gt;Spear==
Just to cut the article size down, I'm eliminating spears as pole-weapons.  A pole-arm is different than a [spear] in that the 'edge' is perpendicular to the pole, rather than parallel. Some pole-arms include a spear. Also cutting mauls and mallets. While they are 'haft' weapons, they aren't really 'staff' weapons. To make an (arbitrary) distinction, I'll say something needs to be longer than 5' to count as a pole-arm. (So the Dane-Axe can stay.)
[[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]]) 02:26, 19 March 2012 (UTC)

:While the removal of spears/pikes  may be a good idea (leaving you with some issues about spear derivatives but not insurmountable) where does the idea come from that a pole-arm is defined as something with an edge perpendicular to the pole come from?  Also that there is a differential between edged and percussive polearms? If your concern is that the article is too long, I would suggest the answer is probably to split European from Oriental weapons.  If you take spears out, there is little in the Ancient category worth keeping, so that could trim down too. [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 09:05, 19 March 2012 (UTC)

::The list of pole-arms in the article seemed like such a mixed bag, some of which have very little similarity in form or function (Maul, Sarissa, etc). In general, I was bothered by the confusion of two-handed hafted weapons with pole-arms. Was trying to find some sort of categorical similarity--thus the 'parallel' as a working categorization. There are some medieval pole-arms (Godendag, staff flail from peasant rebellions, but most of the proliferation of pole-arms come out of the Renaissance, within a relatively short period of time. Most are anti-cavalry weapons for dismounting riders, (thus the hook/beak), with armor penetration attachments (hammer/spike). There are also many designed for the 'push of pike' (as depicted in the Hans Holbein 'bad war' image--to catch, tangle, and lift other pikes, and maybe cause some damage. Are spears pole-arms? I would so no. Spears/pikes/lances are primarily thrusting weapons. The more weight you add to the head of a thrusting weapon, the more difficult it is to handle. Barring lugs/wings/tsuba, I'm unaware of any that violate this. [[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]]) 08:28, 22 March 2012 (UTC)

::Timing--Almost all of it post 1500. Wait--greater inspection of the fechtbooks shows some 1400 stuff. Fiore dei Liberi includes pole-axe techniques, as does Le jeu de la hache (&quot;play of the axe&quot;). Nürnberger Handschrift GNM 3227a (1389) doesn't mention it. Fiore dei Liberi is supposed to have some 'Exotic poleaxes (f 35r)' in its The Pisani-Dossi MS (Flos Duellatorum) variant, but I can't find any images from it beyond this one: http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Flos_Pisani_36A_detail.jpg http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Bundesschwur_Zuerich.jpg shows some, but is probably from the late 1400s. As far as I can tell, the only 'pole arm' in Europe prior to 1400: A 'pole axe' with either axe head or hammer head. Of course, the Dane axe has to have existed--think either the Saga's or the Anglo-Saxon chronicle attests to that.[[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]]) 08:28, 22 March 2012 (UTC) 

::Not sure what you mean asking about the difference between edged and percussion weapons. The 'melange' nature of many of the pole-arm heads makes that seem like a strange method of distinction. My edits contain only two reference to edges... The ancient category could almost certainly go. A falx is hardly a pole-arm, and the Trajan's column pic of the Rhompeia shows something more like a Nagimaki. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:AdamclisiMetope14.jpg. Kontos is a lance/pike. [[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]]) 08:28, 22 March 2012 (UTC)

:::While I'm still not sure I agree with defining polearms as edged weapons, I've tidied up a bit to ensure that we weren't losing any unique content.  The maul subsection had already been copied across to [[Warhammer]], winged spears have coverage under spear.  You didn't explain why you'd deleted scottish polearms - most fit your blade definition - I've shifted that content to a separate page [[Scottish polearms]]. [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 18:09, 19 April 2012 (UTC)

::::In terms of timing, IIRC the English were using the bill/longbow combination during the hundred years war ... whether from the beginning or not I have no idea.  If so, that would place it before 1400, if not, still before 1500. [[Special:Contributions/62.196.17.197|62.196.17.197]] ([[User talk:62.196.17.197|talk]]) 14:34, 12 June 2013 (UTC)

==Handy guide to knowing your pole-arm!==
REALLY need a public domain version of this:
http://surbrook.devermore.net/herosource/fantasy_hero/armor/polearms2.jpg
[[User:Theblindsage|Theblindsage]] ([[User talk:Theblindsage|talk]]) 09:08, 22 March 2012 (UTC)

Pole-arms is a kind of a difficult category, because many pole-arms are just 'long' versions of regular weapons.

==Pike==

&lt;blockquote&gt;A '''pike''' is a [[pole weapon]], a very long thrusting [[spear]] formerly used extensively by [[infantry]]. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

Currently, this is the opening sentence of the Wikipedia article for the [[pike]]. So, follow the internal hyperlink to [[pole weapon]] and what does the reader discover? That the [[pike]] appears nowhere in the article.

This happens too often in Wikipedia. Editors have to try somehow to ensure at least the semblance of consistency between information provided in articles. This is of course a major problem for Wikipedia that is highlighted by this example. No editor-in-chief to ensure that contradictions between articles are removed, or resolved, or at least explained. This example also demonstrates the lack of precision and rigour that so often accompanies articles on military history cobbled together by enthusiastic amateurs. Somehow, Wikipedia editors have got to try harder. Curb your enthusiasm. Think about what you write. In the end, if a Wikipedia article is to be encyclopaedic rather than an extension of someone's [[blog]], we will all benefit from more thought, more rigour and less waffle.[[Special:Contributions/124.186.130.7|124.186.130.7]] ([[User talk:124.186.130.7|talk]]) 06:15, 17 March 2013 (UTC)

:: The pike appears nowhere in the article because spears (of which pikes are but a lengthened version) type weapons are excluded from the definition in the lead paragraph.  Editors perhaps should read at least the lead para before placing comments on the talk page of articles. However, if the author of the above wishes to return and discuss whether the definition here should be expanded to include spear-type weapons (which is certainly an arguable point), please do. [[User:Monstrelet|Monstrelet]] ([[User talk:Monstrelet|talk]]) 09:33, 17 March 2013 (UTC)

== Why does &quot;maul&quot; redirect here? ==
For some reason &quot;maul&quot; redirects here, despite being roughly as much of a pole weapon as a battleaxe is ... anyone know why? [[Special:Contributions/62.196.17.197|62.196.17.197]] ([[User talk:62.196.17.197|talk]]) 14:25, 12 June 2013 (UTC)

== Article needs restructuring ==

This article is largely inconsistent both within itself and with rest of Wikipedia, where every other article about pole arms includes spears and pikes as polearms and spears have their own subcategory in Pole weapons category, but this article says otherwise. I've seen literally no weapons scholar imply that spears AREN'T pole weapons - this is not an attempt at argument to authority, but pointing out that Wikipedia should probably be consistent with rest of the world - and it's not like said definition at the beginning of the article is sourced in any way, making things even more dubious (the only reason I mentioned 'common knowledge' in the first place, since we don't have an expert's definition anyway); and article DOES mention pike in a one-off link, making entire situation a complete mess... And even then, only thing implying spears shouldn't be included is mention that pole weapons should be swung (which is again a contradiction, since like half of weapons in the article have spear points and could be used for stabbing, too).
And worst of all, removal of spears appears to have been done to 'cut the article size down'. I'm not blaming anyone, articles being concise and accessible is of course important, it just seems that there were so many different conflicting attempts to improve this article, in the end they created some glaring inconsistencies that need to be sorted out in some way.

Okay, so currently the article is a hot mess, inconsistent with itself, unsourced in some relatively big chunks (opening definition and every Asian pole weapon), and inconsistent with rest of Wikipedia - including category it is a main article for.

My suggestions are: a) find a good definition of a pole weapon from a notable source; b) include all pole weapons that fit this definition; c)If the article is too long, instead of cutting things out, it may be a good idea to split it into two articles - main &quot;Pole weapon&quot; describing evolution, history and usage of pole weapons over the ages (so e.g from Stone Age when spears were popular, through Medieval times were they were common anti-cavalry weapons, and include a section of decline of use, and remaining use in modern times, and also a section on their use as tools/hunting implements (fishing spears, harpoons) - and instead of listing all pole weapons in the same article, make a new one, &quot;List of pole weapons&quot;, that transcribes majority of content from this article.

Of course, I'm kind of new to Wikipedia, so sorry if I came across as rude - not my intention, I'm just surprised by the state of the article and hope to improve it, and of course, any other ideas to improve state of the article are welcome. [[User:Shinobody|Shinobody]] ([[User talk:Shinobody|talk]]) 22:01, 26 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fmapjnl6qotyljtlsw0v680xv5olqu5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
