<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Border Guards Bangladesh</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>11841855</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748061680</id>
      <parentid>643109687</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-06T03:08:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12070">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Cold War|class=start}}
{{WikiProject Bangladesh|class=start|importance=high|photo=yes}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=start
&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|South-Asian-task-force=yes}}
}}

== NPOV on human rights abuses ==

NPOV removed, there are only factual statements there. two references added (they were already there, but removed by a bot) --[[User:Naught101|naught101]] ([[User talk:Naught101|talk]]) 02:06, 6 February 2008 (UTC)

:While the incident is indeed true, the first reference is from a blogspot blog, and hence not a [[WP:RS]].  I suggest removal of this ref, and substitute it with something from news media or other [[WP:RS|reliable sources]]. --[[User:Ragib|Ragib]] ([[User talk:Ragib|talk]]) 02:38, 6 February 2008 (UTC)

::I know what you're saying, but just because the reference is biased doesn't mean that it doesn't include facts, and also doesn't mean that the bias tarnishes this article. --[[User:Naught101|naught101]] ([[User talk:Naught101|talk]]) 04:56, 6 February 2008 (UTC)

:::I'm not claiming the blogspot-hosted blog as biased, I'm just pointing out that it can't be used as a reference. Anyone can open a blog in blogspot and can virtually write anything. See [[Wikipedia:Verifiability#Sources]], which explicitly states that: ''Anyone can create a website or pay to have a book published, then claim to be an expert in a certain field. For that reason, self-published books, newsletters, personal websites, open wikis, blogs, forum postings, and similar sources are largely not acceptable.'' --[[User:Ragib|Ragib]] ([[User talk:Ragib|talk]]) 05:15, 6 February 2008 (UTC)

:::Point taken, I added another new-based reference (easy to find, there's probably more). I'm leaving the blog reference in for the moment, I think perhaps another sentence about the protest groups could accommodate it. Not attacking the NPOV claim on this section, but I feel that without it the whole article is slightly biased in favour of the Rifles - only talks about their good points, especially the &quot;activities section&quot;. Some sections could be collapsed. I'll have a go. --[[User:Naught101|naught101]] ([[User talk:Naught101|talk]]) 22:46, 20 February 2008 (UTC)

== NPOV (Nov 2008) ==

Article now reads like a total advert, extolling the virtues of the force ad infinitum. [[User:Ninetyone|ninety]]:[[User talk:Ninetyone|one]] 19:35, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

:Agreed. Cleaned up a few sentences of the intro, and the article needs major cleanup for removing the laudatory tone. --[[User:Ragib|Ragib]] ([[User talk:Ragib|talk]]) 21:12, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

::I messed around with it a little, but I really don't have the knowledge to do a full overhaul. Are these the same Bangladesh Rifles who have been in the news recently? That would seem to be worth a mention.[[User:Deadlyhair|Deadlyhair]] ([[User talk:Deadlyhair|talk]]) 06:54, 26 February 2009 (UTC)

== [[Bangladesh Rifles#Liberation War .26 BDR|#Liberation War &amp; BDR]] ==

This section is clearly written from a patriotic Bangaladeshi perspective (&quot;the independence and sovereignty of our nation&quot;, etc).  However, I don't think that I know enough about the subject to do a good rewrite.  Also some of it is included in the previous section (History) and perhaps the actual facts in it should simply be placed there.  —[[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]] ([[User talk:Toby Bartels|talk]]) 22:42, 26 February 2009 (UTC)

This is how it read:
: In 1958 this force was additional task of anti-smuggling. It is the only force whose members took up arms against the erstwhile pak. This organization is proud of its contribution for the independence and sovereignty of our nation boasting 14 awards comprising 2 highest gallantry awardees Bir Srestho Lance Naik Nur Mohammad Sheik, and Bir Srestho Munshi Abdur Rouf, 8 Bir Uttams, 40 Bir Bikrams and 91 Bir Pratiks. After the independence, on 3rd March 1972 had been renamed as Bangladesh Rifles. As a mark of recognition of great courage and bravery of soldiers, Rifles introduced Bangladesh Rifles Podok in 1985 and President Rifles podok’ in 1989. So far, 21 members Bangladesh Rifles podok’ and 29 received ‘President Rifles podok’. During the border skirmish at BOROIBARI post in 2001 3 of our valiant Riflemen made supreme sacrifice for the sovereignty of our with Indian Border country. These 3 martyrs were honored by Bangladesh Rifles podok while the other 5 were awarded press podok.
Some anons have shortened it, without changing the tone and removing (possibly true) facts that aren't otherwise in the article.  So I'll preserve it all here, since there is probably material worth salvaging, but which would just have to be checked by somebody who knows what they're doing with it (so not me, sorry).  —[[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]] ([[User talk:Toby Bartels|talk]]) 03:42, 28 February 2009 (UTC)

== article shows extreme bias ==

I suggest everything related to the &quot;gallantry awards&quot; is simply removed (including but not limited to the entire decorations section). [[User:CapnZapp|CapnZapp]] ([[User talk:CapnZapp|talk]]) 22:17, 28 February 2009 (UTC)
:I'm not sure; there's precedent for that kind of section; see [[442nd Infantry Regiment (United States)]]; then again, they're famous for being the most decorated military unit in the US Army; in the case of the Rifles, it may be undue weight.[[User:Deadlyhair|Deadlyhair]] ([[User talk:Deadlyhair|talk]]) 19:20, 1 March 2009 (UTC)
:I'm guessing somebody just copy-pasted BDR's official website. [[User:Ratibgreat|Ratibgreat]] ([[User talk:Ratibgreat|talk]]) 09:36, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

==Templates==
Do you think we have enough warning templates at the top of this article? I think we could use one more. --[[User:Tocino|Tocino]] 01:44, 4 March 2009 (UTC)

==Name change==
Name for BDR is still BDR, and not BGB. The name change from BDR (Bangladesh Rifles) to BGB (Border Guards Bangladesh) is yet to be approved. Somebody unknowingly changed ALL the &quot;BDR&quot; to &quot;BGB&quot; and &quot;Bangladesh Rifles&quot; to &quot;Border Guards Bangladesh&quot; in the article. Please re-edit it back. I'm not really sure how to do it without doing it manually. Thanks, and cheers.[[User:Ratibgreat|Ratibgreat]] ([[User talk:Ratibgreat|talk]]) 09:34, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

I would like to edit the following, not to change the information or tone, just the readability leaving content considerations to knowledgeable researchers.
&lt;br /&gt;
-- from current (2013/02/25) -- 
During the war of independence members of the EPR were the first to respond against Pakistan Army. Adjutant Captain Mr. Rafiqul Islam was a smart guy in Chittagong sector. He understand the situation of 1971 and prepare them self to fight against any situation. At 25th march Dr. Jafor a famous eye specialist informed Mr. Rafiq that Pakistan Army has left the cantonment.Mr. Rafiq tells a book named by, A Tale of Millions, page 56, &quot; I told Dr. Zafar, I alongnith my troops of E.P.R. will fight The Pakistan Army to save our people and to free them.Move to Sholashahar and the Cantonment and tell all Bangali soldiers to join us. Meet me at my tactical HQ on the Railway Hill. Immediately I dialled Halishahar E.P.R. HQ where the Bangli JCOs were waiting my orders.&quot; The E.P.R. Officers captured all Pakistani Officers and move forward. At 26th March Pakistan Army send a trop by Bregedear Iqbal. The E.P.R. take an ambush against them. Captain Rafiq Tells &quot; This ambush by the E.P.R. troops at kumira was the first direct action agains the enemy in the history of our liberation war.&quot;[3].At 26th March 1971 Sheikh Mujibs's declaration of independence also stimulate Rifles' members participated in the liberation struggle right from its inception. At the final Bangladesh Forces Sector Commanders Conference presided by General M.A.G Osmani, on January 29, 1972, the East Pakistan Rifles was renamed as the Bangladesh Rifles .
&lt;br /&gt;
-- to suggested --
During the war of independence members of the EPR were the first to respond against Pakistan Army. Adjutant Captain Mr. Rafiqul Islam was a smart guy in Chittagong sector. He understood the situation of 1971 and prepared to deal with any situation. At 25th march Dr. Jafor, a famous eye specialist, informed Mr. Rafiq that Pakistan Army had left the cantonment. On page 56 of the book ''A Tale of Millions'' Mr. Rafiq relates &quot;I told Dr. Zafar, I along with my troops of E.P.R. will fight The Pakistan Army to save our people and to free them. Move to Sholashahar and the Cantonment and tell all Bangali soldiers to join us. Meet me at my tactical HQ on the Railway Hill. Immediately I dialled Halishahar E.P.R. HQ where the Bangli JCOs were waiting my orders.&quot; The E.P.R. Officers captured all Pakistani Officers and moved forward. At 26th March Pakistan Army sent a troop by Brigadier Iqbal. The E.P.R. ambushed them. Captain Rafiq relates &quot;This ambush by the E.P.R. troops at Kumira was the first direct action against the enemy in the history of our liberation war.&quot;[3] At 26th March 1971 Sheikh Mujibs's declaration of independence also stimulated Rifles' members participation in the liberation struggle right from its inception. At the final Bangladesh Forces Sector Commanders Conference presided by General M.A.G Osmani, on January 29, 1972, the East Pakistan Rifles was renamed as the Bangladesh Rifles .
------------------
Not being knowledgeable of the English of the subcontinent, I have left style and usage unfamiliar to me as-is, rather than replace it with what may merely be personal preference or American dialectal choice. Comments?
--[[User:Yellow-lab|Yellow-lab]] ([[User talk:Yellow-lab|talk]]) 23:08, 25 February 2013 (UTC)

== Citation problem ==

The page says:
According to Captain Rafiq , &quot;This ambush by the E.P.R. troops at Kumira was the first direct action against the enemy in the history of our liberation war.&quot; with citation:
(Major Rafiq: A Tale of Millions, Page 56 and Aberar Shongram Shadhinotar Shongram, P:135, by: Lieutenant Colonel [[Abu Osman Chowdhury]]){{verify source}}.
A Tale of Millions, Page 56, available [http://dspace.wbpublibnet.gov.in:8080/jspui/bitstream/10689/12641/6/Chapter%201-7_1-77p.pdf here] doesn't say that. [[User:Sminthopsis84|Sminthopsis84]] ([[User talk:Sminthopsis84|talk]]) 19:09, 7 June 2014 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Border Guards Bangladesh]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=748061676 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20140307070434/http://www.bangladeshchronicle.net:80/index.php/2013/02/pilkhana-massacre-collaborator-mixes-in-the-crowd to http://www.bangladeshchronicle.net/index.php/2013/02/pilkhana-massacre-collaborator-mixes-in-the-crowd

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 03:08, 6 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8fousaukxvid13z32n4vpj2srbv5xzp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
