<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ottoman–Habsburg wars in Hungary (1526–1568)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12644814</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751071043</id>
      <parentid>751063146</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T05:45:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GeoffreyT2000</username>
        <id>21491290</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>GeoffreyT2000 moved page [[Talk:Ottoman-Habsburg Wars in Hungary (1526-1568)]] to [[Talk:Ottoman–Habsburg wars in Hungary (1526–1568)]]: Use en dash.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7464">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=start|&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=y
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=y
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=y
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=y|Ottoman=y|Early-Modern=y}}
{{WikiProject Ottoman Empire|class=Start|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Hungary|class=start|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Turkey|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=start|importance=low|Crusades-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=Start|importance=|HRE-taskforce=yes}}
{{WikiProject Austria|class=Start|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=C|importance=mid}}
}}

==Untitled==
&quot;thanks to brave leadership by Captain Nikola Jurišić the city fought off every assault. As a result, the city was offered terms; the garrison was spared in return for the surrender of the city.&quot;  

This quotation is just one of many, many legends and lies.

Haha, it seems like all leaders against the Ottomans are gods and heroes! They are Humans, all commanders cannot be so brave! I am very tired of reading articles with European benefit Only! Nobody writes for Turkish benefit. The Whole wikipedia is Anti-Turkish, almost nothing is correct when talking about battle against Turks. Everyone transforms legends into real history. All articles considering the Ottomans, and all other Turkish related articles should be deleted from wikipedia, it is just a bunch of legends, unreliable sources and Anti-Turkish comments.

:These so called legengs and lies you speak of are all derived from the works of the following source:

{{cite book|last=Stephen|first=Turnbull|title=The Ottoman Empire 1326 - 1699|location=New York|publisher=Osprey|year=2003|pages=p.}}

:I don't know what you believe in but the fact that the Captain defended it heroically and bravely is not a biased statement. What are you saying? Of course the Ottoman Empire was mighty one, you would have to be insane or very brave to fight it with such bad odds as that at Koszeg. 

: Listen here, there is nothing anti-Turkish going on. I cannot believe how ridiculous your statements are and how you have just made countless logical fallacies in your argument - tell me why this is anti-Turkish. Quite frankly wikipedia does not listen to such nonesense as yours, which is why I have to leave this comment for you. There are many good Turkish articles out there made by Turkish Wikipedians. Good luck getting rid of them.[[User:Tourskin|Tourskin]] 22:10, 21 August 2007 (UTC)

hmm as i know this war the ottoman won because they defeat the armies of ferdindan in hungary the ottoman won important battles and then the habsburg kaiser had to pay every year a tribute to the sultan all historians say this for example Die Türkenkriege from Klaus-Peter-Matschke so i would propose that the result was not indeccisive but ottoman victory because main reason is that the habsburg kaiser had to have pay every year a tribute and lost important battles also historians say that this first war beetween ottoman and habsburg the ottoman won Die Türkenkriege Klaus-Peter-Matschke or Türkenbeute srry for my bad englisch i´m from germany    &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/85.181.43.77|85.181.43.77]] ([[User talk:85.181.43.77|talk]]) 15:43, 10 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Merger proposal ==

There are two different pages about the same military conflict (the second is [[Austro-Turkish War (1526–1552)]]). It seems to me that it could be reasonable to merge new page with more old. --[[User:Slb nsk|Slb nsk]] ([[User talk:Slb nsk|talk]]) 15:49, 28 October 2010 (UTC)
* Nobody protested. Done --[[User:Slb nsk|Slb nsk]] ([[User talk:Slb nsk|talk]]) 19:06, 4 December 2010 (UTC)
==File:Hungary 1550.png Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Hungary 1550.png|File:Hungary 1550.png]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests September 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 16:35, 29 September 2011 (UTC)
|}

== Complete misunderstanding of the meaning of kleinkrieg ==

This article seems to erroneously identify the ''kleinkrieg'' with a single conflict limited to 1530-1552. In fact ''kleinkrieg'' refers to the type of low-intensity warfare which took place during peacetime between the Ottomans and Habsburgs during the whole period of Ottoman rule in Hungary, but particularly 1568-1683. This article totally misses the point and mischaracterizes its topic. It describes Ottoman military campaigns in Hungary - but if there's an imperial army involved, then it's '''not''' a ''kleinkrieg''. The war is not &quot;little&quot; when the sultan is marching into Hungary at the head of an army. ''Kleinkrieg'' refers to, say, an Ottoman or Habsburg district governor leading a couple thousand men on a raid against the other side, not Suleiman the Magnificent attacking Habsburg fortresses with tens of thousands of men. [[User:Chamboz|Chamboz]] ([[User talk:Chamboz|talk]]) 23:29, 3 November 2016 (UTC)

:I renamed the article, but Wikipedia still has lots of pages referring to this conflict as the &quot;Little War&quot;. I don't know who decided this term should be applied to the general Ottoman-Habsburg conflict in Hungary during this period, but this is what the &quot;Little War&quot; was in reality:

:&quot;Although the years between 1568 and the outbreak of full war in 1593 were disturbed by the ''Kleinkrieg'', a state of intermittent raid and counter-raid along the length of the extensive and ill-defined border demarcating the Ottoman and Habsburg spheres of influence, both sides lacked the will and the strength to open official hostilities.&quot;

:Caroline Finkel, ''The Administration of Warfare: The Ottoman Military Campaigns in Hungary, 1593-1606'' (1988), p. 8.

:Wikipedia's pages linking to this article need to be checked to remove incorrect usage of the term &quot;Little War&quot;, and this article needs to be expanded to include conflict up until the peace treaty of 1568, because that's when the war actually ended, not at the siege of Eger, which this article had picked for some reason. [[User:Chamboz|Chamboz]] ([[User talk:Chamboz|talk]]) 04:18, 23 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8zhhuljwsfmf83lln2819q4rysqim28</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
