<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Czesław Piątas</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1121271</id>
    <revision>
      <id>679019359</id>
      <parentid>670586506</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-09-02T00:45:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dthomsen8</username>
        <id>6277327</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up, replaced: {{WikiProject Poland}} → {{WikiProject Poland|class=stub|importance=low}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6697">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Poland|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=yes
|class=Start
|military-work-group=yes
|listas=Piatas, Czeslaw
}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=Start
|&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|Polish-task-force=yes|Biography-task-force=yes}}
| blp=yes
}}

==Untitled==
A quick voting: Biobox or no Biobox&lt;br&gt;
&lt;u&gt;end date:&lt;/u&gt; October 6th, 19:30 CET
* Yes
:# [[User:Halibutt|[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User Talk:Halibutt|tt]]]] 19:27, Oct 31, 2004 (UTC)
:#--[[User:Emax|Emax]] 21:20, 31 Oct 2004 (UTC)
* No
* I don't care

This vote has already been had on [[Talk:Charles Darwin]]. Obviously the specific person makes no difference here, the question is should we have &quot;infoboxes&quot; that contain no information that is not already in the text of the article. [[User:Gzornenplatz|Gzornenplatz]] 04:24, Nov 1, 2004 (UTC)

:Was that voting on [[Charles Darwin]] about [[Czeslaw Piatas|Czes&amp;#322;aw Pi&amp;#261;tas]]? How are the two related? [[User:Halibutt|[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User Talk:Halibutt|tt]]]] 12:23, Nov 1, 2004 (UTC)

::Wasn't Gzornenplatz banned from reverting any Polish-related articles? [[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]]

:::What's the point of an info box if it doesn't contain any info? (Sorry, that's all I can say.) [[User:KF|&lt;KF&gt;]] 11:05, Jan 28, 2005 (UTC)

::::Indeed. Will Halibutt, Witkacy, or Piotrus explain what the purpose of this infobox here could possibly be, other than creating an ugly overhang at the right due to being longer than the article text in order to give the reader such essential information as &quot;Died: -&quot;, &quot;Major wars and battles: -&quot;, and &quot;Medals: ?&quot;. [[User:NoPuzzleStranger|NoPuzzleStranger]] 12:34, 27 May 2005 (UTC)

:It's an infobox we plan to add to all articles on Polish militarymen (take a look at [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Template%3AInfobox_Polish_Soldiers]). It gives much more info than the original Infobox Biography and the purpose of it is to standarize the bio articles and to give the reader a brief overview of the person. It's sort of an extended image caption. If you dispute the usefulness of the template or the Image captions in general, feel free to start a RfC process or simply state your objections at the relevant talk page of the project. Also, feel free to join the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Polish Army]], whose purpose is the standarization and reorganization of all Polish Army-related articles. 

:Starting a revert war over this particular article makes no sense to me at all. [[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 12:43, May 27, 2005 (UTC)

::This infobox does not give any information that is not in the text. And it is hardly needed to give a &quot;brief overview&quot; when it is more voluminous than the text. Infoboxes are only justified when they either provide tabular data which is not suitable to be included in the article text, or when they summarize data from the text of a very long article (such as the U.S. presidents, where usually all the information is also in the text, but widely distributed over many pages, so that the infobox makes sense in allowing the reader to look up immediately what the name of the first lady was, for example). Neither justification applies here, and it applies even less at stubs like [[Slawomir Petelicki]], but for certain ''major'' Polish military figures it may make sense, so I'm not taking issue with the existence of the template, only with its being used where it's useless. So the relevant talk page is this one, not the template talk. [[User:NoPuzzleStranger|NoPuzzleStranger]] 12:56, 27 May 2005 (UTC)

:Then I don't understand you at all. If the commander in chief and the chief of staff of the entire [[Polish Army]] are not ''important military figures'', then who is? Also, why do you waste your time for a revert war you're unlikely to win? Why not expand the article instead? [[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 00:59, May 28, 2005 (UTC)

::He is of no historical importance, as indicated by the shortness of the article (and there's probably not much that could usefully be added to it). Important figures would be those who fought in wars and maybe have a certain name recognition beyond Poland. And do you think ''you'' are likely to win this revert war? [[User:NoPuzzleStranger|NoPuzzleStranger]] 01:30, 28 May 2005 (UTC)

:::Wikipedia is not a historical encyclopedia, but a general one. So, the fact that the guy is still alive is irrelevant here. He is the most important figure in the Polish Army currently and as such is almost as notable as the president of Poland. Whether people outside of Poland know the guy or not is also quite irrelevant here, the guy is notable enough to have a note on him in WP. So, all in all, it seems that you're waging this revert war just for fun. 

:::As a sidenote, I was hoping that it is clear to both of us that nobody can win a revert war, since it's the wiki who looses. But apparently it is not that clear to you. Anyway, what is the point you're trying to prove with your blanking of the template? [[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 04:54, May 28, 2005 (UTC)

::::You don't understand. I could also have said he is of relatively little ''encyclopedic'' importance. Of course by Wikipedia's standards he's clearly notable enough to have an article - I'm not disputing that - but you wouldn't find him in an encyclopedia like the Britannica although you could probably find ''some'' Polish military figures there, which indicates that he is ''relatively'' unimportant. Still, I see you managed to expand the article so that the infobox doesn't appear as ridiculous as before, so I'll leave it in place.

::::As to revert wars in general, if it is apparent to you that nobody can win them, why do you wage them? We both know the answer - it may be hard to win a revert war, but it's very easy to lose one. One rather keeps it going than to lose it - this is ultimately a fault of the system rather than of the particular participants in any revert war. [[User:NoPuzzleStranger|NoPuzzleStranger]] 11:28, 28 May 2005 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ddxsk3hexng7ena25jibjvynudiaf76</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
