<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Singapore Army</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1870712</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751096968</id>
      <parentid>751096502</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T09:52:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cahk</username>
        <id>1218696</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/আইশ্টে হায়লেশ|আইশ্টে হায়লেশ]] ([[User talk:আইশ্টে হায়লেশ|talk]]) to last revision by Bruce1ee. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10607">{{talkheader}}
{{WPMILHIST
|class=start
|&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|Southeast-Asian-task-force=yes
|National-task-force=yes
}}
{{SG|class=Start|importance=mid}}

==Howitzer link incorrect==
Theres something wrong with the link for the M71 howitzer. It redirects to the M71 star cluster instead.
Howitzers 	
M71 155 mm Towed Howitzer
[[User:Venny85|Venny85]] ([[User talk:Venny85|talk]]) 15:45, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

*Problem fixed! It is supposed to be the [[Soltam M-71]] 155 mm howitzer. ...''[[User:Dave1185|Dave1185]] ([[User talk:Dave1185|talk]]) 02:35, 15 October 2008 (UTC)''

== Needs a little more work ==
I've copyedited the opening part of this article, but it needs a lot more from someone who understands the subject. [[User:Sjorford|sjorford]] [[User talk:Sjorford|&amp;rarr;&amp;bull;&amp;larr;]] 09:26, 11 May 2005 (UTC)

== AMX-10RC and Tempest ==
I removed the [[AMX_10_RC|AMX-10RC]] from the table since there are no sources about Singapore operating this variant. Also placed &quot;Tempest (modernized Centurion MBT)&quot; in the line about the Cents. [[User:Sandstig|Edward Sandstig]] 11:59, 31 May 2006 (UTC)

== Merging IFV and MICV ==
Merged the [[MICV]] and [[IFV]] section since they're the same thing. (MICV being the British term an IFV being the term used by most other countries) --[[User:Sandstig|Edward Sandstig]] 18:05, 30 August 2006 (UTC)

== M-16S1 - Similar to the A1 or A2? ==

I've reverted the text to A1 - the M-16S1 does not have among other things, easily adjustable windage and elevation knobs, three-round burst, upper/lower handguards which the M-16A2 has. --[[User:Rifleman 82|Rifleman 82]] 01:52, 8 June 2006 (UTC)]

The M-16S1 is similar to the M-16A1 model because it was license produced even before the M-16A2 came out [[User:Assassin3577|Assassin3577]] ([[User talk:Assassin3577|talk]]) 11:48, 28 December 2008 (UTC)

== Largest in quantity ==

Regarding the sentence: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;...  military force, the largest in quantity ... South-East Asia region.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In terms of active troops, Singapore actually has the smallest military among its immediate neighbours. If we include the reserve, things get abit fuzzy, like: are there 3 divs, or 6 divs etc (note that some units are never mobilised and exist on paper only), should we include paramilitary of Malaysia and Indonesian etc. It is not entirely clear.--[[User:Vsion|Vsion]] 17:40, 11 August 2006 (UTC)

== MBT ==

Is there a reference for the information of &quot;Tempest (modernized Centurion MBTs)&quot; found in the table, both for the quantity as well as the name of &quot;Tempest&quot;. Thanks.  --[[User:Vsion|Vsion]] 00:44, 31 August 2006 (UTC)
: Only references I've seen have been messageboard posting and a few personal websites. The official Singapore Army website makes no mention of it, but some people have claimed this has to do with OPSEC. I'm of the impression that either the claim of OPSEC is true, or the Singaporean Ministry of Defence has already withdrawn their Centurions from service. If someone could post a reliable source on this that'd be great, but if the existence of those Centurions is supposed to be classified, then let's just remove the line about the &quot;Tempest&quot; from the article. --[[User:Sandstig|Edward Sandstig]] 09:05, 31 August 2006 (UTC)
::As far as I can remember, SAF never had any MBTs commissioned or operational. --[[User:Vsion|Vsion]] 13:54, 31 August 2006 (UTC)

== #### ==

(1)  The number of Centurions should be 60, as this is often cited. Although this is fuzzy territory, as the figure varies, with some sources citing the higher figure of 80-100. However, the dominant one is 60 centurions.&lt;br /&gt;
(2)  The number of 105mm arty guns (60) is exaggerated. More commonly seen figure for LG1 is 40+. I know there is no official figures for all these, but then we should stick to what is commonly cited by foreign publications.&lt;br /&gt;
(3)  The figures for Primus as well as Pegasus (cited as 54) is the target figure, not present operational strength. Since they are both new, there should be one battalion each, yielding a figure of 18 for each weapon.&lt;br /&gt;
(4)  The figure for Bionix total (excluding Bionix II) should be 500 instead of 600. And the claim of 100 Bionix II is unlikely to be true, as this is new equipment. Most probably one battalion active. And not all will be 30 mm cannon-armed, as the structure is one 40/50 Bx for every Cannon-armed Bx.&lt;br /&gt;
(5)  Having said all these, it must be pointed out that it is highly probable that Singapore has more weapons of certain types than is reported by sources like Janes'.
[[User:Daniel Ehud|Daniel Ehud]] 15:26, 14 December 2006 (UTC)

==Graphic of the Army Structure==

I'm currently working on a project to create graphics of the structure of the most important Armies. i.e. [[Structure of the French Army|France]]. I want to make also a graphic of the structure of the Singapore Army, but the information at this point is not sufficient, as there is no information what units compose the single divisions, brigades and Regiments. Does anyone have this information- down to the Battalion and Company levels?
Thanks
[[user:noclador|noclador]]
: 6th and 9th Division have the most number of NS battalions so you can't name them.[[User:Phd8511|Phd8511]] ([[User talk:Phd8511|talk]]) 14:54, 14 March 2013 (UTC)

==M551 Sheridan (In Storage)==
Since when did the Singapore Army have such a tank? The Tempests do exist, but I don't think they have this old US made tank. Which source is this from?[[User:Cibwins|Cibwins]] 03:08, 13 July 2007 (UTC)

*I too, don't think so that Singapore Army operates the M551 Sheridan but I have seen with my own eyes one M551 Sheridan and one SK-105 Kürassier parked in the garage of ST kinetics at Portsdown road (I have the photo too but I can't show it here due to obvious reasons), probably for research purposes. ...''[[User:Dave1185|Dave1185]] ([[User talk:Dave1185|talk]]) 02:41, 15 October 2008 (UTC)''

==SIMON says==
According to an un-named source of mine, SAF has acquired a small quantity of [[SIMON breach grenade]], a new kind of [[Door breaching]] [[rifle grenade]] (RELM/GREM) that is currently in use by the US Army and Israeli Defense Force, for test and evaluation purposes. Please provide me with any additional data so I can add this into the main page. Thank you. -- [[User:Dave1185|Dave1185]] ([[User talk:Dave1185|talk]]) 05:12, 14 March 2008 (UTC)

==Image copyright problem with Image:BX mk2.jpg==
The image [[:Image:BX mk2.jpg]] is used in this article under a claim of [[WP:NFC|fair use]], but it does not have an adequate explanation for why it meets the [[WP:NFCC|requirements for such images]] when used here.  In particular, for each page the image is used on, it must have an [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|explanation]] linking to that page which explains why it needs to be used on that page.  Please check

:* That there is a [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|non-free use rationale]] on the image's description page for the use in this article.
:* That this article is linked to from the image description page.
&lt;!-- Additional 10c list header goes here --&gt;

This is an automated notice by [[User:FairuseBot|FairuseBot]]. For assistance on the image use policy, see [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]]. --13:42, 12 May 2008 (UTC)

==Someone should start a section on its history==
As in history of the Singapore army. Use the ST archives--http://newspapers.nl.sg/Default.aspx as a start[[User:Foxhound66|Other dictionaries are better]] ([[User talk:Foxhound66|talk]]) 10:29, 21 April 2011 (UTC)

== Page temporarily protected from editing ==

I have temporarily protected this page from editing to force discussion on the talk page and stop the current edit war. Please discuss the disputed content here. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 16:19, 6 July 2013 (UTC)

== Merkava ==

How reliable is intelligenceonline? The merkava purchase seems to be a rumour and there does not seem to be any other source backing this claim.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Orangewarning|Orangewarning]] ([[User talk:Orangewarning|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Orangewarning|contribs]]) 10:21, 27 June 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:A Google search turns up no reliable sources which verify this claim. Intelligenceonline seems to be some kind of subscribers-only newsletter, and its reliability is open to question. I've just re-removed this claim pending verification from a clearly reliable source. While Singapore's defence procurements aren't always publicly announced (eg, the recent purchase of additional F-15s), publications like Jane's try their best to track them, and it's unlikely that a purchase of 50 unusual tanks would go un-noticed. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 11:35, 14 July 2015 (UTC)

== State of the article ==

This article (like many Singapore military-related articles) is a mess. It's less of a mess now, after I edited for style, flow and clarity, excised clumsy expressions and weird syntax, trimmed sentences for economy, and terminated clauses that read as though someone wrote them in Singlish before translating them to English. It was horrible to read, offensive to anyone who doesn't have a tin ear for English.

So please, do not revert. Do not insert unnecessary localisms and superfluous words that interrupt the flow of the article. Less is more.

Years ago Singapore-related Wikipedia articles used to be good. Most of them are shit now, near-incoherent because of piecemeal edits (often made using unidiomatic English) that ruin, just ruin, the explanatory flow of an article. [[Special:Contributions/121.6.144.209|121.6.144.209]] ([[User talk:121.6.144.209|talk]]) 17:12, 11 August 2015 (UTC)

== The history section is really small ==

needs improvement suggest looking at ST archives

[[User:Cantab1985|Cantab1985]] ([[User talk:Cantab1985|talk]]) 14:38, 13 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jrh91gkztt1t4xe72rlyk96micbnry8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
