<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1631708</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745941209</id>
      <parentid>745941165</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T08:43:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/82.24.122.84|82.24.122.84]] - &quot;/* &quot;there seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships today&quot; */ and Beatty's culpability&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14211">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=n|class=B|listas=Beatty, David Beatty, 1st Earl|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Low|peerage-work-group=y|peerage-priority=Low}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=C
&lt;!-- B-Class 5-criteria checklist --&gt;
|B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; =y
|B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; =y
|B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; =y
|B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; =y
|B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; =y
|Biography=y|Maritime=y|British=y|WWI=y|Majestic-Titan=4|portal1-name=Battleships|portal1-link=Selected biography/4}}
{{WikiProject Cheshire|class=C|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class=C|importance=Low}}
}}

== Where born? ==
So, was he born in Ireland or Cheshire? (One web page says Howbeck, Cheshire, other Nantwich, Cheshire) [[User:Pibwl|Pibwl]] 16:54, 21 Mar 2005 (UTC)

...According to [http://www.thepeerage.com/p7165.htm#i71647] he was born in Nantwich, Cheshire. I'm changing. [[User:Pibwl|Pibwl]] 16:59, 21 Mar 2005 (UTC)

...I was born in Enniscorthy (Co. Wexford), and I was always told that he was a local.  Reading that he was born in Cheshire was confusing, so I thought perhaps the second Earl was born in Wexford; BUT:  http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/David_Beatty_Beatty   &quot;DAVID BEATTY BEATTY, 1ST Earl (1871-), British admiral, was born in Ireland in 1871, the son of Capt. D. L. Beatty, 4th Hussars, of Borodale&quot;  Someone really needs to sort this one out authoritatively.  See also http://www.new-zealands.com/slaney/history.htm  &quot;Admiral Earl Beatty Born at Borodale near Wexford in 1871 and died in London in 1936.&quot;  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.18.164.7|75.18.164.7]] ([[User talk:75.18.164.7|talk]]) 05:04, 11 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:The entry in the Dictionary of National Biography by the editor of ''The Beatty Papers&quot; has him being born in Cheshire.  I'll have a look in Roskill's &quot;intimate biography&quot; later today.  [[User:Harlsbottom|Harlsbottom]] ([[User talk:Harlsbottom|talk]]) 10:37, 11 March 2008 (UTC)

Roskill and http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9013970/David-Beatty-1st-Earl-Beatty both list Howbeck. Also local school in Stapeley have a Beatty House as one of their houses in his honour and he is considered a local hero. [[Special:Contributions/86.133.57.180|86.133.57.180]] ([[User talk:86.133.57.180|talk]]) 09:53, 17 March 2008 (UTC)

In the book the life and papers of Admiral Beatty - which was apparently collected and published at his sons request it also states Howbeck Lodge. Indeed it has a photo of him in the drawing room.
:I think we can regard ODNB (which says Howbeck Lodge) as the most authoritive source unless anyone thinks strongly otherwise. [[User:Dormskirk|Dormskirk]] ([[User talk:Dormskirk|talk]]) 20:09, 11 November 2012 (UTC)

::The ODNB article doesn't mention the fact that Beatty was born out of wedlock, so it's hardly authoritative.  But the consensus amongst biographies (his nephew Charles Beatty, Roskill) is that he was born at Howbeck Lodge. &amp;mdash;[[User:Simon Harley|Simon Harley]] ([[User talk:Simon Harley|Talk]] | [[User:Simon Harley/Library|Library]]). 23:19, 11 November 2012 (UTC)
:::I am happy to go with the consensus. Many thanks. [[User:Dormskirk|Dormskirk]] ([[User talk:Dormskirk|talk]]) 23:54, 11 November 2012 (UTC)

::::Despite the circumstances of his birth and parental marriage, his being born in Nantwich area was publicly known locally even during World War I when the ''Crewe Chronicle'' carried a story about his &quot;Birthplace&quot;, which was then in the process of being demolished as the story was headed (I speak from memory of reading it in 2009) &quot;Admiral Beatty's Birthplace - Looks as if Germans had shelled it&quot;![[User:Cloptonson|Cloptonson]] ([[User talk:Cloptonson|talk]]) 19:34, 6 July 2014 (UTC)

== Trenchard ==
No mention has been made with regard to the clash with Trenchard over the return, or not as it turned out, of the FAA. I understand Beatty threatened to resign over the issue. I think this should be added. [[User:Dapi89|Dapi89]] ([[User talk:Dapi89|talk]]) 18:15, 11 March 2009 (UTC)
:Short comment on this now included under &quot;Postwar career&quot;. [[User:Dormskirk|Dormskirk]] ([[User talk:Dormskirk|talk]]) 21:39, 17 November 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;Anecdote&quot; ==
I removed this recently added section for two reasons. One, being a draft from an archive it's patently [[WP:OR|original research]].  There is a published version however.  The second point is that the story of Beatty delaying his departure from Rosyth just to pick up a chair is garbage.  Take it from someone who has many books about Jutland and has read dozens of accounts of the battle both official and private - not one supports the notion that &quot;the whole fleet had to be drawn up while his talisman was fetched&quot;. --[[User:Simon Harley|Simon Harley]] ([[User talk:Simon Harley|talk]] | [[User:Simon Harley/Library|library]] | [[User:Simon Harley/Reviews|book reviews]]) 20:46, 20 January 2010 (UTC) 

{{cquote|[[Seton Montolieu Montgomerie|Viva Montgomerie]] was a friend of Ethel Beatty and recalls in her memoirs that ''There was a certain armchair which accompanied them everywhere they went, and when the Admiral was leading forth his fleet, en route for his great Battle of Jutland, he discovered that the chair had been left behind. I shall have no luck without it, he said, and the whole fleet had to be drawn up while his talisman was fetched. It was a chair he had looted during his campaign in China and he firmly believed it was haunted by its former owner. Ethel confirmed this, for she told me that she had distinctly seen a Chinese figure sitting in it as she came into the room, and she saw it fade as she drew near.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=My Scrapbook of Memories| Draft copy. Eglinton Archive |page=66 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{reflist}}

Are you saying that someone, in print, disputes the accuracy of this anecdote? On the face of it you seem to be saying that in your opinion a published reminiscence is incorrect? [[User:Sandpiper|Sandpiper]] ([[User talk:Sandpiper|talk]]) 14:15, 6 March 2010 (UTC)

== Affair ==
According to historian Robert Massie, Beatty in 1917-18 escaped from his unhappy marriage to Ethel Field by conducting a torrid affair with Eugenie Godfrey-Faussett. Massie quotes from love letters between the two. See:

{{cite book |title=Castles of Steel: Britain Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea |last=Massie |first=Robert Kinloch |year=2003 |authorlink=Robert K. Massie |publisher=Ballantine Books |location=New York |isbn=0-345-40878-0 }}, pp. 750-752.  

[[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 13:39, 28 May 2012 (UTC)
:Short comment on this now included under &quot;World War I&quot;. [[User:Dormskirk|Dormskirk]] ([[User talk:Dormskirk|talk]]) 21:51, 17 November 2012 (UTC)

== David Richard Beatty ==
I see that his middle name has been removed, although he doesnt appear to have used the middle name in the Navy some primary sources mention it:
*Birth Index for Nantwich district for 1871 Q3 shows  &quot;David Richard Beatty&quot;
*1871 Census of Nantwich district shows &quot;David R Beaty&quot; son of David Longfield Beaty at &quot;Howbeck Villa&quot;.
*In the 1881 Census at St Thomas College he is listed as just &quot;David Beatty&quot;.
*In the 1891 Census at RN College, Greenwich he is listed as &quot;David Beatty&quot; born Howbeck, Cheshire. All subsequent records that I can see make no mention of a middle name. Not particularly asking for it to be restored but just keeping it here for information. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 20:28, 18 November 2012 (UTC)
:That's very helpful. Many thanks. [[User:Dormskirk|Dormskirk]] ([[User talk:Dormskirk|talk]]) 21:13, 18 November 2012 (UTC)

== David Beatty and Ernest King and handkerchiefs ==
Hello all-

FADM [[Ernest King]], USN, wore a breast pocket handkerchief under his ribbons (true).  My reference says it was &quot;worn in emulation of [his] erstwhile joint commander, the jaunty, publicity-fond, and lauded British Admiral David Beatty,&quot; following WWI, and King did it in spite of his anglophobia. Adjectives aside &amp;#9786; , I can't find a picture of Beatty and a handkerchief.  Can anyone comment?  Thanks.  [[User:JMOprof|JMOprof]] ([[User talk:JMOprof|talk]]) 14:21, 25 May 2013 (UTC)

== Incomplete sentences ==
As it stands, the last sentence of the section &quot;First Sea Lord&quot; is obviously incomplete - &quot;Without his strong leadership events like the Invergordon Mutiny of 1931 might have been seen.&quot; Seeen as what? Perhaps the original writer would like to add a completion? [[User:Cenedi|Cenedi]] ([[User talk:Cenedi|talk]]) 12:43, 28 December 2013 (UTC)

::::It's not an incomplete sentence, although as somebody has tried to remove it obviously reads that way to at least two people, even though there is actually nothing grammatically wrong with it. It's a near direct quote of the views of Stephen Roskill, a well-regarded naval historian. It means that in his view defence cuts might have caused unrest on the lower decks as there was in protest at pay cuts at Invergordon in 1931.[[User:Paulturtle|Paulturtle]] ([[User talk:Paulturtle|talk]]) 22:50, 27 June 2014 (UTC) Just refreshing my memory of some material I added to Mountbatten's biog last autumn, over half his annual intake of young officers had to leave the Royal Navy at this time. The cuts of the early 1920s were very deep indeed.[[User:Paulturtle|Paulturtle]] ([[User talk:Paulturtle|talk]]) 13:20, 7 June 2016 (UTC)


:::::I have discovered another apparent incomplete sentence in the Assessment section, third point, on signals in that there may be a missing word of words between &quot;Although&quot; and &quot;encountered&quot;:
:::::''Although Beatty was supposed as a fast armoured scout and report to Jellicoe the exact position of the German ships he encountered, or to keep in contact with the German fleet while he retreated to the main British Grand Fleet, he failed to do so.''[[User:Cloptonson|Cloptonson]] ([[User talk:Cloptonson|talk]]) 21:21, 29 May 2016 (UTC)

::::Well, I didn't write that section but I've sorted it anyway. Amazing how the eye glazes over these things.[[User:Paulturtle|Paulturtle]] ([[User talk:Paulturtle|talk]]) 13:20, 7 June 2016 (UTC)

== &quot;Assessment&quot; section ==
The &quot;Assessment&quot; section mentions that there's a debate between supporters of Beatty and Jellico, but all I see is criticism of Beatty. [[User:Blaylockjam10|Blaylockjam10]] ([[User talk:Blaylockjam10|talk]]) 09:52, 13 June 2014 (UTC)

::::The article is about Beatty, so most of the discussion is of his handling of the battlecruisers at Jutland, with a mention that people were disappointed at Jellicoe's failure to win a decisive victory. The &quot;debate&quot;, such as it was, was in the interwar period and was accompanied by some disreputable behaviour on Beatty's part, more so than in fact is discussed here. By and large historians have long since agreed that Jellicoe handled the Grand Fleet cautiously and well, and that Beatty's record left a bit to be desired.[[User:Paulturtle|Paulturtle]] ([[User talk:Paulturtle|talk]]) 22:53, 27 June 2014 (UTC)

::::For those who take an interest in these things, &quot;The Unfinished Battle&quot;, a recent book about Jutland by Jellicoe's grandson Nicholas, discusses the controversy of the inter-war period. I haven't had a chance to read it yet.[[User:Paulturtle|Paulturtle]] ([[User talk:Paulturtle|talk]]) 14:26, 8 May 2016 (UTC)
.
== &quot;there seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships today&quot; ==

This is repeated twice, but neither of those mentions, nor the &quot;Assessment&quot; section, mention that the 'something wrong' was almost certainly the result of Beatty and Jellicoe's own actions. In the aftermath of Dogger Bank, Beatty criticised rate of fire and Jellicoe had ordered his captains to take whatever measures would increase their rate of fire (as more shells fired would result in more hits, even if accuracy was not improved). In several ships, including those lost, this had taken the form of removing the flashproof scuttles from the ammunition lobbies and removing propellant charges from their protective cases, in direct contravention to ammunition handling regulations. When Invincible, Indefatigable and Queen Mary took penetrating turret hits this meant the flash progressed unhindered to their magazines, at which point they blew up. However, Beatty's flag captain, Chatfield, had refused to allow this on his ship, Lion, which therefore did not explode when Q turret took similar damage, giving time for Q's magazine to be flooded before the flash-fire that occurred some 30 minutes later. Immediately post action, Beatty and Jellicoe ordered that these measures were to be reversed on any ship which had carried them out, without admitting the actions had been done at their instigation. Beatty was therefore aware, as early as the day after the battle, that the problem resulted from his and Jellicoe's own orders, but then spent the rest of his career furthering the proposition that the design of the ships was at fault and that they had instead been lost to plunging fire penetrating their deck armour (DNC pointed out that if this was the case there would be evidence of it in the other ships hit, and there was not). As First Sea Lord, Jellicoe suppressed reports from both DNO and DNC identifying the departure from magazine regulations as the fault, a process continued by Beatty when he replaced Jellicoe. There are extensive discussions of this in both D K Brown's &quot;Grand Fleet&quot;, and Norman Friedman's &quot;British Battleships&quot;. Friedman points out that Beatty's continued insistence while C in C Grand Fleet that the problem was plunging fire, and his insistence on design changes to the Hood class as a result, likely cost the Royal Navy Hood's three sisterships, with effects cascading all the way through to WWII.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.24.122.84|82.24.122.84]] ([[User talk:82.24.122.84#top|talk]]) 08:43, 24 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>0p20b7knfhacp4ly3acmzzx8ho4ujrz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
