<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Fall of Saigon</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1795782</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737518949</id>
      <parentid>737466062</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-03T10:20:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guccisamsclubs</username>
        <id>27259540</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Aftermath */ policy</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21486">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military History|class=B|US-task-force=yes|Southeast-Asian=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes}}
{{WikiProject Vietnam|class=B|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Cold War history|class=B|importance=high}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2007-04-30|oldid1=127175894|date2=2008-04-30|oldid2=209227671|date3=2009-04-30|oldid3=287029592|date4=2012-04-30|oldid4=489964762|date5=2015-04-30|oldid5=659659888}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
| algo=old(70d)
| archive=Talk:Fall of Saigon/Archive %(counter)d
| counter=1
| maxarchivesize=100K
| archiveheader={{Automatic archive navigator}}
| minthreadsleft=5
| minthreadstoarchive=1
}}

==(2005)==

As I learned from what I read and information from my family members who fought in the war (I'm Vietnamese by the way), it looked a lot more like 'liberation' instead of 'fall', even though my family has been in the south for generations.
Just an opinion
------
I was just wondering if anyone knew how many people died in the 'Fall' or 'Liberation' of Saigon.

The Fall of Saigon does not seem to be a neutral term. Did the north not regard the &quot;fall&quot; as a liberation? [[User:Stevertigo|SV]]|[[User_talk:Stevertigo|t]]|[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Stevertigo&amp;action=edit&amp;section=new add] 18:18, 25 Apr 2005 (UTC)
:Wikipedia should definitely include mention of what the event is called by different parties in different languages. But whatever the term preferred by the north, it has not popularized it in English-speaking countries; the &quot;Fall of Saigon&quot; would seem to be the most common name in not just the U.S. but the UK (and ''[[The Independent]]'' is not known for its sympathy for U.S. military adventures), Australia, and New Zealand. &quot;Saigon Giai Phong&quot; meaning &quot;Saigon Liberation&quot; does appear to be a term used in Vietnam.  -[[User:Choster|choster]] 05:02, 27 Apr 2005 (UTC)

== Did all the Americans get out? ==
One thing I have not been able to ascertain from the article (and other sources) is whether all Americans, particularly civilian contractors, journalists, and so forth, managed to get out of Saigon (and out of Vietnam, per se) during the fall of Saigon.  There was a lot of turmoil and I can imagine that there may have been some American (and perhaps Australian/Thai/Korean civilians) that couldn't get out.  Is anything known about this?  It is an angle that would be worth adding to the article. -[[User:Rolypolyman|Rolypolyman]] ([[User talk:Rolypolyman|talk]]) 01:41, 22 March 2010 (UTC)
:Interestingly the article opens with: &quot;The fall of the city was preceded by the evacuation of '''almost all''' the American civilian and military personnel in Saigon&quot;.... so what happened to the rest? -[[User:Rolypolyman|Rolypolyman]] ([[User talk:Rolypolyman|talk]]) 21:27, 23 March 2010 (UTC)
::I would assume that those who stayed (if there are any) married and got stuck in Saigon, although I'm wondering why they didn't return back to the United States, because I doubt they'd enjoy living in Communist Vietnam. My father was a Saigon native and explained that they left gradually, so if there are any Americans still living in Vietnam, they're either very few or dead, and some mixed up with the people who still live there. [[Special:Contributions/75.4.252.249|75.4.252.249]] ([[User talk:75.4.252.249|talk]]) 02:35, 29 April 2010 (UTC)
-A not insignificant number of Western journalists (among other people) stayed behind. This is mentioned in the Vietnam War documentary &quot;The Last Days in Vietnam&quot;, among other places. It's pretty common for journalists to do this -- ie, not relying on a military force to get in/out of a conflict zone, and not relying on them for the &quot;schedule&quot;/&quot;timetable&quot;.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.119.234.255|76.119.234.255]] ([[User talk:76.119.234.255|talk]]) 20:08, 26 February 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Symbolic picture of the event ==

I think this the symbolic picture of the fall of Saigon. The current imagine describes the US' activites, not of Vietnam's ones. The current picture is not symbolic because it describes the evacuation of Americans, not the fall of Saigon regime. The new one really described the fall of Saigon regime.

[[File:Các chiến sỹ Quân Giải phóng miền Nam Việt Nam cắm lá cờ Chính phủ Cách mạng Lâm thời Cộng hòa miền Nam Việt Nam trên nóc Dinh Độc lập, đánh dấu kết thúc chiến tranh.jpg|300px]] 

[[People's Liberation Armed Forces of South Vietnam]] Lieutenant Captain Bùi Quang Thận planted [[Viet Cong]]'s flag on the roof of the Presidential Palace at 11:30 am on April 30th, 1975 that is the symbol of the war ends an the fall of Saigon regime
 
I think we should change the picture[[User:Honglienhoa|Honglienhoa]] ([[User talk:Honglienhoa|talk]]) 03:45, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
:'''Oppose''' While the picture is indeed representative of the fall of the Republic of Vietnam, the Van Es picture is the iconic photo of the Fall of Saigon and known worldwide. I would also note that your proposed photo is nominated for deletion for potential breach of copyright. Whatever the decision on the notability of your proposed photo, we can't use it if it is a copyvio. [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 04:16, 30 August 2016 (UTC)

== Aftermath ==

* [[Reeducation camp]]s not mentioned.
:Done [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 11:22, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
* ''The evacuation'' describes 1977 state of art. [[User:Xx236|Xx236]] ([[User talk:Xx236|talk]]) 09:43, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
:Don't understand what you mean. [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 11:22, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
::''In 1977, National Review alleged''. The world has changed since 1977.[[User:Xx236|Xx236]] ([[User talk:Xx236|talk]]) 11:27, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
:::I really don't understand what you are trying to say. The world changes constantly...[[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 03:10, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::Either the subject is important and discussed or totally unimportant and forgotten since 1977. [[User:Xx236|Xx236]] ([[User talk:Xx236|talk]]) 05:32, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::I really don't see the point you are trying to make. [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 07:04, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
*{{ping|Mztourist}} Xx is probably saying that the National Review allegation is outdated and not taken seriously, which it correct. Or he is being sarcastic or something. I recommend deleting it. Go ahead and insert info about re-education camps, just don't make it too long and don't use Desbarats or OC Register's 1-2.5 million. These figures are a fringe hoax/citogenesis. A good overview of the camp numbers is provided [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2759306?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents here on page 305], the range is 200-300K based on official and exile sources. It is not necessarily clear what percentage of the inmates were &quot;politicals&quot;, but the camps in question are &quot;re-education camps&quot; and not common prisons.[[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 22:14, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
::Porter is repeating official communist statistics as gospel truth, as is his modus operandi. As ''The Black Book of Communism'' states: &quot;Pham Van Dong, the prime minister at the time, admitted in 1980 that 200,000 had been reeducated in the South. '''Serious estimates range from 500,000 to 1 million''' out of a population of 20 million. The victims included a large number of students, intellectuals, monks (both Buddhist and Catholic), and political militants (including Communists). Many of these people had been in sympathy with the National Liberation Front of South Vietnam, which revealed itself to be no more than a cover for Northern Communists and which almost immediately broke all its promises to respect the wishes of the people of the South.&quot; I'm not aware of anything that would allow us to confidently proclaim the indisputable accuracy of the official Vietnamese government statistics over the numerous independent sources that arrived at far higher figures.[[User:TheTimesAreAChanging|TheTimesAreAChanging]] ([[User talk:TheTimesAreAChanging|talk]]) 23:05, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
:::Nope, read Porter's footnote. Jstor is free and BBoC is a crap source, though by no means the crappiest. [[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 01:45, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:::: Porter's sources are all from 1976 or 1977. That 200,000 to 300,000 individuals were imprisoned within the first two years of communist rule is, indeed, ''widely'' repeated in sources from that period. However, the ''Black Book'' and ''OCR'' are referring to the total number of people who passed through the camps for a period of time extending more than a decade after those figures were published. The ''ORC'' is clearly a RS, though you may question its weight, and the ''Black Book'' is published by Harvard University Press, and therefore cannot simply be dismissed as &quot;crap.&quot; There appears to be a growing consensus favoring some mention of the camps, so your total deletion is not warranted.[[User:TheTimesAreAChanging|TheTimesAreAChanging]] ([[User talk:TheTimesAreAChanging|talk]]) 03:14, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::'''You'll note that I was the first one here who said &quot;go ahead and add info about the camps, BUT...(ignored).&quot;'''The BBoC is a simple compendium of Communist crimes, assembled for political effect, containing little unbiased original research. But it's certainly superior to the OCRegister, I'll lend you that! It is not the ultimate authority for any contentious claim. What sources does it cite? I see you've changed your argument from &quot;Porter cites commie stats&quot; to &quot;Porter cites outdated stats&quot;. This ignores the fact that it's perfectly possible that the vast majority of reeducation-camp-proper internees (as opposed to people routinely jailed in Vietnam, from Various parts of the country and for various reasons) were sent there immediately after the fall of Saigon. This also ignores the fact that Porter cites Truong Nhu Tang (1985) for 300,000 and &quot;A former member of the National Assembly of reunified Vietnam who also escaped from the country&quot; (1977) for &quot;not under 200,000.&quot;  Now we are supposed to believe that re-education camp imprisonment ''accelerated'' after 1977 to create 1 million victims? Or that Truong Nhu Tang writing in 1985 was a secret commie propagandist? When you've ''actually'' checked Porter's sources and found his footnotes to be wrong, you can come back and tell us about it. But for now, all you've done is misinterpret Porter (and whoever co-wrote his article). [[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 03:33, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::Re: OCRegister. Debarats misquotes a Vietnamese official (see Porter) and takes 1M as the number of camp prisoners, then OCR takes Desbarats' 1M and reproduces it as an unsourced estimate, giving no reference to any sources or data of any kind as backup. If that's not citogenesis, I dunno what is.[[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 04:03, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::It seems to me that this discussion should be taking place on the [[Reeducation camp]] page rather than here. I simply added in a short para regarding reeducation camps in the aftermath section because obviously that was a direct effect of the end of the war. There doesn't seem to be any disagreement that the camps existed and that numerous South Vietnamese military and government members were sent for reeducation. The argument seems to be solely about how many were sent for reeducation, which I have attempted to address in the paragraph. I'm happy to consider rewording but you can't just keep blanking it. I will check my reference books later but am sure I can add some more WP:RS on this are. [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 04:24, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Well, the Orange County register asserts &quot;over a million&quot; in a caption to a photograph, which is as good as no source at all. But be that as it may, the info you put in has nothing in common with the OCR source. 
:::::::I'd be wary of blindly cross-posting stuff anything from [[Reeducation Camps]]. ''Some'' of the info there does not reflect any real consus, just reflects what some pov-pushing pro-Saigon editors have been able to get away with.
:::::::The only real source ATM is Porter (linked above and free from Jstor). I'll look into the BBoC to see if there is anything there.[[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 12:19, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::*Update on ''[[The Black Book of Communism]]'' figure of 500K-1M brought up by TheTimesAreAChanging. I took a look at that source and was immediately reminded of just how sloppy and tendentious it really is. There is no footnote and no explanation of the claim at all. It just says a range of &quot;serious&quot; estimate''s''. I guess they has so many &quot;serous&quot; estimates that they could not figure out which one to cite. Or perhaps they just pulled the number form Desbarats and mixed it in with some other shit they heard somewhere. More citogenesis, figuratively speaking. The only figure the ''BBoC'' actually deigns to attribute is 200,000, to [[Pham Van Dong]], from 1980.
:::::::*I should also add another point on Desbarats. It is ''she'' not Porter, who relies exclusively on &quot;official&quot; Vietnamese sources—unfortunately those sources did not say what she thought they said. [[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 16:25, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::*FWIW, [https://books.google.ru/books?id=p-SaTzYEbFEC&amp;pg=PP4&amp;dq=reeducation+camps&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjVheyVmO_OAhWENpoKHYfACXwQ6AEIPzAD#v=snippet&amp;q=250%2C000&amp;f=false here's a source] that refers to a &quot;conservatively estimated 250,000&quot;. Like the BBoC it cites no sources, but unlike Porter, it can not be accused of having any sympathy for the Vietnamese govt.[[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 22:24, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Here's what [https://www.ocf.berkeley.edu/~sdenney/Vietnam-Reeducation-Camps-1982 Ginetta Sagan and Stephen Denney] came up with in late 1982:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:::::::Over one million Vietnamese have been re-educated and returned to society since 1975, according to the Hanoi government. However, this would seem to contradict another official statement from Hanoi which said that 40,000 is the total number of Vietnamese who have gone through the reeducation camps since 1975, and that 26,000 remained in the camps as of 1980. So if we are to take these figures seriously, and try to reconcile them with each other, then we might assume that the one million figure includes those who attended &quot;short-term, on-the-spot&quot; re- education, in which Vietnamese would come to the &quot;classes&quot; during the day and go home at night, while the 40,000 figure refers to those who underwent long-term re-education, meaning internment in the camps. With regard to the latter, we must note that the estimates of foreign observers of those detained in the camps since 1975 are much higher, ranging up to 300,000. Our own estimate is that 100,000 Vietnamese are still in the camps. It would be more difficult for us to estimate the total number detained in the camps since 1975, and we will not attempt to estimate the number of dissidents detained in the many prisons of Vietnam.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
::::::::During the 1980s, we see that the remaining 100,000 gradually declines to tens of thousands and then mere thousands, until the camps are abolished. So while Porter's 200,000-300,000 is probably somewhat conservative, it is nevertheless in the right ballpark. In contrast, it is more difficult to see how the higher numbers cited by the ''Black Book'' et al. could be consistent with these earlier reports (particularly the high estimate of 1 million, shocking and conveniently round though it is). In the absence of any new, compelling evidence, we should certainly go with the earlier figures. (Note as well that it would be original research on our part to add the 300,000 detained and the 100,000 remaining for a total of 400,000, as we have no basis to assume that the latter were not part of the former group.)[[User:TheTimesAreAChanging|TheTimesAreAChanging]] ([[User talk:TheTimesAreAChanging|talk]]) 23:56, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::{{re|TheTimesAreAChanging}}It may be somewhat conservative if it can shown that Truong Nhu Tang's 300,000 pertains only to the first year or two after the fall of Saigon. But I am sort of wondering now how to reconcile the 40,000 cited in Sagan with 200,000 cited in Porter. The obvious explanation is that Vietnamese figures are crap: for example, Desbarats identified ''two'' figures for the number of people &quot;returned to civilian life&quot; (which she interpreted as the &quot;the number thrown into labor camps&quot;). One was 1 million and the other was 2.5 million. But there is a one in a hundred chance that Porter himself misinterpreted his source, just like Desbarats misinterpreted hers. p.s.: as usual, props on your research. [[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 00:13, 2 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::George Veith in Black April on page 495 refers to &quot;hundreds of thousands&quot; undergoing reeducation and states that many ARVN officers holding a rank of major or above were not released until 1987, while the last 4 ARVN Generals were not released until 1992. [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 10:13, 2 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::Larry Engelmann's Tears before the rain contains several individual accounts of Vietnamese who were sent to reeducation camps for periods of between 3 and 17 years but doesn't provide any numbers of these who underwent reeducation. [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 10:21, 2 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::I am sure you know this already, but a thing to keep in mind is that re-education is not the same as camps.[[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 11:13, 2 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Mztourist, would you mind replacing the ''ORC'' cite with Engelmann? If the ''ORC'' is as inaccurate as we currently believe it to be, then it should really be dropped—otherwise, I can guarantee it will turn up again.[[User:TheTimesAreAChanging|TheTimesAreAChanging]] ([[User talk:TheTimesAreAChanging|talk]]) 22:14, 2 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::(Commenting from the sidelines) I haven't been following this, but the addition of this talk page comment caught my eye. I had some difficulty figuring out what &quot;ORC Cite&quot; you were saying that &quot;we&quot; think is inaccurate. My guess is that you may be referring to [http://www.ocregister.com/articles/april-298485-vietnamese-black.html this] piece from the Orange County Register which the article currently cites twice (the cite is duplicated). Regarding whether or not &quot;we&quot; think the piece is inaccurate and whether or not that opinion ought to bear on its mention here, please see [[WP:DUE]]. Regarding mention in an earlier comment of page 495 of Veith's ''Black April'' book referring to &quot;hundreds of thousands&quot; undergoing reeducation, I don't see that [https://books.google.com.ph/books?id=fXRKAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA495 here] and a [https://books.google.com.ph/books?id=fXRKAQAAQBAJ&amp;q=%22hundreds%20of%20thousands%22 search] within the book fails to find the string &quot;hundreds of thousands&quot; fails (there are [https://books.google.com.ph/books?id=fXRKAQAAQBAJ&amp;q=reeducation lots of hits] on &quot;reeducation&quot;, though). [[User:Wtmitchell|Wtmitchell]]  [[User talk:Wtmitchell|(talk)]] &lt;small&gt;(earlier ''Boracay Bill'')&lt;/small&gt; 00:12, 3 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::Our arguments here may not be explicitly couched in WP policy because the priority was to explain the source material in human-speak, so we at least know what we are talking about. But replacing OCR and Desbarats with the other sources is consistent with policies on fringe, due, [[WP:EXCEPTIONAL]], and probably others I am too lazy to think about.[[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 10:20, 3 September 2016 (UTC)

== Black April ==

Deleted &quot;many other countries&quot; as it's unsourced and possibly misleading. for example France has a substantial Vietnamese expat community and [[fr:Chute_de_Saïgon]] only cites American sources, most of which talk explicitly about Vietnamese Americans. I may be wrong, but I see no evidence of an ''Avril Noire'' being commemorated in France, for example. [[User:Guccisamsclubs|Guccisamsclubs]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclubs|talk]]) 17:08, 1 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>snd022skh1xxhtw70y1pnnohjvs7rkg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
