<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Leros</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7206722</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746652987</id>
      <parentid>725316007</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T18:19:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14654">{{WikiProject Military history|class=B
|B-Class-1=yes
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|British-task-force=yes
|Balkan-task-force=yes
|WWII-task-force=yes
|Italian-task-force=yes
|German-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Greece|class=B
|peer-review= 
|old-peer-review=
|importance=mid 
|attention= 
|B-Class-1=yes
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
}}

==Image copyright problem with Image:RHS Vasilissa Olga.jpg==
The image [[:Image:RHS Vasilissa Olga.jpg]] is used in this article under a claim of [[WP:NFC|fair use]], but it does not have an adequate explanation for why it meets the [[WP:NFCC|requirements for such images]] when used here.  In particular, for each page the image is used on, it must have an [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|explanation]] linking to that page which explains why it needs to be used on that page.  Please check

:* That there is a [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|non-free use rationale]] on the image's description page for the use in this article.
:* That this article is linked to from the image description page.
&lt;!-- Additional 10c list header goes here --&gt;

This is an automated notice by [[User:FairuseBot|FairuseBot]]. For assistance on the image use policy, see [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]]. --02:50, 2 October 2008 (UTC)

== Victory fanfare ==

Many, many years ago I read a book about the Battle of Leros and I remember it stating that this was the last time, after the victory, that the Nazi Germany victory fanfare was sounded on German radio. Has anybody ever heared about that one or even have a reliable source? [[User:EA210269|EA210269]] ([[User talk:EA210269|talk]]) 12:19, 20 March 2009 (UTC)

== NPOV ==

As now, this article looks like the only defenders of Leros were the British. This is not only false, because italian coastal and AA batteries pounded heavily german boats and stukas, but also counter-landing italians squads fighted Brandeburghers and Fallschirmjaegers, causing heavy losses. One of the reasons of german victory was the undecision of Brittorous at first and of Tilney afterwards, in ordering a counterattack while still detaining control of central part of the island and of key positions (batteries, airport and port). Many italians were shot after surrender by germans for the fierce resistence, and twelve officers were killed some days later. A great amount of ammunitions for the italian batteries, sent by Supermarina via Alexandria of Egypt was blocked there for unkonwn reasons and a mimimum part finally reached Leros on board of destroyers Velite and Artigliere. This description is totally inaccurate and if you want more informations please consult ''Aldo Levi, Avvenimenti in Egeo dopo l'armistizio (Rodi, Lero e isole minori), Roma, Ufficio storico della Marina Militare, 1993. (no ISBN)''; this book is written by an italian admiral and printed by the Historical Office of the Italian Navy. Also useful can be the corrisponding article on Italian wiki, [[it:Battaglia di Lero]]. [[User:Pigr8|Pigr8]] [[User talk:Pigr8|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#purple;&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Melius esse quam videri&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 11:47, 11 July 2013 (UTC)
:Great! Go ahead and [[WP:SOFIXIT|add]] anything you like, provided it is well-sourced. --[[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 12:24, 11 July 2013 (UTC)
::I'm undoubtedly bold, but also very busy with an article running for Fearured article, another 80+k in completiond, a WikiProject, [[it:Progetto:Marina]] needing constant care and many adds every day, on it.wiki. Great! If you think to fix the voice, I'll try to help you, elsewhere keep in mind that a skill user with 20+k contributions probably knows policies and pages like [[WP:SOFIXIT]]. It doesn't suffice having an article on Watchlist, you must also take care of it. Bye. --[[User:Pigr8|Pigr8]] [[User talk:Pigr8|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#purple;&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Melius esse quam videri&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 12:33, 11 July 2013 (UTC)
:::Again, I don't disagree with the essence of your comments. But I also think a veteran editor knows that simply pointing out an article's deficiencies at the talk page will, by itself, get nothing done. The bias you pointed out is true but also understandable, as the article is based on easily available English-language sources, and not Italian ones, to which most people around here (including me, sadly) have no access. So if you have access to some good sources, and are interested in and know a thing or two about the period, the best thing to do is to put this article on your schedule for a rewrite. [[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 17:03, 11 July 2013 (UTC)
::::Ok, this is a very different answer respsct to the previous. But the problem is that time is limited for all of us. I'm glad I haven't found another possessive user like some others that take every change on some articles as a personal challenge, as I did a pair of days ago, and so I'll try to work on it as I can, and also to vector some other forces here ;) But, anyway, I could not leave the article as it was, time or not time, and if I was on it.wiki I has done exactly the same. Incidentally, I'l be glad to cooperate on any article with you and to exchange documentation where possible. Just as example, I suggest [http://www.dodecaneso.org/leros%201943.htm this site] if you can translate from italian. Bye. --[[User:Pigr8|Pigr8]] [[User talk:Pigr8|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#purple;&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Melius esse quam videri&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 12:52, 12 July 2013 (UTC)
:::::What about now?--[[User:Olonia|Olonia]] ([[User talk:Olonia|talk]]) 11:38, 18 December 2015 (UTC)

== Casualties ==

The British and Italian casualties listed in the Infobox are quite different from those mentioned in the &quot;Casualties&quot; section. What are the correct figures?--[[Special:Contributions/188.152.96.79|188.152.96.79]] ([[User talk:188.152.96.79|talk]]) 19:36, 9 December 2015 (UTC)
:Indeed. Besides, for Italian casualties, there is something strange: Italian forces are listed as 8,320, with casualties being 254 killed or missing and 5,350 prisoners. That is, 5,600 overall. Where did the other 2,700 go?--[[User:Olonia|Olonia]] ([[User talk:Olonia|talk]]) 12:05, 18 December 2015 (UTC)

== Providing a Coherent Picture of the Land Battle ==

I have inserted lines and paragraphs in order to provide a coherent picture of the land battle.  The article was almost unintelligible, and provided almost no useful descriptive geographic references of where the fighting took place.  

The article seemed to be overly made up of descriptions of battle fought by the Italian coastal batteries; not only in driving off some German invasion attempts, but the minor ground battles fought at Italian batteries themselves.

The Italian coastal batteries were very important.  On the other hand, the Italian infantry forces were put in coastal defense positions by the British commander and told to stay there and not move.  Italian infantry had little part in the land battle.

I have a couple of very good military type maps of the island I could insert, but I am not sure about the copyright issues, or even how to insert them.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:SageMan|SageMan]] ([[User talk:SageMan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/SageMan|contribs]]) 20:53, 7 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Athough I have sympathy for your edits most or all of them were effectively unsourced. Please add sources. &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid green; padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;[[User:The Banner|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:'Old English Text MT',serif;color:green&quot;&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Banner&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:The Banner|&lt;i style=&quot;color:maroon&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/i&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 20:59, 7 June 2016 (UTC)

I am a source.  The whole Leros affair was a waste that got many people killed for nothing.  There is a lesson to be learned from the campaign.  This was Churchill's third little disaster in the area:  Gallipoli in WWI, the Greece and Crete intervention in 1941, and Leros in 1943.  

It was obvious the British occupation of the islands east of Greece would fail once the Americans made it quite clear the focus was on Italy and the coming invasion of France.  The nearest air bases in Cyprus were outside the range of most British fighters to begin with, much less those fighters having enough fuel for the loiter time necessary to gain air superiority.  Given the British track record in these matters it looked like an ill-conceived scheme for the British to gain bases giving them more control over the Turkish Straits, as much as anything else.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:SageMan|SageMan]] ([[User talk:SageMan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/SageMan|contribs]]) 00:10, 8 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Please, do not get angry at me but read [[WP:RS]]. What we need are reliable, independent, prior published sources. Unpublished work can not be used, as it is considered [[WP:OR|own research]]. &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid green; padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;[[User:The Banner|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:'Old English Text MT',serif;color:green&quot;&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Banner&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:The Banner|&lt;i style=&quot;color:maroon&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/i&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 22:14, 8 June 2016 (UTC)
:Ow, and please keep your edits neutral in style and tone. Off course, being critical is allowed but you have to source that (by the way: sources in English are NOT mandatory, just preferred). &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid green; padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;[[User:The Banner|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:'Old English Text MT',serif;color:green&quot;&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Banner&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:The Banner|&lt;i   style=&quot;color:maroon&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/i&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 22:19, 8 June 2016 (UTC)

Banner, it appears you deleted an entire section I had written, which gave a coherent listing of the order of battle of both sides in the battle, and where the Germans landed on the island.  Next I was going to show where the British battalions were located at the start of the battle.  Then I was going to provide a comprehensible description of the battle.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:SageMan|SageMan]] ([[User talk:SageMan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/SageMan|contribs]]) 21:48, 13 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The article has serious deficiencies as it is written.  You have to pick your way through it and solve a crossword puzzle to make any sense of it.  Whoever wrote it didn't even seem to have a grasp of when to insert a paragraph, or how to keep events in sequence.  They mix up the north and south of the island.  I can vastly improve the article using expert knowledge of warfare and good sources.  If you don't think the official After Action Report written by the commander of the German invasion force, or the official British history of the campaign are good sources, then you evidently don't know what a &quot;source&quot; is.  I am an expert is warfare and foreign policy. You, Banner, seem to be an expert in eating and restaurants.  Please stick to what you know.   Hmmm, perhaps I will start inserting a multitude of my thoughts about eating and Dutch restaurants, of which I know little and have no interest.
:And you, Sir, have a blatant lack of manners.
:Please read again what I have written about Reliable Sources: ''Please, do not get angry at me but read [[WP:RS]]. What we need are reliable, independent, prior published sources. Unpublished work can not be used, as it is considered [[WP:OR|own research]].'' In fact, what an ''encyclopaedia'' needs is that you tell the world where you got your information. You mentioned a few, but failed to give those sources in your writings. Just use &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;your sources as detailed as possible, preferably with URL or page numbers&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid green; padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;[[User:The Banner|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:'Old English Text MT',serif;color:green&quot;&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Banner&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:The Banner|&lt;i style=&quot;color:maroon&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/i&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 22:49, 13 June 2016 (UTC

A lack of manners is deleting things of which you have no knowledge.  Stick to eating and restaurants Banner.  I have no desire to read what you have written, since I consider whatever you write to be trivial and irrelevant.  Stick to what you know.
:Yep, and I know the rules of Wikipedia. And I know manners. Goodbye, Sir. &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid green; padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;[[User:The Banner|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:'Old English Text MT',serif;color:green&quot;&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Banner&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:The Banner|&lt;i style=&quot;color:maroon&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/i&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 08:55, 14 June 2016 (UTC)

Yep, you are a pathetic little petty bureaucrat type of person Banner, like a child who thinks they have some power.  Typical.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:SageMan|SageMan]] ([[User talk:SageMan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/SageMan|contribs]]) 22:43, 14 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Battle of Leros]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=746652985 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20151222173241/http://www.anb-online.it/navi-da-guerra/posamine-e-dragamine/0301-legnano-l-f-t-6257-m-150/ to http://www.anb-online.it/navi-da-guerra/posamine-e-dragamine/0301-legnano-l-f-t-6257-m-150/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20061019010707/http://www.duxbury.plus.com:80/ww2.html to http://www.duxbury.plus.com/ww2.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:19, 28 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3ttr93eabie6sr05ajczpmsdqhzat0c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
