<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:HAL Dhruv</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5438008</id>
    <revision>
      <id>734161469</id>
      <parentid>726554952</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-12T15:03:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Blacklisted Links Found on the Main Page */spelling: necessaryily -&gt; necessarily</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13755">{{Talk header |search=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=12:50, 27 August 2011 (UTC)
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=446952021
|currentstatus=FGAN
|topic=War and military
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=B
|B-Class-1=y &lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=y&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes &lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes &lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes &lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|Rotorcraft= yes}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=C
|B-Class-1=y |B-Class-2=y |B-Class-3=yes |B-Class-4=yes |B-Class-5=yes
|Aviation=yes |Indian=yes}}
{{WikiProject India|class= B |importance=Mid |auto=yes
|B-Class-1=y |B-Class-2=y |B-Class-3=yes |B-Class-4=y |B-Class-5=yes}}
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=12 |units=months }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(365d)
|archive = Talk:HAL Dhruv/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== Pawan Hans ==
The issue of Pawan Hans operation of MOH helicopters has come into serious question.[http://www.telegraphindia.com/1111021/jsp/frontpage/story_14650522.jsp] The current version in the page only states that the MOH is going to replace Dhruv's with Mi-17's. This don't point out the role of Pawan Hans in making helis crash. The present version is just trying to project Dhruv as a bad Heli even though the fault lies with Pawan Hans, of which about six helis of various types has crashed in 2011 (upto Oct 2011), including Dhruv.[[User:Diahel|Diahel]] ([[User talk:Diahel|talk]]) 04:11, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
:Current revision of the section (minus my bolding for highlighting purposes here):
::''&quot;In October 2011, Jharkhand's regional government issued an urgent appeal for [[Mil Mi-17]] helicopters, as operations of their Dhruvs had been disrupted by prolonged maintenance delays and a major crash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://telegraphindia.com/1111022/jsp/frontpage/story_14653990.jsp |title = State copter out of action, pilots idle - On 9-month upkeep break |publisher = Telegraph India |date = 22 October 2011 |location=Calcutta, India |first=Amit |last=Gupta}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.telegraphindia.com/1111020/jsp/frontpage/story_14645424.jsp |title = SOS to Centre for MI-17s |publisher = Indian Telegraph |date = 19 October 2011 |location=Calcutta, India}}&lt;/ref&gt; '''In October 2011, allegations emerged about the quality of work peformed by Dhruv maintaince contractor, Pawan Hans Helicopters Ltd.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first = Nishit |last = Dholabhai |url = http://www.telegraphindia.com/1111021/jsp/frontpage/story_14650522.jsp |title = Glare on chopper operator - Pawan Hans-run copters involved in six accidents this year |publisher = Indian Telegraph |date = 20 October 2011 |location=Calcutta, India}}&lt;/ref&gt;''' In February 2012, the Home Ministry reported that the Dhruv remained grounded and that other helicopters such as the Mi-17 were being [[wet-lease]]d in its place; and in the long term, the Dhruv fleet is to be entirely replaced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.hindustantimes.com/India-news/NewDelhi/MHA-plans-to-buy-wet-lease-choppers-as-Dhruv-fleet-grounded/Article1-805127.aspx |title = MHA plans to buy, wet-lease choppers as Dhruv fleet grounded |publisher = Hindustan Times |date = 1 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;''
:This makes mention of the Pawan Hans incident, I had not removed it, only modified its placement in line with the timing of events and re-wording the sentence, along with implimenting formatting of the citation. [[User:Kyteto|Kyteto]] ([[User talk:Kyteto|talk]]) 04:14, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
::o.k it's for MOH only. Also it need to be checked whether they are just maintenance contractor for MOH or MoH is leasing helis from Pawan Hans.[[User:Diahel|Diahel]] ([[User talk:Diahel|talk]]) 04:18, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
::Other sources (Aviation Week) mention Panwa Hans provide services for other civil organisations operating Dhruvs beyond just the MOH. In terms of the article, going into a list of the operators with arrangements to PH strikes me as being a level of excessive detail, that they maintain Dhruvs and they're accused of being bad at it should be enough really. [[User:Kyteto|Kyteto]] ([[User talk:Kyteto|talk]]) 04:28, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
::In February 2012, the Home Ministry reported that the Dhruv remained grounded and that other helicopters such as the Mi-17 were being wet-leased in its place; and in the long term, the Dhruv fleet is to be entirely replaced. That seems unfair if it's not mentioned that the Mi-17 has also crashed in the hands of PH.[[User:Diahel|Diahel]] ([[User talk:Diahel|talk]]) 04:34, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
::The problem is that it's the Dhruv that always takes the negative comments, even though Eurocopter, Mi-17 and many other helis crashed in the hands of Pawan Hans. Even Chief ministers were killed with Eurocopter heli crash. But in HAL Dhruv page is so detailed, it tries to put all the blames of others on the Heli. That's the problem. If it has not been mentioned about the fault of PH, how will a reader know. They may mistake it to be a fault of Dhruv. That's the issue. And these kinds of things are that makes an impression of Dhruv being bad, even though the users like Indian Army and it's chief recently after using the heli has said it's a good helicopter.[[User:Diahel|Diahel]] ([[User talk:Diahel|talk]]) 04:41, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
:::''&quot;If it has not been mentioned about the fault of PH, how will a reader know.&quot;'' In terms of this particular pargraph? The previous sentence on the PH allegations should be sufficient, it'd seem really odd to pop it up after every other sentence in the paragraph, it'd be duplication. 05:00, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
:::This article is primarily about the Dhruv, not the Mi-17 or any of Eurocopter's product range, the accidents involving the Mi-17 should be brought up on the Mi-17's article, it'd be over-the-top bringing it up here. I wouldn't say that the Dhruv's being given an awful deal here, or that it is being unfairly picked on in the coverage: Take a look at the problems and accidents of the [[AgustaWestland Merlin]] for instance, I'd dare say it got as good a coverage of its flaws such as the rotor-cracking issue and several customer dropouts. And both the [[Bell Boeing V-22 Osprey]] and the [[Boeing-Sikorsky RAH-66 Comanche]] have huge entire sections throwing the flaws of those birds at the readers - I think the Dhruv isn't getting unfairly singled out, but new, grand projects get a huge amount of coverage and attention - issues are covered in greater detail. This can lead to some things negative getting magnified beyond the extent of less popular, pre-internet era helicopters with less material for article building and less editorial drive, but vast plains of positive information also gets brought in as well. The [[Lockheed Martin F-35 Lightning II]] gets a tremenously huge panning by critics, and has an enormous article of praise and flaws galore, it is the kind of article way too big for its own justification IMO, but that's an issue aside. I'd take the view that the article for the Dhruv has got to this level of development, and grown larger than most helicopter articles, as a sign of flattery. [[User:Kyteto|Kyteto]] ([[User talk:Kyteto|talk]]) 05:00, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
::::Agree completely that there must be openness in each and every article. Everything must be fairly point out. But what i'm saying is that Dhruv has taken a lot more criticisms and a lot of propaganda. Some of that propaganda has even poured in here into Dhruv's wiki page. Good that it's been corrected by pointing out the source. Now again a lot of its capabilities are still hidden and not projected properly. I agree with your view of this article being fair and to a level can be claimed to be one of the best article in terms of fairness (From the criticism point of view) and if the strengths are also projected in the same manner over a period of time, it will be a fair article of the Dhruv.[[User:Diahel|Diahel]] ([[User talk:Diahel|talk]]) 05:08, 10 February 2012 (UTC)
One more minor issue is that the reader must not feel that the Pawan Hans is the maintenance contractor for the Dhruv. The major operators of Dhruv are the Services and they maintain Dhruv's on their own and also HAL does for export customers. So i am rephrasing the sentence to read &quot;quality of maintenance work performed and operation of helicopters by Pawan Hans Helicopters Ltd&quot;.[[User:Diahel|Diahel]] ([[User talk:Diahel|talk]]) 05:16, 10 February 2012 (UTC)

==Machine-gun sentences==
For some reason the author th8inks that a reference means that a sentence has to end, resulting in lots of dis-jointed small sentences, which I call ''Machine-gun sentences''. It is a shame to hold back B-class because authors can't be bothered to link their sentences coherently and introduce their references mid sentence--[[User:Petebutt|Petebutt]] ([[User talk:Petebutt|talk]]) 04:05, 28 March 2013 (UTC).

== Blacklisted Links Found on the Main Page ==

Cyberbot II has detected that page contains external links that have either been globally or locally blacklisted.
Links tend to be blacklisted because they have a history of being spammed, or are highly innappropriate for Wikipedia.
This, however, doesn't necessarily mean it's spam, or not a good link.
If the link is a good link, you may wish to request whitelisting by going to the [[MediaWiki talk:Spam-whitelist|request page for whitelisting]].
If you feel the link being caught by the blacklist is a false positive, or no longer needed on the blacklist, you may request the regex be removed or altered at the [[MediaWiki talk:Spam-blacklist|blacklist request page]].
If the link is blacklisted globally and you feel the above applies you may request to whitelist it using the before mentioned request page, or request its removal, or alteration, at the [[meta:Talk:Spam Blacklist|request page on meta]].
When requesting whitelisting, be sure to supply the link to be whitelisted and wrap the link in nowiki tags.
The whitelisting process can take its time so once a request has been filled out, you may set the invisible parameter on the tag to true.
Please be aware that the bot will replace removed tags, and will remove misplaced tags regularly.

'''Below is a list of links that were found on the main page:'''

*&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.army-technology.com/projects/dhruv/&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*:''Triggered by &lt;code&gt;\barmy-technology\.com\b&lt;/code&gt; on the local blacklist''
*&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.airforce-technology.com/news/news68521.html&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*:''Triggered by &lt;code&gt;\bairforce-technology\.com\b&lt;/code&gt; on the local blacklist''

If you would like me to provide more information on the talk page, contact [[User:Cyberpower678]] and ask him to program me with more info.

From your friendly hard working bot.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Neuropol&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]] [[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:arnprior&quot;&gt;Notify]]&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-6.1ex;color:green;font-family:arnprior&quot;&gt;Online&lt;/sub&gt; 10:05, 3 April 2014 (UTC)


{{done|Resolved}} This issue has been resolved, and I have therefore removed the tag.  No further action is necessary.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 22:50, 22 June 2016 (UTC)== Copyright problem removed ==

Prior content in this article duplicated one or more previously published sources. The material was copied from: http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/India-joins-elite-club-with-heliborne-geo-survey-capability/articleshow/29262865.cms?referral=PM. Copied or closely paraphrased material has been rewritten or removed and must not be restored, ''unless'' it is duly released under a compatible license. (For more information, please see [[Wikipedia:COPYRIGHT#Using_copyrighted_work_from_others|&quot;using copyrighted works from others&quot;]] if you are not the copyright holder of this material, or [[Wikipedia:Donating copyrighted materials|&quot;donating copyrighted materials&quot;]] if you are.) For [[Wikipedia:Copyrights|legal reasons]], we cannot accept [[Wikipedia:Copyrights|copyrighted]] text or images borrowed from other web sites or published material; such additions will be deleted. Contributors may use copyrighted publications as a source of ''information'', and according to [[fair use]] may copy sentences and phrases, provided they are included in quotation marks and referenced properly. The material may also be rewritten, but only if it does not infringe on the copyright of the original ''or'' [[Wikipedia:Plagiarism|plagiarize]] from that source. Therefore such paraphrased portions must provide their source. Please see our [[Wikipedia:NFC#Text|guideline on non-free text]] for how to properly implement limited quotations of copyrighted text. Wikipedia takes copyright violations very seriously, and persistent violators '''will''' be [[Wikipedia:Blocking policy|blocked]] from editing. While we appreciate contributions, we must require all contributors to understand and comply with these policies. Thank you. &lt;!-- Template:Cclean --&gt; [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 00:11, 26 May 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>t6vn39sm1i23ndgi145lwxgtdrr8n4d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
