<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:NHIndustries NH90</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5523176</id>
    <revision>
      <id>734157636</id>
      <parentid>728065412</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-12T14:33:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Blacklisted Links Found on the Main Page */spelling: necessaryily -&gt; necessarily</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15052">{{WikiProject Aviation|class=B
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; =y
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; =y
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; =y
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; =y
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; =y
|Rotorcraft= yes }}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = y
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = y
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; =y
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; =y
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = y
|Aviation= yes |French= yes}}

== Saudi Arabia sale ==

http://www.defense-aerospace.com/cgi-bin/client/modele.pl?session=dae.16783124.1132671768.Q4MzGMOa9dUAAF6SoX0&amp;modele=jdc_34

''PARIS --- The Saudi government last week agreed to purchase a total of 142 helicopters from France, in a deal that will modernize its military helicopter fleet at a single stroke and that, together with additional contracts to follow, firmly establishes France as the kingdom’s main weapons supplier.  
 
The helicopter contract, due to be signed with France’s Sofresa arms export agency, will cover 64 NH-90 battlefield helicopters; 20 Eurocopter Cougar utility helicopters in Combat Search and Rescue version; 42 Eurocopter Fennec light helicopters; four Panther naval Search and Rescue helicopters; and an initial batch of 12 Tiger attack helicopters. The NH-90s are made by NH Industries, a joint company in which France’s Eurocopter has a 62.5% share, while all other types are produced by Eurocopter.  
 
The contract also includes the provision of weapons, spare parts, training services and support equipment, as well as the construction of several helicopter bases, boosting its total value to well over 7 billion euros, sources say. It is the largest single arms export deal ever signed by France.  
 
The NH-90 order includes 10 naval NFH-90s for the Saudi navy; 42 TTH-90 battlefield helicopters for the Saudi Army and 12 more for the Saudi Arabian National Guard, while the Fennec order comprises 30 helicopters for the Saudi air force and 12 for the national guard. The 12 Tigers will be operated by the Saudi Arabian National Guard, which is to eventually procure a total of 36 or 48.  
 
A separate contract will cover an unspecified number of Airbus A330 aerial tankers, similar to the KC-30 that EADS, the corporate parent of both Airbus and Eurocopter, has offered to the US Air Force. '' 
-- [[User:Adeptitus|Adeptitus]] 18:32, 25 July 2006 (UTC)`

&quot;a joint company in which France’s Eurocopter has a 62.5% share&quot;

What's this? French jingosism?!

The shares of NH-Industries are held by:

Eurocopter 62.5% 
Agusta: 32% 
Fokker: 5.5% 

whereas Eurocopter is a 100% subsidiary of EADS.

Status on the Saudi sale?  The NHI website doesn't mention it.  Sometimes contracts fall through or at least
end up being suspended for a time. MrG [[Special:Contributions/71.208.24.153|71.208.24.153]] ([[User talk:71.208.24.153|talk]]) 01:25, 18 February 2011 (UTC)

==Enforcer==
Is this a variant of the [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/aircraft/mh-90.htm MH-90 Enforcer] or is that another machine?

:The MH-90 Enforcer is the [[USCG]]'s unofficial designation for the [[MD Helicopters MD Explorer]]. It is a completely different aircraft. I noticed that the MH-90 is not mentioned on the MD Explorer page, so I will try to add something on it to that page shortly. Thanks. - [[User:BillCJ|BillCJ]] ([[User talk:BillCJ|talk]]) 14:09, 29 May 2008 (UTC)

==Helibras???==
Someone has entered a claim that the NH90 is manufactured by Helibras as well as NHI.  I cannot find any reference at all to this in the real world - this would only make sense if Brazil were an export customer - they are not.
I am prepared to concede that as a Eurocopter subsidiary they may manufacture some components in the progamme, but until someone can provide a reference for this wild claim I'll place a &quot;citation needed&quot; on the claim and remove it entirely in 24 hours.

[[User:Benjym|Benjym]] ([[User talk:Benjym|talk]]) 14:21, 16 May 2009 (UTC)

:Ive gone ahead and removed it. I looked at the NHI website, and could find no mention of Helibras in a quick scan. - [[User:BillCJ|BillCJ]] ([[User talk:BillCJ|talk]]) 20:32, 16 May 2009 (UTC)

== Primary users ==

What is a primary user? The list seems a bit arbitrary (yes, it contains most of the big users but not for example Saudi. It isn't the founding countries either as Australia is part of it). Should the list be removed or renamed and edited (for example project launch countries)? [[User:Nasula|Nasula]] ([[User talk:Nasula|talk]]) 13:44, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

:Generally, it's the top 4 operators by quantity/amount ordered. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 17:10, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

::The order of listing is quite strange. In the infobox, order  by quantity amount should show France as first, instead of behind Germany and Italy. In the description text, countries are placed in alphabetical order less France which is after Germany and Greece when it should have been before (abcdeFg). I'm correcting both listings[[Special:Contributions/86.66.196.163|86.66.196.163]] ([[User talk:86.66.196.163|talk]]) 18:25, 1 February 2013 (UTC)
::Edit: after verification the Infobox order with Germany first and Italy second looks correct. I let it as it is.[[Special:Contributions/86.66.196.163|86.66.196.163]] ([[User talk:86.66.196.163|talk]]) 18:37, 1 February 2013 (UTC)

== Operators map ==
Hi. Operators map is incorrect. It has the UAE coloured in, when it should have Oman coloured in. [[User:Chwyatt|Chwyatt]] ([[User talk:Chwyatt|talk]]) 12:55, 12 October 2010 (UTC)

==Payload Capability==

Doesn't this seem a little 'inadequate' for a Sea King/ Ch-53G &amp; too large for a Lynx/UH-1D replacement? Since it appears the Deutsche Heer is buying them to replace the ancient Ch-53G &amp; UH-1D &amp; the Deutsche Marine is replacing it's Westland Sea King &amp; Lynx. This is what Europe ends up with when consolidating all it's aerospace into a non-competitive monopoly.[[Special:Contributions/96.238.134.140|96.238.134.140]] ([[User talk:96.238.134.140|talk]]) 10:18, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

== Update on program/ deliveries ==

This article is severely out of date. Is there any news on the NH90 for 2011? The progress on this helicopter is glacially slow.[[Special:Contributions/96.238.128.115|96.238.128.115]] ([[User talk:96.238.128.115|talk]]) 12:52, 7 September 2011 (UTC)
:Seems like it needs an update alright. I don't know the details, but according to this Volkskrant-article a Dutch frigate has just been fitted with the NH-90 helicopter. So the weight problem mentioned on Wikipedia seems to be solved:
http://www.volkskrant.nl/vk/nl/2686/Binnenland/article/detail/3380103/2013/01/20/Hr-Ms-De-Ruyter-op-weg-naar-Somali-euml.dhtml [[User:Arumes|Arumes]] ([[User talk:Arumes|talk]]) 20:55, 20 January 2013 (UTC)
::Not solved, just being lived with. They've taken out the (heavy, expensive) ASW kit on helicopters using the old frigates where weight was a problem. So effectively they've ended up with navalised TTH's for VERTREP and troop-transport (eg anti-piracy), and are keeping their fingers crossed that their old frigates won't have to look for submarines before they are retired. Not ideal, but pragmatic in the circumstances.[[User:Le Deluge|Le Deluge]] ([[User talk:Le Deluge|talk]]) 13:49, 9 April 2013 (UTC)

==Operators==
The operators section is a bit misleading most of the information relates to orders not to actual numbers operated, anybody have a reliable reference to update the list. We should at least label most of them to indicate they are orders. In November 2012 only 128 had been delivered. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 17:55, 26 March 2013 (UTC)

: True. Flight has a directory from early 2013 at {{cite web |last = |first = |coauthors = |title= World Air Forces 2013 |work= Flightglobal Insight |publisher= |date= 2013 |url= http://www.flightglobal.com/airspace/media/reports_pdf/emptys/101015/world-air-forces-2013.pdf |accessdate= }}  I can also check Aviation Week's Aerospace source book from this January. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 18:16, 26 March 2013 (UTC)

:::We should omit the numbers cause they will change time to time (orders bill filled / accidents / write offs) we can't name them all  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/FOX 52|contribs]]) 19:59, 26 March 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::::I'm not a fan of omitting the numbers de facto, we manage to maintain them fine enough on plenty of other aircraft articles. If they're not immediately up-to-this-very-second's-status, but are reliably cited and periodically updated as appropriate, that is all that is necessary as per the practice of other aircraft articles that conduct this practice as a matter of routine. [[User:Kyteto|Kyteto]] ([[User talk:Kyteto|talk]]) 20:07, 26 March 2013 (UTC)

::::Thanks for the comments, if nobody else get round to it I will have a look at the Flighglobal list tomorrow. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 20:11, 26 March 2013 (UTC)

:::: On listing numbers in service: stating the date of the source shows that later losses and/or deliveries are not included. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 20:16, 26 March 2013 (UTC)
::::: Good point, something we rarely but should do. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 20:22, 26 March 2013 (UTC)

== Blacklisted Links Found on the Main Page ==

Cyberbot II has detected that page contains external links that have either been globally or locally blacklisted.
Links tend to be blacklisted because they have a history of being spammed, or are highly innappropriate for Wikipedia.
This, however, doesn't necessarily mean it's spam, or not a good link.
If the link is a good link, you may wish to request whitelisting by going to the [[MediaWiki talk:Spam-whitelist|request page for whitelisting]].
If you feel the link being caught by the blacklist is a false positive, or no longer needed on the blacklist, you may request the regex be removed or altered at the [[MediaWiki talk:Spam-blacklist|blacklist request page]].
If the link is blacklisted globally and you feel the above applies you may request to whitelist it using the before mentioned request page, or request its removal, or alteration, at the [[meta:Talk:Spam Blacklist|request page on meta]].
When requesting whitelisting, be sure to supply the link to be whitelisted and wrap the link in nowiki tags.
The whitelisting process can take its time so once a request has been filled out, you may set the invisible parameter on the tag to true.
Please be aware that the bot will replace removed tags, and will remove misplaced tags regularly.

'''Below is a list of links that were found on the main page:'''

*&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.airforce-technology.com/projects/nh90/&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*:''Triggered by &lt;code&gt;\bairforce-technology\.com\b&lt;/code&gt; on the local blacklist''
*&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.airforce-technology.com/news/news85711.html&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*:''Triggered by &lt;code&gt;\bairforce-technology\.com\b&lt;/code&gt; on the local blacklist''

If you would like me to provide more information on the talk page, contact [[User:Cyberpower678]] and ask him to program me with more info.

From your friendly hard working bot.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Neuropol&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]] [[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:arnprior&quot;&gt;Notify]]&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-6.1ex;color:green;font-family:arnprior&quot;&gt;Online&lt;/sub&gt; 11:28, 3 April 2014 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[NHIndustries NH90]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=686518503 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100226222546/http://www.tagesschau.de:80/inland/hubschrauber110.html to http://www.tagesschau.de/inland/hubschrauber110.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120710032719/http://www.janes.com:80/products/janes/defence-security-report.aspx?ID=1065969205 to http://www.janes.com/products/janes/defence-security-report.aspx?id=1065969205
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20111112203027/http://www.forsvarsmakten.se/sv/Materiel-och-teknik/Flyg/Helikopter-14/ to http://www.forsvarsmakten.se/sv/Materiel-och-teknik/Flyg/Helikopter-14/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 16:36, 19 October 2015 (UTC)

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=203|lastedit=20100302144105|comment=
;Stub
[[User:Born2flie|Born2flie]]: Weak paragraph construction, lacks [[WP:Air]] organization, and the depth of the article do not quite meet Start-class description to me. --00:42, 1 January 2007 (UTC)}}
Substituted at 00:45, 30 April 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[NHIndustries NH90]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=727929149 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20120117175026/http://www.revistatenea.es/revistaatenea/revista/PDF/documentos/Documento_1026.pdf to http://www.revistatenea.es/revistaatenea/revista/PDF/documentos/Documento_1026.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20111112203027/http://www.forsvarsmakten.se/sv/Materiel-och-teknik/Flyg/Helikopter-14/ to http://www.forsvarsmakten.se/sv/Materiel-och-teknik/Flyg/Helikopter-14/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 02:44, 2 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mosrcujkzp34u4wzq1wqzt7dhrw727j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
