<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:190th Fighter Squadron, Blues and Royals friendly fire incident</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>9394104</id>
    <revision>
      <id>715752779</id>
      <parentid>715751655</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-17T19:57:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MarnetteD</username>
        <id>220924</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links modified */ the update was successful</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13942">{{WPMILHIST
|class=B
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|Aviation-task-force=yes
|US-task-force=yes
|British-task-force=yes
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2010-03-28|oldid1=352284904|date2=2011-03-28|oldid2=421093510|date3=2013-03-28|oldid3=547483264}}

==Video still==
Does anyone know how to copy a still from the cockpit video of the incident and then upload it to use as an image in this article?  The still would be copyright-free (despite what The Sun says on their website) because the video was made by the US Government and is, therefore, public domain once released. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] 23:52, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
:Already done. Also made the video available. --&lt;small&gt;[[User:Cool Cat|Cat]] [[User talk:Cool Cat|out]]&lt;/small&gt; 14:24, 10 February 2007 (UTC)
::Take care with this. If the video were modified or processed enough that it would be consider a deriviative work it would be copyrightable and would not be in the public domain unless Sun or whoever owned the deriviative work choose to release it into such. This is the same as the way we license all our content as GFDL even tho some if it was taken from the public domain. People can take the public domain work from us but if they take any of our derivative work, they would have to release it under the GFDL. Note also that outside of the US, the kind of effort required to make it copyrightable remains unclear. The [[Bridgeman Art Library v. Corel Corp.]] suggests unless they've done something fairly major requiring originality, it's unlikely to be copyrightable in the US but in any case, it's always advisable to get it from a source which doesn't claim copyright if at all possible. Remember the public domain isn't GFDL. Deriviatives of work in the public domain doesn't have to stay in the public domain. [[User:Nil Einne|Nil Einne]] 13:28, 12 March 2007 (UTC)
::Actually I've looked into it a bit more and it appears it's a little simpler then that. Only the derivative portion of the work would be considered copyrightable evidently [http://www.photosig.com/go/main/help?name=help/copyright] so this case should be fine in the US (although obviously you should still stick to stuff that doesn't claim copyright) [[User:Nil Einne|Nil Einne]] 13:47, 12 March 2007 (UTC)
:::I would welcome a better quality version of the video but the US military seemingly isn't very cooperative. All SUN did was rencode the video into flash format - which was later converted to a .ogg format by a wikipedian. If you convert a png into a jpg you do not get a new copyright. --&lt;small&gt; [[User:Cool Cat|Cat]]&lt;/small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Cool Cat|chi?]]&lt;/sup&gt; 02:51, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

== Title ==

This is a remarkably clumsy title. Couldn't it be better placed at something like [[March 28th 2003 friendly fire incident]]? [[User:Shimgray|Shimgray]] | [[User talk:Shimgray|talk]] | 18:12, 3 March 2007 (UTC)

:We could just AfD it and be done....[[User:ALR|ALR]] 22:50, 3 March 2007 (UTC)

::It's going to be in the news again in a few days when the British inquest reconvenes.  We'll see what happens to the story after that. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] 08:25, 5 March 2007 (UTC)

:::I still don't think it's all that notable, blue/ blue incidents happen frequently, particularly if one is operating with US forces.  I've been fired on twice by USMC.  It definetly doesn't deserve the half dozen articles it has dedicated to it.
:::[[User:ALR|ALR]] 08:46, 5 March 2007 (UTC)
::::It's not so much the incident itself that is notable, it's the handling of the aftermath of the incident by the U.S. and UK governments that has contributed to it being the size of a story that it has become.  Like I said on the discussion page of a related article, if the U.S. had been more open about the incident investigation, had sent a representative to the inquest to fully explain the results of the investigation, shown the video, and answered questions, and had expressly apologized to Matty Hull's family, then this story probably would have been barely mentioned by the media. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] 10:35, 5 March 2007 (UTC)
:::::Whatever the reasons for it's noteability, it's IMHO largely irrelevant. It's not up to us to decide whether it's fair that something is noteable or whether something should be noteable. What we do know and what is important is that it is noteable. Cla68's story sounds plausible but whether it's that or &quot;Stun&quot; as ALR calls it or whatever it's irrelevant. Besides that, I think ALR is missing the point. The fact that friendly fire incidents involving the US happen so frequently means that there was always probably going to be something like this because they're something the media sees as significant. As with most things, they prefer to concentrate on one case to highlight the issue [[User:Nil Einne|Nil Einne]] 13:20, 12 March 2007 (UTC)

I like using just the date as the title, it's much shorter and still unambiguous. [[User:Night Gyr|Night Gyr]] ([[User talk:Night Gyr|talk]]/[[User:Night Gyr/Over|Oy]]) 22:01, 4 June 2007 (UTC)

::Think about someone searching for the information - are they more likely to know the date or the parties involved? OK title and good article for detail.&lt;small&gt; [[User:Mdw0|Mdw0]] ([[User talk:Mdw0|talk]]) 08:45, 28 July 2009 (UTC) &lt;/small&gt;

== Video ==

As I understand it, the existance of the video was continually denied by the British authorities initially. It was only when the inquest came up that they finally confirmed there was a video. If so, this should be in the article [[User:Nil Einne|Nil Einne]] 13:12, 12 March 2007 (UTC)

== POPOV vs. POPOFF ==

This article seems to use the term POPOV to refer to the fighter pilots, but the British MOD report (linked at the end of the article) uses POPOFF.  Which is correct? [[User:Adw2000|Adw2000]] 15:02, 16 March 2007 (UTC)
:The articles in the British media use &quot;POPOV&quot; while, as you point out, the MOD report says &quot;POPOFF&quot;.  Using either one in the article is probably fine since both are used in the article's sources.  Perhaps a note should be inserted in the article discussing the difference in spelling by the sources. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] 01:14, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

==Opening paragraph==
This really needs a sentnce regarding what happened. We dont know who shot who until well down the page. &lt;small&gt; [[User:Mdw0|Mdw0]] ([[User talk:Mdw0|talk]]) 08:47, 28 July 2009 (UTC) &lt;/small&gt;
:[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=190th_Fighter_Squadron%2C_Blues_and_Royals_friendly_fire_incident&amp;diff=304771708&amp;oldid=304641146 Done].  Nothing personal, but it saves time when you see a problem if you try to fix it yourself first.  Thanks for pointing this out, though. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 23:20, 28 July 2009 (UTC)

::True, but when I saw this I was short on time, and figured by the time I got back to it someone more familiar with the article would have it finished, saving time. &lt;small&gt;[[User:Mdw0|Mdw0]] ([[User talk:Mdw0|talk]]) 01:47, 29 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

== About your Third Opinion request ==

I'm a Third Opinion Wikipedian. I've removed the request for a third opinion from the [[WP:3O|Third Opinion Project]] request list because the guidelines for that project require disputes to be discussed on the talk page before being listed there. Best regards, [[User:TransporterMan|'''&lt;font face=&quot;Trebuchet MS&quot; size=&quot;2&quot; color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;T&lt;font size=&quot;1&quot;&gt;RANSPORTER&lt;/font&gt;M&lt;font size=&quot;1&quot;&gt;AN&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;''']] ([[User talk:TransporterMan#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Trebuchet MS&quot; size=&quot;1&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]) 22:44, 23 February 2011 (UTC)

Alright, one coroner with a history of controversial rulings does not make the &quot;friendly fire&quot; thing appropriate. Unless you have indisputable evidence that those airmen went out gunning for friendly troops (and if you do I'm sure the media would love to hear it), putting friendly fire in quotations implies that the action was intentional homicide, and not friendly fire at all. I'm going to remove the quotes once more, and I'm going to request a third opinion once the guy that keeps putting them back responds. [[Special:Contributions/99.250.244.54|99.250.244.54]] ([[User talk:99.250.244.54|talk]]) 02:47, 9 March 2011 (UTC)
:It could be that the other editor keeps adding the quotation marks simply because the phrase &quot;friendly fire&quot; is a slang term or idiom for this kind of incident. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 04:33, 9 March 2011 (UTC)
::Friendly fire is the recognized term, among others (fratricide, blue-on-blue). Either way, the article here on Wikipedia for the killing of one's own troops (or allied troops) is Friendly Fire. [[Special:Contributions/99.250.244.54|99.250.244.54]] ([[User talk:99.250.244.54|talk]]) 11:05, 9 March 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory?id=2852243&amp;page=2
** In [[Gus Kohntopp]] on 2011-03-22 16:02:41, 404 Not Found
** In [[190th Fighter Squadron]] on 2011-05-25 02:39:36, 404 Not Found
** In [[190th Fighter Squadron]] on 2011-06-02 02:22:42, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 02:25, 2 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 2 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://edition.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/europe/02/06/iraq.video/index.html
** In [[190th Fighter Squadron, Blues and Royals friendly fire incident]] on 2011-05-25 02:39:42, 404 Not Found
** In [[190th Fighter Squadron, Blues and Royals friendly fire incident]] on 2011-06-02 02:25:15, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 02:25, 2 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 3 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.farmhouse.org/p&amp;r/P&amp;R_v100_i3.pdf
** In [[Gus Kohntopp]] on 2011-03-22 16:02:45, 404 Not Found
** In [[190th Fighter Squadron]] on 2011-05-25 02:39:37, 404 Not Found
** In [[190th Fighter Squadron]] on 2011-06-02 02:23:32, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 02:26, 2 June 2011 (UTC)

== Merge proposal ==
{{archive top}}
I think [[Gus Kohntopp]] should be merged into this article. That article seems to be a clear case of [[WP:BLP1E]]: living people 'notable' for a single event. That article has a considerable overlap with this one, as there's not very much to say about Colonel Kohntopp that isn't related to the friendly fire incident. As such, he doesn't need an independent article; a summary of his biography can be incorporated into this one. (Note that the article on the victim, L/CoH [[Matty Hull]], was merged and redirected to this one for the same reasons.) [[User:Robofish|Robofish]] ([[User talk:Robofish|talk]]) 20:44, 23 February 2012 (UTC)
:I agree. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 22:27, 23 February 2012 (UTC)

'''OK, Done'''. This was tagged, discussed [[Talk:Gus Kohntopp#Untitled|and agreed]] in June 2007, but was untagged as ''no consensus'' (!) in August 2008: It has been discussed and agreed again, here. So I've [[WP:BOLD|gone ahead and done it]]. There was nothing to merge (rationale is [[Talk:Gus Kohntopp#Merge|here]]) so I've simply blanked and redirected it. I trust everyone is OK with that. [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 01:22, 15 January 2014 (UTC)
{{archive bottom}}

== THIS PAGE IS A JOKE == 
Really a whole separate page for this incident, just because of the British media hype. You really need to look at the British freindly fire incidents using ground attack aircraft - as well as close range misidentification. [[Special:Contributions/217.16.113.220|217.16.113.220]] ([[User talk:217.16.113.220|talk]]) 06:10, 2 November 2012 (UTC)
:The media hype you refer to has made this a notable incident and it is indeed well known in the UK, so yes, it has it's own page. Other apparent British friendly fire incidents are irrelevant to that end.--[[User:Allthestrongbowintheworld|Allthestrongbowintheworld]] ([[User talk:Allthestrongbowintheworld|talk]]) 21:24, 5 February 2013 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[190th Fighter Squadron, Blues and Royals friendly fire incident]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=715751650 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://edition.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/europe/02/06/iraq.video/index.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:50, 17 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rq0ko7hfzqs1toidbwebx97gg81jxiw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
