<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Israel Defense Forces</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>39238</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748418658</id>
      <parentid>748221588</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-08T02:51:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Brewcrewer</username>
        <id>5452240</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Wrong link */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14776">{{Talk header}}
{{ARBPIA}}

{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=B&lt;!-- B-Class 5-criteria checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;|B1=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;|B2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;|B3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;|B4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;|B5=yes|Middle-Eastern=yes|National=yes}}
{{WikiProject Israel|class=B|importance=Top}}
}}
{{autoarchivingnotice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=90|small=yes|dounreplied=yes}}
&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[User:MiszaBot I]] --&gt;
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{Talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Israel Defense Forces/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== Where is the criticism or controversy section?  Why is so much missing? ==

The Idf is an extremely controversial entity,  I'm shocked that there's no controversy section on this article. 

Further,  the history section seems very whitewashed, with no mention that a founding organization of the Idf (lehi)  was a terrorist organization that intentionally targeted civilians (see &quot;the Stern gang&quot;  for more information).  

I implore that a controversy section be added,  as the Israeli border dispute and Israeli conflict are extremely contentious and controversial topics. 

I'm able to provide Hundreds (perhaps thousands) of respectable  references to back up this claim. ~~Harrisberg
: Have you checked if there's a criticism or controversy section for other military forces? --''[[User:Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font family:Arial;color:green&quot;&gt;brew&lt;/span&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Arial;color:#2E82F4&quot;&gt;crewer&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Brewcrewer|(yada, yada)]]'' 16:08, 6 April 2016 (UTC)

== Absence of a &quot;criticism&quot; section ==

It's obviously a tremendously well written page, with excellent sources for its various paragraphs. I notice however an absence of a &quot;controversies/criticism&quot; section. May I suggest that this oversight be addressed? Something along the lines of &quot;The IDF takes criticism seriously and does its utmost to follow the rules of law&quot; etc etc. [[User:Glen Gormley|Glen Gormley]] ([[User talk:Glen Gormley|talk]]) 21:31, 7 June 2016 (UTC)

:Per [[Wikipedia:Criticism]]: &quot;In most cases separate sections devoted to criticism, controversies, or the like should be avoided in an article because these sections call undue attention to negative viewpoints. Articles should present positive and negative viewpoints from reliable sources fairly, proportionately, and without bias.&quot; Hope that explains why there isn't a criticism section, nor should there be. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 21:48, 7 June 2016 (UTC)
:There is no criticism within the article either. Trying to add counterpoints into this article would be an impossible task. [[User:Sepsis II|Sepsis II]] ([[User talk:Sepsis II|talk]]) 22:38, 7 June 2016 (UTC)

== Video ==

[[File:Channel 2 - Israel Defence Force.webm|thumb|300px|Video clip about the IDF]]
Recently Israel News Company of [[Channel 2 (Israel)]] released a series of free-license videos as a contribution to Wikipedia. One of them was about the [[Israel Defense Forces]]. The film contains no text nor speech (other than the title &quot;'''צה&quot;ל'''&quot;) and mainly shows the various units of the IDF training or maneuvering, and shows some of the weapons, gear and combat vehicles of the IDF. The relevant aspect of the video is clear and central. These footage are clearly neutral and carry no emotional charges. However, it was removed with the explanation &quot;Remove propaganda video&quot; even though I proved that the video is informative, neutral and adheres to the [[WP:NPOV]] policy. The video should be kept in the article because of its informative value. '''[[User:MathKnight|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;ath&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;K&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;night&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  18:09, 10 July 2016 (UTC)
:Those images, that music... all that is missing is a &quot;Join the IDF&quot; caption. A neutral, factual video has a completely different look and feel than this one. You have not proven anything, whether a video comes across as neutral or not is hardly something anyone can prove. The video gives me, as a neutral viewer, not the idea of a neutral, infomative video at all, but looks like an &quot;approved&quot;, official video with nice images and poor music and no information at all (all one knows is that it supposedly is a video of the IDF, but what are we looking at? The same kind of video every army produces, with fake images of &quot;dangerous&quot; actions taken by a camera going backwards in front of the special forces, close-ups of flags, and so on. Not the kind of video we should have on Wikipedia. [[User:Fram|Fram]] ([[User talk:Fram|talk]]) 21:34, 10 July 2016 (UTC)
:: This video was compiled by a news channel - [[Channel 2 (Israel)]] - and not by the IDF. It shows soldiers training, ships sailing, tanks moving and airplanes flying - displaying the units and technology of the IDF. What's not factual in that? The video doesn't deal with history and politics issues, contains no text nor speech. What's not neutral in showing tanks rolling and soldiers during training? It just like presenting moving images of tanks, infantry and warplanes. Are you going to argue that a photo of the Merkava tank is not NPOV? This video presents this aspect of the IDF's activity: training, arsenal, technology. And about the music: it is the standard tune of the Channel 2 News broadcast and not any sort of a military march. I don't think that not liking the music is a valid reason to ban and remove a video. '''[[User:MathKnight|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;ath&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;K&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;night&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  19:16, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
:[[WP:ONUS]]: ''[t]he onus to achieve consensus for inclusion is on those seeking to include disputed content.'' There absolutely should not be edit-warring to restore disputed material, and it very clearly is disputed material. I personally find the video to be non-neutral and promotional. But I also think this article is fairly non-neutral. But regardless, theres a dispute over the video, and if people want to include they need to show there is consensus for it. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 00:34, 11 July 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

::I concur. Further, the user has claimed that the video is &quot;informative&quot;, yet he states, &quot;The video doesn't deal with history and politics issues, contains no text nor speech.&quot; So the video is informative but contains no information as such? - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 19:24, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
::: The video is informative about the aspects of trainings, vehicles and equipment of the IDF. It is a short video, not a full-length documentary. It is like having a short video showing a crocodile swimming and you want to remove it because it doesn't show the crocodile eating. '''[[User:MathKnight|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;ath&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;K&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;night&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  20:13, 11 July 2016 (UTC)

::::I didn't say I wanted to remove it because it wasn't informative. You said it should stay because it's informative, and then showed why it wasn't informative. And no, I wouldn't want to see a crocodile eating. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 21:09, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
::::: You misunderstood my point. A less than 2-minutes video cannot be comprehensive and survey all the possible aspects of a subject. This video shows training and gear of the IDF. It is bad form to disqualify or remove it on the reason that it doesn't deal with history and politics. This video is just showing soldiers training, tanks rolling, jets flying and ships sailing - what's not NPOV in that? '''[[User:MathKnight|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;ath&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;K&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;night&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  22:11, 14 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::I'll agree that the video is propaganda that's missing the &quot;Join the IDF today&quot; frame. [[User:Sepsis II|Sepsis II]] ([[User talk:Sepsis II|talk]]) 23:15, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
::::::This is not a recruitment video. The IDF enlists Israeli citizens by law. '''[[User:MathKnight|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;ath&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;K&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;night&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  19:34, 18 July 2016 (UTC)
::::::Can you describe what in your opinion would a neutral video showing IDF equipment and training look like? —[[User:Ynhockey|Ynhockey]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Ynhockey|Talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 11:19, 12 July 2016 (UTC)

:Just FYI, the music there is the same music that is used as background music in all Channel 2 news reports.
:I'm an Israeli myself, so feel free to think I'm biased, but this feels nowhere near propaganda. It is a news report. A news report by an Israeli TV channel, released under a free license. Is is not government-''sanctioned''—it is from a private commercial TV channel. Is it an Israeli ''perspective''?—yes, it certainly is. More precisely, a perspective of an Israeli private commercial TV channel. Just like a BBC report would be a British perspective and a Palestinian TV report would be a Palestinian perspective. If it's OK to add hyperlinks to Israeli news sources, it's OK to include this video—it's just more directly embedded than an external link.
:Linking to other news sources that provide different perspectives or including (freely-licensed) videos from them would be great as well. --[[User:Amire80|Amir E. Aharoni]] ([[User talk:Amire80|talk]]) 10:38, 12 July 2016 (UTC)

== Minorities ==
Hello . Is it non-Jews or Jewish-related citizens, in the section that concerns minorities . [[User:BatmobileFire|BatmobileFire]] ([[User talk:BatmobileFire|talk]]) 12:04, 15 July 2016 (UTC)
:What do [[User:BatmobileFire|you]] mean by &quot;Jewish-related citizens&quot;? the first and the second sub-sections of the 'minorities' section are about non-Jews. The rest of that section is mostly about Jews. I have never heard the term &quot;Jewish-related citizen&quot;. [[User:Amitayzl|Amitayzl]] ([[User talk:Amitayzl|talk]]) 16:30, 15 July 2016 (UTC)

== The name ==

The full name of the IDF in Hebrew, by the Israeli Basic Law: The Military is '''''צבא הגנה לישראל''''' ('''''Tsva Hagana le-Yisra'el''''') and not צבא '''ה'''הגנה לישראל (Tsva '''ha-'''Hagana le-Yisra'el). In the Hebrew Wikipedia page they had a talk about it, and decided to use the correct name, צבא הגנה לישראל. If someone can edit the page, please do so. 

[[Special:Contributions/85.64.113.49|85.64.113.49]] ([[User talk:85.64.113.49|talk]]) 18:43, 5 August 2016 (UTC)

:Notwithstanding whatever discussion you may have had on he.wiki, according to [http://www.idf.il/ the IDF website], the name is '''צבא &lt;u&gt;ה&lt;/u&gt;הגנה לישראל''' (underlining added for emphasis), as written in the first sentence of this article and shown in the emblem in the infobox. In addition, when I entered your version of the name in Google.co.il, it corrected me—usually (but not always) an indication that mine is the more common version of the name. —&amp;nbsp;[[User:Malik Shabazz|Malik Shabazz]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Malik Shabazz|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Malik Shabazz|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt; 03:47, 6 August 2016 (UTC)

:I would add that, as the IP editor wrote, the he.wiki article is titled '''צבא הגנה לישראל'''. Right after that phrase is bolded in the first sentence is a parenthetical where it says it's best known by the abbreviation '''צה&quot;ל''' or as '''צבא ההגנה לישראל''', followed by this footnote:
::בשנות ה-90 החל צה&quot;ל להשתמש בשם &quot;צבא ההגנה לישראל&quot;, בעקבות המלצת האקדמיה ללשון העברית להשתמש בצורה המיודעת. עם זאת, שם הצבא בחוק יסוד: הצבא לא שונה ונותר &quot;צבא הגנה לישראל&quot;, וגם בחקיקה מאוחרת יותר בנושאי צה&quot;ל השם המלא נותר &quot;צבא הגנה לישראל&quot;.
:An editor with a better understanding of Hebrew may be able to offer a better translation, but the gist of the footnote is that during the 1990s, the IDF began to use the name '''צבא ההגנה לישראל''' [editorial note: as does the en.wiki article] following the recommendation of the [[Academy of the Hebrew Language]], but nevertheless the [[Basic Laws of Israel|Basic Law concerning the Military]] was not changed and continues to refer to '''צבא הגנה לישראל''', as does subsequent relevant legislation [editorial note: and the he.wiki article]. —&amp;nbsp;[[User:Malik Shabazz|Malik Shabazz]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Malik Shabazz|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Malik Shabazz|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt; 04:11, 6 August 2016 (UTC)

::From what I understand, this is the situation. The law says the army is called &quot;Tsva Hagana le-Yisra'el&quot; while in the 90s the IDF decided to use the version &quot;Tsva HaHagana le-Yisra'el&quot; because of a suggestion of the Hebrew Academy. So the official name according to the law is &quot;Tsva Hagana Le-Yisrae'l&quot; (צבא הגנה לישראל) while the official name according to the IDF (and the correct form according to the Hebrew Academy) is &quot;Tsva HaHagana Le-Yisra'el&quot; (צבא ההגנה לישראל).--[[User:Bolter21|'''Bolter21''']] &lt;small&gt;''([[User talk:Bolter21|talk to me]])''&lt;/small&gt; 14:22, 6 August 2016 (UTC)

:::Do you think this issue is worth mentioning, either in a footnote to the Hebrew name in the first sentence or in the &quot;Etymology&quot; section of the article, or is it much ado about nothing? —&amp;nbsp;[[User:Malik Shabazz|Malik Shabazz]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Malik Shabazz|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Malik Shabazz|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt; 16:44, 6 August 2016 (UTC)

== Wrong link ==

&quot;IDF Wordpress Blog – news and updates from the field&quot; - It's linking to Idaho Falls' spokesperson website. Wrong IDF? :) [[Special:Contributions/87.68.49.46|87.68.49.46]] ([[User talk:87.68.49.46|talk]]) 02:04, 7 November 2016 (UTC)
:Fixed. --''[[User:Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font family:Arial;color:green&quot;&gt;brew&lt;/span&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Arial;color:#2E82F4&quot;&gt;crewer&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Brewcrewer|(yada, yada)]]'' 02:51, 8 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>a4ex7xmtt6kjizr62k954v0ygl1dsrh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
