<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Arleigh Burke-class destroyer</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5305139</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748521173</id>
      <parentid>744933744</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-08T16:56:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.7)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33844">{{talk header|search=yes}}
{{WikiProject Ships|class=B |importance=high
|B-Class-1=yes &lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;  |B-Class-2=yes &lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;  
|B-Class-3=yes &lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt; 
|B-Class-4=yes &lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt; 
|B-Class-5=yes &lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt; 
}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=B|B-Class-1=yes |B-Class-2=yes |B-Class-3=yes |B-Class-4=yes |B-Class-5=yes 
|US=yes |Maritime=yes}}

== Removed paragraph on steel construction ...==
Based on this FAQ http://www.hazegray.org/faq/smn6.htm#F7 and another US Navy FAQ (which I can't re-locate) that says the same thing, I have removed the paragraph discusing the use of steel as a construction material due to Falklands experience.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/219.90.136.228|219.90.136.228]] ([[User talk:219.90.136.228|talk]]) 16:53, 21 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: That link supports all the paragraph except for the Falklands War part.  Removing the whole paragraph because of a small inaccurate part is not helpful.  It's been restored with corrected wording. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 22:14, 21 November 2009 (UTC)

::What possibly did the U.S. learn from the RN and the Falklands War that was incorporated in the Arleigh Burkes? There's not one, but two unsupported references to the Falklands in this article - the above reference makes it pretty clear that going all steel had nothing whatsoever to do with the Brits - looks like just some more imaginative editing by the pro-UK Wiki brigade. As for capabilities, can't see where the Brits' experience would be much good either.[[User:Jmdeur|Jmdeur]] ([[User talk:Jmdeur|talk]]) 15:52, 1 January 2010 (UTC)

::: The all-steel construction paragraph was corrected weeks ago.  But the previous paragraph similarly mentioned the RN and Falklands War.  That was either missed then or something.  In any event, that's been fixed too. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 17:03, 1 January 2010 (UTC)

:::: What influence did the Falklands have on ship design, I don't know, maybe 1. The Broadsword/Coventry incident proved the need for VLS, which was incorporated into Ticonderogas from then on (the first few still used obsolete launcher arms). 2. The Sheffield having RADAR and missiles incapable of tracking and engaging sea-skimming targets, with no secondary protection - hence ships needed AEGIS and better missiles and Phalanx for extra protection (something the USS Stark didn't have), not to mention the RADAR cross-section reduction design.
There's 2 things - looks like just some more imaginative editing by the pro-USA Wiki brigade.

::::: I like the line &quot;In July 2010, BAE Systems announced that they had been awarded a contract to modernise 11 ships.&quot;, so it seems that the US Navy needs to employ the Brits' knowledge - &quot;can't see where the Brits' experience would be much good either&quot; doesn't really stand up as a sensible comment when the US Navy learned a LOT from the Falklands, having conducted their own extensive investigation into that conflict.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.194.239.175|90.194.239.175]] ([[User talk:90.194.239.175|talk]]) 21:19, 15 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::::::BAE bought UD who made things like the Mk41 launchers, although BAE's artillery division includes elements from Vickers and others. The US Navy did learn a lot from the Falklands - see [http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf&amp;AD=ADA133333 Lessons of the Falklands] (PDF) - but steel construction was not one of them (see page 60), that decision had already been made after the Bellknap fire and in any case it's not clear that making the T21s of steel would have helped much. VLS was already happening - the early version of Sea Wolf was VLS back in 1968 before the RN ditched it; VLS was already being revived for &quot;new Sea Wolf&quot; in 1982. [[Special:Contributions/82.26.208.252|82.26.208.252]] ([[User talk:82.26.208.252|talk]]) 18:37, 23 October 2011 (UTC)

:::::::1986 BBC ''[[Horizon (BBC TV series)|Horizon]]'' programme &quot;In the Wake of HMS Sheffield&quot; here: [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LqV4YKMMkUk]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/80.7.147.13|80.7.147.13]] ([[User talk:80.7.147.13|talk]]) 09:15, 28 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Harpoon Removal? ==
The article discusses how the latest flight have had their Harpoon launchers removed. Does anyone have any specifics on what the Arleighs are using for ASuW capability now? Does it all rest on the SM-2s? [[User:TheSwordandScales|TheSwordandScales]] ([[User talk:TheSwordandScales|talk]]) 19:52, 7 May 2010 (UTC)
:yes nowadays I think the USNavy hates the Harpoon. Google around and there are sources explaining the removal.[[User:Foxhound66|Other dictionaries are better]] ([[User talk:Foxhound66|talk]]) 20:57, 20 April 2011 (UTC)

== Sentences don't match ==
The Arleigh Burke class are among the most powerful destroyers ever built in the United States.[citation needed] Only the Spruance class destroyers were larger (563 feet)--one is about power the other size[[User:Foxhound66|Other dictionaries are better]] ([[User talk:Foxhound66|talk]]) 20:57, 20 April 2011 (UTC)

== Kevlar ==
These ships are armored

http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ship/ddg-51-flt1.htm

Worth a mention? [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 06:54, 5 September 2011 (UTC)

:It is not armored with Kevlar in the traditional &quot;armored warship&quot; sense. This isn't an armor belt. --[[User:OuroborosCobra|OuroborosCobra]] ([[User talk:OuroborosCobra|talk]]) 09:15, 5 September 2011 (UTC)

::And globalsecurity.org is no longer considered a reliable source, per the discussions [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia_talk:MILHIST#GlobalSecurity.org_and_FAS.org_.E2.80.93_RS_or_not.3F here]. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 09:25, 5 September 2011 (UTC)

Another source:

http://www.public.navy.mil/surfor/ddg90/pages/specs.aspx
In the ARLEIGH BURKE Class, all-steel construction is used. Extensive top-side armor is placed around vital combat systems and machinery spaces. The bulkheads are constructed of steel from the waterline to the pilot house. The bulkheads are designed with double-spaced plate construction for fragment protection. The frontal plate causes fragments to break up and the backup plate stops the fragments from causing further damage to the interior of the ship. Other Aegis combat system equipment rooms are protected by Kevlar shielding. And, topside weight is reduced by incorporating an aluminum mast.

These are about the best armored surface combatants of our times. [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 16:02, 5 September 2011 (UTC)
:There is armor, but that doesn't make them &quot;armored&quot; - splinter protection is pretty common these days, it's not enough to make a big deal of IMHO. They're still pretty puny compared to a Long Beach or a Suffren, and ton for ton a Udaloy is probably better protected.  [[Special:Contributions/82.26.208.252|82.26.208.252]] ([[User talk:82.26.208.252|talk]]) 18:22, 23 October 2011 (UTC)

== DDG-113 — DDG-116 ==
The construction contracts for these hull numbers have recently been [http://www.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=62942 awarded]. [[User:Brad101|Brad]] ([[User talk:Brad101|talk]]) 19:50, 27 September 2011 (UTC)

== Aegis radar ==
[[Aegis radar]] is dumb. There ain't no such thing, and there isn't an article about it in the Wikipedia. The [[Aegis Combat System]] is a very sophisticated combination of computers, radars, missiles, and man-machine interfaces. Get rid of &quot;Aegis radar&quot;.&lt;br&gt;[[Special:Contributions/98.67.108.12|98.67.108.12]] ([[User talk:98.67.108.12|talk]]) 05:10, 28 August 2012 (UTC)

== Multirole destroyers ==
These are multirole destroyers, not multi-role destroyers.&lt;br&gt;
For many decades now &quot;multi'''anything'''&quot; has not been hyphenated, except by people from certain countries who are too dim to catch up, and they aren't Americans. Here are some examples of the use of &quot;multi&quot;:

multibranched, multicolored, multifactored, multimode, multinational, multipurpose, multiracial, multiregional, multisensory, multistage, multistory, multitalented, multitonal, multitudinous,  multivariable, multiverse, multiyear.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.67.108.12|98.67.108.12]] ([[User talk:98.67.108.12|talk]]) 05:24, 28 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Take it up with the US Navy or the defense contractors.  Sources says &quot;multi-&quot;whatever. [http://www.navy.mil/navydata/fact_display.asp?cid=4200&amp;tid=900&amp;ct=4]  Same thing for SPY-3 [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ship/systems/mfr.htm] [http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/The-US-Navys-Dual-Band-Radars-05393/] [http://www.raytheon.com/capabilities/radar/sea/index.html]  [[User:ViriiK|ViriiK]] ([[User talk:ViriiK|talk]]) 05:32, 28 August 2012 (UTC)

::As a rule, [[English grammar]] does not allow compound words to be created, unlike [[German language|German]]. Hence 'multi-role' is correct, as it is two words with no pause between them when spoken, the hyphen indicating this. The same goes for company names such as [[Rolls-Royce]], the hyphen indicating that it is pronounced as one word.

::This is to prevent convoluted words such as thisonewheretheseperatewordsallrunintooneanother, which although often seen in written German, is not acceptable in proper English. This is also why words like 'co-operation' are also properly hyphenated otherwise written 'cooperation' it looks like something to do with [[Cooper (profession)|barrel making]].  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/80.7.147.13|80.7.147.13]] ([[User talk:80.7.147.13|talk]]) 13:26, 28 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Superseded, eh (or huh)? ==

'''Succeeded by''': Zoomwalt-class - '''not'''.
&quot;''What had once been seen as the backbone of the navy's future surface fleet with a planned production run of 32, has since been replaced by destroyer production reverting to the Arleigh Burke class after ordering (a measly) 3 Zumwalters''&quot;
Perhaps the article should revert to superseded by None, and the Zumwalt-class articles updated to read superseded by A. Burkes.

:Agreed. It's esp. true now that they're restarting AB production. Will update the article. -[[User:Oosh|Oosh]] ([[User talk:Oosh|talk]]) 00:15, 14 April 2014 (UTC)

::{{ping|BilCat}}, I believe you're misinterpreting what Succeeded means in this context and draw you attention to [[Template:Infobox_ship_begin/Usage_guide#Infobox_ship_class_overview|Infobox ship class overview]]:
:::'''Class after'''
:::* Used to indicate the succeeding class in cases where there is a direct design or type lineage across classes.
:::* Alternately, used to indicate the ships that have/will replace this class.
::Please describe how the Zumwalt meets either of those clauses? It's as big as a cruiser, vastly different in design, intended to fulfil a role closer to that of a battleship, and is not replacing the AB. -[[User:Oosh|Oosh]] ([[User talk:Oosh|talk]]) 11:09, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
::::* See description in the [http://www.navy.mil/navydata/fact_display.asp?cid=4200&amp;tid=900&amp;ct=4 Navy destroyer fact file], especially the part about the Zumwalt class (DDG 1000) being &quot;next-generation&quot; destroyer and was to replace the DDG 51 until 2008. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 19:30, 2 October 2014 (UTC)

== Blacklisted Links Found on the Main Page ==

Cyberbot II has detected that page contains external links that have either been globally or locally blacklisted.
Links tend to be blacklisted because they have a history of being spammed, or are highly innappropriate for Wikipedia.
This, however, doesn't necessarily mean it's spam, or not a good link.
If the link is a good link, you may wish to request whitelisting by going to the [[MediaWiki talk:Spam-whitelist|request page for whitelisting]].
If you feel the link being caught by the blacklist is a false positive, or no longer needed on the blacklist, you may request the regex be removed or altered at the [[MediaWiki talk:Spam-blacklist|blacklist request page]].
If the link is blacklisted globally and you feel the above applies you may request to whitelist it using the before mentioned request page, or request its removal, or alteration, at the [[meta:Talk:Spam Blacklist|request page on meta]].
When requesting whitelisting, be sure to supply the link to be whitelisted and wrap the link in nowiki tags.
The whitelisting process can take its time so once a request has been filled out, you may set the invisible parameter on the tag to true.
Please be aware that the bot will replace removed tags, and will remove misplaced tags regularly.

'''Below is a list of links that were found on the main page:'''

*&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.naval-technology.com/projects/burke&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*:''Triggered by &lt;code&gt;\bnaval-technology\.com\b&lt;/code&gt; on the local blacklist''

If you would like me to provide more information on the talk page, contact [[User:Cyberpower678]] and ask him to program me with more info.

From your friendly hard working bot.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Neuropol&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]] [[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:arnprior&quot;&gt;Notify]]&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-6.1ex;color:green;font-family:arnprior&quot;&gt;Online&lt;/sub&gt; 11:45, 3 April 2014 (UTC)

{{done|Resolved}} This issue has been resolved, and I have therefore removed the tag, if not already done.  No further action is necessary.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]] [[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;Notify]]&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-5.8ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;Online&lt;/sub&gt; 19:22, 9 April 2014 (UTC)

== Interview on Flight III ==

Lots of detail [http://www.defensemedianetwork.com/stories/an-interview-with-capt-mark-vandroff-ddg-51-program-manager-peo-ships-naval-sea-systems-command/ here] in an interview with the DDG-51 program manager if anyone wants to incorporate it.[[Special:Contributions/86.23.80.112|86.23.80.112]] ([[User talk:86.23.80.112|talk]]) 18:03, 2 October 2014 (UTC)


== Flight IIA landing deck ==
They have a &quot;bubble&quot; like those in aircraft carriers ? thanks  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/190.18.113.211|190.18.113.211]] ([[User talk:190.18.113.211|talk]]) 12:45, 21 January 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== armament ==

Who added that Bullcrap about 1 or 2 127mm lightweight guns? It has a single DP 127mm Mark 45 Mod 4 gun, not 2, I am immediately removing that stupid edit. 

Have a great day
--[[User:Luis Santos24|Luis Santos24]] ([[User talk:Luis Santos24|talk]]) 18:53, 20 July 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Arleigh Burke-class destroyer]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=686128085 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20061102142340/http://armedservices.house.gov/NDAA2007CommiteeReport.pdf to http://armedservices.house.gov/NDAA2007CommiteeReport.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20061025175652/http://armedservices.house.gov/NDAA2007CommiteeReport.pdf to http://armedservices.house.gov/NDAA2007CommiteeReport.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 05:32, 17 October 2015 (UTC)

== Hyphen or en dash? ==

I believe the use of the class name preceding the class makes &quot;''Arleigh Burke''-class&quot; a compound modifier, and per Wikipedia's Manual of Style, it should be hyphenated (as the article name already is). The use of an en dash in &quot;''Arleigh Burke''–class&quot; in the infobox and a few other places is inconsistent with the rest of the article.[[Special:Contributions/180.93.253.88|180.93.253.88]] ([[User talk:180.93.253.88|talk]]) 02:03, 10 November 2015 (UTC)

== Crew size? ==

Word &quot;crew&quot; appears just once in the article, re USS Cole.  What is the nominal size of the crew for normal operations? Shouldn't this be listed in the infobox, as a sort of &quot;basic fact&quot; of what it takes to operate one of these things?  [[Special:Contributions/67.198.37.16|67.198.37.16]] ([[User talk:67.198.37.16|talk]]) 04:32, 17 December 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Arleigh Burke-class destroyer]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707304278 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20130904001234/http://www.dodmedia.osd.mil/Assets/Still/2007/Navy/DN-SD-07-24674.JPEG to http://www.dodmedia.osd.mil/Assets/Still/2007/Navy/DN-SD-07-24674.JPEG

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tl|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=failed}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 02:03, 28 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Arleigh Burke-class destroyer]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=708481093 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20130820182239/http://www.defense.gov//releases/release.aspx?releaseid=16035 to http://www.defense.gov/releases/release.aspx?releaseid=16035

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 21:25, 5 March 2016 (UTC)

== DDG-121 ==

Please see discussion [[User_talk:GDK#DDG-121|here]] regarding the new name for this ship. -  ''[[User: Thewolfchild|&lt;sup&gt;the&lt;/sup&gt;'''&lt;big&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Matisse itc;color:red&quot;&gt;WOLF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/big&gt;'''&lt;small&gt;child&lt;/small&gt;]]'' 19:08, 31 March 2016 (UTC)

== Source for claim on DDG-125? ==
Claims for 124 and 125 to each be &quot;the&quot; first Flight III need better sourcing. For example we've got this:

http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/adding-arleigh-burkes-northrop-grumman-underway-06007/
* both FY 2017 ships (DDG 124-125), will “incorporate Flight III capability,” but not the new radars themselves.

So can we withdraw the claim for now and give the refs time to clarify? [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 14:03, 2 May 2016 (UTC)
:If you want to cite real sources [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Arleigh_Burke-class_destroyer&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=718198834&amp;oldid=718161678 instead of your own personal twitter, which you did not even link to, as you did in your edit summary], then sure. --[[User:OuroborosCobra|OuroborosCobra]] ([[User talk:OuroborosCobra|talk]]) 14:13, 2 May 2016 (UTC)

::I was removing my personal math when a closer check on the sources didn't back it up. If you want to keep the claim that DDG-125 is the first Flight III then please provide a source for this. [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 14:34, 2 May 2016 (UTC)
:::Please respond to what people actually say to you. The issue is you making edits, and citing your own personal twitter as a source. Are you going to respond showing that you know that is not acceptable? --[[User:OuroborosCobra|OuroborosCobra]] ([[User talk:OuroborosCobra|talk]]) 15:04, 2 May 2016 (UTC)

What exactly is the format for a ref that doesn't exist? I adjusted a number by calculation from the existing information listed here then found that it didn't line up. I went on Twitter to ask the author of the referenced article and he reported he didn't know either. At that point I went back and removed the unsupported claim. Twitter isn't the source of information here nor is it a confirmation of the negative. It's simply one of the places I went to search. [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 21:17, 2 May 2016 (UTC)
:You claimed in your edit summary that your twitter was the source. Put what you just said in your edit summary next time (or better yet, don't do personal calculations that are essentially [[WP:SYNTH]]) in the first place). If you come here and just say &quot;look at my twitter&quot; in your edit summary, you will be reverted. You made no mention of all of the rest of this, your own calculations, or anything, and you STILL haven't linked to your twitter for us to see all of this. --[[User:OuroborosCobra|OuroborosCobra]] ([[User talk:OuroborosCobra|talk]]) 22:49, 2 May 2016 (UTC)

Here is the author of the reference on the subject:

https://twitter.com/samlagrone/status/727590869843496963
Sam LaGrone ‏@samlagrone
@henrycobb The additional DDG in 16 complicates the math. Until the NAVSEA puts it out, we're not going to hang a number on it.

So can we withdraw the claim about DDG-125 for now? (DDG-124 and DDG-126 have their own references, but I'm the only person who prematurely fingered DDG-125.) [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 20:14, 3 May 2016 (UTC)
:Had you not synthesized a number not in your source to begin with, this would not be a problem. Yes, you can withdraw the claim, but have you learned anything from this about not making up numbers and not using your own twitter as a cited source for your edits? Can you answer anything asked of you? This circle has been getting danced for YEARS, you never seem to respond to the criticism levied at your editing behavior. Will it take bringing in administrators? --[[User:OuroborosCobra|OuroborosCobra]] ([[User talk:OuroborosCobra|talk]]) 18:06, 9 May 2016 (UTC)
: Suddenly twitter becomes a source (sarcasm)[[User:Cantab1985|Cantab1985]] ([[User talk:Cantab1985|talk]]) 14:13, 18 May 2016 (UTC)

== Incorrect primary mission for SM-3 ==

The SM-3s primary mission is ballistic missile defense(BMD),&lt;ref&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n7wKEQFf5JY&lt;/ref&gt; not anti-aircraft warfare (AAW). SM-2 and SM-6 are the primary Area Air Defense weapons, with the SM-6 supplanting, but not fully replacing the SM-2 in service as it is produced in numbers.&lt;ref&gt;http://breakingdefense.com/2014/08/non-standard-navy-sm-6-kills-cruise-missiles-deep-inland/&lt;/ref&gt; SM-6 is also capable of a secondary Anti Surface Warfare (SUW) mission. &lt;ref&gt;https://news.usni.org/2016/03/07/navy-sinks-former-frigate-uss-reuben-james-in-test-of-new-supersonic-anti-surface-missile&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://breakingdefense.com/2015/08/sm-6-can-now-kill-both-cruise-and-ballistic-missiles/&lt;/ref&gt; 


I propose correcting the article from:


Their AEGIS Combat System differs from a traditional rotating radar that mechanically rotates 360 degrees for each sweep scan of the airspace. Instead, Aegis uses a passive electronically scanned arrays, which allow continual tracking of targets simultaneous with area scans. The system's computer control also allows centralization of the previously separate tracking and targeting functions. The system is also resistant to electronic counter-measures. Their standalone Harpoon anti-ship missile launchers give them an anti-ship capability with a range in excess of 64 nautical miles (119 km; 74 mi).[9] With the retirement of the Tomahawk anti-ship missile variant, only Arleigh Burke-class ships before Flight IIA versions are well-equipped for anti-surface warfare with Harpoon launchers. Others are not, but are loaded with SM-2 missiles in their vertical launch cells capable of an anti-ship mode, though they have limited range and damage potential.[19] &quot;The 5-inch/54 caliber Mark 45 gun, in conjunction with the Mark 34 Gun Weapon System, is an anti-ship weapon which can also be used for close-in air contacts or to support forces ashore with Naval Gun-Fire Support (NGF), with a range of up to 20 miles (32 km) and capable of firing 20 rounds per minute.&quot; The class's RIM-7 Sea Sparrow/RIM-162 ESSM missiles provide point defense against missiles and aircraft while the Standard Missile-3 provides area anti-aircraft defense. Additionally the ship has an electronics warfare suite that provides passive detection and decoy countermeasures.[9]

to 

Their AEGIS Combat System differs from a traditional rotating radar that mechanically rotates 360 degrees for each sweep scan of the airspace. Instead, Aegis uses a passive electronically scanned arrays, which allow continual tracking of targets simultaneous with area scans. The system's computer control also allows centralization of the previously separate tracking and targeting functions. The system is also resistant to electronic counter-measures. Their standalone Harpoon anti-ship missile launchers give them an anti-ship capability with a range in excess of 64 nautical miles (119 km; 74 mi).&lt;ref&gt;https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/ship/ddg-51.htm&lt;/ref&gt; With the retirement of the Tomahawk anti-ship missile variant, only Arleigh Burke-class ships before Flight IIA versions are well-equipped for anti-surface warfare with Harpoon launchers. Others are not, but are loaded with SM-2 missiles in their vertical launch cells capable of an anti-ship mode, though they have limited range and damage potential.&lt;ref&gt;https://news.usni.org/2013/06/06/u-s-navys-next-bid-for-ship-to-ship-combat&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The 5-inch/54 caliber Mark 45 gun, in conjunction with the Mark 34 Gun Weapon System, is an anti-ship weapon which can also be used for close-in air contacts or to support forces ashore with Naval Gun-Fire Support (NGF), with a range of up to 20 miles (32 km) and capable of firing 20 rounds per minute.&quot; The class's RIM-7 Sea Sparrow/RIM-162 ESSM missiles provide point defense against missiles and aircraft while the Standard Missile-2 and 6 provide area anti-aircraft defense and the SM-6 provides over the horizon missile defense.&lt;ref&gt;https://news.usni.org/2016/03/07/navy-sinks-former-frigate-uss-reuben-james-in-test-of-new-supersonic-anti-surface-missile&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://breakingdefense.com/2015/08/sm-6-can-now-kill-both-cruise-and-ballistic-missiles/&lt;/ref&gt; Standard Missile 3 and 6 also provide Ballistic Missile Defense (BMD). Additionally the ship has an electronics warfare suite that provides passive detection and decoy countermeasures.&lt;ref&gt;https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/ship/ddg-51.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
[[User:Calvinstrikesagain|Calvinstrikesagain]] ([[User talk:Calvinstrikesagain|talk]]) 00:16, 11 May 2016 (UTC)

{{Reflist-talk}}

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:4|one external link|4 external links}} on [[Arleigh Burke-class destroyer]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=744887036 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.businessweek.com/ap/financialnews/D9CUFPFO0.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110109012157/http://www.gibbscox.com:80/historyofgibbscox.htm to http://www.gibbscox.com/historyofgibbscox.htm
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://peoships.crane.navy.mil/Modernization/ModDDG51.htm
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://www.navsea.navy.mil/Media/SAS2010/Lyle_DDGRestart.pdf
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to https://opencrs.com/document/RL32109/2012-03-02/?26751
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090124231702/http://www.opencrs.com/document/RL32109 to http://opencrs.com/document/RL32109
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://opencrs.com/document/RL32109/2010-06-14/download/1013/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20150402123343/http://www.navsea.navy.mil/NewsView.aspx?nw=NewsWires&amp;id=518 to http://www.navsea.navy.mil/NewsView.aspx?nw=NewsWires&amp;id=518
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://destroyerhistory.org/arleighburkeclass/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090219202357/http://destroyerhistory.org/ to http://destroyerhistory.org/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 01:48, 18 October 2016 (UTC)

== Article name ==

{{re|DocWatson42}} You recently [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Arleigh_Burke-class_destroyer&amp;diff=744922008&amp;oldid=744921953 renamed] this article from &quot;Arleigh Burke-class destroyer&quot; to &quot;Arleigh Burke–class destroyer&quot; (with an en-dash) with the suggestion that this was done to comply with [[MOS:PUNCT]].  I think the original was correct, ship class names should should use a hyphen. See [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (ships)#Naming_articles_about_ship_classes]].  I reverted your change.  You also changed some of the uses of &quot;Arleigh Burke-class&quot; in the text.  I changed some of them back as well, but I may not have gotten them all. Please feel free to revert my changes if you think I've misinterpreted the guidelines, but all of the other U.S. ship class articles have adopted the style from [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (ships)]]. —[[User:RP88|RP88]]&lt;small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:RP88|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 08:39, 18 October 2016 (UTC)
:{{ping|RP88}} Aw, foo.  I'm sorry—I was not familiar with that specific rule, and was following the general usage of punctuation, in which en dashes are used a &quot;super hyphens&quot; for compound terms.  See, for instance, ''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'', 15th edition, 6.80 &quot;En dashes with compound adjectives&quot;.—[[User:DocWatson42|DocWatson42]] ([[User talk:DocWatson42|talk]]) 09:29, 18 October 2016 (UTC)
::Thanks for the explanation, I am happy to see that we are now on the same page. —[[User:RP88|RP88]]&lt;small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:RP88|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:40, 18 October 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Arleigh Burke-class destroyer]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=748521163 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20140811152641/https://opencrs.com/document/RL33745/ to http://opencrs.com/document/RL33745/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 16:56, 8 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>p0r5frmgret8xzzizyxxagxde9wfhcd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
