<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Cyprus Navy</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20534014</id>
    <revision>
      <id>710712752</id>
      <parentid>710712642</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-18T16:28:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/194.42.141.19|194.42.141.19]] - &quot;/* Natzi flag in Cyprus navy Wiki page */ new section&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8226">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B
&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B1=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B5=yes
|Maritime=yes|National=yes}}
{{WikiProject Cyprus|class=B|importance=}}
{{WikiProject Law Enforcement|class=B}}
}}

== Status of Ships &quot;11&quot; and &quot;12&quot; at Golcuk Naval Museum ==

According to the Golcuk Naval Museum website, pendant numbers 11 and 12 belong to the T1 and T3, which were refloated and sent there in the 70s. 

www.turkishnavy.info/thumbnails.php?album=12

If this is correct, then the statement about two more ships being captured at Boghazi is innaccurate. 

[[User:Copperhead331|Copperhead331]] ([[User talk:Copperhead331|talk]]) 20:15, 3 December 2008 (UTC)

In reality refloating of T-1 and T-3 was impossible. T-3 during the attack was directly hitted by the bomb and after few second exploded (detonation of torpedoes). No one survived except someone S.Maghetos. T-1 was seriously damaged, lost it's control and finally was sunk by its own crew in a 1 or 2 miles off the coast (and there is deep water). Rest of MTBs were sunk by it's own crews at Naval base in Boghazi. I think Greek sources are correct and these two boats are from there. 
Also there is no source indicating real pennant numbers of T-1 and T-3. For example there is a model of T-3 in Piraeus Naval Museum with pennant number &quot;30&quot;, which, I think, is also not correct. Beside this, I have a suspicion that this boats were &quot;numbered&quot; later by Turks and their present pennants are not &quot;original&quot;. For example, before 2007 left boat on display had pennant 12, but now it is 11.

Regards... 

[[User:Rohirrim|Rohirrim]] ([[User talk:Rohirrim|talk]]) 04:04, 5 December 2008 (UTC)

== Cyprus navy R-218 group MMS drawing ==

Dear Copperhead331... Can you please specify source you used to draw Cyprus navy R-218 group MMS... If it is just drawing of German MMS of WWII era then it's not correct for Cypriot one (named '''Dedalos'''). It's known that during it's service in Danish navy some changes were applied to it's architecture. Beside this, '''Dedalos''' (ex Danish '''М-555 Trellenæs''', ex '''MR-236''', ex German '''R-236''') were purchased disarmed. So by 1964 '''Dedalos''' had different look and arms.

Regards...
[[User:Rohirrim|Rohirrim]] ([[User talk:Rohirrim|talk]]) 15:04, 5 December 2008 (UTC)

== Re: Cyprus navy R-218 group MMS drawing ==

Actually, you are correct Rohirrim. I am at fault here and will remove the picture of the boat, as it was sourced from a Russian book and I falsely assumed the architecture and armament would be the same.  I believe I have a black and white low-res picture of the Phaethon, from which I will try to produce a new photoshop image in time. The Cypriot flag should also have been placed over the bridge, rather than aft. 

Many thanks.

[[User:Copperhead331|Copperhead331]] ([[User talk:Copperhead331|talk]]) 20:16, 5 December 2008 (UTC)

== Re: Cyprus navy boats ==
If you know Russian well, then you can read my article on Cyprus navy (unfinished yet) here (http://artofwar.ru/r/ruben_d/cyprusno1.shtml). Beside this, I already have my own drawings of Cypriot PBs (Leventis, T-3 and others) but I wont place them here before official publication of my article. 

Regards...
[[User:Rohirrim|Rohirrim]] ([[User talk:Rohirrim|talk]]) 10:21, 6 December 2008 (UTC)

== Corrections &amp; Add-ons ==
I made all possible corrections and contributions to the article. I think it's left only to place more images... 
Regards...
[[User:Rohirrim|Rohirrim]] ([[User talk:Rohirrim|talk]]) 21:41, 10 December 2008 (UTC)


== Cyprus navy Phaethon &amp; Arion boats ==
Hi Copperhead331! Can you please specify sources you find these rare images of boats?... And thanks alot for your contribution. 

Regards...
[[User:Rohirrim|Rohirrim]] ([[User talk:Rohirrim|talk]]) 15:04, 21 May 2009 (UTC)

==Re: Phaethon and Arion==

Hello Rohirrim. I got the pictures from the Cyprus National Guard official website (link included on picture pages). I asserted fair use for the pictures as they depict historical, but there are many more pictures of the current Cyprus Navy on the English part of the site(Themes&gt;Organisation&gt;Cyprus Navy) 

Hope this helps! 

([[User:Copperhead331|Copperhead331]] ([[User talk:Copperhead331|talk]]) 18:50, 21 May 2009 (UTC))

==Re: Rare images==

Hello Copperhead331. Thanks for link. It helped me alot. I also added two more images in article and a bit reorganize already published ones. By the way, image of Chrysulis Naval base is most interesting one - it proofs existing of Yugoslav made MTB's in Cyprus Navy by 1974 (one of them is visible in the left part of the image, behind the cranes).

Best regards!

([[User:Rohirrim|Rohirrim]] ([[User talk:Rohirrim|talk]]) 15:32, 23 May 2009 (UTC)

== Staff and Operations Directorate? ==

Does anyone know whether or not the Staff and Operations Directorate is part of the '''Command of the Navy Base'''? It seems likely, but I want to be sure. [[Special:Contributions/83.71.98.198|83.71.98.198]] ([[User talk:83.71.98.198|talk]]) 18:50, 15 July 2011 (UTC)

== You do not have a Completely Reliable source. ==

http://maxhnews.com/content/6349

An Israeli consortium has since proposed, via Israel's Government, to completely refurbish and modernise the base for all types of military capability, in a deal that it is also reported to include favourable financing and licensing.

In addition, Israel has offered to supply the Cyprus Navy with two modern warships, capable of far greater operational range and much greater weapons capability than that already offered by existing Cypriot patrol boats. According to reports, the ships are offered for immediate production with a 3200 nautical miles range and 32 knot top speed, a helicopter flight deck capability and three automatic gun armaments with a high rate of fire, as well as missile armaments for surface-air and surface-surface roles
----------------
It is not true the excessive use of maxhnews as a source. This website, they can't be considered objective, as they support an extreme agenda,
their articles are full of bias towards everything have nothing to do with government and civil servants;  So, I recommend stopping the use of this website as a source, or trying to counter-balance it by providing more diversified sources, sympathetic to more progresive  positions, in order for the reader to hear the other side of the story. 

Impossible to rule out, but I haven't seen any reliable sources mentioning it.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.222.233.232|82.222.233.232]] ([[User talk:82.222.233.232|talk]]) 11:30, 19 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Reliable is based on perspective,--[[User:Degen Earthfast|Degen Earthfast]] ([[User talk:Degen Earthfast|talk]]) 23:40, 19 December 2011 (UTC)

An English language source or English translation of the source would be nice for this, the English langauge wikipedia.--[[User:Degen Earthfast|Degen Earthfast]] ([[User talk:Degen Earthfast|talk]]) 23:42, 19 December 2011 (UTC)

== Natzi flag in Cyprus navy Wiki page ==

On the wikipedia page for the Cyprus navy there is a table -  Cyprus Navy vessels
in 1964-1974

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyprus_Navy
The first 3 boats came from Germany but the flag is the Natzi’s flag.
I believe it should be replaced by the German flag.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/194.42.141.19|194.42.141.19]] ([[User talk:194.42.141.19|talk]]) 16:28, 18 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>k4urkxu2qpihjdir1f6a49ey4dex5ws</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
