<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Kim Jong-un</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7418263</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751053605</id>
      <parentid>750932543</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T02:41:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Kim Jong-un/Archive 6]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19647">{{talk header}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|blp=yes|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=yes |class=B |listas=Kim, Jong-Woon 
 |politician-priority=mid |needs-photo=y |politician-work-group=yes
 |military-work-group=yes |military-priority=mid
}}
{{WikiProject Korea|class=B|importance=high|nk=yes}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=B|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Biography=yes|Korean=yes}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=B|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Socialism|class=B|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Terrorism|class=B|importance=low}}
}}
{{ITN talk|29 September|2010}}
{{ITN talk|1 January|2012}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Kim Jong-un/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=2 |units=months }}
{{On this day |date1=2012-01-08|oldid1=470175381|date2=2013-01-08|oldid2=532038756|date3=2014-01-08|oldid3=589786944|date4=2015-01-08|oldid4=641203893}}
{{Image requested|people of North Korea|politicians and government-people|military-people}}
{{American English}}
{{FAQ|collapsed=no}}

== Year of birth ==

This [https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/the-secret-life-of-kim-jong-uns-aunt-who-has-lived-in-the-us-since-1998/2016/05/26/522e4ec8-12d7-11e6-a9b5-bf703a5a7191_story.html?wpmm=1&amp;wpisrc=nl_rainbow Washington Post article] claims his year of birth is 1984. Personally, I trust this source, his aunt, more than Dennis Rodman. [[Special:Contributions/71.198.174.42|71.198.174.42]] ([[User talk:71.198.174.42|talk]]) 11:59, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
*The citation already present indicates 1983, and that is what North Korea apparently publishes as well. Can we find another source indicating 1984? --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 13:35, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
** &quot;apparently&quot;? Do you have an official DPRK source giving a year of birth for Kim? Rodman is more likely to be mistaken than the aunt, who was present during Kim's infancy.[[User:Quelcrime|Quelcrime]] ([[User talk:Quelcrime|talk]]) 14:15, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
*** As far as I know, North Korea has never published Kim's age or the year or date of his birth. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: serif; letter-spacing: 0.1em&quot;&gt;–&amp;nbsp;[[User:Finnusertop|Finnusertop]]&lt;/span&gt; ([[User talk:Finnusertop|talk]] ⋅ [[Special:Contributions/Finnusertop|contribs]]) 14:19, 27 May 2016 (UTC) 
**** I'm not sure if we should trust North Korean sources about years of birth anyway. For example, Soviet sources provide much more credible information about the year, location and circumstances of the birth of [[Kim Jong-il#Birth|Kim Jong-il]] than North Korean sources. --[[User:Stefan2|Stefan2]] ([[User talk:Stefan2|talk]]) 15:42, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
The early life section has long said sources disagree. The lead should reflect the uncertainty in body of the article. [[User:Jonathunder|Jonathunder]] ([[User talk:Jonathunder|talk]]) 13:42, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
*Agreed. Whether or not the aunt is correct or not really isn't the point. Everyone should please remember we are not after truth here. We are after verifiability. See [[Wikipedia:Verifiability, not truth]]. If the best we can do, with secondary sources, is indicate there is uncertainty about his birth year, than that's the best we can do. The aunt's statements don't trump that. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 16:14, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
**Agree that the uncertainty should be mentioned. Most media currently say &quot;1983 or early 1984&quot; but that may change with the statement by his aunt who looked after him as a kid that it was 1984. We should watch for acceptance of this by major sources (SK or US government), and then rapidly change to &quot;probably 1984&quot;. But until then, the quoted source for 1983 should be better than Dennis Rodman's repitition of what he was told, such as, supposedly, AFP reporting a S Korean defence ministry spokesman, which I can't find.[[User:Onanoff|Onanoff]] ([[User talk:Onanoff|talk]]) 16:49, 28 May 2016 (UTC)
**By the way, let's not be afraid to switch to &quot;probably  1984&quot; over the deceptively specific &quot;8 Jan 1983&quot;, if that's where the evidence points. [[User:Onanoff|Onanoff]] ([[User talk:Onanoff|talk]]) 17:27, 28 May 2016 (UTC)
*** Sure, IF. But, the aunt in isolation isn't enough to assert that IS the birth date. Again, verifiability not truth. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 16:19, 29 May 2016 (UTC)

*Agreed. This very woman changed the diapers of the Respected Marshal, so I insist she is reliable. By the way Dennis Rodman could be wrong because Koreans originally count their age from pregnancy. It means when someone is born, becomes 1-year-old already. So it might be the reason of the misunderstanding. Even when Kim Jong Un used to visit the school in Switzerland he was registered under the birth year of 1984. &lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt;(What a fine coincidence.)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt; [[User:Oppashi|Oppashi]] ([[User talk:Oppashi|talk]]) 13:31, 7 June 2016 (UTC)
**Can you produce a cite verifying the claim of registration of birth year at the school in Switzerland? The aunt may or may not be a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] (and your insistence that she is does not make her so). Having a second source helps support it. In isolation, it's not enough to go on to only indicate in the article that 1984 was the birth year. We have to have more. There are multiple sources pointing to 1983, even 1982 as well as 1984. The reality; [http://www.cnn.com/2015/01/07/asia/kim-jong-un-birthday/ we just don't know]. Given that, and that any official source isn't saying, we're left in this state of uncertainty. Therefore, attempting to assert one year over another is wrong. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 14:03, 7 June 2016 (UTC)
:In this report of [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UVXjtIjOsRk EuroNews], the registration card is shown of the three Kims visiting the school. Around 0:57 you can read that:&lt;br&gt;
*Pak Chol (Kim Jong Chol) was born September 25th, 1982
*Pak Houn (Kim Jong Un) was born July 5th, 1984
*Pak Mi Hyang (probably Kim Yo Jong) was born April 28th, 1991&lt;br&gt;
The quality of the video is awful but I hope it helps - we can assume some modification not just around the names but the birth dates too, though. [[User:Oppashi|Oppashi]] ([[User talk:Oppashi|talk]]) 09:59, 8 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;br&gt;
The US sanctions on July 6, 2016 [https://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/sanctions/OFAC-Enforcement/Pages/20160706.aspx?src=ilaw] list his birth year as 1984
:Gleaning a date of birth from a video is what we consider [[WP:OR|original research]], which we do not allow here. [[User:Jonathunder|Jonathunder]] ([[User talk:Jonathunder|talk]]) 18:28, 6 July 2016 (UTC)
::I don't see why citing a video is any different from citing an article.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 13:24, 7 August 2016 (UTC)

== Why don't we use an actual picture of him?  ==

I've noticed this page always uses a sketch instead of a real picture of him. Why is that so?  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/156.212.82.137|156.212.82.137]] ([[User talk:156.212.82.137|talk]]) 15:07, 26 July 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:As Wikipedia is a free content work, we do not allow the use of non-free pictures when free imagery could be obtained, as is the case for nearly all living persons. As Jong-un is still alive and a publicly visible figure, it is possible to get a free photo of him, just none have come about as of yet. So we use a freely general sketch of him until we can get a free photo. --[[User:Masem|M&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;ASEM&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User Talk:Masem|t]]) 15:21, 26 July 2016 (UTC)
:: This article may be dealing with an extrmist but you yourselves seem to be extremists in dealing with your stance on free content. w[[Special:Contributions/195.138.228.54|195.138.228.54]] ([[User talk:195.138.228.54|talk]]) 09:27, 7 August 2016 (UTC)
:::Please see the FAQ above.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 13:21, 7 August 2016 (UTC)
::::Still the old arguments... Many people have tried to explain that it is extremely difficult to obtain a free picture of him (which is the reason why we don't have one here) which would make him eligible to use an image under the fair use rationale. But there are a few users here who have, so far, blocked any initiative to find a solution. --[[User:Maxl|Maxl]] ([[User talk:Maxl|talk]]) 21:20, 2 September 2016 (UTC)
::::* If the people against the use of a non-free image are a &quot;few users&quot; then the people in favor are an even smaller number, as has been proven in both RfCs to date. If your argument in favor of using a non-free image were strong, it would garner more support. It hasn't. I'm very sorry, but that's reality. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 00:58, 3 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::The set of people who read or comment on Wikipedia pages is greater than those who participate in RfCs. That's the reality, and I'm not sorry.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 11:42, 3 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::* RfCs is how we handle disputes such as these. If you don't like how such disputes are handled, please seek to replace the RfC system with something you think would work. Both RfCs were run and handled properly. Nevertheless, if you feel you are right and everyone else is wrong, you are welcome to move to the next step of dispute resolution; [[WP:SEEKHELP]]. Until such time as you either replace the RfC system or figure out someway to overturn the result of two different RfCs, neither of which agreed to allow the use of non-free imagery to depict Kim Jong-un, the status quo is we aren't going to allow a non-free image, regardless of some vague silent majority that may or may not exist. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 15:30, 4 September 2016 (UTC)
{{out|::::::}}
Since we're on this topic again, is there a possibility we could leave the sketch as the image that's displayed, but in the caption add something like &quot;For a photograph of Kim Jong-un, see [https://img.washingtonpost.com/rf/image_908w/2010-2019/Wires/Images/2016-05-11/AP/North_Korea_The_Real_Kim-fbf19.jpg this image].&quot;? That would be a good compromise as it would link to a real image of KJU while respecting Wikipedia rules on non-free content. [[User:Tonystewart14|Tonystewart14]] ([[User talk:Tonystewart14|talk]]) 04:17, 5 September 2016 (UTC)
*First, this is called &quot;deep linking&quot;. Second, apparently under U.S. law, this is considered a usage under fair use law. Therefore, no. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 16:18, 5 September 2016 (UTC)
:*It appears to comply with [[Template:External_media]]. Specifically, the image is available online, it cannot be uploaded to Wikipedia due to copyright and NFCC issues, and from the ad nauseum posts about this topic, meets the third criterion that &quot;readers will expect this type of media in the article&quot;. Per the template page, we could use this until a freely licensed image of him surfaces. [[User:Tonystewart14|Tonystewart14]] ([[User talk:Tonystewart14|talk]]) 16:35, 5 September 2016 (UTC)
::*The template documentation is not policy. Anyway, I'm not a lawyer, but from what I've read such a deep linking constitutes a usage under fair use law. Allowed under law? Yes. Allowed here on this article? No. It's not a question of whether we can technically do it. We can. The issue is the NFCC policy. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 01:47, 6 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Hammersoft is not a lawyer. He's just a judge in the highest court.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 10:07, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
::::: One, I remind you of [[Wikipedia:No personal attacks]] which says &quot;Comment on content, not on the contributor&quot;. Two, I'm no judge here (not that we have judges, though the closest parallel is ArbCom). In fact, I have less privileges on this project than you do. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 13:07, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::Please don't mistake irony for a personal attack. @ Jack: Wouldn't a judge be expected to be impartial? --[[User:Maxl|Maxl]] ([[User talk:Maxl|talk]]) 13:09, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::* Calling me a &quot;judge in the highest court&quot; is commenting on me. Quoting from [[Wikipedia:No personal attacks]], &quot;Comment on content, not on the contributor.&quot; Further meta discussions on what might or might not be a personal attack are pointless. Either restrain yourself to commenting on content and not those with whom you disagree here or expect to have this escalated through dispute resolution. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 13:39, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Not every comment on a person (or, account) is necessarily an attack. Please read beyond the introduction of [[Wikipedia:No personal attacks|the project page cited by you]] to find out what is an attack. --[[User:Maxl|Maxl]] ([[User talk:Maxl|talk]]) 15:16, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::: You have repeatedly insulted people on this talk page in the past. You've repeatedly been pointed to [[WP:NPA]]. I strongly recommend you take that policy to heart. It's not hard. All you have to do is not comment on people. It's quite simple really. Just don't do it. Easy. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 15:32, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::: No I did not. I just occasionally make known that I don't share your opinion. That's all. --[[User:Maxl|Maxl]] ([[User talk:Maxl|talk]]) 14:17, 23 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::* It is frequently the case that people who violated the NPA/CIVIL policies believe they have not. It's a meta discussion that lacks merit. The overarching issue is this; do not comment on people making comments. Instead, comment on content. I strongly recommend you take that policy to heart. It's not hard. All you have to do is not comment on people. It's quite simple really. Just don't do it. Easy. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 17:20, 23 October 2016 (UTC)

== The non-free image and how long we plan to wait ==

So, how long have we been waiting? [[User:Anna Frodesiak|Anna Frodesiak]] ([[User talk:Anna Frodesiak|talk]]) 12:26, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
:We'll keep waiting until he passes away or when a free image becomes available. The Foundation has specifically identified that we are not allowed to use non-free for living persons that have a clear public presence. Just because it is difficult to actually get a free image doesn't mean we can ignore that. --[[User:Masem|M&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;ASEM&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User Talk:Masem|t]]) 14:44, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
::It might be worth considering a link to an image, as I mentioned in the previous section before the discussion went off topic. This should comply with all Wikipedia rules including NFCC and would at least be better than what we have now, until we can find a freely licensed image of him. [[User:Tonystewart14|Tonystewart14]] ([[User talk:Tonystewart14|talk]]) 19:47, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
:::{{u|Tonystewart14}}, not a bad idea. [[User:Anna Frodesiak|Anna Frodesiak]] ([[User talk:Anna Frodesiak|talk]]) 21:03, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
:::: As discussed in the prior section, it's actually a bad idea. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 22:04, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
::{{u|Masem}}, fair enough. I'm just so sick of looking at that drawing. I should really unwatch this page. :) [[User:Anna Frodesiak|Anna Frodesiak]] ([[User talk:Anna Frodesiak|talk]]) 21:03, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
:::Since the last time this was discussed, we've had one major development: dozens of foreign journalists were let in to report the [[7th Congress of the Workers' Party of Korea]] in May when Kim made an appearance. As a result, we now have a considerable number of new copyright holders of photos of Kim. We should contact some of them; it's enough if even one agrees. E.g. here are photos by the Finnish national broadcaster: [http://yle.fi/uutiset/3-8868522 &quot;YLE in North Korea: Our journalist was allowed to see Kim Jong-un&quot;]. These photos no longer have the immediate news value they did back in May, many of these are news instead of photo agencies, and some of them have cooperated with Wikimedia projects before. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: serif; letter-spacing: 0.1em&quot;&gt;–&amp;nbsp;[[User:Finnusertop|Finnusertop]]&lt;/span&gt; ([[User talk:Finnusertop|talk]] ⋅ [[Special:Contributions/Finnusertop|contribs]]) 21:16, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Hi{{u|Finnusertop}}. Yes, yes, yes, yes! Good plan! Point me to email addresses and I'll beg. I can't get facebook here, so if you want to try that fine. Let's bug everyone who has a pic. Cheers. [[User:Anna Frodesiak|Anna Frodesiak]] ([[User talk:Anna Frodesiak|talk]]) 21:32, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::I don't have a list, and I haven't come across a list of foreign journalists accredited to cover the Congress. Your best bet would be to use Google News to find coverage of the Congress and look for photos that are given credit for. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: serif; letter-spacing: 0.1em&quot;&gt;–&amp;nbsp;[[User:Finnusertop|Finnusertop]]&lt;/span&gt; ([[User talk:Finnusertop|talk]] ⋅ [[Special:Contributions/Finnusertop|contribs]]) 21:46, 25 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::One good thing about this thread is we now have an acknowledgement that the defenders of the status quo would NEVER accept a non-free image (while Kim is alive apparently).--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 09:19, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::: ...which, not coincidentally, is the position the Foundation takes. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 13:06, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::: ...which is what you claim. --[[User:Maxl|Maxl]] ([[User talk:Maxl|talk]]) 13:07, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::: I'm [[Foundation:Resolution:Licensing policy|not making it up]]. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 13:36, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::: This is a special case. So this rule doesn't apply. --[[User:Maxl|Maxl]] ([[User talk:Maxl|talk]]) 14:15, 23 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::* As determined in both prior RfCs, this is not a special case like we have for incarcerated for life individuals or known recluses. Therefore, the rule does apply. If you believe it doesn't, you are welcome to start another RfC to see if consensus has changed. It's unlikely it has, but you are welcome to try. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 17:19, 23 October 2016 (UTC)

== Third time... ==

After same topics during July and September ^^, are there any photos now? There are some in the google images, but at least there are photos of him (not like a sketch). Sorry if I'm or we users are impatient, hehe. [[User:Typhoon2013|&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue; font-family:Palatino Linotype&quot;&gt;''Typhoon2013''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Typhoon2013|(talk)]] 05:19, 22 November 2016 (UTC)
:Actually you guys are right. Wikipedia ''should'' contain a picture of Kim Jong-un, but it's hard for anyone to shoot a photo of him and publish it under a free license. [[User:Oppashi|Oppashi]] ([[User talk:Oppashi|talk]]) 09:26, 22 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ijlixy41a5b9dg07vyyr6mup97x4btz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
