<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Arthur Nebe</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1364045</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735372079</id>
      <parentid>726902684</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-20T07:53:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>K.e.coffman</username>
        <id>22615369</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>GA nomination</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26489">{{GA nominee|07:53, 20 August 2016 (UTC)|nominator=[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]])|page=1|subtopic=World history|status=|note=}}
{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=n|class=B|listas=Nebe, Arthur|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Mid|politician-work-group=y|politician-priority=Low}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=B|importance=Mid
&lt;!-- B-Class 5-criteria checklist --&gt;
|B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; =y
|B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; =y
|B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; =y
|B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; =y
|B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; =y}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B
&lt;!-- B-Class 5-criteria checklist --&gt;
|B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; =y
|B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; =y
|B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; =y
|B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; =y
|B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; =y
|Biography=y|German=y|WWI=y|WWII=y}}
}}
{{GOCE|user=Twofingered Typist|date=5 February, 2016}}
{{Translated page|de|Arthur Nebe}}

== Untitled ==
This bio of arthur Nebe looks like it was just taken straight of the pages of the book Fatherland. Shouldn't there be a more definitive source on him, not just a paragraph taken from a book?

----

I've understood that it's a myth that Nebe and others involved in the plot we're hanged with piano wire.
----
The biography of Arthur Nebe is a very difficult one to write. Myth, weak sources to what actually lay behind his decisions and a very contradictionary set of facts. First a well renowned crime fighter within the Weimar democracy, then at a rather late stage (1931) a member of the DNSAP and a blitz-krieg avancement through the system in the Nazi State from 1933. An then again, at the time when everything looked bright for the 3rd. Reich, in the late 30thies he turned against the regime - the same so from 1939-1942 when even more conservative forces within Preussia and Die Wermacht became impressed with the impressive results in France, the early advance in Russia etc. etc.
It is known (sources, please) that he tried to avoid being associated with the Einsatz Gruppen, even before operation Barbarossa, knowing that it would make him responsible for unbelievable crimes against humanity. And that he was persuaded by other anti-hitler associates to take the position (sources please).
In Easterne Europe and Russia it is known that his Einsatz Gruppe did not kill nearly as many as expected and that he exagerated the results in his reports and thereby probably saved thousands of civilians, while being directly responsible for the murder of thousands of others.
It is not the wiki's job to judge: Hero or murder. But when writing this article we can hope that over time some of us will be able to find better sources to cast light onto the history of Arthur Nebe. Was he playing on two horses, was he - from 1938 - only a nazi by name but in reality a trojan horse for the resistance?
I will try to gather better sources and more information and hope to be able to help improving this article. Arthur Nebe is probably a good looking glass to see through if you dont just want a black or white picture of Germany 1933-1945.
--[[User:Carsten Levin|Carsten Levin]] ([[User talk:Carsten Levin|talk]]) 11:53, 29 March 2008 (UTC)

== Criminal Police ==
Criminal Police isn't a very good translation and it would be more correct to use a term like CID or Detective police.([[User:Morcus|Morcus]] ([[User talk:Morcus|talk]]) 17:10, 7 May 2008 (UTC))
:Good point; I edited it a little. [[User:Salmanazar|Salmanazar]] ([[User talk:Salmanazar|talk]]) 16:12, 8 May 2008 (UTC)

== Arthur ==
From German wikipedia (my translation):

:In biographies, for instance in [[Der Spiegel|DER SPIEGEL]], in the writings of his friend [[Hans Bernd Gisevius]], or in research on the holocaust, he is always called Art'''h'''ur (no initial) Nebe.

--[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 14:38, 23 June 2008 (UTC)

::A Google Books search gives 590 results for &quot;Arthur Nebe&quot; and 161 for &quot;Artur Nebe&quot;. Are &quot;Arthur&quot; and &quot;Artur&quot; different names in Germany, is is &quot;Artur&quot; just a variant spelling of &quot;Arthur&quot;? [[User:Salmanazar|Salmanazar]] ([[User talk:Salmanazar|talk]]) 16:30, 23 June 2008 (UTC)
:::He must have had one official name, either &quot;Arthur&quot; or &quot;Artur&quot; (the pronunciation of both name variants is the same in German). --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 13:07, 25 June 2008 (UTC)
::::The only way it could be confirmed would be to see an image of his birth certificate or NSDAP card. But if Gisevius refers to him as &quot;Artur&quot; that would seem a strong indication that &quot;Artur&quot; is correct. [[User:Salmanazar|Salmanazar]] ([[User talk:Salmanazar|talk]]) 11:44, 26 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::Yes, but according to German wiki discussion page, Gisevius wrote &quot;Arthur&quot;, I did not check that myself. --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 08:01, 30 June 2008 (UTC)
::::::I've now checked using Google Books. Gisevius' &quot;To the Bitter End&quot; [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=RRVLAAAAMAAJ&amp;pgis=1] is searchable in &quot;snippet&quot; view, which is enough to confirm &quot;Arthur&quot; rather than &quot;Artur&quot;. The same is true for the original German language version.[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=s2xCAAAAIAAJ]. So, &quot;Arthur&quot; would seem to be correct, and the article should be moved appropriately. [[User:Salmanazar|Salmanazar]] ([[User talk:Salmanazar|talk]]) 10:32, 30 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::::I have redirected to [[Arthur Nebe]]. --[[User:Alex1011|Alex1011]] ([[User talk:Alex1011|talk]]) 09:10, 16 July 2008 (UTC)
::::::::I moved the Talk page to match. [[User:Salmanazar|Salmanazar]] ([[User talk:Salmanazar|talk]]) 14:00, 16 July 2008 (UTC)
Surely usage in interchangeable? 'Arthur' would suggest a more Anglophile spelling, whereas 'Artur' is a more continental, dare I say Germanic, version.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/62.25.109.197|62.25.109.197]] ([[User talk:62.25.109.197|talk]]) 16:20, 23 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Verdict against Nebe had he survived WW2? ==
Assuming Nebe survived the war and was brought to an international tribunal, say along the Nuremberg model, what do contributors think the judgement would have been? Would Nebe's work for the resistance mitigate against his role as head of an Einsatzgruppen?

:Adolf Hitler survived the assassination attempt. More than 45.000 Soviet civilians who were killed by the Einsatzgruppe B under Arthur Nebe's command did not. Still questions? -- [[Special:Contributions/88.64.217.77|88.64.217.77]] ([[User talk:88.64.217.77|talk]]) 17:21, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

Nebe's case is not black and white. Many generals and SS personnel who did not oppose Hitler and who were responsible for war crimes were leniently treated after the war. There is well documented evidence supporting Nebe's role in the resistance, and the fact that the Nazis executed him tends to support the possibility that the Allies may have taken a different view.

== President of Interpol ==
Is it for sure that Nebe was president of Interpol as mentioned in the final frame of this article?? --[[User:Ttzavaras|Ttzavaras]] ([[User talk:Ttzavaras|talk]]) 20:02, 8 August 2012 (UTC)

== Use of source ==
Original statement:

&quot;Foreseeing the crimes in which he would be involved, he tried to escape it by asking for a move to the International Police Commission but is said to have been persuaded by [[Ludwig Beck]] and Hans Oster to accept the appointment, which would place him in a position where he could give them information on what was happening inside the SS and the Gestapo. {{cite book | last = Hoffman | first = Peter | authorlink = | title = German Resistance to Hitler | publisher = [[Harvard University Press]] | year = 2005 | location = | pages = | isbn = 0-674-35086-3}} 

'''''He worked with [[Henning von Tresckow]] and [[Fabian von Schlabrendorff]] to reduce the atrocities committed, and often massaged the numbers reported to his superiors (including one claim that his task force was responsible for more than 45,000 killings)'''''. {{cite book | last = Heer | first = Hannes | authorlink = |author2=Klaus Naumann | title = War Of Extermination: The German Military In World War II | publisher = Berghahn Books | year = 2004 | location = | pages = 129 | isbn = 1-57181-232-6}}&quot;
'''

The ''War of Extermination'', page 129 (used as reference #2 in the paragraph above), chapter &quot;Men of 20th July&quot; by Christian Gerlach, does not characterize 45,000 as a mere claim. Instead, Gerlach says: &quot;von Schlabrendorff claimed that &quot;[he and Tresckow] had convinced themselves [that Nebe] ... invented pretexts for sabotaging Hitler's murderous orders.&quot; According to von Schlabrendorff, von Tresckow personally brought Nebe to the army group [of conspirators]. Nothing was said about the 45,467 murder victims of Einsatzgruppe B by November 1941. ... It was said that Nebe was filing false reports. ...&quot;

In fact, Gerlach provided evidence to discredit the idea that &quot;the high command [of Army Group center] prevented what could be prevented; &quot;the SS&quot; had deceived the officers by filing incomplete reports or none at all; if staff offices protested, the SS threatened them.&quot; Gerlach concludes: &quot;This is, of course, nonsense.&quot; 

'''In summary:''' I believe it was improper to use ''War of Extermination'' to characterize the number of killings as 'claims' and use it in context of supporting the idea of false reports being filed, or that Nebe worked with the conspirators &quot;to reduce the atrocities committed.&quot; The source referenced in the original statement says no such thing.--[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 18:18, 13 November 2015 (UTC)
::I don't have the time to review in detail right now. Why don't you re-write/re-work the parts in question; contrasting what was claimed with the other information, all cited to [[WP:RS]] sources; the problem was that your addition was too redundant as to what was already present. Cheers, [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 19:43, 13 November 2015 (UTC)

:::Thanks for the response. I reworked the area in question and used the source listed appropriately. I also added {{citation needed}} to the statement &quot;He [Nebe] worked with [[Henning von Tresckow]] and [[Fabian von Schlabrendorff]] to reduce the atrocities committed, and often massaged the numbers reported to his superiors.&quot; [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 20:53, 13 November 2015 (UTC)

::::Further to the &quot;reducing authorities committed&quot; - this may have originated from von Schlabrendorff post-WWII. The expanded quote from Gerlach: &quot;Von Schlabrendorff claimed that he and Tresckow had convinced themselves that &quot;under the mask of the SS leader lurked a committed anti-Nazi..., who invented pretexts for sabotaging Hitler's murderous orders. '''We succeeded in saving the lives of many Russians. The Russian population often expressed their thanks to us.'''&quot;&quot;

::::I could replace &quot;He worked with [[Henning von Tresckow]] and [[Fabian von Schlabrendorff]] to reduce the atrocities committed, and often massaged the numbers reported to his superiors&quot; with something along the lines of &quot;Post WWII, von Schlabrendorff claimed: &quot;We [Nebe, Tresckow, Schlabrendorff] succeeded in saving the lives of many Russians. The Russian population often expressed their thanks to us.&quot;&quot; I think this speaks for itself :-).  Thoughts? --[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 21:20, 13 November 2015 (UTC)
:::::I made some copy edits, see what you think. Also check this part I tweaked: &quot;Gerlach does go on to state that...&quot; from part of your addition; I was not 100% sure what you were driving at there. Anyway, look it all over. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 22:47, 13 November 2015 (UTC)

::::::That edit &quot;Gerlach does go on to state that...&quot; changed the meaning to the opposite. Gerlach essentially dispels the notion of protests from the army; &quot;we prevented what could be prevented&quot;; &quot;SS deceived the officers&quot;,  etc. Now it reads as the opposite. This is more about post-war recollections of Army Group Center staff, rather than Nebe. But I believe it provided the context for the Schlabrendorff quote. If this is confusing, I can edit to clarify or remove it. --[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 23:03, 13 November 2015 (UTC)
:::::::Please edit it for clarity or remove. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 23:06, 13 November 2015 (UTC)
::::::::I made the edit to highlight that it provides context to von Schlabrendorff's quote [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 23:25, 13 November 2015 (UTC)
:::::::::Better indeed. Also see the comments I left on your talk page. The article is better but still needs work. Cheers, [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 16:40, 14 November 2015 (UTC)

::::::::::Thanks for your suggestion. I shortened both quotes. Re: more info on Nebe, I will look for additional sources for this activities in the SS. I also want to see the context around Gerald Reitlinger's quote. Given the improper (if not deceptive) use of ''War of Extermination'', I want to make sure this is not &quot;selective quoting&quot;. I'm getting Reitlinger's book, so it may be a week or two. 
::::::::::BTW, I don't have a particular passion for the Nebe subject, but as I was reading the article I said to myself &quot;wait a minute, I have this book and I can't believe my eyes that it's being referenced in this context.&quot;--[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 16:58, 14 November 2015 (UTC)
:::::::::::The article is better than before; many articles, especially the smaller ones, need copy edit work, to say the least. Here it was good you had that one book to check. Also, it is good you will check Reitlinger, per above (although his book is quite dated). No one has time to keep up with them all, so any additional eyes, is welcome. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 18:57, 16 November 2015 (UTC)

Indeed, Reitlinger's reference was another case of misleading quoting. The statement: ''&quot;Nebe is said to have fought against Heydrich's orders and disclosed them to the Oster circle, who had used him as an information post for the past four years. No doubt that is why Heydrich's reports credit Nebe's stewardship with the quite modest score of 46,000 executions as against [[Franz Walter Stahlecker|Stahlecker]]'s 221,000.'' {{cite book | last = Reitlinger| first = Gerald| authorlink = Gerald Reitlinger| title = The SS – Alibi of a Nation 1922–1945| publisher = Viking Press | year = 1957| location = | pages = 182–183| isbn = 0-306-80351-8}} was footnoted to the same self-serving Schlabrendorff source. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 01:36, 17 November 2015 (UTC)
:Good job. I must admit, it is becoming somewhat discouraging, the amount being found (of late) which is mis-quoted works. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 02:10, 17 November 2015 (UTC)

== Hoffmann ==
Original text: 

&quot;Foreseeing the crimes in which he would be involved, he tried to escape it by asking for a move to the International Police Commission but is said to have been persuaded by [[Ludwig Beck]] and Hans Oster to accept the appointment, which would place him in a position where he could give them information on what was happening inside the SS and the Gestapo.&quot; {{cite book | last = Hoffman | first = Peter | authorlink = | title = German Resistance to Hitler | publisher = [[Harvard University Press]] | year = 2005 | location = | pages = | isbn = 0-674-35086-3}}

I will go ahead and remove the Hoffmann reference, as his work does not include Nebe in the index of personalities. Given what happened with the references around Gerlach and Reitlinger (see above section) and that the page is not specified, I assume this is another case of misuse / misrepresentation of reliable sources.

If I'm mistaken in my assumption, please provide page number for Hoffmann's reference. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 00:59, 20 November 2015 (UTC)
:I agree with the removal. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 16:29, 26 November 2015 (UTC)

== Research notes ==
Notes to self: 
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=LGUY_C3UJCYC&amp;pg=PT236&amp;dq=Pfeffer-Wildenbruch&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj0j-vUpL7JAhXFHT4KHQbNAEI4ChDoAQgbMAA#v=onepage&amp;q=nebe&amp;f=false ''Hitler's bandit hunters'']

* Waitman Wade Beorn, ''Marching into darkness'': [https://cdr.lib.unc.edu/indexablecontent/uuid:78921817-8def-4a32-baf4-8eaf2f740592 dissertation]; [http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674725508 book]

== Extensive quoting ==
The article contains extensive quoting in the ''Einsatzgruppe B'' section: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;....The idea of the gas van originated with SS-''[[Brigadeführer]]'' Artur Nebe [sic], commander of ''Einsatzgruppe B'', which operated in territories close to the central front and which had carried out in Belorussia large-scale shooting actions of Jews, communists, and other &quot;asocial elements&quot;.  Nebe...was familiar with [[Action T4|the euthanasia program]] and killing by gas.

In September 1941, ''Einsatzgruppe B'' was faced with the task of liquidating the patients of the lunatic asylums in the cities of [[Minsk]] and [[Mogilev]]. Nebe decided to find a simpler way for his men to kill the mentally diseased, other than by shooting them.  He contacted Kripo headquarters and asked for their help in carrying out the killing of the insane with either explosives or poison gas. Dr. Widmann of the Criminal Police was sent to Nebe in Minsk, but before he left, Dr. Widmann discussed with the director of the Criminal Police Technological Institute, [[Walter Heess|Dr. Heess]], ways of using the [[carbon monoxide]] gas from automobile exhaust for killing operations in the East, based on the experience gained from the euthanasia program.  Dr. Widmann took to Minsk 400 [[kg]]s of explosive material and the metal pipes required for the gassing installations.

Nebe and Dr. Widmann carried out an experimental killing using explosives.  Twenty-five mentally ill people were locked into two bunkers in a forest outside Minsk.  The first explosion killed only some of them, and it took much time and trouble until the second explosion killed the rest.  Explosives therefore were unsatisfactory.

A few days later an experiment with poison gas was carried out by Nebe and Dr. Widmann in Mogilev.  In the local lunatic asylum, a room with twenty to thirty of the insane was closed hermetically, and two pipes were driven into the wall.  A car was parked outside, and one of the metal pipes that Dr. Widmann had brought connected the exhaust of the car to the pipe in the wall.  The car engine was turned on and the carbon monoxide began seeping into the room.  After eight minutes, the people in the room were still alive.  A second car was connected to the other pipe in the wall.  The two cars were operated simultaneously, and a few minutes later all those in the room were dead.

After these experimental executions, Nebe came up with the idea of constructing a car with a hermetically sealed cabin for killing purposes.  The carbon monoxide from the car's exhaust would be channeled into the sealed cabin, in which the victims stood.  Nebe discussed the technical aspects of the idea with Dr. Heess and together they brought the proposal before [[Heydrich]], who adopted it.{{sfn|Arad|1987|pp=10-11}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;
{{reflist-talk}}

What should be done about this? I do believe some 'blockquote' treatment is appropriate, since the gas van is perhaps what Nebe is 'best known' for. But some of it can perhaps be converted to a narrative. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 00:41, 24 December 2015 (UTC)
:Try to re-write in a narrative where you can. I agree, I would keep the one as to history of use of the infamous gas vans. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 00:46, 24 December 2015 (UTC)

== Confused by 2 articles ==
[[Einsatzkommando]] is linked to from this article (with it's subsection on [[Einsatzkommando#Einsatzgruppe_B | Einsatzgruppe B]]). While there's also the [[Einsatzgruppen]] article - shouldn't Einsatzgruppe B be part of the Einsatzgruppen article? At first glance, the two articles seem to be covering the same ground, although from somewhat different perspectives and using different sources. 

Here's the passage that directs to Einsatzkommando article; it appears that &lt;nowiki&gt;[[Einsatzgruppe B]]&lt;/nowiki&gt; redirects to &lt;nowiki&gt;[[Einsatzkommando]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;:

* In 1941, just prior to [[Operation Barbarossa|Operation ''Barbarossa'']], Nebe volunteered to command ''[[Einsatzgruppe B]]'', a mobile killing unit...

??? [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 04:00, 24 December 2015 (UTC)
:Einsatzkommando was a sub-unit of the larger Einsatzgruppen (task force). 
:You would have the RSHA at the top - then below that the: SD and SiPo command offices, then below that:
*Einsatzgruppen A with Sonderkommando 1a, 1b and Einsatzkommando 1c, 2 and 3
*Einsatzgruppen B with Sonderkommando 7a, 7b, 7c and Einsatzkommando 8 and 9
*Einsatzgruppen C with Sonderkommando 4a, 4b and Einsatzkommando 5, 6 and 1005
*Einsatzgruppen D with Sonderkommando 10a, 10b, 11a, 11b and Einsatzkommando 12.
:The above for the Eastern Front 1941-44.
:Einsatzgruppe B linked to the Einsatzgruppen article. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 04:48, 24 December 2015 (UTC)

== Uncited statement ==
I'd like to submit this for assessment as a MILHIST article - I believe it qualifies, right?

There are two areas that I don't have RS for:

* From 1918–19, he was a member of the Freikorps.

* Following the Nazi seizure of power, Daluege recommended Nebe to the position of Chief Executive of the State Police in April 1933. In October 1933 Nebe was ordered by Rudolf Diels, then head of the Gestapo, to arrange the liquidation of Hitler's rival Gregor Strasser.

Does anyone have sources to confirm this? If not, then I think the first point is fairly minor and can be dropped. On the second one - I'm not sure. I have a feeling that these details may have originated with the account by Gisevius, so I'm a bit skeptical, plus there's no follow up: what happened? Did Nebe do something? [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 03:09, 16 January 2016 (UTC)

:I will go ahead and remove. The statements can be retrieved through the article history, if anyone indeed has the sources. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 06:14, 18 January 2016 (UTC)

== CE ==
Changed some spellings before noticing that it's in American and may have missed some when I changed them back. Used &lt;nowiki&gt;{{quote|&lt;/nowiki&gt; for consistency with sfns, removed synonyms and commentary about historians' comments (I think it's a fact that &quot;he wrote&quot; but not a fact that &quot;he concluded&quot; unless he wrote that he did). ''The results are believed to have reached Himmler.'' is a bit weasel, &quot;He wrote that...&quot; might be better. Feel free to revert anything as desired. Regards [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 10:16, 19 January 2016 (UTC)
:Thanks Ke, I doubt that with the new wording anyone will wonder who is having the insights. Regards [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 09:14, 20 January 2016 (UTC)
::As I stated in my edit summary two RS books state the same thing that it was &quot;believed&quot; or presumed the results were reported by Nebe to Himmler but there is no definitive statement as to it having been done, so that is why I removed it. By the way, the article is shaping up nicely, gentlemen. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 12:52, 20 January 2016 (UTC)
:I see no reason not to report speculation from RS but I was uneasy about the wording, because I wasn't sure whose it was. Regards [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 13:12, 20 January 2016 (UTC)
::It does not add anything in the end and is only speculation; the more important point which followed shortly thereafter as to the conversion/use of [[gas vans]] was shown to have been reported to Heydrich and the RSHA. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 14:43, 20 January 2016 (UTC)

== CE questions ==
This is copy paste from my Talk page:

------

&lt;blockquote&gt; Hello: I have just completed a first editorial pass of the article on [[Arthur Nebe]]. I will do a second pass tomorrow. I wanted to draw your attention to a number of things that I found so far while editing.

In the &quot;Head of Kripo&quot; section, I may have missed it, but what does “SD” at the end of this sentence mean? &quot;At that point, [[Reinhard Heydrich]] was in overall command of the SiPo (Gestapo and Kripo) and the SD.&quot;

Possibly flesh out why Nebe had an “aversion” to Heydrich and Himmler? Did Heydrich report to Himmler? It’s not clear why he would be lunching with both of them.

Did the Nazis really use the term “reservations” (&quot;…to the planned reservations for the Jews and others…&quot;) to refer to what we refer to as concentration camps? I think that the term “reservations” refers solely to Native Americans’ homesteads.

Killing Operations section – “Einsatzgruppe B's activities were also stymied by inefficiencies.” – needs clarification.

New Killing Methods section –  “Nebe discussed the technical aspects of the idea with Dr. Heess…” – who is Dr. Heess??

In the meantime, please let me know if you have any questions or concerns. I'll continue working tomorrow.

Kind regards,&lt;br/&gt;
[[User:Twofingered Typist|Twofingered Typist]] ([[User talk:Twofingered Typist|talk]]) 22:27, 4 February 2016 (UTC)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

----

I will address these issues by editing the article. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 03:53, 5 February 2016 (UTC)

:{{ping|Twofingered Typist}} Thank you for your comments. I've clarified the issues in the article. &quot;Reservations&quot; was indeed the term that the source used so I kept it as is. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 04:15, 5 February 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>bk9s62b2luywpyee2dcn14f1twh8pwe</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
