<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:David Owen Dodd</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>15964539</id>
    <revision>
      <id>583931091</id>
      <parentid>540948023</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-11-30T17:31:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>65.64.177.101</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>checklist</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6264">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=23:44, 27 March 2008 (UTC)
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=196936936

|action2=PR
|action2date=15:11, 18 April 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/David Owen Dodd/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=205131612

|dykdate=26 February 2008
|currentstatus=FGAN
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=C
|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=Low
|listas=Dodd, David Owen}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=C|importance=low|AR=yes|AR-importance=low}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=Start
|&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|Biography-task-force=yes|ACW-task-force=yes}}
}}

== Aristotle reference ==

It's really gotta go. It's just somebody's personal website. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;[[User:NRen2k5|NRen2k5]]&lt;/em&gt;, 00:12, 27 February 2008 (UTC)

:It has been removed and replaced with a reliable source that contains the same information. I suspect the information on the personal website came from there ... they are very similar. [[User:Truthanado|Truthanado]] ([[User talk:Truthanado|talk]]) 00:54, 3 April 2008 (UTC)

==GA failure==
I have had to fail this article at GAN, not because I don't think it has the potential to be a good article.  I just think that what needs to be done to bring it to GA standard will take a while, certainly more than seven days. I would be very pleased to see the article eventually renominated, if the points below can be addressed. 

The main problem I had is that there are so many loose ends that it seems as though only about half of the article has been written. There is a whole lot of stuff missing that we (the readers) needs to know if we are to make proper sense of this story. The following is a list, not necessarily exhaustive, of questions that need attention:-

*What was the nature of the business that Dodd's father sent him to Little Rock for?
:''This has been added to the article''
*Who was Mary Dodge - an old or a new acquaintance? 
:''Unknown ... some info about Dodd and his popularity with girls has been added to the article''
*Why did Dodd visit the Dodge home?
:''This has been added to the article''
*Were the Dodges thought to be implicated, and if so, why were they merely sent to Vermont while Dodd was put on trial for his life?
:''This has been added to the article''
*What defence did Dodd put up at his trial? Did he explain how he came to be carrying messages in morse code about Union troop strengths.  Did he admit they were his and that he'd sent them, or claim they were planted, or what? How did he plead? Was he legally represented?
:''This has been added to the article''
*How, if at all, did Dodd explain the Derringer found on him? Was this held against him, or was it acceptable - there was a war going on, after all.
*What was the significance of the parcel found &quot;between his shirts&quot;?
*What was his family doing while all this was going on? Were they suspects? Was his father, who had sent him to Little Rock in the first place, questioned?  
*Who were the character witnesses that testified for him?

That's enough for the moment. Please let me know if anything is not clear.
[[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 23:44, 27 March 2008 (UTC)

:(This is being posted on the article's talk page as well as on the reviewer's talk page.) As the one who started this article, I appreciate your taking the time to review it. I was flattered that the article was nominated for GA status. I will try to address your questions, although it is difficult to find [[verifiable]] [[source]]s for the level of detail you are asking about. Having been involved in some GA reviews previously, I would be curious how you rate the article using the six criteria in [[Wikipedia:Good article criteria]]. Thanks. [[User:Truthanado|Truthanado]] ([[User talk:Truthanado|talk]]) 00:56, 28 March 2008 (UTC)


: Thank you for your comment, and I apologise for not including the following criteria list in my original review. 
**'''Well-written, etc''': Marginal fail. It's not badly written but the lead is not in accordance with MoS guidelines
**'''Verifiable''': Pass
**'''Breadth of coverage etc''': Fail. This is the main area of concern - as indicated, too much is presently left out of the story.
**'''Neutral''': Pass
**'''Stable''': Pass
**'''Images''': So-so. As you have the only confirmed photograph of Dodd there probably aren't any other specific images you could use, but you could consider brightening the article with some background stuff (Civil War, maps etc?). I wouldn't make this a GA pass-fail issue, though.

So what it amounts to is writing a proper lead, and dealing with the points previously posted in order to provide a more complete story. It may be necessary, where the details asked for are simply not available, to say things like: &quot;The  exact nature of this business is unknown&quot;, or: &quot;The contents of these documents have not been recorded&quot; - these are of course examples, not suggestions.  I imagine, however, that at least some of the key missing details are available somewhere, and will be interested to see how the article develops. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 11:32, 28 March 2008 (UTC)

:I am trying to improve the article by addressing the GA review comments above. As I find and add things, they are added in ''italics'' after the appropriate comment. Everyone is welcome to help with this. Thanks. [[User:Truthanado|Truthanado]] ([[User talk:Truthanado|talk]]) 00:46, 3 April 2008 (UTC)

== Dodge-y age ==

In the intro, it says Mary was 15. Then later on, it says 16. Which is it? [[User:Clarityfiend|Clarityfiend]] ([[User talk:Clarityfiend|talk]]) 14:12, 27 February 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7ry8ue3v0j85viafp3e5pr52gzn196p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
