<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Liège</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>888280</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735829120</id>
      <parentid>735813328</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-23T10:51:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith-264</username>
        <id>925588</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Recent edits */ Comment</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18870">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=B|German=y|WWI=y|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y}}
{{WPBelgium|class=B|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=C|importance=low}}
}}

==No Casualties==

I've found no web site that lists casualties on either side in this important opening battle of the Great War.  Not even Barbara Tuchman's Pulitzer-winning &quot;The Guns of August&quot; contains that material.  Most peculiar.

BT 11-06

==

All right, I'm done for now, I'll finish the article later. It's going to be rather long... ^_^ [[User:Ugen64|ugen64]] 18:07, Aug 9, 2004 (UTC)

:Don't worry, I'll get to it... eventually...

::At least tell me who won the battle!--[[User:Milicz|Milicz]] 00:15, 9 February 2006 (UTC)

== Why is this &quot;not global&quot;? ==

Any idea why this was tagged as &quot;not having a global perspective&quot;?  From my own perspective it seems fine...  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.102.147.50|128.102.147.50]] ([[User talk:128.102.147.50|talk]]) 16:55, 11 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

*Agree with previous comment; the tag doesn't seem relevant - I've removed it; it can of course go back, if we've both missed something here. [[User:Scoop100|Scoop100]] ([[User talk:Scoop100|talk]]) 21:56, 17 April 2008 (UTC)

== Cleanup ==

Started some cleanup, and adding some references.
[[User:MarcoLittel|MarcoLittel]] ([[User talk:MarcoLittel|talk]]) 10:17, 8 August 2009 (UTC)

==Errors about the figures and the beginning of the battle ( humbly )==

[With my bad English]. According to Horne and Kramer who have strongly learned this chapter of [[World War I]], the first German troops attacking Liège were not 59,000 but only 39,000. The first three days of the invasion was a huge disaster for the Brigades (of which the name is right on the page but they had less soldiers, firstly because some soldiers were not comitted in the battle). Five of the six German brigades must withdraw. On 5 August the 34th Brigade lost 1,500 soldiers and 30 officers (wounded or killed I think: a Brigade have  two regiments of 3,500 soldiers).  On 6 August 14th Brigade lost more than an half of all its soldiers. According to Horne and Kramer, between 3,500 and 5,000 German soldiers were killed during this first attack (and others were wounded). So, until 8 August, the attack '''failed'''. It is important to underline that because in order to be successfull the Schlieffen plan must work quickly!!!  The German army must go quickly until France and Paris. But after three, even four days, the German army was not further than its position from the beginning and perhaps back (Horne and Kramer wrote that). For Horne and Kramers the Belgian resistance during the Battle of Liège is one of the main causes of which they named [[German atrocities]] and these atrocities linked to the [[Rape of  Belgium]]. Why? The German army and perhaps also the German government  found this Belgian resistance ''illegal'' or ''illégitime'' because of the neutrality of Belgium (the resistance in itself was helping France but on the other hand Belgium had the right to resist according the Europen treaties of 1839)). It seems actually the  plan Schlieffen really failed because of this resistance of [[Liège]]. It is impossible to read that in French literature about the World War I but I think it is right (even if I am hesitating, the question is very disputed). Which is certain, it is the fact you are able to understand the atrocities in Belgium (and France):  because of this resistance Germany failed.

I have their book only (Horne &amp; Kramer), in French. But it is possible to find some good books in English on the Web or in the libraries. For instance Gerhard Ritter ''The Schlieffen plan: critique of a myth'' (I read  only some passages). This book is interesting because following its author, the Schlieffen plan was the reason why Germany lost the war, on the political and diplomatic plan but perhaps  also on the military plan. It is important also for the [[History of Belgium]] because of the so-called Belgian atrocities, and for the [[History of Wallonia]] because the most of the casualties of these atrocities (also in France and Flanders), were in Wallonia (2/3 I think), Wallonia being the most important territory on the road of the German invasion. I have also ''World War One'' by Priscilla Mary Roberts (one of the authors) ''History and strategy'' by Marc Trachtenberg (Princeton 1991) : [[http://books.google.com/books?id=0glIMk1wLf0C&amp;pg=PA60&amp;dq=Gerhard+Ritter+The+Schlieffen+plan:+critique+of+a+myth&amp;hl=fr&amp;ei=4RhQTPaEB5iUsQbokNWdAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Gerhard%20Ritter%20The%20Schlieffen%20plan%3A%20critique%20of%20a%20myth&amp;f=false]. I have aslo an older book (on the Web), who gvers the same figures fort the number of soldiers in the two regiment of the German Brigades (3,500 soldiers). For the whole German army on 4, 5, 6 and 7 August, there were 39,000 troops. After German army added 60,000 other troops and a many pieces of artillery. Sincerely, [[User:José Fontaine|José Fontaine]] ([[User talk:José Fontaine|talk]]) 12:59, 28 July 2010 (UTC)
:The title of the Horne &amp; Kramer's book is John N. Horne, Alan Kramer. ''German Atrocities, 1914: A History of Denial.'' New Haven: Yale University Press, 2001. 608 S. $40.00 (leinen), ISBN 978-0-300-08975-2. [http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=9779] [[User:José Fontaine|José Fontaine]] ([[User talk:José Fontaine|talk]]) 14:54, 28 July 2010 (UTC)

== CE ==

Added citations from OH, revised the conclusion and centred pic captions, put convert template round metric numbers and tidied some prose (adjective frenzy). Recommend that some of the recent writing more sceptical of the Schlieffen Plan as a blueprint rather than a deployment plan be incorporated (or linked) in the background section.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 14:30, 9 January 2014 (UTC)
:Had another go at CE, removed some repetition, did more convert templating, tried to make level 2 and 3 headers the same as the Antwerp ones and moved several paragraphs which were out of sequence. Will look for more sources to cite the first half of the page tomorrow. Gave Namur a cameo in the subsequent operations section.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 23:11, 9 January 2014 (UTC)
:Found some citations in the Belgian OH and added &lt;nowiki&gt;{{Citation needed|date=January 2014}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; while searching.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 11:31, 10 January 2014 (UTC)
::Found OOB details on a website which seems pretty decent quality but still looking for one about smelly forts. ;O) A fresh pair of eyes cast over the page would help. Regards[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 15:23, 10 January 2014 (UTC)
:The delay of the German advance needs a balancing sentence because at least one source had the railways open before the last fort fell.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 11:23, 11 January 2014 (UTC)

== CE ==

Started copy editing the page using Namur as a model but it needs a lot more than I can do today, revert as desired in the meantime as I've copied it into a sandbox for surgery. [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 18:02, 6 March 2014 (UTC)
:Finished the additions from the GOH but need to integrate the rest of the narrative.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 17:20, 7 March 2014 (UTC)

== German allegations of franc tireur crimes ==

Recent edits suggest that the recounting of German allegations of civilian involvement in military operations have not been sufficiently shown to be allegations. The existing text puts the claims in inverted commas, to show that they are claims rather than facts but this has been challenged. Is it the custom in Belgian writing to use &quot;You've got a big bum&quot; rather than You've got a big bum to demonstrate the recounting of a claim rather than an endorsement of it?[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 18:52, 5 May 2014 (UTC)

== Infobox result ==

There has been some editing about what the infobox should display in as the battle's &quot;result&quot;. I think it might be worth having a discussion here.

Speaking personally, I agree with {{u|Indy beetle}} that &quot;German victory&quot; is not sufficient. I also respect {{u|Keith-264}}'s citing of the template guidance at [[Template:Infobox military conflict]] that the result perimeter &quot;may use one of several standard terms&quot; only. However, as I mentioned, I think &quot;German victory&quot; is actually misleading and we have a duty under [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Infoboxes]] (which, unlike the template instructions, is actually binding) to &quot;[summarize] key features of the page's subject&quot;. Personally, I think that means some mention of the city's role in delaying the German advance which is already enumerated in the article itself. The exact magnitude of the delay is debatable, as Keith says, but mentioning it is far from a [[Wikipedia:Fringe theories|fringe theory]] and therefore reasonable to include.—''[[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]'' ([[User talk:Brigade Piron|talk]]) 10:09, 21 April 2016 (UTC)
:I suggest we go back to See Aftermath Section. That it took time to capture the forts is not disputed by the sources but control of the railways is what mattered to the Germans. In the Analysis section the effect of the Belgian defence of Liege is described. It's not for us to arbitrate between the authors' conclusions.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 10:21, 21 April 2016 (UTC)
::I'll return it to &quot;See Aftermath Section.&quot; I agree that we shouldn't summarize any effect unless we find multiple sources with a definitive conclusion on the effect of the delay. [[User:Indy beetle|Indy beetle]] ([[User talk:Indy beetle|talk]]) 14:41, 21 April 2016 (UTC)
:::With full respect to both of you, the &quot;see aftermath&quot; idea fails to meet ''any'' of the guidelines which were at issue in the first place. Frankly, if we can't summarise the content of the article, we should bin the infobox in its entirety. Is there really any ''doubt'' that the defence actually delayed the German advance (&quot;German advance delayed&quot;, for example, would seem pretty uncontroversial)? {{u|Keith-264}}, I agree with you in principle, but in practice we all choose selectively from [[WP:RS]] content because we have limited space on Wikipedia and so need to make some kind of judgment about what gets included and what doesn't. 
:::My suggestion would be &quot;German victory&quot; with &quot;German advance delayed&quot; as a bullet point underneath AND a footnote to the effect that the magnitude of the delay is disputed by historians.—''[[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]'' ([[User talk:Brigade Piron|talk]]) 16:48, 21 April 2016 (UTC)
::No[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 17:19, 21 April 2016 (UTC)
:::I'm not sure if the phrase &quot;German advance delayed&quot; is quite suitable. I think &quot;Successful Belgian delaying action&quot; would be better, because it conveys the that the Belgians achieved their goal as well, and from what it seems to me reading about this is that the Belgians wanted to delay for as long as possible to buy the French enough time to enter Belgium (which they did, but the French still lost the [[Battle of the Frontiers]]). We could also put bullet for &quot;Strategic result disputed&quot; under that, and make a note with a link to the aftermath, eh? Like {{u|Brigade Piron}}, I think we can eventually change the &quot;See Aftermath&quot; tag, but it works at present. At the moment I'm still looking for sources that discuss the strategic outcome. I've found some books, but anything you guys can do would be nice. And {{u|Keith-264}}, could you please explain your dissent with what Brigade Piron suggested (even if it's what you said before, just to be clear)? [[User:Indy beetle|Indy beetle]] ([[User talk:Indy beetle|talk]]) 21:12, 21 April 2016 (UTC)
::This always happens when tactics, operations and strategy don't coincide but either it goes down as a German victory because it was or See aftermath where the differences between tactical, operational and strategic results are described. The infobox is not the place for a discussion.

{{quotation|result – optional – this parameter may use one of several standard terms: &quot;X victory&quot;, &quot;Decisive X victory&quot; or &quot;Inconclusive&quot;. The choice of term should reflect what the sources say. In cases where the standard terms do not accurately describe the outcome, a link to the section of the article where the result is discussed in detail (such as &quot;See the 'Aftermath' section&quot;) should be used instead of introducing non-standard terms like &quot;marginal&quot; or &quot;tactical&quot; or contradictory statements like &quot;decisive tactical victory but strategic defeat&quot;. It is better to omit this parameter altogether than to engage in speculation about which side won or by how much.}}

Could this be more explicit? [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 21:27, 21 April 2016 (UTC)

::Yes, but then would it confuse the reader to add a bullet point below such a statement that adds a little more information, as per summarizing the info in infoboxes? It's certainly much better than the &quot;tactical X victory&quot; or the like which the guide condemns.  [[User:Indy beetle|Indy beetle]] ([[User talk:Indy beetle|talk]]) 15:31, 22 April 2016 (UTC)
:Which reader? You can have German victory, Belgian victory, inconclusive or what you put earlier, See aftermath section. How have you been getting on looking for RS on the verdict? If you fancy a laugh, look at the reviews for Ten Days in August: The Siege of Liège 1914 [https://www.amazon.co.uk/s/ref=nb_sb_noss?url=search-alias%3Dstripbooks&amp;field-keywords=liege+1914] here. [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 15:41, 22 April 2016 (UTC)

:::{{u|Keith-264}}, I don't believe that the guidance you cite from the template has any binding status like an official WP essay or MOS has. I may be wrong. Either way, I'm really not convinced by the argument that adding a bullet point makes it impossible for the reader to follow. By the way, Hew Strachan supports the delay thesis, even if he plays down its magnitude, which he argues contributed to the collapse of the German strategic plan.—''[[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]'' ([[User talk:Brigade Piron|talk]]) 16:20, 22 April 2016 (UTC)

::Either you follow

{{quote|result – optional – this parameter may use one of several standard terms: &quot;X victory&quot;, &quot;Decisive X victory&quot; or &quot;Inconclusive&quot;. The choice of term should reflect what the sources say. In cases where the standard terms do not accurately describe the outcome, a link to the section of the article where the result is discussed in detail (such as &quot;See the 'Aftermath' section&quot;) should be used instead of introducing non-standard terms like &quot;marginal&quot; or &quot;tactical&quot; or contradictory statements like &quot;decisive tactical victory but strategic defeat&quot;. It is better to omit this parameter altogether than to engage in speculation about which side won or by how much.}}

or you don't but it isn't a matter of opinion. You can have German victory, Belgian victory, inconclusive or See aftermath section.

Strachan wrote &quot;in practice the delay to the German advance was at most a couple of days, as the concentration of the active corps was not completed until 13 August&quot;.

Zuber wrote &quot;...contrary to the legend, the resistance of Liege did not delay the beginning of the German advance by a single day.&quot;

Herwig wrote &quot;Leman's gallant defence of Liege had cost the Germans perhaps two days....&quot;

Foley wrote &quot;...the fortress was eventually neutralised sufficiently to allow the troops of the right wing to pass, creating just a small bump in the road for the advancing Germans.&quot;

Der Weltkrieg &quot;...the fortress of Liege was in German hands - just in time to allow the German army to begin its advance....credit for the rapid success....&quot;

OH 1914 I &quot;.... the German armies were to reach Thionville-Sedan-Mons on the 22nd day of mobilisation - 23 August and were ahead of schedule.&quot;[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 16:36, 22 April 2016 (UTC)


:::Just to note, William R. Griffiths argument is basically the same as Herwig's, that the battle caused a 2 day delay. Also, {{u|Keith-264}}, I have yet to look into &quot;Ten Days in August,&quot; but keep in mind that the bad &quot;reviews&quot; you said it had is actually just a single 2-star rating. So can we please evaluate books by other means? [[User:Indy beetle|Indy beetle]] ([[User talk:Indy beetle|talk]]) 20:47, 22 April 2016 (UTC)
:: I. was. joking. ...Terry is famously stroppy when his judgement is questioned but his descriptions of German army organisation are very good. The review by Japer has him to a T.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 21:18, 22 April 2016 (UTC)

[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]], [[User:Brigade Piron|Brigade Piron]]. I hope no one is too bothered by me bringing the subject up so long after the discussion, but I actually want to revisit this. About the bullet points as a result (non)option. I believe that if we except the &quot;delaying action&quot; theory, then we ''should'' add a bullet that further explains a result of &quot;German victory.&quot; I think this would truly be a beneficial addition to the page, ignoring the rules as per [[WP:BUREAU]]. Thoughts?
:That sort of hair-splitting is what &quot;see Aftermath section&quot; and leaving it blank is for; there's no need for it. That said you might care to look at the ''Territory'' criterion to see if you can use that. [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 08:07, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

'''territory – optional – any changes in territorial control as a result of the conflict[; this should not be used for overly lengthy descriptions of the peace settlement].'''[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 08:11, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

::[[Template:Infobox military operation]] there might be something in adding this under the infobox if you want more details of what was intended and how it went. Regards[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 08:13, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

== Recent edits ==

I've reverted recent edits for a lack of citation but would prefer to discuss them with the new editor 71 to avoid wasting effort. [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 08:09, 23 August 2016 (UTC)
::71 has been kind enough to add the citations, thanks very much; I've altered them to sfn for consistency. Let's hope that Zuber's book is on offer soon at a discount. Regards [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 10:51, 23 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>4jm29219uk1htwljg0eetevati4shtc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
