<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Landing Craft Assault</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>15988772</id>
    <revision>
      <id>706342938</id>
      <parentid>704925411</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-02-22T20:14:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BattyBot</username>
        <id>15996738</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */[[WP:AWB/GF#Talk page general fixes|talk page general fixes]] &amp; other cleanup per [[WP:TPL]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (11926)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15547">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|1=
{{WikiProject Ships|class=B|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B
&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|Maritime=yes|British=yes|Canadian=yes|Indian=yes|WWII=yes}}
{{WikiProject Canada|military=yes}}
}}

==An LCA Picture is Worth?==
Dear fellows, &lt;br /&gt; Thanks for all the formatting help and critique. I know you might all be tempted to jump all over the content – thanks for giving me a bit of time to fine it up. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Here is something: I know that a world of photos is not necessarily a good thing for Wikipedia, but a few really are helpful illustrations in my eye. I have an image (line drawing) from the US Navy &quot;Allied Landing Craft&quot; 1944. Would complement the illustration on the LCVP page.

Also these: &lt;br /&gt;http://www.combinedops.com/DIEPPE/Dieppe_Commandos%20rn%20lst.jpg&lt;br /&gt;great illustration of the troop well&lt;br /&gt;http://www.combinedops.com/COM_PHOTOS/CHFT%20landing%20craft6.jpg&lt;br /&gt;nice illustration of the general lines of the boat&lt;br /&gt;http://www.strijdbewijs.nl/landing/lca1.jpg&lt;br /&gt;This one is a lovely colour photo of LCA from Prins Baudouin? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is a part where I can’t imagine figuring it out for myself. Any techno savvy, copyright understanding help around?[[User:AmesJussellR|AmesJussellR]] ([[User talk:AmesJussellR|talk]]) 02:18, 23 September 2009 (UTC)

:I've found the original source of that last one and since it's usable, I've put it on commons. Here: [[:File:British LCA 1944.jpg]] [[User:Hohum|Hohum]] ([[User talk:Hohum|talk]]) 23:52, 23 September 2009 (UTC)
:Here's the first one [[:File:British LCA commandos.jpg]] 
:The middle one appears to be from a private collection, so it may be difficult getting permission to use it.
:Several more [http://collectionscanada.ca/base-de-donnees/visages/001048-110.01-f.php?interval=20&amp;q5=lca&amp;submit=Soumettre here] that can be put on commons if specific ones are useful 
:The following is also worth a browse: {{Commonscat|Landing craft}} 
:[[User:Hohum|Hohum]] ([[User talk:Hohum|talk]]) 00:21, 24 September 2009 (UTC)

==A Question of Proportion==
Anyone who associates LCA with anything will probably associate them with world war 2. Right now I have all these flags for various Commonwealth countries when they all flew the White Ensign in ww2. I haven't put the French and German flags up because I think of this as mostly a ww2 page. Still, there's no denying LCA served in these navies too. Right? Wrong? Is there a Wiki standard?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thanks everyone for your comments - I haven't done this before a few days ago. I'm glad for some critique.[[User:AmesJussellR|AmesJussellR]] ([[User talk:AmesJussellR|talk]]) 02:18, 23 September 2009 (UTC)

==What? No 10lb. DIHT?==
What does this stand for? '''10''' pound weight of '''D'''=Deformed? '''I'''=? '''HT'''=High Tensile? I have a JD Ladd source identifying this by brand name: Hadfield's Resista 1/4&quot; armour plate.

:I've added this to article - its &quot;D1 Heat Treated&quot; ie a heat treated D1 quality steel.  [[User:GraemeLeggett|GraemeLeggett]] ([[User talk:GraemeLeggett|talk]]) 15:09, 24 September 2009 (UTC)

==Time for some review==
I don't know how to invite review (and wonder whether I should be asking for it). No, I haven't bothered to read any wiki style guides - I've just looked at some other WW2 articles for style cues. Well, any thoughts?[[User:AmesJussellR|AmesJussellR]] ([[User talk:AmesJussellR|talk]]) 20:43, 21 September 2009 (UTC)
:I've requested a reassessment from [[WP:WikiProject Ships]] and [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Requests]] as the article is now clearly above start class. Cheers, {{#if:DerbyCountyinNZ|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:red;color:lime;&quot;&gt;DerbyCountyinNZ&lt;/span&gt;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:lime;&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt;}} &lt;sup&gt; ([[User talk:DerbyCountyinNZ|Talk]] [[Special:Contributions/DerbyCountyinNZ|Contribs]])&lt;/sup&gt; 22:32, 22 September 2009 (UTC)

I am trying to edit on Wikipedia for the first time. I welcome any assistance. I'm not a professional historian or a sailor. I'm lost when it comes to posting images - though there appear to be rather a few appropriate photos out on the web; a Canadian photo pre-Dieppe shows the well with three benches of infantry. I have an image (line drawing) from the US Navy &quot;Allied Landing Craft&quot; 1944 - I'd love to learn how to put it up. I don't know if I'm satisfying the style guide very well. I have some questions: 

I don't know how to get &quot;Royal Indian Navy&quot; in the Class Overview section.

I don't know of any references that put LCA on UTAH on D-Day. Ladd in &quot;Assault from the Sea&quot; says there were 40 LCA transporting US troops - 9 made it to Pointe du Hoc w/2nd Rangers, another 3 or so foundered. 7 for the 116th, same maybe for the 5 Rangers. That's almost 3/4 right there.

I'm confident that LCA were manufactured to be filled at the boat deck and then lowered into the sea. I have seen quotes from veterans saying they went down scramble nets into LCA. Are they perhaps mistaken or were some LCA on D-day in particular loaded while bobbing in the water? Might be true as the boat got heavier as the war went on.

[[Special:Contributions/66.173.190.190|66.173.190.190]] ([[User talk:66.173.190.190|talk]]) 23:28, 17 September 2009 (UTC)amesJussellR

:I've just done a B class MILHIST review. It's almost B class, but not quite. The Lead, Overview, Origins and Design sections need more references, and the Overview and Origins sections wax lyrical and drift from the subject. 
:Not B class related, and not preventing B rating, the current reference style is a rather verbose. &quot;Author year, p. pagenumber&quot; is enough for each reference, the entire title and ISBN each and every time is rather distracting. [[User:Hohum|Hohum]] ([[User talk:Hohum|talk]]) 23:42, 22 September 2009 (UTC)

== German Navy ==

The German Navy received 10 LCA from Britain in 1958 and operated them until 1967 (see [http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amphibische_Gruppe#LCA_.28Landungsboot_Klasse_552.29 German wikipedia]). --[[User:KuK|KuK]] ([[User talk:KuK|talk]]) 15:44, 20 September 2009 (UTC)

&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dear Kuk,
Thank you for the kind assistance. Now you can laugh . . . I have tried to translate the German!! Tell me how bad it is.

Thanks again.

The first amphibious craft of the Navy of the [[Federal Republic of Germany]] were 10 LCA obtained from Britain in October 1958. These boats were regarded as well built by the [[German Navy]], having good timber, and were fitted with a machinegun and carried 25 soldiers. Though well regarded, they were small for the tactical plans of the time and sometime about 1967 they were mustered out. [[Special:Contributions/66.173.190.190|66.173.190.190]] ([[User talk:66.173.190.190|talk]]) 20:00, 20 September 2009 (UTC)amesJussellR

:It needs to be noted that Wikipedia is not self-referencing. The German and English articles on this topic reference each other. These references needs to be removed and either an external reference added or a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{citation needed}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag. Cheers, {{#if:DerbyCountyinNZ|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:red;color:lime;&quot;&gt;DerbyCountyinNZ&lt;/span&gt;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:lime;&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt;}} &lt;sup&gt; ([[User talk:DerbyCountyinNZ|Talk]] [[Special:Contributions/DerbyCountyinNZ|Contribs]])&lt;/sup&gt; 23:01, 22 September 2009 (UTC)

== Osprey Book ==

Osprey Publishing, they of the often obscure subjects and wonderful drawings, has a book out entitled 'Landing Craft, Infantry and Fire Support'. Now, I've no idea if that would be helpful or not, but I thought I'd let you all know. Might be able to find it in a library or something. [[User:Skinny87|Skinny87]] ([[User talk:Skinny87|talk]]) 13:46, 25 September 2009 (UTC)

== Pointe du Hoc LCA ==

Of particular interest to commando enthusiasts and American readers would be the LCA used for Pointe du Hoc. These were from LCA Flotillas 510 and 522. In the early 1980s it was possible to get a couple of images of these craft from the Imperial War Museum - they were coded &quot;MH789&quot; and &quot;MH790.&quot; Also, a BBC programme, the Huw Weldon programme, about D-Day, broadcast 29 May 1984, had some footage. There are three big tackle boxes mounted down either side of the LCA decks and three big mortars down either side behind the corresponding boxes. Any chance of including these images here? They would make lovely additions to the article - probably the most intriguing LCA in American eyes.[[User:AmesJussellR|AmesJussellR]] ([[User talk:AmesJussellR|talk]]) 20:06, 25 September 2009 (UTC)
:The IWM used to have a brilliant online photo collection (google 'IWM Photo Collection') but they've done something to it now; most of the photos either can't be found when they could be before, or when they exist they're blank. You might get lucky though. [[User:Skinny87|Skinny87]] ([[User talk:Skinny87|talk]]) 20:11, 25 September 2009 (UTC)

== LCA line drawing ==

Below is an image from the 1944 USN pamphlet &quot;Allied Landing Craft and Ships&quot;. A photo from the same publication appears on the Wikipedia &quot;LCVP&quot; page. I'm lost as to what copyright restrictions must be satisfied in order to make this part of the LCA article. Does the image need to come from the US Navy itself?  
http://i480.photobucket.com/albums/rr167/amesJussellR/LCA/LCA.jpg


Thanks for any help or suggestions.[[Special:Contributions/66.173.190.190|66.173.190.190]] ([[User talk:66.173.190.190|talk]]) 18:53, 29 September 2009 (UTC)

== Service History ==

I had originally thought of writing a prose description for all (or most) WW2 uses of LCA. I've slowed in this project. It is probably a useful subject to include. I was also beginning to toy with the idea of just linking to the operations already extant on the Wikipedia. This would seem to be the only place where very specific descriptions of LCA on operations would fit though. Any thoughts?

I'd also like to get the line drawing for the LCA from the 1944 USN publication included in this article. Wikimedia remains a mystery to me.

== Over detail on service ==

the fine detail of their use belongs on the relevant article eg the Blue Beach etc on [[Dieppe Raid]]. What does belong here is an indication of numbers used, how they were used and lessons learnt from the action. [[User:GraemeLeggett|GraemeLeggett]] ([[User talk:GraemeLeggett|talk]]) 12:27, 21 July 2010 (UTC)

== Way too much OT detail ==

This article is clearly created by an enthusiast for British WW II amphibious and commando operations. Unfortunately this enthusiasm has led to inclusion of a great deal of OT detail, especially in the operational history section. In many parts, it becomes a general history of various British amphib/commando ops.

This detail belongs in the articles for these operations, except that which specifically applies to usage of the LCA. Even then it should be summarized, except for events which specifically affected design and usage practice.

Also (a style point): &quot;LCA&quot; is a ''designation'', not an abbreviation, even though the letters match. It is a word in itself, not a representation of other words. Thus it is pluralized like any other word. It is pronounced by saying the letters, but that is true of other designations which are not initialisms, such as &quot;PBY&quot;, &quot;DUKW&quot;, or &quot;CV&quot;. (I can't think of a British example, but landing craft designations were common across the Allies.)

Besides which, omitting the plural because &quot;craft&quot; is both singular and plural is pedantic. One wouldn't write &quot;LSsI&quot; or &quot;LCsT&quot;.

So I have changed this throughout the article.

Also, since it is pronounced by saying the letters, it should be preceded with &quot;an&quot;, not &quot;a&quot;. I've never seen anyone say &quot;''a'' aR-Ay-eF base&quot;, or &quot;''a'' eL-aR-Dee-Gee truck&quot;.

That too has been changed.

[[User:rrostrom|Rich Rostrom]] ([[User_talk:Rrostrom|Talk]]) 20:16, 11 August 2011 (UTC)
:All good points.  Thanks.  [[User:Shem1805|Shem]] ([[User talk:Shem1805|talk]]) 18:33, 10 May 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Landing Craft Assault]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=699600235 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20010706183629/http://www.dstan.mod.uk:80/data/02/706/00000100.pdf to http://www.dstan.mod.uk/data/02/706/00000100.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20110716062142/http://www.thedropzone.org/europe/Sicily/harris.htm to http://www.thedropzone.org/europe/Sicily/harris.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20091031005638/http://www.hostpage.co.uk:80/persimmon/index.htm to http://www.hostpage.co.uk/persimmon/index.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 08:50, 13 January 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:4|one external link|4 external links}} on [[Landing Craft Assault]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=704925405 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20091007163404/http://www.royalmarinesmuseum.co.uk:80/museumresearch/PDFs/Royal%20Marines%20&amp;%20Landing%20Craft.pdf to http://www.royalmarinesmuseum.co.uk/museumresearch/PDFs/Royal%20Marines%20&amp;%20Landing%20Craft.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20091001170327/http://www.thedropzone.org:80/scrapbook/stern4.html to http://www.thedropzone.org/scrapbook/stern4.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20110706173010/http://www.cliffchadderton.ca/blog/?p=44 to http://www.cliffchadderton.ca/blog/?p=44
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20100527043821/http://members.multimania.co.uk:80/Indochine/cefeo/boats.html to http://members.multimania.co.uk/Indochine/cefeo/boats.html#LCA

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 13:12, 14 February 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>61bspj9pq4bjnb5eza2an17eswz6m8d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
