<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Charles Robert Jenkins</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1216610</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751368329</id>
      <parentid>748868722</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-25T05:55:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Brad101</username>
        <id>1347855</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>assess</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7880">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|blp=y|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=y|class=b|listas=Jenkins, Charles Robert|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Low}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=b|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Korea|class=b|importance=Low|nk=y}}
{{WikiProject Japan|class=b
|b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; =y
|b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; =y
|b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; =y
|b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; =y
|b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; =y
|b6 &lt;!--Accessibility          --&gt; =y|importance=Low|bio=y}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=b|B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; =y
|B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; =y
|B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; =y
|B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; =y
|B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; =y
|Biography=y|US=y|Cold-War=y}}
}}

== Charles' aged face ==
He's only 65, yet he looks 20-25 years older.

Contrast that with [[Jesse Jackson]], born 1941, who looks like he's still in his 40s!

So why does Charles' face look much older than he is? --[[User:Shultz|Shultz]] 13:05, 4 November 2005 (UTC)

:lol! Living a very hardlife in a thirdworld nation for nearly 40 years would wear you down to. Jesse Jackson's, as much as he is to be admired, can't exactly claim the same circumstances. [[User:Shadowrun|Shadowrun]] 21:42, 23 September 2006 (UTC)

:::Life in North Korea isn't easy. Clean water isn't easy to come by, food is scarce that and his heavy drinking all will age any one.[[User:FLJuJitsu|FLJuJitsu]] 13 September 2007 (UTC)
::::On the contrary, clean water is abundant in North Korea. There is very little industrial pollution because there is very little industry. I have stood on the banks of the Taedong River in the heart of Pyongyang and looked at stones on the bottom of the river. Water is extremely clean! I suggest Jenkins looked so haggard when he first departed North Korea due to years of smoking and drinking. He confessed that in the year immediately prior to departing for Indonesia he spent most of the time drunk on the floor of his quarters. Don’t blame the water -- clean water might be the only thing in North Korea easy to come by.
:::::Clear water is not the same thing as clean water. As Jenkins explained in his book, the river water was often contaminated with human waste, making it undrinkable. In any case, I don't think his appearance has anything to do with the water. Jenkins seems to be haggard because of a combination of biology and hard living&amp;mdash;smoking and drinking in the large quantities he admits to will do that to you. Joe Dresnok, in ''Crossing the Line'', says that when he first met Jenkins, from afar he thought he was an old man, because he looked so wrinkled. But Jenkins was 24 years old! So Jenkins likely had a tendency to wrinkle, anyway. What gets me is how old his wife looks. Japanese people are envied for so often looking younger than their age. They DID have hard living, and that very likely contributed to their aged appearances, and took a toll on their health. Abshier died at age 40 of a heart attack and Parrish died at age 52 after years of kidney problems. Dresnok  has major heart and liver problems, as explained in ''Crossing the Line''. The producer said in an interview that he didn't think he'd live much longer (but he's still alive, and now in his mid-60s). And when Jenkins went to Indonesia, the Japanese doctors were very worried about his health due to &quot;botched&quot; prostate surgery. Jenkins definitely looks better in the videos of him from Japan.[[User:QuizzicalBee|QuizzicalBee]] ([[User talk:QuizzicalBee|talk]]) 14:02, 19 April 2008 (UTC)

== missing stuff ==
60 minutes interviewed him. From [http://drudgereport.com/flash.htm this link] I found out that...

''&quot;They also assigned him a Korean woman, with whom he was supposed to have sex twice a month. &quot;The leaders almost tell her when to do it, and I got in a big fight one time over it,&quot; recalls Jenkins.ÊÊ &quot;I told [the leader], 'It's none of his business if I want sleep with her. She wants to sleep -- we sleep.' 'No -- two times a month'&quot; He says he was severely punished for talking back. &quot;That's the worst beating I ever got -- over that,&quot; he tells Pelley, showing a scar where he says his teeth came through his lower lip.&quot;''

Also:

''&quot;When Jenkins finally stepped outside the North Korean culture after 40 years, he was most surprised to see women in the Army, limits on where you could smoke and black policemen. He had never heard of 60 MINUTES and thought Life magazine would be the place where he would tell his story.&quot;''

Maybe somebody can figure out how to link to that; hopefully Google will cover it soon enough. It was titled:

U.S. ARMY DESERTER DESCRIBES 40 YEARS IN NORTH KOREA HELL
&lt;br/&gt;
Thu Oct 20 2005 14:43:07 ET

This may do:

http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/10/20/60minutes/main959455.shtml

[[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 02:56, 23 October 2005 (UTC)

== How was Dresnok involved in the movie? ==
Dresnok, according to the article, was a fellow American captive.  How is it that he was responsible for post-production dubbing of the propaganda film, ''Nameless Heroes''?  Needs clarity edit. [[User:Sugarbat|Sugarbat]] ([[User talk:Sugarbat|talk]]) 04:59, 8 July 2008 (UTC)
:I saw the documentary about Dresnok; I don't know who originally put this nonsense about Dresnok saying that Jenkins' performance in the movie was atrocious, needed dubbing, etc. Dresnok actually ''praises'' Jenkins' acting in Nameless heroes, even though he does not like the guy ! [[User:Jean-Jacques Georges|Jean-Jacques Georges]] ([[User talk:Jean-Jacques Georges|talk]]) 10:17, 26 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;br /&gt;

== Jenkins' accent ==
Jenkins is described as having a &quot;thick North Carolina accent&quot; (discussing his teaching English to N Koreans). Changed this to read &quot;thick Southern US accent&quot;. This is more accurate (there is no N.Carolina accent; NC has various accents by region) and corresponds more directly to the highlighted link of Southern US English...[[User:Engr105th|Engr105th]] ([[User talk:Engr105th|talk]]) 20:22, 12 December 2011 (UTC)

== Controversial ==
&quot;This interfered with the government's goal of teaching spies English so that they could pass as South Korean, and when the North Koreans realized this, he was fired from that job.[citation needed]&quot;. This is a very controversial and provocative claim, especially with citation. It should be removed or else strongly emphasised that it purely represents what Jenkins himself said. [[User:Bonzostar|Bonzostar]] ([[User talk:Bonzostar|talk]]) 20:00, 22 December 2011 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Charles Robert Jenkins]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=748868716 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070620145941/http://www.dprkstudies.org:80/2007/05/12/kokuhaku-pictures/ to http://www.dprkstudies.org/2007/05/12/kokuhaku-pictures/
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070518113614/http://www.dprkstudies.org:80/2007/05/12/kokuhaku-pictures-2/ to http://www.dprkstudies.org/2007/05/12/kokuhaku-pictures-2/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 21:33, 10 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>j3mfzgeu5hz7jmqy5t6shouxjpiafrp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
