<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Yemeni Civil War (2015–present)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>46229174</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749920738</id>
      <parentid>749920607</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T21:40:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Qrmoo3</username>
        <id>21657500</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Yemen map */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="49945">{{ITN talk|26 March|2015}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Middle-Eastern=yes}}
{{WikiProject Terrorism|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Yemen|class=B|importance=high}}}}

==On which side Yemen's Armed Forces are fighting?==
I have put most of Yemen's Army on the side of the Houthis / Saleh, and I've sourced it well: my source was Mr. &quot;President&quot; Hadi's foreign minister, quoted by Reuters on 01/04/2015, saying:

: &quot;Although the only forces in Aden still loyal to the Saudi-backed Hadi are from local militias, some parts of the army continue to back him elsewhere including the eastern province of Hadramawt and near Marib, he said.&quot;

I also listed army units known to be loyal to Hadi one by one, adding a source for each of those. However, someone with the nick &quot;LightandDark2000&quot; just put Yemen's army then on the side of Mr. Hadi again without giving any source for this, deleting my sources and just saying &quot;That section is for the military strength, not units.&quot; See here:

http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Yemeni_Civil_War_%282015%29&amp;diff=659268951&amp;oldid=659266998

As I'm just a guest here, I don't want to start any &quot;edit war.&quot; However, I would like to review someone with credentials here at this platform the reverse edit by &quot;LightandDark2000&quot; - which was done without any addition of sources, but deleting sources. The key question in substance is here: &quot;On which side Yemen's Armed Forces are fighting?&quot; Or put it in another way: Which parts of Yemen's Armed Forces are with or against whom? I think this question is a crucial one for the whole Yemeni Civil War 2015, isn't it? So I think the answer to this question shall be well sourced. --[[Special:Contributions/84.189.1.143|84.189.1.143]] ([[User talk:84.189.1.143|talk]]) 12:58, 26 April 2015 (UTC)

==Split==
Propose to split the section on [[GCC military intervention in Yemen (2015)]] into a separate article, as this is clearly a notable and differing event.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 05:55, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

*'''Support''' per nom, although I'd prefer the title [[2015 military intervention in Yemen]], to match [[2011 military intervention in Libya]] and avoiding the exclusion of non-GCC nations. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 05:57, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
**Actually, since I really don't anticipate any objections, I'm going to go ahead and spin it off as a stub-class article. Please, add more to it once it's up. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 05:58, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
:::It seems you made the split too early and without an agreement on proper article naming. The result was immediate re-merge request and i guess quite a few of us may challenge your naming of the new article.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 07:45, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
* I '''Support''' the proposal while insist on maintaining the following sentence in this article:
''According to the Saudi news outlet Al Arabiya, Saudi Arabia is contributing 100 warplanes and 150,000 soldiers to the military operation in Yemen. According to Reuters, planes from Egypt, Morocco, Jordan, Sudan, Kuwait, the United Arab Emirates, Qatar and Bahrain are also taking part in the operation. In addition, Egypt, Pakistan, Jordan and Sudan are ready to participate in a ground offensive''--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 06:22, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

::Curious why you think that line needs to remain in this article when it more aptly relates to the military intervention? -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 06:29, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

:::We do not move all of the important information in such cases. There should be something which helps the reader to understand the importance of the issue in the main article and lead him/her to the sub-article. --&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 06:35, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

::::I understand -- I just don't think we need to go into the specifics like that on this article. What about mentioning the other countries that are participating in the operation, without going into detail about a prospective ground offensive or force strength? -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 07:07, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' - the [[Saudi Arabian-led intervention in Yemen]] was split into a separate article.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 06:56, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

==Merge==
It has been proposed to re-merge the [[2015 military intervention in Yemen]] article back into Southern Yemen offensive (2015).[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 07:18, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

*'''Oppose''' per above discussion. The apparent consensus is that these are two discrete operations, with the offensive being a Houthi campaign directed toward Aden and the intervention being a Saudi-led campaign striking targets principally in the vicinity of Sana'a. They are connected, and one has clearly followed onto the other, but they are different. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 07:24, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
::[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]]'s reasoning seems logical to me. [[User:Mhhossein|Mhhossein]] ([[User talk:Mhhossein|talk]]) 15:44, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' - just to clarify the re-merge was proposed by [[user:Gire 3pich2005]]. My position here is neutral.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 07:44, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

*'''Comment''': I just restored the content of this page after it was blanked overnight, about five hours ago, and redirected to the intervention page. Friendly reminder to everyone: don't blank pages without consensus, and if you see a page that has been blanked without consensus, please feel free to fix it. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 14:56, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' I think these are two related issues and agree with [[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]].--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 16:35, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' - no consensus, long overdue.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 06:57, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

==Reactions==
{{ping|Kudzu1}} I noticed that [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Southern_Yemen_offensive_%282015%29&amp;diff=653616018&amp;oldid=653615932 you removed my edit] to this article. Your edit summary was informative but please consider that some parts of the air strikes occured in the southern area hence reactions may be included here. What do you think? [[User:Mhhossein|Mhhossein]] ([[User talk:Mhhossein|talk]]) 15:51, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

:Yeah, I wondered if you might have put the section into the wrong article by mistake. Sorry about that. My thinking is that to keep a relatively bright line between the Houthi ground offensive and the Saudi-led intervention, we should just put reactions to the bombing campaign on that page, but if there were notable outside reactions to the Houthi advance that preceded it, then they would go here. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 17:27, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

==Fighting with Al-Qaede==
{{ping|Kudzu1|Mhhossein}} I think we should make a third column in the template and add [[Al-Qaede]] to it. Please look at this news: ''Today, the fighting centered on the Shabwa Province, in the oil-rich Usaylan region, where al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP) and Ansar al-Sharia hold sway. 38 were killed in fighting between the Houthis and Sunni tribesmen.''[http://news.antiwar.com/2015/03/29/38-killed-as-yemens-houthis-clash-with-tribesmen-in-oil-rich-south/]--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 08:38, 30 March 2015 (UTC)

:I'm going to say let's wait on this. For one, Antiwar.com isn't a very good source. For another, I haven't seen compelling evidence to support the notion that AQAP is a significant faction ''in this offensive'', the goal of which is the fall of Aden and the defeat of Hadi's holdouts. Clashes between AQAP and both the &quot;official&quot; government and the Houthis/Saleh loyalists have been ongoing for literally years, and while I certainly think jihadist groups are taking advantage of the power vacuum, that's best covered on [[al-Qaeda insurgency in Yemen]] and [[Aftermath of the 2014–15 Yemeni coup d'état]] for right now. That ''could'' and very well may change, if this offensive brings the Houthis into a more direct confrontation with AQAP, Ansar al-Sharia, and/or ISIL. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 07:18, 3 April 2015 (UTC)

== Massive overhaul ==

So obviously this article used to look a lot different. But in discussing the matter with [[User:EkoGraf]], we agreed that the conflict has proven durable enough and has had enough impacts across Yemen, not just in the governorates targeted by the southern offensive, that it needed an overarching article. [[WP:RS|Reliable sources]] are increasingly describing this conflict as a &quot;civil war&quot;, albeit one with significant foreign military involvement (there's precedent, e.g. Libya and Syria).

From now on, all casualties associated with fighting or bombing or shelling in Yemen (or across the border into Saudi Arabia, or in the waters of the Bab-el-Mandeb or Gulf of Aden) should be counted here. This article's scope now covers victims of Saudi bombing in Sana'a, Sa'dah, and wherever else, as well as violence between jihadist groups and others throughout Yemen. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 06:57, 9 April 2015 (UTC)
:This &quot;civil war&quot; did not begin in 2015. It began way earlier than that. The [[Houthi insurgency in Yemen]] began in 2004. We need to seriously organize these Yemen articles.--[[User:FutureTrillionaire|FutureTrillionaire]] ([[User talk:FutureTrillionaire|talk]]) 23:23, 9 April 2015 (UTC)

::They ''are'' seriously organized in a way they were not before. The Houthis are no longer simply insurgents; they now claim to be the Yemeni government, and at this point, they probably have a better claim than anyone else. The civil war didn't start in 2004, according to reliable sources that indicate Yemen was &quot;slipping into&quot; or &quot;on the verge of&quot; civil war a couple weeks ago (and now refer regularly to &quot;Yemen's civil war&quot; or &quot;the conflict in Yemen&quot;). There was virtually no armed conflict between Hadi loyalists and the Houthis/Saleh loyalists from the [[Battle of Sana'a (2014)|Fall of Sana'a]] last September up until Hadi fired General al-Saqqaf last month; indeed, for a significant portion of that time, there was a &quot;unity government&quot; in place that was led by Hadi while the Houthis were calling the shots.
::As structured now: there was the insurgency from 2004 to 2014/15, when the Houthis mounted their coup (starting with their takeover of Sana'a and ending with their &quot;constitutional declaration&quot; of a new government), then there was about a month and a half of chess pieces moving around the board in the aftermath of the coup, and then the civil war (or whatever we want to call it) broke out. These are discrete phases, broken down along obvious chronological dividing points, of the Yemeni crisis (which was preceded by the Houthi insurgency, which had its ebbs and flows until accelerating rapidly over the past couple years and culminating in the Houthis taking control of the government). The organization is sound, and each article has a distinct scope. That's really the best you can hope for in coverage of a crisis that has been anything but clear-cut. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 23:43, 9 April 2015 (UTC)
:::The 2011 Libyan Civil War began with protests, then insurgency, then the rebels took over Tripoli (the capital), then defeated Gadafi's forces once and for all. This Yemeni conflict is very similar, although the amount of time it took is different. Since there was never a break in the fighting, this has been a '''continuous''' conflict since 2004. Dividing up this conflict into multiple articles is conufusing and misleading.--[[User:FutureTrillionaire|FutureTrillionaire]] ([[User talk:FutureTrillionaire|talk]]) 00:52, 10 April 2015 (UTC)
:::One solution is to create an article called &quot;War in Yemen (2004-present)&quot;, similar to [[War in Afghanistan (1978-present)]].--[[User:FutureTrillionaire|FutureTrillionaire]] ([[User talk:FutureTrillionaire|talk]]) 00:55, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

::::There have been numerous breaks in the fighting, and there was actually little direct conflict between the Houthis and the Yemeni government after the 2010 ceasefire, up until much more recently. Most of the fighting in 2011-14 was between the Houthis and Sunni tribes.
::::It is a right mess, riddled with sourcing issues and missing quite a bit of pertinent information, but we ''do'' have the [[Houthi insurgency in Yemen]] page... I made some changes last night to cut it off at the point the Houthis announced the formation of a government, since at that point it seems like a real stretch to keep calling the conflict an &quot;insurgency&quot;, but if you feel strongly that this current conflict should be considered part of that lengthier campaign, you can always revert my changes per [[WP:BRD]]. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 00:59, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

*'''Question''' - Why is this article kept separate from the aftermath one? I'm not opposed to the &quot;civil war&quot; naming, but people like [[Robert Fisk]] [http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/an-old-hand-is-at-work-in-yemens-bloody-civil-war-9993454.html described] this conflict, &lt;span class=&quot;plainlinks&quot;&gt;[http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jan/14/yemen-aqap-civil-war-extremism along] [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/middleeast/yemen/11355794/Shia-Houthi-rebels-attack-presidential-palace-in-Yemen-in-attempted-coup.html with] [http://www.ibtimes.com/yemen-civil-war-tenuous-cease-fire-called-dozens-killed-clashes-between-al-qaeda-houthis-1707416 others]&lt;/span&gt;, as such even before the Houthis' takeover in early February. I'm just wondering: why shouldn't the scope of this article be broadened to also cover both the coup and post-coup events?

:However, regarding FutureTrillionaire's other concerns; the &quot;Yemen articles&quot; are fairly organized at the moment, and &quot;solutions&quot; like that are the reason why we end up with a lot with conflicts that are hard to organize in the first place. This is also the reason why we sometimes fail to determine start/end dates. Contrary to your opinion, I believe that such splits are actually helpful for readers to make a distinction between the breaks and escalations in any conflict. After all, escalations are usually notable enough to merit separate articles, something you sadly failed to realize last summer during the IS offensive in Iraq when some editors kept calling for a new umbrella article. I strongly reject having 2004 as a start date for this war unless you provide sufficient reliable sources (if there are any) that explicitly say so, otherwise we are clearly in WP:OR territory. Please don't let this topic end up like Iraq and Afghanistan, FT, and kindly wait till the developments are a little clearer to go ahead with such procedures. Thank you, [[User:Fitzcarmalan|Fitzcarmalan]] ([[User talk:Fitzcarmalan|talk]]) 13:22, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

::I'm agnostic on having this article fall under the umbrella of the aftermath article, so long as that article continues to be focused on the political developments after the coup. It's difficult, as we all know quite well, to write historiography of a history that is currently in progress; it may turn out, in the fullness of time, that this conflict is a relatively brief coda to the coup, as FT suggests. Or it may last months or years, especially if Saudi ground troops get involved. At this stage, who knows? -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 15:07, 10 April 2015 (UTC)
::I would add, at any rate, that the coup itself unfolded pretty slowly and was largely political maneuvering, at least after al-Ahmar was beaten and fled the country; even when the Houthis took over the presidential palace, I don't think anyone was killed, and Hadi and his ministers resigned (under duress) rather than being executed or even jailed. Hadi was under house arrest for one month, and then after he fled to Aden, another month went by before the full-scale clashes broke out (at the airport, and then the offensive). -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 15:12, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

== Name consistency ==

1. [[1994 civil war in Yemen]]



2. [[Yemeni Civil War (2015)]]

Any comments on that?--[[Special:Contributions/93.137.158.240|93.137.158.240]] ([[User talk:93.137.158.240|talk]]) 19:52, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

== Fourth column ==

It's completely unnecessary. ISIL has ''claimed'' (not even necessarily ''made'') one attack that could be considered part of this conflict. It controls no territory in Yemen. It has not been a target of the Saudi air campaign. Giving it its own infobox column is [[WP:UNDUE]] and makes the page look unnecessarily messy. As one of the editors who actually got Wikipedia to allow 4+ column infoboxes in the first place, I strongly believe they should only be used when it is absolutely needed to convey the dynamics of this conflict. There is no information I have seen in reliable sources to suggest ISIL has clashed with Hadi loyalists or AQAP has part of this conflict. There is no independent verification of their claim to have perpetrated a terrorist attack in the capital. They shouldn't be in the infobox, at least not with their own combatant column. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 20:28, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

==Merging [[Aftermath of the 2014–15 Yemeni coup d'état]]==
{{archivetop|No consensus to merge. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 05:26, 30 April 2015 (UTC)}}
{{ping|Kudzu1|RGloucester|Nannadeem|Mhhossein|Googol30|Mbcap|EkoGraf}}; Regarding [[Aftermath of the 2014–15 Yemeni coup d'état#Requested move 27 March 2015|this discussion]] I propose to merge that article in this one. What is your idea?--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 06:12, 17 April 2015 (UTC)

:'''Oppose''': I don't think so. During the period covered in the aftermath article, there were no notable clashes between Hadi and Houthi fighters. There is no need to merge the pages, as their scopes are distinct. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 08:12, 17 April 2015 (UTC)

*'''Strongly Support''' The civil war began after the coup d'état. --[[User:Panam2014|Panam2014]] ([[User talk:Panam2014|talk]]) 07:55, 18 April 2015 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' {{ping|Sa.vakilian}}:Can you support your proposal?
::I think the explanation in the [[Aftermath of the 2014–15 Yemeni coup d'état#Requested move 27 March 2015|moving]] discussion is clear. In my view, both of these articles include the 2015 conflict while this article has broader viewpoint.--&lt;font face=&quot;monospace&quot;&gt;[[User:Sa.vakilian|Seyyed]]([[User talk:Sa.vakilian|t]]-[[Special:Contributions/Sa.vakilian|c]])&lt;/font&gt; 13:38, 18 April 2015 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per [[WP:SIZE]] The result will create a long unreadable mess. - [[User:Knowledgekid87|Knowledgekid87]] ([[User talk:Knowledgekid87|talk]]) 15:39, 18 April 2015 (UTC)

*'''Comments''': I have read the draft constitution which was under final shape in January 2015.  Personally I am of the opinion that present situation has route causes based on socio economics.  Thus, it is more appropriate to a title of Civil war rather than a coup.  Encyclopedia Britannica provides that: “a coup is a change in power from the top that merely results in the abrupt replacement of leading government personnel. A coup rarely alters a nation’s fundamental social and economic policies, nor does it significantly redistribute power among competing political groups.” See here [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/140445/coup-detat].  An example is [[1999 Pakistani coup d'état]]

:::Yemeni Civil War (2015) has page length of 80,867 (in bytes), whereas the page length of Aftermath of the 2014–15 Yemeni coup d'état is 46,563 bytes.  I have seen pages with approximate length of above 95,000 bytes.  Page length issue can be covered in merger process with a concise gist of two texts on the same issue/subject.  However, page length issue is a technical concern and cannot be ignored.[[User:Nannadeem|Nannadeem]] ([[User talk:Nannadeem|talk]]) 12:43, 19 April 2015 (UTC)

*'''Support''' - When we do eventually have a WP:SIZE issue, we can easily consider splitting the merged parts into a separate &quot;Background of the Yemeni Civil War&quot; article or anything of the same order. But right now I believe it is redundant to have an article {{tq|focused on the political developments after the coup}} and another about military confrontations, which kind of constitutes original research, as suggested in a discussion above. Isn't the civil war itself is part of the aftermath? [[User:Fitzcarmalan|Fitzcarmalan]] ([[User talk:Fitzcarmalan|talk]]) 22:53, 19 April 2015 (UTC)

'''complaint''' {{ping|Kudzu1}} I also complaint against your behavior. You can not send me warning. Do you think what you say is correct and others don't know anything ?!?!?  Oh please be LOGICAL. OK? I wish you have better solution to solve the problems.
Regards,
Rastegarfar.mo

:'''Oppose''' There was no conflict during the aftermath of the coup. Only political negotiations and re-negotiations. Some of it can be put in the background section though. [[User:EkoGraf|EkoGraf]] ([[User talk:EkoGraf|talk]]) 06:24, 23 April 2015 (UTC)

*'''Strongly Oppose''' - There was no actual conflict between the Houthis and the Yemeni Government forces during the aftermath of the coup (except possibly in 3 cities to the east of Sana'a). Also, the scope of the topic is distinct, and the focus is different from that of the Yemeni Civil War itself, despite their relation. [[User:LightandDark2000|LightandDark2000]] ([[User talk:LightandDark2000|talk]]) 21:05, 25 April 2015 (UTC)
{{archivebottom}}

== Chronological order ==

Why are the order of events in the article ordered by location? It's better to have everything in chronological order. Also, the section about military intervention should be placed before events that happened after it began.--[[User:FutureTrillionaire|FutureTrillionaire]] ([[User talk:FutureTrillionaire|talk]]) 14:37, 17 April 2015 (UTC)

:Having them broken down by location makes linking to their specific battle pages easier and more accessible. We can workshop it, but I think convenience and navigibility should be prized over simple chronology, especially as the areas of conflict have changed little since 24 or 25 March. -[[User:Kudzu1|Kudzu1]] ([[User talk:Kudzu1|talk]]) 15:13, 17 April 2015 (UTC)

== US providing intelligence/logistical support ==

in the intro paragraphs it mentions that the US provided Saudi coalition with Intel and logistics and links to an NYT article. the article does not mention this anywhere. so the citation should be removed. (citation 5)  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.151.10.142|99.151.10.142]] ([[User talk:99.151.10.142|talk]]) 22:02, 24 April 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Name consistency ==

1. [[1994 civil war in Yemen]]

2. [[Yemeni Civil War (2015)]]


Why so??--[[Special:Contributions/78.0.1.237|78.0.1.237]] ([[User talk:78.0.1.237|talk]]) 13:24, 27 April 2015 (UTC)

== Damage to historical sites ==

http://globalvoicesonline.org/2015/05/31/did-saudi-arabia-bomb-yemens-ancient-marib-dam/

http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2015/06/150603-Yemen-ancient-Sheba-dam-heritage-destruction-Middle-East-archaeology/

http://www.unesco.org/new/en/media-services/single-view/news/unesco_director_general_condemns_airstrikes_on_yemens_cultural_heritage/#.VXH3AEZGR9g

http://www.yourmiddleeast.com/opinion/its-been-done-before-it-can-be-done-again-saving-the-middle-easts-cultural-diversity_32653

https://theintercept.com/2015/11/16/u-s-and-saudi-bombs-target-yemens-ancient-heritage/

19:48, 5 June 2015 (UTC)

== Israel ==
Some users seem to have an obsession with adding Israel in every military infobox on Wikipedia. This time an [[Special:Contributions/191.185.212.150|IP]] [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Yemeni_Civil_War_%282015%29&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=667839484&amp;oldid=667781601 did so] citing an article by Veterans Today, which is filled to the brink with holocaust denial and conspiratorial theories. Unless claims of Israeli involvement can be backed by '''serious, mainstream sources''', please stick it with your personal agenda and refrain from inserting them anywhere on Wikipedia. This is vandalism ''at best''. --[[User:Mikrobølgeovn|Mikrobølgeovn]] ([[User talk:Mikrobølgeovn|talk]]) 23:26, 21 June 2015 (UTC)
:{{replyto|Mikrobølgeovn}} This is very problematic all across wikipedia - mainly concerning Israel and to some degree Turkey.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 09:29, 27 March 2016 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' - i invite users to comment at [[Wikipedia:Categories_for_discussion/Log/2016_March_22#Category:Turkish_airstrikes_during_the_Syrian_Civil_War]].[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 09:29, 27 March 2016 (UTC)

== Civilian casualties: what kind of figures do you provide here? ==
[[User:EkoGraf]], could you explain, where you got this [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Yemeni_Civil_War_%282015%29&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=670735626 civilian casualty number &quot;1,630&quot;] from? You are citing channelnewsasia.com (http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/world/yemen-truce-begins-relief/1976692.html), but there is no such number given. And you even claim it was a &quot;UN&quot; number, so why don't you cite the original UN source or at least any reliable source that gives &quot;your&quot; special number. If it exists at all. Greetings,--[[User:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki]] ([[User talk:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|talk]]) 18:08, 13 July 2015 (UTC)

:[[User:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki]], source clearly says that according to the UN around half of the overall number of estimated dead are civilians. Half of the confirmed 3,261 is 1,630. PS Please refrain from using talk such as ''my special number...if it exists at all''. Its not per WP: Civil or WP: Good faith. Thank you. [[User:EkoGraf|EkoGraf]] ([[User talk:EkoGraf|talk]]) 18:16, 13 July 2015 (UTC)
::Just read carefully, you might understand then:
::1.) Your source (http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/world/yemen-truce-begins-relief/1976692.html) does not say &quot;3,261&quot;, but &quot;'''3,200'''&quot;. Why do you falsificate again the figure given in your own source?
::2.) Even if it was saying &quot;3,261&quot; &quot;around half of them&quot; wouldn't mean &quot;1,630&quot;. You give a special, a specified number, where your source does not do.
::3.) You just admitted that you constructed your own number and did not use existing figures. This means, the number &quot;1630&quot; never existed but was your personal invention. You showed this kind of behaviour (wrong usage of sources according to the civilian death toll in Yemen) several times ago and I already recommended you to use the original figures of the UN-OHCHR. You'll find the Press Briefing Notes easily there on the home page. So why don't you just use them as recommended? It's completely improper to provide and spread private calculations via Wikipedia. 
::4.) There is no WP good faith existing that protects falsification of information. Instead of citing WP: Civil or WP: Good faith you should be grateful, if someone informs you when you are giving wrong figures. I never said, you are doing it intentionally. But it is too obvious that you proceed to misuse sources. Greetings,--[[User:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki]] ([[User talk:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|talk]]) 17:59, 14 July 2015 (UTC)
:::[[User:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki]] Not seeing how its falsification when the UN says half of the dead are civilians and the latest confirmed number of dead by the UN is 3,261 (per the 1st of 2 refs cited). I did not construct my own number and I did in fact use existing figures. And its not private calculations when its per [[WP: CALC]] (calculated numbers based on sources). Instead of attacking and insulting me, and assuming bad faith from the start, you could have simply requested to change the number from 1,630 to 1,600 (which I would have gladly done as compromise). In any case, this latest report [http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/yemen-anti-rebel-forces-south-aden-airport-32438774] which gives a concrete figure of 1,670 dead civilians per the UN makes this issue effectively resolved and done. [[User:EkoGraf|EkoGraf]] ([[User talk:EkoGraf|talk]]) 19:18, 14 July 2015 (UTC)
::::UN-OHCHR never gave the figure 1,630 for a civilan death toll in Yemen. This was your very own constructed number. You'll find it in no single UN source. I'm not interestet in a horse-trade. There is a good reason, why your source did not (and could not) provide a precise civilian death toll:
::::1) UN-OHCHR gives precise figures for the civilian death toll since March 26th, that is since begin of the Saudi-led military intervention. 
::::2) UN-WHO and UN-OCHA give no precise figures for the civilian death toll since March 19. From the beginning it was said: &quot;[http://www.webcitation.org/6XyeGyYEo The WHO toll does not distinguish between civilians and fighters].&quot;
::::3) What your source did, was to compare the UN provided overall death toll (since March 19th) with the civilian death toll (since March 26th). That's why it did not give a precise figure, because it wouldn't be correct.
::::What you tried to construct is simply impossible. There is no precise correct number for the civilian death toll since March 19th existing. If you insist on giving a precise number, you have to cite the UN-OHCHR civilan death toll. The recent (as of July 14 for the period of March 26 to July 13) is: [http://www.webcitation.org/6a1KMuATt 1,670]. The previous figure was [http://www.webcitation.org/6ZriGPQy8 1,528]. But there was never a figure existing as your &quot;1,630&quot; or &quot;1,600&quot; or whatever you are trying to launch here without any source. Once again I recommend you to use the original UN websites instead of all your ABC news and channelnewsasia.com and whatever you were digging out in the past. I got the impression, you are simply not understanding the sources and how the figures were generated, what they mean and what they don't mean. I hope you'll act some more precise in future instead of trying to &quot;calculate&quot; formally &quot;precise&quot; but in fact invented figures. Read the sources well. Greetings,--[[User:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki]] ([[User talk:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|talk]]) 21:14, 14 July 2015 (UTC)
:::::''This was your very own constructed number. What you tried to construct is simply impossible.'' It was all per [[WP: CALC]]. ''horse-trade'' Nope, its [[WP: Compromise]]. In any case. An ''exact'' figure/source has been provided now. Regards! [[User:EkoGraf|EkoGraf]] ([[User talk:EkoGraf|talk]]) 21:39, 14 July 2015 (UTC)
::::::[[WP: CALC]] does not back clear corruption of a UN death toll figure. And [[WP: Compromise]] does not help you when you purport a non-existing statistic. Don't use WP rules for improper usage of sources. Better stick to the UN Press Briefing Notes as recommended and you get the civilian death toll for the period since March 26. There is no other UN civilian death toll existing. And you can't calculate a precise figure of a non-existing statistic. This is original research. And even more: it's simply wrong and when you continue to spread false information - in spite of being informed you are doing - it's even disinformation. Don't disinform the encyclopedia's readers in future. Greetings,--[[User:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki]] ([[User talk:Anglo-Araneophilus~enwiki|talk]]) 05:56, 15 July 2015 (UTC)

== map is wrong ==

The red faction does not control all of Taiz as shown on the map. Regards. 

[[Special:Contributions/69.166.122.245|69.166.122.245]] ([[User talk:69.166.122.245|talk]]) 17:23, 20 August 2015 (UTC)

:It's just terribly out of date. [[User:Doyna Yar|Doyna Yar]] ([[User talk:Doyna Yar|talk]]) 18:24, 14 August 2016 (UTC)

== title should be renamed to Yemeni war ==

This is not a civil war because of direct external parties. Regards.

[[Special:Contributions/207.35.219.34|207.35.219.34]] ([[User talk:207.35.219.34|talk]]) 20:25, 20 August 2015 (UTC)

: I was going to propose the same. I think the best name is ('''Yemen war 2015''') as we have now troops on the ground from Saudi Arabia, UAE and Qatar. not merely Aerial support [[User:3bdulelah|3bdulelah]] ([[User talk:3bdulelah|talk]]) 00:03, 7 September 2015 (UTC)

:: The presence of foreign troops does not change the identification of this conflict as a civil war. Se [[Spanish Civil War]] or [[Syrian Civil War]] as an example. --[[Special:Contributions/188.79.86.177|188.79.86.177]] ([[User talk:188.79.86.177|talk]]) 11:21, 26 September 2015 (UTC)

== map needs to update with Qaeda gains in the south ==

http://news.antiwar.com/2015/08/06/yemeni-al-qaeda-seizes-three-towns-near-southern-port-of-aden/

http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/yemen-officials-al-qaida-seizes-key-areas-aden-33247412

[[Special:Contributions/104.243.111.224|104.243.111.224]] ([[User talk:104.243.111.224|talk]]) 17:43, 22 August 2015 (UTC)

:: map also needs to highlight the situation inside Saudi Arabia, where there are now constant fightings and gains by both sides. --[[Special:Contributions/188.79.86.177|188.79.86.177]] ([[User talk:188.79.86.177|talk]]) 11:21, 26 September 2015 (UTC)

== Russian and North Korean involvement in Yemen ==

Accord to the [http://www.ibtimes.com/putins-latest-moves-military-alliance-among-iran-hezbollah-russia-syria-could-spread-2113386 article], A senior Hezbollah said that Russia is providing weapons to the Houthis. This article is not poorly written, biased or libelous. For the [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/samuel-ramani/north-koreas-balancing-ac_b_7995688.html North Korean part], if you read carefully it stated that North Korea's military support for Houthi rebels in Yemen is the latest manifestation of its support for anti-American forces&quot;. Article made by student also counts a source. The reason why this is not biased, libelous and poorly written is because International Buisness Times and Huffington Post are good news source. UA Today has some positive views about Russia and all Russians. Based on your edits, I suspected you are from the Russian military. If am wrong, explain who you actually are. You are really misunderstanding the articles if you have not read these carefully. But since you have misunderstood these article, we must discuss this in the [[Wikipedia:Dispute resolution noticeboard]] [[User:FrankieL1985|FrankieL1985]] ([[User talk:FrankieL1985|talk]]) 20:24, 2 November 2015 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' - providing weapons is defined as support, not involvement/intervention. Anyway doesn't seem Russia is in direct support of the Houthis, but rather Russian weapons are perhaps redirected to Yemen, with no Russian intention.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 06:59, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

== &quot;(by far the largest force)&quot; Language ==

I don't like to reach into another person's fridge without asking (especially the first PP of a highly charged issue), but I'm unclear what work this phrase does in the intro. Are Southern Separatists the largest force among all Hadi government belligerents, or among all belligerents generally? The non-pay walled reference does not distinguish among these two choices or some other, nor does the statistical data in the infobox imply that the Southern Separatists holds numbers sufficiently greater to qualify as the largest force &quot;by far.&quot; Was there an archived discussion on this I missed with relevant pro/cons, or can I dump the phrase? 

[[User:Clyde Miller|CM]] ([[User talk:Clyde Miller|talk]]) 17:29, 5 December 2015 (UTC)
:I've removed that phrase. It was clearly an unsourced POV, which inexplicably remained in the lead for months. [[User:Nykterinos|Nykterinos]] ([[User talk:Nykterinos|talk]]) 11:40, 26 February 2016 (UTC)

==Daish/ISiL territory==
According to the &quot;more detailed map&quot; Daish control [[Lawdar]] while  Al Mukallah and other nearby coastal towns are controlled by Aqab.  According to this map, at first blush, Dais control Saudi Arabia, Oman, Somalia, Djibouti and Ethiopia.  On comparing greyscales and zooming in they control Al Mukallah and other nearby coastal towns.

We should choose a distinct colour, and ensure that the maps correspond to reliably sourced information.

All&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;best: ''[[User:Rich Farmbrough|Rich]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Rich Farmbrough|Farmbrough]]'',&lt;small&gt; 20:00, 13 January 2016 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
:al-Qaeda gets grey for towns/villages and white for territory, and ISIL gets black for town/villages and grey for territory (on the map file). This is how the color was assigned for the other Middle East maps, so it will also apply to this map. [[User:LightandDark2000|LightandDark2000]] ([[User talk:LightandDark2000|talk]]) 10:24, 24 January 2016 (UTC)

== US involvment ==

The article says that the US conducts only airstrikes against al Qaeda while worldwide press reported on multiple occasions that the US also gives intel to the Saudis on Huthis.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/104.162.113.212|104.162.113.212]] ([[User talk:104.162.113.212|talk]]) 16:02, 20 January 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Yes, the US provides intel to the Saudi-led Coalition on the Houthis, but that isn't really a full military intervention. The US is still airstriking al-Qaeda, and they will probabably start targeting ISIL as well, if they haven't yet already. [[User:LightandDark2000|LightandDark2000]] ([[User talk:LightandDark2000|talk]]) 10:25, 24 January 2016 (UTC)
:I believe this is still &quot;support&quot;, rather than &quot;involvement&quot;.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 07:00, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:9|one external link|9 external links}} on [[Yemeni Civil War (2015–present)]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707067760 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/saudi-arabia-has-150000-troops-for-yemen-operation-report/article23628188/
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20151118224504/http://www.yemenobserver.com/front-page/1397-supreme-revolutionary-commission-declares-general-mobilization.html to http://www.yemenobserver.com/front-page/1397-supreme-revolutionary-commission-declares-general-mobilization.html
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.saudigazette.com.sa/index.cfm?method=home.regcon&amp;contentid=20150325238084
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/article16355684.html
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.chron.com/news/world/article/Pakistan-says-Saudi-led-coalition-in-Yemen-wants-6180919.php
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.france24.com/en/20150418-least-27-dead-fighting-yemens-taez/
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://tribune.com.pk/story/871660/at-least-76-dead-in-yemen-air-raids-fighting/
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20150928121643/http://www.france24.com/en/20150516-south-yemen-clashes-kill-dozens-ceasefire-nears-end to http://www.france24.com/en/20150516-south-yemen-clashes-kill-dozens-ceasefire-nears-end
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20151118235325/http://www.thenewstribune.com/2015/04/28/3765544/saudi-king-names-counterterrorism.html to http://www.thenewstribune.com/2015/04/28/3765544/saudi-king-names-counterterrorism.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:56, 26 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Yemeni civil war (2015–present)]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=725455464 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot*this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive {newarchive} to http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-36011794http://www.wsj.com/articles/saudi-led-coalition-promises-to-adhere-to-yemen-cease-fire-1460359998

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:27, 15 June 2016 (UTC)

== Strength ? ==

According to the strength section the revolutionaty committee has a total amount of 400.000-500.000 fighters on it's site while the hadi government stands with 37.500 fighters. There is no way this could be possible because otherwise the Houthis would have ran over entire Yemen a long time ago.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/91.115.79.185|91.115.79.185]] ([[User talk:91.115.79.185|talk]]) 23:32, 6 August 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==  Saudi Special Forces in yamen ==

* [[Major general]] Prince [[Fahad Bin Turki Bin Abdulaziz Al Saud]] (Commander of Airborne Units &amp; Special Security Forces)&lt;ref name=&quot;Fahad&quot;&gt;[https://twitter.com/ammar82/status/644971039567552512 Arrival of Commander of Special Forces Major-General Prince Fahd Bin Turki Bin Abdulaziz to Marib]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
* [[Lieutenant colonel]] [[Obeid Fadel Al-Shammari]] (Commander of Saudi Special Forces in yamen)&lt;ref name=&quot;Obeid&quot;&gt;[https://translate.google.com/translate?sl=ar&amp;tl=en&amp;js=y&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=ar&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.alweeam.com.sa%2F374115%2F%25D8%25AA%25D8%25B9%25D9%258A%25D9%258A%25D9%2586-%25D8%25A7%25D9%2584%25D9%2585%25D9%2582%25D8%25AF%25D9%2585-%25D8%25B9%25D8%25A8%25D9%258A%25D8%25AF_%25D9%2581%25D8%25A7%25D8%25B6%25D9%2584_%25D8%25A7%25D9%2584%25D8%25B4%25D9%2585%25D8%25B1%25D9%258A-%25D8%25A8%25D8%25AF%25D9%2584%25D9%258B%25D8%25A7-%25D9%2585%25D9%2586%2F&amp;edit-text=&amp;act=url تعيين المقدم عبيد فاضل الشمري بدلًا من السهيان]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
* [[Brigadier general]] [[Auni Al Qurni]] (Deputy Commander of Saudi Special Forces in yamen)&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM2016&quot;&gt;[http://www.thenational.ae/world/middle-east/mukallas-liberation-sends-a-warning-to-supporters-of-terrorism-says-uae-commander Mukalla’s liberation sends a warning to supporters of terrorism, says UAE commander]&lt;/ref&gt;
--[[User:Qrmoo3|Qrmoo3]] ([[User talk:Qrmoo3|talk]]) 19:31, 1 October 2016 (UTC)

== Houthi forces ==

* [[Brigadier general]] Hasan Abdullah Almalsi {{KIA}} &lt;small&gt;(Commander of Houthi special forces)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/us-yemen-security-general-idUSKCN11U0KG|title=Coalition forces kill Houthi general on Saudi-Yemen border: sources|work=[[reuters]]|date=Sep 24, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ibrahim Badr Al-Houthi {{KIA}} &lt;small&gt;(the brother of [[Abdul-Malik Badreddin al-Houthi|Abdulmalik al-Houthi]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.alarabiya.net/en/News/middle-east/2015/11/29/Brother-of-Houthi-militia-chief-killed-near-Yemen-border.html|title=Houthi militia chief’s brother killed in Yemen|work=[[Al Arabiya]]|date=29 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Abdullah Qayed al-Fadeea {{KIA}} &lt;small&gt;(senior Houthi militia leader)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.alarabiya.net/en/News/2016/10/04/Houthi-senior-militia-leader-killed-near-Najran.html Houthi senior militia leader killed near Najran]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Hashim al-Barawi {{KIA}} &lt;small&gt;(senior Houthi militia leader)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alamy.com/stock-photo-epa04900798-houthi-militiamen-carry-the-coffin-of-a-senior-houthi-86869531.html|title=Houthi militiamen carry the coffin of a senior Houthi military leader, Hashim al-Barawi, killed three days ago while fighting Saudi-backed forces|work=[[Alamy]]|date=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Major general]] Abdul Razzaq Al-Marwani {{KIA}} &lt;small&gt;(Head of Yemens Special Security Forces)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://translate.google.com/translate?sl=ar&amp;tl=en&amp;js=y&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=ar&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.nbn.com.lb%2F%25D9%2582%25D8%25A7%25D8%25A6%25D8%25AF-%25D8%25A7%25D9%2584%25D8%25AD%25D8%25B1%25D8%25B3-%25D8%25A7%25D9%2584%25D8%25AC%25D9%2585%25D9%2587%25D9%2588%25D8%25B1%25D9%258A-%25D8%25A7%25D9%2584%25D9%258A%25D9%2585%25D9%2586%25D9%258A-%25D9%2588%25D9%2582%25D8%25A7%25D8%25A6%25D8%25AF-%25D9%2582%25D9%2588%25D8%25A7%25D8%25AA%2F&amp;edit-text=&amp;act=url|title=Commander of the Republican Guard and the commander of the Yemeni capital, security forces among the victims of the raids that targeted a funeral in Sanaa|author=|date=08 October 2016|accessdate=|work=[[National Broadcasting Network (Lebanon)|National Broadcasting Network]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;8October2016&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://translate.google.com/translate?sl=ar&amp;tl=en&amp;js=y&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=ar&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.alalam.ir%2Fnews%2F1870267&amp;edit-text=|agency=[[Al-Alam News Network]]|title=military leaders among the victims of the martyrs of the massacre Sanaa|date=08 October 2016|accessdate=|first=|last=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Major general]] Ali bin Ali Al-Jaifi {{KIA}} &lt;small&gt;(Republican Guard commander)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://translate.google.com/translate?sl=ar&amp;tl=en&amp;js=y&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=ar&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.manartv.com.lb%2F821500&amp;edit-text=&amp;act=url|title=Al-Manar correspondent: the commander of the Republican Guard and the commander of the Yemeni Central Security Forces among the martyrs of the massacre Sanaa|author=|date=8 October 2016|accessdate=|work=[[Al-Manar]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;8October2016&quot; /&gt;
* [[Major general]] Abdul-Qader Hilal {{KIA}} &lt;small&gt;(Mayor of Sanaa City)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2016/10/yemen-blasts-hit-event-attended-jalal-al-ruweishan-161008141316494.html|title=Yemen: Blasts hit event attended by Jalal al-Ruweishan|author=|date=8 October 2016|accessdate=|work=[[Al Jazeera]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
--[[User:Qrmoo3|Qrmoo3]] ([[User talk:Qrmoo3|talk]]) 19:41, 1 October 2016 (UTC)
{{reflist}}

== Timeline? ==

Maybe I'm missing it, but shouldn't this article and/or a subarticle contain a timeline of the war? This article is ''heavily'' focused on events in early 2015, with not a lot about recent changes in territory or clashes. The most recent stuff I can find is about ceasefire talk in April 2016, something which of course did not last. Is there any article with a chronology of the war? Even [[Saudi Arabian-led intervention in Yemen]] seems to taper off around the end of 2015. [[User:PBP|PBP]] ([[User talk:PBP|talk]]) 15:37, 8 October 2016 (UTC)

==Alleged==
I must put your attention that we do not add &quot;alleged&quot; parties to the infobox per [[WP:EXCEPTIONAL]]. Moreover, currently only Turkish-language sources seem to support the claims regarding Iran and Hezbollah and frankly - even though sources are reliable (Hurriyet and al-Jazeera) this is not sufficient, since most English-lang wikipedians do not speak Turkish and cannot verify the claims. Would be happy if someone brings English lang sources or otherwise i delete those parties from the infobox.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 21:08, 19 October 2016 (UTC)
*{{ping|Pahlevun}} i'm raising this issue following our discussion.[[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 21:10, 19 October 2016 (UTC)
* removed.{{done}} [[User:Greyshark09|'''''GreyShark''''']] ([[User talk:Greyshark09|''dibra'']]) 06:54, 30 October 2016 (UTC)

== Yemen map &quot;14 november&quot;==

Yemen map: Fighting continued along the frontlines areas in Hajja, Jawf, Marib, Nihm and Taiz - no major changes in almost locked conflict
https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CxYE_LpUUAA3TDQ.jpg --[[User:Qrmoo3|Qrmoo3]] ([[User talk:Qrmoo3|talk]]) 21:40, 16 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>grb1779n7z3shkpxs7gw1kl43efinuc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
