<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:March Days</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5122317</id>
    <revision>
      <id>654258925</id>
      <parentid>578876469</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-03-31T00:02:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2015-03-30.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22473">{{Talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST
|class=B
|&lt;!--B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations.--&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!--B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies.--&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!--B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content.--&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!--B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors.--&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!--B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams.--&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|Russian-task-force=yes
|Ottoman-task-force=yes|WWI=y}}
{{WPTR|class=Start|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=B|importance=Low|mil=yes|hist=yes}}
{{WikiProject Azerbaijan|class=C|importance=High}}
{{WPAM|class=Start}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=b|importance=mid}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2012-03-30|oldid1=484634739|date2=2013-03-30|oldid2=547836170|date3=2015-03-30|oldid3=653852402}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:March Days/Archive %(counter)d
}}

__TOC__
{{Clear}}

== Number of deaths &lt;nowiki&gt;{{disputed}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; ==

*According to [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50D11FC3D5A11738DDDA90A94DD405B888DF1D3　New York Times]

'''''2,000''' killed and 3,000 wounded in straggle between Russians and '''Mussulmans'''.''

*According to [http://www.hrw.org/legacy/reports/1995/communal/#P986_419147 PLAYING THE &quot;COMMUNAL CARD&quot;: Communal Violence and Human Rights]:

''In '''March 1918''', in an effort to seize Baku from local Muslim forces, Soviet Bolsheviks made a pact with the Armenian nationalist Dashnak party. In an orgy of violence that followed, '''between 3,000 and 3,500''' '''Muslims''' were massacred.''

*According to [http://intersci.ss.uci.edu/wiki/eBooks/Articles/Rumor%20in%20Baku%20Smith.pdf Michael Smith]

''up to 12,000 '''Muslim''' civilians perished; thousands of others fled Baku in a mass exodus''

*According to [http://books.google.com/books?id=RSxt-JB-PDkC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=%22the+massacre+of+some+12,000+Azeris+in+Baku+%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ts5OToOAG86KmQWs59H0Bg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22the%20massacre%20of%20some%2012%2C000%20Azeris%20in%20Baku%20%22&amp;f=false James Minahan], 

''The tensions and fighting between the Azeris and the Armenians in the federation culminated in the massacre of some '''12,000 Azeris''' in Baku by radical Armenians and Bolshevik troops in '''March 1918''' ''

*According to [http://books.google.com/books?id=llwiAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22during+which+more+than+3000+people+were+killed.+Outside+Baku,+the+Azerbaijanis%22&amp;dq=%22during+which+more+than+3000+people+were+killed.+Outside+Baku,+the+Azerbaijanis%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=iNFOTu6RJo2NmQXEqojjBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA The Newly Independent States of Eurasia: Handbook of Former Soviet Republics]:

''When the latter surrendered, the Armenians engaged in a killing and looting spree, remembered by the Azerbaijanis as the &quot;'''March Days'''&quot;, during which more than '''3000 people''' were killed.''

*According to [http://books.google.com/books?id=wYLiAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22During+three+days+in+March+1918+Bolsheviks+killed+3000+Azerbaijanians+in+Baku+%22&amp;dq=%22During+three+days+in+March+1918+Bolsheviks+killed+3000+Azerbaijanians+in+Baku+%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=adJOTtegDO7smAWrldDgBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA Ukrainian Congress Committee of America]

''During three days in March 1918 Bolsheviks killed '''3000 Azerbaijanians''' in Baku alone.''


[[User:Takabeg|Takabeg]] ([[User talk:Takabeg|talk]]) 20:53, 19 August 2011 (UTC)

Some people said 3,500, some 30,000. 12,000 is the mostly quoted and researched. No need to finish numbers of killed by cherry picking. Look at google searches for 12,000. [[User:Dighapet|Dighapet]] ([[User talk:Dighapet|talk]]) 13:45, 22 August 2011 (UTC)

: WE must use all [[Wikipedia:Identifying reliable sources|Identifying reliable sources]]. We must behave by sources not by users' POV. -- [[User:Takabeg|Takabeg]] ([[User talk:Takabeg|talk]]) 13:52, 22 August 2011 (UTC)

Takabeg, the Ukrainian Congress of America is not an [[WP:RS]] source vs. historian scholars like Michael Smith or Firuz Kazemzadeh. And Richard Hovhanissian is not an [[WP:NPOV]] source on the subject. As far as the New York Times source, the later, thus more conclusive, publication of this newspaper in 1920 used a figure of 12,000. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 14:30, 22 August 2011 (UTC)

::Added also an OR tag in Oil Factor section, as it seems to be completely needless or irrelevant to the subject of this article. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 01:15, 23 August 2011 (UTC)

MarshallBagramyan, regarding your edit, are you disputing the numbers provided by the Armenian National Committee? Also Kazemzadeh did not question but actually did provide the ANC numbers as well as cited the fact that although ANC is not impartial to the issue (for obvious reasons), the numbers were likely to be true. Also, Alex Marshall reference did not say 10,000 but used the word thousands. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 06:26, 26 August 2011 (UTC)

:I'm not; but the figure that seems to be the average in our sources is roughly 10,000. But the phrase &quot;whom one can hardly expect to be objective in such a matter&quot; is highly POV and I suspect that someone simply copied Kazemzadeh exact wording without proper attribution. I thus modified that sentence to in the belief that this is the meaning that Kazemzadeh was attempting to convey. But it seems to me that that line is unnecessary and it would be preferable if we just attribute those numbers to the source itself without demeaning the intelligence of the reader by telling him whether a source is impartial or not (especially when its provenance is clear enough).--[[User:MarshallBagramyan|Marshal Bagramyan]] ([[User talk:MarshallBagramyan|talk]]) 01:12, 30 August 2011 (UTC)

I removed the cleanup and reference &quot;ibid&quot; tags, as they are no longer relevant. Will work on improving the references in the article. In any case, there is no use for factual accuracy tag in the article, as all references are verifiable. Unless the contributor who placed this tag in first place, has something to add. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 22:53, 1 September 2011 (UTC)

== Anon edits ==

First of all, I would like to point out to the anonymous editor 76.191.230.234 that such massive changes to an article must not be done without discussing them first. The edit is reverted until consensus is reached on the following changes and additions.
* '''Nationalism'''. I feel unsure about the appropriatness of this term. The constant use (I would even say overuse) of the term 'Azerbaijani nationalists' is based on one partisan Soviet source, which could not be expected to label the democratic movements in the Caucasus states any other way for political reasons. There are in fact tons more sources who refer to this so-called 'nationalist' movement as democratic.
* '''Turkish protectorate'''. In his book ''Russian Azerbaijan'', Swietochowski among others argues that there was a lot more opposition to the idea of establishing Turkish protectorate over Azerbaijan than solidarity. The claim made by the anonymous user, on top of this, is not based on any source.
* '''Shamkhor events'''. These events were not a direct prelude to March Days. The clashes there took place between supporters of Musavat and remnants of the Czarist Army, whereas the Azeri massacres in Baku were carried out by Bolsheviks and Dashnaks.
* '''12,000 killed'''. I do not understand the use of the phrase &quot;Azerbaijanis claim that 12,000 Muslim were killed&quot;, when there are so many non-Azerbaijani sources providing the same number. So far no scholar has explicitely described this figured as exaggerated or inaccurate. [[User:Parishan|Parishan]] ([[User talk:Parishan|talk]]) 17:07, 17 September 2011 (UTC)

::When Atabay made massive changes without discussions to the point of vandalism, there was no such uproar. The objections above are not serious. 

::Nationalist is the appropriate term to use when describing the anti-Soviet struggle waged by the Musavat and other Muslim forces against the Soviet. Scholarship identifies the Musavat as a nationalist party. To use the term &quot;Azerbaijani&quot; is misleading because it gives the impression that the majority of Muslims in Baku supported the Musavat when in fact large sections of the Muslim community supported the Soviet forces, while many others were politically passive. Baku during the Russian Civil War was not a struggle about nationality, as suggested in Suny's work. The anti-Soviet side consisted of Azerbaijani nationalists and Russian officers, while the Soviet side was multinational.

::You make claims about the presence of the phrase &quot;Turkish protectorate&quot;, but there is no such thing in the previous version of the article. Rather, it says that the Musavat with Turkish help wanted to to drive out the Soviets and establish their own regime. Turkish invasions of Russia's Caucasus were an important part of the background of the Baku events. Musavat-Turkish links were demonstrated during the September 1918 conquest of Baku.

::Concerning the Shamxor massacre, it's rather disingenuous to try to isolate this incident from events in Baku. Most scholarship on the subject goes into detail about Shamxor when analyzing the background of the Baku events. Shamxor had a significant impact on the psychology of the Soviet leaders and the masses throughout the Caucasus. 

::Concerning the death toll, this article makes note of how the Azerbaijani nationalist groups at the 1919 conference painted a sensationalist picture of the Baku events with a 12,000 death toll. Other sources, such as the ones cited by Dadayan, say that up to 2000 on the anti-Soviet side and up to 1200 on the Soviet and Armenian sides were killed. There are several estimates of the death toll, and they should be mentioned.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.191.230.234|76.191.230.234]] ([[User talk:76.191.230.234|talk]]) 21:22, 18 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I suggest that the anon IP provides and discusses neutral references prior to making massive edits in the article. The edits made by myself are all based on neutral references, majority of which were already used in the article. With all due respect to the anonymous editor, Shamkhor massacre was not the primary topic of March days events, so devoting overwhelming amount of effort into that topic is distracting from major subject, which remains to be the massacre of 12,000 Azerbaijanis and other Muslims on the territory of Baku Governorate from March 31 to April 2, 1918. Moreover, Dadayan is by no means a neutral author when it comes to discussing Armenian-Azerbaijani conflict or March Days, while Michael Smith, Firuz Kazemzadeh, New York Times are most definitely neutral and reliable references in this regard. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 06:19, 19 September 2011 (UTC)

:The edits you made in fact amount to providing support for the post-1990 POV from Azerbaijani regime line about a &quot;genocide&quot; and &quot;massacres&quot; committed against Azerbaijanis, particularly the way you try to cover up discussion of the Shamxor massacre. You're doing this under &quot;neutral references&quot; like Michael Smith and Kazemzadeh when in fact they advance their own POV and arguments just like all authors do. For example, Smith argues in his article that Baku went through'' &quot;less an instance of class war against the Soviet, more a battle of rumors on national terms.&quot;'' Russian historians like Mints as well as western ones like Suny advance arguments very different from this thesis. Your description of Smith and Kazemzadeh as &quot;neutral&quot; authors is false. It is not problematic that historians and primary sources advance their own POV. What is problematic is the way you are promoting certain sources over others. Neutral point of view does not mean that certain points of view can be promoted over others the way you seem to be doing. 

:Concerning your objection to using Dadayan, there is no justification for this. Dadayan cites an Armenian source for the following statement: ''По разным данным, потери обеих сторон были таковы: азербайджанцы – 700-2000 убитыми, большевики (русские и армяне) – 300-12001.'' This is very different from Azerbaijani claims in 1919 about 12,000 massacred Muslims. Since Dadayan's material has been clearly attributed, it is allowed to stay in accordance with Wikipedia policies.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.191.230.234|76.191.230.234]] ([[User talk:76.191.230.234|talk]]) 18:16, 19 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::I requested a semi-protection of the page, so that the anonymous IP contributor above can discuss contributions on the talk page, before making massive edits to the article. Again, Dadayan is neither reliable, nor qualified reference to be used versus multitude of established, neutral and [[WP:RS]] experts on the March Days of 1918. It is problematic to use non-neutral source in this article. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 18:21, 19 September 2011 (UTC)

:::Dadayan's source says up to 2000 on the Muslim side and 1200 on the other side were killed. The source has been clearly attributed and there is not attempt to state that this is the truth. NPOV and RS does not mean that POV-advancing sources are not allowed, but that they have to be attributed.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.191.230.234|76.191.230.234]] ([[User talk:76.191.230.234|talk]]) 18:27, 19 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::::Aliyev, Victor Serge, Rasulzade, Shahumyan are all cited in this article even though they are not neutral sources. Point is that they are allowed in this article because they have been properly attributed and their thoughts are not presented as fact. By the same standards, Dadayan's claims about the death toll can be used.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.191.230.234|76.191.230.234]] ([[User talk:76.191.230.234|talk]]) 18:38, 19 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Well, and ARF member Pasdermadjian says, over 10,000 Muslims were killed. The number is confirmed by Michael Smith, Firuz Kazemzadeh, New York Times and other established neutral sources. So Dadayan's figures do not seem to be real as opposed to reliable scholars and sources. For some reason, Dadayan's claim that 2,000 were killed and 1,200 on other side, does not compel you to adjust the number of ARF/Armenian victims, but only that of Muslims. So your edit is not neutral and does not rely on proper sources. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 20:49, 19 September 2011 (UTC)

::And using word &quot;Azerbaijani nationalists&quot; is [[WP:LABEL]]. According to various reliable sources, ARF is a radical neo-nationalist organization, yet, such words are not used in the article to describe its activity during March Days. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 20:56, 19 September 2011 (UTC)

:::Smith did not confirm that 12,000 Muslims were killed, and he is not in a position to do so. All he did was cite the 12,000 figure from primary sources without going into detail about it. Plenty of other sources refer to Shahumyan's figure of 3000 killed on both sides. It's really strange that you think it's okay to cite Pasdermadjian while at the same time protesting against the inclusion of Dadayan's work. Pasdermadjian was not a party to this conflict and did not have some special qualification to provide his own original estimate of the death toll. This article should not present any death toll as a fact, but should cite the various estimates that exist in the relevant literature.

:::And again, Musavat ≠ Azerbaijanis. It is completely inappropriate to label the Musavatists as Azerbaijanis when in fact the majority of Azerbaijanis either supported the Soviet or were politically passive.

:Yes, Pastermadjian is more relevant reference because he was not a party to conflict, but he was directly involved with ARF at the time of events. Dadayan is completely irrelevant here, and the fact that he used Shahumyan figures (which were not neutral, because Shahumyan was a party of conflict), makes him even less reliable. 
:Using term &quot;Azerbaijani nationalists&quot; is completely inappropriate POV, violating [[WP:LABEL]]. The same way, based on its activity, Dashnaks can be considered a neo-Nazi group, it does not mean that all Armenians are Dashnaks or that such wording can be used in the article. [[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 00:49, 20 September 2011 (UTC)
::Dadayan did not use Shahumyan's figures and does not cite Shahmyan for the death toll. You don't seem to be familiar with the source. Dadayan is a member of Armenia's National Academy of Sciences and his work is mainstream. It should be included here to show Armenian historians' perspective, just like how Azerbaijani nationalist parties' claims at the 1919 conference are mentioned.

::You selectively refer to Pastermadjian because the cherry-picked text seems to support your version of events, but you are adamant about deleting Dadayan's material because you disagree with it. And it seems that Pastermadjian has been distorted because he specifically events in Baku as military battles rather than massacres. He wrote: ''&quot;the small Armenian garrison of Baku, together with a few thousand Russians, defended Baku and its oil wells against tens of thousands of Tatars, the Caucasian mountaineers, and more than one division of regular Turkish troops which had come to the assistance of the latter by way of Batum.&quot;''

::The way you try to provide support to Azerbaijani claims about 12,000 killed in a massacre is in violation of NPOV and undue weight. This sentence is completely inappropriate because there is the suggestion that Shahumyan's figure is false while the higher figures are true one is true.

''The leader of Baku Soviet, Stepan Shahumyan, claimed that more than 3,000 killed in two days. However, in his October 1918 article for the Armenian Herald, publication of the Boston-based Armenian National Union of America...''  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.191.230.234|76.191.230.234]] ([[User talk:76.191.230.234|talk]]) 02:13, 20 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::There was no cherry picking. Karekin Pasdermadjian, member of Armenian Revolutionary Federation at the time of events and the ambassador of the [[Democratic Republic of Armenia]] to the United States, would have a stronger say in figures than some Dadayan, member of the Soviet Armenian Academy of Sciences, several decades later. The estimate provided by Pasdermadjian, who was a nationalist, seems to match the figure provided by Azerbaijani (opposite) and independent sources, thus more reliable than some claim by Dadayan. 
:::Also, Firuz Kazemzadeh, Professor Emeritus of History at Yale University and the author of &quot;Struggle for Transcaucasia: 1917-1921&quot;, is a more reliable and neutral reference on the subject than Dadayan whose subject of study was not specifically the period of 1918-1921.
:::Finally, I am not sure why you try to move Bakinskiy Rabochiy reference to the text of the article. It has not been removed in my edits, just moved to the notes section. I actually plan to do that with all quotations, because it makes the text clearer for reading.[[User:Atabəy|Atabəy]] ([[User talk:Atabəy|talk]]) 16:24, 20 September 2011 (UTC)
== File:Arf logo.jpg Nominated for Deletion ==

{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Arf logo.jpg|File:Arf logo.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Media without a source as of 29 March 2012'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[commons:File:Arf logo.jpg|image page (File:Arf logo.jpg)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 04:53, 29 March 2012 (UTC)
|}

== Biased and incomplete ==

It's probably obvious to many readers that this article is more sympathetic to the Muslim side.  Although informative and with lots of references, I assume  a more balanced  description is possible.  In particular, there's precious little mention of '''world war 1''', not to mention the '''armenian genocide''' just  in neighboring Turkey where something like 1.2 M were killed.  Search for the word 'genocide' and only one of many refers to the Armenian one.  You can't tell me that the Azeri genocide wasn't influenced heavily by the Armenian genocide.  [[User:OsamaBinLogin|OsamaBinLogin]] ([[User talk:OsamaBinLogin|talk]]) 07:58, 31 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>36elh0ys876m83yoi7wt13tp6rv611s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
