<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Wounded Knee Massacre</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>395018</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747519645</id>
      <parentid>743082488</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-02T21:08:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>38.102.240.66</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* US victory? */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13176">{{Talk header|search=yes}}

{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1={{WikiProject Indigenous peoples of North America|class=c}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=b
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|US=yes}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=c|importance=High|ND=yes|ND-importance=High|USOldwest=Yes|USOldwest-importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject South Dakota|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject National Register of Historic Places|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Indigenous peoples of the Americas|class=c|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=b|importance=mid}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-12-29|oldid1=16335536|date2=2005-12-29|oldid2=33182518|date3=2006-12-29|oldid3=97142623|date4=2013-12-29|oldid4=588227081|date5=2015-12-29|oldid5=697087815}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Wounded Knee Massacre/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot= lowercase sigmabot III |age= |units= 30 days}}

== Image vandalism?  Skyrim guard edited into image on main page ==
Yeah, I think this is the reference to the arrow meme.  It's completely out of place here, and quite tasteless, nevermind being completely irrelevant. &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:94.173.229.73|94.173.229.73]] ([[User talk:94.173.229.73|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/94.173.229.73|contribs]]) 2 August 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; (UTC) 

== US victory? ==
How come the infobox reads ''United States victory''? The US soldiers weren NOT fighting against a foreign army. They were fighting against Lakota Indians, born on American soil. --[[User:AndeanThunder|AndeanThunder]] ([[User talk:AndeanThunder|talk]]) 19:50, 1 February 2009 (UTC)

:The Sioux considered themselves a sovereign nation, and were recognized as such by the U.S., although the U.S. considered the Indian tribes to be &quot;domestic dependent nations&quot; rather than independent nations.  Thus, the U.S. could make treaties with the Sioux, send them ambassadors, or make war on them, just as with other nations.  Not until the Indian Nationality Act, in 1924, did the U.S. cease to recognize the Indian tribes as nations and declare Indian people to be simply citizens of the U.S.  Ultimately, that's the significance of Wounded Knee; the tragic end of the last effort by an Indian tribe to survive as an independent nation.  [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] ([[User talk:Piratedan|talk]]) 17:03, 11 February 2009 (UTC)

::My problem with the infobox is that it treats this the same way as any other battle in a declared war. But it certainly wasn't a battle. I have to admit that I don't have a neutral point of view on the topic (I don't think one is possible, or even desirable), but it seems clear to me that what happened between the indian removal act and wounded knee was not a war and wounded knee was not a battle. Leaving it like this is both false and insulting.  The US troops at wounded knee didn't 'win' anything, they slaughtered a bunch of people. Under My Lai Massacre, there's a much more reasonable sort of infobox. [[Special:Contributions/146.115.123.180|146.115.123.180]] ([[User talk:146.115.123.180|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 01:42, 12 May 2009 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::I just noticed that sometime back in March, somebody changed the &quot;Result&quot; in the infobox from &quot;US victory / Great loss&quot; to &quot;US / Great loss,&quot; which makes no sense whatsoever.

:::As I said below, Wounded Knee was both a battle and a massacre; there were armed Miniconjou warriors who fought the U.S. [[7th Cavalry]] troopers (arguably with justification), and in what was essentially a single action the 7th Cavalry crushed the warriors' resistance and indiscriminately slaughtered the warriors' families and children.  (This is easily distinguishable from My Lai, where all of the US soldiers' victims were unarmed and unresisting).  In my mind, to the extent that Wounded Knee was a battle, it was indisputably a US victory, albeit not one that many Americans (including myself) are proud of today.  I am therefore in favor of changing the infobox back to &quot;US victory.&quot;  Thoughts? [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] ([[User talk:Piratedan|talk]]) 18:23, 11 August 2009 (UTC)
::::I am repulsed by the idea of seeing Wounded Knee as a victory (if anything it was a defeat for civilization), but thats not really an argument. I tend to agree with 146.115.123.180 that the infobox used at the my lai massacre is more tasteful and considerate. At the very least if we follow the argument of a short battle followed by an extended massacre we should use both infoboxes to show the US soldiers changing category from victors to perpetrators in a matter of minutes. [[User:Maunus|·Maunus·&lt;span class=&quot;Unicode&quot;&gt;ƛ&lt;/span&gt;·]] 18:41, 11 August 2009 (UTC)
:::::Although I sympathize with your feeling of repulsion, I argue that the &quot;Result&quot; category should simply say who won, regardless of what criminal or horrific actions the winners perpetrated.  By analogy, the infobox for [[Battle of Agincourt]] says &quot;Decisive English victory,&quot; without reference to the fact that Henry V, in violation of all rules of chivalry, massacred hundreds of French prisoners.  Or for a perhaps better example, the infobox in [[Massacre of Elphinstone's Army]] simply says &quot;Afghan victory,&quot; even though the 12,000 civilians butchered by the Afghans vastly outnumbered the actual regulars in British uniform killed.  When we say something is a victory, we're not necessarily saying that it was a good thing; we're just saying who prevailed at the end of the fight. [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] ([[User talk:Piratedan|talk]]) 20:12, 11 August 2009 (UTC)
::::::As I said, I realize that personal sentiment is not an argument.[[User:Maunus|·Maunus·&lt;span class=&quot;Unicode&quot;&gt;ƛ&lt;/span&gt;·]] 20:31, 11 August 2009 (UTC)
:::::::Well, an anonymous editor followed [[WP:Be bold]] and changed the result to &quot;Native force massacred.&quot;  I'm almost OK with this, but to me &quot;force&quot; suggests military effectives only, and gives short shrift to the civilians killed.  How about &quot;Native band massacred&quot; or &quot;Sioux band massacred&quot;?  [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] ([[User talk:Piratedan|talk]]) 13:41, 12 August 2009 (UTC)
:::::::::I'd agree with either of those.[[User:Maunus|·Maunus·&lt;span class=&quot;Unicode&quot;&gt;ƛ&lt;/span&gt;·]] 13:53, 12 August 2009 (UTC)
What I find most self serving is the part of the info box that lists the participants as the 7th calvary and &quot;Sioux warriors&quot; when most of the casualties consisted of women and children and what &quot;warriors&quot; there were were in the process of being disarmed. In the Sand Creek Massacre box it lists some of the casualties as being &quot;civilians&quot; when again the vast majority of those killed were women and children and it was a friendly encampment. Medals of bravery were awarded rather than any punishment. These soldiers were little more than criminal, murdering, yelow cowards.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Tonegunman|Tonegunman]] ([[User talk:Tonegunman|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Tonegunman|contribs]]) 02:08, 3 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I agree that this is a shameful moment in American history; but the view at the time was that it was a battle, and that America was victorious. So it's historically accurate to record it as such. Furthermore, I find that recording it as such highlights the immorality of the action by emphasizing the delusion that it was a just military action. If the article neutrally described a mere military action, you'd be correct to be outraged. But the article describes in quite some detail the unjust massacre. I don't think a reader, who reads even just a portion of the entry, can come away with confusion about this matter.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/88.64.17.213|88.64.17.213]] ([[User talk:88.64.17.213|talk]]) 06:23, 14 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

There is NO confusion on the subject. A group of armed cavalry soldiers attacking women and children? No doubt their husbands, father's and brothers were fighting back. But a U.S. victory? Shameful.
[[User:1blackandwhite|1blackandwhite]] ([[User talk:1blackandwhite|talk]]) 14:51, 19 August 2016 (UTC)

== Charged Language ==
Can we avoid charged language?  Please remove from the InfoBox, perpetrators and helpless victims.  Please stick to combatants whichever side you wanted to win.

== Weapons and casualties ==

The article mentions that the cavalry had four Hotchkiss guns on the ridge above the meeting place, but it doesn't specify which type of Hotchkiss gun. There were two, one a light artillery piece, and the other a revolving machine gun. Wikipedia has two separate articles on these guns, and both articles claim theirs was the weapon used at Wounded Knee. I think the confusion here needs clearing up, since the use and effect of the two different weapons would be very different. The high level of collateral damage to the US troopers, along with the large number of non-combatants killed, would seem to indicate that it was the machine gun which was used that day, rather than the cannon – unless the latter was loaded with a version of &quot;grapeshot.&quot; 

As to casualties, I wouldn't take the word of the burial party necessarily, since the article states that they didn't begin to clean up the site until several days had passed; in that time, things may have been changed. Was a guard posted at the site? Dee Brown's book cites a number of Indian eye-witnesses, and it's disturbing to see that none of those are used in the article itself. Those sources allege that after the Indians had piled up their weapons, the soldiers conducted a second search to make sure, and came up with mostly axes and knives, which they also took. A third search was then instituted, in the course of which Black Coyote revealed his weapon and his unwillingness to part with it. On the face of it then, it seems unlikely that Black Coyote, deaf or not, didn't understand what was going on. Brown's sources note he was considered a trouble-maker by his own people. A second consequence may be that it is equally unlikely that there were several Indians who, all through these three searches, had successfully concealed weapons under their blankets, and who then pulled them out and began firing, once Black Coyote's weapon had discharged. The source for this statement appears to be Lt. Garlington, but consider that he would have every reason, after the event, to portray the soldiers as merely reacting to a provocation, rather than (as appears to be the case) participating in a classic FUBAR event. 

As to the medals, even though standards did change in the twentieth century, making the medal harder to get, the number awarded for this &quot;battle&quot; seems excessive. Perhaps a comparison with the number awarded at a Civil War battle might serve as a benchmark, say, Antietam? To me it seems like a case of the military &quot;cleaning up&quot; a FUBAR by (1) declaring a victory and (2) awarding a bunch of medals. That way, none of the injured participants will raise too much of a fuss about being victims of friendly fire. It would be interesting to know whether all of the MofH winners were wounded? [[User:Theonemacduff|Theonemacduff]] ([[User talk:Theonemacduff|talk]]) 01:25, 25 March 2009 (UTC)

:The [[Hotchkiss gun]] article shows the non-repeating 42mm cannon with one barrel and the Repeating Cannon with a Gatling-like bundle of three barrels. In the photo in this article, I can see only one barrel on each gun, so they must be the cannons, unless the fourth one, not shown in the photo, was a Repeating Cannon. [[User:Hieronymus Illinensis|Hieronymus Illinensis]] ([[User talk:Hieronymus Illinensis|talk]]) 06:01, 23 July 2012 (UTC)

::I made the edit on the page a year ago, but just to clarify here for reference, I confirmed through another source (though not 100% spelled-out) that they used four [[M1875 mountain gun]]s, 1.65in, which were at the time also just shorthanded to &quot;Hotchkiss guns.&quot; I don't know what kind of shells were used. [[User:SamuelRiv|SamuelRiv]] ([[User talk:SamuelRiv|talk]]) 00:22, 13 June 2016 (UTC)

== Spotted Elk / Big Foot caption ==

Never mind. Bigfoot IS Spotted Elk.</text>
      <sha1>hhf63o1i2wlwz9fu10n5sz2bwckrcp4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
