<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Tom Carper</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3903658</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717884907</id>
      <parentid>689294363</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-30T08:58:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot</username>
        <id>27446209</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>subst /Comments to [[WP:DCS|discontinue comments subpage]]) ([[Project:AWB|AWB]] [12009]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10939">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|blp=yes|activepol=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=yes|class=B|activepol=yes|politician-work-group=yes|politician-priority=mid|listas=Carper, Thomas R.}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=B|importance=mid|DE=yes|DE-importance=mid|USgovernors=yes|USgovernors-importance=low|listas=Carper, Thomas R.}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B|US=yes|B-Class-1= yes|B-Class-2= yes|B-Class-3= yes|B-Class-4= yes|B-Class-5= yes}}
{{WikiProject U.S. Congress|class=B|importance=mid|subject=person}}
}}

== Wrong Information ==
According to the New York Times Online (http://www.nytimes.com/ref/elections/2006/DE.html) Carper won the 2006 Senate election with 70% of the vote, not 67%. Can someone explain where the vote percentage for 2006 in the Infobox came from? [[User:U R A GR8 M8|U R A GR8 M8]] 07:40, 14 June 2007 (UTC)
* I'm not sure where that 67% came from. Could have been a mistake in math, since there was a Libertarian candidate for that office that garnered 1.1% of the vote. The [http://elections.delaware.gov/archive/elect06/elect06_general/html/elect06_general_office.shtml official Delaware election results] show Carper with 70.2% and Ting with 28.7%. I've corrected that in the main article, with slight rounding to conform to the round numbers from the other elections.[[User:Dcmacnut|Dcmacnut]] 13:52, 14 June 2007 (UTC)

== Spousal and child abuse ==
Does anyone know how legitimate these accusations of spousal and child abuse mentioned in this article are?  If they were proven untrue, as it seems they were (see the letter from the Chief Judge of the Family Court), I believe that should be more strongly noted.  Right now it seems like they were true and he just managed to politically survive them.
[[User:68.204.200.39|68.204.200.39]] 04:10, 31 January 2006

:Information in wikipedia - particularly negative information about a person - MUST be [[wikipedia:verifiable|verifiable]].  If the article is going to state that Carper abused his wife, then it needs a high-quality link/reference.  Otherwise, this needs to stay out.

:For what it's worth, the ONLY websites where Google shows such statements are this article and all of its mirrors, as far as I can tell.  [[User:John Broughton|John Broughton]] 13:12, 13 June 2006 (UTC)

:better attribution for the version at this moment added. [[User:Stilltim|stilltim]] 22:37, 13 June 2006 (UTC)

OP, here are some sources about this. Tom Carper admitted to &quot;slapping&quot; his wife. 
:http://articles.philly.com/1996-10-22/news/25664401_1_martha-carper-delaware-republican-party-delawareans ([[Tom Carper]] &quot;admitted slapping his first wife once during their marriage. The admission was initially reported in 1982 by the [[New York Post]].&quot;)
:http://www.delawaregrapevine.com/11-12carper.asp ('''[[Tom Carper]]:  &quot;Did I slap my wife 20 years ago? Yes.&quot;''' There is some suggestion that Carper does this to garner the &quot;sympathy&quot; vote... sickening &amp; disgusting)
:http://www.delawareliberal.net/2008/06/20/tom-carper-really-is-a-vicious-killer/ 
:http://www.delawareliberal.net/2010/10/12/her-masters-voice/ (&quot;Geezer: Re: [[Tom Carper]] beating up his wife. Thats not only true but was verified by the babysitter at the time. A history professor at the UofD’s and his wife lived next door to the Carper family. The wife many times saw Carpers wife with bumps and bruises. The wife was babysitting for the Carpers and knew the truth about Tom. It was kept secret from the press, but those who knew the Professor and his wife knew the truth. We don’t need men who use domestic violence against women anywhere near public office.&quot;)
:https://italkyoubored.wordpress.com/2014/02/15/roger-stone-pretty-reckless-is-going-straight-to-hell-part-eight/ (Ann Stone held a news conference where she made a stunning accusation. There were, said Stone, sealed court records which proved that [[Tom Carper]] abused his wife. Further, Stone said, “people in Delaware I trust,” had told her it was true. '''Carper had admitted to slapping his first wife once during their marriage''' in documents from a 1981 child custody dispute.)
:https://delaware.craigslist.org/rnr/5251717774.html (SENATOR TOM CARPER BEAT HIS FIRST WIFE SO BADLY (True City) That she sought shelter at People's Place in Milford. yep THOMAS CARPER BEAT MISS DELAWARE, AND THE NEWS URINAL STAYS SILENT......Funny how the socialist jew media pretends they care about women, yet has played cover-up for this pathetic cowardly excuse for a man for over 35 years. I just don't understand how women from delawre can keep electing a cowardly wife beater.)
[[User:Sir04995|Sir04995]] ([[User talk:Sir04995|talk]]) 19:32, 5 November 2015 (UTC)

:thank you, sir.
[[User:Mayipleasehaveanother|Mayipleasehaveanother]] ([[User talk:Mayipleasehaveanother|talk]]) 04:49, 6 November 2015 (UTC)

== Change of name of article? ==
Wikipedia naming convention is FirstName Lastname, no middle initial, unless the middle initial is needed for disambiguation - see [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (people)]].  A google search shows 77K ghits for &quot;Thomas Carper&quot; and 60K ghits for &quot;Thomas F. Carper&quot;, so this isn't absolutely clearcut, but I don't see any reason for the middle initial, and would like the opinion of others on moving this article to &quot;Thomas Carper&quot;, which is currently a redirect.   [[User:John Broughton|John Broughton]] 13:08, 15 September 2006 (UTC)
*Thanks for asking, but please do not change this. The middle initial is optional per the naming convention, and is appropriate here because it is the form of the name used by most official references, and it is the form of the name he generally uses. IMO for members of the U.S. Congress we should always use the form Congress uses, in this case, [http://a257.g.akamaitech.net/7/257/2422/26jan20061725/www.gpoaccess.gov/serialset/cdocuments/hd108-222/108th.pdf], unless we have to expand it to diambiguate. [[User:Stilltim|stilltim]] 01:26, 17 September 2006 (UTC)

::Thank you for the enlightment; I'll drop the suggestion.   [[User:John Broughton|John Broughton]] 19:16, 17 September 2006 (UTC)

Question: if it is common to use the nickname for politicians (like [[Ted Kennedy]] or [[Chuck Grassley]]), why don't we use Tom Carper for the name of the article? Or is he referred mostly as Thomas R. Carper? [[User:Cassandro|Cassandro]] ([[User talk:Cassandro|talk]]) 20:59, 17 January 2009 (UTC)

=== &quot;Tom&quot; vs. &quot;Thomas R.&quot; ===
I think it should be [[Tom Carper]].  His senate website, http://carper.senate.gov, is titled &quot;Thomas R. Carper…&quot; but most of the references there are to &quot;Tom.&quot;  After all, if he goes by &quot;Tom&quot; AND WP policy says we should use &quot;Tom&quot; then why make an exception here?   Readers are going to search for &quot;Tom&quot; and Google will prefer &quot;Tom.&quot;  Those are WP standards.  —[[User talk:Markles|Markles]] 14:24, 16 June 2009 (UTC)
:I see both names used, but the subject's own campaign website uses &quot;Tom&quot;, so that is a good indication that it's the preferred name. &amp;nbsp; &lt;b&gt;[[User:Will Beback|&lt;font color=&quot;#595454&quot;&gt;Will Beback&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp; [[User talk:Will Beback|&lt;font color=&quot;#C0C0C0&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp; &lt;/b&gt; 19:26, 16 June 2009 (UTC)
:*{{done}}.  (Also see [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (common names)]].) —[[User talk:Markles|Markles]] 21:55, 28 June 2009 (UTC)

==Infobox==
Although I don't agree, I suppose it is reasonable to accept the argument that incumbent office holders should use the office specific infobox, instead of the generic politician infobox that appropriately notes their other important offices, but there is no need to use nicknames when the Congress itself uses the full form of the name. Further, the word &quot;term,&quot; generally refers to the full time elected, not time served. If you want it to say the later, please change the label. I don't much care for the use of this infobox, nor the label, but in an effort to be cooperative, only insist that if this template must be used, it contain quality information. I will be restoring this information as discussed and would appreciate your consideration of my points and my efforts to reach a consensus. [[User:Stilltim|stilltim]] 02:54, 17 November 2006 (UTC)
:In order to conform with wikipedia's 'don't perdict the future' policy, terms of office should not contain future dates in which terms will expire or officials will run for reelection.  As can be seen by skiming other wikipedia political articles, both on American and foreign leaders, term refers to time served, not the time for which the leader is elected.  If you feel placing a full name in the top of the infobox is that important, I'm not going to argue.  But I do know that the term box should not contain future dates.  I personally have gotten criticized for attempting the change the dates on the retiring Senators Sarbanes and Dayton to 2007, but I was overrun with complaints stating that adding a date in which a term expires does not correspond to wikipedia standards.  I completely understand your point as to why you are changing the dates, but from what I've been told over and over, this is an incorrect pratice.  Please excuse my action, but I must revert that change.[[User:VitaleBaby|VitaleBaby]] 04:07, 17 November 2006 (UTC)

== Biased, promotional, propagandistic ==

This article reads as if it was developed by Carper campaign staff, and/or the Delaware State Chamber of Commerce.  I don't have time now to do much on it, but in its present form it reflects very poorly on Wikipedia.

Alan Muller  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/8.24.110.70|8.24.110.70]] ([[User talk:8.24.110.70|talk]]) 17:02, 19 June 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=973|lastedit=20090628215358|comment=
*The framework for this article is '''COMPLETE''' and meets the current standard for this series of articles, including:
:introductory paragraph, section formatting, and categories 
:infobox, succession boxes, nav boxes, public offices table and election results table
:references, links, and places with information
*suggestions for future improvements:
#additional detail about the economic situation in Delaware in the late 20th century
#additional details about the issues and accomplishments of Carper's term as governor
#additional details about the issues and accomplishments of Carper's term as senator
*The best known sources for additional information are: '''(please add others known to you)'''
#{{cite book| last {{nw=}} Cohen| first {{nw=}} Celia| authorlink {{nw=}}| coauthors {{nw=}} | year {{nw=}} 2002| title {{nw=}} Only in Delaware, Politics and Politicians in the First State| publisher {{nw=}} Grapevine Publishing, LLC| location {{nw=}}| id {{nw=}}}}
[[User:Stilltim|stilltim]] 01:42, 31 August 2006 (UTC)}}
Substituted at 08:58, 30 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qnxzseuhwjyxb463war68q9ylbjy5zj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
