<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Bombing of Dresden in World War II</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>19961816</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748063629</id>
      <parentid>748052957</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-06T03:28:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Bombing of Dresden in World War II/Archive 18]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11960">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{Automatic archive navigator}}
|maxarchivesize = 200K
|counter = 18
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Bombing of Dresden in World War II/Archive %(counter)d
}}

{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=4 April 2007
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=119926199
|currentstatus=FGAN
|topic=war
}}
{{Not a forum}}
{{Controversial}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B
|B-Class-1=yes
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|Aviation-task-force=yes
|British-task-force=yes
|German-task-force=yes
|US-task-force=yes
|WWII-task-force=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Alternative Views}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-02-14|oldid1=16335606|date2=2006-02-13|oldid2=38352814|date3=2007-02-13|oldid3=107925216|date4=2008-02-13|oldid4=191083115|date5=2009-02-13|oldid5=270463804|date6=2010-02-13|oldid6=343664962|date7=2013-02-13|oldid7=538002039|date8=2015-02-13|oldid8=646620952}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=30|dounreplied=yes}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Bombing of Dresden in World War II/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Bombing of Dresden in World War II/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}

== Counting dead ==

Counting casualties is a bit mean, in that reduces to numbers the personal tragedies involved, however, with 3'900 tons of bombs dropped on Dresden, the figure in article, of 22'000 to 25'000 victims, would yield around 6 victims per ton of bombs, that seems quite low for the densely populated, several stories buildings residential area Dresden was then, and continues being. The 135'000 overal casualties figure that David Irving proposed in his early 70s book: 'The destruction of Dresden', looks more realistic, but this historian was put in jail later in XX century, in Austria, under the accusation of: 'Holocaust denial', that even if it were an untrue accusation, I won't discuss this, would reduce the credibility of his writings. 135'000 (one hundred and thirty five thousand) may be the accurate balance of victims from the two days of 1945 Dresden bombings, that destroyed also the home where Richard Wagner lived, one of the composers loved by A Hitler, with the peculiar element that the piece favourite to A H was in its structure and general sound somehow close to the baroque work by the great British composer Henry Purcell. Regards, + Salut--[[User:Caula|Caula]] ([[User talk:Caula|talk]]) 20:38, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
:Irving's work on Dresden is not considered credible, nor are estimates of 100,000+; the death toll is generally put at 25,000 to 35,000. See the [https://www.hdot.org/evans/# Evans Report] on Irving's distortions regarding this issue (and others). Even ''without'' taking into account the issue of Holocaust denial, his work has still been heavily criticized. [[User:GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:GeneralizationsAreBad|gab]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:47, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::Casualties were limited by the well-practiced use of air raid shelters, and the high proportion of civilians was due to poor knowledge of local shelters by refugees (mostly former settlers of the recently occupied and then lost territories annexed from Poland and the USSR). The 20-22,000 was arrived by a double entry bookkeeping, of counting dead bodies against missing ration holders and was arrived at by both the Nazis (as per their internal reports) at the time, and much later by a group of historians who had little reason to fudge the numbers. All other estimates have good reasons for overestimating casualties and are therefore suspect.[[User:NiD.29|&amp;#32;- NiD.29]] ([[User talk:NiD.29|talk]]) 12:27, 10 October 2016 (UTC)

== Falsified figure? ==

As I understand it, the German medical authorities offered a figure of 260,000 dead and stated that others in the centre of the city were disintegrated. The figure of 20,000 referred to those victims who could be identified and named. A website of 2016 states a figure of 10,000 deaths. Such a figure would be a seventh of the deaths during the bombing of Hamburg - it is ludicrous.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/1.144.96.234|1.144.96.234]] ([[User talk:1.144.96.234#top|talk]]) 03:58, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The death toll is fully discussed in the article. This is not a page for debate, only for offering improvements to the article. [[User:Rmhermen|Rmhermen]] ([[User talk:Rmhermen|talk]]) 04:17, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::The 22,000 refers to the total number of actual dead rather than being an estimate - the Germans had incredibly good records thanks to almost everyone being on rations. The death toll was relatively low because they had a very effective system for getting people under cover during air raids, and Dresden was at the limit of the RAF and USAAF's range, so the Germans had more than their usual amount of time to take cover. The majority of casualties were civilian refugees who had the least preparation and experience for doing so and they tried to use whatever cover they could find, which included the basements of buildings that were not adequately fireproofed. That Kurt Vonnegut survived on the surface (as a POW and hence of low priority for the Germans) should tell you something in that regard.[[User:NiD.29|&amp;#32;- NiD.29]] ([[User talk:NiD.29|talk]]) 16:08, 30 October 2016 (UTC)

== Blitz ==

The bombing of England extended beyond London. I (born 1947) grew up in a Liverpool street, about two miles from the docks, where three houses had been bombed. It was a slum area, so the houses were never rebuilt ([[User:Pamour|Pamour]] ([[User talk:Pamour|talk]]) 22:10, 19 October 2016 (UTC)).

== War crime / Claim==
{{hat|Clear consensus against the edit demonstrated. Discussion now Hijacked by suspicious I.P. activity. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 20:02, 31 October 2016 (UTC)}}
Given the enduring controversy, the allegations that the raid was a war crime need to be included in the lede. ([[User:Dsklw|Dsklw]] ([[User talk:Dsklw|talk]]) 17:59, 30 October 2016 (UTC))
:I would suggest you would be better off expanding the existing sections dealing with this debate. If consensus indicates  it should be in the lede, it should be reworded in a [[WP:NPOV]] style. See [[WP:LEDE]]. It is an ongoing debate, and you should mention that others disagree that it was a &quot;war crime&quot;. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 18:15, 30 October 2016 (UTC)
::: A single sentence saying some think it was a war crime in the lead does not accurately reflect the body of the article. The controversy of the bombing is already mentioned in the lead, and the arguments for it being or not being a war crime are made fully in their own section. Please abide by [[WP:BRD]] while it is discussed. ([[User:Hohum|&lt;font color=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;'''Hohum'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Hohum|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;@&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]) 18:18, 30 October 2016 (UTC)
::::I think there should be some mention in the lede because the raid was widely regarded as a war crime under the international laws on aerial warfare at the time, unlike other Allied raids on Germany in World War II. ([[User:Dsklw|Dsklw]] ([[User talk:Dsklw|talk]]) 18:25, 30 October 2016 (UTC))
:::::I don't believe that the current consensus is for inclusion, as three editors have disagreed with the addition. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 03:34, 31 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::Please see [[Aerial bombardment and international law#International law up to 1945]]. Your assertion that it was &quot;widely regarded as a war crime under the international laws on aerial warfare at the time..&quot; is unsupported and incorrect. It was a defended city, which existing laws at the time made it a legitimate target for attack. It was also a major supplier of war-related components, despite the myth of it being an &quot;innocent&quot; target. The debate amongst historians continues, and your proposed edit is [[WP:UNDUE]]. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 03:51, 31 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Dresden was neither defended nor a military target. Churchill admitted the raid was illegal at the time. ([[User:Bndjs|Bndjs]] ([[User talk:Bndjs|talk]]) 07:43, 31 October 2016 (UTC))
::::::::Thanks but Wikipedia requires [[WP:RS|reliable sources]], not opinions or wild claims. [[User:Johnuniq|Johnuniq]] ([[User talk:Johnuniq|talk]]) 08:20, 31 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::Churchill famously wrote in 1945 that the city was not a military target and the raid was ordered simply to kill civilians. ([[User:Bndjs|Bndjs]] ([[User talk:Bndjs|talk]]) 08:33, 31 October 2016 (UTC))
{{od}}
First, everything in Germany was a defended target thanks to the Luftwaffe, second, Dresden was a major center of manufacture of a wide variety of war materiel, third, it was the centerpiece in the German defence against the advancing Russians as well as being one of the largest transportation hubs in Germany, and quotes taken out of context from years later when Churchill was senile hardly count as references.[[User:NiD.29|&amp;#32;- NiD.29]] ([[User talk:NiD.29|talk]]) 15:09, 31 October 2016 (UTC)
:The Luftwaffe no longer existed in 1945. Churchill wrote in February 1945 that Dresden was bombed only to terrorize the civilian population. ([[Special:Contributions/81.159.6.116|81.159.6.116]] ([[User talk:81.159.6.116|talk]]) 15:42, 31 October 2016 (UTC))
::[[WP:DNFTT]] may be applicable at this point; should this discussion be hatted? [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 15:50, 31 October 2016 (UTC)
:::Indeed. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 15:56, 31 October 2016 (UTC)
::::I don't think this requires discussion. Not even the arch-detractors (Grayling and his mob) have been able to show, beyond opinion, this was a war crime. In any case, international law permitted bombing of this kind or certainly didn't regard it as criminal. I also think the IP shows a lack of appreciation for how dangerous air operations were in 1945. Does he care to know how many Bomber Command crews lost their lives at the hands of this &quot;non-existent Luftwaffe&quot; in 1945? [[User:Dapi89|Dapi89]] ([[User talk:Dapi89|talk]]) 17:38, 31 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::Bomber Command crews were only terrorists like ISIS and al Queda. Churchill admitted in his secret note that the raid was only ordered to terrorize German civilians, and that the myths about Dresden being a military target were only used as a pretext for the terrorism. ([[Special:Contributions/81.159.6.116|81.159.6.116]] ([[User talk:81.159.6.116|talk]]) 17:41, 31 October 2016 (UTC))
{{hab}}

== Churchill's secret memo / Another claim==
{{hat|OP indeffed as sock. [[User:Johnuniq|Johnuniq]] ([[User talk:Johnuniq|talk]]) 01:38, 6 November 2016 (UTC)}}
Churchill's secret memo on 28 March 1945, in which he admitted Dresden was only bombed in order to spread terror among the civilian population, should be mentioned in the intro as it proves the city had no military significance, despite later claims. ([[User:Sjdkl&amp;#59;|Sjdkl&amp;#59;]] ([[User talk:Sjdkl&amp;#59;|talk]]) 17:29, 5 November 2016 (UTC))
:&lt;s&gt;*A case of [[WP:DNFTT]]?&lt;/s&gt; [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 17:48, 5 November 2016 (UTC)
::Huh? I'm just saying the secret memo should be mentioned in the intro. ([[User:Sjdkl&amp;#59;|Sjdkl&amp;#59;]] ([[User talk:Sjdkl&amp;#59;|talk]]) 18:05, 5 November 2016 (UTC))
:::This was discussed recently in the thread immediately above: &quot;War crime / Claim&quot;. The consensus was not to include such material in the lead. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 18:17, 5 November 2016 (UTC)
{{hab}}</text>
      <sha1>9om06m0s1utt3gyhmqj5hp092u3hvrw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
