<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Confederate States of America</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>80804</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745639512</id>
      <parentid>745542687</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-22T10:33:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheVirginiaHistorian</username>
        <id>9266570</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Wrong Flag */ You can help</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22377">{{Talk header}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 19
|algo = old(45d)
|archive = Talk:Confederate States of America/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes
}}
{{Article history|action1=GAN
|action1date=13 March 2007
|action1link=Talk:Confederate_States_of_America/Archive_3#GA_Failed
|action1result=failed
|currentstatus=FGAN}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=History|class=B}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject United States|class=B |importance=Top 
 |listas=Confederate States of America
 |LA=yes|LA-importance=Top |MS=yes|MS-importance=High|SC=yes|SC-importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=B|GOV-taskforce=yes
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
| b6 &lt;!--Accessibility          --&gt; = yes}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=b
&lt;!-- 1.suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations--&gt;|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2.reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies--&gt;|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3.defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content--&gt;|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4.free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5.contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams--&gt;|B-Class-5=yes
|US-task-force=yes|ACW-task-force=yes}}
}}
{{On this day|date1=2009-12-20|oldid1=332903046|date2=2010-12-20|oldid2=403276437|date3=2012-12-20|oldid3=528761630|date4=2013-12-20|oldid4=586755126|date5=2014-12-20|oldid5=638612474|date6=2015-12-20|oldid6=695968390}}
{{Controversial}}
{{Not a forum}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|small=yes|age=45}}

== Wrong year? ==

''Preparations for Lee's incursion into Pennsylvania were underway to influence the midterm U.S. elections. Confederate independence and nationhood was at a turning point. &quot;Southerners had a right to be optimistic, or at least hopeful, that their revolution would prevail, or at least endure&quot;. The result was a defeat at Gettysburg...''
:This seems to refer to Lee's first attempt to invade Pennsylvania (Sept. 1862), shortly before the mid-term elections, when Britain and France came closest to granting recognition to the Confederacy. It was Lee's defeat at Antietam, not Gettysburg, that killed this prospect. [[User:Valetude|Valetude]] ([[User talk:Valetude|talk]]) 12:51, 17 April 2016 (UTC)
::Material about consideration of influencing midterm U.S. elections was not to be found in referenced pages. It is removed. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 15:14, 18 April 2016 (UTC)
:::I can't add a better reference at the moment, but there is ample documentation of Lee's intention to influence the U. S. mid-term elections, including, IIRC, a letter or report from Lee himself.  See, e.g., Joseph L. Harsh, [https://books.google.com/books?id=FaFFBun_jC8C ''Taken at the Flood: Robert E. Lee and Confederate Strategy in the Maryland Campaign of 1862''].  In any event, unless unsourced matter is false or at best dubious, it's better to add a &quot;citation needed&quot; tag, rather than to delete it.  [[User:Jdcrutch|&lt;tt&gt;''J.&amp;nbsp;D.&amp;nbsp;Crutchfield''&lt;/tt&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jdcrutch|Talk]] 20:06, 18 April 2016 (UTC)
::::{{Ping|Valetude|Rjensen}} Valetude's point was that the &quot;midterm&quot; consideration was of 1862, which the Harsh title refers to, not Gettysburg's 1863 incursion, which was meant to threaten the capital at Washington DC and/or the mint at Philadelphia (see routes of march for elements of Lee's army at turn-around for Gettysburg). 
::::The capture of gold from Philadelphia (as had been taken from the mints at New Orleans, Georgia and North Carolina) and the subsequent capture of DC (or a demonstration before its fortifications) would have influenced the presidential election of 1864 as well as down ticket elections, so yes, I personally POV agree with your speculation. It just doesn't conform with the pagination of the reliable source referenced. In any case, nesting favorite facts into the narrative as referenced WITHOUT sourcing is bad practice. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 04:33, 19 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::the statement is correct re 1862 and Antietam.  See {{cite book|author=John David Hoptak|title=The Battle of South Mountain|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WKnw9izfNZEC&amp;pg=PA16|year=2011|page=16}}  [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 06:20, 19 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::Thanks to Rjensen for the citation.  In an article about the CSA, I'd use ''Sharpsburg'', rather than Antietam, just as we'd use British spelling conventions in an article on England.  [[User:Jdcrutch|&lt;tt&gt;''J.&amp;nbsp;D.&amp;nbsp;Crutchfield''&lt;/tt&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jdcrutch|Talk]] 17:48, 19 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Agree, but. My preference is to name battles here after the style, &quot;Sharpsburg (Antietam)&quot; -- so as BOTH to conform with the preponderance of sources using &quot;Antietam&quot;, AND to allow for Southron eccentricity. But I am not sure my POV can fly in an encyclopedia for the general reader.

:::::::So {{Ping|Jdcrutch}} -- we are agreed to delete &quot;to influence the midterm U.S. elections&quot; for Gettysburg in 1863, and make the narrative conform to the source in Thomas as referenced -- and now confirmed -- both in Harsh and Hoptak -- that strategic consideration applies only to 1862? The elections in 1863 were in the spring for U.S. (Federal) Government in West Virginia and Virginia Confederate state offices -- Gettysburg was too late to effect those. As Hoptak put it on page 16, “In early September 1862...The 1862 midterm elections were less than two months away&quot;. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 04:28, 20 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::::{{done}}. also, note that the section is under &quot;diplomacy&quot;, and the &quot;midterm U.S. elections&quot; is a domestic consideration. Information on the consideration of midterm elections introduced in the midst of material take from Emory Thomas is in the wrong year and wrong narrative section. Perhaps the sourced information belongs in &quot;military strategy&quot;.  [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 15:42, 21 April 2016 (UTC)

== &quot;The cause of slavery&quot; revert ==

On 19 April, Jdcrutch reverted a contribution by IP.97 as, “anonymous, unsourced, and based on an unjustified premise”.  The copyedit was &quot; In addition, abolitionist sentiment was on a steady rise in Britain, making any adhesion to the cause of slavery politically difficult [there].” 

Abolitionist sentiment among European nations in the 19th century is a well known development. The only “white” nation still tolerating slavery was the United States, which had during the Civil War begun emancipation under the Lincoln Administration. That left only the insurgents of the Confederacy supposing to constitutionally guarantee slavery into the twentieth century, -- making it very unlikely that Europeans would recognize it, whether or not the summer 1863 incursion at Gettysburg was successful. 

If that premise is not found in Blumenthal (1966), Jones (2009) or Owsley (1959), another source should be found to supplement the narrative on “diplomacy#international diplomacy”, pointing out that, &quot;abolitionist sentiment was on a steady rise in Britain, making any adhesion to the cause of slavery politically difficult [there].&quot; [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 09:23, 24 April 2016 (UTC)

::What &quot;whiteness&quot; has to do with anything is a mystery to me.  Does the writer mean to suggest that &quot;white nations&quot; (whatever those may be) are to be held to a higher moral standard than others?  Are we to understand that Brazilians and Cubans (let alone Mexicans, Chinese, Turks, and Arabs) were not &quot;white&quot; enough in 1863 to appreciate the enormity of slavery?  I really did not expect to see a racist variation on the &quot;They Deserved It&quot; theme advocated in the Twenty-first Century.

::Be that as it may, my chief objection to the assertion I reverted was that it seemed to be based on the premise, that the cause of the C.&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;A. was absolutely equivalent with &quot;the cause of slavery&quot;.  It is beyond reasonable dispute that the main precipitating cause for the secession of the first seven States that formed the C.&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;A.—and a powerful contributing cause for that of the States which seceded after Lincoln launched his war against the C.&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;A.—was the fear of their governing classes, that the Republican party, having achieved complete dominance in the federal government, would move to destroy the South's remaining political power by abolishing its economic foundation, ''viz''., slavery.  That fact, however, by no means makes the cause of the C.&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;A. absolutely equivalent with &quot;the cause of slavery&quot;.

::I would not object to something along the following lines, if properly supported by reference to reliable sources:

:::In addition, abolitionist sentiment, which portrayed the Confederate cause as a &quot;slaveholders' rebellion&quot;, was on a steady rise in Britain, making any action favorable to the CSA politically difficult.

::[[User:Jdcrutch|&lt;tt&gt;''J.&amp;nbsp;D.&amp;nbsp;Crutchfield''&lt;/tt&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jdcrutch|Talk]] 15:44, 25 April 2016 (UTC)

:::The subject is the Confederacy, Confederates called themselves a white Christian nation, yet were so blind to &quot;the enormity of slavery&quot; so as to guarantee its perpetuation constitutionally. As the &quot;cornerstone&quot; of the CSA was slavery, it follows the rebellion was absolutely equivalent with &quot;the cause of slavery&quot;. The economic value of exports in cotton would not have gone down without slavery, only the profit margins -- although some contemporaries believed wage labor was cheaper than slavery. Free black and slave labor was used in the Tredegar Iron Works, steel might have been had at Birmingham, Alabama with a rail connection or two. Slavery was a drag on Southern economic development, not its &quot;economic foundation&quot;. 

:::Not only did abolitionists consider the Confederate cause as a &quot;slaveholders' rebellion&quot;, so did most of the common soldiers fighting in grey, as they referred to the late conflict as a &quot;rich man's war and a poor man's fight.&quot; [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 16:19, 25 April 2016 (UTC)

::::The writer is free to present this one-sided, moralistic misrepresentation of history on his own web site, but it does not belong on Wikipedia.  I feel no need to answer his fallacious arguments here, as abler hands have long since refuted them.  [[User:Jdcrutch|&lt;tt&gt;''J.&amp;nbsp;D.&amp;nbsp;Crutchfield''&lt;/tt&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jdcrutch|Talk]] 16:32, 25 April 2016 (UTC)

:::::Many influential slave holders in the Confederacy intended to conquer Mexico to re-enslave people of color there, leaving &quot;white&quot; hidalgos free, imposing a race-based slavery as provided for in the Confederate Constitution. The slave power in Virginia successfully made it unconstitutional to abolish slavery in Virginia in the 1850 Convention and authorized removal of free blacks, because of their continuing fears of emancipation as sought by a majority of the white male voters, since abolition passed in 1832 in the House of Delegates but only failed in the malapportioned Virginia State Senate favoring slave &quot;property&quot; counties. The [http://avalon.law.yale.edu/19th_century/csa_csa.asp Confederate Constitution] reads, &quot;the institution of negro slavery, as it now exists in the Confederate States, shall be recognized and protected be Congress&quot;. That was, in the words of Jdcrutch, &quot;the enormity of slavery&quot; in the Confederate cause. -- Recalling that history is not a misrepresentation of it.  

:::::Your white-washing twist to history in an alternative text, &quot;abolitionist sentiment, which portrayed the Confederate cause as a &quot;slaveholders' rebellion&quot; is unsatisfactory as [[wp:weasel]] style. Amateur writers paraphrasing the Jefferson Davis post war defense of the Confederacy in a &quot;Lost Cause&quot; literature are not reliable sources for historical analysis and interpretation. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 11:10, 26 April 2016 (UTC)

{{od}}I think the writer ought to have looked up the word ''enormity'' in a dictionary.  [[User:Jdcrutch|&lt;tt&gt;''J.&amp;nbsp;D.&amp;nbsp;Crutchfield''&lt;/tt&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jdcrutch|Talk]] 21:01, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
:Okay, lets not use code words from a fringe subculture. &quot;enormity&quot; does not just mean &quot;big&quot;, it is &quot;a grave crime or sin&quot; it is &quot;something perceived as bad or morally wrong&quot; on a &quot;great or extreme scale, seriousness, or extent&quot; -- in the foundation of the Confederate States of America by its ruling slaveholders. 

:You will note that in most Confederate states, to ensure slaveholder rule, the voting franchise is more limited than that under the United States by state Constitutions promulgated by slave power fiat during the Rebellion, and large landowners owning slaves were exempted from an otherwise universal conscription at first...though the more restrictive Virginia Constitution proposed by the Secession Convention failed ratification by the people there. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 09:21, 27 April 2016 (UTC)

== Issues with the map of the CSA ==

The map's caption is &quot;The Confederate States in 1862. Light green denotes claims made by the Confederacy. Medium green denotes western counties of Virginia that separated from that State and were admitted to the Union as West Virginia. Teal denotes the rest of the Indian Territory that did not sign a treaty with the CSA.&quot;

Relevant:

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_treaties_of_the_Confederate_States_of_America

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Territory_in_the_American_Civil_War

The CSA had signed treaties with all of the tribes of the Indian Territory, which makes the caption factually incorrect. 

The map seems to be an attempt to show that the Indians in Indian Territory were divided in their sympathies, but it is not an accurate depiction of political geography of the Indian Territory. The Cherokees and Creeks were divided into factions which supported the South and factions that did not. The Indians that did not support the Confederacy fled to Kansas, leaving their lands in control of the factions of their tribes which supported the Confederacy. The Union did not regain control over the Cherokee and Creek lands in 1862, which is the year mentioned in the map's caption.

Can we get a more logical map?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.12.46.136|68.12.46.136]] ([[User talk:68.12.46.136|talk]]) 18:05, 24 April 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:{{Done}} I copy edited the caption to read, &quot;Teal denotes the still contested Indian Territory.&quot;  [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 08:21, 25 April 2016 (UTC)

== Were slaves &quot;African American&quot;? ==

Surely they were just African at that point? [[User:Mazz0|Mazz0]] ([[User talk:Mazz0|talk]]) 16:25, 13 July 2016 (UTC)

:No, they were African-American, see the earlier transition to Anglo-African at [https://www.amazon.com/Transformation-1740-1790-Published-Omohundro-Williamsburg/dp/080784814X The Transformation of Virginia, 1740-1790] by Rhys Isaac. By the way, the first Africans to Virginia from Angola were Roman Catholic, which on conversion to Anglican Protestantism, made them eligible for emancipation after seven years' service until the 1680s. See the interracial [[Bacon's Rebellion]] of 1676 for more context in the first half-century of slavery in America. Later, there were other streams of African immigrants from west Africa to America who were Animists and Muslim, but by the mid 1800s, the inroads of Baptists and Methodists proselytizing among slave populations in the First and [[Second Great Awakening]] had made the American-held slave an African-American. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 05:45, 14 July 2016 (UTC)

::All, or virtually all, slaves in the C. S. A. had been born in America; and their ancestors, generically speaking, had been settled in English-speaking America since the early seventeenth century; so they were at least as thoroughly ''American'' as their white neighbors, and modern usage would not consider them ''African''.  Polite usage in the 1860s might refer to them so, as reflected in the name of the ''African Methodist-Episcopal Church'', and the institution sometimes referred to as ''African slavery'' (though it was more common, I believe, to refer to them as ''negroes''—using a lower-case ''n''—or ''mulattoes'', respectively).  I would not favor Wikipedia's following that outdated practice.  Calling black Americans &quot;Africans&quot; seems to imply that they are (or were) not ''really'' Americans, and thereby to legitimate their unequal status in American society.  That subordinate status fostered the development of a distinct sub-culture (or several sub-cultures) among black Americans, but that was no less ''American'' than the New England Yankee sub-culture, the Pennsylvanian Quaker sub-culture, or the Virginian Cohee sub-culture, and no more ''African'' than those were ''British''.

::Whether or not, and under what circumstances, Wikipedia should refer to the slaves of the Confederate States as &quot;African American&quot; is an open question, as far as I'm aware.  There is an argument that all Americans of African ancestry should be referred to as ''African Americans'', regardless of context.  Alternatively, one could argue that Wikipedia should follow the polite usage of the time and place under discussion.  Then again, some white people appear to believe that they should use &quot;African American&quot; wherever somebody else might use &quot;black&quot;.  (I've even seen a reference to the plight of &quot;African Americans in South Africa&quot;!)  I'm not aware of any current scholarly consensus on the subject (and I confess I haven't tried to find out if there is one).  If there is one, we should follow that (even though I suspect I wouldn't like it, if current academic usage in other areas is any indication).

::My own preference is generally to refer to persons born in Africa as Africans (or according to their respective nationalities, if I know them), and to persons born in the United States (or the Confederate States, if there is ever a case where that matters) as Americans (or according to their respective States, if that seems appropriate).  If race or ancestry is significant, I try to use an inoffensive adjective or noun consistent with that practice.  I tend to prefer ''black'' over ''African American'', first, because it's a term black people chose for themselves as a badge of pride, when well-meaning white people tended to call them &quot;Negroes&quot;; and, second, because ''African American'' seems to suggest that white people like me, who are generally called &quot;American&quot;, without a modifier, are the ''real'' Americans—a notion I reject.

::In any event, in the present context, it certainly is not ''incorrect'' to refer to the slaves of the Confederate States as ''African Americans''; and it certainly is not ''preferable'', if it is acceptable at all, to refer to them as ''Africans''.  [[User:Jdcrutch|&lt;tt&gt;''J.&amp;nbsp;D.&amp;nbsp;Crutchfield''&lt;/tt&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jdcrutch|Talk]] 19:57, 14 July 2016 (UTC)
:::Well said, indeed! [[User:Cleopatran Apocalypse|Cleopatran Apocalypse]] ([[User talk:Cleopatran Apocalypse|talk]]) 05:20, 16 July 2016 (UTC)

== 20 August  1866 end of the Confederacy  ==

The end of the Civil war is 20 August 1866 by presidential proclamation. The last Confederate fighters in Texas fought until Early August 1866. After they surrendered the President proclaimed the Civil War over. The reason for this is to make it a federal crime of treason for shooting Union soldiers after that date.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/50.102.141.170|50.102.141.170]] ([[User talk:50.102.141.170#top|talk]]) 03:33, 13 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Wrong Flag ==

I was wondering why the 1st National Flag is shown as the flag of the CSA when it should be the 3rd National Flag. [[User:Barrowscv|Barrowscv]] ([[User talk:Barrowscv|talk]]) 19:05, 21 October 2016 (UTC)

:The “Third national flag”, the Blood Stained Banner with battle flag union, white field, red vertical stripe; official only 14 days to final Congressional adjournment, and less than a month to the “collapse” of the Confederacy (Coulter, p. 119) when Jefferson Davis reported in his memoir, the Confederacy “disappeared&quot;. The Third National Flag was reported by scholarly Confederate authorities after the War as “never seen&quot; in the Confederacy of history ([http://mshistorynow.mdah.state.ms.us/articles/107/history-of-the-confederate-flags%7CA%7C Sansing, A brief history of the Confederate flags]), although it is widely adopted anachronistically by neo-Confederate groups of the modern era. 

:You can help the accuracy of WP articles by restoring the First National Flag, the &quot;Stars and Bars&quot; as the flag icon to replace the wrong flag -- the Third National Flag -- that is found in error on many pages. Based on Coulter and Sansing, the Second National Flag should be limited to the info box for an article on the Confederate Capitol building, and the Third National Flag should not appear at all except to illustrate the fleeing Confederate Congress at the fall of Richmond. [[User:TheVirginiaHistorian|TheVirginiaHistorian]] ([[User talk:TheVirginiaHistorian|talk]]) 10:32, 22 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9gn8mxdjw206nb0qumy51adp5fkz5rp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
