<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ancient Macedonian army</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6356480</id>
    <revision>
      <id>606679602</id>
      <parentid>564395877</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-01T20:43:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TeriEmbrey</username>
        <id>17423488</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added GLAM class</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16807">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class = Start|Classical=yes
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Classical Greece and Rome|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{Pritzker-GLAM|class= B|importance=mid }}
{{WikiProject Greece|class=B
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
|importance=Mid}}
}}

==Comments==
As i have appointed in the image &quot;Macedonian Battle Formation&quot; there is a problem because the hypaspists are called &quot;heavy cavalry&quot; when they was infantry.

-Fco


==Deleted this portion==
&quot;but this would contradict statues and reports contemporary to phalangist troops that showed these soldiers wearing large and heavy shields over one arm; regardless&quot;

The phalangites did not &quot;hold onto&quot; their shields directly in their left hard - the small heavy shield the phalangites used were strapped onto their left arm, leaving both their left and right hands free to wield the heavy sarissa pike. 
[[User:Intranetusa|Intranetusa]] ([[User talk:Intranetusa|talk]]) 02:40, 20 December 2007 (UTC)

== Changes and corrections ==

&quot;It seems to appear that Alexander would organize his left flank into a thin line to make it appear weak, while a massive phalanx would be on the right.&quot;
There is no evidence of Alexander varying the depth of his phalanx.  Was is true is that his left was often the point of the hardest fighting--as in Issus, where the Persians focused the brunt of their cavalry assault.

&quot;It is the belief of some that these pikes were so large and heavy ...&quot;
Weight had nothing to do with it.  Length did.

&quot;... that they had to be wielded with two hands in battle.&quot;
It's not the &quot;belief of some&quot;; it is physically impossible to use a sarissa effectively with one hand.

&quot;The phalangite training was sufficient to permit proper use of the shield and sarissa.&quot;
Actually, it was the shield's sling, suspended around the wielder's neck and shoulder that kept the shield in place.  Connolly also asserts that there was a forearm sleeve that helped keep it from moving and gave the phalangite better control--and a hand-grip that could be used when the spear was not in hand.

&quot;The typical Macedonian phalanx was divided into groups of 800 phalangites, ...&quot;
According to whom?  Very little is known about Phillip's phalanx, and even less about its sub-divisions.

&quot;Before a battle the sarissa were carried in two pieces and then slid together when they were being used.&quot;
Spoken as a fact... there is no evidence in the extant record of this happening.

I deleted the &quot;short&quot; from &quot;short sword&quot;, as it was unecessary.  The xiphos, machaira and falcata that would have been used by a phalangite are hardly smaller than the average swords of their contemporaries, and only mere inches shorter (if that) than the gladius they would be conquered by.

&quot;So long as everyone was using the same tactics these weaknesses were not immediately apparent, but with the advent of the Roman legion they proved fatal in every major engagement, the most famous being the Battle of Pydna, as the Romans were able to advance through gaps in the line and easily defeat the Phalangites once in close.&quot;
Deleted due to innaccuracy and lack of relevance.

1) Pyrrhus defeated the Romans twice.
2) The armies fielded by Flamininus and Paulus at Cynoscephalae and Pydna were largely non-Roman.  The armies Pyrrhus defeated were actually much moreso, with fewer non-Roman troops.
3) Pydna was decided partially by the rough terrain Perseus' phalanx marched into, but the extant record (largely Plutarch and Livy) makes it clear that the deciding factor was the departure of the cavalry on the flanks.  By the time the gaps were forming, Paulus' cavalry and elephants were already destroying the phalanx's flank.

[[User:Phoebus Americanos|Phoebus Americanos]] ([[User talk:Phoebus Americanos|talk]]) 15:19, 6 January 2008 (UTC)

== Name of article ==

So I moved this article to ''Army of '''a'''ncient Macedon'' yesterday....but should the &quot;a&quot; be capitalized? (I.e. move the page to [[Army of Ancient Macedon]] or [[Army of Ancient Macedonia]]?) Thanks in advance. &lt;font face=&quot;Monotype Corsiva&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:the_ed17|&lt;font color=&quot;8000000&quot;&gt;the_ed&lt;/font&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/the_ed17|&lt;font color=font color=&quot;8000000&quot;&gt;17&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/font face&gt; 14:57, 2 May 2008 (UTC)

:I don’t quite understand the question. Can you please rephrase? [[User:Seleukosa|Seleukosa]] ([[User talk:Seleukosa|talk]]) 08:48, 12 May 2008 (UTC)

::I apoligize. I am referring the the ''a'' in &quot;ancient&quot;...I am wondering if it should be capitalized for the title of the article.....So instead of its current name, [[Army of ancient Macedon]], I am wondering if it should be [[Army of Ancient Macedon]] (The &quot;A&quot; in Ancient now being capitalized)...any clearer? &lt;font face=&quot;Monotype Corsiva&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:the_ed17|&lt;font color=&quot;8000000&quot;&gt;the_ed&lt;/font&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/the_ed17|&lt;font color=font color=&quot;8000000&quot;&gt;17&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/font face&gt; 14:57, 12 May 2008 (UTC)


This artical refers to Macedonia as a state or province of Greece. It is well documented that Macedonia was it's own sovereign nation with it's own language that is spoken today. I find this reference not only infactual, but also insulting. Please make the required changes so reflect the facts as it should be.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.247.42.187|99.247.42.187]] ([[User talk:99.247.42.187|talk]]) 08:51, 31 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:A) No it doesn't. B) This isn't an article about language - Ancient Macedonian is a dead language and the Ancient Macedonian upper classes spoke both Ancient Macedonian and Koine Greek - and it is recorded that they did so. And C) No![[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 12:52, 31 May 2012 (UTC)

::However, since the article about the state is now at [[Macedonia (ancient kingdom)]], and [[Macedonian army]] redirects here, why don't we move this to [[Macedonian army]] (along the likes of [[Roman army]], [[Byzantine army]] etc)? [[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 13:03, 31 May 2012 (UTC)

:::I don't know?  Certainly any additions to &quot;Macedonian army&quot; dilutes its searchability and not many people will be looking for the army of modern Macedonia (FYROM).[[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 14:36, 31 May 2012 (UTC)

== Personal pronouns ==

There appear to be a lot of personal pronouns (we, I, etc.) in the article. Per [[Wikipedia:Pronoun#Tone]] we should not use first person narrative. I'm going to work on it a bit, but I'd appreciate if anyone else that notices it helps. ''[[User:C6541|C6541]]'' &lt;small&gt;''([[User talk:C6541|T]]↔[[Special:Contributions/C6541|C]])&lt;/small&gt;'' 18:17, 13 April 2012 (UTC)

== Requesting move ==

&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of the proposal. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the proposal was '''move to [[Ancient Macedonian army]]'''. There's a rough consensus that the suggested title requires this further disambiguation but that the current title isn't preferable. [[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 16:21, 13 June 2012 (UTC)
----

[[Army of Macedon]] → {{no redirect|1=Macedonian army}} – As pointed out above, the country article has been moved from [[Macedon]] to [[Macedonia (ancient kingdom)]], and [[Macedonian army]] already redirects here. The army of Philip II, Alexander and their successors is and most probably will remain a far more popular subject that the military of the Republic of Macedonia, a fact confirmed by a GBook search. [[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 19:27, 31 May 2012 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' the army of the current country of Macedonia would be a scholarly topic of modern history and military studies, and current geopolitics, so if you want to match the other article, it would be [[Macedonian (ancient kingdom) army]] or [[Macedonian army (ancient kingdom)]]. The way we treat topics on Wikipedia, modern extant countries get the primary position, or we have a disambigation page like at [[Macedonia]]. So &quot;Macedonian army&quot; should be a disambiguation page like [[Macedonia]] and [[Macedonian]]. [[Special:Contributions/70.24.251.208|70.24.251.208]] ([[User talk:70.24.251.208|talk]]) 04:45, 2 June 2012 (UTC)
**Erm, not necessarily. When there is a clear [[WP:PRIMARY|primary topic]], then the primary topic gets the simple title, and the others get to be disambiguated. And usage is [http://www.google.com/search?q=%22Macedonian+army%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1#q=%22Macedonian+army%22&amp;hl=en&amp;tbo=1&amp;tbm=bks&amp;ei=tl7LT-mYEqOo4gSgqu3pDw&amp;start=90&amp;sa=N&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.,cf.osb&amp;fp=6d4397b224e7a071&amp;biw=1280&amp;bih=603 overwhelming]: out of the first hundred results in GBooks for &quot;Macedonian army&quot;, only nine refer to the Army of the RoM, and a couple of others to various Greek and Ottoman armies. In other words, the [[Macedonian army]] can easily be at its proper name ([[Ancient Macedonian army]] would be another possibility), and a disambiguation notice can be added pointing to the [[Army of the Republic of Macedonia]].  [[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 12:58, 3 June 2012 (UTC)

*'''Comment''' [[Army of Macedonia]] currently points to the FYRM army article. [[Special:Contributions/70.24.251.208|70.24.251.208]] ([[User talk:70.24.251.208|talk]]) 04:59, 2 June 2012 (UTC)
* Weak '''oppose''' move, keep [[Macedonian army]] as a disambiguation page, per guideline at [[WP:NCMAC#Other page titles]]: ''&quot;If a sub-article of the type &quot;X of the Republic of Macedonia&quot; conflicts with an existing article &quot;X of Greek/ancient Macedonia&quot;, a regular disambiguation page pattern according to [[WP:DAB]] with no &quot;primary topic&quot; will be used (i.e. &quot;X of Macedonia&quot; will be a disambiguation page)&quot;''. (To clarify: if it came to an actual primacy argument, I'd probably side with Cplakidas, given the overwhelmingly more prominent historical role of the ancient as opposed to the modern army, but the NCMAC process deliberately decided in favour of a single wholesale solution for all &quot;M.&quot; subpage pairs rather than the alternative of deciding each pair separately.) [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 13:12, 3 June 2012 (UTC)
*: (Note: something needs to be fixed about the capitalized alternative [[Macedonian Army]]: it currently redirects to [[Army of Macedon]], but it is automatically linked to from {{tl|Armies in Europe}}, which assumes that all page titles of the type &quot;X'ian Army&quot; refer to the modern states.) [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 13:16, 3 June 2012 (UTC)
**Hmmm, all right. How about the [[Ancient Macedonian army]] alternative?  On &quot;Macedonian Army&quot;, should it redirect to the modern army or to the [[Macedonian army]] dab page? [[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 13:34, 3 June 2012 (UTC)
*** No objection to &quot;Ancient Macedonian army&quot;, if you find &quot;of Macedon&quot; ugly. About &quot;Macedonian Army&quot;, to prevent confusion, I'd strongly favour keeping the uppercase and lowercase versions in sync with each other, which means [[Macedonian Army]] should lead to the same dab page. (Which means the {{tl|Armies in Europe}} template would still be broken.) [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 13:38, 3 June 2012 (UTC)
**** &quot;[[ Ancient Macedonian army ]]&quot; is fine by me. [[Special:Contributions/70.24.251.208|70.24.251.208]] ([[User talk:70.24.251.208|talk]]) 11:35, 5 June 2012 (UTC)

*'''Support''' in the Reliable English language sources the ''Macedonian army'' always (or close to it) refers to King Philip's and Alexander the Great's army ([[WP:COMMONNAME]]). A hatnote would take care of anyone who arrives at the page by mistake. If in the future that usage changes then the pages can always be moved when that happens. --[[User:Philip Baird Shearer|PBS]] ([[User talk:Philip Baird Shearer|talk]]) 19:18, 4 June 2012 (UTC)
**You have an expansive view of &quot;always&quot; then.  Try a perusal of [http://www.bbc.co.uk/search/news/?q=Macedonian%20army BBC News articles].  — [[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #000073;background:#4D4DA6;padding:2px;color:#F9FFFF;text-shadow:black 0.2em 0.2em 0.3em&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Georgia&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;'''AjaxSmack'''&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:10, 10 June 2012 (UTC)

*'''Support''' In agreement with the comment above. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 20:45, 4 June 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' [[Ancient Macedonian army]]. — &lt;span style=&quot;letter-spacing:1pt; font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;[[User:Cardiffchestnut|&lt;sup&gt;[dave]&lt;/sup&gt; cardiff]]&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#124; &lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;letter-spacing:1pt; font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cardiffchestnut|chestnut]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; —  15:51, 5 June 2012 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' - I've solved the inbound linking issue by editing {{tl|European topic}}, assuming this doesn't cause any side effects.  Designing templates so that they only work correctly if ''every'' related article conforms to some arbitrary naming convention, with no exceptions, is a Bad Idea&amp;trade;. --[[User:R'n'B|R'n'B]] ([[User talk:R'n'B|call me]] Russ) 20:17, 6 June 2012 (UTC)
**'''Comment''' there are alot of those templates. &quot;Topics of X&quot; for each continent, or each US state... [[Special:Contributions/70.24.251.208|70.24.251.208]] ([[User talk:70.24.251.208|talk]]) 04:27, 7 June 2012 (UTC)

*'''Oppose''' original proposal per [[WP:PRIMARYTOPIC]].  '''Support''' [[ancient Macedonian army]] if others agree.  — [[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #000073;background:#4D4DA6;padding:2px;color:#F9FFFF;text-shadow:black 0.2em 0.2em 0.3em&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Georgia&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;'''AjaxSmack'''&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:10, 10 June 2012 (UTC)
**Actually, per [[WP:PRIMARYTOPIC]] the article should be at &quot;Macedonian army&quot;. BBC News is, by its nature, ''not'' going to have much news about the army of Alexander, so it is not a reliable indicator as to usage. A search even in simple Google shows that the overwhelming majority refers to the ancient army and not the modern one. The main obstacle here, as Fut Perf indicated, is the [[WP:NCMAC]] guideline. [[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 20:04, 12 June 2012 (UTC)
*'''Comment'''. This article doesn't quite qualify as the [[WP:PRIMARYTOPIC]], but neither does [[Army of the Republic of Macedonia]]. In May, [[army of Macedon]] received [http://stats.grok.se/en/201205/Army%20of%20Macedon 3517 views], and [[Army of the Republic of Macedonia]] received [http://stats.grok.se/en/201205/Army%20of%20the%20Republic%20of%20Macedonia 3529 views]; almost exactly even. I think [[Macedonian army]] should remain a disambiguation page, but this article ''should'' be moved to something less ambigious, such as [[ancient Macedonian army]], or possibly even [[Macedonian army (ancient kingdom)]], mirroring [[Macedonia (ancient kingdom)]]. [[User:BlindMic|BlindMic]] ([[User talk:BlindMic|talk]]) 02:17, 13 June 2012 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the proposal.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;

== Image ==

The new heading image is so very dull! 

Other possibilities:

[[File:Philip-ii-of-macedon.jpg|thumb|Philip II]]

[[File:Hypaspist.jpg|thumb|Hypaspist - modern reconstruction]]
[[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 20:52, 14 July 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>duvry5eedsokat6se2cr5aq9o429r24</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
