<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Blood Diamond</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6358671</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749597039</id>
      <parentid>748149187</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-15T04:59:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyphoidbomb</username>
        <id>8363265</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Nation of origin? */ new section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18743">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Albums|class=b
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
| b6 &lt;!--Accessibility          --&gt; = yes
|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=b|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Films=yes}}
{{WikiProject Film|American-task-force=yes|War-task-force=yes|class=b
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes}}
{{AfricaProject|
|Sierra Leone=yes
|class=B
|importance=mid
|Sierra Leone-importance=mid}}}}

- Changed the release date to Dec. 15th, not Dec. 18th.  (Friday instead of Monday).  My proof/justification for this is various movie release websites &amp; also the fact that common practice has movies very rarely released on a monday.

==Reception==

Am I the only one who's sceptical that &quot;Rotten Tomatoes shows a 63% rating, with 127 favorable reviews out of 203, and an average rating of 6.4/10&quot; gives justification to the statement &quot;Blood Diamond was released to positive reviews from both critics and audiences&quot;? That sounds a lot more like a reception of which I would be disappointed, a reception which is lukewarm. [[Special:Contributions/78.145.172.171|78.145.172.171]] ([[User talk:78.145.172.171|talk]]) 14:27, 13 December 2009 (UTC)

==Title==

I see many sites and magazines (such as [[Entertainment Weekly]]) refer to this film as simply Blood Diamond. Is there any official word from the WB on whether it's called THE Blood Diamond or just Blood Diamond? [[User:Gunslinger|Gunslinger]] 01:48, 16 August 2006 (UTC)

==Plot==

I cut the plot down by about half.  Couldn't cull anything more though without losing too much detail, I thought.  Let me know what you think though! .--[[User:nicolae_brocolae|nicolae_brocolae]] 10:35, 09 January 2007 (EST)
:: DId Archer Die?? It doent say, it just shows him there an after he make the final phone call it doesn't show him again! &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Realg187|Realg187]] ([[User talk:Realg187|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Realg187|contribs]]) 18:41, 9 May 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;
He must be died !?--[[User:Max Mayr|Max Mayr]] 16:02, 27 September 2007 (UTC)


--- I changed the time frame back to 1999, I dont know who keeps changing that to 1994. The movie takes place during the Sierra Leone civil war, not the start of it. Freetown was captured in 1999. Don't change it again. - rgrDknob  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/65.33.88.211|65.33.88.211]] ([[User talk:65.33.88.211|talk]]) 18:46, 7 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Controversy==
While I agree that De Beers must be mentioned, I have reservations about the comment &quot;De Beers makes more money on Blood Diamonds than any other business in the world regardless of that number being 1% or 4%. De Beers is most deserving of the term &quot;making a killing&quot; off of the diamond market.&quot; Comments? --[[User:Stretch 135|Stretch]] 09:03, 18 August 2006 (UTC)

:I would encourage people to simply remove such astoundingly bad statements rather than merely raising a question on the talk page.  You were right to question it, but please do not hesitate to go further.  Accurate sourcing is crucial.--[[User:Jimbo Wales|Jimbo Wales]] 03:55, 20 August 2006 (UTC)

There is new site on this www.diamondfacts.org that I saw the other day. Lots of content on Blood Diamonds.
Afterwards, you should pay apscuhuru.org a visit!

If you watch back to the part where Danny goes and sees his former commander about the diamonds, he tells him if he thinks he found a diamond of an adequate size he would not be on the continent thats when the commander says this is your home you will die here (he says this as he brushes the red dirt through his hands)...in the end of the movie Danny is telling Maddie he is right where he needs to be (as he also is brushing the red dirt through his hands).[[Special:Contributions/66.186.246.33|66.186.246.33]] ([[User talk:66.186.246.33|talk]]) 22:33, 9 April 2011 (UTC)

==Plot too short==
It is far too abbreviated and makes no mention of Maddy Bowen, who was a strong supporting character. [[User:Cliff smith|Cliff smith]] 02:37, 29 January 2007 (UTC)

==Cast==
When Danny and solomon and maddy get on the car with solomon carrying an injured child, is the driver played by Tom Sizemore? And the reporter who stopped solomon and said: there's not enough space, he's an indian soap actor(i dont know his name though). Shouldn't it be in the trivia?

RE: TOM SIZEMORE - I just watched it and paused at that section - I cannot find a citation for the actor, but it is definitively not Tom Sizemore.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.76.142.218|69.76.142.218]] ([[User talk:69.76.142.218|talk]]) 02:31, 29 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Language ==

add German to Languages?

[[User:66.75.229.195|66.75.229.195]] 03:08, 6 February 2007 (UTC)

:There is already an interlanguage link to the German Wikipedia article. - [[User:Gilliam|Gilliam]] 03:22, 6 February 2007 (UTC)

==De Beers Group==

De Beers Group, which is the largest player in the diamond trade, has expressed reservations that the film will reduce public demand for diamonds.



Eh? So the de Beers Group believes the film will ''not'' reduce public demand etc? The above sentence, if not construed in the aforesaid fashion, is essentially meaningless. Is this what passes for literacy these days? [[User:TharkunColl|TharkunColl]] 00:26, 17 March 2007 (UTC)

==Anachronisms etc.==
I added a new trivia section with the appearance of an 07 passat on a movie set in the 90s. I thought it was funny, however, is it worthy of this article? please comment. [[User:NeoXtremeX|NeoXtremeX]] 04:07, 18 December 2006 (UTC)

:I noticed it as well and thought it was funny. No reason not to keep it, I would think. Cheers. --[[User:Pnencka|Pnencka]] 19:08, 23 December 2006 (UTC)
:I also noticed that, when Maddy was taking pictures of the refugees, the fence was directly in front of the camera lens. --[[User:2ltben|2ltben]] 03:23, 25 December 2006 (UTC)
:: My friends and I all laughed at that too. And at the red lid on the previously uncapped bottle that Danny passes to Maddy. [[User:Drcwright|Drcwright]] 03:29, 25 December 2006 (UTC)
:::The refugees are a far enough distance away from the fence that it would be very easy for Maddy to focus through the fence, having little to no obstruction in the photos. [[User:TheMagicalMan|TheMagicalMan]] 22:58, 25 December 2006 (UTC)

Could we add what they did well? Rhodesian Accent, the Rhodesian mutt in a scene, the Shona saying etc?--[[User:Economic.mip|Economic.mip]] 20:21, 26 May 2007 (UTC)

My car trivia was taken out...any reasons? [[User:NeoXtremeX|NeoXtremeX]] 16:07, 7 June 2007 (UTC)

The article says that Danny Archer is from South Africa. In the film, however, he tells Maddy that he was born in Rhodesia (modern-day Zimbabwe).  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.76.142.218|69.76.142.218]] ([[User talk:69.76.142.218|talk]]) 01:22, 29 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

it seems to be a bit superflous. eh?
:Yes indeed, zing. --[[User:NEMT|NEMT]] 22:47, 29 May 2007 (UTC)

That sections is just a disguised trivie section. Write into the prose of the article or remove it. [[User:DurinsBane87|DurinsBane87]] 23:06, 15 August 2007 (UTC)

TO DURINSBANE87: In re your note on the recent removal of this section, I didn't say &quot;you&quot; needed to be encyclopedic, I merely quote the dictionary in order to do my bit to counter the current trend toward removal of anything remotely fun, controversial or even discursive from Wikipedia entries. These deletions and the Twitter enties that result help anyone to better use the encyclopedia to understand our world? An encyclopedia is not a dictionary; an encyclopedia is made up of essays. Terseness is not a virtue.

Danny Archer is a stereotype of a racist and arrogant &quot;Boer&quot;.  But he is actually meant to be a Rhodesian of British descent - Archer is hardly a Boer name.  His accent is bad, but closer to South African than Rhodesian.  It's ironic that a film about abuse and racism, etc, should be so confused about one of the major protagonists.[[Special:Contributions/124.197.15.138|124.197.15.138]] ([[User talk:124.197.15.138|talk]]) 03:05, 29 April 2009 (UTC)

The presence or absence of the ANACHRONISM section here will not prevent me from buying and distributing dozens of copies of this film to any of my friends I can force to take one. I put the list back into the entry because 1. It is fun, 2. The awareness of &quot;faults&quot; within a film plays an important technical role in the development of the film critic's opinions and thus are, by definition, important to students of the film (we the readers), and 3. In this film anachronisms might have more than one cause.

It may be that the film's director did not really care about the kinds of mundane details encompassed by this list. OK then, that says something about him and the professionalism of the continuity people he hired to help him.

But, if you know anything of the background of this film then you know that the diamond industry worked against the making of the film and later, the distribution of the film. Are these and other faults the result of opposition-induced funding squeezes? If so, the director can perhaps be forgiven for cost-cutting in the continuity department.

Unfortunately, I am not an expert on the long-running battle to bring this film to the theatre and cannot do a decent job of describing it to readers. So, until a person with the needed expertise comes forward to write the back story of the film's production, we are stuck for an explanation of why the director didn't control the film better. But we still should know that the film exhibits a lack of directorial control. [[User:Parsnip13|Parsnip13]] 05:40, 3 November 2007 (UTC)

:That's fantastic and all, but wikipedia has policies. These are basically just movie goofs. They belong on IMDB, not wikipedia. [[User:DurinsBane87|DurinsBane87]] 17:15, 3 November 2007 (UTC)

== Weapon used by DiCaprio ==

There is no way to be M4 the barrel lenght is 11.5 inches while the M4 barrel is 14.5 inches so I change it to CAR-15 .
--[[User:Max Mayr|Max Mayr]] 19:52, 27 August 2007 (UTC)
:: I'm fascinated to hear how you're so sure a gun in a movie has an 11.5 inch barrel. [[Special:Contributions/86.154.209.238|86.154.209.238]] ([[User talk:86.154.209.238|talk]]) 22:53, 14 May 2011 (UTC)
Obviously you don't have much knowledge about the M4/M16 family. The M4's upper receiver can be changed to have different barrel lengths, common barrels are 10, 14.5, 16 and 20 inch barrels. However you may be correct in assuming the rifle he uses in the last scene is a CAR15/XM177.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/211.27.152.66|211.27.152.66]] ([[User talk:211.27.152.66|talk]]) 08:16, 26 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

No. The rifle at the end of the film is the M4, without a doubt. --[[Special:Contributions/67.172.13.176|67.172.13.176]] ([[User talk:67.172.13.176|talk]]) 14:36, 23 May 2009 (UTC)

:No, not an M4 specifically, but most likely some kind of hybrid judging by its unusual combination of features. Similar carbines were seen in ''Black Hawk Down'', which had the same armorer (Bapty &amp; Co.) as ''Blood Diamond''. Even the [http://www.imfdb.org/index.php/Blood_Diamond#Unknown_.28custom.3F.29_Colt_CAR-15_variant| IMFDB crew] can't make a definite identification of it as any specific model. I would say, by looking at the receiver, it most resembles an M727 or 733. Barrel length is never the best way to identify an AR variant, ''always'' look at the receiver. The civilian world uses &quot;M4&quot; as a generic term for AR-15 carbines, both military models and civilian models, but an ''actual'' M4 or M4A1 has a flattop upper receiver, A2-type lower receiver, collapsible stock, and 14.5-inch barrel with M203 groove. The lower receiver may say &quot;Colt M4 or Colt M4A1, but changing receivers essentially makes it an entirely different weapon. E.G., putting a fixed A2 carry handle upper like in the movie makes it essentially a 727 because that's what a 727 is. I think it more appropriate to just call it &quot;CAR-15&quot;. [[User:Spartan198|Spartan198]] ([[User talk:Spartan198|talk]]) 16:06, 1 October 2009 (UTC)

== Danny Archer's Clothing &amp; Equipment ==
1) Boots - It has been speculated that he was wearing Desert Operations Series boots by Magnum Boots USA
2) Knife - Something from Cold Steel?
3) Shirt - Something from 5.11 Tactical?
4) Pants - Something from 5.11 Tactical?
5) Watch - Breitling Chrono Avenger. Source: http://forums.watchuseek.com/showthread.php?t=76150  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nickgomez|Nickgomez]] ([[User talk:Nickgomez|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nickgomez|contribs]]) 09:53, 2 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== WikiProject class rating==

This article was automatically assessed because at least one WikiProject had rated the article as start, and the rating on other projects was brought up to start class. [[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 19:06, 28 August 2007 (UTC)

==Fair use rationale for Image:Blooddiamondposter.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:Blooddiamondposter.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:Blooddiamondposter.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is  other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;

[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 00:15, 30 October 2007 (UTC)

== Archer or Aocher ? ==

Was Di Caprio name in the movie Archer or Aocher because I remember it Aocher ...--[[User:Blain Toddi|Blain Toddi]] 14:59, 12 November 2007 (UTC)

:That may just be caused by the accent that DiCaprio used for his character.  In my limited experience of white African accents, these do sometimes alter the sound, and apparent spelling, of words.  Your mileage may vary.

:Incidentally, I reverted an edit you made to the article earlier but forgot to explain why in the edit summary.  You'd added the name of a weapon used by a character at one point in the film.  I removed it because it seemed an unnecessary detail for this scene - the article doesn't reference other weapons used (nor are weapons a particularly relevant detail for the film).  Anyway, my apologies for the earlier slip - I hope this explains my edit.  Cheers, --[[User:Plumbago|Plumbago]] 15:16, 12 November 2007 (UTC)

== Who is ''Colonel Coetzee''? ==
*Weird or strange figuration on the page visible. The main story is well told, but there isn't any white lady with a fourtyfour bcrgd visible. Just t(h)ree black soldiers! The imagination of the writer of the page is fabolous!--[[User:Danaide|Danaide]] ([[User talk:Danaide|talk]]) 14:58, 31 March 2010 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Blood Diamond (film)]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=747772433 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20141102054428/http://www.wga.org/content/default.aspx?id=3136 to http://www.wga.org/content/default.aspx?id=3136
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://blooddiamondmovie.warnerbros.com/

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 08:20, 4 November 2016 (UTC)

== Nation of origin? ==

I get that American-German is sourced by [http://www.metacritic.com/movie/blood-diamond/details Metacritic]. From what I understand though, (and this information may be outdated) we used to not use Metacritic for this sort of detail, because they were pulling it from IMDb, thus making it [[WP:RS/IMDB|inherently unreliable]]. [http://www.afi.com/members/catalog/DetailView.aspx?s=&amp;Movie=63723 AFI calls it American-South African]. I don't have any further information on the subject, so I'm not sure what should be done here. [[User:Cyphoidbomb|Cyphoidbomb]] ([[User talk:Cyphoidbomb|talk]]) 04:59, 15 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>4zn2e9mhxmdjh263mvfbrgjvopxktnh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
