<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:922d Expeditionary Reconnaissance Squadron</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>28619407</id>
    <revision>
      <id>617669445</id>
      <parentid>616953759</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-20T05:30:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anotherclown</username>
        <id>8567476</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>assess as B class</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5498">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject United States|class=B|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=B|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y }}
{{MILHIST|class=B|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|US=y|Aviation=y|Cold-War=y}}
}}

== 22d Air Transport Squadron (Provisional) during the Berlin Airlift ==
There was also a (Provisional) 22d Air Transport Squadron during the Berlin Airlift, operating at least between 26 June 1948 &amp; 30 Sep. 1949, as such a unit is eligible for the [[Berlin Airlift Device]] (though I didn't think the Air Force was eligible for that) and the [[Medal for Humane Action]] (see AFP900-2 Volume 1, Book 1, page 139, and apparently also DAFGO 38 of 1948 &amp; DAFGO 68 of 1950).

Is that a different unit entirely?  If so, the [[22d Air Transport Squadron]] redirect should probably be changed to a disambiguation.

Cheers, [[User:Gecko G|Gecko G]] ([[User talk:Gecko G|talk]]) 02:31, 11 July 2014 (UTC)

: That unit is an entirely different unit, and was stationed at Fairfield-Suisun AFB from 1947 to 1948 and assigned to the 2d Air Transpprt Group (Provisional).  It was replaced in June 1948 by the newly designated 22d Air Transport Squadron (no Provisional), assigned to the 530th Air Transport Group, in October 1948 it became the &lt;s&gt;1269th&lt;/s&gt; 1267th Air Transport Squadron (and the group became the 1501st Air Transport Group).  If it had any independent notability (I doubt it) from the [[1501st Air Transport Wing]], its article would be more appropriately at [[1267th Air Transport Squadron|&lt;s&gt;1269th&lt;/s&gt; 1267th Air Transport Squadron]] under [[WP:MILMOS#UNITNAME]].
: There was also another (non-notable) 22d Air Transport Squadron (Provisional) at Morrison Field assigned to another 2d Air Tranport Group (Provisional) in 1947.
: I doubt there's a need for a disambiguation page until someone finds notability in one of the other three 22d ATSs.

:I appreciate your edits (hate to look like an owner).  --[[User:Lineagegeek|Lineagegeek]] ([[User talk:Lineagegeek|talk]]) 02:22, 12 July 2014 (UTC)

::I figured that was probably the case [that it was an unrelated unit with basically the same name].
::I think either the [[22d Air Transport Squadron]] redirect needs to be turned into a disambiguation page, and/or it needs mentioning in ''this'' article (either in the prose or perhaps in the Hatnote), because anyone searching for ''those'' units (ie perhaps a veteran looking up their old unit) would get redirected to this page and think the 922d was the modern successor of that unit.  [[User:Gecko G|Gecko G]] ([[User talk:Gecko G|talk]]) 02:57, 12 July 2014 (UTC)

: I believe the page number changes in the AFP 900-2 references were in error.  The revisions seem to refer to the page of the .pdf file, rather than the page number shown at the bottom of each page, which is the actual page in 900-2.  At any rate, I have changed these references to the AFHRA Factsheet, which contains them all, so that they are uniform (except, that is, for the 1989-1990 award which is omitted there).  The award site search reference is retained for that award.  Each of these is a separate award, represented by a different embroidered streamer (no oak leaf clusters for units), so I don't think it's appropriate to lump them altogether, although I agree it would be excessive to include them individually in the infobox.

: Hatnote added for other uses of 22d Air Transport Squadron.  --[[User:Lineagegeek|Lineagegeek]] ([[User talk:Lineagegeek|talk]]) 20:26, 12 July 2014 (UTC)

::I just double checked, the page number's are correct - perhaps we are looking at different editions?  For Vol I I've got (and linked to) the 15 June 1971 version book 2.  pg 480 is on that pdf's page 170.  there is no pdf page 480 as it's only 318 page long.  For Vol II it's the 23 Nov. 1981 version (though it includes pages about change's 1–3 — #3 is dated 20 Sep 1984), It's the same one you linked to.  Page 91 is on the pdf's page 111 (conversly the PDF's page 101 is actually page 91).  There also seems to be 2 different Vol III's that I can't figure out.  In any event, as you said- by changing it to the Factsheet it's ultimately a moot point.
::I didn't know that about the streamers.  What are they embroidered with? the dates?
::The Hatnote works.  In-all, let me say good work.  Cheers, [[User:Gecko G|Gecko G]] ([[User talk:Gecko G|talk]]) 22:59, 12 July 2014 (UTC)

oh, just noticed something while proofreading: On this talk page you wrote that the ''other'' 22d ATS became the '''1269'''th ATS, but on the 22d ATS disambiguation page you wrote that it became the '''1267'''th ATS.  1269 vs. 1267, one must be a typo.  If the one here is the misteak, then nothing needs to be done, but if the misteak is the version on the disambiguation page then that should be changed, cheers [[User:Gecko G|Gecko G]] ([[User talk:Gecko G|talk]]) 23:13, 12 July 2014 (UTC)

: Unit number typo is here. Although I provide links in AFP 900-2 references, I work from hard copies of the 1971 and 1976 publications.  &quot;Volume 1&quot; actually has no volume number.  When USAF decided to update (mostly to include SEA material) in 1976, it decided not to start again from scratch, but to issue a Volume 2 containing only updates.  Award streamers are typically embroidered with the dates, and if applicable, the location or operation.  Campaign streamers are embroidered with the campaign name.  --[[User:Lineagegeek|Lineagegeek]] ([[User talk:Lineagegeek|talk]]) 19:46, 14 July 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3x7kmh2svn4vfdfrdyiezxgkqbbfwlk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
