<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Kosovo War</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>17393</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745955940</id>
      <parentid>745955683</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T11:35:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pincrete</username>
        <id>17723088</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Serb or Yugoslav? */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15515">
{{talk header}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 2
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Kosovo War/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Ds/talk notice|topic=b|style=long}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST
|class=B
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes
|attention=yes
|French-task-force=yes
|US-task-force=yes
|past-collaboration=[[October 30]], [[2006]]–[[November 12]], [[2006]]

}}
{{Wikiproject Serbia|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Kosovo|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Albania|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject European history|class=|importance=}}
}}

__TOC__

== Ibrahim Rugova and other LDK members ==

Whoever listed the LDK leaders: Rugova, Zemaj, Krasniqi as part of the war, please provide substantial references. This is a false claim! Rugova was not involved in the war, even after the NATO air campaign he was hosted by Milloshevic in Belgrade, with his own request. This comes up from the Milloshevic's trial transcripts and video. The so-called Kosovo Defence Minister A.Krasniqi was killed in 1998 by KLA members in Tirana, before the main conflict even begun. How could he be a belligerent? Zemaj was the only one that participated at a certain point, but under regular KLA format. His divergences with KLA leaders that led to his alleged assassination came after the war.
&lt;br&gt;If I.Rugova and other LDK leaders who did not support the war, came to support KLA and NATO intervention at a certain point, like all Albanians did, that does not make them belligerents. Rugova/LDK stance might be subject to a separate section withing the article due to its complexity.
&lt;br&gt;--[[User:Mondiad|Mondiad]] ([[User talk:Mondiad|talk]]) 03:01, 2 February 2016 (UTC)

:[[User:Mondiad|Mondiad]], sections covering Rugova and FARK, would I think be an asset. [[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete|talk]]) 18:57, 9 February 2016 (UTC)
::{{Ping|Pincrete}} I have prepared a subsection for Rugova's Democratic League of Kosovo and FARK during the war. I was thinking of adding it under the &quot;Reaction to the war&quot; as 6 (in front of &quot;Casualties&quot; which would shift to 7), or inside the &quot;Reaction to the war&quot; as 5.3. Regarding the title, I was thinking &quot;Democratic League of Kosovo and FARK&quot;. Any suggestions? --[[User:Mondiad|Mondiad]] ([[User talk:Mondiad|talk]]) 04:15, 25 February 2016 (UTC)
:::[[User:Mondiad|Mondiad]], difficult to say without seeing the text, this is partly a 'sequence' matter and partly weight, I suggest you put it where you see fit and see reactions. [[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete|talk]]) 09:06, 25 February 2016 (UTC)
::::Ok, done.--[[User:Mondiad|Mondiad]] ([[User talk:Mondiad|talk]]) 00:51, 26 February 2016 (UTC)

:::::I made some minor ce's and think there might be room for a few more 'tidies'. Initial reaction is that I'm not sure it is in the right place (reactions to the war). I can't see an obvious place for it to go and wonder whether it should have its own section, though where in the sequence I'm not sure.[[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete|talk]]) 22:18, 26 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Kosovo War]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707193810 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20130201000150/http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5iI-Ix5tQ59McTX8NyBF1R120X4dAD97O8IRO0 to http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5iI-Ix5tQ59McTX8NyBF1R120X4dAD97O8IRO0

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 11:05, 27 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Kosovo War]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=739101624 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://www.hvkk.tsk.tr/PageSub/Kurumumuz/Tarihce/1944-Today.aspx
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20121219093335/https://www.un.org:80/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/1199(1998) to http://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=S/RES/1199(1998)
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://pdf.thelancet.com/pdfdownload?uid=llan.355.9222.original_research.1004.1&amp;x=x.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20081207191558/https://jurist.law.pitt.edu:80/ramb.htm to http://jurist.law.pitt.edu/ramb.htm
*Added {{tlx|dead link}} tag to http://pdf.thelancet.com/pdfdownload?uid=llan.355.9222.original_research.1004.1&amp;x=x.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 19:50, 12 September 2016 (UTC)

== Serb or Yugoslav? ==

[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kosovo_War&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=745341300 this conversation took place in response to these edits, inc prev and next], and whether to refer to 'Serb' or 'Yugoslav' troops, decisions etc. I am moving it here as a permanent record. [[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete|talk]]) 22:06, 22 October 2016 (UTC)

Hi Pincrete. I'm well aware of what sources may use in connection to the Kosovo war, however this doesn't make them trump the tangible points. To see how and why sources can be anecdotal and often are (e.g Russian troops instead of Soviet), I refer you to a previous discussion where I took part [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Kosovo_Verification_Mission#Third_Opinion here]. Note the sources I provide. Thanks. --[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]] ([[User talk:Oranges Juicy|talk]]) 15:44, 20 October 2016 (UTC)

PS. For imstance [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/363314.stm this source] uses &quot;Serb withdrawal&quot; and &quot;Yugoslav forces&quot; interchangeably. --[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]] ([[User talk:Oranges Juicy|talk]]) 15:48, 20 October 2016 (UTC)

:[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]], I'm aware of the ambiguity in the two terms and dangers of using either,''(one suggesting something too specific/ethnic, one too broad which is only understood by those who understand how the term changed meaning during the 'breakup')''. I find the logic of the 3rd opinion bizarre, but so be it. [[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete#top|talk]]) 16:06, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
::Well I'm all ears (or eyes!), I'd like to read why you found it bizarre and I'm certianly in favour of exploring further options. If you reply here, I'll keep watch. --[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]] ([[User talk:Oranges Juicy|talk]]) 14:21, 21 October 2016 (UTC)
:::[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]], the 'Russian/Soviet' example is clear, the former is a commonly used, but imprecise, metonym for the latter and it doesn't cause any confusion to use the more 'correct' form. It is less clear in the post-USSR world since 'Russia' is both a constituent state of, and the general metonym for the federation.

:::In the case of 'Yugoslavia', there is possible confusion for the reader, since the term is used both for the lonstanding, multi-region socialist republic, and also the only elements of that republic to NOT secede ''(ie Srb + Mnt + their territorial 'satellites', notably Kosovo)''. This use was short-lived and widely disputed, even the WP article has FRY as a redirect to Srb + Mnt.

:::I don't have a clear answer, I agree that sources often use the two terms interchangably for this period, I agreed with your '3rd op' point that where specific units/paramilitaries were involved, it was possible to designate them correctly. I didn't quite agree that this is wholly a non-pov issue. The claim to the name was a part of Srb+Mnt's claim to be the legitimate inheritor's of the older republic's rights and territories. 

:::I don't think article writers of this period were ignorant of the difference in meaning of the two terms, but presumably thought it insignificant. Political writers commonly use UK or GB to mean 'the UK of GB and NI', but no-one misunderstands that a GB proposal or action, also involves the junior partner NI, ''(in this example there is of course a simple solution, - 'British').'' 

:::My own preferred solution would be to use the term used by the source, with clarifying text within the article, if nec. ''(which I think there is at present)''.[[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete#top|talk]]) 15:05, 21 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::Several good points. On the whole, I'm in agreement. There are a handful of solutions here. &quot;Serb forces&quot; in scare quotes is one, but that is sloppy. A repetition of the passage in question in quotes has more credibility, but this too would be done for avoidance reasons. A simple caveat such as the Kosovo footnote may well be a solution and a tidy one at that. Here it would only need to be added to the first mention and then it can be used indiscriminately throughout the rest of the article in question. I certainly take your point about the confusion ''Yugoslavia'' causes since the vast majority of people in the English-speaking world associate this name with the pre-1992 country. There are actually a fair few solutions though each one needs to be looked at case by case. For example, in [[Kosovo war]] where it is said that NATO and its opponent government reported separate figures for soldiers killed, here it naturally needs some form of link to VJ, but with regards ''who spoke for VJ'', I believe the answer would be to use ''Belgrade'' as a metonym. After all, it is common to speak of &quot;Washington said to Moscow, etc.&quot;, and it is totally unambiguous to the point the reader need not even concern himself with the logistics. At this moment, I don't have time to go further but I am sure there are things we can do. Thanks for your new insight, leave your suggestions and we will arrive at a solution. --[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]] ([[User talk:Oranges Juicy|talk]]) 15:35, 21 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]], I don't disagree with anything significant here. To compound difficulties, the legal status of various components altered over time, and were/are often disputed. An extremely inelegant solution would be to use FRY, however that is also open to being confused with FYR and did not gain much general use. There is already a mention in the lead of who FRY were. [[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete#top|talk]]) 17:01, 21 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::I think we'd at least require a parenthesised addition (commonly referred to in publication by the metonym ''Serb forces''), and on from there. --[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]] ([[User talk:Oranges Juicy|talk]]) 15:55, 22 October 2016 (UTC)
::Simple. Don't use the terms &quot;Yugoslav&quot; or &quot;Serb&quot; when referring to military groupings. If you are referring to the Yugoslav Army, then use VJ. If you are referring to police forces, use MUP. If you are referring to nationalist militias or paramilitaries, use &quot;Serbian nationalist militia&quot; or actually name the militia/paramilitary group in question, i.e. Scorpions, etc. If you are referring to government delegations, use Yugoslav, i.e. &quot;the Yugoslav delegation&quot;, as these individuals were representatives of a countyou are called Yugoslavia. Problem solved. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 22:11, 22 October 2016 (UTC)
:::Not quite that simple, paramilitaries and other specific groups, yes you are right, name them. Sometimes 'generic' terms are used (by sources), Serb/Yugoslav forces, Serb/Yugoslav authorities, sometimes alternate terms by the same sources. Just as importantly, the use of (FR of) Yugoslavia was short-lived, and is not generally understood by most readers to mean the much smaller, inheritor of the name (ie Srb+Mnt+). If reasonably 'sound' sources use 'Serb' do we alter it for consistency, and if so do we explain in some way why our text doesn't match the source? [[User:Pincrete|Pincrete]] ([[User talk:Pincrete|talk]]) 22:45, 22 October 2016 (UTC)
::I should have made myself more clear. If the authorities were ''federal'', use Yugoslav. There is no way of getting around that; that is simply what the country was called. If they were from one of the two republics, i.e. Serbia or Montenegro, use Serbian or Montenegrin. And yes, there should be a note saying that Western media organizations used the generic term &quot;Serb&quot; to refer to all forces fighting the KLA, albeit imprecisely. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 16:52, 23 October 2016 (UTC)
{{outdent}}I agree with 23 editor for any force that is specifically named. Pincrete's points on the wider problem are also valid, and there is no silver bullet for this obstacle. Let's look at the dilemma when choosing a comprehensive term for Serbia/Yugoslavia on Kosovo 1998-99 related issues: 
*If an editor wishes to be official and unimpeachable, he could use ''Yugoslav'' but this can create confusion as many people's general perception of ''Yugoslavia'' is the pre-1992 bigger country.
*If an editor wishes to be clear and keep this simple, he may refer to the metonym ''Serbian'' but this is at the expense of accuracy, especially with regards readers slightly more knowledgeable in the subject.

Pincrete rightly states that ''following sources'' is a safe option. The two problems here are that sources can be interchangeable (so which shall we use?), and even if the source is using one unsparingly, it won't overcome the problem which we have established.

Would the two editors to have commented so far agree to the avoidance trick or using terms such as ''government forces'', ''state troops'' or terms to this effect? --[[User:Oranges Juicy|OJ]] ([[User talk:Oranges Juicy|talk]]) 10:20, 24 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>g97vqwyxpk1vm95138idl72fzhcwnan</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
