<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Frederick the Great</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>160185</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733923163</id>
      <parentid>733922237</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-11T00:01:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Obenritter</username>
        <id>18162346</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* What are German names bastardized? */ add</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10505">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|search=yes }}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=People|class=B}}
{{Article history
|action1=GAN
|action1date=19:01, 13 August 2006 (UTC)
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=69239339

|action2=WAR
|action2date=15 September 2006
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Frederick II of Prussia
|action2result=not approved
|action2oldid=75420393

|currentstatus=FGAN
}}
{{On this day|date1=2006-08-29|oldid1=72500039 |date2=2007-08-29|oldid2=154170512 |date3=2008-08-29|oldid3=234894035 |date4=2009-08-29|oldid4=310724748 |date5=2010-08-29|oldid5=381514226 }}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history
|class=B
|B1=yes
|B2=yes
|B3=yes
|B4=yes
|B5=yes
|A-Class=fail
|German=yes
|Early-Modern=yes
|Biography=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=B
|politician-work-group=yes
|politician-priority=top
|royalty-work-group=yes
|royalty-priority=top
|military-work-group=yes
|military-priority=high
|listas=Frederick 02 Of Prussia
|core=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Composers|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=B|importance=Top|Prussia=yes|PrussiaImp=Top
|b1=yes
|b2=yes
|b3=yes
|b4=yes
|b5=yes}}
{{WikiProject Silesia|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Pritzker-GLAM|class=B |importance=mid }}
{{WikiProject LGBT studies|class=|importance=}}
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Frederick the Great/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}

{{V0.5|class=B|category=History}}

== reputation reestablished ==

Current article text says &quot;Since reunification in 1990 his popularity in Germany has been reestablished&quot;. It is cited to this source [http://opus.kobv.de/ubp/volltexte/2006/741/pdf/angelow_kontexte.pdf], I think. I'm not seeing  the support for that claim in the source, though maybe I'm missing it. What I do see is that it says: ''&quot;Doch schon bald nach Herstellung der deutschen Einheit ebbte die  Begeisterung für den Hohenzollernkönig wieder ab&quot;'' - &quot;But soon after German unification enthusiasm for the Hohenzollern King died down again &quot;. Which means that even if his &quot;reputation has been reestablished&quot; (which is dubious) even that was short lived.

Removing.&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Volunteer Marek|&lt;font style=&quot;color:blue;background:orange;font-family:sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;nbsp;Volunteer Marek&amp;nbsp;'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 00:12, 23 December 2013 (UTC)

== reflist problem ==

I am currently attempting to correct the backlog of pages with [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Pages_with_missing_references_list reflist errors] and just came to this page but I can't seem to figure out the problem. There is a {{tlx|reflist}} already placed and I did not find any &lt; ref &gt; tags placed incorrectly. Could someone assist? [[User: Azcolvin429|''&lt;font color=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;A. Z. Colvin&lt;/font&gt;'']]&amp;nbsp;• [[User talk:Azcolvin429|''&lt;font color=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;'']] 04:42, 27 December 2013 (UTC)

== languages Frederick spoke (or not) ==

re:
:Frederick spoke French, Italian, English, Spanish and Portuguese; he also understood Latin, ancient and modern Greek, and Hebrew

German speaker here--the above should be checked for accuracy. German Wikipedia mentions that he spoke German, French, and had received Latin lessons. He had intimate knowledge of German literature, which he did nod esteem anyway, and his spoken German is rumoured to have been somewhat funny. As with most European aristocrats of the time, French was his first and preferred language. Too lazy to find quotes and sources, sorry. --[[User:Tickle me|tickle]] [[User_talk:Tickle me|me]] 07:50, 26 January 2014 (UTC)

:We have no source stating he spoke so many languages; I say we remove it.  --[[User:A D Monroe III|A D Monroe III]] ([[User talk:A D Monroe III|talk]]) 22:29, 14 August 2014 (UTC)

== Any notability to his writings? ==

&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; At the risk of personal embarrassment, i'll ask that someone comment on whether he is noted for what he ''wrote'' on military strategy: Is our article on him incomplete in failing to mention any titles by him?&lt;br&gt;&lt;!--
 --&gt;  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(The embarrassment part reflects the impetus for my question:  i quote from the SF novel ''[[Ender's Shadow]]'', p. 211 of the &quot;First mass market edition&quot; of Dec. 2000, where a &quot;Command School&quot; instructor says of the title character, one of the students,
: &quot;I should have guessed. He picks up the voice of the strategists he's been reading. Or their translators. Though I don't know what will happen now that he's he's [sic] been reading Frederick and Bulow in the original -- French and German....&quot;
Not a [[WP:RS]]!)&lt;br&gt;&lt;!--
 --&gt;  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The char's presumably reading [[Frederick the Great]] (master of [[Sanssouci]]) in French and [[Dietrich Heinrich von Bülow]] in German.&lt;br&gt;&lt;!--
 --&gt; I did find on [https://www.google.com/#q=strategy+of+frederick+the+great&amp;safe=off first try]  [http://www.sonshi.com/frederickthegreat.html FREDERICK THE GREAT &quot;MILITARY INSTRUCTIONS&quot;] and [http://www.amazon.com/Frederick-The-Great-Art-War/dp/0306809087 Frederick The Great On The Art Of War Paperback by Jay Luvaas]; are [[Orson Scott Card|Card]]'s characters referring to French commentaries on what Fritz ''did'', rather than any wisdom ''he put on paper'' (in French  as he would apparently have naturally chosen, rather than German)? Or should we suppose that Card is exercising literary license to imagine Fritz having left extended 1st-hand testimony for the ages?&lt;br&gt;--[[User:Jerzy|Jerzy]]•[[User talk:Jerzy|t]] 18:37, 17 March 2014 (UTC)&lt;br&gt;
:::His military writings were influential.  Luvaas says, &quot;He was also a brilliant military thinker whose observations arose from extensive battlefield experience.  This volume [edited by Luvaas] presents a balanced selection from Frederick's writings on strategy, tactics, and mobility; the problems of logistics and etc &quot; [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 00:39, 18 March 2014 (UTC)

== POV Tag ==
The article lacks basic info about the rather differentiated reception, either with regard to the post WWII developement - East Germany changed its derogatory image of Frederick after 1980 significantly, and the role of the King in the West after 1948 till today is left out completely. Fuerthermore, the role of Frederick pre 1870 was much more differentiated as well, e.g. with rather harsh critisism about his role in the [[Austria–Prussia rivalry]]. Serten 08:13, 28 November 2014 (UTC)
::If you have access to fresh information please add it--don't accuse editors of being biased. You have not cited any sources for your personal opinions [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 10:04, 28 November 2014 (UTC)

:::: Point is, the information lacking is not very fresh, but rather old. Honeckers reinstallment of Frederick II rider statue [[Unter den Linden]] start of the 1980ies, Helmut Kohl's role with the reburial in Sanssouci 1991 or the Preussenjahr 2001 festivities have been decades ago, triggered major debates and have been topic of thousands of publications, exhibitions and studies. Nothing in the article.Major scholars like [[:de:Hans-Peter Schwarz (Historiker)]], [[Heinrich August Winkler]] [[Thomas Nipperdey]] are not quoted, not even easter German scholar [[:de:Ingrid Mittenzwei]]s ground breaking biography is included, instead the article relies mostly on the fringy works of a Mr. [[Robert B. Asprey]], a military author with a funny hat, far from academia. Its insofar a little bit more than private opinion and the tag is highly appropriate.  Serten 10:51, 28 November 2014 (UTC)
:::Serten misunderstands the POV rules--he has no complaints that allege. POV -- he suggests new scholarship on some minor points re remembrance that he believes should be added, for which the solution is for Serten to update the article.  If he does not do so then it's unlikely anyone will [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 05:46, 29 November 2014 (UTC)

:::: Goodness, an article about a major figure in German history which leaves out the complete reception history since 1945, does not quote the basic German research and uses funny-hat-hobbyists for a dozen citations? I don't see a problem with a tag per se, but the current one might be more specific. I wont work on any bad article I encounter btw. Serten 06:12, 29 November 2014 (UTC)

== What are German names bastardized? ==

Why does the article call him &quot;Frederick&quot;? And his predecessor and successor &quot;Frederick William&quot;? 

It is an insult to the German People. There is no other group of people that have their names changed into English...[[Special:Contributions/112.198.83.123|112.198.83.123]] ([[User talk:112.198.83.123|talk]]) 11:19, 7 September 2015 (UTC)
:It's sweet of you to defend our language from all the way in the Phillipines, but to be fair, Germans are doing exactly the same thing: Elizabeth II is Elisabeth, her father is Georg, his brother is Eduard. That's just the way it is. [[User:Zwerg Nase|Zwerg Nase]] ([[User talk:Zwerg Nase|talk]]) 11:26, 7 September 2015 (UTC)

::''So ist das Leben.'' [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 17:53, 15 September 2015 (UTC)

I came here looking for his full name in German.  I assume he had more of a name than just &quot;Frederick&quot;, but I can't seem to find anything on the web that has full name. Does anyone have a source? -- [[User:Sam/R|&amp;#x2611; ]]&lt;b&gt;[[User:Sam|Sam]]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#CCCCFF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Sam|uelWantman]]&lt;/font&gt; 22:09, 27 May 2016 (UTC)
::He was known as Friedrich II aus Preußen, or as he later became known, Friedrich der Große. He was the child of König Friedrich Wilhelms I and his wife Sophie Dorothea von Hannover. Georg I of Great Britain was his grandfather on his mother's side and his grandmother on her side was Sophie Dorothea von Braunschweig-Lüneburg. Since he was royalty, he carried the name of his father and the lands to which he was an heir. Not sure what else there is to tell you. In terms of sources for the German name, here is a reliable yet older one. Thomas Carlyle, ''Friedrich der Grosse''; ausgabe in einem Bande, besorgt und eingeleitet von Karl Linnebach (Berlin : M. Warneck, 1910), pp. 13–18.[https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=inu.39000005722652;view=1up;seq=46]-- Hope this helps. [[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 23:50, 10 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>oefe33dyabxdr20t6tyb47qaphglv4b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
