<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Royal Australian Air Force</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2575931</id>
    <revision>
      <id>653096071</id>
      <parentid>653095971</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-03-23T01:42:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fnlayson</username>
        <id>1216158</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Number of B model F/A-18s currently in service */ typo fix</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="66761">{{Talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B|Australian=yes|Aviation=yes|WWI=yes|WWII=yes|National=yes
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=B|importance=high|military=yes|military-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=B
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
}}
}}

== Rating ==
The reason I rated it as a &quot;Start&quot; is that it could be much more than what it currently is.  Just my humble opinion.  --[[User:Looper5920|Looper5920]] 13:22, 18 August 2006 (UTC)
:Do you have any specific suggestions for how the entry could be improved? --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] 23:54, 18 August 2006 (UTC)

== BAE Hawk ==

I changed the Hawk's country of origin from EU to Britain. The EU flag should be used only for European multi-national companies/programs such as the Airbus KC-30. [[User:CMarshall|CMarshall]] ([[User talk:CMarshall|talk]]) 07:26, 14 February 2012 (UTC)

== Future equipment ==
This section is not intirely correct. It should be updated as nothing has been desided officaly as to the replacement of the fleet. Sorry for adding the new section (Fleet retirment and replacements), should have put it in the future equipment section (i'm only new to all this) -- Powderhound11 09:56, 17 October, 2006 (UTC)
: While the F-35 hasn't been 'officially' selected, the Minister for Defence and RAAF have recently ruled out purchasing any other aircraft to replace the F/A-18s and F-111s. The F-22 was explicitly ruled out as being unsuitable. See: http://www.news.com.au/story/0,23599,20556293-31037,00.html If you copy and paste non-neutral material from Karlo Copp's website it will be removed - [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view]] is worth reading and should help. Kopp's point of view appears to be a minority, with the RAAF, Department of Defence and Australian Security Policy Institute supporting the F-35 over the other available aircraft (the ASPI publication at: http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=42&amp;pubtype=5 is a good example of the arguments in favour of the F-35 and the unfeasibility of purchasing F-22s and keeping the F-111's airworthy as Kopp proposes) --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] 10:06, 17 October 2006 (UTC)
: Thanks for your help :) . From what i have read and what Kopp's saying it looks to me that buying the F-22s and keeping the F-111's is the best option for the RAAF, as the F-35 is outclassed by surrounding Countries Fighters. --Powderhound11 10:27, 17 October 2006 (UTC)
:: Aparently the RAAF considers the F-22 unsuitable for Australia's requirements as it is only effective in a single role (air superiority) while the F-35 is a much more capable attack aircraft. Kopp isn't held in high regard by much of the Australian defence community and while his articles are typically interesting they shouldn't be considered the last word on the topic. --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] 10:53, 17 October 2006 (UTC)
:Yes i agree with you on that last point, although the issue is quiet intriguing. It's a pitty little is published about this issue. --Powderhound11, 17 October 2006
::I just came across an interesting online news paper article stating that the US wonnt let us buy the F/A - 22, if true it could explain alot. see: http://www.theage.com.au/news/National/US-decisions-threaten-fighter-project/2006/08/04/1154198330441.html -- Powderhound11, 17 October 2006
:::Yes, and the fact that the F-22 is too expensive. If it were for sale and a purchase was made by the RAAF, they won't be available in significant numbers to be effective. My rationale for the F-35 is 1)multi-role better for a middle power nation 2)upgrade and spares capability - the RAAF doesn't want to stuck with an aircraft that is only used by few or is too old (eg. F-111) 3)Asia-pacific region has a US bias - geopolitical reality. The procurement debate seems to be a clash of the multi-role vs air superiority paradigm. [[User:Htra0497|Htra0497]] 15:04, 11 November 2006 (AEST)
:What does JSF stand for? (the article does not say) --AUser 14:30 11 December 2006 &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/218.214.46.95|218.214.46.95]] ([[User talk:218.214.46.95|talk]]) 03:33, 11 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

It stands for Joint Strike Fighter.

Acquisition of 24 F/A-18F Block II as an interim replacement for the F-111 was announced today. Text updated with link to media release. [[User:Dbromage|Dbromage]] 04:21, 6 March 2007 (UTC)

== Munitions ==
Could we get a list of the munitions utilised by RAAF aircarft? eg. JDAMs, GBUs, Harpoons etc [[User:Htra0497|Htra0497]] 15:04, 11 November 2006 (AEST)

== Today's photo removal ==
Why were the aircraft photos removed by [[User:Imgi12]]? I think they added a lot to the page. [[User:Mlouns|Mlouns]] 07:15, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
: I presume it was becuase they were squishing the table of aircraft up. I've reduced the size of the photos, but they really need to be moved so the table works properly. --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] 07:28, 1 February 2007 (UTC)

:: Would arranging them in a horizontal strip (Gallery fashion) make sense? [[User:Mlouns|Mlouns]] 16:16, 1 February 2007 (UTC)

== Deletion ==
Removed Robert Little's name from the list of WWI aces. He never served in any Australian formation. He served in the Royal Naval Air Service.  --[[User:Catstroke|Catstroke]]

: OK, that makes sense, sorry for the revert. I hope Little is mentioned in an appropriate list for that service? [[User:Mlouns|Mlouns]] 23:25, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

: Little listed in the Notable Personnel section of the RNAS article [[user:Catstroke|Catstroke]] 

== F-22==

If anyone is still following the yes/no/maybe/wrong aeroplane/too expensive/unavailable debate in Canberra re the US denying F-22s for the RAAF then the following link should be an eye-opener. http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/2006/10/retired-raaf-vicemarshal-abandon-f35-buy-f22s-updated/index.php 
-- [[User:Catstroke|Catstroke]]

== F-35 numbers ==
I read in Australian press that the USAAF has halved it's orders for the F-35 but have not been able to confirm this. I left a similar note in the F-35 talk pages but no one has replied. This is very serious for us. Does anyone know more? [[User:Brettr|Brettr]] 01:58, 19 February 2007 (UTC)
: None have actually been ordered. A final decision on placing an order will not be made until 2008. [[User:Dbromage|Dbromage]] 04:19, 6 March 2007 (UTC)

==Roundel==
I find the history of the RAAF Roundel pretty interesting and believe a paragraph on the subject to be worthy of inclusion. I intend to put it at the bottom of the page, and move the pictures of the Roundel. Any objections? [[User:RP Bravo|RP Bravo]] 12:10, 15 March 2007 (UTC)
:[[Wikipedia:Be bold in updating pages|Go for it]] --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] 08:38, 16 March 2007 (UTC)

== Userbox ==
I've prepared some userboxes for different Air Forces freaks - if you would like to use it, feel free to copy &amp; paste following code in your Babel Tower or another place:

&lt;nowiki&gt;{{User:Piotr Mikołajski/Userboxes/RAAFhv}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;

or

&lt;nowiki&gt;{{User:Piotr Mikołajski/Userboxes/RAAFlv}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;

First one is [[User:Piotr Mikołajski/Userboxes/RAAFhv|high visibility]] roundel (and colours), second one is [[User:Piotr Mikołajski/Userboxes/RAAFlv|low-vis]] - see examples below. --[[User:Piotr Mikołajski|Piotr Mikołajski]] 07:20, 13 April 2007 (UTC)

{{User:Piotr Mikołajski/Userboxes/RAAFhv}} {{User:Piotr Mikołajski/Userboxes/RAAFlv}}

&lt;br/&gt;
== New Government ==

Does anyone know what Rudd is intending to do, regarding the finilisation of the purchase of the f-35, potentially switching to the f-22 and/or cancelling the super hornets?
This is in light of the F-22 article that says australia's (then) opposition is in favour of purchasing some F-22's. So basically, is Rudd going to put the pressure on to get some Raptors?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/58.165.107.1|58.165.107.1]] ([[User talk:58.165.107.1|talk]]) 19:42, 19 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I don't see any signs of the current Democrat Party-controlled US Congress changing the laws to allow exports of the F-22, which is currently illegal. That might change after the Federal Elections this year, depending upon who wins the White House, and what party controls the House and/or Senate, but it's unlikely to make a difference at this point. - [[User:BillCJ|BillCJ]] ([[User talk:BillCJ|talk]]) 19:57, 19 January 2008 (UTC)

:The new Government has ordered a full review of the RAAF's fighter replacement program. While it looks like the F/A-18Fs might get the chop, there's been no mention of F-22s from Labor for a while now - presumably for the reason Bill notes. See [http://www.smh.com.au/news/national/axe-to-fall-on-fighter-jets/2007/12/30/1198949675365.html] for a news report on this. --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] ([[User talk:Nick Dowling|talk]]) 22:25, 19 January 2008 (UTC)


Not true, a new edit in the f-22 article claims that the new defence minister is thinking of attempting to acquire the plane in lieu of the super hornets, with the possibility of even investigating russian built planes mentioned in the cited article, so i think the future equipment section should be edited, especially since the f-35 looks far from scheduled for delivery to the RAAF right now.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/58.165.107.1|58.165.107.1]] ([[User talk:58.165.107.1|talk]]) 14:58, 27 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:That text didn't reflect what the source actually said. The F-35 and F/A-18 purchase is under review and no decision has been taken to walk away from the F-35. I believe that Labor's policy is to operate a mix of F-22s and F-35s. --[[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] ([[User talk:Nick Dowling|talk]]) 22:02, 27 January 2008 (UTC)

Yes, but there is no concrete order for a set ammount of F-35's at the moment, so I find it hard to believe that they are scheduled for delivery.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/58.165.107.1|58.165.107.1]] ([[User talk:58.165.107.1|talk]]) 06:15, 28 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== New Current Aircraft Article ==

I have created a new article called [[Current Royal Australian Air Force Aircraft]], I also added a link to it under the &quot;Current strength&quot; section.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jezstar|Jezstar]] ([[User talk:Jezstar|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jezstar|contribs]]) 03:24, 10 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Incidents and accidents==
How come this article does not have a section like this, as articles about commercial airlines typically do?  Certainly some of the events are notable. &lt;font style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Socrates2008 (&lt;font size=3&gt;[[User talk:Socrates2008|Talk]]&lt;/font&gt;)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 12:04, 2 September 2008 (UTC)
:Because no-one has written it yet. I don't think that any of the air force articles have such sections, however, and such a section may not be appropriate given that the RAAF has lost hundreds of aircraft in accidents and combat. Which notable incidents and accidents would you like to include? [[User:Nick Dowling|Nick Dowling]] ([[User talk:Nick Dowling|talk]]) 12:12, 2 September 2008 (UTC)


Um, the biggest jet crash in Australia's history perhaps?

== RAAF during Confrontation with Indonesia==
Although Confrontation was primarily a ground war, and the RAAFs role in it quite limited, does anyone else think it would be appropriate to include a paragraph on the RAAF during this conflict? I would add the material myself however I don't really have suitable knowledge or sources on this topic. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 11:48, 2 January 2009 (UTC)
:Yes, though this kind of detail might be best placed in the [[History of the Royal Australian Air Force]] article... [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 02:06, 3 January 2009 (UTC)
::Didn't the Canberra's go operational during this period?--[[User:Senor Freebie|Senor Freebie]] ([[User talk:Senor Freebie|talk]]) 05:43, 25 May 2009 (UTC)

Sorry folks, just felt it needed to be pointed out that the introduction has an error or perhaps is unclear in meaning. It mentions the RAAF was formed in 1921, then claims it was engaged in World Wars I  ( ~ and II). Although of coarse Australia was heavily involved in the first World War's air war, the Australian Air Force and later the ROYAL Australian Air Force was not.

Sorry to be a fly in the ointment, kindest regards

Walt [[User:Outofthewoods|Outofthewoods]] ([[User talk:Outofthewoods|talk]]) 01:36, 1 June 2009 (UTC)

:I don't see that it's unclear. The article states clearly &quot;The RAAF began in March 1912 as the '''Australian Flying Corps''' and became a fully independent Air Force in March 1921&quot;, so when it says the RAAF took part in both world wars it was obviously as the AFC in WWI. --[[User:AussieLegend|AussieLegend]] ([[User talk:AussieLegend|talk]]) 10:20, 1 June 2009 (UTC)

== Motto question ==
Uninformed wikipedian beginner here, my apologies in advance: Isn't the motto more accurately translated as &quot;Through Adversity to the Stars&quot;?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/60.228.2.150|60.228.2.150]] ([[User talk:60.228.2.150|talk]]) 21:50, 2 June 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:As far as I'm aware, yes it is. When I first joined the RAAF in 1978 that was the English translation that was used officially but, for some reason, the current translation is what has been officially adopted now. --[[User:AussieLegend|AussieLegend]] ([[User talk:AussieLegend|talk]]) 22:27, 2 June 2009 (UTC)

== Boeing 707 ==

The article presently contains an image of a Boeing 707.  See [[Royal Australian Air Force#Service since 1945|HERE]].  I understand that the last RAAF 707 was retired in 2008.  To avoid conveying a misleading impression about the current status of the 707, I suggest an alternative image is used, or the caption changed to indicate the historical nature of the photograph. [[User:Dolphin51|Dolphin51]] ([[User talk:Dolphin51|talk]]) 06:57, 3 March 2010 (UTC)
:Great idea - I've replaced it with a more interesting photo [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 07:20, 3 March 2010 (UTC)

== World's second oldest air force? ==

The South African Air Force also claims to be the second oldest air force in the world.  Which one is it?
[[Special:Contributions/121.216.18.128|121.216.18.128]] ([[User talk:121.216.18.128|talk]]) 09:58, 23 April 2010 (UTC)
:It is difficult to find accurate information on that matter.
*The RAAF website says October 22, 1912 for the date of official approval. [http://www.raaf.gov.au/history/ww1.aspx]
*This unofficial SAAF run website says 1913 [http://www.saairforce.co.za/the-airforce/history/saaf/south-africa-aviation-corps]
*The SAAF website doesn't specify an official establishment date, instead it refers to a provision for the formation of the South African Aviation Corps in 1912 [http://www.af.mil.za/about_us/history.html#2]
If you are referring to the date of formation as an air force. SAAF was formed on 1 February 1920. RAAF was formed on 31 March 1921.
So, it's hard to say. I think this subject requires more research and investigation. [[User:SCΛRECROW|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;SCΛRECROW&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:SCΛRECROW|&lt;font color=&quot;#007400&quot;&gt;CrossCom&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 10:32, 23 April 2010 (UTC)

:Honestly - the lead was highly POV (coming directly from an RAAF site quite understandably)- I have rewritten it as:
:* The AFC and RAAF were two different services, although the second can accurately be described as continuing the role and traditions of the first. 
:* &quot;Air force&quot; in the sense of an &quot;organised force of military aircraft&quot; - there were obviously any number of these during WWI - and prior to 1912 for that matter. The German and French air forces (in this sense) date from 1910!
:* &quot;Air Force&quot; in the sense of a separate service with no connection with the army or navy - the RAF and the SAAF at least, are both older, and I suspect so are some other services - in any case the article mentioned 1912 in this regard - which would have predated the formation of the RAF (in 1918) by 6 years.

:Until somebody comes up with some real research on this matter (which obviously needs to look outside the British Empire!! I think the new lead is fair enough - and at least more encyclopedic than the old one. 
:--[[User:Soundofmusicals|Soundofmusicals]] ([[User talk:Soundofmusicals|talk]]) 11:12, 18 May 2010 (UTC)

the thing is when you looking into the RAAF history is that it was once know by at least 3 different names the AFC, AAF, RAAF and a few before others the 31 march 21' (origanaly the 1st was planned but they did't want to be knowen as a joke)was when the AAF was formed the prefix royal wasent added until AUG that year
&quot;Final approval to establish the Australian Flying Corps was promulgated in Military Order No.570 on 22 October 1912, with orders placed for two B.E.2a, two Deperdussin and a Bristol Boxkite to equip the new air arm&quot;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/124.182.117.114|124.182.117.114]] ([[User talk:124.182.117.114|talk]]) 10:33, 15 August 2010 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP2 --&gt;
:Whilst the AFC was formed prior to World War I, it was raised as a Corps of the Australian Army, not as an independant service. [[User:AusTerrapin|AusTerrapin]] ([[User talk:AusTerrapin|talk]]) 15:19, 15 August 2010 (UTC)

== F-111's? ==

Just wandering should not the F-111 be given some more information regarding the problems and difficulties faced by the air force. From what I know these air craft are still in hangar's/limited use and should therefore be listed as still being actively used or at the very least be referred to as F-111(to be phased out).

Thanks in advance [[User:AussieSkeptic82|AussieSkeptic82]] ([[User talk:AussieSkeptic82|talk]]) 16:57, 7 December 2010 (UTC)

F-111 final flight was 3 December, they will never fly again.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mrteeve|Mrteeve]] ([[User talk:Mrteeve|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mrteeve|contribs]]) 23:08, 31 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Procurement review section removed ==

I've just [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=420124901&amp;oldid=420118097 removed] the 'Procurement review' section as the topic it covers (the 2007-2008 review of whether to go ahead with the F/A-18Fs and F-35s) is now outdated as the review endorsed these purchases and they've since gone ahead (albeit partially in the case of the F-35). [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 10:41, 22 March 2011 (UTC)

==C-130J==
in this model it cannot take an Australian tank (bushmaster i think) due to the cargo door not opening upwards
this is different to the last model (C-123H)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/124.189.148.38|124.189.148.38]] ([[User talk:124.189.148.38|talk]]) 06:25, 12 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Uniform Colour ==

Midnight Blue has a lot more white in it and is lighter than Navy Blue.  Navy Blue is very close to black.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/117.120.18.135|117.120.18.135]] ([[User talk:117.120.18.135|talk]]) 06:37, 27 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Official RAAF Colours ==

The US Air Force included their official colours on their wiki page, like this:
|colors= [[Ultramarine|Ultramarine Blue]] and [[Gold (color)#Yellow|Air Force Yellow]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AFcolors&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lackland.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-070324-002.pdf |title=The Air Force Flag|date=24 March 2007 |work=Air Force Historical Research Agency |publisher=United States Air Force |accessdate=27 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Color box|#120a8f}}{{Color box|#FFDF00}}
and I was wondering if the RAAF had official colours as well? [[User:Brandon.hargraves|Brandon.hargraves]] ([[User talk:Brandon.hargraves|talk]]) 05:23, 8 December 2012 (UTC)

{{reflist-talk}}

== RAAF Heron ==
Hello, I was wondering what picture we can use in the current aircraft table? I uploaded http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:RAAF_IAI_Heron_on_the_ground.jpg because there weren't any RAAF Herons on wikipedia, but apparently there is an obtainable free version of the RAAF Heron we can use. If somebody could aid me in my search for a free image of a '''RAAF''' Heron, then that would be greatly appreciated. If we cannot find an alternative, will we be able to use http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:IAI_Heron_1_in_flight_2.JPEG? It is in use by the US however. [[User:Brandon.hargraves|Brandon.hargraves]] ([[User talk:Brandon.hargraves|talk]]) 05:17, 8 December 2012 (UTC)
:Unless the RAAF has been showing off its single-Australia based Heron at airshows (which I've never seen any indication of in the Aviation press) I really doubt that a free alternative for that photo exists. The other two Herons are permanently deployed to Afghanistan. I've removed the tag from that image as it didn't make much sense. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 05:49, 8 December 2012 (UTC)
::Actually, it seems that the RAAF put the thing on display last year: [http://www.airliners.net/photo/Australia---Air/Israel-Aircraft-Industries/1917193/&amp;sid=c85929b20d3c2f0e7cb7b8849ceaab38]. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 10:30, 8 December 2012 (UTC)

== Engagements ==
Doesn't Vietnam count as an &quot;Engagement&quot;?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Lexysexy|Lexysexy]] ([[User talk:Lexysexy|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Lexysexy|contribs]]) 03:39, 23 December 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: Indeed, seems to be an oversight to me. I've added it now to the infobox. BTW I've removed Sudan from the infobox as RAAF involvement (indeed ADF involvement) is minor and doesn't even rate a mention in the article. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 05:29, 23 December 2012 (UTC)

== F-35s in the list of current aircraft ==

I've just, hopefully accurately, added the two Australian F-35s to the list of current RAAF aircraft. It appears they they've been accepted into service given that they're about to start being used for training flights, but I can't find a source which explicitly says this. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 03:14, 20 December 2014 (UTC)

== New aircraft numbers table ==

{{ping|FOX 52}} I've just reverted the article back to the version before your most recent changes. While I agree that the aircraft table would benefit greatly from a revamp and appreciate your efforts, the material you were adding contained a lot of mistakes. For instance, Australia has ordered 72 F-35s, not 100 (the government has an intention to order 100 eventually, but hasn't signed up to do so); 16 AP-3s are in service, not 4 ([http://australianaviation.com.au/2014/10/raaf-orion-drawdown-begins/]); 8 P-8s have been ordered, not 12 (though options for a further 4 have been taken out); and 3 CL-600s are in service, not 1. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 22:31, 28 December 2014 (UTC)

:As most of the detail is at [[List of current Royal Australian Air Force aircraft]] perhaps it could be made a lot simpler and changed to prose to detail types by roles rather than a chunky table. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 23:47, 28 December 2014 (UTC)

::That's a good idea. I'd also suggest omitting the column with the source country national flags: these add visual clutter and aren't very useful, and including a statement somewhere that the RAAF sources its aircraft from the US and Europe would be more helpful to readers. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 23:59, 28 December 2014 (UTC)

{{ping|Nick-D}} If there's an issue with a few number(s) discrepancies, off of different sources (mine: [http://www.flightglobal.com/ flightglobal’s] 2015 World Air Forces report) then simply change what you think needs fixing. A full roll back accomplishes zero, and puts a few dead links back in play. Since you agree the section needed a face lift, I’m going restore my updates, with your numbers (which were 4 out of 16 aircraft) not really “major mistakes” and we'll work it from there. On a side note I’m for the table(s), because one just about every military article uses them, and two I think it's an easy and concise way for the reader to obtain the information they seek.  - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 05:35, 29 December 2014 (UTC)
: In my opinion these were major mistakes and if Nick hadn't reverted I would have (although you now seem to have corrected the ones I saw). That said if these mistakes represent what is published in the &quot;2015 World Air Forces&quot; report then I question whether it is a [[WP:RS|reliable source]]. I'm not an aviation expert though so I'll leave that assessment up to others with more knowledge. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 05:48, 29 December 2014 (UTC)
::To be more specific the some numbers are based on projected acquisitions, and really should be left out per [[WP:CBALL]] - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 06:47, 29 December 2014 (UTC)
:::Has has been suggested this article doesnt need the numbers (that is what the sub-article is for) just a summary of the types and roles. [[User:MilborneOne|MilborneOne]] ([[User talk:MilborneOne|talk]]) 11:19, 29 December 2014 (UTC)

== Number of B model F/A-18s currently in service ==

Gday. This was recently changed from 18 to 16 by IP 101 here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;diff=652063078&amp;oldid=652061260] but then reverted by another editor. As far as I'm aware though there are only a total of 71 F/A-18 As and Bs as four have crashed. Indeed this is stated in the [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet]] article which states: &quot;''Australia had 71 Hornets in service in 2006, after four were lost to crashes.''&quot;[34] which is referenced to: Crick, Darren. [http://www.adf-serials.com/3a21.shtml &quot;ADF Aircraft Serial Numbers RAAF A21 McDonnell Douglas F/A-18A/B Hornet.&quot;] ''adf-serials.com''. Retrieved: 31 December 2006. (which has now moved to here [http://www.adf-gallery.com.au/]). This ref confirms that two As have crashed from the original total of 57 (leaving 55) and two B models from the original total of 18 (leaving 16). The article previously stated that the RAAF currently has 55 As and 18 Bs which equals 73 not 71 so was therefore wrong. Also our article [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service]] confirms a total of 71 following four crashes and provides the details of the four lost with citations listing the details of those incidents. As such the World Air Forces 2015 source looks to be wrong in this case if it does indeed state 18 Bs in service. As such I have restored the edits. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 14:21, 19 March 2015 (UTC)
: BTW I've added a new ref for the 16 F/A-18Bs now. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 16:17, 19 March 2015 (UTC)
::adf-gallery.com appears to be a [[WP:SPS|self published]] site, perhaps there is a [[WP:NOTRELIABLE|reliable source]] news source or secondary source to verify claim on the numbers - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 19:27, 19 March 2015 (UTC)
:::* Firstly the ADF Serials website has been used as a reference in [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service]] which is a featured article so I'd say it is considered reliable. 
:::*Regardless, Yes there are numerous reliable sources which indicate that only 71 remain (not 73). For instance:
::::* The Australian National Audit Office report here - [http://www.anao.gov.au/Publications/Audit-Reports/2012-2013/F18/Audit-brochure] which states: &quot;'''This audit examines the upgrade and sustainment of the Royal Australian Air Force’s (RAAF’s) fleet of 71 F/A-18A/B Hornet aircraft and the sustainment of 24 F/A-18F Super Hornet aircraft. These aircraft form the basis of the RAAF’s air combat and airborne ground-attack capability.''&quot;; and
::::* The RAAF site here [http://www.airforce.gov.au/Technology/Aircraft/Hornet/?RAAF-9SSttIt/E93/3lV4LgVxgxc0y4P09YW2] which states: &quot;''Based at RAAF Base Williamtown and RAAF Base Tindal, the 71 F/A-18A/B Hornets are an integral part of Australia’s air combat capability.''&quot;
:::* I cannot find any source other than Crick which states succinctly that only 55 As and 16 Bs remain; however, this is fairly clear from the fol:
::::* The fact that a total of 75 were purchased, including 57 As and 18 Bs is a referenced fact in the [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service]] (Wilson, Stewart (January–March 2005). &quot;Made in Australia: Hornet&quot;. Aero Australia. No. 5: pp. 32–42. ISSN 1448-8086, p. 42). 
::::* Wilson, Stewart (1994) &quot;Military Aircraft of Australia&quot; p. 147 states that the As were allocated tail numbers A21-1 to A2-57, while the Bs were given tail numbers A21-101 to A21-118 (also confirmed here by the RAAF Museum if you wish to verify [http://www.airforce.gov.au/raafmuseum/research/aircraft/series3/A21.htm]).
::::* The details of the four lost in accidents are included (with references) in [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service]] which states: &quot;''Four of the RAAF's Hornets were destroyed in flying accidents during the late 1980s and early 1990s. A21-104 was the first aircraft to be lost when it crashed at Great Palm Island in Queensland on 18 November 1987; its pilot was killed. The next loss occurred on 2 August 1990 when two No. 75 Squadron Hornets (A21-21 and A21-42) collided. A21-42 crashed, killing the unit's commanding officer; the other aircraft was damaged but managed to return to base. On 5 June 1990 A21-41 crashed 100 kilometres (62 mi) north-east of Weipa, Queensland, killing its pilot. A21-106 was the fourth aircraft to be lost when it crashed inland from Shoalwater Bay in Queensland on 19 May 1992 – its pilot and a passenger from the Defence Science and Technology Organisation died.''&quot; This is referenced to ADF Serials and to Wilson, Stewart (1993). Phantom, Hornet, and Skyhawk in Australian Service. Weston Creek, ACT: Aerospace Publications. ISBN 187567103X, pp. 124-125.
::::* So from the tail numbers we can see two As have been lost (A21-42 and A21-41) and two Bs (A21-104 and A21-106). That means that there are 55 As left (from the 57 purchased) and 16 Bs (from the 18 purchased).
::::* Currently the article states there are 55 As and 18 Bs which equals 73, which is clearly incorrect. As such I will amend it ''again'' to the correct figures and provide the additional citation as you have requested. However, if you still have an issue with the break down of the number of As and Bs we can just say there are 71 A/Bs as this is clearly supported by numerous reliable sources as I have shown above. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:06, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
{{od}} On further looking, there is another very interesting source available here, which covers the details of the loss of these four aircraft in detail: {{cite book |author=Directorate of Defence Aviation and Air Force Safety|date=2007 |title=Sifting through the evidence : RAAF F-111 and AF/A-18 aircraft and crew losses |url=http://www.pigzbum.com/accidents/sifting-through-the-evidenc.pdf|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|location=Canberra|oclc=271545224}}. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:25, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
:{{U|Anotherclown}} my apologies as I’ve found the culprit to the confusion, user ''“Markdukes21”'' made a number change [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;diff=640609491&amp;oldid=640609311 here].  Thus when I corrected the format, the incorrect numbers were passed along. For the record I did input the accurate [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;diff=639908239&amp;oldid=639908144  number(s)] prior to ''Markdukes21'' erroneous switch – cheers [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 04:52, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
:: No worries at least that issue is resolved - However, I disagree with you consistently changing back IP 101s edits to &quot;AWACS&quot; as this is not a term used by the RAAF. They use &quot;AWE&amp;C&quot; - pls see here [http://www.airforce.gov.au/Technology/Aircraft/B737-Wedgetail/?RAAF-yFLAkgbpvuhRf7dG5J3kHi1Q4caywtso], equally describing the B model as a trainer is not accurate either. Whilst used for conversion training by No. 2 OCU it is a mult-role fighter and is described as so by the RAAF, see here [http://www.airforce.gov.au/Technology/Aircraft/Hornet/?RAAF-9SSttIt/E93/3lV4LgVxgxc0y4P09YW2] which states &quot;''The Royal Australian Air Force F/A-18A and F/A-18B Hornets are multi-role fighter aircraft, capable of air-to-air and air-to-ground missions''&quot;. Also per my earlier posts so does the ANAO report which states: &quot;''the Royal Australian Air Force’s (RAAF’s) fleet of 71 F/A-18A/B Hornet aircraft and the sustainment of 24 F/A-18F Super Hornet aircraft. These aircraft form the basis of the RAAF’s air combat and airborne ground-attack capability''...&quot;. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 06:43, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
:::As another source for 71 aircraft remaining in service, see page 42 of the [http://www.defence.gov.au/budget/14-15/2014-2015_Defence_PBS_03_Defence.pdf 2014-15 Defence Portfolio Budget Statements]. The F/A-18Bs have received exactly the same upgrades as the As, and are just as capable of participating in combat. Their main role is pilot conversion training though (most are with 2 OCU, and each of the three frontline squadrons apparently has a F/A-18B on strength). [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 06:50, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
:::: Gday Nick, thanks for confirming that. My understanding is that the main difference (other than the Guy in Back) is the Bs carry slightly less fuel. Also I have changed &quot;Electronic Aircraft&quot; to &quot;Electronic Warfare&quot; as that more accurately reflects the terminology used by the RAAF here [http://www.airforce.gov.au/Technology/Aircraft/EA18G-Growler/?RAAF-wWtm2RqFW2K0Pyup3hIJncFVFKb02OLN] - it also happens to more closely follow the naming convention used on Wikipedia (our article is called [[Electronic-warfare aircraft]] after all. I have no idea what an &quot;Electronic Aircraft&quot; is. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 06:57, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
AEW&amp;C or AWACS is fine either way. Now the F-18B is a different story the RAAF website only speaks in general terms of the “F/A-18A/B” of what they “can” do operationally.  The B model was intended as a conversion/trainer aircraft –according to Dennis R. Jenkins book ''F/A-18 Hornet: A Navy Success Story'' (pg. 19) Mcgraw-Hill, 2000; ISBN 0071346961 he states the TF-18A two-seat training version of the F/A-18A fighter, was later re-designated F/A-18B – [http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pictures-australia39s-f-111-retirement-to-close-chapter-of-aviation-350223/ This]  article specifies ''“Australia's air force inventory also includes 55 F/A-18A fighters and 16 F/A-18B trainers”''.  Hence the larger number of 55 A’s for actual combat versus only 16 B’s which you’d normally use for training. [http://www.airforce.gov.au/raafmuseum/research/aircraft/series3/A21.htm RAAF Museum cook point] mentions in December 1988, the last dual-seat Hornet, A21-118, was delivered, each squadron is allocated one dual-seaters, the [[Aircraft Research and Development Unit RAAF|ARDU]] operates one, and the remainder equip [[No. 2 Operational Conversion Unit RAAF|2OCU]] for their '''primary role''' of type conversion (trainer). [http://r.search.yahoo.com/_ylt=AwrSbni2dwxVPH0A9ORXNyoA;_ylu=X3oDMTEya2xybDRnBGNvbG8DZ3ExBHBvcwMyBHZ0aWQDUTFNQzFfMQRzZWMDc3I-/RV=2/RE=1426909239/RO=10/RU=http%3a%2f%2fwww.flightglobal.com%2fassets%2fgetasset.aspx%3fItemID%3d26061/RK=0/RS=NN_X2acrYcjW6S.tPUv0G0gAr6g- World Air Force 2008] refers to the RAAF F/A-18B as trainer.
Here on the [http://www.navy.mil/navydata/fact_display.asp?cid=1100&amp;tid=1200&amp;ct=1 US Navy website] also states ''&quot;The B model is used primarily for training&quot;.'' 
Wikipedia's article [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service#Production|F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service]] has sourced text stating ''“order of 75 Hornets comprised 57 single-seat &quot;A&quot; variant fighters and 18 two-seat &quot;B&quot; variant operational training aircraft”''. It's a difference between primary and secondary roles. - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 22:19, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
::G'day, it seems like a matter of semantics to me (but I'm purely a ground based mammal) so I think a note of some description seems to best way to resolve the issue/compromise. But whether it is listed as primarily trainer with a secondary combat role, or vice versa should be determined by consensus first instead of constantly being changed. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 23:08, 20 March 2015 (UTC)
:::{{done}} - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 00:28, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
{{od}}{{ping|FOX 52}} - I still disagree with your latest amendments, and with you changing this yet again without waiting for consensus to develop like AR suggested. My objective is based on the following points:
# You cite US Navy, Flight Global, Jenkins etc, all of which appear to be primarily American sources. The RAAF source and the Australian National Audit Office report I have provided above are far more authoritative as they both describe their role specifically in ''Australian service'' which is the issue here. They use the term &quot;multi-role&quot; and state that both the As and the Bs are part of Australia's &quot;air-combat&quot; capability. 
# You ask &quot;what they “can” do operationally&quot; - well we have already established that haven't we? As Nick showed above &lt;u&gt;the Bs are fully combat capable aircraft in Australian service&lt;/u&gt;; however, they are primarily used for pilot conversion training. This is of cse their peace-time role though. What role would / could they be used in if req'd? Combat obviously. This is evidenced by the fact that they have received all the same upgrades as the As (why spend all that money on an advanced trainer?). Australia has a very small air combat capability (unlike the US) and were it involved in a major regional conflict would inevitability end up having to use its Bs in this role (as unlikely as such a situation might seem at this moment). Undoubtedly this is very different to the US Navy or Marine Corps as they have a much larger fleet of aircraft to use so would not have to use their Bs in that role. 
#Such points aside, your argument misses a fairly obvious point which is that the majority of ''all military equipment'' is used primarily for training and only ever rarely used for actual combat (for instance the F/A-18As have only been deployed twice on operations by the RAAF - 2003 and 2015 - but have been in service since the mid 1980s, while the F-111s and Mirages were never used in combat). So should we list it all under &quot;training&quot;? Obviously we would not. The RAAF - the user of this equipment - calls them multi-role combat air craft and maintains them to be used this way if required, but during normal peace-time operations uses them for conversion (primarily) but also for wpns testing with ARDU, and for exercises. 
As such I propose the As and Bs be both listed together under the combat aircraft heading (where they were previously until changed without discussion by Fox 52 in Dec 14 [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;diff=639908239&amp;oldid=639908144]), the numbers of As and Bs be split and specified, and a note included (as it was recently) describing the As as &quot;multirole&quot; and the Bs as &quot;multrole / conversion training&quot; or some similar variation per the below example.&lt;br&gt;
'''Proposed entry #1'''
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|Aircraft
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#acc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align:left; background:#acc;&quot;|Variant
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|In service
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Notes
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Military aircraft#Combat aircraft|Combat Aircraft]]
|-
|[[F/A-18]]
|{{USA}}
|multirole&lt;hr&gt;multirole&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/Technology/Aircraft/Hornet/?RAAF-9SSttIt/E93/3lV4LgVxgxc0y4P09YW2|title=Technology: Aircraft: F/A-18A/B Hornet |date=|website=airforce.gov.au|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|access-date=20 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; / conversion trainer&lt;ref name=&quot; WAF 2014&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last = |first = |url= http://img.en25.com/Web/flightglobal/%7B88f2f053-6c3d-4ab4-a297-0b453358a560%7D_FC055_PREM_201312.pdf?elq=&amp;elqCampaignId= World Air Forces 2014|title = WAF 2014|work= |publisher= Flightglobal Insight |year= 2014 |doi = |accessdate= 15 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web|url= http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pictures-australia39s-f-111-retirement-to-close-chapter-of-aviation-350223/|title= Australia's F-111 retirement to close chapter |publisher= flightglobal.com |date=|accessdate=10 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[F/A-18#Variants|F/A-18A]]&lt;hr&gt;[[F/A-18#Variants|F/A-18B]]
| 55&lt;ref name=&quot; World Air Forces 2015 pg. 11&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last = |first = |url= http://forms.flightglobal.com/WorldAirForces2015?product=PREM&amp;mode=DOWNLOAD&amp;DMDcode=FGWC4&amp;fcid=%7B05ceef25-b72e-4bea-9a83-a7ab7d02e55a%7D_FC078_PREM_201412&amp;fcfileext=pdf |title = World Air Forces 2015 pg. 11|work= |publisher= Flightglobal Insight |year= 2015 |doi = |accessdate= 26 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;hr&gt;16&lt;ref name=&quot; World Air Forces 2015 pg. 11&quot;/&gt;
|
|} 
{{reflist}}
{{ping|AustralianRupert}} and {{ping|Nick-D}}, as you have participated in this discussion to date I also request your further opinion about this specific proposal. If the issue is one of primary vs secondary role then we can switch the order to &quot;conversion trainer / mult-role&quot;. Of cse I am more than happy for some other proposal to be put forward by you or someone else; however, my bottom line is that placing the F/A-18Bs under the &quot;Training Aircraft&quot; section is inaccurate and is not supported by the most appropriate sources (i.e. the official RAAF and government auditor description of them which is &quot;multirole&quot; and &quot;combat&quot; aircraft). BTW as an example of how these aircraft are treated elsewhere see the [[Spanish Air Force]] article which lists all models of their F/A-18s together under a very similar &quot;Combat Aircraft&quot; heading. Equally [[List of military aircraft of the United States]] which lists all models (A/B/C/D) under the &quot;fighter&quot; heading. Similar groupings occur with air forces operating C and Ds - see [[Kuwait Air Force]], [[Finnish Air Force]] and [[List of aircraft of the Swiss Air Force]] for instance. Indeed the RAAF article seems to be the odd one out. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 03:07, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
: Likewise [[List of current Royal Australian Air Force aircraft]] which also lumps the F/A-18s together. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 03:28, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
::You couldn’t have stated it more clearly ''“the Bs are fully combat capable aircraft in Australian service, &lt;u&gt;'''however, they are primarily used for pilot conversion training'''”&lt;/u&gt;''; And if you want pull out Wikipedia articles, then you have to see [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet#Export variants| F/A-18 Hornet export variants]]:
*'''(A)F/A-18A''': Single-seat fighter/attack version for the [[Royal Australian Air Force]].
*'''(A)F/A-18B''': Two-seat training version for the Royal Australian Air Force.
*'''EF-18A''': Single-seat fighter/attack version for the [[Spanish Air Force]]
*'''EF-18B''': Two-seat training version for the Spanish Air Force.
the [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service#Production|F/A-18 Hornet in Australian service]] article has &lt;u&gt;sourced&lt;/u&gt; text stating ''“order of 75 Hornets comprised 57 single-seat &quot;A&quot; variant fighters and 18 two-seat &quot;B&quot; variant operational training aircraft”''.
The [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet# Variants|C/D variants]] are a moot point because the &quot;D&quot; model was built with the intention as a multi-role aircraft having a [[Weapon systems officer|WSO]] in the back seat, validated by this [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1990/1990%20-%200020.html article]. Furthermore 3 of the 4 sources call the RAAF F/A-18B a trainer, and the RAAF website [http://www.airforce.gov.au/Disclaimer/?RAAF-PLcxMZ4R0xaxF2ajINEU2+bvTEIvzAJv disclaimer] notes ''&quot; we take no responsibility for content inaccuracies&quot;.'' The form below should just be fine to cover all bases
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|Aircraft
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#acc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align:left; background:#acc;&quot;|Variant
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|In service
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Notes
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Trainer (aircraft)|Trainer Aircraft]]
|-
|[[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18]]
|{{USA}}
|advanced trainer
| [[F/A-18#Variants|F/A-18B]]
| 16
|Can also perform a combat role
|}
- [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 05:43, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
:I can't recall seeing any reliable sources which describe the B variant as an &quot;advanced trainer&quot; - this term is usually applied to specialised training aircraft such as the [[BAE Systems Hawk]]. Suggesting that the RAAF's website isn't a reliable source of information on how the RAAF classifies and operates its aircraft because of the presence of boilerplate legal text is stretching things rather a lot... ''The Military Balance'' classifies Australia's F/A-18Bs as being &quot;fighter/ground attack&quot; aircraft, like the A variants. I'd place very little value on the Flight International ''World Air Forces'' entry for Australia - it contains several obvious, and significant, errors which indicate that it wasn't fact-checked properly (eg, a totally wrong claim that a further 12 F/A-18Fs are on order and the wrong number of F-35s and P-8 orders) [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 06:00, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
::Indeed the ''World Air Forces'' report has been caught out on several occasions here. Despite what [[User:FOX 52]] says the majority of reliable ''Australian'' sources describe the F/A-18Bs as &quot;multirole&quot;, &quot;combat&quot; or &quot;fighter/ground attack&quot;. I'm not remotely interested in generic US sources which only talk about US Navy or Marine Corps use of this variant as they are not at all relevant to the Australian context. And I only mentioned the Wikipedia articles because they provide examples of similar tables. I'm not going to bother posting the same links as that would be pointless, however from this needlessly long discussion we can see that the ''RAAF'', the ''Australian National Audit Office'' and the ''Military Balance'' all describe the Bs as combat aircraft or some variation of that, and that there are no reliable sources calling them an &quot;advanced training&quot; aircraft so calling them the is probably [[WP:OR]]. As such what are your thoughts on something like this?
::'''Proposed entry # 2'''
::{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|Aircraft
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#acc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align:left; background:#acc;&quot;|Variant
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|In service
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Notes
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Military aircraft#Combat aircraft|Combat Aircraft]]
|-
|[[F/A-18]]
|{{USA}}
|multirole
| [[F/A-18#Variants|F/A-18A]]&lt;hr&gt;[[F/A-18#Variants|F/A-18B]]
| 55&lt;ref name=&quot; World Air Forces 2015 pg. 11&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last = |first = |url= http://forms.flightglobal.com/WorldAirForces2015?product=PREM&amp;mode=DOWNLOAD&amp;DMDcode=FGWC4&amp;fcid=%7B05ceef25-b72e-4bea-9a83-a7ab7d02e55a%7D_FC078_PREM_201412&amp;fcfileext=pdf |title = World Air Forces 2015 pg. 11|work= |publisher= Flightglobal Insight |year= 2015 |doi = |accessdate= 26 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;hr&gt;16&lt;ref name=&quot; World Air Forces 2015 pg. 11&quot;/&gt;
|&lt;hr&gt;Used for operational conversion
|}
{{reflist}}
::Alternatively we can simply return the entry to what it was before it was changed without discussion on 28 December 2014 by [[User:FOX 52]] here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;diff=639908239&amp;oldid=639908144] to this version [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;oldid=639743555#Aircraft] which lists both the As and Bs together under the heading &quot;Fighter Aircraft&quot; and describes them as &quot;Fighter/Attack&quot;. If there is no consensus for either [[User:FOX 52]]'s version - and so far it seems to only have the support one person (FOX 52) or one of my proposals then we are left with no alternative than to revert it back to that. The alternative is a change to amend the current table to a more generic variation of the original Dec 14 table, like this:
::'''Proposed entry # 3'''
::{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|Aircraft
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#acc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align:left; background:#acc;&quot;|Variant
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|In service
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Notes
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Military aircraft#Combat aircraft|Combat Aircraft]]
|-
|[[F/A-18]]
|{{USA}}
|fighter/attack
| A/B
| 71
|
|}
:: [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:12, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
:::Flight International not a reliable source? {{U|Nick-D}} I guess you missed the asterisk next to the number(s) on order, it means they are pending purchase approval or contract signature (In other words they are potential). Like a potential order of a 100 F-35’s, and echoed by [http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/defence/kevin-rudd-signs-off-on-purchase-of-14-f-35-joint-strike-fighters/story-e6frg8yo-1225803790418 The Australian] ''“bringing the total number of F-35's to around 100”''. And I guess will turn a blind eye to your own findings ''“the Bs are fully combat capable...&lt;u&gt;however, they are primarily used for pilot conversion training”&lt;/u&gt;''.  I think you guys are missing the point of Primary Role. - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 16:54, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
:::* My Hornet books describe the 2-seat B-model as a trainer version, while the later 2-seat D-model is used for combat for recon and forward air control mainly by USMC. I like the idea of listing them by aircraft type, such as Fighters/Attack aircraft in one group and Trainer aircraft in another. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 17:30, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
::::: Gday - the main issue I see is that this is US Navy and US Marine Corps specific and ignores how they are considered in Australian service. There are numerous reliable sources (government reports, books, official websites, the military balance etc) which treat both the As and Bs in ''Australian'' service as part of its air combat capability, either describing them both as &quot;fighter/attack&quot; aircraft, &quot;multi-role&quot;, &quot;combat aircraft&quot;, &quot;tactical fighters&quot; etc. For instance (from a quick Google Book search):
::::::* The Defence Portfolio Budget Statements 2014-15, p. 42: which lists the A/Bs together in terms of Air Force deliverable flying hours [http://www.defence.gov.au/budget/14-15/2014-2015_Defence_PBS_03_Defence.pdf].
::::::* The Australian National Audit Office report here - [http://www.anao.gov.au/Publications/Audit-Reports/2012-2013/F18/Audit-brochure] which states: &quot;'''This audit examines the upgrade and sustainment of the Royal Australian Air Force’s (RAAF’s) fleet of 71 F/A-18A/B Hornet aircraft and the sustainment of 24 F/A-18F Super Hornet aircraft. &lt;u&gt;These aircraft form the basis of the RAAF’s air combat&lt;/u&gt; and airborne ground-attack capability.''&quot;; and
::::::* The Royal Australian Air Force site here [http://www.airforce.gov.au/Technology/Aircraft/Hornet/?RAAF-9SSttIt/E93/3lV4LgVxgxc0y4P09YW2] which states: &quot;''Based at RAAF Base Williamtown and RAAF Base Tindal, the 71 F/A-18A/B Hornets are an integral part of Australia’s air combat capability.''&quot;
::::::* ''Australia Air Force Handbook: Strategic Information and Weapons Systems''  2013, p. 87: &quot;A/B Multi-Role Fighters&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=dJydBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA88&amp;dq=Australia+F/A-18B+fighter&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=2lINVY3YKtGA8gWi34HoBw&amp;ved=0CCMQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Australia%20F%2FA-18B%20fighter&amp;f=false]
::::::* ''Military Modernization in an Era of Uncertainty'' by Ashley J. Tellis, Michael Wills 2005, p. 315: &quot;Australia’s core air combat capability today lies in its 71 F/A-18 Hornet multi-role fighters. Though the Hornets are older A/B models...&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=HcnAcsd6vrEC&amp;pg=PA315&amp;dq=F/A-18B+Hornet+Australia&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=mFYNVeGcIszt8gXfkoHADQ&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=F%2FA-18B%20Hornet%20Australia&amp;f=false]
::::::* ''The Armed Forces: Instrument of Peace, Strength, Development and Prosperity'' by Joseph Babatunde Fagoyinbo 2013, p. 173: &quot;The combat aircraft force comprises 19 F-111 bombers and 71 F/A-18 Hornet fighters...&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=qM0uxPH8RasC&amp;pg=PA173&amp;dq=F/A-18B+Hornet+Australia&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=mFYNVeGcIszt8gXfkoHADQ&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=F%2FA-18B%20Hornet%20Australia&amp;f=false]
::::::* ''The Information Revolution in Military Affairs in Asia'' by Emily Goldman 2004, p. 33: &quot;The RAAF's 71 F/A-18 Hornet tactical fighters were gradually losing parity with the best regional air forces.&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=mePJAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA33&amp;dq=F/A-18B+Hornet+Australia&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=mFYNVeGcIszt8gXfkoHADQ&amp;ved=0CE4Q6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=F%2FA-18B%20Hornet%20Australia&amp;f=false]
::::::* ''Defense &amp; Foreign Affairs Handbook'' by Gregory R. Copley 1999, p. 98: &quot;16 McDonnell Douglas AF/F-18B Homet tactical fighters...&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=p-Y-AQAAIAAJ&amp;q=Australia+18B+Hornet&amp;dq=Australia+18B+Hornet&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=118NVc-gB8SD8gWe3IL4Cw&amp;ved=0CB4Q6AEwATgK]
::::::* ''Strategic Asia 2010-11: Asia's Rising Power and America's Continued Purpose'' by Ashley J. Tellis, ‎Andrew Marble, ‎Travis Tanner 2010, pp. 100-101: &quot;The Royal Australian Air Force (RAAF) is in the process of replacing its aging F-111 and F/A-18A/B fighters...&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=JbkCAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA331&amp;dq=Australian+air+combat+capability&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NskNVaHCBsSB8QWLg4CwBQ&amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Australian%20air%20combat%20capability&amp;f=false]
::::::* ''Aircraft &amp; Aerospace Asia-Pacific'' by Peter Isaacson Publications 2000, p. 52: &quot;multi-role F/A18A/B Hornets&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=eGApAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=Australia+air+combat+capability+B+Hornet&amp;dq=Australia+air+combat+capability+B+Hornet&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=X8wNVf3NOYjj8AWk1YHAAw&amp;ved=0CE8Q6AEwCQ]
::::::* ''The Australian Defence Force: Its Structure and Capabilities'' By Australian Government Publishing Service 1984, p. 54: &quot;75 F/A-18 Hornet multi-role fighter aircraft&quot; [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=qg4JAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=Australia+air+combat+capability+B+Hornet&amp;dq=Australia+air+combat+capability+B+Hornet&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=780NVf-xLoeF8QWrg4GQAw&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAzgo] [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 21:23, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
:::::* You should be more careful with what what you assume.  My first sentence was based on all Hornet users covered in my books, not simply US ones.  I mentioned the D-model only as an example of different usage. -[[User:Fnlayson|Fnlayson]] ([[User talk:Fnlayson|talk]]) 01:41, 23 March 2015 (UTC)

::::::: I suppose another point is that the Australian Hornets were pretty much upgraded to C/D models before the last one was even delivered, with upgrade work in 1990-91. This point is made in Wilson (1994) ''Military Aircraft of Australia'' p. 146-147, which is well before the latest updates in mid 2000s. This muddies the waters a bit when using generic reference material to what a B model is. Specific Australian references are really required to determine this question and they all call them &quot;combat aircraft&quot; of some description. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 22:26, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
::::::::Three more sources:
::::::::*The [[Australian Strategic Policy Institute]]'s ''Australian Defence Almanac'' also groups the F/A-18As and Bs together [https://www.aspi.org.au/publications/australian-defence-almanac-2011-2012] (the only difference it notes is that the B variant's has a crew of two; a pilot and an instructor)
::::::::*ASPI's 2010 summary of the RAAF does the same [https://www.aspi.org.au/publications/raaf-capability-review-2010-by-andrew-davies/Policy_Analysis63_RAAF_capability_review_2010.pdf]
::::::::*[[David Horner]] (Australia's leading military historian) also groups the A and B variants together in his book ''Making the Australian Defence Force'', and notes that while 2 OCU is primarily a training unit &quot;in particular circumstances it could carry out operational tasks&quot; (page 210)
::::::::The only source which has been advanced which treats the aircraft separately appears to be Flight Global publications, which are clearly mistaken about the RAAF's force structure so I think that this is getting conclusive. I think that we should go with option 2 above. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 22:40, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
:::::::::G'day, I'd give my support to treating them together, with a note or something similar (so Proposal # 2). Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 22:58, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
::Well you've showed serveral reports, books, official websites that lump together the F/A-18A/B and referred to it as a single aircraft. Yet your skirting the issue on what predominate role the &quot;B&quot; model has in the RAAF. I find it interesting that the [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1983/1983%20-%201400.html  Canadian Armed Forces review] obtained ''“24 CF-18B trainers for nine squadrons”'' [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1994/1994%20-%202034.html Spain’s Air force review] has 12 EF-18B for training. Canada, Spain and Australia have all followed the same acquisition model, a large number of A variants, &amp; small number of B variants, which makes sense for the combat vs training ratio. Yet somehow Australia should be excluded? My last concern to the Aussie (editors) can you be objective about this, being a Australian as there can be [[Wikipedia:Conflict of interest|Conflict of interest]] (no implications, just a note). - And with that said it should be left that way it is - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 23:13, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
:::How the Canadian and Spanish air forces classify their B variant Hornets is of no relevance whatsoever to this article on the Australian Air Force. Your &quot;last concern&quot; is, to put things plainly, moronically stupid and offensive: we're referring to high-quality sources here, not some kind of nationalistic viewpoint. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 23:33, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
::::In situations where there is a dispute about content etc, editing decisions are made by consensus, not whether or not someone is one nationality or another. So far it doesn't appear that there is consensus to support your (FOX 52) edit. If consensus develops to support it, then I've no doubt that Nick, AC and everyone else here (as experienced editors) will abide by that consensus. Casting aspersions about objectivity is not the way to establish that consensus, nor does it promote a collaborative editing environment. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 23:53, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
:::{{U|Nick-D}} as an administrator you of people should know name calling like &quot;moronically stupid&quot; dose not support [[Wikipedia:Civility|civility]]. I spoke in general terms, for those to consider objectivity. Words like &quot;high-quality&quot; sources which all are Australian defense notes. Yet I introduce Flight International (A british news source and somehow it's not worthy [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 00:12, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
::::And claiming that people are being something other than objective and editing with a conflict of interest is polite? [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 00:22, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
::::::No, I ask those to consider their objectiveness. In no way did I say you '''weren't being objective''', but just the same sad to you had to resort to name calling. - [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 00:44, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
:::::::: One of the longest and silliest arguments I,ve seen on this site. The dual seat classic Hornets are obviously classified as combat aircraft by RAAF and that seems to be well backed up by numerous documents listed above. No comparison between it and a Hawk which is obviously a trainer. Putting them as training aircraft is just ignorant. I,d change it myself but it's a bit beyond my coding ability. [[User:Mongoose Army|Mongoose Army]] ([[User talk:Mongoose Army|talk]]) 04:35, 22 March 2015 (UTC)

=== F/A-18Bs listed under the &quot;combat aircraft&quot; or &quot;training aircraft&quot; section ===

My take on the discussion to this point:
# Sources which refer to B models as “trainers” primarily describe their previous use by the US Navy or Marine Corps (and a few Spanish and Canadian - mostly taken out of context though) and are not relevant to Australian use, or have been proven to be inaccurate (i.e. World Air Forces Report 2015);
# Sources which refer to the Bs in Australian service as “trainers” describe their primary peace-time use only, which neglects their stated operational role (combat) and the obviously fact that all military aircraft are primarily used for training in peace-time;
#In Australian service both have received the same upgrades and a fully combat capable aircraft (being upgraded first to C/D standard and then HUG);
# In the RAAF both As and Bs are used by the operational squadrons (No. 3, 75 and 77) and by the training unit (No. 2 OCU) and the Bs are considered part of its overall “air combat capability”;
# Key Royal Australian Air Force, Australian National Audit Office, and Department of Defence sources, as well as the IIS Military Balance refer to the B models in ''Australian service'' as “multirole fighters”, “combat aircraft” or something similar;
# Numerous other reliable sources including books, reports, authors etc either refer to the As and Bs ''in Australian service'' together as part of its “air combat capability” or as being “combat aircraft”, “multi-role fighters” or “fighter/attack aircraft”;
# Splitting the As and Bs into two separate entries is inconsistent with how they are presented in other articles on Wikipedia; and
# There is currently no consensus for the previous move of the Bs from the &quot;Combat Aircraft&quot; section to the &quot;Training Aircraft&quot; section as occurred without discussion by [[User:FOX 52]] here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Royal_Australian_Air_Force&amp;diff=639908239&amp;oldid=639908144].
# As such I have moved them back to the &quot;Combat Aircraft&quot; section. If a consensus develops to move it a later date then of cse that can occur. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 06:39, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
::* All Spanish and Canadian &quot;B&quot; variants are trainers - and you state ''as “trainers” describe their primary peace-time use'' really? - World Air Forces Report 2015 is very accurate, asterisks is something you have to look up, but since that source goes against your POV it must be wrong. - Thanks for compromising [[User:FOX 52|FOX 52]] ([[User talk:FOX 52|talk]]) 07:12, 22 March 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>6ub1soubmfxpgn1lvkaod1jzhu9wspm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
