<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Rorke's Drift</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2657593</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746670798</id>
      <parentid>732898859</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T20:35:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12483">{{WPMILHIST|class=B
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=y
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=y
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|African=yes
|British=yes}}
{{WikiProject South Africa |class=B |importance=High }}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2011-01-22|oldid1=409189609}}
{{archive box|[[/Archive 1|Archive 1]][[/Archive 2|Archive 2]]}}

== Euphemisms ==

Why are the British atrocites described euphemistically?[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 19:22, 9 November 2011 (UTC)
:Don't know. Have restored original and appropriate description.[[User:Tttom|Tttom1]] ([[User talk:Tttom|talk]]) 04:06, 10 November 2011 (UTC)

== Rate of fire per rifle/man. ==

There were 20,000 rounds stored at Rorkes Drift. 19,100 were expended. Allow 140 rifles as the defenders amount of firepower available. The battle lasted 11.5 hours. 136 rounds per rifle fired.
its an average of 11.8 rounds per rifle per hour. About one shot every 4 minutes. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 03:20, 24 May 2012 (UTC)

Bad mathematics.
Or better good mathemactics but bad tactical analysis.

- not every soldier fired constantly.
- the hospitalizied soldiers entered late in the battle
- the troops where shifted from one sector to another
- some troops were used as reserve
- massive &quot;platoon volleys&quot; were only used to counter breakthroughs

Well its a pity but I don't have a staged description of the battle. --[[Special:Contributions/88.153.184.211|88.153.184.211]] ([[User talk:88.153.184.211|talk]]) 23:07, 27 May 2012 (UTC)

I am aware of the &quot;phases&quot; of the battle. But I have just given an average ammo expenditure per man, based on some broad figures.

Thats just the average based on garrison strength, ammo expenditure and the duration of the attack. Points 2-4 seem irrelevant to the figures. There were only a half dozen in the hospital, and they were engaged for the majority of the engagement, esp the fight for the hospital. 

The movement of troops doesnt bear on ammo consumption. The whole perimeter was under sustained assault.

Only a dozen occupied a final redoubt position I believe. But they fought in the meantime. Having a dozen troops sitting and drinking tea while waiting for the final defence is improbable.

Volley fire would only have been in the first minutes of the engagement. Once the Zulu units closed with the walls, it was a case of individual fire for the remainder of the engagement. There was widescale use of the Martini-Henry socket bayonet by the defenders, the fearsome 22&quot; &quot;lunger&quot;, especially in combat over the mealie bag defences. This would have slowed individual firing by the perimeter defenders. Much of the combat was close quarter assingai .v. bayonet. Accounts after the battle described many of the troops bayonets as being &quot;Twisted like corkscrews&quot; from extreme use. ( The Washing Of The Spears). A shot every 2-4 minutes is therefore plausable I would argue. No wonder so many RD vets displayed symptoms of what we would now recognise as PTSD, especially in their final years.  Nice to see a response. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 01:06, 28 May 2012 (UTC)

== Zulu name for Rorke's Drift ==

Donald Morris, in his book The Washing of the Spears states that the Zulu name is kwaJumu (not kwaJim)[[User:Dobryen|Dobryen]] ([[User talk:Dobryen|talk]]) 07:10, 16 October 2012 (UTC)
:You're right, thanks. 'kwaJimu', I believe, p. 168, have changed and referenced it. It was that way some time ago.[[User:Tttom|Tttom1]] ([[User talk:Tttom|talk]]) 01:40, 10 October 2013 (UTC)

==Reformatted images== 

I discovered in doing this that the campaign box caused problems to the layout of text and images adjacent to it, causing the text to overwrite the image. I tried half a dozen arrangements of the picture box and concluded that the practical solution was to move the campaign box above to battle box.  

Before changing, permanently, take a look at the effect. NOTE: if you are viewing on vertical rather than horizontal screen you will not see the problem that is caused on wide/shallow format.  
Don't change, unless it is a serious breach  of protocol, in which circumstance you will need to discover a better solution. 

[[User:Amandajm|Amandajm]] ([[User talk:Amandajm|talk]]) 01:28, 10 October 2013 (UTC)

== Late of? ==

Quote:  ''Later that evening a portion of the No. 2 Column under Brevet Colonel Anthony Durnford, late of the Royal Engineers''

I don't get the meaning of &quot;late of&quot; in this context.  Thanks.  [[User:Maikel|Maikel]] ([[User talk:Maikel|talk]]) 13:26, 30 December 2013 (UTC)

== Infobox parameters ==

*The NNC foot company can not be listed under &quot;Strength&quot; or &quot;Casualties&quot;, as it did not engage in the Battle of Rorke's Drift.
*the NNH cavalry fleeing (esp. only after after a brief skirmish) can not be listed as &quot;Casualties&quot;. While they ''can'' be listed under &quot;Strength&quot;, their limited participation in the battle has to be made clear.
The remaining changes are standard ordering/cosmetics for this infobox. Its not necessary to explain this was a &quot;tactical&quot; victory unless there is a different strategic impact of said battle. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 03:22, 2 February 2014 (UTC)

:I see you're making a good faith edit and  not vandalizing and welcome your interest and work. NNC is stated by reliable sources to be part of the garrison and must included in strength section - see main article. Missing are also casualties and do not necessarily get broken down in an info box as to  why they are missing e.g.: desertion at some point, rout, various separations from unit, capture - plenty of armies lose strength at the start of a battle without engaging, or have strengths that play no part and when it is a notable proportion, as it is here, its included in the overall strength &amp; often, but not necessarily, mentioned. Participation of the NNC is clear in the body of the article where these are supposed to be made clear. Removing them from the info box is misleading as to the facts. Before reverting (3RR) you should have brought this up in talk, those are pertinent ref'd statements and that are further explained in the body of the article. The info box is not an opportunity to rewrite the article before you discuss a major change here in talk.[[User:Tttom|Tttom1]] ([[User talk:Tttom|talk]]) 05:13, 2 February 2014 (UTC)
::..does this place get vandalized frequently?
::&quot;Misleading&quot;? on the contrary: the current state of affairs is misleading:
::*The NNC company may be &quot;part of the garrison&quot;, but its not part of ''the battle''. It is &lt;u&gt;highly misleading&lt;/u&gt; to have them listed in the military conflict infobox, which [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_military_conflict#Parameters lists only combatants] ('parties participating in the conflict'). It gives the inescapable impression that there were not 150 men, but ''450 men'' engaged in defending the outpost against the Zulus (or more, if we count the NHH entry that's without the necessary note). Imo this is an entirely unacceptable state of affairs.
::*Fleeing men are not usually viewed as &quot;casualties&quot; ([http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/casualty casualty], 'a person killed or injured in a war or accident'). More importantly, the {{template|Infobox military conflict}} template does not use the parameter to list men who have fled the battle. As you can [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_military_conflict#Parameters see], the thing is for 'casualties suffered, including dead, wounded, missing, captured, and civilian deaths'. And this is followed throughout Wikipedia, hence rendering the listing of the NHH cavalry as &quot;casualties&quot; misleading. It gives the impression they were killed by the Zulus.
::*Finally, while its necessary to list the NNH under &quot;strength&quot;, due to their having participated in the battle, the limited extent of said participation must be made clear with a brief note.
::It is necessary to make clear the fact that the battle essentially took place between 150 men and 4,000 men. That's the only thing that makes this skirmish relevant. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:42, 2 February 2014 (UTC)

::::This article has been vandalized and subject to edit warring in the past and our last few edits of this constitute a violation of the [[Wikipedia:Edit warring|3RR]] rule. The garrison is part of 'the conflict' and that means, and in the link, more than a narrow opinion view of the battle from when the British start firing, as explained before. It is not misleading in the info box as their participation is clearly explained and ref'd in the body of the article. If you wish to say  'fled' that should be short and clear as required. The guidline says 'casualties suffered including' not 'casualties suffered limited to' and the guideline includes includes general non-combatant civilian deaths (including those who do not fight and were not part of the opposing forces). If something is too vague or confusing or disputed, the casualties section is optional according to the guidline and can be left blank so that the entire story will be in the article itself - this is policy for disputed results - a far more crucial info box fact that is often disputed by editors - it doesn't have to be in the info box if there is no consensus and I don't see a consensus here. The info box should briefly summarize what is in the article - not just the part that shows the gallant stand by the remainder of the garrison once part of it flees. I believe your definition of info box 'casualties and losses' would ignore 'missing' and 'captured' as well (as per the OED definition) and it should not. Would it help to change that section title to 'losses'? There is no misleading as the information which clarifies this is appropriately in the body of the article. Statements in the info box can be ref'd, but need not be, if the fact is clarified in the body which in this case it is.[[User:Tttom|Tttom1]] ([[User talk:Tttom|talk]]) 15:52, 4 February 2014 (UTC)

== Inappropriate link? ==

Surgeon James Henry Reynolds; Army Medical Department

The link in &quot;Army Medical Department&quot; above links to an article about the US Army. This is inappropriate for an article about a British Army engagement. [[Special:Contributions/86.24.15.85|86.24.15.85]] ([[User talk:86.24.15.85|talk]]) 21:59, 3 August 2016 (UTC)
:Fixed, and thank you for raising it. [[User:YSSYguy|YSSYguy]] ([[User talk:YSSYguy|talk]]) 00:15, 4 August 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Battle of Rorke's Drift]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=746670790 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20120317184009/http://www.talana.co.za/html/map.html to http://www.talana.co.za/html/map.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20120323111043/http://www.rrw.org.uk/museums/brecon/faq.htm to http://www.rrw.org.uk/museums/brecon/faq.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 20:35, 28 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>py71dgux3rxfmrkw3ae4p1nllujws10</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
