<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>8585271</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749452110</id>
      <parentid>725381983</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T12:14:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Crisco 1492</username>
        <id>356335</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>info</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6962">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=B
&lt;!-- B-Class 5-criteria checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|military-work-group=yes
|military-priority=High
|peerage-work-group=yes
|peerage-priority=High
|listas=Jellicoe, John Jellicoe, 1st Earl
}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=B|B1=yes|B2=yes|B3=yes|B4=yes|B5=yes
|portal1-name=Royal Navy|portal1-link=Selected biography/3
|portal2-name=Battleships|portal2-link=Selected biography/3
|Maritime=yes|British=yes|Biography=yes|WWI=yes|OMT=4}}
{{WikiProject New Zealand|class=B|importance=Mid|politics=yes|politics-importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class=B|importance=High}}
}}

==Pictures==
*Are four, partly almost equal pictures of him really necessary? &lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgreen&quot;&gt;~~ [[User:Phoe|&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgreen&quot;&gt;Phoe&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Phoe|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:sans-serif;color:darkgreen&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 21:04, 15 February 2007 (UTC) ~~ &lt;/span&gt;

== Reference taken out of context ==

In the first paragraph of the section &quot;World War 1&quot; a passing reference is made to the effect that Winston Churchill referred to Jellicoe as 'the only man on either side who could lose the war in an afternoon'. This is apparently taken out of context from writings by Winston Churchill. In Churchill's series &quot;The World Crisis 1911~1918&quot; the complete text from which this was originally taken (Volume II, page 1015 of the two volume complete edition), in which Churchill described the difference in effect on the war between the Germans winning the battle of Jutland (i.e., total blockade of the British Isles, interdiction of supplies and re-inforcements moving to France from England for the Allies, America unable to join the war effort in the face of an overwhelming enemy navy, and the eventual loss of the war for England, France, Italy and Russia) and the British navy winning the battle of Jutland (basically a continuance of total sea supremacy that they already maintained), and that a mistake made by Jellicoe during a conflict of this nature could result in the destruction of the British navy, with the aforementioned results. This reference was only meant to imply the awesome responsiblity of Sir John Jellico's position, and the reason he was conservative in his actions at Jutland as he knew he had far more to lose in pursuing the engagement beyond what he thought was safe for the conservation of the British battleship superiority. 
      
It seemed to me an unfair reflection on both Winston Churchill and Sir John Jellicoe, who's promotion had been planned for some time, and was only promoted ahead of time due to the outbreak of war, as Admiral Callaghan was due to retire as Commander-in-Cheif by December 1914 anyway, and it was never the Admiralty's intention to have the old Admiral command the fleet at war anyway.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.252.64.194|66.252.64.194]] ([[User talk:66.252.64.194|talk]]) 17:07, 26 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Explanation added.[[User:Paulturtle|Paulturtle]] ([[User talk:Paulturtle|talk]]) 13:09, 28 September 2011 (UTC)

:You made an amendment to the opening paragraph[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=John_Jellicoe%2C_1st_Earl_Jellicoe&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=452868640&amp;oldid=447148881], so that it said:
::His handling of the fleet at that battle remains controversial: he made no serious mistakes and the German High Seas Fleet retreated to port - at a time when defeat when would have been catastrophic for Britain - but at the time the public were disappointed that he had lost more ships (mainly due to design faults on British battlecruisers) and had not won a victory as crushing as Trafalgar. 
:I have changed &quot;design faults&quot; to &quot;dangerous ammunition-handling procedures&quot;.[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=John_Jellicoe,_1st_Earl_Jellicoe&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=452868640]  The ammunition handling procedures on the battlecruisers were dangerous given the propellant in use and the fact that the armour of the hooded barbettes was not impenetrable.  That people chose not to use the safety measures available, can hardly be called a design fault.--[[User:Toddy1|Toddy1]] ([[User talk:Toddy1|talk]]) 16:44, 28 September 2011 (UTC)

Well it's arguably a design fault that the guns could not be loaded quickly enough, with the result that safety guidelines were flouted for speedy and efficient loading in battle, but it's not really worth arguing about. To be honest I'm not sure Jutland is all that &quot;controversial&quot; any more - when I first started reading about WW1 thirty years ago it was already largely agreed that Beatty was a bit vainglorious and Jellicoe won a strategic victory (&quot;The German Fleet has assaulted its jailer - but it is still in Jail&quot; as the headline went at the time). It would be truer to say that it was controversial at the time and in the 1930s when proponents of Beatty and Jellicoe engaged in controversy in print.[[User:Paulturtle|Paulturtle]] ([[User talk:Paulturtle|talk]]) 11:17, 29 September 2011 (UTC)

== Ammunition ==

[[User:AT Kunene|AT Kunene]] ([[User talk:AT Kunene|talk]]) 15:36, 14 November 2011 (UTC)A veteran from the &quot;New Zealand&quot; at Jutland, told me in the 1960s, that after the poor British Battlecruiser gunnery at the Falklands, the only way to be sure of eventually hitting the enemy was to fire as frequently as possible. To do this the ammunition was stacked inside the turrets and passage ways to keep up the rate of fire.

In other actions, such as the Dogger Bank, where the battlecruiser ammunition supply was carefully controlled the, Battlecruisers seem to have successfully stood up the hits by German heavy shells.

References.

Didn't Jellicoe write his own account of the battle as &quot;The Grand Fleet&quot; or some such title?[[User:AT Kunene|AT Kunene]] ([[User talk:AT Kunene|talk]]) 15:36, 14 November 2011 (UTC)
:Mention of Jellicoe's book &quot;The Crisis of the Naval War&quot; now included under &quot;further reading&quot;. [[User:Dormskirk|Dormskirk]] ([[User talk:Dormskirk|talk]]) 15:22, 1 December 2012 (UTC)

== [[:File:John Jellicoe, Admiral of the Fleet.jpg]] to appear as POTD soon ==
Hello! This is a note to let the editors of this article know that [[:File:John Jellicoe, Admiral of the Fleet.jpg]] will be appearing as [[Wikipedia:picture of the day|picture of the day]] on December 5, 2016. You can view and edit the POTD blurb at [[Template:POTD/2016-12-05]]. If this article needs any attention or maintenance, it would be preferable if that could be done before its appearance on the [[Main Page]].&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;[[User:Crisco 1492|Chris Woodrich]] ([[User talk:Crisco 1492|talk]]) 12:14, 14 November 2016 (UTC)
{{POTD/2016-12-05}}</text>
      <sha1>a05bvtv293hmyid46azghwdehuufh23</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
