<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Shenyang J-11</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5908604</id>
    <revision>
      <id>556643471</id>
      <parentid>556609716</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-24T21:37:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OuroborosCobra</username>
        <id>1538022</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* More advanced than their Russian Counterparts? */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19983">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=start
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = y
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = y
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = y
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = y
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = y
|Aircraft-project=yes}}
{{WikiProject China|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=start|Aviation=y|China=y
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = y
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = y
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = y
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = y
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = y
}}
}}

== Merge with Su-27 article? ==
Should we merge this article with Su-27?  Technically the J-11 is a Chinese-assembled Su-27SK from Russian-provided &quot;kits&quot;, I don't think there's enough variation to really justify a completely seperate article.  But if the PRC ever produce domestic upgrades (J-11B/C) with different technology than the Russians, then that'd be a different story. --
[[User:Adeptitus|Adeptitus]] 17:55, 10 July 2006 (UTC)

:'''NO''' Because I believe that the PRC has allready upgraded it with different technology than the Russians [[User:TheftByEating|TheftByEating]] 23:35, 29 July 2006 (UTC)

:NO, I agree with TheftByEating. Although still not known that it has already been upgraded yet and it is a licence production of Su-27. It is produced by a chinese company. However, it should be added on the list of variant of Su-27.(GMT)

'''Merge Cancelled''' - see [[Su-27]] discussion for rationale

==Update==
I've completely updated the article, re-wrote some parts, moved some sections around, and added in an additional source as well. I will continue to revamp the article to cleanup grammar and add in additional information as I come across it -- [[User:ThePointblank|ThePointblank]] 22:17, 16 January 2007 (UTC)

:Thanks for doing so.  But please be careful: you overwrote the conversion of several inline links to footnotes.  [[User:Karl Dickman|Karl&amp;nbsp;Dickman]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Karl Dickman|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 22:37, 16 January 2007 (UTC)

: Thanks for correcting them. -- [[User:ThePointblank|ThePointblank]] 22:48, 16 January 2007 (UTC)

==Correct Picture?==
I think an actual picture of a J-11 should eventually be found and used for this article, I have found a picture of the J-11B that could be used safely from the 47th issue of Joint Forces Quarterly for the Chairman of the Joint Chief of the Staff by national Defense University (http://www.ndu.edu/inss/Press/jfq_pages/i47.htm). [[User:Semi-Lobster|Semi-Lobster]] ([[User talk:Semi-Lobster|talk]]) 12:31, 27 February 2008 (UTC)

== J-11B Images? ==

I'm curious to see the difference between the J-11B and its original Su-27 base.  The Indians have the MKI version of the Su-27, complete with canards, so I'm curious about what the J-11B looks like and how it compares with the MKI.  ([[User:Psychoneko|Psychoneko]] ([[User talk:Psychoneko|talk]]) 06:22, 27 November 2008 (UTC))

== J-11 Picture ==

[[User:Midgetman433|Midgetman43]] has repeatedly attempted to use a picture of a [[Sukhoi Su-27|Sukhi Su-27UBK]] fighter-trainer in this article, an article for the Shenyang J-11. I disagree with him on this matter as I believe that a Wikipedia page should have standards, and one of those standards it, at the very least to post the correct aircraft in the info box and not just post whatever somebody thinks is convenient. An example of this is that it would be utterly ridiculous to post a picture of a [[T-38 Talon]] right in the info box on the article for the [[Northrop F-5]] even though both aircraft nearly have the exact same airframe and latter is based on the former. While as we all know the J-11 is based on the Su-27 airframe, it is an indigenised licensed produced variant. The main difference between the two is the equipment onboard and the country of origin. Moreover the picture in question is of an Su-27UBK. The Su-27UBK is SOLELY a tandem seat fighter-trainer aircraft, therefore it cannot even be classified as anything similar in role to the single engine J-11 fighter or to the similar tandem-seat [[Sukhoi Su-30MKK]] strike fighter aircraft. This is why I oppose the use of of File:Chinese Su-27.JPG for this article. While I may be willing to concede to a picture of a single seat Su-27SK, the use of a picture of an Su-27UBK trainer for an article on the J-11 fighter is out of the question in my opinion. [[User:Semi-Lobster|Semi-Lobster]] ([[User talk:Semi-Lobster|talk]]) 06:43, 8 November 2009 (UTC)

its not based on the su-27 it its a licensed copy. the airframe is exactly the same, and there is no way to tell a difference between them except for the avionics and the radar, which some people also allege that it has been copied. its a lisence production, china cant export it. russia's sukhoui owns the airframe design not china.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Midgetman433|Midgetman433]] ([[User talk:Midgetman433|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Midgetman433|contribs]]) 03:01, 10 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I said RIGHT THERE IN MY PARAGRAPH THAT THE J-11 IS A LICENSED PRODUCTION, I also see no reason why that would be relevant to this topic as we are talking about a picture. The argument that because they share the same airframe that we should use a picture of an Su-27 is invalid because as I have pointed out, the picture in question is an Su-27UBK FIGHTER-TRAINER, there is no J-11 fighter-trainer, the only twin seat J-11 variant currently in development is the J-11BS strike fighter. Because there is no J-11 fighter-trainer variant we should not use a picture of an Su-27UBK in the info box. The info box is only for pictures of an example of the actual aircraft. If you wanted to put this picture underneath the info box with a caption stating that the picture is NOT of an J-11 but of a similar BUT NOT THE SAME J-11UBK fighter-trainer then I would be fine with that but such picture has no place in the info box itself. We have multiple precedents that just because an aircraft has more or less the same airframe, differences in roles such as this demonstrate that such pictures should not be used (we don't have a picture of a [[T-38 Talon]] in the [[Northrop F-5]] info box, nor do we have a picture of a [[Mitsubishi T-2]] in the [[Mitsubishi F-1]] info box nor do we have a picture of an [[Sukhoi Su-28]] in the [[Sukhoi Su-25]] info box. [[User:Semi-Lobster|Semi-Lobster]] ([[User talk:Semi-Lobster|talk]]) 05:25, 10 November 2009 (UTC)

Just to wade into the discussion as a third opinion, Wikipedia policy for images in infoboxes is that the image should directly relate to the subject at hand. Therefore, I would support the removal of the image until we have an confirmed image of the subject at hand. [[User:ThePointblank|ThePointblank]] ([[User talk:ThePointblank|talk]]) 01:02, 16 November 2009 (UTC)

it is directly related, it is a lisence production, the only difference is that it was produced in china and it has some different avionics. there is no way to tell a difference between a su-27 and j-11, unless its labeled.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Midgetman433|Midgetman433]] ([[User talk:Midgetman433|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Midgetman433|contribs]]) 17:13, 16 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Or it has the wrong number of seats.  Therefore a simple reference to the main article will suffice, or perhaps just redirect back to the main article with a paragraph on the minor Chinese differences.  [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 22:34, 16 November 2009 (UTC)

::Thats more or less what I'm asking. For the image to be moved out of the infbox and into the article itself with an explanation that the picture is of a PLAAF Su-27UBK fighter-trainer (identified here http://www.sinodefence.com/airforce/fighter/su27.asp ) not of a J-11. [[User:Semi-Lobster|Semi-Lobster]] ([[User talk:Semi-Lobster|talk]]) 17:24, 17 November 2009 (UTC)

So is there any sort of consensus or... what? [[User:Semi-Lobster|Semi-Lobster]] ([[User talk:Semi-Lobster|talk]]) 01:25, 23 November 2009 (UTC)

:Yes, we've reached the conclusion that even China admits that there is no real J-11 and so no need for this article.  For example:

http://www.chinatoday.com/arm/index.htm
&quot;J-11 (Su 27) Fighter&quot;

[[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 02:00, 23 November 2009 (UTC)

::China Today is run by InfoPacific Development Inc. in Canada. Its just a website [[User:Semi-Lobster|Semi-Lobster]] ([[User talk:Semi-Lobster|talk]]) 02:48, 23 November 2009 (UTC)

The People's Daily says it's the same airframe.  (Yes, the People's Daily is entirely staffed by CIA agents, so what?)

http://english.people.com.cn/90002/98666/98775/6803174.html

[[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 03:37, 23 November 2009 (UTC)

:::Listen, you can take your vendetta or whatever to a new discussion section but the scope of this specific topic is the wikipedia policy of the useage of aircraft pictures in info boxes. You can go run off and start your other new section in this talk page on merging this article with the Su-27 so you can lose a merge vote just like what happened last time. If the only thing you have to contribute is something completely off-topic, by all means, post it somewhere else. [[User:Semi-Lobster|Semi-Lobster]] ([[User talk:Semi-Lobster|talk]]) 03:58, 23 November 2009 (UTC)

If the aircraft is diffrent enough to have it's own article, it's necessary to have an image of the example the article references. Near enough isn't good enough Midgetguy. Consensus is that the changes in the J-11 ammount to it being distinguishing enough to be a significant variant. Your opinion is in the minority in this case. ([[Special:Contributions/203.26.122.12|203.26.122.12]] ([[User talk:203.26.122.12|talk]]) 04:59, 16 December 2009 (UTC))(Bobbo9000)

== New article on the J-15 ==

There's a new article on the [[Shenyang J-15]] that editors of this article may be interested in and able to improve. I cleaned up as best I can, but I know exactly nothing about airplanes, so there wasn't much I could do in the way of expansion. [[User:Pais|Pais]] ([[User talk:Pais|talk]]) 15:16, 17 November 2009 (UTC)

==Speculation Section==
The &quot;speculation section&quot; in this article is unencyclopedic, and mentions such wonderful things as &quot;rumors on internet military forums. I will remove it unless anyone has anything to say in its defense. Thanks -[[User:SidewinderX|SidewinderX]] ([[User talk:SidewinderX|talk]]) 16:09, 29 December 2009 (UTC)

== What's the explanation ==

...for the &quot;FWS-10A&quot;? I always thought Taihang was WS-10A?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.149.159.247|68.149.159.247]] ([[User talk:68.149.159.247|talk]]) 01:40, 7 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Technical issues with J-11B==
My addition of a report on the rejection of the 2009 J-11 production lot by the Chinese Air Force was [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Shenyang_J-11&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=362961491&amp;oldid=362948848 reverted] with the explanation that ''Kanwa'' is not a reliable source.  Actually, the source is [[Kyodo News]] which quoted a Kanwa report for part of the information.  I am restoring the bit about the national day parade and ask that the reverting editor explain his rationale for reverting in more detail. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 09:19, 19 May 2010 (UTC)

: As pursuant to the discussion with [[User:Cla68]] on his talk page [[User_talk:Cla68#Shenyang_J-11|here]] the agreement is to remove this information for now until a more credible source reports on the matter because there are images from of the J-11 participating in the PRC national parade. (Another source [http://www.china-defense-mashup.com/?page_id=4393]) [[User:Vedant|Vedant]] ([[User talk:Vedant|talk]]) 13:10, 19 May 2010 (UTC)

== Specifications ==

Someone provide specs or i'm going back to Su-27SK specs.  The currents specs have gone without citations for far too long.
--[[User:Nem1yan|Nem1yan]] ([[User talk:Nem1yan|talk]]) 20:45, 10 September 2010 (UTC)

:Shouldn't we just &quot;main article&quot; link back to the Su page here? [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 18:27, 2 November 2010 (UTC)

== J-11B Split ==

Should the J-11B like the J-15 have a seperate article?
It is a quite deferent warplane from the J-11 or J-11A which are more or less the basic SU-27SK. While the J-11B has evolved into something unique in the Flanker family.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/78.21.214.42|78.21.214.42]] ([[User talk:78.21.214.42|talk]]) 22:01, 1 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Isn't the plan to upgrade the entire fleet because the airframe and the engine is the same? [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 23:21, 1 December 2010 (UTC)

No, the j-11 and j-11a airframes are made of standard metals and the j-11b is made out of composite matrials the j-11 and j-11a engines are a Russian made the al-31 and the j-11b is a Chinese made w-10a engine  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/78.21.214.42|78.21.214.42]] ([[User talk:78.21.214.42|talk]]) 01:22, 2 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Have you read this article? The native engines just ain't useful yet.  [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 04:28, 2 December 2010 (UTC)

This article is outdated read this links:http://enginespareparts.blog.com/2010/04/30/the-united-states-said-the-chinese-f-11b-has-been-installed-ws10a-engine-spare-parts/  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/78.21.214.42|78.21.214.42]] ([[User talk:78.21.214.42|talk]]) 09:08, 2 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:What exactly is a &quot;U.S. global strategic networks 3&quot; please?  [[User:Hcobb|Hcobb]] ([[User talk:Hcobb|talk]]) 18:14, 2 December 2010 (UTC)

::The &quot;ref&quot; is a blog, and a very poorly written on at that. That's not a reliable source, and whatever &quot;U.S. global strategic networks 3&quot; is, I doubt it's much better. - [[User:BilCat|BilCat]] ([[User talk:BilCat|talk]]) 18:25, 2 December 2010 (UTC)

There is also a lack of specifications on the aircraft.  Given the amount of information on it you could only justify an entirely separate article if it was a completely new aircraft, not simply an upgrade. -[[User:Nem1yan|Nem1yan]] ([[User talk:Nem1yan|talk]]) 21:07, 2 December 2010 (UTC)

== Photo please ==

Will somebody please ask the CIA for a copyright free pic?  And if that fails then try WikiLeaks.  Regards [[Special:Contributions/122.148.41.172|122.148.41.172]] ([[User talk:122.148.41.172|talk]]) 14:38, 6 December 2010 (UTC).

== number built ==

On page 45 of the given source found [http://china.usc.edu/App_Images/military%20conflict%202008.pdf here] it says there are 132 in service, but this number includes Su-27SK's from Russia.  Technically the fighters are more or less the same, so while I'm not against listing the number built as 132 I would like some feedback on if anyone else felt otherwise. -[[User:Nem1yan|Nem1yan]] ([[User talk:Nem1yan|talk]]) 02:17, 9 April 2011 (UTC)

:Subtracting the 69 Su-27SK's found on the [[People's Liberation Army Air Force|PLAAF]] that leaves us with 63 J-11's produced. -[[User:Nem1yan|Nem1yan]] ([[User talk:Nem1yan|talk]]) 02:22, 9 April 2011 (UTC)

== Rumours? ==

The source for the Further Improved Variants section says that the aircraft are &quot;rumored&quot; to be in development, not &quot;believed&quot;.  Those words carry completely different connotations and can not be substituted.  There entire statement has questionable reliability, it could be argued that more verification is needed in order to add it. -[[User:Nem1yan|Nem1yan]] ([[User talk:Nem1yan|talk]]) 14:54, 25 April 2011 (UTC)

== Thrust to weight ratio ==

Why is the thrust to weight ratio for the J-11A so low ? Only 0,66 dry thrust even the first SU-27 has a thrust to weight of greater than 1.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/213.118.162.20|213.118.162.20]] ([[User talk:213.118.162.20|talk]]) 00:48, 22 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Dry thrust is thrust without the afterburner. The afterburner greatly enhances the thrust of the engines, sometimes as much as doubling them. The Su-27 has a more than 1 to 1 thrust to weight ratio ''with afterburner'', just at the J-11A does. In fact, their thrust to weight ratios are rather comparable. --[[User:OuroborosCobra|OuroborosCobra]] ([[User talk:OuroborosCobra|talk]]) 00:54, 22 November 2011 (UTC)
==File:Chinese-shenyang-j-11b-fighter-800x600.jpg Nominated for speedy Deletion==
&lt;!--TSTAMP:{{{4}}}--&gt;
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| &lt;!--IMAGES--&gt;
An image used in this article, [[:File:Chinese-shenyang-j-11b-fighter-800x600.jpg|File:Chinese-shenyang-j-11b-fighter-800x600.jpg]], has been nominated for speedy deletion for the following reason: ''All Wikipedia files with unknown copyright status'' 
&lt;!--/IMAGES--&gt;
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; you should have time to contest the deletion (although please review [[WP:CSD|deletion guidelines]] before doing so). The best way to contest this form of deletion is by posting on the image talk page.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to provide a [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]]
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no fair use rationale, then it cannot be uploaded or used.
* If the image has already been deleted you may want to try [[WP:DRV|Deletion Review]]
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[:File:Chinese-shenyang-j-11b-fighter-800x600.jpg|image page (File:Chinese-shenyang-j-11b-fighter-800x600.jpg)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 17:13, 4 March 2012 (UTC)
|}

== More advanced than their Russian Counterparts? ==

Is there a reliable 3rd party source that states that the J-11 and J-15 are more advanced than their Russian counterparts? If not, that sentence should be removed.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:37and7|37and7]] ([[User talk:37and7|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/37and7|contribs]]) 17:19, 24 May 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:That seems to be a fairly recent addition, along with claims about potential sales to Mongolia, comparisons to the F-15SE Silent Eagle, and competition for sales against the Silent Eagle and Su-35. I've removed all of them. In addition to your points, the comparisons to the Silent Eagle and suggestion of Mongolian purchase of either these Chinese aircraft or the Silent Eagle seem unsourced and possibly far-fetched. Mongolia barely has a fixed-wing air force to speak of, and doesn't look to be seeking designs that are still in development, such as the Silent Eagle. --[[User:OuroborosCobra|OuroborosCobra]] ([[User talk:OuroborosCobra|talk]]) 21:37, 24 May 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mnccm1cmjzj29jq1ru0pos4qerfjjc5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
