<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Cave of the Patriarchs massacre</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1600645</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744373942</id>
      <parentid>744329880</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-14T20:06:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wiking</username>
        <id>11248740</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* palestinians killed by IDF */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="55594">{{ARBPIA}}

{{WikiProjectBannerShell|{{WikiProject Palestine|class=C|importance=High}}
{{WP Crime|class=|importance=}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=b| B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; = y
| B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; = y
| B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; = y
| B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; = y
| B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; = y|Middle-Eastern=y}}
{{WikiProject Serial Killer task force|class=|importance=}}
{{WikiProject Terrorism|class=|importance=}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2009-02-25|oldid1=273249922|date2=2011-02-25|oldid2=415897434|date3=2014-02-25|oldid3=596880530}}
{{archives|auto=long|search=yes|bot=MiszaBot I|age=3|units=months}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Cave of the Patriarchs massacre/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== Unnecessary ==

[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Cave_of_the_Patriarchs_massacre&amp;diff=740954590&amp;oldid=740624773 This] addition of material by Nishidani IMHO adds unnecessary detail. It is not customary to add people who are wounded, or how precisely they ended up being wounded. Compare other articles, e.g. about the 9/11 attacks. I can not escape from the thought that this is a POV inspired edit, trying to overly stress the gore of terrorism in this case. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 16:29, 24 September 2016 (UTC)
* I agree; this also violates guidelines of generally not naming people who are not notable. There are further NPOV issues with lumping people killed in violent incidents elsewhere which followed with the victims of the massacre. I reverted recent edit about age of some of the victims as it is not found in source referenced, but Nishidani restored his edit in violation of 1RR. Separately, I would question Al Jazeera article as RS. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 16:19, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::Debresser. Suspicions are not material to an objection. Wiking:none of your objections above are based on policy, and all happen to be wrong. (a) [[WP:NOTABILITY]] nowhere states victims, dead or otherwise, are not to be mentioned. All of the lists of dead in terrorism are given where available, and were it not for the incident remain unnotable. It's about page creation re non notable people.Read it; (b) the massacre had an immediate aftermath and this is always noted; (c) I did not break IR, read the policy and check the edit history; [[Al Jazeera]] is regularly cited on wiki pages, as are [[Haaretz]], [[Ynet]] and other similar newspapers. No serious editor questions it. I might waste more time checking for parallels, such as [[Ben Yehuda Street bombings]] where non-lethal fatalities are noted in later incidents. (d) you complain that 'several as young as 12' is not in the source. Well, 'several' means generally four or more, and 4 children aged 12 were killed. If you wish to write 4, you're welcome to do so.
::So, there is no policy substance to these objections. Judgments are based on policy, not [[WP:IDONTLIKEIT]], which is evidently the case here.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 16:49, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
:::No, I do not object to either ''four'' or ''several'', but that's not in the linked source. Please add another source there. I also do not object to including brief info on the casualties of violent protests that followed, as well as of Hamas bombings claimed to have been carried out in retribution, but I object including those killed and injured in separate incidents in the total tally. That's different from including critically injured who died a short while later without recovering in the number of victims. As far as listing the wounded, please see [[Wikipedia:Biographies of living persons#Privacy of names]]. Thank you. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 17:13, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::I saw it (by the way, an editor who changes his policy objection successively, after the first is confuted, is not doing his job. If the removal was based on erroneous policy, and then you adopt another policy objection, the problem is not policy, but the use of policy to keep the stuff out of the article on any pretext). The policy reads:
::::&lt;blockquote&gt;The names of any immediate, ex, or significant family members or any significant relationship of the subject of a BLP may be part of an article, if reliably sourced, subject to editorial discretion that such information is relevant to a reader's complete understanding of the subject. &lt;/blockquote&gt;
::::The names of the wounded or survivors come from a widow, or from the wounded, speaking directly in an interview with the press, here Al Jazeera, therefore the information was released to the public domain where it is reliably sourced. The accounts of survivors is self-evidently 'relevant to a reader's complete understanding of the subject.'
::::As to your point that 4 or several is not in the source. Well, all you had to do was glance up at the list of the dead, where the dates are given, see that Nabeel Abraham, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cave_of_the_Patriarchs_massacre#cite_note-Abraham-31 What About The Victims?,] Lies of Our Times, May 1994, pp 3-6, provided those details, and either leave it at that, or make a ref name=&quot;Abraham&quot; and adjust accordingly. Editing should be efficient, meaning one reads the page and figures things out, adjusting here and there, not removalist. In any case, I have B'tselem's detailed coverage, name by name, of people killed that day and in the immediate aftermath, and will be adding it. And yes, I'll include Hamas's retaliations, if nobody beats me to the 'gun'.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 18:49, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::I did not know which source had explicit info about victims' ages, hence could not add that ref; it appeared as WP:SYNT at first glance, and certainly is not present in source referenced immediately after the statement. Will wait for you to add it.
:::::As far as their names, the issue is has nothing to do with info being in public domain or with source reliability (bolding is mine):
:::::&lt;blockquote&gt;'''Caution should be applied when identifying individuals who are discussed primarily in terms of a single event.''' When the name of a private individual has not been widely disseminated or has been intentionally concealed, such as in certain court cases or occupations, it is often preferable to omit it, '''especially when doing so does not result in a significant loss of context.''' When deciding whether to include a name, its publication in '''secondary sources other than news media''', such as scholarly journals or the work of recognized experts, should be afforded greater weight than the brief appearance of names in news stories. Consider whether the inclusion of names of living private individuals who are not directly involved in an article's topic adds significant value.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:::::So, I think my (and Debresser's) objection is well grounded and I am not sure what you are referring to as ''changing his policy objection successively''. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 19:14, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::That is your 5th mistake, you are confusing your several arguments with those of Dovid whose objection differed. Debresser made one argument, you are making several others. The fact that 2 object has no weight. What has weight is making a policy based objection, consistent with wiki practice, and getting agreement. Otherwise any Tom, Dick or Harry can show up, and cast a vote arbitrary to swing stuff in or out according to the numbers game.
:::::Debresser objected, on the basis of a suspicion about my ulterior motives, as to the purpose of adding details about the wounded or survivors. That itself was improper. I've never seen him object to the use, in a perfect parallel article to this, of photos of wounded survivors on the [[1929 Hebron massacre]]. I don't either. In fact, I helped put some of the uglier details in. So Dovid can't have it both ways: objecting to an innocuous addition of details about the wounded when they are Palestinian, while keeping mum with an article that deals with the Jewish victims of a similar scale massacre in the same place, Hebron. In my view, one must be consistent here to avoid being an ethnonationalist partisan. 
:::::You quoted one part of the policy, I quoted the other. In both cases however, read properly, the WP:BLP entry does not say one cannot use such names. It says caution and judgment should be used. You say the content lost by erasure is 'insignificant'. Tell that to the survivors, who informed the larger world via a mainstream article of what they suffered. You may think wounded Palestinian are 'insignificant' and need not be mentioned. But the article is incomplete unless we include them, since the documentary record we base the article on mentions them. Finally, you have no answered my points. Address them. [[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 19:51, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::I do not follow what you refer to as 'parallel articles'. No idea why you bring up that the fact that 2 object has no weight, as I have not used this argument. Not sure what relevant points I have not addressed either; your count of my 'mistakes' is also confusing. I feel that I am being very consistent, but once I noticed that you quoted irrelevant part of the policy, I quoted the relevant part explicitly, above. Indeed, as you pointed out, it does not prohibit listing names, but strongly discourages the practice. Please do not infer from my very straight forward objection that I think ''wounded Palestinian are 'insignificant'''. While objecting to listing their names in this article or presenting quotes from a newspaper interview as facts, I have no objections to including information about the number of the wounded, their ages, or seriousness of their wounds, as long as it's properly sourced. Similarly, I have no objections to mentioning casualties of the aftermath clashes, but not in the same section of the article. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 20:23, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::: No, Nishidani, I objected not because of your motives! Don't put words in my mouth that never left it. :)
::::::: I object because those names and especially ages and the details about the wounded are superfluous, and not encyclopedical. I wrote that very clearly. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 19:59, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Well I'm afraid those words did fly past what the Homeric poets called  your ''herkos odontôn,'' (barrier of the teeth). See (b) below 
::::::::&lt;blockquote&gt;(a)It is not customary to add people who are wounded, or how precisely they ended up being wounded. Compare other articles, e.g. about the 9/11 attacks. (b) I can not escape from the thought that this is a POV inspired edit, trying to overly stress the gore of terrorism '''in this case'''&lt;/blockquote&gt;
::::::::(a) is your objection? Then (I) answer my point about the photos of the wounded surviovors with names at the 1929 hebron massacre page. I find nothing objectionable, but logically you must exclude them, if that is your principle. If you don't then it means you allow for Jewish victims of terrorism what you prohibit for Palestinian victims of terrorism. 
::::::::(ii) Your statement that it 'is not customary to add people who are wounded' is flawed. In 2 minutes I found 3 articles on Jewish victims of terrorism which add precisely this:
::::::::(a)(1) [[Mike's Place suicide bombing]]:'Critically injured Keith Trowbridge, 37, of United States'.
::::::::(a)(2) [[Beersheva bus station shooting]]:'At least one of the wounded Israeli soldiers, Daniel Harush (19), was shot and critically injured by fellow security officers who mistook him for a terrorist.'
::::::::(a)(3)) [[Lions' Gate stabbings]] under '''Victims'''
::::::::The dead were Aharon Benita, 21, and Nehemia Lavie, 41, who attempted to come to the couple's rescue.
::::::::Adele Banita and her small son were injured, Adele wounded seriously with stab wounds. Visiting Mrs. Benita in hospital along with Minister of Public Security Gilad Erdan, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said: &quot;Let’s make this clear,&quot;... &quot;just as we’ve smashed previous waves of terrorism, we will also smash this wave of terrorism.&quot;
::::::::On this evidence, it very much looks like you are trying to keep out the kind of detail on the Palestinian article which wiki editors find acceptable on articles regarding Jeweish victims of terrorism. So?[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 20:25, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::: I am not responsible for other editors. Please look at the good articles, and bring your arguments from them; do not look at the bad articles to bring your arguments from them. I can only state my opinion as it is, and at the moment I am trying to improve this article only. I might very well be of the opinion, that those article need to be improved too, but that is irrelevant to this discussion. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 20:37, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::You are obliged under WP:NPOV to apply the rule as you understand them neutrally over all articles that come to your attention. You made a false statement, that it is not customary. It is, to the contrary, frequent, as a few minutes googling on comparable articles showed. A 'feeling' is not enough to constitute a legitimate objection.As to 'trying to improve the article', of your 84 edits, the majority consist of removal of information. The only substantial addition is [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=273174668 this, regarding the 'good character' testimony for the mass murderer].[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 20:51, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::: And I am applying good editing rules to this article. As I said, if you see something wrong on an article, fix it. You can't use a few instances of bad editing to prove your point against simple rules of editing which are basic to Wikipedia. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 20:57, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::Try and focus, instead of drifting. You have given  no policy basis in your remarks for objecting to the added content. This is a constant issue with you so please give and argue from policy not from self-esteem.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 21:00, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::: Please strike that [[WP:NPA|personal attack]]. I mean the &quot;drifting&quot; thing. I have given you the policy/guideline-based reason. Your reaction is as always to say none was given. This is WP:AE material, sorry. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 21:48, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::You open this with calling something a &quot;POV inspired edit&quot;, and complain about &quot;drifting&quot;? Thats a bit odd. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 22:09, 27 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::::::::::::: I said that I can't escape the thought. Also, there is hardly an insult in saying an edit is POV inspired, while Nishidani was personally insulting, and not for the first time. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 22:27, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
Al-Jazeera is unquestionably a reliable source, and I dont think theres an actual reason to suppress the listing of those wounded, but I dont think its necessary. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 22:13, 27 September 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
* The question isn't whether Al-Jazeera is RS, but rather that a newspaper interview is (1) far from ideal as source of factual statements, and (2) per the guideline I quoted, ''When deciding whether to include a name, its publication in '''secondary sources other than news media''' (...)'' --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 22:39, 27 September 2016 (UTC)
::To repeat. The perfect parallel to this article is that dealing with an  earlier massacre in the same city, [[1929 Hebron massacre]]. This deals with the slaughter of Jews by Arab fanatics, and details with photos of the wounded, extensive mention of the survivors, and even cites contemporary newspaper reports of what the survivors said. No editor has objected to this, rightly so. This article deals with a Jewish mass murderer in Hebron slaughtering Arabs, and I added exactly what the other article had. Namely, testimony re the wounded and from the survivors, and you, and Debresser protest. You objected to the use of Al Jazeera first as unreliable. Now you say it is reliable, but its use here violates [[WP:BLP]]. If it does then you and Debresser would be obliged to elide [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1929_Hebron_massacre#Account_of_Jacob_Joseph_Slonim the use of eyewitness testimony mentioning people's names from a contemporary newspaper report] in the [[Jewish Telegraphic Agency]]. The objection you raise here would apply, now, to 4 articles regarding Jewish victims of terrorism. No one in their respective edit history has ever objected to them on any grounds, let alone the one you adduce. The analogy is perfect, but the editing attitude is profoundly divergent. Palestinian wounded must not be mentioned. Jewish wounded can and will be mentioned. That is a total violation of editorial obligations to construct articles to ensure neutrality of representation.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 13:08, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
:::I've requested outside advice on this interpretation of policy [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Biographies_of_living_persons/Noticeboard#Can_wounded_be_named_if_they_speak_to_the_press here.][[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 14:05, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
::::''To repeat.'' - Please, don't. You have not addressed my objections previously raised. I am not an active editor of what you call 'parallel articles'. Let's focus on this one. I am not as well versed in the en-wiki policy lingo as some, so needed to clarify on what grounds I objected to quoting Al Jazeera interview as facts. I never called it 'unreliable', and with proper attribution, of course it can be used. As far as naming the wounded, it is a separate issue. I appreciate your BLPN request, but do not appreciate misrepresenting my position there.
::::In general, per my understanding of BLP, whether the victims should or should not be named depends on the details of news coverage at the time of the event as well as the type of sources other than news media. As I checked some 'parallel' articles about events that took place same decade, I see that names of the wounded are generally not given. In some cases, a great deal of details is given, but that just reflects the news coverage at the time, particularly when there are fewer victims to describe (and may well be excessive). How scholarly sources will describe these events after as many decades as have passed since the 1929 Hebron massacre, remains to be seen. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 16:54, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
:::Let me be clear. I don't care what the outcome is, ''as long as a policy is consistently applied across all relevant pages, without ethnonationalist description''. If the verdict is not to name the wounded, for me, this just means a clunky name-avoidance problem. 'One man was paralysed by a shot to the throat, another man was paralysed after being shot three times' is stupid prose when you have the name from an interview where the person gives his name and the details, etc. I find nothing exceptional in the following:
:::[[Yeshivat Beit Yisrael massacre]]
:::&lt;blockquote&gt;'''Shlomo'''. I was speaking with everyone and when I turned around I saw people flying in the air. My brother fell onto me. I didn't know if my brother was wounded or the blood of other wounded people was on him. All I felt was pain.&lt;/blockquote&gt;	”
:::&lt;blockquote&gt;'''Eitan''' of the Magen David Adom recounted:&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:::&lt;blockquote&gt;We arrived at the site and saw scenes of horror. Young children, old people, women, lying in the road without hands, without legs, blood everywhere and enormous destruction all about. Only some had the strength to scream or cry. The quiet was the thing I remember most... This was one of the worst attacks I can remember.&lt;/blockquote&gt;	”
:::&lt;blockquote&gt;'''Livnat, the sister of Sofia Ya'arit Eliyahu''' who died in the blast with her seven-month-old son, described her experience:&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:::&lt;blockquote&gt;On Saturday night, we went out for a walk with two baby carriages. Sofia's baby started crying and she bent down to pick him up, while I continued walking with her little girl. We were 10 meters from them when we heard a horrendous explosion ... I looked back and saw only a huge inferno. Sofia and the baby had disappeared.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
:::I find suppressing those names ugly, indeed deeply distasteful but, if the consensus is not to use them, fine. I'll not add them there and replace Shlomo with 'One witness', Eitan 'A person from Magen David Adom', and '''Livnat''' = sister. etc.etc. This would be all unnecessary, but it would flow from the consequences of the interpretation of policy given.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 17:37, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Providing eyewitness accounts verbatim in general seems unencyclopedic to me. There needs to be some special reason to include them rather than summarize and paraphrase the sources. It helps solve the issue of attribution, but there are other ways. I would appreciate if we could also reach consensus that rioters shot and killed in the aftermath elsewhere should not be listed among the victims or in the same section. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 18:12, 28 September 2016 (UTC)
*Coming from BLPN.  There is certainly no BLP violation in adding this material, and I don't see valid objections on other grounds either.  Certainly not the fact that it is &quot;unnecessary&quot;.  There's no problem with the sourcing.  What I see is a fair amount of sniping that is getting in the way of sensible discussion.  Again, though, the main issue is that the material meets our policy requirements, in my view.  [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] ([[User talk:Nomoskedasticity|talk]]) 14:11, 28 September 2016 (UTC)

== terror ==

let me get this straight. Hamas terrorists, but JDL, lets take out terrorist and hate group. Very NPOV. Im going to go through some of these changes in a bit and fix the slant thats been introduced. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 19:37, 6 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
* Hamas is a designated foreign terrorist organization per US, EU, UN, etc, etc, etc. This is hardly POV. Kach and Kahane Chai were designated foreign terrorist organizations per US as well. JDL was certainly involved in violent acts, but it functioned legally in the US all along and was never a designated terrorist organization. Those are just facts. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 20:10, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
:Please read the [[Hamas]] article before stating which countries think it a terrorist organization.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 21:58, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
::[[Jewish_Defense_League#Terrorism_and_other_illegal_activities|Ahem]]. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 21:19, 6 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::The report linked there calls JDL a ''known violent extremist Jewish Organization''. I do not dispute this. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 21:55, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
::::Could you please just stop editing a while. You have made numerous errors. I just removed Hall of Abraham glossing the Ibrahimni Mosque. The Hall of Abrhama is one thing, the Hall of Isaac another, and both are in the Ibrahmi Mosque.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 22:03, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::Ok, sure. Thanks for the revert, see my comment below. I waited a few days for your promised edit, but it never materialized. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 22:05, 6 October 2016 (UTC)

: I removed the mention that the JDL is an extremist organization founded by Kahane. That is all in the link. If anybody wants to add it back in, then please also mention that Hamas is designated a terrorist organization by a number of countries. We have to be evenhanded here. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 00:32, 7 October 2016 (UTC)
:: You shouldn't have. It adds relevant information about Goldstein's background and JDL is certainly not as well known as Hamas. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 14:00, 7 October 2016 (UTC)

== Ibrahimi mosque ==

[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Cave_of_the_Patriarchs_massacre&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=742959632&amp;oldid=742959064] - thanks for the revert. Yes, I have been inside, if that matters. Merely trying to harmonize terms used later in the article and in the main [[Cave of the Patriarchs]] article, but here I made a mistake. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 22:04, 6 October 2016 (UTC)

== Before and after ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;The massacre immediately set off mass Palestinian protests and riots throughout the West Bank, and within 48 hours, nine Palestinian protesters had been killed by the Israeli Defense Forces.[6] Goldstein was widely denounced in Israel and by communities in the Jewish diaspora,[4] with many attributing his act to insanity.[7] Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin condemned the attack, describing Goldstein as a &quot;degenerate murderer&quot;, &quot;a shame on Zionism and an embarrassment to Judaism&quot;.[8][9][10] Some Jewish settlers in Hebron lauded him as a hero and viewed his attack and subsequent death as an act of martyrdom.[11]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Rewritten by Wiking
&lt;blockquote&gt;The massacre immediately set off mass Palestinian protests and riots throughout the West Bank, and within 48 hours, nine Palestinian protesters had been killed by the Israeli Defense Forces.[5] '''Hamas terrorists carried out two separate suicide bombings a few weeks later, allegedly in retaliation for the Cave of the Patriarchs massacre.[6]8 Israeli civilians were killed and 55 wounded in the attack, which took place in Afula on April 6,[7][8] and six more were killed and 30 injured Hadera bus station suicide bombing on April 13.'''&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Goldstein was widely denounced in Israel and by communities in the Jewish diaspora,[9] with many attributing his act to insanity.[10] Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin condemned the attack, describing Goldstein as a &quot;degenerate murderer&quot;, &quot;a shame on Zionism and an embarrassment to Judaism&quot;.[11][12][13] However, some Jewish settlers in Hebron lauded him as a hero and viewed his attack as a preemptive strike and his subsequent death as an act of martyrdom.[14]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Leads summarize the content, they are not to be written to balance Goldstein's murder with Hamas murders later. Note that we do not add details of the IDF retaliation over the next 2 weeks, specifying the huge extra toll that took etc. It's not alleged with Hamas. They announced their intention of retaliation, etc.etc.etc. Nothing is gained by this. Condemnation choruses in the lead are useless. One just mentions that in a line. There are many things the lead should sum up but doesn't. [[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 22:16, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
:Im going to go through the edits later tonight and keep the improvements but revert the problems. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 22:36, 6 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:: @Nableezy And who are you to decide what the &quot;problems&quot; are? I for one think that the fact that retaliation took place is lead material. The details of how many people died on those retaliations are not, but the fact itself is just as much lead material as the protests. By the way, if the numbers of people killed in the retaliations are removed, then so should the numbers of people who were killed during protests. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 00:29, 7 October 2016 (UTC)
:::Im an editor like any other, but BRD would be one thing to keep in mind. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 02:57, 7 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

== recent changes ==

# Lead changes, Hamas attacks after the fact arent a main part of this story, and if it is to be included it should not be included in that way. I for one say it should not be.
# Background of Goldstein - we have an article on him, this should be relatively brief here. Im leaving it mostly that for now but it needs to be pared down. Mostly, as the part of there being warning of a Hamas attack has nothing to do with Goldstein's background.
# Prior violence at the site That section contains sources that predate this event, it is entirely WP:SYNTH
#Rabin, regarding [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Cave_of_the_Patriarchs_massacre&amp;diff=742915585&amp;oldid=742915329 this] edit, [http://www.timesofisrael.com/in-1976-interview-rabin-likens-settlements-to-cancer-warns-of-apartheid/ yes], but it doesnt really matter here so not restoring that
#If the injured are removed the casualties section should be renamed deaths, as casualties include injuries. I kept it casualties by returning information on the injured without naming any of them. That hopefully satisfies yall on that count
&lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 03:14, 7 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
* Hamas retaliation attacks are already summarized in LEAD, but can be shortened further. Details of Goldstein's background irrelevant to the story should be moved to his articles. Agreed that warning of a Hamas attack has nothing to do with Goldstein's background and should go into a separate section, please propose the name. Prior violence and symbolic meaning of the site are relevant and are taken straight from [[Cave of the Patriarchs]], how is it WP:SYNTH? I added summary of the injured information into the Massacre section itself; no issues with either renaming Casualties or moving the summary of the injured there, although it seemed more appropriate in the narrative, so just boils down to the amount of info you'd like to add. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 14:13, 7 October 2016 (UTC)
::Its SYNTH because none of the references connect it to the topic of this article, the attack by Goldstein. And they couldnt, because all the sources predate this attack. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 16:21, 7 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::I am sorry, but I still do not understand the nature of your objection. If you are looking for a single RS mentioning both past violent events and the 1994 massacre, there are plenty, e.g. [http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4592921,00.html], basically any source tracing the history of the cave to modern times. If the same site has been the location of other terrorist attacks in recent past, it is relevant and deserves being mentioned. So is its symbolic significance, which explains why it would attract nationalistic Jews like Goldstein in the first place (as a place of worship). And you removed sourced material regarding a warning of an impending Hamas attack just because ... it was placed in a wrong section? Really? --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 18:22, 7 October 2016 (UTC)
::::Last things first, I removed material on a warning on a Hamas attack from the wrong section. It is still  in the relevant sections (Shamgar Commision, Veneration of Goldstein). It seems as though you think I removed it entirely, I did not, that is discussed already where it is relevant. You added it to where it is not relevant, and I removed it from there. As far as SYNTH, yes my objection is that there is no single source that connected those acts to the topic. I wouldnt use an op-ed (what you just brought) to do that, but if you have any reliable sources that discuss those attacks as they relate to this ones by all means use that. But you cant claim a background for an attack that reliable sources dont say is a background for this attack, and using sources that pre-date this does that. They cannot be connecting the topics, this topic didnt exist when they were published. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 18:37, 7 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::::So, you think that ''Goldstein's background'' is the wrong section for warning on an impending Hamas attack '''before the massacre''', but ''Shamgar Commission'' is the right section??? There just needs to be a separate section dealing with the atmosphere and background of the event, which isn't &quot;Goldstein's background&quot;. As far as prior attacks that happened at the same place, agreed, op-ed is not a good RS, but then again, I didn't add it to the article. Nor did I write that previous attacks at the same site were ''a background for an attack'', not sure where you got that idea. So your sole objection is lack of a single source mentioning those events together the way [[Cave of the Patriarchs#Israeli control]] does? --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 19:32, 7 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::The material is from the Shamgar Commission, why wouldnt that be the proper spot? It talks about the conclusions drawn in the report, that was one of them. To restate my objection, cus Im not sure how much simpler I can make it, a single source needs to connect whatever topic that you want to connect to this article's topic. By including it in the article you are implicitly making it relevant background. We cannot do that absent a source that does, doing that is original research in that you are deciding what is relevant and what is not. The sources decide what is relevant and what is not. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 20:16, 7 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::::::The Hamas theory is not treated seriously by most students of that topic. The Purim theory is, and was in the lead, and you took it out, and replaced it with a detailed list of Hamas incidents that followed. That was pure POV pushing, and whether you knew it or not, gave the reader the impression that somehow Goldstein's shooting upwards of 150 peopleat prayer was a saintly atempt to prevent what Hamas then did. I'm sure you can'0t seriously believe that? Hebron's settlers do.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 19:55, 7 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::The re-interpretation of Purim story which I removed from the LEAD is not directly connected to the topic, most certainly does not belong in LEAD, and is probably [[WP:FRNG|too fringe]] to be mentioned elsewhere in the article, though this is debatable. No, I did not mean to give the reader the impression that somehow Goldstein's shooting was an attempt to prevent Hamas bombings ''in Afula and Hadera'', not sure how you would get this impression either, but maybe you could point out. As far as his shooting preventing a Hamas attack on fellow settlers in his area, what matters is whether ''he'' and other settlers believed this, not whether you or I believe it. It is written clearly that some ''settlers viewed his attack as a preemptive strike'', not that it was one. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 20:48, 7 October 2016 (UTC)

::::::::: I agree with Wiking that the retaliatory actions are lead material, as I said in the section above as well. The Purim story is not mentioned in the article proper, so can not be in the lead (which is supposed to summarize the article). [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 17:20, 8 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::I agree, but it should be in the last line, and simply state Hamas retaliated with several suicide bombings of Israeli civilians.' (leaving the details to the relevant section' (b) What Ian S.Lustick and others state is not WP:Fringe. He is one of the world's leading authorities on settlement, and wrote a monograph on West Bank settlers, published by the American Council for Foreign Relations. Please try to understand the quality of sources, the authority behind them, instead of waving inexactly irrelevant policies.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 17:41, 8 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::: As I stated above, if details like the number of people killed in the retaliations are removed, then so should the number of people who were killed during protests. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 17:55, 8 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::Suicide bombings generally have casualties, protests do not. You removed any mention of violence against protesters, but retained violence by Hamas. And you call that &quot;neutral&quot;? No, I dont think so. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 22:19, 8 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::::::::::: What are you talking about? I removed the number of casualties of the protests, just like there was no number of casualties of the retaliations.You seem to forget that the protests were &quot;protets and riots&quot;, and riots do have casualties. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 09:05, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::The word 'riot' is Israelispeak for any opposition to the Israeli occupational authorities. All protests, demonstrations that are conducted on a daily basis in most civilized countries are automatically (following the IDF report handouts) described as 'riots' in the Israeli press. If you protest that some friend was shot, and scream, you are a rioter, and can be shot. When 29 people were shot dead and 125 wounded,(154 casualties  in a few minutes at the Israeli official estimate, though Palestinians count over 200) and crowds surged into the streets, and relatives, on hearing the news, ran out to help, protest, they were shot at as 'rioters', where in any normal world that would be understood to be an expression of victim-panic or succour. If any historian wrote that some of the Jews murdered in the [[Kishinev pogrom]] were killed when they 'rioted' at the first sign of violence, (s)he's promptly be given his or her marching orders from tenure. [[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 09:20, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::: Really, Nishidani? What you are saying is that those were not riots. So they were peaceful protests. So the Israelis decided to start killing peaceful protesters and opened fire. Do I understand you correctly? Do you understand how far-fetched that accusation is? And how unsourced? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 09:37, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::Not far-fetched at all when one is aware of the history of such things. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 09:45, 9 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::::::::::::::: @Nableezy First of all thank you for leaving out the number. Although you reverted my removal, you left out the number, and thus addressed my main problem with that sentence.
::::::::::::::::: In view of [[Purity of arms]] and the lack of sources, I'd say that is far-fetched. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 09:48, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::I didn't say riots did not occur on that day. I said that Israeli and Israelocentric reportage customarily crushes a clear distinction between protests and riots, and this distinction was collapsed on the day of the event. [[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 10:39, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::: There exists television. You can see for yourself the difference. You don't need to rely on Israeli sources to see the difference between a rioting mob and a peaceful protest march. I find your POV especially unpleasant in view of the biased reporting of Arab media, and even mainstream Western media, which has been proven many times. Compared to that, Israeli media are a paradigm of truthful reporting. Whatever, I think we have strayed a bit from the subject, and have a version that satisfies all, as a compromise. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 10:57, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::::Sure. For 20 years I've watched things [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=19-hmgaM1ZQ like this], while reading of the  [[Purity of arms]] fantasy, and noting down the statistics of 29,000 Palestinian youths hospitalized in the 7 years before this massacre and its riots, with fractures from Rabin's 'Break their Bones' if they protest policy. I'm sure those who look at this react in one of two ways: 'shit happens, let's move on'/'Good grief, we did that?'  Zionism is an ideology, and like all the others. ideologies mean systems of thought whose core belief structure is  impermeable to information. You can have the last word, but this is distracting from editing[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 14:57, 9 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::::[[Death of Khalil al-Mughrabi|For the record]]. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 01:34, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::::::::::::::::::::And you have sources claiming that something similar happened following the event we are discussing? --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 16:42, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::::::You understand I was responding to what Debresser wrote, right? &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 17:23, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::::::::::::::::::::: I didn't understand that either. Nishidani and I are in agreement that we already strayed to far from the subject (so I don't see reason to provide sources, although yes, I could), so unless you think there is reason to change the article, I think we should leave it at this. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 19:58, 12 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::::::::You wrote that so called purity of arms makes something that has happened several times far-fetched. I was responding to that erroneous thought. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 20:16, 12 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::::::::::::::::::::::: Oh, what that what you were replying to. I agree with you. At the same time, you have to differentiate between the rule and the exception. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 20:33, 12 October 2016 (UTC)

== palestinians killed by IDF ==

How is it not NPOV to say they were killed by the IDF? That is a factual statement. It does not say &quot;murdered&quot;, it says killed. What the source says. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 22:23, 10 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
* by leaving out the fact that they were killed in violent clashes, maybe? --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 22:46, 10 October 2016 (UTC)
::By who? You left out who killed them. When the IDF uses live ammunition it is by definition a &quot;violent clash&quot;. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 00:10, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::Not at all. They could be ambushing unsuspecting civilians the way Palestinian terrorists do frequently (and no, this isn't by definition a &quot;violent clash&quot;). That's the impression that a reader unfamiliar with the topic is likely to receive from present wording. I understand Nishidani's point above that it may be difficult to draw the line between a protest and a riot. However, some protests turn into riots and others do not. I believe all live ammo shootings occurred '''after''' protests turned into riots (e.g. when rioters were hurling rocks at the soldiers). Leaving this out is NPOV violation. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 00:46, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::::it's a NPOV violation based off of what you believe? We are faithfully reflecting the source here, not a Wikipedia editors belief. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 00:49, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::::Sure, let's examine your sources that support what you are suggesting... --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]])
::::::Its cited at the end of the sentence. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 04:06, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:There is a good point here to be honest. There are enough educated, intelligent humans who believe that Israel is simply killing Palestinians for fun, or people who don't know it at all. &quot;In the first 6 days following the massacre, 21 Palestinians were killed by live ammunition from the IDF&quot;, sounds like you are saying &quot;although the massacre ended on sunday, the Israeli army continued it till friday&quot;. The people were killed by the IDF during clashes. Don't know what is going on with the juicy argument above this section, but this one spesific edit was not POV pushing. (though the comment here was quite nonsense).--[[User:Bolter21|'''Bolter21''']] &lt;small&gt;''([[User talk:Bolter21|talk to me]])''&lt;/small&gt; 01:03, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::If there are other sources that support that wording we can discuss it. As it stands however the source cited makes no mention of riots. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 01:35, 11 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::Bolter.'There are enough educated, intelligent humans who believe that Israel is simply killing Palestinians for fun, or people who don't know it at all.'
::::I've never met people or read statements from 'educated' people who believe that. What 'educated' critics    usually say is that the operational rules of the IDF are based on 'exceptionalism', i.e., that is, that this is a 'unique' situation for obscure mythological reasons, and so the normal criteria for evaluation don't apply. Well, those of us trained to think analytically in comparative terms use different criteria, comparing similar phenomena to note analogies and distinctions. So if some speak of 'apartheid', one compares: in some senses it is true, in others it is obviously false. In terms of the shooting bullets live or not at an occupied people, it is not permitted in any democratic nation. 'Clashes' means stone throwers were shot by snipers at a distance of 80+ yards operatively. It is not normal to shoot on excited, exasperated people who are bereaved, or relatives of the bereaved in such circumstances. As Nableezy says, we just use sources.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 07:47, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::So throwing stones at armed soldiers is normal and not suicidal, huh. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 14:07, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::I&quot;ve been to a Breaking the Silence conference and not a one sponsered by Roger Waters, but actually in Tel Aviv, Israel. My main assumption is that the people talking to me were educated and intelligent. Anyway the Jerusalem Post calls it an &quot;[http://www.jpost.com/Features/In-Thespotlight/This-Week-in-History-The-second-Hebron-massacre unrest]&quot;--[[User:Bolter21|'''Bolter21''']] &lt;small&gt;''([[User talk:Bolter21|talk to me]])''&lt;/small&gt; 14:38, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::'Israel is simply killing Palestinians for fun'. Whoever makes that kind of remark is anti-Semitic. Nations don't kill, some of its members do, for a variety of reasons. To take every example of criticism of a specific act or serious of acts as indicative of a nation's 'mentality', applicable to all and sundry is stupid. If you ever see [[Green Street (film)|Green Street]], it would be like saying the English love bashing the living shit out of each other, because soccer hooligans  regularly do so. It's a very good film on what a buddy mentality does to decent people.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 15:54, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Oh, that's quite different then from what [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Cave_of_the_Patriarchs_massacre&amp;diff=742961192&amp;oldid=742960076 you wrote] just a few days ago, isn't it? &quot;''Note that we do not add details of the IDF retaliation over the next 2 weeks''&quot;. So were the Israeli soldiers '''retaliating'''? For what? Or were they assaulted by violent rioters hurling rocks at them, as confirmed even by the Al-Jazeera article you added regarding the one person shot near the hospital? Somehow you felt that it was relevant to add to the article that he donated blood, that he saw his friend wounded, and his connection to the massacre is very indirect as is! If that's not POV pushing, I don't know what is. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 16:49, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Please focus by mastering the construal of English sentences, to get right what your interlocutors say. The point made above is totally obscure. [[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 18:36, 11 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::: Nishidani, per the recent [[WP:AE]] conclusion, please refrain from commenting on the fluency of editors in the English language. [[WP:CIVIL|Comment on content, don't comment on editors]]. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 19:58, 12 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::I will note whenever necessary someone's clear misconstrual of simple English. If people persist in not being clear in writing then then need a nudge.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 22:39, 13 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::: There are educated and intelligent people who deny the Holocaust. That does not mean there was no Holocaust. The point being that there were riots (it's in the source, Nableezy, please look again), and there is nothing strange about violent riots ending with the death of some rioters. As long as our article makes it clear that that is what happened, NPOV is respected. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 20:02, 12 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::As said a hundred times it is an Israeli POV to confuse 'riots', 'protests', 'demonstration': the last two are invariably erased for the default 'riot'. It is unacceptable.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 22:39, 13 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::: There is no confusion: the riots were riots: mobs of people who (spontaneously or premeditated) turned violent, in order to vent their feelings of frustration and disagreement with the powers that be. No creative re-writing of fact will be tolerated on Wikipedia. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 06:46, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::: By the way, your source[https://books.google.co.il/books?id=YAd8efHdVzIC&amp;pg=PA438&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false] also uses the term &quot;major rioting&quot;. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 06:51, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::: I hope that you will find my rephrasing in simple English helpful. Please explain what you meant by [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Cave_of_the_Patriarchs_massacre&amp;diff=742961192&amp;oldid=742960076 this] comment when you wrote about &quot;''details of the IDF retaliation over the next 2 weeks''&quot;. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 17:09, 13 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::You added Hamas retaliation a month later
:::::::::&lt;blockquote&gt;[6]8 Israeli civilians were killed and 55 wounded in the attack, which took place in Afula on April 6,[7][8] and six more were killed and 30 injured Hadera bus station suicide bombing on April 13&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:::::::::To a text that had nothing about the IDF response in the immediate aftermath.
:::::::::In the edit which Debresser removed. I added both Palestinian and Jewish casualties in the aftermath. I  did so because the lead still speaks, quite correctly of a Hamas retaliation, but has nothing of the Israeli onslaught as people protested. Leads reflect the section. The sections have (a&gt;) Palestinian casualties in the aftermath, and Israeli casualities in the aftermath, but only the latter is alluded to in the lead. So I reintroduced them for balance. When I revert that well sourced text back in I'll add the casualties from the Hamas bombings. [[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 22:51, 13 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::I fail to see how your answer relates to my question. You mentioned here &quot;''the IDF retaliation''&quot;. There was no 'IDF retaliation'.
::::::::::As far as your and Debresser's edits of the LEAD, now it says that &quot;''a number of Palestinians were killed or injured in confrontations with the IDF, while 9 Jews were killed.''&quot; Really? Just like that, killed? This is a very biased way to describe the events, assigning responsibility for the Palestinians (who were either rioting or otherwise engaged in violent protests!) to the IDF, while not mentioning the party responsible for the murder of the 9 Jews, who were not engaged in any violence. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 23:27, 13 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::: You are absolutely correct. Will fix that right away. Sorry. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 06:46, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::: It's not clear which 9 Jews that source is referring to. Need something more detailed. --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 13:57, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::It's the sunm of the Jews in the confrontations and violence that immediately followed, as for the Palestinians. Any further detail you find goes down page.[[User:Nishidani|Nishidani]] ([[User talk:Nishidani|talk]]) 14:43, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::::: Jews (other than the military) participated in the confrontations and violence that immediately followed? That's news to me, and I don't think these casualties are military... --[[User:Wiking|Wiking]] ([[User talk:Wiking|talk]]) 20:06, 14 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>5pdxk8db8pvo9zk8pb7zvd384x0f7hd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
