<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Race to the Sea</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2670333</id>
    <revision>
      <id>706770060</id>
      <parentid>625811851</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-02-25T05:09:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mztourist</username>
        <id>11292517</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Background too long */ new section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5292">{{WikiProject Germany|class=B|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|importance=low}}
{{MILHIST|class=B|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|French=y|German=y|British=y|WWI=y}}

==Clean Up==
Somebody really needs to clean up this article. It has little to no structure and the information is clouded and it does not flow.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/202.168.19.196|202.168.19.196]] ([[User talk:202.168.19.196|talk]]) 10:00, 15 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== natural obstacle ==

Was the natural obstacle the sea or Antwerp? --[[User:Gbleem|Gbleem]] 14:35, 24 September 2006 (UTC)

== North and South ==

Why did they go north and not south? --[[User:Gbleem|Gbleem]] 14:47, 24 September 2006 (UTC)
:The [[OKW]], German High Command, employed the [[Schlieffen Plan]] in its attack on France. Its aim was to come between the bulk of the French Army and the bulk of France so that French forces could not be supplied. This was done by attacking through Belgium and looked like working until the German advance stalled at the Marne. This stalling was partly due to an inability to keep the German supply system up with its army and partly to the weary state of its soldiers. Once stalled, its army's right flank was exposed, particularly to an attack from the relatively fresh, French garrison of Paris. This could have meant that the French Army had come between the German Army and its planned supplies. It would also have opened the German rear to attack. Each side therefore moved forces northwards to outflank the other and to avoid being outflanked
:It was also essential that the Franco-Belgian-British forces should be in position in the North, in time to stop the taking of he Channel ports by German forces released by the breaking of Belgian opposition. This would have prevented the supply of the [[British Expeditionary Force|BEF]]. 
:On foot, it is a long way to go from the Marne to the North Sea coast, across seemingly endless chalk plateau but the 'race' was conducted with the help on the one side, of Entente marine forces in the extreme North and on the other, of German forces directly from Belgium. ([[User:RJP|RJP]] 17:24, 24 September 2006 (UTC))

::The army couldn't move North because it had no supplies so it moved north?? --[[User:Gbleem|Gbleem]] 17:42, 24 September 2006 (UTC)

:::The German army did not move further South as it had been stopped by mainly French forces and fatigue. Once its momentum was lost, its enemies had time to move into the vacuum behind it, attack its rear and cut off some at least of its supply lines. It withdrew to the Aisne to reduce the length of its front and moved its right wing further northward to close the remaining gap. This closure process came to be called the 'Race to the Sea'. See [[First Battle of the Marne]].
:::In a medieval war, an army could replenish its supplies by foraging and making more arrows and so on. In the seventeenth century it could make more bullets from the lead of someone's church roof. In the early twentieth century it needed ammunition to fit its own weapons and that needed an industrial infrastructure to produce it. Logistics had become more significant. ([[User:RJP|RJP]] 19:54, 24 September 2006 (UTC))

==Assessment==
Would this article benefit from a list of battles, or a similar treatment of chronology? [[User:LordAmeth|LordAmeth]] 09:09, 28 October 2006 (UTC)

== Recent edits ==

Added some gleanings from Doughty and Foley and began assembly of a casualty section, which I will add to as I discover sources.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 10:05, 5 January 2014 (UTC)

:the First Battle of Artois (27 September – 10 October) title doesn't match the dates[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 22:54, 26 January 2014 (UTC)

::Finished the re-edit and expansion but it could do with a fresh pair of eyes casting over it.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 17:04, 22 February 2014 (UTC)

== Associated pages ==

Have begun to move the detail on here to specific pages so will prune the overwritten sections accordingly to 1-2 paragraphs.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 08:00, 7 August 2014 (UTC)

: Have pruned the battle sections of material transferred to the specific pages and made sure each section has a link.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 11:51, 7 August 2014 (UTC)

== Mud ==

Is it true that the Germans opened the dykes, and that's where all the mud came from? [[User:Valetude|Valetude]] ([[User talk:Valetude|talk]]) 12:22, 16 September 2014 (UTC)
:No, the Belgians did that to stop the Germans, see here [[Battle of the Yser]].[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 13:42, 16 September 2014 (UTC)

== Background too long ==

The Background section while all correct and very well written is '''vastly''' too long. It comprises practically the entire history of WWI to that point which is just an overload of detail. I believe that the background should be slimmed down to something more like in the [[First Battle of the Marne]]. [[User:Mztourist|Mztourist]] ([[User talk:Mztourist|talk]]) 05:09, 25 February 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>etthmgsyo2f5no9m1pubi1t5nd4ij23</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
