<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>147 Squadron (Israel)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33119187</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747395404</id>
      <parentid>688548554</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-02T04:04:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9816">{{infobox military unit
|dates= 1956, 1967, 1978-1986
|unit_name= 147 Squadron
|image= [[File:The Goring Ram Squadron logo.jpg|180px]]
|country= {{flag|Israel}}
|branch= {{air force|Israel}}
|role= light strike
|garrison=
|nickname=Goring Ram / Flying Ibex
|colors=
|equipment=
|battles=[[Suez Crisis]]&lt;br&gt;[[Six Day War]]
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Aircraft --&gt;
|aircraft_attack=[[Fouga Magister]]&lt;br&gt;[[A-4 Skyhawk]]
|aircraft_trainer=[[Boeing-Stearman Kaydet]]
}}
'''147 Squadron''', often referred to as the '''Flying Ibex'''&lt;ref name=A4s/&gt; or '''Goring Ram'''&lt;ref name=Norton222/&gt; squadron, is a former unit of the [[Israeli Air Force]]. Fielding [[Israeli Air Force flight academy|IAF Flight Academy]] aircraft, it flew the [[Boeing-Stearman Kaydet]] during the 1956 [[Suez Crisis]] and the [[Fouga Magister]] during the 1967 [[Six Day War]], in the course of which it suffered six fatalities. Between 1978 and 1986 it flew the [[A-4 Skyhawk]].

== Formation ==
In January 1953 the IAF formed the flight academy's fleet of Stearmans into a reserve liaison and surveillance unit, to be activated in times of emergency. Seconded to [[100 Squadron (Israel)|100 Squadron]], the unit was initially designated 1000 Squadron, but was redesignated 147 Squadron on January 1, 1955. It was activated on October 27, 1956, for the Suez Crisis. Commanded by Captain Meir Shefer, the unit had 25 servicable aircraft but only 12 pilots, consisting of both reserves and qualified students and including Rina Levinson, one of a handful of female pilots serving with the IAF. 147 Squadron flew 401 sorties during the war, clocking 233 hours. Flying from [[Ramla]], next to IAF headquarters, the squadron flew communications, liaison, transport, patrol and reconnaissance missions, operating during both day and night.&lt;ref&gt;[[#citeNorton|Norton 2004]], p. 145&lt;/ref&gt; Once the fighting was over, the aircraft reverted to their original training role and the squadron was deactivated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iaf.org.il/200-18266-he/IAF.aspx?indx=4|language=Hebrew|accessdate=September 17, 2011|publisher=Israeli Air Force website|title=Boeing-Stearman PT-13 Kaydet}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Six Day War==
The [[Fouga Magister]] entered service with the IAF Flight Academy in 1960, and on November 1, 1961, 147 Squadron was reformed to operate the type during emergencies.&lt;ref name=NortonF/&gt;

The squadron was reactivated at [[Hatzerim Airbase|Hatzerim]] in May 1967, on the eve of the [[Six Day War]].&lt;ref name=ShalomF/&gt; Commanded by Major Arieh Ben-Or, there were 44 aircraft and 42 pilots on hand on the morning of June 5, when Israel launched [[Operation Focus]], the strike that started the war. While the Fougas were initially slated to participate in attacks on the Egyptian air bases at [[El Arish]] and Jabl Libni, their light armament and lack of effective combat range led to their reassignment to the deception, interdiction and [[close air support]] roles.&lt;ref&gt;[[#citeShalom|Shalom 2003]], pp. 109, 119&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, while the majority of IAF combat aircraft were en route to their respective targets in Egypt and the Sinai, 147 Squadron Fougas took to the air flying seemingly routine training missions and generating seemingly routine radio traffic to give the impression that Israel was on a low state of alert.&lt;ref name=NortonF/&gt; Other Fougas, however, were making their way to attack Egyptian troop concentrations along the front in support of the Israeli push into the Sinai.&lt;ref&gt;[[#citeShalom|Shalom 2003]], p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; The first strikes targeted a pair of Egyptian radar stations near [[El-Arish]], during which the squadron suffered its first fatality of the war, deputy squadron leader Arnon Livnat.&lt;ref name=ShalomF/&gt;

With the IAF's combat squadrons occupied by ''Focus'', 147 Squadron's Fougas were effectively the only attack aircraft available to provide support for [[Israel Defense Forces|IDF]] ground forces. They subsequently attacked Egyptian artillery in the northern Sinai, convoys, supply trains and troop concentrations. 147 Squadron was also active on other fronts, and late on June 5 the Fougas went into action against the Jordanians in the [[West Bank]]. Several aircraft struck Jordanian artillery that had been shelling various points in Israel, tanks operating in the [[Jenin]] region were attacked as well, while the squadron also managed to halt a Jordanian armored brigade attempting to intervene in the heavy fighting under way in [[Jerusalem]]. Three further aircraft and their pilots were lost.&lt;ref name=NortonF/&gt;

147 Squadron returned to the West Bank on the morning of June 6, flying 104 sorties and firing over 1200 rockets at Jordanian targets throughout the region. One aircraft was lost and its pilot killed by the time the squadron was ordered to stand down during the latter half of the day. Having flown an average of 5 sorties on June 5, 147 Squadron  pilots flew an average of 3 on June 6. Operations on the Jordanian front resumed the following day, during which Iraqi reinforcements were attacked, but on June 8 the squadron was informed that its role in the fighting had come to an end. Fighting on the [[Golan Heights]], however, prompted a change of heart, and on the morning of June 9 147 Squadron deployed to [[Ramat David Airbase|Ramat David]]. The first formation to head into action over the Golan, led by squadron leader Ben-Or, encountered heavy Syrian anti-aircraft fire. Ben-Or was killed and further Fouga missions were promptly canceled.&lt;ref name=NortonF/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fischer/&gt;

The squadron claimed 128 tanks destroyed during the war, 43 other armored vehicles, 292 lorries, 2 trains, 47 artillery pieces, and 4 anti-aircraft guns. 419 sorties had been flown and 4,384 rockets expended, including Egyptian stocks captured at the air base at El Arish. Slow, lightly armed, lacking both defensive armor and ejection seats, six Magisters and their pilots had been lost, including both the squadron leader and his deputy. Virtually every single aircraft suffered battle damage. The end of the war led to the deactivation of the squadron and the Fouga Magisters were henceforth restricted to the training role.&lt;ref name=NortonF/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#citeShalom|Shalom 2003]], p. 248&lt;/ref&gt;

== Flying the A-4 Skyhawk ==
[[File:Goring Ram A-4 Hatzerim 230204.jpg|thumb|147 Squadron A-4 Skyhawk at the [[Israeli Air Force Museum]], Hatzerim]]
147 Squadron was reactivated once again at Hatzerim on August 6, 1978, commanded by Hanoch Patishi.&lt;ref name=Norton222/&gt;&lt;ref name=symbol/&gt; Operating a mix of A-4Es, A-4Fs and A-4Ns, it was the IAF's eighth and last A-4 Skyhawk squadron. Initially conceived as a unit manned by reservists with a skeleton crew of air force regulars, this arrangement was soon found unsatisfactory by both groups and the squadron reverted to the usual IAF combination of regulars, emergency postings and reserves.&lt;ref name=A4s/&gt; It adopted an emblem depicting a ram with wings against a yellow background, an all-yellow rudder and yellow-tipped external fuel tanks.&lt;ref name=symbol/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#citeNorton|Norton 2004]], p. 226&lt;/ref&gt;

The squadron flew its first operational mission on April 24, 1979, when four aircraft struck Palestinian artillery north of [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]]. In subsequent years the squadron routinely took part in IAF operations in [[Lebanon]], as fighting intensified in that country.&lt;ref name=A4s/&gt; In 1981 it was transformed into a reserve squadron, maintained by a small cadre of air force regulars, and was finally disbanded in 1986, its A-4Ns passing to [[102 Squadron (Israel)|102 Squadron]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#citeNorton|Norton 2004]], p. 224&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iaf.org.il/1703-25965-HE/IAF.aspx|first=Nina|last=Minderol|language=Hebrew|accessdate=September 16, 2011|date=April 27, 2006|publisher=Israeli Air Force Magazine|title=שלמה והנמרים}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==

=== Notes ===
{{Reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=A4s&gt;[[#Skyhawks|Aloni 2009]], pp. 75-76, 78&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=symbol&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iaf.org.il/2024-27677-HE/IAF.aspx|first1=Kalia|last1=Ben Amram|first2=Noa|last2=Kafri|language=Hebrew|accessdate=September 17, 2011|date=February 29, 2008|publisher=Israeli Air Force Magazine|title=סיפורי סמלים}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Norton222&gt;[[#citeNorton|Norton 2004]], p. 222&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=NortonF&gt;[[#citeNorton|Norton 2004]], pp. 183-184&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=ShalomF&gt;[[#citeShalom|Shalom 2003]], pp. 249-252&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Fischer&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fisherinstitute.org.il/?CategoryID=22&amp;ArticleID=335|language=Hebrew|accessdate=September 17, 2011|publisher=The Fisher Institute for Air and Space Strategic Studies|first=Eli|last=Eyal|date=August 2007|title=147 &quot;Fougas&quot; Squadron during the Six Day War}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

=== Bibliography ===
*{{cite book|last=Aloni|first=Shlomo|title=Israeli A-4 Skyhawk Units in Combat|series=Combat Aircraft|year=2009|publisher=Osprey|location=UK|isbn=978-1-84603-430-5|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xoeBjenEN9AC|ref=Skyhawks}}
*{{cite book|last=Norton|first=Bill|title=Air War on the Edge – A History of the Israel Air Force and its Aircraft since 1947|publisher=[[Ian Allan Publishing|Midland Publishing]]|year=2004|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q84hAQAAIAAJ|isbn=1-85780-088-5|location=Surrey, UK|ref=citeNorton}}
*{{cite book|last = Shalom|first = Danny|title = Like a Bolt Out of the Blue|publisher = Bavir Aviation &amp; Space Publications|year = 2002|language = Hebrew|isbn = 965-90455-0-6|ref=citeShalom}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Squadron 147 (Israeli Air Force)}}
*[http://a4skyhawk.org/2e/israel/israel-ibex/flying-ibex.htm IAF Flying Ibex Squadron] at the A-4 Skyhawk Association website

{{Israeli Air Force}}
{{Israeli Air Force Squadrons}}

[[Category:Israeli Air Force squadrons]]
[[Category:Six-Day War]]</text>
      <sha1>b1ti6k4prcprjmafcj0tke3tyl6mo2r</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
