<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>185th Aero Squadron</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39610655</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750972061</id>
      <parentid>676431546</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T16:02:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The PIPE</username>
        <id>710065</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Training in England */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16398">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}
{{infobox military unit
|unit_name= 185th Aero Squadron
|image= [[File:185th Aero Squadron - Group.jpg|300px]]
|caption= Officers of the 185th Aero Squadron, Rembercourt Aerodrome, France, November 1918
|dates= 11 November 1917&amp;nbsp;– 30 June 1919
|country={{flag|United States|23px}}
|allegiance= 
|branch= [[File:US Army Air Roundel.svg|15px]]&amp;nbsp; [[Air Service, United States Army]]
|type= Squadron
|role=  Night Pursuit
|size=  
|command_structure= [[American Expeditionary Forces]] (AEF)
|garrison=  
|garrison_label=
|nickname=    
|patron=
|motto=  
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment= &quot;Bats&quot;
|equipment_label= Fuselage Code
|battles= [[File:World War I War Service Streamer without inscription.png|150px]]&lt;BR&gt;[[World War I]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations= 
|battle_honours=
|battle_honours_label=
|disbanded=
|flying_hours=
|website=  
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=  
|commander1_label=
|notable_commanders= Lt. Seth Low&lt;ref name=&quot;OTF&quot;&gt;Over the Front: A Complete Record of the Fighter Aces and Units of the United States and French Air Services, 1914–1918 Norman Franks, Frank W. Bailey. Grub Street, 1992. ISBN 0-948817-54-2, ISBN 978-0-948817-54-0.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Capt. [[Jerry Vasconcells|Jerry C. Vasconcells]] &lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol= [[File:185th Aero Squadron - Emblem.jpg|125px]]
|identification_symbol_label= 185th Aero Squadron Emblem
&lt;!-- Aircraft --&gt;
|aircraft_attack=
|aircraft_bomber=   
|aircraft_electronic=
|aircraft_fighter=  [[Sopwith Camel F.1]], 1918&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;
|aircraft_interceptor=
|aircraft_patrol= 
|aircraft_recon=
|aircraft_trainer=  
|aircraft_transport=  
|aircraft_tanker=  
}}
{{service record
|is_ship=
|is_multi=
|label= 
|partof=
|codes=
|commanders=
|operations= [[1st Pursuit Group]]&lt;BR&gt;Western Front, France: 5 October-11 November 1918&lt;ref&gt;Series &quot;H&quot;, Section &quot;O&quot;, Volume 29, Weekly Statistical Reports of Air Service Activities, October 1918-May 1919. Gorrell's History of the American Expeditionary Forces Air Service, 1917–1919, National Archives, Washington, D.C.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sorties:  126
* Combat missions: 34  
* Enemy combats:  6  
* Enemy Aircraft shot down: 0 (1 probable)&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

|victories= No official victories, however the [[1st Pursuit Group]] commander, Col. [[Harold Hartney|Harold E. Hartney]] flew a night patrol in a squadron aircraft on 22 October 1918 and engaged a German [[Gotha G.V]] bomber.  He attacked the aircraft and the aircraft he flew came back bullet-ridden, however no claim of a victory was made. Later, the crashed remains of a Gotha was found in the area where he was engaged in combat.  It may have been the first (and only) night victory of the Air Service during World War I.&lt;ref name=&quot;OTF&quot;/&gt;   
|awards=
}}

The '''185th Aero Squadron''' was a [[Air Service, United States Army]] unit that fought on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] during [[World War I]].

Known as the &quot;Bats&quot;, the 185th Aero Squadron is notable as it was the first and only night pursuit (fighter) squadron organized by the United States during World War I.  Its mission was night interception of enemy aircraft, primarily bombers and observation aircraft.   It was engaged in combat for less than a month before the [[1918 Armistice with Germany]].  After the armistice, the squadron returned to the United States in June 1919 and was demobilized.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;&gt;Series &quot;E&quot;, Volume 20, History of the 149th–199th Aero Squadrons. Gorrell's History of the American Expeditionary Forces Air Service, 1917–1919, National Archives, Washington, D.C.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OOB&quot;&gt;Order of Battle of the United States Land Forces in the First World War, Volume 3, Part 3, Center of Military History, United States Army, 1949 (1988 Reprint)&lt;/ref&gt;

There is no modern [[United States Air Force]] or [[Air National Guard]] unit that shares its lineage and history.

==History==

===Origins===
The 185th Aero Squadron was organized on 11 November 1917 at [[Kelly Field]] #2, Texas by the transfer of men from the [[24th Aero Squadron]].  Many of the men had experience flying or maintaining the [[Curtiss JN-4]]B &quot;Jenny&quot; trainers.  On the 15th, additional men were transferred to the squadron from the 2d Recruit Battalion and 3d Recruit Battalion.   On 20 January 1918, the squadron was transferred to Aviation Concentration Center, [[Mitchell Field]], Long Island for duty overseas. After just over a week, the squadron embarked on the RMS Adriatic, arriving in [[Liverpool]], England on 16 February after being delayed in [[Halifax Regional Municipality|Halifax]], Nova Scotia for a convoy.    At Liverpool, the squadron boarded a train and arrived at [[Winchester]], England that evening, where it was assigned to the Romney Rest Camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

===Training in England===
On 28 February, the squadron was divided into Flights and placed under control of the [[Royal Flying Corps]] for training. &quot;B&quot;, &quot;C&quot; and &quot;D&quot; flights were transferred to 4 Training Depot Station (TDS) at [[RFC Hooton Park]] in [[Cheshire]].  &quot;A&quot; flight was transferred to 63 TDS, [[RFC Ternhill]], [[Shropshire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

At Hooton, the squadron was trained in the airplane repair shop, the engine repair shop and also in motor transport repair. Other men were trained in various clerical duties.  The men at Ternhill were trained in a similar manner.   The squadron was trained on both [[Sopwith strutter]]s and [[Sopwith Camel]]s with rotary engines and [[Sopwith Dolphin]] fighters equipped with [[Hispano-Suiza 8]]B engines.  In April, the 185th Aero Squadron was recombined at RFC Hooton where the squadron continued training.  On 16 June, the squadron was inspected by RFC Colonel Mansfield, Commander of the 37 Wing and he expressed his appreciation for the work provided by the squadron, owing to the shortage of British men who were at the front.    By July, the men of the 185th were becoming impatient, as it was rumored the squadron would remain in England on a permanent basis, however orders were finally relieved to report to the Flower Down Rest Camp near [[Winchester]] on 7 August.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

After a final inspection at Flower Down, the squadron received a final inspection before boarding a train to [[Southampton]] on 11 August.   Late the next afternoon, the squadron crossed the [[English Channel]] and arrived at American Rest Camp #2 in [[Le Havre]], France.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

===Combat in France===
The next day the squadron boarded a troop train, bound for the [[St. Maixent Replacement Barracks]], arriving on 16 August.  There the squadron was equipped with steel helmets and [[gas mask]]s and training in the [[tear gas]] chamber.   On 20 August, the squadron boarded a troop train and proceeded to the 1st Air Depot, [[Colombey-les-Belles Airdrome]], arriving on the 23d.   Once the authorities at the depot realized the 185th was fully trained,  the men were assigned to aircraft maintenance duties and also at the depot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

The need for pilots being so great on 16 September, seventeen squadron pilots were transferred out to fill vacancies in other squadrons at the front, leaving the 185th with two trained pilots, and still without any aircraft to fly.  Finally, on 7 October, orders were received to move to [[Rembercourt Aerodrome]] and join the [[1st Pursuit Group]].  After a rainy, long, uncomfortable trip by truck, the squadron arrived on the 10th late in the afternoon.     On 12 October, fourteen [[Sopwith Camel]]s were assigned to the 185th and the pilots began trial flights.  A few days later, five pilots, who had been transferred out at Colombey returned to the 185th.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

At Rembercourt, the 185th was designated as a &quot;Night Chase&quot; Squadron, the first of its type organized by the American Army.  Night Pursuit work was in its infancy.  The Sopwith Camels were planes that were considered almost to be obsolete, except for training.   The pilots were not trained in night flying, with many of them never having taken off after dusk.   Also, the squadron had to experiment with wing flares,  parachute flares and instrument lights.   Also the airdrome had no landing lights, and the searchlights and Anti-Aircraft batteries were not versed with American planes flying after dusk.   In addition, there were not enough searchlights for the guidance of our pilots, who frequently could not find the airfield at night and had to make forced landings after running out of gasoline.   Many accidents were caused and there was a chronic lack of spare parts for the airplanes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

====Night Pursuit Operations====
Nevertheless, on 18–19 October 1918, the first orders were issued and the 185th Aero Squadron (Night Pursuit) stood its first alert that night from dusk until dawn.  On the night of the 21st the squadron was alerted that there were several enemy aircraft flying over [[Troyon]], and the squadron took off in its first night interception mission.   However upon arrival over the area, no enemy aircraft were seen.     On the night of the 22d, the squadron made a low-level fight over enemy territory and Lieutenant Kelton fired about 100 rounds into a troop train between [[Spincourt]] and [[Longuyon]].  However, due to poor visibility, he was unable to report the results.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

The only aerial combat of the squadron happened on the night of 23 October when Lts Kelton and Johnson were on alert when a report came in that enemy [[Gotha]] bombers were over [[Bar-le-Duc]].  Immediately, both pilots took off to intercept the enemy aircraft.  Kelton reported that he observed searchlights in the Bar-le-Duc area performing sweeps to locate the enemy aircraft.  He saw one bomber and fired a burst of 20 shots that struck the aircraft.   He then saw another enemy aircraft that he fired a burst of 10 shots at.   He observed Anti-Aircraft fire and searchlights in the sky and saw tracer bullets being fired into the air.   He fired at long range at the aircraft but the results were unobserved.    It was later learned that Kelton and Johnson frightened away the enemy aircraft by their unexpected appearance before dropping all of their bombs.   They later jettisoned the remainder of their bombs in an open countryside area as they returned to their lines.   Although the 185th did not shoot down any of the aircraft,  by disrupting their mission, a symbolic victory was achieved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

One pilot was killed in an aircraft accident, Lt Ewing on 28 October.   His plane caught on fire and crashed 500 yards southwest of Rembercourt due to a malfunctioning altimeter. Lieutenant Kelton went missing on the 30th. He was on a strafing mission in enemy territory and was shot down.  Taken POW, he escaped and walked back to the unit arriving one month later. &lt;ref&gt;Over the Front 22 #3 2007 “185th Aero - A shadow in the moonlight”&lt;/ref&gt;  

Active operations of the squadron ended on 11 November with the signing of the Armistice with Germany.

===Demobilization===
Daylight Proficiency flights were conducted after the Armistice with Germany, however, no flights were permitted to be flown over German-controlled territory. The squadron remained at Rembercourt for about a month.   On 11 December 1918 orders were received from First Army for the squadron to report to the 1st Air Depot, [[Colombey-les-Belles Airdrome]] to turn in all of its supplies and equipment and was relieved from duty with the AEF. The squadron's Sopwith aircraft were delivered to the Air Service American Air Service Acceptance Park No. 1 at [[Orly Air Base|Orly Aerodrome]] to be returned to the British.  There practically all of the pilots and observers were detached from the Squadron. &lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell2&quot;&gt;Series &quot;E&quot;, Volume 27, Supplemental History of the 10th–636th Squadrons. Gorrell's History of the American Expeditionary Forces Air Service, 1917–1919, National Archives, Washington, D.C.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the organization's stay at Colombey, the men attended to the usual camp duties. Personnel at Colombey were subsequently assigned to the Commanding General, Services of Supply and ordered to report to one of several staging camps in France.  There, personnel awaited scheduling to report to one of the Base Ports in France for transport to the United States and subsequent demobilization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Demob&quot;&gt;Series &quot;D&quot;, Weekly Statistical Reports of Air Service Activities, October 1918 – May 1919. Gorrell's History of the American Expeditionary Forces Air Service, 1917–1919, National Archives, Washington, D.C.&lt;/ref&gt;  On 6 May 1919, the 185th was moved to Base Station #5 near the port of [[Brest, France|Brest]] prior to its return to the United States.  Upon arrival the men were caught up on any back pay owed to them, de-loused, a formal military records review was performed and a passenger list was created prior to the men boarding a ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell2&quot;/&gt;

On 1 June 1919, the 185th Aero Squadron boarded a troop ship and sailed for New York Harbor, arriving on the 28th. It proceeded to Mitchel Field, Long Island on 15 June where the personnel of the squadron were demobilized and returned to civilian life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell2&quot;/&gt;

===Lineage===
* Organized as '''185th Aero Squadron''', on 11 November 1917
: Re-designated: '''185th Aero Squadron (Night Pursuit)''', on 10 October 1918
: Demobilized on 30 June 1919.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;

===Assignments===
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* Post Headquarters, Kelly Field, 11 November 1917
* Aviation Concentration Center, 20 January 1918
* Port of Entry, [[Hoboken, New Jersey]]
:: Overseas transport, ''[[RMS Adriatic]]'', 28 January-16 February 1918
* Air Service Headquarters, AEF, British Isles
: Detached to the [[Royal Flying Corps]] for training, 28 February-12 August 1918
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* Air Service Replacement Concentration Barracks, AEF, France, 16 August 1918
* 1st Air Depot, 23 October 1918
* [[1st Pursuit Group]], 10 October 1918
* 1st Air Depot, 11 December 1918
* Commanding General, Services of Supply, 6–19 February 1919
* Post Headquarters, Mitchel Field, 15–30 June 1919&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;
{{col-end}}

===Stations===
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* [[Kelly Field]], Texas, 11 November 1917
* [[Aviation Concentration Center]], Garden City, New York, 20 January 1918
* [[Liverpool]], England, 16 February 1918
* Romney Rest Camp, [[Winchester]], England, 17 February 1918
: Squadron divided into flights,  being assigned to [[RFC Hooton Park]] and [[RFC Ternhill]]
: Squadron re-assembled at RFC Hooton, April 1918
* Flower Down Rest Camp, Winchester, England, 7 August 1918
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* American Rest Camp #2, [[Le Havre]], France, 11 August 1918
* [[St. Maixent Replacement Barracks]], France, 16 August 1918
* [[Colombey-les-Belles Airdrome]], 23 August 1918
* [[Rembercourt Aerodrome]], 10 October 1918
* Colombey-les-Belles Airdrome, 11 December 1918
* [[Brest, France]], 6 May 1919
* [[Mitchel Field]], New York, 15–30 1919&lt;ref name=&quot;Gorrell&quot;/&gt;
{{col-end}}

===Combat sectors and campaigns===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#efefef&quot;
! Streamer !! Sector/Campaign !! Dates !! Notes
|-
| [[File:Streamer MEUSE-ARGONNE 1918 ARMY.png|250px]]
| Meuse-Argonne Offensive Campaign
| 26 September-11 November 1918
| &lt;ref name=&quot;USWD&quot;&gt;United States War Department (1920), Battle Participation of Organizations of the American Expeditionary Forces in France, Belgium and Italy, 1917–1919, Washington, Government Printing Office, 1920&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Notable personnel===
* Lt. Elihu H. Kelten, [[Citation Star|Silver Star Citation]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.militarytimes.com/citations-medals-awards/search.php?term=185th+Aero+Squadron Military Times Hall of Valor Search, 185th Aero Squadron]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Organization of the Air Service of the American Expeditionary Force]]
* [[List of American Aero Squadrons]]

==References==
{{Portal|United States Air Force|Military of the United States|World War I}}
{{Air Force Historical Research Agency}}
{{Reflist}}
{{refbegin}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|185th Aero Squadron}}
{{US Air Force navbox}}
{{Wwi-air}}

[[Category:20th-century military history of the United States]]
[[Category:Aviation units and formations of the United States in World War I]]</text>
      <sha1>qfcx3gbk0npl1rzjsea8s6jk334xswb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
