<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>190th Fighter Squadron, Blues and Royals friendly fire incident</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9390792</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738523379</id>
      <parentid>724474037</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-09T13:26:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26914">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict= 190th Fighter Squadron, Blues and Royals friendly fire incident
|image=[[File:Thunderbolt II flight above.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Two [[Fairchild Republic A-10 Thunderbolt II|A-10 Thunderbolt]] jets
|date=28 March 2003
|place=[[Iraq]]
|casus=
|result=Two United Kingdom [[FV107 Scimitar]]s destroyed,&lt;br&gt;1 British soldier killed,&lt;br&gt;5 British soldiers wounded
|combatant1= {{flagicon|United States}} [[United States]] 
|combatant2= {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]] 
|strength1= 2 A-10 attack aircraft
|strength2= two [[FV107 Scimitar]]s&lt;br&gt; two [[FV103 Spartan]]s&lt;br&gt; Infantry
|casualties1=
|casualties2=2 armoured reconnaissance vehicles destroyed,&lt;br&gt;1 soldier killed,&lt;br&gt;5 wounded 
}} 
The '''190th Fighter Squadron, Blues and Royals friendly fire incident''' was a [[friendly fire]] incident involving two [[United States Air Force]] (USAF) [[Air National Guard]] [[190th Fighter Squadron]] attack aircraft, and vehicles from the United Kingdom's D Squadron, The [[Blues and Royals]] of the [[Household Cavalry]], and took place on 28 March 2003 during the invasion of Iraq by armed forces of the United States and United Kingdom.  In the incident, the two USAF A-10s fired on and destroyed two Blues and Royals armored vehicles, killing one British soldier, and injuring five others.

Although not the only fratricide incident during the invasion, the circumstances of the inquest into the death of British [[Lance-Corporal of Horse]] Matty Hull – and the subsequent verdict of [[unlawful killing]] – led to much media controversy in the UK. This was related to the release of video evidence from the attacking aircraft, and perceived levels of cooperation by government agencies of both the United States and United Kingdom with the British inquest.

==Operation Telic – 28 March 2003==
{|align=right
|{{Wikisource|Transcript of the 'friendly fire' incident video (28 March 2003)|Transcript of the 'friendly fire' incident video}}
|-
|{{Listen|filename=Friendly Fire Iraq.ogg|title=View from the A-10|description=Video of 28 March 2003 'friendly fire' incident – 40MB|format=[[Ogg]]}}
|-
|{{Listen|filename=Friendly Fire Iraq (audio).ogg|title=Audio from the A-10s|description=Audio of 28 March 2003 'friendly fire' incident – 5.8MB|format=[[Ogg]]}}
|}
The Blues and Royals were serving as an armoured reconnaissance element for [[16th Air Assault Brigade]].  Four vehicles from D Squadron, two [[FV107 Scimitar]]s and two [[FV103 Spartan]]s, were moving north of the main force, patrolling the [[Forward Edge of Battle Area]].  The area of the patrol had been declared as a ''no engagement zone'' to the allied forces and the vehicles were marked with the agreed coalition [[Combat Identification]] markings including orange overhead canvas panels, thermal reflectors and [[Union Flag]]s.

Two [[A-10 Thunderbolt II]] aircraft of the [[Idaho Air National Guard]], [[190th Fighter Squadron]] were completing a two-hour mission; engaging artillery and rocket launchers of Iraq's [[6th Division (Iraq)|6th Armoured Division]], dug in {{convert|25|mi|km}} north of [[Basra]].  The aircraft were guided to their targets by US Marine Corps [[forward air control]]lers, embedded with British ground units, and flown by a major and [[lieutenant colonel]] on their first operational flight of the invasion.  According to media reporting of the subsequent investigation, the flight was commanded by the major.&lt;ref name=&quot;politics.guardian.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://politics.guardian.co.uk/iraq/story/0,,2003887,00.html | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Coroner demands explanation in 'friendly fire' death | date=1 February 2007 | accessdate=1 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From an altitude of {{convert|12000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, the aircraft spotted Iraqi vehicles 800 yards north, and the British patrol less than three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) west. Following dialogue with the FAC and between the aircrew, the British convoy was engaged by the A-10s in a gun and rocket attack which left the vehicles disabled.  The British soldiers exited the vehicles, taking cover underneath the hulls.  The aircraft conducted a second attack, resulting in the death of L/CoH Hull, still within his Scimitar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2007/feb/04/iraq.military |title=Why won't the US tell us how Matty died?| newspaper=[[The Guardian]] | location=London| first=Mark | last=Townsend|date=4 February 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130831020847/http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2007/feb/04/iraq.military|archivedate=31 August 2013 |dead-url=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Trooper [[Christopher Finney]], 18, driving the lead Scimitar&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-432598/U-S-warplanes-hit-tank-convoy-says-soldier.html | location=London | work=Daily Mail | title=U.S. warplanes hit our tank convoy, says soldier | date=30 January 2007| accessdate= 22 August 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; re-entered his burning vehicle calling a [[Mayday (distress signal)|Mayday]] report on his still-functional radio.  Trooper Finney then dragged a badly wounded L/Cpl Tudball from the burning vehicle before attempting to recover Hull in the second Scimitar, but being beaten back by exploding [[munitions]] and heat.  For his actions, Trooper Finney was later awarded the [[George Cross]], the highest award for gallantry &quot;not in the face of the enemy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/3518887.stm | work=BBC News | title=Teenage hero gets bravery medal | date=25 February 2004 | accessdate=12 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As well as the death of Hull, a further five soldiers were injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.strategypage.com/militaryforums/567-6256.aspx |title=Soldier tells how he tried to rescue colleague |work=The Daily Telegraph |location=London |date=31 January 2007 |first=Stewart |last=Payne| accessdate= 21 April 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Boards of inquiry==

The [[US Air Force]] conducted an investigation into the incident in 2003, but the results of that investigation were not publicly released, and did not result in a court-martial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory?id=2852243&amp;page=2|title=International News - World News - ABC News|author=ABC News|work=ABC News|accessdate=21 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent reporting of the US Air Force investigation states that the investigation found fault with both pilots' actions in the incident, including, &quot;findings of cognitive and physical task overload, ineffective communication and failure to recognise identification panels by the two pilots.&quot;  The investigation report recommended administrative or disciplinary action against both pilots.  Higher [[United States Department of Defense]] officials, however, cleared both pilots of any wrongdoing.&lt;ref&gt;Dunn, Tom Newton, &quot;Pilots in court martial cover-up,&quot; ''The Sun'', 9 February 2007, [http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007060633,00.html].&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[British Army]] Board of Inquiry (BoI) was held in 2004, the findings of which, among others, stated that the major authorised the lieutenant colonel to attack, but no authorisation was given by controllers on the ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;politics.guardian.co.uk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;British Army, ''Board of Inquiry Report'', p. 5-2.&lt;/ref&gt; The report was released to the family of Lance Corporal Hull and later to the public. It has been alleged that certain [[Classified information in the United States#Secret|classified]] material available to the BoI was withheld from the family.

==Inquest into the death of L/CoH Hull==
[[File:FV107 CVR(T) Scimitar.png|200px|thumb|[[FV107 Scimitar]] armoured reconnaissance vehicle]]
At the time, the bodies of those service personnel dying overseas were repatriated to the UK via [[RAF Brize Norton]], leading to the responsibility for inquests being under the civilian jurisdiction of the [[Oxfordshire]] [[coroner]].  An inquest into the death of L/CoH Hull was convened in 2006, presided over by Assistant Deputy Coroner [[Andrew Walker (barrister)|Andrew Walker]].

===Discussion prior to the inquest===

The stated position of the United States government is that US servicemen do not attend non-US courts,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=29 August 2007 | accessdate=14 November 2007 | title=US will never let 'friendly-fire' witnesses go to a British court | url = http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article2343930.ece | publisher= The Times | location=London | first=Frances | last=Gibb}}&lt;/ref&gt; with written statements normally being provided.

British media reported that the UK government had pressured the US government, via the US embassy in London, to release all evidence related to the incident.  A meeting between Constitutional Affairs Minister [[Harriet Harman]] and Deputy Head of Mission, David Johnson, was reported on 20 November 2006&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://politics.guardian.co.uk/iraq/story/0,,1952821,00.html | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Washington to hear of UK 'friendly fire' concerns | date=20 November 2006 | accessdate=1 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; where assurances were given that concerns of the UK government over the US policy on attendance were to be relayed to Washington.

Harman reiterated this position on 1 February 2007, highlighting the request for evidence and indicating that the US personnel could not be compelled to attend the inquest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/tm_headline=someone-is-going-to-jail-for-this---&amp;method=full&amp;objectid=18558731&amp;siteid=94762-name_page.html|title='FRIENDLY FIRE FILM' DAMNS USA PILOTS|author=Don Mackay|date=1 February 2007|work=mirror|accessdate=21 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conduct of the inquest===
[[File:MattyHull.jpg|150px|thumb|left|Matty Hull (1976–2003)]]
The inquest took oral testimony from the various British personnel associated with the incident, including those in the convoy, and a FAC who expressed the opinion that the aircrew were acting independently.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6318565.stm | work=BBC News | title='Friendly fire' Iraq video found | date=31 January 2007 | accessdate=1 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Walker commented on the actions of L/Cpl Finney GC, stating: ''“You are a brave man. You are to be commended for what you did.”''&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph.co.uk&quot;/&gt;

It was publicly acknowledged during the inquest that a cockpit video of the [[head-up display]] from one of the aircraft existed, which media reports indicated had been shown to the BoI,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/world/archives/2007/02/04/2003347637|title=Widow of friendly-fire accident victim condemns US over lack of cooperation|publisher=|accessdate=21 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; but not released to Hull's family with the findings.

The video was shown to the coroner in private, although permission to use it in public was refused by the Ministry of Defence, citing international agreements related to the release of classified information, and the US classification of the tape as [[Classified information in the United States#Secret|secret]].  This adherence to international protocols led to significant criticism in the British media, leading to a public statement by Armed Forces Minister [[Adam Ingram (Labour politician)|Adam Ingram]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/DefencePolicyAndBusiness/DefenceNewsDaily.htm Ministry of Defence | Defence News | DEFENCE NEWS DAILY]&lt;/ref&gt; which reiterated the requirement for US de-classification of the video and highlighting ongoing engagement to achieve that.

Media reporting indicated that the MOD had previously denied the existence of the video.{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}

On 2 February 2007 Walker opted to adjourn the inquest until the video could be displayed in open court.

===Unauthorised leak and subsequent de-classification of video evidence===
The video was leaked to ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]'' [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|tabloid]] newspaper, and reported on 6 February 2007, as well as published on the newspaper's website.&lt;ref name=&quot;thesun.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007060133,00.html | location=London | work=The Sun | title=Joy at direct hit turns to horror | date=10 May 2007 | deadurl=yes| accessdate= 8 February 2007 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The newspaper indicated that the leak had come from a US military source.  The US government subsequently announced that the video would be declassified, but noted that the leak was likely to be a criminal offence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=fire' video will go to UK coroner |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/europe/02/06/iraq.video/index.html |work=CNN |deadurl=yes |accessdate=8 February 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070207235200/http://edition.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/europe/02/06/iraq.video/index.html |archivedate=7 February 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The video released was 19 minutes long, and was accompanied with recordings of cockpit audio and radio communications.

British media allege six errors on the part of the aircrew:&lt;ref name=&quot;thesun.co.uk&quot;/&gt;
[[File:190thKohntopp.jpg|150px|thumb|right|Gus Kohntopp, identified as POPOV36.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| last = Vincelli
| first = Tony
| year = 2006
| url = http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?storyID=123024809
| title = Air Guard pilots train in escape, evasion
| format =
| work = Air Force Link
| accessdate = 7 February 2007
| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070214210320/http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?storyID=123024809| archivedate= 14 February 2007 | deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

# The pilots asked the Forward Air Controller (&quot;Manila Hotel&quot;) if friendly forces were around the Iraqi vehicles – not to the west.
# Neither pilot gave the precise grid references for the Household Cavalry patrol to double check its identity.
# The pilots convinced themselves that the orange identification panels were in fact orange rocket launchers.
# POPOV36 decided to attack, saying he is &quot;rolling in&quot; without permission from the [[Forward Air Controller]].
# POPOV35 asked for artillery to fire a marker round into the target area to clear up confusion, but POPOV36 attacked without waiting for it.
# POPOV36 strafed the column for a second time, but still doubted its identity.

The audio track includes debate over the identity of the targets and the order, from the FAC, to disengage identifying a likely &quot;[[blue-on-blue]]&quot; incident.  The audio track also includes notification of one death and several injuries with the order to return to base.&lt;ref&gt;Jordan, Mary, &quot; 'I Think They're Rocket Launchers'&quot;, ''The Washington Post'', 7 February 2007, [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/02/06/AR2007020600206.html?nav=rss_world].&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent audio indicates frustration and crying with the comment: &quot;We're in jail, dude&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6334769.stm | work=BBC News | title=US 'to release cockpit footage' | date=6 February 2007 | accessdate=1 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon viewing the video, Matty Hull's widow, Susan, stated that the pilots were, &quot;more concerned for themselves than their victims&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Manchester Evening News'', &quot;Anguish of 'friendly-fire' soldier's widow,&quot; 7 February 2007, [http://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/s/235/235423_anguish_of_friendlyfire_soldiers_widow.html?rss=yes].&lt;/ref&gt;

A statement released by the Oxfordshire coroner's office later confirmed that Walker was of the view that, being in the public domain, the video could now be presented as evidence without the approval of the US government, and that the inquest would resume on 12 March 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/iraq/article1339175.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=Pentagon backs down on friendly fire video | first=David | last=Byers | date=6 February 2007 | accessdate=1 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 February 2007 the ''Sun'' named POPOV36 as Colonel Gus Kohntopp, a commercial pilot for [[Southwest Airlines]] and member of the [[Idaho Air National Guard]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2007060452,00.html | location=London | work=The Sun | title=The Sun Online – The Best for News, Sport and Showbiz – The Sun | deadurl=yes| accessdate= 8 February 2007 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6341055.stm | work=BBC News | title=Friendly fire pilot 'experienced' | date=8 February 2007 | accessdate=1 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mundt, Peter, &quot;From Stealth to Southwest Airlines&quot; ''Pearls &amp; Rubies'', Fall, 2005 (Year 100, No. 3), p. 12-13, [https://web.archive.org/web/20060507052926/http://www.farmhouse.org/p&amp;r/P&amp;R_v100_i3.pdf].&lt;/ref&gt; The British inquest was set to resume on 12 March 2007.  As of 9 February 2007, Kohntopp was reported to be, &quot;in hiding.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Emily, &quot;It wasn't my fault,&quot; ''The Sun'', 9 February 2007, [http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007060633,00.html].&lt;/ref&gt; He had previously been &quot;hailed as [a] hero&quot; by his neighbors in Boise, Idaho.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/17532/Friendly-fire-pilot-hailed-as-hero.html|title=The Sun|publisher=|accessdate=21 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Inquest reconvened===
The Oxfordshire inquest resumed as scheduled on 12 March with testimony from a British Forward Air Controller (FAC) involved in the incident, who stated that the incident wouldn't have happened if the two U.S. pilots involved had followed the same procedures that UK pilots must follow in the same type of situation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007110670,00.html ''The Sun'', &quot;US bombing rules rapped,&quot; (12 March 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 March, the same British FAC testified that POPOV36 committed a &quot;catalogue of serious failures&quot; when he shot at the British vehicles in the incident, including &quot;ignoring crucial warning signs, attacking without permission, and failing to wait for an artillery shell marker on a proposed target.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dunn, Tom Newton, &quot;Matt killed by 'serious failures',&quot; ''The Sun'', (14 March 2007), [http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007120133,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt; After the inquest revealed that portions of relevant evidence from the U.S. investigation into the incident were blacked out in the copy of the report given to the inquest, Matty Hull's widow made a personal appeal to U.S. president [[George W. Bush]] for the information to be released to the inquest.&lt;ref&gt;Online Reporter, &quot;Widow's plea to President,&quot; ''The Sun'', (15 March 2007), [http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007120412,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Inquest verdict ===

On 16 March, coroner Andrew Walker returned a narrative verdict, stating that the killing of Hull was &quot;[[Unlawful killing|unlawful]]&quot;. Walker said: &quot;The attack on the convoy amounted to an assault. It was unlawful because there was no lawful reason for it and in that respect it was criminal.&quot;  Neither of the two U.S. pilots involved nor any other representative from the U.S. government appeared at the inquest, despite numerous requests from Walker, Harman, and Hull's family to do so.&lt;ref&gt;''BBC News'', &quot;'Friendly fire' killing unlawful&quot;, (16 March 2007) [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6449227.stm] and Bell, Pete, &quot;Verdict: Matty's death 'criminal',&quot; ''The Sun'', (16 March 2007), [http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007120545,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research focused on the incident===

As the only case where video of an incident of fratricide or 'friendly fire' has become publicly available, the case has attracted a great deal of interest among researchers interested in exploring the question of why such incidents occur and what might be done about them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Masys|first1=A.J.|title=Pilot Error: Dispelling the Hegemony of Blamism – A Case of De-Centered Causality and Hardwired Politics|journal=Disaster Prevention and Management|volume=17|issue=2|pages=221–31|doi=10.1108/09653560810872523}}&lt;!--|accessdate=25 February 2016--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Nevile|first1=M.|title=&quot;You Are Well Clear of Friendlies&quot;: Diagnostic Error and Cooperative Work in an Iraq War Friendly Fire Incident|journal=Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)|volume=18|issue=2/3|pages=147–173|doi=10.1007/s10606-008-9089-0}}&lt;!--|accessdate=25 February 2016--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Poteet|first1=S.|last2=Giammanco|first2=C.|last3=Patel|first3=J.|last4=Kao|first4=A.|last5=Xue|first5=P.|last6=Whiteley|first6=I|title=Miscommunications and Context Awareness|journal=Proceedings of the 3rd Annual Conference of the International Technology Alliance (ACITA’09)|date=2009|url=https://www.usukitacs.com/papers/5234/ACITA2009_Miscommunication_submitted_revised.pdf|accessdate=25 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Cadell|first1=J.W.|title=Targeting-Error Fratricide in Modern Airpower: A Causal Examination|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10822/553459|website=Georgetown University Repository|publisher=Georgetown University|accessdate=25 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Howe|first1=S.|last2=Poteet|first2=S.|last3=Xue|first3=P.|last4=Kao|first4=A.|last5=Giammanco|first5=C.|title=Shared Context-Awareness: Minimizing and Resolving Miscommunication during Coalition Operations|journal=Proceedings of the 4th Annual Conference of the International Technology Alliance|date=2010|url=https://www.usukita.org/papers/6044/TA4_08_Howe_shared_context_awareness.pdf|accessdate=25 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Masys|first1=A.J.|title=Fratricide in Air Operations, Opening the Black Box: Revealing the Social|url=http://hdl.handle.net/2381/8324|website=University of Leicester Repository|publisher=University of Leicester|accessdate=25 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kirke|first1=C.|title=Fratricide in Battle: (Un)Friendly Fire|date=2012|publisher=Continuum|location=London|isbn=9781441161642|url=http://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/fratricide-in-battle-9781441161642/|accessdate=25 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mair|first1=M.|last2=Watson|first2=P.G.|last3=Elsey|first3=C.|last4=Smith|first4=P.V.|title=War-Making and Sense-Making: Some Technical Reflections on an Instance of 'Friendly Fire'|journal=British Journal of Sociology|date=2012|volume=63|issue=1|pages=75–96|doi=10.1111/j.1468-4446.2011.01394.x|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1468-4446.2011.01394.x/full|accessdate=25 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mair|first1=M.|last2=Elsey|first2=C.|last3=Watson|first3=P.G.|last4=Smith|first4=P.V.|title=Interpretive Asymmetry, Retrospective Inquiry and the Explication of Action in an Incident of Friendly Fire|journal=Symbolic Interaction|date=2013|volume=36|issue=4|pages=398–416|doi=10.1002/symb.78|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/symb.78/abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Nevile|authorlink1=M.|editor1-last=De Rycker|editor1-first=A.|editor2-last=Mohd Don|editor2-first=Z.|title=Collaboration in Crisis: Pursuing Perception through Multiple Descriptions (How Friendly Vehicles became Damn Rocket Launchers)|date=2013|publisher=John Benjamins|location=Amsterdam|isbn=9789027206435|pages=159–183|url=https://benjamins.com/#catalog/books/dapsac.52.05nev/details}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Nevile|first1=M|editor1-last=Haddington|editor1-first=P.|editor2-last=Mondada|editor2-first=L.|editor3-last=Nevile|editor3-first=M.|editor1-link=Interaction and Mobility: Language and the Body in Motion|title=Seeing on the Move: Mobile Collaboration on the Battlefield|date=2013|publisher=Walter de Gruyter|location=Berlin|pages=152–176}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Liverpool&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Mair|first1=M.|last2=Elsey|first2=C.|last3=Smith|first3=P.V.|last4=Watson|first4=P.G.|title=190th Fighter Squadron/Blues and Royals Fratricide: Modified Incident Transcript|url=http://repository.liv.ac.uk/2005800/|website=University of Liverpool Repository|publisher=University of Liverpool|accessdate=25 February 2016|date=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Elsey|first1=C.|last2=Mair|first2=M.|last3=Smith|first3=P.V.|last4=Watson|first4=P.G.|editor1-last=Jenkings|editor1-first=K.N.|editor2-last=Williams|editor2-first=A.|editor3-last=Woodward|editor3-first=R.|editor4-last=Rech|editor4-first=M.|title=The Routledge Companion to Military Research Methods|date=2016|publisher=Routledge|location=Abingdon|url=https://www.routledge.com/products/9781472442758|chapter=Ethnomethodology, Conversation Analysis and the Study of Action-in-Interaction in Military Settings}}&lt;/ref&gt; Drawing on the sociological research traditions of ethnomethodology and conversation analysis, the work of Nevile and the work of Elsey, Mair, Smith and Watson, among these, has offered detailed accounts of how the incident unfolded in real-time as well as how it was subsequently investigated by the various military and non-military inquiries after-the-fact. In the course of their research,  Elsey, Mair, Smith and Watson developed an alternative version of the transcript, based in part on the detailed information released in the USAF Friendly Fire Investigation Board Report,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=United States Air Force|title=Investigation of a Suspected Friendly Fire Incident Involving an A10 and a United Kingdom (UK) Reconnaissance Patrol near Ad Dayr, Iraq, Operation Iraqi Freedom, 28 March 2003|date=2003|publisher=United States Central Command, Office of the Commander in Chief|location=Macdill Airforce Base, FL}}&lt;/ref&gt; to make it easier to follow the incident’s interactional dynamics. The transcript is available open access.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Liverpool&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of post-1945 U.S. friendly-fire incidents with British victims]]

==References==

===Notes===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Web===
* {{cite web
| last = British Army
| first =
| year = 2005
| url = http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/887DE696-1DB9-4512-AF8E-2ECFED455356/0/boi_lcpl_hull.pdf
| title = Board of Inquiry Report into the Death of the Late 25035018 Lance Corporal of Horse Matthew Richard Hull
| format = PDF
| work = Official British investigation of the incident
| accessdate = 16 February 2007
| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070214003804/http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/887DE696-1DB9-4512-AF8E-2ECFED455356/0/boi_lcpl_hull.pdf| archivedate= 14 February 2007 | deadurl= no}}
{{Coord|33.054716|N|43.022461|E|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:190th Fighter Squadron, Blues And Royals Friendly Fire Incident}}
[[Category:21st-century history of the British Army]]
[[Category:21st-century military history of the United States]]
[[Category:Accidents and incidents involving United States Air Force aircraft]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 2003]]
[[Category:Friendly fire incidents]]
[[Category:Household Cavalry]]
[[Category:Iraq War legal issues]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>o8ih923b1eldcyrg2ndq5m2vp4rw2i5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
