<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>4th Brigade (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6328968</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738402158</id>
      <parentid>733322393</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-08T19:05:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28183">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=4th Brigade
|image=[[File:Australian 4th brigade formation graphic.PNG|100px]]
|caption=
|dates=1914–19&lt;br&gt;1921–present
|country={{flag|Australia|23px}}
|allegiance=[[Monarchy of Australia|HM Queen Elizabeth II]]
|branch=[[Australian Army]]
|type=
|role=
|size=200 (Active)&lt;br&gt;2,100 (Reserve)&lt;br&gt;40 (Civilian)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Australian Army. Modernisation from Beersheba and Beyond|publisher=Commonwealth of Australia|page=5|url=http://www.army.gov.au/~/media/Content/Our%20future/About/Army%20101%20Brief%20Ver%207%20-%20Modernising%20from%20Beersheba%20and%20Beyond%20v4.pdf|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150326190445/http://army.gov.au/~/media/Content/Our%20future/About/Army%20101%20Brief%20Ver%207%20-%20Modernising%20from%20Beersheba%20and%20Beyond%20v4.pdf|accessdate=4 December 2014|archivedate=26 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|command_structure=[[2nd Division (Australia)|2nd Division]]
|current_commander= Brigadier David Westphalen
|garrison=[[Melbourne]]
|ceremonial_chief=
|ceremonial_chief_label=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|identification_symbol=[[File:4 Bde HQ Unit Colour Patch.PNG|70px]]
|identification_symbol_label=[[Unit Colour Patch]]
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=World War I &lt;br&gt;
*[[Gallipoli campaign]]
*[[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]
World War II
*[[New Guinea campaign]]
*[[New Britain campaign]]
|notable_commanders= General Sir [[John Monash]]&lt;br&gt;
Hon. Major General [[Greg Garde]] AO, RFD, QC&lt;br&gt;
Major General Jim E. Barry, AM, MBE, RFD, ED &lt;br&gt;
Brigadier Robert Marsh, RFD – now Director-General Reserves
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
}}
The '''4th Brigade''' is a [[brigade]]-level formation of the [[Australian Army]]. Originally formed in September 1914 for service during World War I, elements of the brigade served at [[Gallipoli campaign|Gallipoli]] and in the trenches on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] before being disbanded in 1919. In 1921, the brigade was re-raised as a unit of Australia's part-time military forces, based in the state of [[Victoria, Australia|Victoria]]. During World War II the brigade served in the [[New Guinea campaign|New Guinea]] and [[New Britain campaign]]s. Following the war, the brigade formed part of the [[3rd Division (Australia)|3rd Division]], however, it was later reallocated to the [[2nd Division (Australia)|2nd Division]], where it serves as a [[Australian Army Reserve|Reserve]] combined-arms formation including units and personnel from all corps of the Army including armoured, infantry, artillery, engineers, signals and ordnance.

==History==

===World War I===
The 4th Brigade was originally formed in September 1914 as part of the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] (AIF), which was an all-volunteer force that was raised for service during World War I shortly after the outbreak of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; Under the command of Colonel (later General Sir) [[John Monash]], at that time the brigade consisted of four infantry battalions which were raised from all Australian states: the [[13th Battalion (Australia)|13th]] (NSW), [[14th Battalion (Australia)|14th]] (Vic), [[15th Battalion (Australia)|15th]] (Qld/Tas) and [[16th Battalion (Australia)|16th Battalions]] (SA/WA).&lt;ref name=AWM&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11200.asp|title=13th Battalion, First World War|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=6 June 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090614114852/http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11200.asp| archivedate= 14 June 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:4th Australian Brigade at the rear of Quinn's Post.jpg|thumb|left|4th Brigade soldiers at Quinn's Post, May 1915]]

Following initial training at [[Broadmeadows, Victoria|Broadmeadows]] in Victoria, they embarked for overseas in the second wave of Australian forces to be dispatched, leaving in December 1914.&lt;ref name=adb/&gt; They arrived in [[Egypt]] in early 1915, where they were assigned to the [[New Zealand and Australian Division]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; In April 1915, the brigade participated in the [[Australian and New Zealand Army Corps|ANZAC]] landing at [[Gallipoli campaign|Gallipoli]], arriving on the second day as the division's reserve,&lt;ref name=adb/&gt; before joining the eight-month campaign that followed. During the [[August Offensive]], the brigade attacked Hill 971 and then, later, [[Battle of Hill 60 (Gallipoli)|Hill 60]]. In December 1915 the decision was made to evacuate Gallipoli and subsequently the brigade was transported back to Egypt.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Following this, the AIF underwent a period of reorganisation and expansion.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, pp. 99–100.&lt;/ref&gt; As a part of this process, the 4th Brigade provided a [[en cadre|cadre]] of experienced personnel to the newly formed [[12th Brigade (Australia)|12th Brigade]].&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the brigade was reassigned to the [[4th Division (Australia)|4th Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Bean 1941, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1916, after spending a couple of months manning defences along the [[Suez Canal]], the brigade, along with the rest of the 4th Division was transferred to Europe where they joined the war on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] in France and Belgium.&lt;ref name=adb/&gt; Assigned to the front line around [[Armentières]], they undertook their first operation on 2 July, undertaking an unsuccessful raid.&lt;ref name=adb/&gt; During the next two years, the brigade rotated in and out of the line along with the rest of the 4th Division. In April 1917, the brigade took part in heavy fighting around Bullecourt where, on 11 April, they suffered heavy casualties, losing 2,339 men out of the 3,000 that were committed.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1918, the 4th Brigade was involved in significant fighting around [[Second Battle of Villers-Bretonneux|Villers-Bretonneux]], and eventually succeeded in liberating the town. The liberation was the third anniversary of [[ANZAC Day]], 25 April 1918. In commemoration of the sacrifices made by Australians, in 1926 the main street of the town was renamed &quot;Rue de Melbourne&quot;, while another was named &quot;Rue de Victoria&quot;. The school, which was damaged during the fighting, was rebuilt with donations from Victorian school children and was subsequently called &quot;Victoria School&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/in-depth/anzac-day/french-children-honour-war-debt/story-e6frgdaf-1225703311774 |title=Bound by history, French children honour their debt |author1=Wilson, Peter  |author2=Wilson, Lauren |work=The Australian |date=25 April 2009 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:13thBattalionAIF Le Verguier.jpeg|right|thumb|Men of the 4th Brigade at Le Verguier, France in 1918.]]

Later, in July, the 4th Brigade took part in the fighting around Le Hamel. The tactics used during the battle on 4 July 1918 were conceived by General [[John Monash]] and largely carried out by Australian infantrymen, along with a number of US troops. It was the scene of one of Allies greatest military victories during the war.&lt;ref&gt;Odgers 1988, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt; So great was this victory that French prime minister [[Georges Clemenceau]] came to address the Australian troops in the field: &quot;When the Australians came to France, the French people expected a great deal of you, but we did not know that from the very beginning you would astonish the whole continent&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Odgers 1994, pp. 121–122.&lt;/ref&gt; On 12 August 1918 Monash was knighted in the field by [[King George V]].&lt;ref name=adb&gt;{{Australian Dictionary of Biography |last= Serle |first= Geoffrey |authorlink= Geoffrey Serle  |year= 1986   |id=A100533b   |title= Monash, Sir John (1865–1931)   |accessdate= 12 March 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 4th Brigade remained in the front line until late September 1918,&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; taking part in the [[Hundred Days Offensive]], including the fighting on 8 August, which was later described as the &quot;Black Day&quot; by the German commander, [[Erich Ludendorff]].&lt;ref&gt;Odgers 1994, p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; In early October the rest of the [[Australian Corps]] was withdrawn from the line for rest and re-organisation in order to prepare for further operations.&lt;ref&gt;Odgers 1994, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the brigade did not take part in any further fighting before the Armistice in November 1918, after which the brigade's component infantry battalions began the demobilisation process and were eventually disbanded in 1919.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11201.asp |title=14th Battalion, First World War |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11202.asp |title=15th Battalion, First World War |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=10 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11203.asp |title=16th Battalion, First World War |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the course of the war, eight members of the brigade received the [[Victoria Cross]]. These were: [[Albert Jacka]], [[Martin O'Meara]], [[John Dwyer (VC)|John Dwyer]], [[Harry Murray]], [[Henry Dalziel]], [[Thomas Axford]], [[Maurice Buckley]] and [[Dominic McCarthy]].&lt;ref name=4bdehistory&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.gov.au/HQ4BDE/History.asp |title=History&amp;nbsp;– HQ 4th Brigade&amp;nbsp;– Forces Command |publisher=Australian Army |accessdate=11 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Inter war years===
In 1921, Australia's part-time military forces were re-organised to perpetuate the numerical designations and structure of the AIF formations that had existed during World War I.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, in May the 4th Brigade was re-raised as part of the [[Australian Army Reserve|Citizens Forces]].&lt;ref name=Palazzo63&gt;Palazzo 2002, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; Where possible the decision was made to raise the new formations in the recruiting areas from where the World War I units had drawn their personnel. Due to the fact that the 4th Brigade had consisted of battalions that had been drawn from a number of Australian states, upon re-forming when it was decided to base the brigade in Victoria—with its headquarters in [[Prahran, Victoria|Prahran]]—only one of its four component battalions had the numerical designation of units that had been assigned to the brigade previously.  The four infantry battalions that were assigned to it at this time were: the 14th, [[22nd Battalion (Australia)|22nd]], [[29th Battalion (Australia)|29th]] and [[46th Battalion (Australia)|46th Battalions]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-badges/patches/infantry.htm |title=Australian Infantry Unit Colour Patches 1921–1949 | publisher=Digger History |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070712164357/http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-badges/patches/infantry.htm |archivedate=12 July 2007 |accessdate=6 March 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade was assigned to the [[3rd Division (Australia)|3rd Division]] at this time.&lt;ref name=Palazzo63/&gt;

Initially, despite a level of [[war-weariness]] in Australia, numbers within the Citizens Force were maintained through voluntary recruitment and the [[Conscription in Australia|compulsory training scheme]], and due to strategic concerns around the expansion of Japanese naval power within the Pacific, there was a need to maintain a strong part-time military force. As a result, each infantry battalion within the brigade was able to report being at full strength, with over 1,000 men in each of the four battalions.&lt;ref name=Palazzo65_67&gt;Palazzo 2002, pp. 65–67.&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 1922 following the conclusion of the [[Washington Naval Treaty]], which theoretically resolved Australia's security concerns, the decision was made to reduce the Army's budget and reduce the authorised strength of each battalion to 409 men.&lt;ref name=Palazzo65_67/&gt;

The manpower situation grew more acute in 1929 when the [[James Scullin|Scullin]] [[Australian Labor Party|Labor]] government suspended the compulsory training scheme and replaced it with a voluntary &quot;Militia&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2001, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt; This decision, coupled with the economic downturn of the [[Great Depression]] resulted in further scarcity of recruits for the brigade's infantry battalions and, as a result, the decision was made to amalgamate two of the battalions,&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; the 22nd and the 29th, to form the [[29th/22nd Battalion (Australia)|29th/22nd Battalion]].&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2002, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the 1930s, the situation was characterised by poor attendance and limited training opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2002, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt; This resulted in further changes in the brigade's composition, and by 1934, the 14th Battalion had been reassigned to the 2nd Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Kuring 2004, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; The manpower situation, however, began to improve in 1936 and then again in 1938 when tensions in Europe increased concerns about the possibility of another war. The result of this was a concerted recruitment drive and more funding for training courses and camps, which in turn resulted in more enlistments.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2002, pp. 72–86.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the improved attendance within the 4th Brigade, 29th/22nd Battalion was split in August 1939 and the 22nd and 29th Battalions were reconstituted in their own right.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ordersofbattle.com/UnitData.aspx?UniX=6836&amp;Tab=Uhi&amp;Titl=29/22%20Infantry%20Battalion |title=29/22 Battalion |publisher=Orders of Battle.com |accessdate=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War II===
At the outbreak of World War II, the brigade was a part-time formation of the [[Australian Army Reserve|Militia]], based in Victoria.&lt;ref name=orders&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ordersofbattle.com/UnitData.aspx?UniX=6226&amp;Tab=Uhi&amp;Titl=4%20Australian%20Infantry%20Brigade |title=4 Australian Infantry Brigade |publisher=Orders of Battle.com |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the provisions of the ''Defence Act (1903)'' precluded the deployment of Militia formations outside of Australian territory to fight, the Australian government decided to raise a separate force for dispatch to Europe and the Middle East. This force was known as the [[Second Australian Imperial Force]].&lt;ref name=Grey146&gt;Grey 2008, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, it was decided that the Militia would be used to improve the country's overall readiness for war through undertaking periods of continuous training, undertaking defensive duties and managing the training of recruits called up following the re-establishment of the compulsory training scheme in January 1940.&lt;ref name=Grey146/&gt;

[[File:Australian 29th-46th Inf Bn at Guisika in November 1943 (AWM image 016298).jpg|right|thumb|Soldiers from the 29th/46th Battalion evacuate a wounded comrade following fighting around Gusika on New Guinea, November 1943]]

In September 1939, the brigade consisted of three infantry battalions—the 22nd, 29th and 46th Battalions&lt;ref name=orders2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ordersofbattle.com/UnitData.aspx?UniX=6226&amp;Tab=Sub&amp;Titl=4%20Australian%20Infantry%20Brigade |title=4 Australian Infantry Brigade: Subordinates |publisher=Orders of Battle.com |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;—and it was initially assigned to the 3rd Division.&lt;ref name=orders3&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ordersofbattle.com/UnitData.aspx?UniX=6226&amp;Tab=Sup&amp;Titl=4%20Australian%20Infantry%20Brigade |title=4 Australian Infantry Brigade: Superiors |publisher=Orders of Battle.com |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following Japan's entry into the war in December 1941, however, the 4th Brigade was mobilised for war service and raised to a higher state of training at [[Bonegilla, Victoria]].&lt;ref name=orders/&gt; In April 1942, the brigade was transferred to the [[5th Division (Australia)|5th Division]] and later,&lt;ref name=orders3/&gt; in 1943, it was deployed to [[New Guinea]], being dispatched to [[Milne Bay]] to relieve the [[7th Brigade (Australia)|7th Brigade]].&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 577.&lt;/ref&gt; Later it was amongst the first of the Militia brigades to see action against the Japanese at Guiska. At that time, the brigade consisted of the 22nd, [[29th/46th Battalion (Australia)|29th/46th]] and [[37th/52nd Battalion (Australia)|37th/52nd Infantry Battalions]].&lt;ref name=AWM2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11313.asp|title=29th/46th Battalion|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=28 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout 1943 and 1944 the brigade was transferred between the 5th and [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]] a number of times, taking part in the [[New Guinea campaign]].&lt;ref name=orders3/&gt;

In September 1944, the brigade returned to Australia for reorganisation and training before taking part in the [[New Britain campaign]]. Due to a shortage of shipping, the brigade's deployment was delayed and they did not land until January 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 251.&lt;/ref&gt; Following this, the brigade helped to undertake a containment campaign against the Japanese forces on the island until the end of the war in August 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post World War II===
In 1948, following the completion of the demobilisation process, Australia's part-time military forces were re-organised under the guise of the Citizens Military Force.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon re-formation, the 4th Brigade was assigned to the 3rd Division and consisted of three infantry battalions: the [[5th Battalion (Australia)|5th]], [[6th Battalion (Australia)|6th]] and [[8th/7th Battalion (Australia)|8th/7th]].&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2002, p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the Cold War period which followed, the composition of the brigade changed a number of times as the role of part-time military forces evolved. Initially, post war service was voluntary, however, in 1951 national service was instituted and this increased the size of the CMF units.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 205.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, due to increased manpower and resources, the brigade was able to achieve full manning and equipment scales and, as a result, in 1959, formed the basis of a 3,500-man combined arms exercise undertaken at Puckapunyal.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2002, pp. 167–168.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, the national service scheme was suspended in 1960,&lt;ref name=2div/&gt; due to the large amount of resources required to administer it.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the introduction of the [[Pentropic organisation|Pentropic divisional establishment]] saw the disbandment or amalgamation of many infantry battalions as regional-based battalions were formed into multi-battalion State-based regiments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grey 2008, p. 228&quot;&gt;Grey 2008, p. 228.&lt;/ref&gt; This saw the adoption of the five battalion division and resulted in the disbandment of the old three battalion brigade formations.&lt;ref&gt;Kuring 2004, p. 262.&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 1964, however, the decision was made to end the experiment with the Pentropic establishment,&lt;ref&gt;McNeill 1993, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; partly because of the difficulties it created with allied interoperability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grey 2008, p. 228&quot;/&gt; Early the following year the brigade formations were re-established, although they were designated &quot;task forces&quot; instead of brigades.&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy 2003, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blaxland 1989, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1976, due to limited resources and manpower the brigade's parent formation, the 3rd Division, had become a largely hollow structure. As a result, the division's headquarters were merged with the 4th Task Force's headquarters as the 3rd Division was redesignated as the &quot;3rd Division Field Force Group&quot; and the 4th Task Force ceased to exist.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2002, pp. 190–191.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 July 1981 the formation was reraised as the &quot;4th Task Force&quot;, however, in 1982 it was renamed as the &quot;4th Brigade&quot;.&lt;ref name=4bdehistory/&gt; In 1981 the brigade's infantry battalions were the 1st and 2nd Battalions, Royal Victoria Regiment (RVR).  In December 1982 the 5th/6th Battalion was raised by establishing a new BHQ and utilising some of the 1 RVR companies.  Until 1987 the Briagde had three infantry battalions, 1 RVR, 2 RVR and [[5th/6th Battalion, Royal Victoria Regiment|5/6 RVR]].  During this period 2 RVR was renamed 8/7 RVR.  In 1987 the brigade was reduced to just two infantry battalions, namely 5/6 RVR and 8/7 RVR and supporting arms.&lt;ref name=2div/&gt; In the early 1990s the brigade was assigned to the 2nd Division.&lt;ref name=2div&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/army/AHU/docs/Brief_History_of_2nd_Division.pdf|title=Brief History of the 2nd Division|publisher=Army History Unit|accessdate=7 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1991, following a force structure review, the 3rd Division was disbanded and its units were placed under the 4th Brigade's command. As a result, in the late 1990s it had a vital asset protection mobilisation role as part of the &quot;Protective Force&quot; in the Tindal area of the Northern Territory.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2002, p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current structure and recent operations==
Currently, the 4th Brigade is headquartered at [[Simpson Barracks]] in [[Melbourne]]. It consists of about 2,400 personnel, who are based in a number of locations in Melbourne and regional Victoria.&lt;ref name=media1&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.defencereserves.com/cms_resources/Boss_Lift_Media_Release.pdf |title= Press Release: Benefits of Employing Reservists Highlighted on Boss Lift to Solomon Islands |author = Mike Kelly, Parliamentary Secretary for Defence Support |publisher=Department of Defence |accessdate=11 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade currently consists of the following units:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.army.gov.au/HQ4BDE/  |title=Home&amp;nbsp;– HQ 4th Brigade&amp;nbsp;– Forces Command |publisher=Australian Army  |accessdate=11 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Headquarters 4th Brigade
*[[4th/19th Prince of Wales' Light Horse]], [[Royal Australian Armoured Corps]]
*[[5th/6th Battalion, Royal Victoria Regiment]]
*[[8th/7th Battalion, Royal Victoria Regiment]]
*[[Melbourne University Regiment]]
*[[22nd Engineer Regiment (Australia)|22nd Engineer Regiment, Royal Australian Engineers]]
*108th Signals Squadron; and
*4th Combat Service Support Battalion.
(Note – Monash University Regiment (MonUR) and the 2nd/10th Medium Regiment were removed from the Australian Army Order of Battle in 2012. The Officer Cadet Company of MUR was renamed Monash University Company, and the artillery was amalgamated with 5/6 RVR as the 2nd/10th Light Battery, which employs mortars rather than artillery.  The 4th Combat Engineer Regiment (4 CER) was removed from the Australian Army Order of Battle in 2013. 4 CER and 22nd Construction Regiment (22 Const Regt) were amalgamated in 2013 to form the 22nd Engineer Regiment (22 ER)).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.minister.defence.gov.au/2013/04/17/minister-for-defence-and-parliamentary-secretary-for-defence-ministerial-visit-for-ringwood-army-reserves/ |title=Minister for Defence and Parliamentary Secretary for Defence – Ministerial visit for Ringwood Army Reserves |publisher=Department of Defence |work=Media Release |date=17 April 2013|accessdate=3 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recently the brigade has contributed personnel to deployments in [[Iraq War|Iraq]], [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Afghanistan]], [[Operation Astute|East Timor]] and the [[Regional Assistance Mission to Solomon Islands|Solomon Islands]].&lt;ref name=media1/&gt; The current Commander, Brigadier David Westphalen is an Iraq and Afghanistan veteran.  It also continues to support Australia's commitment to [[Rifle Company Butterworth]]. Within Australia, the brigade provided engineer and logistic support during the 2003 Alpine Bushfires, the 2006 Gippsland Fires, as well as support to the community during the [[Black Saturday bushfires|2009 Victorian bushfires]] and the [[2011 Victorian floods|2011 floods]] and 2012 floods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Operation Vic Fires Assist |author =Toohill, Ian |journal=Australian Infantry Magazine |issue=Oct 2009&amp;nbsp;– April 2010 |pages=16–20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=ADF Reservists Assist SES During Flood Crisis |author =Toohill, Ian |journal=The Australian Reservist |issue=16 |date=April 2011 |pages=12–15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under [[Plan Beersheba]] currently being implemented the 4th Brigade would be paired with the reserve [[9th Brigade (Australia)|9th Brigade]] to reinforce the regular [[1st Brigade (Australia)|1st Brigade]]. In the event of the 1st Brigade being deployed, the two reserve brigades would be tasked with generating a battalion-sized [[Battlegroup (army)|battle group]]. This battle group would be called &quot;Jacka&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://armynews.realviewdigital.com/#folio=6 |title=Integrating Capability on Predators Gallop |edition=1371 |newspaper=Army: The Soldiers' Newspaper |date=21 April 2016 |pages=6&amp;ndash;7 |issn= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bean|first=Charles|title=The Australian Imperial Force in France, 1916 |series= [[Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918]]|volume=Volume III|edition=12th|year=1941|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069752/|oclc=220623454}}
*{{cite book|last=Blaxland|first=J.C.|title=Organising an Army: The Australian Experience, 1957–1965|url=http://ips.cap.anu.edu.au/publications/organising-army-australian-experience-1957-1965|year=1989|publisher=Strategic and Defence Studies Centre, the Research School of Pacific Studies, the Australian National University|location=Canberra|isbn=0-7315-0530-1}}
*{{Cite book|last=Grey |first=Jeffrey|authorlink=Jeffrey Grey |title=A Military History of Australia |edition=3rd |publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria|year=2008|series= |url= |isbn=978-0-521-69791-0}}
*{{Cite book|last=Keogh|first=Eustace|title=South West Pacific 1941–45|year=1965|publisher=Grayflower Publications|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn=|oclc=7185705}}
*{{Cite book|last=Kuring|first=Ian|title=Redcoats to Cams: A History of Australian Infantry 1788–2001|year=2004|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales|isbn=1-876439-99-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|title=The Final Campaigns|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1—Army. Volume VII|year=1963|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/|oclc=1297619}}
*{{cite book|last=McCarthy|first=Dayton|title=The Once and Future Army: A History of the Citizen Military Forces, 1947–74|year=2003|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=South Melbourne|isbn=0-19-551569-2}}
*{{cite book|last=McNeill |first=Ian |title=To Long Tan: The Australian Army and the Vietnam War 1950–1966|series=The Official History of Australia's Involvement in Southeast Asian Conflicts 1948–1975 |publisher=Allen and Unwin |location=St Leonards, New South Wales |year=1993 |edition= |isbn=1-86373-282-9}}
*{{Cite book|last=Odgers|first=George|title=Army Australia: An Illustrated History|year=1988|publisher=Child &amp; Associates|location=Frenchs Forest, New South Wales|isbn=0-86777-061-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Odgers |first=George |authorlink=George Odgers |title=Diggers: The Australian Army, Navy and Air Force in Eleven Wars |publisher=Lansdowne |location=London |year=1994 |volume=1 |isbn=978-1-86302-385-6 |oclc=31743147}}
*{{Cite book |last=Palazzo |first=Albert |title=The Australian Army. A History of its Organisation 1901–2001 |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=0-19-551507-2}}
*{{Cite book| last = Palazzo| first = Albert| year = 2002| title = Defenders of Australia: The 3rd Australian Division 1916–1991| publisher = Australian Military Historical Publications| location = Loftus, New South Wales| isbn = 1-876439-03-3}}
{{Refend}}

[[Category:Brigades of Australia]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1914]]
[[Category:1914 establishments in Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>hs4vlnoczj3v3rbsz3rapgq44wgokk5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
