<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Action of 7 February 1813</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39150006</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742426494</id>
      <parentid>740757385</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-03T17:06:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 0 sources and tagging 1 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20423">{{coord|20|23|25|S|57|44|02|E|display=title|type:event}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 7 February 1813
|partof=the [[Napoleonic Wars]]
|image=[[File:Arethuse vs Amelia-NAPB05251-b.jpg|300px|]]
|caption=''The fight of the French frigate ''Aréthuse'' and ''Amelia'' on the shores of Guinea, 7 February 1813'', after [[Louis-Philippe Crépin]].
|date=7 February 1813
|place=[[Îles de Los]], off [[Guinea]]
|result=Stalemate
|combatant1={{flagcountry|First French Empire}}
|combatant2=[[Image:Flag of the United Kingdom.svg|22px|link=|alt=]] [[United Kingdom]]
|commander1=[[Pierre François Étienne Bouvet de Maisonneuve|Pierre Bouvet]]
|commander2=[[Frederick Paul Irby]] {{WIA}}
|strength1=40-gun ''[[French frigate Aréthuse (1812)|Aréthuse]]''
|strength2=38-gun [[HMS Amelia (1796)|HMS ''Amelia'']]
|casualties1=20 killed, 88 to 98 wounded
|casualties2=46 killed, 44 wounded
}}
The '''Action of 7 February 1813''' was a naval battle between two evenly matched [[frigates]] from the [[French Navy]] and the British [[Royal Navy]], ''[[French frigate Aréthuse (1812)|Aréthuse]]'' and [[HMS Amelia (1796)|HMS ''Amelia'']]. The battle was fought in the night of 7 February 1813 at the [[Îles de Los]], off [[Guinea]]. It lasted four hours, causing significant damage and casualties to both opponents, and resulted in a stalemate. The two ships parted and returned to their respective port of call, both sides claiming victory.

==Background==
After the British victory in the [[Mauritius campaign of 1809–1811]], all French possession in the Indian Ocean were at the hands of Britain. France had already lost the use of [[Cape Town]] in 1806 after the [[Battle of Blaauwberg]], and of [[History of Jakarta|Batavia]] in 1811 with the British [[Invasion of Java (1811)|Invasion of Java]]. Thus, in 1813, the French Navy lacked the advanced bases it needed to support the [[commerce raiding]] frigate squadron that it had operated in the previous decade. It was therefore decided to send a force off the Western coast of Africa to disrupt British shipping closer to the metropole, but still far enough to be unreachable to the powerful British naval divisions that blockaded the [[English Channel]] and the [[Bay of Biscay]].

To this end, a frigate division was given to Captain [[Pierre François Étienne Bouvet de Maisonneuve|Pierre Bouvet]], a skilled frigate captain,&lt;ref group=note&gt;James ([http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_189.html p.189]) credits Bouvet as being &quot;one best officers in the French navy&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; veteran of the [[Mauritius campaign of 1809–1811|Mauritius campaign]] and who had led the French forces during the second half of the [[Battle of Grand Port]]. The squadron comprised the 40-gun frigate ''[[French frigate Aréthuse (1812)|Aréthuse]]'', under Bouvet himself, and the ''[[French frigate Rubis (1812)|Rubis]]'', under Commander [[Louis-François Ollivier]].&lt;ref name=quintin86&gt;Quintin, p.86&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fonds476&gt;Fonds Marine, p.476&lt;/ref&gt; Another two-frigate squadron, made up of ''[[French frigate Aréthuse (1805)|Elbe]]'' and ''[[French frigate Hortense (1803)|Hortense]]'', was to perform the same mission with a two-week interval.&lt;ref name=james190 /&gt;

== Cruise of Bouvet's division ==
[[File:Bouvet maisonneuve.jpg|thumb|upright|Captain [[Pierre François Étienne Bouvet de Maisonneuve|Pierre Bouvet]], who commanded the French squadron, his flag on ''Aréthuse''.]]
On 25 November 1812,&lt;ref name=quintin86 /&gt; Bouvet's division departed from Nantes, sneaked through the British blockade, and established a station to the North-East of the [[Azores]], near the group of five rocks called &quot;Vigie des Cinq Grosses-Têtes&quot;&lt;ref name=Troude171&gt;Troude, p.171&lt;/ref&gt; (44°17'N, 21°45'W&lt;ref&gt;Maiseau, p.614&lt;/ref&gt;). The frigates then continued to cruise off [[Madeira]] and [[Cape Verde]].&lt;ref name=quintin86 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Troude171 /&gt;

In the course of January, continual gale&lt;ref name=lecomte291&gt;Lecomte, p.291&lt;/ref&gt; and preliminary symptoms of a fever epidemic&lt;ref name=Troude171 /&gt; decided Bouvet sail South with two prizes, the British cutter&lt;ref name=lecomte291 /&gt; ''Hawk'',&lt;ref name=james185&gt;James, [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_185.html p.185]&lt;/ref&gt; and the other the Portuguese slave ship ''Serra'',&lt;ref name=lecomte291 /&gt; to anchor at the [[Îles de Los]], off [[Sierra Leone]].&lt;ref name=Troude171 /&gt; On 27 January, the frigates and their prizes came in view of the islands when the 16-gun [[HMS Daring (1804)|HMS ''Daring'']], under Lieutenant William Pascoe, appeared. Mistaking the French frigates for British cruisers, ''Daring'' launched a boat towards ''Rubis'', which altered her course to intercept; as the frigate approached, the boat realised her error and attempted to flee, to no avail.&lt;ref name=lecomte291 /&gt; Questioning his prisoners, Ollivier learnt the identity of his opponent, and gave chase. Hopelessly outmanned and outgunned, Pascoe threw his brig on the coast, on the North-Western point of Tamara,&lt;ref name=Troude171 /&gt; and scuttled her by fire.&lt;ref name=Troude171 /&gt;&lt;ref name=lecomte292&gt;Lecomte, p.292&lt;/ref&gt; ''Daring''{{'}}s magazines detonated at 5 in the evening, and the French frigates dropped anchor one hour later.&lt;ref name=lecomte292 /&gt;

Ashore, the French gathered fruits, resupplied their fresh water, and gathered intelligence on the British deployment: the station of Sierra Leone comprised two frigates and several corvettes, but only [[HMS Amelia (1796)|HMS ''Amelia'']] was anchored in the bay at the time.&lt;ref name=lecomte292 /&gt; After six days of repairs and resupply, ''Aréthuse'' and ''Rubis'' were ready for a six-month cruise; to unburden himself of his prisoners and prizes, Bouvet returned ''Serra'' to the Portuguese, and on 29 January,&lt;ref name=james184 /&gt; the British were released on parole and sent to Sierra-Leone on ''Hawk''. Bouvet departed on 4 February.&lt;ref name=lecomte293&gt;Lecomte, p.293&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;Troude (p.171) say on the 1st; Lecomte (293) says the 4th; Roche (p.390) dates the destruction of ''Rubis'' to the 5th, entailing that her departure was on the 4th; The ''Fonds Marine'' (p.477) concurs with Roche.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Frederick Paul Irby.jpg|thumb|upright|Frederick Paul Irby, in 1822. He commanded ''Amelia'' during the action.]]
Meanwhile, on 29 January, Lieutenant Pascoe had arrived on [[Freetown]], with some of his men, and informed ''Amelia'' of the presence of what he believed to be three French frigates at Tamara.&lt;ref name=james184 /&gt; ''Hawk'' arrived the same evening with the prisoners on parole, confirming Pascoe's account;&lt;ref name=james185 /&gt; she was then equipped with a boat from ''Amelia'' and sent for a reconnaissance of the French squadron. Having volunteered, Pascoe returned with, this time, an accurate description of the French division, including the names of the frigate and of their prize.&lt;ref name=james185 /&gt; On the 3rd, at 10:30, ''Amelia'' departed her anchorage and took the direction of île de Lot to intercept the French squadron.&lt;ref name=james185 /&gt;

At île de Lot, ''Aréthuse'' had, upon departure, maneuvered to catch the wind and struck the bottom, breaking her rudder and forcing the squadron to drop anchor on the spot.&lt;ref name=Troude171 /&gt; That very night, a violent storm broke out, and both frigates broke their cables. ''Aréthuse'' managed to avoid running aground using a makeshift rudder, and in the morning found herself drifted twelve miles to the North-West of Tamara; Bouvet dropped anchor as soon as he found the bottom to repair his rudder.&lt;ref name=Troude171 /&gt; Meanwhile, ''Rubis'' had been cast aground on the shore of Tamara.&lt;ref name=Troude172&gt;Troude, p.172&lt;/ref&gt; At ten, she fired distress shots and signals; ''Aréthuse'' launched her [[longboat]] to assist, but could not maneuver herself without her rudder;&lt;ref name=lecomte294&gt;Lecomte, p.294&lt;/ref&gt; the launch carried two additional pumps to ''Rubis'', but returned with the news that she was unsalvageable and that her crew was transferring on ''Serra''&lt;ref name=james184&gt;James, [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_184.html p.184]&lt;/ref&gt; The following night, the hull of the stranded ''Rubis'' broke under the stress of the waves.&lt;ref name=lecomte295&gt;Lecomte, p.295&lt;/ref&gt; Commander Ollivier scuttled her by fire&lt;ref name=quintin86 /&gt; and embarked his crew on ''Serra''.&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roche, p.390&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 January, around 20:00, ''Amelia'' sighted a strange sail making night signals which, the next morning, turned out to be ''Princess-Charlotte'', a government-schooner from Sierra-Leone,&lt;ref name=james185 /&gt; ''Amelia'' got sight of the French squadron half an hour later, and dispatched ''Princess-Charlotte'' to Sierra Leone to instruct any incoming  British warship to come to her aid at once. She then observed what was deemed to be a prize being unloaded into one of the frigate, but was in fact ''Rubis'' transferring her crew to ''Serra'', and the second frigate in the distance.&lt;ref name=james185 /&gt;

==Battle==
[[File:John Christian Schetky, HMS Amelia Chasing the French Frigate Aréthuse 1813 (1852).jpg|thumb|''HMS 'Amelia' chasing the French frigate 'Arethuse' 1813'', a fancifully titled representation of the early stages of the battle, by [[John Christian Schetky]], 1852. On display at [[Norwich Castle]].]]
In the morning of 6 February, while ''Aréthuse'' was completing her repairs, [[HMS Amelia (1796)|HMS ''Amelia'']] appeared under the wind. Bouvet set sails to meet her and in the evening, the frigate sailed on parallel courses;&lt;ref name=lecomte295 /&gt; As Irby was not aware of the demise of ''Rubis'', he was attempting to lure ''Aréthuse'' away from her to prevent the two French frigates from supporting each other.&lt;ref name=james186&gt;James, [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_186.html p.186]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Aréthuse'' having a slight advantage, and hoping to overhaul his opponent during the night, Bouvet hoisted the French colours and fired a carronade; ''Aréthuse'' answered by hoisting the Union Jack and firing a shot.&lt;ref name=lecomte295 /&gt;

At dawn, a fog obscured the frigates from each other, and Bouvet could not engage. The next morning, ''Aréthuse'' found herself alone on the sea, an Bouvet followed the course that he assumed ''Amelia'' had taken; around eleven, she appeared on the horizon and ''Aréthuse'' put on all sails to give chase. The frigates raced all day and at 19:30,&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt; Irby decided that he was far enough to avoid interference from ''Rubis'',&lt;ref name=james186 /&gt; and ''Amelia'' turned to confront her opponent.&lt;ref name=lecomte296&gt;Lecomte, p.296&lt;/ref&gt;

''Aréthuse'' was pierced for 44 guns, but actually mounted only 42: as her two foremost guns, obstructed by bollards, could not be maneuvered properly, Bouvet had ordered them stored in the hold.&lt;ref name=Troude173&gt;Troude, p.173&lt;/ref&gt; This left ''Aréthuse'' with twenty-six [[18-pounder long gun]]s, two [[8-pounder long gun|8-pounder]] [[chase gun]]s, and fourteen 24-pounder [[carronade]]s.&lt;ref name=Troude173 /&gt; ''Amelia'' mounted twenty-six 18-pounders and twenty 32-pounder carronades. Her crew was reinforced by that of ''Daring''.&lt;ref name=Troude173 /&gt;

The frigates closed in to pistol range without opening fire.&lt;ref name=lecomte297&gt;Lecomte, p.297&lt;/ref&gt; As they passed each other, ''Aréthuse'' came about and fired her broadside at ''Amelia'' that cut the [[Braces (sailing)|braces]] of her [[topsail]]; ''Amelia'' answered in kind, and then veered and abruptly decreased her speed, her davit touching ''Aréthuse'' at starboard.&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt; ''Aréthuse'' fired another broadside a point-blank range, and for the following hour and a half, the two frigates remained entangled, exchanging volleys,&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt; gunners from both sides snatching the ramrods of their opponents and duelling with sabres from one gunport and the other,&lt;ref name=lecomte297 /&gt; but neither side attempting to board the other.&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt;

After 90&amp;nbsp;minutes of cannonade and gunfire, Captain Irby and his two Lieutenants, John James Bates and John Pope,&lt;ref name=james187&gt;James, [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_187.html p.187]&lt;/ref&gt; were wounded. The third lieutenant, George Wells,&lt;ref name=james187 /&gt; was killed soon after taking command, and the master of ''Amelia'', Anthony De Mayne,&lt;ref name=james187 /&gt; replaced him.&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt; Then, Bouvet attempted a boarding to decide the issue, but with her clewlines cut by shots,&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt; ''Aréthuse'' could not maneuver.&lt;ref name=lecomte297 /&gt;

At 21:00, the frigates separated.&lt;ref name=lecomte298&gt;Lecomte, p.298&lt;/ref&gt; The cannonade continued until eleven, until the frigates lost contact.&lt;ref name=lecomte298 /&gt; Soon, a dense fog hid the frigates one from another, and it was not until the next morning that ''Amelia'' was spotted again. According to Bouvet's report, ''Aréthuse'' attempted to give chase, but to no avail.&lt;ref name=Troude172 /&gt;&lt;ref name=lecomte298 /&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:John Christian Schetky, HMS Amelia and the French Frigate Aréthuse in Action 1813 (1852).jpg|thumb|''HMS'' Amelia ''in action with the French Frigate ''Aréthuse'', 1813'', by [[John Christian Schetky]], 1852. This painting was originally in the possession of the family of Frederick Paul Irby, captain of HMS ''Amelia''.]]

Both captains accused the other of having fled.&lt;ref name=james187 /&gt; Irby stated that ''Aréthuse'' &quot;bore up, having the advantage of being able to do so, leaving us in an ungovernable state&quot;;&lt;ref name=james187 /&gt; while Bouvet wrote &quot;At eleven o'clock, firing ceased on both sides; we were no longer in range; and the enemy, putting on all sail, surrendered the battlefield to us&quot;.&lt;ref group=note&gt;&quot;''A onze heures, le feu cessa de part et d'autre ; nous n'étions plus à bonne portée, et l'ennemi se couvrit de voiles, nous abandonnant le champ de bataille.''&quot; Original quoted in James, p.187, with a few errors. Translation from the original. Bouvet's complete report is available at [http://www.lebardeschoufs.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=117&amp;Itemid=48 lebardeschoufs.com]{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another view is that the ships, their riggings both damaged, simply drifted away from each other under the effect of the cannonade.&lt;ref&gt;William Laid Clowes, ''The Royal Navy : a history from the earliest times to the present'', Vol V, [http://threedecks.org/index.php?display_type=show_battle&amp;id=715 p.521]&lt;/ref&gt;

''Aréthuse'' had 20 killed and 98 wounded.&lt;ref name=lecomte298 /&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;Quintin (p.86) gives a figure of 88 wounded; James (p.188) gives a somehow different figure of 31 killed and 74 wounded.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Amelia'' suffered 51 killed and 90 wounded.&lt;ref name=james188&gt;James, [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_188.html p.188]&lt;/ref&gt;

Bouvet sailed to Tamara,&lt;ref name=lecomte298 /&gt; where he rejoined ''Serra'' and the crew of ''Rubis'' on the 10th.&lt;ref name=james190&gt;James, [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_190.html p.190]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Serra'' was taken in tow for a few days before Bouvet scuttled her by fire,&lt;ref name=Troude173 /&gt; off Madeira, as she retarded ''Aréthuse''.&lt;ref name=james190 /&gt; ''Aréthuse'' returned to Saint-Malo with no further encounter,&lt;ref name=Troude173 /&gt; where she arrived on 19 April 1813. During their mission, ''Rubis'' and ''Aréthuse'' had captured ten prizes.&lt;ref name=quintin86 /&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;James ([http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_190.html p.190]) gives a figure of fifteen prizes.&lt;/ref&gt;

Irby sailed to England, where he had been bound before the battle to repatriate sick sailors.&lt;ref name=james185 /&gt; He arrived at Spithead on 22 March,&lt;ref name=james190 /&gt; carrying large quantities of gold.&lt;ref name=james189&gt;James, [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_190.html p.189]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Arethuse-2686350918.jpg|thumb|''The fight of the French frigate ''Aréthuse'' and ''Amelia'' on the shores of Guinea, 7 February 1813'', by [[Louis-Philippe Crépin]].]]
Navy Minister Decrès gave a mixed review of the events. On one hand, he praised Bouvet's bravery and conduct during the battle itself; in his report of the events, on 26 April 1813, he wrote:
{{cquote|This fight leaves well behind that of ''Belle Poule'' in 1778, that of ''Nymphe'' in 1780 and all the others, that have had more or less fame. I request from Your Majesty permission to commission on government funds a painting of this battle.&lt;ref group=note&gt;&quot;''Ce combat laisse loin derrière lui celui de la ''Belle Poule'' en 1778, celui de la ''Nymphe'' en 1780 et tous les autres, qui ont eu plus ou moins de célébrité. Je demande à Votre Majesté, la permission de faire aux frais du Gouvernement le tableau de ce combat.''&quot;Quoted in Granier, p.355&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[Louis-Philippe Crépin]] did paint a 258 by 162&amp;nbsp;cm depiction of the battle, which is currently in the collections of the Musée de Versailles.

On the other hand, Decrès sharply criticised Bouvet for the wreck of ''Rubis'' and near-loss of ''Aréthuse'' in the storm of 5 February:
{{cquote|While giving him his due for his brilliant valour and his good results, I am not allowed to hide from Your Majesty that a sailor of long experience would not have, as he did, put the two frigates in distress at the îles de Los. This opinion is not only mine, it was cast by all to whom I communicated the report.&lt;ref name=quintin86 /&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;&quot;''Tout en rendant justice à son éclatante valeur et à ses beaux résultats, il ne m'est pas permis de dissimuler à Votre Majesté qu'un marin de vieille expérience n'eût pas mis, comme il l'a fait, les deux frégates en perdition aux îles de Los. Cette opinion n'est pas seulement la mienne, elle a été émise par tous ceux à qui j'ai donné connaissance du rapport.''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Probably because of these mixed reviews, Bouvet was awarded the rank of Officer in the [[Legion of Honour]], on 2 July, but was neither promoted to rear-admiral, nor made a [[Baron of the Empire]], as had been requested in his favour.&lt;ref name=quintin87&gt;Quintin, p.87&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes and References==
{{Commons category|Paintings of the naval battle between the HMS Amelia (1796) and the French frigate Aréthuse (1812)}}

===Notes===
{{Reflist|group=note}}

===References===
{{reflist|colwidth=20em}}

===Bibliography===
*{{cite book|title=Histoire des Marins français 1789–1815|first=Hubert|last=Granier|others=illustrations by Alain Coz|publisher=Marines éditions|year=1998|isbn=2-909675-41-6}}
*[[William James (naval historian)|James, William]] (1837) ''The Naval History of Great Britain, 1793–1820'', Volume VI, R. Bentley, London.
*{{cite book|title=Chroniques de la marine française: de 1789 à 1830, d'après les documents officiels|first=Jules|last=Lecomte|publisher=H. Souverain|year=1836|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=J00U8L1g0FgC|language=French|volume=5}}
*{{Cite book|first=Raymond-Balthasar|last=Maiseau|authorlink=Raymond-Balthasar Maiseau|year=1833|publisher=|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=stjpdmth2R0C|title=Annuaire du commerce maritime|language=French}}
*{{cite book|first1=Danielle|last1=Quintin|first2=Bernard|last2=Quintin|year=2003|title=Dictionnaire des capitaines de Vaisseau de Napoléon|isbn=2-901952-42-9|publisher=S.P.M.|language=French}}
*{{cite book|first=Jean-Michel|last=Roche|year=2005|title=Dictionnaire des bâtiments de la flotte de guerre française de Colbert à nos jours|isbn=978-2-9525917-0-6|oclc=165892922|publisher=Group Retozel-Maury Millau|volume=1}}
*{{Cite book|first=Onésime-Joachim|last=Troude|authorlink=Onésime-Joachim Troude|year=1867|publisher=Challamel ainé|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zfFrDVTkcpsC|title=Batailles navales de la France|language=French|volume=4}}
*Fonds Marine. Campagnes (opérations ; divisions et stations navales ; missions diverses). Inventaire de la sous-série Marine BB4. Tome deuxième : BB4 1 à 482 (1790–1826) [http://www.servicehistorique.sga.defense.gouv.fr/contenu/module-dc/functions/dc/attached/FRSHD_PUB_00000226_dc/FRSHD_PUB_00000226_dc_att-FRSHD_PUB_00000226_02.pdf]

[[Category:1813 in France]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1813]]
[[Category:Naval battles of the Napoleonic Wars]]
[[Category:Wars involving Sierra Leone]]</text>
      <sha1>he8k3f7xk1tjybpxxx5jq632gxwopdb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
