<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Action of 12–17 January 1640</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28880821</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733339924</id>
      <parentid>700397845</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-07T03:46:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jasonanaggie</username>
        <id>11835288</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Unlinked: [[Lagunas]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9812">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 12–17 January 1640
|partof=the [[Eighty Years' War]], [[Dutch–Portuguese War]]
|image
|caption= Action of 12–17 January 1640
|date=12–17 January 1640
|place=[[Itamaracá]], off [[Pernambuco]], Brazil
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Tactically  Inconclusive
|combatant1=[[Iberian Union]]:
*{{flag|Spain|1506}}
*{{flag|Portugal|1640}}
|combatant2={{flag|United Provinces}}
|commander1=[[Fernando de Mascarenhas]]
|commander2=Willem Loos{{KIA}}
|strength1= 30 Galleons,&lt;br&gt;34 armed transports,&lt;br&gt;13 small vessels&lt;ref name=&quot;Warnsinck 146&quot;&gt;Warnsinck, 1940, p. 146&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2=  30 warships and supply ships,&lt;br&gt; 10 small vessels&lt;ref name=&quot;Warnsinck 148&quot;&gt;Warnsinck, 1940, p. 148&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1= 2 vessels lost 
|casualties2= 2 vessels &lt;ref&gt;Warnsinck, p. 152&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;or 8 vessels lost 
}}
{{Campaignbox Dutch-Portuguese War}}
{{Campaignbox Eighty Years' War}}
{{Dutch colonial campaigns}}
{{Portuguese colonial campaigns}}
The '''Action of 12–17 January 1640''' was a naval battle between a [[Netherlands|Dutch]] fleet and a combined Spanish-Portuguese fleet during the [[Eighty Years' War]]. The battle took place on the Brazilian coast off [[Pernambuco]] and was an attempt by a fleet consisting of approximately eighty vessels transporting about 5,000 soldiers under the command of Portuguese Admiral Fernando de Mascarenhas to land reinforcements to bolster the Portuguese militia besieging the city of [[Recife]]. On 12 January this fleet was intercepted by a Dutch task force of about forty ships commanded by [[Willem Loos]]. The ensuing battle lasted with occasional breaks until the evening of 17 January, when the Spanish and Portuguese fleet retreated and sailed away to the north.

==Background==
About 30 Spanish and Portuguese vessels under Admiral don [[Lope de Hoces]] arrived off the Dutch Brazil in November 1635. Although the fleet failed to overran Pernambuco, supplies and 2,500 Spanish, Portuguese, and Neapolitan reinforcements were successfully landed at the Lagunas under General [[Luis de Rojas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley123&quot;&gt;Marley, p. 123&lt;/ref&gt; The Dutch vessels in the area were driven off and De Hoces spent some months escorting a sugar convoy to the [[Spanish Main]] and preparing a counter-invasion of the Dutch-held island of [[Curaçao]] which was finally abandoned because the siege train was lost in a wreck.&lt;ref&gt;Marley, p. 124&lt;/ref&gt; The expedition was seen as success in Spain, however, because the landed troops greatly contributed to defeat [[John Maurice, Prince of Nassau-Siegen|John Maurits of Nassau]]'s attack over Bahia.&lt;ref&gt;Fernández Duro, p. 130&lt;/ref&gt; Another expedition was planned at Hoces'a arrivel to retake the Dutch base of Pernambuco.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro132&quot;&gt;Fernández Duro, p. 132&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cidade mauricia.jpg|thumb|left|View of the city of Mauricia (Recife), based on a drawing from [[Frans Post]], 1645.]]
The command of this expedition would be entrusted to [[Miguel de Noronha, 4th Count of Linhares]], for which he was appointed Capitán General del Mar Océano, but he eventually declined to lead the fleet as he did not trust in the success of the expedition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro132&quot;/&gt; [[García Álvarez de Toledo, 6th Marquis of Villafranca]] also rejected its command, but not the [[Marquis of Fronteira|Count of Torre]], Dom Fernando de Mascarenhas, former Portuguese governor of [[Tangier]]. The same day that the French [[Siege of Fuenterrabía (1638)|siege of Hondarribia]] was lifted, he was given the command of 41 ships, of which 23 were Portuguese and were commanded by Admiral Dom [[Francisco Melo de Castro]] and Vice Adm. Dom [[Cosme Couto de Barbosa]], and 18 were Castilian under Admiral [[Juan de la Vega y Bazán]] and Vice Adm. [[Francisco Díaz de Pimienta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro132&quot;/&gt; 5,000 soldiers of infantry were embarked aboard this ships. Half of them were of the Tercio de Anfibios, a unit specialized in the naval fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro 133&quot;&gt;Fernández Duro, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt;

The fleet stopped at the islands of [[Cape Verde]], where an epidemic struck the crews of the ships, resulting in the death of 3,000 men and a number plus larger of incapacitated at the arrival of the fleet to Salvador da Bahia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro 133&quot;/&gt; Mascarenhas, ignoring his orders for an immediate assault upon Recife, spent about a year in the town before set sail again, which was done in January 1640 with the intention of land 1,200 soldiers under [[Luís Barbalho Bezerra]] to reinforce the Portuguese guerrilla surrounding the Dutch garrison of Pernambuco.&lt;ref&gt;Marley, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle ==
[[File:George Marcgraf - Mapa da Paraíba e Rio Grande do Norte, 1643.jpg|thumb|right|Map of Paraíba and Rio Grande do Norte, 1643, by [[Frans Post]].]]
A Dutch fleet of 36 ships under Admiral Willem Corneliszoon Loos and Vice Adm. [[Jacob Huygens]] emerged from Recife and intercepted the Spanish-Portuguese fleet between Itamaracá and [[Goiana]] on 12 January, before any attempt of disembarkation could be effected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley128&quot;&gt;Marley, p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; The battle degenerated in a confused melee in which Loos lost 2 of his vessels,while Loos himself was killed aboard his flagship, while confronting Mascarenhas flagship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro 133&quot;/&gt; Some Dutch ships managed to approach and disengage it from the Spanish flagship, but the vessel sank, taking down the admiral.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeClerc200&quot;&gt;Le Clerc, p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; Another Dutch ship, the ''Alemar'', was riddled by the Spanish guns and nearly sank, being unable to continue the pursuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeClerc200&quot;/&gt;

Vice Adm. Huygens,now aboard Loos' former flagship the ''Faam'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Warnsinck 151&quot;&gt;Warnsinck, 1940, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; continued the chase and the action was resumed the following day between Goiana and [[Cabo Branco]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LeClerc200&quot;/&gt; The Dutch fought a long-range battle using their superior artillery, but the only ship lost that day was the Dutch ''Soleil Brillant'', badly damaged and sank with its commander and 44 soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeClerc201&quot;&gt;Le Clerc, p. 201&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 January Huygens renewed the attack off [[Paraíba]]. The Portuguese galleon of Capt. António da Cunha Andrade was captured, and another Spanish vessel of the Squadron of Castile ran aground and was boarded while fighting the Dutch ''Zwaan''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley128&quot;/&gt; Its crew under the Neapolitan Colonel Ettore della Calce was taken prisoner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro134&quot;&gt;Fernández Duro, p. 134&lt;/ref&gt; The Dutch ''Zwaan'', under Rear Admiral Aldrichsz, lost its mainmast and, washed away, ran aground on the coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeClerc201&quot;/&gt;

Compelled to sail northwest, the Spanish-Portuguese fleet arrived before [[Potenji River|Rio Grande]] closely followed by the Dutch.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley128&quot;/&gt; The lack of wind prevented both fleets from attack each other until 17 January. That day the Dutch won the winward and attacked the Spanish-Portuguese.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeClerc201&quot;/&gt; Mascarenhas ship was damaged, after which the Dutch fleet abandoned the pursuit and the Spanish-Portuguese vessels could land the army at [[Cape São Roque]], too far to threaten Recife.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley128&quot;/&gt; Although the battle had been largely indecisive, the Dutch objective of impede the Spanish disembarkation near Recife was accomplished.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley128&quot;/&gt; The behavior of three captains in the battle, nevertheless, displeased the Count of Nassau, who condemned them to death &quot;''for not fulfilling his military duties in front of the galleons of Spain''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro134&quot;/&gt; Mascarenhas was also punished, being arrested upon his arrival on Spain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duro134&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
The Dutch garrison of Recife was increased in March 1640 by 2,500 soldiers carried aboard 28 ships under Amidrals [[Cornelis Jol]] and [[Jan Lichthart]], who was in charge of naval operations to disrupt the Portuguese sugar trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley128&quot;/&gt; In December Portugal [[Portuguese Restoration War|revolted]] against the Spanish Habsburg rule, proclaiming the seventh [[Duke of Bragança]] as King [[João IV]] in place of [[Philip IV of Spain]]. Although the Dutch welcomed the news of the revolt, expecting the Portuguese to become their allies, this did not happen, as the Dutch had no wish to restore the occupied territories to Portugal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley129&quot;&gt;Marley, p. 129&lt;/ref&gt; Recife served as base for an expedition under Jol and Lichthart, in 1641, to seize Portugal's slaving depots in [[Angola]] before any treaty could be concluded in Europe,&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley129&quot;/&gt; and despite a ten-year truce between both countries that was signed on 12 June, the hostilities continued, resulting in the expulsion of the Dutch from Brazil in 1654.&lt;ref&gt;Marley, p. 134&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*{{es icon}} Cesáreo Fernández Duro. ''Armada española desde la unión de los reinos de Castilla y de León'', Vol. IV. Est. tipográfico Sucesores de Rivadeneyra, Madrid, 1898.
*{{fr icon}} Le Clerc, Jean. ''Histoire des Provinces-Unies des Pays-Bas, depuis la naissance de la République jusqu'à la Paix d'Utrecht &amp; le Traité de la Barrière en 1716. Avec les principales médailles et leur explication'', Vol. 2. L'Honoré et Chatelain, 1728.
*Marley, David. ''Wars of the Americas: a chronology of armed conflict in the New World, 1492 to the present.'' ABC-CLIO, 2008. ISBN 978-0-87436-837-6
*{{nl icon}} Warnsicnk, J.C.M.''Van vlootvoogden en zeeslagen'', Amsterdam, 1940.

{{coord missing|Brazil}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Action of 12-17 January 1640}}
[[Category:Naval battles of the Eighty Years' War]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving the Dutch Republic]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving Spain]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving Portugal]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1640]]
[[Category:1640 in South America]]</text>
      <sha1>912wzvyq83fv0fjb26ykajag4ydggzv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
