<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Dahlen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7535580</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750059593</id>
      <parentid>737232111</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-17T16:40:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Imminent77</username>
        <id>29246608</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fix duplicate ref names – [[:Category:Pages with duplicate reference names|You can help!]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11926">{{infobox military conflict
|conflict    =Battle of Dahlen
|partof      =[[Eighty Years' War]]
|image       =[[File:Bor-Nederlantsche-Oorloghen 9147.tif|300px]]
|caption     =''The siege before Dalen, july 22 1568'' (engraving) by [[Frans Hogenberg]].
|date        =April 25, 1568
|place       =[[Rheindahlen, Mönchengladbach|Rheindahlen]], [[Bishopric of Liège]]&lt;br&gt;(present-day [[Germany]])
|coordinates ={{coord|51|8|N|6|22|E|source:eswiki_region:DE|display=title}}
|map_type    =
|latitude    =
|longitude   =
|map_size    =
|map_caption =
|map_label   =
|territory   =
|result      =Spanish victory
|status      =
|combatant1  =Dutch Rebels
|combatant2  ={{flagicon|Spain|1506}} [[Spanish Empire|Spain]]
|combatant3  =
|commander1  =Jean de Montigny
|commander2  =[[Sancho d'Avila]]
|commander3  =
|units1      =
|units2      =
|units3      =
|strength1   =3,000&lt;ref name=Motley&gt;Motley, p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2   =1,600&lt;ref name=Motley/&gt;
|strength3   =
|casualties1 =~2,000 killed&lt;ref name=Cabrera&gt;{{es icon}} Cabrera de Córdoba, p. 484.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Carnero&gt;{{es icon}} Carnero, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2 =Very few&lt;ref&gt;''Luis Cabrera de Córdoba mentioned 12 Spaniards killed and nearly 50 wounded''. Cabrera de Córdoba, p. 484&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Antonio Carnero put the Spanish loss as 20 killed and 50 wounded''. Carnero, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''John Lothrop Motley credited the total Spanish loss as 20 men''. Motley, p. 161.&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties3 =
|notes       =
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Eighty Years' War}}
}}
The '''Battle of Dahlen''' was fought on April 23, 1568, between a Dutch rebel army led by Jean de Montigny, Lord of [[Villers-au-Bois|Villers]], and a Spanish army commanded by [[Sancho d'Avila|Sancho Dávila y Daza]]. As a part of [[William I of Orange|William of Orange's]] planned invasion, the Dutch rebels were trying to conquer the town of [[Roermond]] when the arrival of the Spanish force compelled them to withdraw. Dávila pursued the retreating force and inflicted a defeat upon Villers near the small town of Dahlen (today known as [[Rheindahlen, Mönchengladbach|Rheindahlen]]). The survivors of this encounter sought refuge under the walls of Dahlen, where the Spanish infantry finally defeated them. This battle is sometimes considered the official start of the [[Eighty Years' War]].

== Background ==
In 1568, [[William I of Orange]], stadtholder of [[Holland]], [[Zeeland]] and [[Utrecht]], and other noblemen dissatisfied with the Spanish rule in the Netherlands, the [[Geuzen]], were determined to expel [[Fernando Álvarez de Toledo, 3rd Duke of Alba]], and his Spanish troops from the country.&lt;ref name=Motley0&gt;Motley, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt; William, based in [[Dillenburg]], designed a triple attack upon the Netherlands by his rebel followers and foreign mercenary forces.&lt;ref name=Motley0/&gt; An army of [[Huguenots]] and Netherlander refugees would attack [[Artois]] across the French border; another, under William's brother [[Louis of Nassau|Louis]], would try to raise the province of [[Friesland]] in arms against the Spanish; and a third one, under [[Antoine II de Lalaing]], Count of [[Hoogstraten]], would operate in the [[Meuse-Rhenish|Meuse-Rhin area]].&lt;ref name=Motley0/&gt;

The first force to be put in arms was that of Hoogstraten, though he had to be replaced by Jean de Montigny, Lord of Villers, who crossed the frontier of the [[United Duchies of Jülich-Cleves-Berg|Jülich-Cleves County]] on April 20 accompanied by [[William II de La Marck]], Lord of [[Lummen|Lumey]],&lt;ref name=Bentivoglio&gt;{{es icon}} Bentivoglio, p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; and in charge of about 3,000 men, both cavalry and infantry,&lt;ref name=Motley/&gt; amongst them French [[Huguenots]] and German cavalry recently dismissed from Spanish service.&lt;ref name=Cordoba1&gt;{{es icon}} Cabrera de Córdoba, p. 483.&lt;/ref&gt; Villers was expected to raise the country and to take an important city to serve as a base for a large offensive.&lt;ref name=Motley/&gt; The city selected was [[Roermond]], a fortified town of considerable size situated at the confluence of the [[Meuse (river)|Meuse]] and [[Rur]] rivers.&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt;

== Prelude ==
As soon as he received news of the invasion, Alba organized an improvised army to secure [[Maastricht]] and prevent the junction of the Dutch rebels with his French fellows.&lt;ref name=Cordoba1/&gt; He ordered the [[Maestro de Campo|maestre de campo]] don [[Sancho de Londoño]] to move his [[tercio]] from the village of [[Lier, Belgium|Lier]] up to Maastricht and its neighborhood.&lt;ref name=Cordoba1/&gt; To blockade the route linking northern France with the valley of the Meuse, the Duke mobilized most of the cavalry under his illegitimate son, [[Fernando de Toledo]], Grand Prior of Castile, who sent his men from [[Tournai]] up to the neutral [[Bishopric of Liège]] under the command of his lieutenant, don Lope de Acuña.&lt;ref name=Cordoba1/&gt;

Alba ordered the captain of his guard, don [[Sancho d'Avila|Sancho Dávila y Daza]], to go after the rebel army with his own company of Spanish [[demi-lancer|lances]] and those of Albanese lances under captain Nicolò Basta, and of horse arquebusiers under Pedro Montañés.&lt;ref name=Cordoba1/&gt; 300 horse in all,&lt;ref name=Bentivoglio/&gt; which were later reinforced with the tercio of Londoño, Lope's cavalry, and four companies of German pikemen, numbering 300 men, from Colonel's [[County of Eberstein|Count of Eberstein]] regiment, from the Maastricht garrison.&lt;ref name=Cordoba1/&gt;&lt;ref name=Carnero1&gt;{{es icon}} Carnero, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; In all the small Spanish army numbered about 1,600 men.&lt;ref name=Motley/&gt;

While being searched by the Spanish, Villers and his army passed through [[Eijsden]] and advanced upon [[Roermond]]. There, they tried to enter the town pretending to be soldiers of the King of Spain, but the town's inhabitants were not fooled.&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt;&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt; Then the rebels resorted to their weapons and attempted to seize the town's gates, only to be driven off.&lt;ref name=Bentivoglio/&gt; Fearing that they would be caught by the Spanish, Villers decided to withdraw, taking the road to the [[Duchy of Guelders|Guelders]] exclave of [[Erkelenz]].&lt;ref name=Motley/&gt; There were some doubts on the Spanish side about what to do then.&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt; Londoño advised caution,&lt;ref name=Bentivoglio/&gt; but Dávila decided to pursue the rebels, seeking to gain a victory that would serve as a warning for them.&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt;

== Battle ==
[[File:Erkelant.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Excerpt of the manuscript atlas by [[Christian Sgrothen]] showing the area in where the battle was fought.]]
Sancho Dávila went ahead with his cavalry and was informed by his scouts that the rebels were close to the village of [[Erkelenz]].&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt; There Villers found his path cut off because a nearby bridge over the [[Rur|Rur river]] had been demolished.&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt; He decided to take the road to Dahlen, a small walled town in the [[Bishopric of Liège]], while Dávila followed him and soon discovered the rebel army on the road between the two towns.&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt;

Villers deployed his troops for the battle on a plain with some groves behind and a [[hollow way]] covering one of his flanks, and dispatched his baggage towards Dahlen as soon as he learned of Dávila's presence nearby.&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt; To distract the Spanish general, he sent some of his cavalry against him, but Dávila dispersed it and made his way through the hollow way.&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt;
{{double image
|1=right
|2=
|3=150
|4=Sancho d'Avila.jpg
|5=132
|6=The commander of the battle of Dahlen: Sancho Dávila y Daza
|7=
|8=Left image alt text
|9=Right image alt text}}
After a brief [[reconnaissance]], Dávila, together with the Count of Eberstein and the cavalry companies under captains don Alonso de Vargas and Nicolò Basta, charged across the plain and frontally lunged over the rebel squadrons, which they broke.&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt; Villers then lost most of his cavalry and two [[War flag|flags]].&lt;ref name=Motley/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt; He and some 1,300 men retreated in some order with part of the [[baggage]] and managed to reach Dahlen, under whose walls they entrenched in order to withstand a second attack.&lt;ref name=Motley/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt;

Villers covered his men behind a [[ravelin]] of the wall, which had also a [[moat]], and reinforced his weak flank with some baggage wagons.&lt;ref name=Bentivoglio/&gt;&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt; Sancho Dávila was unable to reach such positions with his cavalry due to the rough groves, so he called Sancho de Londoño to come rapidly with the infantry.&lt;ref name=Carnero1/&gt; By early afternoon, the 300 German pikemen were detached behind the ravelin to prevent any attempt to flee,&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt; while 600 Spaniards, organized in five flags and under the personal leadership of Londoño, were ready to make a [[frontal attack]] over the fort, which they did shortly thereafter.&lt;ref name=Carnero/&gt;

The fight lasted half an hour, after which the Spaniards took the ravelin. Just a few rebels succeeded in escaping and sought refuge in Dahlen, climbing through scales;&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt; the others were butchered.&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt;&lt;ref name=Carnero/&gt;

== Aftermath ==
Villers was amongst those who escaped inside Dahlen, but was afterwards handed to the Spanish.&lt;ref name=Motley1&gt;Motley, p. 161.&lt;/ref&gt; The Lord of Lumey, on the other hand, evaded capture. All the baggage, seven flags, a large number [[corslet]]s, pikes, harquebuses, other weapons and munitions were seized by the victors.&lt;ref name=Carnero/&gt; Some 2,000 rebels, most of whom were French, were killed, as opposed to light Spanish casualties. Shortly thereafter, the Spanish army was split up. Dávila went to [[Brussels]] with the foremost captives to execute them, the Count of Eberstein returned to Maastricht with his German pikemen, and Sancho de Londoño lodged his men at Roermond, where he ordered several prisoners &amp;ndash; natives of the place &amp;ndash; to be hanged.&lt;ref name=Cabrera/&gt;&lt;ref name=Carnero/&gt;

A month later, Louis of Nassau scored an important victory over the Spanish at [[Battle of Heiligerlee (1568)|Heiligerlee]].&lt;ref name=Motley2&gt;Motley, p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, however, the planned rebel invasion of Artois was defeated in the bailiwick of [[Hesdin]].&lt;ref name=Motley0/&gt; The local Spanish forces under the Count of Roleux drove the rebels across the French frontier.&lt;ref name=Motley0/&gt; There, in [[Picardy]], at [[Saint Valery]], the French royal army destroyed what remained of the Netherlander force.&lt;ref name=Motley0/&gt; On July 21, Alba decisively defeated Nassau at [[Battle of Jemmingen|Jemmingen]], which put end to the Dutch rebel campaign in Friesland.&lt;ref name=Motley1p194&gt;Motley, p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Sources ==
*{{cite book|last=Bentivoglio|first=Guido|title=Las guerras de Flandes|year=1687|publisher=Geronymo Verdussen|location=Antwerp|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=R0hDAAAAcAAJ}}
*{{cite book|last=Cabrera de Córdoba|first=Luis|title=Filipe Segundo, Rey de España|year=1619|publisher=Luis Sanchez|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9uABH7lcvXoC}}
*{{cite book|last=Carnero|first=Antonio|title=Historia de las guerras ciuiles que ha auido en los estados de Flandes des del año 1559 hasta el de 1609 y las causas de la rebelion de dichos estados|year=1625|publisher=Juan de Meerbeque|location=Brussels|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=j3fTbqQjDSQC}}
*{{cite book|last=Lothrop Motley|first=John|title=The Rise of the Dutch Republic: A History|year=1883|location=New York and London |publisher=Harper &amp; Brothers|url=https://archive.org/details/risedutchrepubl00motlgoog |oclc=631636}}

[[Category:1568 in Europe]]
[[Category:Battles of the Eighty Years' War|Rheindalen 1568]]
[[Category:Battles involving Spain|Dahlen]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Dutch Republic|Dahlen]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1568|Dahlen]]</text>
      <sha1>b4l20ukgmkdv3pnr7d8br0nrgds5s0b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
