<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Norridgewock</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33967565</id>
    <revision>
      <id>726120707</id>
      <parentid>703600187</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-20T04:59:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>APersonBot</username>
        <id>21527109</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Wikipedia:Bots/Requests for approval/APersonBot 8|Bot]] updating 3 categories with sort keys for an article about a battle</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13948">{{Infobox military conflict
|image=[[Image:Death of Father Sebastian Rale of the Society of Jesus.jpg|300px]]
|caption= Battle of Norridgewock: Death of [[Sebastian Rale]]
|conflict= Battle of Norridgewock
|partof=[[Father Rale's War]]
|date= 23 August 1724
|place=  [[Norridgewock]], [[Maine]]
|result=massacre of Abenaki villagers
|combatant2=[[New England Colonies]]
|combatant1=[[Abenaki]]
|commander2=[[Johnson Harmon]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/stream/maineatlouisburg00burruoft#page/94/mode/2up  Harmon would later fight with Moulton at Louisbourg in 1745]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jeremiah Moulton]], Richard Bourne
|commander1=[[Chief Mog]]{{KIA}}, [[Chief Bomoseen]]{{KIA}}, [[Chief Wissememet]]{{KIA}}, [[Chief Job]]{{KIA}}, [[Chief Carabesett]]{{KIA}} 
|strength2= 160
|strength1=Unknown
|casualties2=3 dead
|casualties1=approx. 80; 14 wounded
|coordinates = {{Coord|44|46|01.2|N|69|52|59.9|W|display=title}}}}
{{Campaignbox Dummer's War}}
The '''Norridgewock Raid''' occurred in contested lands being fought over by [[England]], [[France]] and the [[Wabanaki Confederacy]], during the colonial frontier conflict referred to as [[Father Rale's War|Governor Dummer's War]]. Despite being called a 'battle' by some, the raid was essentially a massacre of Indians by colonial British troops. Captains [[Johnson Harmon]],&lt;ref&gt;https://archive.org/stream/harmongenealogyc00harm#page/140/mode/2up/search/jeremiah&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jeremiah Moulton]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite DCB |title=Moulton, Jeremiah |first=Alice R. |last=Stewart  |volume=3 |url=http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/moulton_jeremiah_3E.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Richard Bourne (soldier)|Richard Bourne]] (Brown) led a force of two hundred colonial New Englanders, which attacked the [[Abenaki]] village of Narantsouak, or Norridgewock, on the [[Kennebec River]]; the current town of [[Norridgewock]], [[Maine]] developed near there. The village was led by, among others, the sachems Bomazeen and [[Chief Mog|Welákwansit]], known to the English as Mog. The village's Catholic mission was run by a French [[Jesuit]] priest, Father [[Sebastian Rale|Sébastien Râle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite DCB |first=Thomas |last=Charland |title=Râle, Sébastien |volume=2 |url=http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/rale_sebastien_2E.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The raid was undertaken to check Abenaki power in the region, limit Catholic proselytizing among the Abenaki (and thereby perceived French influence), and to allow the expansion of [[New England]] settlements into Abenaki territory and [[Acadia]]. New France defined this area as starting at the [[Kennebec River]] in southern Maine.&lt;ref&gt;William Williamson. ''The History of the State of Maine.'' Vol. 2.  1832. p. 27; Griffiths, E. ''From Migrant to Acadian.'' McGill-Queen's University Press. 2005. p.61; Campbell (2005), ''The Road to Canada'', p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; Other motivations for the raid included the special ₤100 scalp bounty placed on Râle's head by the Massachusetts provincial assembly and the bounty on Abenaki scalps offered by the colony during the conflict. Casualties, depending on the sources consulted, vary, but most accounts record about eighty Abenaki being killed. But both English and French accounts agree that the raid was a surprise nighttime attack on a civilian target, and they both also report that many of the dead were unarmed when they were killed, and those massacred included many women and children. As a result of the raid, New Englanders flooded into the lower Kennebec region, establishing settlements there in the wake of the war.&lt;ref&gt;While Massachusetts secured parts of Maine in order to establish settlements, not until the treaty of 1752 did Massachusetts officially lay claim to the entire Penobscot watershed, and in 1759 the Pownall Expedition, led by Governor [[Thomas Pownall]], established [[Fort Pownall]] on [[Cape Jellison]] in what is now [[Stockton Springs, Maine|Stockton Springs]].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Historical context ==
[[File:Father Rasle Monument.jpg|thumb|The memorial monument for Father Sébastien Rale at the Norridgewock battle site in Madison, Maine.]]
The [[Treaty of Utrecht]] (1713), which ended [[Queen Anne's War]], had facilitated the expansion of New England settlement. The treaty, however, had been signed in Europe and had not involved any member of the [[Wabanaki Confederacy|Wabanaki natives]].  Since they had not been consulted, they protested this incursion into their lands by conducting raids on British fishermen and settlements.&lt;ref&gt;William Wicken. &quot;Mi'kmaq Decisions: Antoine Tecouenemac, the Conquest, and the Treaty of Utrecht&quot;. in John Reid et al (eds). ''The Conquest of Acadia, 1710: Imperial, Colonial and Aboriginal Constructions.'' University of Toronto Press. 2004. pp. 96&lt;/ref&gt;  For the first and only time, Wabanaki fought New Englanders and the British on their own terms and for their own reasons and not principally to defend French imperial interests.&lt;ref&gt;William Wicken, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt; In response to Wabanaki hostilities toward the expansion, the Governor of Nova Scotia Richard Phillips built a fort in traditional Mi'kmaq territory at Canso in 1720, and Massachusetts Governor [[Samuel Shute]] built forts on traditional Abenaki territory at the mouth of the Kennebec River. The French claimed the same territory on the Kennebec River by building a church in the Abenaki villages of [[Norridgewock]] on the Kennebec River and a church in the Maliseet village of [[Meductic Indian Village / Fort Meductic|Medoctec]] on the Saint John River.&lt;ref&gt;John Grenier. ''The Far Reaches of Empire''. University of Oklahoma Press. 2008. p. 51, p. 54)&lt;/ref&gt; These fortifications and missions escalated the conflict. By 1720, Massachusetts had placed a bounty on Râle.&lt;ref&gt;Grenier, 2003. p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

In the winter of 1722, New England rangers raided Norridgewock, trying to capture Râle.  While he escaped, the rangers destroyed the church and mission house.&lt;ref&gt;Grenier. 2003.p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; As revenge for the first raid on Norridgewock, the Mi'kmaq laid siege to the Lt. Governor of Nova Scotia [[John Doucett]] in May 1722 at [[Annapolis Royal, Nova Scotia|Annapolis Royal]].&lt;ref&gt;John Grenier. ''First Way of War.'' 2003. p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; On June 13, 1722, in present-day Maine, the tribe and allied groups burned [[Brunswick, Maine|Brunswick]] at the mouth of the Kennebec, taking hostages to exchange for those of their people held in Boston. Consequently, on July 25 Shute declared war on the eastern Indians. But on January 1, 1723, Shute abruptly departed for [[London, England|London]]. He had grown disgusted with the intransigent [[Legislative Assembly|Assembly]] (which controlled funding) as it squabbled with the Governor's Council over which body should conduct the war. Lieutenant-governor [[William Dummer]] assumed management of the government. Further Abenaki incursions persuaded the Assembly to act in what would be called [[Father Rale's War]].

== The Raid ==
In August 1724, a force of 208 soldiers (which split into 2 units under the commands of captains Johnson Harmon and [[Jeremiah Moulton]] left Fort Richmond (now [[Richmond, Maine|Richmond]]) in 17 [[whaleboat]]s to go up the Kennebec.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson Harmon was known for his bloodthirsty attitude towards the Indians.  In 1715, male members of the Harmon family massacred Native Americans at a pow-wow in [[York, Maine]].  The local minister, [[Samuel Moody]], stated that God would punish the Harmons so that there would be no more males to carry on the name. Three of the four officers in command of the little troop had been captives in earlier wars. They were Captains Harmon and Moulton and Lieutenant Bean or Bane. (See ''New England Captives carried to Canada'' by Emma Lewis Coleman, p. 4)&lt;/ref&gt;  At Taconic Falls (now [[Winslow, Maine|Winslow]]), 40 men were left to guard the boats as the troops continued on foot. On August 21, the Rangers killed [[Chief Bomoseen]], fatally wounded his daughter, and took his wife captive.&lt;ref&gt;William Williamson, p. 129. Note that Following the peace of Utrecht in April 1713, Mog, Bomoseen, Moxus, Taxous, and other chiefs concluded a peace with New England at Portsmouth, N.H., on 11–13 July.&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 22, 1724, Captains [[Jeremiah Moulton]] and Johnson Harmon led 200 [[United States Army Rangers|rangers]] to the main Abenaki village on the Kennebec River, [[Norridgewock, Maine]], to kill Father [[Sébastien Rale|Sébastien Râle]] and destroy the settlement.  On the 23rd, there were 160 Abenaki, many who were killed as they tried to escape.  The Rangers fired around the canoes filled with families.  Harmon noted that at least 50 bodies went downstream before the rangers could retrieve them for their scalps.&lt;ref&gt;Grenier. 2003. p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; At least 31 Abenaki chose to fight, which allowed the others to escape. Most of the defenders were killed.&lt;ref&gt;William Wicken, 2002, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt; Lieut. Richard Jaques killed Rale in the opening moments of the battle, Chief Mog was killed, and the rangers massacred nearly two dozen women and children.&lt;ref&gt;John Grenier, 2008. p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; The English had casualties of two militiamen and one [[Nauset]].&lt;ref&gt;The man killed, Jeremy Queach, was misidentified as a [[Mohawk people|Mohawk ]] in a contemporary history by Samuel Penhallow. However, recent research has shown he was a [[Nauset]] Indian from what is today [[Yarmouth, Massachusetts]], on [[Cape Cod]]. Brian D. Carroll, ''From Warrior to Soldier: New England Indians in the Colonial Military,'' Ph.D. dissertation (University of Connecticut, 2009), p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt; Harmon destroyed the Abenaki farms, and those who had escaped were forced to abandon their village and moved northward to the Abenaki village of St Francois ([[Odanak, Quebec]]).&lt;ref&gt;William Wicken, 2002, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt;  Many of the Indians were routed, leaving 26 warriors dead and 14 wounded. Harmon's son-in-law Lieutenant Richard Jaques scalped Fr. Rale.  [[Chief Wissememet]] was also killed.&lt;ref&gt;Williams.&lt;/ref&gt;

The soldiers mutilated Rale's body; his [[scalping|scalp]] was later redeemed in [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]] with those of the other dead. The Boston authorities gave a reward for the scalps, and Harmon was promoted. Thereafter, the French and Indians claimed that the missionary died &quot;a [[martyr]]&quot; at the foot of a large [[cross]] set in the central square, drawing the soldiers' attention to himself to save his parishioners. The English militia claimed that he was &quot;a bloody incendiary&quot; shot in a cabin while reloading his [[flintlock]].  A [[Mohawk nation|Mohawk]] named Christian, who accompanied the troops, slipped back after they had departed and set the village and church ablaze.

== Aftermath ==
The 150 Abenaki survivors returned to bury the fallen before abandoning Norridgewock for [[Saint-François-du-Lac, Quebec|St. Francis]] and Becancour, Quebec.&lt;ref&gt;''The Western Abenakis of Vermont, 1600-1800: War, Migration, and the Survival''... p.&amp;nbsp;123 –&lt;/ref&gt; Some later returned to the area. Rale was interred beneath the altar at which he had ministered his converts. In 1833, Bishop [[Benedict Joseph Fenwick]] dedicated an 11-foot tall [[obelisk]] monument, erected by subscription, over his grave at what is today St. Sebastian's Cemetery at Old Point in [[Madison, Maine]].

== References ==
*''The Scalp Hunters: Abenaki Ambush at Lovewell Pond, 1725.'' By Alfred E. Kayworth, Raymond G. Potvin
*William Durkee Williamson. [http://books.google.ca/books?id=XEMlAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA541&amp;lpg=PA541&amp;dq=The+history+of+the+state+of+Maine:+from+its+first+discovery,+1602+...,+Volume+1+By+William+Durkee&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=rTnP-oX0NY&amp;sig=tPgd62h2swA1AtpnAy1DW7FHGlk&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=kKC7TPqPGsWBlAenkYSiDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CCQQ6AEwAw#v=snippet&amp;q=rale&amp;f=false ''The History of the State of Maine: from Its First Discovery, A.D ...,''] Volume 2. 1832.
*John Grenier. ''The Far Reaches of Empire''. University of Oklahoma Press. 2008
*John Grenier. ''The First Way of War: American War Making on the Frontier, 1607-1814.'' 2003. 47-52.
*William Wicken. ''Mi'kmaq Treaties on Trial''. University of Toronto Press. 2002.
*John Mack Faragher. ''A Great and Noble Scheme''. New York; W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2005.
*William Wicken. &quot;Mi'kmaq Decisions: Antoine Tecouenemac, the Conquest, and the Treaty of Utrecht&quot;. In John Reid ''et al.'' (eds). ''The Conquest of Acadia, 1710: Imperial, Colonial and Aboriginal Constructions.'' University of Toronto Press. 2004.
* John Fiske, ''New England and New France'', 1902, Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Company, Boston, Massachusetts
* Francis Parkman, ''A Half-Century of Conflict'', 1907, Brown, Little &amp; Company, Boston, Massachusetts
* Herbert Milton Sylvester, ''Indian Wars of New England'', Volume III, 1910, W. B. Clarke, Boston, Massachusetts
* [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Journals/NEQ/7/3/Attack_on_Norridgewock*.html Fannie Hardy Eckstorm.  &quot;Attack on Norridgewock 1724&quot;], ''The New England Quarterly,'' Vol. 7, No. 3 (Sep., 1934), pp.&amp;nbsp;541–578;

Endnotes
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/rale_sebastien_2E.html Biography of Sébastien Râle (or Rasle)]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12635b.htm Biography of Sébastien Râle (or Rasle), Catholic Encyclopedia]
* [http://rootsweb.com/~aehs/indvill.htm Norridgewock Indian Village &amp; Monument]
* [http://www.mainememory.net/sitebuilder/site/820/page/1230/display?use_mmn= Father Rale, the Indians and the English], Maine Memory
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K4ZHN8FVn_E Battle of Norridgewock - Video]

[[Category:Military history of Acadia|Norridgewock]]
[[Category:Military history of New England|Norridgewock]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada|Norridgewock]]
[[Category:Pre-statehood history of Maine|Norr]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1724|Abenaki]]
[[Category:Battles involving Native Americans|Abenaki]]
[[Category:1724 in the Thirteen Colonies|Norr]]
[[Category:Somerset County, Maine]]
[[Category:Massacres of Native Americans]]</text>
      <sha1>k2qlhhmbzfntiv1hjk3yborep3t637a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
