<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Philomelion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13991536</id>
    <revision>
      <id>726122275</id>
      <parentid>717103150</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-20T05:17:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>APersonBot</username>
        <id>21527109</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Wikipedia:Bots/Requests for approval/APersonBot 8|Bot]] updating 3 categories with sort keys for an article about a battle</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7792">{{Infobox military conflict|
conflict=Byzantine-Seljuq wars|
image=|
caption=|
partof=|date= 1117 |
place=[[Philomelium|Philomelion]], [[Asia Minor]]|
result=Byzantine victory&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Norwich|first=John Julius|title=A Short History of Byzantium|location=New York|publisher= Vintage Books|year=1997|pages=264}}&lt;/ref&gt;|
combatant1= [[Byzantine Empire]]|
commander1=[[Alexios I Komnenos]]|
commander2=Sultan [[Malik Shah (Rûm)|Malik Shah]]|
strength1=Unknown|
strength2=Unknown|
combatant2= [[Sultanate of Rum]]|}}
{{Campaignbox Byzantine-Seljuk War}}
The '''Battle of Philomelion''' ([[Latinised]] as '''Philomelium''' - modern [[Akşehir]]) of 1117 consisted of series of clashes over a number of days between a [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] expeditionary army under Emperor [[Alexios I Komnenos]] and the forces of the [[Sultanate of Rûm]] under Sultan [[Malik Shah (Rûm)|Malik Shah]]; it occurred in the course of the [[Byzantine-Seljuq wars]]. The Seljuk forces attacked the Byzantine army a number of times to no effect; having suffered losses to his army in the course of these attacks, Malik Shah sued for peace.

==Background==
Following the success of the [[First Crusade]], the Byzantine armed forces, led by [[John Doukas (megas doux)|John Doukas]] the ''[[megas doux]]'', reconquered the Aegean coastline and much of the interior of western Anatolia. However, after the failure of the [[Crusade of 1101]], the [[Seljuq Turks|Seljuq]] and Danishmend Turks resumed their offensive operations against the [[Byzantine]]s. Following their defeats, the Seljuqs under [[Malik Shah (Rûm)|Malik Shah]] had recovered control of central Anatolia, re-consolidating a viable state around the city of [[Konya|Iconium]]. Emperor [[Alexios I Komnenos]], aged and suffering from an illness which proved to be terminal, was unable to prevent Turkish raids into the recovered areas of Byzantine Anatolia, though an attempt to [[Siege of Nicaea (1113)|take Nicaea]] in 1113 was thwarted by the Byzantines. In 1116 Alexios was able to personally take the field and was engaged in defensive operations in northwest Anatolia.  Basing his army at [[Lopadion]], and later at [[Nicomedia]], he succeeded in defeating raiding Turks in a minor battle at Poemanenon.&lt;ref&gt;Birkenmeier, p.78&lt;/ref&gt; After receiving reinforcements to his army Alexios decided to move onto the offensive.&lt;ref&gt;Birkenmeier, p.79&lt;/ref&gt;

==Byzantine advance to Philomelion==
[[File:Alexios I Komnenos.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Emperor Alexios I]]
In the campaign of Philomelion Alexios led a sizeable Byzantine army deep into the Anatolian interior. [[Anna Komnene]], the primary source for the campaign, implies that the Seljuq capital of Iconium was the goal of the expedition, but evidently Alexios abandoned this plan and contented himself with staging a conspicuous show of force and evacuating the native Christian population from the Turkish dominated areas his army passed through.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, ed. Sewter (1969), p.481&lt;/ref&gt; The Byzantines were to employ a new battle formation of Alexios' devising, the ''parataxis''. Anna Komnene's description of this formation is so imprecise as to be useless.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, ed. Sewter (1969), pp. 479-480&lt;/ref&gt;  However, from her account of the army in action it is obvious that the ''parataxis'' was a defensive formation, a hollow square with the baggage in the centre, infantry on the outside and cavalry in-between, from whence they could mount attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Birkenmeier, p.79&lt;/ref&gt; An ideal formation for tackling the fluid Turkish battle tactics, reliant on swarm attacks by horse-archers.  A similar formation was later employed by [[Richard I of England]] at the [[Battle of Arsuf]].

The Byzantines moved through Santabaris, sending detachments via [[Polybotos]] and Kedros, and, after dispersing Turkish resistance, took Philomelion by assault. Parties of scouts were then sent out to round up the local Christian population for evacuation to areas under firm Byzantine control.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, ed. Sewter (1969), p.483&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Birkenmeier, p.79&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
Alexios became aware that a substantial Seljuq army was approaching from the north and began his retreat to his own territory. His army resumed its defensive formation with the civilians accompanying the baggage in the centre. The Turks, under an officer called Manalugh, were initially baffled by the Byzantine formation and did not attack with any vigour. However, the following day Sultan [[Malik Shah (Rûm)|Malik Shah]] arrived and the Byzantines were attacked in earnest.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, ed. Sewter (1969), p.484-485&lt;/ref&gt; The Turks mounted a simultaneous attack on the van and rear of the Byzantine army. The Byzantine cavalry made two counterattacks, the first seems to have been unsuccessful, with Alexios' son Andronikos being killed.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, ed. Sewter (1969), p.485&lt;/ref&gt; A further counterattack was more fortunate, led by [[Nikephoros Bryennios the Younger]] (Anna Komnene's husband and Alexios' son-in-law) the leader of the Byzantine right wing, it broke that part of the Turkish force led in person by the Sultan, which then turned to flight. Malik Shah narrowly escaped capture.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, ed. Sewter (1969), p.486&lt;/ref&gt; The Seljuqs then made a night attack, but the Byzantine dispositions again frustrated them. The following day Malik Shah again attacked, his troops completely surrounding the Byzantine army on all sides. The Turks were once more repulsed with loss, having achieved nothing. The next day Malik-Shah sent to Alexios with proposals for peace.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, ed. Sewter (1969), pp.486-487&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Alexios and Malik Shah met, Alexios throwing his own costly cloak around the sultan's shoulders. A peace involving an undertaking by Malik Shah to stop Turkish raiding and an admission by the sultan of some measure of, largely theoretical, dependence on the Byzantine emperor was made. Anna Komnene records that the peace treaty involved an undertaking by Malik Shah to evacuate Anatolia, but this is unlikely in the extreme and must represent hyperbole on her part.&lt;ref&gt;Komnene pp. 487-488&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign was remarkable for the high level of discipline shown by the Byzantine army. Alexios had demonstrated that he could march his army with impunity through Turkish dominated territory.&lt;ref&gt;Birkenmeier, pp. 79-80&lt;/ref&gt; The reverse suffered by Malik Shah at Philomelion and the consequent loss of prestige probably contributed to his demise as he was soon deposed, blinded and eventually murdered by his brother [[Mesud I|Mas'ud]].&lt;ref&gt;Komnene, pp. 488-491&lt;/ref&gt;
Alexios' death in 1118 meant that the ambition of reconquering all of Asia Minor was left to his 31-year-old son, [[John II Komnenos]].

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{cite book
|first = John W.
|last = Birkenmeier
|title = The Development of the Komnenian Army: 1081–1180
|publisher = Brill
|year = 2002
|isbn = 90-04-11710-5
}}
*{{cite book | last=Komnene (Comnena)| first=Anna|author2=Sewter, Edgar Robert Ashton |authorlink=Anna Komnene | title=The Alexiad of Anna Comnena translated by Edgar Robert Ashton Sewter| publisher=Penguin Classics | year=1969 | isbn=0-14-044215-4 | chapter=XLVIII-The First Crusade}}
*{{cite book|last=Norwich|first=John Julius|title=A Short History of Byzantium|location=New York|publisher= Vintage Books|year=1997}}

==See also==
* [[Komnenian Byzantine army]]
* [[Komnenian restoration]]

{{coord|38|21|27|N|31|24|59|E|display=title}}
[[Category:Battles of the Byzantine–Seljuq Wars|Philomelion]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Sultanate of Rum|Philomelion]]
[[Category:Alexios I Komnenos]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1117|Philomelion]]
[[Category:History of Konya Province]]
[[Category:1117 in Asia]]
[[Category:1117 in the Byzantine Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>t14pq5qlntmwov7bcgvjyc1oj98kztb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
