<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Newton</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38501635</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749324342</id>
      <parentid>746662151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T19:33:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>2 archive templates merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15658">{{distinguish|Battle of Newtown|Battle of Newton's Station|Battle of Newtonia (disambiguation){{!}}Battle of Newtonia|}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Newton, Alabama
|partof=[[American Civil War]]
|date={{Start date|1865|3|14|df=yes}}
|place=[[Newton, Alabama]]
|result=[[Confederate Home Guard]] victory
|combatant1= {{flagicon|USA|1865}} [[United States]] ([[Union (American Civil War)|Union]])
|combatant2= {{flagicon|CSA|1865}} [[Confederate States of America|CSA (Confederacy)]]
|commander1=2LT [[Joseph G. Sanders]]
|commander2=CPT [[Joseph Breare]]
|strength1  = 44&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot;&gt;[http://www.battleofnewton.org/battlehistory.html The Raid on Newton].&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2  = ~40&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;
|casualties1=3 killed, 5 wounded
|casualties2=No casualties
|}}

The '''Battle of Newton''' was a minor skirmish that took place in the small town of [[Newton, Alabama]], on 14 March 1865, during the final days of the [[U.S. Civil War]].  It was fought between local [[Confederate Home Guard|Home Guard]] troops and elements of the 1st Florida Cavalry (US), who had invaded the [[Wiregrass Region|Wiregrass]] region of [[Alabama]] in violation of a directive given by Brigadier General [[Alexander Asboth]], commanding [[Union Army|Union]] forces in [[Pensacola, Florida]].

Led by Second Lieutenant [[Joseph G. Sanders|Joseph Sanders]], a former captain in the [[Confederate States Army|Confederate Army]] who had switched sides and joined with the [[Union Army|Federals]],&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt; the Floridians intended to burn the [[County Courthouse|courthouse]] of [[Dale County, Alabama|Dale County]]—which was then located in Newton—as had been done in other nearby counties during this same period of time.  However, their movement toward the town was detected by local citizens, and they were ambushed and routed on the town square by Newton's home guard before they could do any damage.  Sanders reported three dead and five wounded, while no casualties were reported among the home guard troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory&quot;&gt;[http://www.exploresouthernhistory.com/newtonbattle.html Battle of Newton].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[File:Downtown Newton.jpg|thumb|150px|[[Newton, Alabama]], in 2009.  The old courthouse square sits just to the right of where this photo was taken.]]
An area of relatively low population and economic importance in [[Antebellum era|Antebellum]] Alabama, Dale County had been relegated to the status of a backwater during the Civil War era, largely neglected by the state government in [[Montgomery, Alabama|Montgomery]].&lt;ref&gt;David Williams, [https://books.google.com/books?id=V6PJ-8wmMzIC&amp;pg=RA1-PA122&amp;lpg=RA1-PA122&amp;dq=williams+rich+man's+war+sketoe&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=AMeVWroRIx&amp;sig=b2CWZ1m5-6wFvkDHVAgx8sBY8cY&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=BLsBSombD5mwMaz03dcH&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1#PRA1-PA122,M1 ''Rich Man's War: Caste, Class and Confederate Defeat in the Lower Chattahoochee Valley''] University of Georgia Press, 1999.  ISBN 0-8203-2033-1. pg. 122.&lt;/ref&gt;  Mostly covered by [[Pine|pine forest]] and with few big [[farm]]s or [[plantations in the American South|plantation]]s, the area proved an attractive gathering location for [[Desertion|deserters]] from the Confederate Army, as well as Southern [[Unionist (United States)|Unionist]]s who had been harassed or worse by their &quot;Secessh&quot; neighbors.  These &quot;[[Bushwhacker|bushwackers]]&quot;, as they were called,&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt; hid out in the forests of Dale and adjacent counties, seeking aid and supplies from Federal forces in Pensacola—or, more often than not, simply seizing them from the largely-defenseless locals.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.usgennet.org/usa/ga/topic/news/Alabama/alabamaletters.htm Letter to Alabama Governor T.H. Watts] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090527022037/http://www.usgennet.org/usa/ga/topic/news/Alabama/alabamaletters.htm |date=May 27, 2009 }}, written by citizens of adjacent Henry County, concerning &quot;the bands of deserters, tories and outlaws&quot; working in Henry and Dale Counties.  Retrieved on 2009-05-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

One &quot;bushwacker&quot; leader was [[Joseph G. Sanders]], a [[millwright]] and resident of Dale County who had first served as a [[Private (rank)|private]] in the 31st Georgia Infantry before being elected [[Captain (army)|captain]] of Company C in that regiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#51674509 Official Confederate Records of Joseph G. Sanders], 31st Georgia Infantry&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1864 Sanders had resigned his commission; facing the possibility of being [[Conscription|drafted]] to fight for the South as a private, he chose to go over to the Union side, where he was commissioned as a [[second lieutenant]] and assigned to Company F, 1st Regiment of Florida Cavalry (US).&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.civilwarmicrofilm.com/site/viewer/surnameIndex.php?surnamePrefix=S Sanders, Joseph G.]&lt;/ref&gt; Sanders' unit attracted not just Confederate deserters and local Unionists, but also outright criminals and other less-than-desirable elements, as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory&quot; /&gt;

In the late winter of 1865, Brigadier General Alexander Asboth, commanding Federal forces in the [[Florida Panhandle]], ordered Sanders to make a raid into [[Washington County, Florida]], to  raise recruits and also to &quot;confiscate&quot; horses and cattle.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#260072129 Official U.S. Military Records of Joseph G. Sanders], original operational order issued to Sanders.  Sanders' main mission was to raise recruits for the Federal Army at East Pass, Santa Rosa Island, as well as confiscate horses and cattle belonging to &quot;Rebels&quot; in that area of Florida.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, instead of carrying out these orders, Sanders and his men made their way into the Forks of the Creek swamp near [[Campbellton, Florida|Campbellton]], where they waited for a chance to attack Newton and [[Arson|burn]] the courthouse there, which contained records of Sanders' previous service with the Confederate Army.  The courthouse at [[Elba, Alabama|Elba]] in adjacent [[Coffee County, Alabama|Coffee County]] had been torched by a &quot;bushwacker&quot; unit under the leadership of John Ward, and Sanders hoped to repeat their escapade in Newton.  Accordingly, he set out for there on the night of 14 March 1865.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory&quot; /&gt;  Newton was also the location of the local Confederate [[conscription]] office, staffed at the time by Captain Joseph Breare, a former officer with the [[15th Regiment Alabama Infantry|15th Alabama Infantry]] who had been wounded at [[Battle of Gettysburg|Gettysburg]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://history-sites.com/~kjones/15emstr.html Co. &quot;E&quot;, 15th Alabama Infantry] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120225000000/http://history-sites.com/~kjones/15emstr.html |date=February 25, 2012 }}. Retrieved on 2009-05-01.&lt;/ref&gt; and returned home to lead efforts against local [[draft-dodger]]s and deserters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flemingmultimedia.com/15thAlaCoE/BrearJoseph.html Breare, Joseph R.]. Retrieved on 2009-05-02.  See also [http://history-sites.com/cgi-bin/bbs53x/alcwmb2/webbbs_config.pl?noframes;read=30570 Deserter Hanging in Dale County]. Retrieved on 2009-05-05. See also [http://www.exploresouthernhistory.com/sketoe.html The Hole That Will Not Stay Filled]. Retrieved on 2009-05-05.&lt;/ref&gt;  This made it an even more tempting target for Sanders, who was seen as a [[traitor]] by the citizens of Dale County.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;

==Battle==
Unbeknownst to Sanders, he and his men had been spotted on the roads leading toward Newton, and their probable destination had been guessed.  Jesse Carmichael, a [[veteran]] of the 15th Alabama who had served as a [[corporal]] and lost a [[hand]] at [[Battle of Antietam|Antietam]] in 1862,&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt; was notified by his father of Sanders' impending arrival in Newton that night, and he hastened to warn the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;  As the citizens formed up to defend their village, Carmichael and another wounded veteran of the 15th, John McEntyre, rode some distance outside of town, to provide an early warning of Sanders' arrival.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;  Spotting Sanders at the head of a mounted company of 44 men, Carmichael quickly rode back to Newton, where he led his neighbors to an [[ambush]] site he had chosen near a spring a mile east of town.  However, once he had headed out on another [[reconnaissance]] mission these men abandoned this position and returned to town, fearful for the safety of their families.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;

Meanwhile, Breare and his home guard unit had arrived in Newton, and upon hearing what was happening, Breare immediately took charge of the town's defense.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory_a&quot;&gt;[http://www.exploresouthernhistory.com/newtonbattle.html Battle of Newton]&lt;/ref&gt;  Breare wanted to keep the defenders close to the square, so that they might surprise Sanders and catch him amidst Newton's buildings and streets, leaving him less room to maneuver.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory_a&quot; /&gt;  Accordingly, he formed his men on the west side of the square, opposite of the direction that Carmichael believed that Sanders would be coming.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory_a&quot; /&gt;

[[Image:Civil War Monument.jpg|thumb|Civil War Monument in [[Newton, Alabama|Newton]].  Located just south of the battle site.]]
Disagreeing with Breare's approach, and unable to dissuade him from this course of action, Carmichael took nine of his friends and arranged them to the east of the square: Carmichael and three of the men took up positions near a hotel, while the other six formed up further down in a side street between the hotel and the square.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory_a&quot; /&gt;  Sanders and his company rode into Newton from the southeast at full gallop, yelling &quot;huzzah, huzzah; here we are!&quot; and heading for the courthouse.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;  Carmichael and his outfit let them pass, then opened up on them from behind with [[double-barrelled shotgun]]s and [[rifle]]s while their friends up ahead simultaneously fired into the front of the attacking column.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;  Thoroughly alarmed by this unexpected development, the attackers bolted for the edge of town and rode off into the night, reportedly hampered by malfunctioning pistols and rifles as they tried to return fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;  A one-handed ex-corporal and his nine friends had routed a Union [[cavalry]] force four times their size—on foot and in the dark, without one of them being hurt or killed, and with Breare's men on the other side of the square never getting off a shot in the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory_a&quot; /&gt; Sanders, for his part, reported three dead and five wounded among his troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;exploresouthernhistory&quot; /&gt;

==Aftermath==
Sanders' actions in Alabama became the subject of an investigation in June 1865 when he returned to Pensacola after an unauthorized four-month absence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#260071401 Official U.S. Military Record of Joseph G. Sanders], Orders issued 23 June 1865, by Col. John W. Wilson, Dept. of the Gulf, New Orleans.&lt;/ref&gt;  He had been given fourteen days for his mission,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#260071481 Official U.S. Military Record of Joseph G. Sanders], Special Orders 149, Dated 16 June 1865, regarding absence of 2LT Joseph Sanders, amended by statement made 24 July 1865 by Adjutant General Theodore Markle.&lt;/ref&gt; and when he returned after four months with only eight men out of the twenty he started with,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#260071481 Official U.S. Military Record of Joseph G. Sanders], Special Orders 149, Dated 16 June 1865, regarding absence of 2LT Joseph Sanders.  The orders state he was authorized only twenty men for the mission; no explanation is given for where the other fourteen men involved in the Newton attack came from.&lt;/ref&gt; the Army demanded to know why.  Sanders' proffered explanation&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#260071747 Official U.S. Military Record of Joseph G. Sanders], official statement of Joseph G. Sanders on his prolonged absence.  Sanders claimed that sore feet, floodwaters, &quot;700 Rebels&quot; and lack of forage for his horses had all combined to force him to hide in the swamp for four months despite numerous attempts (he claimed) to get back to Pensacola.  No mention whatsoever was made of Sanders' unsuccessful attack on Newton, or any of the other alleged depredations committed by his men against local civilians during this time.&lt;/ref&gt; seems to have satisfied his superiors, for no [[court-martial]] ensued, and he was permitted to resign at his own request and &quot;for the good of the service&quot; on 13 September 1865,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#260071559 Official U.S. Military Record of Joseph G. Sanders], Casualty Sheet.  See also [http://www.fold3.com/image/#260072232 Official U.S. Military Record of Joseph G. Sanders], statement by Brigadier General Asboth, indicating that Sanders was not guilty (in his opinion) of any &quot;criminality,&quot; but that he was guilty of &quot;gross neglect and incompetency to fill a position as a commissioned officer,&quot; and recommended his discharge &quot;for the good of the service.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; after saying that he feared for the safety and welfare of his family (who were living in Dale County at the time).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fold3.com/image/#260071672 Official U.S. Military Record of Joseph G. Sanders], Resignation of 2LT Joseph G. Sanders.&lt;/ref&gt;  Sanders returned to Alabama after leaving the army, where several citizens of Newton attempted to [[arrest]] him at his home but were repulsed with one of them being killed in the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;  He fled to [[Decatur County, Georgia]], where his victim's father allegedly tracked him down and killed him.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;

Though completely unimportant in terms of the war as a whole, Carmicheal reported that the successful outcome of the home guard's minuscule engagement at Newton gave hope to local citizens, who had suffered much at the hands of raiders like Sanders and Ward.&lt;ref name=&quot;battleofnewton&quot; /&gt;  The town later constructed a [[monument]] to those of its citizens who defended it that evening, which can be seen adjacent to the square (now minus the courthouse; the [[county seat]] was moved to nearby [[Ozark, Alabama|Ozark]] in 1870).

In recent years, the battle has become an item of immense local interest, with an annual [[festival]] and [[reenactment]] on the third weekend of October.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.battleofnewton.org/ Battle of Newton]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lasr.net/travel/city.php?AL+newton+the-battle-of-newton&amp;TravelTo=AL0409091&amp;VE=Y&amp;EventCategory=&amp;Event_ID=AL0409091e001 Battle of Newton Reenactment]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.battleofnewton.org/ Battle of Newton Website].  Local website contains history of the battle, plus photos and info on periodic reenactments.
*[http://www.southeastsun.com/news/article_5d9c2102-1224-11e2-a951-001a4bcf6878.html Southeast Sun – 12th Annual Battle of Newton Reenactment]. Local newspaper article on the most recent festival and reenactment of the Battle of Newton.

{{Alabama in the Civil War}}

{{coord missing|Alabama}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1865|Newton]]
[[Category:1865 in Alabama]]
[[Category:Battles of the American Civil War in Alabama|Newton]]
[[Category:Confederate victories of the American Civil War|Newton]]
[[Category:Dale County, Alabama]]</text>
      <sha1>pxagaianitloozwo5tovkeuvgnsx2vq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
