<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bombing of Dresden in World War II</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>64692</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749029514</id>
      <parentid>749028785</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T22:36:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GeneralizationsAreBad</username>
        <id>24080262</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 749028785 by [[Special:Contributions/40.138.169.66|40.138.169.66]] ([[User talk:40.138.169.66|talk]]) More specific</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="98858">{{Use British English|date=June 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Bombing of Dresden
| partof      = [[Strategic bombing during World War II]]
| image       = [[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1994-041-07, Dresden, zerstörtes Stadtzentrum.jpg|350px]]
| caption     = Dresden after the bombing raid
| date        = 13–15 February 1945
| place       = [[Dresden]], [[Germany]]
| coordinates =
| map_type    = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_caption = 
| territory   = 
| result      = Allied victory 
*Strategic targets destroyed 
*Extensive German casualties
| status      = 
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Royal Air Force|RAF]]&lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|United States|1912}} {{nowrap|[[United States Army Air Forces|USAAF]]}}
| combatant2  = [[File:Flag of the German Reich (1935–1945).svg|border|23px]] [[Nazi Germany]]
| combatant3  = 
| commander1  = 
| commander2  = 
| commander3  = 
| strength1   = {{plainlist|
*769 [[heavy bomber]]s (RAF)
*527 heavy bombers (USAAF)
*784 [[North American P-51 Mustang]]s
}}
| strength2   = {{plainlist|
*28 [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]] night fighters
}}
| strength3   = 
| casualties1 = 8 planes shot down
| casualties2 = 22,700–25,000 deaths &lt;!--best sources, includes civilians and military personnel, as well as prisoners of war--&gt; 
| casualties3 = 
| notes       = 
}}
[[File:Fotothek df ps 0000010 Blick vom Rathausturm.jpg|thumb|[[Dresden]], 1945, view from the city hall (Rathaus) over the destroyed city]]

The '''bombing of Dresden''' was a [[United Kingdom|British]]/[[United States|American]] aerial bombing attack on the city of [[Dresden]], the capital of the German state of [[Saxony]], that took place during the [[Second World War]] in the [[European Theatre of World War II|European Theatre]]. In four raids between 13 and 15 February 1945, 722 [[heavy bomber]]s of the British [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) and 527 of the [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) dropped more than 3,900 tons of [[high-explosive]] bombs and [[incendiary device]]s on the city.&lt;ref&gt;
*The number of bombers and tonnage of bombs are taken from a USAF document written in 1953 and classified secret until 1978 {{harv|Angell|1953}}.&lt;!--I think it's 1948 and 1962--&gt;
* Taylor (2005), front flap,{{verification needed|date=November 2013}}&lt;!--Taylor 2005 as cited else where in this article is a paper back--&gt; which gives the figures 1,100 heavy bombers and 4,500 tons. 
* Webster and Frankland (1961) give 805 Bomber Command aircraft 13 February 1945 and 1,646 US bombers 16 January – 17 April 1945. {{harv|Webster|Frankland|1961|pp=198, 108–109}}.
[http://books.guardian.co.uk/reviews/history/0,6121,1142632,00.html &quot;Mission accomplished&quot;], ''[[The Guardian]]'', 7 February 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; The bombing and the resulting [[firestorm]] destroyed over {{convert|1600|acre|km2}} of the city centre.{{sfn|Harris|1945}} An estimated 22,700&lt;ref name=&quot;Shortnews&quot;/&gt; to 25,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Rolf&quot;/&gt; people were killed. Three more USAAF air raids followed, two occurring on 2 March aimed at the city's [[Classification yard|railroad marshaling yard]] and one small raid on 17 April aimed at industrial areas.

Immediate German propaganda claims following the attacks and post-war discussions&lt;ref name=&quot;Norwood, 2013, page 237&quot;&gt;Norwood, 2013, page 237&lt;/ref&gt; on whether the attacks were justified has led to the bombing becoming one of the moral ''[[Cause célèbre|causes célèbres]]'' of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Selden|2004|p=30}}: Cites Ronald Schaffer. Note: The casualty figures are now considered lower than those from the firebombing of some other [[Axis powers|Axis]] cities; see [[Bombing of Tokyo in World War II|Tokyo]] 9–10 March 1945, approximately 100,000 dead, and [[Bombing of Hamburg in World War II#Battle of Hamburg|Operation Gomorrah campaign against Hamburg]] July 1943, approximately 50,000 dead {{harv|Grayling|2006|p=20}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 1953 [[United States Air Force]] report defended the operation as the justified bombing of a strategic target, which they claimed was a major rail transport and communication centre, housing 110 factories and 50,000 workers in support of the German war effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHD&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Angell|1953}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Several researchers have asserted that not all of the communications infrastructure, such as the bridges, was targeted, nor were the extensive industrial areas outside the city centre.{{sfn|McKee|1983|p=62}} Critics of the bombing argue that Dresden was a cultural landmark of little or no strategic significance, and that the attacks were indiscriminate [[area bombing]] and not [[Proportionality (law)#International law|proportionate]] to the commensurate [[military necessity|military gains]].{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|loc=Chapter 9 p. 194}}{{sfn|McKee|1983|pp=61–94}}

Large variations in the claimed death toll have fueled the controversy. In March 1945, the German government ordered its press to publish a falsified casualty figure of 200,000 for the Dresden raids, and death toll estimates as high as 500,000 have been given.{{sfn|Bergander|1998|p=217}}{{sfn|Taylor|2004|p=370}}{{sfn|Atkinson|2013|p=535}} The city authorities at the time estimated no more than 25,000 victims, a figure that subsequent investigations supported, including a 2010 study commissioned by the city council.{{sfn|Neutzner|2010|p=68}}
{{TOC limit}}
==Background==
{{more information|Vistula–Oder Offensive}}
[[File:Dresden photochrom2.jpg|thumb|Image of Dresden during the 1890s. Landmarks include [[Dresden Frauenkirche]], Augustus Bridge, and the [[Dresden Cathedral|Katholische Hofkirche]].]]
[[File:Dresden-blickvomrathausturm1910.jpg|right|thumb|A view from the town hall over the ''Altstadt'' (old town), 1910]]
Early in 1945, the German offensive known as the [[Battle of the Bulge]] had been exhausted, as was the disastrous attack by the [[Luftwaffe]] [[Operation Bodenplatte|on New Year's Day]] involving elements of eleven combat wings of the Luftwaffe's day fighter force. The [[Red Army]] had launched their [[Silesian Offensives]] into pre-war German territory. The [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German army]] was retreating on all fronts, but still resisting strongly. On 8 February 1945, the Red Army crossed the [[Oder River]], with positions just 70&amp;nbsp;km from [[Berlin]].{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=262}} The [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern]] and [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Fronts]] were getting closer, the Western Allies started planning to bomb Berlin and several other eastern cities in conjunction with the Soviet advance in order to cause confusion among German troops and refugees.

A special British Joint Intelligence Subcommittee report titled ''German Strategy and Capacity to Resist'', prepared for [[Winston Churchill]]'s eyes only, predicted that Germany might collapse as early as mid-April if the Soviets overran its eastern defenses. Alternatively, the report warned that the Germans might hold out until November if they could prevent the Soviets from taking [[Silesia]]. Hence,  any assistance provided to the Soviets on the Eastern Front could shorten the war.{{sfn|Davis|2006|p=491}} At the time of bombing, the Soviets were conducting their [[Lower Silesian Offensive]].

Plans for a large and intense aerial bombing of Berlin and the other eastern cities had been discussed under the code name [[Operation Thunderclap]] in mid-1944, but had been shelved on 16 August.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=207}} These were now re-examined, and the decision was made to draw up a more limited operation.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=332}}

On 22 January 1945, the RAF director of bomber operations, [[Air Commodore]] [[Sydney Bufton]], sent a memo to the [[Deputy Chief of the Air Staff]], Air Marshal Sir [[Norman Bottomley]], suggesting that what appeared to be a coordinated air attack by the RAF to aid the current Soviet offensive would have a detrimental effect on German morale.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|p=21}} On 25 January, the Joint Intelligence Committee supported the idea, as it tied in with the [[Ultra (cryptography)|ULTRA]]-based intelligence that dozens of German [[Division (military)|divisions]] deployed in the west were moving to reinforce the Eastern Front, and that [[interdiction]] of these troop movements should be a &quot;high priority.&quot;{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=209}} [[Sir Arthur Harris, 1st Baronet|Arthur Harris]], [[Air Officer Commanding|AOC]] [[RAF Bomber Command|Bomber Command]], nicknamed &quot;Bomber&quot; Harris in the British press, and known as an ardent supporter of [[area bombing]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/harris_sir_arthur_bomber.shtml |title=Sir Arthur 'Bomber' Harris (1892–1984) |work=Historic Figures |publisher=BBC |accessdate= |deadurl= |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080116211800/http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/harris_sir_arthur_bomber.shtml |archivedate=16 January 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; was asked for his view, and he proposed a simultaneous attack on [[Chemnitz]], [[Leipzig]] and Dresden.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=332}} That evening Churchill asked the [[Secretary of State for Air]], Sir [[Archibald Sinclair, 1st Viscount Thurso|Archibald Sinclair]], what plans had been drawn up to carry out these proposals. He passed on the request to Sir [[Charles Portal]], the [[Chief of the Air Staff (United Kingdom)|Chief of the Air Staff]], who answered that &quot;We should use available effort in one big attack on Berlin and attacks on Dresden, Leipzig, and Chemnitz, or any other cities where a severe blitz will not only cause confusion in the evacuation from the East, but will also hamper the movement of troops from the West.&quot;{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=332}} He mentioned that aircraft diverted to such raids should not be taken away from the current primary tasks of [[Oil Campaign of World War II|destroying oil production facilities]], [[List of jet aircraft of World War II|jet aircraft]] factories, and [[Submarine pen|submarine yards]].{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=332}}{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=209–211}}

Churchill was not satisfied with this answer and on 26 January pressed Sinclair for a plan of operations: &quot;I asked [last night] whether Berlin, and no doubt other large cities in east Germany, should not now be considered especially attractive targets.... Pray report to me tomorrow what is going to be done&quot;.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=212}}

In response to Churchill's inquiry, Sinclair approached Bottomley who asked Harris to undertake attacks on Berlin, Dresden, Leipzig, and Chemnitz, as soon as moonlight and weather allowed, &quot;...with the particular object of exploiting the confused conditions which are likely to exist in the above mentioned cities during the successful Russian advance.&quot;{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=212}} This activity allowed Sinclair to inform Churchill on 27 January of the Air Staff's agreement that, &quot;subject to the overriding claims&quot; on other targets under the [[Pointblank Directive]], strikes against communications in these cities to disrupt civilian evacuation from the east and troop movement from the west would be made.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|pp=332,333}}{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=212–3}}

On 31 January, Bottomley sent a message to Portal saying a heavy attack on Dresden and other cities &quot;will cause great confusion in civilian evacuation from the east and hamper movement of reinforcements from other fronts&quot;.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|loc=Chapter by Sebastian Cox &quot;The Dresden Raids: Why and How&quot;, p. 26}} British historian [[Frederick Taylor (historian)|Frederick Taylor]] mentions a further memo sent to the [[Chiefs of Staff Committee]] by Sir [[Douglas Evill]] on 1 February, in which Evill states interfering with mass civilian movements was a major, even key, factor in the decision to bomb the city centre. Attacks there, where main railway junctions, telephone systems, city administration and utilities were located, would result in &quot;chaos.&quot; Ostensibly, Britain had learned this after the [[Coventry Blitz]], when loss of this crucial infrastructure had supposedly longer-lasting effects than attacks on war plants.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=215}}

During the [[Yalta Conference]] on 4 February, the Deputy Chief of the Soviet General Staff, General [[Aleksei Antonov]], raised the issue of hampering the reinforcement of German troops from the western front by paralysing the junctions of Berlin and Leipzig with aerial bombardment. In response, [[Chief of the Air Staff (United Kingdom)|Chief of the British Air Staff]] Portal, who was in [[Yalta]], asked Bottomley to send him a list of objectives to discuss with the Soviets. Bottomley's list included oil plants, tank and aircraft factories and the cities of Berlin and Dresden.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=217–220}}{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|pp=27, 28}} A British interpreter later claimed that Antonov and [[Joseph Stalin]] asked for the bombing of Dresden, but there is no mention of these requests in the official record of the conference and the claim was assessed as possible [[Cold War|Cold War propaganda]].{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|loc=Chapter by Sebastian Cox (2006) &quot;The Dresden Raids: Why and How&quot;, p. 28}}

===Military and industrial profile===
[[File:1945-02-15GerWW2BattlefrontAtlas.jpg|thumb|right|Situation of battlefronts in Europe by the time of Dresden bombings. The white-colored areas were held by Germany, the rose ones by the Allies, and the bright-red color denotes the Allied advances in the fronts]]
Dresden was Germany's seventh-largest city and, according to the RAF at the time, the largest remaining unbombed built-up area.{{sfn|Ross|2003|p=180}} Taylor writes that an official 1942 guide to the city described it as &quot;one of the foremost industrial locations of the [[Third Reich|Reich]]&quot; and in 1944 the [[German Army High Command]]'s Weapons Office listed 127 medium-to-large factories and workshops that were supplying the army with [[materiel]]&lt;!--not a spelling mistake this is a from the French and used for military material --&gt;.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=169}} Nonetheless, according to some historians, the contribution of Dresden to the German war effort may not have been as significant as the planners thought.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|loc=Chapter by Sonke Neitzel &quot;The City Under Attack&quot; p. 76}}

The [[Air Force Historical Research Agency|US Air Force Historical Division]] wrote a report in response to the international concern about the bombing - the report remained [[Classified information|classified]] until December 1978.{{sfn|Ross|2003|p=184}} This said that there were 110 factories and 50,000 workers in the city supporting the German war effort at the time of the raid.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Angell|1953}}: Cites &quot;Dresden, Germany, City Area, Economic Reports&quot;, Vol. No. 2, Headquarters U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey, 10 July 1945; and &quot;OSS&quot; London, No. B-1799/4, 3 March 1945.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the report, there were aircraft components factories; a [[poison gas]] factory (Chemische Fabrik Goye and Company); an [[anti-aircraft]] and [[field gun]] factory (Lehman); an optical goods factory ([[Zeiss Ikon]] AG); as well as factories producing electrical and X-ray apparatus (Koch &amp; Sterzel AG); gears and differentials (Saxoniswerke); and electric gauges (Gebrüder Bassler). It also said there were barracks, hutted camps, and a [[munitions]] storage depot.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Angell|1953}}: Cites &quot;Interpretation Report No. K. 4171, Dresden, 22 March 1945&quot;, Supporting Document No. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The USAF report also states that two of Dresden's traffic routes were of military importance: north-south from Germany to [[Czechoslovakia]], and east-west along the [[central European uplands]].&lt;ref name=ChambersUSAFHD&gt;{{harvnb|Angell|1953}}: Cites Chambers Encyclopedia, New York, 1950, Vol. IV, p. 636,&lt;/ref&gt; The city was at the junction of the [[Berlin]]-[[Prague]]-[[Vienna]] railway line, as well as the [[Munich]]-[[Breslau]], and [[Hamburg]]-[[Leipzig]] lines.&lt;ref name=ChambersUSAFHD/&gt; Colonel Harold E. Cook, a US [[Prisoner of war|POW]] held in the [[Friedrichstadt (Dresden)|Friedrichstadt]] marshaling yard the night before the attacks, later said that &quot;I saw with my own eyes that Dresden was an armed camp: thousands of German troops, tanks and artillery and miles of freight cars loaded with supplies supporting and transporting German [[Military logistics|logistics]] towards the east to meet the Russians&quot;.{{sfn|Miller|2006b|p=435}}

An RAF memo issued to airmen on the night of the attack indicated that a secondary purpose of the raid was to &quot;show the Russians when they arrive [at Dresden] what [the British] [[RAF Bomber Command|Bomber Command]] can do.&quot; The memo stated:

{{quotation|Dresden, the seventh largest city in Germany and not much smaller than [[Manchester]] is also the largest unbombed builtup area the enemy has got. In the midst of winter with [[refugee]]s pouring westward and troops to be rested, roofs are at a premium, not only to give shelter to workers, refugees, and troops alike, but to house the administrative services displaced from other areas. At one time well known for its [[Porcelain|china]], Dresden has developed into an industrial city of first-class importance.... The intentions of the attack are to hit the enemy where he will feel it most, behind an already partially collapsed front... and incidentally to show the Russians when they arrive what [[RAF Bomber Command|Bomber Command]] can do.{{sfn|Ross|2003|p=180}}{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=333}} }}

In the raid, major industrial areas in the suburbs, which stretched for miles, were not targeted.{{sfn|McKee|1983|p=62}} According to historian [[Donald L. Miller|Donald Miller]], &quot;the economic disruption would have been far greater had Bomber Command targeted the suburban areas where most of Dresden's manufacturing might was concentrated&quot;.{{sfn|Miller|2006a|p=437}}

==The attacks==

===The night of 13/14 February===
[[File:De Havilland Mosquito-DK338-1942.jpg|thumb|right|[[de Havilland Mosquito|Mosquito marker planes]] dropped the target indicators, which glowed red and green to guide the bombers.]]

The Dresden attack was to have begun with a [[United States Army Air Forces|USAAF]] [[Eighth Air Force]] bombing raid on 13 February 1945. The Eighth Air Force had already bombed the railway yards near the centre of the city twice in daytime raids: once on 7 October 1944 with 70 tons of [[high-explosive]] bombs killing more than 400,&lt;ref&gt;Hahn, Alfred and Neef, Ernst. ''Dresden. Werte unserer Heimat''. Bd. 42. Berlin 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; then again with 133 bombers on 16 January 1945, dropping 279 tons of high-explosives and 41 tons of [[Incendiary device|incendiaries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHD&quot;/&gt;

On 13 February 1945, bad weather over Europe prevented any USAAF operations, and it was left to [[RAF Bomber Command]] to carry out the first raid. It had been decided that the raid would be a double strike, in which a second wave of bombers would attack three hours after the first, just as the rescue teams were trying to put out the fires.{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|pp=203–206}} Other raids were carried out that night to confuse [[Defense of the Reich|German air defences]]. Three hundred and sixty heavy bombers ([[Avro Lancaster|Lancasters]] and [[Handley Page Halifax|Halifaxes]]) bombed a synthetic oil plant in [[Böhlen]], {{convert|60|mi|km}} from Dresden, while [[de Havilland Mosquito]] medium bombers attacked [[Magdeburg]], [[Bonn]], Misburg near [[Hanover]] and [[Nuremberg]].{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|p=205}}

When Polish crews of the designated squadrons were preparing for the mission, the terms of the Yalta agreement were made known to them. There was a huge uproar, since the Yalta agreement handed parts of Poland over to the Soviet Union. There was talk of mutiny among the Polish pilots, and their British officers removed their side arms. The Polish Government ordered the pilots to follow their orders and fly their missions over Dresden, which they did.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Halik Kochanski|title=The Eagle Unbowed: Poland and the Poles in the Second World War|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=Cambridge|year=2012|page=498|isbn=0-674-06814-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lancaster I NG128 Dropping Blockbuster - Duisburg - Oct 14, 1944.jpg|thumb|left|A [[Avro Lancaster|Lancaster]] releases the main part of its load, a {{convert|4000|lb|abbr=on}} HC [[Blockbuster bomb|&quot;cookie&quot;]] and 108 {{convert|30|lb|abbr=on}} &quot;J&quot; incendiaries. (over Duisburg 1944)]]

The first of the British aircraft took off at around 17:20 hours [[Central European Time|CET]] for the {{convert|700|mi|km|sing=on}} journey.{{efn|All raid times are [[Central European Time|CET]]; Britain was on [[double summer time]] in early 1945, which was the same time as CET.}} This was a group of [[Avro Lancaster|Lancasters]] from Bomber Command's [[No. 83 Squadron RAF|83 Squadron]], [[No. 5 Group RAF|No. 5 Group]], acting as the [[Pathfinder (RAF)|Pathfinders]], or flare force, whose job it was to find Dresden and drop [[magnesium]] parachute flares, known to the Germans as &quot;Christmas trees&quot;, to light up the area for the bombers. The next set of aircraft to leave England were twin-engined [[de Havilland Mosquito|Mosquito marker planes]], which would identify target areas and drop 1,000-pound [[target indicator]]s (TIs)&quot;{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=6}} that created a red glow for the bombers to aim at.{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|pp=203–4}} The attack was to centre on the [[Ostragehege]] sports stadium, next to the city's medieval ''Altstadt'' (old town), with its congested, and highly combustible timbered buildings.{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|pp=209}}

The main bomber force, called ''Plate Rack'', took off shortly after the Pathfinders. This group of 254 Lancasters carried 500 tons of high explosives and 375 tons of [[Incendiary device|incendiaries]] (&quot;fire bombs&quot;). There were 200,000 incendiaries in all, with the high-explosive bombs ranging in weight from 500 pounds to 4,000 pounds—the so-called two-ton ''[[Blockbuster bomb|cookies]]'',{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|pp=209}} also known as &quot;blockbusters,&quot; because they could destroy an entire large building or street. The high explosives were intended to rupture water mains and blow off roofs, doors, and windows to create an air flow to feed the fires caused by the incendiaries that followed.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=287, 296, 365}}{{sfn|Longmate|1983|pp=162–164}}

The Lancasters crossed into French [[airspace]] near the [[Somme (river)|Somme]], then into Germany just north of [[Cologne]]. At 22:00 hours, the force heading for Böhlen split away from Plate Rack, which turned south east toward the Elbe. By this time, ten of the Lancasters were out of service, leaving 244 to continue to Dresden.{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|p=206}}

The sirens started sounding in Dresden at 21:51 (CET).{{efn|During the Second World War, Britain was on summer time and [[double summer time]] or UTC+1 and UTC+2, the same as CET and CET+1}}{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=4}} [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]] [[Maurice A Smith|Maurice Smith]], flying in a Mosquito, gave the order to the Lancasters: &quot;Controller to Plate Rack Force: Come in and bomb glow of red target indicators as planned. Bomb the glow of red TIs as planned.&quot;.&lt;ref name=Burleigh&gt;Burleigh, Michael. [http://books.guardian.co.uk/reviews/history/0,6121,1142632,00.html &quot;Mission accomplished&quot;], ''The Guardian'', 7 February 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The first bombs were released at 22:14, the Lancasters flying in at {{convert|8000|ft|m}},{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|p=210}} with all but one Lancaster's bombs released within two minutes, and the last one releasing at 22:22. The fan-shaped area that was bombed was {{convert|1.25|mi|km}} long, and at its extreme about {{convert|1.75|mi|km}} wide. The shape and total devastation of the area was created by the bombers of No. 5 Group flying over the head of the fan ([[Ostragehege]] stadium) on prearranged compass bearings and releasing their bombs at different prearranged times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/history/bombercommanddresdenfebruary1945.cfm|title=Dresden, February 1945 |publisher=RAF|accessdate=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=277–288}}

The second attack, three hours later, was by Lancaster aircraft of [[No. 1 Group RAF|1]], [[No. 3 Group RAF|3]], [[No. 6 Group RAF|6]] and [[No. 8 Group RAF|8]] [[List of Royal Air Force groups|Groups]], 8 Group being the Pathfinders. By now, the thousands of fires from the burning city could be seen more than {{convert|60|mi|km}} away on the ground, and {{convert|500|mi|km}} away in the air, with smoke rising to {{convert|15000|ft|m}}.&lt;ref name=BBCOnthisDay&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/14/newsid_3549000/3549905.stm &quot;14 February 1945: Thousands of bombs destroy Dresden&quot;], BBC ''On this Day'', 14 February 1945. Retrieved 10 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The Pathfinders therefore decided to expand the target, dropping flares on either side of the firestorm, including the ''[[Dresden Hauptbahnhof|Hauptbahnhof]]'', the main train station, and the ''[[Großer Garten]]'', a large park, both of which had escaped damage during the first raid. The German sirens sounded again at 01:05, but as there was practically no electricity, these were small hand-held sirens that were heard within only a block.{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|p=206}} Between 01:21 and 01:45, 529 Lancasters dropped more than 1,800 tons of bombs.

===14–15 February===
On the morning of 14 February 431 bombers of the 1st Bombardment Division of the United States [[VIII Bomber Command]] were scheduled to bomb Dresden at around midday, and the 3rd Bombardment Division were to follow the 1st and bomb [[Chemnitz]], while the 2nd Bombardment Division would bomb a [[Brabag|synthetic oil]] plant in [[Magdeburg]]. The bomber groups would be protected by the 784 [[North American P-51 Mustang]]s of [[VIII Fighter Command]], which meant that there would be almost 2,100 aircraft of the United States [[Eighth Air Force]] over Saxony during 14 February.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=364}}

There is some confusion in the primary sources over what was the target in Dresden, whether it was the [[marshalling yard]]s near the centre or centre of the built up area. The report by the 1st Bombardment Division's commander to his commander states that the targeting sequence was the centre of the built up area in Dresden if the weather was clear. If clouds obscured Dresden but Chemnitz was clear, Chemnitz was the target. If both were obscured, they would bomb the centre of Dresden using [[H2X radar]].{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=365}} The mix of bombs for the Dresden raid was about 40% incendiaries—much closer to the RAF city busting mix than that the USAAF usually used in precision bombardment.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=366}} Taylor compares this 40% mix with the [[Bombing of Berlin in World War II#March 1944 to April 1945|raid on Berlin]] on 3 February, where the ratio was 10% incendiaries. This was a common mix when the USAAF anticipated cloudy conditions over the target.{{sfn|Davis|2006|pp=425, 504}}

316 [[B-17 Flying Fortress]]es bombed Dresden, dropping 771 tons of bombs.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|p=65}}{{sfn|Davis|2006|p=504}} The rest misidentified their targets. Sixty [[bombing of Prague in World War II|bombed Prague]], dropping 153 tons of bombs on the Czech city while others bombed [[Brux (city)|Brux]] and [[Plzeň|Pilsen]].{{sfn|Davis|2006|p=504}} The 379th bombardment group started to bomb Dresden at 12:17 aiming at marshalling yards in the Friedrichstadt district west of the city centre as the area was not obscured by smoke and cloud. The 303rd group arrived over Dresden 2 minutes after the 379th found that their view was obscured by clouds so they bombed Dresden using [[H2X radar]] to target this location. The groups that followed the 303rd, (92nd, 306th, 379th, 384th and 457th) also found Dresden obscured by clouds and they too used H2X to locate the target. H2X aiming caused the groups to bomb inaccurately with a wide dispersal over the Dresden area. The last group to bomb Dresden was the 306th and they had finished by 12:30.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=374}}

[[Strafing]] of civilians has become a traditional part of the oral history of the raids since a March 1945 article in the Nazi-run weekly newspaper ''[[Das Reich (newspaper)|Das Reich]]'' claimed that this had occurred.{{efn|Civilian strafing was in fact a regular practice of the Luftwaffe throughout the war.{{sfn|Neitzel|Welzer|2012|pp=57–58}} }} Historian Götz Bergander, who was himself an eyewitness of the raids, found no reports on strafing for 13–15 February, neither by any of the pilots nor by the German military and police. He asserted in ''Dresden im Luftkrieg'' (1977) that only a few tales of civilians being strafed were reliable in details, and all were related to the daylight attack on 14 February. He concluded that some memory of eyewitnesses was real, but that it had misinterpreted the firing in an airfight as being deliberately aimed at people on the ground.{{sfn|Bergander|1998|pp=204–209}} In 2000, historian Helmut Schnatz found that there was an explicit order to RAF pilots not to strafe civilians on the way back home from Dresden. He also reconstructed timelines with the result that strafing would have been almost impossible due to lack of time and fuel.&lt;ref&gt;Helmut Schnatz, ''Tiefflieger über Dresden? Legenden und Wirklichkeit'' (Böhlau, 2000, ISBN 3-412-13699-9), pp. 96, 99&lt;/ref&gt; Frederick Taylor in ''Dresden'' (2004), basing most of his analysis on the work of Bergander and Schnatz, concludes that no strafing took place, although some stray bullets from an aerial dog fight may have hit the ground and been mistaken for strafing by those in the vicinity.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|loc=Appendix A. &quot;The Massacre at Elbe Meadows&quot;}} The official historical commission collected 103 detailed eyewitness accounts and let the local bomb disposal services search according to their assertions: They found no bullets or fragments that would have been used by planes of the Dresden raids.{{sfn|Neutzner|2010|pp=71–80}}

On 15 February, the 1st Bombardment Division's primary target—the [[Böhlen]] synthetic oil plant near [[Leipzig]]—was obscured by cloud, so the Division's groups diverted to their secondary target, Dresden. Dresden was also obscured by clouds, so the groups targeted the city using H2X. The first group to arrive over the target was the 401st, but it missed the city centre and bombed Dresden's southeastern suburbs, with bombs also landing on the nearby towns of [[Meissen]] and [[Pirna]]. The other groups all bombed Dresden between 12:00 and 12:10. They failed to hit the marshalling yards in the Friedrichstadt district and, as on the previous raid, their ordnance scattered over a wide area.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=392, 393}}

===German defensive action===
Dresden's air defenses had been depleted by the need for more weaponry to fight the Red Army, and the city lost its last heavy flak battery in January 1945. By this point in the war, the Luftwaffe was seriously hampered by a shortage of both pilots and aircraft fuel; the German radar system had also been degraded, lowering the warning time to prepare for air attacks. The RAF also had an advantage over the Germans in the field of electronic radar countermeasures.{{sfn|Biddle|2008|pp=418, 421}}

Of a total of 796 British bombers that participated in the raid, six bombers were lost, three of those hit by bombs dropped by aircraft flying over them. On the following day, a single US bomber was shot down, as the large escort force was able to prevent Luftwaffe day fighters from disrupting the attack.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|pp=66-68}}

===On the ground===
[[File:Fotothek df ps 0000047 Eine Mutter über dem Kinderwagen ihrer Zwillinge im Tode.jpg|thumb|right|Bodies of civilian casualties]] {{quotation|It is not possible to describe! Explosion after explosion. It was beyond belief, worse than the blackest nightmare. So many people were horribly burnt and injured. It became more and more difficult to breathe. It was dark and all of us tried to leave this cellar with inconceivable panic. Dead and dying people were trampled upon, luggage was left or snatched up out of our hands by rescuers. The basket with our twins covered with wet cloths was snatched up out of my mother's hands and we were pushed upstairs by the people behind us. We saw the burning street, the falling ruins and the terrible firestorm. My mother covered us with wet blankets and coats she found in a water tub.

We saw terrible things: cremated adults shrunk to the size of small children, pieces of arms and legs, dead people, whole families burnt to death, burning people ran to and fro, burnt coaches filled with civilian refugees, dead rescuers and soldiers, many were calling and looking for their children and families, and fire everywhere, everywhere fire, and all the time the hot wind of the firestorm threw people back into the burning houses they were trying to escape from.

I cannot forget these terrible details. I can never forget them.|Lothar Metzger, survivor.&lt;ref name=Metzer&gt;&quot;Timewitnesses&quot;, moderated by Tom Halloway, ''[http://timewitnesses.org/english/~lothar.html The Fire-bombing of Dresden: An Eyewitness Account]'' Account of Lothar Metzer, recorded May 1999 in Berlin.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The sirens had started sounding in Dresden at 21:51 (CET).{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=4}} Frederick Taylor writes that the Germans could see that a large enemy bomber formation—or what they called ''&quot;ein dicker Hund&quot;'' (lit: a fat dog, a &quot;major thing&quot;)—was approaching somewhere in the east. At 21:39, the Reich Air Defence Leadership issued an enemy aircraft warning for Dresden, although, at that point, it was thought Leipzig might be the target. At 21:59, the Local Air Raid Leadership confirmed that the bombers were in the area of Dresden-[[Pirna]].{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=278, 279}} Taylor writes the city was largely undefended; a night fighter force of ten [[Messerschmitt]]s at [[Dresden Airport|Klotzsche airfield]] was scrambled, but it took them half an hour to get into an attack position. At 22:03, the Local Air Raid Leadership issued the first definitive warning: &quot;Warning! Warning! Warning! The lead aircraft of the major enemy bomber forces have changed course and are now approaching the city area&quot;.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=280}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-Z0309-310, Zerstörtes Dresden.jpg|right|thumb|Over ninety percent of the city centre was destroyed.]] {{quotation|To my left I suddenly see a woman. I can see her to this day and shall never forget it. She carries a bundle in her arms. It is a baby. She runs, she falls, and the child flies in an arc into the fire.

Suddenly, I saw people again, right in front of me. They scream and gesticulate with their hands, and then—to my utter horror and amazement—I see how one after the other they simply seem to let themselves drop to the ground. (Today I know that these unfortunate people were the victims of lack of oxygen). They fainted and then burnt to cinders.

Insane fear grips me and from then on I repeat one simple sentence to myself continuously: &quot;I don't want to burn to death&quot;. I do not know how many people I fell over. I know only one thing: that I must not burn.|Margaret Freyer, survivor.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Freyer, survivor, cited in Cary, John. &quot;The Bombing of Dresden,&quot; in ''Eyewitness To History''. New York: Avon Books, 1987, pp. 608–11. Also see [http://www.spartacus-educational.com/2WWdresden.htm &quot;Bombing of Dresden&quot;], Spartacus Educational, retrieved 8 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

There were very few public [[air raid shelter]]s—the largest, underneath the main railway station, was housing 6,000 refugees.{{sfn|Taylor|2004|pp=243–4}} As a result, most people took shelter in their cellars, but one of the air raid precautions the city had taken was to remove the thick cellar walls between rows of buildings, and replace them with thin partitions that could be knocked through in an emergency. The idea was that, as one building collapsed or filled with smoke, those using the basement as a shelter could knock the walls down and run into adjoining buildings. With the city on fire everywhere, those fleeing from one burning cellar simply ran into another, with the result that thousands of bodies were found piled up in houses at the end of city blocks.{{sfn|Bruhl|2006|p=237}}
[[File:Fotothek df ps 0000123 Frauenleichnam in einem Luftschutzkeller.jpg|thumb|upright|Body of a woman who died in an air-raid shelter]]
A Dresden police report written shortly after the attacks reported that the old town and the inner eastern suburbs had been engulfed in a single fire that had destroyed almost 12,000 dwellings.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=408}} The same report said that the raids had destroyed 24 banks, 26 insurance buildings, 31 stores and retail houses, 640 shops, 64 warehouses, 2 market halls, 31 large hotels, 26 public houses, 63 administrative buildings, 3 theatres, 18 cinemas, 11 churches, 6 chapels; 5 other cultural buildings, 19 hospitals including auxiliary, overflow hospitals, and private clinics, 39 schools, 5 consulates, the zoo, the waterworks, the railways, 19 postal facilities, 4 [[tram]] facilities, and 19 ships and barges. The [[Wehrmacht]]'s main command post in the [[Taschenbergpalais]], 19 military hospitals and a number of less significant military facilities were also destroyed.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=408}} Almost 200 factories were damaged, 136 seriously damaged (including several of the Zeiss Ikon precision optical engineering works), 28 with medium to serious damage, and 35 with light damage.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=409}}

An RAF assessment showed that 23 percent of the industrial buildings, and 56 percent of the non-industrial buildings, not counting residential buildings, had been seriously damaged. Around 78,000 dwellings had been completely destroyed; 27,700 were uninhabitable, and 64,500 damaged, but readily repairable.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;

During his post-war interrogation, [[Albert Speer]], Minister of Armaments and War Production for the Third Reich, indicated that Dresden's industrial recovery from the bombings was rapid.&lt;ref&gt;Robin Cross (1995) ''Fallen Eagle: The Last Days of the Third Reich''. London, Michael O' Mara Books: 106&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fatalities===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-08778-0001, Dresden, Tote nach Bombenangriff.jpg|thumb|left|A pile of bodies before cremation]]
According to official German report ''Tagesbefehl'' (Order of the Day) no. 47 (&quot;TB47&quot;) issued on 22 March the number of dead recovered by that date was 20,204, including 6,865 who were cremated on the ''Altmarkt'' square, and they expected that the total number of deaths would be about 25,000.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|p=75}}{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=42}}{{sfn|Evans|1996|loc=&quot;[http://www.hdot.org/en/trial/defense/evans/5-3.html The Bombing of Dresden in 1945]; [http://www.hdot.org/en/trial/defense/evans/520dv.html The real TB 47]}} Another report on 3 April put the number of corpses recovered at 22,096.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|p=75}} Three municipal and 17 rural cemeteries outside Dresden recorded up to 30 April 1945 a total of at least 21,895 buried bodies of the Dresden raids, including those cremated on the ''Altmarkt''.{{sfn|Neutzner|2010|pp=38-39}}

Between 100,000 and 200,000 refugees{{sfn|Biddle|2008|p=420}} fleeing westwards from advancing Soviet forces were in the city at the time of the bombing. Exact figures are unknown, but reliable estimates were calculated based on train arrivals, foot traffic, and the extent to which emergency accommodation had to be organised.&lt;ref name=Evans-Chapter-5.2.vii&gt;{{harvnb|Evans|1996|loc=[http://www.hdot.org/en/trial/defense/evans/520dvii.html (vii) Further misuse of figures: refugees, burials, and excavations]}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The city authorities did not distinguish between residents and refugees when establishing casualty numbers and &quot;took great pains to count all the dead, identified and unidentified&quot;.&lt;ref name=Evans-Chapter-5.2.vii/&gt; This was largely achievable because most of the dead succumbed to suffocation; in only four places were recovered remains so badly burned that it proved impossible to ascertain the number of victims. The uncertainty introduced by this is thought to amount to a total of no more than 100.&lt;ref name=Evans-Chapter-5.2.vii/&gt; 35,000 people were registered with the authorities as missing after the raids, around 10,000 of whom were later found alive.&lt;ref name=Evans-Chapter-5.2.vii/&gt;

A further 1,858 bodies were discovered during the reconstruction of Dresden between the end of the war and 1966.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|loc=last page of Appendix B p.509}} Since 1989, despite extensive excavation for new buildings, no war-related bodies have been found.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=509}} Seeking to establish a definitive casualty figure, in part to address propagandisation of the bombing by far-right groups, the Dresden city council in 2005 authorized an independent Historian's Commission (Historikerkommission) to conduct a new, thorough investigation, collecting and evaluating available sources. The results were published 2010 and stated that a minimum of 22,700&lt;ref name=&quot;Shortnews&quot;&gt;{{citation |author=Shortnews staff |date=14 April 2010 |url=http://www.shortnews.de/id/826593/alliierte-bombenangriffe-auf-dresden-1945-zahl-der-todesopfer-korrigiert |title=Alliierte Bombenangriffe auf Dresden 1945: Zahl der Todesopfer korrigiert |language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a maximum of 25,000 people&lt;ref name=&quot;Rolf&quot;&gt;{{citation |editor-first=Rolf-Dieter |editor-last=Müller |editor2-first=Nicole |editor2-last=Schönherr |editor3-first=Thomas |editor3-last=Widera |title=Die Zerstörung Dresdens: 13. bis 15. Februar 1945. Gutachten und Ergebnisse der Dresdner Historikerkommission zur Ermittlung der Opferzahlen. |publisher=V&amp;R Unipress |year=2010 |isbn=3899717732 |language=de |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=02xJmNFrjY0C&amp;pg=PA48 48]}}&lt;/ref&gt; were killed.

==Wartime political responses==

===German===
Development of a German political response to the raid took several turns. Initially, some of the leadership, especially [[Robert Ley]] and [[Joseph Goebbels]], wanted to use it as a pretext for abandonment of the [[Geneva Conventions]] on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]]. In the end, the only political action the German government took was to exploit it for propaganda purposes.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=420–6}} Goebbels is reported to have wept with rage for twenty minutes after he heard the news of the catastrophe, before launching into a bitter attack on [[Hermann Göring]], the commander of the Luftwaffe: &quot;If I had the power I would drag this cowardly good-for-nothing, this Reich marshal, before a court. ... How much guilt does this parasite not bear for all this, which we owe to his indolence and love of his own comforts. ...&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Victor Reimann (1979) ''Joseph Goebbels: The Man Who Created Hitler''. London, Sphere: 382–3&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 February, the [[Ministry of Public Enlightenment and Propaganda|Propaganda Ministry]] issued a press release that stated that Dresden had no war industries; it was a city of culture.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|pp=421-422}}

On 25 February, a new leaflet with photographs of two burned children was released under the title &quot;Dresden—Massacre of Refugees,&quot; stating that 200,000 had died. Since no official estimate had been developed, the numbers were speculative, but newspapers such as the [[Stockholm]] ''Svenska Morgonbladet'' used phrases such as &quot;privately from Berlin,&quot; to explain where they had obtained the figures.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=423}} Frederick Taylor states that &quot;there is good reason to believe that later in March copies of—or extracts from—[an official police report] were leaked to the neutral press by Goebbels's Propaganda Ministry ... doctored with an extra zero to make [the total dead from the raid] 202,040&quot;.{{sfn|Taylor|2004|p=370}} On 4 March, ''[[Das Reich (newspaper)|Das Reich]]'', a weekly newspaper founded by Goebbels, published a lengthy article emphasizing the suffering and destruction of a cultural icon, without mentioning any damage the attacks had caused to the German war effort.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=424}}&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Richard. ''Telling Lies about Hitler: The Holocaust, History and the David Irving Trial'' p. 165.&lt;/ref&gt;

Taylor writes that this propaganda was effective, as it not only influenced attitudes in neutral countries at the time, but also reached the [[British House of Commons]] when [[Richard Stokes]], a [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] [[Member of Parliament]] (MP), a long term opponent of area-bombing,&lt;ref&gt;Max Hastings (1980) ''Bomber Command'': 171–2&lt;/ref&gt; quoted information from the German Press Agency (controlled by the Propaganda Ministry). It was Stokes' questions in the House of Commons that were in large part responsible for the shift in the UK against this type of raid. Taylor suggests that, although the destruction of Dresden would have affected people's support for the Allies regardless of German propaganda, at least some of the outrage did depend on Goebbels' massaging of the casualty figures.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=426}}

===British===
[[File:Churchill portrait NYP 45063.jpg|thumb|upright|British Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]] was ultimately responsible for the bombing even though he later tried to distance himself from it.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=345}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.learningcurve.gov.uk/heroesvillains/g1/ Churchill and the Bombing of Dresden]&lt;/ref&gt; ]]
The destruction of the city provoked unease in intellectual circles in Britain. According to [[Max Hastings]], by February 1945, attacks upon German cities had become largely irrelevant to the outcome of the war and the name of Dresden resonated with cultured people all over Europe—&quot;the home of so much charm and beauty, a refuge for [[Anthony Trollope|Trollope's]] heroines, a landmark of the [[Grand Tour]].&quot; He writes that the bombing was the first time the public in Allied countries seriously questioned the military actions used to defeat the Germans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.royalacademy.org.uk/ ''RA Magazine''], Vol 78, Spring 2003. Retrieved 26 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The unease was made worse by an [[Associated Press]] story that the Allies had resorted to [[terror bombing]]. At a press briefing held by the [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force]] two days after the raids, British Air Commodore [[Colin McKay Grierson]] told journalists:

{{quotation|First of all they (Dresden and similar towns) are the centres to which evacuees are being moved. They are centres of communications through which traffic is moving across to the Russian Front, and from the Western Front to the East, and they are sufficiently close to the Russian Front for the Russians to continue the successful prosecution of their battle. I think these three reasons probably cover the bombing.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=413}} }}

One of the journalists asked whether the principal aim of bombing Dresden would be to cause confusion among the refugees or to blast communications carrying military supplies. Grierson answered that the primary aim was to attack communications to prevent the Germans from moving military supplies, and to stop movement in all directions if possible. He then added in an offhand remark that the raid also helped destroy &quot;what is left of German morale.&quot; Howard Cowan, an Associated Press war correspondent, subsequently filed a story saying that the Allies had resorted to terror bombing. There were follow-up newspaper editorials on the issue and a longtime opponent of strategic bombing, Richard Stokes [[Member of Parliament|MP]], asked questions in the House of Commons on 6 March.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=344}}{{sfn|Taylor|2004|p=363}}

Churchill subsequently distanced himself from the bombing.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=345}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Churchill HMSO&quot;&gt;&quot;The Strategic Air Offensive against Germany&quot; (SOA), HMSO (1961) vol 3 pp. 117–9.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=431}} On 28 March, in a memo sent by telegram to [[Hastings Lionel Ismay|General Ismay]] for the British Chiefs of Staff and the Chief of the Air Staff, he wrote:

{{quotation|It seems to me that the moment has come when the question of bombing of German cities simply for the sake of increasing the terror, though under other pretexts, should be reviewed. Otherwise we shall come into control of an utterly ruined land… The destruction of Dresden remains a serious query against the conduct of Allied bombing. I am of the opinion that military objectives must henceforward be more strictly studied in our own interests than that of the enemy.

The Foreign Secretary has spoken to me on this subject, and I feel the need for more precise concentration upon military objectives such as oil and communications behind the immediate battle-zone, rather than on mere acts of terror and wanton destruction, however impressive.&lt;ref name=Siebert&gt;Siebert, Detlef. [http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/area_bombing_01.shtml &quot;British Bombing Strategy in World War Two&quot;], 1 August 2001, BBC, retrieved 8 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=430}} }}
[[File:Air Chief Marshal Sir Arthur Harris.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Air Chief Marshal [[Sir Arthur Harris, 1st Baronet|Arthur Harris]], head of [[RAF Bomber Command]], strongly objected to Churchill's comparison of the raid to an &quot;act of terror,&quot; a comment Churchill withdrew in the face of Harris's protest.]]

Having been given a paraphrased version of Churchill's memo by Bottomley, on 29 March, Air Chief Marshal [[Sir Arthur Harris, 1st Baronet|Arthur Harris]] wrote to the Air Ministry:{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=432}} {{quotation|I ... assume that the view under consideration is something like this: no doubt in the past we were justified in attacking German cities. But to do so was always repugnant and now that the Germans are beaten anyway we can properly abstain from proceeding with these attacks. This is a doctrine to which I could never subscribe. Attacks on cities like any other act of war are intolerable unless they are strategically justified. But they are strategically justified in so far as they tend to shorten the war and preserve the lives of Allied soldiers. To my mind we have absolutely no right to give them up unless it is certain that they will not have this effect. I do not personally regard the whole of the remaining cities of Germany as worth the bones of one British Grenadier.

The feeling, such as there is, over Dresden, could be easily explained by any psychiatrist. It is connected with German bands and Dresden shepherdesses. Actually Dresden was a mass of munitions works, an intact government centre, and a key transportation point to the East. It is now none of these things.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=346}} }}

The phrase &quot;worth the bones of one British grenadier&quot; echoed a famous sentence used by [[Otto von Bismarck]]: &quot;The whole of the Balkans is not worth the bones of a single Pomeranian grenadier&quot;.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=432}} Under pressure from the Chiefs of Staff and in response to the views expressed by Portal and Harris among others, Churchill withdrew his memo and issued a new one.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=346}}&lt;ref&gt;Harris quotes as his source the Public Records Office ATH/DO/4B quoted by Lord Zuckerman &quot;From Apes to Warlords&quot; p. 352.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=433}} This was completed on 1 April 1945:

{{quotation|It seems to me that the moment has come when the question of the so called 'area-bombing' of German cities should be reviewed from the point of view of our own interests. If we come into control of an entirely ruined land, there will be a great shortage of accommodation for ourselves and our allies. ... We must see to it that our attacks do no more harm to ourselves in the long run than they do to the enemy's war effort.{{sfn|Longmate|1983|p=34}}{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=434}} }}

==Timeline==
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;margin:0 auto 0 auto;&quot;
|+Table of the air raids on Dresden by the Allies during World War II.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;
|-
!Date
!Target area
!Force
!Aircraft
!High explosive&lt;br /&gt;bombs on target&lt;br /&gt;(tons)
!Incendiary&lt;br /&gt;bombs on target&lt;br /&gt;(tons)
!Total tonnage
|-
|7 October 1944
|Marshalling yards
|8th AF
|30
|72.5
|—
|72.5
|-
|16 January 1945
|Marshalling yards
|8th AF
|133
|279.8
|41.6
|321.4
|-
|14 February 1945
|City area
|RAF BC
|772
|1477.7
|1181.6
|2659.3
|-
|14 February 1945
|Marshalling yards
|8th AF
|316
|487.7
|294.3
|782.0
|-
|15 February 1945
|Marshalling yards
|8th AF
|211
|465.6
|—
|465.6
|-
|2 March 1945
|Marshalling yards
|8th AF
|406
|940.3
|140.5
|1080.8
|-
|17 April 1945
|Marshalling yards
|8th AF
|572
|1526.4
|164.5
|1690.9
|-
|17 April 1945
|Industrial area
|8th AF
|8
|28.0
|—
|28.0
|}

==Reconstruction and reconciliation==
{{Further|Dresden Frauenkirche|Semperoper|Zwinger (Dresden)|Coventry Cathedral}}
[[File:FrauenkircheCataloguedFragments gobeirne (cropped).jpg|thumb|Catalogued fragments of the [[Dresden Frauenkirche|Frauenkirche]] in 1999]]
[[File:Semperoper at night.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Semperoper]], the Dresden state opera house, in 2007. It was destroyed during the bombing, and was rebuilt in 1985. It opened exactly 40 years after the bombing on 13 February with the same opera that was last performed before its destruction, ''[[Der Freischütz]]'' by [[Carl Maria von Weber]].]]

After the war, and again after [[German reunification]], great efforts were made to rebuild some of Dresden's former landmarks, such as the [[Dresden Frauenkirche|Frauenkirche]], the [[Semperoper]] (the Saxony state opera house) and the [[Zwinger Palace]] (the latter two were rebuilt before reunification).

In 1956, Dresden entered a twin-town relationship with [[Coventry]]. As a centre of military and munitions production, Coventry suffered some of the worst attacks on any British city at the hands of the Luftwaffe during the [[Coventry Blitz]]es of 1940 and 1941, which killed over 1,200 civilians and destroyed its [[Coventry Cathedral|cathedral]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.familyresearcher.co.uk/CoventryRaids.htm Coventry Air Raids], The Coventry Blitz Resource centre.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Semper Synagogue|Dresden synagogue]], which was burned during ''[[Kristallnacht]]'' on 9 November 1938, was rebuilt in 2001 and opened for worship on 9 November and is called the [[New Synagogue, Dresden|New Synagogue]]. The original synagogue's [[Star of David]] was installed above the entrance of the new building—Alfred Neugebauer, a local firefighter, saved it from the fire and hid it in his home until the end of the war. Dresden's Jewish population declined from 4675 in 1933, to 1265 in 1941 (the eve of the implementation of the Nazis' extermination programme), to just a handful after almost all of those who had remained were forcibly sent to [[Riga]], [[Auschwitz]] and [[Theresienstadt]] between 1941 and 1945.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|loc=Chapter by Jeremy Crang (2006) &quot;Victor Klemperer's Dresden&quot; pp. 83–3}} On the morning of 13 February 1945, the Jews remaining in Dresden were ordered to report for deportation on 16 February. But as one of them, [[Victor Klemperer]], recorded in his diaries: &quot;... on the evening of this 13 February the catastrophe overtook Dresden: the bombs fell, the houses collapsed, the phosphorus flowed, the burning beams crashed on to the heads of Aryans and non-Aryans alike and Jew and Christian met death in the same firestorm; whoever of the [Jews] was spared by this night was delivered, for in the general chaos he could escape the [[Gestapo]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''I Shall Bear Witness: The Diaries of Victor Klemperer 1933–41'' edited by Martin Chalmers (1998). London, Weidenfield and Nicolson: ix, xvii, xxii&lt;/ref&gt; But in recent years the Jewish population has increased in Dresden, as it has elsewhere in Germany.&lt;ref name=BBCNov92001&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1647310.stm Dresden synagogue rises again], BBC News, 9 November 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Paul Spiegel]], the then head of [[Central Council of Jews in Germany]], called the new synagogue a concrete expression of the Jewish community's desire to stay.&lt;ref name=BBCNov92001/&gt;
[[File:Dresden Abschluss Dixieland 2010 mit PD Dresden.jpg|thumb|The reconstructed Frauenkirche is again a part of the baroque skyline of Dresden]]
In 1990, after the [[fall of the Berlin Wall]], a group of prominent Dresdeners formed an international appeal known as the &quot;Call from Dresden&quot; to request help in rebuilding the [[Martin Luther|Lutheran]] Frauenkirche, the destruction of which had over the years become a symbol of the bombing.&lt;ref name=Boobbyer&gt;Boobbyer, Philip. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0KZH/is_4_19/ai_n16621314/pg_1 &quot;Answering Dresden's Call&quot;], ''For a Change'', August–September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The baroque Church of Our Lady (completed in 1743) had initially appeared to survive the raids, but collapsed a few days later, and the ruins were left in place by later Communist governments as a symbol of British aggression.
[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F088675-0031, Dresden, Ruine der Frauenkirche.jpg|thumb|left|The ruins of the [[Dresden Frauenkirche|Frauenkirche]] in 1991]]
A British charity, the Dresden Trust, was formed in 1993 to raise funds in response to the call for help, raising £600,000 from 2,000 people and 100 companies and trusts in Britain. One of the gifts they made to the project was an eight-metre high orb and cross made in London by goldsmiths Gant MacDonald, using medieval nails recovered from the ruins of the roof of [[Coventry Cathedral]], and crafted in part by Alan Smith, the son of a pilot who took part in the raid.&lt;ref name=Furlong&gt;Furlong, Ray. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3830135.stm Dresden ruins finally restored], BBC News, 22 June 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

During her visit to Germany in November 2004, [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Queen Elizabeth II]] hosted a concert in Berlin to raise money for the reconstruction of the Frauenkirche. The visit was accompanied by speculation in the British and German press, fueled mostly by the tabloids, over a possible apology for the attacks, but none was forthcoming.

The new Frauenkirche—reconstructed over seven years by architects using 3D computer technology to analyse old photographs and every piece of rubble that had been kept—was formally [[consecration|consecrated]] on 30 October 2005, in a service attended by some 1,800 guests, including Germany's president, [[Horst Köhler]]; previous and current chancellors, [[Gerhard Schröder]] and [[Angela Merkel]]; and [[Prince Edward, Duke of Kent|the Duke of Kent]].&lt;ref name=HardingOct2005&gt;Harding, Luke. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/secondworldwar/story/0,14058,1605133,00.html Cathedral hit by RAF is rebuilt], ''The Guardian'', 31 October 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-war debate==
British historian [[Frederick Taylor (historian)|Frederick Taylor]] wrote of the attacks: &quot;The destruction of Dresden has an epically tragic quality to it. It was a wonderfully beautiful city and a symbol of baroque humanism and all that was best in Germany. It also contained all of the worst from Germany during the [[Nazi]] period. In that sense it is an absolutely exemplary tragedy for the horrors of 20th century warfare and a symbol of destruction&quot;.&lt;ref name=Hawley&gt;Hawley, Charles. [http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,341239,00.html &quot;Dresden Bombing Is To Be Regretted Enormously&quot;], interview with Frederick Taylor, ''Spiegel Online'', 11 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Several factors have made the bombing a unique point of contention and debate. First among these are the Nazi governments exaggerated claims immediately afterwards,{{sfn|Bergander|1998|p=217}}{{sfn|Taylor|2004|p=370}}{{sfn|Atkinson|2013||p=535}} which drew upon the beauty of the city, its importance as a cultural icon; the deliberate creation of a firestorm; the number of victims; the extent to which it was a necessary military target; and the fact that it was attacked toward the end of the war, raising the question of whether the bombing was needed to hasten the end.

===Legal considerations===
{{See also|Aerial bombardment and international law#International law up to 1945}}
The [[Hague Conventions (1899 and 1907)|Hague Conventions]], addressing the codes of wartime conduct on land and at sea, were adopted before the rise of air power. Despite repeated diplomatic attempts to update [[international humanitarian law]] to include aerial warfare, it was not updated before the outbreak of World War II. The absence of positive international humanitarian law does not mean that the [[laws of war]] did not cover aerial warfare, but there was no general agreement of how to interpret those laws.&lt;ref&gt;Gómez, Javier Guisández. [http://www.icrc.org/web/eng/siteeng0.nsf/iwpList200/42F64C9A4212EA07C1256B66005C0BF1 &quot;The Law of Air Warfare&quot;], ''[[International Review of the Red Cross]]'', nº 323, 20 June 1998, pp. 347–63.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Falsification of evidence===
The bombing of Dresden has been used by [[Holocaust denial|Holocaust deniers]] and pro-Nazi polemicists—most notably by the British writer [[David Irving]] in his book ''[[The Destruction of Dresden]]''—in an attempt to establish a moral equivalence between the war crimes committed by the Nazi government and the killing of German civilians by Allied bombing raids.{{sfn|Shermer|Grobman|2009|p=261}} As such, &quot;grossly inflated&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Norwood, 2013, page 237&quot;/&gt; casualty figures have been promulgated over the years, many based on a figure of over 200,000 deaths quoted in a forged version of the casualty report, ''Tagesbefehl'' No. 47, that originated with Hitler's Reich Minister of Propaganda [[Joseph Goebbels]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Evans|1996|loc=&quot;[http://www.hdot.org/en/trial/defense/evans/520e.html Chapter 3: Dresden and Holocaust Denial]}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Gray |first=Charles |title=Irving v. Lipstadt |chapterurl=http://www.hdot.org/en/trial/judgement/13-54.html |chapter=Judgement: Whether Irving has bent of falsified or misrepresented evidence|accessdate=July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Gray |first=Charles |title=Irving v. Lipstadt |chapterurl=http://www.hdot.org/en/trial/judgement/11-7.html|chapter=Judgement: Irving's case as to the death toll and his use of TB47|accessdate=July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Official U.S. inquiries on justification===
There were two such inquiries conducted after the war.

====Marshall inquiry====
An inquiry conducted at the behest of U.S. Army Chief of Staff, General [[George C. Marshall]], stated the raid was justified by the available intelligence. The inquiry declared the elimination of the German ability to reinforce a counter-attack against Marshal Konev's extended line or, alternatively, to retreat and regroup using Dresden as a base of operations, were important military objectives. As Dresden had been largely untouched during the war due to its location, it was one of the few remaining functional rail and communications centres. A secondary objective was to disrupt the industrial use of Dresden for munitions manufacture, which American intelligence believed was the case. The shock to military planners and to the Allied civilian populations of the German counterattack known as the [[Battle of the Bulge]] had ended speculation that the war was almost over, and may have contributed to the decision to continue with the aerial bombardment of German cities.{{sfn|Taylor|2004|p=196}}

The inquiry concluded that by the presence of active German military units nearby, and the presence of fighters and anti-aircraft within an effective range, Dresden qualified as &quot;defended&quot;.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;&lt;!--Probably for compliance with the Draft Convention for the Protection of Civilian Populations Against New Engines of War. Amsterdam, 1938. Art 2.  http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/0/910f79361f226492c125641e004057ed?OpenDocument --&gt; By this stage in the war both the British and the Germans had integrated air defences at the national level. The German national air-defence system could be used to argue—as the tribunal did—that no German city was &quot;undefended&quot;.

Marshall's tribunal declared that no extraordinary decision was made to single out Dresden (e.g. to take advantage of the large number of refugees, or purposely terrorize the German populace). It was argued that the intent of area bombing was to disrupt communications and destroy industrial production. The American inquiry established that the Soviets, pursuant to allied agreements for the United States and the United Kingdom to provide air support for the Soviet offensive toward Berlin, had requested area bombing of Dresden to prevent a counterattack through Dresden, or the use of Dresden as a regrouping point after a strategic retreat.&lt;ref name= &quot;HABD_paragraph33-34&quot;&gt;[[#References|USAF]], II. Section ANALYSIS: Dresden as a Military Target, ¶ 33, 34.&lt;/ref&gt;

====U.S. Air Force Historical Division report====
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right; margin:0 1em 1em 2em; float:right;&quot;
|+align=&quot;bottom&quot; style=&quot;caption-side:bottom; text-align:center; font-weight:normal;&quot;|A U.S. Air Force table showing the tonnage of bombs dropped by the Allies on Germany's seven largest cities during the war.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;
|-
! rowspan=2 |City
! rowspan=2 |Population&lt;br /&gt;(1939)
!colspan=3|Tonnage
|-
!American
!British
!Total
|-
|[[Berlin]]
|4,339,000
|22,090
|45,517
|67,607
|-
|[[Hamburg]]
|1,129,000
|17,104
|22,583
|39,687
|-
|[[Munich]]
|841,000
|11,471
|7,858
|19,329
|-
|[[Cologne]]
|772,000
|10,211
|34,712
|44,923
|-
|[[Leipzig]]
|707,000
|5,410
|6,206
|11,616
|-
|[[Essen]]
|667,000
|1,518
|36,420
|37,938
|-
|[[Dresden]]
|642,000
|4,441
|2,659
|7,100
|}

A report by the U.S. Air Force Historical Division (USAFHD) analyzed the circumstances of the raid and concluded that it was militarily necessary and justified, based on the following points:&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;
# The raid had [[Military necessity|legitimate military ends]], brought about by exigent military circumstances.
# Military units and anti-aircraft defences were sufficiently close that it was not valid to consider the city &quot;undefended.&quot;
# The raid did not use extraordinary means but was comparable to other raids used against comparable targets.
# The raid was carried out through the normal chain of command, pursuant to directives and agreements then in force.
# The raid achieved the military objective, without excessive loss of civilian life.

The first point regarding the legitimacy of the raid depends on two claims: first, that the railyards subjected to American precision bombing were an important logistical target, and that the city was also an important industrial centre.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt; Even after the main firebombing, there were two further raids on the Dresden railway yards by the USAAF. The first was on 2 March 1945, by 406 B-17s, which dropped 940 tons of high-explosive bombs and 141 tons of incendiaries. The second was on 17 April, when 580 B-17s dropped 1,554 tons of high-explosive bombs and 165 tons of incendiaries.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;

As far as Dresden being a militarily significant industrial centre, an official 1942 guide described the German city as &quot;...one of the foremost industrial locations of the Reich,&quot; and in 1944, the [[German Army High Command]]'s Weapons Office listed 127 medium-to-large factories and workshops that supplied materiel to the military.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=169}} Dresden was the seventh largest German city, and by far the largest un-bombed built-up area left, and thus was contributing to the defence of Germany itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Taylor|2005|p=3}} quoting an RAF Group briefing paper.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the USAFHD, there were 110 factories and 50,000 workers supporting the German war effort in Dresden at the time of the raid.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt; These factories manufactured fuses and bombsights (at Zeiss Ikon A.G.),{{sfn|Grant|2004}} aircraft components, [[88 mm gun|anti-aircraft guns]], [[field gun]]s, and [[small arms]], [[Chemical warfare|poison gas]], [[gear]]s and [[Differential (mechanical device)|differentials]], electrical and X-ray apparatus, electric gauges, [[gas mask]]s, [[Junkers (Aircraft)|Junkers]] aircraft engines, and [[Messerschmitt]] fighter cockpit parts.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;

The second of the five points addresses the prohibition in the [[Hague Conventions (1899 and 1907)|Hague Conventions]], of &quot;attack or bombardment&quot; of &quot;undefended&quot; towns. The USAFHD report states that Dresden was protected by anti-aircraft defences, antiaircraft guns, and searchlights, under the Combined Dresden (Corps Area IV) and Berlin (Corps Area III) Luftwaffe Administration Commands.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;

The third and fourth points say that the size of the Dresden raid—in terms of numbers, types of bombs and the means of delivery—were commensurate with the military objective and similar to other Allied bombings. On 23 February 1945, the Allies [[Bombing of Pforzheim in World War II|bombed Pforzheim]] and caused an estimated 20,000 civilian fatalities; the most devastating raid on any city was on [[Bombing of Tokyo in World War II|Tokyo]] on 9–10 March (the ''Meetinghouse'' raid)&lt;ref&gt;Crane, Conrad C. &quot;[http://www.pbs.org/thewar/detail_5229.htm The War: Firebombing (Germany &amp; Japan)].&quot; [[PBS]]. Accessed 24 August 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; caused over 100,000 civilian casualties. The tonnage and types of bombs listed in the service records of the Dresden raid were comparable to (or less than) [[Throw-weight|throw weights]] of bombs dropped in other air attacks carried out in 1945. In the case of Dresden, as in many other similar attacks, the hour break in between the RAF raids was a deliberate ploy to attack the fire fighters and rescue crews.{{sfn|Taylor|2005|p=8}}

In late July 1943, the city of [[Hamburg]] was bombed in [[Operation Gomorrah]] by combined RAF and USAAF strategic bomber forces. Four major raids were carried out in the span of 10 days, of which the most notable, on 27–28 July, created a devastating [[firestorm]] effect similar to Dresden's, killing at least 45,000 people.{{sfn|Grayling|2006|p=20}} Two thirds of the remaining population reportedly fled the city after the raids.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/bombercommand/hamburg.html Hamburg, 28 July 1943] RAF Bomber Command. Retrieved 7 January 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

The fifth point is that the firebombing achieved the intended effect of disabling the industry in Dresden. It was estimated that at least 23% of the city's industrial buildings were destroyed or severely damaged. The damage to other infrastructure and communications was immense, which would have severely limited the potential use of Dresden to stop the Soviet advance. The report concludes with: {{quotation|The specific forces and means employed in the Dresden bombings were in keeping with the forces and means employed by the Allies in other aerial attacks on comparable targets in Germany. The Dresden bombings achieved the strategic objectives that underlay the attack and were of mutual importance to the Allies and the Russians.&lt;ref name=USAFHD/&gt;}}
&lt;!-- Please provide page numbers from &quot;Der Brand&quot; -- the online references cited here do not seem to support these points, and in any case are not the book itself -- Also, if the position being advanced here is that the raid was militarily unnecessary, then we need to provide reliable mainstream published sources who specifically make that point for us. For example, if a source says the Luftwaffe was short on fuel or aircraft, using that to conclude the raid was unnecessary would be synthesis, per WP:SYNT –
Countering the claim Dresden was a significant military target, Friedrich's earlier book, ''Der Brand: Deutschland im Bombenkrieg 1940–1945'' focuses on evidence showing German forces were in full retreat by February 1945. He argues the impact on civilians was out of all proportion to the military goal, reiterating the argument Allied forces were aware of the destruction caused by incendiary bombs. Friedrich also argues that the Allies had known that future attacks were likely to cause ever-increasing numbers of civilian deaths.&lt;ref&gt;Douglas Peifer [http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/GENOCIDE/reviewsw159.htm A review of ''Der Brand''] Published in November 2003, by H-German, a member of [[H-Net]] Humanities &amp; Social Sciences OnLine.&lt;/ref&gt; He suggests that, by 1945, the German air defence had collapsed. As for the counter claim nationalization of the air defence system, the [[Kammhuber Line]], meant Dresden was defended, and therefore, a permissible military target, the book calls for a closer examination. Friedrich argues given the state of the ''Luftwaffe'' after December 1944, the ability for routine air patrols was severely reduced due to fuel shortages.&lt;ref name=&quot;OM&quot;&gt;Mehr, Otto. JSTOR review of Wolfgang Birkenfeld, ''Der synthetische Treibstoff 1933–1945'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1967), 429.&lt;/ref&gt; The Allies were reportedly in complete control of the air,&lt;ref name=&quot;OM&quot;/&gt; and Germany had committed all its fighters originally dedicated to air defence at the [[Battle of the Bulge]].{{sfn|Davis|2006|p=473}} As for [[anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] guns, it took an average of 16,000 [[88 mm gun|88 mm]] [[Flak]] shells to bring down a single Allied [[heavy bomber].{{sfn|Davis|2006|p=594}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jhuapl.edu/POW/bios/murray.htm Williamson Murray], ''German Military Effectiveness'', Nautical &amp; Aviation Pub Co of Amer (July 1992), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

===Arguments against justification===
[[File:Dresden. Zwinger &amp; Sophienkirche. - Detroit Publishing Co.jpg|thumb|The [[Zwinger Palace]] in 1900]]

====Military reasons====
The journalist [[Alexander McKee (author)|Alexander McKee]] cast doubt on the meaningfulness of the list of targets mentioned in the 1953 USAF report, pointing out that the military barracks listed as a target were a long way out of the city and were not in fact targeted during the raid.{{sfn|McKee|1983|pp=61–62}} The &quot;hutted camps&quot; mentioned in the report as military targets were also not military but were camps for refugees.{{sfn|McKee|1983|pp=61–62}} It is also stated that the important Autobahn bridge to the west of the city was not targeted or attacked, and that no railway stations were on the British target maps, nor any bridges, such as the railway bridge spanning the Elbe River.{{sfn|McKee|1983|pp=62–63}} Commenting on this, McKee says: &quot;The standard whitewash gambit, both British and American, is to mention that Dresden contained targets X, Y and Z, and to let the innocent reader assume that these targets were attacked, whereas in fact the bombing plan totally omitted them and thus, except for one or two mere accidents, they escaped&quot;.{{sfn|McKee|1983|p=61}} McKee further asserts &quot;The bomber commanders were not really interested in any purely military or economic targets, which was just as well, for they knew very little about Dresden; the RAF even lacked proper maps of the city. What they were looking for was a big built up area which they could burn, and that Dresden possessed in full measure.&quot;{{sfn|McKee|1983|p=63}}

According to the historian [[Sönke Neitzel]], &quot;it is difficult to find any evidence in German documents that the destruction of Dresden had any consequences worth mentioning on the Eastern Front. The industrial plants of Dresden played no significant role in German industry at this stage in the war&quot;.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|loc=Chapter &quot;The City under Attack&quot; by Sonke Neitzel p. 76}} Wing Commander [[H. R. Allen]] said, &quot;The final phase of Bomber Command's operations was far and away the worst. Traditional British chivalry and the use of minimum force in war was to become a mockery and the outrages perpetrated by the bombers will be remembered a thousand years hence&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|McKee|1983|p=315}} quoting H. R. Allen (1972) ''The Legacy of Lord Trenchard''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Sandsteinmauerheidefriedhof.jpg|thumb|right|A memorial at cemetery Heidefriedhof in Dresden. It reads: &quot;''Wieviele starben? Wer kennt die Zahl?; An deinen Wunden sieht man die Qual; der Namenlosen die hier verbrannt; im Höllenfeuer aus Menschenhand.''&quot; (&quot;How many died? Who knows the count?; In your wounds one sees the ordeal; Of the nameless who in here were conflagrated; In the hellfire made by hands of man.&quot;)]]

=====Military facilities in the north=====
The [[Albertstadt]], in the north of Dresden, had remarkable military facilities that the bombings failed to hit. Today they are officer's schools (&quot;Offiziersschule des Heeres&quot;) for the [[Bundeswehr]] and it's [[Bundeswehr Military History Museum|military history museum]] (from prehistoric to modern times).

====As an immoral act, but not a war crime====
{{quotation|...ever since the deliberate mass bombing of civilians in the second world war, and as a direct response to it, the international community has outlawed the practice. It first tried to do so in the [[Fourth Geneva Convention]] of 1949, but the UK and the US would not agree, since to do so would have been an admission of guilt for their systematic &quot;area bombing&quot; of German and Japanese civilians.|[[A.C. Grayling]].{{sfn|Grayling|2006b}} }}

Frederick Taylor told ''[[Der Spiegel]]'', &quot;I personally find the attack on Dresden horrific. It was overdone, it was excessive and is to be regretted enormously,&quot; but, &quot;A war crime is a very specific thing which international lawyers argue about all the time and I would not be prepared to commit myself nor do I see why I should. I'm a historian.&quot;&lt;ref name=Hawley/&gt; Similarly, British philosopher [[A. C. Grayling]] has described British area bombardment as an &quot;immoral act&quot; and &quot;moral crime&quot; because &quot;destroying everything ... contravenes every moral and humanitarian principle debated in connection with [[just war|the just conduct of war]],&quot; but, &quot;It is not strictly correct to describe area bombing as a 'war crime'.&quot;.{{sfn|Grayling|2006|pp=245–246; 272-275}}

====As a war crime====
Though no one involved in the bombing of Dresden was ever charged with a war crime, some hold the opinion that the bombing was a [[war crime]].

According to Dr. [[Gregory Stanton]], lawyer and president of [[Genocide Watch]]:
{{quote|...every human being having the capacity for both good and evil. The Nazi Holocaust was among the most evil genocides in history. But the Allies’ firebombing of Dresden and nuclear destruction of Hiroshima and Nagasaki were also war crimes – and as [[Leo Kuper]] and [[Eric Markusen]] have argued, also acts of genocide. We are all capable of evil and must be restrained by law from committing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanton-1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.genocidewatch.org/HOWWECANPREVENTGENOCIDE.htm|title=How Can We Prevent Genocide: Building An International Campaign to End Genocide|last=Stanton|first=Gregory|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927005226/http://www.genocidewatch.org/HOWWECANPREVENTGENOCIDE.htm|archivedate=27 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Historian [[Donald Bloxham]] states, &quot;The bombing of Dresden on 13–14 February 1945 was a war crime&quot;.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|p=180}} He further argues there was a strong ''[[prima facie]]'' case for trying Winston Churchill among others and a theoretical case Churchill could have been found guilty. &quot;This should be a sobering thought. If, however it is also a startling one, this is probably less the result of widespread understanding of the nuance of international law and more because in the popular mind 'war criminal', like 'paedophile' or 'terrorist', has developed into a moral rather than a legal categorisation&quot;.{{sfn|Addison|Crang|2006|p=180}}

German author [[Günter Grass]] is one of several intellectuals and commentators who have also called the bombing a war crime.&lt;ref name=Elliott&gt;Elliott, Michael. [http://www.time.com/time/europe/etan/story.html Europe: Then And Now], ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' Europe, 10 August 2003. Retrieved 26 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Proponents of this position argue that the devastation from firebombing was greater than anything that could be justified by [[military necessity]] alone, and this establishes a ''prima facie'' case. The Allies were aware of the effects of firebombing, as British cities had been subject to them during [[the Blitz]].{{efn|Longmate describes a 22 September 1941 memorandum prepared by the British Air Ministry's Directorate of Bombing Operations that puts numbers to this analysis {{harv|Longmate|1983|p=122}}.}} Proponents disagree that Dresden had a military garrison and claim that most of the industry was in the outskirts and not in the targeted city centre,&lt;ref name=GG20051026&gt;Gerda Gericke (lucas) [http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,2144,1265990,00.html The Destruction of Dresden's Frauenkirche] ''[[Deutsche Welle]]'', 26 October 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; and that the cultural significance of the city should have precluded the Allies from bombing it.

British historian [[Antony Beevor]] wrote that Dresden was considered relatively safe, having been spared previous RAF night attacks, and that at the time of the raids there were up to 300,000 refugees in the area [[Flight and evacuation of German civilians during the end of World War II|seeking sanctuary]] from the advancing Russian army from the [[Eastern Front (WWII)|Eastern Front]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=83}} In ''Fire Sites'', German historian [[Jörg Friedrich (author)|Jörg Friedrich]] believes that the RAF's bombing campaign against German cities in the last months of the war served no military purpose.&lt;ref name=HardingOct2003&gt;Harding, Luke. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,3604,1067232,00.html German historian provokes row over war photos], ''The Guardian'', 21 October 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Political response in Germany====
[[File:Dresden 130205 Fronttransparent.jpg|left|thumb|A demonstration by the German [[National Democratic Party of Germany|NPD]] on 13 February 2005. The text says: &quot;Terror bombings: never again!&quot;]]
[[Image:Antideutsche rassisten.jpg|thumb|right|Anti-German banner expressing support for [[Arthur Harris (RAF officer)|Arthur Harris]]]]

[[Far-right]] politicians in Germany have sparked a great deal of controversy by promoting the term &quot;''Bombenholocaust''&quot; (&quot;holocaust by bomb&quot;) to describe the raids.&lt;ref&gt;Volkery, Carsten. [http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,339833,00.html &quot;War of Words&quot;], ''Der Spiegel'', 2 February 2005;
[http://www.guardian.co.uk/secondworldwar/story/0,,1411436,00.html Casualties of total war] Leading article, ''[[The Guardian]]'', 12 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Der Spiegel'' writes that, for decades, the Communist government of East Germany promoted the bombing as an example of &quot;Anglo-American terror,&quot; and now the same rhetoric is being used by the far right.&lt;ref name=Volkery&gt;Volkery, Carsten. [http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,339833,00.html &quot;War of Words&quot;], ''Der Spiegel'', 2 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; An example can be found in the extremist nationalist party ''[[National Democratic Party of Germany|Nationaldemokratische Partei Deutschlands]]'' (NPD). A party's representative, [[Jürgen Gansel]], described the Dresden raids as &quot;mass murder,&quot; and &quot;Dresden's holocaust of bombs&quot;.&lt;ref name=Bernstein-2005-02-12&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/12/international/europe/12germany.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=print&amp;position=&amp;oref=slogin Germany Seeks Tighter Curbs on Protests by Neo-Nazi Party], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 12 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; This provoked an outrage in the German parliament and triggered responses from the media. Prosecutors said that it was illegal to call the bombing a holocaust.&lt;ref name=Cleaver&gt;Cleaver, Hannah. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/1487678/German-ruling-says-Dresden-was-a-holocaust.html &quot;German ruling says Dresden was a holocaust&quot;], ''[[Daily Telegraph]]'', 12 April 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, several demonstrations by organizations opposing the far-right [[2010 Dresden anti-fascist blockade|blocked a demonstration of far-right organizations]].

[[Phrase]]s like &quot;Bomber-Harris, do it again!&quot;, &quot;Bomber-Harris Superstar - Thanks from the red [[Antifa]]&quot;, and ''&quot;Deutsche Täter sind keine Opfer!&quot;'' (&quot;German perpetrators are no victims!&quot;) are popular [[slogan]]s among the so-called &quot;[[Anti-Germans (political current)|Anti-Germans]]&quot;—a small radical left-wing political movement in Germany and Austria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.revolution.de.com/zeitung/zeitung09/bomber.htm Bomber Harris, Superstar] (German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Die Antideutschen – kein vorübergehendes Phänomen&quot; - Verfassungsschutz des Landes Nordrhein-Westfalen Im Oktober 2006 |url= http://www.im.nrw.de/sch/doks/vs/antideutsche.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1995, the fiftieth anniversary of the bombing, Anti-Germans praised the bombing on the grounds that so many of the city's civilians had supported Nazism. Similar rallies take place every year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,2144,2145701,00.html |title=Strange Bedfellows: Radical Leftists for Bush &amp;#124; Germany &amp;#124; DW.DE &amp;#124; 25.08.2006 |publisher=Dw-world.de |accessdate=February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==

===Kurt Vonnegut===
[[Kurt Vonnegut]]'s novel ''[[Slaughterhouse-Five|Slaughterhouse-Five or The Children's Crusade: A Duty-Dance with Death]]'' (1969) used some elements from his experiences as a [[prisoner of war]] at Dresden during the bombing. His account relates that over 135,000 were killed during the firebombings. Vonnegut recalled &quot;utter destruction&quot; and &quot;carnage unfathomable.&quot; The Germans put him and other POWs to work gathering bodies for mass burial. &quot;But there were too many corpses to bury. So instead the Nazis sent in troops with [[flamethrower]]s. All these civilians' remains were burned to ashes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;rolling&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|first=Douglas|last=Brinkley|title=Vonnegut's Apocalypse|work=[[Rolling Stone]]|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/story/11123162/kurt_vonnegut_says_this_is_the_end_of_the_world|date=24 August 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070416061205/http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/story/11123162/kurt_vonnegut_says_this_is_the_end_of_the_world |archivedate=16 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the special introduction to the 1976 [[Franklin Library]] edition of the novel, he wrote:
{{quotation|The Dresden atrocity, tremendously expensive and meticulously planned, was so meaningless, finally, that only one person on the entire planet got any benefit from it. I am that person. I wrote this book, which earned a lot of money for me and made my reputation, such as it is. One way or another, I got two or three dollars for every person killed. Some business I'm in.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Kurt|last= Vonnegut| title=[[Palm Sunday (book)|Palm Sunday]]| publisher= Delacorte Press| location= New York| year= 1981 |page= 302}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This experience was also used in several of his other books and is included in his posthumously published stories: ''[[Armageddon in Retrospect]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;rolling&quot; /&gt; The firebombing of Dresden was depicted in [[George Roy Hill]]'s 1972 [[Slaughterhouse-Five (film)|movie adaptation of Vonnegut's novel]].

[[Freeman Dyson]], a British (and later American) physicist who had worked as a young man with [[RAF Bomber Command]] from July 1943 to the end of the war,{{sfn|Dyson|2006}} wrote in later years: &quot;For many years I had intended to write a book on the bombing. Now I do not need to write it, because Vonnegut has written it much better than I could. He was in Dresden at the time and saw what happened. His book is not only good literature. It is also truthful. The only inaccuracy that I found in it is that it does not say that the night attack which produced the holocaust was a British affair. The Americans only came the following day to plow over the rubble. Vonnegut, being American, did not want to write his account in such a way that the whole thing could be blamed on the British. Apart from that, everything he says is true.&quot;{{sfn|Dyson|1979|pages=28-29}} Dyson later goes on to say: &quot;Since the beginning of the war I had been retreating step by step from one moral position to another, until at the end I had no moral position at all&quot;.{{sfn|Dyson|1979|pages=30-31}}

===Other===
* The German diarist [[Victor Klemperer]] includes a first-hand account of the firestorm in his published works.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,341230,00.html|title=Victor Klemperer's Dresden Diaries: Surviving the Firestorm|authors=SPIEGEL ONLINE, Hamburg, Germany|date=11 February 2005|work=SPIEGEL ONLINE}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The main action of the novel ''[[Closely Observed Trains]]'', by Czech author [[Bohumil Hrabal]], takes place on the night of the first raid.
* In the 1983 Pink Floyd album ''[[The Final Cut (album)|The Final Cut]]'', &quot;[[The Hero's Return]]&quot;, the protagonist lives his years after World War II tormented by &quot;desperate memories&quot;, part of him still flying &quot;over Dresden at angels 1–5&quot; (fifteen-thousand feet).
* [[Jonathan Safran Foer]]'s novel ''[[Extremely Loud and Incredibly Close]]'' (2005) incorporates the bombings into essential parts of the story.
* The bombings are a central theme in the 2006 German TV production ''[[Dresden (2006 film)|Dresden]]'' by director Roland Suso Richter. Along with the romantic plot between a British bomber pilot and a German nurse, the movie attempts to reconstruct the facts surrounding the Dresden bombings from both the perspective of the RAF pilots and the Germans in Dresden at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title|0461658|Dresden|(2006) (TV)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Siege of Dresden]], 1760. In some histories the term &quot;bombardment of Dresden&quot; refers to an early bombardment by the Prussian army in July 1760 that destroyed many buildings but killed only 49 citizens
* [[The Blitz]] – German air raids on British cities in which at least 40,000 died, including 57 consecutive nights of air raids just over London.
* [[Bombing of Warsaw in World War II]] 
&lt;!--* [[Bombing of Guernica]] – German/Italian air raid, and first terror bombing.--&gt;

==References==

===Notes===
{{notelist}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |editor-last=Addison |editor-first=Paul |editor2-last=Crang |editor2-first=Jeremy A. |year=2006 |title=Firestorm: The Bombing of Dresden |publisher=Pimlico  |isbn=1-84413-928-X  |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=obPq5HGDWrkC&amp;pg=PA67&amp;dq=dresden+1944+bombers+shot+down&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=aQc4UuPZCc-rhQev94D4BA&amp;ved=0CGkQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=dresden%201944%20bombers%20shot%20down&amp;f=false 66–68] |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Angell |first=Joseph W. |year=1953 |url=http://www.afhso.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-110208-030.pdf |edition=1962 |title=Historical Analysis of the 14–15 February 1945 Bombings of Dresden |publisher=USAF Historical Division Research Studies Institute, [[Air University (United States Air Force)|Air University]], hq.af.mil |accessdate=January 2008 |oclc=878696404 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Atkinson |first1=Rick |year=2013 |title=The Guns at Last Light |publisher=Henry Holt |location=New York |isbn=978-0-8050-6290- 8|page=535 |edition=1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Beevor |first=Antony |authorlink=Antony Beevor |year=2002|title=Berlin: the Downfall, 1945 |publisher=Penguin Viking |isbn=0-670-88695-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Bergander |first=Götz |year=1998 |title=Dresden im Luftkrieg |publisher=Flechsig |location=Würzburg  |isbn=3-88189-239-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Biddle|first1=Tami|title=Dresden 1945: Reality, History, and Memory|journal=Journal of Military History|date=April 2008|volume=72|issue=2|pages=413-450|doi=10.1353/jmh.2008.0074|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/235758 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Bruhl |first=Marshall de |year=2006 |title=Firestorm: Allied Airpower and the Destruction of Dresden |publisher=Random House |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Davis |first=Richard G |year=2006 |url=http://www.au.af.mil/au/aul/aupress/Books/Davis_B99/Davis_B99.pdf |title=Bombing the European Axis Powers. A Historical Digest of the Combined Bomber Offensive 1939–1945 |location=Alabama |publisher=Air University Press  |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |editor-last=«Dissonanz» Author Collective |year=2015 |url=http://www.abolishcommemoration.org |title=Abolish Commemoration: Critique To The Discourse Relating To The Bombing Of Dresden In 1945 |publisher=Verbrecher Verlag |isbn=9783943167238 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Dyson |first=Freeman |year=1979 |title=Disturbing the Universe |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |isbn=0-06-011108-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Dyson |first=Freeman |date=1 November 2006 |title=A Failure of Intelligence |url=http://www.technologyreview.com/article/406789/a-failure-of-intelligence/ |work=MIT Technology Review Magazine |publisher=MIT Technology Review |accessdate=20 October 2013 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Evans |first=Richard J. |authorlink=Richard J. Evans |year=1996 |url=http://www.hdot.org/en/trial/defense/evans.html |title=David Irving, Hitler and Holocaust Denial: Electronic Edition |publisher=[http://www.hdot.org Emory University and the Tam Institute for Jewish Studies] |accessdate=July 2013 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite news |last=Furlong |first=Ray |date=22 October 2003 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3211690.stm |title=Horrific fire-bombing images published |publisher=BBC News |accessdate=August 2014}}
* {{cite journal |last=Grant |first=Rebecca |url=http://www.afa.org/magazine/oct2004/1004dresden.asp |title=The Dresden Legend |journal=[[Air Force Magazine]] |date=October 2004 |volume=87 |number=10 |accessdate=January 2008 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Grayling|first=A. C. |authorlink=A.C. Grayling |year=2006 |title=Among the Dead Cities |publisher=Walker Publishing |isbn=0-8027-1471-4 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite news |first=A. C. |last=Grayling |date=27 March 2006b |title=Bombing civilians is not only immoral, it's ineffective |publisher=The Guardian |accessdate=October 2008 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2006/mar/27/comment.secondworldwar |location=London |ref=harv }}
* {{cite web |last=Harris |first=Arthur |year=1945 |title=Extract from the official account of Bomber Command by Arthur Harris, 1945 (Catalogue ref: AIR 16/487) |url=http://www.learningcurve.gov.uk/heroesvillains/g1/cs3/g1cs3s1.htm |publisher=British National Archives |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120812234016/http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/education/heroesvillains/g1/cs3/g1cs3s1.htm |archivedate=12 August 2012 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book | last=Joel | first=Tony | title=The Dresden firebombing : memory and the politics of commemorating destruction | publisher=I.B. Tauris | location=London | year=2013 | isbn=1-78076-358-1 | page=}}
* {{cite news |last=Keegan |first=Sir John |authorlink=John Keegan |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/personal-view/3620700/Necessary-or-not-Dresden-remains-a-topic-of-anguish.html |title=Necessary or not, Dresden remains a topic of anguish |newspaper=Daily Telegraph |date=31 October 2005 |accessdate=August 2014}}
* {{cite book |last=Longmate |first=Norman |year=1983 |title=The Bombers |publisher=Hutchins &amp; Company |isbn=0-09-151580-7 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=McKee |first=Alexander |year=1983 |title=Dresden 1945: The Devil's Tinderbox |publisher=Granada |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Miller |first=Donald L. |year=2006a |title=Eighth Air Force |location=London |publisher=Aurum |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Miller |first=Donald L. |year=2006b |title=Masters of the Air – America's Bomber Boys Who Fought the Air War Against Nazi Germany |publisher=Simon and Schuster |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Neitzel |first=Sönke |last2=Welzer |first2=Harald |year=2012 |title=Soldaten: On Fighting, Killing and Dying |publisher=Simon and Schuster |isbn=978-1-84983-949-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Neutzner |first=Matthias  |year=2010 |url=http://www.dresden.de/media/pdf/infoblaetter/Historikerkommission_Dresden1945_Abschlussbericht_V1_14a.pdf  |title=Abschlussbericht der Historikerkommission zu den Luftangriffen auf Dresden zwischen dem 13. und 15. Februar 1945 |language=German |pages=17, 38–39, 70–81 |publisher=Landeshauptstadt Dresden |accessdate=7 June 2011 |ref=harv|display-authors=etal}}
* {{cite book |last1=Norwood |first1=Stephen H.|year=2013 |title=Antisemitism and the American Far Left|publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=9781107036017|pages=237}}
* {{cite book |last=Ross |first=Stewart Halsey |year=2003 |title=Strategic Bombing by the United States in World War II: The Myths and the Facts |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company |isbn=978-0-7864-1412-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Selden |first=Mark |year=2004 |title=War and State Terrorism: The United States, Japan, and the Asia-Pacific in the Long Twentieth Century |publisher=Rowmand and Littlefield |isbn=978-0-7425-2391-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Shermer |first=Michael |last2=Grobman |first2=Alex |year=2009 |title=Denying History: Who Says the Holocaust Never Happened and Why Do They Say It? |edition=2nd, illustrated |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=978-0-520-26098-6 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=uACijKy-cbgC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA261#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 261] |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Taylor |first=Frederick |year=2004 |title=Dresden: Tuesday, 13 February 1945 |location=New York |publisher=HarperCollins |isbn=0-06-000676-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Taylor |first=Frederick |year=2005 |title=Dresden: Tuesday 13 February 1945 |location=London |publisher=Bloomsbury |isbn=0-7475-7084-1 |ref=harv }}.&lt;!-- Note the two editions used as references use different page numbers--&gt;
* {{cite book |last1=Webster |first1=C. |last2=Frankland |first2=N. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |year=1961 |title=The Strategic Air Offensive Against Germany 1939–1945: 5, Victory |series=History of the Second World War: United Kingdom Military Series |volume=III |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |edition=Battery Press &amp; IWM 1994 |isbn=0-89839-205-5  |ref={{harvid|Webster|Frankland|1961}} }}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Bombing of Dresden in World War II}}
* [http://www.13februar.dresden.de/en/index_en.php Official Memorial]

{{RAF WWII Strategic Bombing}}
{{World War II city bombing}}
{{World War II}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bombing Of Dresden In World War Ii}}
[[Category:1945 in Germany]]
[[Category:1945 in military history]]
[[Category:British World War II crimes]]
[[Category:Crimes against humanity]]
[[Category:History of Dresden]]
[[Category:Firebombings]]
[[Category:History of the Royal Air Force during World War II]]
[[Category:History of the United States Air Force]]
[[Category:World War II strategic bombing of Germany|Dresden]]
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II by town or city|Dresden]]</text>
      <sha1>ijx1phrujj7cwi6zeyl5nys6pvjbf81</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
