<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Celtic settlement of Eastern Europe</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18778180</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738126132</id>
      <parentid>738124484</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-07T01:48:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Audaciter</username>
        <id>5839510</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Attack on Delphi */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20886">[[File:Galatian head Thrace detail.jpg|thumb|A Galatian's head as depicted on a gold Thracian ''objet d'art'', 3rd century BC.]]
[[Gauls|Gallic]] groups, originating from the various [[La Tène culture|La Tène chiefdoms]], began a southeastern movement into the [[Balkan peninsula]] from the 4th century BC. Although Celtic settlements were concentrated in the western half of the [[Carpathian Basin]], there were notable incursions, and settlements, within the Balkan Peninsula itself.

From their new bases in northern [[Illyria]] and [[Pannonia]], the Gallic invasions climaxed in the early 3rd century BC, with the invasion of [[Greece]]. The 279 BC invasion of [[Hellenistic Greece|Greece]] proper was preceded by a series of other military campaigns waged toward the southern Balkans and against the [[Macedonia (ancient kingdom)|kingdom of Macedonia]], favoured by the state of confusion ensuing from the [[Diadochi|intricated succession to Alexander]]. A part of the invasion crossed over to [[Anatolia]] and eventually settled in the area that came to be named after them, [[Galatia]].

== Settlement of Southeastern Europe ==
[[File:Celtic Expansion.svg|320px|thumbnail|Celtic expansion in Europe (in grey), 6th-3rd century B.C.]]
From the 4th century BC, Celtic groups pushed into the Carpathian region and the Danube basin, coinciding with their movement into Italy. The ''[[Boii]]'' and ''Volcae'' were two large Celtic confederacies who generally cooperated in their campaigns. Splinter groups moved south via two major routes: one following the Danube river, another eastward from Italy. According to legend, 300,000 Celts moved into Italy and Illyria.&lt;ref name=&quot;celts&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Celts. A history |first=Daithí |last=Ó hÓgáin |publisher=Boydell Press |isbn=0-85115-923-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 3rd century, the native inhabitants of Pannonia were almost completely Celticized.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mocsy&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=András |last=Mócsy |others=Translated by S. Frere |title=Pannonia and Upper Moesia. A History of the Middle Danube Provinces of the Roman Empire |publisher=[[Routledge]] &amp; Kegan Paul |year=1974 |isbn=978-0-7100-7714-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; La Tène remains are found widely in Pannonia, but finds westward beyond the [[Tisza river]] and south beyond the [[Sava river|Sava]] are rather sparse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mocsy&quot; /&gt; These finds are deemed to have been locally produced ''Norican-Pannonian'' variation of Celtic culture. Nevertheless, features are encountered that suggest ongoing contacts with distant provinces such as Iberia. The fertile lands around the Pannonian rivers enabled the Celts to establish themselves easily, developing their agriculture and pottery, and at the same time exploiting the rich mines of modern Poland. Thus, it appears that the Celts had created a new homeland for themselves in the southern part of [[Central Europe]]; in a region stretching from Poland to the river Danube.

== Early expeditions ==

The political situation in the northern Balkans was in constant flux with various tribes dominant over their neighbors at any one time. Within tribes, military expeditions were conducted by &quot;an enterprising and mobile warrior class able from time to time to conquer large areas and to exploit their population&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mocsy&quot; /&gt; The political situation in the Balkans during the 4th century BC played to the Celts' advantage. The Illyrians had been waging war against the Greeks, leaving their western flank weak. While [[Alexander the Great|Alexander]] ruled Greece, the Celts dared not to push south near Greece. Therefore, early Celtic expeditions were concentrated against Illyrian tribes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stipcevic&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Aleksandar |last=Stipčević |authorlink=Aleksandar Stipčević |others=Translated by Stojana Čulić Burton |title=The Illyrians |publisher=Noyes Press |location=Park Ridge, New Jersey |page=44 |year=1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first Balkan tribe to be defeated by the Celts was the [[Illyrians|Illyric]] [[Autariatae]], who, during the 4th century BC, had enjoyed a hegemony over much of the central Balkans, centred on the [[Morava rivers, Serbia|Morava valley]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mocsy&quot; /&gt; An account of Celtic tactics is revealed in their attacks on the [[Ardiaei]].

In 335 BC, the Celts sent representatives to pay homage to [[Alexander the Great]], while [[Macedon]] was engaged in wars against [[Thracians]] on its northern border. Some historians suggest that this 'diplomatic' act was actually an evaluation of Macedonian military might.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stipcevic&quot; /&gt; After the death of Alexander the Great, Celtic armies began to bear down on the southern regions, threatening the Greek kingdom of Macedonia and the rest of Greece. In 310 BC, the Celtic general [[Molistomos]] attacked deep into Illyrian territory, subduing the [[Dardanians (Balkans)|Dardanians]], [[Paeonians]] and [[Triballi]]. The new Macedonian king [[Cassander]] felt compelled to take his old Illyrian enemies under his protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stipcevic&quot; /&gt; In 298 BC, the Celts attempted a penetrating attack into [[Thrace]] and [[Macedon]], where they suffered a heavy defeat near [[Haemus Mons]] at the hands of Cassander. However, another body of Celts led by the general [[Cambaules]] marched on Thrace, capturing large areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;celts&quot; /&gt;

== Invasions of Greece ==

=== ''Great expedition'' of 279 BC ===
{{further|Brennus (3rd century BC)}}
[[File:ThracianTribes.jpg|thumb|right|350px|The routes taken by the Gauls]]
The Celtic military pressure toward Greece in the southern Balkans reached its turning point in 281 BC. The collapse of [[Lysimachus]]' successor kingdom in Thrace opened the way for the migration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Green 133&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Alexander to Actium |last=Green |first=Peter |authorlink= |coauthors= |year= |publisher= |location= |isbn= |page=133 |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The cause for this is explained by [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]] as greed for loot,&lt;ref name =&quot;Pausanias&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.livius.org/di-dn/diadochi/diadochi_t11.html |title=Description of Greece |first= |last=Pausanias |authorlink=Pausanias (geographer) |others=Translated by Peter Levi |work=livius.org |year=2013 |accessdate=12 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Justin (historian)|Justin]] as a result of overpopulation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/justin/english/trans24.html |title=Justin Book XXIV |accessdate=2008-09-21 |work=Justin |publisher=forumromanum.org |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[Memnon of Heraclea|Memnon]] as the result of famine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.attalus.org/translate/memnon1.html |title=Memnon: History of Heracleia |work=attalus.org |year=2011 |accessdate=12 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], an initial probing raid led by [[Cambaules]] withdrew when they realized they were too few in numbers.&lt;ref name =&quot;Pausanias&quot; /&gt;
In 280 BC, a great army comprising about 85,000 warriors&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Les Celtes, histoire et dictionnaire |last=Kruta |first=Venceslas |authorlink= |coauthors= |year= |publisher= |location= |isbn= |page=493 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; left [[Pannonia]], split into three divisions, and marched south in a ''great expedition''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Barry |last=Cunliffe |authorlink=Barry Cunliffe |title=The Ancient Celts |year=1997 |location=Oxford |publisher= Oxford University Press |isbn=0-14-025422-6 |pages=80–81 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The term is a [[calque]] of the parallel [[French language|French]] '''Grande expédition''', that indicates, in French scholarly usage, the 279 BC surge of military campaigns on Greece.&lt;/ref&gt; to Macedon and [[central Greece]]. Under the leadership of [[Cerethrius]], 20,000 men moved against the Thracians and Triballi. Another division, led by [[Brennus (3rd century BC)|Brennus]]&lt;ref&gt;Brennus is said to have belonged to an otherwise unknown tribe called the Prausi. See: [[Strabo]], ''[[Geographica|Geography]]'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Strabo/4A*.html#1.13 4:1.13]. Not to be confused with the [[Brennus (4th century BC)|Brennus]] of the previous century, who [[Sack of Rome (387 BC)|sacked Rome in 387 BC]].&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Acichorius]]&lt;ref&gt;Some writers suppose that Brennus and Acichorius are the same person, the former being only a title and the latter the real name. Schmidt, &quot;De fontibus veterum auctorum in enarrandis expeditionibus a Gallis in Macedoniania susceptis,&quot; Berol. 1834&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Smith
  | first = William
  | author-link = William Smith (lexicographer)
  | contribution = Acichorius
  | editor-last = Smith
  | editor-first = William
  | title = [[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]]
  | volume = 1
  | pages = 12
  | publisher =
  | place = Boston, MA
  | year = 1867
  | contribution-url = http://www.ancientlibrary.com/smith-bio/0021.html
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt; moved against the [[Paionia]]ns, while the third division, headed by [[Bolgios]], aimed for the [[Macedon]]ians and [[Illyria]]ns.&lt;ref name =&quot;Pausanias&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Dying gaul.jpg|thumb|left|''[[The Dying Gaul]]'', a Roman copy of a Greek statue commemorating the victory over the Galatians]]

Bolgios inflicted heavy losses on the Macedonians, whose young king, [[Ptolemy Keraunos]], was captured and decapitated. However, Bolgios' contingent was repulsed by the Macedonian nobleman [[Sosthenes of Macedon|Sosthenes]], and satisfied with the loot they had won, Bolgios' contingents turned back. Sosthenes, in turn, was attacked and defeated by Brennus and his division, who were then free to ravage the country.

After these expeditions returned home, Brennus urged and persuaded them to mount a third united expedition against central Greece, led by himself and Acichorius.&lt;ref name =&quot;Pausanias&quot; /&gt; The reported strength of the army of 152,000 infantry and 24,400 cavalry is impossibly large.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=W.W. |last=Tarn |authorlink=William Woodthorpe Tarn |title=Antigonas Gonatas |page=148 |location=Oxford |publisher=Clarendon Press |year=1913 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The actual number of horsemen has to be intended half as big: [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]] describes how they used a tactic called ''[[trimarcisia]]'', where each cavalryman was supported by two mounted servants, who could supply him with a spare horse should he have to be dismounted, or take his place in the battle, should he be killed or wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;10.23.1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Paus.+10.23.1 |title=Description of Greece: 10.23.1 |first= |last=Pausanias |others=Translation by W.H.S. Jones &amp; H.A. Ormerod |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=Harvard University Press |year=1918 |accessdate=12 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.attalus.org/translate/justin3.html#24.4 24.4-6 |title=Epitome of Pompeius Trogus' Histories |accessdate=2008-09-21 |work=Junianus Justinus |publisher=attalus.org |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Battle of Thermopylae (279 BC) ===
{{Main|Battle of Thermopylae (279 BC)}}
A Greek coalition made up of [[Aetolians]], [[Boeotia]]ns, Athenians, [[Phocians]], and other Greeks north of Corinth took up quarters at the narrow pass of [[Thermopylae]], on the east coast of central [[Ancient Greece|Greece]]. During the initial assault, Brennus' forces suffered heavy losses. Hence he decided to send a large force under Acichorius against [[Aetolia]]. The Aetolian detachment, as Brennus hoped, left Thermopylae to defend their homes. The Aetolians joined the defense en masse – the old and women joining the fight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.livius.org/di-dn/diadochi/diadochi_t12.html |title=Description of Greece |first= |last=Pausanias |others=Translated by Peter Levi |work=livius.org |year=2013 |accessdate=12 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Realizing that the Gallic sword was dangerous only at close quarters, the Aetolians resorted to [[Skirmisher|skirmishing tactics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Green 133&quot; /&gt; According to Pausanias, only half the number that had set out for Aetolia returned.&lt;ref name =&quot;Pausanias&quot; /&gt;

Eventually, Brennus found a way around the pass at Thermopylae, but by then the Greeks had escaped by sea.

=== Attack on Delphi ===
[[File:07Delphi Theater03.jpg|thumb|300px|Delphi]]
Brennus pushed on to [[Delphi]], where he was defeated and forced to retreat, after which he died of wounds sustained in the battle. His army fell back to the river [[Spercheios River|Spercheios]], where it was routed by the [[Thessaly|Thessalians]] and [[Malians (Greek tribe)|Malians]].

Both historians who relate the attack on Delphi, Pausanias and [[Junianus Justinus]], say that the Gauls were defeated and driven off. They were overtaken by a violent thunderstorm, which made it impossible to manoeuvre or even hear their orders. The night that followed was frosty, and in the morning the Greeks attacked them from both sides. Brennus was wounded and the Gauls fell back, killing those of their own wounded who were unable to retreat. That night, a panic fell on the camp, as the Gauls divided into factions and fought amongst themselves. They were joined by Acichorius and the rest of the army, but the Greeks forced them into a full-scale retreat. Brennus took his own life by drinking neat wine according to Pausanias, or by stabbing himself according to Justinus. Pressed by the Aetolians, the Gauls fell back to the Spercheios, where the waiting [[Thessaly|Thessalians]] and [[Malians (Greek tribe)|Malians]] destroyed them.&lt;ref name=&quot;10.23.1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.attalus.org/translate/justin3.html#24.7 24.7-8 |title=Junianus Justinus, Epitome of Pompeius Trogus' Philippic Histories |accessdate=2008-09-21 |work= |publisher=attalus.org |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Cursed Gold of Delphi ====
{{Main|The Gold of Tolosa}}

In spite of the Greek accounts about the defeat of the Gauls, the [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] literary tradition preferred a far different version.{{clarify|date=June 2014|reason=Constrasting a supposed Greek to a supposed Roman tradition and then citing Strabo (following previous citations of Pausanias etc.) presumably as belonging to the latter, seems to say the least strange. Provided there indeed exists such a dichotomy, please cite and/or quote, inter alia, authors belonging to both the former and the latter.}}
[[Strabo]] reports a story told in his time of a semi-legendary treasure – the ''aurum Tolosanum'', fifteen thousand talents of gold and silver – supposed to have been the cursed gold looted during the sack of Delphi and brought back to Tolosa (modern [[Toulouse]], [[France]]) by the [[Tectosages]], who were said to have been part of the invading army.

More than a century and a half after the alleged sack, the Romans ruled [[Gallia Narbonensis]].
In 105 BC, while marching to [[Arausio]], the [[Proconsul]] of [[Cisalpine Gaul]] [[Quintus Servilius Caepio]] plundered the sanctuaries of the town of [[Toulouse|Tolosa]], whose inhabitants had joined the [[Cimbri]], finding over 50,000 15&amp;nbsp;lb. bars of gold and 10,000 15&amp;nbsp;lb. bars of silver. The riches of Tolosa were shipped back to Rome, but only the silver made it: the gold was stolen by a band of marauders, who were believed to have been hired by Caepio himself and to have killed the legion guarding it. The Gold of Tolosa was never found, and was said to have been passed all the way down to the last heir of the Servilii Caepiones, [[Marcus Junius Brutus]].

In 105 BC, Caepio refused to co-operate with his superior officer, [[Gnaeus Mallius Maximus]], because he thought of him as a ''[[novus homo]]'', deciding by himself to engage in battle against the [[Cimbri]], on the [[Rhone]]. There, the Roman army suffered a crushing defeat and complete destruction, in the so-called [[Battle of Arausio]] (modern [[Orange, Vaucluse|Orange]]).

Upon his return to Rome, Caepio was tried for &quot;the loss of his Army&quot; and [[embezzlement]]. He was convicted and given the harshest sentence allowable; he was stripped of his [[Roman citizenship]], forbidden fire and water within 800 miles of Rome, fined 15,000 [[Talent (weight)|talents]] (about 825,000&amp;nbsp;lb) of gold, and forbidden from seeing or speaking to his friends or family until he had left for [[exile]].

He spent the rest of his life in exile in [[Smyrna]] in [[Asia Minor]]. His defeat and ensuing ruin were looked upon as a punishment for his sacrilegous theft.

Strabo distances himself from this account, arguing that the defeated Gauls were in no position to carry off such spoils, and that, in any case, Delphi had already been despoiled of its treasure by the [[Phocis|Phocians]] during the [[Third Sacred War]] in the previous century.&lt;ref name=&quot;strabo&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Strabo/4A*.html#1.13 4:1.13 |title=Strabo, Geography |accessdate=2008-09-21 |work= |publisher=penelope.uchicago.edu |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Brennus' legendary pillage of Delphi is presented as fact by some popular modern historians.&lt;ref&gt;As did, for example, [[Peter Berresford Ellis]], in his ''The Celtic Empire'', Constable, 1990, pp.&amp;nbsp;82–84.&lt;/ref&gt;

== After the Greek campaigns ==
{{Further|Galatia|Tylis}}
[[File:Volcae Arecomisci and Tectosages (migrations).svg|thumb|left|550px|Ethnogenesis and migrations of the [[Volcae]].]]

Most scholars deem the Greek campaign a disaster for the Celts.

Some of the survivors of the Greek campaign, led by Comontoris (one of Brennus' generals) settled in [[Thrace]]. In 277 BC, [[Antigonus II Gonatas]] defeated the Gauls at the [[Battle of Lysimachia]] and the survivors retreated, founding a short-lived city-state named [[Tylis|Tyle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.caorc.org/fellowships/mellon/pubs/Theodossiev.pdf |format=PDF|title=Celtic Settlement in North-Western Thrace during the Late Fourth and Third Centuries BC |accessdate=2008-09-21 |work=Nikola Theodossiev |publisher=caorc.org |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another group of Gauls, who split off from Brennus' army in 281 BC, were transported over to [[Asia Minor]] by [[Nicomedes I of Bithynia|Nicomedes I]] to help him defeat his brother and secure the throne of [[Bithynia]]. They eventually settled in the region that came to be named after them, [[Galatia]]. They were defeated by [[Antiochus I]], and as a result, they were confined to barren highlands in the center of Anatolia.&lt;ref&gt;Cunliffe (1997), p.83&lt;/ref&gt;

Celtic groups were still the pre-eminent political units in the northern Balkans from the 4th to the 1st century BC. The ''[[Boii]]'' controlled most of northern Pannonia during the 2nd century BC, and are also mentioned as having occupied the territory of modern Slovakia. We learn of other tribes of the Boian confederation inhabiting Pannonia. There were the ''[[Taurisci]]'' in the upper Sava valley, west of [[Sisak]], as well as the ''Anarti'', ''Osi'' and ''Cotini'' in the Carpathian basin. In the lower Sava valley, the ''[[Scordisci]]'' wielded much power over their neighbours for over a century.

[[File:Roman period tribes in Illyria and Lower Pannonia.png|thumb|400px|Tribes in Pannonia and western Dacia, c. 50 BC]]

The later half of the 1st century BC brought much change to the power relations of barbarian tribes in Pannonia. The defeat of the Boian confederation by the [[Getae|Geto]]-[[Dacia]]n king [[Burebista]] significantly curtailed Celtic control of the Carpathian basin, and some of the Celticization was reversed. Yet, more Celtic tribes appear in sources. The [[Hercuniates]] and [[Latobici]] migrated from the northern regions (Germania). Altogether new tribes are encountered, bearing Latin names (such as the [[Arabiates]]), possibly representing new creations carved out of the defeated Boian confederation. To further weaken Celtic hegemony in Pannonia, the Romans moved the Pannonian-Illyrian ''[[Azali]]'' to northern Pannonia. The political dominance previously enjoyed by the Celts was overshadowed by newer barbarian confederations, such the [[Marcomanni]] and [[Iazyges]]. Their ethnic independence was gradually lost as they were absorbed by the surrounding Dacian, Illyrian and Germanic peoples, although Celtic names survive until the 3rd century AD.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=H. D. |last=Rankin |title=Celts and the Classical World |location=London &amp; Sydney |publisher=Croom Helm |year=1987 |isbn= 0-7099-2295-7 |page=17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Celts in Transylvania]]
* [[La Tène culture]]
{{Clear}}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Celts|state=uncollapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gallic Invasion Of The Balkans}}
[[Category:279 BC]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Celts]]
[[Category:270s BC conflicts]]
[[Category:Battles of the Hellenistic period]]
[[Category:Wars involving Antipatrid Macedon]]
[[Category:Wars involving Antigonid Macedon]]
[[Category:Wars involving Illyria]]
[[Category:Hellenistic-era tribes in the Balkans]]
[[Category:Hellenistic Greece]]</text>
      <sha1>5rkx8c205dsq9trw57bgegj6mlqbeuz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
