<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Charge at Khan Ayash</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37199711</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748958012</id>
      <parentid>748957759</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T12:28:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AustralianRupert</username>
        <id>8731061</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Battle */ fix typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22532">{{infobox military conflict
|conflict    =Charge at Khan Ayash
|partof      =the [[Middle Eastern theatre of World War I]]
|image       =[[File:AWMB00341Khan Ayash.jpg|300px|Australian Light Horse at Khan Ayash]]
|caption     =Australian Light Horsemen at Khan Ayash
|date        =2 October 1918
|place       = Khan Ayash {{convert|17|mi|km}} north of [[Damascus]] on the inland road to [[Rayak (Riyaq)|Rayak]] and [[Homs]]
|coordinates =
|map_type    =
|latitude    =
|longitude   =
|map_size    =
|map_caption =
|map_label   =
|territory   =
|result      =British Empire victory
|status      =
|combatant1  ={{flag|British Empire}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Australia}}
|combatant2  ={{flag|Ottoman Empire}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|German Empire}}
|commander1  ={{flagicon|Great Britain}} [[Edmund Allenby, 1st Viscount Allenby|Edmund Allenby]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Australia}} [[Harry Chauvel]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Great Britain}} [[Henry West Hodgson]]
|commander2  ={{flagicon|German Empire}} [[Otto Liman von Sanders]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Mustafa Kemal Atatürk|Mustafa Kemal Pasha]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Cevat Çobanlı|Jevad Pasha]]
|units1   =[[3rd Light Horse Brigade]]&lt;br&gt;[[Australian Mounted Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[Desert Mounted Corps]]
|units2   =146th Regiment Army Troops, [[Fourth Army (Ottoman Empire)|Fourth Army]] and unidentified cavalry
|casualties1 =
|casualties2 =2,000 prisoners
|notes       =
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Sinai and Palestine}}
{{Campaignbox World War I}}
}}

The '''Charge at Khan Ayash''' occurred on 2 October 1918 about {{convert|17|mi|km}} north of [[Damascus]] after the pursuit to, and [[Capture of Damascus (1918)|capture of Damascus]], which followed the decisive [[Egyptian Expeditionary Force]] victory at the [[Battle of Megiddo (1918)|Battle of Megiddo]] on 25 September during the [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign]] of World War I. After Damascus had been encircled by [[Desert Mounted Corps]] on 30 September, the [[3rd Light Horse Brigade]] advanced through the city on 1 October to charge and capture remnants of the  [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] [[Yildirim Army Group]] withdrawing along the road north to [[Rayak (Riyaq)|Rayak]] and [[Homs]].

Following the victories at the [[Battle of Sharon]] and [[Battle of Nablus (1918)|Battle of Nablus]] during the Battle of Megiddo, and the Capture of Damascus, remnants of the [[Seventh Army (Ottoman Empire)|Seventh]] and [[Eighth Army (Ottoman Empire)|Eighth]] Armies retreated in columns towards [[Damascus]] from the [[Judean Hills]]. Rearguards at [[Battle of Samakh (1918)|Samakh]], at [[Capture of Tiberias (1918)|Tiberias]] and at [[Battle of Jisr Benat Yakub|Jisr Benat Yakub]] were captured by the Australian Mounted Division. Remnants of the [[Fourth Army (Ottoman Empire)|Fourth Army]] also retreated in columns towards Damascus along the Pilgrims' Road from Amman. The rearguard at [[Charge at Irbid|Irbid]] was attacked by the [[4th Cavalry Division (British Indian Army)|4th Cavalry Division]] and [[Deraa]] was captured by the Sherifial Army.

The last formation to leave Damascus, the 146th Regiment (Fourth Army) left during the night of 30 September, was followed early the next morning; 1 October by the 10th Light Horse Regiment (3rd Light Horse Brigade), in the process accepting the surrender of the city. The Australian light horsemen followed the retreating columns north along the road to Homs during the day, encountering numerous rearguards which were attacked and captured, until they we were stopped by strong defences protecting a 2,000-strong column near Khan Ayash. Early the next morning a large column of retreating [[German Empire|German]] and [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] combatants was seen moving towards a pass just north of Khan Ayash. Two squadrons of the 9th Light Horse Regiment (3rd Light Horse Brigade) rode north to cut the road in front of the column while the third squadron charged into the column splitting it and forcing it to surrender.

== Background ==
{{see also|Charge at Irbid|Battle of Jisr Benat Yakub|Charge at Kaukab|Charge at Kiswe|Capture of Damascus (1918)|Battle of Sharon (1918)|Battle of Nablus (1918)|Battle of Megiddo (1918)|Sinai and Palestine Campaign}}
The day after the victory at the Battle of Megiddo, the pursuit to Damascus began on 26 September, when the [[4th Cavalry Division (British Indian Army)|4th Cavalry Division]] advanced east across the Jordan River to [[Irbid]] and on to Deraa which was captured by Sherifial forces. The pursuit to Damascus {{convert|140|mi|km}} away, continued with the cavalry division's right flank covered by Sherifial forces. Meanwhile, the [[Australian Mounted Division]] with the [[5th Cavalry Division (British Indian Army)|5th Cavalry Division]] in reserve, began their {{convert|90|mi|km}} pursuit to Damascus on 27 September around the northern end of the [[Sea of Galilee]], also known as Lake Tiberias, via [[Battle of Jisr Benat Yakub|Jisr Benat Yakub]] and [[Kuneitra]].&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1955 pp. 252–3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 pp. 582–3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;These advances have been characterised as a &quot;race for Damascus&quot;. [Gullett 1919 pp. 39–40] See also Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 567&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Yildirim Army Group retreat ===
[[File:GullettMap43AmmanDeraa25.9.jpeg|thumb|Gullett's Map 43 Detail shows positions of the retreating remnants of the Yildirim Army Group, Beisan, Irbid and Deraa with the Jordan River on the left and the Pilgrims' Road on right]]

By 26 September the Fourth Army's Amman garrison (less the [[Third Transjordan attack (1918)#Battle of Amman 25 September|rearguard captured at Amman]]) had not been &quot;heavily engaged,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wavell 1968 pp. 224–5&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;was still intact as a fighting force even though it was in rapid retreat&quot; north along the [[Hejaz railway]] and Pilgrims Road, some miles to the east of the [[Jordan River]].&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 2002 p. 241&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 6,000 and 7,000 German and Ottoman soldiers from the Ottoman Fourth, Seventh and Eighth Armies had managed to retreat via Tiberias or Deraa, before these places were captured on 25 and 27 September, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Cutlack 1941 pp. 167–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls567&quot;&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 567&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, the retreating columns which moved via Deraa were at or north of Muzeirib on their way to Damascus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls567&quot;/&gt;

Two days later, on 29 September, Mustafa Kemal Pasha, commander of the Seventh Army arrived at Kiswe, {{convert|50|mi|km}} north of Deraa, and {{convert|9|mi|km}} south of Damascus, with his army's leading troops. Here [[Otto Liman von Sanders|Liman von Sanders]] commanding Yildirim Army Group ordered him to withdraw to the north of Damascus, to Rayak.&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 pp. 594–5&lt;/ref&gt;

By the next morning, the leading column of the Fourth Army consisting of an Ottoman cavalry division and some infantry, was approaching Kiswe, followed along the Pilgrims' Road by the 4th Cavalry Division {{convert|30|mi|km}} behind.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wavell227&quot;&gt;Wavell 1968 p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls574&quot;&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 574&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Australian Mounted Division ===
During the cavalry phase of the [[Battle of Sharon (1918)|Battle of Sharon]] the Australian Mounted Division's [[3rd Light Horse Brigade]] had captured [[Capture of Jenin (1918)|Jenin]] in the evening of 20 September 1918. By the next morning they had captured 8,000 remnants of the two Ottoman armies which had been fighting in the [[Judean Hills]].&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 pp. 529–32&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prelude ==

=== Yildirim Army Group ===
Liman von Sanders had ordered the 24th, 26th and 53rd Infantry Divisions, XX Corps (Seventh Army) and the 3rd Cavalry Division, Army Troops Fourth Army, under the command of Colonel Ismet Bey (commander of the III Corps Seventh Army) to defend Damascus, while the remaining Ottoman formations were ordered to retreat northwards.&lt;ref&gt;Erickson 2001 pp. 200–1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 674&lt;/ref&gt; The remains of the Tiberias Group which had defended Samakh and Tiberias, commanded by Jemal Pasha, (commander of the Fourth Army) had also been ordered to defend Damascus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls595&quot;&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 595&lt;/ref&gt; However, Liman von Sanders realised he could not defend the city and withdrew his Yildirim Army Group headquarters north to Aleppo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keogh253&quot;&gt;Keogh 1955 p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; Only von Oppen's force which had travelled by train direct to Rayak before the Barda Gorge was closed and the 146th Regiment remained &quot;disciplined formations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls594&quot;&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 594&lt;/ref&gt;

The 146th Regiment was the last formation to leave Damascus; leaving during the night of 30 September. After hearing the Barada Gorge [[Charge at Kaukab#Barda Gorge|was captured]] von Hammerstein commanding the 146th Regiment, retreated along the Homs road, following the III Corps, the 24th Division and the 3rd Cavalry Division to concentrate at Rayak with troops which left Damascus at 21:00 on the last Ottoman train out of Damascus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls595&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Preston276–7&quot;&gt;Preston 1921 pp. 276–7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 2002 p. 245&lt;/ref&gt; These retreating Ottoman army units passed through the outposts established by Colonel von Oppen's Asia Corps at Rayak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls595&quot;/&gt;

=== Desert Mounted Corps 30 September ===
[[File:FallsSkMap39AdvDamCapture.jpeg|thumb|Falls Sketch Map 39 detail Capture of Damascus]]
By midnight on 30 September, the Australian Mounted Division was at El Mezze {{convert|2|mi|km}} to the west of the city with orders to block the road to Beirut and the road north to Homs, Hama and Aleppo, the 5th Cavalry Division at Kaukab was ordered to the east of Damascus, while the 4th Cavalry Division was at Zeraqiye 34 miles (55&amp;nbsp;km) south of Damascus on the Pilgrims' Road with the 11th Cavalry Brigade at Khan Deinun and Arab Sherifial forces north east of Ashrafiye.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wavell227&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 586&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carver 2003 p. 242&lt;/ref&gt;

==== 3rd Light Horse Brigade ====
During the night of 29/30 September, the brigade attacked and captured a strong rearguard position at Sa'sa on the road to Damascus from Kuneitra. Here two regiments advanced on the right and left flanks while a third regiment made a dismounted frontal attack to capture 20 prisoners, two 77mm field guns and two machine guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wavell227&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;3rd Light Horse Brigade War Diary AWM4-10-3-44 Appendix 4 p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 570&lt;/ref&gt;

The 3rd Light Horse Brigade subsequently bivouacked outside Damascus during the night of 30 September/1 October, having establishing picket lines to &quot;prevent all troops except Sherifian Regulars from entering the city.&quot; With orders to cut the Homs road, the brigade entered Damascus at 05:00 on 1 October 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls574&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hughes 1999 pp. 98–9&lt;/ref&gt;

At the Serai, Hall of Government or Town Hall, Major A.C.N. Olden, commanding the 10th Light Horse Regiment accepted the surrender of the city from Emir Said Abd el Kader.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls589&quot;&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 589&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hill178&quot;&gt;Hill 1978 p. 178&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones 1987 p. 157&lt;/ref&gt;

Damascus was in a state of revolt; both the civil and military administrations had completely broken down and Olden warned that the shooting must stop.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keogh253&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hill178&quot;/&gt; He requested a guide to show the Australian light horsemen through the city to the Homs road.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls589&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hill178&quot;/&gt;

== Battle ==
After taking the surrender of Damascus, the 3rd Light Horse Brigade was involved in virtually continual skirmishes throughout the day, in short but severe engagements as they moved north along the Homs road in pursuit of the retreating columns. During these attacks on Ottoman rearguards they captured many prisoners and machine guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wavell229&quot;&gt;Wavell 1968 p. 229&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gullett776&quot;&gt;Gullett 1941 p. 776&lt;/ref&gt;

As they were leaving Damascus by the [[Bab Tuma]], the 10th Light Horse Regiment learned that rearguards held the Nahr Ma'raba about {{convert|5|mi|km}} north east of Damascus. The leading squadron supported by the regiment attacked the German machine gunners who were eventually forced to abandon their position &quot;when [the rearguard] ... saw that the attack was about to be pressed home&quot; by a cavalry charge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls589&quot;/&gt; The Wadi Ma'raba rearguard was captured by 09:00 along with 600 prisoners and about 40 machine guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Preston277&quot;&gt;Preston 1921 p. 277&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baly200–1&quot;&gt;Baly 2003 pp. 200–1&lt;/ref&gt; The Australian light horse regiment was followed through Damascus and the Bab Tuma gate at 10:30 by the 14th Cavalry Brigade (5th Cavalry Division) which established outposts and gained touch with the 13th Cavalry Brigade (5th Cavalry Division) which had advanced round the east side of the city to the Homs road.&lt;ref name=&quot;Preston276–7&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 591&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Captured Ottoman battle flag Khan Ayash (AWM image B02838).jpg|thumb|The colour of the 146th Regiment captured at Khan Ayash by the Australian Light Horse]]

The 10th Light Horse Regiment continued their advance about {{convert|4|mi|km}} north to [[Duma]], {{convert|10|mi|km}} from Damascus where they captured about 500 prisoners and 37 machine guns, before continuing on to [[Al-Qusayr, Syria|Khan Kusseir]] {{convert|2|mi|km}} further on. Here, in the evening they were opposed by a German rearguard armed with a number of machine guns.&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 pp. 589–90&lt;/ref&gt; The defenders were broken by a charge &quot;delivered from the cover of some vineyards and olive groves on their right flank, and all of them were killed or captured.&quot; Street fighting with the bayonet captured Khan Kusseir, 160 prisoners and a number of machine guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Preston277&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baly200–1&quot;/&gt;

Another 50 prisoners were captured after a further attack before another large retreating column of between 1,500 and 2,000 Ottoman soldiers was seen {{convert|7|mi|km}} away moving towards a pass in the hills near Khan Ayash {{convert|17|mi|km}} north of Damascus on the Homs road. The column was protected here by a strong fortress defended by a rearguard armed with about 20 machine guns established by the Fourth Army's German 146th Regiment. Without the support of field guns several unsuccessful attacks were launched by the Australian light horsemen on the fortress. The rear of the retreating column was also attacked, inflicting some loss and capturing more prisoners and machine guns. At 19:00 the 10th Light Horse Regiment withdrew back to Khan Kusseir arriving at 22:00 to bivouac with brigade headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gullett776&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 pp. 589–90, 674&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;10LHR1.10&quot;&gt;10th Light Horse Regiment War Diary 1 October 1918 AWM4-10-15-40&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;The 146th Regiment, together with the 3rd Cavalry Division, 63rd Regiment  and &quot;etc.&quot; had formed the Fourth Army's Army Troops. [Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 674]&lt;/ref&gt;

At 06:15 on 2 October 1918 a long column was reported retreating northwards. The 9th Light Horse Regiment trotted out at 06:45 and after several groups of machine gunners failed to delay the light horse, they rode up level with the main body of the column. Two squadrons were then ordered forward to Khan Ayash to cut the road ahead before it entered a pass, while a third squadron charged the left flank of the column, forcing it to surrender.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls590&quot;&gt;Falls 1930 Vol. 2 p. 590&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The brigade galloped on, through a hot fire, and charged clean through the enemy force, killing a large number of them ...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Preston 1921 p. 279&lt;/ref&gt; An advanced guard of cavalry also surrendered to the leading squadrons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls590&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Khan Ayash machine guns and artillery trails 1918 (AWM image B02817).jpg|thumb|Captured machine guns by the roadside near Khan Ayash. Maxim MG08s and Bergman LMG15s on left, artillery trails on right]]

The 10th Light Horse Regiment had been ordered to advance in support, to arrive at 07:45 after the surrender of 91 officers including a divisional commander, 318 cavalry, 1,072 infantry, three guns and 26 machine guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;10LHR1.10&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls590&quot;/&gt; They had captured over 2,000 prisoners including a divisional commander and the 146th Regimental standard, the only enemy colour taken by Australians in the First World War.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls594&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wavell229&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gullett776&quot;/&gt;

== Aftermath ==
After their last battle of the war, the 10th Light Horse Regiment occupied the pass and the hills covering the road to Homs while a squadron reconnoitred to the east until they were relieved by the 8th Light Horse Regiment (3rd Light Horse Brigade) and returned to bivouac at Khan Kusseir. The brigade returned to camp south west of Damascus on 4 October 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wavell229&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gullett776&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;10th Light Horse Regiment War Diary October 1918 AWM4-10-15-40&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 19 September, Desert Mounted Corps suffered battle casualties of just 500 killed, wounded or missing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falls594&quot;/&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

== Citations ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== References ==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite web
| url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/records/awm4/subclass.asp?levelID=1455
|title=10th Light Horse Regiment War Diary
|work=First World War Diaries AWM4, 10-15-40
|date=October 1918
|publisher=Australian War Memorial
|location=Canberra
}}
* {{cite web
| url = http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/war_diaries/first_world_war/subclass.asp?levelID=1469
| title = 3rd Light Horse Brigade War Diary
| work= First World War Diaries AWM4, 10-3-44
| date =September 1918
| publisher = Australian War Memorial
| location = Canberra
}}
* {{cite book |last=Baly |first=Lindsay|title=Horseman, Pass By: The Australian Light Horse in World War I |year=2003|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=East Roseville, Sydney |oclc=223425266}}
* {{cite book |title=The Last Crusade: The Palestine Campaign in the First World War |last=Bruce |first=Anthony |year=2002 |publisher=John Murray |location=London|isbn=978-0-7195-5432-2}}
* {{cite book |title=The National Army Museum Book of The Turkish Front 1914–1918: The Campaigns at Gallipoli, in Mesopotamia and in Palestine |last=Carver |first=Michael, Field Marshal Lord |year=2003 |publisher=Pan Macmillan |location=London|isbn=978-0-283-07347-2}}
* {{cite book|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069925/|title=The Australian Flying Corps in the Western and Eastern Theatres of War, 1914–1918|last=Cutlack|first=Frederic Morley| year=1941|edition=11th|series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918|volume=Volume VIII|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra|oclc=220900299}}
* {{cite book |title=Ordered to Die: A History of the Ottoman Army in the First World War: Forward by General Hüseyiln Kivrikoglu |last=Erickson|first= Edward J.|series= No. 201 Contributions in Military Studies |year=2001| publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport Connecticut|oclc=43481698}}
* {{cite book |title=Military Operations Egypt &amp; Palestine from June 1917 to the End of the War |last=Falls |first=Cyril |series=Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |coauthor=A. F. Becke (maps) |year=1930 |volume=Volume 2 Part II |publisher=H.M. Stationery Office |location=London|oclc=256950972}}
* {{cite book |title=Australia in Palestine |editors= Henry S. Gullett, Charles Barnet, Art Editor David Baker |year=1919 |publisher=Angus &amp; Robertson |location=Sydney | oclc=224023558}}
* {{cite book|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069924/|title=The Australian Imperial Force in Sinai and Palestine, 1914–1918|last=Gullett|first=Henry S.|year= 1941|edition=11th|series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918|volume=Volume VII|publisher= Australian War Memorial|location= Canberra|oclc=220900153}}
* {{cite book |title=Chauvel of the Light Horse: A Biography of General Sir Harry Chauvel, GCMG, KCB |last=Hill |first=Alec Jeffrey|authorlink=Alec Hill|year=1978 |publisher=Melbourne University Press |location=Melbourne |oclc=5003626}}
* {{cite book |title=Allenby and British Strategy in the Middle East 1917-1919 |editors=John Gooch, Brian Holden Reid |last=Hughes |first=Matthew |year=1999 |series=Military History and Policy | volume=1 |publisher= Frank Cass |location=London |oclc=470338901}}
* {{cite book |title= The Australian Light Horse |last=Jones |first=Ian |series= Australians at War |year=1987 |publisher=Time-Life Books |location= Australia |oclc=18459444}}
* {{cite book |title=Suez to Aleppo |last=Keogh |first=E. G. |author2=Joan Graham |year=1955 |publisher=Directorate of Military Training by Wilkie &amp; Co. |location=Melbourne|oclc=220029983}}
* {{cite book |title=The Desert Mounted Corps: An Account of the Cavalry Operations in Palestine and Syria 1917–1918 |last=Preston |first=R. M. P. |year=1921 |publisher=Constable &amp; Co. |location=London|oclc=3900439}}
*{{cite book |chapter=The Palestine Campaigns |last=Wavell |first=Field Marshal Earl|authorlink=Archibald Wavell, 1st Earl Wavell|editor-last=Sheppard|editor-first=Eric William |edition=4th |title=A Short History of the British Army |year=1968|origyear=1933|publisher=Constable &amp; Co. |location=London|oclc=35621223}}
{{Refend}}
{{Ottoman battles in the 20th century}}

{{Coord|33|39|00|N|36|30|00|E|type:event|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Khan Ayash, Charge at}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1918]]
[[Category:1918 in Mandatory Syria]]
[[Category:Ottoman Empire in World War I]]
[[Category:British Empire in World War I]]
[[Category:German Empire in World War I]]
[[Category:Middle Eastern theatre of World War I]]
[[Category:Campaigns and theatres of World War I|Sinai and Palestine]]
[[Category:Military campaigns and theatres of World War I involving Australia]]
[[Category:Battles of the Sinai and Palestine Campaign]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Indian Princely States]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Australia]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving British India]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Germany]]
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War I]]
[[Category:History of the Royal Air Force during World War I]]
[[Category:Mustafa Kemal Atatürk]]
[[Category:İsmet İnönü]]</text>
      <sha1>byy13iuu7zc4os08c44tvxytpbe3ymr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
