<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chronology of Provisional Irish Republican Army actions (1970–79)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3946427</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751239747</id>
      <parentid>750882883</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-24T07:49:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 1 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="171061">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}
This is a '''chronology of activities by the Provisional Irish Republican Army''' (IRA) from 1970 to 1979. For actions after this period see [[Chronology of Provisional Irish Republican Army actions]].

==1970==
*26 June: three [[Provisional IRA]] [[Volunteer (Irish republican)|volunteers]] and two young girls (the daughters of one of the volunteers) were killed when an IRA bomb prematurely exploded in a house in [[Creggan, Derry]].&lt;ref name=c70&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1970|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/othelem/chron/ch70.htm|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 June: rioting erupted in working class parts of [[Belfast]] following [[Orange Order]] marches past Catholic areas. IRA volunteers used firearms to defend the [[Short Strand]] and [[Ardoyne]] from attack by [[Ulster loyalism|Ulster loyalist]] gunmen and rioters. Five loyalists and one republican died in the cross-shooting (see [[Battle of St Matthew's]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Taylor|first=Peter|authorlink=Peter Taylor (Journalist)|title=Provos: The IRA &amp; Sinn Féin|publisher=[[Bloomsbury Publishing]]|year=1997|pages=74–77|isbn=0-7475-3818-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*3–5 July: [[Falls Curfew]] - a [[British Army]] raid on the [[Falls Road, Belfast]] developed into a riot between soldiers and residents and then into gun battles between soldiers and the [[Official Irish Republican Army|Official IRA]]. The Provisional IRA also attacked troops with improvised grenades. The British Army sealed off the area, imposed a 36-hour curfew and raided hundreds of homes under the cover of [[CS gas]]. The British Army eventually admitted there had been incidents of looting during these raids.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Oo7lRo4DQw4C&amp;pg=PA120&amp;lpg=PA120&amp;dq=falls+curfew+looting+1970&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=rpafTjDIdJ&amp;sig=zn9nvRF1Ulk4ibnCXDs1uJ3xTBg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=vYCdVdClMoT6ygO9n7joDA&amp;ved=0CEsQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=falls%20curfew%20looting%201970&amp;f=false |title=Ireland's Terrorist Dilemma |page=120 |website=Books.google.com |date=1986-01-01 |accessdate=2016-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four civilians were killed by British soldiers and more than 60 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, pp. 78-83.&lt;/ref&gt;
*11 August: two [[Royal Ulster Constabulary]] (RUC) officers were killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb attached to an abandoned car near [[Crossmaglen]], [[County Armagh|South Armagh]]. The bomb contained {{convert|20|lb|abbr=on}} of [[gelignite]] and exploded when one of the officers attempted to open one of the car's doors.&lt;ref name=&quot;CAIN&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1970.html|title=CAIN: Sutton Index of Deaths|publisher=Cain.ulst.ac.uk|date=8 July 1970}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.tcm.ie/businesspost/2005/07/03/story6123.asp|title=What now for the Fighting Men from Crossmaglen? The Post 03-07-2005|publisher=Archives.tcm.ie|date=3 July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=McKittrick|first=David|authorlink=David McKittrick|author2=Seamus Kelters|author3=Brian Feeney|author4=Chris Thronton|title= Lost Lives |publisher=Mainstream Publishing|year=2000|isbn=1-84018-227-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*4 September: an IRA volunteer was killed when a bomb he was planting at an electricity transformer in Belfast exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=&quot;CAIN&quot;/&gt;
*16 November: the IRA shot dead two alleged criminals in the [[Ballymurphy, Belfast|Ballymurphy]] area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;CAIN&quot;/&gt; The men were alleged to have been involved in protection rackets, fencing stolen goods, minor racketeering, moneylending, burglary and robbery.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 58–59&lt;/ref&gt;

==1971==
===January-February===
*January 1971: following months of clashes between British soldiers and [[Irish nationalist]]s in Ballymurphy, the British Army held secret talks with the IRA. It was agreed that, in parts of West Belfast, the IRA would be responsible for policing and there would be no activity by the British Army or RUC.&lt;ref name=reed158&gt;Reed, David. ''Ireland: The Key to the British Revolution''. Larkin Publications, 1984. pp. 158-59.&lt;!-- ISSN/ISBN needed --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Moloney, Ed. ''A Secret History of the IRA''. Penguin, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 February 1971: under pressure from the [[Unionism in Ireland|unionist]] [[government of Northern Ireland]], the British Army began a series of raids in nationalist areas of West and North Belfast. This sparked clashes between residents and British soldiers, and between nationalists and loyalists. Eight soldiers and a number of civilians were wounded.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA saw the raids as a breach of the policing agreement, and violence continued for the next few nights.&lt;ref name=reed158/&gt;
*6 February 1971: the British Army shot dead IRA staff officer James Saunders (22) in North Belfast. The British Army claimed soldiers removing barricades in the Oldpark district came under gun and bomb attack. In Ardoyne, soldiers shot dead Catholic civilian Bernard Watt (28), whom they claimed was armed, after an [[armoured personnel carrier]] was attacked.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKittrick, p.63&quot;&gt;McKittrick, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; 
*6 February 1971: during clashes between nationalists and British soldiers in the [[New Lodge, Belfast|New Lodge]] district, the IRA opened fire on a group of soldiers, killing Gunner [[Robert Curtis (soldier)|Robert Curtis]]. He was the first British soldier killed in Ireland since the 1920s. The next day, [[James Chichester-Clark]], [[Prime Minister of Northern Ireland]], declared on television that &quot;Northern Ireland is at war with the Irish Republican Army Provisionals&quot;. Eight British soldiers and five civilians were injured in various gun battles around Belfast.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, pp. 89-91.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 64-66&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 February 1971: during clashes on the Crumlin Road, Ardoyne, Belfast, two British Army scout vehicles came under sniper fire and had a bomb thrown at them. A soldier (John Laurie) was shot in the head and died eight days later, on 15 February.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 February 1971: at the funeral of IRA volunteer James Saunders, a [[three-volley salute]] was fired over his coffin by the IRA. The funeral cortege was forced to make a detour when 300 loyalists blocked Oldpark Road and stoned mourners. There were also scuffles with police.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKittrick, p.63&quot;/&gt; There was controversy after a British soldier was filmed saluting the coffin as it passed his armoured car.&lt;ref&gt;Winchester, Simon. ''Northern Ireland in Crisis: Reporting the Ulster Troubles''. Holmes &amp; Meier, 1974. p. 127.&lt;!-- ISSN/ISBN needed --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 February 1971: five men, George Beck (aged 43), John Eakins (aged 52), Harry Edgar (aged 26), David Henson (aged 24), and William Thomas (aged 35) were killed while travelling in Landrover, which detonated a landmine on track, Brougher Mountain, near [[Trillick]], County Tyrone. A British Army mobile patrol was reportedly the intended target. The five were on their way to inspect a transmitter: two of the dead men were BBC engineers, the other three were construction workers. The landmine was intended for a British Army patrol that usually inspected the transmitters.&lt;ref name=c71&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1971|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1971.html|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 66-67&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 February 1971: Two [[RUC Special Patrol Group]] officers, Robert Buckley (aged 30) and Cecil Patterson (aged 45), were killed in a gun battle with the IRA while on Royal Ulster Constabulary mobile patrol, Etna Drive, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 67–68&lt;/ref&gt;

===March-April===
*8 March 1971: Provisional IRA volunteer Charles Hughes (26) was shot dead by the [[Official IRA]], while leaving a house on Leeson Street, Lower Falls, Belfast; part of an ongoing dispute between the PIRA and the OIRA.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt; In response the PIRA shot and seriously injured an OIRA volunteer.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 69–70&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 March 1971: the Provisional IRA kidnapped [[Three Scottish soldiers killings|three off-duty Scottish soldiers (John McCaig, Joseph McCaig, and Dougald McCaughey) in Belfast]], brought them to a mountain road outside the city and shot each in the head. They were the first off-duty soldiers from Britain to be killed in the conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 70–72&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 April 1971: the [[Royal Navy]] survey launch ''Stork'', attached to [[HMS Hecate (A137)|HMS ''Hecate'']], was towed to open seas and sunk by an IRA unit in [[Baltimore, Ireland|Baltimore, County Cork]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/1971/apr/28/royal-navy-hydrographic-survey-launches|title=Parliamentary debate, 28 April 1971|accessdate=22 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===May-June===
*15 May 1971: IRA volunteer [[Billy Reid (Irish republican)|Billy Reid]] was killed during a gun battle between the IRA and the British Army on Academy Street, Belfast. Two British soldiers were wounded in the incident.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 72–73&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 May 1971: a bomb was thrown into [[Springfield Road, Belfast|Springfield Road]] British Army/RUC base in Belfast, killing British Army Sergeant [[Michael Willetts]] as he shielded civilians from the blast with his body. He was posthumously awarded the [[George Cross]]. Seven RUC officers, two British soldiers and 18 civilians were injured.&lt;ref name=s71&gt;{{cite web|title=An Index of Deaths from the Conflict in Ireland|author=Malcolm Sutton|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1971.html|publisher=[[CAIN]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=George Cross awarded to Sergeant Michael Willetts, 3rd Battalion, The Parachute Regiment, 1971|url=http://www.national-army-museum.ac.uk/exhibitions/shortVisits/iconic/page22.shtml|publisher=National Army Museum}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 June 1971: the first recorded Provisional IRA operations in County Tyrone that involved the use of firearms occurred within a short space of time in the east and west of the county. In the first operation a number of shots were fired from a passing commandeered car at a British Army sentry on duty at [[Pomeroy, County Tyrone|Pomeroy]] RUC barracks. This attack occurred at around 1:30am. Shortly afterwards a British Army mobile patrol was ambushed near [[Victoria Bridge, County Tyrone|Victoria Bridge]]. No injuries were reported in either incident.{{cn|date=October 2015}}

===July-August===
*12 July 1971: a British soldier (David Walker, aged 30) was shot dead by an IRA sniper at a British observation post on Northumberland Street, Lower Falls, Belfast. The IRA claimed his death was in retaliation for the killings of two civilians in Derry by the British Army the previous week.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 July 1971: a British soldier (Richard Barton, aged 24) was shot dead in an IRA ambush on a mobile patrol in [[Andersonstown]], Belfast. Three IRA gunmen using automatic weapons fired at least 35 shots at the patrol.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 77–78&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 August 1971: a British soldier (Malcolm Hatton, aged 21) was shot dead in an IRA sniper attack while on foot patrol, Brompton Park, Ardoyne, Belfast. The IRA claimed he was shot in retaliation for the shooting death of a civilian by the British Army the day before on the Springfield Road.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 August 1971: 343 suspects were detained as [[internment]] was introduced (see [[Operation Demetrius]]). In the following two days 17 people were killed in gun battles between the IRA and British Army. The IRA killed two British soldiers (one of them UDR) while the British Army shot dead one IRA volunteer and 14 civilians. Between 1971-75, 1,981 people were interned; 1,874 were Catholic and 107 were Protestant.&lt;ref name=c71/&gt;
*9 August 1971: a UDR soldier (Winston Donnell, aged 22), was killed in a joint PIRA/OIRA ambush at a vehicle check point in [[Clady, County Tyrone]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hanley &amp; Millar|first=B &amp; S|title=The Lost Revolution: The story of the Official IRA and the Workers Party|year=2009|publisher=Penguin Ireland|location=Ireland|isbn=978-1-84488-120-8|page=166}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 August 1971: Norman Watson, a Protestant civilian, was killed in the crossfire between the IRA and soldiers in [[Armagh]]. 
*10 August 1971: Paul Challoner (aged 23), a British soldier, was shot dead by the IRA while on foot patrol, Bligh's Lane, Creggan, Derry.&lt;ref name=c71/&gt;
*11 August 1971: an IRA volunteer (Seamus Simpson, aged 21), was shot dead while throwing a bomb at a British Army foot patrol, Rossnareen Avenue, Andersonstown, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*16 August 1971: the commander of the [[Provisional IRA Belfast Brigade|Provisionals' Belfast Brigade]], [[Joe Cahill]], gave a press conference claiming only 30 IRA volunteers had been interned.&lt;ref name=c71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, pp. 93-94.&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 August 1971: an IRA volunteer (Eamon Lafferty, aged 20) was shot dead during a gun battle between the IRA and the British Army in [[Creggan, Derry|Kildrum Gardens, Creggan, Derry City]].&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*23 August 1971: a British soldier (George Crozier, aged 23) was shot dead by an IRA sniper on Flax Street, [[Ardoyne]], Belfast. The soldier was shot in the head as he exited a British armoured vehicle.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 93–94&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 August 1971: a civilian (Henry Beggs, aged 23) was killed when the IRA bombed the [[Northern Ireland Electricity]] office on Malone Road, Belfast. An inadequate warning was given.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*29 August 1971: Battle of Courtbane, a British soldier (Ian Armstrong, aged 33) was shot dead by an IRA sniper near [[Crossmaglen]], County Armagh. The soldier was travelling in a patrol consisting of two armoured Ferret Scout cars which crossed the [[Irish border]] into [[Co. Louth]] near the vilage of Courtbane. When attempting to retreat back angry locals blocked their way and set one of the vehicles on fire. After eventually managing to get back across the border the patrol had to stop to change a damaged wheel.{{cn|date=November 2016}} While this was happening a six-man IRA unit arrived on the scene and took up sniping positions in nearby fields. The soldier was killed after being shot in the neck. Another soldier was injured when he was struck in the shoulder.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 95–96&lt;/ref&gt;
*31 August 1971: a British soldier (Clifford Loring, aged 18) was killed when he was shot by an IRA sniper at a vehicle checkpoint at Stockman's  Lane, Andersonstown, Belfast. A single shot was fired by a sniper which passed through the shoulder strap of another soldier's flak-jacket before hitting Loring in the head.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref name=k96&gt;McKittrick, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt;

===September-October===
*3 September 1971: a UDR soldier (Francis Veitch, aged 23) was shot dead while on guard duty outside Kinawley Royal Ulster Constabulary, County Fermanagh, when an IRA unit attacked.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref name=k96/&gt;
*3 September 1971: a 17-month old toddler (Angela Gallagher) was killed after being hit by a ricochet bullet in her pram during an IRA sniper attack at a British army patrol in the Iveagh Drive/Iveagh Street area, Falls Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt; 
*9 September 1971: a British Army bomb-disposal expert (David Stewardson, aged 29) died while attempting to defuse a bomb at Castlerobin Orange Hall, Drumankelly, near [[Lisburn]], County Antrim.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*14 September 1971: a British soldier (John Rudman, aged 21) was shot dead while on mobile patrol, Edendork, near [[Coalisland]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*15 September 1971: a British soldier (Paul Carter, aged 21) died one day after being shot outside Royal Victoria Hospital, Falls Road, Belfast by the IRA.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*17 September 1971: a British soldier (Peter Herrington, aged 28) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol, Brompton Park, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*18 September 1971: an RUC officer (Robert Leslie, aged 20) was shot dead while on foot patrol by the IRA at Abercorn Square, [[Strabane]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*23 September 1971: a patrol boat belonging to the Northern Ireland Fishery Conservancy Board was bombed and wrecked by an IRA unit at Derryinver, [[Lough Neagh]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=Nx8-AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=a0oMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3554,3533800&amp;dq=neagh+bomb+boats&amp;hl=en Evening News] 23 September 1971&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 October 1971: a British soldier (Peter Sharpe, aged 22) was shot dead in an IRA gun attack on a British Army foot patrol, Kerrera Street, [[Ardoyne]], Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*2 October 1971: an IRA volunteer (Terence McDermott, aged 19) died after the bomb he was transporting to an electricity sub-station at Lambeg, near Lisburn, County Antrim, exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*3 October 1971: an Agriculture Ministry imports inspector (Patrick Daly, aged 57) from [[Moira, County Down]] was shot dead by the IRA.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1454&amp;dat=19711004&amp;id=3alOAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=tQkEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1704,691497&amp;hl=en Notice of death of Patrick Daly]; accessed 9 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; 
*11 October 1971: a British soldier (Roger Wilkins, aged 32) was shot dead by the IRA while on foot-patrol on Letterkenny Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*15 October 1971: two RUC officers, Cecil Cunningham (aged 46) and John Haslett (aged 21), were shot dead by an IRA unit while sitting in stationary RUC vehicle at the junction of Woodvale Road and Twaddell Avenue, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*16 October 1971: a British soldier (Joseph Hill, aged 24) was shot dead by the IRA during street disturbances, Columcille Court, Bogside, Derry.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*17 October 1971: a British soldier (Graham Cox, aged 35) died two days after being shot by an IRA sniper while travelling in a British Army armoured personnel carrier, Oldpark Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*17 October 1971: a British soldier (George Hamilton, aged 21) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol, Glenalina Park, Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt; 
*23 October 1971: two female IRA volunteers, Maura Meehan (aged 30) and Dorothy Maguire (aged 19), were shot dead by the British Army while travelling in car warning local residents of house raids, Cape Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*24 October 1971: an IRA volunteer (Martin Forsythe, aged 19) was shot dead by the RUC during a bomb attack, Celebrity Club, Donegall Place, Belfast. His partner in the mission, IRA volunteer and later Sinn Féin politician [[Rita O'Hare]], was seriously wounded.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*27 October 1971: two British soldiers, David Tilbury (aged 29) and Angus Stevens (aged 18), were killed in an IRA bomb attack on an observation post at the rear of Rosemount RUC/British Army base, Derry.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*27 October 1971: an RUC officer (Ronald Dodd, aged 34) was shot dead by an IRA sniper when he arrived with a mobile patrol at the scene of fire in a house, Gallagh, near [[Toome]], County Antrim.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*27 October 1971: a British soldier (David Powell, aged 22) was killed when a British Army armoured personnel carrier struck an IRA landmine in [[Kinawley]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*29 October 1971: an RUC officer (Alfred Devlin, aged 42), was killed in a bomb attack on Chichester Road Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) base, off the [[Antrim Road]], Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*30 October 1971: a British soldier (Norman Booth, aged 22) was killed when the IRA bombed a British Army Observation Post on the junction of Springfield Road and Cupar Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*31 October 1971: a British soldier (Ian Doherty, aged 27) died three days after being shot while on mobile patrol, Stockman's Lane, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;

===November-December===
*1 November 1971: two RUC officers, Stanley Corry (aged 28) and William Russell (aged 31), were shot dead by an IRA unit while investigating a burglary, Avoca Shopping Centre, Andersonstown, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*2 November 1971: three civilians (John Cochrane, Mary Gemmell, and William Jordan) were killed in bomb attacks on a drapery shop and Red Lion Bar, either side of Ormeau Road Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) base, Belfast. They were drinking in the Red Lion Bar, next door to the base at the time. Jordan died on 4 November 1971. Inadequate warning given.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*4 November 1971: a British soldier (Stephen McGuire, aged 20) died seven weeks after being shot in an IRA attack on the Henry Taggart British Army base, Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*7 November 1971: an off-duty British soldier (Paul Genge, aged 18) was shot dead while walking along Tandragee Road, [[Lurgan]], County Armagh, in an IRA drive-by attack.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*9 November 1971: a British soldier (Ian Curtis, aged 23) was shot dead while on foot patrol by an IRA sniper on Foyle Road, Derry City.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*11 November 1971: two RUC officers, Dermot Hurley (aged 50) and Walter Moore (aged 37), were shot dead by the IRA in a shop at the rear of Oldpark Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) base, Oldpark Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*18 November 1971: a British soldier (Edwin Charnley, aged 22) was shot dead by the IRA while guarding a bus depot, Anderson Street, [[Short Strand]], Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*22 November 1971: Michael Crossey (aged 21), an IRA volunteer was killed in a premature bomb explosion at Cellar Lounge Bar, Church Place, Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt; 
*23 November 1971: a civilian from [[County Donegal]] (Bridget Carr, aged 24) died four days after being shot during a sniper attack on a nearby British Army patrol while walking along Lifford Road, [[Strabane]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*24 November 1971: a British Army bomb disposal expert (Colin Davies, aged 38) was killed attempting to defuse a car-bomb left in a car showroom, William Street, Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*27 November 1971: two Customs Officials were killed when IRA snipers attacked Killeen Customs Post near [[Newry]]. The soldiers guarding the post were reportedly the intended targets.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*27 November 1971: a British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol, [[Falls Road, Belfast]].&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*29 November 1971: an off-duty British soldier was shot dead by the IRA near [[Crossmaglen]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*6 December 1971: a civilian was killed in an IRA bomb attack in Belfast. The bomb destroyed a business premises. The damage resulted in one of the walls collapsing in on top of the building next door, crushing the civilian.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*7 December 1971: a UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA, Curlagh, Aghaloo, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*8 December 1971: two British soldiers were killed in separate IRA gun attacks in Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*10 December 1971: a UDR soldier and an ex-soldier were killed when their car was attacked by an IRA unit near Clady, Strabane, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*11 December 1971: a bomb attack on a furniture shop on the [[Shankill Road]] in Belfast killed four [[Protestant]] civilians, including two children.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt; No organisation claimed responsibility, but there was speculation that it may have been planted by the IRA in retaliation for the [[McGurk's Bar bombing]] of 4 December.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 129&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 December 1971: a British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper in the Lower Falls area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*18 December 1971: three IRA volunteers died in [[Magherafelt]], [[County Londonderry]], when the bomb they were transporting exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=c71/&gt;
*21 December 1971: a Catholic publican was killed when he picked up and attempted to remove a bomb that had been planted in his pub on Lisburn Road, Belfast. Although Catholic-owned pubs were usually targeted by loyalists, the ''Sutton'' database lists the IRA as responsible.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*21 December 1971: an IRA volunteer was shot dead after being captured by the British Army in the Ardoyne area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*29 December 1971: a British soldier was shot dead in an IRA gun attack on a foot patrol in the Brandywell area of Derry City.&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;
*31 December 1971: an IRA volunteer was killed when a bomb he was assembling exploded accidentally in [[Santry]], [[Dublin]].&lt;ref name=s71/&gt;

==1972==
===January===
*5 January 1972: A British soldier (Keith Bryan, aged 18), was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol, Ardmoulin Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1972|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1972.html|accessdate=9 December 2015|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 January 1972: An IRA volunteer (Daniel O'Neill, aged 20) died two days after being shot during a gun battle with British troops, Oranmore Street, Clonard, West Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*12 January 1972: An off-duty RUC reservist (Raymond Denham, aged 42) was shot dead by an IRA unit at his workplace, Waterford Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 January 1972: An off-duty UDR soldier (Maynard Crawford, aged 38) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while driving his firm's van along King's Road, off Doagh Road, [[Newtownabbey]], County Antrim.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*17 January: Seven IRA volunteers, jailed in the prison ship [[HMS Maidstone (1937)|HMS ''Maidstone'']], made good their escape through a porthole on the side away from the dock. They swam to the dockside and hijacked a bus which they drove to the Markets area.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=NpgrAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=mvUFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6826,1893057&amp;dq=belfast+ship+ira&amp;hl=en &quot;British troops search for IRA ship escapees&quot;], Associated Press, 18 January 1972.&lt;/ref&gt; The escapees later held a press conference.&lt;ref&gt;Hamill, Desmond (1985). ''Pig in the Middle - The Army in Northern Ireland, 1969-1984''. Methuen London Ltd., p. 95; ISBN 0413508005&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 January 1972: A British soldier (Philip Stentiford, aged 18) was killed when he stepped on an IRA landmine, Derrynoose, near [[Keady]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*26 January 1972: An IRA volunteer (Peter McNulty, aged 47) was killed when a bomb he was planting at an RUC base in [[Castlewellan]], County Down, exploded accidentally.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*27 January 1972: An IRA unit fought a 4-hour gun battle with a British Army detachment at Dungooley, County Armagh. The British Army alone fired over 4,500 rounds while the IRA returned fire with assault rifles and an anti-tank gun. There were no casualties in the battle with the exception of a pig which was caught in the crossfire. Eight IRA volunteers were arrested south of the border but were eventually acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;''Bandit Country'' by [[Toby Harnden]], Coronet Books, 2010; ISBN 0-340-71737-8, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 January 1972: Two RUC officers, Peter Gilgunn (aged 26) and David Montgomery (aged 20), were killed when their patrol vehicle was hit by IRA gunfire in [[Creggan, Derry]].&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 January 1972: An off-duty RUC officer (Raymond Carroll, aged 22)) was shot dead in an IRA gun attack at a garage, Oldpark Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*30 January 1972: A British soldier Robin Alers-Hankey (aged 35) died four months after being injured in an IRA sniper attack in the [[Bogside]], Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===February===
*1 February 1972: A British soldier, Ian Bramley (aged 25), was shot dead by an IRA sniper while leaving Hastings Street Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC)/British Army (BA) base, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*2 February 1972: A bomb exploded at the Catholic-owned Imperial Bar in [[Stewartstown, County Tyrone]]. The pub was officially closed in mourning for those who died on [[Bloody Sunday (1972)|Bloody Sunday]], but some customers had gone in through the back door for a drink. One Catholic civilian, Louis O'Neill (aged 49), was killed. There was initial newspaper speculation that the IRA had bombed the bar because it had not closed fully, and the ''Sutton'' database lists the IRA as responsible.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; However, some believe loyalists were responsible for the attack.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 February 1972: Paul McFadden (aged 31), a Catholic civilian, died six days after being injured in a van bomb explosion at Castle Arcade, off Castle Lane, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; 
*5 February 1972: Two IRA volunteers (Phelim Grant and Charles McCann) were killed when a bomb they were transporting exploded accidentally on a [[barge]] near [[Crumlin, County Antrim|Crumlin]], [[Lough Neagh]], [[County Antrim]].&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*10 February 1972: An IRA volunteer (Joseph Cunningham, aged 26) was killed in a gun battle with the RUC at O'Neill's Road, [[Newtownabbey]], County Antrim.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*10 February 1972: Two British soldiers, Ian Harris (aged 26) and David Champ (aged 23), were killed in an IRA [[landmine]] attack on their Armoured Personnel Carrier in [[Cullyhanna]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 February 1972: An off-duty British soldier, Thomas McCann (aged 19), from [[Dublin]], was shot dead by the IRA near [[Newtownbutler]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*16 February 1972: Thomas Callaghan (aged 45), a Catholic member of the [[Ulster Defence Regiment]], was found shot dead shortly after being abducted while driving a bus along Foyle Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; 
*16 February 1972: Michael Prime (aged 18), British Army, was shot dead while on mobile patrol by a sniper by the Moira roundabout, MI Motorway, County Down.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*17 February 1972: Elizabeth English (aged 65), a Catholic civilian, died seven days after being shot during an attempted ambush of a British Army foot patrol, Barrack Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; 
*21 February 1972: Four IRA volunteers (Gerard Bell, Robert Dorrian, Joseph Magee, and Gerard Steele) died in Belfast when a bomb they were transporting exploded prematurely along Knockbreda Road, near the Castlereagh Road roundabout, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*29 February 1972: An off-duty UDR soldier, Henry Dickson (aged 46), was shot dead by the IRA at his home, Lawrence Street, Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===March===
*1 March 1972: An off-duty UDR soldier, John Fletcher (aged 43), was shot dead by the IRA outside his home, Frevagh, near [[Garrison, County Fermanagh]].&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*3 March 1972: A British soldier (Stephen Keating, aged 18) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol, Manor Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; 
*4 March 1972: An IRA volunteer, Albert Kavanagh (aged 18), was shot dead by the RUC during an attempted bomb attack on factory, Boucher Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*4 March 1972: A bomb exploded at the Abercorn Restaurant in Belfast without any warning. Two Catholic civilians (Anne Owens, aged 22, and  Janet Bereen, aged 21) were killed and over 100 people maimed and injured. IRA operatives blamed, but the PIRA has never acknowledged responsibility for what may have been a rogue operation.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 March 1972: A UDR soldier (Joseph Jardine, aged 44), off-duty Ulster Defence Regiment (UDR) soldier, shot dead at his workplace, Ministry of Agriculture office, [[Middletown, County Armagh]].&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*9 March 1972: Four IRA volunteers, Gerard Crossen (aged 19), Sean Johnson (aged 19), Anthony Lewis (aged 16), and Thomas McCann (aged 20), were all killed in a premature bomb explosion inside a house on Clonard Street, Lower Falls, Belfast, when a bomb they were assembling exploded accidentally.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*14 March 1972: Two IRA volunteers, Colm Keenan (aged 19) and Eugene McGillan (aged 18) were shot dead by the British Army in an entry off Dove Gardens, Bogside, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*14 March 1972: A two-man IRA unit armed with sub-machine guns ambushed a joint British Army/RUC patrol on Brackaville Road outside [[Coalisland]], County Tyrone. Over 50 shots were fired by the unit. The RUC officer, William Logan (aged 23), who was driving the police patrol vehicle was mortally wounded and died the following day.&lt;ref&gt;Sheehy, p. 58&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 March 1972: After the end of a three-day cease fire, an IRA bomb caused widespread damage in the main street of [[Lisburn]]. Three soldiers and an RUC officer were wounded.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=eTwaAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=dCcEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4527,4140828&amp;dq=derry+ira+1972+wounded&amp;hl=en ''Spokane Daily Chronicle''] via [[Associated Press]], 14 March 1972&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 March 1972: Two British soldiers, Christopher Cracknell (aged 29) and Anthony Butcher (aged 24), were killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb hidden in an abandoned car, Grosvenor Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*20 March 1972: Two RUC officers, a British soldier and four civilians were killed when the [[1972 Donegall Street bombing|IRA detonated a car bomb on Donegall Street]] in Belfast. The warning had been inadequate.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*20 March 1972: Royal Green Jackets Rifleman John Taylor (aged 19) was shot dead by an IRA sniper at Lower Road near William Street in Derry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.irishtimes.com/news/call-for-mcguinness-to-give-details-of-ira-killings-1.411469 |title=Call for McGuinness to give details of IRA killings |website=Irishtimes.com |date=2002-01-25 |accessdate=2016-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 March 1972: The IRA detonated two car bombs in Main Street, [[Bangor, County Down]].&lt;ref&gt;Sheehy, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 March 1972: An IRA volunteer (Patrick Campbell, aged 16) was shot dead in error by another IRA volunteer, while preparing for an ambush of a British Army patrol at the junction of Springhill Avenue and Springfield Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 March 1972: The IRA carried out a car-bomb attack on Limavady RUC base, [[Limavady]], County Londonderry. Joseph Forsythe (aged 57) and Robert McMichael (aged 27), unrelated Protestant civilians, were killed while driving past the Royal Ulster Constabulary base, [[Limavady|Limavady, County Londonderry]] when a van bomb explosion was detonated.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*29 March 1972: A British soldier (Bernard Calladene, aged 39) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb hidden inside an abandoned car, Wellington Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*30 March 1972: A Catholic civilian, Martha Crawford (aged 39), was killed in the crossfire of a gun-battle between the IRA and the British Army, Rossnareen Avenue, [[Andersonstown]], Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===April===
*7 April 1972: Three IRA volunteers, Samuel Hughes, Charles McCrystal, and John McErlean (all aged 17), were killed in a premature bomb explosion in a garage in Bawnmore Park, Greencastle, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*8 April 1972: A British soldier (Peter Sime, aged 22) on foot patrol was killed in an IRA sniper attack on the Springfield Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 April 1972: The IRA detonated a car-bomb on Main Street, [[Ballymoney]], County Antrim. Despite a warning to evacuate the area, a Protestant civilian, Elizabeth McAuley (aged 64), was killed.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*17 April 1972: A British Army officer and three soldiers were shot and wounded by an IRA unit at Divis Flats, Belfast. A nine-year-old boy was also injured.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=O7EiAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=OrMFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5529,553275&amp;dq=defused+bomb+1972+derry&amp;hl=en Beaver County Times], United Press International, 18 April 1972.&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 April 1972: An off-duty UDR soldier, James Elliott (aged 36), was abducted and murdered by the IRA near [[Newtownhamilton]], County Armagh. He was found shot dead by the side of the road, Altnamackan, near [[Newtownhamilton]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; 
*19 April 1972: A Catholic civilian, Martin Owens (aged 22), was found dead shortly after being thrown from a car, Horn Drive, Suffolk, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; 
*25 April 1972: A British soldier, Joseph Gold (aged 29), died four days after being shot in an IRA gun-attack on a British Army Vehicle Check Point, Donegall Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*29 April 1972: A Catholic civilian (Rosaleen Gavin, aged 8) was killed in the crossfire during an IRA sniper attack on the British Army base at Oldpark Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===May===
*10 May 1972: An IRA bomb set a fire that destroyed the Belfast Co-operative store.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*11 May 1972: A British soldier (John Ballard, aged 18) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on patrol, Sultan Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 May 1972: An IRA volunteer (John Starrs, aged 19) was shot dead in a gun-battle with the British Army on William Street, Derry City.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 May 1972: A British soldier (Alan Buckley, aged 22) was shot dead in a gun-battle with the IRA in Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*14 May 1972: A Protestant civilian (John Pedlow, aged 17), died one day after being shot during a gun battle between IRA volunteers and loyalists, Springmartin Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*17 May 1972: A British soldier (Ronald Hurst, aged 25), a British Amy soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while repairing a damaged perimeter fence at the British Army base, Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*18 May 1972: A British soldier (John Hillman, aged 28) died three days after being shot by a sniper, Flax Street, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*20 May 1972: A UDR soldier (Henry Gillespie, aged 32), was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on mobile patrol, Killyliss, near Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*23 May 1972: A British soldier (Eustace Handley, aged 20) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol, Springhill Avenue, Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*26 May 1972: The IRA detonated a car-bomb on Oxford Street in Belfast. A Protestant civilian (Margaret Young, aged 64) was killed in the explosion.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 May 1972: Four IRA volunteers (Joseph Fitzsimmons (aged 17), John McIlhone (aged 17), Edward McDonnell (aged 29), and Martin Engelen (aged 19)), along with four Catholic civilians (Henry Crawford (aged 39), Mary Clarke (aged 27), John Nugent (aged 31), and Geraldine McMahon (aged 17)) were killed when a bomb being prepared detonated prematurely inside a house on Anderson Street, Short Strand, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*30 May 1972: A Protestant civilian, Joan Scott (12), died three days after being shot during an IRA sniper attack on a RUC mobile patrol, Oldpark Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; 
*30 May 1972: A British Army soldier, Marcel Doglay (aged 28), was killed when a time bomb exploded inside the Springfield Road RUC/British Army base, Belfast. 
*30 May 1972: A British Army soldier on mobile patrol, Michael Bruce (aged 27), was shot dead by an IRA sniper, Kennedy Way, Andersonstown, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===June===
*2 June 1972: Two British Army soldiers, Victor Husband (aged 23) and Brian  Robertson (aged 23) were killed by an IRA land mine attack on their foot patrol, Derryvolan, near [[Rosslea]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*6 June 1972: Two British Army soldiers were killed in separate IRA sniper attacks in Belfast. George Lee (aged 22), shot by sniper while on foot patrol, Ballymurphy Parade, Ballymurphy, Belfast. Charles Coleman (aged 29) was shot by a sniper while on mobile patrol, Tullymore Gardens, Andersonstown, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*8 June 1972: A member of the [[Garda Síochána]], Samuel Donegan (aged 61), was killed when he set off an IRA booby-trap bomb left by the side of a road. He had inadvertently strayed a few yards across the border into Legakelly, near Newtownbutler, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*8 June 1972: A UDR soldier on mobile patrol, Edward Megahey (aged 44), died three days after being shot by an IRA sniper, Buncrana Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*9 June 1972: An off-duty UDR soldier, Roy Stanton (aged 27), was shot dead as he left his workplace, Autolite factory, Finaghy Road North, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*11 June 1972: Colonel [[Muammar al-Gaddafi]] announced he had supplied arms to &quot;revolutionaries&quot; in Ireland. There were shooting incidents across Belfast and Northern Ireland, including a gun battle between loyalist and republican paramilitaries in the Oldpark area of Belfast. A Catholic civilian (John Madden, aged 24) was shot dead outside his shop on Oldpark Road, Belfast. An Irish Republican Army Youth Section (IRAF) volunteer (Joseph Campbell (aged 16) was shot dead during a gun battle at Eskdale Gardens, Ardoyne, Belfast. A Protestant civilian (Norman McGrath, aged 18)  was shot from a passing British Army Armoured Personnel Carrier as he walked along Alloa Street, Lower Oldpark, Belfast. A British soldier (Peter Raistrick, aged 18) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while at the Brooke Park British Army base, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*12 June 1972: A British Army soldier, Alan Giles (24), was shot dead by the IRA during a gun-battle in the Ardoyne area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1972.html|title=CAIN: Sutton Index of Deaths|publisher=Cain.ulst.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 June 1972: Three British soldiers (Arthur McMillan (aged 37), Ian Mutch (aged 31) and Colin Leslie (aged 26)) were killed in an IRA booby-trap bomb attack. The bomb had been left in a derelict house in [[The Troubles in Bleary|Bleary, County Armagh]].&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=June 1972 |work=Operation Banner - Deaths - Roll of Honour |url=http://www.operationbanner.com/roh/default.asp?MonthAsNumber=6 |accessdate=2 December 2011 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110930162715/http://www.operationbanner.com/roh/default.asp?MonthAsNumber=6 |archivedate=30 September 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 June 1972: An associate of the OIRA{{cn|date=November 2016}} (Desmond Mackin, aged 37) was shot dead by the PIRA during a dispute in the Cracked Cup Social Club, Leeson Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*19 June 1972: A British soldier, Bryan Sodden (aged 21), was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on mobile patrol, Brompton Park, Ardoyne, Belfast. &lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*21 June 1972: A British soldier, Kerry McCarthy (aged 19), was shot dead while on sentry duty outside Victoria Royal Ulster Constabulary/British Army base, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*24 June 1972: Three British soldiers were killed by an IRA [[land mine]] attack near [[Dungiven]], [[County Londonderry]].&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*26 June 1972: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on mobile-patrol in the Short Strand area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*26 June–8 July 1972: IRA ceasefire and talks with British government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geraghty|first=Tony|title=The Irish War|publisher=[[Harper Collins]]|year=2000|pages=68–70|isbn=978-0-00-638674-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 June 1972: A civilian was shot dead by the IRA after attempting to drive though one of their vehicle checkpoints.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===July===
*7 July 1972: A civilian was shot dead after crashing his car into an IRA roadblock.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*9 July 1972: A UDA member was shot dead by the IRA in the Markets area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*11 July 1972: A British soldier was shot dead in an IRA gun attack in Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 July 1972: Four British soldiers and an IRA volunteer were killed in various gun-battles across Belfast. The British Army also killed two armed men.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*14 July 1972: An IRA volunteer was shot dead in a gun battle with the British Army. Also killed in the violence were three British soldiers, an OIRA volunteer and a civilian.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*15 July 1972: Two British soldiers were killed in separate IRA attacks in Belfast and Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; [[William Whitelaw, 1st Viscount Whitelaw|William Whitelaw]], Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, speaking at the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]], claimed that the IRA had six rocket launchers in its inventory to this date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = 10 Killed in Ulster; I. R. A. Fires Rockets (July 15, 1972)|url = http://archives.chicagotribune.com/1972/07/15/page/1/article/10-killed-in-ulster-i-r-a-fires-rockets|accessdate = 2015-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*16 July 1972: Two British soldiers were killed in an IRA landmine attack on their armoured vehicle in Crossmaglen, County Armagh. In Belfast an RUC officer was killed in an IRA gun attack on his patrol car. A member of the IRA Youth Section ([[Fianna Éireann|Na Fianna]]), was killed by a rubber bullet fired by security forces in Strabane, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*18 July 1972: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper at the British Army base in Ballymurphy, Belfast. The IRA also shot dead a civilian who attempted to stop a bomb attack on a building in Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;/&gt;
*20 July 1972: A civilian was shot dead attempting to stop an IRA bomb attack on his business premises.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*21 July 1972: On &quot;[[Bloody Friday (1972)|Bloody Friday]]&quot; 22 bombs in Belfast killed two British soldiers, a UDA member and six civilians and injured 130 others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bloody Friday: What happened|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/2132219.stm|publisher=BBC|date=16 July 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA officially apologised for this set of attacks in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Q&amp;A: The IRA's apology|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/2132188.stm|publisher=BBC|date=16 July 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; An IRA volunteer was killed in a gun battle with British troops in the Markets area of Belfast.
*23 July 1972: A UDR soldier was kidnapped and shot dead by the IRA in the Ardoyne area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*24 July 1972: A Chinese restaurant was destroyed by an IRA bomb in the Dockside area of Derry. As British troops arrived on the scene they were ambushed by a sniper. One civilian was wounded in the crossfire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,877932,00.html|title=The World: The War of the Flea|publisher=Time.com|date=31 July 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 July 1972: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper in Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*26 July 1972: A British soldier was shot dead in an IRA attack on a British foot-patrol in the Unity Flats, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 July 1972: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by a British sniper while sitting in a car outside the &quot;Starry Plough Bar&quot; in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*31 July 1972: Three car bombs exploded in the [[Claudy bombings]], killing nine people on [[Claudy]] High Street near Derry. The IRA have always denied involvement, but they are believed to have been responsible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Does this letter prove a priest was behind IRA bombing?|author=Rosie Cowan|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/Northern_Ireland/Story/0,2763,796304,00.html|publisher=The Guardian|date=21 September 2002|location=London, UK}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Operation Motorman]], the biggest British military operation since the [[Suez crisis]], the army used 12,000 soldiers supported by tanks and bulldozers to dismantle barricades and take IRA held &quot;no go areas&quot; in Belfast and Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===August===
*3 August 1972: An IRA volunteer and a British soldier were killed in separate attacks in Belfast and Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*4 August 1972: A British soldier was killed by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol in the Andersonstown area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*7 August 1972: Four British soldiers were killed in three separate IRA attacks across Northern Ireland.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*9 August 1972: An IRA volunteer was killed when a bomb exploded accidentally in a garage in Newry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*11 August 1972: Two IRA volunteers died when the vanbomb they were transporting exploded prematurely in the Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*14 August 1972: Two British soldiers were killed in an IRA booby-trap bomb attack at Casement Park British Army base in Belfast. A civilian was also killed in the crossfire between an IRA unit and a British patrol in the Ardoyne area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*17 August 1972: A British soldier was shot dead by the IRA in a sniper attack just off the Grosvenor Road in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*18 August 1972: Two British soldiers were killed in separate IRA sniper attacks in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*22 August 1972: The IRA shot dead a member of the [[Loyalist Association of Workers]] on Turin Street in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*22 August 1972: A bomb prematurely exploded at a customs post in Newry, killing nine people, including three IRA volunteers.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*23 August 1972: A British soldier was shot dead in an IRA sniper attack in the Andersonstown area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*24 August 1972: A British soldier was killed in an IRA landmine attack on a British mobile-patrol in Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*25 August 1972: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper in the [[Shantallow]] area of Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*26 August 1972: Two UDR soldiers were killed in an IRA remote controlled bomb attack in Cherrymount, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*26 August 1972: Two IRA volunteers died in a premature bomb explosion in [[Downpatrick]], County Down.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*27 August 1972: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper in Creggan Heights, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 August 1972: A British soldier was shot dead in an IRA sniper attack on Beechmount Avenue in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt; A civilian was also killed when he triggered a booby-trap bomb near his farm in County Fermanagh. It was reported that the bomb had been intended for soldiers who were patrolling the area following reports of gunfire.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 257&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 August 1972: Two British soldiers were killed in separate IRA gun and bomb attacks in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===September===
*10 September 1972: three British soldiers were killed in an IRA landmine attack on a British Army armoured personnel carrier near Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*15 September 1972: a British soldier was shot dead in an IRA sniper attack in the Bogside area of Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;/&gt;
*17 September 1972: an IRA volunteer was shot dead by the British Army during a riot in the Creggan area of Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*18 September 1972: a British soldier was shot dead in an IRA gun attack while on foot-patrol in the Lecky Road area of Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*20 September 1972: a British soldier was killed in a gun battle with the IRA on Springhill Avenue in Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*21 September 1972: a UDR soldier and his wife were killed in an IRA gun attack on their home in [[Derrylin]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*22 September 1972: a British soldier was killed in an IRA sniper attack in Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*27 September 1972: a British soldier was killed in an IRA gun attack in Derry. A civilian was killed in an IRA gun attack at the corner of Ligoniel Road and Mill Avenue, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*29 September 1972: an IRA volunteer and a British soldier were killed in a gun-battle in the Lower Falls area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*30 September 1972: a British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper in the Ardoyne area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===October===
*2 October 1972: an undercover British soldier (Edward Stuart, aged 20) was shot dead by the IRA while driving laundry van, Juniper Park, Twinbrook, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*2 October 1972: the IRA kidnapped three alleged informers (Edward Bonner, Kevin McKee and Seamus Wright), who were later killed and buried.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*6 October 1972: an IRA volunteer (Daniel McAreavey, aged 21) was killed during an IRA attack on a British Army base,  Osman Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*10 October 1972: an off-duty UDR soldier (John Ruddy, aged 50) was shot dead by the IRA outside his home, Dromalane Park, Newry, County Down.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*10 October 1972: three IRA volunteers died (John Donaghy, Patrick Maguire and Joseph McKinney) when a bomb they were assembling exploded in a house, Balkan Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 October 1972: an off-duty RUC officer (Robert Nicholl, aged 22) was shot dead by the IRA while driving his car along Castle Street in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*18 October 1972: a British soldier (Anthony David, aged 27) died four weeks after being shot by an IRA sniper while on mobile-patrol, Falls Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*22 October 1972: an off-duty UDR soldier (John Bell, aged 21) was shot dead by the IRA on his farm, Derrydoon, near Newtownbutler, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*22 October 1972: two barges were bombed and sunk by the IRA at [[Lough Neagh]] with a loss of £80,000.&lt;ref&gt;Deutsch, Richard and Magowan, Vivian: ''Northern Ireland, 1968-73: 1968-74, a Chronology of Events'', Blackstaff Press, 1973, p. 231&lt;!-- ISSN/ISBN needed --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 October 1972: two British soldiers were killed in separate IRA sniper and bomb attacks in Belfast and Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 October 1972: a British soldier (Thomas McKay, aged 29), was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol on Bishop Street, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*31 October 1971: a British soldier (Richard Sinclair, aged 19) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol, Antrim Road, New Lodge, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===November===
*8 November 1972: a UDR soldier  (Irwin Long, aged 29) was shot dead by the IRA while driving his car along Lake Street, Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*10 November 1972: a British soldier (Ronald Kitchen, aged 20) was shot dead by the IRA while manning a vehicle checkpoint, Oldpark Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 November 1972: an IRA volunteer (Stanislaus Carberry, aged 34), was shot dead by the British Army while driving his car along La Salle Drive, Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*14 November 1972: a British soldier (Stanley Evans, aged 19) was shot dead by the IRA as he stood guarding homes being raided by the British Army, Stanhope Street, Unity Flats, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*16 November 1972: an RUC officer  (Joseph Calvin, aged 42) was killed by an under-car booby trap bomb which detonated in car park, Quay Lane, Enniskillen, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*20 November 1972: two British soldiers, William Watson (aged 28) and James Strothers (aged 31), were killed by a booby-trap bomb hidden in an abandoned house in Cullyhanna, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*22 November 1972: an off-duty UDR soldier (Samuel Porter, aged 30) was shot dead by the IRA at his home, Ballinahone, near Maghera, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 November 1972: the IRA fired 15 rockets at ten security posts throughout Northern Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Soviet rockets used in Ulster&quot;. ''The Age'', 30 November 1972.&lt;/ref&gt; One RUC officer (Robert Keys, aged 55) was killed in a rocket attack on [[Belleek, County Fermanagh|Belleek RUC/British Army]] base, County Fermanagh. This marks the first recorded use of an [[RPG-7]] by the IRA.&lt;ref&gt;Oppenheimer, p. 240&lt;/ref&gt; Two IRA volunteers, John Brady (aged 21) and James Carr (aged 19), were killed in a premature bomb explosion in the Bogside, Derry. A British Army bomb disposal expert, Paul Jackson (aged 21), was killed while attempting to defuse an IRA bomb, Strand Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

===December===
*5 December 1972: the IRA fired 15 rockets and mortars at security posts throughout Northern Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;''The Age'', 7 December 1972.&lt;/ref&gt; An off-duty UDR soldier (William Bogle, aged 27) was shot dead by the IRA outside a post office, Main Street, Killeter, near Castlederg, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*6 December 1972: eleven British soldiers were hurt when their APC was hit by a rocket in the Lower Falls district of Belfast. One of them lost an arm. Another three soldiers were hurt in a gun attack on their APC in the Ballymurphy district of Belfast.&lt;ref&gt;''The Glasgow Herald'', 7 December 1972.&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 December 1972: a widowed mother of ten, [[Jean McConville]], was kidnapped and killed by the IRA, purportedly for being an informer, although her family denied the claim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Army thought McConville disappearance a hoax|url=http://www.policeombudsman.org/modules/press/press.cfm/action/detail/Press_ID/139/Archive/2006/year/2006/level/page|publisher=Police Ombudsman|date=13 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA denied any involvement in the killing until the 1990s, when it issued an acknowledgement and helped to locate the body. An investigation many years later by N.I. Ombudsman [[Nuala O'Loan]] found no evidence Mrs McConville had been an informer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=IRA 'sorry' for Disappeared|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/3210967.stm|publisher=BBC|date=24 October 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 December 1972: a British soldier (John Joesbury, aged 18) died two days after being shot by the IRA while on mobile patrol, Whiterock Road, Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*10 December 1972: a British soldier (Stewart Middlemass, aged 33) was killed by a booby-trapped bomb attached to a rocket launched by the IRA at Fort Monagh British Army, Turf Lodge, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*13 December 1972: an off-duty RUC officer (James Nixon, aged 49) was shot dead by the IRA outside the Chester Park Hotel, Antrim Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*16 December 1972: an IRA volunteer (Louis Leonard, aged 26) was shot dead by loyalists at his butchers shop in Derrylin, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*18 December 1972: [[Ulster Unionist Party]] councillor William Johnston (aged 48) was kidnapped from his home on the Drumarg estate, Armagh. He was found shot dead a short time later at Knockbane, near Middletown, County Armagh. He was also a member of the Police Authority.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*20 December 1972: an off-duty UDR soldier (George Hamilton, aged 28) was shot dead by the IRA at his workplace, a building site, Kildoag, Claudy, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*24 December 1972: a British soldier (Colin Harker, aged 23) died three months after being shot by an IRA sniper on Lecky Road, Derry. He was injured on 14 September 1972.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*27 December 1972: an IRA volunteer (Eugene Devlin, aged 22) was killed by the British Army during an attempted sniper attack on their patrol, Townsend Street, Strabane, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;
*28 December 1972: an IRA volunteer (James McDaid, aged 30) was shot dead by the British Army while walking across a field, Ballyarnet,  County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=c72/&gt;

==1973==
*1 January 1973: a rocket hit Springfield Road RUC base in Belfast, injuring two people. The following night, another rocket was fired at [[Beragh]] RUC base, County Tyrone. It missed the target and hit an unoccupied house nearby.&lt;ref&gt;''Star News'', 3 January 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*4 January 1973: a UDR soldier (James Hood, aged 48) was shot dead by the IRA outside his home in Straidarran, near Feeny, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=d73&gt;{{cite web|title=Sutton Index of Deaths - 1973|author=Malcolm Sutton|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1973.html|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 January 1973: a civilian (Trevor Rankin, aged 18) was shot dead by the IRA outside a Ben Madigan filling station, Shore Road, Belfast. He had been mistaken for an off-duty UDR soldier.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*14 January 1973: three members of the RUC (David Dorsett, Henry Sandford, and Mervyn Wilson) were killed in separate IRA bomb attacks in Cappagh and Derry City.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*15 January 1973: an off-duty UDR soldier (David Bingham, aged 22) was kidnapped while driving his car along Grosvenor Road, Belfast, and shot dead by the IRA. His body was found the next day, 16 January, in an abandoned car on Institution Place, off Durham Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*18 January 1973: an IRA volunteer (Francis Liggett, aged 25) was shot dead by the British Army during an attempted robbery in the grounds of the Royal Victoria Hospital in Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*25 January 1973: William Staunton, a resident magistrate, aged 46, died of his injuries three months after being shot on 11 October 1972 outside St Dominic's School, Falls Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*26 January 1973: a UDR landrover was hit by an IRA grenade and gunfire near Whitecross, County Armagh. Three soldiers were hurt. Another soldier was badly wounded by a sniper while patrolling in Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref&gt;''Beaver County Times'', 27 January 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 January 1973: a UDA member, Francis Smith (aged 28), was kidnapped and shot dead by the IRA near Rodney Parade, Belfast, allegedly in response to the killing by loyalists of a 15-year-old Catholic boy (Peter Watterson), the previous day.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*1 February 1973: a British soldier (William Boardley, aged 30) was shot dead in an IRA sniper attack while he was manning a Vehicle Check Point (VCP), Meeting House Street, Strabane, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*2 February 1973: James Greer (aged 21), a Protestant civilian, was shot at his workplace, a paint store, off Springfield Road, Belfast. Reason remains unknown. The body of Patrick Brady, a member of the Catholic Ex-Servicemen's Association, was found the same day in an  abandoned car, Maurice Street, off Springfield Road, Belfast.&lt;ref&gt;[http://alphahistory.com/northernireland/political-violence-troubles-1972-73/#sthash.TIMFR3cp.dpuf NI Troubles], alphahistory.com; accessed 12 October 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*2 February 1973: a UDA member (Robert Burns, aged 18), was killed in an IRA drive-by gun attack on the Oldpark Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*4 February 1973: an IRA volunteer (Anthony Campbell, aged 19), along with three civilians (Ambrose Hardy (26), Brendan Maguire (33), and John Loughran (35)), were shot dead by British Army snipers in New Lodge, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*6 February 1973: a British soldier (Michael Murtagh, aged 22) was killed in an IRA rocket attack on an Armoured Personnel Carrier, Servia Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*7 February 1973: a UDA member (Glenn Clarke, aged 18) was kidnapped by the IRA and later found shot dead off Hallidays Road, New Lodge, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*8 February 1973: an RUC officer (Charles Morrison, aged 26) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while sitting in stationary patrol car, Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*10 February 1973: two IRA volunteers, Leonard O'Hanlon (aged 23) and Vivienne Fitzsimmons (aged 17), were killed when a bomb they were assembling exploded prematurely in the grounds of Castleward National Trust Estate, near [[Strangford]], County Down.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*14 February 1973: a British soldier (Edwin Weston, aged 20) was shot dead by an IRA while patrolling the Divis Flats complex, West Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*20 February 1973: two British soldiers, Malcolm Shaw (aged 23) and Robert Pearson (aged 19), were shot dead when their mobile-patrol was ambushed by IRA snipers in Cupar Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*21 February 1973: a British soldier (Michael Doyle, aged 20) was killed in an IRA gun attack on Fort Pegasus British Army base, Whiterock, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*25 February 1973: a child, Gordon Gallagher (aged 9), was killed after he accidentally triggered an IRA booby trap bomb which had been planted at the rear of his home, Leenan Gardens, Creggan, Derry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*27 February 1973: two RUC officers, Raymond Wylie (aged 25) and Ronald Macauley (42) were shot dead while on mobile patrol during an IRA sniper attack, Aghagallon, near Moira, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*28 February 1973: a British soldier (Alan Kennington, aged 20) was killed in an IRA gun attack while on foot-patrol, Crumlin Road, [[Ardoyne]], Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*3 March 1973: an off-duty UDR soldier (David Deacon, aged 39) was shot dead by the IRA in Mullennan, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*4 March 1973: a British soldier (Gary Barlow, aged 19) was tortured and later shot dead after being abducted by the IRA while his Army unit was raiding homes on Albert Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*6 March 1973: a British soldier (Anton Brown, aged 22) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while patrolling Whitecliff Crescent, Ballymurphy, Belfast. Another British soldier (Joseph Leahy, aged 31) was wounded by an IRA booby-trap bomb planted in a derelict house in Mullaghbawn, near [[Forkill]], County Armagh. He died two days later, on 8 March 1973.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*8 March 1973: the Provisional IRA conducted its first operation in England, planting four car bombs in London. Two bombs exploded, killing one person and injuring 265 others. Ten members of the IRA team, including [[Gerry Kelly]] and sisters [[Dolours Price|Dolours]] and [[Marian Price]], were arrested at [[Heathrow Airport]] trying to leave the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The IRA campaigns in England|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/1201738.stm|publisher=BBC|date=4 March 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=g236&gt;{{cite book|last=McGladdery|first=Gary|title=The Provisional IRA in England|publisher=Irish Academic Press|year=2006|isbn=0-7165-3373-1|page=236}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 March 1973: a British soldier (John Green, aged 21) was shot dead by the IRA while guarding a polling station, Slate Street School, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Northern Ireland - The Troubles'' by Charles Messenger (ISBN 0-86124-236-X), p. 102.&lt;!--publisher needed--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 March 1973: a British soldier (John King, aged 22) was killed by an IRA booby trap bomb while on foot-patrol, Coolderry, near Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*16 March 1973: an off-duty UDR soldier driving his car (William Kenny, aged 28) was kidnapped by the IRA at Halliday's Road, New Lodge, Belfast. Found shot dead a short time later in entry off Edlingham Street, New Lodge.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*17 March 1973: a British soldier (Michael Gay, aged 21) was killed in an IRA landmine attack on his armoured patrol, Parkanaur, near [[Dungannon]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*23 March 1973: three British soldiers, Barrington Foster (aged 28), Michael Muldoon (aged 25), and Thomas Penrose (aged 28), were shot dead by the IRA in a house on Antrim Road, Belfast, to which the soldiers had been lured.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*26 March 1973: the IRA fired four rockets at British and RUC targets. One was fired at a British ''Saracen'' APC near the border, one at an RUC landrover near the border and another at a British patrol in Belfast.&lt;ref&gt;''Bangor Daily News'', 27 March 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 March 1973: a British soldier (Andrew Somerville, aged 20) was killed in an IRA landmine attack on a British mobile patrol in Ballymacilroy, near [[Ballygawley, County Tyrone]].&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*27 March 1973: Patrick McCabe (aged 16), a member of the [[Irish Republican Army Youth Section]], was shot dead by a British Army sniper while walking along Etna Drive, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*29 March 1973: a British soldier (Michael Marr, aged 33) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol in Andersonstown, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*7 April 1973: two British soldiers, Terence Brown (aged 26) and Steven Harrison (aged 26), were killed in an IRA landmine attack on a British armoured mobile patrol, Tullyogallaghan, near [[Newtownhamilton|Newtownhamilton, County Armagh]].&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*9 April 1973: a British soldier (Charles Marchant, aged 18) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol, North Street, [[Lurgan]], County Armagh. He had previously been injured on 26 January 1973, also in Lurgan.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*11 April 1973: a British soldier (Keith Evans, aged 20) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol on Westland Street, [[the Bogside|Bogside, Derry]].&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*12 April 1973: an IRA volunteer (Edward O'Rawe, aged 27) was shot dead by the British Army at the rear of a house on Cape Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*17 April 1973: an IRA volunteer (Brian Smyth, aged 32) was shot dead by a British Army sniper while standing with group of men, Etna Drive, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*20 April 1973: a British soldier was shot by an IRA sniper in New Lodge, Belfast, but survived. A British post was hit by a rocket and then raked with gunfire in Ballymurphy, Belfast. There were no other casualties.&lt;ref&gt;''Spokane Daily Chronicle'', 21 April 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*28 April 1973: a British soldier (Kerry Venn, aged 23) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol, Carn Hill, [[Shantallow]], Derry City.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*29 April 1973: a British soldier, Graham Cox (aged 19), was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on mobile-patrol, New Lodge Road, New Lodge, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*3 May 1973: a British soldier, Thomas Crump (aged 27), died one day after being shot by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol at the junction of Foyle Road and Bishop Street, Derry City.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*5 May 1973: three British soldiers (John Gibbons, William Vines, and Terence Williams) were killed by a booby trap landmine attack on their foot patrol, Moybane, near [[Crossmaglen]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*10 May 1973: an off-duty UDR soldier, [http://www.nivetsannex.com/ROH/certs/M0170.pdf Franklin Caddoo] (aged 24), was shot dead by the IRA at his farm, Rehaghy, near [[Aughnacloy, County Tyrone]].&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*10 May 1973: an IRA volunteer, Anthony Ahern, a native of [[County Cork]], was killed when a landmine he was preparing at Mullanahinch, near [[Rosslea]], County Fermanagh, exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*13 May 1973: two British soldiers, Thomas Taylor (aged 26) and John Gaskell (aged 22), were killed when the IRA detonated a remote-controlled bomb as their foot patrol passed by a disused factory on the Donegall Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*13 May 1973: in County Tyrone, an IRA volunteer, Kevin Kilpatrick (aged 21), was shot dead when he attempted to smash his car through a UDR Vehicle Check Point (VCP), The Diamond, near [[Coagh|Coagh, County Tyrone]].&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*14 May 1973: a civilian, Roy Rutherford (aged 33), was killed after triggering an IRA booby-trap bomb, intended for the security forces; the bomb had been hidden in a derelict cottage on Moy Road, Portadown, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*17 May 1973: four off-duty British Army soldiers (Barry Cox, Arthur Place, Derek Reed, and Sheridan Young) were killed by a booby trap bomb while getting into a car outside the Knock-na-Moe Castle Hotel, [[Omagh, County Tyrone]]; a fifth soldier (Frederick Drake) died of his injuries on 3 June.&lt;ref name=c73&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1973|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/othelem/chron/ch73.htm|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 May 1973: an IRA volunteer (Sean McKee, aged 17) was shot dead by the British Army while carrying out a sniper attack on a British patrol on Fairfield Street, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*24 May 1973: two British soldiers, John Wallace (aged 32) and Ian Donald (aged 35), were killed in an IRA remote-controlled bomb attack as they searched houses in [[Cullaville]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*26 May 1973: Paul Crummey, aged 4, was killed during an IRA sniper attack on a British Army foot patrol on Finaghy Road North, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*5 June 1973: the IRA shot dead a patrolling RUC officer (David Purvis, aged 22) on Belmore Street, [[Enniskillen]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*5 June 1973: a civilian, Terence Herdman (aged 17) was found shot dead near [[Clogher]], County Tyrone. The IRA claimed he was an informer.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*12 June 1973: six Protestant civilians (Francis and Dinah Campbell, Elizabeth Craigmile, Nan Davis, Robert Scott and Elizabeth Palmer) were killed by an IRA car bomb on Railway Road in [[Coleraine]], County Londonderry; the warning given by the IRA had been inadequate.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*21 June 1973: a British soldier (Barry Gritten, aged 29) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb in an empty building on Lecky Road, [[Bogside]], Derry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*21 June 1973: a British soldier (David Smith, aged 31) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb in an empty building in Strabane.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*25 June 1973: three IRA volunteers were killed when the bomb they were transporting exploded prematurely in their car on Gortin Road near [[Omagh]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*26 June 1973: the IRA shot dead a civilian (Noorbaz Khan, aged 45) who worked for the British Army as he left Bligh's Lane British Army Base, Derry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*1 July 1973: an IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (Reginald Roberts, aged 25) at Bull Ring, Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*4 July 1973: a British base in Derry was hit by two rockets and raked with gunfire. Another rocket exploded against the fence of a British base in Belfast, hurting two people. Two British patrols were ambushed elsewhere in Belfast and two people injured in the crossfire.&lt;ref&gt;''Ellensburg Daily Record'', 5 July 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Press Courier'', 5 July 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 July 1973: the IRA shot dead a former UDR soldier (Isaac Scott, aged 41) outside Tully's Bar, [[Belleek, County Armagh|Belleek]], near [[Newtownhamilton]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*11 July 1973: a rocket was fired at a British post guarding a gasworks in Derry. It hit an anti-rocket screen but there were no casualties. The IRA claimed responsibility.&lt;ref&gt;''The News and Courier'', 12 July 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 July 1973: two British soldiers, Christopher Brady (aged 21) and Geoffrey Breakwell (aged 20), were killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb in an electricity junction box at Divis Flats, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*18 July 1973: a patrolling British soldier (Brian Criddle, aged 34) was wounded by an IRA landmine near Clogher, County Tyrone. He died four days later, on 22 July 1973.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*20 July 1973: a patrolling British soldier (Richard Jarman, aged 37) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb in [[Middletown, County Armagh]].&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*20 July 1973: the IRA shot dead an off-duty UDR soldier (Sidney Watt, aged 36) outside his home in Ballintemple, near Meigh, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*21 July 1973: two IRA volunteers were killed when the bomb they were transporting exploded prematurely in their car in Newcastle, County Down.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*3 August 1973: IRA members, carrying out an armed robbery, shot dead a civilian, James Farrell (aged 50), who was delivering wages to the British Leyland factory on Cashel Road, [[Dublin]].&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*11 August 1973: an IRA volunteer died when the bomb he was transporting exploded prematurely in a car at Kilclean, County Donegal.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*11 August 1973: an IRA assault team consisting of over 20 volunteers surrounded Crossmaglen RUC barracks. The barracks was hit with rockets, mortars and machine gun fire. The RUC fired a large number of shots at the unit. There were no serious injuries on either side.&lt;ref&gt;Messenger, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 August 1973: the IRA shot dead an off-duty RUC reservist (William McIlveen, aged 36) at his workplace, a factory on Cathedral Road, Armagh town.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*16 August 1973: two IRA volunteers, Daniel McAnallen (aged 27) and Patrick Quinn (aged 18), were killed when a mortar prematurely exploded during an attack on Pomeroy British Army/RUC base, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*18 August 1973: a Protestant civilian (Trevor Holland, aged 36) was shot dead by the IRA from a passing car while he was standing outside a cafe on West Street, Edgarstown, [[Portadown]].{{Why|date=November 2016}}&lt;!-- any reason? --&gt;&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*18 August 1973: two IRA firebombs exploded at Harrods Department store in London causing slight damage.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*20 August 1973: book bombs were sent to a number of places in London including the Old Bailey and the Union Jack Club. Ten incendiary devices were also defused in London's West End.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*22 August 1973: an IRA book bomb exploded at the Conservative Party Central Office in London.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*23 August 1973: the IRA shot dead a Protestant civilian (Margaret Meeke, aged 52) as she drove her car at Tullyvallan, near [[Newtownhamilton]], County Armagh; the sniper mistook her car for that of a UDR soldier.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*24 August 1973: a civilian (Patrick Duffy, aged 37) was found shot dead in a car on Buncrana Road, Derry. The IRA said he had been shot for being an informer.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*24 August 1973: one person was injured when an IRA letterbomb exploded at the London Stock Exchange.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*25 August 1973: one person was maimed when an IRA letterbomb exploded at the [[Bank of England]] in London. An IRA bomb was also defused in Oxford Street.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*25 August 1973: the IRA shot an undercover British soldier (Richard Miller, aged 21) outside Royal Victoria Hospital, Falls Road, Belfast. He died on 18 September 1973.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*27 August 1973: the IRA destroyed The Royal Bastion monument to British Governor Walker in Derry with a large bomb.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goireland.com/derry/governor-george-walker-memorial-attraction-monuments-id14646.htm|title=Governor George Walker Memorial Derry. Find and Reserve your Monuments in Derry, Ireland|publisher=Goireland.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*28 August 1973: the IRA shot dead a UDR soldier (Kenneth Hill, aged 25) in the Culdee section of Armagh town while evacuating the area during a bomb alert.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*29 August 1973: two IRA bombs exploded in [[Solihull]] Shopping Centre in England. A building society was extensively damaged.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*30 August 1973: a British Army officer (Ronald Beckett, aged 36) was killed while trying to defuse an IRA bomb at Tullyhommon Post Office, Tullyhommon, near Pettigoe, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*30 August 1973: two IRA volunteers, Francis Hall (aged 29) and Anne Marie Petticrew (or Pettigrew; aged 19), were fatally wounded in a premature explosion in a house on Elaine Street, [[Stranmillis]], Belfast. Hall died on 30 August and Petticrew (or Pettigrew) died on 1 September.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*31 August 1973: one IRA volunteer (Patrick Mulvenna, aged 19) was killed and another fatally wounded in a shootout with the British Army, Ballymurphy Road, [[Ballymurphy, Belfast]]. The other IRA volunteer (James Bryson, aged 25) died on 22 September 1973.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*5 September 1973: a Catholic civilian (Patrick Duffy, aged 21) was killed when he triggered a booby-trap bomb by driving his tractor into a field at a farm at Greaghnagleragh, near [[Belcoo]], County Fermanagh. It is believed it was planted by the IRA and intended for the security forces. The RUC had just removed a dummy bomb at the scene.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 390&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 September 1973: the IRA shot dead an off-duty UDR soldier (Matthew Lilley, aged 54) near [[Belcoo]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*8 September 1973: an IRA bomb exploded at the ticket office in Victoria Station, London, injuring five people.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*10 September 1973: the IRA detonated bombs at two train stations in London; 13 people were injured.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*12 September 1973: two police officers were injured when an IRA bomb exploded at the offices of the Royal Naval Association in London. A woman collapsed and died during an evacuation following a hoax bomb alert at Euston Station, London.&lt;ref name=g236/&gt;
*17 September 1973: a British Army bomb disposal expert (Ronald Wilkinson, aged 30) was wounded attempting to defuse an IRA bomb which had been planted in [[Birmingham]], England; he died on 23 September 1973. Another IRA bomb was discovered at a Household Cavalry camp in [[Surrey]].&lt;ref name=g237&gt;McGladdery p. 237&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 September 1973: five people were injured when an IRA bomb exploded at the headquarters of the [[Prince Andrew, Duke of York|Duke of York]] in London.&lt;ref name=g237/&gt;
*22 September 1973: a civilian (James Brown, aged 26) was found shot dead on Foyle Road, Derry; the IRA claimed he was an informer.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*2 October 1973: an IRA incendiary bomb caused extensive damage to a department store in [[Colchester]], [[Essex]]; another IRA firebomb caused damage at [[Heathrow Airport]].&lt;ref name=g237/&gt;
*3 October 1973: a British soldier (Lindsay Dobie, aged 23) was killed by a booby-trap bomb in a parcel left at Bligh's Lane British Army Base, Derry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*3 October 1973: the IRA shot dead a former UDR soldier (Ivan Vennard, aged 32) in Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*4 October 1973: four people were injured when an IRA bomb exploded at a British Army careers office in London.&lt;ref name=g237/&gt;
*12 October 1973: a civilian (Raymond McAdam, aged 24), killed in an IRA bomb attack on shop, Annaghmore, near Newtownbutler, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*16 October 1973: the IRA shot dead a patrolling RUC officer (William Campbell, aged 27), near Capital Cinema, Antrim Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*28 October 1973: an IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (Stephen Hall, aged 27) in Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*28 October 1973: the IRA shot dead an off-duty RUC officer (John Doherty, aged 31, a native of [[County Donegal]]), near his mother's home, [[Lifford]], County Donegal.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*31 October 1973: [[1973 Mountjoy Prison helicopter escape|Mountjoy Prison helicopter escape]]. Three IRA volunteers escaped from [[Mountjoy Prison]], [[Dublin]] after a hijacked helicopter landed in the exercise yard. One of the escapees was former IRA [[List of IRA Chiefs of Staff|Chief of Staff]] [[Seamus Twomey]].&lt;ref name=c73/&gt;
*6 November 1973: an IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (John Aikman, aged 25) in [[Newtownhamilton]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*13 November 1973: a civilian (Bernard Teggart, aged 15) was found shot near Floral Hall, Zoological Gardens, Antrim Road, Belfast. The IRA claimed he was an informer.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*14 November 1973: a civilian (John Lundy, aged 61) was killed during an IRA sniper attack on a British Army observation post on Moira Street, Short Strand, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*14 November 1973: a civilian (Kathleen Feeney, aged 14) was killed during an IRA sniper attack on a British Army patrol on Lecky Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*15 November 1973: the RUC shot dead an IRA volunteer (Michael McVerry, aged 23) during gun attack on Keady British Army (BA)/Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) base, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*24 November 1973: a patrolling British soldier (David Roberts, aged 25) was killed by an IRA landmine near Carlingford Street, Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*24 November 1973: the British Army shot dead a Fianna (IRA Youth Section) volunteer (Michael Marley, aged 17) during a bomb attack on a British Army patrol at Divis Flats, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*25 November 1973: the IRA shot dead two patrolling British soldiers (Joseph Brooks, aged 20, and Heinz Pisarek, aged 30), at Rossville Flats, Bogside, Derry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; Six rockets and heavy gunfire hit Belleek RUC base, County Fermanagh. The attack came from across the border.&lt;ref&gt;''The Pittsburgh Press'', 26 November 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 November 1973: the IRA shot dead a civilian (Anthony Braden, aged 58) who was driving his car along Jamaica Street, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; 
*27 November 1973: the British Army shot dead an IRA volunteer (Desmond Morgan, aged 18) as he tried to hijack a car in Coalisland, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*1 December 1973: an IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling RUC officer (Robert Megaw, aged 29) on Edward Street, Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*3 December 1973: the British Army shot dead an IRA volunteer (Joseph Walker, aged 18), who was part of a unit attempting to ambush a British patrol at The Rath, Central Drive, Creggan, Derry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*10 December 1973: an IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (James Hesketh, aged 21) on Leeson Street, Lower Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*11 December 1973: an off-duty RUC officer (Maurice Rolston, aged 37) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb attached to his car at his home in Newcastle, County Down.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt; Another under-car bomb blew-off an unidentified RUC officer's leg in [[Downpatrick]], County Down. Belcoo RUC base in County Fermanagh was attacked with rockets and machine-guns, wounding one officer.&lt;ref&gt;''Beaver County Times'', 12 December 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 December 1973: the IRA shot dead a former RUC officer (Ivan Johnston, aged 34) at Derrynoose near Keady, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*15 December 1973: an IRA volunteer (James McGinn, aged 20) died when the bomb he was carrying exploded prematurely as he walked across Clady Bridge on the Tyrone-Donegal border.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*18 December 1973: the IRA carried out a series of attacks in London. In one attack, two police officers were injured in an explosion in Ronan Way. More than fifty were injured (two seriously) when a bomb exploded on Thorney Street (an inaccurate telephone warning was called in), and six others were injured when a bomb exploded at a postal sorting office.&lt;ref name=g237/&gt;
*19 December 1973: one person was injured when an IRA letterbomb exploded at a postal sorting office in London.&lt;ref name=g237/&gt;
*20 December 1973: the IRA accidentally shot dead a civilian (Rodney Fenton, aged 23) on Atlantic Avenue, New Lodge, Belfast; an RUC reservist was the intended target.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*24 December 1973: the IRA left two packages which exploded almost simultaneously in the late evening on Christmas Eve. One was in the doorway of the North Star public house, [[South Hampstead]], which exploded injuring six people, and the other exploded on the upstairs verandah of the nearby Swiss Cottage Tavern, in which an unspecified number of people were injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;g236&quot;/&gt;
*24 December 1973: two IRA volunteers (Edward Grant and Brendan Quinn) died, killing one civilian (Aubrey Harshaw), when their bomb prematurely exploded in Clarke's Bar, Monaghan Street, Newry.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;
*26 December 1973: one person was injured when an IRA bomb exploded at Stage Door public house in London.&lt;ref name=g237/&gt;
*31 December 1973: an IRA sniper shot dead a British soldier (Alan Daughtery, aged 23) traveling in an APC on Beechmount Avenue, Falls, Belfast.&lt;ref name=d73/&gt;

==1974==
*1 January 1974: A Catholic civilian (John Whyte, aged 24) was shot dead during an IRA sniper attack on a British Army patrol on McClure Street, off Ormeau Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*17 January 1974: The IRA shot dead an off-duty UDR soldier (Robert Jameson, aged 22) near his home at [[Trillick]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*20 January 1974: A UDR soldier (Cormac McCabe, aged 42) was shot dead by the IRA; his body was found in a field near [[Aughnacloy, County Tyrone|Aughnacloy]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*21 January 1974: A British soldier (John Haughey, aged 32) was killed by an IRA remote-controlled bomb hidden in an electricity distribution box on Lone Moor Road, Creggan, Derry. It was detonated when a British foot-patrol passed.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*23 January 1974: An IRA unit which included [[Rose Dugdale]] and Eddie Gallagher hijacked a helicopter and used it to drop bombs on Strabane RUC station. One of the bombs landed on the grounds of the station, but failed to explode.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Messenger|first=Charles|title=Northern Ireland: The Troubles|publisher=[[Bison Books]]|year=1985|isbn=0-86124-236-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 January 1974: A British soldier (Howard Fawley, aged 19) was killed by an IRA landmine as he and his patrol searched a field at Ballymaguigan, near Ballyronan, County Londonderry. 
*26 January 1974: The IRA shot dead a patrolling RUC officer (John Rodgers, aged 50) on Antrim Road, [[Glengormley]], County Antrim.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*29 January 1974: An IRA sniper fired at a bus carrying [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) personnel at Shimna Parade, [[Newcastle, County Down]]. The RAF personnel returned fire, killing an elderly civilian, Matilda Withrington (aged 79).&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*29 January 1974: The IRA shot dead a patrolling RUC officer (William Baggley, aged 43) on Dungiven Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*4 February 1974: Eleven people were killed in the [[M62 Coach Bombing]], when a bomb exploded on a coach as it was travelling along the [[M62 motorway]] at [[Birkenshaw, West Yorkshire|Birkenshaw]]. The dead included eight soldiers, and the wife and two young children of one of the soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=1974: Soldiers and children killed in coach bombing|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/4/newsid_4148000/4148933.stm|publisher=BBC|date=4 February 1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 February 1974: A British soldier (Allan Brammagh, aged 31) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb hidden in a parcel which was left at the side of the road, while on foot-patrol at Moybane, near Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*23 February 1974: A large gun battle between the IRA and the British army occurred near Strabane, County Tyrone. The engagement also involved mortar rounds fired by the IRA. Some 25 [[Irish Travellers|traveller caravans]] were trapped between the warring factions; one caravan was destroyed by a mortar bomb.&lt;ref&gt;[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F00F10F83458147B93C1AB1789D85F408785F9 &quot;I.R.A. and Soldiers Fight Fierce Gun Battle at Border&quot;], ''[[New York Times]]'', 23 February 1974&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 February 1974: A civilian (Patrick Lynch, aged 23) was found shot dead at Rathlin Drive, Derry. He was killed by the IRA as an alleged informer.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*2 March 1974: The IRA shot dead a patrolling RUC officer (Thomas McClinton, aged 28) on Donegall Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*3 March 1974: An IRA landmine exploded and killed a UDR soldier (Robert Moffett, aged 30) at Dunnamore, near Cookstown, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*10 March 1974: Two civilians, Michael McCreesh (aged 15) and Michael Gallagher (aged 18), were killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb hidden in an abandoned car at [[Dromintee]], near [[Forkill]], County Armagh. It was meant for a British foot-patrol. Gallagher died on 14 March 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*12 March 1974: A [[Fine Gael]] senator, [[Billy Fox (politician)|Billy Fox]], was kidnapped by the IRA and later found shot dead at Tircooney,  near [[Clones]], County Monaghan.{{Why|date=November 2015}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1974.html|title=CAIN: Sutton Index of Deaths|publisher=Cain.ulst.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 March 1974: The IRA shot dead a British soldier (David Farrington, aged 23) at a pedestrian checkpoint on Chapel Lane, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*15 March 1974: Two IRA volunteers, Patrick McDonald (aged 21) and Kevin Murray (aged 27), were killed when their landmine prematurely exploded on Aughnacloy Road, Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*15 March 1974: A civilian (Adam Johnston, aged 34) was killed by an IRA lorry bomb on Queen Street in Magherafelt, County Londonderry. The warning sent by the IRA had been inadequate.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*16 March 1974: IRA snipers shot dead two patrolling British soldiers, Roy Bedford (aged 22) and Philip James (aged 22), at Moybane, near Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*17 March 1974: An IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling RUC officer (Cyril Wilson, aged 37) in Rathmore, Craigavon, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*17 March 1974: An IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (Michael Ryan, aged 23), on Foyle Road, Brandywell, Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*19 March 1974: An off-duty RUC officer (Frederick Robinson, aged 40), was killed by a booby trap bomb attached to his car outside his home, Glenkeen Avenue, Greenisland, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*21 March 1974: An IRA sniper shot a patrolling British soldier (James Macklin, aged 28), on Antrim Road, Belfast. He died on 28 March.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*23 March 1974: The IRA shot dead a former British soldier from Northern Ireland (Donald Farrell, aged 56), while he was sitting in a stationary car near his home, Mountfield, near Omagh, County Tyrone. He had recently retired.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*26 March 1974: A civilian (Joseph Hughes, aged 25), was killed when an IRA car bomb exploded on Springfield Road, Ballymurphy, Belfast. He had been driving past at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*31 March 1974, a civilian (Sean McAstocker, aged 28), was found shot dead, Lagan Street, Markets, Belfast. CAIN lists PIRA as responsible.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt; 
*1 April 1974: It was reported that &quot;small arms fire, mortar bombs and possibly rockets were used&quot; in an attack on a British base in Derry. Two British soldiers were injured.&lt;ref&gt;''The Palm Beach Post'', 2 April 1974.&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 April 1974: The IRA shot dead John Stevenson, a Commanding Officer of the [[British Army]], at his home near Otterburn British Army base, [[Northumberland]], England.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*10 April 1974: The IRA shot dead a former UDR soldier (George Saunderson, aged 58), at his workplace, Derrylin Primary School, [[Derrylin]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*11 April 1974: A patrolling British soldier (Norman McKenzie, aged 25) was killed by an IRA land mine attack while on mobile patrol, Mullynaburtlan, near Lisnaskea, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*11 April 1974: A patrolling UDR soldier (David Sinnamon, aged 34), was killed by a remote controlled bomb, hidden in a derelict house which detonated when an Ulster Defence Regiment foot patrol passed by, Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*14 April 1974: The IRA shot dead an undercover British soldier (Anthony Pollen, aged 27), observing a republican commemoration parade at Meenan Square, Bogside, Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*16 April 1974: An IRA sniper shot dead an RUC officer (Thomas McCall, aged 34), outside Newtownhamilton RUC base, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*18 April 1974: A civilian (Seamus O'Neill, aged 32), was killed when he triggered a booby-trap bomb on his farm, The Loup, near Moneymore, County Londonderry. It exploded about 8&amp;nbsp;ft from his tractor as he drove past Saltersland church hall. There had been a small explosion there earlier in the day. It is believed both bombs were planted by the IRA and that the second bomb was for security forces investigating the first.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 440&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 April 1974: A civilian (James Corbett, aged 20), was shot dead by the IRA as an alleged informer. His body was found by the side of Upper Springfield Road, Hannahstown, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*22 April 1974: A civilian (Mohammed Khalid, aged 18), who worked for the British Army was shot dead by the IRA in his car at Silverbridge, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*1 May 1974: A British outpost came under IRA attack at Crossmaglen, County Armagh. It was hit by three rockets and a 15-minute gun-battle followed. No injuries were reported.&lt;ref&gt;''Rome News-Tribune'', 2 May 1974.&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 May 1974: Up to 40 members from the [[Provisional IRA East Tyrone Brigade]] attacked the isolated 6 UDR Deanery base in [[Clogher]], [[County Tyrone]] with machine gun and RPG fire resulting the death of Private Eva Martin, a UDR Greenfinch, the first female UDR soldier to be killed by enemy action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The lying: a former terrorist describes his life in the IRA, and looks at the current peace negotiations through the prism of what he learned in his old life|author=Sean O'Callaghan|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1282/is_n1_v49/ai_19071766/pg_3|publisher=National Review|date=27 January 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 May 1974: The IRA shot dead two patrolling RUC officers, Brian Bell (aged 29) and John Ross (aged 40), on Finaghy Road North, Finaghy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*13 May 1974: Two IRA volunteers, Eugene Martin (aged 18) and Sean McKearney (aged 19), were killed when their bomb prematurely exploded at a petrol filling station, Donnydeade, near Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*31 May 1974: A former Royal Navy serviceman, Alfred Shotter (aged 54), was killed by an IRA booby trap bomb hidden in a dustbin at his former home, Strabane Old Road, Gobnascale, Derry. It is believed to have been planted by the IRA.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 456&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt; 
*5 June 1974: An IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (Frederick Dicks, aged 21) on Irish Street, Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*17 June 1974: A bomb exploded at the [[Houses of Parliament]] in London, causing extensive damage and injuring 11 people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=1974: IRA bombs parliament|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/june/17/newsid_2514000/2514827.stm|publisher=BBC|date=17 June 1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 June 1974: A patrolling RUC officer (John Forsythe, aged 30) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb in an entry off Market Street, Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*22 June 1974: An RUC officer (Daniel O'Connor, aged 35) was shot dead from a passing car driven by IRA volunteers while on Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) foot patrol, at the junction of Crumlin Road and Clifton Park Avenue, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*22 June 1974: An IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (Kim Ian McCunn, aged 18), New Lodge Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*24 June 1974: Two IRA volunteers, Gerard Craig (aged 17) and David Russell (aged 18), died when the bomb they were planting at a supermarket, Greenhaw Road, Shantallow, Derry, exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*29 June 1974: An IRA sniper shot a patrolling British soldier (David Smith, aged 26) on Whiterock Road, Ballymurphy, Belfast. He died on 4 July.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*2 July 1974: A patrolling British soldier (John Walton, aged 27) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb in a derelict house, Carrickgallogly, near Belleek, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*12 July 1974: The IRA shot dead a UDA member (John Beattie, aged 17) while he was standing on the corner of Glenrosa and Moyola streets, Tiger's Bay, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*17 July 1974: The IRA bombed the White Tower, [[Tower of London]]; one English civilian (Dorothy Household, aged 48) was killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*20 July 1974: A former British soldier (Brian Shaw, aged 21) was found shot dead in a derelict house on Arundel Street, off Grosvenor Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*23 July 1974: A UDR soldier (John Conley, aged 43) was killed when a car bomb exploded while he was helping to evacuating civilians from the area, at Bridge Street, Garvagh, County Londonderry. Inadequate warning given.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*30 July 1974: The IRA devastated the commercial centre of Bangor, County Down, in an overnight firebomb attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheehy 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Sheehy|first=Kevin B.|title=More Questions Than Answers: Reflections on a life in the RUC|publisher=G&amp;M|date=September 2008|isbn=978-0-7171-4396-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 July 1974: An IRA sniper shot dead a patrolling British soldier (Bernard Fearns, aged 34), on Hillman Street, New Lodge, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*3 August 1974: A Protestant civilian (Charles McKnight, aged 25) was killed by a booby trap bomb when he entered the cab of his employer's lorry, parked outside house, Ballycraigy, Newtownabbey, County Antrim. CAIN cites IRA as responsible. Reason unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*13 August 1974: Two [[Royal Marines]], Dennis Leach (aged 24) and Michael Southern (aged 19), were killed when the IRA detonated a remote-controlled bomb in their observation post at Drummuckavall, near Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*23 August 1974: The IRA shot dead an undercover RUC officer (Peter Flanagan, aged 47) inside the Diamond Bar, George Street, Omagh, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*23 August 1974: The IRA shot dead a former UDR soldier (William Hutchinson, aged 29), while engaged in traffic census, Cabragh, near Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*26 August 1974: A patrolling British soldier (Philip Drake, aged 20) was killed by an IRA sniper in Drumbeg, Craigavon, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*27 August 1974: An IRA volunteer (Patrick McKeown, aged 29) died when his bomb prematurely exploded in a house in Barcroft Park, Newry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*7 September 1974: A civilian (Mary Bingham, aged 58) was shot dead during an IRA sniper attack on a British foot patrol, Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*8 September 1974: A Catholic man (Arthur Rafferty, aged 56) died three weeks after being shot on Newington Street, New Lodge, Belfast, by the IRA. A piece of cardboard was found nearby that had written on it: &quot;this is the penalty for a sexual assault on a child of seven years old at the Waterworks&quot;. After the shooting a caller rang the ''Irish News'' and said it had been a &quot;punishment shooting&quot; carried out by the IRA.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 474&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 September 1974: The IRA shot dead [[Martin McBirney]], a resident magistrate (aged 55), at his home on Belmont Road, East Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt; His sister-in-law, Frances Cooke, suffered a fatal heart attack upon hearing the news.&lt;ref&gt;Susan McKay, ''Bear in Mind These Dead'', p. 206&lt;!--publishing info, ISSN/ISBN needed--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 September 1974: The IRA shot dead Rory Conaghan (aged 54), a judge, at his home, Beechlands, off Malone Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*22 September 1974: The IRA shot dead a former prison officer (William McCully, aged 58) at his home, Hillmount Gardens, Finaghy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*29 September 1974: Twenty-three mortar bombs were launched by the IRA at a British Army facility in Crossmaglen. The facility was also hit by automatic fire. The attack was to be combined with an air strike that was eventually called off.&lt;ref name=IRAAF/&gt;
*29 September 1974: An aerial bombing was attempted on the British Army base at Crossmaglen by two IRA members who hijacked a three-seat [[Cessna]] plane from a flying club at [[Dundalk]], while another two IRA men remained on the ground to prevent club members from raising the alarm. The IRA unit loaded the aircraft with four cylinder bombs and forced the pilot to fly over the border. The attack failed after the hijackers became lost, and one of them launched a bomb five miles away from the intended target before flying back to the Republic. The dropping of the bomb was witnessed by British soldiers manning a border outpost. The Cessna eventually made a safe landing in a field near Ravensdale, [[County Louth]]. The strike was intended to support the mortar attack on the same compound.&lt;ref name=IRAAF&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=JZtlAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=PYsNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3176,4801570&amp;hl=en &quot;IRA guerrillas flop again in bombing raid on Ulster&quot;], Associated Press, 30 September 1974.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=EoY0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=7qEFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=902,4390884&amp;dq=plane+hijacked+ira&amp;hl=en &quot;Plane hijacked in Ireland, but bombing attempt fails&quot;], Reuters, 30 September 1974.&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 October 1974: A civilian (Asha Chopra, aged 25) was killed during an IRA sniper attack on an RUC patrol at Greenhaw Road, Shantallow, Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*5 October 1974: [[Guildford pub bombing]] - four British soldiers and a civilian were killed and 182 were hurt when the IRA bombed a pub frequented by off-duty soldiers. Four people, dubbed the &quot;[[Guildford Four]]&quot;, would be convicted for the bombing and imprisoned for life. Fifteen years later Lord Lane of the Court of Appeal would overturn their convictions noting &quot;the investigating officers must have lied&quot;. Some of the Four had spent the entire 15 years in prison.
*8 October 1974: An RUC officer (Arthur Henderson, aged 31) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb in an abandoned car, West Street, Stewartstown, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*21 October 1974: The IRA kidnapped and shot dead an off-duty British Territorial Army soldier (Malcolm Gibson, aged 28) in Belfast. He was found shot dead in a derelict house, shortly after being abducted while driving a laundry van, Velsheda Park, Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*23 October 1974: A British soldier (Michael Simpson, aged 21) died three weeks after being shot by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol on Racecourse Road, Shantallow, Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*28 October 1974: The IRA detonated a van bomb outside the British Army base at Ballykinlar, County Down, killing two British soldiers, Alan Coughlan (aged 22) and Michael Swanick (aged 20).&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*30 October 1974: An IRA volunteer (Michael Meenan, aged 16) died when his bomb prematurely exploded at a garage on Strand Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*30 October 1974: a civilian (Gordon Catherwood, aged 44), shot dead by an IRA sniper aiming at the victim's son, a UDR soldier, Upper Hightown Road, near Belfast, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt; &lt;!-- reason?? --&gt;
*6 November 1974: An IRA sniper shot dead two patrolling British soldiers, Brian Allen (aged 20) and Stephen Windsor (aged 26), while on foot patrol, Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*6 November 1974: An IRA volunteer,  Hugh Coney (aged 24), was shot dead by the British Army during an escape attempt from Long Kesh Prison, County Down.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;  
*7 November 1974: Two British soldiers, Vernon Rose (aged 30) and Charles Simpson (aged 35) were killed by an IRA booby trap bomb at an electricity sub station at Aghalarg, near [[Stewartstown, County Tyrone]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*7 November 1974: An off-duty British soldier (Richard Dunne, aged 42) and a civilian (Alan Horsley, aged 20), were killed when a bomb was thrown through the window of the [[Kings Arms, Woolwich]], England. Twenty-eight people were injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1974|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1974.html|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 November 1974: An IRA volunteer (Gerard Fennell, aged 28), was shot dead by a British Army sniper from a concealed observation post during the attempted hijacking of a van, Stewartstown Road, Twinbrook, Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt; 
*12 November 1974: Two civilians, Leonard Cross (aged 19) and Hugh Slater (aged 29), who worked for the British Army were found shot dead by the side of Sheriffs Road near Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*14 November 1974: An IRA volunteer, James McDade (aged 28), died after the bomb he was planting outside a telephone exchange in [[Coventry|Coventry, Warwickshire, England]] exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*15 November 1974: A patrolling British soldier (Anthony Simmons, aged 19), was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol, Fountain Street, Strabane, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*16 November 1974: A UDR soldier (Thomas McCready, aged 32) on mobile patrol was killed by an IRA sniper in Newryy, County Down.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*20 November 1974: An RUC officer (Robert Forde, aged 29) was killed by an IRA booby trap bomb hidden under pathway, Rathmore, Craigavon, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*21 November 1974: The [[Birmingham pub bombings]] kill 19 people. The &quot;[[Birmingham Six]]&quot; would be tried for this and convicted. Many years later, their convictions would be quashed and they would be released. The IRA never claimed responsibility.{{cn|date=October 2015}}
*2 December 1974: A British soldier (John Maddocks, aged 32), was killed while on foot patrol by an IRA booby trap bomb hidden in a milk churn in a field, Gortmullan, near Derrylin, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*2 December 1974: An IRA volunteer, Ethel Lynch (aged 22), was wounded when her bomb prematurely exploded in a house on Crawford Square, Derry. She died on 7 December.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*7 December 1974: An IRA volunteer, John McDaid (aged 16), died when his bomb prematurely exploded in a house on Bridge Street, Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*14 December 1974: IRA snipers shot a British Army soldier (Michael Gibson, aged 20) and an RUC officer (David McNeice, aged 19) while on joint foot patrol, Killeavy, near Forkill, County Armagh. Gibson died from his injuries on 30 December 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*17 December 1974: An IRA bomb exploded at Tottenham Court Road, London, killing a passer-by, George Arthur (35).&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*21 December 1974: A bomb was defused in [[Harrods]] department store in [[Knightsbridge]], [[London]]. A second bomb was defused in the King's Arms public house in [[Warminster]], [[Wiltshire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c74&quot;/&gt;
*22 December 1974: The IRA leadership declared a temporary ceasefire, pending talks with British government officials. Shortly before the ceasefire came into effect, the IRA bombed the London home of the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] leader and former [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] [[Edward Heath]]. No one was injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=1974: Heath's home is bombed|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/december/22/newsid_2539000/2539621.stm|publisher=BBC|date=22 December 1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1975==
*10 January 1975: the British Army shot dead an IRA volunteer, [[John Francis Green]] (aged 27), in a shed on a farm in Tullynageer, near [[Castleblaney|Castleblaney, County Monaghan]].&lt;ref name=s75&gt;{{cite web|title=An Index of Deaths from the Conflict in Ireland|author=Malcolm Sutton|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1975.html|publisher=[[CAIN]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 January 1975: IRA volunteer [[Kevin Coen]] was shot dead by the British Army, at Cassidy's Cross near [[Kinawley|Kinawley, County Fermanagh]].&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*21 January 1975: two IRA volunteers, John Kelly (aged 26) and John Stone (aged 23), driving along Victoria Street, Belfast, were killed when the bomb they were transporting exploded prematurely. A series of bomb attacks across Belfast later ensued.&lt;ref name=&quot;c75&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1975|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/othelem/chron/ch75.htm|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 January 1975: a British soldier (Thomas Lea, aged 32) died eight months after being injured in an IRA bomb attack, Colinward Street, off Springfield Road, Belfast. He was wounded on 5 May 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;s75&quot;/&gt;
*31 January 1975: an RUC officer (George Coulter, aged 43) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on mobile patrol on Donaghmore Road, [[Dungannon]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*8 February 1975: a British soldier (William Robson, aged 22) died two days after being shot by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol in the village of Mullan, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*10 February 1975: the IRA leadership declare a truce. The ceasefire was to last officially until 23 January 1976, however it was not respected by all IRA units and violence continued throughout the year.
*11 February 1975: a mailman on relief duty (Christopher Mein, aged 25) was killed on his milk round by the IRA in Galbally, Cappagh, County Tyrone. The regular milkman was apparently the intended target.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*27 February 1975: an off-duty police officer [[Stephen Tibble]] was shot dead as he joined in the chase of a suspect on his motorbike in [[Barons Court]], [[London]]; the suspect had been spotted by a detective coming out of a house discovered to be an IRA bomb factory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=1975: PC murder linked to IRA bomb factory|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/27/newsid_2515000/2515789.stm|publisher=BBC|date=27 February 1975}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 March 1975: an IRA volunteer (Thomas Smith, aged 28), a native of [[Dublin]], was shot dead by the [[Irish Army]] while attempting to escape from [[Portlaoise Prison]], [[County Laois]].&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*24 March 1975: a post office official (William Elliott, aged 51) was shot dead when he arrived at the scene of a robbery at the post office in [[Silverbridge, County Armagh]]. It is alleged that the IRA was responsible and that the gunmen thought Elliott was an RUC officer.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 528&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 April 1975: a UDA member (Samuel Johnston, aged 33) was shot dead as he walked at the junction of Batchelors Walk and Carrickblatter Road, Portadown, County Armagh. Gunmen, thought to be IRA volunteers, pulled-up alongside him in a car and opened fire. Although the ''Sutton Database'' lists him as a civilian, ''Lost Lives'' lists him as a &quot;high-ranking local UDA member&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 537&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 May 1975: a UDA member (Alexander Millar, aged 55) was shot dead by the IRA at his workplace, Ardoyne Bus Depot, Ardoyne Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*10 May 1975: an RUC officer (Paul Gray, aged 20) was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot-patrol, Waterloo Street, Derry.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*18 May 1975: an IRA volunteer (Francis Rice, aged 17) was stabbed to death by the UVF in a lane off Rathfriland Road, [[Castlewellan]], County Down.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*31 May 1975: the IRA kidnapped and shot dead one of their own members (Eamon Molloy, aged 22) from Belfast whom they alleged was an informer. His remains were located and returned to his family by the IRA on 28 May 1999.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*1 June 1975: Margaret Kilfedder (aged 61), a Protestant civilian, was killed in a bomb attack on her home, Garrison, County Fermanagh. House was previously owned by Ulster Defence Regiment (UDR) soldier.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*3 June 1975: the IRA shot a UDR soldier (Alfred Doyle, aged 24) and two civilians, David Thompson (aged 34) and John Presha (aged 30), dead in Thompson's car in Killeen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*4 June 1975: an IRA volunteer (Francis Jordan, aged 21) was shot dead while planting a bomb outside the British Army barracks at Pit Bar, Mill Vale, near [[Bessbrook]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*10 June 1975: a UVF member (Roy Suitters, aged 39) was shot dead by the IRA at his greengrocer's shop, Crumlin Road, near Ligoniel Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*22 June 1975: Thomas Irvine (aged 23), a Protestant civilian was shot dead by the IRA from a passing car while he was standing at Westland Road, Belfast.{{Why|date=November 2016}}&lt;!-- any reason? --&gt;&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*7 July 1975: an RUC officer (Andrew Johnston, aged 26), was killed by an IRA booby trap bomb, attached to a desk at Carrick Primary School, Sloan Street, Lurgan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*12 July 1975: a purported UDA member (James Carberry, aged 20) was found shot dead on Old Templepatrick Road, Ballyutoag, County Antrim. He was a doorman at a UDA club. It is believed the IRA was responsible. Although the ''Sutton Database'' lists him as a civilian, ''Lost Lives'' lists him as UDA member.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 552&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 July 1975: the IRA killed four British soldiers (Calvert Brown, Edward Garside, Robert McCarter, and Peter Willis) in a remote controlled bomb attack near Forkill, County Armagh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harnden|first=Toby|authorlink=Toby Harnden|title=Bandit Country|publisher=[[Hodder &amp; Stoughton]]|year=1999|pages=476–77|isbn=0-340-71736-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 August 1975: the IRA shot dead a former UDR soldier (George McCall, aged 22), while he was walking near his home, Moy, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*13 August 1975: four Protestant civilians and a member of the UVF were killed in a gun and bomb attack on the Bayardo Bar in Belfast.&lt;ref name=&quot;c75&quot;/&gt;
*13 August 1975: the IRA kidnapped and shot dead a former RUC officer in County Armagh; his body was found near Newtownhamilton on 15 August 1975.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*15 August 1975: the IRA shot dead a Protestant civilian (Norman Kerr, aged 28), a disc jockey packing up his equipment at the Camrick Bar, Market Street, Armagh town. The IRA claimed they killed Kerr due to his alleged association with Captain [[Robert Nairac]] and claimed it was in possession of his diary, which had been stolen in Portadown.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 563&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 August 1975: a bomb exploded without warning at the Caterham Arms public house in [[Caterham]], [[Surrey]], England; ten off-duty British soldiers and 23 civilians were injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;c75&quot;/&gt;
*28 August 1975: seven people were injured when a bomb exploded in [[Oxford Street]], [[London]]; a telephone warning was issued to ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]'' newspaper five minutes before the explosion.&lt;ref name=&quot;c4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Year London Blew Up: August to November 1975|url=http://www.channel4.com/history/microsites/H/history/t-z/year04.html|publisher=[[Channel 4]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*29 August 1975: a British Army bomb-disposal expert (Roger Goad, aged 40) attached to the police was killed attempting to defuse an IRA bomb which had been left in a shoe shop on Church Street, Kensington, London.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://mp.channel4.com/history/microsites/H/history/t-z/year04.html The Year London Blew Up, Channel 4]{{dead link|date=November 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 August 1975: the IRA shot dead an off-duty UDR soldier (Robert Frazer, aged 50) while he was driving away from a friend's farm, Ballymoyer, near Whitecross, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*31 August 1975: the IRA shot dead an off-duty UDR soldier (Joseph Reid, aged 46) at his farm, Farnaloy, near Keady, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*5 September 1975: two people (Robert Lloyd and Grace Loohuis) were killed and 63 injured when an IRA bomb exploded in the lobby of the Hilton hotel in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=London Hilton bombed|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/september/5/newsid_2499000/2499203.stm|publisher=BBC|date=5 September 1975}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 September 1975: a UDA member (Andrew Craig, aged 20) was shot dead by the IRA at the corner of Alfred and Russell streetsd,  Markets, South Belfast.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*6 October 1975: an RUC officer (David Love, aged 45), was killed in an IRA bomb attack at Roeview Inn, near [[Limavady]], County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*6 October 1975: a civilian (Alice McGuinness, aged 57) was killed three days after sustaining critical injuries in an IRA bomb attack on [[John McKeague]]'s hardware shop on the Albertbridge Road, Belfast. John McKeague's sister was severely injured in the same bombing.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*9 October 1975: a British soldier on patrol (Edward Gleeson, aged 28) was killed in an IRA landmine attack, Lurgancullenboy, near  [[Crossmaglen]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*9 October 1975: a civilian (Graham Tuck, aged 23) was killed when an IRA bomb exploded outside [[Green Park tube station]], London, England.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*10 October 1975: a UDA member (Ernest Dowds, aged 21) was shot dead by the IRA while walking near his home, Haywood Avenue, off Ormeau Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*14 October 1975: an RUC officer was killed in an IRA booby-trap bomb attack in Portadown, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*23 October 1975: a civilian ([[Gordon Hamilton-Fairley]], aged 45) was killed when a bomb attached to the car of Conservative MP [[Hugh Fraser (British politician)|Hugh Fraser]] exploded prematurely, Campden Hill Square, Kensington, London.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt; 
*29 October 1975: the IRA (PIRA) shot dead an [[Official IRA]] (OIRA) volunteer (Robert Elliman, aged 27), in McKenna's Bar, Stanfield Street, Markets, South Belfast. Between 29 October 1975 and 12 November 1975, 11 people would die in the continuing feud between the two wings of the IRA. Most of those killed were members of the OIRA.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*30 October 1975: Eileen Kelly (aged 6) was shot dead by the IRA at her home, Beechmount Grove, Falls, Belfast. Her OIRA volunteer father was the intended target during the OIRA/(P)IRA feud.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*31 October 1975: the IRA abducted and killed Columba McVeigh (17) as a suspected informer; his body has never been recovered.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*31 October 1975: the PIRA shot dead an OIRA volunteer (Thomas Berry, aged 27) outside Sean Martin's Gaelic Athletic Association Club, Beechfield Street, Short Strand, Belfast. OIRA/(P)IRA feud.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*31 October 1975: an IRA volunteer (Seamus McCusker, aged 40), was shot dead by the OIRA in New Lodge, Belfast. OIRA/(P)IRA feud.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*3 November 1975: the IRA shot dead a [[Republican Clubs]] member (James Fogarty, aged 22) at his home, Rock Grove, Ballymurphy, Belfast. OIRA/(P)IRA feud.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*6 November 1975: a UDR soldier (John Bell, aged 59) was shot dead by the IRA, while driving home from work, Ballymoyer, near Newtownhamilton, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*9 November 1975: the IRA shot an OIRA volunteer (John Kelly, aged 19) dead as he walked along Ponsonby Avenue, New Lodge, Belfast. OIRA/(P)IRA feud.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*10 November 1975: a UDR soldier (Joseph Nesbitt, aged 53) was shot dead by an IRA sniper outside Gough British Army Base, Carramoyle, near Keady, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*11 November 1975: the IRA shot dead an OIRA volunteer, a Republican Clubs member, and his relative in separate attacks in Belfast. Part of the ongoing PIRA/OIRA feud.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*12 November 1975: a civilian (John Batey) was killed when an IRA unit threw a bomb into [[Scott's (restaurant)|Scott's Restaurant]], Mount Street, Mayfair, London.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*16 November 1975: an RUC officer (Joseph Clements, aged 48) on mobile patrol, was killed in a land mine attack, near [[Sixmilecross]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*18 November 1975: two civilians, Audrey Edgson (aged 45) and Theodore Williams (aged 49) were killed when an IRA unit threw a bomb into Walton's Restaurant, Walton Street, [[Chelsea, London]].&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*21 November 1975: a British soldier (Simon Francis, aged 29) was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb hidden in an abandoned rifle close to a crashed car, Carrive, near Forkill, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*22 November 1975: three British soldiers (James Duncan (19), Peter McDonald (19), and Michael Sampson (20)) were killed in a gun battle when an IRA unit attacked their undercover observation post at Drummuckavall, County Armagh (see [[Drummuckavall ambush]]).&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*25 November 1975: two RUC officers, Samuel Clarke (aged 35) and Patrick Maxwell (aged 36), were killed when their mobile patrol was caught in an IRA sniper ambush in Clonavaddy, near Ballygawley, County Tyrone. In a separate incident a UDR soldier, Robert Stott (aged 22), was shot dead by the IRA outside his home in The Fountain area of Derry.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*27 November 1975: the IRA killed businessman and TV personality [[Ross McWhirter]] (aged 50) at his home, Village Road, [[Enfield, London]]; he had offered reward money to anyone who would inform on the IRA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=1975: TV presenter Ross McWhirter shot dead|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/november/27/newsid_2528000/2528787.stm|publisher=BBC|date=27 November 1975}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 December 1975: two IRA volunteers, Laura Crawford (aged 25) and Paul Fox (aged 20), died when killed when the bomb they were transporting exploded prematurely at a car park, King Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*6 December 1975: two IRA volunteers, Sean Campbell (aged 20) and James Lochrie (aged 19), died when the landmine they were setting exploded prematurely, Kelly's Road, Killeen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=s75/&gt;
*6–12 December 1975: four IRA volunteers held two people hostage in the [[Balcombe Street Siege]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=1975: Balcombe Street siege ends|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/december/12/newsid_2546000/2546477.stm|publisher=BBC|date=12 December 1975}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 December 1975: the IRA killed two British soldiers, Cyril McDonald (aged 43) and Colin McInnes (aged 20), in a bomb attack, Bank Place, near Guildhall Square, Derry. It was later established that the soldiers had been lured out of their sangar by children who offered them sweets. While the soldiers were distracted IRA volunteers lowered a bomb onto the roof of their sangar which exploded a few minutes later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheehy 2008&quot;/&gt;

==1976==
*5 January 1976: an RUC officer on mobile patrol (Clifford Evans, aged 30) was shot dead by an IRA sniper near Castledawson, County Londonderry.
*13 January 1976: two IRA volunteers (Rosemary Bleakley and Martin McDonagh), along with two civilians (Mary Dornan and Ian Gallagher) were killed when the bomb they were transporting exploded prematurely in North Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1976.html|title=CAIN: Sutton Index of Deaths|publisher=Cain.ulst.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 January 1976: a British soldier Mark Ashford (aged 19) was shot dead in an IRA gun attack on a British checkpoint in Derry City.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*17 January 1976: a civilian, Seamus O'Brien (aged 25), was found shot dead by the IRA at junction of Glen Road and Glenside Road, Andersonstown, Belfast; the IRA claimed he was an informer.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*22 January 1976: an off-duty UDR soldier, John Arrell (aged 32), was shot dead while driving his firm's minibus home from work, by an IRA sniper in [[Claudy]], County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*22 January 1976: a civilian, Kieran McCann (aged 20), was shot dead at his workplace in Eglish, near [[Dungannon]], [[County Tyrone]], by the IRA as an alleged informer.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*23 January 1976: the IRA ceasefire was officially called off.&lt;ref name=&quot;c76&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1976|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/othelem/chron/ch76.htm|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 January 1976: a civilian, John Smiley (aged 55), was killed in an IRA bomb attack on the Klondyke Bar, a pub reportedly frequented by paramilitaries in the loyalist [[Sandy Row]] area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*6 February 1976: two RUC officers, James Blakely (aged 42) and William Murtagh (aged 31), were fatally wounded in an IRA gun attack while on foot patrol in the Cliftonville area of Belfast. Murtagh died the following day.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*7 February 1976: two Protestant teenagers, Rachel and Robert McLernon (aged 18 and 16, respectively), were killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb, intended for members of the security forces, which had been hidden in an abandoned crashed car, Tyresson Road, Cookstown, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*12 February 1976: IRA volunteer [[Frank Stagg (Irish republican)|Frank Stagg]] (34) died on his 62nd day of a hunger strike in [[Wakefield Prison]] in England.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*12 February 1976: an RUC officer, William Hamer (aged 31), was shot dead while on foot patrol in Claudy, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*12 February 1976: James O'Neill (aged 17), Irish Republican Army Youth Section (IRAF), died after being badly burnt during an arson attack on a furniture warehouse, Antrim Road, New Lodge, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; 
*13 February 1976: an IRA volunteer died in a premature explosion in the Falls Road area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; Three mortars hit Fort Monagh British Army base in West Belfast. There were no casualties.&lt;ref&gt;''Eugene Register-Guard'', 14 February 1976&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 February 1976: an IRA volunteer was shot dead by the British Army while escaping from a gun attack on the Ballygomartin Road in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*22 February 1976: a civilian was shot dead by the IRA during an attempted hijacking of her car near Killeen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*26 February 1976: Joseph McCullough, a UDR soldier, was stabbed to death by an IRA unit while arriving to his farm in Newtownhamilton, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; IRA member Anthony McCooey, later convicted for taking part in the killing, claimed that another IRA man slit the soldier's throat with a [[bayonet]].&lt;ref name=Harn76&gt;Harnden, pp. 183-184&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, author [[Toby Harnden]] interviewed a [[Real IRA]] member who claimed McCullough had been targeted for supplying loyalists with arms and was also allegedly involved in the [[Dublin and Monaghan bombings]] of 1974.&lt;ref name=Harn76/&gt;
*27 February 1976: a UVF member was shot dead by the IRA in a drive-by shooting in the Donegall Pass area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*27 February 1976: a male civilian was wounded when he triggered an IRA booby-trap bomb in a derelict house on Landseer Street, Belfast. The man was an electricity meter-reader and accidentally triggered the anti-handling device on a bomb hidden in the meter box. It is believed a British foot-patrol was the intended target. The civilian died on 28 February.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*7 March 1976: the IRA launched six mortar rounds into [[Belfast International Airport]], injuring an RUC member and damaging cars in a parking area and the arrival lounge door.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=g_xUAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=V5IDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6806,1814872&amp;dq=mortar+ira&amp;hl=en Irish airport shelled in IRA attack], Reuters, 7 March 1976&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 March 1976: Former UDA spokesman [[Sammy Smyth (loyalist)|Sammy Smyth]] was shot dead by the IRA on Alliance Avenue in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*13 March 1976: a former British soldier was shot dead on Alliance Avenue in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*15 March 1976: a tube-train driver was shot dead {{Why|date=October 2015}} by the IRA shortly after a bomb exploded prematurely on his train.{{Where|date=October 2015}}&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*18 March 1976: the IRA attacked a British base in the Creggan, Derry City, with nine mortars and sniper fire.&lt;ref&gt;''The Montreal Gazette'', 19 March 1976&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 March 1976: a British soldier was killed by an IRA booby-trap bomb left near an Orange Order Hall, Ballygargan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*31 March 1976: three British soldiers were killed when their patrol-vehicle detonated an IRA landmine near Belleeks, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*1 April 1976: an UDR soldier was killed in an IRA gun attack in Castledawson, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*2 April 1976: an UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Maghera, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*5 April 1976: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA at his home near Newtownhamilton, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; 
*5 April 1976: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by the RUC shortly after carrying out a bomb attack on the Conway Hotel in Dunmurry, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*6 April 1976: A UDR soldier was shot dead in an IRA sniper attack on a British mobile-patrol near Middletown, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*7 April 1976: Three civilians were killed when IRA firebombs exploded in their Drapery shop at The Square in [[Dromore, County Down|Dromore]], County Down.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; They lived above the shop, whose owner was reportedly a loyalist.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 638&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 April 1976: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by the British Army shortly after having been arrested near Forkill, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*16 April 1976: Two civilians were killed when a bomb exploded inside their workplace on Servia Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; Although no group claimed responsibility it was reported that the blast was likely caused by &quot;an IRA bomb stored on the premises&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 641&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 April 1976: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA in Dunmurry, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*22 April 1976: An RUC Officer was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on patrol in Coalisland, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*29 April 1976: A UDR soldier and a civilian were killed in an IRA gun-attack in Dunamony, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*15 May 1976: Three RUC officers were killed in an IRA landmine attack on their patrol in Belcoo, Fermanagh. Another RUC officer was killed in a sniper attack in Warrenpoint, County Down.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*16 May 1976: The IRA shot dead an RUC officer outside his home in Derryfubble, County Tyrone. Two civilians were shot dead as they stood outside a social club on Alliance Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*17 May 1976: An IRA volunteer was killed when British soldiers opened fire on a bus in the Strand Road, Derry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*21 May 1976: A civilian was killed when a bomb exploded on a train near Moira, County Down. A warning was given but the bomb detonated before the area could be evacuated.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*22 May 1976: An RUC officer was shot dead in an IRA gun attack in Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*2 June 1976: Two RUC officers were shot dead in separate IRA attacks in Derry and Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*2 June 1976: A UDA member was shot dead at his home on the Shankill Road in Belfast by an IRA unit.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*11 June 1976: Four British bases in Belfast were attacked with mortars and gunfire within minutes of each other. Several British soldiers were hurt and an IRA volunteer was shot.&lt;ref&gt;''The Journal'', 12 June 1976&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 June 1976: A UDA member was shot dead at his home in Dunmurry, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*28 June 1976: A British soldier was killed when the [[landing zone]] of his helicopter-borne patrol was the subject of an IRA landmine attack near Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bramley, Vincent (2012). ''Two Sides of Hell''. John Blake, p. 57; ISBN 184454821X&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 June 1976: A British soldier was shot dead in an IRA gun-attack on the Springfield Road in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*30 June 1976: An IRA volunteer was killed during an attack on a British patrol when a [[grenade]] he was handling exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*1 July 1976: A Catholic civilian was shot dead by the IRA in the Finaghy area of Belfast. The IRA claimed he was an informer.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*3 July 1976: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while manning a checkpoint on Butcher Street in Derry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*6 July 1976: A Catholic civilian was shot dead by the IRA in [[Hannahstown]], Belfast. The IRA claimed he was an informer.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*7 July 1976: Two senior RUC officers were seriously injured after an IRA double agent led them to an arms dump outside Portadown. When the officers picked up one of the weapons it triggered a booby trap which detonated. One of the officers lost an arm, a leg and an eye in the explosion.&lt;ref&gt;Sheehy, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 July 1976: Two IRA volunteers died when the bomb they were transporting exploded accidentally near Castlederg, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*18 July 1976: A civilian was killed by a booby-trap bomb planted in the laneway of his home at Drumgole, County Fermanagh. It is thought that the bomb was planted by the IRA and was meant for two close relatives who were RUC reserve officers.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 663&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 July 1976: An IRA landmine killed [[Christopher Ewart-Biggs]], the newly appointed [[United Kingdom|British]] ambassador to the [[Republic of Ireland]], and his secretary Judith Cook. Two others in the car, including the driver were seriously injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Memorial for ambassador|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/1451064.stm|publisher=BBC|date=21 July 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; A British soldier was also killed in a bomb attack in Derry City the same day.
*30 July 1976: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Moneymore, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*31 July 1976: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA sniper on Church Street in Lurgan.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*8 August 1976: A British soldier was killed by an IRA bomb hidden in a booby-trapped bicycle in Crossmaglen.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*10 August 1976: An IRA volunteer, Danny Lennon, was killed when he was shot while escaping from a British Army patrol. After being shot his car went out of control, crashing and killing three Catholic children, whose mother later committed suicide and whose aunt was [[Mairead Corrigan Maguire]].&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*11 August 1976: A civilian was killed during an IRA gun attack on a British observation post at Meenan Square, Derry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*19 August 1976: There was a gun attack on the home of the Grand Master of the Orange Order at West Circular Crescent, Belfast. His son was shot and died of his wounds on 26 August 1976. The attack was blamed on the IRA. The Grand Master, a frequent critic of the IRA, was thought to have been the target.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 673&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 August 1976: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA unit in the Andersonstown area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*1 September 1976: A British Army post in Crossmaglen was hit by 10 mortars. It caused extensive damage and some soldiers were hurt.&lt;ref&gt;''The Age'', 2 September 1976&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 September 1976: The [[blanket protest]] began when IRA prisoner [[Kieran Nugent]] refused to wear prison clothing, in protest at the loss of [[Special Category Status]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c76&quot;/&gt;
*18 September 1976: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA unit while directing traffic in Portadown.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*1 October 1976: A Protestant man died one month after being shot at his relative's house on Copperfield Street, Belfast. The ''Sutton Database'' claims he was a civilian who was shot by the IRA.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; However, ''Lost Lives'' claims he was a former British soldier. It also notes that a man was imprisoned for his murder but there was no charge of IRA membership.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 677&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 October 1976: An RUC officer and a Prison Officer were killed in IRA gun attacks in Derry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*9 October 1976: A civilian was killed when IRA firebombs exploded in a shop on Bridge Street, Ballymena.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*13 October 1976: IRA volunteers shot dead a UVF member outside his home in [[Annaghmore, County Armagh]] by opening fire on his car as he arrived home. Although the ''Sutton Database'' lists him as a civilian, ''Lost Lives'' lists him as a UVF member and notes that he had received a two-year suspended sentence for handling ammunition which he was said to have bought from a UDR soldier. His son was wounded in the attack and died on 25 October 1976.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 682&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 October 1976: Garda Michael Clerkin was killed in a booby-trap bomb attack in [[Mountmellick]], [[County Laois]].{{Why|date=November 2016}}
*16 October 1976: Three IRA volunteers died when a bomb they were transporting exploded accidentally at Belfast Gas Works.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*24 October 1976: Two British soldiers were killed when an IRA sniper team ambushed a British patrol in Ardoyne, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*26 October 1976: A UDR soldier was shot dead at his workplace on Eglish Street, Armagh town.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*28 October 1976: A UDR soldier was killed in an IRA gun-attack in Pomeroy, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*2 November 1976: 26 year old RUC detective DC Noel McCabe shot dead by the IRA on the Falls Road, Belfast. He was later posthumously awarded the Queen's Gallatry medal.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*2 November 1976: RUC officer shot by the IRA at Fintona, County Tyrone as he alighted his patrol car in the town's main street; he survived the attack. {{cn|date=November 2016}}
*2 November 1976: A 52 year old RUCR officer was seriously injured when a booby-trapped device planted by the IRA exploded in his lorry at Grange Park, Balleygawley.
*3 November 1976: 59 year old Protestant businessness and former B Special Samuel McConnell shot dead by the IRA at his home in Dunrod, County Antrim.
*3 November 1976: 50 year old Georgina Strain shot dead by the IRA at her home on Hogarth Street in the Tiger Bay area of North Belfast; the reason is unknown.
*6 November 1976: A former RUC sergeant now working for the force as an office manager lost both legs when the IRA left a booby-trapped device attached to the garage door of his house in Newry, County Down.
*7 November 1976: 40 people injured by a 500lbs bomb planted by the IRA in a stolen car. Exploded outside the Raglan Bar, Queen Street, Ballymena, County Antrim.  
*7 November 1976: Two British soldiers seriously injured by an IRA landmine which caught two armoured vehicles at Donagh, County Fermanagh.
*7 November 1976: 33 year old UDR soldier Lance Corporal Winston McCaughey, a father of two, was shot dead by the IRA outside his home on Abercorn Road, Derry.
*9 November 1976: 46 year old UDR soldier Lance Corporal Jimmy Spears, a father of three, shot dead by two IRA gunmen as he worked off-duty at his garage in South Londonderry.
*11 November 1976: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA outside his home in Kilrea, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*11 November 1976: A former IRA quartermaster was shot dead inside a social club on Saul Street, Belfast. He allegedly gave information to the RUC under interrogation and was ordered to leave the district. It was reported he was shot for repeatedly returning to the district.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 688&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 November 1976: 35 year old employee of the Ministry of Agriculture forced by the IRA to drive a van packed with explosives into Magherafelt, County Londonderry, and to the Co-op on Union Street. Explosives partially neutralized by the British Army caused with less damage than intended when the remainder exploded.
*14 November 1976: On a Sunday morning 21 year old Lieutenant Robert William Glazebrook (from [[Hampshire]], England) of the Royal Hussars killed in an RTA on duty. 
*15 November 1976: During a rain storm in Lurgan, North Armagh, a four man UDR foot patrol was ambushed in the town centre by PIRA gunmen, one of whom was firing an American-supplied [[Armalite]]. Two soldiers were hit; one was a 19 year old who later recovered in hospital, the other was 41 year old Private George Lutton who died at the scene and was buried at Armagh cemetery in Lurgan.
*16 November 1976: 48 year old Catholic James Duffy shot dead by a lone republican gunman on the Falls Road. Suspected case of mistaken identity. He was shot in the back of the head as he chatted with a work colleague while making a delivery to a butcher's shop.
*18 November 1976: A UDR soldier was shot dead in an IRA attack in [[Altnagelvin]], County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*27 November 1976: In Lurgan, a civilian accidentally triggered an IRA booby-trap bomb attached to a derelict house on Mary Street that had been used as a British Army observation post. In Derry, a civilian accidentally triggered an IRA booby-trap bomb left in an entry off Lecky Road.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt; The IRA admitted planting the Derry bomb, which was also intended for the security forces. The IRA statement said that when it was clear the bomb plan had failed they had contacted the British Army and a local priest. Soldiers and the priest then warned people to stay away.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 691&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 December 1976: An IRA rocket hit a British APC in Belfast. No injuries were reported.&lt;ref&gt;''The News and Courier'', 2 December 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 December 1976: An RUC Officer was shot dead by the IRA in Dungannon.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*11 December 1976: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on patrol in the Bogside, Derry.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;
*15 December 1976: An RUC Officer was shot dead by an IRA unit while manning a security barrier in Portadown.&lt;ref name=rB/&gt;

==1977==
*1 January 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper in Crossmaglen. The IRA also carried out a carbomb attack at Harmin Park, Newtownabbey. A civilian was killed after an inadequate warning was given.&lt;ref name=cr77/&gt;
*9 January 1977. A British soldier was killed in an IRA booby trap bomb attack on his patrol near Newtownbutler, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=rA&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1977.html|title=CAIN: Sutton Index of Deaths|publisher=Cain.ulst.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*11 January 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper at a security barrier in the Oldpark area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*14 January 1977: An RUC officer was killed in an IRA bomb attack in [[Inishrush]], County Londonderry.
*16 January 1977: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by undercover British soldiers near Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*19 January 1977: A number of IRA booby trap bombs targeted security force members.&lt;ref name=cr77&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1977|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/othelem/chron/ch77.htm|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 January 1977: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA unit on the Strand Road in Derry.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*29 January 1977: Seven IRA bombs explode in Londons West End. Warnings are given and there are no casualties.&lt;ref name=cr77/&gt;
*2 February 1977: [[Jeffery Agate]] (59), then Managing Director of the American Du Pont factory in Derry was shot dead by PIRA volunteers outside his home at Talbot Park, Derry. This killing marked the beginning of a series of attacks on businessmen. There were further killings on 2 March 1977 and 14 March 1977.
*4 February 1977: An IRA bomb factory is discovered by police in [[Liverpool]], England.&lt;ref name=cr77/&gt;
*5 February 1977: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on patrol in Gilford, County Down.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*12 February 1977: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA unit in [[Cloughmills]], County Antrim.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*23 February 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by an IRA unit in the Waterside area of Derry City.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*24 February 1977: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA unit while manning a security barrier in [[Lurgan]], County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*26 February 1977: Robert Mitchell, a Justice of the Peace, was shot dead by the IRA in Newry.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*27 February 1977: An ex-British soldier was shot dead by the IRA in the [[Ardoyne]] area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*2 March 1977: Donald Robinson, an English businessman, was shot dead by the IRA in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*4 March 1977: Rory O'Kelly, Senior Department of Public Prosecutions official, was shot dead by the IRA in Coalisland, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*9 March 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA on his farm near Caledon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*10 March 1977: A civilian was shot dead by the IRA during a bomb attack on a business on York Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*13 March 1977: An RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on patrol in [[Lisnaskea]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*14 March 1977: James Nicholson, an English businessman, was shot dead when his car was ambushed by an IRA unit in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*15 March 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by an IRA unit in [[Bellaghy]], County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*25 March 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by an IRA unit in Coalisland, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*28 March 1977: A civilian was shot dead by an IRA unit in Crosskeys, County Antrim. Her son, an RUC officer, was the intended target.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*4 April 1977: A British soldier was killed in an IRA landmine attack on an Armoured Personnel Carrier near Belleek, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*6 April 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead while driving a vehicle in the Northland Road area of Derry City.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*8 April 1977: Two RUC officers were shot dead in an IRA ambush in [[Moneymore]], County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*9 April 1977: A civilian was shot dead by the IRA in Hannahstown, near Belfast. The IRA claimed he was a British informer.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*10 April 1977: The relative of an OIRA volunteer was shot dead by the PIRA in the Turf Lodge area of Belfast as part of an ongoing feud.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*15 April 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by the IRA in the City Cemetery, Derry.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*17 April 1977: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by a British Army sniper on Flax Street in the Ardoyne area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*23 April 1977: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by the British Army while in a car park in the Stewardstown area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*29 April 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA outside his home in Dungannon, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*3 May 1977: A civilian was found shot dead in a field off Glen Road, Belfast. He was shot by the IRA as an alleged informer.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*5 May 1977: An ex-British soldier was shot dead by the IRA in the Andersonstown area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*12 May 1977: Douglas Deering, a Justice of the Peace, was shot dead by the IRA in Rosslea, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*14 May 1977: Undercover British Army and SAS operative Captain [[Robert Nairac]] was captured by the IRA in south County Armagh. He was shot dead. His body has never been found.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*20 May 1977: An off-duty UDR soldier was shot dead while driving a school bus in near Benburb, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*21 May 1977: An ex-RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA in the Lisburn Road area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*30 May 1977: A civilian was shot dead by the IRA in College Square, Belfast. He was mistaken for an off-duty member of the British Army.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*2 June 1977: Three members of a Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) mobile patrol were shot dead by Irish Republican Army (IRA) snipers near Ardboe, County Tyrone. Part of ongoing attacks on Police and Army.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*8 June 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA after leaving the Victoria Hospital on the Falls Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*22 June 1977: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA in a [[drive-by]] attack outside the Crumlin Road Prison in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*29 June 1977: Two British soldiers were killed when their patrol was ambushed by IRA snipers outside North Howards Street British Army base in Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*6 July 1977: An RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA while sitting in a stationary patrol vehicle in Aughnacloy, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*22 July 1977: A Prison Officer was shot dead in Ballymoney, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*27 July 1977: The IRA shot dead a UDR soldier at his home on Woodvale Avenue, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*27 July 1977: The IRA shot dead a Republican Clubs (political wing of the OIRA) member at Alexander House, Belfast, as part of a republican feud.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*27 July 1977: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by the OIRA as he drove along Divismore Crescent, Ballymurphy. Part of a republican feud.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*9 August 1977: [[Fianna Éireann]] (IRA youth wing) volunteer Paul McWilliams was shot dead by a British Army sniper in the Ballymurphy area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*9 August 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper outside Henry Taggart British Army base in the Ballymurphy area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*10 August 1977: The IRA planted a small bomb in the grounds of the New University of Ulster, which [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Queen Elizabeth II]] was visiting. The bomb exploded shortly after the Queen had left. There were no injuries.&lt;ref name=cr77/&gt;
*12 August 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on patrol in the Turf Lodge area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*22 August 1977: A civilian was kidnapped from his home near Crossmaglen by the IRA and shot dead. The IRA claimed he was a British informer.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*28 August 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on foot patrol in the Ardoyne area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*31 August 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while on a British Army mobile patrol in the Antrim Road area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*7 September 1977: A civilian was shot dead by the IRA in a bar in Dublin. The IRA claimed he was an informer.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*8 September 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in the Finaghy area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*13 September 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while driving a vehicle in [[Gortin]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*25 September 1977: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Brantry, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*7 October 1977: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA in the Wellington Park area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*8 October 1977: A female UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Tynan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*12 October 1977: The IRA shot dead a civilian near Ballygawley, County Tyrone. The victim was mistaken for an off-duty UDR soldier.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*18 October 1977: An ex-RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA near Keady, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*19 October 1977: The IRA shot dead a civilian at his home on Ainsworth Pass, Belfast. The motive for the killing remains unclear.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*2 November 1977: A UDR soldier was killed in an IRA booby-trap bomb attack in Magherafelt, County Londonderry.
*11 November 1977: The IRA detonated a car bomb on King Street, Belfast. A warning was given to evacuate the area although one civilian was killed.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*15 November 1977: A British soldier was shot dead by the IRA while visiting his mother in Andersonstown, Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*3 December 1977: [[Seamus Twomey]], a former Chief of Staff of the IRA was arrested in Dublin.&lt;ref name=cr77/&gt;
*14 December 1977: An undercover British soldier was shot dead in an IRA ambush in the Turf Lodge area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=rA/&gt;
*21 December 1977: Five hotels across [[Northern Ireland]] were damaged when IRA firebombs exploded in them.&lt;ref name=cr77/&gt;
*22 December 1977: The IRA announced a [[Christmas]] ceasefire.

==1978==
*12 January 1978: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Newry.&lt;ref name=c78&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1978.html|title=Sutton Index of Deaths by Malcolm Sutton - 1978|accessdate=22 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 January 1978: The IRA seriously damaged the Guildhall in Derry in a bomb attack. There were no injuries.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*23 January 1978: A number of British soldiers were wounded and had to be airlifted to hospital following an IRA mortar attack on the British Army/RUC base in Forkill, County Armagh. The mortars were fired from a flatbed truck and hit the sleeping quarters. Afterward, three RUC officers were hurt by a booby-trap bomb planted in the truck.&lt;ref&gt;''The Leader-Post'', 24 January 1978&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harnden, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 January 1978: Bernard Brown, a supermarket employee, was shot and wounded during a robbery of the premises in [[Killygordon]], County Donegal; Brown died of his injuries five days later.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*4 February 1978: A civilian was accidentally shot dead during an IRA attack on an RUC foot patrol on Shore Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*7 February 1978: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA near [[Pomeroy, County Tyrone]].&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*8 February 1978: A UDR soldier and his 10-year-old daughter were killed by a bomb planted under their car outside their home in Maghera, County Londonderry.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*17 February 1978: Twelve Protestant civilians were killed and 23 badly injured in the [[La Mon Restaurant Bombing]], at [[Gransha]] near Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*17 February 1978: [[1978 British Army Gazelle shooting|British Lieutenant Colonel [[Ian Corden-Lloyd]] was killed and two other soldiers injured]] when the [[Aérospatiale Gazelle|Gazelle]] helicopter he was travelling in was attacked by an IRA unit. The helicopter crashed while taking evasive manoeuvers during the engagement.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dewar, Michael (1985). ''The British Army in Northern Ireland''. Arms and Armour Press, p. 156; ISBN 0-85368-716-1&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 February 1978: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by an undercover British Army unit at an arms-dump in [[Ardboe]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*28 February 1978: An RUC officer was shot dead in an IRA sniper attack in the Rosemount area of Derry City.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*1 March 1978: A British soldier was killed in an IRA machine-gun attack on British Army patrol on Cliftonpark Avenue, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*3 March 1978: The IRA launched a gun attack on a British Army checkpoint on Donegall Street, Belfast. A civilian who helped the British Army to search people was shot dead.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*4 March 1978: A British soldier was killed in a booby-trap bomb attack in [[Crossmaglen]], County Armagh. The soldier was killed while attempting to remove an [[Irish tricolour|Irish flag]] from a telegraph poll. The flag was wired to a landmine below the poll and exploded when it was removed.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*17 March 1978: An IRA unit and an SAS unit became embroiled in a gun battle in a field near Maghera, County Londonderry. One British soldier was killed in the battle. Prominent IRA member [[Francis Hughes]] was wounded and arrested after the shoot out.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*14 April 1978: A UDR soldier was shot dead while driving a school bus near Pomeroy, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*15 April 1978: An RUC officer was killed in a booby-trap bomb attack outside his home near [[Armoy]], County Antrim.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*22 April 1978: An RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA at his home in Lisburn.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*25 May 1978: Two civilians were kidnapped by the IRA in Belfast and later killed and secretly buried. Their remains were found in 1999 in County Monaghan.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt; The two had been executed for robbing an IRA-run bar. They reportedly admitted stealing IRA weapons for use in robberies, but had apparently handed back the weapons and any money they gained from robberies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/338183.stm &quot;Hope for families of 'disappeared'&quot;], bbc.co.uk, 9 May 1999; accessed 7 October 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 June 1978: An alleged criminal was shot dead by the IRA near Jonesborough, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*10 June 1978: An IRA volunteer was shot dead by undercover British soldiers while hijacking a car in the [[Bogside]] area of Derry City.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*16 June 1978: An RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA in the Foyle Street area of Derry.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*17 June 1978: An IRA unit ambushed an RUC vehicle near Camlough, County Armagh. One RUC officer was killed outright and another was wounded and captured. The IRA gave back the body of the second officer on 9 July. A post-mortem revealed he had died of his wounds soon after the ambush.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheehy 2008&quot;/&gt;
*20 June 1978: Three IRA volunteers and a passing UVF member were shot dead by undercover British soldiers during an attempted bombing at a Post Office depot on Ballysillan Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*25 June 1978: A UDR soldier was shot dead by during a bomb and sniper ambush of a British military convoy near [[Belcoo]], County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*4 July 1978: An RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA outside [[Castlederg]] RUC barracks in County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*12 July 1978: A British soldier was killed in an IRA radio-controlled booby-trap bomb attack while on foot-patrol in Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*19 July 1978: A British soldier was killed in an IRA remote-controlled bomb attack in [[Dungannon]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*2 August 1978: An RUC officer was shot dead in an IRA drive-by shooting while on foot-patrol in Ballymena, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*8 August 1978: A civilian was critically wounded when a bomb exploded near her home on Forfar Street, Belfast. It is thought that it was planted by the IRA and meant for a British Army patrol. She died of her wounds on 27 September 1978.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 766&lt;/ref&gt;
*11 August 1978: An undercover British soldier was shot dead in an IRA ambush on the Letterkenny Road in Derry.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*17 August 1978: A British soldier was killed in an IRA car bomb attack on a British patrol in Forkill, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*19 August 1978: Two ex-British soldiers were killed in IRA gun attacks in Belfast and Keady.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*5 September 1978: A British soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Newry.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*11 September 1978: The IRA shot dead an off-duty RUC officer in [[Loughmacrory]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*21 September 1978: The IRA carried out a large bomb attack against Eglington airfield. The Terminal building, two hangars and four planes were destroyed in the attack. There were no injuries.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*28 September 1978: The IRA launched a gun attack on a British Army foot-patrol on Waterloo Place, Derry. A civilian who helped the British Army to search people was shot dead.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*29 September 1978: The IRA fired shots at the car of an RUC officer in Newry. A civilian who was traveling in the car was accidentally shot dead but not the officer.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*6 October 1978: A UDR soldier was shot dead while at a cattlemart in Newry.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*12 October 1978: A civilian was killed when the IRA bombed a train at Belfast Central station. A bomb warning was given but there was not enough time to carry out a full evacuation.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*12 November 1978: A British soldier was killed when an IRA booby trap bomb detonated as a British patrol passed by in Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*14 November 1978: The IRA launched a large-scale bombing offensive in towns across Northern Ireland. Serious damage was caused to the centres of Castlederg, Enniskillen, Armagh, Belfast and Cookstown. There were 37 injuries in the attacks although warnings were issued.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*16 November 1978: A firefighter was killed when an IRA grenade exploded in a house which had been set alight in a bomb attack in the Andersonstown area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*24 November 1978: An IRA volunteer was shot dead in an undercover British Army ambush in Maureen Avenue, Derry City.
*26 November 1978: The Deputy-Governor of Long Kesh Prison was assassinated by the IRA outside his home in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*27 November 1978: An off-duty UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA near Durham Street, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*30 November 1978: The IRA carried out 14 bomb attacks in towns and villages across Northern Ireland. The IRA issued a statement saying it was preparing for a &quot;long-war&quot;.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*1 December 1978: The IRA carried out 11 bomb attacks on towns across Northern Ireland. There were no injuries.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*14 December 1978: A Prison Officer who worked at Crumlin Road Jail was shot dead by the IRA while leaving the prison.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*17 December 1978: The IRA carried out bomb attacks on cities in England including [[Bristol]], [[Coventry]], [[Liverpool]], [[Manchester]] and [[Southampton]].&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*19 December 1978: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while guarding other soldiers who were raiding a house in the New Lodge area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c78/&gt;
*21 December 1978: A four-man IRA unit ambushed a British patrol near St. Patrick's church in Crossmaglen, County Armagh. The IRA unit fired a large number of shots from three Armalites and one AK-47. Three British soldiers were killed in the ambush. The army unit returned fire but the IRA unit made its escape in an armour-plated van.&lt;ref&gt;Harnden pp. 84-86&lt;/ref&gt;

==1979==
*5 January 1979: Two IRA volunteers were killed in Ardoyne, Belfast, when the bomb they were transporting in a car exploded prematurely.&lt;ref name=c79&gt;{{cite web|title=A Chronology of the Conflict - 1979|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/othelem/chron/ch79.htm|publisher=CAIN}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*4 February 1979: Former prison officer Patrick Mackin (60), and his wife Violet (58), were shot dead by the IRA at their home in Oldpark Road, Belfast. This was part of an escalating campaign against prison officers, co-inciding with the [[Dirty protest]] and [[Blanket protest]] in the [[Maze prison]].&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*14 February 1979: A British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper on the Abercorn road in Derry.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*19 March 1979: An IRA unit launched a mortar attack on Newtownhamilton British army base. One British soldier was killed.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*22 March 1979: [[Richard Sykes (diplomat)|Richard Sykes]], then British Ambassador to the Netherlands, and his Dutch valet, Krel Straub, were killed in a gun attack in [[Den Haag]], [[Netherlands]]. The IRA also carried out 24 bomb attacks across Northern Ireland.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*5 April 1979: Two British soldiers were killed when IRA snipers attacked the Andersonstown British Army barracks in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*11 April 1979: Two British soldiers were killed when IRA snipers ambushed their armoured mobile patrol in Ballymurphy, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*13 April 1979: An off-duty UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Tynan, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*16 April 1979: An IRA unit shot dead a Prison Officer in Clogher, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*17 April 1979: Four RUC officers were killed when the IRA exploded an estimated 1,000&amp;nbsp;pound van bomb at Bessbrook, County Armagh, believed to be the largest bomb used by the IRA up to that point.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt; 
*19 April 1979: A prion officer was killed and three others seriously injured in an IRA gun and bomb attack outside Armagh Prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.impartialreporter.com/articles/1/38520 |title=Woman disabled in IRA attack died after shock of servicemen&quot;s deaths |publisher=Impartialreporter.com |date=23 April 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110713022433/http://www.impartialreporter.com/articles/1/38520/ |archivedate=13 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Belfast a British soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*25 April 1979: A UDR soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper while driving a lorry in County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*29 April 1979: A UDR soldier was shot dead by an IRA sniper in Edendork, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*6 May 1979: Two undercover British soldiers were shot dead by an IRA unit which ambushed their vehicle in Lisnaskea, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*9 May 1979: A British soldier was killed in an IRA bomb attack on his foot-patrol in the Turf Lodge area of Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*19 May 1979: An ex-UDR man was shot dead by the IRA while delivering bread to a shop in Garrison, County Fermanagh 
*20 May 1979: An RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA outside of a church in Derry.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*3 June 1979: Two RUC officers were killed when the IRA detonated a bomb underneath their patrol vehicle near Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*6 June 1979: A UDR soldier was shot dead in an IRA attack on a British Army base on the Malone Road in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*9 June 1979: During a gun battle between the IRA and the British Army, an IRA volunteer was shot dead.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*19 June 1979: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Omagh, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*22 June 1979: An RUC officer was shot dead by the IRA near Coagh, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*24 June 1979: An off-duty UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA while at his home in Markethill, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*8 July 1979: A British soldier was killed in an IRA bomb attack on his foot patrol in Crossmaglen, County Armagh.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*15 July 1979: A Catholic civilian was shot dead in the car-park of Falls Bowling Club on Andersonstown Road, Belfast. The ''Sutton Database'' claims that he was shot by the IRA.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt; However, ''Lost Lives'' claims that the IRA denied responsibility and says that there is no obvious motive.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 790&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 July 1979: An IRA unit launched a bomb attack on a British Army patrol in Rosslea, County Fermanagh. A civilian who was in the area was killed by shrapnel.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*2 August 1979: Two British soldiers were killed by the IRA in a landmine attack at Cathedral Road, Armagh town. In Belfast, an RUC officer was shot dead by an IRA sniper.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*7 August 1979: A civilian, [[Murder of Eamon Ryan|Eamon Ryan]], was shot dead by the IRA during a bank robbery in [[Tramore|Tramore, County Waterford]].&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*27 August 1979: An IRA bomb killed [[Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma|Earl Mountbatten of Burma]] at Mullaghmore, [[County Sligo]] the British Queen's first cousin, as well as [[Doreen Knatchbull, Baroness Brabourne|The Dowager Baroness Brabourne]], Mountbatten's elder daughter's mother-in-law (aged 83), [[Nicholas Knatchbull|The Hon. Nicholas Knatchbull]], Mountbatten's elder daughter's fourth son (aged 14) and [[Paul Maxwell (death of Louis Mountbatten)|Paul Maxwell]], a 15‑year-old Protestant youth from County Fermanagh who was working as a crew member. On the same day, the IRA launched the [[Warrenpoint ambush]], which resulted in the deaths of 18 British soldiers at [[Narrow Water Castle]], near Warrenpoint, County Down. As a British convoy passed, the IRA unit detonated a roadside bomb, killing six soldiers. IRA sniper fire then drove the soldiers to cover behind a nearby gatehouse, where a second bomb was detonated and killed a further twelve.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*28 August 1979: Four British soldiers are wounded when the IRA detonates a bomb under a bandstand in [[Brussels, Belgium]], as British Army musicians were preparing to perform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=m_8sAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=WswFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2422,10762&amp;dq=ira+germany&amp;hl=en|title=The Palm Beach Post via Google News Archive Search|accessdate=22 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 September 1979: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA off the Crumlin Road in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*19 September 1979: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA outside the Crumlin Road Prison in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*8 October 1979: An undercover British soldier was shot dead when his car was ambushed by an IRA unit on the Falls Road, Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*12 October 1979: The IRA shot dead a solicitor as he left Andersonstown British Army/RUC base in Belfast.&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, p. 803&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 October 1979: A UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in Roslea, County Fermanagh.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*19 October 1979: An off-duty UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in [[Fintona]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*28 October 1979: A British soldier and an RUC officer were killed when an IRA unit launched a heavy machine gun attack on Springfield Road Barracks, Belfast,&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*29 October 1979: An off-duty UDR soldier was shot dead by the IRA in [[Dungannon]], County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*5 November 1979: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA outside the Crumlin Road Prison, in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*13 November 1979: A British [[de Havilland Canada DHC-2 Beaver|Beaver reconnaissance aircraft]] was hit six times by an IRA unit which had mounted a roadblock in [[County Armagh|South Armagh]].&lt;ref&gt;Harndedn pp. 172-173&lt;/ref&gt; In Crossmaglen, a British soldier was killed in an IRA booby-trap bomb attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1979.html|title=CAIN: Sutton Index of Deaths|publisher=Cain.ulst.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 November 1979: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA while at his home in Glengormley, County Antrim.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*3 December 1979: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA at his home in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*16 December 1979: A landmine bomb killed four British soldiers near [[Dungannon]], County Tyrone. Another soldier was killed by a booby-trap bomb planted in a concealed observation post in a derelict house at Forkill, County Armagh. A former member of the Ulster Defence Regiment (UDR), James Fowler, was shot dead by the IRA in Omagh, County Tyrone.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*17 December 1979: A Prison Officer was shot dead by the IRA off the Crumlin Road in Belfast.&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;
*22 December 1979: An off-duty RUC officer traveling in his car was shot dead by an IRA sniper in [[County Monaghan]].&lt;ref name=c79/&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons category|Northern Ireland Troubles}}
*[[Timeline of Continuity Irish Republican Army actions]]
*[[Timeline of Real Irish Republican Army actions]]
*[[Timeline of Irish National Liberation Army actions]]
*[[Timeline of Ulster Volunteer Force actions]]
*[[Timeline of Ulster Defence Association actions]]
*[[Timeline of Ulster Defence Regiment operations]]
*[[Timeline of the Northern Ireland Troubles]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{PIRA}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chronology Of Provisional Irish Republican Army Actions (1970-1979)}}
[[Category:Chronology of Provisional Irish Republican Army actions]]
[[Category:The Troubles (Northern Ireland)]]
[[Category:Terrorist incidents in the 1970s]]</text>
      <sha1>n75l3ve6g799yl5h1ube3yzy5sg3ncy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
