<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Civil wars of the Tetrarchy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24204781</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749094756</id>
      <parentid>718117670</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T10:36:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Filedelinkerbot</username>
        <id>20611691</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bot: Removing [[Commons:File:132 Licinius.jpg]] ([[:File:132 Licinius.jpg|en]]). It was deleted on Commons by [[:Commons:User:Sealle|Sealle]] (per [[Commons:Commons:Deletion requests/Files in Category:PD-Coins-Krenzer]]).</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30886">The '''Civil wars of the Tetrarchy''' were a series of conflicts between the co-emperors of the [[Roman Empire]], starting in 306 AD with the usurpation of [[Maxentius]] and the defeat of [[Flavius Valerius Severus|Severus]], and ending with the defeat of  [[Licinius]] at the hands of [[Constantine I]] in 324 AD.

==Background==
[[File:Istanbul - Museo archeol. - Diocleziano (284-305 d.C.) - Foto G. Dall'Orto 28-5-2006.jpg|right|thumb|The emperor Diocletian who established the Tetrarchy.]]
The [[Tetrarchy]] refers to the administrative division of the Roman Empire instituted by [[Roman Emperor]] [[Diocletian]] in 293 AD, marking the end of the [[Crisis of the Third Century]] and the recovery of the Roman Empire. The first phase, sometimes referred to as the [[Diarchy]] ('the rule of two'), involved the designation of the general [[Maximian]] as co-emperor - firstly as ''[[Caesar (title)|Caesar]]'' (junior emperor) in 285, followed by his promotion to ''[[Augustus (title)|Augustus]]'' in 286. [[Diocletian]] took care of matters in the Eastern regions of the Empire while Maximian similarly took charge of the Western regions. In 293, feeling more focus was needed on both civic and military problems, Diocletian, with Maximian's consent, expanded the imperial college by appointing two ''[[Caesar (title)|Caesar]]s'' (one responsible to each ''[[Augustus (honorific)|Augustus]]'') - [[Galerius]] and [[Constantius Chlorus]].

The senior emperors jointly abdicated and retired in 305 AD, allowing Constantius and Galerius to be elevated in rank to ''[[Augusti]]''. They in turn appointed two new Caesars - [[Flavius Valerius Severus|Severus]] in the west under Constantius, and [[Maximinus Daia]] in the east under Galerius.

==Opening gambits==
The death of Constantius at [[Eburacum]] (now [[York]]) in 306 AD saw the first crack in the political edifice of the Tetrarchy. Rather than accepting the elevation of Severus from Caesar to Emperor, the troops at Eburacum elevated Constantius’ son, [[Constantine I|Constantine]], to the position of emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Eutropius, ''Breviarum'' [http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/eutropius/trans10.html#1 10.1&amp;ndash;2]&lt;/ref&gt; Galerius, the senior emperor, was sent a portrait of Constantine wearing a crown of laurels; by accepting this symbol, Galerius would be acknowledging Constantine as heir to his father's throne.&lt;ref&gt;Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 25.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine passed off responsibility for his unlawful ascension on his army, claiming they had &quot;forced it upon him&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Treadgold, 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Galerius was put into a fury by the message; he almost set the portrait on fire. His advisers calmed him, and argued that outright denial of Constantine's claims would mean certain war.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 28–29; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 62; Odahl, 79–80; Rees, 160; Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 25.&lt;/ref&gt; Galerius was compelled to compromise: he granted Constantine the title &quot;Caesar&quot; rather than &quot;Augustus&quot; (the latter office went to Severus instead).&lt;ref name=&quot;GCA&quot;&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 29; Elliott, ''Christianity of Constantine'', 41; Jones, 59; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 39; Odahl, 79–80.&lt;/ref&gt; Wishing to make it clear that he alone gave Constantine legitimacy, Galerius personally sent Constantine the emperor's traditional [[Tyrian purple|purple robes]].&lt;ref&gt;Odahl, 79–80.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine accepted the decision,&lt;ref name=&quot;GCA&quot;/&gt; knowing that it would remove doubts as to his legitimacy.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 29.&lt;/ref&gt;

This act motivated [[Maxentius]], the son of Maximian to also declare himself Emperor at [[Rome]] in 306 AD. Galerius, by now fearful that others would also attempt to become emperor, ordered Severus into Italy to deal with the usurper. Severus moved from his capital, [[Mediolanum]], towards Rome, at the head of an army previously commanded by Maximian. Fearing the arrival of Severus, Maxentius offered Maximian the co-rule of the empire. Maximian accepted, and when Severus arrived under the walls of Rome and besieged it, his men deserted him and passed to Maximian, their old commander. Severus fled to [[Ravenna]], an impregnable position: Maximian offered to spare his life and treat him humanely if the latter surrendered peaceably, which he did in March or April 307. Despite Maximian's assurance, Severus was nonetheless displayed as a captive and later imprisoned at [[Tres Tabernae]], before being eventually killed.

The joint rule of Maxentius and Maximian in Rome was tested further when Galerius himself marched to Italy in the summer of 307 with an even larger army. While negotiating with the invader, Maxentius could repeat what he did to Severus: by the promise of large sums of money, and the authority of Maximian, many soldiers of Galerius defected to him. Galerius was forced to withdraw, plundering Italy on his way. Some time during the invasion, Severus was put to death by Maxentius, probably at Tres Tabernae near Rome (the exact circumstances of his death are not certain). After the failed campaign of Galerius, Maxentius' reign over Italy and Africa was firmly established. Beginning in 307 already, he tried to arrange friendly contacts with Constantine, and in the summer of that year, Maximian travelled to [[Roman Gaul|Gaul]], where Constantine married his daughter [[Fausta]] and was in turn appointed Augustus by the senior emperor. However, Constantine tried to avoid breaking with Galerius, and did not openly support Maxentius during the invasion.

In 308, probably April, Maximian tried to depose his son in an assembly of soldiers in Rome; surprisingly to him, the present troops remained faithful to his son, and he had to flee to Constantine.

In the conference of [[Carnuntum]] in the autumn of 308, Maxentius was once again denied recognition as legitimate emperor, and [[Licinius]] was appointed Augustus with the task of regaining the usurper's domain.

In 310, Maximian rebelled against Constantine while the emperor was on campaign against the Franks. Maximian had been sent south to Arles with part of Constantine's army to defend against attacks by Maxentius in southern Gaul. In Arles, Maximian announced that Constantine was dead and took up the [[Tyrian purple|imperial purple]]. Despite offering bribes to any who would support him as emperor, most of Constantine's army remained loyal, and Maximian was compelled to leave. Constantine soon heard of the rebellion, abandoned his campaign against the Franks, and moved quickly to southern Gaul, where he confronted the fleeing Maximian at Massilia ([[Marseille]]). The town was better able to withstand a longer siege than Arles, but it made little difference as loyal citizens opened the rear gates to Constantine. Maximian was captured, reproved for his crimes, and stripped of his title for the third and last time. Constantine granted Maximian some clemency but strongly encouraged his suicide. In July 310, Maximian hanged himself.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', 34&amp;ndash;35; Elliott, 43; Lenski, 65&amp;ndash;66; Odahl, 93; Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', 17; Potter, 352.&lt;/ref&gt;

==War of Constantine and Maxentius==
[[File:Milvbruck.jpg|left|thumb|The [[Battle of the Milvian Bridge]] saw the death of Maxentius in 312 AD.]]
{{Campaignbox Constantine Wars}}
By the middle of 310 Galerius had become too ill to involve himself in imperial politics.&lt;ref&gt;Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 31–35; Eusebius, ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' 8.16; Elliott, ''Christianity of Constantine'', 43; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 68; Odahl, 95–96, 316.&lt;/ref&gt; His final act survives: a letter to the provincials posted in Nicomedia on 30 April 311, proclaiming an end to the persecutions of Christians, and the resumption of religious toleration.&lt;ref&gt;Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 34; Eusebius, ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' 8.17; Barnes, ''CE'', 304; Jones, 66.&lt;/ref&gt; He died soon after the edict's proclamation,&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 39; Elliott, ''Christianity of Constantine'', 43–44; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 68; Odahl, 95–96.&lt;/ref&gt; destroying what little stability remained in the tetrarchy.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41; Elliott, ''Christianity of Constantine'', 45; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 69; Odahl, 96.&lt;/ref&gt; Maximinus mobilized against Licinius, and seized Asia Minor. A hasty peace was signed on a boat in the middle of the Bosphorus.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 39–40; Elliott, ''Christianity of Constantine'', 44; Odahl, 96.&lt;/ref&gt; While Constantine toured Britain and Gaul, Maxentius prepared for war.&lt;ref&gt;Odahl, 96.&lt;/ref&gt; He fortified northern Italy, and strengthened his support in the Christian community by allowing it to elect a new [[Bishop]] of [[diocese of Rome|Rome]], [[Pope Eusebius|Eusebius]].&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 38; Odahl, 96.&lt;/ref&gt;

Maxentius' rule was nevertheless insecure. His early support dissolved in the wake of heightened tax rates and depressed trade; riots broke out in Rome and Carthage;&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 37; Curran, 66; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 68; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 62.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Domitius Alexander]] was able to briefly usurp his authority in Africa.&lt;ref name = &quot;leohak&quot;&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 37.&lt;/ref&gt; By 312, he was a man barely tolerated, not one actively supported,&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 37–39.&lt;/ref&gt; even among Christian Italians.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 38–39; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 62.&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer of 311, Maxentius mobilized against Constantine while Licinius was occupied with affairs in the East. He declared war on Constantine, vowing to avenge his father's &quot;murder&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 40; Curran, 66.&lt;/ref&gt; To prevent Maxentius from forming an alliance against him with Licinius,&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine forged his own alliance with Licinius over the winter of 311–12, and offered him his sister Constantia in marriage. Maximinus considered Constantine's arrangement with Licinius an affront to his authority. In response, he sent ambassadors to Rome, offering political recognition to Maxentius in exchange for a military support. Maxentius accepted.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41; Elliott, ''Christianity of Constantine'', 44–45; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 69; Odahl, 96.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Eusebius, inter-regional travel became impossible, and there was military buildup everywhere. There was &quot;not a place where people were not expecting the onset of hostilities every day&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius, ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' 8.15.1–2, qtd. and tr. in MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 65.&lt;/ref&gt;

Constantine's advisers and generals cautioned against preemptive attack on Maxentius;&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71.&lt;/ref&gt; even his soothsayers recommended against it, stating that the sacrifices had produced unfavorable omens.&lt;ref&gt;''Panegyrici Latini'' 12(9)2.5; Curran, 67.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine, with a spirit that left a deep impression on his followers, inspiring some to believe that he had some form of supernatural guidance,&lt;ref&gt;Curran, 67.&lt;/ref&gt; ignored all these cautions.&lt;ref&gt;MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 70–71.&lt;/ref&gt; Early in the spring of 312,&lt;ref name = &quot;esyyqc&quot;&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41; Odahl, 101.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine crossed the [[Cottian Alps]] with a quarter of his army, a force numbering about 40,000.&lt;ref&gt;''Panegyrici Latini'' 12(9)5.1–3; Barnes, ''CE'', 41; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71; Odahl, 101.&lt;/ref&gt; The first town his army encountered was Segusium ([[Susa (TO)|Susa]], [[Italy]]), a heavily fortified town that shut its gates to him. Constantine ordered his men to set fire to its gates and scale its walls. He took the town quickly. Constantine ordered his troops not to loot the town, and advanced with them into northern Italy.&lt;ref name = &quot;esyyqc&quot;/&gt;

At the approach to the west of the important city of Augusta Taurinorum ([[Turin]], Italy), Constantine encountered a large force of heavily armed Maxentian cavalry.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41; Jones, 70; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71; Odahl, 101–2.&lt;/ref&gt; In the ensuing [[Battle of Turin (312)|battle]] Constantine's army encircled Maxentius' cavalry, flanked them with his own cavalry, and dismounted them with blows from his soldiers' iron-tipped clubs. Constantine's armies emerged victorious.&lt;ref&gt;''Panegyrici Latini'' 12(9)5–6; 4(10)21–24; Jones, 70–71; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71; Odahl, 102, 317–18.&lt;/ref&gt; Turin refused to give refuge to Maxentius' retreating forces, opening its gates to Constantine instead.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41; Jones, 71; Odahl, 102.&lt;/ref&gt; Other cities of the north Italian plain sent Constantine embassies of congratulation for his victory. He moved on to Milan, where he was met with open gates and jubilant rejoicing. Constantine rested his army in Milan until mid-summer 312, when he moved on to Brixia ([[Brescia]]).&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 41–42; Odahl, 103.&lt;/ref&gt;

Brescia's army was easily dispersed,&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42; Jones, 71; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71; Odahl, 103.&lt;/ref&gt; and Constantine quickly advanced to [[Verona]], where a large Maxentian force was camped.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, 71; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71; Odahl, 103.&lt;/ref&gt; Ruricius Pompeianus, general of the Veronese forces and Maxentius' praetorian prefect,&lt;ref&gt;Jones, 71; Odahl, 103.&lt;/ref&gt; was in a strong defensive position, since the town was surrounded on three sides by the [[Adige]]. Constantine sent a small force north of the town in an attempt to cross the river unnoticed. Ruricius sent a large detachment to counter Constantine's expeditionary force, but was defeated. Constantine's forces successfully surrounded the town and laid siege.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42; Jones, 71; Odahl, 103.&lt;/ref&gt; Ruricius gave Constantine the slip and returned with a larger force to oppose Constantine. Constantine refused to let up on the siege, and sent only a small force to oppose him. In the desperately fought [[Battle of Verona (312)|encounter]] that followed, Ruricius was killed and his army destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42; Jones, 71; Odahl, 103–4.&lt;/ref&gt; Verona surrendered soon afterwards, followed by [[Aquileia]],&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42; Jones, 71; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 69; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71; Odahl, 104.&lt;/ref&gt; Mutina ([[Modena]]),&lt;ref&gt;Jones, 71; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Ravenna]].&lt;ref&gt;MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 71.&lt;/ref&gt; The road to Rome was now wide open to Constantine.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42; Curran, 67; Jones, 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

Maxentius prepared for the same type of war he had waged against Severus and Galerius: he sat in Rome and prepared for a siege.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42; Jones, 71; Odahl, 105.&lt;/ref&gt; He still controlled Rome's praetorian guards, was well-stocked with African grain, and was surrounded on all sides by the seemingly impregnable [[Aurelian Walls]]. He ordered all bridges across the [[Tiber]] cut, reportedly on the counsel of the gods,&lt;ref&gt;Jones, 71.&lt;/ref&gt; and left the rest of central Italy undefended; Constantine secured that region's support without challenge.&lt;ref&gt;Odahl, 104.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine progressed slowly&lt;ref name=&quot;BCE42&quot;&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42.&lt;/ref&gt; along the ''[[Via Flaminia]]'',&lt;ref&gt;MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 72; Odahl, 107.&lt;/ref&gt; allowing the weakness of Maxentius to draw his regime further into turmoil.&lt;ref name=&quot;BCE42&quot;/&gt; Maxentius' support continued to weaken: at chariot races on 27 October, the crowd openly taunted Maxentius, shouting that Constantine was invincible.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42; Curran, 67; Jones, 71–72; Odahl, 107–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Maxentius, no longer certain that he would emerge from a siege victorious, built a temporary boat bridge across the Tiber in preparation for a field battle against Constantine.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 42–43; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 78; Odahl, 108.&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 October 312, the sixth anniversary of his reign, he approached the keepers of the [[Sibylline Books]] for guidance. The keepers prophesied that, on that very day, &quot;the enemy of the Romans&quot; would die. Maxentius advanced north to meet Constantine in battle.&lt;ref&gt;Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 44.8; Barnes, ''CE'', 43; Curran, 67; Jones, 72; Odahl, 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

Maxentius organized his forces&amp;mdash;still twice the size of Constantine's&amp;mdash;in long lines facing the battle plain, with their backs to the river.&lt;ref name = &quot;bvubfs&quot;&gt;Odahl, 108.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine's army arrived at the field bearing unfamiliar symbols on either its standards or its soldiers' shields.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 43; Digeser, 122; Jones, 72; Odahl, 106.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Lactantius, Constantine was visited by a dream the night before the battle, wherein he was advised &quot;to mark the heavenly sign of God on the shields of his soldiers...by means of a slanted letter X with the top of its head bent round, he marked Christ on their shields.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lactantius, ''De Mortibus Persecutorum'' 44.4–6, tr. J.L. Creed, ''Lactantius: De Mortibus Persecutorum'' (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1984), qtd. in Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 71.&lt;/ref&gt; Eusebius describes another version, where, while marching at midday, &quot;he saw with his own eyes in the heavens a trophy of the cross arising from the light of the sun, carrying the message, ''In Hoc Signo Vinces'' or &quot;Conquer By This&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius, ''Vita Constantini'' 1.28, tr. Odahl, 105. Barnes, ''CE'', 43; Drake, &quot;Impact of Constantine on Christianity&quot; (CC), 113; Odahl, 105.&lt;/ref&gt; in Eusebius's account, Constantine had a dream the following night, in which Christ appeared with the same heavenly sign, and told him to make a standard, the ''[[labarum]]'', for his army in that form.&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius, ''Vita Constantini'' 1.27–29; Barnes, ''CE'', 43, 306; Odahl, 105–6, 319–20.&lt;/ref&gt; Eusebius is vague about when and where these events took place,&lt;ref&gt;Drake, &quot;Impact of Constantine on Christianity&quot; (CC), 113.&lt;/ref&gt; but it enters his narrative before the war against Maxentius begins.&lt;ref&gt;Cameron and Hall, 208.&lt;/ref&gt; Eusebius describes the sign as [[Chi (letter)|Chi]] (Χ) traversed by [[Rho (letter)|Rho]] (Ρ), or ☧ a symbol representing the first two letters of the Greek spelling of the word ''Christos'' or Christ.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 306; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 73; Odahl, 319.&lt;/ref&gt; The Eusebian description of the vision has been explained as a &quot;[[Halo (optical phenomenon)|solar halo]]&quot;, a meteorological phenomenon which can produce similar effects.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 306; Cameron and Hall, 206–7; Drake, &quot;Impact of Constantine on Christianity&quot; (CC), 114; Nicholson, 311.&lt;/ref&gt; In 315 a medallion was issued at Ticinum showing Constantine wearing a helmet emblazoned with the Chi-Rho,&lt;ref&gt;Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 71, citing ''Roman Imperial Coinage'' 7 Ticinum 36.&lt;/ref&gt; and coins issued at Siscia in 317/18 repeat the image.&lt;ref&gt;R. Ross Holloway, ''Constantine and Rome'' (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2004), 3, citing Kraft, &quot;Das Silbermedaillon Constantins des Grosses mit dem Christusmonogram auf dem Helm,&quot; ''Jahrbuch für Numismatik und Geldgeschichte'' 5&amp;ndash;6 (1954/55): 151&amp;ndash;78.&lt;/ref&gt; The figure was otherwise rare, however, and is uncommon in imperial iconography and propaganda before the 320s.&lt;ref&gt;Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

Constantine deployed his own forces along the whole length of Maxentius' line. He ordered his cavalry to charge, and they broke Maxentius' cavalry. He then sent his infantry against Maxentius' infantry, pushing many into the Tiber where they were slaughtered and drowned.&lt;ref name = &quot;bvubfs&quot;/&gt; The battle was brief:&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 43; Curran, 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Maxentius' troops were broken before the first charge.&lt;ref&gt;MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 78.&lt;/ref&gt; Maxentius' horse guards and praetorians initially held their position, but broke under the force of a Constantinian cavalry charge; they also broke ranks and fled to the river. Maxentius rode with them, and attempted to cross the bridge of boats, but he was pushed by the mass of his fleeing soldiers into the Tiber, and drowned.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 43; Curran, 68; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 70; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 78; Odahl, 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

Constantine entered Rome on 29 October.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 44; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 81; Odahl, 108.&lt;/ref&gt; He staged a grand ''[[Adventus (ceremony)|adventus]]'' in the city, and was met with popular jubilation.&lt;ref&gt;Cameron, 93; Curran, 71–74; Odahl, 110; Schmidt-Hofner, 33–60;&lt;/ref&gt; Maxentius' body was fished out of the Tiber and decapitated. His head was paraded through the streets for all to see.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 44; Curran, 72; Jones, 72; Lenski, &quot;Reign of Constantine&quot; (CC), 70; MacMullen, ''Constantine'', 78; Odahl, 108; Wienand, ''Civil War Triumphs'', 176–182.&lt;/ref&gt; After the ceremonies, Maxentius' disembodied head was sent to [[Carthage]]; at this Carthage would offer no further resistance.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''CE'', 44–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

==War of Licinius and Maximinus Daia==
Meanwhile, to the east, on Galerius’ death in 311 the eastern provinces were divided between [[Maximinus Daia]] and [[Licinius]]. Daia was unhappy that Licinius had been made senior emperor by Galerius, and took the first available opportunity to declare himself as emperor. Licinius held the eastern European provinces, while Daia took possession of the Asiatic provinces.

In the autumn of 312, while Constantine was fighting Maxentius, Daia was busy campaigning against the Armenians. He had returned to Syria by February 313 when discovered the alliance that had been forged by Constantine and Licinius in Mediolanum. Deciding to take the initiative, Daia left Syria with 70,000 men and reached [[Bythinia]], although harsh weather he encountered along the way had gravely weakened his army. In April 313, he crossed the [[Bosporus]] and went to [[Byzantium]], which was held by Licinius' troops. Undeterred, he took the town after an eleven-day siege. He moved to Heraclea, which he captured after a short siege, before moving his forces to the first posting station. With a much smaller body of men, possibly around 30,000,&lt;ref&gt;Kohn, George Childs, ''Dictionary Of Wars, Revised Edition'', pg 398.&lt;/ref&gt; Licinius arrived at [[Adrianople]] while Daia was still besieging [[Heraclea Pontica|Heraclea]]. On 30 April 313, the two armies clashed at the [[Battle of Tzirallum]], and in the ensuing battle Daia's forces were crushed. Ridding himself of the imperial purple and dressing like a slave, Daia fled to [[Nicomedia]]. Believing he still had a chance to come out victorious, Daia attempted to stop the advance of Licinius at the [[Cilician Gates]] by establishing fortifications there. Unfortuately for Daia, Licinius' army succeeded in breaking through, forcing Daia to retreat to [[Tarsus in Cilicia|Tarsus]] where Licinius continued to press him on land and sea. The war between them only ended with Daia’s death in August 313.

==Wars of Constantine and Licinius==
After Maxentius’ defeat, Constantine gradually consolidated his military superiority over his rivals in the crumbling Tetrarchy. In 313, he met [[Licinius]] in [[Milan]] to secure their alliance by the marriage of Licinius and Constantine's half-sister [[Flavia Julia Constantia|Constantia]]. During this meeting, the emperors agreed on the so-called [[Edict of Milan]],&lt;ref&gt;The term is a misnomer as the act of Milan was not an edict, while the subsequent edicts by Licinius - of which the edicts to the provinces of Bythinia and Palestine are recorded by Lactantius and Eusebius, respectively - were not issued in Milan.&lt;/ref&gt; officially granting full tolerance to &quot;Christianity and all&quot; religions in the Empire.&lt;ref&gt;Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', 24.&lt;/ref&gt; The document had special benefits for Christians, legalizing their religion and granting them restoration for all property seized during Diocletian's persecution. It repudiates past methods of religious coercion and used only general terms to refer to the divine sphere &amp;mdash; &quot;Divinity&quot; and &quot;Supreme Divinity&quot;, ''summa divinitas''.&lt;ref&gt;Drake, &quot;Impact,&quot; 121–123.&lt;/ref&gt; The conference was cut short, however, when news reached Licinius that his rival Maximinus had crossed the [[Bosporus]] and invaded European territory. Licinius departed and eventually defeated Maximinus, gaining control over the entire eastern half of the Roman Empire. Relations between the two remaining emperors deteriorated, though, and either in 314 or 316, Constantine and Licinius fought against one another in the war of [[Battle of Cibalae|Cibalae]], with Constantine being victorious. They clashed again in the [[Battle of Mardia|Battle of Campus Ardiensis]] in 317, and agreed to a settlement in which Constantine's sons  [[Crispus]] and [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]], and Licinius' son Licinianus were made [[Caesar (title)|''caesars'']].&lt;ref&gt;Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', 38–39.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the year 320, [[Licinius]] reneged on the religious freedom promised by the [[Edict of Milan]] in 313 and began to oppress Christians anew.&lt;ref&gt;Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', 41–42.&lt;/ref&gt; It became a challenge to Constantine in the west, climaxing in the great civil war of 324. Licinius, aided by [[Goths|Goth]] [[Mercenary|mercenaries]], represented the past and the ancient [[Paganism|Pagan]] faiths. Constantine and his [[Franks]] marched under the standard of the ''[[labarum]]'', and both sides saw the battle in religious terms. Supposedly outnumbered, but fired by their zeal, Constantine's army emerged victorious in the [[Battle of Adrianople (324)|Battle of Adrianople]]. Licinius fled across the Bosphorus and appointed [[Martinianus|Martius Martinianus]], the commander of his bodyguard, as Caesar, but Constantine next won the [[Battle of the Hellespont]], and finally the [[Battle of Chrysopolis]] on 18 September 324.&lt;ref&gt;Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', 42–43.&lt;/ref&gt; Licinius and Martinianus surrendered to Constantine at Nicomedia on the promise their lives would be spared: they were sent to live as private citizens in Thessalonica and Cappadocia respectively, but in 325 Constantine accused Licinius of plotting against him and had them both arrested and hanged; Licinius's son (the son of Constantine's half-sister) was also eradicated.&lt;ref&gt;Scarre, ''Chronicle of the Roman Emperors'', 215.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus Constantine became the sole emperor of the Roman Empire, ending the Civil Wars of the Tetrarchy.&lt;ref name=&quot;macmullen&quot;&gt;MacMullen, ''Constantine''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== References ==
* Barnes, Timothy D. ''Constantine and Eusebius'' (''CE'' in citations). Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1981. ISBN 978-0-674-16531-1
* Cameron, Averil and Stuart G. Hall. ''Life of Constantine''. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1999. Hardcover ISBN 0-19-814917-4 Paperback ISBN 0-19-814924-7
* Curran, John. ''Pagan City and Christian Capital''. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 2000. Hardcover ISBN 0-19-815278-7 Paperback ISBN 0-19-925420-6
* Digeser, Elizabeth DePalma. ''The Making of A Christian Empire: Lactantius and Rome''. London: Cornell University Press, 2000. ISBN 0-8014-3594-3
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/severus.htm DiMaio, Michael &quot;Severus II (306-307 A.D.)&quot;; ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/chlorus.htm DiMaio, Michael, &quot;Constantius I Chlorus (305&amp;ndash;306 A.D.)&quot;, ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/galerius.htm DiMaio, Michael, &quot;Galerius (305-311 A.D.)&quot;, ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/maxherc.htm DiMaio, Michael, &quot;Maximianus Herculius (286–305 A.D.)&quot;, ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/maxentiu.htm DiMaio, Michael, &quot;Maxentius (306–312 A.D.)&quot;, ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/licinius.htm DiMaio, Michael, &quot;Licinius (308–324 A.D.)&quot;, ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/daia.htm DiMaio, Michael, &quot;Maximinius Daia (305–313 A.D.)&quot;, ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* Drake, H. A. &quot;Constantine and Consensus.&quot; ''Church History'' 64 (1995): 1–15.
* Elliott, T. G. ''The Christianity of Constantine the Great'' . Scranton, PA: University of Scranton Press, 1996. ISBN 0-940866-59-5
* [[Eusebius of Caesarea]], ''Historia Ecclesiastica'' (''Church History'') first seven books ''ca''. 300, eighth and ninth book ''ca''. 313, tenth book ''ca''. 315, epilogue ''ca''. 325.
* Eusebius of Caesarea, ''Vita Constantini'' (''The Life of the Blessed Emperor Constantine'') ''ca''. 336–39.
* [[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''Breviarium ab Urbe Condita'' (''Abbreviated History from the City's Founding'') ''ca''. 369.
* [[Arnold Hugh Martin Jones|Jones, A.H.M.]] ''Constantine and the Conversion of Europe''. Buffalo: University of Toronto Press, 1978 [1948]
* [[Lactantius]], ''Liber De Mortibus Persecutorum'' (''Book on the Deaths of the Persecutors'') ''ca''. 313–15.
* Lenski, Noel, ed. ''The Cambridge Companion to the Age of Constantine''. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2006. Hardcover ISBN 0-521-81838-9 Paperback ISBN 0-521-52157-2
* Nicholson, Oliver. &quot;Constantine's Vision of the Cross.&quot; ''Vigiliae Christianae'' 54:3 (2000): 309–323.
* [[Ramsay MacMullen|MacMullen, Ramsay]]. ''Constantine''. New York: Dial Press, 1969. ISBN 0-7099-4685-6
* Odahl, Charles Matson. ''Constantine and the Christian Empire''. New York: Routledge, 2004. Hardcover ISBN 0-415-17485-6 Paperback ISBN 0-415-38655-1
* Pohlsander, Hans. ''The Emperor Constantine''. London &amp; New York: Routledge, 2004a. Hardcover ISBN 0-415-31937-4 Paperback ISBN 0-415-31938-2
*[http://www.roman-emperors.org/conniei.htm Pohlsander, Hans, &quot;Constantine I (306–337 A.D.)&quot;, ''De Imperatoribus Romanis'']
* Potter, David S. ''The Roman Empire at Bay: AD 180–395''. New York: Routledge, 2004. Hardcover ISBN 0-415-10057-7 Paperback ISBN 0-415-10058-5
* Rees, Roger. ''Layers of Loyalty in Latin Panegyric: AD 289–307''. New York: Oxford University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-19-924918-0
* Schmidt-Hofner, Sebastian. &quot;Trajan und die symbolische Kommunikation bei kaiserlichen Rombesuchen in der Spätantike&quot; In ''Rom in der Spätantike'', edited by R. Behrwald, C. Witschel, 33–60. Stuttgart: Steiner. ISBN 978-3-515-09445-0
* Treadgold, Warren. ''A History of the Byzantine State and Society''. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1997. ISBN 0-8047-2630-2
* Wienand, Johannes. &quot;O tandem felix civili, Roma, victoria! Civil War Triumphs From Honorius to Constantine and Back&quot; In ''Contested Monarchy: Integrating the Roman Empire in the Fourth Century AD'', edited by Johannes Wienand, 169–197. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2015. ISBN 978-0-19-976899-8

{{DEFAULTSORT:Civil Wars Of The Tetrarchy (306-324)}}
[[Category:4th-century conflicts]]
[[Category:Civil wars of the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:4th century in the Roman Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>ocmku95grwtyzd3j0d58y3ntbccf31s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
