<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Coagh ambush</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33995029</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748047264</id>
      <parentid>704359313</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-06T01:10:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MartinKassemJ120</username>
        <id>28021005</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15097">{{EngvarB|date=October 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Coagh ambush
| partof      = [[the Troubles]] and [[Operation Banner]]
| image       = [[File:Tamlaght, Coagh.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = Coagh as seen from County Londonderry
| date        = 3 June 1991
| place       = [[Coagh]], [[County Tyrone]]&lt;br&gt;[[Northern Ireland]]
| coordinates = {{coord|54|38|49|N|6|37|03|W|region:GB_type:event|display=title,inline}}
|map_type     = Northern Ireland
|map_relief   = yes
|latitude     = 54.646724
|longitude    = -6.617074
|map_size     = 300px
|map_marksize = 5
|map_caption =
|map_label   =
|territory   =
| result      = SAS success
| combatant1  = [[File:IrishRepublicanFlag.png|border|22px]] [[Provisional IRA]]
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;
* [[File:BritishArmyFlag2.svg|border|22px]] [[British Army]] ([[Special Air Service|SAS]])
| commander1  =
| commander2  =
| strength1   = 3 [[Volunteer (Irish republican)|volunteers]]
| strength2   = 8 soldiers
| casualties1 = 3 killed
| casualties2 = none
| notes       =
}}{{Campaignbox Northern Ireland Troubles|state=collapsed}}

The '''Coagh ambush''' took place on 3 June 1991, when a [[Provisional Irish Republican Army]] (IRA) [[active service unit|unit]] from the [[East Tyrone Brigade]] was ambushed by the [[Special Air Service]] (SAS) in the village of [[Coagh]], [[County Tyrone]]. The three-man IRA team was on its way to kill a part-time member of the [[Ulster Defence Regiment]] (UDR). Eight SAS members opened fire on the IRA unit's car, killing the three men and causing the car to burst into flames. 

==Background==
In May 1987, an eight-man unit of the [[Provisional IRA East Tyrone Brigade]] was [[Loughgall ambush|ambushed and shot dead]] by a Special Air Service (SAS) unit seconds after bombing the [[Royal Ulster Constabulary]] (RUC) base at [[Loughgall]], [[County Armagh]]. The SAS also killed a civilian who had accidentally driven into the ambush. This was the IRA's greatest loss of life in a single incident during [[Provisional Irish Republican Army campaign 1969–1997|its campaign]].&lt;ref&gt;Murray, Raymond (1990). ''The SAS in Ireland''. Mercier Press, p. 380; ISBN 0-85342-938-3&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this major setback, IRA activity in East Tyrone didn't lessen in the following years.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, Mark (1992). ''Big Boys' Rules''. Faber and Faber, p. 242; ISBN 0-571-16112-X&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1988, the SAS shot dead another three IRA members who were stalking a UDR soldier near [[Carrickmore]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nuzhound.com/articles/irish_news/arts2003/sep12_DUP_protest_IRA_commemoration.php DUP slams GAA club IRA commemoration], Newshound.com, 27 September 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; British intelligence sources claimed the men were involved in the [[Ballygawley bus bombing]], which killed eight British soldiers and injured 28.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Land Mine Kills 7 British Soldiers on Bus in Ulster|work=New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/08/21/world/ira-claims-killing-of-8-soldiers-as-it-steps-up-attacks-on-british.html|accessdate=24 March 2011|date=20 August 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=IRA Claims Killing of 8 Soldiers As It Steps Up Attacks on British|work=New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/08/21/world/ira-claims-killing-of-8-soldiers-as-it-steps-up-attacks-on-british.html|accessdate=9 December 2010|first=Steve|last=Lohr|date=21 August 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; The British military had to ferry its troops in and out of East Tyrone by helicopter as result of the Ballygawley bombing.&lt;ref&gt;Bijl, Nick van der (2009). ''Operation Banner: The British Army in Northern Ireland 1969 to 2007''. Pen &amp; Sword Military, p. 179; ISBN 1-84415-956-6&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tit-for-tat killings in East Tyrone===
According to Scottish author [[Kevin Toolis]], the series of killings which led to the Coagh ambush began on 26 April 1988, when a 23-year-old UDR soldier from Coagh, Edward Gibson, was shot dead by an IRA unit at [[Ardboe]]. Gibson was working for [[Cookstown]] Council on a bin lorry at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Toolis, p. 57&lt;/ref&gt; Off-duty UDR soldiers, who tended to be Protestants, were common targets of the IRA in County Tyrone. These kind of assassinations fostered a perception among some Protestants that the IRA was waging a sectarian war against them.&lt;ref&gt;Toolis, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ulster Volunteer Force]] (UVF) retaliated by killing Phelim McNally (brother of local Sinn Féin councillor Francie McNally) on 24 November  1988.&lt;ref&gt;Toolis, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA revenge took the form of a shooting at Leslie Dallas's garage on 7 March 1989. Dallas, a former UDR soldier, whom the IRA claimed was a UVF volunteer, was killed along with two elderly civilian pensioners.&lt;!--so far I only see IRA claims regarding this unconfirmed claim--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McKittrick, pp. 1164–65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Moloney|first=Ed|authorlink=Ed Moloney|title=A Secret History of the IRA|publisher=[[Penguin Books]]|year=2002|isbn=0-14-101041-X|page=332}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.palacebarracksmemorialgarden.co.uk/roll.html Palace Barracks Memorial Garden]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[tit-for-tat]] rampage in and around Coagh continued on 29 November 1989, when UVF gunmen burst into a pub owned by IRA member Liam Ryan; Ryan and a customer were shot dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toolis, p. 66&quot;&gt;Toolis, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 March 1990, UDR soldier and construction worker Thomas Jamison was killed when the IRA, using guns and a grenade, ambushed the truck he was driving near [[Donaghmore, County Tyrone|Donaghmore]]. Jamison was returning from delivering concrete to a UDR base.&lt;ref&gt;[[David McKittrick|McKittrick, David]] (1999). ''Lost lives''. Mainstream, p. 1193; ISBN 1-84018-227-X&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Toolis, p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; He was an employee of Henry Brothers, a construction company that had rebuilt and refurnished a number of security bases across Northern Ireland since 1985. Harold Henry, one of the two brothers who owned the company, had been killed by the IRA in  1987 in [[The Loup]], [[County Londonderry]].&lt;ref&gt;Toolis, pp. 55-56&lt;/ref&gt;

The UVF renewed the bloodshed on 3 March 1991, when [[1991 Cappagh killings|four men were shot dead]] in the strongly republican village of [[Cappagh, County Tyrone|Cappagh]]. Three of the four were IRA members. Republican sources claim the attack could have been carried out only with help from the security forces.&lt;ref&gt;Toolis, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA retaliated on 9 April 1991, when alleged UVF member Derek Ferguson (a cousin of local Member of Parliament Reverend [[William McCrea (politician)|William McCrea]]) was shot dead in Coagh by the East Tyrone Brigade. His family denied any paramilitary links.&lt;ref name=glen/&gt;

Toolis includes as part of this cycle of violence the [[Glenanne barracks bombing|destruction of Glenanne UDR barracks]] in nearby [[County Armagh]], in which three soldiers were killed and 10 injured by an IRA truck bomb on 30 May.&lt;ref name=glen&gt;Toolis, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA later claimed the killings in Coagh were retaliation by the SAS for the Glenanne bombing.&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;Summers, Chris (2009). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/northern_ireland/7852138.stm &quot;The SAS broke the rules of war&quot;], bbc.co.uk, 28 January 2009; accessed 5 May 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The ambush==
[[Image:Cav DSCF0370.JPG|thumb|200px|A red Vauxhall Cavalier like that driven by the IRA men at the time of the ambush]]
At about 7.30 am on 3 June 1991, three Tyrone IRA volunteers – Tony Doris, Michael &quot;Pete&quot; Ryan and Lawrence McNally – drove from [[Moneymore|Moneymore, County Londonderry]] to the village of Coagh in a hijacked [[Vauxhall Cavalier]],&lt;ref name=in&gt;Burrell, Ian [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/army-goes-to-war-over-sas-mans-revelations-1244144.html &quot;Army goes to war over SAS man's revelations&quot;], [[The Independent]], 7 August 1997; accessed 4 May 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; crossing the bridge between counties Londonderry and Tyrone. The IRA acknowledged that the trio was en route to kill a part-time UDR soldier, who was also a contractor to the security forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;glen&quot;&gt;Toolis, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; The plan, however, was betrayed either by an informer inside the IRA,&lt;ref name=&quot;glen&quot;/&gt; or by technical surveillance.&lt;ref name=pet&gt;Taylor, Peter, (2001). ''Brits: the war against the IRA''. Bloomsbury Publishing, p. 305; ISBN 0-7475-5806-X&lt;/ref&gt; The SAS unit was waiting for the car on both sides of Coagh's main street&lt;ref&gt;Toolis, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt; and in a disguised lorry.&lt;ref name=in/&gt; According to witnesses, they were wearing boiler suits and gas masks.&lt;ref name=lib/&gt; The car was driven by Doris toward the center of the village.&lt;ref name=shot&gt;Toolis, p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; The IRA unit's journey from Moneymore had been tracked on the ground and even from the air. The undercover team set up a &quot;decoy&quot; for the IRA, played by an SAS soldier who behaved like the intended victim, sitting in a car while waiting for a friend on his way to work.&lt;ref name=pet/&gt;

When the car reached a pre-established spot, eight SAS members opened-fire from close range, riddling the Vauxhall with over 200 rounds of high-velocity automatic fire. Tony Doris was immediately hit, and the out-of-control Vauxhall crashed into two parked cars.&lt;ref name=shot/&gt; The shooting continued for about ten minutes, until the car exploded in flames and set one of the parked vehicles (a [[Volkswagen Golf]]) alight.&lt;ref name=lib&gt;MacThomáis, Shane (2005). [http://saoirse32.blogsome.com/2005/05/27/remembering-volunteers-pete-ryan-lawrence-mcnally-and-tony-doris &quot;Three Volunteers killed in Coagh&quot;], saoirse32.blogsome.com, 27 May 2005; accessed 4 May 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; According to an eyewitness, one of the PIRA volunteers returned fire on the SAS after the car crashed.&lt;ref name=guardian&gt;Boycott, Owen (1991). [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/1991/jun/04/northernireland.owenbowcott &quot;Unionists approve hard line as army shoots IRA team&quot;], guardian.co.uk, 4 June 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; Some reports claim at least two of the men fled the blazing car&lt;ref&gt;Pogatchnik, Shawn (1991). [http://articles.latimes.com/1991-06-04/news/mn-179_1_northern-ireland &quot;3 IRA Guerrillas in Hijacked Car Slain by British&quot;], ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', 4 June 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; and were found lying half out of the vehicle.&lt;ref name=guardian/&gt; Some relatives believe the two men had escaped but were then shot and dragged back into the car by SAS members. A crime-scene report stated that a [[Balaclava (clothing)|balaclava]] of one of the men was found some distance away.&lt;ref name=bbc/&gt; The bodies were so badly burnt that they had to be identified using dental records.&lt;ref name=shot/&gt; Two rifles were recovered from the charred car. Forensics later found that the weapons had been used in the killings at Leslie Dallas's garage in 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toolis, p. 66&quot;/&gt;

==Reactions==
Local [[Democratic Unionist Party]] (DUP) politician [[William McCrea (politician)|William McCrea]] – cousin of Derek Ferguson, killed by the IRA on 9 April – declared that &quot;They have fallen into the pit they planned for others.... Justice has now been done&quot;.&lt;ref name=pet/&gt; [[Ian Paisley]], leader of the DUP, welcomed the ambush and said &quot;The time has come for a full war&quot;.&lt;ref name=guardian/&gt; [[Sinn Féin]] councillor [[Francie McNally]] – brother of Lawrence McNally – said the three men were &quot;good soldiers ... executed by the British Crown forces&quot;. Republican sources criticised both the RUC and [[Gardaí]]
for &quot;delaying and harassing&quot; the funerals of the three men, who were buried with full Irish republican honours. Republican sources assailed initial RUC claims that the IRA unit was in the process of shooting Protestant workmen.&lt;ref name=lib/&gt; [[Social Democratic and Labour Party]] MP [[Seamus Mallon]] warned that an &quot;ethic of violence is eating into the soul of this community&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/74687973.html?dids=74687973:74687973&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Jun+04%2C+1991&amp;author=Glenn+Frankel&amp;pub=The+Washington+Post+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=British+Commando+Squad+Kills+3+IRA+Gunmen+in+Ambush&amp;pqatl=google British Commando Squad Kills 3 IRA Gunmen in Ambush] by Glenn Frankel, ''[[The Washington Post]]'', 4 June 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; and that he &quot;hoped that every effort at arrest had been made&quot;.&lt;ref name=guardian/&gt;

==Later East Tyrone Brigade operations==
IRA recruiting in Tyrone continued unabated despite the ambush.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, 306&lt;/ref&gt; Just two months later it shot dead a former UDR soldier driving a truck on Altmore road, near Cappagh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/sutton/chron/1991.html CAIN Database of deaths −1991]&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1992 an IRA landmine at Teebane killed eight construction workmen (one of them a [[Royal Irish Rangers]] soldier)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.royalirishrangers.co.uk/role.html Royal Irish Rangers roll of honour]&lt;/ref&gt; who were working on a British Army base.&lt;ref&gt;O'Brien, Brendan (1999). ''The Long War: The IRA and Sinn Féin''. Syracuse University Press, pp. 219–20; ISBN 0-86278-606-1&lt;/ref&gt; [[Clonoe ambush|Another SAS ambush]] killed four IRA volunteers in [[Coalisland]] in February 1992,&lt;ref&gt;[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10612FF3D550C738EDDAB0894DA494D81 &quot;British try to end the fear in Ulster&quot;] by Steven Prokesch&lt;/ref&gt; but a month later a bomb attack maimed a soldier at Cappagh and prompted a [[1992 Coalisland riots|series of clashes between nationalist residents and British troops in heavily republican Coalisland]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emigrant.ie/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=37019&amp;Itemid=18 &quot;New Paratroop Controversy&quot;]. ''The Irish Emigrant'',  Issue No. 276, 18 May 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Fortnight Magazine|Fortnight]]'' (1992), issues 302–12&lt;!--ISBN, author name needed--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1993 there were reports of an apparent IRA campaign of assassinations to drive Protestants land-owners out of Tyrone and Fermanagh, especially after a bomb attached to his car killed former UDR soldier and land-owner David Martin in [[Kildress]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/heathwood/static/1993.html CAIN: &quot;Listing of Programmes for the Year&quot;], cain.ulst.ac.uk, 29 April 1993; accessed 4 May 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Clonoe ambush]]
*[[1992 Coalisland riots]]
*[[1997 Coalisland attack]]
*[[Provisional IRA East Tyrone Brigade]]
*[[Chronology of Provisional Irish Republican Army actions (1990-1999)]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* Toolis, Kevin (1995). ''Rebel Hearts: journeys within the IRA's soul''. Picador; ISBN 0-330-34243-6

{{The Troubles|collapsed}}

[[Category:The Troubles in County Tyrone]]
[[Category:Provisional Irish Republican Army actions]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in Northern Ireland]]
[[Category:People killed by security forces during The Troubles (Northern Ireland)]]
[[Category:Operations involving British special forces]]
[[Category:Special Air Service]]
[[Category:1991 in Northern Ireland]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1991]]
[[Category:Military history of County Tyrone]]
[[Category:British Army in Operation Banner]]
[[Category:Military actions and engagements during the Troubles (Northern Ireland)]]
[[Category:20th century in County Tyrone]]</text>
      <sha1>3clr24f1bvy1y0xth4zn3lyu0tny6bp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
