<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Collins-class submarine replacement project</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15174021</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745037421</id>
      <parentid>745011700</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-18T23:16:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anotherclown</username>
        <id>8567476</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Selected: Shortfin Barracuda (France; DCNS) */ rm wikilink from heading</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45383">{{DISPLAYTITLE:''Collins''-class submarine replacement project}}
Identified as the most expensive defence procurement project to date in Australian history, the Collins-class replacement will provide Australia with a submarine capability deep into the twenty-first century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smh.com.au/federal-politics/political-news/coalition-casts-doubt-on-plan-to-replace-collins-class-submarines-20140407-zqryi.html|title=Coalition casts doubt on plan to replace Collins Class submarines|work=The Sydney Morning Herald|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the [[Royal Australian Navy]]'s (RAN's) [[Collins class submarine|''Collins''-class submarines]] scheduled to begin leaving service from 2025 onwards, plans to replace them began in 2007 with the commencement of the defence acquisition project '''SEA 1000''', also referred to as the '''Future Submarine Programme'''. Australia's unique operating environment (including significant variations in ocean climate and conditions) and rejection of nuclear propulsion had previously driven it to operate in the Collins-class the world's largest diesel-electric submarines, capable of transiting the long distances from [[HMAS Stirling]] to their deployment areas.

In the early phases of the replacement project, four design options were identified: purchase a [[Military-Off-The-Shelf]] (MOTS) design, modify a MOTS design for Australian conditions, design an evolution of the Collins-class, or create a new design. [[Nuclear marine propulsion|Nuclear propulsion]] has been ruled out due to the lack of an indigenous nuclear industry in Australia and [[Anti-nuclear movement in Australia|public opposition to nuclear technology]].

In 2009, the Australian Government's [[Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030|Defence White Paper]] announced that a class of twelve submarines would be built.&lt;ref name=&quot;2009 Defence White Paper, p. 70&quot;&gt;2009 Defence White Paper, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt; The selected design was to be built in Australia at the [[ASC Pty Ltd]] shipyard in South Australia, but, if a company other than ASC was selected to build the submarines, they would be granted access to the government-owned facility. Concept work was to start in 2009, with a winning design to be identified by 2013 and design work to be completed by 2016, enabling the construction of the first submarine to be completed before 2025. However, there were significant delays in implementing the project, with meetings to define intended capabilities not occurring until 2012, which pushed the start of construction beyond 2017.

By the end of 2014, operational capabilities had still not been defined, amidst increasing speculation that the Australian government would purchase [[Sōryū class submarine|''Sōryū''-class]] submarines directly from Japan, skipping any tendering processes and ignoring previous commitments to build the boats in Australia. However, in February 2015 the [[Abbott Government]] announced a &quot;competitive evaluation process&quot; between competing Japanese, French, and German designs.

On 26 April 2016, Prime Minister [[Malcolm Turnbull]] announced the [[French Barracuda-class submarine#Conventional variant|Shortfin Barracuda]], a conventionally-powered variant of the ''Barracuda''-class nuclear submarine by French firm [[DCNS (company)|DCNS]], as the winner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-04-26/pm-announces-france-has-won-submarine-contract/7357462|title=Australian submarines to be built in Adelaide after French company DCNS wins $50b contract|work=ABC News|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Australian diesel-electric submarines operate in a wide range of geographic and oceanographic conditions, from the cold [[Southern Ocean]] to the tropics of the [[Coral Sea|Coral]], [[Arafura Sea|Arafura]], and [[Timor Sea|Timor]] Seas – requiring the submarines to handle significant variances in temperature, salinity, density, and climate. Australian submarines provide a [[Deterrence theory|deterrent]] towards military aggression against Australia, by patrolling the waters of Australia and nearby nations, and in addition, gather intelligence through the interception of electronic communications by foreign nations, and assist in the deployment and retrieval of special forces operatives. Because RAN submarines operate from a remote location at {{HMAS|Stirling}}, and because some of Australia's strategic interests are located as far afield as the [[Persian Gulf]] and the North Pacific, Australian submarines have to transit long distances to reach some of their potential patrol areas. This requirement for range and endurance resulted in the 1980s Collins-class design incorporating a large fuel load, large engines and sufficient batteries to transit these long distances, although technological improvements since then have enabled smaller diesel-electric submarines such as the German [[Type 214 submarine]] and Dutch [[Walrus-class submarine]] to achieve similar range and endurance as the Collins-class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asiapacificdefencereporter.com/articles/272/WHAT-LIES-BENEATH-Sea-1000|title=WHAT LIES BENEATH? Sea 1000|work=asiapacificdefencereporter.com|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been noted that the transit distances Australian submarines travel could be reduced by operating the submarines from {{HMAS|Coonawarra}} in Darwin, rather than the more remote location of {{HMAS|Stirling}} in Western Australia.&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace/&gt;

[[File:HMAS Rankin 2007.jpg|thumb|right|The ''Collins''-class submarine {{HMAS|Rankin|SSG 78|6}}. The SEA 1000 project will replace the six ''Collins''-class boats.]]
The ''Collins'' class were the first diesel-electric submarines specifically designed for Australian conditions of long transit distances and diverse sea states, and thus represent an 'orphan' design with no evolved design to replace them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theconversation.com/beyond-the-collins-class-what-next-for-australias-submarines-2499|title=Beyond the Collins Class: what next for  Australia's submarines?|author=John Thornton|date=31 July 2011|work=The Conversation|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The submarines were enlarged and heavily modified versions of Swedish shipbuilder [[Kockums]]' [[Västergötland-class submarine|''Västergötland'' class]].&lt;ref name=OxCom138&gt;Dennis et. al., ''The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History'', p. 138&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange7&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; Built during the 1990s and 2000s, the ''Collins''-class submarines have a predicted operational life of around 30 years, with the lead boat {{HMAS|Collins|SSG 73|6}} due to be decommissioned around 2025.&lt;ref name=Coleman&gt;Coleman, ''More problems with Collins class submarines&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Stewart&gt;Stewart, ''Defence to reach new depths''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Project history==
The Submarine Institute of Australia released a report in July 2007 arguing that planning for the next generation of Australian submarines had to begin soon if they were to be replaced by the 2020s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stewart&quot;/&gt; In December 2007, a month after coming into office following the [[Australian federal election, 2007|2007 federal election]], [[Minister for Defence (Australia)|Minister for Defence]] [[Joel Fitzgibbon]] announced that planning for the ''Collins'' class replacement (designated SEA 1000) had commenced.&lt;ref name=Stewart/&gt; The SEA 1000 project office was established within the [[Defence Materiel Organisation]] in October 2008, and was being jointly administered with Defence's [[Capability Development Group]].&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt;&lt;ref name=ABC4.6mil&gt;ABC News, ''4.6m for next generation submarine study''&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2009, Rear Admiral [[Rowan Moffitt]] was appointed as project head.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt;

===2009 Defence White Paper===
The 2009 ''[[Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030]]'' white paper confirmed the replacement project, and announced that the submarine fleet would be increased to twelve vessels.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence, ''Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century'', pp. 70–1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AWship24&gt;''Future Force'', in ''Australian Warship'', p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; Reasons for the increase presented in the white paper included the growing quantity and sophistication of Asian-Pacific naval forces (particularly submarine forces), the need to sustain submarine operations in any conflict, and the greater deterrent an increased submarine force would provide.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence, ''Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century'', pgs. 38, 64, 70–1&lt;/ref&gt;

Originally, the planned timeline called for concept work to start in 2009, preliminary designs to be established between 2011 and 2013, then detailed design work completed in time for construction to start in 2016.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000&gt;Kerr, ''Sea 1000''&lt;/ref&gt; This was to ensure that the new class would be in service before the ''Collins'' class began decommissioning in 2025.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt; However, meetings between Moffitt and the National Security Committee to clarify concept details and intended capabilities, scheduled for November 2009, did not go ahead until March 2012.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt; On 3 May 2012, the Australian government announced funding for the initial design phase.&lt;ref name=Depts3&gt;Offices of the Prime Minister, Minister for Defence, and Minister for Defence Materiel, ''Next stage of future submarine project announced''&lt;/ref&gt; The initial phase would encompass studies to select the new submarines' design, [[Defence Science and Technology Organisation]] projects to establish parameters for propulsion, combat system, and stealth capabilities, along with initiating programs to develop the required industry skills for the actual construction.&lt;ref name=Depts3/&gt; Under the 2012 revised timeline, the preliminary phase would conclude in 2013, with 'first pass approval' to be done by early 2014, and 'second pass approval' in 2017.&lt;ref name=Depts3/&gt; The best case prediction for seeing the first new submarine enter service, made in 2012, was &quot;after 2030&quot;.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt; At least some of the slow pace and lack of decision making has been attributed to politicians fearing being held responsible for a repeat of the [[Collins-class submarine#Problems during construction and trials|problems experienced by the ''Collins'' class]] during their construction and early career.&lt;ref name=HamishSnow&gt;McDonald &amp; Snow, ''Submarines no longer all at sea''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Speculation of a Sōryū class decision===
[[File:JS Unryū(SS-502) in Kure Naval Base 140915-01.JPG|thumb|left|The [[Sōryū class submarine|''Sōryū''-class]] submarine ''Unryū'' in 2014. The Japanese submarines had been widely speculated as the forerunner for the replacement project.]]
Although the German [[Type 214]] submarine has comparable range and endurance to the Collins-class, and superior range and endurance compared to the Sōryū-class, throughout 2014 there was increasing speculation that a Japanese design had been pre-selected as the Collins-class replacement,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.com.au/national/new-japanese-submarines-to-cost-abbott-government-20-billion/story-fncynjr2-1227050682205|title=Navy to get Japanese submarines|date=7 September 2014|work=NewsComAu|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading to public criticism that the Japanese submarines did not have the range or endurance that Australia required.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afr.com/p/inquiry_rejects_inadequate_japanese_8NgzqF3RHHOhv81ddQenDL|title=Inquiry rejects ‘inadequate’ Japanese sub option|work=Financial Review|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A September 2012 weapons technology swap deal and a July 2014 agreement on the sharing of defence technology were seen as preliminary steps towards Australian-Japanese collaboration on a submarine design, or towards integrating technologies like the ''Sōryū''{{'}}s Kockums designed [[air-independent propulsion]] Stirling engines and research into incorporating the Japanese boats' hydrodynamic capabilities into a potential SEA 1000 design.&lt;ref name=&quot;archive.defensenews.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Kallender-Umezu|first=Paul|url=http://archive.defensenews.com/article/20140929/DEFREG03/309290032/Japan-Make-Major-Switch-Sub-Propulsion|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204020745/http://archive.defensenews.com/article/20140929/DEFREG03/309290032/Japan-Make-Major-Switch-Sub-Propulsion|title=Japan To Make Major Switch on Sub Propulsion: Lithium-ion Batteries Will Power Soryu-class Boats|work=Defense News|date=29 September 2014|archivedate=4 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advantages in such a deal between the nations include the attention that securing the SEA 1000 project would bring to Japanese arms manufacturers (particularly after loosening of defence export restrictions in 2014), the provision of a proven high-end submarine design to the Australian military, and improved relations, both directly and as mutual allies of the United States of America.&lt;ref name=Hardy/&gt; However, it has been noted that cooperation on such a major defence project would be high risk due to Japan's lack of previous arms export experience, and any deal could negatively impact on both nations' relations with China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theage.com.au/comment/abbotts-plunge-into-submarine-market-is-a-risk-we-cannot-afford-20150216-13fmw4.html|title=Abbott's plunge into submarine market is a risk we cannot afford|work=The Age|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The close personal relationship between the then-Australian Prime Minister [[Tony Abbott]] and Japanese Prime Minister [[Shinzō Abe]] had also been cited as a factor in the likeliness of such a deal, although with the caveat that a change in government in either nation would compromise any potential deal for construction, or the ongoing maintenance support of the submarines: the [[Australian Labor Party]] has a greater interest in supporting local shipbuilding than Abbott's [[Coalition (Australia)|Coalition]] government, while a souring of [[China-Japan relations]] is something the [[Democratic Party of Japan]] is less likely to risk than the [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic]] government led by Abe.&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace&gt;Nicholson &amp; Wallace, ''Home-built submarines deemed too expensive, too risky''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hardy&gt;Hardy, ''After Collins: Australia's submarine replacement programme''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=KerrAnalysis&gt;Kerr, ''Analysis: European yards face Soryu-shaped hurdle to replacing Collins class&lt;/ref&gt;

By November 2014, initial capabilities had not been decided on, and recommendations were to be made across 2015.&lt;ref&gt;Kerr, ''Submarine chief: Canberra to get recommendations in next 12 months''&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2014, the Australian Coalition government ruled out using a [[Request for tender|tender]] process to identify a new submarine design, blaming the limited time left before the Collins-class were scheduled to begin leaving service.&lt;ref name=Owens&gt;Owens, ''Joe Hockey rules out open tender for new submarines''&lt;/ref&gt; Although there was speculation at the time that the Australian government would purchase directly from Japanese shipbuilders,&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace/&gt;&lt;ref name=KerrAnalysis/&gt; in January 2015, Defence Minister [[Kevin Andrews (politician)|Kevin Andrews]] stated that the government was still considering the options offered by European shipbuilders: [[ThyssenKrupp Marine Systems]] of Germany, [[Saab Group|Saab]] of Sweden, and a partnership of the French companies [[Thales Group|Thales]] and DCNS.&lt;ref name=ScottReynolds&gt;Scott &amp; Reynolds, ''Australia gingerly mulls Japanese submarine offer''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Australian Broadcasting Corporation, ''Defence Minister promises 'conservative' approach to submarines following tour of ASC''&lt;/ref&gt;

In mid-December 2015, the [[Japanese Self Defence Force]] allowed a journalist from the [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] (ABC) to tour the newest of the class, [[Japanese submarine Kokuryū (SS-506)|Kokuryū]] (black dragon), at its base at [[Yokosuka, Kanagawa|Yokoska]] and speak to the [[Commanding Officer]], Commander Takehiko Hirama, and several other personnel.&lt;ref name=&quot;2015-12-14_ABC&quot;&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-12-13/japan's-secret-submarines-revealed/7022560 'The characteristic is secrecy': Behind the scenes on Japan's state-of-the-art submarine], Matthew Carney, [[ABC News Online]], 14 December 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

===2015 policy announcements===
On 8 February 2015 the Abbott Government signalled that both the selection of a design and selection of construction options would be competitive, and on 9 February 2015 announced a &quot;competitive evaluation process&quot; with the possibility of construction in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kelly|first=Joe|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/abbott-leadership-crisis-pm-woos-mps-with-20bn-submarine-contract/story-fn59niix-1227212271695|title=Abbott leadership crisis: PM woos MPs with $20bn submarine contract|work=The Australian|date=8 February 2015|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 February 2015 the Australian Government publicly announced three key strategic considerations that would be taken into account in the competitive evaluation process, these being that the future submarines would have a similar range and endurance to the Collins class, superior sensor performance and stealth compared to the Collins class, and that the combat system and [[Mark 48 torpedo|Mark 48 Mod 7 torpedo]] jointly developed between the United States and Australia would be the future submarines' preferred combat system and main weapon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kevinandrews.com.au/latest-news/2015/02/20/strategic-direction-future-submarine-programme/|title=Strategic Direction of the Future Submarine Programme|work=Kevin Andrews|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government also announced a three-way competition between ThyssenKrupp, the Thales-DCNS partnership and a Japanese design, while Saab was excluded. The process is expected to select the design for the submarine by the end of 2015. It was indicated that the number of submarines would likely be reduced to eight, with specifics to come in the defence white paper slated for later in 2015.

==Technical considerations==
===Propulsion===
Deciding the future submarines' propulsion system is closely tied to determining its operational range, endurance and stealthiness. Two basic options are presented in submarine propulsion, nuclear propulsion, and conventional, [[diesel-electric]] propulsion. The option of nuclear propulsion effectively gives submarines an unlimited range and endurance, only restrained by maintenance and human crew requirements for resupply and rest, and removes the necessity for surfacing to recharge batteries, an unstealthy and risky process. Australian governments have repeatedly rejected the nuclear propulsion option due to the lack of an Australian [[Nuclear power in Australia|nuclear power industry]], (Australia would be the only non-nuclear nation to operate nuclear submarines), related issues of operational sovereignty were Australia to operate an American nuclear powered submarine such as the [[Virginia class submarine|Virginia class]], rendering it dependent on American technical support, and public opposition to nuclear technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Dibb|first1=Paul|last2=Brabin-Smith|first2=Richard|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/opinion/we-need-submarines-not-subservience-to-the-us/story-e6frgd0x-1226247752572|title=We need submarines, not subservience to the US|work=The Australian|date=19 January 2012|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second alternative is to operate a conventional diesel-electric submarine with sufficient fuel and battery power to transit the large operational ranges required by Australia, and to provide maximum range, endurance and stealth (operating underwater), before having to resurface to snorkel and recharge batteries. Previously, this design brief led to the construction of a relatively large conventionally powered submarine, the Collins-class, possessing a large diesel electric engine, fuel load and sufficient batteries capable of transporting the submarines from their remote location at HMAS Stirling to their operational areas, without having to resurface for extended periods.

A further innovation in diesel electric propulsion which might be considered for the Collins-class replacement is Air Independent Propulsion, which is not operated in the existing Collins-class, but is operated in a number of more recent submarine designs including the German Type 214, Japanese Sōryū-class, and French Scorpène-class. Air independent propulsion performs the role of an auxiliary engine, providing submarines with increased stealth by allowing them to operate submerged for longer. The German Type 214 submarine employs advanced [[Proton exchange membrane|polymer electrolyte membrane]] fuel cells that assist in delivering it comparable range and endurance to the Collins-class.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.industry.usa.siemens.com/verticals/us/en/marine-shipbuilding/brochures/Documents/SINAVY-PEM-Fuel-Cell-en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Batteries===
Batteries are an important component of diesel-electric submarines, allowing them to operate underwater for extended periods of time before having to resurface to recharge them. Improvements in battery technology in recent years have allowed smaller diesel-electric submarines to operate with greatly improved range and endurance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Buckingham|first1=John|last2=Hodge|first2=Christopher|last3=Hardy|first3=Timothy ||url=http://www.bmtdsl.co.uk/media/1057650/BMTDSL-Submarine-Power-and-Propulsion-Conpaper-Pacific08-Jan08.pdf|title=Submarine Power and Propulsion - Trends and Opportunities|work=Paper on Submarine Power and Propulsion Presented at Pacific 2008 in Sydney, Australia|date=January 2008|publisher=BMT Defence Services}}&lt;/ref&gt; Future submarine designs might utilise improvements in [[Lithium-ion battery]] technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;archive.defensenews.com&quot;/&gt; The Collins-class replacement might operate battery technology superior to that of the existing Collins-class.

The Australian Government's announcement on 20 February 2015 that the future submarines will have a similar range and endurance to the Collins-class increases the possibility that an evolved MOTS or completely new design will be selected.

===Weapons capabilities===
The 2009 Defence White Paper identified a land strike capability as an important addition to torpedo, mine and anti-ship missile weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;2009 Defence White Paper, p. 70&quot;/&gt; In February 2015 the Australian Government identified its preference for the future submarines to have a US weapon system and heavyweight torpedo.

* Torpedo. 
* Mine 
* Anti-ship missile
* Land attack cruise missile{{citation needed|date=February 2015}}

==Design==
===Candidates===
[[Image:S-120 Papanikolis 1.jpg|300px|thumb|right||A German designed [[Type 214 submarine]] at the HDW building yard in [[Kiel]], 2008. An evolved Type 214 was one of the options under consideration for the replacement program.]] 
In the 2009 Defence white paper, the replacement submarines were outlined as a class of twelve vessels of up to 4,000 tons displacement, fitted with land-attack cruise missiles in addition to torpedoes and anti-ship missiles, capable of launching and recovering covert operatives while submerged, and carrying surveillance and intelligence-gathering equipment.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence, ''Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century'', p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; The submarines would likely be fitted with the United States [[Virginia-class submarine#Other improved equipment|AN/BYG-1]] combat system.

There were four possible routes for the SEA 1000 project to take, in order of increasing design complexity and risk:
* Buy a [[Commercial off-the-shelf|Military-Off-The-Shelf]] (MOTS) design without modification
* Develop a modified MOTS design to better suit Australian service conditions
* Design an evolution of the Collins-class 
* Design an entirely new submarine

&lt;!--[[File:Scorpene Tunku Abdul Rahman.jpg|thumb|left|The Royal Malaysian Navy [[Scorpène class submarine|''Scorpène''-class submarine]] KD ''Tunku Abdul Rahman''. An evolved French-Spanish designed ''Scorpène'' class was one of the options under consideration for the replacement program.]]--&gt;
Designs initially considered for the various MOTS routes included the German-designed Type 214, Japan's [[Sōryū-class submarine|''Sōryū''-class]], the French-designed [[Scorpène-class submarine|''Scorpène'' class]], the Spanish [[S-80 class submarine|S-80 class]], and an evolved Collins-class. The Spanish S-80 class was dropped from consideration due to serious design issues that had been noted in the public domain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rt.com/news/spanish-submarine-cannot-resurface-634/|title=Spain spent $680 million on submarine that ‘can’t resurface’|work=RT International|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  An evolved ''Collins'' class design was also considered in 2013 but was officially dropped from consideration in 2015, due to it being assessed that the work required equated to composing a brand new design.&lt;ref name=swedenbarred&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.skynews.com.au/news/national/2015/02/25/sweden-barred-from-australia-sub-program.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713062244/http://www.skynews.com.au/news/national/2015/02/25/sweden-barred-from-australia-sub-program.html|title=Sweden barred from Australia sub program|work=Sky News|date=25 February 2015|archivedate=13 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Saab pushed an enlarged variant of its Swedish [[A26 submarine]], but was excluded from further consideration in February 2015 due to Sweden having not designed and built a submarine independently for twenty years.&lt;ref name=swedenbarred/&gt; Pure MOTS submarines were initially ruled out by the project in March 2011, but were put back on the table in December 2011.

Evolved designs of the ''Scorpène'' class have been offered, while ThyssenKrupp Marine Systems, in additions to options for an evolved Type 214, has proposed the development of a brand new design, the [[Type 216 submarine|Type 216]], to specifically match Australian requirements.&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace/&gt;&lt;ref name=KerrAnalysis/&gt;

{|{{Infobox ship begin |infobox caption=Shortfin Barracuda Block 1A|sclass=2|display title=none}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=
|Ship caption=
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Name=Shortfin Barracuda Block 1A
|Builders=[[DCNS (company)|DCNS]]
|Operators={{navy|AUS}}
|Class before={{sclass-|Collins|submarine|4}}
|Class after=
|Subclasses=
|Cost=
|Built range= 
|In service range=   
|In commission range= ≈2030–2070 (planned)
|Total ships building=0 
|Total ships planned=12
|Total ships completed=0
|Total ships cancelled=
|Total ships active=
|Total ships laid up=
|Total ships lost=
|Total ships retired=
|Total ships preserved=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption= 
|Ship type=[[Diesel-electric]] [[attack submarine]]
|Ship displacement=*4,500 t surfaced
*4,000 t submerged
|Ship length={{convert|97|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam=
|Ship height=
|Ship draught=
|Ship power=
|Ship propulsion=*({{convert|7|MW|abbr=on}} permanent magnet motor
*4 diesel alternators
|Ship speed=
|Ship range=
|Ship endurance=
|Ship test depth=
|Ship complement=
|Ship time to activate=
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=
|Ship armour=
|Ship aircraft=
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

===Selected: Shortfin Barracuda (France; DCNS)===
On 30 November 2015, DCNS with Thales delivered its proposal for the '''Shortfin Barracuda Block 1A''' design (a diesel-electric variant of the ''Barracuda''-class nuclear submarine under construction for the French Navy) to the Commonwealth of Australia’s Department of Defence. It includes a Government to Government Agreement from the French [[Ministère de la Défense]]’s Direction Générale de l’Armement (DGA) with a binding written agreement for aspects of the deliverables.&lt;ref name=&quot;2015-11-30_DCNS&quot;&gt;[http://en.dcnsgroup.com/news/dcns-delivers-proposal-for-future-submarines/ DCNS delivers proposal for future submarines], DCNS media release, 30 November 2015&lt;/ref&gt; “While exact details remain confidential, DCNS can confirm the Shortfin Barracuda is over 90 metres in length and displaces more than 4,000 tons when dived,” said Sean Costello, CEO DCNS Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://en.dcnsgroup.com/news/dcns-unveils-shortfin-barracuda |title=DCNS unveils Shortfin Barracuda |publisher=DCNS |date=15 July 2015 |accessdate=20 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

DCNS was chosen by the Australian Government on 26 April, 2016 to build 12 of the Shortfin Barracuda Block 1A variant at a projected A$50 billion.  Much of the works will be undertaken in Adelaide, South Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.smh.com.au/federal-politics/political-news/france-wins-50b-submarine-contract-20160425-goeuxh.html|title=France wins $50b contract to help build Australia's new submarines}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Royal Australian Navy the Shortfin Barracuda will displace 4,500 tons (surfaced), measure 97 metres in length, have an 8.8-metre beam, utilise [[pump-jet]] propulsion, have a range of 18,000 nautical miles, a top speed of greater than 20 knots, an endurance of 80 days and a crew of 60.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://navynews.realviewdigital.com/#folio=2|title=Superior sub-mission|newspaper=Navy News: Official Newspaper of the Royal Australian Navy|volume=59|issue=7|date=5 May 2016|publisher=Department of Defence|location=Canberra|oclc=223485215|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Construction==
[[File:Australian Submarine Corporation building.jpg|thumb|left|The ASC shipyard in Osborne, South Australia. The original intention was to build the new submarines at this government-owned shipyard, even if ASC was not the successful tenderer.]]
Initially, the Australian government promised that the government-owned ASC, the company responsible for building the ''Collins'' class, would build the new submarines.&lt;ref name=OwenAkerman&gt;Owen &amp; Akerman, ''Labor reneges on submarine promise to builder ASC''&lt;/ref&gt; In a May 2009 announcement about plans to release a request for tender, the Labor government indicated that if a company other than ASC was the successful tenderer, that company would be granted access to ASC's shipyard in [[Osborne, South Australia]].&lt;ref name=OwenAkerman/&gt; Despite ongoing support for the submarines to be built in South Australia by successive Coalition and Labor governments, in July 2014, the Abbott-led Coalition government abandoned their pre-election commitment to ASC-based construction and opened up the likely possibility of building the submarines at a foreign shipyard.&lt;ref&gt;Pultarova, ''Australia seeks partners to build next-generation submarines''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McGuire &amp; Shepherd, ''Defence Minister David Johnston won’t rule out dumping plans to build submarines in Adelaide''&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2015 the Abbott Government in announcing a 'competitive evaluation process' noted that the government would not approach the submarine decision with an 'open cheque book', but would rather allow a competitive process in which various construction options would be explored, including construction in Australia, overseas, or a 'hybrid approach' of foreign and local construction, along with estimated costs and schedules.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/latest-news/cormann-fronts-senate-hearing-over-subs/story-fn3dxiwe-1227236504755|title=Cormann says no open chequebook for subs|work=The Australian|date=24 February 2015|accessdate=14 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AndrewsPR&gt;{{cite press release |title=Strategic Direction of the Future Submarine Programme |publisher=Office of the Hon Kevin Andrews MP |date=20 February 2015 |url=http://kevinandrews.com.au/latest-news/2015/02/20/strategic-direction-future-submarine-programme/ |accessdate=25 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Original plans for construction indicated a 25-year period from work starting to final completion.&lt;ref name=NicholsonNew&gt;Nicholson, ''New subs to be built in Adelaide whatever the pick''&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the lengthy construction period, building the submarines in evolving 'batches' was under consideration; ongoing research and innovation would see updated equipment and designs incorporated into new submarines as built, then added to existing submarines during refits.&lt;ref name=ScottHorns&gt;Scott, ''Horns of a dilemma''&lt;/ref&gt; The SEA 1000 submarines are predicted to remain in service until the 2070s.&lt;ref name=NicholsonNew/&gt;

==Cost==
When announced, the ''Collins'' replacement project was identified as the most expensive ever undertaken by the Australian Defence Force.&lt;ref name=36bil&gt;Nicholson, ''Sub fleet carries $36b price tag: experts''&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2010, an update to the 2009 Defence Capability Plan forecast the cost of the project as over A$10 billion.&lt;ref name=KerrCapability&gt;Kerr, ''Australia publishes second update to capability plan''&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Australian Strategic Policy Institute]] has predicted that the new submarines will cost over A$36 billion to design and build, with construction of each submarine valued between A$1.4 and A$3.04 billion.&lt;ref name=36bil/&gt;&lt;ref name=KerrTestWater&gt;Kerr, ''Australia tests the water for its largest-ever defence procurement challenge''&lt;/ref&gt; Government predictions in 2014 estimated a total cost of up to A$80 billion for 12 ''Collins'' derivatives built by ASC, although ASC contests this with claims of a cost of A$18–24 billion.&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wroe&gt;Wroe, ''Australian-made submarines substantially cheaper than government suggests''&lt;/ref&gt;

An unspecified number of ''Sōryū''-class submarines, built in Japan by [[Mitsubishi Heavy Industries]] and [[Kawasaki Shipbuilding Corporation]] was estimated at A$25 billion.&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wroe/&gt; European shipbuilder offers in 2014 were valued by the shipbuilders as costing around $A20 billion or otherwise being competitive with the Japanese valuation.&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jennett, ''German shipbuilders ThyssenKrupp convinced they remain in race for Australian submarine contract''&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

==See also==

*[[Dolphin-class submarine]]

==Citations==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
;Books
*{{cite book |last=Dennis |first=Peter |author2=Grey, Jeffrey |author3=Morris, Ewan |author4= Prior, Robin  |title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, VIC |date=2008 |edition=2nd |isbn=9780195517842 |oclc=271822831}}
*{{cite book |last=Kelton |first=Maryanne |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Sdw9aVeNdwkC |title=More than an ally?: contemporary Australia-US relations |year=2008 |publisher=Ashgate |location=Aldershot, Hampshire |isbn=0-7546-7367-7 |oclc=181424108}}

;Journal articles
*{{cite journal |title=Future Force: Australia's 21st century navy |journal=Australian Warship |issue=50 |pages=24–31}}
*{{cite journal |last=Hardy |first=James |url=http://www.janes.com/article/44931/after-collins-australia-s-submarine-replacement-programme |title=After Collins: Australia's submarine replacement programme |date=23 October 2014 |journal=IHS Jane's Navy International |accessdate=3 January 2015}}
*{{cite journal |last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=7 December 2009 |title=Australia tests the water for its largest-ever defence procurement challenge |journal=Jane's Navy International |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal |last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=22 December 2010 |title=Australia publishes second update to capability plan |journal=Jane's Defence Weekly |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal |last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=12 January 2012 |title=Wave of the future |journal=Jane's Defence Weekly |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal |last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=13 April 2012 |title=Sea 1000: Australia's Future Submarine is slow to surface |journal=Jane's Navy International |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal |last=Kerr |first=Julian |url=http://www.janes.com/article/44933/analysis-european-yards-face-soryu-shaped-hurdle-to-replacing-collins-class |title=Analysis: European yards face Soryu-shaped hurdle to replacing Collins class |date=22 October 2014 |journal=IHS Jane's Navy International |accessdate=3 January 2015}}
*{{cite journal |last=Kerr |first=Julian |url=http://www.janes.com/article/45759/submarine-chief-canberra-to-get-recommendations-in-next-12-months |title=Submarine chief: Canberra to get recommendations in next 12 months |date=13 November 2014 |journal=IHS Jane's Navy International |accessdate=3 January 2015}}
*{{cite journal |last=Pultarova |first=Tereza |url=http://eandt.theiet.org/news/2014/jul/australia-submarine.cfm |title=Australia seeks partners to build next-generation submarines |date=28 July 2014 |journal =Engineering and Technology Magazine |publisher=The Institution of Engineering and Technology |accessdate=3 January 2015 |location=London}}
*{{cite journal |last=Scott |first=Richard |date=14 January 2010 |title=Horns of a dilemma: Project SEA 1000 seeks to balance technology and risk |journal=International Defence Review |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal |last=Woolner |first=Derek |date=18 September 2001 |title=Procuring Change: How Kockums was Selected for the Collins Class Submarine |journal=Research Paper |publisher=Department of the Parliamentary Library |location=Canberra |volume=2001–02 |issue=4 |url=http://www.aph.gov.au/binaries/library/pubs/rp/2001-02/02rp04.pdf |accessdate=23 January 2015 |issn=1328-7478}}

;News articles
*{{cite news |title=New subs unlikely to go nuclear: ADA |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/12/26/2127332.htm |work=ABC News |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |date=16 December 2007 |accessdate=3 June 2012}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/10/27/2402521.htm |title=4.6m for next generation submarine study |date=17 October 2008 |work=ABC News |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=3 June 2012}}
*{{Cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-01-22/defence-minister-promises-conservative-approach-to-submarines/6035866 |title=Defence Minister promises 'conservative' approach to submarines following tour of ASC |date=22 January 2015 |accessdate=22 January 2015 |work=ABC News |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation}}
*{{cite news |last=Coleman |first=Matt |url=http://www.abc.net.au/pm/stories/s125474.htm |title=More problems with Collins class submarines |work=PM |publisher=ABC Radio |format=Transcript |date=10 May 2000 |accessdate=19 August 2009}}
*{{cite news |last=Fowler |first=Andrew |url=http://www.abc.net.au/7.30/content/2003/s792830.htm |title=Are leaky Collins class subs all washed up? |date=25 February 2003 |work=The 7:30 Report |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=2 September 2009}}
*{{cite news |last=Jennett |first=Greg |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2014-12-17/germans-convinced-they-remain-in-submarine-contract-race/5973606 |title=German shipbuilders ThyssenKrupp convinced they remain in race for Australian submarine contract  |date=17 December 2014 |work=ABC News |accessdate=5 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-02-20/japan-france-germany-to-compete-for-submarine-build/6159834 |title=Submarine program: Japan, France, Germany to compete for build process; Government promises hundreds of local jobs |work=ABC News |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |date=20 February 2015 |accessdate=21 February 2015}}
*{{cite news |last1=Keck |first1=Zachary |url=http://thediplomat.com/2014/07/australia-and-japan-to-ink-submarine-deal/ |title=Australia and Japan to Ink Submarine Deal |date=8 July 2014 |website=thediplomat.com |publisher=The Diplomat |accessdate=8 July 2014}}
*{{cite news |last1=LaGrone |first1=Sam |url=http://news.usni.org/2014/07/07/japan-australia-cooperate-new-submarine-design |title=Japan and Australia to Cooperate on New Submarine Design |date=7 July 2014 |website=news.usni.org |publisher=U.S. Naval Institute |accessdate=8 July 2014}}
*{{cite news |last=McDonald |first=Hamish |last2=Snow |first2=Deborah |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/submarines-no-longer-all-at-sea-20120708-21pk3.html |title=Submarines no longer all at sea |date=9 July 2012 |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=3 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |last1=McGuire |first1=Michael |last2=Shepherd |first2=Tony |url=http://www.news.com.au/national/south-australia/defence-minister-david-johnston-wont-rule-out-dumping-plans-to-build-submarines-in-adelaide/story-fnii5yv4-1227039345672 |title=Defence Minister David Johnston won’t rule out dumping plans to build submarines in Adelaide |date=28 August 2014 |work=The Advertiser |accessdate=3 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/sub-fleet-carries-36b-price-tag-experts-20091029-hnqj.html |title=Sub fleet carries $36b price tag: experts |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |date=30 October 2009 |accessdate=30 October 2009}}
*{{cite news |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/new-subs-to-be-built-in-adelaide-whatever-the-pick/story-e6frg8yo-1225824141618 |title=New subs to be built in Adelaide whatever the pick  |date=28 January 2010 |work=The Australian |accessdate=29 January 2010}}
*{{cite news |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |last2=Wallace |first2=Rick |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/defence/homebuilt-submarines-deemed-too-expensive-too-risky/story-e6frg8yo-1227052023555 |title=Home-built submarines deemed too expensive, too risky |date=9 September 2014 |work=The Australian |accessdate=3 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/features/choice-of-navys-new-submarine-is-a-20bn-guessing-game/story-e6frg6z6-1227127446112 |title=Choice of navy's new submarine is a $20bn guessing game |date=19 November 2014 |work=The Australian |accessdate=5 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |last1=Owen |first1=Michael |last2=Akerman |first2=Pia |url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,25430228-31477,00.html |title=Labor reneges on submarine promise to builder ASC |date=5 May 2009 |work=The Australian |accessdate=5 May 2009}}
*{{cite news |last=Owens |first=Jared |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/defence/joe-hockey-rules-out-open-tender-for-new-submarines/story-e6frg8yo-1227141998416?nk=86434199faf52fe86f5e321626279810 |title=Joe Hockey rules out open tender for new submarines |date=2 December 2014 |work=The Australian |accessdate=3 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |last=Scott |first=Jason |last2=Reynolds |first2=Isabel |url=http://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2014/12/19/national/politics-diplomacy/australia-gingerly-mulls-japanese-submarine-offer/#.VKn168lMGVo |title=Australia gingerly mulls Japanese submarine offer |date=19 December 2014 |work=The Japan Times |accessdate=5 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |last=Stewart |first=Cameron |title=Defence to reach new depths |url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,22981343-31477,00.html |work=The Australian |date=29 December 2007 |accessdate=25 April 2009}}
*{{cite news |last=Taylor |first=Rob |url=http://www.wsj.com/articles/japan-gains-edge-in-australia-submarine-deal-1417503055 |title=Japan Gains Edge in Australia Submarine Deal |date=2 December 2014 |work=The Wall Street Journal |accessdate=5 January 2015}}
*{{cite news |last=Wallace |first=Rick |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/defence/japan-tech-deal-could-help-power-our-subs/story-e6frg8yo-1226482149198 |title=Japan tech deal could help power our subs |newspaper=The Australian |date=27 September 2012 |accessdate=24 January 2014 |format=behind paywall}}
*{{cite news |last=Wroe |first=David |url=http://www.smh.com.au/federal-politics/political-news/australianmade-submarines-substantially-cheaper-than-government-suggests-20141120-11qimc.html |title=Australian-made submarines substantially cheaper than government suggests |date=20 November 2014 |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=3 January 2015}}

;Press releases and reports
*{{cite book |author=Department of Defence |title=[[Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030]] |publisher=Commonwealth of Australia |date=2 May 2009 |isbn=978-0-642-29702-0 |oclc=426475923}}
*{{cite press release |title=Next stage of future submarine project announced |publisher=Offices of the Prime Minister, Minister for Defence, and Minister for Defence Materiel |date=3 May 2012 |url=http://www.minister.defence.gov.au/2012/05/03/prime-minister-minister-for-defence-minister-for-defence-materiel-joint-media-release-next-stage-of-future-submarine-project-announced/ |accessdate=3 June 2012}}

==External links==
*{{cite web|title=SEA1000 Australia's New Submarines|url=http://sea1000.gov.au/|publisher=Department of Defence}}

{{Australian submarines}}

[[Category:Submarines of the Royal Australian Navy]]
[[Category:Proposed ships]]</text>
      <sha1>oadzbvpbe37k8ibesv9065n8indtp1k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
