<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Curtiss-Wright C-76 Caravan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7621906</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745486265</id>
      <parentid>737496983</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-21T11:51:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Design and development */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13467">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
 |name = C-76 Caravan
 |image = File:Curtiss c76 side USAF.jpg
 |caption = 
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
 |type = Medium transport
 |national origin = United States
 |manufacturer = [[Curtiss-Wright]]
 |designer =
 |first flight = May 3, 1943
 |introduced =
 |retired =
 |produced =
 |primary user = [[United States Army Air Forces]]
 |more users = 
 |number built = 25 (11 prototypes, 5 production C-76, 9 revised YC-76A)
 |status = Canceled
 |unit cost =
 |developed from =
 |variants with their own articles = 
}}
|}

The '''Curtiss-Wright C-76 Caravan''' (company designation '''CW-27''') was an American all-wood military  transport aircraft. The C-76 was intended as a substitute standard aircraft in the event of expected wartime shortages of [[Duralumin|light alloys]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DRE&quot;&gt;Dreher, Carl, ''Wood Is A War Weapon'', Popular Science, Vol. 141 No.3 (September 1942), pp. 48-74&lt;/ref&gt; However, both prototype and production aircraft failed several critical flight and static tests, and after U.S. aluminum production proved sufficient for wartime defense requirements, orders for the C-76 were cancelled and production terminated.&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;&gt;Kleber, John E., ''The Encyclopedia of Louisville'', University Press of Kentucky (2001) ISBN 0-8131-2100-0, ISBN 978-0-8131-2100-0, pp. xxvii, 235-236&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design and development==
[[File:Curtiss C-76 and AT-9 1943.jpg|thumb|[[Curtiss AT-]]A under C-76 Caravan's wing at Curtiss-Wright in 1943.]]

In 1941, [[Curtiss-Wright]] was contracted by the [[United States Army Air Forces]] to design and construct an all-wood military transport aircraft, with performance specifications meeting or exceeding that of the [[Douglas C-47 Skytrain]] then in service.&lt;ref name=&quot;DRE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOR&quot;&gt;Dorrell, David (ed.), ''Curtiss Caravan'', Air Pictorial: Journal of the Air League'', Air League of the British Empire, Volume 35, No. 7 (July 1973), p. 69&lt;/ref&gt;

The Curtiss-Wright CW-27 was designed by Curtiss-Wright's chief designer George A. Page, Jr. as a high-wing, twin-engine, cargo transport aircraft, utilizing [[plywood]] construction with a tricycle undercarriage. Though the British [[de Havilland Mosquito]] had successfully employed a ply construction using a [[Ochroma pyramidale|balsa]] wood core and [[birch]] hardwood exterior, Curtiss-Wright engineers, using research provided by [[Forest Products Laboratory]],&lt;ref&gt;Forest Products Journal, January 1, 2007: &quot;G.A. Page, chief engineer of the Curtiss-Wright Division at St. Louis, Mo., wrote, &quot;It [the Design Handbook] has expedited and facilitated our work in connection with the design of the C-76 airplane to a degree that is hard to estimate.&quot; ''[http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Forest+Products+Journal/2007/January/1-p52579 Forest Products Laboratory: supporting the nation's armed forces with valuable wood research for 90 years]''&lt;/ref&gt; rejected this approach, insisting instead on a ply construction of dense [[mahogany]], which greatly increased the plane's weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot;&gt;Sessums, Col. J.W., ''Design and Engineering Problems of Aircraft Production'' {Restricted}, May 14, 1946, pp. 6-8 [https://digitalndulibrary.ndu.edu/index.php National Defense University Archives]&lt;/ref&gt; At Curtiss' request, Army Materiel Command laid in large supplies of mahogany, and a number of furniture manufacturers, including the [[Baldwin Piano Company]], were subcontracted to build components for the aircraft, which would be assembled at Curtiss-Wright's new defense plant in [[Louisville, Kentucky]].&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot;/&gt;

A [[radial engine]] was mounted on each wing, and the aircraft was capable of carrying 23 personnel or a cargo payload. The Caravan had a nose section that swung out to the right to enable outsize loading, including a jeep or small artillery pieces.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Jt8DAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA21&amp;dq=popular+mechanics+July+1932+airplane&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=IoAZTePWB-DRnAe63OjPDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwBDg8#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true &quot;Army In Long Pants&quot;] ''Popular Mechanics, July 1944'' - bottom of page 21 photo showing front nose opened for loading&lt;/ref&gt;

The original contract called for 11 YC-76 preproduction aircraft, and the first aircraft would be built and tested at Curtiss-Wright's [[St. Louis, Missouri]] Division plant.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOR&quot;/&gt; Subsequently, orders for five C-76 production aircraft and nine revised YC-76As were placed by the USAAF, with line production to commence at the Curtiss-Wright plant in Louisville as well as a [[Higgins Aircraft]] factory in [[New Orleans, Louisiana]].&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOR&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BUR&quot;&gt;Burck, Gilbert, ''Mr. Higgins and His Wonderful Boats'', Life Magazine, 16 August 1943, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; To keep the plywood flexible during construction the factory was kept hot and damp.&lt;ref name=&quot;CURC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aeroweb.brooklyn.cuny.edu/specs/curtiss/c-76.htm|title=Aircraft: Curtiss C-76 Caravan|work=cuny.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[prototype]] YC-76 first flew on May 1, 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOR&quot;/&gt;

Only five production aircraft were completed in 1943: three from Curtiss-Wright's St. Louis Division, and two from a new plant at Louisville, Kentucky, which was finished in May 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOR&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CURC&quot;/&gt; The Higgins Aircraft Co. contract was cancelled by the Army on August 3, 1943 before the Higgins factory in New Orleans had been completed, and Higgins was awarded another contract to produce the [[C-46 Commando]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BUR&quot;/&gt;

==Operational history==
[[File:Curtiss C-76 on ground.jpg|thumb|right|The YC-76]]

The first flight of the YC-76 prototype took place on 3 May 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;/&gt; The C-76 proved severely underpowered from the start, with a cruising speed of {{convert|160|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, a service ceiling of {{convert|22600|ft|m|-2}}, a range of only {{convert|750|mi|km|abbr=on}}, and a cargo capacity of under {{convert|8000|lb|kg|abbr=on}}. Colonel J.W. Sessums, a USAAF officer at the Air Materiel Command at Wright Field, later related:

{{quote|'The first flight [of the C-76] was made and the airplane was very heavy. It developed some serious vibrations. In fact, the pilot was awful glad to make a quick circuit to get back on the ground&amp;nbsp;... two of the Curtiss test pilots took it out on a flight and the Army requested that our project officer on the airplane be allowed to fly along on this trip. The Curtiss Company refused. We were very glad that they refused because on this second flight, it [the C-76] flew apart and the pilots were lost and so was the plane.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot; /&gt;}}

Compared to other cargo aircraft then coming into service, the C-76 was already obsolescent, even allowing for its war-priority method of construction. In addition, the C-76 failed a number of critical flight tests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-3&quot;&gt;Mansfield, Howard, ''Skylark: The Life, Lies, and Inventions of Harry Atwood'', UPNE (1999) ISBN 0-87451-891-1, ISBN 978-0-87451-891-7, pp. 204-205&lt;/ref&gt; It was discovered in testing that the C-76 was unstable when not carrying a cargo load; in order to obtain a stable center of gravity, the plane had to be ballasted beyond its maximum permissible gross takeoff weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-3&quot;/&gt; At any speed, or in any gusting wind, the C-76's elevators would flap back and forth violently.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-3&quot;/&gt; The wing structure failed in eight separate static tests, sometimes with a load as low as 40% of the wing's rated capacity.&lt;ref&gt;Curtiss-Wright Corporate Records, ''Static Tests of Curtiss-Wright C-76 Wings'', ENG-51-C359-10, 7/24/43&lt;/ref&gt; The wing failures were attributed by some sources to the failure of the fasteners used to secure the wood components of the aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-4&quot;&gt;[http://aeroweb.brooklyn.cuny.edu/specs/curtiss/c-76.htm Aviation Enthusiast Corner, ''Curtiss C-76 Caravan'']&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous additional fasteners, metal stirrups, and wood ply reinforcements were added to the structure in an effort to strengthen it, thereby increasing the plane's overall weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-3&quot;/&gt;

At the Louisville plant, Curtiss line workers would later recall two C-76 production planes that were kept for some time in the assembly building, with one plane cannibalized to keep the other in flyable condition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-4&quot;/&gt; On 10 May 1943, the first YC-76 constructed at the [[Louisville, Kentucky]] plant, ''43-86918'', lost its tail unit at due to lack of forgotten securing bolts during test flight, crashing at [[Okolona, Kentucky]], killing three [[Curtiss-Wright]] test crew, pilot Ed Schubinger, co-pilot John L. &quot;Duke&quot; Trowbridge, and engineer Robert G. Scudder.&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-5&quot;&gt;Boyne, Walt, &quot;''C-46 [sic]: 'The Basketcase Bummer' ''&quot; Airpower, Granada Hills, California, May 1974, Volume 4, Number 3, page 64.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A[http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/VII/AAF-VII-1.html rmy Air Forces in World War II, Vol. VII]&lt;/ref&gt; As war priority measures designed to increase aluminum production proved successful, the feared shortage of light alloys never materialized.&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;/&gt; Moreover, USAAF Training Command had begun to forward widespread complaints of insufficient service life on their wooden-winged [[Fairchild PT-19]] primary trainers when exposed to high heat in training bases located in Texas and Florida.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot;/&gt;

The War Department cancelled its orders for the C-76 on 3 August 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;News Article, ''New York Times'', August 4, 1943, October 17, 1943&lt;/ref&gt; The Sara Clark Collection, National Archives, Record Group 342, Box 2719, document the disposition of the 25 YC-76 aircraft as Articles #1, #3, # 4, and #5 were placed in the &quot;Z&quot; category, ZC-76, due to the poor gluing conditions and assembly procedures by subcontractors found through a Material Division inspection of the subcontractors work. These aircraft were assigned to the Technical Training Command and used for ground purposes only. Article #2 was destroyed in static testing at Wright Field. Article #6 was lost in a crash. Article #9 was under repair, but repairs were stopped and the airplane placed in Class 26, non-operational status. Air Service Command operated 12 YC-76s on a service test basis for nine months and found that they required excessive man hours to maintain. It was suggested that these be placed into Class 26 or Survey.

The final disposition of the aircraft as of 1 October 1945, by letter of the Air Technical Service Command; 1-Washout upon delivery from factory, 5-Class 26, 10-Survey, 1-Condemned, 8-Reconstruction Finance Corp. to be sold as surplus. In the interim, the Curtiss-Wright plants at [[Buffalo, New York]] and Louisville, Kentucky went over to full production of the [[Curtiss C-46 Commando]].&lt;ref name=&quot;KLE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.faqs.org/docs/air/avc46.html|title=The Curtiss C-46 Commando|work=faqs.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;News Article, ''New York Times'', August 11, 1944&lt;/ref&gt; USAAF Materiel Command later estimated the entire C-76 project cost the U.S. government $400 million dollars and several months in lost production time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot;/&gt;

==Variants==
;YC-76
:Prototypes, 11 built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrade&quot;&gt;Andrade 1979, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;
;C-76
:Production aircraft built  at St Louis, five built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrade&quot;/&gt;
;YC-76A
:Production variant, nine built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrade&quot;/&gt;
;C-76A
:Production variant, order for 175 cancelled, none built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Andrade&quot;/&gt;

==Specification==
{{aircraft specifications
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=prop
|crew=one-two
|capacity=23 total
|length main=68.33 ft
|length alt=20.83 m
|span main=108.17 ft
|span alt=32.97 m
|height main=27.25 ft
|height alt=8.31 m
|area main=1560.05 ft²
|area alt=144.93 m²
|airfoil=
|empty weight main= 18262 lb
|empty weight alt=8301 kg
|max takeoff weight main=28000 lb
|max takeoff weight alt=12701 kg
|engine (prop)= [[Pratt &amp; Whitney R-1830-92 Twin Wasp]]
|type of prop= radial piston engines
|number of props= 2
|power main=1200 hp
|power alt=895 kW
|cruise speed main=160 mph
|cruise speed alt=260 km/h
|max speed main=192 mph
|max speed alt=309 km/h
|range main=750 mi
|range alt=1207 km
|ceiling main=22,600 ft
|ceiling alt=6,888 m
|climb rate main=
|climb rate alt=
}}

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Air Force|Aviation}}
{{aircontent
|related=
|similar aircraft=
|lists=
*[[List of military aircraft of the United States]]
|see also=
}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last= Andrade |first= John |title= U.S.Military Aircraft Designations and Serials since 1909|year=1979 |publisher=Midland Counties Publications|isbn= 0-904597-22-9}}
*{{cite book |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title= The [[Illustrated Encyclopedia of Aircraft]] (Part Work 1982-1985)|year= |publisher= Orbis Publishing|location= |issn=}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat-inline|Curtiss-Wright C-76 Caravan}}

{{Curtiss-Wright aircraft}}
{{USAF transports}}

[[Category:Curtiss aircraft|C-076]]
[[Category:United States military transport aircraft 1940–1949|Curtiss-Wright C-076 Caravan]]
[[Category:Twin-engined tractor aircraft]]
[[Category:High-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:World War II transport aircraft of the United States|Curtiss-Wright C-76 Caravan]]</text>
      <sha1>on7dq95e0vtoqpqmm45s7fexz6olpgi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
