<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Deptford Dockyard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25443032</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747252132</id>
      <parentid>721132320</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-01T09:55:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Navops47</username>
        <id>13734639</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26592">[[File:Deptford Dockyard - Joseph Farington.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Deptford Dockyard painted in the late-eighteenth/early-nineteenth century by [[Joseph Farington]]]]
[[File:St Albans Deptford.jpg|thumb|right|{{HMS|St Albans|1747|6}}, being launched onto the Thames at Deptford in 1747, depicted by [[John Cleveley the Elder]]]]
'''Deptford Dockyard''' was an important [[Royal Navy Dockyard|naval dockyard]] and base at [[Deptford]] on the [[River Thames]], in what is now the [[London Borough of Lewisham]], operated by the [[Royal Navy]] from the sixteenth to the nineteenth centuries. It built and maintained warships for 350 years, and many significant events and ships have been associated with it.

Founded by [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] in 1513, the dockyard was the most significant royal dockyard of the [[Tudor period]] and remained one of the principal naval yards for three hundred years. Important new technological and organisational developments were trialled here, and Deptford came to be associated with the great mariners of the time, including [[Francis Drake]] and [[Walter Raleigh]]. The yard expanded rapidly throughout the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, encompassing a large area and serving for a time as the headquarters of naval administration, and became the [[Victualling Board]]'s main depot. Tsar [[Peter the Great]] visited the yard officially incognito in 1698 to learn shipbuilding techniques. Reaching its zenith in the eighteenth century, it built and refitted exploration ships used by [[James Cook|Cook]], [[George Vancouver|Vancouver]] and [[William Bligh|Bligh]], and warships which fought under [[Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson|Nelson]].

The dockyard declined in importance after the [[Napoleonic Wars]]. Its location upriver on the [[River Thames|Thames]] made access difficult, and the shallow narrow river hampered navigation of the large new warships. The dockyard was largely inactive after 1830, and though shipbuilding briefly returned in the 1840s the navy closed the yard in 1869. The victualling yard that had been established in the 1740s continued in use until the 1960s, while the land used by the dockyard was sold, the area now being known as [[Convoys Wharf]].

==Foundation==
The Deptford area had been used to build royal ships since the early fifteenth century, during the reign of [[Henry V of England|Henry V]]. Moves were made to improve the administration and operation of the [[Royal Navy]] during the [[Tudor period]], and [[Henry VII of England|Henry VII]] founded the [[HMNB Portsmouth|first royal dockyard]] at [[Portsmouth]] in 1496.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Orser|title=Encyclopedia of Historical Archaeology|page=166}}&lt;/ref&gt; Henry's son, [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] furthered his father's expansion plans, but preferred locations along the Thames to south coast ports, and established [[Woolwich Dockyard]], followed by a dockyard at Deptford in 1513.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LLR180&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Talling|title=London's Lost Rivers|page=180}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Tudor dockyard==
[[File:Deptford Strond.jpg|thumb|right|The Deptford area on a map owned in 1623 by [[John Evelyn]], a resident of the area. Evelyn's house, [[Sayes Court]], is at the bottom left. Above it is marked the &quot;The K's Ship Yard&quot;, the location of the expanding Deptford Dockyard.]]
The dockyard initially consisted of little more than a [[dry dock]] and a storehouse, with a pond being converted into a basin in 1517 to provide mooring for several of the King's ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt; More storehouses were built between 1513 and 1514 at Deptford and further down the Thames at [[Erith]], in order to service the navy's needs in the [[War of the League of Cambrai]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SS222&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=222}}&lt;/ref&gt; The basin converted from the pond in 1517 was divided into three parts, covering a total of eight acres, and deep enough to take a 1000-ton ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;SS223&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=223}}&lt;/ref&gt; The physical expansion of Deptford at this time was reflected in the increasing development and sophistication of naval administration, and with the creation of the antecedent of the [[Navy Board]] in the mid-sixteenth century, a new house was built at Deptford for the &quot;officers' clerks of the Admiralty&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;SS226&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=226}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The dockyard grew to be the most important of the royal dockyards, employing increasing numbers of workers, and expanding to incorporate new storehouses.&lt;ref name=&quot;SS231&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=231}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its importance meant that it was visited on occasion by the monarch to inspect new ships building there. This was reflected in the expenditure of £88 by the [[Treasurer of the Navy]] in 1550 in order to pay for Deptford High Street to be paved, as the road was &quot;previously so noisome and full of filth that the King's Majesty might not pass to and fro to see the building of his Highness's ships.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SS231&quot;/&gt;

The dock was rebuilt and wharves expanded to cover 500–600 feet of the river front by the end of the sixteenth century. It had by then become known as the &quot;King's Yard&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt; Deptford became increasingly sophisticated in its operations, with £150 paid in 1578 to build gates for the dry dock, removing the necessity of constructing a temporary earth dockhead and then digging it away to free the ship once work had been completed.&lt;ref name=&quot;SS335&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=335}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref label|A|a|none}}

The significance of Deptford to English maritime strength was highlighted when [[Elizabeth I of England|Elizabeth I]] knighted [[Francis Drake]] at the dockyard in 1581 after his circumnavigation of the globe aboard the ''[[Golden Hind]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;LLR182&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Talling|title=London's Lost Rivers|page=182}}&lt;/ref&gt; She ordered that the ''Golden Hind'' be moored in [[Deptford Creek]] for public exhibition, where the ship remained until the 1660s before rotting away and being broken up.&lt;ref name=&quot;LLR182&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA167&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Orser|title=Encyclopedia of Historical Archaeology|page=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dockyard is one of the locations associated with the story of [[Walter Raleigh|Sir Walter Raleigh]] laying his cloak before Elizabeth's feet.&lt;ref name=&quot;SE&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=|title=Summer Excursions in Kent|page=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deptford's significant role during this and later periods resulted in it being termed the &quot;Cradle of the Navy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA167&quot;/&gt;

==Expansion==
[[File:John Cleveley the Elder, The Royal George at Deptford Showing the Launch of The Cambridge (1757).jpg|thumb|left|The yard in its heyday. The launch of the 80-gun {{HMS|Cambridge|1755|6}} in 1755, depicted by John Cleveley the Elder. In the foreground a [[first rate]] warship rides at anchor, and in the centre background another warship nears completion.]]
The growth of other shipyards, particularly [[Chatham Dockyard]] on the [[River Medway]], eventually threatened Deptford's supremacy, and by the early seventeenth century the possibility of closing and selling Deptford yard was being discussed. Though Deptford and Woolwich possessed the only working docks, the Thames was too narrow, shallow and heavily used and the London dockyards too far from the sea to make it an attractive anchorage for the growing navy.&lt;ref name=&quot;SS336&quot;/&gt; Attention shifted to the Medway and defences and facilities were constructed at Chatham and [[Sheerness]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SS336&quot;/&gt;

Despite this, Deptford Dockyard continued to flourish and expand, being closely associated with the [[Pett dynasty]], which produced several master shipwrights during the late sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kemp240&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor=Kemp|title=The Oxford Companion to Ships and the Sea|page=240}}&lt;/ref&gt; A commission in the navy in the 1620s decided to concentrate construction at Deptford. The commission ordered the construction of six [[great ship]]s, three middling ships and one small ship, all from Andrew Borrell at Deptford, at a delivery rate of two a year for five years.&lt;ref name=&quot;SotL14&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lavery|title=The Ship of the Line|page=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the seventeenth century the yard covered a large area and included large numbers of storehouses, [[slipway]]s, [[Forge|smiths]], and other maintenance facilities and workshops.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SS370&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=370}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Great Dock was lengthened and enlarged in 1610, several slipways were remodelled and in 1620 a second dry dock was built, with a third being authorised in 1623.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SS377&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=377}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There was further investment in the [[Commonwealth of England|Commonwealth]] period, with money spent on providing a mast dock and three new wharves.&lt;ref name=&quot;CO46&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Command of the Ocean|page=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The yard was visited by [[Peter the Great]], Tsar of Russia, in 1698. He stayed in nearby [[Sayes Court]], which had been temporarily let furnished by [[John Evelyn]] to Admiral [[John Benbow]]. During the Tsar's stay, Evelyn's servant wrote to him to report &quot;There is a house full of people and right nasty. The Tsar lies next your library, and dines in the parlour next your study. He dines at ten o'clock and at six at night, is very seldom at home a whole day, very often in the King's Yard or by water, dressed in several dresses.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Browning 109&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Browning|title=Peter the Great|pages=108–9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peter studied shipbuilding techniques and practices at the dockyard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kemp241&quot;/&gt;{{Ref label|B|b|none}}
[[File:HMSBuckingham.jpg|thumb|right|A ship on the stocks at Deptford, possibly the 70-gun {{HMS|Buckingham|1751|6}}, a [[third rate]] of the [[1745 Establishment]]]]
With the increasing specialisation among the royal dockyards, Deptford concentrated on building smaller warships and was the headquarters of the [[Transport Board (Royal Navy)|naval transport service]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CO297&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Command of the Ocean|page=297}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the various wars of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, the navy sought to relieve pressure on the main fleet bases by concentrating shipbuilding and fitting out at riverine docks like Chatham, Woolwich and Deptford, leaving the front-line dockyards at Portsmouth, Plymouth and the Nore for maintenance and repair.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB124&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor=Lavery|title=The Line of Battle|page=124}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 1790s Deptford had five slipways for building warships, and by 1807 was also served by one [[sheer hulk]] based at the yard.&lt;ref name=&quot;NN224&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lavery|title=Nelson's Navy|page=224}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deptford was associated with a large number of famous ships and people. Several of the ships used by [[James Cook]] on his voyages of exploration were refitted at the dockyard, including {{HMS|Endeavour}}, {{HMS|Resolution|1771|6}} and {{HMS|Discovery|1774|6}}, as were ships used by [[George Vancouver]] on his [[Vancouver Expedition|expedition between 1791 and 1795]], {{HMS|Discovery|1789|6}} and {{HMS|Chatham|1788|6}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winfield366-8&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Winfield|title=British Warships in the Age of Sail 1714–1792|pages=366–8}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{HMS|Bounty}} was refitted at the yard in 1787, as was {{HMS|Providence|1791|6}}, the vessel used by [[William Bligh]] on his second breadfruit expedition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winfield366-8&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paine&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Paine|title=Warships of the World to 1900|page=23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Warships built at the yard include {{HMS|Neptune|1797|6}} and {{HMS|Colossus|1803|6}}, which fought under [[Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson|Nelson]] at the [[Battle of Trafalgar]], and {{HMS|Swiftsure|1787|6}}, which was captured in 1801 and fought for the French at the battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winfieldv&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Winfield|title=British Warships in the Age of Sail 1793–1817|pages=26, 39 &amp; 52}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Victualling Yard==
[[File:Royal Navy victualling yard, Deptford - geograph.org.uk - 79082.jpg|thumb|right|The surviving gates of the former Victualling Yard]]
Dockyard facilities were also used to resupply and victual the navy's warships; Deptford's Victualling Yard was founded upstream of the main dockyard: the [[Victualling Board]] leased the Red House estate in 1743 and established its main depot at Deptford, embarking on the construction of stores and mills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kemp240&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NN25&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lavery|title=Nelson's Navy|page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CO306&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Command of the Ocean|page=306}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref label|C|c|none}} In time, the two yards became physically merged as the dockyard expanded in the victualling yard, both being enclosed by a wall.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt; Deptford's proximity to the food markets of London made it especially convenient for victualling, and it serviced the requirements not only of its own neighbouring Dockyard, but those of [[Woolwich Dockyard|Woolwich]], [[Sheerness Dockyard|Sheerness]] and [[Chatham Dockyard|Chatham]] as well. In 1858 it was renamed the Royal Victoria Victualling Yard, following similar re-brandings in [[Royal William Victualling Yard|Plymouth]], [[Portsmouth Royal Dockyard|Portsmouth]] and [[Haulbowline|Ireland]].

==Decline==
The end of the [[Napoleonic Wars]] and the long period of relative peace that followed caused a decline in both the number of new ships demanded by the navy and the number that needed to be repaired and maintained. Deptford's location and the shallow riverine waters exacerbated the problem as work and contracts were moved to other royal dockyards.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt; The yard had its location close to the main navy offices in London in its favour, but the silting of the Thames and the trend towards larger warships made continued naval construction there an unappealing prospect. Engineer [[John Rennie the Elder|John Rennie]] commented of the yard that &lt;blockquote&gt;Ships-of-the-line which are built there cannot as I am informed with propriety be docked and coppered. Jury masts are put into them and they are taken to Woolwich, where they are docked, coppered and rigged, and I have been told of an instance where many weeks elapsed before a fair wind and tide capable of floating a large ship down to Woolwich occurred.&lt;ref name=&quot;NN234&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lavery|title=Nelson's Navy|page=234}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

From 1821 only maintenance work was carried out at Deptford, and from 1830 the workload was reduced further as only shipbreaking was carried out there.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt; The yard was largely shut down between 1830 and 1844, though the navy was reported to have kept a keel laid down in building slip No. 1, in apparent fulfilment of a lease from John Evelyn, who had made it one of the terms that a ship was always to be under construction at the yard.&lt;ref name=&quot;aq&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=|title=The Antiquary|page=205}}&lt;/ref&gt; The navy had to hastily lay a keel down in 1843 when it was discovered that the term was not being adhered to.&lt;ref name=&quot;aq&quot;/&gt; Small-scale warship construction resumed in 1844, but the yard was deemed surplus to requirements and was closed in 1869.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kemp241&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor=Kemp|title=The Oxford Companion to Ships and the Sea|page=241}}&lt;/ref&gt; The screw corvette {{HMS|Druid|1869|6}}, launched on 13 March 1869, was the final ship built there.&lt;ref name=&quot;aq&quot;/&gt; 

The victualling yard continued in operation, dedicated to the manufacture and storage of food, drink, clothing and furniture for the navy, until its closure in 1961.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kemp241&quot;/&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Thamesmead Clocktower.jpg|thumbnail|The clock and cupola from the old Storehouse (1720, demolished 1984) now stand in Thamesmead.]]
{{See|Convoys Wharf}}
The land occupied by the Dockyard was sold after its closure, the area becoming known as [[Convoys Wharf]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aq&quot;/&gt; T. P. Austin paid £70,000 for the land,{{when|date=June 2013}} which was then bought by the [[City of London Corporation]] for £91,500.{{when|date=June 2013}} Slaughterhouses were then constructed on the site.&lt;ref name=&quot;aq&quot;/&gt; A later periodical described how &quot;Deptford Dockyard, dismantled and degraded from its olden service to the Navy, has just been converted into a foreign cattle market and a shambles.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aq&quot;/&gt; The area's use as a Cattle Market continued until 1913; thereafter it was used as an army depot and then as warehouse space.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pevsner 2002&quot;&gt;Pevsner, The Buildings of England - London 2: South (Yale University Press, 1983 &amp; 2002).&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980 the site was acquired by [[News International]] for the importing and storing of paper products; 28 years later they vacated the site, which now awaits redevelopment as a residential complex.

Many of the Royal Dockyard's buildings, facilities and features have been lost or destroyed since its closure, and its waterways infilled. Henry VIII's Great Storehouse of 1513 was demolished in 1954 (its bricks were used for repairs to [[Hampton Court Palace]]); and demolition of the adjacent eighteenth-century Storehouse buildings followed likewise in 1984.{{Ref label|D|d|none}} A few buildings have survived, however, most notably the Master Shipwright's House of 1708 (built by Joseph Allin), the nearby Office Building of 1720 and (from a late period of the dockyard's existence) the prominent Olympia Warehouse of 1846. (This building, of distinctive iron construction, was originally a double shed, built over dual slipways alongside the main Basin to enable shipbuilding to take place under cover). Moreover, remains of many of the yard's core features, including the slipways, dry docks, basins, mast ponds and building foundations, still exist below ground level and have been studied in archaeological digs.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHA166&quot;/&gt; The subterranean remains of the Tudor Great Storehouse are now a [[Scheduled Ancient Monument]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://list.english-heritage.org.uk/resultsingle.aspx?uid=1021239 English Heritage listing information]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Deptford Strand - geograph.org.uk - 197080.jpg|thumbnail|left|Riverside frontage of the old Royal Victoria Victualling Yard (since converted into  flats).]]
The adjacent former Victualling Yard remained in Navy hands for almost a century after the closure of the dockyard.  A number of its buildings and other features can still be seen (in and around the Pepys Estate) all dating from the 1770-80s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pevsner 2002&quot;/&gt; These include the gateway on Grove Street, the 'Colonnade' behind it (a series of houses fronted by a colonnaded passageway), the terrace of houses on Longshore, and the two former Rum Warehouses on the riverbank. The surrounding housing estate was built after the closure if the yard in the early 1960s, and the surviving naval buildings were converted at the same time to provide housing and community facilities.

===The Lenox Project===
In 2013 the Lenox Project put forward a formal proposal to build a full-size sailing [[Ship replica|replica]] of [[HMS Lenox (1678)|HMS ''Lenox'']], a 70-gun [[ship of the line]] originally built at Deptford Dockyard in 1678.  The ship would actually be constructed on the dockyard site, and would form the centrepiece of a purpose-built museum which would remain as a permanent part of the development of Convoys Wharf.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://councilmeetings.lewisham.gov.uk/mgAi.aspx?ID=6194
 | title =  Build the Lenox
 | date = 11 July 2013
 | website = councilmeetings.lewisham.gov.uk
 | publisher =  Lewisham Borough Council
 | access-date = 19 May 2016
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By late 2015 the project had gathered momentum, with more detailed plans fitting the building of the ''Lenox'' into the overall development of this part of Deptford.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.buildthelenox.org/new-lenox-brochure-published/
 | title =  The Lenox Project: a lasting legacy for Deptford
 | date = 3 December 2015
 | website =  www.buildthelenox.org
 | publisher =   The Lenox Project
 | access-date = 19 May 2016
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The 2015 Feasibility Study identified the Safeguarded Wharf at the Western end of the Convoys Wharf site as the most suitable place for the dry-dock where the ship herself would be built; the existing but disused canal entrance could then be modified to provide an entrance for the dock as well as a home berth for the finished ship. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.buildthelenox.org/feasibility-study-report-published-by-gla
 | title =  Feasibility study report published by GLA
 | date =  8 January 2016
 | website =  www.buildthelenox.org
 | publisher =   The Lenox Project
 | access-date = 19 May 2016
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is hoped that the ''Lenox'' will provide a focus for the regeneration of the area as the comparable replica ship ''[[French frigate Hermione (2014)|Hermione]]'' did for [[Rochefort, Charente-Maritime|Rochefort]] in France.

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
'''a.''' {{Note label|A|a|none}} Dry dock gates existed at Chatham and Woolwich by the early part of the seventeenth century. [[Nicholas Rodger]] considers the introduction of dock gates as marking &quot;...the invention of the true dry dock [which was] a very important development. It was to become one of the key technical achievements underpinning English sea power.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SS336&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea|page=336}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first foreign true dry dock, described as 'a l'anglaise', was ordered at by the French at [[Rochefort, Charente-Maritime|Rochefort]] in 1666, nearly a century after the English.&lt;ref name=&quot;SS336&quot;/&gt;

'''b.''' {{Note label|B|b|none}} The unhappy Evelyn was able to convince the [[HM Treasury|Treasury]] to pay him £350 to cover the necessary repair work to his house after the Russians' stay, after a survey of the damage was made by [[Christopher Wren|Sir Christopher Wren]], the [[Office of Works|Surveyor of the King's Works]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Browning 109&quot;/&gt;

'''c.''' {{Note label|C|c|none}} By the 1790s the Victualling Board had its headquarters at [[Somerset House]], together with the Navy and [[Transport Board (Royal Navy)|Transport Board]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;NN24&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lavery|title=Nelson's Navy|page=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''d.''' {{Note label|D|d|none}} Storehouses were required for storage of all the raw materials and goods necessary for building and fitting out a ship. The 1513 Storehouse was a rectangular building of brick construction c.50m x 10m and two stories high. It stood parallel to the river, on the river front, some 40 metres upstream of the (extant) Master Shipwright's House. (Both buildings are visible in Cleveley's painting of HMS St Albans, above.) The original Storehouse was added to, bit by bit over time, and in the early part of the 18th century it became the north range of a quadrangle of Storehouse buildings. This Storehouse complex, with cupola and clock atop the southern range, formed a prominent landmark for ships on this part of the river for over 200 years.
{{refend}}

==Citations==
{{reflist|2}}

==See also==
*[[Convoys Wharf]]

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|title=The Antiquary|location=London|publisher=E.W. Allen|year=1871|volume=1-2}}
*{{cite book|title=Summer Excursions in Kent, Along the Banks of the Rivers Thames and Medway|location=London|publisher=W.S. Orr &amp; Co|year=1847}}
*{{cite book|title=The Oxford Companion to Ships and the Sea|location=Oxford|publisher=Paladin|year=1976|editor=Peter Kemp|isbn=0-586-08308-1}}
*{{cite book|title=The Line of Battle: The Sailing Warship 1650-1840|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|year=1992|editor=Robert Gardiner|isbn=0-85177-561-6}}
*{{cite book|first=Oscar|last=Browning|authorlink=Oscar Browning|title=Peter the Great|publisher=Hutchinson &amp; Co|location=London|year=1898}}
*{{cite book|first=Brian|last=Lavery|authorlink=Brian Lavery|title=Nelson's Navy: The Ships, Men and Organisation 1793-1815|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|year=1989|isbn=0-85177-521-7}}
*{{cite book|first=Brian|last=Lavery|authorlink=Brian Lavery|title=The Ship of the Line: The Development of the Battlefleet 1650-1850|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|year=2003|volume=1|isbn=0-85177-252-8}}
*{{cite book |first=Charles E.|last=Orser|title=Encyclopedia of Historical Archaeology|publisher=Routledge|year=2002|isbn=978-0-415-21544-2}}
*{{cite book |first=Lincoln P.|last=Paine|title=Warships of the World to 1900|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|year=2000|isbn=978-0-395-98414-7}}
*{{cite book|first=Nicholas|last=Rodger|authorlink=Nicholas Rodger|title=The Safeguard of the Sea: A Naval History of Britain 660-1649|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|year=2004|isbn=978-0-14-029724-9}}
*{{cite book|first=Nicholas|last=Rodger|authorlink=Nicholas Rodger|title=The Command of the Ocean: A Naval History of Britain 1649-1815|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|year=2005|isbn=978-0-14-028896-4}}
*{{cite book |first=Paul|last=Talling|title=London's Lost Rivers|publisher=Random House|year=2011|isbn=978-1-84794-597-6}}
*{{cite book | last = Winfield| first = Rif|title = [[British Warships in the Age of Sail|British Warships in the Age of Sail 1714–1792: Design, Construction, Careers and Fates]] | publisher =  Seaforth| year = 2007|isbn=1-86176-295-X}}
*{{cite book |first=Rif|last=Winfield|title=British Warships in the Age of Sail 1793–1817: Design, Construction, Careers and Fates|publisher=Seaforth|location=London|year=2008|isbn=978-1-84415-717-4}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
*[http://list.english-heritage.org.uk/resultsingle.aspx?uid=1021239 Scheduled Ancient Monument listing by English Heritage (includes an overview of the history of the dockyard and detailed description of the Tudor Storehouse in the context of the rest of the site).]

{{coord|51.4865|N|0.0276|W|source:wikidata-and-enwiki-cat-tree_region:GB|display=title}}
{{Royal Navy air stations, bases, depots, dockyards, facilities, installations, shore establishments, training, units}}
[[Category:Port of London]]
[[Category:Shipyards on the River Thames]]
[[Category:Military history of London]]
[[Category:Shipbuilding in London]]
[[Category:London docks]]
[[Category:Royal Navy dockyards in England]]
[[Category:Royal Navy bases in England]]
[[Category:1513 establishments in England]]</text>
      <sha1>bzoky999vvdurcsxbygga2ivzr8t6f6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
