<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dohasan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14904622</id>
    <revision>
      <id>734832427</id>
      <parentid>728074996</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-17T00:06:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EdwardUK</username>
        <id>28516722</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>fixed infobox error</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17135">{{Infobox person
|name            = Dohäsan (Little Bluff)
|image           = Dohason - head chief of the Kiowa - George Catlin.jpg
|caption         = Chief Dohäsan, painted by [[George Catlin]] 1835.
|nationality     = [[Kiowa people|Kiowa]]
|lead            =
|birth_date      = late 1780s to early 1790s
|birth_place     = [[Oklahoma]] or [[Texas]]
|death_date      = 1866
|death_cause     =  
|death_place     = 
|predecessor     = A'date (Former principal chief of the Kiowa)
|successor       =
|native_name     = 
|other names     = Little Mountain&lt;br/&gt;Little Bluff&lt;br/&gt;Top-Of-The-Mountain
|known_for       = Last Undisputed Principal Chief of the Kiowa, warrior, war-chief
|resting_place   = 
|rp_coordinates  = 
|religion        = 
|party           =
|education       =
|spouse          = 
|partner         =
|children        = 
|parents         = 
|relations       = Dohá (father)&lt;br/&gt;Dohäsan (nephew) 
|occupation      = [[Tribal chief|Chief]]
|signature       =
|footnotes       =
}}

'''Dohäsan''', '''Dohosan''', '''Tauhawsin''', '''Tohausen''', or '''Touhason'''&lt;ref name=weagle&gt;{{cite news |first=Beccy|last=Tanner|title=Betty Nixon dies; helped found Mid-America All-Indian Center |url=http://www.kansas.com/2013/02/05/2664089/betty-nixon-dies-helped-found.html |work= [[Wichita Eagle]]  |publisher= |date=2013-02-05 |accessdate=2013-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; (late 1780s to early 1790s &amp;ndash; 1866&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.45.&lt;/ref&gt;) was a prominent [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]].  He was War Chief of the Kata or Arikara band of the [[Kiowa]] Indians, and then Principal Chief of the entire Kiowa Tribe, a position he held for an extraordinary 33 years.  He is best remembered as the last undisputed Principal Chief of the Kiowa people before the Reservation Era, and the battlefield leader of the Plains Tribes in the largest battle ever fought between the Plains tribes and the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;&gt;Mayhall, Mildred ''The Kiowas''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
Dohäsan's name, which was hereditary, has been variously translated as Little Mountain, Little Bluff, or Top-of-the-Mountain. He was the son of a chief named Dohá (Bluff).  Because his name, and the Chieftainship of his band, was hereditary, (though not necessarily father to son) – Dohäsan himself was succeeded by his nephew, rather than one of his sons, and though his father was a chief, it was his uncle who was the hereditary war chief from whom he got his name.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

==Life before becoming Principal Chief==
The Arikara band was so named because of their close trading relationship with the [[Arikara people|Arikaras]] in the upper Missouri valley during the tribe's early recorded history.  Because of their trading relationships with traders from the US, Spain, and the French, the Kiowa, and the Arikara in particular, were well known to European-Americans. Dohäsan was known to traders as early as the late 1820s.  He gained a reputation as a fierce, but tricky, warrior and successful war chief.&lt;ref name=&quot;hto&quot;&gt;
[http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/fdo47 ''DOHASAN''] Handbook of Texas Online&lt;/ref&gt; Dohäsan was a member of the elite warrior society, the [[Koitsenko]].&lt;ref&gt;Greene 92&lt;/ref&gt;

Although his position as Chief of the Arikara band was hereditary, the Principal Chief of the entire [[Kiowa]] people was not a hereditary position.  The elders of all the bands met together and elected the Principal Chief, and he generally held that position the rest of his life.  Dohäsan became principal chief of the Kiowas in the spring of 1833, after the tribe elders and sub-chiefs deposed then-Principal Chief A'date.  This followed [[Cutthroat Gap Massacre|the massacre of A'date's village]] by [[Osage Nation|Osage]]s at Cutthroat Gap, near the head of Otter Creek in what became the [[Indian Territory]] of the Oklahomas. Dohäsan was the last undisputed Principal Chief of the Kiowa Tribe while they were a free people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

==After ascension to Principal Chieftainship==
After A’date was deposed, and Dohäsan arose to become principal Chief of the entire Kiowa people, the [[United States Army]] became acquainted with Dohäsan. The massacre of an entire village of the Kiowa prompted the dragoon expedition of Colonel [[Henry Dodge]] to Western [[Oklahoma]] in the summer of 1834. Dohäsan was among those on hand to greet the colonel and his expedition. Artist [[George Catlin]], who accompanied the expedition, sketched and painted Dohäsan 's portrait. The expedition found Dohäsan to be a friendly and calm in person under peaceful conditions.

{{quote|A very gentlemanly and high minded man, who treated the dragoons and officers with great kindness while in his country. His long hair, which was put up in several large clubs, and ornamented with a great many silver broaches, extended quite down to his knees.”|-George Catlin
}}

The purpose of the expedition was to end the ferocious fighting between the various Plains Tribes, and in May 1837 Dohäsan was one of the principals who signed the Fort Gibson Treaty, by which the United States government sought to end intertribal warfare in Indian Territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hto&quot;/&gt;

Treaties did little to end the Kiowas' frequent raids for horses and other plunder, and it is arguable whether they even slowed the fighting between the tribes. [[Texas]] was basically wide open to joint Kiowa-Comanche raids, and the annual raids into [[Mexico]] became a dreaded part of life in both Mexico proper and its northern states.   In his raids, Dohäsan and his tribesmen and allied [[Comanche]] came to live in the winter in the [[Staked Plains]], especially along the [[Canadian River]] valley and [[Palo Duro Canyon]], which served as a base for both wintering and the annual raids.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hto&quot;/&gt;

At Palo Duro Canyon, on September 17, 1845, he was sketched by Lt. [[James W. Abert]] in his watercolor portfolio. In the summer of 1851 Dohäsan led a war party of the various Kiowa bands, and allied Comanches against the [[Pawnee people|Pawnee]]s near the head of Medicine Lodge Creek in [[Kansas]], killing most of them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

His name again rises in Army records in 1857 when he successfully led his warriors out of an ambush by Mexican soldiers at Hueco Tanks near El Paso Norte in Texas.  The Mexicans had pursued the raiders north out of Mexico, and hoped to eliminate them.  Instead, most of the Mexican troops were killed or wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

The American Government was anxious to keep the Kiowa friendly as the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] beckoned, and in late 1859, as a goodwill gesture, Major [[John Sedgwick]]'s troops gave Dohäsan an old army ambulance wagon along with the usual presents.  When he was unable to master the art of driving a team, Dohäsan had a couple of Kiowa boys ride the harnessed horses as he sat in the driver's seat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

In 1861, when federal authorities threatened to withhold annuity goods and send troops against the Kiowas if they did not cease their raiding, Dohäsan angrily and contemptuously called the &quot;white chief&quot; a fool with the &quot;heart of a woman.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;hto&quot;/&gt;

===First Battle of Adobe Walls===
{{main article|First Battle of Adobe Walls}}

Other than the extraordinary length of his service as Principal Chief, and being the last Principal Chief of the free Kiowa, Dohäsan will be remembered in military history for commanding the Native American forces at the [[First Battle of Adobe Walls]].&lt;ref name=&quot;texasescapes.com&quot;&gt;Trosser, John (2004). &lt;cite&gt; [http://www.texasescapes.com/TexasPanhandleTowns/Adobe-Walls-Texas.htm]&lt;/cite&gt;. &quot;Adobe Walls Texas” September 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first battle of Adobe Walls occurred on November 26, 1864, in the vicinity of Adobe Walls, the ruins of William Bent's abandoned adobe trading post and saloon near the Canadian River in [[Hutchinson County, Texas]]. The battle was one of the largest engagements in terms of numbers between European-Americans and Indians on the Great Plains, and the largest engagement ever between the Comanche and Kiowa and their allies, against the non-Natives. It came about because Gen. [[James H. Carleton]], commander of the military district of New Mexico, decided to punish Comanche and Kiowa attacks on Santa Fe wagon trains.  The Indians saw the wagon trains as trespassers who killed buffalo and other game the Indians needed to survive.&lt;ref name=&quot;texasescapes.com&quot;/&gt;

Col. [[Kit Carson|Christopher (Kit) Carson]], was given command of the First Cavalry, New Mexico Volunteers, and told to proceed and campaign against the winter campgrounds of the Comanches and Kiowas.  This was the second invasion of the heart of the Comancheria, after the Antelope Hills Expedition.  The campgrounds in question were reported to be somewhere on the south side of the Canadian River. On November 10, 1864 Carson started from Fort Bascom with 335 cavalry, and 75 [[Ute Tribe|Ute]] and [[Jicarilla Apache]] scouts.  Those Carson had recruited from [[Lucien Maxwell]]'s ranch near Cimarron, New Mexico. On November 12, 1864, Carson’s force, supplied with two mountain howitzers under the command of Lt. George H. Pettis, twenty-seven wagons, an ambulance, and forty-five days' rations, proceeded down the Canadian River into the Texas Panhandle. Carson had decided to march first to Adobe Walls, which he was familiar with from his employment there by Bent over 20 years earlier.  Inclement weather, including an early snow storm, caused slow progress, and on November 25, 1864, the First Cavalry reached Mule Springs, in Moore County, approximately {{convert|30|mi|km}} west of Adobe Walls. Scouts reported the presence of a large Indian encampment at Adobe Walls, and Carson ordered his cavalry forward, to be followed by the wagons and howitzers.&lt;ref name=&quot;texasescapes.com&quot;/&gt;

Approximately two hours after daybreak on November 26, 1864,  Carson's cavalry attacked a Kiowa village of 150 lodges.  The Chief, Dohäsan, and his people fled, passing the alarm to allied Comanche villages nearby. Marching forward to Adobe Walls, Carson dug in there about 10 AM, using one corner of the ruins for a hospital.  Carson discovered to his dismay that there were numerous villages in the area, including one very large Comanche village.  The total number of Indians opposing Carson are often estimated at 3,000, but it is unlikely that the total manpower of the Comanche, Kiowa, and Kiowa-Apache amounted to more than one-half that number.&lt;ref&gt;Kavanagh, Thomas W. ''The Comanches'' Lincoln: U of NE Press, 1999, pp. 472-473.  In 1869, five years later, the total population of the three tribes was estimated to be 6,565 of which less than one-fourth would be adult males.&lt;/ref&gt;  Whatever their numbers, Carson saw he was outnumbered by the warriors pouring forward to engage him in battle, a much greater force than he had expected.&lt;ref name=Comanche&gt;The Comanches: Lords of the Southern Plains. University of Oklahoma Press. 1952.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dohäsan, assisted by [[Satank]] (Sitting Bear), [[Guipago]] (Lone Wolf) and [[Satanta (White Bear)|Satanta]] (White Bear), led the Kiowas in the first attack.  Fierce fighting developed as the Kiowa, Kiowa Apache, and Comanche warriors repeatedly attacked Carson's position.  Reportedly, Satanta replied to Carson's [[bugler]] with his own bugle calls.  Carson succeeded in repelling the attacks only through his clever use of supporting fire from the twin howitzers.  After six to eight hours of fairly continuous fighting, Carson realized he was beginning to run low on shells for the howitzers, and ammunition in general, and ordered his forces to withdraw. [http://www.juntosociety.com/native/adobewalls.htm]  The angry Indians tried to block his retreat by setting fire to the grass and brush down near the river.  The wily Carson, however, set back-fires and retreated to higher ground, where the twin howitzers continued to hold off the Indians. When twilight came, Carson ordered a group of his scouts to burn the lodges of the first village, which also resulted in the death of the Kiowa-Apache chief, Iron Shirt, when he refused to leave his [[tepee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;trosser&quot;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;[http://www.texasescapes.com/TexasPanhandleTowns/Adobe-Walls-Texas.htm]&lt;/cite&gt;. &quot;Adobe Walls Texas” September 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the fact that Carson was forced to retreat in the face of much more opposition than he had expected, the United States Army declared the First Battle of Adobe Walls a victory. Carson was probably outnumbered 10-1, and his clever use of backfires and the howitzers prevented his being overrun.   As it was, Carson lost 6 dead, 25 wounded, to approximately 50-60 killed among the Indians.   Nothing could obscure the fact however that the Kiowa and their allies had driven the American army from the field.  Dohäsan, probably in his 70's, had commanded the largest force of Plains Indians ever massed against the army, and compelled a force armed with howitzers to retreat and yield the day.&lt;ref name=&quot;texasescapes.com&quot;/&gt;

==Little Arkansas Treaty and death==
{{main article|Little Arkansas Treaty}}

In October 1865 Dohäsan signed the [[Little Arkansas Treaty]], but he vigorously protested confinement to a reservation, declaring that the Kiowas owned all the land from the North Platte River to the upper Texas Panhandle and needed room to roam about. Shortly afterward, in early 1866, he died.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

==Beginning of the reservation era==
As noted earlier, though the chief position in the Kata or Arikara band of the [[Kiowa]] Indians was hereditary, it was not necessarily given from father to son, and in this case, it was not.

Dohäsan's sister's son, Agiati or &quot;Gathering Feathers&quot; inherited his name in 1864.&lt;ref name=g31&gt;Greene, 31&lt;/ref&gt; The younger Dohäsan took part in the remaining battles as the Kiowa struggled to remain a free people. But time was running out, and he was part of the delegation to Washington in 1872, which appealed to the government to allow the Kiowa to remain free.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

Afterward, as the remaining Kiowa went to the reservation, the younger Dohäsan lived with his family in peace on the reservation near Fort Sill until his death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayhall&quot;/&gt;

==Artist and calendar keeper==
Dohäsan was the primary [[winter count|calendar keeper]] among the Kiowa throughout most of the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;Greene, 25&lt;/ref&gt; He added many innovations to Kiowa pictorial art. In his [[winter count]], he added an image for each year's summer [[Sun Dance]]. To painted [[tipi]] designs, Dohäsan introduced images of [[counting coup]]. When he died, his nephew Agiati became a calendar keeper, followed in turn by Agiati's son, [[Silver Horn]] (1860–1940), one of the most prolific of all Kiowa artists.&lt;ref name=&quot;g31&quot;/&gt;

Dohäsen's original calendar is in the collection of the [[Phoebe Hearst Museum of Anthropology]] at the [[University of California at Berkeley]].&lt;ref&gt;Greene and Thornton, 300&lt;/ref&gt; In 1892 the young Dohäsan gave his annual family calendar history, begun by his uncle, the last great principal chief of the Kiowa, to Capt. Hugh L. Scott, who in turn donated it to the [[Smithsonian Institution]].

Dohasan's descendents included his granddaughter, [[Betty Nixon]], who co-founded the [[Mid-America All-Indian Center]] in [[Wichita, Kansas]], in 1976.&lt;ref name=weagle/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography}}
*[[First Battle of Adobe Walls]]
*[[Texas-Indian Wars]]
*[[List of Native American artists]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*Davis, Lucile, [https://books.google.com/books?id=QPv6EdC_jXsC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''The Kiowa of Texas''], New York : PowerKids Press, 2003. {{OCLC|49529816}}
*Greene, Candace S. ''Silver Horn: Master Illustrator of the Kiowas.'' Norman: University of Oklahoma, 2001. ISBN 978-0-8061-3307-2.
*Greene, Candace S. and Russell Thornton, eds. ''The Year the Stars Fell: Lakota Winter Counts at the Smithsonian''. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution, 2007. ISBN 0-8032-2211-4
*Mayhall, Mildred. ''The Kiowas''. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1962.

==Further reading==
*Bial, Raymond. ''Lifeways: The Comanche''. New York: Benchmark Books, 2000.
*Brice, Donaly E. ''The Great Comanche Raid: Boldest Indian Attack on the Texas Republic'' McGowan Book Co. 1987
*John, Elizabeth and A.H. Storms ''Brewed in Other Men's Worlds: The Confrontation of the Indian, Spanish, and French in the Southwest'', 1540-1795. College Station, TX: Texas A&amp;M Press, 1975.

==External links==
*[http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/D/DO005.html Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture - Dohasan]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dohasan}}
[[Category:18th-century births]]
[[Category:1866 deaths]]
[[Category:Native American leaders]]
[[Category:Native American painters]]
[[Category:Native American people of the Indian Wars]]
[[Category:1866 in the United States]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Comanche]]
[[Category:Kiowa people]]
[[Category:Kiowa]]
[[Category:Texas–Indian Wars]]
[[Category:Painters from Oklahoma]]</text>
      <sha1>8fhuxyke2lhgnb5jfmayyme2w7v95ph</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
