<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>English Electric Canberra</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>201787</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749919718</id>
      <parentid>749716549</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T21:33:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bgwhite</username>
        <id>264323</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fix. Broken bracket problem. Do [[Wikipedia:GENFIXES|general fixes]] and cleanup if needed. - using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (12082)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="100524">{{Use British English|date=January 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name= Canberra
  |image= File:Canberra T.4 MOD 45144928.jpg
  |caption= Canberra T.4 ''WJ874'' in 2005. It had been painted in 1999 to represent the first prototype ''VN799'', first flown in 1949.
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type=[[Bomber]]/[[Reconnaissance aircraft|Reconnaissance]]
  |national origin= United Kingdom
  |manufacturer=[[English Electric]]
  |designer = &lt;!-- Only appropriate for one-person designers, not project leaders or chief designers --&gt;
  |first flight=13 May 1949
  |introduced=25 May 1951
  |retired=23 June 2006 (RAF)
  |primary user= [[Royal Air Force]]
  |more users= {{plainlist|
*[[Indian Air Force]]
*[[Peruvian Air Force]]
*[[Royal Australian Air Force]]}}
  |number built= {{plainlist|
*900 (UK)&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p371&quot;/&gt;
*49 (Australia)&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p371&quot;/&gt;
403 (USA)&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p371&quot;/&gt;}}
  |status= Retired from service
  |unit cost=
  |variants with their own articles= [[Martin B-57 Canberra]]
}}
|}
[[File:Canberra.pr9.takeoff.arp.jpg|thumb|Canberra PR9 ''XH135'']]

The '''English Electric Canberra''' is a British first-generation [[Jet engine|jet]]-powered [[medium bomber]] that was manufactured during the 1950s. It was developed by [[English Electric]] during the mid-to-late 1940s in response to a 1944 [[Air Ministry]] requirement for a successor to the wartime [[de Havilland Mosquito]] fast-bomber; amongst the performance requirements for the type was the demand for an outstanding high altitude bombing capability in addition to flying at high speeds, these were partly accomplished by making use of newly developed jet propulsion technology. When the Canberra was introduced to service with the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF), the type's first operator, in May 1951, it became the service's first jet-powered bomber aircraft.

Throughout the majority of the 1950s, the Canberra could fly at a higher [[altitude]] than any other bomber or even any other aircraft in the world. In 1957, one Canberra established a [[Flight altitude record|world altitude record]] of 70,310&amp;nbsp;ft (21,430&amp;nbsp;m). In February 1951, another Canberra set another world record when it became the first jet aircraft to make a non-stop [[transatlantic flight]]. Due to its ability to evade the early [[Jet aircraft|jet]] [[Interceptor aircraft|interceptor]] aircraft and its significant performance advancement over contemporary [[Reciprocating engine|piston]]-engined bombers, the Canberra became a popular aircraft on the export market, being procured for service in the [[air force]]s of many nations both inside and outside of the [[Commonwealth of Nations]]. The type was also [[Licensed production|licence produced]] in [[Australia]] and the [[United States of America]], the latter building it as the [[Martin B-57 Canberra]].

In addition to being a tactical [[Nuclear warfare|nuclear strike]] aircraft, the Canberra proved to be highly adaptable, serving in varied roles such as [[tactical bombing]] and [[Imagery intelligence|photographic]] and [[Electronic intelligence|electronic]] [[Reconnaissance aircraft|reconnaissance]]. Canberras served in the [[Suez Crisis]], the [[Vietnam War]], the [[Falklands War]], the [[Indo-Pakistani wars and conflicts|Indo-Pakistani wars]], and numerous African conflicts. In several [[war]]s, each of the opposing sides had Canberras in their air forces. The Canberra had a lengthy service life, serving for more than 50 years with some operators. In June 2006, the RAF retired the last of its Canberras, 57 years after its first flight. Three of the [[Martin B-57 Canberra|Martin B-57]] variant remain in service, performing [[Meteorology|meteorological]] work for [[NASA]], as well as providing electronic communication (Battlefield Airborne Communications Node or BACN) testing for deployment to [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref&gt;Cenciotti, David. [http://theaviationist.com/2012/09/04/wb-57-bacn-miramar/ &quot;NASA's WB-57 Battlefield Airborne Communication Node gets new sensors, paint scheme for more clandestine missions.&quot;] ''The Aviationist,'' 4 September 2012. Retrieved: 14 September 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bacon&gt;Axe, David. [http://www.wired.com/dangerroom/2012/09/air-force-universal-translator/ &quot;America's Most Important Warplane Is Old, Ugly&amp;nbsp;... and Flown by NASA.&quot;]  ''wired.com,'' 10 September 2012. Retrieved: 14 September 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==

===Background===
During the [[World War II|Second World War]], a desperate demand for bomber aircraft led to many aircraft being produced by secondary manufacturers via [[Licensed production|licence manufacturing]] arrangements. The [[English Electric]] company mass-produced thousands of [[piston engine|piston-powered]] bombers, such as the [[Handley Page Hampden]] and [[Handley Page Halifax]], in this manner and the firm thus became a well-established British aircraft manufacturer despite having little internal design experience.&lt;ref name = 'law 66'&gt;Law 2002, p. v66.&lt;/ref&gt; [[George Nelson, 1st Baron Nelson of Stafford|Sir George Nelson]], the chairman of English Electric, decided that the company would seek to remain in the business and produce its own designs. In November 1943, the company was invited to participate in discussions over a prospective bomber which would take advantage of the newly developed [[jet propulsion]] technology.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 53&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1944, [[Westland Aircraft]]'s technical director and chief designer [[W. E. W. Petter]] had prepared a design study for a twin-engined fighter bomber, the P.1056, based on two fuselage-mounted [[Metropolitan-Vickers F.2|Metrovick F.2/4 &quot;Beryl&quot;]] engines. The design used a relatively conventional aerodynamic design, Petter having determined that the necessary performance could be attained without adopting [[swept wing]]s or a swept tail.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; The authorities doubted its suitability for operations from unprepared fields and at low altitude but could see its potential as a bomber design; numerous manufacturers refused to take on the design.&lt;ref&gt;Buttler 2004, p.&amp;nbsp;213.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = 'petter 52-3'/&gt; Petter left Westland to join the English Electric company in December 1944, where he was appointed by Nelson to form a design team and encouraged to develop his design.&lt;ref name = 'petter 52-3'&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, pp.&amp;nbsp;52–53.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1945, English Electric formalised its own in-house aircraft design team to pursuit this design.&lt;ref name = 'law 66'/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 53&quot;/&gt;

The Canberra had its formal origins in a 1944 requirement issued by the [[Air Ministry]] for a successor to the [[de Havilland Mosquito]]. This requirement, the initial revision being [[List of Air Ministry specifications|E.3/45]], sought a [[high altitude]], [[high-speed flight|high-speed]] [[bomber]] which was to be equipped with no defensive armament. According to aviation historians Bull Gunston and Peter Gilchrist, Air Ministry officials are alleged to have had difficulty defining what they sought for the proposed type, which led to several revisions of the requirement.&lt;ref&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, pp. 53-54.&lt;/ref&gt; Further specification refinements were issued, including B.3/45 and B.5/47, issued further details such as a three-man crew and other features such as a visual bombing capability. Several British aircraft manufacturers submitted proposals to meet the requirement, including English Electric. The firm was among those companies to be [[short-listed]] to proceed with development studies.&lt;ref name = 'law 66'/&gt;

By June 1945, the aircraft that was to become the Canberra bore many similarities to the eventual design, despite the placement of a single, centrally mounted turbojet engine; Petter had held discussions with [[Rolls-Royce Ltd]] on the topic of the development of a scaled-up derivative of the [[Rolls-Royce Nene|Nene]] engine.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;/&gt; In late 1945, the design was modified further with a pair of engines being adopted instead, initially to be set in the wing roots and later to be mounted in a mid-wing position; this change was made principally due to [[centre of gravity]] issues imposed by the position and weight of a heavy bombload and centrally-mounted single engine.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;walker 758&quot;&gt;Walker 8 May 1969, p. 758.&lt;/ref&gt; The new engine position decreased the aircraft's weight by 13 per cent and improved the aircraft's center of gravity, as well as improved accessibility to the engines and related accessories, downsides were slightly elevated losses in the longer jet pipes and greater [[yaw (rotation)|yaw]] during engine-out instances.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;/&gt;

During the early design stages, the aircraft had grown from being roughly the same size as the Mosquito to being around double its weight.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;/&gt; Although jet-powered, the Canberra design philosophy was very much in the Mosquito mould, providing room for a substantial bomb load, fitting two of the most powerful engines available, and wrapping it in the most compact and aerodynamic package possible. Rather than devote space and weight to defensive armament which historically could not overcome [[fighter aircraft]], the Canberra was designed to fly fast and high enough to avoid air-to-air combat entirely.&lt;ref name = 'polmar 11'&gt;Polmar 2001, p.&amp;nbsp;11.&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 January 1946, the [[Ministry of Supply]] placed a contract for the development and production of four English Electric A.1 aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;walker 759&quot;&gt;Walker 8 May 1969, p. 759.&lt;/ref&gt; It continued to be known as the English Electric A.1 until it was given the name ''[[Canberra]]'' after the capital of [[Australia]] in January 1950 by Sir George Nelson, chairman of English Electric, as Australia had become the aircraft's first export customer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom176&quot;/&gt;

===Prototypes and first flights===
[[File:CanberraVX165.JPG|thumb|alt=The first Canberra B2 prototype, VX165.|The first Canberra B2 prototype, VX165]]

The [[List of Air Ministry specifications|Air Ministry specification]] B.3/45 had requested the production of four prototypes. On 9 January 1946, English Electric received a contract to produce four prototypes, which received the [[Society of British Aerospace Companies]] (SBAC) designation ''A.1''; work commenced on the construction of these prototype aircraft in that same year, which were all built on production jigs.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Flight'' 15 December 1949 p. 766.&lt;/ref&gt; However, progress was slow due to several factors, such as the protracted development of the Avon engine that powered the type; in October 1947, in response to Rolls-Royce's difficulties, English Electric elected to have the second prototype modified to use the existing Nene engine in place of the Avon.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;/&gt; The implementation of post-war military cutbacks also served to slow development.&lt;ref name = &quot;Wings&quot;/&gt;

A further external issue that affected development was the failure of the [[Telecommunications Research Establishment]] to produce the intended [[radar]] bombing system for the aircraft in a timely fashion; this required a redesign in 1947, changing the aircraft's nose to accommodate a glazed tip for visual bombing by a bomb aimer, which was in turn required the cockpit to be restructured to facilitate the ejection system of the additional crewmember.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 56-57&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, pp. 56-57.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1948, the design team relocated to [[Warton Aerodrome]], [[Lancashire]]; establishing a flight test organisation and assembly facilities there.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 54&quot;/&gt;

Ultimately, the first of these prototypes, ''VN799'' did not conduct its [[maiden flight]] until 13 May 1949.&lt;ref name = &quot;Wings&quot;&gt;Halvorson 2009, pp.&amp;nbsp;10–19.&lt;/ref&gt; Piloted by [[Roland Beamont]], the aircraft is claimed to have handled well with the exception of a [[rudder]] overbalance issue encountered. This initial flight was flown with the intended Avon engines, the decision to perform the type's first flight with the Avon-equipped first prototype or the Nene-equipped second prototype, ''VN828'', was not made until weeks beforehand.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 55&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 November 1949, the second prototype, VN828, the first to be equipped with the Nene engine, performed its first flight; the third and fourth followed within the following eight weeks.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 57&quot;/&gt;

Flight testing of the prototypes proved to be vice-free and required only a few modifications to be made. The changes included the installation of a glazed nose to accommodate a bomb-aimer, due to the advanced [[H2S radar|H2S]] Mk9 bombing radar not being ready for production, the turbojet engines that powered the type were replaced by the more powerful [[Rolls-Royce Avon]] R.A.3s, and distinctive teardrop-shaped fuel tanks were fitted under the wingtips.&lt;ref name = &quot;Wings&quot;/&gt; Refinements were also quickly made following early flight testing to the rudder and [[Elevator (aeronautics)|elevator]] to reduce instances of [[Aeroelasticity#Buffeting|buffeting]], after which it is claimed that the Canberra handled much like a fighter, proving to be atypically maneuverable for a bomber.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 56&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

The project had found considerable support from the government in the late 1940s. In March 1949, in advance of the maiden flight of the first prototype, English Electric received an instruction to proceed for production.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 57&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; By the time the first prototype had flown, the Air Ministry had already placed orders for 132 production aircraft in bomber, reconnaissance, and training variants. On 21 April 1950, the first production-standard aircraft, [[British military aircraft designation systems|designated]] as the Canberra B2, conducted its maiden flight, piloted by Beamont. Proving to be fairly free of problems, this first flight was almost immediately followed by the mainstream manufacturing of production Canberras. In May 1951, the Canberra entered RAF squadron service, [[No. 101 Squadron RAF|No. 101 Squadron]] being the first to receive the type.&lt;ref name = &quot;walker 759&quot;/&gt; In a testament to the aircraft's benign handling characteristics, the transition programme for the Canberra consisted of only twenty hours in the Gloster Meteor and three hours in a dual-control Canberra trainer.&lt;ref name=&quot;walker 758 761&quot;/&gt;

===Production and licensed manufacturing===
In July 1949, as English Electric was in the process of setting up production at [[Samlesbury Aerodrome]], a firm order was placed for 132 Canberras; this order consisted of 90 B.5/47 bomber-type aircraft, 34 PR.31/46 photo reconnaissance aircraft, and 8 T.2/49 trainer aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 57&quot;/&gt; On 25 June 1950, what would become known as the [[Korean War]] broke out; this led to a surge of demand for the Canberra and the British government stepping in to establish a far greater level of wartime production. This led to a succession of orders for Canberra B.2s, the initial bomber variant, being placed with [[Avro]], [[Handley Page]], and [[Short Brothers]]; for British needs alone, English Electric produced 196 B.2s, Avro and Handley Page manufactured 75 each, and Short completed 60 aircraft - the B.2 variant of the Canberra exceeded the numbers built of any other version.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes and James 1989, p.&amp;nbsp;508.&lt;/ref&gt; Other nations, notably Australia and the [[United States of America]], also ordered large quantities of Canberras.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 57&quot;/&gt;

[[File:EB-57B 01.jpg|thumb|left|Martin EB-57B]]
In the United States, the [[US Air Force]] had identified the need to replace the obsolete [[Douglas A-26 Invader|B-26 Invader]] and had determined that, at the time, no home-produced aircraft designs could get close to what the Canberra could already offer. Following a competition against rivals such as the [[Martin XB-51]], it was decided to order a total of 403 Canberras. These aircraft were [[Licence-built|manufactured under licence]] by [[Glenn L. Martin Company|Martin]] as the [[Martin B-57 Canberra|B-57 Canberra]], who would develop several versions of the aircraft themselves.&lt;ref name='Don'&gt;Donald 1986, p.&amp;nbsp;18.&lt;/ref&gt; The first examples were the identical to the original English Electric aircraft, following which tandem crew seating was introduced, but later B-57 models were considerably modified.

Australia had been interested in the Canberra early on, which had led to the aircraft being named after the Australian capital city. Particular interest had at one time been expressed in a potential [[Rolls-Royce RB.44 Tay|Rolls-Royce Tay]] powered version of the aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 57&quot;/&gt; The [[Government Aircraft Factories]] (GAF) locally assembled 48 for the [[Royal Australian Air Force]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Wings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name='Don' /&gt; These aircraft were broadly similar to the British B.2. Changes included the adoption of a modified leading edge, increased fuel capacity and room for three [[Coffman engine starter|starter cartridges]], although in practice all three cartridges would sometimes fire, leading to the triple starter units being loaded singly.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Stewart. ''Lincoln, Canberra and F-111 in Australian Service.'' London: Aerospace Publications Pty Ltd., 1989. ISBN 0-9587978-3-8.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Australian built Canberras used a higher proportion of Australian and US sourced components.&lt;ref&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, pp. 57-58.&lt;/ref&gt;

A total of 901 Canberras were manufactured by the various UK based aircraft manufacturers; when combined with overseas license production operations, the overall global production for the Canberras totaled 1,352 aircraft.&lt;ref name='Don'/&gt; With a maximum speed of {{convert|470|kn}}, a standard service ceiling of 48,000&amp;nbsp;ft (14,600&amp;nbsp;m), and the ability to carry a {{Convert|3.6|t|lb|adj=on}} payload, the Canberra proved to be an instant success on the domestic and export markets. It was built in 27 versions that equipped a total of 35 RAF squadrons, and was exported to more than 15 countries, including Australia, Argentina, [[Chile]], [[Ecuador]], [[Ethiopia]], France, India, New Zealand, Pakistan, [[Peru]], [[Rhodesia]], South Africa, Sweden, [[Venezuela]] and West Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;walker 758 761&quot;&gt;Walker 8 May 1969, pp. 758, 760–761.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Photo-reconnaissance and specialised roles===
During the latter part of the Second World War, strategic reconnaissance missions performed by the RAF had been carried out by the de Havilland Mosquito. In 1946, the Air Ministry issued Specification PR.31/46 seeking a jet powered replacement for the Mosquito.&lt;ref name=&quot;pr3&quot;&gt;&quot;Canberra P.R.3.&quot; ''Aeromilitaria,'' ([[Air-Britain]]), Issue 4, 1978, pp. 87–90.&lt;/ref&gt; To meet the requirement, the B2 design was modified by adding a {{Convert|14|in|cm|adj=on}} bay forward of the wing behind the cockpit to house seven cameras.&lt;ref name=&quot;pr3&quot; /&gt; It also had an additional fuel tank in the forward part of the bomb bay and only needed a two-man crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom168&quot;&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;168&lt;/ref&gt; The prototype, designated PR3, first flew on 19 March 1950, followed by the first of 35 production aircraft on 31 July 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;pr3&quot; /&gt; In December 1952, the PR3 entered RAF service, at which point [[No. 540 Squadron RAF]] began converting from its Mosquito PR.34 force.&lt;ref name=&quot;pr3&quot; /&gt; The Canberra PR3 was the first aircraft to be designed for the RAF purely to perform photo reconnaissance missions.&lt;ref name = &quot;walker 759&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Canberra TT18 (16628577520).jpg|thumb|A Canberra TT Mk.18 of the [[Royal Navy]] landing at [[RNAS Yeovilton (HMS Heron)|RNAS Yeovilton]], 1985]]
The initial Canberra PR3 model was shortly succeeded by the improved PR7 variant. The PR7 featured greater fuel capacity via wing storage, the more powerful RA.7 model of the Avon engine, and [[Maxaret]] [[anti-lock braking system]].&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 59&quot;/&gt; The Canberra PR9 was the final photo reconnaissance version; this aircraft was furnished with a new crew compartment, a redesigned inner wing section, and much more powerful RA.24 Avon engine.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 59&quot;/&gt; In later service, bomber models of the Canberra were often converted with cameras and other equipment suited for reconnaissance purposes.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 60&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;

To enable crews to convert to flying the Canberra, a trainer version was developed to meet Air Ministry Specification T2/49.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom161&quot;&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;161.&lt;/ref&gt; On 12 June 1951, the prototype, designated T4, conducted its first flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom173&quot;&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;173.&lt;/ref&gt; It was the same basic design as the B2 apart from the introduction of side by side seating for the pilot and the instructor and the replacement of the glazed nose with a solid nose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom173&quot; /&gt; The first production T4 flew on 20 September 1953 and the variant entered service with [[No. 231 Operational Conversion Unit RAF]] in early 1954.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom176&quot;&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;176.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom179&quot;&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;179&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to those assigned to the operational conversion unit, all of the B2 equipped bomber squadrons received at least one T4 for training purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom179&quot; /&gt;

In addition to the RAF, other users adopted the Canberra in the trainer role. The Indian Air Force (IAF) operated a number of T4 aircraft for conversion training purposes.&lt;ref name = 'Kavic 104'/&gt; The RAAF adopted the Australian built Canberra T21 model, which was broadly similar to the T4.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 58&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; Argentina procured a pair of T64 trainers during the 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huertas p61&quot;/&gt;

From 1960s onwards, increasing numbers of bomber orientated Canberras were deemed surplus as newer, faster ground attack aircraft were introduced; this led to such aircraft being rebuilt to serve in various alternative roles, including unpiloted target aircraft, radar trainers, target tugs, radar calibration aircraft, and [[electronic countermeasures]] trainers.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 59&quot;&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, some Canberras that had originally been manufactured for the high altitude bomber mission were reequipped for low altitude ground attack missions.&lt;ref&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, pp. 59-60.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
[[File:English Electric Canberra B-57 Prototype 061025-F-1234P-002.jpg|thumb|Canberra B2 ''WD940'', 1951]]
The English Electric Canberra is a twin-engine bomber aircraft, capable of conducting high-altitude flights and making use of [[jet propulsion]]. The overall design has been described as being of a simple nature, somewhat resembling a scaled-up [[Gloster Meteor]] fighter, except for its use of a mid-wing.&lt;ref name = 'flight 15 766'/&gt; The Canberra principally differed from its preceding piston-powered wartime bombers via its twin [[Rolls-Royce Avon]] [[turbojet]] engines.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 55&quot;/&gt; The fuselage was circular in cross section, tapered at both ends and, cockpit aside, entirely without protrusions; the line of the large, low-[[aspect ratio (wing)|aspect ratio]] wings was broken only by the tubular engine [[nacelle]]s.&lt;ref name = 'flight 15 766'&gt;''Flight,'' 15 December 1949, p.&amp;nbsp;766.&lt;/ref&gt; The Canberra had a two-man crew under a fighter-style cabin which was furnished with a large blown canopy, but delays in the development of the intended automatic [[radar]] [[bombsight]] resulted in the addition of a bomb aimer's position housed within the nose.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 56&quot;/&gt; The pilot and navigator were positioned in a [[tandem]] arrangement on [[Martin-Baker]] ejection seats.&lt;ref&gt;Gunston and Gilchrist 1993, p. 55-56.&lt;/ref&gt;

The wing is of single-spar construction that passes through the aircraft's fuselage. The wingspan and total length of the Canberra are almost identical at just under 20 metres. Outboard of the engine [[nacelles]], the wing has a [[leading edge]] sweep of 4° and trailing edge sweep of −14°. All [[flight control]]s are manual, using push-rods rather than cables, but are otherwise conventional. These actuate the aircraft's [[flight control surface]]s, including shrouded-nosed [[aileron]]s, four-section conventional split-type [[flap (aeronautics)|flaps]], and atypical [[Air brake (aircraft)|airbrakes]] which comprise 40 [[hydraulics|hydraulically-raised]] fingers located on the top and bottom surfaces of the wings.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 55&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = 'flight 15 full'&gt;''Flight'' 15 December 1949, pp.&amp;nbsp;766–772.&lt;/ref&gt; Swept-wings were considered, but not adopted, since the expected operational speeds did not warrant them and because they could have introduced new aerodynamic problems into what was otherwise anticipated to be a straightforward replacement for RAF [[Hawker Typhoon]] and [[Westland Whirlwind (fighter)|Westland Whirlwind]] fighter-bombers.&lt;ref name = &quot;walker 758&quot;/&gt;

[[File:EE Canberra instument panel, Midland Air Museum. (12780760883).jpg|thumb|left|Instrument panel of a Canberra cockpit, 2006]]
The fuselage of the Canberra is of semi-[[monocoque]] construction with a pressurised nose compartment. The whole lower section of the fuselage is taken up by the sizable bomb bay, which was typically covered by a pair of hydraulically-driven doors.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 56&quot;/&gt; The Canberra's undercarriage used a simple arrangement, the main [[landing gear]] being equipped with a single outboard-mounted wheel and the nose gear being a twin-wheel arrangement.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 56&quot;/&gt; Due to the use of a new alloy, DTD683, the undercarriage suffered from stress corrosion, causing decay to start within only a few years.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford 2001, p.&amp;nbsp;124.&lt;/ref&gt; The extreme hazard posed of undercarriages collapsing during landings, especially if the aircraft were carrying nuclear weapons, led the RAF to institute regular inspections, at first using [[radiography]] before moving to more effective and reliable [[ultrasound]] technology.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford 2001, p.&amp;nbsp;125.&lt;/ref&gt; The Canberra is made up mostly of metal, only the forward portion of the tail-fin is made from wood.&lt;ref&gt;Halpenny 2005, p.&amp;nbsp;59.&lt;/ref&gt;

Thrust was provided by a pair of 30&amp;nbsp;kN axial flow [[Rolls-Royce Avon]] turbojet engines. These were directly mounted in the midsection of the wings using tubular trusses and links between the main mounts and the adjacent leading edge of the wing.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 55&quot;/&gt; Each engine drove a 6-kW generator for the 28-V onboard electronics, as well as a hydraulic pump and a [[bleed air]] system for [[cabin pressurization]]. The wing itself was typically empty, fuel was contained within two internally-support [[self-sealing fuel tank]]s and an additional lace-support bag held within the upper fuselage.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 55&quot;/&gt; The manufacturer specified that [[Coffman engine starter]]s should be used to start the engine. An improvised method of starting the engine using compressed air was heavily discouraged by Rolls-Royce, but some operators successfully operated the Canberra's engines in such a manner, the benefit being significant cost savings over the use of cartridges.&lt;ref&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, pp.&amp;nbsp;95–96.&lt;/ref&gt;

Various avionics were installed on the Canberra, many of these had their origins within the Second World War. Such systems include [[Gee-H (navigation)|Gee-H navigation]], [[Rebecca/Eureka transponding radar|Rebecca beacon-interrogation distance-measuring equipment]], [[very high frequency]] (VHF) [[radio]], [[radio compass]], [[radar altimeter]], [[identification friend or foe]] (IFF), and [[List of Rainbow Codes|Orange Putter]] [[radar warning receiver]].&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 56&quot;/&gt; Perhaps the most crucial of the mission systems was the [[H2S (radar)|HS2]] automatic [[radar]] [[bombsight]], which was mounted in the nose; delays in the development of the HS2 model intended for the Canberra led to early models being fitted with a T.2 [[optical sight]] for visual bombing in its place, which was considerably inferior to the radar-guided counterpart when attacking ground targets while flying at high altitudes.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 56-57&quot;/&gt;

{{Quote box|align=right|width=25%|quote=&quot;The value of the Canberra experience cannot be over-estimated. It is the only modern tactical strike and reconnaissance aircraft in service with the RAF and many other Air Forces. More Canberra aircraft are in service with foreign countries than the Viscount, which holds the record for British civil aircraft. This is due to the flexibility of the Canberra in its operational roles and performance&amp;nbsp;...&quot;|source=&lt;small&gt;Manufacturer's brochure, 1957.&lt;ref&gt;Law 2002, p.&amp;nbsp;68.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;}}

The Canberra could deploy many conventional weapons, typical weapons used were 250-pound, 500-pound, and 1000-pound bombs,&lt;ref&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, p.&amp;nbsp;272.&lt;/ref&gt; the total bomb load could weigh up to {{Convert|10,000|lb|t}}.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Acrobatic Bomber&quot;. ''Popular Mechanics'', 93(3), March 1950, p.&amp;nbsp;105.&lt;/ref&gt; Two bomb-bays are housed within the fuselage, these are normally enclosed by conventional clam-shell doors; a rotating door was substituted for these on the Martin-built B-57 Canberras. Additional stores up to a total of {{Convert|2,000|lb|t}} could be carried upon underwing pylons.&lt;ref name = &quot;walker 760&quot;&gt;Walker 8 May 1969, p. 760.&lt;/ref&gt; Operators often developed and installed their own munitions, such as Rhodesia's anti-personnel bomblets, the ''Alpha bomb'', a varied range of munitions were employed on Canberra fleets around the world.&lt;ref&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, pp.&amp;nbsp;274–276.&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-personnel [[flechette]] bombs were tested successfully from the Canberra by Rhodesia, but not used operationally due to international agreements.&lt;ref&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, p.&amp;nbsp;302.&lt;/ref&gt;

In part due to its range limitation of just {{Convert|2,000|mi|km}}, and its inability to carry the early, bulky nuclear bombs, the Canberra was typically employed in the role of a tactical bomber as opposed to that of a strategic one.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen 1997, p.&amp;nbsp;66.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The inability of the Canberra to perform the nuclear mission led to American [[Boeing B-29 Superfortress]] bombers being loaned to Britain as a stopgap measure until the domestically produced [[V bomber]] trio of medium bombers entered service.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson 1997, p.&amp;nbsp;11.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} In British service, many of the Canberras that were stationed at remote overseas locations did not undertake modifications to become nuclear-capable until as late as 1957.&lt;ref&gt;Hack 2001, p.&amp;nbsp;228.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==

===Royal Air Force===
[[File:Canberrab21024.jpg|thumb|A flight of three RAF Canberra B2s flying in formation during the 1950s]]
The Canberra B2 started to enter service with [[No. 101 Squadron RAF|101 Squadron]] in January 1951, with 101 Squadron being fully equipped by May, and a further squadron, [[No. 9 Squadron RAF|No. 9 Squadron]] equipping by the end of the year. The production of the Canberra was accelerated as a result of the outbreak of the [[Korean War]], orders for the aircraft increased and outpaced production capacity,&lt;ref&gt;Geiger 2004, pp.&amp;nbsp;153, 156.&lt;/ref&gt; as the aircraft was designated as a ''&quot;super priority&quot;''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p370&quot;/&gt; A further five squadrons were able to be equipped with the Canberra by the end of 1952;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p370&quot;&gt;Mason 1994, p.&amp;nbsp;370.&lt;/ref&gt; however, production in the 1951–52 period had only been half of the level planned, due to shortages in skilled manpower, material, and suitable machine tools.&lt;ref&gt;Peden 2007, p.&amp;nbsp;252.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Canberra replaced [[de Havilland Mosquito|Mosquito]]s, [[Avro Lincoln|Lincolns]] and [[Boeing B-29 Superfortress|Washingtons]] as front line bombers, showing a drastically improved performance, and proving to be effectively immune from interception during air defence exercises until the arrival of the [[Hawker Hunter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p370&quot;/&gt; The Canberra also replaced the RAF's Mosquitos in the reconnaissance role, with the Canberra PR3 entering service in December 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIAug06 p40&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' August 2006, p.&amp;nbsp;40.&lt;/ref&gt; The improved Canberra B6, with more powerful engines and a greater fuel capacity, started to supplement the B2s in the UK based squadrons of Bomber Command from June 1954, when they replaced 101 Squadrons B2s. This freed up older B2s to allow Canberra squadrons to form overseas, with bomber and reconnaissance Canberra wings forming in [[RAF Germany]] and on [[Cyprus]], with squadrons also being deployed to the Far East.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIAug06 p40-1,2&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' August 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;40–42.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:E.Electric Canberra PR.3 WE140 540 Sqn LAP 02.06.53 edited-2.jpg|thumb|left|Canberra PR3 of [[No. 540 Squadron RAF]] at London Heathrow in June 1953]]

The PR7 variant of the Canberra, equipped with longer, fuel-filled wings and the Avon 109 engines, executed a 1953 reconnaissance flight over the Soviet rocket launch and development site at [[Kapustin Yar]], although the UK government has never admitted the existence of such a flight. Warned by either radar or agents inside the British government, the Soviets slightly damaged one aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;cia1992&quot;&gt;{{cite book | url=http://www.gwu.edu/sites/www.gwu.edu/files/downloads/U2%20%20history%20complete.pdf | title=The Central Intelligence Agency and Overhead Reconnaissance: The U-2 and OXCART Programs, 1954-1974 | publisher=History Staff, Central Intelligence Agency |author1=Pedlow, Gregory W. |author2=Welzenbach, Donald E. | year=1992 | location=Washington DC | pages=23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spyflight.co.uk/yar.htm &quot;Kapustin Yar.&quot;] ''spyflight.co.uk''. Retrieved: 9 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Further reconnaissance flights are alleged to have taken place along, and over, the borders of the Soviet Union in 1954 under the [[code name]] ''Project Robin'', using the Canberra B2 ''[[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|WH726]]''. The USAF also used the Canberra for reconnaissance flights.&lt;ref&gt;Fensch 2001, p.&amp;nbsp;6.&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft were no longer required after June 1956, following the introduction of the US [[Lockheed U-2]] purpose-built reconnaissance aircraft; ''Project Robin'' was then terminated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spyflight.co.uk/robin.htm &quot;Project Robin.&quot;] ''spyflight.co.uk''. Retrieved: 9 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; These RAF Canberra overflights were later featured in the 1994 BBC ''[[Timewatch]]'' episode; &quot;Spies in the Sky&quot;, and included interviews with some of the Soviet [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-15|MiG-15]] pilots who had attempted to intercept them.&lt;ref&gt;BBC Timewatch episode &quot;Spies in the Sky&quot;, 1994, Episode 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Canberra was the victorious aircraft flown in [[The Last Great Air Race]] from London to [[Christchurch]] in 1953, piloted by Flight Lieutenant [[Roland (Monty) Burton]], which touched down at Christchurch 41 minutes ahead of its closest rival – after 23hr 51min in the air; to this day the record has never been broken.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/obituaries/article610427.ece &quot;Flight Lieutenant Don Gannon.&quot;] ''[[The Sunday Times]].'' Retrieved: 27 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Wing to Wing.ogv|thumb|British Government public information film on the Canberra and its contribution to NATO]]
The [[Vickers Valiant]] entered service in 1955,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p378&quot;&gt;Mason 1994, p. 378.&lt;/ref&gt; capable of carrying much heavier weapon loads (including the [[Blue Danube (nuclear weapon)|Blue Danube]] nuclear weapon) over longer ranges than the Canberra. This led to the Bomber Command force of Canberras equipped for high-level conventional bombing to be gradually phased out. This did not mean the end of the Canberra in front line service, as it proved suitable for the low-level strike and ground attack role, and versions dedicated to this role were brought into service.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIAug06 p41&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' August 2006, p.&amp;nbsp;41.&lt;/ref&gt; The interim B(I)6, converted from the B6 by adding provision for a pack of four [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404#British production|Hispano]] 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon in the rear bomb bay and underwing pylons for bombs and rockets, entered service in 1955, with the definitive, new build B(I)8, which added a new forward fuselage with a fighter-style canopy for the pilot, entering service in January 1956.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIAug06 p41&quot;/&gt;

An important role for the new low-level force was tactical nuclear strike, using the [[Low Altitude Bombing System]] (LABS) to allow a nuclear bomb to be delivered from low level while allowing the bomber to escape the blast of the weapon. RAF Germany's force of four squadrons equipped with the B(I)6 and B(I)8 could carry US-owned [[Mark 7 nuclear bomb]]s from 1960, which were replaced by [[B43 nuclear bomb]]s, also US-owned, from 1965. Three squadrons based on Cyprus and one at [[Singapore]] were armed with British-owned [[Red Beard (nuclear weapon)|Red Beard]] nuclear weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIAug06 p42-3&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' August 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;42–43.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nichols ''Air International'' July 2005, pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bomber Command retired the last of its Canberras on 11 September 1961,&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIAug06 p42&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' August 2006, p.&amp;nbsp;42.&lt;/ref&gt; but the Germany, Cyprus and Singapore based squadrons continued in the nuclear strike role. The Cyprus-based squadrons and one of the RAF Germany squadrons disbanded in 1969, with the Singapore-based unit followed in 1970. The three remaining RAF Germany units, which by now had replaced the old Mark 7 bombs with newer (but still US-owned) [[B43 nuclear bomb]]s, remained operational until 1972, the last Canberra bombers in RAF service.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAISep06 p30-1&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' September 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;30–31.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:45SqnB15s.jpg|thumb|left|Group of RAF Canberra B15s of No. 45 Squadron at [[RAF Tengah]], Singapore, 1963]]
The RAF continued to operate the Canberra after 1972, employing it for reconnaissance (with Squadrons equipped with PR7s and PR9s being based at [[RAF Wyton]] in the UK and [[RAF Luqa]] in [[Malta]]). The PR9s were fitted with special LOROP (Long-Range Optical Photography) cameras, reportedly based on those used by the [[Lockheed U-2]], to allow high-altitude of targets deep into Eastern Europe while flying along the [[inner German border]], as well as [[infrared linescan]] cameras for low level night reconnaissance.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAISep06 p31-2&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' September 2006, pp. 31–32.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The linescan equipment came from reconnaissance pods which were used by RAF [[McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II|Phantoms]] before they were replaced by [[SEPECAT Jaguar|Jaguars]] in the reconnaissance role.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIMar02 p158&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' March 2002, p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} The RAF used Canberras to search for hidden arms dumps using [[False-color|false-colour photography]] during [[Operation Motorman]] in July 1972, when the British Army re-took Irish republican held &quot;no go areas&quot; in [[Belfast]] and [[Derry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIMar02 p159&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' March 2002, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;  Canberras were used for reconnaissance during the [[Bosnian War]] during the 1990s, where they were used to locate mass graves and during the [[Kosovo War]] in 1999. They were also operated from [[Uganda]] during the [[First Congo War]], where they were used to search for refugees.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIMar02 p162&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' March 2002, p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt; Small numbers of specially equipped Canberras were also used for [[signals intelligence]], being operated by [[No. 192 Squadron RAF|192 Squadron]] and then [[No. 51 Squadron RAF|51 Squadron]] from 1953 to 1976.&lt;ref name=&quot;IAPR1 p130,6&quot;&gt;Lake ''International Air Power Review'' 2001, pp. 130, 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Falklands War, a plan to supply two PR9s to the Chilean Air Force, and secretly operate them with RAF crews over the war zone, was abandoned for political reasons. The aircraft got as far as [[Belize]] before the operation was cancelled.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spyflight.co.uk/chile.htm &quot;The Falklands campaign – the Chilean connection.&quot;] ''Spyflight.'' Retrieved: 5 January 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Freedman 2005, p. 394.&lt;/ref&gt; The PR9 variant remained in service with [[No. 39 Squadron RAF|No. 39 (1 PRU) Squadron]] until July 2006 for strategic reconnaissance and photographic mapping, seeing service in the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]] and, up to June 2006, in [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Afghanistan]]. During a ceremony to mark the standing down of 39 (1 PRU) Squadron at [[RAF Marham]] on 28 July 2006, a flypast by a Canberra PR9 on its last ever sortie was conducted.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/5190242.stm &quot;Vintage jet is flying into sunset.&quot;] ''BBC News'', 18 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Australian Air Force===
Shortly after the end of the Second World War, the Australian government initiated a wide-scale reorganisation of the armed forces. As part of this process, the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) developed ''Plan D'' as the basis for its postwar structure; Plan D was built around the concept of a numerically smaller but more agile air arm that would employ leading edge technology.&lt;ref&gt;Stephens 1992, pp. 96, 102, 106.&lt;/ref&gt; During the late 1940s, the RAAF decided to acquire the Canberra as a replacement for, or complement to, the [[Avro Lincoln]],{{#tag:ref|The Avro Lincoln was a development of the famous [[Avro Lancaster]] bomber, the Lincoln would be the last piston-propelled bomber for several nations as jet-powered bombers quickly rendered them obsolete.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 107'/&gt;|group=N}} though fears were raised that the new design was not especially advanced.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 107'/&gt; While Australia never introduced nuclear weapons into service, the Canberra's ability to carry such a payload was a stated factor in its acquisition;&lt;ref name = 'stephens 108'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; Australia's planned force of 48 Canberras, which held the potential for being nuclear-armed, was viewed as far more potent and deterring to potential opponents than the RAAF's entire wartime forces of 254 heavy bombers.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 109'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|In September 1956, Minister for Air [[Athol Townley]] wrote of the Canberra bomber being limited by conventional weapons, and that the deployment of [[tactical nuclear weapons]] would noticeably increase its effectiveness; Prime Minister [[Robert Menzies]] was an opponent to their acquisition.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 1048'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}

[[File:QUS 8.jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|left|An RAAF Canberra during maintenance, circa 1967]]
The Australian government decided that the RAAF's Canberras would be constructed domestically by the [[Government Aircraft Factories]] (GAF) as opposed to being manufactured in the UK.&lt;ref name = &quot;bomber 57&quot;/&gt; On 29 May 1953, the first Australian-built Canberra performed its first flight at [[Avalon Airport]], [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]]; this aircraft was delivered to the RAAF for service trials a few weeks later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom176&quot; /&gt; In December 1953, the Canberra formally entered Australian service.&lt;ref name = 'raaf museum'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/raafmuseum/research/aircraft/series2/A84.htm|title=A84 Canberra|publisher=[[RAAF Museum]]|accessdate=16 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Canberra B20 2 Sqn RAAF over Vietnam 1970.jpg|thumb|RAAF Canberra Mk.20 of No. 2 Squadron during a strike out of [[Phan Rang Air Base]], Vietnam, March 1970]]

From July 1950 to July 1960, during the [[Malayan Emergency]], Canberras from Australia, New Zealand and the UK were deployed into the Malaysia to fight against Communist [[Guerrilla warfare|guerillas]].&lt;ref name = 'stephens 126'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1967, the RAAF deployed eight Canberras to the Vietnam War. The unit, [[No. 2 Squadron RAAF|No. 2 Squadron]], was later commended for its performance by the United States Air Force.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 124'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt; The Canberras were typically operated in the low-level bombing role, taking over South Vietnam's southern most military regions III and IV responsibilities allowing USAF bombers to deploy their aircraft to the [[Ho Chi Minh trail]].  While USAF Canberras were equipped with [[.50 caliber]] machine guns or [[20mm]] cannon for strafing, Australian Canberras were deployed to South Vietnam without guns, hence were deployed strictly for low level bombing missions.&lt;ref&gt;Bell 2011, pp. 74, 75.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = 'stephens 153'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|To help protect against ground anti-aircraft fire, armour plating was designed and fitted to Canberras deployed to Vietnam.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 173'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} Upon their re-deployment from Vietnam in 1971, No. 2 Squadron had flown approximately 12,000 sorties and dropped 76,389 bombs, and lost two of their aircraft to missiles and ground fire during the course of the war.&lt;ref name = 'raaf museum'/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bell 2011, pp. 81, 91.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = 'stephens 156'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 156.&lt;/ref&gt;

As early as 1954, Australia recognised that the Canberra was becoming outdated, and evaluated aircraft such as the [[Avro Vulcan]] and [[Handley-Page Victor]] as potential replacements.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 142'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt; The Canberra was incapable of providing adequate coverage of [[Indonesia]] from Australian bases, and was evaluated as having a &quot;very low&quot; chance of survival if it encountered modern fighters like the [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-17|MiG-17]].&lt;ref name = 'stephens 151'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt;  Political pressure for a Canberra replacement rose to a head in 1962.&lt;ref name = 'Weisbrod'&gt;Weisbrod, Hanno [http://www.jstor.org/pss/20634276 &quot;Australia's Decision to Buy the F-111.&quot;] ''The Australian Quarterly'', 41(2), June 1969, pp. 7–27.&lt;/ref&gt; Australia evaluated the [[BAC TSR-2]], [[Dassault Mirage IV]], [[McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II]] and [[North American A-5 Vigilante]], and initially appeared to favour the TSR-2, but chose to procure the [[General Dynamics F-111C]] in October 1963.&lt;ref&gt;Kinzey 1982, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://naa12.naa.gov.au/scripts/Imagine.asp?B=1345810&amp;I=1&amp;SE=1 &quot;Correspondence between the Australian and British Governments concerning the selection of the F-111 over the TSR-2.&quot;] ''National Archives of Australia''. Retrieved: 11 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Due in part to delays in the delivery of the F-111Cs, the Canberra continued to be used by Australia for a total of 29 years before its retirement in June 1982.&lt;ref name = 'stephens 107'&gt;Stephens 1992, p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = 'raaf museum'/&gt;&lt;ref name = 'Weisbrod'/&gt;

===Indian Air Force===
[[File:English Electric Canberra T4, India - Air Force AN1286034.jpg|thumb|English Electric Canberra T4]]
The Canberra was the backbone of the [[Indian Air Force]] (IAF) for bombing raids and photo-reconnaissance for many decades. Negotiations to acquire the Canberra as a replacement for the  obsolete [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator]] bombers then being used by India began in 1954.&lt;ref name = 'Kavic 104'&gt;Kavic 1967, p.&amp;nbsp;104.&lt;/ref&gt; During the extended negotiations between Britain and India, the Soviet Union is alleged to have offered their own jet bomber, the [[Ilyushin Il-28]], at a significantly lower price than that asked for the Canberra;&lt;ref name = 'Kavic 104'/&gt; by April 1956, however, the Indian government was in favour of the purchase. In January 1957 India placed a large order for the Canberra; a total of 54 B(I)58 bombers, eight PR57 photo-reconnaissance aircraft, and six T4 training aircraft were ordered, deliveries began in the summer of that same year.&lt;ref name = 'Kavic 104'/&gt; A total of 12 more Canberras were ordered in September 1957, as many as 30 more may have also been purchased by 1962.&lt;ref name = 'Kavic 104'/&gt;

First used in combat by the IAF in 1962, the Canberra was employed during the UN campaign against the breakaway [[State of Katanga|Republic of Katanga]] in Africa.&lt;ref name = 'Silicon India'&gt;[http://www.siliconindia.com/shownews/Indian_Air_Force_returns_to_Congo_on_UN_peace_mission_-nid-19963.html &quot;Indian Air Force returns to Congo on U.N. peace mission.&quot;] &quot;Silicon India News&quot;, 1 July 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Indo-Pakistani Wars]] of the 1960s and 1970s, the Canberra was used by both sides. The most audacious use of the bomber was in the ''&quot;Raid on Badin&quot;'' during the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1965]], when the Indian Air Force sent in the Canberra to attack a critical Pakistani radar post in [[West Pakistan]]. The raid was a complete success, the radars in Badin having been badly damaged by the bombing and put out of commission.&lt;ref name = 'India def'/&gt; A later raid by the IAF was attempted on Peshawar Air base with the aim of destroying, amongst other targets, several Pakistani B-57 bombers, American-built Canberras. Due to poor visibility, a road outside of the base was bombed, instead of the runway where PAF B-57 bombers were parked.&lt;ref&gt;Gupta, Aditya. [http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_325.shtml &quot;The Kashmir War, 1965: Raid on Badin.&quot;] ''Air Combat Information Group,'' 29 October 2003. Retrieved: 26 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1971]], Indian Canberras flew a strategically important sortie against the [[Karachi]] oil tanks, this had the effect of helping the [[Indian Navy]] in their own operations, a series of [[missile boat]] attacks against the Pakistani coast.&lt;ref name = 'India def'&gt;[http://www.indiadefence.com/canberra.htm &quot;Canberra in Indian Air Force Service.&quot;] ''indiadefence.com''. Retrieved: 9 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 May 1999, prior to the commencement of the [[Kargil War]], the Indian Air Force Air HQ assigned a Canberra PR57 aircraft on a photographic mission near the [[Line of Control]], where it took a severe blow from a [[FIM-92 Stinger]] [[infrared homing]] missile on the starboard engine; the Canberra successfully returned to base using the other engine.

The entire Indian Air Force Canberra fleet was grounded and then retired following the crash of an IAF Canberra in December 2005. After 50 years of service, the Canberra was finally retired by the IAF on 11 May 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/NEWS/India/IAFs_Canberra_bomber_makes_final_flight/articleshow/1729622.cms &quot;India's IAF Canberra bomber makes final flight.&quot;] ''Times of India'', 7 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===
[[File:Canberra B12 - 453.jpg|thumb|left|SAAF Canberra B12 with inertial navigation and special sensors package over [[Transvaal Province|Transvaal]]]]
During the [[Suez Crisis]] the RAF employed around 100 Canberras, flying conventional bombing and reconnaissance missions from airfields in [[Malta]] and [[Cyprus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p371&quot;&gt;Mason 1994, p.&amp;nbsp;371.&lt;/ref&gt;  A total of 278 Canberra sorties were flown, dropping 1,439 1000&amp;nbsp;lb (450&amp;nbsp;kg) bombs;&lt;ref name=&quot;Delve June 89 p305&quot;&gt;Delve 1989, p.&amp;nbsp;305.&lt;/ref&gt; however low-level strikes by smaller fighters were judged to be more effective than the night time bombing operations performed by both the Canberra and the Vickers Valiant.&lt;ref&gt;Varble 2003, p.&amp;nbsp;53.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, many of the bombs, intended to hit Egyptian airfields, missed their targets, failing to inflict much damage to the Egyptian Air Force or to badly demoralise the enemy.&lt;ref&gt;Varble 2003, p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt; While interception of the Canberra was within the capabilities of Egypt's [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-15|MiG-15]]s and MiG-17s, as shown by the interception of Canberras by MiG-15s prior to the Anglo-French invasion, these did not result in any losses. The only Canberra shot down during the Suez campaign was a PR7 shot down by a Syrian Gloster Meteor fighter on 6 November 1956, the last day of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolle, David. [http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_258.shtml &quot;Canberra Down!&quot;] ''Acig Journal'', 23 September 2003. Retrieved: 18 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Delve June 89 p306&quot;&gt;Delve 1989, p. 306.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland]] considered the Canberra an important objective to holding greater diplomatic sway in the African continent, and ongoing negotiations over the Baghdad treaty, and a step towards [[decolonisation]].&lt;ref name = 'petter 52'&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, p.&amp;nbsp;52.&lt;/ref&gt; The Suez Crisis caused a delay in the sale, but in August 1957 18 Canberras had been earmarked to be refurbished and transferred from the RAF to the [[Royal Rhodesian Air Force]] (RRAF).&lt;ref name = 'petter 52'/&gt; Both [[Rhodesia]] and [[South Africa]] used Canberras in their respective [[Rhodesian Bush War|Bush War]]s; numerous aircraft were lost in the conflicts.&lt;ref&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, pp. 290, 369.&lt;/ref&gt; Rhodesian B2 Canberras together with South African B(I)12 Canberras carried out attacks on insurgents in [[Mozambique]], usually armed with 'Alpha' cluster bombs,&lt;ref&gt;Petter-Bowyer 2005, p. 284.&lt;/ref&gt; several raids on [[Zambia]], and attacks upon multiple insurgents bases in [[Angola]].&lt;ref&gt;Moorcroft, Paul L. ''A Short Thousand Years: The End of Rhodesia's Rebellion''.  Salisbury, Rhodesia: Galaxie Press, 1979. ISBN 978-0-86925-106-5.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ethiopia]]n Canberras were used against [[Eritrea]] and again against [[Somalia]] during the 1970s.

===Sweden===
The [[Swedish Air Force]] purchased two Canberras from the RAF in 1960 and had these modified to T11s by [[Boulton Paul]]. The aircraft were secretly modified in Sweden as [[espionage]] aircraft for eavesdropping on primarily Soviet, Polish and East German military radio transmissions, although this was not publicly admitted until 10 years later. The Canberras were given the designation Tp 52, and taken into service as &quot;testing aircraft&quot;, until they were replaced by two Tp 85 [[Sud Aviation Caravelle|Caravelle]]s in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;van der Aart 1985, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;

===South America===
On 20 April 1960, the [[Venezuelan Air Force]] used its Canberra B2 and B(1)8s to bomb the airport at [[San Cristóbal, Táchira]], which had been seized by rebels, led by General Jose Maria Castro León. The rebels surrendered shortly afterward.&lt;ref&gt;Oliver 1987, p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; On 26 June 1961, Venezuela's Canberras were used against rebelling Army forces in [[Barcelona, Venezuela]].&lt;ref&gt;''Air Enthusiast'' September 1973, p. 123.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Peruvian Air Force]] Canberras flew combat sorties against Ecuadorian positions during the [[Cenepa War]] in 1995. On 6 February 1995, a Canberra Mk.68 disappeared over the operations zone; the aircraft had apparently struck a hill in poor weather conditions. Peru retired its Canberras in June 2008.

====Argentina====
[[File:Canberra Bomber B-108.jpeg|thumb|B-108 on its last mission]]
The [[Argentine Air Force]] received 10 B62 bombers and two T64 trainers at the beginning of the 1970s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Huertas p61&quot;&gt;Huertas 1996, p.&amp;nbsp;61.&lt;/ref&gt; replacing the Avro Lincoln in the bomber role. Argentina retired its last Canberras in April 2000.

During the [[Falklands War]] in 1982, eight of them were deployed to [[Trelew]], 670&amp;nbsp;miles (1,080&amp;nbsp;km) from the islands, to avoid congestion on the closer southern airfields. Although within operating range of the British task force, the Canberra was judged to be a limited threat due to its poor maneuverability compared with the British [[British Aerospace Sea Harrier|Sea Harrier]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Richardson, Doug. &quot;War in the Falklands&quot;. ''[[New Scientist]]'', 94(1302), 22 April 1982, p.&amp;nbsp;203.&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1 May to 14 June 1982, Argentine Canberras made 54 sorties; 36 of them bombing missions, of which 22 were at night against ground troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huertas p63&quot;&gt;Huertas 1996, p.&amp;nbsp;63.&lt;/ref&gt; Two aircraft were lost in combat, the first to a Sea Harrier's [[AIM-9 Sidewinder|AIM-9L Sidewinder]] [[air-to-air missile]] on 1 May 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huertas p63&quot;/&gt;

On 13 June 1982, a second Canberra Mk.62 of {{lang|es|''Grupo de Bombardeo&amp;nbsp;2''}}, ''B-108'' was shot down at 12,000 m (39,000&amp;nbsp;ft) when it was struck by a [[Sea Dart (missile)|Sea Dart]] missile fired from [[HMS Cardiff (D108)|HMS ''Cardiff'']].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fuerzaaerea.mil.ar/conflicto/dias/jun13.html &quot;Domingo 13 de Junio&quot; (in Spanish).] ''Fuerza Aerea Argentine.'' Retrieved: 26 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The pilot ejected safely but the navigator was killed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fuerzaaerea.mil.ar/conflicto/camberra.html &quot;BAC MK-62 Canberra&quot; (in Spanish).] ''Argentine Air Force.'' Retrieved: 26 April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; It was the last Argentine aircraft to be lost in combat during the Falklands War, with Argentine forces surrendering the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huetas p64-5&quot;&gt;Huertas 1996, pp. 64—65.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Development and trials aircraft===
[[File:WH876-Canberra-1308.jpg|thumb|A former Canberra D14 used for development and trials work|alt=Wide view of jet aircraft. The fin is red; short black stripes running perpendicular to and on top of the fuselage.]]
[[File:EECanberraB2-WV787-0144.jpg|thumb|Canberra B2 (WV787) used for development trials, 2006]]
A number of Canberras were used by English Electric for development work and trials on new equipment. It was also used by government establishments such as the [[Royal Aircraft Establishment]] and the [[Royal Radar Establishment]]. The Canberra proved to be a useful platform for such work and was used by a number of British tests and trials establishments. As well as those operated by English Electric, a number of engine manufacturers were also loaned Canberras as engine test beds; [[Armstrong Siddeley]] for the [[Armstrong Siddeley Sapphire|Sapphire]], [[Bristol Siddeley]] for the [[Rolls-Royce Olympus|Olympus]], [[de Havilland Engine Company]] for the [[de Havilland Gyron Junior|Gyron Junior]] turbojet and [[Rolls-Royce Limited]] for the [[Rolls-Royce Avon|Avon]]. [[Ferranti]] used four different Canberra B2s for avionics development work.

One example is ''WV787'' which was built as a Canberra B2 in 1952, it was loaned to [[Armstrong Siddeley]] and was fitted with [[Armstrong Siddeley Sapphire]] engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom175&quot;&gt;Ransom 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;175.&lt;/ref&gt; It was later transferred to [[Ferranti]] for  trials for the [[Blackburn Buccaneer]] radar and fitted with a B(I)8 type nose and a Buccaneer style radome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom175&quot; /&gt; It next was moved to the [[Aeroplane and Armament Experimental Establishment]] where it was modified to be used as a water-spray tanker aircraft for de-icing trials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom175&quot; /&gt; It would fly in front of the aircraft being tested which would fly into the artificial cloud created by the sprayed water to induce icing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom175&quot; /&gt; It was retired in 1984 and later preserved at the [[Newark Air Museum]] and is a National Benchmark airframe on the National Aviation Heritage Register.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newarkairmuseum.org/aircraft_list.html &quot;Canberra.&quot;] ''Newark Air Museum Aircraft List.'' Retrieved: 16 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flight records set by Canberras===
* 21 January 1951 – first non-stop unrefuelled [[Transatlantic flight|transatlantic crossing]] by a jet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jsc-aircraft-ops.jsc.nasa.gov/wb57/history.html &quot;B-57 History.&quot;] ''NASA Johnson Space Center'' (JSC) in Houston website. Retrieved: 18 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis race p357&quot;&gt;Lewis 1971, p. 357.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 26 August 1952 – the prototype B5 made the first double transatlantic crossing by a jet, with a total time of 10 hr 3 min.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis race p369&quot;&gt;Lewis 1970, p. 369.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 4 May 1953 – Canberra B2 ''WD952'', fitted with [[Rolls-Royce Olympus]] engines set a world altitude record, flying at {{convert|63668|ft|m|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name='FAI'&gt;[http://records.fai.org/general_aviation/aircraft.asp?id=3218 &quot;FAI Canberra World Records.&quot;] ''fai.org''. Retrieved: 18 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis race p371&quot;&gt;Lewis 1970, p. 371.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 29 August 1955 – altitude record, {{convert|65889|ft|m|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name ='FAI' /&gt;
* 28 August 1957 – altitude record, {{convert|70310|ft|m|abbr=on}}: Canberra B2 (''[[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|WK163]]'') with a [[Napier Double Scorpion]]'' rocket motor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Centennial of Flight web-site&quot;&gt;[http://www.centennialofflight.gov/user/fact_aug.htm &quot;Canberra Records: 28, 29 August 1957.&quot;] ''Centennial of Flight,'' 2003. Retrieved: 18 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://records.fai.org/general_aviation/aircraft.asp?id=3142 &quot;FAI World Records.&quot;] ''fai.org''. Retrieved: 9 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
:''See [[Martin B-57 Canberra]] article for the US-built variants.''

;English Electric A.1
:Company designation for the first four aircraft before being named Canberra.&lt;ref&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra B.1
:Prototypes for type development work and research at first known by the company designation A.1, four built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom p350&quot;&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p. 350.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra B.2
:First production version, crew increased to three with addition of [[Bombardier (air force)|bomb aimer]], Avon R.A.3 engines with 6,500 lbf (28.91 kN) of thrust, wingtip fuel tanks. 418 built by English Electric (208), [[Avro]] (75), [[Handley Page]] (75) and [[Short Brothers &amp; Harland]] (60)&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070529204743/www.britishaircraft.co.uk/aircraftpage.php?ID=12 &quot;English Electric Canberra.&quot;] ''British Aircraft Directory''. Retrieved: 29 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; including eight for export (Australia, United States and Venezuela).
;Canberra PR.3
:Photo-reconnaissance version with a 14-inch section added to the fuselage to house the camera bay, internal fuel was increased and flat panel in the nose was removed. Needed only two crew. The prototype was flown on 19 March 1950 and the variant entered service in 1953.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'&gt;Chant 1987, p. 377.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra T.4
:First trainer variant with dual controls and a crew of three.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B.5
:Prototype of second-generation Canberra with fuel tanks in the wings and Avon R.A.7 engines with 7,490 lbf (33.32 kN) of thrust, one built.
;Canberra B.6
:Production version based on B.5 with a 1 ft (0.3 m) fuselage stretch, 106 built by English Electric (57) and Short Brothers &amp; Harland (49), includes 12 for export.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B.6(RC)
:RC = Radio Countermeasures (also known as B6(Mod) or PR16) – Specialist ELINT version with enlarged nose and Blue Shadow Side Looking Airborne Radar (SLAR). Only four produced, extended nose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lakeiapr p131-2&quot;&gt;Lake ''International Air Power Review'' 2001, pp. 131–132.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra B(I).6
:Interim [[interdictor]] version for the RAF pending delivery of the B(I)8. Based on the B.6 with a detachable ventral pack housing four [[20 mm Hispano Mk. V]] cannon for strafing; also had provision for two wing hard points. LABS (Low-Altitude Bombing System) for delivery of nuclear bombs. 22 produced.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAIAug06 p41&quot;/&gt;
;Canberra PR.7
:Photo-reconnaissance version based on B.6, had similar equipment to the PR.3 but had the uprated Avon 109 engines of the B.6 and increased internal fuel capacity, 74 built.&lt;ref name=&quot;LakeAISep06p31&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' September 2006, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra B(I).8
:Third-generation Canberra derived from B.6 as an [[interdictor]].&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt; Fitted with a new forward fuselage with teardrop canopy on the port side, and Navigator station forward of pilot (early marks had the navigator behind the pilot. Provision for a ventral pack similar to the B(I).6 with 4 x {{convert|20|mm|abber=on|3}} [[Hispano cannon]], one external hardpoint under each wing for up to 1,000 lb (454 kg) of bombs or unguided rockets, LABS (Low-Altitude Bombing System) for delivery of nuclear bombs. Prototype converted from the only B.5 and first flown 23 July 1954, 72 built including 17 for export and two converted from B.2s.
[[File:G-OMHD-Canberra-0889.jpg|thumb|Preserved PR.9 ''XH135'' at [[Kemble Airport]]. Note the offset pilot's [[aircraft canopy|canopy]]. The navigator sits inside the nose section.]]
;Canberra PR.9
:Photo-reconnaissance version based on B(I).8 with fuselage stretched to 68 ft (27.72 m), wingspan increased by 4 ft (1.22 m), and Avon R.A.27 (Avon 206) engines with 10,030 lbf (44.6 kN) of thrust. Had the offset canopy of the B(I).8 with a hinged nose to allow fitment of an ejection seat for the navigator. A total of 23 built by Short Brothers &amp; Harland with three transferred to [[Chile]] after the Falklands War.
;Canberra U.10 (later designated D.10)
:Remote-controlled target drones converted from B.2. 18 converted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aerop86-7&quot;&gt;Jones 2006, pp. 86–87.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra T.11
:Nine B.2s converted to trainers for pilots and navigators of all-weather interceptors to operate the Airborne Intercept radar, crew of four.
;Canberra B(I).12
:Canberra B(I).8 bombers built for New Zealand and South Africa.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra T.13
:Training version of the T.4 for New Zealand, one built new and one conversion from T.4.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom p350&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra U.14 (later designated D.14)
:Remote-controlled target drones converted from the B.2 for Royal Navy. Six converted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aerop86-7&quot;/&gt;
;Canberra B.15
:Upgraded B.6 for use in the Far and Near East with under-wing hard-points for {{convert|1000|lb|abbr=on}} bombs or rockets. New avionics and fitting of three cameras, 39 conversions.
;Canberra B.16
:Similar to B.15 for use in Germany and fitted with Blue Shadow, 19 conversions
;Canberra T.17
:Electronic warfare training variant used to train surface-based radar and missile operators and airborne fighter and Airborne Early Warning crews in handling jamming (including chaff dropping) aircraft. 24 conversions from B.2 with extended nose for sensors.
[[File:RAF English Electric Canberra T17A Lofting-1.jpg|thumb|Canberra T17A]]
;Canberra T.17A
:Updated version of the T.17 with improved navigation aids, a spectrum analyser in place of the previously fitted AN/APR-20, and a powerful communications jammer.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra TT.18
:Target tug conversion of B.2 for the RAF and Royal Navy, 22 conversions.
;Canberra T.19
:T.11 with radar removed as silent target.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B.20
:B.2 with additional fuel tanks in the wings, [[licence-built]] in Australia.&lt;ref name='raaf museum'/&gt;&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra T.21
:Trainers converted from B.2 and B.20.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra T.22
:Conversion of the PR.7 for Royal Navy's Fleet Requirement and Air Direction Unit, used for training Buccaneer navigators.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B.52
:Refurbished B.2 bombers sold to Ethiopia.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B(I).56
:Refurbished B(I).6 bombers sold to Peru.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra PR.57
:Tropicalized PR.7 for India.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B(I).58
:Tropicalized B(I)8 for India.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B.62
:10 refurbished B.2 bombers sold to Argentina.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra T.64
:2 refurbished T.4 trainers sold to Argentina.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B(I).66
:10 refurbished B(I).6 bombers sold to India.
;Canberra PR.67
:2 refurbished PR.7s sold to India.
;Canberra B(I).68
:1 refurbished B(I).8 bomber sold to Peru.&lt;ref name = 'chant 377'/&gt;
;Canberra B.92
:1 modified B.2 for Argentina, not delivered and embargoed in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom359&quot;&gt;Ranson 1987, p. 359.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra T.94
:1 modified T.4 for Argentina, not delivered and embargoed in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom359&quot; /&gt;
;Short SC.9
:1 Canberra PR.9, modified by [[Short Brothers|Shorts]] as SC.9 and fitted with an AI.23 radar, plus IR installation in the nose for [[Hawker Siddeley Red Top|Red Top]] air-to-air missile trials. Continued in use for radar missile development work, until broken up sometime between 1986 and 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;XH132&quot; &gt;Bywaters, Les. [http://www.bywat.co.uk/xh132.html &quot;Canberra – PR.9 (Shorts SC.9) – XH132.&quot;] ''A tribute to the English Electric Canberra''. Retrieved: 9 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Short SD.1
:1 Canberra PR.3, modified by [[Short Brothers|Shorts]] as SD.1 to be launch vehicle carrying two Short SD.2 variants of the [[Beech AQM-37A Jayhawk]] high-speed target missiles, apparently called Stiletto in the UK, for trials by the Royal Aircraft Establishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom352&quot;&gt;Ransom 1987, p. 352.&lt;/ref&gt;
;Canberra Tp52: Two B.2 aircraft modified with T.17 noses for [[ELINT]] duties with the [[Royal Swedish Air Force]]

==Operators==
[[File:English Electric Canberra and Martin B-57 Canberra operators.png|thumb|300px|Canberra (dark blue) and B-57 (light blue) operators&lt;ref name=&quot;Aero93-7&quot;&gt;Jones 1997, pp. 93–97.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:SAAF Canberra.jpg|thumb|SAAF Canberra T.4 at [[Air Force Base Waterkloof|AFB Waterkloof]], circa 1980]]
[[File:Venezuela Air Force English Electric Canberra Volpati-1.jpg|thumb|Venezuela Air Force Canberra, March 1972]]
[[File:Canberracrash.jpg|thumb|Wreckage of a crashed [[Indian air force|Indian Air Force]] Canberra in Agra, India on 19 December 2005]]

;{{ARG}}
* [[Argentine Air Force]] purchased 10 refurbished ex-RAF B2s and 2 T4s (redesignated B62 and B64 respectively) in 1967. Two further aircraft were ordered in 1981 but were not delivered owing to the Falklands War.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aero96&quot;&gt;Jones 1997, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{AUS}}
* [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (58)
** [[No. 1 Squadron RAAF]]
** [[No. 2 Squadron RAAF]]
** [[No. 6 Squadron RAAF]]
** [[No. 1 Operational Conversion Unit RAAF]]
** [[Aircraft Research and Development Unit RAAF]]
** [[No. 1 Long Range Flight RAAF]]
;{{CHI}}
* [[Chilean Air Force]] (3)
;{{ECU}}
* [[Ecuadorian Air Force]] (6) Six new-build B2 variants delivered in 1955.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ransom356&quot;&gt;Ransom and Fairclough 1987, p. 356.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{flag|Ethiopia|1897}}
*[[Ethiopian Air Force]] (4)
;{{FRA}}
* [[French Air Force]] (6)
** ''Centre d'Essais en Vol
** ''Centre du Tir et de Bombardement&lt;ref name=&quot;Aero95&quot;&gt;Jones 1996, p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{IND}}
* [[Indian Air Force]] (107)
;{{NZL}}
* [[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] (31)
** [[No. 14 Squadron RNZAF]]
** [[No. 75 Squadron RNZAF]]
;{{PER}}
* [[Peruvian Air Force]] (60)
;{{flag|Rhodesia}}
* [[Royal Rhodesian Air Force]] (20)
;{{flag|South Africa|1928}}
* [[South African Air Force]]&lt;ref&gt;Steyn, Leon. [http://www.af.mil.za/news/2008/065.htm &quot;SAAF Museum News: What happened to the Canberra?&quot;] ''[[12 Squadron SAAF|12 Squadron, South African Air Force]]''. Retrieved: 9 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; (9)
;{{SWE}}
* [[Swedish Air Force]] (2)
;{{UK}}
* [[Royal Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Halley81 p351&quot;&gt;Halley 1981, p. 351.&lt;/ref&gt; (782)
{{multicol}}
:*[[No. 3 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 6 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 7 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 9 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 10 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 12 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 13 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 14 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 15 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 16 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 17 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 18 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 21 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 27 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 31 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 32 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 35 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 39 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 40 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 44 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 45 Squadron RAF]]
{{multicol-break}}
:*[[No. 50 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 51 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 57 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 58 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 59 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 61 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 69 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 73 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 76 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 80 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 81 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 82 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 85 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 88 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 90 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 97 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 98 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 100 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 101 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 102 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 103 Squadron RAF]]
{{multicol-break}}
:*[[No. 104 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 109 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 115 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 139 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 149 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 151 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 192 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 199 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 207 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 213 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 245 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 249 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 360 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 361 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 527 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 540 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 542 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 617 Squadron RAF]]
:*[[No. 231 Operational Conversion Unit RAF]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason bomber p371&quot;/&gt;
{{multicol-end}}
* [[Royal Navy]] [[Fleet Air Arm]] (69)
** [[728B NAS]] – [[RNAS Hal Far, Malta]]
** [[Fleet Requirements Unit]] (FRU)
** [[Fleet Requirements and Aircraft Direction Unit]] (FRADU)
* [[Royal Aircraft Establishment]]/[[Defence Evaluation and Research Agency|DERA]] (2), [[RAE Bedford]] &amp; DERA Llanbder&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bywat.co.uk/wk128.html/ &quot;TT.18 – WK128&quot;.] ''bywat.co.uk''. Retrieved: 6 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{USA}}
* [[United States Air Force]] (two only for B-57 development)
;{{flag|Venezuela|1930}}
* [[Venezuelan Air Force]] (46)

;{{FRG}}
* [[German Air Force]] (3)

;{{ZIM}}
*[[Air Force of Zimbabwe]]

==Survivors==
[[File:Canberra B-109 Museo Moron.JPG|thumb|Argentine Air Force Canberra Mk.62 at [[Museo Nacional de Aeronáutica de Argentina|Museo Nacional de Aeronáutica]] in Buenos Aires]]
[[File:A84-235 Canberra Mk20 after the completion of the restoration work.jpg|thumb|Canberra Mk 20 (A84-235) in RAAF [[No. 2 Squadron RAAF|No. 2 Squadron]] livery]]
[[File:English Electric Canberra B2 at Berlin Luftwaffenmuseum 2004.jpg|thumb|One of three Canberras operated by the [[German Air Force|Luftwaffe]] at the museum at [[Gatow Airport]]]]
[[File:EE Canberra (Tp-52) 52001 01 (7618390398).jpg|thumb|Preserved Swedish ELINT Canberra at Svedinos Museum]]
Several ex-RAF machines and RB-57s remain flying in the US for research and mapping work. About 10 airworthy Canberras are in private hands today, and are flown at air displays.

===Argentina===
At least four Canberras retired from the Argentine Air Force have been preserved in [[Argentina]]:
* B Mk.62 ''B-102'' (ex-RAF WJ713). Retired in 1998, and assigned to &quot;Museo Nacional de Malvinas&quot;, Oliva, province of Córdoba.&lt;ref&gt;Fabian. [http://aeron-aves.blogspot.com/search/label/Canberra%20Oliva%20-%20Cordoba &quot;Canberra B.62 in Oliva, Argentina.&quot;] ''Aeron-aves.blogspot.com,'' 30 April 2011. Retrieved: 10 March 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* B Mk.62 ''B-105''. On display at [[Mar del Plata]] Air Base, province of Buenos Aires.&lt;ref&gt;Fabian. [http://aeron-aves.blogspot.com/search/label/Canberra%20Mar%20del%20Plata%20-%20MDQ &quot;Canberra B.62 in Mar del Plata, Argentina.&quot;] ''Aeron-aves.blogspot.com,'' 26 February 2004. Retrieved: 10 March 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* B Mk.62 ''B-109'', the last one to complete a mission in the Falklands War, is on display at the [[Museo Nacional de Aeronáutica de Argentina]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lanacion.com.ar/22349-el-canberra-b-109-se-gano-un-lugar-en-el-museo-aeronautico &quot;El Canberra B 109 se ganó un lugar en el museo aeronáutico.&quot;] ''La Nacion'', 26 June 2000. Retrieved 20 July 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* B Mk.64 ''B-112'', is on display at a roundabout in [[Paraná, Entre Ríos]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url= http://www.avialatina.com.ar/noticias3.php?idnoticia=63 |title= Nuevo emplazamiento del avión Canberra matricula B-112, en Entre Ríos |trans-title= New location of Canberra B-112, in Entre Ríos |journal= Avialatina - Noticias |last1= Peñaloza |first1= Raúl |date=25 April 2015 |publisher= Avialatina}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
* Canberra WJ680 ([[Royal Air Force]]) is on display at the [[Temora Aviation Museum]] in [[New South Wales]]. It was acquired in 2001 and the aircraft was fully restored to airworthiness and painted to represent the Canberras flown by [[No. 2 Squadron RAAF]] during the Vietnam war. It is Australia's only airworthy Canberra.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aviationmuseum.com.au/aircraft_colection/canberra/ &quot;English Electric Canberra TT.18.&quot;] ''Temora Aviation Museum'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mk.20 Canberra A84-225 is on static display at Queensland Aviation Museum, [[Caloundra Airport]], Queensland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://qam.com.au/?portfolio=g-a-f-canberra-mk-20-a84-225 &quot;G.A.F. Canberra Mk 20 A84-225.&quot;] ''Queensland Aviation Museum'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[South Australian Aviation Museum]] at Port Adelaide has a non-flying Canberra B2, WK165 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saam.org.au/ourcanberra.html &quot;English Electric Canberra (WK 165).&quot;] ''South Australian Aviation Museum'', Retrieved: 4 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Two Canberras are on static display by the Cunningham Highway south of [[Amberley, Queensland|Amberley]], Queensland.&lt;ref&gt;[https://campervanaustralia.uk/qld/accommodation/willowbank-village.html &quot;Willowbank Village.&quot;] ''campervanaustralia.uk'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com.au/maps/@-27.671558,152.6898758,3a,75y,305.13h,85.78t/data=!3m4!1e1!3m2!1sdb83hA9akyrAlp0xvDIkIw!2e0 &quot;Cunningham Highway.&quot;] ''Google'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A Canberra bomber is on display at the entrance to [[RAAF Base Wagga]], New South Wales.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airforce.gov.au/News/Refurbishment-of-historic-Canberra-bomber-and-Mirage-fighter/?RAAF-lwkQAZHeAhVh3N3OC3zhZLr7OZs7H/iU &quot;Refurbishment of Historic Canberra Bomber and Mirage Fighter.&quot;] ''Royal Australian Air Force'', 11 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Canberra A84-241 is on display at Woomera Missile Park, [[Woomera, South Australia|Woomera]], South Australia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ausemade.com.au/sa/destination/w/woomera/woomera-information.htm &quot;Woomera - Cities, Towns and Localities.&quot;] ''ausemade.com'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com.au/maps/place/Woomera+SA+5720/@-31.1983762,136.8251123,149m/data=!3m1!1e3!4m2!3m1!1s0x6a98493fd9f95e83:0x4033654628ed840 &quot;Woomera.&quot;] ''Google'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Canberra A84-307 is on display at the [[National Vietnam Veterans Museum]], [[Phillip Island, Victoria]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://vietnamvetsmuseum.org/node/canberra-bomber National Vietnam Veterans Museum - Canberra Bomber] Retrieved September 21, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;
* Canberra A84-226 is under restoration at the [[Australian National Aviation Museum]] in [[Moorabbin, Victoria]]. It was previously on display at [[RAAF Base Wagga]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canberratimes.com.au/act-news/get-your-free-canberra-bomber-here-conditions-apply-20150831-gjbx3f.html Get your free Canberra bomber here! Conditions Apply August 31, 2015] ''[[Canberra Times]]'' Retrieved September 21, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://mobile.twitter.com/ANAMAviation/status/744015573676335109 June 17, 2016 Australian National Aviation Museum] Retrieved September 21, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
* A B(I)58 Canberra, serial IF907 is on display at the [[Indian Air Force Museum, Palam]] in [[Delhi]], India; it is one of several diverted off an RAF contract as part of a 68 aircraft deal for India placed in January 1957.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bywat.co.uk/if907.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.abpic.co.uk/photo/1219887/&lt;/ref&gt;
* A Canberra B(I)58, marked with serial IF908, is on display at the Shri Shivaji Preparatory Military School (SSPMS) in [[Pune]]. This is possibly former Royal New Zealand Air Force serial F1188, acquired by the Indian Air Force in November 1980.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.warbirdsofindia.com/maharashtra/pune/113-canberra-f1188-at-shri-shivaji-preparatory-military-school.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* One more B(I)58 Canberra is preserved at Pune at the [[Pune Airport#Air Force Station, Lohegaon|Lohegaon Air Station]]. Marked serial IF910, it is located on an active military base and is thus not open to the public.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.warbirdsofindia.com/maharashtra/pune/112-canberra-if910-at-lohegaon-afs.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* A Canberra T.4 marked IQ999 is on display at Cadet Hill in Deolali, Nashik.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.warbirdsofindia.com/maharashtra/nasik/360-canberra-iq999-cadet-hill.html|title=Canberra T.4 [IQ999] at Cadet Hill|last=Deolali|first=School of Artillery,|access-date=2016-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Malta===
* A Canberra T.4 (WT483) was shipped to [[Malta International Airport]] in 2010; it is intended to be displayed at the [[Malta Aviation Museum]] eventually.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofmalta.com/articles/view/20101223/local/raf-canberra-returns-to-malta.342219 &quot;RAF Canberra returns to Malta.&quot;] ''Times of Malta'', 23 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Africa===
* A Canberra T Mk.4 ''457'' (71543) of the [[South African Air Force]] is displayed at the [[South African Air Force Museum]], Swartkop Air Force Base, [[Pretoria]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saaffriends.co.za/gallery/aeroplanes/museum_planes/list_of_museum_planes.htm &quot;Museum planes.&quot;] ''Saaffriends.co.za,'' 30 January 2012. Retrieved: 10 March 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
* One Canberra Tp52, modified for ELINT with a T.17 nose is preserved at the [[Svedinos Museum]], Ugglarp.
* The other Swedish Canberra was used for research and is on display at Flygvapenmuseum in Linköping.

===United Kingdom===
* A B.2 Canberra (G-CTTS previously WK163) is located at [[Doncaster Airport]]. In August 1957, WK163 broke the world altitude record when it flew to 70,310&amp;nbsp;ft. As of July 2016, it is currently undergoing restoration to flightworthy condition, at which point it will be the only airworthy Canberra in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-36335556 &quot;Record-breaking 'celebrity' jet bomber to be restored.&quot;] ''BBC News'', 19 May 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mullen, Enda. [http://www.coventrytelegraph.net/news/watch-enthusiasts-unveil-1m-plans-11361811 &quot;Watch as enthusiasts unveil £1m plans to restore record-breaking Coventry-based Canberra jet.&quot;] ''Coventry Telegraph'', 20 May 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A PR.3 Canberra (WF922) is on static display at the [[Midland Air Museum]] at [[Coventry Airport]] in England. It was retired from the RAF in 1975. WF922 was recently fully restored.&lt;ref&gt;Lambert, Malcolm. [http://www.bywat.co.uk/wf922.html &quot;PR.3 – WF922.&quot;] ''bywat.co.'' Retrieved: 26 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.midlandairmuseum.co.uk/aircraftlist.php &quot;Canberra PR.3 WF922.&quot;] ''Midland Air Museum.'' Retrieved: 26 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A PR.7 Canberra (WH773) is on static display at the [[Gatwick Aviation Museum]] in West Sussex, United Kingdom. WH773 was the first production PR.7 Canberra.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gatwick-aviation-museum.co.uk/canberra/canpr7.html &quot;PR7 Canberra.&quot;] ''Gatwick Aviation Museum.'' Retrieved: 16 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A T.4 Canberra (WH846) is on static display at the [[Yorkshire Air Museum]] near York.&lt;ref&gt;[http://yorkshireairmuseum.org/exhibits/cold-war-aircraft/english-electric-canberra-t4/?phpMyAdmin=3a0c50473ae0t41cd598f &quot;English Electric Canberra T.4.&quot;] ''Yorkshire Air Museum'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A PR.7 Canberra (WH791), a T.19 (WH904) and a modded B2 (WV787) Canberra's are on static display at [[Newark Air Museum]] in Nottinghamshire.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newarkairmuseum.org/Aircraft-List &quot;Aircraft List.&quot;] ''Newark Air Museum'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A PR.7 Canberra (WE139) is on display at the [[RAF Museum Hendon]] north London.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/research/collections/english-electric-canberra-pr3/ &quot;English Electric Canberra PR3.&quot;] ''RAF Museum'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A B.2 Canberra (WH725) is on display at the [[Imperial War Museum Duxford]] in Cambridgeshire.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iwm.org.uk/sites/default/files/public-document/List_of_Exhibits_at_IWM_Duxford_20140919.pdf &quot;List of exhibits at IWM Duxford.&quot;] ''Imperial War Museum Duxford'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A T.17 Canberra (WH740) is on static display at East Midlands Aeropark.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mag-umbraco-media-live.s3.amazonaws.com/1004/canberra.pdf &quot;English Electric Canberra B.2/T.17 (WH740).&quot;] ''East Midlands Aeropark'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A TT.18 Canberra (WJ639) is on static display at the [[North East Aircraft Museum]] near Sunderland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nelsam.org.uk/NEAM/Exhibits/History/WJ639.htm &quot;EE Canberra TT.18 (WJ639).&quot;] ''North East Aircraft Museum'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A B(I)8 Canberra (WT333) on display at Bruntingthorpe Proving Ground. It is being maintained to a serviceable condition and performs ground runs on open days.&lt;ref&gt;Healy, Tim. [http://www.leicestermercury.co.uk/Battle-Britain-Flight-appear-Bruntingthorpe-Cold/story-27680576-detail/story.html &quot;Battle of Britain Flight to appear at Bruntingthorpe Cold War Jets Open Day.&quot;] ''Leicester Mercury'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A T.4 Canberra (WE188) is on display at the Solway Aviation Museum, Carlisle Airport, Cumbria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.solway-aviation-museum.co.uk/?page_id=105 &quot;Aircraft.&quot;] ''Solway Aviation Museum'', Retrieved: 12 June 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
* Two British-built Canberras are registered to High Altitude Mapping Missions, Inc. of [[Spokane, Washington]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://registry.faa.gov/aircraftinquiry/NNum_Results.aspx?NNumbertxt=30UP &quot;N30UP.&quot;] ''FAA Register.'' Retrieved: 26 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://registry.faa.gov/aircraftinquiry/NNum_Results.aspx?NNumbertxt=40UP &quot;N40UP.&quot;] ''FAA Register.'' Retrieved: 26 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  These are N30UP, a Canberra B(I)8/B.2/6, originally operated as WT327,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bywat.co.uk/wt327.html &quot;B(I)8/B.2/6 – WT327.&quot;] ''bywat.co.'' Retrieved: 26 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and N40UP, a Canberra B6, originally operated as XH567.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bywat.co.uk/xh567.html &quot;B.6 – XH567.&quot;] ''bywat.co.'' Retrieved: 26 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* One British-built RAF Canberra B2, subsequently converted to TT18 (target tug) for use by the Fleet Air Arm is displayed outside at Airbase Arizona of the [[Commemorative Air Force]] at Falcon Field, [[Mesa, Arizona]]. This aircraft, originally WK142 in RAF and RN service, was sold in 1995 to an American buyer and carries N76764 as its US registration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azcaf.org/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* One British-built RAF Canberra B2, subsequently converted to TT18 (target tug) for use by the Fleet Air Arm is restored by the [http://www.valiantaircommand.com/#!blank/r6c4k Valiant Air Command] in Titusville, FL. This aircraft, WJ574, was involved in 'Operation Robin' flying chase to the overflight Canberra tasked with photographing the Soviet Union's early V-2 rocket tests at Kapustin Yar

==Specifications (Canberra B(I)6)==
[[File:English Electric Canberra.svg|right|350px|Orthographically projection of English Electric Canberra]]
[[File:Rolls-Royce Avon jet engine (Temora).jpg|thumb|Rolls-Royce Avon engine on display, Temora Aviation Museum, 2011]]
{{aircraft specifications
&lt;!-- if you do not understand how to use this template, please ask at [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Aircraft]] --&gt;
&lt;!-- please answer the following questions --&gt;
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=jet
|ref=''Combat Aircraft Recognition''&lt;ref&gt;March, P. R. ''Combat Aircraft Recognition''. London: Ian Allan Ltd, 1988. ISBN 0-7110-1730-1.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Now, fill out the specs.  Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses). If an item doesn't apply, like capacity, leave it blank. For additional lines, end your alt units with a right parenthesis &quot;)&quot; and start a new, fully formatted line beginning with an asterisk &quot;*&quot; --&gt;
|crew=3
|length main=65 ft 6 in
|length alt=19.96 m
|span main=64 ft 0 in
|span alt=19.51 m
|height main=15 ft 8 in
|height alt=4.77 m
|area main=960 ft²
|area alt=89.19 m²
|empty weight main=21,650 lb
|empty weight alt=9,820 kg
|loaded weight main=46,000 lb
|loaded weight alt=20,865 kg
|max takeoff weight main=55,000 lb
|max takeoff weight alt=24,948 kg
|engine (jet)=[[Rolls-Royce Avon]] R.A.7 Mk.109
|type of jet=[[turbojet]]s
|number of jets=2
|thrust main=7,400 lbf
|thrust alt=36 kN
|max speed main=Mach 0.88
|max speed alt=580 mph, 933 km/h
|max speed more=at 40,000 ft (12,192 m)
|combat radius main=810 mi
|combat radius alt=700 nm, 1,300 km
|ferry range main=3,380 mi
|ferry range alt=2,940 nm, 5,440 km
|ceiling main=48,000 ft
|ceiling alt=15,000 m
|climb rate main=3,400 ft/min
|climb rate alt=17 m/s
|loading main=48 lb/ft²
|loading alt=234 kg/m²
|thrust/weight=0.37
|guns=4 x [[20 mm caliber|20 mm]] [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404|Hispano Mk.V]] [[autocannon|cannon]] mounted in rear bomb bay (500 rounds/gun), ''or'' 2 x 0.30 in (7.62 mm) machine gun pods
|rockets=2 x unguided rocket pods with 37 2-inch (51 mm) rockets, ''or'' 2 x Matra rocket pods with 18 [[SNEB]] 68 mm rockets each
|missiles=A variety of missiles can be carried according to mission requirements, e.g: 2 x [[AS-30L]] [[air-to-surface missile]]s
|bombs=Total of 8,000 lb (3,628 kg) of payload can be mounted inside the internal [[bomb bay]] and on two underwing hardpoints, with the ability to carry a variety of bombs.&lt;br/&gt;Typically, the internal bomb bay can hold up to 9 x 500 lb (227 kg) bombs, ''or'' 6 x 1,000 lb (454 kg) bombs, ''or'' 1 x 4,000 lb (1,814 kg) bomb; while the pylons can hold 4 x 500 lb (227 kg) bombs, ''or'' 2 x 1,000 lb (454 kg) bombs.&lt;br/&gt;'''Nuclear weapons:''' in addition to conventional ordnance, the Canberra was also type-approved for [[tactical nuclear weapon]] delivery, including the [[Mark 7 nuclear bomb|Mk 7]], [[B28 nuclear bomb|B28 (Mod 2, 70 kiloton yield)]], [[B57 nuclear bomb|B57]] and [[B43 nuclear bomb|B43]] (as part of a [[Project E|joint program]] with the United States) plus the [[Red Beard (nuclear weapon)|Red Beard]] and [[WE.177]]A (Mod A, 10 kiloton yield) [[nuclear bomb]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Burnell, Brian. [http://nuclear-weapons.info/vw.htm#WE.177 &quot;WE.177.&quot;] ''Nuclear weapons: A Guide to British nuclear weapons''. Retrieved: 3 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; All [[nuclear weapons]] were carried internally.
|avionics=
}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Royal Air Force|British aircraft since World War II|Aviation}}
{{External media|topic= |width=20% |align=right |video1=[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ja54timM5Ws Canberra bomber at Avalon Airshow, 2003] |video2=[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wm2RTbal-_c  Pathe News report on the Canberra, 1951] |video3= [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j3PXQNEDnuA 1998 documentary on the Canberra]}}
{{aircontent
|related=
* [[Martin B-57 Canberra]]
* [[Martin RB-57D Canberra]]
* [[Martin/General Dynamics RB-57F Canberra]]
|similar aircraft=
* [[Arado Ar 234]]
* [[Ilyushin Il-28]]/[[Hong H-5]]
* [[Martin XB-51]]
* [[Sud-Ouest Vautour]]
|lists=
* [[List of aircraft of the RAAF]]
* [[List of aircraft of the Royal Air Force]]
* [[List of bomber aircraft]]
}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{Reflist|group=N|30em}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Anderton, David A. ''Martin B-57 Night Intruders &amp; General Dynamics RB-57F''. ''Aircraft in Profile, Volume 14''. Windsor, Berkshire, UK: Profile Publications Ltd., 1974, pp.&amp;nbsp;1–25. ISBN 0-85383-023-1.
* Barnes C.H. and D.N. James. ''Shorts Aircraft since 1900''. London: Putnam, 1989. ISBN 0-85177-819-4.
* Bell, T E. ''B-57 Canberra Units of the Vietnam War (Osprey Combat Aircraft #85)''. Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing Limited, 2011.  ISBN 978-1-84603-971-3.
* Brzoska, Michael and Frederic S. Pearson. ''Arms and Warfare: Escalation, De-escalation, and Negotiation''.  Columbia, South Carolina: University of South Carolina Press, 1994. ISBN 0-87249-982-0.
* Buttler, Tony. ''British Secret Projects Fighters and Bombers 1935–1950''. Earl Shilton, Leicester, UK: Midland Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-85780-179-2.
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1949/1949%20-%201999.html ''Canberra: Design Analysis of Britain's First Jet Bomber''.] ''[[Flight International|Flight]],'' 15 December 1949, pp.&amp;nbsp;766–772.
* Chant, Christopher. ''A Compendium of Armaments and Military Hardware''. London: Routledge, 1987. ISBN 0-7102-0720-4.
* Cohen, Michael Joseph. ''Fighting World War Three from the Middle East: Allied Contingency Plans, 1945–1954''. London: Routledge, 1997. ISBN 0-7146-4720-9.
* Delve, Ken. ''Canberra&amp;nbsp;... forty years and thriving still''. ''[[Air International]]'', Vol. 36, No. 6, June 1989, pp.&amp;nbsp;296–306. Bromley, UK: Fine Scroll. {{ISSN|0306-5634}}.
* Donald, David. ''The Pocket Guide to Military Aircraft''. London: Temple Press, 1986. ISBN 0-600-55002-8.
* Fensch, Thomas. ''The C.I.A. and the U-2 Program: 1954–1974''. London: New Century Books, 2001. ISBN 0-930751-09-4.
* Freedman, Lawrence. ''The Official History of the Falklands Campaign: Volume II, War and Diplomacy''. London: Routledge, 2005. ISBN 978-0-7146-5207-8.
* Geiger, Till. [https://books.google.com/books?id=M75xrc2FbcEC&amp;pg=PA165&amp;dq=English+Electric+Canberra&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=iOlJTdjOKZO2hAfg6e2sDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwAzg8#v=onepage&amp;q=Canberra&amp;f=false ''Britain and the Economic Problem of the Cold War: the Political Economy and the Economic Impact of the British Defence Effort, 1945–1955''.] Burlington, Vermont: Ashgate Publishing, 2004. ISBN 0-7546-0287-7.
* Gunston, Bill. ''Bombers of the West''.  London: Ian Allan Ltd., 1973, pp.&amp;nbsp;13–30. ISBN 0-7110-0456-0.
* Gunston, Bill and Peter Gilchrist. ''Jet Bombers: From the Messerschmitt Me 262 to the Stealth B-2''. Osprey, 1993. ISBN 1-85532-258-7.
* Hack, Karl. ''Defence and Decolonisation in Southeast Asia: Britain, Malaya and Singapore, 1941–1968''. London: Routledge, 2001. ISBN 0-7007-1303-4.
* Halley, James J. ''The Squadrons of the Royal Air Force''. Tonbridge, Kent, UK: Air Britain (Historians), 1980. ISBN 0-85130-083-9.
* Halpenny, Bruce Barrymore. ''[[English Electric Canberra (book)|English Electric Canberra: The History and Development of a Classic Jet]]''. London: Leo Cooper Ltd., 2005. ISBN 1-84415-242-1.
* Halvorson, Lance. ''Sixty Years of the Canberra Bomber''. ''Wings'', Vol. 61, No. 4, December 2009, pp.&amp;nbsp;10–19. RAAF Association. Coogee, Australia: Flight Publishing. {{ISSN|0043-5880}}.
* Huertas, Salvador Mafé. ''Canberras Over the Falklands: Wartime Exploits of a Venerable Jet Bomber''. ''[[Air Enthusiast]]'', No. 66, November/December 1996, pp.&amp;nbsp;61–65. Stamford, UK: Key Publishing. {{ISSN|0143-5450}}.
* Jefford, C.G.(Ed.) [http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/research/documents/Journal%2026%20-%20Seminar%20the%20RAF%20and%20Nuclear%20Weapons%201960-98.pdf ''The RAF and Nuclear Weapons, 1960–1998.''] London: Royal Air Force Historical Society, 2001.
* Jones, Barry. ''Bomber Command Goes Propless''. ''Aeroplane'', Volume 34, Issue 10, October 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;83–88.
* Jones, Barry. ''A Nice Little Earner.&quot; ''Aeroplane'', Volume 34, Issue 10, October 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;93–97.
* Kavic, Lorne J. ''India's Quest for Security: Defence Policies, 1947–1965''. Berkeley, California: University of California Press, 1967.
* Kinzey, Bert. ''F-111 Aardvark in Detail and Scale'' (Vol. IV). Fallbrook, California: Aero Publishers, 1982. ISBN 978-0-85368-512-8.
* Law, John. [https://books.google.com/books?id=8Chz2rM0HVIC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Aircraft Stories: Decentering the Object in Technoscience.''] Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-8223-2824-0.
* Lake, Jon. ''Canberra PR.9: Supreme Reconnaissance Platform''. ''Air International'', Vol. 62, No. 3, March 2002, pp.&amp;nbsp;156–163. Stamford, UK: Key Publishing. {{ISSN|0306-5634}}.
* Lake, Jon. ''EE Canberra in RAF Service: Part One: The Bomber Years''. ''Air International'', Vol. 71, No 2, August 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;38–43. Stamford, UK: Key Publishing. {{ISSN|0306-5634}}.
* Lake, Jon. ''EE Canberra in RAF Service: Part Two''. ''Air International'', Vol. 71, No 3, September 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;30–39. Stamford, UK: Key Publishing. {{ISSN|0306-5634}}.
* Lake, Jon. ''Wyton's Cold War Spyplanes: No. 51 Squadron Canberras''. ''International Air Power Review'', Volume 1, 2001, pp.&amp;nbsp;130–137. Norwalk, Connecticut: AirTime Publishing. ISBN 1-880588-33-1. {{ISSN|1473-9917}}.
* Lewis, Peter. ''British Racing and Record Breaking Aircraft''. London: Putnam, 1970. ISBN 0-370-00067-6.
* Mason, Francis K. ''The British Bomber since 1914''. London: Putnam, 1994. ISBN 0-85177-861-5.
* Nicholas, Jack. &quot;Big Bangs For A Buck: Britain's Tactical Nuclear Forces 1960–1998&quot;. ''Air International'', Vol. 69, No. 1, July 2005, pp. 45–49. {{ISSN|0306-5634}}.
* Nuñez Padín, Jorge. [http://www.fuerzasaeronavales.com/?p=46 Fuerzas Aeronavales ''Canberra BMK.62 &amp; TMK.64 – Serie Fuerza Aerea Nº11''.] Bahía Blanca, Argentina:, 2006. ISBN n/a.
* Oliver, David. ''British Combat Aircraft in Action Since 1945''. London: Ian Allen, 1987. ISBN 978-0-7110-1678-1.
* Paterson, Robert H. ''Britain's Strategic Nuclear Deterrent: From Before the V-bomber to Beyond Trident''. London: Routledge, 1997. ISBN 0-7146-4740-3.
* Peden, G. C. ''Arms, Economics and British Strategy: from Dreadnoughts to Hyrdrogen Bombs''. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2007. ISBN 0-521-86748-7.
* Petter-Bowyer, Peter J. H. [https://books.google.com/books?id=akwPLOZMZYIC&amp;pg=PA52&amp;dq=Canberra+bomber&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=7vlKTeynEYOKhQfCs_WrDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Canberra&amp;f=false ''Winds of Destruction: The Autobiography of a Rhodesian Combat Pilot''.] Johannesburg, South Africa: 30° South Publishers, 2005. ISBN 0-9584890-3-3.
* Polmar, Norman. ''Spyplane: The U-2 History Declassified''. London: Zenith Imprint, 2001. ISBN 0-7603-0957-4.
* Ransom, Stephen and Robert Fairclough. ''English Electric Aircraft and Their Predecessors''. London: Putnam, 1987. ISBN 0-85177-806-2.
* Stephens, Alan. ''Power Plus Attitude: Ideas, Strategy and Doctrine in the Royal Australian Air Force, 1921–1991''. Canberra, Australia: AGPS Press, 1992. ISBN 0-644-24388-0.
* van der Aart, Dick. ''Aerial Espionage''. Shrewsbury, UK: Airlife Publishing ltd., 1985. ISBN 0-906393-52-3.
* Varble, Derek. [https://books.google.com/books?id=MrP3kgd4sf8C&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=English+Electric+Canberra&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=e_FJTbrpKI2r8QPi9uGbDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CFEQ6AEwBzg8#v=onepage&amp;q=Canberra&amp;f=false ''The Suez Crisis 1956''.] Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 2003. ISBN 1-84176-418-3.
* &quot;Venezuela Refurbishes Her Aerial Sombrero&quot;. ''[[Air International|Air Enthusiast]]'', Volume 5 Number 4, September 1973, pp. 118–124, 150. 
* Wagner, Paul J. [https://books.google.com/books?id=8w6wi6T1TU0C&amp;pg=PA14&amp;dq=English+Electric+Canberra&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=iOlJTdjOKZO2hAfg6e2sDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwBTg8#v=onepage&amp;q=English%20Electric%20Canberra&amp;f=false ''Air Force Tac Recce Aircraft: NATO and Non-aligned Western European Air Force Tactical Reconnaissance Aircraft of the Cold War''.] Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania: Dorrance Publishing, 2009. ISBN 1-4349-9458-9.
* Walker, R. A. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1969/1969%20-%200851.html &quot;The Canberra is 20.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 8 May 1969, pp.&amp;nbsp;758–764.
* Wilson, Stewart. ''Lincoln, Canberra and F-111 in Australian Service''. Weston Creek, ACT, Australia: Aerospace Publications, 1989. ISBN 0-9587978-3-8.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|English Electric Canberra}}
* [http://www.nasa.gov/missions/research/b-57_feature.html NASA Feature on B-57 at 59]
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1952/1952%20-%200163.html &quot;Background to a Bomber&quot;] a 1952 ''Flight'' article on the Canberra
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1954/1954%20-%200739.html ''Holder of 13 world records'' – a 1954 advertisement for the Canberra]
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1956/1956%20-%200182.html &quot;The Capable Canberra&quot;] a 1956 ''Flight'' article
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1958/1958%20-%200318.html &quot;The Canberra Story – Design and Development of a Very Famous Aeroplane&quot;] a 1957 ''Flight'' article on the origins of the Canberra
* [http://vintagetin.net/Canberra/ High-resolution virtual tour of Canberra TT.18 WJ574 involved in 'Operation Robin' in 1953]

{{English Electric aircraft}}
{{Swedish military aircraft}}

[[Category:British bomber aircraft 1940–1949]]
[[Category:British military reconnaissance aircraft 1940–1949]]
[[Category:English Electric aircraft|Canberra]]
[[Category:Signals intelligence]]
[[Category:1951 introductions]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Twinjets]]</text>
      <sha1>lm2arfcfixhnrzu3suonp2ti7pf9fdm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
