<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ernesto Cabruna</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38973477</id>
    <revision>
      <id>722999917</id>
      <parentid>708859240</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-31T11:13:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KasparBot</username>
        <id>24420788</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>migrating [[Wikipedia:Persondata|Persondata]] to Wikidata, [[toollabs:kasparbot/persondata/|please help]], see [[toollabs:kasparbot/persondata/challenge.php/article/Ernesto Cabruna|challenges for this article]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9366">{{Infobox military person
| name          = Ernesto Cabruna
| image         =
| caption       =
| birth_date          = 2 June 1889
| death_date          = 9 January 1960 (aged 70)
| placeofburial_label = [[Vittoriale]], Italy
| placeofburial = [[Gabrielle D'Annunzio]]'s Vittoriale estate
| birth_place  = [[Tortona]], the [[Kingdom of Italy]]
| death_place  =
| placeofburial_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
| nickname      =
| allegiance    = Italy
| branch        = ''[[Corpo Aeronautico Militare]]''
| serviceyears  = 1907–1932
| rank          = ''Capitano''
| unit          = ''[[Carabinier#Law enforcement carabiniers|Carabinieri Reali]]''&lt;br&gt;''28a Squadriglia''&lt;br&gt;''[[80a Squadriglia]]''&lt;br&gt;''[[77a Squadriglia]]''&lt;br&gt;''39a Squadriglia''
| commands      =
| battles       =
| awards        =One Bronze, one Silver, and one Gold award to the [[Medal for Military Valor]]
| relations     =
| laterwork     = [[Aide de camp]] for Italy's Aviation [[Chief of Staff]]
}}

''Capitano'' '''Ernesto Cabruna''' (1889–1960) was a professional soldier who became a World War I [[flying ace]] credited with eight aerial victories. He served in Italy's military police, beginning in 1907. After service in [[Libya]] and [[Rhodes]], he received a Bronze [[Medal for Military Valor]] a year after Italy's involvement in World War I began. He turned to aviation, became a pilot, and as such earned his first Silver Medal for Military Valor at the end of 1917.

In 1918, Cabruna twice singlehandedly attacked swarms of enemy aircraft, winning victories both times. He was also raised into the officers' ranks. On 26 September 1918, he broke his [[clavicle]]. Two days later, he forced his way back to flying to participate in the [[Battle of Vittorio Veneto]]. He claimed his final two aerial victories on 25 October. The day before the [[Austro-Hungarian]] surrender, 2 November 1918, Cabruna strafed two of their airplanes parked on their own airfield. He then won a Gold award of the Medal for Military Valor.

Cabruna remained in military service postwar, serving as [[Aide de Camp]] to the Aviation [[Chief of Staff]]. He became an intimate of proto-fascist poet [[Gabrielle D'Annunzio]]. He left the military on 2 June 1932, having served his nation a quarter of a century. When he died on 9 January 1960, he was interred on D'Annunzio's estate. His [[Spad VII]] fighter plane is enshrined in the [[Italian Air Force Museum]].

==Early life and service==
Ernesto Cabruna was born on 2 June 1889 in [[Tortona]], the [[Kingdom of Italy]]. His family were merchants. Young Cabruna attended technical school until, on 18 October 1907, he joined the ''[[Carabinier#Law enforcement carabiniers|Carabinieri Reali]]'', Italy's version of military police. The following year, he performed commendably during the [[1908 Messina earthquake]]. On 30 September 1911, he was promoted to ''[[Brigadier#Non-commissioned rank|Vice Brigadiere]]''. From April 1912 to May 1913, he was posted to [[Tripolitania]], [[Libya]]. He later took part in the occupation of [[Rhodes]].&lt;ref name=fronts135&gt;Franks et al 1997, pp. 135–136.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=aces28&gt;Varriale 2009, pp. 28–29.&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War I==
On 31 January 1915, Cabruna was promoted to Brigadier. In October 1915, he was posted to the 10th Company of the Turin and Allievi (Cadets) Legion. On 15 May 1916, while stationed near [[Asiago]], he rescued victims of an [[Austro-Hungarian]] bombing raid&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt; while under fire.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt; His valor was rewarded with a Bronze [[Medal for Military Valor]]. In July 1916, Cabruna reported to [[Torino]] for pilot's training. He was granted two licenses for the [[Farman|Maurice Farman 14]], awarded on 6 October and 16 November 1916. He was posted to ''29a Squadriglia'' on 28 December 1916.&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt; He would fly [[reconnaissance]] missions while so assigned.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt;

Ernesto Cabruna flew his first combat [[sortie]] on 2 January 1917. On 31 May 1917, he was promoted to ''[[Maresciallo]]''. After completing training on [[Nieuport]] fighters, he was assigned to a [[fighter squadron]], ''84a Squadriglia''. On 21 September 1917, he was transferred to another fighter squadron, ''[[80a Squadriglia]]''. He scored his first aerial victory on 26 October, and another on 5 December. By the end of 1917, Cabruna merited a Silver award of the Medal for Military Valor.&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt;

[[File:SPAD SVII Ernesto Cabruna 2009-06-06.jpg|thumb|Restoration of the Spad VII that Ernesto Cabruna flew. It bears ''77a Squadriglia'' insignia, as well as Cabruna's personal markings.]]

On 26 January 1918, he was transferred to another fighter squadron, ''[[77a Squadriglia]]''.&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt; Their squadron symbol was a red heart on a while circle; aft of this, Cabruna appended the coat of arms of his native city of Tortona.&lt;ref name=spad67&gt;Guttman 2001, p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

He would score a victory for his new squadron on 12 March 1918.&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt; On 29 March 1918, he broke away from a unit patrol and singlehanded attacked 11 enemy aircraft. Cabruna fired several bursts of machine gun fire into a red fighter, which exited in an abrupt dive. This daring feat was featured on the cover of a leading Italian magazine, ''[[Domenica del Corriere]]''; the illustration was by [[Achille Beltrame]].  Although existing Austro-Hungarian aviation loss files fail to support it, Cabruna was credited with the victory.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt;

On 4 April 1918, he was [[Commission (document)|commissioned]] into the officers' ranks in a [[battlefield promotion]]. On 15 June 1918, the swarm of enemy planes numbered 30, but Cabruna again plunged into solo combat and downed his fifth victim to become an ace.&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt;

Cabruna shot down two more enemies in June, before hitting a dry spell.&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt; On 26 September 1918, he crashed an [[Ansaldo A.1 Balilla]] in a landing accident, breaking his collarbone. The new fighter had broken an oil line; spurting oil blinded Cabruna, and he was fortunate to survive the crashlanding.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt;

He was sidelined two days, then returned to flight duty for Italy's final offensive, the [[Battle of Vittorio Veneto]]. He claimed to have shot down two enemy aircraft on 25 October for his final aerial victories. On 2 November 1918, he strafed two enemy airplanes on the airfield at [[Aiello del Friuli|Aiello]] and destroyed them. The next day, the Austro-Hungarians surrendered. Cabruna would be awarded the Gold Medal for Military Valor for these latter day exploits.&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt;

==Post World War I==
The Bongiovanni commission report of 1 February 1919 confirmed eight of the nine victories that had been symbolized on Cabruna's [[Spad VII]]. He was credited with victories over seven enemy airplanes and an [[observation balloon]]. In April 1919, he was promoted to ''[[Lieutenant|Sottotenente]]''. He was also posted to ''39a Squadriglia'', where he became a familiar of [[Gabrielle D'Annunzio]].&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt; Cabruna joined in D'Annunzio's short-lived proto-fascist revolt against the Italian government. When this ended, the ace was unemployed and penniless.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt;

Cabruna re-entered service. In December 1923, he transferred from the ''Carabineri'' to the ''[[Regia Aeronautica]]''. He returned briefly to Libya. In 1925, he was promoted to ''Capitano''. He was assigned as [[Aide de Camp]] for the Aviation [[Chief of Staff]]. However, his career apparently floundered, and he was discharged on 2 June 1932&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt; for ill health.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt;

He became disgruntled with [[fascism]] after his departure from the military. During World War II, British military intelligence listed him as a member of the &quot;Free Italy&quot; organization, with the cover name of &quot;X-19&quot;.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt;

After World War II, Ernesto Cabruna chose life as a near-hermit. He died on 9 January 1960.&lt;ref name=aces28/&gt;

==Death and legacy==
Ernesto Cabruna died in [[Rapallo]] on 9 January 1960. He is buried on the premises of D'Annunzio's [[Vittoriale]] mansion. Cabruna's original Spad VII fighter is now displayed in the [[Italian Air Force Museum]].&lt;ref name=fronts135/&gt;

==Endnotes==
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{reflist}}

==References==
* [[Norman Franks|Franks, Norman]]; Guest, Russell; Alegi, Gregory.  ''Above the War Fronts: The British Two-seater Bomber Pilot and Observer Aces, the British Two-seater Fighter Observer Aces, and the Belgian, Italian, Austro-Hungarian and Russian Fighter Aces, 1914–1918: Volume 4 of Fighting Airmen of WWI Series: Volume 4 of Air Aces of WWI''. Grub Street, 1997. ISBN 1-898697-56-6, ISBN 978-1-898697-56-5.
* Guttman, Jon. ''SPAD VII Aces of World War 1''. Osprey Publishing, 2001. ISBN 1841762229, 9781841762227.
* Varriale, Paolo. ''Italian Aces of World War 1''. Osprey Pub Co, 2009. ISBN 978-1-84603-426-8.

{{wwi-air}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cabruna, Ernesto}}
[[Category:Italian aviators]]
[[Category:Italian World War I flying aces]]
[[Category:Italian military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:Italian Air Force personnel]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Gold Medal of Military Valor]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Medal of Military Valor]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Medal of Military Valor]]
[[Category:1889 births]]
[[Category:1960 deaths]]</text>
      <sha1>7ut1wsqmsbk20mvust7k13e3wcaahb5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
