<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>George Armstrong Custer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>102739</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750440111</id>
      <parentid>750266007</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T19:30:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.76.192.33</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="75101">{{Redirect|Custer}}
{{Infobox military person
| name                = George Armstrong Custer
| birth_date          = {{Birth date|1839|12|5}}
| death_date          = {{Death date and age|1876|6|25|1839|12|5}}
| birth_place         = [[New Rumley, Ohio]], [[United States]]
| death_place         = [[Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument|Little Bighorn]], [[Montana Territory]]
| placeofburial       = initially on the battlefield;&lt;br/&gt;later reinterred in [[West Point Cemetery]]
| placeofburial_label = Place of burial
| image               = Custer Bvt MG Geo A 1865 LC-BH831-365-crop.jpg
| caption             = Brevet Major General George Armstrong Custer in his field uniform on May 23, 1865 — the day of the [[Grand Review of the Armies]]
| nickname            = &quot;The Boy General&quot;; &quot;Ringlets&quot;
| allegiance          = United States&lt;br/&gt;[[Union (American Civil War)|Union]]
| branch              = [[United States Army]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Union Army]]
| serviceyears        = 1861–1876
| rank                = [[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|Lieutenant Colonel]]
[[File:Union army maj gen rank insignia.jpg|35px]] [[Brevet (military)|Brevet]] [[Major general (United States)|Major General]]
| commands            = [[Michigan Brigade]]&lt;br/&gt;
3rd Cavalry Division&lt;br/&gt;
2nd Cavalry Division&lt;br/&gt;
[[7th Cavalry Regiment]]
| unit                = 
| battles             = '''[[American Civil War]]'''
* [[First Battle of Bull Run]]
* [[Peninsula Campaign]]
* [[Battle of Antietam]]
* [[Battle of Chancellorsville]]
* [[Gettysburg Campaign]]
** [[Battle of Gettysburg]]
* [[Overland Campaign]]
** [[Battle of the Wilderness]]
** [[Battle of Yellow Tavern]]
** [[Battle of Trevilian Station]]
* [[Valley Campaigns of 1864]]
* [[Siege of Petersburg]]
* [[Appomattox Campaign]]
'''[[American Indian Wars]]'''
* [[Battle of Washita River]]
* [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]]{{KIA}}
| awards              =
| spouse              = [[Elizabeth Bacon Custer]]
| relations           = [[Thomas Custer]], brother&lt;br/&gt;
[[Boston Custer]], brother&lt;br/&gt;
[[James Calhoun (soldier)|James Calhoun]], brother-in-law
| signature           = [[File:George Armstrong Custer signature.svg|175px]]
}}
''' George Armstrong Custer''' (December 5, 1839 – June 25, 1876) was a [[United States Army]] officer and [[cavalry]] commander in the [[American Civil War]] and the [[American Indian Wars]]. Raised in [[Michigan]] and [[Ohio]], Custer was admitted to [[United States Military Academy|West Point]] in 1857, where he graduated last in his class in 1861. With the outbreak of the Civil War, Custer was called to serve with the [[Union Army]].

Custer developed a strong reputation during the Civil War. He participated in the first major engagement, the [[First Battle of Bull Run]] on July 21, 1861, near [[Washington, D.C.]] His association with several important officers helped his career, as did his success as a highly effective cavalry commander. Custer was  [[Brevet (military)|brevetted]] to [[Brigadier general (United States)|brigadier general]] less than a week before the [[Battle of Gettysburg]] where he personally led cavalry charges that prevented Confederate troops from turning the Union flank. In 1864 Custer was given another star, being brevetted to [[Major general (United States)|major general]] rank. At the conclusion of the [[Appomattox Campaign]], in which he and his troops played a decisive role, Custer was present at [[General-in-Chief of the Confederate States Army|General]] [[Robert E. Lee]]'s [[Surrender (military)|surrender]] to [[Ulysses  S. Grant|General Ulysses S. Grant]] on April 9, 1865.

After the Civil War, Custer remained a major general in the [[United States Volunteers]] until they were [[Demobilization|mustered out]] in February 1866. He reverted to his permanent rank of captain and was appointed a [[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|lieutenant colonel]] in the [[7th Cavalry Regiment]] in July 1866. He was dispatched to the west in 1867 to fight in the American Indian Wars. On June 25, 1876, while leading the 7th Cavalry Regiment at the [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]] in [[Montana Territory]] against a coalition of [[Tribe (Native American)|Native American tribes]], he and all of his regiment—which included two of his brothers—were killed. The battle is popularly known in American history as &quot;[[Battle of the Little Bighorn#The &quot;Last Stand&quot;|Custer's Last Stand]].&quot; Custer and his regiment were defeated so decisively at the Little Bighorn that it has overshadowed all of his prior achievements.

==Family and ancestry==
Custer's ancestors, Paulus and Gertrude Küster, immigrated to North America around 1693 from the [[Rhineland]] in Germany, probably among thousands of [[German Palatines|Palatine]] refugees whose passage was arranged by the [[Kingdom of England|English]] government to gain settlers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Wert, Jeffry D.|title=Custer: The Controversial Life of George Armstrong Custer|year=1996|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|location=New York|isbn=0-684-81043-3}}, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Connell, Evan S.|title=Son Of The Morning Star|location=San Francisco, California|publisher=North Point Press|year=1984|isbn=0-86547-160-6}}, p. 352.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to family letters, Custer was named after George Armstrong, a minister, in his devout mother's hope that her son might join the clergy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Merington |first=Margurite |title=The Custer Story: The Life and Intimate Letters of George A. Custer and His Wife Elizabeth|year=1987|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|location=Lincoln|isbn=0-8032-8138-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Birth, siblings and nicknames==
Custer was born in [[New Rumley, Ohio]], to Emanuel Henry Custer (1806–1892), a farmer and blacksmith, and Marie Ward Kirkpatrick (1807–1882).&lt;ref&gt;[[Media:1850 census Custer.jpg|Custer]] in the [[1850 US Census]] in North Township, [[Ohio]].&lt;/ref&gt; He had two younger brothers, [[Thomas Custer]] and [[Boston Custer]], who both died with him on the battlefield at Little Bighorn. His other full siblings were the family's youngest child, Margaret Custer, and Nevin Custer, who suffered from asthma and rheumatism. Custer also had several older half-siblings.&lt;ref&gt;Wert (1996), pp. 17–18.&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout his life Custer was known by a variety of nicknames. He was called &quot;Autie&quot; (his early attempt to pronounce his middle name) and Armstrong. During the Civil War, Custer was frequently termed &quot;The Boy General&quot; in the press, reflecting his promotion to [[Brigadier general (United States)|brigadier general]] at the age of 23; during his years on the [[Great Plains]] in the American Indian Wars, his troopers often referred to him with grudging admiration as &quot;Iron Butt&quot; and &quot;Hard Ass&quot; for his physical stamina in the saddle and his strict discipline, as well as with the more derisive &quot;Ringlets&quot; for his vanity about his appearance in general and his long, curling blond hair in particular.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Killing Custer: The Battle of Little Bighorn and the Fate of the Plains Indians|last=Welch|first=James|author2=Stekler, Paul|year=2007|publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Co.|location=|isbn=978-0-393-32939-1|page=60}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
[[File:George-a-custer west-point.jpg|thumb|[[United States Military Academy|USMA]] Cadet George Armstrong &quot;Autie&quot; Custer, ca. 1859]]
Custer spent much of his boyhood living with his half-sister and brother-in-law in [[Monroe, Michigan]], where he attended school. Before entering the [[United States Military Academy]], Custer attended the McNeely Normal School, later known as Hopedale Normal College, in [[Hopedale, Ohio]]. While attending Hopedale, Custer, together with classmate William Enos Emery, was known to have carried coal to help pay for their room and board. After graduating from McNeely Normal School in 1856, Custer taught school in [[Cadiz, Ohio]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Custer Lives Bio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=General George Custer Biography, US 7th Cavalry|url=http://custerlives.com/custer1.htm|publisher=Custer Lives!|accessdate=16 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Custer entered West Point as a cadet on July 1, 1857, to become a member of the class of 1862. At the time, West Point's course of study was five years long. With the outbreak of the [[American Civil War]], the course was shortened to four years allowing Custer and his class to graduate on June 24, 1861. He was last in a class of 34 cadets.&lt;ref name=&quot;e196&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Eicher |first=John H. |last2=Eicher |first2=David J. |title=Civil War High Commands|location=Stanford, California|publisher=Stanford University Press|year=2001|isbn=0-8047-3641-3}} p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt;  Throughout his life, Custer tested boundaries and rules. In his four years at West Point, he amassed a record-total of 726 demerits, one of the worst conduct records in the history of the academy. A fellow cadet recalled Custer as declaring there were only two places in a class, the head and the foot, and since he had no desire to be the head, he aspired to be the foot. A roommate noted, &quot;It was all right with George Custer, whether he knew his lesson or not: he simply did not allow it to trouble him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=George Custer: Facts Summary Information|url=http://www.historynet.com|accessdate=2014-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under ordinary national conditions, Custer's low class rank would represent a ticket to an obscure posting, but Custer had the ironic fortune to graduate as the Civil War broke out. During his rocky tenure at the Academy, Custer came close to expulsion in each of his three years, due to excessive demerits. Many of these were awarded for pulling pranks on fellow cadets.{{Citation needed|date = August 2012}}

==Civil War==

===McClellan and Pleasonton===
[[File:CusterandWashington01.jpg|thumb|Custer with ex-classmate, friend, and captured Confederate prisoner, Lieutenant James Barroll Washington, an aide to [[Joseph E. Johnston|General Johnston]], at Fair Oaks, Virginia, 1862]]
Custer was commissioned a [[US Second Lieutenant|second lieutenant]] in the 2nd U.S. Cavalry Regiment and was assigned to drilling volunteers in Washington, D.C. On July 21, 1861, he was with his regiment at the [[First Battle of Bull Run]] during the [[Manassas Campaign]], where Army commander [[Winfield Scott]] detailed him to carry messages to Major General [[Irvin McDowell]]. After the battle, he continued participating in the defenses of Washington D.C. until October when he was sick and absent from his unit until February 1862. In March, he participated with the 2nd Cavalry in the [[Peninsula Campaign]] (March to August) in Virginia until April 4.

On April 5, he served in the [[5th Cavalry Regiment]] and participated in the [[Siege of Yorktown (1862)|Siege of Yorktown]], from April 5 to and May 4 and was aide to [[Major general (United States)|Major General]] [[George B. McClellan]]; McClellan was in command of the [[Army of the Potomac]] during the Peninsula Campaign. On May 24, 1862, during the pursuit of [[Confederate States Army|Confederate]] General [[Joseph E. Johnston]] up the Peninsula, when General Barnard and his staff were reconnoitering a potential crossing point on the [[Chickahominy River]], they stopped, and Custer overheard his commander mutter to himself, &quot;I wish I knew how deep it is.&quot; Custer dashed forward on his horse out to the middle of the river and turned to the astonished officers of the staff and shouted triumphantly, &quot;That's how deep it is, Mr. General!&quot; Custer then was allowed to lead an attack with four companies of the 4th Michigan Infantry across the [[Chickahominy River]] above New Bridge. The attack was successful, resulting in the capture of 50 Confederate soldiers and the seizing of the first Confederate battle flag of the war. McClellan, termed it a &quot;very gallant affair&quot; and congratulated Custer personally. In his role as aide-de-camp to McClellan, Custer began his life-long pursuit of publicity.&lt;ref&gt;Tagg, Larry. (1988). ''The Generals Of Gettysburg: Appraisal Of The Leaders Of America's Greatest Battle''. Savas Publishing Company, ISBN 1-882810-30-9, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; Custer was promoted to the rank of [[Captain (Union Army)|captain]] on June 5, 1862. On July 17, he was reverted to the rank of [[First Lieutenant|first lieutenant]]. He participated in the [[Maryland Campaign]] in September to October, the [[Battle of South Mountain]] on September 14, the [[Battle of Antietam]] on September 17, and the March to [[Warrenton, Virginia]] in October.

[[File:Lincoln and generals at Antietam.jpg|thumb|Custer (extreme right) with [[Abraham Lincoln|President Lincoln]], [[George B. McClellan|General McClellan]] and other officers at the [[Battle of Antietam]], 1862]]

On June 9, 1863, Custer became aid to Brevet Lieutenant Colonel [[Alfred Pleasonton]] (rank since September 17, 1862), who was now commanding the Cavalry Corps, Army of the Potomac (June 7 to March 26, 1864); after the [[Battle of Chancellorsville]] (April 30-May 6, 1863), Pleasonton's (Brigadier General, July 16, 1862, U.S. Volunteers) first assignment was to locate the army of [[Robert E. Lee]], moving north through the [[Shenandoah Valley]] in the beginning of the [[Gettysburg Campaign]].

===Brigade command and Gettysburg===
[[File:Custer-Pleasonton.jpg|thumb|Custer (left) with [[Alfred Pleasonton|General Pleasonton]] on horseback in [[Falmouth, Virginia]]]]
[[File:Custer&amp;Pleasonton1863.jpg|thumb|Custer (left) with Alfred Pleasonton in Autumn 1863]]
Pleasonton was promoted on June 22, 1863 to Major General of U.S. Volunteers. On June 29, two days prior to the [[Battle of Gettysburg]] (July 1–3), Pleasonton promoted Custer to brigadier general of volunteers, commanding the [[Michigan Brigade|Michigan Cavalry Brigade]] (&quot;Wolverines&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;National Park Service http://www.nps.gov/libi/learn/historyculture/lt-col-george-armstrong-custer.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Despite having no direct command experience, Custer became one of the youngest generals in the [[Union Army]] at age 23. Two other captains—[[Wesley Merritt]] and [[Elon J. Farnsworth]]—were promoted along with Custer, although they did have command experience. Custer lost no time in implanting his aggressive character on his brigade, part of the division of Brigadier General [[Judson Kilpatrick]]. He fought against the Confederate cavalry of Major General [[J.E.B. Stuart]] at [[Battle of Hanover|Hanover]] and [[Battle of Hunterstown|Hunterstown]], on the way to the main event at Gettysburg.{{Citation needed|date = August 2012}}

In his first command, Custer affected a showy, personalized uniform style that alienated his men, but he won them over with his readiness to lead attacks from the front (in contrast to many other officers); his men began to adopt elements of his uniform, especially the red neckerchief. Custer distinguished himself by fearless, aggressive actions in some of the numerous cavalry engagements that started off the campaign, beginning with the  [[Battle of Aldie]] on June 17. Pleasonton was Custer's introduction to the world of extravagant uniforms and political maneuvering, and the young lieutenant had become his protégé, serving on Pleasonton's staff. Custer was quoted as saying that &quot;no father could love his son more than General Pleasonton loves me.&quot;

Custer's style of battle was often claimed to be reckless or foolhardy, but military planning was always the basis of every Custer &quot;dash&quot;. As Marguerite Merrington explains in ''The Custer Story in Letters'', &quot;George Custer meticulously scouted every battlefield, gauged the enemies{{sic}} weak points and strengths, ascertained the best line of attack and only after he was satisfied was the 'Custer Dash' with a Michigan yell focused with complete surprise on the enemy in routing them every time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Marguerite Merrington, ''The Custer Story In Letters''|University of Nebraska Press, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; One of his greatest attributes during the Civil War was what Custer wrote of as &quot;luck&quot; and he needed it to survive some of these charges.{{Citation needed|date = August 2012}}

Custer established a reputation as an aggressive cavalry brigade commander willing to take personal risks by leading his [[Michigan Brigade]] into battle, such as the mounted charges at [[Battle of Hunterstown|Hunterstown]] and [[East Cavalry Field]] at the [[Battle of Gettysburg]]. At Hunterstown, in an ill-considered charge ordered by Kilpatrick against the brigade of [[Wade Hampton III|Wade Hampton]], Custer fell from his wounded horse directly before the enemy and became the target of numerous enemy rifles. He was rescued by Private Norvell Francis Churchill of the 1st Michigan Cavalry, who galloped up, shot Custer's nearest assailant, and allowed Custer to mount behind him for a dash to safety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Connell|first1=Mike|title=Custer and the Man Who Saved Him|url=http://archive.thetimesherald.com/article/20111009/OPINION02/110090313/Custer-man-who-saved-him|website=The Times Herald|publisher=Gannett|accessdate=10 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of Custer's finest hours in the Civil War occurred just east of Gettysburg on July 3, 1863. In conjunction with [[Pickett's Charge]] to the west, Robert E. Lee had dispatched Stuart's cavalry on a mission into the rear of the Union Army. Custer encountered the Union cavalry division of Brigadier General [[David McMurtrie Gregg]] directly in the path of Stuart's horsemen. He convinced Gregg to allow him to stay and fight, while his own division was stationed to the south out of the action. At [[Battle of Gettysburg, Third Day cavalry battles|East Cavalry Field]], hours of charges and hand-to-hand combat ensued. Custer led a mounted charge of the 1st Michigan Cavalry, breaking the back of the Confederate assault. Custer's brigade lost 257 men at Gettysburg, the highest loss of any Union cavalry brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Tagg, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;I challenge the annals of warfare to produce a more brilliant or successful charge of cavalry&quot;, Custer wrote in his report.&lt;ref&gt;Robbins, James S., ''Last in their Class: Custer, Pickett and the Goats of West Point'' (2006), p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt; On July 3, he received the rank of Brevet Major, &quot;For Gallant And Meritorious Services At The Battle of Gettysburg, Pa.&quot; Custer was wounded during action at the [[Battle of Culpeper Court House]] in Virginia on September 13.

===Marriage===
[[File:George Armstrong Custer and Elizabeth Bacon Custer - Brady-Handy.jpg|thumb|George and Libbie Custer, 1864]]
On February 9, 1864, Custer married [[Elizabeth Bacon Custer|Elizabeth Clift Bacon]] (1842–1933), whom he had first seen when he was ten years old.&lt;ref&gt;Connell (1984), p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt; He had been socially introduced to her in November 1862, when home in Monroe on leave. She was not initially impressed with him,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Barnett |first=Louise |title=Touched by Fire: The Life, Death, and Afterlife of George Armstrong Custer|year=1996|publisher=Henry Holt and Company, Inc.|location=New York|isbn=0-8050-3720-9}}, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; and her father, Judge Daniel Bacon, disapproved of Custer as a match because he was the son of a blacksmith. It was not until well after Custer had been promoted to the rank of brevet brigadier general that he gained the approval of Judge Bacon. He married Elizabeth Bacon fourteen months after they formally met.&lt;ref&gt;Connell (1984), pp. 113–114.&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1868, following the [[Battle of Washita River]], Custer was alleged (by Captain [[Frederick Benteen]], chief of scouts Ben Clark, and Cheyenne oral tradition) to have unofficially married [[Mo-nah-se-tah]], daughter of the Cheyenne chief Little Rock in the winter or early spring of 1868–1869 (Little Rock was killed in the one-day action at Washita on November 27).&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-107&quot;&gt;Utley, Robert M. (2001). ''Cavalier in Buckskin: George Armstrong Custer and the Western Military Frontier,'' revised edition. Norman, OK: University of Oklahoma Press. ISBN 0-8061-3387-2, p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt; Mo-nah-se-tah gave birth to a child in January 1869, two months after the Washita battle. Cheyenne oral history tells that she also bore a second child, fathered by Custer in late 1869. Some historians, however, believe that Custer had become sterile after contracting gonorrhea while at West Point and that the father was, in actuality, his brother Thomas.&lt;ref&gt;Wert (1996), pp. 287–288.&lt;/ref&gt; A descendant of the second child, who goes by the name Gail Custer, wrote a book about the affair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Princess_Monahsetah.html?id=EnUVAQAAMAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y|title=Princess Monahsetah|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Valley and Appomattox===
In 1864, with the Cavalry Corps of the Army of the Potomac reorganized under the command of Major General [[Philip Sheridan]], Custer (now commanding the 3rd Division) led his &quot;Wolverines&quot; to the Shenandoah Valley where by the year's end they defeated the army of [[Lt. Gen. (CSA)|Confederate Lieutenant General]] [[Jubal Early]] in the [[Valley Campaigns of 1864]]. During May and June, Sheridan and Custer (Captain, 5th Cavalry, May 8 and Brevet Lieutenant Colonel, May 11) took part in cavalry actions supporting the [[Overland Campaign]], including the [[Battle of the Wilderness]] (after which Custer ascended to [[division (military)|division]] command), and the [[Battle of Yellow Tavern]] (where [[J.E.B. Stuart]] was mortally wounded). In the largest all-cavalry engagement of the war, the [[Battle of Trevilian Station]], in which Sheridan sought to destroy the [[Virginia Central Railroad]] and the Confederates' western resupply route, Custer captured [[Wade Hampton III|Hampton's]] divisional train, but was then cut off and suffered heavy losses (including having his division's trains overrun and his personal baggage captured by the enemy) before being relieved. When Lieutenant General Early was then ordered to move down the Shenandoah Valley and threaten [[Washington, D.C.]], Custer's division was again dispatched under Sheridan. In the [[Valley Campaigns of 1864]], they pursued the Confederates at the [[Battle of Opequon|Third Battle of Winchester]] and effectively destroyed Early's army during Sheridan's [[Battle of Cedar Creek|counterattack at Cedar Creek]].

Sheridan and Custer, having defeated Early, returned to the main Union Army lines at the [[Siege of Petersburg]], where they spent the winter. In April 1865 the Confederate lines finally broke, and Robert E. Lee began his [[Appomattox Campaign|retreat]] to [[Appomattox Court House National Historical Park|Appomattox Court House]], pursued by the Union cavalry. Custer distinguished himself by his actions at [[Battle of Waynesboro, Virginia|Waynesboro]], [[Battle of Dinwiddie Court House|Dinwiddie Court House]], and [[Battle of Five Forks|Five Forks]]. His division blocked Lee's retreat on its final day and received the first flag of truce from the Confederate force. Custer was present at the surrender at Appomattox Court House and the table upon which the surrender was signed was presented to him as a gift for his wife by [[Philip Sheridan|General Philip Sheridan]], who included a note to her praising Custer's gallantry. She treasured the gift of the historical table, which is now in the [[Smithsonian Institution]].&lt;ref&gt;Wert, p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the close of the war Custer received [[brevet (military)|brevet]] promotions to brigadier general and major general (as a result of a plea by his patron General Sheridan)&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-40&quot;/&gt; on March 13, 1865, in the regular army, and major general of volunteers&lt;ref name=&quot;e196&quot;/&gt; on April 15, 1865. As with most wartime promotions, even when issued under the regular army, these senior ranks were only temporary.

On April 25, after the war officially ended, Custer had his men search for, then illegally seize a large, prize racehorse &quot;Don Juan&quot; near Clarksville, Virginia, worth then an estimated $10,000 (several hundred thousand today), along with his written pedigree. Custer rode Don Juan in the grand review victory parade in Washington, D.C. on May 23, creating a sensation when the scared thoroughbred bolted. The owner, Richard Gaines, wrote to General Grant, who then ordered Custer to return the horse to Gaines, but he did not, instead hiding the horse and winning a race with it the next year, before the horse died suddenly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smithsonianmag.com/ist/?next=history/when-custer-stole-thoroughbred-180956961/?no-ist |title=History, Travel, Arts, Science, People, Places &amp;#124; Smithsonian |publisher=Smithsonianmag.com |date= |accessdate=2016-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Promotions and ranks ===
Custer's promotions and ranks including his six brevet [temporary] promotions which were all for gallant and meritorious services at five different battles and one campaign:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Gazetteer/Places/America/United_States/Army/USMA/Cullums_Register/1966*.html|title=George Armstrong Custer: West Point Class of June 24, 1861 • Cullum's Register|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Second Lieutenant, 2nd Cavalry: June 24, 1861&lt;br&gt;
First Lieutenant, 5th Cavalry: July 17, 1862&lt;br&gt;
Captain Staff, Additional Aide-De-Camp: June 5, 1862&lt;br&gt;
Brigadier General, U.S. Volunteers: June 29, 1863&lt;br&gt;
Brevet Major, July 3, 1863 (Battle of Gettysburg, Pennsylvania)&lt;br&gt;

Captain, 5th Cavalry: May 8, 1864&lt;br&gt;
Brevet Lieutenant Colonel: May 11, 1864 (Battle of Yellow Tavern - Combat at Meadow)&lt;br&gt;

Brevet Colonel: September 19, 1864(Battle of Winchester, Virginia)&lt;br&gt;
Brevet Major General, U.S. Volunteers: October 19, 1864 (Battle of Winchester and Fisher's Hill, Virginia)&lt;br&gt;
Brevet Brigadier General, U.S. Army, March 13, 1865 (Battle of Five Forks, Virginia)&lt;br&gt;
Brevet Major General, U.S. Army: March 13, 1865 (The campaign ending in the surrender of the Army of Northern Virginia)&lt;br&gt;

Major General, U.S. Volunteers: April 15, 1865&lt;br&gt;
Mustered out of Volunteer Service: February 1, 1866&lt;br&gt;

Lieutenant Colonel, 7th Cavalry: July 28, 1866 (killed at the Battle of the Little Bighorn, June 25, 1876)&lt;br&gt;

==Reconstruction duties in Texas==
On June 3, 1865, at Sheridan's behest, Major General Custer accepted command of the 2nd Division of Cavalry, Military Division of the Southwest, to march from [[Alexandria, Louisiana]], to [[Hempstead, Texas]], as part of the Union occupation forces. Custer arrived at Alexandria on June 27 and began assembling his units, which took more than a month to gather and remount. On July 17, he assumed command of the Cavalry Division of the Military Division of the Gulf (on August 5, officially named the 2nd Division of Cavalry of the Military Division of the Gulf), and accompanied by his wife, he led the division (five regiments of veteran Western Theater cavalrymen) to Texas on an arduous 18-day march in August. On October 27, the division departed to Austin. On October 29, Custer moved the division from Hempstead to [[Austin, Texas|Austin]], arriving on November 4. Major General Custer became Chief of Cavalry of the Department of Texas, from November 13 to February 1, 1866, succeeding Major General [[Wesley Merritt]].

During his entire period of command of the division, Custer encountered considerable friction and near mutiny from the volunteer cavalry regiments who had campaigned along the Gulf coast. They desired to be mustered out of Federal service rather than continue campaigning, resented imposition of discipline (particularly from an Eastern Theater general), and considered Custer nothing more than a vain dandy.&lt;ref&gt;Wert (1996), pp. 232–238.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richter, William L. &quot;It is Best to Go Strong-Armed: Army Occupation of Texas, 1865–66&quot;, ''Arizona and The West'' (Summer 1985), Vol. 27, No. 2, p. 121-122.&lt;/ref&gt;

Custer's division was mustered out beginning in November 1865, replaced by the regulars of the [[6th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|U.S. 6th Cavalry Regiment]]. Although their occupation of Austin had apparently been pleasant, many veterans harbored deep resentments against Custer, particularly in the [[2nd Regiment Wisconsin Volunteer Cavalry|2nd Wisconsin Cavalry]], because of his attempts to maintain discipline. Upon its mustering out, several members planned to ambush Custer, but he was warned the night before and the attempt thwarted.&lt;ref&gt;Richter, &quot;It is Best to Go Strong-Armed: Army Occupation of Texas, 1865–66&quot;, p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt;

==American Indian Wars==
[[File:GenGACuster.jpg|thumb|left|Brevet Major General George Armstrong Custer, United States Army, 1865]]
[[File:George Amstrong Custer with Grand Duke Alexei Alexandrovitch.jpeg|thumb|left|Custer (left) posing with [[Grand Duke Alexei Alexandrovich of Russia]], 1872]]
[[File:George Armstrong Custer and wife Fort Lincoln Dakota Territory.jpg|thumb|left|Custer and his wife at [[Fort Abraham Lincoln]], [[Dakota Territory]], 1874]]

On February 1, 1866, Major General Custer mustered out of the U.S. volunteer service and took an extended leave of absence and awaited orders to September 24.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Gazetteer/Places/America/United_States/Army/USMA/Cullums_Register/1966*.html|title=George A. Custer • Cullum's Register • 1966|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He explored options in New York City,&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-38&quot;&gt;Utley 2001, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; where he considered careers in railroads and mining.&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-39&quot;&gt;Utley 2001, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; Offered a position (and $10,000 in gold) as adjutant general of the army of [[Benito Juárez]] of [[Mexico]], who was then in a struggle with the Mexican Emperor [[Maximilian I of Mexico|Maximilian I]] (a satellite ruler of French Emperor [[Napoleon III]]), Custer applied for a one-year leave of absence from the U.S. Army, which was endorsed by [[Ulysses S. Grant|Grant]] and Secretary of War Stanton. Sheridan and Mrs. Custer disapproved, however, and when his request for leave was opposed by U.S. Secretary of State [[William H. Seward]], who was against having an American officer commanding foreign troops, Custer refused the alternative of resignation from the Army to take the lucrative post.&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-39&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wert (1996), p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the death of his father-in-law in May 1866, Custer returned to Monroe, Michigan, where he considered running for Congress. He took part in public discussion over the treatment of the [[Southern United States|American South]] in the aftermath of the Civil War, advocating a policy of moderation.&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-39&quot;/&gt; He was named head of the Soldiers and Sailors Union, regarded as a response to the hyper-partisan [[Grand Army of the Republic]] (GAR). Also formed in 1866, it was led by Republican activist [[John A. Logan|John Alexander Logan]]. In September 1866 Custer accompanied President [[Andrew Johnson]] on a journey by train known as the &quot;Swing Around the Circle&quot; to build up public support for Johnson's policies towards the South. Custer denied a charge by the newspapers that Johnson had promised him a colonel's commission in return for his support, but Custer had written to Johnson some weeks before seeking such a commission. Custer and his wife stayed with the president during most of the trip. At one point Custer confronted a small group of Ohio men who repeatedly jeered Johnson, saying to them: &quot;I was born two miles and a half from here, but I am ashamed of you.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-39-40&quot;&gt;Utley 2001, pp. 39–40.&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 28, 1866, Custer was appointed lieutenant colonel of the newly created [[7th Cavalry Regiment]],&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-40&quot;&gt;Utley 2001, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; which was headquartered at [[Fort Riley]], [[Kansas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;utley-41&quot;&gt;Utley 2001, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; He served on frontier duty at Fort Riley from October 18 to March 26, and scouted in Kansas and Colorado to July 28. 1867. He took part in Major General [[Winfield Scott Hancock]]'s expedition against the [[Cheyenne]]. On June 26, Lt. Lyman Kidder's party, made up of ten troopers and one scout, were massacred while en route to [[Fort Wallace]]. Lt. Kidder was to deliver dispatches to Custer from [[William Tecumseh Sherman|General Sherman]], but his party was attacked by Lakota Sioux and Cheyenne (see ''[[Kidder fight|Kidder massacre]]''). Days later, Custer and a search party found the bodies of Kidder's patrol.

Following the Hancock campaign, Custer was arrested and suspended at [[Fort Leavenworth, Kansas]] to August 12, 1868 for being [[AWOL]], after having abandoned his post to see his wife. At the request of Major General Sheridan, who wanted Custer for his planned winter campaign against the Cheyenne, Custer was allowed to return to duty before his one-year term of suspension had expired and joined his regiment to October 7, 1868. He then went on frontier duty, scouting in Kansas and [[Indian Territory]] to October 1869.

Under Sheridan's orders, Custer took part in establishing [[Fort Supply|Camp Supply]] in Indian Territory in early November 1868 as a supply base for the winter campaign. On November 27, 1868, Custer led the 7th Cavalry Regiment in an attack on the Cheyenne encampment of Chief [[Black Kettle]] — the [[Battle of Washita River]]. Custer reported killing 103 warriors and some women and children; 53 women and children were taken as prisoners. Estimates by the Cheyenne of their casualties were substantially lower (11 warriors plus 19 women and children).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Story of the Battle of the Washita|publisher=National Park Service (USA)|date=November 1999|url=http://www.nps.gov/archive/waba/story.htm|accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Custer had his men shoot most of the 875 Indian ponies they had captured.&lt;ref name=Schultz2010&gt;{{cite book|last=Schultz|first=Duane|title=Custer: lessons in leadership|chapter=The snow was made red with blood|pages=111-26|publisher=St. Martin's Press|location=New York|year=2010|isbn=978-0-230-11424-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DorvCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA124&amp;dq=Now+Custer+had+to+decide+what+to+do+with+the+875+horses&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjkw9HP2I_OAhUBSmMKHf_hABYQ6AEIHjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Now%20Custer%20had%20to%20decide%20what%20to%20do%20with%20the%20875%20horses&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Battle of Washita River was regarded as the first substantial U.S. victory in the [[American Indian Wars#Sheridan's campaigns|Southern Plains War]], and it helped force a significant portion of the [[Cheyenne and Arapaho Tribes|Southern Cheyenne]] onto a U.S.-assigned reservation.

In 1873, Custer was sent to the [[Dakota Territory]] to protect a railroad survey party against the [[Lakota people|Lakota]]. On August 4, 1873, near the [[Tongue River (Montana)|Tongue River]], Custer and the 7th Cavalry Regiment clashed for the first time with the Lakota. One man on each side was killed. In 1874 Custer led [[Black Hills Expedition|an expedition]] into the [[Black Hills]] and announced the discovery of gold on [[French Creek (Cheyenne River)|French Creek]] near present-day [[Custer, South Dakota]]. Custer's announcement triggered the [[Black Hills Gold Rush]]. Among the towns that immediately grew up was [[Deadwood, South Dakota]], notorious for lawlessness.

==Grant, Belknap and politics==
{{Refimprove section|date=June 2013}}
{{further|Trader post scandal}}
[[File:Custer9.jpg|thumb|Lieutenant Colonel George A. Custer, 7th U.S. Cavalry, ca. 1875]]
The expedition against the Sioux was originally scheduled to leave [[Fort Abraham Lincoln]] on April 6, 1876, but on March 15 Custer was summoned to Washington to testify at Congressional hearings. These concerned the corruption scandal involving U.S. Secretary of War [[William W. Belknap]] (who had resigned March 2), President Grant's brother Orville, and traders at Army posts in Indian Country, who were charging troops double what they would have paid for the same goods in [[Bismarck, North Dakota]]. Soldiers were required by regulations to purchase goods from the traders. Belknap had been selling trading post positions.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen E. Ambrose.  ''Crazy Horse and Custer:  The Parallel Lives of Two American Warriors.''  Los Angeles:  Premier Digital Publishing (1996).  ISBN 978-1-937624-45-3, Kindle locations 6840 -- 6849.&lt;/ref&gt;  After Custer testified on March 29 and April 4 before the Clymer Committee, Belknap was impeached and sent to the Senate for trial. Custer left Washington on April 20, but instead of immediately returning to Fort Lincoln, he visited the [[Centennial Exposition]] in [[Philadelphia]] and planned to travel to [[New York City]] to meet with publishers.{{Citation needed|date=June 2013}}

Custer's testimony was a sensation because of what he said and because he was the one saying it.  Custer was sharply criticized by the Republican press and praised by Democratic editors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen E. Ambrose 1996&quot;&gt;Stephen E. Ambrose. ''Crazy Horse and Custer:  The Parallel Lives of Two American Warriors.'' Los Angeles:  Premier Digital Publishing (1996). ISBN 978-1-937624-45-3, Kindle location 6963 -- 6972.&lt;/ref&gt; President Grant held up Custer's departure from Washington. Grant and Custer did not get along. Earlier Custer had arrested Grant's son, Fred Grant, for drunkenness. Now Custer was accusing Grant's brother and Secretary of War of corruption. Custer was writing magazine articles criticizing Grant's peace policy towards the Indians. Brigadier General [[Alfred Terry]] determined there were no available officers of rank to take command, but Sherman refused to intercede. Stunned that he would not be in command, Custer approached the impeachment managers and secured his release. General Sherman advised Custer not to leave Washington before meeting personally with President Grant. Three times Custer requested meetings with Grant, but was always turned down. Custer gave up and took a train to [[Chicago]] on May 2, planning to rejoin his regiment.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen E. Ambrose. ''Crazy Horse and Custer: The Parallel Lives of Two American Warriors.'' Los Angeles:  Premier Digital Publishing (1996). ISBN 978-1-937624-45-3, Kindle location 6503, 6945 -- 6963.&lt;/ref&gt;
On May 3, a member of Sheridan's staff greeted Custer in Chicago. President Grant had ordered Custer's arrest for leaving Washington without permission. President Grant had designated General Terry to command the expedition in Custer's place. Custer took a train to St. Paul to meet General Terry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen E. Ambrose 1996&quot;/&gt;

Brigadier General Terry met Custer in [[Fort Snelling, Minnesota]] on May 6. He later recalled, &quot;(Custer) with tears in his eyes, begged for my aid. How could I resist it?&quot;{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} Terry wrote to Grant attesting to the advantages of Custer's leading the expedition. Sheridan endorsed his effort, accepting Custer's &quot;guilt&quot; and suggesting his restraint in future. Grant was already under pressure for his treatment of Custer. His administration worried that if the &quot;Sioux campaign&quot; failed without Custer, Grant would be blamed for ignoring the recommendations of senior Army officers. On May 8, Custer was informed at Fort Snelling that he was to lead the 7th Cavalry, but under Terry's direct supervision.

Before leaving Fort Snelling, Custer spoke to General Terry's chief engineer, Captain Ludlow, saying he would &quot;cut loose&quot; from Terry and operate independently from him. Custer presented Bloody Knife, his [[Arikara]] (&quot;Ree&quot;) scout, with several gifts. Custer told Bloody Knife and some Arikara scouts that this would be his last Indian campaign. Custer further stated that if the scouts helped him win a victory, he would become president and look after the Arikaras from the White House.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen E. Ambrose. ''Crazy Horse and Custer: The Parallel Lives of Two American Warriors.'' Los Angeles: Premier Digital Publishing (1996). ISBN 978-1-937624-45-3, Kindle location 7002.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle of the Little Bighorn==
{{Main|Battle of the Little Bighorn}}

By the time of Custer's [[Black Hills Expedition|Black Hills expedition]] in 1874, the level of conflict and tension between the U.S. and many of the [[Plains Indians]] tribes (including the [[Lakota Sioux]] and the [[Cheyenne]]) had become exceedingly high. Americans continually broke treaty agreements and advanced further westward, resulting in violence and acts of depredation by both sides. To take possession of the Black Hills (and thus the gold deposits), and to stop Indian attacks, the U.S. decided to corral all remaining free Plains Indians. The Grant government set a deadline of January 31, 1876 for all Lakota and Arapaho wintering in the &quot;unceded territory&quot; to report to their designated agencies (reservations) or be considered &quot;hostile&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;1868 Fort Laramie Treaty. The Cheyenne were not part of this treaty and had no designated agency. The reservation was for the Lakota and Arapaho.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 7th Cavalry, Custer commanding, departed from [[Fort Abraham Lincoln]] on May 17, 1876, part of a larger army force planning to round up remaining free Indians. Meanwhile, in the spring and summer of 1876, the Hunkpapa Lakota holy man [[Sitting Bull]] had called together the largest ever gathering of Plains Indians at Ash Creek, Montana (later moved to the Little Bighorn River) to discuss what to do about the whites.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall 2007, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; It was this united encampment of Lakota, Northern Cheyenne, and Arapaho Indians that the 7th met at the Battle of the Little Bighorn.
[[File:Custer Staghounds.jpg|thumb|Custer and [[Bloody Knife]] (kneeling left), Custer's favorite [[United States Army Indian Scouts|Indian Scout]]]]
About June 15, Reno, while on a scout, discovered the trail of a large village on the [[Rosebud River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/r&amp;h/R&amp;H-7Cav.htm|title=Seventh Regiment of Cavalry - Center of Military History|author=U.S. Army Center of Military History|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 22, Custer with his entire regiment was detached to follow this trail. On June 25, some of Custer's [[Crow Indian]] scouts identified what they claimed was a large Indian encampment in the valley near the [[Little Bighorn River]]. Custer had first intended to attack the Indian village the next day, but since his presence was known, he decided to attack immediately and divided his forces into three battalions: one led by Major [[Marcus Reno]], one by Captain [[Frederick Benteen]], and one by himself. Captain Thomas M. McDougall and Company B were with the [[pack train]]. Reno was sent north to charge the southern end of the encampment, Custer rode north, hidden to the east of the encampment by bluffs and planning to circle around and attack from the north,&lt;ref&gt;Welch 2007, p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;amfourthreeseven&quot;&gt;Ambrose, Stephen E. (1996). ''Crazy Horse and Custer: The Parallel Lives of Two American Warriors''. New York: Anchor Books. ISBN 0-385-47966-2, p. 437.&lt;/ref&gt; and Benteen was sent south and west to cut off any attempted escape by the Indians.

Reno began a charge on the southern end of the village, but halted some 500–600 yards short of the camp, and had his men dismount and form a skirmish line.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall 2007, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; They were soon overcome by mounted Lakota and Cheyenne warriors who counterattacked ''en masse'' against Reno's exposed left flank,&lt;ref&gt;Goodrich, Thomas (1997). ''Scalp Dance: Indian Warfare on the High Plains, 1865–1879''. Mechanicsburg, PA: Stackpole Books, p. 242, testimony of scout Billy Jackson.&lt;/ref&gt; forcing Reno and his men to take cover in the trees along the river. Eventually, however, this position became untenable and the troopers were forced into a bloody retreat up onto the bluffs above the river, where they made their own stand.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall 2007, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1996, p. 439.&lt;/ref&gt; This, the opening action of the battle, cost Reno a quarter of his command.

Custer may have seen Reno stop and form a skirmish line as Custer led his command to the northern end of the main encampment, where he apparently planned to sandwich the Indians between his attacking troopers and Reno's command in a &quot;[[hammer and anvil]]&quot; maneuver.&lt;ref&gt;Vern Smalley, More Little Bighorn Mysteries, Chapter 14.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Grinnell's account, based on the testimony of the Cheyenne warriors who survived the fight,&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell, 1915, pp. 300–301.&lt;/ref&gt; at least part of Custer's command attempted to ford the river at the north end of the camp but were driven off by stiff resistance from Indian sharpshooters firing from the brush along the west bank of the river. From that point the soldiers were pursued by hundreds of warriors onto a ridge north of the encampment. Custer and his command were prevented from digging in by Crazy Horse, however, whose warriors had outflanked him and were now to his north, at the crest of the ridge.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall 2007, pp. 7–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional white accounts attribute to [[Gall (Native American leader)|Gall]] the attack that drove Custer up onto the ridge, but Indian witnesses have disputed that account.&lt;ref&gt;Michno, Gregory F. (1997). ''Lakota Noon: The Indian Narrative of Custer's Defeat.'' Mountain Press Publishing Company. ISBN 0-87842-349-4, p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote box|width=23em|&quot;Hurrah boys, we've got them! We'll finish them up and then go home to our station.&quot;|—Famous words reportedly said by General Custer shortly before being killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=E6t3ODKOQkkC&amp;pg=PA86&amp;lpg=PA86&amp;dq=custer+%22We've+got+them.+We'll+finish+them+up+and+then+go+home+to+our+station%22|title=I Fought with Custer: The Story of Sergeant Windolph, Last Survivor of the Battle of the Little Big Horn as told to Frazier and Robert Hunt|page=86|first=Charles|last=Windolph|isbn=9780803247468|year=1954}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
For a time, Custer's men appear to have been deployed by company, in standard cavalry fighting formation—the skirmish line, with every fourth man holding the horses, though this arrangement would have robbed Custer of a quarter of his firepower. Worse, as the fight intensified, many soldiers could have taken to holding their own horses or hobbling them, further reducing the 7th's effective fire. When Crazy Horse and White Bull mounted the charge that broke through the center of Custer's lines, pandemonium may have broken out among the soldiers of Calhoun's command,&lt;ref&gt;Michno (1997), pp. 205–206.&lt;/ref&gt; though [[Myles Keogh]]'s men seem to have fought and died where they stood. According to some Lakota accounts, many of the panicking soldiers threw down their weapons&lt;ref&gt;Welch 2007, p. 183; cf. Grinnell, p. 301, whose sources say that by this time, about half the soldiers were without carbines and fought only with six-shooters.&lt;/ref&gt; and either rode or ran towards the knoll where Custer, the other officers, and about 40 men were making a stand. Along the way, the warriors rode them down, [[counting coup]] by striking the fleeing troopers with their [[quirt]]s or [[lance]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Michno (1997), p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially, Custer had 208 officers and men under his command, with an additional 142 under Reno, just over 100 under Benteen, 50 soldiers with Captain McDougall's rearguard, and 84 soldiers under 1st Lieutenant Edward Gustave Mathey with the pack train. The Lakota-Cheyenne coalition may have fielded over 1800 warriors.&lt;ref&gt;Michno (1997), pp. 10–20.&lt;/ref&gt; Historian Gregory Michno settles on a low number around 1000 based on contemporary Lakota testimony, but other sources place the number at 1800 or 2000, especially in the works by Utley and Fox. The 1800–2000 figure is substantially lower than the higher numbers of 3000 or more postulated by Ambrose, Gray, Scott, and others. Some of the other participants in the battle gave these estimates:

:*Spotted Horn Bull – 5,000 braves and leaders
:*Maj. Reno – 2,500 to 5,000 warriors
:*Capt. Moylan – 3,500 to 4,000
:*Lt. Hare – not under 4,000
:*Lt. Godfrey – minimum between 2,500 and 3,000
:*Lt. Edgerly – 4,000
:*Lt. [[Charles Varnum|Varnum]] – not less than 4,000
:*Sgt. Kanipe – fully 4,000
:*George Herendeen – fully 3,000
:*Fred Gerard – 2,500 to 3,000

An average of the above is 3,500 warriors and leaders.&lt;ref&gt;Vern Smalley, Little Bighorn Mysteries, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the troopers were cut down, the native warriors stripped the dead of their firearms and ammunition, with the result that the return fire from the cavalry steadily decreased, while the fire from the Indians constantly increased. The surviving troopers apparently shot their remaining horses to use as [[breastworks]] for a final stand on the knoll at the north end of the ridge. The warriors closed in for the final attack and killed every man in Custer's command. As a result, the Battle of the Little Bighorn has come to be popularly known as &quot;Custer's Last Stand&quot;.

==Death==
Some eyewitness reports state that Custer was not identified until after his death by the Native Americans who killed him.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Several individuals claimed personal responsibility for the killing, including [[White Bull (Native American)|White Bull]] of the [[Miniconjou]]s, [[Rain-in-the-Face]], Flat Lip and Brave Bear.&lt;ref&gt;Dee Brown, ''Bury my Heart at Wounded Knee'', Vintage, 1991, ISBN 978-0-09-952640-7, p.296-297.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2005 at a public meeting, the Northern Cheyenne broke almost 130 years of silence about the battle. Storytellers said that according to their oral tradition, [[Buffalo Calf Road Woman]], a Northern Cheyenne [[heroine]] of the [[Battle of the Rosebud]], struck the final blow against Custer, which knocked him off his horse before he died.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.helenair.com/news/state-and-regional/article_fcf44c96-cfb6-56f4-9c57-062e944350ce.html|first=Martin J. |last=Kidston|title=Northern Cheyenne break vow of silence|publisher=Helenair.com|date=June 28, 2005|accessdate=October 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A contrasting version of Custer's death is suggested by the testimony of an Oglala named Joseph White Cow Bull, according to novelist and Custer biographer Evan Connell, who relates that Joseph White Bull stated he had shot a rider at the riverside wearing a buckskin jacket and big hat when the soldiers first approached the village from the east. The initial force facing the soldiers, according to this version, was quite small (possibly as few as four warriors) yet challenged Custer's command. The rider who was hit, mounted next to a rider who bore a flag, had shouted orders that prompted the soldiers to attack, but when the buckskin-clad rider fell off his horse after being shot, many of the attackers reined up. The allegation that the buckskin-clad officer was Custer, if accurate, might explain the supposed rapid disintegration of Custer's forces.&lt;ref&gt;Connell (1984), pp. 413–414.&lt;/ref&gt; However, several other officers of the Seventh, including William Cooke and Tom Custer, were also dressed in buckskin on the day of the battle, and the fact that each of the non-mutilation wounds to Custer's body (a bullet wound below the heart and a shot to the left temple) would have been instantly fatal casts doubt on his being wounded or killed at the ford, more than a mile from where his body was found.&lt;ref&gt;Wert, 1996, p. 355.&lt;/ref&gt; The circumstances are, however, consistent with [[David Humphreys Miller]]'s suggestion that Custer's attendants would not have left his dead body behind to be desecrated.&lt;ref&gt;David Humphreys Miller, ''Custer's Fall: The Indian Side of the Story''. University of Nebraska Press, 1985.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1920s two elderly Cheyenne women spoke briefly with oral historians about their having recognized Custer's body on the battlefield, and had stopped a Sioux warrior from desecrating the body. The women were relatives of [[Mo-nah-se-tah]], who was alleged to have been Custer's one-time lover. In the Cheyenne culture of the time, such a relationship was considered a marriage. The women allegedly told the warrior to &quot;Stop, he is a relative of ours,&quot; and then shooed him away. The two women then shoved their sewing awls into his ears, to permit Custer's corpse to 'hear better in the afterlife' because he had broken his promise to  Stone Forehead never to fight against Native Americans again.&lt;ref&gt;Smithsonian Magazine, November, 2010, &quot;How Little Bighorn was won&quot; by Thomas Powers&lt;/ref&gt;

When the main column under General Terry arrived two days later, the army found most of the soldiers' corpses stripped, scalped, and mutilated.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall 2007, p. 11; Welch 2007, pp. 175–181.&lt;/ref&gt; Custer's body had two bullet holes, one in the left temple and one just below the heart.&lt;ref&gt;Welch 2007, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; Capt. Benteen, who inspected the body, stated that in his opinion the fatal injuries had not been the result of .45 caliber ammunition, which implies the bullet holes had been caused by ranged rifle fire.&lt;ref&gt;Connell (1984), P. 410.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the recovery of Custer's body and that of his brother Tom, the remains were buried on the battlefield side by side in a shallow grave, after being covered by pieces of tent canvas and blankets.&lt;ref name=&quot;c411&quot;&gt;Connell (1984), p. 411.&lt;/ref&gt; One year later, Custer's remains and those of many of his officers were recovered and sent back east for [[reinterment]] in more formal burials. Custer was buried again with full [[military honors]] at [[West Point Cemetery]] on October 10, 1877. The battle site was designated a [[U.S. National Cemetery|National Cemetery]] in 1876.

==Controversial legacy==
[[File:GACuster.jpg|thumb|left|George A. Custer in civilian clothes, ca. 1876]]
After his death, Custer achieved the lasting fame that he had sought on the battlefield. The public saw him as a tragic military hero and exemplary gentleman who sacrificed his life for his country. Custer's wife, [[Elizabeth Bacon Custer|Elizabeth]], who had accompanied him in many of his frontier expeditions, did much to advance this view with the publication of several books about her late husband: ''Boots and Saddles, Life with General Custer in Dakota'' (1885), ''Tenting on the Plains'' (1887), and ''Following the Guidon'' (1891). Lt. Col. Custer wrote about the American Indian Wars in ''My Life on the Plains'' (1874). Though considered historically accurate, they were clearly slanted in Custer's favor and did much to enhance his reputation after his death.{{citation needed|date=May 2015}}

The deaths of Custer and his troops became the best-known episode in the history of the American Indian Wars, due in part to a painting commissioned by the brewery [[Anheuser-Busch]] as part of an [[advertising]] campaign. The enterprising company ordered reprints of a dramatic work that depicted “Custer's Last Stand” and had them framed and hung in many United States [[Western saloon|saloons]]. This created lasting impressions of the battle and the brewery’s products in the minds of many bar patrons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Griske |first=Michael |title=The Diaries of John Hunton|location=|publisher=Heritage Books|year=2005|isbn=0-7884-3804-2|pages=78–79}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Custer has been called a &quot;[[media personality]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Ravage|first1=John W.|title=Black pioneers: images of the Black experience on the North American frontier|year=1997|publisher=University of Utah Press|location=Salt Lake City|isbn=978-0-87480-546-8|page=74}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Michael C.C.|last=Adams|editor1-last=Hall|editor1-first=Dennis G.|editor2-last=Hall|editor2-first=Susan|title=American icons: an encyclopedia of the people, places, and things that have shaped our culture|year=2006|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport, Connecticut|isbn=978-0-275-98429-8|chapter=George Armstrong Custer|page=186}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he valued good [[public relations]] in addition to using the [[print media]] of his era effectively. He frequently invited journalists to accompany his campaigns (one, [[Associated Press]] reporter [[Mark Kellogg (reporter)|Mark Kellogg]], died at the Little Bighorn), and their favorable reporting contributed to his high reputation, which lasted well into the 20th century. He paid attention to his image; after being promoted to brigadier general in the Civil War, Custer sported a uniform that included shiny cavalry boots, tight olive-colored corduroy trousers, a wide-brimmed slouch hat, tight [[hussar]] jacket of black velveteen with silver piping on the sleeves, a sailor shirt with silver stars on his collar, and a red [[cravat]]. He wore his hair in long ringlets liberally sprinkled with cinnamon-scented hair oil. Later, in his campaigns against the Indians, Custer wore a [[buckskins]] outfit, along with his familiar red tie.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Custer album: a pictorial biography of General George A. Custer|first=Lawrence A.|last=Frost|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press|year=1990|isbn= 978-0-8061-2282-3|page=179}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The assessment of Custer's actions during the American Indian Wars has undergone substantial reconsideration in modern times. Documenting the arc of popular perception in his 1984 biography ''[[Son of the Morning Star]]'', author [[Evan Connell]] notes the reverential tone of Custer's first biographer Frederick Whittaker (whose book was rushed out the year of Custer's death.)&lt;ref&gt;Connell (1984), p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Henry Wadsworth Longfellow]] wrote an adoring (and often erroneous) poem.&lt;ref&gt;Connell (1984), pp. 380–391.&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Theodore Roosevelt]]'s lavish praise pleased Custer's widow.&lt;ref&gt;Connell (1984), p. 325.&lt;/ref&gt; Connell concludes:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;These days it is stylish to denigrate the general, whose stock sells for nothing. Nineteenth-century Americans thought differently. At that time he was [[Pierre Terrail, seigneur de Bayard|a cavalier without fear and beyond reproach]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;c411&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

President Grant, a highly successful general, bluntly criticized Custer's actions in the battle of the Little Bighorn. Quoted in the ''New York Herald'' on September 2, 1876, Grant said, &quot;I regard Custer's Massacre as a sacrifice of troops, brought on by Custer himself, that was wholly unnecessary – wholly unnecessary.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;b540&quot;&gt;Barnett (1996), p. 540.&lt;/ref&gt; General Phillip Sheridan likewise took a harsh view of Custer's final military actions. General [[Nelson Miles]] (who inherited Custer's mantle of famed Indian fighter) and others praised him as a fallen hero betrayed by the incompetence of subordinate officers. Miles noted the difficulty of winning a fight &quot;with seven-twelfths of the command remaining out of the engagement when within sound of his rifle shots.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Barnett (1996), p. 311.&lt;/ref&gt; The controversy over blame for the disaster at Little Bighorn continues to this day. Major [[Marcus Reno]]'s failure to press his attack on the south end of the Lakota/Cheyenne village and his flight to the timber along the river after a single casualty have been cited as a causal factor in the destruction of Custer's battalion, as has Captain [[Frederick Benteen]]'s allegedly tardy arrival on the field and the failure of the two officers' combined forces to move toward the relief of Custer.

{{quote box|width=23em|&quot;When writing about Custer, neutral ground is elusive. What should Custer have done at any of the critical junctures that rapidly presented themselves, each now the subject of endless speculation and rumination? There will always be a variety of opinions based upon what Custer knew, what he did not know, and what he could not have known...&quot;|—from ''Touched by Fire: The Life, Death, and Mythic Afterlife of George Armstrong Custer'' by [[Louise Barnett]].&lt;ref name=&quot;b540&quot;/&gt;}}

In contrast, some of Custer's critics, including General Sheridan, have asserted several clear tactical errors.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

* While camped at Powder River, Custer refused the support offered by General Terry on June 21, of an additional four companies of the Second Cavalry. Custer stated that he &quot;could whip any Indian village on the Plains&quot; with his own regiment, and that extra troops would simply be a burden.
* At the same time, he left behind at the steamer ''Far West'' on the Yellowstone a battery of [[Gatling guns]], knowing he was facing superior numbers. Before leaving the camp all the troops, including the officers, also boxed their sabers and sent them back with the wagons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.astonisher.com/archives/museum/wm_slaper_little_big_horn.html &quot;William Slaper's Story of the Battle&quot;], Personal account by a trooper in M company 7th Cavalry.&lt;/ref&gt;
* On the day of the battle, Custer divided his 600-man command, despite being faced with vastly superior numbers of Sioux and Cheyenne.
* The refusal of an extra battalion reduced the size of his force by at least a sixth, and rejecting the firepower offered by the Gatling guns played into the events of June 25 to the disadvantage of his regiment.&lt;ref&gt;Goodrich, ''Scalp Dance'', 1997, pp. 233–234.&lt;/ref&gt;

Custer's defenders, however, including historian Charles K. Hofling, have asserted that Gatling guns would have been slow and cumbersome as the troops crossed the rough country between the Yellowstone and the Little Bighorn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=354YOkSKZXcC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;lpg=PA27&amp;dq=nelson+miles+on+little+bighorn#PPA27,M1 |title=Custer and the Little Big Horn: A ... – Google Books |publisher=|date= June 1985|accessdate=2010-11-04|isbn=978-0-8143-1814-0|author1=Hofling |first1=Charles K }}&lt;/ref&gt; Custer rated speed in gaining the battlefield as essential and more important. The additional firepower had the potential of turning the tide of the fight, given the Indians' propensity for withdrawing in the face of new military technology.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} Other Custer supporters{{Who|date=April 2009}} have claimed that splitting the forces was a standard tactic, so as to demoralize the enemy with the appearance of the cavalry in different places all at once, especially when a contingent threatened the line of retreat.

==Monuments and memorials==
[[File:Custer Monument OH.jpg|thumb|Custer Memorial at his birthplace in [[New Rumley, Ohio]]]]
[[File:Custerstatue.jpg|thumb|[[Monroe, Michigan]], Custer's childhood home, unveiled the [[George Armstrong Custer Equestrian Monument]] in 1910]]

* Counties are named in Custer's honor in six states: [[Custer County, Colorado|Colorado]], [[Custer County, Idaho|Idaho]], [[Custer County, Montana|Montana]], [[Custer County, Nebraska|Nebraska]], [[Custer County, Oklahoma|Oklahoma]], and [[Custer County, South Dakota|South Dakota]]. [[Custer County, Idaho]], is named for the General Custer Mine, which was named for Custer. [[Custer Township (disambiguation)|Townships]] in Michigan and Minnesota were named for Custer. There are also the [[Village (United States)|villages]] of [[Custer, Michigan]] and [[Custar, Ohio]], the city of [[Custer, South Dakota]], and the unincorporated town of [[Custer, Wisconsin]]. A portion of [[Monroe County, Michigan]], is informally referred to as &quot;Custerville&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.toledoblade.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060928/NEIGHBORS04/609270311|title=- Toledo Blade|work=Toledo Blade}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Custer National Cemetery]] is within [[Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument]], the site of Custer's death.
* An [[George Armstrong Custer Equestrian Monument|equestrian statue of Custer]] by [[Edward Clark Potter]] was erected in [[Monroe, Michigan]], his boyhood home, in 1910.
* [[Fort Custer Training Center|Fort Custer National Military Reservation]], near [[Augusta, Michigan]], was built in 1917 on 130 parcels of land, as part of the military mobilization for [[World War I]]. During the war, some 90,000 troops passed through Camp Custer. &lt;!--Invalid Security Certificate [http://www.mi.ngb.army.mil/ftcuster/default.asp] --&gt;
* The establishment of [[Fort Custer National Cemetery]] (originally Fort Custer Post Cemetery) took place on September 18, 1943, with the first interment. On Memorial Day 1982, more than 33 years after the first resolution had been introduced in Congress, impressive ceremonies marked the official opening of the cemetery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cem.va.gov/CEMs/nchp/ftcuster.asp |title=Fort Custer National Cemetery |publisher=United States Department of Veterans Affairs |accessdate=2008-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Custer Hill is the main troop billeting area at [[Fort Riley]], [[Kansas]].  Custer's 1866 residence on the post has been preserved and is currently maintained as the Custer House Museum and meeting space (also sometimes referred to as [[Custer Home]]).
* The [[85th Infantry Division (United States)|85th Infantry Division]] was nicknamed The Custer Division.
* The Black Hills of South Dakota is full of evidence of Custer, with a county, town, and the [[Custer State Park]] all located in the area. A prominent mountain peak in the Black Hills also bears his name.{{citation needed|date=December 2015}}
* The [[Fort Abraham Lincoln#Custer House|Custer house]] at Fort Lincoln, near present-day [[Mandan, North Dakota]] has been reconstructed as it was in Custer's day, along with the soldiers' barracks, block houses, etc. Annual re-enactments are held of Custer's 7th Cavalry's leaving for the Little Bighorn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Custer%27s+last+policy:+General+George+Custer%27s+life+insurance+policy+...-a0154692038 |title=The Free Library |publisher=The Free Library |date=2006-11-01 |accessdate=2010-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On July 2, 2008, a marble monument to Brigadier General Custer was dedicated at the site of the 1863 Civil War [[Battle of Hunterstown]] in [[Adams County, Pennsylvania]].
* [[Custer Monument (West Point)|Custer Monument]] at the [[United States Military Academy]] was first unveiled in 1879. It now stands next to his grave in the [[West Point Cemetery]].

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|United States Army|American Civil War}}
* [[Cultural depictions of George Armstrong Custer]]
* [[Fort Abraham Lincoln]]
* [[German-Americans in the Civil War]]
* [[Half Yellow Face]]
* [[White Swan]]
* [[List of American Civil War generals#Union-C|List of American Civil War generals]]
* [[List of German Americans]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* Ambrose, Stephen E. (1996 [1975]). ''Crazy Horse and Custer: The Parallel Lives of Two American Warriors''. New York: Anchor Books. ISBN 0-385-47966-2.
* Barnett, Louise (1996) ''Touched by Fire: The Life, Death, and Mythic Afterlife of George Armstrong Custer''  New York, Henry Holt and Company, Inc. ISBN 0803262663
* Boulard, Garry (2006) ''The Swing Around the Circle: Andrew Johnson and the Train Ride that Destroyed a Presidency''  ISBN 9781440102394
* Caudill, Edward and Paul Ashdown (2015). ''Inventing Custer: The Making of An American Legend.'' Lanham, MD: Rowman and Littlefield. ISBN 9781442251861
* {{Cite book |last=Connell |first=Evan S. | title=Son Of The Morning Star | location=San Francisco, California | publisher=North Point Press | year=1984 | isbn=0-86547-160-6}}
* {{Cite book |last=Eicher |first=John H. |last2=Eicher |first2=David J. |title=Civil War High Commands |location=Stanford, California | publisher=Stanford University Press | year=2001 | isbn=0-8047-3641-3}}
* Goodrich, Thomas. ''Scalp Dance: Indian Warfare on the High Plains, 1865–1879''. Mechanicsburg, PA: Stackpole Books, 1997. ISBN 081171523X
* {{Cite book |last=Gray |first=John S. | title=Custer's Last Campaign: Mitch Boyer and the Little Bighorn Remembered | publisher=University of Nebraska Press | year=1993 | isbn=0-8032-7040-2}}
* {{Cite book |last=Grinnell |first=George Bird | title=The Fighting Cheyennes | publisher=The University of Oklahoma Press reprint 1956 | year=1915 | pages=296–307 | isbn=0-7394-0373-7}}
* Longacre, Edward G. (2000). ''Lincoln's Cavalrymen: A History of the Mounted Forces of the Army of the Potomac.'' Stackpole Books. ISBN 0-8117-1049-1.
* Mails, Thomas E. (1972). ''Mystic Warriors of the Plains''. Doubleday. ISBN  038504741X
* Marshall, Joseph M. III. (2007). ''The Day the World Ended at Little Bighorn: A Lakota History''. New York: Viking Press. ISBN 9780670038534
* Merington, Marguerite, Ed. ''The Custer Story: The Life and Intimate Letters of General Custer and his Wife Elizabeth.'' (1950) {{OCLC|1027056}}
* Michno, Gregory F. (1997). ''Lakota Noon: The Indian Narrative of Custer's Defeat.'' Mountain Press Publishing Company. ISBN 0-87842-349-4.
* Perrett, Bryan. ''Last Stand: Famous Battles Against the Odds.'' London: Arms &amp; Armour, 1993. ISBN 0304350559
* {{Cite book |last=Scott |first=Douglas D. |first2=Richard A. |last2=Fox |first3=Melissa A. |last3=Connor |first4=Dick |last4=Harmon | title=Archaeological Perspectives on the Battle of the Little Bighorn | publisher=University of Oklahoma Press | year=1989 | isbn=0-8061-3292-2}}
* Punke, Michael, &quot;Last Stand: [[George Bird Grinnell]], the Battle to Save the Buffalo, and the Birth of the New West&quot;, Smithsonian Books, 2007, ISBN 978-0-06-089782-6
* Robbins, James S. ''The Real Custer: From Boy General to Tragic Hero.'' Washington, DC: Regnery Publishing, 2014, ISBN 978-1-62157-209-1
* Tagg, Larry. (1988). [https://web.archive.org/web/20080208215607/http://www.generalsandbrevets.com/sgd/daniel.htm ''The Generals of Gettysburg.''] Savas Publishing. ISBN 1-882810-30-9.
* Urwin, Gregory J. W., ''Custer Victorious,'' University of Nebraska Press, 1990, ISBN 978-0-8032-9556-8.
* Utley, Robert M. (2001). ''Cavalier in Buckskin: George Armstrong Custer and the Western Military Frontier,'' revised edition. Norman, OK: University of Oklahoma Press. ISBN 0-8061-3387-2.
* Vestal, Stanley. ''Warpath: The True Story of the Fighting Sioux Told in a Biography of Chief White Bull.'' Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1934.  {{OCLC|	250280757}}
* {{Cite book |last=Warner |first=Ezra J. | title=Generals in Blue: Lives of the Union Commanders | publisher=Louisiana State University Press | year=1964 | isbn=0-8071-0822-7}}
* Welch, James, with Paul Stekler. (2007 [1994]). ''Killing Custer: The Battle of Little Bighorn and the Fate of the Plains Indians''. New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company.
* Wert, Jeffry D. ''Custer: The Controversial Life of George Armstrong Custer.'' New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1996. ISBN 0-684-83275-5.
* {{Cite book |last=Wittenberg |first=Eric J. | title=Glory Enough for All : Sheridan's Second Raid and the Battle of Trevilian Station | publisher=Brassey's Inc | year=2001 | isbn=1-57488-353-4}}

==External links==
{{Commons|George Armstrong Custer}}
* [http://www.friendslittlebighorn.com Friends of the Little Bighorn Battlefield]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.kshs.org/portraits/custer_elizabeth.htm Custer Battlefield Museum]
* [http://www.thelbha.org/home.shtml Little Big Horn Associates]
* [http://www.littlebighorn.info Little Bighorn History Alliance]
* [http://library.uww.edu/special-collections/special-collections/hammer-collection Kenneth M Hammer Collection on Custer and the Battle of the Little Bighorn, Harold G. Andersen Library, University of Wisconsin-Whitewater]
* [[commons:Custer|Gallery of Custer images]]
* [http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/C/CU011.html Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture -Custer, George Armstrong]
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Custer, George Armstrong |short=x}}
* {{Cite Appletons' |last=Custer |first=Elizabeth Bacon |authorlink=Elizabeth Bacon Custer |wstitle=Custer, George Armstrong|year=1900 |notaref=x |short=x}}
* {{librivox author|id=2109|title=Gen. George A. Custer}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Custer |first=Elizabeth Bacon |url=https://books.google.com/?id=EfRkVrJcVLoC&amp;pg=PA314&amp;dq=novel+war#PPP1,M1 |title=Boots and Saddles: Or, Life in Dakota with General Custer|publisher=Harper &amp; Brothers, NY., 1885 |date= 1999-05-19 |accessdate=2010-11-04|isbn=978-1-58218-126-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Custer |first=Elizabeth Bacon |url=https://books.google.com/?id=12kdG7nn6KMC&amp;printsec=frontcover |title=Tenting on the Plains: General Custer in Kansas and Texas|publisher=Charles I.Webster &amp; Co, 1887 |date= 1999-06-19 |accessdate=2010-11-04 |isbn=978-1-58218-051-9}}
* {{Cite book |last=Finerty |first=J.F |year=1890|url=http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/History.Finerty
|title=War-path and bivouac: or, The conquest of the Sioux: a narrative of stirring personal experiences and adventures in the Big Horn and Yellowstone expedition of 1876, and in the campaign on the British border, in 1879 |publisher=Donohue Brothers }}
* {{Cite journal|last=Kraft |first=Louis |authorlink= |year=2008 |title=Custer: The Truth Behind the Silver Screen Myth |journal=American History |volume= |issue=Feb |pages=26–33  |url=}}
* {{Cite book |last=Newsom |first=T.M. |year=2007|url=http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/History/History-idx?id=History.Newson |title=Thrilling scenes among the Indians. With a graphic description of Custer's last fight with Sitting Bull |publisher=Kessinger Publishing, LLC |accessdate=2012-07-17
|isbn=978-0-548-62988-8}}
* {{Cite book |last=Victor |first=F.F. |year=1877|url=http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/History/History-idx?id=History.Victor |title=Eleven years in the Rocky Mountains and life on the frontier also a history of the Sioux war, and a life Gen. George A. Custer, with a full account of his last battle |publisher=Columbian book company }}
* {{Cite book |last=Whittaker |first=F. |year=1876|url=http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/History.Whittaker
|title=A complete life of Gen. George A. Custer : Major-General of Volunteers; Brevet Major-General, U.S. Army; and Lieutenant-Colonel, Seventh U.S. Cavalry |publisher=Sheldon and Company }} ISBN 978-0-9966994-3-3
* {{Cite book |last=Donovan |first=J. |year=2009|url=https://books.google.com/?id=ZS2VPwAACAAJ&amp;dq=A+Terrible+Glory:+Custer+and+the+Little+Bighorn |title=A Terrible Glory: Custer and the Little Bighorn – The Last Great Battle of the American West |publisher= Little, Brown &amp; Company |isbn= 978-0-316-06747-8}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.booknotes.org/Watch/74506-1/Louise+Barnett.aspx |title='Booknotes' interview with Louise Barnett |work=Touched by Fire: The Life, Death, and Mythic Afterlife of George Armstrong Custer |date=October 13, 1996}}

{{Gettysburg figures|state=collapsed}}
{{Black Hills, South Dakota}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Custer, George Armstrong}}
[[Category:1839 births]]
[[Category:1876 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Harrison County, Ohio]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:United States Army generals]]
[[Category:American people of the Indian Wars]]
[[Category:Union Army generals]]
[[Category:People of Ohio in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:People of Michigan in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:People of the Great Sioux War of 1876]]
[[Category:Comanche Campaign]]
[[Category:United States Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:People from Monroe, Michigan]]
[[Category:Michigan Brigade]]
[[Category:American military personnel killed in the American Indian Wars]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in Montana]]
[[Category:Burials at West Point Cemetery]]
[[Category:Battle of the Little Bighorn]]</text>
      <sha1>acuuy7fq3u8c771qy6zqglnfisfolhw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
