<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>German and Sarmatian campaigns of Constantine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42039534</id>
    <revision>
      <id>732456586</id>
      <parentid>725281916</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-01T03:08:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender235</username>
        <id>88026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up; http-&gt;https (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="54799">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict    =German and Sarmatian campaigns of Constantine
|partof= [[Germanic Wars]]
|image=[[File:Rome-Capitole-StatueConstantin-nobg.png|150px]]
|caption=Emperor [[Constantine I]]
|place=[[Rhine]] and [[Danube]] [[Limes]]
|date=306 - 336
|result=Roman victory and reconquest of all the territory occupied at the time of [[Trajan]]&lt;ref name=&quot;JulDeCaes329c&quot;/&gt;
|combatant1=[[File:Vexilloid of the Roman Empire.svg|15px]] [[Roman Empire]]
|combatant2=[[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] and [[Sarmatians|Sarmatian]] peoples
|commander1=[[File:Vexilloid of the Roman Empire.svg|15px]] [[Constantine I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Vexilloid of the Roman Empire.svg|15px]] [[Crispus]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Vexilloid of the Roman Empire.svg|15px]] [[Constans]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Vexilloid of the Roman Empire.svg|15px]] [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Vexilloid of the Roman Empire.svg|15px]] [[Constantius II]]
|commander2= [[Rausimodus]]
|units1=[[Roman legion|Numerous legions]]
|units2=Many people, amounting to some hundreds of thousands of armed
|Perdite1=
|Perdite2=
}}
{{Campaignbox Germanic Wars}}
The '''German and Sarmatian campaigns of Constantine''' were fought by the [[Roman Emperor]] [[Constantine I]] against the neighbouring [[Germanic peoples]], including the [[Franks]], [[Alemanni]] and [[Goths]], as well as the  [[Sarmatians|Sarmatian]] [[Iazyges]], along the [[limes|whole Roman northern defensive system]] to protect the empire's borders, between 306 and 336.

After becoming controller of the western provinces along the Rhine ''limes'' (in 306) following the death of his father [[Constantius Chlorus]] (Augustus of the west) in 306, Constantine initially concentrated his forces on defending this area of the frontier against the Franks and Alemanni, making [[Augusta Treverorum]] his first capital for this purpose. Having defeated the usurper [[Maxentius]] at the [[Battle of the Milvian Bridge]] in 312,&lt;ref name=&quot;EutropioX,4&quot;&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''[[Breviarium ab Urbe condita]]'', 10.4.&lt;/ref&gt; all [[Italia]] passed under Constantine's control and he thus became the sole Augustus of the West.

In February 313, Constantine (who had spent the winter in [[Rome]]) formed an alliance with the Emperor of the East, [[Licinius]], reinforced by Licinius' marriage to Constantine's sister, [[Flavia Julia Constantia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,17,2&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.17.2.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this alliance survived for only a few years, before the two Augusti came into conflict in 316. Constantine defeated Licinius, who was forced to cede [[Diocese of Pannonia|Illyricum]] to Constantine,&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,20,1&quot;/&gt; but not [[Diocese of Thrace|Thrace]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,20,1&quot;/&gt; Constantine advanced ever further east with his territorial acquisitions, now having to defend the important strategic region of the ''limes sarmaticus'' (from 317).

In the following years, Constantine mostly occupied himself in the central section of the [[Danubian Limes]], mostly fighting against the Sarmatians in [[Pannonia]],&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL8,8412&quot;/&gt; residing at [[Sirmium]] almost continuously until 324 (when he [[Civil wars of the Tetrarchy#Wars of Constantine and Licinius|moved against Licinius once more]]), making it his capital&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy277&quot;/&gt; along with  [[Serdica]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst214-276&quot;/&gt; At this time Constantine also demonstrated a very active military bent, travelling along the whole of the ''limites'' of his newly acquired territory. From 320 he appointed his eldest son, [[Crispus]], [[Praetorian prefect]], with military command of [[Diocese of Gaul|Gaul]].

When he learnt that an army of [[Goths]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AurVictDeCaes41&quot;/&gt; had crossed the Danube to raid Roman territory in [[Moesia Inferior]] and [[Thrace (Roman province)|Thrace]], which belonged to Emperor Licinius,&lt;ref name=&quot;Valesiani5.21&quot;/&gt; he left his general headquarters in [[Thessalonica]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,22,3&quot;/&gt; and marched against them (323). The fact that he had trespassed into a part of the empire which was not under his control unleashed the final phase of the [[Civil wars of the Tetrarchy]], which ended with the complete defeat of Licinius and the consecration of Constantine as the sole Roman Emperor.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,28,2&quot;/&gt;

The final period of Constantine's reign, until his death (337), saw the Christian Emperor consolidate the entire defensive system on the Rhine and Danube and obtain important military successes which brought &quot;control&quot; of a large part of the territory that the Romans had been abbandoned by [[Gallienus]] and [[Aurelian]]: the [[Agri Decumates]] from the Alemanni, the area south of the [[Tisza]] from the Sarmatians, as well as [[Oltenia]] and [[Wallachia]] from the Goths. Even in this period, Constantine continued to have his preferred Imperial residences at Serdica, Sirmium and Thessalonica, rather than [[Diocletian]]'s [[Nicomedia]].

==Historical context ==
With the death of Emperor [[Numerian]] in November 284 (who had been entrusted with Eastern Roman empire by his father [[Carus]]) and the refusal of the eastern troops to recognise Carus' eldest son [[Carinus]] as his successor, a proven general of [[Illyria]]n origins, [[Diocletian]], was raised to the purple. At the end of the civil war which followed, Diocletian was victorious and in 285 he named [[Maximian]] as his deputy (or [[Caesar (title)#Tetrarchy|Caesar]]) and then a few months later elevated him to the rank of [[Augustus (honorific)#Division of Empire|Augustus]] (1 April 286), thereby forming a [[diarchy]], in which two emperors divided the government of the empire on geographic lines. This also entailed the division of responsibility for the defence of the northern frontier from Germanic and Sarmatian incursions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grant265&quot;&gt;Grant, p. 265.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scarre, p. 197-198.&lt;/ref&gt;

Given the increasing difficulty of containing the internal revolts and those along the borders, a further territorial division was executed in 293 to facilitate military operations: Diocletian named [[Galerius]] as his Caesar in the east, while Maximian chose [[Constantius Chlorus]] in the west.&lt;ref&gt;Cameron, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, this [[tetrarchy]] fell into crisis only a year after the abdication of the two Augusti in 305, beginning a new [[Civil wars of the Tetrarchy|Civil War]] (306-324), permitting new breaches along the Roman external border, with populations attempting to settle within Roman territory.

It was only with Constantine's accession to the throne, becoming sole Augustus of the West after the [[Battle of the Milvian Bridge]] in 312 and later still defeating Licinius and reuniting the Empire under a single emperor (324) that the northern frontiers were adequately defended once more. It is no coincidence that Constantine is attributed the responsibility for perfecting the military reforms of Diocletian and also for the reconquest or vassalisation of all the territory which [[Trajan]] had controlled.&lt;ref name=&quot;JulDeCaes329c&quot;&gt;[[Julian (emperor)|Julian]], ''De Caesaribus'', 329c.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Background: the death of Constantius Chlorus===

With the death of [[Constantius Chlorus]] at [[Eboracum]] ([[York]]) on 25 July 306,&lt;ref name=&quot;EutropioX,1&quot;&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''[[Breviarium ab Urbe condita]]'', 10.1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,9,1&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''Storia nuova'', 2.9.1.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Tetrarchy]] entered a crisis: the eldest son of the dead emperor, Constantine was proclaimed Augustus&lt;ref name=&quot;EutropioX,2&quot;&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''[[Breviarium ab Urbe condita]]'', 10.2.&lt;/ref&gt; by the Alemanni general [[Chrocus]] and the army of [[Britannia]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Panegyrici latini]], 7.3.3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Orosius]], ''History against the Pagans'', 7.26.1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Aurelius Victor]], ''De Caesaribus'', 40.2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Eusebius of Caesarea]], ''[[Church History (Eusebius)|Church History]]'', 8.13.14.&lt;/ref&gt; His election was in accordance with a dynastic principle rather than the meritocratic system of the Tetrarchy created by Diocletain. Only [[Lactantius]] maintains that Constantine was named Augustus by his father on his deathbed.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lactantius]], ''[[De mortibus persecutorum]]'', 24.8.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Galerius]] was displeased by this act and offered the son of his deceased colleague the title of Caesar, which Constantine accepted, allowing [[Flavius Valerius Severus|Flavius Severus]] to succeed his father Constantius instead.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', pp. 27–28; Barnes, ''New Empire'', p. 5; Lenski, pp. 61–62; Odahl, pp. 78–79.&lt;/ref&gt; A few months later, [[Maxentius]] son of the old Augustus [[Maximian]] was acclaimed Emperor by the [[Praetorian guard]] with the support of officials like Marcellianus, Marcellus and Lucianus (but not [[Abellius]], vicar of the [[Praefectus urbi]], who was cilled), reaffirming the dynastic principle. It was in this period that Constantine began to achieve important military successes against the Alemanni and the Franks, along the stretch of the frontier attributed to him, as is recounted by [[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EutropioX,3&quot;&gt;[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], ''[[Breviarium ab Urbe condita]]'', 10.3.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Forces in the field ==

===Romans===
Regarding the Roman forces garrisoned along the whole stretch of the northern ''limites'' from [[Britannia]] to [[Moesia]], it is important to note that at this time there was a very important reform of the [[Roman army]], a new [[Deployment of the Roman legions]] along the borders and an increase in the [[size of the Roman army]]. In fact, we know that, with Diocletian's Tetrarchy reforms, the total number of legions was brough to 55 or 56 in the year 300.&lt;ref&gt;J. R. González, ''Historia de las legiones romanas'', pp. 709-710.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine's accession to the throne and the return of a dynastic monarchy brought about the final increase of the number of Roman legions to 62 or 64 around the year 330.&lt;ref&gt;J. R. González, ''Historia de las legiones romanas'', pp. 711-712.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Barbarians===
{{See also|Germanic peoples|Sarmatians}}

Along the Rhine ''limes'' the [[Franks]] and [[Saxons]] in particular pressed on [[Gaul]] and [[Britannia]]. The [[Alemanni]] also made some incursions in these regions, but the main goal of their attacks at this time was [[Northern Italy]] via [[Pannonia]] (the western part of the [[Danubian Limes]]). The major clashes occurred along the [[Lower Danube]] in the [[Roman province]]s of the [[Balkan]] region, where the [[Marcomanni]], [[Quadi]], [[Sarmatians]] and especially the [[Goths]] (divided into the [[Tervingi]] and the [[Greutungi]]) concentrated their attacks.

== Phases of the conflict ==

=== First phase (306-316): defence of the Rhine ''limes'' ===
[[File:Limes1-it.png|225px|thumb|The sector of the ''limes'' in the province of [[Germania I]] along the lower course of the [[Rhine]].]]
{{See also|Civil wars of the Tetrarchy}}

;306: The twenty-one-year-old Constantine, unable to get permission to visit his ailing father [[Constantius Chlorus]] (Augustus of the west) from the Augustus of the East, [[Galerius]], in whose court he had lived since the time of Diocletian, decided to escape in the spring of this year. He found his father at Gesoriacum ([[Boulogne-sur-Mer]]) about to cross the [[English Channel]] to [[Britannia]] and joined him in a successful military campaign against the [[Picts]] and [[Scotti]] to the north of [[Hadrian's wall]].&lt;ref&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, pp. 84-85.&lt;/ref&gt; When his father died during the summer, Constantine was proclaimed Augustus of the West by his father's loyal troops at [[Eboracum]] on 25 July.
:The young tetrarch however needed his election to the Imperial office to be recognised, particularly by Galerius, the most senior of the Augusti. Gelerius preferred his friend and [[Sassanid campaign of Galerius|comrade in arms]], [[Licinius]], to Constantine. Confronted with a ''fait accompli'' and in the face of the &quot;secession&quot; of Gaul and Britannia, Galerius appealed to precedent and named the former Caesar, [[Flavius Severus]] as the new Augustus with control over Italy, Africa, and Spain and recognised Constantine only as a Caesar.&lt;ref&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine voluntarily accepted this and in Autumn of the same year he returned to [[Augusta Treverorum]] ([[Trier]]) whence he could more easily monitor the Gallic frontier, which was being menaced by the Franks. He continued to defend this important stretch of the ''limes'' for the next six years, transferring his whole imperial court to Trier and transforming it into his capital (with c.80,000 inhabitants), constructing the imposing [[Aula Palatina]] in 310.&lt;ref&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, pp. 92-93 e 96.&lt;/ref&gt; During these years, not only did he reinforce the defences of this region against the continued incursions of the barbarians, but he also strengthened the forces under his control,&lt;ref&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; augmenting his forces through the creation of new legions.

{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Constantine I]]: [[Follis]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VI 776.&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:Constantinus I Æ Follis 161226.jpg
| caption_left = [[Imperator|IMP]] [[Constantine I|CONSTANTINVS]] [[Pius (epithet)|P]] F [[Augustus (honorific)|AVG]], laureated head looking right with armoured bust;
| caption_right = [[Mars (mythology)|MARTI]] PATRI PROPVGNATORI (with Father Mars, the protector), [[Mars (mythology)|Mars]] looking to the right and holding a lance and a shield in his hands; T F on the sides and [[Coinage of Augusta Treverorum|P TR]] in the exergue.
| width = 225
| footer = 25 mm, 6.52 g, minted in 307/308, celebrating the first successes against the Germans in Gaul.
| position = left
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}

;307: At the beginning of spring, Constantine planned a new campaign in [[Germania|German territory]].  He found it necessary to confront the Franks, [[Chamavi]], [[Bructeri]], [[Cherusci]] and Alemanni. The young emperor had been educated in the military training ground of the east by Diocletian and Galerius and, despite his youth, conducted the war with the sort of determination and energy which his father had not been able to muster in the preceding years.&lt;ref&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; In the course of the military operations, he achieved important successes, managing to heavily wallop the Franks who had invaded the Roman territory east of the Rhine the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;[[Eusebius of Caesarea]], ''Life of Constantine'', 1.25.1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Panegyrici latini]]'', 7.6 [https://archive.org/stream/xiipanegyricila02baehgoog#page/n195/mode/1up QUI].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anselmo Baroni, ''Cronologia della storia romana dal 235 al 476'', p. 1026.&lt;/ref&gt; It is reported that, while the Franks were planning to cross the Lower Rhine, Constantine quickly crossed the river in another location and surprised the enemy with an unexpected attack, which prevented a new invasion. Many of the Franks were killed, captured or enslaved - some of these were employed as [[gladiator]]s. All their livestock was  seized and their villages were burnt to the ground.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Panegyrici latini]]'', 7.12-13 [https://archive.org/stream/xiipanegyricila02baehgoog#page/n200/mode/1up QUI].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt; As a result of these successes, Constantine was awarded the [[List of Roman imperial victory titles|cognomen]] Germanicus Maximus at the end of the year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL6,40776&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Y. Le Bohec, ''Armi e guerrieri di Roma antica. Da Diocleziano alla caduta dell'impero'', Roma 2008. pp. 46 &amp; 53.&lt;/ref&gt; In the course of this campaign and those following it, Constantine may have used the [[castra|legionary fortress]] of [[Castra Vetera]] as a base and the valley of the [[Lippe (river)|Lippe]] (as had been done in the time of [[Augustus]] and again fifty years later under [[Emperor Julian|Julian]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''History'', 17.1.11; 17.10.4; 20.10.2.&lt;/ref&gt;) as an invasion route by which to outflank the enemy, who were found to the north of this major river, and catch them from behind after devastating their territory.

{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Constantine I]]: [[Follis]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VI 774.&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:Constantinus I Æ Follis 161227.jpg
| caption_left = [[Imperator|IMP]] [[Constantine I|CONSTANTINVS]] [[Pius (epithet)|P]] F [[Augustus (honorific)|AVG]], laureate head facing right with armoured bust covered in drapery;
| caption_right = [[Mars (mythology)|MARTI]] [[PATRI]] CONSERVATORI (with Father Mars the conservator), [[Mars (mythology)|Mars]] on his feet, turning to the right, holding a lance and a shield in his hands, S A on the sides and [[Augusta Treverorum|P TR]] underneath.
| width = 225
| footer = 26 mm, 6.72 g, minted in 307/308, celebrating the first successes over the Germans in Gaul and the successful defence of the ''limes''..
| position = right
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}

;308: Further successes were achieved by Constantine against the [[Bructeri]] over the whole year, for which he received the title of Germanicus Maximus once again.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL6,40776&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Y. Le Bohec, ''Armi e guerrieri di Roma antica. Da Diocleziano alla caduta dell'impero'', Roma 2008, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; 
At the end of this new military campaign against the Franks, Constantine built the important &quot;bridgehead&quot; of [[Divitia]] (modern [[Deutz, Cologne|Deutz]]) in German territory opposite [[Colonia Agrippina]] ([[Cologne]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{CIL|13|8502}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Limes2-it.png|225px|left|thumb|The sector of the ''limes'' in the province of [[Germania II]] along the upper course of the [[Rhine]]]]

;310: Once more Constantine achieved important military successes over the Alemanni and the Franks, whose king he is said to have captured and fed to the beasts in the amphitheatre.&lt;ref name=&quot;EutropioX,3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baroni1027&quot;&gt;Anselmo Baroni, ''Cronologia della storia romana dal 235 al 476'', p. 1027.&lt;/ref&gt; In the course of this campaign against the Franks, Constantine added a majestic bridge at Divitia, 420 metres long and 10 metres wide.&lt;ref&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker162&quot;/&gt;
Meanwhile, however, [[Maximian]] had rebelled and Constantine had to cut his campaign against the Franks short, marching rapidly to southern Gaul where he captured Maximian and forced him to commit suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;EutropioX,3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Panegyrici latini]], 7.18-19.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Lactantius]], ''[[De mortibus persecutorum]]'', 29.8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', pp. 34–35; Elliott, p. 43; Lenski, pp. 65–66; Odahl, p. 93; Pohlsander, ''Emperor Constantine'', p. 17; Potter, p. 352; E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, pp. 124-125.&lt;/ref&gt;

;311: With the death of [[Galerius]], the Tetrarchy became ever more unstable. Probably as a result of this, no campaigns against the Germans beyond the Rhine seem to have been undertaken this year. On the contrary, Constantine fortified the Rhine ''limes'' ever further with new construction (as at [[Haus Bürgel]] on the right bank of the river, 30&amp;nbsp;km north of Divitia, or along the roads leading from [[Colonia Agrippina]] (Cologne) to [[Augusta Treverorum]] (Trier)&lt;ref&gt;Hans Schönberger, &quot;The roman frontier in Germany: an archaeological survey&quot;, in ''Journal of Roman Studies'' 1969, p.180. The fortifications at [[Bitburg]], [[Neumagen]] and [[Jünkerath]], as well as the fort of [[Pachten]] (152x134 metres).&lt;/ref&gt;) and with the strengthening of preexisting fortifications. Since the auxiliary fortress of [[Noviomagus Batavorum]] ([[Nijmegen]]) had, apparently, been abandoned at the end of the third century, Constantine constructed two new forts in the area: at [[Valkhof]] (on the banks of the river [[Waal (river)|Waal]]) and another along the coast at [[Valkenburg, South Holland|Valkenburg]] (near Hook).&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker162&quot;&gt;C.R.Whittaker, ''Frontiers of the Roman empire. A social ad economic study'', Baltimora &amp; London, 1997, p.162.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Constantine I]]: [[aureus]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', ''Constantinus I'', VI 823; Depeyrot 18/2; Alföldi 19.&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:CONSTANTINE I-RIC VI 823-612074.jpg
| caption_left = [[Constantine I|CONSTAN-TINUS]] PR [[Augustus (honorific)|AVG]], laureate head facing right;
| caption_right = GAVDIVM ROMANORUM (&quot;Celebration of the Romans&quot;), Alemannia seated, mourning, below a military trophy; [[Alemannia|ALEMANNIA]] in exergue.
| width = 225
| footer = 4.63 gr, minted in 312/313 to celebrate the successes against the [[Alemanni]].
| position = left
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}

;312: Constantine gathered a massive army, including barbarians from the recent wars (Germanic peoples and [[Celt]]s brought over from Britannia), and led it into Italy, defeating his rival Maxentius at [[Battle of Turin (312)|Turin]], [[Battle of Verona (312)|Verona]], and finally at the [[Battle of the Milvian Bridge|Milvian Bridge]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EutropioX,4&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Lactantius]], ''[[De mortibus persecutorum]]'', 44; [[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.16; [[Aurelius Victor]], ''Epitome de Caesaribus'', 40.23; [[Panegyrici latini]], 9.16 ss. ([[Eumenius]]) and 10.28 ss. ([[Nazarius (rhetorician)|Nazarius]]).&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine thus begame sole ruler of the West.&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, ''Constantine and Eusebius'', pp. 42–44.&lt;/ref&gt; The eastern half fell under the control of [[Licinius]] the following year, with whom Constantine entered into a marriage alliance.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,18,1&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.18.1.&lt;/ref&gt;

;313: At this time Constantine conducted another military campaign against the Franks and the Alemanni in Gaul, which lasted until the end of summer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst186&quot;&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt; Pretending to cross the river, he followed his earlier course, marching against the Alemanni, but then turned back and attacked the Franks with a rapid [[Roman navy|fleet]]. He devastated their territories and captured one of their kings. Immediately afterwards he retraced his steps and devastated the territories of the Alemanni as well, a campaign commemorated on the coins of the year, which celebrate the ''GAVDIVM ROMANORVM ALAMANNIA''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baroni1027&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VII, 823.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Panegyrici latini]]'', IX, 21.5-22, 6; X, 16.5 [https://archive.org/stream/xiipanegyricila02baehgoog#page/n239/mode/1up QUI].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,50&quot;&gt;Y. Le Bohec, ''Armi e guerrieri di Roma antica. Da Diocleziano alla caduta dell'impero'', Roma 2008. p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Wars-of-the-Tetrarchy.gif|400px|thumb|The Roman world during the [[Civil wars of the Tetrarchy|Civil war]] of 306-324.]]

;314-315: Once again, Constantine made Augusta Treverorum (Trier) his general quarters for these two years, in order to stay more in control of the Rhine frontier, once again putting things in order against possible incursions of Franks and Alemanni and continuing his fortification works.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst186&quot;/&gt; In July of 315 he left the frontier in order to travel to Rome and celebrate his triumph for the Battle of the Milvian Bridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;VicTriCostantino&quot;&gt;{{CIL|11|5265}}; {{AE|1903|264}}; {{CIL|3|204}} (p 973); {{CIL|6|1135}} (p 4327); {{CIL|6|1142}} (p 3071, 4329); {{CIL|6|1144}} (p 3071, 3778, 4329); {{CIL|6|1146}} (p 3071, 4329); {{CIL|8|7006}} (p 1847); {{CIL|8|7007}} (p 1847); {{CIL|8|12064}}; {{CIL|11|5265}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

;316-317: Conflict arose between Licinius and Constantine,&lt;ref&gt;J.Burckhardt, ''L'età di Costantino il Grande'', Firenze 1990, p.345.&lt;/ref&gt; who defeated the former at [[Battle of Cibalae|Cibalae]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.18.2-5.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Battle of Mardia|Mardia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,19,1-3&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.19.1-3.&lt;/ref&gt; In the following peace agreement, Licinius was forced to cede Illyricum to Constantine.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,20,1&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.20.1.&lt;/ref&gt; Constantine thereby extended his territory to the east and now had another important strategic sector to defend: the ''limes sarmaticus'' (or ''[[Pannonia|pannonicus]]''), also called the [[Pannonian Limes]], where he had earlier fought in 305, as an official of Galerius, managing to defeat a barbarian general in single combat.&lt;ref&gt;[[Anonymus Valesianus]], 2.3; [[Zonaras]], ''Epitome of Histories'', 12.33; [[Lactantius]], ''[[De mortibus persecutorum]]'', 24.4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;E.Horst, ''Costantino il Grande'', Milano 1987, p.82; A.Mócsy, ''Pannonia and Upper Moesia'', p.276.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Second phase (317-324): the defence of the ''limes pannonicus-sarmaticus''===
{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Constantine I]]: [[Follis]]&lt;ref name=&quot;SarmatiaDevicta&quot;&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VII 87.&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:CONSTANTINUS I-RIC VII 87-775046.jpg
| caption_left = [[Imperator|IMP]] [[Constantine I|CONSTAN-TINVS]] MAX [[Augustus (honorific)|AVG]], laureate and helmeted head facing right, with armoured bust;
| caption_right = VICTORIAE LAETAE PRINC PERP (&quot;Joyful victory's eternal prince&quot;), two [[Victoria (mythology)|Victories]] standing facing each other, holding a shield bearing the inscription VOT/PR on two lines on top of an altar with a *; in exergue [[coinage of Ticinum|P T]] (&quot;First official of Ticinum]] in esergo.
| width = 225
| footer = 16 mm, 2.93 gr, minted in 318/319
| position = left
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}
{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Constantine I]]: [[Follis]]&lt;ref name=&quot;SarmatiaDevicta&quot;&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VII 122.&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:CONSTANTINUS I-RIC VII 122-786826.jpg
| caption_left = [[Constantine I|CONST-ANTINVS]] [[Augustus (honorific)|AVG]], laureate and helmeted head facing right, with an armoured bust;;
| caption_right = VIRTUS EXERCIT (&quot;Virtue is practiced&quot;), [[labarum]] inscribed ''VOT/XX'' in two lines; two bound prisoners facing away from each other; [[coinage of Ticinum|ST]] (Second official of Ticinum) in the exergue. 
| width = 225
| footer = 19 mm, 3.23 gr, minted in 319/320
| position = right
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}
{{see also|Devil's Dykes}}

;317-319: Following the events described above, Constantine fought against the [[Sarmatians]] on the [[Pannonia]]n stretch of the ''limes'', earning the victory title of ''Sarmaticus Maximus'' for the first time, as seems to be demonstrated by an inscription found in [[Mauretania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL8,8412&quot;&gt;Inscription datable to 319 on which we find several [[Cognomina ex virtute|victory titles]]: {{Quote|''Imperatori Caesari Flavio Constantino Maximo Pio Felici Invicto [[Augustus (honorific)|Augusto]] [[pontifex maximus|pontifici maximo]], Germanico maximo III, Sarmatico maximo Britannico maximo, Arabico maximo, Medico maximo, Armenico maximo, Gothico maximo, [[Tribunician power|tribunicia potestate]] XIIII, [[imperator]]i XIII, [[Roman consul|consuli]] IIII [[pater patriae|patri patriae]], proconsuli, Flavius Terentianus vir perfectissimus praeses provinciae [[Mauretania (provincia romana)|Mauretaniae Sitifensis]] numini maiestatique eius semper dicatissimus''.|CIL VIII, 8412 (p 1916)}}&lt;/ref&gt; indicating to Mócsy that he remained as [[Sirmium]] almost continuously until 324 (when his armies moved against Licinius), employing it as his capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy277&quot;&gt;A.Mócsy, ''Pannonia and Upper Moesia'', p.277.&lt;/ref&gt; Horst too maintains that his preferred imperial residences in the period between 317 and 323 were [[Serdica]] and Sirmium.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst214-276&quot;&gt;E.Horst, ''Costantino il Grande'', Milano 1987, pp. 214 e 276.&lt;/ref&gt;
: During this year, Constantine again showed an active interest in military activities, since he often travelled along the whole ''limes'' of the territories he had acquired with the peace of Serdica (March 317). He inspected the garrisons of [[Pannonia Inferior]], overseeing their repair and the construction of new bridgeheads towards the plain of the [[Tisza]] River, to face the peril of the barbarians beyond Rome's borders ([[Iazygi]] and [[Goths]]). He strengthened the river fleets of the [[Danube]], [[Sava]], [[Drina]], and [[Morava (river)|Morava]], as well as the maritime fleets of the [[Adriatic]] and [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]] Seas, reinforcing the ports of [[Aquileia]], [[Pireus]], and [[Thessalonica]] (formerly Galerius' capital) through the construction of arsenals, shipyards, and the construction of further naval squads.&lt;ref&gt;E.Horst, ''Costantino il Grande'', Milano 1987, pp. 215-219.&lt;/ref&gt;  Clearly these reconstruction and strengthening works could by employed not only against the barbarians, but also, one day, against Licinius.

;320: Constantine's eldest son, [[Crispus]] (now fifteen, and therefore aided by a Prefect), received the military command of Gaul and conducted military campaigns along the Rhine, achieving victories over the Franks and Alemanni within the year.&lt;ref&gt;E.Horst, ''Costantino il Grande'', Milano 1987, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt;

;322: Constantine managed to repulse a new invasion of Pannonia by the Sarmatians and the Iazygi.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy277&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AurVictDeCaes41&quot;&gt;[[Aurelius Victor]], ''De Caesaribus'', 41.13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;&gt;T.D. Barnes, &quot;Victories of Constantine&quot;, in ''Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik'', 20, pp. 149-155.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,21,1&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.21.1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baroni1028&quot;&gt;Anselmo Baroni, ''Cronologia della storia romana dal 235 al 476'', p. 1028.&lt;/ref&gt; After this, Constantine may have begun the construction of a new stretch of border fortifications, the so-called [[Devil's Dykes]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy279&quot;/&gt; which consisted of a series of north-facing embankments starting by the Danube at [[Aquincum]], heading to the [[Tisza]], then turning south towards the river [[Mureș River|Mureş]], crossing the [[Banat]] and reaching the Danube at [[Viminacium]] (it is possible that this construction resumed earlier work under Diocletain).&lt;ref name=&quot;Maxfield210-213&quot;&gt;V.A. Maxfield, ''L'Europa continentale'', pp. 210-213.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker176-178&quot;&gt;C.R.Whittaker, ''Frontiers of the Roman empire. A social ad economic study'', Baltimora &amp; London, 1997, pp. 176-178.&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, the coinage of this year and the next declared ''SARMATIA DEVICTA'' (&quot;Sarmatia vanquished&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VII, n. 257, 257v &amp; 435v (Arles); VII, n.289 &amp; 290 (London); VII, 48 (Sirmium); VII, n.429, 435 &amp; 435S (Trier).&lt;/ref&gt; and name Constantine as &quot;Sarmaticus Maximus&quot; for the second time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;

{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Constantine I]]: [[Follis]]&lt;ref name=&quot;SarmatiaDevicta&quot;&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VII 290 (R2).&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:Constantinus Follis 323 839174.jpg
| caption_left = [[Constantine I|CONSTAN-TINVS]] [[Augustus (honorific)|AG]], laureate head facing right;
| caption_right = [[Sarmatia|SARMATIA DEVICTA]] (Sarmatia vanquished), [[Victoria (mythology)|Victory]] facing, holds a trophy and a palm, with a prisoner seated at her feet; in the exergue [[Londinium|P LON]].
| width = 225
| footer = 19 mm, 2.68 g, coniato nel 323/324
| position = left
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}

;323: Yet again Constantine was able to repel an invasion of Sarmatian Iazyges, as [[Zosimus]] seems to support, though he might have combined or confused the Sarmatian invasions of two separate years,&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,21,2&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.21.2.&lt;/ref&gt; which had unsuccessfully besieged a city of Pannonia Inferior, identifiable with [[Campona]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy277&quot;/&gt; a little south of the legionary fortress of [[Aquincum]].
{{Quote|''... The Sarmatians first attacked a city which had a constant garrison, where the part of the wall near the ground was built of stone and the upper parts in wood'' &lt;nowiki&gt;[which could be Campona&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy277&quot;/&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;. ''The Sarmatians thought they could easily conquer the city, if they could set the wooden part of the wall on fire, so they lit a fire and shot the people on the walls. But while these people returned fire with darts and arrows, Constantine attacked them from behind, taking them by surprise, killing many and taking numerous prisoners, while the survivors fled.''.|[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.21.1-2.}}

[[File:Limes4-it.png|thumb|225px|The ''limes'' along the border of [[Pannonia Superior]], with the path of the so-called [[Devil's Dykes]] in [[Sarmatia]].]]

:At the same time, the Goths&lt;ref name=&quot;AurVictDeCaes41&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,50&quot;/&gt; of [[Rausimodus]] decided to cross the Danube (further downstream) too and tried to raid the Roman territory of [[Moesia Inferior]] and [[Thracia|Thrace]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Valesiani5.21&quot;&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Excerpta_Valesiana/1*.html [[Anonymus Valesianus]], 5.21].&lt;/ref&gt; Informed of this, Constantine left his general quarters in Thessalonica&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,22,3&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.22.3.&lt;/ref&gt; and marched against them. Hearing of the arrival of the Emperor, the Goths decided to retreat to [[Wallachia]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Schreiber78&quot;&gt;Herman Schreiber, ''I Goti'', Milano 1981, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; but Constantine croosed the Ister, reached the Gothic invaders and massacred them in the battle which followed, managing to kill Rausimodus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,21,3&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.21.3.&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{Quote|''Constantine [...] crossed over the Ister and attacked him'' [i.e. Rausimodus]'' as he fled towards a thickly wooded hill. He killed many barbarians, including Rausimodus himself, and afterwards he captured many more. Taking this multitude, which instantly raised its hands in surrender, he returned with them to his general quarters. After posting them in the cities'' [especially at [[Banoštor|Bononia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy278&quot;&gt;A.Mócsy, ''Pannonia and Upper Moesia'', p.278.&lt;/ref&gt;] ''he returned to Thessalonica''.|[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.21.3 &amp; 22.1.}}
:The barbarians had requested peace&lt;ref name=&quot;Valesiani5.21&quot;/&gt; and Constantine had nevertheless led an army into parts of the Empire which were not under his compitency (i.e. Moesia), but that of the other Augustus, Licinius - thereby initiating a new civil war between Constantine and Licinius.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baroni1028&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;E.Horst, ''Costantino il Grande'', Milano 1987, pp. 242-244.&lt;/ref&gt; Coinage continued to celebrate the ''Sarmatia devicta''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SarmatiaDevicta&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus I'', VII, 48, 257 e 257v (Arles).&lt;/ref&gt;

;324: The civil war which followed saw the complete defeat of Licinius and Constantine's consecration as sole Augustus.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZosimoII,28,2&quot;&gt;[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', 2.28.2.&lt;/ref&gt; Remembering the recent war with the Goths, Constantine decided to construct some stone bridges in order to frighten the Barbarians north of the Danube: One connecting [[Oescus]] to the new fort of [[Sucidava]] on the north bank of the Danube,&lt;ref&gt;{{AE|1949|204}}, {{AE|1950|75}}d e {{AE|1939|19}}; {{AE|1950|75}}d; {{AE|1976|582}}e.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker185&quot;/&gt; another linking [[Transmarisca]] and the fort of [[Daphne]] which was also on the north bank of the Danube.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schreiber78&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker185&quot;&gt;C.R.Whittaker, ''Frontiers of the Roman empire. A social ad economic study'', Baltimora &amp; London, 1997, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt; We cannot, however, exclude the possibility that the construction of these new fortifications dates to the later Gothic campaigns of 326-329.&lt;ref&gt;[http://apar.archaeology.ro/bondoc.htm See this important site on the archaeology of the ''limes'' of Moesia Inferior in the fourth century on apar.archaeology.ro].&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Third phase (324-337): the defence of the ''limes gothicus'' and the &quot;reconquest&quot; of Dacia ===
{{see also|Brazda lui Novac}}

In this new phase, Constantine, now sole monarch of the Roman empire, not only managed to coloidate the entire defensive system along the Rhine and Danube, but also obtained important military successes and regained &quot;control&quot; over a good part of the territories which had been abandoned by [[Gallienus]] and [[Aurelian]]. This included the [[Agri decumates]] from the Alemanni, the plain south of the [[Tisza]] ([[Banat]]) from the Sarmatians and [[Oltenia]] &amp; [[Wallachia]] from the Goths. These gains seem to be demonstrated by the coinage of the period and by new defensive constructions ([[Devil's Dykes]] and [[Brazda lui Novac]]).&lt;ref&gt;V.A. Makfield, &quot;L'Europa continentale&quot;, in ''Il mondo di Roma imperiale'', edited by J. Wacher, Roma-Bari 1989, pp. 210-213.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,52&quot;&gt;Y. Le Bohec, ''Armi e guerrieri di Roma antica. Da Diocleziano alla caduta dell'impero'', Roma 2008. p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini210&quot;&gt;R.Ardevan &amp; L.Zerbini, ''La Dacia romana'', p.210.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker185&quot;/&gt; Additionally, in this period, Constantine brought about a new series of reforms, completing those began some forty years earlier by Diocletian.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohec53&quot;&gt;[[Yann Le Bohec]], ''Armi e guerrieri di Roma antica. Da Diocleziano alla caduta dell'impero'', Roma, 2008, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; This process was accomplished gradually over the last thirteen years of his reign (324-337, the year of his death).

{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Crispus]]: [[Follis]]&lt;ref name=&quot;CrispoAlamannicus&quot;&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Crispus'', VII 49; LRBC 803.&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:Crispus Follis 324 251212.jpg
| caption_left = [[Crispus|FL IVL CRISPVS]] IVN NOB [[Caesar (title)|CAES]], laureate head facing right;
| caption_right = ALEMANNIA DEVICTA (&quot;Alemannia conquered&quot;), facing Victory holding a trophy and a palm, with a prisoner seated at her feat; in the exergue is written [[Sirmium|SIRM]]).
| width = 225
| footer = 20 mma, 3.15 g, minted in 324/325
| position = left
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}

;324/325: In the course of these two years, new military campaigns were conducted against the federation of the Alemanni by Constantine's son [[Crispus]], which were celebrated coinage inscribed &quot;''Alemannia devicta'' (Alemannia conquered&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;CrispoAlamannicus&quot;/&gt; From this time, Constantine began to use [[Nicomedia]] as well as Serdica and Sirmium as his preferred Imperial residences.&lt;ref&gt;E.Horst, ''Costantino il Grande'', Milano 1987, p. 276.&lt;/ref&gt;

;328&lt;ref name=&quot;CostantinoIIAlamannicus&quot;/&gt;-331/332: Once again, Constantine, along with his son [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]]&lt;ref&gt;{{CIL|3|7000}}; {{CIL|3|12483}}.&lt;/ref&gt; was forced to intervene on the Upper Rhine, to defeat the Alemanni who had attempted to invade Gallic territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baroni1029&quot;&gt;Anselmo Baroni, ''Cronologia della storia romana dal 235 al 476'', p. 1029.&lt;/ref&gt; This war seems to have lasted many years, since the Emperor's sons were granted the title of Alamannicus Maximus only in 331/2.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,52&quot;/&gt;

;328:&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini210&quot;/&gt; In this year it seems that there were new clashes with Germans, Sarmatians and Goths on the central and lower Danube and that Constantine was forced to cross the Ister once more, constructed a fortified bridge (between [[Oescus]] and [[Sucidava]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker185&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini210&quot;/&gt;) to take the war to Barbarian territory, such that the road leading to [[Romula]] was paved.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini210&quot;/&gt; He devastated the local territory and reduced them to slavery, according to the account of [[Theophanes the Confessor]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Theophanes the Confessor]], ''Chronographia'', A.M. 5818.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Coin image box 1 double
| header = [[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]]: [[Follis]]&lt;ref name=&quot;CostantinoIIAlamannicus&quot;&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], ''Constantinus II'', VII, 50.&lt;/ref&gt;
| hbkg = #abcdef
| image = File:Constantine II sirmium RIC vII 50.1.jpg
| caption_left = [[Constantine II (emperor)|CONSTANTINVS]] IVN NOB [[Caesar (title)|CAES]], laureate head facing right, with armoured bust;
| caption_right = ALEMANNIA DEVICTA (&quot;Alemannia conquered&quot;), facing Victory, holding a trophy and a palm, with a prisoner seated at her feat; in the exergue is written [[Sirmium|SIRM]]).
| width = 225
| footer = 3.40 g, minted in 324/325
| position = right
| margin = 0
| background = 
}}

;329: The next year, all along the Lower Danube, the Goths went on the offensive, managing to penetrate to Moesia Inferior and Thrace, where they wrecked devastation, but Constantine managed to repel the barbarian hoardes, construct a new bridge in [[Scythia Minor]] and attack their territory, as is recorded in his titulature for these years and in [[Anonymus Valesianus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,52&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Theophanes the Confessor]], ''Chronographia'', A.M. 5820.&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of this campaign or that of the previous year, he seems to have received the title of Germanicus Maximus for the fourth time&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL2,481&quot;&gt;{{CIL|2|481}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and the title of Gothicus Maximus for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;

;331/332:&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini210&quot;/&gt; The [[Visigoths]], who had molested the allied Sarmatians, invading their territory&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy279&quot;&gt;A.Mócsy, ''Pannonia and Upper Moesia'', p.279.&lt;/ref&gt; and then the Balkan provinces of the Romans, were defeated&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy278&quot;/&gt; near the modern city of [[Varna]] ([[Bulgaria]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst297&quot;&gt;E. Horst, ''Costantino il grande'', Milano 1987, p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt; by Constantine and his sixteen-year-old Caesar, Constantine II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst297&quot;/&gt; Reportedly, cold, hunger, and battle took the lives of 100,000 Goths. The survivors were forced to sue for peace with the Emperor, handing over hostages including the King's son Ariaric as a guarantee,&lt;ref&gt;Annales Valesiani, VI, 31.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as a contingent of [[auxilia]]ries, in exchange for seed and grain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst297&quot;/&gt; Most importantly, a treaty was concluded with these people (''[[Foederati|foedus]]''),&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst297&quot;/&gt; under which the Goths (presumably the Visigoths) were employed to defend the Imperial border&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini210&quot;/&gt; and provide 40,000 soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jordanes]], ''[[De origine actibusque Getarum]]'', 21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Anonymus Valesianus]]'', 1.31.&lt;/ref&gt; This peace endured until the time of [[Julian (emperor)|Julian]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker186&quot;&gt;C.R.Whittaker, ''Frontiers of the Roman empire. A social ad economic study'', Baltimora &amp; London, 1997, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt; or even to 375/376.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,52&quot;/&gt; For these successes, he received the victory title of Gothicus Maximus for the second time,&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL2,481&quot;/&gt; as well as &quot;''Debellator gentium barbararum''&quot; (&quot;Conqueror of barbarian peoples&quot;) and the coins of 332 and 333 named ''GOTHIA'' and ''SARMATIA'' as if they had become new Roman provinces.&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], volume 7, ''da Costantino I a Licinio (313-337)'', by P.M. Bruun, 1966, p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Eusebius of Caesarea]], ''Life of Constantine'', 1.8.2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Sozomen]], ''Ecclesiastica Historia'', 1.8.&lt;/ref&gt; Immediately following these events, Emperor Constantine may have begun construction of a new stretch of border defences, the so-called [[Brazda lui Novac]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker185&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy280-282&quot;&gt;A.Mócsy, ''Pannonia and Upper Moesia'', pp.280-282.&lt;/ref&gt; which runs parallel to the north bank of the Danube from [[Drobeta-Turnu Severin|Drobeta]], across the plain of eastern [[Wallachia]] to the [[Siret River]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Maxfield210-213&quot;/&gt; surrounding the newly &quot;reconquered&quot; territories.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini210&quot;/&gt; Not coincidentally, [[Aurelius Victor]] recounts that a bridge was built on the Danube (referring to the bridge built in 328) as well as numerous forts and bastions in diverse locations for protection of the borders.&lt;ref&gt;[[Aurelius Victor]], ''De Caesaribus'', 41.18.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Roman Gothic Walls Romania Plain.svg|thumb|left|350px|Map of [[Roman Dacia]] with its complex system of fortifications and defences. At left (in gray) the so-called [[Devil's Dykes]] and at right (in green) the [[Brazda lui Novac]] of the Constantinian period.]]

;334:&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini211&quot;&gt;R.Ardevan &amp; L.Zerbini, ''La Dacia romana'', p.211.&lt;/ref&gt; Two years later, the same Sarmatians who had requested the &quot;friendly&quot; intervention of the Romans, created new problems for the Emperor, when they were riven by internal conflict between the Limigantes and the Argaragantes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy279&quot;/&gt; It is said that the slaves ([[Limigantes]]) drove their masters ([[Argaragantes]]) from Banat, forcing Constantine to intervene militarily&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini211&quot;/&gt; in order to settle an enormous mass of &quot;refugees&quot; (allegedly 300,000 people) in [[Scythia Minor]], [[Italia]], [[Macedonia (Roman province)|Macedonia]], Thrace,&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,52&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baroni1029&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Annales Valesiani, VI, 32.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moesia Superior]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy279&quot;/&gt; and [[Pannonia Secunda]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mócsy279&quot;/&gt; Some maintain instead that Constantine launched a new military campaign into the plain south of the Tisza to restore order among the warring factions,&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittaker176-178&quot;/&gt; at the end of which Constantine received the victory title of Sarmaticus Maximus for the third time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL2,481&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Y.Le Bohec, ''Armi e guerrieri di Roma antica. Da Diocleziano alla caduta dell'impero'', Roma, 2008, p.53; C.Scarre, ''Chronicle of the roman emperors'', New York, 1999, p.214.&lt;/ref&gt; There are, after all, archaeological hints that Constantine had occupied part of the Banat mountains,&lt;ref name=&quot;ArdevanZerbini211&quot;/&gt; along the &quot;old&quot; Roman roads which led from [[Orșova|Dierna]] and Lederata to [[Caransebeș|Tibiscum]] seventeen years earlier.

;circa 335 circa: [[Jordanes]] recounts an episode datable to this period, in which the [[Vandals]] of [[Visimar]], who inhabited the region between the [[Mureș River|Marisus]] and Danube rivers (perhaps a little northwest of Banat), clashed with the Goths of [[Geberic]] and were defeated. The survivors asked Constantine to be allowed into Roman territory, got permission and settled in Pannonia Inferior, where they remained in peace for around forty years, &quot;obeying the laws of the Empire like the other inhabitants of the region.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jordanes]], ''[[De origine actibusque Getarum]]'', 22.&lt;/ref&gt;

;336: Emperor Constantine achieved new successes beyond the Danube in the territories which had once been the Roman province of [[Roman Dacia|Dacia]] (abbandoned by Aurelian), receiving the honorific title &quot;Dacicus Maximus&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barnes149-155&quot;&gt;T.D. Barnes, &quot;Victories of Constantine&quot;, in ''Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik'', 20 pp. 149-155.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIL6,40776&quot;&gt;{{CIL|6|40776}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBohecII,52&quot;/&gt; It cannot be coincidental that an inscription found near the former legionary fortress of [[Apulum (castra)|Apulum]] (modern [[Alba Iulia]]) mentions a woman named Ulpia Constantia (reflecting connections to [[Trajan]] and Constantine).&lt;ref&gt;{{CIL|3|1203}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This could give serious support to Emperor Julian's claim that Constantine reconquered all the territories controlled by Trajan - which included Dacia.&lt;ref name=&quot;JulDeCaes329c&quot;/&gt;

== Results ==
[[File:Costantino nord-limes png.PNG|400px|thumb|The northern and eastern frontiers of the Roman Empire in the time of Constantine, with the territories acquired in the course of the thirty years of military campaigns between 306 and 337.]]
{{See also|Gothic War (376–382)|Roman–Persian Wars}}

The equilibrium along the lower course of the Danube, after all the campaigns of Constantine and his sons, remained almost unchanged until around 375. The focus of the Emperor turned to the east, where a series of preparations were made for an imminent military campaign against the [[Sassanids]], which was never carried out by Constantine on account of his death in May 337. For twenty five years, the Roman armies of [[Constantius II]] and then Julian, fought against the Sassanid armies with varying success (337-363). However the Lower Danube and Eastern borders remained, for almost thirty years, practically unchanged.

{{clear}}

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==

=== Primary sources ===
*[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Res Gestae''; [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Ammian/home.html Latin text and English translation].
*[[Anonymus Valesianus]], Book 5; [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Excerpta_Valesiana/home.html Latin text and English translation].
*[[Aurelius Victor]], ''Epitome de Caesaribus'' and ''De Vita et Moribus Imperatorum Romanorum''; [http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/victor.html Latin text and English translation].
*[[Corpus Inscriptionum Latinarum]]; [http://oracle-vm.ku-eichstaett.de:8888/epigr/epigraphik_it Website on the Latin inscriptions].
*[[Eusebius of Caesarea]], ''Life of Constantine''.
*[[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], [[Wikisource:la:Breviarium historiae romanae|''Breviarium historiae romanae'' (Latin Text), 9-10]] [[File:Wikisource-logo.svg|15px]].
*[[Julian (emperor)|Julian]], ''De Caesaribus''.
*[[Jordanes]], ''[[De origine actibusque Getarum]]''; [http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/iordanes.html Latin text].
*[[Lactantius]], ''[[De mortibus persecutorum]]'', 26; [http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/lactantius/demort.shtml Latin text].
*[[Orosius]], ''Historiarum adversus paganos libri septem'', book 7 [http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/orosius.html Latin text].
*[[Panegyrici latini]], 7 &amp; 10 [https://archive.org/details/xiipanegyricila02baehgoog Latin text].
*[[Roman Imperial Coinage]], VII.
*[[Sozomen]], Ecclesiastica Historia, Book 1.
*[[Theophanes the Confessor]], ''Chronographia''.
*[[Zosimus]], ''New History'', Books 1-2.

=== Modern sources ===
*Radu Ardevan &amp; Livio Zerbini, ''La Dacia romana'', Soveria Mannelli 2007. ISBN 978-88-498-1827-7
*{{cite journal |last=Barnes  |first=Timothy D.  |year= 1976|title=Victories of Constantine|url= |journal= Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik|publisher= |volume= 20|issue= |pages= |doi= |accessdate=22 February 2014}}
*{{cite book| last=Barnes | first=Timothy | title=Constantine and Eusebius | publisher=MA Harvard University Press | location=Cambridge | year=1981 | isbn=978-0-674-16531-1}}
*{{cite book| last=Barnes | first=Timothy | title=The New Empire of Diocletian and Constantine | publisher=MA Harvard University Press | location=Cambridge | year=1982 | isbn=0-7837-2221-4}}
*{{cite book| last=Baroni | first=Anselmo | title=Cronologia della storia romana dal 235 al 476 | publisher=''Storia Einaudi dei Greci e dei Romani'', vol.19 |location=Milano |year=2009 }}
*{{cite book| last=Cameron | first=Averil | author-link=Averil Cameron | title=Il tardo impero romano | location=Milano | year=1995 | isbn=88-15-04887-1}}
*{{cite book | last=Carrié | first=Jean-Michel |title=Eserciti e strategie |publisher=in Storia dei Greci e dei Romani, vol.18, La Roma tardo-antica, per una preistoria dell'idea di Europa | location=Milano | year=2008}}
*{{cite book | last=González| first=Julio Rodríguez| title=Historia de las legiones Romanas | location=Madrid | year=2003}}
*{{cite book | last=Grant |first=Michel | title=Gli imperatori romani, storia e segreti | location=Roma | year=1984 | isbn=88-541-0202-4}}
*{{cite book| last=Horst | first=Eberhard | title=Costantino il Grande | location=Milano | year=1987}}
*{{cite book| last=Jones | first=Arnold Hugh Martin | title=The Later Roman Empire: 284-602 | location=Baltimora | year=1986 | isbn=0-8018-3285-3}}
*{{cite book| last=Le Bohec | first=Yann | title=Armi e guerrieri di Roma antica. Da Diocleziano alla caduta dell'impero | location=Roma | year=2008 | isbn=978-88-430-4677-5}}
*{{cite book| last=Maxfield|first=V.A.|title=L'Europa continentale|publisher=in ''Il mondo di Roma imperiale'' edited by J. Wacher|location=Roma-Bari|year=1989}}
*{{cite book| last=Mazzarino | first=Santo | author-link=Santo Mazzarino | title=L'impero romano | location=Bari | year=1973 | isbn=88-420-2377-9  |id=ISBN 88-420-2401-5}}
*{{cite book| last=Mócsy | first=András | title=Pannonia and Upper Moesia | location=Londra | year=1974}}
*{{cite book| last=Oliva | first=Pavel | title=Pannonia and the onset of crisis in the roman empire | location=Praga | year=1962}}
*{{cite book| last=Rémondon | first=Roger | title=La crisi dell'impero romano, da Marco Aurelio ad Anastasio | location=Milano | year=1975}}
*{{cite book|last=Scarre|first=Chris | title=Chronicle of the roman emperors | location=New York | year=1999 | isbn=0-500-05077-5}}
*{{cite journal| last=Schönberger | first=H. | title=The Roman Frontier in Germany: an Archaeological Survey|journal=Journal of Roman studies |year=1969}}
*{{cite book| last=Southern | first=Pat | title=The Roman Empire: from Severus to Constantine | location=Londra &amp; New York | year=2001 | isbn=0-415-23944-3}}
*{{cite book| last=Whittaker | first=C.R. | title=Frontiers of the Roman empire. A social and economic study | location=Baltimora &amp; London | year=1997 }}
*{{cite book| last=Williams | first=Stephen | title=Diocleziano. Un autocrate riformatore | location=Genova | year=1995 | isbn=88-7545-659-3}}

== Related links ==
*[[Constantine I]]
**[[Crispus]]
**[[Constantine II (emperor)|Constantine II]]
**[[Constantius II]]
**[[Constans I]]
*[[Limes]]
*[[Germanic peoples]]
**[[Alemanni]]
**[[Franks]]
**[[Goths]]
*[[Sarmatians]]
**[[Iazyges]]

{{Ancient Roman Wars}}
{{Portal|Military of ancient Rome|Ancient Germanic culture|War}}

[[Category:4th century in Germany]]
[[Category:4th century in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:306 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:336 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:300s in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:310s in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:320s in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:330s in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:Alamanni]]
[[Category:Constantine the Great]]
[[Category:Danube]]
[[Category:Franks]]
[[Category:Germania Superior]]
[[Category:Germania Inferior]]
[[Category:Moesia]]
[[Category:Pannonia]]
[[Category:Rhine]]
[[Category:Roman Dacia]]
[[Category:Roman frontiers]]
[[Category:Roman Gaul]]
[[Category:Sarmatians]]
[[Category:Vandals]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Goths]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Roman Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>5xy541qiog26a2qe1is1ojf0mnw0k35</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
