<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>German counter-attacks, 30 September – 4 October 1917</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>52308302</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750686996</id>
      <parentid>750468057</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T07:19:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44701">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = German counter-attacks, 30 September – 4 October 1917
|partof = the [[Battle of Passchendaele|Third Battle of Ypres]], [[World War I]]
|image = [[File:Ypres area north, 1914-1915.jpg|300px]]
|caption = Map of the Ypres–Menin Road–Polygon Wood area, 1917
|date= 30 September – 4 October 1917
|place= [[West Flanders]], [[Belgium]]
|coordinates = {{Coord|50|51|7|N|2|59|7|E|name=Polygon Wood|display=title|type:event}}
|map_type=Belgium
|latitude = 50.8519
|longitude = 2.9852
|map_size=200
|map_caption={{centre|Site of German ''Gegenangriffe'', 30 September, 1 and 4 October}}
|map_label= Cameron Covert
|result= British victory
|combatant1= {{flag|German Empire}}
|combatant2= {{flagcountry|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}}
* {{flag|Australia}}
|commander1= [[Rupprecht, Crown Prince of Bavaria|Crown Prince Rupprecht]]
|commander2= [[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig|Douglas Haig]]
|strength1= 1 division, 1 attached regiment
|strength2= 2 divisions
|casualties1= 30 September: 80+&lt;br /&gt;1 October:356&lt;br /&gt;4 October: 5,669 (partial)
|casualties2=
|campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Passchendaele}}
{{Campaignbox Western Front (World War I)}}
|}}
'''German counter-attacks, 30 September – 4 October 1917''' were made during the Third Battle of Ypres in Flanders, during the [[World War I|First World War]]. Hasty counter-attacks (''Gegenstosse'') by the German 4th Army during the [[Battle of the Menin Road Ridge]] on 20 September [[Battle of Polygon Wood]] on 26 September had been costly failures. A review of the situation on 29 September was held at Roulers by [[Erich Ludendorff]] the ''[[Generalquartiermeister]]'' (Quartermaster-General of the German Army, equivalent to the British Chief of Staff) with the commanders of [[Army Group Rupprecht of Bavaria|''Heeresgruppe Kronprinz Rupprecht von Bayern'']] (Army Group Rupprecht of Bavaria) and the [[4th Army (German Empire)|4th Army]] staffs.

Organised counter-attacks (''Gegenangriffe'') after {{nowrap|24–48 hours}} were to replace the hasty counter-attacks (''Gegenstosse'') made during British attacks, to benefit from greater knowledge of the situation in the front line, air reconnaissance and artillery support. It was hoped that by delaying counter-attacks until they could properly be supported, the shorter British advances and rapid consolidation of captured ground could be overcome. From 30 September to 4 October, the 4th Army made several methodical counter-attacks (''Gegenangriffe'') but these re-captured little ground. The attack delayed from {{nowrap|3 to 4 October,}} after the costly failure of the ''Gegenangriff'' on 1 October, coincided with the big Second Army attack on Broodseinde Ridge and was destroyed. Local attempts to counter-attack during the afternoon met a similar fate.

On 7 October, the 4th Army changed its defensive policy again and more emphasis was placed on reducing British barrage fire with counter-battery bombardments. Front line garrisons in a new advanced defence zone, were dispersed in sentry posts and machine-gun nests. As soon as the British attacked, the outpost troops were to rush back to the main defensive line, which would be protected by a standing barrage, delaying the attackers, while the ''Eingreif'' divisions advanced through the British barrages and conducted ''Gegenstoss'' counter-attacks as soon as possible. If the British had dug in, the ''Gegenstoss'' was to be cancelled and a ''Gegenangriff'' substituted later.

==Background==

===Strategic developments===

The failure of the [[Kerensky Offensive]] in Russia in July had hastened the disintegration of the Russian army, the possibility of an [[Armistice between Russia and the Central Powers|Russian armistice]] and a huge reinforcement of the German [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]. From {{nowrap|15 August to 25 August}} the [[Battle of Hill 70]] was fought by the [[Canadian Corps]] and forestalled the transfer of divisions to Flanders and on 20 August, the French attacked at Verdun and in four days captured much of the ground lost to the Germans in 1916 and captured {{nowrap|9,500 prisoners,}} thirty guns, {{nowrap|100 trench}} mortars and {{nowrap|242 machine-guns.}}{{sfn|Michelin|1919|pp=23–24}}{{sfn|Doughty|2005|pp=382–282}} The French attack at Verdun inflicted a defeat on the German [[5th Army (German Empire)|5th Army]] similar in extent to the defeat of the [[4th Army (German Empire)|4th Army]] in the [[Battle of Messines (1917)|Battle of Messines]] in June. The Germans were not able to mount big counter-attacks because their ''Eingreif'' divisions had been transferred to Flanders.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|p=231}} French preparations continued for an offensive on the [[Chemin des Dames]] at [[Battle of La Malmaison|La Mamaison]] and British [[Third Army (United Kingdom)|Third Army]] preparations continued for a surprise attack with a mass of tanks on the [[Flesquières]] Salient near [[Battle of Cambrai (1917)|Cambrai]].{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=235–236}}

===Tactical developments===

{{main article|Tactical development on the Western Front in 1917}}

The period of dry weather and clear skies which began in early September had greatly increased the effectiveness of British air observation and artillery fire. German ''Gegenstosse'' (immediate counter-attacks) had failed and when ''[[Eingreif division]]s'' had arrived, they found that the British had established a defence in depth on reverse slopes, protected by standing barrages. Specialist air reconnaissances were made to observe German troop movements and the [[Royal Flying Corps]] (RFC) had improved its contact patrolling and ground-attack operations. German artillery-fire was haphazard, due to uncertainty over the position of German infantry, just when the British could rely on massed artillery, accurately directed by observers in the air and on the ground.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=294–295}} The German counter-attacks had become assaults on reinforced field positions, due to the short British infantry advances, greater artillery firepower and tactical emphasis on defeating German {{lang|de|''Gegenstosse''}} (immediate counter-attacks). Following the costly defeats at the [[Battle of the Menin Road Ridge]] on 20 September and the [[Battle of Polygon Wood]] on 26 September, the Germans made more changes to the defensive organisation of the 4th Army and altered their counter-attack tactics.{{sfn|Sheldon|2007|p=184}}

==Prelude==

===German defensive preparations===

[[File:German defences east of Ypres mid-1917.jpg|thumb|{{centre|German defensive lines east of Ypres in mid-1917}}]]
On 28 September, two days after the defeat of the Battle of Polygon Wood, ''Oberstleutnant'' Albrecht von Thaer, the chief of staff of ''Gruppe Wijtschate'', made a diary note that it had been an awful experience; he did not know what to do against the British.{{sfn|Hagenlücke|1997|p=53}} [[Erich Ludendorff]] the ''[[Generalquartiermeister]]'' (Quartermaster-General of the German Army, equivalent to the British Chief of Staff) conferred on 29 September with [[Generalfeldmarschall]] ([[field marshal]]) [[Rupprecht, Crown Prince of Bavaria|Crown Prince Rupprecht]] the commander and [[General (Germany)#Generalleutnant|''Generalleutnant'']] (lieutenant-General) [[Hermann von Kuhl]] the chief of staff, of [[Army Group Rupprecht of Bavaria|''Heeresgruppe Kronprinz Rupprecht von Bayern'']] (Army Group Rupprecht of Bavaria), the 4th Army commander General [[Friedrich Bertram Sixt von Armin|Sixt von Armin]] and the chief of staff ''Generalmajor'' (Major-General) [[Fritz von Loßberg]],

{{quote|The fighting of the Third Battle of Flanders exhibited the same characteristics as the second battle and the fighting before Verdun....Our defensive tactics had to be modified in some way... but it was incredibly difficult to find the correct solution.|Ludendorff (Memoirs){{sfn|Sheldon|2007|p=189}}}}

{{quote|In many cases, the counter-attacks hardly reached the front line then held. Heavy casualties were suffered and the whole thing was a failure, as our enemy contented himself with an objective already gained.|Summary, [[5th Guards Infantry Brigade (German Empire)|Guard Infantry Brigade 5]]{{sfn|Bean|1941|pp=857–858}}}}

and the staffs of the 4th Army ''gruppen'' agreed that mobile defence was to be replaced by a policy of fighting for every piece of ground. Armin thought that even if counter-attacks failed to recapture ground, the British would keep more troops in the front line and that German infantry casualties were no worse in counter-attacks than under British barrages.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=846}} On 30 September, the 4th Army issued an operation order for more bombardments between British attacks by field artillery and at least half of the heavy artillery ammunition was to be used for observed fire on infantry positions in captured pill-boxes, command posts, machine-gun nests, on duck board tracks and field railways. Gas bombardments were to be increased on the British front line and artillery emplacements, winds permitting. Pillboxes were to be recaptured, defensive positions improved and the British infantry were to be harassed by patrols and diversionary bombardments. The British were to be compelled by spoiling attacks to reinforce their forward positions and to counter-attack where they could be engaged by the German artillery.{{sfn|Sheldon|2007|pp=184–186}}

Forward garrisons of the ground holding divisions were to be reinforced and all machine-guns, including those of the support and reserve battalions of the front line regiments, were sent into the forward zone, to make a cordon of four to eight guns every {{convert|250|yd|m}}.{{sfn|Wynne|1976|pp=307–308}} The {{lang|de|''Stoss''}} regiments of the {{lang|de|''Eingreif''}} divisions were moved up to the ''Artillerieschutzstellung'' (artillery protective line) behind the forward battle zone, ready to counter-attacks while the British were consolidating. The rest of the {{lang|de|''Eingreif''}} division was to be held back for a {{lang|de|''Gegenangriff''}} (methodical counter-attack) {{nowrap|24–48 hours}} later.{{sfn|Wynne|1976|p=307}} Between British attacks, the {{lang|de|''Eingreif''}} divisions were to make more spoiling attacks.{{sfn|Sheldon|2007|pp=190–191}} On 27 September in the X Corps area south-east of Polygon Wood, three German attacks on the [[39th Division (United Kingdom)|39th Division]] front were repulsed by artillery fire. On the [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Division]] front astride the Ypres–Roulers railway, the Germans made a determined attack on Bostin Farm, eventually to be forced back; a lull in German ''Gegenangriffe'' followed until 30 September.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|p=302}}

===British offensive preparations===

{{main article|Tactical development on the Western Front in 1917#The British set-piece attack in late 1917|l1=The British set-piece attack in late 1917}}

[[File:Battle of Broodseinde - rough attack planning map.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Battle of Broodseinde - rough attack planning map for 4 October; 23rd Division relieved by the 5th Division, night of 1/2 October}}]]
The British tactical refinements had sought to undermine the German defence-in-depth, by limiting objectives to a shallower penetration and then fighting the principal battle against {{lang|de|''[[Eingreif]]''}} divisions as they counter-attacked. By further reorganising the infantry reserves, Plumer had ensured that the depth of the attacking divisions corresponded closer to the depth of the local German counter-attack reserves and their {{lang|de|''Eingreif''}} divisions, providing more support for the advance and consolidation against German counter-attacks. Divisions attacked on narrower fronts and troops advanced no more than {{convert|1500|yd|m}} into the German defence zone, before digging in. The German counter-attackers found a reciprocal defence-in-depth, protected by a mass of artillery. The tempo of attacks achieved by the British also added to the German difficulty in replacing tired divisions through the transport bottlenecks behind the 4th Army front.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|p=296}}

No formal artillery preparation was to be conducted before 4 October, except for the normal heavy artillery counter-battery fire and destructive fire on German strong-points. To mislead the Germans as to the date and time of the infantry attack, when a hurricane bombardment was to be fired at zero hour, practice barrages were begun on 27 September and increased to two barrages a day from 1 October.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=839}} In a summary of 1 October, British military intelligence predicted the German defensive changes made after the defeat of 26 September, forecasting a big German counter-attack to recapture the area around Zonnebeke.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|p=318}} The British considered cancelling their attack when heavy rain began again on 2 October, turning parts of the ground into a [[Marsh|morass]] but decided to go ahead.{{sfn|Freeman|2011|p=70}} The [[X Corps (United Kingdom)|X Corps]] took over from the I Anzac Corps in the area north of the Menin road, the [[23rd Division (United Kingdom)|23rd Division]] (Major-General J. M. Babington) relieved the 33rd Division on the night of {{nowrap|27/28 September}} from the Menin road north to Cameron Covert. German artillery began to fire on the divisional area at dusk and a German party was seen on the right flank was dispersed by British artillery.{{sfn|Sandilands|2003|pp=196–198}}

A spur into Cameron Covert was taken over from Australian troops and patrols during the night found little sign of German troops. Advanced posts were dug during the night and work continued on field defences, using the thick white mist that rose before dawn for concealment. The German artillery continued to bombard the area during 29 September and during the day, German aircraft flew over the divisional artillery and the rear areas. In the evening, German shelling increased around Black Watch Corner on the south side of Polygon Wood. German troops were seen assembling and engaged by artillery but were not prevented from attacking. The British infantry waited then opened rapid fire with their [[small arms]] and repulsed the attackers. During the night, rear areas were bombed by German aircraft and the divisional artillery was severely bombarded with [[Sulfur mustard|mustard gas]].{{sfn|Sandilands|2003|pp=196–198}} During the night of {{nowrap|30 September/1 October,}} the 23rd Division reorganised, with the left flank of the 69th Brigade around Cameron Covert, in touch with the [[110th Brigade (United Kingdom)|110th Brigade]] on the right of the [[21st Division (United Kingdom)|21st Division]] to the north.{{sfn|Sandilands|2003|p=200}}

===German plans of attack===

====1 October====
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  align=right style=&quot;margin:0 0 1em 1em&quot;
|+'''Weather'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(September–October 1917){{sfn|McCarthy|1995|pp=82–97}}&lt;/small&gt;
|-
! Date
! Rain&lt;br&gt;mm&lt;br&gt;
! Temp&lt;br&gt;(°[[Fahrenheit|F]])
! Outlook
|-
| 27||0.0||67||overcast
|-
| 28||0.0||67||cloudy
|-
| 29||0.0||65||clear
|-
| 30||0.0||67||clear
|-
| 1||0.0||69||clear
|-
| 2||2.7||76||showery
|-
| 3||1.2||64||overcast
|-
| 4||4.6||60||overcast
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;text-align: centre;&quot;|
|}
The ground between Polygon Wood and the Menin road contained the Polygonbeek, between Reutel and Cameron Covert and the Reutelbeek, which drained the south-eastern corner of the Gheluvelt Plateau. The beds of the streams had been smashed by shell-fire and their courses had become swampy and in wet weather formed a slough of mud about {{convert|.5|mi|km|abbr=on}} wide between Reutel to the north and Cameron Covert Polderhoek Spur to the south. A ravine between the Polygonbeek and Jetty Warren was muddy but passable in most places.{{sfn|Snowden|2001|pp=78–79}} The fresh [[45th Reserve Division (German Empire)|45th Reserve Division]], the ''Eingreif'' division of ''Gruppe Ypern'' contributed Reserve Infantry Regiment 210 (RIR 210) and the [[8th Division (German Empire)|8th Division]] of ''Gruppe Wijtshate'' supplied Infantry Regiment 93 (IR 93). The 4th Army ''Sturmbataillon'' provided twelve sections to attack the pillboxes and several [[minenwerfer]] companies were attached, to form a special force under General {{illm|Arthur von Gabain|de|Arthur von Gabain}}, the [[17th Division (German Empire)|17th Division]] commander.{{sfn|Bean|1941|pp=837–838}}

====4 October====

The 4th Guard Division (General von [[Finck von Finckenstein|Finckenstein]]) had been rushed up to relieve the [[3rd Reserve Division (German Empire)|3rd Reserve Division]] at Zonnebeke, after the disaster of 26 September. If the division counter-attacked over the ridge, it would be skylined and destroyed by British small-arms and artillery fire. To hold the ridge, the Guards needed to be able to assemble further west on Tokio Spur. {{lang|de|''Unternehmen Hohensturm''}} (Operation Storm the Heights) was planned by ''Gruppe Ypres'' to recapture the Tokio Spur from Zonnebeke south to Molenaarelsthoek at the eastern edge of Polygon Wood on 3 October.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=846}} The ''Gegenangriff'' was to be conducted by RIR 212 of the 45th Reserve Division, the ''Eingreif'' division of ''Gruppe Ypern'', reinforced by eight sections of the 4th Army ''Sturmbataillon'' and {{nowrap|16 heavy}} and {{nowrap|16 light}} ''minenwerfer''. RIR 212 were to attack through the three regimental sectors of the 4th Guard Division, Guard Grenadier Regiment 5 (GGR 5), Foot Guard Regiment 5 (FGR 5) and Reserve Infantry Regiment 93 (RIR 93), which would stand by in case of a British attack. The infantry of both divisions on the attack front was unified under Lieutenant-Colonel {{illm|Ernst von Radowitz|de|Ernst von Radowitz}} (FGR 5) and divided into two commands: in the GGR 5 sector at Zonnebeke, I Battalion, RIR 212 came under the GGR 5 commander Major Freiherr von Schleinitz and to the south, II and III battalions RIR 212, FGR 5 and the two northernmost companies of RIR 93 were subordinated to Lieutenant-Colonel Rave the commander of RIR 212.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=847}}

The ''Gegenangriff'' (methodical counter-attack) on 3 October was to be made by Reserve Infantry Regiment 212 (RIR 212) on a front of {{convert|2000|yd|m|abbr=on}} through the lines of the 4th Guard Division, to recapture vantage points lost on 26 September, particularly those on Tokio Spur. After the costly failure of the ''Gegenangriff'' at Polygon Wood on 1 October, the attack was put back 24 hours to dawn {{nowrap|(6:10 a.m.)}} on 4 October, after rehearsals from {{nowrap|2–3 October,}} watched by the divisional and corps commanders.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=303–304}} On the southern flank the width of the attack was reduced and half of III Battalion, RIR 212 was made a second wave behind the II Battalion in the centre; a contact patrol aircraft was arranged to fly over the area at {{nowrap|7:30 a.m.}}{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=847}} In the 4th Guard Division, the troops were assembled on or in front of Broodseinde Ridge, the rest of the support battalions on the rear slope and reserve battalions in the ''Artillerieschutzstellung'' (artillery protection line) at the bottom. Since 1 October, the 45th Reserve Division, an ''Eingreif'' division, had been alarmed almost nightly and hurried forward to an assembly position in front of Moorslede, only to be sent back to its billets during the morning. The 20th Division was opposite the II Anzac Corps to the north of Polygon Wood and on {{nowrap|2 and 3 October,}} the 4th Bavarian Division (another ''Eingreif'' division) had been brought up to Passchendaele. On the night of {{nowrap|3/4 October,}} the German commanders had doubts but but decided to proceed with the ''Gegenangriff'', warning the artillery to be ready to commence defensive bombardments.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=858}}

==Battle==

===30 September===

At {{nowrap|4:00 a.m.}} on 30 September a thick mist covered the ground and at {{nowrap|4:30 a.m.}} German artillery began a bombardment on the front of the 70th Brigade (Brigadier-General H. Gordon) between the Menin road and the Reutelbeek on the right flank of the 23rd Division. German mortars fired on the brigade support lines and a cloud of smoke mixed with the morning mist, obscuring the view until about {{nowrap|5:00 a.m.}} At {{nowrap|5:15 a.m.,}} German troops of the 8th Division and the 45th Reserve Division emerged from the mist on an {{convert|800|yd|m|abbr=on}} front.{{sfn|Sandilands|2003|pp=198–199}}{{efn|In 2011, Freeman wrote that the German assembly was reported at {{nowrap|1:30 a.m.}} and patrols checked this, leading to a British bombardment being ordered for {{nowrap|4:45 a.m.}} and at {{nowrap|8:00 a.m.}} the German attacks were stopped by a massed artillery bombardment.{{sfn|Freeman|2011|p=52}}}} The attack was supported by flame-throwers and German infantry threw smoke- and hand-grenades into the trenches held by the 8th Battalion [[King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry]] (8th KOYLI) and the 11th Battalion [[Sherwood Foresters]]. The British replied with small-arms fire and bombs, forcing the Germans to retreat in confusion but post was lost south of the Menin road and retaken by an immediate counter-attack. SOS rockets sent up in the mist were not seen by the British artillery which remained silent and a runner took two hours to get back to the brigade HQ in Sanctuary Wood.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=301, 302}} The Germans attacked and were repulsed again at {{nowrap|6:00 a.m.}} but German artillery-fire continued during the day. The 70th Brigade took two prisoners from RIR 78 and counted about {{nowrap|80 German}} corpses, for few British losses.{{sfn|Sandilands|2003|pp=198–199}}{{efn|Three prisoners were taken and revealed that the attack was by RIR 92 and RIR 78 from the 19th Reserve Division. The attack against X Corps had been intended to straighten the German front line and British military intelligence judged that the confusion in the German lines after the big defeat on 26 September had abated.{{sfn|Freeman|2011|p=53}}}}

===1 October===

At {{nowrap|5:00 a.m.}} a German hurricane bombardment began on a {{convert|1500|yd|m|abbr=on}} front from the Reutelbeek north to Polygon Wood and back to a depth of {{convert|1000|yd|m|abbr=on}}, with barrages on the north bank of the Reutelbeek and on a line south of Black Watch Corner; by coincidence a Second Army practice barrage began at {{nowrap|5:15 a.m.}} Communication with the British front line was lost and RIR 210 attacked in three waves at {{nowrap|5:30 a.m.}}{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=837}} On the 23rd Division front, south of Cameron Covert, two determined German attacks were repulsed but the bombardment continued and during the morning spread to the 70th Brigade on the right, much of it from the south-east, falling in [[Enfilade and defilade|enfilade]] along the British defences. The spur into Cameron Covert blocked the view from the south but small-arms fire could be heard all day. At {{nowrap|7:00 p.m.}} the German artillery began to concentrate on the 70th Brigade front and German troops were seen massing opposite, north of and on the Menin road. The German attack was defeated by small-arms fire and the rapid response of the British artillery to SOS rockets. The battalion on the left of the 69th Brigade retreated from Cameron Covert, when the right hand battalion of the 110th Brigade, 21st Division to the north, were forced back and later retreated another {{convert|50|yd|m|abbr=on}}. A counter-attack coincided with another German attack and was repulsed, the British retiring for another {{convert|150|yd|m|abbr=on}}, before contact was regained with the 110th Brigade to the north. Another attack failed and the German infantry dug in behind some old German barbed wire.{{sfn|Sandilands|2003|pp=200–201}}

As night fell the Germans attacked again at Cameron Covert but made no progress. By the time the German attacks stopped, the line of the 69th Brigade had been pushed back west of Cameron Covert, to a line north from Cameron House to the 110th Brigade.{{sfn|Sandilands|2003|pp=201–204}} On the 21st Division front, the battalion on the right of the 110th Brigade, north of Cameron Covert, was pushed back about {{convert|150|yd|m|abbr=on}}.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|p=302}} On the [[7th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|7th Division]] front on the left of the X Corps area, along the north end of the east fringe of Polygon Wood.{{sfn|Atkinson|2009|p=408}} The [[22nd Brigade (United Kingdom)|22nd Brigade]] had a battalion in Jetty Trench and one to the north in Jubilee Trench. Neither battalion had been able to improve the defences by 1 October but mud limited the effect of the German bombardment by smothering the shells before they exploded but they still caused many casualties. German infantry attacked in waves against the right of the brigade and despite intense small-arms fire, the first wave reached Jetty Trench before being shot down. The following waves were then engaged and forced back, followed by British troops counter-attacking on the right flank and taking several prisoners. The Germans attacked all day and communication with the rear was lost but SOS rockets were still visible and after dark another three SOS barrages were called forth, which repulsed German attacks.{{sfn|Atkinson|2009|pp=410–412}} The troops of RIR 210 had managed to advance {{convert|140|yd|m|abbr=on}} on the right and fewer than {{convert|80|yd|m|abbr=on}} in the centre.{{sfn|Bean|1941|pp=837–838}}

===4 October===

====''Unternehmen Hohensturm''====

[[File:Battle of Broodseinde - situation map.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Situation map showing German dispositions from Cameron Covert to Broodseinde, 4 October}}]]
At {{nowrap|5:25 a.m.}} the German bombardment began and ten minutes later, the trench mortars and artillery of the 4th Guard Division concentrated on the attack front and the divisions on the flanks opened fire. The three battalions of RIR 212 had assembled at midnight on the eastern slope of Broodseinde Ridge and had been guided to the front line, ready to move forward and hug the barrage. Some of the first German shells fell on I Battalion, RIR 212 in the I Battalion, GGR 5 sector at Zonnebeke, causing many casualties and the troops fored yellow cluster flares to warn the artillery. At {{nowrap|6:00 a.m.}} the German bombardment lifted, the last shells being fuzed to explode underground so shell splinters would be smothered to make it safer for the infantry to close up. The barrage was to creep forward {{convert|200|yd|m|abbr=on}} beyond the British front line, then to move further to the rear. When the British artillery opened fire ten minutes later, the German gunners were uncertain if it was for an attack or retaliation. Soon after the first waves of RIR 212 had leap-frogged through the troops of the 4th Guard Division, they reappeared shouting &quot;The English are coming!&quot;.{{sfn|Bean|1941|pp=847–848}}

At about {{nowrap|5:20 a.m.}} a yellow flare rather than the usual white one rose over Broodseinde Ridge, followed by a few more and then lots of flares spreading gradually along the flanks. After a few minutes a German barrage began and increased in extent and depth back to Glencorse Wood.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=842}} The German barrage fell on the troops of the [[I ANZAC Corps|I Anzac Corps]], hitting the [[1st Division (Australia)|1st Australian Division]] and the [[2nd Division (Australia)|2nd Australian Division]] at Zonnebeke and Molenaarelsthoek. The most advanced troops escaped the worst and troops further back edged forward. The [[3rd Division (Australia)|3rd Australian Division]] and the 7th Division on the flanks were not bombarded as extensively and as dawn broke about {{nowrap|14 percent}} of the attacking infantry of the I Anzac Corps had become casualties.  It was too late for the Australians to fire a SOS rocket because the guns were not allowed to respond for the last ten minutes before an attack.{{sfn|Bean|1941|pp=843–844}}

On the X Corps front, opposite the 19th Reserve Division and the 17th Division in close reserve as the ''Eingreif'' division, the 5th Division attacked Polderhoek Spur on the right flank,took some ground towards Gheluvelt, captured Polderhoek Chateau and several pillboxes but were forced from the chateau as dark fell. The 21st Division and four tanks crossed the swamp of the Polygonebeek and routed the German defenders, the division gaining observation to the south-east over the Reutelbeek valley, which protected the main attack on Broodseinde Ridge. The right hand brigade retreated slightly to dead ground to avoid massed machine-gun fire.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=313–314}} The 7th Division on the left of X Corps reached its objectives at the eastern edge of the Gheluvelt Plateau against the left of RIR 93 and reserve troops of IR 93 and IR 94. The British found many dead German infantry in camouflaged shell-holes and the rest retreating rapidly down the eastern slope, except for {{nowrap|600 men}} who were taken prisoner. The advance fell short of the final objective but gave a view across the Heulebeek depression to the Keiberg Spur and towards Dadizeele.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=312–313}}

As the I Anzac Corps divisions began their {{convert|800|yd|m|abbr=on}} advance towards {{nowrap|''Flandern I Stellung''}} on Broodseinde Ridge, men were seen rising from shell-holes and more shell-craters were found where German troops were concealed. Most of the Germans were overrun or retreated through the British barrage, then the Australians attacked pillboxes one-by-one and captured the village of Zonnebeke north of the ridge.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=304–307}} When the British barrage began on Broodseinde Ridge, the Keiberg Spur and Waterdamhoek, some of the German forward headquarters only realised that they were under attack when British and Australian troops appeared among them.{{sfn|Bean|1941|pp=858–859}}

====German counter-attacks====

As the Australians began the second phase of the British attack, RIR 93 was conducting a ''Gegenstoss'' to regain the In de Ster plateau on the southern flank, only to be driven further back. Against the 1st Australian Division to the north, II Battalion, FGR 5 and III Battalion, RIR 211 advanced under machine-gun fire from In de Ster through retreating German troops and could only close up to hedges and woods near the new Australian positions. In the sector of GGR 5 to the north, II Battalion, GGR 5 had got some scattered companies in front of Daisy Wood but German infantry retreating down the slopes to the south led to a fear that the battalion might be cut off. Part of the reserve battalion of FGR 5 and part of II Battalion, RIR 211 were sent out as a flank guard. Australians advancing to the north started another panic and the II Battalion, GGR 5 was ordered to fall back to Daisy Wood, the rest of the II Battalion, RIR 211 was brought up and a call for reinforcements was sent to the ''Kapellenhof'' (Eddy Farm) on the Keiberg Spur.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=872}}

RIR 210 of the 45th Reserve Division, was still recovering from the 1 October ''Gegenangriff'' but its battalions were sent to reinforce the 4th Guard Reserve Division. Part of a battalion got through to GGR 5 in the afternoon but it was so exhausted that it was sent back to the artillery protection line to join the rest of the regiment. Bavarian Infantry Regiment 5 (BIR 5), part of the [[4th Royal Bavarian Division|4th Bavarian Division]], was ordered up between Passchendaele and Moorslede, as ''Eingreif'' troops for the [[20th Division (German Empire)|20th Division]] north of Broodseinde. At {{nowrap|11:25,}} BIR 5 was sent to ''Kapellenhof'' (Eddy Farm), the only easy passage through the wire of Flandern II Stellung, then the I and III battalions were sent to Broodseinde instead. Both battalions were caught by machine-gun fire and took cover in Daisy Wood with the rest of GGR 5.{{sfn|Bean|1941|pp=873–874}}

The rest of the 4th Bavarian Division was to counter-attack astride and north of the railway. At noon, BIR 9 attacked from the north-east against Broodseinde at {{nowrap|12:30 p.m.,}} the II Battalion, BIR 9 advanced south of the railway. On the Keiberg Spur it was bombarded by artillery and machine-gun fire and only scattered parties managed to reach Daisy Wood and the area further south. North of the railway, the I Battalion advance began later at {{nowrap|1:45 p.m.}} and was delayed by the wire at Flandern II Stellung, engaged with small-arms fire at the Ypres–Roulers railway cutting and then from the right flank, which drove the survivors south to Daisy Wood. The III Battalion advanced from Passchendaele Ridge on the right flank but Australian machine-gun fire from the crest forced it to swerve right into a dip east of Gravenstafel Spur. At {{nowrap|3:00 p.m.}} the II Battalion, BRIR 5 was ordered to attack from Eddy Farm towards the Broodseinde cross roads and also ended up in Daisy Wood, still under severe bombardment by British artillery. When the advance resumed, a German barrage fell short on the battalion, ending the counter-attack.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=874}}

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===

After the attack of 26 September, the British had used prisoner interrogation, information gleaned from the battlefield and ground observation to judge the state of the 4th Army. The concentration of the German heavy artillery into the Tenbrielen, Kruiseecke, Becelaere and Keiberg groups directed towards Menin Road Ridge, Tower Hamlets Ridge, Polygon Wood and Broodseinde Ridge was reported on 29 September by I Anzac Corps flash spotters; RFC reconnaissance flights confirmed the changes but took from {{nowrap|1–2 October,}} because Germans hid the redeployment with smoke screens.{{sfn|Freeman|2011|pp=70–71}} By 29 September, the 4th Army had recovered from its defeat on 26 September and in the Second Army intelligence summary for {{nowrap|16–30 September,}} Lieutenant-Colonel Charles Mitchell, the Second Army GSO1 Intelligence, wrote that ''Gegenstoss'' counter-attacks would continue despite their recent failures. The Germans would not continue to sacrifice fresh reserves and instead, to limit British advances more reliance would be made on artillery. Mitchell forecast that methodical counter-attacks (''Gegenangriffe'') would occur when the situation at the front had become clearer, one or two days after a British attack.{{sfn|Freeman|2011|p=60}}

From {{nowrap|26 September – 3 October,}} the Germans attacked and counter-attacked at least {{nowrap|24 times.}}{{sfn|Terraine|1977|p=278}} Despite careful preparation, the ''Gegenangriffe'' were costly failures and made no difference to British preparations for the attack due on 4 October. German losses in the 1 October ''Gegenangriff'', intended to prepare the way for the bigger attack on 3 October were so great that the attacking units had to be relieved, which forced the 4th Army to postpone the ''Gegenangriff'' for 24 hours.{{sfn|Edmonds|1991|pp=302–303}}{{sfn|Atkinson|2009|p=412}} The disaster inflicted by the British attack on 4 October had not been planned, the decision to attack two days early having been made on 26 September, because of the speed of the relief of [[V Corps (United Kingdom)|V Corps]].{{sfn|Freeman|2011|pp=71–72}}

In 2011, Freeman wrote that even though

{{quote|... perfect intelligence in a war must of necessity be out-of-date and therefore cease to be perfect....We deal not with the true but with the likely. Speed is therefore the essence of the matter.|E. T. Williams, 1945{{sfn|Ferris|1992|p=1}}}}

the Second Army intelligence officers had accurately predicted another ''Gegenangriff'' before 4 October, based on analysis of German reliefs, artillery arrangements and air activity but had not anticipated the German postponement. Had the British not attacked on 4 October, ''Unternehmen Hohensturm'' would have gained a measure of surprise, the British not being certain of German intentions until the evening of 4 October.{{sfn|Freeman|2011|pp=55, 70–71}}

The fighting in early October had been very costly for the 4th Army and units were used piecemeal to fill gaps.{{sfn|Sheldon|2007|p=207}} After the defeat of 4 October, Thaer had a heated dispute with Loßberg, who had ordered exhausted divisions to counter-attack and Loßberg said that he could not relieve such divisions.{{sfn|Werth|1997|p=327}} On 7 October, the 4th Army reversed the new policy, more emphasis was placed on reducing British barrage fire with counter-battery bombardments. Front line garrisons were dispersed in an advanced defence zone of sentry posts and machine-gun nests. As soon as the British attacked, the outpost troops were to rush back to the main defensive line, which would be protected by a standing barrage, delaying the attackers until the ''Eingreif'' divisions could advance through the British barrages and conduct ''Gegenstoss'' counter-attacks as soon as possible. If the British had managed to dig in, the ''Gegenstoss'' was to be cancelled and a ''Gegenangriff'' substituted later.{{sfn|Wynne|1976|pp=308–309}}

===Casualties===

On 1 October, the 7th Division had {{nowrap|235 casualties.}}{{sfn|Atkinson|2009|pp=410–412}} On 4 October, German losses in the area of ''Unternehmen Hohensturm'' west of Broodseinde Ridge, were {{nowrap|2,883 men}} of the 45th Reserve Division and {{nowrap|2,786 casualties}} in the 4th Guard Reserve Division. In RIR 212, ''Oberstleutnant'' Rave, {{nowrap|13 officers}} and {{nowrap|328 men}} were killed and {{nowrap|1,050 officers}} and men were reported wounded, missing or ill, some companies having suffered {{nowrap|95 percent}} casualties.{{sfn|Sheldon|2007|p=196}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
'''Books'''
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Atkinson|2009}}
|title=The Seventh Division 1914–1918 |last=Atkinson |first=C. T. |authorlink= |year=2009 |orig-year=1927 |publisher=John Murray |location=London |edition=Naval &amp; Military Press |isbn=978-1-84342-119-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Bean|1941}}
|series=[[Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918]] |volume=IV |title=The Australian Imperial Force in France, 1917 |last=Bean |first=C. E. W. |authorlink=Charles Bean |year=1941 |orig-year=1933 |publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]] |location=Canberra |edition=online |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069753/ |accessdate=27 September 2014 |isbn=978-0-7022-1710-4}}
* {{cite book|ref={{harvid|Doughty|2005}}
|last=Doughty |first=R. A. |title=Pyrrhic Victory: French Strategy and Operations in the Great War |location=Cambridge, MA |publisher=The Belknap Press of Harvard University |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-674-01880-8}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Edmonds|1991}}
|series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Military Operations France and Belgium 1917: 7 June – 10 November. Messines and Third Ypres (Passchendaele) |volume=II |last=Edmonds |first=J. E. |authorlink=James Edward Edmonds |year=1991 |orig-year=1948 |publisher=[[HMSO]] |edition=Imperial War Museum &amp; Battery Press |location=London |isbn=978-0-89839-166-4}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Ferris|1992}}
|series=Publications of the Army Records Society |volume=VIII |title=The British Army and Signals Intelligence during the First World War |editor-last=Ferris |editor-first=J. |authorlink= |year=1992 |publisher=Alan Sutton for Army Records Society |location=Stroud |edition= |isbn=978-0-7509-0247-2}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Hagenlücke|1997}}
|title=Passchendaele in Perspective: The Third Battle of Ypres |editor-last=Liddle |editor-first=P. H. |last=Hagenlücke |first=H. |chapter=Ch 4: The German High Command |pages=45–58 |year=1997 |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword |location=London |isbn=978-0-85052-588-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|McCarthy|1995}}
|title=The Third Ypres: Passchendaele, the Day-By-Day Account |last=McCarthy |first=C. |authorlink= |year=1995 |publisher=Arms &amp; Armour Press |location=London |edition= |isbn=978-1-85409-217-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Sandilands|2003}}
|title=The 23rd Division 1914–1919 |last=Sandilands |first=H. R. |authorlink= |year=2003 |orig-year=1925 |publisher=Wm. Blackwood |location=Edinburgh |edition=Naval &amp; Military Press |isbn=978-1-84342-641-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Sheldon|2007}}
|title=The German Army at Passchendaele |last=Sheldon |first=J. |year=2007 |publisher=Pen and Sword |location=London |isbn=978-1-84415-564-4}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Michelin|1919}}
|title=Verdun and the Battles for its Possession |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |authorlink= |year=1919 |publisher=Michelin and Cie |location=Clermont Ferrand |edition= |url=https://ia700409.us.archive.org/33/items/cu31924027945991/cu31924027945991.pdf |accessdate=23 August 2015 |oclc=654957066}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Terraine|1977}}
|title=The Road to Passchendaele: The Flanders Offensive 1917, A Study in Inevitability |last=Terraine |first=J. |authorlink=John Terraine |year=1977 |publisher=Leo Cooper |location=London |isbn=978-1-84415-564-4}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Werth|1997}}
|title=Passchendaele in Perspective: The Third Battle of Ypres |editor-last=Liddle |editor-first=P. H. |last=Werth |first=G. |chapter=Ch 20: Flanders 1917 and the German Soldier |pages=324–332 |year=1997 |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword |location=London |isbn=978-0-85052-588-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Wynne|1976}}
|title=If Germany Attacks: The Battle in Depth in the West |last=Wynne |first=G. C. |authorlink= |year=1976 |orig-year=1939 |publisher=Faber &amp; Faber |location=London |edition=Greenwood Press, NY |isbn=978-0-8371-5029-1}}

'''Theses'''
* {{cite thesis |ref={{harvid|Freeman|2011}}
|title=A Planned Massacre?: British Intelligence Analysis and the German Army at the Battle of Broodseinde, 4 October 1917 |last=Freeman |first=J. |type=PhD |authorlink= |year=2011 |publisher=Birmingham University |location=Birmingham |url=https://etheses.bham.ac.uk/3037/ |accessdate=13 November 2016 |oclc=767827490}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Snowden|2001}}
|title=British 21st Infantry Division on the Western Front 1914–1918: A Case Study in Tactical Evolution  |last=Snowden |first=K. L. |authorlink= |year=2001 |publisher=Birmingham University |location=Department of Modern History School of Historical Studies |type=PhD |url=http://etheses.bham.ac.uk/21/1/Snowden01MPhil.pdf |accessdate=14 November 2016 |oclc=690664905}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=British Intelligence and the German Army 1914–1918 |last=Beach |first=J. M. |authorlink= |year=2004 |publisher=London University |location=London |type=PhD |url=http://ethos.bl.uk/OrderDetails.do?uin=uk.bl.ethos.416459 |accessdate=13 November 2016 |id=uk.bl.ethos.416459 |oclc=500051492}}
* {{cite book |series=Der Weltkrieg 1914 bis 1918: Militärischen Operationen zu Lande |volume=XIII |title=Die Kriegführung im Sommer und Herbst 1917. Die Ereignisse außerhalb der Westfront bis November 1918 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |authorlink= |year=2012 |orig-year=1942 |publisher=Mittler |location=Berlin |url=http://digi.landesbibliothek.at/viewer/image/AC03617667/1/LOG_0003/ |accessdate=14 November 2016 |edition=Die digitale landesbibliotek Oberösterreich |oclc=257129831}}
* {{cite book |title=The Fifth Division in the Great War |last1=Hussey |first1=A. H. |last2=Inman |first2=D. S. |authorlink= |year=1921 |publisher=Nisbet |location=London |edition=online |url=https://archive.org/details/fifthdivisioning00huss |accessdate=14 November 2016 |oclc=493316031}}
* {{cite thesis |title=The Operational Role of British Corps Command on the Western Front 1914–18 |last=Simpson |first=A. |authorlink= |year=2001 |publisher=London University |type=PhD |location=London |url=https://ethos.bl.uk/OrderDetails.do?did=1&amp;uin=uk.bl.ethos.367588 |accessdate=13 November 2016 |oclc=557496951}}

==External links==
{{portal|World War I}}
* [http://pierreswesternfront.punt.nl/content/2008/03/polygon-wood-zonnebeke Photo essay, Polygon Wood]

{{World War I}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:put title here}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1917]]
[[Category:1917 in France]]
[[Category:Battles of the Western Front (World War I)]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>5wmt5qlu14uhds87zki40zh1u3jokpd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
