<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Grumman Gulfstream II</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3267426</id>
    <revision>
      <id>731644027</id>
      <parentid>731643536</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-26T16:59:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>95.149.247.54</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Design */ Engines</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19146">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
  |name = Gulfstream II
  |image = Mauritania Government G-1159 Gulfstream II at Basle Aiprort March 1987.jpg
  |caption = G-1159 Gulfstream II of the [[Government of Mauritania]] at Basle in 1987
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
  |type = Business jet
  |national origin= [[United States]]
  |manufacturer = [[Grumman]]/[[Gulfstream Aerospace]]
  |designer = 
  |first flight = 2 October 1966
  |introduced = 
  |retired = 
  |status = 
  |primary user = 
  |more users = 
  |produced = 1967- Late 70s
  |number built = 258
  |unit cost = 
  |developed from = [[Grumman Gulfstream I]]
  |variants with their own articles = [[Gulfstream III]] 
}}
|}
[[File:Ng-GII-bams-N82CR-070709-01-16.jpg|thumb|right|A highly modified GII used to flight test systems hardware for the [[Broad Area Maritime Surveillance]] (BAMS) UAV contract bid, seen here taxiing at [[Mojave Spaceport|Mojave]]]]

The '''Gulfstream II''' ('''G-II''') is an American twin engine [[business jet]] designed and built by [[Grumman]] and then in succession, [[Grumman American]] and finally [[Gulfstream American]]. Its Grumman model number is G-1159 and its US military designation is '''C-11 Gulfstream II'''. It has been succeeded by the [[Gulfstream III]]. The first Gulfstream II flew on October 2, 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor, John W 1984&quot;&gt;Taylor, John W.R., ''Jane's All the World's Aircraft 1984-85'', Jane's Publishing Company, 1984.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
The Gulfstream II is a twin-jet swept wing corporate transport powered by two [[Rolls-Royce Spey]] [[turbofan]] engines and designed to provide high speed and long range capability without sacrificing the airport performance, reliability, and other operational advantages of its predecessor, the turboprop [[Grumman Gulfstream I|Gulfstream I]]. Preliminary design of the wing was influenced by both cruise and low speed considerations. The aft-mounted engine location was selected after extensive analysis and design iterations considering aerodynamic, structural, and ground clearance requirements. Airfoil geometry was developed to maximum sweep benefit from the selected planform.  The interference problem at the wing-body juncture was treated by modification of the airfoil shape and thickness over the inner third of the wing span. The basic airfoils for the main area of the wing are similar to those of the [[Grumman A-6 Intruder]] aircraft and utilize NACA 6-series thickness distributions combined with an in-house mean line. A buffet boundary commensurate with the M=.85 speed capability was attained by incorporating a row of co-rotating vortex generators on the outer wing panel. In developing the wing contours, attention was paid to the aircraft's low speed requirements by tailoring the leading edge radius to preclude leading edge separation. The high lift configuration, consists of a one piece, single-slotted [[Fowler flap]] of 30% chord.  Stall initiation on the basic wing was found to occur at midspan but spread rapidly to the tip, particularly at large flap deflections. The addition of an upper surface fence at about midspan provided a strong pitch down at the stall, without sacrificing maximum lift, and also afforded an adequate margin between initial and tip stall.&lt;ref name=Waaland&gt;Waaland, I.T. and Curtis, E.J., &quot;Gulfstream II Aerodynamic Design&quot;, SAE paper 670242.&lt;/ref&gt;

The high angle of attack investigations on the Gulfstream II indicated that stable trim conditions existed up to 45 degrees angle of attack.  The elevator deflection required to trim to the primary stall at most forward center of gravity was sufficient to trim a [[deep stall]] at the aft center of gravity, but recovery from deep stall was immediate upon forward stick motion, and more than adequate nose-down elevator control was available.  The acceptability of the Gulfstream II high angle of attack characteristics and the absence of a deep stall influence on configuration sizing and arrangement was attributed to the mitigating influence of the nacelle-wing overlap on nacelle contribution. Configuration buildup studies revealed the adverse nacelle influence on tail pitching moment contribution above 30 degrees angle of attack was not unduly severe and no appreciable effect on elevator or stabilizer effectiveness was found.&lt;ref name=Waaland /&gt;

It was found in flight testing that the stall characteristics were satisfactory but did not preclude stall penetrations to the point of secondary stall pitchup.  Rather than pursue a lengthy flight test research effort, and in view of the excellent primary stall behavior, it was decided to mechanically limit the extent of stall penetration with a [[stick shaker]] and [[stick pusher]].&lt;ref name=Waaland /&gt;

During installation of the [[Aviation Partners Inc.]] winglets (as the G-IISP), the vortex generators and midspan fence were removed and replaced with six leading edge vortilons similar to those found on the [[Gulfstream IV]].&lt;ref name=APISTC&gt;[http://www.airweb.faa.gov/Regulatory_and_Guidance_Library/rgstc.nsf/0/c725fd441da2e7158625770c007783bd/$FILE/ST00080SE.pdf FAA Supplemental Type Certificate ST00080SE] Retrieved 31 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, the FAA modified 14 CFR part 91 rules to prohibit the operation of jets weighing 75,000 pounds or less that are not stage 3 noise compliant after December 31, 2015.  The Gulfstream II is listed explicitly in Federal Register [http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/granule/FR-2013-07-02/2013-15843/content-detail.html 78 FR 39576].  Any Gulfstream II's that have not been modified by installing Stage 3 noise compliant engines or have not had &quot;hushkits&quot; installed for non-compliant engines will not be permitted to fly in the contiguous 48 states after December 31, 2015.  ''14 CFR §91.883 Special flight authorizations for jet airplanes weighing 75,000 pounds or less'' - lists special flight authorizations that may be granted for operation after December 31, 2015.

==Variants==
;Gulfstream II (G-1159)
:Twin-engined executive, corporate transport aircraft, with accommodation for up to 14 passengers, powered by two [[Rolls-Royce Spey|Rolls-Royce Spey RB.168 Mk 511-8]] turbofan engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor, John W 1984&quot;/&gt; Received FAA Type Certificate A12EA on October 19, 1967.&lt;ref name= typeCert&gt;{{cite web |url= http://rgl.faa.gov/Regulatory_and_Guidance_Library/rgMakeModel.nsf/0/2d504046f9657ec386257f610074fcfb/$FILE/A12EA_Rev46.pdf |title= Type Certificate date Sheet NO. A12EA, revision 46 |publisher= FAA |date= February 22, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
;Gulfstream II TT
:Modified version with tip tanks, increased range. FAA certified May 13, 1977.&lt;ref name= typeCert/&gt;
;Gulfstream IIB (G-1159B)
:Modified version, with the wider, wingleted wings and instruments of the [[Gulfstream III]], Maximum takeoff weight increased to 68,200 lb. or 69,700 lb. FAA certified on September 17, 1981.&lt;ref name= typeCert/&gt;
;Gulfstream II SP
:Aircraft modified by the addition of [[Aviation Partners]] winglets. FAA certified under STC ST00080SE on April 22, 1994.&lt;ref name=APISTC /&gt;
;VC-11A
:VIP transport version for the US Coast Guard. One built.

==Special mission variants==
Gulfstream IIs have been popular as special mission aircraft, particularly when used aircraft became available for less than $1 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.controller.com/list/list.aspx?manu=GULFSTREAM&amp;mdltxt=II 'Gulfstream II For Sale'] Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A modified version of the G-II, called the [[Shuttle Training Aircraft]] (STA), mimics the cockpit configuration and flight characteristics of the [[Space Shuttle]] and is used by [[NASA]] as a training airplane for practice shuttle approaches (referred to as &quot;dives&quot;). Four G-IIs were used for this purpose N944NA, cn 144; N945NA, cn 118; N946NA, cn 146 and N947NA, cn 147.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motherboard.tv/2010/2/22/nasa-s-space-shuttle-training-plane-a-fabulous-1970s-business-jet 'NASA's Space Shuttle Training Plane? A Fabulous 1970s Business Jet'] Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

NASA contracted Lockheed-Georgia to modify one G-II as the Propfan Test Assessment aircraft (N650PF, cn 118). The aircraft had a nacelle added to the left wing, containing an 6000&amp;nbsp;hp Allison 570 turboprop engine (derived from the XT701 turboshaft developed for the [[Boeing Vertol XCH-62]] program), powering a 9-foot diameter Hamilton Standard SR-7 [[propfan]]. The aircraft, so configured, first flew in March 1987. After an extensive test program, the modifications were removed from the aircraft and the aircraft became a Shuttle Training Aircraft (STA).&lt;ref&gt;[http://hdl.handle.net/2060/19900002423 'Propfan Test Assessment (PTA)']  NASA-CR-185138. Retrieved 28 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hdl.handle.net/2060/19900002422 'Propfan Test Assessment (PTA): Flight Test Report'] NASA-CR-182278. Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

One G-II (N82CR, cn 80)was modified for use by [[Northrop Grumman]] as a demonstrator for the [[Broad Area Maritime Surveillance]] (BAMS) contract.&lt;ref&gt;Plomitzer, Gerhard. [http://www.airliners.net/photo/Northrop-Grumman/Grumman-G-1159-Gulfstream/1460757/L/ &quot;Grumman American G-1159 Gulfstream II-SP aircraft.&quot;] ''airliners.net,'' January 4, 2009. Retrieved: June 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

One G-IIB (N74A, cn 36) was modified by Aeromet of Tulsa, Oklahoma for use as the HALO I aircraft for the US [[Missile Defense Agency]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scalecraft.com/gulfstreamhaloi.aspx 'Gulfstream HALO I'] Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A second G-IIB (N178B, cn 125) was modified by the addition of a large dorsal fairing housing a telescope by Aeromet as the HALO II aircraft for the Missile Defense Agency.&lt;ref&gt;Fritsche, Danny. [http://www.airliners.net/photo/Grumman-American-G-1159B/0853662/L/ &quot;Grumman American G-1159B Gulfstream II-B aircraft.&quot;] ''airliners.net,'' June 6, 2005. Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A G-IISP (N950NA, cn 185) was modified by the addition of a wing tip pod and a ventral radome as the HALO III aircraft for the Missile Defense Agency. This aircraft serves as a target for the [[Boeing YAL-1]] Airborne Laser Testbed.&lt;ref&gt;Duenas, Ralph. [http://www.airliners.net/photo/Grumman-American-G-1159/1525822/L/ &quot;Grumman American G-1159 Gulfstream II-SP aircraft.&quot;] ''airliners.net,'' May 15, 2009. Retrieved: June 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another G-IIB (N779LC, cn 88) has been modified with the same large dorsal fairing as N178B, as the HALO IV aircraft for the Missile Defense Agency.&lt;ref&gt;Snyder, Jeff. [http://www.airliners.net/photo/Grumman-G-1159B-Gulfstream/2363402/L/ &quot;Grumman American G-1159B Gulfstream II-B aircraft.&quot;] ''airliners.net,'' November 26, 2013. Retrieved 17 August 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

A G-II (N10123, cn 107) had tip tanks added containing ground mapping radar, along with fairings on the wing undersurface and a centerline pod. This aircraft operated as the Calgis Geosar and is now owned by Earthdata Aviation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://southport.jpl.nasa.gov/html/projects/geosar/geosar.html 'GeoSAR: Geographic Synthetic Aperture Radar'] Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A G-II (N105TB, cn 31) had underwing pylons and various fuselage appendages added to enable it to operate as a sensor testbed for MIT Lincoln Labs.&lt;ref&gt;Duenas, Ralph. [http://www.airliners.net/photo/Untitled-(USA--/Grumman-G-1159-Gulfstream/0881763/L/ &quot;Grumman G-1159 Gulfstream II aircraft.&quot;] ''airliners.net,'' July 18, 2005. Retrieved: June 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A G-II TT (N81RR, cn 246) is being modified for NASA, by the addition of fuselage appendages and underwing pylons, to serve as the High Ice Water Content (HIWC) sampling aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;[http://esrl.noaa.gov/gsd/research/events/nov2010/presentations/Thur-Dec-2/pm/Haggerty_HIWC_InteragencyReview_Nov2010.pptx 'High Ice Water Content Project'] Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A G-II (JA8431, cn 141) is operated by Diamond Air Service in various configurations to support missions involving environmental measurements.  In one configuration, it can carry two 3D X/L band PI SAR (Parametric Interpherometric Synthetic Aperture Radar) pods under the forward fuselage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.das.co.jp/new_html_e/service/02.html 'Observation Flight'] Retrieved 20 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A G-IISP (N510AG, cn 159) is operated by the Orion Air Group in support Northrop Grumman’s development of the multi-role, tactical-command data link (MR-TCDL). The aircraft was modified with 19-inch and nine-inch, satcom dish-antennas, as well as additional radomes on the top and bottom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ainonline.com/news/single-news-page/article/orion-air-group-breaks-cover-to-describe-special-mission-work-30591/ 'Orion Air Group Breaks Cover To Describe Special Mission Work'] Retrieved 31 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airliners.net/photo/Orion-Air-Group/Grumman-American-G-1159/1960193/L 'Picture of the Grumman American G-1159 Gulfstream II-SP aircraft'] Retrieved 31 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A G-III (N186PA, cn 317) has been modified by the addition of a Raytheon SeaVueTM coastal and sea surveillance radar in a belly radome and is operated by the Phoenix Air Group in support of Raytheon Ktech.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ktech.com/it_and_controls/field_test/Airborne_Test_and_Evaluation.html 'Airborne Test and Evaluation'] Retrieved 31 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The aircraft provides airborne maritime range surveillance for the Missile Defense Agency (MDA) and other Department of Defense range facilities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.phoenixair.com/milops_range.html 'Military Ops Range Clearing'] Retrieved 31 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operators==

===Military operators===
;{{GAB}}
* [[Military of Gabon]]
;{{LBY}}
* [[Libyan Air Force (1951-2011)|Libyan Air Force]]
;{{MAR}}
* [[Royal Moroccan Air Force]]
;{{NGR}}
* [[Nigerian Air Force]]
;{{OMA}}
;{{PAN}}
;{{VEN}}
;{{USA}}
* [[NASA]]
* [[United States Army]]
* [[United States Coast Guard]]

===Civil Operators===
The aircraft is operated by private individuals, companies, non-government organizations and executive charter operators. A number of companies also use the aircraft as part of [[fractional ownership]] programs.

==Accidents and incidents==
* May 3, 1982 - A Gulfstream II from the Algerian government was shot down by a fighter jet in the border area of Iraq, Iran and Turkey. All 15 people on board, including the Algerian foreign minister [[Mohammed Seddik Ben Yahia]] were killed.
* In April 1983, Mallow racecourse, in Ireland, became an emergency airfield when a Mexican Gulfstream II business jet made a precautionary landing. A temporary tarmacadam runway of almost 3,000 feet in length was laid to enable the aircraft to leave five weeks later in May. A movie, 'The Runway', was loosely based on the incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=The Corkman|title=Pilot's girl touches down|url=http://www.independent.ie/regionals/corkman/news/pilots-girl-touches-down-27078359.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In January 19 of 1990, an accident occurred at Little Rock municipal airport, Arkansas when a Gulfstream II struck guidance lights and crashed short of the runway while attempting to land in stormy weather. It was carrying employees of an Eastman Kodak Co. subsidiary when the flight was diverted to Little Rock due to unfavorable weather. All 7 on board including 2 pilots were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=1990|title=PLANE CRASHES IN STORM, 7 KILLED|url=http://www.apnewsarchive.com/1990/Plane-Crashes-In-Storm-7-Killed/id-bb2afe8adafb200052716a19954b328a}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aircraft on display==
;United States

* Gulfstream II Serial #001 was donated to the Carolinas Aviation Museum in Charlotte, North Carolina.  It is intact but in storage awaiting the development of another addition to the Museum.
* Gulfstream II Serial #146 N946NA made its final flight on September 21, 2011 when it landed at the Rick Husband Amarillo International Airport in Amarillo, Texas and became a permanent exhibit at the Texas Air &amp; Space Museum.{{citation needed|date=January 2016}}

==Specifications==
{{aerospecs
|ref=Jane's Aircraft Upgrades 2008-2009, 2008, Jane's Information Group Limited, Page 420-421
|met or eng?=&lt;!-- eng for US/UK aircraft, met for all others --&gt;eng
|crew=2
|capacity=19 (maximum certified)
|length m=24.36
|length ft=79
|length in=11
|span m=20.98
|span ft=68
|span in=10
|swept m=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept ft=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept in=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|rot number=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot dia m=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot dia ft=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot dia in=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|dia m=&lt;!-- airships etc --&gt;
|dia ft=&lt;!-- airships etc --&gt;
|dia in=&lt;!-- airships etc --&gt;
|width m=&lt;!-- if applicable --&gt;
|width ft=&lt;!-- if applicable --&gt;
|width in=&lt;!-- if applicable --&gt;
|height m=7.47
|height ft=24
|height in=6
|wing area sqm=75.21
|wing area sqft=809.6
|swept area sqm=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept area sqft=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|rot area sqm=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot area sqft=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|volume m3=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|volume ft3=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|aspect ratio=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|empty weight kg=16.576 &lt;!--(typical operating, without tip-tanks)--&gt;
|empty weight lb=36,544 &lt;!--(typical operating, without tip-tanks)--&gt;
|max fuel weight kg=10 498
|max fuel weight lb=23 125
|gross weight kg=29,711 &lt;!--(maximum take-off weight)--&gt;
|gross weight lb=65,500 &lt;!--(maximum take-off weight)--&gt;
|lift kg=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|lift lb=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|eng1 number=2
|eng1 type=[[Rolls-Royce Spey|Rolls-Royce Spey 511-8]] turbofan
|eng1 kw=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng1 hp=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng1 kn=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;51
|eng1 lbf=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;11,400
|eng1 kn-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng1 lbf-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng2 number=
|eng2 type=
|eng2 kw=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng2 hp=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng2 kn=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng2 lbf=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng2 kn-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng2 lbf-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|max speed kmh=936
|max speed mph=581
|max speed mach=0.85
|cruise speed kmh=778
|cruise speed mph=483
|cruise speed mach=0.72
|range km=6,635 &lt;!-- w/ tip-tanks, NBAA VFR range with 30 min reserve, crew of 3, &amp; 2000 lbs pax --&gt;
|range miles=4,123 &lt;!-- w/ tip-tanks, NBAA VFR range with 30 min reserve, crew of 3, &amp; 2000 lbs pax --&gt;
|endurance h=&lt;!-- if range unknown --&gt;
|endurance min=&lt;!-- if range unknown --&gt;
|ceiling m=13,715
|ceiling ft=45,000
|glide ratio=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|climb rate ms=
|climb rate ftmin=
|sink rate ms=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|sink rate ftmin=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|armament1=
|armament2=
|armament3=
|armament4=
|armament5=
|armament6=
}}

==See also==
{{aircontent
|related=
* [[Grumman Gulfstream I]]
* [[Gulfstream III]]
* [[Shuttle Training Aircraft]]
|similar aircraft=
|sequence=
|lists=
|see also=
}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category-inline|Grumman Gulfstream II}}

{{Grumman aircraft}}
{{Gulfstream}}
{{US transport aircraft}}

[[Category:Gulfstream aircraft|Gulfstream II]]
[[Category:United States business aircraft 1960–1969]]
[[Category:Twinjets]]
[[Category:Grumman aircraft|Gulfstream II]]
[[Category:Low-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:T-tail aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>iurr29py83nz0w399akw0t8jeq0ucyv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
