<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hatsuharu-class destroyer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13966436</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740821121</id>
      <parentid>734918919</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-23T14:14:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* External links */clean up, replaced: WWIIJapaneseShips → WWII Japanese Ships using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (12084)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24688">{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image= [[File:Japanese destroyer Nenohi 1933.jpg|300px|Nenohi]]
|Ship caption= ''Nenohi'' as initially built on full speed trial at Tokyo Bay, 23 August 1933.
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Name=''Hatsuharu'' class
|Builders=
|Operators={{navy|Empire of Japan}}
|Class before={{sclass-|Akatsuki|destroyer (1931)|4}}
|Class after={{sclass-|Shiratsuyu|destroyer|4}}
|Subclasses=''Ariake'' class
|Cost=
|Built range=1931–35
|In service range=
|In commission range=1933–45
|Total ships completed=6
|Total ships lost=6
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=y
|Header caption= (as initially completed)
|Ship type= [[Destroyer]]
|Ship displacement= {{convert|1530|MT|LT|abbr=on}}
|Ship length={{convert|109.5|m|ftin|abbr=on}} overall
|Ship beam={{convert|10|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draught={{convert|3.38|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=2 shafts; 2 [[Kampon]] [[steam turbine]]s 
|Ship power=*{{convert|42000|shp|lk=in|abbr=on}}
*3 [[water-tube boiler]]s
|Ship speed= {{convert|36|kn|lk=in}} 
|Ship range= {{convert|4000|nmi|lk=in|abbr=on}} @ {{convert|14|kn}}
|Ship complement=212
|Ship armament=*2 × twin, 1 × single [[Type 3 127 mm 50 caliber naval gun]]s
*2 × single [[QF 2-pounder naval gun#QF 2-pounder Mark II|40 mm]] AA guns
*3 × triple {{convert|610|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s
*18 × [[depth charge]]s 
|Ship armour=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
The {{nihongo|'''''Hatsuharu''-class destroyers'''|初春型駆逐艦|Hatsuharugata kuchikukan}} were a class of [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] [[destroyer]]s in the service before and during [[World War II]].  The final two vessels in the class, completed after modifications to the design, are sometimes considered a separate &quot;''Ariake'' class&quot;.

==Background==
In compliance with the [[London Naval Treaty|1930 London Naval Treaty]], the ''Hatsuharu''-class vessels were significantly smaller than the previous {{sclass-|Fubuki|destroyer|5}} and {{sclass-|Akatsuki|destroyer (1931)|0}} destroyers. However, Japanese naval designers attempted to stretch contemporary destroyer design to the limit and beyond by equipping the new class with an armament only slightly weaker than that carried by the earlier classes, despite its smaller hull and displacement.&lt;ref name=&quot;global1&quot;&gt;GlobalSecurity.org: [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/japan/hatsuharu-dd.htm IJN ''Hatsuharu'' class]&lt;/ref&gt;

This resulted in a top-heavy design, with severe stability problems, and the weight-control measures used by designers to fit as much armament as possible onto a ship of a given tonnage were carried to an extreme, which further contributed to the structural weaknesses of the ships of this period. This was graphically demonstrated when the [[torpedo boat]] {{ship|Japanese torpedo boat|Tomozuru||2}} capsized in 1934 during heavy seas (the &quot;Tomozuru Incident&quot;) and when a [[typhoon]] ripped the bows off two ''Fubuki''-class destroyers (the &quot;IJN 4th Fleet Incident&quot;) in 1935. As a result of these two incidents the ''Hatsuharu''-class vessels had to be rebuilt (the first two completed had to be rebuilt twice) or modified while building to remedy their stability problems.

==Design==
The ''Hatsuharu''-class destroyers were designed to accompany the Japanese main striking force and to conduct both day and night [[torpedo]] attacks against the [[United States Navy]] as it advanced across the [[Pacific Ocean]], according to Japan's naval strategic projections.&lt;ref&gt;Peattie &amp; Evans, ''Kaigun''&lt;/ref&gt; They were to be armed much as the ''Fubuki'' class despite displacing only 1400 tons compared to the 1700 tons of the earlier destroyers. Furthermore, their fire control systems were to be more modern than the older systems and suitable for [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] use. This required the [[gun turret]]s to be modified for high-angle fire, which also meant more powerful motors to traverse and elevate the guns more quickly to engage high-speed aircraft. The [[torpedo launcher]]s were to be given a protective shield to allow for use in heavy weather and to protect against splinter damage. And the ''Hatsuharu'' vessels were to be fitted with modern, enclosed command spaces protected against [[strafing]] aircraft. These requirements could only be met by adding weight high up on the ship and increased the ship's [[center of gravity]]. The only way to adhere to the allotted displacement was to try to reduce the weight of the hull and other equipment below the [[waterline]] as much as possible. But this put the ship's designers in a [[no-win situation]] as any reduction of weight below the waterline further raised the ship's [[center of gravity]] and reduced her stability.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

The weight of the hull could generally be reduced by using higher grades of steel that were lighter and thinner for the same strength, reducing dimensions, particularly length, or using advanced construction techniques like welding that saved weight over the conventional riveting. The Japanese used the same high tensile [[steel]] for the ''Hatsuharu'' class as they did for the older destroyers and chose not to increase the power of the turbines and boilers to achieve the desired high speed, but lengthened the hull to offset the reduced power of the light-weight machinery. The [[Beam (nautical)|beam]] was increased to counter some of the extra top-weight, but the draft was reduced to reduce hull resistance, which also reduced stability by lessening the area of the hull beneath the waterline in comparison to the area above it, which was subject to pressure from the wind. Electric welding was extensively used to reduce weight although it was at an early stage of development in Japan and was still problematic.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, p. 94&lt;/ref&gt;

Extensive weight-saving measures were used during the design and construction of the hull. More frames of lighter construction were spaced more closely together to reduce the thickness of the hull plating and the extensive use of welding (only the longitudinal [[strength member]]s and a few other parts were riveted) were some of the techniques utilized to reduce hull weight by {{convert|66.5|t|ton}} in comparison to the ''Fubuki'' class. The ''Hatsuharu'' vessels were some {{convert|10|m|ftin}} shorter than the ''Fubuki''-class vessels, but weighed {{convert|4.9|t|ton}} per {{convert|1|m|ft}} of hull length compared to the latter's {{convert|5.09|t|ton}} per {{convert|1|m|ft}}.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 94–95&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
The ''Hatsuharu''-class ships were shorter than their predecessors, at {{convert|109.5|m|ftin|abbr=on}} [[length overall|overall]]. The ships had a beam of 10 metres and at full load a [[draft (ship)|draft]] of {{convert|3.35|m|ftin|abbr=on}}. Despite the emphasis on weight-saving during construction, the ships were significantly overweight as completed and displaced {{convert|1530|MT|LT}} at standard load, and {{convert|1981|MT|LT|-1}} at full load, nearly {{convert|130|MT|LT|-2}} more than planned.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 97–98&lt;/ref&gt;

The hull of the ''Hatsuharu''-class vessels retained the general configuration of the ''Fubuki''-class destroyers with a long [[forecastle]] and a pronounced flare of the forecastle to improve sea-keeping at high speeds by adding buoyancy and reducing the spray and water coming over the deck. A large [[bridge (ship)|bridge]] structure was located at the aft end of the forecastle deck topped by four fire control stations of various types. Lowest, just above the compass bridge, was the torpedo director (''Hassha shikisho''), with the gunnery fire direction station (''Shageki shikisho'') next above. The fire director tower (''Hōiban shagekito'') was third from the bottom and behind it was the {{convert|3|m|ftin|abbr=on}} rangefinder. Each of these was protected by {{convert|10|mm|in|abbr=on}} plates of ''Dücol steel'' against strafing and shell splinters.&lt;ref name=l95&gt;Lengerer, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;

For the first time in a Japanese destroyer a [[Superfire|superfiring]] turret was fitted forward of the bridge. It was only a single gun Model A turret, to save weight high in the ship, and was mounted on a deckhouse to elevate it above the twin gun Model B Mod 2 (B-gata kai-2) turret mounted on the forecastle deck. The second twin gun turret was mounted at the rear of the ship on the main deck. These turrets were slightly heavier than the earlier ''Model A'' and ''Model B'' turrets fitted on the ''Fubuki''s. All turrets were fitted with the [[12.7 cm/50 Type 3 naval gun|{{convert|12.7|cm|in|abbr=on}} Type 3]] gun.&lt;ref name=l95/&gt;

The uptakes of the two forward boiler rooms were trunked together aft of the break in the forecastle into the fore [[funnel (ship)|funnel]] while the rear boiler room exhausted into the smaller rear funnel. Both funnels were inclined to the rear to reduce the amount of smoke that might reach the bridge. A tripod mast was fitted between the bridge and the fore funnel. Between the two funnels was the forward {{convert|61|cm|in}} triple [[torpedo]] tube mount fitted on a low platform. Behind it &quot;was a torpedo locker with its mechanical quick reload system (''Kiryoku sōtenshiki jihatsu sōten sochi'') for the three reserve torpedoes inside.&quot;&lt;ref name=l95/&gt; To preserve lateral stability the aft funnel was offset to starboard while the torpedo mount was offset to port. The reload locker was also offset slightly to port and angled inboard to facilitate reloading. The middle torpedo mount was positioned behind the aft funnel on the centerline, but its reload locker was positioned identically to that of the forward mount. Superimposed to starboard and overlapping the middle mount was the rear triple torpedo mount positioned on the rear deckhouse. Immediately behind the mount was its locker positioned on the centerline, but angled slightly to the right so that its mount only had to traverse slightly to align with the locker and begin reloading. This was the first ship in history to be fitted with superimposed torpedo tubes, made necessary by the designer's insistence on fitting nine torpedo tubes despite the Navy's requirement for only six.&lt;ref name=l95/&gt;

A small platform that carried a {{convert|2|m|ftin|abbr=on}} [[rangefinder]] was mounted above the rear torpedo locker and a {{convert|90|cm|ftin|abbr=on}} [[searchlight]] was mounted on a tower behind the rear funnel. The two license-built [[Vickers]] [[QF 2-pounder naval gun#QF 2-pounder Mark II|{{convert|40|mm|in|abbr=on}} (''pom pom'')]] [[anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] guns were mounted on an elevated platform at the front of the rear funnel. Curiously they were another case where the designer exceeded the requirements laid down by the Navy.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 95, 97&lt;/ref&gt;

===Propulsion===
The ''Hatsuharu''s carried two sets of [[Kampon]] geared [[steam turbine]]s, one for each shaft. Each set consisted one low-pressure and one high-pressure turbine, plus a cruise turbine connected to the high-pressure turbine. The LP and HP turbines were connected to the propeller shaft by a two-[[pinion]] [[reduction gear]]. Each [[propeller (ship)|propellor]] had a diameter of {{convert|3.05|m|ftin|abbr=on}} and a pitch of {{convert|3.7|m|ftin|abbr=on}}. The total horsepower of the ''Hatsuharu'' class was only {{convert|42000|lk=in|shp|abbr=on}} compared to the {{convert|50000|shp|abbr=on}} of their ''Fubuki''-class predecessors, but the machinery was significantly lighter and more powerful on a unit basis. The ''Hatsuharu''s' machinery weighed only {{convert|106|t|ton}} compared to the {{convert|144|t|ton}} of the ''Fubuki'' class, or 396 [[Horsepower#Shaft horsepower|shaft horsepower]] per tonne versus 347 shaft horsepower per tonne for the older ships.&lt;ref name=l101&gt;Lengerer, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly the three Kampon Type Ro-Gō boilers used in the ''Hatsuharu''-class ships weighed {{convert|50|t|ton}} in comparison to the {{convert|51|t|ton}} boilers used in the ''Fubuki'' class, but produced {{convert|14000|shp|abbr=on}} each while the older boilers produced {{convert|12500|hp|abbr=on}}. This gave a ratio of 3.6&amp;nbsp;kg per shaft horsepower for the ''Hatsuharu''{{'}}s compared to the 4.1&amp;nbsp;kg per shaft horsepower of their predecessors. The newer design of boilers initially used steam pressurized to {{convert|20|bar|psi|adj=on}}, just like the older models, but used [[superheater|superheating]] to improve efficiency while the older boilers simply used [[saturated steam]].&lt;ref name=l2&gt;Lengerer, p. 102&lt;/ref&gt;

A single 100&amp;nbsp;kW turbo-generator was fitted behind the reduction gears in a separate compartment and two 40&amp;nbsp;kW [[diesel generator]]s were located between the propeller shafts. As initially completed the ''Hatsuharu'' had a range of {{convert|4000|nmi|lk=in}} at a speed of {{convert|18|kn|lk=in}} with {{convert|460|t|ton}} of fuel. On trials, {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Nenohi||2}} had a top speed of {{convert|37.64|kn}} from {{convert|47150|shp|abbr=on}} at a displacement of {{convert|1677|t|ton}}.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 101–02&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armament===
The ''Hatsuharu''-class destroyers used the same 50 [[Caliber#Caliber as measurement of length|caliber]] 12.7&amp;nbsp;cm gun as the ''Fubuki'' class, but all turrets could elevate to 75° to give the main guns a minimal ability to engage aircraft. During the war the single turret was removed on all surviving ships after 1942. The only [[anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] guns were two water-cooled, license-built Vickers [[QF 2-pounder naval gun#QF 2-pounder Mark II|40-millimeter guns]]. These guns were deemed to be too heavy, slow-firing and short-ranged and were replaced by license-built French [[Hotchkiss et Cie|Hotchkiss]] [[Type 96 25 mm AT/AA Gun|{{convert|25|mm|in|abbr=on}} Type 96]] anti-aircraft guns in single, double and triple mounts from 1943 for the surviving ships. Exact numbers are not always known, but {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Hatsuharu||2}} was carrying three triple power-driven mounts, including one mounted in lieu of the single 12.7&amp;nbsp;cm gun turret, one twin power-driven mount fitted on a platform in front of the bridge and two hand-worked single mounts in June 1944. These powered mounts were unsatisfactory because their traverse and elevation speeds were too slow to engage high-speed aircraft&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNJAP_25mm-60_mg.htm|title=Japan 25 mm/60 (1&quot;) Type 96 Model 1|date=4 March 2009|accessdate=2009-07-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and more single mounts were fitted to ships in the last year of the war. For example, {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Hatsushimo|1933|2}} mounted ten single 25&amp;nbsp;guns when she was lost in July 1945. Four license-built Hotchkiss {{convert|13.2|mm|in|abbr=on}} Type 93 [[machine gun]]s were also fitted to ''Hatsushimo'', but these were of limited utility against modern aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 104–05&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[61 cm Type 90 torpedo]] was mounted in triple tube Type 90 Model 2 launchers, derived from the twin tube Type 89 launcher used in the {{sclass-|Takao|cruiser|0}} [[heavy cruiser]]s. Shields were fitted to both the torpedo mounts and lockers to protect them from the weather and from strafing aircraft. Initially the shields were made from [[Duralumin]] to save weight, but these quickly corroded and had to be replaced. &quot;NiCrMo&quot; steel, taken from the air chambers of obsolete torpedoes, {{convert|3|mm|in|abbr=on}} in thickness, was chosen for the new shields to save weight. The Type 90 Model 2 weighed, including the shield, a total of {{convert|14.4|t|ton}} excluding the torpedo itself. Despite the addition of an extra torpedo tube, it was still lighter than the {{convert|14.5|t|ton}} of the Type 89. It was traversed by an electro-hydraulic system and could traverse 360° in twenty-five seconds. If the backup manual system was used the time required increased to two minutes. Each tube could be reloaded in twenty-three seconds using the endless wire and winch provided.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 102–03&lt;/ref&gt;

Only eighteen [[depth charge]]s were initially carried in a rack at the stern, but this increased to thirty-six after the autumn of 1942. Apparently no [[sonar]] or [[hydrophone]]s were fitted until after the outbreak of the war when the Type 93 sonar and Type 93 hydrophones were mounted. Both of these were inferior to contemporary American and British designs.&lt;ref name=l6&gt;Lengerer, p. 106&lt;/ref&gt;

===Radar===
[[Radar]] was not installed on the surviving ships of this class until late in the war, possibly as late as 1944. They were given a Type 22 radar on the foremast, a Type 13 on the mainmast and a Type E-27 [[Electronic countermeasures|radar countermeasures]] device was carried high on the foremast.&lt;ref name=l6/&gt;

==Construction==
A dozen ''Hatsuharu''-class destroyers were authorized in 1931 as part of the so-called [[1st Naval Armaments Supplement Programme (Japan, 1931)|Circle One Program]] (''Maru Ichi Keikaku''). Three were laid down in Fiscal Year 1931 and the next three in Fiscal Year 1933. The remaining six ships were built as the {{sclass-|Shiratsuyu|destroyer|4}}.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 92–93&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|+ Ships of the ''Hatsuharu'' class&lt;ref&gt;Whitley, pp. 196–97&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! 
! Ship
! Shipyard
! Laid down
! Launched
! Completed
! Fate
|-
| 初春
| {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Hatsuharu|1933|2}}
| [[Sasebo Naval Arsenal]]
| 14 May 1931
| 27 February 1932
| 30 September 1933
| Sunk in action, 13 November 1944
|-
| 子日
| {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Nenohi|1932|2}}
| [[Uraga Dock Company]]
| 15 December 1931
| 22 December 1932
| 30 September 1933
| Sunk in action, 5 July 1942
|-
| 若葉
| {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Wakaba|1934|2}}
| Sasebo Naval Arsenal
| 12 December 1931
| 18 March 1934
| 31 October 1934
| Sunk in action, 24 October 1944
|-
| 初霜
| {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Hatsushimo|1933|2}}
| Uraga Dock Company 
| 31 January 1933
| 4 November 1933
| 27 September 1934
| [[Naval mine|Mined]] and sunk, 30 July 1945
|-
| 有明
| {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Ariake|1934|2}}
| [[Kawasaki Shipbuilding Corporation|Kawasaki Kobe Shipyard]]
| 14 January 1933
| 23 September 1934
| 25 March 1935
| Sunk in action, 28 July 1943
|-
| 夕暮
| {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Yūgure|1934|2}}
| [[Maizuru Naval Arsenal]]
| 9 April 1933
| 6 May 1934
| 30 March 1935
| Sunk in action, 20 July 1943
|-
|}

==Design modifications==
[[File:Japanese destroyer Hatsuharu 1934.jpg|thumb|left|''Hatsuharu'' on 1934 as reconstructed.]]
On trials the ''Hatsuharu'' was found to roll heavily, with a very short period of roll and she heeled at an angle of 38° at high speed when her helm was set to 10°. This demonstrated to the Navy that her [[metacentric height]] was too low. The Navy ordered in September 1933 that {{convert|30|cm|in}} bulges be fitted on each side to increase her beam and thus raise the metacentric height. ''Hatsuharu'' and ''Nenohi'' were modified after completion; ''Wakaba'' and ''Hatsushimo'' were modified during construction. ''Ariake'' and ''Yugure'' were at a much earlier stage of construction and had their beam increased by {{convert|1|m|ft}}. The bulges were estimated to add {{convert|30|t|ton}} to the trial displacement.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer, pp. 97, 109–10&lt;/ref&gt;

The capsizing of the torpedo boat {{ship|Japanese torpedo boat|Tomozuru||2}} in 1934 forced the Navy to re-evaluate the heavy armament of the ''Hatsuharu'' and other classes. As a result of the investigations in ship stability after the capsizing of the torpedo boat ''Tomozuru'', all vessels in the ''Hatsuharu'' class were modified to improve their stability:&lt;ref name=&quot;lengerer97&quot;&gt;Lengerer, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;

* The after deckhouse and rangefinder were removed and the forward single 12.7&amp;nbsp;cm gun mounting was relocated to this position, directly ahead of the after twin gun mount; its magazine was converted for use as a fuel tank.
* The No.3 triple torpedo mount and its reload locker were removed.
* The compass bridge was lowered by one level and the anti-strafing armor was removed from the entire bridge structure.
* Both funnels were shortened by {{convert|1|-|1.5|m}} as were both masts.
* The forward torpedo tube mount was lowered {{convert|30|cm}}, the machine-gun platform by {{convert|1.5|m}} and the searchlight platform by {{convert|2|m}}.
* The bulges were removed and the anchor chain stowage was lowered by one deck.
* The outer bottom plating was reinforced and about {{convert|70|t|ton}} of ballast was added in the ship's bottom.
* An automatic system was fitted which filled part of the fuel tanks with seawater to compensate for the consumption of fuel and resulting rise in the center of gravity and hence loss of stability. When the sea water was added to the fuel tank due to their different specific gravities the seawater sank to the bottom of the tank, while the oil floated on top.&lt;ref name=l6/&gt;

The first two ships of the class — ''Hatsuharu'' and ''Nenohi'' — had already entered by the time of the ''Tomozuru'' Incident. They were removed from service and modified in the [[Kure Naval Arsenal]]. The remaining four members of the class were still under construction and were modified before completion.&lt;ref name=&quot;lengerer97&quot;/&gt;

Based on the stability issues shown by ''Hatsuharu'' during her trials, ''Ariake'' and ''Yūgure'' had been modified for two balanced rudders placed directly behind the propellers and angled outward 18.5° to reduce the angle of heel when turning. These proved to reduce their speed by one knot and were removed after their trials as superfluous since both ships had been rebuilt to reflect the lessons of the ''Tomozuru'' Incident.&lt;ref&gt;Lenger, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reinforcement of the hull===
As a result of hull damage sustained by two {{sclass-|Fubuki|destroyer|2}}s during a typhoon on 26 September 1935, the subsequent investigation led to all ships in the ''Hatsuharu'' class spending 3 months in the shipyards having their hulls strengthened, at the cost of an extra {{convert|54|t|ton}} of weight, and their fixed ballast increased from {{convert|64|to|84|t|ton}}. As a result of these and previous modifications the ships were 23.2% heavier, had lost 33% of their torpedo armament and were {{convert|3|kn|km/h}} slower compared with their original design values.&lt;ref name=l101/&gt;

==Wartime service==
All ''Hatsuharu''-class ships were lost during the [[Pacific War]]. Four were sunk by aircraft attack, and ''Nenohi'' was sunk by the American submarine {{USS|Triton|SS-201|6}}. ''Hatsushimo'', the last Japanese destroyer lost in the war, struck a [[Naval mine|mine]] on 30 July 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Whitley, p. 197&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|3}}

==References==
* {{cite book  | last = Evans  | first = David| first2 = Mark R. |last2=Peattie  | year = 1997  | title = Kaigun: Strategy, Tactics, and Technology in the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1887–1941  | publisher =Naval Institute Press  | location =Annapolis, Maryland  | isbn = 0-87021-192-7|lastauthoramp=y}}
*{{cite book | last = Brown | first = David| year = 1990 | title = Warship Losses of World War Two | publisher = Naval Institute Press| location =Annapolis, Maryland| isbn = 1-55750-914-X}}
* {{cite book|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1922–1946|editor1-last=Chesneau|editor1-first=Roger|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=Greenwich, UK|year=1980|isbn=0-85177-146-7}}
*{{cite book| last = Jentschura| first = Hansgeorg| first2 = Dieter |last2=Jung|first3=Peter |last3=Mickel| year = 1977| title = Warships of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1869–1945| publisher = United States Naval Institute| location = Annapolis, Maryland| isbn = 0-87021-893-X|lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|last=Lengerer|first=Hans|title=The Japanese Destroyers of the Hatsuharu Class|publisher=Conway|location=London|year=2007|series=Warship 2007|pages=91–110|isbn=1-84486-041-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Whitley|first=M. J.|title=Destroyers of World War 2|publisher=Naval Institute Press|date=1988|isbn=0-87021-326-1|location=Annapolis, Maryland}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Hatsuharu class destroyers}}
*[http://www.combinedfleet.com/hatsuh_c.htm  CombinedFleet.com: ''Hatsuharu''-class destroyers]
*[http://www.combinedfleet.com/hatsuh_t.htm  CombinedFleet.com: ''Hatsuharu'' history]
*{{cite web| last = Nishida| first = Hiroshi| url = http://homepage2.nifty.com/nishidah/e/stc0425.htm| title = Materials of IJN: Hatsuharu class destroyer| work = Imperial Japanese Navy}}

{{Hatsuharu class destroyer}}
{{WWII Japanese Ships}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hatsuharu-class destroyer}}
[[Category:Destroyer classes]]
[[Category:Hatsuharu-class destroyers| ]]
[[Category:World War II destroyers of Japan| ]]</text>
      <sha1>1lszflb3js7avegeef32747i5rniiyv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
