<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Heinrich Ehrler</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2000208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750658918</id>
      <parentid>748070370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T02:45:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>K.e.coffman</username>
        <id>22615369</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added {{[[Template:refimprove|refimprove]]}} tag to article ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21152">{{refimprove|date=November 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2011}}
{{Use American English|date=December 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Heinrich Ehrler
|birth_date={{Birth date|1917|9|14|df=y}}
|death_date={{death date and age|1945|4|4|1917|9|17|df=y}}
|birth_place=[[Lauda-Königshofen|Oberbalbach]]
|death_place=[[Stendal]]
|image=ehrler.jpg
|caption=Heinrich Ehrler
|nickname=
|allegiance={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch={{Luftwaffe}}
|serviceyears=1935–45
|rank=[[Major (Germany)|Major]]
|commands=[[JG 5|JG 5 ''Eismeer'']]
|unit=[[JG 77]], [[JG 5]] and [[JG 7]]
|battles=[[Spanish Civil War]]&lt;br/&gt;[[World War II]]
|awards=[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
|laterwork=}}
'''Heinrich Ehrler''' (14 September 1917 – 4 April 1945) was a German [[Luftwaffe]] aviator during [[World War II]], credited with 208 enemy aircraft shot down in over 400 combat missions. The majority of his victories were claimed over the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], with nine claims over the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] which included eight in the [[Messerschmitt Me 262]] jet fighter.

Ehrler joined the military service in the [[Wehrmacht]] in 1935, initially serving with the [[artillery]]. He participated in the [[Spanish Civil War]] and following the outbreak of World War II transferred to the ''[[Jagdwaffe]]'' (fighter force). 

Scapegoated for the loss of the German battleship [[German battleship Tirpitz|''Tirpitz'']], Ehrler was court-martialled, stripped of his command and sentenced to three years and two months.&lt;ref&gt;Toliver &amp; Constable 1996, p. 311.&lt;/ref&gt; Ehrler's sentence was later commuted and his loss of rank rescinded, and in February 1945 he returned to service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toliver p312&quot;&gt;Toliver &amp; Constable 1996, p. 312.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 April 1945, he shot down two Allied bombers for his final two victories, before destroying a third by [[Aerial ramming|ramming]] with his damaged aircraft after having run out of ammunition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toliver p312&quot;/&gt;

==Early life and career==
Ehrler was born on 14 September 1917 in [[Oberbalbach]], today part of Lauda-Königshofen, in the district of [[Tauberbischofsheim]] of the [[Grand Duchy of Baden]]. He was one of eight children of a [[laborer]]. When his mother died, his father married again. The second marriage added four more children to the family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p269&quot;&gt;Stockert 1997, p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following a [[vocational education]] as a [[butcher]], Ehrler joined the military service of the [[Wehrmacht]] on 29 October 1935. He initially served with the 7th battery of ''Artillerie-Regiment'' 25 (25th artillery regiment) in [[Ludwigsburg]]. He then transferred to the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' where he served with ''Flak-Regiment'' 8 (8th anti-aircraft artillery regiment) from 7 April to 1 November 1936.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p269&quot;/&gt;

From 2 November 1936 to 15 August 1937, Ehrler served with the 3./''Flakbteilung'' 88 (3rd company of the 88th anti-aircraft department) of the [[Condor Legion]] in the [[Spanish Civil War]]. Following this assignment, he then served with the 14./''Flak-Regiment'' 5 (14th company of the 5th anti-aircraft artillery regiment) from 24 August  1938 to 1 August 1939. He was then posted to 1./''Reserve-Flakabteilung'' 502 (1st company of the 502nd reserve anti-aircraft department) on 2 August 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p269&quot;/&gt;

==World War II==
World War II in Europe began on Friday 1 September 1939 when German forces [[Invasion of Poland|invaded Poland]]. Ehrler, who was still serving with the anti-aircraft artillery, requested transfer to the fighter force of the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' on 3 January 1940.{{refn|Flight training in the ''Luftwaffe'' progressed through the levels A1, A2 and B1, B2, referred to as A/B flight training. A training included theoretical and practical training in aerobatics, navigation, long-distance flights and dead-stick landings. The B courses included high-altitude flights, instrument flights, night landings and training to handle the aircraft in difficult situations.&lt;ref&gt;Bergström, Antipov &amp; Sundin 2003, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} His transfer request was accepted and he underwent flight training from 1 February to 4 November 1940. During this training period he was promoted to ''[[Feldwebel]]'' (staff sergeant) on 1 July and to ''[[Leutnant]]'' (second lieutenant) on 1 January 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p269&quot;/&gt;

On 1 February 1941, Ehrler was posted to 4. ''[[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–1945)#Staffel|Staffel]]'' (4th Squadron) of [[Jagdgeschwader 77|''Jagdgeschwader'' 77]] (JG 77—77th Fighter Wing), later redesignated to 4. ''Staffel'' of [[Jagdgeschwader 5|''Jagdgeschwader'' 5]] (JG 5—5th Fighter Wing), based in [[Norway]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For an explanation of the meaning of Luftwaffe unit designation see [[Luftwaffe Organization]]&lt;/ref&gt; There, he scored his first victory in May 1940 and was awarded the [[Iron Cross]] 2nd Class ({{Lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz 2. Klasse''}}) on 19 September 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p269&quot;/&gt;

JG 77 supported [[10th Air Corps (Germany)|X. ''Fliegerkorps'']] (under ''[[Luftflotte 5]]'') in operations against [[United Kingdom|Britain]] from bases in Norway, often providing fighter cover for [[Junkers Ju 87|Stuka]] attacks against British shipping.  JG 77 was restructured as [[JG 5]] ''Eismeer'' in January 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Hafsten 1991, p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; JG 5 operated from bases in northern Norway and Finland, and they mostly engaged Russian aircraft, but were also given the task of intercepting British raids on Norway.

[[File:Oak Leaves ceremony August 1943 Rastenburg.jpg|thumb|right|Schröer, Ehrler, Prinz zur Lippe-Weißenfeld, Lent, Meurer, Kirschner and Weissenberger (right) at Rastenburg.]]
Ehrler claimed his second victory on 19 February 1942. He led a patrol of three aircraft of 4. ''Staffel'' and shot down a [[Polikarpov I-18]]. The Allied [[Convoy PQ 16]], consisting of 35 merchant vessels and protected by 15 escort ships, was sighted by German reconnaissance aircraft on 16 May 1942. Over the following days, the convoy came under multiple attacks from [[Kampfgeschwader 30|''Kampfgeschwader'' 30]] (KG 30—30th Bomber Wing) and [[Kampfgeschwader 26|''Kampfgeschwader'' 26]] (KG 26—26th Bomber Wing). On 30 May 1942, JG&amp;nbsp;5 engaged in combat as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p269&quot;/&gt; In aerial combat, JG&amp;nbsp;5 claimed 43 fighter aircraft and 7 bombers shot down. Ehrler was among the most successful pilots that day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p270&quot;&gt;Stockert 1997, p. 270.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was promoted to ''[[Leutnant]]'' and made ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' (squadron leader) in 6./[[Jagdgeschwader 5]] (JG 5—5th Fighter Wing) after his 11th victory on 20 July. On 4 September, he was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] ({{Lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes''}}) for 64 aerial victories. The presentation was made by the ''Fliegerführer Nord'' ''[[Oberst]]'' [[Alexander Holle]]. By 1 June 1943 he was promoted to ''[[Hauptmann]]'' and appointed ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' (Group Commander) of II./JG 5. On 8 June 1943, Ehrler was credited with his 100th aerial victory. He was the 40th ''Luftwaffe'' pilot to achieve the century mark.&lt;ref&gt;Obermaier 1989, p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt; During this period he was also awarded the ''Eichenlaub'' (Oak Leaves) to his Ritterkreuz. On 25 May 1944, he achieved nine victories in one day, bringing his tally up to 155. On 1 August, he was appointed to ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' (Wing Commander) of JG 5 and at the same time was promoted to ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]''.

===Sinking of the Tirpitz===
On 12 November 1944 the [[Royal Air Force|RAF]] launched its final raid against the battleship [[German battleship Tirpitz|''Tirpitz'']]. [[Avro Lancaster]] bombers from [[No. 617 Squadron RAF|617]] and [[No. 9 Squadron RAF|9]] squadrons were sent to [[Håkøya]] a little west of [[Tromsø]] where the ''Tirpitz'' was based.

Ehrler was in command of 9./JG 5 at ''Fliegerhorst'' [[Bardufoss Airfield|Bardufoss]] with 12 operational [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190|Focke-Wulf Fw 190 A-3]]s. The ''Staffel'' was at 10 minutes' readiness status due to the continuing pressure of British bombers in the Tromsø area.  Ehrler's unit was scrambled airborne, but he received conflicting messages as to the enemy aircraft location and course. Some reports claimed [[Alta, Norway|Alta]] was the target area, others indicated [[Bodø]].&lt;ref&gt;Hafsten 1991, p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt; When it finally became clear that the target was the ''Tirpitz'', it was too late for the fighters to intercept, and the ''Tirpitz'' was destroyed with much loss of life.

After this unsuccessful action, Ehrler faced a [[court martial]] hearing in Oslo on the grounds of his not having understood the seriousness of the attack. Evidence was presented that supported the contention that his unit had failed to respond to requests from the Kriegsmarine for help.  Ehrler was found guilty.  He was relieved of command, demoted and sentenced to three years in prison. Ehrler had been recommended for the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross|Knight's Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords]] prior to the disaster, but the award was not approved.&lt;ref&gt;Berger 2000, p. 392.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Walter Schuck]], one of his junior officers, appealed to [[Reichskommissariat Norwegen|Reichskommissar]] [[Josef Terboven]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schuck p183&quot;&gt;Schuck 2009, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt; On 12 January 1945 Terboven hand-delivered Schuck's affidavit in support of Ehrler to ''[[Reichsmarschall]]'' Hermann Göring, Commander-in-Chief of the ''[[Luftwaffe]]''.  Further investigations and testimonies indicated that the aircrews did not know that the ''Tirpitz'' had been moved to the new location at Håkøya a couple of weeks earlier, and Heinrich Ehrler was a convenient scapegoat for the failure to protect ''Tirpitz''.&lt;ref&gt;Hafsten 1991, p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt;  The investigation concluded the reason for the failure was poor communication between the [[Kriegsmarine]] and the Luftwaffe.&lt;ref&gt;Schuck 2009, p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt; Ehrler was exonerated.  Shortly afterward, the Führer HQ announced Ehrler's release and return to front-line service, where he would have the chance to &quot;rehabilitate himself.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schuck p183&quot;/&gt;  Ehrler's sentence was commuted and his loss of rank rescinded. He was reassigned to an [[Messerschmitt Me 262|Me 262]] fighter squadron in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan &amp; Weal, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transfer to Germany===
[[File:Messerschmitt Me 262 at Evergreen Aviation Museum.jpg|thumb|left|A Me 262 of JG 7 similar to those flown by Ehrler on display at the [[Evergreen Aviation &amp; Space Museum]].]]
Ehrler was transferred to [[Jagdgeschwader 7]] (JG 7—7th Fighter Wing) on 27 February 1945. JG 7 was equipped with the [[Messerschmitt]] [[Me 262]] jet fighter, and was given the task of ''Reichsverteidigung'' ([[Defense of the Reich]]). During the next five weeks, Ehrler scored a further 8 kills,&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For a list of Luftwaffe Jet aces see ''[[List of German World War II jet aces]]''&lt;/ref&gt; bringing his tally to 206.

On the morning of 4 April 1945, Maj Ehrler flew his last sortie and achieved the last three of his 208 recorded victories. Flying out of JG 7's airfield at Brandenburg-Briest, accompanied by his wingman, was in the skies {{convert|50|km|mi|abbr=off|sp=us}} east of Hamburg when [[B-24 Liberator]]s from the [[448th Bombardment Group]] began forming their bombing run of [[Parchim]]. Ehrler attacked the lead [[714th Bombardment Squadron]], downing two B-24 Liberator bombers: Lt J. J. Shafter's &quot;Miss-B-Hav'n,&quot; (B-24J-1-FO 42-95620) and Lt Mains' &quot;Red Bow&quot; (B-24M-10-FO 44-50838). At the time of the attack, two [[P-51 Mustang]]s were pursuing ''Major'' Ehrler, and he was being fired upon by the bomber's gunners, taking hits from the tail and waist gunners of Lt G. Brock's B-24 &quot;My Buddie&quot; (B-24H-25-FO 42-95083) who reported pieces of fuselage flying off the jet. The attack took place over [[Büchen]].

Minutes later, as the 448th Bombardment Group circled back towards their Group RP at Stendal, Ehrler engaged a third Liberator, &quot;Trouble in Mind&quot; (B-24H-30-FO 42-95298) flown by Capt John Ray's crew over Kyritz ({{Coord|52|57|N|12|23|E}}). A reference is made by surviving crew members to cannon hits in the fuselage that destroyed the Liberator, but Ehrler had only moments before he radioed ''Major'' [[Theodor Weissenberger]] that he was out of ammunition and intended to ram the bomber. In any case, both planes were destroyed in the ensuing explosion. The B-24 crashed at [[Zernitz-Lohm|Krüllenkempe]], near [[Havelberg]], as Maj Ehrler's jet fell to earth in the woods of [[Klietz|Scharlibbe]], where he was killed. His body was recovered the following day at Scharlibbe, near Stendal, where he was buried. Ehrler's grave at Stendal confirms the date of death as 4 April 1945.

==Quotations==
''&quot;Theo, I have run out of ammunition.  I'm going to ram this one.  Good bye.  We'll see each other in Valhalla.&quot;'' - Heinrich Ehrler's last transmission over the Squadron Radio Network before he rammed the B-24 bomber &quot;Trouble in Mind,&quot; piloted by Captain John Ray, destroying both aircraft and killing himself. &quot;Theo&quot; refers to [[Theodor Weissenberger]].

[[Walter Schuck]] who followed the R/T exchange over the loudspeaker in the ops room recalls Ehrler's last words slightly differently.  He believes they were: ''&quot;Theo, Heinrich here. Have just shot down two bombers. No more ammunition. I'm going to ram. Auf Wiedersehen, see you in Valhalla!&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;Schuck 2009, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
* [[Ehrenpokal der Luftwaffe]] (20 July 1942)&lt;ref&gt;Obermaier 1989, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[German Cross]] in Gold on 18 March 1943 as ''[[Leutnant]]'' in the 6./Jagdgeschwader 5&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall &amp; Scherzer 2001, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Front Flying Clasp of the Luftwaffe]] in Gold
* [[Iron Cross]] (1939)
** 2nd Class (19 September 1941)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p147&quot;&gt;Thomas 1997, p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 1st Class (21 January 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p147&quot;/&gt;
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
** Knight's Cross on 4 September 1942 as ''Leutnant'' and pilot in the 6./Jagdgeschwader 5&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p290&quot;&gt;Scherzer 2007, p. 290.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 265th Oak Leaves on 2 August 1943 as ''[[Hauptmann]]'' and ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' of the III./Jagdgeschwader 5&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p290&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|25em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Berger
  |first=Florian
  |year=1999
  |title=Mit Eichenlaub und Schwertern. Die höchstdekorierten Soldaten des Zweiten Weltkrieges
  |trans_title=With Oak Leaves and Swords. The Highest Decorated Soldiers of the Second World War
  |language=German
  |location=Vienna, Austria
  |publisher=Selbstverlag Florian Berger
  |isbn=978-3-9501307-0-6
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Bergström
  |first1=Christer
  |last2=Antipov
  |first2=Vlad
  |last3=Sundin
  |first3=Claes
  |year=2003
  |title=Graf &amp; Grislawski – A Pair of Aces
  |location=Hamilton MT
  |publisher=Eagle Editions
  |isbn=978-0-9721060-4-7
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Fellgiebel
  |first=Walther-Peer
  |authorlink=Walther-Peer Fellgiebel
  |year=2000
  |origyear=1986
  |title=Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939–1945 — Die Inhaber der höchsten Auszeichnung des Zweiten Weltkrieges aller Wehrmachtteile
  |trans_title=The Bearers of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939–1945 — The Owners of the Highest Award of the Second World War of all Wehrmacht Branches
  |language=German
  |location=Friedberg, Germany
  |publisher=Podzun-Pallas
  |isbn=978-3-7909-0284-6
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Hafsten
  |first=Bjørn
  |year=1991
  |title=Flyalarm — Luftkrigen over Norge 1939–1945
  |trans_title=Air Raid Alarm — Air War over Norway 1939–1945
  |language=Norwegian
  |location=Oslo
  |publisher=Sem &amp; Stenersen AS
  |isbn=82-7046-058-3
}}
* {{cite book
  |last1=Morgan
  |first1=Hugh
  |last2=Weal
  |first2=John
  |title=German Jet Aces of World War 2
  |year=1998
  |location=
  |publisher=Osprey Publishing
  |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RNK3QmgBs-8C&amp;pg=PA60&amp;dq=ehrler+tipitz&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=y4D3To6KHMaSOtSqnYgN&amp;sqi=2&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=ehrler%20tipitz&amp;f=false
  |isbn=1-85532-634-5
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Obermaier
  |first=Ernst 
  |year=1989
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger der Luftwaffe Jagdflieger 1939 – 1945
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers of the Luftwaffe Fighter Force 1939 – 1945
  |language=German
  |location=Mainz, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Dieter Hoffmann
  |isbn=978-3-87341-065-7
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Patzwall
  |first1=Klaus D. 
  |last2=Scherzer
  |first2=Veit 
  |year=2001
  |title=Das Deutsche Kreuz 1941 – 1945 Geschichte und Inhaber Band II
  |trans_title=The German Cross 1941 – 1945 History and Recipients Volume 2
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-45-8
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Schaulen
  |first=Fritjof
  |year=2003
  |title=Eichenlaubträger 1940 – 1945 Zeitgeschichte in Farbe I Abraham – Huppertz
  |trans_title=Oak Leaves Bearers 1940 – 1945 Contemporary History in Color I Abraham – Huppertz
  |language=German
  |location=Selent, Germany
  |publisher=Pour le Mérite
  |isbn=978-3-932381-20-1
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Scherzer
  |first=Veit 
  |year=2007
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  |language=German
  |location=Jena, Germany
  |publisher=Scherzers Militaer-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-938845-17-2
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Schuck
  |first=Walter
  |authorlink=Walter Schuck
  |year=2007
  |title=Abschuss! Von der Me 109 zur Me 262 Erinnerungen an die Luftkämpfe beim Jagdgeschwader 5 und 7
  |trans_title=Victory! From the Me 109 to the Me 262 Memories of the Dogfights with Fighter Wing 5 and 7
  |language=German
  |location=Aachen, Germany
  |publisher=Helios Verlags- und Buchvertriebsgesellschaft
  |isbn=978-3-938208-44-1
}}
* [[Walter Schuck|Schuck, Walter]] (2009), ''Luftwaffe Eagle - From the Me109 to the Me262''. Hikoki Publications. ISBN 978-1-902109-06-0.
* {{Cite book
  |last=Stockert
  |first=Peter
  |year=1997
  |title=Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 3
  |trans_title=The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 3
  |language=German
  |location=Bad Friedrichshall, Germany
  |publisher=Friedrichshaller Rundblick
  |isbn=978-3-932915-01-7
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Thomas
  |first=Franz
  |year=1997
  |title=Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 1: A–K
  |trans_title=The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 1: A–K
  |language=German
  |location=Osnabrück, Germany
  |publisher=Biblio-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-7648-2299-6
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Von Seemen
  |first=Gerhard
  |year=1976
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 : die Ritterkreuzträger sämtlicher Wehrmachtteile, Brillanten-, Schwerter- und Eichenlaubträger in der Reihenfolge der Verleihung : Anhang mit Verleihungsbestimmungen und weiteren Angaben
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 : The Knight's Cross Bearers of All the Armed Services, Diamonds, Swords and Oak Leaves Bearers in the Order of Presentation: Appendix with Further Information and Presentation Requirements
  |language=German
  |location=Friedberg, Germany
  |publisher=Podzun-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-7909-0051-4
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Toliver
  |first1=Raymond F.
  |last2=Constable
  |first2=Trevor J.
  |year=1996
  |title=Fighter Aces of the Luftwaffe
  |location=Atglen, PA
  |publisher=Schiffer Military/Aviation History
  |isbn=0-88740-909-1
}}
{{Refend}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
|before= Oberstlt. [[Günther Scholz]]
|after= Oberstlt. [[Günther Scholz]]
|title= Commander of [[Jagdgeschwader 5]] ''Eismeer''
|years= 1 August 1944 – 27 February 1945
}}
{{s-end}}

{{KCwithOL}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of JG 5}}
{{Top German World War II Aces}}
{{German World War II jet aces}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Aviation
| portal2=Biography
| portal3=Military of Germany
| portal4=World War II
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ehrler, Heinrich}}
[[Category:1917 births]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Lauda-Königshofen]]
[[Category:Condor Legion personnel]]
[[Category:German World War II flying aces]]
[[Category:German military personnel killed in World War II]]
[[Category:Aviators killed in aviation accidents or incidents in Germany]]
[[Category:People from the Grand Duchy of Baden]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Gold German Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]</text>
      <sha1>2nd3n43tw41zhcj2sr31u04j14ywf97</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
