<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hippolyte Bouchard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>657539</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745707515</id>
      <parentid>744323326</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-22T20:31:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CommonsDelinker</username>
        <id>2304267</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Replacing Kamehamehaportrait.jpg with [[File:Kamehameha_I,_portrait_by_James_Gay_Sawkins.jpg]] (by [[commons:User:CommonsDelinker|CommonsDelinker]] because: [[:commons:COM:FR|File renamed]]:).</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39709">{{Infobox person 
|name   = Hippolyte Bouchard
|birthname=André Paul Bouchard
|parents={{unbulleted list
    |André Louis Bouchard
    |Thérèse Brunet}}
|image = Hipólito Bouchard.jpg
|caption  = Hippolyte Bouchard, oil on canvas &lt;br /&gt;by [[José Gil de Castro]] 
|birth_date  = {{Birth date|1780|1|15|df=y}},{{sfn|Pigna|2005|p=73}}{{efn-ua|name=birthdate|The [[California State Military Museum]] gives 1783 as his birth date. Also, note that this website's form of the name - &quot;de Bouchard&quot; - does not agree with published sources.&lt;ref name=mm1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.militarymuseum.org/deBouchard.html|accessdate=15 January 2012|title=Hippolyte de Bouchard and His Attacks on the California Missions|publisher=[[California State Military Museum]] – California State Military Department|place=Sacramento, CA|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140106041030/http://www.militarymuseum.org/deBouchard.html|archivedate=6 January 2014|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|birth_place = [[Bormes-les-Mimosas]], [[France]] 
|death_date  = {{death date and age|1837|1|4|1780|1|15|df=y}} 
|death_place = [[Peru]] 
|
}}
'''Hippolyte Bouchard''', or '''Hipólito Bouchard''' (15 January 1780{{sfn|Pigna|2005|p=73}}{{efn-ua|name=birthdate}} – 4 January 1837), was a [[French Argentine]]&lt;ref name=mm1/&gt;{{sfn|Pérez Pardella|1997}} [[sailor]] and [[Privateer|corsair]] who fought for [[Argentina]], [[Chile]], and [[Peru]].

During his first campaign as an Argentine corsair he attacked the Spanish colonies of Chile and Peru, under the command of the [[Irish-Argentine]] Admiral [[William Brown (admiral)|William Brown]].
He was the first [[Argentina|Argentine]] to circumnavigate the world. During his voyage around the globe he blockaded the port of [[Manila]]. In [[Hawaii]], he recovered an Argentine privateer which had been seized by mutineers. He also met the local ruler, King [[Kamehameha I]]. His forces occupied [[Monterey, California]], then a Spanish colony, raised the [[Flag of Argentina|Argentine flag]] and held the town for six days. After raiding Monterey, he plundered [[Mission San Juan Capistrano]] in [[Southern California]]. Toward the end of the voyage Bouchard raided Spanish ports in [[Central America]].{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=180}} His second homeland remembers him as a hero and patriot; several places are named in his honour.

==Early life==
Bouchard was born in a small village close to [[Saint-Tropez]], [[Bormes-les-Mimosas]], in 1780{{sfn|Pigna|2005|p=73}}{{efn-ua|name=birthdate}} The son of André Louis Bouchard and Thérèse Brunet was baptized as André Paul but eventually went by the name [[Hippolytus (mythology)|Hippolyte]]. He initially worked in the French merchant fleet, then served in the [[French Navy]] in their campaigns against the English, thus starting his life at sea. After many campaigns in [[French Campaign in Egypt and Syria|Egypt]] and the [[Saint-Domingue expedition]], disillusioned with the direction of the [[French Revolution]], Bouchard went to Argentina in 1809 and, to aid the [[May Revolution]], became a part of the National Argentine Fleet, led by [[Juan Bautista Azopardo|Azopardo]]. On 2 March 1811 he fought for the first time under the [[Flag of Argentina|Argentine Flag]] when the Spanish Captain Jacinto de Romarate defeated the first Argentine flotilla at [[San Nicolás de los Arroyos]], and in July and August of that year he played a major role in defending the City of [[Buenos Aires]] from a Spanish [[blockade]]. In March 1812 Bouchard joined the [[Granaderos a caballo|Mounted Grenadiers Regiment]] led by [[José de San Martín]] and took part in the [[Battle of San Lorenzo]] in 1813, where he captured a Spanish flag and therefore was granted Argentine citizenship.{{sfn|Pérez Pardella|1997}} Some months later he married Norberta Merlo.&lt;ref name=iese1/&gt;

==Campaign with William Brown==
In 1815 Bouchard started a naval campaign under the command of Admiral [[William Brown (admiral)|William Brown]], wherein he attacked the fortress of [[El Callao]] and the [[Ecuador]]ian city of [[Guayaquil]]. On 12 September 1815 he was granted a [[Privateer|corsair]] license to fight the Spanish aboard the French-built [[corvette]] ''Halcón'', which had been bought for the Argentine State by [[Vicente Anastacio Echeverría]]. Most of the officers were French, except for the second commander, the Englishman Robert Jones, and Ramón Freire. Before weighing anchor a conflict between Bouchard and his superiors arose when the expedition's agent, Severino Prudant, promoted several sailors. Echevarría intervened and settled the conflict.

The campaign fleet was composed of the [[frigate]] ''Hercules'' under the command of William Brown, the ''Santísima Trinidad'' under the command of his brother, Miguel Brown, the [[schooner]] ''Constitución'' under the command of Oliverio Russell, and the ''Halcón''. The ''Hércules'' and ''Santísima Trinidad'' set sail from [[Montevideo]] on 24 October; the other two ships departed five days later. The plan was for all four ships to rendezvous at [[Mocha Island]] where they would establish a plan of operation. The Brown brothers arrived at the island on 28 December, with the ''Halcón'' arriving the following day. Upon arrival Bouchard announced that while circumnavigating [[Cape Horn]] his ship was exposed to fourteen days of severe weather, and it was on that basis that he had concluded that the ''Constitución'' had sunk (neither the ship nor its crew were ever seen again). On 31 December Brown and Bouchard agreed to operate together during the first hundred days of 1816. Any plunder would be divided as follows: two parts to Brown, as the commander-in-chief, and one-and-a-half parts each for the ''Santísima Trinidad'' and the ''Halcón''.{{sfn|Prieto|Marí|1927|p=12}} Bouchard and Miguel Brown subsequently set course for the [[Peru]]vian coast, while the ''Hércules'' sailed to the [[Juan Fernández Islands]] in order to free a number of patriots that were being held prisoner there.

On 10 January 1816 the three vessels met again near the fortress of [[El Callao]]. The ships formed a blockade and bombarded Guayaquil and its nearby the fortification. The following day the group seized the [[brigantine]] ''San Pablo'', which was used to transport sick and injured sailors as well as the liberated prisoners. On the 13th the frigate ''Gobernadora'' was captured, and Lt. Colonel Vicente Banegas, officer of the Republican Army of Nueva Granada, joined the fleet. Four more ships were commandeered on the 18th, including the [[schooner]] ''Carmen'' and the brig ''Místico'' along with two other ships, one of which was sacked and sunk. On 21 January the Argentine fleet again attacked the fortress, sinking the frigate ''Fuente Hermosa'' in the process. Seven days later two more vessels were captured, the frigates ''Candelaria'' and ''Consecuencia''. The next day the expanded fleet sailed north in the search of the [[Guayas River]]. On 7 February the Argentine contingent arrived at [[Puná Island]], near Guayaquil. As they arrived, William Brown ordered Bouchard and his brother to stay close to the seven ships they had captured. Brown took the command of the ''Santísima Trinidad'', with which he wanted to attack Guayaquil. The next day his attack demolished the fort of Punta de Piedras, located some five [[League (unit)|leagues]] from Guayaquil. However, on 9 February Brown failed in his attempt to take the castle of San Carlos, and was instead captured by the royalist forces. After a long negotiation, the Argentine corsairs traded Brown for the ''Candelaria'', three brigantines and five correspondence chests that had been taken from the ''Consecuencia''.&lt;ref name=albiceleste/&gt;

After three days, Bouchard informed Brown that his ship was close to sinking and that the officers wished to return to [[Buenos Aires]]. He then asked for a division of the booty, and received the ''Consecuencia'', the ''Carmen'', and 3,475 [[peso]]s as compensation (he had to leave the ''Halcón'' behind). Bouchard elected to return to Buenos Aires via Cape Horn, and it was there that new incidents with the crew arose, many of which were solved with violence, such as a duel with one of his sergeants. When an officer on the ''Carmen'' notified Bouchard that the ship was in imminent danger of foundering, Bouchard nonetheless ordered the man to continue the journey. As a result, the crew mutinied and headed to the [[Galápagos Islands]]. The ''Consecuencia'', with Bouchard still in command, made port in Buenos Aires on 18 June.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=124–125, 142–143}}

==Campaign with ''La Argentina''==

===The beginning of the campaign===
[[File:Juan Martin de Pueyrredon.jpg|thumb|right|[[Juan Martín de Pueyrredón]] was an [[List of Heads of State of Argentina|Argentine head of state]] who assisted Bouchard in his exploits.]]

Bouchard decided to stay with the frigate ''Consecuencia'' for his next campaign. In concert with Vicente Echevarría the ship's name was changed to [[La Argentina (1816)|''La Argentina'']]. Preparing the ship was not an easy task, as it was very heavy and some {{convert|100|m|abbr=off}} long. Echevarría acquired 34 [[artillery]] pieces and hired experienced carpenters to mount them in place. Upon Bouchard's request, the [[Argentina|Argentine State]] gave him 4 bronze cannons and 12 iron cannons, 128 guns, and 1,700 cannonballs, but he was unable to requisition small arms such as boarding guns or sabers (even cavalry sabers).{{sfn|Alonso Piñeiro|1984|loc=ch. 33}} Even more difficult was finding the 180 men he needed for a crew, especially given Bouchard's reputation as ill-tempered (which dogged him after the conflicts in the [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]]){{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}. Most of the sailors he did enlist were foreigners, though some were from the provinces of [[Corrientes Province|Corrientes]] and [[Entre Ríos Province|Entre Ríos]].

On 25 June, with ''La Argentina'' still in port, a sailor struck one of his superiors, an act of insubordination. When Bouchard discovered this he ordered the sailor's arrest, provoking general unrest. One of the fellow sailors attacked Commander Sommers, who killed him in self-defense. This did not prevent other members of the crew from barricading themselves inside the ship, which led their being forcibly removed by the marine infantry, led by Sommers. Two crewmen were killed in the conflict, and four others were wounded. Following the altercation Echevarría sent a letter to [[List of Heads of State of Argentina|Supreme Director]] [[Juan Martín de Pueyrredón]] explaining that the incident was the result of the crew having been stuck in Buenos Aires for an extended period, and that chances of further outbreaks would be lessened once the ship put to sea. Two days later ''La Argentina'' headed to Ensenada de Barragán, which started rumors flying that Bouchard had deserted the service. In reality, the frigate disembarked under the authority of a general order which required ships that were subjected to loading delays and such but were otherwise seaworthy leave the harbor in order that they not be caught at anchor should the Spanish attempt an invasion.

[[File:Bouchard letter of marque.jpg|thumb|right|A portion of the &quot;letter of marque&quot; issued to Bouchard by the Argentine government.]]

On 27 June Bouchard obtained the Argentine corsair patent (a &quot;[[letter of marque]]&quot;) that authorized him to prey on Spanish commerce, the countries of [[Spain]] and Argentina being in a state of war at the time.&lt;ref name=albiceleste&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quintadimension.com/televicio/index.php?id=150|last=Cerone|first=Pablo Martín|year=2004|title=El Corsario Albiceleste|publisher=Quinta Dimensión|language=Spanish|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130602223109/http://www.quintadimension.com/televicio/index.php?id=150|archivedate=2 June 2013|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On 9 July 1817 (the first anniversary of the signing of the [[Argentine Declaration of Independence]]) Bouchard set out from Ensenada de Barragán in command of ''La Argentina'' on a two-year voyage, intending to travel across the Atlantic to the [[Africa]]n coast in order to circumnavigate around the [[Cape of Good Hope]] and engage a fleet of ships operated by the [[Company of the Philippines]] that had sailed from Spain to [[India]]. However, a fire broke out on 19 July which the crew had to fight for hours until it was extinguished. Consequently, when the ship subsequently arrived in the [[Indian Ocean]] it headed northeast to [[Madagascar]], where it laid up at [[Tamatave]] (on the east of the island) for a period of two months while repairs were effected. Once in Tamatave, a [[United Kingdom|British]] officer requested Bouchard's assistance in preventing four &quot;[[slave ship|slaver]]&quot; ships (three British and one French) from leaving the island, whereupon Bouchard offered the use of all his available troops. The ''La Argentina'' seized the slavers' food supplies and recruited five French sailors prior to departing Madagascar with the intent of launching attacks on the Spanish merchant vessels that sailed in region. Unfortunately, much of the crew was soon afflicted with [[scurvy]], which required that ship's operations be conducted by those few sailors who had escaped illness. On 18 October ''La Argentina'' encountered an [[United States|American]] frigate that passed on the news that the Company of the Philippines had ended trade with India three years prior.

[[File:Straat van soenda.jpg||thumb|right|Before arriving in the Philippines, Bouchard and his crew passed through the [[Sunda Strait]].]]

===The Philippines===
[[File:Fort Santiago Gate.jpg|thumb|right|The main gate at Fort Santiago in [[Manila]].]]
''La Argentina'' headed toward the [[Philippines]], weathering several storms in the [[Sunda Strait]] (that divides [[Java|Island of Java]] and [[Sumatra]], and connects the [[Java Sea]] with the Indian Ocean) along the way. On 7 November Bouchard decided to land at Java in order to let his sick crew members recuperate. After leaving the island, ''La Argentina'' continued on its journey to the Philippines. Traveling through the region was fraught with danger due to the presence of [[Malay people|Malayan]] pirates, and was compounded the crew's weakened condition. The pirate ships were equipped with cannons in the prow and in the stern, and were outfitted with one mast and many oars. The ''[[Lanun]]'' as they were known to the Malay people were not seen until the morning of 7 December, when the watchman sighted four small ships. Combat was delayed until midday when the largest of the pirate vessels attempted to close in on ''La Argentina''. As Bouchard preferred to instigate boarding actions and relied on hand-to-hand combat he therefore chose to forgo firing upon the aggressor. ''La Argentina's'' crew prevailed and were ordered to take the ship; in the meantime, the other would-be attackers fled. Bouchard convened a &quot;war council&quot; to judge the prisoners, sentencing all of them to death, save for the youngest. The condemned prisoners were returned to their ship and locked below the deck; the damaged vessel was subjected to salvo after salvo of cannon fire from ''La Argentina'' until she sank with all hands aboard.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=155–157}}

After passing through the [[Makassar Strait]], ''La Argentina'' crossed the [[Celebes Sea]] and made landfall on the island of Joló. There she re-supplied and headed to the Spanish port at [[Manila]] for the purpose of establishing a blockade. Upon arrival on 31 January 1818 the Argentines stopped an English frigate attempting to dock to determine whether or not it carried supplies for the Spanish colony. Bouchard attempted to hide his origin, but the frigate's captain discerned what his true intentions were and warned the Spanish authorities of his intentions. The City of Manila had fortified walls and was protected by a redoubt, [[Fort Santiago]], with powerful artillery. Bouchard instead began to plunder nearby vessels, all the while staying clear of the Spanish cannons. For the next two months ''La Argentina'' captured a total of 16 ships through the use of intimidating cannon fire and quick boardings, while Manila's inhabitants fell into a state of despair as the price of food doubled, and even tripled. The governor sent two armed merchant vessels, accompanied by a corvette, to engage ''La Argentina''. The group missed its opportunity, however, as Bouchard had already departed the area on 30 March.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=157–159}}

Few days after, the ship sighted a brigantine from the [[Mariana Islands]]. When it noticed the proximity of ''La Argentina'', it fled to the port of Santa Cruz.
The Argentine frigate was unable to approach the harbor because of its [[draft (hull)|draft]], so Bouchard ordered Sommers, Greissac and Van Buren to use three boats to capture the ship. The three officers and many crew members started to approach the brigantine that had not arrived to the port. Sommers managed to arrive get very close to the vessel when it anchored but his boat sunk as it crashed with the [[Hull (watercraft)|hull]] of the enemy ship. The brigantine's crew, instead of taking them prisoners they decided to attack them and killed fourteen of them. The others were rescued by Greissac and Van Buren and returned to the frigate.
Bouchard wanted to revenge the deaths, but in order to capture the brigantine he needed a vessel with a smaller stern. So he ordered Greissac to lead some sailors and take any of the [[schooners]] that sailed near the port. Once captured, Bouchard put a number of cannons in her. He placed Greissac and Oliver in command of her with 35 sailors. The schooner attacked on 10 April but the brigantine's crew had fled. When they were away from Santa Cruz, the Argentines took a Spanish schooner loaded with precious cargo. However, because of the strong winds it was possible to send only an officer and eight sailors to sail the vessel. The schooner was in sight until 15 April, possibly the insubordination was caused by the value of the shipment.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=160–161}} ''La Argentina'' traveled to the [[Hawaiian Islands|Sandwich Islands]] (now [[Hawaii]]) to find new crew members to replace the those who had died from scurvy. Bouchard hired Sir [[Peter Corney]] to captain the ''Santa Rosa'', a captured ship whose crew had mutinied.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=170}}

===Sandwich Islands (Hawaii)===
[[File:Kamehameha I, portrait by James Gay Sawkins.jpg|thumb|right|King [[Kamehameha I]].]]
On 17 August Bouchard arrived at [[Kealakekua]] Bay on the western coast of the island of Hawaii. A group of natives came close to the ship in a canoe and informed them, in English, that a corvette, which used to be Spanish but had been sold to King [[Kamehameha I]], was also at anchor in the harbor. They also told them that, on the previous night, a frigate had departed.
Bouchard decided to chase the frigate, which they found becalmed. He ordered Sheppard to take a rowboat to ask the frigate's commander for information about the ship in the Hawaiian harbor. Sheppard found out that it was the ''Santa Rosa'' or the ''Chacabuco'', a corvette that had weighed anchor at [[Buenos Aires]] almost the same day the ''La Argentina'' had. The crew of ''Santa Rosa'' had mutinied near [[Geography of Chile|Chile's coast]] and headed to Hawaii, where the crew had attempted to sell the vessel to the Hawaiian king.{{sfn|Chapman|1921|pp=442–443}}
The French privateer forced the frigate to return to the harbor, because he suspected that among its crew were hiding some of the mutineers. While investigating the men he found nine men he had seen in Buenos Aires and punished them. After an interrogation he found out the revolt's leaders were hiding in [[Kauai|Kauai Island]].

When he arrived at the harbor he found the ''Santa Rosa'' almost dismantled, therefore he decided to meet King [[Kamehameha I]] wearing his uniform of [[Lieutenant Colonel]] of the [[United Provinces of River Plate]]. During the meeting Bouchard demanded the restitution of the corvette. However, the king argued he had paid 600 [[hundredweight]] of [[sandalwood]] for her and that he deserved a compensation. Bouchard traded his sword and commanders hat, along with an honorific title of Lieutenant Colonel of the United Provinces awarded to the king for the corvette and some supplies, with the condition of leaving Kauai for [[Molokai]]. Argentine historian, author and 6th [[President of Argentina]] [[Bartolomé Mitre]] wrote of this agreement as the first &quot;[[international treaty]]&quot; signed by Argentina with a non-Latin American country, an interpretation dismissed by later historians.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=168–170}} Historian Pacho O'Donnell affirms that Hawaii was the first state that recognized Argentina's independence.{{sfn|O'Donnell|1998}}

On 26 August he took charge of the ''Santa Rosa'', which he had to rebuild partially. Six days later he arrived to Kauai island. There he captured those who had mutinied in the ''Santa Rosa'', executed  the leaders and punishing the rest with twelve blows with a lash in the face.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=172}} After buying food, ammunition and hiring eighty men, the fleet left, heading to [[California]].

===California and Central America===
[[File:South Monterey Bay.jpg|thumb|right|South [[Monterey Bay]], [[California]].]]

Bouchard sailed towards [[California]] to exploit the [[History of California to 1899#Spanish colonization and governance|Spanish trade]]. However the Spanish authorities knew his intentions since on 6 October the ''Clarion'' had reported two corsair ships were ready to attack the Californian coast. The governor, [[Pablo Vicente de Solá]], who resided in [[Monterey, California|Monterey]], ordered removed from the city all valuables and two thirds of the [[gunpowder]] stocked in the military outposts.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=177}}

On 20 November 1818, the [[Point Pinos Lighthouse|watchman of Punta de Pinos]], located at the tip of the southern end of [[Monterey Bay]], sighted the two Argentine ships. The governor was informed; the Spanish prepared the cannons along the coastline, the garrison manned their battle stations, and the women, children, and men unfit to fight were sent to an inland mission at [[Mission Soledad|Soledad]].{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=178}}

Bouchard met with his officers to design the attack plan. Sir Peter Corney knew the bay from two previous visits to Monterey. They used the [[corvette]] ''Santa Rosa'' to attack since the [[Draft (hull)|deep draft]] [[frigate]] ''La Argentina'' might [[run aground]]. The frigate had to be towed by small boats and out of range of the Spanish [[artillery]]. Once it was out of range, Bouchard sent [[Captain (naval)|captain]] Sheppard to the ''Santa Rosa'', leading two hundred soldiers, carrying firearms and [[lances]].{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=178}}

''Santa Rosa'' corvette, led by Sheppard, anchored by midnight near the [[Presidio of Monterey]].&lt;ref name=mm1/&gt; Since, after towing the frigate and rowing back to the corvette the men were very tired, Sheppard decided not to attack in the night. At dawn he discovered that he had anchored too close to the coast and that few meters ahead the Spanish artillery was ready to attack them. The captain opened fire, but after fifteen minutes of combat the corvette surrendered.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=179}}

From the frigate, Bouchard saw his men defeated, but also noticed that the Spanish lacked boats to seize ''Santa Rosa''. The corsair ordered his ships to weigh anchor and move towards the port. However, due to the frigate's draft, he could not get close enough to open fire. After sunset they brought the corvette's survivors aboard the frigate.
On 24 November, before dawn, Bouchard ordered his men to board the boats. They were 200: 130 had rifles and 70 had spears. They landed  {{convert|7|km|mi|abbr=on}} away from the fort in a hidden [[Creek (tidal)|creek]]. The fort resisted ineffectively, and after an hour of combat the [[Flag of Argentina|Argentine flag]] flew over it.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=180}} The Argentines took the city for six days, during which time they stole the cattle and burned the fort, the artillery headquarters, the governor's residence and the Spanish houses. The town's residents were unharmed.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=180–181}}

On 29 November they left Monterey, passed [[Point Conception]], and anchored off of Refugio Canyon, about twenty miles west of [[Santa Barbara, California|Santa Barbara]], where they went to the hacienda of the [[Rancho Nuestra Señora del Refugio|Ortega family rancho]].  Bouchard was told the family had strongly supported the Spanish cause. On 5 December the Argentines disembarked near the farm and, meeting no resistance, took all the food, killed the cattle, and slit the throats of the saddle horses in the corrals. A small squadron of cavalry, sent by [[José de la Guerra y Noriega]] from the [[Santa Barbara Presidio]], waited quietly nearby for an opportunity to capture some stragglers.  They captured an officer and two sailors, whom they brought back to the Presidio in chains. Bouchard waited for them the whole day, because he thought they were lost, until he decided to burn the farm and go to [[Mission Santa Barbara]], where the three men could have been taken as prisoners. Once he arrived at Santa Bárbara, and seeing the town was heavily defended (in reality, what Bouchard saw through his spyglass was the same small [[troop]] of [[cavalry]], which stopped and changed costume each time it passed behind a heavy clump of brush), the privateer sent a messenger to speak to the governor. After the negotiation the three captured men returned to the ''Santa Rosa'' and Bouchard freed one prisoner.{{sfn|Tompkins|1975|pp=16–17}}

[[File:Mission San Juan Capistrano.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Mission San Juan Capistrano]].]]

On 16 December the ships [[weighed anchor]] and headed to [[Mission San Juan Capistrano|San Juan Capistrano]]. There he requested food and ammunition; a Spanish officer said &quot;he had enough gunpowder and cannonballs for me&quot;. Threats annoyed Bouchard; he sent one hundred men to take the town. After a short fight the corsairs took some valuables and burned the Spanish houses. On 20 December he left for [[Sebastián Vizcaíno Bay|Vizcaíno Bay]], where he repaired the ships and allowed his men to rest.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=183}}
Among the Spanish settlements in California the raids earned Bouchard a reputation as &quot;California's only [[pirate]]&quot; (and was therefore often referred to as ''Pirata Buchar'' by the Spanish colonists of the day).{{sfn|Yenne|2004|p=77}}{{sfn|Jones|1997|p=170}}

On 17 January they sailed to the port of [[San Blas, Nayarit|San Blas]], located on the west coast of mainland [[Mexico]], and began a blockade eight days later. During the approach, they seized the Spanish brig ''Las Ánimas'', with a cargo of cacao. Near [[Islas Marías|Tres Marías islands]], ''La Argentina'' boarded the British ''Good Hope''. After four days, they allowed the ship to weigh anchor, but not before confiscating her cargo of Spanish goods. On 1 March, while blockading San Blas, they sighted a [[schooner]]. The two ships began to chase her but failed to reach her. Afterwards, Bouchard ordered them to proceed south to [[Acapulco]] following the coastline. Once they arrived, he sent a boat with an officer to explore the place, and to report the quantity and quality of the ships in the harbour. The officer reported there was no relevant ship nearby, and Bouchard decided to sail on.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=185–187}}

On 18 March the Argentines went to a town called Sonsonete in [[El Salvador]]. An officer sent to spy on the port reported there were reasonable ships to board. On that day Bouchard captured a brigantine. On 2 April they arrived at the port of [[El Realejo]], and prepared two boats with cannons and sixty men, led by Bouchard himself. They were sighted by the port's watch, however, and Spanish troops went to defend the ships. In addition, they had protected the port with four ships: a [[brig]], two [[schooner]]s and a [[lugger]]. After an intense combat three ships were taken. Bouchard burned the brig ''San Antonio'' and the schooner ''Lauretana'', because their owners had not offered enough money for them, 30,000 and 20,000 [[Spanish coins|duros]] respectively. Due to their quality he kept the lugger, ''Neptuno'', and the second schooner, ''María Sofía''.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|pp=187–188}}

After the combat in [[El Realejo]], the Argentines found the same schooner with the Spanish flag that they had lost in San Blas. The ship went forward towards the ''Santa Rosa'', whose crew was composed of inexpert Hawaiian sailors and had few artillery. A first attack killed three Argentines and wounded many more. When the Argentine ship was going to repel the enemy's boarding, the schooner took out the Spanish flag and showed it was a Chilean ship, called ''Chileno'' (Chilean). It was commanded by a corsair whose surname was Croll. Bouchard demanded that his surgeon heal the wounded, but the Chilean corsair decided to go away.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=189}}

On 3 April 1819 Hippolyte Bouchard's long expedition ended. He went to [[Valparaíso]], in [[Chile]] in order to collaborate with [[José de San Martín]]'s campaign to liberate [[Perú]]. Some historians, for example Miguel Ángel de Marco,{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=190}} suggest that the flags of the [[United Provinces of Central America]] and most of the states that composed it were inspired by the [[Flag of Argentina|Argentine Flag]] that Bouchard took with him. While others claim that the flag was modeled on the Argentine flag, but introduced by [[Commodore (rank)|Commodore]] [[Louis-Michel Aury]].

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;gallery caption=&quot;Flags of Argentina, the United Provinces of Central America &amp; Current National Flags&quot;&gt;
File:Flag of Argentina.svg|[[Flag of Argentina|Argentina]]
File:Flag_of_the_Federal_Republic_of_Central_America.svg|[[United Provinces of Central America]]
File:Flag_of_Nicaragua.svg|[[Flag of Nicaragua|Nicaragua]]
File:Flag_of_Honduras.svg|[[Flag of Honduras|Honduras]]
File:Flag_of_El_Salvador.svg|[[Flag of El Salvador|El Salvador]]
File:Flag_of_Costa_Rica.svg|[[Flag of Costa Rica|Costa Rica]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

=== Arrest in Chile ===
[[File:Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald.jpg|thumb|[[Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald|Thomas Cochrane]] decided to accuse and arrest Bouchard under charges of [[piracy]].]]
On 9 July 1819, exactly two years after Bouchard left [[Buenos Aires]], the ''Santa Rosa'' and the ''María Sofía'' arrived to [[Valparaíso]]. the 12th of the same month arrived the ''Neptuno'' and one day later arrived ''La Argentina''. Bouchard was informed that [[Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald|Thomas Cochrane]] had ordered his arrest.&lt;ref name=albiceleste/&gt; The corsair replied that the Chilean government had no authority to judge him and that he would only speak about his travels to the Argentine authority.
The trial for piracy started on 20 July. In September a Chilean fleet had left to [[Peru]] to try to take [[El Callao]] fortress. In order to put pressure on the court, Argentine Colonel [[Mariano Necochea]] along with 30 [[Regiment of Mounted Grenadiers|Mounted Grenadiers]] and sailors stormed ''La Argentina'' and took control of the ship in the name of the United Provinces.{{sfn|Pigna|2005|p=94}} Then, the corsair's defense decided to accelerate the trial and the judge decided, on 9 December, to return all ships, papers and documents to Bouchard; however the money and the booty were not given back.
The ships had no sails nor cannons, because they had been requested by the Chilean navy. Bouchard, virtually in bankruptcy, used a schooner to deliver clay to [[Buenos Aires]], and due to the poor future of his ships, he decided to change the name of ''La Argentina'' to ''Consecuencia'', the name she had before being taken. They were used as transport ships: the ''Consecuencia'' carried 500 soldiers to Peru, while ''Santa Rosa'' took cattle and weapons.

== Later life ==
[[File:Flag of Peru (1821 - 1822).svg|thumb|right|Peru's national flag (1821-1822), created by San Martín.]]
In 1820 Bouchard was in Perú serving with the Chilean navy. In December of that year he requested [[José de San Martín]], who had been named Protector of Peru, to be allowed to return to [[Argentina]] due to his economic situation. San Martín ordered him to stay in [[Lima]] for four months more.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=204}}

When Lord Cochrane took the money stored in the warships he commanded to compensate the wages he did not receive, San Martín decided to fight against him. He created the [[Peruvian Navy]] and Bouchard was given the frigate ''Prueba'', captured to the Royalists in Callao.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=207}} Cochrane complained again and [[Tomás Guido]] asked him to protest to the [[Chile]]an government and ordered Bouchard to be ready to fight if the Scottish admiral decided to attack the Peruvian fleet. Bouchard confronted Cochrane at sea, to the point of challenging him to a single duel; however, the Chilean Admiral refused to fight and sailed back to Valparaíso.{{sfn|Pigna|2005|p=94}}

After the incident, he continued to sail in Peruvian waters commanding the ''Santa Rosa'', because ''Consecuencia'' had to be sold as firewood. ''Santa Rosa'' would end up being burned during the [[El Callao]] rebellion of 1824. Bouchard would also participate, in 1828, in [[Gran Colombia-Peru War|the war]] against [[Gran Colombia]]. After the death of the Admiral [[Martín Jorge Guise]], he was in charge of the Peruvian Navy, but he would retire one year later, after the loss of the ensign ship, ''Presidente''.{{sfn|De Marco|2002|p=208}}

During his retirement he decided to live in the properties that had been given to him by the Peruvian Government, ''San Javier y San José de la Nazca'', near [[Palpa, Peru|Palpa]]. He established a [[sugar mill]]. A long time ago he had lost contact with his family: after the expedition with Brown he had lived with his wife only ten months, and he never knew his younger daughter who was born after the beginning of the expedition around the world. He was killed by one of his servants on 4 January 1837.&lt;ref name=iese1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iese.edu.ar/eude/biografias/B/bouchard_hipolito_bio.html|title=Bouchard, Hipólito (1780–1837)|publisher=IESE – Instituto Universitario del Ejército|language=Spanish|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120306051620/http://www.iese.edu.ar/eude/biografias/B/bouchard_hipolito_bio.html|archivedate=6 March 2012|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his adopted country of Argentina, Bouchard is revered as a patriot and several places (one being a street in downtown [[Buenos Aires]] close to the waterfront) are named in his honor.&lt;ref name=mm1/&gt; [[USS Borie (DD-704)|USS ''Borie'']], a [[Sumner class destroyer]] sold to Argentina in July 1972, was renamed as ARA ''Hipólito Bouchard''; the ship saw action in the [[Falklands War]].&lt;ref name=histarmar1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.histarmar.com.ar/Armada%20Argentina/Buques1900a1970/DDBouchard-1974.htm|title=Destructor A.R.A. &quot;Bouchard&quot; D-26|publisher=Histarmar|language=Spanish|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120717043624/http://www.histarmar.com.ar/Armada%20Argentina/Buques1900a1970/DDBouchard-1974.htm|archivedate=17 July 2012|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[May Revolution]]
* [[Argentine War of Independence]]
* [[Spanish American wars of independence]]
* [[Jean Lafitte]]
* [[Pierre Lafitte]]

==Notes==
{{notelist-ua}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Alonso Piñeiro|first=Armando|year=1984|title=La historia Argentina que muchos argentinos no conocen|edition=5th|publisher=Depalma|place=Buenos Aires|language=Spanish|isbn=978-9501402025|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Chapman|first=Charles Edward|year=1921|title=A History of California: The Spanish Period|publisher=The Macmillan Company|place=New York|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Cichero|first=Daniel E.|year=1999|title=El corsario del plata|publisher=|place=Buenos Aires|language=Spanish|isbn=950-07-1560-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=De Marco|first=Miguel Ángel|year=2002|title=Corsarios Argentinos|publisher=|place=Buenos Aires|language=Spanish|isbn=950-49-0944-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Departamento de Estudios Históricos Navales de la Armada Argentina|year=1987|title=Historia marítima Argentina|volume=V|publisher=Cuántica Editora|place=Buenos Aires|language=Spanish|isbn=950-9257-05-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Gregory|first=Kristiana|year=1995|title=The Stowaway: A Tale of California Pirates|publisher=Scholastic Trade|isbn=0-590-48822-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Jones|first=Roger W.|year=1997|title=California from the Conquistadores to the Legends of Laguna|publisher=Rockledge Enterprises|place=Laguna Hills, CA|asin=B0006R3LVM|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Leffingwell|first=Randy|year=2005|title=California Missions and Presidios|publisher=Voyageur Press, Inc.|place=Stillwater, MN|isbn=0-89658-492-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Mitre|first=Bartolomé|year=1909|title=Páginas de Historia|publisher=La Nación|place=Buenos Aires|language=Spanish|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=O'Donnell|first=Pacho|year=1998|title=El Aguila Guerrera: La Historia Argentina Que No Nos Contaron|url=http://www.odonnell-historia.com.ar/anecdotario/EL%20AGUILA%20GUERRERA%20parte%20IV.htm#1|publisher=Editorial Sudamericana|edition=3rd|language=Spanish|isbn=978-9500714617|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Pérez Pardella|first=Agustín|year=1997|title=José de San Martín, El Libertador Cabalga|publisher=Planeta|place=Buenos Aires|language=Spanish|isbn=978-9507428166|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Pigna|first=Felipe|authorlink=Felipe Pigna|year=2005|title=Los mitos de la historia argentina|volume=2|publisher=Editora Argentina|language=Spanish|isbn=950-49-1342-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Pitt|first=Leonard|year=1970|title=Decline of the Californios: A Social History of the Spanish-Speaking Californians, 1846-1890|publisher=University of California Press|place=Los Angeles, CA|isbn=0-520-01637-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Prieto|first1=N.|last2=Marí|first2=A.|year=1927|title=Historia Completa de la Nación Argentina|volume=XXIV|publisher=|place=Buenos Aires|language=Spanish|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Tompkins|first=Walker A.|year=1975|title=Santa Barbara, Past and Present|publisher=Tecolote Books|place=Santa Barbara, CA|asin=B0006XNLCU|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Yenne|first=Bill|year=2004|title=The Missions of California|publisher=Advantage Publishers Group|place=San Diego, CA|isbn=1-59223-319-8|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.mchsmuseum.com/bouchard.html Hipólito (Hypolite) Bouchard and the Raid of 1818] at Monterey County Historical Society

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bouchard, Hippolyte}}
[[Category:1783 births]]
[[Category:1843 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Var (department)]]
[[Category:French sailors]]
[[Category:Maritime history of Argentina]]
[[Category:People of Alta California]]
[[Category:Argentine Navy personnel]]
[[Category:Maritime history of California]]
[[Category:Privateers]]
[[Category:French emigrants to Argentina]]
[[Category:Argentine pirates]]
[[Category:French pirates]]
[[Category:Burials at La Chacarita Cemetery]]
[[Category:Piracy in the Pacific Ocean]]
[[Category:19th-century pirates]]</text>
      <sha1>h4n0wbp08flbr78s1qs9f2xy43zne8m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
