<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hiram Bingham III</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>735185</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743458232</id>
      <parentid>739504020</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-09T19:12:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category People from Honolulu, Hawaii to [[:Category:People from Honolulu]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2016 September 6]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18139">{{sprotect|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox senator
|name = Hiram Bingham III
|nationality = American U.S.
|image name = Hiram Bingham III in 1916.jpg&lt;!--hirambinghamIII.jpg--&gt;
|jr/sr and state = [[List of United States Senators from Connecticut|United States Senator]]&lt;br/&gt; from [[Connecticut]]
|party = [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
|term_start = December 17, 1924
|term_end = March 4, 1933
|preceded = [[Frank Bosworth Brandegee]]
|succeeded = [[Augustine Lonergan]]
|order2=69th [[Governor of Connecticut]]
|term_start2=January 7
|term_end2=January 8, 1925
|lieutenant2=[[John H. Trumbull]]
|preceded2=[[Charles A. Templeton]]
|succeeded2=[[John H. Trumbull]]
|order3=58th [[Lieutenant Governor of Connecticut]]
|term_start3=1923
|term_end3=1925
|governor3=[[Charles A. Templeton]]
|preceded3=[[Charles A. Templeton]]
|succeeded3=[[John H. Trumbull]]
|birth_date = {{Birth date|1875|11|19}}
|birth_place = [[Honolulu, Hawaii]]
|death_date = {{death date and age|1956|6|6|1875|11|19}}
|death_place = Washington, D.C.
|spouse =
1) Alfreda Mitchell (div.)&lt;br/&gt;
2) Suzanne Carroll Hill
|children=[[Jonathan Brewster Bingham]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Hiram Bingham IV]]&lt;br/&gt; Charles Tiffany Bingham&lt;br/&gt; Brewster Bingham&lt;br/&gt; Mitchell Bingham&lt;br/&gt; Woodbridge Bingham&lt;br/&gt; Alfred Mitchell Bingham
|alma_mater=[[Yale University]]&lt;br/&gt; [[University of California-Berkeley]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Harvard University]]
|religion = [[Protestantism|Protestant Christian]]
|branch=[[United States National Guard]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Aviation Section, U.S. Signal Corps|United States Army Signal Corps Aviation Section]]&lt;br/&gt; [[United States Army Air Service]]
|rank=[[Captain (U.S. Army)|Captain]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Lieutenant Colonel]]
}}

'''Hiram Bingham III''' (November 19, 1875 &amp;ndash; June 6, 1956) was an American academic, explorer and politician. He made public the existence of the [[Inca Empire|Inca]] citadel of [[Machu Picchu]] in 1911 with the guidance of local indigenous farmers. Later, Bingham served as a member of the [[United States Senate]] for the state of [[Connecticut]].

==Early life and early academic career==
Bingham was born in [[Honolulu, Hawaii]], the son of Clara Brewster and [[Hiram Bingham II]] (1831&amp;ndash;1908), an early Protestant missionary to the [[Kingdom of Hawai'i]], the grandson of [[Hiram Bingham I]] (1789&amp;ndash;1869), another missionary. He attended O'ahu College, now known as [[Punahou School]] in Hawai'i from 1882 to 1892. He went to the United States in his teens in order to complete his education, entering [[Phillips Academy]] in [[Andover, Massachusetts]], from which he graduated in 1894. He earned a B.A. degree from [[Yale University]] in 1898, a degree from the [[University of California, Berkeley]] in 1900, where he took one of the first courses on Latin American history offered in the United States, and Ph. D. from [[Harvard University]] in 1905. Since Harvard at the time did not have a specialist in [[Latin American history]], [[Edward Gaylord Bourne]] of Yale served as the examiner for Bingham's qualifying exams.&lt;ref&gt;Howard F. Cline, &quot;Latin American History: Development of Its Study and Teaching in the United States Since 1898,&quot; in ''Latin American History: Essays on Its Study and Teaching, 1898-1965''. Austin: University of Texas Press 1967, vol. 1, pp. 7-8.&lt;/ref&gt;  While at Yale, Bingham was a member of [[Acacia Fraternity]]. He taught history and politics at Harvard and then served as preceptor under [[Woodrow Wilson]] at [[Princeton University]]. Princeton &quot;did not much favor Latin American history,&quot; so that in 1907, when Yale University sought a replacement for Bourne, who had died an early death, it appointed Bingham as a lecturer in South American history.&lt;ref&gt;Cline, &quot;Latin American History,&quot; p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;  Bingham has been considered one of the pioneers of teaching and research on Latin American history in the U.S. In 1908, he published an assessment of the field's prospects entitled &quot;The Possibilities of South American History and Politics as a Field for Research,&quot; in which he surveyed library and archival resources in the U.S. as well as in South America.&lt;ref&gt;Hiram Bingham, &quot;The Possibilities of South American History and Politics as a Field for Research&quot;, reprinted in ''Latin American History: Essays in Its Study and Teaching'', section III &quot;Pioneers, 1900-1918.&quot; Austin: University of Texas Press 1967, vol. 1, pp. 58-65.&lt;/ref&gt;  From 1924, he was a member of the [[Acorn Club]].

==Explorer==
[[File:Hiram Bingham at Espiritu Pampa ruins 1911.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Bingham (upper right) with a local guide on a jungle bridge at [[Vilcabamba, Peru|Espiritu Pampa]] in Peru, hand-colored glass slide, 1911]]

Bingham was not a trained archaeologist. Yet, it was during Bingham's time as a lecturer – later professor – in South American history at Yale that he re-discovered the largely forgotten Inca city of [[Machu Picchu]]. In 1908, he had served as delegate to the First Pan American Scientific Congress at [[Santiago, Chile]]. On his way home via [[Peru]], a local prefect convinced him to visit the pre-Columbian city of [[Choquequirao]]. Bingham published an account of this trip in ''Across South America; an account of a journey from Buenos Aires to Lima by way of Potosí, with notes on Brazil, Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, and Peru''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bingham |first=Hiram |coauthors=|title=Across South America: An Account of A Journey from Buenos Aires to Lima by Way of Potosí, with Notes on Brazil, Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, and Peru |publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company  |location=Boston &amp; New York  |year=1911 |chapter= |url=https://archive.org/stream/acrosssouthameri00bing#page/n9/mode/2up |pages=   |accessdate=7 August 2016 |via=Internet Archive}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bingham was thrilled by the prospect of unexplored Inca cities, and organized the 1911 Yale Peruvian Expedition&lt;ref name=yale&gt;{{cite book|title=Bulletin of the Geographical Society of Philadelphia|year=1912|volume=vol. 10|chapter=Yale Expedition to Peru|pages=134–136|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DHBIAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA134}}&lt;/ref&gt; with one of its objectives to search for the last capital of the Incas. He in fact, guided by locals, rediscovered and correctly identified both [[Vitcos]] (then called Rosaspata) and [[Vilcabamba, Peru|Vilcabamba]] (then called Espíritu Pampa), which he named &quot;Eromboni Pampa&quot;.&lt;ref name=yale/&gt; However, he did not correctly recognize Vilcabamba as the last capital, instead continuing onward and misidentifying Machu Picchu as the &quot;Lost City of the Incas&quot;, as his book titled it.

On July 24, 1911, Melchor Arteaga led Bingham to Machu Picchu, which had been largely forgotten by everybody except the small number of people living in the immediate valley (possibly including two local missionaries named Thomas Payne and Stuart McNairn whose descendants claim that they had already climbed to the ruins in 1906){{citation needed|date=September 2014}}. Also the Cusco explorers Enrique Palma, Gabino Sanchez and Agustín Lizarraga are said to have arrived at the site in 1901.

Bingham returned to Peru in 1912, 1914 and 1915 with the support of Yale and the [[National Geographic Society]].  In ''The Lost City of the Incas'' (1948), Bingham related how he came to believe that Machu Picchu housed a major religious shrine and served as a training center for religious leaders.  Modern archaeological research has since determined that the site was not a religious center but a royal estate to which Inca leaders and their entourage repaired during the Andean summer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last=Fellman |first=Bruce |date=December 2002 |title=Rediscovering Machu Picchu |url=http://archives.yalealumnimagazine.com/issues/02_12/machupicchu.html |magazine=Yale Alumni Magazine|access-date= 7 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Machu Picchu has become one of the major tourist attractions in South America, and Bingham is recognized as the man who brought the site to world attention, although many others helped to bring this site into the public eye. The switchback-filled road that carries tourist buses to the site from the [[Urubamba River]] is called the Hiram Bingham Highway.

Bingham has been cited as one possible basis for the &quot;[[Indiana Jones]]&quot; character.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/travel/destinations/2005-09-22-peru_x.htm The trail less trampled on''] in [[USA Today]] by Gene Sloan, September 23, 2005: &quot;The iconic mountaintop citadel, discovered less than a century ago by American explorer Hiram Bingham, the inspiration for Indiana Jones, is a thrilling reward after days of exertion.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; His book ''Lost City of the Incas'' became a bestseller upon its publication in 1948.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.senate.gov/reference/reference_item/LostCity.htm Lost City of the Incas]'' biographical profile from the United States Senate website&lt;/ref&gt;

Peru has long sought the return of the estimated 40,000 artifacts, including mummies, ceramics and bones, that Bingham had excavated and exported from the Machu Picchu site. On September 14, 2007, an agreement was made between Yale University and the Peruvian government for the return of the objects. On April 12, 2008, the Peruvian government stated that it had revised previous estimates of 4,000 pieces up to 40,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/spanish/latin_america/newsid_7345000/7345808.stm Perú en reclamo por Machu Picchu]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prior discoverers of Machu Picchu==
Soon after Bingham announced the existence of [[Machu Picchu]] others came forward claiming to have seen the city first, such as the British missionary Thomas Payne and a German engineer named J. M. von Hassel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/08/world/americas/08iht-journal.1.18479442.html The fights of Machu Picchu: Who got there first?] - The New York Times&lt;/ref&gt;  Recent discoveries have put forth a new claimant, a German named Augusto Berns who bought land opposite the Machu Picchu mountain in the 1860s and then tried to raise money from investors to plunder nearby Incan ruins.  An 1874 map shows the site of Machu Picchu.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/so-was-the-lost-city-of-machu-picchu-ever-lost-1058004.html So, was the 'lost' city of Machu Picchu ever lost?] - The Independent&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marriage and family==
[[File:Hiram Bingham portrait by Mary Foote 1921.jpg|thumb|left|Hiram Bingham painted by [[Mary Foote]], sister of Harry Ward Foote, the Yale chemistry professor who was Bingham's companion on his trips to Peru]]

He married Alfreda Mitchell, granddaughter of [[Charles L. Tiffany]], on November 20, 1900, and had seven sons: Woodbridge (1901–1986) (professor), [[Hiram Bingham IV]] (1903–1988) (diplomat and World War II hero), Alfred Mitchell Bingham (1905–1998) (lawyer and author), Charles Tiffany (1906–1993) (physician), Brewster (1908–1995) (minister), Mitchell (1910–1994) (artist), and [[Jonathan Brewster Bingham]] (1914–1986) (Democratic [[United States House of Representatives|Congressman]]).&lt;ref&gt;''Portrait of an Explorer'', biography of Bingham by his son Alfred, Iowa State University Press, Ames, 1989. ISBN 0-8138-0136-2&lt;/ref&gt; After a divorce he married Suzanne Carroll Hill in June 1937.

In 1982 Temple University Press published Char Miller's doctoral dissertation on the Bingham family titled &quot;Fathers and sons: The Bingham family and the American mission.&quot;

==Military==
Bingham achieved the rank of captain of the Connecticut National Guard in 1916. In 1917, he became an aviator and organized the United States Schools of Military Aeronautics at eight universities to provide ground school training for aviation cadets. He served the [[Aviation Section, U.S. Signal Corps]] and the [[United States Army Air Service|Air Service]], attaining the rank of lieutenant colonel. In [[Issoudun]], France, Bingham commanded the Third Aviation Instruction Center, the Air Service's largest primary instruction and pursuit training school.&lt;ref name=&quot;usas&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | quotes = | last = | first = | year = 1920| title = An Explorer in the Air Service| journal = U.S. Air Service| volume = 4| issue =December| pages =  | accessdate =June 3, 2012}} p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;  He became a supporter of the Air Service in their post-war quest for independence from the Army and supported that effort, in part, with the publication of his wartime experiences titled, ''An Explorer in the Air Service'' published in 1920 by Yale University Press.&lt;ref&gt;Bingham, Hiram Yale University Press, 1920.  260 pages&lt;/ref&gt;

==Politics==
[[File:HiramBingham.jpg|thumb|Hiram Bingham III at his desk in 1917]]

In 1922, Bingham was elected Lieutenant Governor of Connecticut, an office he held until 1924. In November 1924, he was elected Governor. On December 16, 1924, Bingham was also elected as a Republican to serve in the United States Senate to fill a vacancy created by the suicide of [[Frank Bosworth Brandegee]]. Bingham defeated noted educator [[Hamilton Holt]] by a handy margin. Now both Governor-elect and Senator-elect, Bingham served as Governor for one day, the shortest term of any Connecticut Governor.

Bingham was re-elected to a full six-year term in the Senate in 1926.

Senator Bingham was Chairman of the Committee on Printing and then Chairman of the Committee on Territories and Insular Possessions. President Calvin Coolidge appointed Bingham to the President's Aircraft Board during his first term in the Senate; the press quickly dubbed the ex-explorer &quot;The Flying Senator&quot;.

Bingham failed in his second reelection effort in the wake of the 1932 Democratic landslide following the Great Depression and left the Senate at the end of his second term in 1933.

During World War II, Bingham lectured at several United States Navy training schools. In 1951, Bingham was appointed Chairman of the [[Civil Service Commission]] Loyalty Review Board, an assignment he kept through 1953.

===Censure in the Senate===

The Senate Judiciary Subcommittee investigated an arrangement between Bingham, his clerk, and a lobbyist who agreed to pass information on to Bingham's office after executing a plan that was irregular, &quot;even by the standards of his day.&quot; Bingham took his clerk off duty, and paid his salary to the lobbyist, thus allowing him to attend as a Senate staffer to closed meetings of the Finance Committee's deliberations on tariff legislation.

The initial ruling of the Judiciary Subcommittee was a condemnation of Bingham's scheme; but recommended no formal Senate action. Subsequently, Bingham decided to label the subcommittee's inquiry as a partisan witch hunt, provoking further Senate interest which eventually led to a resolution of censure that passed on November 4, 1929, by a vote of 54 to 22.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/minute/Senator_Censured_In_Lobbyist_Case.htm U.S. Senate: Art &amp; History Home &gt; Historical Minutes &gt; 1921–1940 &gt; Senator Censured in Lobbyist Case&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death==
On June 6, 1956, Bingham died at his Washington, D.C. home. He was interred at [[Arlington National Cemetery]] in Virginia.

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Army}}
*''Eternity in their Hearts'' by [[Don Richardson (missionary)|Don Richardson]], Regal Books, Ventura, CA, 1981. ISBN 0-8307-0925-8, pages 34–35

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Hiram Bingham (born 1875)}}
{{wikisource author}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Bingham,+Hiram | name=Hiram Bingham}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Hiram Bingham}}
* {{Librivox author |id=3004}}
*[https://books.google.com/books?q=%22hiram+bingham%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;as_brr=1 Works by Hiram Bingham] at [[Google Books]]
*[http://hdl.handle.net/10079/fa/mssa.ms.0664 Guide to the Records of the Yale Peruvian Expedition], including Bingham's diaries
*[http://www.labyrinthina.com/bingham.htm Selection from Bingham's ''The Lost City of the Incas'']
*[http://www.isidore-of-seville.com/machu/2.html Machu Picchu on the Web - The Discovery]
*[http://www.kellscraft.com/IncaLand/incalandscontents.html ''Inca Land'', by Hiram Bingham]
*[http://www.machupicchuexplorer.com/ ''The Explorer of Machi Picchu'' by Alfred M. Bingham web site]
*[http://www.telusplanet.net/public/dkbing/HB3DESC.htm Descendants of Hiram]
*[http://www.corbisimages.com/stock-photo/rights-managed/U186863P-A/view-of-ceremony-for-wright-brothers-initial?popup=1 Bingham in fur coat with Orville Wright and Amelia Earhart at dedication of Wright Brothers National Memorial; Kitty Hawk North Carolina, December 1928]

{{S-start}}
{{S-par|us-sen}}
{{U.S. Senator box
|class=3
|before=[[Frank Bosworth Brandegee]]
|after=[[Augustine Lonergan]]
|state=Connecticut
|years=1924&amp;ndash;1933
|alongside=[[Frederic Walcott]]}}
{{S-off}}
{{Succession box
|before=[[Charles A. Templeton]]
|title=[[List of Governors of Connecticut|Governor of Connecticut]]
|after=[[John H. Trumbull]]
|years=1925}}
{{S-end}}

{{USSenCT}}
{{Governors of Connecticut}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bingham 03, Hiram}}
[[Category:1875 births]]
[[Category:1956 deaths]]
[[Category:Historians of Latin America]]
[[Category:Latin Americanists]]
[[Category:20th-century American historians]]
[[Category:American aviators]]
[[Category:Aviators from Hawaii]]
[[Category:American explorers]]
[[Category:Governors of Connecticut]]
[[Category:Incan scholars]]
[[Category:People from Honolulu]]
[[Category:Punahou School alumni]]
[[Category:United States Army officers]]
[[Category:United States Senators from Connecticut]]
[[Category:Censured or reprimanded United States Senators]]
[[Category:Yale University alumni]]
[[Category:University of California, Berkeley alumni]]
[[Category:Harvard University alumni]]
[[Category:Princeton University faculty]]
[[Category:Harvard University faculty]]
[[Category:Yale University faculty]]
[[Category:Explorers of South America]]
[[Category:Republican Party state governors of the United States]]
[[Category:Republican Party United States Senators]]
[[Category:Connecticut Republicans]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]
[[Category:American Protestants]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Connecticut]]</text>
      <sha1>t9bf44pnp5d0wjq4nnwdto87pbz3tsa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
