<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>HMAS Vendetta (D08)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3338434</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738122315</id>
      <parentid>733327474</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-07T01:22:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25246">{{otherships|HMAS Vendetta}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=
|Ship caption=
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Ship country=Australia
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|Australia|naval}}
|Ship builder=[[Williamstown Naval Dockyard]]
|Ship laid down=4 July 1949
|Ship launched=3 May 1954
|Ship commissioned=26 November 1958
|Ship decommissioned=9 October 1979
|Ship motto=*''Vindico''
*I Avenge
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honours=*'''Battle honours:'''
*[[Indonesia–Malaysia confrontation|Malaysia]] 1964–66
*[[Vietnam War|Vietnam]] 1969–70
*Seven [[HMAS Vendetta#Battle honours|inherited battle honours]]
|Ship fate=Sold for scrap in 1987
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Ship class=[[Daring class destroyer (1949)|''Daring'' class destroyer]]
|Ship displacement=*2,800 tons standard
*3,600 tons full load
|Ship length={{convert|390|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|43|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship draught=*{{convert|12|ft|9|in|m|abbr=on}} mean
*{{convert|14|ft|6|in|m|abbr=on}} deep
|Ship propulsion=*2 × Foster Wheeler boilers
*2 × English Electric geared turbines
*2 shafts
*{{convert|54,000|hp|abbr=on}}
|Ship speed=Over {{convert|30|kn}}
|Ship range={{convert|3700|nmi}} at {{convert|20|kn}}
|Ship endurance=
|Ship complement=20 officers, 300 sailors
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=*6 × 4.5-inch guns (3 twin turrets)
*6 × 40 mm Bofors (2 twin, 2 single)
*5 × 21-inch torpedo tubes (pentad mount)
*1 × Limbo mortar
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
'''HMAS ''Vendetta''''' was one of three [[Daring class destroyer (1949)|''Daring'' class]] destroyers built for and operated by the [[Royal Australian Navy]] (RAN). The destroyer was built by [[Williamstown Naval Dockyard]] and entered service in 1958. During her early career, ''Vendetta'' was deployed to the [[Far East Strategic Reserve]] on multiple occasions. In 1965 and 1966, the destroyer undertook deterrence patrols during the [[Indonesia-Malaysia Confrontation]]. Along with several runs escorting the troop transport {{HMAS|Sydney|R17|6}} to Vietnam, from late 1969 to early 1970 ''Vendetta'' was assigned to combat operations, and became the only Australian-built warship to serve in a shore bombardment role during the [[Vietnam War]].

The ship underwent a two-year modernisation from 1971 to 1973, and in December 1974 was one of thirteen RAN warships involved in [[Operation Navy Help Darwin]] after [[Cyclone Tracy]] devastated Darwin. Several more deployments were made to the Far East, up until 1978. In October 1979, the destroyer was decommissioned, and served as a [[parts hulk]] for sister ship {{HMAS|Vampire|D11|6}}. ''Vendetta'' was sold for [[ship breaking]] in January 1987.

==Design and construction==
{{Main|Daring class destroyer (1949)}}
The Royal Australian Navy initially ordered four [[Daring class destroyer (1949)|''Daring'' class destroyers]], which were to be named after the ships of the &quot;[[Scrap Iron Flotilla]]&quot; of World War II. The ships were modified during construction: most changes were made to improve habitability, including the installation of air-conditioning.&lt;ref name=Coop167&gt;Cooper, in Stevens, ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 167&lt;/ref&gt; ''Vendetta'' and her sister ships were the first all-welded ships to be constructed in Australia.&lt;ref name=Coop168&gt;Cooper, in Stevens, ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 168&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Daring''s had a standard [[displacement (ship)|displacement]] of 2,800 tons, which increased to 3,600 tons at full load.&lt;ref name=Bastock320&gt;Bastock, ''Australia's Ships of War'', p. 320&lt;/ref&gt; ''Vendetta'' and her sisters were {{convert|390|ft|m}} long, with a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|43|ft|m}}, and a [[draught (hull)|draught]] of {{convert|12|ft|9|in|m}} at mean, and {{convert|14|ft|6|in|m}} at full or deep load.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt; Her propulsion system consisted of two Foster Wheeler boilers, feeding two English Electric geared turbines, which provided {{convert|54000|hp}} to two propeller shafts.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt; ''Vendetta'' could sail at over  {{convert|30|kn|lk=in}}, and had a range of {{convert|3700|nmi|lk=in}} at {{convert|20|kn}}.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt; Her standard ship's company consisted of 20 officers and 300 sailors.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt;

''Vendetta''{{'}}s main armament consisted of six 4.5-inch guns mounted in three twin turrets, two forward and one aft.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt; Her anti-aircraft outfit consisted of six [[40 mm Bofors]]; two single mountings on the forward superstructure, and two twin mountings on the aft superstructure.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt; Five 21-inch torpedo tubes were fitted to a single pentad mount on the deck between the forward and aft superstructures.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt; For anti-submarine warfare, a [[Limbo (weapon)|Limbo]] anti-submarine mortar was carried on the aft deck, offset to port.&lt;ref name=Bastock320/&gt;

''Vendetta'' was laid down at [[Williamstown Naval Dockyard]], Melbourne on 4 July 1949.&lt;ref name=Bastock324&gt;Bastock, ''Australia's Ships of War'', p. 324&lt;/ref&gt; By 1950, it was already apparent that the Australian ''Daring''s would not be completed on time, as the Australian dockyards were experiencing difficulty in keeping up with the construction schedule.&lt;ref name=Coop167/&gt; The destroyer was launched on 3 May 1954 by the widow of [[Hector Waller]], who commanded the Scrap Iron Flotilla (including the original {{HMAS|Vendetta|D69|6}}) during World War II.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; On 18 July 1958, on the first occasion ''Vendetta'' engaged her engines during builder's trials, the destroyer accidentally rammed the [[Alfred Graving Dock|Alfred Dock]] caisson.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt;&lt;ref name=Frame36&gt;Frame, ''Where fate calls'', p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; The collision was caused when the sailor manning the [[Engine order telegraph|engine telegraph]] incorrectly relayed an order of &quot;half astern&quot; as &quot;half ahead&quot;, then repeated the mistake when the order was repeated to compensate for the first error.&lt;ref name=Frame36/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cassells160&gt;Cassells, ''The Destroyers'', p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; ''Vendetta''{{'}}s bow breached the caisson, and threatened to flood the dock with {{HMAS|Quickmatch|G92|6}} inside.&lt;ref name=Frame36/&gt; A controlled flooding kept the caisson from failing and prevented damage to ''Quickmatch'' or further damage to ''Vendetta'', but the repairs to the destroyer's bow set completion back by three months.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt;&lt;ref name=Frame36/&gt;

''Vendetta'' was commissioned on 26 November 1958.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; By the time she was commissioned, the ship's cost increased from [[Australian pound|A£]]2.6 million to A£7 million.&lt;ref name=Coop168/&gt; Only three ships, {{HMAS|Voyager|D04|2}}, ''Vendetta'', and {{HMAS|Vampire|D11|2}}, were completed; the fourth was cancelled to save money.&lt;ref&gt;Cooper, in Stevens, ''The Royal Australian Navy'', pp. 168–9&lt;/ref&gt; Like the preceding destroyer, ''Vendetta'' took her name from the concept of [[wikt:Vendetta|vendetta]], with the [[ship's badge]] depicting a [[stiletto]] dagger clenched in a fist, and the ship carrying the motto &quot;''Vindico''&quot;, Latin for &quot;I Avenge&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cassells, ''The Destroyers'', pgs. 153, 163–4&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==
===1959–1969===
In April 1959, ''Vendetta'' operated in New Zealand waters, before visiting New Guinea in June.&lt;ref&gt;Cassells, ''The Destroyers'', pp. 160–1&lt;/ref&gt; After a refit, ''Vendetta'' and the frigate ''Quickmatch'' sailed to Singapore in October for a deployment to the [[Far East Strategic Reserve]] (FESR), which lasted until July 1960.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cassells161&gt;Cassells, ''The Destroyers'', p. 161&lt;/ref&gt; ''Vendetta'' and the sloop {{HMAS|Swan|U74|2}} visited Tasmania in February 1961 for the [[Royal Hobart Regatta]].&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; On 19 February, ''Vendetta'' rescued passengers from the [[Shaw Savill Line|Shaw Savill]] vessel ''Runic'', which had run aground on [[Middleton Reef]].&lt;ref name=Cassells161/&gt; The destroyer sailed for her second FESR deployment in April.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; During the six-month deployment, ''Vendetta'' operated on [[South East Asia Treaty Organisation]] exercises, visited ports in Borneo, Japan and Malaysia, and represented Australia at the [[Philippines]] independence celebrations.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; On her return, the destroyer underwent a refit at Williamstown.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt;

[[File:Melbourne Darings 301014.jpg|thumb|left|An aircraft carrier sailing in close formation with two destroyers, one on each side.|''Vendetta'' sailing in close formation with sister ship ''Vampire'' and the aircraft carrier {{HMAS|Melbourne|R21|2}} in 1959]]
''Vendetta'' was deployed to the Far East in March 1962, and returned to Sydney in late June.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; The destroyer visited [[Noumea]] in August, then participated in Exercise Tuckerbox off North Queensland.&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; In November, ''Vendetta'' visited Fremantle for the [[1962 British Empire and Commonwealth Games|1962 Commonwealth Games]].&lt;ref name=Bastock324/&gt; After another refit, the destroyer's fourth FESR deployment commenced on 9 July 1963, when she left Sydney with {{HMAS|Quiberon|G81|2}}.&lt;ref name=Cassells161/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bastock325&gt;Bastock, ''Australia's Ships of War'', p. 325&lt;/ref&gt; While in the Far East, the two ships participated in SEATO Exercise Sea Dovetail, visited Japan, and assisted a disable United States-flagged freighter.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; ''Vendetta'' and ''Quiberon'' returned home via Guam Island and Manus Island on 20 February, after which ''Vendetta'' proceeded to Williamstown for refit.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt;

''Vendetta'' returned to the FESR in mid-1964, this time escorting the aircraft carrier {{HMAS|Melbourne|R21|2}}, and remained in [[Southeast Asian]] waters until December.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; She remained in dock for the first half of 1965 undergoing refits, and on 11 August, sailed for her sixth Far East assignment, in company with {{HMAS|Duchess|D154|2}}.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; On 20 September, ''Vendetta'' and ''Duchess'' met the troop transport {{HMAS|Sydney|R17|2}} off [[Manus Island]]; ''Sydney'' was on her second troop transport voyage to Vietnam.&lt;ref name=NottPayne170&gt;Nott &amp; Payne, ''The Vung Tau Ferry'', p. 170&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Grey106&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 106&lt;/ref&gt; The two destroyers accompanied ''Sydney'' to [[Vung Tau]], where they arrived on 28 September, then escorted the troopship clear of the [[Market Time]] area before breaking off for Hong Kong.&lt;ref name=NottPayne170/&gt;&lt;ref name=Grey106/&gt; In October, ''Vendetta'' operated as [[plane guard]] destroyer for {{HMS|Ark Royal|R09|6}}.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; During late 1965 and early 1966, the destroyer was assigned to deterrence patrols off [[Malaysian Borneo]] and the [[Singapore Straits]] as part of the Commonwealth involvement in the [[Indonesia-Malaysia Confrontation]].&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt;

''Vendetta'' and ''Duchess''' returned to Australia in March.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; On 20 May, the destroyer sailed to Jervis Bay following the sinking of the [[dredger]] ''W. D. Atlas'', and spent the next two days searching for survivors and bodies.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; ''Vendetta'' was again involved as a ''Sydney'' escort in May and June 1966, during the troopship's fourth voyage.&lt;ref name=NottPayne171&gt;Nott &amp; Payne, ''The Vung Tau Ferry'', p. 171&lt;/ref&gt; This run ended on 11 June, when ''Vendetta'' and ''Sydney'' reached Hong Kong.&lt;ref name=NottPayne171/&gt; On 3 November, the ship came to the aid of the [[United States Navy]] (USN) submarine {{USS|Tiru|SS-416|2}}, which had run aground on [[Frederick Reef]].&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; After the submarine was refloated, ''Vendetta'' escorted her to Brisbane for repairs.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; On 5 March 1968, ''Vendetta'' and {{HMAS|Parramatta|DE 46|2}} sailed for six months in the Far East; ''Vendetta''{{'}}s seventh FESR deployment.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; The destroyer returned to Australia in October.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt; The destroyer visited [[Newcastle, New South Wales]] for [[Australia Day]] (26 January) 1969, and operated in New Zealand waters during May.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt;

===Vietnam deployment===
{{further|Military history of Australia during the Vietnam War}}
In 1968, it was realised that the combination of maintenance requirements and other operational deployments meant that none of the RAN's three US-built [[Perth class destroyer|''Perth'' class]] destroyers would be available to serve in the [[Vietnam War]] once {{HMAS|Brisbane|D 41|6}} completed her deployment in late 1969.&lt;ref name=FrameNPC235&gt;Frame, ''No Pleasure Cruise'', p. 235&lt;/ref&gt; They started investigating the possibility of deploying a ''Daring'' class destroyer, with the main concern being the supply of {{convert|4.5|in|mm|adj=on}} shells, as the USN destroyers were standardised to {{convert|5|in|mm|adj=on}} shells.&lt;ref name=FrameNPC235/&gt; After receiving reassurance from the USN that any logisitcal issues regarding Australian supplies, including ammunition, were &quot;merely a problem to be overcome&quot;, ''Vendetta'' was marked for the deployment in November 1968, as she was the only available ''Daring'' or [[River class destroyer escort|River]] class vessel available.&lt;ref name=FrameNPC235/&gt;&lt;ref name=Grey207&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 207&lt;/ref&gt; The decision to send ''Vendetta'' meant that the consistent deployment of an Australian warship with the [[United States Seventh Fleet]] since March 1967 would continue, and steps towards breaking a 'two-tier' culture within the RAN favouring the ''Perth'' class ships would be made, with associated benefits to morale.&lt;ref name=Grey207/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cooper204&gt;Cooper, in Stevens, ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 204&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 September 1969, ''Vendetta'' left Australia for South Vietnam, and relieved ''Brisbane'' at Subic on 26 September.&lt;ref name=Bastock325/&gt;&lt;ref name=Grey208&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 208&lt;/ref&gt; While deployed to Vietnam, the destroyer was placed under the administrative control of [[Commander Australian Forces Vietnam]] in addition to that of the [[Flag Officer Commanding Australian Fleet]], while operationally, she was under the command of the Seventh Fleet.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', pp. 82–3&lt;/ref&gt; A USN lieutenant was assigned to ''Vendetta'' to serve as a liaison.&lt;ref name=Grey144&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 144&lt;/ref&gt; Australia was the only allied nation to provide naval support to the United States Navy during the Vietnam War.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', pp. 94–5&lt;/ref&gt; The destroyer's main activities were the provision of [[naval gunfire support]] to assist ground forces, particularly the United States Marine Corps units operating closest to the North Vietnam border.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', pp. 130–5&lt;/ref&gt; Seven ships were usually stationed on the 'gunline', and attacks fell into two categories: 'unspotted' shelling of areas where North Vietnamese or Viet Cong forces and facilities were known or believed to be, and 'spotted' fire missions in direct support of ground troops.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; In this role, ''Vendetta'' was assigned the callsign &quot;Premier&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', pp. 155–6&lt;/ref&gt;

''Vendetta'' sailed for a gunline assignment at [[Danang]] on 30 September.&lt;ref name=Grey208/&gt; While en route, the destroyer was replenished by a USN oiler, but there were problems because of the incompatibility between American fuel lines and British intakes, along with the standard pumping pressure being too high for ''Vendetta''{{'}}s system to handle; the first of numerous difficulties experienced by the British-designed ship operating with an American force.&lt;ref name=Grey208/&gt; Poor weather meant the ship did not arrive in Danang Harbour until 2 October, and she commenced naval gunfire support missions a day later.&lt;ref name=Grey208/&gt; After time at Danang, the ship sailed to the II Corps operating area, and continued gunline duties until 24 October.&lt;ref name=Grey208/&gt; She sailed to Singapore for maintenance, then resumed gunline duties on 9 November, assigned to the III Corps area.&lt;ref name=Grey209&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 209&lt;/ref&gt; ''Vendetta'' moved north to the I Coprs area two days later, then down to II Corps on 16 November.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 210&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of November, the destroyer sailed to Taiwan for rebarrelling and other maintenance.&lt;ref name=Grey211&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 211&lt;/ref&gt; She returned to the gunline on 21 December, and on 1 January 1970, was called on to assist Market Time operations by firing on two small craft suspected to be on a supply run to Viet Cong positions.&lt;ref name=Grey211/&gt;

On 17 January, ''Vendetta'' was forced to sail to Hong Kong for boiler repairs.&lt;ref name=Grey212&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 212&lt;/ref&gt; Returning on 17 February, the destroyer was assigned to III Corps, and operated off Vung Tau in support of Australian and South Vietnamese units, along with a mercenary group.&lt;ref name=Grey212/&gt; Four days later, she was reassigned to II Corps.&lt;ref name=Grey212/&gt; On 6 March, the ship left the gunline to have two of her turrets rebarrelled at Subic, then returned to duty on 13 March.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 214&lt;/ref&gt; The destroyer sailed to Subic on 23 March, and was relieved by {{HMAS|Hobart|D39|6}} on 30 March, after having fired 13,295 4.5-inch shells at 751 targets over five deployments.&lt;ref name=Bastock326&gt;Bastock, ''Australia's Ships of War'', p. 326&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cassells162&gt;Cassells, ''The Destroyers'', p. 162&lt;/ref&gt;

The destroyer was the only Australian-built warship to serve as a combatant in Vietnam,&lt;ref name=Bastock326/&gt; and the only ''Daring'' class destroyer to be operationally deployed in the shore bombardment role.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 321&lt;/ref&gt; ''Vendetta''{{'}}s deployment to Vietnam under the new [[Australian White Ensign]], and patrols during the Indonesia-Malaysia Confrontation under the old ensign (identical to the British [[White Ensign]]), made the destroyer one of only two RAN vessels to deploy operationally under both ensigns.&lt;ref&gt;Fairfax, ''Navy in Vietnam'', p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; Personnel awards for the deployment included one appointment as an [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire]], two [[Mentions in Despatches]], and 16 Naval Board commendations.&lt;ref&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;

===1970–1979===
''Vendetta'' sailed for a FESR deployment in September 1970.&lt;ref name=Bastock326/&gt; She escorted the troopship ''Sydney'' for the third and final time during the former carrier's seventeenth voyage: ''Vendetta'' met the transport off Manila in late October, with the two ships in Vietnam during 31 October and 1 November.&lt;ref name=Grey108&gt;Grey, ''Up Top'', p. 108&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NottPayne175&gt;Nott &amp; Payne, ''The Vung Tau Ferry'', p. 175&lt;/ref&gt; During November, the destroyer visited ports in India, before returning to Hong Kong for Christmas.&lt;ref name=Bastock326/&gt; She returned to Sydney in April 1971, and after participating in training exercises and a cruise in northern Australian waters, arrived in Williamstown on 29 September for her half-life modernisation refit.&lt;ref name=Bastock326/&gt; The modernisation cost US$20 million.&lt;ref name=Jones218&gt;Jones, in Stevens, ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; The fire-control system was replaced, a long-range air radar was installed, and the superstructure was modified, including a roof for the bridge.&lt;ref name=Jones218/&gt; ''Vendetta'' re-entered service on 2 May 1973.&lt;ref name=Bastock326/&gt;

From March until July 1974, ''Vendetta'' was again deployed to the Far East.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassells162&quot;/&gt; In October, the destroyer represented the RAN at celebrations of the centenary of [[Colonial Fiji|Fiji's cession to Britain]].&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; Following the destruction of Darwin by [[Cyclone Tracy]] in December 1974, ''Vendetta'' was one of thirteen RAN ships deployed as part of the humanitarian aid mission [[Operation Navy Help Darwin]].&lt;ref&gt;Jones, in Stevens, ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 234&lt;/ref&gt; The destroyer sailed on 27 December from Sydney, and arrived on 3 January, with shore parties primarily assigned to the [[Nightcliff, Northern Territory|Nightcliff]] area.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; The destroyer remained in the area until late January.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; During mid-1975, ''Vendetta'' operated in the Far East.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; In August 1975, following tensions between Indonesia and the former Portuguese colony of East Timor (which cumulated in the Indonesian [[Indonesian invasion of East Timor|invasion]] in December), ''Vendetta'', ''Vampire'', and the supply ship {{HMAS|Supply||6}} were pre-positioned in Darwin in case they were needed for evacuations of Australian citizens or Timorese refugees.&lt;ref name=Jones231&gt;Jones, in Stevens, ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; Action by the ships was not required.

Most of 1976 was spent undergoing maintenance at Williamstown.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; In 1977, ''Vendetta'' was deployed to the Far East.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; Another deployment was made in 1978, starting in July.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; While en route, the destroyer visited Honiara to participate in celebrations of [[Solomon Islands]] independence from Australia.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt;

==Decommissioning and fate==
''Vendetta'' paid off on 9 October 1979.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; After spending time moored near [[Bradleys Head]], during which she was used as a parts [[hulk (ship)|hulk]] for sister ship ''Vampire'', the destroyer was sold for [[ship breaking]].&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt; ''Vendetta'' was towed to her fate in January 1987.&lt;ref name=Cassells162/&gt;

Following an overhaul of the RAN [[battle honour]]s system, completed in March 2010, ''Vendetta''{{'}}s service was recognised with the honours &quot;Malaysia 1964–66&quot; and &quot;Vietnam 1969–70&quot;.&lt;ref name=newhonours&gt;Royal Australian Navy, ''Navy Marks 109th Birthday With Historic Changes To Battle Honours''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=honourslist&gt;Royal Australian Navy, ''Royal Australian Navy Ship/Unit Battle Honours''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Citations==
{{reflist|3}}

==References==
;Books
*{{cite book |last=Bastock |first=John |title=Australia's Ships of War |year=1975 |publisher=Angus and Robertson |location=Cremorne, NSW |isbn=0-207-12927-4 |oclc=2525523}}
*{{cite book |last=Cassells |first=Vic |title=The Destroyers: their battles and their badges |year=2000 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=East Roseville, NSW |isbn=0-7318-0893-2 |oclc=46829686}}
*{{cite book |last=Fairfax |first=Denis |title=Navy in Vietnam: a record of the Royal Australian Navy in the Vietnam War 1965–1972 |publisher=Australian Government Publishing Service |location=Canberra |year=1980 |isbn=0-642-02821-4 |oclc=9854447}}
*{{cite book |last=Frame |first=Tom |authorlink=Tom Frame (bishop) |title=Where fate calls: the HMAS Voyager tragedy |year=1992 |publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton |location=Rydalmere, NSW |isbn=0-340-54968-8 |oclc=26806228}}
*{{cite book |last=Frame |first=Tom |authorlink=Tom Frame (bishop) |title=No Pleasure Cruise: the story of the Royal Australian Navy |year=2004 |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Crows Nest, NSW |isbn=1-74114-233-4 |oclc=55980812}}
*{{cite book |last=Grey |first=Jeffrey |authorlink=Jeffrey Grey  |title=Up Top: the Royal Australian Navy and Southeast Asian conflicts, 1955–1972 |year=1998 |series=The Official History of Australia's Involvement in Southeast Asian Conflicts 1948–1975 |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=St. Leonards, NSW |isbn=1-86448-290-7 |oclc=39074315}}
*{{cite book |last=Nott |first=Rodney |author2=Payne, Noel  |title=The Vung Tau Ferry: HMAS Sydney and Escort Ships |publisher=Rosenberg |location=Dural, NSW |origyear=1994 |year=2008 |edition=4th |isbn=978-1-877058-72-1 |oclc=254773862}}
*{{cite book |editor=Stevens, David |title=The Royal Australian Navy |series=The Australian Centenary History of Defence (vol III) |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, VIC |isbn=0-19-555542-2 |oclc=50418095}}
**{{cite book |last=Cooper |first=Alastair |title=The Royal Australian Navy |chapter=The Korean War Era&quot;; &quot;The Era of Forward Defence}}
**{{cite book |last=Jones |first=Peter |title=The Royal Australian Navy |chapter=Towards Self Reliance&quot;; &quot;A Period of Change and Uncertainty}}

;News articles
*{{cite news |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/Navy_Marks_109th_Birthday_With_Historic_Changes_To_Battle_Honours |title=Navy Marks 109th Birthday With Historic Changes To Battle Honours |date=1 March 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110613184920/http://www.navy.gov.au/Navy_Marks_109th_Birthday_With_Historic_Changes_To_Battle_Honours |archivedate=13 June 2011 |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |accessdate=23 December 2012}}

;Websites
*{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/Units_entitlement_list.pdf |title=Royal Australian Navy Ship/Unit Battle Honours |date=1 March 2010 |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110614064156/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/Units_entitlement_list.pdf |archivedate=14 June 2011 |accessdate=23 December 2012}}

{{Daring class destroyer (1949)}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vendetta (D08)}}
[[Category:Daring-class destroyers (1949) of the Royal Australian Navy]]
[[Category:Ships built in Victoria (Australia)]]
[[Category:1954 ships]]
[[Category:Vietnam War destroyers of Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>ayvu50p3bpp3j0c292jmdp47v6va2zb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
