<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>HMS Favourite (1794)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23515809</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739718453</id>
      <parentid>739717894</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-16T14:31:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acad Ronin</username>
        <id>70274</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24427">{{other ships|HMS Favourite|HMS Goree}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=
|Ship caption=
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=[[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|UK]]
|Ship flag=[[File:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|60px|Royal Navy Ensign]]
|Ship name=HMS ''Favourite''
|Ship ordered=18 February 1793
|Ship builder= Randall &amp; Brent, [[Rotherhithe]]
|Ship laid down=April 1793
|Ship launched=1 February 1794
|Ship acquired=
|Ship completed=By 14 May 1794
|Ship commissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship struck=
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship honours=
|Ship captured=By the French on 6 January 1806
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=title
|Ship country=France
|Ship flag=[[File:Civil and Naval Ensign of France.svg|60px]] 
|Ship name=''Favorite''
|Ship acquired=6 January 1806 by capture
|Ship commissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship captured=27 January 1807, by the [[Royal Navy]]
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=title
|Ship country=[[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|UK]]
|Ship flag=[[File:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|60px|Royal Navy Ensign]]
|Ship name=HMS ''Goree''
|Ship acquired=27 January 1807
|Ship completed=
|Ship commissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship reclassified=[[Prison ship]] in 1813/14
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship honours=[[Naval General Service Medal (1847)|Naval General Service Medal]] with clasp &quot;Martinque&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=20939|startpage=242|date=26 January 1849}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=Broken up in 1817
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=&lt;ref name=Winfield253/&gt;
|Ship class=16-gun [[Cormorant class ship-sloop|''Cormorant''-class]] [[sloop-of-war|sloop]]
|Ship tons burthen=426&lt;small&gt;{{fraction|88|94}}&lt;/small&gt; [[Builder's Old Measurement|bm]]
|Ship length=*{{convert|108|ft|5|in|m|1|abbr=on}} (overall)
*{{convert|90|ft|8+1/4|in|m|1|abbr=on}} (keel)
|Ship beam={{convert|29|ft|9|in|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship draught=
|Ship hold depth={{convert|9|ft|m|2|abbr=on}}
|Ship sail plan=[[Sloop]]
|Ship propulsion=Sails
|Ship complement=*'''British service''':121
*'''French service''':150
|Ship armament=*'''Originally''':16 x 6-pounder guns + 12 x ½-pounder [[swivel gun]]s
*'''French capture''':18 x 6-pounder guns + 11 x 12-pounder [[carronade]]s
*'''British capture''':16 x 6-pounder guns + 13 x 12-pounder carronades
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''HMS ''Favourite''''' (or ''Favorite'') was a 16-gun [[Cormorant class ship-sloop|''Cormorant''-class]] [[sloop-of-war|sloop]] of the [[Royal Navy]], launched in 1794 at [[Rotherhithe]]. The French captured her in 1806 and renamed her ''Favorite''. However, the British recaptured her in 1807 and renamed her HMS ''Goree''. She became a [[prison ship]] in 1810 and was broken up in Bermuda in 1817.

==French Revolutionary Wars==
;Commander James Athol Wood
''Favourite'' was commissioned in March 1794 under Commander Charles White.&lt;ref name=Winfield253&gt;Winfield (2008), p.253.&lt;/ref&gt; In September of the next year Commander [[James Athol Wood]] took command and sailed her for the Leeward Islands.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM-WH-366690&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nmm.ac.uk/upload/pdf/Warship_Histories_Vessels_i.pdf|title=NMM, vessel ID 366690|work=Warship Histories, vol i|publisher=[[National Maritime Museum]]|accessdate=30 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Favourite''{{'}}s first task was to assist in the quelling of insurrections on [[Grenada]] and [[Saint Vincent (Antilles)|St. Vincent]].&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;On Grenada [[Julien Fédon]], a &quot;free coloured&quot; French-African planter, led a pro-French revolt between 1795 and 1796. On St. Vincent there was conflict between the British and the Black Caribs, who were led by defiant Paramount Chief [[Joseph Chatoyer]]. In 1796 British General Sir [[Ralph Abercromby]] put an end to the open conflict by crushing a revolt that the French radical [[Victor Hugues]] had instigated.&lt;/ref&gt; In support of these operations, Captain [[Robert Otway]] of {{HMS|Mermaid|1782|2}} had Wood patrol the waters to intercept vessels carrying provisions to the insurgents.

On 5 February 1796 ''Favourite'' captured two French privateers and ran one ashore within the [[List of islands of Trinidad and Tobago#Bocas Islands|Bocas Islands]] between Trinidad and Venezuela. The largest privateer was the ''Général Rigaud'', of eight guns and 45 men, mostly Italians and Spaniards. The second privateer was the [[packet ship]] ''Hind'', which the ''Général Rigaud'' had taken off St. Vincent's. Her crew escaped before ''Favourite'' could take possession. The vessel that ran ashore was the ''Banan''.&lt;ref name=LG13917&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=13917|startpage=732|date=30 July 1796}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Less than a month later, on 1 March, ''Favourite'', the armed transport ''Sally'', and two large sloops that Wood commandeered, evacuated 11-1200 British troops from [[Sauteurs]], where an insurgent force had trapped them. The next day Woods delivered the troops safely to [[St. George's, Grenada|St. George's]].&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

A week later, on 9 March, ''Favourite'' encountered three vessels windward of Grenada. They were two French privateer schooners, one of 10 guns and one of 12, and a ship of 14 guns. After an all-day chase, ''Favourite'' was able to capture the ship without a fight; the two schooners escaped.{{refn|Biographies of Wood state that when he captured the ship he also captured the vessels' private night signals, enabling him to capture her two consorts later that night.&lt;ref name=Marshall&gt;Marshall (1823), Vol. 1, Part. 2, pp.786-91.&lt;/ref&gt; If so, Wood did not mention the subsequent captures in his letter reporting the capture of the ''Susanna''.|group=Note}}   The ship turned out to be the ''Susanna'', of Liverpool, which the privateers had captured a few days earlier and manned to also serve as a privateer. In all, ''Favourite'' ended up with 70 prisoners. Wood distributed most of them in two or three-man groups to the transports and merchant vessels of a convoy heading for Britain. The officers he put aboard {{HMS|Charlotte|1798|2}}.&lt;ref name=LG13917/&gt;

On 22 July ''Mermaid'' and ''Favorite'' recaptured the sloop ''Two Sisters''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=154665|startpage=324|date=27 March 1802}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November ''Favourite'' was enforcing a blockade of the port of [[Paramaribo]].&lt;ref&gt;Williams (2009), p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 1797, Wood reconnoitered [[Trinidad]] for General Sir [[Ralph Abercromby]]. Admiral Sir [[Henry Harvey]], commander-in-chief for the Navy in the Leeward Islands then had Wood draw up a plan for an attack.&lt;ref&gt;Ralfe (1828), pp.175-181.&lt;/ref&gt; The result was that in February, ''Favourite'' was at the [[Invasion of Trinidad (1797)|capture of Trinidad]]. The flotilla sailed from [[Carriacou and Petite Martinique|Carriacou]] on 15 February and arrived off [[Port of Spain]] on the next day.&lt;ref name=LG13995/&gt; At Port of Spain they found a Spanish squadron consisting of four [[ship of the line|ships of the line]] and a frigate, all under the command of Rear-Admiral Don Sebastian Ruiz de Apodaca. Harvey sent ''Favourite'' and some of the other smaller ships to protect the transports and anchored his own ships of the line opposite the Spanish squadron. At 2am on 17 February the British discovered that four of the five Spanish vessels were on fire; they were able to capture the 74-gun ''San Domaso'' but the others were destroyed.&lt;ref name=LG13995/&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The five Spanish ships were ''San Vincente'' (Captain Don Geronimo Mendoza; 84 guns), ''Gallardo'' (Captain Don Gabriel Sororido; 74 guns), ''Arrogante'' (Captain Don Raphael Benasa; 74 guns), ''San Damaso'' (Don Tores Jordan; 74 guns), and ''Santa Cecilia'' (Captain Don Manuel Urtesabel; 36 guns).&lt;/ref&gt; Later that morning General Sir [[Ralph Abercrombie]] landed the troops, with Wood, together with Captain Wolley of {{HMS|Arethusa|1781|2}}, superintending the landing.&lt;ref name=NC24/&gt;  The Governor of Trinidad, [[José Maria Chacón]], surrendered the next day.&lt;ref name=LG13995&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=13995|startpage=286|date=27 March 1797}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Favourite'' shared with the rest of the flotilla in the allocation of £40,000 for the proceeds of the ships taken at Trinidad and of the property found on the island.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15084|startpage=1144|date=27 November 1798}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 March Wood received his promotion to [[post captain]] and command of ''San-Damaso''.&lt;ref name=NC24&gt;''Naval Chronicle'', Vol. 24, pp.181-2.&lt;/ref&gt; He then sailed her to England as escort to a large convoy.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

;Lieutenant Lord Camelford
Wood's replacement, in May 1797, was Commander S. Powell.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM-WH-366690&quot;/&gt; Some months later, in July, Commander James Hanson assumed command. Then [[Thomas Pitt, 2nd Baron Camelford|Thomas Pitt]], Lieutenant Lord Camelford, took command, replacing Hanson, who had taken ill.&lt;ref name=Mostert&gt;Mostert (2007), pp. 238-45.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Pitt was a cousin of the then Prime Minister, [[William Pitt the Younger|William Pitt]].&lt;ref name=Mostert/&gt;|group=Note}} Although Camelford was apparently appointed in January, he had been acting captain for some time. On 13 January 1798, Camelford shot and killed Lieutenant Charles Peterson, acting captain of [[French corvette Perdrix (1784)|''Perdrix]] for mutiny, in a dispute over which of them was senior to the other. At the time, both vessels were in [[English Harbour]], Antigua, serving as guardships. What triggered the dispute was the departure from the harbour on the previous day of {{HMS|Babet|1794|6}}, whose captain, Jemmet Mainwaring, had previously been the senior officer in the port. Peterson had been [[First lieutenant#Royal Navy|first lieutenant]] under Camelford for three months when Camelford had taken over ''Favourite'', even though Peterson was senior on the lieutenants list and represented Captain Fahie of ''Perdrix'', who was away in St. Kitts. The two ships' companies almost fired on each other when Camelford shot Petersen. Captain Henry Mitford of [[French corvette Jacobine (1794)|''Matilda'']] arrived that evening and put Camelford under arrest. Mitford put Lieutenant Parsons of ''Favourite'' in command of ''Perdrix'' and sent her out to sea. The subsequent court martial acquitted Camelford.{{refn|Camelford died in a duel in 1804. Apparently few people regretted his demise.&lt;ref name=Mostert/&gt;|group=Note}}

;Commander Joseph Westbeach
In May 1799, Commander Joseph Westbeach took command and in July/August sailed her home with the trade. She then sailed in the North Sea.&lt;ref name=Winfield253/&gt;

On 15 January 1801, ''Favourite'' captured a [[cutter (ship)|cutter]] off [[Flamborough Head]], after a seven-hour chase. The cutter proved to be the French privateer ''Voyageur'', of 14 guns and 47 men, under the command of Egide Colbert. Colbert was four days out of Ostend and the day before had captured the merchant vessel ''Camilla'', of [[Sunderland, Tyne and Wear|Sunderland]], which had been sailing in ballast.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15329|startpage=86|date=17 January 1801}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two months later, on 13 March, ''Favourite'' chased a lugger for eleven hours from Scarborough before losing her. She then saw another sail, which she pursued and captured. She was the French privateer schooner ''Optimiste'', of Dunkirk, armed with 14 guns and had a crew of 47 men under the command of Jean Baptiste Corenwinder.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15345|startpage=297|date=14 March January 1801}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Then on 17 April, ''Favourite'' captured a French privateer lugger off Plymouth after a four-hour chase. The lugger was the ''Antichrist'', armed with fourteen 2 and 9-pounder guns. She had a crew of 60 men under the command of Henry Alexandre Scorffery. She was 15 days out of Dunkirk and ''Favourite'' recaptured her sole prize, the ship ''Brotherly Love'', of [[South Shields]], which had been sailing to London when she was captured.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15356|startpage=423|date=18 April 1801}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between May 1803 and June 1804, ''Favourite'' underwent repairs at Sheerness.&lt;ref name=Winfield253/&gt;

==Napoleonic Wars==
Commander Charles Foote commissioned ''Favourite'' in May 1804. On 1 August she then participated in a bombardment of [[Le Havre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM-WH-366690&quot;/&gt; ''Favourite'' was among the vessels that shared in the proceeds of the capture on 15 September of the ''Flora de Lisboa''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15925|startpage=7043|date=3 June 1806}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
On 12 December 1804, ''Favorite'' encountered two French privateer luggers and gave chase.&lt;ref name=LG15763/&gt; They were in possession of a brig and were boarding a [[bark]] as ''Favorite'' approached. Foote signaled to a cutter that was in sight, which he believed was the hired armed cutter [[Hired armed cutter Countess of Elgin|''Countess of Elgin'']], to chase the merchant vessels, and set out after the privateers, which however separated.&lt;ref name=LG15763/&gt; After three hours ''Favorite'' caught up with ''Raccrocheuse'', which was under the command of Captain Jacques Broquant.&lt;ref name=LG15763/&gt; She was armed with fourteen 4-pounder guns and had a crew of 56 men. She was one day out from [[Saint-Valery-en-Caux]].&lt;ref name=LG15763&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15763|startpage=1513|date=15 December 1804}}&lt;/ref&gt; The privateer that escaped was the ''Adolphe'', which too carried fourteen 4-pounder guns, which however she had thrown overboard during the chase. Foote believed that she had returned to Saint-Valery-en-Caux.&lt;ref name=LG15763/&gt;

In December 1804 John Davie became captain of ''Favourite''. A year later, in December 1805, ''Favourite'' was at the [[Îles de Los]], searching for a privateer at the behest of Captain Keith Maxwell of {{HMS|Arab|1798|6}}.&lt;ref name=LG15908&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15908|startpage=447|endpage=448|date=8 April 1806}}&lt;/ref&gt; Having received intelligence there that the privateer was at the [[Pongo River (Guinea)|Pongo River]], to the south, Davie sailed there. Near there he spotted two vessels, which the pilot believed were the privateer's prizes. Still it took three days during which the ship's crew had to man the sweeps and boats to tow her through water that was no more than three [[fathom]]s deep to reach entrance of the river. Once there, on 28 December ''Favourite'' sighted the privateer sailing out and attempting to escape.  ''Favourite'' sailed towards her and when within half-a-gunshot, fired his [[chase gun|bow chasers]] at her. The privateer raked ''Favourite'' with  her guns, leading Davies to reply with a broadside. The captain of the privateer &quot;had the Temerity to continue to engaging us for Twenty Minutes&quot; before [[striking the colours|striking]].&lt;ref name=LG15908/&gt;

The privateer was the ''General Blanchard'', of sixteen guns and a crew of 120 French and Spaniards. The engagement had cost her 11 men killed, including the captain, and 25 wounded. ''Favourite{{'}}''s only casualty was one man lightly wounded, a passenger, Lieutenant Odhum of the [[Royal African Corps]].&lt;ref name=LG15908/&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The Royal African Corps was composed of military offenders from various regiments pardoned on condition of life-service in Africa and the West Indies.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Capture and re-capture==

While ''Favorite'' was sailing under Commander John Davie, [[L'Hermite's expedition|L'Hermite's squadron]] captured her on 6 January 1806.&lt;ref name=Hepper/&gt; During the night before she had been sailing off Cape Verde, towing a prize, when the watch spotted some vessels. ''Favourite'' cast off her tow and attempted to move to windward of the strangers but lost track of them. Next morning ''Favourite'' saw what appeared to be three large [[East Indiaman|East Indiamen]] with a brig as escort, sailing towards her. As they closed, Davie realized that the strange vessels were a ship of the line, two frigates and a sloop. He tried to sail away, but eventually had to surrender when he found himself trapped between [[French ship Régulus (1805)|''Régulus'']] and [[French frigate Président|''Président'']].&lt;ref name=Hepper&gt;Hepper (1994), p.113.&lt;/ref&gt; The French brought their prize into service as ''Favorite''.

On 20 June 1806, she reached Cayenne, where she was re-armed with ''Lieutenant de vaisseau'' Le Marant Kerdaniel as captain. She sailed from there on Christmas Eve 1806, along with the 16-gun brig [[French brig Argus (1800)|''Argus'']].{{refn|''Argus'' had a crew of 120 men and was armed with fourteen brass 8-pounder guns, which were the equivalent of English 9-pounders.&lt;ref name=LG16020/&gt;|group=Note}}

On 27 January 1807 the British 32-gun frigate {{HMS|Jason|1804|2}} intercepted ''Argus'' and ''Favorite''. ''Favorite'' stayed behind and battled for one hour to allow ''Argus'' to escape but was forced to [[Striking the colours|strike]]. At the time, ''Favorite'' was armed with sixteen 6-pounder guns and thirteen 12-pounder [[carronade]]s, and had a crew of 150 men. In the action she lost one man killed and one man wounded; ''Jason'' only had one man wounded.&lt;ref name=LG16020&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16020|date=14 April 1807|startpage=479}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Head money for the crew of ''Favorite'' was paid in August 1817. Captain Thomas Cochrane of ''Jason'' received a first class share or [[£sd|£]] 257 and 15[[shilling|s]]; a seaman received a fifth-class share or 16s 2½[[pence|d]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=17277|date=16 August 1817|startpage=1772}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}  {{HMS|Wolverine|1805|2}} was in sight at the time of the capture but did not join the engagement.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16725|date=1 May 1813|startpage=862}}&lt;/ref&gt; The British brought ''Favorite'' into service as HMS ''Goree'', though it took some time for the name change to register in the West Indies.

''Favourite'' participated in the second British [[Invasion of the Danish West Indies (1807)|invasion of the Danish West Indies]], which took place in December 1807. A British fleet captured the Danish islands of [[Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands|St Thomas]] on 22 December and [[Saint Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands|Santa Cruz]] on 25 December. The Danes did not resist and the invasion was bloodless.

==HMS ''Goree''==

On 22 April 1808, ''Goree'', under Commander Joseph Spear, engaged the French brigs [[French brig Palinure (1804)|''Palinure'']] and ''Pilade'' in an inconclusive action. The schooner {{HMS|Superieure|1803|2}} was at anchor a few miles to the NW while refilling her water casks. When the Governor of [[Marie-Galante]], which the British had just occupied a month earlier, informed him that ''Goree'' was engaged, Captain William Robillard immediately came to ''Goree''{{'}}s assistance. ''Superieure'' then prevented the French brigs from reaching Guadeloupe and kept up a running fight with ''Pilade'' until they reached the [[Îles des Saintes|Saintes]].&lt;ref name=Marshall470/&gt; A little while later the frigate {{HMS|Circe|1804|2}} and the brig-sloop ''Wolverine'' arrived, but too late to engage.&lt;ref&gt;James (1837), Vol. 5, pp.41-2.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Goree'' had one man killed and the French lost eight men killed and 21 wounded.&lt;ref name=Marshall470&gt;Marshall (1827), Supplement, Part 1, pp.470-472.&lt;/ref&gt; On 31 October ''Circe'' captured ''Palinure''.

In January 1809, ''Goree'' participated in the [[Invasion of Martinique (1809)|invasion of Martinique]]. In 1847 the Admiralty awarded the Naval General Service Medal with clasp &quot;Martinique&quot; to all surviving claimants from the campaign. In October, ''Goree'' came under the command of the newly promoted Commander Henry Dilkes Byng, formerly of {{HMS|Bream|1807|2}}.&lt;ref name=Marshall2/&gt; 

From 1810 to 1813 ''Goree'' was on the [[City of Halifax|Halifax]] station. That year Byng and ''Goree'' intercepted the schooner {{USS|Revenge|1806|6}} under Lieutenant [[Oliver Hazard Perry]]. Fortunately, no more dramatic incident ensued.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie (1910), p.63-4.&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Little Belt Affair]] on 16 May 1811, ''Goree'' encountered and escorted the damaged {{HMS|Little Belt|1807|2}} to Halifax. Also in 1811, Byng intercepted and took into [[Nassau, Bahamas|Nassau]] the ''San Carlos'', after determining from an inspection of her papers that she was &quot;An American ship engaged in the African Salve Trade under Spanish Colours.&quot; The court in Nassau released the ''San Carlos'' back to her owners as she had no slaves aboard and the charge rested only on Byng's belief that she had forged documents.&lt;ref&gt;Adderley (2006), p.29.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the start of the [[War of 1812]], on 2 October, ''Goree'' captured the American ship ''Ranger'', which was sailing from the Pacific to Nantucket with a valuable cargo.&lt;ref name=Marshall2&gt;Marshall (1829), Supplement 3, pp. 242-6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16173|startpage=579|date=20 March 1813}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1813 ''Goree'' became a [[Prison ship|prison hulk]] and Byng transferred to [[USS Viper (1806)|''Mohawk'']].

''Goree'' moved to Bermuda where from July 1814 she was under Commander [[Constantine Richard Moorsom]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Winfield253&quot; /&gt; ''Goree'' shared with {{HMS|Euryalus|1803|2}} in a grant of £3988 19[[Shilling|s]] 9[[pence|d]] for the capture of the ship ''St. Nicolay'' on 30 November 1814.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=17390|startpage=1499|date=22 August 1818}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lieutenant Edward Stone Cottgrave became acting commander in April 1815.&lt;ref&gt;O'Bryne 1849), Vol. 1, p.232.&lt;/ref&gt; Lieutenant John Boulton replaced him in June 1815, only to have Commander John Wilson replace him in turn within the month.

==Fate==
''Goree'' was broken up in Bermuda in 1817.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winfield253&quot; /&gt;

==Notes, citations, and references==
;Notes
{{reflist|group=Note}}
;Citations
{{reflist|30em}}

;References
*Adderley, Rosanne Marion (2006) ''&quot;New negroes from Africa&quot;: slave trade abolition and free African settlement in the nineteenth-century Caribbean''. (Indiana University Press). ISBN 978-0-253-21827-8 
*{{Colledge}}
*{{cite book|last=Hepper|first=David J.|authorlink=|year=1994|title=British Warship Losses in the Age of Sail, 1650-1859|publisher=Jean Boudriot|location=Rotherfield|isbn=0-948864-30-3}}
* {{cite book| last = James| first = William| authorlink = William James (naval historian)| year = 1837| title = The Naval History of Great Britain, from the Declaration of War by France in 1793, to the Accession of George IV.| publisher = R. Bentley}}
*Mackenzie, Alexander Slidell (1910) ''Commodore Oliver Hazard Perry: famous American naval hero, victor of the Battle of Lake Erie, his life and achievements''. (D.M. MacLellan).
*Marshall, John (1823-1835) ''Royal naval biography, or, Memoirs of the services of all the flag-officers, superannuated rear-admirals, retired-captains, post-captains, and commanders, whose names appeared on the Admiralty list of sea officers at the commencement of the present year 1823, or who have since been promoted ...'' (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme and Brown).
*Mostert, Noël  (2007) ''The line upon a wind: the great war at sea, 1793-1815''. (W. W. Norton &amp; Company). ISBN 978-0-393-06653-1
*O’Byrne, William R. (1849) ''A naval biographical dictionary: comprising the life and services of every living officer in Her Majesty's navy, from the rank of admiral of the fleet to that of lieutenant, inclusive''. (London: J. Murray), vol. 1.
*Ralfe, James (1828) ''The naval biography of Great Britain: consisting of historical memoirs of those officers of the British Navy who distinguished themselves during the reign of His Majesty George III.'' (Whitmore &amp; Fenn).
*Williams, Greg H. (2009) ''The French assault on American shipping, 1793-1813: a history and comprehensive record of merchant marine losses''. (McFarland &amp; Co.). ISBN 978-0-7864-3837-2 
*{{cite book |first=Rif|last=Winfield|title=British Warships in the Age of Sail 1793&amp;ndash;1817: Design, Construction, Careers and Fates|publisher=Seaforth|year=2008|isbn=1-86176-246-1}}

{{Cormorant class ship-sloop}}
{{WarshipHist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Favourite (1794)}}
[[Category:Cormorant-class ship-sloops]]
[[Category:Age of Sail naval ships of France]]
[[Category:1794 ships]]
[[Category:Rotherhithe-built ships]]
[[Category:War of 1812 ships of the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>ti84a9ul6lwrt52m74uqoud97a8aj34</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
