<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>HMS Paz (1807)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37997241</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742158706</id>
      <parentid>718470807</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-02T01:32:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acad Ronin</username>
        <id>70274</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Service */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16484">{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image = 
| Ship caption = 
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header =
| Ship country = Spain
| Ship flag =  {{shipboxflag|Spain|1785}}
| Ship name = ''Paz''
| Ship builder = 
| Ship original cost = 
| Ship laid down = c.1804
| Ship commissioned = 
| Ship decommissioned = 
| Ship renamed = 
| Ship honours = 
| Ship captured = By the Royal Navy, February 1807
| Ship fate = 
| Ship status = 
| Ship notes = 
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header =title
| Ship country = United Kingdom
| Ship flag = {{shipboxflag|United Kingdom|naval}}
| Ship name = HMS ''Paz''
| Ship acquired = By capture, February 1807
| Ship commissioned = 
| Ship decommissioned = 
| Ship in service = 
| Ship out of service = 
| Ship renamed = 
| Ship struck = 
| Ship reinstated = 
| Ship fate = Sold, 1816
| Ship status = 
| Ship notes = 
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = (in Spanish service)
| Ship type = [[Schooner]]
| Ship tons burthen =  
| Ship displacement =  
| Ship length = 
| Ship beam =
| Ship draught = 
| Ship hold depth = 
| Ship propulsion = 
| Ship sail plan = 
| Ship complement = 
| Ship armament = 10 guns
| Ship notes = 
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = (in British service)&lt;ref name=Winfield/&gt;
| Ship type = [[Schooner]]
| Ship tons burthen = 141 ([[Builder's Old Measurement|bm]])
| Ship displacement =  
| Ship length =  
| Ship beam =  
| Ship draught = 
| Ship hold depth = 
| Ship propulsion = 
| Ship sail plan = 
| Ship complement =40
| Ship armament = 2 × long 6-pounder [[chase gun|bow chasers]] + 10 x 12-pounder [[carronade]]s
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}
'''HMS ''Paz''''' was a Spanish naval schooner that the [[Royal Navy]] captured at [[British invasions of the Río de la Plata#Battle of Montevideo|Monte Video]] on 3 February 1807. She served on the River Plate, North Sea, and North American Stations, where she captured numerous privateers and merchant vessels. She was sold in 1816.

==Capture==
The time of her capture, the British described ''Paz'' as being &quot;pierced for 10 Guns, about 3 Years old, Sails on Shore, is coppered, and pretty well found.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16019|startpage=473|date=13 April 1807}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June ''Paz'' was on the River Plate in the squadron under Admiral [[George Murray (Royal Navy officer)|George Murray]] supporting General [[John Whitelocke]]'s soldiers in the [[British invasions of the Río de la Plata|operations to capture Buenos Aires]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16065|startpage=1210|date=13 September 1807}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Service==
HMS ''Paz'' was registered on 4 June 1808. However, she was already commissioned in February 1807 under Lieutenant George Mitchenor. In April, Lieutenant John Pierie replaced Mitchenor, still on the River plate station.&lt;ref name=Winfield/&gt; Pierie had been a [[impressment|pressed]] man, an unusual background for an officer. He quarreled with his sailing master and froze him out of the running of the vessel.&lt;ref&gt;''Army Quarterly'' (1994), Vol. 124, p.443.&lt;/ref&gt; During Pierie's command, 14 of his 31 crewmen deserted. This may not have been entirely due to Pierie. When captains of four other vessels on the station were asked to provide crew to man ''Paz'', they naturally sent over &quot;the clumsy, the stupid, the violent, and the disobedient&quot;, and these men represented over half of her crew.&lt;ref&gt;''Army Quarterly'' (1994), Vol. 124, p.478.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Paz'' sailed to the [[Cape of Good Hope]]. There Lieutenant [[Daniel Pring]] took command and sailed her to England.&lt;ref name=Tucker&gt;Tucker ''et al.'', (2012), p.592.&lt;/ref&gt; There she was refitted at Portsmouth between 24 April 1808 and 6 June 1808. In 1809 in the North Sea.&lt;ref name=Winfield/&gt; Still under Pring's command, on 23 May 1809, ''Paz'' was in company when the gun-brig {{HMS|Exertion|1805|2}} when they destroyed two Danish privateers, one was the ''Elsigneur'' and the other ''Sylt''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16360|startpage=549|date=10 April 1810}}&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Exertion'', ''Paz'', and {{HMS|Censor|1801|2}} then captured the French privateer ''Fortune'' on 16 June.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16619|startpage=1285|date=30 June 1812}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Paz'' destroyed the privateer ''Betsey'' on 20 July.{{refn|A first-class share of the head money was worth £6 3s 6d; a sixth-class share was worth 5s 5¼d.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=17283|startpage=1903|date=6 September 1814}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

Some three weeks later, on 10 August, ''Paz'' was in company with the gun-vessel (and ex-Dutch schuyt) {{HMS|Patriot|1808|2}} at Hocksyl. There they captured the Danish privateer ''Blankanaise'', a sloop laden with linen, a [[lugger]] in ballast, and sundry goods.&lt;ref name=LG16463&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16463|startpage=486|date=12 March 1811}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|A first-class share of the prize money was worth £46 17s 11½d; a sixth-class share, that of an ordinary seaman, was worth £3 8s 6d.&lt;ref name=LG17283&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=17283|startpage=1901|date=6 September 1814}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} Two weeks later, ''Patriot'', ''Paz'', and the gun-vessels ''Censor'' and {{HMS|Jahde|1809|2}} captured property at Harlinger Zyl, together with a Danish privateer and a mutt in ballast.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16538|startpage=2145|date=5 November 1811}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next month, on 11 September, {{HMS|Pincher|1804|2}}, ''Patriot'', ''Paz'' and ''Jahde'' shared in the capture of vessels referred to in the prize-money announcement as ''Young Pincher'', ''Young Paz'', and ''Young Patriot''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16542|startpage=2223|date=16 November 1811}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then on 3 November  ''Paz'' and {{HMS|Blazer|1804|2}} detained the ''Twee Gebroders'' and the ''Jonge Jeltzie''.&lt;ref name=LG16463/&gt;{{refn|A first-class share of the prize money was worth £55 12s 4d; a sixth-class share was worth £3 16s 4½d.&lt;ref name=LG17283/&gt;|group=Note}}

On 26 December 1809, ''Blazer'' and ''Paz'' were serving independently blockading the river [[Ems (river)|Ems]] when ''Blazer'' captured an American vessel that was a ttempting to breach the blockade. ''Paz'' sued to share in the proceeds on two grounds: first, that the two British vessels were engaged in a joint enterprise, and second, that ''Paz'' had been in sight at the time of the capture. The court ruled that Lord George Stuart, who commanded the station at Heligoland, had sent the two British vessels out with parallel, but not joint orders. It further ruled that there was no independent evidence that ''Paz'' had been in sight. The court therefore denied the claim. The case was nevertheless important in that it helped define the meaning of blockade.&lt;ref&gt;Howard ''et al.'', (1853), pp.424-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Paz'' sailed for North America on 22 April 1811. ''Paz'' recaptured the schooner ''Martha'', J. Darley, master, on 18 July.&lt;ref name=Essex/&gt; In September 1812 ''Paz'' arrived at Halifax with a convoy and Pring transferred to the flagship of [[Admiral Herbert Sawyer]].&lt;ref name=Tucker/&gt; ''Paz'' then came under the command of Lieutenant Perry Dumaresque.&lt;ref name=Winfield/&gt;

On 4 December ''Paz'' captured the privateer schooner ''Revenge'', of 69 tons, and 27 men, under the command of John Sinclair, Jnr., master. ''Revenge'' was out of Salem and was carrying guns, ammunition and provisions for a cruise.&lt;ref name=Essex&gt;[http://www.1812privateers.org/United%20States/Halifax.htm Essex Institute (1911)]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Paz'' had captured ''Revenge'', the former ''John and George'' (of three guns and 38 men, out of Salem),&lt;ref&gt;Emmons (1853), p.182.&lt;/ref&gt; off the [[Head of Jeddore, Nova Scotia|Jeddore Ledges]]. An American account reported that a sloop of six guns had set out from Nova Scotia with 100 volunteers on board to attempt to capture ''Revenge''. A running fight of four hours ensued before the sloop gave up. Casualties on ''Revenge'' were one man killed and three wounded. The newspaper claimed that 40 to 50 men aboard the Nova Scotian vessel had been killed or wounded. The account reported that a three-masted schooner or lugger, of 17 guns, then came out and that it was that vessel that captured ''Revenge''.&lt;ref&gt;''Niles Weekly Register'', Vol. 5, p. 202.[http://www.1812privateers.org/United%20States/REVENGE/index.htm] - accessed 23 December 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Halifax, two successful privateers, Thomas Freeman and Snow Parker, bought ''Revenge'' at Halifax for £530 and renamed her ''Retaliation''. She was armed with two 4-pounder guns and a long 12-pounder gun on a pivot; to these her new owners added two 12-pounder carronades. ''Retaliation'' went on to have a successful career preying on American shipping.&lt;ref&gt;Harris and MacPhie (2005), pp.65-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 1813, ''Paz'' was part of a squadron under the command of Admiral Sir [[Sir John Beresford, 1st Baronet|John Poo Beresford]] in {{HMS|Poictiers|1809|2}}, which was blockading the [[Delaware River]]. The squadron also included {{HMS|Belvidera|1809|2}} and two sloops. On 16 March, Beresford sent a demand to [[Lewes, Delaware|Lewistown]], for the Americans to provide his vessels with twenty live bullocks, in return for payment, or face bombardment. The governor of Delaware played for time as he moved in troops to resist a landing.&lt;ref name=Marine&gt;Marine (1901), Vol. 33, pp.3-47.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 March ''Paz'' captured the 10-gun schooner ''Pennsylvania'', out of [[Cape May, New Jersey]]. The Royal Navy kept ''Pennsylvania'' for use as a tender.&lt;ref name=LG16771&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16771|startpage=1769|endpage=1770|date=7 September 1813}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 11 April, ''Pennsylvania'' captured ''Pilgrim'', which was sailing to Boston. The British took out her cargo and proceeded to use ''Pilgrim'' too as a tender.&lt;ref name=LG16771/&gt; ''Paz'' was part of a squadron of 12 ships that shared in the capture on 13 and 14 March of ''Christina'' and ''Massatoit''.{{refn|! first-class share was worth £37 3d; a sixth-class share was worth 5s 5d.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=17369|startpage=1079|date=13 June 1818}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} 

Dumaresque and ''Paz'' also captured ''Montesquieu'',&lt;ref&gt;Burke (1891), p.329.&lt;/ref&gt; which occurred on 27 March 1813. She belonged to the Philadelphia banker [[Stephen Girard]] and was bringing a valuable cargo of tea, [[nankeen]], silk, copper, and cassia (Chinese cinnamon - [[Cinnamomum cassia]]),&lt;ref name=LG16771/&gt; from Canton. Dumaresque put the entire crew of ''Montesquiue'' and their baggage into the ship's [[pinnace (ship's boat)|pinnace]], except for the ship's supercargo, Arthur Grelaud, and the ship's steward. The captain and crew arrived safely in [[Lewes, Delaware|Lewis Town]] that same day and the captain immediately sent a letter to Girard. Beresford arrived on the scene in ''Poictiers''. Beresford took ''Montesqieu'' into the Delaware River and immediately entered into negotiations with Girard's agents instead of sending the vessel to be condemned at the [[Vice admiralty court]] in [[City of Halifax|Halifax]]. Girard, with the authorization of the American authorities, paid 180,000 Spanish milled dollars ransom for his vessel, an amount that Grelaud had negotiated. Girard applied to the US authorities for permission to pay the ransom, which he received.&lt;ref name=McMaster&gt;McMaster (2006), pp.214-20.&lt;/ref&gt; (Girard's Bank was a principal source of government credit during the [[War of 1812]].) Dumaresque, and his descendents, blamed Beresford for having deprived them of the prize.&lt;ref&gt;Dictionary of Canadian Biography Online - Perry Dumaresque. (Accessed 21 December 2012).[http://www.biographi.ca/EN/009004-119.01-e.php?&amp;id_nbr=3361]&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Newspapers had put the value of ''Montesquieu{{'}}''s cargo at $1.5 million. Girard stated that the value was $164,744.20. Girard was also unimpressed with the lack or resistance by John Wilson, the captain of ''Montesquieu'', as Girard felt that his crew, though outnumbered, and his vessel, though somewhat outgunned, were still capable of having put up a fight.&lt;ref name=McMaster/&gt;|group=Note}} ''Paz'' shared the ransom with ''Belvidera'' and ''Poictiers''.{{refn|A first-class share of the ransom was worth [[£sd|£]]1704 9[[shilling|s]] 5[[pence|d]]; a sixth-class share was worth £7 14s 10d.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16969|date=27 December 1814|startpage=2537|endpage=2538}}&lt;/ref&gt; For an ordinary seaman, the amount was worth about four to five months' pay. For a captain, the first-class share was worth more than four or five years' pay. This payment represented money reserved to answer ''Paz{{'}}''s claims before the Vice admiralty court at Halifax.|group=Note}}

This business having been completed around the end of March, on 6 and 7 April, the British squadron, including ''Paz'',  bombarded Lewes (Lewistown), the Americans having declined to deliver the bullocks that Beresford had requested. The British fired some 400 shot, but with little or no effect and no infliction of any casualties, and then withdrew.&lt;ref name=Marine/&gt;

Then on 10 May ''Paz'' captured the sloop ''Juliet'', of 92 tons, which was sailing from Cuba to [[Newport, Rhode Island]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16837|startpage=20|date=1 January 1814}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under her master, C. Southworth, ''Juliet'' was carrying 113 [[hogsheads]] and 19 [[English wine cask units#Tierce|tierces]] of molasses.&lt;ref name=Essex/&gt; ''Paz{{'}}''s war on commerce continued with the capture on 13 September of the schooner ''Richard D. Stanley'', of 115 tons, sailing to Boston with a cargo of 506 barrels of tar, 170 of pitch, 69 of turpentine and 100 of flour.&lt;ref name=Essex/&gt; In October, ''Paz'' captured three vessels. The first, on 4 October, was the 95-ton sloop ''Charles'', of Ocracocke, J. Cook, master, which was carrying 679 barrels of flour to St. Johns, New Brunswick.&lt;ref name=Essex/&gt; The second, on 14 October, was the schooner ''Randolph'', W. Clarke, master.&lt;ref name=Essex/&gt; The third, on 27 October, was the schooner ''William'', S. Nevis, master, which was carrying provisions from New York to Charlestown.&lt;ref name=Essex/&gt;

==Fate==
''Paz'' was paid off in October 1814. She was sold in 1816, but her name was not deleted from the Navy List until 7 February 1817.&lt;ref name=Winfield&gt;Winfield (2008), pp.366-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
;Notes
{{reflist|group=Note}}
;Citations
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*Burke, Sir Bernard (1891) ''A Genealogical and Heraldic History of the Colonial Gentry ...''. (Harrison).
*Emmons, George Foster Emmons (1853) ''The navy of the United States, from the commencement, 1775 to 1853; with a brief history of each vessel’s service and fate ... Comp. by Lieut. George F. Emmons ... under the authority of the Navy Dept. To which is added a list of private armed vessels, fitted out under the American flag ... also a list of the revenue and coast survey vessels, and principal ocean steamers, belonging to citizens of the United States in 1850.'' ( Washington: Gideon &amp; Co.) Available at website &quot;1812 Privateers&quot; accessed 22 December 2012.[http://www.1812privateers.org]
*Harris, Graham, and Les MacPhie (2005) ''Oak Island and Its Lost Treasure: Third Edition''. (Formac Publishing Company). ISBN 0887806724
*Marine, William M. (1901) &quot;The Bombardment of Lewes by the British, April 6 and 7, 1813&quot;. ''Papers of the Historical Society of Dleaware'', Vol. 33. (Historical Society of Delaware: Wilmington).
*Howard, Jacob Merritt, George Minot, Christopher Robinson, Thomas Edwards, Sir James Marriott, Sir George Hay, Jerome William Knapp, Edmund F Moore, John Dodson, Thomas Harman Acton, John Haggard, William Robinson (1853) ''English Admiralty Reports: Reports of cases argued and determined in the High court of admiralty, commencing with the judgments of the Right Hon. Sir William Scott, Trinity term, 1811[-1822] By John Dodson''. (Little, Brown).
*McMaster, John Bach (2006) ''The Life and Times of Stephen Girard V2: Mariner and Merchant''. (Kessinger Publishing). ISBN 978-1428637542
*Tucker, Spencer, James R. Arnold, Roberta Wiener, Paul G. Pierpaoli, Jr., John C. Fredriksen (2012) ''Encyclopedia of the War of 1812: A Political, Social, and Military History''. (ABC-CLIO). ISBN 978-1851099566
*{{cite book |first=Rif|last=Winfield|title=British Warships in the Age of Sail 1793&amp;ndash;1817: Design, Construction, Careers and Fates|publisher=Seaforth|year=2008|isbn=1861762461}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Paz (1807)}}
[[Category:Captured ships]]
[[Category:Schooners of the Royal Navy]]
[[Category:1804 ships]]</text>
      <sha1>gjiicwwkuxffoa9hulf5ewlq3lkgycg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
