<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Kitos War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1956203</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746004104</id>
      <parentid>745807192</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T18:13:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Greyshark09</username>
        <id>12404882</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Egypt */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15821">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Kitos War
or
Second Judean-Roman War
|partof=the [[Jewish–Roman wars]]
|image=[[File:Roman Empire Map.png|280px]]
|caption=The Roman Empire after 120 CE
|date=115–117
|place=[[Eastern Mediterranean]], [[Roman Empire]]
|casus= 
|territory=[[Status quo ante bellum]]
|result=Roman Empire victory
|combatant1={{flag|Roman Empire}}
|combatant2=[[Jews|Jewish]]/[[Judea]]n [[Zealots (Judea)|zealots]]
|commander1={{flagicon|Roman Empire}} Emperor Trajan&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon|Roman Empire}} [[Marcius Turbo]]&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon|Roman Empire}} [[Lusius Quietus]]
|commander2=[[Lukuas]] (Andreas);&lt;br/&gt; Artemio;&lt;br/&gt;Julian and Pappus
|casualties1=Massive civilian casualties with some areas utterly annihilated, 460,000+ Roman citizens (largely [[Roman Greece|Roman Greeks]]) killed in Cyrene and Cyprus alone and unknown numbers in [[Roman Egypt|Aegyptus]], [[Ancient Libya|Libya]] and the rest of the [[Eastern Mediterranean]]
|casualties2=Jewish communities of Cyprus, Cyrene and possibly others completely depopulated and permanently expelled to the eastern edges of the Empire (mainly [[Judea (Roman province)|Judea]])
|strength1=
|strength2=
}}
{{Campaignbox Jewish-Roman wars}}

The '''Kitos War''' (115–117) ({{lang-he|מרד הגלויות}}: ''mered ha'galuyot'' or ''mered ha'tfutzot'' (מרד התפוצות); translation: rebellion of the diaspora. {{lang-la|Tumultus Iudaicus}}) occurred during the period of the [[Jewish–Roman wars]], 66–136. While the majority of the [[Roman armies]] were fighting [[Roman–Parthian Wars#Trajan.27s Parthian War|Trajan's Parthian War]] on the eastern border of the [[Roman Empire]], major uprisings by ethnic [[Judeans]] in [[Creta et Cyrenaica|Cyrenaica]], [[Roman Cyprus|Cyprus]] and [[Egypt (Roman province)|Egypt]] spiraled out of control, resulting in a widespread slaughter of left behind Roman garrisons and Roman citizens by Jewish rebels. Some of the areas with the heaviest massacres were left so utterly annihilated that others were made to settle these areas to prevent the absence of any remaining presence. The rebellions were finally crushed by [[Roman legion]]ary forces, chiefly by the Roman general [[Lusius Quietus]], whose [[Roman naming conventions|nomen]] later gave the conflict its title, as &quot;Kitos&quot; is a later corruption of Quietus.

==Background==
{{main article|First Jewish-Roman War}}
Tension between the [[Anti-Judaism#In the pre-Christian Roman Empire|Jewish population of the Roman Empire and the Greek and Roman populations]] mounted over the course of the 1st century CE, gradually escalating with various violent events, mainly throughout [[Judea (Roman province)|Judea]] (Iudaea), where parts of the Judean population occasionally erupted into violent insurrections against the [[Roman Empire]]. Several incidents also occurred in other parts of the Roman Empire, most notable the [[Alexandria pogroms]], targeting the large [[History of the Jews in Egypt|Jewish community of Alexandria]] in the province of Egypt.

The escalation of tensions finally erupted as the [[Great Revolt of Judea]], which began in the year 66 CE. It erupted initially due to Greek and Jewish religious tensions, but later escalated due to [[tax resistance|anti-taxation protests]] and attacks upon Roman citizens.&lt;ref&gt;Josephus, ''War of the Jews'' II.8.11, II.13.7, II.14.4, II.14.5&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman military garrison of Judaea was quickly overrun by rebels and the pro-Roman king [[Agrippa II]] fled [[Jerusalem]], together with Roman officials to [[Galilee]]. [[Cestius Gallus]], the [[legatus|legate]] of [[Syria (Roman province)|Syria]], brought the Syrian army, based on [[Legio XII Fulminata|XII Fulminata]], reinforced by auxiliary troops, to restore order and quell the revolt. The legion, however, was ambushed and defeated by Jewish rebels at the [[Battle of Beth Horon (66)|Battle of Beth Horon]], a result that shocked the Roman leadership.

The Roman command of the revolt's suppression was then handed to general [[Vespasian]] and his son [[Titus]], who assembled four legions and began advancing through the country, starting with Galilee, in the year 67 CE. The revolt ended when [[Roman legion|legions]] under Titus [[Destruction of Jerusalem|besieged and destroyed]] the center of rebel resistance in Jerusalem in the year 70 CE, and defeated the remaining Jewish strongholds later on.

==Revolt and warfare==
In 115, the emperor [[Trajan]] was in command of the eastern campaign against the [[Parthian Empire]]. The Roman invasion had been prompted by the imposition of a pro-Parthian king on the [[Kingdom of Armenia (antiquity)|throne of Armenia]] after a Parthian invasion of that land.
This encroachment on the traditional sphere of influence of the Roman Empire — the two empires had shared [[hegemony]] over Armenia since the time of Nero some 50 years earlier — could only lead to war.

As Trajan's army advanced victoriously through Mesopotamia, Jewish rebels in its rear began attacking the small garrisons left behind. A revolt in far off [[Cyrenaica]] soon spread to Egypt and then Cyprus, inciting revolt in [[Judaea (Roman province)|Judaea]]. A widespread uprising centered at [[Lod|Lydda]] threatened grain supplies from Egypt to the front. The Jewish insurrection swiftly spread to the recently conquered provinces. Cities with substantial Jewish populations – [[Nisibis]], [[Edessa, Mesopotamia|Edessa]], [[Seleucia]], [[Arbel]]a – joined the rebellion and slaughtered their small Roman garrisons.

===Cyrenaica===
In Cyrenaica, the rebels were led by one [[Lukuas]] or Andreas, who called himself &quot;king&quot; (according to [[Eusebius of Caesarea]]). His group destroyed many temples, including those to [[Hecate]], [[Jupiter (mythology)|Jupiter]], [[Apollo]], [[Artemis]], and [[Isis]], as well as the civil structures that were symbols of Rome, including the [[Caesareum]], the [[basilica]], and the [[thermae|public baths]].

The 4th century Christian historian [[Paulus Orosius]] records that the violence so depopulated the province of Cyrenaica that new colonies had to be established by Hadrian:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The Jews ... waged war on the inhabitants throughout Libya in the most savage fashion, and to such an extent was the country wasted that, its cultivators having been slain, its land would have remained utterly depopulated, had not the Emperor Hadrian gathered settlers from other places and sent them thither, for the inhabitants had been wiped out.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;orosius&quot;&gt;Orosius, Seven Books of History Against the Pagans, 7.12.6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Dio Cassius]] states of Jewish insurrectionaries: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;'Meanwhile the Jews in the region of Cyrene had put one Andreas at their head and were destroying both the Romans and the Greeks. They would cook their flesh, make belts for themselves of their entrails, anoint themselves with their blood, and wear their skins for clothing. Many they sawed in two, from the head downwards. Others they would give to wild beasts and force still others to fight as gladiators. In all, consequently, two hundred and twenty thousand perished. In Egypt, also, they performed many similar deeds, and in Cyprus under the leadership of Artemio. There, likewise, two hundred and forty thousand perished. For this reason no Jew may set foot in that land, but even if one of them is driven upon the island by force of the wind, he is put to death. Various persons took part in subduing these Jews, one being Lusius, who was sent by Trajan.&quot;&lt;ref name=diosrome&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/10890/10890-h/10890-h.htm#a68_32
|title=Dio's Rome, Volume V., Book 68, paragraph 32}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The original 1906 [[Jewish Encyclopedia]] cited this about the Cyrene massacres: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;By this outbreak [[Libya]] was depopulated to such an extent that a few years later new colonies had to be established there (Eusebius, &quot;Chronicle&quot; from the Armenian, fourteenth year of Hadrian). Bishop [[Synesius]], a native of Cyrene in the beginning of the fifth century, speaks of the devastations wrought by the Jews (&quot;Do Regno,&quot; p.&amp;nbsp;2).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishencyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/4826-cyrene |title=Cyrene |publisher=JewishEncyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[Jewish Encyclopedia]] acknowledges Dio Cassius's importance as a source, though believes his accounts of the actions at Cyrene and on Cyprus may have been embellished: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;For an account of the Jewish war under Trajan and Hadrian Dion is the most important source (lxviii. 32, lxix. 12–14), though his descriptions of the cruelties perpetrated by the Jews at Cyrene and on the island of Cyprus are probably exaggerated.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishencylopediacassius&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/5212-dion-cassius |title=Dion Cassius |publisher=JewishEncyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Egypt===
Then [[Lukuas]], leader of rebel Jews, moved towards [[Alexandria]], entered the city, which had been abandoned by the Roman troops in Egypt under the leadership of governor [[Marcus Rutilius Lupus]], and set fire to the city. The Egyptian temples and the tomb of [[Pompey]] were destroyed. A 116 CE battle at [[Hermopolis]] was reportedly also prevailed by Jewish rebels, as indicated in a papirus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seder-olam.info/seder-olam-g33-bar-kochba.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Trajan sent new troops under the ''praefectus praetorio'' [[Quintus Marcius Turbo]], but Egypt and Cyrenaica were pacified only in autumn 117.

===Cyprus===
In [[Cyprus]] a Jewish band under a leader named [[Artemion]] took control of the island, killing tens of thousands of Cypriot Greek civilians. The Cypriot Jews participated in the great uprising against the Romans under [[Trajan]] (117), and massacred 240,000 Greeks.&lt;ref name=diosrome/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/4825-cyprus |title=Cyprus |publisher=JewishEncyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Roman army was dispatched to the island, soon reconquering the capital. After the revolt had been fully defeated, laws were created forbidding any Jews to live on the island.

===Mesopotamia===
A new revolt sprang up in [[Mesopotamia]], while [[Trajan]] was in the [[Persian Gulf]]. Trajan reconquered ''[[Nisibis]]'' (Nusaybin in Turkey), the capital of [[Osroene]] ''[[Edessa, Mesopotamia|Edessa]]'', and ''[[Seleucia on the Tigris]]'' (Iraq), each of which housed large Jewish communities.

A pro-Roman son of the Parthian king [[Osroes I of Parthia|Osroes I]], named [[Parthamaspates of Parthia|Parthamaspatas]], had been brought on the expedition as part of the emperor's entourage. Trajan had him crowned in Ctesiphon as king of the Parthians. &quot;Trajan, fearing that the Parthians, too, might begin a revolt, desired to give them a king of their own. Accordingly, when he came to Ctesiphon, he called together in a great plain all the Romans and likewise all the Parthians that were there at the time; then he mounted a lofty platform, and after describing in grandiloquent language what he had accomplished, he appointed Parthamaspates king over the Parthians and set the diadem upon his head.&quot; (Dio Cassius). With this done, Trajan moved north to take personal command of the ongoing siege of [[Hatra]].

The siege continued throughout the summer of 117, but the years of constant campaigning in the baking eastern heat had taken their toll on Trajan, who suffered a heatstroke. He decided to begin the long journey back to Rome in order to recover. Sailing from Seleucia, the emperor's health deteriorated rapidly. He was taken ashore at Selinus in Cilicia, where he died, and his successor, [[Hadrian]], assumed the reins of government in 118.

===Judaea===
{{see also|Judea (Roman province)}}
Jewish leader [[Lukuas]] fled to Judea.&lt;ref&gt;Abulfaraj, in Münter, &quot;Der Jüdische Krieg,&quot; p. 18, Altona and Leipsic, 1821&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marcius Turbo]] pursued him and sentenced to death the brothers Julian and Pappus, who had been key leaders in the rebellion. Lusius Quietus, the conqueror of the Jews of Mesopotamia, was now in command of the Roman army in Judaea, and laid siege to [[Lod|Lydda]], where the rebel Jews had gathered under the leadership of Julian and Pappus. The distress became so great that the patriarch Rabban [[Gamaliel II]], who was shut up there and died soon afterwards, permitted fasting even on Ḥanukkah. Other rabbis condemned this measure.&lt;ref&gt;Ta'anit ii. 10; Yer. Ta'anit ii. 66a; Yer. Meg. i. 70d; R. H. 18b&lt;/ref&gt; Lydda was next taken and many of the rebellious Jews were executed; the &quot;slain of Lydda&quot; are often mentioned in words of reverential praise in the Talmud.&lt;ref&gt;Pes. 50a; B. B. 10b; Eccl. R. ix. 10&lt;/ref&gt; Rebel leaders Pappus and Julian were among those executed by the Romans in the same year.&lt;ref&gt;Ta'anit 18b; Yer. Ta'anit 66b&lt;/ref&gt;

Lusius Quietus, whom the Emperor Trajan had held in high regard and who had served Rome so well, was quietly stripped of his command once Hadrian had secured the Imperial title. He was murdered in unknown circumstances in the summer of 118, possibly by the orders of Hadrian.

Hadrian took the unpopular, but far-sighted, decision to end the war, abandoning much of Trajan's eastern conquests and stabilising the eastern borders. Although he abandoned the erstwhile province of Mesopotamia, he installed Parthamaspates – who had been ejected from Ctesiphon by the returning Osroes – as king of a restored [[Osroene]]. For a century Osroene would retain a precarious independence as a buffer state, sandwiched between the two empires.

The situation in Judaea remained tense for the Romans, who were obliged under Hadrian to permanently move the [[Legio VI Ferrata|Legio VI ''Ferrata'']] into [[Caesarea Maritima]] in Judaea.

==Aftermath==
{{main article|Bar Kokhba revolt}}
Further developments occurred in Judaea Province in the year 130, when Emperor Hadrian visited the Eastern Mediterranean and, according to Cassius Dio, made the decision to rebuild the city of Jerusalem as the Roman city of [[Aelia Capitolina]], derived from his own name. The decision, together with Hadrian's other sanctions against the Jews, was allegedly one of the reasons for the eruption of the 132 [[Bar Kokhba revolt]] — an extremely violent uprising. The rebellion ended with the deaths of the majority of the Judaean population and a ban upon the Jewish faith across the Roman Empire, which was lifted in 138, upon Hadrian's death.

== See also ==
*[[List of conflicts in the Near East]]
*[[Samaritan Revolts]]
*[[Jewish revolt against Heraclius]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading and external links ==
*&quot;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=237&amp;letter=B &lt;small&gt;BAR KOKBA AND BAR KOKBA WAR&lt;/small&gt;]&quot; article from [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/index.jsp Jewish Encyclopedia] (public domain)
*&quot;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=948&amp;letter=C&amp;search=egypt%20roman &lt;small&gt;Cyprus: In Roman Times&lt;/small&gt;]&quot; article from [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/index.jsp Jewish Encyclopedia] (public domain)
*&quot;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=948&amp;letter=C&amp;search=egypt%20roman &lt;small&gt;Cyrene&lt;/small&gt;]&quot; article from [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/index.jsp Jewish Encyclopedia] (public domain)
* &quot;[http://www.livius.org/ja-jn/jewish_wars/jwar06.html The revolt against Trajan]&quot;, from [http://livius.org livius.org]
*[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf201.iii.ix.ii.html Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers], [[Eusebius]], ''[[Church History (Eusebius)|Ecclesiastical History]]'', 4.2.

[[Category:2nd-century conflicts]]
[[Category:2nd-century Judaism]]
[[Category:115 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:116 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:117 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:Jewish–Roman wars]]</text>
      <sha1>bh5ta8oa4ay9t04wtrofslibhssbiwj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
