<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Kurt Chew-Een Lee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33654794</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743707592</id>
      <parentid>741543176</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-10T20:24:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category People from San Francisco, California to [[:Category:People from San Francisco]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2016 September 6]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23625">{{Infobox military person
|name = Kurt Chew-Een Lee
|birth_date = January 21, 1926
|death_date = {{Death date and age|2014|3|3|1926|1|21}}
|birth_place = [[San Francisco, California]]
|death_place = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|placeofburial =
|placeofburial_label = Place of burial
|image = File:Kurt Chew-Een Lee - 2010.jpg
|caption = Kurt Chew-Een Lee in 2010
|nickname = Kurt
|allegiance = {{Flag|United States of America}}
|branch = {{Flag|United States Marine Corps}}
|serviceyears = 1944–1968
|rank = [[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|23px]] [[Major]]
|commands = Machine-Gun Platoon of Baker Company, [[1st Battalion 7th Marines]], [[1st Marine Division]] (Reinforced)
|unit =
|battles = [[Korean War]]
* [[Battle of Inchon]]
* [[Battle of Chosin Reservoir]]
|awards = [[Navy Cross (United States)|Navy Cross]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Silver Star]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Legion of Merit]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Purple Heart]] (2)
|laterwork =
}}
[[File:Cheweenlee1.jpg|thumb|Kurt Chew-Een Lee as a marine lieutenant in Korea.]]

Major '''Kurt Chew-Een Lee''' ({{zh |first = t |t = 呂超然 |s = 吕超然 |p = Lǚ Chāorán}} (January 21, 1926 – March 3, 2014) was the first [[U.S. Marine Corps]] officer of Chinese descent. Lee earned the [[Navy Cross (United States)|Navy Cross]] under fire in Korea in September 1950, serving in the [[1st Battalion 7th Marines]].

Lee and his younger brothers Chew-Fan Lee and [[Chew-Mon Lee]] all earned bravery medals in the [[Korean War]].

== Early life ==
Chew-Een Lee was born in 1926 in [[San Francisco]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://lcweb2.loc.gov/diglib/vhp/bib/80441 |title = Kurt Lee Collection |work=Veterans History Project |publisher = Library of Congress |accessdate = November 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and grew up in [[Sacramento, California]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url = http://www.asianweek.com/2011/02/01/chinese-american-hero-major-kurt-chew-een-lee/ |title = Chinese American Hero: Major Kurt Chew-Een Lee |last = Robison |first = Michael |date = February 1, 2011 |work=AsianWeek}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lee's father was M. Young Lee, born in [[Guangzhou]] (Canton), emigrating in the 1920s to the [[Territory of Hawaii]] and then [[California]]. Once established in America, M. Young Lee returned to China to honor an [[arranged marriage]].&lt;ref&gt;Drury, 2009, p. 254&lt;/ref&gt; He brought his bride to California and worked as a distributor of farm produce to hotels and restaurants. Lee's brother Chew-Fan Lee was born in 1927 in Sacramento.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury256&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=TOftPVDRtIcC&amp;pg=PA256 |pages = 256–257 |title = The Last Stand of Fox Company: A True Story of U.S. Marines in Combat |last1 = Drury |first1 = Bob |last2 = Clavin |first2 = Tom |last3 = Drury |first3 = Tom |publisher = Grove Press |year = 2009 |ISBN = 0-8021-4451-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1928, a third son was born to the family: [[Chew-Mon Lee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury256&quot; /&gt; The Lee family included three daughters: Faustina, Betty and Juliet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title = Part Two: The One Week Visit of American Military Hero – Major Kurt Chew-Een Lee |url = http://www.chineseamericanveterans.org/newsletter/2011/042011-newsletter.pdf |work = Cathay Chronicle |publisher = American Legion, Cathay Post No. 384 |volume = 2 |number = 4 |date = April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Military career ==

=== World War II ===
At the time of the [[Attack on Pearl Harbor]], Chew-Een Lee was a high school student going by the nickname &quot;Kurt&quot;, associated with the [[Junior Reserve Officers' Training Corps]] (Junior ROTC). In 1944 when he was an 18-year-old student of mining engineering, Lee joined the [[U.S. Marine Corps]] (USMC).&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; Small for a recruit, Lee was about {{convert|5|ft|6|in}} tall, and around {{convert|130|lb}}, but he was wiry and muscular.&lt;ref&gt;Drury, 2009, p. 255&lt;/ref&gt; At the [[Marine Corps Recruit Depot San Diego]], Lee was assigned the task of learning the [[Japanese language]]. At graduation, he was retained as the language class instructor, a decision that disappointed Lee because he wanted to ship out and fight in the war. He earned the rank of [[sergeant]] and had just been accepted to officer training class when [[World War II]] ended.

From October 1945 to April 1946, Lee was enrolled in [[The Basic School]], newly reactivated for USMC officer training. Second Lieutenant Lee graduated to become the first non-white officer and the first Asian-American officer in the Marine Corps.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; He deployed to Guam and China to interrogate Japanese prisoners of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury256&quot; /&gt;

=== Korean War ===
At the start of the [[Korean War]], First Lieutenant Lee was in command of the 1st Platoon, [[Company (military unit)|Company]] B, [[1st Battalion 7th Marines|1st Battalion]], [[7th Marine Regiment (United States)|7th Marine Regiment]] training at [[Camp Pendleton]] under Colonel [[Homer Litzenberg]]. Soon, his unit received notice that it would ship out for the war zone at the beginning of September. Lee wanted to set a strong example of a fighting Chinese American. He said he &quot;wanted to dispel the notion about the Chinese being weak, meek, and obsequious.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LATimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://articles.latimes.com/2010/may/31/entertainment/la-et-chosin-20100531 |title = A tale of Korean War heroism: U.S. Marine Chew-Een Lee's bravery at the battle of the Chosin Reservoir is a focus of Smithsonian Channel documentary. |last = Perry |first = Tony |date = May 31, 2010 |work = Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; He did not expect to survive the war, and intended his death to &quot;be honorable, be spectacular&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;

Lee's brother Chew-Mon Lee had by this time joined the [[U.S. Army]] and was also training for Korea. Lee described the difficulty of leaving home as the family's first-born son: {{blockquote|I came from a family of limited means. My father, whose Chinese name was Brilliant Scholar, distributed fruit and vegetables to restaurants and hotels in Sacramento. He stayed home from work that morning, and my mother, whose Chinese name was Gold Jade, made a special meal. There was an awkward moment when the clock on the wall said it was time to depart. My mother was very brave. She said nothing. My father had been reading the Chinese newspaper, or pretending to. He was a tough guy, my father, and I admired his toughness. He rose from his chair and shook my hand abruptly. He tried to talk, but couldn't, and that's when my mother broke down.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title = Breakout: The Chosin Reservoir Campaign, Korea 1950 |last = Russ |first = Martin |page = 9 |publisher = Penguin Books |year = 2000 |ISBN = 0-14-029259-4 |edition = 2}} Sample text hosted by [http://www.nytimes.com/books/first/r/russ-breakout.html ''The New York Times''].&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==== Battle of Inchon ====
Lee's unit shipped out on September 1, 1950. For two weeks he drilled his men day and night on the deck of the ship, enduring derision from the other platoon leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury252&quot;&gt;Drury, 2009, pp. 252–253&lt;/ref&gt; After arriving in Japan for final battle preparations, Lee's superiors tried to reassign him as staff officer handling translation duties. Lee insisted that he was only there to &quot;fight communists&quot;, and was allowed to retain command of his platoon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury256&quot; /&gt;

The [[1st Battalion 7th Marines]], including Lee, landed at [[Inchon]] on September 21, 1950, to attack the [[North Korea]]ns and force them to retreat northwards. The [[People's Republic of China]] sent troops to stiffen the North Korean fighting response. On the night of November 2–3 in the Sudong Gorge, Lee's unit was attacked by Chinese forces. Lee kept his men focused by directing them to shoot at the enemy's [[muzzle flash]]es. Following this, Lee single-handedly advanced upon the enemy front and attacked their positions one by one to draw their fire and reveal themselves. His men fired at the muzzle flashes and inflicted casualties, forcing the enemy to retreat. While advancing, Lee shouted to the enemy in [[Mandarin Chinese]] to sow confusion and then attacked with [[hand grenade]]s and gunfire. Lee was wounded in the knee and in the morning light was shot in the right elbow by a sniper, shattering the bones. He was evacuated to a [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital|MASH unit]] (an army field hospital) outside of [[Hamhung]]. For bravely attacking the enemy and saving his men, Lee was awarded the [[Navy Cross (United States)|Navy Cross]], the second highest honor given for combat bravery.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.legionofvalor.com/citation_parse.php?uid=994696107 |title = Navy Cross Commendation for Kurt C. E. Lee, U.S.M.C. |publisher = Legion of Valor |accessdate = November 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lee was under hospital care for five days when he learned he was to be sent to Japan for recuperation. Unauthorized, he and another wounded marine took an army jeep and drove it back to his unit, walking the last {{convert|10|mi}} when the jeep ran out of gas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury252&quot; /&gt; He was assigned to command the 2nd Rifle Platoon whose officer had been wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; Lee exercised his platoon in combat maneuvers while his arm was in a sling.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; This extra training helped his platoon take a leading role in heavy fighting a month later.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;

Some time in mid-November 1950, Lee met up with his brother U.S. Army First Lieutenant Chew-Mon Lee at a Marine field headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury256&quot; /&gt; Both men had been wounded and were resting up before further battle. The ''[[Sacramento Bee]]'' published a photograph and a brief report of the meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arcadia&quot; /&gt; Chew-Mon Lee addressed his brother respectfully as ''daigo'', meaning &quot;elder brother&quot;, and gave him a gift of army-issue 30-round &quot;banana&quot;  [[Magazine (firearms)|magazines]] which could be taped together to make quicker reloads without the needs of going for one's ammo pouch. This was regarded as superior to the USMC regulation 15-round clips then in service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=RKncgh1mbioC&amp;pg=PA86 |title = Colder Than Hell: A Marine Rifle Company at Chosin Reservoir |last = Owen |first = Joseph R. |page=86 |publisher = Naval Institute Press |year = 2000 |ISBN = 1-55750-416-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; A week or two later, on November 30, 1950, Chew-Mon Lee performed heroically in battle, earning the [[Distinguished Service Cross (United States)|Distinguished Service Cross]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DSC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/chew-mon-lee.htm |title = Distinguished Service Cross Citation for Chew-Mon Lee |publisher = Arlington National Cemetery |accessdate = November 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Battle of Chosin Reservoir ====
[[File:Marines engage during the Korean War.jpg|thumb|left|U.S. Marines battling uphill through rocks and snow at [[Chosin Reservoir]]]]

Late on December 2 after several days of exhausting combat during the [[Battle of Chosin Reservoir]], Lee's platoon was given the task of spearheading a 500-man thrust against the Chinese forces in an effort to relieve the outnumbered Fox Company of [[2nd Battalion 7th Marines]] trapped on Fox Hill, part of Toktong Pass and strategic to controlling the Chosin Reservoir road. Lee's relief force was given heavier loads to carry through the snow, up and down lightly wooded hills, through extreme cold (−20&amp;nbsp;°F, −29&amp;nbsp;°C), and under the very limited visibility of snow blizzard and darkness. Lieutenant Colonel [[Ray Davis (general)|Ray Davis]], commanding officer of 1st Battalion, had no instructions for Lieutenant Lee on how to accomplish the mission except to stay off the roads with their heavily reinforced roadblocks. As [[Take point|point man]] of 2nd Rifle Platoon in Baker Company, Lee used only his compass to guide his way, leading 1st Battalion in single file.&lt;ref&gt;Drury, 2009, p. 262&lt;/ref&gt; Suddenly [[pinned down]] by heavy enemy fire coming from a rocky hill, Lee refused to be delayed in his mission. He directed the men to attack the hill with &quot;[[marching fire]]&quot;, a stratagem used by General [[George S. Patton]] in which troops continue to advance as they apply just enough [[suppressive fire]] to keep the enemy's heads down. Upon reaching the rocky hill, Lee and the battalion [[Charge (warfare)|charged]], attacking enemy soldiers in their foxholes. Lee, with his right arm still in a cast, shot two enemy soldiers on his way to the top. When he reached the top, he noticed that the other side of the hill was covered with enemy foxholes facing the other way in expectation of an attack from the road, but the foxholes were now empty and the enemy soldiers were over {{convert|400|yd}} away in rout because of the fearfully sudden 1st Battalion attack from their rear.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;

Following this success, communication was established with nearby Fox Company on Fox Hill. 1st Battalion directed mortar fire against the enemy and called in an airstrike, then Lee led Baker Company forward in an attack which forced a path to Fox Company. During this attack Lee took a bullet to the upper part of his right arm, above the cast on his elbow.&lt;ref&gt;Drury, 2009, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt; Regrouping his men, Lee led Baker Company in more firefights against pockets of enemy soldiers in the Toktong Pass area, securing the road. On December 8, 1950, a Chinese machine gunner targeted Lee, wounding him seriously enough to end his Korean War service.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; Lieutenant Colonel Davis received the [[Medal of Honor]] for commanding the relief of Fox Company. Lee was awarded the [[Silver Star]].

Throughout Lee's time in Korea, his brother Chew-Fan Lee was a student at the [[University of California, San Francisco]], School of Pharmacy. Upon graduating in 1951, Chew-Fan Lee joined the [[Medical Service Corps (United States Army)]] at the rank of lieutenant, despite being a [[pacifist]]. In Korea, he performed bravely in action and was awarded the [[Bronze Star Medal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury256&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Arcadia&quot; /&gt;

=== Vietnam War ===
Lee served at The Basic School from 1962 to 1965, beginning as commanding officer of the Enlisted Instructor Company at the rank of captain. He earned the rank of major on January 1, 1963, at which time he was made chief of the Platoon Tactics Instruction Group. In his 27 months at this position he trained future Generals [[Charles C. Krulak|Charles &quot;Chuck&quot; Krulak]] and [[John J. Sheehan|John &quot;Jack&quot; Sheehan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; Lee served overseas in Vietnam during 1965–1966 as Division Combat Intelligence Officer for [[3rd Marine Division]], [[III Marine Amphibious Force]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; He organized a division-level translation team for quickly processing foreign language documents captured by marine field units.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;

== Later life and death ==
Lee retired from military service at the rank of major in 1968&lt;ref name=&quot;LATimes&quot; /&gt; and worked a civilian job with [[New York Life Insurance Company]] for seven years. During this period, Lee's mother died in Sacramento, and Lee's brother Chew-Mon Lee died at the rank of colonel in the US Army while serving as an attache in [[Taiwan]]. His brother Chew-Fan Lee advanced in his career as hospital pharmacist. In 1975, Lee began working as a regulatory compliance coordinator for the [[National Rural Electric Cooperative Association]]; a position he held for almost two decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-22102252.html |title = The Marine who fought his own people; 'Uncommon Courage' in Korea: Documentary recalls bravery amid the horrors of battle at Chosin |last = Tucker |first = Neely |work = Washington Post |date = May 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lee was married twice, producing no children. He had a step-daughter from his second marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker&quot; /&gt; Lee retired from his civilian career, living near Washington, D.C. in [[Arlington, Virginia]].

Lee died on March 3, 2014 at the age of 88.&lt;ref&gt;http://abclocal.go.com/kgo/story?section=news/local/san_francisco&amp;id=9454838&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sacbee.com/2014/03/04/6209319/obituary-maj-kurt-chew-een-lee.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;deathcnn&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last = Park|first = Madison|title = Maj. Kurt Chew-een Lee, Asian-American Marines trailblazer dies at 88|url = http://www.cnn.com/2014/03/06/us/major-lee-marines/|accessdate = March 6, 2014|newspaper=CNN|date = March 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
The vigorous fighting spirit that Lee gave to his USMC company resulted in it being allowed to keep the name &quot;Baker Company&quot; even after the U.S. military switched in 1956 from the [[Joint Army/Navy Phonetic Alphabet]] (B for Baker) to the [[NATO phonetic alphabet]] (B for Bravo).&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt; In a 2002 speech about the Chosin Reservoir battle, General Ray Davis said that Lee was the bravest Marine he ever knew.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;

In 2000, the [[California Military Museum]] mounted an exhibit describing the bravery and military service of the three Lee brothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arcadia&quot; /&gt; Lee is a member of the [[Legion of Valor]], and represented the group in a meeting with President [[George W. Bush]] in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arcadia&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=SOXth7IZYrYC&amp;pg=PA102 |title = Sacramento's Chinatown |author = Chinese American Museum of Northern California |publisher = Arcadia Publishing |year = 2000 |pages = 95, 102–103 |ISBN = 0-7385-8066-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The story of Lee's bravery in the Korean War was the subject of a documentary produced by the [[Smithsonian Channel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.smithsonianchannel.com/site/sn/show.do?show=136060 |title = Uncommon Courage: Breakout At Chosin |publisher = Smithsonian Channel |accessdate = November 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The documentary, titled ''Uncommon Courage: Breakout at Chosin'', was broadcast on [[Memorial Day]], May 31, 2010. David Royle of the Smithsonian Channel said that the filmmakers interviewed a number of veterans who served alongside Lee, many of whom believed that &quot;he should have been awarded the Medal of Honor.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LATimes&quot; /&gt; Joe Owen was one of the marines fighting under Lee's leadership, and he told Smithsonian Channel documentarians that if it had not been for the death of Lee's company commander soon after the November 2–3 action, Lee would have been properly nominated for the [[Medal of Honor]], the highest military honor of the United States.

Lee gave his final film interview for the Korean War documentary &quot;[[Finnigan's War]]&quot;, directed by [[Conor Timmis]].

Early in his career, Lee's superior officers criticized him for his aggressive [[Chip on shoulder|chip-on-shoulder]] attitude.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drury256&quot; /&gt; Lee maintained the pugnacious stance throughout his life. Lee responded to critics by saying that the chip is &quot;my teaching tool to dispel ignorance.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AsianWeek&quot; /&gt;

== Awards ==
Lee received decorations for bravery and service in the Korean War and in Vietnam. In addition to the Navy Cross, he also received the Silver Star and the Navy Marine Corps Commendation Ribbon with &quot;V&quot; Device (for valor in combat).&lt;ref name=&quot;Awards&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a8HBeks_T4g#t=2m54s |title = YouTube: Happy 235th Birthday Marine Corps |publisher = U.S. Marine Corps}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
{|
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = award-star |ribbon = Navy_Cross_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = award-star |ribbon = Silver_Star_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 1 |type = award-star |ribbon = Purple Heart BAR.svg |width = 106}}
|-
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = oak|other_device=v |ribbon = Navy_and_Marine_Corps_Commendation_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = award-star |ribbon = Combat_Action_Ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 2 |type = award-star |ribbon = US_Navy_Presidential_Unit_Citation_Ribbon.png |width = 106}}
|-
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = Navy Unit Commendation ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = Marine_Corps_Expeditionary_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = China_Service_Medal_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
|-
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = American_Campaign_Medal_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = World_War_II_Victory_Medal_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = Army_of_Occupation_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
|-
| {{ribbon devices |number = 1 |type = service-star |ribbon = National_Defense_Service_Medal_ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 2 |type = service-star |ribbon = Korean_Service_Medal_-_Ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 2 |type = service-star |ribbon = Vietnam_Service_Ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
|-
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = United_Nations_Service_Medal_for_Korea_Ribbon.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = Vietnam_gallantry_cross_unit_award-3d.svg |width = 106}}
| {{ribbon devices |number = 0 |type = service-star |ribbon = Vietnam_Campaign_Medal_ribbon.png |width = 106}}
|-
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
! 1st Row
| [[Navy Cross (United States)|Navy Cross]]
| [[Silver Star]]
| [[Purple Heart]] w/ 1 [[award star]]
|-
! 2nd Row
| [[Navy and Marine Corps Commendation Medal]] w/ [[valor device]]
| [[Combat Action Ribbon]]
| [[Presidential Unit Citation (United States)|US Navy Presidential Unit Citation Ribbon]]
|-
! 3rd Row
| [[Navy Unit Commendation]]
| [[Marine Corps Expeditionary Medal]]
| [[China Service Medal]]
|-
! 4th Row
| [[American Campaign Medal]]
| [[World War II Victory Medal]]
| [[Navy Occupation Service Medal]]
|-
! 5th Row
| [[National Defense Service Medal]] w/ 1 [[service star]]
| [[Korean Service Medal]] with 2 bronze service stars
| [[Vietnam Service Medal]] with 2 bronze service stars
|-
! 6th Row
| [[United Nations Korea Medal|United Nations Service Medal for Korea]]
| [[Vietnam Gallantry Cross Unit Citation]]
| [[Vietnam Campaign Medal]]
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
* {{IMDb name|4352985}}
* {{cite web |url = http://www.nj.gov/military/korea/factsheets/asian.html |title = Asian Americans in the United States Military during the Korean War |work=New Jersey Korean War Memorial |publisher = New Jersey Department of Military &amp; Veterans Affairs}} Photograph of Lieutenant Lee in Korea, 1950
* {{cite web |url = http://www.sacbee.com/2014/03/04/6209319/obituary-maj-kurt-chew-een-lee.html |title = Obituary: Maj. Kurt Chew-Een Lee, 88, was Korean War hero |work=The Sacramento Bee |first1 = Robert D. |last1 = Dávila |date = March 5, 2014 |accessdate = March 5, 2014}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lee, Kurt Chew-Een}}
[[Category:American military personnel of Chinese descent]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Korean War]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:1926 births]]
[[Category:2014 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Sacramento, California]]
[[Category:People from San Francisco]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Navy Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:United States Marine Corps officers]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Star]]
[[Category:History of the United States Marine Corps]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Star Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Merit]]</text>
      <sha1>p7waro22wrizhsrgv7ax4qwk0v50ntu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
