<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lista Air Station</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14052631</id>
    <revision>
      <id>680027534</id>
      <parentid>679599949</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-09-08T07:27:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Davidcannon</username>
        <id>36171</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26210">{{Infobox airport
| name         = Lista Air Station
| nativename   = Lista flystasjon
| nativename-a =
| nativename-r =
| image        = Farsund IMG 3410 lista flyst.JPG
| image-width  = 300px
| caption      =
| IATA         = FAN
| ICAO         = ENLI
| type         = Joint (military and civilian)
| owner        = [[Royal Norwegian Air Force]]
| operator     =
| city-served  = [[Farsund]], [[Norway]]
| location     = [[Lista]], Farsund
| elevation-f  = 29
| elevation-m  = 9
| coordinates  = 
| latd =  58 | latm = 06 | lats = 01 | latNS = N
| longd= 006 | longm= 37 | longs= 30 | longEW= E
| pushpin_map            = Norway
| pushpin_label_position =
| pushpin_label          = '''FAN'''
| pushpin_map_alt        =
| pushpin_mapsize        = 300px
| pushpin_image          =
| pushpin_map_caption    =
| pushpin_relief         = yes
| website      =
| metric-elev  = yes
| metric-rwy   = yes
| r1-number    = 14/32
| r1-length-f  =
| r1-length-m  = 2990
| r1-surface   = Concrete
| r2-number    = &lt;s&gt;09/27&lt;/s&gt;
| r2-length-f  = &lt;s&gt;4902&lt;/s&gt;
| r2-length-m  = &lt;s&gt;1494&lt;/s&gt;
| r2-surface   = &lt;s&gt;Concrete&lt;/s&gt;
| footnotes    =
}}

'''Lista Air Station''' ({{lang-no|Lista flystasjon}}, {{airport codes|FAN|ENLI|p=n}}) was a [[military airbase]] situated on the [[Lista]] peninsula in [[Farsund]], [[Norway]]. It features a {{convert|2990|m|sp=us|adj=on}} concretd runway aligned 14/32, and a {{convert|1521|m|sp=us|adj=on}} runway aligned 09/21. The facility was shared with [[Farsund Airport, Lista]], which remains in operation.

The airbase was built by [[Luftwaffe]] between 1941 and 1944, during the [[German occupation of Norway]]. Throughout the [[Second World War]] it was predominantly used for [[fighter aircraft]] and served as part of the [[Atlantic Wall]]. Most of the buildings at the station date from this period. It was taken over by the [[Royal Norwegian Air Force]] in 1946. It was at first closed and then reopened, originally serving a weapon-technical school and a shooting and bombing school. The latter utilized the shooting area at Marka.

Lista received [[North Atlantic Treaty Organization]] (NATO) funding for a runway extension, which was built between 1955 and 1959. Lista was designated a reserve airbase throughout the [[Cold War]]. The RNoAF's [[recruit training|recruit school]] was located at Lista from 1963 to 1984. Thereafter it was mostly used for conferences. Lista Air Station was closed on 6 June 1996. The sale of the base, in which the military paid to the new owners to buy the property, resulted in a series of investigations and a change to the way the military sold properties.

==History==

===Establishment===
The [[Norwegian Armed Forces]] never considered the suitability of Lista as an air base prior to the Second World War, despite its natural suitability in a flat, open landscape.&lt;ref name=a227&gt;Arheim: 227&lt;/ref&gt; The German occupation of Norway started on 9 April 1940 as part of [[Operation Weserübung]].&lt;ref&gt;Ettrup: 12&lt;/ref&gt; Lista was initially not prioritized by the [[Wehrmacht]]. The first landing of fifteen troops took place on 24 April, in an action to secure [[Lista Lighthouse]].&lt;ref name=e16&gt;Ettrup: 16&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lista nordberg fort museum IMG 0940.JPG|thumb|[[Nordberg Fort]] was located just north of the aerodrome]]
Lista was regarded as crucial to secure the safe transport of convoys along the coast. By 22 May 60 men had been stationed in Farsund. The first work on establishing defenses in Lista commenced later in the summer by the [[Kriegsmarine]] in what would later develop into [[Nordberg Fort]] and part of the [[Atlantic Wall]]. Guns were installed by October, making the [[coastal artillery]] operative.&lt;ref name=e16 /&gt;

The Luftwaffe's took control over [[Kjevik Air Station]] and [[Sola Air Station]] upon the occupation. They quickly assessed that there would be need for an additional airfield located between [[Kristiansand]] and [[Stavanger]]. Work therefore commenced on building [[Mandal Airport]], which was completed in August 1940. By then Lista had been assessed as a more suitable location. Planning started in August and surveying was completed by the end of the month. The work was carried out by German personnel through Luftwaffe Bau-Batalionen and German contractors who hired Norwegian workers.&lt;ref name=e64&gt;Ettrup: 64&lt;/ref&gt; Construction began on 2 September.&lt;ref name=h42&gt;Hjelmeland: 42&lt;/ref&gt;

The runway was built in the area around Langåker and Stave. After leveling, a runway was built with prefabricated wooden elements.&lt;ref name=e64 /&gt; It measured {{convert|1700|by|120|m|sp=us}} and westwards it reached the beach at Verevågen. It was at the time the longest wooden runway in Norway. The runway was completed in April 1941, allowing the first aircraft to land. Mandal Airport was closed and the aircraft transferred to Lista.&lt;ref name=e65&gt;Ettrup: 65&lt;/ref&gt;

The first anti-aircraft defenses arrived on 27 December 1940, originally placing [[88 mm gun]]s at Vågsvold, Lista Lighthouse and at Stave. Four more positions were established in 1941. This was reorganized in 1943, when some of the units were moved out of Lista.&lt;ref name=e97&gt;Ettrup: 97&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Farsund IMG 3417 lista flyst.JPG|thumb|left|The officer's mess hall]]
Next work started on the main part of the air station. Contracted to Ed Zublin, the first part of the work was to drain the vast mires located throughout the peninsula. The terraforming proved difficult and work ran gradually for three years. Several smaller hills were demolished and moved to fill up where necessary. The landscape was dug out to create a series of drainage passages. The work resulted in a {{convert|1571|by|80|m|sp=us}} concrete runway, in addition to {{convert|3620|m|sp=us}} of taxiways and associated hangars, barracks and other buildings.&lt;ref name=e66&gt;Ettrup: 66&lt;/ref&gt;

The work employed more than 10,000 Norwegian workers and several thousand Eastern Europeans. An [[industrial railway]], the Lunde Line, was completed in April 1943.&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt; Two [[Würzburg radar]]s and a [[Freya radar]] were installed at Lista from May 1943, along with one at [[Flekkerøy]].&lt;ref name=e87&gt;Ettrup: 87&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, a [[bearing (navigation)|bearing station]] and [[radio jamming|jamming station]] were also installed.&lt;ref name=e89&gt;Ettrup: 89&lt;/ref&gt;

===Luftwaffe operations===
Lista Air Station was primarily used by fighter aircraft throughout the Second World War. Its main task was to provide support for the [[North Sea]] and [[Skagerrak]] areas along the coastline. The squadrons and aircraft stationed and dispatched to Lista varied over time, and often Lista was one of several airbases in Southern Norway used by a division at any given time.&lt;ref name=e82&gt;Ettrup: 82&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Farsund IMG 3413 lista flyst.JPG|thumb|Hangar]]
The 2nd Group of [[Jagdgeschwader 77]] (2./JG77) was the first unit based at Lista, from March 1941. It became [[Jagdgeschwader 5|2./JG5]] in January 1942. Lista was one of several bases used by the ''ad hoc'' Jagdgruppe Losigkeit to escort the German cruisers [[German cruiser Prinz Eugen|''Prinz Eugen'']] and [[German cruiser Admiral Scheer|''Admiral Scheer'']] along the coast in February. From August 1942 to March 1943 Lista was regularly used by [[Jagdgeschwader 1 (World War II)|8./JG1]], operating [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]F and [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]A.&lt;ref name=e82 /&gt;

From August to October 1943 the base was used for [[Jagdgeschwader 11|10./JG11]] to escort convoys along Skagerrak using the BF 109T.&lt;ref name=e82 /&gt; From October the base was used by a detachment of [[Seenotdienst|Seenotgruppe 5]] using [[Dornier Do 24]] seaplanes. From November 1943 to June 1944 Lista was the base of 11./JG11 with Bf 109T. They were replaced in June with 10./JG5 [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]]G and Nachtjagdstaffel Norwegian with [[Junkers Ju 88]]G and [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]]G, who remained until March 1945. These were sometimes supplemented with [[Zerstörergeschwader 26]], also with Bf 100G. 13./JG5 and 15./JG5 and their Bf 109Gs were moved to Lista in November 1944. [[Luftflotte 1]]/120 used Lista for its [[Junkers Ju 88]]D and [[Junkers Ju 188]]F reconnaissance duties from December.&lt;ref name=e83&gt;Ettrup: 83&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Norwegian Air Force operations===
Lista Air Station remained under German control until [[Royal Air Force]] troops arrived on 22 May 1945. The RAF retained control of the facility in November 1945, when it was transferred to the Royal Norwegian Air Force.&lt;ref name=e68&gt;Ettrup: 68&lt;/ref&gt; During the RAF period their troops cleaned up the site, including [[minesweeping]] and destruction of ammunition and aircraft.&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt;

[[File:Farsund IMG 3386 lista flyst.JPG|thumb|left|Three hangars form the Second World War remain today]]
The Norwegian military had no use for the entire encampment and defensive structures, and therefore most of the area was quickly returned to civilian use. However, the air station itself was of interest to the air force and was kept as a military installation. In December 1946 the military concluded that there was no need for the aerodrome and started the process of closing the facility.&lt;ref name=a227 /&gt; The wooden runway was dismantled and given as building supplies to the local population. Most of buildings were dismantled and moved elsewhere. The concrete runway was kept as an emergency airfield for civilian aircraft. Two of the major hangars burned down in 1947.&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt;

The air force concluded in 1948 that it needed to upgrade eight of the rudimentary bases which they had abandoned after the end of the war, including Lista. This was part of a strategy to spread out the squadrons in more locations.&lt;ref name=a50&gt;Arheim: 50&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, Lista was selected as a suitable site for parts of the air force's schools. This consisted of a shooting- and bombing school and a weapon-technical school.&lt;ref name=a227 /&gt; The latter opened in 1948 and the former the following year. They used existing German barracks for their quarters and two hangars for their classrooms.&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt;

The {{convert|100|ha|adj=on}} artillery range Marka was designated as part of the reopeneing, which was used both by the artillery and by the air force.&lt;ref name=a227 /&gt; It was commissioned on 1 March 1951. The artillery range was found to be unsuitable and instead the sand dunes of [[Jæren]] were preferred. The shooting- and bombing school was therefore moved to Sola in 1953.&lt;ref name=a240&gt;Arheim: 240&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Farsund IMG 3401 lista flyst.JPG|thumb|A former RNoAF building]]
Between 1955 and 1959 the base underwent a major redevelopment. Through funding from the [[North Atlantic Treaty Organization]] (NATO), List was designated a full-scale reserve base. This involved the construction of a new, {{convert|2990|m|sp=us|adj=on}} runway and taxiway and stands for two squadrons of fighter jets, each in a designated area.&lt;ref name=a227 /&gt;  An anti-aircraft defense was established as part of the runway extension, manned by reserves and equipped with a [[Bofors 40 mm gun]].&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt;  The reserve status was never removed and the base was never home to any squadrons.&lt;ref name=a227 /&gt;

The air force's recruit school was moved to Lista in 1963, replacing the weapon-technical school, which moved to Kjevik.&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt; The latter was gradually closed down between 1982 and 1984 and moved to [[Gardermoen Air Station]].&lt;ref name=a227 /&gt; However, due to the then large amount of new buildings at the station, it was used for courses and conferences within the military. It peaked at 12,000 guest-days. From 1988 to 1993 the Air Force's fire protection assistants were trained at Lista. This consisted of five courses per year, each of 25 to 30 pupils.&lt;ref name=a228&gt;Arheim: 228&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Farsund IMG 3415 lista flyst.JPG|thumb|left|Hangar and redeveloped building]]
As part of the [[Oslo Airport location controversy]], a 1988 report proposed that Lista be upgraded as an active air station, should Gardermoen be chosen as the new main airport. However, these plans were rejected by the [[Chief of Defence (Norway)|Chief of Defence]]. Instead the base was upgraded to take in recruits for the [[Home Guard (Norway)|Home Guard]]. Lista was upgraded Four new quarters were built, along with upgrades to the canteens, kitchens, storage facilities and classrooms. From 1990 it had a capacity for 232 recruits at a time, training them for six months before transferring them to reserve service in the Home Guard.&lt;ref name=a228 /&gt;

===Closing===
Due to the restructuring of the military in the 1990s, [[Parliament of Norway|Parliament]] voted on 8 June 1994 to close Lista Air Station. Effective from 1 June 1996, the military was set to retain ownership of the facility for ten years.&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt; Parliament granted the [[Norwegian Defence Estates Agency|Defence Estates Agency]] the right to sell the air station for market price as part of a large-scale sale of defunct military estates. The condition was that any other state or public uses be given priority and that the sale take place through an open sales process.&lt;ref name=r3&gt;Office of the Auditor General of Norway: 3&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1996 the Defence Estates Agency signed a ten-year lease on the entire air station with the latter company for an annual rent of 10,000 [[Norwegian krone]] per year. The agency retained the responsibility to maintain the property. Lista Lufthavn received an option for the company to buy the entire facility for NOK&amp;nbsp;25 million.&lt;ref&gt;Office of the Auditor General of Norway: 2&lt;/ref&gt; In 1999 the agency were in talks with Farsund Municipality, but stipulated a sales price of NOK&amp;nbsp;200 million. The municipality therefore withdrew their interest.&lt;ref name=r5&gt;Office of the Auditor General of Norway: 5&lt;/ref&gt; The agency sold the air station to Lista Flypark. They took over ownership on 9 December 2002.&lt;ref name=r3 /&gt;

[[File:Farsund IMG 3414 lista flyst.JPG|thumb|Military building since redeveloped to civilian use]]
The air station was valuated at NOK&amp;nbsp;11 million, yet sold for NOK&amp;nbsp;3.5. There was no documentation for why this discount was given. Both Lista Lufthavn and Lista Flypark's contracts were such structured that they had incentives to delay any commercial development of the property. The sale was carried out without public announcement. Eight sections were also sold between 1998 and 2003 without announcement.&lt;ref&gt;Office of the Auditor General of Norway: 4&lt;/ref&gt; [[Avinor]] asked to take over the control tower and the [[Norwegian Directorate for Nature Management|Directorate for Nature Management]] asked to take over Slevdalsvannet, but both of these requests were ignored.&lt;ref name=r5 /&gt;

All in all the military spent NOK&amp;nbsp;53 million on the process of selling the property. Subtracted the sales price, this was what the military spend on operating the base after closure, maintaining it and in various discounts to purchasers for them to fix up the base after the sale took place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Forsvaret sløste bort 53 mill. på Lista |last=Jacobsen |first=Hans E. H. |work=[[Stavanger Aftenblad]] |date=8 February 2005 |page=3 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; The scandal resulted in Parliament changing the sales procedures so that they had to be approved of by the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nrk.no/sorlandet/avslappet-forhold-til-gransking-1.2642586 |title=Avslappet forhold til gransking |last=Nilsen |first=Hanne Torhild |publisher=[[Norwegian Broadcasting Corporation]] |date=7 June 2007 |accessdate=8 December 2014 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Defence Estates Agency retrospectively admitted their mistake and restructured their processes and organization to better handle sales and avoid future scandals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forsvarsbygg.no/Arkiv/2013/Statlig-eiendomssalg-til-beste-for-fellesskapet/ |title=Statlig eiendomssalg til beste for fellesskapet|last=Sjursen |first=Frode |publisher=[[Norwegian Defence Estates Agency]] |date=20 December 2013 |accessdate=8 December 2014 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the base has been listed as a cultural heritage. This includes the runways, the taxiway and the road network, the remaining buildings from the Second World War and Marka. An important aspect when listing was that many of the structures had not been modified since the war.&lt;ref&gt;Hjelmeland: 43&lt;/ref&gt; Slevdalsvannet Nature Reserve is situated southwest of the runway. A former lake, it has since been drained. It remains an important wetland area for migratory birds and is part of a [[Ramsar site]]. The nature reserve was established in 2005 and in 2014 three small lakes were artificially recreated. The site was bought by the [[Ministry of the Environment (Norway)|Ministry of the Environment]] in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nrk.no/sorlandet/lager-innsjo-av-sump-1.12076883 |title=Larger innsjø av sump |publisher=[[Norwegian Broadcasting Corporation]] |date=2 December 2014 |accessdate=8 December 2014 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Facilities==
Farsund Airport, Lista is situated on the flat section of the Lista peninsula in Farsund, Norway.&lt;ref name=a227 /&gt; It is situated between the villages of [[Vanse]] and [[Vestbygd, Vest-Agder|Vestbygd]],&lt;ref name=&quot;g15&quot;/&gt; and {{convert|12|km|sp=us}} from Farsund.&lt;ref name=h40&gt;Hjelmeland: 40&lt;/ref&gt; The aerodrome has an reference elevation of {{convert|9|m|sp=us}} [[above mean sea level]].&lt;ref name=g15&gt;Gustafsen: 15&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second World War===
[[File:Farsund IMG 3388 flipside.JPG|thumb|left|The interior of one of the hangars, since redeveloped to a skating park]]
During the Luftwaffe period the airport was gradually built out, changing character over time. The main runway was concrete and measured {{convert|1571|by|80|m|sp=us}}, aligned 09/27. It was connected via a network of taxiways which measured a total {{convert|3620|m|sp=us}}. Their width was {{convert|15|m|sp=us}}. The runway was {{convert|80|cm|sp=us}} thick, while the taxiways were {{convert|25|cm|sp=us}} thick. A further {{convert|1380|m|sp=us}} of taxiways were made of shingle. Aircraft stands were covered in shingle and wood. Around the airport there were twenty small protective hangars.&lt;ref name=e66 /&gt; In the western part of the aerodrome was a {{convert|1700|by|120|m|sp=us|adj=on}} wooden runway.&lt;ref name=e65 /&gt;

Most of the buildings at Lista Air Station were built during the Second World War. They were modernized by the RNoAF, but retained their original structure. Most of the buildings were of standard German design and were found both at other Norwegian and other Luftwaffe airports from the era.&lt;ref&gt;Ettrup: 259&lt;/ref&gt; The operative headquarters were located at the eastern end of the wooden runway.&lt;ref&gt;Ettrup: 77&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the buildings were located on the west side of the main runway. The facilities included offices, quarters, mess halls, storage buildings, a cinema and storage areas.&lt;ref name=h40&gt;Hjelmeland: 40&lt;/ref&gt; The most elaborate building is the officer's mess, which remains today as a listed building. The two-story building features a roofed [[colonnade]], a hipped roof and cob-worked log walls.&lt;ref name=h41&gt;Hjelmeland: 41&lt;/ref&gt; The entire base consisted of about 300 buildings. The airbase and surrounding area were connected by a [[narrow-gauge railway]], the Lunde Line.&lt;ref name=h42 /&gt;

[[File:Farsund IMG 3421 lista flyst.JPG|thumb|Remaining barracks]]
The location of the anti-aircraft defenses varied throughout the Second World War. Flak positions were at various times situated at Vågsvold, Dyngvold, Tjøvrenes, Lista Lighthouse, Venneim, Steinodden, Torp, Østre Hauge, Tjørveneset, Stave and Farsund. These were predominantly [[8.8 cm Flak 18/36/37/41|8.8 cm guns]], supplemented with [[3.7 cm Flak 18/36/37/43|3.7 cm guns]] and [[2 cm Flak 30/38/Flakvierling|2.0 cm guns]]. The various flak positions were built with bunkers serving as quarters and support.&lt;ref name=e97 /&gt;

The site had a radar complex named &quot;Wolf&quot; situated in Marka. It consisted of two [[Würzburg radar]]s, one [[Freya radar]] and a [[Wassermann radar]], situated on the site of [[Farsund Radio]]. A second Wassermann radar was located at Grimsby. These were used both for detection and to aid fighters during night operations.&lt;ref name=e87 /&gt; Communications with fighters took place by a transmitter at Vere, which had a range of {{convert|200|km|sp=us}}.&lt;ref&gt;Ettrup: 88&lt;/ref&gt; The site also featured a bearing station and a jamming station.&lt;ref name=e89 /&gt;

===Cold War===
Following the NATO expansion in the late 1950s, a new {{convert|2990|by|45|m|sp=us}} concrete runway was built, aligned 14/32. Parallel to this runs a {{convert|2500|m|sp=us|adj=on}} concrete [[taxiway]].&lt;ref name=g15 /&gt; This is a rebuilding and extension of the former wooden runway. The German concrete runway was kept, although relegated to serve as a secondary runway.&lt;ref name=h40 /&gt; The shooting field of Marka was located southeast of the aerodrome. It features twenty-four bunkers, including a commando bunker from the Second World War.&lt;ref name=h41 /&gt;

The facilities which have remained since the war and were still used at the end of the air station's operation were the hangars, the officer's mess hall and Mark. Three of the six main hangars have survived.&lt;ref name=h41 /&gt; These were standard German types. The one consisted of a lean-to roof supported by a truss. The other two had a semicircular arch roof. Both were built with wooden walls and roofs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.verneplaner.no/?f=landsverneplan&amp;k=3&amp;id=247392&amp;a=5 |title=Det tyske militærbyggeriet i Norge |last=Wilberg |first=Janne |publisher=[[Norwegian Defence Estates Agency]] |language=Norwegian |accessdate=8 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Civilian sector==
[[File:Flydåp.jpg|thumb|[[Air Stord]] [[Dornier Do 328]] at Lista in 1996]]
{{main|Farsund Airport, Lista}}

Given the readiness of the infrastructure, Lista was selected as a suitable location for a civilian airport. Prior to the privatization the civilian operations were limited, typically with two daily trips each day to [[Oslo Airport, Fornebu]] and [[Stavanger Airport, Sola]], and operations were carried out by the air force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lista uten brannmenn |last=Hjort-Larsen |first=Arvid |work=[[Verdens Gang]] |date=30 December 1977 |page=14 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Braathens SAFE]] started flights on 6 June 1955.&lt;ref&gt;Tjomsland &amp; Wilsberg: 106&lt;/ref&gt; With a few periods without services,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lista mister anløp av Braathen-fly |work=[[Verdens Gang]] |date=24 February 1959 |page=12 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; they retained flights until 1980.&lt;ref&gt;Tjomsland &amp; Wilsberg: 272&lt;/ref&gt; Nordsjøfly,&lt;ref&gt;Melling: 171&lt;/ref&gt; and its successor [[Norving]], took over the routes,&lt;ref&gt;Melling: 200&lt;/ref&gt; which lasted until February 1988.&lt;ref&gt;Melling: 289&lt;/ref&gt;

After the privatization, [[Air Stord]] operated services from 1996 to 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Flyplass gjenåpner etter åtte år: Lista på lufta igjen |last=Bø |first=Trond |work=[[Aftenposten]] |date=25 May 1996 |page=6 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Slutt for Air Stord |last=Furnes |first=Hilde Mari |work=[[Aftenposten]] |date=20 February 1999 |page=4 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; An [[aerodrome flight information service]] was retained until 2007, although the airport saw very limited use. The main client was [[CHC Helikopter Service]], who used it as a reserve base for flights to the [[North Sea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;e68&quot;/&gt; The main challenge for Farsund Airport has been the proximity to [[Kristiansand Airport, Kjevik]] and the limited [[catchment area]] which only covers Lister.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Kjevik og Lista er komplementære |last=Brøvig |first=Gunnar |work=[[Fædrelandsvennen]] |date=20 October 2005 |page=5 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{commons category|Lista Air Station}}
* {{cite book |last=Arheim |first=Tom |last2=Hafsten |first2=Bjørn |last3=Olsen |first3=Bjørn |last4=Thuve |first4=Sverre |title=Fra Spitfire til F-16: Luftforsvaret 50 år 1944–1994 |url=http://www.nb.no/nbsok/nb/2bb06c47357b69c0081d12c7bb647284 |location=Oslo |publisher=Sem &amp; Stenersen |year=1994 |language=Norwegian |isbn=82-7046-068-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Ettrup |first=Erik |last2=Schellenbergen |first2=Daniel |last3=Ritterbach |first3=Erik |title=Festung Lista |publisher=Commentum Forlag |location=Sandnes |isbn=978-82-92309-71-1 |language=Norwegian, German}}
* {{cite book |last=Gustavsen |first=Roar |title=Flyplasshåndbok for Farsund lufthavn, Lista |year=2014 |publisher=Lista Lufthavn |location=Farsund |language=Norwegian |url=http://listalufthavn.no/global/106/H_NDBOK_LISTA_011_-_010214.pdf |accessdate=9 December 2014}}
* {{cite book |last=Hjelmeland |first=Britt-Elise |title=Landsverneplan for Forsvaret : verneplan for eiendommer, bygninger og anlegg : Katalog Sør- og Vestlandet, Trøndelag og Nord-Norge |year=2000 |publisher=Forsvarets bygningstjeneste |location=Oslo |language=Norwegian |url=http://www.nb.no/nbsok/nb/1c25831424cfb067345542ad86aa267a}}
* {{cite book |last=Melling |first=Kjersti |title=Nordavind fra alle kanter |year=2009 |publisher=Pilotforlaget |location=Oslo |language=Norwegian}}
* {{cite book |author=[[Office of the Auditor General of Norway]] |title=Riksrevisjonens undersøkelse av salget av Lista flystasjon |year=2005 |format=PDF |accessdate=9 December 2014 |language=Norwegian}}
* {{cite book |last=Tjomsland |first=Audun |last2=Wilsberg |first2=Kjell |year=1995 |title=Braathens SAFE 50 år: Mot alle odds |location=Oslo |language=Norwegian |isbn=82-990400-1-9}}

{{Royal Norwegian Air Force}}
{{Airports in Norway}}
{{Portal bar|Aviation|War|World War II|Cold War|Norway|Nazi Germany}}

[[Category:Airports in Vest-Agder]]
[[Category:Defunct airports in Norway]]
[[Category:Royal Norwegian Air Force stations]]
[[Category:Luftwaffe airports in Norway]]
[[Category:Farsund]]
[[Category:Airports established in 1941]]
[[Category:Airports disestablished in 1996]]
[[Category:1941 establishments in Norway]]
[[Category:1996 disestablishments in Norway]]
[[Category:Military installations in Vest-Agder]]</text>
      <sha1>q8b41160nfyhjxc69hp2v5fjpvueivl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
