<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lithuanian–Soviet War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18990438</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738488814</id>
      <parentid>695486611</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-09T07:20:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>92.216.107.245</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* German offensive */  typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45652">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Lithuanian–Soviet War
|date=December 1918 – August 1919
|partof = the [[Lithuanian Wars of Independence]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Soviet westward offensive of 1918–1919]]
|place=[[Lithuania]]
|image=[[File:Soviet POWs in Lithuania.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Soviet prisoners of war in a Lithuanian camp. As of December 1, 1919 Lithuanians held 1,773 Soviet soldiers.&lt;ref name=l173&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=173}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Bolshevik forces driven out
|combatant1={{flagicon|Lithuania}} [[Republic of Lithuania (1918–1940)|Lithuania]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Weimar Republic|name=Saxon Volunteers}}
|combatant2={{flag|Russian SFSR|1918}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Lithuanian-Byelorussian SSR.svg}} [[Lithuanian–Belorussian Soviet Socialist Republic|Lithuanian–Belorussian SSR]]
|commander1=[[Silvestras Žukauskas]]
|commander2=[[Vincas Kapsukas]]
|commander3=
|strength1=
{{flagicon|Lithuania|1918}} 8,000 Lithuanians in August 1919&lt;ref name=skiri-b/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
{{flagicon|Weimar Republic}} 10,000 Germans&lt;ref name=skiri-b&gt;{{harvnb|Skirius|2002b}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2={{flagicon|Russian SFSR|1918}} 18,000–20,000
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
}}
The '''Lithuanian–Soviet War''' or '''Lithuanian–Bolshevik War''' ({{lang-lt|karas su bolševikais}}) was fought between [[Act of Independence of Lithuania|newly independent]] [[Lithuania]] and the [[Russian Soviet Federated Socialist Republic]] in the [[aftermath of World War I]]. It was part of the larger [[Soviet westward offensive of 1918–1919]]. The offensive followed retreating German troops with intentions to establish [[Soviet republics]] in [[Ukraine]], [[Belarus]], [[Lithuania]], [[Latvia]], [[Estonia]], [[Poland]] and link up with the [[German Revolution of 1918–19|German Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davies|1998|p=934}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of December 1918 Soviet forces reached Lithuanian borders. Largely unopposed, they took one town after another and by the end of January 1919 controlled about ⅔ of the Lithuanian territory. In February the Soviet advance was stopped by Lithuanian and German volunteers, who prevented the Soviets from capturing [[Kaunas]], the [[temporary capital of Lithuania]]. From April 1919 the Lithuanian war went parallel with the [[Polish–Soviet War]]. Poland had territorial claims over Lithuania, especially the [[Vilnius Region]], and these tensions spilled over into the [[Polish–Lithuanian War]]. Historian [[Norman Davies]] summarized the situation: &quot;the German army was supporting the Lithuanian nationalists, the Soviets were supporting the Lithuanian communists and the Polish Army was fighting them all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davies|1982|p=506}}&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-May the Lithuanian army, now commanded by General [[Silvestras Žukauskas]], began an offensive against the Soviets in northeastern Lithuania. By mid-June the Lithuanians reached the Latvian border and cornered the Soviets among lakes and hills near [[Zarasai]], where the Soviets held out until the end of August 1919. The Soviets and Lithuanians, separated by the [[Daugava River]], maintained their fronts until the [[Battle of Daugavpils]] in January 1920. As early as September 1919 the Soviets offered to negotiate a peace treaty, but talks began only in May 1920. The [[Soviet–Lithuanian Peace Treaty]] was signed on July 12, 1920. Soviet Russia fully recognized independent Lithuania.

==Background==
[[File:PL-RU war 1919 phase I.svg|thumb|300px|Bolshevik forces advance following retreating German troops (red arrows). The red line shows the Soviet front in January 1919.]]
Lithuania became part of the [[Russian Empire]] after the final [[partitions of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth|partition of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] in 1795. During World War I Lithuania was occupied by Germany and made part of [[Ober Ost]]. On February 16, 1918 the [[Council of Lithuania]] [[Act of Independence of Lithuania|declared independence]] from both Germany and Russia. Three weeks later, the [[Bolsheviks]], encumbered with the [[Russian Civil War]], sued for peace with the [[Central Powers]] and signed the  [[Treaty of Brest-Litovsk]]. They renounced Russian claims to Finland, Estonia, Latvia, Ukraine, Lithuania and Poland.&lt;ref name=langs/&gt; However, the Lithuanians were only allowed minimal autonomy and could not establish ''de facto'' independence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eidintas|1999|p=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; That changed when Germany lost the war and signed the [[Armistice with Germany (Compiègne)|Compiègne Armistice]] on November 11, 1918. Lithuania soon began organizing basic institutions, and established their first government led by [[Augustinas Voldemaras]].

On November 13, 1918, the Soviet Russian government renounced the [[Treaty of Brest-Litovsk]], which had assured Lithuania's independence.&lt;ref name=langs&gt;{{harvnb|Langstrom|2003|p=52}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bolshevik [[Western Army (Russia)|Western Army]] followed retreating German troops maintaining a distance of about {{convert|10|-|15|km}} between the two armies.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Čepėnas|1986|p=315}}&lt;/ref&gt; Demoralized Germans often left valuable armaments and other equipment to the Soviets.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Čepėnas|1986|p=316}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets attempted to spread the [[World revolution|global proletarian revolution]] and sought to establish Soviet republics in the region. They saw [[Baltic states]] as a barrier or a bridge into Western Europe, where they could join the [[German Revolution of 1918–19|German]] and the [[Hungarian Soviet Republic|Hungarian Revolutions]].&lt;ref name=rauch51/&gt; By the end of December 1918, Bolshevik forces reached eastern Lithuania.

==Opposing sides==

===Lithuanian government===
[[Augustinas Voldemaras]], the first [[Prime Minister of Lithuania]], did not believe that forming the military was a priority and advocated Lithuanian neutrality.&lt;ref name=kamun352&gt;{{harvnb|Kamuntavičius|2001|p=352}}&lt;/ref&gt; He trusted that German mercenaries would protect Lithuania until the upcoming [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|Paris Peace Conference]] could establish peace.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Residents organized local self-defense units to defend themselves from retreating Germans.&lt;ref name=kamun352/&gt; The first laws regarding the army were not issued until November 23. Some Lithuanians, who had served in the Russian army during the World War, returned to Lithuania and started organizing battalions in [[Kaunas]], [[Hrodna]], [[Alytus]].&lt;ref name=kamun352/&gt; They lacked guns, ammunition, and officers.

At the end of December, with the Bolsheviks already in the country, Lithuania was left leaderless. [[Augustinas Voldemaras]], [[Antanas Smetona]], Chairman of the Council of Lithuania, and [[Martynas Yčas]], Minister of Finance, departed for Germany to ask for financial assistance.&lt;ref name=skiri-b/&gt; General [[Kiprijonas Kundratavičius]], Vice Minister of Defense, suggested a retreat to Hrodna and refused to command the Lithuanian defense.&lt;ref name=kamun352/&gt; The first Cabinet of Ministers resigned on December 26, 1918. [[Mykolas Sleževičius]] stepped in and organized a new government. On December 29, he issued the first mass appeal in four languages calling for volunteers for the Lithuanian Army.&lt;ref name=blaze&gt;{{harvnb|Blaževičius|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sleževičius government adopted new policy on land reform, which could be summarized in a slogan &quot;land for those who cultivate it.&quot;&lt;ref name=truska52&gt;{{harvnb|Truska|1995|p=52}}&lt;/ref&gt; It meant the land would be taken from large landowners and redistributed first to the volunteers for free and then to small peasants for a fee.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Truska|1995|pp=52–53}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mobilization]] of officers was announced only on January 25; about 400 people responded.&lt;ref name=blaze/&gt;

===Saxon Volunteers===
In Berlin, Smetona and Yčas signed a loan agreement with Germany for 100 million marks.&lt;ref name=truska52/&gt; The money was used primarily to build and supply the army. They further negotiated direct German support in the war against the Soviets. Article 12 of the Compiègne Armistice required the Germans to protect Lithuania from possible Soviet attacks,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lane|2001|pp=6–7}}&lt;/ref&gt; but Germany was also interested in maintaining its influence in the region and weakening Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Čepėnas|1986|p=317}}&lt;/ref&gt; At first they tried to organize volunteers from the retreating soldiers of the [[10th Army (German Empire)|10th German Army]], commanded by General [[Erich von Falkenhayn]]. However, the soldiers were tired and demoralized and wanted to return home as soon as possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|White|1994|pp=1359–1360}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recruitment continued in Germany, especially in [[Saxony]]. The volunteers were paid 30 marks per month plus 5 marks per day and had to sign up for three months.&lt;ref name=l40&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first Saxon Volunteers, as they became known, arrived to Kaunas at the beginning of January, but quite a few of them were judged unfit for duty and sent back. By the end of January, German volunteers numbered 4,000.&lt;ref name=l40/&gt; They were not very reliable as the [[German Revolution]] increased popularity of the [[Spartacist League]] and Soviet causes. There were several attempts at a coup against the Lithuanian government.&lt;ref name=l40/&gt; These volunteers were stationed in and around Kaunas: [[Alytus]], [[Jonava]], [[Kėdainiai]], [[Baisogala]].&lt;ref name=l40/&gt;

At first they were organized into the 46th Saxon Volunteer Division.&lt;ref name=l40/&gt; On February 22, Lieutenant-General [[Walter von Eberhardt]] became its commander. In April–May German forces were reorganized into the South Lithuania Volunteer Brigade composed of three regiments (18th, 19th, and 20th) and a separate battalion in [[Raseiniai]].&lt;ref name=rasti/&gt; The 18th Regiment fought alongside Lithuanians; the 19th Regiment guarded Kaunas area and did not participate in battle; the 20th Regiment was stationed in Hrodna and then in [[Kėdainiai]]; the separate battalion joined the [[Bermontians]].&lt;ref name=l40/&gt; The [[Baltische Landeswehr]], led by General [[Rüdiger von der Goltz]], organized a coup against Latvian government and captured [[Riga]]. On May 23, the [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|Paris Peace Conference]] reacting to these events asked Germany to withdraw its troops from both Latvia and Lithuania as soon as local forces could defend themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rauch|1970|pp=62–63}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last Saxon Volunteers left Lithuania in mid-July.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kamuntavičius|2001|p=354}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soviet government===
{{main|Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic (1918–1919)}}
On December 8, 1918, a temporary revolutionary government, chaired by [[Vincas Mickevičius-Kapsukas]], was formed solely from members of the [[Communist Party of Lithuania]].&lt;ref name=skiri-b/&gt; On December 16, 1918, the revolutionary government declared establishment of the [[Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic (1918–1919)|Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic]]. Between December 31, 1918 and January 1, 1919, the German garrison withdrew from Vilnius and passed authority over the city to a local Polish committee, against the pleas of the Lithuanian administration.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|White|1994|pp=1361–1362}}&lt;/ref&gt; Polish self-defense units made up of local inhabitants, called [[Lithuanian and Belarusian Self-Defence]], took over the posts. The Lithuanian government withdrew to [[Kaunas]], the [[temporary capital of Lithuania]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Snyder|2004|pp=61–62}}&lt;/ref&gt; On January 5, 1919, Vilnius was taken by the Soviets after a five-day fight with Polish paramilitary platoons led by general [[Władysław Wejtko]]. Kapsukas and his government arrived in Vilnius from [[Daugavpils]] on January 7.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=32}}&lt;/ref&gt; On February 27, the Lithuanian SSR was incorporated into the [[Lithuanian–Belorussian Soviet Socialist Republic]] or Litbel.

In the occupied territory the Soviets created [[Revolutionary committee (Soviet Union)|revolutionary committee]]s and [[soviet (council)|soviets]] based on structures developed in Russia.&lt;ref name=e36/&gt; Unlike elsewhere, Lithuanian communist organizations were young and had not yet developed a network of supporting local councils.&lt;ref name=rauch51&gt;{{harvnb|Rauch|1970|p=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; They nationalized commercial institutions and large estates. The land was to be used for [[collective farming]] instead of being redistributed to small farmers.&lt;ref name=lane7/&gt; The Soviet propagated internationalism and [[atheism]] in a country of staunch Catholics and determined nationalists.&lt;ref name=e36/&gt;&lt;ref name=lane8&gt;{{harvnb|Lane|2001|p=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soviets were supported by the industrial working class, but it was too small in Lithuania.&lt;ref name=lane8/&gt; The Soviets demanded large war contributions from captured cities and villages. For example, Panevėžys was required to pay 1,000,000, Utena – 200,000, villagers – 10 rubles.&lt;ref name=l34&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such policies alienated local population and contributed to the eventual defeat of the Soviets.&lt;ref name=lane8/&gt; For example, in February Kapsukas sent a telegram to Moscow arguing that conscription of local Lithuanians to the Red Army would only encourage Lithuanians to volunteer for the Lithuanian army.&lt;ref name=e36/&gt;

==Soviet advance==

===Soviet military gains===
Soviet troops (about 18,000&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kamuntavičius|2001|p=353}}&lt;/ref&gt;–20,000 men&lt;ref name=a94&gt;{{harvnb|Ališauskas|1953–1966|p=94}}&lt;/ref&gt;) approached the Lithuanian territory on December 12, 1918.&lt;ref name=a94/&gt; About 5,000 of them were Lithuanians.&lt;ref name=c319&gt;{{harvnb|Čepėnas|1986|p=319}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three divisions were employed: Pskov division (later renamed Lithuanian Division), International Division (later renamed 2nd Latvian Riflemen Division; included 39th, 41st, 47th, and 60th Regiments), and 17th Division (later renamed Western Division; included 5th Vilnius Regiment).&lt;ref name=l34/&gt; The divisions did not have a common military commander.&lt;ref name=rasti&gt;{{harvnb|Raštikis|1973|pp=88–91}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later more units were sent from Russia. The soviets also recruited partisan groups behind the front lines.&lt;ref name=c319/&gt; Soviet soldiers were poorly supplied and had to support themselves by requisitioning food, horses, and clothes from local residents.&lt;ref name=e36&gt;{{harvnb|Eidintas|1999|p=36}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lithuania could not offer serious resistance as at the time its army consisted only of about 3,000 untrained volunteers.&lt;ref name=cekut/&gt; Only local partisans, armed with weapons acquired from retreating Germans, offered brief resistance.

Red Army captured one town after another: [[Zarasai]] and [[Švenčionys]] (Dec. 22), [[Utena]] (Dec. 23), [[Rokiškis]] (Dec. 27), [[Vilnius]] (Jan. 5), [[Ukmergė]] and [[Panevėžys]] (Jan. 9), [[Šiauliai]] (Jan. 15), [[Telšiai]] (Jan. 25).&lt;ref name=a94/&gt; That accounted for about ⅔ of the Lithuanian territory. The front somewhat stabilized when Soviet forces were stopped near the [[Venta River]] by Latvian and German units ([[Baltische Landeswehr]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ališauskas|1953–1966|pp=94–95}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also Germans slowed down withdrawal of their troops after the [[Spartacist uprising]] was subdued on January 12.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|White|1994|p=1365}}&lt;/ref&gt; Southern Lithuania was a little better protected as Germans retreated from Ukraine through Hrodna. To prevent fights between retreating Germans and the Red Army, the Soviets and Germans signed a treaty on January 18. The treaty drew a temporary [[demarcation line]] that went through [[Daugai]], [[Stakliškės]], and {{convert|10|km}} east of [[Kaišiadorys]]–[[Jonava]]–[[Kėdainiai]] railway.&lt;ref name=a95&gt;{{harvnb|Ališauskas|1953–1966|p=95}}&lt;/ref&gt; That barred Bolshevik forces from directly attacking [[Kaunas]], Lithuania's second-largest city. The Red Army would need to encircle Kaunas and attack through [[Alytus]] or [[Kėdainiai]]. The operation to take Kaunas began on February 7.

===Encirclement of Kaunas===
[[File:Soviet plans for Kaunas (1919).png|thumb|300px|Planned Soviet attacks to encircle and capture Kaunas]]
Kėdainiai was attacked by the 2nd Riflemen Regiment of Lithuanian (former Pskov) Division (about 1,000 men). Lithuanian forces from Panevėžys, commanded by [[Jonas Variakojis]], and from Kėdainiai numbered only about 200 men.&lt;ref name=a95/&gt; Lithuanians withstood Red Army advance near Kėdainiai and with German support repelled it. On February 8, during the course of a reconnaissance mission, [[Povilas Lukšys (soldier)|Povilas Lukšys]] became the first Lithuanian soldier to die in the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.mond.gov.lt/lt/naujienos_874/archyvas_930/ziniu_archyvas_2007_metai/ziniu_archyvas_2007_-_02/minima_pirmoji_lietuvos_nepriklausomybes_kovu_pergale.html?pbck=30 |title=Minima pirmoji Lietuvos nepriklausomybės kovų pergalė |date=2007-02-09 |publisher=Ministry of National Defence |accessdate=2008-08-25|language=lt}}&lt;/ref&gt; On February 10, joint Lithuanian and German forces captured [[Šėta]] and forced the Red Army to retreat. The success of this operation lifted the Lithuanian army's morale and prevented the Red Army from encircling Kaunas from the north.&lt;ref name=a95/&gt;

On February 9, Soviet 7th Riflemen Regiment (900 men) took over [[Jieznas]], south of Kaunas.&lt;ref name=l47&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=47}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following day Lithuanian forces (300 men) from [[Prienai]] and Kaunas attacked before the Red Army could consolidate position, but were betrayed by their Russian commander and suffered a defeat: 18 Lithuanians were killed and 33 were taken prisoners.&lt;ref name=l47/&gt; Lithuanians retreated, were reinforced by new Lithuanian and Saxon Volunteers, attacked again, and took Jieznas on February 13.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=49–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets continued to push for Kaunas. The 3rd and 4th Riflemen Regiments (about 2,000 men) attacked [[Alytus]] on February 12. Germans did not engage in battle and retreated; not yet fully formed Lithuanian 1st Infantry Regiment could not withstand pressure from the Red Army and had to retreat towards [[Marijampolė]] and Prienai.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=54–57}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Antanas Juozapavičius]], the first Lithuanian officer to die in the wars, was killed during this battle. On the night of February 14–15, German forces and one company of the Lithuanians returned to Alytus and retook the city.&lt;ref name=l60&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=60}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kaunas was defended and the front stabilized for a while. Soviets were ordered to abandon the offensive and maintain defensive position.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=79}}&lt;/ref&gt; This break allowed Lithuanians to better organize and train the volunteers.

==Counterattacks==

===German offensive===
[[File:PL-RU war 1919 phase II.svg|thumb|300px|The advance of Polish (blue arrows), Lithuanian/German (dark purple arrows), Latvian/German (white arrows from west), and Estonian/Latvian (white arrows from north) forces. The blue line shows the Polish front in May 1920.]]

Northern Lithuania ([[Samogitia]]) was overtaken by the Soviet International Division (about 3,000 men). Its objective was to reach the [[Baltic Sea]] and cut off German supplies to Latvians in [[Latvian War of Independence|their war against the Soviets]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=70}}&lt;/ref&gt; Local communists were more active in northern Lithuania as the shortest route for Russian prisoners to return to Russia was through Samogitia.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=33}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their biggest achievement was formation of a 1,000-man Samogitian Regiment, commanded by [[Feliksas Baltušis-Žemaitis]], in the city of [[Šiauliai]]. The regiment included Russian [[POW]]s, German deserters, and criminals.&lt;ref name=l36&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=36}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were no units of regular Lithuanian army in Samogitia except for [[Partisans (military)|partisans]] in [[Skuodas]], rallied by [[Povilas Plechavičius]] and his brother Aleksandras, and in [[Joniškėlis]].&lt;ref name=a95/&gt;

The movement of the Bolsheviks towards [[East Prussia]] worried Germany, and they sent volunteers (Brigade Schaulen) commanded by General [[Rudiger von der Goltz]] to free a section of the [[Libau–Romny Railway]] line linking [[Liepāja]], [[Mažeikiai]], [[Radviliškis]], and [[Kėdainiai]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=71}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was part of a larger counter-offensive in Latvia.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rauch|1970|pp=59–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of February the Lithuanian partisans, supported by German artillery, took Mažeikiai and [[Seda, Lithuania|Seda]], and pursued Bolsheviks to [[Kuršėnai]]. On February 27, 1919, German volunteers supported by Plechavičius' partisans and Joniškėlis' partisans, defeated the Samogitian Regiment in a battle near [[Luokė]].&lt;ref name=l36/&gt; The regiment disbanded. Before mid-March the Germans took Kuršėnai, Šiauliai, Radviliškis, [[Šeduva]], [[Joniškis]] and stopped.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=72}}&lt;/ref&gt; On few occasions they were aided by Lithuanian partisans and regular units. Joniškėlis' partisans continued to guard the front along the [[Mūša River]].&lt;ref name=a96&gt;{{harvnb|Ališauskas|1953–1966|p=96}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were later incorporated into regular Lithuanian military.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=78}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lithuanian preparations===
As the Soviet forces were stopped, Lithuanian army slowly began to prepare itself for an offensive. After the Battle of Kėdainiai, Panevėžys volunteer regiment had secured its positions and grew in strength.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=62}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between mid-February and end of March it carried out small ''expeditions'' into nearby towns. Their main purpose was to demoralize the enemy forces and boost confidence of local residents and Lithuanian volunteers.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a reward for its successful operations, the volunteer regiment was given a name on March 22: the Separate Panevėžys Battalion ({{lang-lt|Panevėžio atskirasis batalionas}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=64}}&lt;/ref&gt; Demoralization campaign was successful: the Bolshevik forces stationed in [[Panevėžys]] and [[Kupiškis]] rebelled, and were quelled only by a Red Army Division from neighboring Latvia.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=66}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bolshevik morale underwent deeper declines, and between March 19 and March 24 their forces left Panevėžys. Lithuanian forces entered the city on March 26, but the Red Army retook it on April 4.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=66, 69}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The lull between Soviet attacks was used to strengthen and organize the army. On March 5, Lithuanians announced mobilization of men born 1887–1889.&lt;ref name=skiri-b/&gt; Lithuanian forces rapidly increased their numbers. By May 3 the official headcount reached 440 officers and 10,729 privates.&lt;ref name=l91&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=91}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, only about half of them were properly trained, armed, and assigned to military units.&lt;ref name=l91/&gt; In February–April Lithuanian soldiers were actively undergoing training, the chain of command was streamlined, new military units formed. Lithuania also received new shipments of arms and munitions. Soldiers received first uniforms.&lt;ref name=l80/&gt;

The first organized Lithuanian offensive was carried out between April 3 and April 8, 1919. Lithuanians decided to take advantage of large Polish attacks against the Soviets in [[Hrodna]] area in order to test enemy strength and capture Vilnius.&lt;ref name=l80/&gt; The southern group, formed on the basis of the 1st Riflemen Regiment and led by [[Kazys Ladiga]], was to attack from Alytus along [[Daugai]]–[[Valkininkai]] line.&lt;ref name=l80&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=80–81}}&lt;/ref&gt; The northern group, formed on the basis on the 2nd Riflemen Regiment and led by [[Juozas Butkus]], was to attack from Kaišiadorys along [[Žasliai]]–[[Vievis]] line.&lt;ref name=l80/&gt; Germans did not participate. Both regiments were initially successful, but Soviets gathered their forces and stopped the advance. As Lithuanian flanks were not defended, they decided to abandon to offensive. Soviets also accused Germans of violating the demarcation line set on January 18 and pressured them to retreat.&lt;ref name=a96/&gt;

===Polish offensive===
{{main|Polish–Soviet War}}

Poland started an offensive against the Soviets in March 1919. They pushed east and north, entering [[Vilnius Region]], the territory claimed by Lithuanians. Between April 19 and 21, Poles captured Vilnius during the [[Vilna offensive]] and by May secured their positions.&lt;ref name=snyde62&gt;{{harvnb|Snyder|2004|p=62}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Polish army forced Soviets to withdraw their left wing from territories south of the [[Neris River]]. Polish advance significantly shortened the Lithuanian–Soviet front line and allowed Lithuania to concentrate its forces for operations in northeastern Lithuania.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it also meant that a new front line with Poland was open. At first, both Poles and Lithuanians cooperated against the Soviets, but soon the cooperation gave way to increasing hostility.&lt;ref name=los47&gt;{{harvnb|Łossowski|1966|p=47}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first clashes between Polish and Lithuanian soldiers occurred on April 26 and May 8 near [[Vievis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=252}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Poland did not recognize Lithuania, as its Chief of State [[Józef Piłsudski]] wanted a union with Lithuania in hopes to revive the old [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] (see [[Międzymorze]] federation).&lt;ref name=lane7&gt;{{harvnb|Lane|2001|p=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poland justified its actions not only as part of a military campaign against the Soviets but also as the right of self-determination of local Poles, who formed a significant minority in eastern Lithuania.&lt;ref name=e71&gt;{{harvnb|Eidintas|1999|pp=71–72}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lithuanians claimed Vilnius as their historical capital and opposed to any federation with Poland, desiring an independent national Lithuanian state.&lt;ref name=snyde62/&gt; The Lithuanian government in Kaunas saw the Polish presence in Vilnius as occupation. In addition to the Vilnius Region, the nearby [[Suwałki Region]] was also disputed. The [[Polish–Lithuanian relations]] were not immediately hostile, but grew worse as each side refused to compromise.&lt;ref name=los47/&gt;

===Lithuanian offensive===
[[File:LT attacks May-June 1919.png|thumb|300px|Lithuanian offensive May–June 1919. Dates indicate when the town was taken by Lithuanian forces. Pink line marks the border of Lithuania since 1990.]]
Polish advances against the Soviets necessitated changes in Lithuanian strategy. On April 26, General [[Silvestras Žukauskas]], who just recovered from [[typhus]], was designated Chief of [[Staff (military)|Staff]].&lt;ref name=rasti/&gt; He decided to mount offensive in northeastern Lithuania. The first objective was to take over [[Ukmergė]]. On May 3, the Separate Panevėžys Volunteer Regiment, supported by the 18th Regiment of Saxon Volunteers, had secured the town. The operation was risky as for a while Kėdainiai was unprotected opening a path to Kaunas,&lt;ref name=cekut/&gt; but also very successful: some 500 Soviets were taken prisoner and about 50 Poles, captured by the Soviets in the battles near Vilnius, were liberated and returned to Poland.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=94}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 7 Lithuanians entered [[Širvintos]], where they found Polish troops. Lithuanians and Poles mounted a joint operation to take [[Giedraičiai]] on May 9.&lt;ref name=cekut&gt;{{harvnb|Čekutis|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Lithuanian army's chain of command was reformed. On May 7, General Žukauskas assumed command of the entire Lithuanian army and initiated a complete reorganization of Lithuanian forces into two groups.&lt;ref name=l97&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=97–98}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first brigade, stationed in Ukmergė, was called the ''Vilkmergė Group'' and included a battalion of Saxon Volunteers. Its first commander [[Kazys Ladiga]] was ordered to push along the [[Utena]]–[[Zarasai]] line.&lt;ref name=cekut/&gt; The second brigade, called the ''Panevėžys Group'', was charged with capturing Panevėžys and then pushing along the [[Kupiškis]]–[[Rokiškis]]–[[Obeliai]] line.&lt;ref name=cekut/&gt; The group, initially commanded by [[Jonas Variakojis]], was aided by Joniškėlis' partisans from the north. The Ministry of Defense and the Staff were also reorganized.&lt;ref name=l97/&gt;

On May 18 the reorganized army carried out its first operation. The Vilkmergė Group captured [[Kurkliai]] and [[Anykščiai]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=106}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 22, the Group launched an attack on Utena. The initiative was met by a Soviet counterattack, and the Lithuanian forces retreated. Further attacks were stopped for several days to wait for the results of the advance on Kupiškis.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ališauskas|1953–1966|p=97}}&lt;/ref&gt; The drive towards Utena resumed on May 31, and the city was secured on June 2. The Panevėžys Group launched a drive towards Panevėžys on May 18 and secured the city the following day, but lost it to a Bolshevik counterattack, carried out on May 21.&lt;ref name=cekut/&gt; However, Soviets left Panevėžys without a fight two days later.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=117}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Group charged towards Kupiškis and secured [[Subačius]]. On May 30 Joniškėlis' partisans broke through the Soviet lines and took Rokiškis in Soviet rear;&lt;ref name=a98&gt;{{harvnb|Ališauskas|1953–1966|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bolshevik forces, afraid that they will encircled, left Kupiškis on the night of May 30–31, and Lithuania secured that city on June 1.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=132}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the capture of Utena, Saxon Volunteers left the front and by mid-July departed from Lithuania.&lt;ref name=cekut/&gt; However, Lithuanian advance continued, and on June 10 Lithuanian forces reached the territory controlled by Latvian partisans (Green Guard) and supplied them with munitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=133}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 12, the Soviets counterattacked and Lithuanians were stopped. Another Soviet push came on June 20 and the front stabilized.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=136}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets were cornered in a small region around [[Zarasai]]. Between July 6 and 12, Lithuanians with some Latvian assistance attempted to drive out the Bolsheviks. The Soviets gathered their forces from calmer fronts and forced Lithuanians to retreat to their former positions.&lt;ref name=a98/&gt;

===Polish–Lithuanian conflict===
[[File:PL-LT War 1919.png|thumb|300px|Map of demarcation lines of June 18 (light green) and July 26 (dark green) between Poland and Lithuania. Poland ignored both lines&lt;ref name=lane7/&gt; and continued to advance up to the orange line. Railroads are marked by black stitched lines.]]
{{main|Polish–Lithuanian War}}
While Lithuanian forces battled the Soviets in northeastern Lithuania, tension between Poland and Lithuania grew. Direct negotiations between May 28 and June 11, 1919 collapsed as neither side was inclined to compromise.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=251–252}}&lt;/ref&gt; Trying to prevent a direct military conflict the Allied Supreme Council drew the first demarcation line on June 18, 1919.&lt;ref name=e71/&gt; The line was drawn several kilometers west of the [[Warsaw – Saint Petersburg Railway]]. Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs rejected it as it required the Polish forces to retread up to {{convert|30|–|35|km|abbr=on}}; Lithuanians were not content with it as well, as it left Vilnius and Hrodna under Polish control.&lt;ref name=los49&gt;{{harvnb|Łossowski|1966|pp=49–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; As German volunteers were departing from Lithuania (their last units left Kaunas in mid-July), Poland mounted an offensive on {{convert|100|km|abbr=on}} wide front moving {{convert|20|–|30|km|abbr=on}} deeper into the Lithuanian territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=254}}&lt;/ref&gt; Preoccupied with Soviet threat, Lithuania could not organize an effective defense and the Entente intervened again by drawing the second demarcation line, known as the [[Foch Line]], on July 26, 1919. Two major modifications were made: [[Suwałki Region]] was assigned to Poland and the entire line was moved about {{convert|7|km|abbr=on}} west.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=254, 257}}&lt;/ref&gt; Neither Lithuanians, Poles, nor Germans (still present in the Suwałki Region) were content with the new demarcation line.&lt;ref name=los51&gt;{{harvnb|Łossowski|1966|p=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between July 29 and August 2, Polish troops carried out several attacks against the Lithuanians.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=258}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 3, a Polish diplomatic mission in Kaunas declared that Poland has no plans to annex Lithuania and proposed a [[plebiscite]] in the contested territories, allowing local inhabitants to determine their future.&lt;ref name=los56&gt;{{harvnb|Łossowski|1966|pp=56–57}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the Lithuanian government rejected the Polish proposal, Józef Piłsudski decided that further military action was not a solution. Instead, the Lithuanian government itself needed to be replaced by a party more willing to negotiate a compromise.&lt;ref name=los56/&gt;&lt;ref name=los66&gt;{{harvnb|Łossowski|1966|p=66}}&lt;/ref&gt; The front stabilized, but bilateral relations worsened in the aftermath of the [[Sejny Uprising]] (August 23 – September 9) which in turn ruined the [[1919 Polish coup d'état attempt in Lithuania|attempted coup d'état]] by the [[Polish Military Organisation]] against the Lithuanian government (August 28–29).&lt;ref name=snyde63&gt;{{harvnb|Snyder|2004|p=63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final battles===
Due to threat from Poland, the front with the Soviets was quiet for more than a month. There were minor incidents involving scouts or outpost guards.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=150}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Red Army used the time to reorganize and strengthen their forces, using natural barriers, like plentiful lakes, rivers, and hills, enhanced with trenches and barbed wires, to secure their position.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also had fortifications built during World War I about {{convert|10|km|abbr=on}} south of [[Daugavpils]].&lt;ref name=a98/&gt; The Soviets had larger forces: Lithuanians had two infantry regiments and five separate battalions; the Soviets had six regiments and one separate battalion.&lt;ref name=a98/&gt; The Lithuanians together with Poles planned to push for [[Daugavpils]] starting August 9, but the plans were delayed until August 23.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|pp=151–152}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ukmergė Group attacked first and captured Zarasai on August 25. The Group moved about {{convert|30|km|abbr=on}} into the Soviet-controlled territory, but neither its right or left flanks were adequately protected by the Polish units or the Panevėžys Group.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=160}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Panevėžys Group began its advance on August 26 and Polish troops moved along the railroad towards [[Turmantas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=164}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lithuanians maneuvered around the old Russian fortifications, forcing the Red Army to retreat.&lt;ref name=a98/&gt; Converging on Daugavpils, the Lithuanian–Soviet front shortened and the Lithuanians were able to concentrate their forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=169}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 28, the Soviets began retreating north across the [[Daugava River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; By August 31, on the southern shore of the Daugava, the Soviet held only Grīva, a suburb of Daugavpils.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ališauskas|1953–1966|p=99}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The enemy was driven out from the Lithuanian territory and the narrow front stabilized as Lithuanians and Soviets were separated by the Daugava River. The Lithuanian main forces could be redeployed elsewhere, including protection of the demarcation line with Poland and planned attacks against the [[Bermontians]] in northern Lithuania.&lt;ref name=l173/&gt; In September 1919, joint Polish and Latvian forces took the southern shore of Daugava, including Grīva. The Lithuanian–Soviet front remained open until the [[Battle of Daugavpils]] when Latvian and Polish forces captured Daugavpils in January 1920. The Lithuanians did not participate in these operations.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lesčius|2004|p=174}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lithuanians claimed the territory, taken by their soldiers, for themselves despite Latvian protests.&lt;ref name=jekab&gt;{{harvnb|Jēkabsons|2006|pp=41–64}}&lt;/ref&gt; This led to several skirmishes between Latvian and Lithuanian troops, but the border issue was successfully mediated by Britain and finally resolved in March 1921.&lt;ref name=jekab/&gt;

==Peace treaty==
[[File:PL-RU war 1919 phase III.svg|thumb|300px|Advance of Soviet forces (red arrows) against Polish troops in June–August 1920]]
{{main|Soviet–Lithuanian Peace Treaty}}

The first Lithuanian–Soviet attempt at negotiations took place on September 11, 1919, after the [[People's Commissar]] of Foreign Affairs of Soviet Russia, [[Georgy Chicherin]], sent a note with a proposal for a [[peace treaty]].&lt;ref name=skiri-a/&gt; However, Lithuanian delayed the talks as it feared that negotiations with communist Russia, which was isolated from European politics, would damage its relationships with the western powers that had not yet recognized Lithuania.&lt;ref name=skiri-a&gt;{{harvnb|Skirius|2002a}}&lt;/ref&gt; The talks began only in May 1920 and were highly influenced by the events in the [[Polish–Soviet War]]. Russia recognized Lithuania's independence and its right to the [[Vilnius Region]]; in exchange Lithuania granted Soviet forces unrestricted movement during the war against Poland.&lt;ref name=snyde63/&gt; This compromised Lithuania's declared neutrality and further deepened the Polish–Lithuanian crisis.&lt;ref name=e70&gt;{{harvnb|Eidintas|1999|p=70}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 14, 1920 the Soviets captured Vilnius, but did not transfer the city to Lithuanian administration, as agreed in the treaty. Instead Soviets planned a coup to overthrow Lithuanian government and establish a Soviet republic.&lt;ref name=e70/&gt; However, Soviets lost the [[Battle of Warsaw (1920)|Battle of Warsaw]] and were pushed back by the Poles. Some historians credit this victory for saving Lithuania's independence from the Soviet coup.&lt;ref name=snyde63/&gt;&lt;ref name=senn/&gt; Despite the [[Soviet–Lithuanian Peace Treaty]], Lithuania was very close to being invaded by the Soviets in summer 1920 and being forcibly incorporated into the Soviet state, and only the Polish victory derailed this plan.&lt;ref name=senn&gt;{{harvnb|Senn|1962|pp=505–506}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 26, the Red Army left Vilnius and Lithuanians prepared to defend their borders as they were drawn in the treaty. This led to further hostilities with Poland as it did not recognize the treaty. Eventually Lithuania lost the Vilnius Region during the [[Żeligowski's Mutiny]]. When mediation at [[League of Nations]] failed to change the situation, Lithuania and Poland were suspended in the state of &quot;no war, no peace&quot; until the [[1938 Polish ultimatum to Lithuania|Polish ultimatum of 1938]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|MacQueen|1998|pp=27–48}}&lt;/ref&gt; During all this time Soviet Russia was Lithuania's strongest ally against Poland.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eidintas|1999|pp=109, 156}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Latvian War of Independence]]
*[[Estonian War of Independence]]

==Notes and references==
;Notes:
{{reflist|22em}}
;References:
{{refbegin}}
* {{citation |first=Kazys |last=Ališauskas | title=Lietuvių enciklopedija | contribution=Lietuvos kariuomenė (1918–1944) | location=Boston, Massachusetts | publisher=Lietuvių enciklopedijos leidykla |year=1953–1966 |volume=XV |id={{LCC|55020366}} |language=lt}}
* {{citation |first=Kazys |last=Blaževičius|url=http://www.xxiamzius.lt/numeriai/2004/11/24/isving_01.html|title=Lietuvos laisvės kovos 1919-1923 metais |date=November 24, 2004 | issue=1291 |volume=88 |journal=XXI amžius|language=lt}}
* {{citation | url=http://www.bernardinai.lt/index.php?url=articles/57787 | title=Laisvės kryžkelės. 1918–1920 m. laisvės kovos |date=January 29, 2007 |first1=Ričardas |last1=Čekutis |publisher=Bernardinai.lt |first2=Dalius |last2=Žygelis |accessdate=2008-08-25|language=lt}}
* {{citation |first=Pranas |last= Čepėnas  |authorlink= Pranas Čepėnas | title=Naujųjų laikų Lietuvos istorija |volume= II |year= 1986 |publisher= Dr. Griniaus fondas | location= Chicago |isbn= 5-89957-012-1 |language=lt}}
* {{citation | first=Norman |last=Davies |title=Europe: A History | publisher=HarperPerennial |year=1998 |isbn=0-06-097468-0 }}
* {{citation | first=Norman |last=Davies |title=God's Playground: A History of Poland |volume=II |url=https://books.google.com/?id=8ODKUkNYqxsC&amp;pg=PA506 |publisher=Columbia University Press |year=1982 |isbn=0-231-05353-3 }}
* {{citation | first1=Alfonsas |last1=Eidintas | first2=Vytautas |last2=Žalys |first3=Alfred Erich |last3=Senn | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback | url=https://books.google.com/?id=0_i8yez8udgC&amp;pg=PA33 | year=1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3}}
* {{citation |first=Ēriks |last=Jēkabsons |url=http://vddb-dt.library.lt/fedora/get/LT-eLABa-0001:J.04~2006~ISSN_1392-6489.V_21.PG_41-66/DS.002.0.01.ARTIC |title=Lietuvos kariuomenė Ilūkstės apskrityje 1919–1920 metais  |journal=Karo archyvas |volume=XXI |issn=1392-6489 |year=2006 |language=lt}}
* {{citation |title=Lietuvos istorija 11–12 klasėms |first1=Rūstis |last1=Kamuntavičius |first2=Vaida |last2=Kamuntavičienė |first3=Remigijus |last3=Civinskas |first4=Kastytis |last4=Antanaitis |year=2001 |publisher=Vaga |location=Vilnius |isbn=5-415-01502-7|language=lt}} 
* {{citation | first=Thomas |last=Lane | url=https://books.google.com/?id=fecMC0LXU-sC&amp;pg=PA7 |title=Lithuania: Stepping Westward |publisher=Routledge |year=2001 |isbn=0-415-26731-5|language=lt}}
* {{citation | first=Tarja |last=Langstrom |title=Transformation in Russia and International Law |url=https://books.google.com/?id=_Y1ITouKQooC&amp;pg=PA52 |publisher=Martinus Nijhoff Publishers |year=2003 |isbn=90-04-13754-8}}
* {{citation | first=Vytautas |last=Lesčius |url=http://www.kam.lt/EasyAdmin/sys/files/LIETUVOS_KARIUOMENE_1.pdf | title=Lietuvos kariuomenė nepriklausomybės kovose 1918–1920 |year=2004 |location=Vilnius |publisher=[[General Jonas Žemaitis Military Academy of Lithuania]] |series=Lietuvos kariuomenės istorija | isbn=9955-423-23-4|language=lt}}
* {{citation | first=Piotr |last=Łossowski |title =Stosunki polsko-litewskie w latach 1918&amp;ndash;1920 |year=1966 | publisher =Książka i Wiedza |location=Warsaw |oclc=9200888|language=pl}}
* {{citation |first=Michael |last=MacQueen |title=The Context of Mass Destruction: Agents and Prerequisites of the Holocaust in Lithuania |journal= Holocaust and Genocide Studies |volume=12 |issue=1 |year=1998 |url= http://hgs.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/12/1/27 |doi=10.1093/hgs/12.1.27}}
* {{citation | first=Stasys |last=Raštikis| url=http://aidai.us/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=843&amp;Itemid=124 |authorlink=Stasys Raštikis |title=Kovos dėl Lietuvos nepriklausomybės 1918–1919 |date=February 1973 |volume=2 |journal=[[Aidai]] |issn=0002-208X|language=lt}}
* {{citation | first=Georg von |last=Rauch | title=The Baltic States: The Years of Independence |year=1970 |publisher=University of California Press| isbn=0-520-02600-4 }}
* {{citation | first=Alfred Erich |last=Senn |authorlink=Alfred Erich Senn |title=The Formation of the Lithuanian Foreign Office, 1918–1921| journal=Slavic Review | issue=21 |volume=3 |date=September 1962 |issn=0037-6779 | doi=10.2307/3000451}}
* {{citation | first=Juozas |last=Skirius | title=Gimtoji istorija. Nuo 7 iki 12 klasės | url=http://mkp.emokykla.lt/gimtoji/ | accessdate=2008-03-30 | year=2002a | publisher=Elektroninės leidybos namai | location=Vilnius | isbn=9986-9216-9-4 | chapter=Lietuvos–Rusijos Sovietų Federacinės Socialistinės Respublikos taikos sutartis | chapterurl=http://mkp.emokykla.lt/gimtoji/?id=1018|language=lt}}
* {{citation | first=Juozas |last=Skirius | title=Gimtoji istorija. Nuo 7 iki 12 klasės | url=http://mkp.emokykla.lt/gimtoji/ | accessdate=2008-08-26 | year=2002b | publisher=Elektroninės leidybos namai | location=Vilnius | isbn=9986-9216-9-4 | chapter=Nepriklausomybės kovos 1918–1920 metais | chapterurl=http://mkp.emokykla.lt/gimtoji/?id=1017|language=lt}}
* {{citation | first=Timothy |last=Snyder | title=The Reconstruction of Nations: Poland, Ukraine, Lithuania, Belarus, 1569–1999 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=xSpEynLxJ1MC&amp;pg=PA63 |publisher=Yale University Press |year=2004 |isbn=0-300-10586-X }}
* {{citation | first=Liudas |last=Truska | title=Lietuvos Respublikos prezidentai |editor-first=Antanas |editor-last=Drilinga |publisher=Valstybės leidybos centras |location=Vilnius |year=1995 | isbn=9986-09-055-5|language=lt}}
* {{citation | first=James D. |last=White| title=National Communism and World Revolution: The Political Consequences of German Military Withdrawal from the Baltic Area in 1918–19  |journal=Europe–Asia Studies |issue=46 |volume=8 |year=1994 |issn=0966-8136}}
{{refend}}
{{Russian Conflicts}}
{{Lithuania topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lithuanian-Soviet War}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1918]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1919]]
[[Category:Wars involving Lithuania]]
[[Category:Wars involving Russia]]
[[Category:Lithuanian–Russian wars]]
[[Category:1918 in Lithuania]]
[[Category:1919 in Lithuania]]
[[Category:Russian Civil War]]
[[Category:Lithuania–Soviet Union relations]]
[[Category:Wars involving Germany]]
[[Category:Germany–Soviet Union relations]]</text>
      <sha1>ltvaj5x0atqoa2vskbii41zkj3o40pq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
