<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>M3 Half-track</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1873940</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748356210</id>
      <parentid>741376955</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T20:36:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Valentinejoesmith</username>
        <id>205654</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Former operators */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26562">{{infobox weapon
| name               = Carrier, Personnel Half-track M3
| image              = [[File:Halftrack-fort-knox-1.jpg|300px|border]]
| image_size         =
| alt                =
| caption            = An M3 half-track at Fort Knox.
| origin             = [[United States]]
| type               = [[Half-track]] [[armored personnel carrier]]
&lt;!-- Type selection --&gt;
| is_vehicle         = yes
&lt;!-- Service history --&gt;
| service            = 
| used_by            = 
| wars               = 
&lt;!-- Production history --&gt;
| designer           = 
| design_date        = 
| manufacturer       = Autocar &lt;br&gt; Diamond T &lt;br&gt; White Motor Company
| unit_cost          = 
| production_date    = 
| number             =  
| variants           =
&lt;!-- General specifications --&gt;
| spec_label         = M3&lt;ref&gt;http://afvdb.50megs.com/usa/halftrackm3.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| weight             = 20,000 lb (9.07 metric tons)
| length             = 20 ft 2 5/8 in (6.17 m) with roller
| width              = 6 ft 5 1/4 in (1.96 m)
| height             = 7 ft 5 in (2.26 m)
| crew               = 1
| passengers         = 12
&lt;!-- Vehicle/missile specifications --&gt;
| armour             = 0.25-0.50 in (13.2-25.4 mm)
| primary_armament   = 
| secondary_armament = 
| engine             = White 160AX
| engine_power       = 147 hp (110 kW) at 3,000 rpm
| pw_ratio           = 16.2 hp/metric ton
| payload_capacity   = 
| transmission       = Spicer 3461 constant mesh
| suspension         = Front: semi-elliptic longitudinal leaf spring &lt;br&gt; Rear: Vertical volute spring
| fuel_capacity      = 60 US gallons (230 litres)
| vehicle_range      = 200 mi (320 km) 
| speed              = 45 mph (72 kph) on road
| steering = Steering wheel
}}

The '''M3 Half-track''', known officially as the '''Carrier, Personnel Half-track M3''', was an [[United States|American]] [[armored personnel carrier]] widely used by the Allies during [[World War II]] and in the [[Cold War]]. Derived from the [[M2 Half Track Car]], the slightly longer M3 was extensively produced, with about 15,000 units and more than 50,000 derivative variants manufactured (most of which were interim designs).

The design was based on the [[Kégresse track|Citroen-Kégresse half-track]]. The developers attempted to use as many commercial parts as possible. There were also several dozen variants for different purposes. The M3 and its variants were supplied to the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] and [[United States Marine Corps|Marines]], as well as [[British Commonwealth]] and Soviet [[Red Army]] forces, serving on all major fronts throughout the war. Although at first unpopular, it was used by most of the Allies at some point in the war.

== Design ==
Racks under the seats were used for ammunition and rations; additional racks behind the seat backs held the squad's rifles and other stowage. A small rack for mines was added on the outside of the hull just above the tracks. In combat, most units found it necessary to stow additional food, rucksacks and other crew stowage on the outside of the vehicle. Luggage racks were often added in the field, and very late vehicles had rear-mounted racks for this crew stowage.&lt;ref name=Zaloga6&gt;Zaloga (1994), pp. 6–7&lt;/ref&gt;

Early vehicles had a pintle mount, just behind the front seats, that mounted a .50-caliber (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) [[M2 Browning machine gun]]. The later M3A1 adopted a raised, armored 'pulpit mount' for the .50-caliber, and .30-caliber (7.62&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns could be used from mounts along the sides of the passenger compartment. Many M3s were later modified to the M3A1 standard. The body was armored all around, with an adjustable armored shutter for the engine's radiator and a bulletproof windscreen.&lt;ref name=Zaloga6 /&gt;

== Development ==
[[File:M3 half track 9-08-2008 14-47-56.JPG|thumb|upright|float|left|On display in Ursel (Northwest of [[Ghent]]), Belgium]]
Between the world wars, the U.S. Army sought to improve the tactical mobility of its forces. With the goal of finding a high-mobility infantry vehicle, the Ordnance Department had evaluated the [[half-track]] design by testing French [[Kégresse track|Citroën-Kégresse]] vehicles. The [[White Motor Company]] produced a prototype halftrack using their own chassis and the body of the [[M3 Scout Car]].&lt;ref name=Zaloga3 /&gt;

The design, using as many commercial components as possible to improve reliability and the rate of production, was standardized in 1940 and built by the [[Autocar Company]], [[Diamond T]] Motor Company, and the [[White Motor Company]].&lt;ref name=Zaloga3 /&gt; Offered with a choice of White 160AX or IHC Red Diamond 450 engines, the M3 was driven through a [[manual transmission|manual]] constant-mesh (non-synchromesh) transmission with four forward and one reverse gear, as well as a two-speed transfer case. The front suspension was leaf spring, tracks by vertical [[volute spring]]. Braking was vacuum-assisted hydraulic, steering manual, without power assist. The electrical system was 12-volt.&lt;ref name=Berndt152&gt;Berndt (1993), p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt;

The M3 was the larger and longer counterpart to the [[M2 Half Track Car]]. The M2 was originally intended to function as an artillery tractor. The M3 had a single access door in the rear and seating for a 12-man rifle squad. Five seats were arranged on each side in the rear of the vehicle and three seats inside the cab.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Hufper |first=Simon |date=30 September 2013 |title=Historic M3 vehicles leave USAG Bamberg |url=http://www.army.mil/article/112358/Historic_M3_vehicles_leave_USAG_Bamberg/ |newspaper=Franconian News |accessdate=23 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Service history==
Although originally intended for armored infantry regiments, it was quickly put into action with the Provisional Tank Group when the [[Philippines Campaign (1941–42)|Japanese Army began their invasion of the Philippines]]. Initially, there were multiple complaints due to several mechanical difficulties. These were rectified by the Ordnance Department after receiving field reports from the Philippines. The M3's first use for its intended role was during [[Operation Torch]]. Each armored division had 433 M2s or M3s, 200 in the armored regiments and 233 in the armored infantry regiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zaloga8&quot; /&gt;

The halftracks were initially extremely unpopular and dubbed &quot;[[Purple Heart]] Boxes&quot; (a grim reference to the US Army's decoration for combat wounds) by American troops. The chief complaints centered on the complete lack of overhead protection from airbursting artillery shells and that the armor was inadequate against machine gun fire. [[Omar Bradley]] quoted in his report about half-tracks that it was &quot;a competent and dependable contrivance. Its bad name resulted from the inexperience of our troops who attempted to use it for too many things&quot;.&lt;ref name=Zaloga8&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1943, the M3 served in [[Allied invasion of Sicily|Sicily]] and [[Operation Avalanche|Italy]] and received positive reports of it in action. It went into service in 1944 in [[Operation Overlord]] and served in Europe for the remainder of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga (1994), pp. 15–16.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Production===
Total production of the M3 ran to nearly 41,000 vehicles. To supply the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] nations [[International Harvester]] produced several thousand of a very similar vehicle, the [[M5 Half-track]] for [[Lend-Lease]].&lt;ref name=Zaloga12&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Variants ==

=== Armored personnel carriers ===
[[File:M5 inter.jpg|thumb|The [[M5 Half-track|M5]] personnel carrier]]
* M3 – White and [[Autocar_Company|Autocar]] Half-Track with White {{convert|386|in3|cc|abbr=on}} 160AX engine. Fitted with either an M32 anti-aircraft machine gun mount or a pedestal mount, both featuring an M2HB machine gun.&lt;ref name=Berndt152 /&gt;
** M3A1 – A M3 with the improved M49 machine gun ring mount over the right hand front seat. Between 1942 and 1943 all M3 Half-Tracks (standard and A1s) were continually upgraded. These improvements included a number of drive train, engine, and stowage improvements.&lt;ref name=Berndt152 /&gt;
** T29/M3A2 – Developed in 1943 to combine features such that existing M2 and M3 production could be switched to a common vehicle. Came at a time where the need for additional half tracks turned out to be not as great as projected. The M3A2 was, therefore, not produced.&lt;ref name=Berndt152 /&gt;
* M3E2/[[M5 Half-track]] – International Harvester Half-Track, externally largely identical to the M3, but with {{convert|450|in3|cc|abbr=on}},&lt;ref name=Berndt152 /&gt; IHC RED-450-B engine, different drive train and fuel and electrical system. In fact, only the chassis, bogies, track, idler and drive sprockets, wheels, winches, transfer case, rollers, and machine gun mount were interchangeable. The M5 is heavier than the M3, due in part to heavier armor. Its body was welded, rather than bolted. The M5 was primarily for Lend-Lease, to Britain, Canada, France, and the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=Berndt147&gt;Berndt (1993), p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;
** M5A1 – As for the M3A1, an M5 with the M49 machine gun mount. It could fit one .50-caliber (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) and two .30-caliber (30.06) machine guns.&lt;ref name=Berndt147 /&gt; The IHC models had a slightly lower top speed (only {{convert|42|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}) and lower range ({{convert|125|mi|km|abbr=on}}) as well.&lt;ref name=Berndt152 /&gt;
** T31/M5A2 – Similar in principle to the M3A2, a vehicle developed by the US Ordnance Department to combine the production of the M5 and M9 into a single vehicle. As with the M3A2, the projected need was never seen, and this version was never produced en masse.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt52&gt;Hunnicutt (2001), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[M9 Half-track]] – Same vehicle as the M5, with stowage arranged as in the [[M2 Half Track Car|M2 halftrack]], with access to radios from inside (as opposed to outside) and rear doors, plus pedestal MG mount.&lt;ref name=Berndt147 /&gt;
** M9A1 – Same as M9, with ring mount and three MG pintles.&lt;ref name=Berndt147 /&gt;

=== Self-propelled guns ===
[[File:T48 57 mm GMC SU-57 Poklonnaya Hill Moscow 2.JPG|thumb|A T48 57&amp;nbsp;mm GMC / SU-57 in the [[Museum of the Great Patriotic War, Moscow|Museum of the Great Patriotic War]], Poklonnaya Hill Victory Park]]
[[File:M3 75mm Bougainville, Solomon Islands November 1943.jpg|thumb|A M3 GMC on the [[Bougainville Island]], in the Solomon Islands, November 1943]]

* [[M3 Gun Motor Carriage|T12/M3 75&amp;nbsp;mm GMC]] – M3 based Gun Motor Carriage equipped with the M1897A5 75&amp;nbsp;mm gun. These vehicles were fitted with the M2A3 gun carriage and shield.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt98&gt;Hunnicutt (2001), p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt;
** M3A1 75&amp;nbsp;mm GMC – The M2A2 gun carriage was substituted for the A3, as stocks were exhausted. Later variants featured a purpose-built gun shield (59 rounds).&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt98 /&gt;
* [[T19 Howitzer Motor Carriage|T19 105&amp;nbsp;mm HMC]] – M3 based Howitzer Motor Carriage equipped with the [[M101 howitzer|M2A1 105&amp;nbsp;mm howitzer]] (8 rounds).&lt;ref name=Zaloga36 /&gt;
* T19/[[M21 Mortar Motor Carriage|M21 81&amp;nbsp;mm MMC]] – M3-based Motor Mortar Carriage equipped with the [[M1 mortar]] (81&amp;nbsp;mm)(97 rounds), designed to allow the mortar to be fired from within the vehicle.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt110&gt;Hunnicutt (2001, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt;
* T21 – M3 based mortar carrier fitted with a [[M2 4.2 Inch Mortar|4.2 inch mortar]]. Never adopted.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt96&gt;Hunnicutt (2001), p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt;
** T21E1 – The T21's mortar could only fire rearward as with the M2 based [[M2 Half Track Car#Self-propelled guns|M4 MMC]]. The T21E1 reoriented to the mortar to fire forward.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt96 /&gt;
* [[T30 Howitzer Motor Carriage|T30 75&amp;nbsp;mm HMC]] – M3 based Howitzer Motor Carriage equipped with the [[M116 howitzer|M1A1 75&amp;nbsp;mm howitzer]] in a simple box mount (60 rounds). Used by the US Army. Also provided to the [[Free French Forces|Free French Army]], later used in [[Indochina]].&lt;ref name=Zaloga36&gt;Zaloga (1994), pp. 36–37&lt;/ref&gt;
* T38 105&amp;nbsp;mm HMC – M3 based Howitzer Motor Carriage equipped with the [[M3 howitzer|M3 105&amp;nbsp;mm howitzer]]. Cancelled with the success of the T19 105&amp;nbsp;mm HMC.&lt;ref&gt;Hunnicutt (2001), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[T48 Gun Motor Carriage]] – M3 based Gun Motor Carriage equipped with the M1 57&amp;nbsp;mm gun, an American copy of the British [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|QF 6 pounder]] anti-tank gun. A total of 962 T48s were produced during the war. Of these, 60 were supplied under lend lease to Britain, and 650 to the USSR – who called it '''SU-57''' (99 rounds). 31 ended up getting converted into M3A1s, while one entered service with the U.S. Army.&lt;ref name=Zaloga35&gt;Zaloga (1994), pp. 35–36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mesko, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Anti-aircraft variants {{anchor|Anti-aircraft variants}}&lt;!--linked from another article--&gt; ===
* T1E4/[[M13 Half-track]] – M3 based Multiple Gun Motor Carriage equipped with the Maxson M33 mount with two M2HB machine guns (5,000 rounds). The T1E4 prototypes had the hull sides removed for ease of working with the mount. These were reintroduced on production M13s. This was a development of previous [[M2 Half Track Car#Anti-aircraft variants|T1s]] that had all been based on the M2 Half-track Car.&lt;ref name=Zaloga38 /&gt;
** [[M14 Half-track]] – M13 MGMC variant, based on the M5 chassis. Supplied under lend-lease to Britain (5,000 rounds).&lt;ref name=Zaloga38&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:US Army M16 MGMC AA Half-track.jpg|thumb|A M16 MGMC in action in [[Korean War|Korea]], 1953]]
* [[M16 Half-track]] – M3 based Multiple Gun Motor Carriage equipped with the Maxson [[M45 Quadmount]] (specifically the M45D) with four M2HB machine guns (5,000 rounds).&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt123&gt;Hunnicutt (2001), pp. 123–126&lt;/ref&gt;
** M16A1 MGMC – Standard M3 Personnel Carriers converted to Multiple Gun Motor Carriages by removing rear seats and installing a Maxson M45 mount (more specifically the M45F, which featured folding &quot;bat wing&quot; gun shields on both sides of the mount over the machine guns). These vehicles are easily identified by the lack of the folding armored hull panels found on purpose-built M16s.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt123 /&gt;
** M16A2 MGMC – M16 MGMC variant, basically M16s brought up to M16A1 standard and with the addition of a rear door to the hull compartment. For existing M16s, this essentially meant a replacement of the M45D mount for the M45F mount.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt123 /&gt;
** [[M17 Half-track]] – M16 MGMC variant, based on the M5 chassis. Sent under lend-lease to USSR (5,000 rounds).&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt123 /&gt;
* T58 – Similar to the M16/M17, the T58 featured the Maxon quad-mount fitted to a special electric powered turret. Prototype only.&lt;ref name=Zaloga42/&gt;
* T28E1 CGMC – M3 based Combination Gun Motor Carriage equipped with one [[37mm Gun M1|M1A2 37&amp;nbsp;mm autocannon]] (240 rounds) flanked by 2 M2WC machine guns (3,400 rounds). The original [[M2 Half Track Car#Anti-aircraft variants|T28]] had been based on the shorter M2 Half-Track Car chassis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S9YDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA7&amp;dq=Popular+Science+1935+plane+%22Popular+Mechanics%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Uu44TpGOEquGsgLepeUC&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwADgU#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true|title=Hit-Run Ack-Ack Guns Mounted on a Half-Track|journal=Popular Mechanics |date=December 1943|publisher=Hearst Corporation|location=New York, NY |accessdate=3 August 2011}} (including [https://books.google.com/books?id=S9YDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA0&amp;dq=Popular+Science+1935+plane+%22Popular+Mechanics%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Uu44TpGOEquGsgLepeUC&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwADgU#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true &quot;cover artwork&quot;])&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[M15 Half-track]] – T28E1 variant, equipped with an armored superstructure on the turreted mount to provide crew protection, and switched to M2HB machine guns.&lt;ref name=Berndt33&gt;Berndt (1994), p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;
** M15A1 CGMC – Reorganization of the weapons, with the M2HB machine guns being fitted under the M1A2 37&amp;nbsp;mm autocannon instead of above as on the M15.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt131&gt;Hunnicutt (2001), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;
* T10E1 – Variant to test the feasibility of mounting US made copies of the [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404]] 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon on modified Maxson mounts. All were later rebuilt as M16s. The original [[M2 Half Track Car#Anti-aircraft variants|T10]] was based on the shorter M2 Half-Track Car chassis.&lt;ref name=Zaloga39&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

====40&amp;nbsp;mm Experiments====
Various attempts were made to mate the [[40 mm Bofors|40&amp;nbsp;mm Bofors]] L/50 gun to the M3 chassis. In most cases the weapon's recoil was too severe or the mounting too heavy, and the attempts were finally stopped with the adoption of the [[M24 Chaffee#Variants|M19 MGMC on the M24 light tank chassis]].&lt;ref name=Gander231 /&gt;
* T54/E1 – Tested in 1942, the gun mount quickly proved to be unstable when fired, and the improved T54E1, which also added a circular armored shield and rear armor to the vehicle, could not fix the inherent problem. Prototype only.&lt;ref name=Gander231&gt;Gander (2013), p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt;
* T59 – A development of the T54/E1, fitted with outriggers to help stabilize the vehicle during sustained firing. Still proved to be too unstable for anti-aircraft use. Prototype only.&lt;ref name=Gander231 /&gt;
** T59E1 – T59 fitted with the T17 fire control system. Prototype only.&lt;ref name=Gander231 /&gt;
* T60/E1 – Similar to the T54 and the T59, but featured two .50 caliber M2 machine guns flanking the 40&amp;nbsp;mm cannon (the mounting's designation was T65). The T60E1 featured an armor configuration similar to that of the T54E1. Suffered from the same stability issues as previous attempts. Prototype only.&lt;ref name=Gander232 /&gt;
* T68 – Perhaps the most radical of the experiments, the T68 featured two 40&amp;nbsp;mm cannons, one mounted on top of the other, plus a stabilizer on top of the two guns. The recoil force proved to be too much for the mount, and the idea was abandoned. Prototype only.&lt;ref name=Gander232&gt;Gander (2013), p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt;
* M15 &quot;Special&quot; – Field conversions by US Army depots in [[Australia]] of standard M3s, not M15s, fitted with turreted [[40 mm Bofors]] L/50 guns. These were the only successful mating of this weapon to the M3 chassis, and were used more for direct fire support than for anti-aircraft purposes.&lt;ref name=Berndt33 /&gt;
* M34 – Like the M15 &quot;Special&quot; above, 102 M15s were converted to M34s in Japan in 1951. The M34 mounted a single 40&amp;nbsp;mm Bofors gun in place of the M15's combination gun mount. This was due primarily to a shortage of 37&amp;nbsp;mm ammunition, which was no longer manufactured. M34s served with at least two AAA (automatic weapons) battalions (the 26th and 140th) in the Korean War.&lt;ref name=Hunnicutt194&gt;Hunnicutt (2001), p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Post-war Israeli variants ===
[[File:M3-Halftrack-with-20mm-cannon.jpg|thumb|An Israeli modified M3 Half-track, armed with a 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon]]
* M3 Mk. A – M5 APC. Israeli Half-Tracks were all designated M3, even M2/M9 variants and known as Zachlam זחל&quot;ם in Hebrew. The Mk. An APCs are identified as IHC M5s by the use of RED-450 engines for the most part. While the M49 mount was retained, a variety of machine guns were used.&lt;ref name=Zaloga24&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;
* M3 Mk. B – M5 converted as a command carrier with extra radios and a front winch bumper. Mk. Bs featured M2HB machine guns.&lt;ref name=Zaloga24 /&gt;
* M3 Mk. C – Essentially an M21 MMC, an M3 type (assumed from the common use of the White 160AX engine) Half-Track with an M1 81&amp;nbsp;mm Mortar.&lt;ref name=Zaloga24 /&gt;
* M3 Mk. D – Another M3 based mortar carrier, fitted with the [[Soltam M-65|120 mm Soltam mortar]]. Entered service in 1960.&lt;ref name=Zaloga24 /&gt;
* M3 TCM-20 – M3/M5 Half-Tracks fitted with the Israeli [[TCM-20]] armament turret with two 20&amp;nbsp;mm [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404]] cannon fitted to old Maxson turrets. The right hand vision port was often replaced with a ball mount for a machine gun. They proved to be very effective fighting anti-tank missile teams, their cannons would at least keep the teams under cover or [[Suppressive fire|suppress]] them so they could not use their missiles effectively.&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Former operators ==
* {{flag|Belgium|size=23px}} – [[Belgian Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Brazil|1960|size=23px}}&lt;ref name=Zaloga42 /&gt;
* {{flag|Canada|1921|size=23px}} – [[Canadian Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga13&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Chile|size=23px}}&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Republic of China (1912–49)|size=23px}} – [[National Revolutionary Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Czechoslovakia|size=23px}}&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Denmark|size=23px}} – [[Danish Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga42 /&gt;
* {{flag|Dominican Republic|size=23px}} – [[Dominican Army]] 16 still in service. &lt;ref name=Zaloga42 /&gt;
* {{flag|France|size=23px}} – [[French Army]]&lt;ref name= Zaloga21&gt;Zaloga (1994), pp. 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Nazi Germany|size=23px}} – The German [[Wehrmacht]] used captured vehicles in the north African and western fronts during World War II.&lt;ref name=Zaloga36/&gt;
* {{flag|West Germany|size=23px}} – West German [[Bundeswehr]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga42 /&gt;
* {{flag|Greece|size=23px}} – [[Greek Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Israel|size=23px}} – [[Israeli Defense Forces]] (IDF)&lt;ref name=Zaloga23&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Italy|size=23px}} – [[Italian Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|India|size=23px}} – [[Indian Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Japan|1947|size=23px}} – [[Japan Ground Self-Defense Force|GSDF]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga42&gt;Zaloga (1994), p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Lebanon|size=23px}} – [[Lebanese Army]]
* {{flag|Mali|size=23px}} – [[Military of Mali|Malian Army]]&lt;ref name=trade&gt;{{cite web|url=http://armstrade.sipri.org/armstrade/page/trade_register.php |title=Trade Registers |publisher=Stockholm International Peace Research Institute |date=2009 |accessdate=20 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Mexico|size=23px}}&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|New Zealand|size=23px}}&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Norway|size=23px}}&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Pakistan|size=23px}} – [[Pakistani Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga42 /&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Philippine Commonwealth|size=23px}} – [[Philippine Army]] and [[Philippine Constabulary]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Portugal|size=23px}} – [[Portuguese Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Poland|size=23px}}&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Soviet Union|1923|size=23px}} – [[Red Army|Soviet Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|Turkey|size=23px}} – [[Turkish Army]]&lt;ref name=Zaloga42 /&gt;
* {{flag|United Kingdom|size=23px}} – British Army&lt;ref name=Zaloga21 /&gt;
* {{flag|United States|1912|size=23px}} – United States Army&lt;ref name=Zaloga3&gt;Zaloga (1994), pp. 3–5&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Yugoslavia|size=23px}} – [[Yugoslav People's Army]]&lt;ref name=&quot;B81&quot;&gt;Bishop, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Non-state former operators===
*&lt;!-- Commented out: [[Image:Logo of Lebanese Forces.png|22px]] --&gt; [[Lebanese Forces (militia)|Lebanese Forces]] – supplied by Israel.&lt;ref&gt;Kassis, ''30 Years of Military Vehicles in Lebanon'' (2003), pp. 41-47.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[South Lebanon Army]] (SLA) – supplied by Israel.&lt;ref&gt;Kassis, ''30 Years of Military Vehicles in Lebanon'' (2003), pp. 85-89.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[File:Flag of the Amal Movement.svg|22px]] [[Lebanese Resistance Regiments|Amal Movement]] – captured from the SLA.&lt;ref&gt;El-Assad, ''Blue Steel: M-3 Halftracks in South Lebanon'' (2006), p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kassis, ''30 Years of Military Vehicles in Lebanon'' (2003), p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon image|InfoboxHez.PNG}} [[Hezbollah]] – captured from the SLA.

== See also ==
{{Portal|World War II|Half-track|Cold War}}
* [[List of U.S. military vehicles by supply catalog designation]]
* [[List of U.S. military vehicles by model number]]
* [[Sd.Kfz. 251]]

== References ==

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
* Berndt, Thomas (1993). ''Standard Catalog of U.S. Military Vehicles''. Iola, WI: Krause Publications. ISBN 0-87341-223-0.
* {{cite book |last=Berndt |first=Thomas |date=1994 |title=American Tanks of World War II |url=https://www.google.com.au/search?tbo=p&amp;tbm=bks&amp;q=ISBN0-87938-930-3&amp;gws_rd=cr&amp;ei=n3-qVITaCcXPmwWdi4K4CA |location=Minneapolis, MN |publisher=MBI Publishing Company |isbn=0-87938-930-3}}
* {{cite book |last=Bishop |first=Chris |date=1998 |title=The Encyclopedia of Weapons of WWII |location=London, UK |publisher=Orbis Publishing and Aerospace Publishing |isbn=0-7607-1022-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Gander |first=Terry |date=2013 |title=The Bofors Gun |location=Barnsley, UK |publisher=Pen and Sword|isbn=1-4738-3680-8}}
* {{cite book | title=Half-tracks: A History of American Semi-Tracked Vehicles | publisher=Presidio Press | author=Hunnicutt, R.P. | year=2001 | location=Santa Barbara, CA | isbn=0-89141-742-7}}
* Mesko, Jim (1996). ''M3 Half-tracks in Action''. Carrollton, TX: Squadron/Signal Publications. ISBN 0-89747-363-9
* {{cite book
|last=Zaloga
|first=Steven J.
|year=1994
|title=M3 Infantry Half-Track 1940–73
|location=Oxford, UK
|publisher=Osprey Publishing
|isbn=1-85532-467-9
}}
* Moustafa El-Assad, ''Blue Steel 2: M-3 Halftracks in South Lebanon'', Blue Steel books, Sidon 2006. 
* Samer Kassis, ''30 Years of Military Vehicles in Lebanon'', Beirut: Elite Group, 2003. ISBN 9953-0-0705-5

==Further reading==
* Janda, Patryk (2009). ''Half-Track Vol. I''. Gdańsk, Poland: Aj-Press Publishing. ISBN 978-83-7237-207-9
* United States, Department of War (1944). ''TM 9-710 Basic Half-Track Vehicles (White, Autocar, and Diamond T)''. Washington, D.C.: Department of War. {{oclc|853748834}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|M3 Halftrack}}
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=hCQDAAAAMBAJ&amp;lpg=PA151&amp;dq=m3%20half-track&amp;as_brr=1&amp;pg=PA151#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Half-track Gets Farm Job]
* [http://www.wwiivehicles.com/united-states/vehicle/half-tracks/m3-half-track.asp WWII Vehicles – US Half tracks]
* [http://www.lonesentry.com/manuals/fm17-71-halftrack-crew-drill/index.html FM 17–71: Crew Drill for Half-Track Vehicles]
* {{fr}} [http://www.tsahal-miniature.com/halftrac.html The various versions of Israeli Half-track]

{{WWIIAmericanAFVs}}

[[Category:World War II armored fighting vehicles of the United States|M3]]
[[Category:Armored personnel carriers of the United States]]
[[Category:Armoured personnel carriers of Israel|M3]]
[[Category:World War II half-tracks]]
[[Category:Half-tracks of the United States]]
[[Category:Cold War Half-tracks]]</text>
      <sha1>2xpqx9syrbfqjyuu9cqippytj3zqin5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
