<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Musha incident</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>882887</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749896100</id>
      <parentid>749293664</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T18:47:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>141.239.154.191</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Consequences */ added violation of Geneva Protocol</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12860">{{infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Musha Incident
| partof      = 
| image       = [[File:The scene of the Wushe Incident.JPG|300px]]
| caption     = A photo taken by the Japanese authorities in the aftermath of the Incident.
| date        = October 27 - December 1930
| place       = Musha, Nōkō District, [[Taichū Prefecture]], [[Taiwan under Japanese rule|Japanese Taiwan]] (modern-day [[Ren'ai, Nantou|Ren'ai Township]], [[Nantou County]], [[Taiwan]])
| coordinates = 
| map_type    = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_marksize =
| map_caption = 
| map_label   = 
| territory   = 
| result      = Japanese victory
| status      = 
| combatant1  = [[Seediq people#Background|Tkdaya]]&lt;ref name=&quot;culture.tw&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | title=Wushe Incident - Encyclopedia of Taiwan| work=| url=http://taiwanpedia.culture.tw/en/content?ID=3722| date=| year=| accessdate=November 23, 2012|dead-url=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant2  = {{flag|Empire of Japan}}&lt;br&gt;[[Seediq people#Background|Toda]]&lt;br&gt;[[Truku people|Truku]]&lt;ref name=&quot;culture.tw&quot;/&gt; (Taroko)
| combatant3  = 
| commander1  = [[Mona Rudao]]{{KIA}}
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} Eizo Ishizuka
| commander3  = 
| units1      =
| units2      =
| units3      = 
| strength1   = ~1,200
| strength2   = ~2,000 
| strength3   = 
| casualties1 = 644 killed&lt;ref name=&quot;culture.tw&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--Casualties for the &quot;Second Wushe Incident&quot; in 1931 are not included.--&gt;
| casualties2 = ~134 killed and 215 wounded on the October 27th attack&lt;ref name=&quot;culture.tw&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;Military casualties unknown.
| casualties3 = 
| notes       = 
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Taiwanese rebellions against Japan}}
}}

The '''Musha Incident''' ({{CJKV|c=霧社事件|j=霧社事件|r=Musha Jiken|w=Wu&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;-she&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Shih&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;-chien&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;|p=Wùshè Shìjiàn}}; {{zh|poj=Bū-siā Sū-kiāⁿ}}), also known as the '''Wushe Rebellion''' and several other similar names, began in October 1930 and was the last major [[Rebellion|uprising]] against colonial [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] forces in [[Taiwan under Japanese rule|Japanese Taiwan]]. In response to long-term oppression by Japanese authorities, the [[Seediq people|Seediq]] indigenous group in Musha (Wushe) attacked the village, killing over 130 Japanese. In response, the Japanese led a relentless counter-attack, killing over 600 Seediq in retaliation. The handling of the incident by the Japanese authorities was strongly criticised, leading to many changes in aboriginal policy.

==Background==
Previous armed resistance to Japanese imperial authority had been dealt with harshly, as evident in responses to previous uprisings such as the [[Tapani Incident]], which resulted in a cycle of rebel attacks and strict Japanese retaliation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Roy |first1=Denny |year=2003|title=Taiwan: A Political History |publisher=Cornell University Press |location=Ithaca |isbn=9780801488054 |page= 35|ref=harv |chapter=The Japanese Occupation}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, by the 1930s, armed resistance had largely been replaced by organised political and social movements among the younger Taiwanese generation. Direct police involvement in local administration had been relaxed, many harsh punishments were abolished, and some elements of self-government, albeit of questionable effectiveness, had been introduced to colonial Taiwan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Harry J.|last=Lamley|chapter=Taiwan Under Japanese Rule, 1895-1945: The Vicissitudes of Colonialism |year=2007 |title=Taiwan: A New History |editor=Rubinstein, Murry A. |publisher=M.E. Sharpe |place=New York |isbn=9780765614940 |edition=expanded|page=224}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, a different approach was used in order to control Taiwan's indigenous peoples. [[Taiwanese aborigines]] were still designated as {{nihongo||生蕃|seiban|&quot;raw barbarians&quot; or &quot;wild tribespeople&quot;}}, and treated as savages rather than equal subjects. Tribes were 'tamed' through assimilation, the process of disarming traditional hunting tribes and forcing them to relocate to the plains and lead an agrarian existence. Further resistance was then dealt with by military campaigns, isolation and containment.{{sfnp|Roy|2003|p=49}} In order to access natural resources in mountainous and forested indigenous-controlled areas, Governor-General [[Sakuma Samata]] adopted a more aggressive terrain policy, attempting to pacify or eradicate aboriginal groups in areas scheduled for logging within five years; by 1915, this policy had been largely successful, although resistance still existed in more remote areas.{{sfnp|Roy|2003|p=51}}

===Proximal causes===
The Seediq aborigines in the vicinity of Musha had been considered by Japanese authorities to be one of the most successful examples of this &quot;taming&quot; approach, with [[Tribal chief|Chief]] [[Mouna Rudao]] being one of 43 indigenous leaders selected for a tour of Japan a few years earlier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Chien-Chao|last1=Hung|title=A history of Taiwan|date=2000|publisher=Il Cerchio|location=Rimini|isbn=9788886583800|page=222|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, resentment still lingered, due largely to police misconduct, the continuing practice of forced labor, and the ill treatment of indigenous beliefs and customs.{{sfnp|Roy|2003|p=51}}

In the days immediately prior to the incident, chief Mouna Rudao held a traditional wedding banquet for his son Daho Mona, during which animals were slaughtered and wine was prepared and drunk. A Japanese police officer named Katsuhiko Yoshimura was on patrol in the area, and was offered a cup of wine by Daho Mouna as a symbolic gesture. The officer refused, saying that Daho Mouna's hands were soiled with blood from the slaughtered animals. Daho Mouna attempted to take hold of the officer, insisting he participate, and the officer struck him with his stick. Fighting ensued, and the officer was injured. Chief Mouna Rudao attempted to apologize by presenting a flagon of wine at the officer's house, but was rejected.&lt;ref name=TakaoClub&gt;{{cite web|title=The Wushe Incident|publisher=The Takao Club|url=http://www.takaoclub.com/monaludao/wusheincident.htm|accessdate=21 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The simmering resentment among the Seediq in Musha was finally pushed to the limit.

==Incident==
[[File:Commander and Staff of Musha Punitive force.JPG|thumb|200px|Commander and staff of the Musha Punitive force.]]
[[File:Mikata-Ban2.JPG|thumb|200px|Mikata-Ban, a force of pro-Japanese aborigines.]]
[[File:二次霧社事件.jpg|thumb|200px|Beheaded Seediq]]

On October 27, 1930, hundreds of Japanese converged on Musha for an athletics meet at the Musyaji Elementary School. Shortly before dawn, Mouna Rudao led over 300 Seediq warriors in a raid of strategic police sub-stations to capture weapons and ammunition. They then moved on the elementary school, concentrating their attack on the Japanese in attendance. A total of 134 Japanese, including women and children, were killed in the attack. Two [[Han Taiwanese]] dressed in Japanese clothing were also mistakenly killed,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=11 Mar 2014 |title=Wushe Incident |website=Encyclopedia of Taiwan |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140325180546/http://taiwanpedia.culture.tw/en/content?ID=3722 |archivedate=25 Mar 2014 |url=http://taiwanpedia.culture.tw/en/content?ID=3722 }}&lt;/ref&gt; one of whom was a girl wearing a Japanese kimono.{{sfnp|Hung|2000|p=222}} The Aboriginals aimed to only kill Japanese specifically.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Heé|first1=Nadin|title=Taiwan under Japanese Rule. Showpiece of a Model Colony? Historiographical Tendencies in Narrating Colonialism|journal=History Compass|date=August 2014|volume=12|issue=8|pages=632–641|doi=10.1111/hic3.12180}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Consequences==
The Japanese authorities responded with unprecedentedly harsh military action. A press blackout was enforced, and [[Governor-General of Taiwan|Governor General]] Eizo Ishizuka ordered a counter-offensive of two thousand troops to be sent to Musha, forcing the Seediq to retreat into the mountains and carry out guerrilla attacks by night. Unable to root out the Seediq despite their superior numbers and firepower, the Japanese faced a political need for a faster solution. Consequently, Japan's army air corps in Taiwan ordered bombing runs over Musha to smoke out the rebels, dropping [[mustard gas]] bombs in violation of the [[Geneva Protocol]] in what was allegedly the first such use of chemical warfare in Asia.&lt;ref&gt;Eric Croddy, &quot;China's Role in the Chemical and Biological Disarmament Regimes&quot;, The Nonproliferation Review Spring 2002: 16, &lt;http://cns.miis.edu/npr/pdfs/91crod.pdf&gt;, accessed September 24, 2011, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TakaoClub /&gt; The uprising was swiftly quelled, with any remaining resistance suppressed by the third week of December 1930;&lt;ref name=TakaoClub /&gt; Mouna Rudao had committed suicide on November 28, but the uprising had continued under other leaders.{{sfnp|Hung|2000|p=223}} Of the 1,200 Seediq directly involved in the uprising, 644 died, 290 of which committed suicide to avoid dishonor.

Due to internal and external criticism of their handling of the incident, Governor-General Kamiyama and Goto Fumio, his chief civil administrator, were forced to resign in January 1931. However, Kamiyama's replacement, Ota Masahiro, also took a harsh approach to controlling Taiwan's indigenous peoples: certain tribes were disarmed and left unprotected, giving their aboriginal enemies an opportunity to annihilate them on behalf of the Japanese administration.{{sfnp|Roy|2003|p=51}} Around 500 of the Seediq involved in the Musha Incident surrendered and were subsequently confined to a village near Musha. However, on April 25, 1931, indigenous groups working with the Japanese authorities attacked the village, [[Taiwanese aborigines#Headhunting|beheading]] all remaining males over the age of 15. This came to be known as the &quot;Second Musha Incident&quot;.

However, the uprising did affect a change in the authorities' attitudes and approaches towards aborigines in Taiwan. Musha had been regarded as the most &quot;enlightened and compliant&quot; of the aboriginal territories, and the colonial power's inability to prevent the massacre provoked a fear of similar nationalist movements starting in Taiwan, Korea, and Japan itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ching|first1=L.|title=Savage Construction and Civility Making: The Musha Incident and Aboriginal Representations in Colonial Taiwan|journal=positions: east asia cultures critique|date=1 December 2000|volume=8|issue=3|page=799|doi=10.1215/10679847-8-3-795|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; A change in policy was clearly needed. Ching suggests that the ideology of imperialisation (''kominka'') became the dominant form of colonial control; aborigines became represented as imperial subjects on equal footing with other ethnic groups in Taiwan, and were upgraded in status from &quot;raw savages&quot;  to {{nihongo4||高砂族|takasagozoku|&quot;tribal peoples of Taiwan&quot;}}. Furthermore, Japanization education was intensified, promoting Japanese culture and loyalty to the emperor in the younger generation.

During the Musha Incident Seediq Tkdaya under Mona Rudao revolted against the Japanese while the Truku and Toda did not. The rivalry between the Seediq Tkdaya vs the Toda and Truku (Taroko) was aggravated by Musha Incident, since the Japanese had long played them off against each other. Tkdaya land was given to the Truku (Taroko) and Toda by the Japanese after the incident.

==In the media==
The Musha Incident has been depicted three times in movies, in 1957 in the film ''Qing Shan bi xue'' ({{lang|zh|青山碧血}}),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lee|first1=Daw-Ming|title=Historical dictionary of Taiwan cinema|date=2013|publisher=Scarecrow Press|location=Lanham, Md.|isbn=9780810879225|page=395}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the 2003 TV drama {{Interlanguage link multi|Dana Sakura|zh|3=風中緋櫻}}, and in the 2011 Taiwanese film ''[[Seediq Bale]]''.

==See also==
{{commons category|Wushe Incident}}
* [[History of Taiwan]]

==References==
{{reflist|32em}}

==External links==
*{{cite news|author1=Han Cheung|title=Taiwan in Time: The long road to retaliation|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/feat/archives/2016/10/23/2003657728|accessdate=23 October 2016|work=Taipei Times|date=23 October 2016}}
*{{cite news|author1=Han Cheung|title=Taiwan in Time: Fighting for the oppressor|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/feat/archives/2016/10/30/2003658203|accessdate=30 October 2016|work=Taipei Times|date=30 October 2016}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1930]]
[[Category:Rebellions in Asia]]
[[Category:Taiwan under Japanese rule]]
[[Category:1930 in Japan]]
[[Category:1930 in Taiwan]]
[[Category:Combat incidents]]
[[Category:Taiwanese aboriginal culture and history]]
[[Category:Violence against indigenous peoples]]
[[Category:Seediq people]]
[[Category:Truku people]]</text>
      <sha1>4idukv7pjtbuosujc2vfs7i6822d909</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
