<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Native Americans in the American Civil War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21791624</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749662573</id>
      <parentid>746533860</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-15T15:42:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BD2412</username>
        <id>196446</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Choctaw */Per consensus in discussion at [[Talk:New York#Proposed action to resolve incorrect incoming links]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32122">[[File:Ely S. Parker.jpg|thumb|200px|upright|[[Ely S. Parker]] was a Union Civil War Colonel who wrote the terms of surrender between the United States and the [[Confederate States of America]].&lt;ref&gt;Ely Parker [http://www.nativeamericans.com/FamousNativeAmericans.htm Famous Native Americans]&lt;/ref&gt; Parker was one of two Native Americans to reach the rank of Brigadier General during the Civil War.]]

'''Native Americans in the American Civil War''' composed various [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] bands, tribes, and nations.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Native Americans served in both the [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]] and [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] military during the [[American Civil War]]. At the outbreak of the war, for example, the majority of the [[Cherokees]] sides with the Union, but soon after allied with the Confederacy.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Native Americans in the Civil War|url=http://www.civilwarhome.com/nativeamericans.htm|date=2009-01-05 |accessdate=2009-01-05|publisher=Ethic Composition of Civil War Forces (C.S &amp; U.S.A.)
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Native Americans fought knowing they might jeopardize their sovereignty, unique cultures, and ancestral lands if they ended up on the losing side of the Civil War.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;/&gt; 28,693 Native Americans served in the Union and Confederate armies during the Civil War, participating in battles such as [[Battle of Pea Ridge|Pea Ridge]], [[Second Manassas]], [[Antietam]], [[Battle of Spotsylvania Court House|Spotsylvania]], [[Cold Harbor]], and in Federal assaults on [[Siege of Petersburg|Petersburg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Native_American_Participation_Numbers&gt;
{{cite book
 | last      = Rodmans
 | first     = Leslie
 | title     = The Five Civilized Tribes and the American Civil War
 | publisher =  
 | url       = http://www.amtour.net/downloadable/The_5_Civilized_Tribes_in_the_Civil_War_a_Biographical_Essay.pdf
 | page      = 2
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Native Americans in the Confederate army==

[[File:AlbertPikeYounger.jpeg|right|200px|thumb|At the beginning of the American Civil War, Pike was appointed as Confederate envoy to the Native Americans.]]

Native Americans
served in both the Union and Confederate military during the [[American Civil War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Native_American_Participation_Numbers&quot;/&gt; Many of the tribes viewed the Confederacy as the better choice due to its opposition to a central federal system which lacked a respect for the sovereignty of Indian nations. In addition, some Native American tribes, such as the Creek and the Choctaw, were slaveholders and found a political and economic commonality with the Confederacy.&lt;ref name=Native_American_Slave_Ownership&gt;
{{cite book
 | last      = Rodman
 | first     = Leslie
 | title     = The Five Civilized Tribes and the American Civil War
 | publisher =  
 | url       = http://www.amtour.net/downloadable/The_5_Civilized_Tribes_in_the_Civil_War_a_Biographical_Essay.pdf
 | page      = 5
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Sir: To enable the Secretary of War most advantageously to perform the duties devolved upon him in relation to the Indian tribes by the second section of the Act to establish the War Department of February 21, 1861, it is deemed desirable that there should be established a Bureau of Indian Affairs, and, if the Congress concur in this view, I have the honor respectfully to recommend that provision be made for the appointment of a Commissioner of Indian Affairs, and for one clerk to aid him in the discharge of his official duties.|Jefferson Davis to Howell Cobb, Confederate States of America – Message to Congress, March 1861&lt;ref name=Davis&gt;
{{cite web
| url        = http://avalon.law.yale.edu/19th_century/csa_m031261.asp
| title      = Confederate States of America – Message to Congress March 12, 1861 (Indian Affairs)
| accessdate = 2010-08-11
| year       = 1861
| publisher  = Yale Law School
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

At the beginning of the war, [[Albert Pike]] was appointed as Confederate envoy to [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]]. In this capacity he negotiated several treaties, one such treaty was the [[Treaty with Choctaws and Chickasaws]] conducted in July 1861. The treaty covered sixty-four terms covering many subjects like Choctaw and Chickasaw nation sovereignty, [[Confederate States of America]] citizenship possibilities, and an entitled delegate in the House of Representatives of the Confederate States of America. The [[Cherokee]], [[Choctaw]], [[Chickasaw]], [[Seminole]], [[Catawba (tribe)|Catawba]], and [[Muscogee (Creek)|Creek]] tribes were the only tribes to fight on the Confederate side. The [[Confederate States of America|Confederacy]] wanted to recruit Indians east of the Mississippi River in 1862, so they opened up a recruiting camp in [[Mobile, Alabama]] &quot;at the foot of Stone Street.&quot;&lt;ref name=j_matte1&gt;
{{cite book
 | last      = Matte
 | first     = Jacqueline
 | title     = They Say the Wind is Red
 | publisher = New South Books
 | chapter   = Refugees- Six Towns Choctaw, 1830–1890
 | page      = 65
 | isbn        = 1-58838-079-3
 | year  = 2002
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Mobile Advertiser and Register'' would advertise for a chance at military service.

{{quote|A Chance for Active Service. The Secretary of War has authorized me to enlist all the Indians east of the Mississippi River into the service of the Confederate States, as Scouts. In addition to the Indians, I will receive all white male citizens, who are good marksmen. To each member, Fifty Dollars Bounty, clothes, arms, camp equipage &amp;c: furnished. The weapons shall be Enfield Rifles. For further information address me at Mobile, Ala. (Signed) S.G. Spann, Comm'ing Choctaw Forces.|Jacqueline Anderson Matte, ''They Say the Wind is Red''&lt;ref name=j_matte1 /&gt;}}

===Cherokee===
{{main article|Cherokee in the American Civil War}}
[[Stand Watie]], along with many Cherokee, sided with the Confederate Army, in which he was made colonel and commanded a battalion of Cherokee.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Reluctantly, on October 7, 1861, Chief Ross signed a treaty transferring all obligations due to the Cherokee from the U.S. Government to the Confederate States.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; In the treaty, the Cherokee were guaranteed protection, rations of food, livestock, tools and other goods, as well as a delegate to the [[Confederate Congress]] at Richmond.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; In exchange, the Cherokee would furnish ten companies of mounted men, and allow the construction of military posts and roads within the Cherokee Nation. However, no Indian regiment was to be called on to fight outside Indian Territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; As a result of the treaty, the 2nd Cherokee Mounted Rifles, led by Col. John Drew, was formed. Following the [[Battle of Pea Ridge]], Arkansas, March 7–8, 1862, Drew's Mounted Rifles defected to the Union forces in Kansas, where they joined the Indian Home Guard. In the summer of 1862, Federal troops captured Chief Ross, who was paroled and spent the remainder of the war in Washington and Philadelphia proclaiming Cherokee loyalty to the Union army.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

[[William Holland Thomas]], the only white chief of the [[Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians]], recruited hundreds of Cherokees for the Confederacy, particularly for [[Thomas' Legion]]. The Legion, raised in September 1862, fought until the end of the war.

===Choctaw===
{{main article|Choctaw in the American Civil War}}
[[File:J f mccurtain.jpg|right|175px|thumb|Jackson McCurtain, Lieutenant Colonel of the First Choctaw Battalion in Oklahoma, [[Confederate States of America|CSA]].]]

Choctaw [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] battalions were formed in Indian Territory and later in Mississippi in support of the southern cause. The Choctaws, who were expecting support from the Confederates, got little. Webb Garrison, a Civil War historian, describes their response: when Confederate Brigadier General [[Albert Pike]] authorized the raising of regiments during the fall of 1860, Creeks, Choctaws, and Cherokees responded with considerable enthusiasm. Their zeal for the Confederate cause, however, began to evaporate when they found that neither arms nor pay had been arranged for them. A disgusted officer later acknowledged that &quot;with the exception of a partial supply for the Choctaw regiment, no tents, clothing, or camp and garrison equippage was furnished to any of them.&quot;&lt;ref name=webb_garrison&gt;
{{cite book
 | last      = Garrison
 | first     = Webb
 | title     = More Civil War Curiosities
 | publisher = Rutledge Hill Press
 | chapter   = Padday Some Day
 | year  = 1995
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Albert Pike negotiated several treaties with Native American tribes, including the [[Treaty with Choctaws and Chickasaws]] in July 1861. The treaty covered sixty-four terms, covering many subjects like Choctaw and Chickasaw nation sovereignty, [[Confederate States of America]] citizenship possibilities, and an entitled delegate in the House of Representatives of the Confederate States of America.&lt;ref name=choctaw_ok_statehood&gt;
{{Cite web
 | url        = http://www.okhistory.org/publications/enc/entry.php?entry=CH047
 | title      = Choctaw
 | accessdate = 2008-08-11
 | author    = Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Up to this time, our protection was in the United States troops stationed at Fort Washita, under the command of Colonel Emory. But he, as soon as the Confederate troops had entered our country, at once abandoned us and the Fort; and, to make his flight more expeditious and his escape more sure, employed Black Beaver, a Shawnee Indian, under a promise to him of five thousand dollars, to pilot him and his troops out of the Indian country safely without a collision with the Texas Confederates; which Black Beaver accomplished. By this act the United States abandoned the Choctaws and Chickasaws.

[...]

Then, there being no other alternative by which to save their country and property, they, as the less of the two evils that confronted them, went with the Southern Confederacy.|Julius Folsom, September 5, 1891, letter to H. B. Cushman}}

Mississippi Choctaws were captured in [[Ponchatoula, Louisiana]], and several died in a [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]] prison in [[New York (state)|New York]].&lt;ref name=kidwell&gt;
{{cite book
 | last      = Kidwell
 | first     = Clara
 | title     = Choctaws and Missionaries in Mississippi, 1818–1918
 | publisher = University of Oklahoma
 | chapter   = The Choctaws in Mississippi after 1830
 | page      = 170
 | isbn      = 0-8061-2691-4
 | year  = 1995
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Spann describes the incident, &quot;[Maj. J.W. Pearce] established two camps – a recruiting camp in Newton County and a drill camp at Tangipahoa – just beyond the State boundary line in Louisiana in the fall of 1862. [[New Orleans]] at that time was in the hands of the Federal Gen. [[Benjamin Butler (politician)|B.F. Butler]]. Without notice a reconnoitering party of the enemy raided the camp, and captured over two dozen Indians and several noncommissioned white officers and carried them to New Orleans. All the officers and several of the Indians escaped and returned to the Newton County camp; but all the balance of the captured Indians were carried to New York, and were daily paraded in the public parks as curiosities for the sport of sight-seers.&quot;&lt;ref name=choctaw_confederate&gt;
{{cite magazine
| title       = Choctaw Indians As Confederate Soldiers
| last        = Spann
| first       = S. G.
| magazine    = Confederate Veteran Magazine
| volume      = XIII
| number      = 12
| pages       = 560–561
| date        = December 1905
| url         = http://www.choctaw.org/history/confederate.htm
| accessdate  = 2008-02-06
| archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20071025034356/http://www.choctaw.org/history/confederate.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt;
| archivedate = 2007-10-25
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

In Choctaw Nation in Indian Territory, Jackson McCurtain, who would later become a district chief, was elected as representative from Sugar Loaf County to the National Council in October 1859. On June 22, 1861, he enlisted in the First Regiment of Choctaw and Chickasaw Mounted Rifles. He was commissioned Captain of Company G under the command of Colonel Douglas H. Cooper of the Confederate Army. In 1862 he became a Lieutenant Colonel of the First Choctaw Battalion.&lt;ref name=ok_choctaw_battalion&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.choctawnation.com/History/index.cfm?fuseaction=HArticle&amp;HArticleID=14 |title=Choctaw Nation of Oklahoma: 1880 – Jackson F. McCurtain |accessdate=2008-02-08 |year=1880 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090202121021/http://www.choctawnation.com/History/index.cfm?fuseaction=HArticle&amp;HArticleID=14 |archivedate=February 2, 2009 }} 
&lt;/ref&gt;
The Choctaw probably owned over 2,000 slaves.&lt;ref name=Choctaw_Slave_Numbers&gt;
{{cite web
 | title     = The Choctaw
 | year  = 2005
 | publisher = Museum of the Red River
 | url       = http://www.museumoftheredriver.org/choctaw.html
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Native Americans in the Union Army==
The [[Delaware tribe]] had a long history of allegiance to the U.S. government, despite removal to the Wichita Indian Agency in Oklahoma and the Indian Territory in Kansas.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; On October 1, 1861 the Delaware people proclaimed their alliance to the Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; A journalist from ''Harper's Weekly'' described them as being armed with tomahawks, scalping knives, and rifles.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

In January 1862, William Dole, U.S. Commissioner of Indian Affairs, asked Native American agents to &quot;engage forthwith all the vigorous and able-bodied Native Americans in their respective agencies.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; The request resulted in the assembly of the 1st and 2nd Indian Home Guard.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

In Oklahoma, much of the [[Creek tribe|Creek]] peoples sided with the Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;EOHC-RoundMt&quot;/&gt; The majority of the Creek initially sided with the Union as two-thirds of the people preferred to be guided by the advice of their chief [[Opothleyahola]]. However, former Chief McIntosh sided with the South, whose leaders appointed him a colonel in the Confederate Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;ab&quot;/&gt;

==Overview of the war==
[[File:Cherokee Confederates Reunion.gif|left|325px|thumb|Cherokee confederates (Thomas' Legion) reunion in New Orleans, 1903.]]

Many Native American tribes fought for either side in the war including: the [[Delaware tribe|Delaware]], [[Creek tribe|Creek]], [[Cherokee]], [[Seminole]], [[Kickapoo people|Kickapoo]], [[Seneca Nation|Seneca]], [[Osage Nation|Osage]], [[Shawnee]], [[Choctaw]], [[Lumbee]], [[Chickasaw]], [[Iroquois Confederacy]], [[Powhatan]], [[Pequot]], [[Ojibwe|Ojibwe (Chippewa)]], [[Huron tribe|Huron]], [[Odawa people|Odawa]], [[Potawatomi]], [[Catawba tribe|Catawba]], and [[Pamunkey]]. Like other American communities, some tribes had members fighting on either side of the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;ab&quot;/&gt;

During November 1861, the [[Creek tribe|Creek]], Black Creek Indians, and White Creek Indians of their tribe were led by Creek Chief [[Opothleyahola]], fought three pitched battles ([[Battle of Round Mountain]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;EOHC-RoundMt&quot;&gt;[http://www.okhistory.org/publications/enc/entry.php?entry=RO035  Chad Williams,  &quot;Battle of Round Mountain&quot; ''Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture''.]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Battle of Chusto-Talasah]]&lt;ref name=&quot;EOHC-Battle of CT&quot;&gt;[http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/C/CH066.html Michael A. Hughes, &quot;Battle of Chusto-Talasah.&quot; ''Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture''].&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Battle of Chustenahlah]] &lt;ref name =&quot;Chustenalah&quot;&gt;[http://www.okhistory.org/publications/enc/entry.php?entry=CH065 Michael A. Hughes, &quot;Battle of Chustenahlah,&quot;  &quot;'Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture''.]&lt;/ref&gt; against Confederate white troops and other Native Americans that joined the Confederates to reach Union lines in Kansas, and offer their services.&lt;ref name=&quot;wil&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.williamlkatz.com/Essays/History/AfricansIndians.php|title=Africans and Indians: Only in America|author=William Loren Katz |accessdate=2008-09-20 |year=2008 |publisher=William Loren Katz }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Civil War battles occurred in Indian Territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;civ2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.african-nativeamerican.com/battles.htm|title=Battles Fought in Indian Territory and Battles Fought by I.T. Freedmen outside of Indian Territory|author=Angela Y. Walton-Raji|accessdate=2008-10-24 |year=2008 |publisher=Oklahoma's Black Indians}}&lt;/ref&gt; The First [[Battle of Cabin Creek]] occurred July 1–2, 1863, along the Grand River in modern-day [[Mayes County, Oklahoma]] which involved the 1st Kansas Colored Infantry.&lt;ref name=&quot;civ2&quot;/&gt; The Confederate force was led by General Stand Watie. A second battle was fought near the same location on September 19, 1864. This time the Union forces under Major Henry M. Hopkins were defeated by a Confederate force under Brigadier Generals [[Richard Montgomery Gano|Richard Gano]] and Stand Watie. This was the last major battle of the Civil War in Indian Territory.&lt;ref name =&quot;EOHC-CabinCreek&quot;&gt;[http://www.okhistory.org/publications/enc/entry.php?entry=CA001  Steven L. Warren, &quot;Battles of Cabin Creek,&quot; ''Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History''  ]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Native Americans swearing in.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Native Americans swearing in for the [[American Civil War]].]]

The Delaware demonstrated their &quot;loyalty, daring and hardihood&quot; during the attack of the Wichita Agency, or the [[Tonkawa Massacre]] in October 1862. A minor skirmish, Union Native Americans attacked Confederate Native Americans, and also killed five Confederate agents, took the Rebel flag and $1200 in Confederate currency, 100 ponies, and burned correspondence along with the Agency buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

The [[Cherokee Nation (19th century)|Cherokee Nation]] had an internal civil war.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; The Nation divided, with one side led by [[Principal Chiefs of the Cherokee|Principal Chief]] [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|John Ross]] and the other by renegade [[Stand Watie]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Chief John Ross wanted to remain neutral throughout the war, but Confederate victories at First Manassas and Wilson's Creek forced the Cherokee to reassess their position.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ab&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title= Union and Confederate Indians in the Civil War &quot;Battles and Leaders of the Civil War&quot;|url=http://www.civilwarhome.com/unionconfedindians.htm|date=2009-01-05 |accessdate=2009-01-05|publisher=Civil War Potpourri|author=Wiley Britton}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stand Watie, along with many Cherokee, sided with the Confederate Army, in which he was made Colonel and commanded a battalion of Cherokee.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Reluctantly, on October 7, 1861, Chief Ross signed a treaty transferring all obligations due to the Cherokee from the U.S. Government to the Confederate States.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; In the treaty, the Cherokee were guaranteed protection, rations of food, livestock, tools and other goods, as well as a delegate to the Confederate Congress at Richmond.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; In exchange, the Cherokee would furnish ten companies of mounted men, and allow the construction of military posts and roads within the Cherokee Nation. However, no Indian regiment was to be called on to fight outside Indian Territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; As a result of the Treaty, the 2nd Cherokee Mounted Rifles, led by Col. John Drew, was formed. Following the Battle of Pea Ridge, Arkansas, March 7–8, 1862, Drew's Mounted Rifles defected to the Union forces in Kansas, where they joined the Indian Home Guard. In the summer of 1862, Federal troops captured Chief Ross, who was paroled and spent the remainder of the war in Washington and Philadelphia proclaiming Cherokee loyalty to the [[Union army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

In his absence, Col. Stand Watie was chosen principal chief of the Cherokee Nation. He immediately drafted all Cherokee males aged 18–50 into Confederate military service.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Watie was a daring cavalry rider who was skilled at hit-and-run tactics. He was considered a genius in guerrilla warfare and the most successful field commander in the Trans-Mississippi West.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Promoted to brigadier general in May 1864, Watie was placed in charge of the Indian Cavalry Brigade, which was composed of the 1st and 2nd Cherokee Cavalry and battalions of Creek, Osage and Seminole. He led the [[Ambush of the steamboat J. R. Williams]], achieved one of his more notable raids at Pleasant Bluff on the Arkansas River, near the present town of [[Tamaha, Oklahoma]] on June 10, 1864, capturing the Union steamboat ''J.R. Williams''. which was loaded with supplies valued at $120,000 bound for Fort Gibson.

At the Second Battle of Cabin Creek, (Indian Territory), Watie's cavalry brigade captured 129 supply wagons and 740 mules, took 120 prisoners, and left 200 casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; The Cherokee who had not been removed were also caught in the middle of the Civil War. Some chose to side with the Confederate Army since they were located in the southern states.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

The Thomas Legion, an Eastern Band of Confederate Cherokee, led by Col. William Holland Thomas, fought in the mountains of Tennessee and North Carolina.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Another 200 Cherokee formed the Junaluska Zouaves.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Nearly all [[Catawba tribe|Catawba]] adult males served the South in the 5th, 12th and 17th South Carolina Volunteer Infantry, Army of Northern Virginia. They distinguished themselves in the [[Peninsula Campaign]], at [[Second Manassas]], and [[Antietam]], and in the trenches at [[Siege of Petersburg|Petersburg]]. A monument in Columbia, South Carolina, honors the Catawbas' service in the Civil War.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; As a consequence of the regiments' high rate of dead and wounded, the continued existence of the Catawba people was jeopardized.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Company K of the 1st Michigan Sharpshooters.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Company K of the [[1st United States Volunteer Sharpshooter Regiment|1st Michigan Sharpshooters resting]].]]

In Virginia and North Carolina, the [[Pamunkey]] and [[Lumbee]] chose to serve the Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; The Pamunkey served as civilian and naval pilots for Union warships and transports, while the Lumbee acted as guerrillas.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Members of the Iroquois Confederacy joined Company K, 5th Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry, while the Powhatan served as land guides, river pilots, and spies for the Army of the Potomac.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

During the Civil War, there was no distinction made when a Native American joined the U.S. Colored Troops. Well into the twentieth century, the word &quot;colored&quot; included not only [[African American]]s, but Native Americans as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; Individual accounts revealed that many Pequot from New England served in the 31st U.S. Colored Infantry of the Army of the Potomac, as well as other U.S.C.T. regiments.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

The most famous Native American unit in the Union army in the east was Company K of the 1st Michigan Sharpshooters.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; The bulk of this unit was Ottawa, Delaware, Huron, Oneida, Potawami and Ojibwe.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; They were assigned to the Army of the Potomac just as Gen. Ulysses S. Grant assumed command. Company K participated in the [[Battle of the Wilderness]] and Spotsylvania, and captured 600 Confederate troops at Shand House east of Petersburg.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; In their final military engagement at the Battle of the Crater, Petersburg, Virginia, on July 30, 1864, the Sharpshooters found themselves surrounded with little ammunition.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; A lieutenant of the 13th U.S. C.T. quoted their actions as
{{quote|splendid work. Some of them were mortally wounded, and drawing their blouses over their faces, they chanted a death song and died – four of them in a group.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;}}

General [[Ely S. Parker]], a member of the [[Seneca tribe]], created the articles of surrender which General [[Robert E. Lee]] signed at [[Appomattox Court House National Historical Park|Appomattox Court House]] on April 9, 1865. Gen. Parker, who served as Gen. Ulysses S. Grant's military secretary and was a trained attorney, was once rejected for Union military service because of his race. At Appomattox, Lee is said to have remarked to Parker, &quot;I am glad to see one real American here&quot;, to which Parker replied, &quot;We are all Americans.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=&quot;We are all Americans&quot;, Native Americans in the Civil War
|url=http://oha.alexandriava.gov/fortward/special-sections/americans/|date=2009-01-05 |accessdate=2009-01-05|publisher=Native Americans.com|author=W. David Baird|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cherokee Nation was the most negatively affected of all Native American tribes during the Civil War, its population declining from 21,000 to 15,000 by 1865. Despite the Federal government's promise to pardon all Cherokee involved with the Confederacy, the entire Nation was considered disloyal, and their rights were revoked. At the end of the war, Gen. [[Stand Watie]] was the last Confederate general to surrender, laying down arms two months after Gen. [[Robert E. Lee]], and a month after Gen. [[E. Kirby Smith]], commander of all troops west of the Mississippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt;

===Problems in the Midwest and West===
The west was mostly peaceful during the war due to the lack of U.S. occupation troops.  The federal government was still taking control of native land, and there were continuous fights.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;/&gt;  From January to May 1863, there were almost continuous fights in the New Mexico territory, as part of a concerted effort by the Federal government to contain and control the [[Apache]]; in the midst of all this, President [[Abraham Lincoln]] met with representatives from several major tribes, and informed them he felt concerned they would never attain the prosperity of the white race unless they turned to farming as a way of life.&lt;ref name=&quot;aa&quot;/&gt; The fighting led to the [[Sand Creek Massacre]] caused by [[John Chivington|Colonel J. M. Chivington]], of the [[Colorado Territory|Colorado Territorial Militia]], whom settlers asked to retaliate against natives.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;/&gt;  With 900 volunteer militiamen, Chivington attacked a peaceful village of some 500 or more Arapaho and Cheyenne natives, killing women and children as well as warriors.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;/&gt; There were few survivors of the massacre.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;/&gt;

In July 1862, settlers fought against Santee Sioux in Minnesota.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Native Americans|url=http://www.historycentral.com/civilwar/people/Native.html|date=2009-01-05 |accessdate=2009-01-05|publisher=History Central.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because the war absorbed so many government resources, the annuities owed to the Santee Sioux in Minnesota were not paid on time in the summer of 1862.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt; In addition, Long Trader Sibley refused the [[Santee Sioux]] access to food until the funds were delivered. In frustration, the Santee Sioux, led by Little Crow (Ta-oya-te-duta), attacked settlers in order to get supplies.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt; After the [[Sioux]] lost the fighting, they were tried (without defense lawyers), found guilty on flimsy evidence,and many were sentenced to death.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt;

When President Lincoln found out about the incident, he immediately requested full information about the convictions.  He assigned two attorneys to examine the cases and differentiate between those guilty of murder and those who simply engaged in battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt;  General Pope, as well as Long Trader Sibley, whose refusal to allow the Sioux access to food had been largely responsible for the war, were angered by Lincoln's failure to immediately authorize the executions.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt; They threatened that the local settlers would take action against the Sioux unless the President allowed the executions, and they quickly tried to push forward with them.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt; In addition, they arrested the rest of the Santee Sioux, 1,700 people, of whom most were women and children, although they were accused of no crime.

On December 6, 1861, based on information he was given, Lincoln authorized the execution of 39 Sioux, and ordered that the others be held pending further orders, &quot;taking care that they neither escape nor are subjected to any unlawful violence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt;  On December 26, 39 men were taken. At the last minute, one was given a reprieve.  It was not until years later that information became public that two men were executed who had not been authorized for punishment by President Lincoln.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt; In fact, one of these two men had saved a white woman's life during the fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt;  [[Little Crow]] was killed in July 1863, the year in which the Santees were transported to a reservation in Dakota Territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;ad&quot;/&gt;

==Tribes involved in battles==
{{div col|3}}
* [[Catawba tribe|Catawba]]
* [[Cherokee]]
* [[Choctaw]]
* [[Chickasaw Nation|Chickasaw]]
* [[Creek tribe|Creek]]
* [[Delaware tribe|Delaware]]
* [[Huron tribe|Huron]]
* [[Kickapoo people|Kickapoo]]
* [[Lumbee]]
* [[Mohawk nation|Mohawk]]
* [[Odawa people|Odawa]]
* [[Ojibwe|Ojibwe/Chippewa]]
* [[Osage Nation|Osage]]
* [[Pamunkey]]
* [[Pequot]]
* [[Potawatomi]]
* [[Powhatan]]
* [[Shawnee]]
* [[Seminole]]
* [[Seneca Nation|Seneca]]
* [[Oneida Nation|Oneida]]
{{div col end}}

==See also==
{{Portal|American Civil War}}
* [[Native Americans and World War II]]
* [[Slavery among Native Americans in the United States]]
* [[Indian Territory in the American Civil War]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Confer, Clarissa W. ''The Cherokee Nation in the Civil War'' (Univ.of Oklahoma Press, 2007)
* Dale, Edward Everett. &quot;The Cherokees in the Confederacy.&quot; ''Journal of Southern History'' 13.2 (1947): 159-185. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2197976 in JSTOR]
* Fisher, Paul Thomas. &quot;Confederate empire and the Indian treaties: Pike, McCulloch, and the Five Civilized Tribes, 1861-1862&quot; (MA thesis Baylor U. 2011). [https://baylor-ir.tdl.org/baylor-ir/bitstream/handle/2104/8133/Paul_Fisher_masters.pdf online]; bibliography pp 107–19.
* Gibson, Arrell Morgan. &quot;Native Americans and the Civil War,&quot; ''American Indian Quarterly'' (1985)  9#4 pp.&amp;nbsp;385–410 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1183560 in JSTOR]
*{{Citation 
| last = Gibson
| first = Arrell
| title = Oklahoma, a History of Five Centuries 
| location = 
| publisher = University of Oklahoma Press
| year = 1981
| isbn = 0-8061-1758-3}}  
* Hauptman, Laurence M. ''Between Two Fires: American Indians in the Civil War'' (1995) [http://www.amazon.com/Between-Two-Fires-American-Indians/dp/002914180X/ excerpt]
* Johnston, Carolyn. ''Cherokee Women in Crisis: Trail of Tears, Civil War, and Allotment, 1838-1907'' (University of Alabama Press, 2003).
* Minges, Patrick. ''Slavery in the Cherokee Nation: The Keetowah Society and the Defining of a People, 1855-1867'' (Routledge, 2003)
* Moore, Jessie Randolph. &quot;The Five Great Indian Nations: Cherokee, Choctaw, Chickasaw, Seminole, and Creek: The Part They Played in Behalf of the Confederacy in the War Between the States.&quot; ''Chronicles of Oklahoma'' 29 (1951): 324-336.
* Smith, Troy. &quot;The Civil War Comes to Indian Territory,&quot; '' Civil War History'' (Sept 2013) 59#3 pp 279–319  [http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/civil_war_history/v059/59.3.smith.html online]
* Wickett, Murray R. ''Contested Territory: Whites, Native Americans and African Americans in Oklahoma, 1865-1907'' (Louisiana State Univ. Press, 2000)

==Primary sources==
*  Edwards, Whit. ''&quot;The Prairie Was on Fire&quot;: Eyewitness Accounts of the Civil War in the Indian Territory'' (Oklahoma Historical Society, 2001)

{{Cherokee}}
{{American Civil War |expanded=CTCBS}}

[[Category:History of the Cherokee]]
[[Category:Native Americans in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:Indian Territory in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:North Carolina in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:Cherokee Nation (1794–1907)]]
[[Category:Native American history]]</text>
      <sha1>75r3lqwf1s2dijt5b1kmyqssazjel5m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
