<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Northrop T-38 Talon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>357874</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747706825</id>
      <parentid>746261718</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T22:27:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cnwilliams</username>
        <id>10190671</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Disambiguated: [[Gallup]] → [[Gallup, New Mexico]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33194">{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
 |name= T-38 Talon
 |image= File:T-38 560FTS RandolphAFB 2001.jpeg
 |caption= A T-38A from [[560th Flying Training Squadron]], flying over the Texas countryside in 2001
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
 |type= Advanced trainer
 |manufacturer= [[Northrop Corporation]]
 |national origin= United States
 |first flight= 10 March 1959
 |introduced= 17 March 1961
 |retired= 
 |status= Operational
 |primary user= [[United States Air Force]]&lt;!--Limit one (1) primary user. Top 4 users listed in 'primary user' and 'more users' fields based on number of their fleets. --&gt;
 |more users= [[United States Navy]]&lt;br&gt; [[NASA]]&lt;br&gt; [[Turkish Air Force]]&lt;!-- Limit is three (3) in 'more users' field, four (4) total users with primary user. Please separate with &lt;br/&gt;.--&gt;
 |produced= 1961–1972
 |number built= 1,146
 |unit cost= [[United States dollar|US$]]756,000 (1961 [[constant dollars]])&lt;br&gt;US$5.879 million (2013 dollars)
 |developed from= [[Northrop N-156]]
 |variants with their own articles= [[Northrop F-5]]
 |developed into= [[Northrop F-20 Tigershark]]
}}
|}
[[File:T38-Bank.JPEG|thumb|Air-to-air right side view of a USAF T-38 Talon aircraft from 560th Flying Training Squadron, Randolph AFB, TX as his lead performs a left pitchout]]
[[File:T-38C cockpit.jpg|thumb|T-38C cockpit]]
[[File:ThunderbirdsT38.jpg|thumb|USAF [[U.S. Air Force Thunderbirds|Thunderbirds]] flying T-38s in formation]]
[[File:STS-3 landing.jpg|thumb|Two T-38 chase planes follow [[Space Shuttle Columbia|Space Shuttle ''Columbia'']] as it lands at Northrop Strip in [[White Sands, New Mexico]], ending its mission [[STS-3]].]]
[[File:T-38 in flight over Dry Lake.jpg|thumb|NASA Dryden's T-38 in flight over [[Cuddeback Lake|Cuddeback Dry Lake]] in Southern California]]
[[File:479ftg-t38cs.jpg|thumb|Picture of the formation leader, taken from the backseat of a T38C, of the 479th Fighter Training Group, Moody AFB, Georgia, 2006]]
[[File:T-38.JPG|thumb|T-38 in [[Portuguese Air Force]] colours at [[Beja Air Base|Air Base No. 11 (BA11 – Beja)]]]]
[[File:T-38As Vance AFB 1997.jpeg|thumb|A U.S. Air Force 25th Flying Training Squadron instructor pilot and his student walk to a T-38A to begin flight training at Vance Air Force Base, Oklahoma, on 23 November 1997.]]
[[File:X-15 and B-52 Mother ship.jpg|thumb|X-15 in flight attached to B-52 mother ship, with T-38 chase plane (1961)]]
[[File:T-38 051017-F-0000S-002.jpg|thumb|A T-38 takes off from Edwards Air Force Base with only one engine during single-engine takeoff testing, to evaluate recommended speeds for takeoff if an engine fails.]]

The '''Northrop T-38 Talon''' is a two-seat, twin-engined supersonic [[jet trainer]]. It was the world's first supersonic trainer and is also the most produced. The T-38 remains in service {{asof|2016|lc=on}} in several air forces.

The [[United States Air Force]] (USAF) operates the most T-38s. In addition to training USAF pilots, the T-38 is used by [[National Aeronautics and Space Administration|NASA]]. The [[U.S. Naval Test Pilot School|US Naval Test Pilot School]] is the principal US Navy operator (other T-38s were previously used as USN [[Aggressor squadron|aggressor]] aircraft until replaced by the similar [[Northrop F-5 Tiger II]]). Pilots of other [[NATO]] nations fly the T-38 in joint training programs with USAF pilots.

{{Asof|2015}}, the T-38 has been in service for over 50 years with its original operator, the United States Air Force.

==Design and development==
In 1952 Northrop began work on a fighter project, the ''[[Northrop N-102 Fang|Fang]]'', with shoulder-mounted delta wing and a single engine.&lt;ref&gt;Johnsen 2006, pp. 5–6&lt;/ref&gt; The proposed [[General Electric J79]] engine, weighing nearly two tons, meant the resulting aircraft would be large and expensive.&lt;ref&gt;Eden 2004, p. 344&lt;/ref&gt; Then in 1953, representatives from [[General Electric Aviation]]'s newly created Small Aircraft Engine Department showed Northrop a relatively tiny engine (around 400&amp;nbsp;lb installed wt) capable of 2,500&amp;nbsp;lb of thrust, and Northrop VP-Engineering [[Edgar Schmued]] saw the possibility of reversing the trend toward the large fighters. Schmued and chief engineer Welko Gasich decided on a small twin-engine &quot;hot-rod&quot; fighter, the N-156. Northrop began its N-156 project in 1954, aiming for a small supersonic fighter jet capable of operating from the US Navy's [[escort carrier]]s. However, when the Navy chose not to pursue equipping its fleets in that fashion, Northrop continued the N-156 design using in-house funding, recasting it as  a lightweight fighter (dubbed N-156F) and aimed at the export market.

In the mid-1950s the USAF issued a General Operating Requirement for a supersonic trainer, planning to retire its 1940s-era [[Lockheed T-33]]s. Northrop officials decided to adapt the N-156 to this competition. The only other candidate was the two-seat version of the [[North American F-100 Super Sabre]]. Although the F-100 was not considered the ideal candidate for a training aircraft (it is not capable of recovering from a spin),&lt;ref&gt;Due to its elongated fuselage - the pilot's operating handbook for the two-seat version contains an instruction to avoid spins.&lt;/ref&gt; NAA was still considered the favorite in the competition due to that company's favored-contractor status with the Air Force. However, Northrop officials convincingly presented life-cycle cost comparisons which could not be ignored, and they were awarded the contract, receiving an order for three prototypes. The first (designated YT-38) flew on 10 March 1959.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defencetalk.com/northrop-marks-50th-anniversary-of-t-38-talon-first-flight-17679/ &quot;Northrop marks 50th anniversary of T-38 Talon first flight.&quot;] defencetalk.com, 14 April 2009. Retrieved: 21 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The type was quickly adopted and the first production examples were delivered in 1961, officially entering service on 17 March that year, complementing the [[Cessna T-37 Tweet|T-37]] primary jet trainer. When production ended in 1972, 1,187 T-38s had been built (plus two N-156T prototypes). Since its introduction, it is estimated that some 50,000 military pilots have trained on this aircraft. The USAF remains one of the few armed flying forces using dedicated supersonic final trainers, as most, such as the US Navy, use high subsonic trainers.&lt;ref name=USAF_factsheet/&gt;

The T-38 is of conventional configuration, with a small, low, long-chord wing, a single vertical stabilizer, and [[Landing gear|tricycle undercarriage]]. The aircraft seats a student pilot and instructor in tandem, and has intakes for its two [[turbojet]] engines at the wing roots. Its nimble performance has earned it the nickname ''white rocket.'' In 1962 the T-38 set absolute time-to-climb records for 3,000, 6,000, 9,000 and 12,000 meters, beating the records for those altitudes set by the F-104 in December 1958. (The F-4 beat the T-38's records less than a month later.)

The F-5B and F (which also derive from the N-156) can be distinguished from the T-38 by the wings; the wing of the T-38 meets the fuselage straight and ends square, while the F-5 has [[leading edge extension]]s near the wing roots and wingtip launch rails for [[air-to-air missile]]s. The wings of both the T-38 and the F-5 family use conventional skin over spar-rib structure.&lt;ref&gt;TO 1T-38A-4, USAF T-38 Tech Order&lt;/ref&gt;

Most T-38s built were of the '''T-38A''' variant, but the USAF also had a small number of aircraft converted for weapons training (designated '''AT-38B'''), which were fitted with a gunsight and could carry a gunpod, rockets, or bombs on a centerline pylon. In 2015, 504 T-38s were still operational with the USAF, with many more in operation around the world. Most of the USAF variant aircraft (T-38A and AT-38B) have been converted to the T-38C through an avionics upgrade program. Improvements include the addition of a [[Head-Up Display|HUD]], [[GPS]], INS ([[Inertial Navigation System]]), and [[Traffic Collision Avoidance System|TCAS]]. Most jets have also received PMP (a propulsion modification to improve low-altitude engine thrust). Approximately a third of the fleet (those that experience more severe usage) are currently undergoing structural replacements and upgrades, as well as receiving new wings, to extend their service life to 2029.

The fighter version of the N-156 was eventually selected for the US [[Military Assistance Program]] and produced as the [[Northrop F-5|F-5 Freedom Fighter]]. Many of these have since reverted to a weapons training role as various air forces have introduced newer types into service. The F-5G was an advanced single-engined variant later renamed the [[Northrop F-20 Tigershark|F-20 Tigershark]].

==Operational history==

===Military===
The USAF [[Strategic Air Command]] (SAC) had T-38s in service from 1978 until SAC's 1991 inactivation. These aircraft were used to enhance the career development of bomber copilots through the &quot;Accelerated Copilot Enrichment Program.&quot; They were later used as proficiency aircraft for all [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress|B-52]], [[Rockwell B-1 Lancer|B-1]], [[Lockheed SR-71 Blackbird|Lockheed SR-71]], [[Lockheed U-2|U-2]], [[Boeing KC-135]], and [[McDonnell Douglas KC-10 Extender|KC-10]] pilots. SAC's successors, the [[Air Combat Command]] (ACC) and the [[Air Force Global Strike Command]] (AFGSC), continue to retain T-38s as proficiency aircraft for U-2 pilots and B-2 pilots, respectively.&lt;ref name=USAF_factsheet/&gt;

The [[Air Training Command]]'s (ATC) successor, the [[Air Education and Training Command]] (AETC), uses the T-38C to prepare pilots for the [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle|F-15C Eagle]] and [[McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagle|F-15E Strike Eagle]], the [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16 Fighting Falcon]], [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress|B-52 Stratofortress]], [[Rockwell B-1 Lancer|B-1B Lancer]], [[B-2 Spirit]], [[Fairchild Republic A-10 Thunderbolt II|A-10 Thunderbolt]], [[Lockheed Martin F-22 Raptor|F-22 Raptor]] and [[F-35 Lightning II]]. The AETC received T-38Cs in 2001 as part of the Avionics Upgrade Program. The T-38Cs owned by the AETC have undergone propulsion modernization which replaces major engine components to enhance reliability and maintainability, and an engine inlet/injector modification to increase available takeoff thrust.&lt;ref name=USAF_factsheet/&gt; These upgrades and modifications, with the Pacer Classic program, should extend the service life of T-38s past 2020. The T-38 has an [[availability]] goal of 75% which it maintained in 2011, however in 2015 availability is 60%.&lt;ref name=aw2015-04-06&gt;{{cite news |first=Amy |last=Butler |url=http://aviationweek.com/defense/t-x-competition-fierce-despite-gd-alenia-split |title=T-X Competition Fierce Despite GD, Alenia Split |work=[[Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology]] |date=6 April 2015 |accessdate=7 April 2015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150407211453/http://aviationweek.com/defense/t-x-competition-fierce-despite-gd-alenia-split |archivedate=7 April 2015 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Besides the USAF, USN and NASA, other T-38 operators included the [[German Air Force]] (''Luftwaffe''), the [[Portuguese Air Force]], the [[Republic of China Air Force]], and the [[Turkish Air Force]].&lt;ref name=USAF_factsheet/&gt;

===NASA===
[[NASA]] operates a fleet of thirty-two T-38 aircraft&lt;ref name=&quot;registry.faa.gov&quot;&gt;[http://registry.faa.gov/aircraftinquiry/AcftRef_Results.aspx?Mfrtxt=&amp;Modeltxt=T38&amp;PageNo=1  &quot;Aircraft – Make / Model Results: Northrop T-38.&quot;] ''FAA Registry.'' Retrieved 21 August 2011&lt;/ref&gt; and uses the aircraft as a jet trainer for its astronauts, as well as a [[chase plane]]. Its fleet is housed primarily at [[Ellington Field]] in [[Houston]], Texas. NASA's internal projections show the number of operational jet trainers falling to 16 by 2015. The agency spends $25–30 million annually to fly and maintain the T-38s.&lt;ref&gt;Creech, Gray. [http://www.nasa.gov/missions/research/T-38.html &quot;T-38 Supersonic Trainer Jet Gets New Home.&quot;] ''NASA.'' Retrieved 21 August 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accidents===
More than 210 aircraft losses and ejections have been documented over the lifetime of the T-38.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ejection-history.org.uk/Aircraft_by_Type/t_38_talon.htm] ''Northrop T-38 Losses and Ejections''&lt;/ref&gt;

NASA's T-38s were involved in four separate fatal accidents in the 1960s and 1970s, and several non-fatal incidents.
* 1964 Oct 31: Astronaut [[Theodore Freeman]] was killed as a result of a bird strike.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=_mMhAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=54YFAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=theodore%20freeman&amp;pg=2525%2C4569 &quot;Crash Kills Astronaut.&quot;] ''Richland, WA – Tri City Herald'', 1 November 1964&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=YqYyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=NOkFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1474,394194 &quot;Goose Hit Jet, Killing Astronaut.&quot;] ''The Miami News'', 17 November 1964&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1966 February 28 ([[1966 NASA T-38 crash]]): Astronauts [[Elliot See]] and [[Charles Bassett]] were killed when they struck a building in fog.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=Zf4cAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=EpsEAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=see%20bassett%20crash&amp;pg=6560%2C4113604 &quot;2 Astronauts Die In Plane Crash.&quot;] ''The Tuscaloosa News'', 28 February 1966&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=E20eAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=S8kEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2560,5750 &quot;See – Bassett Backup Crew Gets Gemini.&quot;] ''Daytona Beach, FL – Morning Journal newspaper'', 1 March 1966&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1967 October 5: Astronaut [[Clifton Williams|Clifton &quot;C.C.&quot; Williams]] was killed in a crash due to an aileron jam.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=BcIwAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=MFcDAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=williams%20crash&amp;pg=7184%2C1086744 &quot;Williams Wanted To Be First On The Moon.&quot;] ''St. Petersburg, FL -Evening Independent newspaper'', 6 October 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=4OYhAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=5GUEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5402,1608439 &quot;Board Pinpoints Astronaut's Death.&quot;] ''Sarasota, FL – Herald-Tribune newspaper'', 7 June 1968&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1972 Jan 20: NASA pilots Stuart M. Present and Mark C. Heath were killed when they crashed during an instrument approach in fog.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=mV4sAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=D80EAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2124,3339203 &quot;Two Civilian Test Pilots Die In Crash.&quot;] ''Spartanburg, SC – Herald-Journal newspaper'', 21 January 1972&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the [[1973 OPEC oil embargo]], from 1974 to 1983, the [[U.S. Air Force Thunderbirds]] aerobatic display team adopted the T-38 Talon, which used far less fuel than the [[McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II|F-4 Phantom]]. The [[Blue Angels]] downsized to the [[Douglas A-4 Skyhawk]] at roughly the same time. After the infamous 1982 &quot;[[Diamond Crash]]&quot; incident that killed four of the Thunderbirds' six demonstration pilots, the T-38 was replaced in this role by the front line [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16A Fighting Falcon]].

Two fatal crashes in 2008, on 23 April at [[Columbus Air Force Base]] in Mississippi and on 1 May at [[Sheppard Air Force Base]] in [[Wichita Falls]], [[Texas]], resulted in four fatalities, causing the Air Force to temporarily ground the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Planes Grounded After Crashes,&quot; ''[[The New York Times]], 2 May 2008, p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 May 2009, a T-38 crashed just north of [[Edwards Air Force Base]] in the [[Mojave Desert]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123150668|title=T-38 crash claims life of Edwards' pilot|work=U.S. Air Force|date=22 May 2009|accessdate=21 August 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130722130017/http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123150668|archivedate=22 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Replacement===
The USAF has launched the [[T-X program|T-X Program]], to replace the T-38. ''[[Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology]]'' reporters wrote in 2010 &quot;there appears to be no rush to purchase T-38 replacements&quot;; &quot;the service is conducting an analysis of alternatives&quot; with results &quot;not expected to be ready until the [[United States federal budget|Fiscal 2013 budget]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aviationweek.com/aw/generic/story_generic.jsp?channel=awst&amp;id=news/awst/2010/09/20/AW_09_20_2010_p30-255290.xml &quot;USAF Braces For Fiscal Bombardment.&quot;] ''AW &amp; ST'', 20 September 2010&lt;/ref&gt; In subsequent years, the Air Force indicated it would launch a competition for the T-38's replacement. Likely bidders include: A partnership of [[BAE Systems]] and Rolls Royce, offering the [[BAE Systems Hawk|Hawk trainer]], equipped with Rolls' Adour Mk951 engine offering 6,500&amp;nbsp;lb of thrust and [[FADEC]]; [[Lockheed Martin]] and [[Korea Aerospace Industries]], offering the [[KAI T-50 Golden Eagle|T-50]]; and [[Raytheon]] and [[Alenia Aermacchi]] offering the T-100, an aircraft  whose design originated with the[[Alenia Aermacchi M-346 Master|M-346]].&lt;ref&gt;Power play, The World column, ''AW &amp; ST'', 16 September 2013, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil===
There are seven privately owned T-38s in the U.S.&lt;ref name=&quot;registry.faa.gov&quot;/&gt;
[[Boeing]] owns two T-38s, which it uses as [[chase plane]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;registry.faa.gov&quot;/&gt; Thornton Corporation owns two T-38s and three F-5s and the [[National Test Pilot School]] owns one T-38.&lt;ref name=&quot;registry.faa.gov&quot;/&gt; In addition, ILOAJP HOLDING and Wayne L. Siltanen own one each.&lt;ref name=&quot;registry.faa.gov&quot;/&gt;

==Variants==
* '''N-156T''': Northrop company designation.
* '''YT-38''': Prototypes, two built with YJ85-GE-1 engines, later designated YT-38A and four pre-production aircraft with YJ-85-GE-5 engines, later designated T-38A.&lt;ref name=&quot;andrade&quot;&gt;Andrade 1979, p. 167&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''T-38A''': Two-seat advanced training aircraft, production model, 1,139 built.&lt;ref name=&quot;andrade&quot;/&gt;
* '''T-38A(N)''': Two-seat astronaut training version for NASA.  See T-38N below.
* '''AT-38A''': A small number of T-38As were converted into weapons training aircraft.
* '''DT-38A''': A number of US Navy T-38As were converted into drone directors.
* '''GT-38A''': Permanently grounded aircraft, often due to flight or ground mishap, converted into ground procedural trainers or aircraft maintenance trainers.
* '''NT-38A''': A small number of T-38As were converted into research and test aircraft.
* '''QT-38A''': Unmanned target drone aircraft.
* '''AT-38B''': Two-seat weapons training aircraft.
* '''T-38C''': A T-38A with structural and avionics upgrades.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAF_factsheet&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.af.mil/information/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=126|title=T-38 TALON Fact Sheet|work=U.S. Air Force|date=2 May 2008|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130801121407/http://www.af.mil/information/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=126|archivedate=1 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''T-38M''': Modernized Turkish Air Force T-38As with full [[glass cockpit]] and avionics, upgraded by [[Turkish Aerospace Industries]] under the project codename &quot;ARI&quot; ({{lang-tr|Arı}}, for [[Bee]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://export.ssm.gov.tr/content/productDetails.aspx?ID=124 &quot;Modifications &amp; Modernization T-38 Avionics Modernization Program.&quot;] Turkish International Cooperation and Export Activities. Retrieved 21 August 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''T-38N''': Former USAF T-38As bailed to [[NASA]] and T-38As directly assigned to NASA that received an Avionics Upgrade Program (AUP), modernizing communications and navigation systems, replacing outdated avionics, and adding a weather radar, flight management system, altitude alert systems, and modern controls and displays.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airliners.net/photo/NASA/Northrop-T-38N-Talon/1874670/] airliners.net&lt;/ref&gt; 
* '''N-205''': &quot;Space trainer&quot; variant proposed in May 1958, with triple rocket engines for vertical launch.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Northrop Space Trainer&quot;. ''The Aeroplane'', 3 April 1959, p. 393&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hetutrechtsarchief.nl/collectie/kranten/un/1959/1112 Article] from ''[[Utrechts Nieuwsblad]]'', 12 November 1959&lt;/ref&gt; Capable of Mach 3.2 on its way to an altitude of {{convert|200000|ft|m}}.
* '''ST-38''' or '''N-205B''': Revised proposal in April 1963 for the new Aerospace Research Pilot School, with a rolling takeoff, top speed of Mach 3.3 and a ceiling of {{convert|285000|ft|m}}, high enough to qualify its pilots for [[Astronaut Badge|astronaut wings]].
* '''T-38 VTOL''' Proposed vertical takeoff variant with four lift nozzles behind the pilot.

==Operators==
;{{GER}}
*[[German Air Force]] obtained 46 T-38A in 1968, now upgraded to T-38C. All aircraft are stationed at Sheppard AFB, Texas and are painted in US markings.
;{{TUR}}
*[[Turkish Air Force]] has 33 T-38M in service.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.hvkk.tsk.tr/en-us/Turkish_Air_Force/Todays_Air_Force/Aircraft_in_the_Inventory&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{USA}}
'''[[United States Air Force]]''' has 508 T-38 trainers in service as of September 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Magazine%20Documents/2012/May%202012/0509facts_fig.pdf &quot;The Air Force in Facts and Figures.&quot;] ''Air Force Magazine,'' May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''[[Air Combat Command]]'''
*[[9th Reconnaissance Wing]] – [[Beale AFB]], [[California]]
::[[1st Reconnaissance Squadron]]
*[[325th Fighter Wing]] - [[Tyndall AFB]], [[Florida]]
::[[2d Fighter Training Squadron]]
:'''[[Air Education and Training Command]]'''
*[[12th Flying Training Wing]] – [[Randolph AFB]], [[Texas]]
::[[435th Flying Training Squadron]]
::[[560th Flying Training Squadron]]
*[[14th Flying Training Wing]] – [[Columbus AFB]], [[Mississippi]]
::[[49th Flying Training Squadron]]
::[[50th Flying Training Squadron]]
*[[47th Flying Training Wing]] – [[Laughlin AFB]], Texas
::[[87th Flying Training Squadron]]
*[[71st Flying Training Wing]] – [[Vance AFB]], [[Oklahoma]]
::[[25th Flying Training Squadron]]
*[[80th Flying Training Wing]] – [[Sheppard AFB]], Texas
::[[88th Flying Training Squadron]]
::[[90th Flying Training Squadron]]
::[[469th Flying Training Squadron]]
:'''[[Air Force Reserve Command]]'''
*[[340th Flying Training Group]] – Randolph AFB
::[[43d Flying Training Squadron]] (Columbus AFB)
::[[96th Flying Training Squadron]] (Laughlin AFB)
::[[97th Flying Training Squadron]] (Sheppard AFB)
*[[413th Flight Test Group]] – Randolph AFB
::[[415th Flight Test Flight]]
:'''[[Air Force Global Strike Command]]'''
*[[509th Bomb Wing]] – [[Whiteman AFB]], [[Missouri]]
::[[394th Combat Training Squadron]]
:'''[[Air Force Materiel Command]]'''
*[[96th Test Wing]] – [[Eglin AFB]], [[Florida]]
::[[586th Flight Test Squadron]] ([[Holloman AFB]], [[New Mexico]])
*[[412th Test Wing]] – [[Edwards AFB]], [[California]]
::[[445th Flight Test Squadron]]

'''[[United States Navy]]''' has ten aircraft in use as November 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;FI_AirForces_2008&quot;&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/assets/getasset.aspx?ItemID=26061 &quot;Directory: World Air Forces.&quot;] ''[[Flight International]]'', 11–17 November 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''[[Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division]]'''
*[[United States Naval Test Pilot School]] – [[Naval Air Station Patuxent River]], [[Maryland]]

'''[[NASA]]''' has approximately 32 aircraft bailed from USAF.

==Former operators==
;{{POR}}
* [[Portuguese Air Force]] received 12 aircraft in 1977. Initially operated by [[201 Squadron (Portugal)|201 Sqn. &quot;''Falcões''&quot;]] (Falcons) at [[Monte Real Air Base|Air Base No. 5]], in 1980 they were transferred to [[103 Squadron (Portugal)|103 Sqn. &quot;''Caracóis''&quot;]] (Snails) being stationed in [[Beja Air Base|Air Base No. 11]]. They were retired in 1993.
;{{ROC-TW}}
*[[Republic of China Air Force]]
;{{ROK}}
*[[Republic of Korea Air Force]] leased thirty T-38A from the US in April 1999. All units were returned to the US by 2009 after near completion of production of [[KAI T-50 Golden Eagle|T-50 Golden Eagle]] supersonic trainer.

==Aircraft on display==
[[File:Frontiers of Flight Museum December 2015 099 (Northrop T-38 Talon).jpg|thumb|A T-38 Talon on display at the [[Frontiers of Flight Museum]]]]
;T-38A
*58-1196 – [[California Science Center]], in [[Los Angeles, California]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://californiasciencecenter.org/exhibits/air-space/air-aircraft/northrop-t-38-talon] California Science Center. Retrieved 16 June 2015&lt;/ref&gt;
*59-1601 – On base display, [[Air University (United States Air Force)|Air University]] area, [[Maxwell AFB]], Alabama&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warbirdinformationexchange.org/phpBB3/viewtopic.php?f=3&amp;t=30251&amp;start=0] warbird information exchange&lt;/ref&gt;
*59-1602 – On base display, [[United States Air Force Academy]], in [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]].  Painted as &quot;Thunderbird 1&quot;
*59-1604 – [[National Naval Aviation Museum]], [[NAS Pensacola]], Florida; former USAF aircraft bailed to [[United States Navy|USN]] and utilized by the [[U.S. Naval Test Pilot School]] at [[NAS Patuxent River]], Maryland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fc/Northrop_T-38_Talon,_Naval_Aviation_Museum,_Pensacola,_Florida.jpg] NAM, Pensacola FL&lt;/ref&gt;
*59-1605 – On base display, USAF History and Traditions Museum, [[Lackland AFB]], Texas&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aero-web.org/museums/tx/htm.htm] aero-web&lt;/ref&gt;
*60-0549 – Prairie Aviation Museum, in [[Bloomington, Illinois]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://prairieaviationmuseum.org/exhibits/aircraft/northrop-t-38a-talon/ &quot;T-38 Talon/60-0549.&quot;] Prairie Aviation Museum. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*60-0558 – American Legion Post 233 in [[Edinburgh, Indiana]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.flickr.com/photos/lunken_spotter/11897721614/ &quot;GT-38A Talon 60-0558 in Edinburgh.&quot;] Talon in Edinburgh&lt;/ref&gt;
*60-0570 – Edward F. Beale Museum, [[Beale AFB]], California&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aero-web.org/museums/ca/efbm.htm] aero-web&lt;/ref&gt;
*60-0574 – On base display, [[Laughlin AFB]], Texas&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aero-web.org/museums/tx/lafbtx.htm] aero-web&lt;/ref&gt;
*61-0817 – Oklahoma Welcome Station, adjacent to [[Tinker AFB]], [[Oklahoma]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warbirdregistry.org/jetregistry/t38-610817.html &quot;T-38 Talon/61-0817.&quot;] Warbird Registry. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*61-0829 - Gallup Municipal Airport, [[Gallup, New Mexico|Gallup]], New Mexico &lt;ref&gt; Google Maps 35.5155497,-108.7794413,276&lt;/ref&gt;
*61-0838 – On base display, in front of Randolph Inn Visiting Officers Quarters (VOQ), [[Randolph AFB]], Texas&lt;ref&gt;[http://warbirdinformationexchange.org/phpBB3/viewtopic.php?p=422922] Warbird Information Exchange&lt;/ref&gt;
*61-0854 – [[Pima Air and Space Museum]], adjacent to [[Davis-Monthan AFB]] in [[Tucson, Arizona]], on display in the markings of the [[479th Tactical Training Wing]] at [[Holloman AFB, NM]], circa 1982.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pimaair.org/collection-detail.php?cid=217 &quot;T-38 Talon/61-0854.&quot;] Pima Air &amp; Space Museum. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*61-0858 – Sheppard AFB Air Park, [[Sheppard AFB]], Texas&lt;ref name=&quot;aero-web.org&quot;&gt;http://www.aero-web.org/museums/tx/safbap.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*61-0902 – [[Science Spectrum]] in [[Lubbock, Texas]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warbirdregistry.org/jetregistry/t38-610902.html &quot;T-38 Talon/61-0902.&quot;] Warbird Registry. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*63-8125 – Sheppard AFB Air Park, Sheppard AFB&lt;ref name=&quot;aero-web.org&quot; /&gt;
*63-8224 – [[Evergreen Aviation &amp; Space Museum]] in [[McMinnville, Oregon]]; painted in NASA colors, suspended from the ceiling in the Air and Space Exhibit Hall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.evergreenmuseum.org/the-museum/aircraft-exhibits/space-flight/ &quot;T-38 Talon/63-8224.&quot;] Evergreen Aviation &amp; Space Museum. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*65-10405 – On base display, [[Columbus AFB]], Mississippi&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airliners.net/photo/USA---Air/Northrop-T-38A-Talon/1322457/L/] airliners.net&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aero-web.org/museums/ms/cafbms/65-10405.htm] aero-web&lt;/ref&gt;
*65-10426 – On base display, [[Vance AFB]], Oklahoma&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aero-web.org/museums/ok/vafbok/65-10426.htm] aero-web&lt;/ref&gt;
*66-8381 / NASA 901 (N901NA) – Assigned directly to [[NASA]] as the second NASA T-38 to be designated as 'NASA 901' and 'N901NA'; on display at Aviation Heritage Park, [[Bowling Green, Kentucky]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviationheritagepark.com/nasa-t-38-talon/] Aviation Heritage Park&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bgdailynews.com/news/nasa-t--talon-plane-arrives-in-bg/article_3436bdee-9d0f-54e8-ab1a-6712ef168527.html] ''Bowling Green Daily News''&lt;/ref&gt;

;GT-38A
*60-0592 – Dyess Linear Air Park, [[Dyess AFB]], Texas&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aero-web.org/museums/tx/dlap.htm] aero-web&lt;/ref&gt;
*60-0593 – [[March Field Air Museum]] at [[March ARB]] (former [[March AFB]]) in [[Riverside, California]], on display in Thunderbirds markings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marchfield.org/gt38a.htm &quot;T-38 Talon/60-0593.&quot;] March Field Air Museum. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*61-0824 – [[Hill Aerospace Museum]] adjacent to [[Hill AFB]], [[Utah]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hill.af.mil/library/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=5784 &quot;T-38 Talon/61-0824.&quot;] Hill Aerospace Museum. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

;YT-38A
*58-1192 – [[South Dakota Air and Space Museum]] at [[Ellsworth AFB]], [[South Dakota]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sdairandspacemuseum.com/exhibits &quot;T-38 Talon/58-1192.&quot;] South Dakota Air and Space Museum. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

;AT-38B
*60-0576 – On base display, [[Holloman AFB]], [[New Mexico]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warbirdregistry.org/jetregistry/t38-600576.html &quot;T-38 Talon/60-0576.&quot;] Warbird Registry. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*65-10441 – [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] at [[Wright-Patterson AFB]] in [[Dayton, Ohio]]. This aircraft was retired in 1991, came to the museum in 1999, and was placed on display in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=398 &quot;T-38 Talon/65-10441.&quot;] National Museum of the USAF. Retrieved 12 April 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

;T-38N
*65-10329 / NASA 969 (N969NA) – On display at Kennedy Space Center Visitor Center, [[NASA]]/[[John F. Kennedy Space Center]], [[Merritt Island, Florida]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://tinfeathers.com/Museum/Airports/NSAS/NASA.htm] tinfeathers.com&lt;/ref&gt;
*66-8381 / NASA 901 (N901NA) – Assigned directly to NASA as the second NASA T-38 to be designated as NASA 901 and N901NA; on display at Aviation Heritage Park, Bowling Green, Kentucky

==Specifications (T-38A)==
[[File:Northrop T-38A Talon 3-side view.png|right|500px]]
{{aircraft specifications
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=jet
|ref= USAF factsheet&lt;ref name=USAF_factsheet/&gt;
|crew=two: student and instructor
|length main=46 ft 4.5 in
|length alt=14.14 m
|span main=25 ft 3 in
|span alt=7.7 m
|height main=12 ft 10.5 in
|height alt=3.92 m
|area main=170 ft²
|area alt=15.79 m²
|empty weight main=7,200 lb
|empty weight alt=3,270 kg
|Armament=None
|loaded weight main=11,820 lb
|loaded weight alt=5,360 kg
|max takeoff weight main=12,093 lb
|max takeoff weight alt= 5,485 kg
|engine (jet)=[[General Electric J85]]-5A (J85-5R after PMP modification)
|type of jet=afterburning [[turbojet]]s
|number of jets=2
|thrust main= 2,050 lb
|thrust alt= 9.1 kN
|afterburning thrust main=2,900 lbf&lt;ref&gt;&quot;T-38s modified by the propulsion modernization program have approximately 19 percent more thrust, reducing takeoff distance by 9 percent.&quot; (T-38 Talon USAF Fact Sheet)&lt;/ref&gt;  
|afterburning thrust alt= 17.1 kN
|max speed main=[[Mach number|Mach]] 1.3
|max speed alt=858 mph, 1,381 km/h
|range main=1,140 mi
|range alt=1,835 km
|ceiling main=50,000 ft
|ceiling alt=15,240 m
|climb rate main=33,600 ft/min&lt;ref&gt;Even though this value has been printed in USAF outlets for many years, it is probably incorrect. The T-38 time-to-climb record, set in 1962, was 3 minutes to 30,000 feet. According to Northrop's Roy Martin (quoted on p. 64 of [[Air &amp; Space/Smithsonian]], Vol. 20, No. 3 (August/September 2005), a normal climb at military power - that is, maximum power without afterburner - is around 6,000 feet/minute.&lt;/ref&gt; (170.7 m/s)
|climb rate alt=
|loading main=69.53 lb/ft²
|loading alt=339.4 kg/m²
|thrust/weight=0.65
}}

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Air Force}}
{{aircontent
|see also=
|related=
* [[Northrop F-5]]
* [[Northrop F-20 Tigershark]]
* [[T-X program]]
|similar aircraft=
|lists=
* [[List of active United States military aircraft]]
* [[List of spaceflight-related accidents and incidents]]
}}

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}
;Bibliography
{{Refbegin}}
* Andrade, John ''U.S. Military Aircraft Designations and Serials since 1909'' Midland Counties Publications, 1979, ISBN 0 904597 22 9
* Eden, Paul, ed. &quot;Northrop F-5 family&quot;. ''Encyclopedia of Modern Military Aircraft''. London: Amber Books, 2004.  ISBN 1-904687-84-9
* Johnsen, Frederick A. ''Northrop F-5/F-20/T-38.'' North Branch, Minnesota: Specialty Press, 2006. ISBN 1-58007-094-9
* Shaw, Robbie. ''F-5: Warplane for the World.'' St. Paul, Minnesota: Motorbooks International, 1990. ISBN 0-87938-487-5
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Northrop T-38 Talon}}
*[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/aircraft/t-38.htm T-38 Talon page on GlobalSecurity.org]
*[http://www.sr-71.org/aircraft/t-38.php T-38 Talon page on SR-71.org]
*[http://www1.dfrc.nasa.gov/Gallery/Photo/T-38/index.html NASA photo gallery]
*[http://www.airspacemag.com/military-aviation/white-rocket.html &quot;White Rocket,&quot; [[Air &amp; Space/Smithsonian]] Magazine, Vol. 20, No. 3 (August/September 2005), pp.&amp;nbsp;58–65]

{{Northrop aircraft}}
{{USAF trainer aircraft}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Northrop aircraft|T-038]]
[[Category:United States military trainer aircraft 1950–1959]]
[[Category:Twinjets]]
[[Category:Low-wing aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>4udnfh2pid78l4zleohpv4f4mkpt3oy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
