<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Palmiry massacre</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46308107</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747608642</id>
      <parentid>747586345</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T09:44:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dreamcatcher25</username>
        <id>12930220</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */ parameters</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31309">[[File:Palmiry ostatnia droga.jpeg|thumb|Polish women led to mass execution in a forest near Palmiry]]
{{Coord|52.33|N|20.74|E|display=title}}
The '''Palmiry massacre''' was a series of mass executions carried out by [[Nazi Germany|Nazi German]] forces, during the [[Second World War]], near the village of [[Palmiry]] in the [[Kampinos Forest]], located northwest of [[Warsaw]].

Between December 1939 and July 1941 more than 1700 Poles and Jews &amp;ndash; mostly the inmates of [[Pawiak]] prison &amp;ndash; were executed by the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] and the [[Ordnungspolizei]] in the forest glade near Palmiry. The best documented of these massacres took place on 20–21 June 1940, wherein 358 members of the Polish political, cultural and social elite were murdered in a single operation.

Palmiry is one of the most infamous sites of [[Nazi crimes against the Polish nation|Nazi crimes]] in Poland, as well as &quot;one of the most notorious places of mass executions&quot; in Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lukas2004&quot;/&gt; Along with the [[Katyn massacre]] it has become a symbol of the martyrdom of Polish [[intelligentsia]] during the Second World War.

== Prelude ==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1974-132-33A, Warschau, Parade vor Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|[[Adolf Hitler]] attends a [[Wehrmacht]] victory parade in [[Warsaw]]. 5 October 1939]]
[[File:Więzienie Pawiak przed 1939.jpg|thumb|[[Pawiak]] prison in Warsaw]]
[[Warsaw]] was perceived by Nazi leaders as one of the biggest obstacles to their plan to subjugate the [[Poles|Polish nation]]. After the [[Nazi invasion of Poland]], Warsaw was reduced to a provincial city in the newly created [[General Government]]. However, it remained a center of Polish cultural life.{{efn|Before [[Second World War|World War II]] about 40% of Polish university students and academic [[lecturer]]s lived in [[Warsaw]]. There were more than 900 schools and colleges of various types, as well as about 200 museums, [[archive]]s, libraries, theaters and cinemas. About half of all Polish newspapers and magazines were printed in Warsaw. See: Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 39–40.}} Warsaw also headquartered the high command of the [[Polish Underground State]] and soon became a stronghold of armed and political resistance against the [[Occupation of Poland (1939–45)|German occupation]].&lt;ref&gt;Dunin-Wąsowicz (1984), p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 December 1943 Governor-General [[Hans Frank]] noted in his diary:
{{quotation|There is a one place in this country which is a source of all our misfortunes &amp;ndash; it is Warsaw. Without Warsaw we wouldn't have four-fifths of the troubles which we're facing now. Warsaw is the focus of all disturbances, the place from which discontent is spread through the whole country.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 442.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The Polish capital surrendered to the [[Wehrmacht]] armies on 28 September 1939. Three days later members of [[Einsatzgruppen|Einsatzgruppe IV]] led by SS-[[Brigadeführer]] [[Lothar Beutel]] entered the city. They immediately conducted a search in public and private buildings, as well as [[mass arrest]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 39–40.&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 October 1939 about 354 Polish [[teacher]]s and [[Priesthood (Catholic Church)|catholic priests]] were detained because occupational authorities assumed that they are “full of Polish chauvinism” and “created an enormous danger” for public order.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardzyńska240&quot;&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), p. 240.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon Warsaw's prisons and detention centers [[Pawiak]], [[Mokotów Prison]], the Central Detention Center at Daniłowiczowska Street, the cellars of the [[Mausoleum of Struggle and Martyrdom|Gestapo headquarter on 25 Szucha Avenue]] were full of inmates.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1976), p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the prisoners were deported to [[Nazi concentration camps]]. Many others were murdered.

In the first months of German occupation political prisoners from Warsaw were secretly executed in the back of the Polish parliament ([[Sejm]]) building complex at Wiejska Street{{efn|After the beginning of [[Occupation of Poland (1939–45)|German occupation]], the [[Sejm]] buildings were converted into barracks for [[Ordnungspolizei]] units.}} (in the so-called Sejm gardens, ''ogrody sejmowe''). Between October 1939 and April 1940 several hundred people were murdered in this place. However Nazi German police authorities soon realized that they would not be able to keep executions secret if they were conducted in the very center of a large city.&lt;ref&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), pp. 241–242.&lt;/ref&gt; It was decided that henceforth mass executions would be carried out in the small forest glade in [[Kampinos Forest]], located near the villages of [[Palmiry]] and Pociecha,&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; about {{convert|30|km}} northwest of Warsaw.

== ''Modus operandi'' ==
[[File:Glade of death near Palmiry.jpg|thumb|“Glade of death” near the Palmiry. Post-war photography]]
[[File:Polish Hostages preparing in Palmiry by Nazi-Germans for mass execution 2.jpg|thumb|Pamiry. Prisoners are blindfolded before execution]]
[[File:Palmiry before execution.jpg|thumb|Victims and their executioners]]
[[File:Palmiry death transport.jpg|thumb|Death transport with empty trucks back to Warsaw after the execution in Palmiry]]
[[File:Museum of Palmiry massacre - 15.jpg|thumb|Official death notice sent by Nazi authorities to the family of one of the victims]]
[[File:Investigation at the place of mass executions in Palmiry 02.jpg|thumb|Forester Adam Herbański (right) with Stanisław Płoski, Chairman of the Commission for the Investigation of Nazi Crimes in Warsaw]]
Executions in Palmiry were carried out by the members of the Ordnungspolizei or by the SS-Reiterei (SS Cavalry) regiment which was quartered in Warsaw. They were overseen by Gestapo officers led by the [[Sicherheitsdienst|SD]] and [[Sicherheitspolizei]] Commander in Warsaw, SS-[[Standartenführer]] [[Josef Meisinger]].&lt;ref&gt;Böhler, Mallmann, Matthäus (2009), p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;

In every case mass executions in Palmiry were prepared in a careful manner. Mass graves were always dug a few days before the planned execution. Usually it was done by the [[Reichsarbeitsdienst|Arbeitsdienst]] unit which was quartered in [[Łomna, Nowy Dwór Mazowiecki County|Łomna]] or by [[Hitler Youth|Hitlerjugend]] members who camped near Palmiry. In most cases the graves were shaped like a ditch and were more than {{convert|30|m}} long and {{convert|2.5-3|m}} deep. Sometimes, for smaller groups of convicts or for individual victims, irregularly shaped graves were prepared, similar to natural terrain landslides or to [[explosion crater]]s. The glade where executions took place was soon enlarged by tree-cutting.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt; On the day of planned execution Polish forestry workers always received a day off. In the meantime German police undertook intensive patrolling near the glade and in the surrounding forest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski66&quot;&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt;

Victims were transported to the place of execution by trucks. Usually they were brought from Pawiak prison, rarely from Mokotów Prison. SS soldiers tried to convince their victims that they are going to transfer them to another prison or to a concentration camp. For this reason, death transports were usually formed at dusk and prisoners were allowed to take their belongings with them. Sometimes before departure convicts received an additional food ration and they were given back their documents from the prison's depository.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski65&quot;&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, these methods were so effective that the prisoners were not aware of the fate awaiting them.&lt;ref&gt;Domańska (1978), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, when the truth about what was happening in Palmiry spread through Warsaw, some victims tried to throw short letters or small belongings from the trucks, in hopes that in this way they would be able to inform their families about their fate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski65&quot;/&gt; During postwar exhumation some bodies were found with a card reading &quot;Executed in Palmiry&quot;, written by the victims shortly before their death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski 1970, p. 112&quot;&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the glade the prisoners' bags were taken but they were permitted to keep their documents and small belongings. Jews could keep their [[yellow badge]]s, and people who worked in Pawiak's infirmary could keep their badges with the [[Emblems of the International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|Red Cross symbol]]. Sometimes prisoners' hands were tied and their eyes blindfolded. The victims were then taken to the edge of the grave and executed by machine gun fire. Sometimes victims were forced to hold a long pole or ladder behind their back. Such supports were later lowered so that the bodies fell into the grave in an even layer. Postwar exhumation proved that the wounded victims were sometimes buried alive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski65&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1976), p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; SS and OrPo members photographed the executions until it was forbidden by the SS-Standartenführer Meisinger, as happened on 3 May 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Domańska (1978), p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; After the execution was finished, the graves were filled in, covered with [[moss]] and needles, and then planted over with young [[pine]] trees. Families of the victims were later informed by the Nazi authorities that their relatives had &quot;died from natural causes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski66&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardzyńska242&quot;&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), p. 242.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite all efforts, the Nazis were not able to keep the massacres secret. Local Polish inhabitants, especially forestry workers and inhabitants of Palmiry and Pociecha, had many opportunities to observe the death transports and to hear the gunshots. Several times they also saw groups of convicts being led to the place of execution. Forester Adam Herbański and his subordinates from the Polish Forest Service helped reveal the truth about the Palmiry massacre. At risk of their lives, they visited the forest glade after the executions (usually at night) in order to secretly mark out the mass graves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski66&quot;/&gt; Also, a few photos taken by the executioners in Palmiry were stolen by members of the [[Union of Armed Struggle]].{{efn|Some of these photos were included in a brochure titled ''Totaler Terror. Polen am Marterpfahl'' (&quot;Total terror. Poland at the torture stake&quot;), which was published by the [[Polish Underground State]] in 1943. The brochure was written in German because German soldiers stationed in occupied Poland were its target.}}

==Timeline of the Palmiry massacre ==

=== First executions  ===
Probably the first executions in the forest glade near Palmiry were carried out on 7 and 8 December 1939, when 70 and 80 people were murdered, respectively. According to the Wehrmacht soldiers who guarded a nearby ammunition warehouse, all the victims were Jewish. However, it is impossible to confirm that information.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 67–68.&lt;/ref&gt;

The next execution was conducted on 14 December 1939 when 46 people were shot dead. At least some of the victims came from [[Pruszków]]. Among them were Stanisław Kalbarczyk, a Polish teacher from Pruszków, and two unidentified women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski68&quot;&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Egzekucja w Palmirach.jpg|thumb|Mass execution in Palmiry]]
The circumstances of the last mass execution conducted in Palmiry in 1939 are at least partially known. However, according to Maria Wardzyńska (a Polish historian employed in the [[Institute of National Remembrance]]), at least 70 other people were secretly executed in Palmiry before the end of 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardzyńska244&quot;&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January and February 1940 the Gestapo infiltrated and crushed the underground organization ''Polska Ludowa Akcja Niepodległościowa'' (PLAN) (&quot;Polish People's Independence Action&quot;). On 14 January, the PLAN commander, Kazimierz Andrzej Kott, escaped from the Gestapo headquarters at 25 Szucha Avenue. Soon after, several hundred people were arrested in Warsaw, among them 255 leading Jewish intellectuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski68&quot;/&gt; On 21 January about 80 hostages, including two women, were executed in Palmiry. Among the victims were Fr. Marceli Nowakowski (rector of the [[Church of the Holiest Saviour|Church of the Holiest Saviour in Warsaw]], and former member of parliament) and 36 Jews (including attorney Ludwik Dyzenhaus, dentist Franciszek Sturm and chess master [[Dawid Przepiórka]]). Another 118 people arrested after Kott's escape, mostly Jews, were probably murdered in Palmiry in the first months of 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Maria Wardzyńska, about 40 inhabitants of [[Zakroczym]] were also executed in Palmiry in January 1940. Among them was the mayor of Zakroczym, Tadeusz Henzlich.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardzyńska244&quot;/&gt;

The next mass execution in Palmiry was carried out on 26 February 1940. In retaliation for the death of the German mayor of [[Legionowo]], who had been assassinated two days earlier by unknown perpetrators, about 190 people were murdered at the &quot;glade of death&quot;. Among the victims were six women. In most cases the victims of this execution came from Legionowo or from surrounding localities.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Domańska (1978), p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the night of 28 March 1940, German police officers entered the house at Sosnowa Street in Warsaw where Józef Bruckner, commander of the underground organization ''Wilki'' (&quot;The Wolves&quot;), had his conspiratorial flat. Bruckner and his aide opened fire on the policemen, and after a brief fight, they escaped from the building. In retaliation, the Germans arrested 34 Polish men who lived in this building (aged 17 to 60). All of them were murdered in Palmiry on 23 April 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 78–79.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 April 1940, about 100 inmates of Pawiak and Mokotów prisons were murdered in Palmiry. The execution was conducted in retaliation for the assassination of two German soldiers in Warsaw. Among the victims were Fr. Jan Krawczyk (theologian, parson of Catholic parish in [[Wilanów]]), Bogumił Marzec (attorney), Stefan Napierski (literary critic, editor of monthly magazine of literature ''Ateneum''), Bohdan Offenberg (deputy director of the Labour Fund), Zbigniew Rawicz-Twaróg (captain of the Polish Army), Jacek Szwemin (architect), and 27 women.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 76–77.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Polish historians, between 700&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 445.&lt;/ref&gt; and 900&lt;ref&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt; people were executed in Palmiry from December 1939 until April 1940.

=== ''AB-Aktion'' ===
[[File:Secret list of the Palmiry massacre victims.jpg|thumb|Secret list smuggled from [[Pawiak]] by the Polish female guard Janina Gruszkowa (member of the Polish resistance). It contains some of the names of Polish political prisoners who were executed in Palmiry on 20–21 June 1940]]
[[File:Palmiry cemetery 20080713 02.jpg|thumb|Grave of [[Maciej Rataj]] at the cemetery in Palmiry]]
{{Further|German AB-Aktion in Poland}}
In the spring of 1940, the highest [[Nazi Party|NSDAP]] and SS authorities in the General Government decided to conduct a wide-ranging police operation aimed at the extermination of the Polish political, cultural, and social elite. The mass murder of Polish politicians, intellectuals, artists, social activists, as well as people suspected of potential anti-Nazi activity, was seen as a preemptive measure to keep the [[Polish resistance movement in World War II|Polish resistance]] scattered and to prevent the Poles from revolting during the planned German [[Battle of France|invasion of France]]. This operation was given the code name ''AB-Aktion'' (shortcut from ''Außerordentliche Befriedungsaktion''{{efn|English: &quot;Extraordinary Operation of Pacification&quot;.}}).&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 60–62.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mańkowski (1992), pp. 10–12.&lt;/ref&gt; It officially lasted from May to July 1940 and claimed at least 6500 lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardzyńska240&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mańkowski (1992), p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rozett &amp; Spector (2013), p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the end of March 1940, Warsaw and surrounding cities were hit by a wave of arrests. During the next two months, hundreds of Polish intellectuals and prewar politicians were detained and imprisoned in Pawiak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardzyńska244&quot;/&gt; On 20 April, the Gestapo arrested 42 Polish attorneys in the building of Warsaw's Chamber of Attorneys. On 10 May, occupants detained over a dozen Polish school headmasters who, despite the German interdict, had closed their school on [[May 3rd Constitution Day]].&lt;ref&gt;Mańkowski (1992), p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; The frequency and number of executions in Palmiry increased with the beginning of ''AB-Aktion''.&lt;ref&gt;Mańkowski (1992), p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first mass execution conducted in Palmiry in the course of ''AB-Aktion'' took place on 14 June 1940. About 20 people were murdered on that day, among them Polish historian Karol Drewnowski and his son Andrzej.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1976), p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

The best-documented massacre took place on 20–21 June 1940 when three transports with 358 inmates were sent from Pawiak to the place of execution near Palmiry. Among the victims were:&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 83–94.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), pp. 262–263.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Maciej Rataj]]  (politician, former [[Marshal of the Sejm]])
* [[Mieczysław Niedziałkowski]] (politician of the [[Polish Socialist Party]])
* [[Jan Pohoski]] (prewar deputy [[president of Warsaw]])
* [[Ludomir Skórewicz]] (prewar [[starosta]] of Warsaw [[powiat]])
* [[Halina Jaroszewiczowa]] (politician, former member of parliament)
* Henryk Brun ([[Business magnate|industrialist]], former member of parliament, chairman of the Polish Merchants Association)
* [[Janusz Kusociński]] (athlete, winner of the 10,000 m race at the [[1932 Summer Olympics]])
* Feliks Zuber (athlete, deputy president of &quot;[[Warszawianka Warszawa|Warszawianka]]&quot; sport club)
* [[Tomasz Stankiewicz]] ([[Track cycling|track cyclist]] who competed in the [[1924 Summer Olympics]])
* Jan Wajzer ([[doctor of law]], secretary general of the Polish Union in [[Free City of Danzig]])
* Stefan Kwiatkowski (deputy chairman of the Association of teachers of secondary and third degree schools)
* Władysław Dziewałtowski-Gintowt, Tadeusz Fabiani, Edmund Grabowski, Czesław Jankowski, Stanisław Jezierski, Józef Krasuski, Jerzy Niżałowski, Józef Starzewski, Wacław Tyrchowski (attorneys)
* Stanisław Beer, Jadwiga Fuks, Maria Witkowska (painters);
* Helena Łopuszańska (actress)
* Alicja Bełcikowska, Jan Bełcikowski, Grzegorz Krzeczkowski, Wojciech Kwasieborski, Tadeusz Lipkowski, Jan Werner (writers and publicists)

=== Last executions ===
[[File:Announcement of death of Polish hostages executed after the death of Igo Sym.jpg|thumb|SS-[[Gruppenführer]] [[Paul Moder]] announcement of execution of “a number of Poles”  in retaliation of death of [[Igo Sym]]]]
On 23 July 1940, Governor-General Hans Frank officially announced the end of ''AB-Aktion''. Despite that, massacres in Palmiry continued for over a year. On 30 August 1940, at least 87 persons were executed at the forest glade. Among the victims were a number of people who were arrested in [[Włochy]] three months earlier.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another mass execution was carried out on 17 September 1940 when about 200 prisoners of Pawiak, including 20 women, were murdered at the forest glade near Palmiry. Among the victims were: Tadeusz Panek and Zbigniew Wróblewski (attorneys), Fr. Zygmunt Sajna (parson of Catholic parish in [[Góra Kalwaria]]), Jadwiga Bogdziewicz and Jan Borski (journalists).&lt;ref&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), p. 263.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Regina Domańska, this massacre might be connected with the uncovering of an underground printing house at Lwowska Street in Warsaw.&lt;ref&gt;Domańska (1978), p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;

This was the last execution conducted in Palmiry in 1940 for which circumstances are at least partially known. However, during the postwar exhumation, three mass graves filled with 74, 28, and 24 corpses respectively, were found at the forest glade. It is certain that first two of them were filled and buried in the winter of 1940, while the third one was probably dug in the winter of 1940 or 1939.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1976), pp. 102–104.&lt;/ref&gt; Polish historians were not able to determine the circumstances of those massacres. According to Regina Domańska, about 27 prisoners of Pawiak were executed in Palmiry on 4 December 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Domańska (1978), p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Maria Wardzyńska, up to 260 people could have been murdered in Palmiry in the winter of 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Wardzyńska (2009), pp. 263–264.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 March 1941, actor [[Igo Sym]], well-known Nazi [[Collaboration|collaborator]] and Gestapo agent, was assassinated by the soldiers of the [[Union of Armed Struggle]]. In retaliation,  21 Pawiak prisoners were executed in Palmiry four days later. Among the victims were [[Stefan Kopec|Stefan Kopeć]] (biologist, professor at the [[University of Warsaw]]) and [[Kazimierz Zakrzewski]] (historian, professor at the University of Warsaw).&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Domańska (1978), p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 April 1941 about 20 men from [[Łowicz]] were executed in Palmiry. Among the victims was deputy mayor of Łowicz, Adolf Kutkowski.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another massacre was conducted on 12 June 1941 when 30 prisoners of Pawiak, including 14 women, were murdered in Palmiry. Among the victims were: [[Witold Hulewicz]] (poet and radio journalist), [[Stanisław Piasecki]] (right-wing politician and literary critic), Jerzy Szurig (lawyer, [[Syndicalism|syndicalist]]), Stanisław Malinowski (attorney).&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Domańska (1978), p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt;

The last known mass execution in Palmiry was carried out on 17 July 1941 when 47 people, mostly prisoners of Pawiak, were murdered in the forest glade. Among the victims were Zygmunt Dymek (journalist and labor activist) and six women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski 1970, p. 112&quot;/&gt;

After 17 July 1941, German authorities ceased using the forest glade in Palmiry as a place of mass executions. The reason probably was that they realized the Polish resistance and the civilian population were well aware of what was happening in Palmiry.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1976), pp. 66–67.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Remembrance ==
[[File:Exhumation of bodies of victims massacred by Nazi-Germans in Palmiry 01.jpg|thumb|Exhumation in Palmiry in 1946]]
[[File:Exhumation of bodies of victims massacred by Nazi-Germans in Palmiry 03.jpg|thumb|[[Human skull]] found in a mass grave. Note entrance and exit gunshot wounds.]]
[[File:Palmiry Cemetery.JPG|thumb|Cemetery and a mausoleum in Palmiry]]
[[File:Museum of Palmiry massacre - 12.jpg|thumb|Palmiry National Memorial Museum. Part of the exposition]]
After the war, the [[Polish Red Cross]], supported by the Chief Commission for the Investigation of German Crimes in Poland, began the search and exhumation process in Palmiry. The work was carried out between 25 November and 6 December 1945, and later from 28 March until the first months of summer 1946. Thanks to Adam Herbański and his subordinates from the Polish Forest Service, who in the years of occupation were risking their own lives to mark the places of execution, Polish investigators were able to find 24 mass graves. More than 1700 corpses were exhumed, but only 576 of them were identified. Later Polish historians were able to identify the names of another 480 victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardzyńska242&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt; It is possible that some graves still lie undiscovered in the forest near Palmiry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartoszewski66&quot;/&gt;

In 1948 the forest glade near Palmiry was transformed into a war cemetery and a mausoleum.&lt;ref name=&quot;Misiak&quot;&gt;Misiak (2006), pp. 6–7.&lt;/ref&gt; Victims of Nazi terror whose bodies were found in some other places of execution within the so-called &quot;Warsaw Death Ring&quot;{{efn|In Lasy Chojnowskie, Laski, Łuże, Szwedzkie Góry, Wólka Węglowa.}} were also buried in the Palmiry cemetery. Altogether, approximately 2204 people are buried there.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1976), p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, the Palmiry National Memorial Museum, a branch of the [[Museum of Warsaw]], was created in Palmiry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Misiak&quot;/&gt;

Fr. Zygmunt Sajna, who was murdered in Palmiry on 17 September 1940, is one of the [[108 Martyrs of World War II|108 Polish Martyrs of World War II]] [[Beatification|beatified]] on 13 June 1999 by Pope [[John Paul II]].&lt;ref&gt;Stelmasiak (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Idziemy&quot;&gt;Świątkiewicz (2015)&lt;/ref&gt; Fr. Kazimierz Pieniążek (member of the [[Resurrectionist Congregation]]), another victim of the Palmiry massacre, has been accorded the title of [[Servant of God#Roman Catholic Church|Servant of God]]. He is currently one of the 122 Polish martyrs of the Second World War included in the beatification process initiated in 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;Idziemy&quot;/&gt;

Palmiry has become, as [[Richard C. Lukas]] puts it, &quot;one of the most notorious places of mass executions&quot; in Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lukas2004&quot;&gt;Lukas (2004), p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also one of the most famous sites of [[Nazi crimes against the Polish nation|Nazi crimes in Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warsawtour.pl/en/tourist-attractions/palmiry-national-memorial-museum-miejsce-pami-ci-palmiry-4021.html Palmiry National Memorial Museum]&lt;/ref&gt; Along with the [[Katyn massacre|Katyn Forest]] it became a symbol of the martyrdom of the Polish [[intelligentsia]] during the Second World War.&lt;ref&gt;Sierchuła &amp; Muszyński (2008), p. I.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011 Polish president [[Bronisław Komorowski]] said that &quot;Palmiry is to some extent the Warsaw Katyn&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prezydent.pl/aktualnosci/wizyty-krajowe/art,67,prezydent-palmiry-to-warszawski-katyn.html |title=Prezydent: Palmiry to warszawski Katyń |trans_title=President: Palmiry is a Warsaw Katyn |publisher=President of the Polish Republic |date=31 March 2011 |accessdate=23 April 2015 |language=Polish |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150518091517/http://www.prezydent.pl/aktualnosci/wizyty-krajowe/art,67,prezydent-palmiry-to-warszawski-katyn.html |archivedate=May 18, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Justice ==
Some of the Palmiry murderers were brought to justice. [[Ludwig Fischer]], governor of Warsaw district in 1939–1945, and SS-Standartenführer [[Josef Meisinger]], who occupied the post of SD and SiPo Commander in Warsaw in years 1939–1941, were arrested after the war by [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] forces and handed over to the Polish authorities. Their trial took place between 17 December 1946 and 24 February 1947. On 3 March 1947, the [[Supreme National Tribunal]] in Warsaw condemned both of them to death. Meisinger and Fischer were hanged in Mokotów Prison in March 1947.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), pp. 54 and 423.&lt;/ref&gt;

SS-[[Gruppenführer]] [[Paul Moder]], [[SS and Police Leader]] in Warsaw district in 1940–1941, was killed in action on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] in February 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Bartoszewski (1970), p. 424.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{notes}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{cite book|author1=[[Władysław Bartoszewski]] |title= Palmiry|year= 1976 |publisher=Książka i Wiedza|location= Warszawa|language=pl}}
* {{cite book|author1=Władysław Bartoszewski | title= Warszawski pierścień śmierci 1939–1944|year= 1970 |publisher=Interpress|location= Warszawa|language=pl}}
* {{cite book|author1= [[Jochen Böhler]]|author2= [[Klaus-Michael Mallmann]]|author3= Jürgen Matthäus |title= Einsatzgruppen w Polsce |year=2009 |publisher=Bellona|location= Warszawa|isbn= 978-83-11-11588-0|language=pl}}
* {{cite book|author1=Regina Domańska|title= Pawiak – więzienie Gestapo. Kronika lat 1939–1944|year= 1978 |publisher=Książka i Wiedza|location= Warszawa|language=pl}}
* {{cite book|author1=Krzysztof Dunin-Wąsowicz| title= Warszawa w latach 1939–1945|year= 1984 |publisher=Państwowe Wydawnictwo Naukowe|location= Warszawa|isbn=83-01-04207-9|language=pl}}
* {{cite book|author=Richard C. Lukas|authorlink=Richard C. Lukas|title=Forgotten Survivors: Polish Christians Remember the Nazi Occupation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rEtnAAAAMAAJ|year=2004|publisher=University Press of Kansas|isbn=978-0-7006-1350-2|accessdate=2016-03-24}}
* {{ cite book|author1= Zygmunt Mańkowski|title = Außerordentliche Befriedungsaktion 1940 – akcja AB na ziemiach polskich|publisher = Zakład Historii Najnowszej Uniwersytetu Marii Skłodowskiej-Curie i OKBZpNP-IPN w Lublinie | location= Warszawa | year = 1992|language=pl}}
* {{ cite book| author1= Jerzy Misiak | title = Palmiry| publisher = Kampinoski Park Narodowy | location= Izabelin | year = 2006 | isbn = 83-89961-22-9|language=pl }}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.co.il/books?id=J5EuAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA101|author1=Robert Rozett|author2=Shmuel Spector|title=Encyclopedia of the Holocaust|year=2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=1135969507|accessdate=2016-03-24}}
* {{cite journal|author1= Rafał Sierchuła |author2= Wojciech Muszyński |date= 2008-04-04|title= Katyń i Palmiry 1940 (Dodatek specjalny IPN)|language= pl|journal= Niezależna Gazeta Polska}}
* {{cite web|author1=Artur Stelmasiak|title= Dobry proboszcz na złe czasy|date=August 2008|language=pl|url=http://e-civitas.pl/dobry-proboszcz-na-zle-czasy/ |publisher= e-civitas.pl |accessdate= April 23, 2015}}
* {{cite web|author1=Wojciech Świątkiewicz|title= Palmiry: warszawski Katyń |date=21 June 2015|language=pl|url= http://idziemy.pl/spoleczenstwo/palmiry-warszawski-katyn|publisher= idziemy.pl|accessdate= June 12, 2016}}
* {{cite book|author1= Maria Wardzyńska| title= Był rok 1939. Operacja niemieckiej policji bezpieczeństwa w Polsce. Intelligenzaktion|year= 2009 |publisher=[[Institute of National Remembrance|Instytut Pamięci Narodowej]]|location= Warszawa|isbn=978-83-7629-063-8|language=pl}}
* {{cite web|title= Palmiry National Memorial Museum (Miejsce Pamięci Palmiry) |url= http://www.warsawtour.pl/en/tourist-attractions/palmiry-national-memorial-museum-miejsce-pami-ci-palmiry-4021.html|publisher= warsawtour.pl|accessdate=April 23, 2015}}
*{{cite web|title=Prezydent: Palmiry to warszawski Katyń |date=March 31, 2011 |url=http://www.prezydent.pl/aktualnosci/wizyty-krajowe/art,67,prezydent-palmiry-to-warszawski-katyn.html |publisher=prezydent.pl |accessdate=April 23, 2015 |language=pl |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150518091517/http://www.prezydent.pl/aktualnosci/wizyty-krajowe/art,67,prezydent-palmiry-to-warszawski-katyn.html |archivedate=May 18, 2015 }}

{{Commons category|Palmiry massacre}}
{{Massacres of Poles}}

[[Category:1939 in Poland]]
[[Category:1940 in Poland]]
[[Category:1941 in Poland]]
[[Category:Anti-Polish sentiment in Europe]]
[[Category:History of Warsaw]]
[[Category:Massacres in Poland]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 1939]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 1940]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 1941]]
[[Category:Nazi war crimes in Poland]]
[[Category:Holocaust locations in Poland]]</text>
      <sha1>jf39qph0msutgkkl7zrtytn9qi8f4g8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
