<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Plan Z</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2144739</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748691026</id>
      <parentid>748669267</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-09T19:04:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FockeWulf FW 190</username>
        <id>19468137</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>improved wording</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19622">{{About|the pre-WWII plan to re-equip Nazi Germany's Kriegsmarine navy|other uses|Z Plan{{!}}Z Plan (disambiguation)}}

'''Plan Z''' was the name given to the planned re-equipment and expansion of the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' (German navy) ordered by [[Adolf Hitler]] in early 1939. The fleet was meant to challenge the naval power of the [[United Kingdom]], and was to be completed by 1948. Development of the plan began in 1938, but it reflected the evolution of the strategic thinking of the ''[[Oberkommando der Marine]]'' (Naval High Command) over the two decades following [[World War I]]. The plan called for a fleet centered on ten battleships and four aircraft carriers which were intended to battle the [[Royal Navy]]. This force would be supplemented with numerous long-range cruisers that would attack British shipping. A relatively small force of [[U-boat]]s was also stipulated.

When [[World War II]] broke out in September 1939, almost no work had been done on the new ships ordered under Plan Z. The need to shift manufacturing capacity to more pressing requirements forced the ''Kriegsmarine'' to abandon the construction program, and only a handful of major ships&amp;mdash;all of which had been ordered before Plan Z&amp;mdash;were completed during the war. Nevertheless, the plan still had a significant effect on the course of World War II, in that only a few dozen U-boats had been completed by the outbreak of war. Admiral [[Karl Dönitz]]'s U-boat fleet only reached the 300 U-boats he deemed necessary to win a commerce war against Britain in 1943, by which time his forces had been decisively defeated.

==Naval construction under Versailles==
[[File:Light Cruiser Emden in China 1931 crop.jpg|thumb|{{ship|German cruiser|Emden||2}}, the first major warship built after World War I]]
Following the end of [[World War I]], the German armed forces became subject to the restrictions of the [[Treaty of Versailles]]. For the new ''[[Reichsmarine]]'', this meant it was limited to six [[pre-dreadnought battleship]]s, six old [[light cruisers]], 12 [[destroyer]]s and 12 [[torpedo boat]]s. A further two pre-dreadnoughts, two cruisers, and four destroyers and torpedo boats apiece could be kept in reserve.&lt;ref name=GC218&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; The first major ship to be built after the war was the light cruiser {{ship|German cruiser|Emden||2}} in the early 1920s. This was followed by a further three light cruisers of the {{sclass-|Königsberg|cruiser (1927)|4}}: {{ship|German cruiser|Königsberg||2}}, {{ship|German cruiser|Karlsruhe||2}} and {{ship|German cruiser|Köln||2}}, and a further two ships that were modified versions of the ''Königsberg''-class, {{ship|German cruiser|Leipzig||2}} and {{ship|German cruiser|Nürnberg||2}}.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, pp. 229&amp;ndash;231&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the Germans created a dummy corporation, [[NV Ingenieurskantoor voor Scheepsbouw]] (IvS), in the Netherlands to secretly continue development of submarines.&lt;ref&gt;Rössler, p. 88&lt;/ref&gt; This was in violation of Article 191 of the Treaty of Versailles, which prohibited Germany from possessing or building submarines for any purpose.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Treaty of Versailles/Part V#Article 191|Treaty of Versailles, Part V, Section II, Article 191]]&lt;/ref&gt; IvS built several submarines for foreign navies, including the Turkish [[TCG Gür (1936)|''Gür'']], which was the basis for the [[German Type I submarine|Type I U-boat]], and the Finnish [[Finnish submarine Vesikko|''Vesikko'']], which was the prototype for the [[German Type II submarine|Type II U-boat]].&lt;ref&gt;Rössler, p. 98&amp;ndash;99&lt;/ref&gt;

The Treaty also stipulated that Germany could replace its pre-dreadnought battleships after they reached twenty years of age, but new vessels could [[Displacement (ship)|displace]] no more than {{convert|10000|LT|t|lk=on|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; In response to these limitations, the Germans attempted to build a powerful heavy cruiser&amp;mdash;classified as a ''panzerschiff'' (armored ship)&amp;mdash;that outclassed the new heavy cruisers built by Britain and France. British and French [[heavy cruiser]] designs were bound by the [[Washington Naval Treaty]] (and subsequent [[London Naval Treaty]]) to a caliber of {{convert|8|in|abbr=on}} on a displacement of 10,000 tons, the Germans chose to arm {{ship|German cruiser|Deutschland||2}} with six {{convert|11|in|mm|abbr=on}} guns. The Germans hoped that by building a ship significantly more powerful than the Allies, they could force the Allies to admit Germany to the Washington treaty system in exchange for cancelling ''Deutschland'', thereby abrogating the naval limitations imposed by Versailles. The French vehemently opposed any concessions to Germany, and therefore, ''Deutschland'' and two further units&amp;mdash;{{ship|German cruiser|Admiral Scheer||2}} and {{Ship|German cruiser|Admiral Graf Spee||2}}&amp;mdash;were built.&lt;ref&gt;Bidlingmaier, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1932, the ''Reichsmarine'' secured the passage of the ''Schiffbauersatzplan'' (&quot;Replacement ship construction program&quot;) through the ''[[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]]''. The program called for two separate production phases, the first from 1930 to 1936, and the second from 1936 to 1943. The latter phase was secretly intended to break the Versailles restrictions.&lt;ref name=GC219&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, [[Adolf Hitler]] became the Chancellor of Germany. He unilaterally withdrew from the restrictions of the Treaty of Versailles and began the systematic re-building of the armed forces. The prestige brought by the ''Panzerschiffe'' led to two improved vessels, the [[D class cruiser (Germany)|D class]], to be ordered. These ships were cancelled and reordered as the battleships {{ship|German battleship|Scharnhorst||2}} and {{ship|German battleship|Gneisenau||2}},&lt;ref&gt;Gröner, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; which were {{convert|32000|LT|adj=on}} ships armed with nine 28&amp;nbsp;cm guns and much greater armor protection than their predecessors.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; In 1935, Hitler signed the [[Anglo-German Naval Agreement]], which permitted Germany to build up to 35&amp;nbsp;percent of the strength of the [[Royal Navy]] in all warship categories.&lt;ref name=GC220&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 220&lt;/ref&gt; The initial designs for two follow-on ships&amp;mdash;the {{sclass-|Bismarck|battleship|4}}&amp;mdash;initially called for a displacement of {{convert|35000|LT}} with {{convert|13|in|abbr=on}} guns, but to counter the two new, French {{sclass-|Richelieu|battleship|1}}s, the new ships were significantly enlarged, to a displacement of over {{convert|41000|LT}} and {{convert|15|in|abbr=on}} guns.&lt;ref&gt;Garzke &amp; Dulin, pp. 203&amp;ndash;209&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational philosophies==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1980-128-63, Erich Raeder.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Erich Raeder]], commander of the ''Kriegsmarine'']]
The postwar German navy was conflicted over what direction future construction should take. In September 1920, ''[[Konteradmiral]]'' (Rear Admiral) [[William Michaelis]] issued a memorandum laying out the goals of the new ''Reichsmarine''; these goals emphasized coastal defense rather than significant expansion. The Army viewed Poland as the primary future enemy, and the Navy assumed that in a conflict with Poland, France would support Poland. Thus, the [[French Navy]] would be the most likely opponent for the ''Reichsmarine''; Britain was expected to remain neutral in such a conflict. The construction of warships through the mid-1930s was primarily directed against the perceived French threat.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, pp. 218&amp;ndash;219&lt;/ref&gt; Any hypothetical U-boats would generally support the main fleet rather than embark on a commerce-raiding campaign, and any raiding would be done strictly according to [[cruiser rules]].&lt;ref&gt;Herwig, p. 237&lt;/ref&gt; This view remained the established orthodoxy until the mid-1930s, when then-''[[Kapitän zur See]]'' (Captain at Sea) [[Karl Dönitz]] came to command the U-boat arm.&lt;ref&gt;Rössler, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; Dönitz advocated a return to [[unrestricted submarine warfare]] and the adoption of [[Wolfpack (naval tactic)|wolfpack tactics]] to overwhelm convoy defenses.&lt;ref&gt;Blair, p. 37&amp;ndash;38&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1920s, the question arose over what to do with the cruisers that would presumably be abroad on training cruises when a war would break out. The high command decided that they should operate as independent commerce raiders. When ''[[Vizeadmiral]]'' (Vice Admiral) [[Erich Raeder]] became the head of the ''Reichsmarine'' in 1928, he fully endorsed the concept of long-range surface raiders. This was in large part due to his service in World War I as the chief of staff to ''Vizeadmiral'' [[Franz von Hipper]], where he saw the fleet rendered impotent by the crushing British naval superiority.&lt;ref name=GC219/&gt; By 1938, Hitler's aggressive foreign policy made conflict with Britain increasingly likely. He ordered that completion of {{ship|German battleship|Bismarck||2}} and {{ship|German battleship|Tirpitz||2}} be expedited, along with six new [[H-class battleship proposals|H-class battleships]] yet to be laid down. These eight battleships would form the core of a new battle fleet capable of engaging the British Royal Navy. Hitler nevertheless assured Raeder that war would not come until 1948.&lt;ref name=GC220/&gt;

Raeder meanwhile believed that Britain could be more easily defeated through the surface raider strategy he favored. The initial version of his plan was based on the assumption that the fleet should be centered on ''panzerschiffe'', long-range cruisers, and U-boats to attack British commerce.&lt;ref name=GC220/&gt; These forces would tie down British naval power and allow a smaller number of battleships to operate in the North Sea. This first draft was called Plan X; a pared-down revision was renamed Plan Y, and the final version presented to Hitler was Plan Z.&lt;ref name=S15&gt;Showell, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler rejected Raeder's proposed construction plan, which led to a more balanced fleet that incorporated the battleships Hitler sought and was accepted on 1 March 1939. Raeder planned to use the battleships and aircraft carriers in task forces to support the ''panzerschiffe'' and light cruisers attacking British merchant traffic.&lt;ref name=GC220/&gt;

==The plan==
[[File:Graf-Zeppelin-2.jpg|thumb|''Graf Zeppelin'' at her launching]]
The plan approved by Hitler called for a surface fleet composed of the following vessels, which included all new ships built in the 1920s and 30s:&lt;ref name=GC220/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Type
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Projected
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Completed
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Battleships
| 10
| 4
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Battlecruisers
| 3
| 0
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Aircraft carriers
| 4
| 0
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | ''Panzerschiffe''
| 15
| 3
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Heavy cruisers
| 5
| 3
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Light cruisers
| 13
| 6
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Scouts
| 22
| 0
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Destroyers
| 68
| 30
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Torpedo boats
| 90
| 36
|}

These figures included the four ''Scharnhorst''- and ''Bismarck''-class battleships already built or building, the three ''Deutschland''-class ''panzerschiffe'' and the six light cruisers already in service.&lt;ref name=GC220/&gt; To complete the core of the Plan Z fleet, six H-class battleships, three [[O-class battlecruiser]]s, twelve [[P-class cruiser|P-class ''panzerschiffe'']], and two {{sclass-|Graf Zeppelin|aircraft carrier|1}}s with two more of a new design, were to be built.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, pp. 224&amp;ndash;226&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=G64&gt;Gröner, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; The five ships of the {{sclass-|Admiral Hipper|cruiser|4}} fulfilled the mandate for heavy cruisers, while the [[M-class cruiser|M class]] of light cruisers would fulfill the requirement for light cruisers.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, pp. 228&amp;ndash;232&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Spähkreuzer 1938]] design would form the basis for the fleet scouts ordered in the program.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 235&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 July 1939, Raeder revised the plan to cancel all twelve of the P-class ''panzerschiffe''.&lt;ref name=G64/&gt;

In the short time from the introduction of Plan Z to the beginning of war with the United Kingdom on 3 September only two of the plan's large ships, a pair of H class battleships, were [[laid down]]; material for the other four ships had started to be assembled in preparation to begin construction but no work had been done.&lt;ref&gt;Gröner, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt; At the time components of the three battlecruisers were in production, but their keels had not yet been laid down.&lt;ref&gt;Garzke &amp; Dulin, p. 354&lt;/ref&gt; Two of the M-class cruisers had been laid down, but they were also cancelled in late September.&lt;ref&gt;Gröner, p. 125&lt;/ref&gt; Work on {{ship|German aircraft carrier|Graf Zeppelin||2}} was cancelled definitively in 1943 when Hitler finally abandoned the surface fleet after the [[Battle of the Barents Sea]] debacle.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact on World War II==
[[File:Bundesarchiv DVM 10 Bild-23-63-65, U-Boot U 36.jpg|thumb|left|[[German submarine U-36 (1936)|''U-36'']], a [[Type VII]] U-boat]]
Since the plan was cancelled less than a year after it was approved, the positive effects on German naval construction were minimal. All of the ships authorized by the plan were cancelled after the outbreak of war, with only a few major surface vessels that predated the plan were completed during the conflict. These included ''Bismarck'' and ''Tirpitz'', along with the heavy cruisers [[German cruiser Blücher|''Blücher'']] and [[German cruiser Prinz Eugen|''Prinz Eugen'']]. Without the six H-class battleships or the four aircraft carriers, the Kriegsmarine was once again unable to meet the Royal Navy on equal terms.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, pp. 224&amp;ndash;232&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the heavy ships of the ''Kriegsmarine'' were used as commerce raiders in the early years of the war. Two of the ''panzerschiffe'', [[German cruiser Deutschland|''Deutschland'']] and [[German cruiser Admiral Graf Spee|''Graf Spee'']], were already at sea at the outbreak of war; the former found little success and the latter was ultimately trapped and forced to scuttle after the [[Battle of the River Plate]] in December 1939.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Biglingmaier, pp. 91&amp;ndash;93&lt;/ref&gt; From October 1940 to March 1941, [[German cruiser Admiral Scheer|''Admiral Scheer'']] went on her own raiding operation and captured or sank seventeen ships, which made her the most successful of the German [[capital ship]] surface raiders in the entire war.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rohwer, p. 65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hümmelchen, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; ''Scharnhorst'' and ''Gneisenau'' conducted [[Operation Berlin (Atlantic)|Operation Berlin]], a major sortie into the Atlantic in early 1941.&lt;ref&gt;Garzke &amp; Dulin, p. 140&lt;/ref&gt; ''Bismarck'' and ''Prinz Eugen'' went on the last Atlantic raiding mission, [[Operation Rheinübung|Operation ''Rheinübung'']], in May 1941. ''Bismarck'' sank the British battlecruiser {{HMS|Hood}} but was [[Last battle of the battleship Bismarck|herself sunk three days later]].&lt;ref&gt;Bercuson &amp; Herwig, pp. 155&amp;ndash;156&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Garzke &amp; Dulin, p. 256&lt;/ref&gt; The loss of ''Bismarck'' led Hitler to prohibit further sorties into the Atlantic; the remaining capital ships were concentrated in Norway for use as a [[fleet in being]] and to threaten convoys to the [[Soviet Union]] on the [[Arctic convoys of World War II|Murmansk Run]].&lt;ref name=GC220/&gt;

Despite the fact that Plan Z produced no new warships in time for World War II, the plan represented the strategic thinking of the ''[[Oberkommando der Marine]]'' (OKM&amp;mdash;&quot;Naval High Command&quot;) at the time. Most significantly, the OKM favored surface combatants over the U-boats Dönitz needed for his [[Battle of the Atlantic|submarine campaign in the North Atlantic]], which left him with only a handful of submarines at the start of war.&lt;ref name=S15/&gt; The two ''Scharnhorst''-class battleships cost close to 150&amp;nbsp;million ''[[Reichsmark]]s'' apiece, and the two ''Bismarck''-class ships cost nearly 250&amp;nbsp;million ''Reichsmarks'' each&lt;ref&gt;Gröner Vol 1., pp. 31&amp;ndash;35&lt;/ref&gt; for this amount of money, the Germans could have built more than a hundred additional [[Type VII]] U-boats.&lt;ref&gt;Gröner Vol 2., p. 44&lt;/ref&gt; The shift to the submarine war was not definitively made until 1943, by which time the campaign had already been lost.&lt;ref&gt;Showell, pp. 15&amp;ndash;16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Syrett, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
* {{cite book | last = Bidlingmaier | first = Gerhard | title = Warship Profile 4 | year = 1971 | location = Windsor, UK| publisher = Profile Publications | oclc = 20229321 | chapter = KM Admiral Graf Spee | pages = 73–96 }}
*{{cite book|last=Blair |first=Clay, Jr. |title=Hitler's U-Boat War: The Hunters 1939–1942 |publisher=Cassell &amp; Co.|location=London, UK|year=1996 |isbn=0304352608}}
*{{cite book|author1=Gardiner, Robert |author2=Chesneau, Roger | title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1922–1946 |publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=1980|isbn=0870219138|location=Annapolis, MD}}
*{{Cite book |last1=Garzke|first1=William H.|last2=Dulin|first2=Robert O.|title=Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II|year=1985|location=Annapolis, MD|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=9780870211010|oclc=}}
*{{cite book |last=Gröner|first=Erich|title=German Warships: 1815&amp;ndash;1945|year=1990|location=Annapolis, MD|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0870217909}}
* {{cite book|last = Hümmelchen|first = Gerhard|year = 1976|language = German|title = Die Deutschen Seeflieger 1935–1945|publisher = Lehmann|location = Munich|isbn = 978-3-469-00306-5}}
* {{cite book|last1=Overy|first1=Richard|authorlink=Richard Overy|last2=Wheatcroft|first2=Andrew|title=The Road To War|publisher=Macmillan Press|location=London, UK|year=1989|isbn=}}
* {{cite book|last=Rössler|first=Eberhard|title=The U-boat: The Evolution and Technical History of German Submarines|others=Translated by Harold Erenberg|location=Annapolis, MD|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=1981|isbn=0304361208}}
* {{cite book|last=Showell|first= Jak P Mallmann|title=German Navy Handbook, 1939&amp;ndash;1945|location=Gloucestershire, UK|publisher= Thrupp, Stroud|year=1999|isbn=0750915560}}
* {{cite book|last=Syrett|first=David|title=The Defeat of the German U-Boats: The Battle of the Atlantic|location=Columbia, SC|publisher=University of South Carolina Press|year=1994|isbn=0585336296}}
* {{cite book | last = Williamson | first = Gordon | title = German Pocket Battleships 1939–1945 | year = 2003 | publisher = Osprey Publishing | isbn = 1841765015 | location = Oxford, UK}}
*{{cite book | last =Woodward | first = David | title = The Tirpitz | year = 1953 | publisher = Vail-Ballou Press | location = United States of America}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last=Breyer|first=Siegfried|title=Der Z-Plan|publisher=Podzun Pallas Verlag|location=Wölfersheim-Berstadt, DE|year=1996|ISBN= 3-7909-0535-6}}
* {{cite journal|last=Hillgruber|first=Andreas|authorlink=Andreas Hillgruber|title=England's Place In Hitler's Plans for World Dominion|pages=5–22|journal=Journal of Contemporary History|volume=9|year=1974|doi=10.1177/002200947400900101}}
* {{cite book|last=Nolte|first=Maik|title=&quot;... mit Anstand zu sterben verstehen.&quot;: Flottenrüstung zwischen Tirpitzscher Tradition, strategischer Notwendigkeit und ideologischem Kalkül 1933 - 1943''|publisher=Der Andere Verlag|location=Tönning, DE|year=2005|isbn=}}

[[Category:Plan Z]]
[[Category:Kriegsmarine]]
[[Category:Naval history of Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>d7fjx3a80wzhuiy8jpx8jzcl1g0qktq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
