<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Polar Line</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10446360</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738467153</id>
      <parentid>648734117</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-09T03:41:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Doremo</username>
        <id>9337959</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>pipe</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20348">{{For|the polar line of a point|Pole and polar}}
{{Infobox rail line
|name        = Polar Line
|image       = Polarbanen ved Elvkroken.jpg
|caption     =
|type        = [[Railway]]
|system      = [[Rail transport in Norway]]
|status      = Never completed
|start       = [[Fauske]]
|end         = [[Drag, Norway|Drag]]
|stations    =
|open        =
|close       =
|owner       =
|operator    =
|character   =
|stock       =
|linelength  =
|tracklength =
|notrack     = [[Single track (rail)|Single]]
|gauge       = {{RailGauge|sg|allk=on}}
|el          = No
|speed       =
|elevation   =
}}

The '''Polar Line''' ({{lang-no|Polarbanen}}, {{lang-de|Polarbahn}}) is an incomplete and abandoned [[railway]] line which had run northwards from [[Fauske]], [[Norway]], to [[Narvik]] and, if finished, ultimately would have run {{convert|1215|km|sp=us}} to [[Kirkenes]]. The railway was constructed by the ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' in [[occupation of Norway by Nazi Germany|occupied Norway]] during the [[Second World War]] as part of ''[[Festung Norwegen]]''. At Fauske, the line would connect with the [[Nordland Line]], with construction stretching as far north as [[Drag, Norway|Drag]], [[Tysfjord]]. After the war, the plans were abandoned by Norwegian authorities, although they were from the 1970s revitalized as part of the proposed [[Northern Norway Line]]. Some tunnels and bridges remain, and part of the route has been used to build [[European route E06|European Road E6]].

==Route==
[[File:Polar Line in Salten and Ofoten map.svg|thumb|left|The section of the Polar Line that was under construction in addition to NSB's three 1923 proposals.]]
Organizationally, the construction of the Polar Line started at [[Finneid]]. It ran through the Bratthaugen Tunnel before reaching [[Fauske (village)|Fauske]], where [[Fauske Station]] was planned. At the time of [[End of World War II in Europe|German capitulation]] on 8 May 1945, most of the right-of-way through Fauske was completed. The line continued northwards, crossed [[Svartosen]] on a bridge and continued to the lake of [[Vallvatnet]], where a [[passing loop]] station was planned.&lt;ref name=e54&gt;Ellingsve: 54&lt;/ref&gt; The line continued to [[Straumen, Nordland|Straumen]], where a station was planned {{convert|1|km|sp=us|1}} north of the village. A power station was built at [[Røyrvatnet]]. The line continued past the lake of [[Hellandsjøen]]. On the {{convert|4.9|km||sp=us|adj=mid|-long}} section from Hellandsjøen to Buvik, five tunnels were planned and a station was planned at [[Hellbukta]].&lt;ref name=e56&gt;Ellingsve: 56&lt;/ref&gt;

At [[Megården]], {{convert|24|km|sp=us}} from Fauske, {{convert|554|m|sp=us}} of Megården Tunnel were built.&lt;ref name=e56 /&gt; A [[Trengsel]], {{convert|27|km|sp=us}} from Fauske, the [[Trengsel Bridge]] was planned.&lt;ref name=e57&gt;Ellingsve: 57&lt;/ref&gt; After passing [[Torkildseng]], {{convert|28|km|sp=us}} from Fauske, the line was to run through two short tunnels. Stations were planned [[Løktehaugen]] and [[Kvarv]], {{convert|31|and|39|km|sp=us}} from Fauske, respectively. Between the two stations there was planned 18 tunnels. A power station was built at Kvarv. The line was planned to run through the {{convert|2710|m||sp=us|adj=mid|-long}} Espenes Tunnel before reaching the next station at [[Kalvik]], {{convert|47|km|sp=us}} from Fauske.&lt;ref name=e59&gt;Ellingsve: 59&lt;/ref&gt;

The next station was planned at [[Sommerset]], {{convert|52|km|sp=us}} from Fauske, followed by a station at [[Lappstorvik]] and then reached Sørfjord.&lt;ref name=e60&gt;Ellingsve: 60&lt;/ref&gt; The next two stations were planned at [[Kobbvatnet]] and [[Gjerdalen]], after which the line would have run through the Basis Tunnel and the Sildhopfjell Tunnel, the latter {{convert|77|km|sp=us}} from Fauske. It then would have continued through the {{convert|5070|m||sp=us|adj=mid|-long}} Tennvatn Tunnel,&lt;ref name=e62&gt;Ellingsve: 62&lt;/ref&gt; the {{convert|2720|m||sp=us|adj=mid|-long}} Tennvatn Tunnel and the Falkelva Tunnel. Stations would have been built at [[Kråkmo]] and Sandnes, {{convert|91|and|100|km|sp=us}} from Fauske, respectively. The line would then run through the {{convert|2000|m||sp=us|adj=mid|-long}} Hellarvik Tunnel just before reaching at station at Tømmernes, {{convert|110|km|sp=us}} from Fauske.&lt;ref name=e64&gt;Ellingsve: 64&lt;/ref&gt; At {{convert|123|km|sp=us}} from Fauske lay the Trollpollhaugen Tunnel after which the station reached Drag, {{convert|130|km|sp=us}} from Fauske.&lt;ref name=e68&gt;Ellingsve: 68&lt;/ref&gt;

From [[Bjørnfjell, Nordland|Bjørnfjell]], the line would have hug the [[Norway–Sweden border]] into the county of [[Troms]], before running down the valley of [[Salangsdalen]]. It would pass through the villages of [[Setermoen]] and [[Andselv]] before running west of the lake of [[Takvatnet]]. It would then have reached [[Balsfjorden]], which is would have hugged until reaching [[Nordkjosbotn]]. It would cross across [[Balsfjordeidet]] to [[Storfjorden (Troms)|Storfjorden]], which is would follow on the east shore of. There it would have passed through the village of [[Skibotn]] and run around the [[Kåfjorden (Troms)|Kåfjorden]] and through [[Kåfjordbotn]]. It would then have run along [[Rotsundet]] and reach [[Nordreisa]],&lt;ref name=e79&gt;Ellingsve: 79&lt;/ref&gt; which would have been located {{convert|335|km|sp=us}} form Bjørnfjell.&lt;ref name=e80&gt;Ellingsve: 80&lt;/ref&gt;

The line would have continued down the valley of [[Reisadalen]], following the river of [[Reisaelva]] for about {{convert|85|km|sp=us}}, at which it would make a large S-bend around the lake of [[Ráisjávri]]. It would then run to {{convert|140|km|sp=us}} from Nordreisa to [[Kautokeino]], from where it would run north-eastwards. It would then have crossed the plateau of [[Finnmarksvidda]] and reach [[Karasjok]], {{convert|280|km|sp=us}} from Nordreisa. The line would then have run northwards, running along the [[Finland–Norway border]] and the [[Tana River (Norway)|Tana River]] until reaching [[Skiippagurra]], {{convert|450|km|sp=us}} from Nordreisa. From there, it would have run along the south shore of [[Varangerfjorden]] and around [[Kjøfjorden]] until reaching Kirkenes.&lt;ref name=e81&gt;Ellingsve: 81&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Planning===
The Nordland Line, which was originally proposed to run from [[Trondheim]] to [[Helgeland]], was first launched by [[Ole Tobias Olsen]] in 1872.&lt;ref&gt;Hoås and Stene: 14&lt;/ref&gt; By 1892, surveying on parts of the route had been started. The first specific plans for a railway north of Fauske was presented by the [[Norwegian State Railways (1883–1996)|Norwegian State Railways]] (NSB) in 1901, which proposed the line be built to [[Røsvik]] with a branch to [[Bodø]].&lt;ref name=e50&gt;Ellingsve: 50&lt;/ref&gt; The first part of the Nordland Line, the [[Hell–Sunnan Line]], was completed in 1905.&lt;ref&gt;Hoås and Stene: 77&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Railway Plan of 1923]], a {{convert|306|km||sp=us|adj=mid|-long}} line between Fauske and Narvik was included and estimated to cost 160 million [[Norwegian krone]] (NOK). At the same time, the [[Standing Committee on Railways]] stated that the Nordland Line would not meet its function until it had crossed [[Finnmark]]. A report on the section from Narvik to [[Kvesmenes]] was published in March 1923, followed by the section from Kvesmenes to [[Alteidet]] in June 1926, Alteidet to [[Porsangerfjorden]] in December 1926, from Porsangerfjorden to [[Tana, Norway|Tana]] in June 1927, from Tana to Vadsø in January 1928 and from [[Nyborg, Finnmark|Nyborg]] to Kirkenes in April 1928. The distance from Fauske to Vadsø was {{convert|1144|km|sp=us}} and from Fauske to Kirkenes {{convert|1215|km|sp=us}}. Construction was estimated to NOK&amp;nbsp;375 million.&lt;ref name=e50 /&gt;

NSB completed the Nordland Line to [[Mosjøen]] in 1940. Following the German occupation of Norway, construction of the line was accelerated.&lt;ref name=svanberg&gt;Svanberg: 369&lt;/ref&gt; On 11 December 1940, the ''[[Reichskommissariat Norwegen]]'' requested that NSB submit their plans. The plans north to Narvik were sent 21 March 1941 and the plans to Kirkenes on 20 January 1942.&lt;ref name=e50 /&gt; NSB had three different proposals for the route between Fauske and Narvik. The first—the Ferry Line—was a railway from Fauske to [[Korsnes]] on Tysfjorden and onwards to Narvik by [[train ferry]]. It would also include a ferry terminal at [[Tjeldsundet]], where there would be a connection northwards towards Kirkenes. The second alternative—the Fjord Line—would run via [[Tømmerneset]], [[Innhavet]] and [[Musken]], around the southern end of Tysfjorden and then followed the shoreline to Ballangen to Narvik. The third—the Mountain Line—would follow an inland route from [[Kobbvatnet]] up [[Gerdalen]] and then through a long tunnel to Tysfjorden. The Fjord Line was {{convert|40|km|sp=us}} longer than the Mountain Line, but considerably cheaper to build. A fourth proposal, launched by the ''Wehrmacht'', was to build a ferry crossing of Tysfjorden, but otherwise build closely to that of the Fjord Line.&lt;ref name=e70&gt;Ellingsve: 70&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Polarbanen ved Hamarøy.jpg|thumb|Underpass of the Polar Line in [[Hamarøy]] in 1947]]
The alternatives were considered by [[Vienna]]-based [[Ladislaus von Rabcewicz]]. He considered the alternatives based on that the railway would be extended to Kirkenes, that the railway should be built as quickly as possible, and considering the line's strategic location. Of military-strategic concerns, he discarded the proposals which involved a ferry.&lt;ref name=e70 /&gt; The Fjord Line was considered advantageous gradients and close access to the fjords would allow for more work days per year. However, it had four tunnels longer than {{convert|5|km|sp=us}}, five tunnels between {{convert|4|and|5|km|sp=us}}, three tunnels between {{convert|3|and|4|km|sp=us}}, five tunnels between {{convert|2|and|3|km|sp=us}} and twelve tunnels shorter than {{convert|2|km|sp=us}}. Rabcewicz stated that it would be necessary with immediate start of construction for all tunnels longer than {{convert|2.8|km|sp=us}}, with the establishment of 24 breaking-in point.&lt;ref name=e72&gt;Ellingsve: 72&lt;/ref&gt;

Rabcewicz recommended a Mountain Line, but chose to build it to intersect with the [[Ofoten Line]] at [[Bjørnfjell Station|Bjørnfjell]], and use that line as a branch to reach Narvik, rather than build the line directly to the town.&lt;ref name=e70 /&gt; The Mountain Line could be built faster because of shorter tunnels, the longest being {{convert|5.5|km|sp=us}}, which with an estimated {{convert|4|m|sp=us}} per day would give a construction time of 33 months. The other main advantage of the line was that it lay so far inland that an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] attack would be improbable.&lt;ref name=e74&gt;Ellingsve: 74&lt;/ref&gt; However, Rabcewicz commented several disadvantages of the line, including steeper gradients, the lack of any fjords or residents between Kobbvatnet and Bjrnfjell and the increased amount of snow in the area. He estimated that the line could be completed by June 1945 given a work-force of 83,700 men.&lt;ref name=e76&gt;Ellingsve: 76&lt;/ref&gt;

Planning of the route from Narvik to Kirkenes was led by Professor Flörke in Narvik. The first report was published on 4 July 1942, regarding the route from Kvesmenes to [[Skibotn]]. The report considered three proposals, that of NSB from the 1920s, that of the ''Reichskommissariat's''s railway division and that of the Flörke's group. NSB had recommended a route which followed the coastline, but Flörke stated that of military-strategic reasons this route had to be discarded. He further wanted to avoid long tunnels to decrease construction time. He also remarked that NSB's maps did not match the terrain, forcing his office to take [[aerial photography]] of the route from [[Nordreisa]] to [[Skippagurra]] between May and August 1942, while Narvik to Nordreisa was aerial photographed from June to August. Plans, consisting of the section from [[Setermoen]] to Nordreisa, {{convert|325|km|sp=us}} from Bjørnfjell, were sent to ''Einsatzgruppe Wiking'' in Oslo on 8 July 1942. The plans from Bjørnfjell to Setermoen were sent 23 July.&lt;ref name=e78&gt;Ellingsve: 78&lt;/ref&gt;

===Construction===
[[File:Polarbanen ved Kobbelvvågen.jpg|thumb|Remains of the Polar Line at [[Kobbelvvågen]] in 1950]]
As part of [[Operation Barbarossa]]—the German invasion of the Soviet Union—plans were immediately dispatched to complete a railway to Kirkenes. The responsibility was given to ''[[Organisation Todt]]''. Immediate plans called for the Nordland Line to be completed to [[Rognan]] on 1 August 1943 and later that fall to Fauske.&lt;ref name=svanberg /&gt; Construction of the section north of Fauske was, unlike the section southwards, without any Norwegian participation, including that of NSB.&lt;ref name=e22&gt;Ellingsve: 22&lt;/ref&gt;

Construction was organized by ''Einsatzgruppe Wiking'', which was based in [[Mo i Rana]] and had clerks of works in Fauske and Tømmerneset. The work was performed through a number of German construction companies. Construction on the Polar Line started from January 1943. The first part of construction was for auxiliary facilities, such as barracks, quays and power supply. The workforce largely provided by Russian and Serbian [[prisoners of war]] (POW).&lt;ref name=e52&gt;Ellingsve: 52&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the enormous amount of labor-force, construction of the railway was notoriously inefficient and the part of the railway which were completed further south was of such bad quality that most of the permanent way had to be replaced.&lt;ref name=svanberg /&gt; North of Tysfjorden, the only work was a tote road between Narvik and Bjørnfjell.&lt;ref name=e78 /&gt;

The area the line was being built was without road connection, and the steep terrain made it difficult to place the railway elsewhere than close by the fjords. As this was also the place where people lived, it caused a conflict of interest. According to the peace-time [[compulsory purchase]] law, the state was forced to pay due compensation for any land they needed to build public infrastructure. However, the Germans showed no interest in following these laws, took what property they needed, often without even informing the locals. In [[Lappstorvika]], the road became so dilapidated that the locals chose to move away until after the war.&lt;ref name=e69&gt;Ellingsve: 69&lt;/ref&gt;

Thirty thousand POWs were brought to work on the railway through Norland. The treatment of the POWs varied depending on their nationality, their status in regard to the [[Geneva Convention]] and their alignment.&lt;ref name=e84&gt;Ellingsve: 84&lt;/ref&gt; Russians who converted to support [[Andrey Vlasov]] were treated better and often sent to own camps. Similarly, only two of over 1,000 Polish POWs in Nordland died, and were treated better because Polish people were generally regarded as pro-Axis.&lt;ref name=e88&gt;Ellingsve: 88&lt;/ref&gt; ''Wehrmacht'' invested the equivalent of NOK&amp;nbsp;15 million in labor and other costs in the line. At the time of the [[End of World War II in Europe|German capitulation]] on 8 May 1945, there were an estimated 8,300 POWs living in camps on the segment between Fauske and Drag.&lt;ref name=&quot;e52&quot;/&gt; About ten percent of those who had worked on the line had died.&lt;ref name=e22 /&gt;

On 4 December 1945, the [[Embassy of Russia in Oslo|Embassy of the Soviet Union in Oslo]] started a process with the [[Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] to establish a common Norwegian–Soviet commission which would investigate issues regarding Russian POWs in Norway. The commission was established with support from Norwegian authorities and established in March 1946.&lt;ref name=e90&gt;Ellingsve: 90&lt;/ref&gt; Both NSB and Norwegian authorities were concerned that the Soviet goal was to claim compensation for the effective work which the POWs had done in Norway.&lt;ref name=e91&gt;Ellingsve: 91&lt;/ref&gt; Although vague estimates of the number of [[man-hour]]s were performed, no monetary value was ever calculated and no claim was ever issued Norwegian authorities from the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=e92&gt;Ellingsve: 92&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Trengsel Bridge.jpg|thumb|[[Trengsel Bridge]] on [[European route E06|European Road E6]] was originally planned as part of the Polar Line and part of a tunnel is still visible from the road.]]

The Nordland Line was completed to Bodø in 1962.&lt;ref&gt;Svanberg: 373&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1960s, Parliament voted to pause any further plans to build a railway northwards for ten years. Instead, the road network was to be expanded. Starting in the 1970s, a series of [[regional airport]]s were built, largely undermining the need for the railway for passenger transport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stortinget.no/no/Saker-og-publikasjoner/Publikasjoner/Innstillinger/Stortinget/1993-1994/inns-199394-133/?lvl=0#a2 |title=Innstilling fra samferdselskomiteen om Nord-Norgebanen |date=10 May 1994 |publisher=[[Ministry of Transport and Communications (Norway)|Ministry of Transport and Communications]] |language=Norwegian |accessdate=23 February 2012 |archivedate=23 February 2012 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/65fVSYDqW |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1968, NSB again considered the [[Northern Norway Line]], a proposal to extend the Nordland Line from Fauske via Narvik to [[Harstad]] and [[Tromsø]]. The [[Ministry of Transport and Communications (Norway)|Ministry of Transport and Communications]] recommended that the line not be built. However, during the 1970s, income from petroleum production started a public debate as to whether the income should be used on domestic infrastructure investments.&lt;ref name=o8&gt;Overland: 8&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1977, the Ribu Commission was established to look into building a new railway north of Fauske. The commission made no clear recommendation as to whether the line should be built,&lt;ref name=o8 /&gt; but stated although it had a cost of NOK&amp;nbsp;4.4 billion and would need operating subsidies, it would provide a positive economic impact on the region, particularly if additional industrial and commercial investments were made along the route.&lt;ref name=o9&gt;Overland: 9&lt;/ref&gt; Parliament did not make a decision when it debated the commission's report in 1983. Instead, a new report was issued in 1992.&lt;ref name=o8 /&gt; This time it was planned as a [[high-speed rail]]way,&lt;ref name=o9 /&gt; but the in 1994, the project was rejected by Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Nei til bane fra Fauske til Narvik |work=[[Aftenposten]] |last=Nilsen |first=Ole Johan |date=27 May 1994 |page=2 |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt;

When the E6 highway was built northwards from Fauske during the 1960s, parts of the right-of-way built for the Polar Line was used for the road. Specifically, the highway follows the railway route from Fauske past Vallvatnet to a point beyond Straumen, in addition to a section of the right-of-way past Torkilseng. The road also used tunnels built at Asp, Eva, Espenes, Kobbvatnet and north of Tømmerneset.&lt;ref name=e54 /&gt;

==References==

;Bibliography
* {{cite book |last=Bjerke |first=Thor |title=Banedata '94 |year=1994 |publisher=Norsk Jernbaneklubb |location=Oslo |language=Norwegian |isbn=82-90286-15-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Ellingsve |first=Arvid |title=Nordlandsbanens krigshistorie |year=1995 |publisher=Norwegian State Railways |location=Oslo |language=Norwegian}}
* {{cite book |last=Hoås |first=Jan |last2=Stene |first2=Morten |year=2005 |title=Hell Sunnanbanen |publisher=Jubileumskomiteen |language=Norwegian}}
* {{cite book |last=Overland |first=Per |title=Med toget til 69°42: Nord-Norgebanen |publisher=Norwegian State Railways |location=Oslo |language=Norwegian |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2010052006062}}
* {{cite book |last=Svanberg |first=Erling |title=Langs vei og lei i Nordland: samferdsel i Nordland gjennom 3000 år |year=1990 |publisher=Nordland County Municipality |language=Norwegian |isbn=82-7416-021-5 |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2010110308003}}

;Notes
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Polarbanen|Polar Line}}
* [http://www.polarbanen.no Private site with many pictures] {{no icon}}

{{Norway during World War II}}
{{Railways in Norway}}

{{coord|67.4211|N|15.6664|E|source:wikidata|display=title}}

[[Category:Railway lines in Norway]]
[[Category:Norway in World War II]]
[[Category:Railway lines in Nordland]]</text>
      <sha1>hzcm51sxggje4p21tiwlelro63ak91m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
