<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2003129</id>
    <revision>
      <id>721753435</id>
      <parentid>705116973</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-23T21:25:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fayenatic london</username>
        <id>1639942</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:130 BC births]]; added [[Category:130s BC births]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16143">'''Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius''' (c. 130 BC &amp;ndash; 63 BC) was a pro-[[Lucius Cornelius Sulla|Sullan]] politician and general who was [[Roman consul]] in 80 BC. He was the principal Senatorial commander during the [[Sertorian War]], fighting alongside [[Pompey|Pompeius Magnus]]. He was given the [[agnomen]] (nickname) “Pius” because of his constant and unbending attempts to have his father officially recalled from exile.&lt;ref&gt;Cic. P. Red. 37; Ad Quir. 6; Arch. 6; Vell. II 15, 3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early career==
[[Image:Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius.jpg|thumb|250px|Coin of Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius]]
Metellus Pius, a member of the distinguished [[plebeian]] ''[[Caecilia (gens)|gens Caecilia]]'' was the son of [[Quintus Caecilius Metellus Numidicus]], who was consul in 109 BC. His career began in that same year, when he accompanied his father to [[Numidia]] as his ''contubernalis'' (cadet) during the [[Jugurthine War]], returning to Rome in 107 BC, when his father was forcibly recalled by the actions of [[Gaius Marius]].&lt;ref&gt;Sall. Iug. 64, 4; Plut. Mar. 8, 4&lt;/ref&gt; In 100 BC, after his father was banished as a result of the political manoeuvrings of Gaius Marius and [[Lucius Appuleius Saturninus]], Metellus Pius launched a campaign to have his father brought back from exile. He produced a petition in 99 BC to this effect, and his constant pleading on the subject resulted in Quintus Calidius, the [[Tribune|Plebeian Tribune]] of 98 BC passing a law which allowed his father to return.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 5&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of his fidelity, he was given the [[agnomen]] “Pius” for the constancy and inflexibility with which he fought for his father's political rehabilitation and return to [[Rome]].

Sometime during 90s BC, Metellus Pius was elected to the [[College of Pontiffs]] as a result of his family's eminence and influence.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 37&lt;/ref&gt; The outbreak of the [[Social War (91–88 BC)|Social War]] saw him employed as a [[Legatus|legate]] in late 89 BC, probably of the [[Roman consul|consul]] [[Pompeius Strabo]], where he won some battles against the [[Marsi]].&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pg. 377&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of these victories, he was elected [[Praetor]] in the following year (88 BC).&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pg. 378; Broughton III, pg. 41&lt;/ref&gt; During his praetorship, he was tasked with enrolling the Italian allies as new Roman citizens within sixty days, in accordance with the ''[[Lex Plautia Papiria]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pgs. 377-378&lt;/ref&gt; Once this was completed, Metellus Pius was again posted to the Social War, replacing Gaius Cosconius on the southern front. He harassed the territory around [[Apulia]], captured the town of [[Venosa|Venusia]], and defeated the leading Italian leader, [[Quintus Poppaedius Silo]], who died in the storming of Venusia.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 42; Brennan, pg. 378&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diod. XXXVII 2, 9—11; App. BC I 53; Auc. Vir. Ill. 63, 1&lt;/ref&gt;

In 87 BC, Metellus Pius’ command was extended, with his appointment as [[Propraetor]], responsible for continuing the war against [[Samnium]]. Later that year, however, saw a dispute between the two consuls [[Lucius Cornelius Cinna]] and [[Gnaeus Octavius]] flare up into war. Cinna, expelled from Rome, met up with the exiled [[Gaius Marius]], and both laid siege to Rome. During the early phase of this conflict, the [[Roman Senate|Senate]], fearing that they may need additional troops and commanders, ordered Metellus Pius to negotiate a peace with the [[Samnites]].&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

Marching to Rome, he made camp at the [[Alban Hills]], accompanied by [[Publius Licinius Crassus Dives (consul 97 BC)| Publius Licinius Crassus]]. Here he met up with Gnaeus Octavius, who had abandoned Rome, but both men soon fell out with each other, over Metellus Pius’ troops demanding that their commander take over overall command from Gnaeus Octavius. The Senate then asked him to negotiate with Cinna on their behalf, during which time he recognized Cinna as the legitimate consul.&lt;ref&gt;Lovano, pg. 44; Broughton II, pg. 47&lt;/ref&gt; However, with Cinna’s occupation of Rome and the executions initiated by Gaius Marius, Metellus Pius decided to abandon Rome and head to [[Africa (Roman province)|North Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pg. 379; Broughton II, pg. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

==Supporter of Sulla==
Arriving in Africa by early 86 BC, Metellus Pius started raising an army from his private clients, with the intent of joining [[Lucius Cornelius Sulla]], who had been the principal opponent of Cinna and Marius.&lt;ref&gt;Lovano, pg. 71&lt;/ref&gt; He was joined by [[Marcus Licinius Crassus]], but both men fell out, and Crassus was forced to leave and eventually join up with Sulla in Greece.&lt;ref&gt;Lovano, pg. 115; Brennan, pg. 543&lt;/ref&gt; He acted as [[proconsul]]ar governor of the province, but this was unrecognized by Cinna and his regime at Rome.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 55&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, it wasn’t until 84 BC that the Marians at Rome were able to send out their own governor, [[Gaius Fabius Hadrianus]].&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 60&lt;/ref&gt; Upon his arrival, he drove out Metellus Pius who fled to [[Numidia]]; pursued here, he and the Numidian king [[Hiempsal II]] were forced to flee onwards to [[Mauretania]].&lt;ref&gt;Lovano, pg. 95&lt;/ref&gt; From here, Metellus Pius made his way to [[Liguria]] by late 84 BC or early 83 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 61&lt;/ref&gt;

By 83 BC, Sulla had returned from the east and was marching slowly to Rome for his confrontation with the Marian regime. Moving quickly, Metellus Pius was the first to meet him along the [[Via Appia]], bringing new troops with him. He, like many of the aristocracy, only joined Sulla when it was prudent to do so, and not because they approved of his measures, such as his first march on Rome.&lt;ref&gt;Gruen, pgs. 7 &amp; 18&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless, recognizing Metellus as possessing proconsular imperium, Sulla made him his principal subordinate.&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pg. 381; Lovano, pg. 115&lt;/ref&gt; By July 83 BC, the Senate, under the direction of the consul [[Gnaeus Papirius Carbo]], declared Metellus Pius a public enemy.&lt;ref&gt;Lovano, pg. 120&lt;/ref&gt;

In 82 BC, he was sent by Sulla to secure the northern parts of Italy, and accompanied by the young [[Pompey|Gnaeus Pompeius]], Metellus Pius attacked and defeated [[Gaius Carrinas (general)|Gaius Carrinas]] at [[Picenum]]. He then achieved a victory over Papirius Carbo and [[Gaius Norbanus]] at [[Faventia]], pacifying [[Cisalpine Gaul]] for Sulla.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 68&lt;/ref&gt; With Sulla’s victory in 82 BC, he began rewarding his supporters, and made Metellus Pius the [[Pontifex Maximus]] in 81 BC, following the murder of [[Quintus Mucius Scaevola Pontifex]].&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 78&lt;/ref&gt; He was also a [[Monetalis]] from 82 BC to 80 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton III, pgs. 40-41&lt;/ref&gt;

During this entire period, he was shown to be one of Sulla’s best subordinates. A [[Optimates|traditionalist]] supporter of the Senate’s prerogatives, he had no other objective apart from fighting the [[Populares|populism]] of Marius and Cinna, and did not participate in the atrocious violence that marked the arrival of the [[Roman dictator|dictatorship]] of Sulla. Finally in 80 BC, he was appointed [[Roman consul|consul]] alongside Sulla,&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 79&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cic. Arch. 6—7, 9, 31&lt;/ref&gt; Metellus Pius used his position to reward Quintus Calidius, who had helped bring his father back, by supporting his bid for the [[praetor|praetorship]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, pg. 1060&lt;/ref&gt;

==[[Sertorian War]]==
[[File:Quintus Metellus Pius.jpg|thumb|200px|Quintus Metellus from [[Guillaume Rouillé]]'s ''Promptuarii Iconum Insigniorum'']]
Sometime during his consulship, [[Quintus Sertorius]], an opponent of Sulla, established himself in Spain and began a rebellion against the Senate. After defeating the governor of [[Hispania Ulterior]], the Senate decided to send Metellus Pius once his term as consul had ended. Upgrading Hispania Ulterior to a consular [[Roman province|province]], they dispatched Metellus Pius to take charge of the war against Sertorius.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 84; Brennan, pg. 506&lt;/ref&gt; Facing Sertorius and [[Marcus Perpenna Vento]], Metellus Pius established his bases at ''Metellinum'' (today [[Medellín (Spain)|Medellín]]) ''Castra Caecilia'' (today [[Cáceres, Spain|Cáceres]]), ''Viccus Caecilius'', at the [[Sierra de Gredos]], and at ''Caeciliana'', near [[Setúbal]].&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 82&lt;/ref&gt;

From the start, it was clear that Metellus Pius was no match for Sertorius,&lt;ref&gt;Gruen, pg. 18&lt;/ref&gt; suffering repeated defeats through Sertorius’ use of guerrilla tactics. His [[Legatus|legate]] Thorius, dispatched to come to the assistance of the governor of [[Hispania Citerior]], [[Marcus Domitius Calvinus (praetor 80 BC)|Marcus Domitus Calvinus]], was defeated by Sertorius (79 BC).&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pg. 506; Broughton II, pg. 84&lt;/ref&gt; After his unsuccessful push towards the [[Tagus]] in 79 BC, and suffering a defeat by Sertorius at [[Lacobriga]] in 78 BC, Pius was forced to ask for help from the governor of [[Gallia Transalpina]], but he was defeated by Sertorius’ legate and unable to help.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pgs. 82 &amp; 86; Brennan, pg. 506&lt;/ref&gt; The end result was that an exhausted Pius was pushed out of his province of Hispania Ulterior.&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pg. 512&lt;/ref&gt;

When the consuls of 78 BC declined the opportunity to join Metellus Pius as proconsuls in Spain once their terms ended, the Senate in late 77 BC, hearing of Pius’ ongoing reverses at the hands of Sertorius, decided to send [[Pompey|Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus]] together with another army to give Pius what assistance he could, while Pius’ governorship was prorogued.&lt;ref&gt;Gruen, pgs. 18-19&lt;/ref&gt; Both men worked well together, but were hard pressed to win any encounter with Sertorius.&lt;ref&gt;Gruen, pg. 19&lt;/ref&gt; With Pompey’s arrival in 76 BC, Sertorius turned his attention to him, freeing Metellus Pius to campaign against Sertorius’ subordinates.

Almost immediately this paid dividends; in 76 BC he defeated [[L. Hirtuleius|Hirtuleius]], Sertorius’ [[quaestor]], at [[Italica]].&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 93&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by another victory over Hirtuleius at [[Segovia (Baetica)|Segovia]] in 75 BC, where Hirtuleius died.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 98&lt;/ref&gt; Metellius Pius then came to the aid of Pompey after his defeat at Sucro (he had refused to wait for Pius before engaging Sertorius in battle), before both men finally won a battle against Sertorius at [[Saguntum]]. Pius was acclaimed ''[[imperator]]'' by his men.&lt;ref&gt;Brennan, pg. 508; Broughton II, pg. 98&lt;/ref&gt;

Spending the winter in Gaul, Metellus Pius returned to Spain in 74 BC. He captured the towns of [[Augusta Bilbilis|Bilbilis]] and [[Segorbe|Segobriga]], before joining Pompey at the siege of [[Calahorra|Calagurris]]. They were forced to raise the siege when Sertorius approached, after which Pius returned to Gaul.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 104; Brennan, pg. 508&lt;/ref&gt; Continued successes during 73 BC saw him ease up and allow Pompey to take the burden of the final phases of the war, with Sertorius’ murder in 72 BC. He imposed new taxes in Hispania Ulterior after the end of Sertorius’ rebellion.&lt;ref&gt; Matthew Dillon, Lynda Garland, ''Ancient Rome: From the Early Republic to the Assassination of Julius Caesar'' (2005), pg. 92&lt;/ref&gt; Pius’ governorship ended in 71 BC with the end of the war. He disbanded his army after crossing the [[Alps]], and celebrated a [[Roman triumph|triumph]] together with Pompey on December 30, 71 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Broughton II, pg. 122; Smith, pg. 1060&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless of the triumph, during those eight years of resistance he was unable to conclusively defeat Sertorius, and it was only after Sertorius' assassination by his own men that the rebels were forced to cede to the military ability of Metellus Pius.&lt;ref&gt;Sallust Hist. I 110—121; II 28, 59, 68—70; III 45 M; IV 49 M; Liv. Per. 91—93; Strabo III 4, 13; [[Valerius Maximus]] VIII 15, 8; IX 1, 5; Vell. II 30, 2; Plut. Sert. 12—13; 19—22; 27; Pomp. 18—19; App. BC I 108—112, 115, 121; Ib. 101; Auc. Vir. Ill. 63, 2; [[Florus]] II 10; Eutrop. VI 1, 3; 5, 2; Oros. V 23; [[Frontinus]] ''Stratagemata'' I 1, 12; II 1, 2—34 3, 5; 7, 5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later career==
Regardless of his working relationship with Pompey in Spain, Metellus Pius’ politics meant that he was opposed to Pompey’s continued irregular extra-magisterial career throughout the 60s BC. Though Pompey was largely untouchable, senatorial resentment could be visited upon his clients and former subordinates. When the former [[Tribune|Plebeian tribune]] and associate of Pompey, Gaius Cornelius, was accused of ''[[Law of majestas|maiestas]]'', the prosecution called on as witnesses a number of key anti-Pompeian former consuls, including Metellus Pius.&lt;ref&gt;Gruen, pgs. 262-265&lt;/ref&gt;

Metellus Pius was a friend and patron of the noted poet [[Aulus Licinius Archias]].&lt;ref&gt;Gruen, pg. 267&lt;/ref&gt; Pius died around 63 BC, the year that [[Julius Caesar]] replaced him as [[Pontifex Maximus]].

==Family relations==
He married Licinia Crassa Secunda or Minor, daughter of [[Lucius Licinius Crassus|Lucius Licinius Crassus Orator]], and wife [[Lucius Licinius Crassus|Mucia Secunda]], from whom he had no children. For this reason he [[Adoption in ancient Rome|adopted]] his nephew by marriage and son of his second cousin Publius Cornelius Scipio, renamed [[Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius Scipio Nasica]]. He was the son of Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius's wife's sister Licinia Crassa Prima or Major and [[Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica Serapio (consul 111 BC)|Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica Serapio]], who was in turn the son of [[Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica Serapio]] and Caecilia Metella, daughter of [[Quintus Caecilius Metellus Macedonicus]].

==In fiction==
Metellus Pius is a prominent character in the novels [[Masters of Rome|''The First Man in Rome'']], [[Masters of Rome|''The Grass Crown'']] and [[Masters of Rome|''Fortune's Favorites'']] by [[Colleen McCullough]]. In the novels he is characterised as having a stutter, and is referred to by contemporaries, including Sulla, as “the Piglet”.

He is also mentioned in [[John Maddox Roberts]]' [[SPQR series]] as the fictional main character [[Decius Metellus|Decius Caecilius Metellus]]' uncle.

==See also==
* [[Caecilia (gens)]]
* [[Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius Scipio]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Brennan, T. Corey, ''The Praetorship in the Roman Republic'', Vol. 2 (2000)
* [[Thomas Robert Shannon Broughton|Broughton, T. Robert S.]], ''The Magistrates of the Roman Republic, Vol II'' (1952)
* Broughton, T. Robert S., ''The Magistrates of the Roman Republic, Vol III'' (1986)
* Gruen, Erich S., ''The Last Generation of the Roman Republic'' (1995)
* Lovano, Michael, ''The Age of Cinna: Crucible of Late Republican Rome'' (2002)
* Smith, William, ''Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology'', Vol II (1867)

== Further reading ==
* Manuel Dejante Pinto de Magalhães Arnao Metello and João Carlos Metello de Nápoles, &quot;Metellos de Portugal, Brasil e Roma&quot;, Torres Novas, 1998

{{start box}}
{{s-rel}}
{{succession box|
 title=[[Pontifex Maximus]] of [[Roman polytheism]]|
 before=[[Quintus Mucius Scaevola Pontifex|Quintus Mucius Scaevola]]|
 years=81 BC – 63 BC |
 after=Gaius [[Julius Caesar]]
}}
{{s-off}}
{{succession box|
 title=Consul|
 before=[[Marcus Tullius Decula]], [[Gnaeus Cornelius Dolabella]]|
 years=80 BC&lt;br&gt; ''with [[Lucius Cornelius Sulla]]'' |
 after=[[Publius Servilius Vatia Isauricus (consul 79 BC)|Publius Servilius Vatia Isauricus]], [[Appius Claudius Pulcher (praetor 88 BC)|Appius Claudius Pulcher]]
}}
{{end box}}
{{Pontifices Maximi}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Caecilius Metellus Pius, Quintus}}
[[Category:130s BC births]]
[[Category:63 BC deaths]]
[[Category:Roman Republican consuls]]
[[Category:Roman Republican praetors]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman generals]]
[[Category:2nd-century BC Romans]]
[[Category:1st-century BC Romans]]
[[Category:1st-century BC clergy]]
[[Category:Pontifices Maximi of the Roman Republic]]
[[Category:Caecilii]]</text>
      <sha1>9ua9dd4n3jqy6wxguc205znie7fh1q6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
