<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Raid on Godfrey Ranch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>48680838</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745753870</id>
      <parentid>745753743</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-23T03:06:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>112.198.64.34</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6647">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Raid on Godfrey Ranch
|partof=the [[Colorado War]]
|image=
|caption=
|date=January 15, 1865
|place=[[Colorado Territory]]
|coordinates=
|result=American victory&lt;br&gt;Indians retreat
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1861}}
|combatant2=[[Lakota people|Lakota]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cheyenne]]
|commander1=Holon Godfrey
|commander2=Unknown
|strength1= 3 men consisting of Godfrey and his [[Cowboy|ranch hands]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.weldcounty150.org/AgricultureinWeldCounty/HolonGodfreyWasRuggedPioneer.html|title=Holon Godfrey Was A Rugged Pioneer|last=Johnson|first=azel E. |publisher=''The Greeley Journal'' |date=July 5, 1959 |accessdate=November 29, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2=130 [[warrior]]s
|casualties1=None
|casualties2=17 killed
|notes=
}}
{{Colorado War}}

The '''Raid on Godfrey Ranch''' occurred from January 15–16, 1865 in which a large band of Lakota and Cheyenne warriors attacked an isolated ranch in Colorado owned by Holon Godfrey.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michno&quot;&gt;Michno, Gregory. ''Encyclopedia of Indian Wars: Western Battles and Skirmishes, 1850-1890''. Mountain Press Publishing Company (August 10, 2003). pp. 163-164. ISBN 978-0878424689&lt;/ref&gt; The raid was one of the numerous January raids by the Cheyennes and its Indian allies during the [[Colorado War]], and a retaliation for the [[Sand Creek massacre]] that happened on November 29, 1864. The Indians first attacked the neighboring [[American Ranch massacre|American Ranch]] in which a white family and some of their workers perished before setting their sights on Godfrey's ranch nearby. Godfrey learned of the Indian's upcoming attack and so he fortified his ranch together with his family and employees. At night, the Indians which consisted of over 130 warriors, surrounded and attacked Godfrey's ranch. The ranchers inside managed to hold off the Indian attack the whole night. By morning, one of Godfrey's ranch hands managed to sneak out of the siege and call for help from the U.S. cavalry which forced the Indians to finally retreat. The ranch, though burned and having lost some of its horses, was still standing and Godfrey's [[last stand]] was successful.

==Background==
The attack was part of a larger conflict in Colorado between white settlers and its native Indians tribes. Tension arose when both parties started arming themselves because of their distrust to one another. The Indians who sided with the [[Dog Soldiers]] society, started raiding military outposts and settlements throughout the territory.&lt;ref&gt;Hyde, George E. (1968). Life of George Bent Written from His Letters. Ed. by Savoie Lottinville. Norman, OK: University of Oklahoma Press.  pp. 168–195 ISBN 978-0-8061-1577-1.&lt;/ref&gt; In retaliation, a Colorado militia consisting of white volunteers, attacked a Cheyenne village that killed over 200 Indians, including women and children setting up much of the duration of the war. The Indians further increased their raids, not just attacking military outposts but also civilian settlements, focusing much of it on the Colorado ranching business. Ranches, farms and cattle drives were soon raided upon in just a span of a month. The raids weren't just a retaliation in the Indian's part, they were also important for them to gather resources such as horses to supply their cause.

Holon Godfrey heard of the Indian's warpath coming near them, after a [[American Ranch massacre|raid in American Ranch]] occurred a night before that killed almost an entire family of white settlers. Godfrey quickly took action to fortify his ranch so as to not suffer the same fate. He surrounded the place with 6-foot tall adobe walls and fireports, as well as well-placed shooting nests and bucket brigades in case of fire. Together with his wife, [[cowboy]]s and others who sought refuge, they prepared themselves to stand their ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michno&quot;/&gt;

==Battle==
In the night of January 15, a band of 130 Lakota and Cheyenne warriors besieged the Godfrey Ranch. Riding on horseback and encircling the ranch, the Indians tried to punch their way through the well-fortified position. Godfrey's fort on the other hand, repulsed the numerous attempts the Indians made. The women inside loaded the guns, even melting lead bars to make bullets out of, and the men fired from well-stationed gun ports.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ded&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reporterherald.com/columnists/colorado-history/ci_26575054/fort-wicked-outlasted-an-indian-attack|title=Fort Wicked outlasted an Indian attack|last=Jessen |first=Kenneth |publisher=''Reporter Herald'' |date=September 21, 2014 |accessdate=}} November 29, 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

The Indians managed to make a breakthrough into the corral and stole the horses inside. But Godfrey insisted his men to leave it be as their main priority was to defend those inside. Having their attacks repulsed, the Indians tried setting fire to the dry grass surrounding the ranch to burn the building down. Fortunately the men managed to quickly put the fire out with buckets of water that were already prepared. As Godfrey and his men tried to put out a fire, a warrior suddenly ambushed the rancher by the front. Godfrey managed to quickly shoot and kill the Indian with his rifle before continuing their defense. When the initial attacks failed, the Indians started shooting flaming arrows to the ranch's roof, but these were also extinguished quickly by the ranchers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michno&quot;/&gt;

One of the ranch hands, a man named Perkins, volunteered to get help from the outside. He was able to sneak out during the night and sent a telegraph message to Denver asking for help.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ded&quot;/&gt; He managed to contact the military, though only four soldiers accompanied him to the ranch. By morning, the Indians finally gave up and retreated back before Perkins' reinforcements arrived.

==Aftermath==
Godfrey's last stand was a success, and over 17 Indians were killed during their defense. The Indians nicknamed him &quot;Old Wicked&quot; and Godfrey himself christened his ranch as Fort Wicked.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michno&quot;/&gt; His story was published in the ''[[New York Tribune]]'' and today a historical marker stands near [[Merino, Colorado|Merino]] to commemorate the event.&lt;ref&gt;Patten, Jennifer. ''In View of the Mountains: A History of Fort Morgan, Colorado'' Aged Page (June 8, 2011). Chapter: Communication West. ISBN 978-0615497037&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{coord missing|Colorado}}

[[Category:History of Colorado]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Cheyenne]]
[[Category:Massacres by Native Americans]]
[[Category:19th-century military history of the United States]]
[[Category:Military raids]]
[[Category:Last stand battles]]</text>
      <sha1>i4hc7fsg039xzer1dkqsmxdwb30k41y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
