<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Reggiane Re.2000</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6583132</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743318780</id>
      <parentid>743317328</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-09T02:59:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>146.88.41.163</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Hungary */ A little bit of grammar and syntax correction.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28631">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name = Re.2000
  |image = Re2000.jpg
  |caption =
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type = Fighter
  |manufacturer = [[Reggiane]]
  |designer = Roberto Longhi
  |first flight = 24 May 1939
  |introduced = [[1940 in aviation|1940]]
  |retired = July [[1945 in aviation|1945]] (Sweden)
  |number built = 186 + license built
  |status =
  |unit cost =
  |variants with their own articles = [[MÁVAG Héja]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Reggiane Re.2001]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Reggiane Re.2002]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Reggiane Re.2003]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Reggiane Re.2005]]
  |primary user = [[Hungarian Air Force]]
  |more users = [[Swedish Air Force]]&lt;br/&gt;''[[Luftwaffe]]''&lt;br/&gt;''[[Regia Aeronautica]]''
}}
|}

The '''Caproni-Reggiane Re.2000 Falco I''' was an [[Italy|Italian]] all metal, low-wing, monoplane with a [[Curtiss-Wright]]-style retractable undercarriage, used in the first part of [[World War II]]. This lightly built and highly maneuverable  [[interceptor aircraft|interceptor]]/[[fighter (aircraft)|fighter]], similar to the [[Seversky P-35]], flew for the first time in 1939.&lt;ref name= &quot;Ethell p. 72.&quot;&gt;Ethell  1995,  p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; It proved a  technically advanced aircraft, well balanced and extremely aerodynamic, but not without its faults.&lt;ref name=&quot;Angelucci and Matricardi 1978, p. 214&quot;&gt;Angelucci and Matricardi 1978, p. 214.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although potentially superior to Italian contemporary fighters ([[Fiat G.50]] and [[Macchi C.200]]), the Re.2000 was not considered satisfactory by Italian military authorities. Consequently, the manufacturer built it for export and almost all of the first production  served with the [[Swedish Air Force]] and [[Hungarian Air Force]], rather than in the ''[[Regia Aeronautica]]'' (Italian Air Force).&lt;ref name= &quot;Snedden p. 53.&quot;&gt;Snedden 1997, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design and development==
The Reggiane Re.2000 was designed by Roberto Longhi and Antonio Alessio in 1938.&lt;ref name=&quot;Angelucci and Matricardi 1978, p. 214&quot;/&gt; They took inspiration from the contemporary [[Seversky P-35]] which it superficially resembled.&lt;ref&gt;Cappone, Max C.A. [http://planesandpilotsofww2.webs.com/Reggiane.html &quot;Reggiane RE 2000 Falco (Hawk): The Regia Aeronautica: American&quot;.] ''Planes and Pilots of World War Two''  Retrieved: 23 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The Re.2000 was the first aircraft designed by [[Reggiane]] that employed [[Aluminium|aluminum]] [[stressed skin]] rather than the wooden or mixed wood and metal structures normally used in contemporary Italian aircraft such as the [[Savoia-Marchetti SM.79]] built by Reggiane under license. Reggiane introduced several advanced features: a modern structure, well more advanced than the ones used in Macchi's and other Italian fighters of the time; an elliptical wing, with five spars and integral fuel tanks. Reggiane Re.2000 had no fuselage tanks, but nevertheless, with the entire wing volume devoted to fuel, it had up to 460&amp;nbsp;kg (640 lt) gasoline, with a 900 1,100&amp;nbsp;km endurance, far better than Macchis and Fiats. The armament was still two 12.7&amp;nbsp;mm Breda's (300 rounds each), plus the provision for bomblet-dispensers (''spezzoniera'').

The Re.2000 prototype's first flight was on 24 May 1939 at [[Reggio Emilia]], flown by [[Mario De Bernardi]],.&lt;ref name=&quot;State p.57&quot;&gt;Green and Swanborough 1990, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; The Re.2000, with 260&amp;nbsp;kg fuel (the maximum was 460&amp;nbsp;kg/640 lt, but RA did not needed it) was quite light: 2,059&amp;nbsp;kg empty, 2,529&amp;nbsp;kg loaded. It reached 518&amp;nbsp;km/h at 5,250 m and 506&amp;nbsp;km/h/6,000 m, climbed to 6,000 m in 6,5 min, and had 11,500 m ceiling.&lt;ref&gt;Original trials made at Guidonia by ''Regia Aeronautica'', late 1939.&lt;/ref&gt; During test flights the aircraft gave an excellent performance, and on several occasions, it performed better than other fighters then in production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Angelucci and Matricardi 1978, p. 214&quot;/&gt; In mock dogfights, it could successfully fight not only the slower [[Fiat CR.42]] biplane,&lt;ref&gt;'L'aviazione', De Agostini, Novara 1986, vol 12 p.156&lt;/ref&gt; but even the more modern [[Macchi C.200]] and the German [[Bf 109]]E.

The Re.2000GA (Grande Autonomia) version, added extra 340 liters fuel tanks. This version should have been used to reach Eastern Africa, but it wasn't ready before the Italian defeat; the only fighter sent to reinforce ''Regia Aeronautica'' units were 51 C.R.42s disassembled and transported by the large [[Savoia-Marchetti SM.82]]s. Re.2000GAs were heavier and significantly slower than the standard production Re.2000s. At an empty weight was 2,190&amp;nbsp;kg compared to the Re.2000's 2,080&amp;nbsp;kg, maximum speed was 520&amp;nbsp;km/h at 5,300 m. Armament was two 12.7&amp;nbsp;mm SAFAT with 600 rounds, and provisions for a Nardi dispenser with 88 2&amp;nbsp;kg bomblets (a typical 'special armament' for Re.2000s). The Re.2000GA was never really reliable (even for Re.2000 standards), especially its troublesome engine.

The Re.2000bis equipped with P XI bis engine was built in small numbers with only nine examples delivered when 377a Sq. was born, in August 1941.

==Operational history==

In service, the Re.2000's weak point was the engine, a {{convert|986|hp|abbr=on}} Piaggio P.XI RC 40 radial, which was not altogether reliable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Angelucci and Matricardi 1978, p. 214&quot;/&gt; Moreover, it was not as rugged as the Macchi and its fuel tanks were vulnerable (they were not  self-sealing).&lt;ref&gt;Sgarlato 2006, pp. 22–25.&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, the ''Regia Aeronautica'' rejected it.&lt;ref name= &quot;Ethell p. 72.&quot;/&gt;

The Reggiane Re.2000 was much more prominent in the [[Hungary|Hungarian]] and [[Sweden|Swedish]] air forces. In fact, 80 percent of Re.2000 production went to these two countries, with Hungary ordering 70 and Sweden 60 machines. Other countries also exhibited interest, but did not place orders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Angelucci and Matricardi 1978, p. 214&quot;/&gt;

===British Interest===
In December 1939 a British commission, led by [[Lord Hardwick]] and [[Air Ministry]] representatives, came to Italy to purchase (along with marine engines, armaments and light reconnaissance bombers) 300 Re 2000s. The Director of Aircraft Contracts confirmed the British order in January 1940. The German government  approved the sale in March of the same year, but withdrew its approval the following month. The Italian and British governments then decided to  complete the contract through the Italian [[Caproni]]’s Portuguese subsidiary, but the British order was cancelled when Italy entered World War II on 10 June 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duncan-Smith 1981, pag. 174&quot;&gt;Duncan-Smith 1981, page 174.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italy===
[[File:Reggiane2000 San Diego Air Space Museum 1.jpg|thumb|Re.2000]]
Only five ''Serie'' Is served in the [[Regia Aeronautica]], including the prototype.  They were organized into the ''Sezione Sperimentale Reggiane'' inside the 74a ''Squadriglia'' in [[Sicily]]. Later it was renamed ''377a Squadriglia Autonoma Caccia Terrestre'', and received nine further Serie III Re.2000bis; 12 of the 26 Reggianes were later converted to GA standard.

The few Re.2000 and 2000GA were used over Mediterranean Sea as escort and attack aircraft, sometimes with Macchi 200/202s and C.R.20 two-engine fighters. 377a was based in Sicily, and fought in [[Malta]] and [[Pantelleria]], mainly in an escort role and protecting Axis ships almost until Tunisia (with a range up to 300–350&amp;nbsp;km), well beyond the other RA single seat-fighters; sometimes it was used to attack Malta with bomblets (''spezzoni'') and machine guns, typically at dawn. It reported a single 'kill' against a [[Bristol Blenheim]]. Overall, their service was not remarkable: there was at least one sudden fatal flat spin, while another Re.2000 had fatal engine damage (a piston was literally driven through the cylinder) and crash-landed, overturning, catching fire and almost killing its pilot (rescued by the ground crew). Although the Reggiane had a long range, it was disliked and even feared by ground crew and pilots, for its difficult maintenance and unpredictable engine reliability and handling.&lt;ref&gt;Malizia, Nicola. ''Il Reggiane RE 2000''. Rome: Ateneo &amp; Bizzarri, 1978.&lt;/ref&gt; The last Re.2000 was sent back to the factory in September 1942.

The final fate of Re.2000 in ''Regia Aeronautica'' was to serve with 1° ''Nucleo Addestramento Intercettori'' (N.A.I.), based at [[Treviso]], and serving for experimental purposes until the Armistice. The last two serviceable aircraft were demolished by the Germans, with another one destroyed after being captured at [[Furbara]].

The ''[[Regia Marina]]'' (Italian Navy), however, experimented with a [[Aircraft carrier|carrier]] version (''Serie'' II) which was successfully launched by [[Aircraft catapult|catapult]]. Lacking a carrier, Italy used a similar system to the British CAM ships equipped with Hurricanes. The first proposal was made in late December 1940, although the program officially began with an order issued in April 1943. The first modified '''Re.2000 Cat.''' (taken from the Swedish orders) flew on 27 June 1941, the last on 18 January 1942 (MM.8282-8288), but crashed on 10 September. There was another navalized Re.2000, the MM.471. It flew initially with a lower powered A.74 RC.38 engine, but it was lost too, during the travel from [[Reggio Emilia]] to [[Taranto]] (12 May 1941). The first launch was performed on 9 May 1942 with test pilot Giulio Reiner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrauer&quot;/&gt; The work to make suitable the Re.2000 Cat., nicknamed ''Ochetta'' (little goose) took considerable time and only at the beginning of 1943 were they used aboard the [[Littorio-class battleship|''Littorio'' class]], but not more than one for every ship (although capable of holding three aircraft). Initially the Re.2000 Cat. aircraft were issued to {{ship|Italian battleship|Littorio||2}} and {{ship|Italian battleship|Vittorio Veneto||2}}, while {{ship|Italian battleship|Roma||2}} followed only in the summer, after testing had taken place aboard the RN ''Miraglia''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrauer&quot;&gt;Harrauer, Franco. &quot;Re.2000 Catapultabile.&quot; ''Aerei nella Storia,'' W.Ward editions, Parma ago-September 2008, pp. 49–50.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Re.2000 Cat. was slower than a standard Re.2000; instead of {{convert|515–530|km/h|mph kn}}, the maximum speed was only {{convert|505–520|km/h|mph kn}} at {{convert|5500|m|ft|-1}} &amp;nbsp;km/h at 5,500 m, and {{convert|390|km/h|mph kn}} at sea level compared with {{convert|541|km/h|mph kn}} for the Re.2000. The climb to 6,000 m was 7,75 min (vs 6,5-7 min), apparently there was not much difference in ceiling 10,000–11,100 m and endurance, range was 450&amp;nbsp;km, endurance 1,000&amp;nbsp;km (at 460&amp;nbsp;km/h), up to km 1,290 (at m 6,000, full loaded, km/h 430). Weights were 2,120–2,870 or, probably with the complete kit, 2,200–2,970&amp;nbsp;kg; the engine was the P.XIbis, that had {{convert|1000|hp|abbr=on}} both at take-off and at 4,000 meters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrauer&quot;/&gt; Differing from the Serie I, both Serie II and III variants were equipped with radios.&lt;ref name= &quot;Snedden p. 53.&quot;/&gt; There was the usual Italian armament (two 0.50 caliber Breda machine-guns with 300 rounds each), and some provisions for external loads (tanks or bombs), apparently never utilized.

The Re.2000 were assigned to ''Squadriglia di Riserva Aerea delle FF.NN.BB.'' (air reserve squadron for naval battleships), led by Captain Donato Tondi. This was initially based at [[Taranto-Grottaglie Airport|Grottaglie]], then at [[Naples International Airport|Capodichino]] and finally at [[La Spezia]], as air defence for naval bases. The squadron disbanded on April 1943 and was replaced by the 1° Gr. Riserva Aerea delle FF.NN.BB, led by now Maj. Tondi, with three flights. It had all the eight Re.2000s and several old fighters. Many of them were aboard the battleships: two for ''Vittorio Veneto'' and ''Roma'', one for ''Littorio'' (summer 1943).

Six Re.2000 Cat.s were still available at the time of the Armistice and four were in service aboard the battleships ''Italia'' (''Littorio'' before the fall of Mussolini), ''Roma'' and ''Vittorio Veneto'' (the normal load was only one, the battleship had up to three aircraft, but smaller than the Re.2000). The two left at La Spezia were demolished after September 1943 (they served with 1a Squadriglia). During the ''Roma''{{'}}s sinking (9 September 1943) only one was launched, as they were a single mission aircraft (forced to reach a land airfield); therefore, Do 217s attacked facing only [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] guns. The fate of the four Re.2000s was as follows: the one on ''Roma'' was lost with the battleship; the one of ''Italia'' was damaged and jettisoned from the ship, after the [[Fritz-X]] impact. One Re.2000 was launched from ''Vittorio Veneto'' to catch the intruders, but failed and finally crashed while landing near [[Ajaccio]] airfield. The last one survived and it is still extant, being the only Re.2000 remaining in Italy (another is in Sweden). This is the MM.8287.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrauer&quot;/&gt;

===Sweden===
[[File:Caproni Reggiane RE.2000 2.jpg|thumb|Re.2000 at Swedish Air Force Museum in Linköping]]
The Swedish purchases of various types of Italian warplanes in 1939–41 were an emergency measure resulting from the outbreak of war, as no other nations were willing to supply aircraft to this small neutral country whose domestic production did not become sufficient until 1943. The [[Swedish Air Force]] purchased 60 Re.2000 ''Serie'' Is, which received the Swedish designation J 20 and were delivered during 1941-43.&lt;ref name=&quot;avrosys.nu&quot;&gt;Henriksson, Lars. [http://www.avrosys.nu/aircraft/Jakt/111J20.htm &quot;J 20 - Reggiane Re 2000 Falco 1 (1941–1945).&quot;] ''Avrosys.nu''. Retrieved: 27 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

All of the J 20s were stationed at the F10 wing, [[Malmö Bulltofta Airport|Bulltofta airbase]], [[Malmö]], in the southern tip of [[Sweden]] in 1941-45.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A fighter paid with precious metals|url=http://www.ww2incolor.com/other/RE2000-J20-FORUMBILDER.html|work=www.ww2incolor.com|accessdate=5 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were mainly used to intercept [[Axis forces|Axis]] and [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] bombers that violated Swedish airspace. One J 20 was lost in combat, shot down while intercepting a ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' [[Dornier Do 24]] near [[Sölvesborg]] on 3 April 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;avrosys.nu&quot;/&gt;

The pilots appreciated the type, which performed well under harsh conditions.  But its mechanical reliability did not meet Swedish Air Force requirements, with the aircraft having to spend a lot of time in maintenance.  At the end of the war, the 37 J 20s that remained in service were so badly worn out that they were decommissioned in July 1945 and subsequently scrapped, while only one was kept for display purposes.

===Hungary===
German leaders were reluctant to supply the [[Hungarian Air Force|Royal Hungarian Air Force]] (''Magyar Királyi Honvéd Légierő''), MKHL, which was seen to be focused on home defence and the possibility of conflict with [[Romania]]. [[Adolf Hitler]] expressed this in early 1942 when Hungary requested German-built fighters. &quot;They would not use the single-seaters against the enemy but just for pleasure flights!... What the Hungarians have achieved in the aviation field to date is more than paltry. If I am going to give some aircraft, then rather to the Croats, who have proved they have an offensive spirit. To date, we have experienced only fiascos with the Hungarians.&quot;&lt;ref name= &quot;Neulen p. 131.&quot;&gt;Neulen 2000, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;

The MKHL consequently became a significant purchaser of Italian aircraft and was the main operator of the Re.2000. Hungary bought 70 Reggiane Re.2000 Falco Is and then also acquired the licence-production rights for this model to produce a total of 200 aircraft, known as [[MÁVAG Héja]] (&quot;Hawk&quot;) II built between 1940 and 1942.&lt;ref name= &quot;Neulen p. 121.&quot;&gt;Neulen 2000, p.121.&lt;/ref&gt; According to other sources,170–203 aircraft were built. The II series was the same aircraft with a different engine and Hungarian machine guns.
The first aircraft received from Italy were sent to [[Debrecen]] to strengthen home defences, as there was danger that the growing crisis over [[Transylvania]] could lead to a conflict with Romania.&lt;ref name= &quot;Neulen p. 121.&quot;/&gt; Conflict was avoided and the Hungarian  Reggianes were used on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], in the war against the Soviet Union.
The first seven Re.2000 were sent  to the front on an experimental basis in autumn 1941. Flying alongside the [[Fiat CR.32]]s of 1/3 Fighter Company, the Reggiane pilots claimed eight kills, for one loss,  during three months of combat, against Soviet Air Force.&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 7.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer of 1942, Hungarian Air Force contributed with its 1st ''Repülőcsoport'' (aviation detachment) to the German offensive ''[[Case Blue|Fall Blau]]''. 1/1 Fighter Group (1./I ''Vadász Osztály'')  equipped with 13 Re.2000s or ''Héjas'',&lt;ref name= &quot;Bergström-Dikov-Antipov p. 21.&quot;&gt;Bergström-Dikov-Antipov- 2006, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; reached its first front base near Kursk on 2 July.  By 3 August, 2/1 FS joined the other Hungarian fighter unit, that had moved to Ilvoskoje airfield. The task of 2/1 was to escort short-range reconnaissance aircraft, while 1/1 would support bombing missions.&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 7.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;
Combat performance against the [[Soviet Air Force]] was satisfactory. 
On 4 August the Hungarians claimed their first kills, when Ens Vajda shot down two enemy aircraft.&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 7.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;
The first Hungarian ace of the war, 2/Lt Imre Pànczél, claimed his first air victories while flying the Re.2000, three of them in one sortie, in 1942.&lt;ref name= &quot;Shores p. 103.&quot;&gt;Shores  1983, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; 
However, the Re.2000's flight characteristics were markedly different to the Fiat CR.32, from which Hungarian pilots frequently converted. The Re.2000 was much more prone to handling difficulties, especially [[stall (flight)|stall]]s and [[spin (flight)|spin]]s,  as well as reliability issues. All  the 24 Re.2000s had suffered accidents (minor and major) within a month of combat deployment. Piaggio P.XI engine proved to be a mechanical nightmare for the mechanics.&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 7.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; Landing and takeoff accidents were common on the rudimentary Russian airfields and due to the Re.2000 not having a rugged landing gear, compared to that of the CR.32. After a steel plate was added behind the cockpit to protect pilots, the shift in the aircraft's [[Center of gravity of an aircraft|center of gravity]] led to more frequent accidents. In a much publicized mishap, 1/Lt [[István Horthy]] (the son of the Hungarian regent [[Miklós Horthy]]), serving as a fighter pilot with the [[Hungarian Second Army]] died flying a Re.2000 V-421 with 1/3 Fighter Squadron on 20 (on 18, according to other authors &lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 9.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;) August 1942, on his 25th operational sortie. After a pilot flying above asked Horthy to increase height, he pulled up rapidly, stalled and crashed.&lt;ref name= &quot;Neulen p. 127.&quot;&gt;Neulen 2000, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the determined Hungarian pilots kept on flying combat missions and scoring a number of kills against the Soviet fighter, if they managed to force their Russian opponents into a dogfight, thanks to the maneuverability of the Italian built plane.&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 7.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; The Hungarians Re.2000s had their most successful day on 9 August 1942. That day, near the village of Davidovka, 16 [[Ilyushin Il-2]]s and a similar number of [[LaGG-3|LaGG-3S]]
&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 8.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; were intercepted by four Reggianes. The Hungarians downed four LaGGs, suffering the loss of the Re.2000 of Lt Takács, who crash-landed behind his own lines, wounded.&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 9.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; 
The Hungarian Reggianes flew their last sorties on the Soviet front on 14 and 15 January 1943, when they took off for uneventful patrols and reconnaissance missions. Between 16 and 19 January, with the Red Army rapidly approaching Ilovskoje airfield, and with no time to heat the Piaggio engine's frozen oil, the mechanics had to blow up the last unserviceable ''Hejas''. 
&lt;ref name= &quot;Punka p. 10.&quot;&gt;Punka 2002, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

The surviving Reggianes were kept in Hungary for home defence. 
Production of licence-built ''Hejas'' continued: 98 were completed in 1943 and 72 in 1944 although the variant was regarded as no longer suitable for combat against the latest Soviet fighters.&lt;ref name= &quot;Neulen p. 130.&quot;&gt;Neulen 2000, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt; Hungary requested an additional 50–100 Re.2000 airframes made in Italy, as suitable engines and armament could be locally manufactured and other countries expressed interest, including Finland (100 examples), Portugal (50), Spain, Switzerland and Yugoslavia. However, no airframes were available.&lt;ref name= &quot;Sgarlato p. 16.&quot;&gt;Sgarlato 2006, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

By April 1944, the MKHL still deployed four ''Héja'' IIs in 1/1 Fighter squadron and four ''Hejas'' II in 1/2, all of them based in Szolnok for home defence duties, along with about 40 Bf 109s and Messerschmitt Me 210s. The last sortie for the licence-built Reggiane Re.2000 occurred on 2 April 1944. That day, 180 bombers from the USAAF [[15th Expeditionary Mobility Task Force|15th Air Force]], escorted by 170 fighters, bombed the Danube Aircraft Works and other targets in Budapest. The Hungarian fighter control centre in the Géllert hill, near Budapest, scrambled one wing of ''Hejas'' from 1/1 Fighter squadron, along with 12 Bf 109G-4/G-6S and a couple of Messerschmitt Me 210Cas-1s from the Experimental Air Force Institute (RK1). The Hungarians reported 11 aerial victories, of which six were confirmed, while USAAF pilots claimed  27 MKHL aircraft shot down. However, later records showed only two Honvéd pilots were killed.&lt;ref name= &quot;Neulen p. 136.&quot;&gt;Neulen 2000, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==

===Italian versions===
;Re.2000
:Initial prototype, one built.
;Re.2000 Serie I
:Production model, 157 built. Serie I had modified windshield and slight equipment changes.
;Re.2000 Serie II
:Ship-borne version, 10 built. Serie II had a 1,025&amp;nbsp;hp [[Piaggio P.XI]]bis engine and arrester gear.
;Re.2000 (GA) Serie III
:Long-range fighter, 12 built. Serie III had redesigned cockpit, increased fuel capacity and option of a 170 l auxiliary fuel tank or a dispenser of 22 2 kg bomblets.
;RE 2000 &quot;Catapultabile&quot;: Re 2000 aircraft modified for catapult launch from [[Regia Marina]] ships. On the day of the armistice, 8 September 1943, 6 Re 2000 &quot;Catapultabile &quot; were in service, with two on the battleship [[Italian battleship Roma (1940)|''Roma'']] and one each on the [[Italian battleship Vittorio Veneto|''Vittorio Veneto'']] and [[Italian battleship Italia|''Italia'']] (formerly the ''Littorio'').

===Hungarian versions===
;[[MÁVAG Heja I/II|Héja I]]
:Hungarian designation for Serie I.
;[[MÁVAG Heja I/II|Héja II]]
:Hungarian designation for modified license-produced Serie I. ''Héja'' IIs had a 986&amp;nbsp;hp WMK 14 engine and two Hungarian 12.7&amp;nbsp;mm Gebauer machine guns.

==Operators==
;{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
*''[[Luftwaffe]]''
;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Hungary}}
*[[Royal Hungarian Air Force]]
;{{flag|Kingdom of Italy}}
*''[[Regia Aeronautica]]''
;{{SWE}}
*[[Swedish Air Force]]

==Specifications (Re.2000 Series I)==
{{aircraft specifications
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=prop
|ref=RE 2000...The 'State-of-the-Art' Reggiane &lt;ref name=&quot;State p65&quot;&gt;Green and Swanborough 1990, p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Now, fill out the specs.  Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses). 
If an item doesn't apply, like capacity, leave it blank. For additional lines, end your
alt units with )&lt;/li&gt; and start a new, fully-formatted line with &lt;li&gt; --&gt;
|crew=1
|capacity=
|length main= 7.99 m
|length alt= 26 ft 2½ in
|span main= 11.00 m
|span alt= 36 ft  1 in
|height main= 3.20 m
|height alt= 10 ft  5⅞ in
|area main= 20.40 m²
|area alt= 219.6 sq ft
|airfoil=
|empty weight main= 2,090 kg
|empty weight alt= 4,585 lb
|loaded weight main= 2,839 kg
|loaded weight alt= 6,259 lb
|useful load main=
|useful load alt=
|max takeoff weight main=
|max takeoff weight alt=
|engine (prop)= [[Piaggio P.XI]] RC 40
|type of prop=14-cylinder twi-row air-cooled [[radial engine]]
|number of props=1
|power main= 986 hp
|power alt= 736 kW
|power original=  &amp;nbsp;(1000 CV)
|power more=at 4,000 m (13,125 ft)
|propeller or rotor?=propeller&lt;!-- options: propeller/rotor --&gt;
|propellers=Piaggion-D'Ascanio P.1001 three-bladed constant speed
|number of propellers per engine=
|propeller diameter main=3.10 m
|propeller diameter alt= 10 ft 2 in
|max speed main= 530 km/h
|max speed alt=268 knots, 329 mph
|max speed more=at 5,300 m (17,400 ft)
|cruise speed main= 440 km/h
|cruise speed alt=237 knots, 273 mph
|never exceed speed main=
|never exceed speed alt=
|stall speed main=
|stall speed alt=
|range main= 545 km
|range alt=296 [[nautical mile|nmi]], 340 mi
|endurance=1.25 hours
|ceiling main= 11,200 m
|ceiling alt= 36,745 ft
|ceiling more=(practical ceiling)
|loading main=
|loading alt=
|more performance=*'''Climb to 4,000 m (13,125 ft):''' 4 min
|guns= 2× 12.7&amp;nbsp;mm [[Breda-SAFAT machine gun]]s

}}

==See also==
{{aircontent|
|related=
* [[Reggiane Re.2001]]
* [[Reggiane Re.2002]]
* [[Reggiane Re.2005]]
|similar aircraft=
* [[Bloch MB.152]]
* [[Curtiss P-36]]
* [[Curtiss-Wright CW-21]]
* [[IAR 80]]
* [[Macchi MC.200]]
* [[Mitsubishi A6M]]
* [[Nakajima Ki-43]]
* [[Yakovlev Yak-9|Yakovlev Yak-9DD]]
|lists=
* [[List of fighter aircraft]]
* [[Regia Aeronautica#Aircraft|List of aircraft of Italy in World War II]]
* [[List of aircraft of World War II]]
|see also=
}}

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|30em}}
;Bibliography
{{Refbegin}}
* Angelucci, Enzo and Paolo Matricardi. ''World Aircraft: World War II, Volume I'' (Sampson Low Guides). Maidenhead, UK: Sampson Low, 1978. ISBN 0-562-00096-8.
* Bergström, Christer, Andrey Dikov and Vlad Antipov. ''Black Cross Red Star: Air War over the Eastern Front, Volume 3: Everything for Stalingrad''. Hamilton, Massachusetts: Eagle Editions, 2006. ISBN 0-9761034-4-3.
* Cattaneo, Gianni. ''The Reggiane Re.2000 (Aircraft in Profile Number 123)''. Windsor, Berkshire, UK: Profile Publications Ltd., 1972 (reprinted from 1967). No ISBN.
* Duncan-Smith, Wilfred (Grp. Capt ret). ''Spitfire into Battle''. Feltham, Middlesex, UK: Hamlyn Paperbacks, 1981. ISBN 0-7195-3831-9.
* Ethell, Jeffrey L. ''Aircraft of World War II''. Glasgow: Collins and Jane's, 1995. ISBN 0-00-470849-0.
* Green, William and Gordon Swanborough. &quot;RE 2000... The 'State-of-the-Art' Reggiane&quot;. ''[[Air Enthusiast]]'', Forty-one, Midsummer 1990, pp.&amp;nbsp;54–69. Bromley, UK: Tri-Service Press. ISSN 0143-5450.
* Longhi, Roberto. &quot;Reggiane and I... A Fighter Designer Recalls&quot;. ''Air Enthusiast'', Two, 1976, pp.&amp;nbsp;214–224. Bromley, UK: Fine Scroll.
* Mondey, David. ''The Concise Guide to Axis Aircraft of World War II''. New York: Bounty Books, 1996. ISBN 1-85152-966-7.
* Neulen, Hans Werner. ''In the skies of Europe: Air Forces Allied to the Luftwaffe 1939–1945''. Ramsbury, Marlborough, UK: The Crowood Press, 2000. ISBN 1-86126-799-1
* Punka, Gӳorge. ''Hungarian Aces of World War 2''. Osprey Publishing, Oxford, England, 2002. ISBN 978-1-84176-436-8.
* Punka, George. ''Reggiane Fighters in action''. Carrolton, Texas: Squadron/Signal Publications, 2001. ISBN 0-89747-430-9.
* Sgarlato, Nico. ''Reggiane'' (in Italian). Parma, Italy: Westward editions, 2006.
* Snedden, Robert. ''World War II Combat Aircraft''. Bristol, UK: Parragon, 1997. ISBN 0-7525-1684-1.
* Shores, Christopher. ''Air Aces'', Greenwich, Connecticut: Bison Books, 1983. ISBN 0-86124-104-5.
* Taylor, John W. R. &quot;Reggiane Re.2000 Falco I (Falcon)&quot;. ''Combat Aircraft of the World from 1909 to the Present''. New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1969. ISBN 0-425-03633-2.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Reggiane Re.2000}}
* [http://www.xs4all.nl/~fbonne/warbirds/ww2htmls/reggre2000.html The Reggiane Re.2000 Falco]

{{Reggiane aircraft}}
{{Swedish fighter aircraft}}
{{Swedish military aircraft}}

[[Category:Italian fighter aircraft 1930–1939]]
[[Category:World War II Italian fighter aircraft]]
[[Category:Reggiane aircraft]]
[[Category:Propeller aircraft]]
[[Category:Single-engine aircraft]]
[[Category:Low-wing aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>eckcdtm71946av4za139q5mc59w7bkk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
