<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Roger B. Chaffee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>36595</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750745055</id>
      <parentid>750741651</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T16:05:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JustinTime55</username>
        <id>11561890</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:LASTNAME]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31350">{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2014}}

{{Infobox astronaut
| name = Roger B. Chaffee
| honorific_suffix = 
| image = RogerChaffee.1964.ws.jpg
| image_size = 
| alt =
| caption = 
| type = [[NASA]] [[astronaut]]
| native_name = 
| native_name_lang = 
| nationality = American
| status = Killed during training
| birth_name = 
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1935|02|15}}
| birth_place = [[Grand Rapids, Michigan|Grand Rapids]], [[Michigan]], U.S.&lt;ref name=astronautsmemorial/&gt;
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1967|01|27|1935|02|15}}&lt;ref name=astronautsmemorial/&gt;
| death_place = [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station|Cape Kennedy]], [[Florida]], U.S.
| resting_place = [[Arlington National Cemetery]]&lt;ref name=arlington&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/rbchaffe.htm|title=Roger Bruce Chaffee, Lieutenant Commander, United States Navy|website=Arlington National Cemetery|access-date=June 5, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| resting_place_coords = 
| other_names = Roger Bruce Chaffee
| occupation = [[Naval aviator]], [[test pilot]]
| current_occupation = 
| previous_occupation = 
| alma_mater = [[Illinois Institute of Technology|Illinois Tech]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Purdue University]], B.S. 1957&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ispyspace.com/Roger_Chaffee.html|title=Astronaut Roger B. Chaffee|last1=Kelly|first1=Fred|access-date=June 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rank = [[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|20px]] [[Lieutenant Commander (United States)|Lieutenant Commander]], {{flag|United States Navy|size=23px}}
| space_time = 
| selection = [[List of astronauts by selection#1963|1963 NASA Group 3]]
| evas = 
| eva_time =    &lt;!-- h m s --&gt;
| mission =    [[Apollo 1]]
| insignia = [[File:Apollo 1 patch.png|40px]]
| retirement =  &lt;!-- {{end date|YYYY|MM|DD}} --&gt;
| awards = {{CS Medal of Honor}} [[Image:Air Medal front.jpg|20px]] [[File:Naval Aviator Badge.jpg|75px]] 
| memorials = 
| website =     &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
| module = 
| child =
}}
'''Roger Bruce Chaffee''' (February 15, 1935 – January 27, 1967), ([[Lieutenant Commander|LCDR]], [[United States Navy|USN]]), was an American [[United States Navy|naval officer]] and [[United States naval aviator|aviator]], [[Aeronautical engineering|aeronautical]] [[engineer]], [[test pilot]], and [[NASA]] [[astronaut]] in the [[Apollo program]].

He was born in Grand Rapids, Michigan, where he became an Eagle Scout. Chaffee graduated from Central High School in 1953 and accepted a Naval ROTC scholarship. He began his college education at Illinois Institute of Technology, where he was also involved in the fraternity Phi Kappa Sigma. He transferred to Purdue University in the Fall of 1954, where he continued his involvement in Phi Kappa Sigma and also obtained his private pilot's license.

He was selected to be an astronaut along with 13 other pilots as a part of [[NASA Astronaut Group 3]]. In 1967, Chaffee perished in a fire along with fellow astronauts [[Gus Grissom|Virgil &quot;Gus&quot; Grissom]] and [[Edward Higgins White|Edward H. White]] during a pre-launch test for the [[Apollo 1]] mission at the then-[[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station|Cape Kennedy Air Force Station]], [[Florida]]. Chaffee was posthumously awarded the [[Congressional Space Medal of Honor]] and a second Navy [[Air Medal]].&lt;ref name=navalhist&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/biographies-list/bios-c/Chaffee-Roger.html|title=Roger Bruce Chaffee|access-date=September 18, 2016|date=March 7, 2016|website=Naval History and Heritage Command}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Roger Bruce Chaffee was born on February 15, 1935, in [[Grand Rapids, Michigan]]. In January 1935, at their hometown of Greenville, Michigan, his father Don Chaffee (1910–1998) was diagnosed with [[scarlet fever]]. Due to the risk of infection from the disease, his wife Blanche (1912–1996) moved in with her parents in Grand Rapids, where Roger was eventually born. The family spent the next seven years in Michigan, where Roger became an [[Eagle Scout (Boy Scouts of America)|Eagle Scout]].&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot; /&gt;

== Boy scouts ==

Chaffee excelled as a boy scout, earning his first merit badge at the age of thirteen. He earned ten more badges that year. In 1948, he earned badges for home repairs, firemanship, personal health, safety, athletic, public health, swimming, first aid, cooking, and the order of the arrow. Many of these awards were typically won by the older scouts, but he performed exceptionally well.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=&quot;...On Course to the Stars|last1=Chrysler|first1=C. Donald|last2=Chaffee|first2=Donald L.|publisher=Kregel Publications|location=Grand Rapids, Michigan|date=1968}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|32-33}} He continued his success by obtaining four additional badges at the age of fourteen, for scholarship, rowing, life-saving, and canoeing.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}} The following year, he got four additional badges, which were pathfinder, pioneering, music, and seamanship. The next year, Chaffee earned four additional badges, and had almost all of the badges available at the time. He earned camping, civics, bird study, and bugling that year. After becoming an Eagle Scout, he managed to earn another ten merit badges, for which he was awarded the bronze and gold palms.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|33}}

== Education ==

He graduated in the top fifth of his class from [[Central High School (Grand Rapids, Michigan)|Central High School]] in 1953 and had a grade average of over 92%.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|43}} Turning down a possible appointment to the [[United States Naval Academy]] at [[Annapolis, Maryland]], Chaffee accepted a [[Naval ROTC]] scholarship, and in September 1953 enrolled at the [[Illinois Institute of Technology]]. Chaffee performed well at the Illinois Institute of Technology, making the Dean's list and finishing with a B+ average. While enrolled, Chaffee also joined Phi Kappa Sigma.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://history.nasa.gov/Apollo204/zorn/chaffee.htm|title=Detailed Biographies of Apollo I Crew - Roger Chaffee|last=White|first=Mary|website=Nasa|access-date=June 3, 2016|date=August 4, 2006|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110604142258/http://history.nasa.gov/Apollo204/zorn/chaffee.htm|archive-date=June 4, 2011|dead-url=no}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Purdue ===

Chaffee was passionate about flying and had a high aptitude for science and engineering. To apply those talents, Chaffee transferred to [[Purdue University]] in the fall of 1954 to attend the school's well-known aeronautical engineering program.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt; Prior to his arrival in [[West Lafayette]], Chaffee was to report for a 8-week tour on the [[USS Wisconsin (BB-64)|battleship ''Wisconsin'']] as a part of the NROTC program. To qualify, he had to take complete training and pass additional tests. He initially failed the eye exam, but the physician allowed him to retake the test the next morning, and he passed. Chaffee was then allowed to tour on the ''Wisconsin'' to England, Scotland, France, and Cuba. Upon his return to American soil, Chaffee still had some time before his first Fall semester at Purdue. To fill the gap, he worked as a gear cutter.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

Upon starting classes at Purdue in the Fall of 1954, Chaffee sought out a job to complement his coursework and involvement in Phi Kappa Sigma. His first job during his sophomore year was working as a server at one of the women's residences. Chaffee disliked the feminine environment and sought new employment. He was hired as a draftsman at a local company for a small business near Purdue. As a Junior, Chaffee's résumé continued to grow as he was hired as a teaching assistant in the Mathematics Department to teach classes to Freshman.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

Chaffee earned a [[Bachelor of Science]] degree in [[aeronautical engineering]] at Purdue in 1957. There he maintained his membership to the [[Phi Kappa Sigma]] social fraternity, and also joined the [[Tau Beta Pi]] and [[Sigma Gamma Tau]] engineering honor societies.&lt;ref name='chaffee space'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jsc.nasa.gov/Bios/htmlbios/chaffee-rb.html|title=ROGER B. CHAFFEE|year=1997|publisher=Lyndon B. Johnson Space Center|accessdate=April 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; While at Purdue, Chaffee took flight training as part of the Naval ROTC program in order to prepare him for a career as a [[naval aviator]], soloing on 29 March 1957, and obtaining his private pilot's license on 24 May 1957.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

== Family ==

Chaffee married Martha Horn in [[Oklahoma City]] on August 24, 1957; they had met on a blind date in September 1955.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt; The couple had two children, Sheryl Lyn (born November 17, 1958) and Stephen (born July 3, 1961).&lt;ref name=spaceacts&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spaceacts.com/STARSHIP/seh/chaffee.htm|title= Biographical Data|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160307172656/http://spaceacts.com/starship/seh/chaffee.htm|archive-date=March 7, 2016|dead-url=yes|website=Space Acts|accessdate=October 3, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Navy service==
[[File:Roger Chaffee Navy Portrait.jpg|thumb|Chaffee's Navy portrait]]

Following graduation, Chaffee completed his Navy training on August 22, 1957 and was commissioned as an [[Ensign (rank)|ensign]] in the U.S. Navy. Following his honeymoon, he reported to the ''Lake Champlain'' for a six week assignment in Norfolk with the Naval Air Force, U.S. Atlantic Fleet.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|70}} In October 1957, Chaffee attended flight school at the [[Naval Air Station Pensacola]], [[Florida]]. He started his training by flying the T-28, moving onto the T-34 soon after.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|70}} Since he was a naval aviator, he was posted to the [[Naval Air Station Kingsville]], [[Texas]], from August 1958 to February 1959 as a part of Advanced Training Unit 212.&lt;ref name=navyhistory /&gt; In Kingsville, Chaffee trained on the F9F cougar jet fighter.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|70}} His daughter Cheryl was born the day that he left for his first aircraft carrier training.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|71}} Chaffee was awarded his [[United States Aviator Badge|aviator wings]] in early 1959.&lt;ref name=astronautsmemorial/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

He then transferred to [[Naval Air Station Jacksonville|Naval Air Station (NAS) Jacksonville]], Florida, to continue his training. His first project was not flying, but instead repairing a A3D twin engined jet photo reconnaissance plane.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|72}} The plane was typically flown by pilots with the rank of Lieutenant Commander or above, but since Chaffee became so familiar with the plane due to repairing it, he became one of the youngest pilots to ever fly it.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|72}} He joined Attack Squadron 44 in September 1959, and from October 1959 to March 1960 he trained with Heavy Attack Squadron 3.&lt;ref name=navyhistory /&gt;

{{Quote box
 |quote  = There's only room for one mistake. You can buy the farm only once.
 |author = Roger Chaffee
 |source = &lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|73}}
 |width  = 20%
 |align  = right
}}
Chaffee was given a variety of assignments and participated in numerous training duties over the next few years, spending the majority of his time in photo reconnaissance squadrons. He was stationed at NAS Jacksonville as safety officer and quality control officer for Heavy Photographic Squadron 62 ([[VAP-62]]) flying the [[A-3 Skywarrior|A3D-2P (later RA-3B) Skywarrior]].&lt;ref name=astronautsmemorial&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.astronautsmemorial.org/roger-b-chaffee-honored.html|title=Roger B. Chaffee|website=Astronauts Memorial Foundation|access-date=June 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='chaffee space' /&gt; He wrote a quality control manual for the squadron, although some of his peers saw this as too demanding of perfection.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|74}} By coincidence, Chaffee was assigned to a mission where he flew over Cape Canaveral, in which aerial photographs of future launch sites were taken.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|74}} In 1961, he flew several trips back and forth from the United States to Cuba, sometimes up to three flights per day, and achieved over 100 flight hours each month. Some of these trips included shuttling three men per plane back and forth to Guantanamo Bay, which were the pilot, co-pilot, and the photographer.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|75}} After this, Chaffee spent time doing flattop or carrier flight training, including time spent on the ''USS Saratoga'' performing both day and night flights.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|75}} Chaffee said of day flying, &quot;Setting that big bird down on the flight deck was like landing on a postage stamp,&quot; and said of night flying, &quot;Getting catapulted off that flight deck at night is like getting shot into a bottle of ink!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|75}} While working in Jacksonville, he concurrently was working on a Master's degree.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|75}} Chaffee was on a cruise to Africa when his son Stephen was born in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|76}}

Chaffee was awarded the Air Medal after &quot;completing 82 classified missions of paramount military importance to the security of the United States&quot; in Heavy Photographic Squadron 62.&lt;ref name=navyhistory /&gt; During his Navy service he logged more than 2,300 hours flying time, including more than 2,000 hours in jet aircraft.&lt;ref name=astronautsmemorial/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt; On February 1, 1966, Chaffee was promoted to [[Lieutenant Commander (United States)|lieutenant commander]].&lt;ref name=navyhistory&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/biographies-list/bios-c/Chaffee-Roger/Chaffee-Roger-Text.html|title=Roger Bruce Chaffee|access-date=September 18, 2016|date=March 3, 2016|website=Naval History and Heritage Command}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==NASA career==
{{Quote box|The world itself looks cleaner and so much more beautiful. Maybe we can make it that way—the way God intended it to be—by giving everybody that new perspective from out in space.|width=25%|source=Roger Chaffee&lt;ref name=newmexico&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nmspacemuseum.org/halloffame/detail.php?id=73|title=Named Pilot of the Apollo 1 crew.|website=New Mexico Museum of Space History|access-date=June 5, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160308200304/http://nmspacemuseum.org/halloffame/detail.php?id=73|archive-date=March 8, 2016|dead-url=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
===Selection===

In August 1962, Chaffee confided in his family that he had submitted an application for the astronaut training program, and informed his superiors he wanted to train as a test pilot for astronaut status.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|78}} In mid-1962, Chaffee was accepted in the initial pool of 1,800 applicants for the third group of NASA astronauts.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|79}} After his naval tour was over and he had racked up over 1800 hours of flying time, the Navy offered an opportunity to work on his Master's degree.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|79}} In January 1963, he entered the U.S. [[Air Force Institute of Technology]] (AFIT) at [[Wright-Patterson Air Force Base]] in [[Dayton, Ohio]], to work on his [[Master of Science]] degree in [[Reliability Engineering]].&lt;ref name='chaffee space' /&gt; While at AFIT, Chafee would continue to participate in astronaut candidate testing as the pool of candidates dropped to 271 in mid-1963. It was noted during testing that Chaffee had a very small lung capacity, but that he used it better than most people with a large lung capacity.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|82}} Chaffee returned from a hunting trip to Fairborn, Michigan on October 14, 1963, when he found a message from NASA Headquarters in Houston, Texas.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|82}} He called them back, and discovered he was chosen as an astronaut.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt; On October 18, 1963, he was officially announced as one of 14 chosen for [[Astronaut Group 3]].&lt;ref name=astronautsmemorial/&gt; Upon appointment, Chaffee said, &quot;I was very pleased with the appointment. I've always wanted to fly and perform adventurous flying tasks all my life. Ever since the first seven Mercury astronauts were named, I've been keeping my studies up.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|85}}

===Training===
[[File:Apollo 1 astronauts Edward H. White II and Roger B. Chaffee during water egress training.jpg|thumb|Chaffee (sitting on hatch sill) during water egress training for Apollo 1]]
Phase one of training for the third group of astronauts began in 1964. The training began in lecture halls, where astronauts learned about several professional fields. Lectures were supplemented with trips to locations with geological significance so the astronauts could gain hands-on experience. The astronauts traveled from the Grand Canyon to learn about geography all the way to Alaska, Iceland, and Hawaii to learn about rock formations and lava flows.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

The second phase was contingency training. This survival training focused on astronauts learning the skills required to survive if the landing did not occur where planned. The group started their training by being dropped off in the middle of the jungle in Panama. The astronauts performed the survival training in pairs, carrying only their parachutes and survival kits. Chaffee, with help from his Boy Scout training, foraged for enough food to survive during the three day training mission. Following the jungle training, the astronauts traveled to an entirely different environment: the desert of Reno, Nevada. For clothing, the astronauts only had long underwear, shoes, and robes they manufactured from their parachutes. Lizards and snakes were the main source of food, and the astronauts used their parachutes as makeshift tents for shelter for the two days of desert training.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

The third and final phase was operational training for the astronauts. This training focused on giving the astronauts hands-on experience using the instruments and equipment required during their spaceflight. The training also focused on the sensations the astronauts would experience during spaceflight, such as the effects of microgravity and high acceleration. The astronauts spent time in simulators, flying aboard cargo planes to simulate weightlessness, underwater training to practice extravehicular activities (EVAs), and visits to manufacturing plants to check on the progress of the hardware.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

===Project Gemini===
[[File:Roger B. Chaffee at a console in the Mission Control Center, Houston, during the Gemini-Titan 3 flight.jpg|thumb|Chaffee at the consoles in Mission Control during the [[Gemini 3]] mission]]
At the Manned Space Center in Houston, Chaffee served as [[capsule communicator]] (CAPCOM) in March 1965 for Gemini 3.&lt;ref name=ksc&gt;{{cite web|url=http://science.ksc.nasa.gov/history/gemini/gemini-3/gemini-3.html|title=Gemini 3 (3)|access-date=September 20, 2016|date=August 25, 2000|website=Kennedy Space Center: Science, Technology, and Engineering}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, he served as CAPCOM again, along with [[Gus Grissom|Virgil &quot;Gus&quot; Grissom]] and [[Gene Cernan|Eugene Cernan]], for the [[Gemini 4]] mission, in which [[Edward Higgins White|Edward H. White II]] performed the first spacewalk by an American.&lt;ref name=astronautsmemorial/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt; As CAPCOM, Chaffee relayed information between the crew members and the Director of Flight Operations, Christopher Kraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt; He never got a seat on a [[Project Gemini|Gemini]] mission, but was assigned to work on flight control, communications, instrumentation, and attitude and translation control systems in the [[Apollo program]].&lt;ref name='chaffee space' /&gt; During this time, he was also flew chase planes between 30,000 and 50,000 feet with Grissom to take motion pictures of the launch of an unmanned [[Saturn 1B]] rocket.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;{{rp|108}}

===Apollo program===
[[File:Apollo1-Crew 01.jpg|thumb|Apollo 1 crew, [[Gus Grissom|Grissom]], [[Edward Higgins White|White]], and Chaffee]]
Chaffee received his first spaceflight assignment when he was selected in January 1966 for the first manned Apollo flight, AS-204. Joining Command Pilot Grissom and Senior Pilot White, he replaced injured [[Donn F. Eisele]] in the third-ranked Pilot position. Eisele required surgery for a dislocated shoulder which he sustained aboard the [[reduced gravity aircraft|KC135 weightlessness training aircraft]], and was subsequently reassigned to a second Apollo crew, to be commanded by Mercury veteran [[Wally Schirra]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.popsci.com/blog-network/vintage-space/how-donn-eisele-became-whatshisname-command-module-pilot-apollo-7|title=How Donn Eisele Became &quot;Whatshisname,&quot; the Command Module Pilot of Apollo 7|last = Teitel|first = Amy Shira | website= Popular Science| date = December 4, 2013|access-date=June 5, 2016| archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20150422020339/http://www.popsci.com/blog-network/vintage-space/how-donn-eisele-became-whatshisname-command-module-pilot-apollo-7|archivedate =April 22, 2015|dead-url=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crew announcement was made public on March 21, 1966. Grissom, White, and Chaffee got permission to name their flight Apollo 1, as it was going to be the first manned orbital flight of the Apollo spacecraft. The two-week flight was not only to test the spacecraft systems, but also the ground tracking and control facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

While Chaffee had monitored the manufacture of the Gemini spacecraft, he had not witnessed the building of the Apollo spacecraft. Three days after being selected for the Apollo I crew, he flew out to the North American Aviation Plant in Downey, California, to witness spacecraft production.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Apollo 1 fire.jpg|thumb|Charred remains of the Apollo 1 [[Apollo Command/Service Module|Command Module]], in which Chaffee was killed along with Gus Grissom and Ed White]]

====Accident====
{{Details|Apollo 1}}

On January 27, 1967, Grissom, White and Chaffee were participating in a &quot;plugs-out&quot; countdown demonstration test at [[Cape Kennedy]] in preparation for the planned February 21 launch. Chaffee was sitting at the right side of the cabin.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.nasa.gov&quot;/&gt; His main role was to maintain communications with the Blockhouse. A momentary power surge was detected at 23:30:55 GMT, which was believed to accompany an electrical short in equipment located on the lower left side of the cabin, the presumed ignition source for the fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;aibreport&quot; /&gt;{{rp|5–10}} At 23:31:04 GMT, Chaffee's voice is believed by most investigative listeners to be the one declaring, &quot;[We]'ve got a fire in the cockpit.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aibreport&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Thompson|first1=Floyd|last2=Borman|first2=Dolah|last3=Faget|first3=Maxime|last4=White|first4=George|last5=Geer|first5=Barton|date=April 5, 1967|title=Report of Apollo 204 Review Board|url=http://history.nasa.gov/Apollo204/summary.pdf|publisher=NASA|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160514220957/http://history.nasa.gov/Apollo204/summary.pdf|archivedate=May 14, 2016|dead-url=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|5-8}} Assigned emergency roles called for Grissom, in the left-hand seat, to open the cabin pressure vent valve, after which White in the center seat was to open the [[plug door]] hatch, while Chaffee in the right-hand seat was to maintain communications. Grissom was prevented from opening the valve by the intensity of the fire, which started in that region and spread from left to right. Despite this, White removed his restraints and apparently tried in vain to open the hatch, which was held closed by the cabin pressure. The increasing pressure finally burst the inner cabin wall on the right-hand side at 23:31:19 GMT. After approximately thirty seconds of being fed by a cabin atmosphere of pure [[oxygen]] at pressures of 16.7 to 29 psi, and now fed by nitrogen-buffered ambient air, the primary fire decreased in intensity and started producing large amounts of smoke,&lt;ref name=&quot;aibreport&quot; /&gt;{{rp|5-3–5-4}} which killed the astronauts.&lt;ref name=&quot;aibreport&quot; /&gt;{{rp|6-1}} Failed oxygen and [[ethylene glycol]] pipes near the fire's origin point continued burning an intense secondary fire which melted through the cabin floor.&lt;ref name=&quot;aibreport&quot; /&gt;{{rp|5–4}} By the time firefighters were able to open the hatch, the fire had extinguished itself. The back of Chaffee's couch was found in the horizontal position, with the lower portion angled towards the floor. His helmet was closed and locked, his restraints were undone, and the hoses and electrical connections to the suit remained connected.&lt;ref name=&quot;aibreport&quot; /&gt;{{rp|4-7}} As he was farthest from the origin of the fire, he suffered the least amount of burns and suit damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;aibreport&quot; /&gt;{{rp|5-3}}

====Aftermath====

Shortly after the AS-204 fire in 1967, NASA Associate Administrator for Manned Spaceflight Dr. George Mueller announced the mission would be officially designated as Apollo 1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/missions/apollo1.html|title=Apollo 1|date=June 14, 2012|access-date=September 19, 2016|website=NASA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chaffee and Grissom are both buried in Section 3 of [[Arlington National Cemetery]], while White is buried at [[West Point Cemetery]].&lt;ref name=arlington /&gt;&lt;ref name=westpoint&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usma.edu/history/siteassets/sitepages/cemetery/west%20point%20cemetery.pdf|title=Cemetery Map|access-date=September 19, 2016|website=United States Military Academy}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Apollo 1 KSC Mirror.jpg|right|thumb|Chaffee's name, along with Grissom's and White's, on the Space Mirror Memorial]]
Chaffee was memorialized in many ways, from [[Chaffee (crater)|Chaffee Crater]] on the [[Far side of the Moon|far side]] of the [[Moon]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Far Side of the Moon: A Photographic Guide|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Wm7fspWpJBAC&amp;lpg=PT41&amp;dq=chaffee%20crater%20moon&amp;pg=PT41#v=onepage&amp;q=chaffee%20crater%20moon&amp;f=false|last1=Byrne|first1=Charles|isbn=9780387732060|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|date=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|66}} to [[Roger B. Chaffee Planetarium]] located in his hometown of Grand Rapids, Michigan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grpm.org/explore/planetarium/|title=Chaffee Planetarium|access-date=September 19, 2016|website=Grand Rapids Public Museum}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Roger B. Chaffee scholarship named for Chaffee has been awarded annually since 1967 to exceptional students in the Kent Intermediate School District for high school seniors who will be pursuing a career in math and science.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rogerbchaffeescholarship.org/|title=Roger B. Chaffee Scholarship Fund|access-date=September 19, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chaffee Hall, an engineering building, was dedicated to him at his alma mater, Purdue University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Zucrow Laboratories History|url=https://engineering.purdue.edu/Zucrow/about-us/history|publisher=[[Purdue University]]|accessdate=October 3, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another memorial is a hill on [[Mars]], Chaffee Hill, 14.3&amp;nbsp;km (8.9&amp;nbsp;mi) south-southwest of [[Columbia Memorial Station]], part of the [[Apollo 1 Hills]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Martian Landmarks Dedicated to Apollo 1 Crew|url=http://mars.nasa.gov/mer/newsroom/pressreleases/20040127b.html|date=January 27, 2004|access-date=September 20, 2016|website=Jet Propulsion Laboratory California Institute of Technology}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dismantled [[Cape Canaveral Air Force Station Launch Complex 34|Launch Pad 34]] at [[Cape Canaveral]] bears two memorial plaques: One says, ''They gave their lives in service to their country in the ongoing exploration of humankind's final frontier. Remember them not for how they died but for those ideals for which they lived.'' and the other, ''In memory of those who made the ultimate sacrifice so others could reach for the stars. Ad astra per aspera, (a rough road leads to the stars). God speed to the crew of Apollo 1.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cmgww.com/historic/white/about/biography.html|website=The Official Site of Edward White, II|title=Biography|access-date=June 21, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Gallery
|title=Launch Complex 34 Plaques
|width=300| height=170
|align=center
|footer=
|File:Apollo1plaque.JPG
 |alt1=Launch Complex 34 Plaque
 |Plaque inside of structure.
|File:Pad 34 Ad Astra plaque.jpg
 |alt2=Launch Complex 34 Plaque
 |Plaque on right rear column.
}}

==Awards and honors==
*Navy [[Air Medal]], for his involvement in Heavy Photographic Squadron 62.&lt;ref name=navyhistory /&gt;
*Inducted into the [[New Mexico Museum of Space History|International Space Hall of Fame]], in 1983.&lt;ref name=newmexico/&gt;
*Inducted into the [[United States Astronaut Hall of Fame|U.S. Astronaut Hall of Fame]], on October 4, 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://astronautscholarship.org/Astronauts/roger-b-chaffee/|title=Roger B. Chaffee |website=Astronaut Scholarship Foundation|access-date=June 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*NASA Ambassador of Exploration Award for involvement in the U.S. space program, 2007 (posthumous).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=October 4, 2007|first=Yvette |last=Smith |url=http://www.nasa.gov/vision/space/features/chaffee_ambassador_of_exploration.html |title=NASA Honors Roger Chaffee With Exploration Award|website=NASA|access-date=June 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Navy [[Air Medal]] (posthumous, his second).&lt;ref name=navyhistory /&gt;&lt;ref name = navalhist /&gt;
*[[Congressional Space Medal of Honor]], 1997 (posthumous).&lt;ref name=cspan&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.c-spanvideo.org/program/SpaceMed|title=Congressional Space Medal of Honor|website=C-SPAN|date=December 17, 1997|access-date=June 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|United States Navy}}
*[[Fallen Astronaut]]
*[[List of Eagle Scouts]]
*[[List of spaceflight-related accidents and incidents]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Roger Bruce Chaffee}}
*[http://www.shapell.org/manuscript.aspx?lbj-apollo-death Lyndon Johnson Condolence letter to Chaffee Family] Shapell Manuscript Foundation
*[http://www.astronautix.com/astros/chaffee.htm Astronautix biography of Roger B. Chaffee]

{{Congressional Space Medal of Honor}}
{{NASA Astronaut Group 3|state=autocollapse}}
{{US Navy navbox}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chaffee, Roger B.}}
[[Category:1935 births]]
[[Category:1967 deaths]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in Florida]]
[[Category:American aerospace engineers]]
[[Category:American astronauts]]
[[Category:American aviators]]
[[Category:American test pilots]]
[[Category:Aviators from Michigan]]
[[Category:Apollo program astronauts]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]
[[Category:Deaths by smoke inhalation]]
[[Category:Eagle Scouts]]
[[Category:People from Grand Rapids, Michigan]]
[[Category:Illinois Institute of Technology alumni]]
[[Category:Purdue University alumni]]
[[Category:Air Force Institute of Technology alumni]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Air Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Congressional Space Medal of Honor]]
[[Category:Recipients of the NASA Exceptional Service Medal]]
[[Category:Space program fatalities]]
[[Category:United States Astronaut Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:United States Naval Aviators]]
[[Category:United States Navy astronauts]]
[[Category:United States Navy officers]]
[[Category:Tau Beta Pi]]</text>
      <sha1>ast7e4e19ukihprojc0ftytkuk6xjl4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
