<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Run for Tunis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22368641</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747614103</id>
      <parentid>743231358</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T10:38:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Speedily moving category Tunisia Campaign to [[:Category:Tunisian Campaign]] per [[WP:CFDS|CFDS]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22335">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=The Run for Tunis
|partof=the [[Tunisia Campaign]] of [[World War II]]
|image=[[File:Tunisia25Novto10Dec1942.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Tunisia 25 November – 10 December 1942
|date=10 November–25 December 1942
|place=[[Tunisia]]
|coordinates = {{Coord|34|N|09|E|display=INLINE,title}}
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Axis victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Free France}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Kenneth Arthur Noel Anderson|Kenneth Anderson]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Vyvyan Evelegh]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Walther Nehring]]
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
|campaignbox = 
{{Campaignbox Tunisia Campaign}}
{{Campaignbox North Africa}}
{{Campaignbox Free French}}
}}
The '''Run for Tunis''' was part of the [[Tunisia Campaign]] which took place during November and December 1942 during [[World War II]]. Once [[Vichy France|French]] opposition to the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[Operation Torch]] landings had ceased in mid-November, the Allies made a rapid advance by a [[Division (military)|division]]-sized force east from [[Algeria]], to capture [[Tunis]] and forestall an [[Axis powers|Axis]] build up in [[Tunisia]] and narrowly failed. Some Allied troops were fewer than {{convert|20|mi|km}} short of Tunis by late November but the defenders counter-attacked and pushed them back nearly {{convert|20|mi|km}}, to positions which had stabilised by the end of the year.

==Background==

===Allies===
The planners of Operation Torch had assumed that Vichy would oppose the landings and the invasion convoys had a preponderance of infantry to meet ground opposition. At Algiers the disembarkation of mobile forces for an advance did not commence until 12 November, making an advance eastwards possible only by 15 November.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, pp. 472–473, 497&lt;/ref&gt; The Allies had only two infantry brigade groups from the British  [[78th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|78th Infantry Division]] ([[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Vyvyan Evelegh]]), an armoured regimental group from the British  [[6th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|6th Armoured Division]] (Blade Force) and some additional artillery for an advance. An attempt to reach Bizerta and Tunis overland before the Axis could establish themselves, was a gamble which depended on the ability of the navy and air force to delay an Axis build-up.&lt;ref name=&quot;Playfair239&quot;&gt;Playfair, p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|After the event, Anderson and Cunningham, the naval commander, expressed the view that without landings east of Algiers, the race for Tunis was lost before it started.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, p. 492&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Axis===
Although the Allies planned for determined Vichy opposition to the Torch landings they underestimated the speed with which the Axis could reinforce Tunisia.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, p. 487&lt;/ref&gt; Despite intelligence reports regarding the Axis reaction, the Allies were slow to respond and it was not until nearly two weeks after the landings that air and naval plans were made to interdict Axis sea transport to Tunis.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, p. 493&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of November, naval [[Force K]] was reformed in Malta, with three cruisers and four destroyers and Force Q was formed in Bône with three cruisers and two destroyers. No Axis ships sailing to Tunis were sunk in November but the Allied navies sank seven Axis transports in early December. The success was too late because the tanks of the 10th ''Panzer'' Division had arrived. Axis convoys began to sail in daylight when they could be protected by aircraft. Night convoys resumed on completion of the extension of Axis minefields which severely restricted Force K and Force Q.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, pp. 495–496&lt;/ref&gt;

===Vichy===
Tunisian officials were undecided about whom to support and airfields were left open to both sides; on 9 November, reconnaissance flights reported that forty German aircraft had landed at Tunis and next day British photographic reconnaissance showed around 100 German aircraft there.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; That day the {{lang|it|''Regia Aeronautica''}} (Italian Air Force) sent 28 fighters to Tunis and two days later an airlift began which eventually carried 15,000 men and {{convert|581|ST|t|lk=on|abbr=on}} of supplies; ships brought 176 tanks, 131 guns, 1,152 vehicles and {{convert|13000|ST|t|abbr=on}} of supplies. By the end of the month, three German divisions, including the [[10th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|10th ''Panzer'' Division]] (Major-General [[Wolfgang Fischer]]) and two Italian infantry divisions had arrived. On 12 November, [[Walther Nehring]] was appointed to the new [[German XC Corps|XC Corps]] and arrived on 17 November. The French commander in Tunisia, General Barré, moved the Vichy troops into the mountains and formed a defensive line from Tebersouk through [[Majaz al Bab]] (also referred to as Medjez el Bab), with orders to resist an attempt to cross.&lt;ref name=&quot;Watson60&quot;&gt;Watson (2007), p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==

===Vichy Armistice===
By 10 November, French opposition to the Torch landings had ceased, creating a military vacuum in Tunisia.&lt;ref name= &quot;Despatch5450&quot;&gt;Anderson (1946), p. 2 {{LondonGazette|issue=37779|supp=yes|startpage=5450|endapage=| date=5 November 1946|accessdate=2008-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 November, Lieutenant-General [[Kenneth Arthur Noel Anderson|Kenneth Anderson]] took command of the Eastern Task Force in Algiers, which was renamed the [[First Army (United Kingdom)|British First Army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Playfair, p. 153&quot;&gt;Playfair, p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt; Anderson ordered troops eastward to seize the ports of Bougie, Philippeville and Bône and the airfield at Djedjelli, preliminary to advancing into Tunisia. Allied planners had ruled out an assault landing in Tunisia, because of a lack of troops and the threat from the air; the Allies needed to advance before the Axis could reinforce Tunis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Despatch5450&quot;/&gt; On 11 November, the [[36th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|British 36th Infantry Brigade]] had landed unopposed at Bougie but supply difficulties meant Djedjelli was only reached by road on 13 November.&lt;ref name=&quot;Despatch5450&quot;/&gt; Bône airfield was occupied following a parachute drop by 3rd Parachute Battalion and this was followed up on 12 November by No. 6 Commando seizing the port.&lt;ref name=&quot;Despatch5452&quot;&gt;Anderson (1946), p. 4 {{LondonGazette|issue=37779|supp=yes|startpage=5452|endapage=|date=5 November 1946|accessdate=2008-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Advanced guards of 36th Brigade reached Tebarka on 15 November and Djebel Abiod on 18 November where they made first contact with opposition forces.&lt;ref name= &quot;Despatch5453&quot;&gt;Anderson (1946), p. 5 {{LondonGazette|issue=37779|supp=yes|startpage=5453|endapage=| date=5 November 1946|accessdate=2008-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further south, on 15 November, [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] [[paratrooper]]s of the [[509th Infantry Regiment (United States)|509th Parachute Infantry Battalion]] made an unopposed drop on [[Youks-les-Bains Airfield|Youks-les-Bains]], captured the airfield and took the airfield at Gafsa on 17 November.&lt;ref name=&quot;Despatch5453&quot;/&gt; On 19 November, General Nehring demanded passage for his forces across the bridge at Medjez and was refused by Barré. The Germans attacked twice and were repulsed but the French defence was costly and lacking armour and artillery, the French withdrew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Watson60&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Despatch5453&quot;/&gt; Despite some Vichy French forces siding with the Allies, the position of most Vichy forces was uncertain. On 22 November, the [[North African Agreement]] placed Vichy French North Africa on the Allied side and Allied garrison troops were released for the front; the Axis had been reinforced to a corps and outnumbered the Allies.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1966, pp. 162–163, 170–173&lt;/ref&gt;

===Plan===
There were two roads eastwards into Tunisia from Algeria. The Allied plan was to advance along the two roads and take [[Bizerte]] and [[Tunis]]. Once Bizerte was taken Torch would come to an end. Attacking in the north toward Bizerte would be the 36th Infantry Brigade of the 78th Infantry Division, supported by &quot;Hart Force&quot;, a small mobile detachment from the [[11th Infantry Brigade and Headquarters South East|British 11th Infantry Brigade]] and to the south the rest of the 11th Infantry Brigade.&lt;ref name= &quot;Playfair, p. 153&quot;/&gt; On their left was [[Blade Force]] (Colonel [[Richard Amyatt Hull|Richard Hull]]), an armoured regimental group which included the tanks of the [[17th/21st Lancers]], a U.S. light tank battalion plus motorised infantry, paratroops, artillery, anti-tank and anti-aircraft guns and engineers.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), p.15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Watson (2007), p.61&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Allied attack===
[[File:Tunisia1942-1943.svg|thumb|upright=1.5|Sketch map of Tunisia during the 1942–1943 campaign]]
The two Allied columns advanced towards Djebel Abiod and Beja, under attack from the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'', which had local [[air superiority]], because Allied aircraft had to fly from distant bases in Algeria.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; On the northern road, the leading elements of the 36th Brigade made rapid progress until 17 November, when they met a mixed force of 17 tanks, 400 paratroops and self-propelled guns at Djebel Abiod. The British knocked out eleven tanks but having no tank support, were held up for nine days.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, pp. 497–498&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), pp. 19–22&lt;/ref&gt; The Allied columns concentrated at Djebel Abiod and Beja, preparing for an assault on 24 November. The 36th Brigade (Brigadier A.L. Kent-Lemon) was to advance from Djebel Abiod towards Mateur and 11th Brigade was to move down the valley of the river Merjerda, to take Majaz al Bab (also Medjez el Bab or Medjez) and thence to [[Tebourba]], [[Djedeida]] and Tunis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ford 1999, p. 23&quot;&gt;Ford (1999), p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

Blade Force was to strike across country on minor roads, in the gap between the two infantry brigades, towards Sidi Nsir and make flanking attacks on Terbourba and Djedeida.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ford 1999, p. 23&quot;/&gt; The northern attack was cancelled because of torrential rain and in the south, the 11th Infantry Brigade was stopped by the defenders of Medjez. Blade Force passed through Sidi Nsir, to reach the Chouigui Pass north of Terbourba, then Company C, 1st Battalion, 1st Armored Regiment, [[1st Armored Division (United States)|U.S. 1st Armored Division]] (Major Rudolph Barlow) with 17 [[M3 Stuart]] [[light tank]]s, supported by armoured cars of the [[Derbyshire Yeomanry]], infiltrated behind Axis lines to an airbase at Djedeida in the afternoon. The Allied tanks destroyed more than twenty Axis aeroplanes, shot up buildings, supply dumps and caused several casualties; lacking infantry support, the raiders withdrew to Chouigui.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), pp. 23–25&lt;/ref&gt;

The surprise achieved by Blade Force alerted Nehring to the vulnerability of garrison at Medjez to a flanking move and the defenders were  withdrawn to Djedeida, only {{convert|30|km|mi|abbr=on}} from Tunis.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), p.25&lt;/ref&gt; The 36th Infantry Brigade attack began on 26 November but Nehring used the delay at Djebel Abiod, to lay an ambush at Jefna on the road from Sedjenane and Mateur. The Germans occupied high ground on either side of the road, which after heavy rain was very muddy and the ground on either side impassable for vehicles; the leading British battalion had 149 casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; Kent-Lemon sent units into the hills to outflank the Germans but the determined defence of the paratroopers in well-laid out defences could not be overcome. A landing by [[No. 1 Commando]] {{convert|14|mi|km|abbr=on}} west of Bizerta on 30 November to outflank the Jefna position failed; the commandos rejoined 36th Brigade by 3 December and the position remained in German hands, until the last days of the fighting in Tunisia in 1943.&lt;ref name= &quot;Despatch5453&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), p. 40&lt;/ref&gt;

===German retirement===
Early on 26 November, the 11th Infantry Brigade entered Medjez unopposed, reached Tebourba unopposed, ready to advance on Djedeida. Next day, the Germans attacked, inflicted 137 casualties and took 286 prisoners. The brigade attacked again on 28 November towards Djedeida airfield and [[Combat command|Combat Command]] &quot;B&quot;, 1st US Armored Division, lost 19 tanks to anti-tank guns in the town.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), pp. 37–38&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 November, fresh units of the [[1st Armoured Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Guards Brigade]] (78th Infantry Division), which had arrived at Algiers on 22 November, began to relieve the 11th Infantry Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 November, Combat Command &quot;B&quot; had assembled to attack with Blade Force on 2 December. The [[2nd Battalion, Parachute Regiment|2nd Battalion]], [[Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)|Parachute Regiment]] ([[Lieutenant colonel (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-Colonel]] [[John Frost (British Army officer)|John Frost]]) was to be dropped in Operation Oudna on 3 December, near Axis airfields around Depienne {{convert|30|mi|km|abbr=on}} south of Tunis, to destroy [[Junkers Ju 87|''Stuka'']] [[dive bomber]]s and to threaten Tunis from the south. The main attack was forestalled by an Axis counter-attack on 1 December and the attack by Blade Force did not take place; the 2nd Battalion retreated {{convert|50|mi|km}} to Allied lines under frequent attack and lost 23 killed and wounded and 266 missing.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1966, p. 177&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Despatch5454&quot;&gt;Anderson (1946), p. 6 {{LondonGazette|issue=37779|supp=yes|startpage=5454|endpage=|date=5 November 1946| accessdate=2008-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Axis counter-attack was conducted by the 10th ''Panzer'' Division, which had just arrived in Tunisia, from the north toward Tebourba.&lt;ref&gt;Watson (2007), pp. 62–63&lt;/ref&gt; Blade Force suffered considerable casualties and by the evening of 2 December, had been withdrawn, leaving the 11th Infantry Brigade and Combat Command &quot;B&quot; to resist the Axis attack, which nearly cut off the brigade and broke through.&lt;ref name=&quot;Despatch5454&quot;/&gt; Desperate fighting by 2nd Battalion, [[Royal Hampshire Regiment|Hampshire Regiment]] (1st Guards Brigade) and the 1st Battalion, [[East Surrey Regiment]] for four days delayed the Axis advance and with the fight of Combat Command &quot;B&quot; against armoured and infantry attacks from the south-east, enabled a slow retirement to high ground on each side of the river west of Terbourba. The Hampshires suffered 75 percent casualties and the Surreys nearly 60 percent casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), pp. 50, 47&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Watson (2007), p. 63&lt;/ref&gt;

As more Allied troops arrived, the [[V Corps (United Kingdom)|V Corps]] ([[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Charles Walter Allfrey]]) of the First Army took command all forces in the Tebourba sector, which included the 6th Armoured Division, 78th Infantry Division, Combat Command B from US 1st Armored Division, [[1st Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Parachute Brigade]], [[No. 1 Commando|1]] and [[No. 6 Commando|6 Commandos]].&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt; Allfrey considered the depleted units facing Tebourba were vulnerable and ordered a retirement of about {{convert|6|mi|km|abbr=on}} to the high ground of Longstop Hill (djebel el Ahmera) {{convert|900|ft|m|abbr=on}} high and Bou Aoukaz on either side of the river. On 10 December, Axis tanks attacked Combat Command &quot;B&quot; on Bou Aoukaz, bogged in the mud and then U.S. tanks counter-attacked and also mired and were picked off, losing 18 tanks.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), p. 51&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Allfrey ordered another withdrawal and by the end of 10 December, Allied units held a defensive line just east of Medjez el Bab. The Allied defeats in December were costly, with thousands of casualties, 173 tanks, 432 other vehicles and 170 artillery pieces lost.--&gt;

===Subsequent operations===
Another Allied attack was ready by late December 1942, when the Allied force comprised 54,000 British, 73,800 American and 7,000 French troops. A hasty intelligence review showed about 125,000 combat and 70,000 service troops, mostly Italian, in front of them. On the night of 16/17 December, a company of the [[1st Infantry Division (United States)|1st US Infantry Division]] raided Maknassy, {{convert|155|mi|km|abbr=on}} south of Tunis and took 21 German prisoners. The main attack began the afternoon of 22 December, despite rain and insufficient air cover; elements of the [[18th Infantry Regiment (United States)|18th Regimental Combat Team]], 1st Infantry Division (18th RCT) and the 78th Division 2nd Battalion, [[Coldstream Guards]] of the 1st Guards Brigade made progress up the lower ridges of Longstop Hill that dominated the river corridor from Medjez to Tebourba and thence to Tunis. By the morning of 23 December, the Coldstreams had driven back units of the 10th ''Panzer'' Division on the summit, been relieved by the 18th RCT and withdrawn to Mejdez. The Germans regained the hill in a counter-attack, the Coldstreams were ordered back and next day regained the peak and dug-in with the 18th RCT. By 25 December, ammunition running low and Axis forces holding adjacent high ground, the Longstop position became untenable and the Allies were forced to withdraw to Medjez.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (1999), pp. 53–54&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--By 26 December, the Allies had withdrawn to the line they had set out from two weeks earlier, having suffered 20,743 casualties. Can't find a citation--&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II}}
* [[North African Campaign timeline]]
* [[List of World War II Battles]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal |last=Anderson |first=Lt.-General Kenneth |author-link=Kenneth Arthur Noel Anderson |year=1946 |title=Official despatch by Kenneth Anderson, GOC-in-C [[First Army (United Kingdom)|First Army]] covering events in NW Africa, 8 November 1942 – 13 May 1943 |publisher=London Gazette |location=London |issn=0374-3721}} published in published in {{LondonGazette |issue=37779 |supp=yes |startpage=5449 |endpage=5464 |date=5 November 1946 |accessdate=2008-04-23}}
* {{cite book |title=Battleaxe Division |first=Ken |last=Ford |year=1999 |publisher=Sutton Publishing |location=Stroud (UK) |isbn=0-7509-1893-4}}
* {{cite book |last1=Hinsley |first1=F. H. |last2=Thomas |first2=E. E. |last3=Ransom |first3=C. F. G.|last4=Knight |first4=R. C. |authorlink1=Harry Hinsley |title=British Intelligence in the Second World War, its influence on Strategy and Operations |volume=II |location=London |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1981 |isbn=0-11-630934-2}}
* {{cite book |first1=Major-General I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |authorlink1=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |last3=Flynn |first3=Captain F. C. (RN) |last2=Molony |first2=Brigadier C. J. C. |last4=Gleave |first4=Group Captain T. P. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=Sir James |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: The Destruction of the Axis Forces in Africa |volume=IV |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield, UK |year=2004 |orig-year=1st. pub. [[HMSO]]:1966 |isbn=1-84574-068-8 |lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book |last=Watson |first=Bruce Allen |title=Exit Rommel: The Tunisian Campaign, 1942–43 |location=Mechanicsburg, PA |publisher=Stackpole |year=2007 |series=Stackpole Military History |orig-year=1999 |isbn=978-0-8117-3381-6}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |first=Charles R. |last=Anderson |url=http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/tunisia/tunisia.htm |title=Tunisia 17 November 1942 to 13 May 1943 |series=WWII Campaigns |publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |id=CMH Pub 72-12}}
* {{cite book |first=Rick |last=Atkinson |authorlink=Rick Atkinson |title=An Army at Dawn: The War in North Africa, 1942–1943 |year=2003 |location=London |publisher=Little, Brown |isbn=0-349-11636-9}}
* {{cite book |first=Eddy |last=Bauer |editor-last=Young |editor-first=Peter |title=The History of World War II |location=London |publisher=Orbis Publishing |edition=rev. |year=2000 |orig-year=1979 |isbn=1-85605-552-3}}
* {{cite book |first=Gregory |last=Blaxland |title=The Plain Cook and the Great Showman: the First and Eighth Armies in North Africa |year=1977 |publisher=Kimber |location=London |isbn=0-7183-0185-4}}
* {{cite book |first1=Ceva |last1=Lucio |editor-first=John |editor-last=Gooch |title=Decisive Campaigns of the Second World War |chapter=The North African Campaign 1940–43: A Reconsideration |year=1990 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=0-7146-3369-0}}
* {{cite book |first=Richard |last=Mead |title=Churchill's Lions: A biographical guide to the key British Generals of World War II |year=2007 |publisher=Spellmount |location=Stroud (UK) |isbn= 978-1-86227-431-0}}
* {{cite book |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/bizerte/bizerte-fm.htm |series=American Forces in Action |title=To Bizerte with the II Corps 23 April to 13 May 1943 |publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |orig-year=1943 |year=1990 |id=CMH Pub 100-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Tunisia in World War II|Run for Tunis}}
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/II/AAF-II-3.html The Army Air Forces in WWII August 1942 – December 1943, Craven, W. F. &amp; Cate, J. L.]
* [http://www.wwii-photos-maps.com/alliedmiscellaneousmaps/North%20Africa%20and%20Italy/index.html WWII Aerial Photos and Maps]
* [http://www.history.army.mil/books/Staff-Rides/kasserine/Maps_Sketches.pdf Kasserine Pass Battles, Maps and Sketches, US Army]

{{World War II}}

[[Category:Tunisian Campaign]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving the United States|Tunis]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy|Tunis]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States|Tunis]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany|Tunis]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|Tunis]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France|Tunis]]
[[Category:German military occupations]]
[[Category:World War II occupied territories]]</text>
      <sha1>h5stfx0eq9q8bkqdym7d2szlqpnk8q5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
