<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sam Manekshaw</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1704980</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751327830</id>
      <parentid>751270937</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-24T22:57:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peacemaker67</username>
        <id>15690513</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Training at the Indian Military Academy */ dropped Sir</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40085">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2016}}
{{Use Indian English|date=June 2016}}
{{Infobox military person
|honorific_prefix= [[Field marshal (India)|Field Marshal]]
|name=S H F J Manekshaw
|honorific_suffix= [[Military Cross|MC]]
|image= Field Marshal Sam Manekshaw.jpg
|caption=Field Marshal Sam Manekshaw&lt;br&gt;(pictured wearing general's insignia c. 1970)
|birth_date={{Birth date|df=yes|1914|04|03}}
|death_date={{Death date and age|df=yes|2008|06|27|1914|4|03}}
|birth_place=[[Amritsar]], [[Punjab (British India)|Punjab]], [[British Raj|British India]]
|death_place= [[Wellington, Tamil Nadu|Wellington]], [[Tamil Nadu]]
|nickname=Sam Bahadur
|spouse=Silloo Bode
|allegiance= {{plainlist|
*[[British India]]
*India}}
|branch={{plainlist|
*[[British Indian Army]]
*[[Indian Army]]
}}
|serviceyears=1934–2008{{efn|Indian military [[five-star rank]] officers hold their rank for life, and are considered to be serving officers until their deaths.&lt;ref name=&quot;Did You Know That Only 3 People Have Been Given The Highest Ranks In The Indian Armed Forces?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author1=Anwesha Madhukalya|title=Did You Know That Only 3 People Have Been Given The Highest Ranks In The Indian Armed Forces?|url=https://www.scoopwhoop.com/Highest-ranks-in-Indian-Armed-Forces/|accessdate=2 August 2016|language=En}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|rank=[[Field marshal (India)|Field Marshal]]
|commands = {{plainlist|[[Eastern Command (India)|Eastern Army]]|[[Western Command (India)|Western Army]]|[[IV Corps (India)|IV Corps]]|[[Defence Services Staff College]]|[[26th Indian Infantry Division|26th Infantry Division]]|[[Mhow#The Infantry School|The Infantry School]]|167 Infantry Brigade|GSO-I, Military Operations Directorate|[[5 Gorkha Rifles]]||[[Royal Scots]]}}
|battles={{plainlist|
*[[World War II]]
*[[Indo-Pakistan War of 1947]]
*[[Sino-Indian War]]
*[[Indo-Pakistan War of 1965]]
*[[Bangladesh Liberation War]]
}}
|awards={{plainlist|
*[[Padma Vibhushan]]
*[[Padma Bhushan]]
*[[Military Cross]]
}}
|relations=
|laterwork=
|signature= Autograph of Manek Shaw.JPG
| office             = [[Chief of Army Staff (India)]]
| term_start         = 8 June 1969
| term_end           = 15 January 1973
| predecessor        = [[Paramasiva Prabhakar Kumaramangalam|General PP Kumaramangalam]]
| successor          = [[Gopal Gurunath Bewoor|General Gopal Gurunath Bewoor]]
}}

[[Field Marshal (India)|Field Marshal]] '''Sam Hormusji Framji Jamshedji Manekshaw''', [[Military Cross|MC]] (3 April 1914&amp;nbsp;– 27 June 2008), popularly known as '''''Sam Bahadur''''' (&quot;Sam the Brave&quot;), was the [[Chief of the Army Staff (India)|Chief of the Army Staff of the Indian Army]] during the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1971]], and was subsequently the first [[Indian Army]] officer to be promoted to the rank of field marshal. His distinguished military career spanned four decades and five wars, beginning with service in the [[British Indian Army]] in [[World War II]].

Though Manekshaw initially thought of pursuing a career as a medical doctor, he later joined the first intake of the [[Indian Military Academy]] (IMA) when it was established in 1932. Right from his days at IMA, he proved to be witty and humorous in nature. He was first attached to the 2nd Battalion of the [[Royal Scots]], and then later posted to the 4th Battalion of the [[12th Frontier Force Regiment]], commonly known as the [[54th Sikhs]]. During action in World War II, he was awarded the Military Cross for gallantry. Following the [[partition of India]] in 1947, he was later reassigned to the [[16th Punjab Regiment]]. Owing to the [[1947 Indo-Pakistani War|Kashmir]] and [[Operation Polo|Hyderabad crisis]], Manekshaw never commanded a battalion, and was promoted to the rank of brigadier while he was at Military Operations Directorate.

Manekshaw rose to become the 8th Chief of Army Staff in 1969, and under his command, Indian forces conducted victorious campaigns against [[Pakistan]] in the Indo-Pakistani War of 1971 that led to the [[Bangladesh Liberation War|creation of Bangladesh]] in December 1971. For his services, he was awarded the [[Padma Vibhushan]] and the [[Padma Bhushan]], the second and third highest civilian awards of India.

==Early life and education==
Manekshaw was born on 3 April 1914 in [[Amritsar]], [[Punjab Province (British India)|Punjab]] to [[Parsi people|Parsi]] parents, Hormusji Manekshaw, a doctor, and his wife Hilla, who moved to Punjab from the city of [[Valsad]] in the coastal [[Gujarat]] region.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=183}}{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=184}}{{Sfn|Sharma|2007|p=59}} Sam's father served in the [[British Indian Army]] as a [[Captain (rank)|captain]] in the [[Army Medical Corps (India)|medical services]] and also participated in [[World War I]].{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=184}} Hormusji and Hilla had six children of which Sam was the fifth one. Fali, Cilla, Jan and Sehroo preceded Sam and Sam was followed Jemi, who later joined the [[Royal Indian Air Force|air force]] as a doctor and was the first Indian to be awarded the air surgeon's wings from [[Naval Air Station Pensacola|Naval Air Station]], [[Pensacola]], United States.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=184}} After completing his schooling in Punjab and [[Sherwood College]], [[Nainital]], and achieving a distinction in the School Certificate of the [[International General Certificate of Secondary Education|Cambridge Board]], an English language curriculum developed by the [[Cambridge International Examinations|University of Cambridge International Examinations]],  at the age of 15, and he asked his father to send him to London to become a gynaecologist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibnlive.com/videos/india/ftn-sam-interview-291841.html Excerpt from his first personal TV interview, hosted at IBN Live]&lt;/ref&gt; But his father refused, stating that he was not old enough.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=185}}

In the meantime, the Indian Military College Committee which was set up in 1931 and chaired by [[Philip Chetwode, 1st Baron Chetwode|Field Marshal Sir Philip Chetwode]] recommended the establishment of a military training academy in India to train Indians for commissioning into the army. A three-year course was proposed with an entry age of 18 to 20 years, candidates would be selected on the basis of an examination conducted by the Public Service Commission.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=185}} After the approval of the committee's recommendation, a formal notification for entrance examination to enrol in the [[Indian Military Academy]] (IMA) was issued in the early months of 1932 with the examination to be conducted in the months of June or July.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=186}}

In an act of rebellion against his father's refusal, Manekshaw took the examination for enrolment into the academy, and was one of the fifteen cadets to be selected through open competition.{{efn|There were 40 vacancies, of which 15 were filled through open competition, 15 from the army and remaining 10 from the state forces.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=186}}}} He stood sixth in the order of merit.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=186}}

===Training at the Indian Military Academy===
Although the academy was formally inaugurated on 10 December 1932 by Chetwode,{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=186}} formal military training for the cadets commenced from 1 October 1932. After being selected into the first batch of the academy—called the &quot;The Pioneers&quot;, which produced three future chiefs—Manekshaw (India), [[Smith Dun]] (Burma) and [[Muhammad Musa]] (Pakistan). Manekshaw proved to be witty during his stay at the academy and had many firsts to his credit. He was the first of the alumni to join the [[Gorkha regiments (India)|Gorkha Regiment]] and later the first to serve as the Chief of the Army Staff of India and attain the rank of field marshal.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=186}} Of the 40 cadets inducted, only 22 were able to complete the course and were commissioned as [[second lieutenant]]s on 1 February 1935 with their anté-date seniority fixed as 4 February 1934.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=188–189}}

==Military career==
On commissioning, as per the practices of that time, Manekshaw was first attached to the 2nd Battalion, The [[Royal Scots]], a British battalion, and was later posted to the 4th Battalion, [[12th Frontier Force Regiment]], commonly known as the [[54th Sikhs (Frontier Force)|54th Sikhs]].{{Sfn|Singh|2002|p=237–259}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/jun/30/india Obituary—Field Marshal Sam Manekshaw]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/Opinion/Columnists/Tarun_Vijay/The_Right_View/Saluting_Sam_Bahadur/articleshow/msid-3179920,curpg-1.cms| title=Saluting Sam Bahadur| author=Tarun|accessdate=8 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War II===
During World War II, the then-Captain Manekshaw saw action in [[Burma Campaign|Burma]] in the 1942 campaign on the [[Battle of Sittang Bridge|Sittang River]] with the 4th Battalion, 12 Frontier Force Regiment,{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=190}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackenzie&quot;&gt;Compton Mackenzie (1951), ''Eastern Epic'', Chatto &amp; Windus, London, pp. 440–1&lt;/ref&gt; and had the rare distinction of being honoured for his bravery on the battlefield. During the fighting around Pagoda Hill, a key position on the left of the Sittang bridgehead, he led his company in a counter-attack against the invading [[Imperial Japanese Army|Japanese Army]] and despite suffering 50% casualties the company managed to achieve its objective. After capturing the hill, Manekshaw was hit by a burst of [[light machine gun]] fire and was severely wounded in the stomach.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2008-06-27/india/27752774_1_manekshaw-field-marshal-sam-bahadur Sam Bahadur: A soldier's general], [[Times of India]], 27 June 2008.  Retrieved 30 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Observing the battle, Major General [[David Tennent Cowan|David Cowan]], the then commander of the [[17th Infantry Division (India)|17th Infantry Division]], spotted Manekshaw holding on to life and, having witnessed his valour in the face of stiff resistance, rushed over to him. Fearing that Manekshaw would die, the general pinned his own Military Cross ribbon to Manekshaw saying, &quot;A dead person cannot be awarded a [[Military Cross]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackenzie&quot;/&gt;{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=191}}  The official recommendation for the MC states that the success of the attack &quot;was largely due to the excellent leadership and bearing of Captain Manekshaw&quot;. This award was made official with the publication of the notification in a supplement to the ''[[London Gazette]]'' on 21 April 1942 (dated 23 April 1942).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/ London Gazette], [http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/35532/pages/1797 Issue 35532, pg 1797] (date 21 April 1942). Accessed on 3 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documentsonline/details-result.asp?Edoc_Id=7659368&amp;queryType=1&amp;resultcount=1 Recommendations for Honours and Awards (Army)—Image details—Manekshaw, Sam Hormuzji Franji Jamshadji], Documents online, [[The National Archives (United Kingdom)|The National Archives]] (fee required to view pdf of original citation).  Retrieved 30 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Manekshaw was evacuated to [[Rangoon]] and on arrival was close to death, having been hit by seven bullets in his lungs, liver and kidneys. It was Sher Singh, his orderly, who evacuated him from the battlefield. When the surgeon asked what had happened to him, he replied that he was &quot;kicked by a mule&quot;. Over Manekshaw's protests to treat the other patients, the regimental medical officer, Captain G M Diwan, attended to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;EconObit&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Obituary: Sam Manekshaw |url=http://www.economist.com/obituary/displayStory.cfm?story_id=11661408 |journal=The Economist |issue=5 July 2008 |accessdate=7 July 2008|page=107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tarun (2008), [http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/Opinion/Columnists/Tarun_Vijay/The_Right_View/Saluting_Sam_Bahadur/articleshow/msid-3179920,curpg-2.cms p. 2]&lt;/ref&gt;

Having recovered from his wounds, Manekshaw attended the 8th Staff Course at [[Command and Staff College]], [[Quetta]], from 23 August to 22 December 1943. He was then posted as the [[brigade major]] of the [[Razmak Brigade]], serving in that post until 22 October 1944 when he was sent to join the 9th Battalion, 12 Frontier Force Regiment in Burma, as part of General [[William Slim, 1st Viscount Slim|William Slim]]'s [[British Fourteenth Army|14th Army]].{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=191}}  &lt;!--He was once again involved in a fierce battle with the Japanese, and was wounded for a second time.(No ref available)--&gt; Towards the end of World War II, Manekshaw was sent to serve on General Daisy's staff in [[Indo-China]] where, after the [[Surrender of Japan|Japanese surrender]], he helped repatriate over 10,000 former [[prisoners of war]] (POWs). He then went on a six-month lecture tour to Australia in 1946, and after his return was promoted to the rank of [[lieutenant-colonel]], serving as a first grade staff officer in the Military Operations Directorate.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=192}}
===Post-independence===
{{under construction|section=yes|placed by={{u|Krishna Chaitanya Velaga}}|comment=The section is being expanded to meet the GA criteria. Please be patient till 25 November 2016. Regards, [[User:Krishna Chaitanya Velaga|Krishna Chaitanya Velaga]] ([[User talk:Krishna Chaitanya Velaga|talk]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull;&amp;#32;[[Special:EmailUser/Krishna Chaitanya Velaga|mail]]) 15:00, 23 November 2016 (UTC)}}
Upon the [[Partition of India]] in 1947, his parent unit – the 4/12 Frontier Force Regiment – became part of the Pakistan Army (re-designated as the 6 Frontier Force Regiment in 1956), and so Manekshaw was reassigned to the 16th Punjab Regiment. While handling the issues relating to Partition in 1947, Manekshaw demonstrated his sound planning and administrative skills, and later was able put his battle skills to use during operations in [[First Kashmir War|Jammu &amp; Kashmir]] in 1947–48.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title='Jawaharlal, do you want Kashmir, or do you want to give it away?'|url=http://kashmirsentinel.org/jawaharlal-do-you-want-kashmir-or-do-you-want-to-give-it-away/|website=Kashmir Sentinel|accessdate=23 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 1947, Sam was posted as the commanding officer of 3/5 Gorkha Rifles. But before he moved onto his new appointment, on 22 October, Pakistanis infiltrated Kashmir, capturing Domel and [[Muzaffarabad]]. The following day, the ruler of Jammu &amp; Kashmir [[princely state]], [[Hari Singh|Maharaja Hari Singh]], appeal to India to send troops. But Indian government reverted that they would send troops only if they were ready to accede to India. On 25th, [[V. P. Menon]] along with Manekshaw flew to Srinagar, with the [[Instrument of Accession]]. While Menon was with the Maharaja, Sam carried out aerial survey of the situation in Kashmir. After the Maharaja had signed the document, they went flew back to Delhi, the same night. Soon a briefing was held with [[Lord Mountbatten]] and [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], where Manekshaw suggested immediate deployments of troops to save Kashmir from being captured.{{Sfn|Singh|2007|pp=193–197}}

Though Nehru initially was not in favour of deployment of troops, he was persuaded by [[Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel]]. On the morning of 27 October, Indian troops were sent to Kashmir, and in the right time Srinagar was saved. Maneskhaw's posting order as the commander of 3/5 Gorkha Rifles was cancelled, subsequently posted to the Military Operations (MO) Directorate. Incidentally, owing the Kashmir and [[Operation Polo|Hyderabad crisis]], Manekshaw never commanded a battalion. During his term at the MO Directorate, he was promoted to colonel, and brigadier on being appointed as the Director of Military Operations, becoming the first Indian Director of Military Operations.{{Sfn|Singh|2007|pp=193–197}} The appointment of Director of Military Operations was later upgraded to [[major general]] and later to [[lieutenant general]] and is now termed Director General Military Operations (DGMO).{{Sfn|Singh|2002|p=8}}

In April 1952, Maneshaw was appointed as the commander of 167 Infantry  Brigade, headquartered as [[Firozpur]]. After commanding an infantry brigade, he was appointed the Director of Military Training at Army HQ in April 1954. But was soon moved to the Infantry School at [[Mhow]] as the school's commandant and also became the colonel of [[8 Gorkha Rifles]] (which became his new regiment, since his original parent regiment, the 12th Frontier Force Regiment, had become part of the new [[Pakistan Army]] at partition) and the [[61st Cavalry (India)|61st Cavalry]]. During his tenure as the Commandant of the Infantry School, he discovered that the training manuals were outdated, and was instrumental in indeginising the manuals on par with the Indian Army's tactics.{{Sfn|Singh|2007|pp=193–197}}

In 1957, he was sent to [[Imperial Defence College]] to attend a higher command course for one year. On his return, he was appointed the General Officer Commanding (GOC), 26 Infantry Division. While he commanded the division, General [[K. S. Thimayya]] was the army chief, and [[Krishna Menon]], the [[Defence Minister of India|Defence Minister]]. During Menon's visit to Manekshaw's division, he inquired what Manekshaw thought of his chief. Manekshaw replied it is the right way to think of his chief, and told Menon to not commit this again. This annoyed Menon and told that if he wants he can sack Thimayya, to which Manekshaw replied, &quot;You can get rid of him. But then I will get another.&quot; This heated conversation with Menon later proved to be a thorn in his later career.{{Sfn|Singh|2007|pp=193–197}}
{{Quote box|width=300px|bgcolor=#E0E6F8|align=left|quote=Mr Minister, I am not allowed to think about him. He is my Chief. Tomorrow, you will be asking my (subordinate) brigadiers and colonels what they think of me. It's the surest way to ruin the discipline of the Army. Don't do it in future.|author=Major General Sam Manekshaw, GOC, 26 Infantry Division|source=&lt;ref name=&quot;Krishna Menon wanted to sack Manekshaw&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Krishna Menon wanted to sack Manekshaw|url=http://www.sunday-guardian.com/investigation/krishna-menon-wanted-to-sack-manekshaw|website=Sunday Guardian|accessdate=23 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;|title='''Manekshaw's reply to Defence Minister Menon, when he inquired what Manekshaw thought of his chief,'''|title_fnt = Arial |tstyle = font size=&quot;25&quot;;}}

In December 1959, Manekshaw was appointed the Commandant, [[Defence Services Staff College]], [[Wellington]]. Soon, he was in middle of an unwanted controversy that almost ended his career. In May 1961, General Thimayya retired as the army chief, and was succeeded by General [[Pran Nath Thapar]]. Earlier year, Major General [[Brij Mohan Kaul]] was promoted to lieutenant general and appointed the Quarter Master General (QMG) by Defence Minister Menon against the recommendation of Thimayya, who was overruled. This incident led to the resignation of Thimayya. Within no time, Kaul was made the Chief of General Staff (CGS), the second highest appointment in the Army HQ after COAS. Kaul soon became close to Nehru and Menon, and even powerful than the chief himself. This is was however, not liked by the senior army officials, including Manekshaw. He made a few derogatory comments on the political leadership, which led him to be marked as an anit-national.{{Sfn|Singh|2007|pp=193–197}}

Kaul sent informers to spy over Manekshaw and based on the information gained Manekshaw was charged, and a Court of Inquiry was ordered. The court, presided over by the then-[[Western Command (India)|Western Army]] Commander, [[Lieutenant General]] Daulet Singh, exonerated Manekshaw. Before a formal 'no case' could be announced, war with [[Sino-Indian War|China]] broke out. Manekshaw was then promoted to lieutenant general and moved to [[Tezpur]] to take over [[IV Corps (India)|IV Corps]] as its GOC.{{Sfn|Singh|2007|pp=193–197}}{{Sfn|Singh|2002|p=10}}

A year later, Manekshaw was promoted to the position of army commander and took over Western Command. In 1964, he moved from [[Shimla]] to [[Calcutta]] as the GOC-in-C of the [[Eastern Command (India)|Eastern Army]].{{Sfn|Singh|2002|p=10}}{{Sfn|Singh|2002|p=9}} As GOC-in-C, Eastern Command, he successfully responded to an [[insurgency]] in [[Nagaland]] for which he was later awarded the [[Padma Bhushan]] in 1968.{{Sfn|Singh|2002|p=16}}{{Sfn|Sharma|2007|p=60}}

===Chief of the Army Staff===
Then Chief of the Army Staff (COAS) [[Paramasiva Prabhakar Kumaramangalam|General P P Kumaramangalam]] was due to retire in June 1969. Though Manekshaw was the senior-most commander in army, then [[Defence Minister of India|Defence Minister]] [[Sardar Swaran Singh]] was in favour of Lt Gen [[Harbaksh Singh]], who had played a key role as the GOC-in-C of Western Command during the [[1965 Indo-Pak war]]. Putting the rumours of Harbaksh Singh taking charge as the COAS to an end, Manekshaw was appointed as the 8th Chief of the Army Staff on 8 June 1969.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=201}} As the Chief of the Army Staff, he developed the Indian Army into an efficient instrument of war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://indianarmy.nic.in/Site/FormTemplete/frmTemp1PTC2C.aspx?MnId=0mdzgMr6q11GD9+nGBn3qw==&amp;ParentID=YFacr6mydZUr0ffNJYSyEA==|website=Indianarmy.nic.in|title=Manekshaw}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his tenure as COAS, he was instrumental in stopping the implementation of reservations for [[scheduled castes and scheduled tribes]] in the army.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=213}}

====Indo-Pakistani War of 1971====
{{main article|Indo-Pakistani War of 1971}}
[[File:1971 Instrument of Surrender.jpg|250px|thumb|The Instrument of Surrender being signed on 16 December 1971]]
Towards the end of April 1971, [[Indira Gandhi]], the [[Prime Minister of India]], during a cabinet meeting, asked Manekshaw if he was prepared to go to war with Pakistan. In response, Manekshaw told her that his single armoured division and two infantry divisions were deployed elsewhere, that only 13 of his 189 tanks were fit to fight, and that they would be competing for rail carriage with the grain harvest at that point of time. He also pointed out that the Himalayan passes would soon open up, with the forthcoming monsoon in [[East Pakistan]], which would result in heavy flooding.&lt;ref name=&quot;EconObit&quot;/&gt; When Indira Gandhi asked the cabinet to leave the room and the chief to stay, he offered to resign. She declined to accept it, but sought his advice. He then said he could guarantee victory if she would allow him to prepare for the conflict on his terms, and set a date for it. These were acceded to by the Prime Minister.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=204–205}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Manekshaw&quot;&gt;Manekshaw, SHFJ. (11 Nov 1998). &quot;Lecture at Defence Services Staff College on Leadership and Discipline&quot; (Appendix V) in Singh (2002) ''Field Marshal Sam Manekshaw, M.C. – Soldiering with Dignity''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Under Manekshaw's direction, the army launched several preparatory operations in East Pakistan including training and equipping the [[Mukti Bahini]] (a local group of freedom fighters), and about three brigades from the regular [[Bangladesh troops]] were trained. As an additional measure, 75,000 guerrillas were trained and equipped with arms and ammunition. These forces were used to harass the [[Pakistani army]] stationed in East Pakistan sporadically in the lead up to the war.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=206}}

The war started on 3 December 1971, when Pakistani aircraft bombed Indian Air Force bases in the western sector. Manekshaw instructed Lt Gen [[J F R Jacob]], Chief of Staff Eastern Command, to inform the Indian [[prime minister]] that orders were being issued for the movement of troops from Eastern Command. The following day, the navy and the air force also initiated full-scale operations on both eastern and western fronts.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=207}}

The veto used by the [[Russians]] against the United States' proposal to implement a cease-fire in the [[United Nations]] proved decisive in securing India's victory. Manekshaw addressed the Pakistani troops three times via radio messages on the subject of surrender, assuring them that they would receive honourable treatment from the Indian troops. The messages were broadcast on the 9th, 11th and 15 December. The last two messages were delivered as replies to the messages from Maj Gen [[Rao Farman Ali]] and Lt Gen [[Amir Abdullah Khan Niazi]]. These messages from the Pakistani commanders to their troops were to have a devastating effect on their side, subsequently leading to their defeat.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=208}}

Though on 11 December, Ali messaged the United Nations requesting for a cease-fire, it was not authorized by the [[President]] [[Yahya Khan]] and the fighting continued. Following several discussions and consultations, and subsequent attacks by the Indian forces, Yahya decided to stop the war in order to save the lives of the Pakistani soldiers.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=208}} The actual decision to surrender was taken by Niazi on 15 December and was conveyed to Manekshaw through the United States Consul General in Dhaka (then Dacca) via Washington. But Manekshaw replied that he would stop the war only if the Pakistani troops surrendered to their Indian counterparts by 9:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. on 16 December. Later the deadline was extended to 3:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. of the same day on Niazi's request. The Instrument of Surrender was formally signed on 16 December 1971.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=209}}

When the prime minister asked Manekshaw to go to [[Dhaka]] and accept the surrender of Pakistani forces, he declined, saying that the honour should go to the Indian Army Commander in the East, Lieutenant General [[Jagjit Singh Aurora]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ibnlive.in.com/news/field-marshal-sam-manekshaw-dead/67842-3.html|website=ibnlive.in.com|title=Field Marshal Sam Manekshaw dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Concerned about maintaining discipline in the aftermath of the conflict, Manekshaw issued strict instructions forbidding loot and rape. He stressed the need to respect and stay away from women wherever he went. As a result, according to Singh, cases of loot and rape were negligible.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=210}} In addressing his troops on the matter, Manekshaw was quoted as saying:

{{quote|text=When you see a Begum, keep your hands in your pockets, and think of Sam.|author=General Sam Manekshaw, COAS|source={{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=210}}}}

The war, lasting under a fortnight, saw more than 90,000 Pakistani soldiers personnel taken as prisoners of war, and it ended with the unconditional surrender of Pakistan's eastern half, resulting in the birth of Bangladesh as a new nation.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=210}}{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=211}} After the war, Manekshaw was known for his compassion towards the Prisoners of War (POWs). Singh recounts that in some cases he addressed POWs personally, talking to them privately with just his [[Aide-de-camp|ADC]] in his company while they shared a cup of tea. He ensured that POWs were well treated by the Indian Army, making provisions for them to be supplied with the copies of Quran, and allowing them to celebrate festivals, and to receive letters and parcels from their loved ones.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|pp=210&amp;ndash;211}}

===Promotion to field marshal===
After the end of the war, Indira Gandhi decided to promote Manekshaw to the rank of field marshal and subsequently appoint him as the Chief of the Defence Staff (CDS). However, after several objections from the bureaucracy and the commanders of the navy and the air force, the latter was dropped.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=214–215}} Though Manekshaw was to retire in June 1972, his term was extended by a period of six months. On 3 December 1973, Manekshaw was conferred with the rank of field marshal at a ceremony held at [[Rashtrapati Bhavan]].{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=215}}

==Honours and post-retirement==
&lt;!--[[File:Sam Manekshaw's statue in Pune Cantonment.jpg|thumb|150px|Manekshaw's statue in [[Pune Cantonment]]]]--&gt;&lt;!--Freedom of Panorama required--&gt;
For his service to the Indian nation, the [[President of India]] awarded Manekshaw a [[Padma Vibhushan]] in 1972 and conferred upon him the rank of field marshal, a first, on 1 January 1973. He became one of the only two army generals of independent India to be awarded this rank; the other being [[Kodandera Madappa Cariappa]] who was awarded the rank in 1986. Manekshaw retired from active service a fortnight later on 15 January 1973 after a career of nearly four decades; he settled down with his wife Silloo in [[Coonoor]], the civilian town next to [[Wellington Cantonment|Wellington Military Cantonment]] where he had served as commandant of the Defence Services Staff College, at an earlier time in his career. Popular with [[Gurkha]] soldiers, Nepal fêted Manekshaw as an honorary general of the [[Nepalese Army]] in 1972.&lt;ref name=&quot;OutMeh&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?218683|title=Play It Again, Sam: A tribute to the man whose wit was as astounding as his military skill |first=Ashok |last=Mehta |date= 27 Jan 2003|work=Outlook |accessdate=15 Aug 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2007, [[Gohar Ayub]], the son of Pakistani Field Marshal [[Ayub Khan (Field Marshal)|Ayub Khan]], claimed that Manekshaw had sold Indian Army secrets to Pakistan during the Indo-Pakistani War of 1965 for 20,000 rupees, but his accusations were dismissed by the Indian defence establishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2005-06-03/india/27858078_1_war-plan-brigadiers-dgmo |title=1965 war-plan-seller a DGMO: Gohar Khan |author=PTI |date=3 June 2005 |work=The Times of India (website)|publisher=Bennett, Coleman &amp; Co |accessdate=20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2007-05-08/india/27884033_1_field-marshal-sam-manekshaw-sam-bahadur-gohar-khan |title=Military livid at Pak slur on Sam Bahadur |author=PTI |date=8 May 2007 |work=The Times of India (website)|publisher=Bennett, Coleman &amp; Co |accessdate=20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following his service in the Indian Army, Manekshaw successfully served as an independent director on the board of several companies, and in a few cases, as the chairman. He was outspoken and hardly politically correct, and when once he was replaced on the board of a company by a man named Naik at the behest of the government, Manekshaw quipped, &quot;This is the first time in history when a ''[[Naik (military rank)|Naik]]'' (corporal) has replaced a Field Marshal.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;OutMeh&quot;/&gt;

===Controversies===
Though Sam Manekshaw was conferred the rank of field-marshal in 1973, it was reported that he was never given the complete allowances that were entitled to a field-marshal. It was not until President [[A.P.J. Abdul Kalam]] took the initiative when he met Manekshaw in Wellington, and made sure that the field-marshal was presented with a cheque for Rs 1.3 crores that Manekshaw received his arrears of pay for over 30 years. Even more surprisingly, Manekshaw's funeral was not attended by the top brass of civil, military and political leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Making of a Field Marshal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author1=Lt Gen Sk Sinha|authorlink1=Srinivas_Kumar_Sinha|title=The Making of a Field Marshal|url=http://www.indiandefencereview.com/spotlights/the-making-of-a-field-marshall/|website=Indian Defence Review|accessdate=4 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Remembering Sam Manekshaw, India's greatest general, on his birth centenary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author1=Nitin Gokhale|title=Remembering Sam Manekshaw, India's greatest general, on his birth centenary|url=http://www.ndtv.com/india-news/remembering-sam-manekshaw-indias-greatest-general-on-his-birth-centenary-556023|website=NDTV|accessdate=4 September 2016|date=April 3, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
On 22 April 1939, Manekshaw was married to Siloo Bode in Bombay. The couple had two daughters, Sherry and Maya (later Maja), born on 11 January 1940 and 24 September 1945 respectively. Sherry was married to Batliwala and they have a daughter named Brandy. Maja was employed by the British Airways as  a stewardess. She later married Daruwala, a pilot. The couple have two sons named Raoul Sam and Jehan Sam.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=189}}

==Death==
Manekshaw died of complications from pneumonia at the Military Hospital in Wellington, [[Tamil Nadu]], at 0030 hours, on 27 June 2008 at the age of 94.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Haresh|last= Pandya|title=Sam H.F.J. Manekshaw Dies at 94; Key to India's Victory in 1971 War  |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/30/world/asia/30manekshaw.html |work=New York Times |date=30 June 2008  |accessdate=30 June 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He was laid to rest at the [[Parsi]] cemetery in [[Ootacamund]] (Ooty), Tamil Nadu,&lt;ref name=&quot;statue&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|author=Thiagarajan, Shanta|date=3 April 2014|title=Field Marshal Sam Manekshaw statue unveiled on Ooty–Coonoor road|newspaper=The Times of India|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/coimbatore/Field-Marshal-Sam-Manekshaw-statue-unveiled-on-OotyCoonoor-road/articleshow/33185688.cms|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140407182132/http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/coimbatore/Field-Marshal-Sam-Manekshaw-statue-unveiled-on-OotyCoonoor-road/articleshow/33185688.cms?|archivedate=7 April 2014|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; with military honours, adjacent to his wife's grave. He is survived by two daughters and three grandchildren.{{Sfn|Singh|2005|p=189}}

Reportedly, his last words were &quot;I'm okay!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EconObit&quot;/&gt;

That year on 16 December has been celebrated as [[Vijay Diwas (India)|&quot;Vijay Diwas&quot;]] in memory of the victory achieved under Manekshaw's leadership in 1971, a postage stamp depicting Manekshaw in his field marshal's uniform was released by then President Pratibha Patil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hindu.com/2008/12/18/stories/2008121856742000.htm |title=Stamp on Manekshaw released |author=IANS |date=18 Dec 2008 |work=The Hindu (website) |publisher=The Hindu group |accessdate=10 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, neither did the President nor the PM and other leaders from the political class turn up at his funeral,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2008-06-28/india/27768634_1_service-chiefs-defence-wellington |title=Lone minister represents govt at Manekshaw's funeral |first=Rajat |last=Pandit |date=28 June 2008 |work=Times of India |accessdate=15 Aug 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NRIs&quot;&gt;[http://www.dnaindia.com/report.asp?newsid=1176337 DNA – India – NRIs irked by poor Manekshaw farewell – Daily News &amp; Analysis&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; nor was a national day of mourning declared.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.indianexpress.com/news/no-national-mourning-for-manekshaw/328779/ |title=No national mourning for Manekshaw |date=29 June 2008 |work=The Indian Express |accessdate=15 Aug 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, a granite statue was erected in his honor at [[Wellington, Tamil Nadu|Wellington]], in the [[Nilgiris district]], close to the [[Black Bridge (The Nilgiris)|Manekshaw Bridge]] on the Ooty-Coonoor road,&lt;ref name=&quot;statue&quot; /&gt; which had been named after him in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=10 March 2009|title=Manekshaw Bridge thrown open to traffic|newspaper=The Hindu|url=http://www.hindu.com/2009/03/10/stories/2009031050300300.htm|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140407184355/http://www.hindu.com/2009/03/10/stories/2009031050300300.htm|archivedate=7 April 2014|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and decorations==
&lt;center&gt;
{|
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=IND_Padma_Vibhushan_BAR.png|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award‐star|ribbon=IND Padma Bhushan BAR.png|width=106}}
|[[File:IND Poorvi Star Ribbon.svg|105px]]
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=India_General_Service_Medal_1947.svg|width=106}}
|-
|[[File:IND Paschimi Star Ribbon.svg|105px]]
|[[File:IND Raksha Medal Ribbon.svg|105px]]
|[[File:IND Sangram Medal Ribbon.svg|105px]]
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=IND_Sainya_Seva_Medal_Ribbon.svg|width=106}}
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Indian_Independence_medal_1947.svg|width=106}}
|[[File:IND 25th Anniversary Independence medal.svg|105px]]
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=IND 20YearsServiceMedalRibbon.svg|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=IND 9YearsServiceMedalRibbon.svg|width=106}}
|-
| {{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award‐star|ribbon=Military cross BAR.svg|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Ribbon_-_Burma_Star.png|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Ribbon_-_War_Medal.png|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Ribbon_India_Service_Medal.png|width=106}}
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|[[Padma Vibhushan]]
|[[Padma Bhushan]]
|Poorvi Star
|[[General Service Medal 1947]]
|rowspan=4|{{Sfn|Sharma|2007|p=61}}
|-
|Paschimi Star
|Raksha Medal
|[[Sangram Medal]]
|Sainya Seva Medal
|-
|[[Indian Independence Medal]]
|25th Independence Anniversary Medal
|20 Years Long Service Medal
|9 Years Long Service Medal
|-
|[[Military Cross]]
|[[Burma Star]]
|[[War Medal 1939–1945|War Medal]]
|[[India Service Medal]]
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==See also==
*[[Field marshal (India)|Field Marshal]] [[Kodandera Madappa Cariappa|K M Cariappa]]
*[[Marshal of the Air Force|Marshal of the Indian Air Force]] [[Arjan Singh]]

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=lower-alpha}}
;Citations
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*{{citation|first1=Vijay Kumar|last1=Singh|title=Leadership in the Indian Army: Biographies of Twelve Soldiers|author-link = Vijay Kumar Singh|year=2005|isbn=978-0-7619-3322-9|publisher=SAGE|accessdate=July 30, 2016}}
*{{citation|first1=Depinder|last1=Singh|title=Field Marshal Sam Manekshaw, M.C.: Soldiering with Dignity|year=2002|isbn=978-81-85019-02-4|publisher=Natraj Publishers|access-date=30 July 2016}}
*{{citation|first1=Satinder|last1=Sharma|title=Services Chiefs of India|year=2007|isbn=978-81-7211-162-5|publisher=Northern Book Centre|access-date=18 August 2016}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://indianarmy.nic.in/Site/FormTemplete/frmTemp1PTC2C.aspx?MnId=+pFZjV8mz9fc6cOfg7px1g==&amp;ParentID=rLdGLIGh/NUCC0Neg3IFSQ== Indian Army official page on Sam Manekshaw]

{{S-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
|before = Daulet Singh
|title = General Officer Commanding-in-Chief of the [[Western Command (India)|Western Command]]
|years = 1963–1964
|after = [[Harbaksh Singh]]}}
{{succession box
|before = [[Paramasiva Prabhakar Kumaramangalam|P P Kumaramangalam]]
|title = General Officer Commanding-in-Chief of the [[Eastern Command (India)|Eastern Command]]
|years = 1964–1969
|after =[[Jagjit Singh Aurora]]}}
{{succession box
|before = [[Paramasiva Prabhakar Kumaramangalam|P P Kumaramangalam]]
|title = [[Chief of Army Staff of the Indian Army|Chief of Army Staff]]
|years = 1969–1973
|after = [[Gopal Gurunath Bewoor]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{Chief of the Army Staff India}}
{{1971 Indo-Pak War}}

{{Padma Vibhushan Awards}}
{{PadmaBhushanAwardRecipients 1960–69}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2011}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Manekshaw, Sam}}
[[Category:1914 births]]
[[Category:2008 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Amritsar]]
[[Category:Parsi people]]
[[Category:Indian Zoroastrians]]
[[Category:Gujarati people]]
[[Category:British Indian Army officers]]
[[Category:Chiefs of Army Staff (India)]]
[[Category:Field marshals]]
[[Category:Frontier Force Regiment officers]]
[[Category:Generals of the Indo-Pakistani War of 1971]]
[[Category:Generals of the Bangladesh Liberation War]]
[[Category:Indian Army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Indian marshals]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Punjab, India]]
[[Category:Indian military personnel of the Indo-Pakistani War of 1971]]
[[Category:Indo-Pakistani War of 1947]]
[[Category:Sherwood College alumni]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Padma Bhushan in civil service]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Padma Vibhushan in civil service]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Cross]]
[[Category:Deaths from pneumonia]]
[[Category:Infectious disease deaths in India]]</text>
      <sha1>8af4ievtt56kfxoqd0xztwp2nc3s0nm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
