<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Second Battle of Chuenpi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24992492</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744608796</id>
      <parentid>734296575</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-16T10:05:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19985">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Second Battle of Chuenpi
|partof = the [[First Opium War]]
|image = [[File:Storming of Chuenpee.jpg|300px]]
|caption = British forces advancing in Chuenpi
|date = 7 January 1841
|place = [[Humen]], [[Guangdong]], China
|coordinates = {{coord|22|45|41.45|N|113|39|30.58|E|display=title}}
|territory = [[Charles Elliot]] declares cession of [[Hong Kong Island]] to the United Kingdom&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
|result = British victory, [[Convention of Chuenpi]]
|combatant1 = {{flagcountry|UKGBI}}
*{{flagicon image|Flag of the British East India Company (1801).svg}} [[East India Company|British East India Company]]
|combatant2 = {{flagicon image|Flag of the Qing Dynasty (1862-1889).svg|border=no}} [[Qing dynasty|Qing China]]
|commander1 = [[James Bremer]]
|commander2 = [[Guan Tianpei]]
|strength1 = 14 ships&lt;br /&gt;1,500 troops&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|strength2 = 15 [[Junk (ship)|junks]]&lt;br /&gt;2,000 troops
|casualties1 = 38 wounded
|casualties2 = 500+ killed or wounded&lt;br /&gt;11 junks destroyed&lt;br /&gt;191 guns captured
|notes = &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Cession formally ratified in the [[Treaty of Nanking]] (1842).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; In the Chuenpi land force only.
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox First Opium War}}
}}

The '''Second Battle of Chuenpi'''{{efn|[[Charles Elliot]] wrote &quot;Chuenpee&quot; for what some have written &quot;Chuenpi&quot; and is called &quot;Chuanbi&quot; (穿鼻) in [[pinyin]].&lt;ref&gt;Hoe &amp; Roebuck 1999, p. xviii&lt;/ref&gt;}} was fought between British and Chinese forces in the [[Pearl River Delta]], [[Guangdong]] province, China, on 7{{nbsp}}January 1841 during the [[First Opium War]]. The British launched an amphibious attack at the [[Humen]] strait (Bogue), capturing the forts on the islands of Chuenpi and Taikoktow. Subsequent negotiations between British Plenipotentiary [[Charles Elliot]] and Chinese Imperial Commissioner [[Qishan (Manchu official)|Qishan]] resulted in the [[Convention of Chuenpi]] on 20 January. As one of the terms of the agreement, Elliot announced the cession of [[Hong Kong Island]] to the [[British Empire]], after which the British took formal possession of the island on 26 January.

== Background ==
In September 1840, the [[Daoguang Emperor]] of the [[Qing dynasty]] fired Imperial Commissioner [[Lin Zexu]] and replaced him with [[Qishan (Manchu official)|Qishan]].&lt;ref&gt;The Chinese Repository, vol. 9, pp. 412–413&lt;/ref&gt; British [[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs|Foreign Secretary]] [[Lord Palmerston]] instructed Plenipotentiary [[Charles Elliot]] to have the ports of [[Guangzhou|Canton]], [[Amoy]], [[Fuzhou]], [[Ningpo]], and [[Shanghai]] opened for trade; to acquire the cession of at least one island (or if the Chinese refused, the establishment of a secure English enclave on the mainland); and to secure compensation for confiscated opium as well as military costs incurred in China.&lt;ref name=&quot;hanes&quot;&gt;Hanes &amp; Sanello 2004, p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 39&quot;&gt;Le Pichon 2006, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 December, Elliot wrote to Palmerston that these demands would be secured within ten days. Three days after the deadline, Elliot wrote to [[Governor-General of India]] [[George Eden, 1st Earl of Auckland|Lord Auckland]] that he had failed to get the concessions, but one was still in prospect. He then conceded that any settlement would be &quot;far short of the demands of the government.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 270&quot;&gt;Fay 1997, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt;

In negotiations with Qishan, Elliot wanted $7 million over a period of six years and the surrender of Amoy and Chusan as permanent British possessions. Qishan offered $5 million over twelve years, so they agreed to $6 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;hanes&quot; /&gt; However, Qishan refused Elliot's territorial demands. On 17 December, Elliot countered with an offer to abandon [[Zhoushan Island|Chusan]], which the [[Capture of Chusan|British captured]] in July 1840, and for another port to be chosen later in its place.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 270&quot; /&gt; After Qishan rejected the offer, Elliot told him, &quot;There are very large forces collected here, and delays must breed amongst them a very great impatience.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;hanes 2&quot;&gt;Hanes &amp; Sanello 2004, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; The year passed with no final settlements. An opium clipper that subsequently sailed into Canton brought with it a rumour that the emperor had decided to wage war. On 5{{nbsp}}January 1841, Elliot prepared for an attack on Canton, informing Qishan that an attack would commence in two days if agreement could not be reached.&lt;ref name=&quot;hanes 2&quot; /&gt; He allowed Commodore [[James Bremer]], commander-in-chief of the British forces, to make offensive operations.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie 1842, p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle ==
British operations began at 8:00&amp;nbsp;am on 7{{nbsp}}January from Sampanchow Island, {{convert|3|mi|abbrev=off}} below the [[Humen]] strait (Bogue).&lt;ref&gt;''The Chinese Repository'', vol. 10, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt; By 9:00&amp;nbsp;am, the [[East India Company]] steamers ''Enterprise'', ''Madagascar'', and ''[[Nemesis (1839)|Nemesis]]'' assisted in embarking the following forces who landed unopposed {{convert|2|mi|abbrev=off}} below the Chuenpi Island artillery batteries:

*504 [[Royal Marines]] under Captain [[Samuel Burdon Ellis|Samuel Ellis]]
*33 [[Royal Artillery]] under Captain J. Knowles, operating a [[24-pounder long gun|24-pounder]] howitzer and two [[6-pounder]] field guns
*137 seamen from the ''[[HMS Wellesley (1815)|Wellesley]]'', [[HMS Blenheim (1813)|''Blenheim'']], and ''[[HMS Melville (1817)|Melville]]'' under Lieutenant Wilson
*104 troops of the [[26th (Cameronian) Regiment of Foot|26th]] and [[49th (Princess Charlotte of Wales's) (Hertfordshire) Regiment of Foot|49th Regiments]] under Major Johnstone
*607 troops of the 37th [[Madras Army|Madras Native Infantry]] under Captain Duff
*76 [[Bengal Native Infantry|Bengal Volunteers]] under Captain Bolton

An additional 30 seamen assisted in dragging the 24-pounder and two 6-pounders into position, and 15 sailors from the ''Blenheim'' were employed in the rocket and ammunition service. Major [[Thomas Simson Pratt|Thomas Pratt]] of the 26th Regiment commanded the land force of about 1,500 men.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 227&quot;&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hall &amp; Bernard 1844, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt; After advancing {{convert|1.5|mi|abbrev=off}}, the British spotted the upper fort and an entrenchment comprising a deep ditch with surrounding [[Breastwork (fortification)|breastwork]]. The Chinese cheered when they saw the British, waved their flags in defiance, and opened fire from the batteries. In response, the British cannons on the crest of the hill commenced firing. The Chinese then returned fire for about 20 minutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 227&quot; /&gt; The steamers ''Queen'' and ''Nemesis'', under Captain [[Edward Belcher]] of the ''[[HMS Sulphur (1826)|Sulphur]]'', fired shells into the upper fort while the ''[[HMS Calliope (1837)|Calliope]]'', ''[[HMS Hyacinth (1829)|Hyacinth]]'', and ''[[HMS Larne (1829)|Larne]]'' ships (under Captain [[Thomas Herbert (Royal Navy officer)|Thomas Herbert]]) attacked the lower fort. In less than an hour, the combined bombardment silenced the Chinese batteries. By 10:00&amp;nbsp;am, the upper fort had been captured, and the lower fort surrounded and stormed by Royal Marines.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 224&quot;&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, pp. 223–224&lt;/ref&gt; After the capture, the ''Nemesis'' attacked a fleet of about 15 war [[Junk (ship)|junks]] under Admiral [[Guan Tianpei]] in Anson's Bay.{{efn|Anson's Bay lies between Chuenpi and Anunghoy Island, north of Chuenpi.&lt;ref&gt;Hall &amp; Bernard 1844, p. 125&lt;/ref&gt;}} The junks mounted 7 to 11 guns of various calibre from 4- to [[12-pounder long gun|12-pounders]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 267&quot;&gt;MacPherson 1843, p. 267&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Nautical Magazine'' 1841, p. 415&lt;/ref&gt; The ship fired a [[Congreve rocket]] that struck a junk near the admiral, which a British officer described as follows:

[[File:Destroying Chinese war junks, by E. Duncan (1843).jpg|thumb|250px|left|The ''[[Nemesis (1839)|Nemesis]]'' (right background) destroying Chinese war [[Junk (ship)|junks]] in Anson's Bay]]
{{quote|The very first rocket fired from the Nemesis was seen to enter the large junk ... and almost the instant afterwards it blew up with a terrific explosion, launching into eternity every soul on board, and pouring forth its blaze like the mighty rush of fire from a volcano. The instantaneous destruction of the huge body seemed appalling to both sides engaged. The smoke, and flame, and thunder of the explosion, with the broken fragments falling round, and even portions of dissevered bodies scattering as they fell, were enough to strike with awe, if not fear, the stoutest heart that looked upon it.&lt;ref&gt;Hall &amp; Bernard 1844, p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Nemesis in Anson's Bay.jpg|thumb|250px|''Nemesis'' and other British boats engaging Chinese junks at Chuenpi]]
At about 11:30&amp;nbsp;am, the Chinese on board the junks hauled down their flags.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 127&quot;&gt;Hall &amp; Bernard 1844, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt; At noon, two [[Cutter (boat)|cutters]] of the ''Nemesis'' sailed towards Admiral Guan's junk, described by an officer as &quot;immensely large&quot; and mounting 14 or 15 guns, some of them brass and &quot;beautifully chased&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 242&quot;&gt;''The United Service Journal'' 1841, p. 242&lt;/ref&gt; They found only one man on board who after seeing the crew board the ship, jumped over the [[Bow (ship)|bow]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 242&quot; /&gt; Meanwhile, Captain [[James Scott (Royal Navy officer)|James Scott]] of the ''[[HMS Samarang (1822)|Samarang]]'' commanded the attack on Taikoktow Island (west of Chuenpi).&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 224&quot; /&gt; When the forts began firing on the British vessels at 10:20&amp;nbsp;am, the ''Samarang'' returned fire ten minutes later after anchoring {{convert|200|yd|abbrev=off}} away. The ''[[HMS Modeste (1837)|Modeste]]'', ''[[HMS Druid (1825)|Druid]]'', and ''[[HMS Columbine (1826)|Columbine]]'' later anchored in succession. Scott reported that &quot;in a few minutes, so destructive and well directed was the fire of our ships, that that of the enemy was silenced, with the exception of an occasional gun or two.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 232&quot;&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, p. 232&lt;/ref&gt; At 11:20&amp;nbsp;am, the ships embarked their crewmen to storm the forts&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 232&quot; /&gt; where the Chinese remained inside until driven out.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 224&quot; /&gt; The Chinese could not withstand the onslaught of British [[musket]]s during hand-to-hand combat. After capturing the forts, the Chinese guns were spiked and thrown into the river.&lt;ref&gt;''The Chinese Repository'', vol. 10, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt;

In total, 38 British were wounded, many from an explosion of an extensive [[Magazine (artillery)|magazine]] after capturing the Chuenpi fort.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 267&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, p. 229&lt;/ref&gt; Commodore Bremer credited the Chinese for fighting &quot;with the greatest credit and devotion&quot; in the batteries and reported their losses at 500 to 600 out of a force of 2,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; The high Chinese casualties were due to the impression they had that British troops would give [[no quarter]].&lt;ref&gt;Ouchterlony 1844, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt; 100 Chinese prisoners who laid down their arms were released the next day.&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, p. 226&lt;/ref&gt; 11 junks were destroyed &lt;ref name=&quot;p. 127&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Belcher 1843, p. 144&lt;/ref&gt; and 191 artillery pieces were captured.&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, p. 243&lt;/ref&gt; According to Qing scholar [[Wei Yuan]], Kuan sent Rear-Admiral Li T'ing-Yü to Canton to request more troops, which the &quot;whole official body&quot; supported except Qishan, who spent the night writing peace proposals.&lt;ref&gt;Parker 1888, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
Elliot sent a Chinese prisoner to Kuan, with a letter explaining &quot;the usages of civilized warfare&quot; and that if the forts did not hoist their colours the following day, they would not be attacked.&lt;ref&gt;Bingham 1843, p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; At 11:30&amp;nbsp;am on 8{{nbsp}}January, British ships led by the ''Blenheim'' sailed up the Bocca Tigris. As they approached Anunghoy Island (north of Chuenpi), a boat rowed by an old woman displayed a white flag.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie 1842, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ouchterlony&quot;&gt;Ouchterlony 1844, pp. 100–101&lt;/ref&gt; A man from the ship was taken on board a British vessel to deliver a request from Kuan that hostilities be suspended for three days in order to contact Qishan.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie 1842, pp. 25–26&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;MacPherson 1843, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; Cancellation of the attack order prompted Lieutenant John Ouchterlony to note that it &quot;certainly created a feeling of great disappointment throughout the fleet.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ouchterlony&quot; /&gt; Elliot addressed the cancellation in a circular aboard the ''Wellesley'': &quot;A communication has been received from the Chinese commander-in-chief, which has led to an armistice, with the purpose to afford the high commissioner time to consider certain conditions now offered for his acceptance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Chinese Repository'', vol. 11, p. 578&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20{{nbsp}}January, after the [[Convention of Chuenpi]], Elliot announced &quot;the conclusion of preliminary arrangements&quot; between Qishan and himself. They involved the cession of [[Hong Kong Island]] to the United Kingdom, a $6 million indemnity payable to the British government, direct and equal ties between the countries, and trade in Canton to be opened within ten days following the Chinese new year.&lt;ref&gt;''The Chinese Repository'', vol. 10, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; They also agreed to the restoration of Chuenpi and Taikoktow to the Chinese, and the evacuation of Chusan.&lt;ref&gt;''Bulletins of State Intelligence'' 1841, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt; On 26 January, the [[Union Jack]] was raised on Hong Kong, and Commodore Bremer took formal possession of the island, under a ''[[feu de joie]]'' from the marines and a [[21-gun salute|royal salute]] from the anchored men-of-war.&lt;ref&gt;Belcher 1843, p. 148&lt;/ref&gt; On 29{{nbsp}}January, Elliot proclaimed that Chinese natives &quot;shall be governed according to the laws and customs of China, every description of torture excepted&quot; and that &quot;all British subjects and foreigners residing, or resorting to the island of Hongkong, shall enjoy full security and protection, according to the principles and practice of British law&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''The Chinese Repository'', vol. 10, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt;

When the news reached the emperor, he ordered Qishan to be &quot;degraded from his office&quot; and to stand trial at the Board of Punishments.&lt;ref&gt;Martin 1847, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; Qishan faced several charges including giving &quot;the barbarians Hongkong as a dwelling place&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 50&quot;&gt;Davis 1852, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; In his response, he claimed, &quot;I pretended to do so from the mere force of circumstances, and to put them off for a time, but had no such serious intention.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 50&quot; /&gt; The court denounced him as a traitor and sentenced him to death. He was imprisoned for several months, but at the end of 1841 he was allowed, without authority or rank, to deal with the British.&lt;ref&gt;Davis 1852, pp. 51–52&lt;/ref&gt; On 21{{nbsp}}April 1841, Lord Palmerston wrote a letter of reprimand to Elliot and recalled him for not securing the earlier demands as ordered.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 39&quot; /&gt; Palmerston dismissed Hong Kong as &quot;a barren island with hardly a house upon it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 40&quot;&gt;Le Pichon 2006, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1841, [[Henry Pottinger]] replaced Elliot as plenipotentiary.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 40&quot; /&gt; [[Queen Victoria]] addressed the events in a letter to her uncle, [[Leopold I of Belgium|King Leopold I]] of Belgium, on 13{{nbsp}}April:

{{quote|The Chinese business vexes us much, and Palmerston is deeply mortified at it. ''All'' we wanted might have been got, if it had not been for the unaccountably strange conduct of Charles Elliot ... who completely disobeyed his instructions and ''tried'' to get the ''lowest'' terms he could. [...] The attack and storming of the [Chuenpi] Forts on the 7th of January was very gallantly done by the Marines, and immense destruction of the Chinese took place. The accounts of the cruelty of the Chinese to one another are horrible. [[Albert, Prince Consort|Albert]] is so much amused at my having got the Island of Hong Kong, and we think [[Victoria, Princess Royal|Victoria]] ought to be called Princess of Hong Kong in addition to Princess Royal.&lt;ref&gt;Benson &amp; Esher 1907, p. 329&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Notes ==
;Footnotes
{{notelist}}

;Citations
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== References ==
{{refbegin|2}}
*Belcher, Edward (1843). ''[https://www.archive.org/details/narrativeofvoyag02belc Narrative of a Voyage Round the World]''. Volume 2. London: Henry Colburn.
*Benson, Arthur Christopher; Esher, Viscount (1907). ''[https://www.archive.org/details/lettersofqueenvi01vict The Letters of Queen Victoria]''. Volume 1. New York: Longmans, Green, and Co.
*Bingham, John Elliot (1843). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=8TGwqgOCFR0C Narrative of the Expedition to China, from the Commencement of the War to Its Termination in 1842]'' (2nd ed.). Volume 2. London: Henry Colburn.
*''[https://books.google.com/books?id=J9Q1AAAAMAAJ Bulletins of State Intelligence]''. Westminster: F. Watts. 1841.
*''[https://books.google.com/books?id=Li07AQAAMAAJ The Chinese Repository]''. Volume 10. Canton. 1841.
*''[https://books.google.com/books?id=NnIbAAAAIAAJ The Chinese Repository]''. Volume 11. Canton. 1842.
*Davis, John Francis (1852). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=9U4zAAAAMAAJ China, During the War and Since the Peace]''. Volume 1.  London: Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans.
*Fay, Peter Ward (1997) [1975]. ''The Opium War, 1840-1842: Barbarians in the Celestial Empire''. University of North Carolina Press. ISBN 0807847143. 
*Hall, William Hutcheon; Bernard, William Dallas (1844). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=GVQuAQAAIAAJ Narrative of the Voyages and Services of the Nemesis from 1840 to 1843]'' (2nd ed.). London: Henry Colburn.
*Hanes, William Travis; Sanello, Frank (2002). ''The Opium Wars: The Addiction of One Empire and the Corruption of Another''. Naperville, Illinois: Sourcebooks. ISBN 1-4022-0149-4.
*Hoe, Susanna; Roebuck, Derek (1999). ''The Taking of Hong Kong: Charles and Clara Elliot in China Waters''. Richmond, Surrey: Curzon Press. ISBN 0-7007-1145-7.
*Le Pichon, Alain (2006). ''China Trade and Empire''. Oxford: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-726337-2.
*Mackenzie, Keith Stewart (1842). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=yxgMAAAAYAAJ Narrative of the Second Campaign in China]''. London: Richard Bentley.
*MacPherson, Duncan (1843). ''[https://archive.org/details/twoyearsinchinan00macprich Two Years in China]'' (2nd ed.). London: Saunders and Otley.
*Morse, Hosea Ballou (1910). ''[https://archive.org/details/internationalrel00mors The International Relations of the Chinese Empire]''. Volume 1. New York: Paragon Book Gallery.
*[[Robert Montgomery Martin|Martin, Robert Montgomery]] (1847). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=LSR2PEpOtqUC China: Political, Commercial, and Social; In an Official Report to Her Majesty's Government]''. Volume 2. London: James Madden.
*''[https://books.google.com/books?id=PfcVYAWofJEC The Nautical Magazine and Naval Chronicle, for 1841]''. London: Simpkin, Marshall, and Co. 1841.
*Ouchterlony, John (1844). ''[https://www.archive.org/details/chinesewaraccoun00ouchrich The Chinese War]''. London: Saunders and Otley.
*Parker, Edward Harper (1888). ''[https://www.archive.org/details/chineseaccountof00parkrich Chinese Account of the Opium War]''. Shanghai: Kelly &amp; Walsh.
*''[https://books.google.com/books?id=_ljcbRMR2tQC The United Service Journal and Naval Military Magazine]''. Part 2. London: Henry Colburn. 1841.
{{refend}}

== External links ==
*{{Commons-inline|Category:Second Battle of Chuenpi|Second Battle of Chuenpi}}

{{use dmy dates|date=February 2014}}

[[Category:1841 in China]]
[[Category:Battles of the First Opium War|Chuenpi 2]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1841|Chuenpi]]
[[Category:History of Guangdong]]
[[Category:Naval battles of the Opium Wars|Chuenpi 2]]</text>
      <sha1>7df4zv19ogl5hcy5znx0za7yuffle16</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
