<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sopwith Camel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>152993</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750956848</id>
      <parentid>750503851</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T13:54:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>80.229.34.113</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Variants */ lk</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38847">{{About|the fighter aircraft|the 1960s psychedelic rock band|Sopwith Camel (band)}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name = Camel
  |image = File:RAF Sopwith Camel.jpg
  |caption =Sopwith Camel
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type = [[Biplane]] [[fighter aircraft|fighter]]
  |manufacturer = [[Sopwith Aviation Company]]
  |designer =[[Herbert Smith (aircraft designer)|Herbert Smith]]&lt;ref&gt;Mason 1992, p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;
  |first flight = 22 December 1916
  |introduction = June 1917
  |retired =January 1920
  |status =
  |primary user = [[Royal Flying Corps]]
  |more users = [[Royal Naval Air Service]] &lt;br&gt; [[Royal Air Force]]
  |produced = &lt;!--years in production, e.g. 1970-1999, if still in active use but no longer built--&gt;
  |number built = 5,490
  |unit cost =
  |variants with their own articles =
}}
|}

The '''Sopwith Camel''' was a British [[World War I|First World War]] single-seat [[biplane]] [[fighter aircraft]] introduced on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] in 1917. Manufactured by the [[Sopwith Aviation Company]], it used a [[rotary engine]], and had twin [[Synchronization gear|synchronized]] machine guns. Though difficult to handle it offered very good manoeuvrability to an experienced pilot. Camel pilots were credited with shooting down 1,294 enemy aircraft, more than any other Allied fighter of the conflict. 
It also served as a ground-attack aircraft, especially towards the end of the war when it had become outclassed in the air-to-air role. The main variant was the '''F.1''' but dedicated variants were built for a variety of roles including the '''2F.1''' Ship's Camel for [[Aircraft carrier|carrier]] operations,  the '''Comic''' night fighter, the '''T.F.1''' trench fighter armoured ground attack aircraft and as a two-seat trainer.

==Design and development==
[[File:Replica Sopwith Camel (G-BZSC) (12243203404).jpg|thumb|Replica Sopwith Camel showing internal structure]]
The Camel's predecessor, the [[Sopwith Pup]], was no longer competitive against newer German fighters, such as the [[Albatros D.III]], and thus the Camel was developed specifically to replace the Pup,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce ptI p527&quot;&gt;Bruce ''Flight'' 22 April 1955, p. 527.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[Nieuport 17]]s that had been purchased from the French as an interim measure. It was recognised that the new fighter would need to be faster and have a heavier armament. To meet this demand, Sopwith's chief designer, [[Herbert Smith (aircraft designer)|Herbert Smith]], opted to develop a successor, the ''Sopwith F.1''.&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 3&quot;&gt;Bruce 1965, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;Big Pup&quot;, as it was known early in its development, and powered by a 110&amp;nbsp;hp Clerget 9Z was first flown by [[Harry Hawker]] at [[Brooklands]] on 22 December 1916. Its design was conventional for its time, featuring a wooden box-like fuselage structure, an aluminium engine cowling, plywood panels around the cockpit, and fabric-covered fuselage, wings and tail. While having some clear similarities with the Pup, it had a noticeably bulkier fuselage.&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 3&quot;/&gt; For the first time on an operational British-designed fighter, two [[0.303 British|0.303 in]] (7.7&amp;nbsp;mm) [[Vickers machine gun|Vickers]] [[machine gun]]s were mounted directly in front of the cockpit, [[Synchronization gear|synchronised]] to fire forwards through the propeller disc. A metal [[Aircraft fairing|fairing]] over the gun breeches, intended to protect the guns from freezing at altitude, created a &quot;hump&quot;, and it was this feature that led pilots to refer to the aircraft by the name [[Camel]].  This was never an official designation for the aircraft however.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce ptI p527&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 1965, pp. 4-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:AC0158CobbyCamel1918-19.jpg|thumb|[[Harry Cobby]] sitting in the cockpit of a Sopwith Camel]]
The bottom wing was rigged with  3° [[dihedral (aircraft)|dihedral]] but the top wing had no dihedral, so that the gap between the wings was less at the tips than at the roots; this change was made at the suggestion of [[Fred Sigrist]], the Sopwith works manager, in order to simplify construction. The upper wing features a distinctive central cutout section to improve upwards visibility for the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 1965, pp. 3-5.&lt;/ref&gt; Production Camels were powered by various [[rotary engine]]s, most commonly either the [[Clerget 9B]] or the [[Bentley BR1]].&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 1968, pp. 148-149.&lt;/ref&gt; To avoid a production [[Bottleneck (production)|bottleneck]] being imposed on the aircraft by a potential engine shortage, other engines were also used.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 1965, pp. 7-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1917, the first production contract for an initial batch of 250 Camels was issued by the [[War Office]].&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 5&quot;&gt;Bruce 1965, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; During 1917, 1,325 Camels were manufactured, almost entirely of the initial F.1 variant and by the time production came to an end, approximately 5,490 Camels of all types had been built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce ptII p 563&quot;&gt;Bruce ''Flight'' 29 April 1955, p. 563.&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1918, production of the navalised &quot;Ship's&quot; Camel 2F.1 began.&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 6&quot;&gt;Bruce 1965, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike the preceding Pup and [[Sopwith Triplane|Triplane]], the Camel was considered to be difficult to fly.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce 1965, pp. 5-6.&lt;/ref&gt; The type owed both its extreme manoeuvrability and its difficult handling to the close placement of the engine, pilot, guns and fuel tank (some 90% of the aircraft's weight) within the front seven feet of the aircraft, and to the strong [[gyroscope|gyroscopic]] effect of the rotating mass of the cylinders common to [[rotary engine]]s.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;As compared with [[radial engine]]s in which a conventional rotating crankshaft is driven by a fixed engine block.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
The Camel soon gained an unfortunate reputation with pilots.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Jackson 2005, pp.15–16.&lt;/ref&gt; Many crashed on take-off when the load of fuel usually carried pushed the centre of gravity beyond the rearmost safe limits. In level flight, the Camel was markedly tail-heavy. Unlike the Sopwith Triplane, the Camel lacked a variable incidence tailplane, so that the pilot had to apply constant forward pressure on the control stick to maintain a level attitude at low altitude. The aircraft could be rigged so that at higher altitudes it could be flown &quot;hands off&quot;. A stall immediately resulted in a dangerous [[Spin (flight)|spin]].

A two-seat trainer version of the Camel was later built to ease the transition process:&lt;ref name=&quot;bruce 9&quot; /&gt; in his ''Recollections of an Airman'' Lt Col L.A. Strange, who served with the central flying school,  wrote: &quot;In spite of the care we took, Camels continually spun down out of control when flew{{sic|?|date=June 2016}} by pupils on their first solos. At length, with the assistance of Lieut Morgan, who managed our workshops, I took the main tank out of several Camels and replaced [them] with a smaller one, which enabled us to fit in dual control.&quot;  Such conversions, and dual instruction, went some way to alleviating the previously unacceptable casualties incurred during the critical type-specific solo training stage.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

==Operational history==

===Western front===
[[File:148th American Aero Squadron field. Making preparations for a daylight raid on German trenches and cities. The... - NARA - 530739.tif|thumb|Camels being prepared for a sortie.]]
In June 1917, the type entered service with No. 4 Squadron of the [[Royal Naval Air Service]], near [[Dunkirk]]. Its first combat flight and reportedly its first victory claim were both made on 4 July 1917.&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 5&quot;/&gt; By the end of July 1917, the Camel also equipped No. 3 and No. 9 Naval Squadrons; and it had become operational with No. 70 Squadron of the [[Royal Flying Corps]].&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 6&quot;/&gt;  By February 1918, 13 squadrons had Camels as their primary equipment.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}

The Camel proved to have better manoeuvrability than the [[Albatros D.III]] and [[Albatros D.V|D.V]] and offered heavier armament and better performance than the Pup and Triplane. Its controls were light and sensitive. The Camel turned more slowly to the left, which resulted in a nose-up attitude due to the torque of the rotary engine. But the engine torque also resulted in the ability to turn to the right quicker than other fighters,&lt;ref name='Clark1973'&gt;Clark 1973, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; although that resulted in a tendency towards a nose-down attitude from the turn. Because of the faster turning capability to the right, to change heading 90° to the left, some pilots preferred to do it by turning 270° to the right.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}

Agility in combat made the Camel one of the best-remembered [[Allies of World War I|Allied]] aircraft of the [[First World War]]. RFC crew used to joke that it offered the choice between &quot;a [[Headstone|wooden cross]], the [[Emblems of the International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|Red Cross]], or a [[Victoria Cross]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Leinburger [https://books.google.com/books?ei=MxWyUqaFNcuU7Qaco4BI&amp;id=DKv-TahJStsC&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=%22wooden+cross%22  2008, p. 30.]&lt;/ref&gt; Together with the [[Royal Aircraft Factory S.E.5|S.E.5a]] and the [[SPAD S.XIII]], the Camel helped to re-establish the Allied aerial superiority that lasted well into 1918.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}

Major [[William George Barker|William Barker]]'s Sopwith Camel ([[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|serial no]]. ''B6313'', the aircraft in which he scored the majority of his victories),&lt;ref&gt;Ralph 1999, p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; was used to shoot down 46 aircraft and balloons from September 1917 to September 1918 in 404 operational flying hours, more than any other single RAF fighter.

===Home defence and night fighting===
An important role for the Camel was home defence. The RNAS flew Camels from [[RAF Eastchurch|Eastchurch]] and [[RAF Manston|Manston]] airfields against [[German strategic bombing during World War I|daylight raids]] by German bombers, including [[Gotha G.IV|Gothas]], from July 1917.&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 9&quot;&gt;Bruce 1965, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; 
The public outcry against the night raids and the poor response of London's defences forced the RFC to divert Camels from France to home defence, with [[No. 44 Squadron RAF|44 Squadron RFC]] reforming on the Camel in the home defence role in July 1917.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis p96&quot;&gt;Davis 1999, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; When the Germans switched to night attacks, the Camel proved capable of being flown at night, and the home defence aircraft were modified with navigation lights to serve as night fighters. A number of Camels were more extensively modified with the Vickers machine guns being replaced by overwing [[Lewis guns]], with the cockpit being moved rearwards so the pilot could reload the guns. This modification, which became known as the &quot;Sopwith Comic&quot; allowed the guns to be fired without affecting the pilot's night vision, and allowed the use of new, more effective incendiary ammunition that was considered unsafe to fire from synchronised Vickers guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis p97&quot;&gt;Davis 1999, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brucev2 p1151,3&quot;&gt;Bruce 1968, p. 151, 153.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The ammunition in question was the RTS (Richard Thelfall and Sons) round, a combined incendiary and explosive round with a [[nitroglycerin]] and [[phosphorus]] filling. While more effective than earlier incendiary bullets like the phosphorus filled [[Buckingham bullet]], they required careful handling, and were initially banned from synchronised weapons, both because of fears about the consequences of bullets striking the propeller of the fighter, and to prevent [[cooking off]] of the sensitive ammunition in the chambers of the Vickers guns, which fired from a [[closed bolt]] - a required feature for guns used in synchronized mounts - where heat could build up much quicker than in the [[open bolt]]ed Lewis gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis p97&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;flygunI p11,4&quot;&gt;Williams and Gustin 2003, pp. 11, 14.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} By March 1918, the home defence squadrons were equipped with the Camel, with seven home defence squadrons flying Camels by August 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis p98&quot;&gt;Davis 1999, p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:HMS Furious Tondern Raid 1918 IWM SP 1156.jpg|thumb|Navalised Camels on the aircraft carrier [[HMS Furious (47)|HMS ''Furious'']] prior to raiding the [[Tondern raid|Tondern airship hangars]]]]
[[No. 151 Squadron RAF|151 Squadron]] Camel night fighters were also intercepting German night bombers over the Western Front, and carrying out night intruder missions against German airstrips, claiming 26 German aircraft downed in five months of operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis p98-9&quot;&gt;Davis 1999, pp. 98–99.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shipboard use===
The RNAS operated 2F.1 Camels from platforms mounted on the turrets of major warships, from some of the earliest aircraft carriers, and from aircraft lighters which were specially modified barges, which were towed fast enough that a Camel could be launched from one against incoming air raids from a more advantageous position than shore bases allowed.

===Ground attack===
[[File:HMA R 23 Airship With Camel N6814.jpg|thumb|Sopwith 2F.1 Camel suspended from airship R 23 prior to a test flight.]]
By mid-1918, the Camel had become obsolescent as a day fighter as its climb rate, level speed and performance at altitudes over 12,000&amp;nbsp;ft (3,650 m) were outclassed by the latest German fighters, such as the [[Fokker D.VII]]. However, it remained useful as a ground-attack and infantry support aircraft. During the German offensive of March 1918, squadrons of Camels harassed the advancing German Army, inflicting high losses (although suffering high losses in turn) through the dropping of 25&amp;nbsp;lb (11&amp;nbsp;kg) Cooper bombs and low-level strafing. The protracted development of the Camel's replacement, the [[Sopwith Snipe]], meant that the Camel remained in service until after the Armistice.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}

===Parasite fighter===
In summer 1918, a 2F.1 Camel (''N6814'') was used in trials as a [[parasite aircraft|parasite fighter]] under [[Airship]] ''[[No. 23r|R23]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzsimons, p.521.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
Camels were powered by several [[rotary engine]]s:
*130&amp;nbsp;hp [[Clerget 9B]] rotary (standard powerplant)
*140&amp;nbsp;hp Clerget 9Bf rotary
*110&amp;nbsp;hp [[Le Rhône 9J]] rotary
*150&amp;nbsp;hp [[Bentley BR1]] rotary (gave best performance – standard for R.N.A.S. machines)
*100&amp;nbsp;hp [[Gnome Monosoupape]] 9B-2 rotary
*150&amp;nbsp;hp Gnome Monosoupape 9N rotary

===Sopwith Camel F.1===
The F.1 was the main production version. It was armed with twin synchronised Vickers guns.

[[File:Sopwith Camel at the Imperial War Museum.jpg|thumb|The Sopwith 2F.1 Camel used to shoot down [[Zeppelin P Class|Zeppelin L 53]], at the [[Imperial War Museum]], London. Note mounting of twin Lewis guns over the top wing]]

===Sopwith Camel 2F.1===
The 2F.1 was a shipboard variant, flown from {{HMS|Furious|47}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Sopwith 2F.1 Ship's Camel| website= Their Flying Machines|url=http://flyingmachines.ru/Site2/Crafts/Craft31478.htm|accessdate=10 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; It had a slightly shorter wingspan and a [[Bentley BR1]] as its standard engine. Additionally, one Vickers gun was replaced by an overwing [[Lewis gun]].

===Sopwith Camel &quot;Comic&quot; Night fighter===
The &quot;Comic&quot; was a Camel variant designed specifically for [[night fighter|night-fighting]] duties. The twin Vickers guns were replaced by two Lewis guns on [[Foster mounting]]s firing forward over the top wing, as the muzzle flash of the Vickers guns could blind the pilot. To allow reloading of the guns, the pilot was moved about 12 inches (30&amp;nbsp;cm) to the rear and to compensate the fuel tank was moved forward.&lt;ref&gt;Mason 1992, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; It served with Home Defence Squadrons against German air raids. The &quot;Comic&quot; nickname was unofficial, and was shared with the night fighter version of the [[Sopwith 1½ Strutter]].

===F.1/1===
The F1/1 was a version with tapered wings.

===T.F.1===
The T.F.1 was an experimental [[trench fighter]] used for development work for [[Sopwith Salamander]]. Its machine guns were angled downwards for efficient [[strafing]], and it featured armour plating for protection.

===Trainer===
The trainer variant had a second cockpit behind the normal pilot's position. The weapons were removed, although the hump was sometimes kept.

==Operators==
[[File:Sopwith Camel Cremers.jpg|thumb|Belgian Sopwith Camel flown by Adj. Léon Cremers with n° 11 Squadron &quot;Cocotte&quot; marking.]]
;{{AUS}}
*[[Royal Australian Air Force|Australian Flying Corps]]
**[[No. 4 Squadron RAAF|No. 4 Squadron AFC]] in France.
**[[No. 5 Squadron RAAF|No. 5 (Training) Squadron AFC]] in the United Kingdom.
**[[No. 6 Squadron RAAF|No. 6 (Training) Squadron AFC]] in the United Kingdom.
**[[No. 8 Squadron RAAF|No. 8 (Training) Squadron AFC]] in the United Kingdom.
;{{BEL}}
*[[Belgian Air Component|Aviation Militaire Belge]]
**[[1ère Escadrille de Chasse]]
*[[Groupe de Chasse (Belgium)|Groupe de Chasse]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis p96&quot;/&gt;
**[[9 Squadron (Belgian Air Force)|9ème Escadrille de Chasse]]
**[[11 Squadron (Belgian Air Force)|11ème Escadrille de Chasse]]
;{{flag|Canada|1868}}
*[[Royal Canadian Air Force]]
;{{EST}}
*[[Estonian Air Force]]
;{{FRA}}
	
*French Government
;{{GEO}}
*[[Georgian Air Force]] - 3-4 aircraft, 1920 
;{{flag|Greece|old}}
*[[Hellenic Navy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis p102&quot;&gt;Davis 1999, p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{LVA}}
*[[Latvian Air Force]]
;{{NLD}}
*[[Royal Netherlands Air Force]]
;{{POL}}
*[[Polish Air Force]] operated 1 Camel post-war (1921)
;{{RUS}}
*[[Imperial Russian Air Service]]
;{{USSR}}
*[[Soviet Air Force]] - Postwar.
;{{UK}}
*[[Royal Flying Corps]] / [[Royal Air Force]]
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
:*[[No. 3 Squadron RAF|3 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 17 Squadron RAF|17 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 28 Squadron RAF|28 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 37 Squadron RAF|37 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 43 Squadron RAF|43 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 44 Squadron RAF|44 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 45 Squadron RAF|45 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 46 Squadron RAF|46 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 47 Squadron RAF|47 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 50 Squadron RAF|50 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 51 Squadron RAF|51 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 54 Squadron RAF|54 Squadron]]
:*[[No. 61 Squadron RAF|61 Squadron]]
{{col-break}}
*[[No. 65 Squadron RAF|65 Squadron]]
*[[No. 66 Squadron RAF|66 Squadron]]
*[[No. 70 Squadron RAF|70 Squadron]]
*[[No. 71 Squadron RAF|71 Squadron]]
*[[No. 73 Squadron RAF|73 Squadron]]
*[[No. 75 Squadron RAF|75 Squadron]]
*[[No. 78 Squadron RAF|78 Squadron]]
*[[No. 80 Squadron RAF|80 Squadron]]
*[[No. 81 Squadron RAF|81 Squadron]]
*[[No. 89 Squadron RAF|89 Squadron]]
*[[No. 94 Squadron RAF|94 Squadron]]
*[[No. 112 Squadron RAF|112 Squadron]]
*[[No. 139 Squadron RAF|139 Squadron]]
{{col-break}}
*[[No. 143 Squadron RAF|143 Squadron]]
*[[No. 150 Squadron RAF|150 Squadron]]
*[[No. 151 Squadron RAF|151 Squadron]]
*[[No. 152 Squadron RAF|152 Squadron]]
*[[No. 155 Squadron RAF|155 Squadron]]
*[[No. 187 Squadron RAF|187 Squadron]]
*[[No. 188 Squadron RAF|188 Squadron]]
*[[No. 189 Squadron RAF|189 Squadron]]
*[[No. 198 Squadron RAF|198 Squadron]]
*[[No. 201 Squadron RAF|201 Squadron]]
*[[No. 203 Squadron RAF|203 Squadron]]
*[[No. 204 Squadron RAF|204 Squadron]]
*[[No. 208 Squadron RAF|208 Squadron]]
{{col-break}}
*[[No. 209 Squadron RAF|209 Squadron]]
*[[No. 210 Squadron RAF|210 Squadron]]
*[[No. 212 Squadron RAF|212 Squadron]]
*[[No. 213 Squadron RAF|213 Squadron]]
*[[No. 219 Squadron RAF|219 Squadron]]
*[[No. 220 Squadron RAF|220 Squadron]]
*[[No. 222 Squadron RAF|222 Squadron]]
*[[No. 225 Squadron RAF|225 Squadron]]
*[[No. 230 Squadron RAF|230 Squadron]]
*[[No. 233 Squadron RAF|233 Squadron]]
*[[No. 273 Squadron RAF|273 Squadron]]
{{col-end}}
*[[Royal Naval Air Service]]
**[[No. 201 Squadron RAF|No. 1 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 203 Squadron RAF|No. 3 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 204 Squadron RAF|No. 4 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 206 Squadron RAF|No. 6 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 208 Squadron RAF|No. 8 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 209 Squadron RAF|No. 9 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 210 Squadron RAF|No. 10 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 212 Squadron RAF|No. 12 Squadron RNAS]]
**[[No. 213 Squadron RAF|No. 13 Squadron RNAS]]
[[File:Sopwith Camel F.1 Right Rear.jpg|thumb|USAS Sopwith Camel]]
;{{flag|United States|1912}}
*[[American Expeditionary Force]]
*[[United States Army Air Service]]
**[[9th Aero Squadron]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=9784 &quot;9 Bomb Squadron (ACC).&quot;] ''Air Force Historical Research Agency''. Retrieved: 19 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
**[[17th Aero Squadron]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=9849 &quot;17 Weapons Squadron (ACC).&quot;] ''Air Force Historical Research Agency''. Retrieved: 19 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
**[[27th Aero Squadron]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=10190 &quot;27 Fighters Squadron (ACC).&quot;] ''Air Force Historical Research Agency''. Retrieved: 19 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
**[[37th Bomb Squadron|37th Aero Squadron]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=11645 &quot;37 Bomb Squadron (ACC).&quot;]''Air Force Historical Research Agency''. Retrieved: 19 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
**[[148th Aero Squadron]]
*[[United States Navy]]

==Survivors==
{{Commonscat-inline|Sopwith Camel museum aircraft}}
&lt;!-- see talk page---{{prose|section|date=August 2009}}----&gt;
[[File:Sopwith Camel 1.jpg|thumb|Sopwith Camel at the [[Royal Air Force Museum]]]]
There are only eight known original Sopwith Camels left:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://demobbed.org.uk/aircraft.php?type=299 |title=Sopwith Camel |work=Demobbed - Out of Service British Military Aircraft |year=2015 |accessdate=28 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''N6254'' was displayed in the Aerospace Education Center in [[Little Rock, Arkansas]], until it closed in December 2010, and the aircraft was sold to help pay debts. The Camel was sold privately and moved to a museum in New Zealand and has been restored to flying condition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.nwaonline.com/news/2011/mar/16/history-takes-flight-vintage-aircraft-sol-20110316/ |title=History Takes Flight: Vintage aircraft sold to pay center's bills |first=Noel |last=Oman |work=Northwest Arkansas Democrat Gazette |date=16 March 2011 |accessdate=28 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* F.1 Camel ''B5747'' is on display at the [[Royal Museum of the Armed Forces and Military History]] in Brussels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.aviationmuseum.eu/World/Europe/Belgium/Brussel/Brussel_photo/Camel_F.1_B5747_11.htm |title=B5747/11 Sopwith Camel F.1 |work=Koninklijk Leger Museum |year=2012 |accessdate=28 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* F.1 Camel ''B7280'' can be found at the [[Polish Aviation Museum]] in [[Kraków]]. The aircraft was built in [[Lincoln, England|Lincoln]] by [[Clayton &amp; Shuttleworth]]. On 5 September 1918, when being flown by Captain [[Herbert A. Patey]] of [[No. 210 Squadron RAF]] over Belgium, it was shot down by [[Ludwig Beckmann]] of ''[[Jasta 56]]''. Patey survived and was taken prisoner. The Germans repaired the aircraft and flew it until the end of the war. It was then taken to Berlin and exhibited in an air museum. During World War II it was moved to Poland for safekeeping, and put into storage. Restoration began in 2007 and was completed by 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lincolnshireecho.co.uk/Lincoln-built-icon-World-War-restored-glory/story-11223827-detail/story.html |title=Lincoln-built Sopwith Camel from the First World War is restored to its former glory |work=[[Lincolnshire Echo]] |date=22 July 2010 |accessdate=28 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''N6812'', a [[William Beardmore and Company|William Beardmore]] built 2F.1 Camel, was flown by Flight Sub-Lieutenant Stuart Culley on 11 August 1918 when he shot down [[Zeppelin]] LZ100; it is on display at the [[Imperial War Museum]] in [[London]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellis148&quot;&gt;Ellis 2008, p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;
*A Camel 2F.1 ''N8156'' (RAF) is currently on display at the [[Canadian Aviation Museum]]. Manufactured in 1918 by Hooper &amp; Company Ltd., [[Great Britain]], it was purchased by the RCAF in 1924 and last flew in 1967. It is on static display.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aviation.technomuses.ca/collections/artifacts/aircraft/Sopwith2F1Camel.shtml |title=Sopwith 2F.1 Camel |work=Canada Aviation and Space Museum |accessdate=19 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* F.1 Camel ''B6291'' restored to flying condition, is part of the Javier Arango Collection, in Paso Robles, California. It was previously owned by Al Letcher.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}
* A  [[Boulton &amp; Paul]] built F.1 ''F6314'' is on display at the Milestone of Flight exhibition at the [[Royal Air Force Museum]], London,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellis145&quot;&gt;Ellis 2008, p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; painted to represent an aircraft coded ''B'' of [[No. 65 Squadron RAF]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/london/collections/aircraft/aircraft_histories/74-A-18%20Camel%20F6314.pdf |title=Individual History: Sopwith F.1 Camel F6314/9206M |work=[[Royal Air Force Museum]] |year=2007 |accessdate=19 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* F.1 Camel ''C8228'', built by Sopwith in 1917, is on display at the [[National Naval Aviation Museum]] in Pensacola, Florida.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.airport-data.com/aircraft/A5658.html |title=Aircraft Data A5658, 1917 Sopwith F.1 Camel C/N C8228 |work=airport-data.com |year=2015 |accessdate=28 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reproductions===
{{Commonscat-inline|Sopwith Camel replicas}}
[[File:Sopwith F-1 Camel USAF.jpg|thumb|right|Replica of Camel F.1 flown by Lt. George Vaughn Jr., 17th Aero Squadron at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force|USAF Museum]]]]
* In 1969 [[Slingsby Aviation|Slingsby]] built a flyable Type T.57 Camel reproduction powered by a 145&amp;nbsp;hp Warner Scarab engine for use in a [[Biggles]] film. It is on display at the [[Fleet Air Arm Museum]], Yeovilton painted as ''B6401''.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson 1988, p. 349.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.fleetairarm.com/exhibits/planes.asp?plane=51 &quot;Sopwith Camel (replica) ('B6401').&quot;] ''Fleet Air Arm Museum''. Retrieved: 14 November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A reproduction F.1 Camel is on display at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] in [[Dayton, Ohio]]. This aircraft was built by museum personnel from original First World War factory drawings and was completed in 1974. It is painted and marked as the Camel flown by Lt. George A. Vaughn Jr. while flying with the [[17th Aero Squadron]].&lt;ref&gt;''United States Air Force Museum'' 1975, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Camel on display at the Cavanaugh Flight Museum in Addison, Texas is a full scale flying replica built by Dick Day from original factory drawings. The aircraft is fitted with original instruments, machine guns and an original Gnome rotary engine (a rare feature in replicas). It is painted in the scheme of the World War I flying ace Captain Arthur Roy Brown, a Canadian who flew with the Royal Air Force.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}
* In 1977, a flyable reproduction was built for Leisure Sport Ltd by the late Viv Bellamy at Lands End. Painted to represent ''B7270'' of 209 Squadron, RAF, the machine which Captain Roy Brown flew when officially credited with downing [[Baron Manfred von Richthofen]], it has a Clerget rotary engine of 1916 and was registered as G-BFCZ until 2003.  First seen at [[Brooklands Museum]] in January 1988 for Sir [[Thomas Sopwith]]’s 100th birthday celebrations, it was purchased by the Museum later that year, can be taken by road for exhibition elsewhere and is ground run regularly.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}
* [[Old Rhinebeck Aerodrome]] flies a reproduction Camel completed in 1992 with a 160&amp;nbsp;hp [[Gnome Monosoupape]] model 9N rotary, built by Nathaniel deFlavia and Cole Palen.  It replaced one of the Dick Day-built and -flown Camel reproductions formerly flown at Old Rhinebeck by Mr. Day in their weekend vintage airshows, which had left the Aerodrome's collection some years earlier.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}
* ''N8343'' constructed by Dick Day, is part of the Javier Arango Collection, in Paso Robles, California. Powered by a 160&amp;nbsp;hp Gnome Monosoupape rotary. It is regularly flown.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}
* ''B3889'' in The Vintage Aviator Collection, L.T.D., in Masterton, New Zealand. It was originally built by Carl Swanson for Gerry Thornhill. It is often flown. Powerplant is a 160&amp;nbsp;hp [[Gnome Monosoupape]] rotary engine.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}
* A reproduction is on display at the Canadian Museum of The Air in Langley, BC, Canada. Lacking an engine, a full reproduction wooden Rhone R9 130&amp;nbsp;hp engine has been installed.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}
* A reproduction is on display at the Royal Australian Airforce Museum, Perth.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://heinkelscooter.blogspot.com.au/2012/04/royal-australian-airforce-museum-perth.html |accessdate = 21 June 2015 |title = Royal Australian Airforce Museum, Perth}}&lt;/ref&gt; The engine is original and the propeller is suspected to also be genuine.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.raafawa.org.au/museum/replicas/item/231-sopwith-f-1-camel |accessdate = 21 June 2015 |title = Sopwith F.1 Camel}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A reproduction is currently under construction by the Northern Aeroplane Workshops for the [[Shuttleworth Collection]], England.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shuttleworth.org/shuttleworth_aircraft_details.asp?ID=11 &quot;Sopwith Camel.&quot;] ''Shuttleworth Collection.'' Retrieved: 19 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; 
* A replica Camel is being built in the United States by Koz Aero LLC, based on original factory drawings and using many original parts, including an original engine and instruments.&lt;ref&gt;Kozura, Tom. [http://www.kozaero.com/sopwith-f1-camel.html &quot;Sopwith F.1 Camel.&quot;] ''kozaero.com.'' Retrieved: 24 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Two reproductions are being built in France by John Shaw, one with an original Le Clerget 130 9B engine and the second with a new build Gnome Monosoupe 100&amp;nbsp;hp engine; both were built to the original plans and as authentically as materials allow.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.johnsshawaviation.co.uk/wordpress/sopwith-camel-f1-2/sopwith-camel-introduction &quot;Sopwith Camel Introduction.&quot;] ''John S Shaw Aviation'', Retrieved: 9 August 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A replica Sopwith F.1 Camel B5577 is on display at [[Montrose Air Station Heritage Centre]], Angus, Scotland.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}
* Airdrome Aeroplanes LTD, Holden MO USA manufactures a full-scale replica kit. http://www.airdromeaeroplanes.com/sopwithcamel.html

==Specifications (F.1 Camel)==
[[File:Sopwith F.1 Camel drawing.jpg|thumb|Sopwith F.1 Camel drawing]]
{{aircraft specifications
&lt;!-- if you do not understand how to use this template, please ask at [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Aircraft]] --&gt;
&lt;!-- please answer the following questions --&gt;
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=prop
&lt;!-- Now, fill out the specs.  Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses). If an item doesn't apply, like capacity, leave it blank. For additional lines, end your alt units with )&lt;/li&gt; and start a new, fully formatted line with &lt;li&gt; --&gt;
|ref=Quest for Performance,&lt;ref&gt;Loftin, LK, Jr. [http://www.hq.nasa.gov/pao/History/SP-468/cover.htm &quot;Quest for Performance: The Evolution of Modern Aircraft. NASA SP-468&quot;.] ''NASA.'' Retrieved: 22 April 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Profile Publications&lt;ref name = &quot;bruce 12&quot;&gt;Bruce 1965, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;
|crew=1
|length main=18 ft 9 in
|length alt=5.72 m
|span main=28 ft 0 in
|span alt=8.53 m
|height main=8 ft 6 in
|height alt=2.59 m
|area main=231 ft&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|area alt=21.46 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|empty weight main=930 lb
|empty weight alt=420 kg
|loaded weight main=1,453 lb
|loaded weight alt=659 kg
|max takeoff weight main=
|max takeoff weight alt=
|more general='''[[Zero-lift drag coefficient]]:''' 0.0378
*'''[[zero-lift drag coefficient|Drag area]]:''' {{convert|8.73|sqft|m2}}
*'''[[Aspect ratio (wing)|Aspect ratio]]:''' 4.11
|engine (prop)=[[Clerget]] [[Clerget 9B|9B]]
|type of prop=9-cylinder [[Rotary engine]]
|number of props=1
|power main=130 hp
|power alt=97 kW
|max speed main=113 mph
|max speed alt=182 km/h
|stall speed main=48 mph
|stall speed alt=77 km/h
|range main=300 mi ferry
|range alt=485 km
|ceiling main=19,000 ft
|ceiling alt=5,791 m
|climb rate main=1,085 ft/min
|climb rate alt=5.5 m/s
|loading main=6.3 lb/ft&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|loading alt=30.8 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|power/mass main=0.09 hp/lb
|power/mass alt=150 W/kg
|more performance=
*'''[[Lift-to-drag ratio]]:''' 7.7
|guns=2× 0.303 in (7.7 mm) [[Vickers machine gun]]s
}}

==Notable appearances in media==
[[File:Snoopy wwi ace lb.jpg|right|thumb|100px|[[Snoopy]]&lt;br&gt;piloting his&lt;br&gt;&quot;Sopwith Camel&quot;]]
The Camel appears in literature and popular media as:
* One of the aircraft flown by Canadian pilot [[Arthur Roy Brown]] in the 2008 movie ''[[The Red Baron (2008 film)|The Red Baron]]''.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}
* The single-seater scout flown by the Royal Flying Corps Squadron in the semi-autobiographical, First World War air combat book ''[[Winged Victory (novel)|Winged Victory]]'' written by [[Victor Maslin Yeates]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}
* The fighter flown by [[Biggles]] in the novels by [[W.E. Johns]] during Biggles's spell in 266 Squadron during the First World War.  The first collection of Biggles stories, titled ''The Camels are Coming'', was published in 1932.&lt;ref name = Butts&gt;{{cite book |last = Butts | first = D | editor1-first= T |editor1-last= Watkins |editor2-first = D | editor2-last = Jones |title=A Necessary Fantasy?: The Heroic Figure in Children's Popular Culture |publisher= [[Routledge|Garland Publishing]] | chapter = Biggles – Hero of the Air |location=New York |year=2000 |pages= [https://books.google.ca/books?id=3UTyDNVjYxoC&amp;pg=PA137 137–152] |isbn=0-8153-1844-8 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The &quot;plane&quot; of [[Snoopy]] in the ''[[Peanuts]]'' comic strip, when he imagines himself as a World War I flying ace and the nemesis of the [[Manfred von Richthofen|Red Baron]].&lt;ref&gt;Murphy and McNiece 2003, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The type of aircraft flown in the First World War by John and Bayard Sartoris in [[William Faulkner]]'s ''[[Flags in the Dust]]''.{{#tag:ref| Quote: &quot;Under fire from a pupil of Richthofen (the Red Baron), John's Camel caught fire over occupied France. Bayard's last sight of his twin brother was of John jumping out of his fighter feet first.&quot; Faulkner also wrote about the Camel (and Sartoris) in the story &quot;All the Dead Pilots&quot;.|group=Note}}
* In the Percy Jackson book ''[[The Titan's Curse]]'', Annabeth's father, a historian, uses a restored and modified Sopwith Camel to aid the heroes at one point during the novel.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}
* [[Robert Redford]]'s character flies a Sopwith Camel during the climactic aerial battle scene in the 1975 film ''[[The Great Waldo Pepper]]''.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}

==See also==
{{aircontent|
|related=
|similar aircraft=&lt;!--role configuration and era--&gt;
*[[Albatros D.V]]
*[[Fokker D.VI]]
*[[Fokker D.VII]]
*[[Hanriot HD.1]]
*[[Nieuport 27]]
*[[Royal Aircraft Factory S.E.5]]
*[[SPAD S.XIII]]
*[[Vickers F.B.19]]
|lists=
*[[List of aircraft of the Royal Air Force]]
|see also=
* [[Clayton &amp; Shuttleworth]]
}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Bowyer, Chaz. ''Sopwith Camel: King of Combat''. Falmouth, Cornwall, UK: Glasney Press, 1978. ISBN 0-9502825-7-X. 
* Bruce, J.M. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1955/1955%20-%200527.html &quot;Sopwith Camel: Historic Military Aircraft No 10: Part I.&quot;] ''[[Flight International|Flight]]'', 22 April 1955, pp.&amp;nbsp;527–532.
* Bruce, J.M. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1955/1955%20-%200560.html &quot;Sopwith Camel: Historic Military Aircraft No 10: Part II.&quot;] ''[[Flight International|Flight]]'', 29 April 1955. pp.&amp;nbsp;560–563.
* Bruce, J.M. &quot;Aircraft Profile No. 31. The Sopwith Camel F.1&quot; ''Profile Publications'', 1965.
* Bruce, J.M. ''War Planes of the First World War: Volume Two Fighters''. London:Macdonald, 1968. ISBN 0-356-01473-8.
* Clark, Alan. ''Aces High: The War In The Air Over The Western Front 1914 - 1918''. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1973. ISBN 0-297-99464-6.
* Davis, Mick. ''Sopwith Aircraft''. Ramsbury, Malborough, UK: The Crowood Press, 1999. ISBN 1-86126-217-5.
* Ellis, Ken. ''Wrecks &amp; Relics, 21st edition''. Manchester, UK: Crecy Publishing, 2008. ISBN 978-0-85979-134-2.
* Guttman, Jon: &quot;Sopwith Camel (Air Vanguard ; 3)&quot;. Oxford: Osprey Publishing, 2012. ISBN 978-1-78096-176-7.
* Jackson, A.J. ''British Civil Aircraft 1919-1972: Volume III''. London: Putnam, 1988. ISBN 0-85177-818-6.
* Jackson, Robert. ''Infamous Aircraft - Dangerous Designs and their Vices''. Barnsley, UK:Pen and Sword, 2005. ISBN 9781844151721.
* Leinburger, Ralf. ''Fighter: Technology, Facts, History''. London: Parragon Inc., 2008. ISBN 978-1-40549-575-2.
* Mason, Francis K. ''The British Fighter''. London: Putnam, 1992. ISBN 0 85177 852 6
* Murphy, Justin D. and Matthew A. McNiece. ''Military Aircraft, 1919-1945: An Illustrated History of their Impact''. Santa Barbara, California: ABC-CLIO, 2009. ISBN 1-85109-498-9.
* Ralph, Wayne. ''Barker VC: The Classic Story of a Legendary First World War Hero''. London: Grub Street, 1999. ISBN 1-902304-31-4.
* Robertson, Bruce. ''Sopwith: The Man and His Aircraft''. London: Harleyford, 1970. ISBN 0-900435-15-1.
* Sturtivant, Ray and Gordon Page. ''The Camel File''. Tunbridge Wells, Kent, UK: Air-Britain (Historians) Ltd., 1993. ISBN 0-85130-212-2.
* ''United States Air Force Museum Guidebook''. Wright-Patterson AFB, Ohio: Air Force Museum Foundation, 1975.
* Williams, Anthony G. and Emmanuel Gustin. ''Flying Guns: World War I and its Aftermath 1914–32''. Ramsbury, Wiltshire: Airlife, 2003. ISBN 1-84037-396-2.
* Winchester, Jim, ed. &quot;Sopwith Camel.&quot; ''Biplanes, Triplanes and Seaplanes'' (Aviation Factfile). London: Grange Books plc, 2004. ISBN 1-84013-641-3.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Sopwith Camel}}
* [http://oldrhinebeck.org/ORA/sopwith-camel/ Cole Palen/Nat deFlavia reproduction Camel at Old Rhinebeck Aerodrome]
* [http://www.airminded.net/camel/camel.html Camel photos and links to museums with Camels]
* [http://www.aviation.technomuses.ca/collections/artifacts/aircraft/Sopwith2F1Camel/ Canadian Aviation Museum Camel]
* [http://wio.ru/ww1a/sopwith.htm Sopwith fighters in Russia]
* [http://www.airdromeaeroplanes.com/sopwithcamel.html Sopwith Camel Replica Kit from Airdrome Aeroplanes]

{{Sopwith Aviation Company aircraft}}
{{wwi-air}}

[[Category:British fighter aircraft 1910–1919]]
[[Category:Military aircraft of World War I]]
[[Category:Sopwith aircraft|Camel]]
[[Category:Biplanes]]
[[Category:Single-engined tractor aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>e0kz800vxgrp7f93kihyq28jholors1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
