<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SS Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29209</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747968417</id>
      <parentid>742975044</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-05T14:48:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mdnavman</username>
        <id>7061136</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ Added template and categories.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21635">{{For|the World War I battleship of the same name|SMS Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:Kaiser wilhelm der grosse 01.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=SS ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse''
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship name=''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse''
|Ship namesake=[[William I, German Emperor]]
|Ship owner=[[Norddeutscher Lloyd|North German Lloyd]]
|Ship operator=
|Ship registry={{flagicon|German Empire}} [[Bremen]], Germany
|Ship route=
|Ship ordered=
|Ship builder=[[AG Vulcan Stettin|Stettiner Vulcan]], [[Stettin]]
|Ship original cost=
|Ship yard number=
|Ship way number=
|Ship laid down=1896
|Ship launched=4 May 1897
|Ship completed=
|Ship christened=4 May 1897
|Ship acquired=
|Ship maiden voyage=19 September 1897
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship identification=
|Ship fate=scuttled [[Battle of Río de Oro|in battle]], 26 August 1914
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship type=[[Ocean liner]]
|Ship tonnage=*14,349&amp;nbsp;gross tons ([[Gross register tonnage|GRT]])
*24,300 tons [[Displacement (ship)|displacement]]&lt;ref&gt;Schmalenbach p48&lt;/ref&gt; 
|Ship displacement=
|Ship length={{convert|655|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|65|ft|9.6|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft=
|Ship power={{convert|33000|ihp|kW|lk=in|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=*2 [[Marine steam engine#Triple or multiple expansion|triple expansion reciprocating engines]]
*2 screw propellers
|Ship speed={{convert|22.5|kn|lk=in|abbr=on}}
|Ship capacity=1,506 passengers 
|Ship crew=488
|Ship armament=*''In World War I''
** 6 × {{convert|105|mm|abbr=on}} guns
** 2 × {{convert|37|mm|abbr=on}} guns
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse''''' ([[German language|Ger]]. [[orthography|orth]]. ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Große'') was a German transatlantic [[ocean liner]] named after [[Wilhelm I, German Emperor]], the first head of state of the German Empire. Constructed in [[Stettin]] for the [[Norddeutscher Lloyd|North German Lloyd (NDL)]], she entered service in 1897 and was the first liner to have [[four funnel liner|four funnels]]. The first of four [[sister ship]]s built between 1903 and 1907 by NDL (the others being {{SS|Kronprinz Wilhelm}}, {{SS|Kaiser Wilhelm II}} and {{SS|Kronprinzessin Cecilie}}) she marked the beginning of a change in the way maritime supremacy was demonstrated in Europe at the beginning of the 20th century.

The ship began a new era in ocean travel and the novelty of having four funnels was quickly associated with size, strength, speed and above all luxury. Quickly established on the Atlantic, she gained the [[Blue Riband]] for Germany, a notable prize for the quickest trip from Europe to America which had been previously dominated by the British. In 1900, she was involved in [[1900 Hoboken Docks Fire|a fire]] in the port of New York which resulted in several deaths. She was also the victim of a [[naval ram]] in the French port of [[Cherbourg]] in 1906. With the advent of her sister ships, she was then converted to an all-third-class ship to take advantage of the lucrative immigrant market travelling to the United States.

Converted into an [[auxiliary cruiser]] during World War I, she was given orders to capture and destroy enemy ships within the first months of the war. Relatively successful, she destroyed several enemy ships before eventually being destroyed in the [[Battle of Río de Oro]] in August 1914, the first month of the war, by the British cruiser {{HMS|Highflyer}}. Her wreck was rediscovered in 1952 and then dismantled.
99 years after its sinking, the Sahrawi association called &quot;SALAM&quot;, chaired by Mr Ahmed Bazaid Cheikh el Mami, discovered an interesting part that contains the name of the boat ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unesco.org/new/fileadmin/MULTIMEDIA/HQ/CLT/pdf/KaiserWilhemderGrosse.pdf It was also announced by several bodies, including UNESCO]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

=== Origins, conception and construction ===
[[File:Teutonic leaving Liverpool.jpg|thumb|left|SS ''Teutonic'' of the [[White Star Line]], the inspiration for the future &quot;Four Flyers&quot;]]

At the end of the 19th century, the United Kingdom dominated maritime trade with the ocean liners of the principal maritime companies such as the [[Cunard Line|Cunard]] and the [[White Star Line]]. Having gained more influence in Europe after [[William I, German Emperor]], his grandfather, had created the [[German Empire]] in 1870, [[Wilhelm II, German Emperor|Emperor Wilhelm II]] wished to consolidate German influence on the sea and thus decrease that of the British.&lt;ref&gt;Mars, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; In 1889, the Emperor himself had attended a naval review in honour of the jubilee of his grandmother [[Queen Victoria]]. There he saw the strength and size of these British ships, notably the latest and then-largest liner owned by White Star, {{SS|Teutonic|1889|6}}. He particularly admired that these ships could easily be converted to auxiliary cruisers in time of conflict. Leaving a lasting impression, the emperor was heard to say that &quot;We must have some of these...&quot;, clearly showing they had had a lasting effect.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thegreatoceanliners.com/teutonic.html « ''Teutonic'' »], ''The Great Ocean Liners''. 15 July 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Norddeutscher Lloyd]]'', commonly known as NDL or North German Lloyd, was one of only two German maritime companies which had any influence in the hugely profitable transatlantic shipping market. Neither of these lines had up until now shown any interest in operating large liners. NDL, however, was the first company to name any of their liners in honour of members of the Imperial family, purely to flatter the emperor. The company also had important links with the naval architects [[AG Vulcan Stettin|AG Vulkan]] of [[Szczecin|Stettin]]. NDL then approached Vulkan and commissioned them to construct a new &quot;superliner&quot;, which was to be named ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse''. The new ship would set a new style for ocean liners. She was the largest and longest liner afloat and would have been the largest ever had it not been for {{SS|Great Eastern||2}} of 1860.&lt;ref&gt;Ferulli, p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;

The launching of the ship took place on 4 May 1897 in the presence of the Imperial family; it was the emperor who baptised the ship whose name honoured his grandfather Emperor William I, &quot;''the Great''&quot;. Construction and the internal decoration of the liner took place in [[Bremerhaven]] and before long she was ready to begin her regular crossings, her [[maiden voyage]] being scheduled for September the same year.&lt;ref&gt;Ferulli, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; The most striking feature of ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' was her four funnels, the first ship ever to sport such a quartet, which for the next two decades would be a symbol of size and safety.

=== Career ===
[[File:Colour drawing of the SS Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse by an unknown painter.jpg|thumb|Drawing of ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' by an unknown painter]]

''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' set out on her maiden voyage on 19 September 1897, travelling from [[Bremerhaven]] to [[Southampton]] and thence to New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller, p. 2&quot;&gt;Miller, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; With a capacity of 800 third-class passengers, the NDL had ensured that they would profit greatly from the immigrants wishing to leave the continent for a better [[standard of living]] in the United States. From her maiden voyage, she was the only superliner to cross the Atlantic with such speed and such media attention. In March 1898,&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller, p. 2&quot;/&gt; she successfully gained the [[Blue Riband]] with an average crossing speed of {{convert|22.3|kn|lk=in}}, thus establishing the new German competitiveness.&lt;ref&gt;Mars, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; The Blue Riband, an award given for the fastest crossing of the North Atlantic, east and westbound, had previously been held by the Cunard liner {{RMS|Lucania}}.&lt;ref&gt;Mars, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; This turn of events was closely watched by the maritime world of the era, who were eager to see how the British would retaliate.&lt;ref&gt;Piouffre, p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; However, the NDL soon lost the riband in 1900 to the new German superliner, {{SS|Deutschland|1900|2}} of the [[Hamburg America Line]].&lt;ref&gt;Le Goff, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; This change in events was acceptable to Germans, who were able to relax in the knowledge that they were still the owners of the fastest liner; however, NDL promptly ordered that ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' undergo a refit to ensure that they were the dominant German company.&lt;ref&gt;Burgess, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; This refit included the installation of [[wireless communication]], then new technology which allowed ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' to transmit telegraphic messages to a port, emphasising her image of security.&lt;ref&gt;Le Goff, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:The Four Flyers.jpg|thumb|left|Promotion of the &quot;Four Flyers&quot; of the [[Norddeutscher Lloyd|NDL]]]]
The NDL took the battle even further. 1901 saw the addition to their fleet of another four-funnel liner, named {{SS|Kronprinz Wilhelm}} in honour of [[William, German Crown Prince|Crown Prince William]], heir to the German throne, and they subsequently commissioned another two superliners, {{SS|Kaiser Wilhelm II}} and {{SS|Kronprinzessin Cecilie}} of 1903 and 1907 respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Ferulli, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt; From 1903 to 1907 the Blue Riband was held by SS ''Kaiser Wilhelm II''. The company stated that the four liners were of the renowned Kaiser class and decided to market them as the ''Four Flyers'', a reference to their speed and associations with the Blue Riband.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thegreatoceanliners.com/kpc.html SS ''Kronprinzessin Cecilie'' »], ''The Great Ocean Liners''. 15 July 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The career of ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'', despite its prestige, was not without incident. In June 1900 at her [[quay]] in [[Hoboken, New Jersey]], she was the victim of [[1900 Hoboken Docks Fire|a fire]] which killed one hundred staff who were trying to remove the threat.&lt;ref&gt;Server, p 43&lt;/ref&gt; Six years later, on 21 November 1906, she was the victim of a naval ram inflicted by {{RMS|Orinoco}},&lt;ref&gt;http://www.clydesite.co.uk/clydebuilt/viewship.asp?id=15297&lt;/ref&gt; a British ship of the [[Royal Mail Steam Packet Company|Royal Mail]], in [[Cherbourg]]. Five passengers lost their lives in the incident and the liner was found to have an {{convert|8|m|ft|adj=on}} tear in her hull.&lt;ref name=&quot;Le Goff, p. 22&quot;&gt;Le Goff, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; To make matters worse, ever growing technological evolution of steamships soon made NDL's express steamers outdated. Cunard's {{RMS|Lusitania}} and her sister {{RMS|Mauretania|1906|6}} outmatched their German rivals in all fields, and when the future White Star's {{RMS|Olympic}} entered service in 1911, luxury on the high seas was taken one step further. As a result, ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' was rebuilt in 1913 to carry third-class passengers only. It seemed that her glory was fading regardless of her career as the first &quot;four stacker&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;TGOL&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.thegreatoceanliners.com/kwdg.html|title= SS ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'', ''The Great Ocean Liners'' |date= |work= The Great Ocean Liners |accessdate=15 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 26 January 1907, she was charged with carrying passengers between the [[Mediterranean Sea]] and New York, effectively ending the public career of the first of the &quot;four flyers&quot;.{{citation needed|date=April 2015}}

=== First World War ===

From 1908, German naval captains had been receiving orders to make preparations in the event of a sudden war. In fact, ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' was soon fitted with cannons and thus transformed into an [[auxiliary cruiser]].&lt;ref name=TGOL/&gt; Across the world, supply ships carrying weapons and provisions were ready to convert merchant vessels into armed auxiliary cruisers. In August 1914, international relations reached crisis point. The United Kingdom and France declared war on Germany after the Germans invaded Belgium and Luxembourg. ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' was requisitioned and turned into an armed cruiser, painted in grey and black. Her commander at the time, Captain Reymann, operated not only under the rules of war, but also the rules of mercy.&lt;ref name=TGOL/&gt;
[[File:Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse fight painting 1914.jpg|thumb|right|Painting depicting the battle between ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' and HMS ''Highflyer'' in August 1914.]]
[[File:Kaiser Wilhelm Der Grosse's Wreck.jpg|thumb|The wreck of ''Kaiser Wilheim der Grosse'' off Africa]]
Reymann soon sank three ships, ''Tubal Cain'', ''Kaipara'', and ''Nyanza'', but only after taking their occupants on board. Further south in the Atlantic, ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' encountered two passenger liners: ''Galician'' and ''Arlanza''.&lt;ref name=TGOL/&gt; Reymann's first intention was to sink both vessels, but, discovering that they had many women and children on board, he let them go. In this early stage of the war, it was thought that it could be fought in a chivalrous fashion. However, soon it was to become a total war and ships would no longer be warned before being fired upon. As ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' approached the west coast of Africa, her coal bunkers were almost empty and needed refilling. She stopped at [[Río de Oro]], ([[Villa Cisneros]], former Spanish Sahara)  where German and Austrian colliers started the task of refuelling her.&lt;ref name=TGOL/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ferulli, p. 120&lt;/ref&gt;

The task of coaling was still going on on 26 August, when the British cruiser {{HMS|Highflyer|1898|6}} appeared. Reymann quickly prepared his ship and crew for battle and steamed out to engage the enemy after disembarking his prisoners of war. A fierce battle took place, but came to a dramatic end when ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' ran out of ammunition.&lt;ref name=TGOL/&gt; According to the Germans, rather than let the enemy capture the onetime pride of Germany, Reymann ordered the ship to be [[scuttling|scuttled]] using dynamite, which was already in position should this situation ever arise. On detonation, the explosives tore a massive hole in the ship, causing her to [[capsize]]. This version of events was disputed by the British, who stated that ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' had been badly damaged and sinking when Reymann ordered it to be abandoned. The British firmly believed that it was gunfire from HMS ''Highflyer'' which sank the German ship.&lt;ref&gt;''Kludas' Great Passenger Ships of the World''&lt;/ref&gt; Reymann managed to swim to shore, and he made his way back to Germany by working as a [[Stoker (occupation)|stoker]] on a neutral vessel. (Most of the crew were taken prisoner and held in the [[Amherst Internment Camp]] in [[Nova Scotia]] for the remainder of the war.)

The downfall of such great liners in the event of war was their huge fuel consumption. Most liners were subsequently converted from cruisers to [[hospital ship]]s or troopships.&lt;ref&gt;Burgess, p. 231&lt;/ref&gt;

== Characteristics ==

=== Technical aspects ===

''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' measured {{convert|200|m|ft}} long and had a [[Beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|20|m|ft}}. Her overall weight was 14,349 gross tonnes. In fact, her dimensions were similar to those of the 1860 ''Great Eastern'', which was the largest ship of its time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferulli, p. 118&quot;&gt;Ferulli, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; As already noted, her four funnels were her most unusual feature. People associated the safety of an ocean liner with the number of &quot;stacks&quot; or funnels they had. Some passengers would in fact refuse to board ships if they did not have four funnels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller, p. 4&quot;/&gt; In an age when ocean travel was not as safe as today, it was important to ensure that passengers felt at ease.&lt;ref&gt;Ferulli, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;

The special improvement in the arrangement of this steamer, as compared with other express steamers previously built by the NDL or other companies, consisted in the entire upper deck.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller, p. 2&quot;/&gt; Like many four-funnelled liners, ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' did not actually require that many. She had only two uptake shafts from the boiler rooms, which each branched into two to connect to the four funnels&amp;mdash;this design is the reason for the funnels being unequally spaced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller, p. 4&quot;&gt;Miller, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;

''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' became the first liner to have a commercial wireless telegraphy system when the Marconi Company installed one in February 1900.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferulli, p. 118&quot;/&gt; Communications were demonstrated with systems installed at the Borkum Island lighthouse and Borkum Riff lightship {{convert|30|km|nmi mi}} northwest of the island, as well as with British stations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ferulli, p. 118&quot;/&gt; The ship was powered by with two [[triple expansion]] [[reciprocating engines]] and had two {{convert|22|ft|3.75|in|m|1}} [[propellers]],&lt;ref&gt;https://archive.org/stream/monetarytimes31torouoft#page/351/mode/1up&lt;/ref&gt; allowing her to reach speeds of over {{convert|20|kn}}.&lt;ref name=TGOL/&gt; The engines were noted for their stability.&lt;ref name=NH&gt;[http://www.norwayheritage.com/p_ship.asp?sh=kaiwi « SS ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'', Norddeutscher Lloyd »], ''Norway Heritage''. Consulté le 15 July 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The engines were balanced on the Schlick system, which prevented movement being transferred to the body of the ship, thus reducing unpleasant vibration.

=== Interiors ===
[[File:First Class Restaurant of the SS Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse.jpg|thumb|The First Class Dining Room of ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'']]

As a large passenger ship, ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse'' was built to carry a maximum of 1,506 passengers: 206 first class; 226 second class; 1,074 third class. At the time of her construction, she had a crew numbering a mere 488. However, following her refit of 1913, her crew space was increased to 800. The décor of ship was in the style of [[Baroque Revival architecture|Baroque revival]], overseen by [[Johann Poppe]], who carried out all of the interior decoration. This was unique as usually a ship would have several interior designers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Le Goff, p. 22&quot;/&gt;

The interiors were graced with statues, mirrors, tapestries, gilding, and various portraits of the Imperial family. The interiors of her sister ships were also placed in the hands of Poppe. The first class salon was noted for its tapestries and its blue seating.&lt;ref&gt;Server, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; The smoking room, a traditionally male preserve, was made to look like a typical German inn.&lt;ref&gt;Piouffre, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; The dining room, capable of holding all passengers in one sitting, rose several decks and was crowned with a dome. The room also had columns and had its chairs fixed to the deck, a typical feature of ocean liners of the era.&lt;ref&gt;Piouffre, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt;

==Wreck==
On 6 September 2013 the Salam association [http://www.dakhla.org Salam Association] for the Protection of the Environment and Sustainable Development in Western Sahara found the part of the wreck that contains the name &quot;Der Grosse Wilhelm&quot; when they [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7t1oqxOhg1k filmed] the wreck under water. This was confirmed by the Moroccan Ministry of Culture on 8 October 2013.

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Sources ==
* {{en icon}} Burgess. Douglas D. ''Seize the trident: the race for superliner supremacy and how it altered the Great War''. McGraw-Hill Professional. 1999. 9780071430098
* {{en icon}} Miller. William H. Jr. ''The First Great Ocean Liners in Photographs''. Courier Dover Publications, 1984. 9780486245744
* {{fr icon}} Ferulli. Corrado. ''Au cœur des bateaux de légende''. Hachette Collections. 1998. 9782846343503
* {{fr icon}} Le Goff. Olivier ''Les Plus Beaux Paquebots du Monde''. 9782263027994
* {{fr icon}} Mars. Christian. ''Paquebots''. Sélection du ''Reader's Digest''. 2001. 9782709812863
* {{fr icon}} Piouffre. Gérard. ''L'Âge d'or des voyages en paquebot''. Éditions du Chêne. 2009. 9782812300028
* {{fr icon}} Server. Lee. ''Âge d'or des paquebots''. MLP. 1998. 2-7434-1050-7
* Matthias Trennheuser: Die innenarchitektonische Ausstattung deutscher Passagierschiffe zwischen 1880 und 1940, Hauschild-Verlag, Bremen 2010, ISBN 978-3-89757-305-5.

== External links ==
* [http://www.navegar-es-preciso.com/news/el-trasatlantico-kaiser-wilhelm-der-grose-un-express-steamer-imperial-de-finales-del-siglo-xix/ El trasatlántico &quot;Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse&quot; un express liner del siglo XIX] (Spanish)
{{commonscat-inline|Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse (ship, 1897)|SS ''Kaiser Wilhelm der Grosse''}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-ach|rec}}
{{S-bef|rows=2|before={{RMS|Lucania|3=2}}}}
{{S-ttl|title=Holder of the [[Blue Riband]] (Westbound)|years=1898–1900}}
{{S-aft|rows=2|after={{SS|Deutschland|1900|2}}}}
|-
{{S-ttl|title=[[Blue Riband|Atlantic Eastbound Record]] |years=1897–1900}}
{{End}}
{{Four funnels}}
{{Kaiser class ocean liners}}
{{Largest passenger ships}}
{{Norddeutscher Lloyd ships}}
{{1900 shipwrecks}}
{{August 1914 shipwrecks}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kaiser Wilhelm Der Grosse, Ss}}
[[Category:Ships of Norddeutscher Lloyd]]
[[Category:World War I cruisers of Germany]]
[[Category:World War I commerce raiders]]
[[Category:Auxiliary cruisers of the Imperial German Navy]]
[[Category:World War I passenger ships of Germany]]
[[Category:Blue Riband holders]]
[[Category:Kaiser-class ocean liners]]
[[Category:Four funnel liners]]
[[Category:1897 ships]]
[[Category:Ships built in Stettin]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1900]]
[[Category:Ship fires]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1914]]
[[Category:Scuttled vessels of Germany]]
[[Category:World War I shipwrecks in the Atlantic Ocean]]</text>
      <sha1>55r3pqe8mtm12ayqbt8irr4imbn9nu1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
