<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Battle Box</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2412720</id>
    <revision>
      <id>719955888</id>
      <parentid>710606051</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-12T20:36:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MageLam</username>
        <id>11902970</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9498">{{EngvarB|date=July 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2014}}
[[File:The Battle Box ticketing office, Fort Canning Park, Singapore - 20051104.jpg|thumb|The Battle Box ticketing office, Fort Canning Hill]]

'''The Battle Box''' is the popular name of the underground command centre constructed under [[Fort Canning]], [[Singapore]], as an emergency, bomb-proof command centre during the [[Malayan Campaign]] and the [[Battle of Singapore]]. The Battle Box is now a museum and tourist attraction.

==History==
Given its position in the western Pacific, Singapore had long been recognised as being strategically important for the [[Royal Navy]] to counter the growing influence of the Japanese, who were regarded as being the logical threat to Britain's interests in the Far East and the Pacific. To counter this, the [[Admiralty]] devised the [[Singapore strategy]], which required a well equipped naval base.&lt;ref name=McIntyre19-23&gt;McIntyre, 1979, p. 19–23&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, the [[Singapore Naval Base]] was constructed on the north shore of Singapore Island. The base, and its associated defences, required a large British military presence on the island.&lt;ref name=Elphick15&gt;Elphick, 1995, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fort Canning]] was used by the British army as their headquarters in Singapore, with a number of buildings built for this purpose in the 1920s. However, the lack of a headquarters combining all three services present in Singapore – the [[British Army|Army]], Royal Navy and [[Royal Air Force]] – was appreciated in 1936 by the then Colonel [[Arthur Percival]], the Chief of Staff to General [[William Dobbie|Dobbie]], 'General Officer Commanding, Malaya'. To remedy this, a Combined Operations Headquarters was proposed for Fort Canning.&lt;ref name=Bose40&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt;

===Construction===
Fort Canning is actually a small hill in the [[Central Area, Singapore|Central Area]] of Singapore Island. [[Stamford Raffles]] had built a residence there in 1823, but when the [[Straits Settlement]], which included Singapore, became a crown colony in 1867, a fort was constructed on the hill.&lt;ref name=Warren2&gt;Warren, 2002, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; However, by the turn of the century, the construction of other defences around Singapore rendered the Fort Canning fortifications surplus to requirements.&lt;ref name=Bose39&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;   

Located nearly 30 feet beneath the hill, the Battle Box complex was constructed as an emergency bunker for the Combined Operations Headquarters. Sources vary as to the number of rooms in the bunker; one states 22,&lt;ref name=Smith22&gt;Smith, 2005, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; while another, authored by the journalist who rediscovered the Battle Box, claims 29 rooms.&lt;ref name=Bose40&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; The bunker was constructed with one metre thick (3 feet) reinforced concrete walls to withstand direct hits from bombs and shells.&lt;ref name=Smith22&gt;Smith, 2005, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; The complex included a telephone exchange connected to all military and most civilian switchboards in Malaya,&lt;ref name=Bose45&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; various signals and operations rooms, sleeping quarters and latrines. The Battle Box also included a cipher room for coding and decoding messages, but by the time of the fall of Malaya, this work had been shifted elsewhere and the cipher room was used as sleeping quarters.&lt;ref name=Bose48-49&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 48-49&lt;/ref&gt; The Commander of Fixed Defences, Brigadier Curtis, co-ordinated the coastal artillery strikes on naval targets from the Battle Box.&lt;ref name=Bose60-61&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 60-61&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War Two===
[[File:BattleBoxEntrance.JPG|thumb|One of the entrances to the Battle Box museum]]
By 1941, the Battle Box was considered to be too small for its intended use.&lt;ref name=Bose70&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; Percival, having returned to Malaya as a [[lieutenant general]] and 'General Officer Commanding, Malaya', authorised construction of a new Combined Operations Headquarters at the Royal Air Force headquarters in Sime Road. The construction of this new headquarters began in 1941, and was finished in December of that year. Although Combined Operations Headquarters had been relocated to Sime Road, the Battle Box remained the Headquarters of [[Major General]] [[Frank Keith Simmons]], who as the 'Fortress Commander, Singapore', was responsible for the defence of Singapore Island. The Anti-Aircraft Gun Operations Room and Naval Extended Defences offices also remained at the Battle Box.&lt;ref name=Bose74&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese invaded Malaya on 8 December 1941 by moving south through Siam (now known as [[Thailand]]), as well as by making landings at [[Kota Baharu]], on the north east coast of Malaya.&lt;ref name=Bose87&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; Rapidly retreating through Malaya, Allied forces were forced back to Singapore Island by 31 January 1942.&lt;ref name=Bose92&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 February, Japanese troops then crossed the [[Straits of Johor]] at the [[Battle of Sarimbun Beach]] on the north-west coast of Singapore Island, followed by a second landing near the Kranji River, at the [[Battle of Kranji]].

The Sime Road location had to be abandoned during the [[Battle of Kranji]],&lt;ref name=Bose101&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; with Percival shifting the Combined Operations Headquarters to Fort Canning on 11 February 1942.&lt;ref name=Warren247&gt;Warren, 2002, p. 247&lt;/ref&gt; By the latter stages of the battle for Singapore, the Japanese were bombing the Central Area of Singapore, including Fort Canning, at will. Fort Canning was also within range of the Japanese artillery, forcing personnel into the Battle Box. There were around 500 officers and men in the Battle Box in the latter stages of the battle.&lt;ref name=Bose17&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

The decision to surrender Singapore was made by Percival in a meeting on the morning of 15 February 1942. Held in the 'Commander, Anti-Aircraft Defence Room' of the Battle Box,&lt;ref name=Bose64&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; a number of senior officers were in attendance, including Generals [[Gordon Bennett (general)|Bennett]], [[Lewis Heath|Heath]] and Simmons. With diminishing water supplies, and no viable options for launching a counterattack, the decision was made to seek terms with the Japanese.&lt;ref name=Elphick355&gt;Elphick, 1995, p. 355&lt;/ref&gt;

The Battle Box was later occupied by Japanese forces during the [[Japanese Occupation of Singapore]] and used for communications right up to the time of the Japanese surrender.&lt;ref name=Bose120&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 120&lt;/ref&gt; At the conclusion of the Second World War, the Battle Box complex itself appears to have been looted in the aftermath of the Japanese surrender. Upon re-entry to the complex in 1988, evidence of a number of excavations were observed, presumably attempts to find loot that may have been concealed by the Japanese.&lt;ref name=Bose54&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;

==Present day==
After the war, Fort Canning was again used by the British as the Singapore Base District Headquarters. The British handed over Fort Canning to the [[Singapore Armed Forces]] in 1968–69, and the buildings of Fort Canning served for a time as the [[Singapore Command and Staff College]]. The Battle Box, having remained empty and unused since the war, was sealed off in the late 1960s due to safety concerns&lt;ref name=Bose127&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt; and its exact location forgotten. The Battle Box was brought back into the public eye when it was &quot;rediscovered&quot; by a journalist in 1988, who was following a number of leads claiming the existence of an underground bunker complex on Fort Canning Hill.&lt;ref name=Bose23-36&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 23-36&lt;/ref&gt;

The Battle Box was developed into a museum, depicting the final days of the Battle of Singapore. The museum was formally opened on 15 February 1997, on the 55th anniversary of the surrender of Singapore.&lt;ref name=Bose127&gt;Bose, 2005, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Battle of Singapore]]
* [[Fort Canning]]
* [[Singapore strategy]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Bose|first=Romen|year=2005|title=Secrets of the Battlebox: The History and Role of Britain’s Command HQ in the Malayan Campaign|publisher=Marshall Cavendish Editions|location=Singapore|isbn=978-981-261-064-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Elphick|first=Peter|year=1995|title=Singapore: The Pregnable Fortress: A Study in Deception, Discord and Desertion|publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton|location=London |isbn=0-34061-316-5}}
* {{cite book|last=McIntyre|first=W. David|year=1979|title=The Rise and Fall of the Singapore Naval Base|series=Cambridge Commonwealth series|publisher=MacMillan Press|location=London |isbn=0-33324-867-8}} 
* {{cite book|last=Smith|first=Colin|year=2005|title=Singapore Burning: Heroism and Surrender in World War II|publisher=Viking|location=London|isbn=978-0-670-91341-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Warren|first=Alan|year=2001|title=Singapore 1942: Britain's Greatest Defeat|publisher=Talisman|location=Singapore|isbn=978-981-04-5320-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|The Battle Box}}

* Battlebox Official Website [http://battlebox.com.sg]

{{Major tourist attractions in Singapore}}
{{coord missing|Singapore}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Box}}
[[Category:1997 establishments in Singapore]]
[[Category:Bunkers]]
[[Category:Military and war museums in Singapore]]
[[Category:Military of Singapore under British rule]]
[[Category:Museum Planning Area]]
[[Category:Museums established in 1997]]
[[Category:World War II sites in Singapore]]</text>
      <sha1>rl5n0fys3qkjdnxno4sijo045zdpdh4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
