<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Battle of the Somme (film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>276527</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742303210</id>
      <parentid>742290880</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-02T22:32:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>P0mbal</username>
        <id>5151728</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>consensus of sources has duration 74 minutes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32149">{{Use British English|date=April 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2014}}
{{See also|Battle of the Somme|Hawthorn Ridge Redoubt}}
{{Infobox film
| name           = The Battle of the Somme
| image          = [[File:Somme-film-ad.jpg]]
| caption        = [[Yorkshire Evening Post]] advert for the film, 1916
| director       =
| producer       = W. F. Jury
| writer         =
| music          = J. Morton Hutcheson (original 1916 medley)&lt;br&gt;[[Laura Rossi]] (2006)
| cinematography = G. H. Malins&lt;br&gt;J. B. McDowell
| editing        = [[Charles Urban]]&lt;br&gt;G. H. Malins
| distributor    = British Topical Committee for War Films
| released       = {{film date|1916|8|21|df=yes}}
| runtime        = 74 minutes
| country        = United Kingdom
| language       = Silent film&lt;br&gt;[[English language|English]] intertitles
| budget         =
}}
'''''The Battle of the Somme''''' (US title, ''Kitchener's Great Army in the Battle of the Somme''), is a 1916 British [[documentary film|documentary]] and [[propaganda]] [[war film]], shot by two official [[cinematographer]]s, [[Geoffrey Malins]] and John McDowell. The film depicts the [[British Army]] in the preliminaries and early days of the [[Battle of the Somme]] (1 July – 18 November 1916). The film had its [[première]] in London on 10 August 1916 and was released generally on 21 August. The film depicts [[trench warfare]], marching infantry, artillery firing on German positions, British troops waiting to attack on 1 July, treatment of wounded British and German soldiers, British and German dead and captured German equipment and positions. A scene during which British troops crouch in a ditch then &quot;go over the top&quot; was staged for the camera behind the lines.

The film was a great success, watched by about 20 million people in Britain in the first six weeks of exhibition and distributed in eighteen other countries. A second film, covering a later phase of the battle, was released in 1917 as ''The Battle of the Ancre and the Advance of the Tanks''. In 1920 the film was preserved in the film archive of the [[Imperial War Museum]]. In 2005 it was inscribed on [[UNESCO]]'s [[Memory of the World Programme|Memory of the World Register]] and digitally restored, and in 2008, was released on DVD. ''The Battle of the Somme'' is significant as an early example of film propaganda, an historical record of the battle and as a popular source of footage illustrating the [[First World War]].
{{TOC limit|2}}

==Film==

===Content===

''The Battle of the Somme'' is a black-and-white [[silent film]] in five parts, with sequences divided by [[intertitles]] summarising the contents. The first part shows preparations for battle behind the British front line; there are sequences of troops marching towards the front, French peasants continuing their farm work in rear areas, the stockpiling of munitions, Major-General [[Beauvoir De Lisle]] addresses the [[29th Division (United Kingdom)|29th Division]] and some of the preparatory [[Barrage (artillery)|bombardment]] by [[Ordnance QF 18 pounder|18-pounder]], [[BL 60 pounder gun|60-pounder]] and [[QF 4.7 inch Gun Mk I–IV|4.7-inch]] guns, [[BL 6 inch 30 cwt howitzer|6-inch]], [[BL 9.2-inch howitzer|9.2-inch]] howitzers and [[2 inch Medium Mortar|2-inch mortars]] is shown. The second part depicts more preparations, troops moving into front line trenches, the intensification of the artillery barrage by [[BL 12 inch railway howitzer|12-inch]] and [[BL 15-inch howitzer|15-inch]] howitzers, a [[9.45 inch Heavy Mortar|9.45-inch Heavy Mortar]] and the detonation of the mine under the [[Hawthorn Ridge Redoubt]]. Part three begins with the attack on [[First day on the Somme]] (1 July 1916), with some re-enactments and shows the recovery of British wounded and German prisoners. The fourth part shows more scenes of British and German wounded, the clearing of the battlefield and some of the aftermath. The final part shows scenes of devastation, including the ruins of the village of [[Mametz, Somme|Mametz]], British troops at rest and preparations for the next stage of the advance.{{sfn|Smither|2008|pp=4–28}}

==Production==

===Background===
[[File:Hawthorn Ridge mine 1 July 1916.jpg|thumb|{{center|[[Hawthorn Ridge Redoubt]] mine, 1 July 1916. Photograph by [[Ernest Brooks (photographer)|Ernest Brooks]].{{efn|&quot;The ground where I stood gave a mighty convulsion. It rocked and swayed. I gripped hold of my tripod to steady myself. Then for all the world like a gigantic sponge, the earth rose high in the air to the height of hundreds of feet. Higher and higher it rose, and with a horrible grinding roar the earth settles back upon itself, leaving in its place a mountain of smoke.&quot;{{sfn|Malins|1920|p=163}}}}}}]]

On 2 November 1915, the British Topical Committee for War Films, representing British [[newsreel]] producers and supported by the [[War Office]], despatched two cameramen to France. Geoffrey Malins of [[Gaumont British]] and Edward Tong of Jury's Imperial Pictures, were to shoot footage for short newsreels.{{sfn|Badsey|1983|p=104}} By early June Tong had fallen ill and been sent home but he and Malins had made five series of newsreels, which although well-received, had failed to impress the British cinema trade.{{sfn|Badsey|1983|p=104}} John McDowell, of the [[British and Colonial Films|British &amp; Colonial]] film company, volunteered to replace Tong and left for France on 23 June 1916.{{sfn|Badsey|1983|p=104}} On 24 June, the British Army began the preparatory artillery bombardment of German positions for the [[Battle of the Somme]].{{sfn|Prior|Wilson|2005|p=61}}

===Photography===

Malins and McDowell shot the film between 26 June and {{nowrap|7–9 July}}. Malins filmed in the vicinity of [[Beaumont-Hamel|Beaumont Hamel]], on attachment with the 29th Division (VIII Corps);  McDowell worked further south near [[Fricourt]] and Mametz with the [[7th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|7th Division]] (XV Corps).{{sfn|Duffy|2006|p=93}}

Before the battle, Malins worked at the north end of the British Somme sector, photographing troops on the march and heavy artillery west of [[Gommecourt, Pas-de-Calais|Gommecourt]]. De Lisle suggested to Malins that he view the bombardment of Beaumont Hamel from Jacob's Ladder near White City, an abrupt drop down the side of a valley, with about {{nowrap|25 steps}} cut into the ground, showing up white because of the chalk.{{sfn|Cave|1994|p=51}} Sappers had dug the large mine under [[Mines on the first day of the Somme|Hawthorn Ridge]] in front of White City.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.army.mod.uk/firstworldwarresources/archives/1555/white-city-located-near-beaumont-hamel-on-the-somme-1916&lt;/ref&gt; German shells were falling as Malins made his way to Lanwick Street Trench. Malins had to rise above the parapet to remove sandbags and then set up his camera, which was camouflaged with sackcloth. Malins returned to film the speech by de Lisle to the 2nd [[Royal Fusiliers]], after which Malins heard of the postponement of the battle for {{nowrap|48-hours}}. Malins returned to White City to film the bombardment of the Hawthorn Ridge Redoubt by trench mortars, during which there were three misfires, which destroyed a trench-mortar position nearby.{{sfn|Cave|1994|pp=51–52}}

[[File:The Battle of the Somme film image1.jpg|thumb|{{center|Scene of British troops advancing, staged for the film}}]]

On 1 July Malins filmed troops of the 1st Battalion [[Lancashire Fusiliers]] waiting to advance at Beaumont Hamel from a [[sunken lane]] in no man's land, which had been occupied by digging a {{convert|2|×|5|ft|m|adj=on}} tunnel overnight. Malins then went back to Jacob's Ladder to film the explosion of the Hawthorn Ridge mine. At {{nowrap|7:19 a.m.}} Malins began filming and the mine detonation shook the ground as troops of [[Royal Engineers]] advanced on either side to occupy the crater. Later in the day a shell explosion damaged the camera tripod; Malins repaired the tripod and in the evening filmed roll-calls.{{sfn|Cave|1994|pp=53–54}} Next day Malins shot film at [[Capture of La Boisselle|La Boisselle]] before leaving for London around 9 July.{{sfn|Smither|2008|p=3}} Malins returned to France, and from {{nowrap|12–19 July}} filmed sequences of shellfire and of troops advancing from trenches, which were staged for the camera at a [[Third Army (United Kingdom)|Third Army]] mortar school near [[Saint-Pol-sur-Ternoise|St Pol]].{{sfn|Smither|2008|p=3}} 

McDowell reached the Somme front after Malins and began filming British preparations on 28 or 29 June, to the east of [[Albert, Somme|Albert]].  He covered the opening day of the battle from the vicinity of [[Carnoy]] and from the dressing-station at Minden Post. The success of the 7th Division enabled McDowell to film captured German trenches near [[Capture of Fricourt|Fricourt]] and [[Capture of Mametz|Mametz]].{{sfn|Smither|2008|p=3}}

===Editing===
[[File:Hawthorn crater Somme Nov 1916 IWM Q 1527.jpg|thumb|{{center|Hawthorn Ridge crater November 1916, photograph by Ernest Brooks}}]]

On 10 July, Brigadier General [[John Charteris]] reported to the War Office that some {{convert|8000|ft|m}} of [[footage]] had been shot and recommended that sections of film should be released as soon as possible. Footage was first viewed as a [[Negative (photography)|negative]] on 12 July and [[Charles Urban]] is thought to have begun work on the film as [[Film editing|editor]], with the assistance of Malins.{{sfn|Fraser|Robertshaw|Roberts|2009|p=172}} Urban later claimed to have proposed that the film be issued as a [[feature film]] rather than in short sections. The change in format was agreed with the British Topical Committee for War Films and a {{convert|5000|ft|m}} cut of the film was ready by 19 July.{{sfn|Fraser|Robertshaw|Roberts|2009|p=172}} Much footage was [[censored|cut]] from the public version, as the War Office wanted the film to contain images that would support the war effort and raise morale.{{sfn|Duffy|2006|p=93}} A {{nowrap|77-minute}} version was ready by 31 July and a rough cut was screened at the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War I)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF) General Headquarters (GHQ) at [[Montreuil, Pas-de-Calais]] and at the [[Fourth Army (United Kingdom)|Fourth Army]] headquarters. The commander Lieutenant-General [[Henry Rawlinson, 1st Baron Rawlinson|H. Rawlinson]] said &quot;some of it is very good but it cut out many of the horrors in dead and wounded&quot;.{{sfn|Philpott|2009|p=302}}{{sfn|Fraser|Robertshaw|Roberts|2009|p=173}} The film was shown to the [[Secretary of State for War]], [[David Lloyd George]] on 2 August and members of the cinema trade late on 7 August, the day that the film received final approval for release.{{sfn|Fraser|Robertshaw|Roberts|2009|p=173}}

===Release===

The film comprises five reels and is {{nowrap|77-minutes}} long.{{sfn|Reeves|1983|p=467}} The first screening took place on 10 August 1916 at the [[Scala Theatre]], to an audience of journalists, [[Foreign Office]] officials, cinema trade figures and officers of the [[Imperial General Staff]]. The screening was preceded by the reading of a letter from Lloyd George, exhorting the audience to &quot;see that this picture, which is in itself an epic of self-sacrifice and gallantry, reaches everyone. Herald the deeds of our brave men to the ends of the earth. This is your duty.&quot;{{sfn|Badsey|1983|p=99}}

A musical medley with excerpts from classical, folk, contemporary and popular pieces, to be played live in cinemas by accompanying musicians, was devised by [[J. Morton Hutcheson]] and published  in [[The Bioscope]] on 17 August 1916.{{sfn|Haggith|2002|pp=11–24}} On 21 August, the film began showing simultaneously in thirty-four London [[movie theater|cinemas]] and opened in provincial cities the following week, when the film was shown simultaneously at twenty cinemas in [[Birmingham]], at least twelve cinemas in [[Glasgow]] and [[Edinburgh]], six cinemas in [[Cardiff]] and three in [[Leeds]].{{sfn |Fraser|Robertshaw|Roberts|2009|p=173}}{{sfn|Badsey|1983|p=108}}{{sfn|Reeves|1997|p=14}} The [[British Royal Family|Royal Family]] received a private screening at [[Windsor Castle]] on 2 September; the film was eventually shown in more than eighteen countries.{{sfn|Badsey|1983|pp=108, 100}}

==Reception==

===Britain===
[[File:The Battle of the Somme film image2.jpg|thumb|{{center|[[Film frame|Frame]] from sequence 34: ''British Tommies rescuing a comrade under shell fire.'' (''This man died 30 minutes after reaching the trenches.''){{sfn|Smither|2002|pp=390–404}}{{efn|Smither described this sequence as a symbol of the First World War, &quot;one of the most famous images in the Imperial War Museum's collections&quot; and that the identity of the &quot;trench rescuer&quot; is unknown.{{sfn|Smither|2002|pp=390–404}}}}}}]]

The popularity of the film was unprecedented and cinemas played the film for longer runs than usual, often to packed houses, while some arranged additional screenings to meet demand.{{sfn|Reeves|1986|p=14}} The film is thought to have achieved attendance figures of twenty million in its first six weeks of release.{{sfn|Reeves|1986|p=15}} The film also attracted more middle-class audiences, some of whom had never been to a cinema before.{{sfn|Reeves|1986|p=14}} William Jury, as the film's booking director, initially charged exhibitors £40, with the fee decreasing by £5 a week; after two months, a reduced fee of £6 for three nights put the film within the price range of village halls wishing to show the film.{{sfn|Badsey|1983|p=108}} By October 1916, the film had been booked by more than two thousand cinemas in Britain, earning over £30,000.{{sfn|Reeves|1986|p=472}}
British authorities showed the film to the public as a [[morale]]-booster and in general it met with a favourable reception. [[The Times]] reported on 22 August that

{{quote|Crowded audiences ... were interested and thrilled to have the realities of war brought so vividly before them, and if women had sometimes to shut their eyes to escape for a moment from the tragedy of the toll of battle which the film presents, opinion seems to be general that it was wise that the people at home should have this glimpse of what our soldiers are doing and daring and suffering in Picardy.|The Times, 22 August 1916{{sfn|Times|1916|p=3}}}}

Some members of the audience considered it immoral to portray scenes of violence; the [[Dean (religion)|Dean]] of [[Durham, England|Durham]] protested &quot;against an entertainment which wounds the heart and violates the very sanctity of bereavement&quot;. Others complained that such a serious film shared the cinema programme with [[comedy film]]s.{{sfn|Badsey|1983|p=110}} On 28 August, the [[Yorkshire Evening Post]] printed the comment, attributed to Lloyd George, &quot;If the exhibition of this Picture all over the world does not end War, God help civilisation&quot;.{{sfn|Philpott|2009|p=303}} The film was shown to British troops in France from 5 September; Lieutenant-Colonel Rowland Feilding, an officer who saw the film in a muddy field near [[Morlancourt]], described it as &quot;a wonderful and most realistic production&quot; but criticised the film for failing to record the sound of rifles and machine-guns, although there was an artillery accompaniment from guns firing nearby.{{sfn|Duffy|2006|p=93}} Feilding suggested that the film could reassure new recruits, by giving them some idea of what to expect in battle; the [[intertitle]]s were forthright, describing images of injury and death.{{sfn|Feilding|1929|pp=109–110}}

===International===
The film was shown in [[New Zealand]] in October 1916. On 12 October, the [[Wellington]] [[The Evening Post (New Zealand)|''Evening Post'']] ran an advertisement for the film, describing it as &quot;the extraordinary films of 'the big push' and &quot;an awe-inspiring, glorious presentation of what our heroes are accomplishing today&quot;.{{sfn|Evening Post|1916a|p=2}} In a review published on 16 October, it was written that &quot;these pictures of the Battle of the Somme are a real and valuable contribution to the nation's knowledge and a powerful spur to national effort&quot;.{{sfn|Evening Post|1916b|p=3}} The film premièred in [[Australia]] on 13 October at [[Hoyts|Hoyt's Picture Theatre]] in [[Melbourne]]. The Melbourne ''[[The Argus (Australia)|Argus]]'' considered that after the attack sequence, &quot;... you are not in a Melbourne picture theatre, but in the very forefront of the Somme battle&quot; and called the film &quot;this moving reality of battle&quot;.{{sfn|The Argus|1916|p=18}}

The film and its reception was of great interest to Germans, who were able to read a report from a neutral reporter in London, filed in the {{lang|de|''[[Berliner Tageblatt]]''}}. British cinema was said to be taking a serious view of the war, helped by the government, which had arranged for the production of &quot;real war films&quot;, ''The Battle of the Somme'' was &quot;absorbing&quot; and had attracted huge audiences. German troops recovered a letter from a British civilian, who had seen the film on 26 August and written to a soldier in France, describing the issue of a leaflet to each filmgoer, that stated that the film was not entertainment but an official film. Having viewed the film, the writer was sure that it would enlighten the audience in a way never before achieved.{{sfn|Duffy|2006|pp=93–94}}

===Other films===
During the second week of August, the [[George V of the United Kingdom|King]], [[Herbert Henry Asquith|Prime Minister]] and Lloyd George toured the Western Front and were filmed by Malins. The War Office released the film in October as ''The King Visits His Armies in the Great Advance''.{{sfn|Philpott|2009|p=323}} Malins made a third film ''The Battle of the Ancre and the Advance of the Tanks'' which opened in January 1917.{{sfn|Philpott|2009|p=369}}{{efn|&quot;I'd like to see a tank come down the stalls/Lurching to rag-time tunes, or 'Home sweet home'/And there'd be no more jokes in Music-halls/To mock the riddled corpses round Bapaume.&quot; (Siegfried Sassoon, ''Blighters'' 1917).{{sfn|Philpott|2009|p=369}}}} In the same month a German film ''With our Heroes on the Somme'' was shown but &quot;lacked the immediacy&quot; of the British film, being re-enactments at training establishments behind the lines, which received a lukewarm reception.{{sfn|Philpott|2009|p=311}} A booklet to accompany the film proclaimed that it  depicted &quot;the German will in war&quot; and implied that the enemies of Germany were using colonial troops to undermine &quot;German honour&quot;.{{sfn|Sheffield|2003|p=154}} Malins' final feature film ''The German Retreat and the Battle of Arras'' was released in June 1917, showing the destruction of Péronne and the first British troops across the Somme, following-up the German withdrawal; the film failed to attract the audiences of 1916.{{sfn|Philpott|2009|pp=461–462}}

==Preservation==
In 1920 the original [[nitrate film|nitrate negative]] was passed to the [[Imperial War Museum]] for preservation. A nitrate protection [[Master recording|archive master]] was made in 1921 and an [[safety film|acetate safety]] master in 1931. The nitrate masters were destroyed in the 1970s after the onset of irreversible nitrate decomposition.{{sfn|UNESCO|2012|p=438}} Excerpts have been taken for [[Television documentary|television documentaries]], including [[The Great War (documentary)|''The Great War'']] (1964. [[BBC]]), ''[[The Great War and the Shaping of the 20th Century]]'' (1996, [[PBS]]) and ''The First World War'' (2003, [[Channel 4]]).{{sfn|Smither|2004|p=1}} The film was offered on [[VHS]] in 1987, as the first title from the Imperial War Museum film archive to be released on video.{{sfn|Smither|2004|p=7}} In 2005, ''The Battle of the Somme'' was inscribed on [[UNESCO]]'s [[Memory of the World|Memory of the World Register]] for the preservation of global documentary heritage. The film was described by UNESCO as a &quot;compelling documentary record of one of the key battles of the First World War [and] the first feature-length documentary film record of combat produced anywhere in the world&quot; and had &quot;played a major part in establishing the methodology of documentary and propaganda film.&quot;{{sfn|Smither|2004|p=5}}{{sfn|UNESCO|2012|p=438}}

==Recent screenings==
On 22 October 2006, after a [[film restoration|restoration]] project. a refined version of the film was screened at the [[Queen Elizabeth Hall]] in London, accompanied by the [[Philharmonia Orchestra]] performing an original orchestral score by [[Laura Rossi]].{{sfn|Times|2006|p=17}} The restoration was later nominated for an Archive Restoration or Preservation Project award by the Federation of Commercial Audiovisual Libraries.{{sfn|FOCAL|2007|nopp=y}} In November 2008, the restored film was released on [[DVD]], to mark the 90th anniversary of the [[Armistice with Germany]] in 1918. The DVD included the score by Laura Rossi, an accompanying 1916 musical medley, a commentary by Roger Smither, a film archivist at the Imperial War Museum and interviews with Smither, Rossi, Toby Haggith (film archivist) and Stephen Horne (silent film musician) on the reconstruction of the contemporary medley; film fragments and missing scenes were also included in the DVD.{{sfn|McWilliams|2009|pp=130–133}}

In 2012, with the support of the Imperial War Museum, there were public screenings of the restored film accompanied by a live orchestra playing the soundtrack of Rossi's music.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.focalint.org/assets/files/2012_02_battlesomme.pdf Press release 20 January 2012]&lt;/ref&gt; Somme100 FILM has a target of a hundred performances of the film by amateur and professional orchestras in the centenary year, between July 2016 and July 2017.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.somme100film.com/ Somme100 FILM - ''The Battle of the Somme Centenary Tour'' - 100 Performances of Battle of the Somme]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|World War I}}
* [[The Somme (film)|The Somme (1927)]]
* [[The Somme – From Defeat to Victory|The Somme – From Defeat to Victory (2006)]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
;Books
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Cave|1994}}
|title=Beaumont Hamel |last=Cave |first=N. |authorlink= |year=1994 |publisher=Leo Cooper |location=Barnsley |edition= |isbn=0-85052-398-2}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Duffy|2006}}
|title=Through German Eyes: The British and the Somme 1916 |last=Duffy |first=C. |year=2007 |orig-year=2006 |authorlink=Christopher Duffy|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicholson |location=London |edition=Phoenix |isbn=978-0-7538-2202-9}}
* {{Cite book |ref={{harvid|Feilding|1929}}
|title=War Letters to a Wife: France and Flanders, 1915–1919 |last=Feilding |first=R. |year=1929 |location=London |publisher=Medici |oclc=752947224}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Malins|1920}}
|title=How I Filmed the War : A Record of the Extraordinary Experiences of the Man Who Filmed the Great Somme Battles, etc |last=Malins |first=G. H. |authorlink= |year=1920 |publisher=Herbert Jenkins |location=London |edition= |url=http://ia700307.us.archive.org/12/items/ifilmedwar00maliuoft/ifilmedwar00maliuoft.pdf |accessdate=5 October 2013 |oclc=246683398}}
* {{Cite book |ref={{harvid|Philpott|2009}}
|title=Bloody Victory: The Sacrifice on the Somme and the Making of the Twentieth Century |last=Philpott |first=W. |authorlink= |year=2009 |publisher=Little, Brown |location=London |edition=1st |isbn=978-1-4087-0108-9}}
* {{Cite book |ref={{harvid|Prior|Wilson|2005}}
|last1=Prior |first1=R. |last2=Wilson |first2=T. |title=The Somme |publisher=Yale University Press |year=2005 |isbn=0-300-10694-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Reeves|1986}}
|title=Official British Film Propaganda During the First World War |last=Reeves |first=N. |authorlink= |year=1986 |publisher=Croom Helm |location=London |edition= |isbn=0-70994-225-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Fraser|Robertshaw|Roberts|2009}}
|title=Ghosts on the Somme: Filming the Battle, June–July 1916 |last1=Fraser |first1=Alastair |last2=Robertshaw |first2=Andrew |last3=Roberts |first3=Steve |authorlink= |year=2009 |publisher=[[Pen and Sword Books]] |location=Barnsley |isbn=1-84415-836-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Sheffield|2003}}
|title=The Somme |last=Sheffield |first=G. |authorlink=Gary Sheffield (historian) |publisher=Cassell |year=2003 |location=London |isbn=0-304-36649-8}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Smither|2008}}
|title=The Battle of the Somme (DVD viewing guide) |last=Smither |first=R. B. N. |year=2008 |publisher=Imperial War Museum |edition=2nd rev. |location=London |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/upload/package/100/Somme%20DVD/documents/viewing_guide.pdf |accessdate=6 October 2013 |isbn=0-90162-794-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|UNESCO|2012}}
|title=Memory of the World: The Battle of the Somme |author=[[UNESCO]] |year=2012 |publisher=UNESCO |url=http://www.unesco.org/new/en/communication-and-information/flagship-project-activities/memory-of-the-world/register/full-list-of-registered-heritage/registered-heritage-page-8/the-battle-of-the-somme/#c183653 |accessdate=6 October 2013 |isbn=978-92-3-104237-9}}

;Journals
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Badsey|1983}}
|title=Battle of the Somme: British War-Propaganda |last=Badsey |first=S. |year=1983 |journal=Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television |volume=3 |issue=2 |publisher=Routledge |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01439688300260081 |accessdate=21 June 2012 |issn=0143-9685 |doi=10.1080/01439688300260081}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Haggith|2002}}
|title=Reconstructing the Musical Arrangement for &quot;The Battle of the Somme&quot; |last1=Haggith |first1=Toby |year=2002 |journal=Film History |volume=14 |issue=1 |jstor=3815576 |issn=0892-2160}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|McWilliams|2009}}
|title=The Battle of the Somme (DVD review) |journal=[[Journal of Film Preservation]] |last=McWilliams |first=D. |editor=Dimitriu C. |date=April 2009 |issue=79/80 |publisher=[[International Federation of Film Archives]]  |url=http://www.fiafnet.org/content/finFIAF_79%201%201.pdf |accessdate=4 November 2010 |issn=1609-2694}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Reeves|1983}}
|title=Film Propaganda and Its Audience: The Example of Britain's Official Films during the First World War |last1=Reeves |first1=Nicholas |year=July 1983 |journal=[[Journal of Contemporary History]] |volume=18 |issue=3 |page=467 |jstor=260547 |issn=1461-7250 |doi=10.1177/002200948301800306}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Reeves|1997}}
|title=Cinema, Spectatorship and Propaganda: 'Battle of the Somme' (1916) and its Contemporary Audience |last=Reeves |first=N. |year=1997 |journal=[[Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television]] |volume=17 |issue=1 |issn=1465-3451}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Smither|2002}}
|title=&quot;Watch the Picture Carefully, and See If You Can Identify Anyone&quot;: Recognition in Factual Film of the First World War Period |last=Smither |first=R. B. N. |year=2002 |journal=Film History |volume=14 |issue=3/4 |jstor=3815439 |issn=0892-2160}}

;Newspapers
* {{cite news |ref={{harvid|The Argus|1916}}
|title=Real War Pictures |newspaper=[[The Argus (Australia)|The Argus (Melbourne, Vic.: 1848–1957)]] |publisher=National Library of Australia |location=Melbourne, VIC |date=14 October 1916 |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article1596249 |accessdate=6 October 2013 |issn=1833-9700}}
* {{cite news |ref={{harvid|Evening Post|1916a}}
|title=The Battle of the Somme (advertisement) |work=[[The Evening Post (New Zealand)|The Evening Post]] |location=[[Wellington]], New Zealand |date=12 October 1916 |url=http://paperspast.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/paperspast?a=d&amp;cl=search&amp;d=EP19161012.1.2&amp;srpos=3&amp;e=12-10-1916-12-10-1916--100-EP-1-byDA-on--0-- |accessdate=6 October 2013 |oclc=320805360}}
* {{cite news |ref={{harvid|Evening Post|1916b}}
|title=The Battle of the Somme: The Big Push in Pictures |newspaper=[[The Evening Post (New Zealand)|The Evening Post]] |location=[[Wellington]], New Zealand |date=16 October 1916 |url=http://paperspast.natlib.govt.nz/cgi-bin/paperspast?a=d&amp;cl=search&amp;d=EP19161016.1.3&amp;srpos=4&amp;e=16-10-1916-16-10-1916--100-EP-1-byDA-on--0-- |accessdate=6 October 2013 |oclc=320805360}}
* {{cite news |ref={{harvid|Times|1916}}
|title=War's Realities on the Cinema |newspaper=The Times |date=22 August 1916 |location=London |issn=0140-0460}}
* {{cite news |ref={{harvid|Times|2006}}
|title=The Battle of the Somme |author=Geoff Brown |date=25 October 2006 |newspaper=[[The Times]] |url=http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/arts/article2404641.ece |accessdate=6 October 2013 |issn=0140-0460}}

;Websites
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|FOCAL|2007}}
|title=Focal Award Nominations 2007 |author=http://www.focalint.org/ |year=2007 |url=http://www.focalint.org/focal-international-awards/2007/the-focal-international-awards-2007/nominations/award-for-archive-restoration-or-preservation-project |accessdate=6 October 2013 |issn=1359-8708}}
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|Smither|2004}}
|title=Memory of the World Register: The Battle of the Somme (nomination form) |last=Smither |first=R. B. N. |year=2004 |work=UNESCO |publisher=[[UNESCO]] |url=http://www.unesco.org/new/fileadmin/MULTIMEDIA/HQ/CI/CI/pdf/mow/nomination_forms/united_kingdom_battle_of_the_somme.pdf |accessdate=6 October 2013}}

{{refend}}

===Further reading===
{{refbegin}}
;Books
* {{cite book |editor-last1=Cecil |editor-first1=Hugh |editor-last2=Liddle |editor-first2=Peter H. Liddle |title=Facing Armageddon: The First World War Experienced |year=1996 |last=Reeves |first=Nicholas |chapter=55 Through the Eye of the Camera: Contemporary Cinema Audiences and Their Experience of War in the Film &quot;Battle of the Somme&quot; |location=London |publisher=Leo Cooper |edition=Pen &amp; Sword paperback |isbn=0-85052-506-3}}

;Journals
* {{cite journal |last=Culbert |first=David |title=The Imperial War Museum: World War I Film Catalogue and ''The Battle of the Somme'' (video) |journal=Historical Journal of Film, Radio &amp; Television |year=Oct 1995 |volume=15 |issue=4 |issn=1465-3451}}
* {{cite journal |last=McKernan |first=L. |year=2002 |title=Propaganda, Patriotism and Profit: Charles Urban and British Official War Films in America during the First World War |journal=Film History |volume=14 |issue=3/4 |pages=369–389  |jstor=3815438 |issn=0892-2160 |doi=10.2979/fil.2002.14.3-4.369}}
* {{cite journal |last=Smither |first=R. |year=1993 |title=&quot;A Wonderful Idea of the Fighting&quot;: The Question of Fakes in 'The Battle of the Somme' |journal=Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television |volume=13 |issue=2 |issn=0143-9685}}

;websites
* {{cite web |title=The Film Programme: The Battle of the Somme |last1=Tookey |first1=C. |last2=Walsh |first2=D. |date=20 October 2006 |publisher=BBC |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/arts/filmprogramme/rams/filmprogramme_20061020.ram  |accessdate=6 October 2013}}

{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|The Battle of the Somme (film)}}
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/guides/zc3dhyc BBC article]
* [http://explore.bfi.org.uk/4ce2b9792c2b1 Filmography, British Topical Committee for War Films]
* {{IMDb title|0006405|The Battle of the Somme (1916)}}
* [http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-29724852 Viewpoint: The WW1 film over 20 million people went to see, 7 November 2014, BBC]
* [http://www.focalint.org/assets/files/2012_02_battlesomme.pdf Screenings of the film in 2012 with live soundtrack of Laura Rossi's score]
* [http://www.somme100film.com/ Somme100 FILM - The Battle of the Somme Centenary Tour 2016]
* [http://www.somme100film.com/performances Somme100 FILM - List of Performances of The Battle of the Somme in 2016]

{{World War I}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of The Somme, The (Film)}}
[[Category:1916 films]]
[[Category:1910s documentary films]]
[[Category:Black-and-white documentary films]]
[[Category:British films]]
[[Category:British documentary films]]
[[Category:British silent films]]
[[Category:British World War I propaganda films]]
[[Category:British black-and-white films]]
[[Category:Western Front films (World War I)]]
[[Category:Memory of the World Register]]
[[Category:Collection of the Imperial War Museum]]
[[Category:Documentary films about the Battle of the Somme]]</text>
      <sha1>do7jzz0iud3tkuwnoyxhurb05y7559v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
