<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Togoland Campaign</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35197805</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742128557</id>
      <parentid>742094119</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-01T21:36:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Morningstar1814</username>
        <id>4934695</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reformatting; moving image positions</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28043">{{EngvarB|date=April 2016}}
{{infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Togoland Campaign
| partof      = the [[African theatre of World War I]]
| image       = [[File:M 46&amp;47 13 troupes anglaises au Togo.jpg|250px]]
| caption     = British troops in Togoland in 1914
| date        = 9–26 August 1914
| place       = [[Togoland|German Togoland]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(modern [[Togo]] and [[Ghana]])&lt;/small&gt;
|coordinates = {{Coord|06|07|55|N|01|13|22|E|type:event_region:TG|display=inline,title}}
| map_type    = Togo
| latitude    = 6.131944
| longitude   = 1.222778
| map_size    = 150
| map_caption = {{center|Map of independent Togo}}
| map_label   = Lomé
| territory   = Britain annexed [[British Togoland|Western Togoland]] and [[France]] [[French Togoland|Eastern Togoland]]
| result      = Allied victory
| status      =
| combatant1  = {{flag|British Empire}}
* {{flagicon|Gold Coast}} [[Gold Coast (British colony)|Gold Coast]]
{{flagicon|France}} [[French Third Republic|France]]
* {{flagicon|France}} [[French Dahomey]]
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|German Empire}} [[German Empire]]
* {{flagicon image|Reichskolonialflagge.svg}} [[Togoland]]
| commander1  = [[Charles Macpherson Dobell|Charles M. Dobell]]&lt;br /&gt; Frederick Carkeet Bryant
| commander2  =  Hans-Georg von Döring{{POW}}&lt;br&gt; Georg Pfähler{{KIA}}
| commander3  =
| units1      = [[Royal West African Frontier Force|West African Frontier Force]]&lt;br /&gt;''[[Tirailleurs Senegalais]]''
| units2      = Paramilitary and police forces
| strength1   = British: 600&lt;br/&gt;France: 500
| strength2   = 693–1,500 (including reservists)
| casualties1= British: 83&lt;br&gt;French: {{circa|54}}
| casualties2= 41
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Togoland Campaign}}{{Campaignbox World War I}}
}}
The '''Togoland Campaign''' (9–26 August 1914) was a [[Third French Republic|French]] and [[British Empire|British]] invasion of the [[German Empire|German]] colony of [[Togoland]] in west Africa, during the [[African theatre of World War I|West African Campaign]] of the [[First World War]]. German colonial forces withdrew from the capital Lomé and the coastal province and then fought delaying actions on the route north to Kamina, where a new wireless station linked Berlin to Togoland, the Atlantic and South America. The main British and French force from the neighbouring colonies of [[Gold Coast (British colony)|Gold Coast]] and [[Dahomey]], advanced from the coast up the road and railway, as smaller forces converged on Kamina from the north. The German defenders were able to delay the invaders for several days at the battles of Agbeluvhoe and Chra but surrendered the colony on 26 August 1914. In 1916, Togoland was partitioned by the victors and in July 1922, [[British Togoland]] and [[French Togoland]] were established as [[League of Nations]] [[League of Nations mandate|mandates]].

== Background ==
===Togoland, 1914===
[[File:Togoland, 1914.jpg|thumb|left|{{center|Togoland, 1914}}]]
The [[German Empire]] had established a protectorate over Togoland in 1884, which was slightly larger than Ireland and had a population of {{circa|1,000,000 people}} in 1914. A mountain range with heights of over {{convert|3000|ft|m}} ran south-east to north-west and restricted traffic between the coast and hinterland. South of the high ground the ground rises from coastal marshes and lagoons to a plateau about {{convert|200|–|300|ft|m}} high, covered in forest and high grass and scrub, where farmers had cleared the forest for oil palm cultivation. The climate was tropical, with more rainfall in the interior and a dry season with little rain in August.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=6}} Half of the border with Gold Coast ran along the Volta river and a tributary but in the south, the border for {{convert|80|mi|km}} was beyond the east bank. The Germans had made the southern region one of the most developed colonies in Africa, having built three metre-gauge railway lines and several roads from [[Lomé]] the capital and main city. There was no port and ships had to lie off Lomé and transfer freight by surf boats. One line ran along the coast from Anekho to Lomé, one ran from Lomé to Atakpame and one from Lomé to Palime. Roads had been built from Lomé to: Atakpame and Sokode, Palime to Kete Krachi and from Kete Krachi to Sansame Mangu and in 1914, were reported to be fit for motor vehicles.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=4–5}}

German military forces in Togoland were exiguous, there were no German army units, only {{nowrap|693 ''[[Schutztruppe|Polizeitruppen]]''}} (paramilitary police) under the command of Captain Georg Pfähler and about {{nowrap|300 colonists}} with military training.{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=14}} The colony was adjacent to [[Allies of World War I|Allied]] territory, with [[French Dahomey]] on its northern and eastern borders and the [[British Gold Coast]] to the west. Lomé and the wireless station at Kamina about {{convert|100|km|mi}} inland, which was connected to the coast by road and rail, were the only places of military significance. Kamina was near the town of [[Atakpame]] and had been completed in June 1914. The transmitter was a relay station for communication between Germany, the overseas colonies, the [[Imperial German Navy]] and South America.{{sfn|Killingray|2012|p=116}} The [[Admiralty]] wished to prevent the station from being used to co-ordinate attacks on shipping in the Atlantic. At the outbreak of war the Governor of Togoland, [[Duke Adolf Friedrich of Mecklenburg]] was in Germany and his deputy, Major Hans-Georg von Döring was the acting-Governor.{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=14}}

===Gold Coast, 1914===
[[File:West Africa 1914-1918.jpg|thumb|{{center|West Africa, 1914–1918}}]]
Sir [[Hugh Clifford]], the Governor of the Gold Coast, Lieutenant-General [[Charles Macpherson Dobell]], commander of the [[Royal West African Frontier Force|West African Frontier Force]] and Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. de B. Rose, commander of the [[Gold Coast Regiment]] were absent in July 1914. W. C. F. Robertson was the acting-Governor and Captain Frederick Carkeet Bryant was acting-Commandant of the Gold Coast Regiment.{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=14}} The Gold Coast Regiment had one pioneer, seven infantry companies with a machine-gun each and a battery of four [[QF 2.95-inch Mountain Gun]]s, with {{nowrap|1,595 men}} including {{nowrap|124 carriers}} and {{circa|330}} reservists. There were four &quot;Volunteer Corps&quot; with {{circa|900 men}} and {{nowrap|1,200 police}} and customs men. The Defence Scheme for the Gold Coast (1913) provided for war against the French in neighbouring Ivory Coast and the Germans in Togoland; in the event of war with Germany, the colony was to be defended along [[Lake Volta]] and the north-eastern frontier against the possibility of a raid, which was the most that the Germans in Togoland were thought capable.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=9}}

The plan also provided for an offensive across the lake into the north of Togoland, before making a thrust south to the more populated portion of the colony. On 29 July, a Colonial Office telegram arrived at Accra, ordering the adoption of the ''precautionary stage'' of the Defence Scheme and Robertson forwarded the information to Bryant the next day.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=11}} Bryant dispensed with the Scheme, which had not been revised after the wireless station at Kamina was built and by 31 July, had mobilised the Gold Coast Regiment along the southern, rather than the northern border with Togoland.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=9–10, 13}} In London on 3 August, Dobell proposed an advance if war was declared, along the coast road from Ada to Keta and thence to Lomé, which was fewer than {{convert|2|mi|km}} from the border. Bryant had reached the same conclusion as Dobell and had already organised small expeditionary columns at Krachi and Ada and assembled the main force at Kumasi, ready to move in either direction.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=13–14}}

==Prelude==
===Anglo-French offensive preparations===
On 5 August 1914, a day after Britain declared war on Germany, the Allies cut the German sea cables between Monrovia and Tenerife, leaving the radio station at Kamina the only connexion between the colony and Germany.{{sfn|Friedenwald|2001|p=11}} The same day the acting-Governor of Togoland, Major von Döring sent a telegram to Robertson proposing neutrality, in accordance with articles X and XI of the [[Berlin Conference|Congo Act]], which stated that colonies in the [[Congo Basin]] were to remain neutral in the event of a conflict in Europe.{{sfn|Chappell|2005|p=7}} Von Döring also appealed for neutrality because of the economic interdependence of the west African colonies and their common interest in dominating local populations.{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=15}} On 6 August, the Cabinet in London refused the offer of neutrality and Bryant on his own initiative, after hearing that the French in Dahomey wished to co-operate, sent Captain Barker and the District Commissioner of Keta to von Döring, with a demand the surrender of the colony and gave {{nowrap|24-hours}} to reply. Next morning the British intercepted a wireless message from von Döring that he was withdrawing from the coast to Kamina and that Lomé would be surrendered if attacked.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=17–19}} A similar proposal for neutrality from von Döring had been received by the Governor of Dahomey, who took it as a declaration of war and ordered an invasion, according to a plan to seize Lomé and the coast, which had been drafted in ignorance of the wireless station at Kamina, only {{convert|60|km|mi}} from the Dahomey border.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=21}}

== Invasion ==
=== Capture of Lomé ===
Late on 6 August, French police occupied customs posts near Athieme and next day Major Maroix, the commander of French military forces in Dahomey, ordered the capture of Agbanake and [[Aného|Aneho]]. Agbanake was occupied late on 7 August, the Mono river was crossed and a column under Captain Marchand took Aneho early on 8 August; both moves were unopposed and local civilians helped to see off the Germans, by burning down the Government House at Sebe. The {{circa|460}} colonists and [[Askaris]] retreated inland, impressing civilians and calling up reservists as they moved north.{{sfn|Friedenwald|2001|p=11}} Repairs began on the Aneho–Lomé railway and the French advanced to Porto Seguro and Togo before stopping the advance, once it was clear that Lomé had been surrendered to British forces.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=21–22}} The British invasion began late on 7 August, the British emissaries returned to Lomé by lorry, to find that the Germans had left for Kamina and given a Herr Clausnitzer discretion to surrender the colony up to Chra, {{convert|120|km|mi}} inland, to prevent a naval bombardment of Lomé. On 8 August, the emissaries took command of fourteen British soldiers and police from Aflao; a telegraph operator arrived by bicycle and repaired the line to Keta and Accra.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=21–22}}

The British flag was raised and on 9 August, parties of troops arrived having marched {{convert|50|mi|km}} in exhausting heat.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=21–22}} Over the border, Bryant had arranged to move the main force by sea and embarked on the ''Elele'' on 10 August. Three other companies had been ordered to Krachi, to begin a land advance to Kamina. The ''Elele'' arrived off Lomé on 12 August and the force disembarked through the surf.{{efn|A British patrol near a factory in [[Notsé|Nuatja]], came into contact with German police and exchanged fire. Private [[Alhaji Grunshi]] (who retired after the war as a Regimental Sergeant-Major) is believed to be the first British soldier to fire a rifle in anger in the First World War.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=8}}}} Arrangements were made with the French, for a converging advance towards Atakpame by the British and the French from Aneho, a French column under Maroix from [[Tchetti]] in the north and the British column at Krachi under Captain Elgee. Small British forces on the northern border, were put under the command of Maroix and ordered to move south, as {{circa|560 French}} cavalry were ordered across the northern border from Senegal and Niger, towards Sansane Mangu from {{nowrap|13–15 August.}} The British force at Lomé comprised {{nowrap|558 soldiers,}} {{nowrap|2,084 carriers,}} police and volunteers, who were preparing to advance inland, when Bryant received news of a German foray to Togblekove.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=25–27}}

=== Advance to Kamina ===
{{Main|Battle of Agbeluvhoe}}
The Battle of Bafilo was a skirmish between [[French Third Republic|French]] and German troops in north-east [[Togoland]] on 13 August. French forces had crossed the border between [[Dahomey|French Dahomey]] and Togoland on {{nowrap|8–9 August}} and were engaged by German troops in the districts of Sansane-Mangu and Skode-Balfilo. The French company retreated, after facing greater resistance than expected.{{sfn|Schreckenbach|1920|p=886}} After the capture of Lomé on the coast, Bryant was promoted to Lieutenant-Colonel, made commander of all Allied forces in the operation and landed at Lomé on 12 August, with the main British force of {{nowrap|558 soldiers,}} {{nowrap|2,084 carriers,}} police and volunteers. As preparations began to advance northwards to Kamina, Bryant heard that a German party had travelled south by train the day before. The party had destroyed a small wireless transmitter and railway bridge at Togblekove, about {{convert|10|mi|km}} to the north. Bryant detached half an infantry company on 12 August and sent another {{frac|1|1|2}} companies forward the next day, to prevent further attacks.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=25–26}}

By the evening, &quot;I&quot; Company had reached Tsevie, scouts reported that the country south of Agbeluvhoe was clear of German troops and the main force had reached Togblekove; at {{nowrap|10:00 p.m.}} &quot;I&quot; Company began to advance up the road to Agbeluvhoe. The relatively harsh terrain of bushland and swamp impeded the Allied push to Kamina, by keeping the invaders on the railway and the road, which had fallen into disrepair and was found to be impassable by wheeled vehicles. Communication between the parties was difficult, because of the intervening high grass and thick scrub. The main force moved on from Togblekove at {{nowrap|6:00 a.m.}} on 15 August and at {{nowrap|8:30 a.m.,}} local civilians told Bryant that a train full of Germans had steamed into Tsevie that morning and shot up the station.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=26–28}} In the afternoon the British advanced guard met German troops near the Lili river, who blew the bridge and dug in on a ridge on the far side.{{efn|British engineers were quick to build replacement bridges.{{sfn|Morlang|2008|p=36}}}} The demolitions and the delaying action, held up the advance until {{nowrap|4:30 p.m.}} and the force spent the night at Ekuni rather than joining &quot;I&quot; Company as intended.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=28–29}}

[[File:Transmitter mast kamina togo.jpg|thumb|{{center|A radio mast at Kamina}}]]

Von Döring had sent two raiding parties with {{nowrap|200 men}} south in trains, to delay the advancing Allied force.{{sfn|Fecitte|2012|nopp=y}} &quot;I&quot; Company had heard the train run south at {{nowrap|4:00 a.m.,}} while halted on the road near Ekuni, a village about {{convert|6|mi|km}} south of Agbeluvhoe. A section was sent to cut off the train and the rest of &quot;I&quot; Company pressed on to Agbeluvhoe. A local civilian guided the section to the railway, where Lieutenant Collins and his men piled stones and a heavy iron plate on the tracks, about {{convert|200|yd|m}} north of the bridge at Ekuni and then set an ambush. One of the trains of {{nowrap|20 cars}} was derailed by the obstacles placed on the tracks and the other train was halted by the rest of &quot;I&quot; Company at the [[Battle of Agbeluvhoe]]. In the fight between German troops in the railway carriages and the British, Pfähler was killed, the Germans were defeated and lost a quarter of the force.{{sfn|Friedenwald|2001|p=12}}{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=17}}

=== Battle of Chra, 22 August ===
{{main|Battle of Chra}}
Despite the skirmish in the north-west at Bafilo and the action at Agbeluvhoe, Allied forces advancing towards the German base at Kamina, had not encountered substantial resistance. The last natural barrier south of Kamina was the Chra river, where Von Döring chose to make a stand. The railway bridge over the river was destroyed and the approaches to the river and village were mined.  On 21 August, British scouts found {{nowrap|460–560 German}} police troops entrenched on the north bank of the river.{{sfn|Friedenwald|2001|p=12}} The West African Rifles, supported by French forces from the east, assembled on the south bank and during 22 August, Bryant launched a series of assaults on the German entrenchments, which were repulsed and in which the British suffered {{nowrap|17 percent casualties.}}{{sfn|Morlang|2008|p=36}}{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=16}} Lieutenant George Masterman Thompson, became the first British officer to be killed in action in the First World War.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=36}}

Although the Germans had repelled the Allied force from a fortified position, which was easy to supply, French troops were advancing from the north and east towards Kamina unchecked and a British column was advancing on the station from [[Kete Krachi]] in the west.{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=17}} On the morning of 23 August, the British found that the German trenches had been abandoned. German forces from the Chra had withdrawn to the wireless station and during the night of {{nowrap|24/25 August,}} explosions were heard from the direction of Kamina. French and British forces arrived at Kamina on 26 August, to find that the nine radio towers had been demolished and the electrical equipment destroyed. Von Döring and {{nowrap|200 remaining}} troops surrendered the colony to Bryant; the rest of the German force had deserted.{{sfn|Friedenwald|2001|p=12}} The Allied troops recovered three [[Maxim gun|Maxim]] machine-guns, {{nowrap|1,000 rifles}} and {{circa|320,000 rounds}} of ammunition.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|p=39}}

== Aftermath ==
===Analysis===
[[File:Togoland.svg|lang=en|thumb|{{center|Partition of German Togoland between Britain (green) and France (purple)}}]]
Before the wireless station at Kamina was destroyed, {{nowrap|229 messages}} were passed between Germany, the navy and colonies following the outbreak of war.{{sfn|Strachan|2004|p=17}} The first military operations of British soldiers during the First World War occurred in Togoland and ended soon after British operations began in continental Europe.{{sfn|Andrew|Kanya-Forstner|1981|p=61}} In December 1916, the colony was split into British and French occupation zones, which cut through administrative divisions and civilian boundaries.{{sfn|Louis|2006|p=217}} Both powers sought a new partition and in 1919, Article 22 of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] partitioned former German colonies between the Allies.{{sfn|Strandman|1967|p=9}} In July 1922, [[British Togoland]] and [[French Togoland]] were created from former German Togoland, as [[League of Nations]] [[League of Nations mandate|mandates]].{{sfn|Gorman|Newman|2009|p=629}} The French acquisition consisted of {{circa|60 percent of}} the colony, including the coast. The British received the smaller, less populated and less developed portion of Togoland, to the west.{{sfn|Louis|2006|p=217}} The part administered by the British, united with Ghana upon its independence in 1957; French Togoland gained independence in 1960, becoming the modern [[Togolese Republic]].{{sfn|Gorman|Newman|2009|p=629}} The surrender of Togoland marked the beginning of the end for the [[German colonial empire]], which lost its African and Pacific possessions.{{sfn|Strachan|2001|p=642}}

===Casualties===
British casualties in the campaign were {{nowrap|83, French}} casualties were {{circa|54 and}} German casualties were {{nowrap|41. An}} unknown number of troops and carriers deserted on both sides.{{sfn|Moberly|1931|pp=29, 30–31, 36–39}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

== Footnotes ==
{{reflist|20em}}

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
;Books
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Andrew|Kanya-Forstner|1981}}
|last1=Andrew |first1=C. M. |last2=Kanya-Forstner |first2=A. S. |title=The Climax of French Imperial Expansion, 1914–1924 |year=1981 |publisher=Stanford University Press |location=Stanford, CA |isbn=0-80471-101-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Chappell|2005}}
|last=Chappell |first=M. |title=Seizing the German Empire. The British Army in World War I: The Eastern Fronts |volume=III |year=2005 |location=Oxford |publisher=Osprey |isbn=1-84176-401-9}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Gorman|Newman|2009}}
|last1=Gorman |first1=A. |last2=Newman |first2=A. |editor=Stokes, J. |title=Encyclopaedia of the Peoples of Africa and the Middle East |year=2009 |publisher=Facts on File |location=New York |isbn=0816071586}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Killingray|2012}}
|last=Killingray |first=D. |title=The Conquest of Togo. Companion to World War I |year=2012 |publisher=Blackwell |location=London |isbn=978-1-4051-2386-0}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Louis|2006}}
|last=Louis |first=W. R. |title=Ends of British Imperialism: The Scramble for Empire, Suez and Decolonization: Collected Essays |year=2006 |publisher=I. B. Tauris |location=London |isbn=1-84511-309-8}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Moberly|1931}}
|series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Military Operations Togoland and the Cameroons 1914–1916 |last=Moberly |first=F. J. |authorlink= |year=1995 |orig-year=1931 |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |edition=Imperial War Museum and Battery Press |isbn=0-89839-235-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Morlang|2008}}
|last=Morlang |first=T. |title=Askari und Fitafita: &quot;farbige&quot; Söldner in den deutschen Kolonien |trans_title=Askari and Fitafita: Colored (sic) Mercenaries in the German Colonies |language=German |year=2008 |publisher=Links |location=Berlin |isbn=3-86153-476-2}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Schreckenbach|1920}}
|last=Schreckenbach |first=P. |series=Der Weltbrand: illustrierte Geschichte aus großer Zeit mit zusammenhängendem text |title=Die deutschen Kolonien vom Anfang des Krieges bis Ende des Jahres 1917 |trans_title=The German Colonies by the Beginning of the War until the End of 1917 |language=German |volume=III |year=1920 |location=Leipzig |publisher=Weber |oclc=643687370}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Strachan|2001}}
|title=The First World War: To Arms |volume=I |last=Strachan |first=H. |authorlink= |year=2001 |publisher=OUP |location=Oxford |edition=2003 |isbn=0-19-926191-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Strachan|2004}}
|last=Strachan |first=H. |title=The First World War in Africa |year=2004 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-199-25728-0}}

;Journals
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Strandman|1967}}
|last=Strandman |first=P. |title=The First World War in African History: Great Britain and Germany's Lost Colonies, 1914–1919 |journal=The Journal of African History |volume=IX |issue=2 |year=1967 |doi=10.1017/s0021853700008975 |publisher=Clarendon Press |location=Oxford |others=trans. W. M. Louis |issn=0021-8537}}

;Websites
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|Fecitte|2012}}
|last=Fecitte |first=H. |title=The Soldier's Burden: Togoland 1914 |year=2012 |publisher=Harry's Africa Web |url=http://www.kaiserscross.com/188001/300143.html |accessdate=24 February 2014}}
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|Friedenwald|2001}}
|last=Friedenwald |first=M. |title=Funkentelegrafie Und Deutsche Kolonien: Technik Als Mittel Imperialistischer Politik |trans-title=Telegraphy and German Colonies: Imperialist Technology as a Means of Policy |language=German |year=2001 |publisher=Familie Friedenwald |url=http://www.friedewald-family.de/Publikationen/GAGFriedewald.pdf |accessdate=22 February 2014 |oclc=76360477}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
;Books
* {{cite book |last=Buchan |first=J. |title=A History of the Great War |volume=I |year=1922 |location=Boston and New York |publisher=Houghton Mifflin |url=https://ia700406.us.archive.org/7/items/historyofgreatwa01buch/historyofgreatwa01buch.pdf |accessdate=26 February 2014 |oclc=558495465}}
* {{cite book |last1=Burg |first1=D. F. |last2=Purcell |first2=L. E. |title=Almanac of World War I |year=1998 |publisher=University of Kentucky |location=Lexington, KY |isbn=0-81312-072-1}}
* {{cite book |last=Dane |first=E. |title=British Campaigns in Africa and the Pacific, 1914–1918 |year=1919 |location=London |publisher=Hodder and Stoughton |url=https://ia600301.us.archive.org/31/items/britishcampaigns00dane/britishcampaigns00dane.pdf |accessdate=26 February 2014 |oclc=150586292}}
* {{cite book |last=Längin |first=B. G. |title=Die deutschen Kolonien: Schauplätze und Schicksale 1888–1918 |language=German |trans-title=The German Colonies: Scenes and stories from 1884–1918 |year=2005 |publisher=Mittler |location=Berlin |isbn=3813208540}}
* {{cite book |last=Margeurat |first=Y. |title=Un document Exceptionnel: La Guerre de 1914 au Togo vue par un combattant allemand |language=French |year=1987 |publisher=Centre ORSTOM de Lomé |location=Lomé |oclc=713065710}}
* {{cite book |last=O'Neill |first=H. C. |title=The War in Africa and the Far East |year=1918 |publisher=Longmans Green |location=London |url=https://ia600409.us.archive.org/20/items/warinafrica1914100onei/warinafrica1914100onei.pdf |accessdate=26 February 2014 |oclc=5424631}}
* {{cite book |last1=Reynolds |first1=F. J. |last2=Churchill |first2=A. L. |last3=Miller |first3=F. T. |series=The Story of the Great War |volume=III |pages=62–63 |title=Togoland and the Cameroons |year=1916 |publisher=P. F. Collier and Son |location=New York |url=https://ia600305.us.archive.org/25/items/storygreatwar01palmgoog/storygreatwar01palmgoog.pdf |accessdate=3 March 2014 |oclc=2678548}}
* {{cite book |last=Sebald |first=P. |title=Togo 1884–1914: Eine Geschichte Der Deutschen &quot;Musterkolonie&quot; Auf Der Grundlage Amtlicher Quellen |language=French |year=1988 |publisher=Akademie-Verlag |location=Berlin |isbn=3-05000-248-4}}

;Websites
* {{cite web |last=Steward |first=K. |title=Lieut. Colonel FC Bryant CMG CBE DSO Gold Coast Regiment &amp; The Short Campaign In Togo August 11–26, 1914 |year=2006 |publisher=British Colonial Africa |url=http://www.britishcolonialafrica.com/PDFS/10_LIEUT_COLONEL_BRYANT_8_Single_20_3.pdf |accessdate=26 February 2014&lt;!--no bibliographical data available--&gt;}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Togoland Campaign}}
{{portal|World War I|Military history of Africa}}
* [http://horizon.documentation.ird.fr/exl-doc/pleins_textes/pleins_textes_5/b_fdi_18-19/24344.pdf  La Guerre de 1914 au Togo Vue Par Un Combattant Allemand (French)]
* [http://horizon.documentation.ird.fr/exl-doc/pleins_textes/pleins_textes_5/b_fdi_18-19/26043.pdf  L'histoire Vécue : Sokodé, 1914 les Allemands Évacuent le Nord-Togo (French)]
* [http://lucy.ukc.ac.uk/Machin/machin_51.html An Old Coaster Comes Home: Chapter 5, Rattray’s War]
* [http://www.kaiserscross.com/188001/300143.html Togoland 1914: The Anglo-French Invasion]
* [http://horizon.documentation.ird.fr/exl-doc/pleins_textes/pleins_textes_5/b_fdi_18-19/24344.pdf French site with campaign map]
* [http://www.seitengewehr.de/ptk.pdf German site, Polizeitruppen in Togo and Cameroon with photographs]
* [http://www.traditionsverband.de/magazin/polizeiuniform.html Schutzpolizei uniforms]

{{World War I}}

[[Category:Military history of Togo]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving France]]
[[Category:African theatre of World War I]]
[[Category:20th century in Togo]]
[[Category:Togoland]]
[[Category:1914 in Africa]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1914]]
[[Category:Campaigns and theatres of World War I]]</text>
      <sha1>ssf8xezwd4njil3etlowa34glcr6f83</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
