<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>VP-1</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49243765</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750769604</id>
      <parentid>727167552</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T18:51:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BD2412</username>
        <id>196446</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Designations, assignments, and aircraft */Per consensus in discussion at [[Talk:New York#Proposed action to resolve incorrect incoming links]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31699">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= Patrol Squadron 1
|image=[[File:Patrol Squadron 1 (US Navy) insignia 2015.png|200px]]
|caption=
|dates=15 February 1943 – Present
|country=United States of America
|allegiance=
|branch= {{nowrap|[[Image:United States Department of the Navy Seal.svg|30px|United States Navy Seal]] [[United States Navy]]}}
|type= Squadron
|role= Anti-Submarine Patrol
|size=
|command_structure= 
|garrison= [[Naval Air Station Whidbey Island|NAS Whidbey Island]]
|garrison_label= Home Port
|nickname= Fleet's Finest (1955 - 1985)&lt;br&gt;Screaming Eagles (1985 - Present)
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=Eagle
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles='''[[World War II]]'''&lt;br&gt;'''[[Korean War]]'''&lt;br&gt;'''[[Vietnam War]]'''&lt;br&gt;'''[[Desert Shield]]'''
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label= Commanding Officer
|commander2=
|commander2_label= Executive Officer
|commander3=
|commander3_label= Command Master Chief
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
&lt;!-- Aircraft --&gt;
|aircraft_patrol= [[Lockheed Ventura|PV Harpoon]] (1943)&lt;br&gt;[[Lockheed P-2 Neptune|P-2 Neptune]] (1947)&lt;br&gt;[[Lockheed P-3 Orion|P-3 Orion]] (1969)
|}}

'''Patrol Squadron One (VP-1)''', established 15 February 1943, is an active aviation [[squadron (aviation)|squadron]] of the [[United States Navy]] operating the [[Lockheed P-3 Orion|P-3C Orion]] aircraft from its home port at [[Naval Air Station Whidbey Island]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]], [[United States]].&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3&gt;{{cite book|last=Roberts|first=Michael D.|title=Dictionary of American Naval Aviation Squadrons, Volume 2, Chapter 3 Patrol Squadron (VP) Histories (1st VP-1 to 2nd VP-4)|publisher=Naval Historical Center, Department of the Navy|year=2000|location=Washington, D.C.|url=https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/naval-aviation-history/dictionary-of-american-naval-aviation-squadrons-volume-2/chapter-3-patrol-squadron-vp-histories-1st-vp-1-to-2nd-vp-4.html|pages=17-24|accessdate=27 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The squadron is known by its nickname '''&quot;Screaming Eagles&quot;''', adopted in 1985 replacing its previous nickname '''&quot;Fleet's Finest&quot;'''.  The squadron went by the call sign &quot;BACKDOOR&quot; during the 1960s and 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;vpnavy&quot;&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.vpnavy.com/vp1.html|title=VP-1|work=U.S. Navy Patrol Squadrons|publisher=VPNavy.org|accessdate=29 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Lineage ==
The squadron was originally established as '''Bombing Squadron 128 (VB-128)''' on 15 February 1943, redesignated '''Patrol Bombing Squadron 128 (VPB-128)''' 1 October 1944, redesignated '''Patrol Squadron 128 (VP-128)''' on 15 May 1946, redesignated '''Medium Patrol Squadron (Landplane) 1 (VP-ML-1)''' on 15 November 1946 and redesignated '''Patrol Squadron ONE (VP-1)''' on 1 September 1948. It is the ﬁfth squadron to be designated VP-1. The [[VP-1 (1921-2)|first VP-1]] was disestablished in July 1922, the [[VP-1 (1924-6)|second VP-1]] was disestablished on 3 May 1926, the [[VPB-29|third VP-1]] was redesignated VP-21 on 1 July 1939 and the [[VPB-1|fourth VP-1]] was redesignated VPB-1 on 1 October 1944.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;

== History ==

=== Establishment and World War II ===
Bombing Squadron One Hundred Twenty Eight (VB-128) was established at [[Naval Air Station DeLand]], [[Florida]] on 15 February 1943 as part of the build-up of [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] aircraft engaged in the [[Battle of the Atlantic]].  Under operational control of [[Fleet Air Wing Twelve]], the squadron took only two weeks to bring aircrew and their [[Lockheed Ventura|PV-1 Ventura]] aircraft to operational status, and by May the squadron was able to send a detachment of aircraft to [[Guantanamo Bay Naval Base]] to provide aerial cover for [[convoy]]s while the squadron moved to [[Floyd Bennett Field]] in [[New York City]].  The squadron's first loss in action came on 7 August 1943 when a Ventura was shot down by a German [[U-boat]] it had attacked and damaged.  The pilot, Lieutenant JG [[Frederick Cushing Cross, Jr.]], was awarded the [[Navy Cross]] for his heroic actions in saving his crew's lives despite suffering a mortal wound.&lt;ref name=&quot;danfs&quot;&gt;{{DANFS}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Later in August, the squadron was moved into the heart of the fight by switching from coastal patrols to covering a large area of the open ocean from their new base at [[Reykjavik]], [[Iceland]].  Now under control of [[Fleet Air Wing Seven]], the squadron operated as part of the antisubmarine efforts in the [[North Atlantic Ocean]], cooperating with [[RAF Coastal Command]].  On October 4, the squadron recorded its first confirmed kill, sinking [[German submarine U-279|''U-279'']] off the southwest coast of Iceland, where Lieutenant Charles L. Westhofen had spotted it on the surface and bombed it.  All 48 hands aboard ''U-279'' were lost.

December saw another change of scenery for the squadron with its relocation to [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]] under control of [[Fleet Air Wing Eleven]].  The squadron's aircraft were refitted with rockets and training undergone in the use of them against surface targets.  Upon completion of training, the squadron moved to [[Ensenada Honda]], [[Puerto Rico]] and mounted routine anti-submarine patrols throughout May 1944.  With the reduction of the German submarine threat in 1944, the squadron had time for leave and training before being transferred to the [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]] for service in the [[Pacific War]], first arriving at [[Naval Air Station Alameda]], [[California]] on 26 September and then at [[Naval Air Station Kaneohe]], [[Hawaii]] on 6 October.  Training was undertaken in Hawaii with routine rotations to [[Midway Island]] for weather patrols.  Ultimately, the squadron was moved to [[Owi Airfield]], [[Territory of Papua|Papua]] on 21 December and by 3 January 1945, its aircraft were transferred to other squadrons to bring them up to strength.

The squadron, now designated Patrol Bombing Squadron One Hundred Twenty Eight (VPB-128) received new aircraft on 28 February 1945 at [[Guiuan]], [[Samar]], [[Philippines]], from which the squadron began operating daily anti-shipping and convoy protection patrols.  A pair of squadron aircraft recorded the first kills against the Japanese on 18 March when one [[midget submarine]] was sunk and another was damaged in [[Davao Gulf]].  Four days later, a strike against the wharf in [[Cebu City]] netted another midget submarine sinking by rockets, though one of the attacking aircraft was hit by [[antiaircraft]] fire and lost with all crew members.  At the end of the month, the squadron relocated to [[Tacloban]], [[Leyte]], and then on to [[Puerto Princesa International Airport|Puerto Princesa]], [[Palawan]], continuing with its primary responsibilities of anti-shipping and convoy coverage.

At the end of April, the squadron switched to supporting ground operations and began striking land targets selected by the [[United States Army]], including [[Itu Aba Island]], [[Muara, Brunei|Brooketon]], [[Brunei]], [[Kudat]], [[Seria]], and Tagai Town.  During this period, the Navy changed its policy on patrol squadron designations, and the designation was changed to Patrol Squadron One Hundred Twenty Eight (VP-128) in May.  On 21 June 1945, the squadron was transferred to the operational control of [[Fleet Air Wing One]] and relocated to [[Tinian Island]] resuming its traditional role of sea patrol.  It conducted such patrols daily until the surrender of Japanese forces, though it later undertook regular weather patrols.  The squadron was moved to [[Okinawa]], [[Japan]] and redesignated Medium Patrol Squadron (Landplane) One (VP-ML-1) before finally returning to the United States in March 1947.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;

=== A new home at Whidbey ===
[[File:P2V-5 VP-1 in flight over Japan 1952.JPG|left|thumb|[[Lockheed P-2 Neptune|P2V-5 Neptune]] in flight over Japan]]
The squadron's first home port upon its return to the States was [[Naval Air Station San Diego]], California where it underwent transition to the new [[Lockheed P-2 Neptune|P2V Neptune]] aircraft.  With transition complete, the squadron was permanently assigned to [[Naval Air Station Whidbey Island]], Washington, on 13 January 1948.  That same year it would receive its final redesignation as Patrol Squadron One.  The first deployment from its new home was in support of American military forces engaged in [[South Korea]] with a detachment sent on 7 August 1950 to [[Naha Air Force Base]], [[Okinawa]]. Combat operations commenced on 19 August patrolling sea lanes in the [[Formosa Straits]] in an attempt to interdict supply vessels.  By the end of the conflict, the squadron conducted four deployments to Naha.

In the mid-1950s, the Navy was under considerable pressure to cutback on land-based patrol aircraft in the wake of the Korean War and the [[United States Air Force]] was making demands to control all of America's land-based military aircraft.  To face these challenges, the Navy needed to demonstrate the ability to quickly deploy the Neptune aircraft in squadron strength to any part of the globe, and VP-1 was tasked with making this demonstration.  On 21 April 1955, the entire squadron departed on what would become the first around-the-world flight by a patrol squadron, returning to Whidbey Island on 5 May.  Together with the Navy's record-setting effort of the [[Lockheed P-2 Neptune#The Truculent Turtle|Truculent Turtle]], the Navy was able to demonstrate the value of its Neptune fleet and preserve support for the patrol aviation community.  Operational activity included a deployment to [[Kwajalein]] for [[Operation Redwing]], during which the squadron conducted radiation monitoring flights following nuclear testing.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;

=== Service in Vietnam ===
[[File:SP-2H VP-1 during Market Time mission.JPG|right|thumb|[[Lockheed P-2 Neptune|SP-2H Neptune]] patrolling the waters off Vietnam]]
VP-1 was again called upon for operational service as the conflict in [[Vietnam]] ramped up.  On 7 October 1964, the squadron deployed to [[Marine Corps Air Station Iwakuni]], Japan from which it mounted antisubmarine patrols and reported on Communist shipping in the [[Gulf of Tonkin]].  Closer in, a detachment was deployed to [[Tan Son Nhut Air Base|Tan Son Nhut]] and [[Da Nang]], [[Vietnam]].  This first deployment to Vietnam was concluded with the squadron's return to Whidbey Island on 1 April 1955.  A second deployment was made on 13 February 1966, replacing [[Patrol Squadron 22]] at Iwakumi and deploying a detachment of seven aircraft to Tan Son Nhut.  These aircraft participated in [[Operation Market Time]], a joint United States - South Vietnam effort begun on 11 March 1965, by mounting coastal patrols aimed at stopping supply of equipment and munitions to the North Vietnamese by sea.  VP-1 was the first patrol squadron to suffer casualties in Vietnam with one person killed and five wounded during an attack on Tan Son Nhut on 13 April 1966.  Five of the squadron's aircraft were damaged as well during the action.

The squadron's third Vietnam deployment was out of [[Naval Station Sangley Point|Naval Air Station Sangley Point]] in [[Cavite]], [[Philippines]] with a forward detachment becoming the first to operate full-time from the recently completed [[Cam Ranh Bay Naval Base|Naval Air Facility Cam Ranh]] in Vietnam.  This 1967 deployment was followed by another rotation the following year using the same facilities, but in 1970, the squadron's return to the West Pacific was back at Iwakuni and several detachments were supported, including to the previously utilized Cam Ranh and Tan Son Nhut air bases as well as a new detachment to [[U-Tapao Royal Thai Navy Airfield]] in [[Thailand]].  The squadron returned to Sangley Point for its 1971 deployment, but had to move to [[Naval Air Station Cubi Point]], also in the Philippines, as Sangley Point was shut down in May.  VP-1 thus became the first patrol squadron to operate from the new Cubi Point facility.  The squadron's final Vietnam combat deployment was to Cubi Point in 1972 with a six aircraft detachment at U-Tapao.

In 1980, the squadron deployed to Cubi Point again with a three aircraft detachment at [[Naval Air Station Diego Garcia]] in the [[Indian Ocean]].  While the Vietnam War had ended several years prior, the squadron was heavily involved in search and rescue efforts for [[Vietnamese boat people]].  The squadron would end up being involved in the rescue of more than 4,000 people, earning its receipt of the [[Humanitarian Service Medal]].&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;

=== Changes in equipment and basing ===
[[File:C-130F and P-3Bs of Patrol Wing 2 at NAS Barbers Point 1970s.jpg|thumb|left|A VP-1 P-3B Orion with other aircraft of PatWing 2 at Barbers Point]]
After more than twenty years of operating the P-2 Neptune, the squadron began receiving [[Lockheed P-3 Orion|P-3B Orion]] aircraft to replace its aging SP-2H fleet in July 1969.  VP-1 was the last fleet squadron to still operate the Neptune, and as the transition was completed by 1 October 1969, it retired the P-2 from frontline service with the United States Navy.  At that point, VP-1 also found itself as the last patrol squadron based at Whidbey Island.  A congressional review of force structure and bases was made in 1969 as the increasing costs of the war in Vietnam put pressure on the services to find cost reductions.  VP-1 found itself in a tenuous position as the sole Whidbey-based patrol squadron and still in transition to the new P-3 aircraft.  As such, in October 1969 it was nominated for deactivation and placed in stand-down, limiting the flow of personnel to the squadron.  By December, however, the [[Chief of Naval Operations]] had determined to keep VP-1 operational, though to relocate it to [[Naval Air Station Barbers Point]] in [[Hawaii]] where it would join other Orion-equipped squadrons.

The Orion continued to be upgraded throughout its service life, and VP-1 marked the final transition for several technologies during the 1970s.  Not only had the squadron been the last to transition from the P-2, but its P-3B aircraft were not equipped with Directional Low Frequency Analysis and Recording (DIFAR) gear until the unit's final deployment to Vietnam.  The squadron's deployment to [[Naval Air Station Agana]] in [[Guam]] in December 1976 marked the last time an active fleet squadron would deploy with the baseline P-3B to the Western Pacific.  In July 1978, crews from VP-1 were the last to fire [[AGM-12 Bullpup]] missiles in exercises before removal of the missile from Navy inventory the following month.  The following year, the squadron was deployed temporarily to [[Moffett Federal Airfield|Naval Air Station Moffett Field]] in [[California]] as they transitioned to the P-3B TAC/NAV MOD version of the Orion.  This aircraft had significant improvements in power and avionics, replacing the final baseline P-3B in January 1980.

Further modification of the squadron's aircraft was undertaken in 1982 with implementation of Infra-Red Detection System/Harpoon Airborne Command and Launch Subsystem (IRDS/HACLS) which added the ability to detect targets using infrared sensors and allowing the aircraft to carry and launch [[Harpoon (missile)|Harpoon]] missiles.  These modifications were undertaken at [[Naval Air Station Alameda]] in California.  The P-3B was finally replaced by the much more capable P-3C MOD, with the first such aircraft being transferred from [[Patrol Squadron 30]] in October 1984.  While the P-3C MOD was not the most advanced model of the P-3C in Navy service at the time, the airframes received by the squadron did include a number of retrofits, giving them features of the newer production aircraft.  VP-1 received actual P-3C Update III aircraft in February 1991, with training on the new equipment done at Moffett Field on a rotational basis until completed in July of that year.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;

=== End of the Cold War ===
[[File:P-3B VP-1 over Soviet Victor class sub 1987.JPG|right|thumb|P-3B passing over a Soviet submarine]]
Patrol Squadron 1's detachment to Diego Garcia in 1980 provided support during the [[Iranian hostage crisis]], earning the [[Navy Expeditionary Medal]].  The squadron would later play host to a [[Japanese Maritime Self Defense Force]] deployment at Barber's Point in July 1983, providing maintenance and administrative support for their guests as they engaged in a month of joint training.  Into the 1980s, VP-1 retained a proud record of safe operations, having amassed over 100,000 flight hours without an accident by 1983.  Unfortunately this ended with a pair of accidents that year, one of which resulted in the death of fourteen aircrew.  The subsequent investigation into these incidents resulted in the sacking of both commanding and executive officers of the squadron.

Iraq's [[invasion of Kuwait]] on 2 August 1990 drew an immediate response by the United States to defend [[Saudi Arabia]] and prepare to eject Iraq from Kuwait.  On the 11th, VP-1 received orders to deploy to Diego Garcia in support of these efforts and were deployed there within 72 hours.  A four aircraft detachment was deployed to [[RAFO Masirah]], [[Oman]] along with a two aircraft detachment further forward to [[Jeddah]], Saudi Arabia.  These aircraft operated in the [[Persian Gulf]] to monitor shipping and maintain vigilance should the Iraqi Navy attempt to sortie into the Persian Gulf.  No significant Iraqi attempt was made however, and the squadron's deployment was completed without incident.

During the 1990s, the squadron made several dispersed deployments.  In 1990, the squadron supplied a pair of aircraft to the Joint Task Force in Panama Law Enforcement Operations in Central America.  These aircraft completed a pair of deployments in June/July and October/November 1991 operating from [[Howard Air Force Base]] in the [[Panama Canal Zone]].  The aircraft supported drug interdiction efforts in Central America as part of the follow-up to [[United States invasion of Panama|Operation Just Cause]].  In 1992, a third detachment to Howard AFB was made by the squadron for counter-narcotics operations, though this detachment also operated from [[Pie de la Cuesta, Guerrero]], [[Mexico]], making it the first patrol squadron of the US Navy to operate from the [[Mexican Air Force]] facility.  Other deployment locations in the 1990s included [[Naval Air Station Adak]] and [[Eielson Air Force Base]] in [[Alaska]] and [[Naval Air Facility Kadena]] and [[Misawa Air Force Base]] in Japan, as well as deployments to Guam, [[Indonesia]], [[Malaysia]], [[Oman]], [[Singapore]], [[South Korea]], and [[Thailand]].  During their 1996 deployment to the Indian Ocean, the squadron participated in a pair of [[search and rescue]] missions to assist foreign vessels in distress.  Combat operations included escort and patrol as part of [[Operation Desert Strike]] in September 1996, and the first patrol aircraft missions in the [[Persian Gulf]] to carry [[AGM-65 Maverick]] missiles, carried out in November.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;

=== Post-Cold War support ===
A further performance enhancement came with the squadron's transition to the P-3C AIP version of the Orion in the late 1990s.  VP-1 successfully deployed with this aircraft to the [[Persian Gulf]] from June to December 1999, operating it from Diego Garcia, Masirah, [[Manama]], [[Bahrain]], and [[Doha]], [[Qatar]].  Quite unusually, the squadron deployed a pair of aircraft to support [[NATO|NATO's]] [[Kosovo Force]] with armed flights in the [[Adriatic Sea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gsec&quot;&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/agency/navy/vp-1.htm|title=Patrol Squadron ONE (VP-1)|publisher=GlobalSecurity.org|accessdate=29 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The following year, back at home, the squadron participated in [[Exercise RIMPAC|RIMPAC]], a multi-national exercise in the Pacific Ocean, while preparing crews on the AIP aircraft.  The squadron's next deployment came in 2001, and in addition to normal antisubmarine warfare missions, the squadron was active in the search and role efforts in several exercises.  These included participation in the Hong Kong Search and Rescue Exercise and the Maritime Sea-Surveillance Exercise.  The latter was the first trilateral exercise involving the Philippines, Thailand, and the United States.  Antisubmarine exercises included work with the [[Republic of Singapore Navy]], [[Royal Australian Navy]] (Operation Tandem Thrust), the [[Royal Thai Navy]] (Operation Cobra Gold), and {{USS|Kitty Hawk|CV-63|6}} battle group and {{USS|Essex|LHD-2}} amphibious readiness group.

[[File:US Navy 021101-N-4374S-032 P-3C Orion on a routine mission.jpg|thumb|left|A P-3C Orion crew member during [[Operation Enduring Freedom]]]]
Deployed to Diego Garcia again from June 2001 to June 2002, the squadron operated in support of [[United States Fifth Fleet|Fifth]] and [[United States Sixth Fleet|Sixth Fleet]] areas, operating detachments in Manama and Masirah.  During this deployment the squadron flew more than 6000 hours in support of [[Operation Enduring Freedom]] and [[Operation Southern Watch]] without incident in close cooperation with all branches of the United States military as well as several foreign air forces.  Returning home, VP-1 completed a successful inter-deployment training cycle (IDRC) before a six-month deployment to the Western Pacific began in December 2003.  Operating as part of [[Seventh Fleet]], the squadron operated primarily from Misawa and Kadena in addition to smaller operations from six other airfields as they took part in a number of international exercises, including locations in Australia, Guam, the Philippines, South Korea, Singapore, and Thailand.  More than 3000 hours were compiled during the deployment.

The squadron repeated its Japanese deployment in December 2005 on the heels of winning the Arnold J. Isbell award for ASW excellence during their IDRC.  During the deployment's 4700 flight hours, they participated in exercises with the [[Japanese Maritime Self Defense Force]], operated with five major US Navy groups, and deployed detachments to Australia, [[Brunei]], Guam, the Marshall Islands, the Philippines, Singapore, South Korea, and Thailand.  Upon their arrival, the squadron celebrated 135,000 hours without a mishap, a feat extending over 23 years of operations.  They participated after their return in RIMPAC 2006 and [[Mojave Viper]] exercises and supported the {{USS|John C. Stennis|CVN-74|6}}, {{USS|Nimitz|CVN-68|6}}, and {{USS|Bonhomme Richard|LHD-6|6}} groups.  Several aircraft from the squadron returned to the Middle East in 2007 in support of Operations Enduring Freedom and [[Operation Iraqi Freedom|Iraqi Freedom]], while exercises such as Empire Challenge and Valiant Shield helped the rest of the squadron ready themselves for deployment and demonstrate further capabilities of their aircrews and aircraft.

Deployed to Kadena in November 2007, VP-1 aircraft additionally were detached to Misawa and the Philippines.  After exercises with the Royal Australian Navy (TAMEX) and the [[Republic of Korea Navy]] (LINKEX), the squadron was cut to only four operational aircraft as the Navy's Red Stripe program came into effect, withdrawing operational P-3 aircraft for overhaul.  This reduced complement did not excuse the squadron from its operational commitment, and the unit was able to uphold its participation in further exercises including Snapdragon Red, Distant Thunder, CMPOP, and Cobra Gold, as well as detachments to Guam and Thailand before returning home in 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;VP1&quot;&gt;{{Citation| url   = http://www.vp1.navy.mil/history.html| title = VP-1 History| work  = Command Information| publisher  = Patrol Squadron 1| accessdate = 29 January 2016| ref = none}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Patrol Squadron 1 detached a pair of aircrews in January 2013 to Kaneohe Bay for participation in Undersea Warfare Exercise 13-1.  The crews worked in cooperation with both fellow American forces as well as the [[Royal Canadian Air Force]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vp1news&quot;&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.vp1.navy.mil/news.html|title=VP-1 Participate in USWEX 13-1|work=VP-1 News|publisher=Patrol Squadron 1|date=25 January 2013|accessdate=29 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Designations, assignments, and aircraft ===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!colspan=5| Designations, home ports, command assignments, and aircraft of Patrol Squadron One&lt;ref name=&quot;danas2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Michael|last=Roberts|title=Dictionary of American Naval Aviation Squadrons Volume 2: The History of VP, VPB, VP(HL) and VP(AM) Squadrons|publisher=Naval Historical Center|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vpnavy&quot;/&gt;
|-
! Date !! Designation !! Home Port !! Assignment !! Aircraft
|-
| 1943 February 15 ||align=center valign=top rowspan=4| Bombing Squadron ONE HUNDRED TWENTY EIGHT&lt;br&gt;(VB-128) || {{flagicon|Florida}} [[DeLand, Florida|DeLand]], [[Florida]] || Fleet Air Wing Twelve ||rowspan=9| [[Lockheed Ventura|PV-1 Ventura]]
|-
| 1943 May 17 ||rowspan=4| {{flagicon|New York}} [[Floyd Bennett Field]], [[New York (state)|New York]] || Fleet Air Wing Nine
|-
| 1943 August 23 || Fleet Air Wing Seven
|-
| 1943 December 19 ||rowspan=2| Fleet Air Wing Eleven
|-
| 1944 October 1 ||align=center valign=top rowspan=4| Patrol Bombing Squadron ONE HUNDRED TWENTY EIGHT&lt;br&gt;(VPB-128)
|-
| 1944 October 6 ||rowspan=2| {{flagicon|Hawaii}} [[Marine Corps Air Station Kaneohe Bay|NAS Kaneohe]], [[Hawaii]] || Fleet Air Wing One
|-
| 1944 December 21 ||rowspan=3| Fleet Air Wing Seventeen
|-
| 1945 June 21 || {{flagicon|Northern Mariana Islands}} [[Tinian Island]], [[Northern Mariana Islands]]
|-
| 1946 May 15 ||align=center rowspan=2 valign=top| Patrol Squadron ONE HUNDRED TWENTY EIGHT&lt;br&gt;(VP-128) ||rowspan=4| {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Naha Air Base]], [[Okinawa]]
|-
| 1946 November 7 ||rowspan=2| Fleet Air Wing One ||rowspan=2| PV-2 Harpoon
|-
| 1946 November 15 ||align=center valign=top rowspan=3| Medium Patrol Squadron (Landplane) ONE&lt;br&gt;(VP-ML-1)
|-
| 1947 March || Fleet Air Wing Fourteen ||rowspan=3| [[Lockheed P-2 Neptune|P2V-2 Neptune]]
|-
| 1948 January 13 ||rowspan=8| {{flagicon|Washington}} [[Naval Air Station Whidbey Island|NAS Whidbey Island]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]] ||rowspan=8| Fleet Air Wing Four
|-
| 1948 September 1 ||align=center valign=top rowspan=13| Patrol Squadron ONE&lt;br&gt;(VP-1)
|-
| 1950 July || P2V-3 Neptune
|-
| 1953 May || P2V-5 Neptune
|-
| 1957 || P2V-5F Neptune
|-
| 1959 August || P2V-7 Neptune
|-
| 1963 August || SP-2H Neptune
|-
| 1969 July ||rowspan=2| [[Lockheed P-3 Orion|P-3B Orion]]
|-
| 1970 June 30 ||rowspan=4| {{flagicon|Hawaii}} [[Naval Air Station Barbers Point|NAS Barbers Point]], Hawaii ||rowspan=4| Patrol Wing Two
|-
| 1979 November || P-3B MOD Orion
|-
| 1984 October || P-3C MOD Orion
|-
| 1991 February ||rowspan=3| P-3C Update IIIR Orion
|-
| 1995 July ||rowspan=2| {{flagicon|Washington}} NAS Whidbey Island, Washington || Patrol Wing Ten
|-
| 1999 June 1 || Patrol and Reconnaissance Wing Ten
|}

== Awards ==
Patrol Squadron One has been recognized with the following awards during its establishment:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=90% style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;
|-
!colspan=4| Unit Awards received by Patrol Squadron One&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;
|-
! Ribbon !! Award !! Dates !! Notes
|-
|align=center valign=top rowspan=3| [[File:Navy Unit Commendation ribbon.svg|100px]] ||valign=top rowspan=3| [[Navy Unit Commendation]] || 1 January 1967 - 14 May 1967
|-
| 16 November 1967 - 31 March 1968
|-
| 2 August 1990 - 1 November 1990
|-
|align=center valign=top rowspan=7| [[File:Navy Meritorious Unit Commendation ribbon.svg|100px]] ||valign=top rowspan=7| [[Meritorious Unit Commendation]] || 15 May 1967 - 15 November 1967
|-
| 20 April 1970 - 1 August 1970
|-
| 1 April 1971 - 20 April 1971
|-
| 28 August 1982 - 7 September 1982
|-
| 10 June 1988 - 10 December 1988
|-
| 20 April 1970 - 1 August 1970 || selected crews only
|-
| 1 April 1971 - 20 April 1971
|-
|align=center valign=top rowspan=2| [[File:Vietnam gallantry cross-w-palm-3d.svg|100px]] ||valign=top rowspan=2| [[Gallantry Cross (Vietnam)|Gallantry Cross]] || 13 May 1967 - 5 November 1967 || awarded by the government of the [[Republic of Vietnam]]
|-
| 1 August 1968 - 1 March 1969
|-
|align=center| [[File:Vietnam Service Ribbon.svg|100px]] || [[Vietnam Service Medal]] || 7 February 1966 - 2 June 1966
|-
|align=center valign=top rowspan=4| [[File:AFEMRib.svg|100px]] ||valign=top rowspan=4| [[Armed Forces Expeditionary Medal]] || 28 March 1952 - 30 April 1952
|-
| 1 May 1952 - 3 October 1952
|-
| 20 May 1980 - 10 November 1980 || select crews
|-
| 5 August 1981 - 20 October 1981 || Guam Detachment
|-
|align=center valign=top rowspan=3| [[File:Army of Occupation ribbon.svg|100px]] ||valign=top rowspan=3| [[Navy Occupation Service Medal]] || 15 November 1946 - 7 November 1947
|-
| 1 August 1950 - 7 November 1950
|-
| 12 May 1951 - 23 July 1951
|-
|align=center| [[File:Southwest Asia Service ribbon.svg|100px]] || [[Southwest Asia Service Medal]] || 14 August 1990 - 19 November 1990
|-
|align=center| [[File:Humanitarian Service ribbon.svg|100px]] || [[Humanitarian Service Medal]] || 9 May 1980 - 10 November 1980 || For assistance in rescuing more than 4,000 refugees
|}

== Incidents ==
* 7 August 1943:  A [[Lockheed Ventura|PV-1 Ventura]] was shot down by a German submarine's antiaircraft fire in the Atlantic Ocean about 300 miles off the coast of [[Virginia]].  The aircraft had spotted and attacked the submarine, damaging it in the attack.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;danfs&quot;/&gt;
* 22 March 1945:  A PV-1 Ventura piloted by Lieutenant Tepuni was shot down by Japanese antiaircraft fire during an attack on Japanese naval facilities in [[Cebu City]], [[Philippines]].  The aircraft had been involved in rocket attacks which sunk a midget submarine.  The PV-1 was lost with all hands.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;
* 3 January 1953:  A [[Lockheed P-2 Neptune|P2V Neptune]] crashed off the coast of [[Washington (state)|Washington]].  Four of the crew survived, one was lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;koreanwar&quot;&gt;{{Citation|url=|title=VP-1 Patrol Squadron|work=Navy Air - Patrol|publisher=Korean War Project|accessdate=29 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 13 April 1966:  Five P-2 Neptune aircraft were damaged on the ground at [[Tan Son Nhut Air Base]] during attacks by Communist forces.  The squadron suffered one killed and five wounded in the attack.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;
* 15 December 1967:  SP-2H Neptune aircraft coded YB-2 crashed in the Pacific Ocean off the coast of [[Alaska]].  The aircraft was engaged in tracking Soviet submarines.  No trace of aircraft or crew was found.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;
* 17 May 1983:  [[Lockheed P-3 Orion|P-3B Orion]] BuNo. 152733 made a belly landing at [[Naval Air Station Barbers Point]], [[Hawaii]].&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;
* 16 June 1983:  P-3B Orion BuNo. 152720 crashed into a mountain in [[Kauai]], Hawaii.  All fourteen people on the aircraft were killed.&lt;ref name=DANAS2-3/&gt;

== See also ==
{{Commons category|Patrol Squadron 1 (United States Navy)}}
* [[List of United States Navy aircraft squadrons]]
* [[List of squadrons in the Dictionary of American Naval Aviation Squadrons]]

== References ==
{{DANAS}}
{{reflist}}

{{US Navy navbox}}
{{United States Navy Aircraft Squadrons}}

[[Category:Patrol squadrons of the United States Navy]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1943]]
[[Category:Wikipedia articles incorporating text from the Dictionary of American Naval Aviation Squadrons]]</text>
      <sha1>kk48emgjsel5jop9xhdxxxmxl4fyy3w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
