<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Walter Schellenberg</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>351718</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749425217</id>
      <parentid>748508024</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T07:14:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CitationCleanerBot</username>
        <id>15270283</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up, url redundant with jstor, and/or remove accessdate if no url using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40717">{{Infobox military person
|name= Walter Schellenberg
|birth_date=16 January 1910
|death_date= {{death date and age|df=yes|1952|3|31|1910|1|16|}}
|image=Bundesarchiv Bild 101III-Alber-178-04A, Walter Schellenberg.jpg
|caption=Schellenberg as a SS-Oberführer
|birth_place=[[Saarbrücken]], [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]], [[German Empire|Germany]]
|death_place=[[Turin]], [[Italy]]
|nickname=
|allegiance={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany]]|
|branch=[[File:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|23px]] [[Schutzstaffel]]
|serviceyears=1933–1945
|rank=[[Brigadeführer]] und Generalmajor der Polizei
|commands=Chief of Amt VI, [[Sicherheitsdienst#Ausland-SD|Ausland-SD]]
|unit=[[Sicherheitsdienst]]
|battles=
|awards=[[Iron Cross|Iron Cross First Class]]&lt;br&gt;[[Iron Cross|Iron Cross Second Class]]&lt;br&gt;[[War Merit Cross|War Merit Cross First Class with Swords]]&lt;br&gt;[[War Merit Cross|War Merit Cross Second Class with Swords]]
}}

'''Walter Friedrich Schellenberg''' (16 January 1910 – 31 March 1952) was a [[Germans|German]] [[Schutzstaffel|SS]]-''[[Brigadeführer]]'' who rose through the ranks of the [[SS]], becoming one of the highest ranking men in the ''[[Sicherheitsdienst]]'' (SD) and eventually assumed the position as head of [[foreign intelligence]] for the Reich following the abolition of the ''[[Abwehr]]'' in 1944.

==Career==
Schellenberg was born in [[Saarbrücken]], [[German Empire|Germany]].{{sfn|Hamilton|1996|p=64}} He was the seventh child born to his parents and his father was a piano manufacturer.{{sfn|Wistrich|1995|p=221}} Schellenberg moved with his family to [[Luxembourg]] when the [[France|French]] occupation of the [[Saar (League of Nations)|Saar Basin]] after the [[World War I|First World War]] triggered an economic crisis in the [[Weimar Republic]]. Like many young intellectuals who would later join the SD, Schellenberg was deeply affected by the economic woes which befell Germany in the wake of the [[First World War]].{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=255}}

Schellenberg returned to Germany to attend university, first at the [[University of Marburg]] and then, in 1929, at the [[University of Bonn]]. He initially studied medicine, but soon switched to law. While in law school, Schellenberg performed some spy work for the SD.{{sfn|Höhne|2001|p=214}} He reported actually having been recruited by two SD agents who were college faculty, who also advised him to join the Civil Service.{{sfn|Browder|1996|pp=225–226}} After graduating he joined the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] in 1933.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=141}} From what Schellenberg later wrote, the &quot;better type of people&quot; preferred the SS over the other Nazi organizations.{{sfn|Höhne|2001|p=132}} While educated as a lawyer, Schellenberg distrusted administrative attorneys and was intent on ensuring the SD could operate outside the constraints of normal law.{{sfn|Höhne|2001|pp=254–255}} Subscribing to the ''Führer-Prinzip'', Schellenberg also thought Hitler's directives were beyond the framework of the legal system and believed it was best to &quot;unquestioningly&quot; carry-out anything ordered by the Nazi leader.{{sfn|Höhne|2001|p=255}}

In 1935, Schellenberg met [[Reinhard Heydrich]] and worked for him in the [[counter-intelligence]] department of the ''[[Sicherheitsdienst]]'' (SD).{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=141}} Besides his native German, Schellenberg also spoke French and English fluently.{{sfn|Wistrich|1995|p=221}} Correspondingly, his first foreign-intelligence assignment was to Paris in 1934, where his role was to check up on the political views of a professor.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|pp=255–256}} Then in 1937, Schellenberg was sent to Italy for a police assignment which included security duties for an upcoming visit by Mussolini; his outstanding work in providing security garnered positive attention from Heydrich, who then tasked him with additional organizational responsibilities, some of which later helped birth the RSHA.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=256}} The official SS personnel report on Schellenberg described him as &quot;open, irreproachable, and reliable&quot;; the file also delineated him as &quot;firm, tough, possesses energy&quot; and one who was &quot;very sharp thinking&quot;; and his National Socialist worldview was labeled, &quot;thoroughly fortified.&quot;{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=258}} Many of the SS street-brawling types despised men like Schellenberg, considering them effete, but for the most part Schellenberg made a good impression on the Nazi elite.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=260}}

Sometime in 1938, Schellenberg married Käthe Kortekamp, a seamstress three years his senior, who he dated for seven years and had supported him through college. Their marriage was short due partially to her social standing and the fact many things about her embarrassed him; the relationship ended in divorce in 1939 but only after Schellenberg promised her an &quot;aryanized&quot; fashion business expropriated from Jewish owners.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|pp=256–257}} Shortly thereafter, he married a more socially-acceptable woman, the daughter of an insurance executive named Irene Grosse-Schönepauck, but this relationship was also troubled.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=257}}

As the Nazis tightened their grip on German society, Hitler and ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] determined that the SS and police organs should merge, a move which Schellenberg fully supported by releasing a memorandum in 24 February 1939 which advocated further centralization within the state.{{sfn|Buchheim|1968|p=204}} In summer 1939, Schellenberg became one of the directors of Heydrich's foundation, the ''[[Stiftung Nordhav]]''. Schellenberg was mentored by [[Herbert Mehlhorn]] while at the ''[[SS-Hauptamt]]''.{{sfn|Doerries|Weinberg|2009|pp=19–20}} When Heydrich announced his intentions to create the [[Reich Main Security Office]] (RSHA) in July 1939, he had Schellenberg to thank as both the organisation's name and its existence were resultant from his plans. On 27 September 1939, Himmler made the RSHA an official state organ by decree.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=470}}

As the role of the SS and its action groups, the SS-''[[Einsatzgruppen]]'', expanded in the war zones in May 1941, it was Schellenberg who negotiated with the [[Wehrmacht]] in acquiring logistical support from the army (both on the front-line and rear areas) so the ''Einsatzgruppen'' could carry out their killing operations more effectively.{{sfn|Rhodes|2003|p=15}} Acting on behalf of Heydrich, Schellenberg issued a circular on 20 May 1941 to all segments of the German Security Police which forbade any Jews from emigrating out of German-controlled territory; this new policy was part of the nefarious [[Final Solution]].{{sfn|Gilbert|1989|pp=187–188}} The language within the circular Schellenberg issued even contained the explicit expression, &quot;in view of the undoubtedly imminent Final Solution of the Jewish question&quot;, a statement that makes it clear he was both complicit and aware of the impending extermination activities.{{sfn|Fleming|1994|pp=44–45}} Despite being Heydrich's direct subordinate, Schellenberg skillfully ingratiated himself to Himmler by first delivering his intelligence reports to him instead of Heydrich, which earned him the ''Reichsführer's'' confidence.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=267}}  After Heydrich's death in June 1942, Schellenberg became the &quot;closest professional confidant&quot; of Himmler.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=398}} Himmler bestowed upon Schellenberg a unique position beyond that of a simple aide, making him his special-[[plenipotentiary]] (''Sonderbevollmächtigter'').{{sfn|Doerries|2003|p=29}}

==SD operations==
When Walter Schellenberg moved to Frankfurt in 1934, he recalled meeting an SS-Oberführer, who explained to him the mission of the SD; he was told the following, which he wrote in his memoirs: 
::The SD was the chief organ of the information service of the party. Its task was to inform the top Party leaders of all opposition movements and forces at home and abroad. It covered the administration, the Party, industry, the theatre, journalism, the police—in fact there was no sphere that was not under the watchful eye of the SD, no place where it did not seek out the first signs of opposition among movements or individuals 'hostile' to the state'.{{sfn|Schellenberg|1956|p=9}}
 
In March 1938, Schellenberg traveled with Himmler and Heydrich to Vienna for the impending ''[[Anschluss]]'' with Austria. One of the reasons for their journey was so the SD could &quot;confiscate Austrian secret service material.&quot;{{sfn|Gerwarth|2012|pp=163–164}} During the trip, Schellenberg allegedly saved Himmler from a potential mishap when he noticed that the aircraft door which he had been leaning against was not properly secured. Throwing Himmler aside in the process, Schellenberg earned the gratitude of the ''Reichsführer'', who promised to reciprocate the favor if the chance ever presented itself.{{sfn|Manvell|Fraenkel|1987|p=68}} Following the exuberant reception of Hitler when he arrived in Vienna, Schellenberg later wrote, &quot;‘never...have I seen such tremendous, enthusiastic and joyous crowds.&quot;{{sfn|Manvell|Fraenkel|1987|p=70}}

Much like Austria, the Nazis set their sights on the [[Sudetenland]] of [[Czechoslovakia]], a region with over three-million ethnic Germans which they wanted to incorporate into the Reich; more than that, Hitler once told his generals that he desired for Czechoslovakia to &quot;disappear from the map&quot;.{{sfn|Evans|2006|pp=664–667}} In the summer of 1938, the [[Gestapo]] and ''SD-Ausland'', which had taken control of the Secret Service in Czechoslovakia, helped the Sudeten Nazis from the ''Sudetendeutsche Partei'' infiltrate regional and local organizations, veterans groups, musical societies, sporting associations, sailing clubs, and cultural societies—which gave them insight into the economic, political, and military situation there. So thorough was the Nazi penetration in much of the Sudetenland, that Schellenberg stated later it was necessary to establish two telephone transmission stations along the frontier to communicate with Berlin.{{sfn|Delarue|2008|pp=166–167}} Eventually after strained negotiations with the West, Hitler acquired the Sudetenland when the [[Munich Agreement]] was concluded.{{sfn|Evans|2006|pp=678–683}} Following this event, Schellenberg accompanied Hitler, Himmler, and Heydrich into Prague on 15 March 1939 and reported that Himmler was so pleased with the performance and racial makeup of the Czech police, that he incorporated them into the SS.{{sfn|Delarue|2008|pp=170–171}} 
 
In November 1939, Schellenberg played a major part in the [[Venlo Incident]], which led to the capture of two [[Secret Intelligence Service|British MI6 agents]], [[Sigismund Payne Best|Captain Sigismund Payne-Best]] and Major [[Richard Henry Stevens|Richard Stevens]].{{sfn|Waller|1996|pp=104–118}} Schellenberg posed as a &quot;Major Schaemmel&quot; claiming to be part of an anti-Nazi group of officers planning a coup against Hitler. At Schellenberg's third meeting with Stevens and Best in the German-Dutch border town of Venlo, the trap was sprung; the two British agents were captured.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=147}} Hitler awarded Schellenberg the [[Iron Cross]] for his actions.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=259}}{{Efn|&quot;The Venlo Kidnapping&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 19 February 1948.}} Success in this operation directly contributed to Schellenberg's promotion to SS Major-General and helped the SD acquire greater leverage in foreign policy and gave their police Attachés access to foreign networks through the diplomatically immune offices of the German embassies abroad.{{sfn|Grunberger|1993|p=47}} The operation also damaged British morale and inclined them not to trust the opposition in Germany.{{sfn|Hassell|MacRae|Ameskamp|2006|p=60}}

In June 1940 he was charged with compiling the ''[[Informationsheft Grossbritannien|Informationsheft G.B.]]'', a blueprint for the occupation of Britain after a proposed invasion by Nazi Germany. The preparations for invasion, known as [[Operation Sea Lion]] (''Unternehmen Seelöwe''), were ultimately abandoned. He based his work on the interrogations of British agents Best and Stevens, along with his own &quot;preconceptions&quot;.{{sfn|Gerwarth|2012|p=177}} Part of what he prepared was described as &quot;a handbook for German troops and officials as a guide to the British institutions they would encounter.&quot;{{sfn|Evans|2010|p=139}} The extent of his direct involvement in compiling the book and its supplement, however, has been disputed.{{sfn|Doerries|Weinberg|2009|p=33}} The supplement was the &quot;Special Wanted List, GB&quot; (''Sonderfahndungsliste G.B.'', also known as &quot;The Black Book&quot;), which was a list of 2,300 prominent [[United Kingdom|Britons]] to be arrested immediately after the successful invasion of Britain.{{sfn|Shirer|1990|p=965}} Both Schellenberg and Heydrich perceived Great Britain as a country run by &quot;Freemasons, Jews, and a small public-school-trained elite.&quot;{{sfn|Gerwarth|2012|p=177}} Despite the poor opinion of Britain shared by both men, their full attention was turned there when on 10 May 1941, Deputy Führer [[Rudolf Hess]] made his infamous flight to Scotland.{{sfn|Evans|2006|pp=167–170}} Subsequently, SD Chief Schellenberg informed Hitler that Hess had been long under the influence of the British Secret Service and German collaborators.{{sfn|Waller|1996|p=178}} Upon further investigation, Schellenberg also reported to Hitler that Hess made his flight under the advice of an astrologer, which incited the activity of Heydrich who promptly arrested as many mediums, psychics, and astrologers he could round up in Berlin.{{sfn|Waller|1996|p=181}}

Besides reactive intelligence reports like those he provided concerning Hess, Schellenberg arranged numerous plots of subterfuge and [[Intelligence (information gathering)|intelligence gathering]], including the [[covert listening device|bugging]] of [[Salon Kitty]], a high-class Berlin brothel. Some of the Nazi regime's upper echelons even visited this brothel unaware at first, like Foreign Minister [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]].{{sfn|Manvell|Fraenkel|1987|pp=80–81}} However, intelligence collection efforts at Salon Kitty were essentially a failure as they never revealed anything significant.{{sfn|Gerwarth|2012|p=166}}

Direct access to Himmler also made Schellenberg privy to some of the Reich's most sensitive material. For example, Schellenberg knew early on about the arrangement between Germany and Russia concerning the partition of Poland, an agreement which presaged the military invasion.{{sfn|Manvell|Fraenkel|1987|p=83}} Once the Nazis invaded and occupied Polish territory, Schellenberg was entrusted with securing the rear areas by Himmler and Heydrich, which meant he oversaw the deployment of special commandos from the SD and Gestapo, units which carried-out brutal measures against the Poles.{{sfn|Delarue|2008|p=176}} Another one of his areas of responsibility was counter-espionage, both within Germany and the occupied territories—a task for which Schellenberg seemed well-suited given his penchant for intrigue.{{sfn|Manvell|Fraenkel|1987|pp=83–84}} Operating as an intelligence adviser to Himmler in Poland meant Schellenberg was at the front edge of the spear, but this did not mean he was incapable of being surprised. In fact, he was particularly shocked at the utter devastation wrought by the Wehrmacht in Poland and commented in his ''Memoirs'' upon seeing it that, &quot;Until then I had no real conception of what total war meant.&quot;{{sfn|Schellenberg|1956|p=75}}

In 1940, Schellenberg was sent to [[Portugal]] by Heydrich at Foreign Minister [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]]'s request to intercept the [[Duke of Windsor|Duke and Duchess of Windsor]] and try to persuade them to work for Germany.{{sfn|Read|2005|p=658}} Schellenberg was supposed to offer them $50 million Swiss francs to go to neutral Switzerland. But [[Winston Churchill]] dispatched an attorney, who happened to be an old friend of the Duke, to convince them to leave Portugal.{{sfn|Hassell|MacRae|Ameskamp|2006|p=102}} In the end, the mission was a failure; Schellenberg managed nothing more than a delay of the Duke's baggage for a few hours.{{sfn|Hamilton|1996|p=64}} However, in March 1940, he did help convince Hitler that Dutch military intelligence was working closely with the British intelligence services, which Hitler used as a pretext to attack the Netherlands &quot;for violating their  neutrality.&quot;{{sfn|Manvell|Fraenkel|1987|p=96}}

In February 1942, after the 1941 German attack on the Soviet Union had failed,  Schellenberg conceived and implemented a large-scale spy operation designed to penetrate into the Soviet Union, an initiative known as Operation Zeppelin (''Unternehmen Zeppelin'').{{sfn|Biddiscombe |2000|pp=1115–1142}} Using anti-Communists selected from the many thousands of POWs captured by the Germans, he soon had anywhere from 10,000 to 15,000 potential candidates in training, who were accordingly indoctrinated. Only between 2,000 to 3,000 completed the training and as little as a few hundred of them ever were committed to the operation due to insufficient numbers of aircraft and radio communication equipment.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=360}} What started as a large-scale effort by Schellenberg, quickly became a precision one with very limited success. Most of them produced little to no useful intelligence and/or were killed once deployed. One German intelligence officer commented that if losses &quot;were not over 90 percent, we were satisfied.&quot;{{sfn|Kahn|1978|pp=360–361}}

In March 1942, [[Heinz Jost]] was fired as RSHA Chief of Amt VI, ''[[Sicherheitsdienst#Ausland-SD|SD-Ausland]]'' (SD foreign intelligence).{{sfn|Doerries|2003|pp=21, 80}} In his place, Schellenberg was appointed chief of ''SD-Ausland'' by Heydrich.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=61}} Sometime in mid-1942, Schellenberg had been involved in planning operations in neutral [[Ireland]] including [[Operation Osprey|Operation ''Osprey'']], a plan involving No.1 SS Special Service Troop.{{Efn|Later becoming [[500th SS Parachute Battalion]] a/k/a/ SS-Fallschirmjäger-Bataillon 500, an amalgamation of No. 1 Troop and various SS penal battalions. Notably participating in [[Operation Rösselsprung (1944)|Operation Rösselsprung]], the raid against Tito's HQ in 1944.}} Knowledge that Germany might lose the war prompted Schellenberg to open communication channels during the fall of 1942 with the Swiss intelligence chief, Colonel Roger Masson.{{sfn|Hassell|MacRae|Ameskamp|2006|p=196}} He even went so far as providing Masson with a list of all the ''Abwehr'' agents operating in Switzerland with the intention of &quot;having them expelled.&quot;{{sfn|Halbrook|2010|p=293}}

When the Allies invaded Italy in 1943, Schellenberg went to great lengths to ensure the safety of [[Amin al-Husseini]], the anti-Semitic and anti-British Grand Mufti of Jerusalem, who was residing in Rome, by having him transported away to Berlin.{{sfn|Hastings|2016|p=476}} As the Red Army repulsed the Germans and began driving their forces back towards the west, the German General Staff began planning a retreat into Fortress Europe which included the incorporation of  Switzerland into the defensive operation. Using his previous channels to Schellenberg, the Swiss intelligence chief Masson, who was privy to this plan known as &quot;Case Switzerland&quot;, contacted Schellenberg as to whether or not an attack on Switzerland was imminent.{{sfn|Halbrook|2010|p=247}} By asking Schellenberg this question, Masson naively revealed to Schellenberg that a leak existed within Hitler's headquarters, but it also meant the Germans lost the opportunity for a surprise attack against Switzerland. To further ingratiate himself to the Swiss, Schellenberg claimed that he had convinced the German high-command of the needlessness for such an operation.{{sfn|Halbrook|2010|p=247}} Despite having direct contacts to Schellenberg himself, the Swiss Director of the [[Office of Strategic Services|OSS]], [[Allen Dulles]], expressed deep concern about the possible intelligence leaks between Masson and Schellenberg.{{sfn|Halbrook|2010|p=287}}

Signals intelligence intercepts alerted the Gestapo and SD to [[Red Orchestra (spy)|the &quot;Red Orchestra&quot;, the Soviet spy ring in Germany]].{{sfn|Richelson|1995|p=126}} Schellenberg led extensive efforts over many months were  to identify the participants. 116 were arrested by the Gestapo, half of whom were executed following intense interrogations.{{sfn|Hastings|2016|pp=241–247}} By this time, Schellenberg had become a general (''Brigadeführer'') in the [[Allgemeine-SS]] (General-SS).{{sfn|Zentner|Bedurftig|1997|pp=833–834}} The operation was a major victory for the RSHA at the expense of the ''Abwehr'', who had been oblivious to the Soviet operatioon.{{sfn|Hastings|2016|p=243}} Historian Klaus Fischer asserts that Schellenberg's &quot;only major success was smashing the Red Orchestra.&quot;{{sfn|Fischer|1995|p=544}}

Reportedly, Schellenberg and [[Wilhelm Canaris]], the head of the ''[[Abwehr]]'' (military intelligence) were friends. They would go horseback-riding together in Berlin's wooded Grunewald, where they would discuss the future of Nazi Germany.{{sfn|Doerries|Weinberg|2009|pp=51–52}} Often present at these equestrian outings were Heydrich and [[Werner Best]].{{sfn|Höhne|1979|pp=370–371}} Their alleged friendship aside, Canaris was careful around Schellenberg, a man whose ambitions included controlling all intelligence for the Reich.{{sfn|Hassell|MacRae|Ameskamp|2006|p=24}} Like Heydrich, Schellenberg ultimately envisioned a centrally directed &quot;all-embracing security system&quot; and a singular &quot;Greater German Intelligence Service&quot; under direct Nazi control (unlike the ''Abwehr'', which was part of the Wehrmacht).{{sfn|Höhne|1979|p=371}} Nonetheless, there are indications that Schellenberg preferred to deal with Canaris' ''Abwehr'' over the Gestapo, particularly since he distrusted its chief, [[Heinrich Müller (Gestapo)|Heinrich Müller]].{{sfn|Doerries|Weinberg|2009|p=52}} But after the [[20 July plot|attempted assassination of Hitler on 20 July 1944]], which Canaris had been involved in, the ''Abwehr'' was dissolved and the SD was given additional powers over intelligence across the Reich.{{sfn|Kahn|1978|p=62}}{{Efn|Despite Canaris falling from grace and being implicated as a double-agent who worked against Germany, Schellenberg referred to Canaris as &quot;Germany's finest spy&quot; until the end of his life.{{sfn|Höhne|1979|p=371}} }}

As a result, sections of the ''Abwehr'' were incorporated into RSHA Amt VI ''SD-Ausland'' and therefore placed under Schellenberg's command.{{sfn|Weale|2012|pp=398, 400}} Assumption of these powers made Schellenberg the &quot;absolute master&quot; of Nazi intelligence&quot;.{{sfn|Delarue|2008|p=320}} He was infamous for his &quot;office fortress&quot; desk, which had two automatic guns built into it that could be fired by the touch of a button.{{sfn|Infield|1981|pp=22–23}} According to the memoirs of SS intelligence officer Wilhelm Hoettl, Schellenberg was very suspicious of Gestapo Chief Müller, whom he claimed to have evidence against by way of radio surveillance recordings (allegedly revealing Müller's plans to work with the Russians); when he informed then RSHA chief [[Ernst Kaltenbrunner]] of possessing proof to that end, he was ignored.{{sfn|Waller|1996|p=297}} Kaltenbrunner disliked Schellenberg, perhaps due to his direct access to Himmler, and complained about him in particular on a number of occasions.{{sfn|Delarue|2008|p=267}} Despite Kaltenbrunner's animosity towards Schellenberg, the latter's soothing manners kept him in good graces with Himmler and allowed him to &quot;retain the ear of the SS overlord&quot;.{{sfn|Hastings|2016|p=477}}

===Operation &quot;Modelhut&quot;===
Allied military intelligence documents dating from World War II, previously classified top secret, have been unearthed linking French couturier [[Coco Chanel]] to espionage activity in concert with Schellenberg, who was her lover.{{sfn|Zeitz, ''New York Times'' (8 May 2005)}} In 1943/44, an operation codenamed &quot;Modelhut&quot; was conceived to capitalize on Chanel’s long-standing associations with British aristocracy and specifically her friendship with Winston Churchill. Schellenberg, recruited Chanel to act as an intermediary in a plan whose ultimate goal was to broker a separate peace between Nazi Germany and Britain independently of other Allied powers, but Operation Modelhut ultimately proved a failure.{{sfn|Vaughan|2011|pp=163–175}}

==Peace negotiations and capture==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-S72707, Heinrich Himmler.jpg|thumb|125px|Himmler, 1942]]
During early 1945, Schellenberg encouraged Himmler to overthrow Hitler in order to negotiate a separate peace with the [[Western Allies]], using as an excuse Hitler's poor health; however, Himmler never took action toward doing it and vacillated instead.{{sfn|Graber|1978|p=187}} He also convinced Himmler to meet with the former president of Switzerland, [[Jean-Marie Musy]], who promised to pay in Swiss francs for the release of Jews.{{sfn|Toland|1966|p=163}} At the end of the war, Schellenberg was able to persuade Himmler to try negotiating with the Western Allies through Count [[Folke Bernadotte]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=943}} Schellenberg had earlier in the year worked as an intermediary between Count Bernadotte and Himmler for the [[White Buses|release and safe passage of a number of prisoners and inmates]] held in [[Nazi concentration camps|concentration camp]]s through the [[Sweden|Swedish]] [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|Red Cross]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=943}}

In the spring of 1945, Schellenberg instigated further meetings with Count Bernadotte as an opening to the western powers.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=943}} He personally went to [[Stockholm]] in April 1945 to arrange the meetings for Himmler. Both Himmler and Schellenberg continued to believe that the Jews interred in concentration camps represented a bargaining chip for the Nazi leadership, one they could use to derive concessions from the Western allies.{{sfn|Mayer|2012|p=444}} To foster goodwill for their negotiations, Schellenberg—with Himmler's consent—organised the transport of 1,700 Jews out of German controlled territory to Switzerland and Sweden.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=944}} Hitler found out and put a stop to further evacuations.{{sfn|Doerries|2003|pp=23–24}}

After the first set of failed meetings, Schellenberg requested Bernadotte to intercede directly with General Eisenhower but this final action proved futile as well.{{sfn|Mayer|2012|pp=444–445}} At war's end, Schellenberg was in [[Denmark]] attempting to arrange his own surrender when the [[United Kingdom|British]] took him into custody in June 1945. The U.S., British, and Soviet intelligence services had all been searching for him as a valuable intelligence asset. Captain [[Horace Hahn]], a member of the OSS, was one of the few Americans allowed to interrogate Schellenberg.{{sfn|Doerries|2003|p=360}} Looking to recover as much information as they could from Schellenberg, the British sent him to London in July 1945 where he was extensively interrogated; their intention (along with the Americans) was to extract information on any remaining Nazi resistance yet to surface and to gather what they could on Germany's possible post-war intelligence activities. Schellenberg confirmed to the Allies that no such plans were in place, which was supported by Allied intelligence efforts.{{sfn|Breitman|Goda|Naftali|Wolfe|2005|p=113}} The fact that Schellenberg had been on the opposite side of the RSHA faction which included Kaltenbrunner, Müller, Ohlendorf, Skorzeny, along with other war criminals, was the &quot;best thing&quot; he had going for him at the end of the war. Additional independent signals intelligence also proved helpful in evaluating Schellenberg.{{sfn|Breitman|Goda|Naftali|Wolfe|2005|pp=113–114}}

==Nuremberg trials==
After the war, Schellenberg was arrested by British military police and eventually stood trial in Nuremberg. On 4 November 1949, he was sentenced to six years in prison for his role in the murder of Soviet POWs who were employed as agents in Operation Zeppelin.{{sfn|Deutsche Biographie, ''Walter Schellenberg''}} During the postwar [[Nuremberg Trials]], Schellenberg testified about the SS organisation and the Nazi leaders in its fold.{{Efn|http://avalon.law.yale.edu/imt/01-04-46.asp ''Nuremberg Trial Proceedings'' Twenty-Seventh Day, Yale University's '''AVALON Project'''  (cited 15 April 2016)}} During the [[Ministries Trial]], he wrote his memoirs, ''The Labyrinth''. Historian Robert Gerwarth describes certain content of Schellenberg's memoirs as &quot;questionable.&quot;{{sfn|Gerwarth|2012|p=95}}{{Efn|A formerly classified book review by CIA intelligence officer Clinton Gallagher from 1957 reveals that doubt has long been cast on the validity of some of Schellenberg's claims. See: [https://www.cia.gov/library/readingroom/docs/DOC_0000606545.pdf Gallagher, CIA Book Review of ''The Labyrnth'']}}  He was released from prison after two years on the grounds of ill-health, due to a worsening [[liver]] condition, and moved to [[Switzerland]],{{Efn|Some of his memoir was also written while he was in Switzerland with the assistance of his favorite secretary, Marie-Luise Schienke.{{sfn|Hastings|2016|p=541}} }} before settling in [[Verbania|Verbania Pallanza]], [[Italy]]. He died in [[Turin]], Italy in 1952.{{sfn|Hamilton|1996|p=66}}

==Summary of military career==

===Dates of rank===
* [[Mann (military rank)|SS-''Mann'']] (private) – 10 January 1934
* SS-''[[Sturmmann]]'' (lance-corporal) – 17 October 1934
* SS-''[[Rottenführer]]'' (senior lance-corporal) – 15 January 1935
* SS-''[[Unterscharführer]]'' (corporal) – 15 May 1935
* SS-''[[Scharführer]]'' (sergeant) - 9 November 1935
* SS-''[[Oberscharführer]]'' (staff sergeant) - 13 September 1936
* SS-''[[Untersturmführer]]'' (second lieutenant) – 20 April 1937
* SS-''[[Obersturmführer]]'' (first lieutenant) – 30 January 1938
* SS-''[[Hauptsturmführer]]'' (captain) – 1 August 1938
* SS-''[[Sturmbannführer]]'' (major) – 30 January 1939
* SS-''[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' (lieutenant colonel) – 1 September 1941
* SS-''[[Standartenführer]]'' (colonel) – 21 June 1942
* SS-''[[Oberführer]]'' (senior colonel) – 21 June 1943
* SS-''[[Brigadeführer]] und Generalmajor der Polizei'' (brigadier general) – 21 June 1944

===Notable decorations===
*[[Iron Cross]], 1st and 2nd Class
*[[War Merit Cross]], 1st and 2nd Class with Swords
*[[SS Honour Ring]]
*[[SS Honor Sword|Honour Sword of the Reichsführer-SS]]

==See also==
*[[Glossary of Nazi Germany]]
*[[List of Nazi Party leaders and officials]]
*[[List of SS personnel]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite journal|last= Biddiscombe |first= Perry.|date=2000|title= Unternehmen Zeppelin: The Deployment of SS Saboteurs and Spies in the Soviet Union, 1942–1945|journal= Europe-Asia Studies | volume=52 | issue=6| pages = 1115–1142| jstor=153592.|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Breitman | first1 = Richard | last2= Goda | first2= Norman J.W. |last3= Naftali | first3=Timothy | last4= Wolfe | first4 = Robert | year=2005 | title = U.S. Intelligence and the Nazis | location = Cambridge and New York | publisher = Cambridge University Press | isbn = 978-0-52161-794-9 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Browder | first = George C | title = Hitler’s Enforcers: The Gestapo and the SS Security Service in the Nazi Revolution | year = 1996 | place = Oxford and New York | publisher = Oxford University Press | isbn = 978-0-19820-297-4| ref = harv}} 
* {{cite book | last = Buchheim | first = Hans | chapter = The SS – Instrument of Domination | title = Anatomy of the SS State | editor1-last = Krausnick | editor1-first = Helmut | editor2-last = Buchheim | editor2-first = Hans | editor3-last = Broszat | editor3-first = Martin | editor4-last = Jacobsen | editor4-first = Hans-Adolf,  eds. | year = 1968 | publisher = Walker and Company | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-00211-026-6 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Delarue | first= Jacques | year=2008 | title= The Gestapo: A History of Horror | location= New York | publisher= Skyhorse | isbn= 978-1-60239-246-5 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite web|title= Deutsche Biographie|work=Walter Schellenberg|accessdate=15 August 2016|url=https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/gnd118607014.html#ndbcontent|ref={{sfnRef|Deutsche Biographie, ''Walter Schellenberg''}} }}
* {{cite book|last=Doerries|first=Reinhard R.|year=2003|title=Hitler's Last Chief of Foreign Intelligence: Allied interrogations of Walter Schellenberg|place=Portland|publisher=Frank Cass Publishers|isbn=0-7146-5400-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Doerries|first1=Reinhard R.|last2=Weinberg|first2=Gerhard L.|year=2009|title=Hitler's Intelligence Chief: Walter Schellenberg|location=New York|publisher=Enigma Books|isbn= 978-1-92963-177-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Evans | first=Richard | year=2006 | title= The Third Reich in Power | location= New York | publisher= Penguin | isbn= 978-0-14303-790-3| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Evans | first=Richard | year=2010 | title= The Third Reich at War | location= New York | publisher= Penguin | isbn= 978-0-14311-671-4| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Fischer | first = Klaus | year = 1995 | title = Nazi Germany: A New History | location = New York | publisher = Continuum | isbn = 978-0-82640-797-9 | ref= harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Fleming | first = Gerald| year = 1994 | title = Hitler and the Final Solution | location = Berkeley and Los Angeles | publisher = University of California Press | isbn= 0-520-06022-9 | ref= harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Gerwarth| first=Robert | year=2012 | title= Hitler's Hangman: The Life of Heydrich | location= New Haven, CT | publisher= Yale University Press | isbn=978-0-30018-772-4| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Gilbert | first = Martin | title = The Second World War: A Complete History | year = 1989 | place = New York |publisher = Henry Holt and Company | isbn = 0-8050-0534-X | ref = harv}} 
* {{cite book | last = Graber | first = G. S.| title = The History of the SS | year = 1978 | place = New York |publisher = D. McKay | isbn = 0-679-50754-X | ref = harv}} 
* {{cite book | last = Grunberger | first = Richard | year =1993 | title =Hitler’s SS | place = New York |publisher = Dorset Press | isbn =978-1-56619-152-4 | ref = harv}} 
* {{cite book | last = Halbrook | first = Stephen | title = The Swiss and the Nazis | year = 2010 | place = Philadelphia, PA | publisher = Casemate Publishing | isbn = 978-1-93514-934-7| ref = harv}} 
* {{cite book | last = Hamilton | first = Charles | title = Leaders &amp; Personalities of the Third Reich, Vol. 2 | year = 1996 | publisher = R. James Bender Publishing | isbn = 0-912138-66-1 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last1= Hassell | first1=Agostino von| last2=MacRae | first2=Sigrid | last3= Ameskamp | first3=Simone | year=2006| title= Alliance of Enemies: The Untold Story of the Secret American and German Collaboration to End World War II | location= New York | publisher= Thomas Dunne Books | isbn= 978-0-31237-482-2| ref = harv}}
* {{cite book| last=Hastings | first=Max | year=2016 | title= The Secret War: Spies, Ciphers, and Guerrillas, 1939–1945| place= New York | publisher=Harper | isbn=978-0-06225-927-1| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last= Höhne | first=Heinz | year=1979 | title= Canaris: Hitler’s Master Spy | location= New York | publisher= Doubleday | isbn = 0-385-08777-2 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last= Höhne | first=Heinz | year=2001 | title= The Order of the Death’s Head: The Story of Hitler’s SS | location= New York | publisher= Penguin Press | isbn = 978-0-14139-012-3 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last = Infield|first = Glenn B.|year = 1981|title = Skorzeny: Hitler's Commando|location = New York| publisher = St. Martin's|isbn = 978-0-312-72777-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Kahn | first=David | year=1978 | title= Hitler’s Spies: German Intelligence in World War II | location= New York | publisher= MacMillan | isbn=0-02-560610-7| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Kershaw | first = Ian | title = Hitler: A Biography | publisher = W. W. Norton &amp; Company | location = New York | year = 2008 | isbn = 978-0-393-06757-6 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Longerich| first = Peter | title = Heinrich Himmler | year = 2012 | place = Oxford and New York | publisher = Oxford University Press | isbn = 978-0199592326 | ref = harv}} 
* {{cite book | last1= Manvell | first1=Roger | last2=Fraenkel | first2 = Heinrich | year=1987| title= Heinrich Himmler | location= New York | publisher= Skyhorse Publishing | isbn= 978-1-85367-740-3| ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Mayer | first=Arno | year=2012 | title= Why Did the Heavens Not Darken?: The &quot;Final Solution&quot; in History | place=New York | publisher=Verso Publishing |isbn= 978-1-84467-777-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Read | first = Anthony | title = The Devil's Disciples: Hitler's Inner Circle | place = New York | publisher = Norton | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-039332-697-0 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book| last=Rhodes| first=Richard | year=2003 | title= Masters of Death: The SS-Einsatzgruppen and the Invention of the Holocaust | place= New York | publisher= Vintage | isbn= 978-0-37570-822-0 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last= Richelson | first= Jeffrey | year = 1995 | title= A Century of Spies: Intelligence in the Twentieth Century | location= Oxford and New York |publisher= Oxford University Press | isbn=0-19-511390-X|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Schellenberg|first=Walter|year=1956|title=The Schellenberg Memoirs|translator=Louis Hagen|place=New York|publisher=André Deutsch|asin= B0012NS1H8|ref=harv}}
* Schellenberg, Walter (2000) [1956]. ''The Labyrinth: Memoirs Of Walter Schellenberg, Hitler's Chief Of Counterintelligence'', translated by Louis Hagen. Da Capo Press. ISBN 978-0306809279
* {{cite book | last = Shirer | first = William  | year = 1990 | title = The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich | location = New York | publisher = MJF Books | isbn = 978-1-56731-163-1| ref= harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Toland | first = John | title = The Last 100 Days | year = 1966 | location = New York | publisher = Random House | asin = B0006D6MJO | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Vaughan|first=Hal|year=2011|title=Sleeping with the Enemy: Coco Chanel's Secret War|location=New York|publisher=Knopf|isbn=978-0-307-59263-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Waller | first = John | title = The Unseen War in Europe: Espionage and Conspiracy in the Second World War | year = 1996 | place = New York | publisher = Random House | isbn = 978-0-67944-826-6 | ref = harv}} 
* {{cite book | last = Weale | first = Adrian | title = Army of Evil: A History of the SS | year = 2012 | publisher = Caliber Printing | place = New York | isbn = 978-0-451-23791-0 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Wistrich | first = Robert | year = 1995 | title = Who's Who In Nazi Germany | location = New York | publisher = Routledge | isbn = 978-0-41511-888-0 | ref= harv}}
* {{cite news |last=Zeitz | first=Joshua M. |date=8 May 2005| title=The Nazis and Coco|newspaper=[[New York Times]]|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/08/arts/design/08zeit.html|ref={{sfnRef|Zeitz, ''New York Times'' (8 May 2005)}} }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Zentner | first1 = Christian | last2 = Bedurftig | first2 = Friedemann | year = 1997 | origyear = 1991 | title = The Encyclopedia of The Third Reich | publisher = Da Capo Press | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-3068079-3-0 | ref = harv }}
{{refend}}

==External links and further reading==
* [http://histclo.com/essay/war/ww2/code/sci/sci-ger.html World War II: Spying and Counterintelligence—Germany]
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}

{{Heinrich Himmler}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Schellenberg, Walter}}
[[Category:1910 births]]
[[Category:1952 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Saarbrücken]]
[[Category:People from the Rhine Province]]
[[Category:Personal staff of Heinrich Himmler]]
[[Category:SS-Brigadeführer]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Iron Cross (1939), 1st class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the War Merit Cross, 1st class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the SS-Ehrenring]]
[[Category:University of Bonn alumni]]
[[Category:World War II espionage]]
[[Category:World War II spies for Germany]]
[[Category:German prisoners and detainees]]
[[Category:Prisoners and detainees of the United States military]]
[[Category:People convicted by the United States Nuremberg Military Tribunals]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in Italy]]
[[Category:RSHA personnel]]</text>
      <sha1>6eu34gxwn911aerpqcj3lbps788yw2m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
