<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>War in Abkhazia (1992–93)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9288347</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745341774</id>
      <parentid>741054722</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T15:44:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Georgiano</username>
        <id>25093213</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="64696">{{For|the war in 1998|War in Abkhazia (1998)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = War in Abkhazia (1992–1993)
| partof      = The [[Georgian–Abkhazian conflict]] and the [[Georgian Civil War]]
| image       = Abkhazia map-fr.svg
| caption     = A map of the conflict region
| date        = 14 August 1992 – 27 September 1993&lt;br&gt;(1 year, 1 month and 13 days)
| place       = [[Abkhazia]], Western [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]
| territory   = [[Abkhazia]] becomes a de facto independent republic, but remains internationally recognized as part of Georgia
| result      = Victory of Abkhaz separatists&lt;br&gt;[[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia]]
| status      = 
| combatants_header = 
| combatant1  = 
{{Flag icon|Abkhazia}} [[Abkhazia]]&lt;br&gt;
{{flag|Russia}} &lt;ref&gt;https://www.hrw.org/reports/pdfs/g/georgia/georgia953.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kholodov&gt;Dmitry Kholodov, Moscow journalist covering the Conflict, September 1993, ''Nezavisimaya Gazeta'', Moscow&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia&gt;Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia and the Russian Shadow. Gothic Image Publications, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WhiteBookOfAbkhazia&gt;''White Book of Abkhazia. 1992–1993 Documents, Materials, Evidences''. Moscow, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon image|Flag_of_Kuban_People%27s_Republic.svg}} [[Cossacks]]
*{{Flagicon image|KHNK.png}} [[Confederation of Mountain Peoples of the Caucasus]]
{{flagicon image|Flag_of_Armenia.svg}} [[Bagramyan Battalion]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|Georgia|1990}}
*[[Military of Georgia (country)|Georgian Defense Ministry forces]]
*[[Internal Troops of Georgia]]
*[[National Guard of Georgia]]
*[[Mkhedrioni]]
*[[Zviadists|Pro-Gamsakhurdia fighters]] 
{{Flagicon image|UNSO-flag.svg}} [[UNA-UNSO]] &quot;Argo&quot;
| commander1  = {{Flagicon|Abkhazia}} [[Vladislav Ardzinba]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|Abkhazia}} [[Vladimir Arshba]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|Abkhazia}} [[Sergei Dbar]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon image|KHNK.png}} [[Musa Shanibov]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon image|KHNK.png}} [[Sultan Sosnaliyev]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon image|KHNK.png}} [[Shamil Basayev]]
| commander2  = [[Eduard Shevardnadze]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tengiz Kitovani]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jaba Ioseliani]]&lt;br&gt;[[Giorgi Karkarashvili]]&lt;br&gt;[[Geno Adamia]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt;[[David Tevzadze]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gujar Kurashvili]]
| units1      = 
| units2      = 
| units3      = 
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| strength3   = 
| casualties1 = 2,220 combatants killed&lt;br&gt;~8,000 wounded&lt;br&gt;122 missing in action&lt;ref name=&quot;hrw.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/legacy/reports/1995/Georgia2.htm#P117_4464 GEORGIA/ABKHAZIA: VIOLATIONS OF THE LAWS OF WAR AND RUSSIA'S ROLE IN THE CONFLICT]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;1,820 civilians killed (Abkhaz claim)&lt;ref name = &quot;hrw.org&quot;/&gt;
| casualties2 = 2,600, combatants, killed 10,000 were wounded, and 1,000 are missing&lt;ref name=&quot;hrw.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
20,000-30,000 Civilians killed&lt;ref name=&quot;Russia p 27&quot;&gt;The Guns of August 2008, Russia's War in Georgia, Svante Cornell &amp; Frederick Starr, p 27&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anatol Lieven, &quot;Victorious Abkhazian Army Settles Old Scores in An Orgy of Looting, The Times, 4 October 1993&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;In Georgia, Tales of Atrocities Lee Hockstander, International Herald Tribune, 22 October 1993&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Human Rights Field Operation: Law, Theory and Practice, Abkhazia Case, [[Michael C. O'Flaherty|Michael O'Flaherty]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Politics of Religion in Russia and the New States of Eurasia, Michael Bourdeaux, p. 237–238&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Managing Conflict in the Former Soviet Union: Russian and American Perspectives,
Alekseĭ Georgievich Arbatov, p. 388&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Empire p. 72&quot;&gt;On Ruins of Empire: Ethnicity and Nationalism in the Former Soviet Union Georgiy I. Mirsky, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Freedom in the World: The Annual Survey of Political Rights and Civil Liberties by Roger Kaplan, p 564&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Small Nations and Great Powers: A Study of Ethnopolitical Conflict in the Caucasus, p 174&lt;/ref&gt; also known as the '''massacres of Georgians in Abkhazia'''&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. ''Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia, and the Russian Shadow.'' Gothic Image Publications, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Small Nations and Great Powers: A Study of Ethnopolitical Conflict in the Soviet Union, Svante E. Cornell&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;200,000–250,000 ethnic Georgians displaced&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://assembly.coe.int/documents/adoptedtext/ta96/erec1305.htm |accessdate=2 April 2014 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140407080334/http://assembly.coe.int/documents/adoptedtext/ta96/erec1305.htm |archivedate=7 April 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://drc.dk/relief-work/stories-from-the-field/story/artikel/durable-solutions-for-the-long-term-displaced/ |accessdate=2 April 2014 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140407080112/https://drc.dk/relief-work/stories-from-the-field/story/artikel/durable-solutions-for-the-long-term-displaced/ |archivedate=7 April 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-11-880_en.htm?locale=en |title=European Commission – PRESS RELEASES – Press release – European Union promotes Justice Reform and support to Internally Displaced People in Georgia |publisher=Europa.eu |date= |accessdate=2016-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| notes       = 
| campaignbox = 
}}
{{Campaignbox Post-Soviet Conflicts}}
{{Campaignbox War in Abkhazia}}

The '''War in Abkhazia from 1992 to 1993''' was fought between [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]n government forces for the most part, and [[Abkhaz people|Abkhaz]] separatist forces, Russian armed forces and North Caucasian militants. Ethnic [[Georgians]] who lived in [[Abkhazia]] fought largely on the side of Georgian government forces. Ethnic [[Armenians]] and [[Russians]]&lt;ref&gt;Helen Krag and Lars Funch. The North Caucasus: Minorities at a Crossroads. (Manchester, December 1994)&lt;/ref&gt; within Abkhazia's population largely supported the Abkhazians,&lt;ref name=&quot;Today&quot;&gt;[http://www.crisisgroup.org/home/index.cfm?l=1&amp;id=4377 Abkhazia Today.] ''The [[International Crisis Group]] Europe Report N°176, 15 September 2006, page 5''. Retrieved on 30 May 2007. ''Free registration needed to view full report''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;AGBU, [http://www.agbu.org/publications/article.asp?A_ID=159 ABKHAZIA ARMENIANS: HOLDING A HOME IN AN UNSTABLE TERRITORY], 11/1/2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Security of the Caspian Sea Region pg 286 by Alexander Kyrlov edited by Genadi Chufrin&lt;/ref&gt; and many fought on their side. The separatists received support from thousands of [[North Caucasus]] and [[Cossack]] militants and from the [[Russian Federation]] forces stationed in and near Abkhazia.&lt;ref name=&quot;crisisgroup.org&quot;&gt;http://www.crisisgroup.org/~/media/Files/europe/195_russia_vs_georgia___the_fallout.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;conflicts.rem33.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.conflicts.rem33.com/images/Georgia/RUSSIA%20VERSUS%20GEORGIA.htm Rusiant-Georgian War 1992–93&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The handling of this conflict was aggravated by the [[Georgian Civil War|civil strife]] in Georgia proper (between the supporters of the ousted Georgian president, [[Zviad Gamsakhurdia]] – in office 1991–1992 – and the post-coup government headed by [[Eduard Shevardnadze]]) as well as by the [[Georgian–Ossetian conflict]] of 1989 onwards.

Significant [[human rights violations|human-rights violations]] and atrocities were reported on all sides, peaking in the aftermath of the Abkhaz [[Sukhumi massacre|capture of Sukhumi]] on 27 September 1993, which (according to the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]]) was followed by a large-scale campaign of [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic cleansing against the ethnic Georgian population]].&lt;ref name=&quot;un.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs//2008/ga10708.doc.htm General Assembly Adopts Resolution Recognizing Right Of Return By Refugees, Internally Displaced Persons To Abkhazia, Georgia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A fact-finding mission dispatched by the [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|UN Secretary General]] in October 1993 reported numerous and serious human rights violations committed both by Abkhazians and by Georgians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/Docs/journal/asp/ws.asp?m=S/26795 Links to documents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
From 13,000 to 20,000 ethnic Georgians and approximately 3,000 Abkhaz have been reported{{by whom|date=June 2015}} killed, more than 250,000 Georgians became [[internally displaced person|internally displaced]] or [[refugee]]s and 2,000 are considered [[missing person|missing]].

The war heavily affected post-[[Soviet Union|Soviet]] Georgia, which suffered considerable financial, human and psychological damage. The fighting and subsequent continued sporadic conflict have devastated Abkhazia.

==War==

The situation in the [[Abkhaz Autonomous Soviet Socialist Republic|Autonomous Soviet Socialist Republic of Abkhazia]] had been tense since the end of the 1980s when the anti-Soviet, Georgian opposition began demanding independence from the [[Soviet Union]]. In March 1989, Abkhaz nationalists demanded in the Lykhny Declaration the official establishment of a separate Soviet Socialist Republic (based on the precedent of the existence of a separate [[Abkhazian SSR]] during 1925 – 1931, which was associated with the [[Georgian SSR]] by a confederative &quot;Union Treaty&quot;). The Declaration was signed by the rector of the Sukhumi University. Ethnic Georgian students of the university announced protests, but these were forbidden by the Georgian government. Nevertheless, the students rallied and were attacked by ethnic Abkhazians.&lt;ref&gt;Kaufman, Stuart J. (2001), ''Modern Hatreds: The Symbolic Politics of Ethnic War'', p. 104-5. Cornell University Press, ISBN 0-8014-8736-6&lt;/ref&gt; The Georgian anti-Soviet movement was outraged by the event and included the claims of the students against Abkhazian secession into its list of slogans by several thousand Georgian demonstrators in [[Tbilisi]]. In response to the protests Soviet troops were dispatched to Tbilisi, resulting in the [[April 9 tragedy]].

In the aftermath, the [[1989 Sukhumi riots|first armed clashes]] between the representatives of the Abkhazian and Georgian populations took place on 16–17 July 1989 in [[Sukhumi]]. The conflict was sparked by the decision of Georgian government to convert the Georgian sector of Sukhumi State University into a branch of Tbilisi State University.  Abkhazians vehemently opposed to the new university, saw it as an instrument to extend Georgian dominance. Although the USSR Supreme Soviet concluded that the Georgian government had no legal right to authorize the new university, an entrance exam was scheduled for 15 July.  The resulting civil unrest quickly turned into militarized clashes that, according to official accounts, resulted in [[1989 Sukhumi riots|18 deaths]] and at least 448 wounded, 302 of whom were Georgian. In response, Interior Ministry troops were deployed to quell the unrest.

By July 1990, since neither side had felt strong enough to force the issue militarily, Georgian-Abkhaz antagonisms became largely relegated to the legislatures, demarcating Abkhazia as a legal contest, a &quot;war of laws&quot;, until armed hostilities broke out in August 1992. During that time, the government of the Soviet Union had very few options to prevent inter-ethnic conflicts, being itself [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union|on the verge of collapse]].

Ethnic allocations, or quotas, were introduced prior to the 1991 elections to the Supreme Soviet of Abkhazia, resulting in a composition that did not accurately reflect the ethnicity of the constituent population. Thus, of 65 seats, the Abkhazians (17% of the population) gained 28; Georgians (45%), 26; with the remaining 11 being divided amongst other groupings (Armenians, Russians; the latter comprising 33% of the population).&lt;ref&gt;[http://abkhazeti.info/war/200601261553433412425.php Правда о трагедии Абхазии&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Georgian offensive===

{{Main article|Battle of Sukhumi (1992)|l1=Battle of Sukhumi}}
[[Image:1992 Georgia war.svg|thumb|right|Events of the war in August 1992 – October 1992]]
In June 1992 the tensions over autonomy approached a critical stage, when Abkhaz militants attacked the government buildings in [[Sukhumi]]. On 23 July 1992, the [[Government of the Republic of Abkhazia|Abkhazian government]] proclaimed the independence of the region, though this was not internationally recognized. On 14 August 1992, Georgian police and National Guard units were dispatched to restore government control over Abkhazia. The ranks of Georgian troops were filled partially by &quot;emptying the jails&quot; as some of the inmates were released on the condition that they fight in Abkhazia.&lt;ref name=hrw&gt;[[Human Rights Watch]] report [http://www.hrw.org/reports/pdfs/g/georgia/georgia953.pdf GEORGIA/ABKHAZIA: VIOLATIONS OF THE LAWS OF WAR AND RUSSIA'S ROLE IN THE CONFLICT], March 1995&lt;/ref&gt; Fighting broke out the same day. On 18 August 1992, the separatist government fled from Sukhumi to [[Gudauta]]. Georgian government forces subsequently captured large parts of Abkhazia.

On 22 August 1992, the [[Confederation of Mountain Peoples of the Caucasus]] published a 'decree' of its president Musa Shanibov and the chairman of the parliament Iysuph Soslanbekov: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;As there is no other way to withdraw Georgian occupants' army from the territory of the sovereign Abkhazia and in order to implement the resolution of the 10th Session of the CMPC, we order:

# All headquarters of the Confederation have to dispatch volunteers to the territory of Abkhazia to crush the aggressor militarily. 
# All military formations of the Confederation have to conduct military actions against any forces who oppose them and try to reach the territory of Abkhazia by any method. 
# To announce Tbilisi as a zone of disaster. At that use all methods, including [[terrorism|terrorist acts]]. 
# To declare all people of Georgian ethnicity on the territory of Confederation as hostages. 
# All type of cargoes directed to Georgia shall be detained.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chervonnaya Svetlana, [http://abkhazeti.info/war/2006012625576883383764.php Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia and the Russian Shadow], p. 131 {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 August, [[Giorgi Karkarashvili]], the Georgian military commander, announced via television that the Georgian forces would not take any POWs. He promised that no harm would be done to peaceful residents of Abkhazia and that peace talks would be conducted. He warned separatists that if the peace talks wouldn't succeed and if 100,000 Georgians were killed, that the remaining 97,000 ethnic Abkhaz, who supported Ardzinba would perish.&lt;ref name=karkarashvili&gt;G. Amkuab, T. Illarionova, Abxazija: Xronika neobjavlennoj vojny. Chast' I. 14 avgusta – 14 sentiabria 1992 goda. Moskva, 1992, p. 128, retrieved from Georgians and Abkhazians. The Search for a Peace Settlement, 1998, Vrije Universiteit Brussel&lt;/ref&gt; Karkarashvili later allegedly threatened the Abkhaz politician, [[Vladislav Ardzinba]], not to take any actions that would leave the Abkhaz nation without descendants and thus placed the responsibility for future deaths on Ardzinba personally.&lt;ref name=karkarashvili/&gt; Later, his speech was used by the separatists as propaganda and to justify their own actions.&lt;ref&gt;Червонная С.М. ''Абхазия – 1992: посткоммунистическая Вандея''. Москва, 1993&lt;/ref&gt;

Significant [[ethnic cleansing]] accompanied by atrocities occurred on both sides&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia&gt;Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia and the Russian Shadow. Gothic Image Publications, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; with Abkhazians displaced from Georgian-held territory and vice versa. Many human rights abuses, principally looting, pillage and other outlaw acts, along with hostage-taking and other violations of humanitarian law, were committed by all sides throughout Abkhazia.&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt;

On 26 August armed Chechens fighting for Abkhazia captured Valery Maliuk from Eshera, just because he expressed his sympathy to Georgians. On the same day they raped Georgian teenagers, and along with the Abkhaz militants, committed atrocities against Georgian civilians in the village of Ordzhonikidze.&lt;ref&gt;Annex to the Report of the UN Secretary General on the situation in Abkhazia, Georgia, Proposals for political and legal elements for a comprehensive settlement of the Georgian-Abkhaz conflict&lt;/ref&gt;

After taking Sukhumi, Georgian forces (including [[Mkhedrioni]] paramilitaries) engaged in &quot;vicious, ethnically based pillage, looting, assault and murder.&quot;&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt; In addition to the looting, Abkhaz cultural monuments were destroyed in a manner that, according to some reports, suggests deliberate targeting. University buildings were sacked and museums and other cultural collections broken up. The irreplaceable Abkhaz national archives were burned by Georgian troops, reportedly, local firefighters didn't attempt to douse the blaze.&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Institute for War and Peace Reporting]], [http://www.iwpr.net/?p=crs&amp;s=f&amp;o=161411&amp;apc_state=henicrs2002 Abkhazia: Cultural Tragedy Revisited]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[OpenDemocracy]], [http://www.opendemocracy.net/democracy-caucasus/abkhazia_archive_4018.jsp Abkhazia's archive: fire of war, ashes of history]&lt;/ref&gt; A family of Abkhaz refugees from Sukhumi claimed that drunken Georgian troops broke into their apartment firing automatic weapons, and telling them &quot;to leave Sukhumi forever, because Sukhumi is Georgian.&quot; According to the family, the Georgian soldiers stole jewelry, assaulted the husband, and then threw them all out into the street. The same witnesses reported seeing dead Abkhaz civilians, including women and elderly people, scattered in the streets, even though the fighting had ended days before.&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt;

At the end of this stage of the conflict, the Georgian Army had taken most of Abkhazia. Pockets of Abkhaz forces were besieged in parts of [[Ochamchira District]] and [[Tkvarcheli]], while in [[Gudauta]] they were pinched between Georgian troops in Gagra and Sukhumi.

===Fall of Gagra===
{{Main article|Battle of Gagra}}
[[Image:1992-1993 Georgia war.svg|thumb|right|Events of the war in October 1992 – August 1993]]
On 3 September 1992, a ceasefire was negotiated in Moscow. According to the agreement, Georgian forces were obliged to withdraw from Gagra district. The Georgian side carried out the implementation of the agreement and left its positions. As a result, the local Georgian population of Gagra remained defenseless. The ceasefire was soon violated by the Abkhaz side. Thousands of volunteer paramilitaries, mainly [[Chechens]] and [[Cossacks]] from the militarized [[Confederation of Mountain Peoples of the Caucasus]] (CMPC) and the [[Military of Abkhazia|Abkhaz military]], equipped with [[T-72]] tanks, [[BM-21 Grad]] rocket launchers, [[Sukhoi Su-25]] attack planes, and helicopters. Georgia accused Russia of supplying this equipment, as it had not been previously used by the Abkhaz. Abkhaz and CMPC forces attacked the town of [[Gagra]] on 1 October. The small Georgian force remaining in the town briefly defended Gagra before retreating, then regrouped and recaptured the town. The Abkhaz and CMPC forces reconsolidated and launched another attack, capturing Gagra on 2 October. The Russian navy began to blockade the seaport near Gagra. The naval vessels: &quot;SKP-Bezukoriznenniy&quot;, &quot;KIL-25&quot;, &quot;BTH-38&quot;, &quot;BM-66&quot;, &quot;Golovin&quot;, &quot;Landing 345&quot;, &quot;Aviation 529&quot; (&quot;SU-25&quot;, &quot;SU-27&quot;), &quot;MI- and Anti-Aircraft 643&quot;. Regiments were commanded by the first deputy Minister of Defense of the Russian Federation, G. Kolesnikov, took part in the occupation of Gagra. The Russian tanker &quot;Don&quot; delivered 420 tons of fuel to Separatist-held Gudauta.

Thousands of Georgian soldiers and civilians fled north, entering Russia before being transported to Georgia proper. With the Abkhaz conquest of Gagra, those who remained were forcibly expelled, and a total of 429 were killed.&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia/&gt;&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt; One Georgian woman recalled watching her husband being tortured and buried alive:

{{cquote|My husband Sergo was dragged and tied to a tree. An Abkhaz woman named Zoya Tsvizba brought a tray with lots of salt on it. She took a knife and started to inflict wounds on my husband. She then threw salt onto my husbands exposed wounds. They tortured him like that for ten minutes. They then forced a young Georgian boy (they killed him after that) to dig a hole with a tractor. They placed my husband in this hole and buried him alive. The only thing I remember him saying, before he was covered with the gravel and sand, was: 'Dali, take care of the kids!'&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia/&gt;}}

Abkhaz forces, largely supported by the Russian military presence in the region, were now in control over Gagra, Gudauta (where a former Russian military base remains) and Tkvarcheli and rapidly approaching Sukhumi.

The expelled Georgians fled to Russia through the land border or were evacuated by Russian Navy.&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt;

===Abkhaz offensive on Eshera, Gulripsh, Kamani and Shroma===
The villages along the Gumista river (north and east of Sukhumi) such as Achadara, Kamani and Shroma, which were heavily populated by ethnic Georgians became a strategically important area, which enabled motorized units to reach Sukhumi, the capital of Abkhazia. After a failed attempt to storm Sukhumi from the west, the Abkhaz formations and their allies diverted their offensive on the northern and eastern sides of Sukhumi. On 2 July 1993 under Russian military directives and naval support, the Abkhaz and their ([[Confederation of Mountain Peoples of the Caucasus]]) allies attacked the villages on the Gumista river. The Georgian side didn't expect any offensive from the northern or eastern side of [[Sukhumi District]]. The Georgian forces suffered heavy losses (as many as 500 dead within an hour of the attack)&lt;ref name=Lynch&gt;''The Conflict in Abkhazia: Dilemmas in Russian 'Peacekeeping' Policy'' by Dov Lynch, p 153&lt;/ref&gt; and the defensive line around Sukhumi was breached by the Abkhaz offensive. On 5 July 1993, Abkhaz, Armenian [[Bagramyan Battalion|Bagramyan battalion]], Russian and North Caucasian detachments stormed the villages of Akhalsheni, Guma and Shroma of Sukhumi district. The residents from the villages were rounded up and massacred.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} The last offensive took place on 9 July, on the village of Kamani. Kamani was a [[Svan people|Svan]] (sub-ethnic group of the Georgian people) village, which also included an [[Georgian Orthodox and Apostolic Church|Orthodox Church]] (named after [[St. George]]) and convent. After the fall of the village, most of its inhabitants (including nuns and priests) were killed by Abkhaz formations and their allies (see [[Kamani massacre]]).&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia2&gt;Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. ''Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia and the Russian Shadow''. p. 50. Gothic Image Publications, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bombing and siege of Sukhumi===
In December 1992, Abkhaz troops began the shelling of Georgian-held Sukhumi. On 4 March 1993, [[Eduard Shevardnadze]], head of the State Council of Georgia, arrived in the capital of the region to take control over the defensive operations in the city. The Minister of Economy, Beslan Kobakhia, arrived in Sukhumi during the negotiations with Goga Khaindrava. According to Kobakhia, separatist leader Ardzinba would resign if Shevardnadze would do the same. He didn't approve of the vandalism in Gagra and noted that Abkhazia officially never declared its intention to secede from Georgia. As commander-in-chief of Georgian Military Forces, Eduard Shevardnadze issued the order &quot;measures on the defense of Ochamchira and the Sukhumi regions&quot; that stated: ''&quot;Military formations of different countries are concentrating in Gudauta and Gumista area. We have information that those forces have the serious goal of seizing Sukhumi and bringing chaos and turmoil to all of Georgia.&quot;'' On 10 February, Shevardnadze appointed [[Guram Gabiskiria]] as Mayor of Sukhumi. Meanwhile, the Georgian Parliament made an official declaration blaming Russia for aggression against Georgia and demanding the withdrawal of all Russian military forces from the territory of Abkhazia.

On 16 March 1993, at 6 and 9&amp;nbsp;am the Abkhaz and the Confederation forces launched a full-scale attack on Sukhumi resulting in mass destruction and heavy casualties among civilians.&lt;ref&gt;UN observers report DL47596, December 1993, New York&lt;/ref&gt; At 2&amp;nbsp;am the Abkhaz side began artillery bombardments of Georgian positions at the Gumista River and Sukhumi. Later in the day several Russian Su-25 planes attacked Sukhumi through the morning of the next day. A Russian special detachment led the operation followed by Abkhaz fighters and CMPC volunteers. They crossed the river Gumista and took part of Achadara, but Georgian forces successfully stopped their advance.

On 14 May, a short-lived ceasefire was signed. On 2 July, Russian navy ship landed up to 600 navy &quot;desant&quot; - Russian Airborne Troops close to the village [[Tamishi]], and engaged in a fierce battle with Georgian troops.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Heros of Tamish|url=http://www.for.ge/view.php?for_id=24834&amp;cat=16|publisher=Kviris Palitra Media}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ტამიში, 1993 წ. 2 ივლისი – დიდება გმირებს!|url=http://kar.ge/ტამიში-დიდება-გმირებს/|website=http://kar.ge}}&lt;/ref&gt; The battle was one of the bloodiest in the war, with several hundred killed and wounded on both sides. Despite initial setbacks, the Georgian forces managed to retake their positions. In July, Russian detachments, Abkhaz military and CMPC volunteers captured the villages of Akhalsheni, Guma and Shroma of the Sukhumi region. The fiercest struggle was in the village of [[Kamani, Georgia|Kamani]], defended by the [[National Guard of Georgia|Georgian National Guard]] and battalions of armed Georgian volunteers. After several hours of combat, the village fell. During the following two days, the Abkhaz engaged in a campaign of systematic torture, rape, and murder against Kamani's civilian population. Nuns at the church and the covenant were raped and killed in front of the Orthodox priest, and the priests were then taken outside, briefly questioned on the ownership of land in Abkhazia, and murdered. Approximately 120 Georgians were killed in the [[Kamani massacre]].

By this time, Abkhaz separatists occupied almost all the strategic heights and began to besiege Sukhumi. Soon after, the Chairman of the Georgian Council of Defense of Abkhazia [[Tamaz Nadareishvili]] resigned due to ill health and was succeeded by Member of the Georgian Parliament [[Zhiuli Shartava]].

On 15 August 1993, Greece carried out a humanitarian operation, [[Operation Golden Fleece]], evacuating 1,015 [[Greeks in Georgia|Greeks]] who had decided to flee from the war-ridden Abkhazia.&lt;ref&gt;Kathimerini, [http://www.ekathimerini.com/4dcgi/_w_articles_ell_100003_09/08/2003_32859 The anniversary of Operation Golden Fleece to evacuate diaspora Greeks from war in Abkhazia], Dionyssis Kalamvrezos&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, 170 [[Estonian people|Estonians]] of Abkhazia were evacuated with three flights by the Republic of Estonia in 1992&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Kalev Vilgats, toimetaja |url=http://www.parnupostimees.ee/244841/kalev-vilgats-abhaasia-eestlaste-saatus-eestis |title=Kalev Vilgats: Abhaasia eestlaste saatus Eestis – Artiklid |publisher=parnupostimees.ee |date= |accessdate=2016-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; (according to another source, around 400 Estonians altogether fled to Estonia during the war&lt;ref&gt;http://ida.aule.ee/ajalehed/tagakaukaasia/1993abhaasia_eestlased.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;).

===Fall of Sukhumi===
[[Image:1993 Georgia war1.svg|thumb|right|Events of the war in August 1993 – October 1993]]
Another Russian-mediated ceasefire was agreed in [[Sochi]] on 27 July and lasted until 16 September, when Abkhazian separatists violated the agreement (citing Georgia's failure to comply with the terms of the agreement) and launched a large-scale offensive against Sukhumi.&lt;ref name = &quot;hrw.org&quot;/&gt; During the siege, Russian [[MiG-29]]s dropped [[thermobaric bombs]] on Georgian residential districts in Sukhumi and Georgian villages along the Gumista River.&lt;ref&gt;Goltz, Thomas. Georgia Diary: A Chronicle of War and Political Chaos in the Post-Soviet&lt;/ref&gt;  Russian journalist [[Dmitry Kholodov]] stayed in Sukhumi before it fell, and reported that the city was repeatedly shelled by Russian forces, causing heavy civilian casualties.

After a fierce battle, Sukhumi fell on 27 September. Shevardnadze appealed to the population of Sukhumi by radio:

:Dear friends, Citizens of Sukhumi and Georgia! Georgia is facing the most difficult days, especially Sukhumi. Separatists and foreign invaders entered into the city. I am proud of your courage... Separatists and opportunists will be judged by history... They do not want Georgians to live in this Georgian city. Many of them dream to repeat the Gagra tragedy here... I know that you understand the challenge we are facing. I know how difficult the situation is. Many people left the city but you remain here for Sukhumi and for Georgia.... I call on you, citizens of Sukhumi, fighters, officers and generals: I understand the difficulties of being in your position now, but we have no right to step back, we all have to hold our ground. We have to fortify the city and save Sukhumi. I would like to tell you that all of us – Government of Abkhazia, Cabinet of Ministers, Mr. Zhiuli Shartava, his colleagues, the city and regional government of Sukhumi, are prepared for action. The enemy is aware of our readiness, that's why he is fighting in the most brutal way to destroy our beloved Sukhumi. I call on you to keep peace, tenacity and self-control. We have to meet the enemy in our streets as they deserve.

After the Abkhaz capture of the city one of the [[Sukhumi massacre|largest massacres]] of the war was committed against the remaining and trapped Georgian civilians in the city.&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt; Almost all members of the Georgian-backed Abkhaz government, who refused to leave the city, including [[Guram Gabiskiria]], [[Raul Eshba]] and [[Zhiuli Shartava]], were murdered (see [[Sukhumi Massacre]]).&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia/&gt;

The 1994 U.S. State Department Country Reports also describes scenes of massive human rights abuse:

:The Abkhaz separatist forces committed widespread atrocities against the Georgian civilian population, killing many women, children and elderly, capturing some as hostages and torturing others.... They also killed large numbers of Georgian civilians, who remained behind in Abkhaz-seized territory....&lt;ref name=StateDepartment&gt;U.S. State Department, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1993, February 1994, pp 877, 881, 891&lt;/ref&gt;

:The separatists launched a reign of terror against the majority Georgian population, although other nationalities also suffered. Chechens and other north Caucasians from the Russian Federation reportedly joined local Abkhaz troops in the commission of atrocities.... Those fleeing Abkhazia made highly credible claims of atrocities, including the killing of civilians without regard for age or sex. Corpses recovered from Abkhaz-held territory showed signs of extensive torture (the evidence available to Human Rights Watch supports the U.S. State Department’s findings).&lt;ref name=StateDepartment/&gt;

Eduard Shevardnadze left the city narrowly escaping death. Soon Abkhaz forces and the Confederates overran the whole territory of Abkhazia, but the [[Kodori Valley]] remained in Georgian hands. The total defeat of Georgian forces was accompanied by the [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic cleansing of the Georgian population]].&lt;ref name=StateDepartment/&gt; As a result of the war, more than 250,000 people (mainly Georgians, also [[Greeks]] and others) fled from or were forced out of Abkhazia. In September 1994, several reports indicated ethnic clashes between Abkhaz and [[Armenians]], a significant part of whom supported the former during the war. Chechen militants of the CMPC later left Abkhazia to take part in the [[First Chechen War]] with Russia.

{{cquote|When the Abkhazians entered my house, they took me and my seven year old son outside. After forcing us to our knees, they took my son and shot him right in front of me. After, they grabbed me by hair and took me to the nearby well. An Abkhazian soldier forced me to look down that well, there I saw three younger man and couple of elderly women, who were standing soaking in the water naked. They were screaming and crying, while the Abkhazians were dumping dead corpses on them. They then threw a grenade there and placed more people inside. I was forced again to my knees in front of the dead corpses. One of the soldiers took his knife and took the eye out from one of the dead near me. Then he started to rub my lips and face with that decapitated eye. I could not take it any longer and fainted. They left me there in pile of corpses.&lt;ref name=WhiteBookOfAbkhazia&gt;''White Book of Abkhazia. 1992–1993 Documents, Materials, Evidences''. Moscow, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the concluding phase of the battle of Sukhumi, the Abkhaz forces [[Transair Georgia airliner shootdowns|shot down]] three Georgian civilian airliners belonging to [[Transair Georgia]], killing 136 people (some of whom were Georgian soldiers, according to Russian sources&lt;ref&gt;Mihail Zhirohov, [http://www.airwar.ru/history/locwar/xussr/abhazia/abhazia.html Авиация в абхазском конфликте] (''Aviation in the Abkhazian conflict'') {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

Large numbers (about 5,000) of Georgian civilians and servicemen were evacuated by Russian ships during the last hours of the battle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1993/09/29/world/georgian-leader-charges-atrocity.html?pagewanted=1 (NYT on the Battle of Sukhumi)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Refugee exodus===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Georefugees1992.jpg|thumb|200 px|Georgians leaving capital of Abkhazia during siege]] --&gt;
After the fall of Sukhumi thousands of refugees started to flee Gali, Ochamchira and the Sukhumi regions. The plight of refugees became deadly due to snow and cold on the pathway in the [[Kodori Gorge]]. Georgian authorities were unable to evacuate all remaining civilians (previously many people were evacuated from Sukhumi by Russian navy&lt;ref name = hrw/&gt; and via airplanes and cargo ships to the Ukraine). The refugees started to move in through the Kodori Gorge on foot, bypassing the Gali region, which was blocked by advancing Abkhaz separatist forces. The crossing of the Kodori Gorge on foot became another death trap for the fleeing IDPs.&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia/&gt; Most of the people, who didn't survive the crossing, died from freezing cold and starvation. The survivors, who reached the [[Svan people|Svan]] mountains were attacked and robbed by local criminal groups. One of the survivors recalls the crossing:&lt;ref name=StateDepartment/&gt;

{{cquote|They were killing everyone, who was Georgian. Every road was blocked. There was only one way out, through the mountains. It was terrible and horrific, nobody knew where it ended or what would happen on the way. There were children, women and elderly people. Everyone was marching not knowing where they are headed. We were cold, hungry, there was no water.... We marched the whole day. By the end of the day we were tired and could not go on. To rest, it meant to die, so we marched and marched. Some woman near me didn't make it, she had fallen dead.  As we marched, we saw people frozen and dead, they apparently stopped for a break and it was their end. The path never ended, it seemed that we would die at any time. One young girl, who marched beside me all the way from Sukhumi was pregnant. She delivered her baby in the mountains. The child died on the third day of our deadly march. She separated from us and we never saw her again. Finally we made it into the Svan villages. Only women and children were allowed in their huts. Buses came later on that day. We were then taken to Zugdidi.&lt;ref name=WhiteBookOfAbkhazia/&gt;}}

According to the [[United States State Department]] Commission on Foreign Relations and International Relations, 104th Cong., 1st Sess., Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1994, at 815 (Joint Comm. Print 1995), the victorious Abkhaz separatists &quot;moved through captured towns with prepared lists and addresses of ethnic Georgians, plundered and burned homes and executed designated civilians.&quot; Georgians were specifically targeted, but all non-Abkhaz suffered.&lt;ref&gt;[[United States State Department]] Commission on Foreign Relations and International Relations, 104th Cong., 1st Sess., Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1994, at 815 (Joint Comm. Print 1995), cited in: [http://www.asylumlaw.org/docs/showDocument.cfm?documentID=1040 Melkonian v. Ashcroft (9th Cir. 2003) (United States)] case. ''Asylumlaw.org''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ethnic cleansing campaign===
{{Main article|Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia}}
[[File:Abkhazia genocide anniversary 2005.jpg|200px|thumb|The 12th anniversary of ethnic cleansing in Abkhazia, which was held in Tbilisi in 2005. One of the visitors of the gallery recognized her dead son on the photograph]]
The ethnic cleansing and massacres of Georgians has been officially recognized by the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] (OSCE) conventions in 1994, 1996 and again in 1997 during the [[Budapest]], [[Istanbul]] and [[Lisbon]] summits and condemned the “perpetrators of war crimes committed during the conflict&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osce.org/documents/mcs/1994/12/4048_en.pdf Resolution of the OSCE Budapest Summit], [[Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development]], 6 December 1994&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 May 2008, the UN [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] adopted (by 14 votes to 11, with 105 abstentions) a resolution A/RES/62/249 in which it “Emphasizes the importance of preserving the property rights of refugees and internally displaced persons from Abkhazia, Georgia, including victims of reported “ethnic cleansing”, and calls upon all Member States to deter persons under their jurisdiction from obtaining property within the territory of Abkhazia, Georgia in violation of the rights of returnees”.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/ga/62/resolutions.shtml A/RES/62/249, A/62/PV.97]&lt;/ref&gt;

The former resident of Ochamchire district, Leila Goletiani, who was taken prisoner by Abkhaz separatists, gave the following account of her captivity to the Russian film director [[Andrei Nekrasov]]:

{{quotation| I lived in Abkhazia 15 years ago, in the small town of Akhaldaba, Ochamchire district. Abkhaz attacked our village on September 16, 1993. It was impossible to hide anywhere from the bullets which rained down on us. ... The Russian Cossacks approached me and started to beat me. One of these Russian Cossacks approached me and asked me if I have ever had sex with a Cossack. He grabbed me and tried to rip off my clothes, after which I started to resist but they hit my head on the ground and started to beat me with AK-47 butts. While hitting me all over my body, they yelled, &quot;We will kill you, but we will do so slowly.&quot; Then they took me to an Abkhaz school where they kept Georgian civilian prisoners. There were only Georgians there, women, children and men. There were some women who were pregnant, and children of different ages. The Battalion of Cossacks kept coming there regularly. They took young girls and children and raped them systematically.  These were children aged 10, 12, 13, and 14. They especially targeted children. One of the girls there was 8 years old. She was taken by different groups of these Cossacks and was raped numerous times. I don’t know how she managed to survive after so many rapes but I don’t want to mention her name in order to protect her identity. They also took women but later they started to take elderly women. They raped these elderly women in the way which I don’t want to go into detail ... it was horrific.&lt;ref name=A.Nekrasov&gt;Andrei Nekrasov, {{YouTube|rewD7JxoUAM|Russian Lessons}}, video file&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Russia's role in the conflict===
Although Russia officially claimed neutrality during the war in Abkhazia, Russian military officials and politicians were involved in the conflict in several ways. Russia's warfare market was the main source of weapons for both conflicting sides, it unofficially supported the Abkhaz and Georgia side.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/reports/pdfs/g/georgia/georgia953.pdf Human Rights Watch. VIOLATIONS OF THE LAWS OF WAR AND RUSSIA'S ROLE IN THE CONFLICT.] pp. 6, 19, 32, 34, 39, 45&lt;/ref&gt; Finally Russia carried out some humanitarian operations in Abkhazia.

Russian arms used by Georgia were transferred to it under the bilateral agreements with Russia and included main battle tanks, armored personnel carriers, heavy artillery and heavy mortars. The whole Akhaltsikhe motorised rifle division was turned over to Georgia on 22 September 1992.&lt;ref&gt;58 ITAR-TASS World Service, 22 September 1994, cited in FBIS-SOV-92-187, 25 September 1992, p. 53., acknowledged in the HRW VIOLATIONS OF THE LAWS OF WAR AND RUSSIA'S ROLE IN THE CONFLICT report&lt;/ref&gt; Some weapons were gained by local raids on Russian Army bases in [[Akhalkalaki]], [[Batumi]], [[Poti]] and Vaziani by irregular Georgian paramilitary forces.&lt;ref&gt;See Dale, op. cit., ''Small Arms World Report'', August 1993, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; After several attacks Russia declared it would defend its bases with force.

Prior to the outbreak of the war, the Abkhaz leadership arranged for the redeployment of a Russian [[Airborne forces|airborne]] battalion from the [[Baltic states]] to Sukhumi.&lt;ref name=Cornell&gt;Svante E. Cornell (2001), ''Small Nations and Great Powers: A Study of Ethnopolitical Conflict in the Caucasus'', pp. 347–9. Routledge, ISBN 0-7007-1162-7.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Russian historian Svetlana Mikhailovna Chervonnaya, a number of Russian security servicemen also arrived in Abkhazia as &quot;tourists&quot; during that summer: &quot;The main load in the preparation of Abkhazian events was given to staff of the former [[KGB]]. Almost all of them got appointments in Abkhazia under cover of neutral establishments, which had nothing to do with their real activities. To distract attention, various ruses were resorted to, such as the private exchange of apartments, or the necessity of moving one’s place of work to Abkhazia due to a sudden deterioration of health.&quot;&lt;ref name=Seely&gt;Robert Seely (2001), ''Russo-Chechen Conflict, 1800–2000: A Deadly Embrace'', p. 191-192. Routledge, ISBN 0-7146-4992-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to another Russian expert, Evgeni Kozhokin, director of the Russian Institute of Strategic Studies, prior to the outbreak of hostilities, Abkhaz guardsmen had been supplied with weaponry by Russia’s 643rd [[anti-aircraft missile]] regiment and a military unit stationed in [[Gudauta]]. Ardzinba had major supporters in Moscow as well, including Vice President [[Alexander Rutskoy]] and the [[Chechen people|Chechen]] speaker of the [[Russian Supreme Soviet|Russian parliament]], [[Ruslan Khasbulatov]].&lt;ref name=Cornell/&gt;&lt;ref name=Seely/&gt;

After the eruption of armed conflict, the Abkhaz separatist paramilitary units, along with their political supporters fled to Gudauta from where they obtained significant amount of military and financial aid.&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia/&gt;&lt;ref name=WhiteBookOfAbkhazia/&gt; In Gudauta, the Russian Army base housed and trained Abkhaz paramilitary units and provided protection for the leader of the Abkhaz separatists, Vladislav Ardzinba.&lt;ref name=Chervonnaia3&gt;Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. ''Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia and the Russian Shadow''. p. 28. Gothic Image Publications, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; The high level of corruption in the Russian military also contributed in the leakage of Russian arms to both sides.

From the outset of the hostilities Russia called upon both sides to negotiate and it brokered several ceasefires, which mostly proved ineffective (Sukhumi offensive was undertaken by the Abkhaz side in violation of the previous ceasefire agreement). On the other hand, the Russian military offered protection to the retreating Abkhaz detachments during the summer 1992 Georgian offensive. In November 1992, the Russian Air Force conducted heavy air strikes against the villages and towns in Abkhazia predominantly populated by Georgians. In response, the Georgian Defense Ministry accused Russia for the first time in public of preparing a war against Georgia in Abkhazia. This led to the Georgian attacks on targets under Russian and Abkhaz control and the retaliation from the Russian forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACIG&quot;&gt;[http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_282.shtml &quot;Georgia and Abkhazia, 1992–1993: the War of Datchas&quot;] by Tom Cooper, Air Combat Information Group. 29 September 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Russian attitude began to tilt further to the Abkhaz side, after a Russian MI-8 helicopter (reportedly carrying humanitarian aid) was brought down by Georgian forces on 27 October, which triggered retaliation from Russian forces. On 14 December 1992, the Russian military suffered the loss of another military helicopter, carrying evacuees from [[Tkvarcheli]], resulting in 52 to 64 deaths (including 25 children). Although Georgian authorities denied any responsibility, many believed the helicopter was shot down by the Georgian forces. On 16 December, the government of Georgia requested the Russians to evacuate their nationals from Abkhazia via other routes, foremost the Black Sea, but also to limit the number of missions flown from Gudauta, the main Russian air base in the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACIG&quot;/&gt; However, this incident &quot;raised the level of general malevolence in the war and catalyzed more concerted Russian military intervention on the Abkhaz side.&quot;&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;RFE/RL News Briefs, 10–23 December 1992, p. 10, Moscow Radio Rossii, 15 December 1992, cited in FBIS-SOV-92-242, 16 December 1992, pp. 55–56&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[UNHCR]], [http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/publ/opendoc.htm?tbl=RSDCOI&amp;id=3ae6a6c54&amp;page=publ The Dynamics and Challenges of Ethnic Cleansing: The Georgia-Abkhazia Case], also in ''Refugee Survey Quarterly'' 1997, Volume 16, Number 3, pp. 77–109&lt;/ref&gt; The town of Tkvarcheli had been besieged by Georgian forces and its population (mostly Abkhaz, Georgians and Russians) suffered a severe humanitarian crisis. Russian military helicopters supplied the city with food and medicine and mobilized Russian-trained fighters to defend the city.&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt;

The Human Rights Watch states: &quot;Although the Russian government continued to declare itself officially neutral in the war, parts of Russian public opinion and a significant group in the parliament, primarily Russian nationalists, who had never been favourably disposed toward the Georgians, began to tilt toward the Abkhaz at least by December.&quot;&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt; During this period the Abkhaz side obtained a large number of armor, tanks (T-72 and T-80) and heavy artillery. The question remains whether there were specific orders concerning the transfer of weapons to Abkhaz side and if so, whom they were issued by. Russian border guards allowed the Chechen fighters led by Shamil Basayev to cross into Abkhazia or at least did nothing to prevent them from arriving in the conflict zone.&lt;ref&gt;Murphy, Paul J. (2004), ''The Wolves of Islam: Russia and the Faces of Chechen Terror'', pp. 14–5. Brassey's, ISBN 1-57488-830-7.&lt;/ref&gt; The defense minister in the secessionist government and one of the main organizers of the Abkhaz armed units was the professional Russian military officer [[Sultan Sosnaliyev]] from the [[Kabardino-Balkaria Republic]].

The most obvious example of Russian support to the Abkhaz side in 1993 was the bombing of Georgian-held [[Sukhumi]] by Russian fighter-bombers. The Russian Defence minister [[Pavel Grachev]] consistently denied it, but after Georgians succeeded in bringing down one [[SU-27]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://mdb.cast.ru/mdb/3-2008/item3/article3/ Moscow Defense Brief&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; fighter-bomber and UN experts identified the dead pilot as Russian it became irrefutable. Nevertheless, some equipment was turned over to Georgia according to the previous agreements in 1993. Russian general Grachev claimed that Georgian side has painted the aircraft to resemble Russian Air Force aircraft and bombed their own positions, killing hundreds of their own people in Eshera and Sukhumi. This statement raised anger and utter contempt among Georgians toward the Russian side.

The Russian journalist Dmitry Kholodov, who has witnessed the Russian bombardment of Sukhumi, wrote a couple of compiling reports with detailed description of humanitarian catastrophe:

:&quot;The shelling of Sukhumi by Russians is the most disgusting thing in this war. All the residents of Sukhumi remember the first shelling. It took place on 2 December 1992. The first rocket fell on Peace Street. They struck at crowded places. The next strategic target was the town market, which was hit with great precision. Eighteen people were killed that day. There were always lots of people in the market.&quot;&lt;ref name=Kholodov&gt;Dmitry Kholodov, Moscow journalist covering the Conflict, September 1993, ''Nezavisimaya Gazeta'', Moscow&lt;/ref&gt;

Kholodov also reported on the Russian volunteers fighting on the separatist side:

:&quot;Russians, too, are fighting there. We often heard from Georgian guards how Russian mercenaries were attacking: It's a blood-curdling sight – they have helmets and firm, bullet-proof jackets on and their legs are armored as well. They advance with their heads bent down, like robots ready to kill. There is no use shooting at them. No tanks are needed, they are followed by the Abkhaz behind.&quot;&lt;ref name=Kholodov/&gt;

On 25 February, the Georgian Parliament appealed to the UN, European Council and Supreme Council of the Russian Federation demanding the withdrawal of Russian forces from Abkhazia and stating that Russia waged &quot;an undeclared war&quot; against Georgia.&lt;ref&gt;Decree issued by the Parliament of Georgia on the Presence of Russian Military Units on the Territory of Abkhazia. 25  February 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;

Georgian Parliament adopted another resolution on 28 April 1993, which openly blamed Russia in political facilitation of ethnic cleansing and genocide against Georgians.&lt;ref&gt;Decree issued by the Parliament of Georgia on withdrawal of Russian Military Units from the Conflict Zone in Abkhazia, 27 April 1993&lt;/ref&gt;

Russian policy during the final battle for Sukhumi in September 1993, immediately, after the breach of the ceasefire by the Abkhaz forces, appeared to follow several lines. Russian officials condemned the attack, issued calls to Abkhaz forces to cease the offensive and its accompanying human rights violations and reportedly cut off electricity and telephone service to parts of Abkhazia from September to December 1993. Russia also supported resolutions in the Security Council condemning Abkhaz forces for breaching the ceasefire. At the same time, the Russian government criticized the Georgian government for refusing, once the attack was underway, to negotiate. As the Human Rights Watch report notes &quot;it is doubtful, however that Russian forces in or near Abkhazia were as surprised as the Russian government seemed to be. Initiating an offensive as large as the one undertaken, in three different directions at once, must have required extensive movement of forces and resupply during the days leading up to it.&quot; Russian forces on the Georgian-Abkhaz border, who were supposed to police the ceasefire made no attempt to forestall the attack. The Abkhaz weapons were stored near the front and were returned to the Abkhaz by Russian military mission when hostilities restarted.&lt;ref&gt;Svante E. Cornell (2001), p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ataman]] Nikolay Pusko, a notable commander of some 1,500 Cossack volunteers fighting against Georgians in Abkhazia, later claimed that his [[sotnia]] was the first to enter Sukhumi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abkhaziainfo.f2o.org/publications/EpZyuAuFFZIOiFE.shtml|title=IS. Abkhazia, ''Кубанские казаки берут Сухуми'' 11 February 2004|accessdate=25 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pusko and two other Cossack atamans in Abkhazia, Mikhail Vasiliyev and Valery Goloborodko, all died in unclear circumstances from 1993 to 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Mukhin|first1=Aleksey|last2=Pribylovsky|first2=Vladimir|script-title=ru:Казачье движение в России и странах ближнего Зарубежья (1988–1994)|date=1994|publisher=Panorama|location=Moscow|isbn=5-85895-009-4|pages=94–96|language=Russian|trans_title=Cossack movement in Russia and the countries of Near Abroad}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a [[Time (magazine)|''Time'']] magazine article published on 4 October 1993, Georgians said Russian Army officers provided Abkhazian separatists, at the beginning using mere [[hunting rifle]]s and [[shotgun]]s, with sophisticated weapons like [[BM-21]] multiple rocket launchers and Sukhoi SU-25 jet aircraft, plus battlefield intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,979327,00.html Siege of Sukhumi], ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'', 4 October 1993&lt;/ref&gt;

====Humanitarian actions====
In the beginning of the conflict (August 1992) Russia evacuated many people from Abkhazian resorts by means of Black Sea fleet and Russian Air Force. As the war progressed Russia began to supply humanitarian aid to both sides, it also brokered numerous agreements concerning the exchange of prisoners of war. In the course of the war, Russian humanitarian efforts were chiefly focused on the town of Tkvarcheli, which had large ethnic Russian population and was besieged by the Georgian forces. The landmines installed along the mountain highway to this town made Russian helicopters the only safe means of transportation into it. However, Russian navy also evacuated tens of thousands of Georgian civilians, after the fall of [[Gagra]] (October 1992) and Sukhumi (September 1993) to the separatist forces.&lt;ref name=hrw/&gt;

===Results===
Georgia effectively lost control over Abkhazia and the latter established as a de facto independent territory. The relations between Russia and Abkhazia improved in the late 1990s and the economic blockade of Abkhazia was lifted. The laws were also passed allowing other countries to become part of Russian Federation, which was interpreted by some as an offer to Abkhazia and other unrecognised countries of the former Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_282.shtml &quot;Georgia and Abkhazia, 1992–1993: the War of Datchas&quot;] by Tom Cooper, 29 Sep 2003,
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Abkhazia War Monument in Tbilisi (President of Poland visit).jpg|thumb|&quot;Monument to the heroes, who fell fighting for the territorial integrity of Georgia&quot;, Tbilisi]]
[[File:Alley of the Glory monument.JPG|thumb|The names of Abkhaz troops and their allies killed in action during the war are inscribed on the &quot;Alley of Glory&quot; monument in Sukhumi]]

Georgia claimed that Russian army and intelligence contributed decisively to the Georgian defeat in the Abkhazian war and considered this conflict (along with the [[Georgian Civil War]] and [[1991–92 South Ossetia War|Georgian–Ossetian War]]) as one of Russia's attempt of restoring its influence in the post-Soviet area.&lt;ref&gt;Professor Zaza Gachechiladze, [http://www.ndu.edu/inss/strforum/SF_21/forum21.html The Conflict in Abkhazia: A Georgian Perspective]&lt;/ref&gt;

At [[Sukhumi massacre|the end]] of the war, the [[foreign minister of Russia|Russian Foreign Minister]] [[Andrey Kozyrev]] said at the [[UN General Assembly]]: “Russia realizes that no international organization or group of states can replace our [[peacekeeping]] efforts in this specific [[Post-Soviet states|post-Soviet space]].”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,979366,00.html In Russia's Shadow], ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'', 11 October 1993&lt;/ref&gt;

A wide array of opinions on Russian policy with respect to Georgia and Abkhazia is expressed in the media and parliament.&lt;ref name=mcfarlane&gt;MacFarlane, S.N., “On the front lines in the near abroad: the CIS and the OSCE in Georgia’ s civil wars”, ''Third World Quarterly'', Vol 18, No 3, pp 509- 525, 1997.,&lt;/ref&gt; Leonid Radzikhovsky, a political analyst and independent journalist, wrote that gaining new territories is the last thing Russia needs and compared the support of foreign separatists to throwing stones at one's neighbours, while living in the glass house.&lt;ref&gt;[http://se1.isn.ch/serviceengine/FileContent?serviceID=RESSpecNet&amp;fileid=F3A5C5C8-8D3E-14AE-51F7-1278E2604E0C&amp;lng=en Georgiophobia, Or the Model of Double Standards] Izvestia daily, 22 September 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Oxford Professor S.N. MacFarlane, notes on the issue of Russian mediation in Abkhazia:&lt;ref name=mcfarlane/&gt;
:&quot;Notably, it is clear that Russian policy makers are uncomfortable with the idea of a prominent role being granted to external actors in dealing with conflict in the former Soviet space. More recently, this has been extended specifically to the activities of international organisations in the management of conflict. As one group of influential Russian foreign policy commentators and policy makers put it in May 1996, it is definitely not in Russia’s interest to see outside mediation and peacekeeping operations on the territory of the former Soviet Union.
:&quot;Russia has clear hegemonic aspirations in the former Soviet space. Although a wide array of opinions is expressed on Russian policy in the newly independent states in the media and in parliament, a dominant consensus appears to have emerged among foreign policy influentials on the need for active presence and influence in the area. Such views have been widely expressed in official statements, influential statements by independent policy groups and by advisers to the president, influential political figures and the president himself. The hegemonic component of Russian policy in the near abroad is evident in its efforts to restore Russian control over the external borders of the former Soviet Union, to reassume control over the Soviet air defence network, to obtain agreements on basing Russian forces in the non-Russian republics and by its obvious sensitivity to external military presences (including multilateral ones) on the soil of the former Soviet Union. To judge from Russian policy on Caspian Sea and Central Asian energy development, it extends beyond the political/security realm and into the economic one. Its sources are diverse and include the Russian imperial hangover, but more practically the fate of the Russian diaspora, the lack of developed defences along the borders of the Russian Federation proper, concern over Islam and discomfort with the spill-over effects of instability in the other republics.&quot;

On 28 August, Senator [[Richard Lugar]], then visiting Georgia's capital Tbilisi, joined the Georgian politicians in criticism of the Russian peacekeeping mission, stating that &quot;the U.S. administration supports the Georgian government’s insistence on the withdrawal of Russian peacekeepers from the conflict zones in Abkhazia and the Tskhinvali district.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://mosnews.com/news/2006/08/22/lugarspeaks.shtml ''U.S. Senator Urges Russian Peacekeepers’ Withdrawal From Georgian Breakaway Republics.'' (MosNews)].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Conflict mediation==
During the war the peace mediation was done first by Russia and second by the UN. From 1993 onwards, the pressure for a peace settlement mounted from UN, Russia and the then Group of Friends of Georgia (Russia, U.S., France, Germany and UK). In December 1993, an [[Sochi agreement|official ceasefire]] was signed by Georgian and Abkhaz leaders under the aegis of the UN and with Russia as intermediary. The venues shifted from Geneva to New York and finally to Moscow. On 4 April 1994 the &quot;declaration on measures for a political settlement of the Georgian-Abkhazian conflict&quot; was signed in Moscow. Instead of the deployment of a traditional UN peacekeeping force, the deployment of a CIS, mainly Russian peacekeeping forces, was agreed in Moscow on 14 May 1994. In June 1994, [[Commonwealth of Independent States|CIS]] peacekeeping forces comprising only the Russian soldiers were deployed along the administrative border between Abkhazia and the remaining Georgia. The UN mission ([[United Nations Observer Mission in Georgia|UNOMIG]]) also arrived. However, these could not prevent further atrocities against the Georgians in the following years (around 1,500 deaths have been reported by the Georgian government in the post-war period). On 14 September 1994, Abkhaz leaders appeared on local TV to demand that all ethnic Georgians depart from the region by 27 September (the anniversary of the capture of Sukhumi). On 30 November 1994, Abkhazia promulgated a new constitution declaring independence of the breakaway region. However, none of the foreign governments recognised this. On 15 December 1994, the [[United States Department of State|US State Department]] condemned Abkhazia’s declaration of independence. On  21 March 1995, The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees accused Abkhaz militias of torturing and murdering dozens of returning ethnic Georgian refugees in [[Gali District, Abkhazia|Gali District.]] Despite an official economic blockade imposed on Abkhazia by Russia and CIS in 1995 (virtually ended by the Russian government in 1997), the breakaway region has been enjoying both military and economic support by Russia.

===UN involvement===
The [[United Nations Observer Mission in Georgia]] (UNOMIG) was established in 1993 to monitor the ceasefire and later expanded to observe the operation of the CIS peacekeeping forces. The Organization for Security in Europe (OSCE) and other international organizations are also involved in monitoring developments. Negotiations toward a permanent peace settlement have made little progress, but the Georgian and Abkhaz governments have agreed to limit the size of their military forces and extend the authorization for UNOMIG. Meanwhile, Georgian refugees maintain a government in exile.

==See also==
*[[Transair Georgia airliner shootdowns]]
*[[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia]]
*[[Sukhumi massacre]]
*[[Politics of Abkhazia]]
*[[Russian-Circassian War]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. ''Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia and the Russian Shadow.'' Gothic Image Publications, 1994.
* Andersen, Andrew. [http://www.conflicts.rem33.com/images/Georgia/RUSSIA%20VERSUS%20GEORGIA.htm &quot;Russia Versus Georgia: One Undeclared War in the Caucasus.&quot;], Young Experts’ Think Tank (YETT)
* Blair, Heather. ''Ethnic Conflict as a Tool of Outside Influence: An Examination of Abkhazia and Kosovo.'', Young Experts’ Think Tank (YETT)
* McCallion, Amy. ''Abkhazian Separatism'', Young Experts’ Think Tank (YETT)
* Lynch, Dov,  ''The Conflict in Abkhazia: Dilemmas in Russian 'Peacekeeping' Policy.'' Royal Institute of International Affairs, February 1998.
*MacFarlane, S., N., “On the front lines in the near abroad: the CIS and the OSCE in Georgia’ s civil wars”, ''Third World Quarterly'', Vol 18, No 3, pp 509– 525, 1997.
*Marshania L., ''Tragedy of Abkhazia'' Moscow, 1996
*''White Book of Abkhazia.'' 1992–1993 Documents, Materials, Evidences. Moscow, 1993.

==External links==
*[http://www.c-r.org/our-work/accord/georgia-abkhazia/contents.php Accord issue on the Georgia Abkhazia peace process] also includes chronology and key texts &amp; agreements. {{en icon}}&amp;{{ru icon}}
*http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/mar/chronology.asp?groupId=37201

{{Georgian-Abkhazian conflict}}
{{Post-Cold War European conflicts}}
{{Georgia (country) topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:War In Abkhazia (1992-1993)}}
[[Category:1992 in Abkhazia]]
[[Category:1993 in Abkhazia]]
[[Category:1992 in Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:1993 in Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1992]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1993]]
[[Category:Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia]]
[[Category:Georgian–Abkhazian conflict]]
[[Category:Post-Soviet conflicts]]
[[Category:Wars involving Georgia (country)]]</text>
      <sha1>3jezjbednoihgyiubp47ce699gmzqq9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
