<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Western Virginia Campaign</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32604382</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744739875</id>
      <parentid>728832950</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-17T04:11:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dallyripple</username>
        <id>4503208</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Background */ add link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9638">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict	= Western Virginia Campaign
| partof  	= the [[American Civil War]]
| image   	= 
| caption 	= 
| date    	= May to December, 1861
| place   	= Western [[Virginia]] (modern [[West Virginia]])
| territory   =
| result= [[United States of America|Union]] victory
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|USA|1861}} [[United States]] ([[Union (American Civil War)|Union]])
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|CSA|1861}} [[Confederate States of America|CSA (Confederacy)]]
| commander1  = [[George B. McClellan]]&lt;br /&gt;[[William S. Rosecrans]]
| commander2  = [[Robert E. Lee]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Robert S. Garnett]]{{KIA}}
| strength1   =
| strength2   =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| notes   	=
}}
{{Campaignbox Operations in Western Virginia}}
The '''Western Virginia Campaign''', also known as '''Operations in Western Virginia''' or the '''Rich Mountain Campaign''', occurred from May to December 1861 during the [[American Civil War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Civil War Battle Summaries by Campaign|url=http://www.nps.gov/history/hps/abpp/battles/bycampgn.htm|publisher=Civil War Sites Advisory Commission, American Battlefield Protection Program, National Park Service|accessdate=7 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Union forces under [[Major General]] [[George B. McClellan]] invaded the western portion of [[Virginia]]; this area occupied by the Union later became the state of [[West Virginia]]. Although Confederate forces would make several raids into the area throughout the remainder of the war, they would be unable to reoccupy the state.

Western Virginia was an important source of minerals the Confederates needed for the production of arms and ammunition. It also contained several roads and turnpikes which would grant the Union access to [[Tennessee]], [[North Carolina]], and the [[Shenandoah Valley]], while the [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]] in the northern part of the area connected the eastern Union states to the Midwest.&lt;ref&gt;Boeche, p. 33; Newell, pp. 29–31, 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[File:George B McClellan - retouched.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.9|alt=Photo of man with goatee and his right hand thrust into a dark military uniform|George B. McClellan, Union commander in western Virginia from May to June 1861]]
In April 1861 a [[Virginia Secession Convention of 1861|Virginia state convention]] voted to secede and join the Confederacy. However, there was much opposition to this action from the western counties of the state, which were economically tied closer to western [[Pennsylvania]] and [[Ohio]] than to eastern Virginia. Following the secession vote in Richmond, John Carlile, a Unionist leader from northwest Virginia, led a meeting at [[Clarksburg, West Virginia|Clarksburg]] which called for a convention to meet at [[Wheeling, West Virginia|Wheeling]] the next month for determining what steps &quot;the people of Northwest Virginia should take in the present emergency.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Newell, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;  To organize Union forces in the area, George B. McClellan was appointed commander of the [[Department of the Ohio]], covering Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, western Pennsylvania, and western Virginia. He gathered several regiments raised in Ohio, Indiana, and western Virginia and moved into Virginia in early May, moving along the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and the [[Kanawha River]].&lt;ref&gt;Newell, p. 59-60.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Confederates appointed several commanders to organize troops in western Virginia: Colonel [[George A. Porterfield]] in northwestern Virginia, and [[Brigadier General]]s [[John B. Floyd]] and [[Henry A. Wise]] in the Kanawha Valley. This divided command structure prevented the Confederates from coordinating their response to the Union invasion; in addition, General [[Robert E. Lee]], commander of the Virginia militia forces, underestimated the strength of Unionist support in western Virginia.&lt;ref&gt;Newell, p. 50, 75, 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battles==
===Philippi===
{{further|Battle of Philippi (West Virginia)}}
Confederate Colonel Porterfield concentrated a force of 775 new recruits at the town of Philippi during the month of May. On June 3, a Union column under the command of Brigadier General [[Thomas A. Morris]] launched a two pronged attack on the Confederate camp. The Confederates fired a single volley and then retreated from the town. Only a few were wounded on each side.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rich Mountain and Laurel Hill===
{{further|Battle of Rich Mountain}}
Confederate Brigadier General [[Robert S. Garnett]] concentrated a small force around [[Laurel Mountain (West Virginia)|Laurel Hill]] and Rich Mountain. McClellan detached a small force which outflanked and routed the Confederate left wing on Rich Mountain, which left the main Confederate force at Laurel Mountain isolated and forced Garnett to retreat.&lt;ref&gt;Gallagher, p. 7-8&lt;/ref&gt;

===Corrick’s Ford===
{{further|Battle of Corrick's Ford}}
During the Confederate retreat from Rich Mountain, Garnett deployed a small force of skirmishers at a ford at the [[Cheat River]] in order to delay the Union pursuit. However, Garnett was killed by a Union volley, thus becoming the first [[general officer]] of either army to die in the war. The Confederate force was routed.&lt;ref&gt;Newell, pp. 138–140.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kessler's Cross Lanes===
{{further|Battle of Kessler's Cross Lanes}}
The Confederate brigade of Floyd attacked a Union regiment under Colonel [[Erastus Tyler]] at Kessler’s Cross Lanes and routed it, temporarily securing the eastern Kanawha Valley for the Confederates.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

===Carnifax Ferry===
{{further|Battle of Carnifex Ferry}}
Brigadier General [[William S. Rosecrans]] took three brigades from Clarksburg and attacked Floyd’s brigade at Carnifex Ferry. Although the Confederates were able to hold off the Union attacks, they were outnumbered and were forced to retreat that night.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cheat Mountain===
{{further|Battle of Cheat Mountain}}
During the summer, the Union army concentrated their forces to protect the main highways through western Virginia. Brigadier General [[Joseph J. Reynolds]] commanded the Union garrison on [[Cheat Mountain]] that was supposed to protect the [[Staunton and Parkersburg Turnpike]]. Lee attempted to drive this force off the mountain with a complicated plan involving several columns which would converge on and surround the garrison. However, one of the brigade commanders who was scheduled to start the attack retreated at the last minute, forcing Lee to cancel the offensive.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

===Greenbrier River===
{{further|Battle of Greenbrier River}}
Union Brigadier General Reynolds attacked the camps of [[Henry R. Jackson]]'s brigade but was repulsed. Following an artillery bombardment, Reynolds withdrew back to Cheat Mountain.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

===Camp Allegheny===
{{further|Battle of Camp Allegheny}}
Union Brigadier General [[Robert H. Milroy]] attacked Camp Allegheny, where Colonel [[Edward Johnson (general)|Edward Johnson's]] main Confederate force in western Virginia was located. The Federal soldiers were repulsed.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Robert Edward Lee.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.9|alt=Photo of Robert E. Lee in gray military uniform|Robert E. Lee would be blamed for the Confederate defeats in western Virginia]]
The Union army would occupy the western region of Virginia for the rest of the war, despite several raids by the Confederates into the area. West Virginia would later be split from the Department of the Ohio and be formed into a new [[Department of Western Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;Newell, p. 256.&lt;/ref&gt; The Wheeling convention eventually organized a new state government for the region, which would be admitted to the Union as the state of West Virginia in 1863.&lt;ref&gt;Newell, p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to his victories in western Virginia, McClellan's reputation quickly grew in the North, where the newspapers called him the “Young Napoleon.” Following the Union defeat at the [[First Battle of Bull Run]], he was given command of the [[Army of the Potomac]].&lt;ref&gt;Newell, pp. 164, 170; Boeche, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lee was much criticized in the press because of his defeat in Western Virginia. Called by the press and the soldiers “Granny Lee” and “Evacuating Lee”, he was transferred to South Carolina to supervise construction of coastal fortifications. The remaining forces in Western Virginia were organized into the [[Confederate Army of the Northwest|Army of the Northwest]] until it was incorporated into the Valley District of the [[Army of Northern Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;Cochran, pp. 35–36.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[West Virginia in the American Civil War]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* Boeche, Thomas L.  &quot;McClellan's First Campaign.&quot; America's Civil War, January 1998.
* Cochran, Darrell. &quot;Granny Lee's Inauspicious Debut.&quot; America's Civil War, September 1994.
* Gallagher, Gary W. &quot;Rich Mountain, West Virginia (WV003), Randolph County, July 11, 1861.&quot; from ''The Civil War Battlefield Guide'', 2nd Edition, edited by Frances H. Kennedy. New York: Houghton Mifflin, 1998
* Kennedy, Frances H. ''The Civil War Battlefield Guide'', 2nd Edition. New York: Houghton Mifflin, 1998
* Newell, Clayton R. ''Lee Vs. McClellan: The First Campaign''. Washington, D.C.: Regnary Publishing Inc., 1996. ISBN 0-89526-452-8
* Mallinson, David &quot;Confused First Fight.&quot; America's Civil War, January 1992.

[[Category:Western Virginia Campaign| ]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1861]]
[[Category:1861 in Virginia]]
[[Category:Military operations of the American Civil War in West Virginia]]
[[Category:Campaigns of the Eastern Theater of the American Civil War]]</text>
      <sha1>eyzt586el6wwazwzqd5vrbjpmkwba6s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
