<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Winfield Scott</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>61403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749213988</id>
      <parentid>749213968</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T03:04:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jackfork</username>
        <id>3430766</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2600:1001:B007:8E41:2C98:C534:6763:62B8|2600:1001:B007:8E41:2C98:C534:6763:62B8]] ([[User talk:2600:1001:B007:8E41:2C98:C534:6763:62B8|talk]]) to last revision by OberRanks. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58225">{{Other uses}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military person
|image         = Winfield Scott by Fredricks, 1862.jpg
|caption       = Scott in 1862
|birth_date    = {{Birth date|1786|06|13}}
|death_date    = {{Death date and age|1866|05|29|1786|06|13}}
|birth_place   = [[Dinwiddie County, Virginia|Dinwiddie County]], [[Virginia]]
|death_place   = [[West Point, New York|West Point]], [[New York (state)|New York]]
|placeofburial = [[West Point Cemetery]]
|placeofburial_label =
|placeofburial_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{Coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
|nickname      = &quot;Old Fuss and Feathers&quot;, &quot;The Grand Old Man of the Army&quot;
|birth_name    = Winfield Scott
|allegiance    = [[United States of America]]
|branch        = {{Plainlist|
* [[United States Army]]
* [[Union Army]]}}
|serviceyears  = 1808–1861
|rank          = [[File:Union army lt gen rank insignia.jpg|35px]] [[Brevet (military)|Brevet]] [[Lieutenant general (United States)|lieutenant general]]
|servicenumber =
|unit          =
|commands      = [[United States Army]]
|battles       = [[War of 1812]]
* [[Battle of Queenston Heights]]
* [[Battle of Fort George]]
* [[Capture of Fort Erie]]
* [[Battle of Chippawa]]
* [[Battle of Lundy's Lane]]
[[Seminole Wars]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Black Hawk War]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Mexican–American War]]
* [[Siege of Veracruz]]
* [[Battle of Cerro Gordo]]
* [[Battle of Contreras]]
* [[Battle of Churubusco]]
* [[Battle of Molino del Rey]]
* [[Battle of Chapultepec]]
* [[Battle for Mexico City]]
[[American Civil War]]
|battles_label =
|awards        =
|relations     =
|laterwork     = {{Plainlist|
* Lawyer
* [[Military occupation|Military governor]] of [[Mexico City]]
* [[United States Whig Party|Whig]] candidate for President of the United States, [[U.S. presidential election, 1852|1852]]}}
|signature     = Winfield scott signature.svg
}}
'''Winfield Scott''' (June 13, 1786 – May 29, 1866) was a United States Army general and unsuccessful presidential candidate of the [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig Party]] in 1852.

Known as &quot;Old Fuss and Feathers&quot; and the &quot;Grand Old Man of the Army&quot;, he served on active duty as a general longer than any other person in American history, is rated as one of the most [[United_States_military_seniority#Historical_seniority_list|senior commissioned officers]] of all time, and many historians rate him as the best American commander of his time. Over the course of his 53-year career, he commanded forces in the [[War of 1812]], the [[Black Hawk War]], the [[Mexican–American War]], the [[Seminole Wars|Second Seminole War]], and, briefly, the [[American Civil War]], conceiving the [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]] strategy known as the [[Anaconda Plan]] that was used to defeat the [[Confederate States of America|Confederacy]]. He served as [[Commanding General of the United States Army]] for twenty years, longer than any other holder of the office.

A national hero after the [[Mexican–American War]], he served as military governor of [[Mexico City]]. Such was his stature that, in [[United States presidential election, 1852|1852]], the [[United States Whig Party]] passed over its own incumbent President of the United States, [[Millard Fillmore]], to nominate Scott in that year's [[United States presidential election, 1852|United States presidential election]]. At six feet five inches in height, he remains the [[Heights of presidents and presidential candidates of the United States|tallest]] man ever nominated by a major party. Scott lost to [[United States Democratic Party|Democrat]] [[Franklin Pierce]] in the general election, but remained a popular national figure, receiving a [[Brevet (military)|brevet]] promotion in 1855 to the rank of [[Lieutenant general (United States)|lieutenant general]], becoming the first American since [[George Washington]] to hold that rank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Civil War Biographies&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.civilwarhome.com/scottbio.htm |publisher=The Home of The American Civil War|title=Civil War Biographies |accessdate=December 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.army.mil/html/books/070/70-14/CMH_Pub_70-14.pdf Commanding Generals and Chiefs of Staff]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early years==
[[File:Coat of Arms of Winfield Scott.svg|175px|thumb|left|Coat of Arms of Winfield Scott]]
Winfield Scott was born to William Scott (1747–1791), a farmer and veteran of the [[American Revolution]] who served as an officer in the [[Dinwiddie County, Virginia|Dinwiddie County]] militia, and Ann Mason (1748–1803) on Laurel Branch, the family plantation in Dinwiddie County, [[Virginia]], near [[Petersburg, Virginia]], on June 13, 1786.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Eisenhower, John S.D., ''Agent of Destiny: The Life and Times of General Winfield Scott'' (New York: The Free Press, 1997), 1.&lt;/ref&gt; He was educated by tutors and in the local schools, and briefly attended the [[College of William and Mary]].  He then studied law in the office of attorney David Robinson, where his contemporaries included [[Thomas Ruffin]].  Scott attained admission to the bar, and made a brief attempt to practice law.  He also gained his initial military experience as a [[Corporal#United States|corporal]] of [[cavalry]] in the [[Virginia]] [[militia]] near Petersburg in 1807, during the response to the ''[[Chesapeake–Leopard Affair|Chesapeake–Leopard]]'' Affair.

==Army captain==
Scott's long career in the [[United States Army]] began when Senator [[William Branch Giles]] of Virginia arranged for Scott to be interviewed by [[Henry Dearborn]], the [[Secretary of War]], and President [[Thomas Jefferson]].  He was subsequently commissioned as a captain in the [[Light Artillery]] in May 1808, shortly before his 22nd birthday.

Scott's early career in the army was tumultuous. Scott openly criticized the then [[Commanding General of the United States Army|Commanding General of the Army]], [[James Wilkinson]] over Wilkinson's refusal to follow orders and remove troops from an unhealthy bivouac site he owned near [[New Orleans]], which caused several illnesses and deaths.  Scott's commission was suspended for one year, and after returning to duty, he served in New Orleans on the staff of General [[Wade Hampton I|Wade Hampton]] from 1811 to 1812.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/CG&amp;CSA/Scott-W.htm |title=Winfield Scott |publisher=History.army.mil |date=February 24, 2006 |accessdate=March 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scott earned the nickname &quot;Old Fuss and Feathers&quot; for his insistence on military bearing, courtesy, appearance and discipline. In his own campaigns after reaching high rank, Scott preferred to use a core of [[Regular Army (United States)|Army regulars]] augmented by volunteers whenever possible. Scott perennially concerned himself with the welfare of his men, as demonstrated by his quarrel with Wilkinson over the New Orleans bivouac site. In another instance, when cholera broke out at a post under his command, Scott was the only officer who stayed to nurse the stricken enlisted men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Civil War Biographies&quot;/&gt;

==War of 1812==
[[File:Winfield Scott, ca. War of 1812.jpg|thumb|right|Scott during the War of 1812]]

===Lieutenant Colonel at Queenston Heights===
The army promoted Scott to lieutenant colonel of the [[2nd Air Defense Artillery Regiment (United States)|2nd Artillery Regiment]] in July 1812. Scott served primarily on the [[Niagara Campaign]] front in the War of 1812. He took command of an American landing party during the [[Battle of Queenston Heights]] ([[Upper Canada]]) on October 13, 1812. Most New York militia members refused to cross into Canada in support of the invasion, and the British compelled New York militia commander [[Brigadier General]] [[William Wadsworth (officer)|William Wadsworth]] and Scott, the Regular Army commander, to surrender.

The British held Scott as a prisoner of war. The British considered Irish-American prisoners of war British subjects and traitors and executed 13 such Americans captured at Queenstown Heights. The British paroled and released Scott in a [[prisoner exchange]]. Upon release, Scott returned to Washington to pressure the Senate to take punitive action against British prisoners of war in retaliation for the British executions of Irish-American soldiers. The Senate wrote a bill after this urging, but President [[James Madison]] believed the summary execution of prisoners of war unworthy of civilized nations and so refused to enforce the act.

===Colonel at Fort George===
Scott was promoted to colonel in March 1813.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;/&gt; Scott planned and led the capture of [[Fort George, Ontario|Fort George]], Upper Canada, on the [[Niagara River]]. By crossing the Niagara and landing on the [[Lake Ontario]] shore, Scott forced the British to abandon Fort George. Colonel Scott was wounded in this battle, which is considered among the best-planned and best-executed U.S. operations of the war.

===Brigadier General at Chippawa and Lundy's Lane===
Scott was promoted to brigadier general on March 19, 1814. He was only 27 years old at the time, one of the youngest generals in the history of the U.S. Army.

Scott commanded the 1st Brigade, and was instrumental in the American success at the [[Battle of Chippawa]] on July 5, 1814.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Feltoe |first=Richard |date=2013 |title=The Tide of War: The 1814 Invasions of Upper Canada |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QcfB0h0rPJ8C&amp;pg=PA127 |location=Toronto, Canada |publisher=Dundurn |page=127 |isbn=978-1-4597-1411-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This battle was regarded as inconclusive from the strategic point of view, because the British army was intact and able to continue operations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Peskin |first=Allan |date=2003 |title=Winfield Scott and the Profession of Arms |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LToKephWGXEC&amp;pg=PA46 |location=Kent, OH |publisher=Kent State University Press |page=46 |isbn=978-0-87338-774-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was decisive from the point of view of British morale; American soldiers had fought professionally against a professional European army, and ended the fight in control of the battlefield.  The morale of British soldiers ebbed, and their Native American allies refused to cooperate with them.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=LToKephWGXEC&amp;pg=PA46 Winfield Scott and the Profession of Arms]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Scott had a major role in the bloody [[Battle of Lundy's Lane]] on July 25, and suffered serious wounds. The American commander, Major General [[Jacob Brown]], and the British-Canadian commander, Lieutenant General [[Gordon Drummond]], were also wounded.

===Brevet Major General===
For his valor at Lundy's Lane, Scott received a brevet (i.e., an honorary promotion) to major general to date from July 25, 1814. However, the severity of his wounds prevented his return to active duty for the remainder of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas G. Mitchell|title=Indian Fighters Turned American Politicians: From Military Service to Public Office|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OcMct2s5KKkC&amp;pg=PA100|year=2003|publisher=Greenwood |page=100}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1815, Scott was admitted as an honorary member of the Pennsylvania [[Society of the Cincinnati]] in recognition of his service in the War of 1812.&lt;ref&gt;Members of the Society of the Cincinnati. William Sturgis Thomas. 1929.&lt;/ref&gt;  Scott's Society of the Cincinnati insignia was a one of a kind solid gold eagle measuring nearly three inches in height, making it one of the most impressive military society insignias ever produced.&lt;ref&gt;The Insignia of the Society of the Cincinnati.  Minor Myers, Jr. The Society of the Cincinnati. Washington, D.C.  1998. pg. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; There are, however, no known portraits or photographs of Scott wearing the insignia. Scott's insignia is in the collection of the West Point Museum.

==After the War of 1812==
From the War of 1812 until he became commanding general of the U.S. Army in 1841, Scott had a rivalry with Brevet Major General [[Edmund P. Gaines]]. The central issue was the question of which had seniority; should brevet ranks count, which would favor Scott, or were regular Army ranks what mattered, which would favor Gaines?  Scott claimed he outranked Gaines because Scott's brevet rank of major general, dated July 25, 1814 made him senior to Gaines, whose brevet was dated August 15, 1814.  Gaines argued that he should be senior; his and Scott's promotions to brigadier general, colonel, and lieutenant colonel were all issued on the same dates, but Gaines had been promoted to major first.  The dispute was important to both because they realized that assignment as the Army's commanding general might be at stake. (Gaines became increasingly marginalized as Scott continued to gain influence, and died in 1849 while still on active duty.)

Scott supervised the preparation of the first standard drill regulations for the Army and headed a postwar officer retention selection board in 1815. He also served as president of Board of Tactics in 1815.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;/&gt; Scott visited Europe to study French military methods in 1815/1816.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;/&gt; He translated several military manuals of [[Napoleon I of France]] into English.

Scott held regional command in the Division of the North in 1816. He married Maria D. Mayo (1789&amp;nbsp;– June 10, 1862&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Appletons' annual cyclopaedia and register of important events of the year: 1862|year=1863|publisher=D. Appleton &amp; Company|location=New York|page=667|url=https://archive.org/stream/1862appletonsan02newyuoft#page/n674/mode/1up}}&lt;/ref&gt;) in 1817.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;/&gt;

Scott served as president of the Board of Tactics in 1821, 1824 and 1826.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;/&gt;  He commanded the Eastern Department in 1825.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;/&gt;

Scott and Gaines were passed over for the commanding general's post in 1828, following the death of [[Jacob Brown]].  Aware of the Scott/Gaines rivalry, President [[John Quincy Adams]] nominated [[Alexander Macomb, Jr.|Alexander Macomb]], who had been a brigadier general, but agreed to reduction in rank to colonel in order to serve as the Army's chief of engineers. Scott attempted to resign, but it was not accepted. Scott again visited Europe and then resumed command of the Eastern Department in 1829.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.army.mil&quot;/&gt; Upon direction of the War Department, Scott in 1830 published ''[http://www.drillnet.net/ABSTRACT/Abstract.htm Abstract of Infantry Tactics, Including Exercises and Manueuvres of Light-Infantry and Riflemen, for the Use of the Militia of the United States]'' for the use of the American militia.

==Nullification Crisis==
[[File:General-Winfield-Scott-(1786-1866)1835.jpg|200px|right|thumb|Winfield Scott, 1835 portrait by [[George Catlin]]]]
[[Cholera]] among his reinforcing troops prevented Scott from taking field command during the [[Black Hawk War]]. In late November and early December 1832, Scott organized U.S. Army troops for possible enforcement of [[President of the United States|President]] [[Andrew Jackson]]'s authority during the [[Nullification Crisis]]. In late 1832 and early 1833 Scott served as an emissary from President Jackson to [[South Carolina]]. His tactful diplomacy and the use of his troops in suppressing a major fire in Charleston did much to defuse the crisis.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

==Indian Wars==
In 1832, Scott replaced [[John E. Wool]] as commander of Federal troops in the [[Cherokee Nation (19th century)|Cherokee Nation]] lands in Georgia.

Scott commanded the field forces in [[Second Seminole War]] and [[Creek War]] in 1836. Scott was recalled to Washington due to the highly politicized nature of the tactics he employed and the huge expenditures incurred in policing the frontier, compounded by controversies between regular army and local militia officers. Brigadier General [[Edmund Meredith Shackelford]] was appointed commander in the area by President Jackson until Brigadier General [[Thomas Jesup]] could arrive. A
court of inquiry later cleared Scott of wrongdoing in the Seminole and Creek operations.

Scott felt that his recall was a political intrigue. In 1845, Shackelford wrote to Jackson for a clarifying statement that Shackelford had had no part in Scott's recall to Washington.

Scott assumed command of the Eastern Division in 1837. Scott was responsible for maintaining order on the Canada–US border, where the [[Patriot War]] threatened to entangle the U.S. in the [[Upper Canada Rebellion]].

==Cherokee Removal==
Presidents Jackson and [[Martin Van Buren|Van Buren]], ignoring the [[United States Supreme Court|Supreme Court]]'s ruling in ''[[Worcester v. Georgia]]'', tacitly supported Georgia's expulsion of the Cherokees. In 1838, Scott was placed in charge of enforcing the [[Treaty of New Echota]], including removal of the Cherokees to the [[Indian Territory]] (now [[Oklahoma]]).

Van Buren put Scott in command of the &quot;Army of the Cherokee Nation&quot;, headquartered at [[Fort Cass]] and [[Fort Butler (Murphy, North Carolina)|Fort Butler]].&lt;ref&gt;Garrison, Tim Alan, ''The Legal Ideology of Removal: The Southern Judiciary and the Sovereignty of Native American Nations'' (Athens: University of Georgia Press, 2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

Arriving at [[New Echota]], Cherokee Nation, on April 6, 1838, Scott immediately divided the Cherokee Nation into three military districts. He designated May 26, 1838 as the beginning date for the first phase of the removal. The first phase involved the Cherokees in Georgia. Scott wanted Army regulars rather than Georgia militia for this operation, because the militia had personal gains at stake; some claimed Cherokee land.&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, 188–191.&lt;/ref&gt; The promised regulars did not arrive in time, so Scott proceeded with 4,000 Georgia militia.

The moral implications of the Jackson-Van Buren policies did not make Scott's role easy. Representative (and ex-President) [[John Quincy Adams]] opposed the removal, imputing it to &quot;Southern politicians and land grabbers&quot;; many Americans agreed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenhower190&quot;&gt;Eisenhower, 190.&lt;/ref&gt; Scott reassured the Cherokee people of proper treatment. In his instructions to the militia, Scott called any acts of harshness and cruelty &quot;abhorrent to the generous sympathies of the whole American people.&quot; Scott also admonished his troops not to fire on any fugitives they might apprehend unless they should &quot;make stand and resist&quot;. Scott detailed help to render the weak and infirm: &quot;Horses or ponies should be used to carry Cherokees too sick or feeble to march.&quot; Also, &quot;Infants, superannuated persons, lunatics, and women in a helpless condition with all, in the removal [deserve] peculiar attention, which the brave and humane will seek to adopt to the necessities of the several cases.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenhower190&quot;/&gt;

Scott's good intentions, however, did not adequately protect the Cherokees from terrible abuses, especially at the hands of &quot;lawless rabble that followed on the heels of the soldiers to loot and pillage&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenhower190&quot;/&gt; At the end of the first phase of the removal in August 1838, 3,000 Cherokees left Georgia and Tennessee by water toward Oklahoma, but camps still retained another 13,000. By the intercession of [[John Ross (Cherokee chief)|Chief John Ross]] in Washington, these Cherokees traveled &quot;under their own auspices, unarmed, and free of supervision by militiamen or regulars.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, 191–193.&lt;/ref&gt;

Though government contractors, steamboat owners, and others who stood to profit protested, Scott carried out this new policy. Ex-President Jackson demanded of the Attorney General the replacement of Scott and the arrest of Chief Ross.&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, 193.&lt;/ref&gt;

Within months, Scott captured (or killed) every Cherokee in north Georgia, Tennessee, and Alabama who could not escape. His troops reportedly rounded up the Cherokee and held them in rat-infested stockades with little food. Private John G. Burnett later wrote, &quot;Future generations will read and condemn the act and I do hope posterity will remember that private soldiers like myself, and like the four Cherokees who were forced by General Scott to shoot an Indian Chief and his children, had to execute the orders of our superiors. We had no choice in the matter.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cherokee-nc.com/index.php?page=62 Trail of Tears], Cherokee North Carolina website.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cherokee.org/Culture/CulInfo/TOT/128/Default.aspx Cherokee Nation official website] John Burnett's Story of the Trail of Tears&lt;/ref&gt;

More than 4,000 Cherokee died in this confinement before ever beginning the trip west. As the first groups herded west died in huge numbers in the heat, the Cherokee pleaded with Scott to postpone the second phase of the removal until autumn, and he complied. Determined to accompany them as an observer, Scott left [[Athens, Georgia]], on October 1, 1838, and traveled with the first &quot;company&quot; of a thousand people, including both Cherokees and black slaves, as far as Nashville.&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, 194–195&lt;/ref&gt; The Cherokee removal later became known as the [[Trail of Tears]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cherokee.org/Culture/CulInfo/TOT/58/Default.aspx A Brief History of the Trail of Tears], Cherokee Nation website.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aroostook War==
When Brigadier General Winfield Scott reached Nashville, superiors abruptly ordered him to return to Washington to deal with troubles on the Canada–US border. On this assignment, he helped defuse tensions between officials of the state of [[Maine]] and the British colony of [[New Brunswick]] in the undeclared and bloodless [[Aroostook War]] in March 1839.

==Authorship of manual on tactics==
In 1840, Scott wrote ''Infantry Tactics, Or, Rules for the Exercise and Maneuvre of the United States Infantry''. This three-volume work served as the standard drill manual for the United States Army until [[William J. Hardee]]'s ''Tactics'', published in 1855.

==Commanding General==
On June 25, 1841, Macomb died, and Scott and Gaines were the two most obvious choices to succeed him.  [[John Bell (Tennessee politician)|John Bell]], the Secretary of War, had no interest in rekindling the Scott/Gaines seniority dispute; he quickly recommended Scott to President [[John Tyler]].  Tyler approved, and Scott assumed office as commanding general on July 5, 1841.  He was promoted to major general, then the highest rank in the Army, with June 25, 1841, as his date of rank.

As commanding general of the Army, Scott took great interest in the professional development of the cadets of the [[United States Military Academy]].&lt;ref&gt;Waugh, John, ''The Class of 1846: From West Point to Appomattox: Stonewall Jackson, George McClellan, and Their Brothers'', Ballantine Books, 1999, ISBN 0-345-43403-X.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mexican–American War==

===Command appointments===
[[File:General Winfield Scott.JPEG|thumb|left|A drawing of Scott at the battle of Veracruz]]
During the [[Mexican–American War]], Major General Scott was appointed by President [[James K. Polk]] to lead an army of regulars and volunteers to the [[Rio Grande]] for a hasty campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Bauer p.73&lt;/ref&gt; During the planning and initial movement, worsening political tensions between Scott and the president led to a very public shellacking and relief of Scott as field commander. With reluctance, [[Zachary Taylor]] was charged with leading the charge to the Rio Grande.

While Taylor was largely successful in securing the northeastern provinces of Mexico after war broke out, it became obvious by the mid-1846, the Mexicans would not surrender the captured territories without a direct assault on their capital. Deeming an overland campaign from northeastern Mexico unfeasible (required marching over {{convert|560|mi|km|abbr=on|0}} of arid Mexican desert), Scott planned an expedition to Gulf port city of Veracruz. As Taylor gained notoriety for victories in northeastern Mexico, Polk became increasingly reluctant to posture Taylor for a presidential run post-bellum. Further, Polk and his cabinet had reasonable doubts whether Taylor could lead the complex operation. Left to choose between Taylor and Scott, Polk reluctantly chose Scott at the behest of his cabinet.&lt;ref&gt;Bauer p.235&lt;/ref&gt;

Even while Scott was en route to the theater of operations, Polk continued to search for a fellow [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]] to command the expedition in lieu of Scott. Senator [[William O. Butler]] and [[Robert Patterson]] were both selected as early options, but neither were deemed acceptable by Congress. Patterson, who was Irish-born and not eligible to be President, was dismissed early on as a suitable choice. Butler's capacity to command an army was questionable at best, never seeing combat and lacking experience in the regular Army.

===Military campaigns===
[[File:Winfield Scott on horseback.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|&lt;center&gt;Allegorical depiction of Winfield Scott on horseback during the Battle of Cerro Gordo.&lt;/center&gt;]]
Landing at [[Veracruz (city)|Veracruz]] on March 9, 1847, Scott, assisted by one of his staff officers, Captain [[Robert E. Lee]], and perhaps inspired by [[William H. Prescott]]'s ''History of the Conquest of Mexico'', followed the approximate route taken by [[Hernán Cortés]] in 1519, and assaulted [[Mexico City]]. Scott's opponent in this campaign, Mexican president and general [[Antonio López de Santa Anna]], had just suffered a crushing defeat at Buena Vista and faced impending revolt by the Mexican populace. Santa Anna chose to meet Scott after the landing, assuming the American force to be significantly degraded after a costly offense on the well-fortified Vera Cruz. Despite high heat, rains, and difficult terrain, Scott won the battles of [[Battle of Cerro Gordo|Cerro Gordo]] on April 18, 1847, [[Battle of Contreras|Contreras/Padierna]] on August 19–20, 1847, [[Battle of Churubusco|Churubusco]] on August 20, 1847, and [[Molino del Rey]] on September 8, 1847. He then assaulted the fort of [[Battle of Chapultepec|Chapultepec]] on September 13, 1847, after which Mexico City surrendered.

When the [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Duke of Wellington]], victor of Waterloo, learned that Scott had succeeded against alarming odds in capturing Mexico City, he proclaimed Scott &quot;the greatest living general&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Timothy D., ''Winfield Scott'' (Lawrence, Kansas: University of Kansas Press, 1998), 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Saint Patrick's Battalion===
A group of Irish-American deserters from the U.S. Army joined the Mexican army as the [[Saint Patrick's Battalion|''San Patricio'' (St. Patrick) Battalion]]. Seventy-two of them were captured at Churubusco.

The San Patricio men were deserters in action, and had traitorously joined the enemy army. There was no question about this, and the punishment for desertion and treason was death. Scott's army was still facing a dangerous enemy and possible insurgency, so he placed the prisoners before courts martial to have them settle it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenhower2878&quot;&gt;Eisenhower, 287–288.&lt;/ref&gt; Eisenhower says the men were tried in two groups. The trials were conducted fairly by Brevet Colonel [[John Garland (general)|John Garland]] and by Colonel [[Bennet Riley]]. Because all the men captured were wearing Mexican uniforms, they were found guilty and sentenced to hang.

This created a serious problem for Scott. He was troubled by the sweep of guilty verdicts. He did not want to alienate the Mexican public, who by now had made the deserters national heroes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenhower2878&quot;/&gt; Nor did he want to encourage insurgency among the Mexican people that would weaken his pacification program in progress. He also knew that the deserters were Irish-born Catholics, who had deserted Taylor's army because they allegedly felt mistreated and had witnessed atrocities &quot;sufficient to make Heaven weep&quot; against fellow Catholics, the Mexicans.&lt;ref&gt;Chichetto, James Wm., &quot;General Winfield Scott's Policy of Pacification in the Mexican American War of 1846–1848,&quot; ''Combat Literary Journal'', Volume 5, Number 4, Fall/October 2007, 4–5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Commenting on Taylor's initial occupation, Scott wrote to the [[Secretary of War]], William Marcy:&quot;Sir, our militia and volunteers [under Taylor], if a tenth of what is said be true, have committed atrocities – horrors – in Mexico, sufficient to make Heaven weep, and every American, of Christian morals, blush for his country. Murder, robbery – rape on mothers and daughters, in the presence of the tied up males of the families, have been common all along the Rio Grande. I was agonized with what I heard – not from Mexicans and regulars alone; but from respectable individual volunteers – from the masters and hands of our steamers.&quot; Chichetto, 5.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to these, in 1847, Scott ordered that Protestants respect Catholic ceremonies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gilderlehrman.org/collections/6b999baa-f4ef-40c2-9042-978707415870 Scott, Winfield (1786–1866) General orders: No. 297] (24 September 1847) – The Gilder Lehrman Institute of American History&lt;/ref&gt;

Scott believed he needed to confirm the trials and sentences. He concluded that some men deserved less punishment, and sat up nights attempting to find excuses to avoid the universal application of capital punishment.&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, 288.&lt;/ref&gt; In the end he approved the death penalty for 50 of the 72 San Patricios, but later pardoned five and reduced the sentence of fifteen others, including the ringleader, Sergeant John Riley.&lt;ref&gt;Chichetto, 5&lt;/ref&gt; This left 30 slated for execution, 16 of whom were hanged on September 10, 1847. Four were hanged the next day, and the remainder assigned to Colonel [[William S. Harney|William Harney]] for execution at some later date.

[[File:GenWScott-engraving.jpg|thumb|left|Engraving of Winfield Scott]]

On the day of execution, Harney ordered each deserter placed on a mule cart with a rope around his neck, fastening each rope to a mass [[gibbet]]. Then, during the battle of Chapultepec, just as the American flag was about to rise above the walls of the Mexican citadel, he ordered the executioners to give the mules a whack, causing the beasts to lurch forward, leaving the deserters in mid-air, dangling &quot;en masse&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenhower297&quot;&gt;Eisenhower, 297.&lt;/ref&gt; Some argue that this adversely affected Scott's record, as the events violated numerous [[Articles of War]]. Eisenhower, however, attributes the incident to Harney.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenhower297&quot;/&gt;

During political intrigues later in his life, Scott ignored the events, stating &quot;not one [Irishman]&amp;nbsp;... was ever known to turn his back upon the enemy or friend&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;peskin, Allan, ''Winfield Scott and the Profession of Arms'', Kent State University Press, 2003, ISBN 0-87338-774-0, p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In a private letter to William Robinson, Scott wrote about his Irish American soldiers: &quot;In Mexico, we estimated the number of persons, foreigners by birth, at, about, 3,500, and of these more than 2,000 were Irish. How many had been naturalized I cannot say; but am persuaded that seven out of ten, had at least declared their intentions, according to law, to become citizens. It is hazardous, or may be invidious to make distinctions; but truth obliges me to say that, of our Irish soldiers – save a few who deserted from General Taylor, and had never taken the naturalization oath – not one ever turned his back upon the enemy or faltered in advancing to the charge. Most of the foreigners, by birth, also behaved faithfully and gallantly. Chichetto,5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;On another occasion, Scott remarked to Robinson: &quot;In my recent campaign in Mexico, a very large proportion of the men under my command were your country men (Irish), German, etc. I witnessed with admiration their zeal, fidelity, and valor in maintaining our flag in the face of every danger. Vying with each other, and our native-born soldiers in the same ranks, in patriotism, constancy, and heroic daring, I was happy to call them brothers in the field, as I shall always be to salute them as countrymen at home.&quot; Chichetto, 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Military governor===
As military commander of Mexico City, he was held in high esteem by Mexican civil and American authorities alike, primarily owing to his pacification policy and fairness. For example, when he drew his &quot;martial law order&quot; to be issued and enforced in Mexico (to prevent looting, rape, murder, etc.), all offenders, both Mexicans and Americans, were treated equally.&lt;ref&gt;Chichetto, 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conflict with American civil authorities===
Apart from his military career, Scott's vanity, as well as his corpulence, led to a catch phrase that haunted him for the remainder of his political life.

Complaining about the division of command between himself and General Taylor, in a letter to [[United States Secretary of War|Secretary of War]] [[William Marcy]], Scott wrote of not wishing to &quot;have a fire in his rear (from Washington) while he met a fire in front of the Mexicans&quot;.&lt;ref name=Sargent297/&gt; This offended Marcy and also Polk. In another letter, Scott wrote that a letter from Marcy arrived as &quot;at about 6&amp;nbsp;pm as I sat down to take a hasty plate of soup&quot;.&lt;ref name=Sargent297&gt;Sargent, Nathan. ''Public Men and Events from the Commencement of Mr. Monroe's Administration''. 1875, J. B. Lippincott &amp; Co., p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt; The Polk administration, eager to embarrass Scott, promptly published the letter, and the cryptic phrase appeared in political cartoons and comic songs for the rest of his life.

Scott was made an honorary member of the [[Aztec Club of 1847]], an organization of American officers who served in the Mexican War.  Originally, the only officers who could join were those who served in the occupation of Mexico City.  Later, the organization allowed for other officers who served during the Mexican War to join along with their descendants.

==Presidential campaigns==
===1840===
{{main|1839 Whig National Convention}}

Scott was one of the candidates to be the [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig]] nominee for [[United States presidential election, 1840|president in 1840]]. The leading contenders were [[William Henry Harrison]] and [[Henry Clay]], with Scott in third place. Scott's hope was that delegates might turn to him if Harrison and Clay deadlocked.  During the balloting at the party's December 1839 convention in [[Harrisburg, Pennsylvania]], Clay and Scott were at the [[Astor House]] hotel in [[New York City]], and played cards with Whig politicians [[John J. Crittenden]] and [[George Evans (American politician)|George Evans]].  When the group received word of Harrison's victory on the fifth ballot, Clay blamed his loss on Scott for not withdrawing and instructing his delegates to vote for Clay. In the ensuing argument, Clay struck Scott, with the blow landing on the shoulder which had been wounded during Scott's participation in the [[Battle of Lundy's Lane]].  Afterwards Clay had to be physically removed from the hotel room. Scott then sent Crittenden to Clay with Scott's challenge for a duel, but Crittenden reconciled them by convincing Clay to apologize.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Eisenhower |first=John S. D. |date=1999 |title=Agent of Destiny: The Life and Times of General Winfield Scott |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vkVCQmU9nfYC&amp;pg=PA212&amp;dq=%22agent+of+destiny%22+clay+crittenden+whist&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiey6GvgOvJAhXHjz4KHU_vB9EQ6AEIJTAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22extract%20an%20apology%22&amp;f=false |location=Norman, OK |publisher=University of Oklahoma Press |pages=205–206 |isbn=978-0-8061-3128-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1852===
{{main|1852 Whig National Convention}}
[[File:Scott vs Pierce campaign.jpg|thumb|300px|right|''The Game-cock &amp; the Goose'', an 1852 Whig cartoon favoring Winfield Scott]]
In the [[United States presidential election, 1852|1852 presidential election]], anti-slavery Whigs were able to block the nomination of incumbent President, [[Millard Fillmore]], who had succeeded to the presidency on the death of Taylor. These Whigs were angry by Fillmore's signing of the [[Fugitive Slave Act of 1850|Fugitive Slave Act]], part of the [[Compromise of 1850]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/millardfillmore |title=Millard Fillmore |publisher=''The White House'' |access-date=June 6, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Seeking to repeat their previous successes with war heroes, the Whigs nominated Scott instead, who faced [[History of the United States Democratic Party|Democrat]] [[Franklin Pierce]]. However, the nomination process foreshadowed the general election:

&lt;blockquote&gt;More grievously rent by sectional rivalries than the Democrats, the Whigs balloted fifty-three times before nominating Scott. The delegates then unanimously approved the platform except for the central plank that pledged &quot;acquiescence&quot; in the [[Compromise of 1850]], &quot;the act known as the [[Fugitive slave laws|Fugitive Slave law]] included.&quot; The plank carried by a vote of 212 to 70, opposition coming largely from Scott's supporters. The old soldier, faced with disarray in the Whig ranks, sought out to resolve his dilemma by announcing, &quot;I accept the nomination with the resolutions annexed.&quot; To this, antislavery Whigs rejoined, &quot;We accept the candidate, but we spit on the platform.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Race and Politics&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Rawley|first=James A.|title=Race &amp; Politics: &quot;Bleeding Kansas&quot; and the Coming of the Civil War|location=Lincoln, Nebraska|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|year=1979|isbn=0-8032-3854-1|pages=19–21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Scott's anti-slavery reputation undermined his support in the South, while the Party's pro-slavery platform depressed turnout in the North, and Scott's opponent was a Mexican–American War veteran as well, which lessened the effectiveness of Scott's war hero status. Pierce was elected in an overwhelming win, leaving Scott with the electoral votes of only [[Massachusetts]], [[Vermont]], [[Kentucky]] and [[Tennessee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Race and Politics&quot;/&gt; A contemporary newspaper called the 1852 election  the most &quot;ludicrous, ridiculous, and uninteresting presidential campaign&quot; in history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://millercenter.org/president/biography/pierce-campaigns-and-elections |title=Franklin Pierce: Campaigns and Elections |publisher=''The Miller Center'' |access-date=July 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1852 campaign is the only one in American history where one candidate (Pierce) had served under the command of the other (Scott) in time of war.
[[File:WinfieldScott.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Scott in civilian clothes]]

==Later career==
Despite his defeat in the election, Scott was still a popular national hero. In February 1855, by a special act of Congress, Scott was given a brevet promotion to the rank of [[Lieutenant general (United States)|lieutenant general]], making him the second person in U.S. military history, after [[George Washington]], to hold that rank.

In 1859, Scott traveled to the [[Pacific Northwest]] to settle a dispute with the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|British]] over [[San Juan Island]], which had escalated to the so-called [[Pig War (1859)|Pig War]]. The old general established a good rapport with the British, and brought about a peaceful resolution.

==American Civil War==
[[File:Winfield Scott Seated 1861.jpg|thumb|Lieut. Gen. Winfield Scott, 1861]]

When the [[American Civil War]] began in the spring of 1861, Scott was 74 years old and suffering numerous health problems, including [[gout]], [[rheumatism]], and [[dropsy]]. He was also extremely overweight and unable to mount a horse or review troops.

As Scott could not lead an army into battle, he offered the command of the United States' army to Colonel [[Robert E. Lee]] on April 17, 1861, whom Scott referred to as &quot;the very finest soldier I've ever seen&quot;. However, Virginia declared that it had left the [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]] on that same day. Lee, though disapproving of secession, was hesitant at the possibility of taking up arms against his home state and asked if he could keep out of the war. Scott replied &quot;I have no place in my army for equivocal men.&quot; Lee then resigned and went south to join the [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] army instead.

Although Scott was born and raised in Virginia, he remained loyal to the U.S., the nation that he had served for most of his life, and refused to resign his commission.

The command of the U.S. troops at Washington was given to Brigadier General [[Irvin McDowell]].

At this time, public opinion throughout the Northern states called for an immediate campaign to crush the rebellion quickly. Scott considered this wrong-headed and probably impossible. Instead, he drew up a plan to defeat the Confederacy by blockading Southern ports and sending an army down the Mississippi Valley. Scott's scheme was derided as the &quot;[[Anaconda Plan]]&quot;, intended to crush the Confederacy slowly; eventually the actual Union victory followed its broad outlines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tcr.org/tcr/essays/CB_Blockade.pdf |title=Blockade essays |format=PDF |publisher=1995 [[The Concord Review]], Inc. |accessdate=June 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Blockade-Run Covers&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2028278 |title=Blockade-Run Covers |publisher=National Postal Museum, Blockade-Run Covers |accessdate=November 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Scott-anaconda.jpg|thumb|left |250px|1861 characterized map of Scott's &quot;Anaconda Plan&quot; to squeeze the South]]

But in July 1861, the pressure to march &quot;Forward to Richmond&quot; was overwhelming. Lincoln set aside Scott's plan and directed McDowell to attack in Virginia.

When Lincoln received news that the Union Army had been defeated at [[First Battle of Bull Run|Manassas]] on July 21, 1861, he went to Scott's residence. Scott assumed responsibility for the Union defeat. Major General [[George B. McClellan]] took command of the army at Washington (now the [[Army of the Potomac]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Lincoln-Scott, West Point&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mrlincolnandnewyork.org/inside.asp?ID=27&amp;subjectID=2 |publisher=The Lincoln Institute |title=Mr. Lincoln and New York |accessdate=November 29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scott's physical infirmities cast doubt on his fitness for command; his weight had ballooned to over 300&amp;nbsp;lbs.  In a play on his old nickname, he was called &quot;Old Fat and Feeble&quot;.

He also ran into conflict with President Lincoln and others who wanted to organize the army into divisions. Scott argued that in the Mexican War, no commands larger than brigades had been needed, and that none were needed now, even though the Army of the Potomac was more than triple the size of Scott's army in Mexico.{{citation needed|date=March 2012}} McClellan, the ambitious new field commander, wanted Scott out, and had many influential political friends. Scott resigned on November 1, 1861. McClellan then succeeded him as [[General-in-Chief#USA|general-in-chief]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mrlincolnswhitehouse.org/inside_search.asp?ID=148&amp;subjectID=2&amp;searchWord=Winfield%20%Scott Mr. Lincoln's White House: an examination of Washington DC during Abraham Lincoln's Presidency]&lt;/ref&gt; Although officially retired, Scott was still occasionally consulted by Lincoln for strategic advice during the war.

==Retirement and death==
After his retirement from the Army, Scott lived the rest of his life at the [[United States Military Academy]] at [[West Point, New York]].  Scott lived to see the Union's victory in the Civil War in April 1865. 

On October 4, 1865, he was elected as a Companion of the Pennsylvania Commandery of the [[Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States]] (MOLLUS), an organization of Union officers who had served in the Civil War. Scott was assigned MOLLUS insignia number 27 but, for undetermined reasons, the insignia was never issued to Scott.  (Scott was one of the few individuals to have belonged to the Society of the Cincinnati, the Aztec Club of 1847 and the Loyal Legion.)

General Scott died at West Point on May 29, 1866, and is buried in the [[West Point Cemetery]].

==Legacy==
Scott served under every President from [[Thomas Jefferson|Jefferson]] to Lincoln, a total of fourteen administrations. Scott served a total of 53 years of active service as an officer—including 47 years as a general, and twenty years (1841–61) as Commanding General. 

Scott is one of a very few American officers who have served as a general during three major wars. (The others were General of the Army [[Douglas MacArthur]] and General [[Lewis B. Hershey]].) Historians rank Scott highly both as a strategist and as a battlefield commander.

Scott's papers can be found at the [[William L. Clements Library]] at the [[University of Michigan]] at [[Ann Arbor, Michigan|Ann Arbor]], [[Michigan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clements.umich.edu/Webguides/Arlenes/S/Scott.html William L. Clements Library].&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Scott County, Iowa|Scott County]] in the state of [[Iowa]] is named in Winfield Scott's honor, as he was the presiding officer at the signing of the peace treaty ending the [[Black Hawk War]]. [[Scott County, Kansas|Scott County]], [[Kansas]]; [[Scott County, Virginia|Scott County]], Virginia;&lt;ref&gt;''The Origin of Certain Place Names in the United States'' by Henry Gannett&lt;/ref&gt; [[Scott County, Minnesota|Scott County]], [[Minnesota]]; [[Scott County, Tennessee|Scott County]], [[Tennessee]];  [[Scottsdale, Arizona|Scottsdale]], [[Arizona]]; [[Winfield, Illinois|Winfield]], Illinois; [[Winfield, Indiana|Winfield]], Indiana; [[Winfield, Alabama|Winfield]], [[Alabama]]; and [[Winfield, Tennessee|Winfield]], Tennessee were also named for him. [[Fort Scott, Kansas|Fort Scott]], Kansas, a former Army outpost, was also named for him, as were the towns of [[Scott Depot, West Virginia|Scott Depot]] and [[Winfield, West Virginia|Winfield]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kenny|first=Hamill|title=West Virginia Place Names: Their Origin and Meaning, Including the Nomenclature of the Streams and Mountains|url=https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015009099824;view=1up;seq=709;size=125|year=1945|publisher=The Place Name Press|location=Piedmont, WV|page=685}}&lt;/ref&gt; in West Virginia. Scott Township in [[Mahaska County, Iowa]], was formerly called Jackson before residents formally petitioned to change the township's name in light of their strong support of Scott in the 1852 presidential campaign.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beforetime.net/iowagenealogy/mahaska/HistoryOfScottTWP/3637.gif History of Scott Township]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, [[Cerro Gordo County, Iowa]], and the town of [[Churubusco, Indiana]], were named for battles where Scott led his troops to victory. [[Lake Winfield Scott]], near [[Suches, Georgia|Suches]], is one of [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]'s highest elevation lakes. [[Mount Scott (Oklahoma)]] was named after Winfield Scott by Captain [[Randolph B. Marcy]] in 1851.&lt;ref&gt;[http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/F/FO038.html Fort Sill]. Digital.library.okstate.edu. Retrieved on August 17, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1882, the fort now known as [[Fort Point, San Francisco|Fort Point]] at the foot of the [[Golden Gate Bridge]] in the Presidio was given the name &quot;Fort Winfield Scott&quot; by U.S. Army Headquarters. That fort officially retained the name until 1886, when the fort was downgraded to a sub-post of the [[Presidio of San Francisco]]. The name was then used once again for the new coast artillery post established in 1912 in the Presidio.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/archive/prsf/coast_defense/harbor_defense_sf/fort_scott/index.htm ''Fort Winfield Scott''], NPS website.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[paddle steamer]] named the ''[[SS Winfield Scott|Winfield Scott]]'' launched in 1850 and a [[US Army]] [[tugboat]] currently in service is named ''[[MG Winfield Scott (LT-805)|Winfield Scott]]''.

The [[General Winfield Scott House]], his home in New York City during 1853–1855, was named [[National Historic Landmark]] in 1973. The saying &quot;[[Great Scott!]]&quot; may have originated from a soldier under Winfield Scott.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-gre4.htm World Wide Words website]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Scott's oriole]] was named for him by [[Darius N. Couch]], a major general. It had turned out that the species was described several years earlier by naturalist [[Charles Lucien Bonaparte|Charles Bonaparte]], but Scott's name was retained in the common name anyway.

Union General [[Winfield Scott Hancock]], Confederate General [[Winfield Scott Featherston]] and Admiral [[Winfield Scott Schley]] were named after General Scott.  (Scott was possibly the only general in history to have a subordinate named after himself.)

The actor [[Stuart Randall (actor)|Stuart Randall]] played Scott in the 1960 episode &quot;The Quota&quot; of [[NBC]]'s ''[[Riverboat (TV series)|Riverboat]]'' [[Western (genre)|western]] [[television series]].

Retired United States Supreme Court Justice [[Sandra Day O'Connor]] is a descendant of Winfield Scott.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npg.si.edu/exhibit/frontier/audio.html |title=National Portrait Gallery &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; Faces of the Frontier |publisher=Npg.si.edu |accessdate=March 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dates of rank==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+
! Rank !! Date !! Component
|-
|[[File:Union army cpt rank insignia.jpg|75px]] [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] || 3 May 1808 || [[Regular Army]]
|-
|[[File:Union Army LTC rank insignia.png|75px]] [[Lieutenant Colonel (United States)|Lieutenant Colonel]] || 6 July 1812 || Regular Army
|-
|[[File:Union Army colonel rank insignia.png|75px]] [[Colonel (United States)|Colonel]] || 12 March 1813 || Regular Army
|-
|[[File:Union Army brigadier general rank insignia.svg|75px]] [[Brigadier General (United States)|Brigadier General]] || 9 March 1814 || Regular Army
|-
|[[File:Union Army major general rank insignia.svg|75px]] [[Major General (United States)|Brevet Major General]] || 25 July 1814 || Regular Army
|-
|[[File:Union Army major general rank insignia.svg|75px]] [[Major General (United States)|Major General]] || 25 June 1841 || Regular Army
|-
|[[File:Union army lt gen rank insignia.jpg|75px]] [[Lieutenant General (United States)| Brevet Lieutenant General]] || 29 March 1847 || Regular Army
|}

* Captain, Light Artillery – May 3, 1808
* Lieutenant Colonel, 2nd Artillery – July 6, 1812
* Colonel, 2nd Artillery – March 12, 1813
* Colonel, Adjutant General – March 18 to July 18, 1813
* Brigadier General – March 9, 1814
* Brevet Major General – July 25, 1814
* Major General – June 25, 1841
* Brevet Lieutenant General – February 1855 (Date of rank: March 29, 1847)
* Retired – November 1, 1861

==Scott commemorated==

General Winfield Scott is one of very few US Army Generals to be honored on a US postage stamp. He was the first General to appear on a postage stamp after Washington, who was portrayed as a general on an [[:File:Washington 1861 Issue-90c.jpg|issue of 1861]]. The first Winfield Scott stamp issue was released to the public in 1870, four years after the General's death at West Point. The engraving depicts Scott in classic profile with an arc of 13 stars overhead and allegorical military weaponry at the bottom of the design -- surviving examples are very scarce and quite valuable today. General Scott was honored again on the [[:File:Army Navy 1937 issue10.jpg|Army issue of 1937]], one in a series of five commemorative stamps honoring notable Army heroes where Scott is depicted along with Andrew Jackson on the 2-cent stamp of this series.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson-Scott 1937 stamp, 3c, Quantities issued: 93.8 million issued; Scotts US Stamp Catalogue, Quantities Issued.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scotts US Stamp Catalogue (The ''Scotts US Stamp Catalogue'' and ''Winfield Scott'' have no association.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;mode=1&amp;tid=2029286 Smithsonian National Postal Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;

Scott is also honored in various other ways. Several statues of Scott exist, including the one located on a Street named after him in Washington DC.
&lt;center&gt;
{|
|[[File:Winfield Scott44 1870 issue-24c.jpg|thumb|190px|&lt;center&gt;~ First Winfield Scott stamp ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;Issue of 1870&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]
|[[File:Jackson Scott 1937 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|250px|&lt;center&gt;~ Jackson ~ Scott ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;Army issue of 1937&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]
|[[File:General Winfield Scott statue (45726769).jpg|thumb|[[Brevet Lt. General Winfield Scott|Statue of Winfield Scott]] on [[Scott Circle]] in Washington, D.C.]]
|}
&lt;/center&gt;
{{clear}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Arndt, Jochen S., &quot;The True Napoleon of the West: General Winfield Scott's Mexico City Campaign and the Origins of the U.S. Army's Combined-Arms Combat Division,&quot; ''Journal of Military History'', 76 (July 2012), 649–71.
* {{cite book |title=Commanding Generals and Chiefs of Staff: Portraits and Biographical Sketchs|chapterurl=http://www.history.army.mil/books/CG&amp;CSA/Scott-W.htm|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/CG&amp;CSA/CG-TOC.htm|first=William Gardner|last=Bell|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|year=2005|pages=78–79|chapter=Winfield Scott}}
* [[John Eisenhower|Eisenhower, John S.D.]], ''Agent of Destiny: The Life and Times of General Winfield Scott'', University of Oklahoma Press, 1999, ISBN 0-8061-3128-4.
* Elliott, Charles Winslow, [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=54828930 ''Winfield Scott: The Soldier and the Man''], 1937.
* {{cite book |title=The Life and Military Career of Winfield Scott Hancock |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9NNEAAAAIAAJ |last=Forney |first=John Wien |year=1880 |publisher=United States Book Company|location=New York |accessdate=July 6, 2009}}
* Johnson, Timothy D., ''Winfield Scott: The Quest for Military Glory'', University Press of Kansas, 1998, ISBN 0-7006-0914-8, a standard scholarly biography
* {{cite book|title=Illustrated life of General Winfield Scott; illustrated by D.H. Strother|url=https://archive.org/details/illustratedlifeoscot|last=Mansfield|first=Edward Deering|year=1847|publisher=A.S. Barnes &amp; Co.|location=New York}}
* Peskin, Allan, ''Winfield Scott and the Profession of Arms'', 2003, a standard scholarly biography

===Primary sources===
* {{cite book |title=Memoirs of Lieut.-General Scott, LL.D. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ACsOAAAAIAAJ&amp;vq=navy&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s |last=Scott |first=Winfield |year=1864 |publisher=Sheldon &amp; Company|location=New York |accessdate=July 6, 2009}}
* {{cite book |title=Scott's Militia Tactics; Comprising the Duty of Infantry, Light-Infantry and Riflemen, 2nd ed. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T6t9XQ1N54AC |last=Darrow |first=Pierce |author2=Winfield Scott |year=1821 |publisher=Oliver D. Cooke|location=Hartford |accessdate=July 6, 2009}}
* {{cite book |title=Infantry Tactics; Rules for the Exercise and Manoeuvres of the United States Infantry, Vol I |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vPEVAAAAYAAJ|last=Scott |first=Winfield |year=1835 |publisher=George Dearborn|location=New York}}; [https://books.google.com/books?id=dQAWAAAAYAAJ Vol II] and [https://books.google.com/books?id=B_MVAAAAYAAJ Vol III]
* {{cite book |title=The Campaign of General Scott in the Valley of Mexico |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rAsTAAAAYAAJ |last=Semmes |first=Raphael |year=1852 |publisher=Moore &amp; Anderson |location=Cincinnati}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Winfield Scott}}
* [http://www.cherokee.org/Culture/CulInfo/TOT/128/Default.aspx General Scott and the Trail of Tears]
* [http://www.cherokee.org/Culture/CulInfo/TOT/125/Default.aspx Letter to the Cherokee from Major General Scott]
* [http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-gre4.htm Origin of the phrase ''Great Scott!''.]
* [http://ngeorgia.com/people/scott.html Biography of General Winfield Scott]
* [http://www.riverboatdaves.com/riverboats/w-x-2.html#WSCOT ''Winfield Scott'' riverboat]
* {{Find a Grave|938}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Winfield Scott |sopt=t}}
* Wright, Marcus J., [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/17444/17444-h/17444-h.htm ''General Scott''], a biography at [[Project Gutenberg]]
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Scott, Winfield|short=x}}
* {{Cite NIE|wstitle=Scott, Winfield|year=1905}}
* [http://www.booknotes.org/Watch/102268-1/John+SD+Eisenhower.aspx ''Booknotes'' interview with John S.D. Eisenhower on ''Agent of Destiny: The Life and Times of General Winfield Scott'', April 19, 1998.]

{{S-start}}
{{S-mil}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Alexander Macomb, Jr.|Alexander Macomb]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Commanding General of the United States Army]]|years=1841–1861}}
{{s-aft|after=[[George B. McClellan]]}}
{{S-ppo}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Zachary Taylor]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[United States Whig Party#Candidates|Whig nominee]] for &lt;br&gt; [[President of the United States]]|years=[[United States presidential election, 1852|1852]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Millard Fillmore]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{USWhigPresNominees}}
{{Black Hawk War (1832)}}
{{US Army Chiefs of Staff}}
{{Heads of Government of the Mexican Federal District}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scott, Winfield}}
[[Category:1786 births]]
[[Category:1866 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Dinwiddie County, Virginia]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Mexican–American War]]
[[Category:American prisoners of war]]
[[Category:Burials at West Point Cemetery]]
[[Category:Congressional Gold Medal recipients]]
[[Category:College of William &amp; Mary alumni]]
[[Category:Members of the Aztec Club of 1847]]
[[Category:American people of the Black Hawk War]]
[[Category:Union Army generals]]
[[Category:United States Army generals]]
[[Category:United States presidential candidates, 1840]]
[[Category:United States presidential candidates, 1848]]
[[Category:United States presidential candidates, 1852]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the War of 1812]]
[[Category:People of the Utah War]]
[[Category:Virginia Whigs]]
[[Category:19th-century American politicians]]
[[Category:War of 1812 prisoners of war held by the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Whig Party (United States) presidential nominees]]
[[Category:People from West Point, New York]]
[[Category:Southern Unionists in the American Civil War]]</text>
      <sha1>6mr0sx5fsoqbmzb3grqhtqlcc93zvtj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
