<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Women in World War II</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42828596</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749858389</id>
      <parentid>749268932</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T15:09:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>27.4.6.213</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* India */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="63316">{{Women in warfare}}
[[File:Victory job (AWM ARTV00332).jpg|thumb|In many nations women were encouraged to join female branches of the armed forces or participate in industrial or farm work.]]
'''Women in World War II''' took on a variety of roles from country to country. World War II involved global conflict on an unprecedented scale; the absolute urgency of mobilizing the entire population made the expansion of the role of women inevitable. 
The domestic roles of women are covered in [[Home front during World War II]].

==World patterns==
The hard skilled labor of women was symbolized in the United States of America by the concept of [[Rosie the Riveter]], a woman factory laborer performing what was previously considered man's work. 
With this expanded horizon of opportunity and confidence, and with the extended skill base that many women could now give to paid and voluntary work, women's roles in World War II were even more extensive than in the First World War. By 1945, more than 2.2 million women were working in the war industries, especially in ammunition plants. They participated in the building of ships, aircraft, vehicles and weaponry. Women also worked on farms, drove trucks, provided logistic support for soldiers and entered professional areas of work that were previously the preserve of men.  In the Allied countries thousands of women enlisted as nurses serving in the front-line units. Thousands of others joined defensive militias at home and there was a great increase in the number of women serving for the military itself, particularly in the Soviet Union's Red Army.

Several hundred thousand women served in combat roles, especially in anti-aircraft units. The U.S. decided not to use women in combat because public opinion would not tolerate it.&lt;ref&gt;D'Ann Campbell, [http://americanhistoryprojects.com/downloads/ww2/combat.pdf online edition &quot;Women in Combat: The World War Two Experience in the United States, Great Britain, Germany, and the Soviet Union&quot;], ''[[Journal of Military History]]'' (April 1993), 57:301-323&lt;/ref&gt; However 400,000 women served in uniform in non-combat roles in the U.S. armed forces; 16 were killed by enemy fire.

Many women served in the resistances of [[French Resistance|France]], [[Italian Resistance|Italy]], and [[Polish resistance movement in World War II|Poland]], and in the British [[Special Operations Executive|SOE]] and American [[Office of Strategic Services|OSS]] which aided these.

Other women, called [[comfort women]], were forced into [[sexual slavery]] by the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] before and during World War II.

Approximately 2 million [[Jewish women in the Holocaust]] were killed, and the Nazis also killed other women who belonged to groups they were committing [[genocide]] against, such as women with disabilities and [[Roman people|Rom]] women.

==Comfort women==
[[Comfort women]] were women and girls forced into [[sexual slavery]] by the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] before and during [[World War II]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The Asian Women's Fund|title=Who were the Comfort Women?-The Establishment of Comfort Stations|work=Digital Museum The Comfort Women Issue and the Asian Women's Fund|publisher=The Asian Women's Fund|url=http://www.awf.or.jp/e1/facts-01.html|accessdate=August 8, 2014|archivedate=August 7, 2014|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140807180256/http://www.awf.or.jp/e1/facts-01.html|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The Asian Women's Fund|title=Hall I: Japanese Military and Comfort Women|work=Digital Museum The Comfort Women Issue and the Asian Women's Fund|publisher=The Asian Women's Fund|url=http://awf.or.jp/e1/facts-00.html|accessdate=August 12, 2014|archivedate=March 15, 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130315032343/http://awf.or.jp/e1/facts-00.html|deadurl=no|quote=The so-called 'wartime comfort women' were those who were taken to former Japanese military installations, such as comfort stations, for a certain period during wartime in the past and forced to provide sexual services to officers and soldiers.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Argibay|first=Carmen|title=Sexual Slavery and the Comfort Women of World War II|journal=Berkeley Journal of International Law|date=2003|url=http://scholarship.law.berkeley.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1242&amp;context=bjil}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name &quot;comfort women&quot; is a translation of the Japanese euphemism ''[[:ja:慰安婦|ianfu]]'' (慰安婦) and the similar Korean term ''[[:ko:위안부|wianbu]]'' (위안부).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OxiMJGs2NCQC&amp;lpg=PA189&amp;dq=%22comfort%20women%22%20euphemism%20ianfu&amp;pg=PA189#v=onepage&amp;q=%22comfort%20women%22%20euphemism%20ianfu&amp;f=false|title=Target of Opportunity &amp; Other War Stories|first=Robert |last=McKellar|publisher=AuthorHouse|year= 2011|isbn=1-4634-1656-3|quote=The term 'comfort women', which is a translation of the Japanese euphemism ''jugun ianfu'' ('military comfort women'), categorically refers to women of various ethnic and national backgrounds and social circumstances who became sexual laborers for Japanese troops before and during WWII.|page=189}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=GIHcaFVxXf0C&amp;pg=PA69&amp;dq=%22comfort+women%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22comfort%20women%22&amp;f=false|title=The Comfort Women: Sexual Violence and Postcolonial Memory in Korea and Japan|first=C. Sarah |last=Soh|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year= 2009|isbn=0-226-76777-9|page=69|quote=It referred to adult female (fu/bu) who provided sexual services to &quot;comfort and entertain&quot; (ian/wian) the warrior...}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ianfu'' is a euphemism for ''shōfu'' (娼婦) whose meaning is &quot;prostitute(s)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=b0UzAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%E6%85%B0%E5%AE%89%E5%A9%A6%E3%80%80%E5%A9%89%E6%9B%B2&amp;dq=%E6%85%B0%E5%AE%89%E5%A9%A6%E3%80%80%E5%A9%89%E6%9B%B2|trans_title=Attainder of modern history|first=Nobukatsu|last=Fujioka|publisher= Tokuma Shoten|year=1996|page=39|quote=''慰安婦は戦地で外征軍を相手とする娼婦を指す用語(婉曲用語)だった。'' (''Ianfu'' was a euphemism for the prostitutes who served for the Japanese expeditionary forces outside Japan)|script-title=ja:污辱の近現代史: いま、克服のとき|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimates vary as to how many women were involved, with numbers ranging from as low as 20,000 &lt;ref name=&quot;AWF_CW&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Asian Women'sFund|p=10|Ref=AWF-CW}}&lt;/ref&gt; to as high as 360,000 to 410,000, in Chinese sources;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DmVz_FRmrc8C&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=falseddd|title=The Missing Girls and Women of China, Hong Kong and Taiwan: A Sociological Study of Infanticide, Forced Prostitution, Political Imprisonment, &quot;Ghost Brides,&quot; Runaways and Thrownaways|first=Hua-Lun|last=Huang|publisher=McFarland|year=2012|isbn=0-7864-8834-4|quote=Although Ianfu came from all regions or countries annexed or occupied by Japan before 1945, most of them were Chinese or Korean.  Researchers at the Research Center of the Chinese Comfort Women Issue of Shanghai Normal University estimate that the total number of comfort women at 360,000 to 410,000.|page=206}}&lt;/ref&gt; the exact numbers are still being researched and debated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rose|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=W2nU1Xu0XdkC&amp;pg=PA88 88]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the women were from occupied countries, including [[Korea under Japanese rule|Korea]], [[Republic of China (1912–49)|China]], and the [[Philippines]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womenshistory.about.com/od/warwwii/a/comfort_women.htm |title=Women and World War II – Comfort Women |publisher=Womenshistory.about.com |accessdate=2013-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; although women from [[Burma]], [[Thailand]], [[French Indochina|Vietnam]], [[Malaysia]], [[Taiwan]] (then a [[Taiwan under Japanese rule|Japanese dependency]]), [[Indonesia]] (then the [[Dutch East Indies]]), [[East Timor]] (then [[Portuguese Timor]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Coop |first=Stephanie |date=23 Dec 2006 |title=Japan's Wartime Sex Slave Exhibition Exposes Darkness in East Timor |url=http://www.japanfocus.org/-Stephanie-Coop/2300 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110606151027/http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20061223f2.html |archivedate=6 June 2011|newspaper=Japan Times |accessdate=29 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=YOSHIDA |first=REIJI |date=April 18, 2007 |title=Evidence documenting sex-slave coercion revealed |url=http://www.etan.org/et2007/april/21/18evdenc.htm|newspaper=The Japan Times |accessdate=29 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and other Japanese-occupied territories were used for military &quot;comfort stations&quot;. Stations were located in Japan, China, the Philippines, Indonesia, then [[British Malaya|Malaya]], [[Thailand]], [[Burma]], [[New Guinea]], [[Hong Kong]], [[Macau]], and [[French Indochina]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Reuters|2007-03-05}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  A smaller number of women of European origin from the [[Netherlands]] and [[Australia]] were also involved.

According to testimony, young women from countries in Imperial Japanese custody were abducted from their homes. In many cases, women were also lured with promises of work in factories or restaurants; once recruited, the women were incarcerated in comfort stations in foreign lands.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshimi|2000|pp=100–101, 105–106, 110–111}};&lt;br /&gt;{{Harvnb|Fackler|2007-03-06|Ref=CITEREFNY Times2007-03-06}};&lt;br /&gt;{{Harvnb|BBC|2007-03-02}};&lt;br /&gt;{{Harvnb|BBC|2007-03-08}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
{{Main article|Australian women during World War II}}

Australian women played a larger role in World War II than they had done in [[World War I]]. Many women wanted to play an active role, and hundreds of voluntary women's auxiliary and paramilitary organisations had been formed by 1940. A shortage of male recruits forced the military to establish female branches in 1941 and 1942.

==Canada==
{{Main|Canadian women during the World Wars}}

[[File:Locomotive fast freight cleaning.png|thumb|right|300px|Women replaced men in many of the [[roundhouse]] jobs during World War II. Photo taken January, 1943.]]

When war began to look unavoidable in the late 1930s, Canadian women felt obligated to help the fight. In October 1938, the [[Women’s Royal Voluntary Service|Women’s Volunteer Service]] was established in [[Victoria, BC]]. Soon, all the provinces and territories followed suit and  similar volunteer groups were emerged.  “Husbands, brothers, fathers, boyfriends were all joining up, doing something to help win the war. Surely women could help as well!” &lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot;&gt;Gossage, Carolyn. ‘’Greatcoats and Glamour Boots’’. (Toronto:Dundurn Press Limited, 1991)&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition to the [[Red Cross]], several volunteer corps had designed themselves after auxiliary groups from Britain. These corps had uniforms, marching drills and a few had rifle training.  It soon was clear, that a unified governing system would be beneficial to the corps. The volunteers in British Columbia donated two dollars each to pay the expenses so a representative could talk to politicians in Ottawa. Although all of the politicians appeared sympathetic to the cause, it remained ‘premature’ in terms of national necessity.&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;

In June  1941, the [[Canadian Women’s Army Corps]] was established.  The women who enlisted would take over
*Drivers of light mechanical transport vehicles
*Cooks in hospitals and messes
*Clerks, typists, and stenographers at camps and training centres
*Telephone operators and messengers
*Canteen helpers&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;
On July 2, 1942 women were given permission to enlist in what would be known as the [[Canadian Women’s Auxiliary Air Force]].  Lastly the [[Royal Canadian Navy]] created the [[Women’s Royal Canadian Naval Service]] or the [[WRENS]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt; The WRENS were the only corps that were officially a part of their sanctioning body as a women’s division. This led to bureaucratic issues that would be solved most easily by absorbing the civilian corps governed by military organizations, into women’s divisions as soldiers.
According to the [[RCAF]] the following are the requirements of an enlisted woman:
#Must be at least 18 years of age, and younger than 41 years of age
#Must be of medical category A4B (equivalent of A1)
#Must be equal to or over 5 feet, and fall within the appropriate weight for her height, not being too far above or below the standard
#Must have a minimum education of entrance into high school
#Be able to pass the appropriate trades test
#Be of good character with no record of conviction for an indictable offence&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;	
Women would not be considered for enlistment if they were married and had children dependent on them. 
Training centres were required for all of the new recruits. They could not be sent to the existing centres as it was necessary that they be separated from male recruits. The Canadian Women’s Army Corps set up centres in [[Vermilion, Alberta]] and [[Kitchener, Ontario]]. [[Ottawa]] and [[Toronto]] were the locations of the training centres for the Canadian Women’s Auxiliary Air Force. The WRENS were outfitted in [[Galt, Ontario]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;
Each service had to come up with the best possible appeal to the women joining, for they all wanted them. In reality, the women went where their fathers, brothers and boyfriends were.&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;
Women had numerous reasons for wanting to join the effort; whether they had a father, husband, or brother in the forces, or simply felt the patriotic duty to help. One woman blatantly exclaimed that she could not wait to turn eighteen to enlist, because she had fantasies of assassinating Hitler.  Many women aged 16 or 17 lied about their age in order to enlist.  The United States would only allow women to join that were at least twenty-one. For their young female citizens, Canada was the logical option. Recruitment for the different branches of the Canadian Forces was set up in places like Boston and New York. Modifications were made to girls with US citizenship, having their records marked, “Oath of allegiance not taken by virtue of being a citizen of The United States of America.” &lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;

Women had to adhere to medical examinations, and fitness requirements as well as training in certain trades depending on the aspect of the armed forces they wanted to be a part of.  Enlisted women were issued entire uniforms minus the undergarments, which they would receive a quarterly allowance for.&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;

To be an enlisted woman during the creation stages was not easy. Besides the fact that everyone was learning as they went, they did not receive the support they needed from the male recruits. To begin with, women were initially paid two-thirds of what a man at the same level would make.&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ww2db.com/event/timeline/1942/ |title=1942 Timeline |publisher=WW2DB |accessdate=2011-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the war progressed the military leaders began to see the substantial impact the women could make. This was taken into account and the women received a raise to four-fifths of the wages of a man.&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot; /&gt; A female doctor however, would receive equal financial compensation to her male counterpart.   The negative reaction of men towards the female recruits was addressed in [[propaganda]] films. [[Canada Carries On#1943|Proudly She Marches]] and [[Wings on Her Shoulder]] were made to show the acceptance of female recruits, while showing the men that although they were taking jobs traditionally intended for men, they would be able to retain their femininity. .&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;

Other problems faced early on for these women were that of a more racial stature.  An officer of the [[Canadian Women's Army Corps|CWAC]] had to write to her superiors regarding whether or not a girl of “Indian nationality” would be objected for enlistment. Because of Canada’s large population of immigrants, German women also enlisted creating great animosity between recruits.&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;  The biggest difficulty was however the French-Canadian population.  In a document dated 25 November 1941, it was declared that enlisted women should ‘unofficially’ speak English. However, seeing the large number of capable women that this left out, a School of English was stabled for recruits in mid-1942. .&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt; In 1942, [[Mary Greyeyes|Mary Greyeyes-Reid]] became the first First Nations woman to join the [[Canadian Forces]].&lt;ref name=&quot;forces&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.forces.ca/en/page/aboriginals-93#aproudhistory-2 | title=Aboriginal Programs, A Proud History | publisher=[[Canadian Forces]] | accessdate=January 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was featured in photographs to represent native people in the forces, yet at the same time was not welcome in the barracks due to discrimination.&lt;ref name=&quot;legion&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://legionmagazine.com/en/index.php/2012/08/historical-record-corrected-after-nearly-70-years/ | title=Historical record corrected after nearly 70 years | publisher=[[Legion Magazine]] | date=August 10, 2012 | accessdate=January 25, 2013 | author=Adams, Sharon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Once in training, some women felt that they had made a mistake. Several women cracked under the pressure and were hospitalized. Other women felt the need to escape, and simply ran away. The easiest and fastest ticket home however was pregnancy. Women who found out that they were expecting were given a special, quickly executed, discharge.&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;

The women who successfully graduated from training had to find ways to entertain themselves to keep morale up. Softball, badminton, tennis, and hockey were among popular pastimes for recruits. .&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;

Religion was of a personal matter to the recruits. A minister of sorts was usually on site for services. For Jewish girls, it was custom that they were able to get back to their barracks by sundown on Sabbath and holidays; a [[Rabbi]] would be made available if possible. .&lt;ref name=&quot;gossage&quot; /&gt;

At the beginning of the war 600,000 women in Canada held permanent jobs in the private sector, by the peak in 1943 1.2 million women had jobs.&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot;&gt;[[Veterans Affairs Canada]], [http://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/remembrance/history/second-world-war/fact_sheets/women &quot;Women at War,&quot;] Government of Canada, 2013-08-02&lt;/ref&gt;  Women quickly gained a good reputation for their mechanical dexterity and fine precision due to their smaller stature.&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt; At home a woman could work as:
* Cafeteria workers
* Loggers or lumberjills
* Shipbuilders
* Scientists
* Munitions workers&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot; /&gt;

Women also had to keep their homes together while the men were away. “An Alberta mother of nine boys, all away at either war or factory jobs – drove the tractor, plowed the fields, put up hay, and hauled grain to the elevators, along with tending her garden, raising chickens, pigs, and turkeys, and canned hundreds of jars of fruits and vegetables.” &lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt;

In addition to physical jobs, women were also asked to cut back and ration. Silk and nylon were used for the war efforts, creating a shortage of stockings. Many women actually painted lines down the back of their legs to create the illusion of wearing the fashionable stockings of the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;fact&quot; /&gt;

==Finland==
Much like in the United Kingdom, the Finnish women took part in defence: nursing, air raid signaling, rationing and hospitalization of the wounded. Their organization was called [[Lotta Svärd]], where voluntary women took part in auxiliary work of the armed forces to help those fighting on the front. Lotta Svärd was one of the largest, if not the largest, voluntary group in World War II. They never fired guns (a rule among the Lottas).&lt;ref&gt;Charles Leonard Lundin, ''Finland in the Second World War'' (Indiana UP, 1957)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Germany==
{{See also|Jewish women in the Holocaust}}

On the eve of war 14.6 million German women were working, with 51% of women of working age (16–60 years old) in the workforce. Nearly six million were doing farm work, as Germany's agricultural economy was dominated by small family farms. 2.7 million worked in industry. When the German economy was mobilized for war it paradoxically led to a drop in female work participation, reaching a low of 41% before gradually climbing back to over 50% again. This still compares favorably with the UK and the USA, both playing catchup, with Britain achieving a participation rate of 41% of women of working age in 1944. However, in terms of women employed in war work, British and German female participation rates were nearly equal by 1944, with the United States still lagging. The difficulties the [[Third Reich]] faced in increasing the size of the work force was mitigated by reallocating labor to work that supported the war effort. High wages in war industries attracted hundreds of thousands, freeing up men for military duties. Prisoners of war were also employed as farmhands, freeing up women for other work.&lt;ref&gt;[[Adam Tooze]], ''The Wages of Destruction'' (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Third Reich had many roles for women, including combat. The [[SS]]-Helferinnen were regarded as part of the SS if they had undergone training at a Reichsschule SS but all other female workers were regarded as being contracted to the SS and chosen largely from [[Nazi concentration camps]].  Women also served in auxiliary units in the navy (Kriegshelferinnen), air force (Luftnachrichtenhelferinnen) and army (Nachrichtenhelferin).&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2003&quot;&gt;Gordon Williamson, ''World War II German Women's Auxiliary Services'' (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;historiography1055&quot;&gt;Karen Hagemann,  &quot;Mobilizing Women for War: The History, Historiography, and Memory of German Women's War Service in the Two World Wars,&quot; ''Journal of Military History'' (2011) 75#4 pp 1055-1094&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/review/1183 |title=Das SS-Helferinnenkorps: Ausbildung, Einsatz und Entnazifizierung der weiblichen Angehörigen der Waffen-SS 1942-1949 |publisher=Reviews in History |date=2011-12-05 |accessdate=2013-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5U5kXjVq6p0C&amp;pg=PA223&amp;lpg=PA223&amp;dq=ernst+sachs+children+of+the+ss&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=giOQ_SSjPJ&amp;sig=y8XHO3BXt8I3nrAgocKHOFM6j_U&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=V91cUcX_KIzcPZ3fgIAP&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=ernst%20sachs%20children%20of%20the%20ss&amp;f=false |title=Hitler's Children: The Hitler Youth and the SS |author=Gerhard Rempel |publisher=[[Google Books]] |date= |accessdate=2013-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hundreds of women auxiliaries (Aufseherin) served for the SS in the camps, the majority of which were at [[Ravensbrück]].&lt;ref&gt;Leila J. Rupp, ''Mobilizing Women For War: German and American Propaganda, 1939-1945'' (1979)&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the estimated six million Jews who were killed during the [[Holocaust]], 2 million of them were women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hedgepeth2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Hedgepeth|first=Sonja|title=Sexual Violence against Jewish Women during the Holocaust|date=2010|publisher=University Press of New England|location=Lebanon|page=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Nazis]] also committed mass murder of [[Romani people|Roma]] women (and men) at the [[Auschwitz concentration camp]], murdered women (and men) with disabilities in the [[Action T4|T4]] and other euthanasia operations, and murdered women (and men) as supposed partisans in many Soviet villages in 1943-1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;ushmm1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Women During the Holocaust|url=http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005176|accessdate=29 April 2014|author=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum}}&lt;/ref&gt; Besides the murders, women in the Holocaust were tortured in other ways such as rape, sexual harassment, getting beaten, being the center of [[Nazi human experimentation]]s, etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;ushmm1&quot;/&gt;

In 1944-45 more than 500,000 women were volunteer uniformed auxiliaries in the German armed forces (Wehrmacht). About the same number served in civil aerial defense, 400,000 volunteered as nurses, and many more replaced drafted men in the wartime economy.&lt;ref name=&quot;historiography1055&quot;/&gt;  In the Luftwaffe they served in combat roles helping to operate the anti—aircraft systems that shot down Allied bombers.  By 1945, German women were holding 85% of the billets as clericals, accountants, interpreters, laboratory workers, and administrative workers, together with half of the clerical and junior administrative posts in high-level field headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | first=D'Ann |last=Campbell | title=Women in Combat: The World War Two Experience in the United States, Great Britain, Germany, and the Soviet Union | journal = Journal of Military History | date=April 1993 | volume =57 |pages =301–323 | url = http://americanhistoryprojects.com/downloads/ww2/combat.pdf | doi=10.2307/2944060}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Germany had a very large and well organized nursing service, with four main organizations, one for Catholics, one for Protestants, the secular DRK (Red Cross) and the &quot;Brown Nurses,&quot; for committed Nazi women. Military nursing was primarily handled by the DRK, which came under partial Nazi control. Frontline medical services were provided by male medics and doctors. Red Cross nurses served widely within the military medical services, staffing the hospitals that perforce were close to the front lines and at risk of bombing attacks. Two dozen were awarded the Iron Cross for heroism under fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2003&quot;/&gt; In contrast, the brief historiography ''Nurses in Nazi Germany'' by Bronwyn Rebekah McFarland-Icke (1999) focuses on the dilemmas of German nurses forced to look the other way while their incapacitated patients were murdered.&lt;ref&gt;Bronwyn Rebekah McFarland-Icke, ''Nurses in Nazi Germany''  (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

==India==
In India, policies resembled those of Great Britain, except that women were not used in anti-aircraft units, and there was no conscription of women for munitions work.&lt;ref&gt;Yasmin Khan, ''The Raj At War: A People's History Of India's Second World War'' (2015)&lt;/ref&gt;

The official &quot;Women's Auxiliary Corps&quot; operated 1939 to 1947, with peak strength of 850 officers and 7,200 auxiliaries in the Indian army. A small naval section operated in the Royal Indian Navy.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Harfield, &quot;The Women's Auxiliary Corps (India),&quot; ''Journal of the Society for Army Historical Research'' 83, no 335 (Autumn 2005), pp 243-254&lt;/ref&gt;

The nationalist movements in India during the war split on military service.Mahatma Gandhi opposed fascism and on his advice youths from India join armed forces to fight with Germans along with allies.  

One faction of Congress led by [[Subhas Chandra Bose]] was so opposed that it cooperated with Nazi Germany, and actually enlisted soldiers who fought alongside Japanese soldiers him up against the British and Indians in Burma. The &quot;Rani of Jhansi Regiment&quot; involved these women in combat on behalf of the [[Indian National Army]]. It was active from 1943-45. Bose spent a good deal of effort on him developing anti-British anti-imperialist ideology designed to mobilize models of women as mothers and sisters in Indian tradition. Bose Argued that the direct involvement of women as necessary to achieve total independence of India from colonial powers. Bose articulated a modern definition of female heroism that involved combat. In actual practice, very few of his women soldiers were directly involved in combat; they largely had support roles in logistics and medical care.&lt;ref&gt;Carol Hills and Daniel C. Silverman, 1993. “Nationalism and Feminism in Late Colonial India: The Rani of Jhansi Regiment”, ''Modern Asian Studies'' 27#4 (1993) pp 741-760.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Joyce C. Lebra, ''Women Against the Raj: The Rani of Jhansi Regiment'' (Singapore: Institute of Southeast Asian Studies, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Italy==
In Italy women joined the anti-fascist resistance, and also served in the fascist army of Mussolini’s rump state that formed in 1943.  They did not serve in the main Italian army. Some 35,000 women (and 170,000 men)  joined in the Resistance. However the women ('staffetta' were used only as auxiliary support and were not allowed in senior ranks.   Most did cooking and laundry duty.   Some were guides, messengers, and couriers near the front lines. A few were attached to small attack groups of five or six men engaged in sabotage.  Some all-female units, engaged in civilian and political action.  The Germans aggressively tried to suppress them, sending 5000 to prison, deporting 3000 to Germany. About 650 died in combat or by execution.  On a much larger scale, non-military auxiliaries of the Catholic Centro Italiano Femminile (CIF) and the leftist Unione Donne Italiane (UDI) were new organizations that gave women political legitimacy after the war.&lt;ref&gt;Dan A. D'Amelio, &quot;Italian Women In The Resistance, World War II,&quot; ''Italian Americana,'' 19#2 (2001), 127-141.&lt;/ref&gt;).

Mussolini’s [[Italian Social Republic|Salo Republic]], a puppet state of the Germans, gave their women roles as &quot;birthing machines&quot; and as noncombatants in paramilitary units and police formations (Servizio Ausiliario Femminile).  The commander was the brigadier general Piera Gatteschi Fondelli.&lt;ref&gt;M.  Fraddosio, &quot;Woman and War: Aspects Of Womens Militancy During Fascism, From Civil Mobilization to the The Origins Of The Servizio-Ausiliario-Femminile in the Italian Social-Republic.&quot; ''Storia Contemporanea'' 20#6 (1989): 1105-1181.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Petra  Terhoeven, &quot;Frauen im Widerstand: Das Beispiel der Italienischen Resistenza&quot;, ''Zeitschrift für Geschichtswissenschaft,''  2004. 52#7 pp 608-625.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Poland==
[[File:Female soldiers 1939.JPG|thumb|right|A grave of three Polish female soldiers who were killed during the [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|Invasion of Poland]], 1939, among their colleagues interred at Warsaw's [[Powązki Cemetery]]]]
In occupied Poland, as elsewhere, women played an important role in the resistance movement, putting them in the front line. Their most important role was as couriers carrying messages between cells of the resistance movement and distributing news broadsheets and operating clandestine printing presses. During partisan attacks on [[Nazi]] forces and installations they served as scouts.

During the [[Warsaw Rising]] of 1944, female members of the [[Armia Krajowa|Home Army]] were couriers and medics, but many carried weapons and took part in the fighting. Among the more notable women of the Home Army was [[Wanda Gertz]] who created and commanded ''DYSK'' (Women's sabotage unit). For her bravery in these activities and later in the Warsaw Uprising she was awarded Poland's highest awards - [[Virtuti Militari]] and [[Polonia Restituta]].  One of the articles of the capitulation was that the German Army recognized them as full members of the armed forces and needed to set up separate [[Prisoner-of-war camp]]s to hold over 2000 women prisoners-of-war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ney-Krwawicz |first=Marek |url=http://www.polishresistance-ak.org/12%20Article.htm |title=Women Soldiers of the Polish Home Army |publisher=Polishresistance-ak.org |date= |accessdate=2013-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Romania==
Romanian women played a role in the [[Royal Romanian Air Force]]. Inspired by the Finnish Lotta Svärd, the Ministry of the Air set up a specialized [[air ambulance]] unit called the 108th Medevac Light Transport Squadron, better known as the [[White Squadron (Romania)|White Squadron]] (''Escadrila Albă''), which included mostly female pilots. The unit was active between 1940-1943, participated in the campaigns at [[Siege of Odessa|Odessa]] and [[Battle of Stalingrad|Stalingrad]] and rose to fame during the war as the only unit of its kind in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.mapn.ro/cpresa/13916_COMUNICAT-DE-PRESA | title=Comunicat nr. 183 | publisher=Romanian Ministry of National Defense | date=7 September 2012 | accessdate=12 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Romanian women also served as pilots in other transport and liaison units during the war. Captain Irina Burnaia, for example, commanded the Bessarabian Squadron between 1942-1944.

After the war and the Communist seizure of power in Romania, the White Squadron's service was largely ignored and its former members faded into obscurity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ligamilitarilor.ro/eroii-neamului/femeile-aviatoare-romance-escadrila-alba/ | title=Femeile -aviatoare românce – Escadrila Albă | date=28 September 2011 | accessdate=12 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, since the [[Romanian Revolution]] there has been a new wave of recognition of the female aviators, as exemplified by [[Mariana Drăgescu]]'s promotion to the rank of Commander (''Comandor'') in 2013.

==Soviet Union==
{{main|Soviet women in World War II}}
[[File:Klavdiya Kalugina.jpg|thumb|150px|Klavdiya Kalugina, one of the youngest female [[Soviet snipers]] (age 17 at the start of her military service in 1943)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iremember.ru/snayperi/kalugina-klavdiya-efremovna.html|title= Kalugina Klavdiya Yefremovna|publisher=Iremember.ru|accessdate=2011-01-10|language=ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The Soviet Union mobilized women at an early stage of the war, integrating them into the main army units, and not using the &quot;auxiliary&quot; status. Some 800,000 women served in the Soviet Armed Forces during the war, which is roughly 3 percent of total military personnel, mostly as medics.&lt;ref&gt;The United States Military Academy (2015). &quot;''[https://books.google.pl/books?id=2YDRCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA235&amp;lpg=PA235&amp;dq=soviet+union+in+world+war+ii+mobilized+millions&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=SLFYZOSVgb&amp;sig=3wn_pXltRtfdbvIwZ2MsAT_oPDM&amp;hl=pl&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjepLa75JXLAhWid5oKHR8SDxEQ6AEIRTAF#v=onepage&amp;q=soviet West Point History of World War II, Vol. 1]''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bernard A. Cook (2006). &quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=lyZYS_GxglIC&amp;pg=&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Women and war: a historical encyclopedia from antiquity to the present]''&quot;. ABC-CLIO. p.546. ISBN 1-85109-770-8&lt;/ref&gt; About 300,000 served in anti-aircraft units and performed all functions in the batteries—including firing the guns.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell 1993&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;K. Jean Cottam, &quot;Soviet Women in Combat in World War II: The Ground Forces and the Navy,&quot; ''International Journal of Women's Studies,'' 3, no. 4 (1980): 345-57;&lt;/ref&gt;  A small number were combat flyers in the Air Force.&lt;ref&gt;K. Jean Cottam, ''Soviet Airwomen in Combat in World War II'' (Manhattan, KS: Military Affairs/Aerospace Historian Publishing, 1983)&lt;/ref&gt;

==United Kingdom==

===Workplace===

When Britain went to war, [[Women in World War I#United Kingdom|as before in World War I]], previously forbidden job opportunities opened up for women. Women were called into the factories to create the weapons that were used on the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carruthers, Susan L 1947&quot;&gt;Carruthers, Susan L. &quot;'Manning the Factories': Propaganda and Policy on the Employment of Women, 1939-1947.&quot; ''History'' 75.244 (1990): 232-56. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Women took on responsibility of managing the home and became the heroines of the home front.  According to Carruthers, this industrial employment of women significantly raised women’s self-esteem as it allowed them to carry out their full potential and do their part in the war. During the war, women’s normative roles of “house wife” transformed into a patriotic duty.  As Carruther’s put it, the housewife has become a heroine in the defeat of Hitler (235).&lt;ref name=&quot;Carruthers, Susan L 1947&quot;/&gt; 
The roles of women shifting from domestic to masculine and dangerous jobs in the workforce made for important changes in workplace structure and society. During the Second World War, society had specific ideals for the jobs in which both women and men participated in. When women began to enter into the masculine workforce and munitions industries previously dominated by men, women’s segregation began to diminish. 
Increasing numbers of women were forced into industry jobs between 1940-1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley, Ian 2008&quot;&gt;Gazeley, Ian. &quot;Women’s pay in British Industry during the second world War.&quot; ''[[Economic History Review]]''. (2008): 651-671. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; As surveyed by the Ministry of Labour, the percentage of women in industrial jobs went from 19.75 per cent to 27 per cent from 1938-1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley, Ian 2008&quot;/&gt; It was very difficult for women to spend their days in factories, and then come home to their domestic chores and care-giving, and as a result, many women were unable to hold their jobs in the workplace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley, Ian 2008&quot;/&gt; Britain underwent a labour shortage where an estimated 1.5 million people were needed for the armed forces, and an additional 775,000 for munitions and other services in 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley, Ian 2008&quot;/&gt; It was during this ‘labour famine’ that propaganda aimed to induce people to join the labour force and do their bit in the war. Women were the target audience in the various forms of propaganda because they were paid substantially less than men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley, Ian 2008&quot;/&gt; It was of no concern whether women were filling the same jobs that men previously held. Even if women were replacing jobs with the same skill level as a man, they were still paid significantly less due to their gender.  In the engineering industry alone, the number of skilled and semi-skilled female workers increased from 75 per cent to 85 per cent from 1940-1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley, Ian 2008&quot;/&gt;  According to Gazeley, even though women were paid less than men, it is clear that women engaging in war work and taking on jobs preserved by men reduced industrial segregation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley, Ian 2008&quot;/&gt;

[[File:UK worker meets Roosevelt - Toni Frissell LC-F9-01-4211-92-2.jpg|thumb|portrait|right| A woman machinist talking with [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] during her goodwill tour of Great Britain in 1942]]
[[File:War Office Second World War Official Collection H28513.jpg|thumbnail|left|Pte Elizabeth Gourlay transmitting a radio message during the [[Second World War]]]]
In [[United Kingdom|Britain]], women were essential to the war effort. The contribution by civilian men and women to the British war effort was acknowledged with the use of the words [[Home front|&quot;Home Front&quot;]] to describe the battles that were being fought on a domestic level with rationing, recycling, and war work, such as in munitions factories and farms and Men were thus released into the military. Women were also recruited to work on the canals, transporting coal and munitions by barge across the UK via the inland waterways. These became known as the 'Idle Women', initially an insult derived from the initials IW, standing for Inland Waterways, which they wore on their badges, but the term was soon adopted by the women themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Reunion and plaque for the 'Idle Women', the Land Girls of the canals|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/3135333/Reunion-and-plaque-for-the-Idle-Women-the-Land-Girls-of-the-canals.html|accessdate=9 July 2013|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]|date=4 October 2008|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many women served with the Women's [[Auxiliary Fire Service]], the Women's Auxiliary Police Corps and in the [[Air Raid Precautions]] (later [[Civil Defence Corps|Civil Defence]]) services.  Others did voluntary welfare work with [[WRVS|Women's Voluntary Service for Civil Defence]] and the [[salvation Army]].

Women were &quot;drafted&quot; in the sense that they were conscripted into war work by the Ministry of Labour, including non-combat jobs in the military, such as the [[Women's Royal Naval Service]] (WRNS or &quot;Wrens&quot;), the [[Women's Auxiliary Air Force]] (WAAF or &quot;Waffs&quot;) and the [[Auxiliary Territorial Service]] (ATS). Auxiliary services such as the [[Air Transport Auxiliary]] also recruited women.&lt;ref&gt;Shelford Bidwell, ''The Women's Royal Army Corps'' (London, 1977)&lt;/ref&gt; In the early stages of the war such services relied exclusively on volunteers, however by 1941 conscription was extended to women for the first time in British history and around 600,000 women were recruited into these three organizations.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first=Jeremy |last=Crang | title= Come into the Army, Maud': Women, Military Conscription, and the Markham Inquiry | journal = Defence Studies | year= 2008| volume =8 |pages =381–395. EBSCOhost | doi=10.1080/14702430802252537}}&lt;/ref&gt; In these organizations women performed a wide range of jobs in support of the Army, [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) and [[Royal Navy]] both overseas and at home. These jobs ranged from traditionally feminine roles like cook, clerk and telephonist to more traditionally masculine duties like mechanic, [[armourer]], [[searchlight]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Brigstock 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Brigstock|first=Keith|title=Royal Artillery Searchlights|url=http://www.army.mod.uk/images/images-microsites/RA/RASearchlights-Text-Final.doc|publisher=Royal Artillery Historical Society|accessdate=23 June 2013|date=17 January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and anti- aircraft instrument operator.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; British women were not drafted into combat units, but could volunteer for combat duty in anti-aircraft units, which shot down German planes and V-1 missiles.&lt;ref&gt;See Campbell 1993&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Arthur Pile, ''Ack-Ack'' (London, 1949),&lt;/ref&gt; Civilian women joined the [[Special Operations Executive]] (SOE), which used them in high-danger roles as secret agents and underground radio operators in Nazi occupied Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Nigel West, ''Secret War: Story of S.O.E.'' (1993)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Propaganda===

British Women’s Propaganda was issued during the war in attempts to communicate to the house-wife that while keeping the domestic role, she must also take on a political role of patriotic duty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gingrich, Nadine 2005&quot;&gt;Gingrich, Nadine. &quot;&quot;Every Man Who Dies, Dies for You and Me. See You Be Worthy&quot;: The Image of the Hero as Rhetorical Motivation in Unofficial War Propaganda, 1914-1918&quot; ''[[War, Literature &amp; the Arts]]: An International Journal of the Humanities''. November 1, (2005): 108-117. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Propaganda was meant to eliminate all conflicts of personal and political roles and create a heroine out of the women. The implication with propaganda is that it asked women to redefine their personal and domestic ideals of womanhood and motivate them go against the roles that have been instilled in them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gingrich, Nadine 2005&quot;/&gt; 
The government struggled to encourage women to respond to posters and other forms of propaganda. One attempt to recruit women into the labour force was in one short film, ''My Father’s Daughter''. In this propaganda film a wealthy factory owner’s daughter begs to do her part in the war, but her father carries the stereotypical belief that women are meant to be caretakers and are incapable of such heavy work. When one foreman presents one of the most valuable and efficient workers in the factory as the daughter, the father’s prejudices are eliminated. The encouraging message of this short film is, “There’s Not Much Women Can’t Do.” &lt;ref name=&quot;Gingrich, Nadine 2005&quot;/&gt;

===Common roles===

The most common role of women in active service was that of a searchlight operator.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;&gt;De Groot, Gerard J. &quot;`I Love the Scent of Cordite in Your Hair': Gender Dynamics in Mixed Anti-Craft Batteries&quot;. ''History'' 82.265 (1997): 73-92. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, all of the members of the [[93rd Searchlights Regiment]] were females (Harris). Despite being limited in their roles, there was a great amount of respect between the men and women in the mixed batteries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;/&gt; In fact, one report states, “Many men were amazed that women could make adequate gunners despite their excitable temperament, lack of technical instincts, their lack of interest in aeroplanes and their physical weaknesses”.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;/&gt; While women still faced discrimination from some of the highly stereotypical older soldiers and officers who did not like women “playing with their guns”, women were still given rifle practice and taught to use anti-aircraft guns while serving in their batteries. They were told that this was in case the Germans invaded…however if that were to ever happen, they would be evacuated immediately.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;/&gt;).

Three quarters of women who entered the wartime forces were volunteers, compared to men who made up less than a third.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; Single or married women were eligible to volunteer in WAAF, ATS or WRNS and were required to serve throughout Britain as well as overseas if needed, however the age limits set by the services varied from each other. Generally women between 17 and 43 could volunteer and those under 18 required parental consent.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; After applying, applicants had to fulfill other requirements, including an interview and medical examination; if they were deemed fit to serve then they were enrolled for the duration of the war. WRNS was the only service that offered an immobile branch which allowed women to live in their homes and work in the local naval establishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; WRNS was the smallest of the three organizations and as a result was very selective with their candidates. Of the three organizations, WAAF was the most preferred choice; the second being WRNS. ATS was the largest of the three organizations and was least favoured among women because it accepted those who were unable to get into the other forces.  ATS had also developed a reputation of promiscuity and poor living conditions, many women also saw the khaki uniform unappealing and as a result caused women to favour WRNS and WAAF over ATS.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.atsremembered.org.uk/servicedress.htm dress]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Limitations===

Whilst women were limited in some of their roles, they were expected to perform to the same standard as a male soldier performing the same role, and although they could not participate in frontline combat, still manned anti-aircraft guns and defences which actively engaged hostile aircraft above Britain. Women went through the same military training, lived in the same conditions and did almost the same jobs as men, with the exception of not being able to participate in front-line combat. This small but important distinction meant that women did not tend to be nominated for medals of valour or bravery, because they were only awarded for “active operations against enemy in the field”, which women could not take part in.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;/&gt;

Women were also distinct because of the titles by which they were addressed in the army, although these tended to be no different from their male counterparts. They wore the same rank insignia as their male counterparts. Many members of the ATS were respected by the units they were attached to despite their different insignia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;/&gt; The only major difference between an ATS member and a male member of the Regular Army was discipline: a woman was not allowed to be court marshalled unless she herself chose to be. The women in the service were also under the authority of the women officers of the ATS, instead of the male officers they served directly under. This meant any disciplinary action was entirely in the hands of the ATS, removing male influence from the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;/&gt;

===Volunteerism===
Despite their obvious distinctions from men, women were eager to volunteer. Many of the servicewomen came from restricted backgrounds; therefore they found the army liberating.&lt;ref name=&quot;Groot, Gerard J 1997&quot;/&gt; Other reasons women volunteered included escaping unhappy homes or marriages, or to have a more stimulating job. The overwhelming reason for joining the army, though, was patriotism. As in World War I, Great Britain was in a patriotic fervour throughout World War II to protect itself from foreign invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crang, Jeremy A 2008&quot;&gt;Crang, Jeremy A. &quot;'Come into the Army, Maud': Women, Military Conscription, and the Markham Inquiry.&quot; Defence Studies 8.3 (2008): 381-95. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Women, for the first time, were given the opportunity to help in their native land’s defense, which explains the high number of female volunteers at the beginning of the war. Even [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Princess Elizabeth]] was a driver for the Second Subaltern Windsor Unit, having joined to do her part in the protection of the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crang, Jeremy A 2008&quot;/&gt; Despite the overwhelming response to the call for female volunteers, some women refused to join the forces; many were unwilling to give up the civilian job they had, and others had male counterparts that were unwilling to let them go (Crang 384). Others felt that war was still a man’s job, and not something women should be involved in.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crang, Jeremy A 2008&quot;/&gt; 
Similar to the men’s forces, women’s forces were mostly volunteer throughout the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crang, Jeremy A 2008&quot;/&gt; When women’s conscription did come into effect, however, it was highly limited. For example, married women were exempt from any obligation to serve unless they chose to do so, and those who were called could opt to serve in civil defense (the home front).&lt;ref name=&quot;Crang, Jeremy A 2008&quot;/&gt;

During the war, approximately 487,000 women volunteered for women’s services; 80,000 for WRNS, 185,000 for WAAF and 222,000 for ATS.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; By 1941 the demands of the wartime industry called for women’s services to be expanded so that more men could be relieved of their previous positions and take on more active roles on the battle field.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; Of all the women’s services, ATS needed the greatest number of new applicants; however due to ATS’ lack of popularity, they were unable to gain the estimated 100,000 new volunteers needed.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; To try and change women’s opinions on ATS, living conditions were improved and a new more flattering uniform was made. In 1941 the ''Registration for Employment Order'' was introduced in hopes of getting more women enrolled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Little&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first= Stephen |last=Little | title= Shadow Factories, Shallow Skills? an Analysis of Work Organisation in the Aircraft Industry in the Second World War | journal = [[Labor History (journal)|Labor History]] | year= 2011| volume =52 |pages =193–216 EBSCOhost | doi=10.1080/0023656x.2011.571476}}&lt;/ref&gt; This act could not force women to join the forces, but instead required women ages 20–30 to try to find employment through labour exchanges and provide information on their current employment and family situations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Little&quot; /&gt; Those who were deemed eligible were persuaded into the war industry because the Ministry of Labour did not have the power to force.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; Propaganda was also used to persuade women into the women's services. [http://content.lib.washington.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/posters&amp;CISOPTR=7 poster] By the end of 1941, ATS had only gained 58,000 new workers, falling short of expectations.[[Ernest Bevin]] then called for conscription and by late 1941 with the ''National Service Act'' it became compulsory for women ages 20–30 to join military service.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; Married women were exempt from conscription, but those who were eligible had the option to work in war industry or civil defense if they did not want to join one of the women services.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first= Ian |last=Gazeley | title= Women's Pay in British Industry during the Second World War | journal = Economic History Review | year= 2008| volume =61 |pages =651–671 EBSCOhost | doi=10.1111/j.1468-0289.2007.00412.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women were able to request which force they wished to join but most women were put into ATS because of its need for new applicants.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt; The National Service Act was repealed in 1949 but by 1944 women were no longer being called up for service because relying on volunteers was thought to be enough to complete the required tasks during the final stages of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;crang&quot; /&gt;

Women also played an important role in British industrial production during the war, in areas such as metals, chemicals, [[munitions]], shipbuilding and engineering. At the beginning of the war in 1939 17.8% of women made up employment in these industries and by 1943 they made up 38.2%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hart&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first= Robert |last=Hart | title= Women Doing Men’s Work and Women Doing Women’s Work: Female Work and Pay in British Wartime Engineering | journal = [[Explorations in Economic History]]| year= 2007| volume =44 |pages =114–130 EBSCOhost | doi=10.1016/j.eeh.2005.10.005}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the start of the war there was an urgent need to expand the country’s labour force and women were seen as a source of factory labour. Before the war women in industrial production were exclusively on assembly, which was seen as cheap and undemanding work but during the war women were needed in other areas in the production process that were previously done by men such as Lathe operators.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruley&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first= Sue |last=Bruley | title= A New Perspective on Women Workers in the Second World War: The Industrial Diary of Kathleen Church-Bliss and Elsie Whiteman | journal = Labour History Review| year= 2003| volume =68 |pages =217–234 EBSCOhost}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ministry of Labour created training centres that gave an introduction to the engineering process, and by 1941 women were allowed entrance as the importance of the engineering industry grew and became a large source of female employment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruley&quot; /&gt; Areas such as aircraft manufacture, light and heavy general engineering and motor vehicle manufacturing all saw an increase in female employment during the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hart&quot; /&gt; Aircraft production saw the largest rise in female employment as it rose from 7% in 1935 to 40% in 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruley&quot; /&gt; At the start of the war men who were already in engineering were prevented from going to war because engineering was seen as an important industry to war production but in 1940 there became a need for more female workers to supply the necessary labour for factory expansion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley&quot; /&gt; By 1941 with the shortage of skilled labour the ''Essential Workers Order'' was introduced which required all skilled workers to register and prevented workers from quitting from jobs that were deemed essential to the war effort without agreement from a National Service Officer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley&quot; /&gt; The ''Registration for the Employment Order'' in 1941 and the ''Women of Employment Order'' in 1942 also attempted to get more women into the workforce. The Women of Employment Order required women ages 18–45 to register for labour exchanges and by 1943 the maximum age was raised to 50, which brought an additional 20,000 women into the workforce. Aircraft production was given the top labour priority and many women were diverted into it with some even being transferred from agricultural production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Little&quot; /&gt;

===Interpretation of aerial photographs===

One of the most important roles within the forces that women occupied during the war was that of interpreting aerial photographs taken by British spy planes over Allied Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Downing, Taylor. &quot;Spying from the Sky.&quot; ''[[History Today]]'' 61.11 (2011): 10-16. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; There was equality in this work that was not found anywhere else during the war: women were considered equal to men in this field.&lt;ref name=&quot;Downing, Taylor 2011&quot;&gt;Downing, Taylor. &quot;Spying from the Sky.&quot; ''History Today'' 61.11 (2011): 10-16. Web&lt;/ref&gt; Women played an important role in the planning of [[D-Day]] in this capacity-they analyzed the photos of the [[Normandy]] Coast and decided which beaches the troops landed on and which sections. Women as photo analysts also participated in the biggest intelligence coup of the war-the discovery of the German [[V1 flying bomb]]. The participation of women allowed these bombs to be destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Downing, Taylor 2011&quot;/&gt;

Although many women were doing jobs that men had previously done during the war, there were still pay distinctions between the two sexes. Equal pay was rarely achieved as employers wanted to avoid labour costs. Skilled work was often broken down into smaller tasks and labelled skilled or semi-skilled and then paid according to women's pay rates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruley&quot; /&gt; Women who were judged to be doing ‘men’s work’ were paid more than women who were thought to be doing ‘women’s work’ and the employers' definition of this varied regionally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Little&quot; /&gt; Women were receiving closer wages to their male counterparts; however despite the government's expressed intentions, women continued to be paid less than men for equivalent work and were segregated in terms of job description, status, and the hours they put in.&lt;ref name=&quot;Little&quot; /&gt; In 1940 Ernest Bevin persuaded engineering employers and unions to give women equal pay to men since they were taking on the same tasks that men previously had; this became the ''Extended Employment of Women Agreement''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hart&quot; /&gt; Generally, pay increases depended on the industry; industries that were dominated by women before the war, like textiles and clothing, saw no changes in pay. However the gap between male and female earnings narrowed by 20-24% in metals, engineering and vehicle building and by 10-13% in chemicals, which were all deemed important to the war effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeley&quot; /&gt; Overtime hours also differed, with women getting 2–3 hours and men 9-10 a week. Women’s hours were still regulated because of their responsibilities to take care of their family and household.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hart&quot; /&gt;

===Queen Elizabeth II===
In February 1945, [[Queen Elizabeth II]] joined the [[Auxiliary Territorial Service|Women's Auxiliary Territorial Service]] as an honorary second [[Auxiliary Territorial Service#Ranks|subaltern]] with the [[service number]] of 230873.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette| issue=36973| date=6 March 1945| startpage=1315| supp=yes| accessdate=5 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-war===

Post-war, women were returned to many of the mundane jobs they occupied before the war started. Where once the army represented an escape from domestic life and liberty, it now returned to the male-dominated field it was before the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1997&quot;&gt;De Groot, Gerard J. &quot;`I Love the Scent of Cordite in Your Hair': Gender Dynamics in Mixed Anti-Craft Batteries&quot;. ''History'' 82.265 (1997): 73-92. Web&lt;/ref&gt; Women who served in the batteries as gunners and searchlight-operators became secretaries and clerks. &quot;Demob (demobilisation) was a big disappointment to a lot of us. It was an awful and wonderful war. I wouldn't have missed it for anything; some of the friends we made were forever” one female recounted after being dismissed from service to return to her normal job. Married women were released from service sooner at the end of the war, so they could return home before their husbands to ensure the home was ready when he returned from the front.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1997&quot;/&gt; Despite being largely unrecognised for their wartime efforts in the forces, the participation of women in World War II allowed for the founding of permanent women’s forces. Britain instituted these permanent forces in 1949, and the Women’s Voluntary Services are still a standing reserve force today.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, Carol. &quot;Women Under Fire in World War Two&quot;. February 17, 2011.Web. February 17, 2013 .&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States==
See [[American women in World War II]]

See [[Latinas and World War II]]

==Yugoslavia==
===Yugoslav Partisans===
 {{main|Women in the Yugoslav Partisans}}
Tito's [[Yugoslav National Liberation Movement]] claimed 6,000,000 civilian supporters; its two million women formed the [[Antifascist Front of Women]] (AFŽ), in which the revolutionary coexisted with the traditional. The AFŽ managed schools, hospitals and even local governments.  About 100,000 women served with 600,000 men in Tito's Yugoslav National Liberation Army. It stressed its dedication to women's rights and gender equality and used the imagery of traditional folklore heroines to attract and legitimize the partizanka.&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Jancar, &quot;Women in the Yugoslav National Liberation Movement: An Overview,&quot; ''Studies in Comparative Communism'' (1981) 14#2 pp 143-164.&lt;/ref&gt;  After the war women were relegated to traditional gender roles, but Yugoslavia is unique as its historians paid extensive attention to women's roles in the resistance, until the country broke up in the 1990s. Then the memory of the women soldiers faded away.&lt;ref&gt;Vesna Drapac, &quot;Resistance and the Politics of Daily Life in Hitler's Europe: The Case of Yugoslavia in a Comparative Perspective,&quot; ''[[Aspasia (journal)|Aspasia]]'' 2009 3: 55-78&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Jancar-Webster, ''Women and Revolution in Yugoslavia 1941-1945'' (1990)&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* Batinić, Jelena. ''Women and Yugoslav Partisans: A History of World War II Resistance''. (2015) ISBN 978-1107091078
* Binney, Marcus. ''The Women Who Lived for Danger: The Agents of the Special Operations Executive''. (2003) 
* Brayley, Martin. ''World War II Allied Women's Services'' (Osprey Publishing, 2001) short guide to units and uniforms.
* Campbell, D'Ann. &quot;The Women of World War II&quot; in Thomas W. Zeiler, and Daniel M. DuBois, eds. ''A Companion to World War II'' (2 vol 2015) 2:717-38
*  Cook, Bernard A. ''Women and war: a historical encyclopedia from antiquity to the present'' (ABC-CLIO  2006)
* Cottam, K. Jean. &quot;Soviet Women in Combat in World War II: The Ground Forces and the Navy,&quot; ''International Journal of Women's Studies,'' 3#4 (1980): 345-57
* Diamond, Hanna. ''Women and the Second World War in France, 1939-1948: choices and constraints'' (Routledge, 2015).
* Gossage, Carolyn and Roberta Bondar. ''Greatcoats and Glamour Boots: Canadian Women at War, 1939-1945''. (2001) ISBN 978-1550023688
* Lower, Wendy. ''Hitler's Furies: German Women in the Nazi Killing Fields''. (2014) ISBN 978-0544334496
* [[Elizabeth Peet McIntosh|Elizabeth McIntosh]]. ''Sisterhood of Spies: The Women of the OSS''. (2009) ISBN 978-1591145141
* Monahan, Evelyn and Rosemary Neidel-Greenlee. ''And If I Perish: Frontline U.S. Army Nurses in World War II''. (2004) ISBN 978-1400031290
* [[Anne Noggle]]; Christine A. White. ''A Dance with Death: Soviet Airwomen in World War II''. (2001) ISBN 978-1585441778
* Ofer, Dalia and Lenore J. Weitzman. ''Women in the Holocaust''. (1998) ISBN 978-0300073546
* Soderbergh, Peter. ''Women Marines: The World War II Era''. (1992) ISBN 978-0275941314, on US Marines
* Yoshimi, Yoshiaki, translation by Suzanne O'Brien. ''Comfort Women. Sexual Slavery in the Japanese Military During World War II''. (2002) ISBN 0-231-12033-8

{{World War II}}

==External links==
* [https://usnwcarchive.org/items/browse?collection=25 Women in World War II Oral Histories, (American) Naval Historical Collection]

[[Category:Women in World War II|*]]</text>
      <sha1>8ftbgovcon0qobomymnzlsrwpxcre7w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
