<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Wounded Knee Massacre</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>209886</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749648331</id>
      <parentid>749648137</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-15T14:05:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>150.176.165.214</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52097">{{Distinguish|Wounded Knee incident}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2016}}
{{Infobox civilian attack
| title = Wounded Knee Massacre
| partof = the [[Ghost Dance War]] and the [[Sioux Wars]][[File:Woundedknee1891.jpg|300px]]
|caption=[[Mass grave]] for the dead Lakota after the conflict at Wounded Knee Creek
| location=[[Wounded Knee Creek]], [[South Dakota]]
| target = [[Miniconjou]] [[Lakota people|Lakota]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Hunkpapa]] [[Lakota people|Lakota]]
| coordinates = 
| date = 29 December 1890
| time = 
| timezone = 
| type = 
| fatalities = 150-300 killed
* 98 men
* 65 women
* 24 children&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Plains Humanities: Wounded Knee Massacre|url=http://plainshumanities.unl.edu/encyclopedia/doc/egp.war.056|accessdate=9 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Josephy 1990&quot; /&gt;
| victims = 
| injuries = 52 wounded (7 fatally)
| perpetrators = [[United States Army]]
| assailants = 500 effectives:
&lt;br /&gt;[[7th U.S. Cavalry]]:
&lt;br /&gt;438 troopers&lt;ref&gt;Utley, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;22 artillerymen with four [[M1875 Mountain Gun|1.65–inch gun]]s
&lt;br /&gt;30 Oglala Indian scouts
| susperps = &lt;!-- or | susperp = --&gt;
| weapons = 
| numparts = &lt;!-- or | numpart = --&gt;
| dfens = &lt;!-- or | dfen = --&gt;
| motive = 
| inquiry = 
| coroner = 
| accused = 
| convicted = 
| verdict = 
| convictions = 
| charges = 
| litigation = 
| website = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
| module =
}}
{{Ghost Dance War}}

The '''Wounded Knee Massacre''' occurred on December 29, 1890,&lt;ref name=nps&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tps.cr.nps.gov/nhl/detail.cfm?ResourceId=540&amp;ResourceType=Site|title=National Historic Landmarks Program: Wounded Knee|publisher=[[National Park Service]]|accessdate=10 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; near [[Wounded Knee Creek]] ([[Lakota language|Lakota]]: ''Čhaŋkpé Ópi Wakpála'') on the [[Lakota people|Lakota]] [[Pine Ridge Indian Reservation]] in the U.S. state of [[South Dakota]].

The previous day, a detachment of the [[7th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|U.S. 7th Cavalry Regiment]] commanded by Major [[Samuel Whitside|Samuel M. Whitside]] intercepted [[Spotted Elk]]'s band of [[Miniconjou]] Lakota and 38 [[Hunkpapa]] Lakota near [[Porcupine Butte]] and escorted them {{convert|5|miles}} westward to Wounded Knee Creek, where they made camp. The remainder of the 7th Cavalry Regiment, led by Colonel [[James W. Forsyth]], arrived and surrounded the encampment. The regiment was supported by a battery of four [[M1875 Mountain Gun|Hotchkiss mountain gun]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last =Liggett| first = Lorie | title = Wounded Knee Massacre&amp;nbsp;– An Introduction| publisher = Bowling Green State University| year= 1998| url = http://www.bgsu.edu/departments/acs/1890s/woundedknee/WKIntro.html| accessdate =2 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the morning of December 29, the troops went into the camp to disarm the Lakota. One version of events claims that during the process of disarming the Lakota, a deaf tribesman named [[Black Coyote]] was reluctant to give up his rifle, claiming he had paid a lot for it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Randy Parsons |url=http://www.lastoftheindependents.com/wounded.htm |title=The Wounded Knee Massacre&amp;nbsp;– December 1890 |publisher=Lastoftheindependents.com |date=
 |accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A scuffle over the rifle ensued and by the time it was over, more than 150 men, women, and children of the Lakota had been killed and 51 were wounded (4 men and 47 women and children, some of whom died later); some estimates placed the number of dead at 300.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; Twenty-five soldiers also died, and 39 were wounded (6 of the wounded later died).&lt;ref&gt;''Wounded Knee &amp; the Ghost Dance Tragedy'' by Jack Utter, p. 25 Publisher: National Woodlands Publishing Company; 1st edition (April 1991) Language: English ISBN 0-9628075-1-6&lt;/ref&gt; At least twenty soldiers were awarded the [[Medal of Honor]].&lt;ref name=JerryGreen&gt;{{cite web| last = Green| first = Jerry| title = The Medals of Wounded Knee| publisher = Nebraska State Historical Society History| year= 1994| url = http://nebraskahistory.org/publish/publicat/history/full-text/NH1994MedalsWKnee.pdf| website= Nebraska State Historical Society, also available in Nebraska History #75, pp. 200–208 | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, the [[National Congress of American Indians]] passed two resolutions condemning the awards and called on the U.S. government to rescind them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Congress&quot;/&gt; The [[Wounded Knee Battlefield|site of the battlefield]] has been designated a [[National Historic Landmark]].&lt;ref name=nps/&gt; In 1990, both [[House (legislature)|houses]] of the [[U.S. Congress]] passed a [[Resolution (law)|resolution]] formally expressing &quot;deep regret&quot; for the massacre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=AP |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/10/29/us/congress-adjourns-century-afterward-apology-for-wounded-knee-massacre.html |title=CONGRESS ADJOURNS - Century Afterward, Apology For Wounded Knee Massacre |location=Pine Ridge Indian Reservation (Sd); United States |publisher=NYTimes.com |date=29 October 1990 |accessdate=2016-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
[[File:Ghost dance.jpg|thumb|right|The Ghost Dance as depicted]]
In the years leading up to the conflict, the [[U.S. government]] had continued to seize Lakota lands.  The once-large [[American bison|bison]] herds (an [[Plains Indians|indigenous peoples]]' [[Great Plains]] staple) had been hunted to near-extinction by [[Great Plains#Early European settlements on the Great Plains|European settlers]].  Treaty promises&lt;ref&gt;Hall, Kermit L (ed.), ''The Oxford Guide to the Supreme Court of the United States,'' Oxford Press, 1992; section: &quot;Native Americans,&quot; p. 580 ISBN 0-19-505835-6&lt;/ref&gt; to protect reservation lands from encroachment by settlers and gold miners were not implemented as agreed. As a result, there was unrest on the reservations.&lt;ref&gt;To this day, the Sioux have refused to accept compensation for the Black Hills land seized from them. A 1980 Supreme Court decision (''[[United States v. Sioux Nation of Indians]]'') ruled the taking was illegal and awarded compensation, increased by interest to $757 million, but not the return of the land which the Sioux sought. The Lakota have refused to take the money, demanding instead the return of the land.&lt;/ref&gt;
During this time, news spread among the reservations of a [[Paiute people|Paiute]] prophet named [[Wovoka]], founder of the [[Ghost Dance]] religion. He had a vision that the Christian [[Messiah]], [[Jesus Christ]], had returned to Earth in the form of a Native American.&lt;ref name=pbs&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/weta/thewest/people/s_z/wovoka.htm &quot;Wovoka.&quot;] ''PBS: New Perspectives on the West.'' (retrieved 6 August 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Wovoka, the Messiah would raise all the Native American believers above the earth. During this time, the white man would disappear from Native lands, the ancestors would lead them to good hunting grounds, the buffalo herds and all the other animals would return in abundance, and the ghosts of their ancestors would return to Earth&amp;nbsp;— hence the word ''ghost'' in &quot;Ghost Dance&quot;. They would then return to earth to live in peace. All this would be brought about by performance of the slow and solemn Ghost Dance, performed as a shuffle in silence to a slow, single drumbeat. [[Lakota people|Lakota]] ambassadors to [[Wovoka]], [[Kicking Bear]] and [[Short Bull, Arnold|Short Bull]] taught the Lakota that while performing the Ghost Dance, they would wear special [[Ghost Dance shirt]]s as seen by [[Black Elk]] in a vision. Kicking Bear said the shirts had the power to repel bullets.&lt;ref name=pbs/&gt;

American settlers were alarmed by the sight of the many Great Basin and [[Plains tribes]] performing the Ghost Dance, worried that it might be a prelude to armed attack. Among them was the U.S. Indian agent at the [[Standing Rock Agency]] where Chief [[Sitting Bull]] lived. United States officials decided to take some of the chiefs into custody in order to quell what they called the &quot;Messiah craze&quot;. The military first hoped to have [[Buffalo Bill]]&amp;nbsp;— a friend of Sitting Bull&amp;nbsp;— aid in the plan, to reduce the chance of violence. [[Standing Rock]] agent [[James McLaughlin (Indian agent)|James McLaughlin]] overrode the military and sent the Indian police to arrest Sitting Bull.

On December 15, 1890, 40 Native American policemen arrived at Sitting Bull's house to arrest him. Crowds gathered in protest, and the first shot was fired when Sitting Bull tried to pull away from his captors, killing the officer who had been holding him. Additional shots were fired, resulting in the deaths of Sitting Bull, eight of his supporters, and six policemen. After Sitting Bull's death, 200 members of his Hunkpapa band, fearful of reprisals, fled Standing Rock to join Chief [[Spotted Elk]] (later known as &quot;Big Foot&quot;) and his Miniconjou band at the [[Cheyenne River Indian Reservation]].

Spotted Elk and his band, along with 38 Hunkpapa, left the Cheyenne River Reservation on December 23 to journey to the [[Pine Ridge Indian Reservation]] to seek shelter with [[Red Cloud]].&lt;ref&gt;Viola, Herman J. ''Trail to Wounded Knee: The Last Stand of the Plains Indians 1860–1890''. Washington, D.C.: National Geographic Society, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

Former Pine Ridge Indian agent [[Valentine McGillycuddy|Valentine T. McGillycuddy]] was asked his opinion of the 'hostilities' surrounding the Ghost Dance movement, by General [[Leonard Wright Colby]], commander of the [[Nebraska National Guard]] (portion of letter dated Jan. 15, 1891):&lt;ref&gt;Annual report, Part 2 By Smithsonian Institution. Bureau of American Ethnology, [[John Wesley Powell]], Matthew Williams, pp. 831–833 (1896)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;As for the 'Ghost Dance' too much attention has been paid to it. It was only the symptom or surface indication of a deep rooted, long existing difficulty; as well treat the eruption of small pox as the disease and ignore the constitutional disease.&quot;

&quot;As regards disarming the Sioux, however desirable it may appear, I consider it neither advisable, nor practicable. I fear it will result as the theoretical enforcement of prohibition in Kansas, Iowa and Dakota; you will succeed in disarming and keeping disarmed the friendly Indians because you can, and you will not succeed with the mob element because you cannot.&quot;

&quot;If I were again to be an Indian agent, and had my choice, I would take charge of 10,000 armed Sioux in preference to a like number of disarmed ones; and furthermore agree to handle that number, or the whole Sioux nation, without a white soldier. Respectfully, etc., V.T. McGillycuddy.

&quot;P.S. I neglected to state that up to date there has been neither a Sioux outbreak or war. No citizen in Nebraska or Dakota has been killed, molested or can show the scratch of a pin, and no property has been destroyed off the reservation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The ghost-dance religion and the Sioux outbreak of 1890'', by James Mooney, p. 833&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; margin-left:1em; float:right&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background:#b0cce5;&quot; colspan=&quot;54&quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''General Miles's telegram'''&lt;/div&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;background:#fbf4ce;&quot; colspan=&quot;54&quot;|[[File:Nelson A. Miles by Brands Studios, 1898.jpg|thumb|right|140px|[[Nelson A. Miles]]]]
General Miles sent this telegram from Rapid City to General [[John Schofield]] in Washington, D.C., on December 19, 1890:

&quot;The difficult Indian problem cannot be solved permanently at this end of the line. It requires the fulfillment of Congress of the treaty obligations that the Indians were entreated and coerced into signing. They signed away a valuable portion of their reservation, and it is now occupied by white people, for which they have received nothing.&quot;

&quot;They understood that ample provision would be made for their support; instead, their supplies have been reduced, and much of the time they have been living on half and two-thirds rations. Their crops, as well as the crops of the white people, for two years have been almost total failures.&quot;

&quot;The dissatisfaction is wide spread, especially among the Sioux, while the Cheyennes have been on the verge of starvation, and were forced to commit depredations to sustain life. These facts are beyond question, and the evidence is positive and sustained by thousands of witnesses.&quot;

|}
{{clear}}

==Fight and ensuing massacre==
[[File:DeadBigfoot.jpg|thumb|Wounded Knee Battle|[[Spotted Elk]] lies dead after the massacre of Wounded Knee, 1890]]
After being called to the Pine Ridge Agency, Spotted Elk of the Miniconjou Lakota nation and 350 of his followers were making the slow trip to the agency on December 28, 1890, when they were met by a 7th Cavalry detachment under [[Samuel Whitside|Major Samuel M. Whitside]] southwest of Porcupine Butte. John Shangreau, a scout and interpreter who was half Sioux, advised the troopers not to disarm the Indians immediately, as it would lead to violence. The troopers escorted the Native Americans about five miles westward (8&amp;nbsp;km) to Wounded Knee Creek where they told them to make camp. Later that evening, Colonel [[James W. Forsyth]] and the rest of the [[7th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|7th Cavalry]] arrived, bringing the number of troopers at Wounded Knee to 500.&lt;ref name=&quot;SMW&quot;&gt;[[Media:Selfless Service- The Cavalry Career of Brigadier General Samuel M. Whitside from 1858 to 1902.pdf|Russell, Major Samuel L., &quot;Selfless Service: The Cavalry Career of Brigadier General Samuel M. Whitside from 1858 to 1902.&quot; MMAS Thesis, Fort Leavenworth: U.S. Command and General Staff College, 2002.]]&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, there were 350 Lakota: 230 men and 120 women and children.{{citation needed|date=August 2013}} The troopers surrounded Spotted Elk's encampment and set up four rapid-fire Hotchkiss-designed [[M1875 Mountain Gun|M1875 mountain gun]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Axelrod, Alan. (1993) ''Chronicles of the Indian Wars: From Colonial Times to Wounded Knee''. (p. 254).&lt;/ref&gt;

At daybreak on December 29, 1890, Forsyth ordered the surrender of weapons and the immediate removal of the Lakota from the &quot;zone of military operations&quot; to awaiting trains. A search of the camp confiscated 38 rifles, and more rifles were taken as the soldiers searched the Indians. None of the old men were found to be armed. A medicine man named [[Yellow Bird (medicine man)|Yellow Bird]] allegedly harangued the young men who were becoming agitated by the search, and the tension spread to the soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Utley, p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt;

Specific details of what triggered the massacre are debated. According to some accounts, Yellow Bird began to perform the Ghost Dance, telling the Lakota that their &quot;ghost shirts&quot; were bulletproof. As tensions mounted, [[Black Coyote]] refused to give up his rifle; he was deaf and had not understood the order. Another Indian said: &quot;Black Coyote is deaf.&quot; (Black Coyote did not speak English.) When the soldier persisted, he said, &quot;Stop. He cannot hear your orders.&quot; At that moment, two soldiers seized Black Coyote from behind, and (allegedly) in the struggle, his rifle discharged. At the same moment, Yellow Bird threw some dust into the air, and approximately five young Lakota men with concealed weapons threw aside their blankets and fired their rifles at Troop K of the 7th. After this initial exchange, the firing became indiscriminate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last =Utley |first =Robert |title=The Last Days of the Sioux Nation |publisher=Yale University Press |year=1963 |url=http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=978-0-300-10316-8| accessdate =4 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Hotchkiss gun wounded knee.gif|left|thumb|Soldiers pose with three of the four Hotchkiss-designed M1875 mountain guns used at Wounded Knee. The caption on the photograph reads: &quot;Famous Battery 'E' of the 1st Artillery. These brave men and the Hotchkiss guns that Big Foot's Indians thought were toys, Together with the fighting 7th what's left of Gen. Custer's boys, Sent 200 Indians to that Heaven which the ghost dancer enjoys. This checked the Indian noise, and Gen. Miles with staff Returned to Illinois.&quot;]]
According to commanding General [[Nelson A. Miles]], a &quot;scuffle occurred between one warrior who had [a] rifle in his hand and two soldiers. The rifle was discharged and a battle occurred, not only the warriors but the sick Chief Spotted Elk, and a large number of women and children who tried to escape by running and scattering over the prairie were hunted down and killed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, Charles. December 29, 1890. ''American History''. December 2005 40(5) pp. 16–68.&lt;/ref&gt;

At first all firing was at close range; half the Indian men were killed or wounded before they had a chance to get off any shots. Some of the Indians grabbed rifles from the piles of confiscated weapons and opened fire on the soldiers. With no cover, and with many of the Indians unarmed, this lasted a few minutes at most. While the Indian warriors and soldiers were shooting at close range, other soldiers used the Hotchkiss guns against the [[tipi]] camp full of women and children. It is believed that many of the soldiers were victims of friendly fire from their own Hotchkiss guns. The Indian women and children fled the camp, seeking shelter in a nearby ravine from the crossfire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman2008&quot;&gt;{{Citation |last=Bateman |first=Robert |title=Wounded Knee |journal=Military History |date=June 2008 |volume=24 |issue=4 |pages=62–67 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The officers had lost all control of their men. Some of the soldiers fanned out and finished off the wounded. Others leaped onto their horses and pursued the Indians (men, women, and children), in some cases for miles across the prairies. In less than an hour, at least 150 Lakota had been killed and 50 wounded. Historian Dee Brown, in ''Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee'', mentions an estimate of 300&lt;ref&gt;Derived from Nelson Miles' report of some 300 snow covered forms during his inspection of the field three days later, Miles in a letter states: &quot;The official reports make the number killed 90 warriors and approximately 200 women and children.&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; of the original 350 having been killed or wounded and that the soldiers loaded 51 survivors (4 men and 47 women and children) onto wagons and took them to the Pine Ridge Reservation.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 179–180&lt;/ref&gt; Army casualties numbered 25 dead and 39 wounded.
{{clear}}

==Eyewitness accounts==
[[File:Wounded Knee Survivors.jpg|thumb|upright|Brothers, (left to right) White Lance, Joseph Horn Cloud, and [[Dewey Beard]], Wounded Knee survivors; [[Miniconjou]] Lakota]]
[[File:Grabill - Survivors of Big Foots band.jpg|thumb|right|&quot;What's left of Big Foot's band&quot;: John Grabill, 1891]]
* [[Dewey Beard]] (Iron Hail, 1862–1955), Minneconjou Lakota survivor: as told to [[Eli S. Ricker]] :
&quot;...&amp;nbsp;then many Indians broke into the ravine; some ran up the ravine and to favorable positions for defense.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Eli Seavey Ricker, ''Voices of the American West: The Indian interviews of Eli S. Ricker, 1903–1919''&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Black Elk]] (1863–1950); medicine man, Oglala Lakota:
&quot;I did not know then how much was ended. When I look back now from this high hill of my old age, I can still see the butchered women and children lying heaped and scattered all along the crooked gulch as plain as when I saw them with eyes young. And I can see that something else died there in the bloody mud, and was buried in the blizzard. A people's dream died there. It was a beautiful dream&amp;nbsp;... the nation's hoop is broken and scattered. There is no center any longer, and the sacred tree is dead.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7p9VqRLiKqcC&amp;pg=PA218&amp;lpg=PA218| title =Black Elk Speaks: Being the Life Story of a Holy Man of the Oglala Sioux | author =Black Elk, John Gneisenau Neihardt | publisher = [[SUNY Press]] | page= 281 |date =2008|orig-year=1961}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[American Horse]] (1840–1908); chief, Oglala Lakota:
&quot;There was a woman with an infant in her arms who was killed as she almost touched the flag of truce&amp;nbsp;... A mother was shot down with her infant; the child not knowing that its mother was dead was still nursing&amp;nbsp;... The women as they were fleeing with their babies were killed together, shot right through&amp;nbsp;... and after most all of them had been killed a cry was made that all those who were not killed or wounded should come forth and they would be safe. Little boys&amp;nbsp;... came out of their places of refuge, and as soon as they came in sight a number of soldiers surrounded them and butchered them there.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.pbs.org/weta/thewest/resources/archives/eight/wklakota.htm | title =Lakota Accounts of the Massacre at Wounded Knee | publisher =pbs.org | year =2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Edward Settle Godfrey|Edward S. Godfrey]]; captain; commanded Co. D of the 7th Cavalry:
&quot;I know the men did not aim deliberately and they were greatly excited. I don't believe they saw their sights. They fired rapidly but it seemed to me only a few seconds till there was not a living thing before us; warriors, squaws, children, ponies, and dogs&amp;nbsp;... went down before that unaimed fire.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Edward S. Godfrey, &quot;Cavalry Fire Discipline,&quot; ''Journal of the Military Service Institution of the United States'' 19 (1896): 259.&lt;/ref&gt;
(Godfrey was a lieutenant in Captain Benteen's force during the [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]].)&lt;ref&gt;William S. E. Coleman, ''Voices of Wounded Knee,'' p. 278&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Hugh McGinnis]]; First Battalion, Co. K, 7th Cavalry:
&quot;General Nelson A. Miles who visited the scene of carnage, following a three-day blizzard, estimated that around 300 snow shrouded forms were strewn over the countryside. He also discovered to his horror that helpless children and women with babies in their arms had been chased as far as two miles from the original scene of encounter and cut down without mercy by the troopers.&amp;nbsp;... Judging by the slaughter on the battlefield it was suggested that the soldiers simply went berserk. For who could explain such a merciless disregard for life?&amp;nbsp;... As I see it the battle was more or less a matter of spontaneous combustion, sparked by mutual distrust&amp;nbsp;...&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourfamilyhistory.biz/woundedknee.htm Hugh McGinnis, &quot;I Took Part In The Wounded Knee Massacre&quot;], ''Real West Magazine'', January 1966; at Our Family History Website&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Aftermath==
[[File:Woundedkneescenedeadandhorses.jpg|thumb|View of canyon at Wounded Knee, dead horses and Lakota bodies are visible]]
[[File:Burial Party Wounded Knee.jpg|thumb|Civilian burial party, loading victims on a cart for burial]]

Following a three-day blizzard, the military hired civilians to bury the dead Lakota. The burial party found the deceased frozen; they were gathered up and placed in a mass grave on a hill overlooking the encampment from which some of the fire from the Hotchkiss guns originated. It was reported that four infants were found alive, wrapped in their deceased mothers' shawls. In all, 84 men, 44 women, and 18 children reportedly died on the field, while at least seven Lakota were mortally wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Josephy 1990&quot;&gt;Josephy, Jr., Alvin M., Trudy Thomas, and Jeanne Eder. Wounded Knee: Lest We Forget. Billings, Montana: Buffalo Bill Historical Center, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;
Miles denounced Forsyth and relieved him of command. An exhaustive Army Court of Inquiry convened by Miles criticized Forsyth for his tactical dispositions but otherwise exonerated him of responsibility. The Court of Inquiry, however, was not conducted as a formal court-martial.

The [[United States Secretary of War|secretary of war]] concurred with the decision and reinstated Forsyth to command of the 7th Cavalry. Testimony had indicated that for the most part, troops attempted to avoid non-combatant casualties. Miles continued to criticize Forsyth, whom he believed had deliberately disobeyed his commands in order to destroy the Indians. Miles promoted the conclusion that Wounded Knee was a deliberate massacre rather than a tragedy caused by poor decisions, in an effort to destroy the career of Forsyth. This was later whitewashed and Forsyth was promoted to major general.&lt;ref&gt;Ostler, Jeffrey. (2004) ''The Plains Sioux and U.S. Colonialism from Lewis and Clark to Wounded Knee''. (p. 354).&lt;/ref&gt;

The American public's reaction to the massacre at the time was generally favorable. Many non-Lakota living near the reservations interpreted the battle as the defeat of a murderous [[cult]]; others confused Ghost Dancers with Native Americans in general. In an editorial response to the event, the young newspaper editor [[L. Frank Baum]], later the author of ''[[The Wonderful Wizard of Oz]]'', wrote in the ''Aberdeen Saturday Pioneer'' on January 3, 1891:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Pioneer has before declared that our only safety depends upon the total extermination of the Indians. Having wronged them for centuries, we had better, in order to protect our civilization, follow it up by one more wrong and wipe these untamed and untamable creatures from the face of the earth. In this lies future safety for our settlers and the soldiers who are under incompetent commands. Otherwise, we may expect future years to be as full of trouble with the redskins as those have been in the past.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.manataka.org/page1721.html Giago, Tim. &quot;300 reasons not to forget lessons of Wounded Knee&quot;], ''Manataka American Indian Council.'' (retrieved 6 August 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Soon after the event, [[Dewey Beard]], his brother [[Joseph Horn Cloud]], and others formed the [[Wounded Knee Survivors Association]], which came to include descendants. They sought compensation from the U.S. government for the many fatalities and injured. Today the association is independent and works to preserve and protect the historic site from exploitation, and to administer any memorial erected there. Papers of the association (1890–1973) and related materials are held by the University of South Dakota and are available for research.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usd.edu/library/upload/woundedkneesa.pdf &quot;Wounded Knee Survivors Association, Papers (1890–1973)&quot;], Archives and Special Collections, University of South Dakota, accessed 7 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; It was not until the 1990s that a memorial to the Lakota was included in the [[National Historic Landmark]].

More than 80 years after the massacre, beginning on February 27, 1973, Wounded Knee was the site of the [[Wounded Knee incident]], a 71-day standoff between militants of the [[American Indian Movement]]—who had chosen the site for its symbolic value—and federal law enforcement officials.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ww3.startribune.com/blogs/oldnews/archives/186 James Parsons, &quot;AIM Indians with ’story to tell’ made Wounded Knee the medium&quot;], ''Minneapolis Tribune'', March 25, 1973. Retrieved December 28, 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

===Drexel Mission Fight===
[[File:Site of Drexel Mission Fight Pine Ridge Indian Reservation-1890.jpg|thumb|The 'Bloody Pocket'; location of the [[Drexel Mission Fight]]]]
Historically, Wounded Knee is generally considered to be the end of the collective multi-century series of conflicts between colonial and U.S. forces and American Indians, known collectively as the [[Indian Wars]]. It was not however the last armed conflict between Native Americans and the United States.

The [[Drexel Mission Fight]] was an armed confrontation between Lakota warriors and the United States Army that took place on the [[Pine Ridge Indian Reservation]] on December 30, 1890, the day following Wounded Knee. The fight occurred on White Clay Creek approximately 15 miles north of [[Pine Ridge, South Dakota|Pine Ridge]] where Lakota fleeing from the continued hostile situation surrounding the massacre at Wounded Knee had set up camp.

Company K of the 7th Cavalry&amp;nbsp;— the unit involved at Wounded Knee&amp;nbsp;— was sent to force the Lakotas' return to the areas they were assigned on their respective reservations. Some of the 'hostiles' were [[Brulé]] Lakota from the [[Rosebud Indian Reservation]]. The 7th Cavalry was pinned down in a valley by the combined Lakota forces and had to be rescued by the [[9th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|9th Cavalry]], an African American regiment nicknamed the &quot;[[Buffalo Soldier]]s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey Ostler: The Plains Sioux and U.S. colonialism from Lewis and Clark to Wounded Knee, pp. 357–358, Cambridge University Press (2004)
ISBN 0-521-60590-3&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the Lakota warriors was a young Brulé from Rosebud named [[Plenty Horses]] who had recently returned from five years at the [[Carlisle Indian School]] in Pennsylvania. A week after this fight, Plenty Horses shot and killed army lieutenant, Edward W. Casey,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NEBHAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA132&amp;dq=plenty+horses#v=onepage&amp;q=plenty%20horses&amp;f=false |title=Congressional edition By United States. Congress, p. 132 |publisher=|date=2011-04-26 |accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; commandant of the [[Cheyenne]] Scouts (Troop L, 8th Cavalry). The testimony introduced at the trial of Plenty Horses and his subsequent acquittal also helped abrogate the legal culpability of the U.S. Army for the deaths at Wounded Knee.&lt;ref&gt;Roger L. Di Silvestro: In the Shadow of Wounded Knee: The Untold Final Story of the Indian Wars, p. 198, Walker &amp; Company (2007) ISBN 0-8027-1514-1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Medal of Honor controversy==
For this 1890 offensive, the army awarded twenty [[Medal of Honor|Medals of Honor]], its highest commendation.  Recently, in the governmental [[Nebraska State Historical Society]]'s summer 1994 quarterly journal, Jerry Green construes that pre-1916 Medals of Honor were awarded more liberally; however, &quot;the number of medals does seem disproportionate when compared to those awarded for other battles.&quot;  Quantifying, he compares the three awarded for the [[Battle of Bear Paw#The siege|Battle of Bear Paw Mountain's five-day siege]], to the twenty awarded for this short and one-sided action.&lt;ref name=JerryGreen /&gt;

Historian Will G. Robinson notes that, in contrast, only three Medals of Honor were awarded among the 64,000 South Dakotans who fought for four years of [[World War II]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dickshovel.com/WagnerB.html Doctor Sally Wagner Testifies At Wounded Knee Hearings Part Two].&lt;/ref&gt;

Native American activists have urged the medals be withdrawn, as they say they were &quot;medals of dishonor&quot;. According to Lakota tribesman William Thunder Hawk, &quot;The Medal of Honor is meant to reward soldiers who act heroically. But at Wounded Knee, they didn't show heroism; they showed cruelty.&quot; In 2001, the [[National Congress of American Indians]] passed two resolutions condemning the Medals of Honor awards and called on the U.S. government to rescind them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Congress&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.footnote.com/page/1299_lakotawounded_knee_a_campaign_to/ |title=Lakota~WOUNDED KNEE: A Campaign to Rescind Medals: story, pictures and information |publisher=Footnote.com |date= |accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the citations on the medals awarded to the troopers at Wounded Knee state that they went in pursuit of Lakota who were trying to escape or hide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.history.army.mil/html/moh/indianwars.html |title=U.S. Army Indian Wars, Medal of Honor citations |publisher=History.army.mil |date= |accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Another citation was for &quot;conspicuous bravery in rounding up and bringing to the skirmish line a stampeded pack mule.&quot;&lt;ref name=JerryGreen /&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; margin-left:1em; float:center&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background:#b0cce5;&quot; colspan=&quot;54&quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''Medal of Honor citations, Wounded Knee'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dickshovel.com/hill.html |title=Wounded Knee, A Wound That Won't Heal |date=7 October 1999 |accessdate=April 23, 2015 |website=First Nations issues of consequence |publisher= |last=Hill |first=Richard}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;background:#fbf4ce;&quot; colspan=&quot;54&quot;|

*Sergeant [[William G. Austin|William Austin]], cavalry, directed fire at Indians in ravine at Wounded Knee;
*Private [[Mosheim Feaster]], cavalry, extraordinary gallantry at Wounded Knee;
*Private [[Mathew Hamilton]], cavalry, bravery in action at Wounded Knee;
*Private [[Joshua Hartzog]], artillery, rescuing commanding officer who was wounded and carried him out of range of hostile guns at Wounded Knee;
*Private [[Marvin Hillock]], cavalry, distinguished bravery at Wounded Knee;
*Sergeant [[Bernhard Jetter]], cavalry, distinguished bravery at Wounded Knee for &quot;killing an Indian who was in the act of killing a wounded man of B Troop.&quot;
*Sergeant [[George Loyd]], cavalry, bravery, especially after having been severely wounded through the lung at Wounded Knee;
*Sergeant [[Albert McMillain]], cavalry, while engaged with Indians concealed in a ravine, he assisted the men on the skirmish line, directed their fire, encouraged them by example, and used every effort to dislodge the enemy at Wounded Knee;
*Private [[Thomas Sullivan (Medal of Honor, 1890)|Thomas Sullivan]], cavalry, conspicuous bravery in action against Indians concealed in a ravine at Wounded Knee;
*First Sergeant [[Jacob Trautman]], cavalry, killed a hostile Indian at close quarters, and, although entitled to retirement from service, remained to close of the campaign at Wounded Knee;
*Sergeant [[James Ward (Medal of Honor, 1890)|James Ward]], cavalry, continued to fight after being severely wounded at Wounded Knee;
*Corporal [[William Wilson (Medal of Honor)|William Wilson]], cavalry, bravery in Sioux Campaign, 1890;
*Private [[Hermann Ziegner]], cavalry, conspicuous bravery at Wounded Knee;
*Musician John Clancy, artillery, twice voluntarily rescued wounded comrades under fire of the enemy;
*Lieutenant [[Ernest Garlington]], cavalry, distinguished gallantry;
*First Lieutenant [[John Chowning Gresham]], cavalry, voluntarily led a party into a ravine to dislodge Sioux Indians concealed therein. He was wounded during this action.
*Second Lieutenant [[Harry Hawthorne]], artillery, distinguished conduct in battle with hostile Indians;
*Private [[George Hobday]], cavalry, conspicuous and gallant conduct in battle;
*First Sergeant [[Frederick Toy]], cavalry, bravery;
*Corporal [[Paul Weinert]], artillery, taking the place of his commanding officer who had fallen severely wounded, he gallantly served his piece, after each fire advancing it to a better position
|}

==Remembrance==

===Monuments to Indian casualties===
[[File:Wounded Knee 96.jpg|thumb|Wounded Knee hill, location of Hotchkiss guns during battle and subsequent mass grave of Native American dead]]
St. John's Episcopal Mission Church was built on the hill behind the mass grave in which the victims had been buried, some survivors having been nursed in the then-new Holy Cross Mission Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://freepages.genealogy.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~mikestevens/HollyCrossChurchHistory.htm|title=History of Holy Cross Church Pine Ridge, SD|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1903, descendants of those who died in the battle erected a monument at the gravesite. The memorial lists many of those who died at Wounded Knee along with an inscription that reads:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;This monument is erected by surviving relatives and other Ogalala and Cheyenne River Sioux Indians in memory of the Chief Big Foot massacre December 29, 1890. Col. Forsyth in command of US troops. Big Foot was a great chief of the Sioux Indians. He often said, 'I will stand in peace till my last day comes.' He did many good and brave deeds for the white man and the red man. Many innocent women and children who knew no wrong died here.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Last days of the Sioux Nation'', by Robert M. Utley, p. 5 Publisher: Yale University Press; 2 edition (July 11, 2004)
Language: English ISBN 0-300-10316-6&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[Wounded Knee Battlefield]] was declared a U.S. [[National Historic Landmark]] in 1965 and was listed on the U.S. [[National Register of Historic Places]] in 1966.

Beginning in 1986, the group named &quot;Big Foot Memorial Riders&quot; was formed to continue to honor the dead. The ceremony has attracted more participants each year and riders and their horses live with the cold weather, as well as the lack of food and water, as they retrace the path that their family members took to Wounded Knee. They carry with them a white flag to symbolize their hope for world peace, and to honor and remember the victims so that they will not be forgotten.&lt;ref name=&quot;Josephy 1990&quot; /&gt;

===Seventh Cavalry Regiment===
When the 7th Cavalry Regiment returned to duty at [[Fort Riley]] from Pine Ridge, South Dakota, the soldiers of the regiment raised money for a monument for members of the regiment killed at Wounded Knee.  About $1,950 was collected, and on July 25, 1893, the monument was dedicated with 5,500 people in attendance. Today, the stone edifice still stands near Waters Hall.&lt;ref&gt;Mackale,William and Robert Smith(2003) [https://books.google.com/books?id=GYvO3ug4Ib8C&amp;pg=PA21&amp;lpg=PA21&amp;dq=wounded+knee+monument+fort+riley&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=imNz8cR_En&amp;sig=IMeu2qYIrOfvNLf0tKH7lUANjbw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=8fzRUruEFujJsASZtIHoCw&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CGwQ6AEwDg#v=onepage&amp;q=wounded%20knee%20monument%20fort%20riley&amp;f=false &quot;Images of America: Fort Riley&quot;]. Retrieved 11 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==
[[File:The opening of the fight at Wounded Knee by Frederic Remington 1891.jpg|thumb|&quot;The opening of the fight at Wounded Knee,&quot; engraved illustration by [[Frederic Remington]]. Appeared as an illustration in ''[[Harper's Weekly]]'', 1891]]

===Massacre or battle===
The incident was initially referred to as the &quot;Battle of Wounded Knee&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gathering the Dead at the Battle of Wounded Knee (Photograph Annotation)[http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/p15799coll65/id/19104] Retrieved 29 May. 2014&lt;/ref&gt;  Some American Indian groups have objected to this description and refer to it as the &quot;Wounded Knee Massacre&quot;.  The location of the conflict is officially known as the &quot;Wounded Knee Battlefield&quot;. The U.S. Army currently refers to it as &quot;Wounded Knee&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Medal of Honor Recipients&amp;nbsp;– Indian Wars [http://www.history.army.mil/moh/indianwars.html] Retrieved 6 May 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bury my heart at Wounded Knee===
In his 1931 poem &quot;American Names&quot;, [[Stephen Vincent Benet]] [[neologism|coined the phrase]] &quot;Bury my heart at Wounded Knee&quot;.  The poem is about his love of American place names, not making reference to the 'battle'.  However, when the line was used as the title of [[Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee|historian Dee Brown's 1970 best-selling book]], awareness was raised and Benet's phrase became popularly associated with the incident, especially in music.

After the book, &quot;Bury my heart at Wounded Knee&quot; was used many times in reference to the battle, especially in music.  In 1973, Stuttgart, Germany's [[Gila (band)|Gila]] released a [[krautrock]]/[[psychedelic folk]] album by the same name.

In 1992, [[Buffy Sainte-Marie|Beverly (Buffy) Sainte-Marie]] released her song entitled &quot;[[Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee (song)|Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee]]&quot;, on her ''[[Coincidence and Likely Stories]]'' album. &quot;Bury My Heart at Fun Fun Mountain&quot; is a book of Foxtrot comics which was named in reference to this quote. It was published on March 1, 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/520990.Bury_My_Heart_at_Fun_Fun_Mountain|title=Bury My Heart at Fun-Fun Mountain|author=Bill Amend|work=Goodreads}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In other music===
Artists who have written or recorded songs referring to the battle at Wounded Knee include: [[Walela]] &quot;Wounded Knee&quot; from their 1997 self-titled album. [[Nightwish]] (&quot;Creek Mary's Blood&quot; from their 2004 album &quot;Once&quot; featuring [[John Two-Hawks]]); [[Manowar]] (&quot;Spirit Horse Of The Cherokee&quot; from the 1992 album ''The Triumph Of Steel'' ); [[Grant Lee Buffalo]] (&quot;Were You There?&quot; from the album ''Storm Hymnal'' 2001); [[Johnny Cash]] (1972's &quot;Big Foot,&quot; which is strongly sympathetic); [[Gordon Lightfoot]] (&quot;Protocol&quot; from his 1976 album ''[[Summertime Dream]]''); [[Indigo Girls|The Indigo Girls]] (a cover of Sainte-Marie's song); [[Charlie Parr]] (&quot;1890&quot; on his 2010 album ''When the Devil Goes Blind''); [[Nik Kershaw]] (&quot;Wounded Knee&quot; on his 1989 album ''The Works''); [[Southern Death Cult]] (&quot;Moya&quot;); [[The Waterboys]] (&quot;Bury My Heart&quot;); [[Uriah Heep (band)|Uriah Heep]]; [[Primus (band)|Primus]]; [[Nahko and Medicine for the People]]; [[Patti Smith]];&lt;ref&gt;Patti Smith Group, &quot;Ghost Dance&quot;. On ''[[Easter (Patti Smith Group album)|Easter]]'', Arista AB 4171, released 1978.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robbie Robertson]];&lt;ref&gt;Robbie Robertson, &quot;Ghost Dance&quot;, on ''[[Music for the Native Americans]]'', Cema/Capitol 28295, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Five Iron Frenzy]] wrote the 2001 song &quot;The Day We Killed&quot; with mentions of Custard, Black Kettle, and quotes Black Elk's account from ''Black Elk Speaks'' on their album [[Five Iron Frenzy 2: Electric Boogaloo]]; [[Toad the Wet Sprocket]]; [[Marty Stuart]]; [[Bright Eyes (band)|Bright Eyes]]; and &quot;Pocahontas&quot; by Neil Young. On [[Chemical City|Sam Roberts' 2006 ''Chemical City'' album]], the song &quot;The Bootleg Saint&quot; contains line critical of Knee Massacre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://MetroLyrics.com/the-bootleg-saint-lyrics-sam-roberts.html| title= Sam Roberts - The Bootleg Saint Lyrics MetroLyrics| author= [[Sam Roberts]]| publisher= [[MetroLyrics]] |accessdate=8 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also a Welsh song called &quot;Gwaed Ar Yr Eira Gwyn&quot; by [[Tecwyn Ifan]] on this incident. The song &quot;American Ghost Dance&quot; by the Red Hot Chili Peppers makes extensve reference to the massacre as well.

In 1973, the American rock band [[Redbone (band)|Redbone]], formed by Native Americans Patrick and Lolly Vasquez, released the song, &quot;We Were All Wounded at Wounded Knee&quot;. The song ends with the subtly altered sentence, &quot;We were all wounded by Wounded Knee.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.redbone.be/wounded.html &quot;We Were All Wounded at Wounded Knee&quot;], Redbone's unofficial discography site, with lyrics. Webpage found 2010-03-31.&lt;/ref&gt; The song reached the number-one chart position across Europe. In the U.S., the song was initially withheld from release and then banned by several radio stations. Richard Stepp's [[2008 Native American Music Awards]] ''Native Heart'' nominated album, ''[[The Sacred Journey]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.NativeAmericanMusicAwards.com/nama-10| title= NAMA 10| year= 2008| website= [[NativeAmericanMusicAwards.com]]| publisher= [[Native American Music Awards]]| accessdate= 30 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; has &quot;Wounded Knee&quot; as its final track.

===In film===
The massacre has been referred to in films, including ''[[Thunderheart]]'' (1992), ''[[Legends of the Fall]]'' (1994), ''[[The Last Samurai]]'' (2003), and ''[[Hidalgo (film)|Hidalgo]]'' (2004). The 2005 TNT mini-series'' [[Into the West (TV miniseries)|Into the West]]'' included scenes of the massacre. In 2007, [[HBO Films]] released a film adaptation of the [[Dee Brown (novelist)|Dee Brown]] bestseller ''[[Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee (film)|Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee]]''.

===Other===
The massacre is referenced in the 1991 arcade game ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Turtles in Time]]'' by [[Konami]] (later released for the [[Super NES]] in 1992), where it is used for the title of the game's sixth stage (seventh stage in the Super NES version) &quot;Bury My Shell at Wounded Knee&quot;. The stage has the Turtles [[time travel|transported]] to the old west in the year 1885, where they must fight Foot Ninjas led by Leatherhead on a moving train.

In the 1996 DC comic book ''[[Saint of Killers]]'', written by Garth Ennis, the main character becomes a surrogate Angel of Death, reaping souls whenever men kill other men violently. The story is set in the 1880s and, near the end of chapter 4, it is said that &quot;four years later&quot; he was called upon at Wounded Knee.

In the 2013 video game ''[[BioShock Infinite]]'', several main characters are veterans of Wounded Knee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2012/12/21/the-evolution-of-bioshock-infinite
| title=      The Evolution of BioShock Infinite
| date =      21 December 2012
| first =     Andrew
| last =      Goldfarb
| publisher=  IGN
| accessdate= 1 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The protagonist Booker DeWitt is haunted by his deeds during the battle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   | url=        http://www.gameinformer.com/b/features/archive/2013/04/09/free-will-and-hope-in-bioshock-infinite.aspx
   | title=      Free Will And Hope In BioShock Infinite
   | date=       9 April 2013
   | first=      Matt
   | last=       Miller
   | publisher=  Game Informer
   | accessdate= 1 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of battle==
[[File:James W. Forsyth.jpg|thumb|right|100px|Colonel James W. Forsyth]] [[File:Smw-1901.jpg|thumb|right|100px|Major Samuel Whitside]] [[File:Winfield Scott Edgerly.jpg|thumb|right|100px|Captain Winfield Scott Edgerly]] [[File:Allyn K Capron Sr.jpg|thumb|right|100px|Captain Allyn Capron, Sr.]]
'''[[7th U.S. Cavalry]]'''&lt;ref&gt;Utley p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Col [[James W. Forsyth]]
* Adjutant: 1st Lt. Lloyd S. McCormick
* Quartermaster: 1st Lt. Ezra B. Fuller
* Assistant Surgeon &amp; Medical Director: Cpt. John Van Rennselaer Hoff
* Assistant Surgeon: 1st Lt. James D. Glennan

''First Squadron''&lt;br /&gt;
Maj [[Samuel Whitside]]
:Adjutant: 1st Lt. W.J. Nicholson
::Troop A: Cpt. [[Myles Moylan]], 1st Lt. [[Ernest Albert Garlington|Ernest A. Garlington]]
::Troop B: Cpt. [[Charles Varnum|Charles A. Varnum]], 1st Lt. [[John Chowning Gresham|John C. Gresham]]
::Troop I: Cpt. Henry J. Nowlan, 2nd Lt. John C. Waterman
::Troop K: Cpt. George D. Wallace (k), 1st Lt. James D. Mann

''Second Squadron''&lt;br /&gt;
Cpt. Charles S. Isley
:Adjutant: 1st Lt. W.W. Robinson II
::Troop C: Cpt. Henry Jackson, 2nd Lt. T.Q. Donaldson
::Troop D: Cpt. [[Edward Settle Godfrey|Edward S. Godfrey]], 2nd Lt. S.R.J. Tompkins
::Troop E: Cpt. Charles S. Isley, 1st Lt. Horatio G. Sickel, 2nd Lt. Sedgwick Rice
::Troop G: Cpt. [[Winfield Scott Edgerly|Winfield S. Edgerly]], 1st Lt. Edwin P. Brewer

''Battery E, 1st U.S. Artillery''&lt;br /&gt;
[[Captain Allyn Capron]]
:2nd Lt. [[Harry L. Hawthorne]] (2nd U.S. Artillery)
::4 Hotchkiss Breech-Loading Mountain Rifles

''Troop A, Indian Scouts''
:1st Lt. George W. Taylor (9th U.S. Cavalry)
:2nd Lt. Guy H. Preston (9th U.S. Cavalry)

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery mode=packed&gt;
File:Wounded Knee mapa positive.jpg|Map of Wounded Knee
File:Big Foot's band of Miniconjou Sioux in costume at a dance.gif|Miniconjou Lakota dance at Cheyenne River, South Dakota, August 9, 1890
File:Holy Cross Episcopal mission.jpg|Holy Cross Episcopal Mission, used as hospital for wounded Lakota
File:Wounded Knee photographer.jpg|Photographer taking pictures of campsite
File:Wounded Knee 1.jpg|Frozen corpse on field
File:Wounded Knee aftermath5.jpg|The scene three days afterwards, with several bodies partially wrapped in blankets in the foreground.
File:Woundedkneeofficers.jpg|Buffalo Bill, Capt. Baldwin, Gen. Nelson A. Miles, Capt. Moss, and others, on horseback, on battlefield of Wounded Knee.
File:Woundedkneeencampment.jpg|Reenactment of U.S. troops surrounding the Lakota at Wounded Knee (1913).
File:Wounded Knee.jpg|Wounded Knee, 1940
File:WoundedKneePhilKonstantin.jpg|Wounded Knee grave, 2003
File:James W. Forsyth.jpg[[James W. Forsyth]]
File:Portrait of General L. W. Colby of Nebraska State Troops Holding Baby Girl, Zintkala Nuni (Little Lost Bird), Found On Wounded Knee Battlefield, South Dakota, 1890 n.d.jpg|Gen. L. W. Colby holding Zintkala Nuni (Little Lost Bird), found on the Wounded Knee battlefield.
File:Eric Holder at Wounded Knee Memorial.jpg|US Attorney General Eric Holder laying a wreath at the site of the Wounded Knee Memorial
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|South Dakota}}
* [[Wounded Knee incident|Wounded Knee Incident (1973)]]
* [[List of Indian massacres|Indian massacre]]s in the United States
* [[Genocide of indigenous peoples]]
* [[History of South Dakota]]
* [[American Indian Wars#Great Plains|Plains Indians Wars]]
* [[List of battles fought in South Dakota]]
* [[Manifest Destiny]]
* [[Wounded Knee of Alaska]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}
* L. Frank Baum editorial that appeared in the Aberdeen (SD) Saturday Review on January 3, 1891, just five days after the massacre. The author wrote about those terrible &quot;Redskins,&quot; his favorite word for Indians. He wrote, &quot;The Pioneer has before declared that our only safety depends upon the total extermination of the Indians. Having wronged them for centuries we had better, in order to protect our civilization, follow it up by one or more wrong and wipe these untamed and untamable creatures from the face of the earth.&quot;

==Further reading==
* Andersson, Rani-Henrik. ''The Lakota Ghost Dance of 1890.'' Lincoln, NE: University of Nebraska Press, 2009.ISBN 978-0-8032-1073-8.
* Brown, Dee. ''[[Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee]]: An Indian History of the American West'', Owl Books (1970). ISBN 0-8050-6669-1.
* Champlin, Tim. ''A Trail To Wounded Knee : A Western Story.'' Five Star (2001).
* Coleman, William S.E. ''Voices of Wounded Knee'', [[University of Nebraska Press]] (2000). ISBN 0-8032-1506-1.
* Greene, Jerome A. ''American Carnage: Wounded Knee, 1890.'' Norman, OK: University of Oklahoma Press, 2014.
* Smith, Rex Alan. ''Moon of Popping Trees.'' Lincoln, NE: University of Nebraska Press (1981). ISBN 0-8032-9120-5.
* [[Robert M. Utley|Utley, Robert M.]] ''Last Days of the Sioux Nation.'' New Haven, CT: [[Yale University Press]] (1963).
* Utley, Robert M. ''The Indian Frontier 1846–1890.'' Albuquerque, NM: [[University of New Mexico Press]] (2003). ISBN 0-8263-2998-5.
* Utley, Robert M. ''Frontier Regulars The United States Army and the Indian 1866–1891.'' New York: MacMillan Publishing (1973). ISBN 0-8032-9551-0.
* Yenne, Bill. ''Indian Wars: The Campaign for the American West'', Westholme (2005). ISBN 1-59416-016-3.

==External links==
{{commons category|Wounded Knee Massacre|Wounded Knee Massacre&lt;br /&gt;(Pine Ridge Campaign)}}
* [http://www.woundedkneemuseum.org The Wounded Knee Museum in Wall, South Dakota]
* [http://www.pbs.org/weta/thewest/resources/archives/eight/gdmessg.htm Bureau of American Ethnology report on the Ghost Dance Religion], PBS
* [http://contentdm.lib.byu.edu/cdm/search/collection/Camp/ &quot;Walter Mason Camp Collection,&quot; includes photographs from the Battle of Wounded Knee Creek], Brigham Young University
* [http://genforum.genealogy.com/woundedknee/messages/91.html US Army Casualty list of Wounded Knee], GenForum
* [http://www.dakotapathways.org/20/story.htm &quot;A Dark Day&quot;&amp;nbsp;– Education Resource], Dakota Pathways
* [http://www.sdpb.org/Lostbird/default.aspx &quot;Lost Bird of Wounded Knee&quot;&amp;nbsp;– Education Resource], South Dakota Public Television
* [http://www.friendslittlebighorn.com/buryheartwoundedknee.htm Review: ''Bury My Heart At Wounded Knee'', HBO production], Friends of the Little Big Horn
* {{FAG|10792700|Susanna Lee ''Johnson'' Red Bear}}
* {{FAG|19715163|Zintkala Nuni Lost Bird}}
* [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9D04E2DF1E3BE533A25751C2A9679D94619ED7CF &quot;THE GHOST DANCE.; HOW THE INDIANS WORK THEMSELVES UP TO FIGHTING PITCH&quot;], eyewitness account by reporter, ''New York Times'', 22 November 1890
* [http://armyatwoundedknee.wordpress.com/ Army at Wounded Knee]

{{Registered Historic Places}}
{{Coord|43.1411|-102.3628|type:landmark_region:US-SD|display=title}}

[[Category:Pine Ridge Campaign| ]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1890]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1891]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Sioux]]
[[Category:History of South Dakota]]
[[Category:Native American history of South Dakota]]
[[Category:Lakota]]
[[Category:Mass graves]]
[[Category:Massacres of Native Americans]]
[[Category:Massacres committed by the United States]]
[[Category:1890 in South Dakota]]
[[Category:1890 in the United States]]
[[Category:19th-century colonization of the Americas]]
[[Category:Battles involving Native Americans]]
[[Category:Sioux Wars]]
[[Category:United States military war crimes]]</text>
      <sha1>i2qpyzc65p7avuuor333oxwjrdpudag</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
