<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Z Special Unit</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2364416</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749251831</id>
      <parentid>749243892</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T08:56:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AustralianRupert</username>
        <id>8731061</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>add citation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34522">{{Other uses|Z Force (disambiguation){{!}}Z Force}}
{{Use Australian English|date=April 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=Z Special Unit
|image=[[Image:Krait-crew.jpg|300px]]
|caption=The crew of the ''[[MV Krait|Krait]]'' during [[Operation Jaywick]].
|dates=1942–46
|country={{flag|Australia|23px}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|New Zealand|23px}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Netherlands|23px}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom|23px}}
|allegiance=[[Allies of World War II|Allied]]
|branch=
|type=[[Special forces]]
|role=[[Military intelligence|Field intelligence]], [[Raid (military)|raiding]], [[reconnaissance]], [[search and rescue]]
|colours=Red &quot;Z&quot;, with a black dagger through the &quot;Z&quot; and black/gold lettering with a white background
|battles=[[World War II]]
*[[Operation Scorpion (World War Two)|Operation Scorpion]]
*[[Operation Jaywick]]
*[[Operation Rimau]]
*[[Operation Semut|Operation Semut 1]]
*Operation Semut 2
*Operation Semut 3
*Operation Semut 4
*[[Operation Agas|Operation Agas 1]]
*Operation Agas 2
*[[Operation Python (1943–44)|Operation Python]]
*[[Operation Copper]]
*[[Project Opossum]]
|notable_commanders=
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=}}
'''Z ({{IPAc-en|z|ɛ|d|}}) Special Unit'''—also known as '''Special Operations Executive''' (SOE), '''Special Operations Australia''' (SOA) or the '''[[Services Reconnaissance Department]]''' (SRD)—was a joint Allied [[special forces]] unit formed during the Second World War to operate behind Japanese lines in [[Southeast Asia|South East Asia]]. Predominantly Australian, Z Special Unit was a specialist [[reconnaissance]] and [[sabotage]] unit that included British, Dutch, New Zealand, [[Timor]]ese and Indonesian members, predominantly operating on [[Borneo]] and the islands of the former [[Netherlands East Indies]].&lt;ref name=Horner26&gt;Horner 1989, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

The unit carried out a total of 81 covert operations in the [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|South West Pacific theatre]], with parties inserted by [[Paratrooper|parachute]] or [[submarine]] to provide [[Military intelligence|intelligence]] and conduct [[guerrilla warfare]].&lt;ref&gt;Courtney 1993, p. 14 and Horton 1983, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; The best known of these missions were [[Operation Jaywick]] and [[Operation Rimau]], both of which involved [[Raid (military)|raids]] on Japanese shipping in [[Port of Singapore|Singapore Harbour]]; the latter of which resulted in the deaths of 23 commandos either in action or by execution after capture.&lt;ref name=Horner26&gt;Horner 1989, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the unit was disbanded after the war, many of the training techniques and operational procedures employed were later used during the formation of other [[Australian Army]] special forces units and they remain a model for guerrilla operations to this day.&lt;ref name=Horner27&gt;Horner 1989, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

=== Formation and training ===
The [[Services Reconnaissance Department|Inter-Allied Services Department]] (IASD), was an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[military intelligence]] unit, established in March 1942. The unit was created at the suggestion of the commander of Allied land forces in the [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|South West Pacific area]], General [[Thomas Blamey]], and was modelled on the British [[Special Operations Executive]] (SOE) in London. It was renamed '''Special Operations Australia''' or SOA and in 1943 became known as the '''[[Services Reconnaissance Department]]''' (SRD).&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis et al 2008, p. 508&quot;&gt;Dennis et al 2008, p. 508.&lt;/ref&gt;

It contained several British SOE officers who had escaped from Singapore, and they formed the nucleus of the Inter-Allied Services Department (ISD) which was based in Melbourne. In June 1942, an ISD raiding/commando unit was organised—designated '''Z Special Unit'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis et al 2008, p. 508&quot;/&gt;

Several training schools were established in various locations across Australia, the most notable being Camp Z in Refuge Bay, an offshoot of [[Broken Bay]] to the north of Sydney, [[Z Experimental Station]] (also known as the &quot;House on the Hill&quot; or ZES.) near [[Cairns]], Queensland, [[Fraser Commando School]] (or FCS) on [[Fraser Island]], Queensland where a commemorative monument stands on the mainland overlooking the island. As a training exercise, one group paddled folboats between Fraser Island and Cairns. Another training school was the Special Boat Section at Careening Bay Camp, on [[Garden Island (Western Australia)|Garden Island]], Western Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Powell 1996, p. 119 and pp. 196–198.&lt;/ref&gt;  Another, in [[Darwin, Northern Territory|Darwin]] on the site of the Quarantine Station, was named the Lugger Maintenance Section to disguise its true purpose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ntlexhibit.nt.gov.au/items/show/704 |title=Lugger Maintenance Section |work=Northern Territory Library |publisher=Department of the Arts and Museums, Northern Territory Government |accessdate=13 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Plans for an attack on Singapore ===
In 1943, a 28-year-old British officer, Captain [[Ivan Lyon]] of the [[Allied Intelligence Bureau]] and [[Gordon Highlanders]], and a 61-year-old Australian civilian, Bill Reynolds, devised a plan to attack Japanese shipping in [[Port of Singapore|Singapore Harbour]]. Z Special Unit would travel to the harbour in a disguised fishing boat. They would then use folding kayaks to attach [[limpet mines]] to Japanese ships. General [[Archibald Wavell]] approved the plan, and Lyon was sent to Australia to organise the operation.&lt;ref name=Courtney3&gt;Courtney 1993, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bill Reynolds was in possession of a 21.3 metre-long Japanese coastal fishing boat, the [[MV Krait|''Kofuku Maru'']], which he had used to evacuate refugees out of Singapore. Lyon ordered that the boat be shipped from India to Australia. Upon its arrival, he renamed the vessel [[MV Krait|MV ''Krait'']], after the [[krait|small but deadly Asian snake]].&lt;ref name=Courtney3&gt;Courtney 1993, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Lieutenant-Colonel G. Egerton Mott, the chief of the [[Services Reconnaissance Department]], suggested that they should test the effectiveness of the plan by making a mock raid on a tightly guarded Allied port. [[Townsville]], Queensland was chosen for the location of the attack.&lt;ref&gt;McKie 1960, pp. 45–53.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Operation Scorpion ===
In January 1943, Lieutenant [[Samuel Warren Carey]], a Z Special Unit officer based at [[Z Experimental Station]], [[Cairns]], Queensland, approached General [[Thomas Blamey]] with a proposition for a raid on the Japanese-occupied port at [[Rabaul]], [[New Guinea]]. One submarine, with a small group of [[commando]]s on board, would be involved. The commandos would be dropped {{convert|16|km|mi|}} off Rabaul.&lt;ref name=Powell6465&gt;Powell 1996, pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt;

They would then use their Hoehn military folboats ([[Folding kayak|collapsible kayaks]]) to travel into the harbour and attach [[limpet mine]]s to as many enemy ships as possible. They would then retreat to a [[Vulcan (volcano)|volcano]] section roughly {{convert|6|km|mi}} south of Rabaul, where they would hide out until they could safely rendezvous with the submarine. Blamey was sure that the unit would be captured and shot, but he authorised the operation, and issued Carey [[Full Powers|carte blanche]] authority to perform whatever actions he deemed necessary during the planning of the proposed operation, which was codenamed ''Operation Scorpion''.&lt;ref name=Powell6465&gt;Powell 1996, pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Practice raid on Townsville ===
By the end of March 1943, Carey had assembled a team of nine men on their base at [[Magnetic Island]]. Lyon and Mott arranged to have Carey's unit perform a mock attack on Townsville, although they were careful not to commit anything to paper. Townsville was a busy harbour full of [[troop ship|troop transports]], [[cargo ship|merchantmen]] and [[Destroyer|naval escort]] vessels, and tight security was maintained due to the constant threat of Japanese air and submarine attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Thompson and Macklin 2002, pp. 59–61.&lt;/ref&gt;

At midnight on 22 June 1943, the unit left Magnetic Island and paddled by folboat through the heavily mined mouth of Townsville Harbour. Dummy [[limpet mine]]s were attached to ten ships, including two [[destroyer]]s. The men rowed into Ross Creek, dismantled and hid their folboats, then travelled into Townsville to find a place to sleep. Around 10:00&amp;nbsp;am, the limpets were discovered, and panic ensued.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Carey was arrested, and despite producing Blamey's letter and earnest assurances that the mines were dummies, they refused to allow him to leave or to allow the removal of the mines, which the [[Royal Australian Navy|RAN]] feared were real and might accidentally detonate. Mott was able to arrange Carey's release, but only on the condition that he left Z Special Unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; ''Operation Scorpion'' was scrapped due to a lack of submarine transport, but Mott and Lyon had learned many valuable lessons from the raid.&lt;ref name=Powell6465&gt;Powell 1996, pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Operation Jaywick ===
{{Main|Operation Jaywick}}
''Operation Jaywick'' was an Inter-Allied Services Department operation to infiltrate the Japanese-occupied Singapore Harbour and destroy shipping. On 2 September 1943, the ''[[MV Krait|Krait]]'', with a crew of eleven Australian and four British personnel, left [[Exmouth Gulf]], Western Australia. The group, commanded by Ivan Lyon, dyed their skin brown and hair black (the skin dye later caused many skin problems for the members of the team, including irritation and reactions in adverse amounts of sunlight). They also wore [[sarong]]s, so that they resembled Indonesian fisherman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Courtney 1993, pp. 3–4&quot;&gt;Courtney 1993, pp. 3–4.&lt;/ref&gt;

They arrived off Singapore on 24 September, that night, six men left the boat and paddled {{convert|50|km|mi}} to a small island near the harbour where a forward base was established in a cave. On the night of 26 September, using folboats the party paddled into the harbour and placed limpet mines on several Japanese ships, the [[limpet mine]]s sank or seriously damaged four Japanese ships, amounting to over 39,000 tons. The raiders waited until the commotion had died down before returning to the ''Krait''. On 19 October the ''Krait'' arrived back at Exmouth Gulf having achieved a great success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Courtney 1993, pp. 3–4&quot;/&gt;

=== Operation Rimau ===
{{Main|Operation Rimau}}
''Operation Rimau'' was a follow-up to the successful ''Operation Jaywick'', which had taken place in 1943, being a further attack on Japanese shipping at Singapore Harbour. Rimau (Malay for &quot;tiger&quot;) was again led by Lieutenant Colonel [[Ivan Lyon]], a British officer on secondment from the Gordon Highlanders. Originally named ''Operation Hornbill'', the goal of &quot;Rimau&quot; was to sink Japanese shipping by placing limpet mines on ships. It was intended that motorised semi-submersible canoes, known as [[Sleeping Beauty (canoe)|Sleeping Beauties]], would be used to gain access to the harbour.&lt;ref&gt;Powell 1996, p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lyon led a [[Services Reconnaissance Department]] party of twenty-two men. They left their base in Australia aboard the British submarine {{HMS|Porpoise|N14}} on 11 September 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson and Macklin 2002, p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; When they reached the island of Merapas, which was to be their forward base, it was discovered to be inhabited. To ensure that their stores would remain undiscovered by the natives, one of the officers from the ''Porpoise'', Lieutenant Walter Carey, remained on Merapas as a guard. The party then commandeered a Malay [[junk (ship)|junk]] named ''Mustika'', taking the Malay crew aboard the submarine the SRD men transferred their equipment to the junk and the ''Porpoise'' departed. Lyon decided to drop off four more men with Carey: Corporal Colin Craft, Warrant Officer Alf Warren and Sergeant Colin Cameron.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson and Macklin 2002, pp. 154–160.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, the ''Mustika'' neared its target. On the day of the planned attack, 10 October 1944, disaster struck. A Japanese patrol boat from the Malay 'Heiho' challenged the ''Mustika'' and someone on board opened fire, killing three Malays. Their cover blown however, Lyon had no option but to abort the mission. After scuttling the junk and the Sleeping Beauties with explosives, he ordered his men back to Merapas. Unbeknown to Lyon two Malays had escaped overboard during the firing and had made their way ashore to report the incident.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson and Macklin 2002, pp. 165–167.&lt;/ref&gt;

Using folboats, Lyon led a small force of six other men—Lieutenant Commander Donald Davidson, Lieutenant Bobby Ross, Able Seaman Andrew Huston, Corporal Clair Stewart, Corporal Archie Campbell and Private Douglas Warne—into Singapore Harbour, where they are believed to have sunk three ships.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson and Macklin 2002, p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt; Lyon and twelve others were killed in action soon afterwards, and the remaining ten men were captured and later executed by beheading in July 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson and Macklin 2002, p. 210 and 243.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Operation Copper ===
{{main|Operation Copper}}
[[Image:AWM P03953 004.jpg|thumb|300px|Four of the crew members of Motor Launch (ML) 1321 and NX73110 Sapper (Spr) Edgar Thomas 'Mick' Dennis, Z Special Unit, the only survivor of the ill fated raid on Muschu Island (off the coast of New Guinea), at Brisbane dockyard. May 1945.]]
''Operation Copper'' was one of the last Z Special operations in New Guinea. On the night of 11 April 1945, eight operatives were landed near Muschu Island by [[Harbour Defence Motor Launch|HDML]] patrol boat. Their mission was to paddle ashore and [[Amphibious reconnaissance|reconnoitre]] the island to determine the status of Japanese defences and validate reports that two 140&amp;nbsp;mm long-range naval guns were still in position. Intelligence suggested that these weapons were back in service and could prove dangerous during the forthcoming [[Aitape–Wewak campaign|invasion of Wewak]], as they had sufficient range to fire into the proposed landing areas and, while they would not stop the Australian invasion, they could cause significant casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;

Caught by unexpected currents the four folboats were pushed south of their landing area and came ashore amid a [[surf break]]. All boats were swamped and some items of equipment lost, but they made it ashore and harboured up until morning.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, pp. 61–64.&lt;/ref&gt; At daybreak they commenced their reconnaissance of the island, soon encountering Japanese who, unbeknownst to them, had found equipment that was washed ashore further along the island. Thus alerted, the island became a hunting ground, with almost 1,000 Japanese searching for the patrol.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, pp. 65–67.&lt;/ref&gt; Attempts to communicate by radio with the HDML patrol boat failed, as their radios had been swamped and the batteries ruined.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the eight men, only one survived. Sapper Mick Dennis, an experienced commando who had previously fought the Japanese in New Guinea in several significant engagements, escaped after fighting his way through Japanese patrols.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, pp. 179–183.&lt;/ref&gt; He swam the channel to Wewak while being pursued by the Japanese and made his way through enemy territory to eventually meet up with an Australian patrol on 20 April.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, p. 226.&lt;/ref&gt; The information he returned with proved vital to keeping the guns out of action and in preventing the Japanese from using the island as a launching point for attacks against the Australian forces during the Wewak landings a month later.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, pp. 233–234.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 and 2013, expeditions to Muschu Island were conducted by MIA Australia, leading to the discovery of the remains of four of the Z Special Commandos lost on the Muschu raid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gunsofmuschu.com/mia_project.html |title=Australian Z Special MIAs fate determined after 65 years |work=Guns of Musch MIA Project |publisher=Guns of Muschu.com |accessdate=22 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.news.com.au/national-news/exclusive-remains-thought-to-be-lost-diggers/story-fncynjr2-1226645600966 |title=Remains found in PNG thought to be those of lost Australian soldiers |work=News.com.au |publisher=News Limited Network |last=McPhedran|first= Ian|author-link=Ian McPhedran |date=18 May 2013 |accessdate=22 September 2013|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130621053450/http://www.news.com.au/national-news/exclusive-remains-thought-to-be-lost-diggers/story-fncynjr2-1226645600966|archivedate=21 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In late February 2014 it was announced that the remains of former St George first grade rugby league player, Lance Corporal Spencer Henry Walklate, and Private Ronald Eagleton, would be laid to rest in May 2014 with full military honours at the [[Lae War Cemetery]], where the other five men from Operation Copper are buried.&lt;ref name=&quot;buried&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.news.com.au/national/wwii-soldiers-spencer-henry-walklate-and-ronald-eagleton-to-be-buried/story-fncynjr2-1226834243919 |title=WWII soldiers’ Spencer Henry Walklate and Ronald Eagleton to be buried |accessdate=22 February 2014|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160112084609/http://www.news.com.au/national/wwii-soldiers-spencer-henry-walklate-and-ronald-eagleton-to-be-buried/story-fncynjr2-1226834243919|archivedate=12 January 2016|first=Ian|last=McPhedran|author-link=Ian McPhedran}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Borneo ===
During 1943–45, Z Special Unit conducted [[surveillance]], harassing attacks and [[sabotage]] behind Japanese lines in [[Borneo]], as well as the training of natives in [[insurgency|resistance activities]]. The first of these operations was ''[[Operation Python (1943–1944)|Operation Python]]''. Few details of these operations have been officially released, although details have emerged from the personal accounts of some Z Special Unit personnel. On 25 March 1945, [[Tom Harrisson]] was parachuted with seven Z Force operatives from a [[Consolidated Liberator]] onto a high plateau occupied by the [[Kelabit people]]. An autobiographical account of this operation (SEMUT I, one of four SEMUT operations in the area) is given in ''World Within'' (Cresset Press, 1959); there are also reports—not always flattering—from some of his comrades. His efforts to rescue stranded American airmen shot down over Borneo are a central part of &quot;The Airmen and the Headhunters,&quot; an episode of the PBS television series ''[[Secrets of the Dead]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode|title=The Airmen and the Headhunters|url =http://www.pbs.org/wnet/secrets/episodes/the-airmen-and-the-headhunters-watch-the-full-episode/499/|series=Secrets of the Dead| serieslink=Secrets of the Dead|credits=Director: Mark Radice|network=PBS|station=Thirteen/WNET New York|airdate= 11 November 2009|season=9|number=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his memoirs, former leading aircraftsman [[Jack Wong Sue]] claimed that Z Special Unit commandos in Borneo killed 1,700 Japanese for the loss of 112 commandos, as well as training more than 6,000 [[guerrilla]]s. According to Sue, the activities of the commandos laid the groundwork for the [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Allied invasion of Borneo in 1945]].&lt;ref&gt;Sue 2001, p. v.&lt;/ref&gt;

== New Zealand recruits ==
During the southern winter of 1944, twenty-two New Zealand soldiers,&lt;ref&gt;Sgt P. J. Boyle, Sgt W. J. Butt, Maj J. K. L. Brown, Sig A. J. Campbell, Cpl G. R. Edlin, Sig N. G. Flemming, S/Sgt G. R. Greenwood MID, Cpl J. K. Harris, Sgt W. H. Horrocks, WOII R. G. Houghton, Lt F. J. Leckie, Capt L. T. McMillan, Capt R. M. Morton MC, DCM, Sig E. H. Myers, Sgt R. J. Newdick, WOII L. N. Northover MM, Lt A. G. Palmer, Sgt R. B. Shakes, Sgt V. E. Sharp, [[Donald Stott|Maj D. J. Stott DSO &amp; Bar]], Lt R. Tapper and Sgt F. A. Wigzell.&lt;/ref&gt;  based at [[Trentham Military Camp]], {{convert|30|km|mi}} north of [[Wellington]], New Zealand were sent to train with Z Special Unit in Melbourne, Australia. They were then sent to [[Fraser Commando School]], on [[Fraser Island]], Queensland, to be trained in using parachutes, unarmed combat, explosives and the [[Malay language]]. Four New Zealanders were killed during operations in Borneo.&lt;ref name=Wigzell&gt;Wigzell 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McGibbon 2000, p. 627.&lt;/ref&gt;

Major [[Donald Stott]] and Captain McMillan were both presumed drowned in heavy seas while going ashore in a rubber boat from the submarine {{USS|Perch|SS-313}} in [[Balikpapan]] Bay on 20 March 1945. Their bodies were never found. Warrant Officer Houghton made it to shore in a second boat but was captured ten days later and languished in Balikpapan Prison where he died of [[beriberi]] about 20 April 1945.&lt;ref name=Wigzell&gt;Wigzell 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

Signalman Ernie Myers parachuted into enemy-held territory near Mount Mentawir on 30 March 1945, but landed with two other operatives inside a Japanese camp area. They resisted strongly, but the Australian in the party was killed and Myers was captured along with the Malay interpreter of the group. Both men were tortured for three days, before being beheaded. Their bodies were recovered soon after the Japanese surrender when Lieutenant Bob Tapper, another New Zealander who was working with the War Graves Commission, discovered their remains. Evidence given to the commission by native witnesses ensured that the Japanese involved paid the penalty for this atrocity.&lt;ref name=Wigzell&gt;Wigzell 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Vessels allocated to Z Special Unit ==

=== Snake-class boats ===
{{details|Snake class junk}}

[[Image:HMAS Tiger Snake.jpg|thumb|300px|HMAS ''Tiger Snake'' in April 1945.]]
The SRD used a number of vessels for its operations in South East Asia. Over the course of 1944–45 SRD took control of four {{convert|66|ft|m}} trawlers that were constructed at the naval dockyard in [[Williamstown, Victoria|Williamstown]], Victoria.&lt;ref name=gunplot&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gunplot.net/zforce/srd.html|title=Royal Australian Navy Gun Plot: Services Reconnaissance Department|accessdate=16 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; These vessels were modified with more powerful engines and alterations were made to their superstructures in order to disguise them and make them look more like the types of vessels that were operating in the waters around South East Asia.&lt;ref name=gunplot/&gt; They were designated &quot;Snake-class&quot; boats. Later, two more were built but they were not completed in time to see service during the war.&lt;ref name=gunplot/&gt;

On operations the Snake-class vessels operated in tandem with a mother-ship.&lt;ref name=SRDmother&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gunplot.net/zforce/srd2.html|title=Royal Australian Navy Gun Plot: Z Special Unit&amp;nbsp;– SRD Mother Ships|accessdate=16 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; SRD operated two such vessels—HMAS ''Anaconda'' and HMAS ''Mother Snake''—both of which were {{convert|125|ft|m}} long wooden motor vessels.&lt;ref name=SRDmother/&gt; There was a third vessel laid down—AV 1358 (Greenogh)—but it did not see service with SRD during the war.&lt;ref name=SRDmother/&gt; With a crew of 14, these vessels were mainly crewed by a mixture of [[Royal Australian Navy]] and Australian Army personnel with a naval [[Lieutenant#Naval rank|lieutenant]] in command and an army [[Captain (land)|captain]] as chief officer. The boats were officially commissioned ships and were outfitted with two 300–320-[[horsepower]] diesel engines and armed with one [[Oerlikon 20 mm cannon|20mm Oerlikon]] as well as a number of assorted smaller machine guns.&lt;ref name=SRDmother/&gt;

Of the ''Snake''-class boats that saw service, at least three were used to deploy Z operatives with Hoehn military folboats in enemy occupied areas for reconnaissance or small scale raids. HMAS ''Riversnake'' went to Portuguese Timor, to deploy SUNCHARLIE operatives. HMAS ''Blacksnake'' deployed GIRAFFE and SWIFT operatives in the Celebes and HMAS ''Tigersnake'' sailed out of Sarawak to set down operatives of SEMUT IVB.&lt;ref&gt;Hoehn 2011, pp. 69&amp;ndash;71.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the war, the ''Anaconda'' remained in service until November 1946 when she was sold and converted into a fishing boat.&lt;ref name=SRDmother/&gt; The fate of the ''Mother Snake'' is unknown, although it is believed that she remained in Borneo after the war.&lt;ref name=SRDmother/&gt; The six Snake-class boats, however, along with the ''Krait'' were sold to the British Civil Administration in Borneo.&lt;ref name=gunplot/&gt; The MV ''Krait'' was originally restored in 1964 and used for training and recreation purposes by the Royal Volunteer Coastal Patrol. The vessel is part of the [[Australian War Memorial]]'s collection, on loan to the [[Australian National Maritime Museum]] in Darling Harbour, Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/encyclopedia/krait.asp|title=Encyclopedia: ''Krait''|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=18 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other vessels ===
*AL254 ''Charm'', a {{convert|47|ft|m}} [[lugger]].&lt;ref name=Register&gt;''Register of Army Small Craft covering the period 1943 to 1946''. Held by the Naval Historian at the Navy Office, Canberra.&lt;/ref&gt;
*AM355, an {{convert|18|ft|m|adj=on}} launch.&lt;ref name=&quot;Register&quot;/&gt;
*AB1184 ''3064'' and AB1185 ''3065'' (Both ALC15 [[landing craft]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Register&quot;/&gt;
*[[HMAS HDML 1321|HDML 1321]].&lt;ref&gt;Dennis 2006, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[HMAS HDML 1324|HDML 1324]].&lt;ref&gt;Horton 1983, p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
[[File:Rockingham Jetty 2.jpg|thumb|right|upright|120px|A commemorative plaque to the Z Special Unit at [[Rockingham, Western Australia|Rockingham]], Western Australia.]]

There is now a public memorial to the Z Special Unit on the esplanade in Cairns. It was moved from the naval base [[HMAS Cairns (naval base)|HMAS ''Cairns'']] and rededicated on 26 October 2007. Those present at the ceremony were original unit members George Buckingham, John Mackay and the then commander of Special Operations of the [[Australian Defence Force]], Major General [[Mike Hindmarsh]]. The [[Returned and Services League of Australia|RSL]] plans to erect a permanent display of military equipments nearby.&lt;ref&gt;[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation|ABC]] 2 TV News 1900 [[AEST]] 27 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/10/23/2066942.htm Memorial move prompts ceremony for Z Force soldiers]&amp;nbsp;– [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] 23 October 2007, retrieved on 28 August 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Z Special Unit Association (NSW Branch) was disbanded in March 2010 due to a decline in members and the Association's last Sydney ANZAC Day march was held in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.legacy.com.au/Assets/3845/1/SLEG_217328_AnnualReview_web.pdf |title=Sydney Legacy Annual Review, 2010–2011 |publisher=[[Legacy Australia]] |accessdate=22 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commemorative plaques to Z Special Unit have been placed on each lamp post on the new jetty at [[Rockingham, Western Australia|Rockingham]], Western Australia, and the activities of Z Special Unit have been depicted in several Australian films and TV series, including ''[[Attack Force Z]]'', ''[[The Highest Honor]]'', ''[[The Heroes (mini-series)|The Heroes]]'' and ''[[Heroes II: The Return]]''.

== See also ==
{{portal|Australia|World War II}}
*[[Allied Intelligence Bureau]]
*[[Services Reconnaissance Department]]
*[[Far Eastern Liaison Office]]
*[[Secret Intelligence Australia]]
*[[Netherlands East Indies Forces Intelligence Service]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Courtney|first=G.B.|title=Silent Feet: The History of 'Z' Special Operations 1942–1945|year=1993|publisher=R. J. and S. P. Austin|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn=978-0-64612-903-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Dennis|first=Don|title=The Guns of Muschu|year=2006|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Sydney, New South Wales |isbn=978-1-74114-878-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Dennis |first=Peter |title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History |publisher=Oxford University Press Australia &amp; New Zealand |location=Melbourne, Victoria |year=2008 |edition=Second |isbn=9780195517842|display-authors=etal}}
* {{cite book|last=Hoehn|first=John|title=Commando Kayak: The Role of the Folboat in the Pacific War|
year=2011|publisher=Hirsch Publishing |url=http://hirschbooks.net/|isbn=978-3-0330-1717-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Horton|first=Dick|title=Ring of Fire: Australian Guerilla Operations Against the Japanese in World War II|year=1983|publisher=Leo Cooper/Secker and Warburg; Melbourne|location=London|isbn=978-0-43620-157-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Horner|first=David|authorlink=David Horner|title=SAS: Phantoms of the Jungle-A History of the Australian Special Air Service|year=1989|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Sydney, New South Wales |isbn=0-04520-006-8}}
* {{cite book|last=McGibbon|first=Ian|title=The Oxford Companion to New Zealand Military History|year=2000|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=South Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=0-195-58376-0}}
* {{cite book|last=McKie|first=Ronald|authorlink=Ronald McKie|title=The Heroes: They Were Men of Z Force. Their Target–Singapore|year=1960|publisher=Angus &amp; Robertson|isbn=0 207 12133 8}}
* {{cite book|last=Powell|first=Alan|title=War by Stealth: Australians and the Allied Intelligence Bureau 1942–1945|year=1996|publisher=Melbourne University Press|location=Carlton South, Victoria |isbn=0-522-84691-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Sue|first=Jack Wong|authorlink=Jack Wong Sue|title=Blood on Borneo|year=2001|publisher=L. Smith (WA) |isbn=978-0-64641-656-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Thompson|first=Peter|author2=Macklin, Robert |title=Kill the Tiger: The Truth about Operation Rimau|year=2002|publisher=Hodder|isbn=978-0-73361-448-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Wigzell|first=Francis|title=New Zealand Army Involvement: Special Operations Australia–South-West Pacific World War II|year=2001|publisher=Pentland Press|isbn=978-1-85821-815-1}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=C.A.|title=The Official History of Special Operations – Australia. Volume 1: Organization|year=2011|publisher=SOA Books. Printed in Lexington, Kentucky|isbn=978-1-4611-4092-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=C.A.|title=The Official History of Special Operations – Australia. Volume 2: Operations|year=2011|publisher=SOA Books. Printed in Lexington, Kentucky|isbn=978-1-4611-9651-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=C.A.|title=The Official History of Special Operations – Australia. Volume 3: Communications|year=2012|publisher=SOA Books. Printed in Lexington, Kentucky|isbn=978-1-4636-7351-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=C.A.|title=The S.R.D. Technical Handbook: Weapons and Equipment of Z Special Unit|year=2012|publisher=SOA Books. Printed in Lexington, Kentucky|isbn=978-1-4781-7574-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Campbell|first=Lloyd|title=Z-Special: Desert–Jungle–Sabotage|year=2006|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|isbn=978-1-8764-3963-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Connell|first=Brian|title=Return of the Tiger|year=1971|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=978-0-3300-2763-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Feuer|first=A.B|title=Commando! The M/Z Unit's Secret War Against Japan|year=1996|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-2759-5408-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Feuer|first=A.B|title=Australian Commandos: Their Secret War Against the Japanese in World War II |year=2006|publisher=Stackpole Books|isbn=978-0-8117-3294-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Griffiths-Marsh|first=Roland|title=Sixpenny Soldier|year=1990|publisher=Collins-Angus &amp; Robertson|location=Australia|isbn= }} (Republished as: {{cite book|last=Griffiths-Marsh|first=Roland|title=I Was Only Sixteen |year=1995|publisher=ETT Imprint|location=Potts Point, New South Wales |isbn= 1-8758-9209-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Harrisson|first=Tom|authorlink=Tom Harrisson|title=World Within. A Borneo Story|year=1959|publisher=Cresset Press|location=London|oclc=736758 }}
* {{cite book|last=Ind|first=Allison|title=Allied Intelligence Bureau|year=1958|publisher=David Mckay Company Inc|location=New York|isbn=}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Bob|title='Z' Special Unit's Secret War: Operation Semut 1. Soldiering with the Head-hunters in Borneo|year=1999|publisher=Transpereon Press|location=Hornsby, New South Wales |isbn=0-9080-2115-1}}
* {{cite book|last=McDonald|first=Gabrielle|title=New Zealand's Secret Heroes: Don Stott And The 'Z' Special Unit|year=1991|publisher=Reed|isbn=978-0-7900-0216-3}}
* {{cite book|last=McKie|first=Ronald|authorlink=Ronald McKie|title=The Heroes: Daring Raiders of the Pacific War|year=1994|publisher=Angus &amp; Robertson|location=Sydney, New South Wales|isbn=0-2071-8438-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Silver|first=Lynette Ramsay|title=The Heroes of Rimau|year=1991|publisher=S.A. Majeed|isbn=978-9-8389-9156-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Thomas|first=Richard|title=Never Ever Volunteer|year=2002|publisher=Regal Publications|isbn=1-876261-18-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Waddy|first=Rowan|title=On Operations with Z Special Unit&amp;nbsp;– WWII|year=1995|publisher=Rowan E. Waddy|location=Collaroy, New South Wales |isbn=}}
* {{cite book|last=Wigzell|first=Francis Alexander|title=Blood Brotherz|year=2013|publisher=Lulu.com}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Z Special Unit}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160112084609/http://specialoperationsaustralia.com/soa/ Special Operations Australia website] 
* [http://www.gunsofmuschu.com/ The Guns of Muschu]
* [http://www.abc.net.au/news/video/2008/11/24/2427889.htm RSL lays Yass soldier to rest] – Video is expired.
* [http://www.dva.gov.au/media/publicat/2003/jaywick/ Australian Department of Veterans Affairs, 2003, 'Operation Jaywick, 60th Anniversary'] – HTTP 404 Not Found.
* [http://www.specialforcesroh.com/browse.php?mode=viewc&amp;catid=43 Roll of Honour, Awards and Images]
* [http://www.abc.net.au/news/video/2010/08/20/2989314.htm ABC, 2010, Z Special Unit reunion at Fraser Island] – Video is expired.

{{Australian Commando units of the Second World War}}
{{Aust SF}}
{{Australian Commando raids of the Second World War}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Z Special Unit}}
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1942]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1946]]
[[Category:Military units and formations of Australia in World War II]]
[[Category:Military units and formations of the Australian Army]]
[[Category:Special forces of Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>ci4cyp2n7fjtlf9bkoacicrcethv6x3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
