<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Operation Storm</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1080897</id>
    <revision>
      <id>707799023</id>
      <parentid>681962210</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-01T21:25:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zoupan</username>
        <id>13128142</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Mass graves unearthed after March 2012 */ new section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="62369">{{talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WPR
|action1date=00:28, 25 July 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/Operation Storm
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=65658355

|action2=GAN
|action2date=10:36, 28 January 2013
|action2link=Talk:Operation Storm/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=535010971

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war

|action3=WAR
|action3date=11:03, 27 March 2013 (UTC)
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Operation Storm
|action3result=approved
|action3oldid=547089101
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell
|1=
{{WPMILHIST
|class=A
|A-Class=pass
|Balkan=yes
|old-peer-review=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Bosnia and Herzegovina|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Republika Srpska|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Serbia|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Yugoslavia|class=GA|importance=High}}
}}
{{British English}}
{{GOCE |user=Tucoxn |date=22 March 2013}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2015-08-04|oldid1=674582445|date2=2015-08-05|oldid2=674327766}}

== Improvement ==

You should expand the part at the end concering the appeal process. Nothing is written there.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/78.3.76.172|78.3.76.172]] ([[User talk:78.3.76.172|talk]]) 13:40, 22 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: A fair bit is indeed written about the appeal process, but the last paragraph was making it seem everything was written in a purely chronological manner, which wasn't the case; I fixed it. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 07:38, 23 November 2012 (UTC)

== Civilian casulties ==

324 was number from prosecution, but of these only 44 is finaly proved during trial. And second number ( 677 ) is from HHO document which is dissmissed by court as invalid.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.137.146.54|90.137.146.54]] ([[User talk:90.137.146.54|talk]]) 21:20, 23 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Citation needed for the Court dismissing the HHO document. [[User:GregorB|GregorB]] ([[User talk:GregorB|talk]]) 22:27, 23 November 2012 (UTC)
Well this information is provided to public by  Mr.Gotovina Lawyer during Political TV Talk show, 
i can provide link to the show. http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZoblecrdvNI , iam not sure is that enought...especialy becouse it's on croatian. There he explained why ICTY used 324 list on trial and not HHO victim list. ( basicly HHO had no evidence for their list ). If this is not enough i guess somebody will need to dig on ICTY documentation.
:HHO collects data, does field research, but does not conduct investigations. The ICTY, on the other hand, does not aim to enumerate all victims, as their objective is prosecution, not statistics or history. There is a popular misconception that the casualty figure put forward by the ICTY somehow &quot;proves&quot; HHO's numbers are wrong or even fraudulent. Gotovina's lawyers certainly did want people to think that way, all in the interest of their client - they were doing their job, of course, but that's precisely what makes them unreliable, whether they said it in Croatian or not. [[User:GregorB|GregorB]] ([[User talk:GregorB|talk]]) 10:12, 24 November 2012 (UTC)
You are right that Gotovina Lawyer never said that 44 is final number of civilian casulties. But nevertheless...fact that procecussion could not prove anything form HHO list, and only 13% of the second list is indication that those lists are not good sources.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.137.149.131|90.137.149.131]] ([[User talk:90.137.149.131|talk]]) 09:36, 25 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:But IIRC HHO's list is a list of ''all'' civilian casualties, including collateral ones. That's why I don't think it makes sense to speak of percentages or a &quot;hit rate&quot; - the lists don't have the same purpose, so they ''must'' diverge significantly. The article should clarify that: 677 in the HHO's list doesn't mean they claim 677 people were murdered. [[User:GregorB|GregorB]] ([[User talk:GregorB|talk]]) 11:51, 25 November 2012 (UTC)

Problem is not just with with that...i will cite Mr.Gotovina Lawyer..actualy not cite but rather very freely translate his word about it and shot little bit...original is in provided link: &quot;''when Mr.Puhovski come on court to testifie, he told that HHO don't have any prove that list is valid, there is no background material from which court can analyse what is true from list and what is false...that's why ICTY disimissed that list.''&quot; 
So it's not problem that HHO saying...''this is list of 677 civilian victims, but we don't know which victim from that list are murdered and which are colateral victim''...but HHO basicly saying ( on court ) : ''we don't have a clue from where we get this list!!''
:I don't agree with this analysis. Not being able to determine the circumstances of death does not mean that the list fell from the sky, especially if people in it are dead. [[User:GregorB|GregorB]] ([[User talk:GregorB|talk]]) 23:02, 25 November 2012 (UTC)

The HHO report is indeed controversial - on one side Mr Čičak claims that it is more than correct, and on the other hand we have Mr Puhovski testamony and the following verdict of the ICTY: http://www.icty.org/x/cases/gotovina/tjug/en/110415_judgement_vol1.pdf (p.30)
&quot;50. Exhibit P2402 is a report entitled “Military Operation Storm and its Aftermath,”
published by the Croatian Helsinki Committee and edited by Žarko Puhovski.110 The
report contains un-sourced statements and double entries.111 Furthermore, during
examination of Puhovski in court it became apparent that there were errors in the
book.112 For these reasons, the Trial Chamber decided not to rely on exhibit P2402 in
relation to information described therein if uncorroborated by other evidence.&quot;

The question is can number of 677 killed stand as reliable at all (it is written in the box at the beginning of the article)? Further, even if it stays, in my opinion, it should be stated that 677 does not make any difference between casualties-of-war and war-crime-victims. 
[[Special:Contributions/188.129.85.245|188.129.85.245]] ([[User talk:188.129.85.245|talk]]) 16:18, 9 January 2013 (UTC)

------------------------
If you quote source number 218 (http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-11-16/un-war-crimes-court-frees-croatian-generals/4377178) as reliable, then you certainly also want to qoute in the section on &quot;Refugee crisis&quot; that prosecutors claim that &quot;close to 90,000 Serbs were forcibly displaced&quot;. In the box at the right hand side at the beginning of the article, in the section &quot;Casualties and losses&quot;, you also want to change &quot;Refugees: 150,000–200,000 Serbs from the former RSK&quot; to &quot;Refugees: 90,000–200,000 Serbs from the former RSK&quot;. Am I right?

00:20, 25 November 2014 (UTC)

==324 killed==

The problem is that - again contradictory to rules of supporting documents and reliable sources - the text says that &quot;ICTY has concluded that a total of 324 people, both civilians and soldiers were killed.[10][180&quot;. This information is not correct based on the sources. 
Namely, reference no 180, which is the Judgement of the Court NOWHERE mentions 324 killed. 
Reference no 10, is actually an extract at the ICTY portal, which states that &quot;The three stand accused of aiding and abetting the murders of 324&quot; - therefore, this is a prosecution number and NOT that the Court confirmed the number. 

The sentence below states &quot;Before the numbers were official...&quot; - but we can see that the numbers are not official or correct.

Secondly, it is stated that &quot;At least 150,000 Serb civilians left the Krajina before the operation.[181&quot; - there are two problems with this - one is that there is NO article at reference 181 - and second, even if it was - why would this source be reliable and based on - again - what reliable sources?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/188.129.85.245|188.129.85.245]] ([[User talk:188.129.85.245|talk]]) 14:12, 9 January 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

-------------
Further, mentioned source no 218 (http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-11-16/un-war-crimes-court-frees-croatian-generals/4377178) states that prosecution claimed there were 324 civilian deaths. This source is contradictory to the ICTY indictment (http://www.icty.org/x/cases/gotovina/ind/en/got-ai040224e.htm) from which it is obvious that actual prosecution number of murders by Croatian army is &quot;at least 150 Krajina Serbs&quot;, and further, specifically referred to in Indictment are 32 murders. Further, actual number of &quot;killing incidents&quot; by prosecution was later set to 37 (http://www.icty.org/x/cases/gotovina/ind/en/got-coramdjoind080312e.pdf). I would like to point out that number of &quot;324 civilian deaths&quot; (even if correct) implies that there are &quot;324 civilian Serb deaths, caused by Croatian army&quot;, which is obviously not correct. So, I recommend that text is changed accordingly.
[[Special:Contributions/188.129.39.22|188.129.39.22]] ([[User talk:188.129.39.22|talk]]) 00:22, 25 November 2014 (UTC)

==Carl Bildt==

Since Carl Bildt is well documented Serbian advocate and the person who, among other things, accused Croats and Bosniaks for Srebrenica massacre, and the person who advocated Milošević that people should be taken out of RSK before the Operation Storm so that Croatia can be accused for ethnic cleansing, I strongly recommend that his quotes are removed from the text as biased and unobjective. If we go this way, we could easily quote also Vojislav Šešelj about the Operation Storm.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/188.129.85.245|188.129.85.245]] ([[User talk:188.129.85.245|talk]]) 14:22, 9 January 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Add Agim Çeku as commanders on Croatian side ==


Various independent sources write that Agim Çeku was one of the most important commanders of Operation Storm.

For instance: http://www.balkanstudies.org/blog/agim-ceku-war-criminal-not-wanted-canada

&quot;By summer of 1995, when Croatians launched the massive offensive, code-named Operation Storm, to fully reclaim the Krajina, Ceku had completely recovered, been promoted to brigadier-general and was the commander of all Croatian artillery.&quot;

Another source from Government of Kosovo:
&quot;In 1995 Mr. Çeku was appointed Chief of Staff of the Military District of Gospiq. In this position he commanded forces of this district in the offensive operation called “Stuhia” (“Storm”) as well as other operations in Bosnia and Herzegovina up to the Dayton Agreement.&quot;

Invitation by government of Croatia: http://www.kosovapress.com/?cid=2,92,150647

&quot;Minister Çeku was invited by the Government of the Republic of Croatia to participate in this anniversary, as one of the key persons in this operation by which Croatia liberated its territories occupied by Serb army at that time.

Central manifestation connected to this event will be held in 04 and 05 August in Knin.&quot;  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/37.123.175.27|37.123.175.27]] ([[User talk:37.123.175.27|talk]]) 15:45, 17 January 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Hi! Regarding the balkanstudies source - it is not a WP:RS - it is a blog. The Kosovo Govt source is simply wrong - Çeku was 3rd in command in Gospić Corps (Norac was commander then, Ademi was his deputy, then Çeku) see Ministry of Defence source (Davor Marijan: Oluja, page 82). As the 3rd in command of any HV corps, Ademi would normally be invited to participate in the celebration.--[[User:Tomobe03|Tomobe03]] ([[User talk:Tomobe03|talk]]) 15:50, 17 January 2013 (UTC)

:Regarding the artillery billet, Çeku was corps artillery commander in sector S1 (see [http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=28824 this source], page 65) since 1993--[[User:Tomobe03|Tomobe03]] ([[User talk:Tomobe03|talk]]) 16:05, 17 January 2013 (UTC).

:It is not uncommon to see newspaper articles saying in a headline that someone was commanding artillery (implying all of it) in the Operation Storm, like [http://www.slobodnadalmacija.hr/Hrvatska/tabid/66/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/136456/Default.aspx in this case], when it was simply not so. In this case the article is an interview with Brigadier Marko Rajčić, who held a similar post as Çeku, except that he was artillery commander in the Split Corps (see [http://www.tportal.hr/vijesti/hrvatska/11470/Marko-Rajcic-otkriva-tajnu-topnickih-dnevnika.html#.UPgjTiqF-24 here]).--[[User:Tomobe03|Tomobe03]] ([[User talk:Tomobe03|talk]]) 16:16, 17 January 2013 (UTC)

== GA Review ==

Please see http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Operation_Storm/GA1 for details on this articles GA review.

I have put the article on hold until improvements are made.[[User:Retrolord|Retrolord]] ([[User talk:Retrolord|talk]]) 09:59, 28 January 2013 (UTC)

[[User:Retrolord|Retrolord]] ([[User talk:Retrolord|talk]]) 10:02, 28 January 2013 (UTC)

== [[Operation Storm#Order of battle]]: Croatian special police ==

Were the &quot;Croatian special police&quot; listed in this section actually the [[Lučko Anti-Terrorist Unit]]?  This unit is listed as being created in 1990 and &quot;was the first Croatian fighting unit in the [[Croatian War of Independence]]&quot; according to its WP article.  I noticed that the articles weren't linked as part of a requested major copyedit.  Thanks! - &lt;b&gt;[[User:Tucoxn|&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; color=&quot;#522C1B&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;+1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Unicode&quot;&gt;&amp;#x0288;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;u&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#417DC1&quot;&gt;coxn&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/b&gt;\&lt;font face=&quot;serif&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Tucoxn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 00:27, 5 March 2013 (UTC)
:The Lućko ATU is one of the special police units involved. As a matter of fact each of the twenty counties in Croatia had a special police unit attached to the county police command. The Lučko ATU was assigned to Zagreb and Zagreb County. There's simply no way of knowing from the sources of otherwise which articular unit(s) were there, but on the other hand, most of the special police units were grouped at the Velebit Mts (except maybe one or two). In short, linking Lučko ATU would be wrong there.--[[User:Tomobe03|Tomobe03]] ([[User talk:Tomobe03|talk]]) 01:24, 5 March 2013 (UTC)

== Krbava Polje ==

There seems to be a bug in [[:template:lang]] that is not permitting the following to parse correctly in mainspace:&lt;/br&gt;
:&quot;approaching from the opposite side of the [[Krbava|Krbava {{lang|hr|Polje}}]] ({{lang-hr|[[Polje]]}} or [[karst|karst field]])&quot;&lt;/br&gt;
:Here is the code: &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;&quot;approaching from the opposite side of the [[Krbava|Krbava {{lang|hr|Polje}}]] ({{lang-hr|[[Polje]]}} or [[karst|karst field]])&quot;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
It's parsing correctly in user space, talk space, and usertalk space.&lt;/br&gt;
Hopefully the bug will be repaired soon.&lt;/br&gt;
- &lt;b&gt;[[User:Tucoxn|&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; color=&quot;#522C1B&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;+1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Unicode&quot;&gt;&amp;#x0288;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;u&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#417DC1&quot;&gt;coxn&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/b&gt;\&lt;font face=&quot;serif&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Tucoxn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 01:45, 12 March 2013 (UTC)

::I'm finished with the copyedit. Please accept my apologies for taking so long to complete it. This is truly a very good article! - &lt;b&gt;[[User:Tucoxn|&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; color=&quot;#522C1B&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;+1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Unicode&quot;&gt;&amp;#x0288;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;u&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#417DC1&quot;&gt;coxn&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/b&gt;\&lt;font face=&quot;serif&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Tucoxn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 04:49, 22 March 2013 (UTC)

== Qualification of &quot;Ethnic Cleansing&quot; and independent experts' opinion ==

That is not [http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie-Janine_Calic Marie-Janine Calic]'s (a German historian, of Croat ethnic background; herself also with a personal insight working for the UN in Croatia in 1995) personal opinion, as supposedly presented in Tomobe03's comment. She was only in the leader of a team of many authors which worked under her on that chapter. Many other historians and other experts worked on that chapter - Americans [http://globalcenters.columbia.edu/istanbul/profile-wind_ldap/291 Elazar Barkan], [http://www.ceu.hu/profiles/faculty/elissa_helms Elissa Helms], [http://www.uea.ac.uk/history/People/Academic/Cathie+Carmichael Cathie Carmichael], [http://ba.linkedin.com/pub/james-lyon/2/936/916 James Lyon], [[Norman Naimark]] and Lana Obradović, Austrians [http://iog.univie.ac.at/personal/ehemalige-mitarbeiter/ Horst Haselsteiner] and [http://www.andrassyuni.eu/mitteleuropische-studien/mitarbeiter/professoren/prof-dr-habil-georg-kastner Georg Kastner], as well as France's [[Jacques Sémelin]]; and a number of other experts from across the world. 

Therefore, it cannot be considered as Calic's personal viewpoint in no way, she being just among the team coordinators of those in the research team associated for investigating the ethnic cleansing which had occurred during the Yugoslav Wars in 1991-1995. I reckon that it ''does'' warrant enough to be included already in the introduction, because the ''Scholars' Initiative'' led by US historical experts [http://www.cla.purdue.edu/history/facstaff/Ingrao/H-Ingrao.htm Charles W. Ingrao] and [http://www.thepress.purdue.edu/contributors/thomas-emmert Thomas A. Emmert], engulf a vast international project numbering ''over 170 social studies experts'' from across the globe with an effort to try to avoid the many biased points of view and controversies with an objective as possible, at least so far (them themselves admitting that before not long most likely a new version is to be expected with the resurgence of some new facts and new sources). This a unique such project and therefore deserves considering all the facts a significant place in this article, especially due to the [[WP:NPOV|NPOV]] aims. It cannot be said that the participants of the project are not sufficiently relevant, and their position especially cannot be perceived as being somewhat pro-Serbian one; AFAIK if the participants from Serbia who took part in the project are observed, we can rather claim something completely different due to the mere fact that some of them are quite controversially and unpopular persons in Serbia, due to their demystifying and highly critical approach to the country's policies during its darker past in the 1990s; this goes especially more for their Western colleagues. 

The current composition of this article is biased, sharing too much a Croatian POV of Operation Storm and the encircling events. Operation Storm still today remains one of the major controversies of the 1990s Yugoslav wars, and a short notification of a personal opinion of EU emissary [[Carl Bildt]] does not do it justice. I've already mentioned the troubles of presenting this as Calic's personal point of view, but rather the result of a decade-long research on the part of a major (and individually speaking largest, in the world of humanities unprecedented) international initiative aimed at an effort to sum up the most recent professional literature and try to give an as much objective and expert explanation on the story behind the complex issue of SFRY's dissolution. Nothing less preposterous is putting up Galbraith's opinion, regardless how individually very important for the article overall it is, as some sort of a counterweight to that which is most definitely not Calic's personal opinion. 

The article should neutrally reflect that for the Serbs it is almost unanimous that Operation Storm had constituted ''ethnic cleansing'', a position expressed widely by experts in the issue, the political elite as well as wide-spread public opinion. According to [http://www.f.bg.ac.rs/en2/chistory/dep_staff Serbian historian Miloš Ković, PhD, professor at Belgrade's Faculty of Philosophy], Operation Storm also is to attain the key element of the modern Serbian national identity (in accordance to the theory of major suffering being the backbone of a nation's construction). The Serbian position is also clearly presented with the Genocide Convention violations raised against Croatia recently over at the [[International Court of Justice]]. This article also contains no reference at all to the [[Thematic debate on the role of international criminal justice in reconciliation]], which was precisely initiated by the President of the United Nations General Assembly [[Vuk Jeremić]] due to the ICTY Appeal Chamber's judgement. While the open discussion has raised a considerable amount of controversy in itself (as a manifestation of those who want to somehow revise the decisions of the ICTY - which in its effect it actually is), it ''does'' show that there is also a considerable amount of those who are ''not'' Serbs and who view the acquittal of Gotovina and Markac scandalous - and who ''do'' consider Operation Storm as being an example of &quot;ethnic cleansing&quot;. 

It should also be noteworthy that such an opinion is significantly shared by a number of independent scholars, which includes of course most notably Ingrao's ''Confronting the Yugoslav Controversies''. I am not saying that the article should point out that Operation Storm is a text-book example of ethnic cleansing, comparing it somehow to the ethnic cleansing operations committed by the Serbs' paramilitary and military forces during the early 1990s against non-Serbs (Croats and Bosnian Muslims), in any sort of an effort to attempt to somehow balance the Croatian and Serbian sides in the war and thus present an artificial point of view which is not in the encyclopaedic traditions I think should be (are?) also valid in the Wikipedia. Not even all of the 150-200 humanities experts that took part in Ingrao's project share the opinion and I think a number would even perhaps oppose the presentation of the operation as &quot;ethnic cleansing&quot;. However, that won't change the conclusion reached by Calic and her team-members, researching the &quot;ethnic cleansing&quot; of the early 1990s Yugoslavian wars. 

The independent team of experts is not the only one, as there are even, more and more, examples from the Croatian side upholding that Operation Storm was an ethnic cleansing campaign, e.g. [http://www.politika.rs/rubrike/tema-dana/Puhovski-Oluja-je-bila-etnichko-chishcenje-Srba.lt.html notable humanitarian Žarko Puhovski]. The opinion is [http://www.nezavisne.com/novosti/feljton/Protjerivanje-Srba-96752.html to some extent shared] by the University of Split professor, Nikola Visković, PhD, who rather points the deeper roots of the campaign of ethnic hatred that was a basis for the ethnic cleansing of Serbs all the way to the beginning of the war in the early 1990s. The list also includes [http://www.index.hr/vijesti/clanak/nobilo-sekundarni-cilj-quotolujequot-bilo-je-etnicko-ciscenje/268866.aspx lawyer Anto Nobilo], who considers that ethnic cleansing was a &quot;secondary goal&quot; of the military offensive, also if I recall well noting that while both the Croatian and Serbian genocide charges at the ICJ have absolutely no chance, the Serbian case has due to precisely Operation Storm some more validity containing some elements of genocide. Although I have no doubt the Appeal Chamber's overturning final verdict will slow down this trend, it appears that as more and more time passes various individuals in the Republic of Croatia are prone to either think again about their previous convictions, questioning them again, or speak out their opinion that Operation Storm had indeed constituted ''ethnic cleansing''. 

This article grossly violated the attempts to maintain a neutral point of view, adopting a Croatian POV and misplacing a neutral middle for a Serb POV. The article is supposed to be an academic channel of thought relying on available sources in an effort to present a neutral opinion, and is not a judicial body obligated to follow previous verdicts. The reader could not find from the article the fact that the Appeal Chamber's verdict is probably the most controversial of all of the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]]'s trials, but would be mislead to think that the Appeal Chamber had unanimously overturned the initial Trial Chamber's verdict due to some error originally made. However, that is far from the case, as the Appeal Chamber had brought this verdict with a ''very thin'' majority of 3 to 2. This verdict is unique due to the amount of public voice the two dissenting judges raised, as well as the harshness of their dissenting opinions; both [http://www.maltatoday.com.mt/en/newsdetails/news/courtandpolice/Judge-hits-out-at-confusing-extremely-problematic-acquittal-of-Gotovina-Markac-20121117 Judge Carmel Agius] and [http://www.b92.net/eng/news/politics.php?yyyy=2012&amp;mm=11&amp;dd=17&amp;nav_id=83206 Judge Fausto Pocar] have expressed grave concerns that the Appeal Chamber's Majority has willingly ignored blatant evidence and has endangered their own legitimacy to continue to work at The Tribunal. The Wikipedian article on Operation Storm should neutrally not ignore the fact that the ICTY Appeal Chamber had acquitted the Croatian generals and overturned the original perception of the &quot;joint criminal enterprise&quot;, but as an academic source of information it should not ignore the plain fact that ''five out of eight'' international legal experts at the ICTY, meaning ''a '''majority''''', do not share that opinion but rather agree with the perception of ethnic cleansing being a manifestation of Operation Storm. This goes along with the clearly quite critical position of the ICTY's Office of the Prosecutor, currently led by Serge Brammertz, which [http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/serbia-to-prosecute-crimes-committed-in-storm maintains a legal obligation to acknowledge it but notes that it does not agree with the verdict and upholds that the criminal responsibility and the JCE have been proven] - something the ICTY Prosecution seldom, if ever, does. The Wikipedian article on Operation Storm should also include the allegations that [http://iwpr.net/report-news/hague-prosecutor-appeal-controversial-acquittals Brammertz might apply for a review of the final verdict] as per demanded by independent analysts and Serb organizations, if some new evidence emerges. Significantly relevant should also be the opinion of former ICTY chief prosecutor and the one who drafter the indictment against Gotovina, Čermak and Markač, [[Carla Del Ponte]], who [http://www.b92.net/eng/news/politics.php?yyyy=2012&amp;mm=11&amp;dd=20&amp;nav_id=83250 viciously criticized the controversial judgement and in hard words expressed her shock at it]. The final point which ''especially'' marks the acquittals a controversy, none can definitely deny, is the recent accusations publicly raised [http://www.bt.dk/udland/english-version-murderers-are-being-allowed-to-go-free by Judge Frederick Harhoff, claiming that his colleague at the ICTY President Theodore Meron had personally influenced the outcome of the verdict, arguably due to outside political pressure]. According to Harhoff, there was a majority in favor of an upholding verdict but virtually in the very last minute had Meron managed to convince Judge Mehmet Güney to change his mind. There is obviously some truth to this, since it is clear that the [http://www.icty.org/x/cases/gotovina/acjug/en/121116_judgement.pdf ICTY Appeal Chamber verdict, just some 50 or so pages long], was very hastily written, whereas [http://www.icty.org/x/cases/gotovina/tjug/en/110415_judgement_vol2.pdf the original two-book Trial Chamber judgement was a very long and elaborate document numbering almost 1,400 pages]. And lastly but not the least importantly, some of the documents released by the [[Wikileaks]] might incriminate Meron's judicial independence and show at least some credibility to Harhoff's claims. Judge Harhoff is also among people of credible voice who consider that ethnic cleansing had occurred in Operation Storm. 

This, or better said most of these problems, all shares the [[Trial of Gotovina et al]] article too. Neither of these articles acknowledges the huge controversy that surrounds Operation &quot;Storm&quot;, thus also presenting a very biased point of view. It is also very problematic to leave the controversy for one paragraph in the end and omit its neutral presentation in the intro too - which, if I may add, is even currently not the case, the entire controversy boiled down to a statement by an EU representative, which is shared by Marie-Janin Calic (the latter being, as I've explained to the above, false). And yet, this very article mentioned in the ''Background'' section the Krajina Serb-committed ethnic cleansing campaign during the early 1990s as an objective and undeniable fact - which, despite being truthfully sources and not disputed by me, compromises the article's neutrality because of the aforementioned reasons. In a comparison's effort, the [[Bosnian Genocide Case]] article not only underlines that the judgement was ''not'' unanimous, but also in short summarizes the opinion of one single man, one of the 2 of the total 15-member Panel that acquitted Serbia of its implication in the Bosnian genocide - and yes, already in the introduction. 

In short, the article offers a significantly biased article that could lead to the genesis or spread of misinformation on this very controversial event. It undermines the [http://www.ipsnews.net/2012/11/acquittal-in-the-hague-sparks-controversy/ significant amount of controversy] that the ICTY Appeal Chamber's problematic verdict had erupted, reactions from prominent intellectuals to NGOs, e.g. the [http://pescanik.net/2012/11/o-oslobadajucoj-presudi-gotovini-i-markacu/ response] of [[Nataša Kandić]]'s Fund for Humanitarian Law. It should be as presented in [http://pescanik.net/2012/11/the-gotovina-omnishambles/ this ''Pescanik'' article] - a big controversy remains over whether Operation Storm represents ethnic cleansing, with the Croats continually reminding that the Appeal Chamber's verdict that in a way absolved their nation-state leadership's responsibility, and the Serbs not less constantly reminding that a majority (5 out of 8) of the ICTY judges considers that ethnic cleansing had indeed occurred under it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:PurdueIngrao|PurdueIngrao]] ([[User talk:PurdueIngrao|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/PurdueIngrao|contribs]]) 17:57, 21 July 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: Talk about walls of text... let's get back to basics: with articles of non-trivial length, the lead section serves to summarize the article content. You don't plaster it with whatever particular view using a specific reference that is not already used in the article, especially a known non-consensus view, and then edit-war to keep it in [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Operation_Storm&amp;diff=564566530&amp;oldid=563518976][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Operation_Storm&amp;diff=564987943&amp;oldid=564568096][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Operation_Storm&amp;diff=565222790&amp;oldid=564989099]. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 06:59, 22 July 2013 (UTC)

: Also, invoking all those other articles, including the [[thematic debate on the role of international criminal justice in reconciliation]] so early (apparently &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/11/world/denouncing-serbian-tilt-us-boycotts-un-meeting.html?_r=0 a thinly disguised Serb complaint forum]&quot;), makes me think you need to shed some bias of your own. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 07:12, 22 July 2013 (UTC)

:: I apologize for the great length of text, I wanted to present my case clearly and seriously; I would have chosen fewer words if I knew they could've been clearer and made a more significant impact (and considering the time that you Wikipedian authors take to actually write and especially follow all these articles, it is also understandable that my lengthy exposition is quite time-consuming). 

:: I understand your comment and understand that the intro serves for the purpose of summarizing the article. I do not have the free time, or even necessary experience to overtake a significant rewrite which this article much needs, and in addition to that if I started an ëdit war&quot; over just one little sentence think what could happen if I actually started to edit large chunks of the text, including a major review of the ''War crimes'' subsection. The whole post was more the sort of a guideline for those who have the time, will and experience to correct the article and by reducing Croatian POV, to which it is currently significantly aligned, make it more neutral. Perhaps you would be willing to assist? 

:: Of course I admit that I am biased and that I need and will continue to shed some bias as I have done so in the past. We are after all students our entire lives. It is my will to gain a more neutral and scientific observation on the 1990s wars as well as Operation Storm in specific, but I cannot pretend that I am somehow not biased. Due to my life-long personal experience, including direct environment as well sources of information I've picked, it would be plausible to say that I might present a Serb POV rather than a neutral one. It is one of the reasons why I am a bit hesitant to undertake the article's partial rewrite; even before considering such a thing you have already on the Talk page questioned (and most probably rightfully assumed) that I share a biased point of view, in many ways towards the Serbian side in the conflict. I think it is natural to assume that because of similar reasons ''you'' are also biased, probably in at least some ways leaning towards the Croatian side of the coin. We are biased most of the time that we would not even think, and that is e.g. especially what the authors of the ''Confronting the Yugoslav Controversies: A Scholars' Initiative'' noted in the preface as a specific problem in attempting to find the truth somewhere in the middle. 

:: However your comment about the possible indications of my bias is a bit misplaced. While it is true that I have selective chosen different links, that all together combined could very easily paint the image of Operation Storm being a military offensive with a criminal underlining goal conceived by the Croatian state and military leadership, in the aims of solving the Serb national question in Croatia through use of ethnic cleansing - the assumption you've made drives that fact out of context, and the context is that the sources (many of which are relevant) I've linked in my text prove that the current version of the article is greatly biased and in essence presenting a Croatian POV of the military operation, instead of a neutral one. 

:: I have no idea what you meant by my invocation of the Debate at the UN GA. I merely pointed out that such a major event and the direct results of ICTY's Appeal Chamber's verdict are not in this article at all and they should be - along with the not in any way insignificant denouncements which dismiss it as a Serbian revisionist attempt, initialed due to anger at the most recent ICTY judgements. I in no way hinted that the held debate somehow ''proves'' some precise fact about Operation Storm; I merely wanted to point out that this article omits it. The way you react to my writing, it seems almost as if you're opposed to this data's inclusion merely because it does not align with the Croatian POV. The debate was not disguised at all; UN GA President Jeremić had clearly indicated that the reason for its scheduling ''was'' the acquittal of Gotovina and Markač, in what is arguably ICTY's most controversial trial to date. Various relevant political factors which are non-Serbian have expressed more or less a similar view to the Serb when it comes to the acquittals of Gotovina &amp; Markac. A number individuals, who are not Serbs or come from Serbia, wrote in support or directly participated at the debate, including a member of Appeal Chamber from the ''Gotovina et al'' case (Judge Fausto Pocar). The political motifs of the leadership in Belgrade and the Serbian UN GA President that might lie in the roots of the debate, but it still does change the mere fact that the debate itself shows that there is a considerable amount of people who ''do not agree'' with the ICTY Appeal Chamber's final judgement, or at least question it to a major extent. It alone, in combination with a number of other factors I've mentioned, such as the international ''Scholars' Initiative'' headed by Ingrao and Emmert, serves to prove that '''Operation Storm''' is one of the most controversial events of the entire 1990s Yugoslav wars - according to one interpretation it was an offensive against a secessionist entity that reintegrated those areas into the mother-state, and led to a relatively (proportionally?) tolerable number of individual incidents that constitute war crimes; according to another, it was an ethnic cleansing campaign...  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:PurdueIngrao|PurdueIngrao]] ([[User talk:PurdueIngrao|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/PurdueIngrao|contribs]]) 17:18, 23 July 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::: The thing is, the encyclopedic description of these interpretations needs to start with the basic description of who thinks exactly what, as opposed to saying &quot;some consider it to be exceptionally horrible&quot; + 1 ref. See [[WP:WEASEL]] and [[WP:EXCEPTIONAL]].
::: I'm not even saying that your main source is bad - heck, it's already used in the article. But it needs to be presented in a neutral manner.
::: I personally don't think the article is currently slanted towards a &quot;Croatian&quot; point of view - it primarily describes the military operation itself but it doesn't omit the description of the aftermath, the refugee crisis, or the war crimes prosecution. Perhaps that's slanted in and of itself, but if the article title clearly defines its scope to be the specific military operation, then that's what it should focus on.
::: Earlier, I also suggested we start making new general articles about the aftermath, and indeed the Trial of Gotovina et al article was created exactly in that vein - it focuses on that particular aspect. I wouldn't see any problem in starting a new article called, say [[Aftermath of Operation Storm]]. Heck, now that I see you added the exact same phrasing in the [[Operation Flash]] article, it's fairly clear that your main goal was to describe Croatian war policies as the common denominator of these individual operations - so this should be generalized into [[Aftermath of the Croatian War of Independence]]. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 07:50, 25 July 2013 (UTC)
::: Also, thank you for coming clean about your biases, but it's really the way you present these sources is what is controversial - Marie-Janine Calic's chapter of that book clearly talks about numerous other examples of, in her opinion, ethnic cleansing during the Yugoslav Wars, yet you made it a point to add her only in these two articles. If you had added the same information to all those other articles, it wouldn't be seen as improper. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 07:57, 25 July 2013 (UTC)

:I am sorry, but your prose is quite hard to follow, and this post is a bit [[WP:TLDR]]. Could you provide half a dozen dot points that explain what it is you think should be included, along with the source for each (including page)? Thanks, [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 23:11, 23 July 2013 (UTC)

==Contradiction==
In the lead, it is mentioned that the Army of the Republika Srpska (VRS) did not intervene in the battle, and yet in the infobox it is listed as a combatant. Why is this? [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 20:26, 21 July 2013 (UTC)

== sources for the evacuation of civilians ==

The [[Croatian War of Independence]] article, which generally tends to be overly verbose, currently says on the topic:

: Many of the civilian population of the occupied areas fled during the offensive or immediately after its completion, in what was later described in various terms ranging from expulsion to planned evacuation.&lt;ref name=&quot;LATimes-Storm-Complete&quot;&gt;{{cite news | newspaper= Los Angeles Times | url = http://articles.latimes.com/1995-08-08/news/mn-32662_1_serb-refugees | title = Croats Declare Victory, End Blitz | author= Dean E. Murphy | date = August 8, 1995 | accessdate=December 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Krajina Serb sources (Documents of HQ of Civilian Protection of RSK, Supreme Council of Defense published by Kovačević,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovačević and Linta93-94&quot;&gt;[[#Kovačević and Linta|Kovačević and Linta (2003)]], pp. 93–94&lt;/ref&gt; Sekulić,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sekulić|Sekulić (2000)]], pp. 171–246&lt;/ref&gt; and Vrcelj&lt;ref&gt;[[#Vrcelj|Vrcelj (2002)]], pp. 212–222&lt;/ref&gt;) confirm that the evacuation of Serbs was organized and planned beforehand.&lt;ref name=&quot;HJSociety-Knin-Evacuation&quot;&gt;{{cite web | publisher = [[Henry Jackson Society]] | url = http://greatersurbiton.wordpress.com/2008/03/14/how-croatia-and-the-us-prevented-genocide-with-operation-storm/| title = How Croatia and the US prevented genocide with 'Operation Storm' | author= Marko Attila Hoare | date = March 14, 2008 | accessdate=December 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|author=Arhivista |date=May 13, 2007 |url=http://nl.youtube.com/watch?v=UYjh3aAvczc |title=Vježba bježanja | language= Serbian | trans_title=Fleeing Practice |publisher=nl.youtube.com |accessdate=February 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Amnesty International]], the operation led to the ethnic cleansing of up to 200,000 Croatian Serbs, the  murder and torture of Serbs—both soldiers and civilians—as well as the plunder of Serb civilian property.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty2005&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/info/EUR64/002/2005 | title= Croatia: &quot;Operation Storm&quot; – still no justice ten years on | publisher= [[Amnesty International]] | date= August 26, 2005 | accessdate=January 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ICTY, on the other hand, concluded that only about 20,000 people were deported.&lt;ref name=&quot;gotovina judgement&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Judgement Summary for Gotovina et al.|location=The Hague|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/gotovina/tjug/en/110415_summary.pdf|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia |date =April 15, 2011|accessdate =April 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[BBC]] noted 200,000 Serb refugees at one point.&lt;ref name=&quot;storm anniversary&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4125640.stm | title= Croatia marks Storm anniversary |publisher=BBC News | date= August 5, 2005 | accessdate=December 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4747379.stm | title= Evicted Serbs remember Storm | author= Matt Prodger | authorlink= Matt Prodger |publisher=BBC |work=BBC News | date= August 5, 2005 | accessdate=December 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Croatian refugees exiled in 1991 were finally allowed to return to their homes. In 1996 alone, about 85,000 displaced Croats returned to the former Krajina and western Slavonia, according to the estimates of the [[U.S. Committee for Refugees and Immigrants]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.refugees.org/countryreports.aspx?id=822|title=World Refugee Survey—Croatia|publisher= [[U.S. Committee for Refugees and Immigrants]]|accessdate=November 19, 2010| archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080315041821/http://www.refugees.org/countryreports.aspx?id=822 |archivedate=February 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: {{reflist}}

:* {{cite book | ref=Kovačević and Linta| last1=Kovačević | last2= Linta | first1=Drago | first2= Miodrag | url=http://books.google.se/books?id=_wTcAAAACAAJ | title=Kavez: Krajina u dogovorenom ratu | trans_title= Cage: Krajina in an Arranged War | publisher=Srpski demokratski forum | location=Belgrade | language=Serbian | year=2003 | isbn=86-83759-04-0}}
:* {{cite book | ref=Sekulić| last=Sekulić | first=Milisav | url=http://books.google.se/books?id=W0L_GAAACAAJ | title=Knin je pao u Beogradu | trans_title= Knin Fell in Belgrade | publisher=Nidda Verlag | language=Serbian | year=2000 | id= UDK: 3 355.45(497.5-074)&quot;1991/1995&quot;}}
:* {{cite book | ref=Vrcelj | last=Vrcelj | first=Marko | url=http://books.google.hr/books?id=O24tAQAAIAAJ | title=Rat za Srpsku Krajinu: 1991–1995 | trans_title= War for Serbian Krajina: 1991–1995 | year=2002 | publisher=Srpsko kulturno društvo &quot;Zora&quot; | location=Belgrade | language=Serbian | isbn=978-86-83809-06-6}}

This seems like it would merit at least a partial move here. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 18:44, 26 September 2013 (UTC)

== background section sourcing ==

The [[Transaction Publishers]] book certainly seems like something that should be referenced, but the issues are serious: it talks of Tuđman as an advocate of a country &quot;inhabited exclusively by Croats&quot;, unspecified &quot;openly discriminatory laws&quot;, implies that Croatian media also &quot;demonized Muslims&quot;, a &quot;new national coat of arms [with] a design very similar to that used by the Ustasha&quot;, and talks of &quot;atrocities perpetrated by Croats&quot; being used to &quot;create fear among Bosnian Serbs&quot; prior to the Bosnian declaration of independence. This level of factual inaccuracy while making such serious claims is most troubling. Tuđman was certainly a nationalist, but the described level of national exclusivity would necessarily imply genocide not only of Serbs but of all the other minorities, none of which actually happened; the laws stuff is probably a reference to the controversial constitutional changes discussed in [[independence of Croatia]]; the Muslim demonization implication is probably sloppy wording (the latter would not happen before well after 1991); the checkerboard coat of arms was a consistent symbol of SR Croatia, and this controversy is debunked in [[Coat of arms of Croatia]]; the extent of the actual atrocities against the Serbs during the first phase of the war in Croatia can't be described without context (including converse atrocities committed by Serbian forces in a significantly wider scope at the time, and fake incidents such as the [[Vukovar children massacre]]), otherwise it's left unsaid how much of a propaganda feat this actually was. Overall, the war in Croatia is treated more as a prelude to the war in Bosnia in this source, which might help explain the sloppiness, but it doesn't really excuse it. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 00:17, 13 February 2014 (UTC)
== Copyright problem removed ==

This article has been revised as part of [[WP:CCI|a large-scale clean-up project of multiple article copyright infringement]]. (See [[WP:Contributor copyright investigations/20140915|the investigation subpage]].)&amp;nbsp;Prior content in this article duplicated one or more previously published sources. The material was copied from: http://www.icty.org/x/cases/gotovina/trans/en/090323ME.htm http://www.balkanpeace.org/index.php?index=article&amp;articleid=14318. Copied or closely paraphrased material has been rewritten or removed and must not be restored, ''unless'' it is duly released under a compatible license. (For more information, please see [[Wikipedia:COPYRIGHT#Using_copyrighted_work_from_others|&quot;using copyrighted works from others&quot;]] if you are not the copyright holder of this material, or [[Wikipedia:Donating copyrighted materials|&quot;donating copyrighted materials&quot;]] if you are.) For [[Wikipedia:Copyrights|legal reasons]], we cannot accept [[Wikipedia:Copyrights|copyrighted]] text or images borrowed from other web sites or published material; such additions will be deleted. Contributors may use copyrighted publications as a source of ''information'', and according to [[fair use]] may copy sentences and phrases, provided they are included in quotation marks and referenced properly. The material may also be rewritten, but only if it does not infringe on the copyright of the original ''or'' [[Wikipedia:Plagiarism|plagiarize]] from that source. Therefore such paraphrased portions must provide their source. Please see our [[Wikipedia:NFC#Text|guideline on non-free text]] for how to properly implement limited quotations of copyrighted text. Wikipedia takes copyright violations very seriously, and persistent violators '''will''' be [[Wikipedia:Blocking policy|blocked]] from editing. While we appreciate contributions, we must require all contributors to understand and comply with these policies. Thank you. &lt;!-- Template:Cclean --&gt; [[User:Psychonaut|Psychonaut]] ([[User talk:Psychonaut|talk]]) 08:36, 6 November 2014 (UTC)

== Edits made by [[User:23 editor]] ==
As someone who believes in RS you should actually post one before introducing such claims about direct US involvement. Where is the source claiming that the US had participated directly in the Operation? [[User:Shokatz|Shokatz]] ([[User talk:Shokatz|talk]]) 14:39, 19 September 2015 (UTC)
::Are you kidding me? Citing the [[Navy Times]], Aranas 2012 states: &quot;US airstrikes on August 4, 1995 against Serb missile sites [...] were in the same area the Croatians were attacking as they began &quot;Operation Storm&quot;. The airstrikes were said to have been initiated because of a request by Pakistani U.N. peacekeepers who said Croatian artillery fire was hitting too close to their posts. Despite that, U.S. aircraft targeted and hit Serb positions instead of Croatian targets.&quot; This was cited in the article until you [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Operation_Storm&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=681786791&amp;oldid=681786520 removed it], saying &quot;How were NATO and US strikes part of the Operation? Where are the citations?&quot; a) No one mentioned ''NATO'' and b) you just removed the citation! Furthermore, direct support and general support are two different things, though it can certainly be argued that airstrikes targeting Serb positions constituted ''direct'' support. Even if they don't, it's virtually undeniable the U.S. supported the Croatian offensive. It trained Croatian soldiers and provided the Croatian Army with weapons in violation of the U.N. arms embargo (see Glenn P. Hastedt, ''Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy'' p. 107). According to Carole Rogel, Croatia had about 100,000 U.S.-trained troops at the time of the operation (see Rogel, ''The Breakup of Yugoslavia and the War in Bosnia'' p. 37) If NATO didn't support Croatia, the US most certainly did (both covertly and, at least in the case of airstrikes, overtly). [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 15:32, 19 September 2015 (UTC)
:::Navy Times? Seriously? It's a weekly pundit, not a reliable source. I am sorry but I missed the citation, can you repost it here again so we can see it...all I saw was a link to a google books page where no citations were present, only a summary of the book in question. Nothing on the subject. Still I don't see a reliable source which can without any doubt confirm that US was a belligerent in that conflict or that it directly participated. Sure, the Croatian army used those air strikes, but were they coordinated? I smell a conspiracy theory since AFAIK both the Croatian and US government blatantly rejected such claims. [[User:Shokatz|Shokatz]] ([[User talk:Shokatz|talk]]) 16:07, 19 September 2015 (UTC)
::If you think [[Navy Times]] is an unreliable source, then open a thread at [[Wikipedia:Reliable sources/Noticeboard]]. The citation can be found [https://books.google.ca/books?id=8FAnS7cx37kC&amp;pg=PA113&amp;dq=US+airstrike+Croatia&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CBsQ6AEwAGoVChMI4-qjvr6DyAIVhhKSCh3ksAz5#v=onepage&amp;q=US%20airstrike%20Croatia&amp;f=false here ]. As I said towards the end of my post, the ''airstrikes'' don't have to be coordinated to be included under support (a good solution would be to include a line separating the HV and ARBiH from the U.S. in the infobox), though there is no question that providing military advisors and shipping weapons did directly contribute to Croatia's increased military capability, and thus to the operation's (and the war's) eventual outcome. This in of itself qualifies as &quot;support&quot;, though the [[WP:RS]] do appear to indicate that several airstrikes were ''also'' carried out, hence the phrase &quot;limited airstrikes&quot;, which was present in the infobox before you removed it. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 16:23, 19 September 2015 (UTC)
:::The infobox section called &quot;Belligerents&quot; is for one purpose only and that purpose is exactly to the meaning of that word. Belligerent = a nation or person engaged in war or conflict, as recognized by international law. The role of US cannot be part of that section on infobox since US was not a side directly involved in the conflict but a third side overseeing the situation on both sides. The fact Croatian army used the US air strikes to their advantage has absolutely nothing to do with the military operation at all and at best would/should be a part of some other section called &quot;circumstances&quot; or whatever. I've looked on quite a few articles regarding military operations and battles (historical or contemporary) and never have I see anything similar to &quot;support&quot; as you tried to install here. And btw the reference you posted says nothing about US being directly involved in the conflict supporting Croatian side...all we have is mention of one person writing a letter to a daily pundit (NY Times) in which that person stated his opinion. [[User:Shokatz|Shokatz]] ([[User talk:Shokatz|talk]]) 17:35, 19 September 2015 (UTC)
::Not true. Look at the Syrian civil war infobox, or better yet, the [[Iraq War (2014–present)]] infobox. Both list Iran, for example, despite the fact that Iran doesn't actually have soldiers engaging in combat on the ground. It has personnel training and advising both the Syrian and Iraqi armies, provides weapons, supplies and intelligence to both and has bombed ISIS on two or three occasions in Iraq. Again, military training, providing weapons and equipment and limited airstrikes are exactly how the US contributed to 'Storm'. So if you're implying that there aren't precedents on Wikipedia, you're wrong. Second, you've completely ignored the part in Aranas where US military personnel are cited as confirming that US airstrikes were indeed carried out. Indeed, you merely cherry-picked the first passage, where a retired USAF colonel is described writing to a newspaper (the ''[[Washington Times]]'' not the NYT) rhetorically asking why the US bombed Serb targets if it claimed to be neutral. I suggest you read sources more carefully, as you didn't even get the name of the newspaper right. Your dismissal of reliable sources such as the Navy Times and the New York Times (using the dismissive term 'daily pundit') is rather unsettling. Both sources, especially the latter, are cited on numerous en:wiki articles.

::Furthermore, your definition of belligerent is wrong in the context of modern warfare. The U.S. is a belligerent in the Middle East, yet it denies being in a state of war with any party and constantly says it doesn't have &quot;boots on the ground&quot;. It most certainly did ''not'' have &quot;boots on the ground&quot; during 'Storm', but as two sources clearly state, it did carry out airstrikes against one side and not the other—not to mention the military training and weapons provided to the HV without which it is doubtful the offensive would have succeeded. To deny U.S. involvement against the RSK is ludicrous. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 18:40, 19 September 2015 (UTC)
:::The difference between the current conflicts in Iraq and Syria are completely different from a military operation which refers to a much smaller scale conflict. Your claim that US was somehow directly involved in planning and carrying out that operation is unsupported by official sources and borders on [[WP:OR]] and speculation. US never trained anyone...if you refer to MPRI they only had a consulting role and a minimal one at that...plus the fact that MPRI is NOT a US govt. agency of any kind but a private company. And also US never provided any weapons to Croatian military at any point during the wars in the 90s, if that was the case Croatia wouldn't be forced to smuggle weapons in and use obsolete Soviet-era weaponry. You should have direct quotations and reliable source for everything you just stated if you want to be taken seriously. [[User:Shokatz|Shokatz]] ([[User talk:Shokatz|talk]]) 19:07, 19 September 2015 (UTC)

=== Alleged US support through &quot;limited airstrikes&quot; ===
The biggest issue I have with 23 editors change is that, although the incident did occur, the article misinterprets the events. First of all, the &quot;limited airstrikes&quot; which are being implied were a mere '''two''' missiles fired on '''one''' ocassion. An incident, maybe, but hardly an airstrike aimed at supporting one of the belligerents. The second (bigger) problem is that it misinterprets the casues as to why it happened. Using the sources quoted below, I hope to show that the idea of US air support for Croatian forces is a far-stretched construct with no foundation in historical facts.

The August 4 event in which four NATO aircraft attacked a Serb SAM position had nothing to do with helping the Croatian war effort, rather they were acting in self-defense as shown in an [[United Press International]] [http://www.upi.com/Archives/1995/08/04/US-acted-in-self-defense-on-Serb-target/1198807508800/ '''article'''] reporting about the incident.

{{Quote|WASHINGTON, Aug. 4 -- U.S. pilots who fired at a Croatian Serb missile site were acting in '''self-defense''' as a radar device locked onto their planes while they were flying over the embattled area '''at the request of U.N. military commanders''', a NATO spokesman said. The NATO warplanes fired AGM-88 High-Speed Anti-Radiation Missiles, or HARM, at the site near Knin, the stronghold of the Serb rebels. NATO spokesman Jim Mitchell in Aviano, Italy, said the pilots were acting in self-defense and fired after their planes were illuminated by a radar from Serb surface-to-air missile system. Under present rules of engagement, NATO warplanes can fire without permission from the United Nations if they see a perceived threat.}}

The same situation was mentioned in a Human Rights Watch [http://www.hrw.org/reports/1996/Croatia.htm '''report'''] from August 1996.

{{Quote|NATO threatened to attack Croatian forces in retaliation for their assault on U.N. positions. However, the '''only''' NATO attack during the operation was against a Serbian surface-to-air missile site near Knin '''that had locked onto two NATO planes dispatched in response to U.N. calls for support.'''}}

Tom Ripley mentiones this as well in his book &quot;[https://books.google.hr/books?id=hS6xQAAACAAJ&amp;hl=hr&amp;source=gbs_book_other_versions Air War Bosnia - US and NATO Airpower]&quot; on page 82:

{{Quote|Croatian troops launched Operation Storm to drive the Serbs from Krajina region on 4 August and on the same day Krajina Serb radar illuminated US Navy jets, who responded by firing AGM-88 High Speed Anti-radiation missiles at the site.}}

So based on three credible sources, two important things are explained: US aircraft were not operating in the area because they were planning on aiding Croatian forces, but were instead called in by UN peacekeepers on the ground because of the Croatian attack. Second of all, the reason why they opened fire on a Serb position was not to help Croatian forces (which they were actually supposed to deter), but because they were threatened by it (the Serbian illumination of the fighter jets while they were responding to a call by the UN peacekeepers). Keep in mind that just two months before that, [[Scott O'Grady]] was shot down over Bosnia. So if they didn't arrive there to help the Croatians and they didn't fire on the Serbs to help the Croatians, I don't see how the mentioned event is proof of US support for Croatia using &quot;limited airstrikes&quot;.--[[User:Saxum|Saxum]] ([[User talk:Saxum|talk]]) 12:57, 20 September 2015 (UTC)
:::Fair enough. But these airstrikes should at least still be mentioned in the body of the article under the date when they occurred, since we have five sources (including Aranas and the Navy Times) to back up that assertion. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 16:17, 20 September 2015 (UTC)
:Agreed. It happened during the operation and it happened in an area affected by it. Not to mention the reason they took off in the first reason was because of the actions of the Croatian military. I was merely trying to explain the context of the event so it doesn't read as if there was some kind of an air campaign launched to help Croatian forces in Storm. That, and that it gets mentioned in the right place, not the infobox but in the text with the rest of the events of the day.--[[User:Saxum|Saxum]] ([[User talk:Saxum|talk]]) 17:14, 20 September 2015 (UTC)

== Mass graves unearthed after March 2012 ==

The number of mass graves and victims end in March 2012. There are some new findings, such as one [http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/mass-grave-of-serb-civilians-found-in-croatia in Zadar], and another one [http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/storm-mass-grave-exhumed-in-central-croatia-12-02-2015 in Gornje Selište].--[[User_talk:Zoupan|Z&lt;small&gt;oupan&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:25, 1 March 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>py78pejr6dyi7pcztwh8zfexkarjk8n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
