<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:HMAS Sydney (R17)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5989960</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748675472</id>
      <parentid>748675397</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-09T16:45:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/95.150.18.150|95.150.18.150]] - &quot;/* Helicopters in Korea */&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8110">{{talkheader}}
{{Article history
|action1=WPR
|action1date=11:03, 22 February 2010
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/HMAS Sydney (R17)
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=343649920

|action2=WAR
|action2date=11:11, 17 March 2010
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/HMAS Sydney (R17)
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=350375724

|dykdate=25 August 2009
|dykentry=... that '''{{HMAS|Sydney|R17|6}}''' ''(pictured)'' was the first [[aircraft carrier]] owned by a [[Commonwealth of Nations|British Commonwealth]] nation to serve in combat?
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Ships|class=A}}
{{WikiProject Military history|A-Class=pass|old-peer-review=yes|class=A|Aviation=y|Maritime=y|ANZSP=y|WWII=y|Cold-War=y}}
{{WikiProject Vietnam|class=A}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=A|importance=Low|military=y|military-importance=Low|maritime=y|maritime-importance=Low}}
}}

==Fair use rationale for Image:HMAS Sydney (SMH 290851).jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:HMAS Sydney (SMH 290851).jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:HMAS Sydney (SMH 290851).jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is  other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;

[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 00:16, 27 September 2007 (UTC)

== Helicopters in Korea ==
I've recently been told by an on-board witness the the USN helicopter used in Korea was a substitute for the intended Westland build aircraft.  The Westland aircraft had suffered from blade de-lamination, and was unfit for service.  Is this an item that people think should be mentioned in the article?  I can undoubtedly obtain more details if required.
[[User:Number774|Number774]] ([[User talk:Number774|talk]]) 22:01, 31 August 2008 (UTC)
:If you can find some [[WP:RS|reliable, published sources]] making these claims, by all means add them or list the information here. If we can't work them into the article as it stands now (balance, undue weight, etc), I'd happily consider it for the massive expansion of the article I have in the works. -- [[User:Saberwyn|saberwyn]] 23:20, 31 August 2008 (UTC)

::IIRC, Westland introduced metal rotor blades on the Dragonfly before Sikorsky did.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/95.150.18.150|95.150.18.150]] ([[User talk:95.150.18.150#top|talk]]) 16:44, 9 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Australian War Memorial images ==
While undergoing the rewrite of this article, I trawled through the Australian War Memorial image archives, and found several images of use. They are listed below, with the relevant image number(s) indicated in brackets. I have not had an opportunity to download these and upload them to Commons yet...if anyone beats me to some or all of them, I will not complain. -- [[User:Saberwyn|saberwyn]] 09:59, 17 August 2009 (UTC)

* (305532) Launch of the hull ''Terrible'', later Sydney (Construction)
* (304528) First helicopter landing on Sydney (Appropriate history)
* (301438) Sydney entering Sydney Harbour for first time - Fort Denison and Harbour Bridge seen (place in history)
* (044801) Sydney underway with Firefly and Sea Fury aircraft flying overhead (Aircraft)
* (301472/03) Sydney underway with Firefly and Sea Fury aircraft flying overhead (Aircraft - if left-aligned image needed)
* (305197) Bofors being fired during a gunnery exercise (Armament)
* (147462, P01838.005, 147466) Sydney, left, alongside Glory, right, docked alongside each other at Kure Harbour on 29 September 1951. Sydney would go to Korea, while Glory sailed to Australia for refitting (Appropriate Korea)
* (P01838.004) Uncle Peter on the flight deck (Appropriate Korea)
* (P00721.004, P00721.005, P01838.014) Snow on the flight deck and aircraft in January 1952 (History - apprpriate place in Korea)
* (300178, 300179, 300180) HMAS Sydney, Anzac, and Vengeance exercising off Queensland in 1953 (appropriate History, also for Vengeance)
* (301476) Vehicles secured on deck during trials in 1962 for new role as transport. (Appropriate history)
* (P01004.001) Army AA gun on the deck of Sydney (appropriate history - Malaya/Confrontation)
* (P00053.002) Personnel from 1 RAR formed up on the flight deck of Sydney; overhead shot
* (P01539.020) Vehicles secured on deck during a 1968 voyage to Vietnam (appropriate Vietnam)
* (043893) Sydney leaving Sydney Harbour under tow en route to scrapping (Fate)

== Studded with numbers ==
Quite an impressive expansion! A suggestion, though: consider balancing the verifiability benefits of having notes after every single sentence against readability. Right now, the article has a massive redundancy of notes, particularly when the same note is repeated in several consecutive sentences.

[[User:Peter Isotalo|Peter]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Peter Isotalo|Isotalo]]&lt;/sup&gt; 22:02, 25 August 2009 (UTC)
:Thanks for your compliment and suggestion. However, I'm of the stance that every fact is contestible, so every fact should be blatantly cited. It aids in verification (as you mentioned), and in vandalism detection (in an article where every sentance is meant to be cited, a sentance without a cite raises an instant red flag). -- [[User:Saberwyn|saberwyn]] 09:30, 26 August 2009 (UTC)

::Do as you will, but keep in mind that this forest of footnotes will never stop vandalism because that's not what it's intended to do. That issue is properly dealt with through careful reviewing and vandal patrols. Footnotes are there to actually be read, not quantified by drive-by reviewers. Any halfwit POV-warrior or joker can insert whatever disinformation they want next to a footnote or within a footnoted sentence. You need to actually check the information behind the citation for it to be useful, and that makes this type of reference density utterly pointless.
::All requirements need to be balanced, and the &quot;every-sentence-is-guilty-until-proven-innocent&quot;-stance isn't even stipulated by policy. Hell, it's not even required by the latest FAs. The only thing this achieves is to put off all but the most dedicated readers.
::[[User:Peter Isotalo|Peter]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Peter Isotalo|Isotalo]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:41, 27 August 2009 (UTC)

== images to identify ==
There are some images from the State Library of Queensland in [[:commons:Category:Sydney (ship)]] that need identification.  See my comments at [[commons:Commons_talk:State_Library_of_Queensland/Subjects#Sydney_(Ship)]].  &lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;[[User:John Vandenberg|John Vandenberg]] &lt;sup&gt;'''([[User talk:John Vandenberg|chat]])'''&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 06:49, 29 December 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>34cicm7fye42yh39358ucwfgngnii87</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
