<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Wolfgang Lüth</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7440812</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745886277</id>
      <parentid>745884648</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-23T23:33:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian Rose</username>
        <id>502570</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Comment by Ian Rose */ Typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12374">{{Skip to talk}}
{{talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WPR
|action1date=10:12, 10 March 2009
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/Wolfgang Lüth
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=276238173

|action2=GAN
|action2date=19:40, 10 March 2009 (UTC)
|action2link=Talk:Wolfgang Lüth/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=276340583

|action3=WAR
|action3date=10 April 2009
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Wolfgang Lüth
|action3result=approved
|action3oldid=282762218

|action4=GAR
|action4date= 23:02, 13 August 2016 (UTC)
|action4link=Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Wolfgang Lüth/1
|action4result=kept
|action4oldid=734351123

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War
}}
{{American English}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Biography|listas=Luth, Wolfgang|living=no|class=GA|military-priority=mid|military-work-group=yes}}
{{WPMILHIST
|class=A
|A-Class=pass
|German=yes

|old-peer-review=yes
|Biography=y
|WWII-task-force=yes
|German-task-force=yes
|Maritime-task-force=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= no
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= no
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= no
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= no
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= no}}
}}


==Untitled==
Donitz was never the Fueher, he was President. Although the term only means Leader I seem to recall from reading the article he noticeably didn't use it, so I'm changing it to the President gave a few words at his funeral. There, from the Donitz article &quot;Significantly, Dönitz was not to become Führer. Instead, Dönitz became President (Reichspräsident), a post Hitler had abolished years earlier.&quot;.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.137.207.191|24.137.207.191]] ([[User talk:24.137.207.191|talk]]) 16:21, 5 December 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== War Patrols ==

Question - Was 15 war patrols a lot ? -[[User:Jim Sweeney|Jim Sweeney]] ([[User talk:Jim Sweeney|talk]]) 10:23, 27 February 2009 (UTC)
:Take a look here [[List of successful U-boat commanders]]. 15 is on the high end for German WW2 commanders. [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 12:17, 27 February 2009 (UTC)
::Yes I see --[[User:Jim Sweeney|Jim Sweeney]] ([[User talk:Jim Sweeney|talk]]) 15:04, 27 February 2009 (UTC)

== Officer ranks ==

Having copyedited this article, one thing I have come across is the laughable 'translations' of ''Kriegsmarine'' officer ranks. For example, ''Korvettankapitän'' becomes &quot;Corvette Captain&quot;, ''Fregatttenkapitän'' is apparently a &quot;Frigate Captain&quot; and, my favorite: ''Kapitän zur See'' turns into &quot;Captain at Sea&quot;! Does this make a ''Kapitänleutänant'' a &quot;Captain Leiutenant&quot;?!&lt;br&gt;
This list is not complete.&lt;br&gt; 
Having looked up some of the individual articles, it is quite obvious where the 'translations' have come from; but the ''Kriegsmarine'' article ''and'' my reference are more sensible, i.e. &quot;Lieutenant Commander&quot;, &quot;Commander&quot;, &quot;Captain&quot; and so on.

But before I change them all, I thought a bit of consensus might be a good thing.

[[User:RASAM|RASAM]] ([[User talk:RASAM|talk]]) 20:45, 28 April 2011 (UTC)
:This was one of the first articles I had worked on here on the English Wiki. So what you call laughable was my best attempt as a non native English speaking person. Please feel free to correct my ignorance. [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 18:28, 22 May 2011 (UTC)

== Wolfgang Luth ==

Wolfgang Luth was a committed National Socialist and not to be revered. When he sank The Empire Lake in the Indian Ocean there were 5 survivors aboard a raft, he surfaced, one of his men enquired as to the name of the ship, where it was bound and what cargo it was carrying. He later wrote in his log 'Due to the high seas and the distance from land (180 miles), they will probably not survive'. He made no offer to tow the raft closer to the land, no offer of provisions, many U-Boat commanders did tow rafts to some measure of safety. I am sorry to see he has a memorial in Flensberg, I feel Germany should face up to he was.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.31.167.16|82.31.167.16]] ([[User talk:82.31.167.16|talk]]) 16:30, 25 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Unreliable sources tag ==

I tagged the article with Unreliable sources tag; it contains multiple citations to [[Franz Kurowski]] &amp; [[Karl Alman]] (same author); these accounts are likely to be semi-fictional. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 07:32, 16 July 2016 (UTC)

== Community reassessment ==

{{Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Wolfgang Lüth/1}}

== Recent edit ==

I restored the version of the article that was arrived at via a recent GAR; pls see [[Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Wolfgang Lüth/1]]. Here's the [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wolfgang_L%C3%BCth&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=745086303&amp;oldid=745015350 diff]. Please let me know if there are any concerns. 

I would also request that editors be mindful of avoiding personal attacks, such as in this edit summary
*&quot;[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wolfgang_L%C3%BCth&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=745014881&amp;oldid=745014719 complaints of intricate detail are ridiculous]&quot;

Thank you. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 05:38, 19 October 2016 (UTC)

:Don't hide behind personal attacks whinging. Your reversal was based on the false assertion that there was an agreement to keep out the minor details I added back in. There blatantly wasn't. So your edits are ridiculous. You can have differing opinion and discuss things, but don't lie about it.
:Thank you. [[User:Dapi89|Dapi89]] ([[User talk:Dapi89|talk]]) 15:50, 19 October 2016 (UTC)
::By the way, your article on Williamson relies on one real source; with tenuous opinions at best. [[User:Dapi89|Dapi89]] ([[User talk:Dapi89|talk]]) 15:56, 19 October 2016 (UTC)

:::{{ping|Dapi89}} So these are indeed &quot;{{tq|minor details}}&quot;? What do they add to the article? Separately, the edit restored the source by [[Gordon Williamson (writer)]] which was removed as part of the GAR. What is the reason for re-adding it? 

:::Re: &quot;tenuous opinions&quot; -- this appears to be a criticism of [[S.P. MacKenzie]], who is a practicing historian and the work being cited was published with an academic publisher. What is the problem with using this source? And are there reputable historians that praise Williamson's works? BTW, the editor is mistaken: this is not ''my'' article; nobody &quot;owns&quot; articles on Wikipedia. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 03:24, 20 October 2016 (UTC)
::::No, it's a criticism of you, and the way you (try to) use one source to denigrate another because you don't like it. More to the point, Williamson doesn't require an endorsement from anyone with a PhD. In fact, your source couldn't even show he was unreliable. And the three editors that bothered to comment on that re-assessment were '''all''' opposed to deleting him for that reason. In a nut-shell, you've abused the RS source policy and re-assessment protocols here to suit yourself. People are starting to notice (on the [[Joachim Helbig]] page).
::::As that article stands, it is yours. You've wiped out most of the original edits and now your single-sourced critique of him dominates the article.
::::I'm done here. [[User:Dapi89|Dapi89]] ([[User talk:Dapi89|talk]]) 16:26, 21 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::{{ping|Dapi89|K.e.coffman}} Gentlemen, please stop edit warring. If there is an issue, discussion is the best way the resolve it. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 09:55, 22 October 2016 (UTC)

{{od}}

The editor states that the removal of Williamson is &quot;opposed by reassessment discussion&quot; and advises me to &quot;start being honest&quot;: [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wolfgang_L%C3%BCth&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=745619196 diff]. Reviewing the GAR just above, I see the following comments (emphasis mine): 

*&quot;{{tq|Sturma quotes Grey Wolf by Williamson among five other sources (two by Clay Blair) in footnote 8 on page 3 of the introduction. This '''hardly makes Williamson an academic writer'''. The referenced work in this article is basically a compilation of biographic material (...), which might be considered '''a tertiary source at best'''. More importantly, Williamson's figure for Allied tonnage sunk by Lüth is taken from Bodo Herzog's book '''dating from 1970''', which is '''off by 3225 GRT''', and fails to mention a French sub sunk.}}&quot;
*&quot;{{tq|From the article, I have the impression that some of the '''inferior sources''' (i.e. Alman, Berger, Kurowski, Range, Von Seemen, and also Williamson) are merely used to create the impression that there is a wider, academic discussion of Lüth, rather than a mere entry in a biographical index.}}&quot;

In fact citations to Williamson have been removed as part of the GAR. Could {{U|Dapi89}} please clarify where they see the opposition to the removal of Williamson from '''all three''' reviewers? [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 20:24, 22 October 2016 (UTC)

===Third opinion request===

I'm submitting the above disagreement to [[WP:3O]]. The disagreement concerns this edit: 
*[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wolfgang_L%C3%BCth&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=745619196&amp;oldid=745609812 &quot;It's not for you to decide. Opposed by re-assessment discussion. Start being honest.&quot;]

The revert concerns two areas:

#Minor details of the subject's career
#Restoration to the article of the source [[Gordon Williamson (writer)]] which was removed as part of the GAR above ([[Talk:Wolfgang Lüth#Community reassessment]]) and is currently not used for citations. 

[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 03:47, 23 October 2016 (UTC)

====Comment by Ian Rose====
I've not commented on this dispute thus far, nor was I involved in the GAR, so I hope I can be objective here.  I've looked over the GAR in light of the points mentioned above and:
*Re. &quot;minor details&quot;, I don't see a discussion of that in the GAR, so while anyone is entitled to remove what they see as over-detailing (which I think is always in the eye of the beholder), they have to be prepared to see it reverted and then justify it in a subsequent discussion. Now, to step out of my position as disinterested observer of the GAR and offer my opinion on [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wolfgang_L%C3%BCth&amp;diff=734349769&amp;oldid=734349104 an example of &quot;intricate detail&quot; being removed], I have to admit I don't see why exact dates shouldn't be used if available and cited to a reliable source, or why advances in rank shouldn't be noted; I can't recall ever being accused of over-detailing when I've done that in Commonwealth pilot bios, many of which I've taken to FA. 
*Re. Williamson, it appears to me that {{u|Peacemaker67}} pointed out reasons to retain him, and {{u|AustralianRupert}} recommended caution re. removing him. {{u|K.e.coffman}} recommended removing, and {{u|ÄDA - DÄP}} mentioned possible alternatives to him (and others). Assuming I haven't misinterpreted anyone's position, that doesn't suggest to me consensus for removing. Again, moving from observation of the GAR to offer an opinion, I've never written or co-written a German military bio and I don't know Williamson; I can only speak from experience re. Osprey as I've used several of their books to write on Commonwealth pilots and generally found their authors to be careful and as objective as one can reasonably expect in the presentation of their subjects.
Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 23:15, 23 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>b2gz7egavw2jpu0g8mxovasfcrsiz1c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
