<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Operation Southeast Croatia</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>16805908</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747933130</id>
      <parentid>592010379</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-05T08:01:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peacemaker67</username>
        <id>15690513</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added template</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40476">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=12:02, 17 December 2012
|action1link=Talk:Operation Southeast Croatia/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=528461457

|action2=WAR
|action2date=14:09, 22 July 2013
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Operation Southeast Croatia
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=565000278

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war
}}
{{Australian English}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=A|A-Class=pass
| B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; = y
| B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; = y
| B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; = y
| B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; = y
| B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; = y
| Balkan=y|German=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject Bosnia and Herzegovina|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=GA
  |b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; =yes
  |b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; =yes
  |b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; =yes
  |b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; =yes
  |b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; =yes
  |b6 &lt;!--Accessibility          --&gt; =yes
 |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=low
| b1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; = y
| b2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; = y
| b3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; = y
| b4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; = y
| b5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; = y}}
{{WikiProject Serbia|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Yugoslavia|class=GA|importance=mid}}
}}

== German operation names ==

The German operation names for this offensive are Unternehmen Sud-Ost Kroatien (or Kroatien Sud-Ost), Ozren, and Prijedor. The source is Shepherd, Ben. ''Terror in the Balkans''. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 11:12, 28 September 2012 (UTC)
:Excellent research! :) Do you perhaps know which was the &quot;central&quot; of the three so we might rename the article accordingly? &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:48, 28 September 2012 (UTC)
:: Operation Sud-Ost Kroatien. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 23:12, 28 September 2012 (UTC)
:: Although I plan to create separate articles, as the more I look at this stuff, the more I realise the &quot;X enemy offensives&quot; construct has significant issues regarding continuity with some related operations and isn't really practical re: relating directly in WP article terms for some operations. I think the &quot;Operation X&quot; articles should still be related to the &quot;enemy offensive&quot; they are associated with (if in fact they are), but to state that &quot;X enemy offensive&quot; is in some way primarily related to a particular operation in this way really does not work at all with the [[Second enemy offensive]] and [[Sixth enemy offensive]] as they consisted of operations that were geographically widely separated. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 06:49, 29 September 2012 (UTC)
::: But in the meantime, do we go with [[Operation South-east Croatia]]? [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 06:58, 29 September 2012 (UTC)
:::: I certainly don't mind covering more of the myriad operations of the Yugoslav Front, but I would prefer if we covered the three operations here as a group. This is nothing new or strange: many battle and campaign articles are named after the codename for the &quot;central&quot; operation. There are certainly sufficient sources which refer to this as the Second Enemy Offensive and generally use the &quot;seven offensives&quot; organization.

:::: I have no problem with &quot;Operation South-east Croatia&quot;. Though, shouldn't it be &quot;Operation Southeast Croatia&quot; per [[WP:MoS|MoS]]? &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 10:42, 29 September 2012 (UTC)
::::: There's one thing I just remembered.. this operation didn't take place in what would be called &quot;southeast Croatia&quot; at any time other than 1941-45, and that only by the Axis. This is Bosnia.. Its not really a big problem, but it might be considered misleading. We should make it clear that this is not what we'd refer to today as &quot;southeast Croatia&quot;. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:08, 29 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::: Sure, I think it is important that the lead establish this very early on. And I bow to your knowledge of MoS as far as the hyphen is concerned. I'll move it and amend the lead. Feel free to tweak once I'm done. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 11:32, 29 September 2012 (UTC)

== Renaming of this article from &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot; to &quot;Operation Southeast Croatia&quot; ==

I am against renaming of this article from &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot; to &quot;Operation Southeast Croatia&quot;:
* &quot;Operation Southeast Croatia&quot; - [https://www.google.rs/#q=%22Operation+Southeast+Croatia%22&amp;hl=sr&amp;prmd=imvns&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=bks&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=oeRmUJLeKI2LswbnioGwDA&amp;ved=0CAsQ_AUoAA&amp;prmdo=1&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.&amp;fp=c57ffb24f6a47c93&amp;biw=1517&amp;bih=756 0 GBS] hits
* &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot; bosnia 1942 - [https://www.google.rs/#q=%22Second+Enemy+Offensive%22+bosnia+1942&amp;hl=sr&amp;tbm=bks&amp;ei=1uRmUJbYI4_BtAbKzIDABw&amp;start=10&amp;sa=N&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.&amp;fp=c57ffb24f6a47c93&amp;biw=1517&amp;bih=756 14 GBS] hits, many of them sources extensively used as sources in articles on this topic.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 12:11, 29 September 2012 (UTC)
** Well hello, Antidiskriminator. The rationale and discussion behind the moving of all of the [[Seven enemy offensives]] to German operation names (of which this is the last one) is covered here [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Battle_of_Kozara] I invite you to read it. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 00:28, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::I did and my opinion remains the same.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 00:33, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::And you are welcome to it. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 00:37, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::Please revert yourself and return the old name to this article.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 01:03, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::There was no indication that you opposed it prior to the move, which was suggested by DIREKTOR and supported by me. Feel free to submit a RfM if you believe it should be returned to the previous title. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 01:07, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Concur. The move was performed to preserve consistency on this subject, and is in accordance with previous [[WP:CONSENSUS]] on the naming of Yugoslav Front operations. &quot;14 hits ''vs.'' several&quot; is not a particularly convincing argument, such insignificant differences do not present a relevant COMMONNAME. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 02:06, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::::No. You DIREKTOR and Peacemaker67 did not gain consensus for your point. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:12, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::Yes. We did. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:56, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::Please present the list of users who supported your point and link to their discussion.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 16:00, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::May I ask: why are you here, Antidiskriminator? You're currently in conflict with Peacemaker, myself, and several other users on maybe a half-dozen articles, in about twice as many separate sections you created. Now you're starting another battleground. You did not edit or expand any of these articles one relevant iota, even when repeatedly asked, at times, to actually do the edits you propose. You never edited this article either, nor, for that matter, any of the Yugoslav Front operations that I'm aware. How did you happen to find your way here? In the context of previous behavior and [[WP:STICK]] problems, I believe this can now be viewed as convincing evidence of textbook [[WP:WIKIHOUNDING]]. I'd like to take this opportunity to again request that you please discontinue behavior of this sort. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 16:24, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::Wil you please be so kind to prove your claim that you and Peacemaker67 gained consensus for your point by presenting the list of users who supported your point and link to their discussion.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 17:23, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::The consensus was between me and Peacemaker, and I believe PRODUCER has expressed his consent. After some discussion we agreed to implement this format, rather than the communist one I implemented before it (which, in turn, replaced the format I introduced even earlier). And yes, in case you're wondering, that ''is'' a [[WP:CONSENSUS]] - since noone else participates on these articles. It was on one of the talkpages.. and I'm afraid I can't be bothered to post links or &quot;write lists&quot; for you.

:::::::::::::Antidiskriminator, let me be honest. I ''really'' don't like writing reports. Its difficult, it doesn't expand Wikipedia, it takes hours, then lasts for days, ''etc.'' And I've written so many I'm sick and tired of it, plus in principle I believe serious sanctions are used far too often here on our &quot;Free&quot; project. But, at some point, it becomes actually ''easier'' to report [[WP:WIKIHOUNDING|disruption and harassment]] than to deal with it on a daily basis.
:::::::::::::What I'm saying here is: I'm lazy; and I'm basically trying to just resolve this without writing for hours. I've been a participant here for ''years,'' and I know obvious [[WP:T]] and [[WP:STICK]] and [[WP:HOUND]] when I see them. This my absolute ''last'' attempt to resolve this problem of ours with less work (you can tell by the length of the post :)). Please understand: should you ignore this appeal (again), should this textbook WP:HOUNDING continue here as well, should this become another [[WP:BATTLEGROUND]] you've started - this is going up on the appropriate noticeboard. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 17:58, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::: &lt;u&gt;In that case it was wrong to claim that you and Peacemaker67 gained consensus for your point because you did not. I am against it and I presented argument for my position.&lt;/u&gt; New name violates [[WP:TITLE]] and [[WP:COMMONAME]]. None of [[WP:NAMINGCRITERIA]] is met by new title which does not even exist in sources on English language. There are many other names used for this operation, but new name is not among them. It simply does not exist anywhere. There are no books, websites, news... nothing. Nothing support this name. Therefore:
:::::::::::::::#'''Recognizability''' criteria is not met. Nobody would recognize this operation under new name. Therefore it is not ''&quot;recognizable to someone familiar with (though not necessarily expert in) the topic&quot;''. 
:::::::::::::::# '''Naturalness''' criteria is not met. New name is not ''&quot;what the subject is actually called in English&quot;''. Therefore new name is not something ''&quot;readers are likely to look for or search with&quot;'', nor it is something ''&quot;editors naturally use to link from other articles&quot;''
:::::::::::::::#'''Precision''' criteria is not met. Since nobody has ever used that name in English language people can easily be mislead to believe that this was some operation in geographical region of Southeast [[Croatia]].
:::::::::::::::# '''Conciseness''' criteria is also questionable. 
:::::::::::::::#'''Consistency''' criteria is not met. All other articles about military operations meet WP:COMMONAME and WP:TITLE. Name of this article does not. A couple of wikipedia editors forged new name by translating it from German.
:::::::::::::::You and Peacemaker67 did not gain consensus for your point. Not only because I am against it, but because consensus is grounded in arguments based on policies an guidelines. Your position is not.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 20:47, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::No. We gained consensus. And its based on policy. ''None'' of your points above apply. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 20:51, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
{{outdent}}@Antidiskriminator. I'm sick to death of this. Either stop hounding me or you'll get reported. I'm a fairly patient man, but you are stretching my patience to breaking point. I would rather be productive on WP, creating and improving articles, than writing reports, but I will shortly if this behaviour does not stop. I think you've had enough warnings now. The assumption that you are here because I (and possibly Director) are here is a reasonable one. Otherwise why &lt;u&gt;are&lt;/u&gt; you here? You have had no involvement with these [[Yugoslav Front]] articles in my time on WP, have never edited them as far as I can remember (don't get me started on how you rarely if ever actually contribute in article space on articles whose talkpages you treat as a battleground).

PRODUCER (I assume), Director and I make a consensus. Our reasoning for the move of all the seven offensives is available at the link I identified, and the title is in accordance with WP policy. BTW, the name &lt;u&gt;in English&lt;/u&gt; as used for this title is used throughout the main reference for this operation, Shepherd (of which I have a copy). This just shows the weakness of the Google Books hits you love so much. They are a blunt instrument which are trumped by actual sources. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 23:19, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::*Please respect WP:NPA and ''&quot;Comment on content, not on the contributor.&quot;''
::*This is not the first time you and DIREKTOR renamed the article without first gaining consensus for your action, even in case when appropriateness of a move may be or actually is under dispute. According to [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] in such cases you two should have gained consensus first by requesting a move (wp:rm). Please respect wikipedia rules, return the previous name of the article and gain consensus for the new name by startinng WP:RM.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 22:52, 1 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Consensus was gained among participating users, whether you accept that fact or not. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 23:17, 1 October 2012 (UTC)
::::RfM is not required by WP policy when consensus is clear from the participants (you had yet to &quot;appear&quot; here at that stage, in the same way you had not yet turned up at [[Territory of the Military Commander in Serbia]]) when that page was moved. And you've had your last warning for wikihounding, which is exactly what this is, trying to make the same point you've been banging on about at the other article by attacking the move of this article in an effort to show that Director and/or I move pages &quot;without consensus&quot;, so that you can make some case that [[Territory of the Military Commander in Serbia]] and this article are some weird pattern of non-Wiki behaviour. It's a joke, and no-one's laughing. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 00:16, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::Again, please respect WP:NPA and ''&quot;Comment on content, not on the contributor.&quot;'' I presented arguments for my position. My arguments are not ''&quot;banging on&quot;''. They are based on wikipedia rules.
:::::With [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AOperation_Southeast_Croatia&amp;diff=515232635&amp;oldid=515140678 this comment] you pointed to [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Battle_of_Kozara this discussion] and repeatedly claimed that you gained consensus to rename this article. But the discussion at the page you pointed to does not contain such consensus. On the contrary. There is [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3ABattle_of_Kozara&amp;diff=499426704&amp;oldid=499421692 your conclusion] with the list of names for seven offensives. That list includes '''&quot;Second enemy offensive&quot;''' as name for this article. And with [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Battle_of_Kozara&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=499426704 this comment] DIREKTOR confirmed that he is '''&quot;perfectly fine with the list&quot;'''.
:::::Then you changed your mind. On 29 September you [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AOperation_Southeast_Croatia&amp;diff=515114527&amp;oldid=515113919 proposed] to rename this article and in 10:44 DIREKTOR [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Operation_Southeast_Croatia&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=515131605 wrote] that he have ''&quot;no problem with &quot;Operation South-East Croatia&quot;&quot;'' and in 11:33 you renamed this article 49 minutes after DIREKTOR confirmed he does not have problem with it.
:::::'''After 49 minutes.'''
::::: '''27 minutes''' after your move [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AOperation_Southeast_Croatia&amp;diff=515140678&amp;oldid=515136252 I contested] it and presented arguments based on wikipedia policy. 
::::: No. Renaming of this article was not discussed before you moved. You two don't have consensus. Please respect wikipedia rules, return the previous name of the article and gain consensus for the new name by starting WP:RM.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 11:22, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::: This article is no longer about the whole &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot;, it is about a sub-part of it. I would be happy to create a new summary article called [[Second Enemy Offensive]] which has three [[WP:SPINOFF]]'s of [[Operation Southeast Croatia]], [[Operation Ozren]] and [[Operation Prijedor]]. Would that address your concerns? [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 12:21, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::: No. Changing the topic of this article to match new disputed name you gave to this article is circumventing the normal process of consensus. Please respect wikipedia rules, return the previous name of the article and gain consensus for the new name by starting WP:RM.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:17, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::: The move was in accordance with WP policy, and I have no intention of returning to the previous title. I will not be engaging further with this [[WP:WIKIHOUNDING]] disguised as righteous indignation over the title of an article you have shown not one iota of interest in up to now. My warning and your refusal to commit to not hounding me on further pages is indicative of your bad faith involvement here. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 07:09, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::: I don't agree with you. Your move is &lt;u&gt;contested&lt;/u&gt;. Therefore you should return the old name (and topic) to this article and go trough RM process. [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Requested_moves#Requesting_controversial_and_potentially_controversial_moves says]: &lt;u&gt;This process is necessary if there is any reason to believe a move would be contested.&lt;/u&gt; Since we have dispute here I followed [[Wikipedia:Dispute resolution]] and asked for a third opinion. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 12:20, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
{{outdent}} 3O is not applicable here, more than two editors are involved. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 21:20, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:No. Only you and me discussed if it is necessary to follow RM procedure in case of renaming the article from &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot; to &quot;Operation Southeast Croatia&quot;. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 21:56, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:: Antidiskriminator, if I said something was white, you'd say it was black. Clearly Director agreed that a RM wasn't necessary. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 22:18, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:::*Please respect [[Wikipedia:No personal attacks]] policy and Comment on content, not on the contributor.
:::* DIREKTOR explained that you two agreed to rename this article. He referred to your agreement reached after 49 minutes discussion as consensus. 27 minutes after your move I contested it and explained that you should now return the old name (and topic) to this article and go trough RM process because [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Requested_moves#Requesting_controversial_and_potentially_controversial_moves says]: &lt;u&gt;This process is necessary if there is any reason to believe a move would be contested.&lt;/u&gt; Only you disagreed with me about it and thereforee 3O is perfectly applicable here. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 22:49, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
::::* @Antidiskriminator. You have asked for a 3O about moving the page but have not waited for the result before moving the page? Just so we're clear. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 07:47, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::*For what my comment may be worth, titles should be consistent and since the other related articles aren't titled according to the Yugoslav terminology, this one shouldn't be moved.--&lt;span style=&quot;background-color: maroon; color: white&quot;&gt;[[User:ZjarriRrethues|&lt;font color=&quot;white&quot;&gt;'''—&amp;nbsp;''ZjarriRrethues''&amp;nbsp;—'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ZjarriRrethues|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 22:52, 8 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::: With [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Operation_Southeast_Croatia&amp;diff=516704092&amp;oldid=516286200 this edit] the article was again renamed from &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot; to &quot;Operation Southeast Croatia&quot; although it was obvious that this move would be (or already was) contested. [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Requested_moves#Requesting_controversial_and_potentially_controversial_moves says]: &lt;u&gt;This process is necessary if there is any reason to believe a move would be contested.&lt;/u&gt; 49 minutes discussion contested after 27 minutes can not be referred to as consensus. I still believe that editor who thinks this article should be renamed should start RM process, without changing the topic of the article to match new disputed name, circumventing the normal process of consensus.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 06:46, 10 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::: Antid, you are the one that asked for a 3O about the issue but acted to move this article before the 3O was provided. Four editors have now given their view about this article title, you are the only one opposing it, and you did so after it was first moved. It therefore lies with you to submit a RM, which, I will point out now (as I will if and when you submit a RM), would be a move back to a title that is inconsistent with the other six &quot;enemy offensives&quot;. Your opposition to this move has not addressed any of the arguments that were pointed to regarding the moves of the other articles (moving away from titles that reflect &quot;heroic Yugoslav communist&quot; propaganda to relatively neutral Axis operation names etc etc). Your conduct in following me here and your dubious motive for doing so is currently under discussion at [[WP:AE]]. Any attempt to move-war will be reported. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 07:39, 10 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::* I carefully explained why am I opposed to this move with this comment ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AOperation_Southeast_Croatia&amp;diff=515365997&amp;oldid=515342840 diff]) presenting arguments based on wikipedia rules.
::::::::::* Please comment on content, not on contributor and contributor's motives. Please don't repeat your accusations for wikihounding (me following you because of some dubious motives I have) on the articles' talk pages. According to [[Wikipedia:Harassment]] policy [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikihounding#Accusing_others_of_harassment Making accusations of harassment can be inflammatory and hence these accusations may not be helpful in a dispute.] [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Territory_of_the_Military_Commander_in_Serbia&amp;diff=414434652&amp;oldid=413908061 My first edit] of [[Territory of the Military Commander in Serbia]] was on 17 February 2011. &lt;u&gt;Nine months before you started editing of wikipedia&lt;/u&gt; (with your [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Pavle_%C4%90uri%C5%A1i%C4%87&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=459699555 comment about Pavle Đurišić] and his Iron Cross award). My serious involvement with [[Pavle Đurišić]] article (and many other articles about WWII in Yugoslavia, including major battles and offensives) started &lt;u&gt;after you requested its A-class review&lt;/u&gt; at [[WikiProject Serbia]] ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3APavle_%C4%90uri%C5%A1i%C4%87&amp;diff=503260950&amp;oldid=503260224 diff]) (where I am one of the most active editors). --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 09:24, 10 October 2012 (UTC)

===Request for a third opinion===

I am coming here in response to a request for [[WP:3O|third opinion]].

I don't think this is an appropriate subject for a third opinion.  More than two people are involved.  I recommend that you start a [[Wikipedia:Requested moves|request for page move]].

[[User:Yaris678|Yaris678]] ([[User talk:Yaris678|talk]]) 12:23, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:Thanks.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:24, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

== Chetniks as combatants ==

If I recall correctly the Chetniks were not actually combatants in this conflict. They were there, but (rather characteristically) did not fight. Am I wrong? The current infobox makes it out as though we've got 20,000 Chetnik combatants engaging the Axis? &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 10:34, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:It's a good point. Can you weave your infobox magic and make a third column for them? [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 10:38, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::I could - if they're combatants. Non-combatants (by definition) should not be listed as combatants, whether they were there in a joint or separate capacity with regard to one side or another. Did they engage in combat? &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:34, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::Ah! (facepalm) now I see what your getting at. I haven't found any evidence that they did fight either the Germans or the Home Guard as yet. I think most if not all of them headed for the mountains or crossed the Drina. So maybe we leave them out of the infobox completely on the basis they didn't actually engage in combat. They are mentioned in the lead and the body of the article, so that probably enough. I'll pull them out of the infobox. We can always put them back in if some evidence surfaces. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 11:52, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
::::If there's any evidence at all that they engaged in combat, we should restore them. Otherwise, no point. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 13:03, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::Agreed. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 13:46, 30 September 2012 (UTC)

== Include Ozren &amp; Prijedor? ==

As I said previously [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AOperation_Southeast_Croatia&amp;diff=515134077&amp;oldid=515114527], I don't believe operations [[Operation Ozren|Ozren]] and [[Operation Prijedor|Prijedor]] warrant their own articles per [[WP:NOTE]]. Imo they can easily (and more appropriately) be included here as separate sections, or perhaps subsections of the &quot;Aftermath&quot; section. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 07:14, 1 October 2012 (UTC)
:I understand your logic, but I believe that they do in fact meet [[WP:NOTE]] on the basis that; they all have significant coverage in Shepherd (that much is obvious for this article already, and there is a similar level of coverage for the other two operations); Shepherd is a third party secondary WP:RS; details of all three operations are mentioned (not by name but as a subject within the date ranges) to a reasonable extent by both Tomasevich and Hoare (and probably others that deal with the Yugoslav historiography); and because once the three are properly developed merging them into one article will create a &quot;long, bloated article&quot; with a significant degree of complexity given the different geographic areas they were conducted in. I don't believe any of them will be so narrow that they cannot properly be developed. Happy to re-visit when I've put more meat on the bones. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 08:13, 1 October 2012 (UTC)
::Hmm. One source? That's not [[WP:NOTE|WP:NOTABLE]], Peacemaker. In fact, even ''this'' article is barely notable. We should probably integrate.. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 16:42, 9 October 2012 (UTC)
:::I've had another really close look, and I am coming to the conclusion that Operation Prijedor is not clearly part of the &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot;. Have a look at the dates here [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=YZFpAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22second+enemy+offensive%22+-wikipedia+-LLC&amp;dq=%22second+enemy+offensive%22+-wikipedia+-LLC&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=fTfDil0n1c&amp;sig=MrK3vaYKO_AsY2EJKFxszHDVyIc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=yTx1UPzsJ4aYmQWWxYGoBg&amp;ved=0CEsQ6AEwBjgK] and the reference here to &quot;Romanija-Biračani Operations see also Second Enemy Offensive&quot; [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=mFwNAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22second+enemy+offensive%22+-wikipedia+-LLC&amp;dq=%22second+enemy+offensive%22+-wikipedia+-LLC&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=aBy7IS1dTG&amp;sig=79g1HfuIREzbNABTG-SQmJ9o8aE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=yTx1UPzsJ4aYmQWWxYGoBg&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwATgK]. My view is that the reliable sources (the only non-Yugoslav scholarly ones that even use the term &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot; being Tomasevich x 2, Hoare and Shepherd) are clear that the timeframes of both Operations Southeast Croatia and Ozren fall within the &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot; timeframe and eastern Bosnia area of operations, but there is a big question about Operation Prijedor, particularly given the dates used by the Yugoslav National Committee for Historical Studies and the reference to Romanija-Biračani Operations being synonymous with the &quot;Second Enemy Offensive&quot;. I propose merging Operations Southeast Croatia and Ozren, but leaving Operation Prijedor separate, at least in the short term. The forces used were different, the timeframe doesn't fit, the operation was conducted far from eastern Bosnia, and the purpose of Operation Prijedor was significantly different. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 09:37, 10 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Regardless, we should integrate it as the Aftermath. If someone were to really insist, IMO those articles would be deleted in a flash. There was a huge number of operations during this conflict. The majority do not really meet NOTE requirements for separate articles. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 22:31, 12 October 2012 (UTC)
::::: I doubt it. I consider there were sufficient lasting effects, and depth and persistence of coverage. There are several of the [[WP:N(E)]] criteria at play here.
::::: [[WP:EFFECT]] in two respects
::::: 1. the fact that the Germans had moved forces to the east to engage in [[Operation Southeast Croatia]], and that move resulted in the isolation of the Prijedor garrison; and
::::: 2. the fact that [[Operation Prijedor]] was a catalyst for the Partisan liberation of Prijedor three months later, and the Kozara Offensive that followed it. The contestation in the ''Krajina'' impacted directly on the overall outcome of the war and this operation was the first real attempt by the Germans to oppose the growth of the Partisans there. 
::::: [[WP:INDEPTH]] and [[WP:PERSISTENCE]] in that there is in-depth coverage in Shepherd, published in 2012
::::: [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 02:43, 13 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::: I have now merged Operation Ozren into this page. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 08:03, 13 October 2012 (UTC)
Do we, or do we not, treat Ozren and SE Croatia as the same operation (i.e. the former as the aftermath of the latter)? That's pretty standard on Wiki, there's no need to follow German subdivisions exactly. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 07:34, 11 December 2012 (UTC)
: They are not the same operation, they are covered in the same article because they are closely related and per the above discussion. There is absolutely no reason why we can't have the two operations in the article with separate info boxes to clarify the forces involved etc. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 07:40, 11 December 2012 (UTC)
:: I envisioned the article as being about Operation SE Croatia, with Ozren included as its &quot;Aftermath&quot; since it isn't WP:NOTE on its own? I don't know of a single article of this sort that uses two infoboxes.. I think the question is: if we have one article, why do we need two infoboxes? I assure you the template is flexible enough to clearly cover both. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 07:53, 11 December 2012 (UTC)
::: I don't agree. As I pointed out above, my view is that Ozren probably does meet WP:NOTE, but I'm happy with it here for now. If someone appears challenging its notability, I'll make those arguments then. I've recently improved Trio and Rosselsprung, and this one is next. Once it's up to speed I doubt there will be any issues. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 08:21, 11 December 2012 (UTC)
:::: Its just that its kind of strange to have two infoboxes in this type of article. That is to say, its rare altogether, but I've particularly never seen a ''military conflict'' article with two infoboxes. Users generally don't like infoboxes.. &quot;the less the better&quot; is the rule. &lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;-- [[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#353535&quot;&gt;Director&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#464646&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 09:10, 11 December 2012 (UTC)
::::: Well, nothing was said by the B Class reviewer, let's see what happens when I put it up for GAN. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 09:42, 11 December 2012 (UTC)

{{Talk:Operation Southeast Croatia/GA1}}

== Democratic Federal Yugoslavia  ==

The infobox presents Democratic Federal Yugoslavia established in 1943 as one of participants in this conflict of January 1942. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 16:12, 17 January 2014 (UTC)
:good point, fixed. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 23:33, 17 January 2014 (UTC)
::The image of Partisan flag is not sourced. Are there any sources that indicate the Partisan flag depicted was in use by the Partisans at this time?--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 23:41, 22 January 2014 (UTC)
:::Pot this is kettle, over. I will investigate. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 00:20, 23 January 2014 (UTC)
::::Hoare (2006), p. 83-84 mentions the decisions of the Stolice conference on 26 Sep 41, and the decree of the General Staff of B-H that in Serb areas of B-H it would be a red star on a Serbian tricolour. This was most definitely a Serb (as distinct from Croatian) area. I'm going to substitute the flag icon. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 06:06, 23 January 2014 (UTC)
:::::What I did not mention above is that this is not relevant to Tito, the 1st Proletarian Brigade or Popovic, as the 1st Brigade had a red flag with a star and hammer and sickle. Given the Partisan forces were mixed Serb and Proletarian, I have only used the Serb Partisan flag for the local commander and local detachments, which I consider a reasonable position. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 06:45, 23 January 2014 (UTC)
:::::::Has anybody uploaded image of the red flag with a star and hammer and sickle? --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 09:48, 23 January 2014 (UTC)
::::::::Not to my knowledge. I had a look around on Commons, but no cigar. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 09:57, 23 January 2014 (UTC)
:::::::::OK. That means that flag used in the article is somewhat different from actual flag they used? If that is so, is it better to remove it? --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 10:36, 23 January 2014 (UTC)
::::::::::No, I don't think so. The Stolice decree (which covered the whole of the Partisans and preceded this &quot;battle&quot;), covered flags to be used, by all formations. The overall flag for the Partisans was the Yugoslav tricolour with the red star, with subordinate ones for units in Serb and Croat areas. The 1st Proletarian Brigade was not tied to an area, but it was still part of the Partisans, so the overall Partisan flag is still directly relevant to them in the absence of a specific one for the brigade. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 10:42, 23 January 2014 (UTC)
:::::::::::Good point.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 11:41, 23 January 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>5azdv5xhw17ab09r0ruf2ylby0f7bll</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
