<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Operation Sandstone</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7120103</id>
    <revision>
      <id>655295724</id>
      <parentid>653370498</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-04-07T04:14:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SporkBot</username>
        <id>12406635</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove template per [[Wikipedia:Templates for discussion/Log/2015 March 16|TFD outcome]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6570">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=01:34, 9 October 2011 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Operation Sandstone/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=454007604
|action2=WAR
|action2date=09:48, 23 December 2012 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Operation Sandstone
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=528866514
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war
}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=A|A-Class=pass|b1=yes|b2=yes|b3=yes|b4=yes|b5=yes|US=yes|Weaponry=yes}}

== Needs back reference ==
The page needs reference back to [[Nuclear weapon design]] in part for more than alloy testing (e.g., levitation). [[Special:Contributions/143.232.210.150|143.232.210.150]] ([[User talk:143.232.210.150|talk]]) 01:20, 22 January 2011 (UTC)

== Test Locations ==

Test lat/lon coordinates added for each test.  General title level coordinates removed; they were across the atoll from the three shots in any case. [[User:SkoreKeep|SkoreKeep]] ([[User talk:SkoreKeep|talk]]) 07:59, 26 October 2013 (UTC)

==The table on this page is generated by database==

The table on this page and the contents of any nuclear tests infobox are generated from a database of nuclear testing which I have maintained and researched for a number of years. The table is automatically generated from that database by a Visual Basic script, and then has, periodically, been inserted into the page manually. I began doing this in October of 2013.

Recently a user complained (politely) to me about the practice.  It seems to him that it removes control from all editors besides myself over the content.  He believes it is tantamount to WP:OWNED of the pages affected.  He also points out that there is no public mention of the fact anywhere on wikipedia, and that is true, through my own oversight, until now.

There was no intent that the pages affected should be owned by myself; in fact, one of my reasons for building these pages was to solicit (in the wikipedia way) criticism and corrections to the data, perhaps additional references that I had been unable to locate. I have regenerated the tables twice in the days since they were originally placed.  Each time I did so, I performed a diff between the current version and the version that I put up in the previous cycle; all corrections were then either entered into the database or corrected in the programming, as appropriate.  As may be guessed, the programming corrections were frequent to start out as suggestions about the table formatting were raised, and most incorporated. I have not made judgements on the &quot;usefulness&quot; of corrections; all have been incorporated, or I have communicated directly with the editor to settle the matter.  In fact it was in pursuing such a correction that this matter came up.

I am posting this comment on the Talk page of every page containing content which is so generated. If you would like to comment on this matter, please go to the copy on [[Talk:List of nuclear tests]] so the discussion can be kept together.  I will also be placing a maintained template on each Talk page (if anyone would like also to be named as a maintainer on one or all pages, you are welcome). I solicit all comments and suggestions.

[[User:SkoreKeep|SkoreKeep]] ([[User talk:SkoreKeep|talk]]) 02:42, 18 August 2014 (UTC)

== From  http://radiochemistry.org/history/nuke_tests/sandstone/index.html ==

Operation Sandstone - 1948

Although a series of improvements for the implosion bomb were envisioned and under development at Los Alamos even before Trinity, the first nuclear test, the end of the war had derailed these efforts. With the Cold War rapidly developing, an urgent need was felt to bring these improvements to the U.S. weapon stockpile.

On 27 June 1947 President Harry Truman authorized a new test series for weapons development for the following year. Operation Sandstone was conducted at Enewetak Atoll in the Marshall Islands in 1948 to test the first new weapon designs since World War II.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.146.201.152|64.146.201.152]] ([[User talk:64.146.201.152|talk]]) 02:24, 7 February 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== From: Encyclopedia of Military Science ==

From Encyclopedia of Military Science, edited by G. Kurt Piehler:  “In the spring of 1948, new bomb designs tested as part of Operation Sandstone, at the Bikini Atoll, dramatically changed America’s atomic capabilities.   These new developments allowed for greater yield from existing fissionable material (double the explosive power of the [Atomic] bombs used durng World War II) and, therefore, the use of substantially less fissionable material (increasing the total stockpile size) . . . [A]t Sandstone, ‘composite’ cores using both uranium and plutonium were developed for the first time, . . . Improvements in efficiency allow for either an increase in yield or a decrease in size.” (p. 237)  Note: The decrease in size led to multiple developments of tactical nuclear weapons.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.146.201.152|64.146.201.152]] ([[User talk:64.146.201.152|talk]]) 02:44, 7 February 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Sandstone results led directly to Project Vista ==

From page 162, Volume 1, History of Acquisition in the Department of Defense: Rearming for the Cold War 1945-1960 by Elliott V. Converse III, 2012: &quot;In the spring of 1950, Secretary of the Army Gray's special study group had concentrated on the problem of ground defense in Western Europe.  Within a year, the prospect of war on the continent seemed much closer to reality.  Early in 1951, the Army, together with the Navy and Air Force, contracted with Caltech for a study of land and tactical air warfare known as Project Vista.  Its objective was to identify tactics, techniques, and equipment, including the use of tactical nuclear weapons that would improve military effectiveness.  Although not formally stated in the contract, the project was to focus on ways to halt a Soviet attack launched across a wide front in Europe. [Endnote # 111].&quot;  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.146.201.152|64.146.201.152]] ([[User talk:64.146.201.152|talk]]) 09:48, 7 February 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>tuban4tnnccuqhqhsl4afih44v8cb0q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
