<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>13295417</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741043720</id>
      <parentid>736028046</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-25T01:24:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anotherclown</username>
        <id>8567476</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix shell markup</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26716">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=5 March 2008
|action1link=Talk:173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team (United States)#GA on hold
|action1result=Listed
|action1oldid=195651892

|action2=WPR
|action2date=6 March 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team (United States)/Archive 1
|action2result=Reviewed
|action2oldid=195651892

|action3=FAC
|action3date=00:02, 25 March 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team (United States)/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=200250649

|action4=WAR
|action4date=07:59, 5 April 2008
|action4link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team (United States)
|action4result=approved
|action4oldid=203303793

|action5=FAC
|action5date=18:12, 4 May 2008
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team (United States)/archive2
|action5result=not promoted
|action5oldid=209926786

|action6=WPR
|action6date=1600, 30 December 2008
|action6link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team (United States)
|action6result=reviewed
|action6oldid=260438435

|topic=War
|currentstatus=GA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=A
|A-Class=pass
|old-peer-review=yes
|US=yes}}
{{WikiProject Vietnam|class=A|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Pritzker-GLAM|class=A|importance=mid}}
}}

==History merge==
This page was cut-and-paste moved from [[173rd Airborne Brigade (United States)]] on 16 September 2007. I have corrected that. Here are comments from [[Talk:173rd Airborne Brigade (United States)|that talk page]]. [[User:Cool Hand Luke|Cool Hand]] ''[[User talk:Cool Hand Luke|Luke]]'' 00:09, 30 October 2008 (UTC)

===Campaigns===
Anyone know which three campaigns the 173d fought in during WW2? [[User:Blair P. Houghton|Blair P. Houghton]] 20:56, 17 Feb 2005 (UTC)
* I removed this page back to 173rd, as the website for the Brigade says right on the top 173rd.  61,000 hits for ''173rd'' on google, opposed to 9,000 for ''173d''. 173d is an infield abbreviated designation and as such the page isn't named &quot;173d Abn Bde&quot;. &amp;mdash;[[User:ExplorerCDT|ExplorerCDT]] 23:39, 17 Feb 2005 (UTC)
**It's wrong, and Googling isn't probative, but I'll let the military fight with you about it. [[User:Blair P. Houghton|Blair P. Houghton]] 21:03, 18 Feb 2005 (UTC)

BTW, to answer your initial question...The 173rd was made the 87th Recon Group in 1942, but it didn't get into combat until 1944 in Europe.  The Three campaigns were Rhineland, Ardennes-Alsace, and Central Europe. &amp;mdash;[[User:ExplorerCDT|ExplorerCDT]] 21:09, 18 Feb 2005 (UTC)

:I added the proper Lineage and Honors Information for the 173rd and its various permutations from the CMH.[[User:CORNELIUSSEON|SSG Cornelius Seon (Retired)]] 14:19, 10 July 2006 (UTC)

===Fallen Angels===
Should them being mentioned in Fallen Angels be added to the pop culture section? In the soft cover published by Scholastic they are mentioned on pages 174 and 175. [[User:208.34.129.190|208.34.129.190]] 04:51, 3 September 2007 (UTC)

== Wasn't it involved in NEO? ==

IIRC, after Marines covered a NEO in Liberia, at least some 173rd units went into the concurrent NEO in the Central African Republic. [[User:Hcberkowitz|Howard C. Berkowitz]] ([[User talk:Hcberkowitz|talk]]) 02:50, 22 January 2008 (UTC)
:If you could find a source on that and add it, that would be great. I looked around for references to it and I didn't really see anything. -[[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 23:12, 22 January 2008 (UTC)

::I'm not finding it online, but there are a few places I want to look. There is, I'm almost certain, a detailed case study of the two concurrent NEOs in Dan Bolger's ''Death Ground'', but my copy is in storage, somewhere in several 10x2x10 boxes of books. 

::It was Operation QUICK RESPONSE in May 1996, overlapping Operation ASSURED RESPONSE (Liberia) starting in April. It's possible some 173rd units might have been in both. IIRC from Bolger, there was only a company or so available, with the rest in the Balkans. The Marines were trying to cover both places, and the eventual force included SEALs, Special Forces, and anybody else they could find. Again IIRC, they staged airlift through Freetown, Sierra Leone. http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/ops/assured_response.htm alludes to Army personnel, but doesn't specifically mention the 173rd.

::Does their PAO have email? If not, I can check with a PAO friend, about to go to OCS after her broken ankle heals. She was enlisted Public Affairs in Iraq, so should know who to call.[[User:Hcberkowitz|Howard C. Berkowitz]] ([[User talk:Hcberkowitz|talk]]) 01:11, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
:::That would definately be a good source...please do. -[[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 05:01, 23 January 2008 (UTC)

== Campaign Streamers ==
Does anyone know where high quality images of Campaign streamers can be found? I wanted to put in a chart for them similar to the one on the [[3/3]] page, but I can't find any that are very good or up to date. -[[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 05:01, 23 January 2008 (UTC)

http://www.tioh.hqda.pentagon.mil/CampaignStreamers/CampaignStreamerInfoPage.htm - There are a lot of high quality images there. [[User:Hal06|Hal06]] ([[User talk:Hal06|talk]]) 22:11, 8 March 2008 (UTC)

== Peer review==
The following suggestions were generated by a semi-automatic [[User:AndyZ/peerreviewer|javascript program]], and might not be applicable for the article in question.
*Consider removing links that add little to the article or that have been repeated in close proximity to other links to the same article, as per [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (links)]] and [[WP:CONTEXT]]. Guides recommend having greater than 3% words in links, but be sure not to overlink words just to add more links.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#overlink|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*Per [[Wikipedia:Only make links that are relevant to the context|Wikipedia:Context]] and [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (dates and numbers)|Wikipedia:Manual of Style (dates)]], months and days of the week generally should not be linked. Years, decades, and centuries can be linked if they provide [[WP:CONTEXT|context]] for the article.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#contxt|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*Per [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (dates and numbers)#Units of measurement|Wikipedia:Manual of Style (numbers)]], there should be a non-breaking space - &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&lt;/code&gt; between a number and the unit of measurement. For example, instead of ''2KL'', use ''2&amp;nbsp;KL'', which when you are editing the page, should look like: &lt;tt&gt;2&amp;amp;nbsp;KL&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#nbsp|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*Per [[Wikipedia:Only make links that are relevant to the context|Wikipedia:Context]] and [[Wikipedia:Build the web]], years with full dates should be linked; for example, if January 15, 2006 appeared in the article, link it as [[January 15]], [[2006]].&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#linkdate|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*As per [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (dates and numbers)|Wikipedia:Manual of Style (dates)]], dates shouldn't use &lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;; for example, instead of (if such appeared in the article) using ''[[January 30|January 30&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;]] was a great day'', use ''[[January 30]] was a great day''.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#dateth|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*As done in [[WP:FOOTNOTE]], footnotes usually are located right after a punctuation mark (as recommended by the [[The Chicago Manual of Style|CMS]], but not mandatory), such that there is no space in between. For example, ''the sun is larger than the moon [2].'' is usually written as ''the sun is larger than the moon.[2]''&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#footspace|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
Thanks, [[User: auawise|&lt;font size=&quot;2.5&quot; color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;&amp;Lambda;ua&amp;int;&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:auawise|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Wi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:auawise|&lt;font color=&quot;gray&quot;&gt;se&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Auawise|talk]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 18:36, 23 January 2008 (UTC)

==GA on hold==
Hi there, I have reviewed this article against the [[Wikipedia:good article criteria]] and although I am not quite prepared to pass the article for GA immediately, I don't think there is a long way to go. I have listed below the principal problems which prevent this article from achieving GA status. The article now has seven days to address these issues, and should the contributors disagree with my comments then please indicate below why you disagree and suggest a solution, compromise or explanation. Further time will be granted if a concerted effort is being made to address the problems, and as long as somebody is genuinely trying to deal with the issues raised then I will not fail the article. I am aware that my standards are quite high, but I feel that an article deserves as thorough a review as possible when applying for GA and that a tough review process here is an important stepping stone to future FAC attempts. Please do not take offence at anything I have said, nothing is meant personally and maliciously and if anyone feels aggrieved then please notify me at once and I will attempt to clarify the comments in question. Finally, should anyone disagree with my review or eventual decision then please take the article to [[WP:GAR]] to allow a wider selection of editors to comment on the issues discussed here. Well done on the work so far.
===Issues preventing promotion===
(These issues must be satisfactorily addressed, in the article itself or here, before GA promotion can go ahead)
*&lt;s&gt;[[Rhineland]], [[Ardennes-Alsace]], and [[Central Europe]] should link, in the infobox and in the text, to the campaigns, not the places.
::Not yet done in the article itself, only in the infobox.&lt;/s&gt;
:::{{done}} Changed them in the campaign streamers infobox, and changed the wording in the article to reflect location, not campaigns. -[[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 22:02, 26 February 2008 (UTC)
*&lt;s&gt;In the &quot;Vietnam War&quot; section the images are straying across the text. This is a problem I've seen before on [[Battle of the Gebora]], where I think it was solved using [[WP:BUNCH]]. Worth a look as the article is unreadable in placed for certain screen resolutions.&lt;/s&gt;
::I may need some help fixing this, I have a wide large resolution monitor, and though others have complained about images bunching, I can't get the problem to appear on my computer at all and so I can't what this problem is doing at all (even the [[WP:BUNCH]] examples are just fine on all of the machines I use) [[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 22:17, 23 February 2008 (UTC)
:::I'm afraid I'm as clueless as you are on this. I suggest dropping a line at [[User:Carre]]'s talk page, he fixed it last time and might be able to lend support.
::::I had a go at fixing this a while back - it's in the edit history somewhere;  the bunching was much before I got to it.  I've tried about all I could think of to get it better, and I think the best solution would be to slightly shift the images below the infobox.  It's those that's causing the clash with the image to the left.  I'm happy to have a go, if you like.  Jacky &amp;ndash; I take it you're at the same resolution as with the Gebora one?  Cheers. [[User:Carre|Carré]] ([[User talk:Carre|talk]]) 14:38, 24 February 2008 (UTC)
:::::{{done}} &amp;ndash; perfect at my resolution, and only a single line sentence thingie looking a little off-putting at the higher resolution. [[User:Carre|Carré]] ([[User talk:Carre|talk]]) 14:52, 24 February 2008 (UTC)
::::::Nice work, thanks a lot.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] ([[User talk:Jackyd101|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jackyd101|contribs]]) 17:23, 25 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
*More description is needed of the units service in Vietnam - which campaigns did they serve in? Provide detail.
::I'll expand on this, basically the campaign information is given up to 1967, but it is clear that the brigade was in Vietnam until 1970 at least - what happened in the last three years?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] ([[User talk:Jackyd101|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jackyd101|contribs]]) 02:08, 24 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
*Update the article with information about the last year's service in Afghanistan.
*&lt;s&gt;References needed in second paragraph of legacy section.&lt;/s&gt; {{done}}

In all, its a good article but more is needed on Vietnam service and the minor niggles I mentioned above have to be dealt with before I can pass this for GA.--[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] ([[User talk:Jackyd101|talk]]) 17:18, 23 February 2008 (UTC)
:It all looks reasonable, I'll get to work on this stuff. -[[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 22:02, 23 February 2008 (UTC)

OK, Updating on what's still needed, the 1968-1970 period in Vietnam is still not covered. Can you do anything to fill in this gap? Otherwise eveything looks great and I'll be happy to pass once the above is addressed.--[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] ([[User talk:Jackyd101|talk]]) 18:16, 28 February 2008 (UTC)
:Yes, I'm still working on that. The sources all seem to have a gap on the 1967-1970 history. Some of them have implied that the unit was rendered combat ineffective and was being rebuilt during this time, but I can't find anything very reliable. -[[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 22:39, 28 February 2008 (UTC)
::See http://www.skysoldier.org/ops.php &amp;ndash; seems they were still in Vietnam during this period.    Not much detail though.  The Sky Soldier site also lists a bunch of Medal of Honor recipients through these years.  HTH [[User:Carre|Carré]] ([[User talk:Carre|talk]]) 08:37, 29 February 2008 (UTC)
:::I'd like to see this fixed before I promote, but I'm in no hurry to fail it while good work is going on. Take as much time as you need (within reason).--[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] ([[User talk:Jackyd101|talk]]) 10:46, 1 March 2008 (UTC)
::::How about now? It doesn't seem right using one source to fill that area in, but since only one is apparently avaliable, I put in all I could for the time, which apparently was not a very active one for the unit. -[[User:Ed!|Ed!]] ([[User talk:Ed!|talk]]) 21:58, 3 March 2008 (UTC)
:::::That looks fine. Good job and congratulations.--[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] ([[User talk:Jackyd101|talk]]) 09:12, 5 March 2008 (UTC)

Couple of comments:  you sure you used the right reference?  You've used history.php, which doesn't seem to support the cited material.  Did you mean to use ops.php?  Second point is that you say they took part in four operations, but then only list 3.  [[User:Carre|Carré]] ([[User talk:Carre|talk]]) 10:44, 6 March 2008 (UTC)

== Conflict of Interest ==

One of the reasons for this article's failed FAC was that it relied heavily on COI material, because most of the information comes from US Army websites and press releases. What kind of sources exactly would not be COI? The Army sources are all reliable enough to me, but others seem to have a problem with them. -&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;'''[[User:Ed!|Ed!]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Ed!|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;[[User:Ed!/Hall of Fame|(Hall of Fame)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;''' 19:57, 15 April 2008 (UTC)

== lookig for someone ==

Hi
I have a friend by the bane  of Dennis (Denny) Cain who served with the 173rd in Nam. He is looking for anyone who served with him in Nam. If you contact me at puppytoes@charter.net I will put you in contact with him
Thank you
B Moreno  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/97.86.117.66|97.86.117.66]] ([[User talk:97.86.117.66|talk]]) 23:09, 21 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Operation Enduring Freedom 08 ==

Between footnotes 78 and 79 there is mention of &quot;a writer&quot; embedded with Battle Company.  The writer is [[Vanity_Fair_(magazine)|Vanity Fair]] contributing editor [[Sebastian_Junger|Sebastian Junger]], author of [[The_Perfect_Storm|The Perfect Storm]].  His book, [http://www.amazon.com/WAR-Sebastian-Junger/dp/0446556246/ref=tmm_hrd_title_0 WAR], published in the Spring of 2010, published by [[Twelve_(publisher)#Current_imprints|Twelve]], debuted on the New York Times best-seller list at #3.  Embedded with Junger was award-winning photographer [http://www.timhetherington.com/ Tim Hetherington], also a Vanity Fair contributor.  Together they produced and directed the documentary [http://www.restrepothemovie.com/ Restrepo], which won the [http://sundance.bside.com/2010/films/restrepo_sundance2010 Grand Jury Prize] for best documentary at the 2010 [[Sundance_Film_Festival|Sundance Film Festival]].




[[User:8 mouse 8|8 mouse 8]] ([[User talk:8 mouse 8|talk]]) 03:15, 27 May 2010 (UTC)

== Dead link ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www4.army.mil/ocpa/read.php?story_id_key=9586
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:06, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:49:12, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:49, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 2 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.drum.army.mil/sites/tenants/174th/lineage.asp#history
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:06, 404 NOT FOUND
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:49:16, 404 NOT FOUND

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:49, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 3 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.tioh.hqda.pentagon.mil/Abn/173AirborneBrigadeCombatTeam.htm
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:14, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:49:31, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:50, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 4 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.173abnbde.setaf.army.mil/history.htm
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:06, 400 Bad Request
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:49:53, 400 Bad Request

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:50, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 5 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.173abnbde.setaf.army.mil/Muc.htm
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:07, 400 Bad Request
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:50:08, 400 Bad Request

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:50, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 6 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.pressrepublican.com/0214_guest%20Column/local_story_302231534.html
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:08, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:50:22, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:50, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 7 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.173abnbde.setaf.army.mil/medal_of_honor_recipients.htm
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:07, 400 Bad Request
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:50:37, 400 Bad Request

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:51, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 8 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.skysoldier.org/history.php
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:18, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:50:54, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:51, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 9 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.army.mil/-newsreleases/2009/07/14/24343-army-prepares-for-next-rotations-in-oef/index.html
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:18, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:51:26, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:51, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 10 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.treas.gov/organization/bios/kimmitt-e.html
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:08, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:51:27, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:51, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 11 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.house.gov/hunter/biography.shtml
** In [[Duncan Hunter]] on 2011-03-17 17:26:18, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:09, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:52:02, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:52, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 12 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.army.mil/leaders/leaders/sma/former/mckinney.html
** In [[Gene C. McKinney]] on 2011-03-19 19:59:25, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:14, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:52:07, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:52, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Dead link 13 ==

During several automated bot runs the following external link was found to be unavailable. Please check if the link is in fact down and fix or remove it in that case!

* http://www.173airborne.army.mil/home.htm
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-05-25 01:57:07, 404 Not Found
** In [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]] on 2011-06-01 21:53:02, 404 Not Found

--[[User:JeffGBot|JeffGBot]] ([[User talk:JeffGBot|talk]]) 21:53, 1 June 2011 (UTC)

== Copyright problem removed ==

Prior content in this article duplicated one or more previously published sources. The material was copied from: http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/10/07/mock-battle-gone-wrong-injures-dozen-us-paratroopers-in-germany/. Infringing material has been rewritten or removed and must not be restored, ''unless'' it is duly released under a compatible license. (For more information, please see [[Wikipedia:COPYRIGHT#Using_copyrighted_work_from_others|&quot;using copyrighted works from others&quot;]] if you are not the copyright holder of this material, or [[Wikipedia:Donating copyrighted materials|&quot;donating copyrighted materials&quot;]] if you are.) For [[Wikipedia:Copyrights|legal reasons]], we cannot accept [[Wikipedia:Copyrights|copyrighted]] text or images borrowed from other web sites or published material; such additions will be deleted. Contributors may use copyrighted publications as a source of ''information'', but not as a source of ''sentences'' or ''phrases''. Accordingly, the material ''may'' be rewritten, but only if it does not infringe on the copyright of the original ''or'' [[Wikipedia:Plagiarism|plagiarize]] from that source. Please see our [[Wikipedia:NFC#Text|guideline on non-free text]] for how to properly implement limited quotations of copyrighted text. Wikipedia takes copyright violations very seriously, and persistent violators '''will''' be [[Wikipedia:Blocking policy|blocked]] from editing. While we appreciate contributions, we must require all contributors to understand and comply with these policies. Thank you. &lt;!-- Template:Cclean --&gt; [[User:Danger|Danger]] ([[User talk:Danger|talk]]) 14:20, 11 October 2011 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=733704881 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20070927234342/http://www.defendamerica.mil/iraq/update/dec2003/iu121803.html to http://www.defendamerica.mil/iraq/update/dec2003/iu121803.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20080619234142/http://www.history.army.mil/html/forcestruc/lineages/branches/div/173abbde.htm to http://www.history.army.mil/html/forcestruc/lineages/branches/div/173abbde.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 15:41, 9 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>0h0welsqqifb1wt9oams5agyodyhhge</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
