<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1981551</id>
    <revision>
      <id>728306686</id>
      <parentid>727209440</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-04T14:44:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ejgreen77</username>
        <id>10998541</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21688">{{GAR/link|01:50, 11 June 2016 (UTC)|page=1|GARpage=1|status= }}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=18 February 2014
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz/archive1
|action1result=reviewed

|action2=GAN
|action2date=12:10, 17 December 2013 (UTC)
|action2link=Talk:Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz/GA1
|action2result=pass
|action2oldid=586480656

|action3=WAR
|action3date=19:59, 30 March 2014 (UTC)
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz
|action3result=approved
|action3oldid=601990516

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=Warfare
}}
{{British English}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=A|importance=low|Prussia=yes}}
{{WPBiography
|living=no
|class=GA
|military-priority=high
|military-work-group=yes
|royalty-work-group=yes
|royalty-priority=mid
|listas=Strachwitz
}}
{{WPMILHIST
|class=A
|A-Class=pass
|Biography=yes
|German=yes
|WWI=yes
|WWII=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes}}
{{WikiProject Silesia|class=GA|importance=High}}
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 75K
|counter = 5
|minthreadsleft = 3
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Erwin Rommel/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{archives|search=yes}}

== Generalmajor der Reserve ==
The German Arméd Forces had and have no Generals/Admirals &quot;der Reserve&quot;. Generals/Admirals are always regular and professional &quot;life long&quot; serving officers.

The current version states that Strachwitz was &quot;seriously wounded&quot; in the Stalingrad Kessel and flown out- this would have been in Dec 1942. The next section states that he took command of a GD regiment in January 1943. How serious could that have been if he assumed a new command in a few weeks?
:I am wondering if &quot;seriously wounded&quot; is the best translation. What does the original German text say? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 02:25, 10 February 2013 (UTC)
::''schwer verwundet'' [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 06:22, 10 February 2013 (UTC)
:::Hard to get away from that; &quot;seriously wounded&quot; is the only translation that fits, but I agree it doesn't work with his quick return to command. There is some leeway, though. Maybe if we just change it to &quot;wounded&quot;. We are sure of that, while &quot;schwer&quot; might be a matter of opinion. [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 13:10, 10 February 2013 (UTC)
==Hyazinth==
We have two spellings for this. Can we choose one? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 12:58, 11 February 2013 (UTC)
:Good question. Most sources except for Röll, who uses Hyacinth, all use Hyazinth. The &quot;correct&quot; at least if his grave stone is correct is Hyacinth. see [http://ww2gravestone.com/general/strachwitz-von-gross-zauche-und-cammainetz-hyacinth-graf-von picture of grave stone]. I beleive Wiki policy would be to use the variable variant over the correct variant [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 15:29, 11 February 2013 (UTC)
::Strachwitz's entry in ''Genealogisches Handbuch des Adels'', (which is considered quite a reliable source when it comes to german nobility) uses the spelling &quot;Hyacinth&quot; as well [[User:Jake V|Jake V]] ([[User talk:Jake V|talk]]) 20:46, 19 February 2013 (UTC)
:::To make it more interesting, the grave finder site also spells it Hyaczinth. Can we agree on Hyacinth? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 15:20, 21 February 2013 (UTC)

::::[https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyazinth_Graf_Strachwitz German WP] uses Hyazinth, as do [https://et.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyazinth_von_Strachwitz Estonian], [https://no.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyazinth_Graf_Strachwitz_von_Gross-Zauche_und_Camminetz Norwegian] and [https://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyazinth_Graf_Strachwitz Polish] WPs. [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 13:51, 3 June 2015 (UTC)
:::::the rule is how is he known and reflected in English sources. Hyacinth is what was established over the years[[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 16:22, 3 June 2015 (UTC)

==The Spartacists==
The current wording in the lead implies that he fought on the side of the renegades, but I am thinking he would have been Freikorps or perhaps regular army still. Comments? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 14:59, 21 February 2013 (UTC)
:He was with the ''Freikorps'' [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 08:19, 22 February 2013 (UTC)
::OK, thanks. I will make that clearer. [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 13:52, 22 February 2013 (UTC)
:::I see it was already clear in the main text. I should have looked more closely. :) [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 14:05, 22 February 2013 (UTC)
==Versailles==
The Weimar section states that he returned home in &quot;early 1919&quot; and then goes on to say how the family situation had been altered by the Treaty of Versailles. But the Treaty was not signed until 28 June 1919, and not ratified until 21 October 1919. It is probably just a matter of grammar. Can we clarify this? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 16:27, 23 February 2013 (UTC)

==Distillery==
Is the distillery output in litres per year? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 12:16, 24 February 2013 (UTC)
==30 advisors?==
Who were these guys? Were they German ex-military people or someone else? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 14:13, 25 February 2013 (UTC)
==Maps==
The use of Soviet maps notated, of course, in Cyrillic, is not helpful with articles on English WP, IMO. [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 13:42, 3 June 2015 (UTC)

==Name==
&quot;Hyacinth,&quot; customarily an English woman's name, is the [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyacinth_%28plant%29 English spelling] of the generic name of the flower – which in [https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyazinthen German] is spelled with a z. 

The subject was a German male. The subject's given and legal name was Hyazinth. [https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyazinth_Graf_Strachwitz German WP] therefore uses Hyazinth. A newly published English-language history of WWII in the Baltics, Prit Buttar's detailed and thoroughly documented ''Between Giants: The Battle for the Baltics in World War II'' – published by UK-based [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osprey_Publishing Osprey] – uses Hyazinth in every mention.  To persist in using Hyacinth for this person is an error, regardless of what past (mistaken) practice in English may have been.
:'''''Ref.:''''' &lt;small&gt;Buttar, Prit. Between Giants: The Battle for the Baltics in World War II. Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing (2015).  ISBN-10: 1472807499; ISBN-13: 978-1472807496.&lt;/small&gt;

{{U|MisterBee1966}}, please do not revert my edits again. Thanks. [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 13:38, 4 June 2015 (UTC)

: as the main editor who brought this article to the current state, who owns all the sources, I have a strong opionion. It stays as reviewed [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 14:10, 4 June 2015 (UTC)

::{{U|MisterBee1966}}, please enlighten me as to why the name should be spelled with a ''c'' rather than a ''z''. For the reasons stated above, it appears to be historically incorrect – in which case, any sources that spell it with a ''c'' are (were) wrong. Explain why this is not so.
::No doubt you put much effort into the article, but that's not a reason to leave it in an erroneous state, no matter what your (or anyone else's) contributions have been, how many books you own, or how strong your opinion may be. Further, effects on WP templates are in internal issue irrelevant to the readers we serve.
::Wiki is an encyclopedia of information, and you or I don't own any of its articles. An encyclopedia ''must'' be accurate, no exceptions. Of course there's leeway in military history for different interpretations of events, but not for erroneous basic historical facts such as misspelling people's names. &lt;small&gt;(For an analogy, a few English-language books spell Hitler's first name as &quot;Adolph.&quot; This is simply wrong. Would you stick with &quot;Adolph&quot; if you had worked on an article about him?)&lt;/small&gt;
::I note that the Hyaz/cinth issue has come up [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Hyacinth_Graf_Strachwitz_von_Gro%C3%9F-Zauche_und_Camminetz&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=665335199 before] and it probably will again, since it's (IMO) a spelling error. Let's fix it. [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 15:29, 4 June 2015 (UTC)

:::we all have to acknowledge that Wiki relies on how a lema is predominantly known in English. It is irrelevant how the lema is known in its native language. Köln is known as Cologne and the river Rhein as Rhine. The battleship Friedrich der Große is known in English as Friedrich der Grosse. In my sources he is predominantly spelled with a C. I am very much aware that this is incorrect but it is irrelevant and therefore it stays spelled with a C, as most English sources do. [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 16:11, 4 June 2015 (UTC)
:::::to add to that, Röll is the primary authority in English and German. He spelled the name with a C. See the Note in the article to, which I had put there many moons ago[[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 16:24, 4 June 2015 (UTC)

::::::You haven't made a reasonable case for why Hyacinth would be the '''CORRECT''' spelling for someone whose given name was Hyazinth. English-language names of German towns and rivers are not analagous and irrelevant here. Personal names are whatever they are/were on the record. German, Estonian, Norwegian and Polish WPs all use Hyazinth. (And as noted, to English readers Hyacinth is a woman's name – as in the main character of [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeping_Up_Appearances#Cast this sitcom.])

::::::Röll may be considered the primary 'authority' on this person, but that doesn't make him infallible. If historical names are misspelled by some sources, such mistakes obviously should not be perpetuated just because someone doesn't feel like changing an article. (BTW, since you evidently are highly interested in the topic, I recommend Buttar's new book.)

:::::: I've no idea what you mean by [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lema_%28disambiguation%29 ''lema'']. [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 17:16, 4 June 2015 (UTC)

:::::::Support what Sca says. If Mozart was spelled Mocart in some reliable source, shouldn't we honour how he himself signed? (Bad enough that we say Amadeus whyle he signed Amadé.) - To give this man a woman's name seems grotesque, not to mention kafkaesque again, --[[User:Gerda Arendt|Gerda Arendt]] ([[User talk:Gerda Arendt|talk]]) 17:26, 4 June 2015 (UTC)
::::::::Wikipedia in general uses the spelling of foreign names as it is used in the overwhelming number of English-language sources; see [[Franz Josef Strauss]]. However, I'm sure that the English-language coverage of Strachwitz is much thinner, so there is no obstacle to use the German spelling, as done for [[Fritz Geißler]]. However&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, there's a good case that Strachwitz' first name is even in German &quot;Hyacinth&quot;; see his grave [http://ww2gravestone.com/sites/default/files/uploads/image060_16.jpg here] and [http://ww2gravestone.com/sites/default/files/uploads/IMG_0130.JPG here], at [http://ww2gravestone.com/people/strachwitz-von-gross-zauche-und-cammainetz-hyacinth-graf-von/ this website]. He was certainly baptised &quot;Hyacinth&quot;, but, according to [https://books.google.de/books?id=_ZPUAgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PA1&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA15 Bagdonas (2013, p. 15)] later used &quot;Hyazinth&quot;. I can only conclude that the spelling was not fixed in his own lifetime, which is not unusual for that time. -- [[User:Michael Bednarek|Michael Bednarek]] ([[User talk:Michael Bednarek|talk]]) 06:41, 7 June 2015 (UTC)

:::::::::Thank you, {{U|Michael Bednarek|Michael}}. That seems to explain a lot. 
:::::::::Do you have an opinion on whether the article should use Z or C? (I got into this only because I'm reading Buttar's ''Between Giants'', which as noted uses Z.)
:::::::::If Hyacinth was his name, I still have to wonder why German WP and those other WPs use Z. – ??? [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 14:34, 7 June 2015 (UTC)
{{od}}
I am back home now with access to my sources. In Röll's book you will find a number of contemporary images (including an image of his grave which is already linked above), documents and newspaper clippings. In every instance you will find his name spelled Hya&lt;u&gt;'''c'''&lt;/u&gt;inth (with the C). Please remember that his name is derived from the Polish Saint [[Hyacinth of Poland]]. In German, this Saint is ''[[:de:Hyazinth von Polen]]'' (note the Z). I can only assume that his move to West Germany introduced the spelling Hyazinth. Historically, over many generations the first born son in the family was named Hyacinth and spelled with a C.[[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 17:32, 7 June 2015 (UTC)

:{{U|MisterBee1966|Mr. B}}, thank you for your conciliatory message on my talk page. Due to that and [[User:Michael Bednarek|Michael]]'s post, I'm beginning to understand the situation from your point of view. I apologize for acting on (apparently) insufficient information when I changed the article to the Z spelling.
:How about putting some sort of explanatory note or footnote in the article regarding the two spellings? [[User:Sca|Sca]] ([[User talk:Sca|talk]]) 21:45, 7 June 2015 (UTC)

:::From my cursory examination, it doesn't matter whether the article is named using &quot;c&quot; or &quot;z&quot;, but an explanatory footnote – baptised in family tradition as &quot;Hyacinth&quot;, then preferred &quot;Hyazinth&quot; – should be provided. -- [[User:Michael Bednarek|Michael Bednarek]] ([[User talk:Michael Bednarek|talk]]) 23:56, 7 June 2015 (UTC)
::::just tossing a belated 2 cents into the conversation: Hyacinth is the common spelling of the ungendered name. It might also be spelled with an e at the end.  Wikipedia has a set index article with an explanation.  [[User:Auntieruth55|auntieruth]] [[User talk:Auntieruth55|(talk)]] 18:55, 14 June 2016 (UTC)

== Röll ==

Is Röll a [[WP:RS]] source? What are their credentials? There are about 160 citations to Röll -- are there any English language sources available? 

Separately, I've not been able to find Strachwitz's article on De.wiki. Can someone point me to it? [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 06:58, 8 March 2016 (UTC)
:Regarding German wiki, try [[:de:Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz]]. With respect to English language sources, try [https://books.google.de/books?id=_ZPUAgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;hl=de&amp;source=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The Devil's General: The Life of Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz - the &quot;Panzer Graf&quot;]. With respect to Hans-Joachim Röll, I found him reliable, in collaboration with Rainer Busch and their work on submarine warfare, you might want to check [https://www.worldcat.org/search?q=au%3ARo%CC%88ll%2C+Hans-Joachim.&amp;qt=hot_author work by Röll]. You might want to ask user:ÄDA - DÄP, he/she has more insight on naval warfare. Cheers [[User:MisterBee1966|MisterBee1966]] ([[User talk:MisterBee1966|talk]]) 12:57, 8 March 2016 (UTC)

==Proposed article cleanup ==
Although a GA (as of 2014), it appears that this article could stand a copy edit to remove excessive detail, overlinking, piping, etc. I've done several edits to remove excessive intricate detail, such as 
* [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Hyacinth_Graf_Strachwitz_von_Gro%C3%9F-Zauche_und_Camminetz&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=723843441&amp;oldid=723843149 a non-notable Reich sports badge], 
* [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Hyacinth_Graf_Strachwitz_von_Gro%C3%9F-Zauche_und_Camminetz&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=723845231&amp;oldid=723845076 Strachwitz's self-designed physical therapy protocol] and 
* [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Hyacinth_Graf_Strachwitz_von_Gro%C3%9F-Zauche_und_Camminetz&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=723846504&amp;oldid=723845231 discussion of Germany's WWI strategy], on which Strachwitz had no impact. 

Please see article history for other edit summaries and their rationale. My initial impression is that the article appears to have a readability problem due to too much information being presented.

Would there be any objections to proceeding further? [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 16:57, 5 June 2016 (UTC)

:As it appears that there are no objections, I will go ahead with the cleanup. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 05:59, 9 June 2016 (UTC)

::{{ping|AustralianRupert}} This is one of the articles in questions. I highlighted some of the concerns above; the rest are identified in the edit summaries, plus the over reliance on one source, which I mentioned in a separate topic below. 

::The situation with the article appears to be similar to the issues I have raised in the past with the MilHist community (please see the [[Wikipedia_talk:WikiProject_Military_history/Archive_134#WWII_content:_Otto_Kittel.2C_other_GA.2FFA_articles|WWII content: GA &amp; FA articles]]) in the [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Military history/Archive 134]]. I would be happy to revisit my concerns with the larger community. Please let me know what would be the appropriate forum. {{@MILHIST}} [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 22:12, 10 June 2016 (UTC)
:::[[WP:GAR|Good Article Review]] or [[WP:MHACR|A-class reappraisal]], would be the best forums, in my opinion. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 22:38, 10 June 2016 (UTC)
::::I am returning this article to its pre-existing condition (at which it was A-Class), and expect that the editors involved in the editing down of the article explain their actions in a A-Class re-assessment, instead of this death by a thousand cuts. The article was promoted by consensus, and changes of this scope and scale also require consensus. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67|click to talk to me]]) 01:02, 11 June 2016 (UTC)

== Article moved ==

Moved the article to &quot;Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz&quot; as this matches de.Wikipedia, pls see: [https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyazinth_Graf_Strachwitz Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz]. Please let me know if there are any concerns. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 06:20, 9 June 2016 (UTC)

== One Source tag ==

The article relies largely on one source for the article copy:
* {{Cite book
  |last=Röll
  |first=Hans-Joachim
  |year=2011
  |title=Generalleutnant der Reserve Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz: Vom Kavallerieoffizier zum Führer gepanzerter Verbände
  |trans_title=Lieutenant General of the Reserve Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz: From a Cavalry Officer to a Leader of Armoured Units
  |language=German
  |location=Würzburg, Germany
  |publisher=Flechsig
  |isbn=978-3-8035-0015-1
}}

Judging by the [http://www.buecher.de/shop/panzertruppe/generalleutnant-der-reserve-hyazinth-graf-strachwitz-von-gross-zauche-und-camminetz/roell-hans-joachim/products_products/detail/prod_id/25709248/ book cover], this appears to be a laudatory, non-peer reviewed narrative along the lines authored by other similar writers, such as [[Franz Kurowski]]. 

[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 16:20, 9 June 2016 (UTC)
:K.e.: It should be noted that this article did go through and pass GA and I also see it went through and passed &quot;Class A&quot; assessment. I don't object to the edits for concision which have been made, as I did some myself. I would very strongly recommend pinging the editors who were involved with the &quot;Class A&quot; review for this article before further substantial editing/removal. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 16:13, 10 June 2016 (UTC)

== Community reassessment ==

{{WP:Good article reassessment/Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz/1}}

== Request move to &quot;Hyazinth&quot; while GAR in progress ==

The recent move somehow disabled the link to the GAR from the top of the Talk page. I suggest the article be moved back to &quot;Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz&quot; while the GAR is in progress. Would there be any objections? 

Or if someone knows how to re-add the link to [[Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz/1‎]], that would be an alternate solution. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 22:10, 26 June 2016 (UTC)

:Yes; it shouldn't have been moved unilaterally in the first place. You did not address the valid points Misterbee raised the last two times it was discussed. Clearly it was controversial, so [[WP:RM]] should have been used.
:[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wikipedia:Good_article_reassessment/Hyacinth_Graf_Strachwitz/1&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=727208820 Problem solved]. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 12:11, 27 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fqaz7dr0az54xfh4ob8qzkfu0hp36pg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
