<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Operation Rösselsprung (1944)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2240050</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747939043</id>
      <parentid>628307209</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-05T09:11:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peacemaker67</username>
        <id>15690513</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added template</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32911">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=23:20, 17 December 2012
|action1link=Talk:Operation Rösselsprung (1944)/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=528549110
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war

|action2=WAR
|action2date=08:12, 5 October 2014 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Operation Rösselsprung (1944)
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=628307058
}}
{{Australian English}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=A|A-Class=pass|Balkan=yes|German=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject Yugoslavia|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Bosnia and Herzegovina|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=GA|importance=low}}
}}

==Skorzeny==
This is the first time I've heard anything about Skorzny not being involved in the Operation, even every Wikipedia article references his role in the Operation.  A search through various websites containing biographies on Skorzny or the events of Rosselsprung all mention his role in the operation.  I've removed your bit about that being folklore, unless you have quasi-reputable evidence in which case we can perhaps mention a controversy? [[User:Sherurcij|Sherurcij]] 15:14, July 15, 2005 (UTC)

I've done quite an extensive research project on this operation, and from my references he was not directly involved.  One excellent book that describes his role in this operation, as well as Gran Sasso and others, is called &quot;Skorzeny's Secret Missions&quot;.  He was heavily involved in the planning of Roesselsprung, but was not directly involved in the execution.  [[User:Uel|UEL]] 02:43, 7 August 2006 (UTC)

== Casualities ==

YU communist claim &quot;more likely&quot;? :D I just want to let you people know that the German &quot;claims&quot; are based on unit diaries and after action reports, also German units kept book daily on material and personel strenght, transfers and casualities so any sensible person tends to consider those &quot;little bit&quot; &quot;more likely&quot;, but hey, enjoy your revisionism, i wont bother to edit this crap nor will any sensible person believe what is writen here. Its most like with the Warsaw ghetto uprising, German official day to day report names and declares basicly as martyrs for national socialist cause 13 germans during the whole &quot;fighting&quot; in the ghetto the &quot;Stroop Report&quot;, yet the revisionist Zionists claim &quot;hurdreds of germans killed&quot;. :D Just pathetic, as is this commie bs.

Cheers..&lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:62.248.159.240|62.248.159.240]] ([[User talk:62.248.159.240|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/62.248.159.240|contribs]]) 19:30,5 August 2007(UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; 

:&quot;You people&quot;? [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 12:05, 6 February 2008 (UTC)



It does seem rather preposterous to advance political claims made by leaders of disorganized partisan forces over official unit records of professionals. : &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:128.61.32.228 |128.61.32.228 ]] ([[User talk:128.61.32.228 |talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/128.61.32.228 |contribs]]) 07.54,8 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:And &quot;disorganized&quot;? They had, according to just this article, a command structure, an Officer Training School, and were arranged in brigades; how is that not organized? And are &quot;professionals&quot; less likely to spin the facts, embroider the truth, tell lies? [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 17:10, 7 April 2008 (UTC)

::The Germans are likely to embellish the casualty reports for propaganda reasons. The operation was, after all, another in a string of humiliating defeats in this theater. Are we forgetting that the Germans had a little something called the &quot;Ministry of Propaganda&quot;? --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 17:33, 7 April 2008 (UTC)
::: Most likely the number of 213 German KIA is for the Ground Attack only, not including the looses of the Airborn Force.
both combined should add up to a number comparable to that claimed by the Partisans. [[Special:Contributions/134.2.212.61|134.2.212.61]] ([[User talk:134.2.212.61|talk]]) 10:29, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
==Cleanup==
I have added the clean up tag to this article as it requires some substantial work. Many claims and counter claims are listed that should be properly referenced. Much of it breaches [[WP:NPOV]] and some paragraphs need a substantial rewrite. Any questions can be left on my talk page. [[User:Woodym555|Woodym555]] 11:21, 8 August 2007 (UTC)

:I’ve split this into sections to make it easier to follow, but it feels a bit like re-arranging the deck-chairs on the ''Titanic''.I don’t know enough about the subject to re-write it with a NPOV, but it certainly needs it. [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 17:15, 6 February 2008 (UTC)

::Did my best to reference and organize the order of battle for both sides. --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 10:45, 8 April 2008 (UTC)

== Operation Rösselsprung ==

Honestly, I am not sure whether ''&quot;Operation Rösselsprung&quot;'' (&quot;Knight's leap&quot;) was only the name for the airborne landing on Drvar, not for other, much larger operations on the ground. This same landing is known as the &quot;Desant na Drvar&quot; (Raid on Drvar) by ex-Yugoslavs. I believe, though like I said I'm not 100% sure, that the Raid on Drvar/Operation Rösselsprung is just a part of the Seventh anti-Partisan Offensive. Does anyone have any info on this? --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 01:35, 14 June 2008 (UTC)

:Mrg, do you perhaps know the answer to the above? --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 00:59, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
:P.S. If you insist on the attacker being combatant 1 (there's no ''policy'' on that, but it makes sense), please accordingly modify the remaining 6 Anti-Partisan Operations. --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 01:02, 16 June 2008 (UTC)


Here's the full extent of the problem. We've got three terms in use here: '''1)''' &quot;Seventh anti-Partisan Offensive&quot;, '''2)''' &quot;Raid on Drvar&quot;, and '''3)''' &quot;Operation Rösselsprung&quot;. The operation was much wider than the airborne raid, encompassing the coordinated drive of armored spearheads towards Partisan positions, as well as [[Chetnik]] concentrated assaults in support.&lt;br&gt;
The meaning of the first term, &quot;Seventh anti-Partisan Offensive&quot;, is known, as it encompasses the entire operation. However, the exact meaning of &quot;Raid on Drvar&quot; and ''&quot;Operation Rösselsprung&quot;'' are unclear. The meanings of both could encompass the whole of the operation, and could just as easily refer only to the airborne raid itself. Amazingly, this is very hard to clear up. --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 01:31, 16 June 2008 (UTC)

:::Citation from the book &quot;Stvaranje Titove Jugoslavije&quot;: &gt;&gt;It was planned that operation &quot;Rosselsprung&quot; to be organized by blitz air raid to Drvar with simultaneous advancing of motorized and infantry forces from several directions, totally 20000 soldiers. Among them there were several thousands  Ustashes and Chetniks.&lt;&lt;  And there is a copy of the German document with order to 373. German division and 92. regiment (located in Bihać) for advancing. The title of the document is &quot;Rosselsprung&quot;. So, this was code name not only for paratroopers attack on Drvar, but also for the complete operation in the area between Bihać, Knin, Livno, Bugojno, Jajce, Banja Luka, Prijedor, Bosanska Krupa. However, I do not speak German language to be 100% sure, and the document is too small to be scanned.[[User:Megaribi|Megaribi]] ([[User talk:Megaribi|talk]]) 21:32, 20 June 2008 (UTC)

I see, thank you. So &quot;Raid on Drvar&quot; would also refer to the entire operation and not just the airborne raid? --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 21:42, 20 June 2008 (UTC)

::Well, preferred name was &quot;Drvar operation&quot; which lasted for 12 days. After the para assault there were attacks to mountain Klekovača (May 27th-May 30th ). Tito escaped by airplane to Bari on June 3rd.&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Megaribi|Megaribi]] ([[User talk:Megaribi|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Megaribi|contribs]]) 21:57, 20 June 2008&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

(outdent)&lt;/br&gt;
The spelling in the section title has been changed since I was here last; I've changed it back (and some spellings in the text). I don't know where the idea came from that the operation name should be spelt &quot;Rößelsprung&quot;, but it isn't correct. German carries both the double-s and the eszett, to represent different sounds (one is ss, the other sz, though I’m not clear which is which), so an ss doesn’t automatically become a ß. Anyway a google search for &quot;Rößelsprung&quot; gives just 53 hits (compared to over 9,000 for &quot;Rosselsprung&quot;), and the [http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_R%C3%B6sselsprung German WP page] uses the spelling &quot;Rosselsprung&quot;, so I’d say that clinches it. [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 22:23, 30 October 2010 (UTC)

== casualties ==

|combatant2=[[Image:Flag of the Democratic Federal Yugoslavia.svg|22px|border]] [[Yugoslav Partisans]]
|commander1=[[Image:Flag of Germany 1933.svg|22px|border]] [[Kurt Rybka]] (commanding only the special forces)
|commander2=[[Image:Flag of the Democratic Federal Yugoslavia.svg|22px|border]] [[Josip Broz Tito]]
|strength2=One infantry brigade
|strength1= some 3,500 German troops, several thousand Croatian troops
|casualties2='''Partisan claims:'''&lt;br&gt; 500 killed&lt;br&gt; 1,000 wounded&lt;br&gt; 2,000 civilian casualties&lt;br&gt;
'''German claims:'''&lt;br&gt; approximately 6,000 civilians and soldiers killed
|casualties1='''Partisan claims:'''&lt;br&gt; 788 confirmed killed&lt;br&gt; 881 wounded&lt;br&gt; 50 missing&lt;br&gt;
'''German claims:'''&lt;br&gt; 213 killed&lt;br&gt; 881 wounded&lt;br&gt; 51 missing

usually 2 follows 1--[[User:mrg3105|mrg3105]] ([[User talk:mrg3105|comms]]) ♠&lt;font color=&quot;#BB0000&quot;&gt;♥&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#BB0000&quot;&gt;♦&lt;/font&gt;♣ 10:49, 20 June 2008 (UTC)

:The matter is cleared up. --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:21, 20 June 2008 (UTC)

== Clean Up ==

G'day all, I know a little bit about this one, and have a copy of several journal articles on it. Given it is a BIG thing for the Partisans that Tito escaped and the Germans blew it, I think it is important to use military analyses of the operation as much as possible. So, I have sourced a RUSI article, and two published in the Journal of Slavic Military Studies, as well as the brief mentions this op gets in the main texts on this period in Yugoslavia (mainly Roberts).

My plan, as you will have guessed if you examine my edits, is to work through it para by para, adding inline citations and dispelling some well-known but errant nonsense (Evelyn Waugh was probably still writing 'Brideshead Revisited' in England when this little lot went down).

I warmly welcome any other editors who have an interest in improving this article. It is an obscure yet very interesting (to me at least) episode. Much misunderstood, and as one of the few small German parachute ops of the war, 'quite a pearler' as we say down here. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 10:05, 28 December 2011 (UTC)

:Direktor, can you help with a cyrillic version of the translation of Raid on Drvar in the lede?[[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 11:40, 4 January 2012 (UTC)
::Sure. For the record, the actual term used in Serbo-Croatian is not the equivalent of &quot;raid&quot;, but &quot;''desant''&quot;, which is the Serbo-Croatian spelling of the French word &quot;''descente''&quot; (the equivalent of the English &quot;descent&quot; of course). The exact meaning of &quot;''desant''&quot; in Serbo-Croatian is &quot;landing&quot;, and it is a term that is used exclusively to refer to military amphibious or airborne landings. &quot;Landing at Drvar&quot; would be the more accurate translation, and I am not sure whether this operation really qualifies as a &quot;raid&quot; as such.

::The way I would organize this article is I would rename (move) it to &quot;Seventh Enemy Offensive&quot; or &quot;Operation Rösselsprung&quot; or &quot;Operation Knight's Leap&quot;, with a large section entitled &quot;Landing on Drvar&quot;. The landing/raid is just a part of the wider offensive operation. Thoughts? --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 12:56, 4 January 2012 (UTC)
:::I think it should be renamed/moved, but the offensive was all about the coup de main airborne op. Rendulic knew he couldn't beat the Partisans at their own game at this stage, so killing Tito and destroying his headquarters was the aim of the whole offensive. The ground linkup and pursuit was in support of the airborne op and the pursuit resulted from its failure. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 13:21, 4 January 2012 (UTC)
::::Of course, but still, this article isn't just about the landing. No more than [[Operation Overlord]] was just about the [[Normandy landings]], for example... --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:54, 4 January 2012 (UTC)
:::::Agreed. My plan is to continue expanding it, next will be the plans for the ground forces, then a properly sourced description of the actual operation itself followed by the aftermath. There are factual errors in the latter parts of the article which I haven't bothered correcting, as I always planned to rewrite them with sources. In the meantime I will read up on how to rename/move in accordance with the naming policy [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 22:57, 4 January 2012 (UTC)

== Help wanted: lack of sources for Chetnik involvement in this offensive ==

Other than the involvement of a few Chetniks in intelligence gathering before the operation and the inclusion of a few Chetniks in the glider-borne Draufganger Group that landed at the crossroads, I have been unable to find any references to other Chetniks in the ground force or the airborne assault units. Unless someone is able to bring some sources for this other than Vojska.net (which has its problems), I believe that they will need to be removed from the infobox at least. I will mention the minor involvements I have been able to source, but I'm not aware of any source that supports the inclusion of formations or even detachments of Chetniks being involved. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 01:06, 29 December 2011 (UTC)
:Either way the Chetniks in the Draufganger Group should be mentioned.. I know I read somewhere that the Chetniks moved several corps as part of the wider Axis attack in support of the Drvar raid, but that was ages ago since Tomasevich avoids covering Drvar as it was slated for &quot;''The Partisans''&quot; (such a shame that man died before his life's work was done). That's all the &quot;help&quot; I can provide on this question unfortunately. --&lt;font face=&quot;Eras Bold ITC&quot;&gt;[[User:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;DimGray&quot;&gt;DIREKTOR&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:DIREKTOR|&lt;font color=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 09:22, 29 December 2011 (UTC)

User:Knightserbia has removed the reference in the order of battle section to Chetnik formations being on the Axis side in this operation. I have not sourced the involvement of the Chetnik brigades that KnightSerbia has deleted, so I have not restored their inclusion. However, Chetniks are mentioned by Eyre as being part of the Draufganger Group that landed by glider at the Western Cross. I have restored the Chetnik flag on that basis. If I source the involvement of Chetnik formations in the battle I will return them to the order. Any attempt to editwar regarding the Draufganger Group Chetniks without providing reliable published sources that state that Chetniks were not present in this battle on the side of the Germans will be reported. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 22:27, 5 January 2012 (UTC)

== Move to Operation Rösselsprung (1944) ==

Following agreement here ([[Talk:Battle_of_Kozara]]), I am moving this article to 'Operation Rösselsprung (1944)' per the German operation name and disambiguation with the 1942 Kreigsmarine operation of the same name. Please read the discussion for reasoning. The scope of the article will remain unchanged. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]] ([[User talk:Peacemaker67|talk]]) 04:07, 27 June 2012 (UTC)

== Hatnote ==

The hatnote from here was deleted with the edit summary &quot;''removed excess hatnote, this title is not ambiguous (WP:NAMB), it's disambiguated at Operation Rösselsprung''&quot;&lt;/br&gt; 
If that ''is'' the case, there needs to be a link to that page; it can’t be left with none at all. &lt;/br&gt;
However, [[WP:NAMB]] ''does'' allow for a hatnote like the one here, &quot;''when a more specific name is still ambiguous. For example, [[Matt Smith (comics)]] might still be confused for the comics illustrator [[Matt Smith (illustrator)]]''&quot; &lt;/br&gt; 
So, what’s it to be? The current hatnote or a link to the dab page? [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 13:50, 27 June 2012 (UTC)

: Can you please read [[WP:NAMB]] once again and hopefully see how what you're saying isn't making any sense? :) --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 13:57, 27 June 2012 (UTC)

: Sigh, so I have to spell it out. There are two Operations Roesselsprung - one from 1942, the other from 1944. When someone looks up the operation name, they end up at a disambiguation page. When someone arrives here, we know they weren't looking for the 1942 operation, so there's no need for disambiguation. Please do read [[WP:NAMB]]. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 14:03, 27 June 2012 (UTC)

== Dubious ==

The introduction says ''&quot;The operation failed because the various German intelligence agencies did not share the limited intelligence available&quot;''. Surely the operation failed because the Germans were outfought on the ground by the Partisans. Having this in the introduction looks like we are making excuses for them. [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 23:38, 30 November 2012 (UTC)
:I strongly disagree, as do the sources, in particular Eyre who did a comprehensive analysis. The purpose of the operation was to capture or kill Tito. The reason the paras didn't do that was that they were dropped/landed in the wrong places because they had the wrong objective (the cemetery rather than the cave) despite the fact that Skorzeny knew of the cave. This is explained in the article (as noted by several scholars on this topic). There is no doubt that the Partisans fought bravely and slowed the German ground assault down outside Drvar. Due to the poor deployment of the paras (which was based on the partial intelligence) they were unable to quickly capitalise on their short-term combat advantage in the town itself, with the result that nearby Partisan forces were able to affect the outcome and Tito was able to get away. Eyre and others suggest what the paras might have done if they knew of the cave before they jumped, but I didn't think that was a topic for the article. Happy to add it if you think it should be there. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 23:56, 30 November 2012 (UTC)
::To (belatedly) reply to this: Eyre is a useful resource for this article, but he is writing from a very particular perspective; ie. an analysis of the event for the benefit of anyone who might want to stage the same kind of operation. So (quite rightly) he focuses on the factors that are in the planners control (intelligence gathering, force composition, organization and training) rather than those which are not (the nature and strength of the opposition). And the wealth of information on those aspects have (I think) skewed the article. A while ago) this article was the &quot;Raid on Drvar&quot;, which was shaping up to be an even-handed account of a military action told from a neutral standpoint. Now it is &quot;Operation Rosselsprung&quot;, a German military operation, with the attendant shift in perspective. An article on the operation (the aims, planning, organization, outcome) is fair enough as a subject but it shouldn’t be replacing an objective account of the action itself.
::Secondly, simply saying the operation failed because German intelligence failed to co-operate, and the attackers lacked flexibility only tells half the story; the failure to share intelligence was an inevitable result of the internecine warfare that passed for inter-service and inter-departmental co-operation in the Nazi war machine, and that was an inevitable result of Hitler’s Darwinian approach to government. And it wasn’t just a matter of not sharing information; Szorzeny may have known about the cave, but no-one on the German side knew where Tito would be at any one time. None of them knew he had moved  his quarters to Batasi down the road, and it was mere luck that he was at the cave when the attack went in. 
::Also the type of flexibility required would be that generally found in Special forces units; the unit involved (the 500th SS Paratroopers) wasn’t a Special Force in that sense, it was some kind of [[forlorn hope]] unit where defaulters could redeem themselves. Perfect for some dangerous/suicidal operation; not so suitable for an operation demanding a high degree of initiative and independent action. Skorzeny (who was the nearest thing the Germans had to a Special Forces commander) reckoned the operation was doomed to failure and should be cancelled; as it was he was proved right.
::To simply suggest (in this article) that it would have succeeded “if only...” implies that the Germans here were capable of doing any better. Eyre was writing for a military that could; we aren’t. [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 02:30, 15 December 2012 (UTC)
:::To address your first point, the title makes little difference IMO, and the article is vastly improved from this time in 2011. With respect to the editors that had contributed to that point, your assertion that it was &quot;was shaping up to be an even-handed account of a military action told from a neutral standpoint&quot; is unsupportable in my view. Then [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Operation_R%C3%B6sselsprung_(1944)&amp;oldid=465890213] it contained enormous factual errors and virtually no details. As far as the title is concerned, we have a choice between &quot;Raid on Drvar&quot; (a one-sided title drawn from the &quot;heroic&quot; Partisan film of that name and narrowly focused on the airborne op), the current title (admittedly one-sided but more accurate in terms of scope), and &quot;Seventh Enemy Offensive&quot; (which is a straight-out piece of Partisan propaganda, and as vague as you can get). The &quot;Seven Enemy Offensives&quot; is a schema created by the communists to focus on how heroic the Partisans were, and to build the legend of Tito. We made the decision to move away from the Partisan schema with all these operations, as they elevate particular operations above others that are just as important but did not meet the needs of communist propaganda. So as far as I am concerned, the title is as good as we are going to get. I personally would prefer not to use the operation name, but in order to make it as neutral as possible, it is the better of three evils.
:::On your second point, I agree that Eyre had a particular focus (the paper was originally part of his Command and Staff College work after all), and it would benefit from some expansion in respect of the role of stubborn resistance of the Partisans in the area of operations, both in the lead and the body. I will look at that now. I also agree that Hitler's divide and rule approach to command and control made it incredibly difficult for coordination between intelligence agencies. The reality is that that is always a problem, witness 9/11. 
:::Eyre says Skorzeny believed it would fail because it was (in his view) compromised from an intelligence perspective ie the secret was out due to the re-capture of the deserter. As it turned out, it wasn't. It failed, but not for the reason Skorzeny feared.
:::I believe that those that have written on this operation generally are on the same page as Eyre, but I will review them to ensure I have not skewed the article, and will make necessary amendments. I appreciate your interest and feedback on the article, and hope you will have a look at the changes I make and provide further feedback. Regards, [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 03:13, 15 December 2012 (UTC)
::::I hadn’t realized the name &quot;Raid on Drvar&quot; also had a neutrality problem. And yes, the article now is a lot more detailed (and approaching GA status! Good work!) 
::::I’m still trying to get a grasp of the Yugoslav campaign; my impression is that this was Germany's own “[[Spanish Ulcer]]”, but it’s unclear from the articles we have what the partisans were actually doing. The [[Yugoslav Partisan]] article says they disposed 650,000 soldiers in regular units and were engaged in conventional warfare; yet the articles we have are mostly on Axis anti-partisan operations, and (as you say) even the Partisan history is structured around “enemy offensives”. There’s a hint of it in the page on the [[Operation Prijedor|Prijedor operation]] ie. that they had isolated the garrison there and the Axis had to mount a relief  operation to save them; but even there the article is mostly on what the Axis forces were doing. 
::::Anyway, thank you for considering my comments. [[User:Xyl 54|Xyl 54]] ([[User talk:Xyl 54|talk]]) 02:21, 17 December 2012 (UTC)

== Literature and Documents section ==

G'day, this article is currently a GAN, please don't add a list of primary sources and non-[[WP:RS]] memoirs like Kumm's book. There is no scope for such a list in WP:MOS and Greentree's book is already in the References section. Thanks, [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 09:35, 8 December 2012 (UTC)

{{Talk:Operation Rösselsprung (1944)/GA1}}

== Infobox casualty figures for the Partisans ==

Infoboxes do not lend themselves to properly explaining conflicting sources. That is why there is a link to the Aftermath section. That is why I have reverted the IP edits (and possibly why 23 editor did). IPs constantly disrupt and vandalise pages on Yugoslavia in WWII, perhapd you might like to register as a user. BTW, just so we are clear, if you are reverted, the appropriate action for you to take is to create a section such as this on the article talk page, per [[WP:BRD]]. Regards, [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 08:14, 31 March 2014 (UTC)

== &quot;Mixed Irregular Elements&quot; ==

This is probably confusing because Germans were using a curios title for Četniks at that time: ''Kroatische Kampfgemeinschaften'', ie, Croatian Combat Groups. It was some political hocus pocus with which Germans tried to legalize Četniks in a for Pavelić acceptable form, something like what Italians did with MVAC.--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 08:52, 20 July 2014 (UTC)
:I agree, but we still need a source. Perhaps if we identified the commander? [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 10:10, 20 July 2014 (UTC)

== The First Partisan Unit to Attack 500 SS in Drvar ==

It was stated in text that it was 3rd Proletarian Brigade of the 1st Proletarian Division, and it was referenced with Eyre's article in JSMS (2006,353-354). I don't have the article from the journal, but in [http://znaci.net/00002/362.pdf Eyre's original text], it was stated correctly: ''From the west and southwest came three of the battalions of the Third Brigade of the '''Sixth Lika Division'''''.(pp=20-21)--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 09:51, 20 July 2014 (UTC)
:You are right, and the Lika Division was Proletarian (since March 1944). Must have been a typo. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 10:12, 20 July 2014 (UTC)

== Partisan losses - contrasted sources? ==

Actually, there is not the case of contrasted sources between Popović, Lolić and Latas on the other side, and Odić on the other. The former use the same data as Odić,(p. 275) but they state only losses of combat units, while omitting losses of Pioneer Brigade, Guard Battalion, Officer School, and more.--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 11:03, 20 July 2014 (UTC)
:Can we state that then? [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 11:17, 20 July 2014 (UTC)
::You can find both data in Odić: the [http://znaci.net/00003/449.pdf table of combat units losses (Odić) on pp. 275-6] - that's the one used by Popović, Lolić, Latas - and the table with added losses of other formations and institutions on p. 278.--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 11:47, 20 July 2014 (UTC)
:::Ok, I've just listed it as &quot;total&quot; losses, as someone else may come across it and think it over states it. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 11:54, 20 July 2014 (UTC)

== Additional information in Ground forces section ==

Gorran, you've added info about the 202nd Panzer Battalion, V SS Corps and some other units in this section. These details don't appear in Eyre. Can you cite them all closely please? Cheers, [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 23:25, 1 August 2014 (UTC)
:Ok, I'm on it. Please take a look after an hour or so, and notify me if something is omitted.--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 02:24, 2 August 2014 (UTC)
::About V SS Corps - both 7th SS and 369th were V SS Corps, and the numeration &quot;105th SS Reconnaissance Battalion&quot; literally means Reconnaissance Battalion of the Command of the V SS Corps. [http://znaci.net/NARA/T314_563/701.htm This] is the operational order of the PzAOK2 (Rendulic) to V SS (Phleps). It's a common knowledge - but, (maybe for this reason) not mentioned in Odić-1981.--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 02:51, 2 August 2014 (UTC)
:::My understanding is that all formations were placed under operational command of von Leyser, I wasn't aware Phleps had command of them during Rosselsprung. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 02:57, 2 August 2014 (UTC)
::::That is true. These units were elements of the V Corps, tactically subordinated to the XV Corps for the operation. Shall I remove mentioning of the V SS, or mentioning of the Phleps, or both?--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 03:05, 2 August 2014 (UTC)
:::::I don't think it necessary to mention Phleps or V SS Corps. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 03:16, 2 August 2014 (UTC)
::::::Ok, I'm convinced.--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 03:21, 2 August 2014 (UTC)

== Editing the Relief of the paratroopers section ==

This section consists of one sentence, and, with the expansion of the article, it became misplaced, covering the event already described in text. So, I '''did not''' delete one in favour of the other. I preserved and included every bit of information from the sentence, and added the reference at the appropriate place. But became necessary to make this minor re-arangement of the composition. By the way, all the sources are mostly in mutual accordance. So, the intervention was not about favouring one source on behalf of the other - it was only and exclusively about composition.--[[User:Gorran|Gorran]] ([[User talk:Gorran|talk]]) 15:22, 3 August 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>63dmvsjbsmn1ysrfdee41is6s03owtl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
