<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1760772</id>
    <revision>
      <id>649691994</id>
      <parentid>623603537</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-03-03T14:36:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dthomsen8</username>
        <id>6277327</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7499">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=03:24, 6 June 2014 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=611771418
|topic=Warfare
|dykdate=25 June 2014
|dykentry=... that World War II French General '''[[Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque|Leclerc]]''' adopted his ''[[nom de guerre]]'' to avoid risk to his family in the event his missions appeared in the papers?
|currentstatus=GA

|action2=WAR
|action2date=14:10, 12 August 2014 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=618890051
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject France|class=A|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=high|class=GA|listas=Leclerc, Jacques Philippe}}
{{WikiProject Military history|A-Class=pass|class=A|B1=yes|B2=yes|B3=yes|B4=yes|B5=yes|Biography=yes|African=yes|French=yes|Southeast-Asian=yes|WWII=yes}}
}}

==Untitled==
Merged material in from [[Jacques Philippe Leclerc]] - it seemed silly to have two articles on one person. ... and a lot of material from the fr: page, who I assume have the name correct. [[User:Shimgray|Shimgray]] 22:22, 18 Apr 2005 (UTC)

I moved the page to the name under which he is generally known. [[User:David.Monniaux|David.Monniaux]] 09:52, 22 Apr 2005 (UTC)

== Hauteclocque and not Hautecloque ==

the name is Hauteclocque with a &quot;C&quot; Hauteclo&quot;c&quot;que

==Requested move==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived debate of the {{{type|proposal}}}. &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/font&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

{{{result|The result of the debate was}}} '''Moved'''. —[[User:Centrx|Centrx]]→[[User talk:Centrx|''talk'']]&amp;nbsp;• 01:51, 19 August 2006 (UTC)

Philippe Leclerc de Hautecloque → Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque – Reason: correct spelling of surname (See comment above, and French language Wikipedia) [[User:Kahuzi|Kahuzi]] 14:01, 11 August 2006 (UTC)
===Survey===
'''Support'''. His name is spelled with the extra 'c' (Hauteclocque) in Le Petit Larousse Illustré, 2005 edition. [[User:EdJohnston|EdJohnston]] 21:02, 11 August 2006 (UTC)
*Support Nigel Hamilton spells it with the original ''c'' in his biography of Montgomery, under whom Leclerc served for a period.  --[[User:Harlsbottom|Harlsbottom]] 00:55, 12 August 2006 (UTC)
*'''Support''' per EdJohnston. --[[User:Mathew5000|Mathew5000]] 12:52, 12 August 2006 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the debate.  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/font&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;

== Image mistake ==

The French general showed here with (from left to right) US general Bradley, US general Eisenhower and British air chief marshal Tedder is not general Leclerc, but is actually general Koenig, the military governor of Paris. The date may be 29 august 1944, during a parade of American troops on the Champs-Elysées avenue in Paris. --[[User:Sbene|Sbene]] ([[User talk:Sbene|talk]]) 19:42, 28 November 2007 (UTC)


Will someone change this useless picture of general Koenig ?? I guess that for American people, a general with a kepi and a moustache is enough typical of the French to be Leclerc...

== &quot;Killing of French POW's&quot; ==

I have removed the above-named section and retained it here for further reference.  There are a number of reasons for doing so.  It's incorrect and also shoddily sourced, which is no good for verifiability or credibility.

What this section was ''perhaps'' alluding to was an incident involving the 2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; D.B. of the French Army in Bad Reichenhall on [[8 May]] [[1945]] (a very long way from the Rhein-Lahn mentioned in the section).  11 or 12 members of the &quot;Charlemagne&quot; Waffen-Gren. Regt. der SS 58, prisoners of the French were summarily executed.  It is NOT known who gave the order.  See ''For Europe: The French Volunteers of the Waffen-SS'' by Robert Forbes, pp. 480s.  The website given as a source is unsourced and could easily be argued to be biased due to its condemnation of left-wing groups.  The other source, Whiting's ''Operation Northwind'', a book on the Battle of the Bulge, is cited with no page references.

--[[User:Harlsbottom|Harlsbottom]] ([[User talk:Harlsbottom|talk]] | [[User:Harlsbottom/Library|library]]) 20:23, 24 June 2008 (UTC)

===Killing of French POW’s===
In May 1945, French forces under Gen. Philippe Leclerc stopped 11 or 12 French prisoners from the [[33rd Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Charlemagne (1st French)|SS ''Charlemagne'' Regiment ]] in [[Rhein-Lahn]]. These POWs, who had volunteered to fight against the [[Soviet Union]], had been hospitalized fighting on the [[Eastern Front]]. They had since surrendered and were being moved to a POW area.

Gen. Leclerc asked them why they wore the uniform of the enemy. One prisoner replied, &quot;Why do you wear the uniform of the Americans?&quot;.  Enraged, Leclerc declared them to be traitors and ordered them to be shot.

Their bodies were left lying by the side of the road. They were buried nearby a few days later by American soldiers&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thirdreichruins.com/memorials.htm|accessdate=2007-09-11|title=
Gen. Leclerc confronting the prisoners}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Operation Northwind, Charles Whiting&lt;/ref&gt;
{{reflist}}

== French POWs during WWII ==

The article states &quot;After the armistice was signed on 22 June, French soldiers were simply allowed to go home, and the Germans were friendly towards de Hauteclocque, especially when they discovered that he spoke fluent German.&quot;

What???? French soldiers were NOT simply allowed to go home, and most well educated French people at the time spoke German, nothing out of the way there.

Whoever wrote this never heard of the 1.5 million French POWs! According to the French Wikipedia on Leclerc, he did exactly what my father, also a French officer, did before the armistice in June 1940 became effective - get authorization from his commanding officer to leave and try to go to London, where they would be more useful than in a POW camp.[[Special:Contributions/82.120.237.109|82.120.237.109]] ([[User talk:82.120.237.109|talk]]) 09:14, 31 August 2014 (UTC)
:I wrote it and I have heard about the 1.5 million POWs. They were captured before the Armistice became effective. It was hoped that they would soon be released, but only a few were. The majority remained in POW camps for the duration. Leclerc obtained permission from his commanding officer to make his way back to French lines and rejoin the fight, which he did, ''not'' to go to London. From memory, he was listed as a deserter. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 10:17, 31 August 2014 (UTC)

Thanks for prompt answer. You are right, in May 1940, it still made sense for Leclerc to rejoin the French lines rather than go to London. But after the armistice, on June 25, French soldiers had to (military law) let themselves be made prisoner and sent East.[[Special:Contributions/82.120.237.109|82.120.237.109]] ([[User talk:82.120.237.109|talk]]) 18:02, 31 August 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qd3aewinxphmckezsluy0fhrw5qs66j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
