<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Borodino-class battlecruiser</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12268641</id>
    <revision>
      <id>579673164</id>
      <parentid>576006641</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-10-31T23:02:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GamerPro64</username>
        <id>7470528</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Promoted</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6895">{{Talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=21:28, 16 April 2010
|action1link=Talk:Borodino class battlecruiser/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=356315097

|action2=GTC
|action2date=02:20, 17 August 2010
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Battlecruisers of Russia/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=379248547

|action3=WAR
|action3date=03:14, 20 August 2010
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Borodino-class battlecruiser
|action3result=approved
|action3oldid=379458906

|action4=FAC
|action4date=20:02, 11 December 2010
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Borodino class battlecruiser/archive1
|action4result=not promoted
|action4oldid=400585282

|action5=FTC
|action5date=22:33, 31 October 2013 (UTC)
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Battlecruisers of the World/archive1
|action5result=promoted

|ftname=Battlecruisers of the world
|ft2name=Battlecruisers of Russia
|dykdate=19 January 2010
|dykentry=... that the [[Red Army]] prevented the incomplete [[Borodino class battlecruiser|'''''Borodino'' class battlecruiser''']] ''Izmail'' ''(pictured)'' from being converted to a [[aircraft carrier|carrier]] by gaining control of a commission appointed to review the needs of the Navy
|topic=War
|currentstatus=GA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Ships|class=A}}
{{WPMILHIST|A-Class=pass|class=A|Russian=yes|Maritime=yes|WWI=yes|OMT=1}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=A|importance=Low|tech=yes|mil=yes}}
}}

==Question==
:Obvious question - ''why'' did the Red Army not want Izmail converted into a carrier? Conceptual opposition to carriers, a desire to avoid the Navy taking a larger share of the defence budget by having a new capital ship of any type, or something even more complicated? [[User:Shimgray|Shimgray]] | [[User talk:Shimgray|talk]] | 21:31, 19 January 2010 (UTC)
::Too much money not going to the Army.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 23:56, 19 January 2010 (UTC)

==Copyedit thoughts==
Some thoughts for copyediting:

*We introduce one of the ships by name in a sentence &quot;Components for the turbines of the ''Navarin'' that had been ordered&quot; without previously identifying that the ''Navarin'' is a Borodino class battlecruiser. Might be better to introduce the names before making use of them.
*The sentence &quot;but the Duma session ended before it could be voted on&quot; might be better as &quot;but the Duma session ended before it approved funding for the construction&quot;, or some such. Later in the article we learn that the Duma does finally approve funds for the project.
**I changed it to read &quot;but the Duma session ended before the proposal could be voted on&quot;.
*&quot;and some money had to be diverted from the budget for the Svetlana-class cruisers.&quot; strikes me as poor phrasing ... '''had''' based on what? Better to say that the budget was in any event reduced to provide funds for the construction of  Svetlana-class cruisers.
**Changed to &quot;money was diverted from the budget&quot;.
*There are a couple of &quot;In the meantime&quot; phrases; would be nice to rephrase one of them.
**I dropped one instance.
*Check consistency of use of Armament versus Armaments. I may have introduced the latter, possibly in error.
*We have no article on high-tension steel. That seems a pity. I'd prefer to keep the link. There's no use in specifying the material if we have no definition of what it means.
*Not thrilled with the sentence &quot;as shown in the table below, but in some respects the situation was worse than shown as the turrets for Izmail were not expected to be completed until 1919.&quot; I understand the logic, having looked at the table, since we're telling the reader that the situation was worse before they have had a chance to see from the table what the situation was.
**I agree; i have worked the material into the prose.
--[[User:Tagishsimon|Tagishsimon]] [[User_talk:Tagishsimon|(talk)]] 19:45, 2 December 2010 (UTC)
:Hi, Tagishimon. We had an edit conflict there! Suddenly this article is popular. I have looked over your remarks now that my first pass is complete, and taken action on some of your suggestions. My responses are above in intented text. I will do another pass later this evening and see if I can spot anything else. Please feel free to introduce more improvements in the meantime, as I am stopping for now. --[[User:Diannaa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:teal;&quot;&gt;Diannaa&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Diannaa|Talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 21:20, 2 December 2010 (UTC)

Thanks Diannaa. I'll give it a little more time, though I should really do some IRL work... --[[User:Tagishsimon|Tagishsimon]] [[User_talk:Tagishsimon|(talk)]] 21:45, 2 December 2010 (UTC)

*The sentence &quot;and that the effects of muzzle blast on the open sighting hoods on the turret roofs below would cause damage to the guns in the lower turret&quot; is not doing it for me. It previously read &quot;and that the effects of muzzle blast on the open sighting hoods on the turret roofs below prevented superfiring turrets from firing their guns over the lower turret.&quot; I understand the point being made in the paragraph as being that non-superfiring guns were chosen rather than superfiring guns, since the latter would cause damage through the open sighting hoods. But I may have this wrong.
**I don't think there was anything physically preventing them from using the upper guns while the  sighting hoods were open on the lower set; they chose not to do so because they did not want to damage the lower guns. Sturmvogel can fix this if I have misinterpreted.
***I've edited it to make more clear what was going on; its by way of explaining why they went for non-superfiring. --[[User:Tagishsimon|Tagishsimon]] [[User_talk:Tagishsimon|(talk)]] 00:02, 3 December 2010 (UTC)
****Yes, now that I see the edit, I agree this phrasing works better. I am postponing any further work on it until tomorrow when it will seem fresh again. --[[User:Diannaa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:teal;&quot;&gt;Diannaa&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Diannaa|Talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 02:52, 3 December 2010 (UTC)
*In the '''Armament''' section, we speak of one of the gun sets as &quot;were intended to be&quot; but state that the other guns &quot;were mounted&quot;, etc. However we know that no guns ever came close to the ships. Why do we single out only one set of guns as &quot;intended&quot; when, in fact, all were equally only ever proposals/specifications.
**Yea, I agree. The whole paragraph makes it sound like the ship was actually completed. I think we may need to change the whole paragraph to reflect the fact that the ship was never built. You can work on this if you have time, as I have RL things to do for an hour or so. Again, Sturmvogel can re-work anything we misinterpret as presumably he still has his source material available.--[[User:Diannaa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:teal;&quot;&gt;Diannaa&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Diannaa|Talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 22:45, 2 December 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7512stbopxt0jxrgexfudq3loi9vrt8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
