<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Berlin</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12840030</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746716828</id>
      <parentid>746614687</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-29T02:58:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Battle of Berlin/Archive 10]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24419">{{talkheader|noarchive=yes|search=no}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=A|old-peer-review=y|A-Class=pass|German=y|Russian=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=A|importance=High|Prussia=yes}}
{{WikiProject Soviet Union|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=A|importance=Top|hist=y|mil=y}}
}}
{{OnThisDay |date1=2005-05-02|oldid1=16335190|date2=2006-05-02|oldid2=51212000|date3=2007-05-02|oldid3=127611131|date4=2008-05-02|oldid4=209404894|date5=2009-05-02|oldid5=287469370|date6=2010-05-02|oldid6=359542992|date7=2015-05-02|oldid7=660036821|date8=2016-05-02|oldid8=718036562}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WPR
|action1date=01:04, 27 July 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/Battle of Berlin
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=147212362

|action2=WAR
|action2date=03:22, 22 September 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Battle of Berlin
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=239357652

|action3=FAC
|action3date=00:25, 11 October 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Berlin/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=244398092

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 10
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Battle of Berlin/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index
|mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{Archives |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months |search=yes|index=/Archive index}}

== Section &quot;Commemoration&quot; - Victory Banner on Reichstag in 2007 ? ==

In the section &quot;Commemoration&quot;
it is stated that &quot;... on 7 May 2007, as a copy of the flag was raised on the Reichstag ...&quot;

This might just be bad wording, 
actually meaning that the Russian flag-law refers to the banner of 1945,&lt;br /&gt;
but it made me spend hours trying to find anything on 
a Russian flag being raised on the Reichstag in 2007 (There was nothing).

Naturally, me hitting google for a few hours isn't the end all be all, 
so a check would be greatly appreciated.

== Consensus for use of unreliable sources ==

I'm failing to see any consensus amongst editors for the inclusion of sources [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Battle_of_Berlin/Archive_9#RFC_on_Soviet_rapes deemed to be unreliable] or, at the least, undue. Can anyone please demonstrate where this has taken place? In reading over the talk page (and archives), plus the edit history of the article itself, there seems to be nothing outside of a momentum picked up on again, eventually, by a POV editor. The POV pushing of one editor is not the equivalent of [[WP:CON]]. The fact that these same sources have started cropping up on related articles outside of consensus smacks of [[WP:TE|tendentious editing]]. Has anyone else noticed the [[WP:TROJAN]]s being wheeled in? --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 03:24, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
:If you want go read through the archives. Coming to an article you never edited before, making a revert, and asking others to explain things to you is disruptive.
:Those other articles had most of the sources before the dispute here last year. You should understand what is going on before following me here and making reverts. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 03:34, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
::You're not terribly good at nuances. I'm being facetious because there is no evidence for consensus in adding the sources you've added. As for your accusations of my being disruptive, please read this: [[WP:HA#NOT]]. You've been popping up on all sorts of articles on my watchlist and [[WP:REHASH|rehashing]] the same arguments, trying to introduce the same rejected content, and basically making it abundantly clear that you're willing to wait around until no one is watching in order to continue with your [[WP:TE|tendentious editing]] practices. In other words, I understand precisely what is going on both here and in related pages: your [[WP:ADVOCACY]]. Now I will ask you again, civilly, to desist from your [[WP:SPA]] activities. Thank you for your understanding. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 04:46, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
:::Your personal attack is noted.
:::You should not follow users to articles you never edited before to make such attacks.
:::You are claiming that I sneaked in text when there was so much discussion going on and an admin even protected the page... Surely, he would have reverted the stuff I was trying to push. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 05:00, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
::::''&quot; YMB29, with all due respect, you have been warned before on this issue, and this remains the English wikipedia: there is no serious disgreement that this kind of thing occurred after the fall of the city, except by former Soviet writers. I've gone over your quotes immediately above, and they simply don't invalidate the Western scholarly consensus: protests, possibly, but no evidence that says the acts did not occur.&quot;'' - User:Buckshot06, right above. [[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 05:25, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
:::::I replied to him above. I did not question the &quot;Western scholarly consensus,&quot; so what is your point? -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 05:44, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
:::::Further to this, when was the article 'protected' and when was the 'protection' removed? Any [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;action=info page protection] has long since been removed. Do you actually understand what page protection means? Do you imagine that Big Brother is constantly watching this article, or that sysops are only human and not infallible even during periods where an article is 'protected'? The issue is that you are reintroducing dubious sources which, in itself, calls for reviewing where and how they've been used. If you believe your sources to be kosher, take it to the [[WP:RSN]]. An argument as to the reliability of these sources and the context in which they've been used has arisen yet again. No previous version using these sources is sacrosanct while the subject of their being RS or UNDUE is under dispute. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 05:28, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
::::::So you are questioning sources that meet all of the RS criteria? There were no questions about the reliability of these sources by the end of the discussion here anyway, and you know from other pages that they are reliable.
::::::Are you claiming that I made invisible changes while this article was protected? -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 05:44, 11 February 2015 (UTC)
:::::::See this old edit.[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=607155840&amp;oldid=607124898] The text you removed (''Senyavskaya cites an official record of the Soviet military prosecutor of the 1st Belorussian Front, which states that on the Belorussian Front from 22 April to 5 May 1945, only 124 crimes against civilians were recorded, including 72 rapes'') was actually added by the user I was disputing with. So can you admit that you were wrong and undue your revert? -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 19:11, 11 February 2015 (UTC)

[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=646592445&amp;oldid=646592247 This revert by YMB29] does not add any content to the article. It only inserts references to Senyavskaya. Therefore, it looks very much to me as [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:What_Wikipedia_is_not#Wikipedia_is_not_a_soapbox_or_means_of_promotion promotion] of Senyavskaya by YM29, especially given his insistence on including references specifically on her publications in multiple articles. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 03:19, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
:Did you read above? How could it be promotion by me if it was added by another user? That does not make sense. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 03:56, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
::No, it was you who inserted these bare references twice [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=645762405&amp;oldid=645752706],[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=646592445&amp;oldid=646592247]. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 04:03, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
:::That was when you reverted it recently. Don't pretend that you did not see my comment above. Originally, it was added by another user, again see [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=607155840&amp;oldid=607124898 here]. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 04:21, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
::::Oh man, I spent enough time here, but I have never seen anyone who would denied obvious so persistently. Not only two my diffs above show that you edit war to include bare references to Senyavskya, but your diff (let me repeat it [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=607155840&amp;oldid=607124898]) shows that the reference to Senavskaya existed ''before'' the edit by PBS, he only replaced/modified it. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 04:42, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
:::::Yes, modified the text that you removed recently. Note that he modified it, not removed it, so the claim that I sneaked the source in is false. You three should apologize for stalking me to this article, removing text, and making false accusations. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 05:34, 12 February 2015 (UTC)

So in conclusion, the text recently reverted by users who never edited the article before was added by the very user I was disputing with.[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=607155840&amp;oldid=607124898] There was consensus for including the source (reached by discussion, RfC and editing). The issue back then was not if the source and text should be added to the article, but where it should be added. It was eventually left in the footnotes. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 17:23, 12 February 2015 (UTC)


The text by Bird was added by another user too years ago. So again the false accusations continue. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 18:35, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
:It was added by Paul Siebert back in 2009.[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Berlin&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=365270310] -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 18:44, 12 February 2015 (UTC)

{{od}}
{{Anchor|YMB29's first edit}}There was never a consensus for including the fringe views of some Russian historians with undue weight in this article. At first you, [[User:YMB29|YMB29]], tried to change the wording from 
{{quotation|During, and in the days immediately following the assault,{{sfn|Bellamy|2007|p=670}}{{sfn|Grossmann|2009|p=51}} in many areas of the city, vengeful Soviet troops (often rear echelon units{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=326–327}}) engaged in [[rape during the occupation of Germany|mass rape]], pillage and murder,{{sfn|Beevor|May 2002}}{{efn|name=Rapes}} and despite Soviet efforts to supply food and rebuild the city, starvation remained a problem.{{sfn|White|2003|p=126}} In June 1945, one month after the surrender, the average calorie intake of Berliners was still low as they were getting only 64 percent of a 1,240-calorie daily ration.{{sfn|Ziemke|1990|p=303}} Further, across the city over a million people were without a home.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=419}}
{{reflist}}
}}
to
{{quotation|According to Antony Beevor, during, and in the days immediately following the assault, in many areas of the city, vengeful Soviet troops (often rear echelon units{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=326–327}}) engaged in [[rape during the occupation of Germany|mass rape]], pillage and murder.{{sfn|Beevor|May 2002}}{{efn|name=Rapes}} Historian Atina Grossmann claims that for women &quot;Goebbels's fevered prophecies about the threat from the Asiatic hordes seemed to be fulfilled.&quot;{{sfn|Grossmann|2009|p=51}} The looting and rapes gradually subsided.{{sfn|Bellamy|2007|p=670}} According to historian Oleg Rzheshevsky, such portrayal of the Red Army is a return to views that were instilled by Nazi propaganda and Neo-Nazi historians.{{sfn|Rzheshevsky|2002|}}
{{reflist}}
}}
Which was wording in such a way as to imply that Beevor is a Neo-Nazi historian. As to the wording &quot;The Russian historian Elena Senyavskaya has stated that mass rapes did not occur,&quot; That was put in to show what a ludicrous position she hold, ([[Wikipedia:Let the facts speak for themselves|Let the Facts speak for themselves]]) as any one reading it will see that she is not an [[objective historian]]. I stopped arguing with you [[User:YMB29|YMB29]], not because I think that you have not harmed this article by including the text that you have, but because it was too much of a time sink, and I have more constructive things to be doing with my time. A am pleased that someone else has taken up the baton and is willing to discuss it further with you. So to be clear I am in favour of resorting the wording &quot;mass rape, pillage and murder,&quot; and of downplaying the views of these fringe Russian historians, who clearly do not represent the majority view.  -- [[User:PBS|PBS]] ([[User talk:PBS|talk]]) 18:59, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
:The consensus was that the Russian historians are not fringe, but are obviously in the minority. So you said that they should be mentioned in the footnotes, and eventually that is what happened; they were left in the footnotes.
:These users never edited the article and are simply stalking me.
:The text that was removed recently was the exact same text you put into the footnotes. As for not being an objective historian, that is your opinion, but reliable sources say otherwise.[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Rape_during_the_occupation_of_Germany#Senyavskaya_in_Western_sources]
:Plus Bird's text was not added by me, and had consensus for a long time. -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 19:04, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
::Nobody's stalking you. It's just that if you're up to some shenanigans sooner or later more and more people notice. PBS's comment that they gave up editing the article not because they thought your actions were not disruptive but rather out of exasperation, and your reply to this comment, is a perfect illustration of your [[WP:BATTLEGROUND]] attitude, your [[WP:IDIDNTHEARTHAT]] and your tendentious POV pushing. You are not trying to convince anyone, you are simply trying to wear them out.
::I too have better things to do with my time. And it is crystal clear that consensus is against you. So until you can muster new sources and new arguments, there is little point in further discussion.[[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 19:27, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
:::PBS was not the only user forming the consensus here. There was enough support for the Russian view to add it to the article, see [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Battle_of_Berlin/Archive_8#Support_for_the_Russian_view here]. Claiming that I simply wore out all the other users, including an admin who made the last edit in the dispute, is ridiculous.
:::Plus how are you going to excuse your removal of Bird's text? -[[User:YMB29|YMB29]] ([[User talk:YMB29|talk]]) 19:31, 12 February 2015 (UTC)
::::&quot;As for not being an objective historian, that is your opinion&quot; See above and the archives. That she fails several of the bullet points that are used to assess what an [[objective historian]] is:
::::* ''The historian must not dismiss counterevidence without scholarly consideration;'' -- she dismisses all the claims that mass rapes took place either by suggesting it is Nazi propaganda, or obfuscating by asking &quot;what about the behaviour of western Allied troops&quot; implying that the motive of other historians who suggest that the Red Army committed mass rape are somehow not themselves objective historians.
::::* ''The historian must be even-handed in treatment of evidence and eschew &quot;cherry-picking&quot;;'' using one official Soviet document that goes against the mass of other evidence (It is simply not credible that only 72 rapes took place).
::::* ''The historian must weigh the authenticity of all accounts, not merely those that contradict a favored view;''
::::Means that she is not an objective historian.
::::{{green|&quot;There was enough support for the Russian view to add it to the article, see [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Battle_of_Berlin/Archive_8#Support_for_the_Russian_view here]. Claiming that I simply wore out all the other users, including an admin who made the last edit in the dispute, is ridiculous.}} You are doing it again for example the like you give includes a section with a wall of text by you and one other editor who was not exactly whole heartedly behind you proposals does not a summer make. Most other editors left me to argue with you and as I said above there comes a point where it is just not a useful to continue to engage with an editor over a few words in an article when there is so much more that can be done to improve Wikiepdia with less effort. Now if you are true to form you will come back with a long obfuscating response as is your want. I probably will not respond again, as you clearly are continuing to behave in the same way.-- [[User:PBS|PBS]] ([[User talk:PBS|talk]]) 22:07, 13 February 2015 (UTC)
::::*[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Battle_of_Berlin/Archive_8#Support_for_the_Russian_view This] is not &quot;Russian view&quot;, and there is no such thing as &quot;Russian view&quot;. These are views by several nationalist/revisionist historians that were cherry-picked by YMB29. These revisionist historians were criticized for falsifications and [[scientific misconduct]] (no less) by other Russian historians, such as Mark Solonin. Unfortunately, [[Vladimir Medinsky|these revisionist historians]] were placed &quot;in charge&quot; of History by Putin's administration [http://www.rferl.org/content/russia-profile-culture-minister-vladimir-medinsky/24602133.html]. [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 23:38, 13 February 2015 (UTC)
::::::Mark solonin doesn't even have a historical academic degree (he got his higher education as aviation engineer). He is also widely accused of history falsification and folk-history by the russian historians such as D. Gavrilov, Georgy Kumanev, A. Ermolaev, Alexey Isaev, A. Kilichenkov and the veteran of the Great patriotic war Yazov Dmitry (the last surviving Marshal of the Soviet Union). Do you have any other proofs of your statement except your own opinion?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:ForzeX|ForzeX]] ([[User talk:ForzeX|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/ForzeX|contribs]]) 01:56, 23 February 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::::::So, where people you mentioned accused Solonin of falsification and what exactly falsification(s) they are talking about? Any references?  [[User:My very best wishes|My very best wishes]] ([[User talk:My very best wishes|talk]]) 17:06, 24 February 2015 (UTC)
{{od}}
Something that I think needs to be said here is that the test of whether the reputation of Senyavskya has been damaged by these revelations will be how many scholarly papers in future cite her books and papers. Both [[David Irving]] and [[Ward Churchill]] where frequently cited by non-specialist works before their fall from grace -- see also [[Ward Churchill academic misconduct investigation]] and the article on Irving's discredited book ''[[The Destruction of Dresden]]'' (1963) that contains a section on why [[Kurt Vonnegut]] wrote &quot;135,000 Hansels and Gretels had been baked like gingerbread men&quot; (at the time he used Irving's book for the numbers killed, few but some experts, doubted that Irving was a objective historian). -- [[User:PBS|PBS]] ([[User talk:PBS|talk]]) 17:28, 28 March 2015 (UTC)

== rationale for mass-rapes in Berlin ==

&quot;''All they knew about foreign countries was there was unemployment, starvation and exploitation. And when they came to Europe they saw something very different from Stalinist Russia... especially Germany. They were really furious, they could not understand why being so rich, Germans came to Russia&quot;''.&quot; - while possibly adding to the motives for those Russian soldiers that did commit rape, the behavior of the Nazi's in the USSR was no doubt the primary reason, and since there are many Reliable Sources that point out this motive, they should also be cited in the article. [[Special:Contributions/98.67.183.143|98.67.183.143]] ([[User talk:98.67.183.143|talk]]) 22:39, 2 July 2016 (UTC)
:: I had the same reaction - the facts of German mass rape, and German and Finnish genocide in the USSR are well documented but always underplayed. Bergstrom's new book on Barbarossa is very good on these topics. We need to correct this without excusing war crimes of either side. [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 17:21, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
:::I disagree &quot;they are underplayed&quot; at this point in time and frankly all this was discussed and debated at length in the recent archive pages herein (including this page as shown above); what is there is by the consensus reached. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 20:01, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
:::: With respect, I cannot agree. The [[Operation Barbarossa]] article, for example, does not contain the term 'rape' nor is any reference made to sexual assault. Surely it should receive similar weight to the entry here and should perhaps be referenced here? [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 20:16, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::Well, that is an exception to what I have seen overall and if that one needs tweaked then discuss it on that talk page; I note, that article is GA rated and has a &quot;War crimes&quot; section but I don't work on that page and it is not on my watch list. Has it not been discussed therein what should be included? But as to this page, I still am not seeing a need at this point for an addition. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 21:25, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
:: I suggest a good approach could be first to address it on the Barbarossa page and then link to that from here. Otherwise we have an undue weight problem that plays into neo nazi historiography. [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 14:30, 13 September 2016 (UTC)
:::Well as I said, I don't edit that page as there is enough others who have and do edit/watch it (and my time is limited). I leave that up to you to discuss with them on that GA article talk page. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 15:03, 13 September 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Battle of Berlin]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=746614680 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110525014346/http://www.onwar.com/articles/9905.htm to http://www.onwar.com/articles/9905.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110514001340/http://www.onwar.com/faq.htm to http://www.onwar.com/faq.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070318230858/http://www.argo.net.au:80/andre/osmarwhiteENFIN.htm to http://www.argo.net.au/andre/osmarwhiteENFIN.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 13:36, 28 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>l3p4b9xjna5f4rck0a3t2mmicz5p9lu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
