<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Australian Army during World War II</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>22739600</id>
    <revision>
      <id>639097505</id>
      <parentid>637712075</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-12-21T22:22:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anotherclown</username>
        <id>8567476</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>talkheader to the top</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15027">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=12:58, 11 January 2013
|action1link=Talk:Australian Army in World War II/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=532515270

|action2=WAR
|action2date=19:30, 7 February 2013 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Australian Army during World War II 
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=537033449

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{MILHIST|class=A|A-Class=pass|ANZSP=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=A|importance=High|military=y|military-importance=High}}
}}

==A couple of minor observations==
G'day, as I've been going through the article looking for minor issues, I've noticed a couple of inconsistencies that I wanted to clarify before changing:
* the article uses terms like First World War and Second World War, but the article is titled in &quot;World War II&quot;;
* the presentation of infantry battalions/brigades is inconsistent: in some places it is &quot;xth Battalion&quot;, but in others &quot;xth Infantry Battalion&quot; and also &quot;xth Brigade&quot; v. &quot;xth Infantry Brigade&quot;;
* inconsistent presentation: &quot;X Campaign&quot; v. &quot;X campaign&quot; e.g. &quot;New Britain Campaign&quot; v &quot;Bougainville campaign&quot;. Which is correct?
* in the Refs, some of the official history works have &quot;Retrieved&quot; dates, but others don't. I think based on FAC advice, these courtesy links should be removed. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 23:52, 27 December 2012 (UTC)
: Cheers. Think I got these now. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 11:37, 28 December 2012 (UTC)

== Lead ==
Gday. I've added a draft lead and would welcome some feedback. I think it probably needs to summarise equipment, leadership and training/doctrine as well but can't think how to do this currently. Any suggestions? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 11:40, 28 December 2012 (UTC)
: Added a bit further now. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 11:04, 29 December 2012 (UTC)
::G'day, looks good but if possible try to reduce the number of times you mention the Army. I will try to go through the article and copy edit it a bit more, but my net connection is terrible at the moment. A couple more observations: do you wish to use a TOC and is the See also section necessary? [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 21:59, 29 December 2012 (UTC)
:::Hmm, I think that it might be a bit long (its text occupies most of my large-ish monitor). If it's OK, I'll have a go at reducing the size. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 22:54, 29 December 2012 (UTC)
:::: Gday Nick. Pls do - seems a standard problem of mine (long leads that is). AR - I think the TOC is helpful but you're right the &quot;See also&quot; section is probably redundant. Certainly happy with you doing another copy-edit. Thanks greatly for you help to this point. Cheers. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 23:11, 29 December 2012 (UTC)
:::::OK, done. Long leads seem to be increasingly popular though. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 23:49, 29 December 2012 (UTC)
:::::: Gday Nick. I've tweaked it a little again (added a sentence only on demobilisation) and merged two paras for balance (sorry this is my OCD/institutionalisation showing - if you don't think it works pls split again and I'll take my meds...). Cheers. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:35, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
::::::: Oh I also binned the formation of the ARA and CMF post war part - seemed a bit of a tangent and not required in the lead to me (I know I put it in there in the first place but again if you disagree pls revert). Cheers. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:37, 31 December 2012 (UTC)

==A couple more observations==
Ok, I've gone through the article top to bottom. Please check that you are happy with my changes and tweak/change as you see fit. From my last run through, I have the following observations:
*should legislation titles be presented in italics?
** Yes I think so. Done. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:32, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
*the Malaya and Singapore section starts a little abruptly...I wonder if there is a more smooth way of doing this. It almost seems like the first paragraph should be in a different section, but I'm not sure...
** Agree - I've cut the sentence in half and moved the later part to the end of the Defence of Australia section. Does this work better? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:32, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
*there appears to be some off arguably off-topic information in a few places. For instance, &quot;RAAF aircraft operating from bases in Java...&quot;
** Agree - there a product of stealling text from the parent article. Removed a couple, pls cull any others you see. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:32, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
*Some repetition: &quot;The Australian Army's 16th and 17th Brigades formed part of the island's garrison...&quot; and then in the next section &quot;As a compromise two brigades of the 6th Division...&quot;
** Yeah I can see the problem, well spotted. Unfortunately a solution is not readily apparent to me. Would welcome some suggestions if you have them. Otherwise I'll stew on it for a bit and see if a beer sharpens the mind... [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:32, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
***I've just moved this material up to the section on Singapore and Malaya which solves the problem of duplication (albeit at a slight loss of chronological sequence). [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 11:16, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
****Cheers Nick. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 11:33, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
*this sentence seems like it needs something else: &quot;These troops had seen action alongside Australian units throughout the New Guinea campaign&quot;
** Altered this a little. Does this work for you?
*the web link for the Lodge article doesn't appear to click through properly. It has something to do with the &quot;id=&quot; field, but I can't quite work it out. Compare the syntax used for the adb entry in [[Rupert Downes]];
** Fixed. Thanks for pointing that out. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:32, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
*I wonder if the paragraph on demobilisation that is currently in the Post war subsection of the Campaigns section should be split into its own section titled &quot;Demobilisation&quot;.
** Done. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 08:32, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
Anyway, please let me know what you think. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 11:05, 30 December 2012 (UTC)
* G'day, your changes look good. I will try to see what I can do about the point 16th and 17th Brigades tomorrow. Cheers, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 11:06, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
**Nick got it. Cheers. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 11:33, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
{{od}} The copyediting and major edits seem to be done for the moment at least. Do you guys think this is ready for nomination for a GA review? Cheers. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 22:24, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
:I think that it would benefit from a section on the POWs (which could be adapted from the Australian in World War II article), but other that that should be good to go. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 22:31, 31 December 2012 (UTC)
:: Thats right you said that before and it must have slipped my mind. I'm going for a run for a hour or so but I'll see what I can do after that unless someone beats me to it. Got to have a Berroca first though... Cheers Nick. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 01:42, 1 January 2013 (UTC)
::: Ok I've put something here now. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:21, 2 January 2013 (UTC)

; More comments
I have a few more comments, which I'll make here rather than in the GA review, because I think I wrote some chunks of the article myself.
* The background should contain some more material about the Singapore strategy (which is mentioned in the Far East section), and the Army's political resistance to it.
** Done something here last week. Is this adequate? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:33, 6 January 2013 (UTC)
* It should also make it clear that the Militia was a conscript force until 1929, when Labor abolished conscription.
** Done. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 07:38, 1 January 2013 (UTC)
* The bit about the  ''Defence (Citizen Military Forces) Act 1943''is confusing. How about a map showing SWPA and the SWPZ?
**There is a map on p. 341 of Hasluck, Paul. (1970). [http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/second_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67917 ''The Government and the People, 1942–1945'']. Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 4 – Civil Volume II –  (1st edition, 1970). I don't believe it to be PD, though, unfortunately given that it appears to have been published in 1970. Does anyone know any differently about that map? [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 02:31, 2 January 2013 (UTC)
* ''little had been done to prepare for the jungle warfare this would involve'' Sort of true, but possibly  misleading. The Army's concept of fighting Japan involved repelling a Japanese invasion of Australia, so jungle warfare was not required.
** I'm struggling to find a reference for this. Would you pls be able to suggest one? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:21, 2 January 2013 (UTC)
***I found something in Keogh (pp. 34-35) and have added a small sentence. Do you think this is sufficient? Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 10:17, 9 January 2013 (UTC) 
**** Thanks AR. Looks good to me. Does this meet you concerns Hawkeye7? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 10:30, 9 January 2013 (UTC)
**** Yesm that's fine. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 11:05, 9 January 2013 (UTC)
***** Thanks for having another look. Cheers. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:25, 9 January 2013 (UTC)
***Anyone have any luck here? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:33, 6 January 2013 (UTC)
* ''During this year the Army's strength peaked at eleven infantry divisions—the 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 6th, 7th, 9th, 10th, 11th and Northern Territory Force'' But NT Force was not a division until it became the 12th Division in late 1942. Can we get the numbers straight?
** Tweaked this now. Is that what you meant? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:21, 2 January 2013 (UTC)
*** Hmm... I note that Long 1963 p. 81 actually lists NT Force as one of those 14 divisions in August 1942 (not 12 Div) - I wonder if this should be changed back? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:33, 6 January 2013 (UTC) 
* The article mentions that fourteen divisions was too many, but should also mention that the Army was unbalanced, and that it required many more service troops to be functional.
** Good point - will see what I can find for this. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:21, 2 January 2013 (UTC)
*** Nick and I have added some stuff here now. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:33, 6 January 2013 (UTC)
* North Africa: it was more economical in terms of shipping to use Australian troops in the Middle East rather than British or Canadian
* Link [[Battle of Bardia]]
** Done. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 06:50, 1 January 2013 (UTC)
* There is some inconsistency about using the hyphen in &quot;Lieutenant-General&quot; I prefer not to myself, as no hyphen is now standard in Australian English.
** Done. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 06:50, 1 January 2013 (UTC)
* ''The South Seas Force was forced to withdraw back along the track on this day, however, as supply problems made any further advance impossible and an Allied counter-landing at Buna was feared.'' Should also mention that IGHQ decided to withdraw after according priority to the Battle of Guadalcanal.
** Done. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 07:38, 1 January 2013 (UTC)
* I'd mention that Merauke is on the south coast of (then Dutch) West Papua
** Done. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 06:50, 1 January 2013 (UTC)
* Consider moving &quot;Demobilisation&quot; down the bottom.
** Makes sense - I've moved it to just above the casualties section. Does this work? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 06:50, 1 January 2013 (UTC)
* How about a summary to conclude with?
Cheers [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 06:11, 1 January 2013 (UTC)

{{Talk:Australian Army during World War II/GA1}}

== Map &quot;The Mediterranean in 1942&quot; ==
The map showing the mediterranean theatre should be removed from the article as it is largely incorrect. Vichy France is shown as an axis nation, the italian influence in southern France is far too big and the Soviet Union was no longer present on Krim or in Ukraine. And at last: all the borders are pre-1938. How could such a map pass the Good Article review of the article? --[[User:Bomzibar|Bomzibar]] ([[User talk:Bomzibar|talk]]) 18:44, 25 March 2013 (UTC)
: Perhaps you might suggest a suitable replacement? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 09:48, 28 March 2013 (UTC)
::For the whole Mediterranean [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Africa1940.png this] Map showing borders before the start of the Africa Campaign could be taken. Other maps showing the whole of North Africa during the campaign are difficult to find on Commons. --[[User:Bomzibar|Bomzibar]] ([[User talk:Bomzibar|talk]]) 12:21, 28 March 2013 (UTC)
::: I notice that the accuracy of this map is also disputed so probably not really suitable either. Thanks anyway. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 12:49, 28 March 2013 (UTC)
::::Oh, I oversighted that, sorry. Well, I dont see that a map is really needed at that point. Otherwise there is maybe a Mapmaker who can draw an accurate map of the whole theatre. --[[User:Bomzibar|Bomzibar]] ([[User talk:Bomzibar|talk]]) 13:24, 28 March 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7ecbmqeos7o1jsip3ttexl3vse5az71</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
