<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Keith Miller</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5390027</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748982890</id>
      <parentid>748854833</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T16:12:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BlackJack</username>
        <id>359672</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>qa</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23222">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WAR
|action1date=17:43, 25 February 2009
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Keith Miller
|action1result=approved
|action1oldid=271464380

|action2=GAN
|action2date=08:10, 16 March 2009
|action2link=Talk:Keith Miller/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=277592317

|action3=FTC
|action3date=17:11, 6 January 2010
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Australian cricket team in England in 1948/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=335905659

|ftname=Australian cricket team in England in 1948
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=sports
}}
{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=GA|Biography=y}}
{{WPBiography|living=no|class=GA|listas=Miller, Keith|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Mid|sports-work-group=y|sports-priority=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Cricket|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=GA|importance=Mid|Melbourne=yes|Victoria-importance=mid|Melbourne-importance=High|sports=y|sports-importance=high|military=y|VIC=y|afl=yes|afl-importance=low|military-importance=Low}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=A|A-Class=pass|Biography=y|Aviation=y|ANZSP=y|WWII=y}}
}}

==Comments==
When asked about pressure leading up to a cricket test match he was known to have replied

&quot;Pressure is a Messerschmitt up your ass&quot;


I would add it in, but i do not have a source for it. Great Quotation none the less.

___________________________________

Peter Cox's book Sixty Summers, about English postwar cricket, has the Indian rioter saying to Compton, &quot;You very good man Mr Compton but you must go,&quot; in reference to the Indian desire for the British to leave. This would make better sense as the comment that Miller repeated to Compton. - AG, Stockport.

== WikiProject class rating ==
This article was automatically assessed because at least one WikiProject had rated the article as start, and the rating on other projects was brought up to start class. [[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 04:06, 9 November 2007 (UTC)

== FA Drive to-do list ==
# Tackle cn tags
# More free images
# Bowling chart to complement batting
# Flesh out sections to complete narrative
# MOS check
# Complete copyedit
# Peer Review
# FAC

C'est tout. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 12:33, 19 December 2007 (UTC)

:Given that Miller was larger than life, we might need a daughter article or two. Lindwall was just a normal classical player, but Miller had all the shenanigans and did lots of unusual things. '''[[User:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;Blnguyen&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  (''[[User talk:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;bananabucket&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 00:28, 20 December 2007 (UTC)

== Lord's pavillion portraits ==
How many Australians have portraits in the Lord's pavillion?  The article says 4; Trumper, Bradman, Miller and Warne.  This [http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2005/06/08/1386992.htm news article] says 3, leaving out Trumper.  Has anyone seen Trumper's portrait at Lord's? -- [[User:Mattinbgn|Mattinbgn]]\&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mattinbgn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 08:13, 22 December 2007 (UTC)
:I've dealt with this as best I can, leaving out my OR speculation that the Trumper portrait has been moved (presumably to the museum) I could email Lord's to ask, but I don't believe their response would fulfil RS even if they did reply. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 10:39, 15 January 2008 (UTC)

== Guardian obituary... ==
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/australia/story/0,,1325266,00.html is here]   Interesting piece including his falling out with Ian Johnson. -- [[User:Mattinbgn|Mattinbgn]]\&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mattinbgn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 09:01, 22 December 2007 (UTC)
*[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml;jsessionid=NFBADR24R3AQ5QFIQMFCFFOAVCBQYIV0?xml=/news/2004/10/12/db1202.xml ...and the Telegraph] -- [[User:Mattinbgn|Mattinbgn]]\&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mattinbgn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 12:07, 14 January 2008 (UTC)

==War service==
I added a little to the early years section. There is a small problem with Miller's war service as it is currently written. According to the national archive, he joined the army (as a private) on 20/8/1940, served with the AASC (Southern Command) and was discharged (pending transfer to the RAAF) on 8/11/1941.

[[User:Phanto282|Phanto282]] ([[User talk:Phanto282|talk]]) 19:35, 27 December 2007 (UTC)
:If I had to guess, I would say he joined the [[Australian Army Reserve|militia]] in 1940 rather than the [[Second Australian Imperial Force]]. As such, he certainly was not expected to fight overseas, at least until 1942; and his service would have consisted of drilling once or twice a week around his civillian employment. I am not sure how we check this. -- [[User:Mattinbgn|Mattinbgn]]\&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mattinbgn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:42, 27 December 2007 (UTC)
Probably. I tried researching the AASC but couldn't find its exact role, here are his enrolment papers [http://naa12.naa.gov.au/scripts/Imagine.asp?B=6244136&amp;I=1&amp;SE=1]. Fined ten bob for insubordinate language to a superior...lol. He played a few games for the Saints in 1942 before his RAAF posting. A couple of points to digest: I have seen reports that he held Pratt goalless, or to one goal, hence the description in the early life section. Regardless, this prompted his signing by St Kilda, which suggests the match against Pratt was early in the 1940 season, as Pratt played with South in '39 (Lionel Frost's history of Carlton FC suggests Pratt and [[Brighton Diggins]] were discriminated against because they were protestants in a Catholic club, so sectarian bias goes both ways, I guess). I came across  photos that suggest Miller represented NSW at the carnivals in 1947 and 1950 (but not usuable as refs), which means he continued playing footy for quite a while after his move to Sydney, but I have no idea which club he played for in the NSW league. Obviously, Main and Holmesby will be Victorian-centric refs on this and state that he stopped playing after 1946, which doesn't appear to be true. Coleman suggests he is the only player to represent both states at both sports. Totally useless trivia: Miller wore #27, same guernsey worn by [[Barry Breen]] when he kicked the winning point in the '66 Grand Final. Further into Miller's life, [[Gideon Haigh]] claims that he lost the captaincy to Ian Johnson as part of the fallout from the Sid Barnes 12th man incident (that old chestnut) as he was captain of NSW during the game and failed to discipline or censure Barnes. Interesting theory; my guess is Bradman liked Johnson (and was close to his father) and had various blues with Miller...will make an interesting para or two. Phew...it's hot in the kitchen
[[User:Phanto282|Phanto282]] ([[User talk:Phanto282|talk]]) 08:28, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

== Graphs ==
A pair of small graphs showing his rankings for batting and bowling would be nice. The ones at the LG ICC site are poor, as they show up as flatlines, because the y axes include far too many rankings. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 11:53, 2 January 2008 (UTC)

== Pre-war info ==
Coming soon. Hold on there. '''[[User:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;Blnguyen&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  (''[[User talk:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;bananabucket&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 06:37, 9 January 2008 (UTC)

== Opening sentence debate ==
There is a debate about the opening sentence at [[Wikipedia_talk:WikiProject_Cricket#Keith_Miller]]. Please do contribute. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 11:19, 10 January 2008 (UTC)

== Some online sources ==
*[http://content-www.cricinfo.com/allrounder/content/story/281593.html Cricinfo searches for the greatest all-rounder] --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 14:06, 10 January 2008 (UTC)

==Cites needed in lead==
Is it necessary to reference claims in the article lead that are cited in the article body? -- [[User:Mattinbgn|Mattinbgn]]\&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mattinbgn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:38, 11 January 2008 (UTC)
:It's debatable. I'd tend to agree with you that it's not, but The Rambling Man and I have faced opposes at FAC in the past until we cited stuff in the Lead too. On reflection, there's no harm in it and there's the ''possibility'' of good - if the material in the main section becomes damaged or removed at some point in the future. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 09:58, 11 January 2008 (UTC)

== References ==
Somewehre along the way, the actual reference text for the reference named &quot;testlist&quot; has been lost, I've commented out all instances as it was showing a nasty red error message in the footnotes.  I've gone some way back in the article history, but haven't managed to work out what the original ref was.  There were also a couple of refs named for page numbers which had the same issue, but in this case I've assumed that they were furhter references to the perry book, frequently cited.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 12:54, 30 January 2008 (UTC)

== Queries ==
Having just read through a few of the recent changes, I noticed a few problems I couldn't immediately resolve.  I've inserted html comments into the text at the relevant points, but they included:  reference to someone as a flight officer - there was no such rank in the RAAF, but it was impossible to tell if this should be pilot officer, flying officer, or flight lieutenant, which were all valid ranks; V1 rocket - the V1 was the flying bomb (which has already been mentioned in the article), the V2 was the rocket;the grammar around Miller's run in with his instructor is rather confused, it's not always absolutely clear who is meant by &quot;he&quot; at any given point); similar issues occur round some of Miller's laterrun-ins with authority too.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 14:48, 7 July 2008 (UTC)

== To-do list for FA drive ==
In order to get to FA:

* Initial copy-edit
** Reduce length, without losing vital content

** Spread out uneven batching of images

** Look at grouping some sections as subsections

** Check for first-instance wikilinking of all cricket jargon
** Address all citation needed tags
* Address outstanding issues on this page
* Address any hidden comments
* Third-party copy-edit
* Peer Review
* Thorough link check / MOS check / image check
* FAC

Anything I've missed? --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 10:34, 11 August 2008 (UTC)

== Height aged 12 ==
Can someone cleverer than me make this into one of those converty sort of things so people can understand what 150cm means in their own terms? --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 10:36, 11 August 2008 (UTC)
:Ditto for when he gets his growth spurt. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 16:03, 11 August 2008 (UTC)

== First class debut ==
&quot;Late in the summer, he made his [[First-class cricket|first-class]] debut for the Victorian Second XI and hit 181 against [[Tasmanian Tigers|Tasmania]] at the [[Melbourne Cricket Ground]].&quot;

The reference doesn't indicate it was the second XI, and second XI games aren't usually first class. Are you saying it was a reserve side that Tasmania fielded for a nominal first XI game? (presumably because Tasmania were so weak in those days) --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 14:18, 11 August 2008 (UTC)

== &quot;man the greatest forward of the era, [[Bob Pratt]]&quot; ==
I've amended this to &quot;man-mark&quot;, which I assume is the right terminology for Aussie rules. However, I'm concerned about POV over Pratt's description. Is that a quote from the ref? If so, it should be in quote marks. If not, it should be carefully edited. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 16:03, 11 August 2008 (UTC)
:I don't know how widely this view is held but whoever wrote the wikiarticle also thinks so. I'm pretty sure he was the most prolific goalkicker of his time but I thought it might be tough to stick in a few sentences to explain all of Pratt's stats as well. '''[[User:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;Blnguyen&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  (''[[User talk:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;bananabucket&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 08:19, 13 August 2008 (UTC)

== Cars, oil and Beames ==
V. confused.

Article says, &quot;taking a position as a clerk for a car business&quot;
Then it says, &quot;One of Miller's teammates was Percy Beames, who was also his manager at Vacuum Oil.&quot;
That's an odd name for a car business. But if it is the name, it should be mentioned the first time, too, to help sense.
Then, later, &quot;He again showed his disrespect for authority and reputation, striking his boss Beames with a raised elbow at the start of a match against Melbourne&quot;
I took that to mean his team manager, but I think it's the same Percy Beames and it means his work boss, but team mate.
Why did he hit a team mate?
Can all that lot be clarified? --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 10:34, 12 August 2008 (UTC)

== Images ==
Anyone know how to add a thingummyjig showing that there's media about Miller on Commons? Also, I think we have an image of his call-up papers... anyone think that'd be a nice, personal, unusual image to include? His war record is important to his persona. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 10:58, 12 August 2008 (UTC)
:It's not in the cat, who uploaded it? '''[[User:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;Blnguyen&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  (''[[User talk:Blnguyen|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;bananabucket&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 06:56, 14 August 2008 (UTC)
::No idea. Maybe I'm thinking of a different Invincible. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 12:31, 15 September 2008 (UTC)

== BIGgest problem of article ==
Is of course, its size. I'll be looking to hive off some material into the daughter articles. If I move anything that's really crucial, please let me know, discuss it here or revert me with pleasure. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 09:56, 13 August 2008 (UTC)
::Dweller, the tool I have on my computer says this about your page size &quot;Prose size (text only): 79 kB (13925 words) &quot;readable prose size&quot;. [[User:Ling.Nut]] helped me install something on my computer that gave it the ability to click on a page size in the toolbox section to the left of the article page. When I click on it, all text, minus references and images are counted as &quot;readable prose&quot;. Also, there is some guidance here at [[User:Giano/A fool's guide to writing a featured article|Fool's guide to writing a featured article]];  regarding page sizes for FA's. SandyGeorgia posted that to my talk page last June to help me. It specifically discusses appropriate FA article size and what to include or possibly move. I hope that helps. Nice article, good luck with its FA. [[User:NancyHeise|'''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#E75480&quot;&gt;Nancy&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#960018&quot;&gt;Heise&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;''']] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:NancyHeise#top|'''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#F6ADC6&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:40, 29 September 2008 (UTC)
:::I just took a look at the article for a little while and noticed that the lead does not summarize the contents of the article. It seems to discuss his prowess in cricket but says nothing about his actual life outside of the sport. It should really be a short summary of the article contents. If it is not discussed in the body of the article, it should not be in the lead and vice versa. Let me know when you submit it for a peer review and I'll come offer some comments if you like. No I am not a cricket fan, sorry, I do like football and my son forces me to watch boxing sometimes - hence I have a healthy knowledge of that sport, but only reluctantly. [[Image:Face-smile.svg|25px]] [[User:NancyHeise|'''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#E75480&quot;&gt;Nancy&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#960018&quot;&gt;Heise&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;''']] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:NancyHeise#top|'''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#F6ADC6&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:50, 29 September 2008 (UTC)
::About the lead, yes. That predates when the article was written and doesnt match up. '''[[User:YellowMonkey|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;YellowMonkey&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  (''[[User talk:YellowMonkey|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;bananabucket&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 01:28, 30 September 2008 (UTC)

== Change of Date ==
I changed a date from 1946 to 1944, as it related to his service in NW Europe and the date was clearly meant to be before early 1945. TheNeilster (18 Sep 08)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:TheNeilster|TheNeilster]] ([[User talk:TheNeilster|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/TheNeilster|contribs]]) 07:55, 18 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Military career==
I have made a copy of this section at [[User:Mattinbgn/Sandbox|my sandbox]]. Rather than try and trim the existing content, possibly leaving a cut-to-pieces mess that is a poor reflection of the valuable content in the daughter article, I will try and rewrite almost from scratch.  I will be away all weekend&amp;mdash;in Melbourne to watch the [[:AFL Grand Final]] (alas, not at the ground)&amp;mdash;but will start when I return. Feel free to add your two cents worth there should you wish. -- [[User:Mattinbgn|Mattinbgn]]\&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mattinbgn|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:23, 26 September 2008 (UTC)

== Orphaned references in [[:Keith Miller]] ==
I check pages listed in [[:Category:Pages with incorrect ref formatting]] to try to fix reference errors. One of the things I do is look for content for [[User:AnomieBOT/docs/OrphanReferenceFixer|orphaned references]] in wikilinked articles. I have found content for some of [[:Keith Miller]]'s orphans, the problem is that I found more than one version. I can't determine which (if any) is correct for ''this'' article, so I am asking for a sentient editor to look it over and copy the correct ref content into this article.

&lt;b&gt;Reference named &quot;sched&quot;:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Keith Miller with the Australian cricket team in England in 1956]]: {{Cite web|title=Australia in British Isles 1956 |url=http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Seasons/ENG/1956_ENG_Australia_in_British_Isles_1956.html |publisher=[[CricketArchive]] |accessdate=2008-12-10}}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Sam Loxton with the Australian cricket team in England in 1948]]: {{cite web|title=Matches, Australia tour of England, Apr-Sep 1948 |url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/invincibles/engine/series/61329.html |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |accessdate=2008-07-16}}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From [[Keith Miller with the Australian cricket team in England in 1953]]: {{Cite web|title=Australia in British Isles 1953 |url=http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Seasons/ENG/1953_ENG_Australia_in_British_Isles_1953.html |publisher=[[CricketArchive]] |accessdate=2008-12-10}}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

I apologize if any of the above are effectively identical; I am just a simple computer program, so I can't determine whether minor differences are significant or not. [[User:AnomieBOT|AnomieBOT]][[User talk:AnomieBOT|&lt;font color=&quot;#888800&quot;&gt;⚡&lt;/font&gt;]] 06:16, 3 February 2009 (UTC)

== messerschmitt quote ==
* got another book source for the quote if you need it:
* &quot;Pressure? I'll tell you what pressure is. Pressure is a [[Messerschmitt 109]] up your arse firing tracers. Playing cricket is not.&quot;&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Creswell, Toby &amp; Trenoweth 2006, p. 692.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* Creswell, Toby &amp; Trenoweth, Samantha. (2006). ''1001 Australians You Should Know''. Melbourne:Pluto Press Australia. ISBN 1864033614
:Thanks for that. '''[[User:YellowMonkey|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;YellowMonkey&lt;/font&gt;]]'''  (''[[User_talk:YellowMonkey#Straw_poll_for_selecting_photos_of_cyclists_at_the_2009_Tour_Down_Under|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;click here to vote for world cycling's #1 model!&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 23:50, 5 February 2009 (UTC)

== King hit/shoulder bump story ==
Adds a little colour, but I'm unconvinced the story is essential. It's only really relevant if linking the two events as retribution, but that's OR unless the RS specifies it. Does it? Somewhat arrogantly, I've currently hidden it, but do feel free to reinstate it or delete it. --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 12:02, 11 February 2009 (UTC)
:Yeah the book specifies it....quotes Miller talking about the king hit as a big lesson. '''[[User:YellowMonkey|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;YellowMonkey&lt;/font&gt;]]''' (''[[User_talk:YellowMonkey#Straw_poll_for_selecting_photos_of_cyclists_at_the_2009_Tour_Down_Under|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;click here to vote for world cycling's #1 model!&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 23:39, 11 February 2009 (UTC)
::As for the fullback thing, his job was to nullify/stifle the guy completely, no need to attack or anything, just to &quot;spoil&quot; by knocking the ball away. '''[[User:YellowMonkey|&lt;font color=&quot;GoldenRod&quot;&gt;YellowMonkey&lt;/font&gt;]]''' (''[[User_talk:YellowMonkey#Straw_poll_for_selecting_photos_of_cyclists_at_the_2009_Tour_Down_Under|&lt;font color=&quot;#FA8605&quot;&gt;click here to vote for world cycling's #1 model!&lt;/font&gt;]]'') 23:46, 11 February 2009 (UTC)

== Representing two states in cricket and football, Sidney Nolan &amp; subduing Ramadhin==
The lads at WikiProject AFL have put their heads together and state that Miller is one of only three people to represent two states in cricket and Australian rules football, the other two being Laurie Nash (Tas &amp; Vic) and [[Neil Hawke]] (SA &amp; WA). Unfortunately we currently don't have a ref for this but will continue searching. 

While I'm at it, can I mention that [[Sidney Nolan]]'s painting &quot;The Footballer&quot; (see [http://apps.ngv.vic.gov.au/shopimages/p_post_nolan1_t.jpg] is based on Miller? Check the following article [http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/09/05/1031115911903.html] for confirmation.

Finally, [[Everton Weekes]] writes that in this Test match [http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/20/20015.html] Miller and Hassett were the first batsmen to pick [[Sonny Ramadhin]]. &quot;Ram, for the first time, bowled his heart out without reward, and looked tired and broken.&quot; From Weekes ''Mastering the Craft: Ten Years of Weekes 1948-1958'',  p. 138, Universities of the Caribbean Press Inc., Barbados.

Any questions, fire away. --[[User:Roisterer|Roisterer]] ([[User talk:Roisterer|talk]]) 11:24, 24 February 2009 (UTC)

== Football career ==
Just wondering why Miller doesn't have a football player infobox with his stats? 50 games is relevant enough, and every player has one. It could go in the section about his time in the VFL. Any thoughts or objections before I whip one up. '''[[User:Gibbsyspin|Gibbsy]]'''''[[User talk:Gibbsyspin|spin]]'' 10:22, 13 July 2009 (UTC)

Well I've done it as no-one has piped up. I am troubled however as to get the text to wrap around the infobox and accompyaning image. Does anyone have any help? '''[[User:Gibbsyspin|Gibbsy]]'''''[[User talk:Gibbsyspin|spin]]'' 09:38, 17 July 2009 (UTC)

As an added piece of info, which I'll put here before adding to article later, Miller also played three matches for the combined West Adelaide-Glenelg side in the WWI SANFL comp while he was on R&amp;R leave in Victor Harbour. The ref doesn't say what year. Ref is Hornsey, A. &quot;Knock Outs&quot;, ''Football Times'', Messenger Publications: Adelaide. 17 April 1980, p. 2.</text>
      <sha1>77qlvj0tsglzs15yu21seb2jt6kuzpa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
