<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Napoleon</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>30101622</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744902013</id>
      <parentid>744901950</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-18T04:18:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.171.206.39</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Women's Rights Reversed Under Napoleon */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16942">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{British English|date=September 2011}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=12:01, 8 March 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Napoleon I of France/archive2
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=42782019

|action2=GAN
|action2date=17:42, 15 July 2006
|action2link=Talk:Napoleon I/Archive 2#GA nomination
|action2result=failed
|action2oldid=63946557

|action3=GAN
|action3date=14:55, 5 June 2008 (UTC)
|action3link=Talk:Napoleon I/GA1
|action3result=failed
|action3oldid=217376410

|action4=GAN
|action4date=16:27, 16 July 2008
|action4link=Talk:Napoleon I/GA2
|action4result=listed
|action4oldid=226002247

|action5=WAR
|action5date=16 August 2008
|action5link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Napoleon I of France
|action5result=approved
|action5oldid=232290487

|action6=PR
|action6date=23:56, 11 October 2008
|action6link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Napoleon I of France/archive1
|action6result=reviewed
|action6oldid=244672865

|action7=PR
|action7date=02:34, 1 March 2009
|action7link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Napoleon I of France/archive2
|action7result=reviewed
|action7oldid=273469498

|action8=GAR
|action8date=19:45, 16 April 2009 (UTC)
|action8link=Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Napoleon I of France/1
|action8result=kept
|action8oldid=284163525

|action9=GAR
|action9date=17:02, 18 June 2016 (UTC)
|action9link=Talk:Napoleon/GA3
|action9result=kept
|action9oldid=726495055

|topic=history
|currentstatus=GA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography |living=no |class=GA |military-work-group=yes |military-priority=Top |politician-work-group=yes |politician-priority=Top |royalty-work-group=yes |listas=Napoleon 01 Of France |core=yes}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=A|A-Class=pass|French=yes|Napoleonic=yes|Biography=yes}}
{{WikiProject European history |class=GA |importance=top }}
{{WikiProject France|class=GA|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Italy|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Africa|class=GA|importance=mid|Saint Helena=yes|Saint Helena-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WP1.0 |v0.5=pass |class=GA |category=History |VA=yes |WPCD=yes |importance=Top }}
}}
{{to do}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes
}}
{{Vital article|level=3|topic=People|class=A}}
{{OnThisDay |date1=2004-02-26|oldid1=6718489|date2=2004-07-17|oldid2=4760300|date3=2004-10-15|oldid3=6790900|date4=2004-12-02|oldid4=16335543|date5=2005-02-26|oldid5=16332575|date6=2005-07-17|oldid6=18998325|date7=2006-07-17|oldid7=64281053|date8=2007-07-17|oldid8=145212175|date9=2008-02-26|oldid9=194283804|date10=2009-02-26|oldid10=273411876|date11=2010-02-26|oldid11=346496338|date12=2013-02-26|oldid12=540210661|date13=2014-02-26|oldid13=597033200|date14=2015-02-26|oldid14=648818107}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 250K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Napoleon/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}

== Lead too long? ==

Per [[WP:LEAD]], the introduction should be no more than four paragraphs. Currently, it's five. --[[User:George Ho|George Ho]] ([[User talk:George Ho|talk]]) 03:59, 1 July 2015 (UTC)
::that is a general guideline for all 4 million articles.  Wikipedia has no firm rule on the matter, only suggestions that apply in most cases.  The opening of [[wp:lead]] says &quot; Use common sense in applying it; it will have occasional exceptions.  This is one of the obvious exceptions. Is this lead  too long for users? I think not. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 04:31, 1 July 2015 (UTC)
::: What about [[WP:LEADLENGTH]]? From what it says, a lead too short is unsatisfactory, and a lead too long is intimidating, hard to read, and less interesting. Five isn't that &quot;too long&quot; to general readers, is it? --[[User:George Ho|George Ho]] ([[User talk:George Ho|talk]]) 04:43, 1 July 2015 (UTC)
::::people can skip paragraphs easily if they don't want to read it. It just barely covers the main points as it is. Napoleon was a very busy man. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 08:17, 1 July 2015 (UTC)
::::: What if most readers skip some paragraphs, especially in intro? As a reader, I'll try not to doze off from it with five paragraphs. Hopefully, it is a summary of the article and not too much. --[[User:George Ho|George Ho]] ([[User talk:George Ho|talk]]) 09:08, 1 July 2015 (UTC)
::::::The lede is far too long. Napoleon was only a successful figure for less than twenty years and most of his achievements did not survive him. ([[User:CharltonChiltern|CharltonChiltern]] ([[User talk:CharltonChiltern|talk]]) 18:36, 1 July 2015 (UTC))
::Agree with Rjensen, and others here. I've removed the tag. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 18:27, 2 July 2015 (UTC)

The subject of the article is complicated. The size of the lead reflects those complications.&lt;font face=&quot;Century Gothic&quot;&gt;[[User:UberCryxic|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000080&quot;&gt;'''UBER'''&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:UberCryxic|'''&lt;sup&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color:#007BA7&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/sup&gt;''']]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 05:46, 3 July 2015 (UTC)
:I agree with most users above. Napoleon was a very busy man in a very complicated period and had a lasting impact on western culture. Nothing is superfluous in this article, although it could be tightened. [[User:Blaue Max|Blaue Max]] ([[User talk:Blaue Max|talk]]) 15:40, 18 July 2015 (UTC)
::I removed from the lead the sentence which stated that &quot;Napoleon dominated European affairs during the Revolutionary Wars&quot;. It is not true. During the Revolutionary Wars, he was a famous general, a close friend to many republican leaders, but he had no political power in France until Brumaire and certainly no power outside of France (except maybe in Egypt where he ruled as a [[pasha]], but that's not what the original sentence referred to).[[User:Blaue Max|Blaue Max]] ([[User talk:Blaue Max|talk]]) 07:36, 18 September 2015 (UTC)
:I also put a list of Ñapoleon's reforms in note. As noted by many users, the lead is already too long ! Adding a slightly POV list of some of his reforms is burdening unnecessarily the article. [[User:Blaue Max|Blaue Max]] ([[User talk:Blaue Max|talk]]) 07:44, 18 September 2015 (UTC)

For ledes in general, I started latest discussion at &quot;[[Wikipedia talk:Manual of Style/Lead section#Allow fifth paragraph of lede?]]&quot; --[[User:George Ho|George Ho]] ([[User talk:George Ho|talk]]) 06:40, 9 October 2015 (UTC)

Why is the summary of this article a detailed chronology of the man's lifetime? The opening summary is actually a virtual play-by-play of his life's events in 5 very large paragraphs. Shouldn't it be a summary or a synopsis? It is probably one of the largest, least necessary summaries in Wikipedia. In many instances of the opening, these are not contextual details meant to provide a proper understanding of the historical personage but a compendium of facts that ought to be distributed throughout the article where the details can be elaborated on. There is too much unnecessary information in this summary and it ought to be reduced... Regards... [[User:Stevenmitchell|Stevenmitchell]] ([[User talk:Stevenmitchell|talk]]) 07:06, 5 February 2016 (UTC)

== received by shock and grief ==

In the intro, shouldn't &quot;received by shock and grief&quot; be &quot;received with shock and grief&quot;?  [[Special:Contributions/174.47.29.50|174.47.29.50]] ([[User talk:174.47.29.50|talk]]) 14:42, 20 January 2016 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 8 February 2016 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Napoleon|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Be sure to state UNAMBIGUOUSLY your suggested changes; editors who can edit the protected page need to know what to add or remove. Blank edit requests WILL be declined. --&gt;
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;

Height in infobox should be 5'7&quot; rather than simply 5'7
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Andreimikheyev|Andreimikheyev]] ([[User talk:Andreimikheyev|talk]]) 19:46, 8 February 2016 (UTC)
:[[File:Red information icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:'''&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; [[Template:Infobox royalty]], which this article uses, actually doesn't have a &quot;height&quot; parameter. Although &lt;code&gt;|height=5'7&lt;/code&gt; existed in the page's source, it wasn't actually displayed in the infobox because the template doesn't support it. Thus, I have removed the parameter entirely. Thank you for your suggestion, however. Best, [[User:Mz7|Mz7]] ([[User talk:Mz7|talk]]) 20:01, 8 February 2016 (UTC)

== Spelling? ==

In the article of &quot;French Empire&quot; There seems to be a spelling error. It says Lauching, but I think it should stand Launching.

I'm new here so I may have screwed up with this talk thingy

[[User:Equinity|Equinity]] ([[User talk:Equinity|talk]]) 13:33, 18 March 2016 (UTC)

{{done}} [[User:R'n'B|R'n'B]] ([[User talk:R'n'B|call me]] Russ) 14:02, 18 March 2016 (UTC)

== Greatest controversially celebrated commander to ever be taught in military schools worldwide? ==

{{xtn|One of the greatest commanders in history,}} - ''greatest'' is an opinion. That shouldn't be on any article unless in quotations and cite a source that says so.

{{xtn|his wars and campaigns are studied at military schools worldwide.}} - I'm not sure if that can be verified or not, but some veterans will tell us they learn about Civil War and World Wars at military schools.

{{xtn|He also remains one of the most celebrated and controversial political figures in human history.}} - Celebrated? I've never heard of Napoleon Day. Controversial? According to whom?

Does anyone else agree with me / get the point? [[WP:NPOV|It's just that I don't think Wikipedia should praise or demean anything]] unless [[WP:CITE|it's in quotation and reliable sources saying that are cited.]]

Perhaps we can reach a consensus on this. --[[User:Turkeybutt JC|Turkeybutt]] ([[User talk:Turkeybutt JC|talk]]) 01:08, 3 September 2016 (UTC)
::It's unclear if Turkeybutt thinks historians believe there are greater military commanders, or whether he complains about the cites.  The statements are sourced at the end of the paragraph to two leading RS (Roberts &amp; Messenger) -- but Turkeybutt provides zero RS of his own -- instead he invents sources (eg ''some veterans will tell us they learn about Civil War and World Wars at military schools.'') ANyone in doubt should look at the [http://www.westpoint.edu/history/sitepages/napoleonic%20wars.aspx websites of places like West Point.] or that [http://www.da.mod.uk/Publications/category/103/the-military-maxims-of-napoleon-20562 of Sandhurst] instead of inventing mystery &quot;veterans&quot; [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 03:12, 3 September 2016 (UTC)
:::I agree. Also, this is a good article. One should open a discussion on the talkpage before they start tagging, especially if they intend to tag the lead. [[User:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue;font-size: 1em;&quot;&gt;Dr.&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue; font-size: 1em&quot;&gt;K.&lt;/span&gt;]] 03:40, 3 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Someone reverted one of my neutralizing revisions saying that dictionary.com (the first of the two sources cited in a row) is unreliable. 
::::So I revised it by doing the same neutralization thing again (and this time without the dictionary.com references) and it got reverted.

::::We need to verify that lots of military schools do indeed study Napoleon. Napoleon may be the greatest commander to someone and an imperialist tyrant to someone else. 
::::Hitler can be considered to be an evil dictator or a post-Depression war hero. But that doesn't mean that either statement should be mentioned in the articles as if they were facts. 

::::Wikipedia strives for [[WP:NPOV|neutral and fair perspectives]] on both sides with [[WP:UNDUE|undue weight]], and should not praise anything as terrific or demean anything as terrible. Opinions should be cited in quotation, and what may be truth may be nonsense to someone else, so whatever factoids are put on articles must be [[WP:TRUTH|verified.]] Wikipedia should not state that anything is true or wrong. --[[User:Turkeybutt JC|Turkeybutt]] ([[User talk:Turkeybutt JC|talk]]) 13:34, 3 September 2016 (UTC)

:::::Yes it should. When multiple reliable sources, establishing an academic consensus, assert a given fact about Napoleon, or about any other subject, then that fact can be stated in the article without qualifications. This article is also a [[WP:Good article]]. This means that editors here have checked it for NPOV and reliable sources. Tagging it at the lead without first coming to the talkpage to discuss the tags is not helpful. [[User:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue;font-size: 1em;&quot;&gt;Dr.&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue; font-size: 1em&quot;&gt;K.&lt;/span&gt;]] 15:20, 3 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::I agreed with Dr K.  the NPOV rule is a rule for Wiki editors not to take sides between competing reliable sources. When the RS are in agreement, then Wiki reports the consensus --which means we have RS to verify it.  Yes a person can be a great military genius and a controversial political tyrant at the same time.  All the RS I have looked at agree that 1) Napoleon was one of the world'd greatest military commanders and 2) he was politically controversial.  History has lots of examples of military success making political tyranny possible. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 15:38, 3 September 2016 (UTC)

The general consensus from reliable sources is that Napoleon was one of the world's greatest military commanders. I think it's ''especially'' noteworthy that this consensus also existed among his enemies, including the British and the Prussians. But even recent historical opinion hasn't changed; the great British historian David Chandler thinks Napoleon was the greatest commander of all time. If you don't care about reliable sources and are more inclined towards popular opinion, then look at pretty much any online list ever made on the greatest commanders in history. The only two that are included in almost every single list are Alexander and Napoleon. The rest usually vary by national taste.  

The OP seems to be American, yet still not aware that West Point [http://www.westpoint.edu/history/sitepages/napoleonic%20wars.aspx covers Napoleon] extensively in its curriculum. It is difficult to imagine a military school which does not teach his campaigns, as the man is mostly responsible for the organization of modern armies and the strategies of modern warfare. Teaching the history of warfare without Napoleon is like teaching Christianity without Jesus. Does. Not. Compute.

As for the celebrated/controversial sentence, that too is thoroughly cited later throughout the article, from all kinds of different authors. But I wasn't aware that someone had to have a specific day in order to count as being celebrated. I guess Americans don't really celebrate the likes of FDR that much since there is no 'FDR Day.' There are other measures to highlight his fame and popularity, like the fact that more biographies have been written about Napoleon than anyone in the last thousand years. Or the millions who visit his mausoleum at Les Invalides. Or the regular reenactments of his battles across Europe. You get the point.&lt;font face=&quot;Century Gothic&quot;&gt;[[User:UberCryxic|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000080&quot;&gt;'''UBER'''&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:UberCryxic|'''&lt;sup&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color:#007BA7&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/sup&gt;''']]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:44, 11 October 2016 (UTC)

== Women's Rights Reversed Under Napoleon ==

The lead paragraph should include that:

&quot;Napoleon reversed ideas of gender equality articulated by some, such as the [[Girondins]] and [[Olympe de Gouges]], in the French Revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Teaching Women's Rights From Past To Present|url=http://www.womeninworldhistory.com/TWR-07.html|website=Women In World History Curriculum|accessdate=18 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Through the Napoleonic Code, the legal right of men to control women and the basis of the French Constitution in [[Declaration of Rights of Man and Citizen]] was affirmed.  This contrasted significantly with the [[1689 Bill of Rights|1689 English Bill of Rights]], which did/does not use the word &quot;man&quot; at all and was based in &quot;rights and responsibilities of person&quot;.  In the United States, a &quot;head and master&quot; marriage law (a.k.a. a &quot;master and servant&quot; marriage law) deriving from the Napoleonic Code was still in place in Louisiana in the 1970s until it was repealed by Supreme Court ruling in [[Kirchberg v. Feenstra]], interpreting the &quot;rights and responsibilities of person&quot; of the U.S. Constitution and Bill of Rights as prohibiting it.</text>
      <sha1>hrvd1f1et2l8kn324zah9tdfgs6015v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
