<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Ismailia</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>31188159</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746645361</id>
      <parentid>640485560</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T17:19:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6295">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history |A-Class=pass |class=A |Middle-Eastern=yes}}
{{WikiProject Egypt |class=GA |importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Israel |class=GA |importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Arab world |class=GA |importance=Low}}
}}{{oldpeerreview|archive=1}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=19:56, 16 April 2011
|action1link=Talk:Battle of Ismailia/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=424404811
| action2       =  WAR
| action2date   = 12:21, 12 June 2011 (UTC)
| action2link   = Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Battle of Ismailia
| action2result = approved
| action2oldid  = 433815868
|dykdate=23 March 2011
|dykentry=... that when [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 338|the ceasefire]] was issued to end the '''[[Battle of Ismailia]]''', some [[Israel Defense Forces|Israeli paratroopers]] and [[Egyptian Armed Forces|Egyptian Sa'iqa]] found that they were no more than 20 meters apart?
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war
}}

{{Talk:Battle of Ismailia/GA1}}

== Egyptian strategic victory ? ==

While the article covers the combat from 18/10 to 22/10, the described result of this battle, “Egyptian tactical and strategic victory”, ignores the Israeli advancements prior to 22/10. On 22/10 the Israelis were halted south to the Cairo - Ismailia road, but they made advancements before 22/10 and succeeded to capture Serapeum. Eventually, the Israeli positions of 22/10 were norther than those of 18/10. I am not sure the the Egyptian victory on 22/10 had such high value. On the article, it is already mentioned that Israeli bombardments have made the Cairo - Ismailia road unusable for wheeled vehicles, so capturing the road area was not so necessary. For the total isolation of the 2nd field army, and its cutting from all supply measures via land, like tracked vehicle, the Israeli had to push north and reach the Mediterranean, so capturing the Cairo - Ismailia road was not enough. However, it is not mentioned whether there were large stocks of supplies in Ismailia like those that were in Suez. If there were such stocks on Ismailia, and Ismailia would being captured by the Israelis, the 2nd field army would lose a lot of supplies. In that case, an Egyptian victory would be significant. [[User:Megaidler|Megaidler]] ([[User talk:Megaidler|talk]]) 16:15, 27 April 2011 (UTC)

:As far as I understand, Ismailia was Second Army's main supply base, and major supply routes on the way to Second Army from Cairo passed through Ismailia. Its capture basically meant Second Army would be faced with a similar encirclement to Third Army or would be forced to retreat across the canal. To that end, the Israelis wanted to capture Ismailia, and the Egyptians wanted to defend it at all costs. According to the sources used, the end result of the battle is that the Israelis failed to capture Ismailia; a tactical and strategic victory for the Egyptians. Dupuy mentions that the road was made unusable by artillery, but that doesn't mean the significance of the Egyptian victory was lesser, unless a source explicitly says otherwise. --[[User:Sherif9282|Sherif9282]] ([[User talk:Sherif9282|talk]]) 17:23, 27 April 2011 (UTC)

::In 67 the Israelis planned to capture the entire Sinai peninsula but failed to capture Port Fouad, and no one questions their victory back than. During the battles described on the article the Israelis made advancements in comparison to their initial position on 18/10. All sources claims that the Israelis tried and failed to capture Ismailia, no doubt. There is no doubt that Ismailia was a place of much more significance than Serapeum, or Port Fouad. However, the whole supply transportation for the 2nd army was not dependent on the identity of the army that holds that road according to 2 sourced brought by Sherif9282. Even Ismailia was a main of supply base, receiving supplies from the Nile area, and sending supplies to all divisions of the 2nd army, Dupuy and O'ballanceclaims claimed that the Cairo – Ismailia road was unusable due to Israeli artillery. Wheeled vehicles couldn't reach Ismailia through that road because the Israelis did block it - by heavy bombardments. It seems that Dupuy and O'ballanceclaims gave less significance to the Israeli encirclement of the 3rd Army as well as to Egyptian maintaining of the Cairo - Ismailia road. Only one source used the term “strategic” for describing the Egyptian success on 22/10 and it is Gawrych:&lt;br/&gt;
::''A combined Egyptian commando and paratrooper force, for example, registered a tactical victory of strategic import by stopping Sharon's repeated attempts to capture Ismailia, whose loss would have seriously imperiled the logistical lifeblood to the Second Army.''&lt;br/&gt;
::He even didn't use the term “strategic victory”. The use of this term was Sherif's decision only and it is [[Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style_(words_to_watch)#Puffery|WP:Puffery]]. I am expecting Sherif to qoute the exact words of Dupuy and O'ballanceclaims regarding the situation of the Cairo – Ismailia main road. [[User:Megaidler|Megaidler]] ([[User talk:Megaidler|talk]]) 20:31, 27 April 2011 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Battle of Ismailia]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=746645355 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110507130100/http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/gawrych/gawrych_pt1.pdf to http://cgsc.leavenworth.army.mil/carl/download/csipubs/gawrych/gawrych_pt1.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:19, 28 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dzl1j930zqk4g2qgge1sgk70xzee6bk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
