<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Jon Burge</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>13544246</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724957226</id>
      <parentid>711248412</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-12T17:30:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>97.123.115.87</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Small correction needed */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47206">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=16:37, 15 November 2007
|action1result=not listed
|action1link=Talk:Jon Burge#Stubbed
|action1oldid=171390796

|action2=GAN
|action2date=18:58, 15 November 2007
|action2result=not listed
|action2link=Talk:Jon Burge#Stubbed
|action2oldid=171712470

|action3=GAN
|action3date=16:21, 5 January 2008
|action3result=not listed
|action3link=Talk:Jon Burge#GA Review
|action3oldid=181216085

|action4=GAN
|action4date=14:50, 7 August 2008
|action4result=listed
|action4link=Talk:Jon Burge/GA1
|action4oldid=230278308

|action5=PR
|action5date=10:09, 21 January 2009
|action5link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Jon Burge/archive1
|action5result=reviewed
|action5oldid=264000348

|action6=WAR
|action6date=17:49, 4 March 2009
|action6link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Jon Burge
|action6result=approved
|action6oldid=273604222

| action7       = GAR
| action7date   = 12:44, 18 October 2009 (UTC)
| action7link   = Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Jon Burge/1
| action7result = kept
| action7oldid  =318421093


|topic=socsci
|currentstatus=GA
|dykdate=August 07, 2008
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|blp=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=yes|class=GA|listas=Burge, Jon}}
{{WikiProject Criminal Biography |class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Illinois|class=GA|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Chicago|class=GA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Law Enforcement|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Law|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=A|Southeast-Asian=yes|US=yes|old-peer-review=yes|A-Class=pass}}
{{WikiProject Human rights|class=GA |importance=mid}}
}}
{{FOR-CHICOTW}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2013-01-11|oldid1=532322286}}

==Quick note==
Don't get caught up in [[WP:BLP]] concerns with this one, it's already looking like a [[WP:COATRACK]]. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 00:29, 3 October 2007 (UTC)
:I've used only .gov sources. Am I screwing up somehow? [[User:Speciate|Speciate]] 00:32, 3 October 2007 (UTC)
::You're not screwing it up. My concern is that without much detail on Jon Burge the man, this article is inappropriately titled, as it appears to discuss the torture incidents (which are surely notable) more than Jon Burge. By having the article under this title, (unless expansion is planned, which I see its the COTW so I assume it will be worked out) it appears to be heavily biased against Burge (who I can see from the article was not the only officer involved with the incidents.) [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 00:35, 3 October 2007 (UTC)
:::Oh, well I was going to say he is an Irish-American and give his b-day. He was the Commander of an Area (contains many precincts), which is above Watch Commander, which means he was in charge. I'm having trouble with my internet connection right now. [[User:Speciate|Speciate]] 00:53, 3 October 2007 (UTC)
::::The whole reason to have a {{tl|CUR-CHICOTW}} tag is to tell people the article is under construction.  That means both that you should reserve judgement on its quality/notability and you should note that it will likely be a completely different resource in the very near future.  Read the header and take head.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[ User:TonyTheTiger/WPChiDirector |tcfkaWCDbwincowtchatlotpsoplrttaDCLaM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 14:06, 3 October 2007 (UTC)
::::::I hear ya, no probs, just making sure was all. :) [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 22:34, 8 October 2007 (UTC)
:::::::The article is looking real nice too. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 22:39, 8 October 2007 (UTC)

==Areas==
Deleted &quot;Burge and his fellow detective’s conduct were so outrageous that Mayor Richard M. Daley dissolved Burge’s police district, Area 3 in 1991.[citation needed]&quot;, because it's untrue.  
-CPD is broken down by police 25 districts.  Leading multiple districts are &quot;Areas&quot;, numbered 1-5.  Area 3 (where Burge did work for a time roundabouts 1988, after running violent crimes out of Area 2) was never 'dissolved'.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.79.212.130|68.79.212.130]] ([[User talk:68.79.212.130|talk]]) 16:06, 5 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I think you're correct. [[User:Speciate|Speciate]] 20:55, 5 October 2007 (UTC)

==Image==
Would this image be useful?  
[[Image:http://www.moveonandshutup.org/files/images/button_0.jpg]]
It's a button from a fund raiser held in 1993 after Burge was fired.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.175.163.119|67.175.163.119]] ([[User talk:67.175.163.119|talk]]) 12:33, 6 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Criticism==
&quot;....but has been delayed by attempts to protect Mayor Daley from criticism.&quot;

Should be deleted -  it's opinion.  There were a lot of factors into the delay of the settlement.  Perhaps most notably one of the alleged victims being under federal investigation for the same murder/arson he was allegedly tortured to confess too.  Additionally:  saying that the Mayor has been protected from criticism is about as non-factual as saying that Bush hasn't been criticized for the Iraq war.  Quoting John Conroy in the Chicago reader is hardly NPOV.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.175.163.119|67.175.163.119]] ([[User talk:67.175.163.119|talk]]) 18:36, 6 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==More work==
The Jon Burge article needs a bit of rearranging, section-wise. I'm not wedded to my original section titles like &quot;Fallout&quot;, go ahead and change things. The article could use a bit more about the discovery of the torture, it could name a few of the guys that got tortured (some of them already have a Wikipedia article), and the Chicago Reader reporter John Conway needs to be mentioned as the main guy behind breaking and pounding away at the story. [[User:Speciate|Speciate]] 20:55, 5 October 2007 (UTC)
:Also, the connection the death sentence revocations and commutations needs to be better clarified, not sure of its relevance, especially the bit about Ryan's 2003 commutation of all death sentences in Illinois. It all appears to be somewhat of a non sequitur, I was gonna fix it myself but am not familiar enough with the topic to do so. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 12:40, 6 October 2007 (UTC)
::Can someone enlighten me here? Nothing there has changed, the sentence about Ryan commuting death sentence apparently has nothing to do with this, I will remove it unless someone can present a good reason not to, it is still a non sequitur. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 16:21, 8 October 2007 (UTC)
:::What do you mean it has nothing to do with this?--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[ User:TonyTheTiger/WPChiDirector |tcfkaWCDbwincowtchatlotpsoplrttaDCLaM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 19:37, 8 October 2007 (UTC)
::::I can only go off what is in the article, there is no apparent connection between the two, make it clearer if there is one. What did you think I meant? [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:44, 8 October 2007 (UTC)
:::::The connection seems tenuous at best and there is certainly no evidence presented in the article to support the connection. I am guessing you were tying &quot;He then pardoned 4 inmates of the &quot;Death Row 10&quot; inmates&quot; in 2000, to the commutation in 2003, if there isn't a source connecting the two then it would be OR, as you know. This has to be made clearer of removed, as I said, I am not familiar enough with the topic to make any alterations myself, but you must keep in mind that this will be the same case for any reader, it must be clear. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:47, 8 October 2007 (UTC)
::::::I'm afraid I don't know either, perhaps the most that can be said is that there was the climate at the time. [[User:Speciate|Speciate]] 23:06, 8 October 2007 (UTC)

==Ambiguous statement==

I was confused by &quot;A Northwestern University journalism professor and his students uncovered exonerating evidence.&quot; Exonerating evidence of what? Who was exonerated? [[User:Jeff Dahl|Jeff Dahl]] 16:19, 9 October 2007 (UTC)

==Discovery==
Does Discovery here refer to the events being uncovered or legal discovery. If the former, the first instance of the abuse being uncovered was not by the CPD, bu by an independent newspaper, the Chicago Reader. Here is a link to the first article, &quot;House of Screams.&quot; http://www.chicagoreader.com/torture/900126_1.html  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/65.173.199.254|65.173.199.254]] ([[User talk:65.173.199.254|talk]]) 20:14, 9 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Torture Methods==
A sentence in this section is misleading. &quot;The turning point . . . &quot; makes it seem that Burge and his secondaries began torturing over the cop slaying, when allegations of abuse went back to 1973, nine years earlier.

==Auto Peer Review==

The following suggestions were generated by a semi-automatic [[User:AndyZ/peerreviewer|javascript program]], and might not be applicable for the article in question.
*Please expand the lead to conform with guidelines at [[Wikipedia:Lead]]. The article should have an appropriate number of paragraphs as is shown on [[WP:LEAD]], and should adequately summarize the article.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#lead|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*This article has no or few [[WP:IMAGE|images]]. Please see if there are any [[WP:IT|free use]] images that fall under the [[Wikipedia:Image use policy]] and fit under one of the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags]] that can be uploaded. To upload images on Wikipedia, go to [[Special:Upload]]; to upload non-[[WP:FU|fair use]] images on the [[Wikimedia Commons]], go to [[commons:special:upload]].&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#noimg|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*If there is not a [[WP:IT|free use]] image in the top right corner of the article, please try to find and include one.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#leadimg|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*If this article is about a person, please add &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{persondata|PLEASE SEE [[WP:PDATA]]!}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; along with the required parameters to the article - see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] for more information.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#persondata|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*Per [[Wikipedia:Only make links that are relevant to the context|Wikipedia:Context]] and [[Wikipedia:Build the web]], years with full dates should be linked; for example, link [[January 15]], [[2006]].&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#linkdate|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;{{done}}--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 21:04, 13 November 2007 (UTC)
*There are a few occurrences of [[weasel word]]s in this article- please observe [[WP:AWT]]. Certain phrases should specify exactly who supports, considers, believes, etc., such a view.
**''allege''
**might be weasel words, and should be provided with proper [[WP:FOOTNOTE|citations]] (if they already do, or are not weasel terms, please &lt;strike&gt;strike&lt;/strike&gt; this comment).&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#awt|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;!--This javascript cannot determine if a citation is provided; if all weasel terms are covered by citations, please strike this--&gt;
*The script has spotted the following contractions: ''doesn't'', if these are outside of quotations, they should be expanded. {{resolved|This is part of a reference title.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 21:05, 13 November 2007 (UTC)}}
*Please ensure that the article has gone through a thorough copyediting so that it exemplifies some of [[WP:WIAFA|Wikipedia's best work]]. See also [[User:Tony1/How to satisfy Criterion 1a]].&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#copyedit|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
You may wish to browse through [[User:AndyZ/Suggestions]] for further ideas. Thanks, [[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 21:00, 13 November 2007 (UTC)

==Stubbed==
Sorry, but this article really seems to push the limits of BLP. It should be rewritten and carefully sourced, preferrably using ''Unspeakable Acts, Ordinary People''. [[User:Danny|Danny]] 16:37, 15 November 2007 (UTC)

:I second this - it's a well-regarded academic press book that would give a very nicely sourced overview. [[User:Phil Sandifer|Phil Sandifer]] 17:05, 15 November 2007 (UTC)

:Let me note, the BLP issues in this article really were egregious - the price of the man's house? Ironically, the main sources here - the Conroy articles - exist in better forms in the academic book ''Unspeakable Acts, Ordinary People''. But it is important to remember, in any case, that Burge was never convicted of any of this, and that we have to be conservative and careful in our phrasings here. But this is clearly not a GA - no way. [[User:Phil Sandifer|Phil Sandifer]] 19:00, 15 November 2007 (UTC)

:Another note, as apparently the issue is being discussed everywhere but here. In any case, I have no personal doubt that Burge tortured people. But he's a living person, and we need to be careful to report such a huge accusation in as bulletproof a fashion as possible. And a Chicago alternative weekly, while a great paper that I would use without blinking for some claims, just isn't bulletproof enough when there are better, academically vetted sources. to be clear, I would like to see this article re-expanded. But I want the sourcing to be more meticulous, and I want every claim to be bulletproof in its reliability and its significance to why Jon Burge is a notable figure. This is not something we can afford to do any way other than perfectly. [[User:Phil Sandifer|Phil Sandifer]] 04:31, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

::I do understand your concern about [[WP:RS]] as it pertains to this controversial [[WP:BLP]].  However, I think a more appropriate approach might be to leave the text and tag the appropriate sections.  It seems pretty clear you agree the story as written may be fairly accurate and pass [[WP:V]] and [[WP:ATT]], but oddly fail [[WP:RS]].  I am not looking to get into a pissing contest with a pair of admins over this, but I do think the blanking to be excessive.  I think the first thing we should do is expand the article to its previous state and then discuss sentences, facts, and sections that you fell are not properly cited.  I would guess that over half of what you blanked should remain unchanged.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 16:58, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

:::And on that you'd have to talk to Danny - my position is mostly that I agree there were BLP concerns, and I support caution - better to serve a stub for a few days than to serve BLP violations for a few days. I looked, I saw some definite BLP violations, and I was surprised to see the academic source getting passed over for inferior sources, so I shared his concerns. But I'd go talk to him and get him to come to the talk page. :) -- [[User:Phil Sandifer|Phil Sandifer]] ([[User talk:Phil Sandifer|talk]]) 17:06, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

::::As I read the relevant policies (BLP, ATT, RS, V, NPOV), I see nothing where it says you must use the best source available.  I.E., if I can find it in the ''[[USA Today]]'', I don't need to wait until I can get access to the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]''.  Blanking due to ATT preference is not an acceptable argument.  If you look at my user page, you will see I write a ton of fairly well respected content for the project.  I am not a good writer and only a passable photographer with a point and shoot camera.  Where I have found success is in citing my work (usually with linkable sources).  I claim to be one of the most productive [[WP:GA]] authors on the entire project and [[User:Speciate]] has been right by my side on several of them.  I always ask that we find [[WP:RS]] for all our claims and always err on the side of overciting.  In this case we have an article that is highly sourced from the Chicago Reader and ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]''.  I think on a scale of [[WP:RS]] there are better and worse, but these probably achieve the current thresholds of adequacy even for a current [[WP:GA]]. [[User:SandyGeorgia]] would probably contest their adequacy for [[WP:FA]], but they are not unknown bloggers.  What Sandy would say is a good source really boils down to whether the fact are checked or the writer is unfettered.  I do not know the standards at the reader, but know that the Sun-Times would pass.  I suspect the reader passes by this standard, but am not sure.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 17:19, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

:::::If you don't want to discuss the direction of the article after the direct invitations to meet here for discussion, I will revert the article.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 22:05, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

No, frankly there is a lot to say. You just haven't said anything worth answering. You are about to revert to serious allegations about someone, without clarifying notability, without using impeccable evidence, and without considering the impact this may have on a person's life, or the implications for the WMF for that matter--after all, he does live within half an hour's drive of the office. And the justification for this is because you write GAs? Yes, sourcing something adequately is hard, or else we would be inundated with crap like this. Oh, and thank you for establishing that gossip-mongering, not encyclopedia-building, is the true objective of Wikipedia. [[User:Danny|Danny]] ([[User talk:Danny|talk]]) 22:58, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

:I think you missed the point about the meaning of [[WP:ATT]] above.  I was hoping you would clarify your opinion on my statement of its meaning and use.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 23:01, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

TonytheTiger asked me to weigh in here because of my experience reviewing featured article candidates.  Tony, [[WP:BLP]] makes an emphatic distinction about using the highest quality references available when including negative facts on BLPs:
*We must get the article ''right''. Be very firm about the use of high quality [[Wikipedia:Verifiability#Sources|references]]. 
*Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a tabloid; it is not our job to be sensationalist, or to be the primary vehicle for the spread of titillating claims about people's lives. '''Biographies of living persons''' ('''BLP''') must be written conservatively, with regard for the subject's privacy.
*Biographies of living people should be written responsibly, conservatively, and in a neutral, encyclopedic tone.
*[[WP:BLP#Reliable sources]]
To answer your specific queries:  whatever GA accepts is entirely irrelevant here (and usually at FAC as well).  GA is not a community process; its standards depend on what any one editor passes, and for that reason, it has limited credibility.  With respect to whether the Chicago media constitutes a reliable source, reliable sources are not set in stone and vary depending on article type and subject matter.  For example, the popular press is almost never an acceptable source for the kinds of medical articles I usually edit, where the highest quality sources demand peer-reviewed journal articles and the popular press usually gets it wrong or sensationalizes medical reporting.  What the Chicago papers report about Chicago politics may be our best reliable source; what they report about [[autism]] may not.  BLPs require the highest quality reliable sources available, and if there are scholarly or academic publications which are superior to even a well-respected newspaper, we would not pass along newspaper gossip in a BLP.  Just because a major Chicago paper (whose fact checking and reporting might be entirely reliable for reporting on another topic) publishes something, that does not automatically render that content acceptable for our higher BLP standards.  I hope this helps, [[User:SandyGeorgia|Sandy&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Georgia&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User talk:SandyGeorgia|Talk]]) 23:31, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

: I'd question calling the ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', a major and reputable Chicago newspaper, any less than reliable for a major Chicago news item; but fortunately, we don't have to make an either-or choice, as many pages from the book in question are available [http://books.google.com/books?id=NM_y3jOKzx8C&amp;dq=%22unspeakable+acts+ordinary+people%22&amp;pg=PP1&amp;ots=1LV8v39O6X&amp;sig=8NZ6hRT04NxMnbzYVQyxLQ3kplU&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3D%2522unspeakable%2Bacts%2Bordinary%2Bpeople%2522%26btnG%3DGoogle%2BSearch&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=print&amp;ct=title&amp;cad=one-book-with-thumbnail on-line at Google Books]. If Tony is willing to source as much as possible from that book, will the others in the debate agree to let him do it? In other words, if Tony agrees to use the book as much as possible, do the others of you agree to allow me to unprotect? --[[User:AnonEMouse|AnonEMouse]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:AnonEMouse|(squeak)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:02, 17 November 2007 (UTC)

::I am not likely to buy any books to contribute to WP.  I am willing to find more reputable online sources.  If things are online, I will use them and supplement them with  stuff from [http://query.nytimes.com/search/query?query=Jon+Burge&amp;srchst=nyt The New York Times] or [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/results.html?st=basic&amp;uid=&amp;MAC=50a23aa1f3f5c6104e90e36051420d61&amp;QryTxt=Jon+Burge&amp;x=9&amp;y=9&amp;sortby=REVERSE_CHRON Washington Post].--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 04:14, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
::: I don't buy many books to contribute to WP either, but libraries with inter-library loan are free, and darn useful! :-) Don't &quot;swap out&quot; the Chicago Sun-Times refs either, just add additional references from the book, with page number. Anyway, I remember you from even before your RFA way back when, so trust you are well meaning, but Doc Glasgow is afraid that you are a loose cannon, and I am a reckless mouse, so just to make sure we have everything clear, please copy and paste and &quot;sign&quot; the following statement:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I, &lt;nowiki&gt;~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;, will not add any controversial BLP material to the article that is not sourced per the book Danny and Phil suggests, without getting [[wikipedia:consensus|consensus]], hopefully involving at least one of them, on this here talk page. If anyone removes any material I add, I will consider it controversial, and get consensus for it, and will not edit war about adding it back. The medical profession is the queen of professions, and Glasgow is the best city in Scotland.&lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:::The last sentence is optional, but can't hurt. :-)--[[User:AnonEMouse|AnonEMouse]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:AnonEMouse|(squeak)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:35, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
::::Formal statement: I Antonio Vernon, known throughout the Martial Arts world and on WP as TonyTheTiger, have never been involved in an edit war and consider this debate to be fairly inane with arguments that fail to discuss the issue at hand, which is the editorial caliber of the Chicago Reader and Chicago Sun-Times and specific claims that fail [[WP:BLP].  I.E., it does not sound like anyone has made a cogent statement on whether on issues of local news these  sources count as [[WP:RS]] and whether individual claims are meritorious of inclusion in the article.  I have agreed to, as I always have in the past, add sourced facts to the article.  Many of these will be from the book mentioned above.  Others will be from the New York Times and Washington Post.  The article will have a {{tl|underconstruction}} tag on it while it is under construction.  I agree to participate in talk page discussion of controversial material, but given the way this debate has gone with people blanking over 90% of an article without propounding any specific BLP material, it really seems like people are picking fights and demanding to be bowed to.  I am also curious why an argument would be put forth that the article is a cornucopia of junk and then an instruction be given not to remove anything, but just add to it.  I think at this point, people with mops are partaking in gangland wikiviolence that has caused undue destruction of a decent article that would in all likelihood pass [[WP:GA]] otherwise.  I don't weild a mop, but look out for my [[nunchuck]]s.  I hearby pledge that: &quot;Have nunchucks. Will travel.&quot;[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 14:58, 17 November 2007 (UTC)

:I've no idea what you're on about for the most. But I'll assume your threat to replace material that's being disputed under BLP is withdrawn, and I'll remove the protection.--[[User talk:Doc glasgow|Doc]]&lt;sup&gt;g&lt;/sup&gt; 15:07, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
::'''Hey DOC''' Can you show me a diff where I threatened to add BLP material?  Actually, first can you show me which parts of the text from a preceeding diff have been established to be BLP.  I have been trying to get people to disucss which claims stated in the article are BLP to better understand things.  I have done my best to add other credible sources. I will be back later tonight to add more, but no one has named a single claim in the article that is BLP, yet removed things like where he went to high school and such, which clearly aren't.  BLP needs to be specific if it is claimed.  However, I think what I have done is well on the way to being sufficient.  &quot;Have nunchucks. Will travel.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 20:20, 17 November 2007 (UTC)

::There seems to be a misunderstanding.  I intend to work from my contested article.  I will do so in userspace and present the final version, since there is so much disagreement and yet no guidance on what parts are [[WP:BLP]] violations.  You can watch at [[User:TonyTheTiger/Jon_Burge]].--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 16:47, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
:::I will be offline for a few hours, but I have done some of the necessary editing on the article.  I hope to do another hour or two later tonight.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 19:59, 17 November 2007 (UTC)

::::You still don't seem to understand. I've no idea whether this article violates BLP, since I've not recently looked at the contents. However, where a user (and particularly one as established as ex-WMF employee Danny) suggests that material may violate BLP, then we keep the material out of the article until everyone is satisfied that it does not. You clearly indicated that you would revert unless you got a detailed explanation, and that is unacceptable[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Jon_Burge&amp;diff=171971403&amp;oldid=171919035]. We wait till we are sure, even if that takes weeks. There is no rush here - and the onus is on you to show it does not violate BLP - if there is doubt it stays out.--[[User talk:Doc glasgow|Doc]]&lt;sup&gt;g&lt;/sup&gt; 21:25, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
::::: All I am saying is that blanking an article is not proper if it is largely correct.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 22:23, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
:::::::If an editor believes that it violates BLP, he is mandated to remove the material. No other action is proper. If it is later established that he is mistaken, little harm is done, whereas if we mistakenly leave violating material much harm is done. The material stays out as long as any doubt remains - and we never rush to replace it.--[[User talk:Doc glasgow|Doc]]&lt;sup&gt;g&lt;/sup&gt; 22:44, 17 November 2007 (UTC)
::::::::Tomorrow, I intend to renom this at [[WP:GAC]], if all is in order.  I will make a few changes before 23:00 today and let it sit overnight for any remaining contestation before renomination.  Thanks for everyone's concern in the project and noticing this controversial topic.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 19:13, 18 November 2007 (UTC)
:::::::::If one would like to contest, my suggestion would be to name specific quotes that you believe fail [[WP:ATT]] and are either [[WP:OR]] or are sourced by something failing [[WP:RS]].  For a controversial article like this either type of ATT violation would constitute a [[WP:BLP]] violation.  Thus, state &quot;XXX&quot; is [[WP:OR]] or &quot;YYY&quot; is inadaquately sourced as per [[WP:RS]].  That would be most helpful for me to endeavor to bring the article up to BLP standards if it is still considered failing.  Blanket claims would not be very helpful in terms of creating a viable article for the project.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:LOTD]]) &lt;/small&gt; 19:17, 18 November 2007 (UTC)

==Protected==

I am preemptively protecting this article. There is a serious dispute regarding the allegations and sources concerning a living person, and one editor has threated to revert, and replace material that may violate BLP. Until this is resolved, any replacement of the material would be unacceptable. The article should remain as is, until the dispute is satisfactorily resolved. [[WP:DR|Dispute resolution]] lies open to all parties.--[[User talk:Doc glasgow|Doc]]&lt;sup&gt;g&lt;/sup&gt; 23:14, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

==Failed GA again==

This article is not substantively changed from the previous failed version. [[User:Phil Sandifer|Phil Sandifer]] ([[User talk:Phil Sandifer|talk]]) 16:34, 7 December 2007 (UTC)

==GA Review==

This is a difficult one. I was considering offering to undertake the GA review, but as it stands I think this article would have to be quickfailed again. So I'll just make a few comments about where I think it needs work to balance the POV.

*&quot;Police Commander Jon Graham Burge ... has gained notoriety for allegedly torturing more than 200 criminal suspects ...&quot;. Was Burge the alleged torturer of all 200, or is the allegation that he was in charge of a police department (of how many detectives?) that employed torture techniques?
**There should be enough detail in the article now.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 20:18, 15 July 2008 (UTC)
**He seems to be the primary torturer.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 20:19, 15 July 2008 (UTC)
*The lead says that the allegations cover the period 1972-1991, but ''The Turning point'' section says: &quot;The frenzied police effort to seek the most recent assailants in the name of justice may have gone beyond normal police procedures&quot;, suggesting that alleged torture began in 1982, unless normal police procedures already included torture by then.
**This should be cleaner now.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 02:21, 15 July 2008 (UTC)
*&quot;He returned to his parents' home, took a job as a mechanic and gas station attendant, and watched a bitter population shift. Bowen High School, which had been 93 percent white when Burge graduated in 1965, was only 14 percent white in 1972.&quot; Why is the percentage of black/white students at Bowen High School relevant to Burge's life and career? In what way was the population shift &quot;bitter&quot;?
*&quot;Burge's parents sold their home in 1973.&quot; So?
*&quot;Burge became a police officer in March 1970 at age 22 on the South side of Chicago. In May of 1972, he was promoted to detective and assigned to Area Two Robbery. In twenty years of service where he developed a reputation for defusing volatile situations, he earned 13 police commendations and a letter of praise from the Department of Justice.&quot; Not much of a summary of 20 years of police service.
**Getting to it now.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 20:58, 14 July 2008 (UTC)
*Burge joined the police service in 1970, and the torture allegations begin in 1972, the same year the he was promoted to detective. This begs the question of whether torture was already being used by the Chicago police at that time, or is there an allegation that it was introduced by Burge? Whichever it is needs to be made clear instead of leaving the question dangling.
**People don't make allegations that so and so started a pattern of police brutality, they make allegations that you committed police brutality on me.  There is no relevant dangling concern, because it is not relevant if it was done before Burge or not.  He is the guy who is prominently charged.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 21:01, 14 July 2008 (UTC)
*I share the concern raised by SandyGeorgia about using the best possible sources for an article like this one, and the consensus appears to be that that's the Conroy book. So I'd like to see citations to specific page numbers in that book wherever possible, instead of to newspapers whose credentials I'm uncertain of, like the ''Chicago Reader''.
**I am beefing up the article with the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' and ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]''.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 21:03, 14 July 2008 (UTC)
*&quot;Since being fired Burge has lived in Apollo Beach, Florida, a suburb of Tampa. In 1994, he bought his current wood-frame home for $154,000 and a 22 ft (6.7 m) motorboat named The Vigilante.&quot; I think that this is too much personal information, and is neither relevant nor appropriate to include.
**Where a person lives and what kind of property he owns are the type of information that seem relevant to a biography and that should be [[WP:PRESERVE]]d.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 21:05, 14 July 2008 (UTC)

This is a worthwhile subject, and I wish you luck in developing it, but I'd recommend withdrawing the article from GAN for the moment, as I don't think it's got any chance at all of passing as it stands. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuorum]] ([[User talk:Malleus Fatuarum|talk]]) 16:21, 5 January 2008 (UTC)

==More==
Since so much is mentioned about the victims, perhaps it should also be mentioned that Andrew Wilson admitted to being a murderer and that famed alleged victim Aaron Patterson is back in jail.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.176.182.94|67.176.182.94]] ([[User talk:67.176.182.94|talk]]) 02:17, 12 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


**It appears that ([[User:Phil Sandifer|Phil Sandifer]]) quickfailed this article on 7 December, but although he removed the GANominee tag he forgot to remove the article from the GA nomination list. I've updated the article history and the list to reflect that fact, so the article's current status is failed GA and its 23 November GA nomination has been marked as Failed. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuorum]] ([[User talk:Malleus Fatuarum|talk]]) 20:06, 5 January 2008 (UTC)

==profanity in art==

Can we crop http://www.flickr.com/photos/beigephotos/2622689510/ and add it to the article? Does it violate [[WP:BLP]]--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 19:54, 14 July 2008 (UTC)

{{Talk:Jon Burge/GA1}}

==GA pass==

This article has now passed the good article nomination process. Congratulations! The article is very detailed and broad in converage. Areas for furture improvement could include the tone of the article, which in some places is written more like an article for entertainment (say from a book or a newspaper) than for an encyclopeadia. [[User:Million Moments|Million_Moments]] ([[User talk:Million Moments|talk]]) 14:50, 7 August 2008 (UTC)

==Developments==
Jon Burge was arrested today in Florida on charges of perjury and obstruction of justice. See the Sun Times article [http://www.suntimes.com/news/metro/1233077,jon-burge-cop-torture-chicago-arrested-102108.article here]. I'll leave the update up to you guys. --[[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] ([[User talk:IvoShandor|talk]]) 23:47, 21 October 2008 (UTC)

==Burge picture==
This article needs a picture of Burge, uploaded with a fair use rationale.  There must be one somewhere in all the news reports about him.  If you find one and don't know how to add the fair use rationale, leave a note on my talk page and I'll help you out. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 03:23, 12 February 2009 (UTC)
:I understand very much that a picture would be useful.  However, unless we can show him on the cover of something in a way that is relevant to the article, I don't think a fair use image is appropriate.  There are in fact images very high in the search results on the cover of the [[Chicago Sun-Times]].  However, I do not see the newspaper article as significant to his biography.  Thus, I am staying away from fair use.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|c]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|bio]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:LOTM]]) &lt;/small&gt; 07:36, 12 February 2009 (UTC)

I'll probably be going to some of the trial. Maybe I could take one. [[User:Cool Hand Luke|Cool Hand]] ''[[User talk:Cool Hand Luke|Luke]]'' 20:09, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

:An article without a photo of the subject isn't so weird. But articles with multiple photos of other things and none of the subject make it conspicuous by its absence. It's even a tad weirder when three of those four pictures match the subject's description (older white lawman). That Fitzgerald fellow even appears prominently in a Google Image search for &quot;Jon Burge&quot;, thanks to us.

:Did you take one five years ago, [[User:Cool Hand Luke]]? [[User:InedibleHulk|InedibleHulk]] [[User_Talk:InedibleHulk|(talk)]] 18:55, [[May 16]], [[2015]] (UTC)

==Small correction needed==
I should avoid editing this article, but would like to point out a small correction: the caption for Daley is incorrect.  He was not a &quot;city prosecutor.&quot; As State's Attorney, he was the prosecutor for all of Cook County. [[User:Cool Hand Luke|Cool Hand]] ''[[User talk:Cool Hand Luke|Luke]]'' 20:09, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

Thank you to whomever made the above correction [[User:Cool Hand Luke|Cool Hand]] requested.  This article will continue to need revision as history marches on in confirmation of its importance.  Am not sure what to do about: &quot;The cases against Cook County and the other current/former prosecutors continue as of July 2008. Having never been convicted of a felony, Burge continues to receive a police pension to which he is entitled under Illinois state law.[4]&quot; so gonna hope one of you who's been working on it can fix this formerly true statement now contradicted in lede. [[User:Ph7five|- phi]] ([[User talk:Ph7five|talk]]) 12:58, 15 April 2015 (UTC)

As of 6/12/2016 the article continues to contradict itself as to whether he is or is not a felon drawing a pension.  Given the continued national conversation initiated by Ferguson regarding police impunity, accountability, and the possible modalities of reform (which include effects on the pensions of the culpable) it would be well if this historically important case were reliably treated here. [[Special:Contributions/97.123.115.87|97.123.115.87]] ([[User talk:97.123.115.87|talk]]) 17:30, 12 June 2016 (UTC)Lewis Goudy

==Removing sociology project==
I've removed the Sociology project tag from this page. While sociology is interested in felons, human rights, legal abuse, and many similar topics, it does not usually study individuals. The scope of that project is in sociological concepts and terms, and sociologists. Issues that affect Jon Burge are of interest to sociologists, his case may be mentioned in some sociological works, but he himself is IMHO outside the project scope. Because on another level, every single person is of interest to sociologists due to various life circumstances, and we are not going to tag all biographies with sociology tags (or all cities, even through a field of [[urban sociology]] is interested in them in general). --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; talk to me&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 19:44, 5 October 2011 (UTC)

== Fitzgerald image ==

I don't know what the point is about removing Fitzgerald's picture.  It is used in a common manner for the encyclopedia in that article and belongs as a referent.--[[User:TonyTheTiger|TonyTheTiger]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:TonyTheTiger|T]]/[[Special:Contributions/TonyTheTiger|C]]/[[User:TonyTheTiger/Antonio Vernon|BIO]]/[[WP:CHICAGO]]/[[WP:FOUR]]) &lt;/small&gt; 06:08, 20 November 2011 (UTC)

== Newsbank references/citations links are all broken? ==

I'm unable to open a single Newsbank article on this page. On navigation, all I get is a page that says &quot;requester private data is incorrect&quot;, titled &quot;OpenURL Error&quot;, which is literally the entire document! Is this just me or is there a problem with Newsbank??[[User:Test35965|Test35965]] ([[User talk:Test35965|talk]]) 22:00, 7 May 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Jon Burge]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707756191 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090804013329/http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004 to http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:NewsBank:CSTB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=0EB36D1AC13FD28C&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated5&amp;req_dat=AA98CDC331574F0ABEAFF732B33DC0B2
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090804013329/http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004 to http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:NewsBank:CSTB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=0EB36DB094C9F2FB&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated5&amp;req_dat=AA98CDC331574F0ABEAFF732B33DC0B2
*Added archive {newarchive} to http://cbs2chicago.com/local/jon.burge.trial.2.1679040.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 16:37, 1 March 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:3|one external link|3 external links}} on [[Jon Burge]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=711248404 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090804013329/http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004 to http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:NewsBank:CSTB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=0EB36D1AC13FD28C&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated5&amp;req_dat=AA98CDC331574F0ABEAFF732B33DC0B2
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20090804013329/http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004 to http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:NewsBank:CSTB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=0EB36DB094C9F2FB&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated5&amp;req_dat=AA98CDC331574F0ABEAFF732B33DC0B2
*Added archive {newarchive} to http://cbs2chicago.com/local/jon.burge.trial.2.1679040.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:23, 21 March 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>aqs1bgzu0bdogn4ik7ytifp7a9rragj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
