<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Cold War</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1255975</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750887374</id>
      <parentid>750884563</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T01:46:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chewings72</username>
        <id>12824384</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/76.114.96.212|76.114.96.212]] ([[User talk:76.114.96.212|talk]]) to last version by Hires an editor</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10931">{{Talk header}}
{{tmbox
|image=[[File:Dialog-information on.svg|40px]]
|text=A user has '''[[Wikipedia:Good article reassessment#Articles needing review and possible reassessment|requested]]''' that the [[WP:GA|Good article]] community check whether this article's GA status is in need of [[WP:GAR|reassessment]]. &lt;small&gt;This is just an alert and reassessment may not be necessary: any uninvolved editor can remove this tag.&lt;/small&gt;[[Category:Good articles in need of review]]
}}
{{Vital article|level=3|topic=History|class=A}}
{{Controversial}}
{{Not a forum}}
{{calm}}
{{Article history
|action1=WAR
|action1date=02:37, 16 January 2008
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Cold War
|action1result=approved
|action1oldid=184579243

|action2=WPR
|action2date=14:37, 28 May 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/Cold War/Archive 1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=215474397

|action3=FAC
|action3date=02:05, 9 July 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Cold War/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=224425547

|action4=FAC
|action4date=13:43, 7 September 2008
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Cold War/archive2
|action4result=not promoted
|action4oldid=236444643

|action5=GAN
|action5link=Talk:Cold War/GA1
|action5date=13:36, 3 February 2009 (UTC)
|action5result=listed
|action5oldid=268243605

|action6=WPR
|action6date=21 December 2010
|action6link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/Cold War
|action6result=reviewed
|action6oldid=403358189

|otddate=16 April 2008
|otdoldid=205963014
|otd2date=16 April 2009
|otd2oldid=284172030
|otd3date=2010-04-16
|otd3oldid=356149313
|otd4date=2011-04-16
|otd4oldid=424312764
|otd5date=2013-04-16
|otd5oldid=550595404
|aciddate=February 19 2006
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Cold War|class=A|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Soviet Union|class=A|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=A|A-Class=pass|old-peer-review=yes|British=yes|Chinese=yes|French=yes|German=yes|Polish=yes|Romanian=yes|Russian=yes|US=yes|Cold-War=yes}}
{{WikiProject History|class=A|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject European history|class=A|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=A|importance=Top|USMIL=yes|UShistory=yes|UShistory-importance=Top|USGov=yes|USGov-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=A|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Socialism|class=A|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject International relations|class=A|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Conservatism|class=A|importance=top}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=A|category=History|VA=yes|Coresup=yes|WPCD=yes}}}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 9
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Cold War/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=6|units=months}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn|target=/Archive index|mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt;|leading_zeros=0|indexhere=yes}}

== European Integration textual problem (Crisis and Escalation) ==

Under Crisis and Escalation, there is a mention of the beginnings of European Integration through the initiatives of U.S. foreign policy. There are two significant problems. First, the subject itself is only mentioned in passing and deserves more analysis, esp. in regards to its significance to ensuing diplomatic relations. Second, the link to the term forwards to the non-Cold War version, that is, European Integration in relation to the foundations and formation of the EU. Cold War version please!

== Removal of biased sentence needed ==

::

The bit about Bernard Baruch is a bit confusing. What does it mean that &quot;he delivered a speech (by journalist Herbert Bayard Swope)&quot;?  Written for him by Swope perhaps?

== Russia as European power ==

West was generally supporting and practically never restraining Muscovite Russia and its All-Russian tsars (sharing same values of agression, terror and oppression) – rising power starting controlling parts of East and Central Europe – as Russia fighting West‘s traditional enemies like Poland-Lithuania (parts of Poland itself even delivered under Russian rule for a century) or Ottomans (control over Eurasian Straits being sure there a special problem) and another.
Later West was needing Soviet Union (with unprecedented territorial and political gains) as superpower for rallying, closing the ranks, uniting around US and evicting new wars between westerners – Russian and Communist menace should look there worse than even American Imperialism (quite hard as task) and the local differences or contradictions, when another side World sure vitally needing alternative and competition (having certainly a „fight“ with quite predictable result as West always staying there much more powerful) for the two Worlds and Systems, which would be relating, correcting, reforming each other, boosting each other progress, limiting each other excesses.
After a World Crisis of 2008 West needing again Russia in the image of the enemy, so Putin was allowed starting crusade – of course (impossible and forbidden for example against Baltics much before those joining NATO) against Orthodox and Slavics – like Georgia and Ukraine, once richest and flourishing in USSR, now destroyed and sinking in ruin (and whose criminal and corrupted governments now sure not better than Russian). Sure Putin missing of thanking America and West for horribly destroying, pillaging, devastating and corrupting Ukraine or Georgia during those 2 decennia for making them easy victims of Russian aggression. 
[[User:Cheboksari|Cheboksari]] ([[User talk:Cheboksari|talk]]) 19:36, 1 June 2016 (UTC)

== Draft outline ==

There is a draft for a related outline on the Cold War at [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Outlines/Drafts/Outline of the Cold War]]. There's also a related RM on that talk page. -- [[User:Ricky81682|Ricky81682]] ([[User talk:Ricky81682|talk]]) 20:55, 22 June 2016 (UTC)

== Soviet Empire? ==

I hit return too early so my edit summary was garbled- sorry
The contrast initially made in the comparison was between the USA and the USSR in the first sentence, then moves on to the 'Soviet empire' and 'Western states' both of which are appropriate comparisons. The USSR controlled e.g. most of Eastern Europe in a way that the US did not control Western Europe. If you try to change the 'Soviet empire' to the USSR, you are missing half the point and that comparison is thrown away.  I think Soviet empire is perfectly appropriate, complete much of the time with an Emperor even if his title was First secretary.  However, if you want to find another word to describe the method of rule under Soviet hegemony, comprising not just the USSR but its satellite states, feel free.
[[User:Gravuritas|Gravuritas]] ([[User talk:Gravuritas|talk]]) 14:57, 16 August 2016 (UTC)

== Infobox  ==

I made a compact infobox on cold war, showing the main sides of conflict, its result, collage photo, etc. 
Then [[User:Biruitorul]] deleted it and said I'd better take it to talk.
So what i'm telling is that it would be much more easy and visually clear if there would be an infobox. 
[[User:CapLiber|CapLiber]] ([[User talk:CapLiber#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/CapLiber|contribs]]) 20:47, 14 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:I thought the infobox was a nice addition, and—while not perfect—a clear improvement over the status quo.[[User:TheTimesAreAChanging|TheTimesAreAChanging]] ([[User talk:TheTimesAreAChanging|talk]]) 23:03, 14 November 2016 (UTC)
::Veto on the infobox. Please review the many archived discussions that explain why the infobox is not a good idea. For example, there is a Cold War Template for just the people involved in some significant way that, if it wasn't deleted, ran away from any value or usefulness because of all the names it had. Trying to appropriately fill this infobox with this same information is problematic. In addition, just because it has &quot;war&quot; as part of its name, it wasn't a &quot;war&quot; in the traditional sense; rather, it was a rivalry. This means that the rivalry didn't have a &quot;winner&quot; or a &quot;loser&quot; (though we might consider the argument that George H. W. Bush literally said &quot;We won!&quot; in front of a crowd in Europe). The infobox has the wrong dates. When did it start? Historians disagree. (I know this detail because I researched it myself) Again, there are a number of reasons that this infobox is inappropriate. It might be better to create a &quot;Rivalry&quot; infobox, since there several of those through history, and could be used in other places besides the Cold War. [[User:Hires an editor|Hires an editor]] ([[User talk:Hires an editor|talk]]) 01:30, 17 November 2016 (UTC)
:::Disagreements are commonplace. Historians disagree on when the [[Vietnam War]] started (1955? 1959? 1965?)—not to mention when it ended, so should the infobox in that article be removed, too? You propose a &quot;rivalry&quot; infobox, but how would that differ from the &quot;conflict&quot; infobox? We all doubtless agree that the &quot;leaders/countries&quot; should be limited to major players and exclude excessive or UNDUE material (though we might disagree about what that qualifier means in practice), but we shouldn't let the perfect be the enemy of the good.[[User:TheTimesAreAChanging|TheTimesAreAChanging]] ([[User talk:TheTimesAreAChanging|talk]]) 06:58, 17 November 2016 (UTC)
::::Agreed - while not looking for perfection, and looking for good, we have yet to find it. But I'll save that for another day, since we've made all these arguments before. Although, one I have not made is that a military infobox mis-characterizes the Cold War. The rivalry info box would have more general descriptions of what was at stake, what the approximate dates are, where various incidents occurred...whereas the military infobox declares winners and losers (usually), and &quot;important leaders&quot; and other war stats, like numbers of dead and wounded, land gained or lost. Think of a rivalry infobox like a football team rivalry - it's recurring, there are important things that happened during that rivalry, but at the end of the day there is a static quality to it. Everyone goes home, and they &quot;fight&quot; again some other day. France and England were rivals for 400 years or so, from (very roughly) 1500 to 1900, when they became allies. They fought wars against each other during this period, but also competed for land and resources in other parts of the world in less confrontational ways than all out war. I have talked about this before, and I posted a comment [[Wikipedia_talk:WikiProject_History/Archive_4#Infobox_for_International_Political_and_Economic_Rivalry.2C_not_just_military|here]] but no one responded. A rivalry infobox would have a broader perspective than merely a war infobox. [[User:Hires an editor|Hires an editor]] ([[User talk:Hires an editor|talk]]) 13:48, 17 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>t4i4kltcnxc9x810u3s670i9iqr0oz6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
