<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Christiansfjell Fortress</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4026789</id>
    <revision>
      <id>567548262</id>
      <parentid>289185717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-08-07T15:04:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>64.6.124.31</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reassessed as stub per tag on article</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3356">{{WPMILHIST|class=Stub
|Fortifications-task-force=yes
|Nordic-task-force=yes
}}
{{NorwayProject|class=Stub}}

== Material from Norwegian Wikipedia ==

== History == 
The fortification was built on a hill on the east side of [[Glomma]] as one of several defense (the other was [[Elverum skanse]] and [[Grindal Skansen]] on the other side of Glomma) nearby to protect the road to Hedemarken against Swedish attack. This first skansen was called Hammer Berg. When King Christian 5. inspected the plant 14. June [[1685]], ga castle he named Christian Fjeld for themselves. In the years that followed were made comprehensive development and improvement. In [[1709]] the facility was expanded with an outer wall with a gun tower. Outside the castle was already in 1683 paved the equivalent of the fortress shots fields. In this area, soldiers and officers under the permission to organize the housing. This was the origin of the town of [[clay]] that today constitute a large part of [[Elverum]] center. This settlement was divided into South and North Camp that lay on either side of the fortress. In the fortress velmaktsdager was [[Grundset market]] added nordre Camp. 

By Royal Decree of 13.juli [[1742]] was [[Basmo]] and Christian Fjeld also closed down, and the fortress was dismantled. Fixtures, usable building, and even buildings were sold at auction in [[1745]], and the fort was officially closed. 

In [[1811]], it was again decided that the fort would be able and have a garrison of 30 lackeys, 3 and 1 Corporal premiærløytnant. In the following years up to the [[1814]], it was closed down a large project to put the castle and the surrounding line of stand, and after [[Kiel Treaty]] in January 1814, the work was strongly precipitated. During the campaign in 1814 was reinforced garrison of 6 companies from the [[Dragon Søndenfjellske Regiment]], in all 420 men. 

By royal order of 17. December 1814 it was decided that the Christian Fjeld was terminated and the armor is transported to the [[fortress]]. The 25. March [[1815]] fortress was decided evacuated. Also this time the buildings were removed and sold, and eventually was torn down the walls to be used for other walls in the area. 

The fortification was never in combat, and has never been besieged. 

The fortification has many times in the years thereafter have been used in connection with the celebration of national days, in which parts of the event has been added to this area. It was during salute ring 17. May [[1840]] that Elverums the first mayor of [[Hans Øvergaard]] (1795-1840) was killed. 

In the 1930-year was initiated restoration work led by the council engineer Dahl. The area was cleared as recreation, and the walls of the various buildings were highlighted to show where they had stood. 

In 1964 the council's water tower built on top of the fortress, and the remnants of the old tower was demolished. 

Today, we find three Bautaen for Christian Fjeld, one for mayor Øvergaard, one of the fallen 1808-1814 and 1940-1945 for the fallen. 

== == Garrison 
Garrison size has varied considerably over the years. In 1686 the crew of 32 officers and lackeys. In 1716 there were 264 men, but this big crew must be considered in the context that it was the middle of the Great Northern War. 

In the period 1811-1814 was the garrison in the order of 25-35 men.</text>
      <sha1>b6f2lddj92rbb07flgtbe9y21t5y0h6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
