<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>1938 Polish ultimatum to Lithuania</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16305035</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745327011</id>
      <parentid>745221874</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T14:05:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>216.8.144.216</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32979">{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{good article}}
[[Image:Lithuania territory 1939-1940.svg|300px|thumb|Map of the territorial disputes of Lithuania in 1939–1940, including the Vilnius Region in brown and orange]]

The '''1938 Polish ultimatum to Lithuania''' was an [[ultimatum]] delivered to [[Lithuania]] by [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]] on March 17, [[1938 in Poland|1938]]. The Lithuanian government had steadfastly refused to have any [[diplomatic relations]] with Poland after 1920, protesting the annexation of the [[Vilnius Region]] by Poland.&lt;ref name=cd118&gt;{{cite book | last=Skirius | first=Juozas | title=Gimtoji istorija. Nuo 7 iki 12 klasės | url=http://mkp.emokykla.lt/gimtoji/ | accessdate=2008-03-02 | year=2002 | publisher=Elektroninės leidybos namai | location=Vilnius | isbn=9986-9216-9-4 | chapter=Lietuvos–Lenkijos santykiai 1938–1939 metais | chapterurl= http://mkp.emokykla.lt/gimtoji/?id=10118|language=lt}}&lt;/ref&gt; As pre-[[World War II]] tensions in Europe intensified, Poland perceived the need to secure its northern borders. Five days earlier, Poland, feeling supported by international recognition of the [[Anschluss|annexation of Austria]] by [[Nazi Germany]], decided to deliver an ultimatum to Lithuania.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; The ultimatum demanded that the Lithuanian government unconditionally agree to establish [[diplomatic relations]] with [[Warsaw]] within 48 hours, and that the terms be finalized before March 31. The establishment of diplomatic relations would mean a ''de facto'' renunciation of Lithuanian claims to the region containing its historic capital, [[Vilnius]] (known in Polish as Wilno).

Lithuania, preferring peace to war, accepted the ultimatum on March 19. Although diplomatic relations were established as a result of the ultimatum, Lithuania did not agree to recognize the loss of Vilnius ''[[de jure]]''.&lt;ref name=nyt/&gt; The government of Poland made a similar move against the [[Czechoslovakia|Czechoslovak]] government in [[Prague]] on September 30, 1938, when it took advantage of the [[Sudeten Crisis]] to demand a portion of [[Zaolzie]]. On both occasions, Poland used the international crises to address long-standing border disputes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first=Norman |last=Davies |title= God's Playground: A History of Poland |year=2005 |publisher=Columbia University Press | pages=319 | url= https://books.google.com/?id=EBpghdZeIwAC&amp;pg=PA319 | isbn=978-0-231-12819-3| accessdate= June 16, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Vilnius dispute ==
{{main article|Vilnius Region}}
Lithuania severed its diplomatic ties with Poland after the Polish general [[Lucjan Żeligowski]] [[Żeligowski's Mutiny|staged a mutiny]] in October 1920 by order of [[Józef Piłsudski]].&lt;ref name=msn&gt;{{cite web|url=http://encarta.msn.com/sidebar_461500494/1938_lithuania.html |title=1938: Lithuania |publisher=MSN Encarta |work=Collier's Year Book |accessdate=2008-03-14 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5kvWEPG6Z?url=http%3A%2F%2Fencarta.msn.com%2Fsidebar_461500494%2F1938_lithuania.html |archivedate=October 31, 2009 |deadurl=yes |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; He invaded Lithuanian-held territory, captured the disputed city of [[Vilnius]] (known to Poles as Wilno), and established the short-lived [[Republic of Central Lithuania]]. This entity was incorporated into Poland in 1922. In demographic terms Vilnius was the least Lithuanian of Lithuanian cities,&lt;ref name=&quot;MacQueen_context&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first=Michael |last=MacQueen |title=The Context of Mass Destruction: Agents and Prerequisites of the Holocaust in Lithuania |journal=Holocaust and Genocide Studies |volume=12 |issue=1 |pages=27–48 |year=1998 |url= http://hgs.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/12/1/27 |doi=10.1093/hgs/12.1.27}}&lt;/ref&gt; divided almost evenly between the Polish-speaking population and Jews, with Lithuanian-speaking inhabitants constituting about 2–3% of the population, according to Russian (1897)&lt;ref name=&quot;Łossowski11&quot;&gt;{{cite book |authorlink=Piotr Łossowski| first=Piotr |last=Łossowski | title=Konflikt polsko–litewski 1918–1920| location= Warsaw |publisher=Książka i Wiedza |year=1995 |isbn= 83-05-12769-9 |pages=11|language=pl}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Demoskop&quot;&gt;{{ru icon}} [http://demoscope.ru/weekly/ssp/rus_lan_97.php?reg=32 Demoscope].&lt;/ref&gt; and German (1916) censuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brensztejn&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first= Michał Eustachy |last=Brensztejn|year=1919 |title=Spisy ludności m. Wilna za okupacji niemieckiej od. 1 listopada 1915 r. |publisher=Biblioteka Delegacji Rad Polskich Litwy i Białej Rusi |location=Warsaw |language=pl}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lithuania demanded that Polish troops withdraw behind the line drawn in the [[Suwałki Agreement]], while Poland falsely maintained that it had not authorized Żeligowski's actions. The League attempted to mediate the dispute and [[Paul Hymans]] presented concrete proposals to form a federation. However, both sides were unwilling to make compromises and negotiations collapsed in January 1922.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url = https://books.google.com/?id=fecMC0LXU-sC&amp;pg=PA31
|title = Lithuania: Stepping Westward |first=Thomas |last=Lane |year=2001 |publisher=Routledge |pages=31 |isbn= 0-415-26731-5| accessdate= June 16, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1923, Lithuanian troops crossed over to the Allied-held [[Memelland]] and staged the &quot;[[Klaipėda revolt]]&quot;. The Lithuanian occupation of Memel (Klaipėda) was one of the main factors that led to the decision of the [[Conference of Ambassadors]] to award Vilnius to Poland in March 1923.&lt;ref&gt;Alfred Eric Senn. ''The Great Powers Lithuania and the Vilna Question, 1920-1928''. E.J. Brill. 1966. pp. 107-113.&lt;/ref&gt;

The result was a state of &quot;no war, no peace&quot; as Lithuania avoided recognizing any Polish claims to the city and the region,&lt;ref name=&quot;MacQueen_context&quot;/&gt; as well as refusing to undertake any actions that would recognize Poland's control of Vilnius even ''de facto''.&lt;ref name=msn/&gt; Lithuania broke off all diplomatic relations with Poland and continuously emphasized that Vilnius remained its permanent capital ([[Kaunas]] was designated as the [[Temporary capital of Lithuania|temporary capital]]). Poland refused to formally recognize the existence of any dispute regarding the region, since that would have lent legitimacy to the Lithuanian claims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Eidintas | first=Alfonsas |author2=Vytautas Žalys|author3=Alfred Erich Senn | editor=Ed. Edvardas Tuskenis | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback |date=September 1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3 | pages=146}}&lt;/ref&gt; Railroad traffic and telegraph lines could not cross the border, and mail service was complicated. For example, a letter from Poland to Lithuania needed to be sent to a neutral country, repackaged in a new envelope to remove any Polish signs, and only then delivered to Lithuania.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | journal=The New York Times |first=Emil |last=Lengyel |date=1939-03-20 |title=Poland and Lithuania in a Long Feud |pages=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conflict over Vilnius remained the most important foreign policy issue in Lithuania, but it became increasingly marginalized in the international arena. There were unsuccessful informal attempts to normalize the situation, most notably by the Lithuanian Prime Minister [[Augustinas Voldemaras]] between 1927 and 1928 and by Foreign Minister [[Stasys Lozoraitis]] between 1934 and 1936, who asked President [[Antanas Smetona|Smetona]] to re-establish the diplomatic relations with Poland. Both sides engaged in emotional and nationalistic rhetoric.&lt;ref name=eidintas2&gt;{{cite book | last=Eidintas | first=Alfonsas |author2=Vytautas Žalys|author3=Alfred Erich Senn | editor=Ed. Edvardas Tuskenis | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback |date=September 1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3 | pages=146, 152–153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Rationale ==
On March 11,{{#tag:ref|Sometimes incorrectly cited as March 7.|group=note}} a day before Austria was annexed into [[German question#Later influence|Greater Germany]] following the [[Anschluss]], Justas Lukoševičius, a Lithuanian border patrol, shot Stanisław Serafin, a Polish soldier, on the demarcation line in the village of Trasninkai near [[Merkinė]]. The exact circumstances are not clear as the obscure event was variously portrayed as a Lithuanian provocation, a Polish provocation, or as an unfortunate accident.&lt;ref name=vitas&gt;{{cite journal| title= The Polish–Lithuanian Crisis of 1938: Events Surrounding the Ultimatum |url=http://www.lituanus.org/1984_2/84_2_03.htm | first=Robert |last=Vitas |journal=Lituanus |volume=20 |issue=2 |date=Summer 1984 |accessdate=2008-03-02| issn= 0024-5089| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080323160232/http://www.lituanus.org/1984_2/84_2_03.htm| archivedate= March 23, 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1920s and 1930s, similar incidents had occurred: between 1927 and 1937 seven Lithuanian border guards were killed during the course of 78 events.&lt;ref name=eidintas&gt;{{cite book | last=Eidintas | first=Alfonsas |author2=Vytautas Žalys|author3=Alfred Erich Senn | editor=Ed. Edvardas Tuskenis | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback |date=September 1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3 | pages=154–158}}&lt;/ref&gt; Usually, such incidents were handled at the local level in an attempt to forestall escalation. On this occasion, however, Polish radio and newspapers picked up the story and fanned anti-Lithuanian sentiment. Protests were held in [[Warsaw]], [[Vilnius]], and four other cities where the crowds shouted for military action against Lithuania. There is evidence that the [[Camp of National Unity]] was involved in organizing the protests.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt;

On March 13, the Polish government issued a threatening statement accusing Lithuania of provocation. On the following day, the [[Senate of the Republic of Poland]] called for the establishment of diplomatic relations and for the Lithuanian renunciation of claims to Vilnius.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; Upon receiving news that Poland was considering extreme measures, President Smetona was verging towards agreeing to discuss diplomatic relations, but changed his mind at almost the last minute.&lt;ref name=eidintas/&gt; On the night of March 14, the Lithuanians, acting through France's envoy to Warsaw, proposed a commission to investigate the shooting incident and to agree on measures to avoid such incidents in the future.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; This was a partial measure that clearly did not satisfy Poland,&lt;ref name=eidintas/&gt; which responded by refusing, in the first paragraph of the ultimatum delivered three days later,&lt;ref name=docs/&gt; to establish such a commission. At the same time Lithuanian diplomats approached foreign powers in a bid for international support.

== Initial version ==
The first version of the ultimatum, as drafted by [[Edward Rydz-Śmigły]], Prime Minister [[Felicjan Sławoj Składkowski]], and [[Jan Szembek (diplomat)|Jan Szembek]],&lt;ref name=vilnis/&gt; contained six demands:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The New York Times | title=Poland Sends An Ultimatum |first=Jerzy |last=Shapiro |date=1938-03-18 |pages=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

# Establish normal diplomatic and consular relations with Poland
# Allow normal railway and road traffic and direct telephone and telegraph lines across the demarcation line
# Amend the Lithuanian constitution to acknowledge that Vilnius was no longer the capital of Lithuania
# Conclude the convention protecting the rights of the Polish minority in Lithuania in full
# Conclude a trade and tariff agreement
# Fully investigate the incident in Trasnykai

The Polish Foreign Minister [[Józef Beck]], who had just returned from a trip to [[Sorrento]], called for a government meeting on the night of March 16,. During the meeting he argued that the ultimatum needed to contain only one demand: the establishment of diplomatic relations. In his view, such an ultimatum would not have violated any genuine Lithuanian interests and would offer much-improved prospects for peaceful resolution of the conflict and a speedy relief of tension.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; It was in accordance with Beck's vision for Eastern Europe, which was based on a Warsaw-dominated Polish–Baltic–Scandinavian bloc free of Soviet or German influence,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The New York Times |title=Lithuania Surrenders | date=1938-03-21 |pages=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; a modified version of [[Józef Piłsudski]]'s [[Międzymorze]], which required the normalization of relations with Lithuania.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; The removal of the other demands also reflected political pressure on Poland from the Soviet Union, France, and the United Kingdom to prevent the conflict from escalating into warfare.&lt;ref name=nyt&gt;{{cite journal| journal=The New York Times | first=Clarence K. |last=Streit |title=Pressure on Poles Weakens Demands |date=1939-03-19 |pages=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Polish government agreed to Beck's proposal, and the ultimatum was toned down. However, at the same time, Beck ordered military preparations. Poland assembled four divisions along the demarcation line; about 50,000 Polish troops were present, and just over 20,000 Lithuanian troops.&lt;ref name=times&gt;{{cite journal| title=Baltic Peace |journal=Time |url= http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,759356,00.html | date=1938-03-28 |accessdate=2008-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Polish troops were reinforced by armored vehicles, by two air force regiments, consisting of about one hundred aircraft, and by the Polish fleet in the waters of the [[Baltic Sea]] along the Lithuanian shore.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt;

== The ultimatum ==
The final text of the ultimatum, completed by Józef Beck and delivered through a Polish envoy in [[Tallinn]] to Bronius Dailidė, the Lithuanian envoy in Tallinn, was as follows:&lt;ref name=docs&gt;{{cite journal| title= Documents: The Polish Ultimatum to Lithuania – The Despatch of Lithuanian Minister J. Baltrušaitis in Moscow |url=http://www.lituanus.org/1985/85_4_02.htm | first=Robert |last=Vitas |journal=Lituanus |volume=31 |issue=4 |date=Winter 1985 |accessdate=2008-03-02| issn= 0024-5089}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: 1. &quot;The proposition of the Lithuanian Government of 14 March cannot be accepted for it does not give sufficient guarantees concerning the security of the frontier in view of the negative results of all Polish–Lithuanian negotiations made up to the present time.&quot;

: 2. &quot;For this reason the Polish Government declares that it considers as the only solution corresponding to the gravity of the situation the immediate establishment of normal diplomatic relations without any previous condition. This is the only way to regulate the neighborly questions for a Government animated by good faith to avoid events dangerous to peace.&quot;

: 3. &quot;The Polish Government allows the Lithuanian Government 48 hours from the moment the note is presented for the acceptance of this proposition in making it known that diplomatic representations at Kaunas and Warsaw will be accredited not later than March 31, of this year. Until that date all discussions of a technical or other character between the Polish and Lithuanian Governments shall be continued by the envoys extraordinary and ministers [[plenipotentiary]] at Tallinn.
: The exchange of notes attached concerning the establishment of diplomatic relations shall take place, before the expiration of the period of 48 hours mentioned, at Tallinn between the Polish and Lithuanian Ministers at Tallinn.&quot;

: 4. &quot;The proposition above mentioned will not be the subject of discussion with regard to its content or form—it is an unchangeable proposition.
: The failure to respond or the presentation of any supplements or reservations shall be considered by the Polish Government as a refusal. In the event of a negative reply the Polish Government will guarantee the just interest of the state by its proper means.&quot;

The ultimatum contained an attachment: a draft of what would be deemed an acceptable response to the ultimatum. The proposed response stated only that Lithuania agreed to establish regular diplomatic relations, send a [[legation]] to Warsaw, and guarantee normal conditions of operation for a Polish legation in Kaunas.&lt;ref name=docs/&gt;

== International reaction ==
After the [[Soviet–Lithuanian Peace Treaty]] was ratified in 1920, the [[Russian SFSR]] recognized Lithuanian claims to the Vilnius Region and continued to support them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Eidintas | first=Alfonsas |author2=Vytautas Žalys|author3=Alfred Erich Senn | editor=Ed. Edvardas Tuskenis | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback |date=September 1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3 | pages=109}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its responses to the 1938 ultimatum, the [[Soviet Union]] expressed concerns over Lithuania's independence and threatened to abrogate the [[Soviet–Polish Non-Aggression Pact]] of 1932. It made it clear, though, that it did not wish to be drawn into an armed conflict.&lt;ref name=eidintas/&gt; This stance has been attributed to the growth of a threat from Japan;&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; armed assistance to Lithuania would have required the [[Red Army]] to invade either Poland or Latvia&lt;ref name=times/&gt; and could have resulted in a war on two fronts.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; The Soviets urged France, a major ally of Poland at the time, to de-escalate the conflict and encourage a more moderate version of the ultimatum.&lt;ref name=vilnis/&gt; France and the United Kingdom, preoccupied with the Anschluss, pressured Lithuania to normalize the relationship with Poland as soon as possible. They feared that the ultimatum had been approved by Nazi Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| journal=The New York Times |date=1938-03-16 |first=Clarence K. |last=Streit |title=Reich-Polish Deal Feared in Geneva |pages=11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Germany, led by [[Adolf Hitler]], now turned its attention to the [[Klaipėda Region]], then held by Lithuania. In April 1938, Hitler stated that control of the [[Port of Klaipėda]] (German: ''Memel'') and its surrounding area was Germany's second-most important issue, following the status of the [[Germans in Czechoslovakia (1918–1938)|Sudeten area]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=The Baltic and the Outbreak of the Second World War | first=John |last= Hiden |author2=Thomas Lane |page=53 |publisher=Cambridge University Press | year=1992| url= https://books.google.com/?id=HzrpExvg2XgC&amp;pg=PA53 | isbn= 0-521-53120-9 | accessdate= June 16, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the event of armed hostilities between Poland and Lithuania, German troops were to defend and occupy the Klaipėda region and significant portions of western Lithuania.&lt;ref name=eidintas/&gt; The Polish ambassador to Nazi Germany, [[Józef Lipski]], was informed of these plans. The Poles agreed to cooperate with German troops and to respect German interests in Klaipėda if such an armed conflict were to arise.&lt;ref name=vilnis&gt;{{cite book | first=Vilnis |last=Sipols |title=Diplomatic Battles Before World War II |url=http://leninist.biz/en/1982/DBBW313/3.1.4-Polish.Ultimatum.to.Lithuania |chapter=Polish Ultimatum to Lithuania |location=Moscow |publisher=Progress Publishers |year=1982 | accessdate= March 15, 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in Hitler's assessment, an immediate bid for Klaipėda was impolitic; he wished to maintain the ''status quo'' until more time had passed after the [[Anschluss]]. The German suggestion was that Lithuania concede to the Polish demands.&lt;ref name=eidintas/&gt;

Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia, the three [[Baltic states]], had formed the [[Baltic Entente]] in 1934. Its principal purposes were coordination of joint foreign policy and mutual international diplomatic support; it was not a military alliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Anatol |last=Lieven |title=The Baltic Revolution: Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania and the Path to Independence |publisher=Yale University Press |year=1994 |pages=77 | isbn=0-300-06078-5 | url=https://books.google.com/?id=iz3NACNOpCAC&amp;pg=PA77
| accessdate= June 16, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Latvian and Estonian opinion, the Polish–Lithuanian dispute over Vilnius was outside the scope of the Entente, but they wished for a resolution, considering the conflict detrimental to the stability of the region.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; Latvia attempted to persuade Estonia to exert mutual pressure on Lithuania for a speedy acceptance of the ultimatum. This reaction from an ally was unexpected.&lt;ref name=eidintas/&gt;

== Acceptance ==
President Smetona held a government meeting late on the night of March 18, to decide whether to accept the ultimatum.&lt;ref name=ist/&gt; Lithuania clearly lacked international support and the demand was rather tame. A refusal would have cast Lithuania in an unfavorable light as an unreasonable disputant that had irrationally rejected peaceful diplomatic relations for eighteen years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| journal=The New York Times |title=Paris urging Kaunas to Yield to Warsaw |date=1939-03-19 |pages=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lithuanian diplomats were divided on the issue, while popular opinion was strongly against accepting the ultimatum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Alfred Erich |last=Senn |title= Lithuania 1940: Revolution from Above | pages=34 | publisher=Rodopi | year=2007 | url= https://books.google.com/?id=prqkNTCqa9cC&amp;pg=PA34 |isbn= 90-420-2225-6| accessdate= June 16, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various campaigns for the Lithuanian liberation of Vilnius had attracted massive participation. &quot;Mourning of Vilnius Day&quot; (October 9, when Żeligowski invaded Lithuania and captured Vilnius), had become an annual event,&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; and the largest social organization in interwar Lithuania was the League for the Liberation of Vilnius (Vilniaus vadavimo sąjunga, or VVS),&lt;ref name=&quot;MacQueen_context&quot;/&gt; with some 25,000 members.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; Passionate feelings about Vilnius were expressed in a popular slogan &quot;Mes be Vilniaus nenurimsim&quot; (we will not rest without Vilnius),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Alfred Erich |last=Senn |title= Lithuania 1940: Revolution from Above | pages=52 | publisher=Rodopi | year=2007 | url= https://books.google.com/?id=prqkNTCqa9cC&amp;pg=PA52 |isbn= 90-420-2225-6| accessdate= June 16, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; part of a poem by Petras Vaičiūnas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Alexandra |last=Ashbourne |title= Lithuania: The Rebirth of a Nation, 1991–1994 |pages=16 |year=1999 |publisher=Lexington Books |url= https://books.google.com/?id=yFoDJUq4qjQC&amp;pg=PA16 | isbn=0-7391-0027-0 | accessdate= June 16, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; While [[Paul Hymans]]' regional peace plans at the League of Nations were under negotiation, Lithuanian Prime Minister [[Ernestas Galvanauskas]] barely survived an assassination attempt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Eidintas | first=Alfonsas |author2=Vytautas Žalys|author3=Alfred Erich Senn | editor=Ed. Edvardas Tuskenis | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback |date=September 1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3 | pages=83–84}}&lt;/ref&gt; A government decision to open over 80 Polish schools in Lithuania was a probable factor in the [[1926 Lithuanian coup d'état]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Gerutis | first=Albertas | editor=Ed. Albertas Gerutis | translator=Algirdas Budreckis | title=Lithuania: 700 Years | year=1984 | edition=6th | publisher=Manyland Books | location=New York | id={{LCC | 75-80057}} |isbn=0-87141-028-1 | pages=219 | chapter=Independent Lithuania}}&lt;/ref&gt; Any government making concessions to Poland at that time risked an ouster.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The New York Times | title=Poland Ready for Action |first=Jerzy |last=Shapiro |date=1938-03-19 |pages=1–2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

President Smetona received memoranda from nine nationalistic organizations urging the government to reject the ultimatum.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; However, a decisive comment was made by General [[Stasys Raštikis]], the commander of the Lithuanian army: He testified that a military victory over Poland was impossible and argued for a peaceful resolution.&lt;ref name=eidintas/&gt; The government's decision was confirmed by the [[Fourth Seimas]] with minimal discussion.&lt;ref name=ist/&gt; On March 19, Dailidė relayed acceptance of the ultimatum to the Poles, who gave a 12-hour extension to decide on the ultimatum as a show of good faith.&lt;ref name=nyt/&gt;

== Aftermath ==
The ultimatum contributed to the general atmosphere of tension and fear in Europe. It relieved some of the pressure on Germany that had arisen in the aftermath of the Anschluss and tested the Soviets' willingness to defend their interests in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref name=nytaf&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The New York Times |title= Nazis are Pleased with Polish &quot;Peace&quot; |date=1939-03-20 |pages=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fears were expressed, both in Lithuania and abroad, that the establishment of diplomatic relations was not the only goal of Warsaw and that more far-reaching ultimata might follow.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The New York Times |date=1939-03-20 |first=Clarence K. |last=Streit |title=Geneva's Anxiety on Poles Persists |pages=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; Speculations arose that Poland might seek to resurrect the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]], using Germany's annexation of Austria as a precedent.&lt;ref name=nytaf/&gt; Poland announced that it planned to create a neutral bloc comprising Poland, Lithuania, [[Latvia]], Estonia, and [[Romania]] to counter both fascism and communism. It stated that it had no wish to incorporate Lithuanian territories and maintained that the bloc would be formed on the basis of bilateral non-aggression and economic treaties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=The New York Times |title=Envoy Says Poland Plans Neutral Bloc |date=1939-03-22 |pages=1, 12}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''[[The New York Times]]'', the impact of the ultimatum was felt on [[Wall Street]]; on March 17, the foreign currency and bond markets sagged, in some cases reaching the lowest points seen in several years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | journal=The New York Times |date=1939-03-18 |title=Wall St. Reflects Turmoil in Europe |pages=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; These markets recovered on March 19, after the ultimatum was accepted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| journal=The New York Times | title=Bond Prices Rise on a Broad Front |date=1939-03-20 |pages=52}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The acceptance triggered a government crisis in Lithuania: on March 24, Prime Minister [[Juozas Tūbelis]], who held uncompromising positions over Vilnius and at the time of the ultimatum was undergoing medical treatment in Switzerland, stepped down.&lt;ref name=ist&gt;{{cite book |title=Lietuvos istorija 11–12 klasėms | first=Rūstis |last=Kamuntavičius |author2=Vaida Kamuntavičienė|author3=Remigijus Civinskas|author4=Kastytis Antanaitis |year=2001 |publisher=Vaga |location=Vilnius |isbn=5-415-01502-7 |pages=302–303|language=lt}}&lt;/ref&gt; His successor, [[Vladas Mironas]], who was in favor of normalizing relations with Poland, assembled a new cabinet of ministers. Despite increasing pressure to form a broader coalition, the new cabinet was composed solely of members of the [[Lithuanian Nationalists Union]]. The unconditional acceptance hurt Lithuanian pride and damaged the reputation of the party.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; The suppressed opposition used this damage as an opportunity to renew its activities and formed a group called ''Ašis'' (Axis).&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; In Poland the acceptance was greeted with enthusiasm, described as a &quot;great bloodless victory&quot;,&lt;ref name=nytpl&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The New York Times |first=Jerzy |last=Shapiro |title=Warsaw, Pleased with Results, Now Would Form a Baltic Entente |date=1939-03-20 |pages= 1, 33}}&lt;/ref&gt; and celebrated by a military march in Vilnius.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The New York Times |first=Jerzy |last=Shapiro |title=Poland Calls Back Army on Frontier; Talks Will Begin |date=1939-03-21 |pages=1, 4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A few days after the ultimatum, both Lithuania and Poland named their ambassadors. [[Kazys Škirpa]] was sent to Warsaw, and [[Franciszek Charwat]] was sent to Kaunas before March 31, the deadline indicated in the ultimatum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=New York Times |date=1939-04-01 |title=Poland Welcomes Envoy |pages=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Negotiations over practical matters began on March 25, in [[Augustów]], and by June three agreements covering rail transit, mail service, and river navigation had been concluded.&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; The railroad, torn apart for several kilometers at the border, was repaired. A customs post was established in [[Vievis]], and consulates were opened in [[Klaipėda]] and Vilnius. Lithuania closed the League for the Liberation of Vilnius and the Vilnius Foundation; the latter organization had given financial support to Lithuanian activities in the Vilnius Region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Eidintas | first=Alfonsas |author2=Vytautas Žalys|author3=Alfred Erich Senn | editor=Ed. Edvardas Tuskenis | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback |date=September 1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3 | pages=178}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Lithuania continued to claim Vilnius as its ''de jure'' capital. In May 1938 [[Lithuanian Constitution of 1938|a new constitution]] was adopted, which echoed the previous constitution's statement that Vilnius was the permanent capital of Lithuania and that Kaunas was merely a [[Temporary capital of Lithuania|temporary capital]].&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; Poland continued to suppress Lithuanian organizations in Vilnius.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt;&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt;

A thaw in Polish–Lithuanian relations began in spring 1939. After the [[German occupation of Czechoslovakia|German–Czech]] and [[1939 German ultimatum to Lithuania|German–Lithuanian crises]], Poland made more active efforts to ensure Lithuania's assistance, or at least neutrality, in the event of a war with Nazi Germany.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; Lithuanian General Stasys Raštikis and Polish Foreign Minister Józef Beck made high-profile visits to each other's countries,&lt;ref name=vitas/&gt; and Poland improved the conditions of Lithuanians in the Vilnius Region.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt; However, Lithuania did not believe that Poland and its western allies were strong enough to resist Germany and the Soviet Union. When [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|Germany invaded Poland]] in September 1939, Lithuania maintained a policy of strict neutrality, refusing repeated German offers for a joint attack on Poland to capture Vilnius.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Eidintas | first=Alfonsas |author2=Vytautas Žalys|author3=Alfred Erich Senn | editor=Ed. Edvardas Tuskenis | title=Lithuania in European Politics: The Years of the First Republic, 1918–1940 | edition=Paperback |date=September 1999 | publisher=St. Martin's Press | location=New York | isbn=0-312-22458-3 | pages=168}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, Lithuania interned about 15,000 Polish soldiers and accepted about 35,000 Polish civilian refugees.&lt;ref name=cd118/&gt;  The Soviet Union returned Vilnius to Lithuania after the Soviet invasion of Eastern Poland in September 1939.&lt;ref&gt;J.Lee Ready (1995), ''World War Two. Nation by Nation'', London, Cassell, page 191. ISBN 1-85409-290-1&lt;/ref&gt;  Neither country was aware at the time of the secret protocols of the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]], signed in August 1939, in which Germany and the Soviet Union agreed to divide the region into their spheres of influence.  In June 1940, the Soviet Union [[military occupation|occupied]] and [[annexation|annexed]] Lithuania in accordance with the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]].&lt;ref&gt;I. Žiemele. Baltic Yearbook of International Law, 2001. 2002, Vol.1 p.10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;K. Dawisha, B. Parrott. The Consolidation of Democracy in East-Central Europe. 1997 p. 293.&lt;/ref&gt; A year later [[Operation Barbarossa|Russia was attacked]] by [[Nazi Germany]] leading to the [[Occupation of Lithuania by Nazi Germany|Nazi occupation of Lithuania]].

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=note}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite journal |first=George |last=Sakwa |title=The Polish Ultimatum to Lithuania in March 1939 |journal=Slavonic and East European Review |volume=55 |issue=2 |year=1977 |pages=204–26}}

{{Ultimatums presented to Lithuania}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:1938 Polish Ultimatum To Lithuania}}
[[Category:1938 in Lithuania|Polish]]
[[Category:1938 in Poland|Polish Ultimatum To Lithuania, 1938]]
[[Category:Ultimata]]
[[Category:History of Lithuania (1918–40)]]
[[Category:History of Poland (1918–39)]]
[[Category:Lithuania–Poland relations]]
[[Category:Diplomatic incidents]]
[[Category:1938 in international relations]]</text>
      <sha1>11tjpzu53ygilskzq1n3kjwpocqz64v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
