<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Action of 7 May 1794</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25909717</id>
    <revision>
      <id>652099667</id>
      <parentid>652099615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-03-19T17:10:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acad Ronin</username>
        <id>70274</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11389">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 7 May 1794
|partof=the [[French Revolutionary Wars]]
|image=
|caption=
|date=5 May 1794
|place=[[Western Approaches]], [[Atlantic Ocean]]
|result=British victory
|combatant1= {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Great Britain}}
|combatant2={{flagicon|France}} [[First French Republic|French Republic]]
|commander1=Captain [[Charles Boyles]]
|commander2=Captain [[Charles Linois]]
|strength1=[[Ships of the line]] [[HMS Swiftsure (1787)|HMS ''Swiftsure'']] and [[HMS St Albans (1764)|HMS ''St Albans'']]
|strength2=[[Frigate]] [[French frigate Atalante (1768)|''Atalante'']] and [[corvette]] [[French corvette Levrette (1799)|''Levrette'']]
|casualties1=1 killed
|casualties2=10 killed, 32 wounded, ''Atalante'' captured
}}
{{Campaignbox Atlantic campaign of May 1794}}
The '''Action of 7 May 1794''' was a minor naval action fought between a British [[ship of the line]] and a French [[frigate]] early in the [[French Revolutionary Wars]]. The [[French Navy]] sought to disrupt British trade by intercepting and capturing merchant ships with roving [[frigates]], a strategy countered by protecting British convoys with heavier warships, particularly in European waters. On 5 May 1794, the British escorts of a convoy from [[Cork (city)|Cork]] sighted two French ships approaching and gave chase. The ships, a [[sailing frigate|frigate]] and a [[corvette]], outmatched by their opponents, separated and the convoy escorts did likewise, each following one of the raiders on a separate course.

By the evening one of the French ships had successfully escaped, but the other was still under pursuit, Captain [[Charles-Alexandre Léon Durand Linois|Charles Linois]] of [[French frigate Atalante (1768)|''Atalante'']] attempting a number of tactics to drive off his opponent but without success. Eventually, after a chase lasting nearly two days, the French ship came within range of the much larger British [[Seventy-four (ship)|74-gun]] [[third rate]] [[HMS Swiftsure (1787)|HMS ''Swiftsure'']] and despite a brave defence was soon forced to surrender after suffering more than 40 casualties. Although he had surrendered his ship, Linois was widely praised for his actions in defending his ship against such heavy odds.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Linois would later receive extensive criticism for his lack of aggressiveness at the [[Battle of Pulo Auro]] when a fleet of [[East Indiaman|East Indiamen]] would bluff him into breaking off his attack.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the aftermath of the engagement, a French battle squadron that formed part of the developing [[Atlantic campaign of May 1794]] pursued both ships for the rest of the day; their quarry eventually escaped after dark. ''Atalante'' was later taken into the Royal Navy as HMS ''Espion''.

==Background==
The outbreak of war between Britain and France in the spring of 1793 came at a time of differing fortunes for the navies of the two countries. The [[Royal Navy]] had been at a state of heightened readiness since 1792 in preparation for the conflict, while the [[French Navy]] had still not recovered from the upheavals of the [[French Revolution]], which had resulted in the collapse of the naval hierarchy and a dearth of experienced officers and seamen.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW19&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; French naval strategy early in the war was to send squadrons and light vessels to operate along British trade routes, in order to disrupt British mercantile operations. This resulted in Britain forming its merchant ships into convoys for mutual protection, escorted by warships while in European waters to defend against roving attacks by French ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW8&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

By the spring of 1794, France was in turmoil following the failure of the harvest, which threatened the country with starvation. In order to secure food supplies, France turned to its American colonies and the [[United States]], which assembled a large grain convoy in [[Hampton Roads]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NM132&quot;&gt;Mostert, p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; To ensure the security of this convoy, the French Navy dispatched most of its Atlantic Fleet to sea during [[Atlantic campaign of May 1794|May 1794]], operating in a series of large squadrons, independent cruisers and one major fleet under [[Villaret de Joyeuse]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NM133&quot;&gt;Mostert, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 May, two French ships operating independently, the 36-gun frigate ''Atalante'' under Captain Charles Linois and the corvette [[French corvette Levrette (1799)|''Levrette'']], spied a British convoy sailing south-west, three days out from [[Cork (city)|Cork]], and closed to investigate.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW41&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pursuit==
The convoy that Linois had sighted was under the protection of two [[ships of the line]], the ''Swiftsure'' under Captain [[Charles Boyles]] and the 64-gun [[HMS St Albans (1764)|HMS ''St Albans'']] under Captain [[James Vashon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WLC484&quot;&gt;Clowes, p. 484&lt;/ref&gt;  At 17:45, with the French frigates closing from the west and aware that they could not defend the whole convoy without immediate direct action, Boyles turned ''Swiftsure'' and ''St Albans'' towards the newcomers, hoisting their colours and ''Swiftsure'' firing three shots in the direction of the larger ship, ''Atalante''. Together the British ships hugely outweighed and outmatched the French vessels, and as soon as Linois realised his mistake he gave orders for his ships to turn and make all sail to escape pursuit, raising the [[French tricolour]] and firing his stern-chasers, guns fitted in the rear of the ship, at his pursuers.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ204&quot;&gt;James, p. 204&lt;/ref&gt;

The French ships immediately separated. ''St Albans'' then followed ''Levrette'' while ''Swiftsure'' concentrated on ''Atalante''.  Throughout the rest of the evening the two chases continued. Then after darkness fell ''Levrette'' was able to outrun and escape from ''St Albans''.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW41&quot;/&gt; ''Swiftsure'' however remained in touch with ''Atalante'' so that by 04:00 on 6 May the French frigate was approximately {{convert|2.5|nmi|km}} ahead of the ship of the line to the northwest, with the wind direction to the north-northeast. For the entire following day Linois could not escape Boyles' pursuit, and at 17:30 ''Swiftsure'' was close enough to open fire again, using the bow-chasers for an hour and a half until ''Atalante'' once more pulled out of range.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW41&quot;/&gt; During the evening the French frigate was able to keep {{convert|2|nmi|km}} in front of ''Swiftsure'', but at midnight Linois switched his course to the south, hoping that the darkness would cloak the manoeuvre and that ''Atlante'' would be able to escape Boyles.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ205&quot;&gt;James, p. 205&lt;/ref&gt;

At 02:00 it became clear that Linois's ploy had failed and that ''Swiftsure'' was still following ''Atalante''. More importantly, the manoeuvre had severely slowed the frigate. Although Linois hauled closer to the wind, Boyles was able to come within range at 02:30, firing his [[starboard]] guns into the smaller ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ205&quot;/&gt; Although his crew were exhausted by the extended chase Linois returned fire, the warships exchanging shot at long-range and the frigate suffering far more serious damage during the brief engagement.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW485&quot;&gt;Clowes, p. 485&lt;/ref&gt;  By 03:25 Linois was forced to surrender, his ship's rigging in tatters and casualties mounting among his crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW42&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 42&lt;/ref&gt;  Boyles then provided a prize crew to the frigate and took most of the surviving French crew aboard his own ship as [[prisoners of war]]. Casualties on the French ship were heavy, with ten killed and 32 wounded from the 274 men aboard, compared to a single man lost on ''Swiftsure'', which had also suffered some damage to its rigging.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG1&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
Boyles was not long able to enjoy his victory undisturbed: at 10:00 on 7 May, shortly after the removal of the French prisoners had been completed, sails were spotted on the horizon. These were rapidly identified as three French ships of the line that were making all haste to intercept and capture ''Swiftsure'' and ''Atalante''. These ships were part of a squadron under Contre-Admiral [[Joseph-Marie Nielly]] that had sailed from [[Rochefort, Charente-Maritime|Rochefort]] the day before in search of the American grain convoy shortly due in European waters.&lt;ref name=&quot;NM133&quot;/&gt; Issuing rapid orders, Boyles instructed ''Atalante''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s prize crew to separate their ship from ''Swiftsure'' in order to force the French to split their forces; the frigate and the ship of the line fleeing on different courses. ''Atalante'' soon outran pursuit and escaped into the Atlantic, the prize crew even managing to replace the damaged main topsail in the midst of the chase with the assistance of the French prisoners on board. ''Swiftsure'' was slower but Boyles was still able to increase the distance between his vessel and the French during the day, finally losing sight of his pursuers at 22:00.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW42&quot;/&gt;

Both ships arrived safely at [[Cork (city)|Cork]] on 17 May, Rear-Admiral [[Sir Robert Kingsmill, 1st Baronet|Robert Kingsmill]] informing the [[Admiralty]] of the action by letter.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG1&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=13659|startpage=463|date=21 May 1794}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Atalante'' subsequently served the Royal Navy as a 36-gun frigate under the name HMS ''Espion'' as there was already a ship named [[HMS Atalanta (1775)|HMS ''Atalanta'']] in service.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW485&quot; /&gt; For his lengthy and brave resistance, Linois was highly praised, particularly by the historian [[William James (naval historian)|William James]], who wrote in 1827 that Linois' &quot;endeavours . . . were highly meritorious&quot; and considered that in an engagement against a British frigate &quot;the Atalante, if conquered at all, would have been dearly purchased.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ205&quot;/&gt; Shortly after his arrival in Britain, Linois was [[prisoner exchange|exchanged]] and returned to France.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW42&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=Note}}
;Citations
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
;Bibliography

==References==
*{{cite book
 | last = Clowes
 | first = William Laird
 | authorlink = William Laird Clowes
 | year = 1997 |origyear=1900
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Royal Navy, A History from the Earliest Times to 1900, Volume IV
 | publisher = Chatham Publishing
 | location = London
 | isbn = 1-86176-013-2
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = James
 | first = William
 | authorlink = William James (naval historian)
 | year = 2002 |origyear=1827
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Naval History of Great Britain, Volume 1, 1793&amp;ndash;1796
 | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
 | location = London
 | isbn = 0-85177-905-0
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Mostert
 | first = Noel
 | authorlink = 
 | year = 2007
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Line upon a Wind: The Greatest War Fought at Sea Under Sail 1793 &amp;ndash; 1815
 | publisher = Vintage Books
 | location = London
 | isbn = 978-0-7126-0927-2
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Woodman
 | first = Richard
 | authorlink = Richard Woodman
 | year = 2001
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Sea Warriors
 | publisher = Constable Publishers
 | location = London
 | isbn = 1-84119-183-3
}}

{{coord missing|Atlantic Ocean}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1794]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving France]]
[[Category:Naval battles of the French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving Great Britain]]</text>
      <sha1>1hey0mlmn9fptk4oza3t9ar3geaxqby</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
