<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Action of 15 November 1810</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45322073</id>
    <revision>
      <id>695749634</id>
      <parentid>660709427</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-12-18T08:43:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (11757)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11956">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 15 November 1810
|partof=the [[Napoleonic Wars]]
|image=&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative&quot;&gt;[[File:Basse-Normandie region location map.svg|250px]]{{Image label|x=0.358|y=0.072|scale=250|text=[[Image:Red pog.svg|8px|Action]]}}&lt;/div&gt;
|caption=Map of [[Lower Normandy]]&lt;br/&gt;Location of the destruction of ''Elisa''
|date=12&amp;ndash;16 November 1810
|place=[[Baie de la Seine]], [[English Channel]]
|result=British victory
|combatant1={{flagcountry|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2={{flagicon|France}} [[First French Empire|French Empire]]
|commander1=[[Pulteney Malcolm]]
|commander2=[[Bernard-Louis Rosseau]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Louis-Henri Fraycinet-Saulce]]
|strength1=[[Ships of the line]] [[HMS Donegal (1798)|HMS ''Donegal'']], [[HMS Revenge (1805)|HMS ''Revenge'']] [[frigate]] [[HMS Diana (1794)|HMS ''Diana'']], [[HMS Niobe (1800)|HMS ''Niobe'']]
|strength2=[[frigates]] [[French frigate Elisa (1808)|''Elisa'']] and [[French frigate Amazone (1807)|''Amazone'']]
|casualties1=Two killed, nine wounded
|casualties2=1 killed,&lt;br/&gt;''Elisa'' later destroyed
|campaignbox=
}}{{Coord|49|35|20|N|1|15|30|W|type:event|display=title}}

The '''Action of 15 November 1810''' was a minor naval engagement fought during the British [[Royal Navy]] [[blockade]] of the French [[English Channel|Channel]] ports in the [[Napoleonic Wars]]. British dominance at sea, enforced by a strategy of close blockade, made it difficult for the [[French Navy]] to operate even in their own territorial waters. In the autumn of 1810, a British squadron assigned to patrol the [[Baie de la Seine]] was effectively isolating two French squadrons in the ports of [[Le Havre]] and [[Cherbourg]]. On 12 November, the squadron in Le Havre, consisting of [[frigates]] [[French frigate Elisa (1808)|''Elisa'']] and [[French frigate Amazone (1807)|''Amazone'']] attempted to reach Cherbourg at night in order to united the squadrons. This squadron was spotted  in the early hours of 13 November by the patrolling British frigates [[HMS Diana (1794)|HMS ''Diana'']] and [[HMS Niobe (1800)|HMS ''Niobe'']], which gave chase.

The French ships took shelter at the heavily fortified [[Iles Saint-Marcouf]], sailing the following morning for the anchorage at [[Saint-Vaast-la-Hougue]]. For two days the British frigates kept watch, until two [[ships of the line]] from the blockade of Cherbourg, [[HMS Donegal (1798)|HMS ''Donegal'']] and [[HMS Revenge (1805)|HMS ''Revenge'']], arrived. On 15 November, the British squadron attacked the anchored French ships, which were defended by [[shore batteries]] at La Hougue and [[Tatihou]]. After four attempts to close with the French the British squadron, under heavy fire, withdrew. During the night, the British commander, Captain [[Pulteney Malcolm]], sent his [[ship's boat]]s close inshore to attack the French ships with [[Congreve rocket]]s, a newly issued weapon. None are recorded as landing on target, but by morning both frigates had been forced to change position, becoming grounded on the shore. The French ships were later refloated, and Malcolm's squadron maintained the blockade until 27 November when ''Amazone'' successfully escaped back to Le Havre. The damaged ''Elisa'' remained at anchor until 6 December, when an attack by a British [[bomb vessel]] forced the frigate to move further inshore, becoming grounded once more. ''Elisa'' remained in this position until 23 December, when the boats of ''Diana'' entered the anchorage at night and set the beached ship on fire, destroying her.

==Baie de la Seine in 1810==
By 1810 the [[French Navy]] fleet based in the Atlantic ports had been prevented from launching any major operations for four years, penned into harbour by the British strategy of close [[blockade]]. A failed attempt by a French fleet to sail had been defeated at the [[Battle of Basque Roads]] in 1809, and the main operations still carried out by the Navy were undertaken by [[privateers]] and [[frigate]] squadrons operating commerce raiders operating from smaller ports, such as those on the [[English Channel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RG111&quot;&gt;Gardiner, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1810 squadrons were based at [[Cherbourg]], with two [[ships of the line]] and the newly built frigate [[French frigate Iphigénie (1810)|''Iphigénie'']], and [[Le Havre]], with the frigates [[French frigate Elisa (1808)|''Elisa'']] and [[French frigate Amazone (1807)|''Amazone'']], commanded by Captains [[Louis-Henri Fraycinet-Saulce]] and [[Bernard-Louis Rosseau]] respectively. To blockade these squadrons, the [[Royal Navy]]'s [[Channel Fleet]] had assigned the ships of the line [[HMS Donegal (1798)|HMS ''Donegal'']] under Captain [[Pulteney Malcolm]] and [[HMS Revenge (1805)|HMS ''Revenge'']] under Captain [[Charles Paget (Royal Navy officer)|Charles Paget]] to patrol the entrance to Cherbourg, while frigates [[HMS Diana (1794)|HMS ''Diana'']] under Captain [[Charles Grant (Royal Navy officer)|Charles Grant]] and [[HMS Niobe (1800)|HMS ''Niobe'']] under Captain [[John Wentworth Loring]] kept watch on Le Havre.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ239&quot;&gt;James, p. 239&lt;/ref&gt; The blockade had achieved some minor successes; in October 1810 ''Revenge'' had captured the privateer ''Vengeur'' from [[Dieppe]],&lt;ref name=&quot;LG5&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16415|startpage=1638|endpage=|date=16 October 1810}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on 6 November ''Donegal'' ran down and seized the privateer ''Surcouf'' from Cherbourg.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG6&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16422|startpage=1765|endpage=|date=6 November 1810}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pursuit of ''Amazone'' and ''Elisa''===
At 22:00 on 12 November ''Amazone'' and ''Elisa'' sailed from Le Havre to unite with the force at Cherbourg, hoping to evade the blockade in the darkness. They successfully passed the patrolling ''Diana'' and ''Niobe'' but were spotted sailing northwest at 00:30 by the British ships which gave chase, ''Niobe'' turning inshore in an attempt to cut off the French line of advance.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG1&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16426|startpage=1840|endpage=1841|date=17 November 1810}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the wind in the northeast, the French frigates were unable to pass [[Cape Barfleur]] under pursuit, and Rosseau instead turned his squadron towards the [[Iles Saint-Marcouf]] at 04:00, using superior local knowledge to bypass the pursuing British ships. The heavily fortified islands had been under British control during the [[French Revolutionary Wars]], but reverted to the French at the [[Peace of Amiens]] in 1802. ''Diana'' and ''Niobe'' attempted to intercept the French frigates before they came under the shelter of the guns, but were only able to fire two long-distance [[broadside]]s at the trailing ''Elisa''.&lt;ref name=&quot;WLC474&quot;&gt;Clowes, p. 474&lt;/ref&gt;

At 11:00, Rosseau gave orders for the French frigates to sail once more, slipping away from the British ships which had drifted to the north and anchoring safely between the [[gun battery|batteries]] at [[Saint-Vaast-la-Hougue]] and the island of [[Tatihou]]. Observing the strong position the French frigates had taken up, Grant sent messages to Malcolm's force at Cherbourg requesting reinforcements. Malcolm brought ''Donegal'' and ''Revenge'' to support the frigates on 14 November, maintaining position off the anchorage despite a strong [[gale]] which caused ''Elisa'' to drag her anchors.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ240&quot;&gt;James, p. 240&lt;/ref&gt; Captain Fraycinet-Saulce was forced to throw much of the ship's stores overboard to prevent his frigate from being wrecked on the shore. The following day, ''Diana'' took advantage of the rising tide to attack the anchored ''Amazone'', Captain Rosseau withdrawing deeper into the sheltered anchorage under protection from the batteries. Twice more Grant launched probing attacks on the French frigate, each time beaten off by heavy fire from the batteries. Joined by Malcolm and the remainder of the British force, four successive attacks were launched against ''Amazone'', each one driven back by [[cannon]] fire. At 13:00, with the tide falling, the British squadron was compelled to retreat to deeper water, out of range of the French. All four British ships had suffered under fire, with two killed and five wounded on ''Revenge'', three wounded on ''Donegal'' and one wounded on ''Diana''. French losses were a single man killed on ''Amazone''.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG1&quot;/&gt;

On the evening of 15 November Malcolm ordered the [[ship's boat]]s of the squadron to approach the anchorage under cover of darkness, commanded by Lieutenant Joseph Needham Taylor. The boats had been equipped with [[Congreve rocket]]s, a recently invented artillery system which was not then widely in use by the Royal Navy. None of the rockets fired during the night appeared to have hit their targets, but they seem to have panicked the French crews; dawn the following morning revealed that both frigates had cut their anchors and drifted onto the shore, ''Elisa'' in particular had struck hard and heeled over onto her side. Both ships were however  successfully refloated by the rising tide on 16 November, and the situation reached an impasse, with Malcolm's forces blockading Saint-Vaast-la-Hougue to prevent the French from sailing.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ241&quot;/&gt;

===Destruction of ''Elisa''===
For nearly two weeks the French frigates remained at anchor, Malcolm and Grant drawing up plans for an attack with [[fireships]], when ''Amazone'' successfully slipped out of harbour on 27 November, returning successfully to Le Havre before dawn the following day. With ''Amazone'' gone, Grant maintained a closer watch on ''Elisa'', calling up a [[bomb vessel]] to attack the anchorage on 6 December. This proved no more accurate than the rockets, but ''Elisa'' was again driven into shallow waters to avoid the attack, this time becoming irretrievably grounded on a shoal.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ241&quot;&gt;James, p. 241&lt;/ref&gt; Over the next two weeks ''Elisa'' remained grounded, the frigate gradually being reduced to the state of a total wreck. On 23 December Grant sent his boats, commanded by Lieutenant Thomas Rowe, into the anchorage under cover of darkness and set the wreck on fire to ensure that the frigate's stores could not be salvaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG2&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=16438|startpage=2061|endpage=|date=25 December 1810}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the destruction of ''Elisa'', the British squadrons returned to their blockade duties off Cherbourg and Le Havre. The blockade remained in place throughout the remainder of the Napoleonic Wars; Rosseau in ''Amazone'' made another attempt to join the squadron in Cherbourg in March 1811, only to be [[Action of 24 March 1811|run down and destroyed]] by a squadron led by the ship of the line [[HMS Berwick (1809)|HMS ''Berwick'']].&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ332&quot;&gt;James, p. 332&lt;/ref&gt; The new ''Iphigénie'' survived a little longer, being intercepted and captured in the Atlantic during a raiding mission in January 1814.&lt;ref name=&quot;WLC544&quot;&gt;Clowes, p. 544&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== References ==
* {{cite book
 | last = Clowes
 | first = William Laird
 | authorlink = William Laird Clowes
 | year = 1997 |origyear=1900
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Royal Navy, A History from the Earliest Times to 1900, Volume V
 | publisher = Chatham Publishing
 | location = 
 | isbn = 1-86176-014-0
}}
* {{cite book
 | last =  Gardiner (ed.)
 | first = Robert
 | authorlink = 
 | year = 2001 |origyear=1998
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Victory of Seapower
 | publisher = Caxton Editions
 | location = 
 | isbn = 1-84067-359-1
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = James
 | first = William
 | authorlink = William James (naval historian)
 | year = 2002
 | origyear= 1827
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Naval History of Great Britain, Volume 5, 1808&amp;ndash;1811
 | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
 | location = London
 | isbn = 0-85177-909-3
}}

[[Category:Naval battles involving France]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Naval battles of the Napoleonic Wars]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1810]]</text>
      <sha1>svhat7qaol6dibbjqoveboy5z617wj0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
