<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Pakchon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7690881</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740298064</id>
      <parentid>738150078</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-20T05:53:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anotherclown</username>
        <id>8567476</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */ &quot;Allen and Unwin&quot; → &quot;Allen &amp; Unwin&quot; per article on publisher</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="62588">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict   	= Battle of Pakchon
| partof     	= the [[Korean War]]
| image      	= [[File:Map Chinese intervention.jpg|300px|alt=A map with arrows sweeping past Northwest Korea]]
| caption	= Chinese First Phase Offensive, 25 October&amp;nbsp;– 1 November 1950
| date       	= 5 November 1950
| place      	= [[Pakchon]], [[North Korea]]
| result     	= United Nations victory
| combatant1 	={{flag|United Nations}}
*{{flag|Australia}}
*{{flag|United Kingdom}}
*{{flag|United States|1912}}
| combatant2 	= {{flagicon|People's Republic of China}} [[China]]&lt;br&gt;{{flag|North Korea}}
| commander1 	= {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Basil Aubrey Coad]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Australia}} Floyd Walsh&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} Howard M. Moore
| commander2 	= {{flagicon|People's Republic of China}} Wu Xinquan&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|People's Republic of China}} Zhang Jiecheng&lt;ref name=ha5&gt;{{harvnb|Hu|Ma|1987|p=5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
| units1  	= {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[27th British Commonwealth Brigade|27th Brit Com Bde]]
*{{flagicon|Australia}} [[3rd Battalion, Royal Australian Regiment|3 RAR]]
*{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders|1 ASHR]]
*{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Middlesex Regiment|1 MR]]
| units2   	= {{flagicon|People's Republic of China}} [[117th Division (People's Republic of China)|117th Division]]&lt;ref name=cmsa38&gt;{{harvnb|Chinese Military Science Academy|2000|p=38}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength1	=~300 men
| strength2	=~1,500 men
| casualties1 	= 14 killed&lt;br&gt;84 wounded
| casualties2 	= 270 killed&lt;br&gt;200 wounded&lt;br&gt;(estimated)
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Korean War}}
}}

The '''Battle of Pakchon''' (5 November 1950), also known as the '''Battle of Bochuan''' ({{zh|s=博川战斗|p=Bó Chuān Zhàn Dòu}}), took place ten days after the start of the Chinese [[Korean War#China intervenes (October&amp;nbsp;– December 1950)|First Phase Offensive]], following the entry of the [[People's Volunteer Army]] into the [[Korean War]]. The offensive reversed the United Nations (UN) advance towards the [[Yalu River]] which had occurred after their intervention in the wake of the [[North Korea]]n invasion of [[South Korea]] at the start of the war. The battle was fought between British and Australian forces from the [[27th British Commonwealth Brigade]] with American armour and artillery in support, and the Chinese [[117th Division (People's Republic of China)|117th Division]], around the village of [[Pakchon]] on the [[Taeryong River]]. After [[Battle of Chongju (1950)|capturing Chongju]] on 30 October the British and Australians had been ordered to pull back to Pakchon in an attempt to consolidate the western flank of the [[US Eighth Army]]. Meanwhile, immediately following their [[Battle of Unsan|success at Unsan]] against the Americans, the Chinese 117th Division of the [[39th Army (People's Republic of China)|39th Army]] had attacked southward, intending to cut off the UN forces as they withdrew in the face of the unexpected Chinese assault. To halt the Chinese advance, the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade was ordered to defend the lower crossings of the Taeryong and [[Ch'ongch'on River|Chongchon]] rivers as part of a rearguard, in conjunction with the [[24th Infantry Division (United States)|US 24th Infantry Division]] further upstream on the right.

During the night of 4/5 November, the Chinese and North Koreans mounted a full-scale assault on the US 24th Infantry Division, pushing back an American infantry regiment nearly {{convert|2|km|mi}}. The Chinese force subsequently turned west, advancing between the Taeryong and Chongchon rivers and threatening the rear of the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade by cutting the Pakchon–[[Sinanju]] road. The following day they attacked an American artillery battery which was guarding a vital concrete bridge near Kujin. The British and Australians then successfully [[Counterattack|counter-attacked]] the Chinese forces occupying a number of nearby ridgelines during the day but were in turn counter-attacked before being pushed off the high ground during the night. In their first battle with the Chinese, the [[3rd Battalion, Royal Australian Regiment]] (3 RAR) captured a well defended hill with only limited [[fire support|offensive support]], and held it in the face of heavy counter-attacks before confused command decisions resulted in a disorganised night withdrawal while still in contact. The withdrawal threatened to open the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade's left flank and the Australians were ordered to immediately reposition on the ridge, yet ultimately it was too late to regain the feature in darkness. However, following heavy fighting the pressure on the Australians unexpectedly ceased after midnight, and parties of Chinese were observed beginning to withdraw. By early morning the Chinese attack had been checked and 3 RAR had redeployed to new positions in the [[paddy field]]s around the railway crossing north of Maenjung-dong.

The fighting was costly for both sides. Although the Australians halted the advancing Chinese 117th Division and inflicted numerous casualties on them, they also suffered heavy losses. In the aftermath the inexperienced Australian battalion commander—Lieutenant Colonel Floyd Walsh—was relieved of his position by the British brigade commander, having taken over just six days earlier following the death of the previous commanding officer at [[Chongju, North Korea|Chongju]]. Nonetheless, the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade succeeded in preventing a Chinese break-through at Pakchon, keeping open vital withdrawal routes across the river and securing the UN left flank. Suffering significant casualties, the Chinese offensive was halted the next day due to logistic difficulties. The Chinese and North Koreans were temporarily forced to withdraw north, while the UN successfully reinforced its positions, holding on the Chongchon Line. Yet by late November the US Eighth Army was again forced to withdraw after the Chinese began their [[Korean War#China intervenes (October&amp;nbsp;– December 1950)|Second Phase Offensive]], starting a long retreat south. The UN forces were expelled from North Korea, and withdrew to the 38th Parallel where they sought to re-establish defensive positions.{{TOC limit|2}}

==Background==

===Military situation===
{{main|Korean War#The conflict begins (1950)|l1=Initial phase of the Korean War|Military history of Australia during the Korean War}}
The [[Korean War]] began early in the morning of 25 June 1950, following the surprise invasion of the [[Republic of Korea]] (ROK) by its northern neighbour, the communist [[Democratic People's Republic of Korea]] (DPRK).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|MacDonald|1986|p=30}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Numerically superior and better-equipped, the [[Korean People's Army]] (KPA) crossed the [[38th parallel north|38th Parallel]] and rapidly advanced south, easily overcoming the South Koreans. In response, the United Nations (UN) decided to intervene on behalf of South Korea, inviting member states to send forces to restore the situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dennis et al|2008|pp=300–302}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As a consequence, American ground forces were hastily deployed in an attempt to prevent the South Koreans from collapsing; however, they too were under-strength and poorly equipped, and by early August had been forced back by the North Koreans to an enclave around [[Pusan]], known as the [[Battle of the Pusan Perimeter|Pusan Perimeter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|MacDonald|1986|p=39}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Key US allies—Britain, Canada and Australia—also committed forces, although these were initially limited to naval contingents and were largely viewed as token efforts in the US. Under diplomatic pressure the British agreed to deploy an infantry [[brigade (military)|brigade]] in July, and would later dispatch a second brigade as the crisis worsened.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|MacDonald|1986|pp=39–40}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadians also agreed to provide an infantry brigade, although the first [[battalion]] would not arrive until December 1950.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Johnston|2003|p=55}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 21 UN member states eventually contributed forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=706}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Race to Yalu Map.gif|thumb|left|alt=A map showing a Peninsula with US forces moving from the south to the north|Map of the UN advance toward the [[Yalu River]], 1950.]]

Australia was one of the first nations to commit units to the fighting, playing a small but sometimes significant part in the [[United Nations Command]], which was initially led by [[General of the Army (United States)|General]] [[Douglas MacArthur]].&lt;ref name=Dennis302&gt;{{harvnb|Dennis et al|2008|p=302}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Forces deployed in Japan as part of the [[British Commonwealth Occupation Force]] (BCOF) formed the basis of the Australian response, with [[P-51 Mustang]] fighter-bombers from [[No. 77 Squadron RAAF]] flying their first missions on 2 July, while the frigate [[HMAS Shoalhaven (K535)|HMAS ''Shoalhaven'']] and the destroyer [[HMAS Bataan (I91)|HMAS ''Bataan'']] were also committed to naval operations. During this time the [[3rd Battalion, Royal Australian Regiment]] (3 RAR), which had been preparing to return to Australia prior to the outbreak of the war, remained in Japan, however on 26 July the Australian government announced that it would also commit the under-strength and poorly equipped infantry battalion to the fighting, following a period of preparation.&lt;ref name=Dennis302/&gt; Training and re-equipment began immediately, while hundreds of reinforcements were hastily recruited in Australia as part of [[K Force]]; they soon began arriving to fill out the battalion. The battalion's commanding officer, [[Lieutenant Colonel (Australia)|Lieutenant Colonel]] Floyd Walsh, was replaced by Lieutenant Colonel [[Charles Hercules Green|Charles Green]]. An officer with extensive operational experience fighting the Japanese in [[New Guinea campaign|New Guinea]] during the [[Second World War]], Green took over from Walsh due to the latter's perceived inexperience.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|p=3}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 September 1950, 3 RAR embarked for Korea, concentrating at Pusan on 28 September. There it joined the British [[27th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|27th Infantry Brigade]], a garrison formation hurriedly committed from [[Hong Kong]] by the British government as the situation deteriorated around the Pusan Perimeter in late August to bolster the [[Eighth Army (United States)|US Eighth Army]] under [[Lieutenant General (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[Walton Walker]].&lt;ref name=Breen8&gt;{{harvnb|Breen|1992|p=8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Commanded by [[Brigadier (United Kingdom)|Brigadier]] [[Basil Aubrey Coad|Basil Coad]], the brigade was renamed the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade and consisted of the [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders|1st Battalion, Argyll and Sutherland Highland Regiment]] (1 ASHR), the [[Middlesex Regiment|1st Battalion, Middlesex Regiment]] (1 MR) and 3 RAR. Under-strength, the two British battalions had each mustered just 600 men of all ranks, while the brigade was also short on transport and heavy equipment, and had no integral artillery support, for which it would rely entirely on the Americans until the [[16th Field Regiment, Royal New Zealand Artillery]] arrived in January 1951. As such, with a strength of nearly 1,000 men, the addition of 3 RAR gave the brigade increased tactical weight as well as expediently allowing the Australians to work within a familiar organisational environment, rather than being attached to a US formation.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Horner|2008|p=57}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time 3 RAR arrived in the theatre, the North Koreans had been broken and were in rapid retreat, with MacArthur's forces conducting a successful [[Battle of Inchon|amphibious assault at Inchon]] and breaking out along the Naktong perimeter on the southern tip of the Korean peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Horner|2008|p=58}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A steady advance began, driving the North Koreans northwards towards the 38th Parallel.&lt;ref name=Breen8/&gt; The 27th British Commonwealth Brigade was attached to the [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|US 1st Cavalry Division]], under the command of [[Major General (United States)|Major General]] [[Hobart R. Gay]]. On 16 October the brigade took over as the vanguard of the UN advance up the west coast. Although the North Koreans had suffered heavily in the preceding weeks, they continued to resist strongly.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Horner|2008|pp=58–61}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The 27th British Commonwealth Brigade moved {{convert|70|km|mi}} from [[Kumchon]], with the Argylls [[Battle of Sariwon|capturing Sariwon]] on 17 October, killing 215 North Koreans and taking many prisoners for the loss of one man killed and three wounded.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=257}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The British and Australians then passed to the command of the [[24th Infantry Division (United States)|US 24th Infantry Division]] on 21 October, under the overall command of Major General [[John H. Church]], while the US 1st Cavalry Division remained in Pyongyang to complete its capture.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=67}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade was ordered to seize [[Chongju, North Korea|Chongju]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|p=248}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The advance continued north with little respite, and on 22 October the Australians fought their first major action at [[Battle of Yongju|Yongju]], killing 150 North Koreans and capturing 239 of the brigade's 800 prisoners, for the loss of seven men wounded.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=258}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Intending to defeat the North Koreans and bring the war to a close, the UN forces pushed towards the [[Yalu River]], on the Chinese border.&lt;ref name=Coulthard259&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=259}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade crossed the [[Ch'ongch'on River|Chongchon River]], moving towards [[Pakchon]]. On 24 October, MacArthur had removed all restrictions on the movement of his forces south of the Yalu River and prepared for the final phase of the advance, defying a directive of the [[US Joint Chiefs of Staff]] and risking Chinese intervention in support of North Korea.&lt;ref name=Horner62&gt;{{harvnb|Horner|2008|p=62}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 October 3 RAR crossed the [[Taeryong River]].&lt;ref name=Horner62/&gt; The North Koreans attacked the forward Australian companies at [[Battle of Kujin|Kujin]] early the following morning, resulting in Australian losses of eight killed and 22 wounded. However, the North Koreans suffered heavy casualties including over 100 killed and 350 captured, and the Australians succeeded in defending the bridgehead after the North Koreans withdrew.&lt;ref name=Coulthard259/&gt; Intelligence indicated that the British and Australians were facing the North Korean 17th Tank Brigade, which was preparing a last line of defence at Chongju, {{convert|70|km|mi}} away.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=44}}.&lt;/ref&gt; With the war considered all but over the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade continued to pursue the North Koreans towards Chongju; however, the advance increasingly encountered strong resistance as they approached the [[China–North Korea border|Manchurian border]].&lt;ref name=Horner62/&gt;

==Prelude==

===Opposing forces===
[[File:Chinese troops crossing Amrokgang river.jpg|thumb|260px|right|alt=A long orderly line of heavily laden soldiers marching in pairs away from the camera down a road across an open expanse|Chinese forces cross the Yalu River.]]

3 RAR took over as lead battalion of the brigade on 29 October, {{convert|6|km|mi}} from Chongju. That morning a spotter aircraft reported a large North Korean formation consisting of a battalion-sized force of 500–600 infantry supported by several tanks and at least two [[Self-propelled artillery|self-propelled gun]]s, positioned on a thickly wooded ridgeline around Chongju.&lt;ref name=Odgers48&gt;{{harvnb|Odgers|2009|p=48}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Battle of Chongju (1950)|Battle of Chongju]] ensued as the Australians dislodged the strong North Korean armoured force and then defended their positions against North Korean [[counterattack|counter-attack]]s during the evening. The following day the Australians advanced to the high ground overlooking Chongju, killing and capturing a number of North Koreans in skirmishes. That afternoon the town itself was cleared by the remaining elements of the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade without opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|pp=259–260}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting around Chongju was the heaviest undertaken by the Australians since entering the war.&lt;ref name=Odgers48/&gt; North Korean casualties included 162 killed and 10 captured, while Australian losses were nine killed and 30 wounded, including Green, who was wounded in the stomach by artillery fire after the battle, succumbing to his wounds and dying two days later on 1 November.&lt;ref name=Coulthard260&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=260}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the capture of Chongju the US 21st Infantry Regiment had set off rapidly along the road to [[Sonchon]] to the west. Encountering only one strong North Korean position which they quickly turned, by noon on 1 November the lead battalion had reached Chonggodong, just {{convert|30|km|mi}} from the Yalu River where the Americans clashed with another North Korean armoured force. To the north meanwhile, the US 5th and 9th Infantry Regiments of the US 24th Infantry Division secured [[Taechon]] and [[Kusong]], before advancing to within {{convert|40|km|mi}} of the Manchurian border.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=50}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, during the last weeks of October the Chinese had moved 18 [[division (military)|division]]s of the [[People's Volunteer Army]] across the Yalu River under the overall command of Marshal [[Peng Dehuai]] in order to reinforce the remnants of the KPA. Undetected by US and South Korean intelligence, the 13th Army Group crossed the border on 16 October and penetrated up to {{convert|100|km|mi}} into North Korea, and were reinforced in early November by 12 divisions from the 9th Army Group; in total 30 divisions composed of 380,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|pp=55–56}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Chinese Military Science Academy |2000|p=90}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese ambushed MacArthur's forces which were now widely dispersed, decimating [[ROK II Corps]] at [[Battle of Onjong|Onjong]] and encircling and overrunning the [[8th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|US 8th Cavalry Regiment]] at [[Battle of Unsan|Unsan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fehrenbach|2000|p=196}}.&lt;/ref&gt; With the US 24th Infantry Division ordered back to the Chongchon River as a result, the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade also began moving south as part of the UN general withdrawal in the face of the Chinese [[Korean War#China intervenes (October&amp;nbsp;– December 1950)|First Phase Offensive]].&lt;ref name=Horner63/&gt;

Ultimately Chongju was the furthest north that the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade was to penetrate, and on 1 November, while still in divisional reserve, the brigade was ordered to pull back to Pakchon in an attempt to consolidate the western flank.&lt;ref name=Coulthard260/&gt;&lt;ref name=Horner63&gt;{{harvnb|Horner|2008|p=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; Immediately following their success at Unsan, the Chinese [[117th Division (People's Republic of China)|117th Division]] of the [[39th Army (People's Republic of China)|39th Army]]—under the overall command of Zhang Jiecheng—attacked southward, intending to cut off the retreating UN forces and in so doing eliminate the remnants of the ROK [[1st Infantry Division (South Korea)|1st Infantry Division]] and US 1st Cavalry Division by cutting the road junction at Pakchon.&lt;ref name=ha5/&gt;&lt;ref name=cmsa38/&gt;{{refn|Zhang Jiecheng was the commander of Chinese 117th Division.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hu|Ma|1987|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}{{refn|In Chinese military nomenclature, the term &quot;Army&quot; (军) means [[Corps]], while the term &quot;Army Group&quot; (集团军) means [[Field Army]].|group=Note}} Meanwhile, the Chinese [[38th Army (People's Republic of China)|38th]] and [[40th Army (People's Republic of China)|40th Armies]] approached along the Chongchon River from the east.&lt;ref name=Farrar280/&gt; 3 RAR remained at Chongju, however, due to a lack of transport, while the remainder of the brigade moved south; now the most forward element on the US Eighth Army's left flank, the battalion soon became isolated without communications or armour and artillery support.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Neill 1985 60&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=60}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Argent76&gt;{{harvnb|Argent|2002|p=76}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, on 2 November, US Army trucks became available, and the battalion completed its move south without incident, harbouring in the bed of the Taeryong River that evening.&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt; Meanwhile, it was announced that Green would be temporarily replaced by Walsh, who he had himself replaced in Japan several months before.&lt;ref name=Horner64&gt;{{harvnb|Horner|2008|p=64}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|p=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Walsh, by then an observer at US Eighth Army headquarters, was urgently posted back to 3 RAR to resume command,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Breen|1992|p=9}}.&lt;/ref&gt; despite his lack of operational experience as an infantry commander.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=116}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|A regular officer, Walsh had graduated from the [[Royal Military College, Duntroon]] in 1938. During the Second World War he had served in the [[5th Battalion (Australia)|5th Battalion]] and the [[2/13th Battalion (Australia)|2/13th Battalion]], before filling a number of headquarters positions in the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]], [[24th Brigade (Australia)|24th Brigade]] and [[19th Brigade (Australia)|19th Brigade]]. After the war he was posted to BCOF Headquarters in Japan and served as Commanding Officer 3 RAR in 1949–50, prior to the battalion's commitment to Korea.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Neill 1985 60&quot;/&gt;|group=Note}} Taking over amid difficult circumstances following Green's death, and with little time to become acquainted with the battalion, Walsh's inexperience soon told as the local situation deteriorated.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt;

{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 2em; font-size: 85%; background:whitesmoke; color:black; width:29em; max-width: 40%;&quot; cellspacing=&quot;5&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; |&quot;In order to capture the enemies at Yongsan-dong and Yongbyong, you must infiltrate boldly, cutting the Yongsan-dong–Pakchon and Yongbyong–Anju roads, prevent the enemies from escaping, [and] surround the enemies...&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; |Peng Dehuai's order to the Chinese 39th Army.&lt;ref name=cmsa38/&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; |
|}

Walker elected to stand north of the Chongchon and Taeryong rivers in response to the Chinese offensive, and the following day Coad received new orders to hold the left forward section of the bridgehead over the Chongchon.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|pp=279–280}}.&lt;/ref&gt; To halt the Chinese advance, the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade was ordered to defend the lower crossings of the Taeryong and Chongchon rivers as part of a rearguard, in conjunction with the US 24th Infantry Division further upstream on the right.&lt;ref name=Coulthard261_262&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|pp=261–262}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade  concentrated in the Pakchon area.&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt; The Middlesex occupied the town and the high ground to the north and east, while 3 RAR and the Argylls held positions covering the western approaches to the Taeryong, with the latter designated as the brigade reserve.&lt;ref name=Farrar280_281&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|pp=280–281}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Yet the information available to the British and Australians suggested that the Chinese would likely attack from an easterly direction, and the dispositions adopted by Coad were later criticised for failing to take this into account.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=110}}.&lt;/ref&gt; 3 RAR took up a defensive position {{convert|1.5|km|mi}} west of the village, where it remained for the next two days.&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt; Meanwhile, B and C Companies of the Argylls formed a bridgehead over the Taeryong around the far-side of the partially destroyed bridge near Kujin, while A Company occupied positions astride the road to the south. To the right, the US 24th Infantry Division covered the crossing over the Chongchon at [[Anju (city)|Anju]], while the South Korean [[II Corps (South Korea)|II ROK Corps]] held positions further east.&lt;ref name=Farrar280&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|p=280}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bartlett39&gt;{{harvnb|Bartlett|1960|p=39}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Forced to defend on a wide frontage, the UN positions were weakened  by a {{convert|9.5|km|mi|adj=on}} gap between the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade and the nearest American formation—2nd Battalion, US 19th Regimental Combat Team (2/19 RCT)—on the brigade's eastern flank.&lt;ref name=Farrar280/&gt;

==Battle==

===Opening moves, 4/5 November 1950===
[[File:Chongchon bridgehead 3 to 6 Nov 1950.PNG|300px|thumb|right|The Chongchon Bridgehead, 3–6 November 1950]]
During the night of 4/5 November 1950, the Chinese and North Koreans mounted a full-scale assault on US 24th Infantry Division.&lt;ref name=Coulthard260/&gt; Before dawn, US 19 RCT had become heavily engaged,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|p=281}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and was pushed back nearly {{convert|2|km|mi}}. The Chinese force turned west to advance between the Taeryong and Chongchon rivers, threatening the rear of the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade by cutting the Pakchon–[[Sinanju]] road.&lt;ref name=Coulthard260/&gt; The previous afternoon a patrol from the Middlesex had clashed with a large Chinese patrol {{convert|9.6|km|mi}} to the north-east and suffered a number of casualties, yet the main Chinese attack did not come until early the next morning.&lt;ref name=Bartlett39/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=111}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, large numbers of [[refugee]]s continued to move south, causing the British and Australians further concern given the possibility that they might be used by the Chinese to cover the infiltration of their positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=261}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At 08:00 on 5 November a group of around 200 Chinese attacked C Battery, US 61st Field Artillery Battalion, which was attached to the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; The American guns had been supporting the brigade from a position beside the road about {{convert|3|km|mi}} south of Pakchon, and were protecting the vital concrete bridge {{convert|1.8|km|mi}} south of the Argyll's battalion headquarters at Kujin.&lt;ref name=Coulthard260/&gt;

The Chinese established a number of road blocks in the area before proceeding to assault the American gun line and the nearby bridge.&lt;ref name=Farrar280_281/&gt; The attack cut the road to Anju which was the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade's single means of resupply or withdrawal, and exposed the only available crossing over the Chongchon River.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|pp=111–113}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Coad considered that unless the Chinese could be cleared from the gun position and the hills secured, the brigade was in danger of being surrounded and cut off and the crossing at Anju lost, while US 19 RCT would also be threatened.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|pp=261–262}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Under the command of Lieutenant Colonel George Neilson, the Argylls were despatched to restore the situation.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; B and C Companies would be drawn back from the west bank of the Taenyong to reinforce A Company, and then attack south one after the other supported by American tanks. At the same time A Company—under Major Alexander Wilson—was ordered to immediately attack north to clear the road. Hasty control measures were put in place to avoid the possibility of the two forces accidentally engaging one another, while air support was requested at 08:40. After commandeering two American trucks, Wilson's men stepped off with four US [[M4 Sherman tank]]s in support.&lt;ref name=Farrar282&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|p=282}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, to the north, under the command of Captain Howard M. Moore, C Battery, US 61st Field Artillery formed its six 105&amp;nbsp;mm [[M101 howitzer|M2A1 howitzer]]s into a semi-circle and created a perimeter around them, strongly defending their positions with automatic weapons from behind their gun shields. Assaulting from the east, the Chinese attempted to infiltrate the gun-line using a number of creek beds and paddy bunds for concealment.&lt;ref name=Farrar282/&gt; One of the American howitzers was depressed and  brought into action, firing over [[Iron sight#Open sights|open sights]] at point-blank range, bouncing shells off the frozen paddy fields which then exploded among the assaulting troops. A second howitzer was turned around 45 minutes later, augmenting the fire of the first. The Americans expended 1,400 rounds at a range of between {{convert|45|to|270|m|yd}}; however, the weight of fire was insufficient to halt the assaulting force.&lt;ref name=Appleman713&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=713}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Supporting fire from a nearby battery was directed by a spotter aircraft overhead, and this temporarily stemmed the Chinese onslaught. Running low on small arms ammunition and having lost one howitzer destroyed as well as two men killed and seventeen wounded, the Americans faced the prospect of being overrun.&lt;ref name=Farrar282/&gt; The gunners killed a member of a Chinese demolition team just {{convert|18|m|yd}} from the bridge.&lt;ref name=Appleman713/&gt; Finally, after crossing the Taeryong in single file under fire, B and C Companies of the Argylls began to systematically clear the road supported by machine-gun fire from the Middlesex, while A Company also continued to advance.&lt;ref name=Bartlett40&gt;{{harvnb|Bartlett|1960|p=40}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At 09:00 the lead tanks and infantry of the relief force arrived, closely followed by the remainder of A Company. The Argylls rapidly cleared the gun position and the Chinese withdrew north along the railway to a nearby hill while the American tanks continued to engage them.&lt;ref name=Farrar282/&gt; Over 70 Chinese dead were found in the vicinity of the gun-line, however, from their new position the Chinese continued to dominate the road.&lt;ref name=Appleman713/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|p=18}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to open the road the Argylls moved to clear the Chinese off the high ground located {{convert|500|to|1000|m|yd}} east of the road.&lt;ref name=Bartlett40/&gt; The hill, about {{convert|45|m|yd}} high, offered clear fields of fire to the west over the paddy fields to the Taeryong River and dominated the Pakchon–Sinanju road running beside the river.&lt;ref name=Coulthard260/&gt; Supported by four Sherman tanks, machine-guns and mortars, A Company captured the hill at 10:00.&lt;ref name=Bartlett40/&gt; Wilson occupied the summit with a reinforced [[platoon]], before withdrawing the remainder of the [[company]] to the road, where the [[Ordnance ML 3 inch Mortar|3-inch mortar]] and [[Vickers machine gun|Vickers medium machine-gun]] sections were established.&lt;ref name=Farrar282/&gt; Meanwhile, B Company—under the command of Major Alastair Gordon-Ingram—attacked the second Chinese road block, again supported by a number of American tanks. Back in action, the guns from C Battery also fired in support of the British infantry, and after a vigorous engagement in which Gordon-Ingram was wounded the Chinese were compelled to withdraw, leaving many of their dead on the road. A number were later found to have been carrying demolition charges, presumably for use against the bridge at Anju. With the survivors of the battle seen moving into the hills, Neilson then ordered B and C Companies to establish positions on the eastern flank in order to protect the road.&lt;ref name=Farrar282/&gt; Although the Chinese had been cleared from the gun-line and the hills around Pakchon, further attacks to the south continued to threaten the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade's position, which remained perilous.&lt;ref name=Oneill62&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=62}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting continued, and at 11:00 the Chinese mounted a heavy counter-attack on the A Company outpost, wounding six men. The Argylls were then forced to withdraw from the high ground under the cover of sustained fire from two Vickers medium machine-guns sited on the road, and became pinned down on the [[reverse slope]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|pp=282–283}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Odowd19&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|p=19}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the morning a US [[North American T-6 Texan variants#T-6 (Texan)|LT-6G Mosquito]] light observation aircraft had continued to monitor growing concentrations of Chinese in hills to the rear of the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade, with reports indicating their strength at approximately one division.&lt;ref name=Appleman713/&gt; Determining that the Chinese would move to cut the road during the night and believing it dangerous to remain any further forward than required, Coad requested approval for a limited withdrawal.&lt;ref name=Farrar283&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|p=283}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He decided to pull his forward units back across the Taeryong River, before moving south towards the Chongchon River, near Anju.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; The brigade counter-attacked the Chinese forces occupying the nearby ridgelines in order to clear the route south.&lt;ref name=Coulthard261_262/&gt; The plan envisioned the Argylls holding the road open, while 3 RAR recaptured the high ground previously held by A Company, 1 ASHR. The Middlesex would then pass through to clear and occupy the hills east of Maengjung-dong, while the Argylls—as the brigade rearguard—would follow to occupy the right of the new defensive position. The brigade would then adopt a tight defensive perimeter on the hills overlooking the north bank, so as to maintain the bridgehead over the river.&lt;ref name=Farrar283/&gt; Meanwhile, still in position west of Pakchon, the Australians prepared to cross the Taeryong River to regain the lost position, {{convert|7.5|km|mi}} to their south. 3 RAR faced a difficult approach after moving beyond the river, with the battalion's route paralleling the disputed ridge which overlooked it {{convert|800|m|yd}} to the east.&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bartlett40/&gt;

===3 RAR assaults the ridgeline, 5 November 1950===
The Australians crossed the Taeryong at 11:30 and began preparations to assault Chinese positions on the ridgeline {{convert|1|km|mi}} east of the road to Pakchon and {{convert|2|km|mi}} north of Maenjung-dong.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; In support were four P-51 Mustang fighter-bombers from No. 77 Squadron RAAF which attacked the Chinese with rockets and machine-gun fire, one of only a few occasions during the war when Australian aircraft operated in support of 3 RAR.&lt;ref name=Bartlett41&gt;{{harvnb|Bartlett|1960|p=41}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There were three main crests on the ridge running south-east, the first being nearest the road, the second just to its rear, and the third further back still, with the Chinese occupying the first two.&lt;ref name=Odowd19/&gt; Although the Argylls had occupied the ridgeline briefly during the morning, they had been pushed off by the Chinese. Mortar fire fell on 3 RAR while it was forming up; however, using the road as a start line the battalion attack began at 14:00, with A Company on the left flank and B Company on the right, each with two platoons forward and one back in reserve, each in extended line with [[bayonet]]s fixed.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt;&lt;ref name=Gallaway113&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=113}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A Company was commanded by Captain Bill Chitts, while B Company was led by Captain D'arcy Laughlin, after Major George Thirlwell had broken his leg in a vehicle accident two days before.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; The Mortar Platoon was sited with Battalion Headquarters alongside the road, with two sections of Vickers medium machine-guns and two [[Ordnance QF 17 pounder|17 pounder]] anti-tank guns from the Anti-Tank Platoon. The Assault Pioneer Platoon provided local defence, while the mortars laid down a continuous barrage in an attempt to counter the Chinese mortar fire in conjunction with the machine-guns and tanks which began to engage the hilltop.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=114}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mortar crew 3RAR Pakchon 5 Nov 1950 (AWM 146953).png|thumb|left|Australian mortar crew in action at Pakchon, 5 November 1950.]]

Beginning their advance, the Australians began to suffer casualties;&lt;ref name=Gallaway113/&gt; yet they were initially unable to confirm the location of the Chinese. However, as they commenced their ascent they were met by heavy small arms fire from the higher ground to the south and east.&lt;ref name=Farrar283/&gt; After a long approach across {{convert|500|m|yd}} of open paddy field, A Company relieved the beleaguered Argylls.&lt;ref name=Odowd19/&gt; The Chinese then forced the two Australian companies to fight hard in order to gain the {{convert|50|m|yd|adj=on}} crest.&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt; Lacking artillery support, the Australians instead relied on the battalion's integral support weapons,&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; with 3-inch mortars and medium machine-guns in support, as well as four Sherman tanks which provided fire support from a stand-off position near the road.&lt;ref name=Farrar283/&gt; With A and B Companies heavily engaged, Walsh moved D Company—under the command of Major Walter Brown—to attack the hill to the south to reinforce the right flank. A Company succeeded in establishing itself on the first crest, forcing the Chinese from the position, while supporting fire from their [[Bren light machine gun|Bren light machine-gun]]s and Vickers medium machine-guns allowed B Company to move up on their right and capture the second crest.&lt;ref name=Gallaway115&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=115}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally at 16:00, after two hours of heavy fighting, the Australians had achieved their objectives against a determined defence.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; A and B Company prepared for a counter-attack by the Chinese.&lt;ref name=Odowd19_20&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|pp=19–20}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, C Company—under Captain [[Archer Denness]]—had remained in reserve on the road with Battalion Headquarters and Support Company.&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt;&lt;ref name=Odowd20&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|p=20}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although orders for the attack had been hurried and lacking in detail, and the strength of the defenders unknown, the assaulting force had prevailed, securing the ridge with only limited [[fire support|offensive support]].&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt; During the fighting one of the B Company platoon commanders, Lieutenant Eric Larsen, who had only the week before led the crossing at Kujin, was killed.&lt;ref name=Farrar283/&gt; One of the section commanders, Corporal Jeff Jones, immediately took command of the 5 Platoon assault, moving from section to section across the steep slope to direct their fire, even while under heavy Chinese mortar and machine-gun fire. He was awarded the US [[Silver Star]] for his actions.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; The successful assault opened the road south, enabling the Middlesex battalion, brigade headquarters and a number of supporting units to withdraw down the road through the Australians, followed by the Argylls.&lt;ref name=Argent76/&gt;&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; 3 RAR remained behind as a rearguard while the British battalions took up new positions, covering the Chongchon River crossing at Anju.&lt;ref name=Coulthard261&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=261}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese mortars and machine-gun fire continued to fall on 3 RAR, and at 17:00 a round destroyed the A Company headquarters, killing two men and wounding four others, including Chitts who was evacuated by stretcher.&lt;ref name=Gallaway115/&gt;

Coad ordered 3 RAR to consolidate its positions and to secure the railway bridge; however, with all his companies committed there were no troops available for the latter task and Walsh chose to ignore the order.&lt;ref name=Odowd20/&gt; Meanwhile, the Middlesex occupied a hill north-east of Maenjung-dong, which was found to be clear except for one minor feature occupied by the Chinese, while the Argylls moved south with a platoon of tanks and positioned themselves on a small group of hills, {{convert|4|km|mi}} east of Maenjung-dong.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|pp=283–284}}.&lt;/ref&gt; From here the brigade was able to dominate the Pakchon–Maenjung-dong–Anju road. Meanwhile, as the light began to fade the administrative elements of the formation and the US 61st Field Artillery Battalion were moved south of the Chongchon River amid a bitter wind.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; The British and Australians stood-to from dusk until nightfall, and after posting sentries the remainder of the brigade began their night routine.&lt;ref name=Farrar284&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|p=284}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Walsh withdraws from the high ground, 5/6 November 1950===
An hour after last light on 5 November the Chinese attacked C Company 3 RAR—the forward Australian company occupying positions astride the Pakchon road {{convert|3|km|mi}} north of Maenjung-dong—with mortars and machine-guns.  Meanwhile, machine-gun fire also fell on Support Company and Battalion Headquarters, {{convert|400|m|yd}} to the south.&lt;ref name=Oneill62/&gt; Walsh decided to relocate his headquarters {{convert|900|m|yd}} further to the rear.&lt;ref name=Odowd19_20/&gt; The Chinese infantry launched a strong attack against C Company assaulting them across the paddy fields in darkness, while simultaneously also falling upon A and B Companies holding the hills they had captured during the afternoon.&lt;ref name=Farrar284/&gt; In the face of the heavy Chinese counter-attack Walsh feared the loss of his entire force, and at 20:00 he ordered a general withdrawal, pulling them back off the ridgeline in order to concentrate the battalion on the road, without informing Coad.&lt;ref name=Farrar284/&gt;&lt;ref name=Argent77&gt;{{harvnb|Argent|2002|p=77}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Ordered in the dark and with one company still under attack, a disorganised night withdrawal occurred.&lt;ref name=Odowd27&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|p=27}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The decision proved to be a serious tactical error, for as was to be demonstrated often in the months that followed, the Chinese were skilled at moving across the hills to outflank road-bound UN forces who often failed to hold the ridges on either side of the roads only to be confronted by strong concentrations in front and behind them as a result.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; The withdrawal threatened to open the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade's left flank; recognising the danger this posed, Coad ordered Walsh to immediately reposition his companies on the ridge.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; Ultimately this proved unachievable.&lt;ref name=Farrar284/&gt;

A Company—now under Lieutenant Lawrence Clark following Chitts' wounding that afternoon—had only just succeeded in breaking contact from the Chinese, suffering a number killed and wounded during a confused withdrawal. Meanwhile, B Company had also been forced to fight its way down the hill.&lt;ref name=Farrar284/&gt; Both companies were now well clear of their former positions and would have had a hard time fighting their way back.&lt;ref name=Argent77/&gt; Ultimately it was too late for the Australians to regain the feature in darkness, and the weight of the Chinese attack continued to mount.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; Only D Company on the southern right flank—which had been left unmolested—was able to regain its previous position on Hill 63.&lt;ref name=Farrar284/&gt;&lt;ref name=Odowd23&gt;{{harvnb|O'Dowd|2000|p=23}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the positions previously occupied by A and B Companies were occupied by the Chinese in superior numbers, and the remainder of 3 RAR concentrated at the railway crossing instead. At 22:00 Coad arranged to shell and mortar the relinquished ridge, while a standing patrol from the Middlesex was posted on the south-western side of the Maenjung-dong pass in anticipation of a renewed Chinese attack.&lt;ref name=Farrar284/&gt; However, following heavy fighting the pressure on the Australians unexpectedly ceased after midnight, and parties of Chinese were observed beginning to withdraw.&lt;ref name=Coulthard261/&gt;

By 02:00 the Chinese attack had been checked and 3 RAR had redeployed to new positions in the paddy fields around the railway crossing north of Maenjung-dong.&lt;ref name=Oneill63&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=63}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, amid the confusion the exact dispositions of the companies remained unclear for the remainder of the night.&lt;ref name=Odowd23/&gt; Australian losses were 12 killed and 64 wounded, the same number as those suffered during their entire advance into North Korea.&lt;ref name=Gallaway125&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|p=125}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of officers of the battalion were later critical of the decision to withdraw while still engaged, believing that it had been both dangerous and unnecessary, while the lack of detailed planning, reconnaissance and orders were also seen as a factor in the disorganisation that ensued.&lt;ref name=Odowd27/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|pp=122–123}}.&lt;/ref&gt; While A Company had immediately withdrawn as ordered and had suffered a number of casualties in doing so, both B and D Companies, which were commanded by experienced veterans of the [[2nd Australian Imperial Force]], had delayed doing so until more favourable circumstances prevailed and fared better as a consequence.&lt;ref name=Odowd23/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|pp=116–120}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Yet the following morning a patrol from D Company cleared the abandoned A and B Company positions unopposed. The area was found littered with Chinese dead and equipment.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gallaway|1999|pp=124–125}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the casualties were both Chinese and North Koreans, and it became clear that the Australians had been attacked by a mixed force,&lt;ref name=Farrar285/&gt; estimated at around 1,500 men. Many of those killed were also found to have been carrying demolition charges.&lt;ref name=Oneill63/&gt;

[[File:Ian Bruce Ferguson Korea 1950 (AWM146990).PNG|thumb|right|Ferguson shortly after taking command of 3 RAR, 7 November 1950.]]

Despite the events of the previous night the Australians still held the road, while D Company continued to occupy the former Chinese strongpoint on Hill 63, even if it was isolated from the rest of the battalion.&lt;ref name=Bartlett41/&gt; Yet B and C Companies were now precariously positioned in the paddy field to the east and west of the road respectively, and come daylight were exposed to the Chinese positions on the high ground.&lt;ref name=Odowd27/&gt; The same day Coad visited 3 RAR; dissatisfied with the battalion's dispositions and having now lost confidence in its commander, he relieved Walsh of his position, appointing the second-in-command, Major [[Ian Bruce Ferguson|Bruce Ferguson]], in his place.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; Walsh returned to his posting at US Eighth Army headquarters.&lt;ref name=Bartlett41/&gt; Ferguson came forward to take command of the battalion. Ordering 3 RAR to dig-in, he despatched a number of clearing patrols, while C Company advanced unopposed to a hill overlooking the road {{convert|2.2|km|mi}} north-east of D Company. Reaching the top the Australians observed the Chinese withdrawing northwards up the valley.&lt;ref name=Bartlett41/&gt; Further east, the Chinese attacked US 19 RCT;&lt;ref name=Oneill64&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=64}}.&lt;/ref&gt; however, by the afternoon of 6 November it became apparent that the Chinese withdrawal around Pakchon was part of a general disengagement.&lt;ref name=Farrar285/&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Casualties===
After the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade's initial success, they had in turn been counter-attacked by the Chinese before being pushed off the high ground during the night. During the action the brigade lost 12 killed and 70 wounded, the majority of them among the Australians.&lt;ref name=Coulthard262&gt;{{harvnb|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=262}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese losses were not known with many of their dead removed from the battlefield,&lt;ref name=Coulthard262/&gt; but according to Commander Wu Xinquan of the Chinese 39th Army, an infantry company from the Chinese [[350th Regiment (People's Republic of China)|350th Regiment]] of the 117th Division was badly mauled by the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade during the engagement.&lt;ref name=ww107&gt;{{harvnb|Wu|Wang|1996|p=107}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Australian forces later estimated that the Chinese had suffered 200 killed and another 200 wounded.&lt;ref name=Coulthard262/&gt; In their first battle with the Chinese, 3 RAR had successfully captured a well defended hill with only limited offensive support, and had held it the face of heavy counter-attacks before confused command decisions resulted in the battalion conducting a disorganised night withdrawal while still in contact.&lt;ref name=Kuring233&gt;{{harvnb|Kuring|2004|p=233}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting was costly for both sides and although the Australians had halted the advancing Chinese 117th Division and inflicted numerous casualties on them, they had also lost heavily.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; Nonetheless, the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade had succeeding in preventing a Chinese break-through at Pakchon, keeping open vital withdrawal routes across the river and securing the UN left flank.&lt;ref name=Gallaway125/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bartlett42&gt;{{harvnb|Bartlett|1960|p=42}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Suffering significant casualties, the Chinese offensive was finally halted the next day due to logistic difficulties.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Roe|2000|p=176}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Royal Australian Regiment]] and [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]] were later granted the [[battle honour]] &quot;Pakchon&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rodger|2003|p=373}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese and North Koreans were temporarily forced to withdraw north,&lt;ref name=Kuring233/&gt; while Walker successfully reinforced the UN positions, holding on the Chongchon Line.&lt;ref name=Bartlett42/&gt; The Chinese had failed to exploit their initial success, and instead now seemed to adopt a deliberately cautious strategy.&lt;ref name=Oneill64/&gt;

===Subsequent operations===
On 7 November, the 24th US Infantry Division and 27th British Commonwealth Brigade followed up the Chinese withdrawal with a limited probing advance.&lt;ref name=Oneill64/&gt; That morning Australian clearing patrols killed seven Chinese soldiers, before 3 RAR prepared to advance with the remainder of the brigade. C Company occupied Hill 74 {{convert|2.5|km|mi}} to the north-east without opposition, only to discover a North Korean company on the reverse slope. The Australians engaged the North Koreans with machine-gun fire, inflicting heavy losses on the defenders and capturing five before forcing them to withdraw towards Tang-dong harried by artillery and airstrikes. The remainder of the battalion deployed on the right, while the Argylls occupied two hills further north. The brigade's advance had forestalled a planned North Korean attack on the night of 7/8 November,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=65}}.&lt;/ref&gt; while large numbers of Chinese dead from the previous fighting were also discovered.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Argent|2002|p=84}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 November the advance wheeled to the north-west around Pakchon, with 3 RAR moving forward another {{convert|3|km|mi}} to the east, encountering little resistance and taking a number of prisoners in the process.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=66}}.&lt;/ref&gt; From 11 November the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade advanced slowly north. On 16 November 3 RAR occupied Hill 117, on a bend in the Taeryong River {{convert|3|km|mi}} north of Pakchon.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=67}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Over the following weeks they remained in the Pakchon area, conducting extensive patrolling up to company-size, and clashing with small groups of Chinese and North Koreans.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; As winter approached the weather became bitterly cold amid snow and strong winds. Unprepared for the extreme conditions the Australians increasingly suffered health problems, particularly among the older members of the battalion. Lacking the training and equipment for operations in ice and snow, maintenance also proved burdensome before additional US cold weather clothing and equipment was issued.&lt;ref name=Kuring233/&gt;

[[File:3RAR on crest overlooking Chongju 1950 (AWM HOBJ1726).png|thumb|left|260px|C Company, 3 RAR with American tanks during fighting for the Pakchon–Sinanju road, 7 November 1950.|alt=Infantry deployed on the crest of a hill, while in the background a tank provides support.]]

Ferguson ultimately proved to be an able commander. Thirty-seven years old and a New Zealander by birth, he had been commissioned into the Australian [[2/2nd Battalion (Australia)|2/2nd Battalion]] with Green during the Second World War.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; Serving as an intelligence officer on the headquarters of the [[16th Brigade (Australia)|16th Brigade]] during the [[Western Desert Campaign|Libyan campaign]] in 1941, Ferguson had been awarded the [[Military Cross]] for his actions during fighting on the [[Kokoda Track]] in New Guinea in 1942. Later, he had served as a liaison officer with the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]], before finishing the war as a staff officer posted to the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]] headquarters on [[Morotai|Morotai island]], taking part in the [[Battle of Balikpapan (1945)|amphibious landing at Balikpapan]] in 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Argent|2002|pp=79–80}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Ferguson volunteered to serve in the BCOF in Japan after the war and was posted to the [[67th Battalion (Australia)|67th Battalion]] as a company commander, arriving in [[Kure]] in February 1946. After leaving the battalion in 1948 to serve on the headquarters of BCOF for six months, he returned as battalion second-in-command. In 1949 the battalion had been renamed the 3rd Battalion, Australian Regiment, and was later granted the 'Royal' prefix.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Argent|2002|pp=80–81}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He remained with the battalion after that time.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt; The change of command was confirmed by the Commander-in-Chief BCOF, Lieutenant General Sir [[Horace Robertson]],&lt;ref name=Farrar285&gt;{{harvnb|Farrar-Hockley|1990|p=285}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and Ferguson was promoted to lieutenant colonel on 10 November.&lt;ref name=Oneill64/&gt; He developed a good working relationship with Coad, who held him in high regard, and went on to command 3 RAR during its most demanding period in Korea.&lt;ref name=Horner64/&gt;

The United Nations resumed the offensive on 24 November, shortly before the Chinese began their own [[Korean War#China intervenes (October&amp;nbsp;– December 1950)|Second Phase Offensive]].&lt;ref name=Kuring233/&gt; The Chinese 13th Army Group launched a series of surprise attacks on the night of 25 November, [[Battle of the Ch'ongch'on River|pushing the US Eighth Army back to the Chongchon River]]. The Chinese inflicted heavy losses on the South Koreans and decimated the [[2nd Infantry Division (United States)|US 2nd Infantry Division]] on the right flank, as the US Eighth Army began a long retreat south.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fehrenbach|2000|p=203}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the Chinese 9th Army Group ambushed the [[X Corps (United States)|US X Corps]] near the [[Battle of Chosin Reservoir|Chosin Reservoir]] as the freezing winter weather set in.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=56}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the US Eighth Army succeeded in avoiding encirclement, the US X Corps had to be evacuated by sea from [[Hungnam]] during December 1950, despite inflicting heavy casualties on the Chinese. MacArthur's forces were expelled from North Korea and withdrew to the 38th Parallel, where they sought to once again establish defensive positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|O'Neill|1985|p=80}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In reserve at the start of the renewed Chinese offensive, the 27th British Commonwealth Brigade was spared the initial brunt. Yet the offensive soon forced the UN forces into a disorganised withdrawal. 3 RAR withdrew {{convert|320|km|mi}} in nine days, arriving at [[Uijeongbu]], {{convert|24|km|mi}} north-east of Seoul, on 11 December 1950. There the British and Australians occupied defensive positions in an attempt to secure the northern approaches to the South Korean capital during the [[Battle of Uijeongbu (1951)|Battle of Uijeongbu]].&lt;ref name=Kuring233/&gt;

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|4}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Appleman |first=Roy E. |title=South to the Naktong, North to the Yalu: United States Army in the Korean War: June – November 1950 | url = http://www.history.army.mil/books/korea/20-2-1/toc.htm |year=1998|origyear=1961|publisher=[[Department of the Army]]|location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=978-0-16-001918-0|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Argent|first=Alf |year=2002|chapter=The Next Leader: Bruce Ferguson|title=The Fight Leaders: Australian Battlefield Leadership: Green, Hassett and Ferguson 3 RAR&amp;nbsp;— Korea|publisher=Australian Military Historical Publications |location=Loftus, New South Wales |isbn=1-876439-56-4|pages=72–113|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor-last=Bartlett|editor-first=Norman|year=1960|title=With the Australians in Korea|edition=Third |publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|oclc=488462542|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Breen|first=Bob|authorlink=|year=1992|title=The Battle of Kapyong: 3rd Battalion, the Royal Australian Regiment, Korea 23–24 April 1951|edition= |publisher=Headquarters Training Command|location=Georges Heights, New South Wales |isbn=0-642-18222-1|ref=harv}}
*{{zh icon}} {{cite book|last=Chinese Military Science Academy|volume=Volume II|year=2000|title=History of War to Resist America and Aid Korea (抗美援朝战争史)|publisher=Chinese Military Science Academy Publishing House|location=Beijing|isbn=7-80137-390-1|ref={{harvid|Chinese Military Science Academy|2000}}}}
*{{cite book|last=Coulthard-Clark |first=Chris |year=2001 |title=The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles|edition=Second|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=St Leonards, New South Wales|isbn=1-86508-634-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Dennis|first1=Peter|last2=Grey|first2=Jeffrey|last3=Morris|first3=Ewan|last4=Prior|first4=Robin |last5=Bou|first5=Jean |title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria|year=2008|edition=Second|isbn=978-0-19-551784-2|ref=CITEREFDennis_et_al2008}}
*{{cite book|last=Farrar-Hockley|first=Anthony|authorlink=Anthony Farrar-Hockley|year=1990|title=The British Part in the Korean War: A Distant Obligation|publisher = HMSO|volume= Volume I|location=London|isbn = 0-11-630953-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Fehrenbach |first=Theodore |authorlink=T. R. Fehrenbach |title=This Kind of War: The Classic Korean War History |publisher=Brassey's |location=Washington, D.C. |year=2000 |edition=50th Anniversary|origyear=1963 |isbn=1-57488-259-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Gallaway |first=Jack|title=The Last Call of the Bugle: The Long Road to Kapyong |publisher=University of Queensland Press|edition=Second |location=St Lucia, Queensland |year=1999 |isbn=0-7022-3106-1|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor-last=Horner |editor-first=David|editorlink=David Horner| year=2008 |title=Duty First: A History of the Royal Australian Regiment|edition=Second|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Crows Nest, New South Wales |isbn=978-1-74175-374-5|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book| last1 = Hu | first1 = Guang Zheng (胡光正) | last2= Ma | first2= Shan Ying (马善营) | year = 1987 | title = Chinese People's Volunteer Army Order of Battle (中国人民志愿军序列) | publisher = Chinese People's Liberation Army Publishing House | location = Beijing |oclc=298945765|ref=harv|language=zh}}
*{{cite book|last=Johnston |first=William |authorlink=  |year=2003 |title=A War of Patrols: Canadian Army Operations in Korea |edition=|publisher=UBC Press |location=Vancouver, British Columbia |isbn=0-7748-1008-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Kuring |first=Ian |year=2004 |title=Redcoats to Cams: A History of Australian Infantry 1788–2001 |publisher=Australian Military Historical Publications |location=Loftus, New South Wales |isbn=1-876439-99-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=MacDonald |first=Callum A. |title=Korea: The War before Vietnam |year=1986|edition= |publisher=Free Press |location=New York |isbn=0-02-919621-3|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Odgers |first=George |authorlink=George Odgers |year=2009 |title=Remembering Korea: Australians in the War of 1950–53 |publisher=New Holland Publishers (Australia) |location=Chatswood, New South Wales |isbn=978-1-74110-807-1|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=O'Dowd |first=Ben|title=In Valiant Company: Diggers in Battle&amp;nbsp;– Korea, 1950–51 |publisher=University of Queensland Press |location=St Lucia, Queensland |year=2000 |isbn=0-7022-3146-0|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=O'Neill |first=Robert |authorlink=Robert J. O'Neill |year=1985|edition=|title=Australia in the Korean War 1950–53. Combat Operations|volume=Volume II |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |isbn=0-642-04330-2|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Rodger|first=Alexander |year=2003|title=Battle Honours of the British Empire and Commonwealth Land Forces 1662–1991 |publisher=The Crowood Press|location=Ramsbury, Wiltshire|isbn=1-86126-637-5|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Roe|first=Patrick C. |title=The Dragon Strikes|publisher=Presidio|year=2000|location=Novato, California|isbn=0-89141-703-6|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1 = Wu |first1 = Xin Quan (吳信泉) |last2 = Wang |first2 = Zhao Yun (王照运) |title = 1000 Days on the Korean Battlefield: 39th Corps in Korea (朝鲜战场1000天 ： 三十九军在朝鲜) |year = 1996 |publisher = Liaoning People's Publishing House |location = [[Shenyang]], China |isbn = 7-205-03504-X|ref=harv|language=zh}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Forbes|first=Cameron|title=The Korean War: Australia in the Giants' Playground|year=2010|publisher=Macmillan|location=Sydney, New South Wales|isbn=978-1-405040-01-3}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [https://www.awm.gov.au/exhibitions/korea/operations/pakchon/ Out in the Cold: Australia's involvement in the Korean War – Pakchon – 5 November 1950]

{{coord|39|39|32|N|125|35|29|E|name=Pakchon|display=title}}

{{Australia in the Korean War}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pakchon, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1950]]
[[Category:1950 in Korea]]
[[Category:Battles of the Korean War]]
[[Category:Battles of the Korean War involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of the Korean War involving the United States]]
[[Category:Battles of the Korean War involving Australia]]
[[Category:Battles of the Korean War involving China]]
[[Category:Battles involving North Korea]]</text>
      <sha1>e3ww1cmrd69820qsyj21wefdrnvv91f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
