<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Bréville</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32273190</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746619622</id>
      <parentid>746448774</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T13:59:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 2 sources and tagging 1 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32352">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{coord|49|14|25.07|N|0|13|34.19|E|type:event_scale:10000_region:FR|display=title}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Bréville
| partof      = [[Operation Overlord]]
| image       = [[File:D-day - British Forces during the Invasion of Normandy 6 June 1944 B5058.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = British Parachute and Commando troops in Normandy, June 1944
| coordinates =
| date        = 7–13 June 1944
| place       = [[Bréville-les-Monts]], France
| result      = British victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Richard Gale (British Army officer)|Richard Nelson Gale]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erich Diestel]]
| units1   =[[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|6th Airborne Division]]
| units2   = [[346th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|346th Infantry Division]]
| strength1   =  [[Division (military)|Division]]
| strength2   =  Division
| casualties1 =  162 Dead ^
| casualties2 =  418 Dead ^
| notes       = ^ Numbers for the final attack 12 June
}}
{{Campaignbox Normandy}}
{{Campaignbox British airborne forces operations}}

The '''Battle of Bréville''' was fought by the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 6th Airborne Division]] and the [[346th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|German 346th Infantry Division]], between 8 and 13 June 1944, during the early phases of the [[invasion of Normandy]] in the [[World War II|Second World War]].

In June 1944, units of the 346th Infantry Division occupied [[Bréville-les-Monts]], a village on a watershed between the rivers [[Orne (river)|Orne]] and [[Dives (river)|Dives]]. From this vantage point, they could observe the positions of the 6th Airborne Division, defending the River Orne and [[Caen Canal]] bridges and beyond them the British [[Sword Beach]] at [[Ouistreham]]. Following several German attacks on British positions from Bréville-les-Monts, the capture of the village became essential to secure the 6th Airborne Division positions and protect the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[beachhead]].

The British attack occurred over the night of 12/13 June 1944, when [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Richard Gale (British Army officer)|Richard Nelson Gale]] committed his only reserves, the [[12th (Yorkshire) Parachute Battalion]], a [[company (military unit)|company]] from the 12th Battalion, [[Devonshire Regiment]] and the [[Pathfinder (military)|22nd Independent Parachute Company]]. To support the attack, a tank [[squadron (army)|squadron]] from the [[13th/18th Royal Hussars]] and five regiments of artillery were assigned to the division. The assault had to negotiate both the British and German artillery fire, which killed or wounded several men, including some senior officers. The attackers eventually reached and secured the village. However, every officer or [[sergeant major]] who took part in the attack was killed or wounded.

After the capture of Bréville, the Germans never seriously attempted to break through the airborne division's lines again. The British division only being subjected to sporadic artillery and mortar fire. This lasted until 17&amp;nbsp;August, when the Germans started to withdraw and the [[6th Airborne Division advance to the River Seine|6th Airborne Division advanced to the River Seine]].

==Background==
{{further information|Operation Deadstick|Operation Tonga|Operation Mallard|Normandy landings}}

On 6 June 1944, the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|6th Airborne Division]] landed in [[Normandy]] to secure the left flank of the British landing zone. The division's objectives were to capture intact the [[Pegasus Bridge|Caen canal bridge]], the [[Horsa Bridge|Orne river bridge]], destroy the [[Battle of Merville Gun Battery|Merville gun battery]]&amp;nbsp;– which was in a position to engage troops landing at the nearby [[Sword beach]]&amp;nbsp;– and the bridges crossing the [[River Dives]], the latter to prevent German reinforcements approaching the landings from the east.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, pp.79–80&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:6th Airborne Division June 1944.png|thumb|Positions of the 6th Airborne Division from 7&amp;nbsp;June&amp;nbsp;1944]]&lt;!-- PLEASE NOTE THAT, ON THE MAP, SPELLING IS INCORRECT FOR THE HAMLETS OF «&amp;nbsp;LE PLAIN » AND « HAMEAU OGER&amp;nbsp;» which both belong to the village of [[Amfreville, Calvados]] --&gt;

The division's two parachute brigades, landing in the early hours of 6&amp;nbsp;June, were scattered across the countryside during the parachute drop. Most of the battalions could only muster around sixty per cent or less of their total strength on the [[drop zone]]s (DZ). They did carry out all of their objectives, however, before the [[6th Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|6th Airlanding Brigade]] arrived by [[military glider|gliders]] to reinforce them at 21:00 that evening.&lt;ref name=mod&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=28 June 2011 |publisher=[[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)]] |date=30 January 2006 |title=The British Airborne Assault |url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://www.mod.uk/aboutus/dday60/airborne.htm }}{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 6th Airborne Division, now with the [[British Commandos|commandos]] of the [[1st Special Service Brigade]] under command, had to defend the Orne bridgehead. This was not an easy task as it had to face elements of the [[21st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|21st Panzer Division]] from the south and the [[346th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|346th]] and [[711th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|711th]] Infantry Divisions from the east.&lt;ref name=&quot;hastings154&quot;/&gt;

The airborne division's brigades prepared to hold the positions they had captured, with the [[5th Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|5th Parachute Brigade]], as the division's depth formation, dug into the east of the River Orne bridge.&lt;ref name=harclerode327&gt;Harclerode, p.327&lt;/ref&gt; The 6th Airlanding Brigade was in the south between [[Longueval]] and [[Hérouvillette]].&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.338–339&lt;/ref&gt;

The two remaining brigades dug in along a ridge of high ground that, if lost, offered the Germans a position to look down on the British landing zone. The 1st Special Service Brigade was in the north on a line from [[Amfreville, Calvados|Hameau Oger]] to [[Amfreville, Calvados#Sites and monuments|Le Plain]]. In between the commandos and the airlanding brigade was the [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]].&lt;ref name=harclerode327/&gt;

Their defensive line, however, was incomplete, as the small village of [[Bréville-les-Monts]], between the commandos and the 3rd Parachute Brigade, was held by the Germans. Located on the ridge line it gave the Germans a view into [[Ranville]], at the heart of the British position, the two captured bridges and in the distance Sword beach.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson, p.19&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===7/8 June===
At 01:30 on 7 June, the [[9th Parachute Battalion]], with only around ninety men at the time, marched through the unoccupied Bréville.&lt;ref name=crookenden247&gt;Crookenden, p.247&lt;/ref&gt; Upon arrival at the 3rd Parachute Brigade's position, the parachute battalion was ordered to dig in at the northern end of the brigade line. They would be responsible for defending an area from the Château Saint Come, across a clearing in the woods, to a house known as the Bois de Mont.&lt;ref name=harclerode327/&gt; To their front was a stretch of open land leading to Bréville-les-Monts and the road from [[Amfreville, Calvados|Amfreville]] to [[Le Mesnil-les-Monts]].&lt;ref name=harclerode328&gt;Harclerode, p.328&lt;/ref&gt; A shortage in their numbers left a large gap between the 9th Parachute Battalion and [[No. 6 Commando]], the most southern unit in the commando defensive position, to their north.&lt;ref name=crookenden247/&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-721-0373-05, Frankreich, Soldaten auf dem Marsch.jpg|thumb|German troops moving towards the front]]

By now the German [[346th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|346th Infantry Division]] had reached the area from its base at [[Le Havre]]. Their first attack, by the 744th Grenadier Regiment, was against the 1st&amp;nbsp;Special Service Brigade. Attacking in strength, they were near to breaking through the line when [[No. 3 Commando]] counter-attacked and drove them back.&lt;ref name=crookenden248&gt;Crookenden, p.248&lt;/ref&gt;

Later in the morning, No. 6 Commando came under artillery and [[mortar (weapon)|mortar]] fire from Bréville. The commandos attacked and cleared the village of Germans, capturing several prisoners, some machine-guns and four artillery pieces. Then they withdrew to their original position.&lt;ref name=crookenden247/&gt; The Germans reoccupied the village and formed their own defensive positions, facing the ridge line defended by the airborne division.&lt;ref name=crookenden248/&gt; Their positions also isolated the 9th Parachute Battalion, which was almost cut off from the rest of the division.&lt;ref name=crookenden249/&gt;

The next day a patrol from the 9th Parachute Battalion reconnoitred the Château Saint Come. They found it abandoned, but the presence of clothing, equipment, a half-eaten meal and a payroll containing 50,000 [[French franc]]s betrayed the recent German occupancy.&lt;ref name=crookenden249&gt;Crookenden, p.249&lt;/ref&gt;

Units of the 857th Grenadier Regiment, part of the 346th Infantry Division, attacked the battalion's position at midday. It appeared to be only a probing attack, easily fought off by 'A' Company. Later the same day the Germans attacked 'A' and 'C' Companies. This time they were repelled by [[Vickers machine gun]] fire and a counter-attack by the battalion's anti-tank [[platoon]], with a [[Bren machine gun]] group under command of the [[Regimental Sergeant Major]].&lt;ref name=harclerode328/&gt;

===9 June===
[[File:6thbritairborneranville.jpg|thumb|Two soldiers of the 6th Airborne Division man a trench beside the [[Caen]] road just outside [[Ranville]]]]

The next German attack was at dawn on 9 June, when a heavy mortar barrage landed on the 9th Parachute Battalion positions.{{refn|The British later calculated that eighty per cent of all their casualties in Normandy, came from German mortars.&lt;ref&gt;Lucas and Barker, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} Then 'A' and 'C' Companies were attacked simultaneously.&lt;ref name=crookenden249/&gt; After taking heavy casualties, the Germans retreated into the woods surrounding the Château, where they reformed and attempted another unsuccessful attack an hour later.&lt;ref name=harclerode328/&gt;

Brigade Headquarters was attacked by a force of Germans that had infiltrated through the woods. Informed of the attack, [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Terence Otway]], the [[commanding officer]] of 9th Parachute Battalion, collected 'C' Company, his own headquarters staff and a small group armed with captured German [[MG 42]] machine-guns. They approached the Germans from the rear and trapped them in a crossfire, killing nineteen and capturing one.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.328–329&lt;/ref&gt; That afternoon two infantry platoons attacked 'A' Company, but were fought off by a counter-attack from 'C' Company's position.&lt;ref name=harclerode329&gt;Harclerode, p.329&lt;/ref&gt;

At 17:30 a flight of [[Luftwaffe]] [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]s attacked the Orne bridgehead, causing little in the way of any damage. Soon afterward, [[Royal Air Force]] [[Short Stirling]] bombers arrived to carry out a parachute resupply for the division. Included in the parachute drop were [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|6 pounder]] anti-tank guns, which until then had always been delivered by glider.&lt;ref name=crookenden253&gt;Crookenden, p.253&lt;/ref&gt; Some forty-one of the 9th Parachute Battalion's missing men arrived at their position at 21:00, bringing the battalion strength up to around 200 men.&lt;ref name=crookenden253/&gt;

===10 June===
A reconnaissance patrol from the [[13th Parachute Battalion]] reported a large gathering of Germans in Bréville and suspected an attack was imminent. At 08:00 a massive artillery and mortar bombardment fell along the 1st Special Service Brigade lines, while the 857th Grenadier Regiment, which had gathered in the village, attacked No. 6 Commando. By 10:30, the attack on No. 6 Commando had been driven back, but to their left at Hauger [[No.4 Commando]]s had to win a hand-to-hand fight before the Germans withdrew. Twice more during the day the commandos were attacked unsuccessfully, from [[Sallenelles]] in the north and again from Bréville.&lt;ref name=crookenden255&gt;Crookenden, p.255&lt;/ref&gt;

At 09:00 one battalion of the 857th Grenadier Regiment had crossed the drop zone and approached the [[5th Parachute Brigade]]s positions. Its two forward units, the [[7th Parachute Battalion]] and the 13th Parachute Battalion, held their fire until the Germans were only {{convert|50|yd}} away. The few survivors of the onslaught escaped into the nearby woods.&lt;ref name=crookenden255/&gt;

Early on 10 June another group of thirty-one men arrived at the 9th Parachute Battalion position. These and other stragglers, who had arrived through the night, brought the battalion strength to around 270 men.&lt;ref name=harclerode329/&gt; At 11:00 the Germans attacked 'A' Company again, but this time the attack was ill-coordinated and was easily repelled. Shortly afterwards the battalion killed around fifty Germans, who had started digging defences in full view of the British position. Then 'A' Company ambushed a German patrol, causing several casualties. That afternoon a strong force of Germans occupied the Château and used it as a base to start an infantry and [[self propelled gun]] assault on the British battalion. With no mortar ammunition left, the British had to use their [[PIAT]]s and machine-guns to stop the attack.&lt;ref name=harclerode329/&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-2004-0176, Normandie, zerstörter Lastensegler.jpg|thumb|German patrol moving past a crashed Waco Hadrian glider]]

jThe next German attack was in force, using the 2nd Battalion 857th Grenadier Regiment, the 1st and 2nd Battalion's 858th Grenadier Regiment and several companies of the 744th Grenadier Regiment with tank and [[armoured car (military)|armoured car]] support. They attempted to force a gap in the British lines between the commandos and the 3rd Parachute Brigade to reach Ranville.&lt;ref name=harclerode334&gt;Harclerode, p.334&lt;/ref&gt;

Two infantry companies attacked 'B' Company 9th Parachute Battalion's position. This assault was more determined, even [[naval gunfire support]] from the [[BL 6 inch Mk XXIII naval gun|6 inch (150&amp;nbsp;mm) guns]] of [[HMS Arethusa (26)|HMS ''Arethusa'']] did not stop the attack. When they reached the British position a hand-to-hand fight ensued, during which most of the Germans were killed.&lt;ref name=harclerode330/&gt; One of the prisoners taken was the commander of the 2nd Battalion 857th Grenadier Regiment, who informed his captors that &quot;his regiment had been destroyed in the fighting against the airborne division&quot;.&lt;ref name=harclerode330/&gt; The rest of the German assault came up against the [[1st Canadian Parachute Battalion]], and was stopped by an artillery bombardment, two later attacks on them suffered the same fate.&lt;ref name=harclerode334/&gt; Later at 23:00 'C' Company 9th Parachute Battalion fought their way to and occupied the Château, and fought off several small attacks throughout the night.&lt;ref name=harclerode330&gt;Harclerode, p.330&lt;/ref&gt;

With his two parachute brigades and the commando brigade heavily engaged [[Major General]] [[Richard Nelson Gale|Richard Gale]] contacted [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]] for armour support. He had decided to clear the woods at [[Le Mariquet]] of Germans. The objective was given to the 7th Parachute Battalion and 'B' Squadron [[13th/18th Royal Hussars]]. The tanks would advance over the open ground, their only cover being crashed gliders. Meanwhile, 'A' and 'B' Company's would clear the woods.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.336&lt;/ref&gt; In the fighting the only British casualties were ten wounded in the parachute battalion, but eight men from the Hussars were killed and four [[Sherman tank|Sherman]] and two [[Stuart tank|Stuart]] tanks were destroyed. The Germans from the 857th Grenadier Regiment, had twenty killed and 100 men surrendered, and were driven out of the woods.&lt;ref&gt;Crookenden, p.250&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.337&lt;/ref&gt;

The German attacks convinced [[Lieutenant General]] [[John Crocker]], commander of I Corps, to reinforce the 6th Airborne Division, and the [[51st (Highland) Infantry Division]] was ordered to take over the southern sector of the Orne bridgehead.&lt;ref name=harclerode330&gt;Harclerode, p.330&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time the 5th Battalion [[Black Watch]] was attached to the 3rd Parachute Brigade. The Black Watch were informed to prepare for an assault to capture Bréville and formed up to the rear of the 9th Parachute Battalion, ready to begin their attack the next day.&lt;ref name=harclerode330/&gt;

===11 June===
The Black Watch would attack Bréville from the south-west, but before the attack sent a company to take over the defence of the Château. At 04:30 supported by the guns and mortars of the airborne and highland divisions the attack began. To reach Bréville the battalion had to cross {{convert|250|yd}} of open ground, and when they neared the village the British artillery ceased fire. The Germans then opened fire with their artillery, mortars and machine-guns.&lt;ref name=harclerode331/&gt; One company was completely wiped out by the German machine-gun fire as it advanced over the open ground.&lt;ref&gt;Barber, p.181&lt;/ref&gt; Met with such a heavy concentrated fire, the battalion suffered 200 casualties and the attack was repulsed.&lt;ref name=hastings154/&gt; The survivors retreated to the Château,&lt;ref name=harclerode331&gt;Harclerode, p.331&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|The 5th Battalion Black Watch had 327 casualties in their first week in Normandy, compared to 529 for the whole [[North African Campaign]].&lt;ref&gt;Royal, 1st, 5th and 7th Battalions France and North-West Europe Chapter (no page numbers)&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} but were immediately counter-attacked by the 3rd Battalion, 858th Infantry Regiment, who themselves suffered heavy casualties.&lt;ref name=hastings154/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Salmond, p.142&lt;/ref&gt;

That afternoon three troops of tanks from the 13th/18th Royal Hussars, were sent to reinforce the Black Watch, but they had only just started to move towards the Château when three tanks were destroyed by hidden German self-propelled guns. The other tanks were withdrawn being unable to deploy in the wooded ground around the Château. The rest of the day and night passed without another attack, but the Germans sent out reconnaissance patrols to establish the exact location of the British positions and German armoured vehicles could be heard moving up to the front during the night.&lt;ref&gt;Crookenden, p.265&lt;/ref&gt;

===12 June===
At midday on 12 June the entire 3rd Parachute Brigade position came under artillery and mortar fire prior to a major attack scheduled to start at 15:00. A German battalion attacked the 1st Canadian Parachute Battalion, another supported by six tanks and self-propelled guns attacked the 9th Parachute Battalion and the 5th Black Watch.&lt;ref name=harclerode334/&gt; The battle for the Château cost the Black Watch nine [[Bren Gun Carrier]]s and destroyed all of their anti-tank guns. Unable to resist they were forced to pull back to the Bois de Mont, joining the 9th Parachute Battalion, which was being attacked by the German armoured vehicles. One tank in front of 'B' Company was hit by two PIAT rounds, but remained in action.&lt;ref name=harclerode334&gt;Harclerode, p.334&lt;/ref&gt; The tank destroyed two of 'B' company's machine-gun posts, when it was hit by a third anti-tank projectile and withdrew.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.334–335&lt;/ref&gt; The attack killed or wounded the last men in the Machine-Gun Platoon and the Anti-Tank Platoon was reduced to one PIAT detachment.&lt;ref&gt;Crookenden, p.267&lt;/ref&gt; The German infantry were in danger of over-running the battalion, when Otway contacted brigade headquarters, informing them they were not able to hold out much longer. [[Brigadier]] [[James Hill (British Army officer)|James Hill]] personally led a counter-attack of forty men from the Canadian battalion which drove off the Germans.&lt;ref name=harclerode335/&gt; By 20:00 the area defended by the two battalions had been cleared of all opposition and the front line restored.&lt;ref name=crookenden268/&gt;

[[File:9 para btn normandy 1944.jpg|thumb||Men from the [[9th Parachute Battalion]] in [[Amfreville, Calvados|Amfreville]] to the west of [[Breville, Calvados|Breville]]]]

===Night Attack===
Gale concluded that to relieve the pressure on the division, he had to take Bréville. The only units available for the attack were the division reserve, which consisted of the [[12th Parachute Battalion]] (350 men), and 'D' Company 12th Battalion [[Devonshire Regiment]] (eighty-six men). Another unit, the 22nd Independent Parachute Company, the division's [[pathfinder (military)|pathfinders]], were to stand by and respond to any German counter-attack.&lt;ref name=crookenden268&gt;Crookenden, p.268&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.343–344&lt;/ref&gt; To provide fire support, Gale was given a squadron of tanks from the 13th/18th Royal Hussars, three [[field artillery]] regiments armed with [[Ordnance QF 25 pounder|25 pounder guns]], a medium artillery regiment of [[BL 5.5 inch Medium Gun|5.5 inch guns]] and the division's own artillery the [[53rd (Worcester Yeomanry) Airlanding Light Regiment]].&lt;ref name=crookenden268/&gt; The attack on Bréville would start at 22:00, timed to catch the Germans tired and off-guard following the days fighting. The start line was on the outskirts of [[Amfreville, Calvados|Amfreville]], which had already been secured by No.6 Commando.&lt;ref name=harclerode334/&gt;

Lieutenant Colonel [[Johnny Johnson (British Army officer)|Johnny Johnson]] of the 12th Parachute Battalion was in command of the assault. He decided his own 'C' Company would secure the first crossroads, the Devonshire company would then clear the north of the village. At the same time 'A' Company would advance through 'C' Company and secure the south-east. At the rear would be 'B' Company the battalion reserve.&lt;ref name=harclerode334/&gt; The attack had to cross {{convert|400|yd}} of open ground to reach the village, to support the assault and destroy a German position {{convert|200|yd}} from the start line, a [[troop]] of Sherman tanks would accompany them.&lt;ref name=harclerode334/&gt;

[[File:Sherman tank and Horsa glider.jpg|thumb|[[Sherman tank]] of the [[13th/18th Royal Hussars]] supporting the division, with a [[Airspeed Horsa|Horsa glider]] in the background]]

At 21:50 the British artillery opened fire, and the Germans responded with their own artillery and mortars which forced most of the British to take cover, for the next fifteen minutes, until a lull in the German fire allowed them to continue. In the lead 'C' Company had crossed the start line at 22:00,&lt;ref name=harclerode334/&gt; however all its officers and the [[company sergeant major]] (CSM) became casualties and a senior [[non-commissioned officer]] took command of the company.&lt;ref name=harclerode335&gt;Harclerode, p.335&lt;/ref&gt; They continued to advance through the artillery and mortar bombardment, guided towards their objective by [[Tracer ammunition|tracer]] rounds from the Hussars tanks. Repeatedly hit by the artillery and tanks, Bréville was in flames by the time the company's fifteen survivors reached the village.&lt;ref name=harclerode335/&gt;

The battalion's 'A' Company suffered a similar fate, the [[officer commanding]] was wounded crossing the start line, and at the same time every member of the 2nd Platoon was killed or wounded. The CSM assumed command of the company but was killed when they reached Bréville. The company [[second in command]] who had been bringing up the rear, reached the village and found the 3rd Platoon only had nine men left but they had managed to clear the village Château and the 1st Platoon had cleared its grounds.&lt;ref name=harclerode335/&gt;

The Devonshire company, was moving towards Amfreville when an artillery round landed amongst them  wounding several men. As they crossed the start line another shell landed nearby killing Johnson, their company commander Major Bampfylde and wounding [[Brigadier]]s [[Simon Fraser, 15th Lord Lovat|Lord Lovat]] of the commando brigade and [[Hugh Kindersley, 2nd Baron Kindersley|Hugh Kindersley]] of the airlanding brigade, who were observing the attack.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.345–346&lt;/ref&gt; [[Colonel]] Reginald Parker, deputy commander of the airlanding brigade and a former commanding officer of the 12th Parachute Battalion, had been wounded by the same shell but went forward to take over command of the attack.&lt;ref name=harclerode346&gt;Harclerode, p.346&lt;/ref&gt;

By 22:45 the crossroads had been secured by what remained of 'C' Company, the eighteen survivors of 'A' Company were in among the south-eastern buildings of Bréville. In the north-east of the village the twenty survivors of the Devonshire company had captured their objective.&lt;ref name=harclerode346/&gt; The shelling had stopped when 'B' Company reached the village unopposed and occupied abandoned German trenches beside the church.&lt;ref&gt;Crookenden, p.275&lt;/ref&gt; Fearing a German counter-attack on his weakened battalion, Parker ordered a defensive artillery bombardment. However, there was a misunderstanding when the order reached the artillery and a heavy bombardment landed on the British positions in the village, causing several casualties including three of the surviving officers.&lt;ref name=harclerode346/&gt;

At 02:00 on 13 June the 13th/18th Royal Hussars squadron arrived at 'C' Company's position at the crossroads, later followed by fifty-one men from the 22nd Independent Parachute Company.&lt;ref&gt;Crookenden, pp.279 and 279&lt;/ref&gt; Bréville was now in British control again for the third time since the landings on 6 June. But not in the numbers to defend against a German counter-attack, so the 1st Battalion [[Royal Ulster Rifles]], part of the 6th Airlanding Brigade, was moved into the village to take over from the survivors of the attack.&lt;ref name=harclerode347&gt;Harclerode, p.347&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
{{further information|6th Airborne Division advance to the River Seine}}

The final attack had cost the [[12th (Yorkshire) Parachute Battalion|12th Parachute Battalion]] 126 killed, and left its three rifle companies with only thirty-five men between them. The 12th [[Devonshire Regiment|Devonshire]] company had another thirty-six killed. Amongst the casualties, was every officer or [[warrant officer]], who had either been killed or wounded.&lt;ref name=hastings154&gt;Hastings, p.154&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=harclerode347/&gt; The German defenders from the 3rd Battalion 858th Grenadier Regiment, had numbered 564 men before the British assault, by the time the village had been captured there were only 146 of them left.&lt;ref name=hastings154/&gt;

[[File:18th Hussars Breville June 1944.jpg|thumb|[[Sherman Firefly]] on the outskirts of the village after the battle.]]

However the left flank of the invasion zone was now secure.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson, p.20&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 June the [[51st (Highland) Division|51st (Highland) Infantry Division]] took over responsibility for the southern sector of the Orne bridgehead, releasing the [[6th Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|6th Airlanding Brigade]] to strengthen the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|6th Airborne Division]] position along the ridge line. The next two months was a period of static warfare, until 17 August when the division crossed the [[River Dives]] and advanced north along the French coast. By the 26 August they had reached [[Honfleur]] at the mouth of the [[River Seine]], capturing over 1,000 prisoners and liberating {{convert|400|sqmi}} of France.&lt;ref name=mod/&gt;

The battle of Breville has since been claimed to have been &quot;one of the most important battles of the invasion&quot;.&lt;ref name=breville/&gt; Had the division lost the battle, the Germans would have been in a position to attack the landing beaches.&lt;ref name=breville&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=28 October 2011 |publisher=[[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)]] |title=D-Day&amp;nbsp;— The Normandy Landings |url=http://tna.europarchive.org/20061101003926/http://www.army.mod.uk/para/history/normandy.htm |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716050822/http://tna.europarchive.org/20061101003926/http://www.army.mod.uk/para/history/rhine.htm |archivedate=16 July 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; But after the battle the Germans never attempted a serious attack on the division again.&lt;ref&gt;Gale, p.101&lt;/ref&gt; For their accomplishment, Breville was one of six [[battle honours]] awarded to the [[Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)|Parachute Regiment]] for the [[Operation Overlord|Normandy Campaign]].&lt;ref&gt;Griffin, p.187&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=nb}}
;Citations
{{reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book| last=Barber| first=Neil| title=The Day The Devils Dropped In: The 9th Parachute Battalion in Normandy| publisher=Pen &amp; Sword| year=2002|location=Barnsley, United Kingdom| isbn=1-84415-045-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Cole|first=Howard N|title=On wings of healing: the story of the Airborne Medical Services 1940–1960|publisher=William Blackwood|location=Edinburgh, United Kingdom|year=1963|oclc=29847628}}
* {{cite book|last=Crookenden|first=Lieutenant-General Sir Napier|title=Dropzone Normandy|authorlink=Napier Crookenden|publisher=Charles Schriber and Sons|location=New York|year=1976|isbn=978-0-7110-0660-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Ferguson|first=Gregory|title=The Paras 1940–84, Volume 1 of Elite series
|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, United Kingdom|year=1984|isbn=0-85045-573-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Gale|first=General Sir Richard Nelson|authorlink=Richard Nelson Gale|title=With the 6th Airborne Division in Normandy|publisher=Sampson Low, Marston &amp; co ltd|location=Great Missenden, United Kingdom|year=1948|oclc=464063862}}
* {{Cite book|last=Griffin|first=P.D|title=Encyclopaedia of Modern British Army Regiments|publisher=Sutton Publishing|location=Stroud, United Kingdom|year=2006|isbn=978-0-7509-3929-4}}
* {{cite book| last=Harclerode| first=Peter| title=Wings Of War&amp;nbsp;– Airborne Warfare 1918–1945| publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|location=London| year= 2005 | isbn=0-304-36730-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Hastings|first=Max|authorlink=Max Hastings|title=Overlord: D-Day and the Battle for Normandy 1944|series=Pan military classics series|publisher=Pan Macmillan|location=London|year=2010|isbn=0-330-51362-1}}
* {{cite book|title=The killing ground: the battle of the Falaise Gap, August 1944|first1=James Sidney|last1=Lucas|first2=James|last2=Barker|publisher=B.T Batsford|year=1978|isbn=978-0-7134-0433-3|location=London}}
* {{cite book| last=Otway|first=Lieutenant-Colonel T.B.H|authorlink=Terence Otway| title=The Second World War 1939–1945 Army&amp;nbsp;— Airborne Forces| publisher=Imperial War Museum|location=London| year= 1990| isbn=0-901627-57-7}}
* {{cite book|title=The Black Watch: A Concise History|first=Trevor|last=Royle|publisher=Random House|year=2011|isbn=978-1-78057-254-3|location=New York}}
* {{cite book|last=Salmond|first=James Bell|title=The History of the 51st Highland Division, 1939–1945|publisher=W. Blackwood|location=London|year=1953|oclc=59929274}}
* {{cite book|last=Saunders|first=Hilary St George|authorlink=Hilary Saint George Saunders|title=The Red Beret|publisher=New English Library|location=London|year=1971|isbn=0-450-01006-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/stories/90/a1951490.shtml Personal account of the battle at BBC Peoples War]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20111112002308/http://www.normandie44lamemoire.com/versionanglaise/fichesvillesus/brevilleus2.html# Breville at Normandie 1944]

{{World War II}}
{{Battle of Normandy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Breville, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Operation Overlord]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Airborne operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)]]
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]</text>
      <sha1>3mmijjm02rx1x8pmag8w61zgr8uzjdu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
