<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Stillman's Run</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3183713</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750151023</id>
      <parentid>747576802</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T02:33:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>3 archive templates merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24326">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Stillman's Run
|image=[[File:Stillman's Run artist depiction1.jpg|250px]]
|caption=An 1854 artist's depiction of the Battle of Stillman's Run.
|partof=the [[Black Hawk War]]
|date=May 14, 1832
|place= Near present-day [[Stillman Valley, Illinois]]
|result=British Band victory
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1822}}
|combatant2= &quot;[[British Band]]&quot; ([[Sauk people|Sauk]] and [[Fox (tribe)|Fox]]) 
|commander1=[[Isaiah Stillman]]&lt;br /&gt;[[David Bailey (militia officer)|David Bailey]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John Giles Adams]]{{KIA}}
|commander2=[[Black Hawk (chief)|Black Hawk]]
|strength1=275
|strength2=40-50
|casualties1=12
|casualties2=3-5
}}
{{campaignbox Black Hawk War}}

The '''Battle of Stillman's Run''', also known as the '''Battle of Sycamore Creek''' or the '''Battle of Old Man's Creek''', occurred in Illinois on May 14, 1832. The battle was named for the panicked retreat by Major [[Isaiah Stillman]] and his detachment of 275 [[Militia (United States)|Illinois militia]] after being attacked by many fewer [[Sauk people|Sauk]] warriors of [[Black Hawk (Sauk leader)|Black Hawk]]'s [[British Band]]. The engagement was the first battle of the [[Black Hawk War]] (1832), which developed after Black Hawk crossed the [[Mississippi River]] from Iowa into Illinois with his band of Sauk and [[Fox (tribe)|Fox]] warriors to try to reclaim territory. The militia had pursued a small group of Sauk scouts to the main British Band camp following a failed attempt by Black Hawk's emissaries to negotiate a truce.

During the engagement, 12 militia men were killed by Band warriors while making a stand on a small hill. The remainder of the militia fled back to [[Dixon's Ferry]]. Citizens erected a monument in 1901 in [[Stillman Valley, Illinois]] commemorating the battle. A 2006 article corroborates that militia volunteer [[Abraham Lincoln]] was present at the battleground's burials; sources agree about little else. Investigation continues in the early 21st century about facts of the skirmish.

== Background ==
[[Black Hawk (chief)|Black Hawk]], a Sauk chief, believed that the [[Treaty of St. Louis (1804)]] was invalid. It ceded Sauk territory to the US that included his birthplace. He led a number of incursions across the [[Mississippi River]] from Iowa to Illinois beginning in 1830. Each time, he was persuaded to return west without bloodshed. In April 1832, encouraged by promises of alliances with other tribes and the British, he again moved his &quot;[[British Band]]&quot; into [[Illinois]].&lt;ref name=brit&gt;The group was referred to as the &quot;British Band&quot;, because of their earlier support to the British during the War of 1812 and continued reliance on British trade, as well as flying a British flag in their camp in defiance of American authority. However, the British did not keep their promise to help them in the war. See Lewis, &quot;Background.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lewis&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2c.html The Black Hawk War of 1832&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090815021319/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2c.html |date=August 15, 2009 }}, ''Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project,'' Northern Illinois University. Retrieved August 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Finding no allies, he attempted to return to [[Iowa]], but ensuing events led to the Battle of Stillman's Run.&lt;ref name=wiscsr&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002795.asp May 14: Black Hawk's Victory at the Battle of Stillman's Run],&quot; Historic Diaries: The Black Hawk War, ''Wisconsin State Historical Society''. Retrieved August 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of other engagements followed, and the state [[militia]]s of [[Wisconsin]] and Illinois were mobilized to hunt down Black Hawk's band. The conflict became known as the [[Black Hawk War]].
{| style=&quot;text-align:center; float:right; clear:right;&quot;
|-
| {{Black Hawk War Map}}
|-
|Map of Black Hawk War sites&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Red Battle X.png|8px]] {{small|Battle (with name)}} [[File:Red pog.svg|7px]] {{small|Fort / settlement}} [[File:Green pog.svg|7px]] {{small|Native village}}&lt;br /&gt;{{small|Symbols are wikilinked to article}}
|}
On April 5, 1832, Black Hawk and around 1,000 warriors and civilians recrossed the [[Mississippi River]] into Illinois in an attempt to reclaim their land. About half of Black Hawk's band were combatants and the rest were a combination of women, children, and elderly. The band consisted of [[Sauk people|Sauk]], [[Fox (tribe)|Fox]], some [[Potawatomi]], and some [[Kickapoo people|Kickapoo]]; in addition some members of the [[Ho-Chunk]] nation were sympathetic to Black Hawk.&lt;ref name=lewis3&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/scholarshipindex.html Introduction],&quot; The Black Hawk War of 1832, Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, ''Northern Illinois University''. Retrieved August 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nrhp2&gt;Harmet, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=whitecloud&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002678.asp April 6: The U.S. suspects Black Hawk is crossing the Mississippi],&quot; Historic Diaries: The Black Hawk War, ''Wisconsin State Historical Society''. Retrieved August 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Black Hawk's reason for crossing into [[Illinois]] was that he wanted to reclaim lost lands, and perhaps, create a confederacy of Native Americans to stand against white settlement.&lt;ref name=whitecloud/&gt;&lt;ref name=lewis2&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/background.html Background],&quot; The Black Hawk War of 1832, Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, ''Northern Illinois University''. Retrieved August 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Other Illinois tribes promised aid to the British Band and Black Hawk believed that he had been promised assistance by the British in Canada.&lt;ref name=whitecloud/&gt;

Black Hawk led the march of the group along the [[Rock River (Mississippi River)|Rock River]] into Illinois. Illinois Governor [[John Reynolds (U.S. politician)|John Reynolds]] perceived the return of Black Hawk as an invasion, and he immediately called up the militia.&lt;ref name=lewis2A/&gt; General [[Henry Atkinson (soldier)|Henry Atkinson]], whom Black Hawk addressed as &quot;White Beaver,&quot; commanded the military expedition.&lt;ref name=lewis4&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2d.html The Black Hawk War of 1832]&quot;, Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, ''Northern Illinois University'', p. 2D. Retrieved August 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hagan&gt;Hagan, William T. &quot;General Henry Atkinson and the Militia,&quot; ''Military Affairs,'' Vol. 23, No. 4. (Winter, 1959-1960), pp. 194-197.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prelude ==
Atkinson was not told about Governor Reynolds' decision to order Major [[Isaiah Stillman|Isaiah Stillman's]] militia to march on Old Man's Creek, despite being in overall command. Reynolds' orders, issued on his behalf by General [[Samuel Whiteside]] to Stillman, were for Stillman to find Black Hawk and coerce him into submission. Following these orders, Stillman moved on Old Mans Creek.&lt;ref&gt;http://majmchenry.googlepages.com/oldmanscreek Last Stand at Old Mans Creek&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dyer&gt;Dyar, Scott D. &quot;Stillman's Run: Militia's Foulest Hour,&quot; ''Military History,'' March 2006, pp. 38-44, 72.&lt;/ref&gt; Whiteside had refused to accept Stillman's battalion under his command, thus leaving it &quot;orphaned&quot; and under the direct command of Governor Reynolds.&lt;ref name=miller&gt;Miller, Richard Lawrence. ''Lincoln and His World'', ([https://books.google.com/books?id=Wn2mzvAkctIC&amp;pg=PA164 Google Books]), Stackpole Books: 2006, (ISBN 0-8117-0187-5), p. 164. Retrieved September 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The militia commanded by Whiteside grew restless as they awaited the arrival of Atkinson and his Army regulars; many of the volunteer militia wanted to quit the war and head back home.&lt;ref name=miller/&gt; When diplomacy failed to persuade Black Hawk to take his band back west to Iowa, Stillman and Bailey's battalions of Illinois Militia were marched up the Rock River.&lt;ref name=stmuseum&gt;&quot;[http://www.il.ngb.army.mil/Museum/HistoricalEvents/Blackhawk.htm Black Hawk War],&quot; Historical Events, ''Illinois State Military Museum''. Retrieved August 6, 2007. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071105063855/http://www.il.ngb.army.mil/Museum/HistoricalEvents/Blackhawk.htm |date=November 5, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the battle at Stillman's Run, Black Hawk's grand vision of British support, and a [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] confederacy had collapsed.&lt;ref name=nrhp2/&gt; No parties aided him and his followers. The British Band started to weaken with hunger, and Black Hawk soon realized that the only option was to return across the [[Mississippi River]]. When he detected the U.S. militia camp eight miles (13&amp;nbsp;km) away, Black Hawk sent out peace envoys in order to negotiate a truce. They were told to wave a white flag at the militia.&lt;ref name=wiscsr2/&gt;

== Battle ==
[[File:Major Isaiah Stillman.jpg|thumb|right|upright|275 militia under the command of [[Isaiah Stillman]] fled [[Black Hawk (chief)|Black Hawk]] warriors at what became known as Stillman's Run.]]
On May 14, 1832, a detachment of 275 militia under the command of Majors Isaiah Stillman and [[David Bailey (militia officer)|David Bailey]], under orders from [[Governor of Illinois|Illinois Governor]] Reynolds, were encamped near Old Man's Creek, not far from its confluence with the Rock River.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt;&lt;ref name=chronology&gt;Braun, Robert A. &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20091022172920/http://geocities.com/old_lead/bhwchron.htm Black Hawk's War April 5 - August 2, 1832: A Chronology],&quot; September 2001, ''Old Lead Historical Society''. Retrieved August 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The militia camp was located about three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) east of the Rock River near present-day [[Stillman Valley, Illinois]], and seven miles (11&amp;nbsp;km) south of the Sauk encampment.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt; It is believed that the militia and its commanders were unaware of their proximity to Black Hawk's British Band.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt;

In conference with the local [[Potawatomi]], Black Hawk learned of Stillman's presence and sent three [[Diplomat|emissaries]] to the militia camp under a flag of [[parley]] in order to negotiate a peace with the soldiers.&lt;ref name=lewis2A&gt;Lewis, James A. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2a.html The Black Hawk War of 1832] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070806094552/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2a.html |date=August 6, 2007 }},&quot; Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, ''Northern Illinois University'', p. 2A. Retrieved August 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The already suspicious soldiers took the three emissaries to their camp, and during the proceedings the militia became aware of several of Black Hawk's scouts in the surrounding hills, watching the proceedings.&lt;ref name=lewis2A/&gt; Once the scouts were spotted, soldiers shot at the three emissaries, killing one. The other two fled back toward their camp, located near the confluence of the [[Rock River (Illinois)|Rock]] and [[Kishwaukee River|Kishwaukee]] rivers.&lt;ref name=wiscsr2&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002794.asp May 14, Old Man's Creek: The Militia Ignore Black Hawk's White Flag],&quot; ''Historic Diaries: The Black Hawk War,'' Wisconsin State Historical Society. Retrieved August 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The scouts were pursued by the disorganized militia and several were killed. The surviving scouts arrived at Black Hawk's camp ahead of the militia and reported the events. At the camp, the warriors set up a skirmish line in order to fend off the pending militia attack.&lt;ref name=lewis2A/&gt; The militia soldiers, intent on pursuing the scouts, chased them back toward the main force of Black Hawk's warriors and their skirmish line.&lt;ref name=lewis2A/&gt; Black Hawk and his force concealed themselves and ambushed the pursuers.&lt;ref name=wiscsr/&gt; Believing that thousands of Sauk and Fox were attacking them, the militia panicked and fled back to the main force camped at Dixon's Ferry.&lt;ref name=sycamore&gt;&quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/gal/drake5.html Battle of Sycamore Creek], Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, ''Northern Illinois University''. Retrieved August 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Stillman's exact whereabouts are unknown during this point in the battle. His later account published in a newspaper did not mention his location and noted his only order was to retreat. Stillman's account, published in the ''Missouri Republican'', has been called fanciful.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt;

Twelve of Stillman's militia were killed in the melee.&lt;ref name=stillman&gt;&quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/gal/stevens97.html#about Major Isaiah Stillman],&quot; Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, 2002, ''Northern Illinois University''. Retrieved July 31, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; A band of volunteers under the leadership of Captain [[John Giles Adams]] made a stand on a hill south of the main militia camp. The men fought by moonlight as the main body of the militia fled back to Dixon. The entire 12-man detachment, including Adams, was killed in the fight.&lt;ref name=chronology/&gt; Dyer has said that Adams may have been killed by his own men as he attempted to muster them to battle.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt; The number of Sauk and Fox killed in the engagement is largely unknown; the militia party that was sent to locate the &quot;missing&quot; 53 militia men found no dead Sauk.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt; Black Hawk is quoted as saying at least three and maybe as many as five of his warriors were killed.&lt;ref name=blackhawk&gt;[[Black Hawk (Sauk leader)|Hawk, Black]], [[Antoine LeClaire|LeClaire, Antoine]], interpreter; Patterson, J. B., ed., ''[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?c.2836:11.lincoln.297720 Autobiography of Ma-Ka-Tai-Me-She-Kia-Kiak]'', or ''Black Hawk, Embracing the Traditions of his Nation, Various Wars In Which He Has Been Engaged, and His Account of the Cause and General History of the Black Hawk War of 1832, His Surrender, and Travels Through the United States''. Also ''Life, Death and Burial of the Old Chief, Together with a History of the Black Hawk War'', Oquawka, IL: J. B. Patterson, 1882, &quot;History of the Black Hawk War,&quot; Section 169. Retrieved August 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Lincoln's role ==
[[File:Abelincoln1846.jpeg|thumb|right|upright|This image has been claimed as the earliest of [[Abraham Lincoln]] and dates to around 1847, 15 years after the war.]]
{{main|Abraham Lincoln in the Black Hawk War}}
The facts about [[Abraham Lincoln|Abraham Lincoln's]] service during the Black Hawk War have been disputed. Lincoln was associated with two major battle sites, including Stillman's Run, in the aftermath of combat. A number of sources assert that on June 26, 1832, the morning after the [[Battle of Kellogg's Grove|Second Battle of Kellogg's Grove]], members of the company of Captain Jacob M. Early arrived at the grove to help bury the dead. One of these soldiers was Lincoln, who assisted with the burial. His later statement about the events has been linked to both the battle at [[Kellogg's Grove]] and the fight at Stillman's Run.&lt;ref name=nrhp&gt;Dameier, Evelyn. &quot;[http://gis.hpa.state.il.us/hargis/PDFs/200106.pdf Kellogg's Grove],&quot; ([[PDF]]), National Register of Historic Places Nomination Form, January 18, 1978, HAARGIS Database, ''Illinois Historic Preservation Agency''. Retrieved July 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=alo&gt;&quot;[http://showcase.netins.net/web/creative/lincoln/sites/stillman.htm Stillman's Run Memorial],&quot; Historic Places, ''Abraham Lincoln Online''. Retrieved August 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=davis/&gt;

{{cquote|I remember just how those men looked as we rode up the little hill where their camp was. The red light of the morning sun was streaming upon them as they lay head towards us on the ground. And every man had a round red spot on top of his head, about as big as a dollar where the redskins had taken his scalp. It was frightful, but it was grotesque, and the red sunlight seemed to paint everything all over. I remember one man had on buckskin breeches.}}

The Lincoln quote was featured in both [[William H. Herndon]] and Jesse W. Wiek's ''Life of Lincoln'' and [[Carl Sandburg|Carl Sandburg's]] Lincoln biography, ''Abraham Lincoln The Prairie Years''.&lt;ref name=nrhp/&gt; Lincoln's presence at Stillman's Run has been under investigation in the early 21st century, but his presence at Kellogg's Grove has been corroborated by several sources.&lt;ref name=nrhp/&gt;&lt;ref name=davis&gt;[[William C. Davis (historian)|Davis, William]]. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=pNwZWPJRNlkC&amp;pg=PA12&amp;ots=foNHSEkDRQ&amp;dq=Kellogg%27s+Grove+Lincoln&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1&amp;sig=zU9HIXuDVcDC8Fgve3S3c5cB9tk Lincoln's Men]'' ([[Google Books]]), Simon and Schuster: 1999, p. 12, (ISBN 0-684-82351-9). Retrieved August 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=braun&gt;Braun, Robert A. &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20091022072924/http://geocities.com/old_lead/abe.htm Abraham Lincoln's Military Service During the Black Hawk War: An Introduction&quot;], November 2002 and March 2003, ''Old Lead Historical Society''. Retrieved August 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2006 article, author Scott Dyer asserted that Whiteside's men, including Captain Lincoln, &quot;paraded&quot; the area the morning after, and buried the dead from Stillman's Run. Their movements were an unsuccessful effort to draw out the Sauk, after which they returned to Dixon's Ferry.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt;
[[File:Stillman's Run Site Stillman Valley, IL 01.JPG|thumb|right|Inscription on the monument in [[Stillman Valley, Illinois|Stillman Valley]] concerning Lincoln's role in the aftermath of the battle.]]
During an 1848 speech before the U.S. Congress in which he referred to his Black Hawk War service, Lincoln noted Stillman's Run by name:

{{cquote|By the way Mr. Speaker, did you know that I am a military hero? Yes sir, in the days of the Black Hawk War I fought, bled and came away . . . I was not at Stillman's defeat, but I was about as near it as Cass was Hull's surrender, and, like him, I saw the place very soon afterwards.&lt;ref name=browne&gt;[[Browne, Frances Fisher]]. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=IGsgHTorgS8C&amp;pg=PA40&amp;dq=Stillman%27s+Lincoln#PPA40,M1 The Everyday Life of Abraham Lincoln]'', Browne &amp; Howell Company: 1913, p. 40. Retrieved August 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The marble facade on the Stillman Valley monument, erected in 1901 to commemorate the battle, refers to Lincoln's presence at Stillman's Run, &quot;The presence of soldier, statesman, martyr, Abraham Lincoln assisting in the burial of these honored dead has made this spot more sacred.&quot;&lt;ref name=alo/&gt;
Other sources assert that General Whiteside originally buried the dead in a common grave on a ridge south of the battlefield, marked with a rudimentary wooden memorial. These sources make no mention of Lincoln.&lt;ref name=ford&gt;[[Ford, Thomas]] and [[James Shields (politician, born 1810)|Shields, James]]. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=GAyA6ninhBQC&amp;pg=PA123&amp;dq=Battle+of+Stillman%27s+Run+monument&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1 A History of Illinois, from Its Commencement as a State in 1818 to 1847''], ([[Google Books]]), Ivison &amp; Phinney: 1854, p. 123. Retrieved August 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lakeside&gt;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=bgtVOgslpEUC&amp;q=Stillman's+Run+monument+Whiteside&amp;dq=Stillman's+Run+monument+Whiteside&amp;pgis=1 The Lakeside Classics''], ([[Google Books]]), R.R. Donnelley and Sons, Co: 1903, p. 179. Retrieved August 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
[[File:stillman monument.jpg|thumb|right|Monument and graves located in [[Stillman Valley, Illinois|Stillman Valley]]]]
Following the first confrontation with Black Hawk at Stillman Valley, the press reported that 2,000 &quot;bloodthirsty warriors were sweeping all Northern Illinois with the bosom of destruction,&quot; sending shock waves of terror through the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;stmuseum&quot;/&gt; Past midnight on May 15, soldiers from Stillman's ill-fated detachment began streaming back into [[Dixon's Ferry]], wide-eyed and panic-stricken, telling tales of a horrible slaughter that had ensued during the battle. In the immediate aftermath of the battle, 53 militia men were missing. Later officials determined that the majority of these men had simply bypassed Dixon's Ferry on their way home.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt;
[[File:Stillman's Run Site Stillman Valley, IL 09.JPG|thumb|left|The memorial cemetery at the [[Stillman's Run Battle Site]].]]
After this initial skirmish, Black Hawk led many of the civilians in his band to the [[Michigan Territory]].&lt;ref name=stmuseum/&gt; On May 19, the militia traveled up the [[Rock River (Illinois)|Rock River]] trailing and searching for Black Hawk and his band.&lt;ref name=stmuseum/&gt; Several small skirmishes and massacres ensued over the next month in northern Illinois and southern Wisconsin before the militia regained public confidence in battles at [[Battle of Horseshoe Bend (1832)|Bloody Lake]] and [[Battle of Waddams Grove|Waddams Grove]].&lt;ref name=waddams&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002869.asp &quot;James Stephenson Describes the Battle at Yellow Creek&quot;], ''Historic Diaries: The Black Hawk War,'' Wisconsin Historical Society. Retrieved July 31, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of the Illinois Militia, mostly members of the [[United States Army|Regular Army]], attacked their behavior at the debacle at Stillman' Run. They began to refer to the battle at Old Man's Creek as the Battle of Stillman's Run, because Stillman had apparently fled with the panicked militia.&lt;ref name=dyer/&gt;

Armed hostilities during the Black Hawk War began at Stillman's Run, and the victory was unexpected for Black Hawk and his British Band.&lt;ref name=&quot;wiscsr&quot;/&gt; Black Hawk feared that the white militia and its allies would seek revenge through his total defeat.&lt;ref name=wiscsr3&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002803.asp May 15: Militia Commanders Report on Stillman's Run],&quot; Historic Diaries: The Black Hawk War, ''Wisconsin State Historical Society''. Retrieved August 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Leading his starving band, Black Hawk fled from Atkinson's pursuing army. The chase would take them as far as present day [[Madison, Wisconsin]]. It ended at the [[Battle of Bad Axe]], where the militia and its allies massacred a weakened foe, by then made up of mostly women and children.&lt;ref name=mil&gt;McCann, Dennis. &quot;[http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=597233 Black Hawk's name, country's shame lives on],&quot; ''Milwaukee Journal-Sentinel'', April 28, 2007. Retrieved July 30, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The remains of the soldiers at Stillman's Run were originally buried in a common grave, but who buried them remains an open question.&lt;ref name=alo/&gt;&lt;ref name=braun/&gt;&lt;ref name=ford/&gt; A memorial, erected in 1901, stands near their marked graves.&lt;ref name=alo/&gt; The monument and battle site are listed on the U.S. [[National Register of Historic Places]]. They are near [[Illinois Route 72]] a block west of present-day [[Stillman Creek (Illinois)|Stillman Creek]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|version=2010a}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tyler&gt;Tyler, Bob C. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=hJhv_Jwp3AMC&amp;pg=PA125&amp;dq=Stillman%27s+Run+monument&amp;sig=31R8JBB640hjTpQY2KuQFn9fJtE#PPA125,M1 Canoeing Adventures in Northern Illinois: Apple River to Zuma Creek]'', ([[Google Books]]), iUniverse: 2004, p. 125, (ISBN 0-595-31010-9). Retrieved August 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Stillman's Run Battle Site]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
{{coord|42|6|24|N|89|10|33|W|type:event|display=title}}
* Harmet, A. Richard. &quot;[http://gis.hpa.state.il.us/hargis/PDFs/201095.pdf Apple River Fort Site], ([[PDF]]), National Register of Historic Places Nomination Form, March 31, 1997, HAARGIS Database, ''Illinois Historic Preservation Agency''. Retrieved August 1, 2007.
* [[Anthony F. C. Wallace|Wallace, Anthony F. C.]] ''Prelude to Disaster: The Course of Indian-White Relations Which Led to the Black Hawk War of 1832'', ([https://books.google.com/books?id=1ASCAAAACAAJ&amp;dq=Prelude+to+Disaster:+The+Course+of+Indian-White+Relations&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1 Google Books]), Springfield, IL: 1970, ISBN 0-912226-11-0.

== External links ==
* [http://www.iupress.indiana.edu/catalog/product_info.php?cPath=1427&amp;products_id=21510 Frontier Illinois by James E. Davis]
{{Black Hawk War (1832)}}
{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Stillman's Run}}
[[Category:Battles and skirmishes of the Black Hawk War|Stillman's Run 1832]]
[[Category:1832 in the United States]]
[[Category:Stillman Valley, Illinois]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1832]]</text>
      <sha1>282r2uz6ici5yfu9wsb4miry78cu7lc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
