<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Merville Gun Battery</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32863244</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740559306</id>
      <parentid>737980854</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-21T20:45:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.167.3.71</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>corrected factual error</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18301">{{good article}}
{{coord|49|16|12|N|0|11|47|W|source:frwiki|display=title}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Merville Gun Battery
| partof      = [[Operation Tonga]]
| image       = [[File:Merville-Bombardement.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = Overhead view of the battery, showing the damage caused by a bombing raid in May 1944
| date        = 6 June 1944
| place       = [[Merville-Franceville-Plage|Merville]], France
| result      = Inconclusive
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Terence Otway]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Raimund Steiner]]
| units1      = [[9th (Eastern and Home Counties) Parachute Battalion|9th Parachute Battalion]], [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]]
| units2   = 1st Battery, Artillery Regiment 1716, [[716th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|716th Infantry Division]]
| strength1   =  600&lt;br&gt;but only 150 for the assault
| strength2   =  130
| casualties1 =75 during the assault phase
| casualties2 =  22 dead&lt;br /&gt;22 prisoners
| notes       =~ 450 men failed to arrive at the battalion assembly area following the parachute landing
}}
{{Campaignbox Normandy}}
{{Campaignbox British airborne forces operations}}
The '''Battle of Merville Gun Battery''' occurred on 6&amp;nbsp;June&amp;nbsp;1944, as part of [[Operation Tonga]], part of the [[Normandy landings]], during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] intelligence believed the [[Merville Gun Battery]] was composed of heavy-[[caliber|calibre]] guns that could threaten the British landings at [[Sword Beach]], only {{convert|8|mi}} away.

The [[9th (Eastern and Home Counties) Parachute Battalion|9th Parachute Battalion]], part of the [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]] attached to [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|6th Airborne Division]], was given the objective of destroying the battery. However, when the battalion arrived over Normandy, their parachute descent was dispersed over a large area, so instead of over 600 men, only 150 with no heavy weapons or equipment arrived at the battalion assembly point. Regardless, they pressed home their attack and succeeded in capturing the battery, only to discover that the guns were of a lower caliber than expected [Czech-manufacture 100mm]. However, these still had the range (over 8000 metres) to hit targets on Sword Beach and in Ouistreham. Using what explosives they had been able to recover, the surviving 75 men tried to disable the guns.

When the [[Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)|British paratroopers]] had withdrawn, two of the guns were put back into action by the Germans. Another attack the next day by [[British Commandos]] failed to recapture the battery, which remained under German control until 17&amp;nbsp;August, when the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]] started to withdraw from the area.

==Background==
On 6 June 1944, the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 6th Airborne Division]] was given the task of securing the left flank of the Allied seaborne landings. One of their objectives was the destruction of the [[Merville Gun Battery]]. Allied planners had judged from the size of the concrete gun emplacements that the guns must be around 150&amp;nbsp;mm in [[caliber|calibre]]. If so, the guns would have a range of about {{convert|8|mi}} and could threaten [[Sword Beach]], to the west of [[Ouistreham]], where the [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|3rd British Infantry Division]] were due to land later that day.&lt;ref&gt;Horn, p.44&lt;/ref&gt;

===British forces===
The unit assigned to destroy the battery was the [[9th (Eastern and Home Counties) Parachute Battalion|9th Parachute Battalion]], part of the [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]], commanded by [[Lieutenant colonel (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Terence Otway]]. The battalion's normal complement of 600 men&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.135&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Other sources give the number as 635 paratroopers and [[sapper]]s.&lt;ref name=ferg18&gt;Ferguson, p.18&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} was supported by a section of [[sappers]] from the [[Royal Engineers]], eight [[Airspeed Horsa]] glider loads transporting [[Willys MB|Jeeps]] and trailers, and stores including explosives, an [[anti-tank gun]] and [[flamethrower]]s. Three of the gliders, transporting 50 volunteers, were to carry out a [[coup de main]] landing onto the position to coincide with the ground assault.&lt;ref name=ford41&gt;Ford, p.41&lt;/ref&gt; In April&amp;nbsp;1944, the force was taken to [[Walbury Hill]] in [[Berkshire]], where over seven days the Royal Engineers had built a full-scale replica of the battery, including obstacles and barbed wire fences. The following five days were spent holding briefings and getting acquainted with the layout of the battery. They carried out nine practice assaults, four of them at night.&lt;ref name=ferg18/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nigl, p.72&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the nature of the mission, the battalion was given additional medical support from No. 3 Section [[224th (Parachute) Field Ambulance]].&lt;ref&gt;Cole, p.81&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|A medical section was composed of: an officer (doctor) and a staff sergeant (nursing orderly); under their command were three nursing orderlies, a clerk, a dutyman and thirteen stretcher bearers.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, pp.222–223&lt;/ref&gt; All members of No. 3 Section attached to the 9th Parachute Battalion became casualties in the battle.&lt;ref name=cole88&gt;Cole, p.88&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} Another unit that would be present during the attack but not directly involved was A Company of the [[1st Canadian Parachute Battalion]]. This company was tasked to provide covering fire for the 9th Battalion's approach to and withdrawal from the battery.&lt;ref&gt;Horn, p.41&lt;/ref&gt;
The assault had to be completed and the battalion clear of the position by 05:00, when the [[Royal Navy]] [[cruiser]] {{HMS|Arethusa|26|6}} would open fire on the battery in an attempt to destroy it with [[naval gunfire]].&lt;ref&gt;Ford, Zaloga and Badsey, p.224&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battery===
[[File:Marville Battery (12).JPG|thumb|2010 photograph of one of the concrete gun [[casemate]]s]]
The Merville Battery was composed of four {{convert|6|ft|m|adj=mid|-thick}} steel-reinforced concrete gun [[casemate]]s, built by the [[Todt Organisation]]. Each was designed to protect First World War-vintage Czech [[Skoda houfnice vz 14|M.14/19 100&amp;nbsp;mm guns]].&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga and Johnson, p.29&lt;/ref&gt; Other buildings on the site included a command bunker, a building to accommodate the men, and ammunition magazines. During a visit on 6&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;1944, to inspect the defences, [[Field Marshal (Germany)|Field Marshal]] [[Erwin Rommel]] ordered the builders to work faster, and by May&amp;nbsp;1944, the last two casemates were completed.&lt;ref name=merville&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=22 August 2011|title=The Merville Battery|publisher=Merville Battery Museum|url=http://www.batterie-merville.com/the-merville-battery?lang=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The battery was defended by a [[2 cm Flak 30/38/Flakvierling|20&amp;nbsp;mm anti-aircraft gun]] and several [[machine gun]]s in 15 gun positions, all enclosed in an area {{convert|700|by|500|yd}} surrounded by two [[barbed wire]] obstacles {{convert|15|ft}} thick by {{convert|5|ft}} high,&lt;ref name=ford41/&gt; which also acted as the exterior border for a {{convert|100|yd|m|adj=mid|-deep}} [[minefield]]. Another obstacle was an [[Anti-tank trench|anti-tank ditch]] covering any approach from the nearby coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gregory108&quot;&gt;Gregory, p.108&lt;/ref&gt; The original commander of the battery, [[Hauptmann]] Wolter, was killed during a [[Royal Air Force]] bombing raid on 19&amp;nbsp;May&amp;nbsp;1944. He was replaced by [[Oberleutnant]] Raimund Steiner, who commanded 50 engineers and 80 artillerymen from the 1st&amp;nbsp;Battery, Artillery Regiment&amp;nbsp;1716, part of the [[716th Static Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|716th Static Infantry Division]].&lt;ref name=merville/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga and Johnson, p.35&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quotation|The battery had a complement of some one hundred men in all. These were chiefly gunnery crews, of course, such as my team, but also included staff officers and their assistants, medical, cooks, observation teams, maintenance teams and guards with side arms. It was intended that the battery could remain under siege for  up to three months, with sufficient rations and generator fuel kept on site for this event; the water supply came from an aquifer and could not be interrupted. It was a remarkable structure, and it featured prominently in propaganda of the time… |Leutnant L.T.J. Wergens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Eckhertz|first1=Holger|title=D Day Through German Eyes|date=April 2015|publisher=DTZ History Publications|location=loc 1934|accessdate=20 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Assault==
Just after midnight on 6&amp;nbsp;June, the 9th Parachute Battalion's advance party landed with the brigade's [[Pathfinder (military)|pathfinders]], and reached the battalion assembly area without any problems. While some men remained to mark out the company positions, the battalion's [[second in command]], [[Major]] George Smith, and a reconnaissance party left to scout the battery.&lt;ref name=harc318&gt;Harclerode, p.318&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, [[Royal Air Force]] [[Lancaster bomber]]s started their bombing run, which completely missed the battery, their bombs landing further to the south. The pathfinders in the meantime were having problems. Those who had arrived at the correct [[drop zone]] found their [[Rebecca/Eureka transponding radar|Eureka beacons]] had been damaged when they landed, and in the smoke and debris left over from the bombing, their marker lights could not be seen by the pilots of the transport aircraft.&lt;ref name=harc318/&gt; The main body of the 9th Parachute Battalion and their gliders were to land at drop zone 'V', located between the battery and [[Varaville]] from 01:00.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gregory108&quot; /&gt; However, the battalion was scattered, with a number of paratroopers landing a considerable distance from the designated drop zone. Lieutenant Colonel Otway landed with the rest of his &quot;stick&quot; {{convert|400|yd|m}} away from the drop zone at a farmhouse being used as a command post by a German battalion; after a brief fire-fight, they helped other scattered paratroopers, and reached the drop zone at 01:30.&lt;ref&gt;Buckingham, pp.142–143&lt;/ref&gt; By 02:50, only 150 men had arrived at the battalion's assembly point with 20 [[Bangalore torpedoes]] and a [[machine gun]]. The [[Mortar (weapon)|mortars]], anti-tank gun, [[mine detector]]s, jeeps, sappers and [[field ambulance]] section were all missing.&lt;ref name=ferg18/&gt;

[[File:Merville Gun Battery assault.GIF|thumb|left|Plan of the battery and assault]]
Aware of the time constraints, Otway decided he could wait no longer, and the reduced battalion headed for the battery and joined up with [[Major (United Kingdom)|Major]] Smith's reconnaissance party just outside the village of [[Gonneville en Auge]]. The reconnaissance party had cut a way through the barbed wire, and marked four routes through the minefield.&lt;ref name=harc318/&gt; Otway divided his men into four assault groups, and settled down to await the arrival of the three gliders.&lt;ref name=harc319&gt;Harclerode, p.319&lt;/ref&gt;

In England, one of the gliders landed at RAF Odiham as its tow rope had snapped during bad weather. The other two gliders, unable to locate the battery, did not land where expected.&lt;ref&gt;Nigl, p.71&lt;/ref&gt; On their run in, both gliders were hit by anti-aircraft fire. One landed around {{convert|2|mi}} away, the other at the edge of the minefield. The troops from this glider became involved in a fire fight with German troops heading to reinforce the battery garrison.&lt;ref name=harc319/&gt;

Otway launched the assault as soon as the first glider overshot the battery, ordering the explosives to be detonated to form two paths through the outer perimeter through which the paratroopers attacked. The defenders were alerted by the explosions, and opened fire, inflicting heavy casualties; only four attackers survived to reach Casemate Four, which they disabled by firing into apertures and throwing grenades into air vents. The other casemates were cleared with fragmentation and white phosphorus grenades, as the crews had neglected to lock the doors leading into the battery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buckingham 145&quot;&gt;Buckingham, p.145&lt;/ref&gt; During the bombing raid, the battery's guns had been moved inside the casemates and the steel doors left open for ventilation.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.149&lt;/ref&gt; During the battle, 22 Germans were killed and a similar number made [[prisoners of war]]. The rest of the garrison escaped undetected by hiding in the underground bunkers.&lt;ref name=harc319/&gt;

Steiner was not present during the bombing, but at a command bunker in [[Merville-Franceville-Plage|Franceville-Plage]]. After the raid, he set out for the battery, but was unable to gain entry due to the volume of fire from the British paratroopers. At the same time, a reconnaissance patrol from an army [[Flak]] unit with a [[half-track]] mounting a large anti-aircraft gun arrived. The crew had intended to seek cover at the position, but instead used the gun to engage the paratroopers.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.148&lt;/ref&gt;

With the battery in their hands, but no sappers or explosives, the British gathered together what [[plastic explosive]]s they had been issued for use with their [[Gammon bomb]]s to try to destroy the guns.&lt;ref name=harc319/&gt; By this time, Steiner had returned to Franceville-Plage, and directed his regiment's 2nd and 3rd Batteries to fire onto the Merville Battery.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.150&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:9 para btn normandy 1944.jpg|thumb|Men of the [[9th (Eastern and Home Counties) Parachute Battalion|9th Parachute Battalion]] marching through [[Amfreville, Calvados|Amfreville]] later in the month]]

Just before 05:00, the battalion's survivors, just 75 men of the 150 who had set out, left the battery and headed for their secondary objective, the village of [[La Plein]].&lt;ref&gt;Cole, p.83&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion, being too weak, only managed to liberate around half of the village, and had to await the arrival of the [[1st Special Service Brigade|1st Commando Brigade]] later in the day to complete its capture.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.320&lt;/ref&gt;

After the British had withdrawn, the Germans reoccupied the battery position. Steiner was unable to see Sword Beach from his command bunker, so even though he was able to get two of his guns back in action, he was unable to direct accurate fire onto the landings. However, observers with the 736th Infantry Regiment, holding out at [[La Brèche]], were able to direct his guns until that position was neutralised.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.307&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7&amp;nbsp;June, the battery was assaulted again by two [[troop]]s of [[British Commandos|commandos]] from [[No. 3 Commando]], part of the 1st Special Service Brigade. The attack in daylight was repulsed with heavy losses to the commandos. As they withdrew, they were engaged by the battery's guns firing over [[open sights]]. The British never succeeded in completely destroying the battery, and it remained under German control until 17&amp;nbsp;August, when the German Army started to withdraw from France.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.319–320&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=nb}}
;Citations
{{reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book| last=Buckingham| first=William F.| title=D-Day The First 72 Hours| publisher=Tempus Publishing|location=Stroud, Gloucestershire|year= 2005 | isbn=0-7524-2842-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Cole|first=Howard N|title=On wings of healing: the story of the Airborne Medical Services 1940–1960|publisher=William Blackwood|location=Edinburgh, United Kingdom|year=1963|oclc=29847628}}
* {{cite book|last=Ferguson|first=Gregor|title=The Paras 1940–84|series=Volume 1 of Elite series
|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=1984|isbn=0-85045-573-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Ford|first=Ken|title=D-Day 1944 (3): Sword Beach &amp; the British Airborne Landings|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2011|isbn=978-1-84908-721-6}}
* {{cite book|last1=Ford|last2=Zaloga|last3=Badsey|first1=Ken|first2=Steven J|first3=Stephen|title=Overlord: The D-Day Landings|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2009|isbn=978-1-84603-424-4}}
* {{cite book|last1=Gregory|first1=Barry|last2=Batchelor|first2=John|title=Airborne Warfare, 1918–1945|publisher=Exeter Books|year=1979|location=Exeter, UK|isbn=978-0-89673-025-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=Harclerode|first=Peter|title=Wings Of War&amp;nbsp;–Airborne Warfare 1918–1945|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|location=London|year=2005|isbn=0-304-36730-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Horn|first=Bernd|title=Men of Steel: Canadian Paratroopers in Normandy, 1944|publisher=Dundurn Press Ltd|location=Toronto, ON|year=2010|isbn=978-1-55488-708-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Kershaw|first=Robert|title=D-Day Piercing the Atlantic Wall|publisher=Ian Allen Publishing|year=2008|location=Hersham, Surrey|isbn=978-0-7110-3323-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Nigl|first=Alfred J|title=Silent Wings Savage Death|publisher=Graphic Publishers|location=Santa Anna, CA|year=2007|isbn=978-1-882824-31-1}}
* {{cite book|last1=Zaloga|last2=Johnson|first1=Steven J|first2=Hugh|title=D-Day Fortifications in Normandy|series=Volume 37 of Fortress Series|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2005|isbn=978-1-84176-876-2}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.normandiememoire.com/lieux_historiques/index.php?modif=&amp;id=169&amp;lg=gb&amp;aff=&amp;parcours=1 Merville Gun Battery Museum]
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/stories/98/a4160198.shtml Personal account of the battle at BBC Peoples War]

{{Battle of Normandy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Merville Gun Battery}}
[[Category:Operation Overlord]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Airborne operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Glider Pilot Regiment operations]]
[[Category:Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)]]</text>
      <sha1>8jjqn4up6hwwukredslvc2s2t9s1a3e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
