<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Albulena</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1682841</id>
    <revision>
      <id>725950473</id>
      <parentid>720587730</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-18T23:37:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Euripides ψ</username>
        <id>19269166</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20329">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict|conflict= Battle of Albulena|partof=the [[Ottoman wars in Europe]]|image= [[File:Assault on Turkish encampment.jpg|300px]]|caption=Engraving of an Albanian assault on the Turkish camp during the battle|date=2 September 1457&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger152&quot;/&gt;|place=North-central [[Albania]], south of [[Laç]]|result=Decisive Albanian victory|combatant1=[[File:Flag of the Ottoman Empire (1453-1844).svg|21px]] [[Ottoman Empire]]|combatant2=[[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|22px]] [[League of Lezhë]]|commander1=[[File:Flag of the Ottoman Empire (1453-1844).svg|25px]] [[Isak-Beg|Isak Bey Evrenoz]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Flag of the Ottoman Empire (1453-1844).svg|25px]] [[Hamza Kastrioti]]{{POW}}|commander2=[[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|21px]] [[Skanderbeg]]|strength1=50,000-80,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeta telegraf&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Shahin|first1=Leka|title=Skënderbeu,strateg i përmasave të mëdha|url=http://telegraf.al/suplement/mediahorizont/skenderbeu-strateg-i-permasave-te-medha|website=telegraf.al|publisher=Gazeta telegraf}}&lt;/ref&gt;|strength2=8,000-10,000; 
6,000 cavalry&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazeta telegraf&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Shahin|first1=Leka|title=Skënderbeu,strateg i përmasave të mëdha|url=http://telegraf.al/suplement/mediahorizont/skenderbeu-strateg-i-permasave-te-medha|website=telegraf.al|publisher=Gazeta telegraf}}&lt;/ref&gt;|casualties1=15,000-30,000 dead; 
24 standards captured&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Barbinger|first1=Franz|title=Mehmed the Conqueror and His Time|date=1978|publisher=Princeton university press|isbn=0-691-01078-1|pages=152}}&lt;/ref&gt;|casualties2=Unknown}}
{{Campaignbox Ottoman–Albanian Wars}}

The '''Battle of Albulena''', also known as the '''Battle of Ujëbardha''', was fought on 2 September 1457 between [[League of Lezhë|Albanian]] forces led by [[Skanderbeg]] and an [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] army under [[Isak-Beg|Isak bey Evrenoz]] and Skanderbeg's nephew, [[Hamza Kastrioti]].

Skanderbeg had been the leader of the Albanians for over a decade and had seen many victories over Ottoman arms. However, after his [[Siege of Berat (1455)|loss at Berat]] in 1455 at the hands of Isak bey, Skanderbeg was betrayed by some of his most trusted officers, among them [[Moisi Arianit Golemi]]. Golemi returned the next year with an Ottoman force under his command, but was defeated at the [[Battle of Oranik (1456)|Battle of Oranik]] and rejoined Skanderbeg's army. Later, the dissatisfied Hamza Kastrioti betrayed Skanderbeg and was offered joint-command with Isak bey over a second Ottoman invasion force.

The Ottomans arrived in late May 1457 and marched through the [[Mat River]] Valley. Skanderbeg tried to delay the vanguard, composed of [[Akıncı]] cavalrymen, but upon the approach of the main force, decided to retreat. Both Isak bey and Hamza were familiar with Skanderbeg's tactics so the Albanian leader adopted a new one. He split his army into several groups and ordered them to march in separate directions through the mountains and remain unseen by the Ottoman forces until the signal to reassemble was given. The Albanians remained in separate formations until September, by which time the Ottomans had become both exasperated and convinced that Skanderbeg had been defeated. On 2 September 1457, Skanderbeg finally gave the order for his armies to regroup and launched a surprise attack on the Ottoman camp, killing and capturing up to 30,000 men. Among them was Hamza who was later sent as a prisoner to [[Naples]] in Italy.

The victory strengthened the morale of the Albanians. There were few, if not any, officers and soldiers who deserted afterwards. The battle of Albulena has been seen as Skanderbeg's most brilliant victory over the Ottomans. However, it also marked the high point of the Albanian resistance, beginning a new phase in Skanderbeg's quarter-century long war which would include its fiercest Ottoman invasions. Even though Skanderbeg himself had died in January 1468, the war would drag on until 1478 and later in the same year the main Albanian fortress at [[Siege of Krujë (1478)|Krujë fell]], finally effecting the annexation of Skanderbeg's Albania by the Ottoman Empire.

==Background==
[[File:Albania invasions.jpg|250px|thumb|right|The main roads through Albania and the most common Ottoman invasion routes]]
[[Skanderbeg]], the ruler of Albania ({{lang-la|dominus Albaniae}}), had served for several years in the Ottoman army, as both soldier and commander, before returning to his homeland and beginning an uprising against the [[Ottoman Empire]] in 1444.&lt;ref&gt;Elsie p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[battle of Kosovo (1448)|Second Battle of Kosovo]] in 1448 had ended with the defeat of [[John Hunyadi]], [[voivode]] of [[Transylvania]] while Skanderbeg and his forces were on their way; but did not arrive due to his army being blocked off by Đurađ Branković, and so he was unable to provide help; Hunyadi engaged the Ottomans thinking Skanderbeg was not coming. In reparation, Skanderbeg ravaged Brankovic's domains. As a result of the defeat, the Ottomans were free from Hungarian pressure, which had been limited to [[Belgrade]] and its environs.&lt;ref&gt;Runciman p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1455, Skanderbeg [[Siege of Berat (1455)|laid siege to Berat]], a fortress which had been seized from his control in 1450. The result was catastrophic for the Albanians who succumbed to an Ottoman counterattack upon Skanderbeg's temporary departure from the main force. [[Alfonso V of Aragon]], Skanderbeg's most helpful and important ally, also suffered a blow to his ambitions which included a pan-Mediterranean empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri338&quot;/&gt; The Albanians, however, were able to recover their morale when Pope [[Calixtus III]], who had begun to worry that his plans for crusade would be undermined, promised to aid Skanderbeg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri338&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 338.&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Arolsen Klebeband 01 453 4.jpg|left|thumb|208x208px|[[Hamza Kastrioti]]]]Before the planned crusade commenced, Sultan [[Mehmed II]] ''the Conqueror'' ({{lang-tr|el-Fātiḥ}}) decided to march against [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungary]] and Albania. In April 1456, Skanderbeg sent [[Pal Engjëlli]], his ambassador to the West, with a letter to Cardinal [[Domenico Capranica]] informing the [[Holy See]] of his need for aid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri339&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 339&lt;/ref&gt; The Ottoman invasion came in May 1456 when [[Moses Golemi]], Skanderbeg's former captain who had deserted after loss of Berat, met Skanderbeg's men at the [[Battle of Oranik (1456)|Battle of Oranik]]. The force was defeated and, through a show of mercy, Golemi was allowed to return to the Albanian ranks without punishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri341&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 341.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1456 Mehmed marched a large army to [[Siege of Belgrade (1456)|besiege Hungarian-held Belgrade]] in Serbia, but was defeated by Hunyadi.&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton174&quot;&gt;Setton p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, [[İbrahim II of Karaman|İbrahim II]] of the [[Karamanid Dynasty]] tried to create an anti-Ottoman alliance which would include his realm, Skanderbeg, Hunyadi, Calixtus, and Alfonso, all of whom would act in concert to defeat the sultan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri341&quot; /&gt; The plans were never put to practice, however.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri342&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 342.&lt;/ref&gt;
Skanderbeg's resources were worn out after over a decade of continuous war. Alfonso and the pope could not provide for him fully, while [[Republic of Venice|Venice]] continued to undermine Skanderbeg. The latter considered war with Skanderbeg since he maintained his alliance with [[Crown of Aragon|Aragon]]. Relations with the Italian state worsened further when [[Lekë Dukagjini]], Skanderbeg's elusive ally in the north, captured [[Dagnum]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri342&quot;/&gt; Even though Skanderbeg did not participate in this, Venice used it as a ''[[casus belli]]'' to launch an expedition against Skanderbeg. War never started but Albanian-Venetian relations sunk to their lowest point. The Venetian [[rector (politics)|rector]]s continued to provoke Skanderbeg at a time when he had grown relatively weak due to his nephew and one of his most important officers, [[Hamza Kastrioti]], deserting and joining the Ottomans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri343&quot;/&gt; Hamza had become dissatisfied with Skanderbeg's growing power and, upon being received by the sultan, was offered control over much of Albania once conquered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri345&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 345.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson146&quot;&gt;Hodgkinson p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; Stung by the betrayal, Skanderbeg offered an ultimatum to Venice where they had to halt their provocations or begin war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri343&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 343.&lt;/ref&gt; Since a crusade was anticipated against the Ottomans, Venice did not want to seem pro-Ottoman and eased their stance towards Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri344&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 344.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campaign==
By the end of May 1457, a large Ottoman army was seen approaching Albania. Skanderbeg sent a letter to Calixtus informing him of the Ottoman arrival and the dire need for military aid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri345&quot;/&gt; The pope responded with a promise to send a fleet to Albania – even though the enemy was on land – but it did not arrive. Skanderbeg was thus left to fight the oncoming Ottoman army alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri346&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 346.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mehmed II]] had placed [[Isak-Beg|Isak Bey Evrenoz]] and Hamza Kastrioti in command of the force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger152&quot;&gt;Babinger p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; Isak bey was an experienced commander who had crushed [[John Kastrioti]]'s rebellion in 1430 and led the Ottoman counterattack at the [[Siege of Berat (1455)|Siege of Berat]]. Hamza brought along with him several disaffected Albanian nobles and personal knowledge of the tactics they could expect from Skanderbeg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri346&quot;/&gt; In total, Ottoman forces numbered between 50,000 and 80,000 men. Armies of this size were usually commanded by the sultan himself so rumors spread that Mehmed was leading the campaign. In contrast, Skanderbeg had between 8,000 and 10,000 men to stand in opposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri347&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 347.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Skanderbeg's &quot;disappearance&quot;===
[[File:Sueleymanname Akinci-Beys.png|thumb|200px|right|Detail of a miniature, showing two leaders of the Akıncı in the Battle of Mohács, 1526]]
The Ottoman army did not march into Albania in one group. The first detachments to arrive were the [[Akıncı]] who marched through [[Dibër County|Dibra]]. Skanderbeg stalled this force's advance, but, once the main force arrived, the Albanians were not able to offer further resistance and withdrew. Realizing that both Ottoman commanders, Isak bey and Hamza, were familiar with the Albanian terrain and his tactics, Skanderbeg decided to adopt a new means of engagement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri347&quot;/&gt; Normally, he would lure his enemy into a trap and then ambush them. His new tactic was very similar to his normal; however, he chose to approach it in a different manner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri348&quot;/&gt; To make it impossible to be followed, Skanderbeg split his forces into several groups and ordered their respective commanders to march through the forests and mountains in different directions and to never assemble or assault the Ottomans unless instructed to do so. The Albanian warriors were supplied by the locals and supply depots set throughout the mountains as they marched.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri348&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 348.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ottomans marched through [[Mat District|Mat]] and pillaged the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri348&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg took parallel routes through the mountains.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson147&quot;/&gt; Since he had not yet engaged Skanderbeg, Isak bey decided not to besiege [[Krujë]], Albania's main fortress, until he was sure of the Albanian's fate. He thus camped with his men in the area north of Mount Tumenishta (Skënderbeu) to wait for Skanderbeg's appearance. This region was called ''Albulena'' ({{lang-al|Uji i Bardhë}}), located south of modern-day [[Laç]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri348&quot;/&gt; It was surrounded by a series of protective hills where guards were placed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson147&quot;&gt;Hodgkinson p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt; Since Tumenishta had served as the main base for Skanderbeg's forays into the Ottoman camp at the [[Siege of Krujë (1450)]], Isak bey and Hamza prepared to annihilate any resistance they would find there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri349&quot;/&gt; This effort came in vain, however, as they were not challenged by any Albanian forces. Still unsure of Skanderbeg's dispositions, the Ottoman commanders strengthened the camp's northern defenses, while the eastern side, in the direction of Tumenishta, remained lightly defended.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson147&quot;/&gt; Ottoman scouts crossed the [[Mat River]] into northern Albania. They were seen at the gates of Venetian-held [[Lezhë|Alessio]] (Lezhë) and ventured deeper into Venetian territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri349&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 349.&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to Skanderbeg's &quot;disappearance,&quot; rumors began to spread that he had fled since he was unable to confront the Ottomans and that his men had betrayed him. This was further upheld by the Venetians in [[Durrës|Durazzo]] (Durrës).&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri349&quot;/&gt; Isak bey and Hamza continued to be wary, however, and their reconnaissance forces reached as far north as [[Shkodër|Scutari]] (Shkodër). Skanderbeg remained in the mountains throughout July and August. It is not known with certainty what his army did while in the mountains, but he planned to wear the Ottomans out by forcing them to wait and to make them believe that he had been decisively defeated. Skanderbeg then sent Gjergj(George) Pjetri to Rome as an ambassador to give the Pope the impression that Albania had been decisively conquered and that aid was necessary to force the Ottomans out of Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri350&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 350.&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 September 1457, Calixtus notified Skanderbeg that he had sent Johan Navarre to help fund the crusade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton194&quot;&gt;Setton p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; By the time he arrived, however, the situation had already changed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri351&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 351.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle===
The local population remained faithful to Skanderbeg and did not reveal his whereabouts. Isak bey and Hamza grew confident that Skanderbeg had been defeated and had thus began to withdraw. When he judged the time right, Skanderbeg gave the signal for the army, which had up until then been in separate groups, to assemble without being seen by the Ottomans. The army gathered by the hills at Tumenishta – as the weakest point in the Ottoman camp was in this direction – and on 2 September 1457, it was split again into three groups to assault the Ottoman camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri351&quot;/&gt; With some of his most trusted men, he climbed to a high peak to scout on the Ottoman camp and saw that the Ottomans were resting. He descended with his chosen band to eliminate any watching guards, but one saw Skanderbeg and fled into the camp yelling that Skanderbeg had arrived. In order to maintain the surprise, Skanderbeg ordered his men to get ready for battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco320&quot;&gt;Franco p. 320.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson148&quot;&gt;Hodgkinson p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

With the accompaniment of loud noise made from metallic tools and weapons being clapped together, the Albanians charged into the Turkish camp. The Ottomans were caught by surprise and, despite their large numbers, were terrified by the fury of the Albanian assault, thinking they were attacking in larger numbers than they actually had.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri352&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 352.&lt;/ref&gt; Hamza tried to reorder his men, assuring them that the Albanians were few.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson148&quot; /&gt; Isak bey, tried to send reinforcements to Hamza's men, but the arrival of new Albanian contingents forced him to turn his attention. A series of cavalry charges and counter-charges kept the battle moving with a rain of missiles and [[arquebusiers]] forcing the Ottomans into the heart of the camp. Seeing that they were surrounded, the Ottoman force began to panic and melted away.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson149&quot;&gt;Hodgkinson p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; Hamza was thus captured, though Isak bey fled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco320&quot;/&gt; The Ottoman dead may have been as high as 30,000, but it is unlikely that they suffered more than 15,000 deaths. In addition, 15,000 men were taken prisoner, twenty-four standards were captured, and all the riches in the camp were lost to the Albanians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger152&quot;/&gt; A multitude of men were also captured, among them Hamza Kastrioti. The fallen Albanian warriors were buried in the Cathedral of St. Mary in the village of Shumri ({{convert|3|km|mi}} east of [[Mamurrasi]]) near the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri352&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
The Battle of Albulena was significant for the southern resistance against the Ottoman Empire. [[Franz Babinger]], a historian of the Ottoman Empire, describes the battle as Skanderbeg's most brilliant victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger152&quot;/&gt; The battle of Albulena strengthened the morale of Skanderbeg's men who afterwards rarely, if at all, deserted his army as Hamza had.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri356&quot;&gt;Frashëri p. 356.&lt;/ref&gt; Hamza himself was sent as a prisoner to Naples in Alfonso's realm after being captured. An Ottoman envoy was sent to ransom the standard bearers and forty of the distinguished prisoners. The envoy also tried to settle for a truce between Mehmed and Skanderbeg, but the latter responded that he would only accept if Svetigrad and Berat, which had been lost in 1448 and 1450 respectively, were restored to his state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson150&quot;&gt;Hodgkinson p. 150.&lt;/ref&gt; Seeing that Mehmed would not accept such terms, Skanderbeg strengthened his garrisons in the area around Svetigrad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson151&quot;&gt;Hodgkinson p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt; The victory still bought Albania and Italy time; in 1460, Mehmed and Skanderbeg signed an armistice that lasted three years.&lt;ref&gt;Sugar p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; This gave Skanderbeg the opportunity to [[Skanderbeg's Italian expedition|land in Italy]] and help out Alfonso's son, [[Ferdinand I of Naples]], who had been crowned after his father had died.&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton231&quot;&gt;Setton p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt; The battle thus opened a new phase in the Ottoman-Albanian war which saw the high-water mark of the Albanian resistance and the fiercest Ottoman invasions of Albania in the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri356&quot;/&gt; The war would last until the [[Siege of Krujë (1478)|fall of Krujë]] in 1478.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson220&quot;&gt;Hodgkinson p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=33em}}

==Bibliography==
{{Commons category|Battle of Albulena}}
* {{citation|last=Babinger|first=Franz|year=1978|title=Mehmed the Conqueror and His Time|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=0-691-01078-1}}
* {{citation|last=Elsie|first=Robert|year=2004|title=Historical Dictionary of Kosova|publisher=Scarecrow Press|isbn=0-8108-5309-4}}
* {{citation|last=Franco|first=Demetrio|year=1539|title=Comentario de le cose de' Turchi, et del S. Georgio Scanderbeg, principe d' Epyr|publisher=Altobello Salkato|isbn=99943-1-042-9}}
* {{citation|last=Frashëri|first=Kristo |title=Gjergj Kastrioti Skënderbeu: jeta dhe vepra, 1405–1468|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vwR3PQAACAAJ&amp;dq=kristo+frasheri+skenderbeu&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=vD6aTMPAFoPGlQeau_HZDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA|year=2002 |publisher=Botimet Toena|language=Albanian|isbn=99927-1-627-4}}
* {{citation|last=Hodgkinson|first=Harry|authorlink=Harry Hodgkinson (writer)|title=Scanderbeg: From Ottoman Captive to Albanian Hero|year=1999|publisher=Centre for Albanian Studies|isbn=978-1-873928-13-4}}
* {{citation|last=Runciman|first=Steven|year=1990|title=The Fall of Constantinople 1453|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=0-521-39832-0}}
*{{citation|last=Setton|first=Kenneth Meyer|authorlink=Kenneth Setton|year=1978|title=The Papacy and the Levant, 1204-1571|publisher=DIANE Publishing|isbn=978-0-87169-127-9}}
* {{citation|last=Sugar|first=Peter|year=1983|title=Southeastern Europe Under Ottoman Rule, 1354-1804|publisher=University of Washington Press|isbn=0-295-96033-7}}
{{coord missing|Albania}}
{{Ottoman battles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Ujebardha}}
[[Category:Warfare by Skanderbeg]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Ottoman Empire|Albulena]]
[[Category:Battles involving Albania|Albulena]]
[[Category:1457 in Albania]]
[[Category:1457 in the Ottoman Empire|Ujebardha]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1457]]</text>
      <sha1>5ajga3omfirkhufz7kpvyy2zk4cxksg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
