<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Dobro Pole</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9022782</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750570431</id>
      <parentid>750540860</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-20T15:53:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Catlemur</username>
        <id>13510414</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 750540860 by [[Special:Contributions/89.216.56.3|89.216.56.3]] ([[User talk:89.216.56.3|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25503">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Dobro Pole
|partof= the [[Vardar Offensive]], [[Balkans Campaign (World War I)|Balkans Theatre]] of [[World War I]]
|image=[[File:Voras north of Loutraki.jpg|250px]]
|caption=[[Kožuf|Tzena]] mountain
|date=15–18 September 1918
|place=[[Dobro Pole]] (present day [[Republic of Macedonia]])
|result=Decisive Entente victory
|combatant1=[[Central Powers]]:&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|German Empire}} 
|combatant2=[[Entente Powers]]:&lt;br&gt;{{flag|France}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Serbia}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece}}
|commander1={{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Georgi Todorov (general)|Georgi Todorov]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|German Empire}} [[Friedrich von Scholtz]]
|commander2={{flagicon|France}} [[Louis Franchet d'Esperey]] &lt;br&gt; {{flagicon|Kingdom of Serbia}} [[Živojin Mišić]]  &lt;br&gt; {{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} [[Panagiotis Gargalidis]]
|units1=[[11th German-Bulgarian Army|11th German Army]] &lt;br&gt; 2nd Bulgarian Division &lt;br&gt; 3rd Bulgarian Division
|units2=[[Allied Army of the Orient]] &lt;br&gt; [[Armée d'Orient (1915–19)|Armée d'Orient]] &lt;br&gt; [[First Army (Serbia)|1st Serbian Army]] &lt;br&gt; [[Second Army (Serbia)|2nd Serbian Army]]
|strength1={{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} 1 Army &lt;br&gt; 158 Artillery Pieces
|strength2={{flagicon|France}} 3 Divisions &lt;br&gt; {{flagicon|Kingdom of Serbia}} 2 Armies &lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} 3 Divisions &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; 566 guns 
|casualties1={{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} +2,689 {{KIA}} &lt;br&gt; +3,000 {{POW}} &lt;br&gt; +50 Artillery Pieces
|casualties2={{flagicon|France}} +1850 {{KIA}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagicon|Kingdom of Serbia}} +200 {{KIA}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} +158 {{KIA}}
|campaignbox=
{{Campaignbox Macedonian Front (World War I)}}
}}
The '''Battle of Dobro Pole''', also known as the ''Breakthrough at Dobro Pole'' in Bulgarian ({{lang-bg|Пробив при Добро Поле, ''Probiv Pri Dobro Pole''}}), ({{lang-sr|Битка код Доброг Поља, ''Bitka Kod Dobrog Polja''}}), ({{lang-gr|Μάχη του Ντόμπρο Πόλε, ''Máchi tou Dómbro Póle''}}), was a [[World War I]] battle, fought between 15 and 18 September 1918. The battle was fought in the initial stage of the [[Vardar Offensive]], in the [[Balkans Campaign (World War I)|Balkans Theatre]]. On September 15, a combined [[Allied Army of the Orient|force]] of Serbian, French and Greek troops attacked the Bulgarian-held trenches in  Dobro Pole (&quot;Good Field&quot;), at the time part of the [[Kingdom of Serbia]] (present day [[Republic of Macedonia]]). The offensive and the preceding artillery preparation had devastating effects on Bulgarian morale, eventually leading to mass desertions.

Despite being outnumbered and poorly equipped, certain Bulgarian units offered fierce resistance, delaying the [[Triple Entente|Entente]] advance in [[Voreino|Zborsko]]. The collapse of the front-line enabled the Allies to assault Bulgarian positions from multiple directions and eventually quell the last pockets of resistance. The [[Central Powers]]' defeat at the Dobro Pole played a role in the Bulgarian withdrawal from the war and opened the way for the subsequent capture of [[Vardar Macedonia]].

==Prelude==
[[File:DobroPole.jpg|thumb|left|270px|Map of the [[Vardar Offensive]].]]
The 28 June 1914, [[Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria|assassination]] of  Austro-Hungarian [[heir presumptive]] Archduke Franz Ferdinand  precipitated [[Austria-Hungary]]'s declaration of war against [[Serbia]]. The conflict quickly attracted the involvement of all major European countries, pitting the [[Central Powers]] against the [[Allies of World War I|Entente coalition]], and starting [[World War I]].{{sfn|Albertini|1953|p=36}}{{sfn|Fischer|1967|p=73}}{{sfn|Willmott|2003|pp=11–15}}

Serbia was ultimately defeated during the autumn 1915 phase of the [[Serbian Campaign of World War I#Course of the Campaign|Serbian Campaign]] prompting France and Britain to transfer troops from the [[Gallipoli Campaign]] to [[Macedonia (Greece)|Greek Macedonia]]. The [[Macedonian Front]] was thus established in an effort to support the remnants of the Serbian army to conquer Vardar Macedonia.{{sfn|Hall|2010|pp=48–50}}

On 17 August 1916, Bulgaria [[Struma Offensive|invaded Greece]], easily conquering all Greek territory east of the [[Struma (river)|Struma]], since the Greek Army was ordered not to resist by the pro-German [[Constantine I of Greece|King Constantine]]. The surrender of territory recently won with difficulty in the [[Second Balkan War]] of 1913 was the last straw for many supporters of [[Liberal Party (Greece)|Liberal Party]] politician [[Eleftherios Venizelos]]. With Allied assistance, they launched a coup which secured Thessaloniki and most of Greek Macedonia, causing the [[National Schism]]. In June 1917, the [[Venizelism|Venizelists]] gained full control of the country, immediately declaring war on the Central Powers and joining the [[Allied Army of the Orient]] operating on the Balkan Front. The Greek entry into the war along with the 24 division reinforcements that the Army had received in the spring of the same year had created a strategic advantage for the Entente.{{sfn|Falls|1933|pp=152–184}}{{sfn|Falls|1933|pp=208–230}}{{sfn|Falls|1933|pp=348–362}}

In late July 1918, Bulgarian [[commander-in-chief]] [[Nikola Zhekov]] sent German field marshal general [[Paul von Hindenburg]] a message regarding a rumored Entente offensive, and detailed Bulgaria's inability to adequately defend the Vardar portion of the front. Zhekov requested that Germany immediately reinforce the Balkan Front, hinting that [[Austria-Hungary]] would also be required to strengthen its positions in Albania. On 17 August, Hindenburg pledged to provide Bulgaria with support once the situation on other front permits it. Hindenburg's reluctance to support Bulgaria was also manifested by the early September redeployment of the last German [[Jäger (military)|Jäger]] battalion stationed in Macedonia back into Germany.{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|p=111}}

The Bulgarians, using information from escaped prisoners of war, determined that Entente forces would engage in hostile actions west of lake [[Ohrid]], in [[Bitola|Monastir]], Dobro Pole or Human. On 27 August, the 2nd and 3rd Bulgarian Divisions stationed at Dobro Pole were ordered to make emergency preparations, as new evidence indicated a frontal assault on Dobro Pole along with a secondary attack on Human. By 7 September, Dobro Pole was reinforced by one machine gun company, six battalions and ten heavy [[howitzer]]s, General [[Friedrich von Scholtz]] then stated that the defensive measures made the defense of the front feasible. Von Scholtz had, however, failed to take into account the departure of Bulgarian chief of staff Nikola Zhekov and his subsequent replacement by [[Georgi Todorov (general)|Georgi Todorov]]. Widespread [[insubordination]] and [[desertion]]s also plagued the Bulgarian troops who refused to participate in fortification works; poor rationing and fatigue contributed to the low morale.
{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=111–112}}

A day prior to the Entente offensive, General [[Louis Franchet d'Espèrey]] laid out the final plan for the operation. The first phase consisted of a combined Franco-Serbian attack on the positions of the 2nd and 3rd Bulgarian Divisions, which was expected to create a breach of the frontline in the area of Dobro Pole, while also posing a danger to the Bulgarian supply lines on river [[Vardar]]. Τhe {{convert|1,875|m}} Dobro Pole (&quot;Good Field&quot;) peak dominated the region, providing excellent observation points for the defenders. Dobro Pole was surrounded by a well-developed system of trenches which, in combination with the rough terrain, made the area impassable for wheeled transport. Dobro Pole was, however, lower and less steep than the mountains on other parts of the front that averaged {{convert|2,000|m}}.{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=7–8}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|p=89}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=112–113}}{{sfn|Geramanis|1980|p=129}}

A second Anglo-Franco-[[Greece|Hellenic]] force would then attack the [[First Army (Bulgaria)|1st Bulgarian Army]] between [[Kožuf]] and [[Lake Doiran]], preventing it from forming new defensive positions in the area. The initial advance would allow the [[Armée d'Orient (1915–19)|Armée d'Orient]] to progress in support of other units first to [[Prilep]], Disma and Borran. In the meantime, an Anglo-Hellenic force would strike Mount [[Belasica]], occupying the [[Rupel Pass]].{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=112–113}}{{sfn|Geramanis|1980|p=129}}

D'Espèrey expected to march the [[Allied Army of the Orient]] through the towns of [[Demir Hisar (town)|Demir Hisar]], Rupel, Petrici, Blagusa, Gradec, [[Štip]] and Belessa finally seizing Skopje. Units stationed at Katsania and [[Tetovo]] would prevent a Bulgarian [[flanking maneuver]], while the main body of the force would widen the breach both in Štip and Prilep. In case of a collapse of the front between Dobro Pole and Tzena, the [[First Army (Bulgaria)|1st Bulgarian]] and [[11th German-Bulgarian Army|11th German]]{{refn|The 11th German Army consisted of Bulgarian soldiers commanded by German officers.{{sfn|Korsun|1939|p=95}}|group=Note}} armies would either be annihilated or, in less favorable circumstances, perform an organised retreat to a new defensive line on river [[Crna (river)|Crna]]. The prevention of such a retreat was to be achieved by a rapid, penetrating attack on [[Gradsko, Republic of Macedonia|Gradsko]], [[:mk:Дрен (планина)|Dren Planina]] and Visoka.{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|p=113}}{{sfn|Geramanis|1980|p=130}}

==Battle==
[[File:Nudistička plaža na Crna.jpg|thumb|right|270px|German soldiers bathing in the [[Crna (river)|Crna]] river in 1918.]]
At 8 a.m. on 14 September 1918, Entente forces commenced a 566-gun artillery barrage on enemy positions. Their aircraft also bombed enemy positions and strafed a 250-truck column moving towards [[Kozjak (Prilep)|Kozjak]]. On the same day, Scholtz sent Hindenburg a [[Telegraphy|telegraph]] stating that
&quot;all indications point out that an enemy offensive will target the 11th Army on both sides of Vardar as well as Dobro Pole&amp;nbsp;...&quot;
The Bulgarian high command did not attempt to perform a spoiling attack as they lacked the necessary vehicles and pack animals. The barrage did not cause a significant number of casualties but severely affected the Bulgarian ''[[esprit de corps]]''. On the night between 14 and 15 September, Franco-Serbian patrols reported that the artillery barrage had dealt sufficient damage to the [[barbed wire]] entanglements separating the trenches.{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|p=125}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=114–115}}

At 5:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. on 15 September, the French 122nd and 17th (Colonial) Divisions struck Sokol, Dobro Pole, Kravitski Kamene and Kravitsa while the Serbian Shumadia Division assaulted Kamene and Veternik. The Greek [[Archipelago Division|Archipelago]], [[3rd Infantry Division (Greece)|3rd]] and [[4th Infantry Division (Greece)|4th Divisions]] under [[Panagiotis Gargalidis]] acted as a link between the Serbian and French troops without entering combat. The offensive immediately caused a wave of mass desertion among the Bulgarian units; the remaining infantrymen and artillery squadrons were not able to hold their ground. During the course of the battle, the 122nd Division broke into two columns and suffered heavy casualties. The left column managed to reach a position located {{convert|50|m}} from Sokol at 6:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. and take the peak at the end of the day. At 16:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., the right column captured Dobro Pole after rushing a {{convert|200|m}} segment of steep terrain. The 17th Division seized Kravitsa at 7:00&amp;nbsp;a.m., suppressing the last signs of resistance.{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=114–115}}{{sfn|Hall|2010|p=130}}{{sfn|Korsun|1939|p=98}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|p=125}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|p=117}}

Two Franco-Greek Regiments attempted to storm [[Voreino|Zborsko]] but were pushed back in the ensuing counterattack, as powerful pockets of resistance between the Sousnitsa and Bigrut streams facilitated its defense. Greek units then focused on Sousnitsa the fall of which created an opening in the Bulgarian [[Rear (military)|rear]] and put the surrounding units to flight. Using dispersed bluffs as cover, soldiers of the Shumadia Division took over Veternik, Kamene and the western part of a nearby mountain range with considerable difficulty. Elements of the same unit successfully flanked Kravitski Kamene while the 17th Division was engaging in a frontal assault. At 16:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., the Serbian [[First Army (Serbia)|1st Army]]'s thrust on Sokol failed to produce intended results. An attack later that night did secure the peak. The two French divisions were then ordered to remain in position while the Serbian Timok and Yugoslav Divisions moved forward. By the end of the day, Bulgaria lost approximately 40–50 percent of the 12,000 soldiers involved in the battle, including 3,000 [[prisoners of war]], 2,689 dead and 50 out of the initial 158 artillery pieces. Entente casualties amounted to 1,700 Frenchmen and 200 Serbians killed in action.{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=115–116}}{{sfn|Korsun|1939|p=98}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|p=126}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=118–119}}{{sfn|Villari|1922|p=226}}{{sfn|Coates Ulrichsen|2014|p=95}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA563176|title=THE SIGNIFICANCE OF THE BULGARIAN SENIOR MILITARY LEADERSHIP IN WORLD WAR I: A COMPARATIVE STUDY OF THE BULGARIAN ARMY OPERATIONS AT DOBRO POLE AND DOIRAN IN 1918|work=MASTER OF MILITARY ART AND SCIENCE Thesis|author=Ivaylo S. Ivanov|date=2000|page=37|accessdate=13 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the morning of 16 September, the Serbians overran the Kozjak mountain range and the Golo Bilo peak. They were joined by the 35th Greek Regiment which crossed the Poroi river and later marching on Topolets. At 11:00&amp;nbsp;a.m., Franco-Hellenic units stormed Zborsko for a second time and were met by heavy artillery and machine gun fire. The attack was rebuffed with the loss of 158 Greeks and roughly the same number of French lives and attempts to take the area were suspended. [[Živojin Mišić]]'s 1st Army and the ''Armée d'Orient'' performed a night attack on the [[Gradešnica]] fortified zone, suppressing the defenders. The 1st Division Group moved into a position on the Poroi river north of Brahovo in conjunction with  the Timok Division. By the night of 16 September, the gap in what formerly constituted the front-line had extended to {{convert|25|km}} in width and {{convert|7|km}} in depth. The Allied command ordered its air department to continue attacking all bridges on the river Vardar.{{sfn|Korsun|1939|p=98}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=118–119}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=120–122}}

At 4.00 a.m. on 17 September, Hellenic components of the 1st Division Group raided mount Preslap, a key position housing Bulgarian artillery. The Greeks rapidly descended from Golo Bilo and then began climbing the cliffs of Preslap with their bare hands. The Preslap garrison proceeded to abandon their positions and retreat eastwards. Having lost their artillery cover forces at Zborsko followed their comrades in retreat. The Timok Division conquered Topolets and advanced towards Studena Voda and Preslap while the Morava and Yugoslav Divisions overran Koutskov Kamene. At the same time, the Drina and Danube Divisions seized Gradešnica along with the Poltsista and Besistsa peaks, then halted at Melinitsa.{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=122–123}}{{sfn|Villari|1922|pp=227–228}}

On 18 September, the 11th French Colonial Division and the 6th Greek Regiment occupied the villages of [[Zoviḱ]], [[Staravina]] and [[:mk:Чебрен|Cebren]], approaching towards the [[:mk:Чебренски манастир|Cebren Monastery]] bridge on [[Crna (river)|Crna]]. An Entente [[Airstrike|air raid]] destroyed another bridge north of Razim Bey. Bulgarian forces failed at putting a stop to the Allied offensive, abandoning their wounded and large quantities of military equipment. By the end of the day, Allied troops had advanced {{convert|15|km}} into enemy territory while also seizing locales of strategic importance that would later enable them to continue pushing deeper into [[Vardar Macedonia]].{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=116–117}}{{sfn|Korsun|1939|p=98}}

==Aftermath==
[[File:Francuski Grobista Skopje (20).JPG|thumb|French military cemetery in Skopje.]]
Immediately following the battle, Entente forces were defeated in the [[Battle of Doiran (1918)|Battle of Doiran]] at Lake Doiran on 18 September. However the breach of the defensive line at Dobro Pole, enabled the Allies to penetrate into Vardar Macedonia and send reinforcements to Doiran. The Bulgarians rushed to the defense of their homeland, abandoning Vardar Macedonia, in order to prevent a future occupation by the Entente. Having suffered heavy losses at Doiran, the Allied forces allowed the Bulgarians to peacefully withdraw over the border. A combination of multiple factors, including combat fatigue and poor supplies, led to the [[Radomir Rebellion]]. On 25 September, a band of Bulgarian deserters who had previously fled from Dobro Pole arrived at [[Kyustendil]], looting the city and putting the Bulgarian High Command to flight. The mass of retreating Bulgarian mutineers then converged on the railway center of [[Radomir (town)|Radomir]] in Bulgaria, just {{convert|30|mi|km}} from the capital city of Sofia. On 27 September, the leaders of the [[Bulgarian Agrarian National Union]] took control of these troops and proclaimed the establishment of the Bulgarian Republic. About {{nowrap|4,000–5,000}} rebellious troops threatened Sofia the following day.{{sfn|Falls|1935|pp=246–253}}{{sfn|Korsun|1939|pp=105–108}}{{sfn|Omiridis Skylitzes|1961|pp=124–125}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA563176|title=THE SIGNIFICANCE OF THE BULGARIAN SENIOR MILITARY LEADERSHIP IN WORLD WAR I: A COMPARATIVE STUDY OF THE BULGARIAN ARMY OPERATIONS AT DOBRO POLE AND DOIRAN IN 1918|work=MASTER OF MILITARY ART AND SCIENCE Thesis|author=Ivaylo S. Ivanov|date=2000|page=92|accessdate=13 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under those chaotic circumstances a Bulgarian delegation arrived in Thessaloniki to ask for an armistice. On 29 September, the Bulgarians were granted the [[Armistice of Salonica]] by General d'Esperey. The Bulgarian downfall turned the strategic and operational balance of the war against the [[Central Powers]]. The Macedonian Front was brought to an end at noon on 30 September, when the ceasefire came into effect, and the Radomir Rebellion was put down, by Bulgarian forces, as of the 2 October. Tsar [[Ferdinand I of Bulgaria]] abdicated and went into exile the following day.{{sfn|Falls|1935|pp=246–253}}{{sfn|Korsun|1939|pp=105–108}}{{sfn|Doughty|2005|p=491}}

The British Army headed east towards the European side of the [[Ottoman Empire]], while the French and Serbian forces continued north. The British Army neared Constantinople and, without a force capable to stopping the advance, the Ottoman government asked for an armistice (the [[Armistice of Mudros]]) on 26 October. In Serbia, &quot;Desperate Frankie&quot; (as the British nicknamed d'Esperey) continued to advance and [[Liberation of Serbia, Albania and Montenegro (1918)|the Serbo-French Army re-captured the country]], overrunning several weak German divisions that tried to block its push near [[Niš]]. On 3 November, Austria-Hungary was forced to sign an [[Armistice of Villa Giusti|armistice]] on the Italian Front ending the war there. On 10 November, d'Esperey's army crossed the [[Danube]] river and was poised to enter the [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungarian]] heartland. At the request of the French general, Count [[Mihály Károlyi]], leading the Hungarian government, came to Belgrade and signed another armistice.{{sfn|Falls|1935|pp=254–279}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Macedonia|Bulgaria|Serbia|World War I}}
* [[Treaty of Neuilly-sur-Seine]]
* [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]]

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book |first=Aristeidis|last=Omiridis Skylitzes|title=Ο Ελληνικός Στρατός κατά τον Πρώτον Παγκόσμιον Πόλεμον, Τόμος Δεύτερος, Η Συμμετοχή της Ελλάδος εις τον Πόλεμον 1918|trans-title=Hellenic Army During the First World War 1914–1918: Hellenic Participation in the War 1918 |volume=II |publisher=Hellenic Army History Department|language=Greek|location=Athens|year=1961 |oclc= |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Richard|last=Hall|title=Balkan Breakthrough: The Battle of Dobro Pole 1918|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=2010|isbn=978-0-253-35452-5}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Fritz|last=Fischer|title=Germany’s Aims in the First World War|publisher=W.W. Norton|location=New York|year=1967|isbn=978-0-393-09798-6}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Athanasios|last=Geramanis|title=Πολεμική Ιστορία Νεωτέρας Ελλάδος: Επιχειρήσεις εν Μακεδονία κατά τον Α' παγκόσμιον πόλεμον 1915–1918|trans-title=Military History of Modern Greece Operations in Macedonia During WWI 1915–1918|volume=IV|language=Greek|publisher=Kefallinos|location=Athens|year=1980}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Nikolay|last=Korsun|title=Балканский фронт мировой войны 1914–1918 гг.|trans-title=Balkan Front of the World War 1914–1918 |language=Russian|publisher=Boenizdat|location=Moscow|year=1939 |oclc=7970969}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Falls|1933}}
|series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Military Operations Macedonia: From the Outbreak of War to the Spring of 1917 |volume=I |last=Falls |first=C.|year=1996 |orig-year=1933 |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |edition=Imperial War Museum and Battery Press |isbn=0-89839-242-X}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Falls|1935}}
|series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Military Operations Macedonia: From the Spring of 1917 to the End of the War |volume=II |last=Falls |first=C. |year=1996 |orig-year=1935 |publisher=HMSO |edition=Imperial War Museum and Battery Press |location=Nashville, TN |isbn=0-89839-243-8}}
* {{cite book|ref={{harvid|Doughty|2005}}
|title=Pyrrhic Victory: French Strategy and Operations in the Great War |last=Doughty |first=R. A. |location=Cambridge, MA |publisher=The Belknap Press of Harvard University |year=2005 |isbn=0-674-01880-X}}
* {{cite book |ref=harv |first=Luigi |last=Villari |title=The Macedonian Campaign |publisher=T. Fisher Unwin |location=London |year=1922 |url=https://ia600507.us.archive.org/4/items/macedoniancampai00vill/macedoniancampai00vill.pdf |accessdate=13 September 2015 |oclc=6388448}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|Albertini|1953}}
|last=Albertini|first=Luigi|authorlink=Luigi Albertini|title=Origins of the War of 1914|volume=II|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=1953|oclc=168712}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Willmott |first=H.P. |year=2003 |title=World War I |location=New York |publisher=Dorling Kindersley |isbn=0-7894-9627-5 |oclc=52541937}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Kristian|last=Coates Ulrichsen|title=The First World War in the Middle East|publisher=Hurst|location=London|year=2014|isbn=978-1849042741}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book |first=Nikola|last=Nedev |title=Дойранската епопея 1915 - 1918|trans-title=The Doiran Epopee 1915 - 1918|location=Sofia|language=Bulgarian|year= 1923|publisher=Armeiski voenno-izdatelski fond|isbn= 978-954-8247-05-4}}
* {{cite book|first=Alfred|last=Dieterich|title=Weltkriegsende an der mazedonischen Front|trans-title=The End of the World War at the Macedonian Front|publisher=Gerhard Stalling|location=Berlin|language=German|year=1928|url=http://digi.landesbibliothek.at/viewer/image/AC00633956/1/#topDocAnchor|accessdate=13 September 2015|oclc=248900490}}
* {{cite book|first= Andrej|last=Mitrović|title=Serbia's Great War, 1914–1918|publisher=Hurst|location=London|year=2007|isbn=978-1-55753-477-4}}
* {{cite book|first=Collinson|last=Owen|title=Salonica and After the Sideshow That Ended the War|publisher=Forgotten Books|location=Charleston, SC|year=2012|asin=B008VGLK3Q}}
{{refend}}

{{Bulgaria in World War I}}

{{coord|41|03|N|21|53|E|region:GR_source:kolossus-itwiki|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dobro Pole}}
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Serbia]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Bulgaria]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Greece]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of the Balkans Theatre (World War I)]]
[[Category:1918 in Serbia]]
[[Category:1918 in Bulgaria]]
[[Category:Vardar Macedonia (1912–18)]]
[[Category:Macedonian Front]]</text>
      <sha1>hwz40yrjnn6zxpu25h3a4i543nirbjz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
