<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Wanat</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18424092</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750287188</id>
      <parentid>746684628</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T21:22:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Imminent77</username>
        <id>29246608</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fix duplicate ref names – [[:Category:Pages with duplicate reference names|You can help!]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="49330">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Wanat
|partof=the [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|War in Afghanistan]]
|image=Battle of Wanat.jpg
|caption= U.S. Army soldiers guarding Vehicle Patrol Base Kahler the day before the battle.
|date=July 13, 2008
|place=[[Nuristan Province]], [[Afghanistan]]
|result= U.S. and Afghan victory; Taliban attack repulsed
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1960}}
* {{army|United States|name=U.S. Army}}
{{flag|Afghanistan}}
*[[File:Afghan National Army emblem.svg|25px]] [[Afghan National Army|Afghan Army]]
|combatant2={{flagdeco|Afghanistan|Taliban}} [[Taliban insurgency|Taliban]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of Hezbi Islami Gulbuddin.svg}} [[Hezb-e Islami Gulbuddin|Hezb-i-Islami]]&lt;br /&gt;and others&lt;ref name=jazeera14/&gt;
|commander1={{nowrap|{{flagdeco|United States|1960}} Captain Matthew Myer}}
|commander2={{nowrap|{{flagdeco|Afghanistan|Taliban}} Sheikh Dost Mohammad}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://paktribune.com/news/index.shtml?203161|title=Taliban claim killing 20 US troops in Kunar|work=[[Pak Tribune]]|quote=&quot;Dozens die as US jets bomb civilians&quot;|date=July 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Mawlawi Usman]] Hizb-i-Islami leader
|units1=2nd [[Platoon]], Chosen Company, 2nd Battalion, [[503rd Infantry Regiment]] (Airborne), [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]]
|units2=[[Taliban insurgents]]
|strength1=48 U.S. soldiers&lt;br /&gt;24 Afghan soldiers&lt;br /&gt;Close-Air Support&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;
|strength2=200&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;-500&lt;ref name=&quot;joint&quot;/&gt; fighters
|casualties1=9 killed, 27 wounded (U.S.)&lt;br /&gt;4 wounded (ANA)&lt;ref name=jazeera14&gt;{{cite web|url = http://english.aljazeera.net/news/asia/2008/07/200871463317512597.html |publisher = Al Jazeera|title=Taliban fighters storm US base|accessdate = 2008-07-16| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080716011635/http://english.aljazeera.net/news/asia/2008/07/200871463317512597.html| archivedate= 16 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;
|casualties2=21–52 killed, 45 wounded&lt;br /&gt;(U.S. claim)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/Story?id=5373104&amp;page=2|title=Taliban Flexing Muscle in Afghanistan|publisher=[[ABC News]]|author=Martinez, Luis|date=July 15, 2008|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Associated Press]]|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/11/04/AR2008110403571.html?sub=AR|title=Police, Locals Implicated In Attack|date=November 5, 2008|page=14|accessdate=2009-10-12 | work=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gall&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stripes.com&quot; /&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox US war in Afghanistan}}
The '''Battle of Wanat''' occurred on July 13, 2008, when about 200 [[Taliban]] guerrillas attacked [[NATO]] troops near [[Quam, Afghanistan|Quam]], in the [[Waygal district]] in [[Afghanistan]]'s far eastern province of [[Nuristan Province|Nuristan]]. The position was defended primarily by [[United States Army]] soldiers of the 2nd [[Platoon]], Chosen Company, 2nd Battalion, [[503rd Infantry Regiment]] (Airborne), [[173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team]].

The Taliban surrounded the remote base and its observation post, attacking it from Quam and surrounding farmland. They destroyed much of the U.S. heavy munitions, broke through American lines, and entered the main base before being repelled by artillery and aircraft. The United States claimed to have killed at least 21 Taliban fighters for the loss of nine U.S. soldiers killed and 27 wounded, and four Afghan National Army (ANA) soldiers wounded. The U.S. deaths were the most in a single battle since the start of U.S. operations in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/Wanat.pdf|title= Wanat: Combat Action in Afghanistan, 2008|author=U.S. Army Combat Studies Institute|year=2010|work=U.S. Army Combined Arms Center|publisher= Combined Studies Institute Press|accessdate= 20 November 2010 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101202045613/http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/wanat.pdf| archivedate= 2 December 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}; http://militarytimes.com/news/2009/09/army_wanat_investigation_093009/&lt;/ref&gt;

The Battle of Wanat has been described as one of the bloodiest Taliban attacks of the war and one of several attacks on remote outposts.&lt;ref name=&quot;deadlyattack&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/05/world/asia/05afghan.html?_r=0|title=Attacks on Remote Posts Highlight Afghan Risks |last=Tavernise|first=Sabrina|author2=SANGAR RAHIMI|date=October 4, 2009 |publisher=New York Times|accessdate=October 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to previous roadside bombings and haphazard attacks and ambushes, this attack was well-coordinated with fighters from many insurgent groups with an effort that was disciplined and sustained which was able to precisely target key equipment such as a wire-guided missile launcher.

The battle became the focus of debate in the United States, generating &quot;a great deal of interest and scrutiny among military professionals and from outside observers&quot; mainly due to the relatively &quot;significant number of coalition casualties&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Staff of the US Army Combat Studies Institute 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/Wanat.pdf|title= Wanat: Combat Action in Afghanistan, 2008|author= Staff of the US Army Combat Studies Institute|year= 2010|work= US Army Combined Arms Center|publisher= Combined Studies Institute Press|accessdate= 20 November 2010 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101202045613/http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/wanat.pdf| archivedate= 2 December 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several investigations were launched into events leading up to the battle. The initial investigation was completed in August 2008. In July 2009, Senator [[Jim Webb|James Webb]] requested that the U.S. Army formally investigate the battle and previous investigation. Lieutenant General [[Richard F. Natonski]] conducted another investigation in late 2009 which led to orders of reprimand for the chain of command. In June 2010, the U.S. Army revoked the reprimands. They stated that no negligence was involved and said of the soldiers that &quot;by their valor and their skill, they successfully defended their positions and defeated a determined, skillful, and adaptable enemy&quot;.

==Background==
[[File:Map of Nuristan Province.png|thumb|300px|Waygal District in the [[Nuristan Province]] in Afghanistan]]
In 2008, NATO forces in southeastern Afghanistan deployed sub-company-sized patrols to the Pakistan border to disrupt supplies flowing to the Taliban from the Federally Administered Tribal Regions of Pakistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;joint&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2008/07/joint_al_qaeda_and_t.php |title = Joint al Qaeda and Taliban force behind Nuristan base attack|publisher=Long War Journal|date=July 14, 2008|accessdate = 2008-07-18| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080803031341/http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2008/07/joint_al_qaeda_and_t.php| archivedate= 3 August 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; They established small patrol bases, which came under regular attack by Taliban forces.&lt;ref name=abc14&gt;{{cite web|url = http://abcnews.go.com/International/Story?id=5373104&amp;page=1|author=Martinez, Luis|date=July 14, 2008|title =Even 500 Lbs Bombs Couldn't Stop Taliban |publisher=ABC News|accessdate = 2008-07-16| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080715140723/http://www.abcnews.go.com/International/story?id=5373104&amp;page=1| archivedate= 15 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Rock Move OPLAN 8–9 July 2008.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Rock Move OPLAN 8–9 July 2008. The result of the move was the establishment of a Coalition outpost at Wanat]]
[[File:Wanat-Proposed COP.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Proposal for COP at Wanat]]
In June, a small contingent of 48 American and 24 Afghan troops, 72 in total, were operating in and around Wanat, a mountain Quam that was the center of the Waygal District government and about five miles from the coalition military base Camp Blessing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gall&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author1=Gall, Carlotta |author2=Eric Schmitt |lastauthoramp=yes |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/15/world/asia/15afghan.html?hp|title=Taliban Breached NATO Base In Deadly Clash|date=July 15, 2008|page=6|accessdate=2009-10-12 | work=The [[New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stripes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author1=Harris, Kent |author2=Joseph Giordono |lastauthoramp=yes |url=http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=58714|title=Report details attack on GIs in Afghanistan|publisher=[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]]|date=November 9, 2008|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite journal|author=Wiltrout, Kate|title=Soldier From Eastern Shore Recounts Deadly Battle In Afghanistan|journal=[[Virginian-Pilot]]|date=July 19, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 4, a U.S. Army helicopter attacked vehicles they claimed were firing on them and killed 17 people. Locals claimed those killed were civilians, including doctors and nurses from a local clinic. Both sides reported Forward Observation Base Bella was under attack by indirect fire.  Intel reports said that the FOB was going to be overrun from within the base as well. The helicopter attack was in response to the indirect fire received from a mortar tube that was being fired from the bed of a Toyota Hilux pick-up. The initial Taliban radio transmissions that were intercepted reported that the &quot;Big Gun had been hit&quot; (mortar tube) and the Taliban commander had been killed. A few hours after the helicopter attacked, with the Chosen Company commander and the troops in contact confirming the targets, the Taliban radio reports changed to &quot;they killed the shop keeper (that had the same name as the Taliban commander), the big gun was not damaged and all the enemy wounded and KIA were civilians.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;JSalazar&lt;/ref&gt; Five days before the battle, on July 8, a platoon from the Second Battalion, 503rd Infantry Regiment, 173rd Airborne Brigade Combat Team established Vehicle Patrol Base (VPB) Kahler and a separate observation post called &quot;OP Top Side&quot; near Wanat. 8 July, 2nd Platoon, Chosen Company, departed from Camp Blessing after sunset in a ground assault convoy for the 90-minute-long drive to Wanat. The convoy contained five M1114 armored [[Humvee]]s. There was one for each of the three rifle squads, a vehicle for platoon headquarters, and the last vehicle containing the TOW missile squad. The Humvees mounted heavy weapons, two with [[M2 Browning|50-cal machine guns]], and two with [[Mk 19 grenade launcher|MK-19 40mm automatic grenade launchers]] in protected cupolas to provide extra firepower and protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;Staff of the US Army Combat Studies Institute 2010&quot;/&gt; Their goal was to create a Combat Outpost (COP) to connect with and provide security for the local populace, coordinate $1.4 million in reconstruction projects, and disrupt Taliban activity.&lt;ref name=Almost&gt;{{cite journal|title=Almost A Lost Cause|author=Jaffe, Greg|journal=[[Washington Post]]|date=October 4, 2009|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The brigade was to be relieved by a newly arriving U.S. Army unit in two weeks.&lt;ref name=Another&gt;{{cite journal|author=Jaffe, Greg|title=Not 'Just Another Casualty'|journal=[[Washington Post]]|date=October 5, 2009|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The patrol base was situated on an open field about 300 meters long by 100 meters wide surrounded on two sides by buildings which composed the Quam. July 9, a six-man engineer squad arrived by Chinook helicopter. They brought a [[Bobcat Company|Bobcat loader]] and a shipping container with engineer equipment. The soldiers reinforced the base with existing terrain, sandbags, barbed wire, and used the Bobcat to fill a number of [[Hesco bastion|HESCO barriers]] (essentially wall-sized sandbags) around the three squad positions and to create a firing pit for the big 120-mm mortar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Staff of the US Army Combat Studies Institute 2010&quot;/&gt; However, the Bobcat broke down for one day, and could not lift high enough to place barriers to a 7-foot height, but were placed to just a 4-foot level, which would make it vulnerable to direct fire from guns or rockets which the attackers would exploit. The troops dug many of the fortifications and trenches with hand shovels.&lt;ref name=studydetails&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.armytimes.com/news/2009/08/ap_afghanistan_battle_080109/
|publisher = Army Times|title=Study gives new details on deadly Wanat battle |accessdate = 2011-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Still in preparation at the time of the attack, some areas were only protected by a barrier of concertina wire, but with no posts or stakes, the wire was just placed on the ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot;/&gt;

The Afghan company contracted to bring heavy construction equipment delayed its arrival to until 13 July. It was decided that soldier labor with the aid of an engineer squad and a Bobcat front end loader already at Bella would be good enough to prepare an initial defense in the six days until heavier equipment arrived. The number of men at the base was judged enough to defend against intelligence estimates that placed the insurgent forces in the local area at only about 150 experienced fighters, though they did not know that attackers would be backed up by other guerrilla groups from neighboring regions as far away as Pakistan and Kashmir. While they thought it was possible the base might be attacked while the camp was being prepared, they thought it unlikely. Platoon Sergeant Dzwik later remarked &quot;I was expecting harassing fire from any one of the high ground in every direction. I did not think the village itself would let the AAF [Anti-Afghan Force] turn their village into a battle zone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/Wanat.pdf|title= Wanat: Combat Action in Afghanistan, 2008|author= Staff of the US Army Combat Studies Institute|year= 2010|work= US Army Combined Arms Center|publisher= Combined Studies Institute Press|page=77|accessdate= 20 November 2010 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101202045613/http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/wanat.pdf| archivedate= 2 December 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Soldiers at the base noticed warning signs, including groups of men watching the construction from the nearby village, which was set at a higher elevation than the outpost, and other groups of men moving through nearby mountains. At a dinner meeting in the village, a villager told the Americans that they should shoot any men seen in the mountains, and asked them if U.S. UAVs were keeping watch nearby.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=Missteps&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Bernton, Hal |author2=Cheryl Phillips |lastauthoramp=yes |title=Army's Missteps Set Stage For Tragedy, Study Finds|journal=[[Seattle Times]]|date=July 31, 2009|page=1| format=(Link in ''[[Military Times]]'')|url=http://militarytimes.com/news/2009/08/ap_afghanistan_battle_080109/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The day before the attack, the militants began flowing water through an irrigation ditch feeding an unused field, creating background noise that masked the sounds of the advancing fighters.

Although the Americans believed that 100 or 200 attacked the base, a senior Afghan defense ministry official who did not reveal his name told Al Jazeera that he had information it was between 400 and 500 fighters. Tamim Nuristani, former governor of Nuristan, believed that numerous Taliban and Pakistani militant and terrorist groups banded together from surrounding regions including Kunar and the Bajaur tribal agency in neighboring Pakistan. According to U.S. intelligence groups operating in the region included Taliban, al-Qaeda, Kashmir-based [[Lashkar-e-Taiba]] and Pakistan-based,(as of 2013 still located in 1 of many strongholds in the Bajaur agency of F.A.T.A.-Federally administered Tribal areas in Kunar and Nuristan of Afghanistan), Hezb-i-Islami. According to the ''Long War Journal'', Al Qaeda's senior leadership including [[Ayman al Zawahiri]] and [[Osama Bin Laden]] were thought to shelter in the region (Bin Laden was then in Pakistan).&lt;ref name=&quot;joint&quot;/&gt; Taliban spokesman stated &quot;The fighting in Afghanistan is getting heavier. When the Americans drop bombs on civilians ordinary people want revenge – that's why they are joining the Taliban, strengthening us&quot; pointing out their &quot;ability to enter the bases and kill Americans.&quot; A NATO spokesman believed that the Taliban had moved into and expelled a nearby Khel (small village-tribe subdivision) for the attack. On the evening of July 12, Taliban soldiers moved into Wanat and ordered the villagers to leave. Undetected by the I.S.A.F./A.N.S.F. soldiers, they set up firing positions inside Kors and a mosque next to and overlooking the perimeter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;

==Battle==
About 4:20&amp;nbsp;a.m. on July 13, Taliban forces opened fire on the base with  [[machine gun]]s, [[rocket-propelled grenade]]s, and [[mortar (weapon)|mortars]]. Another 100 militants attacked the observation post from farmland to the east.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gall&quot; /&gt;

The initial attack hit the forward operating base's mortar pit, knocking out the 120mm mortar and detonating the stockpile of mortar ammunition. The insurgents next destroyed the [[BGM-71 TOW|Humvee-mounted TOW missile launcher]] inside the combat outpost with coordinated fire from unguided RPG rockets. The mortars and TOW launcher which were to provide the heaviest and most accurate firepower had been quickly taken out by the attackers. The explosion of the mortar shells hurled the anti-tank missiles into the command post.&lt;ref name=Review&gt;{{cite news |author=Shanker, Thom |title=U.S. Review Of Battle Disaster Sways Strategy On Afghanistan |work=[[New York Times]] |date=October 3, 2009 |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From the American perspective, the most serious situation was the attack concentrated on a small team situated at the small observation post &quot;TOPSIDE&quot; nestled among rocks under a tree 50m to 70m outside the main base. The first round hit accurately, wounding or stunning every soldier. Pfc. Tyler Stafford was blown out of his machine-gun position next to Spc. Matthew Phillips who threw a grenade before he was mortally wounded. Cpl. Jason Bogar fired hundreds of rounds from his automatic weapon until the barrel became white-hot and jammed and then tended to Stafford's wounds. A rocket grenade wounded Sgt. [[Ryan M. Pitts]], who was also tended by Bogar with a tourniquet around Pitts' leg before switching to another gun. Bogar then jumped from the outpost bunker to get close enough to kill insurgents who were firing down upon the men from the village hotel.  Once outside the bunker, he was shot through the chest and killed.  The surviving soldiers then ran from the outpost to the main post, leaving Pitts behind.  Alone, Pitts was able to hold-off the Taliban from overrunning his position until his comrades returned two hours later and he was evacuated to receive medical care.&lt;ref&gt;Carroll, Chris, &quot;[http://www.stripes.com/news/us/soldier-in-storied-battle-of-wanat-to-be-given-medal-of-honor-1.290285 Soldier in storied Battle of Wanat to be given Medal of Honor]&quot;, ''[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]]'', 23 June 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

Four U.S. soldiers were killed within the first 20 minutes of the battle, another died later, and at least three others were wounded. Three times teams of soldiers from the main base ran through Taliban fire to resupply the observation post and carry back the dead and wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stripes.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=56237 |title=Soldiers recount deadly attack on Afghanistan outpost| publisher=Stars and Stripes |date=July 19, 2008 |accessdate=October 12, 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090910100544/http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=56237 |archivedate=September 10, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Harris, Kent |url=http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=63595 |title=NCO receives Silver Star for valor in '08 battle at Wanat |journal=[[Military Times]] |date=July 5, 2009 |accessdate=October 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. troops responded with machine guns, [[grenade]]s, and [[claymore mine]]s.  Artillery guns at Camp Blessing fired 96 155mm artillery rounds. The Taliban briefly breached the wire of the observation post before being driven back. After almost half an hour of intense fighting at the observation post, only one soldier remained. He was seriously wounded and fought alone until reinforcements arrived. Some militants also managed to get past the main base's eastern barriers.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Two American soldiers, platoon leader [[First Lieutenant]] Jonathan P. Brostrom, 24, of Hawaii and Corporal Jason Hovater, were killed trying to deliver ammunition to the observation post.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Blitzer, Wolf |author2=Barbara Starr  |lastauthoramp=yes |title=Soldier Discusses Deadly July 13 Attack By Taliban Forces |work=[[The Situation Room]] |publisher=CNN |date=August 19, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  American soldiers were at times flushed out of their fortifications by what they thought were grenades, but which were actually rocks thrown by the attackers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stripes.com&quot; /&gt;  Brostrom, Hovater, and another soldier may have been killed by an insurgent who penetrated the wire perimeter.&lt;ref name=Review/&gt;

[[Boeing AH-64 Apache|AH-64 Apache]] attack helicopters and a [[General Atomics MQ-1 Predator|Predator]] unmanned aircraft drone armed with [[AGM-114 Hellfire|Hellfire]] missiles arrived over the base about 30 minutes after the battle began. During the battle, U.S. soldiers were resupplied by UH-60 Blackhawk helicopter with fire support from the AH-64 Apache Helicopters. Injured troops were evacuated to nearby Camp Wright, where members of E Troop, 2nd–17th Cavalry, 101st Airborne Division would wait to rearm and refuel the UH-60's and AH-64's.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;  Later, a [[Rockwell B-1 Lancer|B-1B Lancer]] bomber, [[Fairchild Republic A-10 Thunderbolt II|A-10]], and [[McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagle|F-15E Strike Eagle]] aircraft were called in. The militants withdrew about four hours later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;  After the militants retreated, mop up operations followed, and the Taliban withdrew from the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gall&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Wood, David |url=http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/bal-te.airstrikes28jul28,0,6638715.story |title=Afghan air war grows in intensity |work=[[Baltimore Sun]] |date=July 28, 2008 |page=1|accessdate=October 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nine U.S. soldiers were killed in the attack,&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite web|url =http://www.defenselink.mil/releases/release.aspx?releaseid=12071 |title = DoD Identifies Army Casualties&amp;nbsp;... |publisher = Department of Defense |accessdate=July 18, 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080726041410/http://www.defenselink.mil//releases/release.aspx?releaseid=12071| archivedate=26 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; mainly in the observation post.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://starbulletin.com/2008/07/17/news/story02.html |title = Hawaii soldier killed in Afghanistan&amp;nbsp;... |publisher=Star Bulletin |accessdate=July 17, 2008 |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080720122642/http://starbulletin.com/2008/07/17/news/story02.html| archivedate=20 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Between 21 and 52 militants were reported killed with another 20 to 40 wounded, but coalition forces found only two Taliban bodies after the battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gall&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stripes.com&quot; /&gt; The attack was the highest death toll for American troops in the country since [[Operation Red Wings]] three years earlier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/asiapcf/07/14/afghan.violence/index.html |title='Heroic' fighting repels Afghan militants|publisher=CNN |accessdate=July 16, 2008 |date=July 14, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080717043347/http://edition.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/asiapcf/07/14/afghan.violence/index.html| archivedate= 17 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational issues==
[[File:COP Kahler 13 July 2008.jpg|thumb|400px|Combat Outpost Kahler – 13 July 2008. Observation post is to the upper right of the main camp with buildings and mosque at and overlooking the edge of the northern perimeter]]
Civilian deaths caused by allied operations had increased sympathy among Waygal residents for the Taliban, who were allowed to move into the Quam. The residents may have been further dismayed by the failure of the Afghan president, [[Hamid Karzai]], to address the concerns of a delegation of elders and maliks in [[Kabul]] two days previously.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.economist.com/world/asia/displaystory.cfm?story_id=11751374|journal=The Economist|title = Dawn Raid|accessdate = 2008-07-31|date=July 17, 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080730215642/http://www.economist.com/world/asia/displaystory.cfm?story_id=11751374| archivedate= 30 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Coalition troops had noticed other warning signs. The day before the attack, the &quot;Spin Giris&quot; (Pashto for &quot;White Beards&quot; – influential tribal elders) of Wanat conducted a [[Jirga]], (elder community council-experienced male members of the Quam have a right to attend), without the post's Officer-in-Charge. As well, the villagers began pouring waste water into an area of dead space near the post more frequently, which may have concealed the movement of militants within the village.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;

A 2009 U.S. Army report criticized the brigade commander, Colonel Chip Preysler, and the battalion commander, Lieutenant Colonel William Ostlund, citing the lack of supplies, equipment, and drinking water for troops stationed in Wanat. At the same time, the report praised the performance of its soldiers under fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;ricks.foreignpolicy.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ricks.foreignpolicy.com/posts/2009/07/23/wanat_viii_an_army_report_finds_a_major_coin_failure|title=Army Report Finds A Major COIN Failure|work=Foreign Policy|publisher=Slate Group|accessdate=2009-10-12|date=October 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The same report criticized the actions of the involved commanding officers as being counterproductive to military goals, stating that &quot;The highly kinetic approach favored by TF Rock&amp;nbsp;... rapidly and inevitably degraded the relationships between the U.S. Army and the Waigal population.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ricks.foreignpolicy.com&quot; /&gt;

This statement, portraying the operational approaches of the 173rd Airborne Brigade (TF Bayonet) and 2-503 PIR (TF Rock) in a negative light, is contradicted by David Kilcullen in his book, ''The Accidental Guerrilla''. Kilcullen stated that in March 2008,

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The fact that Kunar has bucked the general trend [downward trend in security across the country] seems largely to be the result of a consistent U.S. strategy of partnering with local communities to separate the insurgents from the people, bring tangible benefits of governance and development to the population, and help the population choose their own local Khan's(Protectors,usually military), through elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Accidental Guerilla|last= Kilcullin|first= David|year= 2009|publisher= Oxford University Press|location= New York|isbn= 978-0-19-536834-5|pages= 70–71}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Kilcullen also noted a statement by a previous U.S. commander in Kunar regarding LTC William Ostlund, the 2-503 commander: &quot;Bill O. understood deeply that the effect of Coalition operations ''on the people'' was the key question.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Accidental Guerilla|last= Kilcullin|first= David|year= 2009|publisher= Oxford University Press|location= New York|isbn= 978-0-19-536834-5|pages= 93–94}} Statement by &quot;LTC Colonel Chris Cavoli, battalion commander of 1–32 Infantry in the Kunar valley in 2005–2006.&quot; The italics in the quotes are from the source.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

===U.S. withdrawal===
After the battle, Major General [[Jeffrey J. Schloesser]], U.S. Army commander of coalition troops in Regional Command East, Afghanistan, decided to abandon the patrol base and sent additional U.S. troops to assist the base evacuation.&lt;ref name=Another-2&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Associated Press|title=Remote Afghan Outpost Reinforced After Attack That Killed 9 U.S. Troops|date=July 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Three days after the engagement the United States and Afghan armies withdrew from Wanat. An [[International Security Assistance Force|ISAF]] statement says ISAF and Afghan security forces &quot;will continue to perform regular patrols near the village of Wanat.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.nato.int/isaf/docu/pressreleases/2008/07-july/pr080716-320.html |title = ISAF presence will be maintained in Wanat, PR# 2008-320, 2008-07-16|author = International Security Assistance Force|date=July 16, 2008 |accessdate = 2008-07-19| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080801203520/http://www.nato.int/isaf/docu/pressreleases/2008/07-july/pr080716-320.html| archivedate= 1 August 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The coalition forces continued to maintain a larger patrol base about four miles away from Wanat and concentrated on protecting the larger [[Pech River]] Valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Jaffe, Greg|title=They Feel Like Outsiders And They Don't Want To Be|journal=[[Washington Post]]|date=October 6, 2009|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The district police force for the area was disarmed by the Americans and the district chief and police chief were briefly detained and questioned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/world/asia/articles/2008/07/15/govt_7_militants_killed_in_eastern_afghanistan/ |title=19 insurgents killed in Afghanistan |agency=Associated Press |publisher=Boston Globe |date=July 15, 2008 |accessdate=2008-07-18 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080726141248/http://www.boston.com/news/world/asia/articles/2008/07/15/govt_7_militants_killed_in_eastern_afghanistan/ |archivedate=2008-07-26 |deadurl=yes |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both were released within 24 hours according to a spokesperson for the district chief.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;

Speaking at a Pentagon news conference after the attack, U.S. Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Navy Admiral Mike Mullen said the incident indicated that &quot;all involved with operations on the (Pakistan-Afghanistan, especially the pourous Kunar, Kashmir, and Nuristan), border must do a better job of policing the region and eliminating the extremists' safe havens in Pakistan's federally administered tribal areas that are launching pads for attacks on coalition forces.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.defenselink.mil/news/newsarticle.aspx?id=50526 |title = Pakistan Must Do More to Police Tribal Zone, Defense Leaders Say|publisher=American Forces Press Service|date=July 16, 2008|accessdate = 2008-07-19| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080722101151/http://www.defenselink.mil/news/newsarticle.aspx?id=50526| archivedate= 22 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Associated Press reported that the attack underscored a general gain in strength of Afghan militants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/25698636/ |title = U.S. troops quit remote Afghan base after attack|author = MSNBC |accessdate = 2008-07-16| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080717185746/http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/25698636/| archivedate= 17 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the 173rd Brigade Commander, Colonel Charles Preysler, specifically rebutted that conclusion in an interview on July 20, 2008. He stated that previous media accounts of the engagement mischaracterized the level of development of the platoon's defences. He also said that the withdrawal of the platoon did not constitute &quot;abandoning&quot; the position because no permanent defensive infrastructure was developed or left behind. He further stated that the position was &quot;not overrun in any shape, manner, or form&quot;, adding that, &quot;It was close combat to be sure&amp;nbsp;— hand grenade range.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|quote=Colonel Preysler was a battalion commander during Operation Anaconda in March of 2002|url=http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=56252|title=Commander: Media reports on Afghanistan battle were exaggerated|publisher=Stars and Stripes|date=July 20, 2008|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===U.S. Army investigation===
[[File:View of COP Wanat and OP Topside.jpg|thumb|right|300px|View of Wanat COP looking east from mortar position with 2nd Squad position, the bazaar and OP Topside's later location in the background, 9 July 2008.]]
An investigation by the U.S. Army, completed on August 13 and released to the public the first week of November 2008, found that the Taliban attackers had been assisted by the Afghan local police (ALP), forces and a district leader. The evidence included large stocks of weapons and ammunition discovered in the police barracks in Wanat after the battle. The stocks were much more than could be used by the villages' 20-man police force and included dirty weapons which appeared to have been used recently. In response to the report, Schloesser concluded that the governor and local police chief &quot;had probably been acting under duress and had been cooperative with American troops.&quot;  The governor was absolved of blame in the attack but it was unclear about what was done with the local police chief.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Schmitt, Eric|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/04/world/asia/04military.html?partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss|title=Afghan Officials Aided an Attack on U.S. Soldiers|work=The [[New York Times]]|date=November 3, 2008|page=1|accessdate=2009-10-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The investigation also examined whether the Army had intelligence about a possible assault and whether the troops had access to it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Starr|first=Barbara|author2=Jamie McIntyre|title=Military looking at intelligence before deadly Afghan clash|url=http://www.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/asiapcf/07/17/afghan.probe/index.html|publisher=CNN|date=2008-07-17|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The report found that despite reports earlier in July that 200 to 300 militants had been massing to attack another remote outpost in the vicinity, including numerous reports from local villagers that an attack was imminent, the commanders at Wanat had no reason to expect such a large frontal assault. The report, however, criticized the &quot;incredible amount of time&quot;&amp;nbsp;— 10 months&amp;nbsp;— it took NATO military leaders to negotiate arrangements over the site of the outpost, giving the Taliban plenty of time to coordinate and plan an attack on the base.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt&quot; /&gt;

===Further actions===
In July 2009, U.S. Senator [[Jim Webb|James Webb]] asked the U.S. DoD [[Inspector General]] to formally examine the battle and the U.S. Army's investigation into the event. In his request, Webb cited an unreleased report from the Army's [[Combat Studies Institute]] by a contractor, Douglas Cubbison, that criticized how senior Army leaders in Afghanistan, especially Ostlund and Preyser, acted before the assault at Wanat. According to that report, soldiers at the Wanat base were critically short of basic necessities such as water and sandbags and had complained repeatedly, to no avail, that their base was in a precarious position.&lt;ref name=Review/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jaffe, Greg 2009, p. 13&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Jaffe, Greg|title=Army Brass Conduct Before Afghan Attack Is Questioned|journal=[[Washington Post]]|date=July 24, 2009|page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=O'Connor, Phillip|title=Soldier's Dad Gets Wish For Inquiry|journal=[[St. Louis Post-Dispatch]]|date=October 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Cubbison had written the report at the request of Lieutenant General [[William B. Caldwell IV]], commander of the [[United States Army Combined Arms Center]].&lt;ref name=Another-2/&gt; Cubbison wrote that a few days before the battle, on July 4, a U.S. Army helicopter mistakenly attacked and killed 17 civilians, including all of the doctors and nurses at a local clinic, infuriating local Afghans.{{Citation needed|date=August 2014}} Platoon leader Brostrom and company commander Captain Matthew Myer told their commanders that they expected a retaliatory attack and asked for extra surveillance. Brostrom's father, retired Army Colonel David. P. Brostrom, alerted Webb's office to the Army historian's report. Said Brostrom, &quot;After I read the report, I was sick to my stomach.&quot;&lt;ref name=Missteps/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jaffe, Greg 2009, p. 13&quot; /&gt;

Letters of reprimand were issued to Colonel Charles Preysler, Lieutenant Colonel William Ostlund and Captain Myer for &quot;failing to properly prepare defenses&quot; at Wanat, Pentagon officials said March 12.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luis Martinez&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/Afghanistan/silver-star-winner-capt-matthew-myer-reprimanded-attack/story?id=10080860|title= Silver Star Winner Reprimanded for Afghan Battle
|author= Luis Martinez|date= 12 March 2010|publisher= ABC News|accessdate= 6 June 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100425002251/http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/Afghanistan/silver-star-winner-capt-matthew-myer-reprimanded-attack/story?id=10080860| archivedate= 25 April 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
That same month, Myer was awarded the Silver Star for his actions during the battle of Wanat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luis Martinez&quot;/&gt;

On September 30, 2009, U.S. Central Command commander General [[David H. Petraeus]] appointed [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marine Corps]] Lieutenant General [[Richard F. Natonski]] to lead a new inquiry into the battle and which would look into related issues &quot;beyond the tactical level.&quot;&lt;ref name=Review/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=[[New York Times]]|title=New Review Ordered Of Fatal Clash In Afghanistan|date=October 1, 2009|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Shanker, Thom|title=Pentagon To Re-Examine 2008 Afghan Clash|journal=[[New York Times]]|date=October 2, 2009|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; A later review was conducted by General [[Charles C. Campbell (general)|Charles C. Campbell]] which &quot;focused on the totality of circumstances that included and affected actions at Wanat&quot;, including interviews of the officers involved, and reviews of previous investigations with the exception of the [[Fort Leavenworth]] [[Combat Studies Institute]] (CSI) narrative—stating that it had &quot;not undergone pre-publication vetting and academic review in accordance with standing CSI research protocols&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=U.S. Army |authorlink=United States Army |title=Wanat Review |date=23 June 2010 |type=News |url=http://www.army.mil/-news/2010/06/23/41241-wanat-review/ |archiveurl=http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20101202150500/http%3A//www%2Earmy%2Emil/%2Dnews/2010/06/23/41241%2Dwanat%2Dreview/ |archivedate= December 2, 2010 |deadurl=no |accessdate=6 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles_C_Campbell_Review&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first1=Charles C. |last1=Campbell |authorlink=Charles C. Campbell (general) |title=Army Action on the Re–Investigation into the Combat Action at Wanat Village, Wygal District, Nuristan Province, Afghanistan on 13&amp;nbsp;July 2008 |others=(Memorandum for the Honorable John M. McHugh, Secretary of the Army) |type=Redacted Report |date=13 May 2010 |publisher=[[United States Army Forces Command|Headquarters, U.S. Army Forces Command]] |pages=2–3 |url=http://usarmy.vo.llnwd.net/e1/wanat/downloads/campbellWanatReportRedacted.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716075735/http://usarmy.vo.llnwd.net/e1/wanat/downloads/campbellWanatReportRedacted.pdf |archivedate=7 July 2011 |deadurl=no |accessdate=6 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Campbell concluded that the officers involved were not at fault:

&lt;blockquote&gt;[The officers] were neither negligent nor derelict in the performance of their duties, exercising a degree of care that a reasonably prudent person would have exercised under the same or similar circumstance. To criminalize command decisions in a theater of complex combat operations is a grave step indeed. It is also unnecessary, particularly in this case. It is possible for officers to err in judgment—and to thereby incur censure—without violating a criminal statute. This is particularly true where the errors are those of omission, where the standards come from multiple non-punitive doctrinal publications, where there is less than complete and certain knowledge of enemy capabilities and intent, and where commanders enjoy wide discretion in their exercise of their command prerogatives and responsibilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles_C_Campbell_Review&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In June 2010, General Campbell revoked the officers' reprimands, citing that they would have a &quot;chilling effect&quot; on ground operations. The Army said that the second look at the incident proved that the officers were &quot;neither negligent nor derelict&quot; and &quot;by their valor and their skill, they successfully defended their positions and defeated a determined, skillful, and adaptable enemy who masses and attacks at times, ways and places of his choosing&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first1=Richard |last1=Lardner |date=23 June 2010 |title= Officers won't be punished over Afghan war |website=MSNBC.com |publisher=[[Associated Press]] |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/37883421/ns/world_news-south_and_central_asia |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100626121451/http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/37883421/ns/world_news-south_and_central_asia |archivedate=26 June 2010 |deadurl=no |accessdate=6 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Secretary of the Army John McHugh was also humbled by their courage, stating &quot;We remain grateful for and humbled by their extraordinary courage and valor.&quot;
Gen. George W. Casey Jr., Army chief of staff further commended the performance of the soldiers:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
In every review and study conducted to date, the courage, valor, and discipline of the soldiers who fought at Wanat have been universally praised. These soldiers were well-trained, well-led, and fought bravely to defeat a determined and intense enemy action to overrun their base in Wanat. They persevered in a fashion that deserves broad recognition of their bravery and tenacity. Our hearts go out to the families of the fallen soldiers.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Upset over Campbell's decision, family members of those killed in action wrote a letter to the [[Secretary of the Army]] asking that the findings of Natonski's investigation be upheld and the reprimands reinstated.  In addition to the family members, the letter was signed by Senators [[Daniel Akaka]], [[Jim Webb]], [[Saxby Chambliss]], [[Patty Murray]], and [[Claire McCaskill]].&lt;ref&gt;Cole, William, &quot;Senators Want Explanation For Army's Reversal On Wanat&quot;, ''[[Honolulu Advertiser]]'', July 23, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2010, the U.S. Army's Combat Studies Institute published a historical account of the Battle of Wanat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Staff of the US Army Combat Studies Institute 2010&quot;/&gt;  The official U.S. Army history of the battle, published in December 2010, places little blame on the senior officers involved, instead blaming the uncertain nature of war, mistakes by junior officers, lack of knowledge by Army officers on the Wanat region's complex political situation, and lack of intelligence that the attack forces would be drawn from the entire region, not just the local area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/12/28/AR2010122804334.html?hpid=topnews&amp;sid=ST2009100401053 |title= Army edits its history of the deadly battle of Wanat |author= Greg Jaffe|date= 29 December 2010|work= |publisher= Washington Post|accessdate= 31 December 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[Restrepo (film)|Restrepo]]'', a film made by reporters embedded into a similar observation post in the Korengal Valley. The Battle of Wanat is mentioned in the film when Battle Company hears the news of their sister company's losses.
* [[Battle of Nam Dong]], a 1964 battle in the [[Vietnam war]] where communist forces failed to overrun a special forces camp. The battle was dramatized in [[The Green Berets (film)]]
* [[Battle for Hill 3234]] Soviet paratroopers repel Afghan insurgent forces dramatized in the 2005 film ''[[The 9th Company]]''.
* ''[[Battle of Kamdesh]]'', a 2009 battle 20 miles from Wanat, the bloodiest battle for U.S. forces since the Battle of Wanat. An assault by 300 Taliban fighters resulted in eight Americans killed and 22 wounded, and prompt withdrawal from nearly destroyed base.
* [[Ryan M. Pitts]], who received the [[Medal of Honor]] for his actions during the Battle of Wanat.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Combat Studies Institute (U.S.), Combat Studies Institute (U.S.), and U.S. Army Combined Arms Center. ''Wanat: Combat Action in Afghanistan, 2008.'' Fort Leavenworth, Kan: Combat Studies Institute Press, United States Army Combined Arms Center, 2010. ISBN 0-9841901-8-X {{OCLC | 793852339}}
* Johnson, Robert. ''Outnumbered, Outgunned, Undeterred: Twenty Battles Against All Odds.'' New York: Thames &amp; Hudson, 2011. ISBN 0-500-25187-8 {{OCLC | 756058735}}
* Russell, Jesse. ''Battle of Wanat.''  [S.l.]: Book On Demand Ltd, 2012. ISBN 5-510-56639-6 {{OCLC | 855587728}}
* Steeb, Randall. ''Perspectives on the Battle of Wanat: Challenges Facing Small Unit Operations in Afghanistan.'' Santa Monica, CA: RAND, 2011. ISBN 0-8330-5322-1 {{OCLC | 755905563}}
* United States. ''Reinvestigation of Combat Action at Wanat Village, Afghanistan.'' Arlington, Va: Inspector General, Dept. of Defense, 2010. {{OCLC | 785896348}}

==External links==
{{wikinews|Nine US troops killed in Afghanistan as Taliban attack base}}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.TheBattleofWanat.com/ |publisher= www.TheBattleofWanat.com|title= Chosen Few: A True life Documentary film series based on The Battle of Wanat|date= April 2012}}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.vanityfair.com/politics/features/2011/12/battle-of-wanat-201112?fb_ref=social_fblike&amp;fb_source=home_multiline |title= Echoes from a Distant Battlefield |author= Mark Bowden|date= December 2011|publisher= Vanity Fair|accessdate= 28 November 2011 }}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/Wanat.pdf|title= Wanat: Combat Action in Afghanistan, 2008|author= Staff of the US Army Combat Studies Institute|year= 2010|work= US Army Combined Arms Center|publisher= Combined Studies Institute Press|accessdate= 20 November 2010 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101202045613/http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/wanat.pdf| archivedate= 2 December 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}} History of the battle published by the US Army's Combat Studies Institute.
* {{cite news
 | first = Candace
 | last = Rondeaux
 | title = Nine U.S. Soldiers Killed in Firefight
 | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/07/13/AR2008071300292.html?hpid=topnews
 | publisher = Washington Post
 | date = 2008-07-14
 | accessdate = 2008-07-17
 }}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.army.mil/-news/2010/06/23/41241-wanat-review/ |title= Wanat Review |author= United States Army |date= June 23, 2010 |accessdate= 1 July 2010 | archiveurl= http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20101202150500/http%3A//www%2Earmy%2Emil/%2Dnews/2010/06/23/41241%2Dwanat%2Dreview/| archivedate= December 2, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}
* {{cite web |url= http://usarmy.vo.llnwd.net/e1/wanat/downloads/campbellWanatReportRedacted.pdf |title= GEN Campbell Wanat Report Redacted|author= United States Army|date= May 13, 2010|accessdate=1 July 2010}}
* {{cite news
 | first = United States Department of the Army
 | title = AR 15-6 Investigation Findings and Recommendations&amp;nbsp;— Vehicle Patrol Base (VPB) Wanat Complex Attack and Casualties, 13 July 2008
 | url = http://www.scribd.com/doc/51573771
 | publisher = [[United States Army]]
 | date = August 13, 2008
 | accessdate =  2010-03-25
 | format = PDF
 }} (Part 1)
* {{cite news
 | first = United States Department of the Army
 | title = AR 15-6 Investigation Findings and Recommendations&amp;nbsp;— Vehicle Patrol Base (VPB) Wanat Complex Attack and Casualties, 13 July 2008
 | url = http://www.scribd.com/doc/51573898
 | publisher = [[United States Army]]
 | date = August 13, 2008
 | accessdate =  2010-03-25
 | format = PDF
 }} (Part 2)
* {{cite news
 | first = Yunlong
 | last = Zhang
 | title = Nine NATO-led soldiers die in intensified Afghan battles
 | url = http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2008-07/14/content_8540654.htm
 | publisher = [[Xinhua]]
 | date = 2008-07-14
 | accessdate =  2008-07-17
 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080801201605/http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2008-07/14/content_8540654.htm| archivedate= 1 August 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}

{{Coord|35.0525|N|70.9075|E|type:landmark|display=title|name=Battle of Wanat}}

{{Afghanistan War|state=collapsed}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Wanat}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 2008]]
[[Category:2008 in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:Al-Qaeda attacks]]
[[Category:Battles of the War in Afghanistan (2001–2014)]]
[[Category:History of Nuristan Province]]</text>
      <sha1>nk7zr10v639ac1nw4fprt5vgr13nmzy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
