<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Burton Bridge (1643)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30690631</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750058942</id>
      <parentid>725821431</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-17T16:36:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Imminent77</username>
        <id>29246608</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fix duplicate ref names – [[:Category:Pages with duplicate reference names|You can help!]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17415">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}
{{Use British English|date=April 2014}}
{{Good article}}{{infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Burton Bridge
| partof      = the [[First English Civil War]]
| image       = [[File:Burton Bridge pre-1863.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = An early photograph of the medieval Burton Bridge
| date        = 4 July 1643
| place       = [[Burton upon Trent]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|52.8067|-1.6238|type:event_region:GB|display=inline,title}}
| map_type    = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_caption = 
| map_label   = 
| territory   = 
| result      = Royalist victory
| status      = 
| combatant1  = Royalists
| combatant2  = Parliamentarians
| commander1  = Henrietta Maria&lt;br/&gt;Thomas Tyldesley
| commander2  = Richard Houghton{{POW}}&lt;br/&gt;Thomas Sanders{{POW}}
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 200 infantry, 60 dragoons and a cannon
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
| notes       = 
| campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox First English Civil War}}
}}
The '''Battle of Burton Bridge''' was fought between Royalist and Parliamentarian forces at [[Burton upon Trent]] on 4 July 1643 during the [[First English Civil War]].  By the time of the battle the town, which had at various times been held by both sides, was garrisoned by a Parliamentarian unit under the command of Captain Thomas Sanders and the town's military governor, Colonel Richard Houghton.  The key river crossing at Burton was desired by Queen [[Henrietta Maria of France|Henrietta Maria]], who was proceeding southwards from Yorkshire with a convoy of supplies destined for King [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] at Oxford.  The Royalists, led by Colonel [[Thomas Tyldesley]], launched a cavalry charge across the bridge which succeeded in defeating the Parliamentarians and capturing most of their officers, including Sanders and Houghton.  The Queen's convoy proceeded on its way south to Oxford with Tyldesley receiving a knighthood and a promotion in recognition of his victory.  Burton changed hands several more times during the course of the war, before finally coming into Parliament's control in 1646.

== Background ==
The county of Staffordshire, several days travel from the main seat of power in London, had a long-standing disinclination to paying taxes and levies imposed by the King.  [[James I]]'s [[Privy Council of England|Privy Council]] was forced to write to the county's [[Justices of the Peace]] for their failure to raise a single penny to support the King's [[Palatinate campaign|campaign to reclaim the Palatinate]] in [[Holy Roman Empire|Germany]] for his son-in-law [[Frederick V, Elector Palatine|Frederick V]] in the 1620s.&lt;ref name=&quot;p3&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=3}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The county was also slow to pay [[Charles I of England|Charles I]]'s [[ship money]] which began to be levied (in defiance of the Parliament) on the inland counties in 1634 and saw much resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;p3&quot;/&gt;  Open dissent against the King's decrees occurred in 1640 in objection to the levying of 300 men from the county for the King's [[Bishops' Wars|campaign against the Scots]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p5&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Riots took place in [[Uttoxeter]] with an armed guard having to be formed to prevent the levy from deserting.&lt;ref name=&quot;p5&quot;/&gt;

Upon the outbreak of the Civil War in 1642 the town of Burton was largely sympathetic to the Parliamentarian cause.&lt;ref name=county&gt;{{cite book|last=Tringham|first=Nigel J.|title=A History of the County of Stafford: Volume 9 - Burton-upon-Trent&amp;nbsp;— General History|year=2003|publisher=Victoria County History|url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=12328}}&lt;/ref&gt;   This was probably, in part, due to the large [[Puritan]] following in the town and Staffordshire's general disapproval of the [[High Church]] practices of the then Archbishop of Canterbury [[William Laud]] (who was later executed for his opposition of Puritanism).&lt;ref name=county/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p4&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early-war Burton ==
Burton's river crossing, a 36-arched medieval structure known as &quot;Burton Bridge&quot;, was desirable to both sides, being described as &quot;the only passage over the [[River Trent|Trent]] and [[River Dove, Central England|Dove]] to the North&quot;, and was positioned between the Royalist towns of Lichfield, Tutbury, and Ashby-de-la-Zouch and Parliamentarian Stafford and Derby.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p19&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Polkey|1992|p=19}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite this strategic location the town was unfortified and possessed few natural defences.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  Burton would change hands at least a dozen times during the course of the war, first coming to the attention of the Royalists when the [[Philip Stanhope, 1st Earl of Chesterfield|Earl of Chesterfield]] used it as a rendezvous for his forces in late 1642.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  Chesterfield withdrew his forces to Lichfield for the winter, garrisoning the [[Lichfield Cathedral|cathedral]] which would be the scene of much fighting during the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;p15&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=15}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  There were rumours prior to the war that the town held secret supplies of gunpowder for a catholic rebellion, these were investigated by [[William Paget, 5th Baron Paget|Lord Paget]] (who began the war as a parliamentarian, switched allegiance to the King in 1642 before returning to the side of Parliament in 1644) and found to be false, though the explosion of a store of gunpowder did occur in 1643 causing the roof of [[St Modwen's, Burton upon Trent|St Modwen's Church]] to be destroyed.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Tringham|first=Nigel J.|title=A History of the County of Stafford: Volume 9 - Burton-upon-Trent&amp;nbsp;— Established church|year=2003|publisher=Victoria County History|url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=12339}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:John Gell.jpg|thumb|left|Sir John Gell]]
East Staffordshire's strategic importance was heightened by its position at the boundary of Royalist and Parliamentarian garrisons in the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;p16&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=16}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Burton had come to [[roundhead]] attention in early 1643 after the establishment of a garrison at nearby Derby by the county committee leader, [[Sir John Gell, 1st Baronet|Sir John Gell]].&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  In February Gell placed a garrison across the county border at Burton, consisting of an infantry company under Dutch Major Johannes Molanus, but withdrew it less than a month later to assist in an [[Newark-on-Trent#The Civil War|attack on Newark]].&lt;ref name=county/&gt;

Parliament's forces in Staffordshire and Warwickshire were initially under the command of [[Robert Greville, 2nd Baron Brooke|Lord Brooke]] but after his death during the successful siege of Lichfield Cathedral in March 1643 Gell was appointed as his replacement.&lt;ref name=&quot;p16&quot;/&gt;  Gell's forces now amounted to around 1,000 infantry, a few horse and 300 partially armed [[Staffordshire Moorlands|Staffordshire moorlanders]] and he met with [[Sir William Brereton, 1st Baronet|Sir William Brereton]], Commander-in-Chief of Cheshire, to organise an attack upon Stafford.&lt;ref name=&quot;p16&quot;/&gt;  This became known to the Royalists and the [[Spencer Compton, 2nd Earl of Northampton|Earl of Northampton]] was sent with two fast-moving cavalry regiments to thwart Gell and Brereton's plan.&lt;ref name=&quot;p17&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=17}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Northampton met with troops led by [[Henry Hastings, 1st Baron Loughborough|Henry Hastings]] (later Lord Loughborough) and garrisoned Tamworth before engaging Gell at the inconclusive [[Battle of Hopton Heath]], during which Northampton was killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;p17&quot;/&gt;

During this time [[Henrietta Maria of France|Queen Henrietta Maria]] landed at [[Bridlington]], Yorkshire with a supply of weapons purchased abroad that she intended to bring to the King, who was then in [[Oxford]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p19&quot;/&gt;  In advance of this the King sent his nephew, [[Prince Rupert of the Rhine]], from Oxford with 1,200 horse, 700 foot and 6 cannon to clear South Staffordshire.&lt;ref name=&quot;p19&quot;/&gt;  Prince Rupert's troops evicted garrisons from [[Rushall, West Midlands|Rushall]] and [[Birmingham]] and successfully [[Lichfield Cathedral#Devastation of the English Civil War|recaptured Lichfield]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p19&quot;/&gt;  Rupert placed Royalist garrison in key towns including Burton to secure the route of Henrietta's convoy.&lt;ref name=&quot;p19&quot;/&gt;  The garrison at Burton was soon driven out once more by Gell, acting in co-operation with [[Thomas Grey, Lord Grey of Groby|Lord Grey]], commander-in-chief of the East Midlands Association.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  He placed his own garrison there of 200 infantry, 60 dragoons and a cannon from Derbyshire before proceeding with the remainder of his force to [[Tutbury Castle]] which he unsuccessfully attacked.&lt;ref name=&quot;county&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewisp19&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=19}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle ==
[[File:Tyldesley.jpg|thumb|Sir Thomas Tyldesley]]
Gell's garrison at Burton was commanded by Captain Thomas Sanders, who had previously commanded one of the largest companies in Gell's force.&lt;ref name=&quot;p19&quot;/&gt;  Sanders held more radical political views than Gell and was seen as a potential rival.&lt;ref name=&quot;p19&quot;/&gt;  Sanders may have been concerned that his deployment to such a precarious position was a plot by Gell to be rid of him.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  Whatever the case Sanders decided to remove himself from Gell's command and place him and his men under the direction of Colonel Richard Houghton, of the Staffordshire county committee and military governor of Burton.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p20&quot;/&gt;

In July 1643 the Queen's convoy and its guard advanced from Newark to [[Ashby-de-la-Zouch]] and then to Burton.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Polkey|1992|p=20}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Gell summoned the Staffordshire and Nottinghamshire associations forces to defend the town but they refused to [[Muster (military)|muster]] for him.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20&quot;/&gt;  On 4 July 1643 the Roaylist cavalry, led by Colonel [[Thomas Tyldesley]], charged across Burton Bridge and engaged Sanders' men.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;&lt;ref name=plaque/&gt;  The engagement was described as &quot;bloody&quot; and &quot;desperate&quot; and, though damage was caused to the town's St Modwen's church, the battle seems to have been decided by the action at the bridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=plaque&gt;The plaque on the modern bridge commemorating the battle reads: &quot;near this spot on 2nd July 1643, during the English Civil War, Colonel Thomas Tyldesley led a desperate cavalry charge over the famous 36-arched Trent Bridge to storm the town of Burton, the event being personally witnessed by Queen Henrietta Maria. For this exploit of signal valour, Thomas Tyldesley was subsequently knighted by King Charles I.  This plaque was erected on 2nd July 1993 by Sir Thomas Tyldesley's Regiment of the English Civil War Society and Burton upon Trent Civic Society.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p20l&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=lanc&gt;{{cite news|title=Remember Sir Thomas|url=http://www.lancashiretelegraph.co.uk/archive/2001/09/04/Lancashire+Archive/6011305.Remember_SirThomas/|accessdate=18 February 2012|newspaper=Lancashire Telegraph|date=4 September 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The forces of parliament were decisively beaten and, according to Gell, the town was &quot;most miserably plundered and destroyed&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20&quot;/&gt;  Henrietta Maria herself recorded that so much loot was taken that her men &quot;could not well march with their bundles&quot;.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;

The Royalists claimed that they had twice requested the surrender of the town before they attacked and that the Queen forbade any violence against the townsfolk.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20l&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewis|1983|p=20}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Conversely the parliamentarians claimed that 30 of their men were forced into the church and offered to surrender but were refused and were killed by cavaliers in the night.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20l&quot;/&gt;  The Royalists were also alleged to have looted the town and raped women before drowning at least 20 civilians in the river.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20l&quot;/&gt;  The Royalists took most of the Roundhead officers prisoner including Captain Sanders and Colonel Houghton (and his wife).&lt;ref name=&quot;p20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p20l&quot;/&gt;  Sanders was later exchanged and was promoted to Major by the [[Robert Devereux, 3rd Earl of Essex|Earl of Essex]] and commissioned by Gell to act as Colonel and to raise a regiment of horse.&lt;ref name=&quot;p20&quot;/&gt;  Tyldesley was knighted and promoted to brigadier-general for bravery shown in the action.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot;&gt;{{citation |last=Blackwood |first=Gordon |contribution=Tyldesley, Sir Thomas (1612–1651) |title=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography |edition=online |publisher=Oxford University Press |url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/|year=2004 |accessdate=30 August 2010}} {{subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
[[File:HenriettaMariaofFrance02.jpg|thumb|Queen Henrietta Maria]]
Having lost Burton, Gell feared an attack upon Derby and withdrew troops from [[Nottingham]] and [[Leicester]] to defend it.&lt;ref name=&quot;p21&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Polkey|1992|p=21}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He was also able to secure supplies of 20 barrels of powder, 300 muskets, 60 carbines and 60 cases of pistols and an additional troop of horses, allowing him to arm his regiment fully for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;p21&quot;/&gt;  However Derby was not attacked by the Queen's forces who bypassed it and moved through Walsall, proceeding according to the King's instructions to avoid delays.&lt;ref name=&quot;p21&quot;/&gt;

The new Royalist garrison in Burton fortified the bridge and maintained control of the town until driven out by Gell in January 1644.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  During this attack Gell took the commanding officer (a Major), six captains, eight other officers and 500 men prisoner.&lt;ref name=&quot;p31&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Polkey|1992|p=31}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Burton Bridge was again a focal point of the assault with five Royalists losing their lives there, with Gell claiming that he lost no men in the attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;p31&quot;/&gt;  Gell withdrew with his prisoners to Derby, allowing Lord Loughborough to retake the town and bridge which he intended to hold as a means of communication between his &quot;flying army&quot; at Ashby and the Royalist garrisons in Tutbury and Derbyshire.&lt;ref name=&quot;p31&quot;/&gt;

A Parliamentarian raid again attacked and plundered the town in April 1644, afterwards ceding control to the Royalists once more, before Sanders' newly raised regiment of 400 horse retook it  narrowly failing to capture Loughborough himself.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p31&quot;/&gt;  Parliament troops from Derbyshire and Staffordshire were established as a garrison in November 1644 but were driven out by Royalists by February 1645.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  King Charles I briefly made Burton his headquarters in May of that year before the town was retaken for the final time by Parliament in early 1646, becoming a centre of supply of coin and beer to the forces besieging Tutbury and Lichfield.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  After the war and the [[Restoration (England)|Restoration of Charles II]] in 1660 Burton remained a place of [[English Dissenters|dissent]] and [[nonconformism]] with large [[Presbyterian]] and [[Baptist]] congregations, raising doubts within the [[Church of England]] over the town's loyalty.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;

== Legacy ==
The medieval bridge over which the battle was fought was replaced in the Victorian era.&lt;ref name=county/&gt;  A plaque commemorating the battle was erected on the bridge on 2 July 1993 by Sir Thomas Tyldesley's Regiment of the [[English Civil War Society]] (the umbrella group for English Civil War re-enactors).&lt;ref name=plaque/&gt; Another monument erected at the site of Tyldesley's death at the [[Battle of Wigan Lane]] by one of his [[Cornet (military rank)|cornets]], Alexander Rigby, in 1679 notes his &quot;desperate storming of Burton-Upon-Trent over a bridge of 36 arches [for which Tyldesley] received the honour of Knighthood&quot;.&lt;ref name=lanc/&gt;  In honour of the battle the [[Burton Bridge Brewery]] markets an ale known as &quot;Battle Brew&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Battle Brew|url=http://www.burtonbridgebrewery.co.uk/Bridge/Beers/Battle.shtml|publisher=Burton Bridge Brewery|accessdate=26 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A local legend states that Oliver Cromwell was present in the area during the battle and tied his horse to a nail at [[Tatenhill]]'s St Michael's and All Angels Church, just {{convert|3|mi|km}} from the bridge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Moody|first=Jenny|title=All is well at church's holey site|url=http://www.burtonmail.co.uk/News/All-is-well-at-churchs-holey-site.htm|accessdate=9 October 2011|newspaper=Burton Mail|date=19 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The medieval Burton bridge was the site of [[Battle of Burton Bridge (1322)|an earlier battle]] in 1322 where [[Edward II of England|Edward II]] defeated the rebellious [[Thomas, 2nd Earl of Lancaster|Earl of Lancaster]].&lt;ref name=county/&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=33em}}

== Bibliography ==
*{{cite book|last=Polkey|first=Andrew|title=The Civil War in the Trent Valley|year=1992|publisher=JH Hall &amp; Sons|location=Derby|isbn=0-946404-92-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Lewis|first=RA|title=Staffordshire in the Civil War|year=1983|publisher=Staffordshire County Council Education Department|location=Stafford}}

[[Category:1643 in England]]
[[Category:Battles of the English Civil Wars|Burton Bridge 1643]]
[[Category:Military history of Staffordshire|Burton Bridge 1643]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1643|Burton Bridge 1643]]
[[Category:17th century in Staffordshire]]</text>
      <sha1>mh3qs0bvl4tt9ez550h0bb3m1fl2yxb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
