<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Iron Works Hill</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13204652</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745458134</id>
      <parentid>738661141</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-21T07:42:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14962">{{for|another battle during the [[American Revolutionary War]] with a similar name|Battle of Iron Hill}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Iron Works Hill
| partof      = the [[American Revolutionary War]]
| image       = [[File:TrentonPhiladelphia1806.jpg|280px]]
| caption     = Map, c. 1806, showing towns most relevant to the Battle: Bordentown, Moorestown and Mount Holly, NJ.|combatant1={{flag|United States|1776}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Great Britain}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Hesse}} [[Landgraviate of Hesse-Kassel|Hesse-Kassel]]
| date        = December 22–23, 1776
| place       = [[Mount Holly Township, New Jersey|Mount Holly]], [[New Jersey]]
| coordinates = {{coord|39|59|42|N|74|47|13|W|display=title}}
| result      = British tactical victory&lt;br&gt;American strategic victory
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United States|1776}} [[Samuel Griffin]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Hesse}} [[Carl von Donop]]
| strength1   = 500–600 militia{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=198}}{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=211}}
| strength2   = 2,000 British and [[Hessian (soldiers)|Hessian]] troops{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=151}}
| casualties1 = minor (see Aftermath){{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=216}}
| casualties2 = minor (see Aftermath){{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=216}}
| campaignbox = {{campaignbox American Revolutionary War: Northern 1775}}
}}
The '''Battle of Iron Works Hill''', also known as the '''Battle of Mount Holly''', was a series of minor skirmishes that took place on December&amp;nbsp;22 and&amp;nbsp;23, 1776, during the [[American War of Independence]].  They took place in [[Mount Holly Township, New Jersey|Mount Holly, New Jersey]], between an American force mostly composed of colonial militia under Colonel [[Samuel Griffin]] and a force of 2,000 [[Hessian (soldiers)|Hessians]] and [[British Army|British]] regulars under [[Carl von Donop]].

While the American force of 600 was eventually forced from their positions by the larger Hessian force,  the action prevented von Donop from being in his assigned base at [[Bordentown, New Jersey]] and in a position to assist [[Johann Rall]]'s brigade in [[Trenton, New Jersey]] when it was [[Battle of Trenton|attacked and defeated]] by [[George Washington]] after his [[Washington's crossing of the Delaware|troops crossed the Delaware]] on the night of December&amp;nbsp;25–26.{{sfn|Rosenfeld|2006|p=177}}{{sfn|Di Ionno|2000|p=29}}

==Background==
{{main|New York and New Jersey campaign}}

[[File:Joseph Reed by Pierre Eugène du Simitière.jpg|thumb|right|[[Joseph Reed (jurist)|Joseph Reed]] played a role in encouraging the militia's activities.]]

In July 1776 forces of [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]] under the command of General [[William Howe, 5th Viscount Howe|William Howe]] landed on [[Staten Island]].  Over the next several months, Howe's forces, which were [[British Army during the American War of Independence|British Army]] regulars and auxiliary German troops usually referred to as [[Hessian (soldiers)|Hessian]], chased [[George Washington]]'s [[Continental Army]] out of [[New York City]] and across [[New Jersey]].{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=5}}  Washington's army, which was shrinking in size due to expiring enlistments, and desertions due to poor morale, took refuge in [[Pennsylvania]] on the western shore of the [[Delaware River]] in November, removing all the available watercraft to deny the British any opportunity to cross the wide river.{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|pp=24–112}}

General Howe established a chain of outposts across New Jersey, and ordered his troops into winter quarters.  The southernmost outposts were located at [[Trenton, New Jersey|Trenton]] and [[Bordentown, New Jersey|Bordentown]].{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=185}}  The Trenton outpost was manned by about 1,500 men of a [[Hessian (soldiers)|Hessian]] brigade under the command of [[Johann Rall]], and the Bordentown outpost was manned by Hessians and the British [[42nd Regiment of Foot|42nd Regiment]] contingents, about 2,000 troops in all, under the command of the Hessian Colonel [[Carl von Donop]].{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=151}}  Bordentown itself was not large enough to house all of von Donop's force.  While he had hoped to quarter some troops even further south at [[Burlington, New Jersey|Burlington]], where there was strong [[Loyalist (American Revolution)|Loyalist]] support, floating gun batteries from the [[Pennsylvania Navy]] threatened the town, and Donop, rather than expose Loyalist allies to their fire, was forced to scatter his troops throughout the surrounding countryside.{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|pp=170–173}}

As the troops of von Donop and Rall occupied the last outposts, they were often exposed to the actions of rebel raids and the actions of [[Patriot (American Revolution)|Patriot]] militia forces that either arose spontaneously or were recruited by Army regulars.  These actions frayed the nerves of the troops, as the uncertainty of when and where such attacks would take place, and by what size force, put the men and their commanders on edge, leading them to jump up to investigate every rumored movement.  Rall went so far as to order his men to sleep &quot;fully dressed like [they were] on watch.&quot;{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=196}}

One militia force that rose in December 1776 was a company under the command of [[Virginia]] Colonel [[Samuel Griffin]].  Griffin (whose name is sometimes misspelled &quot;Griffith&quot;) was the adjutant to General [[Israel Putnam]], who was responsible for the defense of [[Philadelphia]]. Griffin's force, whose exact composition is uncertain, probably included some Virginia artillerymen, Pennsylvania infantry, and New Jersey militia, and numbered five to six hundred.{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=198}}{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=211}}  By mid-December he had reached [[Moorestown Township, New Jersey|Moorestown]], about ten miles southwest of [[Mount Holly Township, New Jersey|Mount Holly]].{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=213}}&lt;ref&gt;Hunt, December 19, 1776: &quot;... the Soldiers had Taken our Meeing house [in Moorestown] to Lodge in ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; By December 21, Griffin had advanced to Mount Holly and established a rough fortification atop a hill near an iron works, south of the [[Rancocas Creek]] and the village center.{{sfn|Rizzo|2007|p=80}} Von Donop sent a Loyalist to investigate, who reported a force of &quot;not above eight hundred, nearly one half boys, and all of them Militia a very few from Pennsylvania excepted&quot;.{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=198}} Thomas Stirling, who commanded a contingent of the 42nd positioned about seven miles north of Mount Holly at Blackhorse (present-day [[Columbus, New Jersey|Columbus]]), heard rumors that there were 1,000 rebels at Mount Holly and &quot;2,000 more were in the rear to support them&quot;.{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=198}} When von Donop asked Stirling for advice, he replied, &quot;You sir, with the troops at Bordentown, should come here and attack. I am confident we are a match for them.&quot;{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=199}}

==Battle==
[[File:Petticoat Bridge plaque.jpg|thumb|right|Plaque commemorating Petticoat Bridge skirmish]]

On December&amp;nbsp;21, about 600 of Griffin's troops overwhelmed a guard outpost of the 42nd located about one mile south of Blackhorse at Petticoat Bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Petticoat Bridge is located on the map, {{circa|1806}}, where the road leading north from Slab Town crosses the nearest creek, which is [[Assiscunk Creek]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hunt, December 22, 1776: &quot;we had a pretty good Quiet Meeting at our Meeting [in Moorestown] the Soldiers being gone&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; On the evening of December&amp;nbsp;22, Washington's adjutant, [[Joseph Reed (jurist)|Joseph Reed]], went to Mount Holly and met with Griffin.  Griffin had written to Reed, requesting small field pieces to assist in their actions, and Reed, who had been discussing a planned attack on Rall's men in Trenton with Washington, wanted to see if Griffin's company could participate in some sort of diversionary attack. Griffin was ill, and his men poorly equipped for significant action, but they apparently agreed to some sort of actions the next day.{{sfn|Reed|1847|p=273}}

On the morning of December 23, von Donop brought about 3,000 troops (the 42nd British (Highland) Regiment and the Hessian Grenadier battalions ''Block'' and ''Linsing'') to Petticoat Bridge where they overwhelmed Griffin's men. Griffin's troops retreated to Mount Holly where von Donop reported scattering about 1,000 men near the town's meeting house. [[Jäger (military)|Jäger]] Captain [[Johann Ewald]] reported that &quot;some 100 men&quot; were posted on a hill &quot;near the church&quot;, who &quot;retired quickly&quot; after a few rounds of artillery were fired.{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|pp=214–215}} Griffin, whose troops had occupied Mount Holly, slowly retreated to their fortified position on the hill, following which the two sides engaged in ineffectual long-range fire.{{sfn|Rizzo|2007|p=82}}

==Aftermath==
{{further2|[[Washington's crossing of the Delaware]] and [[Battle of Trenton]]}}
[[File:JohannvonEwald.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Jäger Captain [[Johann Ewald]]]]
Von Donop's forces bivouacked in Mount Holly on the night of December&amp;nbsp;23, where, according to Ewald, they plundered the town, breaking into alcohol stores of abandoned houses and getting drunk.{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=199}}  Von Donop himself took quarters in the house that Ewald described as belonging to an &quot;exceedingly beautiful widow of a doctor&quot;,{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=199}}  whose identity is uncertain.{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=200}}{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=215}}  The next day, December&amp;nbsp;24, they moved in force to drive the militia from the hill, but Griffin and his men had retreated to Moorestown during the night.{{sfn|Rizzo|2007|p=82}}  For whatever reason, von Donop and his contingents remained in Mount Holly, {{convert|18|mi|km}} and a full day's march from Trenton,{{sfn|Fischer|2004|p=216}} until a messenger arrived on December&amp;nbsp;26, bringing the news of Rall's [[Battle of Trenton|defeat by Washington]] that morning.{{sfn|Rizzo|2007|p=82}}&lt;ref&gt;Hunt, &quot;Memorandom 24th of the 12 mo: 1776&quot; &quot;...but things Seemed to turn very Strange and unexpected about the 22 of the 12 mo. the two armies Met at Mount Holly and had a Scermish. the Americans were Drove out of the town and Came back to the Moorestown and by Reports the Hessians on the English party did Strip many very much at that time in Mt Holly.  maybe 20 years before this Mt Holly was a Remarkably hilly favourd place but there was an Admirable Strange turn for as was Reported about the 26 of the month a very Stormy Day Some Hundreds of the Hessians or of the English party were taken Prisoners at Trentown &amp; Brought to Phil and the Rest Drove back towards Brunswick.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

News of the skirmishes at Mount Holly was often exaggerated.  Published accounts of the day varied, including among participants in the battle.  One Pennsylvanian claimed that sixteen of the enemy were killed, while a New Jersey militiaman reported seven enemy killed.{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=216}}  Both Donop and Ewald specifically denied any British or German casualties occurred during the first skirmish on December&amp;nbsp;22,{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=215}} while the ''Pennsylvania Evening Post'' reported &quot;several&quot; enemy casualties with &quot;two killed and seven or eight wounded&quot; of the militia through the whole action.{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=216}}

Some reporters, including Loyalist [[Joseph Galloway]], assumed that Griffin had been specifically sent to draw von Donop away from Bordentown, but von Donop's decision to attack in force was apparently made prior to Reed's arrival.  Reed noted in his journal that &quot;this {{sic|manou|ver}}, though perfectly accidental, had a happy effect as it drew off Count Donop ....&quot;{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=216}}  The planning for [[Washington's crossing of the Delaware]] did include sending a militia force to Griffin in an attack on von Donop at Mount Holly; this company failed to cross the river.{{sfn|Dwyer|1983|p=241}}

==Legacy==
The hill that Griffin's militia occupied is located at Iron Works Park in Mount Holly.  The battle is reenacted annually.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mainstreetmountholly.com/Iron_Works_Hill/default.htm|title=Battle of Iron Works Hill reenactment|publisher=Main Street Mount Holly|accessdate=2010-01-04|ref=reenact |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080307204818/http://www.mainstreetmountholly.com/Iron_Works_Hill/default.htm |archivedate = March 7, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==References==
* {{Cite book
  |last=Di Ionno
  |first=Mark
  |title=A Guide to New Jersey's Revolutionary War Trail: For Families and History Buffs
  |year=2000
  |isbn=0-8135-2770-8
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Dwyer
  |first=William M.
  |title=The Day is Ours!
  |location=New York
  |publisher=Viking
  |year=1983
  |isbn=0-670-11446-4
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Fischer
  |first=David Hackett
  |authorlink=David Hackett Fischer
  |title=[[Washington's Crossing (book)|Washington's Crossing]]
  |location=New York
  |publisher=Oxford University Press
  |isbn=0-19-518159-X
  |ref=harv
  |year=2004
}}
* {{cite book|last=Hunt|first=John|title=John Hunt's Journal|publisher=Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College|location=Swarthmore, PA|year=1776}}
* {{Cite book
  |title=Life and Correspondence of Joseph Reed, Volume 1
  |first=William Bradford
  |last=Reed
  |ref=harv
  |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OCJCAAAAIAAJ
  |publisher=Lindsay &amp; Blakiston
  |year=1847
}}
* {{Cite book
  |title=Mount Holly, New Jersey: A Hometown Reinvented
  |first=Dennis
  |last=Rizzo
  |ref=harv
  |publisher=The History Press
  |year=2007
  |isbn=978-1-59629-276-5
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Rosenfeld
  |first=Lucy D.
  |title=History Walks in New Jersey: Exploring the Heritage of the Garden State
  |year=2006
  |isbn=0-8135-3969-2
  |ref=harv
}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book
  |last=Federal Writers' Project of the Works Progress Administration for the State of New Jersey
  |publisher=US History Publishers
  |title=New Jersey: A Guide to Its Present and Past
  |isbn=1-60354-029-6
  |year=2007
  |location=Murrieta, CA
  |ref=harv
}}

==External links==
{{Portal|American Revolutionary War|New Jersey}}
*[http://www.IronWorksHill.org Annual commemoration, 2nd Saturday in December]
*[http://revolutionarywarnewjersey.com/new_jersey_revolutionary_war_sites/towns/mount_holly_nj_revolutionary_war_sites.htm Battle of Iron Works Hill, with photographs]
{{-}}
{{New Jersey in the American Revolutionary War}}

{{good article}}

[[Category:1776 in the United States]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1776|Iron Works Hill]]
[[Category:Battles of the New Jersey Campaign|Iron Works Hill]]
[[Category:Battles of the American Revolutionary War|Iron Works Hill]]
[[Category:Battles involving the United States|Iron Works Hill]]
[[Category:Battles involving Great Britain|Iron Works Hill]]
[[Category:Battles involving Hesse-Kassel|Iron Works Hill]]
[[Category:Mount Holly, New Jersey]]
[[Category:New Jersey in the American Revolution]]
[[Category:1776 in New Jersey]]</text>
      <sha1>etcjdrwch1g46fbmky8tlkiyfuhghyl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
