<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Flores (1592)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>40912019</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745124601</id>
      <parentid>745124152</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-19T11:21:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trappist the monk</username>
        <id>10289486</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>cite repair;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25740">{{good article}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Flores (1592)
|partof=the [[Anglo–Spanish War (1585)|Anglo–Spanish War]]
|image=[[File:Great Carrack 'Madre de Dios'.jpg|300px]]
|caption=The arrival of the 'Madre de Deus' at [[Dartmouth Harbour]], envisaged in a 19th-century English drawing
|date=20 May – 13 August 1592
|place=[[Atlantic]], off [[Flores Island (Azores)]]
|coordinates ={{coord|39|30|43|N|31|10|55|W|display=title}}
|territory=
|result=English victory{{sfn|Bicheno|2012|p=304–06}}{{sfn|Simões|2004|p=55–60}}
|status=
|combatant1={{flag|Spain|1506}}
*{{flagicon|Portugal|1578}} [[Iberian Union|Portugal under Philip of Spain]]
|combatant2={{flagicon|England|23px}} [[England]]
|commander1=[[André Furtado de Mendonça]]&lt;br&gt;[[Alonso de Bazán]]
|commander2=[[Walter Raleigh]]&lt;br&gt;[[John Burrough (Naval)|John Burrough]]&lt;br&gt;[[George Clifford, 3rd Earl of Cumberland|Earl of Cumberland]]&lt;br&gt;[[Martin Frobisher]] (acting)
|strength1=Various Spanish &amp; Portuguese ships
|strength2=9 warships&lt;br&gt;7 support ships{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598}}
|casualties1=1 [[Carrack]] captured,&lt;br&gt;1 Carrack destroyed,&lt;br&gt;1 [[Galleon]] captured&lt;br&gt;3 other ships captured or burned&lt;br&gt;1,000 killed, wounded or captured{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}}
|casualties2=120 killed or wounded&lt;br&gt;3 ships sunk in storm{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}}&lt;br&gt;Unknown to disease
|notes=
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Anglo-Spanish War}}
}}

The '''Battle of Flores (1592)''', also known as '''Cruising Voyage to the Azores of 1592''',  or the '''Capture of the Madre de Deus''' describes a series of naval engagements that took place from 20 May to 19 August 1592, during the [[Anglo-Spanish War (1585)|Anglo-Spanish War]]. The battle was part of an expedition by an English fleet initially led by Sir [[Walter Raleigh]], and then by [[Martin Frobisher]] and [[John Burrough (Naval)|John Burrough]]. The expedition involved the capture of a number of Portuguese and Spanish ships including the large Portuguese [[carrack]] ''[[Madre de Deus]]'', after a long naval battle off the island of [[Flores Island (Azores)|Flores in the Azores]]. The expedition, particularly the capture of the great carrack, was a financial and military success. The rich cargo aboard the carrack, which at the time equaled nearly half the size of the Kingdom of England's royal annual revenue, was subject to mass theft when it arrived in [[Dartmouth, England]], followed by quarrels over the shares of the [[Prize (law)|prize]]. The expedition had formative consequences for the English both financially and on the future of English exploration.{{sfn|Bicheno|2012|p=304–06}}{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}}{{sfn|Lach|1994|p=214–15}}

== Background ==
By virtue of the [[Iberian Union]] that joined the crowns of Portugal and Spain in 1580, the [[Anglo-Portuguese Treaty of 1373]] had fallen in abeyance. As the Anglo–Spanish War was ongoing, Portuguese shipping was a fair target for the [[Royal Navy]]. Sir Walter Raleigh, having only just been released from the [[Tower of London]], received a [[commission (remuneration)|commission]] from [[Queen Elizabeth I]] for an expedition to the [[West Indies]]. He outfitted a sixteen ship [[naval squadron]] of which two, the ''Garland'' and [[English ship Foresight (1570)|''Foresight'']] belonged to the Queen.{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598}}

=== Expedition ===
[[File:Nicholas Hilliard - George Clifford.jpg|thumb|160px|left|George Clifford, seen here in a miniature by [[Nicholas Hilliard]], helped to assemble and finance the expedition]]
The expedition was a private venture much like the [[English Armada|Drake-Norris expedition]], supported by limited assistance and subsidies from the crown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Scott|first=William Robert|title=The Constitution and Finance of English, Scottish and Irish Joint-Stock Companies to 1720. Volume I., Companies for Foreign Trade, Colonization, Fishing and Mining by|year=1911|publisher=CUP Archive|page=98|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gKk8AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA98 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its objective was to pillage Spanish and Portuguese ships within the Atlantic, off the Spanish coast or within the [[Caribbean]] and to make a profit from which the Queen's portion would amount to a large sum.{{sfn|Bicheno|2012|p=304–06}}

Raleigh appointed Burrough as his vice-admiral and was joined in commission with Frobisher, who had knowledge of maritime affairs. [[George Clifford, 3rd Earl of Cumberland|George Clifford, the Earl of Cumberland]] had the largest [[Equity stake|stake]] in the expedition and helped Raleigh to finance and gather the fleet. The majority of the fleet were owned by investors; the ship ''Dainty'' for example was owned by [[John Hawkins (naval commander)|John Hawkins]], but was captained by John Norton.{{sfn|Bicheno|2012|p=304–06}} The fleet included notables such as [[William Monson (Royal Navy officer)|William Monson]], [[Robert Crosse]], captain of the ''Foresight'', [[Samuel Purchas]], [[Richard Hawkins]] and [[Christopher Newport]], captain of the ''Golden Dragon''.{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}}

The expedition launched from [[Dartmouth, Devon|Dartmouth]], setting sail on 6 May 1592 after delays due to bad weather. The planned voyage to the West Indies was put on hold as supplies had already been depleted during the delay. Instead the fleet intended to head towards the Azores to intercept a [[Spanish treasure fleet]] or Portuguese carracks heading homeward from the [[East Indies]]. Initially Raleigh commanded, but on the following day, 7 May, the fleet was overtaken by Frobisher in the [[Full-rigged pinnace|pinnace]] ''Disdain''. Raleigh was given letters from the Queen ordering his immediate recall to England, and thus Frobisher took command.{{sfn|Corbett|1899|p=367–68}} On 11 May a storm struck just off [[Cape Finisterre]], scattering the majority of the fleet; three small ships were sunk and ''Garland'' very nearly [[foundered]].{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598}}

Nearing [[Cape St Vincent]] on the Portuguese coast, the fleet split into two sections as ordered by Raleigh. One, under Burrough, headed to the Azores to lie in wait for Spanish and Portuguese ships. The other, under Frobisher in ''Garland'' with Clifford, cruised off Cape St. Vincent with the strategy to pin the Spanish fleet against their own [[Lee shore|lee coast]].{{sfn|Corbett|1899|p=367–68}}{{sfn|McDermott|2001|p=395–96}}

=== First engagements ===
[[File:British - A Man, called Sir Martin Frobisher Kt - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|160px|Sir Martin Frobisher, assumed to be the subject of this portrait, took command of the fleet when Raleigh was recalled.]]
The fleet sailed further south, and by the end of May encountered the ''Santa Clara'', an armed, 600-ton Spanish [[galleon]], just off Cape St. Vincent. The English captured the ship after heavy resistance, taking whatever goods the Spanish had failed to retrieve from her burnt-out hull. She was carrying a large amount of ironware valued at £7,000 and was sailing to [[Sanlúcar de Barrameda]] where further freight was destined for the West Indies. With the capture, the fleet separated, leaving the prize and goods in the hands of Frobisher and Clifford.{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598}}

As the fleet continued south from the Cape in early June, Burrough in the ''Roebuck'' took a Spanish [[flyboat]] after a long chase that brought him near the Spanish coast. The flyboat's master revealed that a great fleet was prepared at [[Cadiz]] and [[Sanlúcar de Barrameda]]. Having received intelligence that Raleigh was fitted out with a strong force for the West Indies, [[Philip II of Spain]] had provided a large fleet to oppose Raleigh and to escort the rich East India carracks to port. Don [[Alonso de Bazán]], brother to the [[Álvaro de Bazán, 1st Marquis of Santa Cruz|Marquis of Santa Cruz]] and Captain General of the Armada, was to pursue and intercept Raleigh's fleet. As Burrough's men were burning the flyboat, part of the Spanish fleet was spotted, and Burrough, having rejoined his own fleet, soon sailed to the Azores.{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598}}{{sfn|Andrews|1964|p=73}}

Further north off Portugal, Frobisher's position became untenable, although he captured a prize fresh from [[Colonial Brazil|Brazil]] laden with [[sugar]] heading to [[Lisbon]] on 18 June and a few days later captured a Spanish [[caravel]].{{sfn|McDermott|2001|p=395–96}} Frobisher's group returned to England from Cape St. Vincent having missed Alvaro de Bazán's fleet further south.{{sfn|McDermott|2001|p=395–96}}{{sfn|Leinwand|2006}}{{rp|121}}

== Battle ==
Burrough did not have to wait long: on 25 June his scout ships spotted a large vessel approaching them near [[Corvo Island]], the northernmost of the Azores.&lt;ref&gt;The [[Gulf Stream]] and the [[Westerlies]] converge near the Azores, where ships coming from both areas would pass.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Santa Cruz ===
The vessel, the 800-ton Portuguese carrack ''Santa Cruz'', was pursued by three of Cumberland's ships. A storm arrived and forced the English away from the lee shore, but ''Santa Cruz'' was beached on the coast of Corvo.{{sfn|Edelman|2004|p=74–75}} The following morning, once the storm had passed, the Portuguese who had disembarked set up entrenchments nearby, taking off the cargo and burning the vessel. Burrough immediately dispatched 100 soldiers who waded ashore and easily dispersed those who guarded the shore; after some resistance the site was captured, and the Portuguese fled.{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598}} The cargo burnt inside the ship although some was salvaged by the English. Prisoners were taken, including the ship's [[purser]] and two foreign gunners. Under threat of [[torture]] they confessed that within fifteen days, three other carracks would arrive at the island. The fleet of five carracks had departed from [[Goa]] and were headed for [[Lisbon]] and consisted of the ''Santa Cruz'', ''Buen Jesus admiral'', ''Madre de Deus'', ''San Bernardo'', and ''San Christophoro''. ''Madre de Deus'' was the largest of the fleet, a thirty-two gun vessel of 1,600 tons and was one of the Portuguese crown's greatest and one of the largest sailing ships ever built.{{sfn|Smith|1986}}

With the news, the English ships waited and raided the villages on Corvo for supplies. For the month of July the English ships formed a picket line spaced about six miles apart along a north/south axis. From the southern flank near Flores Island, the order of ships was ''Dainty'', ''Golden Dragon'', ''Roebuck'', ''Tiger'', ''Sampson'', ''Prudence'' and ''Foresight''.{{sfn|Leinwand|2006}}{{rp|121}} The Spanish fleet, which had been sighted briefly, seemed no longer a threat; Alvaro de Bazan had made a major miscalculation: he disobeyed orders and headed further west, allowing the English to first reach the area of interception.{{sfn|Corbett|1899|p=367–68}}

=== Madre de Deus ===
[[File:Carrack Madre de Deus.jpg|thumb|300px|Model of the Portuguese carrack ''Madre de Deus'', in the [[Maritime Museum (Lisbon)]]]]
On 3 August ''Dainty'' sighted a large ship heading directly towards them and as it drew nearer, its enormous size became apparent. The carrack was far larger than ''Santa Cruz'', fully three times the size of England's biggest ship.{{sfn|Smith|1986}} ''Madre de Deus'' was attacked by the much smaller ''Dainty''. Around midday Newport's ''Golden Dragon'', followed by ''Roebuck'' - bigger than ''Dainty'', but only a fraction of the ''Madre'', joined the fray.{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}} These were followed at two-hour intervals by ''Foresight'' and ''Prudence'' in the evening. The ''Dainty'' had her foremast shot away and was out of the battle for five hours.{{sfn|Bicheno|2012|p=304–06}}{{sfn|Leinwand|2006}}{{rp|122}}

The English hoped to avoid sinking their opponent and to prevent her from running aground.{{sfn|Edelman|2004}} The damage on ''Madre de Deus's'' defences was becoming serious. With her bow rigging all but disabled, Burrough sent ''Roebuck'' which then crashed into ''Madre de Deus'', followed by ''Foresight''. Both moved directly under her main guns.{{sfn|Leinwand|2006}}{{rp|122}} The English boarded her in the dark at 10 pm. ''Golden Dragon'', ''Sampson'' and ''Tiger'' and the repaired ''Dainty'' came up in support. The English took the ship after a bloody hand-to-hand combat.{{sfn|Bicheno|2012|p=304–06}}{{sfn|Andrews|1964|p=73}}

The bloody decks of ''Madre De Deus'' were strewn with bodies, especially around the helm.{{sfn|Edelman|2004}} The carrack was nearly destroyed when a cabin full of cartridges caught fire, and only quick English action saved the prize. Burrough spared Captain Fernão de Mendonça and the rest of the wounded, sending them ashore.{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}} Burrough was trying to keep his own ''Roebuck'' afloat, as it had sustained damage when it crashed into ''Madre''.{{sfn|Leinwand|2006}}{{rp|122}} Only when Burrough came aboard and claimed the prize in the name of the Queen did pillaging stop. Sailors were stripped of &quot;stolen&quot; goods; however, this proved only temporary.{{sfn|Corbett|1899|p=367–68}}

The carrack was quickly repaired, heavily guarded by all ships, and the expedition set sail for England.{{sfn|Simões|2004|p=55–60}} Bazan now closed in on the English but he was too late; for a hundred leagues he pursued the English in vain before returning to Spain.{{sfn|Corbett|1899|p=367–68}} The fleet reached the [[English Channel]] in early September without incident.{{sfn|McDermott|2001|p=395–96}}

== Aftermath ==
As the fleet sailed back to England, Burrough produced an inventory - the  report mentions
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;''Gods great favor towards our nation, who by putting this purchase into our hands hath manifestly discovered those secret trades &amp; Indian riches, which hitherto lay strangely hidden, and cunningly concealed from us''&quot;.{{sfn|Leinwand|2006}}{{rp|124}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Among these riches were chests filled with jewels and pearls, gold and silver coins, [[ambergris]], bolts of the highest-quality cloth, fine tapestries, 425 tons of [[Cubeb|pepper]], 45 tons of [[clove]]s, 35 tons of [[cinnamon]], 3 tons of [[Nutmeg|mace]] and 3 of [[nutmeg]], 2.5 tons of [[Styrax benzoin|benjamin]] (a highly aromatic balsamic resin used for perfumes and medicines), 25 tons of the precious red dye [[cochineal]] and 15 tons of [[ebony]].{{sfn|Leinwand|2006}}{{rp|125–27}}An inventory was taken: 
&lt;blockquote&gt; ''&quot;spices, drugs, silks, calicos, quilts, carpets and colors, &amp;c. The spices were pepper, cloves, maces, nutmegs, cinnamon and greene [[ginger]]: the drugs were benjamin, [[frankincense]], [[Galangal]], [[Mirabilis (plant)|mirabilis]], aloes zocotrina,''&lt;ref&gt;The &quot;aloe&quot; of [[Socotra]] is ''[[Dracaena cinnabari]], a source of blood-red dye; the plant that is now known as ''[[Aloe succotrina]]'' is limited to the ''[[fynbos]]'' of South Africa and was never an item of commerce.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Camphor Laurel|camphire]]: the [[silk]]s, [[damask]]s, [[Taffeta|taffatas]], alto bassos, that is, counterfeit,  [[cloth of gold]], unwrought China silk, sleeved silk, white twisted silk,''&lt;ref&gt;Unwoven silk fibres might be in the sleeve or spun into &quot;twist&quot; that could be woven; stranded silk [[embroidery thread]]s were described as sleaved or sleided in the sixteenth century.&lt;/ref&gt; ''curled [[cypress]]e. The [[Calico (textile)|calicos]] were book-calicos, calico-launes, broad white calicos, fine starched calicoes, course white calicos, brown broad calicos, brown course calicos. There were also canopies, and course diapertowels, quilts of course [[sarcenet]] and of calico, carpets like those of [[Ottoman Empire|Turky]]; whereunto are to be added the pearl, [[musk]]e, [[civet]], and [[Ambergris|amber-griece]]. The rest of the wares were many in number, but less in value; as [[Ivory|elephants teeth]], [[Chinese porcelain|porcelain vessels of China]], [[Coconut|coco-nuts]], hides,  [[Ebony|ebenwood]] as black as jet, bested of the same, [[Tapa cloth|cloth of the rind's of trees]] very strange for the matter, and artificial in workmanship&quot;''.{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598|p=570}}&lt;/blockquote&gt; There was also a [[rutter (nautical)|rutter]] and a document, printed at [[Colonial Macau|Macau]] in 1590, containing valuable information on the [[China]] and [[Japan]] trade; [[Richard Hakluyt|Hakluyt]] observed that it was &quot;enclosed in a case of sweet [[Cedar wood]], and lapped up almost an hundredfold in fine Calicut-cloth, as though it had been some incomparable jewel&quot;.{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}}

''Madre de Deus'' entered Dartmouth harbor on 7 September, towering over the other ships and the town's small houses as it sailed by. The only vessel guarding the great ship was ''Roebuck'', as the other vessels had slipped off to [[Portsmouth, England|Portsmouth]] to sell off some of the plunder.{{sfn|McDermott|2001|p=395–96}} Nothing like ''Madre'' had ever been seen in England - the [[Frame (nautical)|frame]] from the [[beakhead]] to the [[stern]] was 165 feet long. The breadth at the broadest [[Deck (ship)|deck]], was just over 46 feet and her [[Draft (hull)|draft]] was twenty-six feet at her arrival in Dartmouth. Her several decks; consisted of a main [[orlop]], three main decks, and a [[forecastle]] and a [[Spar (sailing)|spar]] deck of two floors each. The length of the [[keel]] was 100 feet, the [[Mast (sailing)|main-mast]] was 121 feet, and its [[circumference]] at the partners was just over ten feet. The [[Yard (sailing)|main-yard]] was 106 feet long.{{sfn|Hakluyt|1598}}

=== Mass theft ===
[[File:Elizabeth1592.jpg|150px|thumb|left|Queen Elizabeth I made a 2000% profit from the expedition]]
[[File:Sir Walter Raleigh oval portrait by Nicholas Hilliard.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Sir Walter Raleigh, by [[Nicholas Hilliard]]]]
''Madre de Deus'' attracted all manner of traders, dealers, cutpurses and thieves from miles around, from as far as [[London]] and beyond. At seeing this huge vessel, pandemonium broke out amongst the townspeople; they visited the floating castle and sought out drunken sailors in [[tavern]]s and [[pub]]s, buying, stealing, pinching and fighting for the takings. Local fishermen as well ventured aboard, further depleting the cargo.{{sfn|Bicheno|2012|p=304–06}}

English law at the time provided that a large share of the loot was owed to the sovereign. When [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth]] discovered the extent of the theft, she sent Raleigh to reclaim her money and punish the looters. He swore, &quot;If I meet any of them coming up, if it be upon the wildest heath in all the way, I mean to strip them as naked as they were ever born, for Her Majesty has been robbed and that of the most rare things.&quot;{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}} By the time Raleigh had restored order, a cargo estimated at half a million [[Pound sterling|pounds]] nearly, almost half the wealth of the English treasury at the time and perhaps the second-largest treasure ever after the Ransom of [[Atahualpa]], had been reduced to £140,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Andrewes|first=William J. H.|title=The Quest for Longitude: The Proceedings of the Longitude Symposium|year=1996|publisher=Harvard University,|isbn=9780964432901|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Still, ten freighters were needed to carry the treasure around the coast and up the [[River Thames]] to London. In all the expedition as a whole yielded Elizabeth a 20-fold return on her investment.{{sfn|Andrews|1964|p=73}}

Both Burrough and Clifford however were disappointed in what they were given and they and other investors contested their share. Clifford received nothing, although as special compensation, the queen allotted him a sum in consideration of his money venture.&lt;ref name=&quot;DNB00&quot;&gt;{{DNB Cite|wstitle=Clifford, George}}&lt;/ref&gt; For Burrough there was no compensation, and bitter quarrels continued, leading to a fatal [[duel]] two years later.&lt;ref name=&quot;DNB01&quot;&gt;{{DNB Cite|wstitle=Burgh, John}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Consequences ==
Alonso de Bazan, despite having a greater fleet, failed to intercept any English ship, lost two large carracks and was disgraced by the King of Spain for his negligence.{{sfn|Corbett|1899|p=367–68}} By contrast the English learned that the fleet should not divide itself as had been done before capturing ''Madre de Deus'', making a more effective force. When later ships were brought into the Thames for unloading, the dockers were made to dress in &quot;suits of canvas [[Doublet (clothing)|doublet]] without pockets&quot; to reduce opportunities for theft.{{sfn|Seall|Kingsford|1912}}

The taste of the riches of the East galvanized English interest in the region. ''Madre de Deus's'' rutter from Macau was a forerunner to voyages that would end up establishing the [[East India Company]] in 1600.{{sfn|Lach|1994|p=214–15}} By 1603 the newly formed company itself would end up with a [[Factory (trading post)|trading factory]] at [[Bantam (city)|Bantam]].{{sfn|Olson|1991|p=45}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Pratt|first=James Norwood|title=John Company and Tea's Arrival in England|url=http://www.teamuse.com/article_001004.html|accessdate=24 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Battle of Flores (1591)]]
* [[Portuguese India Armadas]]
* [[Santa Catarina (ship)|Santa Catarina]]
* [[Battle of Sesimbra Bay]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}
;Bibliography
* {{cite book|last=Andrews|first=Kenneth R|title=Elizabethan Privateering: English Privateering During the Spanish War, 1585–1603|year=1964|publisher=Cambridge University Press, First Edition|isbn=978-0-521-04032-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last= Bicheno |first= Hugh |authorlink=Hugh Bicheno |title= Elizabeth's Sea Dogs: How England's Mariners Became the Scourge of the Seas |volume= |year=2012 |publisher=  Conway |location= |isbn= 978-1-84486-174-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Bowen|first=H. V.|title=The Worlds of the East India Company|year=2002|publisher=Boydell &amp; Brewer|isbn=978-1-84383-073-3}}
* {{cite book|first=Sir Julian Stafford |last=Corbett | authorlink=Julian Corbett|title=Drake and the Tudor Navy: With a History of the Rise of England as a Maritime Power|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=G61CAAAAYAAJ|year=1899|publisher=Longmans, Green, and Company |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Edelman|first=Charles|title=Shakespeare's Military Language: A Dictionary|year=2004|publisher=Continuum|isbn=978-0-8264-7777-4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yT2YBt-iHgcC&amp;pg=PA74 |ref=harv}}
* [[Edward Edwards (librarian)|Edward Edwards]]: [https://books.google.com/books?id=FK5CAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA59 ''The life of Sir Walter Raleigh''] (1868), vol. II, p.&amp;nbsp;59.
* {{cite book |last= Kerr|first= Roger|authorlink= |title= A General History of Voyages and Travels to the End of the 18th Century |volume= 7|year= 2012|publisher= Ulan Press |location= |asin= B00A8A44EU}}
* {{cite book|first=Richard|last=Hakluyt | authorlink=Richard Hakluyt|title=The Principal Navigations, Voyages, Traffiques and Discoveries of the English Nation|year=1598|page=570|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.03.0070%3Anarrative%3D570 |ref=harv}}
* [[John Knox Laughton]]: ''The taking of the Madre de Dios'', incluido en [https://archive.org/details/navalmiscellany02laug ''The naval miscellany''] (1902), vol. II, page. 87.
* {{cite book|last=Lach|first=Donald F.|title=Asia in the Making of Europe, Volume I: The Century of Discovery. Book 1|year=1994|publisher=University Of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0-226-46731-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | author=Landes, David Saul | title=[[The Wealth and Poverty of Nations: Why Some Are So Rich and Some So Poor]] | publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company | year=1999 | isbn=0-393-31888-5 | authorlink=David Landes}}
* {{cite book|last=Leinwand|first=Theodore B.|title=Theatre, Finance and Society in Early Modern England|year=2006|publisher=Cambridge University|isbn=978-0-521-03466-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=McDermott|first=James|title=Martin Frobisher: Elizabethan Privateer Edition|year=2001|publisher=Yale University Press,|isbn=978-0-300-08380-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Olson|first=James S.|title=Historical Dictionary of European Imperialism|year=1991|publisher=Greenwood|isbn=978-0-313-26257-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Seall|first=Francis |last2=Kingsford |first2=Charles Lethbridge |author-link2=Charles Lethbridge Kingsford |title=The naval miscellany|journal=The taking of the Madre de Dios, anno 1592|year=1912|volume=XL|series=The naval miscellany|pages=85–121|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/taking-of-the-madre-de-dios-anno-1592/oclc/16986103|accessdate=22 September 2013 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Simões|first=Ferdinando Oliveira|title=Carrack of the Route to India &quot;Madre de Deus&quot; 1589–1592|year=2004|publisher=Museu de Marinha,|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6WM5NAAACAAJ|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.newberry.org/smith/slidesets/ss06.html |title=Early Modern Ship-types, 1450–1650 |last=Smith |first=Roger |year=1986 |publisher=The Newberry Library |accessdate=2014-03-11 |ref=harv |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927060952/http://www.newberry.org/smith/slidesets/ss06.html |archivedate=September 27, 2011 }}
;External links
* &quot;[http://redalyc.uaemex.mx/redalyc/pdf/361/36100506.pdf The Presence of the &quot;Portugals&quot; in Macau and Japan in Richard Hakluyt's ''Navigations'']&quot;, Rogério Miguel Puga, ''Bulletin of Portuguese/Japanese Studies'', vol. 5, December 2002, pp.&amp;nbsp;81–116.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Flores, Battle of 1592}}
[[Category:Naval battles of the Anglo-Spanish War (1585–1604)]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1592]]
[[Category:1592 in Europe]]
[[Category:Battles in the Azores]]
[[Category:1592 in England]]
[[Category:1592 in Portugal]]
[[Category:1592 in the British Empire]]
[[Category:1592 in the Spanish Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>49iy2uecqdfj0visk3bmchvxwml21n0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
