<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Belgium in the long nineteenth century</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42522359</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743955875</id>
      <parentid>743090920</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-12T06:25:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dr Gangrene</username>
        <id>156661</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="78037">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}
{{History of Belgium}}
The '''History of Belgium from 1789 to 1914''', the period dubbed the &quot;[[Long Nineteenth Century]]&quot; by the historian [[Eric Hobsbawm]], includes the end of [[Habsburg Empire|Austrian]] rule and periods of [[French First Republic|French]] and [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands|Dutch]] occupation of the region, leading to the creation of the first independent [[Belgium|Belgian state]] in 1830.

In the years leading up to 1789, the territory today known as Belgium was divided into two states, called the [[Austrian Netherlands]] and [[Prince-Bishopric of Liège]], both of which were part of the [[Holy Roman Empire]]. In the aftermath of the [[French Revolution]], both states experienced revolutions in 1789 in which the old order was overthrown and new states created. These revolutions were condemned by the Holy Roman Empire and were crushed by 1792. The territory was only briefly regained, however, as the area was captured by the French during the [[French Revolutionary Wars]] and incorporated into the [[French First Republic]]. This [[French period]] lasted roughly from 1794 to 1815. In the aftermath of [[Napoleon]]'s final defeat in 1815, the [[Congress of Vienna]] added the territory of Belgium to the Netherlands, and until 1830, Belgium was part of the [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands]].

In 1830, the Belgian provinces of the Netherlands revolted in the [[Belgian Revolution]] and declared their independence. Despite widespread international support for Belgian independence, fighting between Belgium and the Netherlands continued under the rule of [[Leopold I of Belgium|King Leopold I]]. Belgian independence was finally recognized by the Dutch in 1839. Under Leopold I's reign, Belgium remained relatively stable and was only lightly affected by the [[Revolutions of 1848]]. On his death in 1865, his son [[Leopold II of Belgium|Leopold II]] was inaugurated as King. Leopold II's reign was dominated by the rise of the Socialist party and calls for reform to the voting system and military as well as the [[First Schools' War|Schools' War]] between Liberal and Catholic political factions. Although Belgian independence was briefly threatened during the [[Franco-Prussian War]], under Leopold II's reign the country reached an unprecedented level of industrialization and prosperity, becoming the second most industrialized state in the world after Great Britain. The period was also marked by the creation of a personal colony by Leopold II, the [[Congo Free State]]. The subsequent international outcry over human rights abuses forced the Belgian state to annex the region in 1908, forming the [[Belgian Congo]]. In 1909, after his father's death, [[Albert I of Belgium|Albert I]] began his reign, which lasted until 1934. In the years leading up to the First World War, the process of military and voting reform begun in the 1880s was finally completed. Despite declaring neutrality, Belgium was invaded by the [[German Empire]] in August 1914, beginning [[Belgium in World War I|the country's involvement in World War I]].

The long nineteenth century saw profound cultural and economic changes in Belgium. The [[Industrial Revolution]], which began to take effect in Belgium during the period of French rule, transformed the region's economy over the course of the period. By 1914, Belgium was acknowledged as one of the most densely industrialized countries in Europe, with notable coal mining and manufacturing industries. The period saw the gradual decline of the various dialects spoken in the country and the establishment of two distinct language groups, French in Wallonia and Dutch in Flanders. French, traditionally spoken by the elite, was given legal predominance across the country. During the nineteenth century, both linguistic groups witnessed a cultural resurgence and developed separate traditions in literature and culture. By the end of the period, the [[Flemish Movement]], seeking legal equality for Dutch language and even regional independence, had emerged in Flanders and [[Walloon Movement|a similar movement]] developed in Wallonia.

==General aspects==

===Geography and demographics===
[[File:Belgium c.1850-60.jpg|thumb|Map of Belgium in the 1850s]]
{{main|Geography of Belgium}}
The territory of Belgium varied little over the period. Belgium's border with the Netherlands was almost the same as that which had been created after the [[Dutch Revolt]] in the early 17th century, and its western border was almost the same as those of the 18th-century [[polities]] the Austrian Netherlands and Prince-Bishopric of Liège.{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=186–7}} It was only after the French annexation of 1795 that the territory became a single entity. In the 1830s, Belgian revolutionaries sought to create an independent state within the borders of the nine provinces that had been established under French occupation while ending the traditional roles of the small duchies, princedoms and counties which had traditionally been the basic territorial units.{{sfn|Carson|1974|p=206}} Aside from [[Zeelandic Flanders]], part of [[Luxembourg]], and [[Limburg (Netherlands)|Northern Limburg]], which were ceded to the Dutch compensate for the loss of the rest of the territory, the outline of Belgium in 1914 was virtually identical to that established by the French in 1795. The three ceded territories had a total of 300,000 inhabitants at the time.{{sfn|Pirenne|1948|pp=82–3}}

[[File:Frans Van Leemputten - Market day in the Campine.jpg|left|thumb|''Market day in the Campine'' (1910) by [[Frans Van Leemputten]] depicts rural life in the Belgian [[Campine|Kempen]] region]]
The northern half of Belgium, which would come to be known as [[Flanders]], was a largely agricultural area containing the important port of [[Antwerp]], the city of [[Ghent]] and the capital, [[Brussels]]. In the southern half, which would come to be known as [[Wallonia]], a number of smaller towns and cities along the valley of the [[Sambre]] and [[Meuse (river)|Meuse]] rivers – the ''[[sillon industriel]]'' (&quot;industrial valley&quot;) – became the focus of industrialization. In the west of the valley, around [[Charleroi]], was the ''[[Pays Noir]]'' (&quot;Black Country&quot;), which held significant coal deposits. In southeast Belgium, along the border with Luxembourg and [[Prussia]] (later Germany), was the heavily forested and agricultural region known as the [[Ardennes]].

In 1784, Belgium's population was 2.6&amp;nbsp;million, with just 25 percent living in cities. During the 19th century, the population both expanded and urbanized.{{sfn|Cook|2004|pp=40–2}} Between 1830 and 1875 the population of Brussels grew from 100,000 to 180,000,{{sfn|De Metsenaere|1990|pp=383–412}} and by 1910 the population of the metropolitan area soared to 750,000.{{sfn|''Flanders Online''}} The population of Belgium was almost universally [[Roman Catholic]], though free-thinking movements like [[Freemasonry]] were also popular among intellectuals and the urban middle classes.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|p=171}}

Throughout the long nineteenth century, as a common destination for political refugees, Belgium was home to important [[émigré]] communities, particularly in Brussels.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|pp=307–8; 312; 319}} From 1871, many of the [[Communards|Paris Communards]] fled to Brussels, where they received political asylum. The far-right politician General [[Georges Ernest Boulanger|Georges Boulanger]] arrived in 1889. Other notable exiles living in Belgium included the writer [[Victor Hugo]] and the theorist [[Karl Marx]].{{sfn|Dumont|1996|pp=307–8; 312; 319}}

===Language===
[[File:The beach at high water, Ostend, Belgium, ca. 1895 (3064721058).jpg|thumb|Belgian holidaymakers at [[Ostend]] in Flanders, {{circa}}1895]]
While in control of Belgium, France and the Netherlands each tried to force assimilation of their national languages, but in neither case did their rule last long enough for the language to become fully entrenched across the region or for local dialects to be displaced.{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=187–8}}

In 1846, 57 percent of Belgians spoke dialects of Dutch or Flemish as their primary language while 42 percent spoke dialects of French, such as [[Walloon language|Walloon]], [[Picard (language)|Picard]] or [[Lorrain dialect|Gaumais]].{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=181–3}} Under one percent of the population spoke German.{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=181–3}} Across the country, the aristocracy and middle classes spoke French, often as a second language, and French was the language of the legal system and government.{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=181–3}} There was a huge variation in accents, spelling and grammar across the country, particularly in Flanders, where regional dialects were almost incomprehensible to those from other regions.{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=181–3}}

In Brussels, situated in a predominantly Dutch-speaking area, 38 percent spoke French in 1842 while 61 percent spoke Dutch; many residents spoke dialects such as [[Marols]] instead of the standard languages.{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=181–3}} By the end of the period, social change and internal immigration from Wallonia contributed to the [[Francization of Brussels|growing importance of French in Brussels]].{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|pp=156–7}}

==Periods==

===Austrian rule and the Prince-Bishopric of Liège===
{{see also|Austrian Netherlands|Prince-Bishopric of Liège}}
[[File:Austrian Netherlands map-fr.svg|thumb|Map of the region of modern-day Belgium at the start of the period. The [[Austrian Netherlands]] was not contiguous and was bisected by the independent [[Prince-Bishopric of Liège]] ]]
In 1789, the area of modern-day Belgium was divided into two independently-governed polities, both part of the [[Holy Roman Empire]]. The [[Austrian Netherlands]], which included most of the territory of modern-day Belgium, had been in existence since the end of the [[War of the Spanish Succession]] in 1714 when the [[Habsburg Monarchy]] annexed the section called the [[Spanish Netherlands]] from the [[Habsburg Spain|Spanish branch of the house]].{{sfn|Cook|2004|pp=40–2}} The traditional principalities, duchies and counties surviving from the Middle Ages retained great regional autonomy.{{sfn|Cook|2004|pp=40–2}} The economy of the Austrian Netherlands developed little, as its neighboring states imposed high export tariffs and the port of Antwerp remained blocked by the Dutch.{{sfn|Cook|2004|pp=40–2}} Although [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] ideals developed among the urban bourgeoisie, most of the population remained suspicious of education and extremely politically conservative.{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=44}} The Catholic church was particularly influential, despite the attempts of [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor Joseph II]] to reduce its power.{{sfn|Cook|2004|pp=44–5}}

The [[Prince-Bishopric of Liège]] was a small ecclesiastical state that had been in existence since the 10th century. It was ruled by a line of [[prince-bishop]]s.{{sfn|Clark|1995|pp=64–6}} By the 1780s the state's capital, [[Liège]], was the largest city in Belgium.{{sfn|Cook|2004|pp=47–8}} The prince-bishopric was not a single continuous country, but rather consisted of several islands of territory surrounded by the Austrian Netherlands.{{sfn|Clark|1995|pp=64–6}} One of the foremost industrial regions of the time, the prince-bishopric was known for its successful wool, armaments and coal-mining industries, and traded widely.{{sfn|Clark|1995|pp=64–6}} The state was notionally governed by agreement of the [[Estates of the realm|Three Estates]] (the clergy, the nobility, and commoners), but from 1684, officials were elected by 16 separate chambers, each composed of wealthy nobles and [[Guild|guild members]] elected for life. Many groups were unrepresented,{{sfn|Clark|1995|pp=259–60}} including the bourgeoisie, industrialists and lower clergy. The spread of the Enlightenment, which became popular in Liège in the 18th century, bred further discontent with the political system.{{sfn|''Le Soir''|1989}}{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=48}}

====Revolutions of 1789====
[[File:Paul-Jacob Laminit (inc.) Jahann Voeltz (dis.) Combat dans les rues de Gand, novémbre 1789.JPG|thumb|left|Brabant revolutionaries mass in the town of [[Ghent]] in November 1789.]]
{{main|Brabant Revolution|Liège Revolution}}

On 18 August 1789, just months after the start of the [[French Revolution]], a revolution broke out in the Prince-Bishopric of Liège. In a meeting at the town hall, the democrat [[Jean-Nicolas Bassenge]] called for the reinstatement of two popular mayors who had been dismissed by the prince-bishop. The revolutionaries forced their way into the [[Citadel of Liège|city's citadel]] and forced Prince-Bishop [[César-Constantin-François de Hoensbroeck|Constantin-François de Hoensbroeck]] to ratify the appointments.{{sfn|''Le Soir''|1989}} The prince-bishop acquiesced but fled the principality for [[Trier]] a few days later. With the prince-bishop gone, the revolutionaries [[Republic of Liège|declared Liège a republic]]. Just twenty days after the [[Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen]] had been approved in France, a nearly identical document was introduced in  Liège declaring all citizens equal before the law and proclaiming freedom of thought and expression.{{sfn|''Le Soir''|1989}} Despite the revolutionaries pleading their case, the [[Perpetual Diet of Regensburg|Diet]] of the Holy Roman Empire condemned the revolution and ordered the restoration of the old regime. The army of Liège was finally defeated by the Austrians, who re-occupied the city in January 1791. The Prince-Bishop was reinstated.{{sfn|Pirenne|1926|pp=552–3}}

In the Austrian Netherlands, a populist revolt called the Brabant Revolution broke out in 1789 as a result of the perceived injustices of the Austrian regime. Emperor Joseph II's liberal reforms particularly angered Catholics, who feared a further decline in church influence, while for some his policies had not been sufficiently radical or liberal.{{sfn|Carson|1974|pp=200–1}} Fighting began in October 1789 as an émigré patriot army in the neighboring [[Dutch Republic]] invaded the country and defeated the Austrians at [[Battle of Turnhout (1789)|Turnhout]]. The émigré army succeeded in pushing the Austrian forces out of all the territory except Luxembourg. A loose confederation of states in the region was formed as the [[United States of Belgium]]. The use of the word &quot;Belgium&quot; in 1789 was the first time that the term had been officially employed to denote the region since Roman times.{{sfn|Beaufays|1988|p=63}} The revolution was conservative in character, not seeking to create a radically different social or religious order.{{sfn|Beaufays|1988|p=63}} Once established, the revolutionaries divided into political factions. The liberal [[Vonckists]], led by [[Jan Frans Vonck]], were eventually denounced and forced into exile by their conservative rivals, the [[Statists (Belgium)|Statists]], led by [[Henri Van der Noot]].{{sfn|Carson|1974|pp=200–1}} The Brabant revolutionaries were finally defeated by Holy Roman forces, who occupied Brussels in December 1790.{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=46}}

Following the crushing of the two revolutions, a number of Brabant and Liège revolutionaries regrouped in Paris, where they formed the joint Committee of United Belgians and Liégois (''Comité des belges et liégeois unis''), which united revolutionaries from both territories for the first time.{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=48}} Three Belgian corps and a Liège Legion were levied to continue the fight for the French against the Austrians.{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=48}}

===French rule===
[[File:Bataille de Fleurus 1794.JPG|thumb|The [[Battle of Fleurus (1794)|Battle of Fleurus]] in 1794 pushed the Austrians out of the territory for the last time.]]
{{see also|French period}}
In the aftermath of the [[Execution of Louis XVI|execution of King Louis XVI]], revolutionary France [[French Revolutionary Wars|was attacked]] by Prussian and Holy Roman forces from the Austrian Netherlands. Though the French defeated the Austrian army in the [[Battle of Jemappes]] in 1792 and briefly occupied the Austrian Netherlands and Prince-Bishopric of Liège, they were pushed out by an Austrian counterattack in the [[Battle of Neerwinden (1793)|Battle of Neerwinden]] the following year.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}} In June 1794, French revolutionary troops expelled Holy Roman forces from the region for the last time after the [[Battle of Fleurus (1794)|Battle of Fleurus]]. The French government voted to formally annex the territory in October 1795 and it was split into nine provincial ''[[Department (country subdivision)|départements]]'' within France.{{sfn|Zolberg|1974|pp=186–7}}

French rule in the region was marked by the rapid implementation and extension of numerous reforms which had been passed in post-Revolution France since 1789.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}} Administration was organized under the French model, with meritocratic selection. Legal equality and state secularism were also introduced.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}}

[[File:Van Bree-Le Friedland.jpg|thumb|left|[[Napoleon]] attends the launch of the warship ''[[French ship Friedland (1810)|Friedland]]'' in Antwerp in 1810]]
The important [[Old University of Leuven|University of Louvain]] was dissolved and re-founded without its religious status. In Liège, [[Jacobin]]-inspired locals pulled down the medieval [[St. Lambert's Cathedral, Liège|St. Lambert's Cathedral]].{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=48}} Use of the French language was actively encouraged and publications in Dutch banned as the government tried to integrate the territory into France, leaving a lasting legacy. Contingents of Belgian revolutionaries had served in the French army since 1792, but after the occupation, [[Levée en Masse|compulsory military conscription]] was extended to Belgians, 160,000 of whom were forced into the French army by 1813. The policy was extremely unpopular, and an insurrection known as the [[Peasants' War (1798)|Peasants' War]] broke out in East Flanders and the Ardennes in 1798 in response.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}} The revolt, which spread rapidly, was quickly and violently suppressed by the French.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}} Under [[Napoleon]], the ''[[Code Napoleon]]'', which would form the basis of all future Belgian legal codes, was implemented.{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=50}}

The period of French rule coincided with the start of the [[Industrial Revolution]] in Belgium.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}} Use of mechanical production techniques was encouraged by the French state. The government particularly encouraged industrialization of Belgian industries of military use, such as the cannon foundries at Liège.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}}

As the course of the [[Napoleonic Wars]] turned, the territory was invaded by Russian and Prussian forces.{{sfn|Carson|1974|pp=211–2}} After Napoleon's defeat and exile in 1814, the Southern Netherlands were occupied jointly by the Austrians, Prussians and Dutch. In an attempt to strengthen their position in Belgium, the Austrians began to recruit a [[Belgian Legion#Restoration|Belgian Legion]] of infantry, cavalry and artillery, which was merged with the Dutch army. The [[Hundred Days|Hundred Days' Campaign]], launched by Napoleon after his escape from exile, was largely fought in Belgium in early 1815, and Napoleon's final defeat at the [[Battle of Waterloo]] occurred just miles from Brussels.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=86–90}}

===Dutch rule===
{{main|United Kingdom of the Netherlands}}

After Napoleon's total defeat in 1815, the [[Congress of Vienna]] merged the French territory in Belgium with the Netherlands to form the [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands]] as a [[buffer state]] against the French.{{sfn|Carson|1974|pp=211–2}} It was ruled by [[William I of the Netherlands|William I of Orange]].{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}} The synergy of combining the manufacturing centers in Belgium with the important exporting ports in the Netherlands encouraged growth of the industrial cloth manufacturing and metallurgic centers in Wallonia.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}} Keen to promote the economic development of the southern provinces as well, William I founded the ''Société Générale des Pays-Bas'' in 1822 to provide businesses with capital to invest in machinery.{{sfn|de Barsy|1972|pp=12–9}}{{efn|In full, the ''Société Générale des Pays-Bas pour favoriser l'Industrie nationale'' (&quot;General Company of the Netherlands for promoting National Industry&quot;). After independence, it would become the ''[[Société Générale de Belgique]]'' (SGB).{{sfn|de Barsy|1972|pp=12–9}} }} The ''Société Générale'' served as a driving force behind Belgian industrialization in the 19th century, and at its height controlled large swathes of the national economy. William I also encouraged the creation of educational facilities in the Southern Provinces, founding the [[State University of Leuven]], the [[University of Liège]] and [[Ghent University]] in 1817.{{sfn|Carson|1974|p=216}}

The period of Dutch rule saw growing hostility between the Catholic Belgian provinces and the predominantly Protestant Dutch. The Belgian provinces also complained that they were underrepresented by the Kingdom's system of government, where 55 Belgian deputies were allocated to represent 3.5&amp;nbsp;million people, while an equal number of Dutch deputies represented just two million.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}} When the [[States-General of the Netherlands|States-General]] voted against adopting the new unrepresentative constitution, William declared that the minority favorable vote outweighed the negative vote. Liberals in Belgium also accused William of attacking personal and religious freedoms.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}}

===Belgian Revolution===
[[File:Attaque du parc de Bruxelles.jpg|thumb|left|Belgian revolutionaries fighting at the barricades around the ''[[Brussels Park|Parc de Bruxelles]]'' in 1830]]
{{main|Belgian Revolution}}
The Belgian Revolution broke out on 25 August 1830, after the performance of a nationalist opera (''[[La muette de Portici]]'') in Brussels led to a minor insurrection among the capital's bourgeoisie, who sang patriotic songs and captured some public buildings in the city. This early revolutionary group was swelled by a large number of urban workers. The following day, the revolutionaries began flying their own flag, clearly influenced by that of the Brabant Revolution of 1789.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}} To maintain order, several bourgeois militia groups were formed. The situation in Brussels led to widespread unrest across the country. William I rejected [[William II of the Netherlands|his son]]'s advice to negotiate with the rebels, forcing them towards a more radical, pro-independence stance, and sent a large military force to Brussels suppress the insurrection.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}}

Between 23 and 27 September 1830, heavy fighting took place between Dutch forces and Brussels revolutionaries, who were reinforced by small contingents from across the country. The Dutch were eventually forced to retreat.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}} In the aftermath of the failed attack and concurrent mass desertions of Belgian soldiers from the Dutch army, the revolution spread around Belgium. Dutch garrisons were pushed out of the area, until only Antwerp and Luxembourg remained occupied.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}} The [[Provisional Government of Belgium]], led by [[Charles Rogier]], was formed on 24 September and Belgian independence was officially proclaimed on 4 October while work began on creating a constitution. In December, international governments at the [[London Conference of 1830|Conference of London]] recognized the independence of Belgium and guaranteed its [[Neutrality (international relations)|neutrality]].{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=91–2}} The Dutch, however, only recognized Belgium's independence and the terms of the Conference in 1839 and the Dutch-Belgian frontier was only fixed by the 1843 [[Treaty of Maastricht (1843)|Treaty of Maastricht]].

====Creation of the Belgian Constitution====
[[File:5-Cent-Belgium-1856-Front.jpg|thumb|The Belgian constitution depicted with the [[Leo Belgicus|Belgian lion]] on a coin]]
{{see also|Constitution of Belgium}}
In November 1830, a [[National Congress of Belgium|National Congress]] was established to create a Belgian constitution. Fears of [[Ochlocracy|mob rule]] associated with republicanism after the French Revolution of 1789, as well as the example of the recent [[July Revolution]] in France, led the Congress to decide that Belgium would be a [[Popular monarchy|popular]], [[constitutional monarchy]]. The Congress approached several candidates, but chose [[Leopold I of Belgium|Leopold of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha]], a minor but well-connected German noble, to be the first [[Monarchy of Belgium|King of the Belgians]]. He was officially inaugurated on [[Belgian National Day|21 July 1831]], after taking an oath to abide by the Constitution. Leopold I was generally unsatisfied with the amount of power allocated to the monarch, and sought to extend it wherever the Constitution was ambiguous or unclear while generally avoiding involvement in routine politics.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Leopold I''|2004}}

The [[Constitution of Belgium|Constitution]] developed by the National Congress was implemented in July 1831. It guaranteed [[Civil liberties|individual liberty]], property rights, [[Freedom of conscience|freedom of religion]] and [[Freedom of the press|the press]], and [[equality before the law]].{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|pp=94–5}} Because of its perceived balance between freedom and rule of law, it was praised by [[Liberalism|liberals]] around the world and promoted as a model for future constitutions.{{sfn|Hawgood|1964|p=191}} Under the new constitution, Belgium had [[Bicameralism|two chambers]], a [[Chamber of Representatives (Belgium)|Chamber of Representatives]] and [[Senate (Belgium)|Senate]], both elected by a small number of wealthy citizens.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|p=96}} The King was allowed substantial power in military affairs, but was given little independent power in any other sphere, which was instead given to the elected chambers.

===Reign of Leopold I===
[[File:Epaulette 10c.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Leopold I, depicted on the [[Epaulettes (stamp)|first Belgian postage stamp]], issued in 1849]]
{{see also|Leopold I of Belgium}}
Leopold I was crowned on 21 July 1831, replacing [[Erasme Louis Surlet de Chokier|Baron Surlet de Chokier]], who had served as [[regent]] since February. Before his selection by the National Congress, Leopold had been Duke of the minor German state of [[Saxe-Coburg and Gotha]].{{sfn|Pirenne|1948|pp=48–9}} He had pursued a distinguished military career fighting for the [[Russian Empire]] during the Napoleonic Wars and was well connected to other European monarchies.{{efn|Leopold was briefly married to [[Princess Charlotte of Wales|Charlotte]], daughter of the British [[George IV of the United Kingdom|King George IV]], making him second in line to the British throne until her death in 1817. His second wife, [[Louise of Orleans]], was the daughter of [[Louis Philippe I]] of France. He was the uncle of [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]] of Great Britain. In February 1830 he had been offered the crown of Greece, but decided to refuse.{{sfn|Pirenne|1948|pp=48–53}} }}

Despite the Congress of London's verdict in 1830, the Dutch continued to resist Belgian independence for much of Leopold I's early reign. On 2 August 1831, days after Leopold's coronation, the Dutch launched an invasion known as the [[Ten Days' Campaign]]. The 50,000-strong Dutch force crossed the border and rapidly pushed the small Belgian army back as far as [[Leuven]].{{sfn|Pirenne|1948|pp=31–3}} Faced with a military disaster, the Belgian government appealed to the French for support.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=18–9}} Without international support of their own and faced with an entire French army under General [[Étienne Maurice Gérard|Étienne Gérard]], the Dutch withdrew on 12 August. In 1832 the French [[Siege of Antwerp (1832)|pushed the Dutch out of Antwerp]], their final garrison in Belgium. Much of the city was destroyed in the fighting.{{sfn|Pirenne|1948|pp=39–40}} Sporadic skirmishes along the border continued until 1839, when the Dutch signed the [[Treaty of London (1839)|Treaty of London]].{{sfn|Pirenne|1948|p=86}} The Ten Days' Campaign revealed the fragility of the Belgian position, and although the Dutch finally recognized the independence of Belgium, the Belgians were forced to give up some disputed territories, including Zeelandic Flanders and the Duchy of Limburg.{{sfn|Pirenne|1948|pp=34–8}} Part of Luxembourg, equivalent to the modern state, remained as a semi-independent protectorate of the Dutch until 1890.

====Politics and the Crisis of the 1840s====
[[File:Neuhuys Départ de la Flèche le 5 mai 1835.jpg|thumb|Opening of the first railway in Belgium in May 1835]]
Politics in Belgium under Leopold I were polarized between liberal and [[Political Catholicism|Catholic]] political factions, though before 1847 they collaborated in [[Unionism in Belgium|unionist]] governments.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Leopold I''|2004}} The liberals were opposed to the church and particularly opposed its influence in politics and society, while supporting [[free trade]], personal liberties and [[secularization]].{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=20–1}} The Catholics saw religious teachings as a fundamental basis for the state and society and opposed all attempts by the liberals to attack the church's official privileges.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=20–1}} Initially, these factions existed only as informal groups with which prominent politicians were generally identified. The liberals held power over much of Leopold I's reign. An official [[Liberal Party (Belgium)|Liberal Party]] was formed in 1846, although a formal [[Catholic Party (Belgium)|Catholic Party]] was only established in 1869. Gradually, these political groups would also spread into Belgium's society, creating a process of social stratification known as [[pillarisation]]. Leopold, who was Protestant, tended to favor Liberals and shared their desire for reform, though he was not partisan.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Leopold I''|2004}}

Leopold I's reign was marked by an economic crisis which lasted until the late 1850s.{{sfn|Carson|1974|p=225}} In the aftermath of the revolution, the Dutch had closed the Scheldt to Belgian shipping, making the port of Antwerp effectively useless. The Netherlands and the [[Dutch Empire|Dutch colonies]], which had been profitable markets for Belgian manufacturers before 1830, were totally closed to Belgian goods.{{sfn|Carson|1974|p=225}} The years between 1845 and 1849, known as the Crisis of the 1840s, were particularly hard in Flanders where harvests failed and a third of the population became dependent on poor relief. The period has been described as the &quot;worst years of Flemish history&quot;.{{sfn|Carson|1974|p=225}} The economic situation in Flanders increased [[Flemish immigration to Wallonia|the internal migration]] to Brussels and the industrial areas of Wallonia, which continued throughout the period.{{sfn|Carson|1974|p=225}}

====Upheaval of 1848====
[[File:Expédition de Risquons-tout.jpg|thumb|left|Fighting between revolutionaries and government troops at [[Risquons-Tout]] in 1848]]
By 1847, Belgium was suffering from economic destabilization as Belgian exporters faced increasing competition from new British firms.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}} Radical parties like the ''Association Démocratique'', founded in 1847 at the instigation of Karl Marx, who had briefly [[Karl Marx#Brussels: 1845–1847|lived in Brussels]] in exile, actively agitated against the unpopular Liberal government under Charles Rogier.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}} However, the success of the Liberals' economic reforms partially mitigated the effects of the economic downturn, which meant that Belgium was not as badly affected as its neighbors by the [[Revolutions of 1848]].{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}} Nevertheless, in early 1848, a large number of radical publications appeared.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}}

The most serious threat of the 1848 revolutions in Belgium was posed by Belgian émigré groups. Shortly after the [[French Revolution of 1848|revolution in France]], Belgian migrant workers living in Paris were encouraged to return to Belgium to overthrow the monarchy and establish a republic.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}} Around 6,000 armed émigrés of the [[Belgian Legion#French Revolution of 1848|Belgian Legion]] attempted to cross the Belgian frontier. The first group, travelling by train, was stopped and quickly disarmed at [[Quiévrain]] on 26 March 1848.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=20–1}} The second group crossed the border on 29 March and headed for Brussels.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}} They were confronted by Belgian troops at the hamlet of [[Risquons-Tout]] and, during fighting, seven émigrés were killed and most of the rest were captured.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}} The defeat at Risquons-Tout effectively ended the revolutionary threat to Belgium. The situation stabilized that summer after a good harvest, and [[Belgian general election, 1848|fresh elections]] returned a strong Liberal majority.{{sfn|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}}

===Reign of Leopold II===
[[File:Coin BE 2F Leopold II obv FR 37.png|thumb|Leopold II, depicted on a coin]]
{{see also|Leopold II of Belgium}}
Leopold II was sworn in as king of the Belgians in 1865. His reign coincided with the ''[[Belle Époque]]'' and rapid economic expansion from the 1880s. It was characterized by the resurgence of the Catholic Party, political confrontation over military action, educational and franchise reform and his creation of a personal empire in Africa.

One of Leopold's long-term preoccupations was increasing the international standing and influence of his country. Throughout much of his early reign, Leopold hoped to regain the territories which had been ceded to the Netherlands in 1839, particularly Luxembourg, which he viewed as an integral piece of Belgian territory.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=67–68}} He also pushed for the implementation of conscription and reforms to the military, many of which would only be realized after his death. From the 1870s, he tried to persuade several Belgian prime ministers to support the creation of an overseas colony in the Far East or Africa to increase Belgian wealth and political influence.{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=12–5}} After being repeatedly turned down, he launched a personal venture to colonize the [[Congo Basin|Congo river basin]] in central Africa, without the backing or support of the Belgian state.{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=12–5}} Some of the vast personal wealth he accumulated from the colony was spent on construction of grandiose public buildings across Belgium, earning him the nickname &quot;Builder King&quot; (''roi batisseur'').{{sfn|Laporte|2005}} [[File:Parc du Cinquantenaire 30-05-06.JPG|thumb|left|View of the [[Cinquantenaire|Cinquantenaire park and arch]], started under Leopold II in 1880. It was only finished in 1905.]]

Most of these projects were focused in Brussels, where he constructed two large palaces,{{efn|The [[Royal Palace of Laeken|Palace of Laeken]], complete with [[Royal Greenhouses of Laeken|huge greenhouses]], and the smaller [[Royal Palace of Brussels|Palace of Brussels]].}} and [[Ostende]], where a [[Royal Galleries of Ostend|vast colonnaded arcade]] was built along the seafront in an attempt to turn the town into a fashionable [[Resort town|seaside resort]].{{sfn|Papadopoulos|1996|pp=244–6}} During Leopold's reign, Belgium hosted five prestigious [[World Exhibition]]s, [[Exposition Universelle d'Anvers (1885)|in 1885]], [[Grand Concours International des Sciences et de l'Industrie|1888]], [[Exposition Internationale d'Anvers (1894)|1894]], [[Brussels International (1897)|1897]] and [[Liège International (1905)|1905]], as well as a major national exhibition in 1880 to mark the 50th anniversary of Belgian independence.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|p=286}}

Politically, Leopold disliked the [[Belgian Labour Party|Socialist party]], preferring to negotiate with the Catholic Party, which held power for much of his reign. He was widely distrusted by politicians, who saw him as meddling in state business and seeking to expand the power of the monarchy. Towards the end of his reign, public awareness of the atrocities committed under his colonial regime, as well as [[Caroline Lacroix|his marital infidelity]], led to a significant fall the monarchy's popularity. Following his death in December 1909, his funeral cortege was booed.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=298–300}}

Although Belgium was officially neutral throughout his reign, significant numbers of Belgians volunteered to fight for right-wing causes abroad. From 1860, large numbers of Belgian Catholic volunteers went to Italy in an ultimately unsuccessful [[Papal Zouaves|attempt to defend]] the independence of the [[Papal States]] against [[Giuseppe Garibaldi]]'s [[Unification of Italy|revolutionaries]]. The Zouaves, as they were known, were ultimately unsuccessful and the Papal States [[Capture of Rome|fell in 1870]].{{sfn|Coulombe|2008|p=101}} A volunteer [[Belgian Legion#Mexico Expedition|Belgian Legion]] fought alongside French forces in the [[Mexican Adventure]] from 1864 on behalf of Mexican [[Maximilian I of Mexico|Emperor Maximilian I]], whose wife was the daughter of Leopold I. The unit suffered heavy casualties at the [[Battle of Tacámbaro]] in 1865, and after heavy fighting was disbanded in December 1866.{{sfn|Chartrand|2004|pp=36–7}}

====&quot;Belgian Question&quot; and Franco-Prussian War====
[[File:Le drapeau belge.jpg|thumb|French and Belgian troops stand off at the border during the [[Franco-Prussian War]]]]
{{main|Belgium and the Franco-Prussian War}}
When the [[Franco-Prussian War]] broke out in July 1870, Belgium was confronted with the greatest threat to its independence since 1848. Shortly before the conflict, a draft treaty from the [[Austro-Prussian War]] of 1866 between [[Napoleon III of France|Napoleon III]] and German Chancellor [[Otto von Bismarck]] discussing the annexation of Belgium as the price for French neutrality was made public.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|p=70}} Napoleon III had also attempted [[Luxembourg Crisis|to annex Luxembourg]] into the French Empire in 1868, which seemed to contemporaries a parallel of Belgium.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|p=68}} European powers worried that French encroachment into Belgium would destabilize the [[Concert of Europe]]. The issue became known as the &quot;Belgian Question&quot;. As the conflict began, Leopold and his advisors believed that either France or Prussia might try to outflank their opponent by disregarding Belgian neutrality and launching an invasion.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=78–9}} The Belgian army was mobilized on the same day that both French and Prussian reserves were called up. As French troops moved towards the border, panic ensued in Belgium. The national [[gold reserve]]s were evacuated to the [[National redoubt of Belgium|National Redoubt fortress]] at Antwerp.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=78–9}} After a restatement of the British guarantee of Belgian neutrality by Prime Minister [[William Ewart Gladstone|Gladstone]], Belgium was able to remain neutral, though much of the fighting (including the key [[Battle of Sedan (1870)|Battle of Sedan]]) occurred just south of the Belgian border.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=78–9}} More crucially, the mobilization of the Belgian army, which was divided into a mobile Army of Observation to guard the frontier and the static Army of Antwerp to hold the National Redoubt, revealed key structural problems in the military, particularly with the system of conscription.{{sfn|Revue militaire|1873|pp=9–10}} Events also re-emphasized the importance of the Treaty of London to Belgium's survival.

====Military reform====
Leopold viewed a strong military as the key to maintaining Belgian independence against France and, after the Franco-Prussian War, an expansionist [[German Empire|Germany]].{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=67–8}} After cutting the defense budget in the 1860s, the government was advised by a military commission to increase the size of the army and to abolish the system of ''[[Remplacement]]'', whereby rich Belgians selected for military service by lot could pay for a substitute to take their place.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=80–1}} Leopold II personally lobbied successive governments to implement the findings of the report and institute a fundamental reform of the army. Reform was opposed by both the Liberal and Catholic Parties, which viewed the army with suspicion and ''Remplacement'' as a key civil right.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=80–1}} In a move supported only by the socialists, ''Remplacement'' was abolished in 1909. This was the last legal document signed before Leopold's death.{{sfn|De Mûelenaere|2012|pp=161–2}} Under the new system, one son per family would be liable for military service regardless of social class but the total size of the military remained the same.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|p=146}}

Although military reform was delayed until the end of his reign, Leopold did succeed in convincing parliament of the need to extend Belgium's defenses. Construction of fortresses along the border by both the French and Germans in the mid-1880s worried the Belgian government that their country might be used as an invasion route. In 1887, a program of fortification construction began along the Sambre and Meuse rivers.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|pp=149–50}} Designed by the leading military architect [[Henri Alexis Brialmont]], nine [[Fortified Position of Namur|forts were built at Namur]] to guard against an offensive from France, while twelve were built [[Fortified Position of Liège|around Liège]], near the German border.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|pp=149–50}} Completed in 1892, they supplemented the existing National Redoubt at Antwerp, which was later modernized and extended.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|pp=149–50}} The fortifications would play a major role in the opening stages of the [[First World War]].

====School War====
[[File:Schoolstrijd.jpg|thumb|upright|The pro-Liberal magazine ''La Bombe'' depicts a priest watching children flock to secular schools.]]
{{main|First School War}}
The political rivalry between Liberal and Catholic parties peaked between 1879 and 1884, when they clashed on the issue of religion in primary education. In June 1879, a Liberal majority government under [[Walthère Frère-Orban]] succeeded in passing an Education Act secularizing primary education across the country, starting the so-called [[First School War]]. New &quot;neutral&quot; schools funded by the local communes with assistance from national government were to be established in all municipalities, while Catholic schools were to receive no support at all.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|p=139}} Outraged at the perceived challenge to its authority, the Catholic church encouraged a boycott of the schools. Though 3,885 secular schools opened across the country by 1883, attendance in private Catholic schools rose from 13 percent to over 60 percent of eligible students.{{sfn|Cook|2004|p=79}}

After elections in 1884, a Catholic government under [[Jules Malou]] passed a new Education Law providing public financial support for religious schools. Religious education became compulsory in all schools in 1895.{{sfn|Galloy|Hayt|2006|p=139}} The Catholic Party's triumph in the issue was another blow to the already-weakened Liberal Party, and ushered in a period of almost unbroken Catholic government until [[World War II]].

====Colonialism====
{{main|Congo Free State}}
Even before his accession to the throne in 1865, Leopold began lobbying leading Belgian politicians to create a colonial empire in the Far East or Africa, which would expand Belgian prestige.{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=12–5}} Politically, however, colonization was extremely unpopular, as it was perceived as a risky and expensive gamble with no obvious benefit to the country and his many attempts were rejected:{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=12–5}}

{{quote|1=Belgium does not need a colony. Belgians are not drawn towards overseas enterprises: they prefer to spend their energy and capital in countries which have already been explored or on less risky schemes&amp;nbsp;... Still, you can assure His Majesty of my whole-hearted sympathy for the generous plan he had conceived, as long as the Congo does not make any international difficulties for us.|2=[[Walthère Frère-Orban]]|3=Liberal Prime Minister, 1878–84{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|p=136}} }}
[[File:Kongovrijstaat.jpg|thumb|left|Map of the [[Congo Free State]] in 1892]]
Determined to look for a colony for himself and inspired by recent reports from central Africa, Leopold began patronizing a number of leading explorers, including [[Henry Morton Stanley]].{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=12–5}} Leopold established the [[International African Association]], a charitable organization to oversee the exploration and surveying of a territory based around the [[Congo River]], with the stated goal of bringing humanitarian assistance and civilization to the natives. In the [[Berlin Conference]] of 1884–85, European leaders officially recognized Leopold's control over the {{convert|1000000|sqmi}} of the notionally-independent [[Congo Free State]].{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=253–5}}

Leopold, however, reneged on his humanitarian promises, and instead brutally exploited the locals and the land to gain what profit he could. Initially, the Congo Free State relied on exporting [[Elephant and mammoth ivory|ivory]] to pay for its upkeep and to fund the [[Congo Arab war]] and [[Emin Pasha Relief Expedition]] in the Eastern Congo.{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=588–9}} As [[Natural rubber|rubber]] became an important resource in the 1890s, it quickly surpassed ivory as a profitable export, which allowed the colony to become extremely profitable for the first time.{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=588–9}} Monopoly concessions to collect rubber in large areas of territory were sold to private companies, and the ''[[Force Publique]]'', the state's private army, was used to force locals to collect it. In some cases, Congolese people who failed to meet their quota were killed or had one of their hands cut off. The system was immensely profitable, but the population of the Congo is thought to have been reduced by as many as ten million during the period that the colony was under Leopold's control.{{efn|Since the first census in the Congo was taken in 1923, all population estimates during the period are guesses. Current estimates of the reduction during the period range from between three to fifteen million caused by a combination of violence, disease and reduced birth rate.{{sfn|Dunn|2003|pp=44–5}} }}{{sfn|Schimmer|2010}}

Eventually, growing scrutiny of Leopold's regime led to [[Congo Free State propaganda war|a popular campaign movement]], centered in Britain and America, to force Leopold to renounce his ownership of the Congo. The &quot;Belgian solution&quot; they proposed was for Belgium to annex it in order to end the overexploitation without disrupting the delicate balance of power in colonial Africa. In 1908, as a direct result of this campaign, Belgium formally annexed the territory, creating the [[Belgian Congo]].{{sfn|Pakenham|1992|pp=657; 663}}

====Rise of socialism and franchise extension====
[[File:Charles Hermans.jpg|thumb|''At Dawn'' (1875) by [[Charles Hermans]] depicts nineteenth-century Belgium's class inequality]]
The reign of Leopold II saw the rise of organized socialist political groups and parties, most notably among the industrial workers in Wallonia. The early socialist movement was characterized by a successful [[cooperative|co-operative movement]] in Flanders. Trade unions were legalized in 1866, opening the way to organized labor politics.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|p=110}} The [[International Workingmen's Association]] held its first conference outside Switzerland in Brussels in 1868 as Belgian socialism, under figures such as [[César De Paepe]], expanded dramatically.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|p=112}}

The first real socialist political party in the country, the [[Belgian Workers' Party]] (POB-BWP), was founded in 1885. The small numbers of workers who were allowed to vote in general elections meant that it achieved little success via conventional political channels. In 1886, [[Belgian strike of 1886|rioting and violence broke out]] among industrial workers in Liège, then spread across Wallonia, and was only repressed by the military.{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|p=99}} Numerous politicians of the Workers' Party were arrested by the government in the subsequent backlash,{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|p=99}} but a wave of industrial legislation, including reforms to ban child labor and limit working hours, were introduced in the aftermath of the strike.{{sfn|Dumont|1996|pp=126–9}} The government reaction to the strikes and their bloody repression were criticized by contemporaries:

{{quote|1=There exists but one country in the civilised world where every strike is eagerly and joyously turned into a pretext for the official massacre of the Working Class. That country of single blessedness is Belgium! the {{sic}} model state of continental constitutionalism, the snug, well-hedged, little paradise of the landlord, the capitalist, and the priest.&amp;nbsp;... The massacre of this year does not differ from last year's massacre, but by the ghastlier number of its victims, the more hideous ferocity of an otherwise ridiculous army, the noisier jubilation of the clerical and capitalist press, and the intensified frivolity of the pretexts put forward by the governmental butchers.|2=[[Karl Marx]]|3=''[[The Belgian Massacres]]'' (1869){{sfn|Marx|1869}} }}
[[File:Bruxelles Laermans greve.JPG|thumb|left|''Un soir de grève'' (1893). Belgian strikers wave [[Red flag (politics)|red banners]] during the huge [[Belgian general strike of 1893|general strike of 1893]]. Painting by [[Eugène Laermans]]]]

Despite making a rapid recovery, the Belgian Workers' Party was still penalized by the Belgian electoral system, which based [[suffrage]] on wealth, stopping most of the party's support base among industrial workers from voting. In August 1885, the party began its Antwerp Programme, which called for [[universal suffrage]] while confirming the party's intention to pursue its goals through [[Social democracy|parliamentary democracy]] rather than [[Proletarian revolution|revolution]].{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|p=150}} The culmination of this policy was the [[1893 Belgian General Strike]], involving some 250,000 workers. Fearing a revolution, the government adopted universal male suffrage in 1894, but only with [[plural voting]], which allowed up to two additional votes for wealthy or educated citizens.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=154–55}} Nevertheless, the percentage of the population eligible to vote rose from 3.9 to 37.3 percent, and in the [[Belgian general election, 1894|1894 elections]] the socialists won 28 of 152 seats.{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|p=85}}{{sfn|Dumont|1996|p=134}} The Belgian Workers' Party called two further unsuccessful general strikes in 1902 and 1913 in an attempt to end the plural voting system.{{sfn|Polasky|1992|pp=449–50}}

The new voting system increased the socialists' influence in parliament significantly, but its major beneficiaries were the Catholic Party. Partly as a result of the creation of a Catholic populist challenger, the [[Christene Volkspartij|Christian People's Party]], the Catholic Party embraced the new ideology of [[Catholic social teaching|Social Catholicism]] introduced following the papal ''[[Rerum novarum]]'' [[encyclical]] of 1891.{{sfn|Hermans|1992|p=14}} This gained it considerable popular support, especially in Flanders.{{sfn|Ascherson|1999|pp=154–5}} In 1894, the Belgian Workers' Party adopted the [[Charter of Quaregnon]], which would form the basis of its ideology until 1979. By 1911, the party had 276,000 members, making it one of the most successful Socialist parties in Europe.{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|p=117}} As a result of lobbying by the Belgian Workers' Party, Belgium was one of the first countries in Europe to launch a comprehensive [[social insurance]] scheme, including sickness compensation (from 1894), voluntary old-age insurance (1900) and unemployment insurance (1907).{{sfn|Flora|Heidenheimer|1995|p=51}} The big losers from voting reform were the Liberals who lost almost all their parliamentary representation in the years between 1894 and 1900.{{sfn|Hermans|1992|p=15}}

===Reign of Albert I (to 1914)===
[[File:Albert I Koning der Belgen.jpg|upright|thumb|Portrait of Albert I]]
{{see also|Albert I of Belgium}}
Albert I inherited the throne after the death of Leopold II in 1909. His rule ended with his death in 1934, encompassing the final half-decade of the long 19th century and continuing through the First World War and into the [[Interbellum]]. The period 1909 to 1913 was marked by continued economic confidence, and two [[World's fair]] were hosted in Belgium [[Brussels International 1910|in 1910]] and [[Exposition universelle et internationale (1913)|in 1913]].{{sfn|Dumoulin et al.|2005|p=9}}

In 1913, [[Belgian general strike of 1913|a huge general strike]] took place across the country at the instigation of the Belgian Workers' Party on the issue of voting rights.{{sfn|Dumoulin et al.|2005|pp=74–6}} The system of plural voting, in force since 1893, was extremely unpopular because of its perceived unfairness, but also because the system tended to favor the Catholic Party.{{sfn|Dumoulin et al.|2005|pp=74–6}} Although between 300,000 and 450,000 workers were involved, the strike was ultimately unsuccessful. The party voted in favor ending the strike and taking future action by parliamentary means, on 22 April 1913.{{sfn|Dumoulin et al.|2005|pp=74–6}}

The issue of military reform, which had been extremely contentious right up to the end of Leopold II's reign, continued to be important up to the outbreak of the First World War. Under the influence of pro-militarist lobbying, expansion and further reform of the army was discussed in parliament, and a new system of universal military conscription was adopted in 1913.{{sfn|De Mûelenaere|2012|pp=161–2}}

====Prelude to World War I====
[[File:World War 1 Headlines R01.jpg|thumb|&quot;Germany Violates Belgian Neutrality.&quot; Headline in ''[[Le Soir]]'', 4 August 1914.]]
{{see also|Belgium in World War I}}
From as early as 1904, [[Alfred von Schlieffen]] of the [[German General Staff]] began to draw up a military strategy, known as the [[Schlieffen Plan]], which could be put into action if Germany found itself involved in a two-front war against France and Russia.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|p=9}} The core of the plan was a rapid attack on France on the outbreak of war, forcing a quick victory in the west before the Russians had time to fully mobilize their forces. The Schlieffen Plan took advantage of the French military's concentration and fortifications along the Franco-German border by prescribing an invasion of neutral Belgium and Luxembourg. According to the plan, the German army would rapidly overwhelm the Belgian military and then move quickly through the country and then towards Paris.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|p=9}} The general staff believed that none of the signatories would be willing to honor their commitments from the 1839 Treaty of London, which a German diplomat dismissed as a &quot;scrap of paper&quot;.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|p=9}}

[[File:Liége - 1914 - Soldats d'infanterie prenant part à la défense de Liège dans les faubourgs d'Herstal.jpg|left|thumb|Belgian troops at the [[Battle of Liège]] in August 1914]]
On 2 August 1914, following the events leading to the outbreak of World War I, the Germans presented an ultimatum to the Belgian government demanding permission to move German soldiers through the country.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|p=9}} The ultimatum stated that Belgian independence would be reinstated upon German victory and that reparations would be made afterwards.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|p=9}} Luxembourg was [[German occupation of Luxembourg in World War I|invaded and occupied]] by the Germans the same day.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|p=9}} On 3 August, the Belgian government rejected the proposal and the [[German invasion of Belgium|German invasion began]].{{sfn|Tucker|1998|p=9}} Contrary to the Germans' expectations, Great Britain, along with the British Empire, declared war on Germany as the Treaty of London had demanded.

The reorganization of the Belgian army that had begun in 1913 was only due to be completed in 1926. Consequently at the outbreak of war, the Belgian army was under-strength and largely unprepared.{{sfn|Strachan|2001|p=210}} Albert I took personal command of the 265,000-strong Belgian army.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|pp=25–6}} However, they could do little against the 1.5&amp;nbsp;million-strong German invading force.{{sfn|Tucker|1998|pp=25–6}} Between August and October 1914, the Germans took the fortified cities of [[Battle of Liège|Liège]], [[Siege of Namur (1914)|Namur]] and [[Siege of Antwerp (1914)|Antwerp]] and occupied Brussels. The fortified positions proved little match for the greatly improved siege artillery available to the Germans at the time, although the greater-than-expected defence did buy some time for the French and British to react. By the end of October, the Belgian army had been forced into a small pocket along the [[Yser|Yser river]] in the far west. In a surprising victory, the Belgian army managed [[Battle of the Yser|to halt the German advance at the Yser]], paving the way for the static trench warfare that which would characterize the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] for the next four years. Most of Belgium, however, was [[German occupation of Belgium during World War I|occupied by Germany]] and would remain under German control until 1918.

==Themes==

===Industrialisation===
[[File:Black Country – Borinage.jpg|thumb|View of mines in the [[Borinage]] region in the 1890s by [[Constantin Meunier]]]]
Belgium was the first country in continental Europe to experience the Industrial Revolution, and was the most intensively industrialized country in the world throughout most of the period.{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|pp=41–2}}{{sfn|Capron|Meeusen|2000|pp=26–8}} Belgian industrialized rapidly over the nineteenth century, with a focus on iron, coal and [[Textile manufacture during the Industrial Revolution|textile production]].{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Industrial Revolution&quot;}} By 1914, Belgium had extensive rail networks, mines and factories, and a productive export sector.

The Industrial Revolution is usually considered to have been spread from Britain to Belgium by two British industrialists, [[William Cockerill|William]] and [[John Cockerill (industrialist)|John Cockerill]], who moved to Liège in 1807 and formed [[John Cockerill (company)|a company]] producing industrial machinery and iron.{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Industrial Revolution&quot;}} Industrial development was possible in Belgium because of large coal deposits located in the ''Sillon industriel'' along the Sambre-Meuse river valley. Although the town of Ghent, a centre of cotton production in Flanders, industrialised rapidly, the effects of the Industrial Revolution were most felt in Wallonia, particularly in the cities of [[Mons]], Charleroi, Liège and [[Verviers]].{{sfn|Capron|Meeusen|2000|pp=26–8}} By the 1840s, Cockerill was the world's largest manufacturer of steel.{{sfn|Capron|Meeusen|2000|pp=26–8}} Belgium also rapidly developed a large railway system. From the outset, the Belgian state supported the construction of railways, envisaging a railway link between the industrial region of Mons and the port of Antwerp via Brussels.{{sfn|Wolmar|2010|pp=18–20}} The first stretch of this line, one of the first railways in Europe, opened in 1835 between Brussels and Mechelen.{{sfn|Wolmar|2010|pp=18–20}}

Belgian firms initially copied and mass-produced British designs, but soon began specializing in railway materials, chemicals, weapons and raw materials. These items were all widely exported, making Belgium one of the foremost industrial powers in the world.{{sfn|Capron|Meeusen|2000|pp=26–8}} One of the most successful exporters was [[Baron Empain|Édouard Empain]], nicknamed the &quot;Tramway King&quot;, whose company ran infrastructure projects across Europe, Asia and South America. Empain's projects included the [[Paris Métro]] system, completed in 1900, and the entire [[Khedivate of Egypt|Egyptian]] suburb of [[Heliopolis (Cairo suburb)|Heliopolis]], which was finished in 1905.{{sfn|Dobrowolska|Dobrowolski|2006|pp=84–5}}

===Language division===
[[File:Nicaise de Keyser02.jpg|thumb|1836 depiction of the [[Battle of the Golden Spurs]] by [[Nicaise de Keyser]]. Evoking Flemish history played a central role in the development of the [[Flemish Movement]]. ]]
As the independent state of Belgium consolidated after the Revolution, the issue of a consensus language in the country became an increasingly important political question.{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|pp=156–7}} At the start of the period, French was the dominant language, and was the only language that was approved for use in legal and government business anywhere in the country. It was also the language of the economic and social elite, even in Flanders. By the 1860s, with Flemish dialects in decline, increasing numbers of Flemish people of all social classes were bilingual, paralleling a similar decline [[French Flanders|in northern France]].{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|pp=156–7}} However, partly inspired by a resurgence in Flemish literature and culture, the ''[[Flamingant]]'' political movement began to develop, with their first political parties formed in the 1860s and 70s. Political agitation by ''Flamingant'' groups, often directed by local priests, led to Belgium becoming officially bilingual in 1870. Teaching Dutch in all secondary schools in Flanders became compulsory, reinforcing the language's presence.{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1995|pp=156–7}} By 1898, Dutch was [[Coremans-De Vriendt law|officially recognized]] as an equal language to French in legal matters. During the first decades of the 20th century, the [[Flemish Movement]] became increasingly radicalized and began to develop as a mass political movement (although not a united one), fully emerging during the First World War.{{sfn|Hermans|1992|p=17}}

In the 1880s, a [[Walloon Movement]] began to emerge in parallel to the Flemish Movement. The early Walloon Movement developed in reaction to the perceived discrimination against French language as Dutch was progressively accorded equality.{{sfn|Hermans|1992|p=14}} At the same time, the movement called on a &quot;Walloon identity&quot; rather than a Belgian one. In his famous ''Lettre au roi sur la séparation de la Wallonie et de la Flandre'' (&quot;Letter to the King on the separation of Wallonia and Flanders&quot;) published in 1912, the Walloon socialist [[Jules Destrée]] argued that the language division in Belgium was irreconcilable, famously stating that &quot;In Belgium, there are the Walloons and the Flemish. There are no Belgians.&quot;{{sfn|Destrée|1912|p=8}}

===Literature===
The 19th century saw a flourishing of Belgian literature in both French and Dutch languages. In Flanders, the [[Romanticism|Literary Romanticist]] movement, aided by a renewed interest in Belgium's medieval past, flourished under authors including [[Hendrik Conscience]], who is credited as &quot;father of the Flemish novel&quot;, and poets like [[Jan Theodoor van Rijswijck|Theodoor van Rijswijck]].{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}}{{sfn|''Dictionary of Biography''|2003|p=354}} Conscience's most famous work, ''[[De Leeuw van Vlaanderen (novel)|De Leeuw van Vlaanderen]]'' (&quot;The Lion of Flanders&quot;, 1838), portrayed a romantic and heavily embellished account of the [[County of Flanders]]' fight against the [[Kingdom of France|French]] in the 14th century, with the Flemish victory at the [[Battle of the Golden Spurs]] in 1302 as the centerpiece. ''De Leeuw van Vlaanderen'' became a source of inspiration for the Flemish Movement and remains one of the best examples of Flemish literature.{{sfn|Govers|Go|2009|p=121}}

From the 1860s, Flemish literature began to reflect the [[Literary realism|Realist style]] already popular in France, under writers such as [[Anton Bergmann]] and [[Virginie Loveling]].{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}} The works feature detailed depictions of ordinary aspects of daily life and often have a pessimistic tone.{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}} Heavily influenced by Belgian dialects such as [[West Flemish]], the poet and priest [[Guido Gezelle]] produced [[Lyric poetry|lyric poems]] in Dutch from the 1850s until his death in 1899.{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}} In 1893, the cultural magazine ''[[Van Nu en Straks]]'' (&quot;Of Today and Tomorrow&quot;) was launched to bring Flemish literature to an audience outside Belgium. Flemish literature continued to flourish in the first decades of the 20th century under writers such as [[Stijn Streuvels]].{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}}

In Wallonia, literature in French began a revival in 1881 with the creation of the ''[[La Jeune Belgique]]'' (&quot;The Young Belgium&quot;) movement, which supported the creation of distinctively Belgian literature and opposed romanticism.{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}} Among the members of the ''Jeune Belgique'' were the writer [[Camille Lemonnier]], whose works were often set against the background of Belgian peasant life in the [[Naturalism (literature)|naturalist style]], and the poet [[Charles Van Lerberghe]].{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}} French language poetry flourished in Belgium in the early 20th century under [[Émile Verhaeren]] and [[Maurice Maeterlinck]]; Maeterlinck was awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Literature|Nobel Prize]] in 1911.{{sfn|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}}

==See also==
{{portal|Belgium|History}}
*[[Antoinism]] - a Spiritualist cult founded in Belgium in 1910
*[[Christianity in the 19th century]]
*[[France in the long nineteenth century]]
*[[Fashion in the nineteenth century]]
*[[19th-century philosophy]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Citations==
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin|30em}}
*{{cite book|last=Ascherson|first=Neal|authorlink=Neal Ascherson|title=The King Incorporated: Leopold the Second and the Congo|year=1999|publisher=Granta|location=London|isbn=1-86207-290-6|edition=New|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor1-last=de Barsy|editor1-first=E.G.|title=La Société Générale de Belgique, 1822–1972|year=1972|language=French|publisher=Société Générale|location=Brussels|oclc=699019|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Beaufays|first=Jean|title=Belgium: A Dualist Political System?|journal=Publius|volume=18|number=2|year=Spring 1988|ref={{sfnRef|Beaufays|1988}} }}
*{{cite web|title=Belgian literature|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/59234/Belgian-literature|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Online|accessdate=27 October 2013|ref={{sfnRef|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Belgian literature&quot;}} }}
*{{cite news|url=http://www.flandersonline.org/nl/flanders/5/70 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071021194233/http://www.flandersonline.org/nl/flanders/5/70 |archivedate=21 October 2007 |title=Brussel verfranst in de 19de eeuw|newspaper=Flanders Online|language=Dutch|accessdate=18 January 2009|ref={{sfnRef|''Flanders Online''}} }}
*{{cite book|editor1-last=Capron|editor1-first=Henri|editor2-last=Meeusen|editor2-first=Wim|title=The National Innovation System of Belgium|publisher=|location=New York|year=2000|isbn=3-7908-1308-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Carson|first=Patricia|title=The Fair Face of Flanders|publisher=E.Story-Scientia|location=Ghent|year=1974|edition=Rev.|oclc=463182600|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Chartrand|first=René|title=The Mexican Adventure 1861–67|year=2004|publisher=Osprey|location=London|isbn=185532430X|edition=4th|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|last=Chastain|first=James|title=Belgium in 1848|url=http://www.ohio.edu/chastain/ac/belgium.htm|work=Encyclopedia of 1848 Revolutions|publisher=[[Ohio University]]|accessdate=16 December 2013|ref={{sfnRef|Chastain, ''Belgium in 1848''|2004}} }}
*{{cite web|last=Chastain|first=James|title=Leopold I|year=2004|url=http://www.ohio.edu/chastain/ip/leopold.htm|work=Encyclopedia of 1848|publisher=Ohio University|ref={{sfnRef|Chastain, ''Leopold I''|2004}} }}
*{{cite book|last=Clark|first=Samuel|title=State and Status: The Rise of the State and Aristocratic Power in Western Europe|publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press|location=Montreal|year=1995|isbn=978-0-7735-1226-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Cook|first=Bernard A.|title=Belgium: A History|publisher=Peter Lang|location=New York|year=2004|edition=3rd|isbn=0-8204-7647-1|series=Studies in Modern European History|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Coulombe|first=Charles A.|title=The Pope's Legion: The Multinational Fighting Force that Defended the Vatican|publisher=Palgrave-MacMillan|location=New York|year=2008|isbn=978-0-230-60058-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Destrée|first=Jules|authorlink=Jules Destrée|title=Lettre au Roi sur la Séparation de la Wallonie et de la Flandre|publisher=M. Weissenbruch S.A.|location=Brussels|year=1912|language=French|url=http://www.institut-destree.eu/Publications/Jules-Destree_Lettre-au-roi_1912-08-15_Extrait_Revue-de-Belgique.pdf|format=PDF|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Dobrowolska|first1=Agnieszka|last2=Dobrowolski|first2=Jarosław|title=Heliopolis: Rebirth of the City of the Sun|date=2006|publisher=American University in Cairo Press|location=Cairo|isbn=9774160088|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Dumont|first=Georges-Henri|title=La Vie Quotidienne en Belgique sous la Règne de Léopold II (1856–1909)|year=1996|publisher=Éd. Le Cri|location=Brussels|isbn=2-87106-173-4|edition=Rev.|language=French|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Dumoulin|first1=Michel|last2=Gerard|first2=Emmanuel|last3=Van den Wijngaert|first3=Mark|last4=Dujardin|first4=Vincent|title=Nouvelle Histoire de Belgique|volume=II: 1905–1950|year=2005|language=French|publisher=Éd. Complexe|location=Brussels|isbn=2-8048-0078-4|ref={{sfnRef|Dumoulin et al.|2005}} }}
*{{cite book|last=Dunn|first=Kevin C.|title=Imagining the Congo: the International Relations of Identity|date=2003|publisher=Palgrave-Macmillan|location=London|isbn=1-4039-6160-3|edition=1st|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor1-last=Flora|editor1-first=Peter|editor2-last=Heidenheimer|editor2-first=Arnold J.|title=The Development of Welfare States in Europe and America|location=New Jersey|publisher=Transaction Publishers|year=1995|edition=2nd|isbn=0-87855-920-5|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Galloy|first1=Denise|last2=Hayt|first2=Franz|title=La Belgique: des Tribus Gauloises à l'Etat Fédéral|year=2006|language=French|publisher=De Boeck|location=Brussels|isbn=2-8041-5098-4|edition=5th|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Govers|first1=Robert|last2=Go|first2=Frank|title=Place Branding: Glocal, Virtual and Physical Identities, Constructed, Imagined and Experienced|date=2009|publisher=Palgrave-Macmillan|location=Basingstoke|isbn=978-0-230-23073-6|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Hawgood|first=J.A.|chapter=Liberalism and Constitutional Developments|title=The New Cambridge Modern History|volume=X: The Zenith of European Power, 1830–70|year=1964|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=0-521-04548-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite news|title=Heureuse révolution au pays de Liège|url=http://archives.lesoir.be/heureuse-revolution-au-pays-de-liege-le-sang-n-a-pas-co_t-19890303-Z01F2D.html|newspaper=[[Le Soir]]|date=3 March 1989|language=French|accessdate=24 December 2013|ref={{sfnRef|''Le Soir''|1989}} }}
*{{cite book|last=Hobsbawm|first=Eric|authorlink=Eric Hobsbawm|title=The Age of Empire, 1875–1914|year=1995|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|location=London|isbn=0-297-81635-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|title=Houghton Mifflin Dictionary of Biography|year=2003|publisher=Houghton Mifflin|location=Boston, MA|isbn=0-618-25210-X|ref={{sfnRef|''Dictionary of Biography''|2003}} }}
*{{cite web|title=Industrial Revolution|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/287086/Industrial-Revolution#toc3502|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Online|accessdate=27 October 2013|ref={{sfnRef|''Britannica Online'', &quot;Industrial Revolution&quot;}} }}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Revue militaire|1873}}|title=La Réorganisation de l'Armée Belge|journal=Revue militaire de l'étranger|date=6 July 1873|volume=4|issue=110}}
*{{cite news|last=Laporte|first=Christian|title=Le Roi bâtisseur|url=http://www.lalibre.be/archive/le-roi-batisseur-51b88ab3e4b0de6db9ac607c|language=French|newspaper=[[La Libre Belgique]]|date=15 July 2005|accessdate=10 December 2013|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=De Metsenaere|first=Machteld|url=http://www.briobrussel.be/assets/andere%20publicaties/btng-rbhc,%2021,%201990,%203-4,%20pp%20383-412.pdf |title=Thuis in gescheiden werelden – De migratoire en sociale aspecten van verfransing te Brussel in het midden van de 19e eeuw|journal=Btng-Rbhc|volume=XXI|issue=3–4|year=1990|pages=383–412|language=Dutch|publisher=Vrije Universiteit Brussel|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|first=Karl|last=Marx|authorlink=Karl Marx|title=The Belgian Massacres|year=1869|url=https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/iwma/documents/1869/belgian-massacre.htm|publisher=[[Marxists Internet Archive]]|series=International Workingmen's Association 1869|accessdate=17 October 2013|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=De Mûelenaere|first=Nel|title=An Uphill Battle? Campaigning for the Militarization of Belgium 1870–1914|journal=Journal of Belgian History (RBHC-BTNG)|volume=XLII|issue=4|year=2012|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|Hermans|1992}}|last1=Hermans|first1=Theo|title=The Flemish Movement: A Documentary History, 1780–1990|date=1992|publisher=Athlone Press|location=London|isbn=0-485-11368-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Pakenham|first=Thomas|authorlink=Thomas Pakenham (historian)|title=The Scramble for Africa: the White Man's Conquest of the Dark Continent from 1876 to 1912|year=1992|publisher=Abacus|location=London|isbn=978-0-349-10449-2|edition=13th|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Papadopoulos|first=Alex G.|title=Urban Regimes and Strategies: Building Europe's Central Executive District in Brussels|date=1996|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=9780226645599|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Pirenne|first=Henri|authorlink=Henri Pirenne|title=Histoire de Belgique|volume=VI: La Fin du Régime espagnol, Le Régime austricien, La Révolution Brabançonne et La Révolution Liégoise|edition=2nd|language=French|publisher=Maurice Lamertin|location=Brussels|year=1926|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Pirenne|first=Henri|title=Histoire de Belgique|volume=VII: De la Révolution de 1830 à la Guerre de 1914|edition=2nd|language=French|publisher=Maurice Lamertin|location=Brussels|year=1948|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Polasky|first=Janet L.|title=A Revolution for Socialist Reforms: The Belgian General Strike for Universal Suffrage|journal=[[Journal of Contemporary History]]|year=July 1992|volume=27|number=3|ref=harv|doi=10.1177/002200949202700304 }}
*{{cite web|last=Schimmer|first=Russell|title=Congo Free State|url=http://www.yale.edu/gsp/colonial/belgian_congo/|publisher=Yale University|year=2010|work=Genocide Studies Program|accessdate=10 December 2013|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|title=The First World War|volume=I: To Arms|last=Strachan|first=Hew|authorlink=Hew Strachan|year=2001|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=0-19-926191-1|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Tucker|first=Spencer C.|authorlink=Spencer C. Tucker|title=The Great War, 1914–1918|series=Warfare and History|publisher=UCL|location=London|year=1998|isbn=0-253-21171-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Wolmar|first=Christian|title=Blood, Iron &amp; Gold: How the Railways transformed the World|location=London|year=2010|publisher=Grove Atlantic|isbn=978-1-84887-171-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Zolberg|first=Aristide R.|title=The Making of Flemings and Walloons: Belgium: 1830–1914|journal=[[Journal of Interdisciplinary History]]|volume=5|number=2|year=1974|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{commons category|Belgium in the 19th century}}
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last1=Deneckere|first1=Gita|last2=Witte|first2=Els|last3=Gubin|first3=Eliane|last4=Nandrin|first4=Jean-Pierre|title=Nouvelle Histoire de Belgique|volume=I: 1830–1905|year=2005|language=French|publisher=Éd. Complexe|location=Brussels|isbn=2-8048-0066-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Dumont|first=Georges-Henri|title=La Vie Quotidienne en Belgique sous la Règne de Léopold II (1856–1909)|year=1996|language=French|publisher=Éd. Le Cri|location=Brussels|isbn=2-87106-173-4|edition=Rev.}}
*{{cite book|last=Emerson|first=Barbara|authorlink=Barbara Emerson|title=Léopold II: le Royaume et l'Empire|edition=French trans.|year=1994|publisher=Éd. Duculot|location=Paris|isbn=978-2801108048}}
*{{cite book|last=Pirenne|first=Henri|authorlink=Henri Pirenne|title=Histoire de Belgique|volume=VII: De la Révolution de 1830 à la Guerre de 1914|edition=2nd|language=French|publisher=Maurice Lamertin|location=Brussels|year=1948}}
{{refend}}

{{Belgium topics}}

{{Good article}}

[[Category:19th century in Belgium| ]]</text>
      <sha1>2dbqqno8z6fh6zweswn6oij6mmktzy0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
