<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Blackburn Firebrand</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4848913</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750107288</id>
      <parentid>750106561</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-17T21:26:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith-264</username>
        <id>925588</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Development */ Copyedit (minor)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16988">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Use British English|date=October 2013}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
  |name= Firebrand
  |image= File:Blackburn TF Mk. IV.jpg
  |caption=Centaurus IX-powered Firebrand T.F. Mk IV
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
  |type=[[Strike fighter]]
  |national origin= United Kingdom
  |manufacturer=[[Blackburn Aircraft]]
  |first flight=27 February 1942
  |introduced=1945
  |retired=1953
  |status=
  |primary user=[[Royal Navy]]
  |produced=1942–47
  |number built=220 + 3 prototypes
  |unit cost=
  |variants with their own articles= [[Blackburn Firecrest]]
}}
|}

The '''Blackburn Firebrand''' was a British single-engine [[strike fighter]] for the [[Fleet Air Arm]] of the [[Royal Navy]] designed during World War II by [[Blackburn Aircraft]]. Originally intended to serve as a pure [[fighter aircraft|fighter]], its unimpressive performance and the allocation of its [[Napier Sabre]] piston engine by the [[Ministry of Aircraft Production]] for the [[Hawker Typhoon]] caused it to be redesigned as a strike fighter to take advantage of its load-carrying capability. Development was slow and the first production aircraft was not delivered until after the end of the war. Only a few hundred were built before it was withdrawn from front-line service in 1953.

==Development==
In general, the Fleet Air Arm had required fighters that were capable of navigating long ranges over sea and speed differential over attackers was not critical. Defence of British naval bases was a RAF commitment but provision had not been made for this and so the Admiralty accepted that it would have to take on the duty. For this it needed an interceptor fighter and experience in the [[Norwegian Campaign]] of early 1940 had also shown a high-performance, carrier-based, single-seat fighter would be an advantage. Blackburn tendered their B-37 design using the [[Napier Sabre]] 24-cylinder [[H engine|H-type engine]], and this was accepted by June 1940 with a proposal to order &quot;off the drawing board&quot; (meaning without prototypes). [[Air Ministry Specification]] N.11/40—stating a minimum top speed of {{convert|350|kn|lk=in}}—was raised to cover this design and an order placed in January 1941 for three prototypes.&lt;ref name=Buttler173&gt;Buttler 2004, p. 173&lt;/ref&gt;

The B-37, given the service name &quot;Firebrand&quot; on 11 July 1941, was a low-winged, all-metal [[monoplane]]. Aft of the [[cockpit]] the fuselage was an oval-shaped stressed-skin [[semi-monocoque]], but forward it had a circular-section, tubular-steel frame that housed the {{convert|169|impgal|l USgal|adj=on|lk=in}} main fuel tank and the {{convert|71|impgal|l USgal|adj=on}} auxiliary fuel tank behind the engine. The [[radiator]]s for the neatly [[Cowling|cowled]] Sabre engine were housed in [[wing root|wing-root]] extensions. The large wing consisted of a two-[[spar (aviation)|spar]] centre section with manually folded outer panels (with five degrees of [[dihedral (aircraft)|dihedral]]) to allow more compact storage in the hangar decks of [[aircraft carrier]]s. To increase [[lift (force)|lift]] and reduce landing speed the wing was fitted with large, hydraulically powered [[Fowler flap]]s that extended to the edges of the [[Frise aileron]]s. The fixed armament of four {{convert|20|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404|Hispano autocannon]] was fitted in the outer wing panels with 200 [[Cartridge (firearms)|rounds]] per gun. The [[vertical stabilizer|fin]] and [[rudder]] were positioned forward of the [[horizontal stabilizer|elevator]] to ensure [[spin (flight)|spin]] recovery and that the rudder would retain its effectiveness. The mainwheels of the [[conventional landing gear]] were mounted at the ends of the centre wing section and retracted inwards.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, p. 27; Jackson, pp. 440–41&lt;/ref&gt; The Firebrand was unusual in that there was an airspeed gauge mounted outside of the cockpit so that during landing the pilot would not have to look down into the cockpit to take instrument readings, foreshadowing the modern [[heads up display|heads-up display]].&lt;ref name=b9&gt;Brown, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

The unarmed first prototype [[maiden flight|first flew]] on 27 February 1942 using the Sabre II, the first of two armed prototypes following on 15 July. The initial flight trials were a disappointment as the aircraft could only reach {{convert|32|mph|abbr=on}} below Blackburn's estimated maximum speed of 390&amp;nbsp;mph. Replacement of the Sabre II with a Sabre III (an engine built specifically for the Firebrand)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1945/1945%20-%202284.html |title=Napier Sabre VII |page=551 |date=22 November 1945 |magazine=Flight }}&lt;/ref&gt; improved its top speed to {{convert|358|mph|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=Buttler173/&gt; The second prototype, DD810, conducted deck-landing trials, with [[Commander (Royal Navy)|Commander]] [[Dennis Cambell]] at the controls, aboard the fleet carrier {{HMS|Illustrious|87|6}} in February 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 26, 28&lt;/ref&gt; The Sabre engine was also used in the Hawker Typhoon, a fighter already in production and the Ministry of Air Production (MAP) decided that the Typhoon had priority for the Sabre. The Sabre was also experiencing production problems&lt;ref name=Buttler173/&gt; and so a new engine was needed, along with the necessary airframe adaptations. To use the time and effort invested in the design, the MAP decided to convert the Firebrand into an interim strike fighter, to meet a Fleet Air Arm requirement for a single-seat [[torpedo bomber]] capable of carrying [[bomb]]s, [[rocket]]s and being capable of [[air-to-air combat]]. Nine production F. Mk I aircraft were built to the original specifications and were retained for trials and development work.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, p. 279; Jackson, pp. 441–42&lt;/ref&gt;

After it was badly damaged during an [[emergency landing]], DD810 was converted into a prototype of the first strike variant, the Firebrand T.F. Mk II (with the company designation B-45), that flew on 31 March 1943. It was an adaptation of the Mk I with the wing centre section widened by {{convert|1|ft|3.5|in|cm}} to make room for the torpedo on the centreline between the mainwheels. Like the Mk I, the TF Mk II only saw a very limited production run of 12 aircraft and they were also allocated for development work, including those assigned to [[708 Naval Air Squadron]], a shore-based trials unit. Blackburn proposed several versions of the Sabre-powered aircraft including one for the RAF as the B-41, a version with a high-lift wing as the B-42, and the B-43 [[floatplane]], none of which were accepted for further development.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, pp. 442–43&lt;/ref&gt;

A new specification was issued as S.8/43 to cover the development of the Firebrand T.F. Mk III (B-45) with the {{convert|2400|hp|adj=on}} [[Bristol Centaurus|Bristol Centaurus VII]] [[radial engine]]. Two prototypes were converted from incomplete F Mk Is and 27 additional aircraft were delivered, completing the first batch of 50 aircraft. The first prototype flew on 21 December 1943, but construction of the new aircraft was very slow with the first flight not being made until November 1944. Most changes were related to the installation of the larger-diameter Centaurus engine, including air intakes for the [[carburetor]] and oil cooler in the wing-root extensions that formerly housed the engine's radiators. Spring-loaded [[trim tab]]s were also fitted to all control surfaces. Production aircraft after the first 10 were fitted with the improved Centaurus IX engine.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, pp. 443–44&lt;/ref&gt; The Mk III was found to be unsuitable for carrier operations for a variety of reasons. The new engine produced more [[torque]] than the Sabre, and rudder control was insufficient on takeoff with the full flaps needed for carrier use. Visibility while landing was very poor, the tailhook attachment to the airframe was too weak, and the aircraft had a tendency to drop a wing at the [[stall (flight)|stall]] while landing, so development continued to rectify these issues.&lt;ref name=b9/&gt;

The T.F. Mk IV (B-46), as the new development was designated, featured larger [[empennage|tail surfaces]] for better low-speed control. The enlarged rudder was [[Balanced rudder#Aerodynamic balancing|horn balanced]] and the vertical stabilizer was offset three degrees to port to counteract the four-bladed Rotol propeller's torque. The wings now featured hydraulically operated [[dive bomber|dive brake]]s on both upper and lower surfaces. The aircraft's wings were now stressed to carry one {{convert|2000|lb|adj=on}} bomb under each wing or a {{convert|45|impgal|l USgal|adj=on}} [[drop tank]] or eight [[RP-3]] rockets. The frame that held the torpedo was connected to the undercarriage so that it pivoted nose-downward to increase ground clearance with the landing gear extended and pivoted upward to reduce drag while in flight. A {{convert|100|impgal|l USgal|adj=on}} fuel tank could be fitted on the centreline in lieu of the torpedo. The Mk IV first flew on 17 May 1945, and was the first version of the Firebrand to enter [[mass production]],&lt;ref&gt;Brown, p. 30; Jackson, p. 445&lt;/ref&gt; with 170 built, although 50 more aircraft were cancelled.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt;

The later Firebrand T.F. Mk 5 featured minor aerodynamic improvements and 123 were converted from Mk IVs. The final version was the Firebrand T.F. Mk 5A with hydraulically boosted ailerons to increase the aircraft's rate of [[Flight dynamics (fixed-wing aircraft)|roll]]. Two Mk 5s and five Mk IVs were converted to the Mk 5A standard.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt;

==Operational history==
[[File:Blackburn Firebrand during trials on HMS Illustrious (IWM photo A14851).jpg|thumb|A prototype Firebrand TF Mk II taxiing along the flight deck of [[HMS Illustrious (87)|HMS ''Illustrious'']] with its flaps extended during trials]]
The Firebrand did not see action in World War II, as TF 4s were not issued to [[813 Naval Air Squadron]] until 1 September 1945. The squadron was disbanded 30 September 1946 without ever deploying to sea. It was reformed with TF 5s on 1 May 1947 and flew them from the carrier {{HMS|Implacable|R86|6}}, later {{HMS|Indomitable|92|6}}, until it was reequipped with turboprop [[Westland Wyvern]] attack aircraft in February 1953. [[827 Naval Air Squadron]] received their TF 5 and 5As on 13 December 1950 and flew them primarily off the carrier {{HMS|Eagle|R05|6}} until it disbanded on 19 November 1952. A variety of second-line squadrons were issued Firebrands of various marks for training or trials at one time or another.&lt;ref&gt;Sturtivant 1984, pp. 212, 214, 280, 282, 437&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[test pilot]] and naval aviator [[Captain (Royal Navy)|Captain]] [[Eric Brown (pilot)|Eric Brown]]'s opinion the aircraft was &quot;short of performance, sadly lacking in manoeuvrability, especially in rate of roll&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the positioning of the cockpit even with the trailing edge of the wing gave the pilot a very poor view over the nose and inhibited his ability to view his target and to land his aircraft aboard a carrier, enough so that Brown called it &quot;a disaster as a deck-landing aircraft&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 31, 46–47&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
;Blackburn B-37
:Three prototypes ordered to meet Specification N.11/40, named ''Firebrand'' on 11 July 1941. Second prototype re-built as T.F. II prototype.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 449&lt;/ref&gt;
;Firebrand F. I
:Production variant of the Blackburn B.37 with an order for 50 aircraft to be built at Brough, most completed as T.F. II and T.F. III variants, first nine completed as F. Is.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot;&gt;Sturtivant 2004, pp. 33–41&lt;/ref&gt;
;Firebrand T.F. II
:Improved variant, 12 built from original production branch.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt;
;Firebrand T.F. III
:Blackburn B-45, a Centarus VII powered-variant, two prototypes to S.8/43&lt;ref name=Buttler174&gt;Buttler 2004, p. 174&lt;/ref&gt; and 27 production aircraft for original production batch.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt;
;Firebrand T.F. IV
:Blackburn B-46, improved variant with 2,520 bhp Centaurus IX or Centaurus 57,&lt;ref name=Buttler174/&gt; 250 ordered, but only 170 were completed, of which 124 were converted to T.F. 5 standard, some before delivery.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt; Six were modified and designated as T.F. IV(mod).&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt;
;Firebrand T.F. 5
:Improved variant, 124 modified from T.F. IV, two conversions to T.F. 5A.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt;
;Firebrand T.F. 5A
:One prototype modified from a T.F. 5 and six conversions from either T.F. IV or Vs.&lt;ref name=&quot;fixedwing&quot; /&gt;

==Operators==
; {{UK}}
* Royal Navy Fleet Air Arm
** [[813 Naval Air Squadron]]&lt;ref&gt;Sturtivant 1984, pp. 212, 214&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[827 Naval Air Squadron]]&lt;ref&gt;Sturtivant 1984, pp. 280, 282&lt;/ref&gt;

==Specifications (Firebrand T.F. Mk IV)==
[[File:Blackburn-Firebrand.png|right|300px|Orthographically projected diagram of the Firebrand Mk.IV.]]
{{Aircraft specs
|ref=The Firebrand...Blackburn's Baby 'Battleship'&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 27, 30&lt;/ref&gt;
|prime units?=imp
&lt;!--
        General characteristics
--&gt;
|genhide=

|crew=1
|length m=
|length ft=38
|length in=9
|span m=
|span ft=51
|span in=3.5
|height m=
|height ft=13
|height in=3
|wing area sqm=
|wing area sqft=383
|wing area note=
|airfoil=
|empty weight kg=
|empty weight lb=11,457
|empty weight note=
|gross weight kg=
|gross weight lb=16,700
|gross weight note=
|fuel capacity={{convert|239|impgal|l USgal|abbr=on}}
|more general=
&lt;!--
        Powerplant
--&gt;
|eng1 number=1
|eng1 name=[[Bristol Centaurus]] IX
|eng1 type=18-cylinder [[radial engine]]
|eng1 kw=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng1 hp=2,520
|eng1 shp=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|more power=

|prop blade number=4
|prop name=Rotol
|prop dia m=
|prop dia ft=13
|prop dia in=3
|prop note=
&lt;!--
        Performance
--&gt;
|perfhide=

|max speed kmh=
|max speed mph=342
|max speed kts=
|cruise speed kmh=&lt;!-- if max speed unknown --&gt;
|cruise speed mph=256
|cruise speed kts=
|never exceed speed kmh=
|never exceed speed mph=
|never exceed speed kts=
|range km=
|range miles=745
|range nmi=
|combat range km=
|combat range miles=
|combat range nmi=
|endurance=&lt;!-- if range unknown --&gt;
|ceiling m=
|ceiling ft=
|climb rate ms=
|climb rate ftmin=2,600
|lift to drag=
|wing loading kg/m2=
|wing loading lb/sqft=
|wing loading note=
|more performance=
&lt;!--
        Armament
--&gt;
|guns= 4 × {{convert|20|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404|Hispano autocannon]]
|bombs= 1 × {{convert|1850|lb|kg|abbr=on}} [[torpedo]] or 2 × {{convert|2000|lb|abbr=on}} bombs
|rockets= 16 × [[RP-3]]
}}

==See also==
{{aircontent
|similar aircraft=
* [[Boeing XF8B]]
* [[Curtiss XBTC]]
* [[Douglas A-1 Skyraider]]
* [[Douglas XTB2D Skypirate]]
* [[Fairey Spearfish]]
* [[Martin AM Mauler]]
* [[Westland Wyvern]]
|related=
* [[Blackburn Firecrest]]
|see also=
|lists=
* [[List of aircraft of the Fleet Air Arm]]
}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
* Brown, Eric. &quot;The Firebrand...Blackburn's Baby 'Battleship'&quot;. ''[[Air International]]'', July 1978, Vol. 15:1. Bromley, UK: Fine Scroll. pp.&amp;nbsp;25–31, 46–47.
* Buttler, Tony. ''Blackburn Firebrand – Warpaint Number 56''. Denbigh East, Bletchley, UK: Warpaint Books, 2000. {{oclc|65202546}}
*Buttler, Tony. ''British Secret Projects: Fighters &amp; Bombers 1935–1950''. Hinckley, UK: Midland Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-85780-179-2.
*[[Norman Friedman|Friedman, Norman]]. ''British Carrier Aviation: The Evolution of the Ships and Their Aircraft''. Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press, 1988. ISBN 0-87021-054-8.
* Jackson, A. J. ''Blackburn Aircraft Since 1909''. London: Putnam, 1968. ISBN 0-370-00053-6.
* [[Ray Sturtivant|Sturtivant, Ray]]. ''Fleet Air Arm Fixed-Wing Aircraft Since 1946''.  Tonbridge, Kent, UK: [[Air-Britain]], 2004. ISBN 0-85130-283-1.
* Sturtivant, Ray. ''The Squadrons of the Fleet Air Arm''. Tonbridge, Kent, UK: Air-Britain (Historians), 1984. ISBN 0-85130-120-7.
*{{cite magazine |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1945/1945%20-%201909.html |title=Blackburn Firebrand IV |format=pdf |magazine=[[Flight International|Flight]] |date= 27 September 1945 |pages=339–41|volume= XLVII|issue= 1918}}
*{{cite magazine |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1945/1945%20-%201958.html |title=Blackburn Firebrand IV |format=pdf |magazine=Flight |date= 4 October 1945 |pages=367–69|volume= XLVII|issue= 1918}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Blackburn Firebrand}}
*[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1947/1947%20-%200267.html Firebrand development versions] ''Flight'' 13 Feb 1947

{{Blackburn aircraft}}

[[Category:Blackburn aircraft|Firebrand]]
[[Category:British attack aircraft 1940–1949]]
[[Category:British fighter aircraft 1940–1949]]
[[Category:Single-engined tractor aircraft]]
[[Category:Low-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Carrier-based aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>h0322erim71d56v702yibt2s8l3yc9z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
