<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bockscar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14616755</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747704981</id>
      <parentid>747549965</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T22:15:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hawkeye7</username>
        <id>302229</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Correct the block number, per Campbell, p. 172</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24489">{{italic title}}
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
| name                = ''Bockscar''
| image               = Bockscar 050809-F-1234P-003.jpg
| caption             = ''Bockscar'' nose art: the Fat Man silhouettes represent four [[pumpkin bomb]] missions (black) and the atomic bomb drop on Nagasaki (a red symbol, fourth in the line of five symbols)
| alt                 = &lt;!-- Alt text for main image --&gt;
}}{{Infobox aircraft career
|sole example of type?= n&lt;!-- only Y or N --&gt;
|aircraft name        = 
|image                = ONLY AVAILABLE IF STANDING ALONE&lt;!--in the ''Image:filename'' format with no image tags--&gt;
|caption              = ONLY AVAILABLE IF STANDING ALONE&lt;!--Image caption; if it isn't descriptive, please skip--&gt;
|other names          = &lt;!--Other names (nicknames, nose art names) this aircraft is known by--&gt;
|type                 = [[B-29 Superfortress|B-29-36-MO Superfortress]]
|manufacturer         = [[Glenn L. Martin Company]], [[Omaha, Nebraska]]
|construction number  = &lt;!-- manufacturer's construction number --&gt;
|construction date    =  &lt;!-- either roll-out date or span of time for lengthy projects, whichever seems more appropriate --&gt;
|civil registration   = &lt;!-- any civil registrations carried by this aircraft --&gt;
|military serial      =  44-27297
|radio code           = &lt;!-- military radio codes where this is a commonly used way of identifying this aircraft (e.g. US, British, and German military aircraft of WWII --&gt;
|first flight         = &lt;!-- date of first flight --&gt;
|owners               = &lt;!-- owners or operators, whether private individuals, companies, or military services --&gt;
|in service           = April 1945 to September 1946
|flights              = &lt;!-- number of flights made by this aircraft, usually only relevant for an aircraft no longer flying --&gt;
|total hours          = &lt;!-- total number of hours flown by this aircraft, usually only relevant for an aircraft no longer flying --&gt;
|total distance       = &lt;!-- total distance flown by this aircraft, usually only relevant for an aircraft no longer flying --&gt;
|fate                 =
|preservation         = The [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]], [[Dayton, Ohio]]
}}
|}

'''''Bockscar''''',  sometimes called '''Bock's Car''', is the name of the [[United States Army Air Forces]] [[B-29]] [[bomber]] that dropped a [[Fat Man]] [[nuclear weapon]] over the Japanese city of [[Nagasaki]] during [[World War II]] in the second – and last – [[Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki#Nagasaki|nuclear attack]] in history. One of 15 [[Silverplate]] B-29s used by the 509th, ''Bockscar'' was built at the [[Glenn L. Martin Company|Glenn L. Martin Aircraft Plant]] at [[Bellevue, Nebraska]], at what is now [[Offutt Air Force Base]], and delivered to the United States Army Air Forces on 19 March 1945. It was assigned to the [[393d Bombardment Squadron]], [[509th Composite Group]] to [[Wendover Army Air Field]], [[Utah]] in April.

''Bockscar'' was used in 13 training and practice missions from [[Tinian]], and three combat missions in which it dropped [[pumpkin bomb]]s on industrial targets in Japan. On 9 August 1945, ''Bockscar'', piloted by the 393d Bombardment Squadron's commander, [[Major]] [[Charles W. Sweeney]], dropped a Fat Man nuclear bomb with a [[Nuclear weapon yield|blast yield]] equivalent to 21 kilotons of TNT over the city of [[Nagasaki]]. About 44% of the city was destroyed; 35,000 people were killed and 60,000 injured.

After the war, ''Bockscar'' returned to the United States in November 1945. In September 1946 it was given to the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] at [[Wright-Patterson Air Force Base]], [[Ohio]]. The aircraft was flown to the Museum on 26 September 1961, and its original markings were restored. ''Bockscar'' is now on permanent display at the National Museum of the United States Air Force, [[Dayton, Ohio|Dayton]], Ohio, next to a replica of a Fat Man.

==Airplane history==
[[File:Boeing B-29 Superfortress Bockscar 3 USAF.jpg|thumb|300px|right|''Bockscar'' at Dayton before it was moved indoors. On the Nagasaki mission, it flew without nose art, and with a triangle N tail marking, rather than the circle arrowhead shown here.]]
''Bockscar'', B-29-36-MO 44-27297, [[Unit identification aircraft markings#XXI Bomber Command|Victor number]] 77, was one of 15 [[Silverplate]] B-29s used by the   [[393d Bombardment Squadron]] of the [[509th Composite Group]]. ''Bockscar'' was built at the [[Glenn L. Martin Company|Glenn L. Martin Aircraft Plant]] at [[Bellevue, Nebraska]], at what is now [[Offutt Air Force Base]], as a Block 35 aircraft. It was one of 10 modified as a Silverplate and re-designated &quot;Block 36&quot;. {{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=172–173}}

Silverplate involved extensive modifications to the B-29 to carry nuclear weapons. The bomb bay doors and the fuselage section between the bomb bays were removed to create a single {{convert|33|ft|adj=on}} bomb bay. British suspensions and bracing were attached for both shape types, with the gun-type suspension anchored in the aft bomb bay and the implosion type mounted in the forward bay. Weight reduction was also accomplished by removal of [[gun turrets]] and [[armor plating]]. These B-29s also had an improved engine, the [[Wright R-3350 Duplex-Cyclone|R-3350-41]]. The Silverplate aircraft represented a significant increase in performance over the standard variants.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=8–15}}

Delivered to the [[United States Army Air Forces]] on 19 March 1945, ''Bockscar'' was assigned to [[Captain (land)|Captain]] [[Frederick C. Bock]] and crew C-13, and flown to [[Wendover Army Air Field]], [[Utah]] in April.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=172–173}} The name chosen for the aircraft, and painted on it after the mission, was a pun on the name of the aircraft commander.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|p=222}} It left Wendover on 11 June 1945 for [[Tinian]], where it arrived 16 June. It was originally given the Victor (unit-assigned identification) number 7 but on 1 August was given the [[Unit identification aircraft markings#509th Composite Group|triangle N tail markings]] of the [[444th Bombardment Group]] as a security measure, and had its Victor changed to 77 to avoid misidentification with an actual 444th aircraft.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|p=19}}

''Bockscar'' was used in 13 training and practice missions from Tinian, and three combat missions in which it dropped [[pumpkin bomb]]s on industrial targets in Japan, in which Bock's crew bombed [[Niihama]] and [[Musashino, Tokyo|Musashino]], and [[First Lieutenant]] [[Charles Donald Albury]] and crew C-15 bombed [[Toyota, Aichi|Koromo]].{{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=113, 139, 142}}

==Atomic bomb mission==
{{main article|Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki}}

===Mission and crew===
''Bockscar'' was flown on 9 August 1945, by the crew of another B-29, ''[[The Great Artiste]]'', and piloted by [[Major]] [[Charles Sweeney|Charles W. Sweeney]], commander of the 393d Bombardment Squadron. The plane was co-piloted by First Lieutenant Charles Donald Albury, the normal aircraft commander of Crew C-15.&lt;ref name=lat&gt;{{cite news |first=|last=|title=Charles Donald Albury dies at 88; copilot on the Nagasaki bomb plane|url=http://www.latimes.com/news/obituaries/la-me-charles-albury9-2009jun09,0,954488.story |newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]] |accessdate=29 March 2013 |publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=9 June 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Great Artiste'' was designated as the observation, instrumentation support plane for the second mission, and another B-29, ''[[Big Stink (B-29)|The Big Stink]]'', flown by Group Operations Officer Major James I. Hopkins, Jr., as the photographic aircraft. The mission had as its primary target the city of [[Kokura]], where the  Kokura Arsenal was located. Its secondary target was Nagasaki, where two large [[Mitsubishi]] armament plants were located.{{sfn|Sweeney|Antonucci|Antonucci|1997|pp=193–195}}

''Bockscar'' had been flown by Sweeney and crew C-15 in three test drop rehearsals of inert [[Fat Man]] assemblies in the eight days leading up to the second mission, including the final rehearsal the day before.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=113–114}} ''The Great Artiste'', which was the assigned aircraft of the crew with whom Sweeney most often flew, had been designated in preliminary planning to drop the second bomb, but the aircraft had been fitted with observation instruments for the Hiroshima mission. Moving the instrumentation from ''The Great Artiste'' to ''Bockscar'' would have been a complex and time-consuming process, and when the second atomic bomb mission was moved up from 11 August to 9 August because of adverse weather forecasts, the crews of ''The Great Artiste'' and ''Bockscar'' instead exchanged aircraft. The result was that the bomb was carried by ''Bockscar'', but flown by the crew C-15 of ''The Great Artiste''.&lt;ref name=&quot;olivi&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.uwosh.edu/faculty_staff/earns/olivi.html | title = Reflections from above | publisher = University of Wisconsin–Oshkosh| accessdate = 9 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kokura and Nagasaki===
[[File:Atomic cloud over Hiroshima from B-29.jpg|thumb|The mushroom cloud as seen from one of the B-29s on the mission]]
During pre-flight inspection of ''Bockscar'', the flight engineer notified Sweeney that an inoperative fuel transfer pump made it impossible to use {{convert|640|USgal}} of fuel carried in a reserve tank. This fuel would still have to be carried all the way to Japan and back, consuming still more fuel. Replacing the pump would take hours; moving the Fat Man to another aircraft might take just as long and was dangerous as well, as the bomb was live. Group Commander Colonel [[Paul Tibbets]] and Sweeney therefore elected to have ''Bockscar'' continue the mission.{{sfn|Sweeney|Antonucci|Antonucci|1997|pp=204–205}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Nagasaki&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hiroshima-remembered.com/history/nagasaki/page3.html |accessdate=29 March 2013 |title=The Story of Nagasaki}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Bockscar'' took off from Tinian's [[North Field (Tinian)|North Field]] at 03:49.{{sfn|Craven|Cate|1953|p=719}} The mission profile directed the B-29s to fly individually to the rendezvous point, changed because of bad weather from [[Iwo Jima]] to [[Yakushima, Kagoshima|Yakushima Island]], and at {{convert|17000|ft|m}} cruising altitude instead of the customary {{convert|9000|ft|m}}, increasing fuel consumption. ''Bockscar'' began its climb to the {{convert|30000|ft|m}} bombing altitude a half hour before rendezvous.{{sfn|Sweeney|Antonucci|Antonucci|1997|pp=204–205}} Before the mission, Tibbets had warned Sweeney to take no more than fifteen minutes at the rendezvous before proceeding to the target. Bockscar reached the rendezvous point and assembled with ''The Great Artiste'', but after circling for some time, ''The Big Stink'' failed to appear. As they orbited Yakushima, the weather planes ''[[Enola Gay]]'' and ''[[Laggin' Dragon (B-29)|Laggin' Dragon]]'' reported both Kokura and Nagasaki within the accepted parameters for the required visual attack.{{sfn|Sweeney|Antonucci|Antonucci|1997|pp=210–211}}{{sfn|Craven|Cate|1953|p=720}}{{sfn|Campbell|2005|p=30}}

Though ordered not to circle longer than fifteen minutes, Sweeney continued to wait for ''The Big Stink'', at the urging of [[Commander]] [[Frederick Ashworth]], the plane's weaponeer, who was in command of the mission.{{sfn|Craven|Cate|1953|p=720}} After exceeding the original departure time limit by a half hour, ''Bockscar'', accompanied by ''The Great Artiste'', proceeded to Kokura, thirty minutes away.  The delay at the rendezvous had resulted in clouds and drifting smoke from fires started by a major firebombing raid by 224 B-29s on nearby [[Yawata, Kyoto|Yawata]] the previous day covering 70% of the area over Kokura, obscuring the aiming point. Three bomb runs were made over the next 50 minutes, burning fuel and exposing the aircraft repeatedly to the heavy defenses of Yawata, but the bombardier was unable to drop visually. By the time of the third bomb run, Japanese anti-aircraft fire was getting close, and Second Lieutenant [[Jacob Beser]], who was monitoring Japanese communications, reported activity on the Japanese fighter direction radio bands.{{sfn|Sweeney|Antonucci|Antonucci|1997|pp=179, 213–215}}

The increasingly critical fuel shortage resulted in the decision by Sweeney and Ashworth to reduce power to conserve fuel and divert to the secondary target, Nagasaki. The approach to Nagasaki twenty minutes later indicated that the heart of the city's downtown was also covered by dense cloud. Ashworth decided to bomb Nagasaki using radar, but, according to ''Bockscar's'' bombardier, Captain [[Kermit Beahan]], a small opening in the clouds at the end of the three-minute bomb run permitted him to identify target features. ''Bockscar'' visually dropped the Fat Man at 10:58 local time.{{sfn|Craven|Cate|1953|p=720}} It exploded 43 seconds later with a blast yield equivalent to 21 kilotons of [[Trinitrotoluene|TNT]] at an altitude of {{convert|1650|ft}}, approximately {{convert|1.5|mi}} northwest of the planned aiming point, resulting in the destruction of 44% of the city.{{sfn|Wainstock|1996|p=92}}

The failure to drop the Fat Man at the precise bomb aim point caused the atomic blast to be confined to the [[Urakami|Urakami Valley]]. As a consequence, a major portion of the city was protected by the intervening hills, but even so, the bomb was dropped over the city's industrial valley midway between the Mitsubishi Steel and Arms Works in the south and the Mitsubishi-Urakami Ordnance Works in the north. An estimated 35,000 people were killed and 60,000 injured during the bombing at Nagasaki.{{sfn|Groves|1962|p=346}} Of those killed, 23,200–28,200 were Japanese munitions workers, 2,000 were Korean slave laborers, and 150 were Japanese soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Nuke-Rebuke: Writers &amp; Artists Against Nuclear Energy &amp; Weapons (The Contemporary anthology series) |pages=22–29 |date=May 1, 1984 |publisher=The Spirit That Moves Us Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Groves|1962|pp=343–346}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoddeson et al., pp. 396-397&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=396–397}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Landing and debriefing===
Because of the delays in the mission and the inoperative fuel transfer pump, the B-29 did not have sufficient fuel to reach the emergency landing field at Iwo Jima, so Sweeney flew the aircraft to [[Okinawa]]. Arriving there, he circled for 20 minutes trying to contact the control tower for landing clearance, finally concluding that his radio was faulty. Critically low on fuel, ''Bockscar'' barely made it to the runway at [[Yontan Airfield]] on Okinawa. With only enough fuel for one landing attempt, Sweeney and Albury brought ''Bockscar'' in at {{convert|150|mph}} instead of the normal {{convert|120|mph}}, firing distress flares to alert the field of the uncleared landing. The number two engine died from fuel starvation as ''Bockscar'' began its final approach. Touching the runway hard, the heavy B-29 slewed left and towards a row of parked B-24 bombers before the pilots managed to regain control. The B-29's reversible propellers were insufficient to slow the aircraft adequately, and with both pilots standing on the brakes, ''Bockscar'' [[Ground loop (aviation)|made a swerving 90-degree turn]] at the end of the runway to avoid running off the runway. A second engine died from fuel exhaustion by the time the plane came to a stop. The flight engineer later measured fuel in the tanks and concluded that less than five minutes total remained.{{sfn|Sweeney|Antonucci|Antonucci|1997|pp=222–226}}

Following the mission, there was confusion over the identification of the plane. The first eyewitness account by war correspondent [[William L. Laurence]] of the ''[[New York Times]]'', who accompanied the mission aboard the aircraft piloted by Bock, reported that Sweeney was leading the mission in ''The Great Artiste''. However, he also noted its &quot;Victor&quot; number as 77, which was that of ''Bockscar'', writing that several personnel commented that 77 was also the jersey number of the football player [[Red Grange]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eyewitness&quot;/&gt; Laurence had interviewed Sweeney and his crew in depth and was aware that they referred to their airplane as ''The Great Artiste''. Except for ''[[Enola Gay]]'', none of the 393d's B-29s had yet had names painted on the noses, a fact which Laurence himself noted in his account, and unaware of the switch in aircraft, Laurence assumed Victor 77 was ''The Great Artiste''.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|p=222}} In fact, ''The Great Artiste'' was Victor 89.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|p=184}}

== Current status ==
[[File:Boeing B-29 Bockscar cockpit 2 USAF.jpg|right|thumb|Engine controls]]

After the war, ''Bockscar'' returned to the United States in November 1945 and served with the 509th at [[Walker Air Force Base|Roswell Army Air Field]], [[New Mexico]]. It was nominally assigned to the [[Operation Crossroads]] task force, but there are no records indicating that it deployed for the tests. In August 1946, it was assigned to the [[AMARG|4105th Army Air Force Unit]] at [[Davis-Monthan Air Force Base|Davis-Monthan Army Air Field]], [[Arizona]], for storage.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=172–173}}

At Davis-Monthan it was placed on display as the aircraft that bombed Nagasaki, but in the markings of ''The Great Artiste''. In September 1946, title was passed to the Air Force Museum (now the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]]) at [[Wright-Patterson Air Force Base]], [[Ohio]]. The aircraft was flown to the Museum on 26 September 1961,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=527 |title=Boeing B-29 Superfortress |publisher=United States Air Force  |accessdate=29 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its original markings were restored.{{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=172–173}} ''Bockscar'' is now on permanent display at the National Museum of the United States Air Force, [[Dayton, Ohio|Dayton]], Ohio. This display, a primary exhibit in the Museum's Air Power gallery, includes a replica of a Fat Man bomb and signage that states that it was &quot;The aircraft that ended WWII&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=3358 |title=Bockscar: The aircraft that ended WWII |publisher=United States Air Force  |accessdate=29 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, a short documentary was made about Charles Sweeney's recollections of the Nagasaki mission aboard ''Bockscar'', including details of the mission preparation, titled &quot;Nagasaki: The Commander's Voice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mputtre.com/id39.html |title=Nagasaki |accessdate=29 March 2013 |publisher=Michael Puttré }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Crew members==

===Regularly assigned crew===
Crew C-13 (manned ''[[The Great Artiste]]'' on the Nagasaki mission):&lt;ref name=&quot;Eyewitness&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.atomicarchive.com/Docs/Hiroshima/Nagasaki.shtml |last=Laurence |first=William L.|authorlink=William Laurence |title=Eyewitness Account of Atomic Bomb Over Nagasaki |publisher=National Science Digital Library |accessdate=28 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Campbell|2005|p=138}}
*Captain [[Frederick C. Bock]], Aircraft Commander, Greenville, MI
*First Lieutenant Hugh Cardwell Ferguson, Sr., Co-pilot, Highland Park, MI
*First Lieutenant Leonard A. Godfrey, Jr., Navigator, Greenfield, MA
*First Lieutenant  Charles Levy, Bombardier, Philadelphia, PA
*Master Sergeant Roderick F. Arnold, Flight Engineer, Rochester, MI
*Sergeant Ralph D. Belanger, Assistant Flight Engineer, Thendara, NY
*Sergeant Ralph D. Curry, Radio Operator, Hoopeston, IL
*Sergeant William C. Barney, Radar Operator, Columbia City, IN
*Sergeant Robert J. Stock, Tail Gunner, Fort Wayne, IN

===Nagasaki mission crew===
[[File:Bocks-Car-enlisted-flight-crew.png|right|thumb|Crew C-15. front row: Dehart, Kuharek, Buckley, Gallagher, Spitzer; back row: Olivi, Beahan, Sweeney, Van Pelt, Albury]]
Crew C-15 (normally assigned to ''[[The Great Artiste]]''):&lt;ref name=&quot;Eyewitness&quot;/&gt;{{sfn|Campbell|2005|pp=141–142}}
*Major [[Charles W. Sweeney]], Aircraft Commander, North Quincy, MA
*Captain [[Charles Donald Albury|Charles Donald &quot;Don&quot; Albury]], Co-pilot (pilot of Crew C-15), Miami, FL
*Second Lieutenant Frederick &quot;Fred&quot; J. Olivi, Regular Co-pilot
*Captain James F. Van Pelt, Jr., Navigator, Oak Hill, WV
*Captain [[Kermit Beahan|Kermit K. Beahan]], Bombardier, Houston, TX
*Master Sergeant John D. Kuharek, Flight Engineer, Sharpsburg, PA
*Staff Sergeant Raymond C. Gallagher, Gunner, assistant flight engineer, Chicago, IL
*Staff Sergeant Edward K. Buckley, Radar Operator, Lisbon, OH
*Sergeant Abe M. Spitzer, Radio Operator, Bronx, NY
*Sergeant Albert T. &quot;Pappy&quot; DeHart, Tail Gunner, Plainview, TX

Also on board were the following additional mission personnel:&lt;ref name=&quot;Eyewitness&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hiroshima-remembered.com/history/nagasaki/page3.html |title=The Story of Nagasaki |publisher=National Science Digital Library |accessdate=28 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Commander (United States)|Commander]] [[Frederick Ashworth]], [[United States Navy|USN]], Weaponeer
*[[Lieutenant (navy)|Lieutenant]] Philip M. Barnes, USN, Assistant Weaponeer
*Second Lieutenant [[Jacob Beser]], Radar Countermeasures, Baltimore, MD (Lt. Beser flew on ''both'' atomic missions, serving as the radar countermeasures crewman on the ''[[Enola Gay]]'', August 6, 1945, and ''Bockscar'', August 9, 1945).

==National Museum of the United States Air Force display==

&lt;gallery mode=packed heights=200&gt;
File:Fat Man and Bockscar.jpg|
File:Boeing B-29 Bockscar cockpit USAF.jpg|
File:Boeing B-29 Superfortress Bockscar USAF.jpg|
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|United States Air Force|World War II}}
*''[[Enola Gay]]'', B-29 that dropped the atomic bomb on Hiroshima

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last=Campbell |first=Richard H. |title=The Silverplate Bombers: A History and Registry of the Enola Gay and Other B-29's Configured to Carry Atomic Bombs |location=Jefferson, North Carolina |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-7864-2139-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Craven|first=Wesley|last2=Cate |first2=James|editor-last=Craven|editor-first=Wesley|editor-last2=Cate |editor-first2=James|contribution=Victory|title=The Pacific: Matterhorn to Nagasaki|pages=703–758|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|year=1953|series=The Army Air Forces in World War II. Volume V|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/V/AAF-V-23.html|accessdate=29 March 2013|oclc=256469807|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Groves|first=Leslie |authorlink=Leslie Groves |title=Now it Can be Told: The Story of the Manhattan Project |location=New York |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |year=1962 |isbn=978-0-306-70738-4 |oclc=537684 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Hoddeson |first=Lillian |first2=Paul W. |last2=Henriksen |first3=Roger A. |last3=Meade |first4=Catherine L. |last4=Westfall |title=Critical Assembly: A Technical History of Los Alamos During the Oppenheimer Years, 1943–1945 |location=New York|publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1993 |isbn=0-521-44132-3|oclc=26764320|ref=harv }}
*{{cite book |last=Sweeney |first=Charles |authorlink=Charles Sweeney |first2=James A. |last2=Antonucci |first3=Marion K. |last3=Antonucci |title=War's End: an Eyewitness Account of America's Last Atomic Mission |location=New York |publisher=Avon Books |year=1997 |isbn=978-0-380-97349-1 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Wainstock |first=Dennis D. |title=The Decision to Drop the Atomic Bomb |publisher=Praeger Publishing |isbn=978-0-275-95475-8 |year=1996|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Bockscar}}
{{Refbegin}}
* [http://www.uwosh.edu/faculty_staff/earns/olivi.html Reflections from above: Fred Olivi's perspective on the mission which dropped the atomic bomb on Nagasaki]
* [http://www.hbo.com/docs/programs/whitelightblackrain/index.html White Light/Black Rain Official Website] (film)
* [http://www1.city.nagasaki.nagasaki.jp/na-bomb/museum/m1-1e.html Records of the Nagasaki Atomic Bombing]
{{Refend}}

{{Coord|39.781976|-84.108892|type:landmark_region:US-OH|display=title}}
{{Manhattan Project}}
{{good article}}

[[Category:Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]]
[[Category:Individual aircraft of World War II]]
[[Category:Manhattan Project]]
[[Category:Boeing B-29 Superfortress]]</text>
      <sha1>s9so1emwzr9umvzbocvt6cu8dxa4rrn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
