<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Burmese–Siamese War (1547–49)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26091715</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749675036</id>
      <parentid>748894302</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-15T16:47:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>2 archive templates merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37505">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
||conflict    = Burmese–Siamese War (1547–1549)
| image       = [[File:Burmese-Siamese War of 1548-49.svg|300px]]
| caption     = Map of the 1548–1549 campaign
| partof      = [[Burmese–Siamese wars]]
| date        = c. October 1547 – February 1549
| place       = Upper Tenessarim coast, western and central Siam
| result      = Siamese defensive victory &lt;br&gt; Burma claims to regain Upper Tenasserim down to [[Dawei|Tavoy]] (Dawei)
| combatant1  = [[Toungoo Dynasty|Toungoo Dynasty (Burma)]]
| commander1  = [[Tabinshwehti]] &lt;br&gt; [[Bayinnaung]] &lt;br&gt; [[Saw Lagun Ein]] &lt;br&gt; [[Thado Dhamma Yaza I of Prome|Thado Dhamma Yaza]] &lt;br&gt; [[Mingyi Swe]] &lt;br&gt; [[Diogo Soares]]
| combatant2  = [[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]] [[Kingdom of Ayutthaya|Ayutthaya Kingdom (Siam)]]
| commander2  = [[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]] [[Maha Chakkraphat]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]] [[Sri Suriyothai]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]] [[Prince Ramesuan|Phra Ramesuan]]{{POW}}&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]] [[Mahinthrathirat|Phra Mahin]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]] [[Mahathammarachathirat (king of Ayutthaya)|Phra Thammaracha]]{{POW}} &lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]]  [[Galeote Pereira]]
| units1      = [[Royal Burmese Army]] &lt;br&gt; [[Royal Burmese Navy]] &lt;br&gt; [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] [[mercenaries]]
| units2      = [[File:Flag of Thailand (Ayutthaya period).svg|20px]] [[Royal Siamese armed forces (1238-1852)|Royal Siamese Army]] &lt;br&gt; [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] [[mercenaries]]
| strength1   = '''1547–48'''&lt;ref name=hy-2-238&gt;Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 238&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;The figures here are reduced by an order of magnitude from those given in the Burmese chronicles per (Harvey 1925: 333–335).&lt;/ref&gt;
12,000 troops &lt;br&gt;
* Army: 8000 men, 200 horses, 20 elephants
* Navy: 4000 men (30 war boats, 10 ships)
----
'''1548–49''' &lt;br&gt;
* Start: 12,000 troops, 1680 horses, 48 elephants&lt;ref name=hy-2-240-241&gt;Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 240–241&lt;/ref&gt;
* Battle of Ayutthaya: 10,000+ troops, 200+ horses, 20+ elephants&lt;ref name=hy-2-242-243&gt;Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 242–243&lt;/ref&gt;
* Battle of Kamphaeng Phet: 11,500 troops, 500 horses, 25 elephants&lt;ref name=hy-2-240-244&gt;Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 240–244&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = '''1547–48'''&lt;ref group=note&gt;Per Burmese chronicles (Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 238), reduced by an order of magnitude per (Harvey 1925: 333–335)&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;
6000 troops
----
'''1548–49'''

}}
{{Campaignbox Burmese–Siamese Wars}}

The '''Burmese–Siamese War (1547–49)''' ({{lang-my|ယိုးဒယား-မြန်မာစစ် (၁၅၄၇–၄၉)}}; {{lang-th|สงครามพม่า-สยาม พ.ศ. 2090–92}} or สงครามพระเจ้าตะเบ็งชเวตี้, lit. &quot;Tabinshwehti's war&quot;) was the first war fought between the [[Toungoo Dynasty]] of [[Burma]] and the [[Ayutthaya Kingdom]] of [[Siam]], and the first of the [[Burmese–Siamese wars]] that would continue until the middle of the 19th century. The war is notable for the introduction of [[early modern warfare]] to the region. It is also notable in [[history of Thailand|Thai history]] for the death in battle of Siamese Queen [[Sri Suriyothai|Suriyothai]] on her [[war elephant]]; the conflict is often referred to in [[Thailand]] as the '''War that Led to the Loss of Queen Suriyothai ''' ({{lang|th|สงครามคราวเสียสมเด็จพระสุริโยไท}}).

The [[casus belli]] have been stated as a Burmese attempt to expand their territory eastwards after a political crisis in Ayutthaya&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 112&quot;/&gt; as well as an attempt to stop Siamese incursions into the upper [[Tenasserim coast]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Phayre 100&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt; The war, according to the Burmese, began in January 1547 when Siamese forces conquered the frontier town of [[Dawei|Tavoy]] (Dawei). Later in the year, the [[Royal Burmese Armed Forces|Burmese forces]] led by Gen. [[Saw Lagun Ein]] retook the Upper Tenasserim coast down to Tavoy. Next year, in October 1548, three Burmese armies led by King [[Tabinshwehti]] and his deputy [[Bayinnaung]] invaded Siam through the [[Three Pagodas Pass]]. The Burmese forces penetrated up to the capital [[Ayutthaya (city)|city of Ayutthaya]] but could not take the heavily fortified city. One month into the siege, Siamese counterattacks broke the siege, and drove back the invasion force. But the Burmese negotiated a safe retreat in exchange for the return of two important Siamese nobles (the heir apparent Prince Ramesuan, and Prince [[Mahathammarachathirat (king of Ayutthaya)|Thammaracha]] of [[Phitsanulok]]) whom they had captured.

The successful defense preserved Siamese independence for 15 years. Still, the war was not decisive. The next [[Burmese–Siamese War (1563–64)|Burmese invasion in 1563]] would force a Siamese surrender in February 1564, and make Ayutthaya a [[vassal]] state of Burma for the first time.

==Background==

===Rise of Toungoo Dynasty===
[[File:ShweMawDaw01.jpg|thumb|right|160px|The [[Shwemawdaw Paya]] in [[Pegu]] (modern day Bago, Myanmar), the city became Tabinshwehti's new capital.]]
Burma in the 15th century was divided into four principal power centers: the [[Ava Kingdom]] in present-day central Burma, the [[Hanthawaddy Kingdom]] on the southern coast, the [[Mrauk-U Kingdom]] (Arakan) in the west, and various [[Shan States]] in the east and the north. Beginning in the 1480s, Ava began to disintegrate into even smaller kingdoms. By the early 15th century, Ava's former vassals—[[Mohnyin]] (and its allies [[Confederation of Shan States]]) in the north and the [[Prome Kingdom]] (Pyay) in the south—were regularly raiding their former overlord's territory with increasing frequency and intensity.&lt;ref name=geh-100-109&gt;Harvey 1925: 100–109&lt;/ref&gt;

During this period of tumult, [[Mingyi Nyo]], then governor of [[Taungoo|Toungoo]] (Taungoo), a small region located at the southeastern corner of Ava Kingdom also declared independence in 1510, and largely stayed out of the internecine fighting in the following years. When Ava fell to the combined forces of the Confederation and Prome in 1527, many people fled to Toungoo, the only region in Upper Burma at peace.&lt;ref name=jf&gt;Fernquest 2005: 20–50&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=geh-124-125&gt;Harvey 1925: 124–125&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1530, Mingyi Nyo's son 14-year-old [[Tabinshwehti]] succeeded him as king. Toungoo's stability continued to attract manpower from the surrounding regions, especially after 1533 when the Confederation sacked its erstwhile ally Prome. The tiny Toungoo was now the only ethnic [[Bamar|Burman]]-led kingdom, and one surrounded by much larger kingdoms. Fortunately for Toungoo, the Confederation was distracted by internal leadership disputes, and Hanthawaddy, then the most powerful kingdom of all post-[[Pagan Dynasty|Pagan]] kingdoms, was weakly led. Tabinshwehti decided not to wait until the larger kingdoms' attention turned to him.

In 1534, Tabinshwehti and his deputy [[Bayinnaung]], then a couple of 18-year-olds, launched their first [[Toungoo–Hanthawaddy War (1534–41)|military campaign against Hanthawaddy]]. It was the first of a series of wars by Toungoo that would engulf western and central mainland Southeast Asia for the next 80 years. In 1538–39, the upstart kingdom captured Hanthawaddy's capital [[Bago, Burma|Pegu]] (Bago), and in May 1541, [[Mottama|Martaban]] (Mottama) and [[Mawlamyaing|Moulmein]] (Mawlamyaing).&lt;ref name=geh-153-158&gt;Harvey 1925: 153–158&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mha-106-112&gt;Htin Aung 1967: 106–112&lt;/ref&gt; Significantly, for the first time, the Burmese and the Siamese shared a common border in the upper-[[Tenasserim coast]].

For the next six years, Toungoo was busy fighting against Hanthawaddy's allies: Prome (1542), the Confederation (1542–1544), and Prome's ally Mrauk-U (1546–1547). On the eve of the Siamese war, in 1547, Toungoo controlled a Lower Burma region from [[Bagan|Pagan]] (Bagan) in the north to Moulmein in the south.&lt;ref name=geh-153-158/&gt;&lt;ref name=mha-106-112/&gt;

===Crisis in Ayutthaya===
[[File:Royal Palace of Ayutthaya.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Ruins of the Royal Palace of Ayutthaya, in the [[Ayutthaya Historical Park]], [[Phra Nakhon Si Ayutthaya Province]]. The stupas of the royal chapel (Wat Phra Si Sanphet) is in the background.]]
King [[Chairacha]] of Ayutthaya was a scion of the [[List of Thai Monarchs#2nd Suphannaphum Dynasty .281409–1569.29|Suphannaphum Dynasty]], which took control of Siam from the [[List of Thai Monarchs#2nd Uthong Dynasty .281388–1409.29|Uthong Dynasty]] in 1409. He came to the throne in 1533 after usurping the crown of his five-year-old nephew, Phra [[Ratsadathirat]], who had reigned for only four months.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 100&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 100&lt;/ref&gt; The boy's father was King [[Borommarachathirat IV]], Chairacha's half-brother. The child-king was subsequently executed by his uncle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 101&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 101&lt;/ref&gt; King Chairacha died in 1546 after reigning for thirteen years, leaving the throne to his eleven-year-old-son, Prince Kaeofa, who was crowned King [[Yodfa|Yot Fa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 108&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 108&lt;/ref&gt;

As the new king had not come of age, the role of [[regent]] was assumed by his mother, Chairacha's [[Concubinage|chief consort]] [[Si Sudachan]] ({{lang|th|ศรีสุดาจันทร์}}, also spelled Sri Sudachan), who was a descendant of the Uthong royal house. Chairacha's half-brother and [[Front Palace#Ayutthaya period|Uparaja]], Prince [[Maha Chakkraphat|Thianracha]], was another contender for the regency. To avoid court intrigues and conflict with Si Sudachan, Prince Thianracha [[Retreat (spiritual)|retreated]] to a [[Vihara|monastery]] as a [[bhikkhu|monk]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 108&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 108&lt;/ref&gt; It is said that even before the previous King's death, Si Sudachan was having an [[adultery|adulterous relationship]] with a [[paramour]] styled [[Thai royal and noble titles#Khun|Khun]] [[Khun Chinnarat|Chinnarat]], who was keeper of the Royal chapel or [[cloister]] ({{lang|th|หอพระเทพบิดร}}, Ho Phra Thep Bidon) within the Royal Palace of Ayutthaya. [[Fernão Mendes Pinto]], a contemporary Portuguese explorer, recorded a rumour alleging that Si Sudachan had poisoned her husband in order to take control of the throne, and perhaps to restore the fallen House of Uthong to power. In support of these allegations, she had many prominent officials executed, including the aged and high-ranking [[Thai royal and noble titles#Phraya|Phraya]] Maha Sena (Minister of Defence), and replaced them with her favourites.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 109&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 109&lt;/ref&gt; It was also recorded that she was heavily pregnant and soon gave birth to a daughter; unable to conceal this secret, she mounted a coup, removed her son and put her paramour on the throne. He was crowned as King (or Khun) [[Worawongsathirat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 109&quot;/&gt; It was said that the young King Yot Fa was either executed or poisoned by his mother.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 110&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 110&lt;/ref&gt;

Worawongsathirat's reign was short. Within 42 days several nobles and government officials of Ayutthaya plotted to remove him from the throne. The conspirators were led by Khun Phiren Thorathep, a descendant on his father's side to the [[Kingdom of Sukhothai|kings of Sukhothai]] and a relation on his mother's side to King Chairacha.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 110&quot;/&gt; The usurper was lured from the safety of the palace into the jungle with a promise of capturing a large [[Indian Elephant|elephant]]. As the usurper king, Si Sudachan and their infant daughter proceeded by [[Royal Barge Procession|royal barge]], Khun Phiren Thorathep and his conspirators sprang an [[ambush]], killing all three.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 111&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 111&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 14&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 14&lt;/ref&gt; Prince Thianracha was immediately invited to leave the [[Sangha (Buddhism)|Sangha]] and assume the throne as King [[Maha Chakkraphat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 15&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 15&lt;/ref&gt; One of his first acts was to appoint Khun Phiren Thorathep as King of [[Sukhothai (city)|Sukhothai]] (but as a [[vassal]] to himself) with a capital at the great fortified town of [[Phitsanulok]]. The king then bestowed upon him the title [[Mahathammarachathirat (king of Ayutthaya)|Maha Thammaracha]] (a title used by the last four kings of Sukhothai), along with the hand of his daughter Princess [[Wisutkasat|Sawatdirat]] in marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 112&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 112&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 13&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 13&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tenasserim (1547–1548)==
The war began in 1547.&lt;ref name=geh-158&gt;Harvey 1925: 158&lt;/ref&gt; The casus belli have been stated as an attempt by Toungoo Dynasty of Burma to expand its territory eastwards after a political crisis in Ayutthaya&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 112&quot;/&gt; as well as an attempt to stop Ayutthaya's incursions into the upper [[Tenasserim coast]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Phayre 100&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt; According to the [[Burmese chronicles]], a Siamese force of 6000 had occupied [[Dawei|Tavoy]] (Dawei) in the Upper Tenasserim coast, which he considered his territory, by January 1547.&lt;ref group=note&gt;Burmese chronicles (Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 238) say Tabinshwehti learned of the Siamese occupation of Tavoy before he agreed to a truce with King [[Min Bin]] of Mrauk-U on 31 January 1547 (9th waxing of Tabodwe 908 [[Burmese calendar|ME]]).&lt;/ref&gt; As frontiers in the pre-modern period were less defined and often overlapped,&lt;ref name=jf-2005-286&gt;Fernquest 2005: 286&lt;/ref&gt; the &quot;occupation&quot; may have been an attempt by Ayutthaya to reinforce the frontier town, which was claimed by Toungoo. At any rate, Tabinshwehti sent a sizable force of 12,000 (8000 army, 4000 navy) led by [[Saw Lagun Ein]], viceroy of Martaban, to take over Tavoy c. October/November 1547.&lt;ref group=note&gt;The invasion likely began in late October/early November 1547 although Burmese chronicles (Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 238–239) simply say the attack on Tavoy began in 909 ME (30 March 1547 to 28 March 1548). The attack probably did not take place in early 1547 since Tabinshwehti's troops evacuated southern Arakan only on 26 March 1547 (5th waxing of Late Tagu 908 ME). The troops would have arrived back only in mid-to-late April, leaving just about a month for a military campaign before the rainy season began in June. The invasion, like most wars by the Burmese kings, probably began toward the end of rainy season and after the end of Buddhist Lent, which ended on 13 October 1547 (New moon of Thadingyut 909 ME) that year.&lt;/ref&gt; A joint land-naval attack on Tavoy drove out the Siamese forces led by the Lord of Kanchanaburi to lower Tenasserim.&lt;ref name=hy-2-238-239&gt;Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 238–239&lt;/ref&gt;

==Invasion of mainland Siam (1548–1549)==
[[File:Attack on Ayutthaya (1549).svg|thumb|320px|left|Map of [[Central Thailand|western central Thailand]], depicting the towns captured by King Tabinshwehti's army. The plan of the [[Ayutthaya (city)|city of Ayutthaya]] is shown with all the surrounding canals depicted.]]

===Burmese battle plan===
Tabinshwehti was not satisfied, and planned an invasion of Siam itself. By October 1548, he had assembled another 12,000-strong force&lt;ref name=hy-2-240-241/&gt; that also included about 400 Portuguese mercenaries led by [[Diogo Soares]].&lt;ref name=geh-158-159&gt;Harvey 1925: 158–159&lt;/ref&gt; The invasion force would have been equipped with the conventional weapons of the day: [[sword]]s, [[bow and arrows]] and [[spear]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Quaritch Wales 1952: 145&lt;/ref&gt; The more elite members would also carry [[matchlocks]] or [[muskets]].&lt;ref&gt;Quaritch Wales 1952: 189&lt;/ref&gt; These [[Early Modern warfare|early modern weapons]] having been introduced to the two kingdoms by the Portuguese a few decades earlier.

Tabinshwehti took personal command and gathered his forces at [[Mottama|Martaban]] (Mottama).&lt;ref name=&quot;Phayre 100&quot;&gt;Phayre 1967: 100&lt;/ref&gt; The invasion forces were organized into three main armies: the vanguard army led by Bayinnaung, the main army led by Tabinshwehti and the rearguard army led by [[Thado Dhamma Yaza I of Prome|Thado Dhamma Yaza]] and [[Mingyi Swe]], each with a strength of 4000 troops.&lt;ref name=hy-2-240-241/&gt; Their route of invasion was via the [[Three Pagodas Pass]] towards [[Kanchanaburi]], and then to the capital [[Ayutthaya (city)|Ayutthaya]].

===Start of invasion===
On 14 October 1548 (13th waxing of Tazaungmon 910 ME), the Burmese three armies left Martaban to start the invasion. The armies marched along the [[Ataran river]] toward the [[Three Pagodas Pass]], entered Siam along the [[Khwae Noi River]] to the town of [[Amphoe Sai Yok|Sai Yok]], then overland towards the [[Khwae Yai River]]. From there they travelled by boat toward the town of [[Kanchanaburi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 16&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 16&lt;/ref&gt; Tabinshwehti travelled in great state with a massive retinue of elephants and servants. Many of these elephants carried muskets and bronze [[cannon]]; these were kept close to the king. Royal elephants were rafted across rivers, while the ordinary war elephants marched upstream to a [[ford (crossing)|ford]]. The Burmese king was accompanied by his crown prince Bayinnaung, Bayinnaung's thirteen-year-old son [[Nanda Bayin|Nanda]], and many richly attired lords. Hundreds of workmen marched ahead of the king's retinue, to pitch a richly decorated wooden camp, painted and gilded for the King's use, only to pack it up and pitch it at a new location every day.&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt;

The invasion initially met little resistance, as the Burmese forces were too large for the small guard posts around the border.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 15&quot;/&gt; Upon hearing of the Burmese invasion, Maha Chakkraphat mobilized his kingdom, then gathered his forces at [[Suphanburi]], a town just west of Ayutthaya.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 17&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 17&lt;/ref&gt; When Tabinshwehti and his army arrived at the walled town of Kanchanaburi, they found it completely deserted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 18&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 18&lt;/ref&gt; About a month into the invasion, mid-November 1548,&lt;ref group=note&gt;The ''[[Hmannan Yazawin]]'' chronicle (Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 241) uses the term {{my|လပြည့်}}, {{IPA-my|la̰bjḛ|}}, which can be translated as either full moon or full month (completion of a month), to describe when he began the march to Ayutthaya. If it was full moon, the date of departure from Kanchanaburi would be 15 November 1548 (Full moon of Natdaw 910 ME). If it was full month, it would be 13 November 1548 (13th waxing of Natdaw 910 ME).&lt;/ref&gt; the King of Burma then continued his march eastward, capturing the villages of Ban Thuan, Kaphan Tru and Chorakhe Sam Phan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 18&quot;/&gt; The Burmese continued their advance and captured the ancient town of [[Amphoe U Thong|Uthong]] as well as the villages of Don Rakhang and Nong Sarai and closing in on Suphanburi. When the Burmese attacked the town, Siamese defenders could not withstand the onslaught and retreated towards Ayutthaya. Tabinshwehti ordered his army southeast along two canals, and crossed the [[Chao Phraya river]] near Phong Phaeng. From here he encamped his army directly north of the Siamese capital of Ayutthaya on a field called the Lumpli plain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 18&quot;/&gt;

===Battle of Ayutthaya===

====At the outskirts====
[[File:Queen Suriyothai elephant combat.jpg|thumb|Painting by Prince [[Narisara Nuvadtivongs]], depicting Queen Suriyothai (center) on her elephant putting herself between King Maha Chakkraphat (right) and the [[Thado Dhamma Yaza I of Prome|Viceroy of Prome]] (left).]]
Maha Chakkraphat decided to leave the capital with his forces, to engage Tabinshwehti and test the Burmese strength. On this occasion, he mounted his chief war elephant. Accompanying him were his Chief Queen, [[Sri Suriyothai]], and one of their young daughters, Princess Boromdhilok, the two riding together on a smaller war elephant. Both royal ladies were dressed in male military attire (helmet and armour), with the queen wearing the uniform of an [[Uparaja]]. Also accompanying their father on elephant mounts were two sons, the [[Front Palace#Ayutthaya period|Uparaja and heir apparent]], [[Prince Ramesuan]], and his brother [[Mahinthrathirat|Prince Mahin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 18&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 113&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 113&lt;/ref&gt;

A battle certainly ensued although there are naturally two accounts as to what actually took place. According to the Burmese chronicles, the Burmese command fielded an army led by [[Thado Dhamma Yaza I of Prome|Thado Dhamma Yaza]], the Viceroy of Prome, as a decoy and the two armies lurked on the flanks in order to encircle any overstretched Siamese forces. As planned, the Siamese vanguard troops pressed on Thado Dhamma Yaza's army, allowing Bayinnaung's army waiting on the left flank to encircle the Siamese forces, which subsequently were wiped out. Tabinshwehti's army on the right flank drove back the remaining Siamese forces into the city.&lt;ref name=hy-2-241-242&gt;Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 241–242&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Thai tradition, however, Thado Dhamma Yaza and Maha Chakkraphat engaged in [[War elephant#Middle Ages|single elephant-combat]]. (The custom of the time was for two commanders/leaders of the same status to fight in single combat. It is unclear as to why the Siamese king would have accepted to face someone of lesser rank. If he did issue the challenge, he would have challenged his counterpart Tabinshwehti and accepted to face only Tabinshwehti.) The Thai narrative continues that Maha Chakkraphat's elephant panicked and gave flight, charging away from the enemy; Thado Dhamma Yaza swiftly gave chase. Fearing for the life of her husband, Queen Sri Suriyothai charged ahead to put her elephant between the King and the Viceroy, thereby blocking his pursuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 113&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 19&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 19&lt;/ref&gt; The Viceroy then engaged the Queen in single combat, fatally cleaving her from shoulder to heart with his spear, also wounding her daughter—both mother and child met their deaths on the back of the same elephant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 112&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 19&quot;/&gt; It is said that the Viceroy did not know he was fighting a woman until his blow struck—as she fell dying her helmet came off, exposing her long hair. Prince Ramesuan and Prince Mahin then urged their elephants forward to fight the Viceroy, drove him and his remaining forces from the field, then carried the bodies of their mother and sister back to Ayutthaya. The Siamese king meanwhile rallied his army, and retreated in good order back towards the capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 113&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 19&quot;/&gt; The Burmese chronicles however do not mention any instance of single combat (on elephant-back or otherwise) by the viceroy of Prome.&lt;ref group=note&gt;Burmese chronicles (Maha Yazawin Vol. 2 2006: 181–192) and (Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 238–248) devote a detailed account of the invasion, down to the names of war elephants the high royalty rode on. Thado Dhamma Yaza rode the war elephant named '''Ye Htut Mingala''' (Hmannan Vol. 2 2033: 244). If he was victorious in combat against any enemy of significance, such a story with a favorable outcome would likely have been included in the chronicles.&lt;/ref&gt;

At any rate, the remaining Siamese forces retreated. Tabinshwehti readied his army for a [[siege]] of the Siamese capital. He made his camp north of the city, with his headquarters at Klum Dong, and had his commanders encamp in strategic places surrounding the city walls, Bayinnaung at Phaniat, the Viceroy at Ban Mai Makham, and the Governor of Bassein at the plain of Prachet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 19&quot;/&gt; The Burmese would not, however, take the Siamese capital so easily.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 20&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 20&lt;/ref&gt;

====Siege====
Ayutthaya sat on an [[River island|island]] surrounded by three rivers—the [[Lopburi River]] to the north, the [[Chao Phraya River]] to the west and south, and the [[Pa Sak River]] to the east, forming a formidable natural [[moat]]. The Chao Phraya [[Structural basin|basin]] where Ayutthaya is situated was low and prone to [[flooding]]—especially intense during the [[Wet season|rainy season]] when torrential waters flowed in great quantity from the north along the Lopburi River. This flood would begin approximately in July and end somewhere between October and November, giving Tabinshwehti only five months to capture Ayutthaya—otherwise his camp grounds and supply routes would be flooded. There was also the possibility that the flood could trap his forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 17&quot;/&gt; The low, swampy area around the city was laced with numerous canals thronging with gun boats armed with cannon to repulse any attempt at an attack on the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 17&quot;/&gt; Also, the Burmese had only small cannon that they had brought with them, while the Siamese had large cannon mounted along the city walls.&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 17&quot;/&gt; The Burmese had the city surrounded, but without the ability to cross the rivers or breach the city walls with cannon fire, were left to camp around it instead, while the interconnected waterways to the north and south made it fairly easy to resupply the defenders in the city. Fifty Portuguese mercenaries, who had elected [[Galeote Pereira]] as their captain, defended the weakest part of the city wall for Maha Chakkraphat. Unable to take the city conventionally, Tabinshwehti offered bribes to these defenders. The Portuguese reacted with derision, and refused. When a Siamese commander heard of this, he swung open the gates of the city and dared the Burmese King to bring the money—a dare that was ignored.&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt;

Maha Chakkraphat, being unable to repel the Burmese, sent a message to his son-in-law [[Mahathammarachathirat (king of Ayutthaya)|Maha Thammaracha]] at [[Phitsanulok]], ordering his vassal to come to his aid by bringing an army southwards towards Ayutthaya and if possible to engage the enemy in battle. Thammaracha quickly mobilized his forces and with the help of the Governor of [[Sawankhalok]], marched southward with a large army to attack the Burmese rear. Upon hearing of this and on the advice of Bayinnaung; Tabinshwehti decided to withdraw, abandoning the mission altogether.&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt; His decision was compounded by news from Burma that the Mons, who had never been entirely subjugated by the Taungoo dynasty, rebelled in the absence of the king.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 113&quot;/&gt; Other factors included the scarcity of supplies and sickness in his army, which was not prepared for a long siege.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 20&quot;/&gt;

Just one month into the siege, the Burmese command decided to withdraw.&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt;

===Retreat===
[[File:Tak province Burmese mountains.jpg|thumb|right|260px|The view from [[Tak Province]] (Thailand) towards the hills of [[Shan State]] (Myanmar), not far from the Mae Lamao pass, the Burmese route of retreat]]

====Battle of Kamphaeng Phet====
The Burmese forces chose to retreat via the Mae Lamao pass (in modern-day [[Mae Sot]], [[Tak Province|Tak]]). In retreat, they tried to plunder the ancient and wealthy town of [[Kamphaeng Phet]] but the town was too well fortified. With the help of more Portuguese mercenaries, the Governor repelled the Burmese with flaming projectiles that forced the Burmese to cease using their cannons and protect them with coverings of damp hides.&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt;

Maha Chakkraphat saw the Burmese army's retreat as an opportunity take advantage of their weakness, so he ordered Princes Ramesuan and Thammaracha to follow and harass the enemy out of Siamese territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 20&quot;/&gt; For three days, the Siamese chased the invaders, inflicting great losses upon them.&lt;ref name=app-101&gt;Phayre 1967: 101&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cocks 44&quot;&gt;Cocks 1919: 44&lt;/ref&gt; Once the forces of Ramesuan and Thammaracha closed in, Tabinshwehti made a stand near Kamphaeng Phet, dividing his forces on both sides of the road. The Siamese in their eagerness fell into the trap.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 21&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 21&lt;/ref&gt; The Burmese captured both Prince Ramesuan and Maha Thammaracha as [[prisoners of war]].&lt;ref name=geh-158-159/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cocks 45&quot;&gt;Cocks 1919: 45&lt;/ref&gt;

==Truce==
The capture of his heir and his son-in-law forced Maha Chakkraphat to negotiate with Tabinshwehti. The Siamese at once sent emissaries bearing gifts, offering a peaceful retreat in return for the two princes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cocks 45&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=geh-160&gt;Harvey 1925: 160&lt;/ref&gt; In exchange Maha Chakkraphat was forced to hand over to Tabinshwehti two prized male war elephants called Sri Mongkol ({{lang|th|ศรีมงคล}}) and Mongkol Thawip ({{lang|th|มงคลทวีป}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 21&quot;/&gt; Once the elephants were handed over, the Burmese army retreated in peace. In addition to the two princes, Tabinshwehti also released many other prisoners he had captured during the campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cocks 45&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=geh-160/&gt; According to the Burmese records, the Siamese king also agreed to provide an annual gift of 30 elephants, a token sum of money, and certain custom duties.&lt;ref name=mha-113&gt;Htin Aung 1967: 113&lt;/ref&gt;

After the treaty, the Burmese king rested for eight days, and returned to Pegu. He arrived back at Pegu on 1 March 1549 (3rd waxing of Late Tagu 910 ME).&lt;ref name=sll-232&gt;Sein Lwin Lay 2006: 232&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Despite his failure to take Ayutthaya, Tabinshwehti claimed to have regained control of the Tavoy frontier. Indeed, the Burmese chronicles claim the Siamese king had agreed to pay an annual tribute.&lt;ref name=sll-296&gt;Sein Lwin Lay 2006: 296&lt;/ref&gt; Even if this claim was true, the Toungoo Dynasty's control over Tavoy lasted a little over a year in any case. Tabinshwehti was assassinated just a year after the Siamese campaign on 30 April 1550, and the empire he had built in the previous 16 years quickly collapsed, with each town claiming a king. Even after Bayinnaung had restored the kingdom in the following years, the frontier region was likely under overlapping spheres of influence. (During his 1554–1555 campaign against Upper Burma, his southernmost garrison was at [[Ye, Mon State|Ye]],&lt;ref name=hy-2-204&gt;Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 204&lt;/ref&gt; not Tavoy.) It was only in 1562 that Bayinnaung made an emphatic claim on the region by setting up a Burmese garrison at Tavoy,&lt;ref group=note&gt;(Hmannan Vol. 2 2003: 338): Wednesday, Full moon of Waso 924 ME = 17 June 1562&lt;/ref&gt; in preparation for his invasion of Siam a year later.

==Legacy==
[[File:Ayutpchedisuriyothai0605a.jpg|thumb|left|170px|The restored Phra Chedi Sri Suriyothai at Wat Suan Luang Sop Sawan, Phra Nakhon Si Ayutthaya Province.]]
The war was the first of the many wars between Burma and Siam that would last well into the mid 19th-century. It was also the first time the city of Ayutthaya was actually attacked by a foreign enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 21&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Queen suriyothai0609 (cropped).jpg|thumb|right|Queen Suriyothai Memorial, Phra Nakhon Si Ayutthaya Province.]]

The [[Cadaver|body]] of Queen Sri Suriyothai was placed at Suan Luang, the Royal Garden. Maha Chakkraphat ordered a grand [[cremation]], and built a temple with a large [[stupa]] to house her remains. The temple, which still exists, is known as Wat Suan Luang Sop Sawan ({{lang|th|วัดสวนหลวงสบสวรรค์}}) and the stupa is called Chedi Phra Sri Suriyothai ({{lang|th|เจดีย์พระศรีสุริโยทัย}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 19&quot;/&gt; The temple and the stupa had been restored and rebuilt several times. Despite her stature among the Thais for her heroism, the [[Recorded history|historicity]] of her story and her existence has been the subject of debate. This is based on the fact that the queen is not mentioned in either the recorded or popular history of [[Myanmar]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rebound88.net/sp/ngb/sthai5.html A Historical Divide] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100612115921/http://www.rebound88.net/sp/ngb/sthai5.html |date=12 June 2010 }} Subhatra Bhumiprabhas. Retrieved 4 March 2010&lt;/ref&gt; All the facts pertaining to her life were taken from fragments of the Siamese royal chronicle the ''Annals of Ayutthaya'' and an account by Domingos Seixas, a Portuguese explorer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asiaticafilmmediale.it/2001/uk2001/database/surijotai.html Suriyothai: The Sun and The Moon.] Retrieved 4 March 2010 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060514084200/http://www.asiaticafilmmediale.it/2001/uk2001/database/surijotai.html |date=14 May 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The war led to the strengthening of Ayutthaya's defences, such as stronger walls and forts. A census of all able-bodied men was taken, as well as a massive hunt for wild elephants for use in future wars. The size of the navy was also increased.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 22-24&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 22–24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood 114&quot;&gt;Wood 1924: 114&lt;/ref&gt;

The Siamese success at repelling the Burmese would not be repeated. This first ever invasion gave the Burmese an important experience on fighting with Siamese. The next invasion would be conducted by Bayinnaung, a man accustomed to fighting against Siamese soldiers and familiar with marching through Siamese terrain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 22&quot;&gt;Damrong Rajanubhab 2001: 22&lt;/ref&gt; The unrest in Burma delayed that next invasion for fifteen years, until the [[Burmese–Siamese War (1563–1564)|War of 1563]] or the War of the White Elephants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Damrong 21&quot;/&gt;

==Media==
The war beginning with the death of Chairacha was dramatized in the 2001 Thai historical drama ''[[The Legend of Suriyothai]]'', directed by Mom Chao [[Chatrichalerm Yukol]].&lt;ref&gt;Jirattikorn&lt;/ref&gt; The film portrays the events leading up to the war and the battles including the death of Queen Sri Suriyothai. The film cost an estimated 350 million baht, and is the highest budget [[Thai film]] {{as of|2010|alt=to date}}. The film was released in the United States in 2003.

The succession crisis Ayutthaya is portrayed in the 2005 English language Thai film ''[[The King Maker]]''. The film ends prior to the Burmese invasion.

== See also ==
* [[Ayutthaya Kingdom]]
* [[Toungoo Dynasty]]
* [[Early Modern warfare]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{cite book |last=Cocks |first=S. W. |title=A Short History of Burma (at www.archive.org) |url=https://archive.org/stream/cu31924022998623/cu31924022998623_djvu.txt |publisher=Macmillan and Co |year=1919 |edition=Second |location=London |isbn=}}
* {{cite book |last=[[Damrong Rajanubhab]] |first=Prince Disuankumaan  |translator-first=Chris |translator-last=Baker |translator-link=Chris Baker (writer) |title=Our Wars with the Burmese: Thai-Burmese Conflict 1539–1767 |publisher=White Lotus Co. Ltd |orig-year= 1917 |date=2001 |location=Thailand |isbn=974-7534-58-4}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Fernquest |first=Jon |title=Min-gyi-nyo, the Shan Invasions of Ava (1524–27), and the Beginnings of Expansionary Warfare in Toungoo Burma: 1486–1539 |date=Autumn 2005 |work=SOAS Bulletin of Burma Research |volume=3 |number=2 |issn=1479-8484}}
* {{cite book |last=Harvey |first=G. E. |title=History of Burma: From the Earliest Times to 10 March 1824 |publisher=Frank Cass &amp; Co. Ltd |year=1925 |location=London}}
* {{cite book |last=[[Htin Aung]] |first=Maung |title=A History of Burma |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=New York and London |year=1967}}
* {{cite journal |last=Jirattikorn |first=Amporn |date=August 2003 |title=Suriyothai: Hybridizing Thai National Identity Through Film |journal=Inter-Asia Cultural Studies |volume=4 |issue=2 |pages=296–308 |doi=10.1080/1464937032000113015}}
* {{cite book |last=Phayre |first=Lt. Gen. Sir Arthur P. |authorlink=Arthur Purves Phayre |title=History of Burma |year=1883 |edition=1967 |publisher=Susil Gupta |location=London}}
* {{cite book |last=Quaritch Wales |first=Horace Geoffrey |authorlink=Horace Geoffrey Quaritch Wales |title=Ancient South-east Asian Warfare |publisher=Bernard Quaritch Ltd |year=1952 |location=London |isbn=}}
* {{cite book |author=[[Royal Historical Commission of Burma]] |title=[[Hmannan Yazawin]] |volume=1–3 |year=1832 |location=Yangon |language=Burmese |edition=2003 |publisher=Ministry of Information, Myanmar}}
* {{cite book |last=Sein Lwin Lay |first=Kahtika U |title=Mintaya Shwe Hti and Bayinnaung: Ketumadi Taungoo Yazawin |language=Burmese |location=Yangon |publisher=Yan Aung Sarpay |year=1968 |edition=2006, 2nd printing}}
* {{cite book |last=Wood |first=William A. R. |title=History of Siam |publisher=Chalermit Press |year=1924 |location=Thailand |isbn=1-931541-10-8}}
{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Burmese-Siamese War (1548)}}
[[Category:Wars involving Myanmar]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Ayutthaya Kingdom]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1547]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1548]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1549]]
[[Category:History of Myanmar]]
[[Category:Myanmar–Thailand relations]]
[[Category:1547 in Asia]]
[[Category:1548 in Asia]]
[[Category:1549 in Asia]]
[[Category:16th century in Burma]]
[[Category:16th century in Siam]]</text>
      <sha1>5lcwn2bqm1m3al21nz8y99462ws4x1f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
