<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Castle Rising (castle)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>113654</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736603695</id>
      <parentid>732780392</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-28T16:45:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WriteinEnglish</username>
        <id>26776908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Corrected typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="54575">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military structure
|name=Castle Rising
|partof=
|location=[[Castle Rising]], [[Norfolk]], England
|map_type=Norfolk
|map_alt=
|map_size=300
|latitude=52.79368
|longitude=0.470146
|coord_display = title
|coord_region = GB-NFK
|coordinates={{gbmapping|TF66572455}}
|image=[[File:Castle Rising Castle - geograph.org.uk - 660628.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Castle Rising's keep, seen from the south-east, with its distinctive [[pilaster]] [[buttresses]], and the forebuilding on the right
|condition=Ruins
|events=[[Revolt of 1173–1174]]
|builder      = [[William d'Aubigny, 1st Earl of Arundel|William d'Aubigny II]]
|ownership=[[Lord Howard of Rising]]
| open_to_public = Yes
}}
'''Castle Rising''' is a ruined [[castle|medieval fortification]] in the village of [[Castle Rising]], [[Norfolk]], England. It was built soon after 1138 by [[William d'Aubigny, 1st Earl of Arundel|William d'Aubigny II]], who had risen through the ranks of the [[Anglo-Norman]] nobility to become the [[Earl of Arundel]]. With his new wealth, he constructed Castle Rising and its surrounding [[Medieval deer park|deer park]], a combination of fortress and palatial hunting lodge. It was inherited by William's descendants before passing into the hands of the de Montalt family in 1243. The Montalts later sold the castle to Queen [[Isabella of France|Isabella]], who lived there after her fall from power in 1330. Isabella extended the castle buildings and enjoyed a regal lifestyle, entertaining her son, [[Edward III of England|Edward III]], on several occasions. After her death, it was granted to [[Edward, the Black Prince]], to form part of the [[Duchy of Cornwall]].

During the 15th century, the castle became increasingly valued for its hunting facilities rather than its military defences. It fell into disrepair and, despite the construction of new living quarters and service facilities, by the middle of the 16th century it was derelict. [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] sold the property to [[Thomas Howard, 3rd Duke of Norfolk|Thomas Howard]], the [[Duke of Norfolk]], and most of the castle buildings were demolished. It was not until the 19th century, when Mary and Fulke Greville Howard inherited the property, that the castle was renovated and restored. [[Victorian era|Victorian]] scholars examined the site, and it was opened to the public. In 1958 the castle passed into the custody of the state, which carried out further stabilisation work and a programme of archaeological investigation. In 1998 [[English Heritage]] passed the management of the site back to its current owner, [[Greville Howard, Baron Howard of Rising|Baron Howard of Rising]], who continues to operate the castle as a tourist attraction.

Castle Rising comprises three [[Bailey (fortification)|baileys]], each defended by large earthworks, covering a total area of {{convert|5|ha}}, which historians Oliver Creighton and Robert Higham consider to be among the most impressive in Britain. In the inner bailey is the great keep, probably modelled on that of [[Norwich Castle]]. It features extensive [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque designs]], including [[pilaster]] [[buttress]]es and arcading. Historians Beric Morley and David Gurney believe this to be &quot;one of the finest of all Norman keeps&quot;, and its military utility and political symbolism have been extensively discussed by academics. The castle was originally surrounded by a carefully managed landscape, from the [[planned town]] in front of the castle, to the deer park and [[rabbit]] warrens that stretched out behind it, intended to be viewed from the lord's chamber in the great keep.

==History==

===12th&amp;nbsp;– 13th centuries===
[[File:Castle Rising Castle 18.jpg|thumb|The earthworks of Castle Rising]]
Castle Rising was built soon after 1138 by [[William d'Aubigny, 1st Earl of Arundel|William d'Aubigny II]], an upwardly mobile Anglo-Norman noble who owned the surrounding manor of Snettisham.&lt;ref name=HulmeP222BrownP80&gt;{{harvnb|Hulme|2007-8|p=222}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=80}}&lt;/ref&gt; William married [[Adeliza of Louvain]], the widow of King [[Henry I of England|Henry I]] in that year, and became the [[Earl of Arundel]] in 1139.&lt;ref name=HulmeP222BrownP80/&gt; This transformed his social position, and one [[chronicler]] at [[Waltham Holy Cross]] complained how he &quot;became intolerably puffed up&amp;nbsp;... and looked down upon every other eminence in the world except the King&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Stalley|1999|p=86}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; With his new wealth, William built Castle Rising and [[New Buckenham Castle]] in [[Norfolk]], and expanded [[Arundel Castle]] in West Sussex.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|p=139}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The castle was located {{convert|5|mi}} from the port of [[King's Lynn]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 12th century it would have typically have been reached by boat, through a channel in the marshy [[Babingley River]] that ran nearby.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=1}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|name=SeaPort|There is a local tradition in Norfolk that Castle Rising was a sea-port in the early medieval period, but modern research has shown this to be incorrect.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} Following the [[Norman conquest of England]], the land had been granted to [[Odo, Earl of Kent|Bishop Odo]], the [[Earl of Kent]], who may have used it as an administrative centre; there were many [[Saxo-Norman]] buildings on the site of the later castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pounds|1994|p=61}}; {{harvnb|Hulme|2007-8|p=222}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Archaeological evidence shows that there was [[Iron Age]] and [[Roman Britain|Roman]] occupation of the surrounding area, with a [[Roman villa]] situated at nearby [[South Wootton]], but there is no firm evidence of pre-Saxo-Norman occupation of the castle site itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=8–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} Although Norfolk was a prosperous region during this period, the location of the castle was not strategically important: its only militarily significance would have been as a regional [[Muster (military)|muster point]], and the surrounding lands were thinly populated, with poor, [[Acidic soil|acidic]] agricultural soil.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=174}}; {{harvnb|Hulme|2007-8|p=222}}; {{harvnb|Pounds|1994|p=61}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The attraction of the site to William is believed to have been that it was a relatively cheap and easy place in which to build a substantial new building and establish a large [[medieval deer park|hunting park]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hulme|2007-8|p=222}}; {{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=175}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historian Richard Hulme argues that William essentially built &quot;a palatial hunting lodge&quot; on the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=175}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Massive resources were required to construct Castle Rising, which included three [[Bailey (fortification)|baileys]] with large earthwork defences and a stone [[keep]], with an adjacent deer park just behind the castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Creighton|2005|p=193}}; {{harvnb|Garnett|2000|p=85}}&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the project, the existing settlement was moved away to the north, where it became a [[planned town|planned settlement]] adjacent to the new castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; A pre-existing Norman [[chapel]] on the site, built around 1100, was encircled by the castle defences, and the new parish church of St Lawrence was built in the town instead, although it is possible that this church also pre-dates the castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=8}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=1–2}}&lt;/ref&gt; William received permission from King [[Stephen of England|Stephen]] to open a [[Mint (coin)|mint]] at the castle in 1145 and, probably linked to this development, settled a community of [[History of the Jews in England|Jews]] in the town.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hillaby|Hillaby|2013|p=87}}; {{harvnb|Garnett|2000|p=85}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|England's Jews during the first half of the 11th century often settled near castles, particularly those operating mints; the castles provided protection from anti-Semitism, and they were heavily involved in both money-lending and often the operation of the mints themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hillaby|2003|pp=20–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Castle Rising Gatehouse bridge.jpg|thumb|left|Earthworks of the inner bailey, with the remaining 14th-century brick wall and 12th-century gatehouse (left) and the stone bridge (centre)]]
It is uncertain how often William actually stayed at his new castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=10–11}}&lt;/ref&gt; He and his wife probably preferred to reside in their estates around Arundel in the south of England, and both William and his descendants chose New Buckingham Castle, rather than Castle Rising, to serve as the ''[[caput]]'', or main castle, for their Norfolk landholdings.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=10–11}}; {{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=185}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A prolonged civil war known as [[the Anarchy]] broke out in England from 1138 until 1154, between the followers of King Stephen and the [[Empress Matilda]], only ending when Matilda's son, [[Henry II of England|Henry II]], finally inherited the kingdom. Despite William having backed Stephen during the war, after the end of the conflict he proved a loyal supporter of Henry and was allowed to retain his possessions. Henry clamped down on the operation of the regional mints, however, and closed the facility at Castle Rising; the local Jews resettled in King's Lynn.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hillaby|Hillaby|2013|p=87}}; {{harvnb|Hillaby|2003|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt; A second, rapid phase of construction work on the castle then occurred, probably in the 1170s in response to a [[Revolt of 1173–74|major rebellion]] against Henry II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liddiard 2000 172&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=172}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Historians Beric Morley and David Gurney prefer a slightly date for the work on the earthworks, potentially pushing the date forward into the early 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=135}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} William supported the King, and fought against the rebels at the [[Battle of Fornham]] in neighbouring [[Suffolk]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around this time the height of the earth defences was doubled and the internal level of the west bailey raised to form a platform.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liddiard 2000 172&quot;/&gt;

The castle was inherited by [[William d'Aubigny, 2nd Earl of Arundel|William d'Albini III]], and in turn by his son, [[William d'Aubigny, 3rd Earl of Arundel|William IV]], and grandson, [[William d'Aubigny, 4th Earl of Arundel|William V]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown 1988 15–16&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=15–16}}&lt;/ref&gt; William V died in 1224, leaving it to his brother [[Hugh d'Aubigny, 5th Earl of Arundel|Hugh]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=16}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=81}}&lt;/ref&gt; Probably by this time the chapel inside the castle walls had fallen out of use as a religious building, and was instead employed for secular purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; The top {{convert|3.7|m}} of the keep's walls are distinctively different from the rest of the building, and one theory to explain this is that the castle keep was not in fact completed during William II's lifetime, and that the final work on walls was carried out between 1200 and 1230 by his descendants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morley 1997 3&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|There is agreement among historians that the top {{convert|3.7|m}} of the keep's walls are different from the remainder of the building: a line of flints in the stonework mark the division between the two, with differences in the carved stonework and evidence of older stonework having been covered up by later additions or reused for new purposes. R. Allen Brown concludes that this is probably the result of renovations to decaying stonework in the early 14th century. He suggests that such a change of style would not be consistent with an attempt to finish an existing building, and that any decay of stonework would begin on the upper layers. He also draws links between this work and the work known to have occurred in the early 14th century in the forebuilding. Beric Morley and David Gurney argue that the dramatic change of style is evidence that the work was not intended to repair an existing building, but rather to complete a previously unfinished one, probably between 1200 and 1230. They also point to the relatively paucity of Norman finds in the excavation of the castle bailey, potentially an indicator that the building was not completed during its initial build.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=40–42}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=33, 42}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} Hugh died childless in 1243, and the castle then passed to [[Roger de Montalt, 1st Baron Montalt|Roger de Montalt]].&lt;ref name=Brown1988P16&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===14th century===
[[File:Castle Rising Castle 14.jpg|thumb|The foundations of the chapel and parts of the west range, built in the inner bailey during Queen [[Isabella of France]]'s ownership of the castle]]
The Montalts were a prominent baronial family, but they had few other estates in the region and their family fortunes declined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown 1988 15–16&quot;/&gt; In 1327, Roger de Montalt's younger brother, [[Robert de Montalt, 1st Baron Montalt|Robert]], who was childless, sold the [[Reversion (law)|reversion]] of his rights in the castle to the Crown in 1327 for 10,000 [[Mark (money)|mark]]s&amp;nbsp;– effectively selling it to the Crown with a life-time lease for him and his wife Emma.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=81}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=16–17}}&lt;/ref&gt; An alternative theory to explain the different style of stonework along the top of the keep is that the building was completed under William d'Albini II, but had become dilapidated by the start of the 14th century, requiring extensive repairs by Robert.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=81}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The forebuilding of the keep was raised in height at one end around this time and a new, peaked roof added to it, and an imposing, timber-framed, brick kitchen was built in the inner bailey.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=81}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=3, 56–59, 135}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the time of Robert's agreement with the Crown, the government of England was controlled by [[Roger Mortimer, 1st Earl of March|Roger Mortimer]] and Queen [[Isabella of France]], who was ruling as [[regent]] in the name of her young son, [[Edward III of England|Edward III]].&lt;ref name=Brown1988P18/&gt; Isabella fell from power when Edward toppled Mortimer in a [[coup d'état]] in 1330, but after a short period of [[house arrest]] she led a relatively normal life, enjoying considerable status as the King's mother.&lt;ref name=DohertyP174Mortimer2008P330&gt;{{harvnb|Doherty|2004|p=174}}; {{harvnb|Mortimer|2008|p=330}}&lt;/ref&gt; Edward granted Isabella several royal castles in England, including Castle Rising.&lt;ref name=DohertyP174Mortimer2008P330/&gt; Robert had died in 1329 and in 1331 Emma sold her rights to the castle to Isabella for £400.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown1988P18&quot;/&gt;

From then on, Isabella used Castle Rising as one of her main residences until her death in 1358.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P18&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Isabella was a wealthy woman, as the King granted her a yearly income of £3,000, which by 1337 had increased to £4,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Doherty|2004|p=173}}&lt;/ref&gt; She enjoyed a regal lifestyle in Norfolk, maintaining [[minstrel]]s, [[hunting|huntsmen]] and [[Groom (profession)|grooms]], and received visits from Edward and the royal household on at least four occasions.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Doherty|2004|p=176}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite her large income, Isabella ran up long-standing debts with the local merchants near the castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Doherty|2004|p=174}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around the time that she took over the castle, a new set of buildings were constructed in the central bailey, including a west range containing a residential suite, a new private chapel, and a south range linking to various service buildings; the existing kitchen was reused.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=18–19}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=4, 58–59}}&lt;/ref&gt; The great hall was reroofed, although Isabella lived in the west range, using the keep only for formal occasions or as accommodation for very senior guests.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=4, 60}}&lt;/ref&gt; A brick wall around the outside of the inner bailey may have been built around this time to provide additional security.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=4, 137}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The castle then passed to Isabella's grandson, [[Edward the Black Prince]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=81}}&lt;/ref&gt; Edward III had decreed in 1337 that his son would inherit the castle after Isabella's death, complete with the surrounding manor and the right to part of the [[tariff|tolls]] from King's Lynn, although these brought in only a relatively modest £100 a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=19}}; {{harvnb|Green|2004|p=87}}&lt;/ref&gt; As part of this arrangement, the King declared the castle to be a permanent part of the [[Duchy of Cornwall]], an estate traditionally assigned for the use of the [[Prince of Wales]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Prince undertook repairs to the castle during the 1360s, including spending £81 on repairing the &quot;Nightegale Tower&quot; in 1365, although it is uncertain which part of the castle this refers to.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=19–20}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Analysis of the other buildings mentioned in the records of repairs suggest that the &quot;Nightegale Tower&quot; was not the keep, but could have been a reference to the gatehouse or one of the towers along the walls.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} The Prince died in 1376, returning the Duchy of Cornwall to the control of the Crown, and during this time Castle Rising appears to have been maintained in good condition.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P20Pounds1994P205&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=20}}; {{harvnb|Pounds|1994|p=205}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was ordered on several occasions during the 1380s to raise local forces to counter the threat of a French invasion, and may have been equipped with two cannons.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P20Pounds1994P205/&gt; If not built by Isabella, the brick wall around the inner bailey may have been constructed during this period.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=137}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under [[Richard II of England|Richard II]], the rights to the castle changed hands several times, despite Edward's charter having made it a permanent part of the Duchy.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P22&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Richard's government gave the castle to [[John V, Duke of Brittany|John]], the [[Duke of Brittany]], in 1378, in exchange for the [[Château de Brest]].&lt;ref name=Brown1988P22/&gt; Richard subsequently gave the reversion of the castle first to his uncle [[Thomas of Woodstock, 1st Duke of Gloucester|Thomas]], [[Duke of Gloucester]], in 1386, and then to another uncle, [[Edmund of Langley, 1st Duke of York|Edmund]], [[Duke of York]] in 1397.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P22/&gt; Shortly after Richard was overthrown, the courts declared these grants to have been illegal, and returned the castle to the Duchy in 1403, then in the possession of the future [[Henry V of England|Henry V]].&lt;ref name=Brown1988P22/&gt;

===15th&amp;nbsp;– 18th centuries===
[[File:Mural Passage - geograph.org.uk - 542862.jpg|thumb|Mural passage, dug out of the walls after the keep had become largely derelict in the 16th century]]
In the 15th and early 16th centuries, Castle Rising continued to be owned by the Duchy of Cornwall.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P22/&gt; Although the castle's military defences were mobilised by [[Henry VI of England|Henry VI]] in 1461 during the [[Wars of the Roses]], it became increasingly more prominent as a hunting facility.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=22, 24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The role of the [[constable]] of the castle was often combined with that of the surveyor or ranger of Rising Chase, the parkland around the castle.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P24&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The castle may have been a prestigious location during this period, although its facilities were not as extensive as those of other castles and manors known for their hunting.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=24}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=138}}&lt;/ref&gt; Senior visitors to the castle included [[Mary Tudor, Queen of France|Mary Tudor]], [[Queen of France]], and [[Charles Brandon, 1st Duke of Suffolk|Charles Brandon]], the [[Duke of Suffolk]], and its constables included nobles such as [[Ralph de Cromwell, 3rd Baron Cromwell|Lord Ralph de Cromwell]] and [[John de Vere, 13th Earl of Oxford|John de Vere]], the [[Earl of Oxford]].&lt;ref name=Brown1988P24/&gt;

Minor repairs on the castle were carried out during the period, including to the castle bridge, but the state of the property gradually declined.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=23–25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The old kitchens were removed in the early 15th century, and a new, larger facility constructed in their place.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=70–71}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once built, however, the new kitchens, along with the rest of the buildings in the inner bailey, were left to deteriorate.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=74–75}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports in 1482 stated that the buildings were no longer weatherproof, and a survey carried around between 1503 and 1506 described the castle as &quot;evyll repayred&quot;, and noted that the roof of the keep was rotten.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=83, 187}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt; This last survey urged that existing repair works on the buildings in the bailey be completed, but suggested that it might not be worth repairing the keep because of the excessive cost.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Engraving of Castle Rising.jpg|thumb|left|Engraving of the ruined keep in 1782, by [[William Byrne (engraver)|William Byrne]]]]
Despite these challenges, fresh construction work was carried out around this time.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=24–25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The southern range and the kitchen were pulled down, and replaced with a new set of lodgings for guests, complete with stables, although the resulting buildings were not particularly robust.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=137}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=24–25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Problems reappeared, and a survey between 1542 and 1543 noted that, with the exception of the new lodgings, the castle was in &quot;greate ruin and decaye&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown 1988 26&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The roof of the keep had by now collapsed, as probably had the floors of the great hall and chamber.&lt;ref name=MorleyGurneyP83&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=83}}&lt;/ref&gt; The survey costed the necessary repairs to the crumbling walls around the inner bailey at £100.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown 1988 26&quot;/&gt; At around this time, the forebuilding of the keep was adapted to form a separate, smaller, set of chambers, and at some point after this a passageway was dug out of the walls to link these to the kitchens in the keep, by-passing the now floor-less rooms of the keep.&lt;ref name=MorleyGurneyP83/&gt;

In 1544 [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] bequeathed the castle to [[Thomas Howard, 3rd Duke of Norfolk|Thomas Howard]], the [[Duke of Norfolk]], but the property continued to decline.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=26–27}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1570s the castle and its earthworks had been allowed to become infested with rabbits, whose warrens caused extensive damage; a survey suggested that fully renovating the castle would cost £2,000, and that even if it were pulled down and sold for the value of its materials, it would only realise £66.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P27&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the century, the inner bailey was finally cleared of most of its buildings; the new lodgings were pulled down, along with most of the west range and the old Norman chapel, leaving only the ruined keep, alongside the latrines and the newer chapel, although what these last two were then used for is uncertain.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=82}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=14, 26}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The foundations of the old chapel were slowly covered up by the earth defences.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=14, 26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 17th century, the ground floor of the keep&amp;nbsp;– made of hardened gravel&amp;nbsp;– was dug up, probably to reuse for surfacing roads or pathways.&lt;ref name=MorleyGurneyP83/&gt; The apartments in the forebuilding were abandoned and this part of the keep fell into decay as well.&lt;ref name=MorleyGurneyP83/&gt; In 1644, the lands surrounding the castle were disparked, bringing an end to Castle Rising Chase.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=128}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1705 stone was stripped from the castle to help repair a nearby [[sluice gate]].&lt;ref name=Brown1988P27/&gt;

===19th&amp;nbsp;– 21st centuries===
[[File:Castle Rising Castle chapel in Victorian period.jpg|thumb|Visitors at the newly uncovered Norman chapel, 1850]]
Castle Rising continued to be owned by the Howard family, and in the 19th century it was inherited by Mary Howard, and her husband Fulke Greville Howard.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P27/&gt; Fulke began to undertake restoration work, excavating the basement of the keep in 1822 and repairing some of the stonework.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=27}}; {{harvnb|Harrod|1857|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ground level of the inner bailey, which had built up over the years, was lowered by about {{convert|1|m}}: according to the contemporary archaeologist [[Henry Harrod]], this process required thousands of loads of earth to be dug out and removed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=27}}; {{harvnb|Harrod|1857|p=49}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=4, 39}}&lt;/ref&gt; A great deal of medieval archaeological evidence was destroyed in the process, but the work uncovered the old Norman chapel and Harrod excavated the building in 1851.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=14, 27}}; {{harvnb|Harrod|1857|p=49}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=24, 138}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mary continued the excavation work on the castle site after Fulke's death, and restored the stonework of the chapel.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=14, 27}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially the chapel was believed to be of [[Anglo-Saxon]] origin and to have been buried under the earthworks when they were first constructed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Harrod|1857|pp=48–53}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; An argument then ensued between the antiquarian William Taylor, who championed the Anglo-Saxon dating for the site, and Harrod, who insisted that the chapel was in fact Norman in origin; the issue was not settled until later in the 20th century, when the Norman date was confirmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1900 the castle was open to the public, overseen by a caretaker who lived in one corner of the keep, the section of which had been reroofed and turned into an apartment.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=4, 83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1958 the castle's condition had deteriorated and the [[Ministry of Works (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Works]] took legal custody of the site, although it continued to be owned by the Howard family.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=27}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conservation work took place during the 1960s, stabilising the stonework of the keep.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Archaeological investigations were then carried out, focusing on the keep in 1970, the church and the earthwork defences during 1971 and 1972, and the inner bailey from 1973 to 1976.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=4–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; This research centred on archaeological excavations and the recording of remains; as with similar castles investigated during this period, the site was then preserved as a monument, and grass lawns laid down around the remaining stonework and foundations.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Creighton|Higham|2003|pp=65–66}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further excavations were carried out in 1987 during the construction of the ticket office beside the castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[English Heritage]] took over control of the castle in 1983 and continued to operate it as a tourist attraction. In the 21st century the castle is protected by UK law as an [[ancient monument]] and a [[grade I listed building]].&lt;ref name=BritishList&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/en-222184-ruins-of-castle-and-eleventh-century-chu | title=Ruins of Castle and Eleventh Century Church, Castle Rising |mode=cs2| accessdate=29 November 2013 |author=English Heritage|publisher=British Listed Buildings}}&lt;/ref&gt; It remains in the custody of English Heritage, but since 1998 has been managed by its owner, [[Greville Howard, Baron Howard of Rising|Baron Howard of Rising]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/daysout/properties/castle-rising-castle/ | title=Castle Rising Castle |mode=cs2| accessdate=29 November 2013 |author=English Heritage|publisher=English Heritage}}; {{cite web | url=http://www.museums.norfolk.gov.uk/view/NCC122717 | title=Castle Rising Castle |mode=cs2| accessdate=29 November 2013 |page =4| author=Lynn Museum|publisher=Norfolk Museums and Archaeology Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Architecture and landscape==

===Landscape===
[[File:Castle Rising - geograph.org.uk - 542750.jpg|thumb|The planned settlement of [[Castle Rising]], seen from the castle]]
The fortification of Castle Rising was constructed in a carefully designed landscape. In front of the castle was the town of Castle Rising, moved to its new site when the castle was built. The settlement appears to have been laid out to a grid-plan design, possibly bounded by ditches; with the castle positioned just behind it, in a similar fashion to that at New Buckenham and [[Malton Castle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Creighton|2005|p=162}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[dovecote|dovecot]] and a religious house were founded nearby; both of these were important symbols of lordship at the time, and were considered essential parts of a properly established castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|pp=177, 181}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The castle's deer park, which merged into the larger Rising Chase, was positioned behind the castle in a similar way to that at [[Devizes Castle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Creighton 2005 193&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Creighton|2005|p=193}}; {{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|p=114}}; {{harvnb|White|2012|pp=47–48}}&lt;/ref&gt; The castle effectively formed an interface between the town and the park; the great hall in the keep faced the settlement, and the lord's chamber overlooked the park, creating a symbolic divide between the public and private aspects of the building.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Creighton|2005|p=193}}; {{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|p=113}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rising Chase was around {{convert|16|mi}} in circumference, enclosing around {{convert|20|sqmi}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;R. Liddiard 2010 7, 17&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.norfolkbiodiversity.org/pdf/reportsandpublications/Norfolk%20Deer%20Parks%20_Rob%20Liddiard_.pdf | title=The Norfolk Deer Parks Project: Report for the Norfolk Biodiversity Partnership  |mode=cs2| year = 2010| accessdate=29 November 2013 | pages = 7, 17| author=R. Liddiard| publisher=Norfolk Biodiversity Partnership}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; It utilised marginal farm-land, which may have contributed to its design; the heathland and light woodland south of the castle would have been ideal for grazing deer.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mileson|2007|p=19}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The park was also designed with aesthetics in mind, being shaped so that its boundaries stretched beyond the horizon when viewed from the keep, in a similar design to that at [[Framlingham Castle|Framlingham]], [[Ludgershall Castle|Ludgershall]] and [[Okehampton Castle]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creighton 2005 193&quot;/&gt; Indeed, while the park would originally have provided the castle venison and other products, it was probably more ornamental than practical in character, including a space of open grazing in the centre of the park, designed to be visible from the castle chamber.&lt;ref name=&quot;R. Liddiard 2010 7, 17&quot;/&gt; The castle also incorporated a large rabbit warren, an important source of food and fur in this period, which stretched {{convert|5|km}} away south-west from the castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Architecture===

====Baileys====
[[File:Plan of Castle Rising Castle.jpg|thumb|300px|Plan of Castle Rising in the 21st century; A - west [[Bailey (fortification)|bailey]]; B - [[keep]]; C - [[Norman people|Norman]] [[chapel]]; D - remains of 14th-century west range and chapel; E - inner bailey; F - [[gatehouse]], [[barbican]] and bridge; G - east bailey]]
Castle Rising is made up of two rectangular baileys to the west and east, and an oval inner bailey in the middle, each with their own substantial earthwork defences and ditches.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P28&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The earthworks of Castle Rising cover a total area of {{convert|5|ha}}, and are considered by historians Oliver Creighton and Robert Higham to be among the most impressive in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=172}};{{harvnb|Creighton|Higham|2003|p=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; The interior of the western bailey has been levelled up to form a platform, and is no longer directly connected to the rest of the castle.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P28/&gt; The eastern bailey is {{convert|82|m}} by {{convert|59|m}} across, and formed a protective buffer, covering the entrance way to the inner bailey.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=28, 80}}; {{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=172}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A stone bridge connects the eastern bailey to the inner bailey, and is {{convert|24|m}} across, still retaining some of its original stonework at its base, although the remainder of it has since been rebuilt many times.&lt;ref name=Brown1988P28/&gt; The bridge leads onto a stone [[gatehouse]], dating from around 1138; when it was first built it was substantially taller and longer than today.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=29–30}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally equipped with a [[portcullis]], and a stone [[barbican]] was later built outside it for additional protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beyond the gatehouse is the inner bailey, which forms a [[ringwork]] {{convert|73|m}} by {{convert|60|m}} in size, with a circumference of {{convert|320|m}}; the banks are now {{convert|18|m}} high from the bottom of the defensive ditch, although they were originally only half this height.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=172}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is uncertain what was placed around the top of this bank when it first built; there may have been a wooden [[palisade]], or possibly a timber [[revetment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=133}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the remains of the 14th-century brick wall, built on an additional {{convert|1|m}} layer of [[Lime (material)|limed]] sand for stability, have survived along part of the bank.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=172}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=137}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were three towers built along the walls during the medieval period, two of which have left their mark in the earth banks; the location of the third is uncertain.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|p=172}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Castle Rising Castle 16.jpg|thumb|left|The Norman chapel, looking east]]
The main architectural focus of the inner bailey was the great keep, but it also contained a Norman chapel and, from at least the 14th century onwards, a complex of smaller residential and service buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=42}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1989|p=80}}; {{harvnb|Pounds|1994|p=188}}&lt;/ref&gt; The visible stone foundations on the north side of the keep belong to the chapel and range built for Queen Isabella around 1330.&lt;ref name=MorleyGurneyPP5657&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=56–57}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Archaeologists divide the buildings in the bailey into six different, numbered periods, covering the period from around 1300 to 1544. Isabella's ownership of the castle falls into phase 1.&lt;ref name=MorleyGurneyPP5657/&gt;}} The bailey well can also still be seen.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=33}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the north side of the bailey are the remains of the Norman chapel, which comprised a [[nave]], a square tower and an [[apsidal]] [[chancel]], 12.7 metres by 6 metres (42&amp;nbsp;ft by 20&amp;nbsp;ft), 4 metres square (13&amp;nbsp;ft square) and 4.6 metres by 4 metres (15&amp;nbsp;ft by 13&amp;nbsp;ft) respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=32}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was built from local grey [[sandstone]], and [[Imbrex and tegula|Roman tiles]] from one of the nearby villas were used to construct its roof and incorporated into the walls.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=9, 24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally the tower would have had a [[church bell]], and the [[Bellfounding|casting pit]] for this is buried under the floor of the nave.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|pp=4, 28–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; A stone bench runs around the base of the walls, and in the 19th century there was also a stone base for a [[font]] in the nave, but this has since been lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=32}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; A piece of early medieval [[graffiti]], possibly depicting a Norman soldier, has survived on the south exterior wall.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; A fireplace was added to the chapel during the [[Tudor period]], although this was only in use for a few years before being abandoned.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=32}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Keep====
[[File:Castle Rising, plan.png|thumb|upright=1.2|Plan of Castle Rising's keep, 1st floor (top), ground floor (bottom); A - kitchen; B - Great hall; C - waiting room; D - throne niche; E - great chambers; F - chapel; G - entrance to forebuilding]]

Historians Beric Morley and David Gurney consider Castle Rising to have &quot;one of the finest of all Norman keeps&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morley 1997 3&quot;/&gt; It is an early example of the longer, oblong form of these buildings, called a hall-keep, and would have taken huge resources to erect.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pounds|1994|p=21}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1962|pp=48–49}}&lt;/ref&gt; Externally, it resembles Henry I's keeps at [[Norwich Castle|Norwich]] and [[Château de Falaise|Falaise]], although Norwich appears to have inspired the latter design, and Rising's internal layout was probably based on that at Norwich as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hulme|2007-8|p=222}}; {{harvnb|Goodall|2011|p=115}}&lt;/ref&gt; In imitating Norwich, which was then the only royal castle in the county, Castle Rising may have been intended to symbolise D'Albini's loyalty to the Crown during the troubled years of the Anarchy.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|pp=117, 119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The keep is built from courses of local, brown [[carrstone]] rubble with [[oolite]] [[ashlar]] facings, and is strengthened with intramural timbers, laid down within the stone walls to reinforce the structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Higham|Barker|2004|pp=184–185}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its main body is {{convert|24|m}} by {{convert|21|m}} wide, with walls approximately {{convert|15|m}} high, with a forebuilding running along the east side.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=36}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has prominent [[pilaster]] [[buttress]]es, giving the keep what Sidney Toy describes as an &quot;impression of strength and dignity&quot;; the corners have clasping buttresses, forming four turrets.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=36}}; {{harvnb|Toy|1985|p=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is extensive [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque]] detail on the outside of the keep, including [[Arcade (architecture)|arcading]] along the west side and decorative stonework on the forebuilding.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Creighton|Higham|2003|p=47}}; {{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=37–38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The interior of the keep is divided by an internal wall to improve its structural strength, the division running north-south through the building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown 1988 46&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=46}}&lt;/ref&gt; The basement of the keep has two main sections, the north room {{convert|18|m}} by {{convert|8|m}}, with pillars supporting the great hall above, and the south chamber {{convert|18|m}} by {{convert|5|m}} in size.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=48}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forebuilding leads from the ground to the first floor, up a passageway {{convert|2.4|m}} wide with 34 steps and through three arched doorways.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=43–45}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the top is a waiting room; the glazed windows are a mixture of Tudor and more modern insertions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown 1988 46&quot;/&gt;

On the first floor is the great hall, {{convert|14|m}} by {{convert|7|m}}, now floorless and open to the sky.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=49, 81}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its original entrance way was blocked up by a chimney when the forebuilding was converted into a separate apartment in the Tudor period, and an additional entrance way inserted into the castle wall.&lt;ref name=Brown1988PP49ListedBuilding&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=49, 81}}; {{cite web | url=http://www.britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/en-222184-ruins-of-castle-and-eleventh-century-chu | title=Ruins of Castle and Eleventh Century Church, Castle Rising |mode=cs2| accessdate=29 November 2013 |author=English Heritage|publisher=British Listed Buildings}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fireplace itself was later filled in with Tudor tiles around 1840.&lt;ref name=Brown1988PP49ListedBuilding/&gt; A mural passageway, dug out in the Tudor period, leads through to the kitchen and service quarters.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=49–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the southern side is the great chamber with a large, original 12th-century fireplace, and a mixture of original tri-lobed windows and 19th-century additions.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=52–53}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the far end of the great chamber is an ornate chapel, with Norman arcading and arching.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=53–54}}&lt;/ref&gt; The keep was originally built to have been relatively self-contained, and would not have needed many additional outbuildings to function as a residence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Goodall|2011|p=113}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second floor of the keep is limited in space, and contains only one small room above the chapel which was possibly used the chaplain or by castle guards.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=55}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forebuilding was later equipped with an additional room on this level, {{convert|4.8|m}} by {{convert|4.8|m}}, which remained inhabited longer than the rest of the castle keep, and which contains a 19th-century fireplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|p=56}}; {{cite web | url=http://www.britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/en-222184-ruins-of-castle-and-eleventh-century-chu | title=Ruins of Castle and Eleventh Century Church, Castle Rising |mode=cs2| accessdate=29 November 2013 |author=English Heritage|publisher=British Listed Buildings}}&lt;/ref&gt; The upper {{convert|3.7|m}} of the keep's walls are different in design to the main body of the building; as described above, this may be the result of either a final phase of construction between 1200 and 1230, or a period of repair and renovation shortly after 1300.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1988|pp=41, 81}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Utility and symbolism===
Many 20th-century historians have stressed the potential military strength of Castle Rising; R. Allen Brown, for example, concluded that &quot;defence&amp;nbsp;... was the overwhelming consideration in [its] design and construction&quot;, and argued that the keep would have been used as a final refuge in the case of attack during a siege.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|1962|pp=44, 56}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beric Morley and David Gurney believe that the military strength of the castle could not have failed to impress contemporaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morley 1997 3&quot;/&gt; Sidney Toy suggested that the forebuilding would have made an effective defensive feature, enabling the defenders to attack intruders as they made their way up the stairs, with Morley and Gurney describing it as &quot;a deadly and near impregnable approach to the castle's interior&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Toy|1985|p=76}}; {{harvnb|Morley|Gurney|1997|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite this, the defensive qualities of Castle Rising have since been extensively debated. The historian Robert Liddiard argues that the large windows at Castle Rising would have been a significant weakness, as it would have been easy to fire arrows through them from the bailey, and George Garnett has questioned the utility of the defensive arrow slits, which he suggests were not well positioned or designed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|p=51}}; {{harvnb|Garnett|2000|p=85}}&lt;/ref&gt; The whole site was also overlooked by higher ground, which Liddiard considers would have been a key defensive weakness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liddiard 2000 175–176&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2000|pp=175–176}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Great keeps such as Castle Rising's were also important ceremonially and symbolically in the 12th century, however, and historian Thomas Heslop has described Castle Rising as &quot;a fortress palace&quot;, with the keep forming the palace, and the surrounding earthworks the more practical defences.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Heslop|2003|p=277}}; {{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|pp=53–54}}&lt;/ref&gt; They reflected lordly status: typically their owners had recently advanced up the social scale, as with William d'Aubigny, and were keen to impress others with their new authority.&lt;ref name=Liddiard2005PP53&gt;{{harvnb|Liddiard|2005|pp=53–54}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The builders of [[Hedingham Castle|Hedingham]] and [[Conisborough Castle|Conisborough]] castles were similarly also new men, keen to reaffirm their new status through constructing grand works.&lt;ref name=Liddiard2005PP53/&gt;}}

With this in mind, the positioning of Castle Rising may have exposed it to higher ground, but it also made it strikingly prominent across the valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liddiard 2000 175–176&quot;/&gt; The whole entrance to the castle was also designed to communicate to a visitor the status of the castle lord.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dixon|1998|pp=55–56}}&lt;/ref&gt; As they came through the gatehouse and past the earthworks into the bailey, the south side of the forebuilding - deliberately facing the entrance - would have been revealed, covered in fashionable carving and decorative features.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dixon|1998|pp=48–49}}&lt;/ref&gt; Visitors would then have walked up the stairs of the forebuilding, have paused in a waiting room, originally largely open to the elements, before being allowed through a decorative entrance door.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dixon|1998|pp=49–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; The doorway led into the great hall, from where the lord, possibly sat in a throne alcove to the left, would have met the  visitor.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dixon|1998|p=50}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ceremonial entrance===
&lt;gallery mode=packed heights=180px&gt;
File:Castle Rising Gatehouse1.jpg|Senior visitors would have passed over the bridge&amp;nbsp;...
File:Castle Rising Castle - geograph.org.uk - 660629.jpg|... into the gatehouse&amp;nbsp;...
File:Stair Way - geograph.org.uk - 1440959.jpg|... through the forebuilding&amp;nbsp;...
File:Castle Rising Entrance vestibule.jpg|... into the waiting room&amp;nbsp;...
File:Castle Rising Great Hall Entrance.jpg|... and through the doorway&amp;nbsp;...
File:Great Hall - geograph.org.uk - 542857.jpg|... to finally meet the lord in the great hall.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[Castles in Great Britain and Ireland]]
*[[List of castles in England]]

==Notes==
{{notelist|notes=}}

==References==
{{reflist|3}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book
  | last = Brown
  | first = R. Allen
  | year = 1962
  | title = English Castles
  | publisher = B. T. Batsford
  | location= London, UK
  | oclc = 1392314
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Brown
  | first = R. Allen
  | year = 1988
  | title = Castle Rising Castle
  | publisher = English Heritage
  | location= London, UK
  | isbn = 1-85074-159-X
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Brown
  | first = R. Allen
  | year = 1989
  | title = Castles From the Air
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | location= Cambridge, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-521-32932-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Creighton
  | first = Oliver Hamilton
  | year = 2005
  | title = Castles and Landscapes: Power, Community and Fortification in Medieval England
  | publisher = Equinox
  | location= London, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-904768-67-8
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Creighton
  | first1 = Oliver Hamilton
  | last2 = Higham
  | first2 = Robert
  | year = 2003
  | title = Medieval Castles
  | publisher = Shire Archaeology
  | location= Princes Risborough, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-7478-0546-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last=Dixon
  | first=Philip
  | year=1998
  | title=Design in Castle-building: The Controlling of Access to the Lord
  | journal = Château Gaillard: études de castellologie médiévale
  | volume =18
  | pages =47–56
  |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Doherty
  | first = Paul
  | year = 2004
  | title = Isabella and the Strange Death of Edward II
  | publisher = Robinson
  | location= London, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-84119-843-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Garnett
  | first = Joe
  | editor-last= Saul
  | editor-first= Nigel
  | year = 2000
  | chapter = Conquered England, 1066–1215
  | title = The Oxford Illustrated History of Medieval England
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location= Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-19-289324-6
  | pages = 61–101
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Goodall
  | first = John
  |authorlink=John Goodall (author)
  | year = 2011
  | title = The English Castle
  | publisher = Yale University Press
  | location= New Haven, US and London, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-300-11058-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Green
  | first = David
  | editor-last= Ormrod
  | editor-first= W. M.
  | year = 2004
  | chapter = Edward the Black Prince and East Anglia: An Unlikely Association
  | title = Fourteenth Century England
  | volume = 3
  | publisher = Boydell Press
  | location= Woodbridge, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-19-289324-6
  | pages = 83–98
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Harrod
  | first = Henry
  | authorlink = Henry Harrod
  | year = 1857
  | title = Gleanings Among the Castles and Convents of Norfolk
  | publisher = C. Muskett
  | location= Norwich, UK
  | oclc = 4253893
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Heslop
  | first = Thomas Alexander
  | editor-last= Liddiard
  | editor-first= Robert
  | year = 2003
  | chapter = Orford Castle: Nostalgia and Sophisticated Living
  | title = Anglo-Norman Castles
  | publisher = Boydell Press
  | location= Woodbridge, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-85115-904-1
  | pages = 273–296
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  |last1=Higham
  |first1=Robert
  |last2=Barker
  |first2=Philip
  |title=Timber Castles
  |year=2004
  |publisher= University of Exeter Press
  |location= Exeter, UK
  |isbn=978-0-85989-753-2
  |ref=harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hillaby
  | first = Joe
  | editor-last= Skinner
  | editor-first= Patricia
  | year = 2003
  | chapter = Jewish Colonisation in the Twelfth Century
  | title = Jews in Medieval Britain
  | publisher = The Boydell Press
  | location= Woodbridge, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-84383-733-6
  | pages = 15–40
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  |last1=Hillaby
  |first1=Joe
  |last2=Hillaby
  |first2=Caroline
  |title=The Palgrave Dictionary of Medieval Anglo-Jewish History
  |year=2013
  |publisher= Palgrave Macmillan
  |location= Basingstoke, UK
  |isbn=978-1-137-30815-3
  |ref=harv
  }}
*{{cite news
  | last=Hulme
  | first=Richard
  | year=2007–2008
  | title=Twelfth Century Great Towers - The Case for the Defence
  | journal = The Castle Studies Group Journal
  | number = 21
  | pages =209–229
  |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Liddiard
  | first = Robert
  | editor-last= Harper-Bill
  | editor-first= Christopher
  | year = 2000
  | volume = 22
  | chapter = Castle Rising, Norfolk: A 'Landscape of Lordship'?
  | title = Anglo-Norman Studies: Proceedings of the Battle Conference 1999
  | publisher = Boydell Press
  | location= Woodbridge, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-85115-796-2
  | pages = 169–186
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  |last=Liddiard
  |first=Robert
  |title=Castles in Context: Power, Symbolism and Landscape, 1066 to 1500
  |year=2005
  |publisher= Windgather Press
  |location= Macclesfield, UK
  |isbn=978-0-9545575-2-2
  |ref=harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Mileson
  | first = Joe
  | editor-last= Liddiard
  | editor-first= Robert
  | year = 2007
  | chapter = The Sociology of Park Creation in Medieval England
  | title = The Medieval Park: New Perspectives
  | publisher = Windgather Press
  | location= Macclesfield, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-905119-16-5
  | pages = 11–26
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Morley
  | first1 = Beric
  | last2 = Gurney
  | first2 = David
  | year = 1997
  | title = Castle Rising Castle, Norfolk
  | publisher = Norfolk Museums Service
  | location= Norfolk, UK
  | isbn = 0-905594-23-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Mortimer
  | first = Ian
  | year = 2008
  | title = The Perfect King: The Life of Edward II, Father of the English Nation
  | publisher = Vintage
  | location= London, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-09-952709-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Pounds
  | first = Norman John Greville
  | year = 1994
  | title = The Medieval Castle in England and Wales: A Social and Political History
  | publisher =  Cambridge University Press
  | location= Cambridge, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-521-45828-3
  | ref=harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Stalley
  | first = Roger A.
  | year = 1999
  | title = Early Medieval Architecture
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location= Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-19-284223-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Toy
  | first = Sidney
  | year = 1985
  | origyear = 1939
  | title = Castles: Their Construction and History
  | publisher = Dover
  | location= New York, US
  | isbn = 978-0-486-24898-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = White
  | first = Graeme J.
  | year = 2012
  | title = The Medieval English Landscape, 1000–1540
  | publisher = Bloomsbury
  | location= London, UK and New York, US
  | isbn = 978-1-4411-6308-0
  | ref = harv
  }}

==External links==
{{commons category|Castle Rising (castle)}}
*[http://www.castlerising.com/ Official website]
*[http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/server/show/conProperty.15 English Heritage website] on Castle Rising Castle

{{coord|52.7928|N|0.4689|E|type:landmark_region:GB|display=title}}

[[Category:English Heritage sites in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Castles in Norfolk]]
[[Category:King's Lynn and West Norfolk]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Grade I listed castles]]
[[Category:Houses in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Ruins in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Ruined castles in England]]
[[Category:Grade I listed ruins]]</text>
      <sha1>s0clzzrspfsekntn6vnomqxndl82lq3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
