<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Charles B. Gatewood</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26726196</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750247167</id>
      <parentid>736980976</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T16:21:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Solomonfromfinland</username>
        <id>11874933</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Category:Geronimo]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20334">{{Good article}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Charles Bare Gatewood 
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1853|4|5}}
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1896|5|20|1853|4|5}}
|birth_place= [[Woodstock, Virginia]]
|death_place= [[Fort Monroe, Virginia]]
|placeofburial= [[Arlington National Cemetery]]
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|image= Charles Bare Gatewood.jpg
|caption= 
|nickname= Scipio Africanus &lt;br /&gt;&quot;Nanton Bse-che&quot; translated as Big Nose Captain
|allegiance= {{flagicon|United States}} [[United States|United States of America]]
|branch= [[File:United States Department of the Army Seal.svg|23px]] [[United States Army]]
|serviceyears= 1877–1896
|rank= [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]]
|commands= 
|unit= [[6th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|6th Cavalry]]
|battles= *[[Victorio's War]]&lt;br&gt;
*[[Apache Wars#Geronimo's War|Geronimo's War]]
*[[Geronimo Campaign]]
*[[Battle of Devil's Creek]]
*[[Johnson County War]]
|awards=
|laterwork= 
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = American politicianUS Army officer who encouraged the surrender of Geronimo
}}

{{for|the American photographer and writer|Charles Gatewood}}

[[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] '''Charles Bare Gatewood''' (April 5, 1853 – May 20, 1896) was an American soldier born in [[Woodstock, Virginia]]. He served in the [[United States Army]] in the [[6th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|6th Cavalry]] after graduating from [[West Point]]. Upon assignment to the American Southwest, Gatewood led platoons of Apache and Navajo scouts against [[Renegade period of the Apache Wars|renegades]] during the [[Apache Wars]]. In 1886 he played a key role in ending the [[Geronimo Campaign]] by persuading [[Geronimo]] to [[surrender (military)|surrender]] to the army.&lt;ref&gt;Greene (2007)p. 242&lt;/ref&gt;  Beset with health problems due to exposure in the Southwest and Dakotas, Gatewood was critically injured in the [[Johnson County War]] and retired from the Army in 1895, dying a year later from [[stomach cancer]].  Before his retirement he was nominated for the [[Medal of Honor]], but was denied the award.  He was portrayed by [[Jason Patric]] in the 1993 film ''[[Geronimo: An American Legend]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| people = [[Walter Hill (filmmaker)|Walter Hill]]  | title = [[Geronimo: An American Legend]]| medium = film | publisher =[[Columbia Pictures]]  | location = United States | date = December 10, 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Gatewood was born into a military family in Woodstock, Virginia, on April 5, 1853.  He became a Cadet at the [[United States Military Academy]] at [[West Point]] in 1873 where he earned the nickname ''[[Scipio Africanus]]'' because of his resemblance to the Roman general of the [[Scipio Africanus|same name]].&lt;ref name=faulk38/&gt;  He graduated in 1877 with a commission as Second Lieutenant and received orders to the 6th Cavalry in the Southwest at [[Fort Wingate, New Mexico]].&lt;ref name=faulk38&gt;Faulk (1993)p.38&lt;/ref&gt;

==Apache Wars==
Gatewood led companies of [[Apache Scouts|Apache]] and [[Navajo Scouts]] in Apache territory throughout the Southwestern United States.  He was respected among the Apaches and earned the nickname ''Nanton Bse-che'', meaning &quot;Big-nosed Captain&quot;.&lt;ref name=kraft221/&gt;  After one year of service at Fort Wingate, Gatewood was made the commander of Apache scouts from the [[White Mountain Apache]] Reservation, and later an [[aide-de-camp]] to General Nelson Miles.&lt;ref name=faulk137&gt;Faulk (1993) p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;  One of his sergeants was a scout who was a former White Mountain Chief named [[Alchesay]].&lt;ref name=kraft221&gt;Kraft (2000) p.221&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victorio's War===
In 1879 Gatewood and his Apache scouts were brought from Arizona to the [[Black Range]] Mountains of [[New Mexico]] to capture the Apache Chief [[Victorio]] in the [[Victorio's War|Victorio Campaign]].&lt;ref name=vic/&gt;  He and his scouts were placed under the command of Major [[Albert P. Morrow]] of the [[9th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|Ninth Cavalry]] at [[Fort Bayard, New Mexico]].&lt;ref name=vic/&gt;  Gatewood's scouts skirmished with Victorio's band, but ultimately failed to capture him.&lt;ref name=vic&gt;Chamberlain (2007) pp. 173–175&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1881 he returned to Virginia on sick leave because he had developed [[rheumatism]] from exposure to the elements in his two years working with the Apache scouts in the harsh Southwest.  He married Georgia McCulloh, the daughter of Thomas G. McCulloh and niece of [[Richard Sears McCulloh]] on June 23, 1881 in [[Cumberland, Maryland]].&lt;ref name=kraft263&gt;Kraft (2000) p. 263&lt;/ref&gt;  His sick leave expired in July and having not returned to his post, he was declared [[AWOL|Absent without leave (AWOL)]].&lt;ref name=kraft263/&gt; Gatewood returned to the Southwest on September 17, 1881 under the command of Colonel [[Eugene Asa Carr]] in his campaign against the Cibecue and White Mountain Apaches.&lt;ref&gt;Gatewood (2009) p. xxv&lt;/ref&gt;

===Geronimo's War===
[[File:Apache chieff Geronimo (right) and his warriors in 1886.jpg|thumb|left|Apache leader [[Geronimo]] (right) is depicted with a small group of followers in northern Mexico in 1886]]

In 1882, the US Army sent Brigadier General [[George Crook]] to take command of Indian operations in Arizona Territory.&lt;ref name=kraft34/&gt;  Crook was an experienced Indian fighter who had long since learned that regular soldiers were almost useless against the Apaches and had based his entire strategy on employing &quot;Indians to fight other Indians&quot;.&lt;ref name=kraft34/&gt;  The Apache, as a mark of respect, nicknamed Crook ''Nantan Lupan'', which means &quot;Grey Wolf&quot;.&lt;ref name=kraft34/&gt;  Despite having subjugated all the major tribes of Apaches in the Territory; the Apaches had once again taken up arms, this time under the leadership of [[Geronimo]].&lt;ref name=kraft34/&gt; Crook repeatedly saw Geronimo and his small band of warriors escape every time.&lt;ref name=kraft34&gt;Kraft(2000) p.34&lt;/ref&gt;

Knowing Gatewood's reputation as one of the army's &quot;Best Apache Men&quot;, Crook made him Commandant of the White Mountain Indian Reservation at [[Fort Apache Indian Reservation|Fort Apache]] under [[Emmet Crawford]].&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt;  Gatewood and Crook disagreed on handling of the reservation and treatment of the Apaches.&lt;ref name=kraft60/&gt;  After a clash with local politicians over grazing rights on reservation land, Crook had Gatewood transferred in 1885 to command [[Navajo Scouts]].&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt;  That same year Crook resigned from the Army and [[Philip Sheridan]] had him replaced by General [[Nelson Miles]] in the [[Geronimo Campaign]].&lt;ref name=kraft60&gt;Kraft(2000) pp.59–64&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Crook and Gatewood had a falling-out, Gatewood was regarded by Miles as a &quot;Crook Man&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;McCallum (2006) p.40&lt;/ref&gt; despite this and Gatewood's failing health,  Miles knew that Gatewood was well known to Geronimo, spoke some Apache, and was familiar with their traditions and values; having spent nearly 10 years in the field with them and against them.&lt;ref&gt;Wooster (1996) pp.150–151&lt;/ref&gt;

Gatewood was dispatched by General Miles to seek out [[Geronimo]] for a parley.&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt; On July 21, when he reached [[San Nicolás de Carretas|Carretas]], [[Chihuahua (state)|Chihuahua]], Gatewood encountered another Army officer, [[James Parker (Medal of Honor)|Lieutenant James Parker]] of the [[4th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|4th Cavalry]], who had orders to follow Geronimo's trail.&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt;  Parker told Gatewood, &quot;The trail is all a myth—I haven't seen any trail since three weeks ago when it was washed out by the rains.&quot;&lt;ref name=runkle&gt;Runkle (2011)pp.29–33&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite his rapidly deteriorating health, Gatewood refused to quit and Parker guided him to Captain [[Henry Lawton]], who was leading a mission to find and kill Geronimo with the Fourth Cavalry.&lt;ref name=wooster150&gt;Wooster (1996) p.150&lt;/ref&gt; It took two weeks through 150 miles of desertmountain ranges to locate Lawton on the banks of the [[Aros River]] on August 3, 1886.  Lawton reluctantly allowed Gatewood and his scouts to join his command.&lt;ref name=wooster150/&gt;  Gatewood's health continued to deteriorate.&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt;  On August 8 he asked Lawron's Surgeon, [[Leonard Wood]], to medically discharge him, but Wood refused.&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt;  On August 23, 1886, Gatewood led 25 men and two Apache scouts into the Sierra Madre and found Geronimo's camp: his band reduced to 20 men and 14 women and children.&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt;  On August 24 Gatewood approached Geronimo's camp with only 2 soldiers: [[George Medhurst Wratten]], who was fluent in all Apache dialects and one other; 2 interpreters: [[Tom Horn]] and Jesús María Yestes; and two  [[Chiricahua]] scouts: Kayitah, a Chokonen, and Martine, a Nedni, so as not to alarm the Apaches.&lt;ref name=kraft154&gt;Kraft (2000) p. 154&lt;/ref&gt;  Kayitah and Martine made the initial contact, being invited into the camp by the [[Bavispe River]].&lt;ref name=kraft154/&gt;  Kayitah remained in the camp as a hostage while Martine left and returned with Gatewood and 15 pounds of [[tobacco]].&lt;ref name=runkle/&gt;  After Gatewood made gifts of tobacco,  Geronimo teased Gatewood about his thinness and sickly look, Gatewood was then told by Geronimo, &quot;you are always welcome in my camp, and it was always safe for you to come&quot;.&lt;ref name=wind&gt;Roberts (1994)p.292&lt;/ref&gt;  Gatewood encouraged Geronimo to abandon his fight against the US Army.  When asked by Geronimo what Gatewood would do in his situation and to &quot;think like an Apache&quot;, Gatewood advised him to &quot;put your trust in Miles&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Capps (1975)p.240&lt;/ref&gt;

Agreeing to meet with General Miles, Geronimo's band rode with Gatewood to Lawton's camp in [[Guadalupe Mountains (Hidalgo County)|Guadalupe Canyon]], the entrance to the United States.  Lawton received Geronimo and agreed to allow the Apaches to retain their weapons for defense against nearby Mexican troops.&lt;ref name=kraft154/&gt;  Lawton left for a [[heliograph]] station to send word to Miles, leaving Lieutenant Abiel Smith in command.&lt;ref name=kraft154/&gt;  Smith and Wood wanted to disarm the Apaches because they were prisoners-of-war. Smith told Gatewood that he wanted a meeting with Geronimo's men, but Gatewood refused because he knew Smith wanted to murder Geronimo, rather than bring him to Miles.&lt;ref name=kraft154/&gt;  Smith persisted and Gatewood threatened to &quot;blow the head off the first soldier in line&quot;, who was [[Leonard Wood]], Wood left to write a dispatch and Gatewood turned to the next man, Smith, who finally relented.&lt;ref&gt;Kraft (2000) pp.185–186&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Geronimo surrender site.jpg|thumb|A pile of stones marking the site of [[Geronimo]]'s [[surrender (military)|surrender]]]]
The troops and the Apaches arrived at [[Skeleton Canyon]], [[Arizona]], in the [[Peloncillo Mountains (Hidalgo County)|Peloncillo Mountains]] without incident on September 2, 1886.&lt;ref name=fourth/&gt;  Miles arrived on September 3, 1886, and Geronimo formally surrendered for the fourth and final time on September 4.&lt;ref name=fourth/&gt;  At the conclusion of the surrender, Geronimo turned to Gatewood and said to him, in Apache, &quot;Good.  You told the truth&quot;.&lt;ref name=fourth&gt;Debo(1989) p. 292&lt;/ref&gt;   The following day [[Naiche]] surrendered, he had been in a nearby canyon mourning his brother,  who had been killed by Mexican soldiers, bringing the Apache wars to an official end in the Southwest.&lt;ref&gt;DeMontravel(1998) p.173&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite his success, Miles chastised Gatewood for &quot;disobeying orders&quot; as Gatewood made the final approach to Geronimo with only a party of 6 instead of 25.&lt;ref name=wooster160&gt;Wooster (1996) p.160&lt;/ref&gt;  Gatewood reasoned that a larger party would have scared the Apache and made them flee.&lt;ref name=wooster160/&gt;  The city of [[Tucson, Arizona]], held a Gala event to celebrate Geronimo's surrender and invited Gatewood to be the guest of honor, but Miles refused to let him attend.&lt;ref&gt;Kraft(2000)p.221&lt;/ref&gt; Miles appointed Gatewood as his &quot;Aide-de-Camp&quot;, to keep the lieutenant under scrutiny, Miles downplayed Gatewood's role in Geronimo's surrender mostly because it would have given legitimacy to Crook's strategy.&lt;ref name=wooster156&gt;Wooster (1996) p.156&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mazzanovich (1926)p.236&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ghost Dance War==
In December 1890, Gatewood was reassigned to the Sixth Cavalry, H Troop.  His regiment was ordered to [[South Dakota]]'s [[Pine Ridge Agency]] in an operation against hostile [[Sioux]] Indians but was not engaged in the final campaign that culminated in the tragedy at [[Wounded Knee Battlefield|Wounded Knee]] in December.  Gatewood developed [[rheumatism]] in both shoulders and was unable to move his arms, again due to the cold weather, in January and had medical orders to leave in February 1891 for [[Hot Springs, South Dakota]].&lt;ref&gt;Kraft(2000) p. 215&lt;/ref&gt;

==Johnson County War==
By September 1891 Gatewood had recovered and he rejoined the Sixth Cavalry, then stationed at [[Fort McKinney (Wyoming)|Fort McKinney, Wyoming]].&lt;ref name=kraft166/&gt;  Wyoming was undergoing a [[range war]] between ranchers and farmers that would be known as the [[Johnson County War]] and the Sixth Cavalry was dispatched at the request of Acting Governor [[Amos W. Barber]].&lt;ref name=kraft166/&gt; On May 18, 1892 cowboys from the [[Red Sash Ranch]] set fire to the [[Post exchange]] and planted a bomb in the form of gunpowder in a barracks stove.&lt;ref name=kraft166/&gt;  Gatewood was responding to the fire and was injured by a bomb blast in a barracks; his left arm was shattered, rendering him too disabled to serve in the Cavalry.&lt;ref name=kraft166&gt;Kraft (2000) p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;

Soon after, The Ninth Cavalry of &quot;[[Buffalo Soldiers]]&quot; was ordered to Fort McKinney to replace the Sixth Cavalry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schubert&quot;&gt;Schubert (1973) pp. 57–68&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and legacy==
On November 19, 1892, Gatewood received orders for [[Denver, Colorado]] to await his muster out of the Army.  On June 4, 1894, he sought a position as the military advisor of [[El Paso County, Colorado]], to aid in the [[Cripple Creek miners' strike of 1894]] in [[Cripple Creek, Colorado]], but was denied.&lt;ref&gt;Kraft (2000) p. 217&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1894 he took a leave of absence from the Army and moved to [[Fort Myer, Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;Kraft (2000) pp. 218–219&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1895 he was recommended for the [[Medal of Honor]] by General [[Nelson A. Miles]], &quot;for gallantry in going alone at the risk of his life into the hostile Apache camp of Geronimo in Sonora, August 24, 1886,&quot; but was denied by the acting Secretary of War because Gatewood never distinguished himself in hostile action.&lt;ref&gt;DeMontravel (1998) p.192&lt;/ref&gt; In 1896 he suffered excruciating stomach pains and went to a Veteran's Hospital in Fort Monroe, Virginia, for treatment. Gatewood died on May 20, 1896, of stomach cancer and his body was buried at Arlington National Cemetery with full [[military honors]].&lt;ref&gt;Kraft (2000) pp. 266–267&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 23, 1896, Colonel D. S. Gordon, commander of the 6th Cavalry, issued General Order 19, which stated:
{{quote|It is with extreme sorrow and regret that the Colonel commanding the regiment announced the death of First Lieutenant Charles B. Gatewood at Fort Monroe May 20. Too much cannot be said in honor of this brave officer and it is lamentable that he should have died with only the rank of a Lieutenant, after his brilliant services to the Government. That no material advantages reverted to him is regretted by every officer of his regiment, who extend to his bereaved family their most profound, earnest and sincere sympathy. As a mark of respect to his memory, the officers of the regiment will wear the usual badge of mourning for the period of 30 days.&lt;ref&gt;Faulk (1993) p. 183&lt;/ref&gt;}}

His son, Charles B. Gatewood, Jr. (January 4, 1883 – November 13, 1953), joined the Army and rose to the rank of colonel.  He campaigned for recognition of his father's name and later compiled and published his father's memoirs.&lt;ref&gt;DeMontravel(1998) p.403&lt;/ref&gt;

The role of Gatewood was portrayed in 1954 by [[Brett King]] in the [[Broadcast syndication|syndicated]] [[television series]], ''[[Stories of the Century]]'', starring and narrated by [[Jim Davis (actor)|Jim Davis]].
 
Gatewood was later portrayed by [[Jason Patric]] in the 1993 film ''[[Geronimo: An American Legend]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Dixon (2000) p.221&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Robert Cummings]] played First Lieutenant Gatewood in the episode &quot;The Last Bugle&quot; (24 Nov. 1960) on ''[[Dick Powell's Zane Grey Theater]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0754305/?ref_=ttep_ep23&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|colwidth=33em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book | last = Capps | first = Benjamin | coauthors = | title = The Great Chiefs| publisher=Time-Life Education| year = 1975| isbn = 978-0-316-84785-8}}
*{{cite book|title=Victorio: Apache warrior and chief|first= Kathleen P. |last=Chamberlain |publisher =University of Oklahoma Press|year= 2007|ISBN = 978-0-8061-3843-5 }}
*{{cite book|title = Geronimo: The Man, His Time, His Place|first= Angie |last=Debo|publisher= University of Oklahoma Press|chapter=I have surrendered for the fourth time|year= 1989 |ISBN = 978-0-8061-1828-4}}
*{{cite book|title=A hero to his fighting men: Nelson A. Miles, 1839–1925 |first=Peter R. |last=DeMontravel |publisher=Kent State University Press|year=1998 |ISBN = 978-0-87338-594-7 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KXmeG_jTQygC&amp;pg=PA171&amp;dq=gatewood+geronimo+martine+kayitah&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=9O2jTvTwA9K28QP85e3-BQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=gatewood%20geronimo%20martine%20kayitah&amp;f=false}}
*{{cite book|title=Film genre 2000: new critical essays: The SUNY series, cultural studies in cinema/video |first= Wheeler W.|last= Dixon |authorlink=Wheeler Dixon|publisher= SUNY Press|year= 2000 |ISBN = 978-0-7914-4514-3 }}
*{{cite book|last=Gatewood|first= Charles B.|editor=Louis Kraft|title=LT. Charles Gatewood &amp; His Apache Wars Memoir|publisher= University of Nebraska Press|year= 2009|  ISBN= 978-0-8032-1884-0}}
*{{cite book|title= Indian War veterans: memories of army life and campaigns in the West, 1864–1898 |first=Jerome A. |last=Greene |publisher=Casemate Publishers|year=2007 |ISBN =978-1-932714-26-5}}
*{{cite book|title=The Geronimo campaign |first=Odie B. |last=Faulk |publisher =Oxford University Press,|year= 1993 |ISBN =978-0-19-508351-4}}
*{{cite book|title=Leonard Wood: Rough Rider, surgeon, architect of American imperialism|first=Jack Edward|last= McCallum |year= 2006 |publisher=NYU Press|isbn=978-0-8147-5699-7}}
*{{cite book|title=Gatewood &amp; Geronimo|first= Louis |last=Kraft |publisher= University of New Mexico Press|year= 2000 |ISBN =978-0-8263-2130-5 }}
*{{cite book|title= Trailing Geronimo: Some hitherto unrecorded incidents bearing upon the outbreak of the White mountain Apaches and Geronimo's band in Arizona and New Mexico |first=Anton |last=Mazzanovich |publisher =Gem Publishing Co.|year=1926 }}
*{{cite book|title=Once They Moved Like The Wind: Cochise, Geronimo, And The Apache Wars|first= David |last=Roberts |publisher =Simon and Schuster|location=New York|year= 1994 |ISBN = 978-0-671-88556-4 }}
*{{cite book|title=Wanted Dead Or Alive: Manhunts from Geronimo to Bin Laden|first=Benjamin|last= Runkle|publisher =Macmillan |year= 2011 |ISBN =978-0-230-10485-3 }}
*{{cite journal|last=Schubert|first= Frank N. |url=http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0043-3810(197301)4%3A1%3C57%3ATSATBC%3E2.0.CO%3B2-L |title=The Suggs Affray: The Black Cavalry in the Johnson County War|journal=[[The Western Historical Quarterly]]| volume=4|issue= 1 |year= 1973|pages= 57–68}}
*{{Cite book|title =Nelson A. Miles and the Twilight of the Frontier Army |first= Robert|last= Wooster |publisher=University of Nebraska Press|year= 1996 |ISBN =978-0-8032-9775-3}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
*[http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/charlesb.htm Arlington Cemetery: Lieutenant Charles Bare Gatewood]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gatewood, Charles Bare}}
[[Category:1853 births]]
[[Category:1896 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Woodstock, Virginia]]
[[Category:Geronimo]]
[[Category:United States Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Indian Wars]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]
[[Category:Deaths from stomach cancer]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in Virginia]]</text>
      <sha1>tqyznpec0ddgmz8p5m36u1mbd9fiuuu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
