<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Citadel of Erbil</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3950496</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744919387</id>
      <parentid>744819292</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-18T07:20:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zoeperkoe</username>
        <id>10449708</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>No good reason to delete link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27410">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military structure
|name = Erbil citadel
|native_name = [[Kurdish language|Kurdish]]: Qelay Hewlêr, [[Arabic language|Arabic]]: قلعة أربيل
|location = [[Erbil]], [[Iraqi Kurdistan]], [[Iraq]]
|image = [[File:Hawler Castle.jpg|300px|Hill with houses on top and surrounded by urban sprawl]]
|caption = Aerial view of the Erbil citadel
|map_type = Iraq Arbil
|latitude = 36.191
|longitude = 44.009
|map_size = 300
|map_alt =
|map_caption =Location of the citadel in [[Erbil]]
|type =
|coordinates =
|code =
|built = Unknown
|builder =
|materials =
|height =
|used =
|demolished =
|condition = Partially ruined
|ownership =
|open_to_public = Yes
|controlledby =
|garrison =
|current_commander =
|commanders =
|occupants =
|battles = Siege by the [[Mongol Empire|Mongols]] (1258)
|events =
|image2 =
|caption2 =
|footnotes = {{designation list | embed=yes
  | designation1 = WHS
  | designation1_offname = Erbil Citadel
  | designation1_date = 2014 &lt;small&gt;(38th [[World Heritage Committee|session]])&lt;/small&gt;
  | designation1_type =  Cultural
  | designation1_criteria = iv
  | designation1_number = [http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1437 1437]
  | designation1_free1name = State Party
  | designation1_free1value = Iraq
  | designation1_free2name = Region
  | designation1_free2value = [[List of World Heritage Sites in the Arab States|Arab States]]
  }}
}}

The '''Erbil Citadel''' ({{lang-ku|قه‌ڵای هه‌ولێر ''Qelay Hewlêr''}}; {{lang-ar|قلعة أربيل}}) is a [[tell]] or occupied mound, and the historical city centre of [[Erbil]] in the [[Iraqi Kurdistan|Kurdistan Region]] of [[Iraq]].  .&lt;ref name=&quot;unesco&quot; /&gt; The citadel has been inscribed on the World Heritage List since 21 June 2014.

The earliest evidence for occupation of the citadel mound dates to the 5th millennium BC, and possibly earlier. It appears for the first time in historical sources in the [[Ebla tablets]] around 2,300 BC, and gained particular importance during the [[Neo-Assyrian Empire|Neo-Assyrian]] period. During the [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanian]] period and the [[Abbasid Caliphate]], Erbil was an important centre for [[Christianity]]. After the [[Mongol Empire|Mongols]] captured the citadel in 1258, the importance of Erbil declined. During the 20th century, the urban structure was significantly modified, as a result of which a number of houses and public buildings were destroyed. In 2007, the High Commission for Erbil Citadel Revitalization (HCECR) was established to oversee the [[building restoration|restoration]] of the citadel. In the same year, all inhabitants, except one family, were evicted from the citadel as part of a large restoration project. Since then, [[archaeology|archaeological]] research and restoration works have been carried out at and around the tell by various international teams and in cooperation with local specialists. The government plans to have 50 families live in the citadel once it is renovated.

The buildings on top of the tell stretch over a roughly oval area of {{convert|430|x|340|m}} occupying {{convert|102,000|sqm}}. The only religious structure that currently survives is the [[Mulla Effendi|Mulla Afandi]] Mosque. The mound rises between {{convert|25|and|32|m}} from the surrounding plain. When it was fully occupied, the citadel was divided in three districts or ''[[mahalla]]s'': from east to west the Serai, the Takya and the Topkhana. The Serai was occupied by notable families; the Takya district was named after the homes of [[dervish]]es, which are called ''takyas''; and the Topkhana district housed craftsmen and farmers.

==History==

===Prehistory===
The site of the citadel may have been occupied as early as the [[Neolithic]] period, as [[sherd|pottery fragments]] possibly dating to that period have been found on the slopes of the mound. Clear evidence for occupation comes from the [[Chalcolithic]] period, with sherds resembling pottery of the [[Ubaid period|Ubaid]] and [[Uruk period|Uruk]] periods in the [[Al-Jazira, Mesopotamia|Jazira]] and southeastern [[Turkey]], respectively.&lt;ref name=novacek276&gt;{{harvnb|Nováček|Chabr|Filipský|Janiček|2008|p=276}}&lt;/ref&gt; Given this evidence for early occupation, the citadel has been called the oldest continuously occupied site in the world.&lt;ref name=unesco&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://whc.unesco.org/en/tentativelists/5479/ |title=Erbil Citadel - UNESCO World Heritage Centre |publisher=whc.unesco.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NavalIntelligenceDivision529&gt;{{harvnb|Naval Intelligence Division|1944|p=529}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Earliest historical records===
Erbil appears for the first time in literary sources around 2300 BC in the archives of [[Ebla]]. According to [[Giovanni Pettinato]], it is mentioned in two tablets as ''Irbilum''.&lt;ref&gt;Martha A. Morrison, David I. Owen, eds, [http://books.google.ca/books?id=agi4O1c3UhQC&amp;pg=PA11 ''General Studies and Excavations at Nuzi 9/1; Volume 2 In Honor of Ernest R. Lacheman.''] Eisenbrauns, 1981 ISBN 0931464080&lt;/ref&gt;

Later, [[Erridupizir]], king of Gutium, captured the city in 2200 BC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.erbilcitadel.org/arbil/index.php?option=com_k2&amp;view=itemlist&amp;layout=category&amp;task=category&amp;id=116&amp;Itemid=696 Timeline] ErbilCitadel.orq&lt;/ref&gt;

At the end of the 3rd millennium BC, Erbil is mentioned in historical records of the [[Ur III]] period as Urbilum. King [[Shulgi]] destroyed Urbilum in his 43rd regnal year, and during the reign of his successor [[Amar-Sin]], Urbilum was incorporated into the Ur III state. In the 18th century BC, Erbil appears in a list of cities that were conquered by [[Shamshi-Adad I|Shamshi-Adad]] of Upper Mesopotamia and Dadusha of [[Eshnunna]] during their campaign against the land of Qabra. Shamshi-Adad installed garrisons in all the cities of the land of Urbil. During the 2nd millennium BC, Erbil was incorporated into [[Assyria]]. Erbil served as a point of departure for military campaigns toward the east.&lt;ref name=villard&gt;{{harvnb|Villard|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eidem|1985|p=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===From the Neo-Assyrian period to the Sassanids===
Erbil was an important city during the Neo-Assyrian period. The city took part in the great revolt against [[Shamshi-Adad V]] that broke out over the succession of [[Shalmaneser III]]. During the Neo-Assyrian period, the name of the city was written as ''Arbi-Ilu'', meaning 'Four Gods'. Erbil was an important religious centre that was compared with cities such as [[Babylon]] and [[Assur]]. Its goddess [[Ishtar]] of Erbil was one of the principal deities of Assyria, often named together with Ishtar of [[Nineveh]]. Her sanctuary was repaired by the kings [[Shalmaneser I]], [[Esarhaddon]] and [[Assurbanipal]]. Inscriptions from Assurbanipal record oracular dreams inspired by Ishtar of Erbil. Assurbanipal probably held court in Erbil during part of his reign and received there envoys from [[Rusa II]] of [[Urartu]] after the defeat of the [[Elam]]ite ruler Teumman.&lt;ref name=villard/&gt;

After the end of the Assyrian Empire, Erbil was first controlled by the [[Medes]] and then incorporated into the [[Achaemenid Empire]] before it became part of the empire of [[Alexander the Great]] after the [[Battle of Gaugamela]], which was fought near Erbil in 331 BC.&lt;ref name=novacek260&gt;{{harvnb|Nováček|Chabr|Filipský|Janiček|2008|p=260}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Roman Empire|Roman]] and [[Parthian Empire]] fought over control of Erbil, or Arbira as it was known in that period, and the city became an important Christian centre. During the Sassanid period, Erbil was the seat of a governor. In 340 AD, Christians in Erbil were persecuted and in 358, the governor became a [[martyr]] when he converted to Christianity.&lt;ref name=sourdel&gt;{{harvnb|Sourdel|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Nestorianism|Nestorian]] school was founded in Erbil by the [[School of Nisibis]] in ''c''. 521.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morony|1984|p=359}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, Erbil was also the site of a [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrian]] [[fire temple]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Morony|1984|p=132}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Muslim conquest until the Ottomans===
[[File:Siège d'Irbil 1258-1259.jpeg|thumb|right|Fifteenth-century depiction of the siege of Erbil by the [[Mongol Empire|Mongols]] in 1258|alt=Painting showing an army encampment with horses, soldiers and tents in front of a walled city with towers and a gate guarded by soldiers]]
Erbil was conquered by the [[Muslim conquests|Muslim]]s in the 7th century. It remained an important Christian centre until the 9th century, when the [[bishop]] of Erbil moved his seat to [[Mosul]]. From the first half of the 12th century until 1233, Erbil was the seat of the Begteginids, a [[Oghuz Turks|Turcoman]] dynasty that rose to prominence under the reign of [[Zengi]], the [[atabeg]] of Mosul. [[Muzaffar al-Din Gökböri]], the second dynast of the Begtegenid dynasty and a staunch supporter of [[Saladin]], created a lower town around the city on the citadel mound and founded hospitals and [[madrasah]]s. Gökburi died in 1233 without an heir and control of Erbil shifted to the [[Abbasid Caliphate|Abbasid Caliph]] [[Al-Mustansir (caliph)|al-Mustansir]] after he had besieged the city.&lt;ref name=sourdel/&gt;&lt;ref name=cahen&gt;{{harvnb|Cahen|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When the Mongols [[Mongol Empire#Middle East|invaded]] the Near East in the 13th century, they attacked Erbil for the first time in 1237. They plundered the lower town but had to retreat before an approaching caliphal army and had to put off the capture of the citadel.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Woods|1977|pp=49–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Siege of Baghdad (1258)|fall of Baghdad]] to [[Hulagu Khan|Hülegü]] and the Mongols in 1258, they returned to Erbil and were able to capture the citadel after a siege lasting six months.&lt;ref name=novacek261&gt;{{harvnb|Nováček|Chabr|Filipský|Janiček|2008|p=261}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hülegü then appointed a Christian governor to the town and there was an influx of [[Syriac Orthodox Church|Jacobite Christians]], who were allowed to build a church. 

As time passed, persecutions of Christians, Jews and Buddhists throughout the [[Ilkhanate]] began in earnest in 1295 under [[Oïrat]] amir [[Nawrūz (Mongol emir)|Nauruz]].&lt;ref&gt;Grousset, p. 379&lt;/ref&gt; This manifested early on in the reign of the [[Ilkhan]] [[Ghazan]]. In 1297, after Ghazan had felt strong enough to overcome Nauruz' influence, he put a stop to the persecutions. 

During the reign of the Ilkhan [[Öljeitü]] some of the Christian inhabitants retreated to the citadel to escape persecution. In the spring of 1310, the [[Malik|Malek]] (governor) of the region attempted to seize it from them with the help of the Kurds. Despite [[Yahballaha III|Mar Yahballaha]]'s best efforts to avert the impending doom, the citadel was at last taken by Ilkhanate troops and Kurdish tribesmen on 1 July 1310, and all the defenders were massacred, including all the Christian inhabitants of the lower town.&lt;ref name=sourdel/&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Grousset, p. 383&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] period, Erbil was part of the [[Baghdad Eyalet|province of Baghdad]], which was established in 1535. In 1743, the city was held for a short time by the [[Afsharid dynasty|Afsharid]] ruler [[Nader Shah]] after a siege lasting 60 days.&lt;ref name=sourdel/&gt; An engraving from 1820 shows that at that time both the citadel mound and the plain at its southern foot were occupied.&lt;ref name=history&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/ErbilCitadel/history.php |title=History |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Mohammed Khor, a local [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] [[bey|beg]] of [[Rowanduz]], controlled Erbil for a short period in 1862. In 1892, the town had approximately 3,200 inhabitants, including a sizeable [[Jews|Jewish]] minority.&lt;ref name=NavalIntelligenceDivision529/&gt;

===Modern period===
During the 20th century, the citadel witnessed significant urban and social changes. A {{convert|15|m|adj=on}} high steel water tank was erected on the citadel in 1924, providing the inhabitants with purified water, but also causing water damage to the foundations of the buildings due to increased water seepage. The number of inhabitants gradually declined over the 20th century as the city at the foot of the citadel grew and wealthier inhabitants moved to larger, modern houses with gardens.&lt;ref name=history/&gt; In 1960, over 60 houses, a mosque and a school were demolished to make way for a straight road connecting the southern gate with the northern gate.&lt;ref name=historicalevolution&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/UrbanContext/HistoricalEvolution.php |title=Historical Evolution |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some reconstruction works were carried in 1979 on the citadel's southern gate and the ''[[Turkish bath|hammam]]''. In 2007, the remaining 840 families were evicted from the citadel as part of a large project to restore and preserve the historic character of the citadel. These families were offered financial compensation. One family was allowed to continue living on the citadel to ensure that there would be no break in the possible 8,000 years of continuous habitation of the site, and the government plans to have 50 families live in the citadel once it is renovated.&lt;ref name=hamad&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.niqash.org/content.php?contentTypeID=74&amp;id=2635&amp;lang=0|author=Qassim Khidhir Hamad |title=The pride of erbil needs urgent care |publisher=www.niqash.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the [[Kurdish Textile Museum]] opened its doors in a renovated mansion in the southeast quarter of the citadel.&lt;ref name&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=7133379#7140666|author=Ivan Watson |title=Kurds Displaced in Effort to Preserve Ancient City |publisher=www.npr.org |accessdate=19 October 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Architecture and layout==
[[File:Center of Hewler Castle.jpg|thumb|Houses on top of the citadel with the main north–south thoroughfare in the centre|alt=Photograph]]
The citadel is situated on a large tell – or settlement mound – of roughly oval shape that is between {{convert|25|and|32|m}} high. The area on top of the mound measures {{convert|430|x|340|m}} and is {{convert|102000|m2}} large. Natural soil has been found at a depth of {{convert|36|m}} below the present surface of the mound.&lt;ref name=novacek262&gt;{{harvnb|Nováček|Chabr|Filipský|Janiček|2008|p=262}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[slope|angle]] of the citadel mound's slopes is ''c''. 45°.&lt;ref name=NavalIntelligenceDivision529/&gt; Three ramps, located on the northern, eastern and southern slopes of the mound, lead up to gates in the outer ring of houses. The southern gate was the oldest and was rebuilt at least once, in 1860, and demolished in 1960. The current gate house was constructed in 1979. The eastern gate is called the Harem Gate and was used by women. It seems unclear when the northern gate was opened. One source claims that it was opened in 1924,&lt;ref name=history/&gt; while another observes that there were only two gates in 1944 – the southern and eastern gates.&lt;ref name=NavalIntelligenceDivision529/&gt;

During the early 20th century, there were three [[mosque]]s, two schools, two ''takyas'' and a hammam on the citadel.&lt;ref name=mahallas&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/Demography/Mahallas.php |title=Mahallas |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The citadel also housed a [[synagogue]] until 1957.&lt;ref name=novacek262/&gt; The only religious structure that currently survives is the [[Mulla Effendi|Mulla Afandi]] Mosque, which was rebuilt on the location of an earlier 19th-century mosque.&lt;ref name=mosque&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/ArchitecturalHeritage/TheMosque.php |title=The Mosque |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The hammam was built in 1775 by Qassim Agha Abdullah. It went out of service during the 1970s and was renovated in 1979, although many original architectural details were lost.&lt;ref name=novacek262/&gt;&lt;ref name=hammam&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/ArchitecturalHeritage/TheHammam.php |title=The Hammam |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

When it was still occupied, the citadel was divided in three districts or ''[[mahalla]]s'': from east to west the Serai, the Takya and the Topkhana. The Serai was occupied by notable families; the Takya district was named after the homes of [[dervish]]es, which are called ''takyas''; and the Topkhana district housed craftsmen and farmers. An inventory made in 1920 shows that at time the citadel was divided in 506 house plots. Since that time, the number of houses and inhabitants has gradually declined. For example, in 1984, 4,466 people lived in 375 houses whereas a 1995 census showed that the citadel had only 1,631 inhabitants living in 247 houses.&lt;ref name=mahallas/&gt; Until the opening-up of the main north–south thoroughfare, the streets on the citadel mound radiated outward from the southern gate like the branches of a tree. Streets were between {{convert|1|and|2.5|m}} wide and ranged in length from {{convert|300|m}} for major alleyways to {{convert|30|–|50|m}} for [[cul-de-sac]]s.&lt;ref name=alleyways&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/UrbanContext/Alleyways.php |title=Alleyways |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The perimeter wall of the citadel is not a continuous fortification wall, but consists of the façades of approximately 100 houses that have been built against each other. Because they have been built on or near the steep slope of the citadel mound, many of these façades were strengthened by [[buttress]]es to prevent their collapse or [[subsidence]].&lt;ref name=perimeterwall&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/UrbanContext/PerimeterWall.php |title=Perimeter Wall |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There were circa 30 city-palaces; most of them located along the perimeter of the citadel.&lt;ref name=houses&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/ArchitecturalHeritage/Houses.php?page=1 |title=Houses |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest surviving house that can be securely dated through an inscription was built in 1893. The oldest houses can be found on the southeastern side of the mound, whereas houses on the northern perimeter date to the 1930s–1940s.&lt;ref name=architecturalheritage&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/ArchitecturalHeritage/index1.php |title=ARCHITECTURAL HERITAGE 01 |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=urbangrowth&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/UrbanContext/UrbanGrowth.php?page=1 |title=Urban Growth |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the introduction of modern building techniques, most houses on the citadel were built around a courtyard. A raised [[Arcade (architecture)|arcade]] overlooking the courtyard, a flat roof and a bent-access entrance to prevent views of the courtyard and the interior of the house were characteristic elements of the houses on the citadel.&lt;ref name=houses/&gt;

==Research and restoration==
[[File:Citadel of Hewlêr (Erbil), Iraqi Kurdistan.jpg|thumb|Restored house façades along the southern perimeter of the citadel|alt=Photograph of houses]]
In 2006 and 2007, a team from the [[University of West Bohemia]], together with [[Salahaddin University]] in Arbil, carried out an extensive survey and evaluation of the entire citadel. As part of this project, [[Geodesy|geodetic]] measurements of the citadel were taken and these were combined with [[satellite imagery]], regular photographic imagery and [[Aerial photography|aerial photographs]] to create a map and digital 3D model of the citadel mound and the houses on top of it. [[Geophysical survey|Geophysical prospection]] was carried out in some areas of the citadel to detect traces of older architecture buried under the present houses. Archaeological investigations included an [[Archaeological field survey|archaeological survey]] on the western slope of the citadel mound, and the [[Excavation (archaeology)|excavation]] of a small test trench in the eastern part of the citadel.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nováček|Chabr|Filipský|Janiček|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Neo-Assyrian [[chamber tomb]] was found at the foot of the citadel mound during construction activities in 2009. It was subsequently excavated by the local Antiquities Service and archaeologists from the [[German Archaeological Institute]] (''DAI''). The tomb was plundered in antiquity but still contained pottery dating to the 8th and 7th centuries BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kehrer|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cooperation between the Antiquities Service and the DAI was continued later that year with a further investigation of the tomb and with a small excavation nearby and geophysical survey of the surrounding area, in which also students from Salahaddin University participated. These investigations revealed the presence of architecture probably dating to the Neo-Assyrian period, as well as more burials belonging to subsequent centuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kehrer|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Arbil Citadel.jpg|thumb|Entrance of Erbil citadel (Front view)]]
In 2007, the [[Kurdistan Regional Government]] (KRG) established the High Commission for Erbil Citadel Revitalization (HCECR) to preserve and restore the citadel with the help of [[UNESCO]].&lt;ref name=unesco/&gt; Among other things, the HCECR advocates the establishment of a zone extending up to {{convert|300|–|400|m}} from the citadel in which building height should be restricted to approximately {{convert|10|m}}. This would ensure the visual dominance of the citadel over its surroundings.&lt;ref name=thecitadel&amp;thecity&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.erbilcitadel.org/TheCitadel&amp;TheCity/ |title=The Citadel &amp; The City |publisher=www.erbilcitadel.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 January 2010, the HCECR and the Iraqi State Board for Antiquities and Heritage (SBAH) submitted the Citadel of Erbil to the Iraqi [[World Heritage Site#Nominating process|Tentative List]] of sites that are considered for nomination as [[World Heritage Site]]. The submission states that &quot;The Citadel is today one of the most dramatic and visually exciting cultural sites not only in the Middle East but also in the world.&quot;&lt;ref name=unesco/&gt; Two further agreements between the HCECR and UNESCO were signed in March 2010, and it was disclosed that [[Erbil Governorate|Arbil Governorate]] will finance the restoration project with US$13&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;unesco office for iraq&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.unesco.org/en/iraq-office/single-view/news/unesco_and_the_kurdistan_regional_government_partner_to_restore_one_of_the_oldest_continually_inhabi/back/9623/cHash/caad0997a8/ |title=UNESCO and the Kurdistan Regional Government partner to restore one of the oldest continually-inhabited sites of the World|publisher=www.unesco.org |accessdate=30 August 2010 }} {{Dead link|date=April 2012|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first restoration works were carried out in June 2010.&lt;ref name=mcdermid&gt;{{harvnb|McDermid|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Citadel was inscribed on the World Heritage List on 21 June 2014.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}
;Sources
*{{Citation |last1=Cahen |first1=Cl. |editor1-first=P. |editor1-last=Bearman |editor2-first=Th. |editor2-last=Bianquis |editor3-first=C.E. |editor3-last=Bosworth |editor4-first=E. |editor4-last=van Donzel |editor5-first=W.P. |editor5-last=Heinrichs |editor3-link=Clifford Edmund Bosworth |title=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]]|edition=second|year=2010 |publisher=Brill Online |chapter=Begteginids |oclc=624382576 }}
*{{Citation |last1=Eidem |first1=Jesper |year=1985 |title=News from the eastern front: the evidence from Tell Shemshāra |journal=Iraq |volume=47 |pages=83–107 |jstor=4200234 |issn=0021-0889 }}
*{{Citation|url=http://www.dainst.org/index.php?id=852800d5bb1f14a199870017f0000011 |title=Deutsche Experten untersuchen assyrische Grabstätte in Arbil |last1=Kehrer |first1=Nicole |year=2009 |work=Deutsches Archäologisches Institut |publisher= |language=German |accessdate=8 July 2010}}
*{{Citation|url=http://www.dainst.org/index.php?id=ca357fcfc99014b46043001c3253dc21 |title=Deutsche Archäologen arbeiten wieder im Irak |last1=Kehrer |first1=Nicole |year=2010 |work=Deutsches Archäologisches Institut |publisher= |language=German |accessdate=8 July 2010}}
*{{Citation |url=http://www.time.com/time/travel/article/0,31542,2007282,00.html |title=A Facelift for an Ancient Kurdish Citadel
 |last=McDermid |first=Charles |work=Time |publisher=Time |accessdate=2 August 2010 | date=29 July 2010}}
*{{Citation|title=Iraq after the Muslim conquest |last=Morony |first=Michael G. |year=1984 |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton |isbn=978-0-691-05395-0 }}
*{{Citation |title=Iraq and the Persian Gulf |last=Naval Intelligence Division |series=Geographical Handbook Series |year=1944 |publisher= |location= |oclc=1077604 |isbn= |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}
*{{Citation |last1=Nováček |first1=Karel |last2=Chabr |first2=Tomáš |last3=Filipský |first3=David |last4=Janiček |first4=Libor |last5=Pavelka |first5=Karel |last6=Šída |first6=Petr |last7=Trefný |first7=Martin |last8=Vařeka |first8=Pavel |year=2008 |title=Research of the Arbil Citadel, Iraqi Kurdistan, First Season |journal=Památky Archeologické |volume=99 |pages=259–302 |url=http://www.kar.zcu.cz/ovp/data/blob.php?table=internet_list&amp;name=FileName&amp;type=FileType&amp;file=Data&amp;id=IDInternet&amp;idname=200 |issn=0031-0506 |accessdate=13 July 2010}}
*{{Citation |last1=Sourdel |first1=D. |editor1-first=P. |editor1-last=Bearman |editor2-first=Th. |editor2-last=Bianquis |editor3-first=C.E. |editor3-last=Bosworth |editor4-first=E. |editor4-last=van Donzel |editor5-first=W.P. |editor5-last=Heinrichs |editor3-link=Clifford Edmund Bosworth |title=Encyclopaedia of Islam|edition=second|year=2010 |publisher=Brill Online |chapter=Irbil |oclc=624382576 }}
*{{Citation |last1=Villard |first1=Pierre |editor1-first=Francis |editor1-last=Joannès |title=Dictionnaire de la civilisation mésopotamienne |series=Bouquins |year=2001 |publisher=Robert Laffont |location=Paris |language=French |isbn=978-2-221-09207-1 |pages=68–69 |chapter=Arbèles }}
*{{Citation|last1=Woods |first1=John E. |year=1977 |title=A note on the Mongol capture of Isfahān |journal=Journal of Near Eastern Studies |publisher= |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=49–51 |jstor=544126 |issn=0022-2968 |doi=10.1086/372531}}
* [[Rene Grousset|Grousset, Rene]], ''The Empire of the Steppes'', (Translated from the French by Naomi Walford), New Brunswick: [[Rutgers University Press]] (1970)

==External links==
{{Commons category|Citadel of Arbil}}
*[http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1437 Citadel of Arbil on the World Heritage List]
*[http://www.erbilcitadel.org/ High Commission for Erbil Citadel Revitalization (HCECR)]
*[http://lfgm.fsv.cvut.cz/citadel/index.php Citadel Documentation Project]
*[http://www.kar.zcu.cz/ovp/projekt.php?id=24 Research of the citadel at Arbil, Iraqi Kurdistan]
{{Good article}}
{{World Heritage Sites in Iraq}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Citadel Of Arbil}}
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Erbil]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Iraq]]
[[Category:Castles in Iraq]]
[[Category:Tells]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Iraq]]</text>
      <sha1>oxjwepchwm5pr7h151wx16xoyht527m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
