<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Confederate Memorial (Romney, West Virginia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1937089</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741449146</id>
      <parentid>741412514</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-27T15:37:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Corinne</username>
        <id>17447580</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removed period/full stop from captions that are not sentences.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27313">{{Other places3|Confederate monuments}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military memorial
| name =Confederate Memorial
| body = Confederate Memorial Association&lt;br&gt;[[Hampshire County, West Virginia|Hampshire County]], [[West Virginia]]
| image = [[File:Confederate Memorial Romney WV 2010 04 25 01.jpg|250px|Confederate Memorial]]
| caption = The Confederate Memorial in 2010
| commemorates = the men of Hampshire County who died fighting for the [[Confederate States of America]] in the [[American Civil War]].
| use_dates = 
| coordinates = {{coord|39.34267|-78.76547|format=dms|display=inline|type:landmark}}
| location = [[Indian Mound Cemetery]]&lt;br&gt;[[Romney, West Virginia|Romney]], [[West Virginia]], [[United States]]
| nearest_town = 
| designer = Gaddes Brothers of [[Baltimore]], [[Maryland]]
| inscription = &quot;The Daughters of Old Hampshire Erect This Tribute of Affection to Her Heroic Sons Who Fell in Defence of Southern Rights.&quot;
| established = 
| unveiled = {{Start date and years ago|1867|09|26}}
| total =
| unknowns =
| commemorated =
| by_country = 
| by_war = 
| source =
}}

The '''Confederate Memorial''' (also referred to as the '''First Confederate Memorial''') at [[Indian Mound Cemetery]] in [[Romney, West Virginia]], commemorates residents of [[Hampshire County, West Virginia|Hampshire County]] who died during the [[American Civil War]] while fighting for the [[Confederate States of America]]. It was sponsored by the Confederate Memorial Association, which formally dedicated the monument on September 26, 1867. The town of Romney has claimed that this is the first [[memorial]] structure erected to memorialize the Confederate dead in the [[United States]] and that the town performed the nation's first public decoration of Confederate graves on June 1, 1866.

The idea to memorialize the Confederate war dead of Hampshire County was first discussed in the spring of 1866. Following the decoration of the graves that summer, the Confederate Memorial Association engaged in fundraising for construction of the memorial, and by 1867 the necessary funds were raised. The inscription &quot;The Daughters of Old Hampshire Erect This Tribute of Affection to Her Heroic Sons Who Fell in Defence of Southern Rights&quot; was selected, and the contract for the memorial's construction was awarded to the Gaddes Brothers firm of [[Baltimore]]. The memorial's components were delivered to Indian Mound Cemetery on September&amp;nbsp;14, 1867, and the memorial was dedicated on September 26 of that year. The construction of the Confederate Memorial marked the beginning of an era of post-war revitalization for Hampshire County following the American Civil War.

The Confederate Memorial is in the form of an [[obelisk]], and it stands on a raised mound. The list of 125 names engraved on the monument includes four captains, seven lieutenants (one of which was a chaplain), three sergeants, and 119 privates. The memorial underwent a restoration in 1984, and is decorated annually with a handmade [[evergreen]] [[garland]] and [[wreath]] on Hampshire County Confederate Memorial Day.

== Confederate Memorial Association ==
{{Double image|right|Colonel Robert White.jpg|124|Captain C. S. White.jpg|127|[[Robert White (attorney general)|Robert White]] ''(pictured left)'' and his brother [[Christian Streit White]] ''(pictured right)'' were among the first residents of [[Romney, West Virginia|Romney]] to conceive of the idea for a Confederate memorial.}}
The idea to memorialize the men of [[Hampshire County, West Virginia|Hampshire County]] who had died fighting in the [[Military of the Confederate States of America]] during the [[American Civil War]] was first discussed at a meeting in early spring of 1866 at the [[Romney, West Virginia|Romney]] residence of former Confederate Colonel [[Robert White (attorney general)|Robert White]]. In addition to White, those present at the meeting included his brother [[Christian Streit White]], his future sister-in-law Elizabeth &quot;Bessie&quot; Jane Schultze, and his sister Frances Ann White, who later married [[Samuel Lightfoot Flournoy]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Maxwell|Swisher|1897|p=692.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the meeting, the concept gained support among other residents of Romney.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;/&gt; Later in the spring of 1866, a group of Hampshire County women held a public meeting to organize the Confederate Memorial Association with the mission of honoring the men who had died fighting for the Confederacy and providing financial aid to their families.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Munske|Kerns|2004|p=137.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Federal Writers' Project|1937|p=65.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | url = http://www.historichampshire.org/civilwar/confed.htm | title =The Confederate Memorial in Indian Mound Cemetery, Romney, W. Va. and The Confederate Memorial Association | work = HistoricHampshire.org | publisher = HistoricHampshire.org, Charles C. Hall | accessdate = October 6, 2015 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151006115036/http://www.historichampshire.org/civilwar/confed.htm | archive-date = October 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; At this meeting, the association appointed officers, adopted a constitution, and organized committees to arrange for the decoration of Confederate interments.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;/&gt;{{efn|name=officers}} 

The people of Hampshire County had been overwhelmingly pro-Confederate during the American Civil War, but the county now lay within [[Union (American Civil War)|Unionist]] [[West Virginia]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Munske|Kerns|2004|p=136.}}&lt;/ref&gt; West Virginia's first [[State constitution (United States)|state constitution]] [[Disfranchisement|disenfranchised]] Confederate veterans and partisans and forbade them from holding elected office. In spite of these impediments and risking the ire of Unionist authorities, members of the Confederate Memorial Association and their families marched through Romney to [[Indian Mound Cemetery]] and formally decorated the [[gravestone]]s at the [[burial|interment]] sites of Confederate dead on June&amp;nbsp;1, 1866.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brannon|1976|p=13.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Few Hampshire County residents participated in this first decoration of the Confederate graves, fearing reproach from Federal authorities; some who had pledged to take part in the decoration later refused to do so for the same reason.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Maxwell|Swisher|1897|p=693.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Indian Mound Cemetery Romney WV 2010 04 25 04.JPG|right|thumb|upright|The Confederate Memorial ''(pictured center right)'' is located atop a small mound in [[Indian Mound Cemetery]] just inside the cemetery's entrance.|alt=An image of the memorial located atop a small mound in a cemetery]]
This adornment in Indian Mound Cemetery has been called the first such public decoration of Confederate burials, but the claim is disputed by other towns in the [[Southern United States]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brannon|1976|p=14.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Romney's decoration contributed to a precedent that spread throughout the South during the [[Reconstruction Era]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt; Relatives and loved ones of the Union dead buried in Indian Mound Cemetery also began to follow this precedent by decorating the cemetery's Union headstones.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt;

== Fundraising ==
Following the first decoration of the graves in 1866, momentum built for the erection of a permanent [[monument]] to the Confederate dead at Indian Mound Cemetery.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt; The Confederate Memorial Association engaged in fundraising for construction of the memorial, including [[sewing circle]]s, bazaars, and [[fair]]s.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Federal Writers' Project|1937|p=13.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Confederate veterans and others in Hampshire County undertook additional fundraising efforts, including [[entertainment]] shows and general [[solicitation]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt; In addition to raising funds for the construction of the memorial, the Confederate Memorial Association also raised money for the widows and children of the Confederate dead.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt; By October&amp;nbsp;15, 1866, the [[Gross (economics)|gross]] receipts returned to the association's treasury amounted to $1,170.91 [[United States dollar|USD]], of which the Confederate Memorial Association provided $421.58 USD to the Confederate widows and orphaned children. Fundraising continued until June 1867.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt;

== Design selection  ==
[[File:Confederate Memorial Romney WV 2005 08 21 02.jpg|left|thumb|upright|The main inscription ''(pictured)'' etched into the façade of the Confederate Memorial|alt=An image of the inscription etched into the façade of the memorial]]
By June 6, 1867, the Confederate Memorial Association had raised the necessary funds and proceeded to select the design, inviting and considering the opinions of Confederate veterans and others across Hampshire County.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt;

In July 1867, a committee of the Confederate Memorial Association narrowed the numerous proposals it had received for the memorial's inscription to three finalists.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt; The first inscription finalist said the Confederate soldiers &quot;died in defense of what they believed to be right&quot;, the second said they were &quot;our sons and brothers, who fell as soldiers in the Confederate army&quot;, and the third, which was ultimately adopted by the committee, read in full: &quot;The Daughters of Old Hampshire Erect This Tribute of Affection to Her Heroic Sons Who Fell in Defence of Southern Rights&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Chambers1&quot;/&gt;

== Construction ==
Once the design and inscription had been chosen, the association appointed committees to select a contractor.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt; At the end of the process, the contract was awarded to the Gaddes Brothers firm of [[Baltimore]]. They were asked to fabricate a white Italian [[marble]] monument.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Chambers1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Chambers|2004|p=510.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The memorial was designed, sculpted, and manufactured at a cost of $1,133.63 USD.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt; According to [[United Daughters of the Confederacy]] historian Mary Bell Foote, the words &quot;Southern Rights&quot; were initially omitted from the end of the memorial's inscription during its fabrication due to the &quot;bitter feelings at the time&quot; following the American Civil War, and Federal statutes banning such monuments. After the memorial's components were packaged for shipping to Romney, the words &quot;Southern Rights&quot; were secretly [[Etching|etched]] into the white marble and the components quickly boarded over and shipped.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt;

The memorial's components were delivered to Indian Mound Cemetery on September&amp;nbsp;14, 1867, and it was erected at its present location by a group of Romney volunteers. Bob Fisher was paid $5.00 USD for raising the earthen mound around the monument's location and $4.11 USD for providing lodging to one of the Gaddes brothers at his residence.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP1&quot;/&gt; William Sheetz was paid $18.80 USD for building the memorial's raised mound and supporting foundation.&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt; Twelve days later on September&amp;nbsp;26, the Confederate Memorial was formally dedicated in a public ceremony.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt;{{efn|name=special}}

== Location and design ==
[[File:Confederate Memorial Romney WV 2014 03 16 09.jpg|thumb|right|upright|A [[Relief|high relief]] on the monument's top block represents either Fame or an angel placing a [[laurel wreath]] upon the head of a dying soldier clasping his sword.|alt=An image of a relief on the monument's top block representing either Fame or an angel placing a laurel wreath upon the head of a dying soldier clasping his sword]]
The Confederate Memorial stands upon a raised mound ringed by five [[Buxus|boxwoods]] within the original section of Indian Mound Cemetery, not far from the cemetery's entrance.&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP1&quot;/&gt; Several family interment plots surround the memorial and its circular raised lawn. A burial ground where Confederate and Union dead were buried during the American Civil War lies adjacent to the memorial.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske3&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Munske|Kerns|2004|p=138.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Confederate Memorial is in the form of an [[obelisk]], measuring {{convert|4|sqft|m2|lk=in|sigfig=2}} at its base and {{convert|12|ft|m}} in [[height]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Riley1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Riley|1906|pp=17–18.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The structure's [[pedestal]] consists of two major stylized blocks of white marble, topped by a sculpture of a cloth draped [[urn]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Chambers1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Riley1&quot;/&gt; Carved into the façade of the smaller top block of the memorial is a [[Relief|high relief]] that represents either Fame or an angel placing a [[laurel wreath]] upon the head of a dying soldier clasping his sword.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Riley1&quot;/&gt; Below, on the façade of the larger block, is the inscription: &quot;The Daughters of Old Hampshire Erect This Tribute of Affection to Her Heroic Sons Who Fell in Defence of Southern Rights.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Chambers1&quot;/&gt; The other three sides of the memorial contain the engraved names of 125 Hampshire County men who died for the Confederate cause.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP1&quot;/&gt; A number representing the total fallen Confederates was not included in the memorial as it was not precisely known at the time of the monument's construction.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt; The memorial's [[Foundation (engineering)|foundation]] block bears the date of its erection, &quot;1867&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Riley1&quot;/&gt;

=== Inscribed names ===
The list of 125 names engraved on the monument consists of four captains, seven lieutenants (one of which was a [[chaplain]]), three sergeants, and 119 privates.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Riley1&quot;/&gt; Since the memorial's erection in 1867, several names of Hampshire County's Confederate dead were found to have been omitted from the memorial.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP3&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Federal Writers' Project|1937|p=66.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon3&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brannon|1976|pp=14–15.}}&lt;/ref&gt; These names have been included in the &quot;Confederate Honor Roll&quot; along with those names etched in the memorial and the names of Confederate veterans.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon4&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brannon|1976|p=15.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each of these names is recited during the annual ceremony held on Hampshire County Confederate Memorial Day.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon4&quot;/&gt; The following is the list of Confederate dead etched into the Confederate Memorial:&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell3&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Maxwell|Swisher|1897|p=694.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Military rank !! Inscribed names 
|-
| '''Captains''' || G. F. Sheetz, A. Smith, G. W. Stump, J. M. Lovett
|-
| '''Lieutenants''' || M. Blue, J. Buzzard, J. Earsom, H. Engle, W. F. Johnson, J. N. Moorehead, F. D. Sherrard, Rev. J. S. Reese
|-
|'''Sergeants''' || B. W. Armstrong, J. C. Leps, G. Cheshire
|-
|'''Privates''' || A. T. Pugh, J. W. Park, S. Park, J. W. Poland, J. Peer, R. J. Parran, C. Parran, H. Powell, N. Pownall, J. W. Ream, G. W. Ruckman, L. Spaid, P. Stump, H. Senoff, A. Shingleton, J. Stewart, S. Swisher, E. Gaylor, M. Taylor, J. Taylor, E. P. Ward, I. Wolfe, J. Washington, M. Watkins, H. Wilson, G. Shoemaker, L. D. Shanholtzer, J. Strother, W. Unglesbee, B. Wills, J. Haines, J. F. Hass, M. Harmison, A. Hollenback, G. Hott, E. Hartley, B. Hare, –. Householder, M. V. Inskeep, J. Johnson, J. H. Johnson, T. Keely, J. Kern, S. Loy, E. Milleson, O. Milleson, S. Mohler, F. M. Myers, J. W. Marker, T. McGraw, I. Mills, J. Merritt, J. W. Pugh, O. V. Pugh, J. Kump, P. Noland, J. Rudolph, J. M. Reese, M. V. Reid, W. O. Lupton, J. Noreland, J. Starns, F. C. Sechrist, G. W. Strother, J. D. Adams, I. P. Armstrong, E. Allen, J. W. Baker, H. Baker, J. W. Barley, H. Bird, W. J. Blue, T. T. Brooks, R. Brown, J. W. Boro, I. D. Carroll, J. Cupp, J. S. Davis, J. A. Daily, J. Davy, S. Engly, J. Floury, J. Furlow, I. V. Gibson, R. C. Grace, T. T. Gross, R. Gill, J. P. Greitzner, A. Haines, J. J. Arnold, F. Abee, A. J. Baker, William Baker, J. Bumgarner, Morgan Brill, Mat Brill, G. Delaplains, J. Doughett, J. Engle, C. Garvin, G. R. Garvin, J. Hammock, T. Harrison
|}

== Restoration ==
In 1984, the Confederate Memorial underwent an extensive [[Architectural conservation|restoration]]. The monument had darkened due to [[weathering]]. The surfaces of the memorial were [[sanding|sanded]] and sealed for future protection. This restoration effort was funded through charitable contributions. The names of the contributors were inscribed within the same treasurer's book used to record the memorial's inaugural contributions on June&amp;nbsp;6, 1866. The monument's restoration cost totaled $2,850 USD.&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske3&quot;/&gt;

== Hampshire County Confederate Memorial Day ==
[[File:Indian Mound Cemetery Romney WV 2015 06 08 34.JPG|left|upright|thumb|Headstones ''(pictured)'' at the [[burial|interment]] sites of Confederate war dead in [[Indian Mound Cemetery]], adjacent to the Confederate Memorial|alt=Headstones for Confederate war dead in the cemetery]]
The tradition of decorating the Confederate graves in Indian Mound Cemetery has continued annually since June&amp;nbsp;1, 1866, and occurs on the first Saturday in June, which is known as Hampshire County Confederate Memorial Day or June Decoration Day.&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt; On this day, participants in the ceremony march down Main Street ([[U.S. Route 50 in West Virginia|U.S. Route 50]]) through Romney with [[American Civil War reenactment|American Civil War reenactors]] carrying [[Flags of the Confederate States of America|Confederate flags]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt; A handmade [[evergreen]] [[garland]] measuring {{convert|30|ft|m}} in length is suspended from the Confederate Memorial, along with evergreen [[wreaths]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt; Flowers and Confederate flags are also placed at each of the Confederate headstones.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske3&quot;/&gt; The decorations are usually placed at the memorial and upon the Confederate gravestones by reenactors.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt; Invited speakers address participants.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske3&quot;/&gt; A [[memorial|roll of honor]] is recited at the memorial, followed by a [[musket]] salute.&lt;ref name = &quot;HH1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske2&quot;/&gt; Ceremony participants include descendants of the founding members of the Confederate Memorial Association.&lt;ref name = &quot;Munske1&quot;/&gt;

== Significance ==
[[File:Confederate Memorial Romney WV 2015 06 08 01.jpg|The Confederate Memorial decorated for Confederate Memorial Day in 2015|alt=An image of the Confederate Memorial festooned with an evergreen garland for Confederate Memorial Day in 2015|upright|right|thumb]]
The construction of the Confederate Memorial marked the beginning of an era of post-war revitalization for Hampshire County following the American Civil War. The memorial became a symbol of the county's restored confidence. The citizens of Hampshire County worked together to reestablish and rebuild the institutions, municipal buildings, and businesses destroyed during the war.&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Brannon4&quot;/&gt; The Confederate Memorial Association that constructed the monument was a part of a larger movement throughout the post-war American South, especially in Virginia, which sought to provide suitable interments for Confederate war dead. Historian Caroline E. Janney averred that these &quot;Ladies' Memorial Associations&quot; used &quot;gender in the interest of Confederate politics&quot;, which laid the groundwork for the establishment of the [[Lost Cause of the Confederacy]] belief.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ayers1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ayers|Gallagher|Torget|2008|p=166.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The memorial is among the first monuments erected to memorialize the Confederate dead in the [[United States]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Maxwell1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;FWP1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;TSJ1&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper  |last=  Pisciotta | first = Marla  |title=Yearlong Birthday Celebration Planned in Romney | url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P3-2475126471.html |location=[[Charleston, West Virginia]] |newspaper=[[State Journal|The State Journal]] |date=September 2, 2011 |accessdate=October 6, 2015 | via=[[HighBeam Research]] | subscription=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Romney's claim to have the first Confederate Memorial is disputed by [[Cheraw, South Carolina]], as its monument was dedicated two months prior on July&amp;nbsp;26, 1867.&lt;ref name = &quot;Johnson1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Johnson|2009|pp=36–38.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Johnson2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Johnson|2009|p=144.}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Cheraw memorial omits the mention of &quot;Confederacy&quot;, &quot;Confederate&quot;, or &quot;Southern&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Johnson1&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
*[[List of historic sites in Hampshire County, West Virginia]]
*[[Romney, West Virginia during the American Civil War]]
*[[West Virginia in the American Civil War]]

== References ==
'''Explanatory notes'''

{{notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = officers
| {{harvnb|Maxwell|Swisher|1897|p=694}}. In their ''History of Hampshire County, West Virginia'' (1897), historians [[Hu Maxwell]] and [[Howard Llewellyn Swisher]] gathered from the Confederate Memorial Association's [[Minutes|minute book]] the officers of the association: &quot;Presidents: Mrs. Robert White, Mrs. Abraham Smith, Mrs. J. P. Wilson, Mrs. J. L. Vance, Mrs. [Garrett Williams] Parsons [(Mary Avery Covell Parsons)]. Vice-Presidents: Mrs. Margaret V. Taylor, Miss Miranda Taylor, Mrs. C. E. Blue, Mrs. C. S, White, Mrs. J. L. Vance, Mrs. John J. Inskeep. Secretaries: Misses Bessie J. Schultze [later Mrs. C. S, White], Tillie Kern, Mary V. Foote, Ellen Kane, Mary Heiskell, Lou McCarty. Treasurers: Mrs. J. D. Armstrong, Mrs. Michael Blue, Miss Virginia Parsons, Mrs. Julius Waddle.&quot;
}}

{{efn
| name = special
| {{harvnb|Maxwell|Swisher|1897|p=695}}. At the end of their chapter &quot;Closing Events of the War&quot; in ''History of Hampshire County, West Virginia'', Maxwell and Swisher give special recognition to the following individuals for their efforts in funding and erecting the Confederate Memorial, although their specific roles are not given: &quot;Mrs. James D. Armstrong, Mrs. James N. Morehead, Misses Susie M. Pancake, Susie Poling, Louise Greitzner, Lizzie Inskeep, Lieutenant C. W. Pattie, D. W. Endler.&quot;
}}

}}

'''Citations'''

{{reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography == 
*{{cite book | editor-last1=Ayers | editor-first1=Edward L. | editor-last2 = Gallagher | editor-first2 = Gary W. | editor-last3= Torget | editor-first3 = Andrew J. | coauthors= | author-link =  | year= 2008 | title=Crucible of the Civil War: Virginia from Secession to Commemoration | publisher= [[University of Virginia Press]] | location = [[Charlottesville, Virginia]] and London | isbn= 978-0-8139-3049-7 | OCLC = 5792807413 |  url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eMjlRM5MbFkC | accessdate=|ref=harv | via = [[Google Books]] }}
*{{cite book | last=Brannon | first=Selden W. | coauthors= | author-link =  | year=1976 | title=Historic Hampshire: A Symposium of Hampshire County and Its People, Past and Present | publisher= [[McClain Printing Company]] | location = [[Parsons, West Virginia]] | isbn= 978-0-87012-236-1 | OCLC = 3121468 |  url= | accessdate=|ref=harv }}
*{{cite book | last=Chambers | first=S. Allen | coauthors= | author-link =  | year=2004 | title=Buildings of West Virginia | publisher= [[Oxford University Press]] | location = Oxford, New York City | isbn= 978-0-19-516548-7 | OCLC = 53315276 |  url= | accessdate=|ref=harv }}
*{{cite book  | author=Federal Writers' Project |authorlink=Federal Writers' Project| coauthors= | author-link =  | year=1937 | title=Historic Romney 1762–1937 | publisher= [[Federal Writers' Project]], The Town Council of Romney, West Virginia | location = [[Romney, West Virginia]] | isbn=  |  OCLC = 2006735 | url= | accessdate=|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book | last=Johnson | first=Kristina Dunn | coauthors= | author-link =  | year=2009 | title=No Holier Spot of Ground: Confederate Monuments &amp; Cemeteries of South Carolina | publisher= The History Press | location = [[Charleston, South Carolina]] | isbn= 978-1-59629-397-7 | OCLC = 301948612 |  url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6Z77XGT4gRgC | accessdate=|ref=harv | via = [[Google Books]] }}
*{{cite book |title=History of Hampshire County, West Virginia From Its Earliest Settlement to the Present |last1=Maxwell |first1=Hu  |authorlink1=Hu Maxwell | last2= Swisher | first2 = Howard Llewellyn | authorlink2 = Howard Llewellyn Swisher | year= 1897 | editor= | publisher=A. Brown Boughner, Printer |location=[[Morgantown, West Virginia]] |isbn= | OCLC = 680931891 |page= |pages= |url=https://openlibrary.org/books/OL23304577M/History_of_Hampshire_County_West_Virginia |accessdate= |ref=harv | via = [[Internet Archive]] }}
*{{cite book| editor-last1=Munske| editor-first1=Roberta R.| editor-last2 = Kerns | editor-first2 = Wilmer L. | year=2004| language =  | title=Hampshire County, West Virginia, 1754–2004| publisher=The Hampshire County 250th Anniversary Committee| location = [[Romney, West Virginia]] |  isbn=978-0-9715738-2-6 | OCLC = 55983178 | url= |ref=harv |accessdate= }}
*{{Cite journal| last =Riley  | first =Elihu S.  | author-link =| title =The First Confederate Monument | journal = Book of the Royal Blue | publication-place = Baltimore | volume = 10 | issue = | date = December 1906 | publisher =Passenger Department, [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]] | pages =17–18 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=-zQOAQAAIAAJ | access date = |oclc = 8378751 | via = [[Google Books]]}}

== External links ==
*{{Commons category-inline|Confederate Memorial (Romney, West Virginia)}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20151006122432/http://www.historichampshire.org/civilwar/confed.htm HistoricHampshire.org Confederate Memorial website]

{{Hampshire County, West Virginia in the American Civil War}}
{{Portal bar|American Civil War|Architecture|West Virginia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Confederate Memorial, Romney}}
[[Category:1867 establishments in West Virginia]]
[[Category:1867 sculptures]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1867]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Romney, West Virginia]]
[[Category:Confederate States of America monuments and memorials in West Virginia]]
[[Category:Hampshire County, West Virginia in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:Indian Mound Cemetery]]
[[Category:Marble sculptures in the United States]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Hampshire County, West Virginia]]</text>
      <sha1>nvdrvtqe2xespecc4xfe7t9fa328baw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
