<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dalj massacre</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17027743</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748461393</id>
      <parentid>733131862</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-08T08:44:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */clean up; http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and other Google services using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29497">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2014}}
{{Infobox civilian attack
| title=Dalj massacre
| map={{Location_map+| Croatia | width=300| float=center 
| caption = 
| overlay_image =
| places =
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Dalj]] | lat=45.560218 | long=19.011244 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=left}}
}}
|map_caption=Dalj on the map of Croatia
|location= [[Dalj]], [[Croatia]]
|target=Croatian police and [[Croatian National Guard]] [[prisoners of war]], [[Croat]] civilians
|date=1 August 1991
|time=
|timezone=
|type=[[Mass murder]]
|fatalities=56–57
|injuries=
|perps= [[SAO Eastern Slavonia, Baranja and Western Syrmia]] [[Territorial Defense Forces (Yugoslavia)|Territorial Defence Forces]], supported by the [[Yugoslav People's Army]] and the [[Serb Volunteer Guard]] paramilitaries
}}
{{Campaignbox Croatian War of Independence}}
The '''Dalj massacre''' was the killing of 56 or 57 [[Croats]] in [[Dalj]], [[Croatia]] on 1 August 1991, during the [[Croatian War of Independence]]. In addition to civilian victims, the figure includes 20 [[Law enforcement in Croatia|Croatian policemen]], 15 [[Croatian National Guard]] (''Zbor narodne garde'' – ZNG) troops and four [[civil defence]]men who had been defending the police station and water supply building in the village. While some of the policemen and the ZNG troops died in combat, those who surrendered were killed after they became [[prisoners of war]]. They tried to fight off an attack by the [[Croatian Serb]] [[SAO Eastern Slavonia, Baranja and Western Syrmia]] (SAO SBWS) [[Territorial Defense Forces (Yugoslavia)|Territorial Defence Forces]], supported by the [[Yugoslav People's Army]] (''Jugoslovenska Narodna Armija'' – JNA) and the [[Serb Volunteer Guard]] paramilitaries. The SAO SBWS was declared an autonomous territory in eastern Croatia following the [[Battle of Borovo Selo]] just to the south of Dalj.

After the attack, the non-Serb civilian population in the village and the surrounding area was persecuted. They were forced to flee their homes, as they would have been imprisoned, physically abused or killed if they did not. After the war, the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY) charged high-ranking SAO SBWS and Serbian officials, including [[Slobodan Milošević]] and [[Goran Hadžić]], with [[war crime]]s committed in Dalj. The killings were extensively covered by German media leading to forming of a public opinion in support of Croatia. By the end of 1991, Germany adopted support for [[diplomatic recognition]] of Croatia as its policy and duty.

==Background==
{{See also|Log revolution}}
In 1990, following the [[Croatian parliamentary election, 1990|electoral defeat]] of the government of the [[Socialist Republic of Croatia]], ethnic tensions in the republic worsened. The [[Yugoslav People's Army]] (''Jugoslovenska Narodna Armija'' – JNA) confiscated Croatia's [[Territorial Defense Forces (Yugoslavia)|Territorial Defence]] (''Teritorijalna obrana'' – TO) weapons to miminize the possibility of resistance following the elections.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=117}} On 17 August, the tensions escalated into an [[Log Revolution|open revolt]] of the [[Serbs of Croatia|Croatian Serbs]],{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=118}} centred on the predominantly Serb-populated areas of the [[Dalmatia]]n hinterland around Knin,{{sfn|The New York Times|19 August 1990}} parts of the [[Lika]], [[Kordun]], [[Banovina (region)|Banovina]] and [[eastern Croatia]].{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007}} They established a Serbian National Council in July 1990 to coordinate opposition to [[Croatian President]] [[Franjo Tuđman]]'s policy of pursuing [[independence of Croatia|independence for Croatia]]. [[Milan Babić]], a dentist from the southern town of [[Knin]], was elected president. Knin's police chief, [[Milan Martić]], established paramilitary militias. The two men eventually became the political and military leaders of the [[SAO Krajina]], a self-declared state incorporating the Serb-inhabited areas of Croatia.{{sfn|Repe|2009|pp=141–142}} In March 1991, the SAO Krajina authorities backed by the [[Socialist Republic of Serbia|Serbian]] government started to consolidate control over Serb-populated areas of Croatia. The move resulted in a [[Pakrac clash|bloodless skirmish in Pakrac]] and the first fatalities in the [[Plitvice Lakes incident]]. By early May, the conflict also escalated in the region of eastern [[Slavonia]], culminating in the [[Battle of Borovo Selo]], just to the south of the village of [[Dalj]].{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=90}} On 25–26 June, Croatian Serbs in the eastern [[Slavonia]] established the [[SAO Eastern Slavonia, Baranja and Western Syrmia]] (SAO SBWS), declaring it an autonomous political entity.{{sfn|ICTY|21 May 2004}}

In the beginning of 1991, Croatia had no regular army and in an effort to bolster its defence, it doubled the number of [[Law enforcement in Croatia|police personnel]] to about 20,000. The most effective part of the force was the [[Croatian special police order of battle in 1991–95|3,000-strong special police]] deployed in twelve battalions adopting military organisation. In addition there were 9,000–10,000 regionally organised reserve police. The reserve police was set up in 16 battalions and 10 companies, but they lacked weapons.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=86}} By July, the [[Croatian National Guard]] (''Zbor narodne garde'' – ZNG) was established, absorbing a part of the special police force reorganised into four professional brigades,{{sfn|Nazor|2007|p=73}} and police reserve force of 40,000 ZNG troops. The reserve units did not possess sufficient heavy or small arms to arm all of their personnel.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=86}}

==Timeline==
{{Location map+| Osijek Županja Ilok | width=300| float=right |alt= Location map of eastern Slavonia
| caption=Map of eastern Slavonia area between Osijek and Vukovar ([[Counties of Croatia|Modern county]] lines provided for reference)
| overlay_image =
| places =
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Vukovar]] | lat=45.35 | long=19.00 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=bottom}}
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Erdut]] | lat=45.524991 | long=19.06005 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=top}}
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Borovo Selo]] | lat=45.41 | long=18.98 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=left}}
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Dalj]] | lat=45.48 | long=18.99 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=left}}
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Vinkovci]] | lat=45.29 | long=18.80 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=left}}
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Osijek]] | lat=45.55 | long=18.69 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=left}}
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Bogojevo]] | lat=45.531365 | long=19.129916 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=right}}
{{Location map~|Osijek Županja Ilok| label=[[Aljmaš]] | lat=45.5292 | long=18.948299 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=left}}
}}
The general area of the villages of Dalj, [[Erdut]] and [[Aljmaš]] was targeted by an artillery bombardment between 3:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. and 4:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. on 1 August 1991. Croatian sources indicate that the artillery fire was coming from units assigned to the JNA 51st Mechanised Brigade deployed on the left bank of the [[Danube]] River, on the territory of [[Socialist Republic of Serbia|Serbia]], as well as the Croatian Serb TO. The JNA report on the events prepared for Croatian authorities denies that the JNA artillery took part in the bombardment, and indicates a somewhat later time of the initial fighting, placing it at 4:10&amp;nbsp;a.m.{{sfn|Nazor|2011a}} Witness testimony given at the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY) [[trial of Slobodan Milošević]] supports the timeline placing the initial combat at 3:00&amp;nbsp;a.m.{{sfn|ICTY|28 August 2003|pp=25561–25562}}

After the artillery fire ceased, the Croatian Serb TO, supported by the [[Serb Volunteer Guard]] (SVG) led by [[Željko Ražnatović]],{{sfn|Pavlaković|Pauković|Raos|2012|p=362}} began an infantry assault of Dalj, organised in three groups, from its base in [[Borovo Selo]].{{sfn|Nazor|2011a}} One of the groups attacked the police station in Dalj, the second assaulted ZNG positions around water supply building in the village, while the third group remained in reserve.{{sfn|ICTY|29 January 2003|p=15153}} The heaviest fighting took place around the Dalj police station defended by the Croatian police and ZNG personnel. At 6:20&amp;nbsp;a.m., the Croatian police requested assistance from [[Osijek]] police administration and the JNA in terminating the TO attack, citing considerable casualties. The JNA decided to intervene and was ordered to Dalj at 6:50&amp;nbsp;a.m.{{sfn|Nazor|2011a}} The JNA reported receiving gunfire from the ZNG 1st Company of the 1st Battalion of the [[3rd Guards Brigade (Croatia)|3rd Guards Brigade]] in Erdut as it moved towards {{convert|15|km|abbr=off}} of road between [[Bogojevo]] and Dalj and returning fire before proceeding to Dalj.{{sfn|Nazor|2011b}} Conversely, the ICTY witness of the event claimed the JNA fired against civilian homes in Erdut unprovoked.{{sfn|ICTY|28 August 2003|pp=25554–25555}} The JNA units reached the Dalj police station at 9:30&amp;nbsp;a.m.{{sfn|Nazor|2011b}}

JNA and Croatian sources disagree on events immediately following arrival of the JNA in Dalj. While the JNA claimed it requested a cessation of the fire only to be refused by the defenders of the police station,{{sfn|Nazor|2011b}} Croatian sources claim the JNA demanded the unconditional surrender of the police and the ZNG, and were refused by the Croatian force. Both versions agree that the combat resumed until approximately 10&amp;nbsp;a.m.,{{sfn|MUP|2 August 2011}} when three tank main gun rounds, fired by the JNA, hit the police station. While the JNA reported there were no Croatian policemen or ZNG troops captured alive, contradicting its own report stating that the Croatian force located outside the police station accepted cessation of hostilities,{{sfn|Nazor|2011b}} the Croatian sources claim that those who surrendered were killed after their capture. Overall, 39 were killed in the fighting for the police station in Dalj—20 policemen, 15 ZNG troops and four [[civil defence]]men.{{sfn|MUP|2 August 2011}}

The same day, several non-Serb civilians were killed in Dalj.{{sfn|Šakić|Sedlar|Tojčić|1993|p=425}} In a subsequent round of negotiations with Croatian authorities, the SAO SBWS representatives reported 56 or 57 Croats were killed in Dalj on 1 August.{{sfn|Rupić|2007|loc=p. 240, note 207}} Twenty-five bodies of the victims, including two civilians, were transferred to ZNG-held [[Osijek]]. [[Post-mortem]] examinations indicated some of the victims were beaten and then executed.{{sfn|Šakić|Sedlar|Tojčić|1993|p=425}}

==Aftermath==
[[Image:Refugees taken from Aljmas to Osijek via Drava River barges August 1991.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Refugees were evacuated to Osijek by [[Drava]] River barges]]
The Croat population felt intimidated and forced to leave Dalj,{{sfn|ICTY|29 January 2003|p=15155}} as the events of 1 August marked the beginning of a series of attacks against the Croat civilian population in ethnically mixed areas.{{sfn|Libal|1997|p=30}} The bulk of the refugees travelled to Aljmaš, and then were taken by boats and barges along the [[Drava]] River to Osijek.{{sfn|Nova TV|1 August 2013}}{{sfn|Bilić|2011|p=290}} Persecution of the non-Serb population of Dalj and other nearby villages started in the immediate aftermath of the attack. The persecution included beatings, arbitrary arrests and [[war rape]].{{sfn|Jutarnji list|4 September 2013}} The TO units arrested a number of Croat civilians and imprisoned them in Dalj. On 21 September, eleven prisoners were killed by the TO personnel led by Ražnatović, and buried in a [[mass grave]] in the village of [[Ćelije, Croatia|Ćelije]]. A further 28 civilians held in Dalj detention facility were tortured and killed by the TO and Ražnatović on 4 October. The bodies of the victims were then dumped in the Danube River.{{sfn|ICTY|21 May 2004}}{{sfn|The New York Times|16 March 2008}} At least 135 Croat and non-Serb civilians were killed in this region by May 1992.{{sfn|BBC News|29 October 2001}}

After the [[Battle of Vukovar|JNA captured Vukovar]], it transferred a large number of the inhabitants of the city to the detention facility in Dalj on 20 November. The transfer occurred on the basis of a request by [[Goran Hadžić]], political leader of the SAO SBWS. Those suspected of involvement in the fighting were interrogated and tortured, and at least 35 were executed.{{sfn|ICTY|21 May 2004}}

The SAO Krajina was renamed the [[Republic of Serbian Krajina]] (RSK) on 19 December, and the SAO SBWS formally joined the RSK on 26 February 1992. After the merger, Hadžić, who had been appointed president of the SAO SBWS on 25 September 1991, assumed the role of the president of the RSK.{{sfn|ICTY|21 May 2004}} The events of 1 August 1991 were extensively covered by German media at the time, leading to a public outcry over the massacre.{{sfn|Libal|1997|p=30}} Germany subsequently advocated quick recognition of Croatia, as a means to stop further violence. By late 1991, Germany presented its decision to recognize Croatia as its policy and duty, lobbying the [[European Economic Community]] (EEC) diplomats. On 19 December, the German government decided to grant [[diplomatic recognition]] to Croatia as the first EEC member state to do so.{{sfn|Lucarelli|2000|pp=125–129}}

In 2013, the Dalj police station was awarded the [[Order of Nikola Šubić Zrinski]] for heroism. A memorial to the 39 police officers, ZNG troops and civil defencemen killed in Dalj on 1 August 1991 was unveiled at the station on the 22nd anniversary of their death.{{sfn|Večernji list|1 August 2013}} On 26 November 2013, a memorial to the killed civilians was completed in Dalj.{{sfn|HRT|26 November 2013}}

===War crimes charges by the ICTY===
[[Slobodan Milošević]], [[President of Serbia]] in 1991, and Hadžić were charged by the ICTY for war crimes, including ordering of the murder, extermination, [[deportation]] and torture of non-Serbs in Dalj through the paramilitaries.{{sfn|ICTY|21 May 2004}}{{sfn|ICTY|23 October 2002}} Milošević died in 2006, four years after his ICTY trial started, before a verdict was reached.{{sfn|Bieber|2010|p=321}} {{As of|2013|12}} the trial of Hadžić is in progress at the ICTY since 2012, and it is expected to be completed by the end of 2015.{{sfn|Meron|5 December 2013}}

The ICTY also charged [[Jovica Stanišić]], head of the State Security Service run by [[Ministry of Internal Affairs (Serbia)|Serbia's Ministry of Internal Affairs]], and [[Franko Simatović]], head of the [[Special Operations Unit (Serbia)|Special Operations Unit]] of the State Security Service, with war crimes. The charges include complicity in the torture of a group of seven non-Serb civilians, including two arrested in Dalj on 11 November 1991. Five of those arrested were killed by the SVG paramilitaries in Erdut and buried in a mass grave in the village of Ćelije.{{sfn|ICTY|10 July 2008}} Stanišić and Simatović were charged with control and training of the SVG.{{sfn|Sense Agency|29 April 2008}} The trial began in 2008, and resulted in acquittal of the two by the ICTY trial chamber on 30 May 2013.{{sfn|ICTY|30 May 2013}} The ICTY prosecutor appealed the verdict, and the process is pending {{as of|2013|12|lc=y}}.{{sfn|ICTY|25 September 2013}}

In 2010, the commanding officer of the JNA 51st Motorised Brigade, Enes Taso, was charged with war crimes and [[crimes against humanity]] committed in Dalj in August–December 1991. Taso is charged with the deaths of two policemen in the JNA attack on the Dalj police station, nine [[prisoners of war]] captured in Dalj, eleven captured in Vukovar, and 90 non-Serb civilians.{{sfn|Dubrovački vjesnik|14 May 2010}} In May 2012, Croatian authorities in Osijek started a trial of two Croatian Serbs charged with [[war crime]]s against Croatian civilians, including the [[gang rape]] of a 20-year-old woman and forcing her parents and siblings to watch the rape. Both of them were convicted in September 2013 and sentenced to 12 years in prison.{{sfn|Jutarnji list|4 September 2013}} In 2013, the [[Ministry of Veterans' Affairs (Croatia)|Croatian Veterans' Affairs Minister]] stated that Croatian authorities have filed 150 indictments for war crimes committed during the Dalj massacre and war crimes perpetrated in Dalj area during the war.{{sfn|Nova TV|1 August 2013}}

==See also==
* [[Erdut massacre]]
* [[List of massacres in Croatia]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
;Books
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=hr&amp;id=oFXdiS25N78C|editor-first=Sabrina P.|editor-last=Ramet|title=Central and Southeast European Politics Since 1989|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2010|isbn=978-1-139-48750-4|chapter=Bosnia and Herzegovina since 1990|first=Florian|last=Bieber|pages=311–327|location=Cambridge, England}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Pravo na dom|language=Croatian|trans_title=Right to a Home|editor-first1=Branko|editor-last1=Pek|editor-first2=Slobodan|editor-last2=Lang|publisher=Studio HS internet|location=Osijek, Croatia|isbn=978-953-7630-37-9|year=2011|first=Zvonimir|last=Bilić|chapter=Uloga osječkih tvrtki u Domovinskom ratu|trans_chapter=Role of Osijek Companies in the Croatian War of Independence|pages=290-296|url=http://slobodan-lang.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Pravo-na-dom.pdf|format=PDF}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|CIA|2002}}|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=it1IAQAAIAAJ|title=Balkan Battlegrounds: A Military History of the Yugoslav Conflict, 1990–1995|publisher=Central Intelligence Agency|author=[[Central Intelligence Agency]], Office of Russian and European Analysis|year=2002|oclc=50396958|location=Washington, D.C.}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=hr&amp;id=oFXdiS25N78C|editor-first=Sabrina P.|editor-last=Ramet|title=Central and Southeast European Politics Since 1989|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2010|isbn=978-1-139-48750-4|chapter=The War of Yugoslav Succession|first=Marko Attila|last=Hoare|authorlink=Marko Attila Hoare|pages=111–136|location=Cambridge, England}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=N9qA2sLb5gkC|title=Limits of Persuasion: Germany and the Yugoslav Crisis, 1991–1992|first=Michael|last=Libal|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|location=Westport, Connecticut|year=1997|isbn=978-0-275-95798-8}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Europe and the Breakup of Yugoslavia: A Political Failure in Search of a Scholarly Explanation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bcxv1eVCyhIC|isbn=978-90-411-1439-6|first=Sonia|last=Lucarelli|publisher=[[Martinus Nijhoff Publishers]]|location=Leiden, The Netherlands|year=2000}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?ei=MB7lUYeIDoKK4ATWqIDAAw&amp;hl=hr&amp;id=rPcVAQAAMAAJ|title=Počeci suvremene hrvatske države: kronologija procesa osamostaljenja Republike Hrvatske: od Memoranduma SANU 1986. do proglašenja neovisnosti 8. listopada 1991|language=Croatian|trans_title=Beginnings of the Modern Croatian State: A Chronology of the Independence of the Republic of Croatia: from 1986 SANU Memorandum to the Declaration of Independence on 8 October 1991|first=Ante|last=Nazor|publisher=Croatian Homeland War Memorial Documentation Centre|location=Zagreb, Croatia|year=2007|isbn=978-953-7439-01-9}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DXSNAQAAQBAJ|title=Confronting the Past: European Experiences|first1=Vjeran|last1=Pavlaković|first2=Davor|last2=Pauković|first3=Višeslav|last3=Raos|publisher=Centar za politološka istraživanja|location=Zagreb, Croatia|isbn=978-953-7022-26-6|year=2012}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=hr&amp;id=1QbX90fmCVUC|first=Božo|last=Repe|editor-first=David P.|editor-last=Forsythe|title=Encyclopedia of Human Rights, Volume 1|chapter=Balkan Wars|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|location=Oxford, England|year=2009|isbn=978-0-19-533402-9|pages=138–147}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|Rupić|2007}}|url=http://www.centardomovinskograta.hr/pdf/izdanja/Dokumenti_01.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=Hrvatski memorijalno-dokumentacijski centar Domovinskog rata|location=Zagreb, Croatia|year=2007|editor-first=Marko|editor-last=Rupić|title=Republika Hrvatska i Domovinski rat 1990. – 1995. – Dokumenti, Knjiga 1.|trans_title=The Republic of Croatia and the Croatian War of Independence 1990–1995 – Documents, volume 1|isbn=978-953-7439-03-3}}
{{refend}}

;Scientific journal articles
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite journal|ref=harv|journal=Društvena istrazivanja: Journal for General Social Issues|publisher=Institute of Social Sciences Ivo Pilar|location=Zagreb, Croatia|issn=1330-0288|volume=2|issue=2–3|date=March 1993|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=51777&amp;lang=en|language=Croatian|title=Ratni zločin i zločin genocida u agresiji Srbije na Republiku Hrvatsku 1991&amp;nbsp;... |trans_title=War Crime and Crime of Genocide in Aggression of Serbia Against the Republic of Croatia in 1991&amp;nbsp;... |pages=407–454|first1=Vlado|last1=Šakić|first2=Slavenka|last2=Sedlar|first3=Anka|last3=Tojčić}}
{{refend}}

;News reports
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Nova TV|1 August 2013}}|publisher=[[Nova TV (Croatia)|Nova TV]]|url=http://dnevnik.hr/vijesti/hrvatska/prije-22-godine-u-dalju-je-stradalo-20-policajaca-15-pripadnika-zbora-narodne-garde-i-cetiri-civila---296934.html|language=Croatian|title=Još jedna tužna obljetnica: Sjećanje na stradale u Dalju i progonstvo iz Aljmaša|trans_title=Another Sad Anniversary: Memory of Killed in Dalj and Exile from Aljmaš|date=1 August 2013}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|HRT|26 November 2013}}|publisher=[[Croatian Radiotelevision]]|date=26 November 2013|url=http://radio.hrt.hr/radio-osijek/clanak/u-dalju-otkriverno-spomen-obiljezje-ubijenim-civilima/31501/|title=U Dalju otkriverno spomen-obilježje ubijenim civilima|trans_title=A Memorial to Killed Civilians Unveiled in Dalj|first=Verica|last=Mađer|language=Croatian}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|BBC News|29 October 2001}}|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=29 October 2001|title=Milosevic Indictment: Text|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/354561.stm}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Večernji list|1 August 2013}}|newspaper=[[Večernji list]]|date=1 August 2013|url=http://www.vecernji.hr/hrvatska/ministar-branitelja-matic-urucio-ratnoj-pp-dalj-odlicje-za-junastvo-592851|language=Croatian|title=Ministar branitelja Matić uručio ratnoj PP Dalj odličje za junaštvo|trans_title=Veterans' Minister Matić Hands Wartime Dalj Police Station a Medal for Heroism}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Sense Agency|29 April 2008}}|date=29 April 2008|publisher=Sense Agency|work=Sense Tribunal|url=http://www.sense-agency.com/icty/‘outside-the-law’-following-milosevic’s-dictate.29.html?cat_id=1&amp;news_id=10883|title=&quot;Outside the Law&quot;, Following Milosevic's Dictate}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Jutarnji list|4 September 2013}}|newspaper=[[Jutarnji list]]|date=4 September 2013|url=http://www.jutarnji.hr/konacno-presuda-za-ratni-zlocin-u-dalju-osudeni-za-silovanje-hrvatice-pred-njenom-obitelji/1124083/|language=Croatian|title=Presuda za ratni zločin u Dalju: Prisilili obitelj da gledaju silovanje njihove kćeri (20)|trans_title=Dalj War Crime Verdict: Family Forced to Watch Rape of their Daughter (20)|agency=[[HINA]]|issn=1331-5692}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Dubrovački vjesnik|14 May 2010}}|newspaper=Dubrovački vjesnik|url=http://dubrovacki.hr/clanak/19357/optuznica-protiv-zapovjednika-jna-zbog-ratnog-zlocina-nad-112-hrvatskih-vojnika-i-civila|language=Croatian|title=Optužnica protiv zapovjednika JNA zbog ratnog zločina nad 112 hrvatskih vojnika i civila|trans_title=Charges Against JNA Commander for War Crimes Against 112 Croatian Troops and Civilians|date=14 May 2010}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The New York Times|19 August 1990}}|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/08/19/world/roads-sealed-as-yugoslav-unrest-mounts.html|agency=[[Reuters]]|title=Roads Sealed as Yugoslav Unrest Mounts|date=19 August 1990|location=New York City|issn=0362-4331}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The New York Times|16 March 2008}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/16/world/europe/16iht-serbs.4.11147074.html?_r=0|title=Serb officers face trial for actions in Bosnia and Croatia|date=16 March 2008|location=New York City|issn=0362-4331}}
{{refend}}

;Other sources
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|30 May 2013}}|date=30 May 2013|publisher=[[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]]|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/stanisic_simatovic/tjug/en/130530_summary.pdf|format=PDF|title=Judgement Summary for Jovica Stanišić and Franko Simatović}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Meron|5 December 2013}}|date=5 December 2013|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|url=http://www.icty.org/x/file/Press/Statements%20and%20Speeches/President/131205_president_meron_un_sc_en.pdf|format=PDF|title=Address to the U.N. Security Council Judge Theodor Meron President, International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia President, Mechanism for International Criminal Tribunals|first=Theodor|last=Meron}}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Nazor|2011a}}|journal=[[Hrvatski vojnik]]|publisher=[[Ministry of Defence (Croatia)|Ministry of Defence]]|url=http://www.hrvatski-vojnik.hr/hrvatski-vojnik/3412011/domovinskirat.asp|first=Ante|last=Nazor|date=April 2011|issue=341|language=Croatian|title=&quot;Informacija o angažovanju jedinice JNA u Dalju 01. 08. 1991. godine&quot; (okupacija Dalja, Aljmaša i Erduta) – (I. dio)|trans_title=Information on Engagement of a JNA Unit in Dalj on 1 August 1991 (Occupation of Dalj, Aljmaš and Erdut) – (Part 1)|issn=1333-9036}}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Nazor|2011b}}|journal=Hrvatski vojnik|publisher=Ministry of Defence (Croatia)|url=http://www.hrvatski-vojnik.hr/hrvatski-vojnik/3422011/domovinskirat.asp|first=Ante|last=Nazor|date=April 2011|issue=342|language=Croatian|title=&quot;Informacija o angažovanju jedinice JNA u Dalju 01. 08. 1991. godine&quot; (okupacija Dalja, Aljmaša i Erduta) – (II. dio)|trans_title=Information on Engagement of a JNA Unit in Dalj on 1 August 1991 (Occupation of Dalj, Aljmaš and Erdut) – (Part 2)|issn=1333-9036}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|MUP|2 August 2011}}|url=http://www.mup.hr/MainPu.aspx?id=100746|title=Obilježena 20. obljetnica tragične pogibije pripadnika PP Dalj|trans_title=20th Anniversary of Tragic Death of Dalj Police Station Marked|date=2 August 2011|language=Croatian|publisher=[[Ministry of the Interior (Croatia)|Ministry of the Interior]]}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|21 May 2004}}|title=The Prosecutor of the Tribunal Against Goran Hadžić|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/hadzic/ind/en/had-ii040716e.htm|date=21 May 2004|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|23 October 2002}}|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/slobodan_milosevic/ind/en/mil-2ai020728e.htm|title=The Prosecutor of the Tribunal Against Slobodan Milošević – Second Amended Indictment|date=23 October 2002|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|10 July 2008}}|title=The Prosecutor v. Jovica Stanišić &amp; Franko Simatović – Prosecution Notice of Filing of the Third Amended Indictment|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/stanisic_simatovic/ind/en/staj-in3rdamd080710.pdf|format=PDF|date=10 July 2008|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|25 September 2013}}|date=25 September 2013|title=The Prosecutor v. Jovica Stanišić, Franko Simatović – Prosecution Appeal Brief|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/stanisic_simatovic/custom6/en/130925.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|12 June 2007}}|title=The Prosecutor vs. Milan Martic – Judgement|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/martic/tjug/en/070612.pdf|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|date=12 June 2007|format=PDF}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|29 January 2003}}|title=Trial of Slobodan Milošević – Transcript|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/slobodan_milosevic/trans/en/030129ED.htm|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|date=29 January 2003|pages=15075–15177}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|28 August 2003}}|title=Trial of Slobodan Milošević – Transcript|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/slobodan_milosevic/trans/en/030828ED.htm|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|date=28 August 2004|pages=25477–25594}}
{{refend}}

{{coord|45.486132|N|18.983002|E|region:HR_type:landmark_source:kolossus-dewiki|display=title}}

{{Croatian War of Independence}}
{{Wars and battles involving Croatia|state=autocollapse}}

[[Category:1991 in Croatia]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 1991]]
[[Category:Massacres in Croatia]]
[[Category:Republic of Serbian Krajina]]
[[Category:Serbian war crimes in the Croatian War of Independence]]</text>
      <sha1>b9imni68paygc1c29nyx6tg1h8swa80</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
