<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Disruptive coloration</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37438477</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745932241</id>
      <parentid>732883438</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T07:11:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Examples */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21604">{{good article}}
{{Use British English|date=March 2016}}
[[File:Podargus papuensis - Daintree River.jpg|thumb|[[Papuan frogmouth]] ''Podargus papuensis'', its outline disrupted by its plumage, its eye concealed in a stripe|alt=photo of a frogmouth in a tree]]

'''Disruptive coloration''' (also known as '''disruptive camouflage''' or '''disruptive patterning''') is a form of [[camouflage]] that works by breaking up the outlines of an animal, soldier or military vehicle with a strongly contrasting pattern. It is often combined with other methods of [[crypsis]] including background colour matching and [[countershading]]. It appears paradoxical as a way of not being seen, since disruption of outlines depends on high contrast, so the patches of colour are themselves conspicuous.

The importance of high-contrast patterns for successful disruption was predicted in general terms by the [[artist]] [[Abbott Thayer]] in 1909 and explicitly by the [[zoologist]] [[Hugh Cott]] in 1940. Later experimental research has started to confirm these predictions. Disruptive patterns work best when all their components match the background.

While background matching works best for a single background, disruptive coloration is a more effective strategy when an animal or a military vehicle may have a variety of backgrounds.

Conversely, poisonous or distasteful animals that advertise their presence with warning coloration ([[aposematism]]) use patterns that emphasize rather than disrupt their outlines. For example, [[skunks]], [[salamanders]] and [[monarch butterfly|monarch butterflies]] all have high-contrast patterns that display their outlines.

==Early research==

[[Image:Disruptive Coloration by Hugh Cott 1940.jpg|thumb|The principle of &quot;maximum disruptive contrast&quot; by [[Hugh Cott]], 1940, &quot;showing the distractive effect upon the eye of patterns which contrast as violently as possible with the tone of their background&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cott, 1940. p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The artist [[Abbott Handerson Thayer]] in his 1909 book ''[[Concealing-Coloration in the Animal Kingdom]]'' argued that animals were concealed by a combination of [[countershading]] and &quot;ruptive&quot; marks, which together &quot;obliterated&quot; their self-shadowing and their shape. Thayer explained that:&lt;ref name=Thayer77&gt;Thayer, 1909. pp. 77–78, and throughout.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Markings... of whatever sort, tend to ''obliterate'',—to cancel, by their separate and conflicting pattern, the visibility of the details and boundaries of form.... If the bird's or butterfly's costume consists of sharply contrasted bold patterns of light and dark, in about equal proportions, its contour will be &quot;broken up&quot; against both light and dark—light failing to show against light, dark against dark. Such is apparently the basal and predominant use of almost all the bolder patterns in animals' costumes.|Thayer&lt;ref name=Thayer77/&gt;}}

[[Cott, H. B.|Hugh Cott]]'s 1940 book ''[[Adaptive Coloration in Animals]]'' introduced ideas such as &quot;maximum disruptive contrast&quot;. This uses streaks of boldly contrasting colour, which paradoxically make animals or military vehicles less visible by breaking up their outlines. Cott explains that in ideal conditions, background colour matching together with countershading would &quot;suffice to render an animal absolutely invisible against a plain background&quot;, but at once adds that conditions are hardly ever ideal, as they are constantly changing, as is the light. Therefore, Cott argues, camouflage has to break up the perceived continuous surfaces of an object and its outlines. In Cott's own words, &quot;for effective concealment, it is essential that the tell-tale appearance of form should be destroyed.&quot;&lt;ref name=CottCh4&gt;Cott, 1940. pp. 47–67.&lt;/ref&gt; Cott draws an analogy with a pickpocket who carefully distracts your attention, arguing that:

{{quote|The function of a disruptive pattern is to prevent, or to delay as long as possible, the first recognition of an object by sight... irregular patches of contrasted colours and tones ... tend to catch the eye of the observer and to draw his attention away from the shape which bears them.|Cott&lt;ref name=CottCh4/&gt;}}

Further, Cott criticises unscientific attempts at camouflage, early in the [[Second World War]], for not understanding the principles involved:

{{quote|Various recent attempts to camouflage tanks, armoured cars and the roofs of buildings with paint reveal an almost complete failure by those responsible to grasp the essential factor in the disguise of surface continuity and of contour. Such work must be carried out with courage and confidence, for at close range objects properly treated will appear glaringly conspicuous. But they are not painted for deception at close range, but at ranges at which ... bombing raids are likely... And at these distances differences of tint ... blend and thus nullify the effect and render the work practically useless.|Cott&lt;ref name=CottCh4/&gt;}}

The pioneering work of Thayer and Cott is endorsed in the 2006  review of disruptive coloration by Martin Stevens and colleagues, which notes that they proposed a &quot;different form of camouflage&quot; from the traditional &quot;strategy of background matching&quot; proposed by authors such as [[Alfred Russel Wallace]] (''[[Darwinism (book)|Darwinism]]'', 1889), [[Edward Bagnall Poulton]] (''[[The Colours of Animals]]'', 1890) and [[Frank Evers Beddard]] (''[[Animal Coloration (book)|Animal Coloration]]'', 1895); Stevens observes that background matching on its own would always fail because of &quot;discontinuities between the boundary of the animal and the background&quot;.&lt;ref name=Disruptive/&gt;

==In animals==
[[File:Caprimulgus aegyptius.jpg|thumb|left|[[Egyptian nightjar]], ''Caprimulgus aegyptius'', rests on the sand, protected by its coloration, immobility, and concealment of shadow as it faces the sun]]
{{further|List of camouflage methods}}

Disruptive patterns use strongly contrasting markings such as spots or stripes to break up the outlines of an animal or military vehicle. Some predators, like the [[leopard]], and some potential prey like the [[Egyptian nightjar]], use disruptive patterns.&lt;ref name=Disruptive&gt;{{cite journal | title=Disruptive contrast in animal camouflage |author1=Stevens, M. |author2=Cuthill, I.C. |author3=Windsor, A.M.M. |author4=Walker, H.J. | journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society B | date=7 October 2006 | volume=273 | issue=1600 | pages=2433–2436 | doi=10.1098/rspb.2006.3614 | pmc=1634902 | pmid=16959632}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disruptive patterns are defined by A. Barbosa and colleagues as &quot;characterized by high-contrast light and dark patches, in a nonrepetitive configuration, that also provide camouflage by disrupting the recognizable shape or orientation of the animal&quot;, as in the cuttlefish.&lt;ref name=Barbosa&gt;{{cite journal | title=Cuttlefish camouflage: The effects of substrate contrast and size in evoking uniform, mottle or disruptive body patterns | journal=Vision Research | year=2008 | volume=48 | pages=1242–1253 | doi=10.1016/j.visres.2008.02.011 | pmid=18395241 | issue=10 | author1=Barbosa | first1=A | last2=Mäthger | first2=L. M. | last3=Buresch | first3=K. C. | last4=Kelly | first4=J | last5=Chubb | first5=C | last6=Chiao | first6=C. C. | last7=Hanlon | first7=R. T. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Oxybelis aeneus (detail).jpg|thumb|[[Mexican vine snake]], ''Oxybelis aeneus'', conceals its eye with a coincident dark stripe, contrasting with its pale underside]]
The strategy appears paradoxical and counter-intuitive as a method of camouflage, since disrupting outlines depends on using patches of colour which contrast strongly with each other, so the patches  are themselves conspicuous.&lt;ref name=Disruptive/&gt;&lt;ref name=Endler&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/273/1600/2425.full.html | title=Disruptive and cryptic coloration | journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society B |date=October 2006 | volume=273 | issue=1600 | pages=2426–2426 | doi=10.1098/rspb.2006.3650 | pmid=16959630 | pmc=1634903| author1=Endler | first1=J. A. }}&lt;/ref&gt; While background matching works best for a single background, disruptive coloration is a more effective strategy when an animal or a military vehicle may have a variety of backgrounds.&lt;ref name=Endler/&gt;

Martin Stevens and colleagues in 2006 made what they believed was the first experimental test that &quot;disruptive coloration is effective even when some colour patches do not match the background and have a high contrast with both the background and adjacent pattern elements (disruptive contrast)&quot;.&lt;ref name=Disruptive/&gt; They used &quot;moth-like targets&quot;, some matching the lightness of the background [[oak]] tree bark, other mismatching it, each with a dead mealworm. If the mealworm was removed it was assumed a bird predator had taken it: this could be distinguished from visits by other predators. They found that disruptive coloration provided the best protection from bird predators when the pattern was matched to background luminance, but even when elements in a pattern did not match, disruptive patterns were still better at reducing predation than either non-disruptive patterns or plain (unpatterned) control targets.&lt;ref name=Disruptive/&gt;

Disruptive patterns can also conceal specific features. Animals such as fish, birds, frogs and snakes can readily be detected by their eyes, which are necessarily round and dark. Many species conceal the eye with a [[eyestripe|stripe that runs through the eye]], sometimes contrasting with a [[supercilium|stripe above the eye]], making it seem just part of a dark area of background. Cott called this a &quot;coincident disruptive pattern&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cott, 1940. pp. 68-93.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The opposite case: aposematism===
[[File:Feuersalamander DE.jpg|thumb|Opposite of disruption: [[Fire salamander]], ''Salamandra salamandra'', advertises its inedibility with bright [[aposematism|warning colours]], in patches that emphasize its body shape]]
{{main|aposematism}}

Many poisonous or distasteful animals that advertise their presence with warning coloration ([[aposematism]]) use patterns that emphasize rather than disrupt their outlines. For example, [[skunks]], [[salamanders]] and [[monarch butterfly|monarch butterflies]] all have high contrast patterns that display their outlines. These advertising patterns exploit the opposite principle to disruptive coloration, for what is in effect the exactly opposite effect: to make the animal as conspicuous as possible.&lt;ref&gt;Cott, 1940. pp. 96, 193–199.&lt;/ref&gt;

===A disputed case: the giraffe===
[[File:Giraffe mother and calf (cropped).jpg|thumb|left|A conspicuous [[giraffe]] mother can defend herself, but her calf relies on its camouflage|alt=photo of a giraffe mother and calf]]

The presence of bold markings does not in itself prove that an animal relies on camouflage.&lt;ref name=Roosevelt&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://digitallibrary.amnh.org/dspace/handle/2246/470 | title=Revealing and concealing coloration in birds and mammals | author=Roosevelt, Theodore | journal=Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History | year=1911 | volume=30 | issue=Article 8 | pages=119–231}} Roosevelt attacks Thayer on page 191, arguing that neither zebra nor giraffe are &quot;'adequately obliterated' by countershading or coloration pattern or anything else.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; According to Mitchell, adult [[giraffe]]s are &quot;inescapably conspicuous&quot;, making the conclusion that their patterns are for camouflage appear counterintuitive: but when standing among trees and bushes, their camouflage is effective at even a few metres' distance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell2003&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Mitchell, G |author2=Skinner, JD | year=2003 | title=On the origin, evolution and phylogeny of giraffes ''Giraffa camelopardalis'' | journal=Transactions of the Royal Society of South Africa | volume=58 | issue= 1| pages=51–73| doi = 10.1080/00359190309519935| url = http://www.bringyou.to/GiraffeEvolution.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|70}}
[[File:Polygonia c-album LC0238.jpg|thumb|Irregular outline of [[comma butterfly]] ''Polygonia c-album'' avoids a typical [[butterfly]] shape]]

Further, young giraffes are much more vulnerable to predation than adults: between 60% and 75% of calves die within a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell2003&quot;/&gt;{{rp|70}} Mothers hide their calves, which spend much of the time lying down in cover. Since the presence of a mother does not affect survival, Mitchell suggests that young giraffes must be extremely well camouflaged. This is supported by the fact that coat markings are strongly inherited.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell2003&quot;/&gt;{{rp|70}} Conversely, far from hiding, adult giraffes move about to gain the best view of an approaching predator, relying on their size and ability to defend themselves even from lions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell2003&quot;/&gt;{{rp|69}}

===Other ways of hiding outlines===
{{further|List of camouflage methods}}

The outlines of an animal's body can be made hard to see by other methods, such as by using a highly irregular outline. For example, the [[Comma butterfly]], ''Polygonia c-album'', is highly cryptic when its wings are closed, with cryptic colours, disruptive pattern, and irregular outer margins to the wings.&lt;ref&gt;Cott, 1940. p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military usage==
{{Main|Military camouflage}}
[[File:Maskowanie.JPEG|thumb|upright=0.7|left|A soldier applying a disruptive pattern to his face; his helmet and jacket are both disruptively patterned|alt=photo of a soldier putting on camouflage face paint]]

Disruptive coloration is common in military usage, for military vehicles, for firing positions and other installations, and for individual soldiers, where uniforms, equipment such as helmets, and face paint may be used to break up outlines and features.&lt;ref name='FM 20-3'&gt;{{cite book | author = Department of the Army | title = Field Manual Headquarters No. 20-3 | date = 30 August 1999 | url = http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/policy/army/fm/20-3/toc.htm | work = Camouflage, Concealment, and Decoys}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disruptive coloration, however, does not always achieve crypsis on its own, as an animal or a military target may be given away by other factors including shape, shine, and shadow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweet&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Transportation and Cargo Security: Threats and Solutions | publisher=Prentice Hall | author=Sweet, KM | year=2006 | page=219}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fm5-20&gt;{{cite book  |title=FM 5-20, CAMOUFLAGE |author=U. S. War Department |year=1944}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:US Woodland pattern.svg|thumb|upright=0.7|M81 Woodland [[camouflage pattern]]]]
Many military [[camouflage pattern]]s since the 1940s have been disruptively coloured, and with the issue of [[US Woodland pattern]] to [[Military of the United States|United States armed forces]] from 1981, disruptive pattern became a dominant feature of military uniforms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olive-drab.com/od_soldiers_clothing_bdu.php Battle Dress Uniform (Bdu)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title=Department of the Army Historical Summary FY 1981| chapterurl=http://www.history.army.mil/books/DAHSUM/1981/ch07.htm| chapter=Chapter 7: Support Services | url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/DAHSUM/1981/index.htm| year = 1988| editor=Christine O. Hardyman| publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1969, [[Disruptive Pattern Material]] (DPM) began to replace plain material for uniforms in the [[British Armed Forces]] and was later used by many other armies.&lt;ref name=IWM&gt;{{cite web |title=Trousers, Camouflage DPM Combat Dress 1968 pattern |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/30094716 |publisher=Imperial War Museum |accessdate=31 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Challenges===
[[Image:Flecktarn.jpg|upright=0.7|thumb|left|Modern German [[Flecktarn]] 1990 is a non-digital pattern designed to disrupt outlines at different distances]]
Three major challenges face the design of disruptively patterned uniforms, however. Firstly, units frequently move from one terrain to another, where the background colours and contrasts may differ greatly. A uniform designed for woodland will be too strongly contrasting for desert use, and too green for urban use. Therefore, no single camouflage pattern is effective in all terrains.&lt;ref name=US-Army&gt;{{cite book |last=US Army |title=FM 21-76 US ARMY SURVIVAL MANUAL |publisher=U.S. Department of the Army |url=https://archive.org/details/Fm21-76SurvivalManual |accessdate=8 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=US Army |title=Photosimulation Camouflage Detection Test |year=2009 |publisher=U.S. Army Natick Soldier Research, Development and Engineering Center |location=Natick, MA |page=27 |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/19823845/Photosimulation-Camouflage-Detection-Test |accessdate=5 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Brayley&gt;{{cite book |last=Brayley |first=Martin J. |title=Camouflage uniforms : international combat dress 1940–2010 | year=2009 | publisher=Crowood  |location=Ramsbury |isbn=1-84797-137-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; The American [[Universal Camouflage Pattern|UCP]] of 2004 attempted to suit all environments but was  withdrawn after a few years of service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Freedberg Jr. |first=S.J. |title=Army Drops Universal Camouflage After Spending Billions |url=http://defense.aol.com/2012/06/25/army-drops-universal-camouflage-after-spending-billions |accessdate=27 September 2012 |newspaper=Aol Defence |date=25 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Terrain specific patterns like &quot;Berlin camouflage&quot;, which was applied to British vehicles operating in [[Berlin]] during the [[Cold War]], have sometimes been developed but are ineffective in other terrains.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Davies|first=W.|title=Berlin Brigade Urban Paint Scheme |url=http://www.emlra.org/index.php/articles/berlin-brigade-urban-paint-scheme|work=Newsletter |publisher=Ex-Military Land Rover Association |accessdate=25 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Secondly, the effectiveness of any pattern in disrupting a soldier's outlines varies with lighting, depending on the weather and the height of the sun in the sky. And thirdly, any given patch of printed colour varies in apparent size with distance from the enemy observing the pattern. A pattern printed with small patches of colour blends into a single perceived mass at a certain range, defeating the disruptive effect. Conversely, a pattern printed with large patches of colour appears conspicuous at shorter ranges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Craemer |first=Guy |title=Dual Texture - U.S. Army digital camouflage |url=http://www.uniteddynamics.com/dualtex/ |publisher=United Dynamics Corp. |accessdate=27 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; This problem has been solved with pixellated shapes, often designed digitally, that provide a [[fractal]]-like range of patch sizes, enabling them to be effectively disruptive both at close range and at a distance. The first genuinely digital camouflage pattern was the Canadian [[CADPAT]], soon followed by the American [[MARPAT]]. A pixellated appearance is not essential for this effect, though it is simpler to design and to print.&lt;ref name=Gye&gt;{{cite news |last=Gye |first=H. |title=How U.S. Army spent $5BILLION on 'failed' pixel camouflage&amp;nbsp;... because they 'wanted to look cooler than Marines' |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2164686/How-U-S-Army-spent-5BILLION-failed-pixel-camouflage--wanted-look-cooler-Marines.html |accessdate=21 November 2012 |newspaper=Mail (online) |date=25 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Engber |first=D. |title=Lost in the Wilderness, the military's misadventures in pixellated camouflage |year=2007 |url=http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/science/2012/07/camouflage_problems_in_the_army_the_ucp_and_the_future_of_digital_camo_.single.html |accessdate=27 September 2012 |newspaper=State |date=5 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples==

&lt;gallery class=&quot;center&quot; widths=150 mode=nolines&gt;
File:Great male Leopard in South Afrika-JD.JPG|[[Leopard]]: a disruptively camouflaged (and [[countershading|countershaded]]) predator|alt=photo of a leopard
File:Ptarmigan and five chicks.JPG|A [[ptarmigan]] and five chicks exhibit exceptional disruptive camouflage|alt=photo of a hen ptarmigan and her chicks
File:Jumping spider with prey.jpg|[[Jumping Spider]]: a disruptively camouflaged invertebrate predator|alt=photo of a jumping spider
File:Armoured personnel carriers, Eriboll - geograph.org.uk - 1316295.jpg|&quot;Shape, shine, shadow&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stirling2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Stirling, Robert  |title=SAS Ultimate Guide to Combat |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SQnD_2YtqEcC&amp;pg=PA181 |year=2012 |publisher=Osprey Publishing |isbn=978-1-78096-399-0 |page=181}}&lt;/ref&gt; make these [[military camouflage|&quot;camouflaged&quot; military vehicles]] easily visible, their outlines not disrupted|alt=photo of armoured vehicles easy to see on bare hillside
File:Challenger 2 Tank MOD 45148907.jpg|A British [[Challenger 2]] tank painted in bold disruptive pattern of sand and green|alt=photo of a Challenger 2 tank at speed on grassy plain
File:Chaetodon striatus Brasil.jpg|The banded butterflyfish, ''[[Chaetodon striatus]]'' has strong disruptive bands through the body and concealing the eye.
File:US Navy WWII ship camouflage measures - detail of USS Alabama in measure 16.jpg|''[[USS Alabama (BB-60)|USS Alabama]]'' wearing measure 16 in 1942
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==

{{reflist|28em}}

==Sources==

* [[Cott, H. B.|Cott, Hugh B.]] (1940). ''[[Adaptive Coloration in Animals]]''. Methuen, London.
* [[Abbott Handerson Thayer|Thayer, Abbott H.]]; Thayer, Gerald H. (1909). ''[[Concealing-Coloration in the Animal Kingdom]]''. Macmillan, New York.

{{camouflage}}

[[Category:Camouflage]]
[[Category:Military camouflage]]</text>
      <sha1>ahwhnk3rs9k6nc3foiwrfrbvrqjjmvg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
