<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dolbadarn Castle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1781263</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745932572</id>
      <parentid>726123231</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T07:15:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14485">{{Good article}}
{{Infobox military installation
|name          = Dolbadarn Castle
|location      = [[Gwynedd]], Wales
|coordinates   = {{gbmapping|SH586598}}
|image         = [[File:dolbadarn.jpg|220px]]
|caption       = Dolbadarn Castle
|latitude      = 53.11649
|longitude     = -4.1141
|coord_format  = dms
|coord_region  = GB
|coord_display = title
|map_type      = Wales
|map_size      = 200
|map_alt       = 
|map_caption   = Dolbadarn Castle, shown within [[Wales]]
|pushpin_mark  = Castle.svg
|type          = 
|materials     = [[Slate]] stone
|height        = 
|condition     = Ruined
|ownership     = [[Cadw]]
|open_to_public= Yes
|controlledby  = 
|battles       =  
|events        = 1283 invasion of North Wales
}}

'''Dolbadarn Castle''' is a fortification built by the Welsh prince [[Llywelyn the Great]] during the early 13th century, at the base of the [[Llanberis Pass]], in [[North Wales]]. The [[castle]] was important both militarily and as a symbol of Llywelyn's power and authority. The castle features a large stone [[keep]], which historian Richard Avent considers &quot;the finest surviving example of a Welsh round tower&quot;.&lt;ref name=AventP11/&gt; In 1284 Dolbadarn was taken by [[Edward I of England|Edward I]], who removed some of its timbers to build his [[Caernarfon Castle|new castle]] at [[Caernarfon]]. The castle was used as a [[manor house]] for some years, before falling into ruin. In the 18th and 19th century it was a popular destination for painters interested in [[Sublime (philosophy)|Sublime]] and [[Picturesque]] landscapes. It is now owned by [[Cadw]] and managed as a [[tourist attraction]], and is protected as a grade I [[listed building]].

==History==
===1220–40===
Dolbadarn Castle was built in either the 1220s or the 1230s by Llywelyn the Great, at the base of the [[Llanberis Pass]], overlooking the lake of Llyn Padarn in North Wales.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.12.&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally the Welsh princes had not constructed castles, instead using undefended palaces called ''{{lang|cy|llysoedd}}'', or courts.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.3.&lt;/ref&gt; From the late 11th century onwards, the [[Norman people|Normans]] had [[Norman invasion of Wales|advanced into Wales]], taking lands in the north and establishing a band of occupied territory in the south called the [[Welsh Marches]]. During the 12th century some timber and earthwork castles began to be built, but in small numbers.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.4.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dolbardarn castle plan.png|thumb|350px|left|Plan of the castle: A – South Tower; B – Keep; C – West Tower; D – East Building; E – Hall]]
Llywelyn the Great initially controlled the princedom of Gwynedd, but grew more powerful over the course of his reign, extending his influence over much of Wales during the early years of the 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.6.&lt;/ref&gt; Llywelyn was faced by several challenges, including dealing with the threat from the kings of England, and maintaining his authority over the native Welsh.&lt;ref name=AventP7&gt;Avent, p.7.&lt;/ref&gt; As part of this strategy, Llywelyn built [[Castell y Bere]], an innovative stone Welsh castle, in the 1220s.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.8.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards he began the first phases of Dolbadarn Castle, constructing the initial stone fortifications on the site, including two square stone towers.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.12; Butler, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;

The location of the castle was important both because it controlled an important mountain pass, and possibly because Llywelyn claimed authority as the lord of the mountains and coasts of Wales: several of his castles appear to have been located with such political symbolism in mind.&lt;ref&gt;Butler, p.29.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also possible that Llywelyn may have built his castle on top of the remains of a previous fortification constructed by [[Maelgwn Gwynedd]], a king of Gwynedd in the 6th century, although no such remains have been found.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.cofiadurcahcymru.org.uk/arch/query/page.php?watprn=GAT5550&amp;dbname=gat&amp;tbname=core Castell Dolbadarn, Llanberis]'', Gwynedd Archaeological Trust, Regional Historic Environment Record, accessed 22 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

As part of his strategy for dealing with the Marcher Lords, Llywelyn married his eldest son, [[Dafydd ap Llywelyn|Dafydd]], to [[Isabella de Braose|Isabella]], the daughter of [[William de Braose (died 1230)|William de Braose]], a powerful lord in [[Brecon]], [[Builth]] and [[Abergavenny]].&lt;ref name=AventP7/&gt; The Marcher Lords had adopted a style of stone castle that included circular [[keep]]s and an integrated system of curtain walls. Following Dafydd's marriage, Llywelyn appears to have started a second phase of building at Dolbadarn, probably in the 1240s, adding these elements to the existing castle.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, pp.7, 12.&lt;/ref&gt; The prince was probably aiming not only to incorporate the latest military technology, but also to create a castle of equal prestige to those of his new allies in the south.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.12; Crouch, p.278.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The interpretation of Dolbadarn, like other Norman and Welsh castles, has shifted over time. Post-war historians such as R. Allen Brown focused on the military advantages of circular keeps, ascribing the design at Dolbadarn to the increased military competition in Wales during the period. Similarly Cathcart King saw the keep as being &quot;very well developed&quot;, noting that it &quot;might pass for an English addition&quot;. Richard Avent's later work on the social and political aspects of these princely castles has led to a more multi-faceted interpretation.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, p.54; Avent, p.12; Crouch, p.278; King, p.135.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;nb&quot;}} Traditionally the surrounding district of Is Gwyrfai had been run from the town of [[Caernarfon|Llanbeblig]]; after the 1240s, this role was transferred to Dolbadarn.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.12.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1240–1300===
[[File:Dolbadarn Castle guarding the pass - geograph.org.uk - 1131204.jpg|thumb|The keep, seen across the hall and courtyard]]
Following Llywelyn's death in 1240, Gwynedd's power declined and many of its eastern lands were taken by [[Henry III of England]] in 1247.&lt;ref name=AventP14&gt;Avent, p.14.&lt;/ref&gt; Llywelyn's grandson, [[Llywelyn ap Gruffudd]], took power in 1255 and imprisoned his brother [[Owain Goch ap Gruffydd|Owain ap Gruffudd]] before extending his power across Wales.&lt;ref name=AventP14/&gt; Owain was eventually released in 1277 and there has been much historical debate over which castle he was held in. [[Hywel Foel ap Griffri ap Pwyll Wyddel|Hywel Foel ap Griffri]] wrote a famous poem describing Owain's long imprisonment in a round tower; historians believe that this refers to the keep at Dolbardarn.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, pp.14–15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The conflict between the Welsh princes and the English kings continued in the reign of [[Edward I of England|Edward I]]. In 1282 Llywelyn fought a final campaign against Edward, ending in the prince's death near [[Builth]] that December.&lt;ref name=AventP16&gt;Avent, p.16.&lt;/ref&gt; His brother, [[Dafydd ap Gruffydd]], assumed power but during 1283 was forced south into [[Snowdonia]] and by May his government was based from Dolbadarn Castle.&lt;ref name=AventP16/&gt; Edward deployed 7,000 troops to detain Dafydd who was finally captured and executed in October; Dolbadarn was occupied by Norman forces.&lt;ref name=AventP16/&gt;

Edward was determined to prevent any further rebellion in North Wales and set about building a sequence of new castles and walled towns, replacing the old Welsh administrative system with a new principality governed from [[Caernarfon]].&lt;ref name=AventP20&gt;Avent, p.20.&lt;/ref&gt; Dolbadarn was no longer relevant and within two years timber from the castle was being used by the Normans for the construction of Caernarfon Castle.&lt;ref name=AventP20/&gt; This was both a practical and a symbolic action, demonstrating Norman power over one of the most important possessions of the Welsh princes.&lt;ref name=AventP20/&gt;

===14th – 21st centuries===
[[File:J.M.W. Turner Dolbadern Castle, 1800.jpg|thumbnail|upright|[[J. M. W. Turner]]'s painting [[Dolbadarn Castle (Turner)|''Dolbadarn Castle'']], 1800.]]
The remaining parts of the castle continued to be used as a manor house into the 14th century.&lt;ref name=AventP20/&gt; By the 18th century, however, Dolbadarn Castle was ruined and uninhabited.&lt;ref name=AventP21&gt;Avent, p.21.&lt;/ref&gt; From the 1760s onwards, however, it became a popular topic for painters interested in the then fashionable landscape styles of the [[Sublime (philosophy)|Sublime]] and the [[Picturesque]].&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.22.&lt;/ref&gt; Typically the castle was painted in the middle ground, allowing the viewer's eye to contrast its ruined outline with the lakes and mountains of Snowdonia; frequently the landscape was misrepresented by the artist, to create a more striking or dramatic effect.&lt;ref name=AventAndrewsP22&gt;Avent, p.22; Andrews, p.135.&lt;/ref&gt; [[J. M. W. Turner]]'s 1800 work [[Dolbadarn Castle (Turner)|''Dolbadarn Castle'']] depicted the back-lit castle looming over the landscape and became particularly famous, but the paintings of the castle by [[Richard Wilson (painter)|Richard Wilson]] and [[Paul Sandby]] also represent important artistic works of the period.&lt;ref name=AventAndrewsP22/&gt;

In 1941 the castle was given to the State by Sir [[Sir Michael Duff, 3rd Baronet|Michael Duff]].&lt;ref name=AventP21/&gt; It is now maintained by [[Cadw]] and is protected as a Grade I [[listed building]] and as a [[scheduled monument]].&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.gatehouse-gazetteer.info/Welshsites/101.html Dolbadarn Castle]'', Gatehouse website, accessed 22 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In the light of [[Welsh devolution]] and other political changes, the history of Dolbadarn Castle and similar Welsh castles has become increasing prominent. In response, Cadw have noted that they intend to give an increased priority to communicating the history of these castles and the Welsh princes.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, pp.200–201.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Architecture==
[[File:Dolbadarn Castle Cadw.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|The castle seen from the north-west, showing (near to far) the hall, the courtyard, the west tower, the east building, the keep and the south tower]]

Dolbadarn Castle comprises a courtyard, surrounded by a number of towers and a round keep.&lt;ref name=AventP31&gt;Avent, p.31.&lt;/ref&gt; The castle is built from purple and green [[slate]] stone, mainly constructed in a [[dry stone]] fashion without mortar, with the exception of the keep.&lt;ref name=AventP31/&gt; The courtyard follows the natural shape of the hill and is protected by a [[curtain wall (fortification)|curtain wall]]; originally perhaps 15&amp;nbsp;feet (5&amp;nbsp;m) high, it is now only at most 3&amp;nbsp;feet (1&amp;nbsp;m) high.&lt;ref name=AventP33&gt;Avent, p.33.&lt;/ref&gt; Of the castle buildings, only the keep remains to any significant height.&lt;ref name=AventP35&gt;Avent, p.35.&lt;/ref&gt;

The keep today is 46&amp;nbsp;feet (14&amp;nbsp;m) high and is modelled on early 13th-century English round towers built in the south of the Welsh Marches.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, pp.11, 31; King, p.135.&lt;/ref&gt; As with other Welsh-constructed towers, the entrance is on the first storey, not at ground level; it may originally have been protected by a porch.&lt;ref name=AventP31/&gt; The keep had a portcullis which would have been drawn up past the window on the second storey of the tower.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.32-33.&lt;/ref&gt; While the castle's flooring has long since disappeared, its interior staircase to the upper storey may still be climbed.&lt;ref name=AventP32&gt;Avent, p.32.&lt;/ref&gt; This second storey would have formed the main chamber in the keep and had a large fireplace and a latrine.&lt;ref name=AventP32/&gt; Originally the keep would have had a [[parapet]] and [[battlements]], since destroyed.&lt;ref name=AventP32/&gt; Historian Richard Avent considers it &quot;the finest surviving example of a Welsh round tower&quot;.&lt;ref name=AventP11&gt;Avent, p.11.&lt;/ref&gt;

The rectangular west tower was a relatively short defensive structure, designed to protect the more vulnerable western slope of the ridge.&lt;ref name=AventP33/&gt; A similar tower in the south overlooks the entrance to the castle.&lt;ref name=AventP35/&gt; At the north end of the castle is the hall, stretching across the courtyard; in the east corner is an additional building, probably built by the English at the end of the 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;Avent, p.34.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the hall is relatively large, 50 by 27&amp;nbsp;feet (15 by 8&amp;nbsp;m), these buildings follow a simpler design to those current in England at the time, where a combination of a hall, chamber and a service block in castles was becoming more common.&lt;ref&gt;Crouch, p.278; Emery, p.660.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Castles in Great Britain and Ireland]]
* [[List of castles in Wales]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=&quot;nb&quot;}}

==References==
{{reflist|3}}

==Bibliography==

*Andrews, Malcolm. (1989) ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=QwirAAAAIAAJ The Search for the Picturesque.]'' Stanford, US: Stanford University Press. ISBN 978-0-8047-1402-0.
*Avent, Richard. (2010) ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=ajf5AAAACAAJ Dolwyddelan Castle, Dolbadarn Castle, Castel y Bere.]'' Cardiff: Cadw. ISBN 978-1-85760-205-0.
*Brown, R. Allen. (1962) ''English Castles.'' London: Batsford. {{OCLC|1392314}}
*Butler, Lawrence. (2010) &quot;The Castles of the Princes of Gwynedd,&quot; in Williams and Kenyon (eds) (2010).
*Crouch, David. (1992) ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Oa4OAAAAQAAJ The Image of Aristocracy in Britain, 1000–1300.]'' London: Routledge. ISBN 978-0-415-01911-8.
*Emery, Anthony. (2000) ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=FRw9AAAAIAAJ Greater Medieval Houses of England and Wales, 1300–1500: East Anglia, Central England, and Wales.]'' Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. ISBN 978-0-521-58131-8.
*Jones, Alan Ffred. (2010) &quot;King Edward' I's Castles in North Wales – Now and Tomorrow,&quot; in Williams and Kenyon (eds) (2010).
*King, D. J. Cathcart. (1991) ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=fwwOAAAAQAAJ The Castle in England and Wales: An Interpretative History.]'' London: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-00350-4.
*Williams, Diane M. and John R. Kenyon. (eds) (2010) ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=QuxyPgAACAAJ The Impact of the Edwardian Castles in Wales.]'' Oxford: Oxbow Books. ISBN 978-1-84217-380-0.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Dolbadarn Castle}}
*[http://cadw.wales.gov.uk/daysout/dolbadarncastle/?lang=en Cadw visitor information]

{{coord|53.1166|N|4.1142|W|type:landmark_region:GB|display=title}}

[[Category:Castle ruins in Wales]]
[[Category:Castles in Gwynedd]]
[[Category:Llanberis]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in Gwynedd]]</text>
      <sha1>g6gzrv9e6v9tjkezj86fvfaiyuwp7iu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
