<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dunnottar Castle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>610029</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735022705</id>
      <parentid>731525246</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-18T05:19:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Internet Archive]] (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37065">{{For|ships of this name|RMS Dunottar Castle|MS Dunnottar Castle}}
{{Redirect|Dunnottar}}
{{Good article}} 
{{Infobox Military Structure
|name        = Dunnottar Castle
|native_name = Dùn Fhoithear
|location  = Near [[Stonehaven]], [[Aberdeenshire]], [[Scotland]]
|image     = [[File:Dunnottar Castle 2.jpg|300px]]
|caption   = Dunnottar Castle
|map_type  = Scotland Aberdeenshire
|map_caption = Location within Aberdeenshire
|coordinates = {{coord|56.946|N|2.197|W|region:GB|display=inline,title}}
|latitude  = 56.946
|longitude = -2.197
|coord_region = GB
|map_size  = 
|type      = 
|built     = c.1400–1600
|builder   =
|materials =
|height    =
|used      = Until 1718
|condition = Ruined
|controlled by = [[Clan Keith]], [[Earl Marischal]]
|ownership = [[Dunecht Estates]]
|open_to_public = Yes
}}

'''Dunnottar Castle''' ({{lang-gd|'''Dùn Fhoithear'''}}, &quot;fort on the shelving slope&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Watson &amp; Macleod (2010), p.8&lt;/ref&gt;) is a ruined [[medieval]] [[fortress]] located upon a rocky headland on the north-east coast of [[Scotland]], about {{convert|3|km}} south of [[Stonehaven]]. The surviving buildings are largely of the 15th and 16th centuries, but the site is believed to have been fortified in the [[Scotland in the Early Middle Ages|Early Middle Ages]]. Dunnottar has played a prominent role in the [[history of Scotland]] through to the 18th-century [[Jacobite risings]] because of its strategic location and defensive strength. Dunnottar is best known as the place where the [[Honours of Scotland]], the Scottish crown jewels, were hidden from [[Oliver Cromwell]]'s invading army in the 17th century. The property of the [[Clan Keith|Keiths]] from the 14th century, and the seat of the [[Earl Marischal]], Dunnottar declined after the last Earl forfeited his titles by taking part in the [[Jacobite rebellion of 1715]]. The castle was restored in the 20th century and is now open to the public.

The ruins of the castle are spread over {{convert|1.4|ha|acre}}, surrounded by steep cliffs that drop to the [[North Sea]], {{convert|50|m}} below. A narrow strip of land joins the headland to the mainland, along which a steep path leads up to the gatehouse. The various buildings within the castle include the 14th-century tower house as well as the 16th-century palace. Dunnottar Castle is a [[scheduled monument]],&lt;ref name=schedule&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2300:35:1560577355318151::NO::P35_SELECTED_MONUMENT:986 |title=Dunnottar Castle |publisher=Historic Scotland |accessdate=27 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and twelve structures on the site are [[listed buildings]].&lt;ref name=listed&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2200:12:0::NO:RP:KEY,COU,PB,CAT,DF,DT,MDE:dunnottar%20castle%2C%2C%2C%2C%2C%2C1 |title=Listed buildings, Dunnottar Castle |publisher=Historic Scotland |accessdate=27 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Early Middle Ages===
[[File:Jacobite broadside - Dunotyr Castle in Merns.jpg|thumb|300px|Historic view of Dunnottar Castle]]
A chapel at Dunnottar is said to have been founded by [[St Ninian]] in the 5th century,&lt;ref name=Coventry/&gt; although it is not clear when the site was first fortified, but in any case the legend is late and highly implausible. Possibly the earliest written reference to the site is found in the [[Annals of Ulster]] which record two sieges of &quot;Dún Foither&quot; in 681 and 694. The earlier event has been interpreted as an attack by [[Bridei III of the Picts|Brude]], the Pictish king of [[Fortriu]], to extend his power over the north-east coast of Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;Alcock &amp; Alcock (1992), p.269&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Scottish Chronicle]] records that King [[Donald II of Scotland|Domnall II]], the first ruler to be called ''rí Alban'' (King of [[Alba]]), was killed at Dunnottar during an attack by Vikings in 900.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson (1990), pp.395–397&lt;/ref&gt; King [[Aethelstan]] of [[Wessex]] led a force into Scotland in 934, and raided as far north as Dunnottar according to the account of [[Symeon of Durham]].&lt;ref&gt;Foot (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; [[W. D. Simpson]] speculated that a [[motte]] might lie under the present caste, but excavations in the 1980s failed to uncover substantive evidence of early medieval fortification. The discovery of a group of [[Pictish stones]] at Dunnicaer, a nearby [[sea stack]], has prompted speculation that &quot;Dún Foither&quot; was actually located on the adjacent headland of Bowduns, {{convert|0.5|km}} to the north.&lt;ref&gt;Alcock &amp; Alcock (1992), pp.281–282&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later Middle Ages===
During the reign of King [[William the Lion]] (ruled 1165–1214) Dunnottar was a center of local administration for [[The Mearns]].&lt;ref name=rcahms&gt;{{cite web|url=http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/36992/details/dunnottar+castle/ |title=Dunnottar Castle |publisher=[[Royal Commission on the Ancient and Historical Monuments of Scotland]] |work=[[Canmore (database)|Canmore]] |accessdate=1 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The castle is named in the ''[[Roman de Fergus]]'', an early 13th-century [[Arthurian]] [[romance (heroic literature)|romance]], in which the hero Fergus must travel to Dunnottar to retrieve a magic shield.&lt;ref name=simpson4&gt;Simpson (1966), p.4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wenthe (2012), pp.45–46&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1276 a church on the site was consecrated by [[William Wishart]], Bishop of St Andrews.&lt;ref name=simpson4/&gt; The poet [[Blind Harry]] relates that [[William Wallace]] captured Dunnottar from the English in 1297, during the [[Wars of Scottish Independence]].  He is said to have imprisoned 4,000 defeated English soldiers in the church and burned them alive.&lt;ref name=Coventry&gt;Coventry (2006), pp.278–279&lt;/ref&gt; In 1336 [[Edward III of England]] ordered William Sinclair, 8th [[Baron of Roslin]], to sail eight ships to the partially ruined Dunnottar for the purpose of rebuilding and fortifying the site as a forward resupply base for his northern campaign. Sinclair took with him 160 soldiers, horses, and a corps of masons and carpenters.&lt;ref name=sumption&gt;Sumption (1991)&lt;/ref&gt; Edward himself visited in July,&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.7&lt;/ref&gt; but the English efforts were undone before the end of the year when the Scottish Regent [[Sir Andrew Murray]] led a force that captured and again destroyed the defences of Dunnottar.&lt;ref name=Coventry/&gt;

In the 14th century Dunnottar was granted to [[William de Moravia, 5th Earl of Sutherland]] (d.1370),&lt;ref name=mcgladdery&gt;McGladdery (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1346 a [[licence to crenellate]] was issued by [[David II of Scotland|David II]].&lt;ref name=geddes&gt;Geddes (2001), pp.25–27&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.8&lt;/ref&gt; Around 1359 William Keith, [[Marischal of Scotland]], married Margaret Fraser, niece of [[Robert the Bruce]], and was granted the barony of Dunnottar at this time. Keith then gave the lands of Dunnottar to his daughter Christian and son-in-law [[Earl of Lindsay|William Lindsay of Byres]], but in 1392 an [[excambion]] (exchange) was agreed whereby Keith regained Dunnottar and Lindsay took lands in Fife.&lt;ref name=mcgladdery/&gt;&lt;ref name=groome/&gt; William Keith completed construction of the tower house at Dunnottar, but was [[excommunicated]] for building on the consecrated ground associated with the parish church. Keith had provided a new parish church closer to Stonehaven, but was forced to write to the Pope, [[Antipope Benedict XIII|Benedict XIII]], who issued a bull in 1395 lifting the excommunication.&lt;ref name=mcgladdery/&gt; William Keith's descendents were created [[Earl Marischal|Earls Marischal]] in the mid 15th century, and they held Dunottar until the 18th century.&lt;ref name=Coventry/&gt;

===16th century rebuilding===
[[File:George Keith, 5th Earl Marischal.jpg|thumb|left|[[George Keith, 5th Earl Marischal]], painted by [[Cosmo Alexander]]]]

Through the 16th century the Keiths improved and expanded their principal seats: at Dunnottar and also at [[Keith Marischal]] in East Lothian. [[James IV of Scotland|James IV]] visited Dunnottar in 1504, and in 1531 [[James V of Scotland|James V]] exempted the Earl's men from military service on the grounds that Dunnottar was one of the &quot;principall strenthis of our realme&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.9&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mary, Queen of Scots]], visited in 1562 after the [[Battle of Corrichie]], and returned in 1564.&lt;ref name=Coventry/&gt; [[James I of England|James VI]] stayed for 10 days in 1580, as part of a [[wikt:progress#Noun|progress]] through Fife and Angus,&lt;ref&gt;Goodare &amp; Lynch (2000), p.1&lt;/ref&gt; during which a meeting of the [[Privy Council of Scotland|Privy Council]] was convened at Dunnottar.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.10&lt;/ref&gt; During a rebellion of Catholic nobles in 1592, Dunnottar was captured by a Captain Carr on behalf of the [[George Gordon, 1st Marquess of Huntly|Earl of Huntly]], but was restored to Lord Marischal just a few weeks later.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), pp.10–11&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1581 [[George Keith, 5th Earl Marischal|George Keith]] succeeded as 5th Earl Marischal, and began a large scale reconstruction that saw the medieval fortress converted into a more comfortable home. The founder of [[Marischal College]] in Aberdeen, the 5th Earl valued Dunnottar as much for its dramatic situation as for its security.&lt;ref&gt;Howard (1995), p.53&lt;/ref&gt; A &quot;palace&quot; comprising a series of ranges around a quadrangle was built on the north-eastern cliffs, creating luxurious living quarters with sea views. The 13th-century chapel was restored and incorporated into the quadrangle.&lt;ref name=geddes/&gt; An impressive stone gatehouse was constructed, now known as Benholm's Lodging, featuring numerous gun ports facing the approach. Although impressive, these are likely to have been fashionable embellishments rather than genuine defensive features.&lt;ref&gt;Cruden (1981), pp.223–224&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil wars===
{{further|Scotland in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms}}
In 1639 [[William Keith, 7th Earl Marischal]], came out in support of the [[Covenanters]], a Presbyterian movement who opposed the established [[Scottish Episcopal Church|Episcopal Church]] and the changes which [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] was attempting to impose. With [[James Graham, 1st Marquess of Montrose]], he marched against the Catholic [[James Gordon, 2nd Viscount Aboyne]], [[Earl of Huntly]], and defeated an attempt by the Royalists to seize [[Stonehaven]]. However, when Montrose changed sides to the Royalists and marched north, Marischal remained in Dunnottar, even when given command of the area by Parliament, and even when Montrose burned Stonehaven.&lt;ref name=Stevenson&gt;Stevenson (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:William Keith, 7th Earl Marischal.jpg|thumb|William Keith, 7th Earl Marischal, painted by [[George Jamesone]] in 1636]]

Marischal then joined with the [[Engager]] faction, who had made a deal with the king, and led a troop of horse to the [[Battle of Preston (1648)|Battle of Preston]] (1648) in support of the royalists.&lt;ref name=Stevenson/&gt; Following the execution of Charles I in 1649, the Engagers gave their allegiance to his son and heir: [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] was proclaimed king, arriving in Scotland in June 1650. He visited Dunnottar in July 1650,&lt;ref name=Stevenson/&gt; but his presence in Scotland prompted [[Oliver Cromwell]] to lead a force into Scotland, defeating the Scots at [[battle of Dunbar (1650)|Dunbar]] in September 1650.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2500:15:0::::BATTLEFIELD:dunbarii |title=Battle of Dunbar II |work=Historic Scotland Battlefields |publisher=Historic Scotland |accessdate=27 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Honours of Scotland===
Charles II was crowned at [[Scone Palace]] on 1 January 1651, at which the [[Honours of Scotland]] (the regalia of crown, sword and sceptre) were used. However, with Cromwell's troops in Lothian, the honours could not be returned to Edinburgh. The Earl Marischal, as Marischal of Scotland, had formal responsibility for the honours,&lt;ref name=Stevenson/&gt; and in June the [[Privy Council of Scotland|Privy Council]] duly decided to place them at Dunnottar.&lt;ref name=groome&gt;Groome (1885), pp.442–443&lt;/ref&gt; They were brought to the castle by Katherine Drummond, hidden in sacks of wool.&lt;ref name=baigent&gt;Baigent (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; Sir George Ogilvie (or Ogilvy) of Barras was appointed lieutenant-governor of the castle, and given responsibility for its defence.&lt;ref name=henderson&gt;Henderson &amp; Furgol (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1651 Cromwell's troops called on Ogilvie to surrender, but he refused. During the subsequent blockade of the castle, the removal of the Honours of Scotland was planned by Elizabeth Douglas, wife of Sir George Ogilvie, and [[Christian Fletcher]], wife of James Granger, minister of Kinneff Parish Church. The king's papers were first removed from the castle by Anne Lindsay, a kinswoman of Elizabeth Douglas, who walked through the besieging force with the papers sewn into her clothes.&lt;ref name=baigent/&gt; Two stories exist regarding the removal of the honours themselves. Fletcher stated in 1664 that over the course of three visits to the castle in February and March 1652, she carried away the crown, sceptre, sword and sword-case hidden amongst sacks of goods. Another account, given in the 18th century by a tutor to the Earl Marischal, records that the honours were lowered from the castle onto the beach, where they were collected by Fletcher's servant and carried off in a [[Creel (basket)|creel]] (basket) of seaweed. Having smuggled the honours from the castle, Fletcher and her husband buried them under the floor of the Old Kirk at [[Kinneff]].&lt;ref name=baigent/&gt;

Meanwhile, by May 1652 the commander of the blockade, Colonel [[Sir Thomas Morgan, 1st Baronet|Thomas Morgan]], had taken delivery of the [[artillery]] necessary for the reduction of Dunnottar.&lt;ref name=henderson/&gt;  Ogilvie surrendered on 24 May, on condition that the garrison could go free. Finding the honours gone, the Cromwellians imprisoned Ogilvie and his wife in the castle until the following year, when a false story was put about suggesting that the honours had been taken overseas.&lt;ref name=henderson/&gt; Much of the castle property was removed, including twenty-one brass cannons,&lt;ref name=m&amp;r/&gt; and Marischal was required to sell further lands and possessions to pay fines imposed by Cromwell's government.&lt;ref name=Stevenson/&gt;

At the [[Restoration (Scotland)|Restoration]] of Charles II in 1660, the honours were removed from Kinneff Church and returned to the king. Ogilvie quarrelled with Marischal's mother over who would take credit for saving the honours,&lt;ref name=Stevenson/&gt; though he was eventually rewarded with a [[baronet]]cy. Fletcher was awarded 2,000 [[merk (coin)|merk]]s by [[Parliament of Scotland|Parliament]] but the sum was never paid.&lt;ref name=baigent/&gt;

[[File:Dunnottar Castle John Slezer.PNG|thumb|left|Dunnottar drawn by [[John Slezer]] in 1693]]

===Whigs and Jacobites===
Religious and political conflicts continued to be played out at Dunnottar through the 17th and early 18th centuries. In 1685, during the [[Archibald Campbell, 9th Earl of Argyll#The .22Argyll expedition.22|rebellion of the Earl of Argyll]] against the new king [[James II of England|James VII]], 167 Covenanters were seized and held in a cellar at Dunnottar. The prisoners included 122 men and 45 women associated with the [[Whiggamore Raid|Whigs]], an anti-Royalist group within the Covenanter movement, and had refused to take an oath of allegiance to the new king.&lt;ref name=DunnottarH2/&gt; The Whigs were imprisoned from 24 May until late July. A group of 25 escaped, although two of these were killed in a fall from the cliffs, and another 15 were recaptured. Five prisoners died in the vault, and 37 of the Whigs were released after taking the oath of allegiance.&lt;ref name=DunnottarH2&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dunnottarcastle.co.uk/history2.cfm |title=Later History |publisher=Dunnottar Castle |accessdate=26 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining prisoners were [[penal transportation|transported]] to [[Perth Amboy, New Jersey]], as part of a colonisation scheme devised by [[George Scot of Pitlochie]]. Many, like Scot himself, died on the voyage.&lt;ref&gt;Handley (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; The cellar, located beneath the &quot;King's Bedroom&quot; in the 16th-century castle buildings, has since become known as the &quot;Whigs' Vault&quot;.&lt;ref name=DunnottarH2/&gt;

Both the [[Jacobitism|Jacobites]] (supporters of the exiled [[House of Stuart|Stuarts]]) and the [[Hanoverians]] (supporters of [[George I of England|George I]] and his descendents) used Dunnottar Castle. In 1689 during [[John Graham, 1st Viscount Dundee|Viscount Dundee]]'s campaign in support of the deposed [[James II of England|James VII]], the castle was garrisoned for [[William and Mary]] with Lord Marischal appointed captain.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.23&lt;/ref&gt; Seventeen suspected Jacobites from Aberdeen were seized and held in the fortress for around three weeks, including George Liddell, professor of mathematics at Marischal College.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www-history.mcs.st-and.ac.uk/Extras/Aberdeen_1.html |title=Mathematics at Aberdeen |work=The MacTutor History of Mathematics archive |publisher=St Andrews University |last=Ponting |first=Betty |accessdate=6 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Jacobite Rising of 1715]] [[George Keith, 10th Earl Marischal]], took an active role with the rebels, leading cavalry at the [[Battle of Sheriffmuir]]. After the subsequent abandonment of the rising Lord Marischal fled to the Continent, eventually becoming French ambassador for [[Frederick the Great]] of [[Prussia]]. Meanwhile, in 1716, his titles and estates including Dunnottar were declared [[wikt:forfeit|forfeit]] to the crown.&lt;ref&gt;Furgol (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later history===
[[File:Dunnottar Castle by Walter Hugh Paton 1867.JPG|thumb|Dunnottar Castle by [[Waller Hugh Paton]], 1867]]
The seized estates of the Earl Marischal were purchased in 1720 for £41,172, by the [[York Buildings Company]] who dismantled much of the castle.&lt;ref name=groome/&gt; In 1761 the Earl briefly returned to Scotland and bought back Dunnottar only to sell it five years later to Alexander Keith, an Edinburgh lawyer who served as [[Knight Marischal]] of Scotland.&lt;ref name=groome/&gt; Dunnottar was inherited in 1852 by [[Murray baronets|Sir Patrick Keith-Murray of Ochtertyre]], who in turn sold it in July 1873 to Major Alexander Innes of Cowie and Raemoir for about £80,000.&lt;ref&gt;Jervise (1875), p.346&lt;/ref&gt; It was purchased by [[Weetman Pearson, 1st Viscount Cowdray]], in 1925 after which his wife embarked on a programme of repairs.&lt;ref name=DunnottarH2/&gt; Since that time the castle has remained in the family, and has been open to the public, attracting 52,500 visitors in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;Martinolli &amp; Bereziat (2010), p.35&lt;/ref&gt;

Dunnottar Castle, and the headland on which is stands, was designated as a [[scheduled monument]] in 1970.&lt;ref name=schedule/&gt;
In 1972 twelve of the structures at Dunnottar were [[listed buildings|listed]].&lt;ref name=listed/&gt;  Three buildings are listed at [[listed building#Scotland|category A]] as being of &quot;national importance&quot;: the keep;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2200:15:0::::BUILDING:2898 |title=Dunnottar Castle: Keep |publisher=Historic Scotland |accessdate=27 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; the entrance gateway;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2200:15:0::::BUILDING:2919 |title=Dunnottar Castle: Entrance gateway and guardrooms |publisher=Historic Scotland |accessdate=27 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Benholm's Lodging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2200:15:0::::BUILDING:2920 |title=Dunnottar Castle: Benholms Lodgings |publisher=Historic Scotland |accessdate=27 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining listings are at category B as being of &quot;regional importance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/index/heritage/historicandlistedbuildings/listing.htm |title=What is Listing? |accessdate=27 November 2012 |publisher=Historic Scotland }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Hon.]] [[Charles Anthony Pearson]], the younger son of the 3rd [[Viscount Cowdray]], currently owns and runs Dunnottar Castle which is part of the {{convert|210|km2|acre|adj=on}} [[Dunecht Estates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dunechtestates.co.uk/ |title=Dunecht Estates |accessdate=26 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Portions of the 1990 film [[Hamlet (1990 film)|''Hamlet'']], starring [[Mel Gibson]] and [[Glenn Close]], were shot there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0099726/locations |title=Filming locations for Hamlet (1990) |work=Internet Movie Database |accessdate=26 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Clear}}

==Description==
[[File:Dunnottar castle plan.png|thumb|right|upright=1.60|Plan of Dunnottar Castle&lt;br/&gt; 
Key: '''A''' Gatehouse and Benholm's Lodging{{·}} '''B''' Tunnels{{·}} '''C''' Tower house{{·}} '''D''' Forge{{·}} '''E''' Waterton's Lodging{{·}} '''F''' Stables{{·}} '''G''' Palace{{·}} '''H''' Chapel{{·}} '''I''' Postern gate{{·}} '''J''' Whigs' Vault{{·}} '''K''' Bowling green{{·}} '''L''' Sentry box{{·}} '''M'''  Cliffs{{·}} '''N''' North Sea]]

Dunnottar's strategic location allowed its owners to control the coastal terrace between the North Sea cliffs and the hills of the [[Mounth]], {{convert|3.5|km}} inland, which enabled access to and from the north-east of Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;Alcock &amp; Alcock (1992), pp.267–269&lt;/ref&gt; The site is accessed via a steep, {{convert|800|m|adj=on}} footpath (with modern staircases) from a car park on the coastal road, or via a {{convert|3|km|adj=on}} cliff-top path from Stonehaven. Dunnottar's several buildings, put up between the 13th and 17th centuries, are arranged across a headland covering around {{convert|1.4|ha}}.&lt;ref name=rcahms/&gt; The dominant building, viewed from the land approach, is the 14th-century [[keep]] or tower house. The other principal buildings are the gatehouse; the chapel; and the 16th-century &quot;palace&quot; which incorporates the &quot;Whigs' Vault&quot;.

[[File:Dunnottar Castle gatehouse.jpg|thumb|left|The gatehouse (centre) and Benholm's Lodging (left) seen from within the castle]]

===Defences===
The approach to the castle is overlooked by outworks on the &quot;Fiddle Head&quot;, a promontory on the western side of the headland.  The entrance is through the well-defended main gate, set in a curtain wall which entirely blocks a cleft in the rocky cliffs.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.29&lt;/ref&gt;  The gate has a [[portcullis]] and has been partly blocked up. Alongside the main gate is the 16th-century Benholm's Lodging, a five-storey building cut into the rock, which incorporated a prison with apartments above.&lt;ref name=geddes/&gt; Three tiers of gun ports face outwards from the lower floors of Benholm's Lodging, while inside the main gate, a group of four gun ports face the entrance. The entrance passage then turns sharply to the left, running underground through two tunnels to emerge near the tower house.&lt;ref name=rcahms/&gt; Simpson contends that these defences are &quot;without exception the strongest in Scotland&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.33&lt;/ref&gt; although later writers have doubted the effectiveness of the gun ports. Cruden notes that the alignment of the gun ports in Benholm's Lodging, facing across the approach rather than along, means that they are of limited efficiency.&lt;ref&gt;Cruden (1981), p.223&lt;/ref&gt; The practicality of the gun ports facing the entrance has also been questioned,&lt;ref name=geddes/&gt; though an inventory of 1612 records that four brass cannons were placed here.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.31&lt;/ref&gt;

A second access to the castle leads up from a rocky cove, the aperture to a marine cave on the northern side of the Dunnottar cliffs into which a small boat could be brought. From here a steep path leads to the well-fortified [[postern|postern gate]] on the cliff top, which in turn offers access to the castle via the Water Gate in the palace. Artillery defences, taking the form of earthworks, surround the north-west corner of the castle, facing inland, and the south-east, facing seaward.&lt;ref name=m&amp;r&gt;MacGibbon &amp; Ross (1887), p.573&lt;/ref&gt; A small sentry box or guard house stands by the eastern battery, overlooking the coast.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.56&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tower house and surrounding buildings===
[[File:Dunnottar Castle - geograph.org.uk - 1550279.jpg|thumb|The tower house of Dunnottar, viewed from the west]]

The late 14th-century tower house has a stone-vaulted basement, and originally had three further storeys and a garret above.&lt;ref name=Coventry/&gt; Measuring {{convert|12|by|11|m}}, the tower house stood {{convert|15|m}} high to its gable.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.35&lt;/ref&gt; The principal rooms included a [[great hall]] and a private chamber for the lord, with bedrooms upstairs.&lt;ref name=geddes/&gt; Beside the tower house is a storehouse, and a blacksmith's [[forge]] with a large chimney.  A stable block is ranged along the southern edge of the headland. Nearby is Waterton's Lodging, also known as the Priest's House, built around 1574,&lt;ref name=&quot;Howard&quot;&gt;Howard (1995), p.83&lt;/ref&gt; possibly for the use of William Keith (died 1580), son of the [[William Keith, 4th Earl Marischal|4th Earl Marischal]].&lt;ref name=geddes/&gt; This small self-contained house includes a hall and kitchen at ground level, with private chambers above, and has a projecting spiral stair on the north side.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howard&quot; /&gt; It is named for Thomas Forbes of Waterton, an attendant of the 7th Earl.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.40&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dunnottar Castle quadrangle.jpg|thumb|left|The palace, from the south-west, with the Silver House in the foreground, and the chapel on the right]]

===The palace===
The palace, to the north-east of the headland, was built in the late 16th century and early to mid-17th century. It comprises three main wings set out around a quadrangle, and for the most part is probably the work of the 5th Earl Marischal who succeeded in 1581.&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;The order of construction of the palace is debated: Simpson (1966, pp.43–49) interprets the west range as the earliest (possibly before 1580), followed by the north and east ranges together, with the north-east wing added last, in 1645. Cruden follows Simpson, though McKean (2004, pp.173–174) states that the north-east wing is contemporary with the east range, and that the north range is later. Geddes (2001, pp.25–27) suggests that the palace was built from east to west.&lt;/ref&gt; It provided extensive and comfortable accommodation to replace the rooms in the tower house. In its long, low design it has been compared to contemporary English buildings, in contrast to the Scottish tradition of taller towers still prevalent in the 16th century.&lt;ref&gt;Cruden (1981), pp.185–186&lt;/ref&gt; Seven identical lodgings are arranged along the west range, each opening onto the quadrangle and including windows and fireplace. Above the lodgings the west range comprised a {{convert|35|m|adj=on}} [[long gallery|gallery]]. Now roofless, the gallery originally had an elaborate oak ceiling, and on display was a Roman tablet taken from the [[Antonine Wall]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/45159/details/auchendavie+east/ |title=Auchendavie East |work=Canmore |publisher=Royal Commission on the Ancient and Historical Monuments of Scotland |accessdate=13 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;The tablet is now in the [[Hunterian Museum]], Glasgow. Simpson (1966), p.43&lt;/ref&gt; At the north end of the gallery was a [[drawing room]] linked to the north range. The gallery could also be accessed from the Silver House to the south, which incorporated a broad stairway with a treasury above.&lt;ref name=geddes/&gt;

The basement of the north range incorporates kitchens and stores, with a dining room and [[great chamber]] above. At ground floor level is the Water Gate, between the north and west ranges, which gives access to the postern on the northern cliffs.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.46&lt;/ref&gt; The east and north ranges are linked via a rectangular stair. The east range has a larder, brewhouse and bakery at ground level, with a suite of apartments for the Countess above. A north-east wing contains the Earl's apartments, and includes the &quot;King's Bedroom&quot; in which Charles II stayed. In this room is a carved stone inscribed with the arms of the 7th Earl and his wife, and the date 1654. Below these rooms is the Whigs' Vault, a cellar measuring  {{convert|16|by|4.5|m}}. This cellar, in which the Covenanters were held in 1685, has a large eastern window, as well as a lower vault accessed via a trap-door in the floor.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), p.50&lt;/ref&gt; Of the chambers in the palace, only the dining room and the Silver House remain roofed, having been restored in the 1920s. The central area contains a circular cistern or fish pond, {{convert|16|m}} across and {{convert|7.6|m}} deep,&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (1966), pp.52–53&lt;/ref&gt; and a bowling green is located to the west.&lt;ref name=Coventry/&gt; At the south-east corner of the quadrangle is the chapel, consecrated in 1276 and largely rebuilt in the 16th century. Medieval walling and two 13th-century windows remain, and there is a graveyard to the south.&lt;ref name=rcahms/&gt;&lt;ref name=geddes/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Dunnottar Parish Church]]
The castle also features in Microsoft Windows 7 desktop themes.

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=&quot;nb&quot;}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite journal |url=http://archaeologydataservice.ac.uk/catalogue/adsdata/arch-352-1/dissemination/pdf/vol_122/122_215_287.pdf |journal=Proceedings of the [[Society of Antiquaries of Scotland]] |volume=122 |year=1992 |pages=215–287 |title=Reconnaissance excavations on Early Historic fortifications and other royal sites in Scotland, 1974-84; 5: A, Excavations &amp; other fieldwork at Forteviot, Perthshire, 1981; B, Excavations at Urquhart Castle, Inverness-shire, 1983; C, Excavations at Dunnottar, Kincardineshire, 1984 |author=Alcock, Leslie |author2=Alcock, Elizabeth A}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=Alan Orr Anderson |last=Anderson |first=Alan Orr |title=Early Sources of Scottish History A.D 500&amp;ndash;1286 |volume=1 |location=Stamford |publisher=Paul Watkins |year=1990 |isbn=1-871615-03-8}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = Baigent | first = Elizabeth | publisher = Oxford University Press | encyclopedia= Oxford Dictionary of National Biography | title=Fletcher, Christian, Lady Abercrombie (1619/20–1691) |format=  | year = 2004 | url =http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/98528|doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/98528}} {{ODNBsub}}
* {{cite book |last=Coventry |first=Martin |title=The Castles of Scotland |edition=4th|publisher=Birlinn |year=2006|isbn=1841584495}}
*{{cite book |author=Cruden, Stewart |title=The Scottish Castle |year=1981 |edition=3rd |publisher=Spurbooks |isbn=0-7157-2088-0}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = Foot | first = Sarah | authorlink= Sarah Foot | publisher = Oxford University Press | encyclopedia= Oxford Dictionary of National Biography | title=Æthelstan (Athelstan) (893/4–939), king of England |format= | year = 2004 | url =http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/833?docPos=2 |doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/833}} {{ODNBsub}}
* {{cite book |last=Geddes |first= Jane |title=Deeside and the Mearns: An Illustrated Architectural Guide |publisher=Rutland Press |location=Edinburgh|year=2001 |isbn=1-873-190-409}}
* {{cite book |last1=Goodare |first1=Julian |last2 = Lynch |first2 = Michael |authorlink2=Michael Lynch (historian) |editor1-last=Goodare |editor1-first = Julian |editor2-last = Lynch |editor2-first = Michael |title=The Reign of James VI |chapter=James VI: Universal King? |year=2000 |publisher=Tuckwell |location=East Linton |isbn=1 86232 095 0 }}
* {{cite book |last=Groome |first= Francis H |authorlink=Francis Hindes Groome |url=http://www.electricscotland.com/history/gazetteer/vol2page442.htm |title=Ordnance Gazetteer of Scotland: A Survey of Scottish Topography, Statistical, Biographical and Historical |publisher=Thomas C. Jack |location=Edinburgh |volume=II |year=1885}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last=Furgol |first=Edward M. | publisher = Oxford University Press | encyclopedia= Oxford Dictionary of National Biography | title=Keith, George, styled tenth Earl Marischal (1692/3?–1778) |format= | year = 2004 | url =http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/15265 |doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/15265}} {{ODNBsub}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = Handley | first = Stuart | publisher = Oxford University Press | encyclopedia= Oxford Dictionary of National Biography | title=Scot, George, of Scotstarvit (d. 1685) |format=| year = 2004 | url =http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/24868 |doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/24868 }} {{ODNBsub}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last1= Henderson | first1= T. F. |last2=Furgol |first2=Edward M. | publisher = Oxford University Press | encyclopedia= Oxford Dictionary of National Biography | title=Ogilvie, Sir George, of Barras, first baronet (fl. 1634–1679) |format= | year = 2004 | url =http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/20594 |doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/20594}} {{ODNBsub}}
*{{cite book |author=Howard, Deborah |year=1995 |title=Scottish Architecture from the Reformation to the Restoration, 1560–1660 |series=The Architectural History of Scotland |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |isbn=978-0-7486-0530-9}}
* {{cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/epitaphsinscript00jerv |last=Jervise |first=Andrew | authorlink=Andrew Jervise |title=Epitaphs &amp; inscriptions from burial grounds &amp; old buildings in the north-east of Scotland, with historical, biographical, genealogical, and antiquarian notes, also, an appendix of illustrative papers |location=Edinburgh |publisher=Edmonston and Douglas |year=1875}}
* {{cite book |title=The Castellated and Domestic Architecture of Scotland |last1=MacGibbon |last2=Ross |first1=David |first2=Thomas |authorlink1=macGibbon and Ross |volume=I |year=1887 |publisher=David Douglas |location=Edinburgh}}
* {{cite book |title=The 2009 Visitor Attraction Monitor |first1=Marina |last1=Martinolli |first2=Claire |last2=Bereziat |others=Moffat Centre for Travel and Tourism Business Development |publisher=VisitScotland |isbn=9781905866496 |url=http://www.moffatcentre.com/media/moffatcentre/documents/visitorattractionreports/vam2009.pdf}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |first=C. A. |last=McGladdery |title=Keith family (per. c.1300–c.1530) |encyclopedia=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography |publisher= Oxford University Press |year=2004 |url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/54235 |format= |doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/54235}} {{ODNBsub}}
* {{cite book |title=The Scottish Chateau |last1=McKean |first1=Charles |authorlink1=Charles McKean |edition=2nd |year=2004 |publisher=Sutton Publishing |location=Stroud |isbn=0 7509 3527 8}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |first=David |last=Stevenson |title=Keith, William, sixth Earl Marischal (1614–1671) |encyclopedia=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography |publisher= Oxford University Press |year=2004 |url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/15278 |format= |doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/15278 }} {{ODNBsub}}
* {{cite book |title=Dunnottar Castle: Historical and Descriptive |last1=Simpson |first1=William Douglas |authorlink1=William Douglas Simpson |edition=10th |year=1966|publisher=Wyllie's |location=Aberdeen}}
*{{cite book |author=Sumption, Jonathan |title=The Hundred Years War |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |year=1991}}
*{{cite book |author=Tabraham, Chris |year=1997 |title=Scotland's Castles |publisher=BT Batsford/Historic Scotland |isbn=0-7134-7965-5}}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Watson |editor1-first=Morag |editor2-last=Macleod |editor2-first=Michelle |title=The Edinburgh Companion to the Gaelic Language |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |year=2010 |location =Edinburgh |isbn=978 0 7486 3709 6}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.openlatch.com/LATCH%20%28Vol.%205,%202012,%20Wenthe,%20Mapping%20Scottish%20Identity,%20pp.%2028-53,%20IP%20Mar%29.pdf |title=Mapping Scottish Identity in the ''Roman de Fergus'' |first=Michael |last=Wenthe |journal=LATCH: A Journal for the Study of the Literary Artifact in Theory, Culture, or History |volume=5 |year=2012 |pages=28–53 |issn = 1940-5731}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Dunnottar Castle}}
*[http://www.dunnottarcastle.co.uk/ Dunnottar Castle homepage]
*[http://www.dunechtestates.co.uk/ Dunecht Estates homepage]
*[http://www.aboutaberdeen.com/dunnottarcastle.php Ghosts, History, Photographs and Paintings of Dunnottar Castle from Aboutaberdeen.com]
* [http://digital.nls.uk/slezer/engraving.cfm?sl=31 Engraving of Dunottar in 1693] by [[John Slezer]] at National Library of Scotland

{{Kincardine and Mearns, Aberdeenshire places|state = collapsed}}

[[Category:Headlands of Scotland]]
[[Category:Category A listed buildings in Aberdeenshire]]
[[Category:Listed castles in Scotland]]
[[Category:Promontory forts in Scotland]]
[[Category:Ruined castles in Aberdeenshire]]
[[Category:Scheduled Ancient Monuments in Scotland]]
[[Category:Romanesque architecture in Scotland]]
[[Category:13th-century establishments in Scotland]]
[[Category:Stonehaven]]
[[Category:Landforms of Aberdeenshire]]</text>
      <sha1>hcokk3sr3ynjcfga2xnfpxcg5cb18w8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
