<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Edward Porter Alexander</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>264462</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750181119</id>
      <parentid>747662104</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T05:48:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>1 archive template merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22551">{{For|the museum administrator|Edward P. Alexander}}
{{good article}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2013}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Edward Porter Alexander
|birth_date= {{birth date|1835|5|26}}
|death_date= {{death date and age|1910|4|28|1835|5|26}}
|image= EdwardPAlexander.jpg
|image_size=250
|caption= Edward Porter Alexander&lt;br /&gt;photo taken between 1862 and 1864
|nickname=
|birth_place= [[Washington, Georgia]]
|death_place= [[Savannah, Georgia]]
|placeofburial= Magnolia Cemetery, [[Augusta, Georgia]]
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|allegiance= {{flagicon|USA|1851}} United States&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Confederate States of America}}
|branch={{army|USA}}&lt;br&gt;{{army|CSA}} [[Military engineer|Engineers]], [[Artillery]]
|serviceyears= 1857–61 (USA)&lt;br /&gt;1861–65 (CSA)
|rank= [[File:Union army 2nd lt rank insignia.jpg|35px]] [[Second Lieutenant#United States|Second Lieutenant (USA)]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Confederate States of America General-collar.svg|35px]] [[Brigadier General (CSA)]]
|unit=
|commands=Artillery
|battles=[[American Civil War]]
* [[First Battle of Bull Run]]
*[[Peninsula Campaign]]
** [[Battle of Williamsburg]]
** [[Battle of Gaines' Mill]]
* [[Northern Virginia Campaign]]
** [[Second Battle of Bull Run]]
* [[Maryland Campaign]]
** [[Battle of Antietam]]
*[[Battle of Fredericksburg]]
*[[Battle of Chancellorsville]]
*[[Battle of Gettysburg]]
*[[Knoxville Campaign]]
*[[Overland Campaign]]
** [[Battle of Spotsylvania Court House]]
** [[Battle of Cold Harbor]]
*[[Richmond-Petersburg Campaign]]
** [[Battle of the Crater]]
** [[Battle of Chaffin's Farm]]
|awards=
|relations=
|laterwork= Railroad executive, planter, and author
}}
'''Edward Porter Alexander''' (May 26, 1835 – April 28, 1910) was a military engineer, railroad executive, planter, and author. He served first as an officer in the [[United States Army]] and later, during the [[American Civil War]] (1861–1865), in the [[Confederate States Army|Confederate Army]], rising to the rank of [[brigadier general]].

Alexander was the officer in charge of the massive artillery bombardment preceding [[Pickett's Charge]], on the third day of the [[Battle of Gettysburg]], and is also noted for his early use of signals and [[History of Military Ballooning|observation balloons]] during combat. After the Civil War, he taught mathematics at the [[University of South Carolina]] in [[Columbia, South Carolina|Columbia]], spent time in [[Nicaragua]], and wrote extensive memoirs and analyses of the war, which have received much praise for their insight and objectivity.  His ''Military Memoirs of a Confederate'' were published in 1907. An extensive personal account of his military training and his participation in the Civil War was rediscovered long after his death and published in 1989 as ''Fighting for the Confederacy''.

==Early life and career==
Alexander, known to his friends as Porter, was born in [[Washington, Georgia]] into a wealthy and distinguished family of planters of the Old South.   He was the sixth of ten children of Adam Leopold Alexander and Sarah Hillhouse Gilbert Alexander.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. 5, 613, 618.&lt;/ref&gt; He became the brother-in-law of [[Alexander R. Lawton]] and [[Jeremy F. Gilmer]].&lt;ref name=Eicher&gt;Eicher, ''Civil War High Commands'', p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; He graduated from the [[United States Military Academy]] at [[West Point, New York|West Point]] in 1857, third in his class of 38 cadets, and was [[brevet (military)|brevetted]] a [[Second Lieutenant#United States|second lieutenant]] of engineers. He briefly taught engineering and fencing at the academy before he was ordered to report to [[Brigadier general (United States)|Brig. Gen.]] [[Albert Sidney Johnston]] for the [[Utah War]] expedition. That mission ended before he could reach Johnston, and Alexander returned to West Point. He participated in a number of weapon experiments and worked as an assistant to Major [[Albert J. Myer]], the first officer assigned to the [[Signal Corps in the American Civil War|Signal Corps]] and the inventor of the code for &quot;wig-wag&quot; signal flags, or &quot;aerial telegraphy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, p. 21; Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. 13–14.&lt;/ref&gt;  Alexander was promoted to second lieutenant on October 10, 1858.&lt;ref name=Eicher/&gt;

Alexander met Bettie Mason of Virginia in 1859 and married her on April 3, 1860.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; They would eventually have six children: Bessie Mason (born 1861), Edward Porter II and Lucy Roy (twins, born 1863), an unnamed girl (1865, died in infancy prior to naming), Adam Leopold (1867), and William Mason (1868).&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', p. 612.&lt;/ref&gt; Lt. Alexander's final assignments for the U.S. Army were at [[Fort Steilacoom]], in the [[Washington Territory]],&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. 16–21.&lt;/ref&gt; and at [[Alcatraz Island]], near [[San Francisco, California]].&lt;ref name=Heidler&gt;Heidler, pp. 29–31.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Civil War service==
After learning of the [[secession]] of his home state of Georgia, Alexander resigned his U.S. Army commission on May 1, 1861, to join the Confederate Army as a captain of engineers. While organizing and training new recruits to form a Confederate signal service, he was ordered to report to [[Brig. Gen. (CSA)|Brig. Gen.]] [[P. G. T. Beauregard|P.G.T. Beauregard]] at [[Manassas, Virginia|Manassas Junction, Virginia]]. He became the chief engineer and signal officer of the [[Confederate Army of the Potomac]] on June 3.&lt;ref name=Eicher/&gt;

At the [[First Battle of Bull Run]], Alexander made history by being the first to use signal flags to transmit a message during combat over a long distance.  Stationed atop &quot;Signal Hill&quot; in Manassas, Alexander saw [[Union Army|Union]] troop movements and signaled to the brigade under Col. [[Nathan George Evans|Nathan &quot;Shanks&quot; Evans]], &quot;Look out for your left, your position is turned&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 43–45; Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. 50–51. Alexander recalls that the signal was &quot;You are flanked.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Upon receiving a similar message, Beauregard and Gen. [[Joseph E. Johnston]] sent timely reinforcements that turned the tide of battle in the Confederates' favor.&lt;ref name=Heidler/&gt;

Alexander was promoted to [[Major (United States)|major]] on July 1 and [[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|lieutenant colonel]] on December 31, 1861.&lt;ref name=Eicher/&gt; During much of this period he was chief of ordnance, under Johnston's command, managing supplies and ammunition in what later became the [[Army of Northern Virginia]].  He was also active in signal work and intelligence gathering, dealing extensively with spies operating around [[Washington, D.C.]]&lt;ref name=Heidler/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. 69–72.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the early days of the [[Peninsula Campaign]] of 1862, Alexander continued as chief of ordnance under Johnston, but he also fought at the [[Battle of Williamsburg]], under [[Major General (CSA)|Maj. Gen.]] [[James Longstreet]].  When [[Full General (CSA)|Gen.]] [[Robert E. Lee]] assumed command of the army, Alexander was in charge of pre-positioned ordnance for Lee's offensive in the [[Seven Days Battles]]. Alexander continued his intelligence gathering by volunteering to go up in an observation balloon at [[Battle of Gaines' Mill|Gaines' Mill]] on June 27, ascending several times and returning with valuable intelligence regarding the position of the Union Army.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. 115–17.&lt;/ref&gt;

Alexander continued in charge of ordnance for the [[Northern Virginia Campaign]] ([[Second Battle of Bull Run|Second Bull Run]]) and the [[Maryland Campaign]] ([[Battle of Antietam|Antietam]]).&lt;ref name=Heidler/&gt;  He barely missed capture by Federal cavalry, under Col. [[Benjamin Franklin Davis|Benjamin F. &quot;Grimes&quot; Davis]], that had escaped from [[Battle of Harpers Ferry|Harpers Ferry]] during the Maryland Campaign; over 40 of Longstreet's 80 ammunition wagons were captured.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', p. 144. In his earlier work, ''Military Memoirs'', p. 232, Alexander incorrectly identified the cavalry as under the command of Brig. Gen. [[David McMurtrie Gregg]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Porter Alexander is best known as an artilleryman who played a prominent role in many of the important battles of the war. He served in different artillery capacities for Longstreet's [[First Corps, Army of Northern Virginia|First Corps]] of the Army of Northern Virginia, starting that role on November 7, 1862, after leaving Lee's staff to command the battalion that was the corps' artillery reserve. He was promoted to colonel on December 5.&lt;ref name=Eicher/&gt; He was instrumental in arranging the artillery in defense of Marye's Heights at the [[Battle of Fredericksburg]] in December 1862, which proved to be the decisive factor in the Confederate victory. While the rest of Longstreet's corps was located around [[Suffolk, Virginia]], Alexander accompanied [[Stonewall Jackson]] on his flanking march at the [[Battle of Chancellorsville]] in May 1863, and his artillery placements in Hazel Grove at Chancellorsville proved decisive.&lt;ref name=Heidler/&gt;

===Gettysburg cannonade===
[[File:AlexandersBattalion.JPG|thumb|The monument on [[Seminary Ridge]] that marks the location of Alexander's artillery.]]

Alexander's most famous engagement was on July 3, 1863, at the [[Battle of Gettysburg]], during which he was in command of the artillery for Longstreet's corps. On that day, he was effectively in control of the artillery for the full army (despite Brig. Gen. [[William N. Pendleton]]'s formal role as chief of artillery under Lee). He conducted a massive two-hour bombardment, arguably the largest in the war, using between 150 and 170 guns&lt;ref&gt;Estimates of guns employed vary; see footnote in [[Pickett's Charge]].&lt;/ref&gt; against the Union position on [[Cemetery Ridge]]. Unfortunately, the poor quality of the Confederate fuses delayed the planned detonation of many of the shells, and a number of the guns were not properly ranged, so that the rear areas sustained more damage than the front lines.&lt;ref&gt;Sears, p. 397.&lt;/ref&gt; General Longstreet effectively put Alexander in charge of launching Maj. Gen. [[George Pickett]] on his famous charge, placing the young colonel under enormous pressure to determine whether the Union artillery defenses had been suppressed.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander's counterpart, Union Brig. Gen. [[Henry J. Hunt]], was able to conserve his artillery and deceive Alexander about its remaining effectiveness; see [[Pickett's Charge]].&lt;/ref&gt; Alexander would blame Lee for the defeat at Gettysburg, writing in 1901: &quot;Never, never, never did Gen. Lee himself bollox {{sic}} a fight as he did this.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gallagher, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Longstreet's Chief of Artillery===

Alexander accompanied the First Corps to northern Georgia in the fall of 1863 to reinforce Gen. [[Braxton Bragg]] for the [[Battle of Chickamauga]]. He personally arrived too late to participate in the battle, but served as Longstreet's chief of artillery in the subsequent [[Knoxville Campaign]] and in the [[Department of East Tennessee and West Virginia|Department of East Tennessee]] in early 1864. He returned with the corps to Virginia for the remainder of the war, now with the rank of [[Brig. Gen. (CSA)|brigadier general]] (as of February 26, 1864). He served in all the battles of the [[Overland Campaign]], and when Lt. Gen. [[Ulysses S. Grant]] slipped around Lee's army to cross the [[James River (Virginia)|James River]] and assault [[Petersburg, Virginia|Petersburg]], Alexander was able to move his guns quickly through the lines, emplacing them to repel the main attack.&lt;ref name=Heidler/&gt;

During the [[Siege of Petersburg]], Alexander had to adapt his artillery tactics to trench warfare, including experimentation with various types of mortars. He became convinced that the Union forces were attempting to tunnel under the Confederate lines, but before he was able to act on this, on June 30, 1864, he was wounded in the shoulder by a sharpshooter. As he departed on medical leave to Georgia, he informed Lee of his suspicion. After unsuccessful attempts were made to locate the tunneling activity, the [[Battle of the Crater]] caught the Confederates by surprise, although it ended in a significant Union defeat. Alexander returned to the Army in February 1865 and supervised the defenses of [[Richmond, Virginia|Richmond]] along the James River. He retreated along with Lee's army in the [[Appomattox Campaign]].&lt;ref name=Heidler/&gt;

At [[Appomattox Court House National Historical Park|Appomattox Court House]], it was Alexander who made the famous proposal to Robert E. Lee that the army disperse, rather than surrendering. Lee rebuked him, and Alexander later wrote about regretting his suggestion. Although this incident is sometimes described as a proposal for &quot;[[guerrilla war]]&quot;, Alexander describes his proposal in his memoir, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', as one in which &quot;the army may be ordered to scatter in the woods &amp; bushes &amp; either to rally upon Gen. Johnston in North Carolina, or to make their way, each man to his own state, with his arms, &amp; to report to his governor.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. 531–33.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Confederate Gold===

Since the end of the Civil War, stories of the [[Confederate gold]] and its vast wealth have been told and retold. One of those stories involves Alexander. He helped organize search parties in [[Lincoln County, Georgia|Lincoln]] and [[Wilkes County, Georgia|Wilkes]] counties. Alexander and bank officials soon located some of the gold through Alexander's neighbors in Wilkes county and persuaded them that the money belonged to wives and children of Confederate veterans. With Alexander's help, bank officials eventually recovered some $111,000 of the stolen money. Former Confederate cabinet official [[Robert Toombs]] also turned over $5,000 that, intentionally or accidentally, had been thrown into his yard in Washington.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Davis|first1=Robert Scott|title=The Georgia Odyssey of the Confederate Gold|journal=Georgia Historical Quarterly|date=2002|volume=86|issue=4|url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=a9h&amp;AN=9425698&amp;site=eds-live&amp;scope=site|accessdate=3 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later life==
[[File:Edward Porter Alexander, circa 1900s.jpg|thumb|Edward Porter Alexander in 1900s]]
After the surrender, Alexander briefly considered joining the [[Brazil]]ian Army.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', p. 531.&lt;/ref&gt; Finding that he no longer desired the Georgia plantation life of his youth, he taught mathematics at the [[University of South Carolina]] in [[Columbia, South Carolina|Columbia]], and then served in executive positions with the [[Charlotte, Columbia, and Augusta Railroad]] (executive superintendent), the [[Savannah and Memphis Railroad]] (president), the [[Louisville and Nashville Railroad]] (president),&lt;ref name=Eicher/&gt; and in the late 1880s the [[Central Rail Road and Banking Company of Georgia]] until 1891.

Alexander became friends with [[Grover Cleveland]] and the two spent many hours hunting for ducks on Alexander's estate. In May 1897, President Cleveland appointed Alexander as the arbiter of the commission tasked with fixing and demarcating the boundary between the Republics of [[Nicaragua]] and [[Costa Rica]], with a view towards the possible construction of [[Nicaragua Canal|an interoceanic canal]] to be dug across [[Central America]]. Alexander spent two years at the head of that commission, headquartered in the coastal village of [[San Juan de Nicaragua|Greytown]] (now San Juan de Nicaragua).  He completed the work to the satisfaction of the two governments and returned to the U.S. in October 1899.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', p. xvi.&lt;/ref&gt; His wife Bettie became ill while he was in Nicaragua and she died shortly after his return, on November 20, 1899. In October 1901, Alexander married Mary Mason, his first wife's niece.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', pp. xix, 559.&lt;/ref&gt;

Alexander was selected to give the Confederate veteran's speech on Alumni Day during the centennial celebration at the United States Military Academy on June 9, 1902.  The speech was so well received that it was reprinted in the NY Times in its entirety in the 15 June 1902 edition. The NY Times referred to the speech as &quot;decidedly the feature of Alumni Day.&quot;&lt;ref&gt; https://archive.org/details/confederateveter00alex&lt;/ref&gt; The audience included President Theodore Roosevelt as well as Alexander's former commander, General Longstreet.
  
After the war, Alexander became a well-respected author.  He wrote many magazine articles and published his ''Military Memoirs of a Confederate: A Critical Narrative'' (1907), praised by [[Douglas Southall Freeman]] as &quot;altogether the best critique of the operations of the Army of Northern Virginia.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, ''Fighting for the Confederacy'', p. xiii.&lt;/ref&gt;  Long after his death, it was realized that Alexander had produced the ''Military Memoirs'', which sought to be a professional work of military history and analysis, after a long effort of editing a collection of much more personal memoirs that he had started compiling during his time in Greytown, Nicaragua, at the behest of his family.  Those earlier memoirs were edited and published posthumously in 1989 as ''Fighting for the Confederacy: The Personal Recollections of General Edward Porter Alexander''.

Unlike such Confederate officers as [[Jubal Anderson Early|Jubal Early]] and [[William N. Pendleton|William Pendleton]], Alexander eschewed the bitter [[Lost Cause of the Confederacy|Lost Cause]] theories of why the South was doomed to fail, given the overwhelming superiority of the North.  He was willing to express in writing his criticisms of prominent Confederate officers, including [[Robert E. Lee|General Lee]] himself.  Many historians regard Alexander's memoirs as among the most objective and sharpest sources produced by a Civil War combatant.  [[David J. Eicher|David Eicher]] called ''Fighting for the Confederacy'' &quot;a superb personal narrative with a good deal of analysis of Lee's operations ... Dramatic and revealing, an important source on the general, his fellow officers, and the Army of Northern Virginia.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Eicher, ''Civil War in Books'', p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; Alexander's other books include ''Railway Practice'' (1887) and ''Catterel, Ratterel (Doggerel)'' (1888).&lt;ref&gt;Dupuy, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; Alexander died in [[Savannah, Georgia]] and is buried in Magnolia Cemetery, [[Augusta, Georgia]].

==In Popular Culture==
*Alexander was portrayed by [[James Patrick Stuart]] in the 1993 film ''[[Gettysburg (1993 film)|Gettysburg]]'' and its 2003 prequel ''[[Gods and Generals (film)|Gods and Generals]]''.
*In the alternate history novel ''[[How Few Remain]]'', Alexander continues his career as a brigadier general long after the [[Confederate States of America]] wins the civil war and was instrumental in defending [[Confederate Kentucky]] and fending off another Union invasion while under [[Stonewall Jackson]] during a second war with the United States in the 1880's.
* Alexander is a character in the [[alternate history (fiction)|alternate history]] novels ''[[Gettysburg: A Novel of the Civil War]]'' (2003), &quot;[[Grant Comes East]]&quot; (2004), and [[Never Call Retreat: Lee and Grant: The Final Victory]] (2005) by [[Newt Gingrich]] and [[William Forstchen]].

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|United States Army|American Civil War}}
*[[List of American Civil War generals (Confederate)]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* Alexander, Edward P. ''Fighting for the Confederacy: The Personal Recollections of General Edward Porter Alexander''. Edited by Gary W. Gallagher. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1989. ISBN 0-8078-4722-4.
* Alexander, Edward P. ''Military Memoirs of a Confederate: A Critical Narrative''. New York: Da Capo Press, 1993. ISBN 0-306-80509-X. First published 1907 by Charles Scribner's Sons.
* Brown, J. Willard. ''The Signal Corps, U.S.A. in the War of the Rebellion''. U.S. Veteran Signal Corps Association, 1896. Reprinted 1974 by Arno Press. ISBN 0-405-06036-X.
* Dupuy, Trevor N., Curt Johnson, and David L. Bongard. ''The Harper Encyclopedia of Military Biography''. New York: HarperCollins, 1992. ISBN 978-0-06-270015-5.
* [[David J. Eicher|Eicher, David J.]] ''The Longest Night: A Military History of the Civil War''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 2001. ISBN 0-684-84944-5.
* Eicher, John H., and David J. Eicher. ''Civil War High Commands''. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 2001. ISBN 0-8047-3641-3.
* Gallagher, Gary W., ed. ''Three Days at Gettysburg: Essays on Confederate and Union Leadership''. Kent, OH: Kent State University Press, 1999. ISBN 0-87338-629-9.
* Heidler, David S., and Jeanne T. Heidler. &quot;Edward Porter Alexander.&quot; In ''Encyclopedia of the American Civil War: A Political, Social, and Military History'', edited by David S. Heidler and Jeanne T. Heidler. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2000. ISBN 0-393-04758-X.
* [[Stephen W. Sears|Sears, Stephen W.]] ''Gettysburg''. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 2003. ISBN 0-395-86761-4.

==Further reading==
* Klein, Maury. ''Edward Porter Alexander''. Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1971. ISBN 0-318-77984-6.

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
* [http://www.lib.unc.edu/mss/inv/a/Alexander,Edward_Porter.html Inventory of the Edward Porter Alexander Papers, 1852–1910], in the [[Southern Historical Collection]], [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill|UNC-Chapel Hill]]
* {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080208215607/http://www.generalsandbrevets.com/sga/alexander.htm |date=February 8, 2008 |title=Photographs of Alexander }}
* [http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=8335 ''Edward Porter Alexander'' Find a Grave No. 8335] Retrieved May 7, 2016.
{{Gettysburg figures|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alexander, Edward Porter}}
[[Category:1835 births]]
[[Category:1910 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Washington, Georgia]]
[[Category:American memoirists]]
[[Category:Confederate States Army brigadier generals]]
[[Category:United States Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:People of Georgia (U.S. state) in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:American planters]]
[[Category:Writers from Georgia (U.S. state)]]</text>
      <sha1>pcdy4s2i6t27y4gdpij1s2h27vkrhuz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
