<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Einsatzgruppen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>510764</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748818090</id>
      <parentid>745599411</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-10T15:46:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CitationCleanerBot</username>
        <id>15270283</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up, url redundant with jstor, and/or remove accessdate if no url using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="74810">{{Other uses|Organisation Todt#Administrative units{{!}}Organisation Todt § Administrative units}}
{{sprotect2}}
{{Italic title}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2016}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox government agency
| agency_name   = ''Einsatzgruppen''
| nativename    =
| nativename_a  =
| nativename_r  =
| logo          =Flag Schutzstaffel.svg
| logo_width    = 100px
| logo_caption  = The ''Einsatzgruppen'' operated under the administration of the ''[[Schutzstaffel]]'' (SS)
| seal          =
| seal_width    =
| seal_caption  =
| picture       =Jew_Killings_in_Ivangorod_(1942).jpg
| picture_width = 250px
| picture_caption = Killing of Jews at [[Ivanhorod]], Ukraine, 1942. A woman is attempting to protect a child with her own body just before they are fired on with rifles at close range.
| formed        =c. 1939
| preceding1    = ''Einsatzkommando''
| preceding2    =
| dissolved     =
| superseding   =
| jurisdiction  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Nazi Germany]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Occupied Europe]]
| headquarters  = [[RSHA]], [[Niederkirchnerstraße|Prinz-Albrecht-Straße]], Berlin
| latd=52  |latm=30  |lats=26  |latNS=N
| longd=13 |longm= 22|longs=57 |longEW= E
| region_code   =
| employees     = c. 3,000 (1941)
| budget        =
| minister1_name  = [[Heinrich Himmler]]
| minister1_pfo   = [[Reichsführer-SS]]
| minister2_name  =
| minister2_pfo   =
| chief1_name     = SS-''[[Obergruppenführer]]'' [[Reinhard Heydrich]]
| chief1_position = Director, RSHA (1939–1942)
| chief2_name     =SS-''Obergruppenführer'' Dr. [[Ernst Kaltenbrunner]]
| chief2_position = Director, RSHA (1943–1945)
| agency_type   =
| parent_agency =[[File:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|23px]] [[Allgemeine SS]] and RSHA
| child1_agency =
| child2_agency =
| child3_agency =
| website       =
| footnotes     =
}}

'''''Einsatzgruppen''''' (German for &quot;[[task force]]s&quot;,{{sfn|LEO Dictionary}} &quot;deployment groups&quot;;{{sfn|Encyclopaedia Britannica}} singular ''Einsatzgruppe''; official full name ''Einsatzgruppen der Sicherheitspolizei und des SD'') were ''[[Schutzstaffel]]'' (SS) paramilitary [[death squad]]s of [[Nazi Germany]] that were responsible for mass killings, primarily by shooting, during [[World War II]]. The ''Einsatzgruppen'' were involved in the murder of much of the [[intelligentsia]] and cultural elite of Poland, and had an integral role in the implementation of the so-called &quot;[[Final Solution]] to the [[Jewish question]]&quot; (''Die Endlösung der Judenfrage'') in territories conquered by Nazi Germany. Almost all of the people they killed were civilians, beginning with the intelligentsia and swiftly progressing to Soviet [[political commissar]]s, [[Jew]]s, and [[Romani people|Gypsies]] throughout Eastern Europe.

Under the direction of ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] and the supervision of SS-''[[Obergruppenführer]]'' [[Reinhard Heydrich]], the ''Einsatzgruppen'' operated in territories occupied by the [[Wehrmacht|German armed forces]] following the [[invasion of Poland]] in September 1939 and [[Operation Barbarossa]] (the invasion of the Soviet Union) in June 1941. The ''Einsatzgruppen'' worked hand-in-hand with the [[Ordnungspolizei#Police Battalions|Orpo Police Battalions]] on the Eastern Front to carry out operations ranging from the murder of a few people to operations which lasted over two or more days, such as the massacre at [[Babi Yar]] with 33,771 Jews killed in two days, and the [[Rumbula massacre]] (with about 25,000 killed in two days of shooting). As ordered by Nazi leader [[Adolf Hitler]], the [[Wehrmacht]] cooperated with the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and provided logistical support for their operations. Historian [[Raul Hilberg]] estimates that between 1941 and 1945 the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and related auxiliary troops killed more than two million people, including 1.3 million Jews. The total number of Jews murdered during [[the Holocaust]] is estimated at 5.5 to 6 million people.

After the close of World War II, 24 senior leaders of the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were prosecuted in the [[Einsatzgruppen Trial]] in 1947–48, charged with [[crimes against humanity]] and [[war crimes]]. Fourteen death sentences and two life sentences were handed out. Four additional ''Einsatzgruppe'' leaders were later tried and executed by other nations.

== Formation and Action T4 ==
The ''Einsatzgruppen'' were formed under the direction of SS-''Obergruppenführer'' Reinhard Heydrich and operated by the ''[[Schutzstaffel]]'' (SS) before and during [[World War II]].{{sfn|Edeiken|2000}} The ''Einsatzgruppen'' had its origins in the ad hoc ''Einsatzkommando'' formed by Heydrich to secure government buildings and documents following the ''[[Anschluss]]'' in [[Austria]] in March 1938.{{sfn|Streim|1989|p=436}} Originally part of the ''[[Sicherheitspolizei]]'' (Security Police; SiPo), two units of ''Einsatzgruppen'' were stationed in the [[Sudetenland]] in October 1938. When military action turned out not to be necessary because of the [[Munich Agreement]], the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were assigned to confiscate government papers and police documents. They also secured government buildings, questioned senior civil servants, and arrested as many as 10,000 Czech communists and German citizens.{{sfn|Streim|1989|p=436}}{{sfn|Longerich|2012|pp=405, 412}} From September 1939, the ''[[Reichssicherheitshauptamt]]'' (Reich Main Security Office; RSHA) had overall command of the ''Einsatzgruppen''.{{sfn|Nuremberg Trial, Vol. 20, Day 194}}

As part of the drive to remove &quot;undesirable&quot; elements from the German population, from September to December 1939 the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and others took part in [[Action T4]], a programme of systematic murder of the physically and mentally handicapped and psychiatric hospital patients undertaken by the Nazi regime. Action T4 mainly took place from 1939 to 1941, but continued until the end of the war. Initially the victims were shot by the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and others, but [[gas chamber]]s were put into use by spring 1940.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=138–141}}

== Invasion of Poland ==
{{main article|Intelligenzaktion|Operation Tannenberg}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1968-034-19A, Exekution von polnischen Geiseln.jpg|thumb|Execution of Poles in [[Kórnik]], 20 October 1939]]

In response to ''[[Führer und Reichskanzler]]'' [[Adolf Hitler]]'s plan to [[invasion of Poland|invade Poland]], Heydrich re-formed the ''Einsatzgruppen'' to travel in the wake of the German armies.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=425}} Membership at this point was drawn from the SS, the ''[[Sicherheitsdienst]]'' (Security Service; SD), and the police.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=144}} Heydrich placed SS-''Obergruppenführer'' [[Werner Best]] in command, who chose leaders for the task forces and their subgroups, called ''[[Einsatzkommando]]s'', from among educated people with military experience. Some had previously been members of paramilitary groups such as the [[Freikorps]].{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=17}}

Numbering some 2,700 men at this point,{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=17}} the ''Einsatzgruppen''{{'}}s mission was the forceful de-politicisation of the Polish people and the elimination of groups most clearly identified with Polish national identity: the intelligentsia, members of the clergy, teachers, and members of the nobility.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=144}}{{sfn|Browning|Matthäus|2004|pp=16–18}} As stated by Hitler: &quot;...&amp;nbsp;there must be no Polish leaders; where Polish leaders exist they must be killed, however harsh that sounds&quot;.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=143}} The ''[[Sonderfahndungsbuch Polen]]'' — lists of people to be killed — had been drawn up by the SS as early as May 1939.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=144}} The ''Einsatzgruppen'' performed these murders with the support of the ''[[Volksdeutscher Selbstschutz]]'', a paramilitary group consisting of ethnic Germans living in Poland.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=144–145}} Members of the SS, the [[Wehrmacht]], and the ''[[Ordnungspolizei]]'' (Order Police; Orpo) also shot civilians during the Polish campaign.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=429}} Approximately 65,000 civilians were killed by the end of 1939. In addition to leaders of Polish society, they killed Jews, prostitutes, [[Romani people]], and the mentally ill. Psychiatric patients in Poland were initially killed by shooting, but by spring 1941 [[gas van]]s were widely used.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=15}}{{sfn|Longerich|2012|pp=430–432}}

Seven ''Einsatzgruppen'' of battalion strength operated in Poland. Each was subdivided into four ''Einsatzkommandos'' of company strength.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=225}}

* ''Einsatzgruppe'' I, commanded by SS-''[[Standartenführer]]'' [[Bruno Streckenbach]], acted with [[14th Army (Wehrmacht)|14th Army]]
* ''Einsatzgruppe'' II, SS-''[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' [[Emanuel Schäfer]], acted with [[10th Army (Wehrmacht)|10th Army]]
* ''Einsatzgruppe'' III, SS-''Obersturmbannführer und Regierungsrat'' Dr. Herbert Fischer, acted with [[8th Army (Wehrmacht)|8th Army]]
* ''Einsatzgruppe'' IV, SS-''[[Brigadeführer]]'' [[Lothar Beutel]], acted with [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|4th Army]]
* ''Einsatzgruppe'' V, SS-''Standartenfürer'' [[Ernst Damzog]], acted with [[3rd Army (Wehrmacht)|3rd Army]]
* ''Einsatzgruppe'' VI, SS-''[[Oberführer]]'' [[Erich Naumann]], acted in [[Wielkopolska]]
* ''Einsatzgruppe'' VII, SS-''Obergruppenführer'' [[Udo von Woyrsch]] and SS-''[[Gruppenführer]]'' [[Otto Rasch]], acted in [[Upper Silesia]] and [[Cieszyn Silesia]]{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=225}}

Though they were formally under the command of the army, the ''Einsatzgruppen'' received their orders directly from Heydrich and for the most part acted independently of the army.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=18}}{{sfn|Gerwarth|2011|p=147}} Many senior army officers were only too glad to leave these genocidal actions to the task forces, as the killings violated the rules of warfare as set down in the [[Geneva Conventions]]. However, Hitler had decreed that the army would have to tolerate and even offer logistical support to the ''Einsatzgruppen'' when it was tactically possible to do so. Some army commanders complained about unauthorised shootings, looting, and rapes committed by members of the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and the ''Volksdeutscher Selbstschutz'', to little effect.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=146}} For example, when ''[[Generaloberst]]'' [[Johannes Blaskowitz]] sent a memorandum of complaint to Hitler about the atrocities, Hitler dismissed his concerns as &quot;childish&quot;, and Blaskowitz was relieved of his post in May 1940. He continued to serve in the army but never received promotion to [[field marshal]].{{sfn|Evans|2008|pp=25–26}}

The final task of the ''Einsatzgruppen'' in Poland was to round up the remaining Jews and concentrate them in [[Ghettos in Nazi-occupied Europe|ghettos]] within major cities with good railway connections. The intention was to eventually remove all the Jews from Poland, but at this point their final destination had not yet been determined.{{sfn|Weale|2012|pp=227–228}}{{sfn|Weale|2012|pp=242–245}} Together, the Wehrmacht and the ''Einsatzgruppen'' also drove tens of thousands of Jews eastward into [[Occupation of Poland (1939–45)#Soviet administration zone|Soviet-controlled territory]].{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=429}}

== Preparations for Operation Barbarossa ==
{{main article|The Holocaust in Belarus|The Holocaust in Ukraine|The Holocaust in Russia}}

On 13 March 1941, in the lead-up to [[Operation Barbarossa]], the planned invasion of the Soviet Union, Hitler dictated his &quot;Guidelines in Special Spheres re: Directive No. 21 (Operation Barbarossa)&quot;. Sub-paragraph B specified that ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] would be given &quot;special tasks&quot; on direct orders from the Führer, which he would carry out independently.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=95}} This directive was intended to prevent friction between the Wehrmacht and the SS in the upcoming offensive.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=95}} Hitler also specified that criminal acts against civilians perpetrated by members of the Wehrmacht during the upcoming campaign would not be prosecuted in the military courts, and thus would go unpunished.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|pp=521–522}}

In a speech to his leading generals on 30 March 1941, Hitler described his envisioned war against the Soviet Union. General [[Franz Halder]], the Army's Chief of Staff, described the speech:{{quote|Struggle between two ideologies. Scathing evaluation of Bolshevism, equals antisocial criminality. Communism immense future danger&amp;nbsp;... This a fight to the finish. If we do not accept this, we shall beat the enemy, but in thirty years we shall again confront the Communist foe. We don't make war to preserve the enemy&amp;nbsp;... Struggle against Russia: Extermination of Bolshevik Commissars and of the Communist intelligentsia&amp;nbsp;... Commissars and GPU personnel are criminals and must be treated as such. The struggle will differ from that in the west. In the east harshness now means mildness for the future.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|pp=95–96}} }}

Though General Halder did not record any mention of Jews, German historian [[Andreas Hillgruber]] argued that because of Hitler's frequent contemporary statements about the coming war of annihilation against &quot;[[Jewish Bolshevism|Judeo-Bolshevism]]&quot;, his generals would have understood Hitler's call for the destruction of the Soviet Union as also comprising a call for the destruction of its Jewish population.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|pp=95–96}} The genocide was often described using euphemisms such as &quot;special tasks&quot; and &quot;executive measures&quot;; ''Einsatzgruppe'' victims were often described as having been shot while trying to escape.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=14, 48}} In May 1941, Heydrich verbally passed on the order to kill the Soviet Jews to the SiPo NCO School in [[Pretzsch, Wittenberg|Pretzsch]], where the commanders of the reorganised ''Einsatzgruppen'' were being trained for Operation Barbarossa.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|pp=94–95}} In spring 1941, Heydrich and the First Quartermaster of the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|''Wehrmacht Heer'']], General [[Eduard Wagner]], successfully completed negotiations for co-operation between the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and the German Army to allow the implementation of the &quot;special tasks&quot;.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|pp=94–96}} Following the Heydrich-Wagner agreement on 28 April 1941, Field Marshal [[Walther von Brauchitsch]] ordered that when Operation Barbarossa began, all German Army commanders were to immediately identify and register all Jews in occupied areas in the Soviet Union, and fully co-operate with the ''Einsatzgruppen''.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=96}}

In further meetings held in June 1941 Himmler outlined to top SS leaders the regime's intention to reduce the population of the Soviet Union by 30 million people, not only through direct killing of those considered [[racial policy of Nazi Germany|racially inferior]], but by depriving the remainder of food and other necessities of life.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=181}}

=== Organisation starting in 1941 ===

{{further information|List of Einsatzgruppen}}

For Operation Barbarossa, initially four ''Einsatzgruppen'' were created, each numbering 500–990 men to comprise a total force of 3,000.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=185}} ''Einsatzgruppen'' A, B, and C were to be attached to [[Army Group North|Army Groups North]], [[Army Group Centre|Centre]], and [[Army Group South|South]]; ''Einsatzgruppe'' D was assigned to the [[11th Army (Wehrmacht)|11th Army]]. The ''Einsatzgruppe'' for Special Purposes operated in eastern Poland starting in July 1941.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=185}} The ''Einsatzgruppen'' were under the control of the RSHA, headed by Heydrich and later by his successor, SS-''Obergruppenführer'' [[Ernst Kaltenbrunner]]. Heydrich gave them a mandate to secure the offices and papers of the Soviet state and Communist Party;{{sfn|Thomas|1987|p=265}} to liquidate all the higher cadres of the Soviet state; and to instigate and encourage [[pogrom]]s against Jewish populations.{{sfn|Rees|1997|p=177}} The men of the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were recruited from the SD, [[Gestapo]], ''[[Kriminalpolizei]]'' (Kripo), Orpo, and [[Waffen-SS]].{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=185}} Each ''Einsatzgruppe'' was under the operational control of the [[SS and Police Leader|Higher SS Police Chiefs]] in its area of operations.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=96}} In May 1941, General Wagner and SS-''Brigadeführer'' [[Walter Schellenberg]] agreed that the ''Einsatzgruppen'' in front-line areas were to operate under army command, while the army provided the ''Einsatzgruppen'' with all necessary logistical support.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=15}}

[[File:Otto Rasch at the Nuremberg Trials.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Otto Rasch]] photographed by Allied forces at the [[Nuremberg Trials]], circa 1948]]

Heydrich acted under orders from ''Reichsführer-SS'' Himmler, who supplied security forces on an &quot;as needed&quot; basis to the local [[SS and Police Leader]]s.{{sfn|Edeiken|2000}} Led by SD, Gestapo, and Kripo officers, ''Einsatzgruppen'' included recruits from the Orpo, Security Service and Waffen-SS, augmented by uniformed volunteers from the local auxiliary police force.{{sfn|Browning|1998|pp=10–12}} Each ''Einsatzgruppe'' was supplemented with a reserve battalion of Orpos and Waffen-SS as well as support personnel such as drivers and radio operators.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=185}} On average, the Orpo formations were larger and better armed, with heavy machine-gun detachments, which enabled them to carry out operations beyond the capability of the SS.{{sfn|Browning|1998|pp=10–12}} Each [[death squad]] followed an assigned army group as they advanced into the Soviet Union.{{sfn|Einsatzgruppen judgment|pp=414–416}} During the course of their operations, the ''Einsatzgruppen'' commanders received assistance from the Wehrmacht.{{sfn|Einsatzgruppen judgment|pp=414–416}} Activities ranged from the murder of targeted groups of individuals named on carefully prepared lists, to joint city-wide operations with ''SS Einsatzgruppen'' which lasted for two or more days, such as the massacres at [[Babi Yar]], perpetrated by the Orpo Reserve Battalion 45, and at [[Rumbula massacre|Rumbula]], by Battalion 22, reinforced by local ''[[Schutzmannschaft]]en'' (auxiliary police).{{sfn|Browning|1998|pp=135–136, 141–142}}{{sfn|Robertson}} The SS brigades, wrote historian [[Christopher Browning]], were &quot;only the thin cutting edge of German units that became involved in political and racial mass murder.&quot;{{sfn|Browning|1998|p=10}}

Many ''Einsatzgruppe'' leaders were highly educated; for example, nine of seventeen leaders of ''Einsatzgruppe'' A held doctorate degrees.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=186}} Three ''Einsatzgruppen'' were commanded by holders of doctorates, one of whom (SS-''Gruppenführer'' [[Otto Rasch]]) held a double doctorate.{{sfn|Browning|Matthäus|2004|pp=225–226}}

Additional ''Einsatzgruppen'' were created as additional territory was conquered. ''Einsatzgruppe'' E operated in [[Independent State of Croatia]] under three commanders, SS-''Obersturmbannführer'' Ludwig Teichmann, SS-''Standartenführer'' Günther Herrmann, and lastly SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Wilhelm Fuchs]]. The unit was subdivided into five ''Einsatzkommandos'' located in [[Vinkovci]], [[Sarajevo]], [[Banja Luka]], [[Knin]], and [[Zagreb]].{{sfn|MacLean|1999|p=23}}{{sfn|Museum of Tolerance}} ''Einsatzgruppe'' F worked with Army Group South.{{sfn|Museum of Tolerance}} ''Einsatzgruppe'' G operated in [[Romania]], [[Hungary]], and [[Ukraine]], commanded by SS-''Standartenführer'' Dr. Josef Kreuzer.{{sfn|MacLean|1999|p=23}} ''Einsatzgruppe'' H was assigned to [[Slovakia]].{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=419}} ''Einsatzgruppen'' K and L, under SS-''Oberführer'' Dr. [[Emanuel Schäfer]] and SS-''Standartenführer'' Dr. [[Ludwig Hahn]], worked alongside [[5th Panzer Army|5th]] and [[6th Panzer Army|6th Panzer Armies]] during the [[Ardennes offensive]].{{sfn|Dams|Stolle|2012|p=168}} Hahn had previously been in command of ''Einsatzgruppe Griechenland'' in Greece.{{sfn|Conze, Frei et al.|2010}}

Other ''Einsatzgruppen'' and ''Einsatzkommandos'' included ''Einsatzgruppe Iltis'' (operated in Carinthia, on the border between Slovenia and Austria) under SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Paul Blobel]],{{sfn|Crowe|2007|p=267}} ''Einsatzgruppe Jugoslawien'' (Yugoslavia){{sfn|Mallmann|Cüppers|2006|p=97}} ''Einsatzkommando Luxemburg'' (Luxembourg),{{sfn|Museum of Tolerance}}  ''Einsatzgruppe Norwegen'' (Norway) commanded by SS-''Oberführer'' Dr. Franz Walter Stahlecker,{{sfn|Larsen|2008|p=xi}} ''Einsatzgruppe Serbien'' (Yugoslavia) under SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Wilhelm Fuchs]] and SS-''Gruppenführer'' August Meysner,{{sfn|Shelach|1989|p=1169}} ''Einsatzkommando Tilsit'' (Lithuania, Poland),{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=197}} and ''Einsatzgruppe Tunis'' ([[Tunis]]), commanded by SS-''Obersturmbannführer'' [[Walter Rauff]].{{sfn|Mallmann|Cüppers|Smith|2010|p=130}}

== Killings in the Soviet Union ==

After the invasion of the Soviet Union on 22 June 1941, the ''Einsatzgruppen''{{'}}s main assignment was to kill civilians, as in Poland, but this time its targets specifically included [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Soviet Communist Party]] [[commissar]]s and Jews.{{sfn|Rees|1997|p=177}} In a letter dated 2 July 1941 Heydrich communicated to his SS and Police Leaders that the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were to execute all senior and middle ranking [[Comintern]] officials; all senior and middle ranking members of the central, provincial, and district committees of the Communist Party; extremist and radical Communist Party members; [[people's commissar]]s; and Jews in party and government posts. Open-ended instructions were given to execute &quot;other radical elements (saboteurs, propagandists, snipers, assassins, agitators, etc.).&quot; He instructed that any pogroms spontaneously initiated by the occupants of the conquered territories were to be quietly encouraged.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=523}}

On 8 July, Heydrich announced that all Jews were to be regarded as partisans, and gave the order for all male Jews between the ages of 15 and 45 to be shot.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=198}} On 17 July Heydrich ordered that the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were to kill all Jewish [[Red Army]] prisoners of war, plus all Red Army prisoners of war from Georgia and Central Asia, as they too might be Jews.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=97}} Unlike in Germany, where the [[Nuremberg Laws]] of 1935 defined as Jewish anyone with at least three Jewish grandparents, the ''Einsatzgruppen'' defined as Jewish anyone with at least one Jewish grandparent; in either case, whether or not the person practised the religion was irrelevant.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|p=368}} The unit was also assigned to exterminate [[Romani people]] and the mentally ill. It was common practice for the ''Einsatzgruppen'' to shoot hostages.{{sfn|Headland|1992|pp=62–70}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-A0706-0018-030, Ukraine, ermordete Familie.jpg|thumb|left|A teenage boy stands beside his murdered family shortly before his own death by the SS. [[Zboriv]], Ukraine, 5 July 1941]]

As the invasion began, the Germans pursued the fleeing Red Army, leaving a security vacuum. Reports surfaced of Soviet guerrilla activity in the area, with local Jews immediately suspected of collaboration. Heydrich ordered his officers to incite anti-Jewish pogroms in the newly occupied territories.{{sfn|Urban|2001}} Pogroms, some of which were orchestrated by the ''Einsatzgruppen'', broke out in [[Latvia]], [[Lithuania]], and [[Ukraine]].{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=526}} Within the first few weeks of Operation Barbarossa, 40 pogroms led to the deaths of 10,000 Jews, and by the end of 1941 some 60 pogroms had taken place, claiming as many as 24,000 victims.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=526}}{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=68}} However, SS-''Brigadeführer'' [[Franz Walter Stahlecker]], commander of ''Einstazgruppe'' A, [[Einsatzgruppen reports|reported to his superiors]] in mid-October that the residents of [[Kaunas]] were not spontaneously starting pogroms, and secret assistance by the Germans was required.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=193–195}} A similar reticence was noted by ''Einsatzgruppe'' B in Russia and Belarus and ''Einsatzgruppe'' C in Ukraine; the further east the ''Einsatzgruppen'' travelled, the less likely the residents were to be prompted into killing their Jewish neighbours.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=208}}

All four main ''Einsatzgruppen'' took part in mass shootings from the early days of the war.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=196–202}} Initially the targets were adult Jewish men, but by August the net had been widened to include women, children, and the elderly—the entire Jewish population. Initially there was a semblance of legality given to the shootings, with trumped-up charges being read out (arson, sabotage, black marketeering, or refusal to work, for example) and victims being killed by a firing squad. As this method proved too slow, the ''Einsatzkommandos'' began to take their victims out in larger groups and shot them next to, or even inside, mass graves that had been prepared. Some ''Einsatzkommandos'' started to use automatic weapons, with survivors being killed with a pistol shot.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=207}}

As word of the massacres got out, many Jews fled; in Ukraine, 70 to 90 per cent of the Jews ran away. This was seen by the leader of ''Einsatzkommando'' VI as beneficial, as it would save the regime the costs of deporting the victims further east over the Urals.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=208, 211}} In other areas the invasion was so successful that the  ''Einsatzgruppen'' had insufficient forces to immediately kill all the Jews in the conquered territories.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=211}} A situation report from ''Einsatzgruppe'' C in September 1941 noted that not all Jews were members of the Bolshevist apparatus, and suggested that the total elimination of Jewry would have a negative impact on the economy and the food supply. The Nazis began to round their victims up into concentration camps and ghettos and rural districts were for the most part rendered ''[[Judenfrei]]'' (free of Jews).{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=211–212}} Jewish councils were set up in major cities and forced labour gangs were established to make use of the Jews as slave labour until they were totally eliminated, a goal that was postponed until 1942.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=212–213}}

''Einsatzgruppen'' used public hangings as a terror tactic on the local population. An ''Einsatzgruppe B'' report, dated 9 October 1941, described one such hanging. Due to suspected partisan activity near Demidov, all male residents aged 15 to 55 were put in a camp to be screened. The screening produced seventeen people identified as &quot;partisans&quot; and &quot;Communists&quot;. Five members of the group were hanged while 400 local residents were assembled to watch; the rest were shot.{{sfn|Headland|1992|pp=57–58}}

=== Babi Yar ===
{{Main article|Babi Yar}}
The largest mass shooting perpetrated by the ''Einsatzgruppen'' took place on 29 and 30 September 1941 at Babi Yar, a ravine northwest of [[Kiev]], a city in Ukraine that had fallen to the Germans on 19 September.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=179}}{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=227}} The perpetrators included a company of Waffen-SS attached to ''Einsatzgruppe'' C under Rasch, members of ''Sonderkommando'' 4a under SS-''Obergruppenführer'' [[Friedrich Jeckeln]], and some Ukrainian auxiliary police.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=315}} The Jews of Kiev were told to report to a certain street corner on 29 September; anyone who disobeyed would be shot. Since word of massacres in other areas had not yet reached Kiev and the assembly point was near the train station, they assumed they were being deported. People showed up at the rendezvous point in large numbers, laden with possessions and food for the journey.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=172–173}}

After being marched two miles north-west of the city centre, the victims encountered a barbed wire barrier and numerous Ukrainian police and German troops. Thirty or forty people at a time were told to leave their possessions and were escorted through a narrow passageway lined with soldiers brandishing clubs. Anyone who tried to escape was beaten. Soon the victims reached an open area, where they were forced to strip, and then were herded down into the ravine. People were forced to lie down in rows on top of the bodies of other victims, and they were shot in the back of the head or the neck by members of the execution squads.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=173–176}}

The murders continued for two days, claiming a total of 33,771 victims.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=227}} Sand was shovelled and bulldozed over the bodies and the sides of the ravine were dynamited to bring down more material.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=178}} Anton Heidborn, a member of ''Sonderkommando'' 4a, later testified that three days later that there were still people alive among the corpses. Heidborn spent the next few days helping smooth out the &quot;millions&quot; of banknotes taken from the victims' possessions.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=317}} The clothing was taken away, destined to be re-used by German citizens.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=178}} Jeckeln's troops shot more than 100,000 Jews by the end of October.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=227}}

== Killings in the Baltic states ==
{{main article|The Holocaust in Lithuania|The Holocaust in Latvia|The Holocaust in Estonia}}

''Einsatzgruppe'' A operated in the formerly Soviet-occupied [[Baltic states]] of [[Estonia]], Latvia, and Lithuania. According to its own reports to Himmler, ''Einsatzgruppe'' A killed almost 140,000 people in the five months following the invasion: 136,421 Jews, 1,064 Communists, 653 people with mental illnesses, 56 partisans, 44 Poles, five Gypsies, and one Armenian were reported killed between 22 June and 25 November 1941.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=98}}

Upon entering [[Kaunas]], Lithuania, on 25 June 1941, the ''Einsatzgruppe'' released the criminals from the local jail and encouraged them to join the pogrom which was underway.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=41}} Between 23–27 June 1941, 4,000 Jews were killed on the streets of Kaunas and in nearby open pits and ditches.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|pp=67–68}} Particularly active in the Kaunas pogrom was the so-called &quot;Death Dealer of Kaunas&quot;, a young man who murdered Jews with a crowbar at the Lietukis Garage before a large crowd that cheered each killing with much applause; he occasionally paused to play the Lithuanian national anthem &quot;[[Tautiška giesmė]]&quot; on his accordion before resuming the killings.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|pp=67–68}}{{sfn|Rees|1997|p=179}}

As ''Einsatzgruppe'' A advanced into Lithuania, it actively recruited local nationalists and antisemitic groups. In July 1941, members of the ''Baltaraisciai'' movement joined the massacres.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=68}} A pogrom in [[Riga]] in early July killed 400 Jews. Latvian nationalist [[Viktors Arājs]] and his supporters undertook a campaign of arson against synagogues.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|pp=68–69}} On 2 July, ''Einsatzgruppe'' A commander Stahlecker appointed Arājs to head the ''[[Arajs Kommando]]'',{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=68}} a ''Sonderkommando'' of about 300 men, mostly university students. Together, ''Einsatzgruppe'' A and the ''Arājs Kommando'' killed 2,300 Jews in Riga on 6–7 July.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|pp=68–69}} Within six months, Arājs and his men would kill about half of Latvia's Jewish population.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=69}}

Local officials, the ''Selbstschutz'', and the [[Schutzmannschaft|''Hilfspolizei'']] (Auxiliary Police) played a key role in rounding up and massacring Jewish Lithuanians, Latvians, and Estonians.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=71}} These groups helped the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and other killing units to quickly identify Jews.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=71}} The ''Hilfspolizei'', consisting of auxiliary police organised by the Germans and recruited from former Latvian Army and police officers, ex-''[[Aizsargi]]'', members of the [[Pērkonkrusts]], and university students, assisted in the murder of Latvia's Jewish citizens.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=69}} Similar units were created elsewhere, and provided much of the manpower for the Holocaust in Eastern Europe.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|pp=69–70}}

With the creation of units such as the ''Arājs Kommando'' and the ''[[Rollkommando Hamann]]'' in Lithuania,{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=70}} the attacks changed from the spontaneous mob violence of the pogroms to more systematic massacres.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=69}} With extensive local help, ''Einsatzgruppe'' A was the first ''Einsatzgruppe'' to attempt to systematically exterminate all the Jews in its area.{{sfn|Rees|1997|p=182}}{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=71}} Latvian historian [[Modris Eksteins]] wrote:
{{quote|Of the roughly 83,000 Jews who fell into German hands in Latvia, not more than 900 survived; and of the more than 20,000 Western Jews sent into Latvia, only some 800 lived through the deportation until liberation. This was the highest percentage of eradication in all of Europe.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=66}} }}

In late 1941, the ''Einsatzkommandos'' settled into headquarters in [[Kovno]], Riga, and [[Tallinn]]. ''Einsatzgruppe'' A grew less mobile and faced problems because of its small size. The Germans relied increasingly on the ''Arājs Kommando'' and similar groups to perform massacres of Jews.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=70}}

Such extensive and enthusiastic collaboration with the ''Einsatzgruppen'' has been attributed to several factors. Since the [[1905 Russian Revolution|Russian Revolution of 1905]], the [[Kresy|''Kresy Wschodnie'']] and other borderlands had experienced a political culture of violence.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=73}} The period of Soviet rule had been profoundly traumatic for residents of the Baltic states and areas that had been part of Poland until 1939; the population was brutalised and terrorised by the imposed Soviet rule, and the existing familiar structures of society were destroyed.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|pp=74–75}}

Historian Erich Haberer notes that many survived and made sense of the &quot;totalitarian atomization&quot; of society by seeking conformity with communism.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=76}} As a result, by the time of the German invasion in 1941, many had come to see conformity with a totalitarian regime as socially acceptable behaviour; thus, people simply transferred their allegiance to the German regime when it arrived.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=76}} Some who had collaborated with the Soviet regime sought to divert attention from themselves by naming Jews as collaborators and killing them.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=77}}

=== Rumbula ===
{{main article|Rumbula massacre}}

In November 1941 Himmler was dissatisfied with the pace of the exterminations in Latvia, as he intended to move Jews from Germany into the area. He assigned SS-''Obergruppenführer'' Jeckeln, one of the perpetrators of the Babi Yar massacre, to liquidate the [[Riga ghetto]]. Jeckeln selected a site about {{convert|10|km}} southeast of Riga near the Rumbula railway station, and had 300 Russian prisoners of war prepare the site by digging pits in which to bury the victims. Jeckeln organised around 1,700 men, including 300 members of the ''Arajs Kommando'', 50 German SD men, and 50 Latvian guards, most of whom had already participated in mass killings of civilians. These troops were supplemented by Latvians, including members of the Riga city police, battalion police, and ghetto guards. Around 1,500 able-bodied Jews would be spared execution so their slave labour could be exploited; a thousand men were relocated to a fenced-off area within the ghetto and 500 women were temporarily housed in a prison and later moved to a separate nearby ghetto, where they were put to work mending uniforms.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=206–209}}

Although Rumbula was on the rail line, Jeckeln decided that the victims should travel on foot from Riga to the execution ground. Trucks and buses were arranged to carry children and the elderly. The victims were told that they were being relocated, and were advised to bring up to {{convert|20|kg}} of possessions. The first day of executions, 30 November 1941, began with the perpetrators rousing and assembling the victims at 4:00&amp;nbsp;am. The victims were moved in  columns of a thousand people toward the execution ground. As they walked, some SS men went up and down the line, shooting people who could not keep up the pace or who tried to run away or rest.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=208–210}}

When the columns neared the prepared execution site, the victims were driven some {{convert|270|m|yd}} from the road into the forest, where any possessions that had not yet been abandoned were seized. Here the victims were split into groups of fifty and taken deeper into the forest, near the pits, where they were ordered to strip. The victims were driven into the prepared trenches, made to lie down, and shot in the head or the back of the neck by members of Jeckeln's bodyguard. Around 13,000 Jews from Riga were killed at the pits that day, along with a thousand Jews from Berlin who had just arrived by train. On the second day of the operation, 8 December 1941, the remaining 10,000 Jews of Riga were killed in the same way. About a thousand were killed on the streets of the city or on the way to the site, bringing the total deaths for the two-day extermination to 25,000 people. For his part in organising the massacre, Jeckeln was promoted to Leader of the SS Upper Section, [[Reichskommissariat Ostland|Ostland]].{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=210–214}}

== Second Sweep ==
''Einsatzgruppe B, C'', and ''D'' did not immediately follow ''Einsatzgruppe'' A's example in systematically killing all Jews in their areas. The ''Einsatzgruppe'' commanders, with the exception of ''Einsatzgruppe'' A's Stahlecker, were of the opinion by the fall of 1941 that it was impossible to kill the entire Jewish population of the Soviet Union in one sweep, and thought the killings should stop.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|p=342}} An ''Einsatzgruppe'' report dated 17 September advised that the Germans would be better off using any skilled Jews as labourers rather than shooting them.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|p=342}} Also, in some areas poor weather and a lack of transportation led to a slowdown in deportations of Jews from points further west.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=549}} Thus, an interval passed between the first round of ''Einsatzgruppen'' massacres in summer and fall, and what American historian [[Raul Hilberg]] called the second sweep, which started in December 1941 and lasted into the summer of 1942.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|pp=342–343}} During the interval, the surviving Jews were forced into ghettos.{{sfn|Marrus|2000|p=64}}

''Einsatzgruppe'' A had already murdered almost all Jews in its area, so it shifted its operations into Belarus to assist ''Einsatzgruppe'' B. In [[Dnepropetrovsk]] in February 1942, ''Einsatzgruppe'' D reduced the city's Jewish population from 30,000 to 702 over the course of four days.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|p=372}} The German Order Police and local collaborators provided the extra manpower needed to perform all the shootings. Haberer wrote that, as in the Baltic states, the Germans could not have killed so many Jews so quickly without local help. He points out that the ratio of Order Police to auxiliaries was 1 to 10 in both Ukraine and Belarus. In rural areas the proportion was 1 to 20. This meant that most Ukrainian and Belarusian Jews were killed by fellow Ukrainians and Belarusians commanded by German officers rather than by Germans.{{sfn|Haberer|2001|p=78}}

The second wave of exterminations in the Soviet Union met with armed resistance in some areas, though the chance of success was poor. Weapons were typically primitive or home-made. Communications were impossible between ghettos in various cities, so there was no way to create a unified strategy. Few in the ghetto leadership supported resistance for fear of reprisals on the ghetto residents. Mass break-outs were sometimes attempted, though survival in the forest was nearly impossible due to the lack of food and the fact that escapees were often tracked down and killed.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=353–354}}

== Transition to gassing ==
{{see also|Final Solution}}

[[File:Chelmno Gas Van.jpg|thumb|Nazi [[gas van]] used to murder people at [[Chełmno extermination camp]]]]
After a time, Himmler found that the killing methods used by the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were inefficient: they were costly, demoralising for the troops, and sometimes did not kill the victims quickly enough.{{sfn|Rees|1997|p=197}} Many of the troops found the massacres to be difficult if not impossible to perform. Some of the perpetrators suffered physical and mental health problems, and many turned to drink.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=52, 124, 168}} As much as possible, the ''Einsatzgruppen'' leaders militarized the genocide. The historian Christian Ingrao notes an attempt was made to make the shootings a collective act without individual responsibility. Framing the shootings in this way was not psychologically sufficient for every perpetrator to feel absolved of guilt.{{sfn|Ingrao|2013|pp=199—200}} Browning notes three categories of potential perpetrators: those who were eager to participate right from the start, those who participated in spite of moral qualms because they were ordered to do so, and a significant minority who refused to take part.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=163}} A few men spontaneously became excessively brutal in their killing methods and their zeal for the task. Commander of ''Einsatzgruppe'' D, SS-''Gruppenführer'' [[Otto Ohlendorf]], particularly noted this propensity towards excess, and ordered that any man who was too eager to participate or too brutal should not perform any further executions.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=165–166}}

During a visit to Minsk in August 1941, Himmler witnessed an ''Einsatzgruppen'' mass execution first-hand and concluded that shooting Jews was too stressful for his men.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|pp=547–548}} By November he made arrangements for any SS men suffering ill health from having participated in executions to be provided with rest and mental health care.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=167}} He also decided a transition should be made to gassing the victims, especially the women and children, and ordered the recruitment of expendable native auxiliaries who could assist with the murders.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=167}}{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=551}} Gas vans, which had been used previously to kill mental patients, began to see service by all four main ''Einsatzgruppen'' from 1942.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=548}} However, the gas vans were not popular with the ''Einsatzkommandos'', because removing the dead bodies from the van and burying them was a horrible ordeal. Prisoners or auxiliaries were often assigned to do this task so as to spare the SS men the trauma.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=243}} Some of the early mass killings at [[extermination camp]]s used carbon monoxide fumes produced by diesel engines, similar to the method used in gas vans, but by as early as September 1941 experiments were begun at [[Auschwitz]] using [[Zyklon B]], a cyanide-based pesticide gas.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=280–281}}

Plans for the total eradication of the Jewish population of Europe—eleven million people—were formalised at the [[Wannsee Conference]], held on 20 January 1942. Some would be [[Extermination through labor|worked to death]], and the rest would be killed in the implementation of the [[Final Solution]] of the [[Jewish question]] ({{lang-de|link=no|Die Endlösung der Judenfrage}}).{{sfn|Longerich|2012|pp=555–556}} Permanent killing centres at Auschwitz, [[Belzec]], [[Sobibor extermination camp|Sobibor]], [[Treblinka]], and other Nazi extermination camps replaced mobile death squads as the primary method of mass killing.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=279–280}} The ''Einsatzgruppen'' remained active, however, and were put to work fighting partisans, particularly in Belarus.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=248}}

After the [[Battle of Stalingrad|fall of Stalingrad]] in February 1943, Himmler realised that Germany would likely lose the war, and ordered the formation of a special task force, [[Sonderaktion 1005|''Sonderkommando'' 1005]], under SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Paul Blobel]]. The unit's assignment was to visit mass graves all along the [[Eastern Front of World War II|Eastern Front]] to exhume bodies and burn them in an attempt to cover up the genocide. The task remained unfinished at the end of the war, and many mass graves remain unmarked and unexcavated.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=258–260, 262}}

By 1944 the Red Army had begun to push the German forces out of Eastern Europe, and the ''Einsatzgruppen'' retreated alongside the Wehrmacht. By late 1944, most ''Einsatzgruppen'' personnel had been folded into Waffen-SS combat units or transferred to permanent death camps. Hilberg estimates that between 1941 and 1945 the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and related agencies killed more than two million people, including 1.3 million Jews.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=257}} The total number of Jews murdered during the war is estimated at 5.5 to six million people.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=318}}

== Plans for the Middle East and Britain ==
According to research by German historians [[Klaus-Michael Mallmann]] and Martin Cüppers, an ''Einsatzgruppe'' was created in 1942 to kill the half-million Jews living in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]] and the 50,000 Jews of Egypt. [[Einsatzgruppe Egypt|''Einsatzgruppe'' Egypt]], standing by in [[Athens]], was prepared to go to Palestine once German forces arrived there.{{sfn|Mallmann|Cüppers|Smith|2010|p=130}} SS-''Obersturmbannführer'' [[Walter Rauff]] was to lead the unit.{{sfn|Mallmann|Cüppers|Smith|2010|p=118}} Given its small staff of only 24 men, ''Einsatzgruppe'' Egypt would have needed help from local residents and from the ''[[Afrika Korps]]'' to complete their assignment. Its members planned to enlist collaborators from the local population to perform the killings under German leadership. {{sfn|Mallmann|Cüppers|Smith|2010|pp=124–125}} Former Iraqi prime minister [[Rashid Ali al-Gaylani]] and the [[Grand Mufti of Jerusalem]] [[Haj Amin al-Husseini]] played roles, engaging in antisemitic radio propaganda, preparing to recruit volunteers, and in raising an Arab-German Battalion that would also follow ''Einsatzgruppe'' Egypt to the Middle East.{{sfn|Mallmann|Cüppers|Smith|2010|pp=127–130}} On 20 July 1942, [[Walther Rauff]], who was responsible for the unit, was sent to [[Tobruk]] to report to Field Marshal [[Erwin Rommel]], Commander of the ''Afrika Korps''. However, since Rommel was 500&amp;nbsp;km away at the [[First Battle of El Alamein]], it is unlikely that the two were able to meet.{{sfn|Mallmann|Cüppers|Smith|2010|pp=103, 117–118}} The plans for ''Einsatzgruppe'' Egypt were set aside after the Allied victory at the [[Second Battle of El Alamein]].{{sfn|Krumenacker|2006}} Historian Jean-Christoph Caron opines that there is no evidence that Rommel knew of or would have supported Rauff's mission.{{sfn|Caron|2007}}

Had [[Operation Sea Lion]], the German plan for an invasion of the United Kingdom been launched, six ''Einsatzgruppen'' were scheduled to follow the invasion force into Britain. They were provided with a list called ''die Sonderfahndungsliste, G.B.'' (&quot;Special Search List, G.B&quot;), known as [[The Black Book]] after the war, of 2,300 people to be immediately imprisoned by the Gestapo. The list included Churchill, members of the cabinet, prominent journalists and authors, and members of the [[Czechoslovak government-in-exile]].{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=783–784}}

== Jäger Report ==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-B0716-0005-007, Oberstes Gericht, Globke-Prozess, Beweisstück.jpg|thumb|Page 6 of the [[Jäger Report]] shows the number of people killed by ''Einsatzkommando'' III alone in the five-month period covered by the report as 137,346.]]

The ''Einsatzgruppen'' kept official records of many of their massacres and provided detailed reports to their superiors. The [[Jäger Report]], filed by Commander ''SS-Standartenführer'' [[Karl Jäger]] on 1 December 1941 to his superior, Stahlecker (head of ''Einsatzgruppe'' A), covers the activities of ''Einsatzkommando'' III in Lithuania over the five-month period from 2 July 1941 to 25 November 1941.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=215}}

Jäger's report provides an almost daily running total of the liquidations of 137,346 people, the vast majority of them Jews.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=215}} The report documents the exact date and place of massacres, the number of victims, and their breakdown into categories (Jews, Communists, criminals, and so on).{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=126}} Women were shot from the very beginning, but initially in fewer numbers than men.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=230}} Children were first included in the tally starting in mid-August, when 3,207 people were murdered in [[Rokiškis]] on 15–16 August 1941.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=126}} For the most part the report does not give any military justification for the killings; people were killed solely because they were Jews.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=126}} In total, the report lists over 100 executions in 71 different locations. Jäger wrote: &quot;I can state today that the goal of solving the Jewish problem in Lithuania has been reached by ''Einsatzkommando'' 3. There are no more Jews in Lithuania, apart from working Jews and their families.&quot;{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=215}} In a February 1942 addendum to the report, Jäger increased the total number of victims to 138,272, giving a breakdown of 48,252 men, 55,556 women, and 34,464 children. Only 1,851 of the victims were non-Jewish.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=216}}

Jäger escaped capture by the Allies when the war ended. He lived in Heidelberg under his own name until his report was discovered in March 1959.{{sfn|Rabitz|2011}} Arrested and charged, Jäger committed suicide on 22 June 1959 in a Hohenasperg prison while awaiting trial for his crimes.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|p=276}}

== Involvement of the Wehrmacht ==
{{main article|War crimes of the Wehrmacht}}
The killings took place with the knowledge and support of the German Army in the east.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=102}} On 10 October 1941 Field Marshal [[Walther von Reichenau]] drafted an order to be read to the [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|German Sixth Army]] on the Eastern Front. Now known as the [[Severity Order]], it read in part:
{{quote|The most important objective of this campaign against the Jewish-Bolshevik system is the complete destruction of its sources of power and the extermination of the Asiatic influence in European civilization&amp;nbsp;... In this eastern theatre, the soldier is not only a man fighting in accordance with the rules of the art of war, but also the ruthless standard bearer of a national conception&amp;nbsp;... For this reason the soldier must learn fully to appreciate the necessity for the severe but just retribution that must be meted out to the subhuman species of Jewry.{{sfn|Craig|1973|p=10}} }}
Field Marshal [[Gerd von Rundstedt]] of Army Group South expressed his &quot;complete agreement&quot; with the order. He sent out a circular to the generals under his command urging them to release their own versions and to impress upon their troops the need to exterminate the Jews.{{sfn|Mayer|1988|p=250}} General [[Erich von Manstein]], in an order to his troops on 20 November, stated that &quot;the Jewish-Bolshevist system must be exterminated once and for all.&quot;{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|p=102}} Manstein sent a letter to ''Einsatzgruppe'' D commanding officer Ohlendorf complaining that it was unfair that the SS was keeping all of the murdered Jews' wristwatches for themselves instead of sharing with the army.{{sfn|Smelser|Davies|2008|p=43}}

Beyond this trivial complaint, the Army and the ''Einsatzgruppen'' worked closely and effectively. On 6 July 1941 ''Einsatzkommando'' 4b of ''Einsatzgruppe'' C reported that &quot;Armed forces surprisingly welcome hostility against the Jews&quot;.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|p=301}} On 8 September, ''Einsatzgruppe'' D reported that relations with the German Army were &quot;excellent&quot;.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|p=301}} In the same month, Stahlecker of ''Einsatzgruppe'' A wrote that Army Group North had been exemplary in co-operating with the exterminations and that relations with the [[4th Panzer Army]], commanded by General [[Erich Hoepner]], were &quot;very close, almost cordial&quot;.{{sfn|Hilberg|1985|p=30}} In the south, the Romanian Army worked closely with ''Einsatzgruppe'' D to massacre Ukrainian Jews,{{sfn|Marrus|2000|p=64}} killing around 26,000 Jews in the [[1941 Odessa massacre|Odessa massacre]].{{sfn|Marrus|2000|p=79}} The German historian [[Peter Longerich]] thinks it probable that the Wehrmacht, along with the [[Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists]] (OUN), incited the [[Lviv pogroms]], during which 8,500 to 9,000 Jews were killed by the native population and ''Einsatzgruppe'' C in July 1941.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=194}} Moreover, most people on the home front in Germany had some idea of the massacres being committed by the ''Einsatzgruppen''.{{sfn|Marrus|2000|p=88}} British historian [[Hugh Trevor-Roper]] noted that although Himmler had forbidden photographs of the killings, it was common for both the men of the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and for bystanders to take pictures to send to their loved ones, which he felt suggested widespread approval of the massacres.{{sfn|Klee|Dressen|Riess|1991|p=xi}}

The Wehrmacht tried to justify their considerable involvement in the ''Einsatzgruppen'' massacres as being anti-partisan operations rather than racist attacks, but Hillgruber wrote that this was just an excuse. He states that those German generals who claimed that the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were a necessary anti-partisan response were lying, and maintained that the slaughter of about 2.2 million defenceless civilians for reasons of racist ideology cannot be justified.{{sfn|Hillgruber|1989|pp=102–103}}

== Einsatzgruppen Trial ==

After the close of the World War II, 24 senior leaders of the ''Einsatzgruppen'' were prosecuted in the [[Einsatzgruppen Trial]] in 1947–48, part of the [[Subsequent Nuremberg Trials]] held under United States military authority. The men were charged with [[crimes against humanity]], [[war crimes]], and membership in the SS (which had been declared a criminal organization). Fourteen death sentences and two life sentences were among the judgments; only four executions were carried out, on 7 June 1951; the rest were reduced to lesser sentences. Four additional ''Einsatzgruppe'' leaders were later tried and executed by other nations.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=274–275}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J08517, Otto Ohlendorf.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Otto Ohlendorf]], 1943]]

Several ''Einsatzgruppen'' leaders, including Ohlendorf, claimed at the trial to have received an order before Operation Barbarossa requiring them to murder all Soviet Jews.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=187}} To date no evidence has been found that such an order was ever issued.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=187–189}} German prosecutor Alfred Streim noted that if such an order had been given, post-war courts would only have been able to convict the ''Einsatzgruppen'' leaders as ''accomplices'' to mass murder. However, if it could be established that the ''Einsatzgruppen'' had committed mass murder without orders, then they could have been convicted as ''perpetrators'' of mass murder, and hence could have received stiffer sentences, including capital punishment.{{sfn|Streim|1989|p=439}}

Streim postulated that the existence of an early comprehensive order was a fabrication created for use in Ohlendorf's defence. This theory is now widely accepted by historians.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=188}} Longerich notes that most orders received by the ''Einsatzgruppen'' leaders—especially when they were being ordered to carry out criminal activities—were vague, and couched in terminology that had a specific meaning for members of the regime. Leaders were given briefings about the need to be &quot;severe&quot; and &quot;firm&quot;; all Jews were to be viewed as potential enemies that had to be dealt with ruthlessly.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=189–190}} British historian Sir [[Ian Kershaw]] argues that Hitler's apocalyptic remarks before Barbarossa about the necessity for a war without mercy to &quot;annihilate&quot; the forces of &quot;Judeo-Bolshevism&quot; were interpreted by ''Einsatzgruppen'' commanders as permission and encouragement to engage in extreme antisemitic violence, with each ''Einsatzgruppen'' commander to use his own discretion about how far he was prepared to go.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=258–259}}

Most of the perpetrators of Nazi war crimes were never charged, and returned unremarked to civilian life. The West German Central Prosecution Office of Nazi War Criminals only charged about a hundred former ''Einsatzgruppe'' members with war crimes.{{sfn|Rhodes|2002|pp=275–276}} And as time went on, it became more difficult to obtain prosecutions; witnesses grew older and were less likely to be able to offer valuable testimony. Funding for trials was inadequate, and the governments of Austria and Germany became less interested in obtaining convictions for wartime events, preferring to forget the Nazi past.{{sfn|Segev|2010|pp=226, 250, 376}}

== See also ==
* [[Functionalism versus intentionalism]]
* [[Glossary of Nazi Germany]]
* [[List of Nazi Party leaders and officials]]
* [[Porajmos]]

== References ==

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|20em}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite web | last = Browning | first = Christopher R. | title = Ordinary Men: Reserve Police Battalion 101 and the Final Solution in Poland | publisher = Penguin | location = London; New York | orig-year = 1992 | year = 1998 | url=http://hampshirehigh.com/exchange2012/docs/BROWNING-Ordinary%20Men.%20Reserve%20Police%20Battalion%20101%20and%20the%20Final%20Solution%20in%20Poland%20(1992).pdf | accessdate = 2 January 2015 | format = PDF | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20131019043400/http://hampshirehigh.com/exchange2012/docs/BROWNING-Ordinary%20Men.%20Reserve%20Police%20Battalion%20101%20and%20the%20Final%20Solution%20in%20Poland%20(1992).pdf | archivedate = 19 October 2013 | deadurl = no | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Browning | first1 = Christopher | author-link = Christopher Browning | last2 = Matthäus | first2 = Jürgen | title = The Origins of the Final Solution: The Evolution of Nazi Jewish Policy, September 1939 – March 1942 | series = Comprehensive History of the Holocaust | publisher = University of Nebraska Press | location = Lincoln | year = 2004 | isbn = 978-0-8032-1327-2 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Caron | first1 = Jean-Christoph | title = Erwin Rommel: Auf der Jagd nach dem Schatz des &quot;Wüstenfuchses&quot; | page = 2 | journal = Spiegel Online | date = 22 December 2007 | language = German | url = http://www.spiegel.de/wissenschaft/mensch/erwin-rommel-auf-der-jagd-nach-dem-schatz-des-wuestenfuchses-a-522484-2.html | accessdate = 9 September 2016 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Conze | first1 = Eckart | last2 = Frei | first2 = Norbert | last3 = Hayes | first3 = Peter | last4 = Zimmermann | first4 = Moshe | title =  Das Amt und die Vergangenheit : deutsche Diplomaten im Dritten Reich und in der Bundesrepublik | year = 2010 | publisher = Karl Blessing | location = Munich | language = German | isbn = 978-3-89667-430-2 | ref = {{sfnRef|Conze, Frei et al.|2010}} }}
* {{cite book | last = Craig | first = William | authorlink = William Craig (author) | title = Enemy at the Gates: The Battle for Stalingrad | year = 1973 | publisher = Konecky &amp; Konecky | location = Old Saybrook, CT | isbn = 1-56852-368-8 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Crowe | first = David | title = Oskar Schindler: The Untold Account of his Life, Wartime Activities and the True Story Behind the List | year = 2007 | origyear = 2004 | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-465-00253-5 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Dams | first1 = Carsten | last2 = Stolle | first2 = Michael | title = Die Gestapo: Herrschaft und Terror im Dritten Reich | series = Becksche Reihe | year = 2012 | origyear = 2008 | language = German | publisher = Beck | location = Munich | isbn = 978-3-406-62898-6 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite web | last = Edeiken | first = Yale F. | publisher = Holocaust History Project | title = Introduction to the Einsatzgruppen | date = 22 August 2000 | url = http://www.holocaust-history.org/intro-einsatz/  | accessdate= 10 January 2013 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | title = Trials of War Criminals before the Nuernberg Military Tribunals under Control Council Law No. 10 | location = Nürnberg | date = October 1946 – April 1949 | volume =Volume 4 | series = Green Series | chapter = Einsatzgruppen case | chapter-url=http://www.loc.gov/rr/frd/Military_Law/pdf/NT_war-criminals_Vol-IV.pdf | url = http://www.loc.gov/rr/frd/Military_Law/NTs_war-criminals.html | format = PDF | accessdate = 2 April 2013 | ref = {{sfnRef|Einsatzgruppen judgment}} }}
* {{cite book | last = Evans | first = Richard J. | authorlink = Richard J. Evans | title = [[The Third Reich at War]] | year = 2008 | publisher = Penguin Group | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-14-311671-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Gerwarth | first = Robert | authorlink = Robert Gerwarth | year = 2011 | title = Hitler's Hangman: The Life of Heydrich | publisher = Yale University Press | location = New Haven, CT | isbn = 978-0-300-11575-8 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | last = Haberer | first = Erich | title = Intention and Feasibility: Reflections on Collaboration and the Final Solution | pages = 64–81 | journal = East European Jewish Affairs | volume = 31 | issue = 2 | year = 2001 | oclc = 210897979 | ref = harv | doi = 10.1080/13501670108577951 |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/13501670108577951}}{{Better source|reason=Source article is based on claims proven false during official state investigation into crimes committed by Kommando SS Zichenau-Schröttersburg|date=January 2015}}
* {{cite book | last = Headland | first = Ronald | authorlink = | title = Messages of Murder: A Study of the Reports of the Security Police and the Security Service | publisher = Associated University Presses | url = https://rowman.com/ISBN/9781611470963/Messages-of-Murder-A-Study-of-the-Reports-of-the-Einsatzgruppen-of-the-Security-Police-and-the-Security-Service-1941-1943 | year = 1992| location = London | isbn = 0-8386-3418-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Hilberg | first = Raul | authorlink = Raul Hilberg | title = [[The Destruction of the European Jews]] | location = New York | publisher = Holmes &amp; Meier | year = 1985 | isbn = 978-0-8419-0832-1 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Hillgruber | first = Andreas | authorlink = Andreas Hillgruber | chapter = War in the East and the Extermination of the Jews | pages = 85–114 | series = The Nazi Holocaust | title = Part 3, The &quot;Final Solution&quot;: The Implementation of Mass Murder, Volume 1 | editor1-first = Michael | editor1-last = Marrus | publisher = Meckler | location = Westpoint, CT | year = 1989 | isbn = 0-88736-266-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Ingrao | first = Christian | title = Believe and Destroy: Intellectuals in the SS War Machine | location= Malden, MA | publisher = Polity | year = 2013 | isbn = 978-0-7456-6026-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Kershaw | first = Ian | authorlink = Ian Kershaw | title = Hitler, the Germans, and the Final Solution | publisher = Yale University Press | location = New Haven, Conn. | year = 2008 | isbn = 978-0-300-12427-9 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Klee | first1 = Ernst | authorlink1 = Ernst Klee | last2 = Dressen | first2 = Willi | last3 = Riess | first3 = Volker | title = &quot;The Good Old Days&quot; – The Holocaust as Seen by its Perpetrators and Bystanders | others = Trans. Burnstone, Deborah | publisher = MacMillan | location = New York | year = 1991 | isbn = 0-02-917425-2 | ref = harv }} (originally published as {{cite book | last1 = Klee | first1 = Ernst | last2 = Dreßen | first2 = Willi | last3 = Rieß | first3 = Volker (Hrsg.) | title = Schöne Zeiten. Judenmord aus der Sicht der Täter und Gaffer. | publisher = S. Fischer | location = Frankfurt / Main | year = 1988 | isbn = 978-3-10-039304-3 | language = German }}
* {{cite web | last = Krumenacker | first = Thomas | title = Nazis Planned Holocaust for Palestine: historians | publisher = Red Orbit | date = 7 April 2006 | url = http://www.redorbit.com/news/international/462094/nazis_planned_holocaust_for_palestine_historians/ | accessdate = 9 September 2016 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Larsen  | first = Stein Ugelvik | title = Meldungen aus Norwegen 1940–1945: Die geheimen Lagesberichte des Befehlshabers der Sicherheitspolizei und des SD in Norwegen, 1 | year = 2008 | publisher = Oldenburg | location = Munich | language = German | isbn = 978-3-486-55891-3 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite web | author = LEO Dictionary Team | title = LEO Deutsch-Englisches Wörterbuch &quot;einsatzgruppe&quot; | publisher = Dict.leo.org | language = German | url = http://dict.leo.org/ende?lp=ende&amp;lang=de&amp;searchLoc=0&amp;cmpType=relaxed&amp;sectHdr=on&amp;spellToler=&amp;search=einsatzgruppe | accessdate = 10 January 2013 | ref = {{sfnRef|LEO Dictionary}} }}
* {{cite book | last = Longerich | first = Peter | authorlink = Peter Longerich | title = Holocaust: The Nazi Persecution and Murder of the Jews | year = 2010 | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford; New York | isbn = 978-0-19-280436-5 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Longerich | first = Peter | year = 2012 | title = Heinrich Himmler: A Life | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford; New York | isbn = 978-0-19-959232-6 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = MacLean | first = French L. | title = The Field Men: The SS Officers Who Led the Einsatzkommandos—The Nazi Mobile Killing Units | series = Schiffer Military History | year = 1999 | publisher = Schiffer | location = Madison, WI | isbn = 978-0-7643-0754-6 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Mallmann | first1 = Klaus-Michael  | authorlink1 = Klaus-Michael Mallmann | last2 = Cüppers | first2 = Martin | title = Crescent and Swastika: The Third Reich, the Arabs and Palestine | year = 2006 | publisher = University of Michigan Press | location = Ann Arbor | isbn = 978-3-534-19729-3 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Mallmann | first1 = Klaus-Michael | last2 = Cüppers | first2 = Martin | last3 = Smith | first3 = Krista | title = Nazi Palestine: The Plans for the Extermination of the Jews in Palestine | publisher = Enigma | location = New York | year = 2010 | isbn = 1-929631-93-6 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Marrus | first = Michael | authorlink = Michael Marrus | title = The Holocaust in History | publisher = Key Porter | location = Toronto | year = 2000 | isbn = 978-1-55263-120-1 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Mayer | first = Arno J | authorlink = Arno J. Mayer | title = Why Did The Heavens Not Darken? | year = 1988 | publisher = Pantheon | location = New York | isbn = 0-394-57154-1 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | title =  Nuremberg Trial Proceedings, Volume 20, Day 194 | work = The Avalon Project | publisher = Yale Law School Lillian Goldman Law Library | url = http://avalon.law.yale.edu/imt/08-03-46.asp | accessdate = 10 January 2013 | ref = {{sfnRef|Nuremberg Trial, Vol. 20, Day 194}} }}
* {{cite web | last = Rabitz | first = Cornelia | title = Biography of Nazi criminal meets resistance from small German town | date = 21 June 2011 | work = dw.de | publisher = [[Deutsche Welle]] | url = http://www.dw.com/en/biography-of-nazi-criminal-meets-resistance-from-small-german-town/a-15161137 | accessdate = 9 September 2016 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Rees | first = Laurence | authorlink = Laurence Rees | title = The Nazis: A Warning From History | others = Foreword by Sir Ian Kershaw | location = New York | publisher = New Press | year = 1997 | isbn = 1-56584-551-X | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | publisher = Encyclopaedia Britannica | title = Reflections on the Holocaust: &quot;The Einsatzgruppen&quot; | url = http://kids.britannica.com/holocaust/article-215489 | accessdate = 9 September 2016 | ref = {{sfnRef|Encyclopaedia Britannica}} }}
* {{cite book | last = Rhodes | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Rhodes | title = Masters of Death: The SS-Einsatzgruppen and the Invention of the Holocaust | location = New York | publisher = Vintage Books | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-375-70822-7 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | last = Robertson | first = Struan | title = The genocidal missions of Reserve Police Battalion 101 in the General Government (Poland) 1942–1943 | work = Hamburg Police Battalions during the Second World War | publisher = Regionalen Rechenzentrum der Universität Hamburg | url = http://www1.uni-hamburg.de/rz3a035//police101.html | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080222023331/http://www1.uni-hamburg.de/rz3a035//police101.html | archivedate = 22 February 2008 | accessdate = 2 January 2015 | ref = {{sfnRef|Robertson}} }}
* {{cite book | last = Segev | first = Tom | authorlink = Tom Segev | title = Simon Wiesenthal: The Life and Legends | year = 2010 | publisher = Doubleday | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-385-51946-5 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Shelach | first = Menachem | editor1-last = Marrus | editor1-first = Michael Robert | editor1-link = Michael Marrus | title = The Victims of the Holocaust: Historical Articles on the Destruction of European Jews | volume = 2 | chapter = Sajmište: An Extermination Camp in Serbia | year = 1989 | publisher = Meckler | location = Westport, CT | isbn =  | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Shirer | first = William L. | authorlink = William L. Shirer | title = [[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]] | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | year = 1960 | isbn = 978-0-671-62420-0 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Smelser | first1 = Ronald | authorlink1=Ronald Smelser|last2 = Davies | first2 = Edward | title = [[The Myth of the Eastern Front]]: The Nazi-Soviet War in American Popular Culture | year = 2008 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | isbn = 978-0-521-83365-3 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Streim | first = Alfred | chapter = The Tasks of the SS Einsatzgruppen, pages 436–454 | title = The Nazi Holocaust, Part 3, The &quot;Final Solution&quot;: The Implementation of Mass Murder, Volume 2 | editor1-last = Marrus | editor1-first = Michael | editor1-link = Michael Marrus | publisher = Meckler | location = Westpoint, CT | year = 1989 | isbn = 0-88736-266-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | title = Book review: ''Tasks of the Einsatsgruppen'' by Alfred Streim | work = Museum of Tolerance Online Multimedia Learning Center, Annual 4, Chapter 9 | publisher = [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] | location = Los Angeles | url = http://motlc.wiesenthal.com/site/pp.asp?c=gvKVLcMVIuG&amp;b=395089 | accessdate = 6 May 2013 | ref = {{sfnRef|Museum of Tolerance}} }}
* {{cite journal | last1=Thomas | first1=David | title=Foreign Armies East and German Military Intelligence in Russia 1941-45 | journal=Journal of Contemporary History | date=April 1987 | volume=22 | issue=2 | pages=261–301 | jstor=260933 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | last = Urban | first = Thomas | url=http://www.rzeczpospolita.pl/gazeta/wydanie_010901/publicystyka/publicystyka_a_1.html | archiveurl = http://classic-web.archive.org/web/20071124014038/http://www.rzeczpospolita.pl/gazeta/wydanie_010901/publicystyka/publicystyka_a_1.html | archivedate = 24 November 2007 | title = Poszukiwany Hermann Schaper | journal = [[Rzeczpospolita (newspaper)]] | language = Polish | issue = 204 | date = 1 September 2001 | accessdate = 5 January 2015 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Weale | first = Adrian | authorlink = Adrian Weale | title = Army of Evil: A History of the SS | year = 2012 | publisher = Penguin Group | location = New York; Toronto | isbn = 978-0-451-23791-0 | ref = harv}}

{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book | last = Earl | first = Hilary | title = The Nuremberg SS-Einsatzgruppen Trial, 1945–1958: Atrocity, Law, and History | year = 2009 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge; New York | isbn = 978-0-521-45608-1 }}
* {{cite book | last = Förster | first = Jürgen | chapter = Complicity or Entanglement? The Wehrmacht, the War and the Holocaust | pages = 266–283 | title = The Holocaust and History: The Known, the Unknown, the Disputed and the Reexamined | editor1-first = Michael  | editor1-last = Berenbaum | editor2-first = Abraham | editor2-last = Peck | location = Bloomington | publisher = Indian University Press | year = 1998 | isbn = 978-0-253-33374-2 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Krausnick | first1 = Helmut | last2 = Wilhelm | first2 = Hans-Heinrich | title = Die Truppe des Weltanschauungskrieges. Die Einsatzgruppen der Sicherheitspolizei und des SD 1938–1942 | year = 1981 | language = German | publisher = Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt | location = Stuttgart | isbn = 3-421-01987-8 }}
* {{cite book | last = Snyder | first = Timothy | authorlink = Timothy D. Snyder | title = Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin | year = 2010 | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-465-00239-9 }}
* {{cite book | last = Stang | first = Knut | title = Kollaboration und Massenmord. Die litauische Hilfspolizei, das Rollkommando Hamann und die Ermordung der litauischen Juden | year = 1996 | language = German | publisher = Peter Lang | location = Frankfurt am Main | isbn = 3-631-30895-7 }}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Einsatzgruppen}}
{{Wikisource|Comprehensive report of Einsatzgruppe A up to 15 October 1941}}
* [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005130 United States Holocaust Memorial Museum article on ''Einsatzgruppen'']
* [http://www.holocaustresearchproject.net/einsatz/index.html &quot;Einsatzgruppen&quot; ] The Holocaust Education &amp; Archive Research Team
{{Einsatzgruppen}}
{{SS organizations}}
{{The Holocaust}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Einsatzgruppen| ]]
[[Category:Holocaust antisemitic attacks and incidents]]
[[Category:Military units and formations of Germany in World War II]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Ukraine]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Latvia]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Lithuania]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Estonia]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Russia]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Belarus]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Poland]]
[[Category:Holocaust terminology]]
[[Category:Gestapo]]
[[Category:Reinhard Heydrich]]
[[Category:Reich Main Security Office]]
[[Category:Police of Nazi Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>btqpivnx5xbc7vi18a8ofjtlcdnippx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
