<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Elyesa Bazna</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>541858</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750842615</id>
      <parentid>750832234</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T23:14:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mandruss</username>
        <id>19082616</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>date format ;; nowrap dates</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="53479">{{good article}}
{{Infobox person
|name          = Elyesa Bazna
|image         =Elyesa_Bazna.jpg
|image_size    = 225px
|caption       = Elyesa Bazna (Cicero)
|birth_name    = Elyesa Bazna
|birth_date    = {{birth date|df=yes|1904|07|28}}
|birth_place   = [[Pristina]], [[Kosovo Vilayet]] (now Kosovo)
|death_date    = {{death date and age|df=yes|1970|12|21|1904|07|28}}
|death_place   = [[Munich]], Germany
|death_cause   =
|resting_place = Friedhof am Perlacher Forst, Munich, Germany{{Sfn|Auer|1995|p=239}}
|resting_place_coordinates =
|residence     =
|nationality   = [[Turkish people|Turkish]]  ([[Albanians|Albanian]] descent)
|other_names   = Cicero
|known_for     = [[Espionage]] for [[Nazi Germany]]
|education     =
|alma_mater    =
|employer      =
|occupation    =
|home_town     =
|title         =
|salary        =
|networth      =
|height        =
|weight        =
|party         =
|religion      =
|spouse        =
|partner       =
|children      =
|parents       =
|relations     =
|signature     =
|footnotes     =
}}

'''Elyesa Bazna''' ({{IPA-tr|ˈeljesɑ ˈbɑznɑ|lang}}), infrequently referred to as '''Iliaz'''{{Sfn|BBC|2005}} and '''Ilyaz Bazna''' ({{IPA-sq|iliaz bazna|lang}}),{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=6}} (28 July 1904&amp;nbsp;– 21 December 1970), was a [[espionage|secret agent]] for  [[Nazi Germany]] during [[World War II]], operating under the [[code name]] '''Cicero'''.

Born in Pristina, Bazna attended a military academy, and joined a French military unit at age 16. He was caught stealing cars and weapons, for which he served three years in a penal labor camp in France. Bazna held a number of manual jobs in Turkish and French cities before obtaining work for foreign diplomats and consulates as a doorman, driver, and guard. He spoke several languages fluently, including French, which was the predominant diplomatic language at the time. In 1943, Bazna was hired as a valet by [[Hughe Knatchbull-Hugessen]], the British ambassador in [[Ankara]], Turkey.  He photographed British documents in Knatchbull-Hugession's possession, and sold them to the Germans through their attaché [[Ludwig Carl Moyzisch]] in what became known as the ''Cicero affair''.

As Cicero, Bazna passed on important information about many of the Allied leaders' conferences, including the  [[Moscow Conference (1943)|Moscow]],  [[Tehran Conference|Tehran]] and [[Cairo Conference]]s. The details for the Tehran Conference were important for [[Operation Long Jump]], the unsuccessful plot to kill [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], [[Joseph Stalin]], and [[Winston Churchill]]. He had also conveyed a document that carried the highest security restriction ([[BIGOT list]]) about [[Operation Overlord]] (the code name for the [[Invasion of Normandy]] in June 1944). It included intelligence that the British ambassador was to request the use of Turkish air bases &quot;to maintain a threat to the Germans from the eastern Mediterranean until Overlord is launched.&quot; The information about the Normandy Invasion was not known by the Germans until after the war. Had it been provided in time, Operation Overlord (the preparations for [[Normandy landings|D-Day]]) could have been compromised.  He also provided intelligence that might have made the Germans believe that there was no danger of attack in the Balkans. The information that he leaked is believed to have been among the potentially more damaging disclosures made by an agent during the Second World War. The [[German Foreign Office]] questioned the intelligence provided by Cicero due to the large quantity of transmitted documents, which meant that little, if any, of it was acted upon.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}

Once the British became aware that there was a spy operating within the Turkish Embassy, they investigated Bazna, installed a new alarm system, and initiated an unsuccessful sting to catch him selling intelligence.  He stopped selling information to the Germans by the end of February 1944 and left the embassy within a month or so. After the war, Bazna was questioned for war crimes, but he was never charged with espionage. He  attempted to buy and operate a hotel in Ankara with the proceeds of his spying career, but it was discovered that much of the money was counterfeit. He served a brief prison sentence for circulating forged notes. Bazna lived in Ankara with his family for many years and obtained work doing odd jobs. He moved to [[Munich]] in 1960 and worked as a night watchman before dying in 1970 of kidney disease.  Bazna published a memoir of the Cicero affair in 1962.

==Early life and family==
[[File:Old Pristina.jpg|thumb|Pristina around the turn of the century]]
Bazna was born in 1904 in [[Pristina]], [[Kosovo Vilayet]] of the [[Ottoman Empire]] (now [[Kosovo]]). His parents were of Albanian heritage.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}} His father was a teacher of [[Islam]]ic doctrine and a landowner.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=29}} He later stated that his father was a [[Muslim]] [[mullah]] named Hafiz Yazan Bazna, his uncle was Major General Kemal, and his grandfather was [[Tahir Pasha (Mosul)|Tahir Pasha]] the Brave. Both his grandfather and uncle were [[Young Turks]] that served under [[Mustafa Kemal Atatürk]].{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}{{Sfn|Denniston|2004}}

When he was 14, Serbs occupied Bazna's birthplace and his family relocated during the [[defeat and dissolution of the Ottoman Empire]]{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=29}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} to [[Istanbul]],{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} which was then occupied by British, Italian and American [[Allies of World War I|Allied forces of World War I]].{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}} The  [[Turkish National Movement]]  (nationalists) opposed the occupying forces.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} Writer [[Yakub Kadri Karaosmanoğlu]] said that &quot;the occupying forces in Istanbul considered all the cruelty and oppression committed by them against the people [of Istanbul] as lawful.&quot;{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}}

According to Bazna, he attended a military academy in [[Fatih]], Turkey before 1919.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} At the age of 16, he joined a French military unit in Istanbul.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}} He claimed to have stolen British weapons and cars for the Turkish National Movement, which was led by Atatürk.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}  Richard Wires, author of ''Cicero'', stated that Bazna was not motivated to steal for political or patriotic reasons.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=29}} When he was caught stealing, Bazna was sent to a [[labor camp|penal labor camp]] in [[Marseille]], France for three years.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=30}} He said that he worked at the [[Berliet]] motor company after he left the labor camp.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} While there,{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} he learned locksmithing skills.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}{{Sfn|Shugaar, Ernest, Guarnaccia|2006|p=44}} In 1925, Bazna moved to Istanbul, where he worked for the Istanbul Corporation in the transportation department. He then worked as a fire brigade chief in [[Yozgat]] before returning to Istanbul to drive taxis.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}

Bazna spoke [[Turkish language|Turkish]], [[Serbo-Croatian|Serbo-Croat]] and [[French language|French]],{{Sfn|Roth|1981|p=86}} the latter of which was the standard language of diplomacy at that time.{{Sfn|Kurbalija, Slavik|2001|p=39}} He also knew a little German from singing [[Lied]]er and said that he could read basic English but had difficulty speaking it.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=72}} He was trained as an opera singer.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=393}}

Bazna married twice; with his first wife, whom he later divorced, he had four children.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=30}}{{Sfn|Simmons|2014|p=151}} He had several live-in mistresses, one of whom, Mara, was a nursemaid to the children of David Busk, a British ambassador.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=31}} Mara lived with him in the [[Kavaklıdere, Ankara|Kavaklıdere]] hills in a small house that he called &quot;Cicero Villa&quot;. Their relationship was tumultuous and Bazna ended the affair due to their fighting and her jealousy. However, she was loyal to him and passed important information to him twice, once about the upcoming arrival of British security men at the embassy and the second time when she said that she had heard rumors that the Germans had a good source of intelligence. Once he began seeing a new mistress, Esra, his relationship with Mara ended permanently.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=127}} After Esra, he took a woman named Aika as his mistress and set her up in an apartment. She left after his pound notes were determined to be counterfeit.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=180}}{{efn|Bazna claimed that he provided for the women and children in his life financially, including providing a dowry for Mara and a university education for Esra.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=180}}}} He then married for a second time to a woman named Duriet and had four more children.{{Sfn|Simmons|2014|p=151}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=180–181}}

==Espionage career==

===Background: Turkey during World War II===
Turkey was neutral during much of World War II,{{Sfn|National Archives and Records Administration|2016}} although in October 1939, Britain signed a treaty to protect Turkey should Germany attack them.{{Sfn|Zurcher|2004|pp=203–5}}{{Sfn|Edwards|1946|pp=389–400 }} It maintained its neutrality by preventing German troops from crossing its borders into Syria or the USSR. During this time, Turkey had lucrative trade relationships with Germany and Britain.{{Sfn|Zurcher|2004|pp=203–5}}{{Sfn|Edwards|1946|pp=389–400 }} Germany had significant business interests in Turkey, including banks, and beginning in 1941 was reliant on [[chromite]] ore from Turkey for its armament production. In 1943, all of the chromite ore Germany imported for its weaponry came from Turkey.{{Sfn|National Archives and Records Administration|2016}} Throughout the war, Turkey's economy was reliant and prospered by virtue of its affiliation with both the Allied and the Axis powers. As a result, Turkey's gold reserve had risen to 216 tons by the end of 1945, from 27 tons at the beginning of the war.{{Sfn|National Archives and Records Administration|2016}} 

[[File:Churchill and İnönü.jpg|thumb|British Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]] and Turkish President [[İsmet İnönü]] in conversation during a two-day conference in a train at [[Adana]], near the Turkish-Syrian border, circa {{nowrap|28 February}} 1943]]
Starting in 1942, the Allies provided military aid,{{Sfn|Zurcher|2004|pp=203–5}}{{Sfn|Edwards|1946|pp=389–400 }} and then they began imposing [[economic sanctions]] in 1943 to force Turkey to enter the war.{{Sfn|National Archives and Records Administration|2016}}{{efn|Turkish leaders conferred with Roosevelt and Churchill at the [[Cairo Conference]] in November 1943, and promised to enter the war.{{Sfn|Zurcher|2004|pp=203–5}}{{Sfn|Edwards|1946|pp=389–400 }} By April 1944, Nazi forces in the [[Crimea]] were in full retreat.{{Sfn|Crump|2013|pp=39–40}} The Turkish Government worried that the advancing Red Army might drive through Bulgaria and seize the [[Turkish Straits]], which the Russians coveted.{{Sfn|Crump|2013|pp=39–40}} Turkish policy had been to stay neutral during the war.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=2, 173–175}} Now that they saw the need to reach some accommodation with the Allies, the Turks replaced their army chief [[Fevzi Çakmak]] with [[Kâzım Orbay]] who was &quot;more sympathetic to the Allies&quot;.{{Sfn|VanderLippe|2012|p=99}}{{Sfn|Osborn|2000|pp=31–33}}}} The western Allied powers wanted Turkey to become engaged in a fight against Germany's eastern flank; however, Turkey was afraid of being overrun by the Russian and German armies, both of which were led by dictators.{{Sfn|Kirkus|1999}}

The Allied and Axis powers became increasingly involved in espionage in Turkey to protect their own strategic interests beginning in 1943. There were two Allied factions, the western Allies and the Soviet Union. Germany was the third entity engaged in intelligence gathering.{{Sfn|Kirkus|1999}} The Germans were able to fund their espionage, propaganda, and diplomacy efforts from the profits of its banks in Turkey.{{Sfn|National Archives and Records Administration|2016}} 

By August 1944, Turkey broke off relations with Germany, as defeat began to seem inevitable. In February 1945, it declared war on Germany and Japan, a symbolic move that allowed Turkey to join the emerging [[United Nations]].{{Sfn|Zurcher|2004|pp=203–5}}{{Sfn|Edwards|1946|pp=389–400 }}

===Employment by diplomats===
Bazna worked for foreign diplomats and consulates as a doorman, driver, and guard upon his return to Turkey.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=130–131}} Enabled by his ability to speak French,{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=30}} he served as a ''[[kavass]]''{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} or [[valet]], first to the Yugoslav ambassador to Turkey.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=30}} In 1942, he worked as a valet for Albert Jenke, a German businessman and later embassy staff member, who came to fire Bazna for reading his mail.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=30}}

Before he worked for [[Hughe Knatchbull-Hugessen|Sir Hughe Knatchbull-Hugessen]] in 1943,{{efn|name=Hire}} Bazna was hired to do some household and vehicle repairs for Douglas Busk, the first secretary of the British Embassy. Due to Bazna's poor English, he answered all interview questions in French. Although he supplied some written biographical information, excluding having been employed and fired by Albert Jenke, none of the biographical information was checked. Turkish secret service apparently warned the embassy at some point about Bazna. Over the few months that Bazna worked for Busk, he secretly photographed a few documents and, with the help of Mrs. Bush's nursemaid named Mara, he tried to gain access to more valuable forms of intelligence.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=31–32}}

Busk agreed to recommend Bazna for the open position of valet to Sir Hughe Knatchbull-Hugessen, the British ambassador to Turkey, who hired him in 1943{{efn|When Bazna begun working for the embassy varies depending upon the source. He has said to have started in mid-July,{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=10}} September,{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}} or October 1943.{{Sfn|Polmar, Allen|2012|p=211}}|name=Hire}} assuming that a background check had been performed.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=31–32}}{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=10}} Knatchbull-Hugessen had been the British ambassador in [[Riga]], Latvia until 1935.{{Sfn|Hanovs, Teraudkalns|2013|p=36}}

[[Anthony Cave Brown]], author of ''Bodyguard of Lies'', wrote &quot;Soon, Bazna had ingratiated himself to the extent that Sir Hughe elevated him from purely household duties to a position of some power within the residency and embassy. He dressed him in an imposing blue uniform, gave him a peaked cap, and used him as a guard to the door of his study; Bazna excluded visitors when Sir Hughe was thinking or napping. For ceremonial occasions, Sir Hughe dressed him in richly embroidered brocade, shoes with turned up toes, a fez with a tassel, gave him an immense [[scimitar]], and placed him on the main door. Sir Hughe also paid him more than the 100 Turkish ''lira'' that was standard for a valet, and quietly turned a blind eye to the fact that Bazna was having an affair with Lady Knatchbull-Hugessen's handmaiden in the servants' quarters.&quot;{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=393}} Bazna often sang German Lieders after lunch while Knatchbull-Hugessen played the piano,{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=393}} much to the ambassador's enjoyment.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=393}}{{Sfn|Tweedie, Day|2003}}

===Beginning of espionage career===
While at Riga, Knatchbull-Hugessen had developed a habit of taking secret papers to his home from the British embassy, and the ambassador continued that practice in Ankara.{{efn||name=&quot;Leak&quot;}} Bazna gained access to documents in the ambassador's document box and safe using his locksmithing skills,{{Sfn|Tweedie, Day|2003}} including making impressions and then copies of the key for the document box.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}  He began photographing  secret documents about war strategy, troop movements, and negotiations with Turkey to enter the war.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|p=128}} He took the photographs while the ambassador slept,{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|pp=128–129}}{{Sfn|Price|2014|pp=26-29}} took a bath, or played the piano.{{Sfn|Tweedie, Day|2003}}

Bazna approached the German Embassy in Ankara on {{nowrap|26 October}} 1943, indicating that he wanted {{nowrap|[[Pound sterling|£]]20,000 for}} two rolls of film of the ambassador's documents.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|p=128}} He became a spy{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=30}} through the connection with his former employer, Albert Jenke. Jenke was the brother-in-law of [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]], the German Foreign Minister in Turkey.  Although he was fired by Jenke, his wife contacted German intelligence officer [[Ludwig Carl Moyzisch]] and told him of the photographs that Bazna had taken of classified information at the British Embassy.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}{{Sfn|von Hassell|MacRae|2013|p=177}}{{efn|The ''Alliance of Enemies: The Untold Story of the Secret American and German Collaboration to End World War II'' states that Jenke was the son-in-law of [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]].{{Sfn|von Hassell|MacRae|2013|p=177}} But other sources states that Jenke was Ribbentrop's brother-in-law.{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=394}}{{Sfn|Keegan|2002|p=10}}{{Sfn|Steinberg|1999}}}} He became a paid German agent under Moyzisch and was given the [[Sicherheitsdienst]] (SD) code name &quot;Cicero&quot;{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}{{Sfn|Trenear-Harvey|2014|pp=44–47}} by German Ambassador [[Franz von Papen]] due to Bazna's &quot;astonishing eloquence&quot;.{{Sfn|Shugaar, Ernest, Guarnaccia|2006|p=44}} His Nazi paymasters made about {{nowrap|one-half}} of his payments in [[counterfeit]] bank notes under [[Operation Bernhard]].{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}

According to Mummer Kaylan, author of ''The Kemalists: Islamic Revival and the Fate of Secular Turkey'', Bazna said that he began spying for the Germans because he needed the money and, although he was not a [[Nazism|Nazi]], he liked Germans and disliked the British. He also alluded to involvement with the ''Milli Emniyet Hizmeti'', which became the Turkish [[National Security Service (Turkey)|National Security Service]] in 1965.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|p=131–135}}{{efn|Bazna told Moyzisch a misleading and melodramatic story about  his hatred of the British was because his father had been killed by a Briton, which initially moved and ultimately left Moyzisch skeptical. This story was untrue. His father died peacefully in his bed.{{Sfn|Maclean|1978}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=40}}}}

===Intelligence===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-2007-0705-502, Chiffriermaschine &quot;Enigma&quot;.jpg|thumb|right|[[Enigma machine|Enigma cipher machine]]]]
During the first three months of 1944, Cicero supplied the Germans with copies of documents taken from his employer's dispatch box or his safe. Photographs of top secret documents were generally handed over in Moyzisch's car, which was parked inconspicuously on an Ankara street. On one occasion, this led to a high-speed chase around Ankara as someone had taken an interest in the hand-over. Bazna, who had perhaps been tailed, escaped.{{Sfn|Price|2014|pp=26-29}} [[Ultra]], the British codebreaking system based at [[Bletchley Park]] routinely read German messages, coded by the [[Enigma machine]].{{Sfn|Nash|1997|p=487}} From that information, the codebreakers knew that there was an intelligence breach, but did not know that the source was the British Embassy in Turkey.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=132}}

[[Guy Liddell]], who worked for [[MI5]], recorded that there was a breach in security at the embassy on {{nowrap|17 October}} 1943, which was later reported by ISOS, Intelligent Service [[Oliver Strachey]]. The leak involved an embassy diplomat bag and two agents. On {{nowrap|3 November}}, Lilddell talked to [[Stewart Menzies]],{{Sfn|Trenear-Harvey|2014|pp=44–47}} head of British Secret Intelligence Service.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|p=136}} Through the discussion, Liddell learned that the leak of the diplomatic bag occurred during or after the air attaché brought it back from Cairo, which put not-yet-deployed re-ciphering tables at risk and required the abandonment of the tables. There were also missing blueprints for a gun at the office of a military attaché. Menzies stated that there was an investigation underway at the embassy, but nothing more was said about the leak for a few months.{{Sfn|Trenear-Harvey|2014|pp=44–47}}{{efn|There was a leak noted before Bazna began work as spy for the Germans.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|p=128}}{{Sfn|Trenear-Harvey|2014|pp=44–47}} In October 1941, a de-crypt from ISOS stated that there was a leak at the embassy.{{Sfn|Trenear-Harvey|2014|pp=44–47}}|name=&quot;Leak&quot;}}

[[File:American and Allied leaders at international conferences - NARA - 292624.jpg|thumb|Allied leaders at the [[Cairo Conference]] held in Cairo, Egypt in November 1943. Seated are Generalissimo [[Chiang Kai-shek]], [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], and [[Winston Churchill]]]]
As Cicero, Bazna passed on important information about many of the Allied leaders' conferences,{{Sfn|Polmar, Allen|2012|p=211}} including the [[Moscow Conference (1943)|Moscow]],  [[Tehran Conference|Tehran]] and [[Cairo Conference]]s.{{Sfn|Tweedie, Day|2003}}{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|pp=3–6}} Fortunately for the British, Knatchbull-Hugessen only had possession of one document of notes from the conferences.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|pp=3–6}}

The intelligence provided by Cicero included a document instructing the British ambassador to request the use of Turkish air bases &quot;to maintain a threat to the Germans from the eastern Mediterranean until Overlord is launched.&quot; The document carried the highest security restriction ([[BIGOT list]]).{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=121}} Cicero conveyed limited information about [[Operation Overlord]] (the code name for the [[Invasion of Normandy]] in June 1944),{{Sfn|Polmar, Allen|2012|p=211}} which was not correlated by the Germans until after the war when films about Cicero were released.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=157}} According to the British Foreign Office's postwar review of Cicero's potential impacts: &quot;It [Bazna's intelligence] provided the Germans with streams of information from the desk of the ambassador about British and Allied intentions in the Near and Middle East and for the conduct of the war generally, and might easily have compromised Operation Overlord (the preparations for D-Day).&quot;{{Sfn|National Archives (UK)|2005}}

When the Cicero documents predicted Allied bombing missions in the [[Balkans]], which took place on the predicted date, the authenticity of the information was supported and his reputation enhanced. Moyzisch told Cicero that at the end of the war Hitler intended to give him a villa.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=149}}

===Appraisal by the Germans===
Copies of the developed film or summaries prepared by Moyzisch were promptly passed on to senior German leaders. Ribbentrop showed the initial set of photographs to Hitler immediately upon receipt. Hitler entered a conference with some Cicero materials in December 1943 and declared that the invasion in the west would come in spring 1944. He concluded, though, that there would also be attacks in other locations, such as Norway or the Balkans.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=81–82}}

According to Moyzisch, the German Foreign Office did not make much use of the documents, because officers there were divided about their reliability{{Sfn|CIA|2016}} for several reasons. There was a steady stream of documents, which was highly unusual. Cicero seemed to have used sophisticated photography techniques to create unusually clear images, which raised the question of whether he acted alone.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=74–75}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|pp=395–398}}{{efn|Moyzisch was convinced that the spy had someone helping him to locate and photograph the documents. German photography experts reviewed 112 photographs provided by Cicero and determined that one person could have held the documents and taken the photographs. Based on the subsequent photograph that showed a hurried image with fingers and Bazna's signet ring, a German investigator was brought to Turkey. He determined that the photographer was quite skilled, but appeared to have assistance taking at least one photograph. Doubts persisted, but a second man was never identified.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=74–75}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|pp=395–398}}}} Antipathy between Papen and Ribbentrop added to the ineffective analysis of the intelligence.{{Sfn|Gladwell|2010}} Aware of the Allied forces attempts to bring Turkey into the war, however, Papen was able to thwart their efforts for a time{{Sfn|Tweedie, Day|2003}} by threatening to destroy [[İzmir]] and Istanbul if Turkey declared war against Germany. Being able to postpone Turkey's alliance with the Allied forces and the use of their airfields, Papen told Ribbentrop that the way was now clear to take the Balkans.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=5}}

===Double agent hypothesis===
The [[Abwehr]] was right to worry about the presence of British double agents within their secret service.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=137}}{{Sfn|Maslin|2012}} They were at that time already running 'Garbo' ([[Joan Pujol Garcia|Juan Pujol]]), 'Zig-Zag' ([[Eddie Chapman]]) and 'Tricycle' ([[Dušan Popov]]), supposedly German agents to whom they were paying large sums of money, but who were in reality working for the British and were supplying the Germans with false information.{{Sfn|Maslin|2012}}

The head of British Secret Intelligence Service, Stewart Menzies, stated that Cicero was indeed a double agent and that among the documents submitted to the Germans were documents of misinformation.{{Sfn|Gladwell|2010}} Author James Srodes states in his biography of [[Allen Dulles]] that some British historians believed that Cicero was &quot;'turned' into a double agent to send disinformation via von Papen&quot;.{{Sfn|Srodes|2000|p=292}} Malcolm Gladwell, author of ''Pandora's Briefcase'', questioned Menzies before he died about whether he was telling the truth. He replied &quot;Of course, Cicero was under our control,&quot; but his truthfulness is questioned.{{Sfn|Gladwell|2010}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=137}} Gladwell stated in an article in ''[[The New Yorker]]''; &quot;if you had been the wartime head of M.I.6, giving an interview shortly before your death, you probably would say that Cicero was one of yours.&quot; Gladwell also mentions that while Ribbentrop was wary of Bazna, which curtailed the dissemination of some of Bazna's intelligence, most German intelligence officials were not wary of him.{{Sfn|Gladwell|2010}}

Anthony Cave Brown suggests in his book ''Bodyguard of Lies'' that [[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]]'s continental secret service chief, Lieutenant Colonel Montague Reaney Chidson, responsible for security of the embassy, would not have overlooked Bazna as a potential threat and may have fed the documents that Bazna in the ambassador's keeping or directly led Cicero as a double agent. Brown states that &quot;Bazna was indeed under British control within a short time after he started to photograph the documents&quot;,{{Sfn|Brown|2007|pp=399–401}} and he was a participant in  [[Operation Bodyguard|Plan Jael and Operation Bodyguard]].{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=137}}&lt;!--- Plan Jael redirects to Operation Bodyguard-----&gt;

Mummer Kaylan states that through his personal knowledge of Bazna, he thought that Bazna supported Turkish interests and was not guided by British Intelligence. Further, he says that Bazna having passed on &quot;genuine&quot;, &quot;important&quot; intelligence and the codeword for Operation Overlord to the Germans supports his theory that Bazna was not a double agent. If he was a double agent, Kaylan believes he was an agent for the Turkish Security Service, Milli Emniyet Hizmeti.{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|p=136}} [[Walter Schellenberg]], too, wondered if Bazna passed on intelligence to the Turkish Secret Service.{{Sfn|Yenne|2015|p=205}}

===Discovery of intelligence leaks===
[[File:Fritzkolbe2.jpg|thumb|[[Fritz Kolbe]], a German [[diplomat]] who became America's most important spy against the Nazis in [[World War II]]. [[Office of Strategic Services]]'s [[Allen Dulles]] said of him, &quot;George Wood (our code name for Kolbe) was not only our best source on Germany but undoubtedly one of the best secret agents any intelligence service has ever had.&quot;{{Sfn|Paterson|2004}} Kolbe identified that there was a spy operating out of a British Embassy in December 1943.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=130–132}}]]
[[Fritz Kolbe]], assistant to German diplomat [[Karl Ritter]], screened German cable messages for information to summarize and supply to [[Allen Dulles]], who was the [[Office of Strategic Services]] (OSS) chief representative in Bern. In late December 1943, Kolbe reported that there was a spy operating out of a British Embassy with the code name Cicero. Dulles forwarded this information to MI6 agent Frederick Vanden Heuvel on {{nowrap|1 January}} 1944.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp= 130–132}} Cave Brown contends that Dulles passed the information to London in December. Since Bazna was about to carry out acts of espionage in December, Brown concludes that Bazna was likely a double agent.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p= 137}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|pp=401, 402–404}}

American agents in Ankara investigated Cicero's identity based upon Dulles' intelligence.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=171}} British intelligence, who were asked by Dulles to interrogate Cicero, gave the impression that they believed that Bazna could not speak English and, furthermore, was &quot;too stupid&quot; to be a spy.{{Sfn|Delattre|2007|p=135}} British Foreign Office workers, though, were concerned about Operation Overlord leaks and thought that Bazna might be Cicero. They implemented a sting in January 1944 using a false Cabinet Office document that was drafted by the chair of the Joint Intelligence Committee, [[Victor Cavendish-Bentinck, 9th Duke of Portland|Victor Cavendish-Bentinck]] and given the forged signature of Foreign Secretary [[Anthony Eden]]. The document was planted in the embassy, but the sting was unsuccessful in trapping Bazna.{{Sfn|BBC|2005}}{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=6}}

About January 1944,{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=160–163}} Moyzisch hired a new secretary named Cornelia Kapp, also known as Nele Kapp, who had spied for the British and Americans in exchange for permission to immigrate to the United States.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}{{Sfn|CIA|2016}} She had worked at the Germany embassy in [[Sofia]], Bulgaria beginning in July 1943 and within a month had become a spy. In January 1944, she moved to Ankara to work at the German embassy under Moyzisch. Kapp was asked by the OSS to learn about the spy that Moyzisch met with. Kapp was adept at gathering intelligence within the office. She flirted with Cicero when he called the office to schedule a meeting with Moyzisch. When she could, Kapp also followed the two men to try to see what the spy looked like, but was unsuccessful at getting a good view of him.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=160–163}} Kapp had gathered and shared a lot of information with the OCC over the months that she worked at the embassy, including all that she felt that she could learn about Cicero.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=164–165}}{{efn|In March 1944, Kapp opened a courier bag, not identified for Moyzisch's eyes only, with information about Cicero at the British Embassy. She asked Moyzisch about the spy, which was unsettling to him. Kapp became fearful that she would be killed and &quot;had a nervous breakdown&quot;.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=164–165}} Fearing for her own safety, Kapp fled Turkey and was placed in a Cairo internment camp before defecting to the United States. Moyzisch, who called his secretary Elisabet in his book,  ''Operation Cicero'', said that he believed that she was responsible for the downfall of the Cicero Affair.{{Sfn|CIA|2016}} Kapp was the daughter of a German consul and anti-Nazi who had spent most of her early life in Calcutta and Cleveland. Moyzisch did not know that Nele hated the Nazis and had been supplying information to the British and the American [[Office of Strategic Services|OSS]]. She eventually [[defection|defected]] and was helped by an OSS agent to board the Taurus Express from Ankara to Istanbul but alighting before the city, was taken to an air base that the RAF was building in Turkey. From there she was driven to İzmir and then ultimately made her way to [[Cairo]], where she was furious to learn that she was to be interned as a German. She eventually reached America, settled in California, and married an American and had at least one child.{{Sfn|CIA|2016}}}}

Once the embassy had been tipped off that there was a spy operating in the facility in early 1944, Bazna found it increasingly difficult to gather intelligence.{{Sfn|Price|2014|pp=26-29}}{{Sfn|CIA|2016}} The British Field Office had warned the embassy of a security leak. Bazna forwarded the document to the Germans. The warning had come to Churchill from Roosevelt, who obtained the information given by a defector to the United States.{{Sfn|Tweedie, Day|2003}} A new alarm system in the British Embassy now required Bazna to remove a fuse whenever he wanted to look in the ambassador's safe.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}}

Bazna gave notice about the third week of January 1944 that he would be leaving the ambassador's employment.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=10}}  He stopped selling information to the Germans by the end of February 1944{{Sfn|Adams|2009}} and left the embassy at the end of the month{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=10}} or about {{nowrap|20 April}}{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=398}} without any trouble.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|dsp=152}} Bazna was identified as Cicero after the war ended.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=2}}

=== Potential consequences ===
{{Quote box|width=33%|align=right|quote=One of the best known spy stories of our time is that of Operation Cicero, a textbook exercise in tradecraft set in neutral Ankara during World War II. It is, perhaps, of little importance that the exercise remained rather academic – that the information pilfered in the best traditions of the cloak-and-dagger business was never fully used by the Nazis; that the British, warned of the Ciceronian activity, took no effective action to stop it; and that Cicero himself was never brought to book. As a matter of fact, the academic nature of the exercise makes Operation Cicero a nice, neat package to handle, uncomplicated by consequences and relatively free of loose ends.|author=Dorothy J. Heatts |source=Footnote to Cicero, CIA Historical Review Program{{Sfn|CIA|2016}}}}
In March 2005, British [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]] historians issued ''The Cicero Papers'', an analysis of the potential consequences of the 'Cicero Affair'. In it, they identified four important ways in which Cicero's intelligence could have harmed the Allied forces during World War II.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|pp=3–6}}

One of the key potential consequences was the possibility of alerting the German regime to the scope of Project Overlord. Fortunately, the location and the date of the planned invasion were not conveyed.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|pp=3–6}} The Allied forces wanted Turkey to declare war and join them in their efforts against Germany, particularly after they had taken the [[Dodecanese|Dodecanese Islands]] and the Allies had secured Italy as a partner against Germany. Turkish airfields were important to maintain their strategic advantage in the area, particularly to support  [[Operation Accolade]], the British assault on [[Rhodes]] and the Dodecanese islands. With Cicero's intelligence, Papen was able to delay Turkey's entry into the war.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|pp=3–6}}

Bazna passed on the details for the Tehran Conference plans, which supported the unsuccessful [[Operation Long Jump]] plot{{Sfn|Yenne|2015|p=102}} to kill  [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], [[Joseph Stalin]], and [[Winston Churchill]].{{Sfn|Craig|2005|p=164}}

Once the British were aware of the leak, they were concerned that Cicero had leaked information that might help crack the British [[cipher]], but that did not occur.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|pp=3–6}} Lastly, the intelligence might have made the Germans believe that there was no danger of attack in the Balkans, which may have been the most potentially damaging information gleaned by Cicero for the Germans.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|pp=3–6}}

==After the war==
After the war ended, the OSS conducted an investigation into Cicero, interviewing key German players including Moyzisch.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=171}}{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=2}} It was postulated that of the intelligence conveyed by Cicero to the Germans, the most notable information came from Knatchbull-Hugessen's notes, particularly regarding diplomatic efforts with the Turkish government. Many of the other documents were considered by Ostuf Schuddekoft, head of the British section of Amt VI [one of the 11 departments of [[Hauptamt Volksdeutsche Mittelstelle]]], to be too old to be of much value to the Germans.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=2}} Moyzisch was aggressively interviewed by the Allies and was a witness at the [[Nuremberg trials]], after which he wrote a book to address rumors and explain his role during the war. He was never charged with a war crime.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|p=178}}

Knatchbull-Hugessen's reputation was severely hampered by the Cicero Affair,{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=2}} particularly as he had been previously warned about leaving his keys and document boxes unattended. On {{nowrap|28 August}} 1945, Knatchbull-Hugessen received a formal, severe reprimand, but he was not court-martialed.{{Sfn|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005|p=7}}

The Abwehr paid Bazna £300,000, or US$1.2 million, which he kept hidden.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}} After the war he tried to build a hotel with a partner, but when his sterling notes were checked by the Bank of England, they were found to be mostly counterfeit (see [[Operation Bernhard]]).{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=398}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=180–181}} The spy remarked that the notes were &quot;not worth even the price of the Turkish linen out of which they had been manufactured.&quot;{{Sfn|Brown|2007|p=398}} Bazna served some time in prison for using counterfeit money.{{Sfn|Polmar, Allen|2012|p=211}}

Bazna lived in an apartment in the European [[Aksaray, Istanbul|Aksaray neighborhood]] of Istanbul with his family in the 1950s.{{Sfn|Simmons|2014|p=151}}{{Sfn|Kaylan|2005|p=127}} He gave singing lessons and worked as a used car salesman{{Sfn|Simmons|2014|p=151}} and a night watchman.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}} Much of the money he earned went to the creditors who had been paid with forged money.{{Sfn|Simmons|2014|p=151}}  He contacted the West German government to be reimbursed for the counterfeit money that he received.{{Sfn|CIA|2016}}{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=180–181, 183}} Although he tried many times and in many ways to get a payment, he never received additional money.{{Sfn|Wires|1999|pp=183, 197}}

In 1960, Bazna moved to Germany and worked in [[Munich]] as a night watchman.{{Sfn|Luce|1971|p=xcvi}} Bazna and Hans Nogly wrote ''I was Cicero'', which was published in 1962. It told the story of the Cicero Affair from Bazna's perspective following Moyzisch's book ''Operation Cicero'' published in 1950.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}} Bazna died in Munich of kidney disease in December 1970.{{Sfn|Luce|1971|p=xcvi}}

==In popular culture==
According to the British Foreign Office: &quot;The tale has become a popular (and frequently mis-told) war story.&quot;{{Sfn|National Archives (UK)|2005}}

Moyzisch published his memoirs, titled ''Operation Cicero'', in 1950.{{Sfn|Polmar, Allen|2012|p=211}}{{efn|Both books by Bazna and Moyzisch had &quot;factual errors&quot;, according to Jefferson Adams.{{Sfn|Adams|2009}} |name=fn2}}  Franz von Papen and Allen Dulles suggested that there was more to the story than was published in the book, but neither provided any details.{{Sfn|CIA|2016}} Twelve years later, in 1962, ''I was Cicero'' was published by Cicero himself.{{Sfn|Polmar, Allen|2012|p=211}}{{Sfn|Bazna|1962}}{{efn|name=fn2}}

A film based on the book ''Operation Cicero'' by Moyzisch was released by [[20th Century Fox]] in 1952. It was titled ''[[5 Fingers]]'' and directed by [[Joseph L. Mankiewicz]]. Bazna, renamed Ulysses Diello, was played by [[James Mason]].{{Sfn|Sweeney|1999|pp=124–125}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Sources==
* {{cite book|first=Jefferson | last=Adams|title=Historical Dictionary of German Intelligence|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gnEWm4kC844C&amp;pg=PA69|date=1 September 2009|publisher=Scarecrow Press|isbn=978-0-8108-6320-0|chapter=Cicero Affair|ref={{SfnRef|Adams|2009}}}}
* {{cite book | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=344gAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Friedhof+am+Perlacher+Forst%22+Cicero&amp;dq=%22Friedhof+am+Perlacher+Forst%22+Cicero&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi3q4fjoYDNAhUNdlIKHYWPD1EQ6AEIHDAA | title=Von Dahlem each Hiroshima | first=Peter | last=Auer | publisher=Aufbau Verlag GmbH | year=1995 | isbn=3-351-02429-0 |ref={{SfnRef|Auer|1995|p=239}}}}
* {{cite book | author=Bazna, Elyesa |title=I was Cicero | location=London | publisher=A. Deutsch | year=1962 | lccn=62048893 |ref={{SfnRef|Bazna|1962}}}}
* {{ cite news | author=BBC Staff|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4399385.stm | title=Secret plot to catch out Nazi spy | newspaper=[[BBC News]] | date=1 April 2005 | accessdate=27 May 2016 |ref={{SfnRef|BBC|2005}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Anthony Cave | last=Brown|title=Bodyguard of Lies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Q0UBW_KysgMC&amp;pg=PA394|date=1 November 2007|publisher=Globe Pequot Press|isbn=978-1-59921-383-5|ref={{SfnRef|Brown|2007}}}}
* {{cite web | author=CIA | url=https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/kent-csi/vol1no4/html/v01i4a06p_0001.htm | title=Footnote to Cicero, CIA Historical Review Program | publisher=[[Central Intelligence Agency]] | date= 18 September 2016 | accessdate=27 May 2016 |ref={{SfnRef|CIA|2016}}}}{{US government sources}}
* {{cite book|first=John S. | last=Craig|title=Peculiar Liaisons: In War, Espionage, and Terrorism in the Twentieth Century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UKlMBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA164|year=2005|publisher=Algora Publishing|isbn=978-0-87586-331-3|ref={{SfnRef|Craig|2005}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Thomas | last=Crump|title=Brezhnev and the Decline of the Soviet Union|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ifMJAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA39|date=7 November 2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-134-66915-8|ref={{SfnRef|Crump|2013}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Lucas | last=Delattre|title=A Spy at the Heart of the Third Reich: The Extraordinary Story of Fritz Kolbe, America's Most Important Spy in World War II|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PerFm77zs_4C&amp;pg=PA135|date=1 December 2007|publisher=Grove/Atlantic, Incorporated|isbn=978-0-8021-9649-1|ref={{SfnRef|Delattre|2007}}}}
* {{cite web | url=http://oxfordindex.oup.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/60870 | title=Bazna, Elyesa [alias Cicero] (b. 1903), spy | first=Robin | last=Denniston | publisher=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography | date=September 2004 | accessdate=29 May 2016|ref={{SfnRef|Denniston|2004}}}}
* {{cite journal | first=A. C. | last=Edwards | title=The Impact of the War on Turkey | journal=International Affairs | year=1946 | volume=22 | number=3 | pages =389–400 | jstor=3017044 |ref={{SfnRef|Edwards|1946}}}}
* {{cite web | url=https://issuu.com/fcohistorians/docs/hpdfba_7 | title=The Cicero Papers | publisher=Foreign and Commonwealth Office | date=March 2005 | accessdate=28 May 2016 | author=FCO Historians |ref={{SfnRef|Foreign and Commonwealth Office historians|2005}}}}
* {{cite news|url=http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2010/05/10/pandoras-briefcase|title=Pandora's Briefcase|first=Malcolm | last=Gladwell|date=10 May 2010|accessdate=28 May 2016 | ref={{SfnRef|Gladwell|2010}}}} 
* {{cite book|first1=Deniss | last1=Hanovs|first2=Valdis | last2=Teraudkalns|title=Ultimate Freedom – No Choice: The Culture of Authoritarianism in Latvia, 1934–1940|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oRczAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA36|date=22 January 2013|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-24464-1|ref={{SfnRef|Hanovs, Teraudkalns|2013}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Muammer | last=Kaylan|title=The Kemalists: Islamic Revival and the Fate of Secular Turkey|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aEh_IofABkYC&amp;pg=PA130|publisher=Prometheus Books|isbn=978-1-61592-897-2|year=2005|ref={{SfnRef|Kaylan|2005}}}}
* {{cite book|first=John | last=Keegan|title=Who's Who in World War II|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TXuBAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA10|date=September 11, 2002|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-134-50964-5|chapter=Bazna, Elyesa|ref={{SfnRef|Keegan|2002}}}}
* {{cite web | author=Kirkus Reviews| url=https://www.kirkusreviews.com/book-reviews/richard-wires/the-cicero-spy-affair/ | title=The Cicero Spy Affair: German Access to British Secrets in World War II |website=Kirkus Reviews | date=15 October 1999 |accessdate=18 October 2016 |ref={{SfnRef|Kirkus|1999}}}}
* {{cite book|editor=Luce, Henry Robinson|title=Time|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2xknAQAAIAAJ|date=January 1971|publisher=Time Incorporated|page=xcvi|chapter=Died. Elyesa Bazna | ref={{SfnRef|Luce|1971}}}}
* {{cite book|first1=Jovan |last1=Kurbalija|first2=Hannah |last2=Slavik|title=Language and Diplomacy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yKcHHU2DaPoC&amp;pg=PA39|year=2001|publisher=Diplo Foundation|isbn=978-99909-55-15-6|ref={{SfnRef|Kurbalija, Slavik|2001}}}}
* {{cite book|author=[[Sir Fitzroy Maclean, 1st Baronet|Maclean, Fitzroy]]|title=Take Nine Spies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=E5YsAAAAYAAJ|date=20 April 1978|publisher=Weidenfeld and Nicolson|ref={{SfnRef|Maclean|1978}}}}
* {{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/09/books/double-cross-and-agent-garbo.html?_r=0 | title=The Agents Who Fooled the Nazis About D-Day | first=Janet | last= Maslin | newspaper=The New York Times | date=8 August 2012 | accessdate=27 May 2016 |ref={{SfnRef|Maslin|2012}} }}
* {{cite book|first=Jay Robert|last= Nash|title=Spies: A Narrative Encyclopedia of Dirty Tricks and Double Dealing from Biblical Times to Today|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0FIWCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA487|date=28 October 1997|publisher=M. Evans|isbn=978-1-4617-4770-3|ref={{SfnRef|Nash|1997|p=487}}}}
* {{cite web | author=National Archives (UK) |url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/releases/2005/highlights_april/april1/cicero.htm | title=Cicero archives at the British Foreign Office | publisher=National Archives (UK) | accessdate=27 May 2016 | year=2005 |ref={{SfnRef|National Archives (UK)|2005}}}}
* {{ cite web | author=National Archives and Records Administration |url=https://www.archives.gov/research/holocaust/finding-aid/civilian/rg-84-turkey.html | title=Records of the Foreign Service Posts of the Department of State (RG 84): Turkey | publisher=State Department and Foreign Affairs Records|via=[[National Archives and Records Administration]] | date=15 August 2016 | accessdate=18 October 2016 |ref={{SfnRef|National Archives and Records Administration|2016}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Patrick R. | last=Osborn|title=Operation Pike: Britain Versus the Soviet Union, 1939–1941|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=39Q6uCjQEWQC&amp;pg=PA32|year=2000|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-313-31368-4 |ref={{SfnRef|Osborn|2000}}}}
* {{ cite news | title= Germany finally honours the 'traitor' spy | first=Tony | last=Paterson | newspaper=The Independent | date= 25 September 2004 |ref={{SfnRef|Paterson|2004}}}}
* {{cite book|first1=Norman | last1=Polmar|first2=Thomas B. | last2= Allen|title=World War II: the Encyclopedia of the War Years, 1941–1945|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=30gRAGjXrIIC&amp;pg=PA211|date=15 August 2012|publisher=Courier Corporation|isbn=978-0-486-47962-0|ref={{SfnRef|Polmar, Allen|2012}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Sean | last=Price|title=World War II Spies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ugBOPAb-qUsC&amp;pg=PT22|year=2014|publisher=Capstone|isbn=978-1-4765-3592-0 |ref={{SfnRef|Price|2014}}}} 
* {{cite book|first=Arthur | last=Roth|title=Great spy stories|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HI2Ryagy3u8C|year=1981|publisher=Scholastic Book Services|isbn=978-0-590-31393-3|ref={{SfnRef|Roth|1981}}}}
* {{cite book|author1=Shugaar, Antony|author2=Peter Earnest|author3=Steven Guarnaccia|title=I Lie for a Living: Greatest Spies of All Times|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oohnZw6xRkkC&amp;pg=PA44|year=2006|publisher=National Geographic|isbn=978-0-7922-5316-7|ref={{SfnRef|Shugaar, Ernest, Guarnaccia|2006}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Mark |last=Simmons|title=Agent Cicero: Hitler's Most Successful Spy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=al4HBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PP151|date=15 July 2014|publisher=History Press|isbn=978-0-7509-5729-8|ref={{SfnRef|Simmons|2014}}}}
* {{cite book|first=James | last=Srodes|title=Allen Dulles: Master of Spies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RIaw7GYDFmwC&amp;pg=PA292|date=July 1, 2000|publisher=Regnery Publishing, Incorporated, An Eagle Publishing Company|isbn=978-0-89526-223-3|ref={{SfnRef|Srodes|2000}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Jonathan | last=Steinberg|title=The Deutsche Bank and Its Gold Transactions During the Second World War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RveyUr-6A4EC&amp;pg=PA55|date=January 1, 1999|publisher=C.H.Beck|isbn=978-3-406-44552-1|ref={{SfnRef|Steinberg|1999}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Kevin | last=Sweeney|title=James Mason: A Bio-bibliography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DVtVA4EajSgC&amp;pg=PA124|year=1999|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-313-28496-0|pages=124–125|ref={{SfnRef|Sweeney|1999}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Glenmore S. | last=Trenear-Harvey|title=Historical Dictionary of Intelligence Failures|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DTOaBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA44|date=20 November 2014|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers|isbn=978-1-4422-3274-7|ref={{SfnRef|Trenear-Harvey|2014}}}}
* {{ cite news | url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/turkey/1430768/Envoys-singing-valet-was-Nazi-spy.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110804223034/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/turkey/1430768/Envoys-singing-valet-was-Nazi-spy.html |archivedate=4 August 2011 | newspaper=Telegraph | title=Envoy's singing valet was Nazi spy | first1=Neil |last1=Tweedie | first2=Peter | last2=Day | date=22 May 2003 | accessdate=27 May 2016 |ref={{SfnRef|Tweedie, Day|2003}}}}
* {{cite book|first=John M. |last=VanderLippe|title=Politics of Turkish Democracy, The: Ismet Inonu and the Formation of the Multi-Party System, 1938–1950|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7u_YRaL42K8C&amp;pg=PA99|date=February 1, 2012|publisher=SUNY Press|isbn=978-0-7914-8337-4 |ref={{SfnRef|VanderLippe|2012}}}}
* {{cite book|first1=Agostino | last1=von Hassell|first2=Sigrid | last2=MacRae|title=Alliance of Enemies: The Untold Story of the Secret American and German Collaboration to End World War II|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=scq6AQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA177|date=December 10, 2013|publisher=St. Martin's Press|isbn=978-1-4668-5998-2|ref={{SfnRef|von Hassell|MacRae|2013|p=177}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Richard | last=Wires|title=The Cicero Spy Affair: German Access to British Secrets in World War II|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iZSuePrAbu4C&amp;pg=PA29|year=1999|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-275-96456-6|ref={{SfnRef|Wires|1999}}}}
* {{cite book|first=Bill | last=Yenne|title=Operation Long Jump: Stalin, Roosevelt, Churchill, and the Greatest Assassination Plot in History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sZJcCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA102|date=September 2015|publisher=Regnery Publishing|isbn=978-1-62157-346-3|ref={{SfnRef|Yenne|2015}}}}
* {{cite book | first=Erik J. | last=Zurcher | title=Turkey: A Modern History | edition=3rd | year=2004 | ref={{SfnRef|Zurcher|2004}}}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | first=Ian Goodhope | last= Colvin | title=Chief of Intelligence | publisher= Gollancz | location=London | year=1951 | lccn=51005512}}
* {{cite book | author=[[François Kersaudy|Kersaudy, François]] | title=L'affaire Cicéron | isbn= 2-262-01921-5 | location=Paris | publisher=Perrin | year= 2005 | language=French}}
* {{cite book | first=L. C. | last=Moyzisch | title= Der Fall Cicero | publisher= Palladium Verlag | location= Heidelberg |year = 1952 | language=German | lccn=52033431}}

==External links==
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IZi3UJ-sooQ Elyesa Bazna at the Eiffel Tower]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bazna, Elyesa}}
[[Category:1904 births]]
[[Category:1970 deaths]]
[[Category:World War II spies for Germany]]
[[Category:Ottoman Albanians]]
[[Category:People from Pristina]]
[[Category:Albanian people of World War II]]
[[Category:People from Kosovo Vilayet]]
[[Category:Albanian spies]]</text>
      <sha1>ovbqme7fa4e8viebahtytq3tl773bv2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
