<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Führerbunker</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>222902</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751280763</id>
      <parentid>751280696</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-24T15:41:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kierzek</username>
        <id>9088688</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Events in 1945 */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31406">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{good article}}
{{ITALICTITLE}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}
{{Infobox building
| name                = ''Führerbunker''
| native_name         = Führer's bunker
| native_name_lang    = Deutsch
| former_names        =
| alternate_names     =
| image               = Bundesarchiv Bild 183-V04744, Berlin, Garten der zerstörte Reichskanzlei.jpg
| image_alt           =
| caption             = July 1947 photo of the rear entrance to the Führerbunker in the garden of the [[Reich Chancellery]]. Hitler and [[Eva Braun]] were cremated in a shell hole in front of the emergency exit at left; the cone-shaped structure in the centre served as the exhaust, and as a bomb shelter for the guards.{{sfn|Arnold|2012}} 
| map_type            =
| map_alt             =
| map_caption         =
| altitude            =
| building_type       =
| architectural_style =
| structural_system   =
| cost                = 1.35 million [[Reichsmark]]s
| ren_cost            =
| client              =
| owner               = [[Nazi Germany]]
| current_tenants     =
| landlord            =
| location            =
| address             =
| location_town       = [[Berlin]]
| location_country    = Nazi Germany
| iso_region          =
| coordinates_display =
| latitude            =
| longitude           =
| latd                =
| latm                =
| lats                =
| latNS               =
| longd               =
| longm               =
| longs               =
| longEW              =
| coordinates         = {{Coord|52.5125|N|13.3815|E|region:DE-BE_type:landmark|display=inline,title}}
| start_date          = 1943
| completion_date     = 23 October 1944
| inauguration_date   =
| renovation_date     =
| destruction_date    = 5 December 1947
| height              =
| diameter            =
| other_dimensions    =
| floor_count         =
| floor_area          =
| seating_type        =
| seating_capacity    =
| main_contractor     =
| architect           = [[Albert Speer]], Karl Piepenburg
| architecture_firm   = [[Hochtief|Hochtief AG]]
| structural_engineer =
| services_engineer   =
| civil_engineer      =
| other_designers     =
| quantity_surveyor   =
| awards              =
| ren_architect       =
| ren_firm            =
| ren_str_engineer    =
| ren_serv_engineer   =
| ren_civ_engineer    =
| ren_oth_designers   =
| ren_qty_surveyor    =
| ren_awards          =
| url                 =
| references          =
}}
[[File:Karte-reichskanzlei.jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|3D model of New Reichs Chancellery with location of bunker complex in red]]
[[File:Karte-fuehrerbunker.jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|3D model of ''Führerbunker'' (left) and ''Vorbunker'' (right)]]

The '''''Führerbunker''''' was an air-raid shelter located near the [[Reich Chancellery]] in [[Berlin]], [[Germany]]. It was part of a subterranean bunker complex constructed in two phases which were completed in 1936 and 1944. It was the last of the [[Führer Headquarters]] (''Führerhauptquartiere'') used by [[Adolf Hitler]] during the Second World War.

Hitler took up residence in the ''Führerbunker'' on 16 January 1945 and it became the centre of the Nazi regime until the last week of [[World War II]] in Europe. Hitler married [[Eva Braun]] here during the last week of April 1945, shortly before [[Death of Adolf Hitler|they committed suicide]].

After the war both the old and new Chancellery buildings were levelled by the Soviets. Despite some attempts at demolition, the underground complex remained largely undisturbed until 1988–89. During reconstruction of that area of Berlin, the sections of the old bunker complex that were excavated were for the most part destroyed. The site remained unmarked until 2006, when a small plaque with a schematic diagram was installed. Some corridors of the bunker still exist, but are sealed off from the public.

== Construction ==
The [[Reich Chancellery]] bunker was initially constructed as a temporary [[air-raid shelter]] for Hitler (who actually spent very little time in the capital during most of the war). Increased bombing of Berlin led to expansion of the complex as an improvised permanent shelter. The elaborate complex consisted of two separate shelters, the ''[[Vorbunker]]'' ( &quot;forward bunker&quot;; the upper bunker), completed in 1936, and the ''Führerbunker'', located {{convert|2.5|m|ft}} lower than the ''Vorbunker'' and to the west-southwest, completed in 1944.{{sfn|Lehrer|2006|pp=117, 119, 123}}{{sfn|Kellerhoff|2004|p=56}} They were connected by a stairway set at right angles and could be closed off from each other by a bulkhead and steel door.{{sfn|Mollo|1988|p=28}} The ''Vorbunker'' was located {{convert|1.5|m|ft}} beneath the cellar of a large reception hall behind the old Reich Chancellery at Wilhelmstrasse&amp;nbsp;77.{{sfn|Lehrer|2006|p=117}} The ''Führerbunker'' was located about {{convert|8.5|m|ft}} beneath the garden of the old Reich Chancellery, {{convert|120|m|ft}} north of the new Reich Chancellery building at [[Voßstraße]]&amp;nbsp;6.{{sfn|Lehrer|2006|p=123}} Besides being deeper under ground, the ''Führerbunker'' had significantly more reinforcement. Its roof was made of concrete almost {{convert|3|m|ft}} thick.{{sfn|McNab|2014|pp=21, 28}} About 30&amp;nbsp;small rooms were protected by approximately {{convert|4|m|ft}} of concrete; exits led into the main buildings, as well as an emergency exit up to the garden. The ''Führerbunker'' development was built by the [[Hochtief]] company as part of an extensive program of subterranean construction in Berlin begun in 1940.{{sfn|Lehrer|2006|pp=117, 119, 121–123}}

Hitler's accommodations were in this newer, lower section, and by February 1945 it had been decorated with high-quality furniture taken from the Chancellery, along with several framed oil paintings.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=97}} After descending the stairs into the lower section and passing through the steel door, there was a long corridor with a series of rooms on each side.{{sfn|McNab|2014|p=28}} On the right side were a series of rooms which included generator/ventilation rooms and the telephone switchboard.{{sfn|McNab|2014|p=28}} On left side was Eva Braun's bedroom/sitting room (also known as Hitler's private guest room), an ante-chamber (also known as Hitler's sitting room), which led into Hitler's study/office.{{sfn|McNab|2011|p=109}}{{sfn|McNab|2014|p=29}} On the wall hung a large portrait of [[Frederick the Great]],  one of Hitler's heroes.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=97, 901–902}} A door led into Hitler's modestly furnished bedroom.{{sfn|McNab|2014|p=29}} Next to it was the conference/map room (also known as the briefing/situation room) which had a door that led out into the waiting room/ante-room.{{sfn|McNab|2011|p=109}}{{sfn|McNab|2014|p=29}}

The bunker complex was self-contained.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=901}} However, as the ''Führerbunker'' was below the [[water table]], conditions were unpleasantly damp, with pumps running continuously to remove [[groundwater]]. A diesel generator provided electricity, and [[well water]] was pumped in as the water supply.{{sfn|Lehrer|2006|pp=124–125}} Communications systems included a [[telex]], a telephone switchboard, and an army radio set with an outdoor antenna. As conditions deteriorated at the end of the war, Hitler received much of his war news from [[BBC]] radio broadcasts and via courier.{{sfn|Taylor|2007|p=184}}

== Events in 1945 ==
{{See also|Battle of Berlin|Death of Adolf Hitler}}

{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| image1    = Reichskanzlei-Fuehrerbunker.svg
| width1    = 300
| caption1  = Plan of the ''Führerbunker''
| image2    = Reichskanzlei-Vorbunker.png
| width2    = 300
| caption2  = Plan of the ''[[Vorbunker]]''
}}

Hitler moved into the ''Führerbunker'' on 16 January 1945. He was joined by his senior staff, including [[Martin Bormann]]. In April 1945, [[Eva Braun]] and [[Joseph Goebbels]] moved into the ''Führerbunker'' while [[Magda Goebbels]] and [[Goebbels children|their six children]] took residence in the upper ''Vorbunker''.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=278}} Two or three dozen support, medical, and administrative staff were also sheltered there. These included Hitler's secretaries (including [[Traudl Junge]]), a nurse named [[Erna Flegel]], and telephone switchboard operator Sergeant [[Rochus Misch]]. Early on, Hitler continued to utilize the undamaged wing of the Reich Chancellery, where he held afternoon military conferences in his large study.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=902}} Afterwards, he would have tea with his secretaries before going back down into the bunker complex for the night. After several weeks of this routine, Hitler seldom left the bunker except for short strolls in the chancellery garden with his dog [[Blondi]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=902}} The bunker was crowded and the atmosphere was oppressive; air raids occurred daily.{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=785}} Hitler mostly stayed on the lower level, where it was quieter and he could sleep.{{sfn|Speer|1971|p=597}} Conferences took place for much of the night,{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=785}} often until 05:00.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=903}}

On 16 April the [[Red Army]] started the [[Battle of Berlin]] and by 19 April they started to encircle the city.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=217–233}} On 20 April, his 56th birthday, Hitler made his last trip to the surface. In the ruined garden of the Reich Chancellery, he awarded the [[Iron Cross]] to boy soldiers of the [[Hitler Youth]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=251}} That afternoon, Berlin was bombarded by Soviet artillery for the first time.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=255}}

In denial about the dire situation, Hitler placed his hopes on the units commanded by Waffen-SS General [[Felix Steiner]], the ''Armeeabteilung Steiner'' (&quot;[[Army Detachment Steiner]]&quot;). On 21 April, Hitler ordered Steiner to attack the northern flank of the encircling Soviet [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] and ordered the German [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|Ninth Army]], south-east of Berlin, to attack northward in a [[pincer attack]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=267–268}}{{sfn|Ziemke|1969|pp=87–88}} By that evening, Red Army tanks reached the outskirts of Berlin.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=255, 256}} At his afternoon situation conference on 22 April, Hitler was told Steiner's forces had not moved. Hitler fell into a tearful rage when he realised that the attack was not going to be carried out. He openly declared for the first time the war was lost—and blamed his generals. He announced he would stay in Berlin until the end and then shoot himself.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=275}}

On 23 April,{{efn|name=appointment}} Hitler appointed [[General of the Artillery (Germany)|General of the Artillery]] [[Helmuth Weidling]], commander of the [[LVI Panzer Corps]], as the commander of the Berlin Defense Area, replacing Lieutenant-Colonel (''[[Oberstleutnant]]'') [[Ernst Kaether]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=934}} Despite the commands being issued from the ''Führerbunker'', by 25 April the Red Army had consolidated their [[investment (military)|investment]] of Berlin, and there was no prospect that the German defence could do anything but delay the city's capture.{{sfn|Ziemke|1969|p=111}} Hitler summoned Field Marshal [[Robert Ritter von Greim]] from Munich to Berlin to take over command of the Luftwaffe from [[Hermann Göring]]. Along with his mistress and crack test pilot, [[Hanna Reitsch]], he arrived on 26 April.{{sfn|Dollinger|1997|p=228}}

On 28 April Hitler learned that ''Reichsführer-SS'' [[Heinrich Himmler]], who had left Berlin on 20 April, was trying to discuss surrender terms with the Western Allies through Count [[Folke Bernadotte]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=923–925, 943}} Hitler considered this treason.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=943–946}} Enraged, he ordered Himmler's arrest and had [[Hermann Fegelein]] (Himmler's SS representative at Hitler's HQ in Berlin) shot.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=946}}{{sfn|Dollinger|1997|p=228}} On the same day, General [[Hans Krebs (Wehrmacht general)|Hans Krebs]] made his last telephone call from the ''Führerbunker'' to [[Field Marshal]] [[Wilhelm Keitel]] Chief of [[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|German Armed Forces High Command]] (OKW) in [[Fürstenberg/Havel|Fürstenberg]]. Krebs told him that if relief did not arrive within 48 hours, all would be lost. Keitel promised to exert the utmost pressure on Generals [[Walther Wenck]], commander of the Twelfth Army, and [[Theodor Busse]], commander of the Ninth Army. Meanwhile, Hitler's private secretary, [[Martin Bormann]], wired to German Admiral [[Karl Dönitz]]: &quot;Reich Chancellery a heap of rubble.&quot;{{sfn|Dollinger|1997|p=228}} He said that the foreign press was reporting fresh acts of treason and &quot;that without exception Schörner, Wenck and the others must give evidence of their loyalty by the quickest relief of the Führer&quot;.{{sfn|Ziemke|1969|p=119}}

That evening, von Greim and Reitsch flew out from Berlin in an [[Arado Ar 96]] trainer. Field Marshal von Greim was ordered to get the Luftwaffe to attack the Soviet forces that had just reached [[Potsdamerplatz]] (only a city block from the ''Führerbunker'').{{efn|name=orders}}{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=342}}{{sfn|Ziemke|1969|p=118}} During the night of 28 April, General Wenck reported to Keitel that his Twelfth Army had been forced back along the entire front and it was no longer possible for his army to relieve Berlin.{{sfn|Dollinger|1997|p=239}} Keitel gave Wenck permission to break off the attempt.{{sfn|Ziemke|1969|p=119}}

After midnight on the night of 28–29 April, Hitler married Eva Braun in a small civil ceremony within the ''Führerbunker''. Hitler then took secretary Traudl Junge to another room and dictated [[last will and testament of Adolf Hitler|his last will and testament]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=343}}{{efn|name=will and marriage}} At approximately 04:00, Hans Krebs, [[Wilhelm Burgdorf]], Goebbels, and Bormann witnessed and signed the documents.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=343}} Hitler then retired to bed.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=950}}

Late in the evening of 29 April, Krebs contacted Jodl by radio: &quot;Request immediate report. Firstly of the whereabouts of Wenck's spearheads. Secondly of time intended to attack. Thirdly of the location of the Ninth Army. Fourthly of the precise place in which the Ninth Army will break through. Fifthly of the whereabouts of General [[Rudolf Holste]]'s spearhead.&quot;{{sfn|Dollinger|1997|p=239}} In the early morning of 30 April, Jodl replied to Krebs: &quot;Firstly, Wenck's spearhead bogged down south of [[Schwielow Lake]]. Secondly, Twelfth Army therefore unable to continue attack on Berlin. Thirdly, bulk of Ninth Army surrounded. Fourthly, Holste's Corps on the defensive.&quot;{{sfn|Dollinger|1997|p=239}}{{sfn|Ziemke|1969|p=120}}{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=357|loc=last paragraph}}{{efn|name=reply}}

During the morning of 30 April, SS-''[[Brigadeführer]]'' [[Wilhelm Mohnke]], commander of the centre (government) district of Berlin, informed Hitler he would be able to hold for less than two days. Later that morning Weidling informed Hitler that the defenders would probably exhaust their ammunition that night and again asked him for permission to break out. At about 13:00 Weidling finally received permission.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=358}} In the ''Führerbunker'' that afternoon, [[Death of Adolf Hitler|Hitler shot himself]] and Braun took [[cyanide]].{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=160–182}} {{sfn|Linge|2009|p=199}} In accordance with Hitler's instructions, the bodies were burned in the garden behind the [[Reich Chancellery]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=956–957}} In accordance with Hitler's last will and testament, Goebbels became the new [[Head of Government]] and Chancellor of Germany (''[[Reichskanzler]]''). At 03:15, ''Reichskanzler'' Goebbels and Bormann sent a radio message to Dönitz informing him of Hitler's death. In accordance with Hitler's last wishes, Dönitz was appointed as the new President of Germany (''[[Reichspräsident]]'').{{sfn|Williams|2005|pp=324, 325}}

At about 04:00 on 1 May, Krebs talked to General [[Vasily Chuikov]], commander of the [[Soviet 8th Guards Army]].{{efn|name=meeting}} Chuikov demanded unconditional surrender of the remaining German forces. Krebs did not have the authority to surrender, so he returned to the bunker.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=1135–1137}} In the late afternoon, Goebbels [[Magda Goebbels#Suicide|had his children poisoned]]. At around 20:30, Goebbels and his wife left the bunker.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|p=52}} There are several different accounts on what followed. According to one account, Goebbels shot his wife and then himself. Another account was that they each bit on a cyanide ampule and were given a ''[[coup de grâce]]'' immediately afterwards.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=381}} Goebbels' SS adjutant [[Günther Schwägermann]] testified in 1948 that the couple walked ahead of him up the stairs and out into the Chancellery garden. He waited in the stairwell and heard the &quot;shots&quot; sound.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|p=52}} Schwägermann then walked up the remaining stairs and once outside he saw the lifeless bodies of the couple. Following Joseph Goebbels' prior order, Schwägermann had an SS soldier fire several shots into Goebbels' body, which did not move.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|p=52}} The bodies were then doused with petrol, but the remains were only partially burned and not buried.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=381}} 
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-M1204-319, Berlin, Reichskanzlei, gesprengter Führerbunker.jpg|thumb|Ruins of the bunker after demolition in 1947]]

Weidling had given the order for the survivors to break out to the north-west; the plan got underway at around 23:00. The first group from the Reich Chancellery, led by Mohnke, tried but could not break through the Soviet rings and was captured the next day. Like others from the ''Führerbunker'' who were captured, he was interrogated by [[SMERSH]]. On the third break-out attempt from the Reich Chancellery, made around 01:00 (2 May), Bormann managed to cross the [[Spree]]. [[Arthur Axmann]], who followed the same route, reported seeing Bormann's body a short distance from the [[Weidendammer bridge]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=383, 389}}{{efn|name=no orders}}

At 01:00 the Soviet forces picked up a radio message from the LVI Panzer Corps requesting a cease-fire. Down in the ''Führerbunker'', General Krebs and General Burgdorf committed suicide by gunshot to the head.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=387}} The last defenders in the area of the bunker complex, French SS volunteers of the [[33rd Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Charlemagne (1st French)]] remained until the early morning.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=407}} The Soviet forces then captured the [[Reich Chancellery]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=387, 388}} General Weidling surrendered with his staff at 6:00 and his meeting with Chuikov ended at 8:23.{{sfn|Dollinger|1997|p=239}} [[Johannes Hentschel]], the master electro-[[mechanic]] for the bunker complex, stayed after everyone else had either committed suicide or left, as the [[field hospital]] in the Reich Chancellery above needed power and water. He surrendered to the Red Army as they entered the bunker complex at 09:00 on 2 May.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|p=287}} The bodies of Goebbels' six children were discovered on 3 May. They were found in their beds in the ''Vorbunker'', with the clear mark of cyanide shown on their faces.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=398}}

== Post-war events ==
[[File:Site of Fuhrerbunker in 2005.jpg|thumb|Site of ''Führerbunker'' in 2005]]
[[File:Place Of the Führerbunker P7120036.JPG|thumb|Site of ''Führerbunker'' in 2007]]

The ruins of both Chancellery buildings were levelled by the Soviets between 1945 and 1949 as part of an effort to destroy the landmarks of Nazi Germany. The bunker largely survived, although some areas were partially flooded. In December 1947, the Soviets tried to blow up the bunker, but only the separation walls were damaged. In 1959, the [[East Germany|East German]] government began a series of demolitions of the Chancellery, including the bunker.{{sfn|Mollo|1988|pp=48, 49}} Because it was near the [[Berlin Wall]], the site was undeveloped and neglected until 1988–89.{{sfn|Mollo|1988|pp=49, 50}} During extensive construction of residential housing and other buildings on the site, work crews uncovered several underground sections of the old bunker complex; for the most part these were destroyed. Other parts of the Chancellery underground complex were uncovered, but these were ignored, filled in, or resealed.{{sfn|Mollo|1988|pp=46, 48, 50–53}}

[[File:Place Of Hitler Bunker 2007.jpg|thumb|Information board at the bunker site in 2007]]

Government authorities wanted to destroy the last vestiges of these Nazi landmarks.{{sfn|McNab|2014|p=21}} The construction of the buildings in the area around the ''Führerbunker'' was a strategy for ensuring the surroundings remained anonymous and unremarkable.{{sfn|Kellerhoff|2004|pp=27, 28}} The emergency exit point for the ''Führerbunker'' (which had been in the Chancellery gardens) was occupied by a [[parking lot|car park]].{{sfn|Kellerhoff|2004|p=27}}

On 8 June 2006, during the lead-up to the [[2006 FIFA World Cup]], an information board was installed to mark the location of the ''Führerbunker''. The board, including a schematic diagram of the bunker, can be found at the corner of In den Ministergärten and Gertrud-Kolmar-Straße, two small streets about three minutes' walk from [[Potsdamer Platz]]. Hitler's bodyguard, [[Rochus Misch]], one of the last people living who was in the bunker at the time of Hitler's suicide, was on hand for the ceremony.{{sfn|''Der Spiegel''|2006}}

== See also ==
* [[Wolf's Lair]]
* [[Nazi architecture]]
* [[Matsushiro Underground Imperial Headquarters]]

== Notes ==
{{notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = appointment
| {{harvnb|Beevor|2002|p=286}} states the appointment was 23 April; {{harvnb|Hamilton|2008|p=160}} states &quot;officially&quot; it was the morning of 24 April; {{harvnb|Dollinger|1997|p=228}}, gives 26 April for the appointment.
}}

{{efn
| name = orders
| The Luftwaffe order differs in different sources. {{harvnb|Beevor|2002|p=342}} states it was to attack [[Potsdamerplatz]], but Ziemke states it was to support Wenck's Twelfth Army attack. Both agree that von Greim was also ordered to make sure Himmler was punished.
}}

{{efn
| name = will and marriage
| &quot;{{harvnb|MI5 staff|2005}}: Hitler's will and marriage&quot; on the website of [[MI5]], using the sources available to [[Hugh Trevor-Roper]] (a World War II MI5 agent and historian/author of ''The Last Days of Hitler''), records the marriage as taking place after Hitler had dictated his last will and testament.
}}

{{efn
| name = reply
| {{harvnb|Dollinger|1997|p=239}}, says Jodl replied, but {{harvnb|Ziemke|1969|p=120}}, and {{harvnb|Beevor|2002|p=537}}, say it was Keitel.
}}

{{efn
| name = meeting
| {{harvnb|Dollinger|1997|p=239}}, states 03:00, and {{harvnb|Beevor|2002|p=367}}, 04:00, for Krebs' meeting with Chuikov.
}}

{{efn
| name = no orders
| {{harvnb|Ziemke|1969|p=126}} says that Weidling gave no orders for a break-out.
}}
}}
{{Clear}}

== Citations ==
{{reflist|20em}}

== Bibliography ==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite web | last=Arnold | first=Dietmar | date=9 January 2012&lt;!--See html source--&gt; | origyear=8 June 2010 | title=Berliner Unterwelten e.V.: The Legend of Hitler’s Bunker | publisher=Berliner-unterwelten.de | url=http://berliner-unterwelten.de/fuehrer-bunker.328.1.html | accessdate=11 June 2011 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Beevor | first=Antony | authorlink=Antony Beevor | year=2002 | title=Berlin: The Downfall 1945 | publisher=Viking–Penguin Books | location=London | isbn=978-0-670-03041-5 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Bullock | first=Alan | authorlink=Alan Bullock | year=1999 | title=Hitler: A Study in Tyranny | origyear=1952 | publisher=Konecky &amp; Konecky | location=New York | isbn=978-1-56852-036-0 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Dollinger | first=Hans | year=1997 | title=Decline and the Fall of Nazi Germany and Imperial Japan | publisher=Chancellor | location=London | isbn=978-0-7537-0009-9 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Hamilton | first=Stephan | year=2008 | title=Bloody Streets: The Soviet Assault on Berlin, April 1945 | publisher=Helion &amp; Co | location=Solihull | isbn=978-1-906033-12-5 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Joachimsthaler | first=Anton | year=1999 | origyear=1995 | title=The Last Days of Hitler: The Legends&amp;nbsp;– The Evidence&amp;nbsp;– The Truth | publisher=Brockhampton Press | location=London | isbn=978-1-86019-902-8 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Kellerhoff | first= Sven | year = 2004 | title = The Führer Bunker | publisher = Berlin Story Verlag | location  = Berlin | isbn = 978-3-929829-23-5 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last=Kershaw | first=Ian | authorlink=Ian Kershaw | year=2008 | title=Hitler: A Biography | publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Co | location=New York | isbn=978-0-393-06757-6 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Lehrer | first=Steven | authorlink=Steven Lehrer | year=2006 | title=[[The Reich Chancellery and Führerbunker Complex]]. An Illustrated History of the Seat of the Nazi Regime | publisher=McFarland | location=Jefferson, NC | isbn=978-0-7864-2393-4 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Linge | first=Heinz | authorlink=Heinz Linge | year=2009 | title=With Hitler to the End | publisher=Frontline Books–Skyhorse Publishing | location=London; New York | isbn=978-1-60239-804-7 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = McNab | first = Chris | title = Hitler's Masterplan: The Essential Facts and Figures for Hitler's Third Reich | publisher = Amber Books Ltd | year = 2011 | isbn = 978-1907446962 | ref=harv }}
* {{cite book | last = McNab | first = Chris | title = Hitler's Fortresses: German Fortifications and Defences 1939–45 | publisher = Osprey Publishing | location = Oxford; New York | year = 2014 | isbn = 978-1-78200-828-6 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal | last=Mollo | first=Andrew | year=1988 | editor-last=Ramsey | editor-first=Winston | title=The Berlin Führerbunker: The Thirteenth Hole | journal=After the Battle | issue=61 | publisher=Battle of Britain International | location=London | ref=harv}}
* {{cite web | author=MI5 staff | year=2005 | title=Hitler's last days | work=mi5.gov.uk | publisher=[[MI5]] | url=https://www.mi5.gov.uk/home/about-us/who-we-are/mi5-history/world-war-ii/hitlers-last-days.html | accessdate=12 June 2011 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Shirer | first=William L. | authorlink=William L. Shirer | year=1960 | title=[[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]] | publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster | location=New York | isbn=978-0-671-62420-0 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Speer | first=Albert | authorlink=Albert Speer | origyear=1969 | year=1971 | title=[[Inside the Third Reich]] | publisher=Avon | location=New York | isbn=978-0-380-00071-5 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite web | author = Staff | title = Debunking Hitler: Marking the Site of the Führer's Bunker | work = [[Spiegel Online]] | publisher = Spiegel-Verlag | date = 9 June 2006 | url = http://www.spiegel.de/international/debunking-hitler-marking-the-site-of-the-fuehrer-s-bunker-a-420483.html | accessdate = 7 April 2014 | ref = {{sfnRef|''Der Spiegel''|2006}} }}
* {{cite book | last = Taylor | first = Blaine | title = Hitler's Headquarters: From Beer Hall to Bunker, 1920–1945 | year = 2007 | publisher = Potomac | location = Dulles, Virginia | isbn = 978-1-57488-928-4 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Weale | first = Adrian | title = Army of Evil: A History of the SS | year = 2012 | place = New York | publisher = Caliber Printing | isbn = 978-0-451-23791-0 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Williams | first = Andrew | year = 2005 | title = D-Day to Berlin | publisher = [[Hodder &amp; Stoughton|Hodder]] |isbn=978-0-340-83397-1 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Ziemke | first=Earl F. | year=1969 | title=Battle For Berlin: End Of The Third Reich | publisher=MacDonald | location=London | oclc=253711605 | ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book | last=Boldt | first=Gerhard | year=1973 | title=Hitler: The Last Ten Days | publisher=Coward, McCann &amp; Geoghegan | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-698-10531-7 }}
* {{cite book | author = C.I.U. General Staff, Geographical Section | editor1-last = Ramsey | editor1-first = Winston G. | title = Berlin: Allied Intelligence Map of Key Buildings | publisher = After the Battle – Battle of Britain International | date = 1990 | isbn = 978-1-870067-33-1}}
* {{cite book | last=Fest | first=Joachim | authorlink=Joachim Fest | year=2005 | title=Inside Hitler's Bunker: The Last Days of the Third Reich | publisher=Picador | location = New York | isbn=978-0-374-13577-5 }}
* {{cite book | last=Junge | first=Traudl | authorlink=Traudl Junge | editor1-last=Müller | editor1-first=Melissa | title=Until the Final Hour: Hitler's Last Secretary | publisher=Arcade Publishing | location = New York | year= 2004 | isbn= 978-1-55970-728-2}}
* {{cite book | last=Neubauer | first=Christoph | year=2010 | title=Stadtführer durch Hitlers Berlin | language=German, English | publisher=Flashback Medienverlag | location = [[Frankfurt (Oder)|Frankfurt]] on the Oder| url=http://www.flashback-medien.de/3d-projekte-stadtfuehrer-durch-hitlers-berlin-e.html | isbn=978-3-9813977-0-3 }}
* {{cite book | last = O'Donnell | first = James P. | authorlink = James P. O'Donnell | title = [[The Bunker (book)|The Bunker]] | publisher = Da Capo Press | location = New York | year = 2001 | origyear = 1978 | isbn = 978-0-306-80958-3 }}
* {{cite book | last=Petrova | first=Ada | last2=Watson | first2=Peter | title=The Death of Hitler: The Full Story with New Evidence from Secret Russian Archives | year = 1995 | publisher = Norton | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-393-03914-6}}
* {{cite book | last=Ryan | first=Cornelius | authorlink=Cornelius Ryan | year=1966 | title=The Last Battle | publisher=Simon and Schuster | location=New York }}
* {{cite book | last=Tissier | first=Tony Le | year=1999 | title=Race for the Reichstag: The 1945 Battle for Berlin | publisher=Routledge | location=London; Portland, OR | isbn=978-0-7146-4929-0 }}
* {{cite book | last=Trevor-Roper | first=Hugh | authorlink=Hugh Trevor-Roper | title=The Last Days of Hitler | publisher=University of Chicago Press | edition=paperback | year=1992 | origyear=1947 | isbn=978-0-226-81224-3}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Führerbunker}}
* {{cite news | title=Hitler Slept Here: The too-secret history of the Third Reich's most famous place |last=Shuger | first=Scott | last2=Berger | first2=Donald | work=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate Magazine]] | date=21 June 2006 | url=http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/slates_10th_anniversary/2006/06/hitler_slept_here.html }}
* [http://www.bunkermuzeum.hu/index_en.html Bunkermuzeum&amp;nbsp;– English version]: Guide to military museums of Europe
* [http://www.reichskanzlei-3d.de/g-rk-ws77-innen-VB-Haupteingang-e.html 3D-stereoscopic images of Chancellery]

{{Final occupants of the Führerbunker}}
{{Adolf Hitler}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fuehrerbunker}}
[[Category:Führer Headquarters]]
[[Category:1940s in Berlin]]
[[Category:Battle of Berlin]]
[[Category:World War II sites in Germany]]
[[Category:Continuity of government]]
[[Category:Bunkers in Germany]]
[[Category:Air-raid shelters]]</text>
      <sha1>kxpbblg3ekloo4xxytt7xr1g7wi5pzw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
