<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Gallipoli Campaign</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>214109</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751093120</id>
      <parentid>751051147</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T09:28:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith-264</username>
        <id>925588</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 751051147 by [[Special:Contributions/Audaciter|Audaciter]] ([[User talk:Audaciter|talk]]) Comma next to a conjunction? Surely not</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="133697">{{other uses}}
{{Redirect|Dardanelles Campaign|other uses|Battle of the Dardanelles (disambiguation){{!}}Battle of the Dardanelles}}
{{use British English|date=July 2013}}
{{use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Gallipoli Campaign
| partof = the [[Middle Eastern theatre of World War I|Middle Eastern theatre]] of [[World War I]]
| image = [[File:G.C. 18 March 1915 Gallipoli Campaign Article.jpg|300px]]
| caption = A collection of photographs from the campaign. From top and left to right: Ottoman commanders including Mustafa Kemal (fourth from left); Allied warships; the view down to [[Anzac Cove]]; Ottoman soldiers in a trench; and Allied positions.
| date = 25 April 1915&amp;nbsp;– 9 January 1916&lt;br /&gt;({{age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=04|day1=25|year1=1915|month2=01|day2=09|year2=1916}})
| place = [[Gallipoli|Gallipoli Peninsula]], [[Sanjak of Gelibolu]], [[Adrianople Vilayet]], [[Ottoman Empire]]
| result =Ottoman victory&lt;br&gt;See [[#Aftermath|Aftermath]] section
| combatant1 = {{flag|British Empire}}
* {{flag|Australia}}
* {{flagcountry|British India}}
* {{flag|Newfoundland}}
* {{flag|New Zealand}}
* {{flagcountry|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}}
{{flagcountry|French Third Republic}}
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Ottoman Empire}}
&lt;small&gt;'''Supported by'''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
{{flag|German Empire}}{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=13}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Austria-Hungary}}{{sfn|Jung|2003|pp=42–43}}
| commander1 =
 {{unbulleted list
  | {{flagicon|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}} [[Ian Standish Monteith Hamilton|Ian Hamilton]]
  | {{flagicon|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}} [[Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|Herbert Kitchener]]
  | {{flagicon|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}} [[John de Robeck]]
  | {{flagicon|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}} [[William Birdwood, 1st Baron Birdwood|William Birdwood]]
  | {{flagicon|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}} [[Winston Churchill]]
  | {{flagicon image|Flag of France.svg}} [[Henri Gouraud (French Army officer)|Henri Gouraud]]
  | {{flagicon image|Flag of France.svg}} [[Maurice Bailloud]]
 }}
| commander2 =
 {{unbulleted list
  | {{flagicon|German Empire}} [[Otto Liman von Sanders|Otto von Sanders]]
  | {{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Enver Pasha]]
  | {{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Mehmet Esat Bülkat]]
  | {{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Cevat Çobanlı]]
  | {{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Mustafa Kemal Atatürk|Mustafa Kemal]]
  | {{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Wehib Pasha|Mehmet Vehip]]
  }}
| units1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Mediterranean Expeditionary Force]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Egyptian Labour Corps]]{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|p=395}}&lt;br /&gt;Maltese Labour Corps{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|p=395}} &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of France.svg}} [[Corps expéditionnaire d'Orient|Oriental Expeditionary Corps]]
| units2 = {{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Fifth Army (Ottoman Empire)|Fifth Army]]
| strength1 = 5 [[Division (military)|divisions]] {{smaller|(initial)}}&lt;br /&gt;15 divisions {{smaller|(final)}}&lt;br /&gt;
'''Total''': 568,000
* 455,000 British (including Indians and Newfoundlanders)
* 79,000 French{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|pp=94–95}}
* ~50,000 Australians
* ~14–17,000 New Zealanders
&lt;small&gt;'''Supported by'''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
~2,000 civilian labourers{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|p=395}}
| strength2 = 6 divisions {{smaller|(initial)}}&lt;br /&gt;16 divisions {{smaller|(final)}}&lt;br /&gt;
'''Total''': 315,500{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|pp=94–95}}
| casualties1 = 252,000{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=94}}
| casualties2 = {{nowrap|218,000 – 251,000{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=94}}}}
| campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Gallipoli}}{{WWITheatre}}
}}

The '''Gallipoli Campaign''', also known as the '''Dardanelles Campaign''', the '''Battle of Gallipoli''' or the '''Battle of Çanakkale''' ({{lang-tr|Çanakkale Savaşı}}), was a campaign of [[World War I]] that took place on the [[Gallipoli]] peninsula ([[Gelibolu]] in modern Turkey) in the [[Ottoman Empire]] between 25 April 1915 and 9 January 1916. The peninsula forms the northern bank of the [[Dardanelles]], a [[strait]] that provided a sea route to the [[Russian Empire]], one of the [[Allies of World War I|Allied powers]] during the war. Intending to secure it, Russia's allies Britain and France launched a naval attack followed by an [[Amphibious warfare#World War I era|amphibious landing]] on the peninsula, with the aim of capturing the Ottoman capital of [[Constantinople]] (modern [[Istanbul]]).{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|pp=51–52}} The naval attack was repelled and after eight months' fighting, with many casualties on both sides, the land campaign was abandoned and the invasion force was withdrawn to [[Egypt]].

The campaign was one of the greatest [[List of Ottoman conquests, sieges and landings|Ottoman victories]] during the war. In Turkey, it is regarded as a defining moment in the nation's history: a final surge in the defence of the motherland as the Ottoman Empire crumbled. The struggle formed the basis for the [[Turkish War of Independence]] and the declaration of the Republic of Turkey eight years later under [[Mustafa Kemal Atatürk|Mustafa Kemal]] (Kemal Atatürk) who first rose to prominence as a commander at Gallipoli. The campaign is often considered as marking the birth of national consciousness in Australia and New Zealand and the date of the landing, 25 April, is known as &quot;[[Anzac Day]]&quot; which is the most significant commemoration of military casualties and [[veteran]]s in those two countries, surpassing [[Remembrance Day]] ([[Armistice Day]]).{{sfn|Dennis et al|2008|pp=32, 38}}{{sfn|Lewis|Balderstone|Bowan|2006|p=110}}{{sfn|McGibbon|2000|p=198}}

==Background==
{{main|Middle Eastern theatre of World War I}}

===Ottoman entry into the war===
{{Main|Ottoman entry into World War I}}
At the beginning of the 20th century, the [[Ottoman Empire]] had the reputation of being the &quot;[[sick man of Europe]]&quot;, weakened by political instability, military defeat and civil strife following a century of slow decline.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=36}} In 1908, a group of young officers, known as the [[Young Turks]], seized power in [[Constantinople]], while [[Mehmed V]] was later installed as a figurehead Sultan in 1909.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=6}}{{sfn|Howard|2002|p=51}} The new régime implemented a program of reform to modernise the outdated political and economic system and to redefine the racial make-up of the empire. An enthusiastic supporter, Germany provided significant investment. German diplomats subsequently found increasing influence, despite Britain previously being the predominant power in the region, while German officers assisted in training and re-equipping the army.{{sfn|Howard|2002|pp=51–52}}

Despite this support, the economic resources of the Ottoman Empire were depleted by the cost of the [[First Balkan War|Balkan Wars of 1912 and 1913]] and the French, British and Germans had offered financial aid. A pro-German faction influenced by [[Enver Pasha]], the former Ottoman military attaché in Berlin, opposed the pro-British majority in the Ottoman cabinet and tried to secure closer relations with Germany.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=6}}{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|pp=1–11}}{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|pp=37–41}} In December 1913, the Germans sent a military mission to Constantinople, headed by General [[Otto Liman von Sanders]]. The geographical position of the Ottoman Empire meant that Russia and her allies France and Britain had a significant interest in Turkish neutrality in the event of war in Europe.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=6}}

During the [[July Crisis|Sarajevo Crisis]] in 1914, German diplomats offered Turkey an anti-Russian alliance and territorial gains in Caucasia, north-west Iran and [[Trans-Caspia]]. The pro-British faction in the Cabinet was isolated due to the British ambassador taking leave until 18 August. As the crisis deepened in Europe, Ottoman policy was to obtain a guarantee of territorial integrity and potential advantages, unaware that the British might enter a European war.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|pp=6–7}} On 30 July 1914, two days after the outbreak of the war in Europe, the Ottoman leaders agreed to form a secret [[Ottoman-German Alliance]] against [[Russian Empire|Russia]], although it did not require them to undertake military action.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=41}}{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=17–18}}{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=6}}

On 2 August, the British requisitioned two modern battleships—{{ship|Ottoman battleship|Sultân Osmân-ı Evvel||2}} and {{ship|Ottoman battleship|Reşadiye||2}} which British shipyards had started building for the Ottoman Navy—for their own use, alienating pro-British elements in Constantinople, despite the offer of compensation if they remained neutral.{{sfn|Howard|2002|p=52}} This action strained diplomatic relations between the two empires and the German government offered {{SMS|Goeben}} and {{SMS|Breslau}} to the Ottoman navy as replacements, in an attempt to gain influence. The Allies tried to [[Pursuit of Goeben and Breslau|intercept]] the ships, which escaped when the Ottoman government opened the [[Dardanelles]] to allow them passage to Constantinople, despite being required under international law, as a neutral party, to block military shipping.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=18}} By allowing the German ships to enter the Dardanelles, the Ottomans confirmed their links to Germany.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=6}}

In September, the British naval mission to the Ottomans, which had been established in 1912 under Admiral [[Arthur Limpus]], was recalled due to increasing concern that Turkey would soon enter the war. Rear Admiral [[Wilhelm Souchon]] of the Imperial German Navy took over command of the Ottoman navy.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=9 &amp; 18}}{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=7}} Acting without orders from the Ottoman government, on 27 September the German commander of the Dardanelles fortifications ordered the passage closed, adding to the impression that the Ottomans were &quot;in the German camp&quot;.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=7}} The German naval presence and the success of German armies on all fronts, gave the pro-German faction in the Ottoman government enough influence to declare war on Russia.{{sfn|Howard|2002|p=53}}

On 27 October, ''Goeben'' and ''Breslau'', having been renamed {{ship|Ottoman battlecruiser|Yavûz Sultân Selîm||2}} and {{ship|Ottoman cruiser|Midilli||2}}, sortied into the Black Sea, bombarded the Russian port of [[Odessa]] and sank several Russian ships.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=44}} The Ottomans refused an Allied demand that they expel the German missions and on 31 October 1914, officially entered the war on the side of the [[Central Powers]].{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=19}}{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=44}} Russia declared war on Turkey on 2 November. The next day, the British ambassador left Constantinople and a British naval squadron off the Dardanelles bombarded the outer defensive forts at Kum Kale and Seddulbahir. A shell hit a magazine, knocked the guns off their mounts and killed {{nowrap|86 soldiers.}}{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=47}}

Britain and France declared war on Turkey on 5 November and the Ottomans declared a ''jihad'' (holy war) later that month, launching an [[Caucasus Campaign|offensive in the Caucasus]] against the Russians to regain former Turkish provinces there.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=48}} Fighting also began in [[Mesopotamian campaign|Mesopotamia]], following a British landing to occupy the oil facilities in the [[Persian Gulf]].{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=577}} The Ottomans prepared to attack Egypt in early 1915, aiming to occupy the [[Suez Canal]] and cut the Mediterranean route to [[British India|India]] and the Far East.{{sfn|Keegan|1998|p=238}} Strachan wrote that in hindsight Ottoman belligerence was inevitable, once {{lang|de|''Goeben''}} and {{lang|de|''Breslau''}} were allowed into the Dardanelles and that delays after that were caused by Ottoman unreadiness for war and Bulgarian neutrality, rather than uncertainty about policy.{{sfn|Strachan|2001|pp=678–679}}

===Allied strategy and the Dardanelles===
[[File:Turkish Strait disambig.svg|thumb|left|Sea access to Russia through the Dardanelles (in yellow)]]
The British had planned to invade amphibiously near [[Alexandretta]] before the Dardanelles operation with the idea originally presented by [[Boghos Nubar]] in 1914.{{sfn|Erickson|2013|p=159}} It was planned by Field Marshal Lord [[Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|Horatio Kitchener]] to sever the capital from Syria, Palestine and Egypt. Alexandretta was an area with a Christian population and was the strategic center of the Empire's railway network&amp;nbsp;– its capture would have cut the empire in two. Vice Admiral Sir [[Richard Peirse (Royal Navy officer)|Richard Peirse]], [[East Indies Station]], ordered Captain Frank Larkin of {{HMS|Doris|1896|6}} to Alexandretta on 13 December 1914. At the same time, in the same area, the {{ship|Russian cruiser|Askold|1900|6}} and the French cruiser ''Requin'' were performing similar operations. Kitchener was working on the plan as late as March 1915. This plan was also the beginning of Britain's successful effort to start an [[Arab Revolt]]. The Alexandretta landing was abandoned because militarily it would have required more resources than France could allocate and politically France did not want the British operating in their sphere of influence, a position to which Britain had agreed in 1912.{{sfn|Tauber|1993|pp=22–25}}

By late 1914 the war on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] had become a stalemate; the Franco-British counter-offensive of the [[First Battle of the Marne]] had ended and the British had suffered many casualties in the [[First Battle of Ypres]] in Flanders. Lines of trenches had been dug by both sides, running from the Swiss border to the [[English Channel]] as the [[Maneuver warfare|war of manoeuvre]] ended and [[trench warfare]] began.{{sfn|Dennis et al|2008|p=224}} The [[German Empire]] and [[Austria-Hungary]] closed the overland trade routes between Britain and France in the west and Russia in the east. The [[White Sea]] in the arctic north and the [[Sea of Okhotsk]] in the Far East were icebound in winter and distant from the [[Eastern Front (World War I)|Eastern Front]], the [[Baltic Sea]] was blockaded by the ''[[Kaiserliche Marine]]'' (Imperial German Navy) and the entrance to the [[Black Sea]] through the Dardanelles was controlled by the Ottoman Empire.{{sfn|Corbett|2009|pp=158, 166}} While the empire remained neutral supplies could still be sent to Russia through the Dardanelles but prior to the Ottoman entry into the war the straits had been closed and in November they began to [[Naval mine|mine]] the waterway.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=6}}{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=34}}

French Minister of Justice [[Aristide Briand]]'s proposal in November to attack the Ottoman Empire was rejected and an attempt by the British to pay the Ottomans to join the Allied side also failed.{{sfn|Strachan|2001|p=115}} Later that month, [[Winston Churchill]], [[First Lord of the Admiralty]], proposed a naval attack on the Dardanelles, based in part on erroneous reports of Ottoman troop strength. Churchill wanted to use a large number of obsolete battleships, which could not operate against the German [[High Seas Fleet]], in a Dardanelles operation, with a small occupation force provided by the army. It was hoped that an attack on the Ottomans would also draw [[History of Independent Bulgaria#World War I|Bulgaria]] and [[Kingdom of Greece|Greece]] (both formerly ruled by the Ottomans) into the war on the Allied side.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=27–28}} On 2 January 1915, [[Grand Duke Nicholas Nikolaevich of Russia (1856–1929)|Grand Duke Nicholas]] of Russia appealed to Britain for assistance against the Ottomans, who were conducting an offensive in the Caucasus. Planning began for a naval [[Demonstration (military)|demonstration]] in the Dardanelles to divert troops from the Caucasian theatre of operations.{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=20}}

==Naval campaign==
{{main|Naval operations in the Dardanelles Campaign}}

===Attempt to force the Straits===
[[File:Graphic map of the Dardanelles.JPG|thumb|Graphic map of the Dardanelles]]
On 17 February 1915, a British seaplane from {{HMS|Ark Royal|1914|6}} flew a reconnaissance sortie over the Straits.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=40}} Two days later, the first attack on the Dardanelles began when a strong Anglo-French task force, including the British [[battleship]] {{HMS|Queen Elizabeth|1913|6}}, began a long-range bombardment of Ottoman [[artillery]] along the coast. The British had intended to utilise ''Ark Royal''{{'}}s eight aircraft to spot for the bombardment but harsh conditions rendered all but one of these, a [[Short Admiralty Type 136|Short Type 136]], unserviceable.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|pp=42–43}} A period of bad weather slowed the initial phase but by 25 February the outer forts had been reduced and the entrance cleared of mines.{{sfn|Hart|2013a|pp=9–10}} After this, Royal Marines were landed to destroy guns at Kum Kale on the northern Asian coast and at Sedd el Bahr on the southern tip of the Gallipoli Peninsula, while the naval bombardment shifted to batteries between Kum Kale and Kephez.{{sfn|Hart|2013a|p=10}}

Frustrated by the mobility of the Ottoman batteries, which evaded the Allied bombardments and threatened the [[minesweeper]]s sent to clear the Straits, Churchill began pressuring the naval commander, Admiral [[Sackville Carden]], to increase the fleet's efforts.{{sfn|Hart|2013a|pp=11–12}} Carden drew up fresh plans and on 4 March sent a cable to Churchill, stating that the fleet could expect to arrive in Constantinople within 14 days.{{sfn|Fromkin|1989|p=135}} A sense of impending victory was heightened by the interception of a German wireless message that revealed the Ottoman Dardanelles forts were running out of ammunition.{{sfn|Fromkin|1989|p=135}} When the message was relayed to Carden, it was agreed a main attack would be launched on or around 17 March. It transpired that Carden, suffering from stress, was placed on the sick list by the medical officer and the fleet was placed under the command of Admiral [[John de Robeck]].{{sfn|Baldwin|1962|p=60}}

On 18 March 1915, the main attack was launched. The fleet, comprising {{nowrap|18 battleships}} with a supporting array of cruisers and destroyers, sought to target the narrowest point of the Dardanelles, where the straits are {{convert|1|mi|km}} wide. Despite some damage sustained by ships engaging the Ottoman forts, minesweepers were ordered to proceed along the straits. According to an account by the Ottoman General Staff, by 2:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. &quot;all telephone wires were cut, all communications with the forts were interrupted, some of the guns had been knocked out&amp;nbsp;... in consequence the artillery fire of the defence had slackened considerably&quot;.{{sfn|James|1995|p=61}} The {{ship|French battleship|Bouvet||2|up=yes}} was sunk by a mine, causing it to capsize with her crew of over {{nowrap|600 still aboard}}.{{sfn|Hart|2013a|p=12}} Minesweepers manned by civilians, under the constant fire of Ottoman shells, retreated, leaving the minefields largely intact. {{HMS|Irresistible|1898|6}} and {{HMS|Inflexible|1907|6}} were critically damaged by mines, although there was confusion during the battle about the cause of the damage—some blamed torpedoes. {{HMS|Ocean|1898|6}}, sent to rescue the ''Irresistible'', was also damaged by an explosion and both ships eventually sank.{{sfn|Fromkin|1989|p=151}} The French battleships {{ship|French battleship|Suffren||2}} and {{ship|French battleship|Gaulois||2}} were also damaged; the ships had sailed through a new line of mines placed secretly by the Ottoman minelayer ''[[Ottoman minelayer Nusret|Nusret]]'' ten days before.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=33–34}}

[[File:Dardanelles fleet-2.jpg|thumb|300px|left|Panoramic view of the Dardanelles fleet]]

The losses forced de Robeck to sound the &quot;general recall&quot; to save what remained of his force.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=35}} During the planning of the campaign, naval losses had been anticipated and so it was mainly obsolete battleships, which were unfit to face the German fleet, that had been sent. Some of the senior naval officers, such as the commander of ''Queen Elizabeth'', Commodore [[Roger Keyes]], felt that they had come close to victory, believing that the Ottoman guns had almost run out of ammunition, but de Robeck, [[John Fisher, 1st Baron Fisher|Jackie Fisher]] and others prevailed and ended Allied attempts to force the straits by naval power, citing unacceptable losses and bad weather.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=35}}{{sfn|Baldwin|1962|p=60}}{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=15}} The defeat of the British fleet had given the Ottomans a morale boost;{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=36}} the day would later come to be celebrated in Turkey as a great victory.{{sfn|Hart|2013a|p=3}} Planning to capture the Turkish defences by land began.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=44}} Two Allied submarines tried to traverse the Dardanelles but were lost to mines and strong currents.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|pp=44–45}}

===Allied preparations for a landing===
{{main|Order of battle for the Gallipoli Campaign}}
[[File:Landing French-Gallipoli.jpg|thumb|right|French troops landing on [[Lemnos]], 1915.]]
After the failure of the naval attacks, ground forces were assembled, tasked with eliminating the Ottoman mobile artillery so that minesweepers could clear the way for the larger vessels. The British [[Secretary of State for War]], Lord Kitchener, appointed General [[Sir Ian Hamilton]] to command the {{nowrap|78,000-strong}} [[Mediterranean Expeditionary Force]] (MEF) that was to carry out the mission.{{sfn|Baldwin|1962|p=60}} At this time, soldiers from the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] (AIF) and [[New Zealand Expeditionary Force]] (NZEF) were encamped in [[Egypt]], undergoing training prior to being sent to France.{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=92}} These troops were formed into the [[Australian and New Zealand Army Corps]] (ANZAC), which comprised the all-volunteer [[1st Division (Australia)|Australian 1st Division]] and the [[New Zealand and Australian Division]] under the command of Lieutenant General [[William Birdwood, 1st Baron Birdwood|William Birdwood]]. The ANZAC troops, along with the regular [[British 29th Division]], the [[Royal Naval Division]]{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=40}} and the French [[Corps expéditionnaire d'Orient|Oriental Expeditionary Corps]], consisting of &quot;metropolitan&quot; and colonial troops,{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=25}} were subsequently placed under Hamilton's command.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=16}}{{sfn|Doyle|Bennett|1999|p=14}} With only five divisions the operation would be complicated by the limited forces available, the rugged terrain of the peninsula and the small number of suitable landing beaches, as well as severe logistical difficulties.{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=343}} As the campaign progressed, the troops of the MEF would eventually be supported by about 2,000 civilian labourers from the Egyptian and Maltese Labour Corps.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|p=395}}

As a landing under fire had not been foreseen, the force was not prepared for such an undertaking. The British and French divisions subsequently joined the Australians in Egypt, while over the following month Hamilton prepared his plan, choosing to concentrate his force on the southern part of the Gallipoli peninsula at Cape Helles and Sedd el Bahr.{{sfn|McGibbon|2000|p=191}} The Allies initially discounted the fighting ability of the Ottoman soldiers but came to respect them during the campaign.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=21}} The early apathy was illustrated by a leaflet that was issued to the British and Australians while they were still in Egypt: &quot;Turkish soldiers as a rule manifest their desire to surrender by holding their rifle butt upward and by waving clothes or rags of any colour. An actual white flag should be regarded with the utmost suspicion as a Turkish soldier is unlikely to possess anything of that colour.&quot;{{sfn|Reagan|1992|p=166}} [[Edward J. Erickson|Erickson]] has argued that this apathy stemmed from a &quot;sense of superiority&quot; amongst the Allies, which had resulted from the decline of the Ottoman Empire and perceptions of its performance in earlier conflicts including the Balkan Wars of 1912 and 1913. As a result, Allied intelligence failed to adequately prepare for the campaign,{{sfn|Erickson|2001b|p=983}} in some cases relying on information gained from Egyptian travel guides.{{sfn|Doyle|Bennett|1999|p=12}}

The troops earmarked for the assault were required to be loaded on the transports in the order they were to disembark and as a result the landings could not be undertaken until the end of April. Whilst the five-week delay offered the Ottomans the opportunity to strengthen their position on the peninsula, unfavourable weather during March and April might have delayed the landings at any rate and would have prevented any troops ashore from being supplied and reinforced. Australian and New Zealand forces departed Egypt in early April, assembling on the island of [[Lemnos]] in Greece, where a small garrison had been established in early March. After arriving on 12 April a number of basic practice landings were undertaken.{{sfn|Dennis et al|2008|p=226}} Meanwhile, on 17 April 1915, the British submarine {{HMS|E15||6}} under the command of Captain T.S. Brodie had also tried to run the straits but hit a submarine net and ran aground. The submarine was subsequently shelled by a Turkish fort, killing Brodie and six of the crew and forcing the survivors to surrender.{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=39}}

===Ottoman defensive preparations===
[[File:Map of Turkish forces at Gallipoli April 1915.png|thumb|left|300px|Dispositions of the [[Fifth Army (Ottoman Empire)|Ottoman Fifth Army]]]]
The Ottomans prepared to repel a landing on either side of the Straits, with the [[Fifth Army (Ottoman Empire)|Ottoman Fifth Army]].{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=38}} The force, which initially consisted of five divisions with another en route, was a conscript force, commanded by Otto Liman von Sanders, a German officer who had been head of the Military Mission sent to Turkey as advisors.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=40}}{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=83}}{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=16}} Many of the senior officers in the Fifth Army were also German.{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=13}} Ottoman commanders and senior German officers debated the best means of defending the peninsula. All agreed that the most effective form of defence was to hold the high ground on the ridges of the peninsula. There was disagreement as to where the enemy would land and hence where to concentrate their forces. [[Mustafa Kemal Atatürk|Mustafa Kemal]], a 34-year-old [[lieutenant colonel]] familiar with the Gallipoli peninsula, from his operations against Bulgaria in the Balkan War, believed Cape Helles (the southern tip of the peninsula) and Gaba Tepe would be the two most likely areas for landing.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=31}}{{sfn|Butler|2011|p=121}} In the case of the former, Kemal believed that the British would use their navy to command the land from every side, which the tip of the peninsula would allow; at Gaba Tepe, the short distance to the eastern coast meant forces could easily reach the Narrows.{{sfn|Kinross|1995|pp=73–74}}

Liman von Sanders considered Besika Bay on the Asiatic coast to be the most vulnerable to invasion, since Allied forces would benefit from more accessible terrain and could attack the most important Ottoman batteries guarding the straits. Sanders placed two divisions, one third of the Fifth Army, in this area.{{sfn|James|1995|p=74}} Two divisions were concentrated at Bulair at the north end of the Gallipoli peninsula, to protect supply and communication lines to the defences further along the peninsula.{{sfn|James|1995|p=75}}

The [[19th Infantry Division (Ottoman Empire)|19th Division]], under the command of Mustafa Kemal and the 9th Division were placed along the Aegean coast and at Cape Helles on the tip of the peninsula. The bulk of the forces, under Sanders, were to be held inland, leaving a minimum of troops guarding the coast.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|p=154}} After the 3rd Division and a cavalry brigade arrived from Constantinople in early April, the front line strength of the Ottoman forces on the Bosporus was {{nowrap|60,000 – 62,077}}, which Sanders concentrated in three groups. He ordered the greatest possible effort to improve land and sea communications so that reinforcements could be moved swiftly to danger points; troops were moved at night to avoid detection by Allied aircraft. Sanders' strategy was opposed by Ottoman commanders, including Mustafa Kemal, who believed Ottoman forces were too widely dispersed to drive the attackers back into the sea as soon as their invasion began.{{sfn|James|1995|p=76}} Sanders was certain that a rigid system of defence would fail and that the only hope of success lay in the mobility of the three groups, particularly Kemal's 19th Division, which was concentrated near Boghali as a general reserve, ready to move to Bulair, Gaba Tepe or the Asiatic shore.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|pp=154–157}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R36225, Türkei, Dardanellen, Schweres Geschütz.jpg|thumb|Heavy artillery from the German armoured cruiser [[SMS Roon|''Roon'']], 1915]]
The delay of the landings by the British allowed Sanders and other German officers such as Colonel [[Hans Kannengiesser]], supported by [[III Corps (Ottoman Empire)|III Corps]] commander [[Mehmet Esat Bülkat|Esat Pasha]], time to prepare their defences.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=40}} Sanders later noted, &quot;the British allowed us four good weeks of respite for all this work before their great disembarkation&amp;nbsp;... This respite just sufficed for the most indispensable measures to be taken.&quot; {{sfn|James|1995|p=77}} Roads were constructed, small boats assembled to carry troops and equipment across the narrows, beaches were wired and improvised mines were constructed from torpedo warheads. Trenches and gun emplacements were dug along the beaches, while troops went on route marches to avoid lethargy.{{sfn|James|1995|p=77}} Kemal, whose 19th Division was vital to the defensive scheme, observed the beaches and awaited signs of an invasion from his post at Boghali, near Maidos.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=42}} The Ottomans created a [[Ottoman Aviation Squadrons|small air force]] with German assistance and had four aircraft operating around Çanakkale in February, conducting reconnaissance and army co-operation sorties and by early April they had established an airfield near Gallipoli.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=46}}{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=40}}

==Land campaign==

===Landings===
{{Main|Landing at Anzac Cove|Landing at Cape Helles}}
[[File:Anzac covering force landing April 25 1915.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Map of the landing of the covering force from [[battleship]]s (red) and [[destroyer]]s (orange) at [[Anzac Cove]], 25 April 1915]]
The Allies planned to land and secure the northern shore, capturing the Ottoman forts and artillery batteries there so that a naval force could advance through the Narrows and the Sea of Marmara towards Constantinople.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=43}} Scheduled for 23 April but postponed until 25 April due to bad weather,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=47}} landings were to be made at six beaches on the peninsula. The 29th Division was to land at Helles on the tip of the peninsula and then advance upon the forts at [[Kilitbahir]]. The Anzacs, with the [[3rd Brigade (Australia)|3rd Infantry Brigade]] spearheading the assault,{{sfn|Stevenson|2007|p=189}} were to land north of Gaba Tepe on the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]] coast, from where they could advance across the peninsula, cutting off the Ottoman troops in Kilitbahir. The small cove in and around which they landed became known as &quot;[[Anzac Cove]]&quot;.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=45}} This sector of the Gallipoli Peninsula became known as &quot;Anzac&quot;; the area held by the British and French became known as the &quot;Helles sector&quot; or simply &quot;Helles&quot;. The French made a diversionary landing at Kum Kale on the Asian shore, before re-embarking to hold the eastern area of the Helles sector. There was a diversion by the Royal Naval Division, including a solo effort by New Zealander [[Bernard Freyberg]] at Bulair,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=108}} for which he was awarded the [[Distinguished Service Order]].{{sfn|Life|1942|p=28}}

The Helles landing was made by the 29th Division, under the command of [[Major General]] [[Aylmer Hunter-Weston]]. The division landed on five beaches in an arc about the tip of the peninsula, named from east to west as 'S', 'V', 'W', 'X' and 'Y' Beaches.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=44}} On 1 May, the [[29th Indian Brigade]] (including the [[6th Queen Elizabeth's Own Gurkha Rifles|1/6th Gurkha Rifles]]) landed, took and secured Sari Bair above the landing beaches and were later joined by two other Gurkha battalions, the [[5 Gorkha Rifles (Frontier Force)|1st/5th]] and the [[10th Princess Mary's Own Gurkha Rifles|2nd/10th]];{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|pp=315–316}} the [[Jewish Legion|Zion Mule Corps]] landed at Helles on 27 April. At 'Y' Beach, during the first engagement around the village of Krithia ([[First Battle of Krithia]]), the Allies were able to land unopposed and advance inland.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=19}} There were only a small number of defenders in the village but lacking orders to exploit the position, the 'Y' Beach commander withdrew his force to the beach. It was as close as they came to capturing the village throughout the rest of the campaign as the Ottomans brought up a battalion of the 25th Regiment, checking any further movement.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=102}}

[[File:Landing at Gallipoli (13901951593).jpg|thumb|Landing at Gallipoli, April 1915]]

The main landings were made at [[Landing at Cape Helles#V Beach|'V' Beach]], beneath the old [[Seddülbahir]] fortress and at [[Landing at Cape Helles#W Beach (Lancashire Landing)|'W' Beach]], a short distance to the west on the other side of the Helles headland. The covering force from the [[Royal Munster Fusiliers]] and [[Hampshire Regiment|Hampshires]] landed from a converted collier, {{SS|River Clyde}}, which was run aground beneath the fortress so that the troops could disembark via ramps to the shore. The [[Royal Dublin Fusiliers]] landed at 'V' Beach from open boats. At 'W' Beach, the [[Lancashire Fusiliers]] also landed in open boats, on a shore overlooked by dunes and obstructed with [[barbed wire]]. On both beaches the Ottoman defenders occupied good defensive positions and inflicted many casualties on the British infantry as they landed. Troops emerging one by one from sally ports on the ''River Clyde'' were shot by machine-gunners at the [[Sedd-el-Bahr|Seddülbahir]] fort. Of the first {{nowrap|200 soldiers}} to disembark, only {{nowrap|21 men}} reached the beach.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|pp=232–236}}

As at Anzac, the Ottoman defenders were too few to defeat the landing but inflicted many casualties and contained the attack close to the shore. By the morning of 25 April 1915, out of ammunition and left with nothing but [[bayonet]]s to meet the attackers on the slopes leading up from the beach to the heights of Chunuk Bair, the 57th Infantry Regiment received orders from Kemal, commanding the 19th Division: &quot;I do not order you to fight, I order you to die. In the time which passes until we die, other troops and commanders can come forward and take our places&quot;.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=xv}} Every man of the regiment was either killed in action or wounded. As a sign of respect, the 57th Regiment no longer exists in the [[Turkish Army]].{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=xv}}

[[File:Cape Helles landing map.jpg|thumb|left|Cape Helles landing beaches]]

At 'W' Beach, thereafter known as Lancashire Landing, the Lancashires were able to overwhelm the defences despite the loss of {{nowrap|600 casualties}} from {{nowrap|1,000 men}}. The battalions which landed at 'V' Beach suffered about {{nowrap|70 percent casualties}}. Six awards of the [[Victoria Cross]] were made among the Lancashires at 'W' Beach. A further six Victoria Crosses were awarded among the infantry and sailors at the 'V' Beach landing and three more were awarded the following day as they fought their way off the beach. Five squads of Ottoman infantry led by Sergeant Yahya distinguished themselves by repulsing several attacks on their hilltop position, the defenders eventually disengaging under cover of darkness.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=84}} After the landings, so few remained from the Dublin and Munster Fusiliers that they were amalgamated into &quot;The Dubsters&quot;.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|p=318}} Only one Dubliner officer survived the landing,{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=232}} while of the {{nowrap|1,012 Dubliners}} who landed, just {{nowrap|11 survived}} the Gallipoli campaign unscathed.{{sfn|Thys-Şenocak|Aslan|2008|p=30}}

After the landings, little was done by the Allies to exploit the situation and apart from a few limited advances inland by small groups of men, most troops stayed on or close to the beaches. The Allied attack lost momentum and the Ottomans had time to bring up reinforcements and rally the small number of defending troops.{{sfn|Perrett|2004|p=192}} Lord Kitchener had ruled that air requirements must be met by the [[Royal Naval Air Service]] (RNAS) and the Allies employed a small force of seaplanes and other aircraft from [[No. 203 Squadron RAF|No. 3 Squadron]], RNAS which arrived at [[Bozcaada|Tenedos]] at the end of March.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1929|p=139}} Under Commander [[Charles Rumney Samson|Charles Samson]], the aircraft were initially unopposed by the small Ottoman air force and during the planning stages the force had been used to provide aerial reconnaissance,{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=43}} although this ultimately proved inadequate to meet the Allies' intelligence needs and make up for the lack of adequate maps.{{sfn|Doyle|Bennett|1999|p=12}} Following the landings, Allied aircraft conducted photographic reconnaissance, observed naval gunfire, reported on Ottoman troop movements and conducted a small number of offensive bombing raids.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=43}}

The Australian submarine {{HMAS|AE2||6}} under the command of Lieutenant Commander [[Henry Stoker]] succeeded in getting through the Straits on the night of 24/25 April. As the army began landing soldiers at Cape Helles and Anzac Cove at dawn on the 25th, by {{nowrap|06:00}}, ''AE2'' reached [[Chanak]] and torpedoed a Turkish gunboat believed to be a [[Peyk-i Şevket-class cruiser|''Peyk-i Şevket''-class cruiser]] while evading a destroyer.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=45}}{{sfn|Jose|1941|p=242}} The submarine ran aground beneath a Turkish fort but the fort's guns could not bear and ''AE2'' was manoeuvred free.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=45}} Shortly after refloating, the submarine's periscope was sighted by a Turkish battleship, which was firing over the peninsula at Allied landing sites; the ship ceased fire and withdrew.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=45}} ''AE2'' advanced toward the [[Sea of Marmara]]; at {{nowrap|08:30}} Stoker decided to rest the boat on the seabed and wait until nightfall before continuing.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=45}} At around {{nowrap|21:00}}, ''AE2'' surfaced to recharge her batteries and sent a wireless report to the fleet.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=45}}{{sfn|Frame|2004|p=119}} Although the [[landing at Cape Helles]] was going well, the [[landing at Anzac Cove]] was not as successful and the commander of the Australian and New Zealand Army Corps, Lieutenant General Sir William Birdwood contemplated the re-embarkation of his troops.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=45}} The news of the Australian submarine's success was one of the factors that led to Birdwood's reconsideration and was relayed to the soldiers ashore to improve morale.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=45}} Stoker was ordered to &quot;generally run amok&quot; and with no enemies in sight, he sailed into the Sea of Marmara. ''AE2'' cruised the Sea of Marmara for five days to give the impression of greater numbers and made several attacks against Turkish ships, which failed because of mechanical problems with the torpedoes.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=46}}

===Early battles===
[[File:Anzac, the landing 1915.jpg|thumb|right|''Anzac, the landing 1915'' by [[George Washington Lambert|George Lambert]], 1922 shows the [[landing at Anzac Cove]], 25 April 1915]]
On the afternoon of 27 April 1915, the {{nowrap|12 battalions}} of Mustafa Kemal's 19th Division, reinforced by six battalions from the 5th Division, launched an attack to drive the six Allied brigades at Anzac back to the beach.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=121}} With the support of naval gunfire, the Allies held back the Ottomans throughout the night. The following day the British, with the support of French troops, who had been transported north across the Dardanelles from Kum Kale on the Asiatic shore to the right of the line near 'S' Beach at [[Morto Bay]], attempted to capture Krithia, in what became known as the First Battle of Krithia.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=122–123}} The plan for the attack which was formulated by Hunter-Weston, proved overly complex and was poorly communicated to the commanders in the field. The troops of the 29th Division were still exhausted and unnerved by the battles for the beaches and for Seddülbahir village, which was captured after much fighting on 26 April. The Ottoman defenders stopped the Allied advance halfway between the Helles headland and Krithia village, at around {{nowrap|6:00 p.m.}} having inflicted {{nowrap|3,000 casualties}}.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=124–125}} As Ottoman reinforcements arrived, the possibility of a swift Allied victory on the peninsula disappeared and the fighting at Helles and Anzac, became a battle of attrition. On 30 April, the Royal Naval Division, under Major General [[Archibald Paris]] landed.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=126}}

The same day, Kemal, believing that the Allies were on the verge of defeat, began moving troops forward through &quot;Wire Gulley&quot;, near the &quot;{{nowrap|400 Plateau}}&quot; and &quot;Lone Pine&quot;. The following afternoon, as eight battalions of reserves were dispatched from Constantinople, Ottoman troops launched strong [[counterattack]]s at Helles and Anzac. Although these briefly broke through in the French sector, the attacks were repulsed by massed Allied machine-gun fire, which inflicted heavy casualties on the attackers.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=129 &amp; 134}} The following night, the ANZAC commander, Lieutenant General William Birdwood, ordered the New Zealand and Australian Division under Major General [[Alexander Godley]], to attack from &quot;Russell's Top&quot; and &quot;Quinn's Post&quot; towards &quot;{{nowrap|Baby 700}}&quot;. Colonel [[John Monash]]'s [[Australian 4th Brigade|Australian 4th Infantry Brigade]], the [[New Zealand Infantry Brigade]] and marines from the Chatham Battalion took part in the attack. The troops advanced a short distance during the night, under a combined naval and artillery barrage but in the dark became separated and after coming under heavy fire from their exposed left flank, were eventually forced to withdraw, having suffered about {{nowrap|1,000 casualties}}.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=129–130}}

[[File:AE2 (AWM H17538).jpg|thumb|left|HMAS ''AE2'']]

At sea, on 30 April, ''AE2'' began to rise uncontrollably and surfaced near the {{ship|Ottoman torpedo boat|Sultanhisar||2|up=y}}, then dropped precipitously, below her [[Submarine depth ratings|safe diving depth]], then broke the surface again at the stern.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=46}} ''Sultanhisar'' immediately fired on the submarine, puncturing the pressure hull. Stoker ordered the boat's company to abandon ship and scuttled the submarine before the crew was captured. ''AE2''{{'}}s achievements showed that it was possible to force the Straits and soon Ottoman communications were badly disrupted by British and French submarine operations.{{sfn|Stevens|2001|p=46}} On 27 April, {{HMS|E14||6}}, commanded by Lieutenant Commander [[Edward Courtney Boyle|Edward Boyle]], entered the Sea of Marmara on a three-week patrol in one of the most successful Allied naval actions of the campaign, sinking four ships including the transport ''Gul Djemal'' which was carrying 6,000 troops and a field battery to Gallipoli. While the quantity and value of the shipping sunk was minor, the effect on Ottoman communications and morale was significant. On his return, Boyle was immediately awarded the Victoria Cross.{{sfn|Pitt|Young|1970|pp=918–919}}{{sfn|McCartney|2008|p=31}} Following the success of ''AE2'' and ''E14'', the French submarine {{Ship|French submarine|Joule||2}} attempted the passage on 1 May but struck a mine and was lost with all hands.{{sfn|Usborne|1933|p=327}} (Several weeks earlier another French boat, {{Ship|French submarine|Saphir|Q44|2}}, had run aground near Nagara Point and had also been lost.){{sfn|O'Connell|2010|p=73}}

===Operations: May 1915===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-S29571, Türkei, Dardanellen, MG-Stellung.jpg|thumb|Ottoman machine-gun teams equipped with [[MG 08]]s]]
On 5 May, the [[42nd (East Lancashire) Division]] was dispatched from Egypt.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=134}} Believing Anzac to be secure, Hamilton moved the Australian [[2nd Brigade (Australia)|2nd Infantry Brigade]] and the New Zealand Infantry Brigade, along with {{nowrap|20 Australian}} field artillery pieces, to the Helles front as reserves for the [[Second Battle of Krithia]].{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=131 &amp; 136}} Involving a force of {{nowrap|20,000 men}}, it was the first general attack at Helles and was planned as a daylight attack. French troops were to capture Kereves Dere and the British, Australians and New Zealanders were assigned Krithia and Achi Baba. After {{nowrap|30 minutes}} of artillery preparation, the assault began at mid-morning on 6 May.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=137}} The British and French advanced along four spurs dubbed &quot;Gully&quot;, &quot;Fir Tree&quot;, &quot;Krithia&quot; and &quot;Kereves&quot; which were separated by deep gullies and fortified by the Ottoman forces. As the attackers reached the Ottoman defences, the Allied units became separated as they attempted to outflank Ottoman strongpoints and found themselves in unfamiliar terrain. Under heavy artillery and then machine-gun fire from Ottoman outposts that had remained hidden from British aerial reconnaissance, the advance stopped; the next day, it was resumed by reinforcements.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=137–142}}

The attack continued on 7 May but the success of the Ottoman defences continued. Four battalions of New Zealanders attacked up Krithia Spur the following day and with the 29th Division they managed to reach a position just south of the village. Late in the afternoon, the Australian 2nd Brigade advanced quickly over open ground to the British front line. Amidst heavy small arms and shell fire, the brigade charged towards Krithia and gained {{convert|600|m|yd}}, about {{convert|400|m|yd}} short of the objective, with {{nowrap|1,000 casualties}}. Near Fir Tree Spur, the New Zealanders managed to get forward and link up with the Australians, although the British were held up and the French were exhausted, despite having occupied a point overlooking their objective. The attack was suspended and the Allies dug in, having failed to take Krithia or Achi Baba.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=137–142}}

A brief period of consolidation followed. Allied stocks of ammunition were almost expended, particularly for artillery and both sides paused to bring in replenishments and expand their trench systems.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=143}} The Ottomans relieved troops opposite the Australian line, which was reinforced by the [[Australian Light Horse]] operating as infantry.{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=96}} Sporadic fighting continued, with sniping, grenade attacks and raids,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=148}} with opposing trenches separated in places by only a few metres.{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=96}} The Australians lost a number of officers to sniping, including the commander of the 1st Division, Major General [[William Bridges (general)|William Bridges]], who was wounded while inspecting the [[1st Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|1st Light Horse Regiment]]'s position near &quot;Steele's Post&quot; and died of his injuries on the hospital ship [[HMHS Gascon|HMHS ''Gascon'']] on 18 May.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=149}}

===Ottoman counter-offensive: 19 May===
{{main|Third attack on Anzac Cove}}
[[File:OttomanBatteryAtGallipoli.jpg|thumb|left|[[Mehmet Esat Bülkat|Esat Pasha]] delivering orders to the batteries at [[Landing at Anzac Cove|Anzac Cove]]]]
On 19 May, {{nowrap|42,000 Turks}} launched an attack at Anzac in an effort to push {{nowrap|17,000 Australians}} and New Zealanders &quot;back into the sea&quot;.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=43}}{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=87}} Lacking sufficient artillery and ammunition, the Turks relied on surprise and weight of numbers for success but their preparations were seen on 18 May by a flight of British aircraft and the defenders forewarned.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=43}}{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=87}} The Turks had {{nowrap|c. 13,000 casualties}}, of which {{nowrap|3,000 men}} were killed; Australian and New Zealand casualties were {{nowrap|160 killed}} and {{nowrap|468 wounded}}.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=87}}{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=154}}{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=161}} The dead included a [[stretcher bearer]], [[John Simpson Kirkpatrick]], whose efforts to evacuate wounded men on a donkey while under fire, became legendary amongst the Australians at Anzac and later resulted in his story becoming part of the Australian narrative of the campaign.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=149–150}} Ottoman losses were so severe that a [[truce]] was organised by [[Aubrey Herbert]] and others on 24 May, to bury the dead lying in [[no man's land]], which led to a camaraderie between the armies, much like the [[Christmas truce]] of 1914 on the Western Front. The truce was not repeated formally.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=156–157}}

The British advantage in ship-to-shore bombardment had diminished by the torpedoing of the battleship {{HMS|Goliath|1898|6}} on 13 May by the {{ship|Ottoman destroyer|Muâvenet-i Millîye||2|up=y}}.{{sfn|Burt|1988|pp=158–159}} A German submarine, {{SMU|U-21|Germany|2}}, sank {{HMS|Triumph|1903|6}} on 25 May and {{HMS|Majestic|1895|6}} on 27 May.{{sfn|Burt|1988|pp=131 &amp; 276}} Samson's aircraft flew more patrols around Gallipoli and ''U-21'' was forced to leave the area. Unaware of this, the Allies withdrew most of their warships to Imbros, where they were &quot;protectively tethered&quot; between brief sorties; this greatly reduced the amount of Allied naval fire support, particularly in the Helles sector.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=165}} Meanwhile, {{HMS|E11||6}}, commanded by Lieutenant Commander [[Martin Eric Nasmith|Martin Nasmith]] (who was awarded a Victoria Cross) passed through the Dardanelles on 18 May and sank or disabled 11 ships, including three on 23 May, before entering Constantinople harbour, firing on a transport alongside the arsenal, sinking a gunboat and damaging the wharf.{{sfn|Brenchley|Brenchley|2001|p=113}}{{sfn|O'Connell|2010|p=74}}{{sfn|Pitt|Young|1970|p=918}}

The Ottoman Turkish forces lacked artillery ammunition and Ottoman field batteries were only able to fire {{nowrap|c. 18,000 shells}} between early May and the first week of June.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=89}} After the defeat of the counterattack at Anzac in mid-May, the Ottoman forces ceased frontal assaults. Late in the month the Ottomans began tunnelling around &quot;Quinn's Post&quot; in the Anzac sector and early in the morning of 29 May, despite Australian counter-mining, the Ottomans detonated a mine and attacked with a battalion from the 14th Regiment. The [[15th Battalion (Australia)|Australian 15th Battalion]] was forced back but counterattacked and recaptured the ground later in the day, before being relieved by New Zealand troops. Operations at Anzac in early June returned to consolidation, minor engagements and skirmishing with grenades and sniper-fire.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=169–170}}

===Operations: June–July 1915===
[[File:French 75 gun at Cape Helles 1915.jpg|thumb|right|A [[French Colonial Forces|French colonial]] [[Canon de 75 modèle 1897|75 mm]] gun in action near Sedd el Bahr during the Third Battle of Krithia, 4 June 1915]]
In the Helles sector, which had been extensively entrenched by both sides, the Allies attacked Krithia and Achi Baba again, in the [[Third Battle of Krithia]] on 4 June, with the 29th Division, Royal Naval Division, 42nd Division and two French divisions.{{Sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=170}} After its failure, the possibility of a decisive breakthrough was gone and trench warfare resumed, with objectives being measured in hundreds of yards. Casualties were approximately {{nowrap|25 percent on}} both sides; the British lost {{nowrap|4,500}} from {{nowrap|20,000 men}} and the French {{nowrap|2,000 casualties}} from {{nowrap|10,000 troops}}. Ottoman losses were {{nowrap|9,000 casualties}} according to the Turkish Official History and {{nowrap|10,000 according}} to another account.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|pp=46, 53}}

In June, a seaplane carrier {{HMS|Ben-my-Chree}} arrived and the Allied air force was expanded from one squadron to a full wing designated &quot;[[Wing (military aviation unit)|No. 3 Wing]] RNAS&quot;.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=44}} The [[52nd (Lowland) Division]] also landed at Helles in preparation for the [[Battle of Gully Ravine|Battle of &quot;Gully Ravine&quot;]], which was launched on 28 June. This battle advanced the British line along the left (Aegean) flank of the battlefield, a limited victory for the Allies. Liman von Sanders credited the defence to two Ottoman officers, Faik Pasa and Albay Refet.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=89}} On 30 June, the French commander, [[Henri Gouraud (French Army officer)|Henri Gouraud]] who had earlier replaced [[Albert d'Amade]], was wounded and replaced by his divisional commander, Maurice Bailloud.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=15}} Between 1 and 5 July the Ottomans counterattacked the new British line several times but failed to regain the lost ground. Ottoman casualties for the period were estimated at {{nowrap|14,000 men}}.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|p=95}} A British action took place at Helles on 12 July, before the Allied main effort was shifted north to Anzac. Two fresh brigades from the 52nd Division attacked at the centre of the line along Achi Baba Nullah (&quot;Bloody Valley&quot;), gained very little ground and lost {{nowrap|2,500 casualties}} out of {{nowrap|7,500 men}}; the Royal Naval Division lost {{nowrap|600 }} and French losses were {{nowrap|800 men}}. Turkish losses were about {{nowrap|9,000 casualties}} and {{nowrap|600 prisoners}}.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|p=111}}

Meanwhile, the submarine campaign continued. Boyle and ''E14'' made two subsequent tours of the Marmara.{{sfn|Brenchley|Brenchley|2001|p=113}} His third tour began on 21 July, when he passed through the straits despite the newly installed [[anti-submarine net]] near the Narrows.{{sfn|Snelling|1995|p=103}} The next attempt was made by {{Ship|French submarine|Mariotte||2}} on 27 July. ''Mariotte'' failed to negotiate the net that ''E14'' had eluded and was forced to the surface. After being shelled from the shore batteries, ''Mariotte'' was scuttled.{{sfn|Willmott|2009|p=387}} On 8 August, during a subsequent tour of the Marmara, ''E11'' torpedoed the [[SMS Kurfürst Friedrich Wilhelm|Ottoman battleship ''Barbaros Hayreddin'']] resulting in the loss of 253 men.{{sfn|Halpern|1995|p=119}}{{sfn|Hore|2006|p=66}} During the tour ''E11'' also sank a gunboat, seven transports and 23 sailing vessels.{{sfn|O'Connell|2010|p=76}}

===August offensive===
{{Main|Battle of Sari Bair|Battle of Krithia Vineyard|Battle of Lone Pine|Battle of Chunuk Bair|Battle of the Nek|Battle of Scimitar Hill|Battle of Hill 60 (Gallipoli)}}
[[File:Periscope rifle Gallipoli 1915.jpg|thumb|left|Australian [[Australian Light Horse|light horseman]] using a periscope rifle]]
The failure of the Allies to capture Krithia, or make any progress on the Helles front, led Hamilton to pursue a new plan to secure the [[Battle of Sari Bair|Sari Bair Range]] and capture high ground on {{nowrap|Hill 971}} and [[Battle of Chunuk Bair|Chunuk Bair]].{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=190}} Both sides had been reinforced, with Hamilton's original five divisions increased to 15, while the six original Ottoman divisions had grown to 16.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=344}}{{sfn|Travers|2001|pp=271–273}} Commanded by Godley, the Allies planned to land two fresh infantry divisions from [[IX Corps (United Kingdom)|IX Corps]],{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=95}} at [[Suvla]], {{convert|5|mi|km}} north of Anzac, followed by an advance on Sari Bair from the northwest.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=191}} At Anzac an offensive would be made against the Sari Bair range by advancing through rough and thinly defended terrain, north of the Anzac perimeter. This would be achieved by an attack on &quot;{{nowrap|Baby 700}}&quot; from [[Battle of the Nek|the Nek]] by dismounted Australian light horsemen from the [[3rd Light Horse Brigade]], in concert with an attack on Chunuk Bair summit by New Zealanders from the New Zealand Infantry Brigade, who would traverse &quot;Rhododendron Ridge&quot;, the &quot;Apex&quot; and the &quot;Farm&quot;. {{nowrap|Hill 971}} would be attacked by a combined force drawn from the Gurkhas of the 29th Indian Brigade and the Australians of the 4th Infantry Brigade.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=191}} The Allies had {{nowrap|40 aircraft}}, mainly of No. 3 Wing, RNAS at [[Imbros]], which had replaced its original [[Voisin (aircraft)|Voisin]] aircraft, with Farmans and [[Nieuport 10|Nieuport Xs]]. A French squadron, Escadrille MF98T, had also been established at Tenedos. Against this the Ottomans had {{nowrap|20 aircraft}}, of which eight were stationed at Çanakkale. Throughout the offensive the Allied aircraft made reconnaissance flights, spotted for naval gunfire support and conducted low-level bombing of Ottoman reserves as they were brought up to the battlefield;{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=44}} they also undertook anti-shipping operations in the Gulf of Saros where a seaplane from HMS ''Ben-my-Chree'' sank an Ottoman tug with an air-launched torpedo.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=83}}

[[File:Lone Pine (AWM A02025).jpg|thumb|right|Captain [[Leslie Morshead]] in a trench at Lone Pine after the battle, looking at Australian and Ottoman dead on the parapet]]

The [[landing at Suvla Bay]] took place on the night of 6 August against light opposition; but the British commander, Lieutenant General [[Frederick Stopford]], had limited his early objectives and then failed to forcefully push his demands for an advance inland and little more ground than the beach was seized. The Ottomans were able to occupy the Anafarta Hills, preventing the British from penetrating inland, which reduced the Suvla front to static trench warfare.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|p=273}} The offensive was preceded on the evening of 6 August by diversions at Helles and Anzac. At Helles, the diversion at [[Battle of Krithia Vineyard|Krithia Vineyard]] became another costly stalemate. At Anzac an attack on the Ottoman trenches at [[Battle of Lone Pine|&quot;Lone Pine&quot;]], led by the [[1st Brigade (Australia)|1st Infantry Brigade]],{{sfn|Stevenson|2007|p=189}} captured the main Ottoman trench line in a diversion to draw Ottoman forces away from the main assaults at the peaks of Chunuk Bair and {{nowrap|Hill 971}}, both of which failed nonetheless.{{sfn|Ekins|2009|p=29}}{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=112}}

The New Zealand Infantry Brigade came within {{convert|500|m|yd}} of the near peak of Chunuk Bair by dawn on 7 August but was not able to seize the summit until the following morning.{{sfn|McGibbon|2000|p=197}} This delay had fatal consequences for another supporting attack on the morning of 7 August, by the Australian 3rd Light Horse Brigade at the Nek, which was to coincide with the New Zealander attack from Chunuk Bair against the rear of the Ottoman defences. The attack went ahead regardless, ending in a costly failure, after the opening artillery barrage lifted seven minutes early, leaving the assaulting troops to attack alerted Ottoman defenders on a narrow front.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=109}} An attack on {{nowrap|Hill 971}} never took place after the Australian 4th Infantry Brigade and an Indian brigade lost direction during the night. Attempts to resume the attack were easily repulsed by the Ottoman defenders, at great cost to the Allies.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=110}} The New Zealanders held out on Chunuk Bair for two days before relief was provided by two New Army battalions from the [[Wiltshire Regiment|Wiltshire]] and [[Loyal North Lancashire Regiment]]s. An Ottoman counterattack on 10 August, led by Mustafa Kemal, swept these two battalions from the heights.{{sfn|McGibbon|2000|p=197}} Of {{nowrap|760 men}} in the New Zealand Wellington Battalion who reached the summit {{nowrap|711 became}} casualties.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=442}} With the Turkish forces having recaptured the vital ground the Allies' best chance of victory was lost.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=110}}

[[File:Scene just before the evacuation at Anzac. Australian troops charging near a Turkish trench. When they got there the... - NARA - 533108.tif|thumb|left|Australian troops charging an Ottoman trench, just before the evacuation at Anzac]]

The Suvla landing was reinforced by the arrival of the [[10th (Irish) Division]] on 7 August, the [[53rd (Welsh) Division]], which began landing on 8 August, the [[54th (East Anglian) Division]] arriving late on 10 August and the dismounted [[yeomanry]] of the [[2nd Mounted Division]] on 18 August.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|pp=248, 286, 312–313}} On 12 August the 54th Division attacked Kavak Tepe and Tekke Tepe, crossing the Anafarta Plain. The attack failed and Hamilton's staff briefly considered the evacuation of Suvla and Anzac. The events of the day later gained significance due to the loss of a company of the [[Norfolk Regiment]]. Having been recruited from men who worked on King George V's Sandringham estate they were dubbed the &quot;Sandringham Company&quot;. After being isolated and destroyed during the 12 August attack it was rumoured that they had advanced into a mist and &quot;simply disappeared&quot;. This gave rise to legends that they had been executed or that they had been taken by some supernatural force but some members were later found to have been taken prisoner.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=232}}

Elements of the newly formed [[2nd Division (Australia)|Australian 2nd Division]] began arriving at Anzac from Egypt with the [[5th Brigade (Australia)|5th Infantry Brigade]] landing on 19–20 August;{{sfn|Cameron|2011|p=17}} the [[6th Brigade (Australia)|6th]] and [[7th Brigade (Australia)|7th]] arrived in early September.{{sfn|Cameron|2011|p=147}} The 29th Division was also shifted from Helles to Suvla. The final British attempt to resuscitate the offensive came on 21 August with attacks at [[Scimitar Hill (battle)|Scimitar Hill]] and [[Battle of Hill 60 (Gallipoli)|Hill 60]]. Control of the hills would have united the Anzac and Suvla fronts but both attacks failed. During the fighting at {{nowrap|Hill 60}}, which ended on 29 August, Hamilton had requested another {{nowrap|95,000 troops}} on 17 August and on 16 August the French had announced plans to Kitchener for an autumn offensive in France. A meeting of the Dardanelles Committee on 20 August determined that the French offensive would be supported with all the forces at Britain's disposal, which left only about {{nowrap|25,000 reinforcements}} for the Dardanelles. On 23 August, after news of the failure at Scimitar Hill, Hamilton felt compelled to assume a defensive strategy as Bulgaria's entry into the war, which would allow the Germans to rearm the Turkish army, was imminent and left little opportunity for the resumption of offensive operations. On 20 September 1915, the [[Newfoundland Regiment]] was deployed at Suvla Bay with the 29th Division in support of the campaign.{{sfn|Nicholson|2007|pp=155–192}} On 25 September Kitchener demanded three divisions—two British and one French—for service in [[Salonika]] in Greece and this marked the beginning of the end of the Allied campaign at Gallipoli.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|pp=363–376}}

[[Alan Moorehead]] records that during the stalemate one old Ottoman [[Batman (military)|batman]] was regularly permitted to hang his platoon's washing on the barbed wire without attracting fire and that there was a &quot;constant traffic&quot; of gifts being thrown across no-man's land: dates and sweets from the Ottoman side and cans of beef and cigarettes from the Allied side.{{sfn|Moorehead|1997|p=158}} Conditions at Gallipoli grew worse for the soldiers on both sides and summer heat and poor sanitation resulted in an explosion in the fly population. Eating became extremely difficult as unburied corpses became bloated and putrid. The precarious Allied bases were poorly situated, which caused supply and shelter problems. A [[dysentery]] epidemic spread through the Allied trenches at Anzac and Helles, while the Ottomans also suffered heavily from disease which resulted in many deaths.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=314}}

===Evacuation===
[[File:Soldiers in trench.jpg|thumb|Troops from the [[Royal Irish Fusiliers]] serving in Gallipoli in Autumn 1915]]
The defeat of Serbia during the autumn 1915 phase of the [[Serbian Campaign of World War I#Course of the Campaign|Serbian Campaign]] prompted France and Britain to transfer troops from the Gallipoli Campaign to [[Macedonia (Greece)|Greek Macedonia]]. The [[Macedonian Front]] was thus established in an effort to support the remnants of the Serbian army to conquer [[Vardar Macedonia]].{{sfn|Hall |2010 |pp = 48–50}}

Following the failure of the August Offensive, the Gallipoli campaign drifted. Ottoman success began to affect public opinion in the United Kingdom, with news discrediting Hamilton's performance being smuggled out by journalists like [[Keith Murdoch]] and [[Ellis Ashmead-Bartlett]].{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=26}} Disaffected senior officers such as General Stopford also contributed to the overall air of gloom. The prospect of evacuation was raised on 11 October 1915 but Hamilton resisted the suggestion, fearing the damage to British prestige. He was dismissed as commander shortly afterwards and replaced by Lieutenant General [[Charles Carmichael Monro|Sir Charles Monro]].{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=244–245}} Autumn and winter brought relief from the heat but also led to gales, blizzards and flooding, resulting in men drowning and freezing to death, while thousands suffered [[frostbite]].{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=515}}

On 4 September, the same anti-submarine net that caught ''Mariotte'' also trapped ''E7'' as it attempted to commence another tour.{{sfn|Pitt|Young|1970|p=919}} Despite such reverses, by mid-September the Allies had succeeded in sealing off the eastern entrance to the Dardanelles to German U-boats using a series of nets and mines, with ''U-21'' finding the way blocked when it attempted to traverse the strait on its way to Constantinople on 13 September.{{sfn|O'Connell|2010|p=77}} The first French submarine to enter the Sea of Marmara was {{Ship|French submarine|Turquoise||2}} but it was forced to turn back and on 30 October, when attempting to pass back through the straits, ran aground beneath a fort and was captured intact. The crew of 25 were taken prisoner and documents detailing planned Allied operations were discovered, including a scheduled rendezvous with {{HMS|E20||6}} on 6 November. The rendezvous was kept by the German U-boat {{SMU|U-14|Germany|2}} instead, which torpedoed and sank ''E20'', killing all but nine of the crew.{{sfn|O'Connell|2010|pp=76–77}}

The situation at Gallipoli was complicated by the entry of Bulgaria into the war on the side of the Central Powers. In early October 1915 the British and French opened a second Mediterranean front at Salonika, by moving three divisions from Gallipoli,{{sfn|Baldwin|1962|pp=61 and 66}} and reducing the flow of reinforcements.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=26}} A land route between Germany and the Ottoman Empire through Bulgaria was opened,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=249 and 252}} enabling Germany to supply heavy artillery to devastate the Allied trench network, especially on the confined front at Anzac, as well as modern aircraft and experienced crews.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=47}} In late November an Ottoman crew in a German [[Albatros C.I]] shot down a French aircraft over Gaba Tepe{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=47}} and two Austro-Hungarian artillery units, the {{lang|de|''36. Haubitzbatterie''}} and {{lang|de|''9. Motormörserbatterie''}} arrived, providing a substantial reinforcement of the Ottoman artillery.{{sfn|Jung|2003|pp=42–43}}{{sfn|Ben-Gavriel|1999|p=258}} Monro recommended evacuation to Kitchener who in early November visited the eastern Mediterranean.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=26}} After consulting with the commanders of [[VIII Corps (United Kingdom)|VIII Corps]] at Helles,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=188}} IX Corps at Suvla,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=191}} and Anzac, Kitchener agreed with Monro and passed his recommendation to the British Cabinet, who confirmed the decision to evacuate in early December.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=254}}

[[File:W Beach Helles Gallipoli.jpg|thumb|left|[[Landing at Cape Helles|W Beach, Helles]], on 7 January 1916 just prior to the final evacuation]]

Due to the proximity of Ottoman forces and the harsh winter weather, many casualties were anticipated during the embarkation. The untenable nature of the Allied position was made apparent when a heavy rainstorm struck on 26 November 1915. It lasted three days and was followed by a blizzard at Suvla in early December. Rain flooded trenches, drowned soldiers and washed unburied corpses into the lines; the following snow killed still more men from exposure.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=255–256}}

The evacuation was the best-executed segment of the entire Allied campaign.{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=98}}{{sfn|Baldwin|1962|pp=61–62}} Suvla and Anzac were to be evacuated in late December, the last troops leaving before dawn on 20 December 1915. Troop numbers had been slowly reduced since 7 December 1915 and ruses, such as [[William Scurry]]'s self-firing rifle,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=260}} which had been rigged to fire by water dripped into a pan attached to the trigger, were used to disguise the Allied departure. At Anzac Cove troops maintained silence for an hour or more, until curious Ottoman troops ventured to inspect the trenches, whereupon the Anzacs opened fire. A mine was detonated at the Nek which killed {{nowrap|70 Ottoman}} soldiers.{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=208}} The Allied force was embarked, with the Australians suffering no casualties on the final night,{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=98}}{{sfn|Hart|2007|p=12}} but large quantities of supplies and stores fell into Ottoman hands.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=93}}

Helles was retained for a period but a decision to evacuate the garrison was made on 28 December.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=526}} Unlike the evacuation from Anzac Cove, Ottoman forces were looking for signs of withdrawal.{{sfn|Hart|2007|p=12}} Having used the intervening time to bring up reinforcements and supplies, Liman von Sanders mounted an attack on the British at &quot;Gully Spur&quot; on 7 January 1916 with infantry and artillery; the attack failed and heavy casualties were inflicted.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=266}} Mines were laid with time fuzes and that night and on the night of 7/8 January, under the cover of a naval bombardment, the British troops began to fall back {{convert|5|mi|km}} from their lines to the beaches, where makeshift piers were used to board boats.{{sfn|Hart|2007|p=12}}{{sfn|Parker|2005|p=126}} The final British troops departed from Lancashire Landing around 04:00 on 8 January 1916.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=266}} The Newfoundland Regiment was chosen to be a part of the [[rearguard]], finally withdrawing from Gallipoli on 9 January 1916.{{sfn|Nicholson|2007|p=480}} Among the first to land, remnants of The Plymouth Battalion, Royal Marine Light Infantry were the last to leave the Peninsula.{{sfn|Lockhart|1950|p=17}} Despite predictions of up to {{nowrap|30,000 casualties}},{{sfn|Parker|2005|p=126}} {{nowrap|35,268 troops}}, {{nowrap|3,689 horses}} and mules, {{nowrap|127 guns}}, {{nowrap|328 vehicles}} and {{convert|1600|LT|MT}} of equipment were removed. {{nowrap|508 mules}} which could not be embarked were killed so as not to fall into Turkish hands and {{nowrap|1,590 vehicles}} were left behind with destroyed wheels.{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|p=478}} As at Anzac, large amounts of supplies (including 15 damaged British and six French artillery pieces which were destroyed), gun carriages and ammunition were left behind; hundreds of horses were also slaughtered, again to prevent them from being utilised by the Ottomans. One sailor was killed by débris from a magazine that exploded prematurely and a lighter and a picket boat were lost.{{sfn|Corbett|2009|p=255}} Shortly after dawn, the Ottoman forces retook Helles.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=266}} In the final days of the campaign, the Ottoman air defences had been increased by a German-Ottoman fighter squadron which began operations over the peninsula and inflicted the first British flying losses a couple of days after the evacuation of Helles, when three [[Fokker Eindecker fighters|Fokker Eindeckers]] shot down two RNAS aircraft.{{sfn|Gilbert|2013|p=47}}

==Aftermath==

===Military repercussions===
Historians are divided about how they summarise the campaign's result. Broadbent describes the campaign as &quot;a close-fought affair&quot; that was a defeat for the Allies,{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=268 &amp; 269}} while [[Les Carlyon|Carlyon]] views the overall result as a stalemate.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=518}} [[Peter Hart (military historian)|Peter Hart]] disagrees, arguing that the Ottoman forces &quot;held the Allies back from their real objectives with relative ease&quot;,{{sfn|Hart|2007|p=12}} while [[Philip Haythornthwaite|Haythornthwaite]] calls it a &quot;disaster for the Allies&quot;.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=90}} The campaign did cause &quot;enormous damage to&amp;nbsp;... [Ottoman] national resources&quot;,{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=90}} and at that stage of the war the Allies were in a better position to replace their losses than the Ottomans,{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=98}} but ultimately the Allied attempt at securing a passage through the Dardanelles proved unsuccessful. While it diverted Ottoman forces away from other areas of conflict in the Middle East the campaign also consumed resources the Allies could have employed on the Western Front,{{sfn|Doyle|Bennett|1999|p=15}} and also resulted in heavy losses on the Allied side.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=90}}

The Allied campaign was plagued by ill-defined goals, poor planning, insufficient artillery, inexperienced troops, inaccurate maps and intelligence, overconfidence, inadequate equipment and logistics and tactical deficiencies at all levels.{{sfn|Hart|2007|pp=11–12}}{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=268}} Geography also proved a significant factor. While the Allied forces possessed inaccurate maps and intelligence and proved unable to exploit the terrain to their advantage, the Ottoman commanders were able to utilise the high ground around the Allied landing beaches to position well-sited defences that limited the Allied forces' ability to penetrate inland, confining them to narrow beaches.{{sfn|Doyle|Bennett|1999|p=12}} The campaign's necessity remains the subject of debate,{{sfn|Stevenson|2007|p=189}} and the recriminations that followed were significant, highlighting the schism that had developed between military strategists who felt the Allies should focus on fighting on the Western Front and those that favoured trying to end the war by attacking Germany's &quot;soft underbelly&quot;, its allies in the east.{{sfn|Hart|2007|p=10}}

British and French submarine operations in the Sea of Marmara were the one significant area of success of the Gallipoli Campaign, forcing the Ottomans to abandon the sea as a transport route. Between April and December 1915, a total of nine British and four French submarines had carried out 15 patrols, sinking one battleship, one destroyer, five [[gunboat]]s, 11 [[troop transport]]s, 44 supply ships and 148 sailing vessels at a cost of eight Allied submarines which were sunk in the strait or in the Sea of Marmara.{{sfn|O'Connell|2010|pp=76–78}} During the campaign there was always one British submarine in the Sea of Marmara, sometimes two; in October 1915, there were four Allied submarines in the region.{{sfn|O'Connell|2010|p=73}} ''E2'' left the Sea of Marmara on 2 January 1916, the last British submarine in the region. Meanwhile, four E-class and five B-class submarines remained in the Mediterranean Sea following the evacuation of Helles.{{sfn|O'Connell|2010|p=78}} By this time the Ottoman navy had been all but forced to cease operations in the area, while merchant shipping had also been significantly curtailed. The official German naval historian, Admiral Eberhard von Mantey, later concluded that had the sea lanes of communication been completely severed the Ottoman 5th Army would likely have faced catastrophe. As it was these operations were a source of significant anxiety, posing a constant threat to shipping and causing heavy losses, effectively dislocating Ottoman attempts to reinforce their forces at Gallipoli and shelling troop concentrations and railways.{{sfn|Brenchley|Brenchley|2001|pp=113–114}}

Gallipoli marked the end for Hamilton and Stopford but Hunter-Weston went on to lead VIII Corps on the first day of the [[Battle of the Somme (1916)|Battle of the Somme]].{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=233 and 270}}{{sfn|Neillands|2004|p= 259}} The competence of Australian brigade commanders, John Monash (4th Infantry Brigade) and [[Harry Chauvel]] ([[1st Light Horse Brigade]], New Zealand and Australian Division), was recognised by promotion to divisional and corps command.{{sfn|Grey|2008|pp=100 and 107}}{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=14}} The influence of Kitchener waned after the coalition government was formed in May 1915, partly because of the growing sense of failure in the Dardanelles and culminated in Kitchener being overruled on support for the French at Salonika in early December 1915, when his influence on the Cabinet was at its lowest.{{sfn|Cassar|2004|pp=202–203, 259, 263}} The campaign gave confidence to the Ottomans in their ability to defeat the Allies.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=268}} In [[Mesopotamia]], the Turks surrounded a British expedition at [[Siege of Kut|Kut Al Amara]], forcing their surrender in April 1916.{{sfn|Baldwin|1962|p=94}} Ottoman forces in southern Palestine were poised to launch an attack against the Suez Canal and Egypt.{{sfn|Pick|1990|pp=181 and 209}} Defeat at the [[Battle of Romani]] and lack of materials to complete the military railway, necessary for such an operation, marked the end of that ambition.{{sfn|Pick|1990|p=210}} The optimism which came from the victory at Gallipoli was replaced by a gathering sense of despair and the British remained on the offensive in the Middle East for the rest of the war.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=127}}{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=117}}

[[File:Gallipoli ANZAC Cove Sphinx 2.JPG|thumb|right|The Sphinx, one of the battlefield's most distinctive physical landmarks]]

The lessons of the campaign had a significant impact upon the development of amphibious operational planning,{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=29}} and have since been studied by military planners prior to operations such as the [[Normandy Landings]] in 1944 and during the [[Falklands War]] in 1982.{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=343}} The campaign also influenced US Marine Corps amphibious operations during the [[Pacific War]] and continues to influence US amphibious doctrine.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=29}}{{sfn|Gatchel|1996|p=10}}

According to authors such as Theodore Gatchel, during the [[interwar period]] the campaign &quot;became a focal point for the study of amphibious warfare&quot; in the United Kingdom and United States,{{sfn|Gatchel|1996|p=10}} because, as Glenn Wahlert points out, it involved &quot;all four types of amphibious operations: the raid, demonstration, assault and withdrawal&quot;.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=29}} [[Russell Weigley]] has written that analysis of the campaign before World War II led to &quot;a belief among most of the armed forces of the world&quot; that amphibious assaults could not succeed against modern defences and that arguably this perception continued until the Normandy Landings in June 1944 despite some successful examples of amphibious operations earlier in the war, such as those in [[Allied invasion of Italy|Italy]] and at [[Battle of Tarawa|Tarawa]] and in the [[Gilbert and Marshall Islands campaign|Gilbert Islands]] in the Pacific.{{sfn|Weigley|2005|pp=393–396}} Hart supports Weighley's supposition, writing that although this negative perception prevailed amongst Allied planners in the interwar years, the war situation after 1940 meant that such operations had to be considered. He also argues that despite early successes in North Africa and Italy, it was not until Normandy that the belief that opposed landings could not succeed was completely excised.{{sfn|Hart|2013b|pp=460–462}}

The memory of Gallipoli also weighed heavily upon the Australians during the planning stages of the [[Huon Peninsula campaign]] in late 1943. In September 1943, Australian forces carried out their first opposed amphibious landing since Gallipoli, when they landed at [[Battle of Finschhafen|Finschhafen]] in New Guinea.{{sfn|Coates|1999|p=70}} The landing was hampered by navigational errors and troops came ashore on the wrong beaches but they had been trained with the lessons of Gallipoli in mind, specifically the need to maintain momentum and they quickly reorganised and pushed inland.{{sfn|Dexter|1961|p=454}}

===Political effects===
The failure of the campaign had significant political repercussions in Britain, which began during the battle. Fisher resigned in May after bitter conflict with Churchill. The crisis that followed after the Conservatives learned that Churchill would be staying forced the Prime Minister [[H. H. Asquith]] to end his [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal]] Government and form a [[Coalition government 1915–1916|Coalition Government]] with the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]].{{sfn|Cassar|2004|p=180}} The Asquith government responded to the disappointment and outrage over Gallipoli and Kut by establishing commissions of inquiry into both episodes, which had done much to &quot;destroy its faltering reputation for competence&quot;.{{sfn|Stevenson|2005|pp=121–122}} The [[Dardanelles Commission]] was set up to investigate the failure of the expedition, the first report being issued in 1917, with the final report published in 1919.{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=13}} Following the failure of the Dardanelles expedition, Sir Ian Hamilton, commander of the MEF, was recalled to London in October 1915, ending his military career.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=270}} Churchill was demoted from First Lord of the Admiralty as a condition of Conservative entry to the coalition but remained in the Cabinet in the [[sinecure]] of Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=203}} Churchill resigned in November 1915 and left London for the Western Front, where he commanded an infantry battalion of the [[Royal Scots Fusiliers]] early in 1916.{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=203}}{{sfn|Neillands|2004|p=384}}

Asquith was partly blamed for Gallipoli and other disasters and was overthrown in December 1916, when [[David Lloyd George]] proposed a war council under his authority, with the Conservatives in the coalition threatening to resign unless the plan was implemented. After failure to reach agreement, Lloyd George and then Asquith resigned, followed by Lloyd George becoming Prime Minister.{{sfn|Taylor|1965|pp=103–106}} Lloyd George formed a new government, from which Churchill, active again in the House of Commons from June 1916, was excluded because of Conservative opposition. In the summer of 1917, Churchill was eventually appointed to the cabinet-level post of [[Minister of Munitions]] but not to the [[War cabinet#First World War|War Cabinet]].{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=203}} The Commission's final report was issued in 1919, concluding that with the forces available, success was dependent on the government giving priority to the expedition and leaving the British Expeditionary Force in France to make do. The Commissioners found that Hamilton had been over-optimistic from the beginning and had added to Stopford's difficulties on 8 August 1915. Hamilton emerged from the investigation more favourably than perhaps was justified, partly because he made devious attempts to gain collusion from witnesses and obtain leaks from the Commission's deliberations; Hamilton was never given another army appointment.{{sfn|Travers|2001|pp=297–298}}{{efn|The enormous Gallipoli casualties among Irish soldiers who had volunteered to fight in the British Army was a causal factor in the [[Irish War of Independence]]; as balladeers sang, ''&quot;Twas better to die 'neath an Irish sky than in [[Suvla]] or [[Sedd el Bahr]]&quot;''.{{sfn|Orr|2006|p=}}}}{{cn|date=November 2016}}

===Casualties===
{{See also|List of war cemeteries and memorials on the Gallipoli Peninsula}}

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float: right; clear: right; margin:0 0 1em 1em&quot;
|+Gallipoli casualties (not including illness)
|-
|&amp;nbsp;
!Dead
!Wounded
!Missing&lt;br&gt;&amp;&lt;br /&gt;Prisoners
!Total
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc; text-align:center;&quot;
|'''Ottoman Empire'''{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=94}}||'''56,643'''||'''107,007'''||'''11,178'''||'''174,828'''
|-#B9B9B9&quot; style=&quot;background:#; text-align:center;&quot;
|-style=&quot;background:#e8e8e8; text-align:center;&quot;
|United Kingdom{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|p=484}}||34,072||78,520||7,654||120,246
|-style=&quot;background:#e8e8e8; text-align:center;&quot;
|France{{sfn|Lepetit|Tournyol du Clos|Rinieri|1923|p=549}}||9,798||17,371||–||27,169
|-style=&quot;background:#e8e8e8; text-align:center;&quot;
|Australia{{sfn|Department of Veterans Affairs|p=}}||8,709||19,441||–||28,150
|-style=&quot;background:#e8e8e8; text-align:center;&quot;
| New Zealand{{sfn|Department of Veterans Affairs}}||2,721||4,752||–||7,473
|-style=&quot;background:#e8e8e8; text-align:center;&quot;
| British India{{sfn|Department of Veterans Affairs}}||1,358||3,421||–||4,779
|-style=&quot;background:#e8e8e8; text-align:center;&quot;
| Newfoundland{{sfn|Department of Veterans Affairs}}||49||93||–||142
|-style=&quot;background:#e8e8e8; text-align:center;&quot;
|'''Total Allies'''{{sfn|Aspinall-Oglander|1992|p=484}}{{sfn|Department of Veterans Affairs}}{{sfn|Lepetit|Tournyol du Clos|Rinieri|1923|p=549}}||'''56,707'''||'''123,598'''||'''7,654'''||'''187,959'''
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc; text-align:center;&quot;
|}
Casualty figures for the campaign vary between sources but it is believed that by the time the Gallipoli Campaign ended over {{nowrap|100,000 men}} were dead, including {{nowrap|56,000–68,000 Turkish}} and around {{nowrap|53,000 British}} and French soldiers.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=94}} Carlyon gives {{nowrap|43,000 British}} killed or missing, including {{nowrap|8,709 Australians}}.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=531}} Among the dead were {{nowrap|2,721 New Zealanders}}, about a quarter of those who had initially landed on the peninsula.{{sfn|McGibbon|2000|p=198}} In total there were nearly half a million casualties during the campaign, with the British Official History listing total losses, including sick, as {{nowrap|205,000 British,}} {{nowrap|47,000 French}} and {{nowrap|251,000 Turkish.}} Yet Turkish casualties have been disputed and were likely higher, with another source listing {{nowrap|2,160 officers}} and {{nowrap|287,000 other}} ranks.{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=3}} Included among this may be as many as {{nowrap|87,000 killed.}}{{sfn|McGibbon|2000|p=198}} Many soldiers became sick due to the unsanitary conditions, especially from [[typhoid]], dysentery and [[diarrhea|diarrhoea]]. It is estimated that at least {{nowrap|145,000}} British soldiers became ill during the campaign. Turkish sick are given as {{nowrap|64,000}}.{{sfn|Erickson|2001a|p=94}}

In November 1918, the [[Canterbury Mounted Rifles Regiment|Canterbury Mounted Rifles]] and the [[7th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|7th Light Horse Regiments]], from the [[Anzac Mounted Division]], were sent from [[Rafah|Rafa]] to Gallipoli to &quot;monitor Turkish compliance with the terms of the Armistice&quot;.{{sfn|Kinloch|2007|p=327}} The {{nowrap|900 troopers}}, sailed from Kantara in the transport ship ''Huntscastle'' to Chanak, camping at Camburnu near Kilid Bahr during three winter months when they reconnoitred the Peninsula, identifying graves and inspecting the Ottoman positions.{{sfn|2nd Light Horse Brigade|1918|p=4}} The troopers returned to Egypt on 19 January 1919 less {{nowrap|11 who}} had died and {{nowrap|110 who were sick}} in hospital.{{sfn|Powles|Wilkie|1922|pp=263–265}} Author Lindsay Baly later wrote that it was &quot;a sad mistake to take worn-out men there in such a season&quot;.{{sfn|Baly|2003|p=312}}

There were allegations that Allied forces had attacked or bombarded Ottoman hospitals and hospital ships on several occasions between the start of the campaign and September 1915. By July 1915, there were {{nowrap|25 Ottoman}} hospitals with a total of {{nowrap|10,700 beds}} and three hospital ships in the area. The French Government disputed these complaints through the [[Red Cross]] and the British response was that if it happened then it was accidental. Russia in turn claimed that the Ottomans had attacked two of their hospital ships, the {{ship|Russian hospital ship|Portugal||2}} and the ''Vperiod'' but the Ottoman Government responded that the vessels had been the victims of mines.{{sfn|Taskiran|2005|p=}} No chemical weapons were used at Gallipoli, although the Allies debated their use throughout the campaign and transported quantities of gas to the theatre, which were used against Ottoman troops in the [[Middle Eastern theatre of World War I|Middle Eastern theatre]] two years later, during the [[Second Battle of Gaza|second]] and [[Third Battle of Gaza|third]] battles of [[Gaza City|Gaza]] in 1917.{{sfn|Sheffy|2005|p=278}}{{sfn|Falls|MacMunn|1996|pp=336–337, 341, 349}}

[[File:Greek boys bones Anzac Cove 1919.jpg|thumb|Greek children standing by the bones of soldiers who died during the 1915 Gallipoli Campaign they have collected on Hill 60, Anzac Cove in 1919.]]
The [[Commonwealth War Graves Commission]] (CWGC) is responsible for developing and maintaining permanent cemeteries for all [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] forces—United Kingdom, Australia, New Zealand, India, Newfoundland and others. There are 31 CWGC cemeteries on the Gallipoli peninsula: six at Helles (plus the only solitary grave, that of Lieutenant Colonel [[Charles Doughty-Wylie]] VC, Royal Welch Fusiliers), four at Suvla and {{nowrap|21 at Anzac}}.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=9}} For many of those killed and those who died on hospital ships and were buried at sea, there is no known grave. These men's names are recorded on one of five &quot;memorials to the missing&quot;; the [[Lone Pine Commonwealth War Graves Commission Cemetery|Lone Pine Memorial]] commemorates Australians killed in the Anzac sector, as well as New Zealanders with no known grave or who were buried at sea, while the Lone Pine, [[Hill 60 Commonwealth War Graves Commission Cemetery|Hill 60]] and [[Chunuk Bair]] Memorials commemorate New Zealanders killed at Anzac. The [[Twelve Tree Copse Commonwealth War Graves Commission Cemetery|Twelve Tree Copse Memorial]] commemorates the New Zealanders killed in the Helles sector, while British, Indian and Australian troops who died there are commemorated on the [[Helles Memorial]] at [[Cape Helles]]. British naval casualties who were lost or buried at sea are not recorded on these memorials but are listed on memorials in the United Kingdom.{{sfn|Cape Helles Memorial|nopp=y}}{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|pp=9–10}} There are two more CWGC cemeteries on the Greek island of Limnos, the first in the town of Moudros and the second in the village of Portianou. Limnos was the hospital base for the Allied forces and most of the buried were among the men who died of their wounds.{{sfn|Mudros Moslem Cemetery|nopp=y}}{{sfn|Portianos Military Cemetery|nopp=y}} There is only one French cemetery on the Gallipoli Peninsula, located at Seddulbahir.{{sfn|Travers|2001|p=229}}

There are no large Turkish military cemeteries on the peninsula but there are numerous memorials, the main ones being the [[Çanakkale Martyrs' Memorial]] at Morto Bay, Cape Helles (near 'S' Beach), the Turkish Soldier's Memorial on Chunuk Bair and the memorial and open-air mosque for the 57th Regiment near Quinn's Post (Bomba Sirt). There are a number of Turkish memorials and cemeteries on the Asian shore of the Dardanelles, demonstrating the greater emphasis that Turkish historians place on the victory of 18 March over the subsequent fighting on the peninsula.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=10}}

=== Subsequent operations ===
[[File:Gallipoligrave.jpg|thumb|Gallipoli campaign epitaph at [[Lone Pine Commonwealth War Graves Commission Cemetery|Lone Pine Cemetery]]]]

Allied troops were withdrawn to Lemnos and then to Egypt.{{sfn|Bean|1941|p=905}} French forces (renamed the &quot;Corps Expeditionnaire des Dardanelles&quot; in late October) were subsumed into the Army of the Orient and later employed at Salonika.{{sfn|Dutton|1998|p=155}}{{sfn|Hughes|2005|pp=64–67}} In Egypt, the British Imperial and Dominion troops from the Dardanelles along with fresh divisions from the United Kingdom and those at Salonika, became the Mediterranean Expeditionary Force (MEF), commanded by Lieutenant General Sir [[Archibald Murray]]. They joined the [[Force in Egypt]] to become the strategic reserve for the British Empire, consisting of 13 infantry and mounted divisions with {{nowrap|400,000 men}}. In March 1916, Murray took command of both these forces, forming them into the new [[Egyptian Expeditionary Force#Order of battle April|Egyptian Expeditionary Force]] (EEF) and reorganising the units for service in Europe, Egypt and elsewhere in the Middle East.{{sfn|Keogh|Graham|1955|p=32}}{{sfn|Wavell|1968|p=41}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=22}} While the ANZAC was disbanded, the AIF was expanded with three new Australian divisions being raised and a [[New Zealand Division]] was also formed. These units moved to the Western Front in mid-1916.{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=98}}

The [[British yeomanry during the First World War|British yeomanry]] units that had fought dismounted at Gallipoli were reinforced and reorganised,{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=23}}{{sfn|Griffith|1998|pp=168–169}} forming the [[74th (Yeomanry) Division]] and a portion of the [[75th Division (United Kingdom)|75th Division]].{{sfn|Keogh|Graham|1955|pp=122, 124}}{{sfn|Becke|1937|p=121}} Along with the Australian Light Horsemen and [[New Zealand Mounted Rifles Brigade|New Zealand Mounted Rifles]] remounted and reorganised into the Anzac Mounted Division, infantry from the 52nd (Lowland) Division, 42nd (East Lancashire) Division,{{sfn|Falls|MacMunn|1996|pp=160–271}} 53rd (Welsh) Division and 54th (East Anglian) Division,{{sfn|Grey|2008|pp=99–100, 117}}{{sfn|Dennis et al|2008|pp=405–407}} later joined by additional remounted Australian Light Horsemen and British yeomanry from the [[Imperial Mounted Division|Australian Mounted Division]],{{sfn|Falls|1930|p=274}} participated in the [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign]]. The Egyptian [[Sinai]] was reoccupied in 1916, while [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]] and the northern [[Levant]] were captured from the Ottoman Empire during 1917 and 1918, before the [[Armistice of Mudros]] ended hostilities in the Middle Eastern theatre on 31 October. The Allies subsequently [[occupation of Constantinople|occupied Gallipoli and Constantinople]] and [[partitioning of the Ottoman Empire|partitioned the Ottoman Empire]].{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=345}} The occupation ended in 1923.{{sfn|Simkins|Jukes|Hickey|2003|p=17}}

==Legacy==
[[File:Attaturkswords5.jpg|thumb|left|The memorial at Anzac Cove, commemorating the loss of Ottoman and [[Australian and New Zealand Army Corps|Anzac]] soldiers on the Gallipoli Peninsula]]

The significance of the Gallipoli Campaign is felt strongly in both New Zealand and Australia, despite their being a small minority of the Allied forces; the campaign is regarded in both nations as a &quot;baptism of fire&quot; and had been linked to their emergence as independent states.{{sfn|Williams|1999|p=260}} Approximately 50,000 Australians served at Gallipoli and from 14,000 to 17,000 New Zealanders.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|2001|p=103}}{{sfn|Green|2013|nopp=y}}{{sfn|Ministry for Culture and Heritage|2016|p=1}} It has been argued that the campaign proved significant in the emergence of a unique Australian identity following the war, which has been closely linked to popular conceptualisations of the qualities of the soldiers that fought during the campaign, which became embodied in the notion of an &quot;[[Anzac spirit]]&quot;.{{sfn|Dennis et al|2008|pp=37–42}}

The landing on 25 April is commemorated every year in both countries as &quot;[[Anzac Day]]&quot;. The first iteration was celebrated unofficially in 1916, at churches in Melbourne, Brisbane and London, before being officially recognised as a public holiday in all Australian states in 1923.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=9}} The day also became a national holiday in New Zealand in the 1920s.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=278}} Organised marches by veterans began in 1925, in the same year a service was held on the beach at Gallipoli; two years later the first official dawn service took place at the [[Sydney Cenotaph]]. During the 1980s it became popular for Australian and New Zealand tourists to visit Gallipoli to attend the dawn service there and since then thousands have attended.{{sfn|Wahlert|2008|p=9}} Over 10,000 people attended the 75th anniversary along with political leaders from Turkey, New Zealand, Britain and Australia.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=13}} Dawn services are also held in Australia; in New Zealand, dawn services are the most popular form of observance of this day.{{sfn|Anzac Day Today|nopp=y}} Anzac Day remains the most significant commemoration of military casualties and [[veteran]]s in Australia and New Zealand, surpassing [[Remembrance Day]] ([[Armistice Day]]).{{sfn|Dennis et al|2008|p=32}}

[[File:Wagga Wagga Anzac Day 2015 march (2).jpg|thumb|[[Anzac Day]] march in [[Wagga Wagga]], Australia in 2015]]
In Turkey the battle is thought of as a significant event in the state's emergence, although it is primarily remembered for the fighting that took place around the port of [[Canakkale|Çanakkale]], where the Royal Navy was repulsed in March 1915.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|pp=6–7}} For the Turks, 18 March has a similar significance as 25 April to Australians and New Zealanders, it is not a public holiday but is commemorated with special ceremonies.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=7}} The campaign's main significance to the Turkish people lies in the role it played in the emergence of Mustafa Kemal, who became the first president of the [[Republic of Turkey]] after the war.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=8}} ''&quot;Çanakkale geçilmez&quot;'' (Çanakkale is impassable) became a common phrase to express the state's pride at repulsing the attack and the song &quot;Çanakkale içinde&quot; (''[[A Ballad for Chanakkale]]'') commemorates the Turkish youth who fell during the battle.{{sfn|Eren|2003|p=5}}

In 1971, Scottish-born Australian folk singer-songwriter [[Eric Bogle]] wrote a song called ''[[And the Band Played Waltzing Matilda]]'' which consisted of an account from a young Australian soldier who was maimed during the Gallipoli Campaign. The song has been praised for its imagery, evoking the devastation at the Gallipoli landings. It remains widely popular and is considered by some to be the iconic anti-war song.{{sfn|Dennis et al|2008|p=426}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Williams|first=Lindsay|title=Teachers Notes: And the Band Played Waltzing Matilda by Eric Bogle and Bruce Whatley|url=https://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:zJ6wTny_3Z4J:https://www.allenandunwin.com/documents/teachers-resources/215-andthebandplayedwaltzingmatilda9781743317051tn+&amp;cd=6&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=au|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|accessdate=11 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last= Keane|first=Daniel|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-04-18/eric-bogle-reflects-on-matilda/6398798|title=Eric Bogle: Australia's anti-war balladeer reflects on his Anzac anthem and his upcoming trip to Gallipoli|date=22 April 2015|work=ABC News|publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation|accessdate=11 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Armed Forces Armoury in Corner Brook, Newfoundland &amp; Labrador (which at the time of the First World War was a British colony and suffered 142 casualties during the campaign) is named the Gallipoli Armouries.

==See also==
* ''[[Çanakkale 1915]]'', a Turkish film based on some of the major political events of the Gallipoli Campaign.
* [[Timeline of the Gallipoli Campaign]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
'''Books'''
* {{cite book |title=Military Operations Gallipoli: Inception of the Campaign to May 1915 |last=Aspinall-Oglander |first=Cecil Faber |publisher=Heinemann |year=1929 |edition= |series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |volume=I |location=London |oclc=464479053 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Military Operations Gallipoli: May 1915 to the Evacuation |last=Aspinall-Oglander |first=Cecil Faber |publisher=Heinemann |year=1992 |edition=Imperial War Museum and Battery Press |series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |volume=II |location=London |orig-year=1932 |isbn=978-0-89839-175-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=World War I: An Outline History |last=Baldwin |first=Hanson |publisher=Hutchinson |year=1962 |location=London |oclc=793915761 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Horseman, Pass By: The Australian Light Horse in World War I |last=Baly |first=Lindsay |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |year=2003 |location=East Roseville, NSW |oclc=223425266 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069751/ |title=The Story of Anzac from 4 May 1915, to the Evacuation of the Gallipoli Peninsula |last=Bean |first=Charles |authorlink=Charles Bean |publisher=Australian War Memorial |year=1941|orig-year=1921 |edition=11th |series=[[Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918]] |volume=II |location=Canberra |oclc=39157087 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Order of Battle of Divisions: The 2nd-Line Territorial Force Divisions (57th–69th) with The Home-Service Divisions (71st–73rd) and 74th and 75th Divisions |last=Becke |first=Major Archibald Frank |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1937 |series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |volume=2b |location=London |isbn=978-1-871167-00-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Tagebücher: 1915 bis 1927 |trans_title=Diaries, 1915–1927 |last= Ben-Gavriel |first=Moshe Ya'aqov |publisher=Böhlau |year=1999 |editor-last=Wallas |editor-first=Armin A. |location=Wien |language=German |isbn=978-3-205-99137-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Stoker's Submarine: Australia's Daring Raid on the Dardanellles on the Day of the Gallipoli Landing |last1=Brenchley |first1=Fred |last2=Brenchley |first2=Elizabeth |publisher=Harper Collins |location=Sydney |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-7322-6703-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli: The Fatal Shore |last=Broadbent |first= Harvey |publisher=Viking/Penguin |location=Camberwell, VIC |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-670-04085-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Shadow of the Sultan's Realm: The Destruction of the Ottoman Empire and the Creation of the Modern Middle East |last=Butler |first=Daniel |publisher=Potomac Books |location=Washington |year=2011 |isbn=978-1-59797-496-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=British Battleships 1889–1904 |last=Burt |first=R. A. |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year=1988  |location=Annapolis, MD |isbn=978-0-87021-061-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli: The Final Battles and Evacuation of Anzac |last=Cameron |first=David |publisher=Big Sky |location=Newport, NSW |year=2011 |isbn=978-0-9808140-9-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli |last=Carlyon |first=Les |authorlink=Les Carlyon |publisher=Pan Macmillan |location=Sydney |year=2001 |isbn=0-7329-1089-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Kitchener's War: British Strategy from 1914 to 1916 |last=Cassar |first=George H. |publisher=Potomac Books |location=Lincoln, NE |year=2004 |isbn=1-57488-709-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Bravery Above Blunder: The 9th Australian Division at Finschhafen, Sattelberg and Sio |last=Coates |first=John |year=1999 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, VIC |authorlink=John Coates (general) |isbn=0-19-550837-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Naval Operations |last=Corbett |first=J. S. |authorlink=Julian Corbett |publisher=Longmans |year=2009 |edition=repr. Imperial War Museum and Naval &amp; Military Press |volume=I |location=London |orig-year=1920 |url=https://ia601602.us.archive.org/28/items/navaloperations01corb/navaloperations01corb.pdf |accessdate=27 May 2014 |isbn=978-1-84342-489-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Naval Operations |last=Corbett |first=J. S. |publisher=Longmans |year=2009 |edition=Imperial War Museum and Naval &amp; Military Press |volume=III |location=London |orig-year=1923 |url=https://ia601609.us.archive.org/28/items/navaloperations03corb/navaloperations03corb.pdf |accessdate=27 May 2014 |isbn=978-1-84342-491-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles |last=Coulthard-Clark |first=Chris |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |year=2001 |edition=Second |location=Crows Nest, NSW |isbn=978-1-86508-634-7 |ref=CITEREFCoulthard-Clark2001}}
* {{cite book |url=http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-CowMaor.html |title=The Maoris in the Great War (including Gallipoli) |last=Cowan |first=James |publisher=Whitcombe &amp; Tombs for the Maori Regimental Committee |year=1926 |location=Auckland, NZ |oclc=4203324}}
* {{cite book |title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History |last1=Dennis |first1=Peter |last2=Grey |first2=Jeffrey |last3=Morris |first3=Ewan |last4=Prior |first4=Robin |last5=Bou |first5=Jean |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Melbourne |year=2008 |edition=2nd |isbn=978-0-19-551784-2 |ref=CITEREFDennis_et_al2008}}
* {{cite book |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070205/ |title=The New Guinea Offensives |last=Dexter |first=David |publisher=Australian War Memorial |year=1961 |edition=1st |series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1—Army |volume=VII |location=Canberra, ACT |oclc=2028994 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Politics of Diplomacy: Britain, France and the Balkans in the First World War |last=Dutton |first=David |publisher= I. B. Tauris |location=London |year=1998 |isbn=978-1-86064-112-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Çanakkale Savaş Alanları Gezi Günlüğü |trans_title=Çanakkale War Zone Travel Diary |last=Eren |first=Ramazan |publisher=Eren Books |location=Çanakkale |language=Turkish |year=2003 |isbn=978-975-288-149-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=[[Ordered to Die: A History of the Ottoman Army in the First World War]] |last=Erickson |first=Edward |publisher=Greenwood |year=2001a |orig-year=2000 |location=Westport, CT |isbn=978-0-313-31516-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Ottomans and Armenians: A Study in Counterinsurgency |last=Erickson |first=Edward J. |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=New York |year=2013 |isbn=978-1-137-36220-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Military Operations Egypt &amp; Palestine from the Outbreak of War with Germany to June 1917 |last1=Falls |first1=Cyril |last2=MacMunn |first2=George (maps) |publisher=HMSO |year=1996 |orig-year=1928 |edition=repr. Imperial War Museum and Battery Press |volume=I |location=London |isbn=978-0-89839-241-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |title=Military Operations Egypt &amp; Palestine: From June 1917 to the End of the War |last1=Falls |first1=Cyril |last2=Becke |first2=A. F. (maps) |publisher=HMSO |location=London |others=Part 1 |year=1930 |volume=II |oclc=644354483 |ref=CITEREFFalls1930}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli: The Turkish Story |last1=Fewster|first1=Kevin |last2=Basarin |first2=Vecihi |last3=Basarin |first3=Hatice Hurmuz |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Crows Nest, NSW |year=2003 |orig-year=1985 |isbn=978-1-74114-045-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=No Pleasure Cruise: The Story of the Royal Australian Navy |last=Frame |first=Tom |authorlink=Tom Frame (bishop) |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |year=2004 |location=Crows Nest, NSW |isbn=978-1-74114-233-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=A Peace to End All Peace: The Fall of the Ottoman Empire and the Creation of the Modern Middle East |last=Fromkin |first=David |publisher=Henry Holt |location=New York |year=1989 |isbn=978-0-8050-0857-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=At the Water's Edge: Defending Against the Modern Amphibious Assault |last=Gatchel |first=Theodore L. |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |year=1996 |isbn=978-1-55750-308-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=A Military History of Australia |last=Grey |first=Jeffrey |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Port Melbourne |year=2008 |edition=3rd |isbn=978-0-521-69791-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=British Fighting Methods in the Great War |last=Griffith |first=Paddy |publisher=Routledge |location=London |year=1998 |isbn=978-0-7146-3495-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069924/|title=The Australian Imperial Force in Sinai and Palestine, 1914–1918 |last=Gullett |first=Henry Somer |publisher=Angus and Robertson |year=1941 |orig-year=1923 |edition=10th |series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918 |volume=VII |location=Sydney, NSW |oclc=220901683 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Balkan Breakthrough: The Battle of Dobro Pole 1918 |last=Hall |first=Richard |publisher=Indiana University Press |location=Bloomington |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-253-35452-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=A Naval History of World War I |last=Halpern |first=Paul G. |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |year=1995 |isbn=978-1-55750-352-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli |last=Hart |first=Peter |publisher=Profile Books |location=London |year=2013b |orig-year=2011 |isbn=978-1-84668-161-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=Campaign Series |title=Gallipoli 1915: Frontal Assault on Turkey |last=Haythornthwaite |first=Philip |authorlink=Philip J. Haythornthwaite |publisher=Osprey |year=2004 |orig-year=1991 |number=8 |location=London |isbn=978-0-275-98288-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Oxford Companion to Military History|publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2001 |editor-last=Holmes |editor-first=Richard |editor-link=Richard Holmes (military historian) |location=Oxford |isbn=978-0-19-866209-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Ironclads |last=Hore |first=Peter |publisher=Southwater |year=2006 |location=London |isbn=978-1-84476-299-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The First World War |last=Howard |first=Michael |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-19-285362-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli: A British Historian's View |last=James |first=Robert Rhodes |publisher=Department of History, University of Melbourne |year=1995 |orig-year=1965 |location=Parkville, VIC |isbn=978-0-7325-1219-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069926/ |title=The Royal Australian Navy, 1914–1918 |last=Jose |first=Arthur |publisher=Australian War Memorial |year=1941 |orig-year=1928 |edition=9th |series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918 |volume=IX |location=Canberra |oclc=271462423 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Austro-Hungarian Forces in World War I |last=Jung |first=Peter |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |others=Part 1 |year=2003 |isbn=978-1-84176-594-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The First World War |last=Keegan |first=John |publisher=Pimlico |year=1998 |location=London |isbn=978-0-7126-6645-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Suez to Aleppo |last=Keogh |first=Eustace |last2=Graham |first2=Joan |publisher=Directorate of Military Training (Wilkie) |year=1955 |location=Melbourne |oclc=220029983 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Devils on Horses: In the Words of the Anzacs in the Middle East 1916–19 |last=Kinloch |first=Terry |publisher=Exisle |year=2007 |location=Auckland, NZ |oclc=191258258 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Ataturk: The Rebirth of a Nation |last=Kinross|first=Patrick |publisher=Phoenix |location=London |year=1995 |orig-year=1964 |isbn=978-0-297-81376-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Ministere de la Guerre, Etat-Major de l'Armee, Service Historique, Les Armées Françaises dans la Grande Guerre |trans_title=Ministry of War, Staff of the Army, Historical Service, French Armies in the Great War |last1=Lepetit |first1=Vincent |last2=Tournyol du Clos |first2=Alain |last3=Rinieri |first3=Ilario |publisher=Imprimerie Nationale |year=1923 |edition= |volume=Tome VIII Premier Volume |location=Paris |language=French |oclc=491775878 |ref=CITEREFLepetitTournyol_du_ClosRinieri1923}}
* {{cite book |title=Events That Shaped Australia |last1=Lewis |first1=Wendy |authorlink1=Wendy Lewis |last2=Balderstone |first2=Simon |last3=Bowan |first3=John |publisher=New Holland |year=2006 |location=Frenchs Forest, NSW  |isbn=978-1-74110-492-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Marines Were There: The Story of the Royal Marines in the Second World War |last=Lockhart |first=Sir Robert Hamilton Bruce |publisher=Putnam |year=1950 |location=London |oclc=1999087 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=British Submarines of World War I |last=McCartney |first=Innes |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |year=2008 |isbn=978-1-84603-334-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |editor-last=McGibbon |editor-first=Ian |title=The Oxford Companion to New Zealand Military History |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Auckland, NZ |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-19-558376-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli |last=Moorehead |first=Alan |authorlink=Alan Moorehead |year=1997 |orig-year=1956 |publisher=Wordsworth |location=Ware |isbn=978-1-85326-675-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Great War Generals on the Western Front 1914–1918 |last=Neillands |first=Robin |publisher=Magpie |location=London Books |year=2004 |orig-year=1998 |isbn=978-1-84119-863-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=Carleton Library Series |volume=209 |title=The Fighting Newfoundlander |last=Nicholson |first=Gerald W. L. |publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-7735-3206-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Submarine Operational Effectiveness in the 20th Century (1900–1939) |others=Part One |last=O'Connell |first=John |publisher=Universe |location=New York |year=2010 |isbn=978-1-4502-3689-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |url=http://www.lilliputpress.ie/book/20416777/philip_orr-field_of_bones_an_irish_division_at_gallipoli.html |title=Field of Bones: An Irish Division at Gallipoli |last=Orr |first=Philip |publisher=Lilliput Press |location=Dublin, Ireland |year=2006 |isbn=978-1-84351-065-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Gurkhas: The Inside Story of the World's Most Feared Soldiers |last=Parker |first=John |publisher=Headline Books |location=London |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-7553-1415-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=For Valour: Victoria Cross and Medal of Honor Battles |last=Perrett |first=Bryan |publisher=Cassel Military Paperbacks |location=London |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-304-36698-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Commonwealth Armies: Manpower and Organisation in Two World Wars |last=Perry |first=Frederick |publisher=Manchester University Press |location=Manchester |year=1988 |isbn=978-0-7190-2595-2 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |title=Ottoman Palestine, 1800–1914: Studies in Economic and Social History |last=Pick |first=Walter Pinhas |publisher=Brill Archive |year=1990 |editor-last=Gilbar |editor-first=Gad |location=Leiden |chapter=Meissner Pasha and the Construction of Railways in Palestine and Neighbouring Countries |isbn=978-90-04-07785-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=History of the First World War |last1=Pitt |first1=Barrie |last2=Young |first2=Peter |publisher=B.P.C.  |location=London |year=1970 |volume=III |oclc=669723700 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |url=http://nzetc.victoria.ac.nz/tm/scholarly/tei-WH1-Sina.html |title=The New Zealanders in Sinai and Palestine |last1=Powles |first1=C. Guy |last2=Wilkie |first2=A. |publisher=Whitcombe &amp; Tombs |year=1922 |series=Official History New Zealand's Effort in the Great War |volume=III |location=Auckland, NZ |oclc=2959465 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Archaeology of Destruction |first1=Lucienne |last1=Thys-Şenocak |last2=Aslan |first2=Carolyn |editor-last=Rakoczy |editor-first=Lila |publisher=Cambridge Scholars |location=Newcastle |year=2008 |pages=29–47 |isbn=978-1-84718-624-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Guinness Book of Military Anecdotes |last=Reagan |first=Geoffrey|publisher=Guinness |location=Enfield |year=1992 |isbn=978-0-85112-519-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The First World War: The War to End All Wars |last1=Simkins |first1=Peter |last2=Jukes |first2=Geoffrey |last3=Hickey |first3=Michael |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |year=2003 |isbn=978-1-84176-738-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli |last=Snelling |first=Stephen |publisher=Gloucestershire Sutton |location=Thrupp, Stroud |year=1995 |isbn=978-0-905778-33-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The First World War: To Arms |volume=I |last=Strachan |first=Hew |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=2003 |orig-year=2001 |isbn=978-0-19-926191-8 |ref=CITEREFStrachan2001}}
* {{cite book |title=The Royal Australian Navy |last=Stevens |first=David |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2001  |series=The Australian Centenary History of Defence |volume=III |location=South Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=978-0-19-555542-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=1914–1918: The History of the First World War |last=Stevenson |first=David |publisher=Penguin |location=London |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-14-026817-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=English History 1914–1945 |last=Taylor |first=Alan John Percivale |authorlink=A. J. P. Taylor  |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=1965 |edition=Pelican 1982 |isbn=978-0-19-821715-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Arab Movements in World War I |last=Tauber |first=Eliezer |date=1993 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=978-0-7146-4083-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli 1915 |last=Travers |first=Tim |publisher=Tempus |location=Stroud |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-7524-2551-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Smoke on the Horizon: Mediterranean Fighting, 1914–1918 |last=Usborne |first=Cecil |year=1933 |publisher=Hodder and Stoughton |location=London |oclc=221672642 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=Australian Army Campaign Series |title=Exploring Gallipoli: An Australian Army Battlefield Guide |last=Wahlert |first=Glenn |publisher=Army History Unit |year=2008 |volume=4 |location=Canberra |isbn=978-0-9804753-5-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=A Short History of the British Army |last=Wavell |first=Field Marshal Earl |authorlink=Archibald Wavell, 1st Earl Wavell |publisher=Constable |location=London |year=1968 |orig-year=1933 |editor-last=Sheppard |editor-first=Eric William |edition=4th |chapter=The Palestine Campaigns |oclc=35621223 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Historical Perspectives of the Operational Art |last=Weigley |first=Russell F.|editor1-last=Krause |editor1-first=Michael D. |editor2-last=Phillips |editor2-first=R. Cody |year=2005 |publisher=Center of Military History, United States Army |location=Washington, D.C. |pages=393–414 |chapter=Normandy to Falaise: A Critique of Allied Operational Planning in 1944 |oclc=71603395 |url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/OpArt/us3.htm |accessdate=12 November 2016 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The ANZACS, the Media and the Great War |last=Williams |first=John |publisher=UNSW Press |year=1999  |location=Sydney |isbn=978-0-86840-569-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Last Century of Sea Power: From Port Arthur to Chanak, 1894–1922 |last=Willmott |first=Hedley Paul |publisher=Indiana University Press |location=Bloomington |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-253-00356-0 |ref=harv}}

'''Journals'''
* {{cite journal |last1=Doyle |first1=Peter |last2=Bennett |first2=Matthew |year=1999 |title=Military Geography: The Influence of Terrain in the Outcome of the Gallipoli Campaign, 1915 |journal=The Geographical Journal |location=London |publisher=Royal Geographical Society |volume=165 |issue=1 (March) |pages=12–36 |doi=10.2307/3060508 |issn=0016-7398 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Ekins |first=Ashley |year=2009 |title=Bloody Ridge: The Assault of Lone Pine |magazine=Wartime |location=Canberra |publisher=Australian War Memorial |issue=47 |pages=12–14, 16–18 |issn=1328-2727 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Erickson |first=Edward |year=2001b |title=Strength Against Weakness: Ottoman Military Effectiveness at Gallipoli, 1915 |journal=The Journal of Military History |volume=65 |pages=981–1012 |doi=10.2307/2677626 |issn=1543-7795 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Gilbert |first=Greg |year=2013 |title=Air War Over the Dardanelles |journal=Wartime |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra  |issue=61 |pages=42–47 |issn=1328-2727 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Hart |first=Peter |year=2007 |title=War is Helles: The Real Fight For Gallipoli |journal=Wartime |location=Canberra |publisher=Australian War Memorial |issue=38 |pages=10–12 |issn=1328-2727 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Hart |first=Peter |year=2013a |title=The Day It All Went Wrong: The Naval Assault Before the Gallipoli Landings |journal=Wartime |location=Canberra |publisher=Australian War Memorial |issue=62 |pages=8–13 |issn=1328-2727 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Hughes |first=Matthew |year=2005 |title=The French Army at Gallipoli |journal=The RUSI Journal |volume=153 |issue=3 |pages=64–67 |issn=0307-1847 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Sheffy |first=Yigal |year=2005 |title=The Chemical Dimension of the Gallipoli Campaign: Introducing Chemical Warfare to the Middle East |journal=War in History |publisher=Sage Publications |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=278–317 |doi=10.1191/0968344505wh317oa |issn=1477-0385 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Stevenson |first=Robert |year=2007 |title=The Forgotten First: The 1st Australian Division in the Great War and its Legacy |journal=Australian Army Journal |volume=IV |number=1 |pages=185–199 |oclc=30798241 |ref=harv}}

'''Websites'''
* {{cite web |url=http://www.dva.gov.au/news_archive/Documents/The%20Gallipoli%20Campaign.pdf |title=ANZAC Day 2010 – The Gallipoli Campaign |publisher=Australian Department of Veterans' Affairs |ref=CITEREFDepartment of Veterans Affairs |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130313050857/http://www.dva.gov.au/news_archive/Documents/The%20Gallipoli%20Campaign.pdf |archivedate=13 March 2013 |accessdate=8 April 2010}}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.rsa.org.nz/remem/anzac_today.html |title=Anzac Day Today |date=4 January 2011 |publisher=rsa.org.nz |ref=CITEREFAnzac Day Today |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120204042459/http://www.rsa.org.nz/remem/anzac_today.html |archivedate=4 February 2012}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/records/awm4/10/2/awm4-10-2-47.pdf |title=AWM 4-10-2-47 2nd Light Horse Brigade War Diary November 1918 Appendix 3 |publisher=Headquarters 2nd Light Horse Brigade |format=pdf |ref=CITEREF2nd Light Horse Brigade1918 |accessdate=27 April 2013}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.cwgc.org/search/cemetery_details.aspx?cemetery=76100&amp;mode=1 |title=Cape Helles Memorial to the Missing |ref=CITEREFCape Helles Memorial |work=Commonwealth War Graves Commission |accessdate=3 December 2006}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.mch.govt.nz/sites/default/files/ENUMERATING%20NEW%20ZEALAND%20EXPEDITIONARY%20FORCE%20SERVICE%20INTERIM%20REPORT%20MARCH%202016%20%28D-0651931%29.PDF#overlay-context=new-research-dramatically-increases-numbers-new-zealand-soldiers-gallipoli |title=Enumerating New Zealand Expeditionary Force Service on Gallipoli |year=2016 |website=Manatū Taonga, the Ministry for Culture and Heritage |publisher=Ministry for Culture and Heritage (MCH) and the New Zealand Defence Force (NZDF) |ref=CITEREFMinistry for Culture and Heritage2016 |accessdate=21 March 2016}}
* {{cite web |url=http://ww100.govt.nz/how-many-new-zealanders-served-on-gallipoli |title=How Many New Zealanders Served on Gallipoli? |last=Green |first=David |date=28 August 2013 |access-date=26 November 2015 |ref=CITEREFGreen2013}}
* {{cite news |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=v04EAAAAMBAJ&amp;lpg=PA2&amp;pg=PA28#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true |title=Nazi Shell in Egypt Wounds One of British Empire's Most Fabulous Soldiers |date=17 August 1942 |work=Life |page=28 |ref=CITEREFLife1942 |accessdate=19 November 2011}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.cwgc.org/find-a-cemetery/cemetery/69002/PORTIANOS%20MILITARY%20CEMETERY |title=Portianos Military Cemetery |ref=CITEREFPortianos Military Cemetery |work=Commonwealth War Graves Commission |accessdate=28 April 2013}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.turkishweekly.net/article/52/allied-attacks-on-turkish-patients-wounded.html |title=Allied Attacks on Turkish Patients &amp; Wounded |date=18 March 2005 |ref=CITEREFTaskiran2005 |work=The Journal of the Turkish Weekly |last=Taskiran |first=Cemalettin |accessdate=2 December 2006}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.cwgc.org/find-a-cemetery/cemetery/69006/WEST%20MUDROS%20MOSLEM%20CEMETERY |title=West Mudros Moslem Cemetery |ref=CITEREFMudros Moslem Cemetery |work=Commonwealth War Graves Commission |accessdate=28 April 2013}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |url=https://www.allenandunwin.com/browse/books/general-books/military/Beneath-the-Dardanelles-Vecihi-Basarin-and-Hatice-Basarin-9781741755954 |title=Beneath the Dardanelles: The Australian Submarine at Gallipoli |last1=Basarin |first1=Vecihi |last2=Basarin |first2=Hatice Hurmuz |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Crows Nest, NSW |year=2008 |isbn=978-1-74175-595-4}}
* {{cite book |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069750/ |title=The Story of ANZAC from the Outbreak of War to the End of the First Phase of the Gallipoli Campaign, May 4, 1915 |last=Bean |first=Charles |publisher=Angus and Robertson |year=1941 |orig-year=1921 |edition=11th |series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918 |volume=I |location=Sydney |oclc=220878987}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/events/talks/oration2004.asp |title=Australian War Memorial Anniversary Oration: Gallipoli in a Nation's Remembrance |others=soundtrack and text |last=Carlyon |first=Les |date=11 November 2004 |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=7 December 2008}}
* {{cite book |series=Military History and Policy |number=26 |title=Ottoman Army Effectiveness in World War I: A Comparative Study |last=Erickson |first=Edward J. |editor1-last=Gooch |editor1-first=John |editor2-last=Reid |editor2-first=Brian Holden |publisher=Routledge |location=Abingdon, Oxon |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-203-96456-9}}
* {{cite book |title=The First World War: A Complete History |last=Gilbert |first=Martin |authorlink=Martin Gilbert |publisher=Henry Holt and Co. |location=New York |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-8050-7617-2}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli |last=Hart |first=Peter |publisher=Profile Books |location=London |year=2011 |isbn=978-1-84668-159-2}}
* {{cite book |title=Het Epos van Gallipoli. Feiten, verhalen en mythen over de geallieerde aanval op Turkije tijdens de Eerste Wereldoorlog |language=Dutch |trans-title=The Epic of Gallipoli. Facts, Stories and Myths about the Allied Attack on Turkey during World War I |year=2009 |last1=Kraaijestein |first1=Martin |last2=Schulten |first2=Paul |publisher=Uitgeverij Aspekt |location=Soesterberg |isbn=978-90-5911-758-7}}
* {{cite book |title=An Anzac's Story |last=Kyle |first=Roy |publisher=Penguin |location=Camberwell |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-14-300187-4}}
* {{cite book |title=Damn the Dardanelles!: The Story of Gallipoli |last=Laffin |first=John |publisher=Osprey |year=1980 |isbn=0-85045-350-X |location=London |oclc=7770209}}
* {{cite book |title=The Ottoman Army: Disease and Death on the Battlefield 1914–1918 |last=Özdemir |first=H. |year=2008 |orig-year=2005 |publisher=University of Utah Press |location=Salt Lake City, UT |isbn=978-1-60781-964-6}}
* {{cite book |title=Gallipoli: The Medical War |last=Tyquin |first=Michael |publisher=University of New South Wales Press |location=Sydney, NSW |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-86840-189-8}}
* {{cite book |series=Australian Army Campaigns |volume=16 |title=The Ottoman Defence Against The Anzac Landing |last=Uyar |first=Mesut |publisher=Big Sky |location=Newport, NSW |year=2015 |isbn=978-1-925275-01-8}}
* {{cite book |url=http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WaiNewZ.html |title=The New Zealanders at Gallipoli |last=Waite |first=Fred |publisher=Whitcombe and Tombs |year=1919 |series=Official History New Zealand's Effort in the Great War |volume=I |location=Auckland, NZ |oclc=8003944}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Library resources box|onlinebooks=no|by=no|label=the Gallipoli Campaign|lcheading=World War, 1914–1918—Campaigns—Turkey—Gallipoli Peninsula}}
{{Commons|Gallipoli Campaign}}
* {{Commons category-inline|Allied evacuation of Gallipoli}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/learning/resources/the-gallipoli-campaign|title=Learning resources from the ''Imperial War Museum''}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/system/topicRoot/Gallipoli/|title=Original reports from ''The Times''}}
* {{cite web |url=http://maps.omniatlas.com/europe/19150426/ |title=Map of Europe during the Gallipoli Campaign |work=Omniatlas.com}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.1914-1918.net/despatches.htm |publisher=The Long Long Trail |work=The campaign at the Dardanelles (Gallipoli) |title=Despatches}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.mq.edu.au/about_us/faculties_and_departments/faculty_of_arts/mhpir/modern_history/research/gallipoli_centenary_research_project/ |title=Gallipoli Centenary Research Project |website=Macquarie University}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.history.com/news/winston-churchills-world-war-disaster/ |title=Winston Churchill's World War Disaster}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/media/interactive/gallipoli-casualties-country |title=Gallipoli casualties by country| website=NZ History}}
* {{librivox book | title=Gallipoli Diary | author=John Graham GILLAM}}

{{World War I}}
{{Tentative list of World Heritage Sites in Turkey}}
{{coord|40|22|2|N|26|27|18|E|type:event|display=title}}

{{good article}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Gallipoli Campaign| ]]
[[Category:1915 in the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:Adrianople Vilayet]]
[[Category:Australia–Turkey relations]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Australia]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Austria-Hungary]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving British India]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving Newfoundland]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:Battles of World War I involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Campaigns and theatres of World War I]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1915]]
[[Category:History of Australia (1901–45)]]
[[Category:History of the Royal Marines]]
[[Category:Military history of New Zealand]]
[[Category:Middle Eastern theatre of World War I]]
[[Category:New Zealand–Turkey relations]]
[[Category:Ottoman Empire in World War I]]
[[Category:Winston Churchill]]
[[Category:WPTR/current/Top/inprocess|galipoli]]
[[Category:ANZAC]]
[[Category:World Heritage Site Tentative list]]</text>
      <sha1>2lfgp27srmu9my9akmxrhidzk2t85dm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
