<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>German cruiser Emden</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1781520</id>
    <revision>
      <id>720114660</id>
      <parentid>685197766</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-13T20:39:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mdnavman</username>
        <id>7061136</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */ Added template.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19667">{{about|the third German cruiser to bear the name ''Emden''|the World War I cruisers|SMS Emden}}
{{good article}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:Light Cruiser Emden in China 1931 crop.jpg|300px|Emden]]
|Ship caption=''Emden'' in China, 1931
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|Weimar Republic|naval}} {{shipboxflag|Nazi Germany|naval}}
|Ship name=''Emden''
|Ship namesake=[[Emden]]
|Ship ordered=1921
|Ship awarded=
|Ship builder=
|Ship original cost=
|Ship yard number=
|Ship way number=
|Ship laid down=8 December 1921
|Ship launched=6 January 1925
|Ship sponsor=
|Ship christened=
|Ship completed=
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=15 October 1925
|Ship recommissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship reclassified=
|Ship refit=
|Ship struck=
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship homeport=
|Ship identification=
|Ship motto=
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honours=
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=Scuttled 3 May 1945, scrapped 1949
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class=
|Ship type=
|Ship displacement=*Standard: {{convert|5300|LT|MT|abbr=on}}
*Full load: {{convert|6990|LT|MT|abbr=on}}
|Ship length={{convert|155.1|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|14.2|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|5.3|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship power=
|Ship propulsion= Steam turbines, 2 shafts, 10 boilers, {{convert|46500|shp|abbr=on}}
|Ship speed={{convert|29.5|kn}}
|Ship range={{convert|6700|nmi|abbr=on}} at {{convert|15|kn}}
|Ship boats=6
|Ship complement=*19–30 officers
*445–653 enlisted men
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=*8 × {{convert|15|cm|abbr=on}} guns
*3 × {{convert|8.8|cm|abbr=on}} guns
*4 × {{convert|50|cm|abbr=on}} torpedo tubes
|Ship armor=*[[Belt armor|Belt]]: {{convert|50|mm|abbr=on}}
*Deck: {{convert|40|mm|abbr=on}}
*[[Conning tower]]: {{convert|100|mm|abbr=on}}
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''''Emden''''' was a [[light cruiser]] built by the [[Reichsmarine]] in the early 1920s. She was the only ship of her class and was the first large warship built in Germany after the end of [[World War I]]. She was built at the [[Kriegsmarinewerft Wilhelmshaven|''Reichsmarinewerft'']] in [[Wilhelmshaven]]; her keel was laid in December 1921 and her completed hull was launched in January 1925. ''Emden'' was commissioned into the German fleet in October 1925. Her design was heavily informed by the restrictions of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] and the dictates of the Allied disarmament commission. She was armed with a main battery of surplus {{convert|15|cm|abbr=on}} guns left over from World War I, mounted in single [[gun turret]]s, as mandated by the Allied powers. She had a top speed of {{convert|29|kn|lk=in}}.

''Emden'' spent the majority of her career as a [[training ship]]; in the inter-war period, she conducted several world cruises to train naval cadets. At the outbreak of war, she laid [[Naval mine|minefields]] off the German coast and was damaged by a British [[bomber]] that crashed into her. She participated in the [[Operation Weserübung|invasion of Norway]] in April 1940, and then resumed training duties in the Baltic Sea. These lasted with minor interruptions until September 1944, when she was deployed to Norway to serve as the [[flagship]] of the minelaying forces there. In January 1945, she carried the disinterred remains of [[Paul von Hindenburg]] from East Prussia to [[Pillau]], to prevent his remains from falling into the hands of the advancing Soviet Army. While undergoing repairs in [[Kiel]], ''Emden'' was badly damaged by British bombers and later run aground outside the harbor and was blown up. The wreck was ultimately broken up in 1949.

==Design==
According to Article 181 of the [[Treaty of Versailles]], the treaty that ended [[World War I]], the German Navy was permitted only six light cruisers. Article 190 limited new cruiser designs to {{convert|6000|LT}} and prohibited new construction until the vessel to be replaced was at least twenty years old.&lt;ref&gt;See: [[s:Treaty of Versailles 1919|Treaty of Versailles]] Section II: Naval Clauses, Articles 181 and 191&lt;/ref&gt; Design work on the first new light cruiser, ordered as &quot;''Ersatz'' {{SMS|Niobe||2}}&quot;, began in 1921.&lt;ref name=G118&gt;Gröner, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; The ship was intended for long-range overseas service, so the designers placed emphasis on a large cruising radius and capacious crew accommodation spaces.&lt;ref name=Wa12/&gt; The designers wanted to use a main battery of eight {{convert|15|cm|adj=on|sp=us}} guns in four dual mounts, but the [[Allies of World War I|Allied powers]] insisted on single [[gun turret]]s. This arrangement placed four guns [[amidships]], which reduced the power of her broadside, as only six guns could fire on either side, as opposed to eight.&lt;ref name=W9&gt;Williamson, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

The ship was based on cruiser designs from late in World War I, primarily due to personnel shortages in the design staff and the closure of the Navy's experimental institute. Nevertheless, the ship incorporated major advances over the earlier designs, including large-scale use of [[welding]] in her construction and a significantly more efficient propulsion system that gave her a cruising radius fifty percent larger than that of the older ships.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt; ''Emden'' was laid down at the [[Kriegsmarinewerft Wilhelmshaven|''Reichsmarinewerft'']] in [[Wilhelmshaven]] on 8 December 1921 and launched on 7 January 1925. She was commissioned into the fleet nine months later, on 15 October 1925.&lt;ref name=C229&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 229&lt;/ref&gt;

===General characteristics===
''Emden'' was {{convert|150.5|m|sp=us}} [[length at the waterline|long at the waterline]] and {{convert|155.1|m|abbr=on}} [[length overall|long overall]]. She had a [[Beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert| 14.2|m|abbr=on}} and a designed [[Draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|5.3|m|abbr=on}}; at [[Standard displacement#Standard displacement|standard load]], the draft was {{convert|5.15|m|abbr=on}}, and at [[Full-load displacement#Full or deep load or loaded displacement|combat load]] the draft increased to {{convert|5.93|m|abbr=on}}. Her designed displacement was {{convert|5960|LT|MT}}, with {{convert|5300|LT|MT}} standard and {{convert|6990|LT|MT}} combat displacements. Her hull was constructed with longitudinal steel frames and incorporated seventeen [[watertight compartment]]s and a [[double bottom]] that extended for 56&amp;nbsp;percent of the length of the keel.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt; She had a waterline [[armored belt]] that was {{convert|50|mm|abbr=on}} thick; her armored deck was {{convert|20|to|40|mm|abbr=on}} thick, and her [[conning tower]] had {{convert|100|mm|abbr=on}} thick sides.&lt;ref name=W9/&gt;

The ship had a standard crew of nineteen officers and 464 enlisted men. While serving on cadet training cruises, her crew numbered twenty-nine officers and 445 enlisted, with 162 cadets. After 1940, her standard crew was increased to twenty-six officers and 556 enlisted, and after being reduced to a [[training ship]], her crew numbered thirty officers and 653 enlisted men. ''Emden'' carried six boats. The German Navy regarded the ship as a good sea boat, with slight lee helm and gentle motion in a swell. The cruiser was maneuverable, but was slow going into a turn. Steering was controlled by a single large rudder. She lost speed only slightly in a head sea, but lost up to sixty percent in hard turns. She had a [[metacentric height]] of {{convert|.79|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt;

===Machinery===
[[File:Diesel engine from the &quot;Emden&quot; (6092678477).jpg|thumb|A replacement engine built for ''Emden'', displayed at the [[Sinsheim Auto &amp; Technik Museum]] (2011 picture)]]
''Emden'' was powered by two sets of [[Brown, Boveri &amp; Cie|Brown, Boverie &amp; Co.]] geared [[steam turbine]]s; they drove a pair of three-bladed screws that were {{convert|3.75|m|abbr=on}} in diameter. Steam was provided by four coal-fired Marine-type boilers and six oil-fired Marine boilers divided into four boiler rooms. The engines were rated at {{convert|46500|shp|lk=in}} and a top speed of {{convert|29|kn|lk=in}}. On speed trials, her engines reached {{convert|45900|shp|abbr=on}} and a maximum of {{convert|29.4|kn}}. The ship was designed to carry {{convert|300|MT|LT|0}} of coal, though additional space could accommodate up to {{convert|875|MT|LT}}. Oil capacity was {{convert|200|MT|LT|0}} as designed, and up to {{convert|1170|MT|LT}} in additional fuel bunkers. This gave the ship a cruising radius of {{convert|6700|nmi|lk=in}} at {{convert|12|kn}}. At {{convert|18|kn}}, her range fell to {{convert|5200|nmi|abbr=on}}. Electrical power was supplied by two systems of three generators each, with a total combined output of {{convert|420|kW|lk=in}} at 220&amp;nbsp;[[Volt]]s.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt;

===Armament===
The ship's main battery was to have been eight 15&amp;nbsp;cm SK L/55 guns in twin turrets, but the Allied disarmament authority refused to permit this armament. Instead, she was equipped with existing stocks of [[15 cm SK L/45]] guns in single turrets.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt; The guns were C/16 models; they fired a {{convert|45|kg|abbr=on}} shell at a [[muzzle velocity]] of {{convert|835|m/s|sp=us}}.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, p. 143&lt;/ref&gt; They could elevate to 40&amp;nbsp;degrees and had a maximum range of {{convert|17600|m|abbr=on}}. The eight guns were supplied with a total of 960 rounds of ammunition. ''Emden'' was also equipped with two [[8.8 cm SK L/45 naval gun|8.8&amp;nbsp;cm SK L/45]] anti-aircraft guns, and a third was later added. These guns had between 900 and 1,200 rounds of ammunition in total. As designed, she was to have carried eight deck-mounted {{convert|50|cm|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s in dual launchers, but only four tubes were fitted as built. In 1934, these were replaced with more powerful {{convert|53.3|cm|abbr=on}} tubes. The ship carried twelve torpedoes.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt;

In 1938, the ship's anti-aircraft battery was strengthened. She received two and later four [[3.7 cm SK C/30]] guns and up to eighteen [[2 cm Flak 30/38/Flakvierling|2&amp;nbsp;cm Flak]] guns. The capacity to carry 120 [[naval mine|mines]] was also added. In 1942, two of the four torpedo launchers were removed, and she was rearmed with a new model of 15&amp;nbsp;cm gun.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt; This gun was the [[15 cm Tbts KC/36 naval gun|Tbts KC/36]] model, and was designed for use on destroyers. It fired a slightly smaller {{convert|40|kg|abbr=on}} shell at a higher muzzle velocity—{{convert|875|m/s|abbr=on}}. The gun could elevate to 47&amp;nbsp;degrees for a maximum range of {{convert|23500|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 243&lt;/ref&gt; By 1945, the ship's anti-aircraft battery consisted of nine 3.7&amp;nbsp;cm guns and six 2&amp;nbsp;cm guns.&lt;ref name=G118/&gt;

==Service history==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-00703, Kiel, Leichter Kreuzer &quot;Emden&quot; III.jpg|thumb|''Emden'' in port, in 1928]]
After her commissioning in 1925, ''Emden'' was used as a training ship for naval cadets. She made a series of world cruises to show the flag in the pre-war period and trained large numbers of cadets. In 1925–1926, a series of modifications were made to the ship, including increasing the height of the second funnel and the installation of a [[flying bridge]] at the base of the battle mast, which was shortened by {{convert|7|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=W911&gt;Williamson, pp. 9–11&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Lothar von Arnauld de la Perière]] commanded the ship from September 1928 until October 1930.&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr &amp; Steinmetz, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1933, her coal-fired boilers were replaced with more efficient oil-fired boilers. The next year, another series of modifications was made, including reducing the main mast and funnels in height and the installation of a small crane on the starboard side of the main mast. In September 1934, [[Karl Dönitz]], the future commander of the [[Kriegsmarine]], took command of the ship and remained in the position until September 1935. ''Emden'' went into dock for further modifications in 1936; the ship's masts were again reworked, and the third 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm anti-aircraft gun was added.&lt;ref name=W911/&gt; [[Leopold Bürkner]] commanded the ''Emden'' from 30 July 1937 to 15 June 1938.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |ref={{harvid|Leopold Bürkner: Wehrmacht History}}|accessdate=2013-10-18
 |title=Leopold Bürkner|work=Wehrmacht History |url=http://www.wehrmacht-history.com/personnel/b/buerkner-leopold-kriegsmarine-personnel-file.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the outbreak of [[World War II]] in September 1939, a [[degaussing]] coil was installed just above the waterline to protect the ship from magnetic mines.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; Her first wartime operation saw her participating in laying a minefield off the German coast in the North Sea on 3 September. She conducted the operation with the other light cruisers [[German cruiser Nürnberg|''Nürnberg'']], [[German cruiser Leipzig|''Leipzig'']], [[German cruiser Köln|''Köln'']], and [[German cruiser Königsberg|''Königsberg'']] and sixteen [[destroyer]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Rohwer, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; After laying her first set of mines, she returned to [[Wilhelmshaven]] to restock her mines. While moored in the harbor, she was attacked by British bombers on 4 September; German anti-aircraft gunners shot down four of the five [[Bristol Blenheim|Blenheim bombers]], one of which inadvertently crashed into the ship. Twenty-nine men were killed or wounded in the crash.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rohwer, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv DVM 10 Bild-23-63-05, Leichter Kreuzer &quot;Emden&quot;.jpg|thumb|left|''Emden'' steaming at low speed in 1935]]

''Emden'' next participated in the [[Operation Weserübung|invasion of Norway]]  (''Operation Weserübung''). She was part of the ill-fated ''Kriegsschiffgruppe 5'', tasked with seizing [[Oslo]]. The group's flagship, the heavy cruiser [[German cruiser Blücher|''Blücher'']], was sunk by the [[Oscarsborg Fortress|Oscarsborg]] coastal fortress inside [[Oslofjord]] and the heavy cruiser [[German cruiser Deutschland|''Lützow'']] was damaged when the squadron attempted to steam up the fjord into Oslo harbor to land troops. After the loss of ''Blücher'', ''Emden'' and the heavy cruiser [[German cruiser Deutschland|''Lützow'']] disembarked their troops further down the fjord. After the ground troops had occupied Oslo, ''Emden'' entered the port serving as a joint communications center to coordinate Kriegsmarine, [[Wehrmacht]], and [[Luftwaffe]] operations. After the conquest of Norway was complete, ''Emden'' returned to Germany and served as a training ship. This lasted until September 1941.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, pp. 11–12&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1941, ''Emden'' was assigned to an operation in the [[Gulf of Riga]] to provide gunfire support to German troops.&lt;ref name=W12&gt;Williamson, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; On the 16th, she was operating off [[Hiiumaa|Dagö]] with ''Leipzig'' and three [[torpedo boat]]s; the ships came under fire from Soviet coastal batteries, but were undamaged. A group of four Soviet torpedo boats also made an unsuccessful attack on the German squadron.&lt;ref&gt;Rohwer, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; ''Emden'' was then assigned to the Baltic Fleet, centered on the newly commissioned [[battleship]] [[German battleship Tirpitz|''Tirpitz'']]; the Baltic Fleet was tasked with preventing the Soviet Navy from breaking out of the Baltic. ''Emden'' and ''Leipzig'' were the core of the southern group, which was based in [[Liepāja|Libau]]. The fleet remained on station only briefly, and by 29 September, the ships were recalled to [[Gotenhafen]].&lt;ref&gt;Rohwer, pp. 102–103&lt;/ref&gt;

After returning to Germany, ''Emden'' was assigned to training duties once again. She continued in this role until June 1942, by which time a major overhaul was in order. The refit was completed in Wilhelmshaven, after which ''Emden'' returned to training cadets. In September 1944, she was deployed to Norway, where she served as the [[flagship]] of the minelaying forces there. While in Norway, she participated in several minelaying operations through October, when she was transferred to convoy escort duty; her primary task was to protect convoys in and out of Oslo. This lasted until December, when she ran aground in the Oslofjord off the island of Flateguri. Her guns were removed while repairs were partially effected in the [[Schichau-Werke]]. Before departing East Prussia, she took on the remains of [[Paul von Hindenburg]] and his wife to carry them to mainland Germany. They had been disinterred to prevent them from falling into the hands of the advancing Soviet Army. The repair work on the ship was not yet completed, and so she was towed to [[Pillau]], where the Hindenburgs' remains were taken off.&lt;ref name=W12/&gt; ''Emden''{{'}}s engines were put back in working order, though she was incapable of reaching top speed, and her guns were reinstalled.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, pp. 12–13&lt;/ref&gt;

''Emden'' departed Pillau on 1 February, bound for Kiel. She arrived on 7 February 1945 and was taken into the [[Deutsche Werke]] dockyard to complete the necessary repairs. British bombers attacked the ship twice and damaged her badly. The ship was listing heavily, and so on 14 April, she was towed out into [[Heikendorfer Bay]] and run aground. The Germans then blew her up on 3 May to prevent the Allies from capturing the ship.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; The wreck was ultimately broken up for scrap in 1949.&lt;ref name=Wa12&gt;Ward, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; Her bow ornament is currently on display in the [[Deutsches Museum]] in [[Munich]].&lt;ref&gt;Gröner, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{commons category|Emden (ship, 1925)}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==References==
* {{cite book|last=Campbell|first=John|title=Naval Weapons of World War II|year=1985|location=London, UK|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|isbn=0-87021-459-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Friedman|first=Norman|title=Naval Weapons of World War I|year=2011|location=Annapolis, MD|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn= 978-1-84832-100-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Gardiner|first=Robert|last2=Chesneau|first2=Roger|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1922–1946|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=1980|isbn=0-87021-913-8|location=Annapolis, MD}}
*{{Cite book |last=Gröner|first=Erich|title=German Warships: 1815–1945|year=1990|location=Annapolis, MD|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-87021-790-9}}
* {{Cite book |last1=Hildebrand|first1=Hans H.|last2=Röhr|first2=Albert|last3=Steinmetz|first3=Hans-Otto|title=Die Deutschen Kriegsschiffe|volume=3|year=1993|location=[[Ratingen]], Germany|publisher=Mundus Verlag|asin=B003VHSRKE |asin-tld=de|oclc=}}
*{{cite book |author=Rohwer, Jürgen|authorlink=Jürgen Rohwer|title=Chronology of the War at Sea, 1939–1945: The Naval History of World War Two |publisher=US Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, MD|year=2005|isbn=1-59114-119-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Showell|first=Jak Mallmann|title=The German Navy Handbook 1939–1945|year=1999|publisher=[[Sutton Publishing]]|location=Gloucestershire, UK|isbn=978-0-7509-1556-4}}
*{{cite book |last=Ward|first=John|title=Ships of World War II|publisher=MBI Pub. Co.|location=Osceola, WI|year=2000|isbn=0-7603-0935-3}}
*{{Cite book |last=Williamson|first=Gordon|title=German Light Cruisers 1939–1945|year=2003|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=1-84176-503-1|location=Oxford, UK}}

{{WWIIGermanShips}}
{{May 1945 shipwrecks}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Emden}}
[[Category:Cruisers of the Reichsmarine]]
[[Category:Ships built in Wilhelmshaven]]
[[Category:1925 ships]]
[[Category:Cruisers of the Kriegsmarine]]
[[Category:World War II cruisers of Germany]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in May 1945]]</text>
      <sha1>kzldeggk6dnqm5m6q8nri6c31k7s7xi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
