<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Gone with the Wind (film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2804704</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751217911</id>
      <parentid>751140943</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-24T03:45:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Markhh</username>
        <id>2423558</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 751140943 by [[Special:Contributions/107.77.220.156|107.77.220.156]] ([[User talk:107.77.220.156|talk]]) Please, do not change the wording of a direct quote.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="109346">{{for|the Afghan film|Gone with the Wind (2005 film)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2015}}
{{Infobox film
| name    = Gone with the Wind
| image   = Poster - Gone With the Wind 01.jpg
| alt     = A film poster showing a man and a woman in a passionate embrace.
| caption = Theatrical pre-release poster
| director = [[Victor Fleming]]
| producer = [[David O. Selznick]]
| screenplay = [[Sidney Howard]]
| based on = {{Based on|''[[Gone with the Wind (novel)|Gone with the Wind]]''|[[Margaret Mitchell]]}}
| starring = {{plainlist|
* [[Clark Gable]]
* [[Vivien Leigh]] &lt;!-- Regardless of where Leigh appears on the posters, she receives second billing in the film itself --&gt;
* [[Leslie Howard (actor)|Leslie Howard]]
* [[Olivia de Havilland]]
}}
| music   = [[Max Steiner]]
| cinematography = [[Ernest Haller]]
| editing = {{plainlist|
* [[Hal C. Kern]]
* [[James E. Newcom]]
}}
| production companies = {{Plainlist|
* [[Selznick International Pictures]]
* [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]]
}}
| distributor = [[Loews Cineplex Entertainment|Loew's Inc.]]{{refn|Loews was the parent company of MGM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Gomery |first1=Douglas |last2=Pafort-Overduin |first2=Clara |title=Movie History: A Survey |edition=2nd |year=2011 |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |isbn=9781136835254 |page=[https://books.google.com.my/books?id=s0PP2Gm8xNcC&amp;pg=PA144&amp;q=Loews+144&amp;hl=en#v=snippet&amp;q=Loews%20144&amp;f=false 144]}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}
| released = {{Film date|1939|12|15|[[Atlanta]] premiere}} &lt;!--Please do not add the January 17, 1940 release date. IMDB list this date but it is not clear what it is for. The film was already playing its roadshow engagements by this point and did not go on general release until 1941. --&gt;
| runtime = {{plainlist|
* 221&amp;nbsp;minutes
* 234–238&amp;nbsp;minutes (with [[overture]], [[intermission]], [[entr'acte]], and exit music)
}}
| country  = United States
| language = English
| budget   = $3.85 million
| gross    = &gt;$390 million&lt;!-- Please do not alter this figure without discussing it at the talk page first. It is not known exactly how much GWTW grossed worldwide, but all sources agree it was in excess of $390 million. --&gt;
}}
'''''Gone with the Wind''''' is a 1939 American [[Epic film|epic]] [[Historical film|historical]] [[romance film]] adapted from [[Margaret Mitchell]]'s 1936 novel ''[[Gone with the Wind (novel)|Gone with the Wind]]''. It was produced by [[David O. Selznick]] of [[Selznick International Pictures]] and directed by [[Victor Fleming]]. Set in the [[American South]] against the backdrop of the [[American Civil War]] and [[Reconstruction Era of the United States|Reconstruction era]], the film tells the story of [[Scarlett O'Hara]], the strong-willed daughter of a Georgia plantation owner, from her romantic pursuit of [[Ashley Wilkes]], who is married to his cousin, [[Melanie Hamilton]], to her marriage to [[Rhett Butler]]. The leading roles are portrayed by [[Vivien Leigh]] (Scarlett), [[Clark Gable]] (Rhett), [[Leslie Howard (actor)|Leslie Howard]] (Ashley), and [[Olivia de Havilland]] (Melanie).

Production was difficult from the start. Filming was delayed for two years due to Selznick's determination to secure Gable for the role of Rhett Butler, and the &quot;search for Scarlett&quot; led to 1,400 women being interviewed for the part. The original screenplay was written by [[Sidney Howard]], but underwent many revisions by several writers in an attempt to get it down to a suitable length. The original director, [[George Cukor]], was fired shortly after filming had begun and was replaced by Fleming, who in turn was briefly replaced by [[Sam Wood]] while Fleming took some time off due to exhaustion.

The film received positive reviews upon its release in December 1939, although some reviewers found it dramatically lacking and bloated. The casting was widely praised and many reviewers found Leigh especially suited to her role as Scarlett. At the [[12th Academy Awards]], it received ten [[Academy Award]]s (eight competitive, two honorary) from thirteen nominations, including wins for [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]], [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]] (Fleming), [[Academy Award for Best Adapted Screenplay|Best Adapted Screenplay]] (posthumously awarded to Sidney Howard), [[Academy Award for Best Actress|Best Actress]] (Leigh), and [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actress|Best Supporting Actress]] ([[Hattie McDaniel]], becoming the first African-American to win an Academy Award). It set records for the total number of wins and nominations at the time. The film was immensely popular, becoming the [[Timeline of highest-grossing films|highest-earning film made up to that point]], and retained the record for over a quarter of a century. When [[Real versus nominal value (economics)|adjusted for monetary inflation]], it is still the [[Highest-grossing films adjusted for inflation|most successful film in box-office history]].

''Gone with the Wind'' has been criticized as historical revisionism glorifying slavery, but nevertheless, it has been credited for triggering changes to the way African-Americans are depicted cinematically. It was re-released periodically throughout the 20th century and became ingrained in popular culture. The film is regarded as one of [[List of films considered the best|the greatest films of all time]]; it has placed in the top ten of the [[American Film Institute]]'s list of [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies (10th Anniversary Edition)|top 100 American films]] since the list's [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies|inception in 1998]], and in 1989, the United States [[Library of Congress]] selected it for preservation in the [[National Film Registry]].

==Plot==
;Part 1
On the eve of the [[American Civil War]] in 1861, [[Scarlett O'Hara]] lives at [[Tara (plantation)|Tara]], her family's cotton [[plantations in the American South|plantation]] in [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], with her parents and two sisters. Scarlett learns that [[Ashley Wilkes]]—whom she secretly loves—is to be [[Cousin marriage|married to his cousin]], [[Melanie Hamilton]], and the engagement is to be announced the next day at a barbecue at Ashley's home, the nearby plantation [[Twelve Oaks]].

At the Twelve Oaks party, Scarlett secretly declares her feelings to Ashley, but he rebuffs her by responding that he and Melanie are more compatible. Scarlett is incensed when she discovers another guest, [[Rhett Butler]], has overheard their conversation; a smitten Rhett promises Scarlett he will keep her secret. The barbecue is disrupted by the declaration of war and the men rush to enlist. As Scarlett watches Ashley kiss Melanie goodbye, Melanie's younger brother Charles proposes to her. Although she does not love him, Scarlett consents and they are married before he leaves to fight.
[[File:Gone With the Wind Poster 1939.jpg|thumb|Scarlett and Rhett at the charity dance]]
Scarlett is widowed when Charles dies from a bout of [[pneumonia]] and [[measles]] while serving in the [[Confederate Army]]. Scarlett's mother sends her to the Hamilton home in [[Atlanta]] to cheer her up, although the O'Haras' outspoken housemaid Mammy tells Scarlett she knows she is going there only to wait for Ashley's return. Scarlett, who should not attend a party while in mourning, attends a charity bazaar in Atlanta with Melanie where she runs into Rhett again, now a [[blockade runner]] for the [[Confederate States of America|Confederacy]]. Celebrating a [[Battle of Chancellorsville|Confederate victory]] and to raise money for the Confederate war effort, gentlemen are invited to bid for ladies to dance with them. Rhett makes an inordinately large bid for Scarlett and, to the disapproval of the guests, she agrees to dance with him.

The tide of war turns against the Confederacy after the [[Battle of Gettysburg]] in which many of the men of Scarlett's town are killed. Scarlett makes another unsuccessful appeal to Ashley while he is visiting on Christmas [[furlough]], although they do share a private and passionate kiss in the parlor on Christmas Day, just before he returns to war.

Eight months later, as the city is besieged by the [[Union Army]] in the [[Atlanta Campaign]], Scarlett and her young house servant Prissy must deliver Melanie's baby without medical assistance after she goes into premature labor. Afterwards, Scarlett calls upon Rhett to take her home to Tara with Melanie, her baby, and Prissy; he collects them in a horse and wagon, but once out of the city chooses to go off to fight, leaving Scarlett and the group to make their own way back to Tara. Upon her return home, Scarlett finds Tara deserted, except for her father, her sisters, and two former slaves: Mammy and Pork. Scarlett learns that her mother has just died of [[typhoid fever]] and her father has become incompetent. With Tara pillaged by Union troops and the fields untended, Scarlett vows she will do anything for the survival of her family and herself.

;Part 2
As the O'Haras work in the cotton fields, Scarlett's father is killed after he is thrown from his horse in an attempt to chase away a [[scalawag]] from his land. With the defeat of the Confederacy Ashley also returns, but finds he is of little help at Tara. When Scarlett begs him to run away with her, he confesses his desire for her and kisses her passionately, but says he cannot leave Melanie. Unable to pay the taxes on Tara implemented by [[Reconstruction Era|Reconstructionists]], Scarlett dupes her younger sister Suellen's fiancé, the middle-aged and wealthy mill owner Frank Kennedy, into marrying her, by saying Suellen got tired of waiting and married another beau.

Frank, Ashley, Rhett and several other accomplices make a night raid on a [[shanty town]] after Scarlett is attacked while driving through it alone, resulting in Frank's death. With Frank's funeral barely over, Rhett proposes to Scarlett and she accepts. They have a daughter whom Rhett names Bonnie Blue, but Scarlett, still pining for Ashley and chagrined at the perceived ruin of her figure, lets Rhett know that she wants no more children and that they will no longer share a bed.

One day at Frank's mill, Scarlett and Ashley are seen embracing by Ashley's sister, India, and harboring an intense dislike of Scarlett she eagerly spreads rumors. Later that evening, Rhett, having heard the rumors, forces Scarlett to attend a birthday party for Ashley; incapable of believing anything bad of her beloved sister-in-law, Melanie stands by Scarlett's side so that all know that she believes the gossip to be false. After returning home from the party, Scarlett finds Rhett downstairs drunk, and they argue about Ashley. Rhett kisses Scarlett against her will, stating his intent to have sex with her that night, and carries the struggling Scarlett to the bedroom. The next day, Rhett apologizes for his [[marital rape|behavior]] and offers Scarlett a divorce, which she rejects, saying that it would be a disgrace. When Rhett returns from an extended trip to London Scarlett informs him that she is pregnant, but an argument ensues which results in her falling down a flight of stairs and suffering a [[miscarriage]]. As she is recovering, tragedy strikes when Bonnie dies while attempting to jump a fence with her pony. 

Scarlett and Rhett visit Melanie, who has suffered complications arising from a new pregnancy, on her deathbed. As Scarlett consoles Ashley, Rhett returns to Tara; realizing that Ashley only ever truly loved Melanie, Scarlett dashes after Rhett to find him preparing to leave for good. She pleads with him, telling him she realizes now that she has loved him all along and that she never really loved Ashley, but Rhett says that with Bonnie's death went any chance of reconciliation. Scarlett begs him to stay but Rhett [[Frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn|rebuffs her]] and walks out the door and into the early morning fog, leaving her weeping on the staircase and vowing to one day win back his love.

==Cast==
Despite receiving top-[[Billing (filmmaking)|billing]] in the [[opening credits]], Gable—along with Leigh, Howard, and de Havilland who receive second, third and fourth billing respectively—has a relatively low placing in the [[cast list]], due to its unusual structure. Rather than ordered by conventional billing, the cast is broken down into three sections: the Tara plantation, Twelve Oaks, and Atlanta. The cast's names are ordered according to the social rank of the characters; therefore Thomas Mitchell, who plays Gerald O'Hara, leads the cast list as the head of the O'Hara family, while Barbara O'Neil as his wife receives the second credit and Vivien Leigh as the eldest daughter the third credit, despite having the most screen time. Similarly, Howard C. Hickman as John Wilkes is credited over Leslie Howard who plays his son, and Clark Gable, who plays only a visitor at Twelve Oaks, receives a relatively low credit in the cast list, despite being presented as the &quot;[[Movie star|star]]&quot; of the film in all the promotional literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFIcatalog&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Gone With the Wind |work=[[The American Film Institute Catalog of Motion Pictures]] |publisher=[[American Film Institute]] |url=http://www.afi.com/members/catalog/DetailView.aspx?s=&amp;Movie=1181 |accessdate=January 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the death of Mary Anderson—who played  Maybelle Merriwether—in April 2014, there are only two surviving credited cast members from the film: Olivia de Havilland who played Melanie Wilkes and Mickey Kuhn, who played her son Beau Wilkes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Claire |last=Noland |title=Mary Anderson dies at 96; actress had role in 'Gone With the Wind' |date=April 8, 2014 |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |url=http://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-mary-anderson-20140408-story.html |accessdate=April 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| width     = 100
| image1    = Clark Gable as Rhett Butler in Gone With the Wind trailer.jpg
| caption1  = Clark Gable
| image2    = Vivien Leigh as Scarlett OHara in Gone With the Wind trailer.jpg
| caption2  = Vivien Leigh
| image3    = Leslie Howard as Ashley Wilkes in Gone With the Wind trailer.jpg
| caption3  = Leslie Howard
| image4    = Olivia de Havilland as Melanie Hamilton in Gone With the Wind trailer.jpg
| caption4  = Olivia de Havilland}}
{{Div col}}
;Tara plantation
* [[Thomas Mitchell (actor)|Thomas Mitchell]] as Gerald O'Hara
* [[Barbara O'Neil]] as Ellen O'Hara (his wife)
* [[Vivien Leigh]] as [[Scarlett O'Hara]] (daughter)
* [[Evelyn Keyes]] as Suellen O'Hara (daughter)
* [[Ann Rutherford]] as Carreen O'Hara (daughter)
* [[George Reeves]] as Brent Tarleton (actually as Stuart){{refn|group=nb|name=Tarleton|The credits at the start of the film contain an error: George Reeves is listed &quot;as Brent Tarleton&quot;, but plays Stuart, while Fred Crane is listed &quot;as Stuart Tarleton&quot;, but plays Brent.&lt;ref name=AFIcatalog/&gt;}}
* [[Fred Crane (actor)|Fred Crane]] as Stuart Tarleton (actually as Brent){{refn|group=nb|name=Tarleton}}
* [[Hattie McDaniel]] as Mammy (house servant)
* [[Oscar Polk]] as Pork (house servant)
* [[Butterfly McQueen]] as Prissy (house servant)
* [[Victor Jory]] as Jonas Wilkerson (field overseer)
* [[Everett Brown]] as Big Sam (field foreman)
;At Twelve Oaks
* [[Howard Hickman]] as John Wilkes
* [[Alicia Rhett]] as [[India Wilkes]] (his daughter)
* [[Leslie Howard (actor)|Leslie Howard]] as [[Ashley Wilkes]] (his son)
* [[Olivia de Havilland]] as [[Melanie Hamilton]] (their cousin)
* [[Rand Brooks]] as [[Gone with the Wind (novel)#Other characters|Charles Hamilton]] (Melanie's brother)
* [[Carroll Nye]] as Frank Kennedy (a guest)
* [[Clark Gable]] as [[Rhett Butler]] (a visitor from Charleston)
;In Atlanta
* [[Laura Hope Crews]] as Aunt Pittypat Hamilton
* [[Eddie &quot;Rochester&quot; Anderson|Eddie Anderson]] as Uncle Peter (her coachman)
* [[Harry Davenport (actor)|Harry Davenport]] as Doctor Meade
* [[Leona Roberts]] as Mrs. Meade
* [[Jane Darwell]] as Mrs. Merriwether
* [[Ona Munson]] as Belle Watling
;Minor supporting roles
* [[Paul Hurst (actor)|Paul Hurst]] as the Yankee deserter
* [[Cammie King|Cammie King Conlon]] as Bonnie Blue Butler
* [[J. M. Kerrigan]] as Johnny Gallagher
* [[Jackie Moran]] as Phil Meade
* [[Lillian Kemble-Cooper]] as Bonnie's nurse in London
* [[Marcella Martin]] as Cathleen Calvert
* [[Mickey Kuhn]] as Beau Wilkes
* [[Irving Bacon]] as the Corporal
* [[William Bakewell]] as the mounted officer
* [[Isabel Jewell]] as Emmy Slattery
* [[Eric Linden]] as the amputation case
* [[Ward Bond]] as Tom, the Yankee captain
* [[Cliff Edwards]] as the reminiscent soldier
* [[Yakima Canutt]] as the renegade
* [[Louis Jean Heydt]] as the hungry soldier holding Beau Wilkes
* [[Olin Howland]] as the carpetbagger businessman
* [[Robert Elliott (actor)|Robert Elliott]] as the Yankee major
* [[Mary Anderson (actress, born 1918)|Mary Anderson]] as Maybelle Merriwether
{{Div col end}}

==Production==
Before publication of the novel, several Hollywood executives and studios declined to create a film based on it, including [[Louis B. Mayer]] and [[Irving Thalberg]] at [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]] (MGM), [[Pandro Berman]] at [[RKO Pictures]], and [[David O. Selznick]] of [[Selznick International Pictures]]. [[Jack L. Warner]] liked the story, but [[Warner Bros.]]'s biggest star [[Bette Davis]] was uninterested, and [[Darryl Zanuck]] of [[20th Century Fox|20th Century-Fox]] did not offer enough money. Selznick changed his mind after his story editor [[Kay B. Barrett|Kay Brown]] and business partner [[John Hay Whitney]] urged him to buy the film rights. In July 1936—a month after it was published—Selznick bought the rights for $50,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedrich&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Friedrich|first=Otto|title=City of Nets: A Portrait of Hollywood in the 1940s|year=1986|publisher=[[University of California Press]]|location=Berkeley and Los Angeles|isbn=978-0-520-20949-7|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=0x8AFchW4JsC&amp;pg=PA17 17]–21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Book Purchase |work=Gone With The Wind Online Exhibit |location=[[University of Texas at Austin]] |publisher=[[Harry Ransom Center]] |url=http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/book |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140602124241/http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/book |archivedate=June 2, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Search for Scarlett: Chronology |work=Gone With The Wind Online Exhibit |location=[[University of Texas at Austin]] |publisher=[[Harry Ransom Center]] |url=http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/scarlett/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140602124241/http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/scarlett |archivedate=June 2, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Casting===
[[File:Clark Gable and Vivien Leigh - Wind.jpg|thumb|upright=1|Publicity photo of Clark Gable and Vivien Leigh as Rhett and Scarlett]]
The casting of the two lead roles became a complex, two-year endeavor. For the role of Rhett Butler, Selznick wanted [[Clark Gable]] from the start, but Gable was under contract to MGM, who never loaned him to other studios.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedrich&quot; /&gt; [[Gary Cooper]] was considered, but [[Samuel Goldwyn]]—to whom Cooper was under contract—refused to loan him out.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lambert&quot; /&gt; Warner offered a package of Bette Davis, [[Errol Flynn]], and [[Olivia de Havilland]] for lead roles in return for the distribution rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Gone with the Wind (1939) – Notes |work=TCM database |publisher=[[Turner Classic Movies]] |url=http://www.tcm.com/tcmdb/title/414427/Gone-With-the-Wind/notes.html |accessdate=January 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; By this time, Selznick was determined to get Gable and eventually struck a deal with MGM. Selznick's father-in-law, MGM chief Louis B. Mayer, offered in August 1938 to provide Gable and $1,250,000 for half of the film's budget but for a high price: Selznick would have to pay Gable's weekly salary, and half the profits would go to MGM while [[Loews Cineplex Entertainment|Loew's, Inc]]—MGM's parent company—would release the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedrich&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lambert&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Gavin |last=Lambert |authorlink=Gavin Lambert |work=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]] |date=February 1973 |title=The Making of Gone With The Wind, Part I |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1973/02/the-making-of-gone-with-the-wind-part-i/306455/?single_page=true |accessdate=March 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The arrangement to release through MGM meant delaying the start of production until the end of 1938, when Selznick's distribution deal with [[United Artists]] concluded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lambert&quot; /&gt; Selznick used the delay to continue to revise the script and, more importantly, build publicity for the film by [[Scarlett O'Hara#Searching for Scarlett|searching for the role of Scarlett]]. Selznick began a nationwide [[casting call]] that interviewed 1,400 unknowns. The effort cost $100,000 and was useless for the film, but created &quot;priceless&quot; publicity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedrich&quot; /&gt; Early frontrunners included [[Miriam Hopkins]] and [[Tallulah Bankhead]], who were regarded as possibilities by Selznick prior to the purchase of the film rights; [[Joan Crawford]], who was signed to MGM, was also considered as a potential pairing with Gable. After a deal was struck with MGM, Selznick held discussions with [[Norma Shearer]]—who was MGM's top female star at the time—but she withdrew herself from consideration. [[Katharine Hepburn]] lobbied hard for the role with the support of her friend, George Cukor, who had been hired to direct, but she was vetoed by Selznick who felt she was not right for the part.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lambert&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm articles&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Miller |first1=Frank |last2=Stafford |first2=Jeff |title=Gone with the Wind (1939) – Articles |work=TCM database |publisher=[[Turner Classic Movies]] |url=http://www.tcm.com/tcmdb/title/414427/Gone-With-the-Wind/articles.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130926003430/http://www.tcm.com/tcmdb/title/414427/Gone-With-the-Wind/articles.html|archivedate=September 26, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many famous—or soon-to-be-famous—actresses were considered, but only thirty-one women were actually screen-tested for Scarlett including [[Ardis Ankerson]], [[Jean Arthur]], [[Tallulah Bankhead]], [[Diana Barrymore]], [[Joan Bennett]], [[Nancy Coleman]], [[Frances Dee]], [[Ellen Drew]] (as Terry Ray), [[Paulette Goddard]], [[Susan Hayward]] (under her real name of Edythe Marrenner), [[Vivien Leigh]], [[Anita Louise]], [[Haila Stoddard]], [[Margaret Tallichet]], [[Lana Turner]] and [[Linda Watkins]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Search for Scarlett: Girls Tested for the Role of Scarlett |work=Gone With The Wind Online Exhibit |location=[[University of Texas at Austin]] |publisher=[[Harry Ransom Center]] |url=http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/scarlett/girltest.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140105182706/http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/scarlett/girltest.html |archivedate=January 5, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Margaret Mitchell refused to publicly name her choice, the actress who came closest to winning her approval was Miriam Hopkins, who Mitchell felt was just the right type of actress to play Scarlett as written in the book. However, Hopkins was in her mid-thirties at the time and was considered too old for the part.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lambert&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm articles&quot; /&gt; Four actresses, including Jean Arthur and Joan Bennett, were still under consideration by December 1938; however, only two finalists, Paulette Goddard and Vivien Leigh, were tested in [[Technicolor]], both on December 20.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Ronald | last = Haver | authorlink = Ronald Haver | title = David O. Selznick's Hollywood | location = New York | publisher=[[Alfred A. Knopf]] | year = 1980 | isbn = 978-0-394-42595-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Goddard almost won the role, but controversy over her marriage with [[Charlie Chaplin]] caused Selznick to change his mind.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedrich&quot; /&gt;

Selznick had been quietly considering Vivien Leigh, a young English actress who was still little known in America, for the role of Scarlett since February 1938 when Selznick saw her in ''[[Fire Over England]]'' and ''[[A Yank at Oxford]]''. Leigh's American agent was the London representative of the [[Myron Selznick]] talent agency (headed by David Selznick's brother, one of the owners of Selznick International), and she had requested in February that her name be submitted for consideration as Scarlett. By the summer of 1938 the Selznicks were negotiating with [[Alexander Korda]], to whom Leigh was under contract, for her services later that year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = William | last = Pratt | title = Scarlett Fever | location = New York | publisher=[[Macmillan Publishers (United States)|Macmillan Publishers]] | year = 1977 | pages = 73–74, 81–83 | isbn = 978-0-02-598560-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Selznick's brother arranged for them to meet for the first time on the night of December 10, 1938, when the burning of Atlanta was filmed. In a letter to his wife two days later, Selznick admitted that Leigh was &quot;the Scarlett dark horse&quot;, and after a series of screen tests, her casting was announced on January 13, 1939.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Marianne |last=Walker |title=Margaret Mitchell and John Marsh: The Love Story Behind Gone With the Wind |year=2011 |publisher=Peachtree Publishers |isbn=978-1-56145-617-8 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=quf-7VPsZWEC&amp;pg=PA405#v=twopage 405–406]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Just before the shooting of the film, Selznick informed newspaper columnist [[Ed Sullivan]]: &quot;Scarlett O'Hara's parents were French and Irish. Identically, Miss Leigh's parents are French and Irish.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Selznick |first=David O. |title=The Search for Scarlett: Vivien Leigh – Letter from David O. Selznick to Ed Sullivan |date=January 7, 1939 |work=Gone With The Wind Online Exhibit |location=[[University of Texas at Austin]] |publisher=[[Harry Ransom Center]] |url=http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/scarlett/sullivan.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131028095558/http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gwtw/scarlett/sullivan.html |archivedate=October 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Screenplay===
Of original screenplay writer [[Sidney Howard]], film historian Joanne Yeck writes, &quot;reducing the intricacies of ''Gone with the Wind'''s epic dimensions was a herculean task ... and Howard's first submission was far too long, and would have required at least six hours of film; ... [producer] Selznick wanted Howard to remain on the set to make revisions ... but Howard refused to leave New England [and] as a result, revisions were handled by a host of local writers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yeck&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Yeck |first=Joanne |volume=American Screenwriters |encyclopedia=[[Dictionary of Literary Biography]] |year=1984 |publisher=[[Gale (publisher)|Gale]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Selznick dismissed director George Cukor three weeks into filming and sought out Victor Fleming, who was directing ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]'' at the time. Fleming was dissatisfied with the script, so Selznick brought in famed writer [[Ben Hecht]] to rewrite the entire screenplay within five days. Hecht returned to Howard's original draft and by the end of the week had succeeded in revising the entire first half of the script. Selznick undertook rewriting the second half himself but fell behind schedule, so Howard returned to work on the script for one week, reworking several key scenes in part two.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Pauline |last=Bartel |title=The Complete Gone with the Wind Trivia Book: The Movie and More |year=1989 |publisher=[[Taylor Trade Publishing]] |isbn=978-0-87833-619-7 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ZJLb5GC35E8C&amp;pg=PA64 64]–[https://books.google.com/books?id=DJUYAcJN3jgC&amp;pg=PA69 69], [https://books.google.com/books?id=ZJLb5GC35E8C&amp;pg=PA127 127] &amp; [https://books.google.com/books?id=ZJLb5GC35E8C&amp;pg=PA161 161]–[https://books.google.com/books?id=DJUYAcJN3jgC&amp;pg=PA172 172]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:DavidOSelznick.jpg|thumb|left|upright|David O. Selznick in 1940]]
&quot;By the time of the film's release in 1939, there was some question as to who should receive screen credit,&quot; writes Yeck. &quot;But despite the number of writers and changes, the final script was remarkably close to Howard's version. The fact that Howard's name alone appears on the credits may have been as much a gesture to his memory as to his writing, for in 1939 Sidney Howard died at age 48 in a farm-tractor accident, and before the movie's premiere.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Yeck&quot; /&gt; Selznick, in a memo written in October 1939, discussed the film's writing credits: &quot;[Y]ou can say frankly that of the comparatively small amount of material in the picture which is not from the book, most is my own personally, and the only original lines of dialog which are not my own are a few from Sidney Howard and a few from Ben Hecht and a couple more from [[John Van Druten]]. Offhand I doubt that there are ten original words of [Oliver] Garrett's in the whole script. As to construction, this is about eighty per cent my own, and the rest divided between [[Jo Swerling]] and Sidney Howard, with Hecht having contributed materially to the construction of one sequence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Selznick&quot;&gt;{{cite book| first = David O.| last = Selznick |year=1938–1939 |editor-last=Behlmer |editor-first=Rudy | title = Memo from David O. Selznick: the creation of Gone with the wind and other motion picture classics, as revealed in the producer's private letters, telegrams, memorandums, and autobiographical remarks| location = New York| publisher=[[Modern Library]]| publication-date = 2000 | ref = harv| isbn = 978-0-375-75531-6 |pages=179–180 &amp; 224–225}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Hecht biographer, William MacAdams, &quot;At dawn on Sunday, February 20, 1939, David Selznick ... and director Victor Fleming shook Hecht awake to inform him he was on loan from MGM and must come with them immediately and go to work on ''Gone with the Wind'', which Selznick had begun shooting five weeks before. It was costing Selznick $50,000 each day the film was on hold waiting for a final screenplay rewrite and time was of the essence. Hecht was in the middle of working on the film ''[[At the Circus]]'' for the [[Marx Brothers]]. Recalling the episode in a letter to screenwriter friend [[Gene Fowler]], he said he hadn't read the novel but Selznick and director Fleming could not wait for him to read it. They would act out scenes based on Sidney Howard's original script which needed to be rewritten in a hurry. Hecht wrote, &quot;After each scene had been performed and discussed, I sat down at the typewriter and wrote it out. Selznick and Fleming, eager to continue with their acting, kept hurrying me. We worked in this fashion for seven days, putting in eighteen to twenty hours a day. Selznick refused to let us eat lunch, arguing that food would slow us up. He provided bananas and salted peanuts ... thus on the seventh day I had completed, unscathed, the first nine reels of the Civil War epic.&quot;

MacAdams writes, &quot;It is impossible to determine exactly how much Hecht scripted ... In the official credits filed with the [[Screen Writers Guild]], Sidney Howard was of course awarded the sole screen credit, but four other writers were appended ... Jo Swerling for contributing to the treatment, Oliver H. P. Garrett and Barbara Keon to screenplay construction, and Hecht, to dialogue ...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=MacAdams |first=William |title=Ben Hecht |year=1990 |publisher=[[Barricade Books]] |location=New York |isbn=978-1-56980-028-7 |pages=199–201}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Filming===
[[Principal photography]] began January 26, 1939, and ended on July 1, with post-production work continuing until November 11, 1939. Director [[George Cukor]], with whom Selznick had a long working relationship, and who had spent almost two years in pre-production on ''Gone with the Wind'', was replaced after less than three weeks of shooting.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt;{{refn|From a private letter from journalist and on-set technical advisor Susan Myrick to Margaret Mitchell in February 1939:
:George [Cukor] finally told me all about it. He hated [leaving the production] very much he said but he could not do otherwise. In effect he said he is an honest craftsman and he cannot do a job unless he knows it is a good job and he feels the present job is not right. For days, he told me he has looked at the rushes and felt he was failing... the thing did not click as it should. Gradually he became convinced that the script was the trouble... David [Selznick], himself, thinks HE is writing the script... And George has continually taken script from day to day, compared the [Oliver] Garrett-Selznick version with the [Sidney] Howard, groaned and tried to change some parts back to the Howard script. But he seldom could do much with the scene... So George just told David he would not work any longer if the script was not better and he wanted the Howard script back. David told George he was a director—not an author and he (David) was the producer and the judge of what is a good script... George said he was a director and a damn good one and he would not let his name go out over a lousy picture... And bull-headed David said &quot;OK get out!&quot;&lt;ref name=Myrick&gt;
{{cite book | first=Susan | last=Myrick | title=White Columns in Hollywood: Reports from the GWTW Sets | location=Macon, Georgia | publisher=[[Mercer University Press]] | year=1982 | pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ctFm2Hetkh0C&amp;&amp;pg=PA126#v=twopage 126–127] | isbn=978-0-86554-044-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Selznick had already been unhappy with Cukor (&quot;a very expensive luxury&quot;) for not being more receptive to directing other Selznick assignments, even though Cukor had remained on salary since early 1937. In a confidential memo written in September 1938, Selznick flirted with the idea of replacing him with Victor Fleming.&lt;ref name=Selznick/&gt;

[[Louis B. Mayer]] had been trying to have Cukor replaced with an MGM director since negotiations between the two studios began in May 1938. In December 1938, Selznick wrote to his wife about a phone call he had with Mayer: &quot;During the same conversation, your father made another stab at getting George off of ''Gone With the Wind''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Scott |last=Eyman |title=Lion of Hollywood: The Life and Legend of Louis B. Mayer |year=2005 |publisher=[[Robson Books]] |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=q0ldNR7gZ1oC&amp;pg=PA258#v=twopage 258–259] |isbn=978-1-86105-892-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group = nb}} Selznick and Cukor had already disagreed over the pace of filming and the script,&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Myrick&quot; /&gt; but other explanations put Cukor's departure down to Gable's discomfort at working with him.  [[Emanuel Levy]], Cukor's biographer, claimed that Clark Gable had worked Hollywood's gay circuit as a [[gigolo|hustler]] and that Cukor knew of his past, so Gable used his influence to have him discharged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Michelangelo |last=Capua |title=Vivien Leigh: A Biography |year=2003 |publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]] |isbn=978-0-7864-1497-0 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=uMdRckjUDvAC&amp;pg=PA59 59]–61}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vivien Leigh and Olivia de Havilland learned of Cukor's firing on the day the Atlanta bazaar scene was filmed, and the pair went to Selznick's office in full costume and implored him to change his mind. [[Victor Fleming]], who was directing ''The Wizard of Oz'', was called in from MGM to complete the picture, although Cukor continued privately to coach Leigh and De Havilland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot; /&gt; Another MGM director, [[Sam Wood]], worked for two weeks in May when Fleming temporarily left the production due to exhaustion. Although some of Cukor's scenes were later reshot, Selznick estimated that &quot;three solid reels&quot; of his work remained in the picture. As of the end of principal photography, Cukor had undertaken eighteen days of filming, Fleming ninety-three, and Wood twenty-four.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Burning of Atlanta.ogg|thumb|The &quot;burning&quot; of Atlanta from the film trailer]]
Cinematographer [[Lee Garmes]] began the production, but on March 11, 1939—after a month of shooting footage that Selznick and his associates regarded as &quot;too dark&quot;—was replaced with [[Ernest Haller]], working with Technicolor cinematographer [[Ray Rennahan]]. Garmes completed the first third of the film—mostly everything prior to Melanie having the baby—but did not receive a credit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Turner |first=Adrian |title=A celebration of Gone with the wind |year=1989 |publisher=Dragon's World |page=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the filming was done on &quot;[[RKO Forty Acres|the back forty]]&quot; of Selznick International with all the location scenes being photographed in California, mostly in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]] or neighboring [[Ventura County, California|Ventura County]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Cynthia Marylee | last = Molt | title = Gone with the Wind on Film: A Complete Reference | location = Jefferson, NC | publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]] | year = 1990 | pages = 272–281 | isbn = 978-0-89950-439-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tara, the fictional Southern plantation house, existed only as a plywood and papier-mâché facade built on the Selznick studio lot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bridges |first=Herb |year=1998 |title=The Filming of Gone with the Wind |publisher=[[Mercer University Press]] |isbn=978-0-86554-621-9 |at=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ekvkZo0mAXcC&amp;pg=PT4 PT4]}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the burning of Atlanta, new false facades were built in front of the Selznick backlot's many old abandoned sets, and Selznick himself operated the controls for the explosives that burned them down.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedrich&quot; /&gt; Sources at the time put the estimated production costs at $3.85&amp;nbsp;million, making it the second most expensive film made up to that point, with only ''[[Ben-Hur (1925 film)|Ben-Hur]]'' (1925) having cost more.&lt;ref name=&quot;Time (1939)&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Cinema: G With the W |date=December 25, 1939 |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |url=http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,762137,00.html |accessdate=July 6, 2011 |pages=[http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,762137-1,00.html 1]–[http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,762137-2,00.html 2] &amp; [http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,762137-7,00.html 7]}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|''Time'' also reports that ''[[Hell's Angels (film)|Hell's Angels]]'' (1930)—directed by [[Howard Hughes]]—cost more, but this was later revealed to be a fallacy; the accounts for ''Hell's Angels'' show it cost $2.8 million, but Hughes publicized it as costing $4 million, selling it to the media as the most expensive film ever made up to that point.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eyman (1997)&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Eyman |first=Scott |title=The speed of sound: Hollywood and the talkie revolution, 1926–1930 |year=1997 |publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]] |isbn=978-0-684-81162-8 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Vc-SjHBM-DcC&amp;pg=PA253 253]}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group = nb}}

Although legend persists that the [[Production Code|Hays Office]] fined Selznick $5,000 for using the word &quot;damn&quot; in Butler's exit line, in fact the [[Motion Picture Association of America|Motion Picture Association]] board passed an amendment to the Production Code on November 1, 1939, that forbade use of the words &quot;hell&quot; or &quot;damn&quot; except when their use &quot;shall be essential and required for portrayal, in proper historical context, of any scene or dialogue based upon historical fact or folklore ... or a quotation from a literary work, provided that no such use shall be permitted which is intrinsically objectionable or offends good taste.&quot; With that amendment, the [[Production Code Administration]] had no further objection to Rhett's closing line.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Leonard J. |last1=Leff |first2=Jerold L. |last2=Simmons |title=The Dame in the Kimono: Hollywood, Censorship, and the Production Code |publisher=[[University Press of Kentucky]] |year=2001 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=bkU7CKBubgMC&amp;pg=PA108 108]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music===
[[File:Tara's Theme.ogg|thumb|&quot;Tara's Theme&quot; from the film trailer]]
To compose the score, Selznick chose [[Max Steiner]], with whom he had worked at RKO Pictures in the early 1930s. Warner Bros.—who had contracted Steiner in 1936—agreed to lend him to Selznick. Steiner spent twelve weeks working on the score, the longest period that he had ever spent writing one, and at two hours and thirty-six minutes long it was also the longest that he had ever written. Five orchestrators were hired, including [[Hugo Friedhofer]], Maurice de Packh, Bernard Kaun, [[Adolph Deutsch]] and Reginald Bassett. The score is characterized by two love themes, one for Ashley's and Melanie's sweet love and another that evokes Scarlett's passion for Ashley, though notably there is no Scarlett and Rhett love theme. Steiner drew considerably on folk and patriotic music, which included [[Stephen Foster]] tunes such as &quot;Louisiana Belle,&quot; &quot;Dolly Day,&quot; &quot;Ringo De Banjo,&quot; &quot;[[Beautiful Dreamer]],&quot; &quot;[[Old Folks at Home]],&quot; and &quot;Katie Belle,&quot; which formed the basis of Scarlett's theme; other tunes that feature prominently are: &quot;Marching through Georgia&quot; by [[Henry Clay Work]], &quot;[[Dixie (song)|Dixie]],&quot; &quot;[[Garryowen (air)|Garryowen]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Bonnie Blue Flag]].&quot; The theme that is most associated with the film today is the melody that accompanies Tara, the O'Hara plantation; in the early 1940s, &quot;Tara's Theme&quot; formed the musical basis of the song &quot;My Own True Love&quot; by [[Mack David]]. In all, there are ninety-nine separate pieces of music featured in the score. Due to the pressure of completing on time, Steiner received some assistance in composing from Friedhofer, Deutsch and [[Heinz Roemheld]], and in addition, two short cues—by [[Franz Waxman]] and [[William Axt]]—were taken from scores in the MGM library.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Laurence E. |last=MacDonald |title=The Invisible Art of Film Music: A Comprehensive History |year=1998 |publisher=[[Scarecrow Press]] |isbn=978-1-880157-56-5 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=bQGbUd83MhYC&amp;pg=PT68 52]–[https://books.google.com/books?id=bQGbUd83MhYC&amp;pg=PT69 53]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release==

===Preview, premiere and initial release===
On September 9, 1939, Selznick, his wife, [[Irene Mayer Selznick|Irene]], investor [[Jock Whitney|John &quot;Jock&quot; Whitney]] and film editor Hal Kern drove out to [[Riverside, California]] to preview it at the [[Riverside Fox Theater|Fox Theatre]]. The film was still a [[rough cut]] at this stage, missing completed titles and lacking special optical effects. It ran for four hours and twenty-five minutes, but would later be cut down to under four hours for its proper release. A [[double bill]] of ''[[Hawaiian Nights]]'' and ''[[Beau Geste (1939 film)|Beau Geste]]'' was playing, and after the first feature it was announced that the theater would be screening a preview; the audience were informed they could leave but would not be readmitted once the film had begun, nor would phone calls be allowed once the theater had been sealed. When the title appeared on the screen the audience cheered, and after it had finished it received a standing ovation.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bell&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Bell |first=Alison |title=Inland Empire cities were once 'in' with Hollywood for movie previews |date=June 25, 2010 |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jun/25/local/la-me-then-20100625 |accessdate=January 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his biography of Selznick, [[David Thomson (film critic)|David Thomson]] wrote that the audience's response before the film had even started &quot;was the greatest moment of [Selznick's] life, the greatest victory and redemption of all his failings&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = David | last = Thomson | authorlink = David Thomson (film critic) | title = Showman: The Life of David O. Selznick | location = New York | publisher=[[Alfred A. Knopf|Knopf]] | year = 1992 | isbn = 978-0-394-56833-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; with Selznick describing the preview cards as &quot;probably the most amazing any picture has ever had.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Gavin |last=Lambert |authorlink=Gavin Lambert |work=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]] |date=March 1973 |title=The Making of Gone With The Wind, Part II |volume=265 |issue=6 |pages=56–72 |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/73mar/wind.htm |accessdate=January 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Selznick was asked by the press in early September how he felt about the film, he said: &quot;At noon I think it's divine, at midnight I think it's lousy. Sometimes I think it's the greatest picture ever made. But if it's only a great picture, I'll still be satisfied.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Time (1939)&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Gone With the Wind Atlanta premiere 1939.jpg|thumb|left|The premiere of the film at Loew's Grand, Atlanta]]
About 300,000 people came out in Atlanta for the film's premiere at the [[Loew's Grand Theatre]] on December 15, 1939. It was the climax of three days of festivities hosted by Mayor [[William B. Hartsfield]], which included a parade of limousines featuring stars from the film, receptions, thousands of Confederate flags and a costume ball. [[Eurith D. Rivers]], the governor of Georgia, declared December 15 a state holiday. An estimated three hundred thousand residents and visitors to Atlanta lined the streets for up to seven miles to watch a procession of limousines bring the stars from the airport. Only Leslie Howard and Victor Fleming chose not to attend: Howard had returned to England due to the outbreak of [[World War II]], and Fleming had fallen out with Selznick and declined to attend any of the premieres.&lt;ref name=&quot;Time (1939)&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot; /&gt; Hattie McDaniel was also absent, as she and the other black cast members  were prevented from attending the premiere due to Georgia's [[Jim Crow]] laws, which would have kept them from sitting with their white colleagues. Upon learning that McDaniel had been barred from the premiere, Clark Gable threatened to boycott the event, but McDaniel convinced him to attend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Harris |first=Warren G. |title=Clark Gable: A Biography |publisher=[[Harmony Books]] |year=2002 |page=211}}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Jimmy Carter]] would later recall it as &quot;the biggest event to happen in the South in my lifetime.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Hamilton |last=Cravens |title=Great Depression: People and Perspectives |series=Perspectives in American Social History |year=2009 |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |isbn=978-1-59884-093-3 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=0gblKwLBrrQC&amp;pg=PA221 221]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Premieres in New York and Los Angeles followed, the latter attended by some of the actresses that had been considered for the part of Scarlett, among them Paulette Goddard, Norma Shearer and Joan Crawford.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot; /&gt;

From December 1939 to July 1940, the film played only advance-ticket [[Roadshow theatrical release|road show]] engagements at a limited number of theaters at prices upwards of $1—more than double the price of a regular first-run feature—with MGM collecting an unprecedented 70 percent of the box office receipts (as opposed to the typical 30–35 percent of the period). After reaching saturation as a roadshow, MGM revised its terms to a 50 percent cut and halved the prices, before it finally entered general release in 1941 at &quot;popular&quot; prices.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schatz (1999)&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Schatz |first=Thomas |title=Boom and Bust: American Cinema in the 1940s |volume=Volume 6 of History of the American Cinema |year=1999 |publisher=[[University of California Press]] |origyear=1st. pub. 1997 |isbn=978-0-520-22130-7 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=dwf5SUcfousC&amp;pg=PA65 65]–[https://books.google.com/books?id=dwf5SUcfousC&amp;pg=PA66 66]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with its distribution and advertising costs, total expenditure on the film was as high as $7 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shearer&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Shearer |first=Lloyd |title=GWTW: Supercolossal Saga of an Epic |date=October 26, 1947 |work=[[The New York Times]] |url=http://www.nytimes.com/packages/html/movies/bestpictures/wind-ar6.html |accessdate=July 14, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later releases===
[[File:Gone With The Wind 1967 re-release.jpg|thumb|upright|1967 re-release poster]]
In 1942, Selznick liquidated his company for tax reasons, and sold his share in ''Gone with the Wind'' to his business partner, John Whitney, for $500,000. In turn, Whitney sold it on to MGM for $2.8 million, so that the studio owned the film outright.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shearer&quot; /&gt; MGM immediately re-released the film in spring 1942,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot;/&gt; and again in 1947 and 1954;&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt; the 1954 reissue was the first time the film was shown in [[widescreen]], compromising the original [[Academy ratio]] and cropping the top and bottom to an aspect ratio of 1.75:1. In doing so, a number of shots were optically re-framed and cut into the three-strip camera negatives, forever altering five shots in the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Haver |first=Ronald |authorlink=Ronald Haver |year=1993 |title=David O. Selznick's Gone with the wind |location=New York |publisher=[[Random House]] |pages=84–85}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 1961 release commemorated the [[centennial]] anniversary of the start of the Civil War, and included a gala &quot;premiere&quot; at the Loew's Grand Theater. It was attended by Selznick and many other stars of the film, including Vivien Leigh and Olivia de Havilland;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown &amp; Wiley&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1=Ellen F. |last1=Brown |first2=John, Jr.|last2=Wiley |title=Margaret Mitchell's Gone With the Wind: A Bestseller's Odyssey from Atlanta to Hollywood |year=2011 |publisher=[[Taylor Trade Publications]] |isbn=978-1-58979-527-3 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Jb6kAdtMHCQC&amp;pg=PA287 287], [https://books.google.com/books?id=Jb6kAdtMHCQC&amp;pg=PA293 293] &amp; [https://books.google.com/books?id=Jb6kAdtMHCQC&amp;pg=PA322 322]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clark Gable had died the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=James Stuart |last=Olson |title=Historical Dictionary of the 1950s |year=2000 |publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]] |isbn=978-0-313-30619-8 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=eSBDF5_L3BgC&amp;pg=PA108 108]}}&lt;/ref&gt; For its 1967 re-release, it was blown up to [[70mm]],&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt; and issued with updated poster artwork featuring Gable—with his white shirt ripped open—holding Leigh against a backdrop of orange flames.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown &amp; Wiley&quot; /&gt; There were further re-releases in 1971, 1974 and 1989; for the fiftieth anniversary reissue in 1989, it was given a complete audio and video restoration. It was released theatrically one more time in the United States, in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last=Block|editor1-first=Alex Ben|editor2-last=Wilson|editor2-first=Lucy Autrey|year=2010|title=George Lucas's Blockbusting: A Decade-By-Decade Survey of Timeless Movies Including Untold Secrets of Their Financial and Cultural Success|publisher=[[HarperCollins]]|isbn=978-0-06-177889-6|pages=220–221}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kramer&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Peter |last=Krämer |title=The New Hollywood: From Bonnie And Clyde To Star Wars |volume=30 |series=Short Cuts |year=2005 |publisher=Wallflower Press |isbn=978-1-904764-58-8 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=B5PjuAbEPooC&amp;pg=PA46 46]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, a [[4K resolution|4K]] [[Digital cinema|digital restoration]] was released in the United Kingdom to coincide with Vivien Leigh's centenary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Andrew |first=Geoff |title=Gone with the Wind |publisher=[[British Film Institute]] |url=http://www.bfi.org.uk/news-opinion/bfi-film-releases/gone-wind |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131201232515/http://www.bfi.org.uk/news-opinion/bfi-film-releases/gone-wind |archivedate=December 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, special screenings were scheduled over a two-day period at theaters across the United States to coincide with the film's 75th anniversary.&lt;ref name=&quot;75th anniversary screenings&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Fristoe |first=Roger |title=Gone with the Wind: 75th Anniversary – Screenings and Events |publisher=[[Turner Classic Movies]] |url=http://www.tcm.com/this-month/article/1028229%7C0/Gone-With-the-Wind-th-Anniversary.html |accessdate=September 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television and home video===
The film received its world television premiere on the [[HBO]] cable network on June 11, 1976, and played on the channel for a total of fourteen times throughout the rest of the month. It made its [[network television]] debut in November later that year: [[NBC]] paid $5 million for a one-off airing, and it was broadcast in two parts on successive evenings. It became at that time the [[List of most-watched television broadcasts#United States|highest-rated television program]] ever presented on a single network, watched by 47.5 percent of the households sampled in America, and 65 percent of television viewers, still the record for the highest rated film to ever air on television. In 1978, [[CBS]] signed a deal worth $35 million to broadcast the film twenty times over as many years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kramer&quot; /&gt; [[Turner Entertainment]] acquired the MGM film library in 1986, but the deal did not include the television rights to ''Gone with the Wind'', which were still held by CBS. A deal was struck in which the rights were returned to Turner Entertainment and CBS's broadcast rights to ''The Wizard of Oz'' were extended.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot; /&gt; It was used to launch two cable channels owned by [[Turner Broadcasting System]]: [[TNT (TV channel)|Turner Network Television]] (1988) and [[Turner Classic Movies]] (1994).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Kenneth R. |last=Clark |title=Tnt Rides In On 'Gone With Wind' |date=September 29, 1988 |work=[[Chicago Tribune]] |url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1988-09-29/features/8802030105_1_basic-cable-industry-jeffrey-selznick-tnt |accessdate=January 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Osborne |last=Robert |authorlink=Robert Osborne |title=Robert Osborne on TCM's 15th Anniversary |publisher=[[Turner Classic Movies]] |url=http://www.tcm.com/this-month/article/236547%7C0/Robert-Osborne-April-2009.html |accessdate=January 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It debuted on [[videocassette]] in March 1985, where it placed second in the sales charts,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot; /&gt; and has since been released on [[DVD]] and [[Blu-ray Disc]] formats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown &amp; Wiley&quot; /&gt;

==Reception==

===Critical response===
''Gone with the Wind'' was well received upon its release, with most consumer magazines and newspapers generally giving it excellent reviews.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt; However, while its production values, technical achievements, and scale of ambition were universally recognized, some of the more notable reviewers of the time found the film to be dramatically lacking. [[Frank S. Nugent]] for ''[[The New York Times]]'' best summed up the general sentiment by acknowledging that while it was the most ambitious film production made up to that point, it probably was not the greatest film ever made, but he nevertheless found it to be an &quot;interesting story beautifully told&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nugent&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Nugent |first=Frank S. |authorlink=Frank S. Nugent |title=The Screen in Review; David Selznick's 'Gone With the Wind' Has Its Long-Awaited Premiere at Astor and Capitol, Recalling Civil War and Plantation Days of South--Seen as Treating Book With Great Fidelity |date=December 20, 1939 |work=[[The New York Times]] |url=http://www.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9807E2DA153EE432A25753C2A9649D946894D6CF |accessdate=February 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Franz Hoellering of ''[[The Nation]]'' was of the same opinion: &quot;The result is a film which is a major event in the history of the industry but only a minor achievement in motion-picture art. There are moments when the two categories meet on good terms, but the long stretches between are filled with mere spectacular efficiency.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoellering&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Hoellering |first=Franz |title=Gone With the Wind |year=1939 |work=[[The Nation]] |publication-date=December 16, 2008 |url=http://www.thenation.com/article/gone-wind |accessdate=February 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Rquote|left|The result is a film which is a major event in the history of the industry but only a minor achievement in motion-picture art.|Franz Hoellering|reviewer for ''The Nation''}}
While the film was praised for its fidelity to the novel,&lt;ref name=&quot;Nugent&quot; /&gt; this aspect was also singled out as the main factor in contributing to the bloated running time, which many critics felt was to the detriment of the overall dramatic impact.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flinn&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Flinn |first=John C., Sr. |title=Gone With the Wind |date=December 20, 1939 |work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |url=http://variety.com/1939/film/reviews/gone-with-the-wind-2-1200412649/ |accessdate=June 14, 2013 |archiveurl=http://www.varietyultimate.com/archive/issue/WV-12-20-1939-14 |archivedate=February 24, 2013 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; John C. Flinn wrote for ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' that Selznick had &quot;left too much in&quot;, and that as entertainment, the film would have benefited if repetitious scenes and dialog from the latter part of the story had been trimmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flinn&quot; /&gt; ''[[The Manchester Guardian]]'' felt that the film's one serious drawback was that the story lacked the epic quality to justify the outlay of time and found the second half, which focuses on Scarlett's &quot;irrelevant marriages&quot; and &quot;domestic squabbles,&quot; mostly superfluous, and the sole reason for their inclusion had been &quot;simply because Margaret Mitchell wrote it that way&quot;. ''The Guardian'' believed that if &quot;the story had been cut short and tidied up at the point marked by the interval, and if the personal drama had been made subservient to a cinematic treatment of the central theme—the collapse and devastation of the Old South—then ''Gone With the Wind'' might have been a really great film.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=From the archive, 28 May 1940: Gone with the wind at the Gaiety |date=May 28, 1940 |work=[[The Manchester Guardian]] |publication-date=May 28, 2010 |url=http://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2010/may/28/archive-gone-with-the-wind-1940 |accessdate=February 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, Hoellering also found the second half of the film to be weaker than the first half: identifying the Civil War to be the driving force of the first part while the characters dominate in the second part, he concluded this is where the main fault of the picture lay, commenting that &quot;the characters alone do not suffice&quot;. Despite many excellent scenes, he considered the drama to be unconvincing and that the &quot;psychological development&quot; had been neglected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoellering&quot; /&gt;

Much of the praise was reserved for the casting, with Vivien Leigh in particular being singled out for her performance as Scarlett. Nugent described her as the &quot;pivot of the picture&quot; and believed her to be &quot;so perfectly designed for the part by art and nature that any other actress in the role would be inconceivable&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nugent&quot; /&gt; Similarly, Hoellering found her &quot;perfect&quot; in &quot;appearance and movements&quot;; he felt her acting best when she was allowed to &quot;accentuate the split personality she portrays&quot; and thought she was particularly effective in such moments of characterization like the morning after the marital rape scene.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoellering&quot; /&gt; Flinn also found Leigh suited to the role physically and felt she was best in the scenes where she displays courage and determination, such as the escape from Atlanta and when Scarlett kills a Yankee deserter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flinn&quot; /&gt; Leigh won in the Best Actress category for her performance at the [[1939 New York Film Critics Circle Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=New York Film Critics Circle Awards – 1939 Awards |publisher=[[New York Film Critics Circle]] |url=http://www.nyfcc.com/awards/?awardyear=1939 |accessdate=July 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of Clark Gable's performance as Rhett Butler, Flinn felt the characterization was &quot;as close to Miss Mitchell's conception—and the audience's—as might be imagined&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Flinn&quot; /&gt; a view which Nugent concurred with,&lt;ref name=&quot;Nugent&quot; /&gt; although Hoellering felt that Gable didn't quite convince in the closing scenes, as Rhett walks out on Scarlett in disgust.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoellering&quot; /&gt; Of the other principal cast members, both Hoellering and Flinn found Leslie Howard to be &quot;convincing&quot; as the weak-willed Ashley, with Flinn identifying Olivia de Havilland as a &quot;standout&quot; as Melanie;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoellering&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flinn&quot; /&gt; Nugent was also especially taken with de Havilland's performance, describing it as a &quot;gracious, dignified, tender gem of characterization&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nugent&quot; /&gt; Hattie McDaniel's performance as Mammy was singled out for praise by many critics: Nugent believed she gave the best performance in the film after Vivien Leigh,&lt;ref name=&quot;Nugent&quot; /&gt; with Flinn placing it third after Leigh's and Gable's performances.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flinn&quot; /&gt;

===Academy Awards===
[[File:Studio publicity Hattie McDaniel.jpg|thumb|upright|Hattie McDaniel, the first African-American Oscar winner]]
At the [[12th Academy Awards]], ''Gone with the Wind'' set a record for [[Academy Award]] wins and nominations, winning in eight of the competitive categories it was nominated in, from a total of thirteen nominations. It won for Best Picture, Best Actress, Best Supporting Actress, Best Director, Best Screenplay, Best Cinematography, Best Interior Decoration, and Best Editing, and received two further honorary awards for its use of equipment and color (it also became the first color film to win Best Picture).&lt;ref name=&quot;Oscars1940&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Results page – 1939 (12th) |work=Academy Awards database|publisher=[[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]] |url=http://awardsdatabase.oscars.org/ampas_awards/BasicSearch?action=searchLink&amp;displayType=1&amp;BSFromYear=12 |accessdate=February 3, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Randall&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Randall |first1=David |last2=Clark |first2=Heather |title=Oscars – cinema's Golden Night: The ultimate bluffer's guide to Hollywood's big night |date=February 24, 2013 |work=[[The Independent]] |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/features/oscars--cinemas-golden-night-the-ultimate-bluffers-guide-to-hollywoods-big-night-8508244.html |accessdate=March 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its record of eight competitive wins stood until ''[[Gigi (1958 film)|Gigi]]'' (1958) won nine, and its overall record of ten was broken by ''[[Ben-Hur (1959 film)|Ben-Hur]]'' (1959) which won eleven.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cutler&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Cutler |first=David |editor1-last=Goldsmith |editor1-first=Belinda |editor2-last=Zargham |editor2-first=Mohammad |title=Factbox : Key historical facts about the Academy Awards |date=February 22, 2013 |work=[[Reuters]] |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/02/22/us-oscars-factbox-idUSBRE91L0KM20130222 |accessdate=March 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Gone with the Wind'' also held the record for most nominations until ''[[All About Eve]]'' (1950) secured fourteen.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm articles&quot; /&gt; It was the longest American sound film made up to that point, and may still hold the record of the longest Best Picture winner depending on how it is interpreted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oscar quotes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Beyond the Page: Famous Quotes |publisher=[[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]] |url=http://www.oscars.org/events-exhibitions/features/read-the-book/part1_beyond.html |accessdate=March 8, 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120905125647/http://www.oscars.org/events-exhibitions/features/read-the-book/part1_beyond.html |archivedate=September 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The running time for ''Gone with the Wind'' is just under 221&amp;nbsp;minutes, while ''[[Lawrence of Arabia (film)|Lawrence of Arabia]]'' (1962) runs for just over 222&amp;nbsp;minutes; however, including the [[overture]], [[intermission]], [[entr'acte]], and exit music, ''Gone with the Wind'' lasts for 234&amp;nbsp;minutes (although some sources put its full length at 238&amp;nbsp;minutes) while ''Lawrence of Arabia'' comes in slightly shorter at 232&amp;nbsp;minutes with its additional components.&lt;ref name=&quot;filmsite&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Dirks |first=Tim |title=Academy Awards: Best Picture – Facts &amp; Trivia |work=[[Filmsite.org]] |publisher=[[AMC Networks]] |page=2 |url=http://www.filmsite.org/bestpics1.html |accessdate=March 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kim&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Kim |first=Wook |title=17 Unusual Oscar Records – Longest Film (Running Time) to Win an Award: 431&amp;nbsp;Minutes |date=February 22, 2013 |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |url=http://entertainment.time.com/2013/02/22/17-unusual-oscar-records/slide/war-and-peace |accessdate=March 7, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hattie McDaniel became the first African-American to win an Academy Award—beating out her co-star Olivia de Havilland who was also nominated in the same category—but was [[Racial segregation in the United States|racially segregated]] from her co-stars at the awards ceremony at the [[Ambassador Hotel (Los Angeles)|Coconut Grove]]; she and her escort were made to sit at a separate table at the back of the room.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haskell&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Haskell |first=Molly |title=Frankly, My Dear: Gone With the Wind Revisited |series=Icons of America |year=2010 |publisher=[[Yale University Press]] |isbn=978-0-300-16437-4 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=V-g1USyUYIwC&amp;pg=PA213 213]–[https://books.google.com/books?id=V-g1USyUYIwC&amp;pg=PA214 214]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, screenwriter Sidney Howard became the first [[List of posthumous Academy Award winners and nominees|posthumous]] Oscar winner and Selznick personally received the [[Irving G. Thalberg Memorial Award]] for his career achievements.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm articles&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Oscars1940&quot; /&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; margin:auto;&quot;
|+Academy Awards and nominations
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Award
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Recipient(s)
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Result
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]]
| [[Selznick International Pictures]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]]
| [[Victor Fleming]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]]
| [[Clark Gable]] &lt;br /&gt; Winner was [[Robert Donat]] for ''[[Goodbye, Mr. Chips (1939 film)|Goodbye, Mr. Chips]]'' || {{nom}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Actress|Best Actress]]
| [[Vivien Leigh]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Writing (Adapted Screenplay)|Best Adapted Screenplay]]
| [[Sidney Howard]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actress|Best Supporting Actress]]
| [[Hattie McDaniel]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actress|Best Supporting Actress]]
| [[Olivia de Havilland]] || {{nom}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography, Color]]
| [[Ernest Haller]] and [[Ray Rennahan]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Film Editing|Best Film Editing]]
| [[Hal C. Kern]] and [[James E. Newcom]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Art Direction|Best Art Direction]]
| [[Lyle R. Wheeler|Lyle Wheeler]] || {{won}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Visual Effects|Best Visual Effects]]
| [[Jack Cosgrove (special effects artist)|Jack Cosgrove]], [[Fred Albin]] and [[Arthur Johns]]&lt;br /&gt; Winners were [[Fred Sersen]] and [[E. H. Hansen]] for ''[[The Rains Came]]'' || {{nom}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Original Music Score|Best Music, Original Score]]
| [[Max Steiner]] &lt;br /&gt; Winner was [[Herbert Stothart]] for ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]'' || {{nom}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Best Sound|Best Sound Recording]]
| [[Thomas T. Moulton]] (Samuel Goldwyn Studio Sound Department) &lt;br /&gt; Winner was Bernard B. Brown (Universal Studio Sound Department) for ''[[When Tomorrow Comes (film)|When Tomorrow Comes]]'' || {{nom}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Honorary Award|Special Award]]
| [[William Cameron Menzies]] &lt;br /&gt; For outstanding achievement in the use of color for the enhancement of dramatic mood in the production of ''Gone with the Wind''. || {{yes|Honorary}}
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Academy Award for Technical Achievement|Technical Achievement Award]]
| Don Musgrave and [[Selznick International Pictures]] &lt;br /&gt; For pioneering in the use of coordinated equipment in the production ''Gone with the Wind''. || {{yes|Honorary}}
|}

===African-American reaction===
Black commentators criticised the film for its depiction of black people and as a glorification of slavery. [[Carlton Moss]], a black dramatist, complained in an open letter that whereas ''[[The Birth of a Nation]]'' was a &quot;frontal attack on American history and the Negro people&quot;, ''Gone with the Wind'' was a &quot;rear attack on the same&quot;. He went on to dismiss it as a &quot;nostalgic plea for sympathy for a still living cause of Southern reaction&quot;. Moss further criticized the stereotypical black characterizations, such as the &quot;shiftless and dull-witted Pork&quot;, the &quot;indolent and thoroughly irresponsible Prissy&quot;, Big Sam's &quot;radiant acceptance of slavery&quot;, and Mammy with her &quot;constant haranguing and doting on every wish of Scarlett&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lupack&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Barbara Tepa |last=Lupack |title=Literary Adaptations in Black American Cinema: From Oscar Micheaux to Toni Morrison |year=2002 |publisher=University of Rochester Press |isbn=978-1-58046-103-0 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=hjO7_Ju7lWUC&amp;pg=PA209&amp;lpg=PA209 209]–211}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following Hattie McDaniel's Oscar win, [[Walter Francis White]], leader of the [[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People]], accused her of being an [[Uncle Tom]]. McDaniel responded that she would &quot;rather make seven hundred dollars a week playing a maid than seven dollars being one&quot;; she further questioned White's qualification to speak on behalf of blacks, since he was light-skinned and only one-eighth black.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haskell&quot; /&gt;

Opinion in the black community was generally divided upon release, with the film being called by some a &quot;weapon of terror against black America&quot; and an insult to black audiences, and demonstrations were held in various cities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haskell&quot; /&gt; Even so, some sections of the black community recognized McDaniel's achievements to be representative of progression: some African-Americans crossed picket lines and praised McDaniel's warm and witty characterization, while others hoped that the industry's recognition of her work would lead to increased visibility on screen for other black actors. In its editorial congratulation to McDaniel on winning her Academy Award, ''[[Opportunity: A Journal of Negro Life]]'' used the film as reminder of the &quot;limit&quot; put on black aspiration by old prejudices.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haskell&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lupack&quot; /&gt; [[Malcolm X]] would later recall that &quot;when Butterfly McQueen went into her act, I felt like crawling under the rug&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Reynolds |first=David |title=America, Empire of Liberty: A New History |year=2009 |publisher=[[Penguin UK]] |isbn=978-0-14-190856-4 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ohbINLMYW4IC&amp;q=white+women+are+elegant 241]–242}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Audience response===
[[File:GoneWithTheWind-ticketsalesinJapan-1952-11.jpg|thumb|A long line of people in Japan waiting to buy a ticket for ''Gone With the Wind'' in 1952.]]Upon its release, ''Gone with the Wind'' broke attendance records everywhere. At the [[Capitol Theatre (New York City)|Capitol Theatre]] in New York alone, it was averaging eleven thousand admissions per day in late December,&lt;ref name=&quot;Schatz (1999)&quot; /&gt; and within four years of its release had sold an estimated sixty million tickets across the United States—sales equivalent to just under [[1940 United States Census|half the population at the time]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Young&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Young |first=John |title='Avatar' vs. 'Gone With the Wind |date=February 5, 2010 |work=[[Entertainment Weekly]] |url=http://www.ew.com/article/2010/02/05/avatar-vs-gone-wind |accessdate=February 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=About the 1940 Census |work=Official 1940 Census Website |publisher=[[National Archives and Records Administration]] |url=http://1940census.archives.gov/about |accessdate=February 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It repeated its success overseas, and was a sensational hit during [[the Blitz]] in London, opening in April 1940 and playing for four years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=London Movie Doings |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=June 25, 1944 |at=X3}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time MGM withdrew it from circulation at the end of 1943 its worldwide distribution had returned a [[gross rental]] (the studio's share of the box office gross) of $32 million, making it the [[Timeline of highest-grossing films|most profitable film ever made up to that point]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm articles&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot;/&gt;

Even though it earned its investors roughly twice as much as the previous record-holder, ''The Birth of a Nation'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Finler&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Finler |first=Joel Waldo |year=2003 |title=The Hollywood Story |publisher=Wallflower Press |isbn=978-1-903364-66-6 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=rvVhEJmbfrsC&amp;pg=PA47 47], [https://books.google.com/books?id=rvVhEJmbfrsC&amp;pg=PA356 356]–363}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Time (1940)&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Show Business: Record Wind|date=February 19, 1940|work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,763541,00.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100202110029/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,763541,00.html|archivedate=February 2, 2010|accessdate=January 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[box-office]] performances of the two films were likely much closer. The bulk of the earnings from ''Gone with the Wind'' came from its roadshow and first-run engagements, which represented 70 percent and 50 percent of the box-office gross respectively, before entering general release (which at the time typically saw the distributor's share set at 30–35 percent of the gross).&lt;ref name=&quot;Schatz (1999)&quot; /&gt; In the case of ''The Birth of a Nation'', its distributor, Epoch, sold off many of its distribution territories on a &quot;states rights&quot; basis—which typically amounted to 10 percent of the box-office gross—and Epoch's accounts are only indicative of its own profits from the film, and not the local distributors. [[Carl E. Milliken]], secretary of the [[Motion Picture Producers and Distributors Association]], estimated that ''The Birth of a Nation'' had been seen by fifty million people by 1930.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stokes&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Stokes |first=Melvyn |title=D.W. Griffith's the Birth of a Nation: A History of the Most Controversial Motion Picture of All Time |year=2008 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn=978-0-19-533678-8 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=fGJFpiTjbKwC&amp;pg=PA119 119] &amp; [https://books.google.com/books?id=fGJFpiTjbKwC&amp;pg=PA287 287]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Grieveson&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Grieveson |first=Lee |title=Policing Cinema: Movies and Censorship in Early-Twentieth-Century America |year=2004 |publisher=[[University of California Press]] |isbn=978-0-520-23966-1 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ZzKR3O7C-wAC&amp;pg=PA308 308]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Crowds line up to see &quot;Gone with the Wind&quot; in Pensacola, Florida (1947).jpg|thumb|left|Line up to see ''Gone with the Wind'' in Pensacola, Florida (1947)]]

When it was re-released in 1947, it earned an impressive $5 million rental in the United States and Canada, and was one of the top ten releases of the year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shearer&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Finler&quot; /&gt; Successful re-releases in 1954 and 1961 enabled it to retain its position as the industry's top earner, despite strong challenges from more recent films such as ''Ben-Hur'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas (1963)&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Thomas |first=Bob |authorlink=Bob Thomas (reporter) |agency=[[Associated Press]] |work=[[The Robesonian]] |title=Movie Finances Are No Longer Hidden From Scrutiny |date=August 1, 1963 |page=[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=QsBVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=iUANAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7022,1836881 10] }}&lt;/ref&gt; but it was finally overtaken by ''[[The Sound of Music (film)|The Sound of Music]]'' in 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berkowitz&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Berkowitz |first=Edward D.  |title=Mass Appeal: The Formative Age of the Movies, Radio, and TV |series=Cambridge Essential Histories |year=2010  | publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-88908-7 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=ofKqd-ElfaoC&amp;pg=PA160 160]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1967 reissue was unusual in that MGM opted to roadshow it, a decision that turned it into the most successful re-release in the history of the industry. It generated a box-office gross of $68 million, making it MGM's most lucrative picture after ''[[Doctor Zhivago (film)|Doctor Zhivago]]'' from the latter half of the decade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hall |first1=Sheldon |last2=Neale |first2=Stephen |title=Epics, spectacles, and blockbusters: a Hollywood history |year=2010 |publisher=[[Wayne State University Press]] |isbn=978-0-8143-3008-1 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=jhvrSwOOsRgC&amp;pg=PA181 181]–[https://books.google.com/books?id=jhvrSwOOsRgC&amp;pg=PA182 182]}}&lt;/ref&gt; MGM earned a rental of $41 million from the release,&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas (1971)&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Thomas |first=Bob |authorlink=Bob Thomas (reporter) |title=Reissues playing big role in movie marketing today |date=May 6, 1971 |agency=[[Associated Press]] |work=[[The Register-Guard]] |page=[https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=hLRVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=L-EDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6732,1474472 9E]}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the U.S. and Canadian share amounting to over $30 million, placing it second only to ''[[The Graduate]]'' for that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Finler&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas (1971)&quot; /&gt; Including its $6.7 million rental from the 1961 reissue,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kay |first=Eddie Dorman |title=Box office champs: the most popular movies of the last 50 years |year=1990 |publisher=[[Random House Value Publishing]] |isbn=978-0-517-69212-7 |page=92}}&lt;/ref&gt; it was the fourth highest-earner of the decade in the North American market, with only ''The Sound of Music'', ''The Graduate'' and ''Doctor Zhivago'' making more for their distributors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Finler&quot; /&gt; A further re-release in 1971 allowed it to briefly recapture the record from ''The Sound of Music'', bringing its total worldwide gross rental to about $116 million by the end of 1971—more than trebling its earnings from its initial release—before losing the record again the following year to ''[[The Godfather]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kramer&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic Monthly (1973)&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Anna |last=Akhmatova |title=Gone With the Wind |work=[[The Atlantic Monthly]] |year=1973 |volume=231 |page=[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=38wmAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22As+of+the+end+of+1971,+GWTW+stood+as+the+all-time+money-drawing+movie,+with+a+take+of+$116+million%22&amp;dq=%22As+of+the+end+of+1971,+GWTW+stood+as+the+all-time+money-drawing+movie,+with+a+take+of+$116+million%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=0W0FULbTJ6KI0AXngszgBw&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAA 2] |quote=As of the end of 1971, GWTW stood as the all-time money-drawing movie, with a take of $116 million, and, with this year's reissues, it should continue to run ahead of the second place contender and all-time ''kaffee-mit-schlag'' spectacle.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Across all releases, it is estimated that ''Gone with the Wind'' has sold over [[List of highest-grossing films in Canada and the United States#Adjusted for ticket-price inflation|200 million tickets in the United States and Canada]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Young&quot; /&gt; and 35 million tickets in the United Kingdom,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Gone with the Wind tops film list |date=November 28, 2004 |work=[[BBC News]] |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4049645.stm |accessdate=June 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; generating more theater admissions in those territories than any other film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/alltime/adjusted.htm?adjust_yr=1&amp;p=.htm |title=Domestic Grosses – Adjusted for Ticket Price Inflation |work=[[Box Office Mojo]] |accessdate=February 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Ultimate Film Chart |publisher=[[British Film Institute]] |url=http://old.bfi.org.uk/features/ultimatefilm/chart/index.php |accessdate=August 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In total, ''Gone with the Wind'' has grossed over $390 million globally at the box office;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Gone with the Wind |work=The Numbers |publisher=Nash Information Services |url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movie/Gone-with-the-Wind#tab=summary |accessdate=February 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2007 Turner Entertainment estimated the gross to be equivalent to approximately $3.3 billion when adjusted for [[inflation]] to current prices,&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm articles&quot; /&gt; while ''[[Guinness World Records]]'' arrived at a figure of $3.44 billion in 2014, making it the [[List of highest-grossing films#Highest-grossing films adjusted for inflation|most successful film in cinema history]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Highest box office film gross – inflation adjusted|year=2014|publisher=[[Guinness World Records]]|url=http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/highest-box-office-film-gross-inflation-adjusted/|accessdate=February 9, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film remains immensely popular with audiences into the 21st century, having been [[List of films considered the best#Audience polls|voted the most popular film]] in two nationwide polls of Americans undertaken by [[Harris Interactive]] in 2008, and again in 2014. The market research firm surveyed over two thousand U.S. adults, with the results weighted by age, sex, race/ethnicity, education, region and household income so their proportions matched the composition of the adult population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |first=Regina A. |last=Corso |title=Frankly My Dear, The Force is With Them as Gone With the Wind and Star Wars are the Top Two All Time Favorite Movies |date=February 21, 2008 |publisher=[[Harris Interactive]] |url=http://www.harrisinteractive.com/vault/Harris-Interactive-Poll-Research-Frankly-My-Dear-The-Force-is-With-Them-as-Gone-Wit-2008-02.pdf |accessdate=July 13, 2014 |format=PDF |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130614055709/http://www.harrisinteractive.com/vault/Harris-Interactive-Poll-Research-Frankly-My-Dear-The-Force-is-With-Them-as-Gone-Wit-2008-02.pdf |archivedate=June 14, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |first=Larry |last=Shannon-Missal |title=Gone but Not Forgotten: Gone with the Wind is Still America's Favorite Movie |date=December 17, 2014 |publisher=[[Harris Interactive]] |url=http://www.harrisinteractive.com/NewsRoom/HarrisPolls/tabid/447/ctl/ReadCustom%20Default/mid/1508/ArticleId/1535/Default.aspx |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141228064846/http://www.harrisinteractive.com/NewsRoom/HarrisPolls/tabid/447/ctl/ReadCustom%20Default/mid/1508/ArticleId/1535/Default.aspx |archivedate=December 28, 2014 |accessdate=February 13, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critical re-evaluation===
{{Quote box | title=[[AFI 100 Years... series]]
|source= American Film Institute&lt;ref name=&quot;afi-lists&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=AFI's 100 Years...The Complete Lists |work=[[American Film Institute]] |url=http://www.afi.com/100Years/downloads.aspx |accessdate=February 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|quote =
* [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies]] – #4
* [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Passions]] – #2
* [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Heroes and Villains]]
** Rhett Butler, Hero – Nominated
** Scarlett O'Hara, Hero – Nominated
* [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movie Quotes]]:
** &quot;[[Frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn]].&quot; – #1
** &quot;After all, tomorrow is another day!&quot; – #31
** &quot;As God is my witness, I'll never be hungry again.&quot; – #59
** &quot;Fiddle-dee-dee.&quot; – Nominated
** &quot;I don't know nothin' 'bout birthin' babies.&quot; – Nominated
* [[AFI's 100 Years of Film Scores]] – #2
* [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Cheers]] – #43
* [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies (10th Anniversary Edition)]] – #6
* [[AFI's 10 Top 10]] – #4 [[Epic film]]
| align = right | salign = right | width = 23em | bgcolor = #F0EAD6}}
In revisiting the film in the 1970s, [[Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr.|Arthur Schlesinger]] noted that Hollywood films generally age well, revealing an unexpected depth or integrity, but in the case of ''Gone with the Wind'' time has not treated it kindly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schlesinger&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Arthur |last=Schlesinger |authorlink=Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. |work=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]] |date=March 1973 |title=Time, alas, has treated Gone With the Wind cruelly |volume=231 |issue=3 |page=64 |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/73mar/schles.htm |accessdate=February 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Schickel]] posits that one measure of a film's quality is to ask what you can remember of it, and the film falls down in this regard: unforgettable imagery and dialogue are simply not present.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schickel&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Richard |last=Schickel |authorlink=Richard Schickel |work=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]] |date=March 1973 |title=Glossy, Sentimental, Chuckle-headed |volume=231 |issue=3 |page=71 |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/73mar/schick.htm |accessdate=February 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stanley Kauffmann]], likewise, also found the film to be a largely forgettable experience, claiming he could only remember two scenes vividly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kauffmann&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Stanley |last=Kauffman |authorlink=Stanley Kauffmann |work=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]] |date=March 1973 |title=The Romantic Is Still Popular |volume=231 |issue=3 |page=61 |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/73mar/kauff.htm |accessdate=February 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Schickel and Schlesinger put this down to it being &quot;badly written&quot;, in turn describing the dialogue as &quot;flowery&quot; and possessing a &quot;picture postcard&quot; sensibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schlesinger&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schickel&quot; /&gt; Schickel also believes the film fails as popular art, in that it has limited rewatch value—a sentiment that Kauffmann also concurs with, stating that having watched it twice he hopes &quot;never to see it again: twice is twice as much as any lifetime needs&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schickel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kauffmann&quot; /&gt; Both Schickel and [[Andrew Sarris]] identify the film's main failing is in possessing a producer's sensibility rather than an artistic one: having gone through so many directors and writers the film does not carry a sense of being &quot;created&quot; or &quot;directed&quot;, but rather having emerged &quot;steaming from the crowded kitchen&quot;, where the main creative force was a producer's obsession in making the film as literally faithful to the novel as possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schickel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarris&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Andrew |last=Sarris |authorlink=Andrew Sarris |work=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]] |date=March 1973 |title=This moviest of All Movies |volume=231 |issue=3 |page=58 |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/73mar/sarris.htm |accessdate=February 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sarris concedes that despite its artistic failings, the film does hold a mandate around the world as the &quot;single most beloved entertainment ever produced&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarris&quot; /&gt; [[Judith Crist]] observes that, kitsch aside, the film is &quot;undoubtedly still the best and most durable piece of popular entertainment to have come off the Hollywood assembly lines&quot;, the product of a showman with &quot;taste and intelligence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crist&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Judith |last=Crist |authorlink=Judith Crist |work=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]] |date=March 1973 |title=Glorious Excesses |volume=231 |issue=3 |page=67 |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/73mar/crist.htm |accessdate=February 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schlesinger notes that the first half of the film does have a &quot;sweep and vigor&quot; that aspire to its epic theme, but—finding agreement with the film's contemporary criticisms—the personal lives take over in the second half, and it ends up losing its theme in unconvincing sentimentality.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schlesinger&quot; /&gt; Kauffmann also finds interesting parallels with ''The Godfather'', which had just replaced ''Gone with the Wind'' as the highest-grosser at the time: both were produced from &quot;ultra-American&quot; best-selling novels, both live within codes of honor that are romanticized, and both in essence offer cultural fabrication or revisionism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kauffmann&quot; /&gt;

The critical perception of the film has shifted in the intervening years, which resulted in it being ranked 235th in ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]''{{'}}s prestigious [[decennial]] critics poll in 2012,&lt;ref name=&quot;sight and sound&quot; /&gt; and in 2015 sixty-two international film critics polled by the [[BBC]] voted it the 97th best American film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=BBC Culture |title=The 100 greatest American films |date=July 20, 2015 |publisher=[[BBC]] |url=http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20150720-the-100-greatest-american-films |accessdate=July 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Industry recognition===
The film has featured in several high-profile industry polls: in 1977 it was voted the most popular film by the [[American Film Institute]] (AFI), in a poll of the organization's membership;&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm notes&quot; /&gt; the AFI also ranked the film fourth on its &quot;[[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies|100 Greatest Movies]]&quot; list in 1998,&lt;ref name=&quot;afi-movie&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies |publisher=[[American Film Institute]] |date=June 1998 |url=http://www.afi.com/100Years/movies.aspx |accessdate=February 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; with it slipping down to sixth place in the [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies (10th Anniversary Edition)|tenth anniversary edition]] in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;afi-movie-10th&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies (10th Anniversary Edition) |publisher=[[American Film Institute]] |date=June 20, 2007 |url=http://www.afi.com/100Years/movies10.aspx |accessdate=February 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Film directors ranked it 322nd in the 2012 edition of the decennial ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]'' poll,&lt;ref name=&quot;sight and sound&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The Greatest Films Poll: Gone with the Wind |year=2012 |publisher=[[British Film Institute]] |url=http://explore.bfi.org.uk/sightandsoundpolls/2012/film/4ce2b6ab5808b |accessdate=March 3, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2016 it was selected as the ninth best &quot;directorial achievement&quot; in a [[Directors Guild of America]] members poll.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The 80 Best-Directed Films |date=Spring 2016 |publisher=[[Directors Guild of America]] |url=http://www.dga.org/Craft/DGAQ/All-Articles/1602-Spring-2016/80th-Film-Poll.aspx |accessdate=May 4, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, it placed fifteenth in an extensive poll undertaken by ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'', which ballotted every studio, agency, publicity firm and production house in the [[Hollywood]] region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Hollywood's 100 Favorite Films |date=June 25, 2014 |work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]] |url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/lists/best-hollywood-movies-all-time-818512 |accessdate=July 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Gone with the Wind'' was selected for preservation in the U.S. [[National Film Registry]] in 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm articles&quot; /&gt;

==Analysis==

===Racial criticism===
''Gone with the Wind'' has been criticized as having perpetuated Civil War myths and black stereotypes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernan&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1=Hernán |last1=Vera |first2=Andrew Mark |last2=Gordon |year=2003 |title=Screen Saviors: Hollywood Fictions of Whiteness |publisher=[[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]] |isbn=978-0-8476-9947-6 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=6ZAPD2YdBXYC&amp;pg=PR8 viii] &amp; [https://books.google.com/books?id=6ZAPD2YdBXYC&amp;pg=PA102 102]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Reynolds (English historian)|David Reynolds]] writes that &quot;The white women are elegant, their menfolk noble or at least dashing. And, in the background, the black slaves are mostly dutiful and content, clearly incapable of an independent existence.&quot; Reynolds likened ''Gone with the Wind'' to ''The Birth of a Nation'' and other re-imaginings of the South during the era of segregation, in which white Southerners are portrayed as defending traditional values and the issue of slavery is largely ignored.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reynolds&quot; /&gt; The film has been described as a &quot;regression&quot; that promotes the myth of the black rapist and the honourable and defensive role of the [[Ku Klux Klan]] during Reconstruction,&lt;ref name=&quot;Silk&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1=Catherine |last1=Silk |first2=Johnk |last2=Silk |year=1990 |title=Racism and Anti-Racism in American Popular Culture: Portrayals of African-Americans in Fiction and Film |publisher=[[Manchester University Press]] |isbn=978-0-7190-3070-3 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=JtNRAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA141 141]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and as a &quot;social propaganda&quot; film offering a &quot;[[white supremacist]]&quot; view of the past.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernan&quot; /&gt; From 1972 to 1996, the [[Atlanta Historical Society]] held a number of ''Gone with the Wind'' exhibits, among them a 1994 exhibit titled, &quot;Disputed Territories:  ''Gone with the Wind'' and Southern Myths&quot;. One of the questions explored by the exhibit was &quot;How True to Life Were the Slaves in GWTW?&quot;  This section showed slave experiences were diverse and concluded that the &quot;happy darky&quot; was a myth, as was the belief that all slaves experienced violence and brutality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dickey |first=Jennifer W. |year=2014 |title=A Tough Little Patch of History: Gone with the Wind and the politics of memory |publisher=[[University of Arkansas Press]] |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=jdtXAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA66#v=onepage 66] |isbn= 978-1-55728-657-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite factual inaccuracies in its depiction of the Reconstruction period, it nevertheless reflects contemporary interpretations common throughout the early 20th century. One pervasive viewpoint argued by academics is reflected in a brief scene in which Mammy fends off a leering [[freedman]]: a government official can be heard offering bribes to the emancipated slaves for their votes. The clear inference is that freedmen are ignorant about politics and unprepared for freedom, unwittingly becoming the tools of corrupt Reconstruction officials. While perpetuating some [[Lost Cause of the Confederacy|Lost Cause]] myths, the film makes concessions in regards to others. After the attack on Scarlett in the shanty town, a group of men including Scarlett's husband Frank, Rhett Butler and Ashley raid the town; in the novel they belong to the Ku Klux Klan, representing the common trope of protecting the white woman's virtue, but the filmmakers consciously neutralize the presence of the Klan in the film by referring to it only as a &quot;political meeting&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruiz&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=W. Bryan Rommel |last=Ruiz |year=2010 |title=American History Goes to the Movies: Hollywood and the American Experience |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |isbn=978-0-203-83373-5 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=MEfE-WxwAJwC&amp;pg=PA61 61]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thomas Cripps has argued that the film in some respects undercuts racial stereotypes;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smyth&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=J.E. |last=Smyth |year=2006 |title=Reconstructing American Historical Cinema: From Cimarron to Citizen Kane |publisher=[[University Press of Kentucky]] |isbn=978-0-8131-7147-0 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=R5_n4834AgYC&amp;pg=PA164 164]}}&lt;/ref&gt; in particular, the film created greater engagement between Hollywood and black audiences,&lt;ref name=&quot;Smyth&quot; /&gt; with dozens of movies making small gestures in recognition of the emerging trend.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lupack&quot; /&gt; Only a few weeks after its initial run, a story editor at Warner wrote a memo to [[Walter Wanger]] about ''Mississippi Belle'', a script that contained the worst excesses of plantation films, suggesting that ''Gone with the Wind'' had made the film &quot;unproducible&quot;. More than any film since ''The Birth of a Nation'', it unleashed a variety of social forces that foreshadowed an alliance of white liberals and blacks who encouraged the expectation that blacks would one day achieve equality. According to Cripps, the film eventually became a template for measuring social change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lupack&quot; /&gt;

===Depiction of marital rape===
One of the most notorious and widely condemned scenes in ''Gone with the Wind'' depicts what is now legally defined as &quot;[[marital rape]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;White&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor1-first=John |editor1-last=White |editor2-first=Sabine |editor2-last=Haenni |year=2009 |title=Fifty Key American Films |series=Routledge Key Guides|publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-203-89113-1 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=u7gZRtn44AAC&amp;pg=PA59 59]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hickok&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Eugene W., Jr. |last=Hickok |year=1991 |title=The Bill of Rights: Original Meaning and Current Understanding |publisher=[[University of Virginia Press]] |isbn=978-0-8139-1336-0 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Eik_eoTn6KEC&amp;pg=PA103 103]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The scene begins with Scarlett and Rhett at the bottom of the staircase, where he begins to kiss her, refusing to be told 'no' by the struggling and frightened Scarlett;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paludi&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Michele A. |last=Paludi |year=2012 |title=The Psychology of Love |volume=2 |series=Women's Psychology |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |isbn=978-0-313-39315-0 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=BtK9MKx8QBQC&amp;pg=PR26 xxvi]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Allison&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1=Julie A. |last1=Allison |first2=Lawrence S. |last2=Wrightsman |year=1993 |title=Rape: The Misunderstood Crime |edition=2 |publisher=[[Sage Publications]] |isbn=978-0-8039-3707-9 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=GI0BXXNQJ-QC&amp;pg=PA90 90]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rhett overcomes her resistance and carries her up the stairs to the bedroom,&lt;ref name=&quot;Paludi&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Allison&quot; /&gt; where the audience is left in no doubt that she will &quot;get what's coming to her&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pagelow&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1=Mildred Daley |last1=Pagelow |first2=Lloyd W. |last2=Pagelow |year=1984 |title=Family Violence |series=Praeger special studies |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |isbn=978-0-275-91623-7 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=VPPapvrJsTcC&amp;pg=PA420 420]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next scene, the following morning, shows Scarlett glowing with barely suppressed sexual satisfaction;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paludi&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Allison&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pagelow&quot; /&gt; Rhett apologizes for his behavior, blaming it on his drinking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paludi&quot; /&gt; The scene has been accused of combining romance and rape by making them indistinguishable from each other,&lt;ref name=&quot;Paludi&quot; /&gt; and of reinforcing a notion about [[forced seduction|forced sex]]: that women secretly enjoy it, and it is an acceptable way for a man to treat his wife.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pagelow&quot; /&gt;

[[Molly Haskell]] has argued that nevertheless, women are mostly uncritical of the scene, and that by and large it is consistent with what women have in mind when they [[Rape fantasy|fantasize about being raped]]. Their fantasies revolve around love and romance rather than forced sex; they assume that Scarlett was not an unwilling sexual partner and wanted Rhett to take the initiative and insist on having sexual intercourse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frus&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Phyllis |last=Frus |editor-first=J. David |editor-last=Slocum |chapter=Documenting Domestic Violence in American Films |year=2001 |title=Violence in American Cinema |series=Afi Film Readers |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-415-92810-6 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=3bIYD6uo3jQC&amp;pg=RA1-PA231 231]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Photograph of First Archivist of the United States R. D. W. Connor Receiving Film &quot;Gone With The Wind&quot; from Senator George of Georgia and Loew's Eastern Division Manager Carter Barron, 1941.tif|thumb|First Archivist of the United States R. D. W. Connor receiving the film ''Gone with the Wind'' from Senator Walter F. George of Georgia (on the left) and Loew's Eastern Division Manager Carter Barron, 1941]]
===In popular culture===
''Gone with the Wind'' and its production have been explicitly referenced, satirized, dramatized and analyzed on numerous occasions across a range of media, from contemporaneous works such as ''[[Second Fiddle (1939 film)|Second Fiddle]]''—a 1939 film spoofing the &quot;search for Scarlett&quot;—to current television shows, such as ''[[The Simpsons]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hernan&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Nugent |first=Frank S. |authorlink=Frank S. Nugent |title=Second Fiddle (1939) The Screen; 'Second Fiddle,' With Tyrone Power and Sonja Heine, Opens at the Roxy--Reports on New Foreign Films |date=July 1, 1939 |work=[[The New York Times]] |url=http://www.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9E04EFD81F3FE432A25752C0A9619C946894D6CF |accessdate=June 19, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gomez&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=M. Carmen |last=Gómez-Galisteo|title=The Wind Is Never Gone: Sequels, Parodies and Rewritings of Gone with the Wind|year=2011|publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]]|isbn=978-0-7864-5927-8|page=173}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Scarlett O'Hara War]]'' (a 1980 television dramatization of the casting of Scarlett),&lt;ref name=&quot;allmovie&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The Scarlett O'Hara War (1980) |work=[[Allmovie]] |publisher=[[Rovi Corporation]] |url=http://www.allmovie.com/movie/the-scarlett-ohara-war-v128737 |accessdate=March 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Moonlight and Magnolias'' (a 2007 play by [[Ron Hutchinson (screenwriter)|Ron Hutchinson]] that dramatizes Ben Hecht's five-day re-write of the script),&lt;ref name=&quot;Spencer&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Charles |last=Spencer |title=Moonlight and Magnolias: Comedy captures the birth of a movie classic |date=October 8, 2007 |work=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/theatre/drama/3668405/Moonlight-and-Magnolias-Comedy-captures-the-birth-of-a-movie-classic.html |accessdate=January 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;[[Went with the Wind!]]&quot; (a sketch on ''[[The Carol Burnett Show]]'' that parodied the film in the aftermath of its television debut in 1976) are among the more noteworthy examples of its enduring presence in popular culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot; /&gt; It was also the subject of a 1988 documentary, ''[[The Making of a Legend: Gone with the Wind]]'', detailing the film's difficult production history.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm legend&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Thames |first=Stephanie |title=The Making Of A Legend: Gone With The Wind (1988) – Articles |work=TCM database |publisher=[[Turner Classic Movies]] |url=http://www.tcm.com/tcmdb/title/304578/The-Making-Of-A-Legend-Gone-With-The-Wind/articles.html |accessdate=March 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1990, the [[United States Postal Service]] issued a stamp depicting Clark Gable and Vivien Leigh embracing in a scene from the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;McAllister&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=McAllister |first=Bill |title=Postal Service Goes Hollywood, Puts Legendary Stars on Stamp |date=March 5, 1990 |work=[[The Daily Gazette]] |page=[https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1957&amp;dat=19900303&amp;id=V3UhAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=AokFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5191,1080306 B9] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sequel===
Following publication of her novel, Margaret Mitchell was inundated with requests for a sequel but claimed to not have a notion of what happened to Scarlett and Rhett, and that she had &quot;left them to their ultimate fate&quot;. Mitchell continued to resist pressure from Selznick and MGM to write a sequel until her death in 1949. In 1975, her brother, Stephens Mitchell (who assumed control of her estate), authorized a sequel to be jointly produced by MGM and [[Universal Studios]] on a budget of $12 million. [[Anne Edwards]] was commissioned to write the sequel as a novel which would then be adapted into a screenplay, and published in conjunction with the film's release. Edwards submitted a 775-page manuscript entitled ''Tara, The Continuation of Gone with the Wind'', set between 1872 and 1882 focusing on Scarlett's divorce from Rhett; MGM was not satisfied with the story and the deal collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartel&quot; /&gt;

The idea was revived in the 1990s, when a sequel was finally produced in 1994, in the form of a television [[miniseries]]. ''[[Scarlett (TV miniseries)|Scarlett]]'' was based upon [[Scarlett (Ripley novel)|the novel]] by [[Alexandra Ripley]], itself a sequel to Mitchell's book. British actors [[Joanne Whalley]] and [[Timothy Dalton]] were cast as Scarlett and Rhett, and the series follows Scarlett's relocation to Ireland after again becoming pregnant by Rhett.&lt;ref name=&quot;scarlett&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Scarlett (1994) |work=[[Allmovie]] |publisher=[[Rovi Corporation]] |url=http://www.allmovie.com/movie/scarlett-v135447 |accessdate=March 3, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of films featuring slavery]]

==References==
'''Explanatory notes'''
{{Reflist|group=nb}}

'''Citations'''
{{Reflist|2}}

'''Further reading'''
* {{cite book |last=Bridges |first=Herb |year=1999 |title=Gone with the Wind: The Three-Day Premiere in Atlanta |publisher=[[Mercer University Press]] |isbn=978-0-86554-672-1}}
* {{cite book |last1=Cameron |first1=Judy |last2=Christman |first2=Paul J |year=1989 |title=The Art of Gone with the Wind: The Making of a Legend |publisher=[[Prentice Hall]] |isbn=978-0-13-046740-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Harmetz |first=Aljean |authorlink=Aljean Harmetz |year=1996 |title=On the Road to Tara: The Making of Gone with the Wind |location=New York |publisher=[[Harry N. Abrams]] |isbn=978-0-8109-3684-3}}
* {{cite book |last=Lambert |first=Gavin |authorlink=Gavin Lambert |year=1973 |title=GWTW: The Making of Gone With the Wind |location=New York |publisher=[[Little, Brown and Company]] |isbn=978-0-316-51284-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Vertrees |first=Alan David |year=1997 |title=Selznick's Vision: Gone with the Wind and Hollywood Filmmaking |publisher=[[University of Texas Press]] |isbn=978-0-292-78729-2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{IMDb title|0031381|Gone with the Wind}}
* {{tcmdb title|414427|Gone with the Wind}}
* [http://www.tcm.com/mediaroom/video/72265/Gone-With-The-Wind-Premiere-A-Short-Subject-.html ''Gone with the Wind''] at the [[Turner Classic Movies|TCM]] Mediaroom
* [http://album.atlantahistorycenter.com/store/Products/94106-william-hartsfield-gone-with-the-wind-premiere-film.aspx William Hartsfield] and [http://album.atlantahistorycenter.com/store/Products/94105-william-j-folsom-gone-with-the-wind-premiere-film.aspx Russell Bellman] premiere films at the [[Atlanta History Center]].
* [http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/exhibitions/web/gonewiththewind/ ''Gone with the Wind'' Online Exhibit] at the [[Harry Ransom Center]]
* [http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/unbound/flashbks/gonewind.htm ''Gone With the Wind'' article series] at ''[[The Atlantic]]''
* [http://catalog.oscars.org/vwebv/holdingsInfo?bibId{{=}}71680 Walter Plunkett costume design drawings for ''Gone with the Wind''] at the [[Margaret Herrick Library]]
* {{Rotten Tomatoes|gone_with_the_wind|Gone with the Wind}}

{{Gone with the Wind}}
{{David O. Selznick}}
{{Victor Fleming}}
{{AcademyAwardBestPicture 1927–1940}}
{{Authority control}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gone With The Wind (Film)}}
[[Category:Works based on Gone with the Wind]]

[[Category:1939 films]]
[[Category:1930s historical films]]
[[Category:1930s romance films]] &lt;!-- http://www.allmovie.com/movie/gone-with-the-wind-v20278 --&gt;
[[Category:1930s romantic drama films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American Civil War films]]
[[Category:American epic films]]
[[Category:Epic films based on actual events]]
[[Category:American romantic drama films]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Best Picture Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Culture of Atlanta]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Film scores by Max Steiner]]
[[Category:Films about American slavery]]
[[Category:Films about revenge]]
[[Category:Films based on American novels]]
[[Category:Films directed by Victor Fleming]]
[[Category:Films featuring a Best Actress Academy Award-winning performance]]
[[Category:Films featuring a Best Supporting Actress Academy Award-winning performance]]
[[Category:Films produced by David O. Selznick]]
[[Category:Films set in Georgia (U.S. state)]]
[[Category:Films set in Atlanta]]
[[Category:Films set in London]]
[[Category:Films set in the 1860s]]
[[Category:Films set in the 19th century]]
[[Category:Films shot in California]]
[[Category:Films whose art director won the Best Art Direction Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films whose cinematographer won the Best Cinematography Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films whose director won the Best Directing Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films whose editor won the Best Film Editing Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films whose writer won the Best Adapted Screenplay Academy Award]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1918–45)]]
[[Category:Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer films]]
[[Category:Rape in fiction]]
[[Category:Romantic epic films]]
[[Category:Selznick International Pictures films]]
[[Category:United States National Film Registry films]]
[[Category:Historical romance films]]</text>
      <sha1>qb6ar4spfxzrioet9x1vvw6tmxsl0rd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
