<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Heilongjiang hand cannon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49808174</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744310805</id>
      <parentid>744310769</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-14T12:17:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yprpyqp</username>
        <id>22826736</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11972">{{good article}}
[[File:Heilongjianghandcannon.jpg|thumb|right|The Heilongjiang hand cannon]]
The '''Heilongjiang hand cannon''' or hand-gun{{cref|a}} is a bronze [[hand cannon]] manufactured no later than 1288 and possibly the world's oldest confirmed surviving [[firearm]].{{sfn|Chase|2003|p=32}} It weighs 3.55&amp;nbsp;kg (7.83 pounds) and is 34 centimeters (13.4 inches) long. The hand cannon was light enough that it could be carried on the backs of [[Yuan dynasty]] soldiers.{{sfnm|Needham|1987|1p=290|Needham|1987|2p=304}}

The Heilongjiang hand cannon was excavated during the 1970s in Banlachengzi, a village in the province of [[Heilongjiang]] in [[Manchuria]].{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=293}} It was found alongside other bronze artifacts made in the style of the [[Jurchen people|Jurchen]] [[Jurchen Jin|Jin]] [[list of Chinese dynasties|Dynasty]] (12th–13th century).{{sfn|Chase|2003|p=32}}

The hand cannon likely originates from battles fought nearby Banlachengzi in 1287 and 1288.{{sfn|Chase|2003|p=32}} The ''[[History of Yuan|Yuanshi]]'' reports that a Jurchen commander led a group of soldiers carrying hand cannons into a military camp in 1288.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=304}} The cannon currently resides at the [[Heilongjiang Provincial Museum]] in [[Harbin]], China.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=290}} 

==Description==
The Heilongjiang hand cannon is 34 centimeters (13.4 inches) long without a handle and weighs 3.55&amp;nbsp;kg (7.83 pounds). The diameter of the interior at the end of the [[Gun barrel|barrel]] is 2.6&amp;nbsp;cm (1.0 inches).{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=290}} The barrel is the lengthiest part of the hand cannon and is 6.9 inches long.{{sfnm|Chase|2003|1p=32|Needham|1987|2p=293}} There is no inscription on the hand cannon.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=293}}

The hand cannon has a bulbous base at the [[breech-loading weapon|breech]] called the ''yaoshi'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|藥室}}) or gunpowder chamber. The explosion that propels the [[projectile]] occurs in the gunpowder chamber.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=293}}{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=289}} The diameter of the Heilongjiang hand-gun gunpowder chamber is 6.6&amp;nbsp;cm (2.6 inches).{{sfn|Chase|2003|p=32}} The gunpowder chamber has a [[touch hole]], a small hole for the fuse that ignites the gunpowder.{{sfnm|Lorge|2008|1p=69|Needham|1987|2p=293}} Behind the gunpowder chamber is a socket shaped like a trumpet where the handle of the hand cannon is inserted.{{sfnm|Chase|2003|1p=32|Needham|1987|2p=293}}

The walls of the explosion chamber were thickened to strengthen the chamber so that it could withstand the [[propellant]] explosion.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=289}} The bulbous shape of the base gave the earliest Chinese and Western cannons a vase-like or pear-like appearance, which gradually disappeared when advancements in [[metallurgy|metallurgical]] technology made the bulbous base obsolete.{{sfnm|Needham|1987|1p=289|Needham|1987|2p=330}}

==Historical context==
{{main|History of cannon|History of firearms}}
Gunpowder was invented in China in the 9th century.{{sfn|Parker|1995|p=106}}  The Taoist alchemical book ''[[Zhenyuan miaodao yaolüe]]'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|真元妙道要略}}) from the mid-800s contains a passage that mentions the use of gunpowder. By the 12th century, Song dynasty forces were fighting battles with gunpowder weapons such as [[fire lance]]s, [[grenades]], and metal [[bombard (weapon)|bombards]].{{sfnm|Parker|1995|1p=106|Chase|2003|2p=31}} Exploding gunpowder bombs were used as early as 1126 during the [[Jingkang Incident]], when the Jurchen [[Jin dynasty (1115–1234)|Jin dynasty]] besieged the Song capital of Kaifeng. The Song launched explosive bombs called ''pili pao'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|霹雳炮}}) at the besiegers.{{sfn|Haw|2013|p=448}}

The ancestor of the cannon and hand cannon is the Chinese fire lance.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=220}}  The fire lance is a spear tied with a bamboo or paper barrel that could fire projectiles.{{sfn|Chase|2003|pp=31–32}} The transition between the fire lance to the cannon or hand cannon was gradual, so literary references to a weapon called ''huotong'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|火筒}}; &quot;fire tube&quot;) can either denote fire lances or metal-barrel firearms.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=222}} The ''Xingjun Xuzhi'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|行軍須知}}; &quot;What an Army Commander in the Field ought to Know&quot;) dated 1230 lists ''huotong'' among other gunpowder weapons, but may refer to either a fire lance or a hand cannon.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=222}} Nevertheless, archaeologists have discovered hundreds of surviving metal cannons and hand cannons in China from the 13th and 14th centuries.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=284}}

The oldest of these excavated cannons is the [[Wuwei cannon]] dated 1227.{{sfn|Haw|2013|p=450}}  It was discovered in [[Wuwei, Gansu]] and likely originates from the [[Western Xia]] period. The Wuwei cannon has a weight of 108.5 kilograms (239 pounds), a diameter of 12 centimeters (5 inches), and a length of 1 meter. An iron [[Round shot|cannonball]] and a small quantity of gunpowder were also discovered at the Wuwei archaeological site.{{sfn|Haw|2013|p=450}}

The earliest cannon inscribed with its date of manufacture is a bronze cannon dated 1298 with an inscription in [['Phags-pa script]].{{sfn|Haw|2013|p=450}} Outside of archaeological finds, appearances of the cannon in Chinese art may suggest that the cannon was invented as early as the 12th century.{{sfn|Parker|1995|p=106}} The oldest artistic representation of a cannon is a stone relief sculpture dated 1128. The sculpture was discovered in 1985 carved in the walls of Cave 149 of the [[Dazu Rock Carvings]] in [[Dazu District|Dazu]], [[Chongqing]].{{sfn|Haw|2013|p=451}}

The Heilongjiang hand-gun dated 1288 is the earliest extant hand cannon.{{sfnm|Lorge|2008|1p=viii|Needham|1987|2p=580}} At 3.55&amp;nbsp;kg (7.83 pounds), it is considerably lighter than older gunpowder weapons such as the bulky [[trebuchet]]s that were used to launch explosive bombs.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=294}}{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=290}} Since the earliest textual reference to a hand cannon is dated 1230 and the oldest surviving hand cannon is dated 1288, the invention of the hand cannon likely occurred in the mid-13th century.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=304}} The invention of the metal-barrel hand cannon in China did not diminish the popularity of the earlier bamboo-barrel fire lances. The fire lance was cheaper and more portable than the hand cannon, so it was still used in China until the 16th century when the [[musket]] replaced the fire lance.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=251}}

==Excavation and dating==
The hand cannon was discovered in July 1970 at an [[archaeological site]] in Banlachengzi village ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|半拉城子}}).{{sfnm|Lorge|2008|1p=69|Needham|1987|2p=293}} The village is situated on the shores of the [[Ashi River]] in [[Harbin]]'s [[Acheng District]].{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=293}}

The archaeologists discovered several bronze objects that were excavated with the hand cannon.{{sfn|Chase|2003|p=32}} The excavated objects were a bronze vase, a bronze mirror, and a bronze cooking pan. All the bronze artifacts were manufactured in the style of the Jurchen Jin dynasty.{{sfn|Chase|2003|p=32}} The Jin dynasty collapsed after the Mongols besieged and [[Siege of Caizhou|captured Caizhou]] in 1234, which suggests that the Heilongjiang hand-gun can reasonably be dated to the 13th century at the latest.{{sfnm|Franke|1994|1pp=264–265|Needham|1987|2p=293}}

The dating of the Heilongjiang hand-gun is based on battles in 1287 and 1288 that were fought near the site where the archaeologists discovered the hand-gun.{{sfn|Chase|2003|p=32}} The battles were part of Mongol prince [[Nayan (Mongol Prince)|Nayan]]'s rebellion in Manchuria against [[Kublai Khan]], the emperor of the Yuan dynasty.{{sfn|Rossabi|1988|p=222}} An account of the 1287 and 1288 battles is documented in the ''[[History of Yuan]]'', which references the use of hand cannons.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=293}} 

In 1287, a group of soldiers equipped with portable hand cannons and led by commander Li Ting ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|李庭}}) attacked Nayan's military camp. The ''Yuanshi'' reports that the hand cannons not only &quot;caused great damage,&quot; but also caused &quot;such confusion that the enemy soldiers attacked and killed each other.&quot; {{sfn|Needham|1987|p=294}}  The hand cannons were used again in the beginning of 1288. Li Ting's &quot;gun-soldiers&quot; or ''chongzu'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|銃卒}}) were able to carry the hand cannons &quot;on their backs&quot; according to the ''Yuanshi''. The passage on the 1288 battle is also the first to coin the name ''chong'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|銃}}) for metal-barrel firearms. ''Chong'' was used instead of the earlier and more ambiguous term ''huo tong'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|火筒}}), which may refer to the tubes of [[fire lances]], proto-cannons, or signal flares.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=304}}

Wei Guozhong ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|魏國忠}}) was the archeologist who excavated and dated the cannon.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=293}}  He wrote a description of the archaeological find in the article &quot;A Bronze Bombard Excavated at [[Banlachengzi]] in Acheng Xian in Heilongjiang Province,&quot; which was published in 1973 for the journal ''Reference Materials for History and Archaeology''.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=610}}{{cref|b}} It was Wei who proposed a connection between the hand cannon discovered in Banlachengzi and the nearby battle sites. The historian [[Joseph Needham]] remarked that Wei's &quot;find will long remain of capital importance, since it is the only metal-barrel hand-gun so far discovered which almost certainly belongs to the 13th century.&quot;{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=294}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{refbegin}}
{{cnote|a|Hand-gun is an alternative name for the hand cannon and should not be confused with modern handguns. Particularly in British English, the term hand-gun refers to historical cannons that could be carried by a single individual due to their small size.{{sfn|Needham|1987|p=276}}}}
{{cnote|b|The journal was later renamed ''Culture Relics'' ({{lang|zh-Hant-TW|文物}}).}}
{{refend}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===

* {{cite book|first=Kenneth Warren|last=Chase|title=Firearms: A Global History to 1700|year=2003|publisher=Cambridge University Press|ref=harv| isbn=978-0-521-82274-9}}
*{{cite book|first=Herbert|last=Franke|chapter=The Chin dynasty|editor=Twitchett|editor2=Herbert Franke|editor3=John King Fairbank|title=The Cambridge History of China: Volume 6, Alien Regimes and Border States, 710–1368|year=1994|pages=215–320|publisher=Cambridge University Press|ref=harv |isbn=978-0-521-24331-5|authorlink = Herbert Franke (sinologist)|editor-first = Denis C.|editor-link = Denis C. Twitchett|editor3-link = John K. Fairbank}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Haw|first1=Stephen G.|title=The Mongol Empire – The First 'Gunpowder Empire'?|journal=Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society|date=July 2013|volume=23|issue=03|pages=441–469|ref=harv|doi=10.1017/S1356186313000369}}
* {{cite book|first=Peter|last=Lorge|title=The Asian Military Revolution: From Gunpowder to the Bomb|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-84682-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|first=Joseph|last=Needham|title=Science and Civilisation in China: Military Technology: The Gunpowder Epic, Volume 5, Part 7|year=1987|publisher=Cambridge University Press|ref=harv|isbn=978-0-521-30358-3}}
*{{cite book|first=Geoffrey|last=Parker|title=The Cambridge Illustrated History of Warfare|chapter=The Gunpowder Revolution|year=1995|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-73806-4|ref=harv|pages=106–119}}
*{{cite book |first=Morris|last=Rossabi|title=Khubilai Khan: His Life and Times|year=1988|publisher=University of California Press|location=Los Angeles |ref=harv |isbn=978-0-520-06740-0}}

[[Category:Early firearms]]
[[Category:Individual cannons]]
[[Category:Yuan dynasty]]
[[Category:Weapons of China]]
[[Category:Weapons of the Mongol Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>idrqjumojy7aqjbgpejpw1irvhjd7gw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
