<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of the United Kingdom during World War I</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1211527</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749823330</id>
      <parentid>749823302</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T09:56:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jim1138</username>
        <id>7695475</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/84.118.26.212|84.118.26.212]] ([[User talk:84.118.26.212|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.1.22)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="101391">{{about|the effect of the war on civilian and military life in the United Kingdom, 1914–18|information on the engagements in which its armed forces fought|World War I}}
{{see also|Timeline of the United Kingdom home front during World War I}}
{{Infobox Historical Era
| name=United Kingdom in World War&amp;nbsp;I
| image=Daddy in the great war.jpg
| alt=A man sits in an armchair, a girl on his knee. The caption reads: 'Daddy, what did YOU do in the Great War?'
| caption=British First World War [[propaganda]] poster
| start=1914
| end=1918
| before=Edwardian period
| after=Interwar period
| monarch=[[George V]]
| leaders='''Civil'''&lt;br&gt;[[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Ministers:]]&lt;br&gt;[[H. H. Asquith]], (pre-1916)&lt;br&gt;[[David Lloyd George]], (post-1916)&lt;br&gt;'''Army'''&lt;br&gt;[[William Robertson (British Army officer)|William Robertson]]&lt;br&gt;[[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|John French]]&lt;br&gt;[[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig|Douglas Haig]]&lt;br&gt;'''Royal Navy'''&lt;br&gt;[[John Fisher, 1st Baron Fisher|&quot;Jackie&quot; Fisher]]&lt;br&gt;[[Henry Jackson (Royal Navy officer)|Henry Jackson]]&lt;br&gt;[[John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe|John Jellicoe]]&lt;br&gt;[[Rosslyn Wemyss, 1st Baron Wester Wemyss|Rosslyn Wemyss]]&lt;br&gt;'''[[Royal Naval Air Service|British air services]]'''&lt;br&gt;[[David Henderson (British Army officer)|David Henderson]]&lt;br&gt;[[Frederick Sykes]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hugh Trenchard, 1st Viscount Trenchard|Hugh Trenchard]]&lt;br&gt;[[Godfrey Paine]]
}}
{{sidebar
| above = Timeline of&lt;br&gt; the United Kingdom during [[World War I|World&amp;nbsp;War&amp;nbsp;I]]
| content1 = {{hlist|[[1914 in the United Kingdom|1914]] | [[1915 in the United Kingdom|1915]] |[[1916 in the United Kingdom|1916]] | [[1917 in the United Kingdom|1917]] | [[1918 in the United Kingdom|1918]]}}
}}
{{Periods in English History}}
The [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland]]—then consisting of England, Scotland, Wales, and the whole of Ireland—was one of the [[Allies of World War I|Allied Powers]] during the First World War of 1914–1918, fighting against the [[Central Powers]] (the [[German Empire]], the [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]], the [[Ottoman Empire]] and the [[Kingdom of Bulgaria]]). The state's armed forces were reorganised—the war marked the creation of the [[Royal Air Force]], for example—and increased in size because of the introduction, in January 1916, of forced [[conscription]] for the first time in the kingdom's history as well as the raising of the largest all-volunteer army in history, known as Kitchener's Army, of more than two million men.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; The outbreak of war has generally been regarded as a socially unifying event,&lt;ref name=&quot;social&quot;/&gt; although this view has been challenged by more recent scholarship. In any case, responses in the United Kingdom in 1914 were similar to those amongst populations across Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory (2008); Pennell (2012)&lt;/ref&gt;

On the eve of war, there was serious domestic unrest in the UK (amongst the labour and suffrage movements and especially in Ireland) but much of the population rapidly rallied behind the government. Significant sacrifices were made in the name of defeating the Empire's enemies and many those who could not fight contributing to philanthropic and humanitarian causes. Fearing food shortages and labour shortfalls, the government passed legislation such as the [[Defence of the Realm Act 1914]], to give it new powers. The war saw a move away from the idea of &quot;[[Business as usual (policy)|business as usual]]&quot; under prime minister [[H. H. Asquith]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker&quot;/&gt; and towards a state of [[total war]] (complete state intervention in public affairs) under [[David Lloyd George]],&lt;ref name=&quot;totalwar&quot;/&gt; the first time this had been seen in Britain. The war also witnessed the first [[German strategic bombing during World War I|aerial bombardments of cities in Britain]].

Newspapers played an important role in maintaining popular support for the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett394&quot;/&gt; Large quantities of propaganda were produced by the government under the guidance of such journalists as [[Charles Masterman]] and newspaper owners such as [[Max Aitken, 1st Baron Beaverbrook|Lord Beaverbrook]]. By adapting to the changing demographics of the workforce (or the &quot;dilution of labour&quot;, as it was termed), war-related industries grew rapidly, and production increased, as concessions were quickly made to [[trade union]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett341&quot;/&gt; In that regard, the war is also credited by some with drawing women into mainstream employment for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;/&gt; Debates continue about the impact the war had on women's emancipation, given that a large number of women were granted the vote for the first time in 1918. The experience of individual women during the war varied; much depended on locality, age, marital status and occupation.&lt;ref&gt;Braybon (1990)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Braybon (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

The civilian death rate rose due to food shortages and [[Spanish Flu]], which hit the country in 1918.&lt;ref name=WAR/&gt; Military deaths are estimated to have exceeded 850,000.&lt;ref name=Mitchell /&gt;  The Empire reached its zenith at the conclusion of peace negotiations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beckett564&quot;/&gt; However, the war heightened not only imperial loyalties but also individual national identities in the dominions (Canada, Newfoundland, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa) and India.  [[Irish nationalists]] after 1916 moved from collaboration with London to demands for immediate independence (see [[Easter Rising]]), a move given great impetus by the [[Conscription Crisis of 1918]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pierce&quot;/&gt;

Military historians continue to debate matters of tactics and strategy. However, in terms of memory of the war, historian Adrian Gregory argues that:
:&quot;The verdict of popular culture is more or less unanimous. The First World War was stupid, tragic and futile. The stupidity of the war has been a theme of growing strength since the 1920s. From [[Robert Graves]], through '[[Oh! What a Lovely War]]' to '[[Blackadder Goes Forth]],' the criminal idiocy of the British High Command has become an article of faith.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Adrian Gregory|title=The Last Great War: British Society and the First World War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VfjZAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT10|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge UP|page=10|isbn=9781107650862}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government==
{{further|Causes of World War I}}
[[File:Herbert Henry Asquith.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Head of a white-haired gentleman with prominent eyebrows and a firm expression, wearing a wingtip collar|[[H. H. Asquith]] (c. 1915), prime minister at the start of the war]]
On 4 August, Britain (and its Empire) entered the World War with H. H. Asquith of the [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal Party]] as British prime minister.  Britain's reasons for declaring war were complex: the [[Treaty of London (1839)|Treaty of London]] of 1839 had committed it to safeguard Belgium's neutrality, and the strategic risk posed by German control of the Belgian coast was unacceptable. Asquith's Liberal government was brought down in {{Nowrap|May 1915}}, due in particular to a [[Shell Crisis of 1915|crisis in inadequate artillery shell production]] and the failed [[Gallipoli Campaign]] in the [[Dardanelles]].  Reluctant to give in to demands for an election, Asquith proceeded to form a new [[Coalition government 1915–1916|coalition government]] on {{Nowrap|25 May}}, with the majority of the new cabinet coming from his own Liberal party and the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Unionist (Conservative) party]] brought in to shore up the government.  By {{Nowrap|January 1915}}, 184 members of parliament were serving with the armed forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett499&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), pp 499–500&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lloyd George as Prime Minister===
This coalition government lasted until 1916, when the Unionists became dissatisfied with Asquith and the Liberals' conduct of affairs, particularly over the [[Battle of the Somme]]. What would prove to be the last majority-Liberal government collapsed&lt;ref name=&quot;mcgill&quot;&gt;Barry McGill, &quot;Asquith's Predicament, 1914–1918,&quot; ''Journal of Modern History'' (1967) 39#3 pp.&amp;nbsp;283–303 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1876582 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; as a result of the political manoeuvrings of [[Bonar Law|Andrew Bonar Law]] (leader of the Conservatives), [[Sir Edward Carson]] (leader of the [[Ulster Unionists]]), and [[David Lloyd George]] (then a minister in the cabinet). Law, who had few allies outside his own party, lacked sufficient support to form a new coalition; the Liberal Lloyd George, on the other hand, enjoyed much wider support and duly formed a majority-Conservative [[Coalition Government 1916–1922|coalition government]].&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett499&quot;/&gt; Asquith was still the party head but he and his followers moved to the opposition benches in Parliament.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcgill&quot;/&gt;

Lloyd George immediately set about transforming the British war effort, taking firm control of both military and domestic policy.&lt;ref&gt;John Grigg, ''Lloyd George: War Leader 1916–1918'' (2002) vol 4 pp&amp;nbsp;1–30&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A. J. P. Taylor, ''English History, 1914–1945'' (1965) pp&amp;nbsp;73–99&lt;/ref&gt; In the first 235 days of its existence, the War Cabinet met 200 times.&lt;ref name=&quot;totalwar&quot; /&gt; Its creation marked the transition to a state of [[total war]]—the idea that every man, woman and child should play his or her part in the war effort. Moreover, it was decided that members of the government should be the men who controlled the war effort, primarily utilising the power they had been given under the ''[[Defence of the Realm Act]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;totalwar&quot;&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2016-04-25|title=Total war|publisher=History Learning Site|last=Trueman|first=Chris |url=http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/total_war.htm|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150530123145/http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/total_war.htm|archive-date=2015-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the first time, the government could react quickly, without endless bureaucracy to tie it down, and with up-to-date statistics on such matters as the state of the [[merchant navy]] and farm production.&lt;ref name=&quot;totalwar&quot;/&gt; The policy marked a distinct shift away from Asquith's initial policy of [[laissez-faire]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker&quot;&gt;Baker (1921) p 21&lt;/ref&gt; which had been characterised by [[Winston Churchill]]'s declaration of &quot;[[Business as usual (policy)|business as usual]]&quot; in {{Nowrap|November 1914}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Oxford Library of Words and Phrases|year=1981|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=71}}&lt;/ref&gt; The success of Lloyd George's government can also be attributed to a general lack of desire for an election, and the practical absence of dissent that this brought about.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett499&quot;/&gt;

[[File:LloydGeorge.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Head and shoulders of a middle-aged gentleman with a bushy moustache| David Lloyd George (c. 1920), prime minister at the end of the war]] In rapid succession in spring 1918 came a series of military and political crises.&lt;ref&gt;A. J. P. Taylor, ''English History, 1914–1945'' (1965) pp&amp;nbsp;100–106&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans, having moved troops from the Eastern front and retrained them in new tactics, now had more soldiers on the Western Front than the Allies. On 21 March 1918 Germany launched a full scale [[Spring Offensive]] against the British and French lines, hoping for victory on the battlefield before United States troops arrived in numbers. The Allied armies fell back 40 miles in confusion, and facing defeat London realized it needed more troops to fight a mobile war. Lloyd George found half a million soldiers and rushed them to France, asked American President Woodrow Wilson for immediate help, and agreed to the appointment of the French Marshal Foch as commander in chief on the Western Front, so that Allied forces could be coordinated to handle the German offensive.&lt;ref&gt;John Grigg, ''Lloyd George: War Leader 1916–1918'' (2002) vol 4 pp&amp;nbsp;478–83&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite strong warnings that it was a bad idea, the War Cabinet [[Conscription Crisis of 1918|decided to impose conscription on Ireland]] in 1918. The main reason was that labour in Britain demanded it as the price for cutting back on exemptions for certain workers. Labour wanted the principle established that no one was exempt, but it did not demand that conscription should actually take place in Ireland. The proposal was enacted, but never enforced. The Roman Catholic bishops for the first time entered the fray, calling for open resistance to compulsory military service, while the majority of Irish nationalists moved to supporting the intransigent [[Sinn Féin]] movement (away from the constitutional [[Irish National Party]]). This proved a decisive moment, marking the end of Irish willingness to stay inside the Union.&lt;ref&gt;Alan J. Ward, &quot;Lloyd George and the 1918 Irish Conscription Crisis,&quot; ''Historical Journal'' (1974) 17#1 pp.&amp;nbsp;107–129 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2638335 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grigg, ''Lloyd George'' vol 4 pp&amp;nbsp;465–88&lt;/ref&gt;

On {{nowrap|7 May 1918}}, a senior army officer on active duty, Major-General [[Frederick Barton Maurice|Sir Frederick Maurice]], prompted [[The Maurice Debate|a second crisis]] when he went public with allegations that Lloyd George had lied to Parliament on military matters. Asquith, the Liberal leader in the House, took up the allegations and attacked Lloyd George (also a Liberal). While Asquith's presentation was poor, Lloyd George vigorously defended his position, treating the debate as a vote of confidence. He won over the House with a powerful refutation of Maurice's allegations. The main results were to strengthen Lloyd George, weaken Asquith, end public criticism of overall strategy, and strengthen civilian control of the military.&lt;ref&gt;John Gooch, &quot;The Maurice Debate 1918,&quot; ''Journal of Contemporary History'' (1968) 3#4 pp.&amp;nbsp;211–228 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/259859 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Grigg, ''Lloyd George: War leader, 1916–1918'' (London: Penguin, 2002), pp&amp;nbsp;489–512&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the German offensive stalled and was ultimately reversed. Victory came on November 11, 1918.&lt;ref&gt;A. J. P. Taylor, ''English History, 1914–1945'' (1965) pp&amp;nbsp;108–11&lt;/ref&gt;

===Collapse of the Liberal Party===
In the [[United Kingdom general election, 1918|general election of 1918]], Lloyd George, &quot;the Man Who Won the War&quot;, led his coalition into another ''[[khaki election]]'' and won a sweeping victory over the Asquithian Liberals and the newly emerging [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]]. Lloyd George and the Conservative leader [[Bonar Law|Andrew Bonar Law]] wrote a joint letter of support to candidates to indicate they were considered the official Coalition candidates – this [[The Coalition Coupon|&quot;coupon&quot;]], as it became known, was issued against many sitting Liberal Members of Parliament to devastating effect.&lt;ref&gt;Trevor Wilson, &quot;The Coupon and the British General Election of 1918,&quot; ''Journal of Modern History,'' (1964) 36#1 pp.&amp;nbsp;28–42 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1874424 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; Asquith and most of his Liberal colleagues lost their seats. Lloyd George still claimed to be leading a Liberal government, but he was increasingly under the influence of the rejuvenated Conservative party. The Liberal party never recovered.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, ''The Downfall of the Liberal Party: 1914–1935'' (1966) pp&amp;nbsp;135–85&lt;/ref&gt;

==Monarchy==
[[Image:A Good Riddance - George V of the United Kingdom cartoon in Punch, 1917.png|thumb|alt=A man, wearing a crown and holding a broom, sweeps away a collection of other crowns|&quot;A good riddance&quot;&lt;br/&gt;A 1917 ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'' cartoon depicts King George sweeping away his German titles.]]
{{further|George V#First World War}}

The British [[Royal House]] faced a serious problem during the First World War because of its blood ties to the ruling family of Germany, Britain's prime adversary in the war. Before the war, the British royal family had been known as the [[House of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha]]. In 1910, [[George V]] became King of the United Kingdom on the death of his father, [[Edward VII|King Edward VII]], and remained king throughout the war. He was the [[Cousin chart|first cousin]] of the German Kaiser [[William II, German Emperor|Wilhelm&amp;nbsp;II]], who came to symbolise all the horrors of the war. [[Mary of Teck|Queen Mary]], although British like her mother, was the daughter of the [[Duke of Teck]], a descendant of the German [[Rulers of Württemberg|Royal House of Württemberg]]. During the war [[H. G. Wells]] wrote about Britain's &quot;alien and uninspiring court&quot;, and George famously replied: &quot;I may be uninspiring, but I'll be damned if I'm alien.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nicolson (1952), p 308&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 July 1917, to appease British nationalist feelings, King George issued an [[Order in Council]] that changed the name of the [[British Royal Family]] to the [[House of Windsor]]. He specifically adopted Windsor as the surname for all descendants of [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]] then living in the United Kingdom, excluding women who married into other families and their descendants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.royal.gov.uk/ThecurrentRoyalFamily/TheRoyalFamilyname/Overview.aspx|title=The Royal Family name|publisher=Official web site of the British monarchy|accessdate=2009-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; He and his relatives who were British subjects relinquished the use of all German titles and styles, and adopted English surnames. George compensated several of his male relatives by creating them British peers. Thus, his cousin, [[Louis Mountbatten, 1st Marquess of Milford Haven|Prince Louis of Battenberg]], became Louis Mountbatten, 1st Marquess of Milford Haven, while his brother-in-law, the [[Adolphus Cambridge, 1st Marquess of Cambridge|Duke of Teck]], became Adolphus Cambridge, 1st Marquess of Cambridge. Others, such as [[Princess Marie Louise of Schleswig-Holstein]] and [[Princess Helena Victoria of Schleswig-Holstein]], simply stopped using their territorial designations. The system for titling members of the royal family was also simplified.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolson (195), p 310&lt;/ref&gt; Relatives of the British royal family who fought on the German side were simply cut off; their British peerages were suspended by a 1919 Order in Council under the provisions of the ''[[Titles Deprivation Act 1917]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-17|publisher=office of public sector information|title=Titles Deprivation Act 1917|url=http://www.statutelaw.gov.uk/content.aspx?LegType=All+Primary&amp;PageNumber=86&amp;NavFrom=2&amp;parentActiveTextDocId=1071411&amp;activetextdocid=1071414}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Tsar Nicholas II &amp; King George V.JPG|thumb|left|alt=Two look-alike men. Both wear beards and are in full military regalia festooned with medals—one uniform dark, the other white.|King George V (right) with his first cousin [[Nicholas II of Russia|Tsar Nicholas&amp;nbsp;II]], Berlin, 1913]]
Developments in Russia posed another set of issues for the monarchy. [[Nicholas II of Russia|Tsar Nicholas&amp;nbsp;II of Russia]] was King George's first cousin and the two monarchs looked very much alike.&lt;ref&gt;At George's wedding in 1893, ''[[The Times]]'' claimed that the crowd may have confused Nicholas with George, because their beards and dress made them look alike (''The Times (London)'' Friday, {{Nowrap|7 July}} 1893, p 5)&lt;/ref&gt; When Nicholas was overthrown in the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]], the British Government was prepared to offer asylum to the Tsar and his family. However, worsening conditions for the British people, and fears that revolution might come to the [[British Isles]], led George V to think that the presence of the Romanovs in the United Kingdom might seem inappropriate to the public.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolson (1952), p 301&lt;/ref&gt; Records of the King's private secretary, [[Arthur Bigge, 1st Baron Stamfordham|Lord Stamfordham]], suggest that George V opposed the granting of asylum for the Romanovs, against the advice of Lloyd George.&lt;ref&gt;Rose (1983), p 210&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Prince of Wales]] – the future [[Edward VIII]] – was keen to participate in the war but the government refused to allow it, citing the immense harm that would occur if the heir to the throne were captured.&lt;ref&gt;Roberts (2000), p 41&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, Edward witnessed trench warfare at first hand and attempted to visit the front line as often as he could, for which he was awarded the [[Military Cross]] in 1916. His role in the war, although limited, led to his great popularity among veterans of the conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Ziegler (1991), p 111&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Duke of Windsor (1998), p 140&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Beatty Rodman KingGeorgeV KingEdwardVIII Sims.jpg|thumb|alt=Five men, all in immaculate naval dress, stand on deck.|[[George V|King George V]] and his son the [[Edward VIII|Prince of Wales]] visiting the Grand Fleet in 1918. From left to right: Admiral [[David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty|David Beatty]], [[Royal Navy|RN]]; Rear Admiral [[Hugh Rodman]], [[USN]]; King George V; Prince of Wales; Vice Admiral [[William S. Sims]], USN]]

Other members of the royal family were similarly involved. The Prince Albert, [[Duke of York]] (later [[George VI]]), was commissioned in the Royal Navy and saw action as a turret officer aboard [[HMS Collingwood (1908)|HMS ''Collingwood'']] against at the [[battle of Jutland]] but saw no further action in the war, largely because of ill health.&lt;ref name=Bradford55&gt;Bradford (1989), pp 55–76&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mary, Princess Royal and Countess of Harewood|Princess Mary]], the King's only daughter, visited hospitals and welfare organisations with her mother, assisting with projects to give comfort to British servicemen and assistance to their families. One of these projects was [[Princess Mary Christmas gift box|Princess Mary's ''Christmas Gift Fund'']], through which £162,000 worth of gifts was sent to all British soldiers and sailors for Christmas 1914.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://archive.iwm.org.uk/server/show/ConWebDoc.994/setPaginate/No
|accessdate=7 April 2013
|work=archive.iwm.org.uk
|title=Princess Mary's Gift to the Troops, Christmas 1914
|author=[[Imperial War Museum]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; She took an active role in promoting the [[Girlguiding UK|Girl Guide]] movement, the [[Voluntary Aid Detachment]] (VAD), the [[Women's Land Army|Land Girls]] and in 1918, she took a nursing course and went to work at [[Great Ormond Street Hospital]].&lt;ref&gt;Thornton-Cook (1977), p.229&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Defence of the Realm Act''==
{{Main|Defence of the Realm Act 1914}}
The first ''Defence of the Realm Act'' (DORA) was passed on {{Nowrap|8 August}} 1914, during the early weeks of the war,&lt;ref&gt;Beckett (2007), ''Chronology''&lt;/ref&gt; though in the next few months its provisions were extended.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck348&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), p 348&lt;/ref&gt; It gave the [[British government|government]] wide-ranging powers,&lt;ref name=&quot;beck348&quot;/&gt; such as the ability to [[Eminent domain|requisition]] buildings or land needed for the [[war effort]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|newspaper=The London Gazette|date=14 August 1914|title=Part 1: General Regulations|author=FitzRoy, Almeric William, Clerk of the Privy Council|quote=It shall be lawful for the competent naval or military authority&amp;nbsp;... (a) to take possession of any land&amp;nbsp;... (b) to take possession of any buildings or other property|url=http://www.gazettes-online.co.uk/issues/28870/pages/6387/page.pdf|page=3|issue=28870}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the things the British public were prohibited from doing included loitering under railway bridges,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|newspaper=The London Gazette|date=14 August 1914|title=Part 2: Regulations specially designed to prevent persons communicating with the enemy&amp;nbsp;... |author=FitzRoy, Almeric William, Clerk of the Privy Council|quote=No person shall trespass on any railway, or loiter under or near any bridge, viaduct, or culvert, over which a railway passes.|url=http://www.gazettes-online.co.uk/issues/28870/pages/6388/page.pdf|page=4|issue=28870}}&lt;/ref&gt; feeding wild animals&lt;ref name=&quot;beck381&quot;/&gt; and discussing naval and military matters.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|newspaper=The London Gazette|date=14 August 1914|title=Part 2: Regulations specially designed to prevent persons communicating with the enemy&amp;nbsp;... |author=FitzRoy, Almeric William, Clerk of the Privy Council|quote=No person shall&amp;nbsp;... communicate any information with respect to the movement or disposition of any of the forces, ships, or war materials&amp;nbsp;... or with respect to the plans of any naval or military operations|url=http://www.gazettes-online.co.uk/issues/28870/pages/6388/page.pdf|page=4|issue=28870}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[British Summer Time]] was also introduced.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck383&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), p 383&lt;/ref&gt; Alcoholic beverages were now to be watered down, pub closing times were brought forward from {{Nowrap|12.30 am}} to {{Nowrap|10 pm}}, and, from {{Nowrap|August 1916}}, Londoners were no longer able to whistle for a [[Cabriolet (carriage)|cab]] between {{Nowrap|10 pm}} and {{Nowrap|7 am}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck383&quot;/&gt; It has been criticised for both its strength and its use of the [[death penalty]] as a [[Deterrence (legal)|deterrent]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Treachery Bill|publisher=Hansard|accessdate=2009-05-13|url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1940/may/22/treachery-bill}}&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;– although the act itself did not refer to the death penalty, it made provision for civilians breaking these rules to be tried in army [[court martial|courts martial]], where the maximum penalty was death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-16|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/catalogue/RdLeaflet.asp?sLeafletID=40&amp;j=1|title=British Army: Courts Martial: First World War, 1914–1918|publisher=National Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==His Majesty's forces==

===Army===
[[Image:British recruits August 1914 Q53234.jpg|thumb|alt=A large throng of people congregate, surrounded by police officers. Approximately half wear peaked caps; the rest wear boaters. Some smile, the rest look pensive.|August&amp;nbsp;1914: London army volunteers await their pay at [[St. Martin-in-the-Fields]]]]
The [[British Army during World War&amp;nbsp;I]] was small in size when compared to the other major European powers. In 1914, the British had a small, largely urban English, volunteer force&lt;ref name=&quot;beck289&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), p 289&lt;/ref&gt; of 400,000 soldiers, almost half of whom were posted overseas to garrison the British Empire. (In {{Nowrap|August 1914}}, 74 of the 157 infantry battalions and 12 of the 31 cavalry regiments were posted overseas.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt;) This total included the Regular Army and reservists in the [[Territorial Force]].&lt;ref name=tr504&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p 504&lt;/ref&gt; Together they formed the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War I)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF),&lt;ref&gt;Chandler (2003), p 211&lt;/ref&gt; for service in France and became known as the [[Old Contemptibles]]. The mass of volunteers in 1914–1915, popularly known as [[Kitchener's Army]], was destined to go into action at the [[battle of the Somme]].&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; In {{Nowrap|January 1916}}, conscription was introduced, and by the end of 1918, the army had reached its peak of strength of four million men.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt;

===Royal Navy===
{{further|Naval warfare of World War&amp;nbsp;I}}
[[File:2nd Battle Squadron.jpg|thumb|left|right|alt=Four battleships at sea|Ships of the 2nd Battle Squadron of the Royal Navy's Grand Fleet]]
The Royal Navy at the start of the war was the largest navy in the world due, in the most part, to ''[[The Naval Defence Act 1889]]'' and the [[Victorian Royal Navy#The &quot;Two-Power Standard&quot;|two-power standard]] which called for the navy to maintain a number of battleships such as their strength was at least equal to the combined strength of the next two largest navies in the world, which at that point were [[French navy#19th century revival|France]] and [[Russian Navy#Imperial Russian Navy|Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus (2001), p 161&lt;/ref&gt;

The major part of the [[Royal Navy]]'s strength was deployed at home in the [[British Grand Fleet|Grand Fleet]], with the primary aim of drawing the [[Hochseeflotte|German High Seas Fleet]] into an engagement. No decisive victory ever came. The Royal Navy and the [[Kaiserliche Marine|German Imperial Navy]] did come into contact, notably in the [[Battle of Heligoland (1914)|battle of Heligoland Bight]], and the [[battle of Jutland]].&lt;ref name=rn1914&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-14|title=The First World War and the Inter-war years 1914–1939|publisher=Royal Navy|url=http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/history/historical-periods/1914-1939/}}&lt;/ref&gt; In view of their inferior numbers and firepower, the Germans devised a plan to draw part of the British fleet into a trap and put it into effect at Jutland in {{Nowrap|May 1916}}, but the result was inconclusive. In {{Nowrap|August 1916}}, the High Seas Fleet tried a similar enticement operation and was &quot;lucky to escape annihilation&quot;.&lt;ref name=rn1916/&gt; The lessons learned by the Royal Navy at Jutland made it a more effective force in the future.&lt;ref name=rn1916&gt;{{cite web|title=Battle of Jutland 1916|publisher=Royal Navy|accessdate=2009-05-21|url=http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/history/battles/battle-of-jutland/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1914, the navy had also formed the [[63rd (Royal Naval) Division]] from reservists, and this served extensively in the Mediterranean and on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]].&lt;ref name=rndiv&gt;{{cite web|title=The First World War and the Inter-war years 1914–1939|publisher=MOD UK, Royal Navy|accessdate=2009-05-21|url=http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/history/historical-periods/1914-1939/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost half of the Royal Navy casualties during the War were sustained by this division, fighting on land and not at sea.&lt;ref name=rn1914/&gt;

===British air services===
{{further|Royal Flying Corps|Royal Naval Air Service}}
[[Image:Royal Flying Corps poster.jpg|thumb|alt=A poster reads &quot;ROYAL FLYING CORPS&quot;, &quot;MILITARY WING&quot;, &quot;VACANCIES EXIST&quot;, information about pay, &quot;GOD SAVE THE KING&quot;.|[[Royal Flying Corps]] recruitment poster]]
At the start of the war, the Royal Flying Corps (RFC), commanded by [[David Henderson (British Army officer)|David Henderson]], was sent to France and was first used for aerial spotting in {{Nowrap|September 1914}}, but only became efficient when they perfected the use of [[Wireless|wireless communication]] at [[Aubers Ridge]] on {{Nowrap|May 9}} 1915. [[Aerial photography]] was attempted during 1914, but again only became effective the next year. In 1915 [[Hugh Trenchard]] replaced Henderson and the RFC adopted an aggressive posture. By 1918, photographic images could be taken from {{convert|15000|ft|m}}, and interpreted by over 3,000 personnel. Planes did not carry [[parachute]]s until 1918, though they had been available since before the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett254&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), p 254&lt;/ref&gt;
On 17 August 1917, General [[Jan Smuts]] presented a report to the War Council on the future of [[Aerial warfare|air power]]. Because of its potential for the 'devastation of enemy lands and the destruction of industrial and populous centres on a vast scale', he recommended a new air service be formed that would be on a level with the army and navy. The formation of the new service however would make the under utilised men and machines of the [[Royal Naval Air Service]] (RNAS) available for action across [[Western Front (World War I)|the Western Front]], as well as ending the inter-service rivalries that at times had adversely affected aircraft procurement. On {{Nowrap|1 April}} 1918, the RFC and the RNAS were amalgamated to form a new service, the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Royal Air Force History|publisher=Royal Air Force|accessdate=2009-08-27|url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/history_old/line1917.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recruitment and conscription==
{{Main|Recruitment to the British Army during World War&amp;nbsp;I}}
[[File:Britain Needs You at Once - WWI recruitment poster - Parliamentary Recruiting Committee Poster No. 108.jpg|thumb|200px|Poster by the Parliamentary Recruiting Committee, featuring [[St. George and the Dragon]].|left]]
Particularly in the early stages of the war, many men, for a wide variety of reasons, decided to &quot;join up&quot; to the armed forces—by {{Nowrap|5 September}} 1914, over 225,000 had signed up to fight for what became known as [[Kitchener's Army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt; Over the course of the war, a number of factors contributed to recruitment rates, including patriotism, the work of the Parliamentary Recruiting Committee in producing posters, dwindling alternative employment opportunities, and an eagerness for adventure to escape humdrum routine.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt; [[Pals battalions]], where whole battalions were raised from a small geographic area or employer, also proved popular. Higher recruitment rates were seen in Wales and Scotland, though in the case of the Welsh and Irish, political tensions tended to &quot;put something of a blight upon enlistment&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Lawson Wood - Parliamentary Recruiting Committee - Your King &amp; Country Need You.jpg|thumb|A 1914 poster shows a Scottish soldier in Belgium, in response to Germany describing the [[Treaty of London (1839)|Treaty of London]], which protected Belgium's independence and neutrality, as a &quot;scrap of paper&quot; when they invaded in August 1914.&lt;ref&gt;[[Museum of New Zealand Te Papa Tongarewa|Te Papa]] (the Museum of New Zealand)'s [http://collections.tepapa.govt.nz/Object/1129245 description of the poster].&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Recruitment remained fairly steady through 1914 and early 1915, but fell dramatically during the later years, especially after the [[Battle of the Somme|Somme campaign]], which resulted in 500,000 casualties. As a result, [[Conscription in the United Kingdom|conscription]] was introduced for the first time in {{Nowrap|January 1916}} for single men, and extended in May–June to all men aged 18 to 41 across England, Wales and Scotland, by way of the ''[[Military Service Act (United Kingdom)|Military Service Acts]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), pp 291–5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-13|title=Britain and World War One, 1901–1918|author=Professor [[Hew Strachan]]|publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/overview_britain_ww1_07.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Urban centres, with their poverty and unemployment were favourite recruiting grounds of the regular British army. Dundee, where the female dominated jute industry limited male employment had one of the highest proportion of reservists and serving soldiers than almost any other British city.&lt;ref name=Lenman&amp;Mackie1991&gt;B. Lenman and J., Mackie, [https://books.google.com/books?id=_cvp_njNb2sC&amp;pg=PT457&amp;dq=martial+races+scotland+%22first+world+war%22&amp;hl=En&amp;ei=yzfQTu7dI8vn8QP0u6GxBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=book-thumbnail&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=martial%20races%20scotland%20%22first%20world%20war%22&amp;f=false ''A History of Scotland''] (Penguin, 1991)&lt;/ref&gt; Concern for their families' standard of living made men hesitate to enlist; voluntary enlistment rates went up after the government guaranteed a weekly stipend for life to the survivors of men who were killed or disabled.&lt;ref&gt;D. Coetzee, &quot;A life and death decision: the influence of trends in fertility, nuptiality and family economies on voluntary enlistment in Scotland, August 1914 to December 1915&quot;, ''Family and Community History'', November 2005, vol. 8 (2), pp. 77–89.&lt;/ref&gt; After the introduction of conscription from January 1916 every part of the country was affected. 
 		 	
The policy of relying on volunteers had sharply reduced the capacity of heavy industry to produce the munitions needed for the war.  Historian [[R. J. Q. Adams]] reports that 19% of the men in the iron and steel industry entered the Army, 22% of the miners, 20% in the engineering trades, 24% in the electrical industries, 16% among small arms craftsmen, and 24% of the men who had been engaged in making high explosives.&lt;ref&gt;[[R. J. Q. Adams]], &quot;Delivering the Goods: Reappaising the Ministry of Munitions: 1915–1916.&quot; ''[[Albion: A Quarterly Journal Concerned with British Studies]]'' (1975) 7#3 pp: 232–244 at p. 238 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4048178 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; In response critical industries were prioritised over the army (&quot;reserved occupations&quot;), including munitions, food production and merchant shipping.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt;

===Conscription Crisis of 1918===
{{Main|Conscription Crisis of 1918}}
In April 1918 legislation was brought forward which allowed for extension of conscription to Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt; Though this ultimately never materialised, the effect was &quot;disastrous&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt; Despite significant numbers [[Ireland in World War I|volunteering for Irish regiments]],&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt; the idea of ''enforced'' conscription proved unpopular. The reaction was based particularly on the fact that implementation of conscription in Ireland was linked to a pledged &quot;measure of self-government in Ireland&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Adams (1999), p 266&lt;/ref&gt; The linking of conscription and [[Government of Ireland Act 1914|Home Rule]] in this way outraged the Irish parties at Westminster, who walked out in protest and returned to Ireland to organise opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Alan J.  | first = Ward  | authorlink = Alan J. Ward  | title = Lloyd George and the 1918 Irish Conscription Crisis  | publisher = The Historical Journal, Vol. XVII, no. 1  | year = 1974  | isbn =}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As a result, a general strike was called, and on {{Nowrap|23 April}} 1918, work was stopped in railways, docks, factories, mills, theatres, cinemas, trams, public services, shipyards, newspapers, shops, and even official munitions factories.  The strike was described as &quot;complete and entire, an unprecedented event outside the [[Continental Europe|continental countries]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  | last = Cahill  | first = Liam  | authorlink = Liam Cahill  | title = Forgotten Revolution: Limerick Soviet, 1919   | publisher = [[O'Brien Press]]  | year = 1990
  | isbn = 978-0-86278-194-1 |url = http://www.limericksoviet.com/Chapter_One.doc}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ultimately the effect was a total loss of interest in Home Rule and of popular support for the nationalist [[Irish Parliamentary Party|Irish Party]] who were defeated outright by the separatist republican [[Sinn Féin]] party in the December 1918 [[Irish general election, 1918|Irish general election]], one of the precursors of the [[Anglo-Irish War]].

===Conscientious objectors===
{{further|Conscientious objector#United Kingdom}}
The conscription legislation introduced the right to refuse military service, allowing for conscientious objectors to be absolutely exempted, to perform alternative [[civilian service]], or to serve as a [[non-combatant]] in the army, according to the extent to which they could convince a Military Service Tribunal of the quality of their objection.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Around 16,500 men were recorded as conscientious objectors,&lt;ref name=&quot;beck291&quot;/&gt; with [[Quakers]] playing a large role.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} 4,500 objectors were sent to work on farms to undertake &quot;work of national importance&quot;, 7,000 were ordered non-combatant duties as stretcher bearers, but 6,000 were forced into the army, and when they refused orders, they were sent to prison, as in the case of the [[Richmond Sixteen]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenorthernecho.co.uk/news/10507058.Silence_in_castle_to_honour_First_World_War_conscientious_objectors/ Silence in castle to honour First World War conscientious objectors] dated 25 June 2013 at thenorthernecho.co.uk, accessed 19 October 2014&lt;/ref&gt;
Some 843 conscientious objectors spent more than two years in prison; ten died while there, seventeen were initially given the death penalty (but received life imprisonment) and 142 were imprisoned on life sentences.&lt;ref&gt;Beckett (2007), p 507&lt;/ref&gt; Conscientious objectors who were deemed not to have made any useful contribution were [[Disfranchisement|disenfranchised]] for five years after the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Taylor (2001), p 116&lt;/ref&gt;

==Naval and air raids==
[[Image:WWI German targets in England (zoomed).png|thumb|alt=A map of England, with towns bombarded during the war marked. All are in the east.|German bombardments were concentrated on the east coast of England]]
At the start of the First World War, for the first time since the [[Napoleonic Wars]], the population of the British Isles was in danger of attack from naval raids. The country also came under attack from air raids by [[zeppelins]] and [[fixed-wing aircraft]], another first.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p 709&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-26|title=Yorkshire Coast Raid, 15–16&amp;nbsp;December 1914|work= Official History of the War, Naval Operations Vol. II|author=Corbett Julian|url=http://www.historyofwar.org/articles/raid_yorkshire_coast_1914.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Naval raids===
{{Main|Raid on Yarmouth|Raid on Scarborough, Hartlepool and Whitby}}
The Raid on Yarmouth, which took place in {{Nowrap|November 1914}}, was an attack by the German Navy on the British [[North Sea]] port and town of [[Great Yarmouth]]. Little damage was done to the town itself, since shells only landed on the beach once German ships laying [[Naval mine|mines]] offshore were interrupted by British destroyers. One British [[submarine]] was sunk by a mine as it attempted to leave harbour and attack the German ships, while one German [[Armored cruiser|armoured cruiser]] was sunk after striking two mines outside its own home port.&lt;ref&gt;Massie (2004), pp 309–311&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Rememberscarborough.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Britannia stands in front of a group of men holding various armaments, looking out over a scene of burning houses. The caption reads &quot;REMEMBER SCARBOROUGH!&quot;, &quot;ENLIST NOW&quot;.|British propaganda fuelled by the German raid on Scarborough]]

In December 1914, the German navy carried out attacks on the British coastal towns of [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]], [[Hartlepool]] and [[Whitby]]. The attack resulted in 137 fatalities and 593 casualties,&lt;ref&gt;His Majesty's stationery Office (1922), pp 674–677&lt;/ref&gt; many of which were civilians. The attack made the German navy very unpopular with the British public, as an attack against British [[civilian]]s in their homes. Likewise, the British Royal Navy was criticised for failing to prevent the raid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Damage by German Raids|publisher=UK Parliament &quot;Hansard&quot;|accessdate=2009-05-13|url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1915/mar/01/damage-by-german-raids#S5CV0070P0_19150301_HOC_140}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=German Attacks on Unfortified Towns|publisher=UK Parliament &quot;Hansard&quot;|accessdate=2009-05-13|url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1915/jun/24/german-attacks-on-unfortified-towns#S5CV0072P0_19150624_HOC_189}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bombardment of Yarmouth and Lowestoft===
{{Main|Bombardment of Yarmouth and Lowestoft}}
In April 1916 a German battlecruiser squadron with accompanying cruisers and destroyers bombarded the coastal ports of Yarmouth and Lowestoft. Although the ports had some military importance, the main aim of the raid was to entice out defending ships which could then be picked off either by the battlecruiser squadron or by the full High Seas Fleet, which was stationed at sea ready to intervene if an opportunity presented itself. The result was inconclusive: nearby Royal Navy units were too small to intervene so largely kept clear of the German battlecruisers, and the German ships withdrew before the first British fast response battlecruiser squadron or the Grand Fleet could arrive.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker, Wood &amp; Murphy (2005), P.193&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:It is far better to face the bullets.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Poster: picture of Zeppelin illuminated by searchlight over silhouetted London skyline; headline: &quot;IT IS FAR BETTER TO FACE THE BULLETS THAN TO BE KILLED AT HOME BY A BOMB&quot;|British propaganda poster from 1915, drawing on the fear of zeppelin attacks to aid recruitment]]

===Air raids===
{{Further2|[[Zeppelin#WW1|Zeppelins in World War&amp;nbsp;I]]}}
German [[zeppelins]] bombed towns on the east coast, starting on {{Nowrap|19 January}} 1915 with [[Great Yarmouth]].&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett258&quot;/&gt; London was also hit later in the same year, on {{Nowrap|31 May}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett258&quot;/&gt; [[Propaganda]] supporting the British war effort often used these raids to their advantage: one recruitment poster claimed: &quot;It is far better to face the bullets than to be killed at home by a bomb&quot; (see image). The reaction from the public, however, was mixed; whilst 10,000 visited [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]] to view the damage there, London theatres reported having fewer visitors during periods of &quot;Zeppelin weather&quot;—dark, fine nights.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett258&quot;/&gt;

Throughout 1917 [[Imperial Germany|Germany]] began to deploy increasing numbers of [[Fixed-wing aircraft|fixed-wing]] [[bombers]], the [[Gotha G.IV]]'s first target being [[Folkestone]] on {{Nowrap|25 May}} 1917, following this attack the number of airship raids decreased rapidly in favour of raids by fixed wing aircraft,&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett258&quot;/&gt; before Zeppelin raids were called off entirely. In total, Zeppelins dropped 6,000 bombs, resulting in 556 dead and 1,357 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Powers (1976), pp 50–51&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after the raid on Folkestone, the bombers began raids on London: one daylight raid on {{Nowrap|13 June}} 1917 by 14 Gothas caused 162 deaths in the [[East End of London]].&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett258&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), pp 258–261&lt;/ref&gt; In response to this new threat, [[Edward Ashmore (British Army officer)|Major General Edward Bailey Ashmore]], a RFC pilot who later commanded an [[artillery]] [[Division (military)|division]] in Belgium, was appointed to devise an improved system of detection, communication and control,&lt;ref&gt;Bourne (2001), p 10&lt;/ref&gt; The system, called the ''Metropolitan Observation Service'', encompassed the [[London Air Defence Area]] and would later extend eastwards towards the [[Kent]]ish and [[Essex]] coasts. The Metropolitan Observation Service was fully operational until the late summer of 1918 (the last German bombing raid taking place on {{Nowrap|19 May}} 1918).&lt;ref&gt;Bourne (2001), p 20&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--[[File:Zeppelin bombing plaque 2005.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A plaque, reading &quot;These premises were totally destroyed by a zeppelin raid, ... September 8 1915&quot;|A plaque on the wall of premises bombed out by zeppelins in 1915]]--&gt;
&lt;!--[[File:Scarborough, North Yorkshire - WWI poster.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Picture of girl holding infant in front of bombed out building. Caption reads &quot;MEN OF BRITAIN !&quot;, &quot;WILL YOU STAND THIS ?&quot;, &quot;78 Women &amp; Children were killed and 228 Women &amp; Children were wounded by the German Raiders&quot;, &quot;ENLIST NOW&quot;.|Propaganda poster following the [[Raid on Scarborough, Hartlepool and Whitby|raid on Scarborough]]]]--&gt;
During the war, the Germans carried out 51 airship raids and 52 fixed-wing bomber raids on the United Kingdom, which together dropped 280 tons of bombs. The casualties amounted to 1,413 killed, and 3,409 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Air Raids|publisher=National Archives|accessdate=2009-05-17|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pathways/firstworldwar/spotlights/airraids.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; The success of anti-air defence measures was limited; of the 397 aircraft that had taken part in raids, only 24 Gothas were shot down (though 37 more were lost in accidents), despite an estimated rate of 14,540 anti-air rounds per aircraft. Anti-zeppelin defences were more successful, with 17 shot down and 21 lost in accidents.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett258&quot;/&gt;

==Media==

===Propaganda===
{{Main|British propaganda during World War&amp;nbsp;I}}
[[File:Stanford’s Geographical Establishment, What Germany Wants 1917 Cornell CUL PJM 1199 01.jpg|thumbnail|upright=1|A reproduction of a world map that marks the  areas that &quot;Germany Wants&quot; by Edward Stanford in 1917.]]

[[Propaganda]] and censorship were closely linked during the war.&lt;ref name=propaganda&gt;{{cite web|title=Espionage, propaganda and censorship|publisher=National Archives|accessdate=2009-05-17|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pathways/firstworldwar/britain/espionage.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; The need to maintain morale and counter German propaganda was recognised early in the war and the [[War Propaganda Bureau]] was established under the leadership of [[Charles Masterman]] in {{Nowrap|September 1914}}.&lt;ref name=propaganda/&gt; The Bureau enlisted eminent writers such as [[H G Wells]], [[Arthur Conan Doyle]], [[Rudyard Kipling]] as well as newspaper editors.  Until its abolition in 1917, the department published 300 books and pamphlets in 21 languages, distributed over 4,000 propaganda photographs every week, and circulated maps, cartoons, and lantern slides to the media.&lt;ref&gt;D. G. Wright, &quot;The Great War, Government Propaganda and English 'Men Of Letters' 1914-16.&quot; ''Literature and History'' 7 (1978): 70+.&lt;/ref&gt;  Masterman also commissioned films about the war such as [[The Battle of the Somme (film)|The Battle of the Somme]], which appeared in {{Nowrap|August 1916}}, while the battle was still in progress as a morale-booster and in general it met with a favourable reception. ''The Times'' reported on {{Nowrap|22 August}} 1916 that &quot;Crowded audiences&amp;nbsp;... were interested and thrilled to have the realities of war brought so vividly before them, and if women had sometimes to shut their eyes to escape for a moment from the tragedy of the toll of battle which the film presents, opinion seems to be general that it was wise that the people at home should have this glimpse of what our soldiers are doing and daring and suffering in Picardy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;'War's Realities on the Cinema', ''The Times'', London, {{Nowrap|August 22}}, 1916, p 3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Newspapers===
Newspapers during the war were subject to the ''Defence of the Realm Act'', which eventually had two regulations restricting what they could publish:&lt;ref name=p22&gt;Paddock (2004), p 22&lt;/ref&gt; Regulation 18, which prohibited the leakage of sensitive military information, troop and shipping movements; and Regulation 27, which made it an offence to &quot;spread false reports&quot;, &quot;spread reports that were likely to prejudice recruiting&quot;, &quot;undermine public confidence in banks or currency&quot; or cause &quot;disaffection to His Majesty&quot;.&lt;ref name=p22/&gt; Where the official [[Press Bureau]] failed (it had no statutory powers until {{Nowrap|April 1916}}), the newspaper editors and owners operated a ruthless [[self-censorship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett394&quot;/&gt; Having worked for government, [[press baron]]s [[Harold Harmsworth, 1st Viscount Rothermere|Viscount Rothermere]],&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue= 31427|date= 1 July 1919|startpage= 8221|city= London|accessdate= 2008-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Max Aitken, 1st Baron Beaverbrook|Baron Beaverbrook]] (in a sea of controversy),&lt;ref&gt;McCreery (2005), pp 26–27&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Alfred Harmsworth, 1st Viscount Northcliffe|Viscount Northcliffe]]&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30533|startpage=2212|date=19 February 1918|accessdate=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; all received titles. For these reasons, it has been concluded that censorship, which at its height suppressed only socialist journals (and briefly the [[Right-wing politics|right wing]] ''The Globe'') had less effect on the British press than the reductions in advertising revenues and cost increases which they also faced during the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett394&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), pp 394–395&lt;/ref&gt; One major loophole in the official censorship lay with [[parliamentary privilege]], when anything said in Parliament could be reported freely.&lt;ref name=p22/&gt;  The most infamous act of censorship in the early days of the war was the sinking of [[HMS Audacious (1912)|HMS ''Audacious'']] in {{Nowrap|October 1914}}, when the press was directed not to report on the loss, despite the sinking being observed by passengers on the liner [[RMS Olympic|RMS ''Olympic'']] and quickly reported in the American press.&lt;ref&gt;Paddock (2004), p 24&lt;/ref&gt;

The most popular papers of the period included dailies such as ''[[The Times]]'', ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' and ''[[The Morning Post]]'', weekly newspapers such as ''[[The Graphic]]'' and periodicals like ''[[John Bull (magazine)|John Bull]]'', which claimed a weekly circulation of 900,000.&lt;ref&gt;Paddock (2004), p 16&lt;/ref&gt; The public demand for news of the war was reflected in the increased sales of newspapers. After the German Navy raid on Hartlepool and Scarborough, the ''[[Daily Mail]]'' devoted three full pages to the raid and the ''[[Evening News (London)|Evening News]]'' reported that ''The Times'' had sold out by a quarter past nine in the morning, even with inflated prices.&lt;ref&gt;Paddock (2004), p 34&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Daily Mail'' itself increased in circulation from 800,000 a day in 1914 to {{Nowrap|1.5 million}} by 1916.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett394&quot;/&gt;

===News magazines===
The public's thirst for news and information was in part satisfied by [[Newsmagazine|news magazines]], which were dedicated to reporting the war. They included amongst others ''[[The War Illustrated]]'', ''[[The Illustrated War News]]'', and ''[[The War Pictorial]]'', and were lavishly filled with photographs and illustrations, regardless of their [[target audience]]. Magazines were produced for all classes, and ranged both in price and tone. Many otherwise famous writers contributed towards these publications, of which H.G. Wells, Arthur Conan Doyle and Rudyard Kipling were three examples. Editorial guidelines varied; in cheaper publications especially it was considered more important to create a sense of [[patriotism]] than to relay up-to-the-minutes news of developments of the front. Stories of German atrocities were commonplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | title = War Weeklies  | publisher = ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''|date =1939-09-25| url = http://www.time.com/time/archive/preview/0,10987,761998,00.html  |accessdate=2009-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music===
On 13 August 1914, the Irish regiment the [[Connaught Rangers]] were witnessed singing &quot;[[It's a Long Way to Tipperary]]&quot; as they marched through [[Boulogne-sur-Mer|Boulogne]] by the ''[[Daily Mail]]'' correspondent George Curnock, who reported the event in that newspaper on {{Nowrap|18 August}} 1914. The song was then picked up by other units of the [[British Army]]. In {{Nowrap|November 1914}}, it was sung in a [[pantomime]] by the well-known [[music hall]] singer [[Florrie Forde]], which helped contribute to its worldwide popularity.&lt;ref&gt;Cryer (2009), p 188&lt;/ref&gt;
Another song from 1916, which became very popular as a [[music hall]] and [[marching song]], boosting British morale despite the horrors of that war, was &quot;[[Pack Up Your Troubles in Your Old Kit-Bag]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Shepherd (2003), p 390&lt;/ref&gt;

===War poets===
{{Further2|[[War poet#WWI|War poetry during World War&amp;nbsp;I]]}}
There was also a notable group of [[war poet]]s who wrote about their own experiences of war, which caught the public attention. Some died on active service, most famously [[Rupert Brooke]], [[Isaac Rosenberg]], and [[Wilfred Owen]], while some, such as [[Siegfried Sassoon]] survived. Themes of the poems included the youth (or naivety) of the soldiers, and the dignified manner in which they fought and died.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} This is evident in lines such as &quot;They fell with their faces to the foe&quot;, from the &quot;[[Ode of Remembrance]]&quot; taken from [[Laurence Binyon]]'s ''[[s:For the Fallen|For the Fallen]]'', which was first published in ''[[The Times]]'' in {{Nowrap|September 1914}}.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Times]]'' on {{Nowrap|21 September}} 1914.&lt;/ref&gt; Female poets such as [[Vera Brittain]] also wrote from the [[home front]], to lament the losses of brothers and lovers fighting on the front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=''Daily Telegraph''|date=13 February 2009|title=Vera Brittain to be subject for film|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/film/4612365/Vera-Brittain-to-be-subject-of-film.html| accessdate=2009-05-18 | location=London | first=Anita | last=Singh}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
{{main|Economic history of World War I#British Empire}}
On the whole the British successfully managed the economics of the war. There had been no prewar plan for mobilization of economic resources. Controls were imposed slowly, as one urgent need followed another.&lt;ref&gt;William Ashworth, ''An Economic History of England, 1870–1939'' (1960) pp 265–84.&lt;/ref&gt;  With the City of London the world's financial capital, it was possible to handle finances smoothly; in all Britain spent 4 million pounds everyday on the war effort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/13/benito-mussolini-recruited-mi5-italy|title=Recruited by MI5: the name's Mussolini. Benito Mussolini|author=Tom Kington}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The economy (in terms of GDP) grew about 14% from 1914 to 1918 despite the absence of so many men in the services; by contrast the German economy shrank 27%. The War saw a decline of civilian consumption, with a major reallocation to munitions. The government share of GDP soared from 8% in 1913 to 38% in 1918 (compared to 50% in 1943).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=David Stevenson|title=With Our Backs to the Wall: Victory and Defeat in 1918|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=06KYLGALKNEC&amp;pg=PA370|year=2011|publisher=Harvard U.P.|page=370|isbn=9780674062269}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Niall Ferguson, ''The Pity of War'' (1998) p 249&lt;/ref&gt;  The war forced Britain to use up its financial reserves and borrow large sums from private and government creditors in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Lobell, &quot;The Political Economy of War Mobilization: From Britain's Limited Liability to a Continental Commitment,&quot; ''International Politics'' (2006) 43#3 pp&amp;nbsp;283–304&lt;/ref&gt; Shipments of American raw materials and food allowed Britain to feed itself and its army while maintaining his productivity.  The financing was generally successful,&lt;ref&gt;M. J. Daunton, &quot;How to Pay for the War: State, Society and Taxation in Britain, 1917–24,&quot; ''English Historical Review'' (1996) 111# 443 pp.&amp;nbsp;882–919 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/577566 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; as the City's strong financial position minimized the damaging effects of inflation, as opposed to much worse conditions in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;T. Balderston, &quot;War finance and inflation in Britain and Germany, 1914–1918,&quot; ''Economic History Review'' (1989) 42#2 p p&amp;nbsp;222–244. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2596203 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;  Overall consumer consumption declined 18% from 1914 to 1919.&lt;ref&gt;B.R. Mitchell, ''Abstract of British Historical Statistics'' (1962) p 371&lt;/ref&gt;
Trade unions were encouraged as membership grew from 4.1 million in 1914 to 6.5 million in 1918, peaking at 8.3 million in 1920 before relapsing to 5.4 million in 1923.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell, ''Abstract of British Historical Statistics'' (1962) p 68&lt;/ref&gt; In Scotland, the shipbuilding industry expanding by a third.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Adrian Gregory|title=The Last Great War: British Society and the First World War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bq-AMQAACAAJ|year= 2008|publisher=Cambridge U.P.|isbn=9780521728836}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The trade unions enthusiastically supported the war, apart from the coal miners who were much less enthusiastic.

Women were available and many entered munitions factories and took other home front jobs vacated by men.&lt;ref&gt;Gail Braybon, ''Women Workers in the First World War: The British Experience'' (1990)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rationing===
{{Main|Rationing in the United Kingdom}}
[[Image:'Breaches of the Rationing Order' poster.jpg|thumb|alt=A document says &quot;DEFENCE OF THE REALM&quot;, &quot;MINISTRY OF FOOD&quot;, &quot;BREACHES OF THE RATIONING ORDER&quot;, &quot;The undermentioned convictions have been recently obtained&quot;, and a list of various offences committed and the punishments handed out.| A British government wartime leaflet detailing the consequences of breaking the rationing laws]]
In line with its &quot;[[Business as usual (policy)|business as usual]]&quot; policy, the government was initially reluctant to try to control the food markets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Samuel J. Hurwitz |title=State Intervention in Great Britain: Study of Economic Control and Social Response, 1914–1919|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZQtYAQAAQBAJ|year=1949|pages=12–29|isbn=9781136931864}}
&lt;/ref&gt; It fought off efforts to try to introduce minimum prices in cereal production, though relenting in the area of controlling of essential imports (sugar, meat and grains). When it did introduce changes, they were only limited in their effect. In 1916, it became illegal to consume more than two courses whilst lunching in a public eating place or more than three for dinner; fines were introduced for members of the public found feeding the [[pigeon]]s or stray animals.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck381&quot;/&gt;

In January 1917, Germany started using [[U-boats]] (submarines) in order to sink Allied and later neutral ships bringing food to the country in an attempt to starve Britain into surrender under their [[unrestricted submarine warfare]] programme. One response to this threat was to introduce voluntary [[rationing]] in {{Nowrap|February 1917}},&lt;ref name=&quot;beck381&quot;/&gt; a scheme said to have been endorsed by the king and queen themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Condell &amp; Liddiard (1987), p 18&lt;/ref&gt; Bread was subsidised from September that year; prompted by [[Local government|local authorities]] taking matters into their own hands, compulsory rationing was introduced in stages between {{Nowrap|December 1917}} and {{Nowrap|February 1918}},&lt;ref name=&quot;beck381&quot;/&gt; as Britain's supply of wheat stores decreased to just six weeks worth.&lt;ref&gt;Morrow (2005), p 202&lt;/ref&gt; It is said to have in the most part benefited the health of the country,&lt;ref name=&quot;beck381&quot;/&gt; through the 'levelling of consumption of essential foodstuffs'.&lt;ref&gt;Beckett attributes this quotation (page 382) to Margaret Barnett, but does not give further details.&lt;/ref&gt; To assist with rationing, [[Rationing|ration books]] were introduced on {{Nowrap|15 July}} 1918 for butter, margarine, lard, meat, and sugar.&lt;ref&gt;Palmer (1992), pp 355–356&lt;/ref&gt; During the war, average calories intake decreased only three percent, but protein intake six percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck381&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), pp 380–382&lt;/ref&gt;

===Industry===
[[File:WWIworkersElisabethville.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Workers stand around a large forge, where a shell burns red-hot.|Belgian refugees work forging shell cases]]
Total British production fell by ten percent over the course of the war; there were, however, increases in certain industries such as steel.&lt;ref name=beckett341/&gt; Although Britain faced a controversial [[Shell (projectile)|shell]] shortage, this has been attributed to extraordinary orders placed by the government at the outbreak of war (without concern for the capacity of its industry), rather than inefficient production.&lt;ref name=beckett341/&gt; In 1915, the [[Ministry of Munitions]] under [[David Lloyd-George]] was formed to control munitions production and had considerable success.&lt;ref&gt;Bentley Gilbert, ''David Lloyd George: Organizer of Victory 1912–1916'' (1992), pp 209–50&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Grigg, ''Lloyd George: From Peace to War 1912–1916'' (1985) pp 223–56&lt;/ref&gt;  By {{Nowrap|April 1915}}, just two million rounds of shells had been sent to France; by the end of the war the figure had reached {{Nowrap|187 million}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pathways/firstworldwar/britain/war_changing.htm|accessdate=2009-05-16|title=The war and the changing face of British society|publisher=The National Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a year's worth of pre-war production of light munitions could be completed in just four days by 1918.  Aircraft production in 1914 provided employment for 60,000 men and women; by 1918 British firms employed over 347,000.&lt;ref name=beckett341&gt;Beckett (2007), pp 341–343&lt;/ref&gt;
===Labour===
Industrial production of munitions was a central feature of the war, and with a third of the men in the labour force moved into the military, demand was very high for industrial labour. Large numbers of women were employed temporarily.&lt;ref&gt;John N. Horne, ''Labour at war: France and Britain, 1914-1918'' (1991).&lt;/ref&gt; Trade unions gave strong support to the war effort, cutting back on strikes and restrictive practices.   Membership doubled from 4.1 million in 1914, 28.3 million in 1920. 65 percent of union members had been associated with the [[Trades Union Congress]] (TUC) In 1914, rising to 77 percent in 1920. Labour's prestige had never been higher, and it systematically placed its leaders into Parliament.&lt;ref&gt; David Swift, &quot;Patriotic labour in the era of the great war&quot; (PhD. Dissertation University of Central Lancashire, 2014) [http://clok.uclan.ac.uk/11810/1/Swift%20David%20Final%20e-Thesis%20Submission%20(Master%20Copy).pdf online] Detailed bibliography on pp 220-35.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Munitions of War Act 1915]] followed the [[Shell Crisis of 1915]] when supplies of material to the front became a political issue. The Act forbade strikes and lockouts and replaced them with compulsory arbitration. It set up a system of controlling war industries, and established munitions tribunals that were special courts to enforce good working practices. It suspended, for the duration,  restrictive practices by trade unions. It tried to control labour mobility between jobs. The courts ruled the definition of munitions was broad enough to include textile workers and dock workers. 1915 act was repealed in 1919, but similar legislation took effect during the Second World War. &lt;ref&gt;F. M. Leventhal, ed. ''Twentieth-Century Britain: An Encyclopedia'' (1995) p 78-80.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beckett (2007), p 369&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gerry R. Rubin, &quot;Law, War and Economy: The Munitions Acts 1915-17 and Corporatism in Context.&quot; ''Journal of Law and Society'' 11.3 (1984): 317-333.&lt;/ref&gt;

It was only as late as December 1917 that a War Cabinet Committee on Manpower was established, and the British government refrained from introducing compulsory labour direction (though 388 men were moved as part of the voluntary National Service Scheme). Belgian refugees became workers, though they were often seen as &quot;job stealers&quot;. Likewise, the use of Irish workers, because they were exempt from conscription, was another source of resentment.&lt;ref&gt;Beckett (2007), p 366&lt;/ref&gt; Worried about the impact of the dilution of labour caused by bringing external groups into the main labour pool, workers in some areas turned to [[strike action]]. 
The efficiency of major industries improved markedly during the war. For example, the Singer Clydebank sewing machine factory received over 5000 government contracts, and made 303 million artillery shells, shell components, fuzes, and airplane parts, as well as grenades, rifle parts, and 361,000 horseshoes. Its labour force of 14,000 was about 70 percent female at war's end.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Bruce Davies, ''Peacefully working to conquer the world'' (Arno Press, 19760 p 170&lt;/ref&gt;

===Energy===
Energy was a critical factor for the British war effort.  Most of the energy supplies came from coal mines in Britain, where the issue was labour supply.  Critical however was the flow of oil for ships, lorries and industrial use.  There were no oil wells in Britain so everything was imported. The U.S. pumped two-thirds of the world's oil. In 1917, total British consumption was 827 million barrels, of which 85 percent was supplied by the United States, and 6 percent by Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;[[Harold F. Williamson]], ''The American Petroleum Industry: the Age of Energy 1899–1959 '' (1963) 2:267&lt;/ref&gt;  The great issue in 1917 was how many tankers would survive the German u-boats. Convoys and the construction of new tankers solved the German threat, while tight government controls guaranteed that all essential needs were covered. An Inter-Allied Petroleum Conference allocated American supplies to Britain, France and Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Yergin, ''The Prize: The Epic Quest for Oil, Money and Power''  (1991) pp 176–77&lt;/ref&gt;

Fuel oil for the Royal Navy was the highest priority.  In 1917, the Royal Navy consumed 12,500 tons a month, but had a supply of 30,000 tons a month from British Petroleum, using BPs oil wells in Persia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Ronald W. Ferrier|author2=J. H. Bamberg|title=The History of the British Petroleum Company: Volume 1, The Developing Years, 1901–1932|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aNBQnow_wbYC&amp;pg=SL1-PA13|year=1982|publisher=Cambridge UP|pages=A–13|isbn=9780521246477}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social change==
{{main|Women's roles in the World Wars#World War I}}
Variously throughout the war, serious shortage of [[able-bodied]] men (&quot;manpower&quot;) occurred in the country, and women were required to take on many of the traditional male roles, particularly in the area of arms manufacture; though this was only significant in the later years of the war, since unemployed men were often prioritised by employers.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), pp 455–460&lt;/ref&gt; Women both found work in the [[munitions]] factories (as &quot;munitionettes&quot;) despite initial [[trade union]] opposition, which directly helped the war effort, but also in the [[Her Majesty's Civil Service|Civil Service]], where they took men's jobs, releasing them for the front. The number of women employed by the service increased from 33,000 in 1911 to over 102,000 by 1921.&lt;ref name=Homefront/&gt; The overall increase in female employment is estimated at {{Nowrap|1.4 million}}, from 5.9 to {{Nowrap|7.3 million}},&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;/&gt; and female trade union membership increased from 357,000 in 1914 to over a million by 1918—an increase of 160 percent.&lt;ref name=Homefront&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-13|title=Women on the Home Front in World War One|author=Professor [[Joanna Bourke]]|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/women_employment_01.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beckett suggests that most of these were [[working class]] women going into work at a younger age than they would otherwise have done, or married women returning to work.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;/&gt; This taken together with the fact that only 23 percent of women in the munitions industry were actually doing men's jobs, would limit substantially the overall impact of the war on the long-term prospects of the working woman.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Women's-Land-Army-1917.jpg|thumb|First World War poster]]
When the government targeted women early in the war focussed on extending their existing roles&amp;nbsp;– helping with Belgian refugees, for example—but also on improving recruitment rates amongst men. They did this both through the so-called &quot;Order of the White Feather&quot; and through the promise of home comforts for the men while they were at the front. In {{Nowrap|February 1916}}, groups were set up and a campaign started to get women to help in agriculture and in {{Nowrap|March 1917}}, the [[Women's Land Army]] was set up. One goal was to attract middle-class women who would act as models for patriotic engagement in nontraditional duties. However the uniform of the Women's Land Army included male overalls and trousers, which sparked debate on the propriety of such cross-dressing. The government responded with rhetoric that explicitly feminized the new roles.&lt;ref&gt;Susan R. Grayzel, &quot;Nostalgia, Gender, and The Countryside: Placing the 'Land Girl' in First World War Britain,&quot; ''Rural History'' (1999) 10#2 pp 155–170.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1918, the [[Board of Trade]] estimated that there were 148,000 women in agricultural employment, though a figure of nearly 260,000 has also been suggested.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;/&gt;

The war also caused a split in the [[Women's suffrage in the United Kingdom|British suffragette movement]], with the mainstream, represented by [[Emmeline Pankhurst]] and her daughter [[Christabel Pankhurst|Christabel]]'s [[Women's Social and Political Union]], calling a '[[ceasefire]]' in their campaign for the duration of the war. In contrast, more [[Extremism|radical]] suffragettes, like the [[Women's Suffrage Federation]] run by Emmeline's other daughter, [[Sylvia Pankhurst|Sylvia]], continued their (at times violent) struggle. Women were also allowed to join the armed forces in a non-combatant role&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;/&gt; and by the end of the War 80,000 women had joined the armed forces in auxiliary roles such as nursing and cooking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-13|title=Women and the Military during World War One|author=Professor [[Joanna Bourke]]|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/women_combatants_01.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the war, millions of returning soldiers were still not entitled to vote.&lt;ref name=Hugh/&gt; This posed another dilemma for politicians since they could be seen to be withholding the vote from the very men who had just fought to preserve the British democratic political system. The [[Representation of the People Act 1918]] attempted to solve the problem, enfranchising all adult males as long as they were over 21 years old and were resident householders.&lt;ref name=Hugh/&gt; It also gave the vote to women over 30 who met minimum property qualifications. The enfranchisement of this latter group was accepted as recognition of the contribution made by women defence workers,&lt;ref name=Hugh&gt;Fraser (1918)&lt;/ref&gt; though the actual feelings of [[Members of parliament#United Kingdom|members of parliament]] (MPs) at the time is questioned.&lt;ref name=&quot;beckett455&quot;/&gt; In the same year the [[Parliament (Qualification of Women) Act 1918]] allowed women over 21 to stand as MPs.&lt;ref&gt;Law (1997), p 115&lt;/ref&gt;

The new coalition government of 1918 charged itself with the task of creating a &quot;land fit for heroes&quot;, from a speech given in [[Wolverhampton]] by David Lloyd George on {{Nowrap|23 November}} 1918, where he stated &quot;What is our task? To make Britain a fit country for heroes to live in.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Times'', {{Nowrap|25 November}} 1918.&lt;/ref&gt; More generally, the war has been credited, both during and after the conflict, with removing some of the social barriers that had pervaded Victorian and Edwardian Britain.&lt;ref name=social&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2009-05-16|publisher=National Archives|title=The war and the changing face of British society|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pathways/firstworldwar/britain/war_changing.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Regional conditions==
The War had a profound influence upon rural areas, as the U-boat blockade required the government to take full control of the food chain, as well as agricultural labour. Cereal production was a high priority, and the [[Corn Production Act 1917]] guaranteed prices, regulated wage rates, and required farmers to meet efficiency standards.  The government campaigned heavily for turning marginal land into cropland.&lt;ref&gt;Pamela Horn, ''Rural Life in England in the First World War'' (St. Martin's Press, 1984)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter E. Dewey, &quot;British Farming Profits and Government Policy During the First World War.&quot; ''Economic History Review'' (1984) 37#3 pp: 373–390.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter E. Dewey, '' British Agriculture in the First World War'' (1989)&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Women's Land Army]] brought in 23,000 young women from the towns and cities to milk cows, pick fruit and otherwise replace the men who joined the services.&lt;ref&gt;Bonnie White, ''The Women's Land Army in First World War Britain'' (2014)&lt;/ref&gt; More extensive use of tractors and machinery also replaced farm labourers. However, there was a  shortage of both men and horses on the land by late 1915. County [[War Agricultural Executive Committee]]s reported that the continued removal of men was undercutting food production because of the farmers' belief that operating a farm required a set number of men and horses.&lt;ref&gt;Bonnie White, &quot;Feeding the war effort: agricultural experiences in First World War Devon, 1914–17,&quot; ''Agricultural History Review'' (2010) 58#1 pp 95–112.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kenneth O. Morgan|Kenneth Morgan]] argues  that, 'the overwhelming mass of the Welsh people cast aside their political and industrial divisions and threw themselves into the war with gusto.&quot; Intellectuals and ministers actively promoted the war spirit.  With 280,000 men  enrolled in the services (14% of the population), the proportionate effort in Wales outstripped both England and Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Kenneth O. Morgan|title=Rebirth of a Nation: Wales, 1880–1980|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2DB2EHJ08aIC&amp;pg=PA159|year=1981|publisher=Oxford UP|pages=159–60|isbn=9780198217367}}&lt;/ref&gt; However Adrian Gregory points out that the Welsh coal miners, while officially supporting the war effort, refused the government request to cut short their vacation time. After some debate, the miners agreed to extend the working day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Adrian Gregory|title=The Last Great War: British Society and the First World War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VfjZAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT5|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge UP|isbn=9781107650862}} ch 1&lt;/ref&gt;

Scotland's distinctive  characteristics have attracted significant attention from scholars.&lt;ref&gt;C. M. M. Macdonald and E. W. McFarland, eds, ''Scotland and the Great War'' (Edinburgh: Tuckwell Press, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike England, Scotland specialized in providing manpower, ships, machinery, food (particularly fish) and money. Daniel shows it supported the war effort with widespread enthusiasm.&lt;ref&gt;D. Daniel, &quot;Measures of enthusiasm: new avenues in quantifying variations in voluntary enlistment in Scotland, August 1914 – December 1915&quot;, ''Local Population Studies,'' Spring 2005, Issue 74, pp. 16–35.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Casualties==
{{see also|World War I casualties}}
[[File:National Fund for Welsh Troops2.jpg|thumb|Poster for a fundraising event in support of Welsh troops by [[Frank Brangwyn]]]]

In the post war publication ''Statistics of the Military Effort of the British Empire During the Great War 1914–1920'' ([[War Office|The War Office]], {{Nowrap|March 1922}}), the official report lists 908,371 'soldiers' as being either [[killed in action]], dying of wounds, dying as [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]] or missing in action in the World War. (This is broken down into the United Kingdom and its colonies 704,121; British India 64,449; Canada 56,639; Australia 59,330; New Zealand 16,711; South Africa 7,121.)&lt;ref name=WAR/&gt; Listed separately were the Royal Navy (including the Royal Naval Air Service until 31 March 1918) war dead and missing of 32,287 and the [[Merchant Navy]] war dead of 14,661.&lt;ref name=WAR/&gt; The figures for the Royal Flying Corps and the nascent Royal Air Force were not given in the War Office report.&lt;ref name=WAR&gt;The War Office (1992), p. 339&lt;/ref&gt;

A second publication, ''Casualties and Medical Statistics'' (1931), the final volume of the ''Official Medical History of the War'', gives British Empire Army losses by cause of death.&lt;ref name=Mitchell&gt;Mitchell (1931), p 12&lt;/ref&gt; The total losses in combat from 1914 to 1918 were 876,084, which included 418,361 killed, 167,172 died of wounds, 113,173 died of disease or injury, 161,046 missing presumed dead and 16,332 died as a prisoner of war.&lt;ref name=Mitchell/&gt;

The [[Commonwealth War Graves Commission]] lists 888,246 war dead from the UK and colonies (excluding the [[dominion]]s, which are listed separately). This figure includes identified burials and those commemorated by name on memorials; there are an additional 187,644 unidentified burials from the Commonwealth (then Empire) as a whole.&lt;ref name=&quot;cwgc.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.cwgc.org/learning-and-resources/publications/annual-report.aspx Commonwealth War Graves Commission Annual Report 2010-2011], page 45.&lt;/ref&gt;

The civilian death rate exceeded the prewar level by 292,000, which included 109,000 deaths due to food shortages and 183,577 from [[Spanish Flu]].&lt;ref name=WAR/&gt; The 1922 War Office report detailed the deaths of 1,260 civilians and 310 military personnel due to air and sea bombardment of the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;Gilbert (1994), pp 674–678&lt;/ref&gt; Losses at sea were 908 United Kingdom civilians and 63 fisherman killed by [[U-boat]] attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Gilbert (1994), p 78&lt;/ref&gt;

With a population of 4.8 million in 1911, Scotland sent 690,000 men to the war, of whom 74,000 died in combat or from disease, and 150,000 were seriously wounded.&lt;ref&gt;I. F. W. Beckett and K. R. Simpson, eds. ''A Nation in Arms: a Social Study of the British Army in the First World War'' (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 1985) p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R. A. Houston and W. W. Knox, eds, ''The New Penguin History of Scotland'' (London: Penguin, 2001),  p. 426.&lt;/ref&gt;  At times Scottish troops made up large proportions of the active combatants, and suffered corresponding loses, as at the [[Battle of Loos]], where there were three full Scots divisions and other Scottish units.&lt;ref name=Lenman&amp;Mackie1991/&gt; Thus, although Scots were only 10 per cent of the British population, they made up 15 per cent of the national armed forces and eventually accounted for 20 per cent of the dead.&lt;ref name=Buchanan2003p49/&gt; Some areas, like the thinly populated Island of [[Lewis and Harris]] suffered some of the highest proportional losses of any part of Britain.&lt;ref name=Lenman&amp;Mackie1991/&gt; Clydeside shipyards and the engineering shops of west-central Scotland became the most significant centre of shipbuilding and arms production in the Empire. In the Lowlands, particularly Glasgow, poor working and living conditions led to industrial and political unrest.&lt;ref name=Buchanan2003p49&gt;J. Buchanan, ''Scotland'' (Langenscheidt, 3rd edn., 2003), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and memory==
{{multiple image
 | align = right
 | direction = vertical
 | width = 300
 | image1 = British Empire in 1898.png
 | alt1 = A map showing various areas highlighted, including Great Britain, Canada, South Africa, Australia and New Zealand
 | caption1 = The extent of the British Empire in 1898
 | image2 = British Empire in 1914.png
 | alt2 = The same map, with additional areas coloured (see text)
 | caption2 = The extent of the British Empire in 1914
 | image3 = British Empire 1921.png
 | alt3 = The same map, with additional areas coloured (see text)
 | caption3 = The extent of the British Empire in 1921
}}
The horrors of the Western Front as well as Gallipoli and Mesopotamia were seared into the collective consciousness of the twentieth century.  To a large extent the understanding of the war in popular culture focused on the first day of the Battle of the Somme.  Historian A.J.P. Taylor argued, &quot;The Somme set the picture by which future generations saw the First World War: brave helpless soldiers; blundering obstinate generals; nothing achieved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Brian Bond|title=The Unquiet Western Front: Britain's Role in Literature and History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=luUIXRu2bSUC&amp;pg=PA62|year=2002|publisher=Cambridge UP|pages=62–63|isbn=9781139434096}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Images of trench warfare became iconic symbols of human suffering and endurance. The post-war world had many veterans who were maimed or damaged by shell shock.  In 1921 1,187,450 men were in receipt of pensions for war disabilities, with a fifth of these having suffered serious loss of limbs or eyesight, paralysis or lunacy.&lt;ref&gt;Chris Wrigley,  &quot;The Impact of the First World War,&quot; in Chris Wrigley, ed., ''A Companion to Early Twentieth-Century Britain'' (2003)  pp 502,  512&lt;/ref&gt;

The war was a major economic catastrophe as Britain went from being the world's largest overseas investor to being its biggest debtor, with interest payments consuming around 40 percent of the national budget.&lt;ref name=inflation/&gt; Inflation more than doubled between 1914 and its peak in 1920, while the value of the Pound Sterling fell by 61.2 percent. Reparations in the form of free German coal depressed the local industry, precipitating the [[UK General Strike 1926|1926 General Strike]].&lt;ref name=inflation&gt;{{cite web|title=Inflation value of the Pound|publisher=House of Commons|accessdate=2009-05-16|url=http://www.parliament.uk/commons/lib/research/rp99/rp99-020.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the war British private investments abroad were sold, raising {{Nowrap|£550 million}}. However, {{Nowrap|£250 million}} new investment also took place during the war. The net financial loss was therefore approximately {{Nowrap|£300 million}}; less than two years investment compared to the pre-war average rate and more than replaced by 1928.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2001), p 123&lt;/ref&gt; Material loss was &quot;slight&quot;: the most significant being 40 percent of the British merchant fleet sunk by German U-boats. Most of this was replaced in 1918 and all immediately after the war.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2001), p 122&lt;/ref&gt; The military historian [[Correlli Barnett]] has argued that &quot;in objective truth the Great War in no way inflicted crippling economic damage on Britain&quot; but that the war only &quot;crippled the British ''psychologically''&quot; (emphasis in original).&lt;ref&gt;Barnett (2002), pp 424–426&lt;/ref&gt;

Less concrete changes include the growing assertiveness of the [[British Dominions|Dominions]] within the British Empire. Battles such as [[Battle of Gallipoli|Gallipoli]] for Australia and New Zealand,&lt;ref name=beaumont&gt;Beaumont (1995), pp 125–148&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Battle of Vimy Ridge|Vimy Ridge]] for Canada led to increased national pride and a greater reluctance to remain subordinate to the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=pierce&gt;Pierce (1992), p 5&lt;/ref&gt; These battles were often portrayed favourably in these nations' propaganda as symbolic of their power during the war.&lt;ref name=pierce/&gt;&lt;ref name=beaumont/&gt; The war released pent-up indigenous [[nationalism]], as populations tried to take advantage of the precedent set by the introduction of [[self-determination]] in eastern Europe. Britain was to face unrest in Ireland (1919–21), India (1919), Egypt (1919–23), Palestine (1920–21) and Iraq (1920) at a time when they were supposed to be demilitarising.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beckett564&quot;&gt;Beckett (2007), p 564&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Britain's only territorial loss came in Ireland,&lt;ref name=&quot;Beckett564&quot;/&gt; where the delay in finding a resolution to the [[home rule]] issue, along with the 1916 [[Easter Rising]] and a failed attempt to introduce [[Conscription Crisis of 1918|conscription in Ireland]], increased support for separatist radicals, and led indirectly to the outbreak of the [[Irish War of Independence]] in 1919.&lt;ref&gt;Hennessey (1998), p 220&lt;/ref&gt;

Further change came in 1919. With the [[Treaty of Versailles]], London took charge of an additional {{convert|1800000|sqmi|km2}} and {{Nowrap|13 million}} new subjects.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (2004), p 315&lt;/ref&gt; The colonies of Germany and the [[Ottoman Empire]] were distributed to the Allied powers (and to Australia, New Zealand and South Africa) as [[League of Nations mandate]]s, with the United Kingdom at least gaining control of [[British Mandate of Palestine|Palestine and Transjordan]], [[British Mandate of Mesopotamia|Iraq]], parts of [[Cameroons|Cameroon]] and [[Togo]], and [[Tanganyika]].&lt;ref&gt;Olson (1996), p 658&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, the British Empire reached its territorial peak after the settlement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beckett564&quot;/&gt;
{{-}}

==References==
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
{{portal|World War I}}
{{refbegin}}
* ''Encyclopaedia Britannica'' (12th ed. 1922) comprises the 11th edition plus three new volumes 30-31-32 that cover events since 1911 with very thorough coverage of the war as well as every country and colony. Included also in 13th edition (1926) [[s:1922 Encyclopædia Britannica|partly online]]
*{{cite book|last=Beckett|first=Ian F.W.|title=The Great war|year=2007|publisher=Longman|edition=2|isbn=1-4058-1252-4}} Available on [https://books.google.com/books?id=CMYbKgcAW88C Google books].
* Beckett, Ian F.W. ''The Home Front, 1914–1918: How Britain Survived the Great War'' (2006) [http://www.amazon.com/Home-Front-1914-1918-Britain-Survived/dp/1903365813/  excerpt and text search]
*{{cite book|last=Chandler|first=David|title=The Oxford History of the British Army|year=2003|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0-19-280311-5}}
* ''The Cambridge History of the First World War Volume 3: Civil Society'' (2014) [http://universitypublishingonline.org/cambridge/histories/subject_title_list.jsf?subjectCode=15&amp;heading=Warfare&amp;tSort=title+closed&amp;aSort=author+default_list&amp;ySort=year+default_list online]
*{{cite book|last=Ferguson|first=Niall|authorlink=Niall Ferguson|title=The Pity of War|year=1999|publisher=Penguin Books| isbn=0-14-027523-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Gilbert|first=Martin|title=Atlas of World War&amp;nbsp;I|year=1994|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn= 0-19-521077-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Massie|first=Robert|authorlink=Robert Massie|title=[[Castles of Steel: Britain, Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea]]|year=2004|publisher=Jonathan Cape|location=London|isbn=0-224-04092-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Mitchell|first=T.J.|title=Casualties and Medical Statistics of the Great War|year=1931|publisher=Reprinted by Battery Press (1997)|location=London|isbn=0-89839-263-2}}
*{{cite book|last1=Palmer|first1=Alan|last2=Palmer|first2=Veronica|year=1992|title= The Chronology of British History|publisher= Century Ltd|location=London|isbn= 0-7126-5616-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Powers|first=Barry D|title=Strategy without slide-rule: British air strategy, 1914–1939|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=1976|isbn=0-85664-219-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Taylor|first=A. J. P.|authorlink=A. J. P. Taylor|title=English History 1914–1945 (The Oxford History of England)|year=2001|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|isbn=0-19-280140-6}}
*{{cite book|last1=Tucker|first1=Spencer|last2=Roberts|first2=Priscilla Mary|title=World War&amp;nbsp;I: encyclopedia|year=2005|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=1-85109-420-2}} Available on [https://books.google.com/books?id=B1cMtKQP3P8C Google books].
* Turner, John, ed. ''Britain and the First World War'' (1988)
*{{cite book|author=The War Office|authorlink=War Office|title=Statistics of the Military Effort of the British Empire During the Great War 1914–1920|year=1922|publisher=Reprinted by Naval &amp; Military Press|isbn=1-84734-682-0}}
*{{cite book|author=[[His Majesty's stationery Office]] (H.M.S.O.)|title=Statistics of the Military Effort of the British Empire During the Great War, 1914–1920|year=1922}}
* Wilson, Trevor. '' The Myriad Faces of War: Britain and the Great War 1914–1918'' (1989) [http://www.amazon.com/Myriad-Faces-War-Britain-1914-1918/dp/0745606458/  excerpt and text search] 864pp; covers both the homefront and the battlefields
* Winter, Jay, and Jean-Louis Robert, eds. ''Capital Cities at War: Paris, London, Berlin 1914–1919'' (2 vol. 1999, 2007), 30 chapters 1200pp; comprehensive coverage by scholars [http://www.amazon.com/Capital-Cities-War-1914-1919-Cultural/dp/052166814X/ vol 1 excerpt]; [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0521870437/ vol 2 excerpt and text search]

===Politics and royalty===
*{{cite book|last=Adams|first=R. J. Q.| authorlink= R. J. Q. Adams | title=Bonar Law|year=1999|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-3716-6}} Available on [https://books.google.com/books?id=9mj2hNGMh6wC Google books].
*{{cite book|last=Bourne|first=J M|title=Who's who in World War One|year=2001|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-14179-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Bradford |first=Sarah|title=King George&amp;nbsp;VI |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |location=London |year=1989 |isbn=0-297-79667-4}}
* Gilbert, Bentley. ''David Lloyd George: Organizer of Victory 1912–1916'' (1992)
* Grigg, John. ''Lloyd George: From Peace to War 1912–1916'' (1985)
* Grigg, John. ''Lloyd George: War Leader 1916–1918'' (2002)
*{{cite book|last=Hennessey|first=Thomas|title=Dividing Ireland, World War&amp;nbsp;I and Partition, The Irish Convention and Conscription|year=1998|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-17420-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Nicolson|first=Sir Harold|authorlink=Harold Nicolson|title=King George the Fifth: His Life and Reign|year=1952|publisher=Constable and Co|location=London|isbn=978-0-09-453181-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Paddock|first=Troy R E|title=A call to arms: propaganda, public opinion, and newspapers in the Great War|year=2004|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0-275-97383-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Pennell|first=Catriona|title=A Kingdom United: Popular Responses to the Outbreak of the First World War in Britain and Ireland|year=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn= 978-0-19-959058-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Pope-Hennessy|first=James|authorlink=James Pope-Hennessy|title=Queen Mary|year=1959|publisher=George Allen and Unwin, Ltd|location=London|isbn=1-84212-032-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Roberts|first=Andrew|year=2000|title=The House of Windsor|publisher=Cassell and Co|location=London|isbn=0-520-22803-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Rose|first=Kenneth|authorlink=Kenneth Rose|title=King George&amp;nbsp;V|year=1983|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|location=London|isbn=0-297-78245-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Thornton-Cook|first=Elsie|title=Royal Marys, Princess Mary and Her Predecessors|publisher=Ayer Publishing|year=1977|isbn=0-8369-0940-2}}
* Turner, John. ''British Politics and the Great War: Coalition and Conflict 1915–1918'' (1992)
*{{cite book|last=Ziegler|first=Philip|year=1991|title=King Edward&amp;nbsp;VIII: The official biography|publisher=Alfred A. Knopf|location=New York|isbn=0-7509-2747-X}}

===Empire===
* Beaumont, '' Broken Nation: Australians in the Great War'' (2014)
*{{cite book|last=Beaumont|first=Joan|title=Australia's War, 1914–1918|year=1995|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=St Leonards|isbn=1-86373-461-9}}
* Fogarty, Richard S., and David Killingray. &quot;Demobilization in British and French Africa at the End of the First World War.&quot; ''Journal of Contemporary History'' (2015) 50#1 pp: 100–123.
*{{cite book|last=McCreery|first=Christopher|title=The Order of Canada|year=2005|publisher=University of Toronto Press|isbn=0-8020-3940-5}} Available on [https://books.google.com/books?id=4f_dQFXQpVkC Google books].
*{{cite book|last=Olson|first=James|title=Historical Dictionary of the British Empire|year=1996|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group| isbn=0-313-29366-X}}
*{{cite book|last=Morrow|first=John Howard|title=The Great War: An Imperial History|year=2005|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-20440-2}}
*{{cite journal|last=Pierce|first=John|title=Constructing Memory: The Vimy Memorial|journal=Canadian Military History|accessdate=2009-05-17| volume=1| issue=1–2|date=Spring 1992|pages=5–14|url=http://www.wlu.ca/lcmsds/cmh/back%20issues/CMH/volume%201/issue%201-2/Pierce%20-%20Constructing%20Memory%20-%20The%20Vimy%20Memorial.pdf|format=PDF}}

===Economics===
* Adams, R. J. Q.  &quot;Delivering the Goods: Reappaising the Ministry of Munitions: 1915–1916.&quot; ''Albion: A Quarterly Journal Concerned with British Studies'' (1975) 7#3 pp: 232–244  [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4048178 in JSTOR]
* Adams, R. J. Q. ''Arms and the Wizard: Lloyd George and the Ministry of Munitions''.  (1978)
* Ashworth, William. ''An Economic History of England, 1870–1939'' (1960)
*{{cite book|last=Baker|first=Charles Whiting|title=Government control and operation of industry in Great Britain and the United States during the World War|year=1921|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|url=https://archive.org/details/governmentcontro00bakeuoft|accessdate=2009-05-18}} As available from [[Archive.org]].
* Barnett, Margaret. ''British food policy during the First World War'' (Routledge, 2014)
*{{cite book|last=Barnett|first=Correlli|authorlink=Correlli Barnett|title=The Collapse of British Power|year=2002|publisher=Pan books|isbn=0-330-49181-4}}
* Hancock, W.K. and M. M. Gowing. ''British War Economy'' (1949) pp 3–40
*{{cite book|author=Hurwitz, Samuel J.|title=State Intervention in Great Britain: Study of Economic Control and Social Response, 1914–1919|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZQtYAQAAQBAJ|year=1949|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781136931864}}
* Whetham, Edith H. ''The Agrarian History of England and Wales: Volume VIII: 1914–39'' (Cambridge University Press, 1978), pp 70–123

===Propaganda and popular culture===
* Bell, Stuart. &quot;‘Soldiers of Christ arise’: Religious Nationalism in the East Midlands during World War I.&quot; ''Midland History'' 39.2 (2014): 219–235.
* Field, Clive. &quot;Keeping the Spiritual Home Fires Burning: Religious Belonging in Britain during the First World War.&quot; ''War &amp; Society'' 33.4 (2014): 244–268.
* Goebel, Stefan and White, Jerry. &quot;London and the First World War&quot;. London Journal 41:3 (2016): 1–20, &lt;URL: http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/03058034.2016.1216758&gt;
* Green, Leanne. &quot;Advertising war: Picturing Belgium in First World War publicity.&quot; ''Media, War &amp; Conflict'' 7.3 (2014): 309–325.
* Haste, Cate. ''Keep the home fires burning: Propaganda in the First World War'' (Lane, Allen, 1977)
* Hynes, Samuel. ''A war imagined: the First World War and English culture'' (2011)
* Kennedy, Kate. &quot;‘A music of grief’: classical music and the First World War.&quot; ''International Affairs'' 90.2 (2014): 379–395.
* [[Harold D. Lasswell|Lasswell, Harold D.]]. ''Propaganda Technique in World War I''. (1927)
* Lonsdale, Sarah. &quot;“Roast Seagull and other Quaint Bird Dishes” The development of features and “lifestyle” journalism in British newspapers during the First World War.&quot; ''Journalism Studies''  (2014): 1–16.
* Millman, Brock. ''Managing Domestic Dissent in First World War Britain'' (Routledge, 2014)
* Monger, David. ''Patriotism and Propaganda in First World War Britain: The National War Aims Committee and Civilian Morale'' (2013) [https://www.questia.com/library/120084907/patriotism-and-propaganda-in-first-world-war-britain online edition]
* O'Prey, Paul. &quot;Poetry of the First World War: Dispelling the Myths.&quot; ''The RUSI Journal'' 159.4 (2014): 102–105.
* Wilkinson, Alan. ''The Church of England and the First World War'' (Lutterworth Press, 2014)
* Williams, Vanessa. &quot;“Welded in a single mass”: Memory and Community in London’s Concert Halls during the First World War.&quot; ''Journal of Musicological Research3.1–3 (2014): 27–38.

===Women, family and society ===
*{{cite book|last=Braybon|first=Gail|title=Women Workers in the First World War: The British Experience|year=1990|publisher=Routledge|location=London}}
*{{cite book|last1=Condell|first1=Diana|last2=Liddiard|first2=Jean|title=Working for victory?: images of women in the First World War, 1914–18|year=1987|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-7102-0974-6}} Available on [https://books.google.com/books?id=r5g9AAAAIAAJ Google books].
* Grayzel, Susan R. ''Women's identities at war: gender, motherhood, and politics in Britain and France during the First World War'' . UNC Press Books, 1999.
*{{cite book|last=Gregory|first=Adrian|title=The Last Great War: British Society and the First World War|location=Cambridge|year=2008|url=http://www.amazon.com/Last-Great-War-British-Society-ebook/dp/B00GA22I5C/}}
*{{cite book|last=Law|first=Cheryl|title=Suffrage and power: the women's movement, 1918–1928|publisher=I.B. Tauris|year=1997|isbn=1-86064-201-2}} Available on [https://books.google.com/books?id=C17PslUo1DYC Google books].
* Marwick, Arthur (1965) ''The Deluge: British Society and the First World War'' ISBN 0-393-00523-2
* Peel, Mrs. C.S. (Dorothy Constance) (1929) ''How We Lived Then, 1914–1918: a Sketch of Social and Domestic Life in England during the War'', London: Bodley Head
* Shields, Rosemary, and Linda Shields. &quot;Dame Maud McCarthy (1859–1949): Matron-in-Chief, British Expeditionary Forces France and Flanders, First World War.&quot; ''Journal of medical biography'' (2015): 0967772013480610.

===Historiography and memory===
* Bond, Brian, ed. ''The First World War and British Military History'' (Oxford UP, 1991) DOI:10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198222996.001.0001 online. 11 topical essays by experts.
*{{cite book|last=Braybon|first=Gail|title=Evidence, History and the Great War: Historians and the Impact of 14–18|year=2005|publisher=Berghahn Books|isbn=978-1-57181-801-0}}
*Gaffney, Angela. ''Aftermath: Remembering the Great War in Wales'' (1998)
* Korte, Barbara and Ann-Marie Einhaus. &quot;Short-Term Memories: The First World War in British Short Stories, 1914–39,&quot; ''Literature &amp; History'' (2009) 18#1 pp 54–67. 
* McCartney, Helen B. &quot;The First World War soldier and his contemporary image in Britain,&quot; ''International Affairs'' (2014) 90#2 pp 299–315.
* Wolford, Scott. &quot;Teaching the First World War in 'Real Time'&quot; (2015). [http://www.scott-wolford.com/uploads/2/5/2/4/25249202/teachingwwi.pdf online]
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|United Kingdom in World War I}}
* [https://www.sheffield.gov.uk/libraries/archives-and-local-studies/research-guides/world-war-one.html Sheffield City Council Libraries and Archives: &quot;Sources for the Study of World War I in Sheffield&quot; website] — ''research guide links''.

{{WWI history by nation}}
{{World War I}}
{{United Kingdom topics}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of The United Kingdom During World War I}}
[[Category:United Kingdom in World War I| ]]
[[Category:British Empire in World War I|*]]
[[Category:History of the United Kingdom|World War I]]
[[Category:1910s in the United Kingdom|*World War I]]
[[Category:Military history of the United Kingdom during World War I| ]]
[[Category:World War I by country|United Kingdom]]
[[Category:20th century in the United Kingdom|World War I]]</text>
      <sha1>ttjzinczqsfvjl1pg3bx61xizo6w9si</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
