<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>In Flanders Fields</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>69259</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749781386</id>
      <parentid>749772534</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T04:02:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nikkimaria</username>
        <id>372290</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 749189738 by [[Special:Contributions/Király-Seth|Király-Seth]] ([[User talk:Király-Seth|talk]]): This refers to published version, see source and image caption. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27587">{{Other uses}}
{{good article}}
[[File:Johnmccraememorialbookcloseup02.JPG|thumb|Inscription of the complete poem in a bronze &quot;book&quot; at the John McCrae memorial at his [[McCrae House|birthplace]] in Guelph, Ontario|alt=A sculpture in the form of an open book. The text of the poem &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; is written within and a small red poppy lies on top.]]

&quot;'''In Flanders Fields'''&quot; is a [[war poet|war poem]] in the form of a [[rondeau (poetry)|rondeau]], written during the [[World War I|First World War]] by Canadian physician [[Lieutenant Colonel (Canada)|Lieutenant-Colonel]] [[John McCrae]]. He was inspired to write it on May 3, 1915, after presiding over the funeral of friend and fellow soldier Lieutenant Alexis Helmer, who died in the [[Second Battle of Ypres]]. According to legend, fellow soldiers retrieved the poem after McCrae, initially dissatisfied with his work, discarded it. &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; was first published on December 8 of that year in the [[London]]-based magazine ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]''.

It is one of the most popular and most quoted poems from the war. As a result of its immediate popularity, parts of the poem were used in propaganda efforts and appeals to recruit soldiers and raise money selling [[war bond]]s. Its references to the [[Papaver rhoeas|red poppies]] that grew over the graves of fallen soldiers resulted in the [[remembrance poppy]] becoming one of the world's most recognized memorial symbols for soldiers who have died in conflict. The poem and poppy are prominent [[Remembrance Day]] symbols throughout the [[Commonwealth of Nations]], particularly in [[Canada]], where &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; is one of the nation's best-known literary works. The poem also has wide exposure in the [[United States]], where it is associated with [[Memorial Day (United States)|Memorial Day]].

==Background==
[[File:Lieut.-Col. John McCrae, M.D..jpg|thumb|right|Lieutenant Colonel John McCrae was a soldier, physician and poet.|alt=Upper body of a man in a soldier's uniform. He has short dark hair parted in the middle and maintains a neutral expression.]]

[[John McCrae]] was a poet and physician from [[Guelph, Ontario]]. He developed an interest in poetry at a young age and wrote throughout his life.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; His earliest works were published in the mid-1890s in Canadian magazines and newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/history/firstwar/mccrae/earlyyears |title=The early years |publisher=Veterans Affairs Canada |accessdate=2012-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCrae's poetry often focused on death and the peace that followed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the age of 41, McCrae enrolled with the [[Canadian Expeditionary Force]] following the outbreak of the [[World War I|First World War]]. He had the option of joining the medical corps because of his training and age, but he volunteered instead to join a fighting unit as a gunner and medical officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gillmor|2001|pp=91–92}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was his second tour of duty in the Canadian military. He had previously fought with a volunteer force in the [[Second Boer War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=31}}&lt;/ref&gt; He considered himself a soldier first; his father was a military leader in Guelph and McCrae grew up believing in the duty of fighting for his country and [[British Empire|empire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bassett|1984|p=14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

McCrae fought in the [[second battle of Ypres]] in the [[Flanders]] region of Belgium where the German army launched one of the first [[Chemical weapons in World War I|chemical attacks]] in the history of war. They attacked the Canadian position with [[chlorine#Use as a weapon|chlorine gas]] on April 22, 1915, but were unable to break through the Canadian line, which held for over two weeks. In a letter written to his mother, McCrae described the battle as a &quot;nightmare&quot;: &quot;For seventeen days and seventeen nights none of us have had our clothes off, nor our boots even, except occasionally. In all that time while I was awake, gunfire and rifle fire never ceased for sixty seconds.... And behind it all was the constant background of the sights of the dead, the wounded, the maimed, and a terrible anxiety lest the line should give way.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/history/firstwar/mccrae/flanders |title=In Flanders Fields |publisher=Veterans Affairs Canada |accessdate=2012-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alexis Helmer, a close friend, was killed during the battle on May 2. McCrae performed the burial service himself, at which time he noted how [[poppy|poppies]] quickly grew around the graves of those who died at Ypres. The next day, he composed the poem while sitting in the back of an ambulance&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gillmor|2001|p=93}}&lt;/ref&gt; at an Advanced Dressing Station outside Ypres. This location is today known as the [[Site John McCrae|John McCrae Memorial Site]].

==Poem==
[[File:In Flanders fields and other poems, handwritten.png|thumb|right|An autographed copy of the poem from ''In Flanders Fields and Other Poems''. Unlike the printed copy in the same book, McCrae's handwritten version ends the first line with &quot;grow&quot;.|alt=The poem handwritten by McCrae. In this copy, the first line ends with &quot;grow&quot;, differing from the original published version.]]

The first chapter of ''In Flanders Fields and Other Poems'', a 1919 collection of McCrae's works, gives the text of the poem as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=In Flanders Fields and Other Poems | year=1919 | publisher=G. P. Putnam's Sons | page=3 | accessdate=5 November 2010}} The [[:File:In Flanders Fields and other poems page 3.png|typeset version of the poem]] ends the first line with &quot;blow&quot;. The same book also includes [[:File:In Flanders fields and other poems, handwritten.png|McCrae's handwritten copy]] of the poem, in which the first line ends with &quot;grow&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;poem&gt;
In Flanders fields the poppies blow&lt;!-- the cited book says &quot;blow&quot;; DON'T change the text here to &quot;grow&quot; --&gt;
Between the crosses, row on row,
That mark our place; and in the sky
The larks, still bravely singing, fly
Scarce heard amid the guns below.

We are the Dead. Short days ago
We lived, felt dawn, saw sunset glow,
Loved and were loved, and now we lie
In Flanders fields.

Take up our quarrel with the foe:
To you from failing hands we throw
The torch; be yours to hold it high.
If ye break faith with us who die
We shall not sleep, though poppies grow
In Flanders fields.
&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

As with his earlier poems, &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; continues McCrae's preoccupation with death and how it stands as the transition between the struggle of life and the peace that follows.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=106}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is written from the point of view of the dead. It speaks of their sacrifice and serves as their command to the living to press on.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT1921&quot; /&gt; As with many of the most popular works of the First World War, it was written early in the conflict, before the romanticism of war turned to bitterness and disillusion for soldiers and civilians alike.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott105&quot; /&gt;

==Publication==
[[File:In Flanders Fields (1921) page 1.png|thumb|right|Illustrated page by Ernest Clegg. Note that the first line ends with &quot;grow&quot;.|alt=A page from a book. The first stanza of the poem is printed above an illustration of a white cross amidst a field of red poppies while two cannons fire in the background.]]

Cyril Allinson was a [[sergeant major]] in McCrae's unit. While delivering the brigade's mail, he watched McCrae as he worked on the poem, noting that McCrae's eyes periodically returned to Helmer's grave as he wrote. When handed the notepad, Allinson read the poem and was so moved he immediately committed it to memory. He described it as being &quot;almost an exact description of the scene in front of us both&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leader-Post1968&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=_-lUAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=lDwNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3692,1914652 |title=Poem depicts war scenes |work=Regina Leader-Post |date=1968-11-12 |accessdate=2012-02-07 |page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to legend, McCrae was not satisfied with his work. It is said he crumpled the paper and threw it away.&lt;ref name=&quot;JournalOpinion2006&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=sc4kAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=-Q8GAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=816,694462 |title=Forever there... In Flanders Fields |work=The Journal Opinion |date=2006-03-29 |accessdate=2012-02-07 |page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was retrieved by a fellow member of his unit, either [[Edward Whipple Bancroft Morrison|Edward Morrison]] or J. M. Elder,&lt;ref name=&quot;AustralianArmy&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.army.gov.au/traditions/documents/inflandersfield_1.htm |title=The Red Poppy |publisher=The Australian Army |accessdate=2012-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; or Allinson himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;JournalOpinion2006&quot; /&gt; McCrae was convinced to submit the poem for publication.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott96&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=96}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another story of the poem's origin claimed that Helmer's funeral was actually held on the morning of May 2, after which McCrae wrote the poem in 20 minutes. A third claim, by Morrison, was that McCrae worked on the poem as time allowed between arrivals of wounded soldiers in need of medical attention.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|pp=95–96}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless of its true origin, McCrae worked on the poem for months before considering it ready for publication.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gillmor|2001|p=94}}&lt;/ref&gt; He submitted it to ''[[The Spectator]]'' in London, but it was rejected. It was then sent to ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'', where it was published on December 8, 1915.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott96&quot; /&gt; It was published anonymously, but ''Punch'' attributed the poem to McCrae in its year-end index.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=105}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The word that ends the first line of the poem has been disputed. According to Allinson, the poem began with &quot;In Flanders Fields the poppies grow&quot; when first written.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leader-Post1968&quot; /&gt; However, since McCrae ended the second-to-last line with &quot;grow&quot;, ''Punch'' received permission to change the wording of the opening line to end with &quot;blow&quot;. McCrae himself used either word when making handwritten copies for friends and family.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Brennan |first=Pat |url=http://www.thestar.com/travel/northamerica/article/723376--guelph-house-commemorates-flanders-poet-mccrae |title=Guelph house commemorates Flanders' poet McCrae |work=Toronto Star |date=2009-11-10 |accessdate=2012-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Questions over how the first line should end have endured since publication. Most recently, the [[Bank of Canada]] was inundated with queries and complaints from those who believed the first line should end with &quot;grow&quot; when a design for the [[Canadian ten-dollar bill|ten-dollar bill]] was released in 2001 that featured the first stanza of &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot;, ending the first line with &quot;blow&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2001/feb/11/news/mn-23881 |title=Flanders poppies blow up furor in Canada |work=Los Angeles Times |date=2001-02-11 |accessdate=2012-02-11 |page=A38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popularity==
[[File:If Ye Break Faith - Victory bonds poster.jpg|thumb|left|Aspects of the poem were used in propaganda, such as this Canadian war bonds poster|alt=Painting of a soldier staring down at a white cross surrounded by red poppies. The text &quot;If ye break faith ~ we shall not sleep&quot; and &quot;Buy Victory Bonds&quot; are written at the top and bottom respectively.]]

According to historian [[Paul Fussell]], &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; was the most popular poem of its era.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fussell315&quot; /&gt; McCrae received numerous letters and telegrams praising his work when he was revealed as the author.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes1938&quot;&gt;{{citation |last=Ragner |first=Bernhard |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F00811F7355A157A93C2AA178AD85F4C8385F9 |title=A tribute in Flanders Fields |work=New York Times Magazine |date=1938-01-30 |accessdate=2012-02-07 |page=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The poem was republished throughout the world, rapidly becoming synonymous with the sacrifice of the soldiers who died in the First World War.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT1921&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0717F93E5D14738DDDA10994DA415B818EF1D3 |title=In Flanders Fields |work=New York Times |date=1921-12-18 |accessdate=2012-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was translated into numerous languages, so many that McCrae himself quipped that &quot;it needs only Chinese now, surely&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bassett|1984|p=50}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its appeal was nearly universal. Soldiers took encouragement from it as a statement of their duty to those who died while people on the home front viewed it as defining the cause for which their brothers and sons were fighting.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bassett|1984|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was often used for propaganda, particularly in Canada by the [[Unionist Party (Canada)|Unionist Party]] during the [[Canadian federal election, 1917|1917 federal election]] amidst the [[Conscription Crisis of 1917|Conscription Crisis]]. [[French Canadian]]s in Quebec were strongly opposed to the possibility of [[conscription]], but [[English Canadian]]s voted overwhelmingly to support Prime Minister [[Robert Borden]] and the Unionist government. &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; was said to have done more to &quot;make this Dominion persevere in the duty of fighting for the world's ultimate peace than all the political speeches of the recent campaign&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott125&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=125}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCrae, a staunch supporter of the empire and the war effort, was pleased with the effect his poem had on the election. He stated in a letter: &quot;I hope I stabbed a [French] Canadian with my vote.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott125&quot; /&gt;

The poem was a popular motivational tool in Great Britain, where it was used to encourage soldiers fighting against Germany, and in the United States where it was reprinted across the country. It was one of the most quoted works during the war,&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott105&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|pp=105–106}}&lt;/ref&gt; used in many places as part of campaigns to sell [[war bond]]s, during recruiting efforts and to criticize [[pacifism|pacifists]] and those who sought to profit from the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott133&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=133}}&lt;/ref&gt; American composer [[Charles Ives]] used &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; as the basis for a song of the same name that premiered in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://lcweb2.loc.gov/diglib/ihas/loc.natlib.ihas.200035609/default.html |title=In Flanders Fields (Song Collection) |publisher=Library of Congress |accessdate=2012-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fussell criticized the poem in his work ''The Great War and Modern Memory'' (1975).&lt;ref name=&quot;Fussell315&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Fussell|2009|p=315}}&lt;/ref&gt; He noted the distinction between the [[pastoral]] tone of the first nine lines and the &quot;recruiting-poster rhetoric&quot; of the third stanza. Describing it as &quot;vicious&quot; and &quot;stupid&quot;, Fussell called the final lines a &quot;propaganda argument against a negotiated peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fussell|2009|pp=314–315}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
McCrae was moved to the medical corps and stationed in [[Boulogne-sur-Mer|Boulogne]], France, in June 1915 where he was promoted to Lieutenant-Colonel, and placed in charge of medicine at the Number 3 Canadian General Hospital.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Prescott|1985|p=101}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was promoted to the acting rank of [[Colonel]] on January 13, 1918, and named Consulting Physician to the British Armies in France. The years of war had worn McCrae down, however. He contracted [[pneumonia]] that same day, and later came down with [[meningitis|cerebral meningitis]]. On January 28, 1918, he died at the military hospital in [[Wimereux]] and was buried there with full military honours.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bassett|1984|pp=59–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; A book of his works, featuring &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; was published the following year.&lt;ref name=&quot;BreakingFaith&quot;&gt;{{citation |last=Holmes |first=Nancy |url=http://journals.hil.unb.ca/index.php/scl/article/view/15269/16346 |title=&quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; — Canada's official poem: breaking faith |work=Studies in Canadian Literature |publisher=University of New Brunswick |year=2005 |volume=30 |issue=1 |accessdate=2012-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Shubenacadie Cenotaph.jpg|thumb|left|''To you from failing hands we throw / The torch; be yours to hold it high.'' - cenotaph sculpture, [[Shubenacadie, Nova Scotia]]]]
&quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; has attained iconic status in Canada, where it is a staple of [[Remembrance Day]] ceremonies and may be the most well known literary piece among English Canadians.&lt;ref name=&quot;BreakingFaith&quot; /&gt; It has an official French adaptation, entitled &quot;[[:fr:Au champ d'honneur|Au champ d'honneur]]&quot;, written by Jean Pariseau and used by the Canadian government in French and bilingual ceremonies.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.veterans.gc.ca/fra/histoire/premiereguerre/vimy/poeme |title=Le Canada pendant la Première Guerre mondiale et la route vers la crête de Vimy |language=French |publisher=Veterans Affairs Canada |accessdate=2012-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to an excerpted appearance on the ten-dollar bill from 2001 to 2013, the Royal Canadian Mint has released poppy-themed [[Quarter (Canadian coin)|quarters]] on several occasions. A version minted in 2004 featured a red poppy in the centre and is considered the first multi-coloured circulation coin in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.mint.ca/store/campaign/poppy_tab2.jsp |title=A symbol of remembrance |publisher=Royal Canadian Mint |accessdate=2012-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; To mark the poem's centennial in 2015, a colored and uncolored poppy quarter and a &quot;toonie&quot; ($2 coin) were issued as circulation coins, as well as other collector coins.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mint.ca/store/product/rcmcoins.jsp?campaignName=CirculationPoppy&amp;pId=3600018&amp;lang=en_CA Never forget with the 2015 Remembrance coins], Royal Canadian Mint order form, October 2015&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mint.ca/store/news/royal-canadian-mint-commemorates-100th-anniversary-of-in-flanders-fields-with-silver-collector-coins-24700040?cat=News+releases&amp;nId=700002&amp;parentnId=600004&amp;nodeGroup=About+the+Mint Royal Canadian Mint Commemorates 100th Anniversary of In Flanders Fields with Silver Collector Coins] Royal Canadian Mint news release, April 30, 2015&lt;/ref&gt; Among its uses in popular culture, the line &quot;to you from failing hands we throw the torch, be yours to hold it high&quot; has served as a motto for the [[Montreal Canadiens]] hockey club since 1940.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://archives.cbc.ca/sports/hockey/clips/16401/ |title=Last game at the Montreal Forum |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=2012-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Canada Post]] honored the 50th anniversary of John McCrae's death with a stamp in 1968, and marked the centennial of his famous poem in 2015. Other Canadian stamps have featured the poppy, including ones in 1975, 2001, 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;MyUser_Https:_November_12_2015c&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.canadapost.ca/cpo/mc/personal/collecting/stamps/2009/2009_Lest_We_Forget.jsf |title=Canada Post - Collecting |newspaper=Https: |date=  |author= |accessdate= November 12, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; 2013 and 2014, and other postal authorities have employed the poppy as a symbol of remembrance, including those of Australia, Gibraltar, the United Kingdom and United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;MyUser_Https:_November_12_2015d&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.canadapost.ca/web/en/blogs/consumer/details.page?article=2015/04/29/in_flanders_fields_s&amp;cattype=Consumer&amp;cat=mailandmore |title=In Flanders Fields stamp issue |newspaper=Https: |date=  |author= |accessdate= November 12, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[McCrae House|McCrae's birthplace]] in Guelph, Ontario has been converted into a museum dedicated to his life and the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Hill |first=Valerie |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/498773431.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS |title=Lest We Forget McCrae House keeps realities of war alive |work=Kitchener Record |date=1998-11-07 |accessdate=2012-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCrae himself was designated a [[Persons of National Historic Significance|National Historic Person]] in 1946, and his house was designated a [[National Historic Sites of Canada|National Historic Site]] in 1966.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pc.gc.ca/apps/dfhd/page_nhs_eng.aspx?id=1206 McCrae, Lieutenant-Colonel John National Historic Person], Parks Canada, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pc.gc.ca/apps/dfhd/page_nhs_eng.aspx?id=378 McCrae House National Historic Site], Parks Canada, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:John McCrae, Essex Farm Military Cemetery.jpg|thumb|right|The monument commemorating ''In Flanders Fields'' at [[Essex Farm Commonwealth War Graves Commission Cemetery]] near Ypres.]]
In Belgium, the [[In Flanders Fields Museum]] in [[Ypres]], named after the poem and devoted to the First World War, is situated in one of Flanders' largest tourist areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://kw.knack.be/west-vlaanderen/nieuws/algemeen/nieuw-streekbezoekerscentrum-ieper-officieel-geopend/article-4000039582184.htm |title=Nieuw streekbezoekerscentrum Ieper officieel geopend |language=Dutch |publisher=Knack.be |date=2012-02-05 |accessdate=2012-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; A monument commemorating the writing of the poem is located at [[Essex Farm Commonwealth War Graves Commission Cemetery]], which is thought to have been the location of Helmer's burial and now lies within the John McCrae Memorial Site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ww1westernfront.gov.au/ieper/essex-farm/lieutenant-colonel-mccrae.php# |title=Ieper (Ypres) – Belgium - Nearby site: Essex Farm Cemetery, Boezinge – Lieutenant Colonel McCrae |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date=July 2013 |website=www.ww1westernfront.gov.au |publisher=Department of Veterans’ Affairs and Board of Studies, New South Wales |access-date=8 April 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Despite its enduring fame, &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot; is often ignored by academics teaching and discussing [[Canadian literature]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BreakingFaith&quot; /&gt; The poem is sometimes viewed as an [[anachronism]]; It spoke of glory and honour in a war that has since become synonymous with the futility of trench warfare and the wholesale slaughter produced by 20th century weaponry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prescott133&quot; /&gt; [[Nancy Holmes]], professor at the [[University of British Columbia]], speculated that its patriotic nature and usage as a tool for propaganda may have led literary critics to view it as a national symbol or anthem rather than a poem.&lt;ref name=&quot;BreakingFaith&quot; /&gt;

===Remembrance poppies===
{{main|Remembrance poppy}}
[[File:Kollebloemen - Red poppies.JPG|thumb|Poppy wreaths at the [[Menin Gate]] in [[Ypres]], Belgium|alt=Several wreaths of artificial red poppies with black centres. The logo of various veterans and community groups are printed in the middle of each.]]

The [[Papaver rhoeas|red poppies]] that McCrae referred to had been associated with war since the [[Napoleonic Wars]] when a writer of that time first noted how the poppies grew over the graves of soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/story/2008/11/07/f-remembrance-day.html |title=Remembrance Day: Lest we forget |publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation |date=2010-11-10 |accessdate=2012-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The damage done to the landscape in Flanders during the battle greatly increased the lime content in the surface soil, leaving the poppy as one of the few plants able to grow in the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCPoppy2006&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/6133312.stm |title=Where did the idea to sell poppies come from? |publisher=BBC News |date=2006-11-10 |accessdate=2012-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Inspired by &quot;In Flanders Fields&quot;, American professor [[Moina Michael]] resolved at the war's conclusion in 1918 to wear a [[Papaver rhoeas|red poppy]] year-round to honour the soldiers who had died in the war. She also wrote a poem in response called &quot;[[We Shall Keep the Faith]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://georgiainfo.galileo.usg.edu/mmichael.htm |title=Moina Michael |publisher=Digital Library of Georgia |accessdate=2012-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; She distributed silk poppies to her peers and campaigned to have them adopted as an official symbol of remembrance by the [[American Legion]]. Madame E. Guérin attended the 1920 convention where the Legion supported Michael's proposal and was herself inspired to sell poppies in her native France to raise money for the war's orphans.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCPoppy2011&quot;&gt;{{citation |last=Rahman |first=Rema |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-15637074 |title=Who, What, Why: Which countries wear poppies? |publisher=BBC News |date=2011-11-09 |accessdate=2012-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1921, Guérin sent poppy sellers to London ahead of [[Armistice Day]], attracting the attention of [[Field marshal (United Kingdom)|Field Marshal]] [[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig|Douglas Haig]]. A co-founder of [[The Royal British Legion]], Haig supported and encouraged the sale.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCPoppy2006&quot; /&gt; The practice quickly spread throughout the British Empire. The wearing of poppies in the days leading up to [[Remembrance Day]] remains popular in many areas of the [[Commonwealth of Nations]], particularly Great Britain, Canada, and South Africa, and in the days leading up to [[ANZAC Day]] in Australia and New Zealand.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCPoppy2011&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Canadian Forces|World War I}}
*[[1915 in poetry]]
*[[Military history of Canada during World War I]]
*[[The Red Poppies on Monte Cassino]]
{{Clear}}

==References==
{{Research help|Mil}}
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|30em}}

;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
*{{citation |last=Bassett |first=John |year=1984 |title=The Canadians: John McCrae |publisher=Fitzhenry &amp; Whiteside Limited |location=Markham, Ontario |isbn=0-88902-651-3}}
*{{citation |last=Fussell |first=Paul |year=2009 |origyear=1975 |title=The Great War and Modern Memory (Illustrated Edition)|publisher=Stirling Publishing |location=New York |isbn=0-19-513331-5}}
*{{Citation |last=Gillmor |first=Don |year=2001 |title=Canada: A People's History|isbn=0-7710-3340-0 |volume=two |publisher=McClelland &amp; Stewart |location=Toronto, Ontario|id=ISBN 0-7710-3341-9}}
*{{citation |last=McCrae |first=John |year=1919 |title=In Flanders Fields and Other Poems |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TecjwVOo5GsC&amp;pg=PP1 |publisher=Arcturus Publishing (reprint 2008) |isbn=1-84193-994-3 |accessdate=2012-02-07}}
*{{citation|last=Prescott |first=John F. |year=1985 |title=In Flanders Fields: The Story of John McCrae |publisher=Boston Mills Press |location=Erin, Ontario |isbn=0-919783-07-4}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource}}
{{commons category}}
* [http://www.legion.ca/Poppy/campaign_e.cfm Royal Canadian Legion] web page about John McCrae, ''In Flanders Fields,'' and the custom of wearing poppies
* [http://www.gladdemusic.com/inflandersfields(2).htm In Flanders Fields], choral piece by composer Bradley Nelson, commissioned by Fresno State Chamber Singers and Chico State Chamber Singers of California State University
* [http://www.torontopubliclibrary.ca/detail.jsp?Entt=RDMDC-1918FLANDERSVS&amp;R=DC-1918FLANDERSVS In Flander's fields by Lt. Col. John McCrae, M.D. and America's answer by R. W. Lillard, 1914-1918]. Hamilton, Ont. : Commercial Engravers, 1918. 8 p. Accessed 4 January 2014, in PDF format.
* {{librivox book | title=In Flanders Fields | author=John MCCRAE}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2012}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:World War I poems]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada]]
[[Category:Poems set in Flanders]]
[[Category:1915 poems]]
[[Category:Canadian poems]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Punch (magazine)]]
[[Category:World War I propaganda]]</text>
      <sha1>l9tiy016n34qn0w0108c7ihddd6go9u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
