<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Invasion of Isle de France</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20751714</id>
    <revision>
      <id>691024158</id>
      <parentid>684508884</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-11-17T04:37:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender235</username>
        <id>88026</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up; http-&gt;https (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34380">{{about|the invasion of Mauritius by the British|invasions of the region in France|History of Île-de-France}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Invasion of Isle de France
|partof=the [[Napoleonic Wars]]
|image=[[Image:Bonne - Isle de France (Detail).jpg|300px]]
|caption=Map of Isle de France, 1791. Grand Baie (''G. de Bay'') is at the northern tip of the island. Port Napoleon is labelled with its pre-Revolutionary name of Port Louis. 
|date=29 November &amp;ndash; 3 December 1810
|place= [[Isle de France (Mauritius)|Isle de France]], [[Indian Ocean]]
|result= Decisive British victory,
|territory=Isle de France ceded to the United Kingdom as Mauritius (1814).
|combatant1={{flagcountry|UKGBI}}
|combatant2={{flagicon|France}} [[First French Empire]]
|commander1= {{flagicon|UKGBI|naval}} [[Sir Albemarle Bertie, 1st Baronet|Albemarle Bertie]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|UKGBI}} [[John Abercromby (British Army officer)|John Abercromby]] 
|commander2= {{flagicon|France}} [[Charles Decaen]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|France}} [[Edmé-Martin Vandermaesen]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|France|naval}} [[Jean Dornal de Guy]]
|strength1= 6,848 soldiers, sailors and [[Royal Marines]]&lt;br/&gt;1 [[ship of the line]], 12 [[frigate]]s, 5 [[brig]]s and around 50 smaller vessels and troops transports
|strength2= 1,300 regular soldiers, 10,000 militia&lt;br/&gt;6 [[frigate]]s, 3 [[brig]]s and 1 smaller vessel
|casualties1= 28 killed, 94 wounded, 45 missing
|casualties2= Isle de France and all military stores captured
}}
{{campaignbox Mauritius campaign of 1809–1811}}

The '''Invasion of Isle de France''' was a complicated but successful [[amphibious operation]] in the [[Indian Ocean]], launched in November 1810 during the [[Napoleonic Wars]]. During the operation, a substantial British military force was landed by the [[Royal Navy]] at [[Grand Baie]] on [[Isle de France (Mauritius)|Isle de France]] (now [[Mauritius]]). Marching inland against weak French opposition, the British force was able to overwhelm the defenders in a series of minor engagements, culminating in the capture of the island's capital [[Port Napoleon]] and the surrender of [[Charles Decaen]], the French governor. The surrender eliminated the last French territory in the [[Indian Ocean]] and among the military equipment captured were five [[French Navy]] [[frigates]] and 209 heavy [[cannon]]. Isle de France was retained by Britain at the end of the war under the name of [[Mauritius]] and remained part of the [[British Empire]] until 1968.

==Background==
The operation was the culmination of two years of conflict over the island and the neighbouring [[Île Bourbon]] between frigate squadrons commanded by [[Josias Rowley]] and [[Jacques Hamelin]]. Hamelin repeatedly raided British trade convoys and Rowley responded with amphibious assaults on French harbours, but neither had gained ascendancy by the time Rowley sent most of his force to attack the port of [[Grand Port]] on Isle de France in August 1810. At the ensuing [[Battle of Grand Port|battle at Grand Port]] the British squadron was destroyed and Hamelin began to blockade Rowley on Île Bourbon. As British reinforcements were urgently despatched, several actions were fought between recently arrived British ships and the more numerous French forces. At the last of these on [[Action of 18 September 1810|18 September 1810]], Hamelin was defeated and captured by Rowley. This allowed Rowley to build his forces over the next two months until they were sufficient for a successful invasion, which was led by the recently arrived Admiral [[Sir Albemarle Bertie, 1st Baronet|Albemarle Bertie]].

The [[Indian Ocean]] had been an important strategic region for British trade since the first British trading posts were developed in [[India]]. By the [[Napoleonic Wars]], millions of [[pound sterling|pounds]] worth of goods crossed the ocean's trade routes every year, mostly in the heavily guarded convoys of [[East Indiamen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RG92&quot;&gt;Gardiner, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; The French recognised the economic importance of these convoys but until 1808 failed to provide sufficient forces to disrupt the Indian trade. Late in 1808, it was decided to send a strong [[frigate]] squadron to the Ocean under the command of [[Jacques Hamelin]] to augment the forces available on the island bases of [[Île Bonaparte]] and [[Isle de France (Mauritius)|Isle de France]] and raid British shipping in the region. Hamelin was an able commander and between May 1809 and July 1810 his ships captured seven East Indiamen and a large number of small merchant ships and warships.&lt;ref name=&quot;RG93&quot;&gt;Gardiner, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

The British response to Hamelin's deployment was provided by Admiral [[Sir Albemarle Bertie, 1st Baronet|Albemarle Bertie]], who collected a squadron of ships from those available at the [[Cape of Good Hope]] and placed them under the command of Commodore [[Josias Rowley]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ192-195&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 5, p. 192&amp;ndash;195&lt;/ref&gt; Bertie gave Rowley instructions to blockade the islands and prepare for invasion attempts once the required forces could be spared. During 1809 and the spring of 1810, Rowley maintained the blockade and launched a series of small raids, the largest being [[Raid on Saint Paul|at Saint Paul]] on Île Bonaparte in September 1809. By July 1810, Rowley had developed sufficient forces at his island base on [[Rodrigues (island)|Rodriguez]] to successfully [[Invasion of Île Bonaparte|invade and capture]] Île Bonaparte, which he restored to its former name of Île Bourbon.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ272&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 5, p. 272&lt;/ref&gt; In August, Rowley attempted to extend his blockade of Isle de France by seizing small islands off the main ports that could control the passage of shipping through the coral reefs that surround the island. The first operation was to capture [[Île de la Passe]] off [[Grand Port]], which was successfully secured on 13 August. Shortly afterwards a French squadron forced passage into the harbour and Captain [[Samuel Pym]] ordered the four frigates of the blockade squadron to attack the ships anchored in the bay. The ensuing [[Battle of Grand Port]] was a disaster for the British, as two frigates were wrecked on the reefs and two others captured with their entire crews: only the very seriously wounded, including Captain [[Nesbit Willoughby]], were repatriated to Île Bourbon.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ295&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 5, p. 295&lt;/ref&gt;

With his squadron reduced to a single frigate, Rowley sent urgent messages  to the British bases at [[Madras]] and [[Cape Town]] requesting reinforcements. The naval authorities responded by sending the forces they had available to join Rowley at Rodriguez. The first two frigates to arrive, [[French frigate Africaine (1798)|HMS ''Africaine'']] and [[HMS Bombay (1805)|HMS ''Ceylon'']] were both attacked while sailing alone and captured by Hamelin's squadron, which was now blockading Île Bourbon. Rowley was able to recapture both ships within hours of their loss, and was also able to seize Hamelin and his flagship ''[[French frigate Vénus (1808)|Vénus]]'' at the [[Action of 18 September 1810]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RW293&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 293&lt;/ref&gt; The loss of the French naval commander was a serious blow to the squadron on Isle de France, which was also beset by supply problems resulting from a lack of naval stores and food supplies. Unable to make the lengthy cruises needed to disrupt the Indian Ocean trade routes, they were forced to remain in harbour as Rowley was heavily reinforced during September and October 1810,&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ324&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 5, p. 324&lt;/ref&gt; and eventually the senior naval officer, Captain [[Jean Dornal de Guy]], had his four frigates, ''[[French frigate Manche (1806)|Manche]]'', ''[[HMS Pomone (1809)|Astrée]]'', ''[[French frigate Bellone (1807)|Bellone]]'' and ''[[French frigate Minerve (1809)|Minerve]]'', moored in [[Port-Louis]] and their crew disembarked to reinforce the garrison of the town.&lt;ref name=troude115&gt;Troude, ''op. cit.'', vol. 4, p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;

==Planning==
The invasion of Isle de France, although prompted by the defeat at Grand Port, had been the ultimate intention of Rowley's squadron since its creation in 1809 and had been planned carefully both on a strategic level by Bertie at [[Cape Town]] and [[Gilbert Elliot-Murray-Kynynmound, 1st Earl of Minto|Lord Minto]] at Madras and on a tactical level by Rowley and his [[British Army]] counterpart Lieutenant-Colonel [[Henry Sheehy Keating|Henry Keating]] on Rodriguez.&lt;ref name=&quot;RG96&quot;&gt;Gardiner, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt; The transport ships and soldiers would come from the Indian garrisons at [[Madras]], [[Bombay]] and [[Calcutta]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ST325&quot;&gt;Taylor, p. 325&lt;/ref&gt; to be led by General [[John Abercromby (British Army officer)|John Abercromby]] (although they were also accompanied by Rear-Admiral [[William O'Bryen Drury]], whom Bertie ordered to return to Madras before the invasion) while the naval forces to protect and support the invasion force were to be provided by Bertie from the Cape of Good Hope. These forces were to gather at Rodriguez in preparation for the invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ324&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 5, p. 324&lt;/ref&gt; The landings themselves were planned by Rowley and Keating, who relied on Willoughby's intimate knowledge of the coastline of Isle de France and a series of careful surveys of the reefs that surrounded the island to select a landing site.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ325&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 5, p. 325&lt;/ref&gt;

The chosen point was at [[Grand Baie]], on the northwestern coastline approximately {{convert|12|mi|km}} north of the island's capital [[Port Napoleon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ST328&quot;&gt;Taylor, p. 328&lt;/ref&gt; The intention was to prepare an elite force of 1,555 men formed from the [[Grenadier]] and [[Light infantry|light]] companies of the regiments attached to the invasion. This vanguard would storm ashore and advance rapidly towards the capital closely supported by a [[naval brigade]] and [[Royal Marines]] units, followed by the main body of the army of 5,293 soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW292&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 292&lt;/ref&gt; The entire force would have logistical assistance and artillery support from Royal Navy ships that would shadow the advance along the coast. The army's orders were to seize Port Napoleon and capture Governor [[Charles Decaen]], action which, it was hoped, would be sufficient to force the surrender of the entire island.&lt;ref name=&quot;RG96&quot;/&gt; Subsequent landings would be made to the west of the capital if French resistance was stronger than expected.&lt;ref name=&quot;AM39&quot;&gt;Macmillan, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 October, Bertie arrived at Rodriguez with his squadron from Cape Town. On 3 November troops from the [[Bombay]] garrison arrived, followed on 6 November by the Madras contingent. On Rodriguez the invasion plans were finalised, [[HMS Staunch (1804)|HMS ''Staunch'']] sent to reconnoitre the northern coastline of Isle de France to seek a suitable beach.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ325&quot;/&gt; Command of the landing and the naval support role was given to Captain [[Philip Beaver]], who had a reputation as an expert in [[amphibious operations]]. Keating was placed in command of the vanguard of the land force, with Captain [[William Augustus Montagu]] commanding of the naval brigade, and Abercromby in overall charge. Rowley would remain offshore in [[HMS Boadicea (1797)|HMS ''Boadicea'']], as would Bertie who took ''Africaine'' as his flagship.&lt;ref name=&quot;WLC294&quot;/&gt;

The French response to the impending British invasion was to mobilise the island's 10,000 strong militia. Despite their large numbers, this force was untrained, poorly armed and poorly motivated. Decaen himself recognised that they would be unreliable in the face of attack by British regular soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;WLC295&quot;&gt;Clowes, p. 295&lt;/ref&gt; He also bolstered his forces by attempting to recruit volunteers from among the hundreds of [[prisoners of war]] held in the island's prisons (a principal cause of the food shortages on Isle de France). Over 500 volunteers agreed to join his army, the majority of them [[Irish people|Irishmen]] promised French assistance in obtaining Irish independence from Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;RG97&quot;/&gt; Altogether, Decaen could muster 1,300 regular soldiers to defend the capital, which he placed under the command of General [[Edmé-Martin Vandermaesen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RW292&quot;/&gt;

==Invasion==
On 22 November 1810, all the British troops and ships were assembled and Bertie ordered the squadron to rendezvous off Grand Baie, which was reached early on 29 November despite adverse winds.&lt;ref name=&quot;WLC294&quot;&gt;Clowes, p. 294&lt;/ref&gt; The vanguard landed unopposed, their landing craft supported by ship's boats carrying [[cannon]], supplemented by the firepower of the larger ships offshore. Although there was some disruption in the early stages of the attack caused by adverse weather conditions, by 21:00 the entire vanguard and naval brigades were ashore. The landing had been effected with just two casualties, both men who died of natural causes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ST330&quot;&gt;Taylor, p. 330&lt;/ref&gt; Keating took command of the vanguard and advanced on Fort Malartic, the garrison retreating before his troops and blowing up the fort as they left.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW292&quot;/&gt; During the morning of 30 November, Keating pushed southwards to the [[Rivière du Tombeau|River Tombeau]] which overlooked Port Napoleon, his front units skirmishing with French defenders across the river, during which Decaen himself was lightly wounded by a [[musket]] ball. The bridge over the river had been held by a force of militia, but they fell back before the British advance and failed to properly demolish the bridge, allowing Keating to rapidly cross and threaten Port Napoleon.&lt;ref name=&quot;AM39&quot;/&gt; At Grand Baie, the remainder of the invasion force were coming ashore, so that the entire army had landed by midday, although Abercromby himself elected to stay with Beaver on [[HMS Nisus (1810)|HMS ''Nisus'']] and follow the advance from offshore.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW293&quot;/&gt;

On 1 December, Vandermaesen made a stand before Port Napoleon, defending the entrance to the town with his available regular troops and some small cannon. Keating attacked him, engaging the French front while a second attack by Madras [[sepoys]] outflanked the French line and disrupted it, allowing a successful frontal assault. With their defences breached the French fell back and on 2 December Decaen proposed a ceasefire, which was accepted.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ326&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 5, p. 326&lt;/ref&gt; The following day Decaen surrendered, although with guarantees that he and the garrison would be repatriated and allowed to retain their personal arms and [[French Imperial Eagle|Eagles]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RW293&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 293&lt;/ref&gt; Although some in the British force were unhappy with the terms of the surrender, the British commanders were relieved to have the invasion complete before the [[hurricane]] season began later in the month. The danger to the 70 ships in the British fleet from such a storm was serious and it was vitally important that they be in a safe harbour when the hurricane season began.&lt;ref name=&quot;RG97&quot;&gt;Gardiner, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The surrender of Isle de France marked the final British operation of the campaign and the capture of the last French territory east of Africa. The island was restored to its pre-1715 name of [[Mauritius]] and the towns renamed under Decaen (such as Port Napoleon) were restored to their pre-[[French Revolution|Revolutionary]] names.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW293&quot;/&gt; Governor [[Robert Townsend Farquhar]] of Île Bourbon was placed in administrative control of the island, Île Bourbon taken over by Keating. Although the French garrison was repatriated, the invaders captured six French frigates (''[[French frigate Manche (1806)|Manche]]'', ''[[HMS Pomone (1809)|Astrée]]'', ''[[French frigate Bellone (1807)|Bellone]]'' and ''[[French frigate Minerve (1809)|Minerve]]'', ''[[HMS Iphigenia (1808)|Iphigénie]]'' and ''[[HMS Madagascar (1811)|Néréide]]'') and several smaller warships (the corvette ''[[French corvette Revenant|Victor]]'', the brig ''[[French brig Entreprenant (1808)|Entreprenant]]'', the aviso ''Lutin'' and schooner-aviso [[Mouche No. 2-class schooner-avisos#Mouche No.23|''Mouche n°23'']]) in the various harbours of Isle de France, as well as 24 merchant ships.&lt;ref name=troude115 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AM40&quot;&gt;Macmillan, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; ''Lloyd's List'' published a list of all the vessels captured, military and civilian, on 15 February 1811.&lt;ref name=LL&gt;''Lloyd's List'', no.4537 [http://www.1812privateers.org/LLOYDS/1811/02-15-1811.jpg] - accessed 28 March 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; The British also seized 209 heavy cannon.

The British recaptured the [[East Indiaman|East Indiamen]] ''Ceylon'', ''Charlton'' and ''United Kingdom'', which the French were using as prison ships.&lt;ref name=LL/&gt; Among the hundreds of prisoners released were the survivors of the [[Battle of Grand Port]] and the crews and passengers from the Indiamen captured over the previous year.&lt;ref name=&quot;RW284&quot;&gt;Woodman, p. 284&lt;/ref&gt; Among the French prisoners, were discovered 12 deserters from the British Army or Royal Navy (at least 40 successfully passed as Frenchmen and were repatriated to France). These 12 were put on trial on their return to Britain: two were later hanged and five [[Penal transportation|transported]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ST331&quot;&gt;Taylor, p. 331&lt;/ref&gt; Rewards were forthcoming, particularly for Bertie, who was made a [[baronet]]. This created a scandal when Admiral Drury accused Bertie of taking credit for the work of others (principally Drury himself).&lt;ref name=&quot;ODNB&quot;&gt;[http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/2272 Bertie, Sir Albemarle], ''[[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]]'', Stephen Howarth, (subscription required), Retrieved 20 December 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Mauritius, unlike Île Bourbon, remained in British hands after the end of the war in 1814 and was retained as part of the [[British Empire]] until granted independence in 1968.

Although there were no further British operations in the region, the Mauritius campaign was not quite over. When news of the victory at Grand Port had reached France, there was pressure to resupply and reinforce the victorious squadron under Hamelin and a small squadron commanded by Commodore [[François Roquebert]] was ordered to sail for Isle de France. This squadron included three frigates: ''[[HMS Java (1811)|Renommée]]'', ''[[French frigate Clorinde (1808)|Clorinde]]'' and ''[[HMS Madagascar (1811)|Néréide]]'' and carried extensive stores to repair and rearm Hamelin's frigates.&lt;ref name=&quot;WLC486&quot;&gt;Clowes, p. 486&lt;/ref&gt; The journey from France to the Indian Ocean was a long one, and it was not until February 1811 that Roquebert's squadron arrived at Mauritius. Discovering that the island was in British hands, Roquebert attempted to return to France but was chased by the frigates stationed on Mauritius and captured at the [[Action of 20 May 1811]]. Only ''Clorinde'' escaped the British pursuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ15&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 6, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

==Orders of battle==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=100%
|-valign=&quot;top&quot;
!colspan=&quot;6&quot; bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;|Admiral Bertie's squadron
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
! width=20%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Ship &lt;/small&gt;
! width=15%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Rate &lt;/small&gt;
! width=5%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Guns &lt;/small&gt;
! width=5%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Navy &lt;/small&gt;
! width=25%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Commander &lt;/small&gt;
! width=29%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt;Notes&lt;/small&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Illustrious (1803)|HMS ''Illustrious'']]
| align= center  | [[Third rate]] 
| align= center  | 74
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Captain [[William Robert Broughton]]
| align= left  | 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | {{HMS|Cornwallis|1805|6}}
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 44
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Captain James Caulfield
| align= left  | 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[French frigate Africaine (1798)|HMS ''Africaine'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 38
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Vice-Admiral [[Sir Albemarle Bertie, 1st Baronet|Albemarle Bertie]]&lt;br/&gt;Captain [[Charles Gordon (Royal Navy officer)|Charles Gordon]]
| align= left  | 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Boadicea (1797)|HMS ''Boadicea'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 38
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Captain [[Josias Rowley]]
| align= left  | 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Nisus (1810)|HMS ''Nisus'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 38
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain [[Philip Beaver]] 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Clorinde (1803)|HMS ''Clorinde'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 38
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain [[Thomas Briggs (Royal Navy officer)|Thomas Briggs]]
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Menelaus (1810)|HMS ''Menelaus'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 38
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain [[Sir Peter Parker, 2nd Baronet|Peter Parker]] 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[French frigate Vénus (1808)|HMS ''Nereide'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 38
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain [[Robert Henderson (Royal Navy officer)|Robert Henderson]] 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Phoebe (1795)|HMS ''Phoebe'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 36
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain [[James Hillyar]]
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Doris (1808)|HMS ''Doris'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 36
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain William Jones Lye 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Cornelia (1808)|HMS ''Cornelia'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 32
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain Henry Folkes Edgell
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Psyche (1805)|HMS ''Psyche'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 32
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Captain John Edgcumbe 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Bombay (1805)|HMS ''Ceylon'']]
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 32
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Commander James Tompkinson 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Hesper (1809)|HMS ''Hesper'']]
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 18
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Commander David Paterson 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Eclipse (1807)|HMS ''Eclipse'']]
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 18
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Lieutenant Henry Lynne 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Hecate (1809)|HMS ''Hecate'']]
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 18
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Lieutenant George Lucas Rennie 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Acteon (1805)|HMS ''Acteon'']]
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 16
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |Lieutenant Ralph, Viscount Neville 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HMS Staunch (1804)|HMS ''Staunch'']]
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 14
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Lieutenant Hector Craig (acting)
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''Emma''
| align= center  | Government armed ship 
| align= center  | 
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Lieutenant Benjamin Street (acting)
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''Egremont''
| align= center  | Government sloop
| align= center  | 
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Lieutenant Robert Forder 
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''Farquhar''
| align= center  | 
| align= center  | 
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Midshipman Harvey
| align= left  |
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[Mouche No. 2-class schooner-avisos#Mouche No. 28|''Mouche'']] 
| align= center  | [[Schooner]]-[[aviso]]
| align= center  | 1
| align= center  | [[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|22px]]
| align= left  |  
| align= left  | {{HMS|Hesper|1809|2}} had captured ''Mouche No. 28'' on 15 November 1810 near Île Bonaparte (Réunion). The British recommissioned her for the attack on Île de France.{{#tag:ref|''Mouche No. 28'' was launched at Bayonne in November 1809.&lt;ref&gt;Winfield and Roberts (2015), p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Hesper'' captured her as she was carrying dispatches to the Île de France. A boarding party in ''Hesper''{{'}}s cutter suffered three men wounded while boarding ''Mouche''; French casualties were two men killed and five wounded, one of whom was ''Mouche No.28''{{'}}s commander.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|date=12 February 1811|issue=16455|startpage=297}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} 
|-
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=&quot;6&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;|In addition to the above warships, the invasion fleet included approximately 50 small transport ships initially under the command of Rear-Admiral [[William O'Bryen Drury]], who was sent back to Madras before the invasion. The [[British Army]] troops attached to the force included [[sepoys]] and garrison artillery from [[Madras]] and soldiers from the [[12th Regiment of Foot|12th Foot]], [[22nd Regiment of Foot|22nd Foot]], [[33rd Regiment of Foot|33rd Foot]], [[56th Regiment of Foot|56th Foot]] and [[59th (2nd Nottinghamshire) Regiment of Foot|59th Foot]] commanded by General [[John Abercromby (British Army officer)|John Abercromby]] and Lieutenant Colonel [[Henry Sheehy Keating|Henry Keating]]. Also attached was a naval brigade of volunteer sailors and [[Royal Marines]] under Captain [[William Augustus Montagu]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=&quot;6&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;|Sources:James Vol. 5, p.&amp;nbsp;325, Clowes, p.&amp;nbsp;294, Woodman, p.&amp;nbsp;291&amp;ndash;292, ''Lloyd's List'', 15 February 1811 [http://www.1812privateers.org/LLOYDS/1811/02-15-1811.jpg] - accessed 23 November 2013
|-valign=&quot;top&quot;
|-
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=100%
|-valign=&quot;top&quot;
!colspan=&quot;6&quot; bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;|French squadron
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
! width=20%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Ship &lt;/small&gt;
! width=15%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Rate &lt;/small&gt;
! width=5%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Guns &lt;/small&gt;
! width=5%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Navy &lt;/small&gt;
! width=25%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt; Commander &lt;/small&gt;
! width=29%; align= center rowspan=1 | &lt;small&gt;Notes&lt;/small&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''[[French frigate Bellone (1807)|Bellone]]''
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 40
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | Captured. Commissioned into the Royal Navy as [[HMS Junon (1810)|HMS ''Junon'']]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''[[French frigate Astrée (1809)|Astrée]]''
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 40
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | Captain [[Pierre Bouvet]]
| align= left  | Captured. Commissioned into the Royal Navy as [[French frigate Astrée (1809)|HMS ''Pomone'']]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''[[French frigate Minerve (1809)|Minerve]]''
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 48
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | Captured. Broken up as unfit for service.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''[[French frigate Manche (1806)|Manche]]''
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 40
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | Captured. Broken up as unfit for service.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''[[HMS Iphigenia (1805)|Iphigénie]]''
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 36
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | Captured. Returned to service as [[HMS Iphigenia (1805)|HMS ''Iphigenia'']].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''[[HMS Nereide (1797)|Néréide]]''
| align= center  | [[Fifth rate]] 
| align= center  | 36
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | Captured. Laid up as unfit for service and sold for breaking up in 1816.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | ''[[French corvette Revenant|Revenant]]''
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 18
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | Captured. Broken up as unfit for service.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[French brig Entreprenant (1808)|''Entreprenant'']]
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 18
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | Captured. Broken up as unfit for service.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[HCS Aurora (1809)|''Aurore'']]
| align= center  | [[Brig]] 
| align= center  | 14
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | HCS ''Aurora'', captured September 1810 by ''Iphigénie'' and ''Astrée''; returned to the service of the [[Royal Indian Navy#1686-1830|Bombay Marine]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align= left  | [[Mouche No. 2-class schooner-avisos#Mouche No. 23|''Mouche No.23'']] 
| align= center  | [[Schooner]]-[[aviso]] 
| align= center  | 1
| align= center  | [[Image:Flag of France.svg|22px]]
| align= left  | 
| align= left  | HMS ''Nereide'' had captured her on 2 June 1810, and ''Astrée'' had recaptured her on 30 August.
|-
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=&quot;6&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;|Note: At the time of the invasion, only two of the above ships were serviceable and as a result many ships were commanded by temporary officers or none at all. Records on which French officers commanded which ships are incomplete, and so only those that are known are inserted in the above table. In addition to the warships, none of which participated in the campaign, Governor [[Charles Decaen]] could muster 1,300 [[French Army]] troops, including 500 volunteers from among the British [[prisoners of war]], and 10,000 unreliable local militia.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|colspan=&quot;6&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;|Sources: James Vol. 5, p.&amp;nbsp;325, Clowes, p.&amp;nbsp;294, 560,  ''Lloyd's List'', 15 February 1811 [http://www.1812privateers.org/LLOYDS/1811/02-15-1811.jpg] - accessed 23 November 2013
|-valign=&quot;top&quot;
|-
|}

==Notes, citations, and references==

===Notes===
{{reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|2}}

===References===
*{{cite book
 | last = Clowes
 | first = William Laird
 | authorlink = William Laird Clowes
 | year = 1997 |origyear=1900
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Royal Navy, A History from the Earliest Times to 1900, Volume V
 | publisher = Chatham Publishing
 | location = 
 | isbn = 1-86176-014-0
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Editor: Gardiner
 | first = Robert
 | authorlink = 
 | year = 2001 |origyear=1998
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Victory of Seapower
 | publisher = Caxton Editions
 | location = 
 | isbn = 1-84067-359-1
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = James
 | first = William
 | authorlink = William James (naval historian)
 | year = 2002 |origyear=1827
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Naval History of Great Britain, Volume 5, 1808&amp;ndash;1811
 | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
 | location = 
 | isbn = 0-85177-909-3
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = James
 | first = William
 | authorlink = William James (naval historian)
 | year = 2002 |origyear=1827
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Naval History of Great Britain, Volume 6, 1811&amp;ndash;1827
 | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
 | location = 
 | isbn = 0-85177-910-7
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Macmillan
 | first = Allister
 | authorlink = 
 | year = 1914
 | chapter = 
 | title = Mauritius Illustrated
 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=_EusZwEdxpAC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Dornal+de+Guy&amp;output=html&amp;cad=0 
 | publisher = W.H.&amp; L. Collingridge
 | location = 
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Taylor
 | first = Stephen
 | authorlink = 
 | year = 2008
 | chapter = 
 | title = Storm &amp; Conquest: The Battle for the Indian Ocean, 1809
 | publisher = Faber &amp; Faber
 | location = 
 | isbn = 978-0-571-22467-8
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Woodman
 | first = Richard
 | authorlink = Richard Woodman
 | year = 2001
 | chapter = 
 | title = The Sea Warriors
 | publisher = Constable Publishers
 | location = 
 | isbn = 1-84119-183-3
}}
* {{cite book
 | title      = Batailles navales de la France
 | last       = Troude
 | first      = Onésime-Joachim
 | authorlink = Onésime-Joachim Troude
 | year       = 1867
 | publisher  = Challamel ainé
 | location   =
 | isbn       =
 | pages       = 160–162
 | url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=zfFrDVTkcpsC&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;redir_esc=y
 | volume     = 4
}}
*Winfield, Rif &amp; Stephen S Roberts (2015) ''French Warships in the Age of Sail 1786 - 1861: Design Construction, Careers and Fates''. (Seaforth Publishing). ISBN 9781848322042
{{Good article}}
{{British colonial campaigns}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Invasion Of Ile De France}}
[[Category:Naval battles of the Napoleonic Wars]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1810]]
[[Category:Military history of Mauritius]]
[[Category:Wars involving Mauritius]]
[[Category:Isle de France (Mauritius)]]
[[Category:1810 in Mauritius]]
[[Category:Invasions by the United Kingdom|Isle de France]]</text>
      <sha1>mil1zzawpxiwmy76lo0lvfvg0ukh72j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
