<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jack Newkirk</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39522013</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748080445</id>
      <parentid>723187389</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-06T06:18:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Books */clean up; http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21460">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
| honorific_prefix  = 
| name              = John V. Newkirk
| honorific_suffix  = 
| native_name       = 
| native_name_lang  = 
| image         = JVNewkirk-Thumb.jpg
| image_size    = 
| alt           = 
| caption       = 
| birth_date    = 15 October 1913
| death_date    = 24 March 1942
| birth_place   = [[New York City]]
| death_place   = [[Chiang Mai, Thailand]]
| placeofburial = St. James the Less Church&lt;br /&gt;[[Scarsdale, NY]]
| placeofburial_label = 
| placeofburial_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{Coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
| nickname      = Scarsdale Jack
| birth_name    = John Van Kuren Newkirk
| allegiance    = [[United States]]
| branch        = [[United States Navy]]
| serviceyears  = 1938–1942
| rank          = Lieutenant
| servicenumber = &lt;!--Do not use data from primary sources such as service records.--&gt;
| unit          = [[USS Yorktown (CV-5)]]
| commands      = 
| battles       = [[World War II]]&lt;br /&gt;[[China Burma India Theater]]
| awards        = [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross (USA)]]&lt;br /&gt;   (posthumous)&lt;br/&gt;
[[Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)|Distinguished Flying Cross (UK)]]&lt;br /&gt;   (posthumous)
| spouse        = Virginia Jane Dunham 
| relations     =
| laterwork     = 
| signature     = 
| website       = &lt;!-- {{URL|example.com}} --&gt;
}}

'''John Van Kuren &quot;Scarsdale Jack&quot; Newkirk''' (15 October 1913&amp;nbsp;– 24 March 1942) was a [[United States Naval Aviator|United States naval aviator]] and squadron leader with the 1st [[American Volunteer Group]] (AVG), also known as the [[Flying Tigers]], who may have led the first American offensive mission of [[World War II]]. Most of his combat experience was during the defense of [[Rangoon, Burma]], from Japanese air attacks. After the fall of Rangoon, his unit was operating from within [[Republic of China (1912–49)|China]] when he set off on his final mission, as part of an attack on Japanese airfields in [[Thailand in World War II|Thailand]].

== Early life and education ==
Newkirk was born in [[New York City]] on 15 October 1913. One year later his family moved to [[Scarsdale, New York]], where his father, Louis Hasbrouck Newkirk, worked as an attorney. Newkirk was known within the extended family as &quot;Scarsdale Jack,&quot; to distinguish him from a younger cousin with the same name. At age ten, Newkirk was awarded a vocal scholarship to the [[Cathedral of St. John the Divine]] where he sang in the boys choir and attended the [[The Cathedral School of St. John the Divine, New York|Cathedral School]] until age 14. Thereafter, Newkirk attended [[Scarsdale High School]] from which he graduated in 1932. During this time he was also active in the [[Boy Scouts of America]] and received his [[Eagle Scout (Boy Scouts of America)|Eagle Scout]] medal from [[Richard E. Byrd|Admiral Richard E. Byrd]] at a ceremony in [[White Plains, New York]]. In the fall of 1932, Newkirk entered [[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]] in [[Troy, New York]], to study aeronautical engineering. However, he was unable to afford tuition during the height of the [[Great Depression]] and dropped out after only one year. Newkirk subsequently worked odd jobs in New York City and served a brief stint in the [[New York National Guard]] until the fall of 1937, when he returned to Rensselaer to continue his studies.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}{{sfn|Newkirk|2008}}{{sfn|Life|1942}}{{sfn|Wings|1942|pp=55–56}}{{sfn|Ford|2014}}

== U.S. Navy service ==
Newkirk learned to fly whilst a student at Rennselaer, eventually accumulating two years of study which gave him the qualifications to become a cadet aviator in the US Navy. He joined the Navy in 1938 and after initial screening at [[Floyd Bennett Field]] in [[Brooklyn]], he was transferred to [[Naval Air Station Pensacola]] in Florida where his classmates included [[David Lee &quot;Tex&quot; Hill]] and [[Bert Christman]]. Newkirk earned his wings in 1939 and was assigned to the {{USS|Yorktown|CV-5|6}} at [[Naval Station Pearl Harbor]] in Hawaii, where he remained on active duty until the summer of 1941.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}{{sfn|Life|1942}}{{sfn|Wings|1942|pp=55–56}}{{sfn|Ford|2014}}{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=27,129,165,185–187}}

While on leave, Newkirk visited his brother in Houston, Texas. Newkirk took a trip to the beach at Galveston where he met his wife to be, Virginia Jane Dunham. Born in Lansing, Michigan, she was known as Jane or Janie.{{sfn|Life|1942}}{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=175,176,185}}

The ''Yorktown'' left Pearl Harbour on 20 April 1941 and docked in Norfolk, Virginia. While on shore leave there, Newkirk was &quot;approached by a man who introduced himself as Commander Rutledge Irvine - retired&quot;. His mission would be to fly American [[P-40]] aircraft against Japanese forces occupying China. Already incensed by reports of [[Japanese atrocities]] against the Chinese people, Newkirk accepted the offer.{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=178, 182,183}}

On 15 June 1941 Newkirk told his sister that he had accepted an offer from the [[Central Aircraft Manufacturing Company]] (CAMCO), for a year, at $600 a month plus bonuses. After the contract was over he would be reinstated in the Navy without any loss of rank or pay. The following day he carried out his final assignment for the U.S Navy. He delivered a new Wildcat from the factory at Long Island to Norfolk, Virginia, where he signed his Navy discharge papers.{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=183,185–187}}

== American Volunteer Group ==

[[File:Curtiss P-40E Warhawk 2 USAF.jpg|thumb|A Hawk 87A-3 (Kittyhawk Mk IA) serial number ''AK987'', in a USAAF [[23d Fighter Group]] (the former &quot;[[Flying Tigers]]&quot;) paint scheme, at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]].]]

CAMCO had been selected in April 1941 to be the front for the AVG, as a way to get round the [[Neutrality Acts of 1930s|neutrality laws]]. CAMCO then formed an agreement with the Chinese government to recruit and pay the pilots and ground crew for &quot;three advanced training and instruction units&quot;.  Chennault, whose idea it had been to use a civilian company, was appointed the &quot;American supervisor&quot;. The 1st AVG, also known as The Flying Tigers, was manned on a one-year contract basis by volunteers recruited from serving U.S. military personnel.{{sfn|Carrozza|2012|pp=63,79-83}} {{sfn|Bond|1984|p=20}}

Although naval aviators were, at that time, prohibited from marriage within two years of getting their wings, having left the navy, the marriage could go ahead. John and Jane were married on 5 July 1941 at the First Presbyterian Church of Houston, Texas. After a two-day honeymoon in a Houston hotel, they flew to San Francisco to meet up with other AVG recruits and their wives. They parted company on 10 July 1941 at the docks, where Newkirk boarded the M.V. ''Jagersfontein'', with some of the AVG recruits on their way to Singapore, whilst Janie stayed in Los Angeles.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=188,190,194,195,377}}

The AVG recruits were transported to [[Rangoon]], [[British rule in Burma|Burma]]. In the latter half of 1941, AVG recruits were based at a British airfield in [[Toungoo]] undergoing training. Meanwhile, their aircraft were assembled and test flown by CAMCO staff at [[Yangon International Airport|Mingaladon Airport]] outside Rangoon.{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=194–195}}{{sfn|Feltus|2003}}

Newkirk was the squadron leader of the 2nd &quot;Panda Bears&quot; Squadron by September 1941.{{sfn|Life|1942}}{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=194–195}} He led his squadron on the AVG's first combat mission, on 20 December 1941, southeast of [[Kunming]], but ordered his flight to break off before contact. Chennault described this action as &quot;buck fever&quot; (nervousness felt by novice hunters when they first sight game).{{sfn|Rice|2003|p=56}}{{sfn|Clements|2001|p=45}}

On 30 December 1941, 2nd Squadron moved south from Toungou to Mingaladon with 18 fresh aircraft, relieving the 3rd Squadron who had been there since 12 December. They shared the air defense of Rangoon with two British squadrons: [[No. 17 Squadron RAF|17 Squadron]] with [[Hawker Hurricane]]s and [[No. 67 Squadron RAF|67 Squadron]] with [[Brewster Buffalo]]es.{{sfn|Clements|2001|pp=4,48,75}}{{sfn|Dethloff|2006|p=34}}

== First offensive mission ==
&lt;!--  [[File:FirstBlood-Grinnell.jpg|thumbnail|left|Artist's depiction of the January 3, 1942 raid on the Raheng Aerodrome]] --&gt;
On the morning of 3 January 1942, Newkirk led Christman, Hill, and [[James H. Howard|Jim Howard]] across [[Burma|Burma's]] [[Dawna Range|Dawna Mountain Range]] in an attack against the Japanese-held [[Tak Airport|Tak airfield]]  near [[Raheng]], [[Thailand]]. Christman's aircraft developed engine trouble, forcing him to return to base and leave Newkirk without a wingman. Upon arrival at the Raheng Aerodrome, the three pilots observed numerous Japanese aircraft parked by the runway but did not immediately notice the Japanese [[Nakajima Ki-27|Ki-27 &quot;Nate&quot;]] fighters already in the air. Howard began to strafe the airfield, apparently unaware that an enemy aircraft was on his tail. Hill shot down the Nate pursuing Howard, then took on an additional one. Newkirk, who had engaged and destroyed one airborne Nate by then, was also credited with the third that Hill had also been engaging. Howard destroyed four Nates on the ground. With multiple enemy aircraft destroyed and the Raheng airfield in flames, Newkirk, Howard, and Hill all returned safely to base.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}{{sfn|Sterner|2014}}{{sfn|Rice|2003|pp=64–66}}

Military historian C. Douglas Sterner{{sfn|US Govt|2012|p=2}} suggests this may have been the first planned American offensive mission of World War II,{{sfn|Sterner|2014}} although the matter is open to debate. While Newkirk, Christman, Howard, and Hill had been U.S. Forces pilots, each had been required to resign his commission in order to join the Flying Tigers and thus were not U.S. military officers at the time.{{sfn|Ford|2013}} In 1991, a Pentagon special service review board ruled the Flying Tigers had indeed been on &quot;active duty&quot; during these battles and awarded them full veterans' status.{{sfn|New York Times|1991}}

The [[USS Enterprise (CV-6)|USS ''Enterprise''{{'}}s]] 1 February attack on the [[Marshall Islands]], traditionally considered America's first World War II offensive, came several weeks after the Flying Tigers' Raheng mission.{{sfn|Washington Correspondent|1942|p=4}}

==Loss of Rangoon and retreat to China==
Newkirk was credited with a Nate on 8 January 1942.{{sfn|Clements|2001|p=45}} The following day, Newkirk led another raid against the Tak airfield. Four 2nd Squadron and six RAF pilots took part and, between them, destroyed 24 Japanese aircraft.{{sfn|Rice|2003|pp=66–67}}

On 12 January 1942, the [[Japanese invasion of Burma]] began and Mingaladon was reinforced with a further eight aircraft.{{sfn|Clements|2001|p=48}}{{sfn|Rice|2003|p=67}}  Another Ki-27 Nate was credited to him on 20 January, and three days later he achieved  another victory but his aircraft was badly shot up and he had to crash land.{{sfn|Clements|2001|p=45}} The remainder of the 2nd Squadron were sent to Rangoon on 25 January.{{sfn|Rice|2003|p=67}}  On 28 January 1942, Newkirk told Chennault that the &quot;aeroplanes we have here are now are beginning to look like patchwork quilts for the holes in them. The engines are also getting tired&quot; {{sfn|Clements|2001|p=48}}  Newkirk left Rangoon on 10 February but, to get to the AVG base in Kunming, he had to go via India.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}} By 7 March 1942, Rangoon had fallen and the defense of the [[Burma Road]] became the priority of the Flying Tigers.{{sfn|Rice|2003|p=72}}

The AVG continued some of its operations from [[Magway, Burma|Magwe]], which was heavily bombed by the Japanese. Chennault ordered retaliatory raids against [[Chiang Mai]] and [[Lampang Airport|Lampang]] on 23 March 1942. Because these bases were out of range of the P-40s, from their main base at Kunming, it was decided to go via Loi Wing (Leiyun), in China, then launch the raid from the RAF airstrip at Nam Sang, Burma.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}

== Death and controversy ==
On 24 March 1942, the aircraft took off in darkness from Nam Sang and by 06:30 all were en route to Chiang Mai. Newkirk's part of the mission was to lead his flight past Chiang Mai to Lampang and, if no targets could be found there, return to help with the main raid on Chiang Mai. Arriving ahead of the main force over Chiain Mai, Newkirk's flight of four aircraft strafed the main railway depot in passing and then continued towards Lampang, approximately {{convert|45|miles|km}} to the southeast.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}
{{Location map|Burma|relief=yes|width=200|float=right
|caption=|mark=Airplane_silhouette.svg|marksize=10
|label=Lamphun crash site&lt;br /&gt;←Burma  Thailand→|position= center
|lat_deg=18|lat_min=32|lat_sec=58|lat_dir=N
|lon_deg=99|lon_min=00|lon_sec=45|lon_dir=E
}}
Newkirk's aircraft crashed in a ball of flame and he was killed instantly close to [[Lamphun]]. It was believed at the time that Newkirk's aircraft was hit by ground fire.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}{{sfn|Rice|2003|pp=72–73}}{{sfn|Ford|2014}}  Later investigations, including discussions with eyewitnesses, raised the possibility that Newkirk may have inadvertently hit a tree.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}} His body was thrown clear of the wreckage and landed in a paddy field. He was buried locally by the Japanese.{{sfn|Bergin|2012}}{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|p=239}}

== Aftermath ==
Newkirk was credited with seven air-to-air victories,{{sfn|Ford|2014}}{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=194–195}}{{sfn|Sterner|2014}}{{sfn|Rice|2003|p=56}}{{sfn|Life|1942}} during his time with the Flying Tigers, and 10.5 kills overall by CAMCO.{{sfn|Clements|2001|p=45}} In 1942, the &quot;Scarsdale Jack Unit&quot; was named in his memory at the U.S. Navy pre-training camp in Chapel Hill, North Carolina.{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|p=240}}{{sfn|Herald|1942|p=3}} He was awarded the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)|British Distinguished Flying Cross]], posthumously, in August 1943.{{sfn|Bond|1984|p=210}}

Newkirk's widow, Virginia Jane remarried after his death, marrying U.S. diplomat Charles Dudley Withers, who later became the U.S. Ambassador to Rwanda, serving in that role from April 1963 until September 1966. She died on 16 July 1982 in Naples, Florida; leaving no children.{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|p=377}}{{sfn|Office of the Historian|2014}}

After the war, Newkirk's body was disinterred by a joint Thai-American military team and reburied in Saint James the Less Cemetery, Scarsdale, Westchester County, New York on 11 May 1949.{{sfn| Eleanor Charles |1988}}{{sfn|Eisner|2014}} Newkirk was awarded the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]], posthumously, in 2007, following the 1991 official recognition of the Flying Tigers as veterans of World War II.{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|p=377}}

== Popular culture ==
The American press, eager for positive stories about U.S. involvement in the war effort, quickly turned &quot;Scarsdale Jack&quot; into one of the nation's most written-about fighter pilots during the first few months of the war. Broadcaster [[Lowell Thomas]] mentioned him by name on several occasions, as did [[Life (magazine)|Life Magazine]],{{sfn|Life|1942}} [[Time Magazine]], the [[Associated Press]], the [[United Press]], and the [[Chicago Daily News]] and [[New York Times]].{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=213–240}}  The [[Walt Disney]] organisation created an official Flying Tigers insignia{{sfn|Carrozza|2012|p=96}} – a winged Bengal tiger with extended claws flying through a large blue V for victory – which Newkirk and other AVG members sewed on their flight jackets and painted on their aircraft. [[Zip Comics]] and Wings Comics{{sfn|Wings|1942|pp=55–56}} each devoted full-color spreads to Newkirk and his aerial exploits.{{sfn|Newkirk|2008|pp=213–240}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2|30em}}

===Books===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book
 | last =Rice
 | first =Earle
 | year =2003
 | title =Claire Chennault
 | publisher =Chelsea House Publishers
 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=Zbr_z99E54QC
 | isbn =0-7910-7217-7
 | ref = harv 
}}
*{{cite book
 |last=Newkirk
 |first=John J.
 |title=The Old Man and the Harley: A Last Ride Through Our Fathers' America
 |year=2008
 |publisher=Thomas Nelson, Inc.
 |location=Nashville
 |isbn=978-1-59555-180-1
 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NdctdlFRJPkC
 |ref=harv
}}

*{{cite book
 |last=Clements
 |first=Terrill J
 |title= American Volunteer Group Colours and Markings
 |year=2001
 |publisher=Osprey Publishing Ltd
 |location=England
 |isbn=1-84176-224-5
 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8HlYBlMplbAC
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last1= Dethloff
 |first1= Henry C
 |title= Texas Aggies Go to War: In Service of Their Country
 |year= 2006
 |publisher= Texas A&amp;M University Press
 |location=Texas, USA
 |isbn= 1-60344-077-1
 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kq0cfayp6lIC
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last1=Bergin
 |first1= Bob
 |title= &quot;Scarsdale Jack&quot; Newkirk
 |year= 2012
 |publisher= Banana Tree Press
 | url=http://www.amazon.co.uk/Scarsdale-Jack-Newkirk-Mystery-Flying-ebook/dp/B009ALURKI/ref=sr_1_30
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last1=Bond
 |first1= Charles
 |title= A Flying Tiger's Diary
 |year= 1984
 |publisher= A&amp;M University Press
 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=voeOKZ8FdI0C
 |isbn= 0-89096-408-4
 |ref=harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last1=Carrozza
 |first1= Anthony
 |title= William D Pawley
 |year= 2012
 |publisher= Potomac Books
 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wRY7DPPKYXcC
 |isbn= 978-1-59797-719-7
 |ref=harv
}}
{{refend}}

===Newspapers, magazines and journals===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite news
 | author=New York Times
 | title=50 Years Later, Flying Tigers Are Given Veterans' Benefits
 | url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/07/08/us/50-years-later-flying-tigers-are-given-veterans-benefits.html
 | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
 | location=New York
 | date=8 July 1991
 | ref=harv
}} 
*{{cite news
 | author=Life
 | title=Flying Tigers in Burma
 | url=http://cbi-theater-1.home.comcast.net/~cbi-theater-1/flyingtigers/flying_tigers.html
 | publisher=Life Magazine
 | date=30 March 1942
 | ref=harv
}} 
*{{cite web
 | author=Wings
 | title=Scarsdale Jack Newkirk
 | url=http://www.rpi.edu/magazine/spring2006/pdf/Jack-Newkirk-Comic.pdf
 | publisher=Wings Comics
 | date=24 August 1942
 | ref=harv
}} 
*{{cite news
 | author= Eleanor Charles
 | title= WESTCHESTER GUIDE
 | url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/10/30/nyregion/westchester-guide-322388.html
 | newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
 | location=New York
 | date=30 Oct 1988
 | ref=harv
}} 
*{{cite news
 | author=Washington Correspondent
 
 | title=A surprise attack
 | url=http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/archive/article/1942-02-02/4/1.html
 | date=2 Feb 1942
 | newspaper=[[The Times]]
 | location=London
 | accessdate=22 October 2014
 | ref= harv
}}
*{{cite news
 |author=Herald
 | title=Cadet Walsh To Join Scarsdale Jack Unit
 |url=http://fultonhistory.com/newspaper%2010/Yonkers%20NY%20Herald%20Statesman/Yonkers%20NY%20Herald%20Statesman%201942%20Grayscale/Yonkers%20NY%20Herald%20Statesman%201942%20Grayscale%20-%203898.pdf
 |publisher=The Herald Statesman
 |location=Yonkers
 |date=12 Nov 1942
 |ref=harv
}}
{{refend}}

===Reports===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite journal
 | author = US Govt
 | title=Statement of C. Douglas Sterner, Curator, Military Times &quot;Hall of Valor&quot;
 | year=2012
 | url = http://oversight.house.gov/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/2-29-12_natsec_sterner_part1.pdf
 | publisher = House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform
 | location   = Washington D.C.
 | ref= harv
}}
{{refend}}

===Websites===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite web
 | last=Sterner
 | first=C. Douglas
 | year = 2014
 |title=Home of Heroes: Flying Tigers
 |url=http://www.homeofheroes.com/wings/part2/14_howard.html
 | accessdate =6 October 2014
 | ref = harv
}} 
*{{cite web
  | last=Ford
  | first=Daniel
  | year=2013
  | authorlink =Daniel Ford
  | title=FDR's 'secret order'
  | url=http://www.warbirdforum.com/fdrnote.htm
  | accessdate =7 October 2014
  | ref= harv
}}
*{{cite web
  | last=Ford
  | first=Daniel
  | year=2014
  | authorlink =Daniel Ford
  | title=Jack Newkirk, down in Thailand
  | url= http://www.warbirdforum.com/newkirk.htm
  | accessdate =7 October 2014
  | ref= harv
}}
*{{cite web
  | author = Office of the Historian
  | year=2014
  | title=CHARLES DUDLEY WITHERS (1916–)
  | url=https://history.state.gov/departmenthistory/people/withers-charles-dudley
  | accessdate =8 October 2014
  | ref= harv
}}
*{{cite web
  | last = Eisner
  | first = Jack
  | year=2014
  | title= John Van Kuren Newkirk
  | url=http://www.warbirdforum.com/jackcras.htm
  | accessdate =8 October 2014
  | ref= harv
}}
*{{cite web
 | last =Feltus
 | first =Pamela
 | author2-link =
 | title =Claire Chennault and the Flying Tigers of World War II
 | publisher =U.S. Centennial of Flight Commission
 | year =2003
 | url =http://centennialofflight.net/essay/Air_Power/tigers/AP24.htm
 | accessdate =9 October 2014
 | ref = harv 
}}
{{refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Newkirk, John V. Scarsdale Jack}}
[[Category:1913 births]]
[[Category:1942 deaths]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Aviators killed by being shot down]]
[[Category:Scarsdale High School alumni]]
[[Category:Military personnel from New York City]]</text>
      <sha1>hg9awtb984yff0efchb1zt87p3rzu7b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
