<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Japanese cruiser Iwate</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3799270</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724612130</id>
      <parentid>719496249</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-10T10:39:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>VileGecko</username>
        <id>12801198</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Construction and career */ Launching photo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34194">{{good article}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image= [[File:Japanese cruiser Iwate.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=A postcard of ''Iwate'' at anchor, 1905
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=[[Empire of Japan]]
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|Japan|naval}}
|Ship name=''Iwate''
|Ship namesake=[[Iwate Prefecture]]
|Ship ordered=19 July 1898
|Ship builder= [[Armstrong Whitworth]], [[United Kingdom]]
|Ship laid down=11 November 1898
|Ship launched= 29 March 1900
|Ship completed= 18 March 1901
|Ship commissioned=  
|Ship decommissioned= 
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship struck=30 November 1945
|Ship reclassified=*1st-class [[Kaibokan|coast-defense ship]], 1 September 1921
*[[Heavy cruiser|1st-class cruiser]], 1 July 1942
*As [[training ship]], 1943
|Ship honours=
|Ship fate=*Sunk by air attack, 25 July 1945
*Raised and [[ship breaking|scrapped]], 1946–47
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption= 
|Ship class= {{sclass-|Izumo|cruiser|0}} [[armored cruiser]]
|Ship displacement= {{convert|9423|t|LT|abbr=on}}
|Ship length={{convert|132.28|m|ftin|abbr=on}} ([[Length overall|o/a]])
|Ship beam={{convert|20.94|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|7.21|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=*2 Shafts
*2 [[Marine steam engine#Triple or multiple expansion|Vertical triple-expansion steam engines]]
|Ship power=*{{convert|14500|ihp|lk=in|abbr=on}}
*24 [[Belleville boilers]]
|Ship speed={{convert|20.75|kn|lk=in}}
|Ship range={{convert|7000|nmi|lk=in|abbr=on}} at {{convert|10|kn}}
|Ship complement=672
|Ship armament=*2 × twin [[20.3 cm/45 Type 41 naval gun]]s
*14 × single QF 6-inch guns
*12 × single [[QF 12 pounder 12 cwt naval gun|QF 12-pounder 12-cwt guns]]
*8 × single QF 2.5-pounder [[Hotchkiss gun|Yamauchi guns]]
*4 × single {{convert|457|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s
|Ship armor=*[[Belt armor|Waterline belt]]: {{convert|89|-|178|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Deck (ship)|Deck]]: {{convert|63|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Gun Turret]]: {{convert|160|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Barbette]]: {{convert|152|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Casemate]]: {{convert|51|-|152|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Conning tower]]: {{convert|356|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Bulkhead (partition)|Bulkhead]]: {{convert|127|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
{{nihongo|'''''Iwate'''''|磐手}} was the second and last {{sclass-|Izumo|cruiser|0}} [[armored cruiser]] built for the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] (IJN) in the late 1890s. As Japan lacked the industrial capacity to build such warships herself, the ship was built in Britain. She participated in most of the naval battles of the [[Russo-Japanese War]] of 1904–05. The ship was moderately damaged during the [[Battle of Port Arthur]], the [[Battle off Ulsan]], and the [[Battle of Tsushima]]. ''Iwate'' played a minor role in World War I and began the first of her many training cruises for [[naval cadet]]s in 1916, a task that would last until the end of 1939. The ship continued to conduct training in home waters throughout the [[Pacific War]]. ''Iwate'' was sunk by American carrier aircraft during the [[Bombing of Kure (July 1945)|attack on Kure]] in July 1945. Her wreck was [[Marine salvage|refloated]] and [[ship breaking|scrapped]] in 1946–47.

==Background and description==
The 1896 Naval Expansion Plan was made after the [[First Sino-Japanese War]] and included four armored cruisers in addition to four more [[battleship]]s, all of which had to be ordered from British shipyards as Japan lacked the capability to build them itself. Further consideration of the Russian building program caused the IJN to believe that the battleships ordered under the original plan would not be sufficient to counter the [[Imperial Russian Navy]]. Budgetary limitations prevented ordering more battleships and the IJN decided to expand the number of more affordable armored cruisers to be ordered from four to six ships. The revised plan is commonly known as the &quot;Six-Six Fleet&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Evans &amp; Peattie, pp. 57–62&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike most of their contemporaries which were designed for [[commerce raiding]] or to defend colonies and trade routes, ''Iwate'' and her half-[[sister ship|sisters]] were intended as fleet scouts and to be employed in the [[line of battle|battleline]].&lt;ref&gt;Milanovich, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;

The ship was {{convert|132.28|m|ftin|sp=us}} long [[length overall|overall]] and {{convert|121.92|m|ftin|sp=us}} [[Length between perpendiculars|between perpendiculars]]. She had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|20.94|m|ftin|sp=us}} and had an average [[draft (ship)|draft]] of {{convert|7.21|m|ftin|sp=us}}. ''Iwate'' [[Displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|9423|t|LT|sp=us}} at normal load and {{convert|10235|t|LT|sp=us}} at [[deep load]]. The ship had a [[metacentric height]] of {{convert|0.73|m|ftin|sp=us}}.&lt;ref&gt;Milanovich, pp. 74, 80&lt;/ref&gt; Her crew consisted of 672 officers and enlisted men.&lt;ref name=j2&gt;Jentschura, Jung &amp; Mickel, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

''Iwate'' had two 4-cylinder [[Marine steam engine#Triple or multiple expansion|triple-expansion steam engine]]s, each driving a single [[propeller shaft]].&lt;ref&gt;Milanovich, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; Steam for the engines was provided by 24 [[Belleville boiler]]s and the engines were rated at a total of {{convert|14500|ihp|lk=on}}. The ship had a designed speed of {{convert|20.75|kn|lk=in}} and reached {{convert|22.3|kn}} during her [[sea trial]]s from {{convert|15739|ihp|abbr=on}}. She carried up to {{convert|1551|t|LT|sp=us|disp=flip}} of coal&lt;ref name=b9&gt;Brook 1999, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; and could steam for {{convert|7000|nmi|lk=in}} at a speed of {{convert|10|kn}}.&lt;ref name=j2/&gt;

The [[main battery|main armament]] for all of the &quot;Six-Six Fleet&quot; armored cruisers was four [[20.3 cm/45 Type 41 naval gun|eight-inch guns]] in twin-[[gun turret]]s fore and aft of the [[superstructure]]. The [[Battleship secondary armament|secondary armament]] consisted of 14 [[Elswick Ordnance Company]] &quot;Pattern Z&quot; [[quick-firing gun|quick-firing (QF)]], {{convert|6|in|mm|0|adj=on}} guns. Only four of these guns were not mounted in armored [[casemate]]s on the main and upper decks and their mounts on the upper deck were protected by [[gun shield]]s. ''Iwate'' was also equipped with a dozen [[QF 12 pounder 12 cwt naval gun|QF 12-pounder 12-cwt guns]]&lt;ref group=Note&gt;&quot;Cwt&quot; is the abbreviation for [[hundredweight]], 12 cwt referring to the weight of the gun.&lt;/ref&gt; and eight QF 2.5-pounder [[Hotchkiss gun|Yamauchi guns]] as close-range defense against [[torpedo boat]]s. The ship was equipped with four submerged {{convert|457|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s, two on each [[broadside]].&lt;ref&gt;Milanovich, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

All of the &quot;Six-Six Fleet&quot; armored cruisers used the same armor scheme with some minor differences. The [[Belt armor|waterline belt]] of [[Krupp cemented armor]] ran the full length of the ship and its thickness varied from {{convert|178|mm|in|sp=us}} amidships to {{convert|89|mm|in|sp=us}} at the bow and stern. It had a height of {{convert|2.13|m|ftin|sp=us}}, of which {{convert|1.33|m|ftin|sp=us}} was normally underwater. The upper [[strake]] of belt armor was {{convert|127|mm|in|sp=us}} thick and extended from the upper edge of the waterline belt to the main deck. It extended {{convert|53.31|m|ftin|sp=us}} from the forward to the rear [[barbette]]. The ''Izumo'' class had oblique 127&amp;nbsp;mm armored [[bulkhead (partition)|bulkhead]]s that closed off the ends of the central armored citadel.&lt;ref&gt;Milanovich, pp. 80–81&lt;/ref&gt;

The barbettes, gun turrets and the front of the casemates were all 6 inches thick while the sides and rear of the casemates were protected by {{convert|51|mm|in|sp=us}} of armor. The deck was {{convert|63|mm|in|sp=us}} thick and the armor protecting the [[conning tower]] was {{convert|356|mm|in|sp=us}} in thickness.&lt;ref name=Conway&gt;Chesneau &amp; Kolesnik, p. 225&lt;/ref&gt;

==Construction and career==
[[File:IJN Iwate launching, 29.03.1900.jpg|thumb|left|''Iwate'' prior to launching, [[Newcastle upon Tyne]]]]
[[File:Japanese cruiser Iwate at Plymouth.jpg|thumb|''Iwate'' at anchor, [[Plymouth]], c. 1901]]
The contract for ''Iwate'', named after the [[Iwate Prefecture|eponymous prefecture]],&lt;ref&gt;Silverstone, p. 331&lt;/ref&gt; was signed on 19 July 1898 with [[Armstrong Whitworth]]. The ship was [[keel laying|laid down]] at their shipyard in [[Elswick, Tyne and Wear|Elswick]] on 11 November 1898 and [[Ship naming and launching|launched]] on 29 March 1900. She was completed on 18 March 1901 and departed for Japan the following day&lt;ref&gt;Milanovich, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; under the command of [[Captain (naval)|Captain]] [[Yamada Hikohachi]], who had been appointed to supervise her construction and bring her back to Japan. ''Iwate'' arrived in [[Yokosuka, Kanagawa|Yokosuka]] on 17 May and Yamada was relieved by Captain [[Taketomi Kunikane]] on 6 July.&lt;ref name=hk&gt;Hackett &amp; Kingsepp&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russo-Japanese War===
At the start of the Russo-Japanese War, ''Iwate'' was the flagship of Rear Admiral [[Misu Sotarō]], commander of the 2nd Division of the [[2nd Fleet (Imperial Japanese Navy)|2nd Fleet]].&lt;ref&gt;Kowner, p. 241&lt;/ref&gt; She participated in the [[Battle of Port Arthur]] on 9 February 1904, when [[Vice Admiral]] [[Tōgō Heihachirō]] led the [[Combined Fleet]] in an attack on the Russian ships of the [[Pacific Fleet (Russia)|Pacific Squadron]] anchored just outside [[Lüshunkou District|Port Arthur]]. Tōgō had expected the surprise night attack by his destroyers to be much more successful than it was, anticipating that the Russians would be badly disorganized and weakened, but they had recovered from their surprise and were ready for his attack. The Japanese ships were spotted by the [[protected cruiser]] {{ship|Russian cruiser|Boyarin|1901|2}}, which was patrolling offshore and alerted the Russians. Tōgō chose to attack the Russian coastal defenses with his main armament and engage the ships with his secondary guns. Splitting his fire proved to be a poor decision as the Japanese eight- and six-inch guns inflicted little damage on the Russian ships, which concentrated all their fire on the Japanese ships with some effect.&lt;ref&gt;Forczyk, pp. 42–43&lt;/ref&gt; Although many ships on both sides were hit, Russian casualties numbered some 150, while the Japanese suffered roughly 90 killed and wounded before Tōgō disengaged.&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1994, I, p. 105&lt;/ref&gt; ''Iwate'' had, in fact, been considerably damaged in the engagement.&lt;ref&gt;Warner &amp; Warner, p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;

In early March, Kamimura was tasked to take the reinforced 2nd Division north and make a diversion off [[Vladivostok]]. While scouting for Russian ships in the area, the Japanese cruisers bombarded the harbor and defenses of Vladivostok on 6 March to little effect. Upon their return to Japan a few days later, the 2nd Division was ordered to escort the transports ferrying the [[Imperial Guards Division]] to Korea and then to join the ships blockading Port Arthur. Kamimura was ordered north in mid-April to cover the [[Sea of Japan]] and defend the [[Korea Strait]] against any attempt by the Vladivostok Independent Cruiser Squadron, under the command of Rear Admiral [[Karl Jessen]], to break through and unite with the Pacific Squadron. The two units narrowly missed each other on the 24th in heavy fog and the Japanese proceeded to Vladivostok where they laid several [[minefield]]s before arriving back at [[Wonsan]] on the 30th.&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1994, I, pp. 138–39, 142–45, 160, 177, 188–89, 191–96&lt;/ref&gt;

The division failed to intercept the Russian squadron as it attacked [[Hitachi Maru Incident|several transports]] south of [[Okinoshima, Shimane|Okinoshima Island]] on 15 June due to heavy rain and fog. The Russians sortied again on 30 June and Kamimura finally was able to intercept them the next day near Okinoshima. The light was failing when they were spotted and the Russians were able to disengage in the darkness. Jessen's ships sortied again on 17 July headed for the eastern coast of Japan to act as a diversion and pull Japanese forces out of the Sea of Japan and the [[Yellow Sea]]. The Russian ships passed through [[Tsugaru Strait]] two days later and began capturing ships bound for Japan. The arrival of the Russians off [[Tokyo Bay]] on the 24th caused the [[Imperial Japanese Navy General Staff|Naval General Staff]] to order Kamimura to sail for Cape Toi Misaki, [[Kyūshū]], fearing that Jessen would circumnavigate Japan to reach Port Arthur. Two days later he was ordered north to the [[Kii Channel]] and then to Tokyo Bay on the 28th. The General Staff finally ordered him back to [[Tsushima Island]] on the 30th; later that day he received word that Jessen's ships had passed through the Tsugaru Strait early that morning and reached Vladivostok on 1 August.&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1994, I, pp. 283–89, 319–25, 337–51&lt;/ref&gt;

====Battle off Ulsan====
{{main|Battle off Ulsan}}
[[File:Japanese cruiser Iwate in 1902.jpg|thumb|''Iwate'' at anchor, 1902]]
On 10 August, the ships at Port Arthur attempted a breakout to Vladivostok, but were turned back in the [[Battle of the Yellow Sea]]. Jessen was ordered to rendezvous with them, but the order was delayed. His three armored cruisers, {{ship|Russian cruiser|Rossia||2}}, {{ship|Russian cruiser|Gromoboi||2}}, and {{ship|Russian cruiser|Rurik|1892|2}}, had to raise steam, so he did not sortie until the evening of 13 August. By dawn he had reached Tsushima, but turned back when he failed to see any ships from the Port Arthur squadron. {{Convert|36|mi|0}} north of the island he encountered Kamimura's squadron, which consisted of four modern armored cruisers, {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Izumo||2}}, {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Tokiwa||2}}, {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Azuma||2}}, and ''Iwate''. The two squadrons had passed during the night without spotting one another and each had reversed course around first light. This put the Japanese ships astride the Russian route to Vladivostok.&lt;ref&gt;Brook 2000, pp. 34, 37&lt;/ref&gt;

Jessen ordered his ships to turn to the northeast when he spotted the Japanese at 05:00 and they followed suit, albeit on a slightly converging course. Both sides opened fire around 05:23 at a range of {{convert|8500|m|yd|sp=us}}. The Japanese ships concentrated their fire on ''Rurik'', the rear ship of the Russian formation. She was hit fairly quickly and began to fall astern of the other two ships. Jessen turned southeast in an attempt to open the range, but this blinded the Russian gunners with the rising sun and prevented any of their broadside guns from bearing on the Japanese. About 06:00, Jessen turned 180° to starboard in an attempt to reach the Korean coast and to allow ''Rurik'' to rejoin the squadron. Kamimura followed suit around 06:10, but turned to port, which opened the range between the squadrons. ''Azuma'' then developed engine problems and the Japanese squadron slowed to conform with her best speed. Firing recommenced at 06:24 and ''Rurik'' was hit three times in the stern, flooding her steering compartment; she had to be steered with her engines. Her speed continued to decrease, further exposing her to Japanese fire, and her steering jammed to port around 06:40.&lt;ref&gt;Brook 2000, pp. 39, 43&lt;/ref&gt;

Jessen made another 180° turn in an attempt to interpose his two ships between the Japanese and ''Rurik'', but the latter ship suddenly turn to starboard and increased speed and passed between Jessen's ships and the Japanese. Kamimura turned 180° as well so that both squadrons were heading southeast on parallel courses, but Jessen quickly made another 180° turn so that they headed on opposing courses. At this time an eight-inch shell struck the roof of ''Iwate''{{'}}s starboard forward upper six-inch casemate and ignited the ready-use ammunition. The fire killed 40 and wounded 24 more and knocked out the six-inch gun in that casemate, as well as those below and aft of it. In addition, the 12-pounder above it was rendered inoperable. The Russians reversed course for the third time around 07:45 in another attempt to support ''Rurik'' although ''Rossia'' was on fire herself; her fires were extinguished about twenty minutes later. Kamimura circled ''Rurik'' to the south at 08:00 and allowed the other two Russian ships to get to his north and gave them an uncontested route to Vladivostok. Despite this, Jessen turned back once more at 08:15 and ordered ''Rurik'' to make her own way back to Vladivostok before turning north at his maximum speed, about {{convert|18|kn}}.&lt;ref name=b3&gt;Brook 2000, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt;

About this time Kamimura's two elderly protected cruisers, {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Naniwa||2}} and {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Takachiho||2}}, were approaching from the south. Their arrival allowed Kamimura to pursue Jessen with all of his armored cruisers while the two new arrivals dealt with ''Rurik''. They fought a running battle with the Russians for the next hour and a half; scoring enough hits on them to force their speed down to {{convert|15|kn}}. The Japanese closed to a minimum of about {{convert|5000|m|yd|sp=us}}, but Kamimura then opened the range up to {{convert|6500|m|yd|sp=us}}.&lt;ref name=b3/&gt;

About 10:00, Kamimura's gunnery officer erroneously informed him that ''Izumo'' had expended three-quarters of her ammunition and he turned back after a five-minute rapid-fire barrage. He did not wish to leave the Tsushima Strait unguarded and thought that he could use his remaining ammunition on ''Rurik''. By this time she had been sunk by ''Naniwa'' and ''Takachiho''. They had radioed Kamimura that she was sunk, but he did not receive the message. Shortly after the Japanese turned back, ''Gromoboi'' and ''Rossia'' were forced to [[heave-to]] to make repairs. ''Iwate'' was the most seriously damaged Japanese ship and suffered a total of 40 killed and 37 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Brook 2000, pp. 43, 45&lt;/ref&gt;

In mid-September, ''Tokiwa'' and ''Iwate'' were transferred to the 1st Division. In early December the cruiser was sent home to refit. In mid-February, she was guarding the Tsugaru Strait and remained there through mid-April.&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1994, II, pp. 52, 104, 162, 176&lt;/ref&gt;

====Battle of Tsushima====
{{main|Battle of Tsushima}}
[[File:Japanese cruiser Iwate 2.jpg|thumb|A Japanese postcard of ''Iwate'' at sea, c. 1905]]
As the Russian 2nd and 3rd Pacific Squadrons approached Japan on 27 May, having sailed from the [[Baltic Sea]], they were spotted by patrolling Japanese ships early that morning, but visibility was limited and radio reception poor. The preliminary reports were enough to cause Tōgō to order his ships to put to sea and the 2nd Division spotted the Russian ships under the command of Vice Admiral [[Zinovy Rozhestvensky]] at around 11:30. Kamimura closed to about a range of {{convert|8000|m|yd|sp=us}} before sheering off under fire to join Tōgō's battleships.&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1994, II, pp. 232, 235&lt;/ref&gt; ''Iwate'', now the flagship of Rear Admiral [[Shimamura Hayao]],&lt;ref&gt;Kowner, p. 352&lt;/ref&gt; was last in the 2nd Division when Tōgō opened fire on the 2nd Pacific Squadron at 14:10 and, like most of the ships in the division, engaged the battleship {{ship|Russian battleship|Oslyabya||2}} which was forced to fall out of formation at 14:50 and sank 20 minutes later. The cruiser also fired upon the battleship {{ship|Russian battleship|Imperator Nikolai I||2}} before 14:50. The protected cruiser {{ship|Russian cruiser|Zhemchug||2}} attempted to make a torpedo attack at about 15:06, but was driven off by fire from ''Iwate'' and the armored cruisers {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Kasuga||2}} and {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Nisshin||2}}. The battleship {{ship|Russian battleship|Knyaz Suvorov||2}} suddenly appeared out of the mist at 15:35 at a range of about {{convert|2000|m|sp=us}}. All of Kamimura's ships engaged her for five minutes or so with ''Azuma'' and the armored cruiser {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Yakumo||2}} also firing torpedoes at the Russian ship without effect.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, Part 2, pp. 128–32&lt;/ref&gt;

After 17:30 Kamimura led his division in a fruitless pursuit of some of the Russian cruisers, leaving Tōgō's battleships to their own devices. He abandoned his chase around 18:03 and turned northwards to rejoin Tōgō. His ships spotted the rear of the Russian battleline around 18:30 and opened fire when the range closed to 8000–9000 meters. Nothing is known of any effect on the Russians and they ceased fire by 19:30 and rejoined Tōgō at 20:08 as night was falling.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, Part 3, pp. 186–87&lt;/ref&gt; The surviving Russian ships were spotted the next morning and the Japanese ships opened fire around 10:30, staying beyond the range at which the Russian ships could effectively reply. Rear Admiral [[Nikolai Nebogatov]] therefore decided to surrender his ships as he could neither return fire nor close the range.&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1994, II, pp. 319–20&lt;/ref&gt;

In the meantime, the [[coast defense ship]] {{ship|Russian coast defense ship|Admiral Ushakov||2}} had fallen well behind Nebogatov's ships and was spotted by the protected cruiser {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Chiyoda||2}} early in the morning, but the Japanese were more intent on locating the main body of the Russian fleet than attacking a single isolated ship. ''Admiral Ushakov'' was then spotted at 14:10, well after Nebogatov's surrender, by Shimamura who received permission to pursue her with ''Iwate'' and ''Yakumo''. They caught up with the Russian ship at 17:00 and demanded her surrender. ''Admiral Ushakov'' attempted to close the range to bring the Japanese cruisers within range of her guns, but they were fast enough to keep the range open and the Russian ship never hit either one. After about half an hour, ''Admiral Ushakov'' was listing heavily enough that her guns could not elevate enough to bear and her commander ordered his crew to abandon ship and the [[scuttling]] charges detonated. The ship sank in three minutes and 12 officers and 327 crewmen were rescued by the Japanese. Between them, ''Yakumo'' and ''Iwate'' fired 89 eight- and 278 six-inch shells during the engagement.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 64–65&lt;/ref&gt; ''Iwate'' was struck 17 times, over the course of the entire battle, including hits that burst in the water alongside. She was, however, only lightly damaged by two hits that caused two compartments on the lower deck to flood. These hits were made by two 12-inch, three 8-inch, two 6-inch, one 120&amp;nbsp;mm (4.7&amp;nbsp;in), five 75&amp;nbsp;mm (3&amp;nbsp;in), and four unidentified shells.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, Part 4, pp. 263, 265&lt;/ref&gt;

As the IJN was preparing to invade [[Sakhalin]] Island in early July, Kamimura's 2nd Division, now reduced to ''Iwate'', ''Izumo'', and ''Tokiwa'', was tasked to defend the Korea Strait before it escorted troops that made an [[amphibious landing]] in northeastern Korea. In mid-August, the division covered the landing at [[Chongjin]], closer to the Russian border.&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1994, II, pp. 356, 363–65, 377–80&lt;/ref&gt; After the war, she was briefly commanded by Captain [[Yamashita Gentaro]] from 2 February to 22 November 1906 before he was relieved by Captain [[Arima Ryokitsu]].&lt;ref name=hk/&gt;

===Subsequent service===
The ship participated in the early stages of the [[Battle of Tsingtao]] before returning to [[Sasebo, Nagasaki|Sasebo]] on 2 October 1914.&lt;ref&gt;Burdick, pp. 228, 241&lt;/ref&gt; The following month she was assigned to the First South Seas Squadron, based at [[Fiji]] and later at the [[Marquesas Islands]].&lt;ref&gt;Corbett 1938, I, pp. 366, 409&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 September 1915, ''Iwate'' was assigned to the Training Squadron where she conducted long-distance oceanic navigation and officer training for cadets in the [[Imperial Japanese Navy Academy]]. She began the first of her 16 training cruises on 20 April 1916, together with ''Azuma'', and visited [[Australia]] and [[Southeast Asia]] before returning home on 22 August. The ship was relieved of her assignment the next month, but rejoined the Training Squadron a year later in preparation for her next training cruise. ''Iwate'' departed on 2 March 1918, bound for [[Central America]], [[Hawaii]] and the [[South Sea Islands]], and returned on 6 July.&lt;ref&gt;Lacroix &amp; Wells, pp. 657–58&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Iwate at Vancouver 1933.jpg|thumb|''Iwate'' at [[Vancouver]], [[Canada]], 1933]]
Two years later, the ship began her next training cruise on 21 August 1920, visiting South America and the South Sea Islands, before returning on 4 April 1921.&lt;ref name=lw7&gt;Lacroix &amp; Wells, p. 657&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 September, she was re-designated as a 1st-class [[Kaibokan|coast-defense ship]].&lt;ref name=hk&gt;Hackett &amp; Kingsepp&lt;/ref&gt; On 26 June 1922, ''Iwate'', accompanied by ''Izumo'' and ''Yakumo'', began a circumnavigation of the world that took them to Hawaii, [[Los Angeles]], [[California]], through the [[Panama Canal]] to [[Rio de Janeiro]], where the cadets viewed the [[Independence Centenary International Exposition]] commemorating Brazilian independence. The ships then visited [[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]] and [[Durban]], [[South Africa]] before heading home via the [[Indian Ocean]], where they arrived on 8 February 1923.&lt;ref name=hk/&gt;
 
In 1924, four of ''Iwate''{{'}}s 12-pounder guns were removed, as were all of her QF 2.5-pounder guns, and a single [[8 cm/40 3rd Year Type naval gun|8&amp;nbsp;cm/40 3rd Year Type]] [[anti-aircraft gun|anti-aircraft (AA) gun]] was added. Refitted again in 1931, her torpedo tubes were removed as were all of her main deck 6-inch guns and their casemates plated over; she now carried only two 12-pounders, although she now had three 8&amp;nbsp;cm/40 3rd Year Type AA guns.&lt;ref&gt;Chesneau, p. 174&lt;/ref&gt; In addition her boilers were replaced by six [[Yarrow boiler]]s with an output of only {{convert|7000|ihp|abbr=on}} which reduced her top speed to {{convert|16|kn}}. She now carried {{convert|1412|LT|t|disp=flip|sp=us}} of coal and {{convert|324|LT|t|disp=flip|sp=us}} of [[fuel oil]]. Her crew now numbered 726 officers and enlisted men.&lt;ref name=j2/&gt;

The ship continued to make training cruises, usually at two-year intervals, for the rest of the decade that took her to the East Coast of North America and the [[Mediterranean Sea]] among other places.&lt;ref name=lw7/&gt; One of her cadets on the 1925–26 cruise was Prince [[Kachō Hironobu|Hironobu Fushimi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/bl/0000325/19260122/027/0006|title=Japanese Training Cruiser on World Tour|date=22 January 1926|work=Gloucester Citizen|page=6| via = [[British Newspaper Archive]]|subscription=yes|accessdate=10 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1928, the ship escorted Emperor [[Hirohito]] during an Imperial fleet review in [[Yokohama]] harbor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/bl/0000329/19281205/061/0007|title=Great Naval Review: British Warships Take Part in Yokohama Pageant|date=5 December 1928|work=Western Morning News|accessdate=10 May 2015| via = [[British Newspaper Archive]]|subscription=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1932 the training voyages became annual events, with the exception of 1935, until they ceased at the end of 1939.&lt;ref name=lw7/&gt;

''Iwate'' was assigned to the 12th Squadron of the 3rd Support Fleet from 1 February 1940. Despite her antiquated age, she was briefly re-classified as a 1st-class cruiser on 1 July 1942 before she was reclassified as a training ship in 1943.&lt;ref name=f4&gt;Fukui, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;
On 19 March 1945, ''Iwate'' was attacked by American carrier aircraft, killing one crewman, although they failed to inflict any significant damage. Shortly afterwards, her 8-inch guns were replaced by four [[12.7 cm/40 Type 89 naval gun|{{convert|12.7|cm|in|abbr=on}} Type 89]] [[dual-purpose gun]]s in two twin mounts and four of her remaining 6-inch guns were removed. Her light anti-aircraft armament was significantly reinforced by the addition of nine license-built [[25 mm Hotchkiss anti-aircraft gun|Hotchkiss]] [[Type 96 25 mm AT/AA Gun|25-millimeter Type 96]] light AA guns in one triple, two twin, and two single-gun mounts and two [[13.2 mm Hotchkiss machine gun|13.2-millimeter Hotchkiss machine gun]]s in single mounts.&lt;ref name=hk/&gt;&lt;ref name=f4/&gt;

The ship was bombed during the American aerial [[Bombing of Kure (July 1945)|attack on Kure]] on 24 July 1945. While not hit by any bombs, the three near misses sprang the ship's seams and the resulting flooding caused her to sink in shallow water at coordinates {{coord|34|14|N|132|30|E|}} the following day. She was removed from the [[navy list]] on 30 November and her [[hulk (ship)|hulk]] was raised and scrapped in 1946–47 by the [[IHI Corporation|Harima Dock Company]].&lt;ref name=hk/&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=Note}}

==Footnotes==
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{cite book|last=Brook|first=Peter|title=Warship 2000–2001|editor=Preston, Antony|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|year=2000|chapter=Armoured Cruiser vs. Armoured Cruiser: Ulsan 14 August 1904|isbn=0-85177-791-0}}
* {{cite book|last= Brook |first= Peter|title=Warships for Export: Armstrong Warships 1867-1927 |publisher= World Ship Society |location= Gravesend |year=1999|isbn=0-905617-89-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Burdick|first=Charles B.|title=The Japanese Siege of Tsingtau: World War I in Asia|year=1976|publisher=Archon Books|location=Hamden, Connecticut|isbn=0-2080-1594-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Campbell|first=N.J.M.|title=Warship|chapter=The Battle of Tsu-Shima, Parts 2, 3 and 4|editor=Preston, Antony|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|year=1978|volume=II|pages=127–35, 186–192, 258–65|isbn=0-87021-976-6}}
*{{cite book|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1922–1946|editor1-last=Chesneau|editor1-first=Roger|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=Greenwich, UK|year=1980|isbn=0-85177-146-7}}
* {{cite book|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1860–1905|editor1-last=Chesneau|editor1-first=Roger|editor2-last=Kolesnik|editor2-first=Eugene M.|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=Greenwich|year=1979|isbn=0-8317-0302-4|lastauthoramp=y}}
*{{cite book|last=Corbett|first=Julian Stafford|authorlink=Julian Corbett|title=Maritime Operations in the Russo-Japanese War, 1904–1905|year=1994|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=1-55750-129-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Corbett|first=Julian|title=Naval Operations to the Battle of the Falklands|edition=2nd, reprint of the 1938|series=History of the Great War: Based on Official Documents|volume=I|publisher=Imperial War Museum and Battery Press|location=London and Nashville, Tennessee|isbn=0-89839-256-X}}
* {{cite book| last = Evans| first = David| first2 = Mark R. |last2=Peattie| year = 1997| title = Kaigun: Strategy, Tactics, and Technology in the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1887–1941| publisher =Naval Institute Press| location =Annapolis, Maryland| isbn = 0-87021-192-7|lastauthoramp=y|author2link=Mark Peattie}}
* {{cite book|title=Russian Battleship vs Japanese Battleship, Yellow Sea 1904–05|author=Forczyk, Robert|publisher=Osprey|year=2009|location=Botley, UK|isbn=978-1-84603-330-8}}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Gardiner|editor1-first=Robert|editor2-last=Gray|editor2-first=Randal|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1921|year=1984|location=Annapolis, Maryland|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-85177-245-5|lastauthoramp=y}}
*{{cite web | url= http://www.combinedfleet.com/Iwate_t.htm| title=HIJMS ''Iwate'': Tabular Record of Movement| last1 = Hackett| first1 =Bob | first2 = Sander |last2=Kingsepp| date=2012| work= SOKO-JUNYOKAN - Ex-Armored Cruisers | publisher= Combinedfleet.com|accessdate =23 April 2015|lastauthoramp=y}}
*{{cite book| last = Jentschura| first = Hansgeorg| first2 = Dieter |last2=Jung|first3=Peter |last3=Mickel| year = 1977| title = Warships of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1869–1945| publisher = United States Naval Institute| location = Annapolis, Maryland| isbn = 0-87021-893-X|lastauthoramp=y}}
*{{cite book|last=Kowner|first=Rotem|authorlink=Rotem Kowner|title=Historical Dictionary of the Russo-Japanese War|series=Historical Dictionaries of War, Revolution, and Civil Unrest|volume=29|year=2006|publisher=Scarecrow Press|location=Lanham, Maryland|isbn=978-0-81084-927-3}}
*{{cite book|last1=Lacroix|first1=Eric|last2=Wells|first2=Linton|title=Japanese Cruisers of the Pacific War|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|year=1997|isbn=0-87021-311-3|lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|editor=Jordan, John|chapter=Armored Cruisers of the Imperial Japanese Navy|last=Milanovich|first=Kathrin|publisher=Conway |location=London|year=2014|title=Warship 2014|isbn=978-1-84486-236-8}}
*{{cite journal|last=McLaughlin|first=Stephen|year=2011|title=The Admiral Seniavin Class Coast Defense Ships|journal=Warship International|publisher=International Naval Research Organization|location=Toledo, Ohio|volume=XLVIII|issue=1|pages=43–66|issn=0043-0374}}
* {{cite book|last=Silverstone|first=Paul H.|title=Directory of the World's Capital Ships|year=1984|publisher=Hippocrene Books|location=New York|isbn=0-88254-979-0}}
* {{cite book|last1=Warner|first1=Denis|last2=Warner|first2=Peggy|title=The Tide at Sunrise: A History of the Russo-Japanese War, 1904–1905|publisher=Frank Cass|location=London|year=2002|edition=2nd|isbn=0-7146-5256-3|lastauthoramp=y}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Iwate (ship, 1901)}}
*{{cite web| last = Nishida| first = Hiroshi| url = http://homepage2.nifty.com/nishidah/e/stc0315.htm | title = Materials of IJN|  work = Imperial Japanese Navy| accessdate = }}

{{Izumo class cruiser}}
{{July 1945 shipwrecks}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Iwate}}
[[Category:Izumo-class cruisers]]
[[Category:Armstrong Whitworth ships]]
[[Category:Tyne-built ships]]
[[Category:1900 ships]]
[[Category:Russo-Japanese War cruisers of Japan]]
[[Category:World War I cruisers of Japan]]
[[Category:Second Sino-Japanese War cruisers]]
[[Category:World War II cruisers of Japan]]
[[Category:Cruisers sunk by aircraft]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks in the Inland Sea]]
[[Category:World War II shipwrecks in the Pacific Ocean]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in July 1945]]
[[Category:Ships sunk by US aircraft]]

[[de:Iwate (1900)]]</text>
      <sha1>e4i38z9zqykhri2sxnqga6a9zb2c22x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
