<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Johnny Williams (rugby player 1882–1916)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18591676</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747891085</id>
      <parentid>747890607</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-05T00:29:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FruitMonkey</username>
        <id>2567040</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28360">{{good article}}
{{About||other people named John, Johnnie or Johnny Williams|John Williams (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{Infobox rugby biography
|                   name = Johnny Williams
|                  image = Johnnie Williams.jpg
|                caption = Williams in Cardiff jersey
|              birth_name = John Lewis Williams
|               nickname =
| birth_date = {{birth date|1882|1|3|df=y}}
|           birth_place = [[Whitchurch, Cardiff|Whitchurch]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wru.wales/eng/matchcentre/squads_wales_player_archive.php?player=26403&amp;includeref=dynamic|title=Welsh Rugby Union|publisher=Welsh Rugby Union}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Wales]]
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1916|7|12|1882|1|3|df=yes}}
|           death_place = [[Mametz, Somme]], [[France]]
|                 height = {{convert|5|ft|8+1/2|in|cm}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Routed&quot; /&gt;
|                 weight = {{convert|11|st|kg}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Routed&quot; /&gt;
|            ru_position = [[Rugby union positions#14. &amp; 11. Wing|Wing]]
|        ru_amateuryears = 
|        ru_amateurclubs = 
|          ru_amclubcaps = 
|        ru_amclubpoints =
| ru_clubyears = {{ubl|1899–1903|1903–1914|1905}}
| ru_proclubs = {{ubl|[[Newport RFC]]|[[Cardiff RFC]]|[[London Welsh RFC]]}}
| ru_clubcaps = {{ubl|?|199&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Teams/Player?personid=101149|title=Jonnie Williams|publisher=Cardiff RFC}}&lt;/ref&gt;|1}}
| ru_clubpoints = {{ubl|?|444| }}
| ru_provinceyears = 1905
| ru_province = [[Glamorgan County RFC]]
| ru_provincecaps = 
| ru_provincepoints = 
|        ru_nationalteam = {{ubl|{{ru|Wales}}|[[British and Irish Lions|Anglo-Welsh]]}}
|       ru_nationalyears = 1906–1911&lt;br /&gt;1908
|        ru_nationalcaps = 17&lt;br /&gt;2
|      ru_nationalpoints = (51)&lt;br /&gt;(0)
|             occupation =
|                 spouse =
|               children =
|              relatives =
|                 school = [[Cowbridge Grammar School]]
|             university =
| module = ----{{infobox military person|embed=yes 
|allegiance = {{UK}} 
|branch = {{Army|UK}}
|serviceyears = 
|rank = Captain
|unit = 
|commands = 
|battles = 
|placeofburial = {{nowrap|Corbie Communal Cemetery Extension}}
|placeofburial_coordinates = 
|mawards = &lt;!-- for military awards - appears as &quot;Awards&quot; if |awards= is not set --&gt; |memorials = }}
}}

'''John Lewis &quot;Johnny&quot; Williams''' (3 January 1882&amp;nbsp;– 12 July 1916) was a [[Wales|Welsh]] international [[Wing (rugby union)|wing]] who played club rugby for [[Cardiff RFC|Cardiff Rugby Football Club]]. A three times [[Triple Crown (rugby union)|Triple Crown]] winner, out of seventeen appearances for Wales he was on the losing side only twice.

Williams began his rugby career professionally with [[Newport RFC]], playing for them from 1899 to 1903. He joined Cardiff RFC after moving to the town, and spent the rest of his career with the team. Shortly after joining Cardiff, he was invited to play for the [[Wales national rugby union team]] in 1906. He continued to represent Wales until 1911 becoming the country's top points scorer. Shortly after retiring, he enlisted in [[World War I]], and was wounded in the [[Battle of the Somme]], dying in France on 12 July 1916.

==Early life==
John Lewis Williams was born the son of Edward Lewis Williams in Llwyncelyn, [[Whitchurch, Cardiff|Whitchurch]], [[Glamorgan]] in 1882. He was educated at [[Cowbridge Grammar School]], where he played [[association football]], rather than rugby.{{sfn|Sewell|1919|pp=228–229}}

==Rugby career==
===Early years===
Having played association football at school, Williams switched to playing rugby with the Whitchurch Village rugby club.&lt;ref name=Cap /&gt; From the start of his career, he played on the left wing.{{sfn|Sewell|1919|p=229}} In 1899, Williams was invited to play at [[Newport RFC]] under the newly appointed captain, [[Llewellyn Lloyd]]. Several players had departed, leaving gaps in the backline, and Williams was brought in, alongside [[Cliff Pritchard]] and W. Isaacs, while the effective pairing of Lloyd and [[Lou Phillips]] at halfback continued. In Williams' first season at Newport, the team scored a total of 416 points compared with the previous season's 192.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyofnewport.co.uk/seasons/seasons.php?id=26|title=History of Newport RFC :: 1874–2013|first=Alun|last=Lee|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following season was Newport's third best on record. However, Williams was injured during the course of the year. Nevertheless, his contributions were noted: against Moseley, despite an early error, he scored a [[try]] in the first quarter &quot;after a grand run&quot;, and at the beginning of the second half, managed to touch down a second try, just before Yates &quot;grassed him&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyofnewport.co.uk/games/games.php?id=000812|title=History of Newport RFC :: 1874–2013|first=Alun|last=Lee|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Moving to Cardiff on business, Williams joined [[Cardiff RFC]], and began a memorable partnership with [[Rhys Gabe]] at left centre, each of them scoring ten tries in their first season, 1903–04.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1141|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1903–1904|publisher=Cardiff RFC}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Sewell|1919|p=229}} The following season, he was the team's top try scorer, with 16 tries to his name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1142|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1904–1905|publisher=Cardiff RFC}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1905–06 season, Cardiff was undefeated except against the [[The Original All Blacks|touring All Blacks]] in December 1905. In the run up to that encounter, Cardiff played [[Blackheath F.C.|Blackheath]] on 9 December. Williams did not play: the Welsh Rugby Union requested that Cardiff field Willie Llewellyn of Pennygraig and Teddy Morgan of London Welsh, who would be representing Wales against New Zealand the following week, alongside Cardiff's centres [[Gwyn Nicholls|Nicholls]] and Gabe. Instead, the same day, Williams took the place of Morgan at [[London Welsh RFC|London Welsh]] against [[Harlequin F.C.|Harlequins]]. Wales won 3–0 against New Zealand, and became the first team in 27 games to beat the tourists. Cardiff then faced the New Zealanders on Boxing Day 1905. Nicholls, Gabe, [[Bert Winfield|Winfield]] and [[Percy Bush|Bush]] had represented Wales against the All Blacks, and it was Nicholls who opened the scoring for Cardiff that day, with Winfield converting. New Zealand levelled the scores 5–5 before the break, and took the lead after it with another converted try. Towards the end, Cardiff scored a try, but Bush was unable to convert, giving the visitors a 10–8 victory.&lt;ref name=Cardiff0506&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1143|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1905–1906|publisher=Cardiff RFC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Williams was again Cardiff's top try scorer for the season, contributing 35 tries,&lt;ref name=Cap /&gt; five of them against the Barbarians in April.&lt;ref name=Cardiff0506/&gt;

===First season for Wales (1906–07)===
By the start of the 1906–07 season, Williams was considered one of the best wings in all of the Home Nations. He was noted for his turn of speed, clever dodging, and determined running for the line. So, when the [[1906–07 South Africa rugby union tour|touring team]] from {{nrut|South Africa}} travelled to Swansea, and [[Billy Trew]] was unavailable due to injury, Williams earned his first cap for {{nrut|Wales}} on 1 December 1906.&lt;ref name=Cap&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4170334|title=The New Welsh Cap|newspaper=Evening Express|date=1 December 1906|accessdate=8 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wales lost the game, the first defeat at home in 11 years, outclassed in every part of the game. In the backline, the Springboks were quicker and combined well in attack. Williams &quot;justified his selection&quot; but was not reckoned to be in the same class as Morgan, who was shifted to the right wing from his usual position on the left, and under-utilised there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4170353|title=Greyness Come|newspaper=Evening Express|date=3 December 1906|accessdate=9 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A month later, on 1 January 1907, Cardiff played hosts to the South Africans and beat the visitors 17–0 in front of 30,000 spectators. Heavy rain turned the ground into a &quot;quagmire&quot;, and a strong wind blew from one end to the other. Cardiff won the toss and opted to play with the wind. Williams' first touch of the ball was erratic, failing to hold on to a catch in the initial stages, when he had a clear run to the tryline. After Cardiff had scored two tries in the first half with no response from the Springboks, Williams had another chance to score, but again fumbled the ball. At half time, Cardiff was leading by 11 points, already the largest score against the South Africans in any of the tour matches. Well into the second half, Williams received a pass from [[Rhys Gabe]]. Between him and the tryline was Marsberg, the opposition fullback, and &quot;one of the most magnificent tacklers&quot; to have played in Wales.&lt;ref name=CBW/&gt; Williams approached Marsberg and, with a swerving run, &quot;diddled&quot; him, and scored a try in the corner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4171339|title=Cardiff Does The Trick|newspaper=Evening Express|date=1 January 1907|accessdate=8 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marsberg then ran up to him and shook him by the hand in recognition of the move.&lt;ref name=CBW&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4171375|title=Cardiff's Big Win|newspaper=Evening Express|date=2 January 1907|accessdate=8 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; The contemporary rugby journalist [[E. H. D. Sewell]] commented that the try he scored &quot;against the South Africans for Cardiff will never be forgotten by those that witnessed it.&quot;{{sfn|Sewell|1919|p=229}}

Williams was then confirmed to play against England at Swansea on 12 January in a team much changed from that which was beaten by South Africa the previous month.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4171460|title=Changes in Welsh Team|newspaper=Evening Express|date=4 January 1907|accessdate=8 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; The London ''Express'' commented that neither he nor [[Hopkin Maddock|Maddock]] on the other wing, had much merit, but were selected for a lack of choice, the whole team being unexceptional.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4171604|title=Wales v England|newspaper=Evening Express|date=9 January 1907|accessdate=8 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; Welsh spectators, expecting defeat at the hands of the English, stayed away from the game, and only 5,000 turned out, a record low for international rugby in Wales. But the headline in the 'Pink Edition' of the ''Evening Express'' read &quot;St George Routed&quot;, as Wales beat England 22–0. Right from the start, the Welshmen seemed up to the task. An early try-scoring opportunity was lost when Gabe was tackled and unable to make the pass to Williams, who was in the clear. Wales came close to scoring a few more times, until Gabe receiving the ball from Trew, timed his pass perfectly to Williams, and he scored in the corner. Most of the play till this point had been in England's 25, but when the English broke out, Williams' defensive play was called into action. At half time, with further tries from [[Reggie Gibbs|Gibbs]] and Maddock, the Welsh were leading 13–0. England started the second half well but, after a long period in the Welsh half, Wales got an attacking opportunity, and Gabe, receiving the ball from Trew, beat his opposite number, and passed to Williams, who scored a second try in the corner. Maddock and Brown then scored two more tries, for a total of six to Wales.&lt;ref name=Routed&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4171744|title=St George Routed|newspaper=Evening Express|date=12 January 1907|accessdate=8 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next game, away to Scotland on 2 February, resulted in defeat for Wales, with the seven forwards system receiving much of the blame. The Williams–Gabe combination performed well on the left wing, but the Welshmen were unable to cross their opponents' line.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4172589|title=Critics and the Match|newspaper=Evening Express|date=4 February 1907|accessdate=9 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; Against Ireland at Cardiff Arms Park on 9 March, Wales fielded a team including eight Cardiffians. Gabe was appointed captain for the match, while Billy Trew - the former captain - and Dicky Jones, were replaced at halfback by Percy Bush, Cardiff's captain, and Dicky David, also from Cardiff and earning his first - and only&lt;ref&gt;{{Scrum|id=1884|name=Richard Jenkin David}}&lt;/ref&gt; - cap for Wales.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4173941|title=International Gossip|newspaper=Evening Express|date=9 March 1907|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4173941|title=The New Welsh Caps|newspaper=Evening Express|date=9 March 1907|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wales beat Ireland 29–0, and 26 of the points came from Cardiff players.&lt;ref name=Cardiff0607/&gt; In the first four minutes of the game, the Welshmen reached the Irish 25. Following a scrum, the ball reached Gabe, and he, after making some ground, passed to Williams, who ran in a try unopposed. Early in the second half, with Wales leading by two tries to nil, a lineout to Wales on the Irish 25, resulted in Williams receiving the ball and, after breaking through the Irish defence, with only Hinton, the fullback, to beat, passed to Gabe to score the try. Williams scored a second try after David, receiving the ball from the forwards, passed to Bush, who got past the Irish halfbacks, and passed to Gabe, missing out Evans. Gabe then ran up to Hinton, and passed the ball to Williams to score. A third try came for Williams in similar style, and he came close to scoring a fourth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4173941 | title=Irishmen Routed | publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce | date=9 March 1907 | accessdate=10 June 2016 | newspaper=Evening Express}}&lt;/ref&gt; The David–Bush halfback pairing, and the Gabe–Williams partnership on the left wing, supported by the excellent play of Winfield at fullback, and that of the forwards, were the decisive factors in the Welsh triumph over Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4173942|title=How Bush and David Played Today|newspaper=Evening Express|date=9 March 1907|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Williams was again Cardiff's top try scorer in 1906–07, touching down 19 times in the season.&lt;ref name=Cardiff0607&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1144|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1906 - 1907 - Cardiff RFC|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Unbeaten seasons (1907–1909)===
[[File:1908 Anglo-Welsh rugby team - cropped.jpg|thumb|1908 Anglo-Welsh rugby team - cropped|The 1908 Anglo-Welsh touring party]]

Wales was unbeaten in 1908 and 1909.{{sfn|Sewell|1919|p=229}} At the end of the 1907–08 season, in which Williams was again top try scorer for Cardiff with 13 tries,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1145|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1907 - 1908 - Cardiff RFC|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Williams was part of [[Arthur Harding]]'s Anglo-Welsh team that toured the [[1908 British Lions tour to New Zealand and Australia|Antipodes]]. Although an unsuccessful tour, he played well and ended as the team's top try scorer.{{sfn|Thomas|1979|p=46}} He then missed the start of the 1908–09 season and did not return to Cardiff until November. The club faced Australia on 28 December 1908, and handed the tourists the biggest defeat of their tour, 24–8, Williams providing two tries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cardiff190809&quot;/&gt; Cardiff finished the season as Welsh Champions, Williams having scored 15 tries in 26 appearances, to [[Billy Spiller|Spiller]]'s 16 in 27.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cardiff190809&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1146|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1908 - 1909 - Cardiff RFC|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final years (1909–1911)===
Williams was captain of Cardiff in 1909–10, winning 22 out of 36 games, with 7 drawn.&lt;ref name=Cardiff0910/&gt; Williams was not the top try scorer that season for Cardiff, managing 13, compared with 21 from Gibbs and 14 from Spiller.&lt;ref name=Cardiff0910&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1147|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1909–1910|publisher=Cardiff RFC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 January 1910, Williams played for Cardiff against Bristol,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4212929|title=Tomorrows Football|newspaper=Evening Express|date=1909-12-31|accessdate=2016-06-10|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Maddocks played on the wing for Wales against France.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/3418483|title=Welsh Rugby Football|newspaper=The Cambrian|date=31 December 1909|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=T. Jenkins}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the match against England on 15 January, Williams was called up as a reserve.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4213175|title=Changes in Welsh Team|newspaper=Evening Express|date=6 January 1910|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in a game for Cardiff against Moseley, he picked up an injury to his thigh that would necessitate a few weeks out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4213508|title=International Rugby|newspaper=Evening Express|date=14 January 1910|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the England game, which Wales lost, it was rumoured that Williams would be recalled to the wing for the match against Scotland,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4213638|title=Football|newspaper=Evening Express|date=18 January 1910|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; but his injury persisted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4214024|title=Changes in Welsh Team|newspaper=Evening Express|date=1910-01-27|accessdate=2016-06-10|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Welsh defeated Scotland, and it was expected that they would field unchanged team for the final game of the tournament, against Ireland at Lansdowne Road on 12 March. Melville Baker, however, was injured playing on the left wing and opened up a place for Williams to be selected. Once again the Welsh backline was filled with Cardiff men: Bush, Spiller, Dyke, Gibbs, who took on the captain's duties, and Williams. Joe Pugsley, another Cardiff man, was in the Welsh pack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4215379|title=Wales v Ireland|newspaper=Evening Express|date=3 March 1910|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ireland were leading by a try until just before half time, when Williams scored a try to bring Wales level. In the second half, he scored two more; Gibbs and Dyke each scored one, while Bush kicked a dropgoal, to win the game 3–19. &quot;Forward&quot; writing in the ''Evening Express'' said: &quot;Williams was right on top of his form, and his cleverness in beating three or four Irishmen, including the fullback, before he scored his three tries was really splendid.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4215818|title=The International|newspaper=Evening Express|date=14 March 1910|accessdate=10 June 2016|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- 
Williams was writing weekly column for the ''Evening Express''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4213277|title=IREFEREEINGUHBERDIFFICULTIES - Evening Express|date=1910-01-08|accessdate=2016-06-10|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10107/4213566|title=TOPROMOTEEFFICIENCY - Evening Express|date=1910-01-15|accessdate=2016-06-10|publisher=Walter Alfred Pearce}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

The following season, however, with Gibbs as captain, Williams scored 27 tries, 8 of them split equally across two games against Moseley.&lt;ref name=Cardiff1011&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardiffrfc.com/Page/Content/1148|title=Cardiff RFC Season Review 1910–1911|publisher=Cardiff RFC}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Williams, who could speak French, skippered Wales against France.&lt;ref name=Cardiff0910/&gt; Williams retired from playing at the end of the 1910–11 season.&lt;ref name=Cardiff1011/&gt;

Williams was part of three Welsh [[Triple Crown (rugby union)|Triple Crown]] winning sides, lost only two matches and scored 17 tries in his 17 games.{{sfn|McCrery|2014}}

===International matches played===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Opposition
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Score 
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Result 
! scope=&quot;col&quot;|Date 
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Venue
!scope=&quot;col&quot; class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | {{abbr|Ref(s)|Reference(s)}}
|-
|{{ru|RSA}}||align=&quot;center&quot;| 0–11||Lost ||align=right|1 December 1906 ||Swansea ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19093.html|title=Wales v South Africa|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|ENG}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|22–0 ||Won ||align=right|12 January 1907 ||Swansea ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19096.html|title=Wales v England|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|SCO}}||align=&quot;center&quot;| 6–3||Lost ||align=right|2 February 1907 ||Inverleith ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19097.html|title=Scotland v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|IRE}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|29–0 ||Won ||align=right|9 March 1907 ||Cardiff ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19100.html|title=Wales v Ireland|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|ENG}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|18–28 ||Won ||align=right|18 January 1908 ||Bristol ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19106.html|title=England v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|SCO}}||align=&quot;center&quot;| 6–5|| Won||align=right|1 February 1908 ||Swansea ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19107.html|title=Wales v Scotland|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|IRE}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|5–11 ||Won ||align=right|14 March 1908 ||Belfast ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19111.html|title=Ireland v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|AUS}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|9–6 || Won||align=right| 12 December 1908||Cardiff ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19116.html|title=Wales v Australia|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|ENG}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|8–0 ||Won ||align=right| 16 January 1909||Cardiff ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19118.html|title=Wales v England|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|SCO}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|3–5 ||Won ||align=right|6 February 1909 ||Inverleith ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19120.html|title=Scotland v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|FRA}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|5–47 ||Won ||align=right|23 February 1909 ||Colombes ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19122.html|title=France v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|IRE}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|18–5 ||Won ||align=right|13 March 1909 ||Swansea ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19124.html|title=Wales v Ireland|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|IRE}}||align=&quot;center&quot;| 3–19||Won ||align=right|12 March 1910 || Lansdowne Road||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19134.html|title=Ireland v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|ENG}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|15–11 ||Won ||align=right|21 January 1911 ||Swansea ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19145.html|title=Wales v England|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|SCO}}||align=&quot;center&quot;| 10–32||Won ||align=right|4 February 1911 ||Inverleith ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19147.html|title=Scotland v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|FRA}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|0–15 ||Won ||align=right|28 February 1911 ||Parc des Princes ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19150.html|title=France v Wales|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{ru|IRE}}||align=&quot;center&quot;|16–0 ||Won ||align=right|11 March 1911 ||Cardiff ||&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.espn.co.uk/statsguru/rugby/match/19151.html|title=Wales v Ireland|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Military service==
Williams fought for his country in the [[World War I|First World War]]. He joined the Royal Fusiliers on 24 September 1914, and was then commissioned second lieutenant into the 16th Battalion Welsh Regiment in December. He was promoted to lieutenant in February 1915, and to captain the following month.{{sfn|Sewell|1919|pp=229–230}} His Regiment, part of the [[38th (Welsh) Infantry Division]], was deployed to the [[Western Front (WWI)|Western Front]] in December 1915, and took part in the [[Battle of the Somme]], which began on 1 July 1916. The 38th Division was brought into action, when it relieved the 7th Division on 5 July to the south of Mametz Wood.{{sfn|Miles|1938|p=21}} On 7 July, the 38th attacked German positions in Mametz Wood.{{sfn|Miles|1938|pp=29–32}} Williams was leading his men in the attack when he was wounded.{{sfn|Sewell|1919|p=230}} He was evacuated but eventually died of his wounds on 12 July at No. 5 [[Casualty Clearing Station]].{{sfn|Sewell|1919|p=228}}

He is buried in Corbie Communal Cemetery Extension, near Amiens, France. He was married to Mabel.&lt;ref name=CWGC&gt;{{CWGC|id=22041|name=WILLIAMS, JOHN LEWIS}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of international rugby union players killed in action during the First World War]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
*{{cite book|last1=McCrery|first1=Nigel|title=Into Touch: Rugby Internationals Killed in the Great War|date=2014|publisher=Pen and Sword|isbn=1-4738-3321-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |series=History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence|title=Military Operations France and Belgium, 1916, 2nd July 1916 to the End of the Battles of the Somme |volume=II |last=Miles |first=W.|year=1992 |orig-year=1938 |publisher=Macmillan |location=London |edition=Imperial War Museum &amp; Battery Press |isbn=0-901627-76-3|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Sewell|first1=Edward Humphrey Dalrymple|authorlink=E. H. D. Sewell|title=The Rugby Football Internationals Roll of Honour|date=1919|publisher=T. C. &amp; E. C. Jack|location=London, Edinburgh|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Smith |first=David |author2=Williams, Gareth  |title=Fields of Praise: The Official History of The Welsh Rugby Union |year=1980 |publisher=University of Wales Press |location=Cardiff |isbn=0-7083-0766-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Thomas |first=Wayne |title=A Century of Welsh Rugby Players |year=1979 |publisher=Ansells Ltd|location= |isbn=|ref=harv}}

==External links==
*{{Scrum|id=1848|name=Johnny Williams}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-sports|ruc}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Cardiff RFC|Cardiff RFC Captain]]|before= [[Percy Bush]] |after=[[Reggie Gibbs]]||years=1909–1910}}
{{S-end}}

{{British and Irish Lions 1908}}
{{WWI Welsh rugby fatalities}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Williams, Johnnie}}
[[Category:Rugby union players from Cardiff]]
[[Category:Welsh rugby union players]]
[[Category:Wales international rugby union players]]
[[Category:Rugby union wings]]
[[Category:1882 births]]
[[Category:1916 deaths]]
[[Category:Wales rugby union captains]]
[[Category:Cardiff RFC players]]
[[Category:Newport RFC players]]
[[Category:London Welsh RFC players]]
[[Category:British military personnel killed at the Battle of the Somme]]
[[Category:Glamorgan County RFC players]]</text>
      <sha1>beor4ffoo2uz0v2th0p1qojsj1cxuxy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
