<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Kaga ikki</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47782591</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733645634</id>
      <parentid>733626184</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-09T06:01:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Legobot</username>
        <id>7304691</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Adding Good Article icon</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23795">{{good article}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:Kaga ''ikki''}}
{{Infobox former country
|conventional_long_name = Kaga ''ikki''
|common_name = The Peasants' Kingdom
|status                 = Confederation
|empire                 = Ikkō-ikki
|status_text            = Confederation of the [[Ikkō-ikki]]
|government_type        = [[Feudalism|Feudal]] [[theocracy|theocratic]] [[militarism|military]] [[confederation]]
|continent              = Asia
|region                 = East Asia
|country                = Japan
|era                    = [[Sengoku period|Sengoku]]
|event_start            = [[Kaga Rebellion]]
|year_start             = 1488
|event_end              = Final resistance in Kaga defeated
|year_end               = 1582
|event1                 = Kaga civil war
|date_event1            = 1531
|event2                 = Establishment of Kanazawa Midō
|date_event2            = 1546
|event3                 = Beginning of [[Ishiyama Hongan-ji War]]
|date_event3            = 1570
|event4                 = [[Oda Nobunaga]] defeats the major opposition in Kaga
|date_event4            = 1575
|event5                 = Oyama Gobo captured; End of Ishiyama Hongan-ji War
|date_event5            = 1580
|event_pre              = Togashi civil war
|date_pre               = 1473
|event_post             = [[Maeda Toshiie]] conquers [[Kanazawa]]
|date_post              = 1583
|p1                     = Togashi clan
|s1                     = Oda clan
|image_s1               = [[File:Mon-Oda.png|20px]]
|s2                     = Maeda clan
|s3                     = Toyotomi clan
|image_s3               = [[File:Goshichi no kiri inverted.svg|20px]]
|image_map              = Provinces of Japan-Kaga.svg
|image_map_caption      = Location of Kaga Province in Japan
|capital                = Oyama Gobo ([[Kanazawa]]) &lt;small&gt;(1546–1580)&lt;/small&gt;
|common_languages       = [[Late Middle Japanese]]
|religion               = [[Jōdo Shinshū]] • [[Shinto]]
|leader1                = [[Rennyo]]
|leader2                = Jitsunyo
|leader3                = Shonyo
|leader4                = [[Kōsa|Kennyo]]
|year_leader1           = 1457–1499
|year_leader2           = 1499–1525
|year_leader3           = 1525–1554
|year_leader4           = 1560–1592
|title_leader           = ''[[Monshu]]''
|title_deputy           = ''[[Shugo]]''
|deputy1                = Togashi Yasakuta
|deputy2                = Togashi Taneyasu
|year_deputy1           = 1488–1504
|year_deputy2           = 1504–1531
|legislature            = Kanazawa Midō
|house1                 = ''[[Hatamoto]]''
|house2                 = ''Kumi''
|type_house1            = District commanders
|type_house2            = Group members
|currency = [[Japanese mon (currency)|mon]], [[ryō]]
|today= {{Flag|Japan}}
}}

The '''Kaga ''ikki''''', also known as '''The Peasants' Kingdom''', was a [[theocracy|theocratic]] [[feudalism|feudal]] [[Confederation|confederacy]] that emerged in [[Kaga Province]] (present-day southern [[Ishikawa Prefecture]]), Japan, during the late 15th and early 16th centuries. The Kaga ''ikki'' was a faction of the [[Ikkō-ikki]], mobs of peasant farmers, monks, priests, and [[ji-samurai]] (lesser nobles) that espoused belief in [[Jōdo Shinshū]] Buddhism. Though nominally under the authority of the [[Hongan-ji]] head abbot, the [[Monshu]], the Ikkō-ikki proved difficult to control. During the [[Ōnin War]], the ''ikki'' in Kaga, with the approval of the Monshu [[Rennyo]], helped restore [[Togashi Masachika]] to the position of ''[[shugo]]'' (military governor). However, by 1474 the ''ikki'' fell into conflict with Masachika, and in late 1487, they launched the [[Kaga Rebellion]]. Masachika was overthrown, and Togashi Yasatuka, his uncle, took his place as ''shugo''. Under Yasatuka's son, Taneyasu, the Kaga ''ikki'' asserted more and more influence over the provincial government. In 1531 a civil war erupted as two factions within the Kaga ''ikki'' vied for control. Renjun, a son of Rennyo, won the war, abolished the position of ''shugo'', exiled Taneyasu, and established a much tighter Hongan-ji hegemony over the province. In 1546, the Kanazawa Midō was established as a governing body in Oyama Gobo, which would eventually grow into the present-day city of [[Kanazawa]]. The Midō oversaw very loosely organized committees of select warlords and priests, who in turn ruled over the local lords and village leaders. The Kaga ''ikki'' controlled Kaga until they were overrun by the forces of [[Oda Nobunaga]] in a series of campaigns lasting from 1573 to 1582.

==History==

===Emergence of the ''ikki'' in Kaga===

====Rise of the Ikkō-ikki====
{{Main article|Ikkō-ikki}}

Throughout the 15th century in Japan, [[peasant revolt]]s, known as ''ikki'', increased in frequency. With the breakout of the Ōnin War in 1467 and resultant chaos, they became even more commonplace. Many of the rebels embraced a militant offshoot of Jōdo Shinshū Buddhism known as [[Ikkō-shū]]. The religious leader Rennyo, eighth Monshu of the Hongan-ji school of Shinshū, tried to distance himself from Ikkō-shū, but attracted many converts from the sect, to the point where Ikkō-shū became synonymous with Jōdo Shinshū.{{Sfn|Dobbins|2002|pp = 110–111}} Due to the violent tendencies of the Ikkō-shū adherents, they became known as Ikkō-ikki, literally &quot;Ikkō-shū riots&quot; or &quot;Ikkō-shū league&quot;.{{Sfn|Banzai|1973|p = 29}}{{Sfn|Turnbull|2012|p = 2}} In 1471, Rennyo relocated from [[Kyoto]] to [[Yoshizaki-gobō|Yoshizaki]] in [[Echizen Province]].{{Sfn|Turnbull|2012|p = 29}}{{Sfn|Bloom|2006|p = 168}} Rennyo had attracted his largest following in Echizen and the bordering Kaga Province, a following which included not only peasants but ji-samurai, or kokujin, the lesser nobility.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 240}}

====Togashi civil war====
In Kaga, a civil war had broken out between Togashi Masachika and Kochiyo Masachika for control of the position of ''shugo'' over the province. Kochiyo was victorious against his brother and drove him out of Kaga. When the Ōnin War began in 1467, Masachika sided with the [[Hosokawa clan]], while Kochiyo sided with the [[Yamana clan|Yamana]].{{Sfn|Turnbull|2005a|p = 42}} Kochiyo also patronized Takada school of Jōdo Shinshū, a fierce rival of the Hongan-ji school of which Rennyo was head.{{Sfn|Solomon|1996|p = 414}} Masachika, seeking to reclaim his land, reached out to the Ikkō-ikki and asked for their support.{{sfn|Davis|1988|p = 239}} In exchange, he promised to end their religious persecution and lift them out of poverty.{{sfn|Davis|1988|p = 239}} The priests in Yoshizaki agreed to aid Masachika, and Rennyo, though alarmed by the rebellious attitude of the rebels, tacitly rendered his support as well.{{Sfn|Solomon|1996|p = 414}}{{sfn|Weinstein|1977|p = 355}} [[Asakura Toshikage]], the ruler of Echizen and ally of the Hosokawa, also lent his support.{{sfn|Weinstein|1977|p = 355}} Kochiyo was defeated, and Masachika restored to power.{{sfn|Davis|1988|p = 239}}{{sfn|Weinstein|1977|p = 355}}

===Kaga Rebellion===
{{Main article|Kaga Rebellion}}

Despite having aided Togashi Masachika in his return to power, within a year the Ikkō-ikki of Kaga fell into conflict with him. Claiming that he failed to adequately deliver on his promises of economic reward, the Ikkō-ikki of Kaga revolted in 1474.{{sfn|Davis|1988|p = 239}} Rennyo refused to support these rebellions, and the Ikkō-ikki were quickly defeated and forced to take refuge in neighboring [[Etchū Province|Etchū]].{{Sfn|Solomon|1996|p = 415-416}}{{sfn|Weinstein|1977|p = 356}}{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 239-240}} Shimotsuma Rensu, a ji-samurai from Echizen and an advisor to Rennyo, led another revolt, falsely claiming that Rennyo authorized his actions.{{Sfn|Solomon|1996|p = 416}}{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 240}} This revolt also failed, and Rennyo excommunicated Rensu.{{Sfn|Solomon|1996|p = 416}}{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 240}}

Though the early revolts in Kaga failed, unrest continued in the province, as the Ikkō-ikki would refuse to pay taxes and even seize tax revenues and land, despite Rennyo's admonitions of submission to the authorities.{{Sfn|Solomon|1996|p = 416}} In 1487, possibly in an effort to secure a favor in the form of military aid, Masachika responded to ''[[shogun]]'' [[Ashikaga Yoshihisa]]'s call for military aid against Rokkaku Tokoyori in [[Ōmi Province]].{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 241}} In Masachika's absence, the Ikkō-ikki launched a massive revolt, their forces numbering between one hundred thousand and two hundred thousand.{{Sfn|Blum|2008|p = 161}} Though Masachika quickly returned, the rebels, aided by several disgruntled former vassal families and nobility, overwhelmed him and trapped him in his castle, where he committed ''[[seppuku]]''.

To replace Masachika as a ''shugo'', the vassal families which opposed Masachika put forward his uncle, Yasakuta, who had previously been a ''shugo'' of the province.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 241}} Ashikaga Yoshihisa was enraged by the rebellion and ordered Rennyo to excommunicate his followers in Kaga. However, [[Hosokawa Katsumoto]], a personal friend and ally of Rennyo, brokered a deal which allowed Rennyo to merely reprimand the Kaga ''ikki''.{{Sfn|Blum|2008|pp = 161–162}}{{Sfn|Solomon|1996|p = 417}}

=== Rule under Togashi Yasakuta and Taneyasu ===
After the overthrow of Togashi Masachika, Kaga became known as &quot;the kingdom of peasants&quot; and &quot;''hyakusho no motaru kuni'' &quot; (&quot;province ruled by peasants&quot;).{{Sfn|Suehiro|2013|p = 92}}{{Sfn|Turnbull|2006|p = 79}} However, the Kaga ''ikki'' were content to live under the rule of Masachika's uncle, Yasakuta. When, in 1493, [[Hosokawa Masamoto]] deposed ''shogun'' [[Ashikaga Yoshitane]], Yasakuta and Yoshitane fled to Kaga. Yasakuta then led several campaigns in an effort to restore the ''shogun'', including two invasions of Echizen: one in 1494 and another in 1504. None of these campaigns featured ''ikki'' participation.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 242}} However, after Yasakuta's death, the ''ikki'' asserted more control. They initiated two invasions, one in Etchū in 1506, and one in Echizen in 1508, both in support of ''ikki'' rebellions within those respective provinces.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 242}} By the 1520s, the Kaga ''ikki'' had become the primary governmental faction within Kaga.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|pp = 241–242}}

===Kaga civil war===
In 1531, the ''ikki'' control of Kaga was of such dominance that a conflict for leadership within the Hongan-ji embroiled the province in a civil war, often called the ''Daishō-Ikki'', or Big League-Little League, war.{{Sfn|de Bary|Keene|Tanabe|Varley|2010|p = 434}} A faction led by Renjun, a son of Rennyo, came to power in the Hongan-ji, and was hostile to the three main Kaga temples. In the resultant war, the three Kaga temples were backed by the Togashi clan, other powerful vassals, local Hongan-ji priests, and the ''ikki'' based in Echizen.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 242}}{{Sfn||Turnbull|2012|p = 16}} Renjun was backed by many of the smaller temples and emerged victorious from the conflict when he brought in an Ikkō-Ikki army from [[Mikawa Province]]. Togashi Taneyasu was exiled, as were the other opposition leaders, and the position of ''shugo'' abolished.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|pp = 242–243}}

===Rule from Oyama Gobo===
In the year immediately after the civil war, 1532, Rennyo led the Ikkō-''ikki'' in a campaign to aid [[Hosokawa Harumoto]] against Miyoshi Motonaga.{{sfn|Berry|1997|p = 149}} During that conflict, the Hongan-ji headquarters at [[Yamashina Mido|Yamashina]] was burned down, and Rennyo established a new city in [[Settsu Province]] called [[Ishiyama Hongan-ji]], the predecessor to modern-day [[Osaka]].{{Sfn|de Bary|Keene|Tanabe|Varley|2010|p = 434}} Due to the Kaga civil war and its aftermath, the Hongan-ji acquired large amounts of land in Kaga and thus exerted a powerful economic influence over the region.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 243}} To manage its increased responsibilities, the Hongan-ji established the Kanazawa Midō, based in the city of Oyama Gobo, in 1546, to oversee Kaga's affairs from then onward.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 243}} Oyama Gobo quickly grew to a population of 3,000–5,000, establishing the beginnings of what would become the present-day city of Kanazawa.{{Sfn||Turnbull|2012|p = 11}}{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 243}} Under the Midō, control of the province was centralized, to the point that rule under it resembled the rule of the daimyos elsewhere in Japan.{{Sfn||Turnbull|2012|p = 11}}

===Conquest by Oda Nobunaga===
In 1570, ''[[daimyo]]'' Oda Nobunaga began a [[Ishiyama Hongan-ji War|campaign against the Ikkō-ikki]], besieging the Hongan-ji headquarters at Ishiyama Hongan-ji and attacking ''ikki'' strongholds throughout Japan. By 1573, forces led by [[Akechi Mitsuhide]] and [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]] pushed through Echizen and into the southern portions of Kaga.{{Sfn|Turnbull|2012|p = 13}} A counter-attack by the Kaga ''ikki'' in 1574 halted this advance, causing Nobunaga to personally lead the assault into Kaga.{{Sfn|Turnbull|2012|pp = 13–14}} In 1575, Nobunaga recaptured Echizen, and Mitsuhide and Hideyoshi again invaded Kaga, this time more rapidly, successively capturing the fortified temples of Daishōji, Hinoya, and Sakumi.{{Sfn|Turnbull|2012|p = 14}} By the end of the year, the southern half of Kaga was conquered, and in November of that year Nobunaga boasted to [[Date Terumune]] that he had &quot;wiped out several tens of thousands of the villainous rabble in Echizen and Kaga.&quot;{{Sfn|Turnbull|2012|p = 14}}

Nobunaga granted Echizen to his general [[Shibata Katsuie]], and in 1576 Katsuie's nephew [[Sakuma Morimasa]] penetrated deeper into Kaga, capturing [[Kaga, Ishikawa|Miyukizuka]]. In 1580, Morimasa destroyed the capital, Oyama Gobo.{{Sfn|Turnbull|2012|p = 14}} The same year, Ishiyama Hongan-ji surrendered. Despite the resistance of the Ikkō-Ikki being effectively suppressed, a few Kaga ''ikki'' fled the plains and entrenched themselves in the mountains at the fortified temples Torigoe and Futoge.{{Sfn|Turnbull|2005b|p = 41}} Shibata Katsuie captured these strongholds in 1581, but the garrisons he established were over-run and the temples recaptured. Still in the year 1581, Katsuie and Sakuma Morimasa again recaptured the temples, killing all the Ikkō-ikki at the sites.{{Sfn|Turnbull|2005b|pp = 41–42}} Despite this, in 1582, resistance elements again recaptured Torigoe and Futoge. A third attack was mounted by Morimasa, and this time the final resistance elements were eliminated, ending the last vestiges of ''ikki'' rule in Kaga.{{Sfn|Turnbull|2005b|p = 42}}

==Governance==
The government structure of the Kaga ''ikki'' evolved over time. After the 1488 revolt, Togashi Masachika's uncle Togashi Yasakuta ruled as ''shugo'', and little changed in the [[Decentralization|decentralized]], feudalist structure of Kaga. Along with Yasakuta, several different factions also controlled Kaga. Three sons of Rennyo; Rengo, Renkō, and Rensei, headed the three Hongan-ji temples and led the ''ikki'' faction. Several former Masachika vassals, including the Mootori and Yamagawa, also held power. Historian David L. Davis explains that although 1488 is the conventional date given for the beginning of ''Ikki'' control in Kaga, it was only under Togashi Yasakuta's son Taneyasu that the ''ikki'' began asserting control over the government, becoming the dominant faction in the 1520s. He cites court documents from Kyoto to support his assertion: Until 1504 (when Yasakuta died), the ''shogun'' and ''[[shōen]]'' considered Yasakuta the legitimate government; from 1504 to 1521, they were uncertain, and after 1521 they would send legal papers to the Hongan-ji office immediately outside of Kyoto.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 242}} Likewise, military expeditions were initiated by Yasakuta during his tenure. For instance, he made several attempts to restore Ashikaga Yoshitane to power, which included two invasions of Echizen, in 1494 and 1504, respectively. However, after Yasatuka's death, the ''ikki'' in Kaga launched an invasion of Etchū in 1506 and Echizen in 1508, both times in support of ''ikki'' rebellions in those respective provinces, and both times without any contributions from the old vassal families.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 242}}

In 1531, Renjun, a son of Rennyo, emerged victorious in the Kaga civil war and established a much tighter Hongan-ji hegemony over the province. The leaders of the opposition, including Togashi Taneyasu, where expelled from Kaga, though those who supported them were allowed to return.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|pp = 242–243}} Without any central governing body, Kaga was consumed by political instability. The [[Asakura clan]] to the south and [[Uesugi clan|Uesugi]] to the north posed threats of invasion for Kaga, so the ji-samurai established a centralized authority at the Kanazawa Midō in Oyama Gobo.{{sfn|Davis|1988|p = 245}} The Midō oversaw four district organizations of ''[[hatamoto]]'' – prominent local warlords. Each ''hatamoto'' commanded a group, ''kumi'', of which there were roughly twenty in total. These ''kumi'' in turn ruled over regional groups of local warriors, priests, and the heads of village communes.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 243}} The highest political organization of the ''ikki'' in Kaga was a committee of ''hatamoto'', and the only permanent political body were the twenty ''kumi''. Important matters would be settled at the meetings of the local ''hatamoto'' in consultation with the local Hongan-ji priests. However, these meetings were sporadic and held at the county, rather than provincial, level, and thus, according to Davis, would probably rarely have involved more than five ''hatamoto'' and one or two Hongan-ji priests.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 245}} ''Kumi'' meetings were probably similar, with the exception that a ''hatamoto'' present at a ''kumi'' meeting would have held great respect.{{Sfn|Davis|1988|p = 245}}

==References==

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Works cited ===
*{{Cite book|title = A Pilgrimage to the 88 Temples in Shikoku Island|last = Banzai|first = Mayumi|publisher = [[Kodansha]]|year = 1973|isbn = |location = Tokyo|pages = |oclc = 969829|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=J1fYAAAAMAAJ|ref = harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Berry|first1=Mary Elizabeth|title=The Culture of Civil War in Kyoto|date=1997|publisher=[[University of California Press]]|location=Berkeley, California|isbn=9780520919037|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z6wudj2tvwUC&amp;pg=PA149#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Bloom|first1=Alfred|authorlink1=Alfred Bloom (Buddhist)|editor1-last=Blum|editor1-first=Mark L.|editor2-last=Yasutomi|editor2-first=Shin'ya|title=Rennyo and the Renaissance of Contemporary Shin Buddhism|journal=Rennyo and the Roots of Modern Japanese Buddhism|date=2006|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dFMSDAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|pages=164-172|publisher=Oxford University|location=New York|isbn=9780195132755|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite journal|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=BYKIANRPXagC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title = Collective Suicide at the Funeral of Jitsunyo: Mimesis or Solidarity?|last = Blum|first = Mark L.|date = 2008|journal = Death and the Afterlife in Japanese Buddhism|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |publisher = [[University of Hawaii Press]]|editor-last = Stone|editor-first = Jacqueline Ilyse|location = Honolulu|pages = 137–174|editor2-last = Walter|editor2-first = Mariko Namba|isbn = 9780824832049|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite journal|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=J-tO9pOjzmsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title = ''Ikki'' in Late Medieval Japan|last = Davis|first = David L.|date = 1988|journal = Medieval Japan: Essays in Institutional History|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |publisher = [[Stanford University Press]]|pages = 221–247|location = Stanford|editor-last = Hall|editor-first = John W.|editor2-last = Mass|editor2-first = Jeffrey P.|ref = harv|isbn = 9780804715119|editor-link = John Whitney Hall}}
*{{cite book|last1=de Bary|first1=Wm. Theodore|last2=Keene|first2=Donald|last3=Tanabe|first3=George|last4=Varley|first4=Paul|authorlink1=Wm Theodore de Bary|authorlink2=Donald Keene|title=Sources of Japanese Tradition: Volume 1: From Earliest Times to 1600|date=2010|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|location=New York|isbn=9780231518055|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aWxN1Fq_ueoC&amp;pg=PA434#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|title = Jōdo Shinshū: Shin Buddhism in Medieval Japan|last = Dobbins|first = James C.|publisher = [[University of Hawaii Press]]|year = 2002|isbn = 9780824826208|location = Honolulu|pages = |author-link = James C. Dobbins|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Xb3BImNUdRAC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite journal|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=tztMqPBReAYC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title = Hoganji under Rennyo: The Development of Shinshū in Medieval Japan|last = Solomon|first = Michael|date = 1996|journal = The Pure Land Tradition: History and Development|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |publisher = Jain Publishing Company|location = Fremont, California|editor-last = Foard|editor-first = James Harlan|pages = 399–428|isbn = 9780895810922|editor2-last = Solomon|editor2-first = Michael|editor3-last = Payne|editor3-first = Richard Karl|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|title = An Introduction to the Buraku Issue: Questions and Answers|last = Suehiro|first = Kitaguchi|publisher = [[Routledge]]|year = 2013|isbn = 9781134250691|location = London|pages = |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=dcC1AQAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|translator = Alastair McLauchlan|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|title = Samurai Commanders: 940–1576|last = Turnbull|first = Stephen|publisher = [[Osprey Publishing]]|year = 2005a|isbn = 9781841767437|location = Oxford|pages = |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=o5rvCwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|volume = 1|author-link = Stephen Turnbull (historian)|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|title = Samurai Commanders: 1577–1638|last = Turnbull|first = Stephen|publisher = Osprey Publishing|year = 2005b|isbn = 9781841767444|location = Oxford|pages = |volume = 2|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=hdYbDAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|title = The Samurai and the Sacred|last = Turnbull|first = Stephen|publisher = Osprey Publishing|year = 2006|isbn = 9781846030215|location = Oxford|pages = |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=iem6CwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|title = Japanese Fortified Temples and Monasteries AD 710–1062|last = Turnbull|first = Stephen|publisher = Osprey Publishing|year = 2012|isbn = 9781782000136|location = Oxford|pages = |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=V5nvCwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite journal|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=aiLYQ22ohmkC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title = Rennyo and the Shinshū Revival|last = Weinstein|first = Stanley|date = 1977|journal = Japan in the Muromachi Age|doi = |pmid = |access-date = |publisher = [[University of California Press]]|location = Oakland|editor-last = Hall|editor-first = John Whitney|editor-link = John Whitney Hall|pages = 331–358|isbn = 9780520028883|editor2-last = Toyoda|editor2-first = Takeshi|ref = harv}}

[[Category:Former countries in Japanese history]]
[[Category:1488 establishments in Asia]]
[[Category:States and territories disestablished in 1582]]
[[Category:Former confederations]]
[[Category:Buddhism in Japan]]
[[Category:Feudal Japan]]
[[Category:Medieval rebels]]</text>
      <sha1>mumj80w2xcfoin9r9k5ydshosrdavrv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
