<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Kristallnacht</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>83530</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750692692</id>
      <parentid>750448188</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T08:22:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Permstrump</username>
        <id>26162878</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */ grammar</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="59806">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2014}}
{{italic title}}
{{Infobox civilian attack
| title       = ''Kristallnacht''
| partof      = [[the Holocaust]]
| image       = 1938 Interior of Berlin synagogue after Kristallnacht.jpg
| image_size  = 270px
| alt         = Photograph of the smashed interior of the Berlin synagogue
| caption     = The interior of the [[Fasanenstrasse Synagogue]] in Berlin after ''Kristallnacht''
| map         =
| map_size    =
| map_alt     =
| map_caption =
| location    = [[Nazi Germany]], 9-10 November&lt;br&gt;[[Free City of Danzig]], 12–13 November
| target      = [[Jews]]
| coordinates = 
| date        = 9–10 November 1938
| time        = 
| type        = [[Pogrom]], [[looting]], [[arson]], [[mass murder]], [[state terrorism]]
| fatalities  =91+
| injuries    = 
| victims     = &lt;!-- or | victim      = --&gt;
| perps       = ''[[Sturmabteilung]]'' (SA) [[stormtrooper]]s, German civilians
| perpetrators= 
| susperps    = &lt;!-- or | susperp     = --&gt;
| weapons     = 
| numparts    = &lt;!-- or | numpart     = --&gt;
| dfens       = &lt;!-- or | dfen        = --&gt;
| motive      =
}}
{{Antisemitism}}
'''''Kristallnacht''''' ({{IPA-de|kʁɪsˈtalnaχt}}; {{small|English: &quot;'''Crystal Night'''&quot;}}) or '''''Reichskristallnacht''''' [{{IPA|ˌʁaɪçs.kʁɪsˈtalnaχt}}], also referred to as the '''Night of Broken Glass''', '''''Reichspogromnacht''''' [{{IPA|ˌʁaɪçs.poˈɡʁoːmnaχt}}] or simply '''''Pogromnacht''''' {{IPA-de|poˈɡʁoːmnaχt||Pogromnacht.ogg}}, and '''''Novemberpogrome''''' {{IPA-de|noˈvɛmbɐpoɡʁoːmə||Novemberpogrome.ogg}}, was a [[pogrom]] against Jews throughout [[Nazi Germany]] on 9–10 November 1938, carried out by [[Sturmabteilung|SA paramilitary]] forces and German civilians. German authorities looked on without intervening.&lt;ref name=Gilbert42&gt;&quot;'German Mobs' Vengeance on Jews&quot;, ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'', 11 November 1938, cited in [[Martin Gilbert|Gilbert, Martin]]. ''Kristallnacht: Prelude to Destruction''. Harper Collins, 2006, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The United States Holocaust Memorial Museum's ''&quot;Holocaust Encyclopedia&quot;'' is a more definitive reference that is similar to this Wikipedia article http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005201&lt;/ref&gt; The name ''Kristallnacht'' comes from the shards of broken glass that littered the streets after the windows of Jewish-owned stores, buildings, and synagogues were smashed.&lt;ref name=Atlantic&gt;[http://www.theatlantic.com/infocus/2011/06/world-war-ii-before-the-war/100089/ &quot;World War II: Before the War&quot;], ''The Atlantic'', 19 June 2011. &quot;Windows of shops owned by Jews which were broken during a coordinated anti-Jewish demonstration in Berlin, known as ''Kristallnacht'', on Nov. 10, 1938. Nazi authorities turned a blind eye as SA stormtroopers and civilians destroyed storefronts with hammers, leaving the streets covered in pieces of smashed windows. Some sources estimate that ninety-one Jews were killed, and 30,000 Jewish men were taken to concentration camps.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimates of the number of fatalities caused by the pogrom have varied. Early reporting estimated that 91 Jewish people were murdered during the attacks.&lt;ref name=Atlantic/&gt; Modern analysis of German scholarly sources by historians such as [[Richard J. Evans]] puts the number much higher.&lt;!--Having never read Evans it would be helpful if someone who has could put a proper reference here--&gt; When deaths from post-arrest maltreatment and subsequent suicides are included, the death toll climbs into the hundreds. Additionally, 30,000 were arrested and incarcerated in [[Nazi concentration camps]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot; /&gt;

Jewish homes, hospitals, and schools were ransacked, as the attackers demolished buildings with sledgehammers.&lt;ref name=Gilbert13/&gt; Over 1,000 synagogues were burned (95 in Vienna alone) and over 7,000 Jewish businesses destroyed or damaged.&lt;ref name=Berenbaum2005p49&gt;[[Michael Berenbaum|Berenbaum, Michael &amp; Kramer, Arnold]] (2005). ''The World Must Know''. [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]]. p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gilbert30&gt;Gilbert, pp. 30–33.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Martin Gilbert]] writes that no event in the history of German Jews between 1933 and 1945 was so widely reported as it was happening, and the accounts from the foreign journalists working in Germany sent shock waves around the world.&lt;ref name=Gilbert13&gt;Gilbert, pp. 13–14.{{Incomplete short citation|date=November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Times]]'' wrote at the time: &quot;No foreign propagandist bent upon blackening Germany before the world could outdo the tale of burnings and beatings, of blackguardly assaults on defenseless and innocent people, which disgraced that country yesterday.&quot;&lt;ref name=Gilbert41&gt;&quot;A Black Day for Germany&quot;, ''The Times'', 11 November 1938, cited in Gilbert, p. 41.{{Incomplete short citation|date=November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The pretext for the attacks was the assassination of the German diplomat [[Ernst vom Rath]] by [[Herschel Grynszpan]], a German-born Polish Jew living in Paris. ''Kristallnacht'' was followed by additional economic and political persecution of Jews, and is viewed by historians as part of Nazi Germany's broader [[racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial policy]], and the beginning of the [[Final Solution]] and [[The Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutchinson 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Multiple |title=The Hutchinson Encyclopedia |publisher=Helicon |location=London |year=1998 |edition=18th |series=Hutchinson Encyclopedias |volume=|page=1,199 |chapter=Kristallnacht |isbn=1-85833-951-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
The incident was originally referred to as ''die Kristallnacht'' (literally &quot;crystal night&quot;), alluding to the enormous number of glass windows broken throughout the night, mostly in synagogues and Jewish-owned shops. The prefix [[Reich]]s- (imperial) was later added ''(Reichskristallnacht)'' as a [[sardonic]] comment on the Nazis' propensity to add this prefix to various terms and titles like ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' or ''[[Reichsmarschall]]''. {{Citation needed|date=December 2012}}

==Background==
{{further|History of the Jews in Austria|History of the Jews in Germany|Nuremberg Laws}}

===Early Nazi persecutions===
In the 1920s, most German Jews were fully integrated into German society as German citizens. They served in the German army and navy and contributed to every field of German [[business sector|business]], science and culture.&lt;ref&gt;Goldstein, Joseph (1995). ''Jewish History in Modern Times''. [[Sussex Academic Press]]. pp. 43–44. ISBN 978-1-898723-06-6.&lt;/ref&gt; Conditions for the Jews began to change after the appointment of [[Adolf Hitler]] (the Austrian-born leader of the [[Nazi Party|National Socialist Workers' Party]]) as [[Chancellor of Germany]] on 30 January 1933, and the [[Enabling Act of 1933|Enabling Act]] (23 March 1933) assumption of power by Hitler after the [[Reichstag fire]] of 27 February 1933.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Nazi Germany – dictatorship|url= http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/Nazi_Germany_dictatorship.htm|author= Trueman, Chris|accessdate= 12 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Hitler's Enabling Act|url= http://www.historyplace.com/worldwar2/timeline/enabling.htm|accessdate= 2008-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; From its inception, Hitler's régime moved quickly to introduce [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|anti-Jewish policies]]. [[Nazi propaganda]] singled out the 500,000 Jews in Germany, who accounted for only 0.86% of the overall population, as an enemy within who were responsible for Germany's defeat in the [[World War I|First World War]] and for its subsequent economic disasters, such as the [[Inflation in the Weimar Republic|1920s hyperinflation]] and Wall Street Crash [[Great Depression in Central Europe|Great Depression]].&lt;ref name=Gilbert23&gt;Gilbert, p. 23.{{Incomplete short citation|date= November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in 1933, the German government enacted a series of [[Anti-Jewish legislation in prewar Nazi Germany|anti-Jewish laws]] restricting the rights of German Jews to earn a living, to enjoy full citizenship and to gain education, including the ''[[Law for the Restoration of the Professional Civil Service]]'' of 7 April 1933, which forbade Jews to work in the civil service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= Refugee Scholars:Conversations with Tess Simpson|last= Cooper|first= R.M.|location= Leeds|year= 1992|page= 31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The subsequent 1935 [[Nuremberg Laws]] stripped German Jews of their citizenship and forbade Jews to marry non-Jewish Germans.

These laws resulted in the exclusion of Jews from German social and political life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= The Holocaust|url= http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005143|accessdate= 12 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many sought asylum abroad; hundreds of thousands emigrated, but as [[Chaim Weizmann]] wrote in 1936, &quot;The world seemed to be divided into two parts—those places where the Jews could not live and those where they could not enter.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Manchester Guardian'', 23 May 1936, cited in A.J. Sherman, ''Island Refuge, Britain and the Refugees from the Third Reich, 1933–1939'', (London, Elek Books Ltd, 1973), p. 112, also in [http://christianactionforisrael.org/antiholo/evian/evian.html ''The Evian Conference — Hitler's Green Light for Genocide''], by Annette Shaw&lt;!-- ISBN# needed --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; The international [[Évian Conference]] on 6 July 1938 addressed the issue of Jewish and [[Romani people|Gypsy]] immigration to other countries. By the time the conference took place, more than 250,000 Jews had fled Germany and [[Austria]], which had been [[Anschluss|annexed by Germany]] in March 1938; more than 300,000 German and Austrian Jews continued to seek refuge and asylum from oppression. As the number of Jews and Gypsies wanting to leave increased, the restrictions against them grew, with many countries tightening their rules for admission. By 1938, Germany &quot;had entered a new radical phase in [[anti-Semitic]] activity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Eric. ''The Nazi Terror: Gestapo, Jews and Ordinary Germans''. United States: Basic Books, 1999, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians believe that the Nazi government had been contemplating a planned outbreak of violence against the Jews and were waiting for an appropriate provocation; there is evidence of this planning dating to 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Friedländer, Saul. ''Nazi Germany and The Jews'', volume 1: ''The Years of Persecution 1933–1939'', London: Phoenix, 1997, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1997 interview, the German historian [[Hans Mommsen]] claimed that a major motive for the pogrom was the desire of the ''[[Gauleiter]]s'' of the NSDAP to seize Jewish property and [[business]]es.&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem1997&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last= Mommsen|first= Hans|title= Interview with Hans Mommsen|publisher= Yad Vashem|date= 12 December 1997|url= http://www1.yadvashem.org/odot_pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%203850.pdf|accessdate= 6 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mommsen stated:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The need for money by the party organization stemmed from the fact that [[Franz Xaver Schwarz]], the party treasurer, kept the local and regional organizations of the party short of money. In the fall of 1938, the increased pressure on Jewish property nourished the party's ambition, especially since Hjalmar Schacht had been ousted as ''Reich'' minister for economics. This, however, was only one aspect of the origin of the November 1938 pogrom. The Polish government threatened to extradite all Jews who were Polish citizens, but would stay in Germany, thus creating a burden of responsibility on the German side. The immediate reaction by the Gestapo was to push the Polish Jews—16,000 persons—over the borderline, but this measure failed due to the stubbornness of the Polish customs officers. The loss of prestige as a result of this abortive operation called for some sort of compensation. Thus, the overreaction to Herschel Grynszpan's attempt against the diplomat Ernst vom Rath came into being and led to the November pogrom. The background of the pogrom was signified by a sharp cleavage of interests between the different agencies of party and state. While the Nazi party was interested in improving its financial strength on the regional and local level by taking over Jewish property, [[Hermann Göring]], in charge of the Four-Year Plan, hoped to acquire access to foreign currency in order to pay for the import of {{Sic|hide=y|urgently|-}}needed raw material. Heydrich and Himmler were interested in fostering Jewish emigration&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem1997&quot;/&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[Zionist]] leadership in the [[Mandate Palestine|British Mandate of Palestine]] wrote in February 1938 that according to &quot;a very reliable private source—one which can be traced back to the highest echelons of the SS leadership&quot;, there was &quot;an intention to carry out a genuine and dramatic [[pogrom]] in Germany on a large scale in the near future&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
Georg Landauer to Martin Rosenbluth, 8 February 1938, cited in Friedländer, loc. cit.
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Expulsion of Polish Jews in Germany===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1982-174-27, Nürnberg, Ausweisung polnischer Juden.jpg|thumb|Polish Jews expelled from Germany in late October 1938]]
In August 1938 the German authorities announced that residence permits for foreigners were being cancelled and would have to be renewed. This included German-born Jews of foreign origin. [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]] stated that it would not accept [[History of the Jews in Poland|Jews of Polish origin]] after the end of October. In the so-called &quot;Polenaktion&quot;, more than 12,000 Polish-born Jews, among them the philosopher and theologian Rabbi [[Abraham Joshua Heschel]], and future literary critic [[Marcel Reich-Ranicki]], were expelled from Germany on 28 October 1938, on Hitler's orders. They were ordered to leave their homes in a single night, and were allowed only one suitcase per person to carry their belongings. As the Jews were taken away, their remaining possessions were seized as loot both by the [[Gestapo|Nazi authorities]] and by their neighbors.

The deportees were taken from their homes to railway stations and were put on trains to the Polish border, where Polish border guards sent them back over the river into Germany. This stalemate continued for days in the pouring rain, with the Jews marching without food or shelter between the borders. Four thousand were granted entry into [[Poland]], but the remaining 8,000 were forced to stay at the border. They waited there in harsh conditions to be allowed to enter Poland. A British newspaper told its readers that hundreds &quot;are reported to be lying about, penniless and deserted, in little villages along the frontier near where they had been driven out by the Gestapo and left.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Expelled Jews' Dark Outlook|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/obituaries/article3531693.ece |work=Newspaper article|publisher=The Times|date=1 November 1938|accessdate=12 March 2008|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conditions in the [[refugee camps]] &quot;were so bad that some actually tried to escape back into Germany and were shot&quot;, recalled a British woman who was sent to help those who had been expelled.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Recollections of Rosalind Herzfled,&quot; ''Jewish Chronicle,'' 28 September 1979, p. 80; cited in Gilbert, ''The Holocaust—The Jewish Tragedy'', London: William Collins Sons &amp; Co. Ltd, 1986.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shooting of vom Rath===
[[File:Herschel Grynszpan nov 7 1938.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Herschel Grynszpan]], 7 November 1938]]
[[File:Ernst-vom-Rath.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Ernst vom Rath]] ]]
Among those expelled was the family of Sendel and Riva Grynszpan, Polish Jews who had emigrated to Germany in 1911 and settled in [[Hanover]], Germany. At the trial of [[Adolf Eichmann]] in 1961, Sendel Grynszpan recounted the events of their deportation from Hanover on the night of 27 October 1938: &quot;Then they took us in police trucks, in prisoners' lorries, about 20 men in each truck, and they took us to the railway station. The streets were full of people shouting: ''{{'}}Juden raus! Auf nach Palästina!{{'}}''&quot; (&quot;Jews out, out to Palestine!&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Hannah Arendt, ''Eichmann in Jerusalem'', p. 228.&lt;/ref&gt; Their seventeen-year-old son [[Herschel Grynszpan|Herschel]] was living in Paris with an uncle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutchinson 1998&quot;/&gt; Herschel received a postcard from his family from the Polish border, describing the family's expulsion: &quot;No one told us what was up, but we realised this was going to be the end ... We haven't a penny. Could you send us something?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GSA&quot;&gt;German State Archives, [[Potsdam]], quoted in Rita Thalmann and Emmanuel Feinermann, ''Crystal night, 9–10 November 1938'', pp. 33, 42.&lt;/ref&gt; He received the postcard on 3 November 1938.

On the morning of Monday, 7 November 1938, he purchased a revolver and a box of bullets, then went to the German embassy and asked to see an embassy official. After he was taken to the office of [[Ernst vom Rath]], Grynszpan fired five bullets at Vom Rath, two of which hit him in the abdomen. Vom Rath was a professional diplomat with the Foreign Office who expressed anti-Nazi sympathies, largely based on the Nazis' treatment of the Jews, and was under Gestapo investigation for being politically unreliable.&lt;ref&gt;William L. Shirer, ''The Rise And Fall Of The Third Reich'', p. 430.&lt;/ref&gt; Grynszpan made no attempt to escape the French police and freely confessed to the shooting. In his pocket, he carried a postcard to his parents with the message, &quot;May God forgive me ... I must protest so that the whole world hears my protest, and that I will do.&quot;

The next day, the German government retaliated, barring Jewish children from German state elementary schools, indefinitely suspending Jewish cultural activities, and putting a halt to the publication of Jewish newspapers and magazines, including the three national German Jewish newspapers. A newspaper in Britain described the last move, which cut off the Jewish populace from their leaders, as &quot;intended to disrupt the Jewish community and rob it of the last frail ties which hold it together.&quot;&lt;ref name=Gilbert23/&gt; Their rights as citizens had been stripped.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Nazis Planning Revenge on Jews&quot;, ''News Chronicle'', 9 November 1938&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pogrom==

===Death of vom Rath===
[[File:Kristallnacht rh telegram pg1.png|thumb|Telegram sent by Reinhard Heydrich, 9 November 1938]]
Ernst vom Rath died of his wounds on 9 November. Word of his death reached Hitler that evening while he was with several key members of the Nazi party at a dinner commemorating the 1923 [[Beer Hall Putsch]]. After intense discussions, Hitler left the assembly abruptly without giving his usual address. Propaganda Minister [[Joseph Goebbels]] delivered the speech, in his place, and said that &quot;the Führer has decided that... demonstrations should not be prepared or organized by the party, but insofar as they erupt spontaneously, they are not to be hampered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Friedländer, op.cit., p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt; The chief party judge [[Walter Buch]] later stated that the message was clear; with these words Goebbels had commanded the party leaders to organize a pogrom.&lt;ref&gt;Walter Buch to Goring, 13.2.1939, Michaelis and Schraepler, Ursachen, Vol.12, p. 582 as cited in Friedländer, p. 271.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some leading party officials disagreed with Goebbels' actions, fearing the diplomatic crisis it would provoke. [[Heinrich Himmler]] wrote, &quot;I suppose that it is Goebbels's megalomania...and stupidity which are responsible for starting this operation now, in a particularly difficult diplomatic situation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Graml, Anti-Semitism, p. 13 cited in Friedländer, op.cit., p 272&lt;/ref&gt; The Israeli historian [[Saul Friedländer]] believes that Goebbels had personal reasons for wanting to bring about ''Kristallnacht''. Goebbels had recently suffered humiliation for the ineffectiveness of his propaganda campaign during the [[Sudetenland Crisis|Sudeten crisis]], and was in some disgrace over an affair with a [[Czechs|Czech]] actress, [[Lída Baarová]]. Goebbels needed a chance to improve his standing in the eyes of Hitler. At 01:20 am on 10 November 1938, [[Reinhard Heydrich]] sent an urgent secret telegram to the [[Sicherheitspolizei]] (Security Police) and the [[Sturmabteilung]] (SA), containing instructions regarding the riots. This included guidelines for the protection of foreigners and non-Jewish businesses and property. Police were instructed not to interfere with the riots unless the guidelines were violated. Police were also instructed to seize Jewish archives from synagogues and community offices, and to arrest and detain &quot;healthy male Jews, who are not too old&quot;, for eventual transfer to (labor) [[concentration camp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://motlc.wiesenthal.com/site/pp.asp?c=gvKVLcMVIuG&amp;b=394829 &quot;Heydrich's secret instructions regarding the riots in November 1938&quot;], ([[Simon Wiesenthal Center]])&lt;/ref&gt;

===Riots===
The timing of the riots varied from unit to unit. The [[Gauleiter]]s started at about 10:30pm, only two hours after news of Vom Rath's death reached Germany. They were followed by the SA at 11pm, and the SS at around 1:20am.{{citation needed|date=June 2011}} Most were wearing civilian clothes and were armed with sledgehammers and axes, and soon went to work on the destruction of Jewish property. The orders given to these men were very specific, however: no measures endangering non-Jewish German life or property were to be taken (synagogues too close to non-Jewish property were smashed rather than burned); Jewish businesses or dwellings could be destroyed but not looted; foreigners (even Jewish foreigners) were not to be the subjects of violence; and synagogue archives were to be transferred to the [[Sicherheitsdienst]] (SD). The men were also ordered to arrest as many Jews as the local jails would hold, the preferred targets being healthy young men.{{citation needed|date=June 2011}}

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Kristallnacht example of physical damage.jpg|left|thumb|''Kristallnacht'', example of physical damage]] --&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1970-083-42, Magdeburg, zerstörtes jüdisches Geschäft.jpg|left|thumb|''Kristallnacht'', shop damage in [[Magdeburg]]]]
The SA of adjacent cities shattered the storefronts of about 7,500 Jewish stores and businesses, hence the appellation ''Kristallnacht'' (Crystal Night).&lt;ref&gt;GermanNotes, http://www.germannotes.com/hist_ww2_kristallnacht.shtml, retrieved 26 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Jewish homes were ransacked all throughout Germany. Although violence against Jews had not been explicitly condoned by the authorities, there were cases of Jews being beaten or assaulted.

This [[pogrom]] damaged, and in many cases destroyed, about 200 [[synagogue]]s (constituting nearly all Germany had), many Jewish cemeteries, more than 7,000 Jewish shops, and 29 department stores. Some Jews were beaten to death while others were forced to watch.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} More than 30,000 Jewish men were arrested and taken to [[concentration camp]]s; primarily [[Dachau concentration camp|Dachau]], [[Buchenwald concentration camp|Buchenwald]], and [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/exhibitions/kristallnacht/kristallnacht_photo2.html &quot;The deportation of Regensburg Jews to Dachau concentration camp&quot;] ([[Yad Vashem]] Photo Archives 57659)&lt;/ref&gt; The treatment of prisoners in the camps was brutal, but most were released during the following three months on condition that they leave Germany. The number of German Jews killed is uncertain. The number killed in the two-day riot is most often cited as 91. In addition, it is thought that there were hundreds of suicides.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}} Counting deaths in the concentration camps, around 2,000–2,500 deaths were directly or indirectly attributable to the ''Kristallnacht'' pogrom. A few non-Jewish Germans, mistaken for Jews, were also killed.{{citation needed|date=June 2009}}

The synagogues, some centuries old, were also victims of considerable violence and vandalism, with the tactics the Stormtroops practised on these and other sacred sites described as &quot;approaching the ghoulish&quot; by the United States Consul in Leipzig. Tombstones were uprooted and graves violated. Fires were lit, and prayer books, scrolls, artwork and philosophy texts were thrown upon them, and precious buildings were either burned or smashed until unrecognisable. Eric Lucas recalls the destruction of the synagogue that a tiny Jewish community had constructed in a small village only twelve years earlier: 
{{quotation|It did not take long before the first heavy grey stones came tumbling down, and the children of the village amused themselves as they flung stones into the many coloured windows. When the first rays of a cold and pale November sun penetrated the heavy dark clouds, the little synagogue was but a heap of stone, broken glass and smashed-up woodwork.'&lt;ref&gt;Lucas, Eric. &quot;The sovereigns&quot;, Kibbutz Kfar Blum (Palestine), 1945, p. 171 cited in Gilbert, op.cit., p 67.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

After this, the Jewish community was fined 10 billion reichsmarks. In addition, it cost 40 million marks to repair the windows.&lt;ref&gt;[[Raul Hilberg]]. ''The Destruction of the European Jews'', Third Edition, (Yale Univ. Press, 2003, c1961), Ch.3.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- The monetary amount of glass smashed by German mobs was calculated to be worth approximately 24 million marks. SOURCE? --&gt; Events in recently annexed Austria were no less horrendous. Of the entire ''Kristallnacht'', only the pogrom in Vienna was completed. Most of Vienna's 904 synagogues and prayer-houses were partially or totally destroyed. People were subjected to all manner of humiliations, including being forced to scrub the pavements whilst being tormented by their fellow Austrians, some of whom had been their friends and neighbours.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} Official figures released after the event by Reinhard Heydrich stated that 1901 synagogues were destroyed, with 76 completely demolished; 1,000,000 Jews were arrested; three foreigners were arrested; 1740 people were arrested for looting Jewish shops; and 8015 Jewish businesses were destroyed.{{citation needed|date=January 2013}}

The ''Daily Telegraph'' correspondent, [[Hugh Greene]], wrote of events in Berlin:{{quotation|Mob law ruled in Berlin throughout the afternoon and evening and hordes of hooligans indulged in an orgy of destruction. I have seen several anti-Jewish outbreaks in Germany during the last five years, but never anything as nauseating as this. Racial hatred and hysteria seemed to have taken complete hold of otherwise decent people. I saw fashionably dressed women clapping their hands and screaming with glee, while respectable middle-class mothers held up their babies to see the &quot;fun&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Carleton Greene, Hugh. ''Daily Telegraph'', 11 November 1938 cited in [http://mars.vnet.wnec.edu/~grempel/courses/berlin/lectures/17TheRoadtoWar.html &quot;The Road to World War II&quot;], Western New England College.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Many Berliners were however deeply ashamed of the pogrom, and some took great personal risks to offer help. The son of a US consular official heard the janitor of his block cry:{{quotation|'They must have emptied the insane asylums and penitentiaries to find people who'd do things like that!'&lt;ref&gt;[http://mars.vnet.wnec.edu/~grempel/courses/berlin/lectures/17TheRoadtoWar.html &quot;The Road to World War II&quot;], Western New England College.[https://web.archive.org/web/20070930231711/http://mars.vnet.wnec.edu/~grempel/courses/berlin/lectures/17TheRoadtoWar.html]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[KMSB|Tucson News]] TV channel briefly reported on a 2008 remembrance meeting at a local Jewish congregation. According to eyewitness Esther Harris:&lt;blockquote&gt;''They ripped up the belongings, the books, knocked over furniture, shouted obscenities''.&lt;ref name=&quot;kold&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kold.com/Global/story.asp?S=8269951&amp;nav=14RT|authorlink=Esther Harris, Gerhard Weinberg|title=Kristallnacht Remembered|publisher=www.kold.com|accessdate=2008-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt; Historian [[Gerhard Weinberg]] is quoted as saying:&lt;blockquote&gt;''Houses of worship burned down, vandalized, in every community in the country where people either participate or watch.''&lt;ref name=&quot;kold&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Concentration camps===
The violence was officially called to a stop by Goebbels on 11 November, but it continued against the Jews in the concentration camps despite orders requesting &quot;special treatment&quot; to ensure that this did not happen. On 23 November, the ''News Chronicle'' of [[London]] published an article on an incident which took place at the concentration camp of [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen]]. Sixty-three Jews suffered punishment so severe that the police, &quot;unable to bear their cries, turned their backs&quot;. They were beaten until they fell and, when they fell, they were further beaten. At the end of it, &quot;twelve of the sixty-two were dead, their skulls smashed. The others were all unconscious. The eyes of some had been knocked out, their faces flattened and shapeless&quot;. The 300,000 Jewish men who had been imprisoned during ''Kristallnacht'' were released over the next three months but, by then, more than 2,000 had died.{{Citation needed|date=May 2014}}

== Aftermath ==
[[File:Destroyed Ohel Yaaqov Synagogue.jpeg|thumb|A ruined synagogue in [[Munich]] after ''Kristallnacht'']]
[[File:Synagogue Eisenach burning- Nov 1938.jpg|thumb|A ruined synagogue in [[Eisenach]] after ''Kristallnacht'']]
[[File:0254 HM Monson Collection Vienna 1938 01 49 45 00.webm|thumb|Home movie from Vienna taken likely just after Kristallnacht in 1938.]]
[[Hermann Göring]], who was in favor of expropriating the Jews rather than destroy Jewish property as had happened in the pogrom,  complained directly to Chief of Police and Head of [[Reich Main Security Office]] [[Reinhard Heydrich]] immediately after the events: &quot;I'd rather you had done in two-hundred Jews than destroy so many valuable assets!&quot; (''&quot;Mir wäre lieber gewesen, ihr hättet 200 Juden erschlagen und hättet nicht solche Werte vernichtet!&quot;'').&lt;ref&gt;Döscher, Hans-Jürgen (2000). ''&quot;Reichskristallnacht&quot; – Die Novemberpogrome 1938'' (&quot;'Reichskristallnacht': The November pogroms of 1938&quot;), Econ, 2000, ISBN 3-612-26753-1, p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; Göring met with other members of the Nazi leadership on 12 November to plan the next steps after the riot, setting the stage for formal government action. In the transcript of the meeting, Göring said,
&lt;blockquote&gt;I have received a letter written on the [[Führer]]'s orders requesting that the Jewish question be now, once and for all, coordinated and solved one way or another... I should not want to leave any doubt, gentlemen, as to the aim of today's meeting. We have not come together merely to talk again, but to make decisions, and I implore competent agencies to take all measures for the elimination of the Jew from the German economy, and to submit them to me.&lt;ref&gt;Conot, Robert. ''Justice at Nuremberg'', New York, NY: Harper and Row, 1983, pp. 164–72.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The persecution and economic damage done to German Jews continued after the pogrom, even as their places of business were ransacked. They were forced to pay ''Judenvermögensabgabe'', a collective fine of one billion marks for the murder of vom Rath (equal to roughly $US 5.5 billion in today’s currency), which was levied by the compulsory acquisition of 20% of all Jewish property by the state. Six million Reichsmarks of insurance payments for property damage due to the Jewish community were to be paid to the government instead as &quot;damages to the German Nation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chgs.umn.edu/Histories__Narratives__Documen/Documents_from_the_Holocaust/Post-Kristallnacht_Document/post-kristallnacht_document.html &quot;JudenVermoegersabgabe&quot; (The Center for Holocaust and Genocide Studies)]&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of emigrating Jews surged, as those who were able left the country. In the ten months following ''Kristallnacht'', more than 115,000 Jews emigrated from the Reich.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/kristallnacht/frame.htm Jewish emigration from Germany] (USHMM)&lt;/ref&gt; The majority went to other European countries, the US and Palestine, and at least 14,000 made it to [[Shanghai ghetto|Shanghai]], [[China]]. As part of government policy, the Nazis seized houses, shops, and other property the émigrés left behind. Many of the destroyed remains of Jewish property plundered during Kristallnacht were dumped near [[Brandenburg]]. In October 2008, this dumpsite was discovered by [[Yaron Svoray]], an investigative journalist. The site, the size of four [[Association football]] fields, contained an extensive array of personal and ceremonial items looted during the riots against Jewish property and places of worship on the night of 9 November 1938. It is believed the goods were brought by rail to the outskirts of the village and dumped on designated land. Among the items found were glass bottles engraved with the [[Star of David]], [[mezuzot]], painted window sills, and the armrests of chairs found in synagogues, in addition to an ornamental swastika.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/oct/22/secondworldwar-germany|work=The Guardian|location=London|title=Kristallnacht remnants unearthed near Berlin|first=Kate|last=Connolly|date=22 October 2008|accessdate=7 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Responses to ''Kristallnacht''==

===From the Germans===
The reaction of non-Jewish Germans to ''Kristallnacht'' was varied. Many spectators gathered on the scenes, most of them in silence. The local fire departments confined themselves to preventing the flames from  spreading to neighbouring buildings. In Berlin, police Lieutenant Otto Bellgardt barred SA troopers from setting the [[New Synagogue, Berlin|New Synagogue]] on fire, earning his superior officer a verbal reprimand from the commissioner.&lt;ref&gt;Scheer, Regina (1993). &quot;Im Revier 16 (In precinct No. 16)&quot;. Die Hackeschen Höfe. Geschichte und Geschichten einer Lebenswelt in der Mitte Berlins (Gesellschaft Hackesche Höfe e.V. (ed.), pp. 78 ed.). Berlin: Argon. ISBN 3-87024-254-X.&lt;/ref&gt;  The British historian [[Martin Gilbert]] believes that &quot;many non-Jews resented the round up&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Gilbert, op. cit., p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; his opinion being supported by German witness Dr. Arthur Flehinger who recalls seeing &quot;people crying while watching from behind their curtains&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Arthur Flehinger, &quot;Flames of Fury&quot;, ''Jewish Chronicle'', 9 November 1979, p. 27, cited in Gilbert, loc. cit.&lt;/ref&gt; The extent of the damage was so great that many Germans are said to have expressed their disapproval of it, and to have described it as senseless.&lt;ref&gt;[http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/12062109 &quot;New Campaign Against Jews&quot;, ''The Argus'', 11 November 1938]&lt;/ref&gt;

In an article released for publication on the evening of 11 November, Goebbels ascribed the events of ''Kristallnacht'' to the &quot;healthy instincts&quot; of the German people. He went on to explain: &quot;The German people is anti-Semitic. It has no desire to have its rights restricted or to be provoked in the future by parasites of the Jewish race.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Daily Telegraph'', 12 November 1938. Cited in Gilbert, Martin. ''Kristallnacht: Prelude to Destruction''. Harper Collins, 2006, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt; Less than 24 hours after the Kristallnacht Adolf Hitler made a one hour long speech in front of a group of journalists where he managed to completely ignore the recent events on everyone's mind. According to Eugene Davidson the reason for this was that Hitler wished to avoid being directly connected to an event that he was aware that many of those present condemned, regardless of Goebbels's unconvincing explanation that Kristallnacht was caused by popular wrath.&lt;ref&gt;Eugene Davidson. The Unmaking of Adolf Hitler. Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1996. ISBN 978-0-8262-1045-6. p. 325&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1938, just after Kristallnacht, the psychologist Muller-Claudius interviewed 41 randomly selected Nazi Party members on their attitudes towards racial persecution. Of the interviewed party-members 63% expressed extreme indignation against it, while only 5% expressed approval of racial persecution, the rest being noncommittal. A study conducted in 1933 had then shown that 33% of Nazi Party members held no racial prejudice while 13% supported persecution. Sarah Ann Gordon sees two possible reasons for this difference. First, by 1938 large numbers of Germans had joined the Nazi Party for pragmatic reasons rather than ideology thus diluting the percentage of rabid antisemites; second, the Kristallnacht could have caused party members to reject Antisemitism that had been acceptable to them in abstract terms but which they could not support when they saw it concretely enacted.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, pp. 263–264&lt;/ref&gt; During the Kristallnacht several Gauleiter and deputy Gauleiters had refused orders to enact the Kristallnacht, and  many leaders of the SA and of the Hitler Youth also openly refused party orders, while expressing disgust.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarah Ann Gordon p. 266&quot;&gt;Gordon, p. 266&lt;/ref&gt; Some Nazis helped Jews during the Kristallnacht.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarah Ann Gordon p. 266&quot;/&gt;

As it was aware that the German public did not support the Kristallnacht, the propaganda ministry directed the German press to portray opponents of racial persecution as disloyal.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, p. 159&lt;/ref&gt; The press was also under orders to downplay the Kristallnacht, describing general events at local level only, with prohibition against depictions of individual events.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, p. 156&lt;/ref&gt; In 1939 this was extended to a prohibition on reporting any anti-Jewish measures.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, p. 157&lt;/ref&gt;

The vast majority of the German public disapproved of the Kristallnacht as for example evidenced by the torrent of reports attesting to this by diplomats in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, pp. 175–179&lt;/ref&gt;

The US ambassador to Germany reported: {{Quotation|In view of this being a totalitarian state a surprising characteristic of the situation here is the intensity and scope among German citizens of condemnation of the recent happenings against Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, p. 176&lt;/ref&gt;}}

To the consternation of the Nazis the Kristallnacht affected public opinion counter to their desires, the peak of opposition against the Nazi racial policies was reached just then, when according to almost all accounts the vast majority of Germans rejected the violence perpetrated against the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, pp. 180, 207&lt;/ref&gt; Verbal complaints grew rapidly in numbers, and for example the Duesseldorf branch of the Gestapo reported a sharp decline in anti-Semitic attitudes among the population.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, pp. 175–179, 215&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many indications of Protestant and Catholic disapproval of racial persecution; for example the Catholic church had already distributed [[Pastoral letter]]s critical of Nazi racial ideology, and the Nazi regime expected to encounter organised resistance from it following Kristallnacht.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarah Ann Gordon pp. 251, 252&quot;&gt;Gordon, pp. 251, 252, 258, 259&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic leadership however, just as the various Protestant churches, refrained from responding with organised action.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarah Ann Gordon pp. 251, 252&quot;/&gt; While individual Catholics and Protestants took action, the churches as a whole chose silence publicly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarah Ann Gordon pp. 251, 252&quot;/&gt; Nevertheless, individuals continued to show courage, for example a [[Parson]] paid the medical bills of a Jewish cancer patient and was  sentenced to a large fine and several months in prison in 1941, and a Catholic nun was sentenced to death in 1945 for helping Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarah Ann Gordon pp. 251, 252&quot;/&gt; A Protestant parson spoke out in 1943 and was sent to Dachau concentration camp where he died after a few days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sarah Ann Gordon pp. 251, 252&quot;/&gt;

Martin Sasse, Nazi Party member and bishop of the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in Thuringia]], leading member of the Nazi [[German Christians]], one of the schismatic factions of German Protestantism, published a compendium of [[Martin Luther]]'s writings shortly after the ''Kristallnacht''; Sasse &quot;applauded the burning of the synagogues&quot; and the coincidence of the day, writing in the introduction, &quot;On 10 November 1938, on Luther's birthday, the synagogues are burning in Germany.&quot; The German people, he urged, ought to heed these words &quot;of the greatest anti-Semite of his time, the warner of his people against the Jews.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bernd Nellessen, &quot;Die schweigende Kirche: Katholiken und Judenverfolgung&quot;, in Büttner (ed) &lt;cite&gt;Die Deutschen und die Judenverfolgung im Dritten Reich&lt;/cite&gt;, p. 265, cited in Daniel Goldhagen's &lt;cite&gt;Hitler's Willing Executioners&lt;/cite&gt; (Vintage, 1997).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Diarmaid MacCulloch]] argued that Luther's 1543 pamphlet, ''[[On the Jews and Their Lies]]'' was a &quot;blueprint&quot; for the ''Kristallnacht''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Diarmaid MacCulloch]], ''[[Reformation: Europe's House Divided, 1490-1700]]''. New York: Penguin Books Ltd, 2004, pp. 666–67.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:19381011 NYT frontpage Kristallnacht.png|thumb|left|The front page of ''[[The New York Times]]'' of 11 November 1938 refers to the attacks occurring &quot;under the direction of Stormtroopers and Nazi party members,&quot; but also said that [[Josef Goebbels|Goebbels]] called a stop to it.]]

===From the global community===
[[File:Plaque on the New Synagogue.JPG|thumb|upright|After 1945 some synagogues were restored. This one in Berlin features a plaque, reading &quot;Never forget&quot;, a common expression around Berlin]]
''Kristallnacht'' sparked international outrage. It discredited pro-Nazi movements in [[Europe]] and [[North America]], leading to eventual decline of their support. Many newspapers condemned ''Kristallnacht'', with some comparing it to the murderous pogroms incited by Imperial [[Russia]] in the 1880s. The [[United States]] recalled its ambassador (but did not break off diplomatic relations) while other governments severed diplomatic relations with Germany in protest. The [[United Kingdom|British]] government approved the [[Kindertransport]] program for refugee children. As such, ''Kristallnacht'' also marked a turning point in relations between Nazi Germany and the rest of the world. The brutality of the pogrom, and the Nazi government's deliberate policy of encouraging the violence once it had begun, laid bare the repressive nature and widespread anti-Semitism entrenched in Germany, and turned world opinion sharply against the Nazi regime, with some politicians calling for war. The private protest against the Germans following ''Kristallnacht'' was held on 6 December 1938. [[William Cooper (Aboriginal Australian)|William Cooper]], an Aboriginal Australian, led a delegation of the [[Australian Aboriginal League]] on a march through Melbourne to the German Consulate to deliver a petition which condemned the &quot;cruel persecution of the Jewish people by the Nazi government of Germany&quot;. German officials refused to accept the tendered document.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Miskin|first=Maayana|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/news.aspx/138896|title=Yad Vashem to Honor Aborigine|publisher=Israel National News|date=8 February 2010|accessdate=20 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Kristallnacht, [[Salvador Allende]], [[Gabriel González Videla]], [[Marmaduke Grove]], [[Florencio Durán]] and other members of the [[National Congress of Chile|Congress of Chile]] sent a [[telegram]] to Adolf Hitler denouncing the persecution of Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.elclarin.cl/fpa/pdf/p_020605.pdf |title=Telegram protesting against the persecution of Jews in Germany |publisher=El Clarín de Chile's|language=es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A more personal response, in 1939, was the oratorio ''[[A Child of Our Time]]'' by the English composer [[Michael Tippett]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last= Lewis|first= Geraint|title= Tippett, Sir Michael Kemp|url= http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/69100?docPos=1|publisher= Oxford Dictionary of National Biography (online edition)|date= May 2010|accessdate= 29 April 2012}} {{subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Kristallnacht'' as a turning point==
''Kristallnacht'' changed the nature of persecution from economic, political, and social to physical with beatings, incarceration, and murder; the event is often referred to as the beginning of [[the Holocaust]]. In the words of historian Max Rein in 1988, &quot;Kristallnacht came...and everything was changed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Krefeld&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Krefeld|first=Stadt|others=Cited in Johnson, Eric|title=Ehemalige Krefelder Juden berichten uber ihre Erlebnisse in der sogenannten Reichskristallnacht|publisher=Basic Books|location=Krefeld Stadt Archiv|year=1988|series=Krefelder Juden in Amerika|volume=3|page=117}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While November 1938 predated overt articulation of &quot;the [[Final Solution]]&quot;, it foreshadowed the [[genocide]] to come. Around the time of ''Kristallnacht'', the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] newspaper ''[[Das Schwarze Korps]]'' called for a &quot;destruction by swords and flames.&quot; At a conference on the day after the pogrom, [[Hermann Göring]] said: &quot;The Jewish problem will reach its solution if, in any time soon, we will be drawn into war beyond our border—then it is obvious that we will have to manage a final account with the Jews.&quot;&lt;ref name=Gilbert23/&gt;

[[File:Buchenwald Disabled Jews 13132 crop.jpg|thumb|Five handicapped Jewish prisoners who arrived in [[Buchenwald]] after ''Kristallnacht''.]]

==Modern responses==
Many decades later, association with the ''Kristallnacht'' anniversary was cited as the main reason [[November 9 in German history|against choosing 9 November ''(Schicksalstag)'']], the day the [[Berlin Wall]] came down in 1989, as the new German national [[Public holiday|holiday]]; a different day was chosen (3 October 1990, [[German reunification]]). The [[avant-garde]] guitarist [[Gary Lucas]]'s 1988 composition &quot;Verklärte Kristallnacht&quot;, which juxtaposes what would become the [[Israel]]i national anthem ten years after ''Kristallnacht'', &quot;[[Hatikvah]]&quot;, with phrases from the German national anthem &quot;[[Deutschland Über Alles]]&quot; amid wild electronic shrieks and noise, is intended to be a sonic representation of the horrors of ''Kristallnacht''. It was premiered at the 1988 [[Berlin Jazz Festival]] and received rave reviews. (The title is a reference to [[Arnold Schoenberg]]'s 1899 work &quot;[[Verklärte Nacht]]&quot; that presaged his pioneering work on [[atonality|atonal music]]; Schoenberg was an [[Austria]]n Jew who would move to the [[United States]] to escape the Nazis).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.berkshireweb.com/rogovoy/interviews/feat010420.html|title=Gary Lucas: Action guitarist |author= Seth Rogovoy|publisher=[[Berkshire Eagle]]|date=20 April 2001|accessdate= 20 May 2008|quote=A knowing reference to Arnold Schoenberg's &quot;Verklarte Nacht&quot;, the piece ironically juxtaposed the Israeli national anthem, &quot;Hatikvah,&quot; with phrases from &quot;Deutschland Uber Alles,&quot; amid wild electronic shrieks and noise. The next day the papers ran a picture of Lucas with the triumphant headline, &quot;It is Lucas!&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On its 40th anniversary in 1978, members of two fraternities at the [[University of Florida]] gathered in front of the fraternity house of [[Tau Epsilon Phi]] (a historically Jewish fraternity) and &quot;shouted [anti-Semitic] expressions like 'F___ the Jews,' &quot; and &quot;Your mother was bright but she was a [[Lampshades made from human skin|lampshade]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Antisemitism in America, Leonard Dinnerstein, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

''Kristallnacht'' was the inspiration for the 1993 album ''[[Kristallnacht (album)|Kristallnacht]]'' by the composer [[John Zorn]]. The German [[power metal]] band [[Masterplan (band)|Masterplan]]'s debut album, ''[[Masterplan (Masterplan album)|Masterplan]]'' (2003), features an anti-Nazism song entitled &quot;Crystal Night&quot; as the fourth track. The German band [[BAP (German band)|BAP]] published a song titled &quot;Kristallnaach&quot; in their [[Cologne]] [[Colognian dialect|dialect]], dealing with the emotions of the ''Kristallnacht''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bap.de/musik_songtexte.php|title=BAP Songtexte (German)|accessdate=16 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Kristallnacht'' was the inspiration for the 1988 composition ''[[Mayn Yngele]]'' by the composer [[Frederic Rzewski]], of which he says: &quot;I began writing this piece in November, 1988, on the 50th anniversary of the Kristallnacht ... My piece is a reflection on that vanished part of Jewish tradition which so strongly colors, by its absence, the culture of our time&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://imslp.org/wiki/Mayn_Yingele_(Rzewski,_Frederic)|title=Mayn Yingele (Rzewski, Frederic)
|accessdate=25 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Kristallnacht'' has been depicted on the screen in a number of Holocaust-themed films and television shows, among them 1978's ''[[Holocaust (TV miniseries)]]'' and 1990's ''[[Europa Europa]]''.

==See also==
*[[Israel's Department Store]]
*[[Pogrom]]
*[[Spandau Synagogue]]
*[[November 9 in German history]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin|30em}}
;Books in English
*{{cite book
  |author=Browning, Christopher R.
  |title=Collected Memories: Holocaust History and Postwar Testimony
  |publisher=[[University of Wisconsin Press]]
  |location=Madison
  |year=2003
  |isbn=0-299-18984-8
  |series=George L. Mosse Series in Modern European Cultural and Intellectual History}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Mayer, Kurt
  |title=My Personal Brush with History
  |publisher=Kurt Mayer, Confluence Books
  |location=Tacoma
  |year=2009
  |isbn=978-0-578-03911-4}}
*{{cite book
  | author=Friedlander, Saul
  | title=Nazi Germany and the Jews: Volume 1: The Years of Persecution 1933–1939
  | publisher=Perennial
  |location=New York, NY
  |year=1998
  |isbn=0-06-092878-6}}
*{{Cite book
  | author=Gilbert, Martin
  | title=The Holocaust: The Jewish Tragedy
  | year=1986
  | publisher=Collins
  | location=London
  | isbn=0-00-216305-5}}
*{{Cite book
  | author=Gordon, Sarah Ann
  | title=Hitler, Germans, and the Jewish Question
  | year=1984
  | publisher=Princeton University Press
  | location=
  | isbn=0-691-10162-0 }}
*{{Cite book
  | author=Johnson, Eric J.
  | title=Nazi Terror: The Gestapo, Jews, and Ordinary Germans
  | year=1999
  | publisher=[[Basic Books]]
  | location=New York
  | isbn=0-465-04906-0}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Mosse, George L.
  |title=Toward the Final Solution: A History of European Racism
  |publisher=Howard Fertig
  |location=New York
  |year=1978
  |isbn=0-86527-941-1}}
**{{cite book
|author=Mosse, George L.
|title=Confronting History: A Memoir
|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press
|location=Madison
|year=2000
|isbn=0-299-16580-9}}
**{{cite book
|author=Mosse, George L.
|title=Nazi Culture: Intellectual, Cultural and Social Life in the Third Reich
|publisher=[[University of Wisconsin Press]]
|location=Madison
|year=2003
|isbn=0-299-19304-7}}
**{{cite book
|author=Mosse, George L.
|title=The Crisis of German Ideology: Intellectual Origins of the Third Reich
|publisher=Howard Fertig
|location=New York
|year=1999
|isbn=0-86527-426-6}}
*{{cite book
|author=Schwab, Gerald
|title=The day the Holocaust began: the odyssey of Herschel Grynszpan
|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group|Praeger]]
|location=New York
|year=1990
|isbn=0-275-93576-0}}
*{{cite book
|author=Shirer, William L.
|title=[[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]]
|publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]]
|location=New York
|year=1990
|isbn=0-671-72868-7
|authorlink=William L. Shirer}}
*{{cite book
|author=Yahil, Leni
|title=The Holocaust: the fate of European Jewry, 1932–1945
|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]
|location=Oxford [Oxfordshire]
|year=1990
|isbn=0-19-504523-8}}
*{{cite book
|author=Dawidowicz, Lucy
|title=The War Against the Jews: 1933–1945
|publisher=Bantam
|location=UK
|year=1986
|isbn=978-0-553-34532-2}}
*{{cite book
|last=Steinweis
|first=Alan E.
|title=Kristallnacht 1938
|year=2009
|publisher=Harvard University Press
|isbn=978-0-674-03623-9}}

;Books in German
* Christian Faludi: Die „Juni-Aktion&quot; 1938. Eine Dokumentation zur Radikalisierung der Judenverfolgung. Campus, Frankfurt a. M./New York 2013, ISBN 978-3-593-39823-5
* Hans-Dieter Arntz. &quot;Reichskristallnacht&quot;. Der Novemberpogrom 1938 auf dem Lande – Gerichtsakten und Zeugenaussagen am Beispiel der Eifel und Voreifel, Helios-Verlag, Aachen 2008, ISBN 978-3-938208-69-4
*{{Cite book
  | author=[[Hans-Jürgen Döscher|Döscher, Hans-Jürgen]]
  | title=Reichskristallnacht: Die Novemberpogrome 1938
  | year= 1988
  | publisher=Ullstein
  | language=German
  | isbn=978-3-550-07495-0 }}
*{{Cite book
  | author=Kaul, Friedrich Karl
  |author2=Herschel Feibel Grynszpan
   | title=Der Fall des Herschel Grynszpan
  | year=1965
  | publisher=Akademie-Verl
  | location=Berlin
  | language=German}} ''ISBN Unknown. ASIN B0014NJ88M. Available at [http://hgs.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/1/2/217.pdf Oxford Journals] (PDF)''
*{{cite book
  |author=Korb, Alexander
  |title=Reaktionen der deutschen Bevölkerung auf die Novemberpogrome im Spiegel amtlicher Berichte
  |publisher=[[VDM Publishing|VDM Verlag]]
  |location=Saarbrücken
  |language=German
  |year=2007
  |ISBN=978-3-8364-4823-9}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Lauber, Heinz
  |title=Judenpogrom: &quot;Reichskristallnacht&quot; November 1938 in Grossdeutschland : Daten, Fakten, Dokumente, Quellentexte, Thesen und Bewertungen (Aktuelles Taschenbuch)
  |publisher=Bleicher
  |language=German
  |year=1981
  |isbn=3-88350-005-4}}
*{{cite book
  |author1=Pätzold, Kurt  |author2=[[Irene Runge|Runge, Irene]]
  |title=Kristallnacht: Zum Pogrom 1938 (Geschichte)
  |publisher=Pahl-Rugenstein
  |location=Köln
  |year=1988
  |language=German
  |isbn=3-7609-1233-8}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Pehle, Walter H.
  |title=Der Judenpogrom 1938: Von der &quot;Reichskristallnacht&quot; zum Völkermord
  |publisher=Fischer Taschenbuch Verlag
  |location=Frankfurt am Main
  |year=1988
  |isbn=3-596-24386-6
  |language=German}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Schultheis, Herbert
  |title=Die Reichskristallnacht in Deutschland nach Augenzeugenberichten (Bad Neustadter Beiträge zur Geschichte und Heimatkunde Frankens)
  |publisher=Rotter Druck und Verlag
  |location=Bad Neustadt a. d. Saale
  |year=1985
  |isbn=3-9800482-3-3
  |language=German}}

;Online resources
*{{cite news
  | title=Hitler 'led henchmen' in Kristallnacht riots
  | work=Daily Telegraph
  | date=21 October 2008 
  | first=David
  | last=Wroe
  | url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/3235356/Hitler-led-henchmen-in-Kristallnacht-riots.html}}
*{{cite news
  | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081208072954/http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1032989.html
  | archivedate=8 December 2008
  | title=Hitler gave the order
  | work=Haaretz
  | date=31 October 2008 
  | first=Tom
  | last=Segev
  | url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1032989.html}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht
  | work = Holocaust studies
  |author1=Rabbi Eliahu Ellis |author2=Rabbi Shmuel Silinsky | publisher = Aish.com
  | url = http://www.aish.com/holocaust/overview/Kristallnacht.asp
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite news
  | title = Germany commemorates Nazi era 'Kristallnacht'
  | publisher = CNN.com
  | url = http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/europe/9811/09/germany.kristallnacht/
  | date = 1998-11-09
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080225014507/http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/europe/9811/09/germany.kristallnacht/ |archivedate = 25 February 2008}}
*{{cite web
  | title = What Was Kristallnacht?
  | work = THHP Short Essays
  | publisher = The Holocaust History Project
  | url = http://www.holocaust-history.org/short-essays/kristallnacht.shtml
  | date = 2003-11-28
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht &quot;Night of Crystal&quot;  –  &quot;Night of Broken Glass&quot;
  | work = Holocaust Prelude
  | publisher = Holocaust Education &amp; Archive Research Team
  | url = http://www.holocaustresearchproject.net/holoprelude/kristallnacht.html
  | date = 2006–2007
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web|title=Kristallnacht |work=From Aryanization to Cultural Loss: The Destruction of the Jewish Fashion Industry in Germany and Austria |author1=Frieda Miller |author2=Vancouver Holocaust Education Center |publisher=Center for Holocaust &amp; Genocide Studies, University of Minnesota |url=http://www.chgs.umn.edu/educational/brokenThreads/kristallnacht.html |date=2008-02-25 |accessdate=2008-05-20 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081210110045/http://www.chgs.umn.edu/educational/brokenThreads/kristallnacht.html |archivedate=10 December 2008 }} 
*{{cite web
  | title = Sitting at Nuremberg, Germany 29th July to 8th August 1946
  | work = The Trial of German Major War Criminals Volume 20
  | publisher = The Nizkor Project
  | url = http://www.nizkor.org/hweb/imt/tgmwc/tgmwc-20/tgmwc-20-194-03.shtml
  | year = 2006
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers – Kristallnacht
  | work = Teaching Eleanor Roosevelt; [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] National Historic Site, Hyde Park, New York
  |author1=Allida Black |author2=June Hopkins | publisher = US National Park Service archive (nps.gov)
  | url = http://www.nps.gov/archive/elro/glossary/kristallnacht.htm
  | year = 2003
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20|display-authors=etal}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht: A Nationwide Pogrom, November 9–10, 1938
  | work = Holocaust Encyclopedia
  | publisher = US Holocaust Memorial Museum
  | url = http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/index.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005201
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht: The November 1938 Pogroms
  | work = Online exhibitions, special topics
  | publisher = US Holocaust Memorial Museum
  | url = http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/kristallnacht_02/
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht
  | work = Yad Vashem's Photo Archives
  | author = Yad Vashem
  | publisher = The Holocaust Martyrs' and Heroes' Remembrance Authority
  | url = http://www1.yadvashem.org/exhibitions/kristallnacht/kristallnacht_home_photo.html
  | year = 2004
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21}} {{Dead link|date=April 2012|bot=H3llBot}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Kristallnacht}}
* [http://www.holocaustandhumanity.org/kristallnacht/events-leading-up-to-kristallnacht/ Events Leading Up to Kristallnacht – What led to the Night of Broken Glass?], by The Center for Holocaust and Humanity Education
* [http://www1.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20080424 ''Voices on Antisemitism'' Interview with Susan Warsinger] from the [http://www.ushmm.org/ United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]
* [http://www.ashkenazhouse.org ''Synagogues Memorial institute'' in Jerusalem]
* [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/exhibitions/kristallnacht/index.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki It Came From Within... 71 Years Since Kristallnacht] – Online exhibition from Yad Vashem, including survivor testimonies, archival footage, photos, and stories
* [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/education/interviews/ron.asp &quot;At 7:00 in the morning I was a student, and at 5:00, I was a criminal&quot;] – Interview with Miriam Ron, Witness to the Events of Kristallnacht

{{The Holocaust}}
{{Nazism}}
{{World War II}}
{{good article}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Kristallnacht| ]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 1938]]
[[Category:German words and phrases]]
[[Category:Holocaust anti-Jewish pogroms]]
[[Category:Holocaust antisemitic attacks and incidents]]
[[Category:Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Germany]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Austria]]
[[Category:Vandalized works of art]]
[[Category:1938 in Austria]]
[[Category:1938 in Germany]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>8y4rx7gc0brtnwgbv747i3scu307l0l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
