<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lord Kitchener Wants You</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6810396</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747606386</id>
      <parentid>747238009</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T09:21:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pintoch</username>
        <id>16990030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>change |id={{citeseerx}} to |citeseerx=</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25771">{{good article}}
{{Infobox advertising
| name                =Lord Kitchener Wants You
| image               = File:30a Sammlung Eybl Großbritannien. Alfred Leete (1882–1933) Britons (Kitchener) wants you (Briten Kitchener braucht Euch). 1914 (Nachdruck), 74 x 50 cm. (Slg.Nr. 552).jpg
| caption             =&quot;Britons: Lord Kitchener Wants You. Join Your Country's Army! God save the King.&quot;
| agency              =
| language            =English
| media               =watercolour; print
| product             =
| released            =1914
| producer            =
| country             =United Kingdom
}}
'''Lord Kitchener Wants You''' was a 1914 advertisement by [[Alfred Leete]] which was developed into a [[Military recruitment|recruitment poster]]. It depicted [[Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|Lord Kitchener]], the British [[Secretary of State for War]], above the words &quot;WANTS YOU&quot;. Kitchener, wearing the cap of a [[Field marshal (United Kingdom)|British Field Marshal]], stares and points at the viewer calling them to enlist in the British Army against the [[Central Powers]]. The image is considered one of the most iconic and enduring images of [[World War I]]. A hugely influential image and slogan, it has also inspired imitations in other countries, from the United States to the Soviet Union.

== Development ==
Prior to [[Conscription in the United Kingdom|the institution of conscription]] in 1916, the United Kingdom relied upon volunteers for military service. Until the outbreak of the First World War, [[Recruitment poster|recruiting posters]] had not been used in Britain on a regular basis since the Napoleonic Wars. UK government advertisements for contract work were handled by [[Office of Public Sector Information|His Majesty's Stationery Office]], who passed this task onto the publishers of [[James White (1775–1820)|R. F. White &amp; Sons]] in order to avoid paying the government rate to newspaper publishers. As war loomed in late 1913 the number of advertising contracts expanded to include other firms. [[J. E. B. Seely, 1st Baron Mottistone|J. E. B. Seely]], then the Secretary of State for War, awarded Sir Hedley Le Bas, Eric Field, and their Caxton Advertising Agency a contract to advertise for recruits in the major UK newspapers. Eric Field designed a prototype full-page advertisement with the [[Royal coat of arms of the United Kingdom|Coat of Arms]] of King [[George V]] and the phrase &quot;Your King and Country Need You.&quot; Britain declared war on the [[German Empire]] on 4 August 1914 and the first run of the full-page ran the next day in those newspapers owned by [[Alfred Harmsworth, 1st Viscount Northcliffe|Lord Northcliffe]].{{sfn|Messinger|1992|pp=214–216}}

[[File:King and Country Need You.JPG|thumb|upright|left|Eric Field's original design that caught the attention of Lord Kitchener]]
[[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom]] [[H. H. Asquith]] had appointed Kitchener as Secretary of State for War.&lt;ref name=Horatio&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/kitchener_lord_horatio.shtml|title=Historic Figures – Lord Horatio Kitchener (1850–1916)|website=[[BBC]]}} Retrieved 31 March 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Kitchener was the first currently serving soldier to hold the post and was given the task of recruiting a large army to fight [[History of Germany during World War I|Germany]]. Unlike some of his contemporaries who expected a short conflict, Kitchener foresaw a much longer war requiring hundreds of thousands of enlistees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qRiDAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT196&amp;lpg=PT196&amp;dq=leete+drawing+kitchener |title=Peace And War: Britain In 1914 |author-first=Nigel |author-last=Jones |publisher=Head of Zeus |date=2013-12-16  |pages=222–223 |isbn=978-1-78185-253-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Welch|Fox|2012|pp=79–80}} According to Gary S. Messinger, Kitchener reacted well to Field's advertisement although insisting &quot;that the ads should all end with 'God Save the King' and that they should not be changed from the original text, except to say 'Lord Kitchener needs YOU.'&quot; In the following months Le Bas formed an advisory committee of ad men to develop further newspaper recruiting advertisements, most of which ran vertically {{convert|11|in|cm}}, two columns wide.{{sfn|Messinger|1992|pp=216–217}}

[[Alfred Leete]], one of Caxton's illustrators, designed the now-famous image as a cover illustration for the 5 September 1914 issue of ''[[London Opinion]]'', a popular weekly magazine, taking cues from Field's earlier recruiting advertisement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tes.co.uk/article.aspx?storycode=385631 |title=Call to arms |last=Stride |first=Helena |publisher=TES |date=2008-05-12 |accessdate=2014-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jTBlAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT324 |title=Kitchener: Double volume |author-first=John |author-last=Pollock |publisher=Constable &amp; Robinson Ltd |date=2013-09-19 |isbn=978-1-4721-1334-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At the time, the magazine had a circulation of 300,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Jasper|last=Copping|date=2013-08-02|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/history/world-war-one/10218932/Your-Country-Needs-You-The-myth-about-the-First-World-War-poster-that-never-existed.html|title='Your Country Needs You' – The myth about the First World War poster that 'never existed'|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]}} Retrieved 16 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to requests for reproductions, the magazine offered postcard-sized copies for sale. The Parliamentary Recruiting Committee obtained permission to use the design in poster form.&lt;ref name=Kitch /&gt; A similar poster used the words &quot;YOUR COUNTRY NEEDS YOU&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sterlingtimes.co.uk/memorable_images53.htm Lord Kitchener &quot;Your country needs you!&quot;]. Sterling Times. Retrieved 31 March 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Kitchener, a &quot;figure of absolute will and power, an emblem of British masculinity&quot;,{{sfn|Tynan|2013|p=35}} was a natural subject for Leete's artwork as his name was directly attached to the recruiting efforts and the newly-forming [[Kitchener's Army]].{{sfn|Tynan|2013|pp=46–47}} Le Bas of Caxton Advertising (for whom Leete worked) chose Kitchener for the advertisement because Kitchener was &quot;the only soldier with a great war name, won in the field, within the memory of the thousands of men the country wanted.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hiley&quot; /&gt; Kitchener made his name in the [[Sudan Campaign]], avenging the death of [[Charles George Gordon|General Gordon]] with brutality and efficiency. He became a hero of &quot;New Imperialism&quot; alongside other widely regarded figures in Britain like [[Garnet Wolseley, 1st Viscount Wolseley|Field Marshal Wolseley]] and [[Frederick Roberts, 1st Earl Roberts|Field Marshal Roberts]].{{sfn|Welch|Fox|2012|pp=48–49}} {{sfn|Surridge|2001|pp=298, 305}} Kitchener's appearance including his bushy mustache and [[Court dress#Queen's Counsel|court dress jacket]] was reminiscent of romanticized [[Victorian era]] styles.{{sfn|Tynan|2013|pp=35–36}} Kitchener, {{convert|6|ft|2|in|cm|abbr=on}} tall and powerfully built, was for many the personification of military ethos so popular in the present [[Edwardian era]].{{sfn|Surridge|2001|pp=307–308}} After the scorched earth tactics and hard-fought victory of the [[Second Boer War]], Kitchener represented a return to the military victories of the colonial era.{{sfn|Welch|Fox|2012|p=52}} The fact that Kitchener's name is not used in the poster demonstrates how easily he was visually recognized.{{sfn|Surridge|2001|p=311}} David Lubin opines that the image may be one of the earliest successful [[celebrity endorsements]] as the commercial practice expanded greatly in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lubin&quot; /&gt; Keith Surridge posits that Kitchener's features evoked the harsh, feared militarism of the Germans which bode well for British fortune in the war.{{sfn|Surridge|2001|p=309}} Kitchener would not see the end of the war; he died onboard [[HMS Hampshire (1903)|HMS ''Hampshire'']] in 1916.{{sfn|Surridge|2001|pp=312–313}}

== Original versions by Alfred Leete ==
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot;&gt;
File:Kitchener poster by Alfred Leete.tif|The 5 September 1914 ''London Opinion'' magazine cover that inspired the posters.  The caption reads &quot;Your Country Needs YOU&quot;
File:Kitchener-leete.jpg|The &quot;Britons (Lord Kitchener) Wants YOU&quot; poster dating from September 1914
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Impact ==
{{Quote box
 |title =
 |quote =&quot;He is not a great man, he is a great poster.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ryQmldcyak4C&amp;pg=PA28 |title=Brushes and Bayonets: Cartoons, Sketches and Paintings of World War I |author-first=Lucinda |author-last=Gosling |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |year=2008 |page=28 |isbn=978-1-84603-095-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |source = [[Margot Asquith, Countess of Oxford and Asquith|Margot Asquith]]
 |align = right
 |width =
 |border =
 |fontsize =
 |bgcolor =
 |style =
 |title_bg =
 |title_fnt =
 |tstyle =
 |qalign =
 |qstyle =
 |quoted =
 |salign =
 |sstyle =
}}

Leete's drawing of Kitchener was the most famous image used in the [[British Army]] [[Recruitment to the British Army during World War I|recruitment campaign]] of [[World War I]].&lt;ref name=Horatio /&gt;&lt;ref name=Kitch /&gt; It continues to be considered a masterful piece of wartime propaganda as well as an enduring and iconic image of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digitalcollections.mcmaster.ca/case-study/british-first-world-war-recruiting-posters?page=2 |title=British First World War Recruiting Posters |publisher=[[McMaster University]] |date= |accessdate=2014-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/education/britain1906to1918/g6/background.htm |title=Propaganda 1914–18 |publisher=[[The National Archives (United Kingdom)|The National Archives]] |date= |accessdate=2014-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zmC1mS35ROcC&amp;pg=PA1&amp;lpg=PA1&amp;dq=kitchener+propaganda |title=British Propaganda in the 20th Century: Selling Democracy |first=Philip M. |last=Taylor |publisher=[[Edinburgh University Press]] |year=1999 |accessdate=2014-03-04 |page=1 |isbn=0-7486-1040-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Alastair |last=Sooke |url=http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20130703-can-propaganda-be-great-art |title=Can propaganda be great art? |publisher=BBC |date=2013-07-03 |accessdate=2014-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1-last=Hardie|author1-first=Martin|author2-last=Sabin|author2-first=Arthur Knowles|location=London|publisher=[[A &amp; C Black]]|title=War posters issued by belligerent and neutral nations 1914–1919|year=1920|url=https://archive.org/details/warpostersissued00hard|p=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ih0YAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT84|title=A History Of The First World War In 100 Objects: In Association With The Imperial War Museum|author1-first=John|author1-last=Hughes-Wilson|author2-first=Nigel|author2-last=Steel|publisher=[[Octopus Books]]|year=2014|isbn=978-1-84403-760-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recruitment posters in general have often been seen as a driving force helping to bring more than a million men into the Army.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/pals_01.shtml|title=British History in depth: The Pals Battalions in World War One|website=[[BBC]]}} Retrieved 31 March 2011&lt;/ref&gt; September 1914, coincident with publication of Leete's image, saw the [[Monthly recruiting figures for the British Army in the First World War|highest number of volunteers]] enlisted.&lt;ref name=Kitch /&gt; ''[[The Times]]'' recorded the scene in London on 3 January 1915; &quot;Posters appealing to recruits are to be seen on every hoarding, in most windows, in omnibuses, tramcars and commercial vans. The great base of [[Nelson's Column]] is covered with them. Their number and variety are remarkable. Everywhere Lord Kitchener sternly points a monstrously big finger, exclaiming 'I Want You'&quot;.&lt;ref name=Kitch /&gt; One contemporaneous publication decried the use of advertising methods to enlist soldiers: &quot;the cold, basilisk eye of a gaudily-lithographed Kitchener rivets itself upon the possible recruit and the outstretched finger of the British Minister of War is levelled at him like some revolver, with the words, 'I want you.' The idea is stolen from the advertisement of a 5c. American cigar.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|p=4|magazine=The Vital Issue|date=May 15, 1915|volume=2|issue=20|title=The Soul of England|author-first=R. L. |author-last=Orchelle|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CZAeAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA274|publisher=Francis J.L. Dorl}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it became one of the most famous posters in history,&lt;ref name=Kitch&gt;{{cite book|author-last=Simkins|author-first=Peter|year=1988|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WAgNAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA122|title=Kitchener's army: the raising of the new armies, 1914–16|pages=122–123|publisher=[[Manchester University Press]]|isbn=9780719026386}}&lt;/ref&gt; its widespread circulation did not halt the decline in recruiting.&lt;ref name=Kitch /&gt;
[[File:Men, Materials, and Money.tif|right|300px|thumb|This 30-word poster was an official product of the Parliamentary Recruitment Committee and was more popular contemporaneously.]] The use of Kitchener's image for recruiting posters was so widespread that Lady Asquith referred to the Field Marshal simply as &quot;the Poster.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lubin&quot; /&gt;
The placement of the Kitchener posters including Alfred Leete's design has been examined and questioned following an [[Imperial War Museum]] publication in 1997. The War Museum suggested that the poster itself was a &quot;non event&quot; and was made popular by postwar advertising by the war museum, perhaps conflating Leete's design with the so-called &quot;30-word&quot; poster, an official product from the Parliamentary Recruitment Committee.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hiley&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hiley|first=Nicholas|title=Kitchener wants YOU and Daddy what did YOU do in the great war?: The Myth of British Recruiting Posters|journal=Imperial War Museum Review|publisher=[[Imperial War Museum]]|pages=40–58|year=1997|volume=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The 30-word design was the most popular recruitment poster at the time having been printed ten times the volume of Leete's image.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-28642846|date=4 August 2014|title=Kitchener: The most famous pointing finger|first=Adam|last=Eley|website=[[BBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Leete's image has been praised for being more arresting while his accompanying text is also far less verbose. The official wording, taken from a Kitchener speech, may seem more fitting for a character in a [[Henry James]] novel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lubin&quot; /&gt; The 30-word recruiting poster was developed as Britons' collective hopes of the war being over by Christmas were dashed in January 1915 and volunteer enlistments fell.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Volunteerism and Early Recruitment Efforts in Devonshire, August 1914 – December 1915|journal=[[The Historical Journal]]|year=2009|volume=52|issue=3|pages=641–666|doi=10.1017/S0018246X09990069|first=Bonnie J.|last=White|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A 2013 book researched by James Taylor counters the popular belief that the Leete design was an influential recruitment tool during the war. He claims the original artwork was acquired by the Imperial War Museum in 1917 and catalogued as a poster in error.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor&quot; /&gt; Though the image of Kitchener (Britain's most popular soldier) inspired several other poster designs, Taylor says he can find no evidence in photographs of the time that the Leete poster was used, although a photograph from 15 December 1914 taken at the [[Lancashire and Yorkshire Railway]] station in [[Liverpool]] clearly depicts Leete's depiction among other recruiting posters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrm.org.uk/ourcollection/photo?group=Horwich&amp;amp;objid=1997-7059_HOR_F_1541&amp;keywords=1914|website=[[National Railway Museum]]|title=First World War posters, 1914}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The effectiveness of the image upon the viewer is attributed to what E. B. Goldstein has called the 'differential rotation effect.' Because of this effect, Kitchener's eyes and his foreshortened arm and hand appear to follow the viewer regardless of the viewer's orientation to the artwork.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|citeseerx = 10.1.1.211.6850|title=Affine Distortions of Pictorial Space: Some Predictions for Goldstein (1987) That La Gournerie (1859) Might Have Made|journal=[[Journal of Experimental Psychology]]:Human Perception and Performance|publisher=[[American Psychological Association]] |year=1988 |volume=14|issue=2|pages=305–311|doi=10.1037/0096-1523.14.2.305|last1=Cutting|first1=James E.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.perceptionweb.com/abstract.cgi?id=p3454 |year=2004 |first1=Jan J. |last1=Koenderink |first2=Andrea J. |last2=van Doorn |author3-first=Astrid M. L. |author3-last=Kappers |author4-first=James T. |author4-last=Todd |title=Pointing out of the picture |journal=[[Perception (journal)|Perception]]|volume=33 |issue=5 |pages=513–530 |accessdate=2014-03-03 |doi=10.1068/p3454}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://people.psych.cornell.edu/~jec7/pubs/compensation.pdf|title=Compensation is unnecessary for the perception of faces in slanted pictures|journal=Perception &amp; Psychophysics|year=1990|volume=48|issue=1|page=2|first1=Thomas A.|last1=Busey|first2=Nuala P.|last2=Brady|author3-first=James E.|author3-last=Cutting|publisher=[[Psychonomic Society]]|doi=10.3758/bf03205006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historian [[Carlo Ginzburg]] compared Leete's image of Kitchener to similar images of Christ and Alexander the Great as depicting the viewer's contact with a powerful figure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.mediastudies.it/IMG/pdf/Carlo_Ginzburg_Your_Country_Needs_You.pdf|author-first=Carlo|author-last=Ginzburg|authorlink=Carlo Ginzburg|year=2001|title='Your Country Needs You': A Case Study in Political Iconography|journal=[[History Workshop Journal]]|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|issue=52|pages=1–22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pearl James commented on Ginzburg's analysis agreeing that the strength of the connotation lies with a clever use of [[discursive psychology]] and that art historical methods better illuminate why this image has such resonance.{{sfn|James|2009|p=21}} The [[All caps|capitalized]] word &quot;YOU&quot; grabs the reader, bringing them directly to Kitchener's message.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lubin&quot; /&gt; The textual focus on &quot;you&quot; engages the reader about their own participation in the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://scientiamilitaria.journals.ac.za/pub/article/viewFile/543/574 |format=pdf |title=Art and Propaganda in an Age of War: The Role of Posters |author-last=Chambers |author-first=R. |journal=[[South African Journal of Military Studies]] |volume=13 |issue=4 |year=1983 |accessdate=2014-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nicholas Hiley differs in that Leete's portrayal of Kitchener is less about immediate recruiting statistics but the myth that has grown around the image, including ironic parodies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hiley&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|James|2009|p=18}} Leete's Kitchener poster caught the attention of a then eleven-year-old [[George Orwell]], who may have used as it the basis for his description of the &quot;Big Brother&quot; posters in his novel ''[[1984 (novel)|1984]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lubin&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Losing Sight: War, Authority, and Blindness in British and American Visual Cultures, 1914–22|first=David M.|last=Lubin|doi=10.1111/j.1467-8365.2010.00847.x|journal=[[Art History (journal)|Art History]]|volume=34|issue=4|pages=796–817|date=September 2011|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1467-8365.2010.00847.x/full|via=[[Wiley Online Library]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997 the British Army created a recruiting advertisement re-using Leete's image substituting Kitchener's face with that of a British Army [[non-commissioned officer]] of African descent.{{sfn|Surridge|2001|p=298}} Leete's image of Kitchener is featured on a 2014 £2 coin produced by sculptor John Bergdahl for the [[Royal Mint]].  The coin was the first of a five-year series to commemorate the centennial of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.royalmint.com/shop/The_100th_Anniversary_of_the_First_World_War_Outbreak_2014_UK_2_pound_Brilliant_Uncirculated_Coin|title=The 100th Anniversary of the FWW – Outbreak UK £2 Brilliant Uncirculated Coin|publisher=[[Royal Mint]] |date=2014-02-20 |accessdate=2014-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Use of Leete's image of Kitchener has been criticized by some for its pro-war connotation in light of the human losses of the First World War and the violence of Kitchener's campaign in Sudan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.heraldscotland.com/news/home-news/calls-for-offensive-kitchener-wwi-centenary-coin-to-be-scrapped.1389700567 |title=Calls for 'offensive' Kitchener WWI centenary coin to be scrapped |work=[[Herald Scotland]] |date=2014-01-14 |accessdate=2014-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2014, one of only four original posters known to exist went to auction for more than [[Pound sterling|£]]10,000. The other three originals exist on display in [[State Library of Victoria]], the [[Museum of Brands, Packaging and Advertising]], and the [[Imperial War Museum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/lord-kitchener-wants-you-rare-first-world-war-posters-go-sale-1455853 |title=Lord Kitchener Wants You: Rare First World War Posters Go On Sale |newspaper=[[International Business Times]] |first=David |last=Sim |date=July 8, 2014 |accessdate=2014-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.robertopiecollection.com/page-GB.asp?id=332 |title=About Us |publisher=Robert Opie Collection |date= |accessdate=2014-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Leete's design was also used for a [[corn maze]] in the Skylark Garden Centre in [[Wimblington]] to mark the centenary of World War I.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=18 July 2014|title=Lord Kitchener WW1 poster created in Cambridgeshire maize maze|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-cambridgeshire-28364737|website=[[BBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Imitations ==
The image of Lord Kitchener with his hand pointing directly at the viewer has inspired numerous imitations:
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:John Bull - World War I recruiting poster.jpeg|British World War I recruiting poster featuring the national personification, [[John Bull]], c. 1915. &quot;Who's absent? Is it you?&quot;
File:Unclesamwantyou.jpg|[[United States]], 1917. [[James Montgomery Flagg|J. M. Flagg]]'s [[Uncle Sam#World War I recruitment poster|Uncle Sam]] recruited soldiers for [[World War I]] and [[World War II]]. &quot;I Want YOU for U.S. Army&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Wc-DRZJ8OwIC&amp;pg=PA3|page=3|title=Uncle Sam Wants You : World War I and the Making of the Modern American Citizen|first=Christopher|last=Capozzola|year=2008|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-533549-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
File:Bat Zion I want your Old New Land join Jewish regiment.jpg|United States, [[World War I]]. [[Zion#Daughter of Zion|Daughter of Zion]] (in [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]]): &quot;Your [[The Old New Land|Old New Land]] must have you! Join the [[Jewish Legion|Jewish regiment]]&quot;
File:Julius Ussy Engelhard 1919 You too must join Reichswehr.jpg|[[Reichswehr]] recruitment poster by Julius Ussy Engelhard, 1919. &quot;You too should join the Reichswehr&quot;
File:Ti zapisalsya dobrovolcem 1920 Moor.svg|Bolshevik recruitment poster from the Civil War of 1920, by Dmitri Moor. &quot;You, have you volunteered?
File:Cartaz Revolucionário.jpg|Brazilian [[Constitutionalist Revolution]] recruitment poster, 1932. &quot;You have a duty to fulfill. Ask your conscience!&quot;
File:Smokey3.jpg|United States 1985 [[Smokey Bear]] poster.  The &quot;Only You&quot; refers to his famous quotation, &quot;Only You Can Prevent Forest Fires&quot;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Recruitment to the British Army during the First World War]]

== References ==

=== Citations ===
{{reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
*{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rziXfHf2L1gC&amp;pg=PA35&amp;lpg=PA35&amp;dq=Hiley+N.+(1997)+Kitchener+wants+YOU+and+Daddy+what+did+YOU+do+in+the+great+war |title=Picture This: World War I Posters and Visual Culture |publisher=[[University of Nebraska]]|year=2009|author-last=James|author-first=Pearl |isbn=978-0-8032-2610-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=u1npAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA150&amp;lpg=PA150&amp;dq=kitchener+propaganda |title=British Propaganda and the State in the First World War |author-first=Gary S. |author-last=Messinger |publisher=[[Manchester University Press]] |year=1992 |pages=214–216 |isbn=0-7190-3014-5|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|title=More than a great poster: Lord Kitchener and the image of the military hero|first=Keith|last=Surridge|journal=[[Historical Research]]|volume=74|issue=185|pages=298|year=2001|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1468-2281.00129/pdf|via=[[Wiley Online Library]]|ref=harv|doi=10.1111/1468-2281.00129}}
*{{cite book|title=British Army Uniform and the First World War: Men in Khaki|first=Jane|last=Tynan|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=b-WxAgAAQBAJ|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|year=2013|isbn=978-1-137-31831-2|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lF7nAR9IpCUC|title=Justifying War: Propaganda, Politics and the Modern Age |publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|editor-first1=David |editor-last1=Welch|editor-first2=Jo|editor-last2=Fox|year=2012|accessdate=2014-03-04|isbn=978-0-230-24627-0|ref=harv}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite book|title=The Amazing Story of the Kitchener Poster|last1=Thatcher|first1=Martyn|last2=Quinn|first2=Anthony|publisher=Funfly Design|date=2013-10-01|isbn=978-0-9569094-2-8}}
{{Commons category}}

[[Category:British culture]]
[[Category:1914 in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Political slogans]]
[[Category:Cultural history of World War I]]
[[Category:Propaganda posters]]
[[Category:Military recruitment]]</text>
      <sha1>n3dxslvwn2m5a150qov2mr7t2l9hwse</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
