<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Madagascar Plan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1376379</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745253140</id>
      <parentid>745253094</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T03:26:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Donner60</username>
        <id>12744454</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/43.255.32.130|43.255.32.130]] ([[User talk:43.255.32.130|talk]]): Editing tests ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.1.21)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19859">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
The '''Madagascar Plan''' was a proposal by the [[Nazi Germany|Nazi German]] government to relocate the [[Jew]]ish population of Europe to the island of [[Madagascar]]. [[Franz Rademacher]], head of the Jewish Department of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs for the German government, proposed the idea in June 1940, shortly before the [[Battle of France|Fall of France]]. The proposal called for the handing over of control of Madagascar, then a French colony, to Germany as part of the French surrender terms.

The idea of deporting [[Polish Jews]] to Madagascar was investigated by the Polish government in 1937,{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=82}}{{sfn|Nicosia|2008|p=280}} but the task force sent to evaluate the island's potential determined that only 5,000 to 7,000 families could be accommodated, or even as few as 500 families by some estimates.{{efn|name=population|[[the World Factbook]] estimates Madagascar's population as 23,812,681 {{as of|2015|July|lc=y}}.{{sfn|World Factbook|2015}} }} As efforts by the Nazis to encourage emigration of the Jewish population of Germany before World War II were only partially successful, the idea of deporting Jews to Madagascar was revived by the Nazi government in 1940.

Rademacher recommended on 3 June 1940 that Madagascar should be made available as a destination for the Jews of Europe. With [[Adolf Hitler]]'s approval, [[Adolf Eichmann]] released a memorandum on 15 August 1940 calling for the resettlement of a million Jews per year for four years, with the island governed as a police state under the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]]. They assumed that many Jews would succumb to its harsh conditions should the plan be implemented.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=162}} The plan was not viable due to the British [[Blockade of Germany (1939–45)|naval blockade]]. It was postponed after the Axis lost the [[Battle of Britain]] in September 1940, and was permanently shelved in 1942 with the commencement of the [[Final Solution]], towards which it had functioned as an important psychological step.{{sfn|Browning|1995|pp=18–19,127–128}}[[File:Madagascar-Pos.png|right|thumb|Madagascar lies off the east coast of Africa]]

==Origins==
[[file:Paul Anton de Lagarde.png|thumb|German [[oriental studies|orientalist]] [[Paul de Lagarde]] was an early author of the concept of relocation of European Jews to Madagascar.{{sfn|Gerdmar|2009|p=180}}]]
In the late 1800s and early 1900s there were a number of resettlement plans for European Jews that were precursors to the Madagascar Plan. [[Paul de Lagarde]], an [[Oriental studies|Orientalist]] scholar, first suggested evacuating the European Jews to Madagascar in his 1878 work ''Deutsche Schriften'' (&quot;German Writings&quot;).{{sfn|Gerdmar|2009|p=180}}{{sfn|Ehrlich|2009|p=452}} Members of the [[Zionist]] movement in 1904–1905 seriously debated the [[British Uganda Programme]], by which [[Russian Jews]], who were in immediate danger from ongoing [[Pogroms in Russia#1903–1906|pogroms]], would be settled in what today is [[Kenya]]. The plan was later rejected as unworkable by the [[Zionist Congress]].{{sfn|Telushkin|2001|pp=280–281}} Adherents of [[Homeland for the Jewish people|territorialism]] split off from the main Zionist movement and continued to search for a location where Jews might settle and create a state, or at least an autonomous area.{{sfn|Cesarani|1995|p=101}} The idea of Jewish resettlement in Madagascar was promoted by British antisemites [[Henry Hamilton Beamish]], [[Arnold Leese]], and others.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=81}} With the cooperation of the French, the Polish government commissioned a task force in 1937 to examine the possibility of deporting [[Polish Jews]] to the island.{{sfn|Nicosia|2008|p=280}} The head of the commission, {{illm|Mieczysław Lepecki|pl}}, felt the island could accommodate 5,000 to 7,000 families, but Jewish members of the group estimated that only 500 or even fewer families could safely be accommodated.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=82}}{{efn|name=population}}

==In Nazi Germany==
[[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|Racism]] and [[antisemitism]] were basic tenets of the [[Nazi Party]] and the Nazi government.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=31}} Discrimination and violent attacks against Jews began immediately after the [[Machtergreifung|seizure of power]] in 1933.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=203}} Violence and economic pressure were used by the Nazis to encourage Jews to voluntarily leave the country.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=67–69}} By 1939, around 250,000 of Germany's 437,000 Jews had emigrated to the United States, Argentina, the United Kingdom, Palestine, and other countries.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=127}}{{sfn|Evans|2005|pp=555–558}}

The Nazi leadership seized on the idea of deporting the remaining German Jews overseas. Barren, unproductive lands were viewed as appropriate destinations as this would prevent the deportees from flourishing in their new location.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=452–453}} In his May 1940 memorandum to Hitler, ''Concerning the Treatment of the Alien Population in the East'', ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] declared that he hoped to see &quot;the term 'Jew'&amp;nbsp;[...] completely eliminated through the massive immigration of all Jews to Africa or some other colony&quot;.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=508}}

===Planning begins===
Initial discussions began to take place in 1938 among Nazi ideologues such as [[Julius Streicher]], [[Hermann Göring]], [[Alfred Rosenberg]], and [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]],.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000|pp=320–322}} Ten per cent of Jews under German jurisdiction by that date were Polish nationals. [[Józef Lipski]], the Polish ambassador to Germany, expressed his country's reluctance to take them back, and the Polish government decreed that Polish passport holders would not be permitted to return except under specific conditions.{{sfn|Hilberg|1973|p=258}} When Ribbentrop raised the matter with French foreign minister [[Georges Bonnet]] in December of that year, Bonnet expressed French reluctance to receive more German Jews and inquired if measures could be taken to prevent their arrival. France itself was contemplating how to deport some 10,000 Jews and considered whether Madagascar might be an appropriate destination.{{sfn|Hilberg|1973|p=259}} Planning for German deportations to Madagascar formally began in 1940.{{sfn|Hilberg|1973|p=260}} [[Franz Rademacher]], recently appointed head of the Jewish Department of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, forwarded on 3 June to his superior, the diplomat [[Martin Luther (diplomat)|Martin Luther]], a memorandum on the fate of the Jews.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=82}} &quot;The desirable solution is: all Jews out of Europe,&quot; said Rademacher.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=508}} He briefly considered Palestine as a destination, but deemed it unsuitable, as he considered it undesirable that a strong Jewish state should be created in the Middle East. As well, Palestine was at the time under British control.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=162}} Rademacher recommended that the French colony of Madagascar should be made available as a destination for the Jews of Europe as one of the terms of the surrender of France, which the [[Battle of France|Germans had invaded]] on 10 May 1940.{{sfn|Browning|2004|pp=82–85}} The resettled Jews, noted Rademacher, could be used as hostages to ensure &quot;future good behaviour of their racial comrades in America&quot;.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=508}} The plan was developed by Referat D III of the ''Abteilung Deutschland''.{{sfn|Hilberg|1973|pp=260–261}}

Luther broached the subject with Foreign Minister Ribbentrop, who was simultaneously developing a similar scheme. By 18 June, Hitler and Ribbentrop spoke of the Plan with Italian leader [[Benito Mussolini]] as a possibility that could be pursued after the defeat of France.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=508}}{{sfn|Kershaw|2000|pp=320–322}} Once he learned of the plan, SS-''[[Obergruppenführer]]'' [[Reinhard Heydrich]], chief of the [[RSHA|Reich Main Security Office]] (RSHA), insisted that Ribbentrop relinquish any future responsibility for the Plan to that office. As Heydrich had been appointed by Göring in January 1939 to oversee Jewish evacuation from German-occupied territory, the [[Jewish question]] was hence under his purview.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000|pp=320–322}} [[Adolf Eichmann]], head of the RSHA Sub-Department IV-B4, which dealt with Jewish affairs and evacuation, soon became involved. On 15 August, he released a memorandum titled ''Reichssicherheitshauptamt: Madagaskar Projekt'' (Reich Main Security Office: Madagascar Project), calling for the resettlement of a million Jews per year for four years and abandoning the idea of retaining any Jews in Europe. The RSHA, he emphasized, would control all aspects of the program.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=87}} While Rademacher called for the colony to be under German control but self-governing under Jewish administration, Eichmann made it plain that he intended for the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] to control and oversee every aspect of life on the island, which they would govern as a police state.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=577}}

Most Nazi bureaux, including the Foreign Office, the Security Police, and the [[General Government|''Generalgouvernement'']]  pinned their hopes on the plan as the last chance to &quot;solve the Jewish problem&quot; through emigration.{{sfn|Hilberg|1973|p=261}} In particular, [[Hans Frank]], governor of the [[General Government]] (the occupied portion of Poland), viewed the forced resettlement to Madagascar as being preferable to the heretofore piecemeal efforts at deportation into Poland. As of 10 July, deportations into Poland were cancelled and construction of the [[Warsaw ghetto]] was halted, since it appeared to be unnecessary.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000|pp=320–322}}

===Planning continues===
Rademacher envisioned the founding of a European bank that would ultimately liquidate all European Jewish assets to pay for the plan. This bank would then play an intermediary role between Madagascar and the rest of the world, as Jews would not be allowed to interact financially with outsiders. Göring's office of the [[Four Year Plan]] would oversee the administration of the plan's economics.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=88}}

Additionally, Rademacher foresaw roles for other government agencies. Ribbentrop's [[Foreign Office (Germany)|Foreign Affairs Ministry]] would negotiate terms with the French for the handover of Madagascar to Germany. It would also play a part in crafting other treaties to deal with Europe's Jews. Its Information Department, along with [[Joseph Goebbels]] and his [[Ministry of Public Enlightenment and Propaganda]], would control the flow of information at home and abroad. [[Viktor Brack]], a division chief in the [[Hitler's Chancellery (Kanzlei des Führers)|Chancellery]] of the [[Führer]], would oversee transportation. The SS would undertake the expulsion of the Jews from Europe and govern the island as a police state.{{sfn|Browning|2004|pp=87–88}} The Nazis expected that after the invasion of the United Kingdom in [[Operation Sea Lion]] that they would commandeer the British merchant fleet to transport the Jews to Madagascar.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=88}} Many deportees were expected to perish in the harsh conditions or die at the hands of the SS.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=509}}

===Plan abandoned===
With the failure to defeat the [[Royal Air Force]] in the [[Battle of Britain]], the proposed invasion of the UK was postponed indefinitely on 17 September 1940. This meant the British merchant fleet would not be at Germany's disposal for use in evacuations, and planning for the Madagascar proposal stalled.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=88}} In late August 1940, Rademacher entreated Ribbentrop to hold a meeting at his ministry to begin drawing up a panel of experts to consolidate the plan. Ribbentrop never responded. Likewise, Eichmann's memorandum languished with Heydrich, who never approved it.{{sfn|Browning|2004|p=88}} Establishment of ghettos in Warsaw and other cities in Poland resumed in August 1940.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=165}} Hitler continued to mention the plan until February 1942, when the idea was permanently shelved.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|p=164}} British Empire forces took the island from [[Vichy France]] in the [[Battle of Madagascar]] in November 1942 and control was transferred to the [[Free French]].

At the end of 1940, Hitler asked Himmler to draft a new plan for the elimination of the Jews of Europe, and Himmler passed along the task to Heydrich. His draft proposed the deportation of the Jews to the Soviet Union via Poland.{{sfn|Longerich|2012|p=511}} The later ''[[Generalplan Ost]]'' (General Plan for the East), prepared by Professor [[Konrad Meyer]] and others, called for deporting the entire population of occupied Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union to Siberia, either for use as slave labour or to be murdered after the Soviet defeat.{{sfn|Snyder|2010|p=416}} After the Axis failure in the [[Battle of Moscow]] and the entry of the United States into the war in December 1941, Hitler resolved that the Jews of Europe were to be exterminated immediately rather than after the war, which now had no end in sight.{{sfn|Longerich|2000|p=2}} Since transporting masses of people into a combat zone would be impossible, Heydrich decided that the Jews would be killed in [[extermination camp]]s set up in occupied areas of Poland.{{sfn|Longerich|2010|pp=309–310}} The total number of Jews murdered during the resulting [[Holocaust]] is estimated at 5.5 to 6 million people.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=318}}

==See also==
*[[Jewish Autonomous Oblast]]
*[[Proposals for a Jewish state]]

==References==

===Explanatory notes===
{{notelist}}

==Citations==
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite book | last = Browning | first = Christopher R. | authorlink = Christopher Browning | title = The Origins of the Final Solution : The Evolution of Nazi Jewish Policy, September 1939 – March 1942 | series = Comprehensive History of the Holocaust | year = 2004 | publisher = University of Nebraska Press | location = Lincoln | isbn = 0-8032-1327-1 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Browning | first = Christopher R. | authorlink = Christopher Browning | title = The Path to Genocide: Essays on Launching the Final Solution | year = 1995 | publisher = Cambridge University Press| location = Cambridge | isbn = 978-0-521-55878-5 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Cesarani | first = David | authorlink = David Cesarani | title = The &quot;Jewish Chronicle&quot; and Anglo-Jewry: 1841–1991 | year = 1995 | origyear = 1995 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge; New York | isbn = 978-0-521-43434-8 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite web | url = https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ma.html| title = The World Factbook | work = [[Central Intelligence Agency]] | accessdate=23 February 2016 | ref = {{sfnRef|World Factbook|2015}} }}
* {{cite book | last = Ehrlich | first = Mark Avrum | title = Encyclopedia of the Jewish Diaspora: Origins, Experiences, and Culture | volume = 1 | year = 2009 | publisher = ABC-CLIO | location = Santa Barbara, CA | isbn = 978-1-85109-873-6 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Evans | first = Richard J. | authorlink = Richard J. Evans | year = 2005 | title = [[The Third Reich in Power]] | publisher = Penguin | location = New York | isbn =978-0-14-303790-3 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Evans | first = Richard J. | year = 2008 | title = The Third Reich at War | publisher = Penguin | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-14-311671-4 | ref = harv}}
*{{cite book | last = Gerdmar | first = Anders | title = Roots of Theological Anti-Semitism: German Biblical Interpretation and the Jews, from Herder and Semler to Kittel and Bultmann | publisher = Koninklijke Brill | location = Leiden | series = Studies in Jewish History and Culture | year = 2009 | isbn = 90-04-16851-6 | ref = harv}}
*{{cite book | last = Hilberg | first = Raul | authorlink = Raul Hilberg | year = 1973 | title= The Destruction of the European Jews | publisher = New Viewpoints| location = New York | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Kershaw | first = Ian | authorlink = Ian Kershaw | title = Hitler: 1936–1945: Nemesis | year = 2000 | publisher = Norton | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-393-04994-7 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Kershaw | first = Ian | title = Hitler: A Biography | year = 2008 | origyear = 2000 | publisher = Norton | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-393-06757-6 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite journal | last = Longerich | first = Peter | authorlink = Peter Longerich | title = The Wannsee Conference in the Development of the 'Final Solution' | year = 2000 | journal = Holocaust Educational Trust Research Papers | volume = 1 | issue = 2 | publisher = The Holocaust Educational Trust | location = London | format = PDF | url = http://www.ghwk.de/ghwk/engl/texts/wannsee-conference.pdf | isbn = 0-9516166-5-X | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Longerich | first = Peter | title = Holocaust: The Nazi Persecution and Murder of the Jews | year = 2010 | isbn = 978-0-19-280436-5 | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford; New York | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Longerich | first = Peter | year = 2012 | title = Heinrich Himmler: A Life | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford; New York | isbn = 978-0-19-959232-6 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Nicosia | first = Francis R.  | title = Zionism and Anti-Semitism in Nazi Germany | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=JTtGXWzfD10C&amp;pg=PA280 | year = 2008 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge; New York | isbn = 978-0-521-88392-4 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Shirer | first = William L. | authorlink = William L. Shirer | title = [[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]] | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | year = 1960 | isbn = 978-0-671-62420-0 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Snyder | first = Timothy | authorlink = Timothy D. Snyder | title = Bloodlands: Europe between Hitler and Stalin | year= 2010 | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-465-00239-9 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Telushkin | first = Joseph | authorlink = Joseph Telushkin | title = Jewish Literacy: The Most Important Things to Know About the Jewish Religion, Its People, and Its History | year = 2001 | origyear = 1991 | publisher = Harper Collins | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-688-08506-3 | ref = harv}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | last = Ainsztein | first = Reuben | title = Jewish Resistance in Nazi-Occupied Eastern Europe | year = 1974 | publisher = Elek Books | location = London | isbn = 978-0-236-15490-6}}
* {{cite book | last = Brechtken | first = Magnus | title = Madagaskar für die Juden: Antisemitische Idee und politische Praxis 1885–1945 | year = 1998 | publisher = Wissenschaftsverlag | location =  Oldenbourg | language = German | isbn = 3-486-56384-X}}
* {{cite web | last = Rademacher | first = Franz | authorlink = Franz Rademacher | title = The Madagascar Plan: The Jewish Question in the Peace Treaty | date = 3 July 1940 | work = Jewish Virtual Library | publisher = American-Israeli Cooperative Enterprise | url = https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Holocaust/Madagascar.html}}

==External links==
* {{YouTube|46pwZyTC3yg|Video overview of the Madagascar Plan}} by the German historian {{illm|Magnus Brechtken|de}}
* [http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Holocaust/Madagascar.html Text of the Madagascar Plan]
{{The Holocaust}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Jewish emigration from Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:History of Madagascar]]
[[Category:Settlement schemes]]
[[Category:Germany–Madagascar relations]]
[[Category:Adolf Eichmann]]
[[Category:Proposed Jewish states]]</text>
      <sha1>tavd0835yfh4xosci0kohes9gtbu0sy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
