<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Military of Mycenaean Greece</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>48407885</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745756393</id>
      <parentid>727003150</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-23T03:27:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Sources */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22465">{{good article}}
[[File:14 century BC Eastern.png|thumbnail|300px|Eastern Mediterranean and the Middle East during the 14th century (Mycenaean Greece in purple).]]
The military nature of [[Mycenaean Greece]] (c. 1600–1100 BC) in the Late [[Bronze Age]] is evident by the numerous [[weapon]]s unearthed, warrior and combat representations in contemporary art, as well as by the preserved Greek [[Linear B]] records.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Cline|2012|p=305}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cline313/&gt; The Mycenaeans invested in the development of military infrastructure with military production and [[logistics]] being supervised directly from the [[Palace|palatial centres]].&lt;ref name=Cline313/&gt;&lt;ref name=Palaima367/&gt; This militaristic [[ethos]] inspired later [[Ancient Greece|Ancient Greek]] tradition, and especially [[Homer#Epics|Homer's epics]], which are focused on the heroic nature of the Mycenaean-era warrior élite.&lt;ref name=Castleden235/&gt;

Late Bronze Age Greece was divided into a series of warrior [[Mycenaean_Greece#Palatial_states|kingdom]]s, the most important being centered in [[Mycenae]], to which the culture of this era owes its name, [[Tiryns]], [[Pylos]] and [[Thebes (Greece)|Thebes]]. From the 15th century BC, Mycenaean power began expanding towards the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]], the [[Anatolia]]n coast and [[Cyprus]]. Mycenaean armies shared several common features with other contemporary Late Bronze Age powers: they were initially based on heavy [[infantry]], with [[spear]]s, large [[shield]]s and in some occasions [[armour|armor]]. In the 13th century BC, Mycenaean units underwent a transformation in [[military tactics|tactics]] and weaponry and became more uniform and flexible and their weapons became smaller and lighter. Some representative types of Mycenaean armor/weapons were the [[boar's tusk helmet]] and the &quot;Figure-of-eight&quot; shield. Moreover, most features of the later [[Hoplite#Equipment|hoplite panoply]] of [[Classical Greece]] were already known at this time.

==Military ethos==
[[File:Pottery soldiers 12 c BC, NAMA 1246 102885.jpg|thumbnail|[[Warrior Vase|Krater]] depicting marching soldiers, Mycenae, c. 1200 BC.]]
The presence of the important and influential military aristocracy that formed in Mycenaean society offers an overwhelming impression of a fierce and warlike people. This impression of militarism is reinforced by the fortifications erected throughout Mycenaean Greece,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|p=118}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cline303&gt;{{harvnb|Cline|2012|p=303}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the large numbers and quality of the weapons retrieved from the Mycenaean royal graves, artistic representations of war scenes and the textual evidence provided by the [[Linear B]] records.&lt;ref name=Cline313&gt;{{harvnb|Cline|2012|p=313}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Palaima367&gt;{{harvnb|Palaima|1999|pp=367–368}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Linear B scripts also offer some detail about the organization of the military personnel, while military production and logistics were supervised by a central authority from the palaces.&lt;ref name=Palaima367/&gt; According to the records in the palace of [[Pylos]], every rural community (the ''damos'') was obliged to supply a certain number of men who had to serve in the army; similar service was also performed by the aristocracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=10}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The main divinities who appear to be of warlike nature were [[Ares]] (Linear B: ''A-re'') and [[Athena|Athena Potnia]] (Linear B: ''A-ta-na Po-ti-ni-ja'').&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tactics and evolution==
[[File:NAMA Mycènes bouclier 2.jpg|thumbnail|150px|Fresco depicting a &quot;figure-of-eight&quot; shield, Mycenae.]]
Mycenaean armies shared several common features with other significant Late Bronze Age powers: they were initially based on heavy [[infantry]], which bore spears, large shields and, in some occasions, armor.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Howard|2011|p=7}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the 13th century BC, Mycenaean warfare underwent major changes both in tactics and weaponry. Armed units became more uniform and flexible, while weapons became smaller and lighter.&lt;ref name=Cline313/&gt; The spear remained the main weapon among Mycenaean warriors until the [[Late Bronze Age collapse|collapse]] of the Bronze Age, while the sword played a secondary role in combat.&lt;ref name=Howard50/&gt;

The precise role and contribution of [[Chariot|war chariots]] in battlefield is a matter of dispute due to the lack of sufficient evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Howard|2011|p=63}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In general, it appears that during the first centuries (16th–14th century BC) chariots were used as a fighting vehicle while later in the 13th century BC their role was limited to a battlefield transport.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fields|2006|p=22}}: &quot;The history of Mycenaean chariot can be divided into two phases&amp;nbsp;... The second coincides with the period 1300–1200 BC (LH IIIB) when chariot design had changed dramatically with the development of the 'rail-chariot'. The shift from box-chariot to rail-chariot marks the transition from a purely mobile vehicle to a battlefield transport at a time when the Mycenaean world was in a state of fragmentation and dissolution.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Horse-mounted warriors were also part of the Mycenaean armies, however their precise role isn't clear due to lack of archaeological data.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=46}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fortifications==
The construction of defensive structures was closely linked with the establishment of the palatial centers in mainland Greece. The principal Mycenaean centers were well-fortified and usually situated on an elevated terrain, such as in [[Athens]], [[Tiryns]] and [[Mycenae]] or on coastal plains, in the case of [[Gla]].&lt;ref name=Fields10/&gt; Mycenaean Greeks appreciated the symbolism of war as expressed in defensive architecture, thus they aimed also at the visual impressiveness of their fortifications.&lt;ref name=Fields10/&gt; The walls were built in ''[[Cyclopean masonry|Cyclopean]]'' style; consisted of walls built of large, unworked boulders more than {{convert|8|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} thick and weighing several [[Tonne|metric tonnes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|p=78}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''Cyclopean'' was derived by the Greeks of the [[Classical Greece|classical era]] who believed that only the mythical giants, the [[Cyclops]], could have constructed such megalithic structures.&lt;ref name=Fields10&gt;{{harvnb|Fields|2004|p=10}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, cut stone masonry is used only in and around gateways.&lt;ref name=Fields11&gt;{{harvnb|Fields|2004|p=11}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Weaponry==

===Offensive weapons===
[[File:Mycenaean swords recostruction.jpg|thumbnail|Reconstructed Mycenaean swords.]]
[[Spear]]s were initially long and two-handed, more than {{convert|3|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} long and possibly handled with both hands. During the later Mycenaean centuries, shorter versions were adopted which were usually accompanied with small types of [[shield]]s, mainly of circular shape.&lt;ref name=Howard50/&gt; These short spears have been used for both thrusting and throwing.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti13&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=13}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

From the 16th century BC, swords with rounded tips appeared, having a [[Handle|grip]] which was an extension of the [[blade]].&lt;ref name=Salimbeti13/&gt; They were {{convert|130|cm|ft|0|abbr=on}} long and {{convert|3|cm|inch|0|abbr=on}} broad.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti15&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=15}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Another type, the single-edged sword was a solid piece of [[bronze]] c. {{convert|66|cm|ft|abbr=on}}–{{convert|74|cm|ft|abbr=on}} long. This shorter sword was most probably used for close-quarters combat.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti15/&gt; In the 14th century BC, both types were progressively modified with stronger grips and shorter blades.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti13/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schofield 2006 123&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|p=123}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally in the 13th century BC, a new type of sword, the [[Bronze Age sword#Naue II|Naue II]], became popular in Mycenaean Greece.&lt;ref name=Howard50&gt;{{harvnb|Howard|2011|p=50}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Archery]] was commonly used from an early period in battlefield.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=16}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Other offensive weapons used were [[Mace (weapon)|maces]], [[axe]]s, [[Sling (weapon)|slings]] and [[javelin]]s.&lt;ref name=Howard50/&gt;&lt;ref name=Salimbeti13/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|p=306}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shields===
[[File:Eberzahnhelm Heraklion.jpg|thumbnail|150px|Boar's tusk helmets were typical of Mycenaean warfare.]]
Early Mycenaean armies used &quot;tower shields&quot;, large [[shield]]s that covered almost the entire body. However, with the introduction of bronze armor, this type was less utilized, even if it didn't completely go into disuse, as attested in [[iconography]].&lt;ref name=Salimbeti20&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=20}}.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Figure-of-eight&quot; shields became the most common type of Mycenaean shields.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti20/&gt; These shields were made of several layers of bull-hide and in some cases they were reinforced with bronze plates.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti17&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=17}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During the later Mycenaean period, smaller types of shields were adopted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schofield 2006 123&quot;/&gt; They were either of completely circular shape, or almost circular with a cut-out part from their lower edge.&lt;ref name=Cline312/&gt; These were made of several layers of leather with a bronze boss and reinforcements. They occasionally appear to have been made entirely of bronze.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti17/&gt;

===Helmets===
The most common type of Mycenaean [[helmet]] is the conical one reinforced with rows of [[boar's tusk helmet|boar tusks]].&lt;ref name=Salimbeti23/&gt; This type was widely used and became the most identifiable piece of Mycenaean armor, being in use from the beginning to the collapse of Mycenaean culture. It is also known from several depictions in contemporary art in Greece and the Mediterranean. Boar's tusk helmets consisted of a felt-lined leather cap, with several rows of cut boar's tusk sewn onto it.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti23&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=23}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|p=119}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Helmets made entirely of bronze were also used, while some of them had large cheek guards, probably stitched or riveted to the helmet, as well as an upper pierced knot to hold a crest. Small holes all around the cheek guards and the helmet's lower edge were used for the attachment of internal padding. Other types of bronze helmets were also used.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=25}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During the late Mycenaean period, additional types were also used such as [[horned helmet]]s made of strips of [[leather]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|p=121}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armor===
[[File:Mycenaean armour from chamber tomb 12 of Dendra 1.JPG|thumbnail|125px|14th century BC [[Dendra panoply]].]]
A representative piece of Mycenaean [[armor]] is the [[Dendra panoply]] (c. 1450–1400 BC) which consisted of a [[cuirass]] of a complete set made up of several elements of [[bronze]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=27}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It was flexible and comfortable enough to be used for fighting on foot,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=28}}.&lt;/ref&gt; while the total weight of the armor is around 18&amp;nbsp;kg (about 40&amp;nbsp;lb).&lt;ref name=Salimbeti30/&gt; Important evidence of Mycenaean armor has also been found in [[Thebes (Greece)|Thebes]] (c. 1350–1250 BC), which include a pair of shoulder guards, smaller than to those from Dendra, with additional plates protecting the upper arms, attached to the lower edge of the shoulder guards.&lt;ref name=Salimbeti30&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=30}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of [[scale armour]] is evident during the later Mycenaean centuries, as shown on iconography and archaeological finds.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=34}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In general, most features of the later [[Hoplite#Equipment|hoplite panoply]] of classical Greek antiquity, were already known to Mycenaean Greece.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kagan|Viggiano|2013|p=36: &quot;In fact, most of the essential items of the &quot;hoplite panoply&quot; were known to Mycenaean Greece, including the metallic helmet and the single thrusting spear.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chariots==
[[File:Chariot Pylos.jpg|thumbnail|125px|Chariot depiction in a fresco from Pylos, c. 1350 BC.]]
The two-horse [[chariot]] appeared on the Greek mainland at least from the 16th century BC.&lt;ref name=Cline312&gt;{{harvnb|Cline|2012|p=312}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Mycenaean chariots differed from their counterparts used by contemporary Middle Eastern powers. According to the preserved Linear B records, the palatial states of [[Knossos]] and Pylos were able to field several hundreds.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fields|2006|p=23}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The most common type of Mycenaean chariot was the &quot;dual chariot&quot;, which appeared in the middle of the 15th century BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=43}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 14th century BC, a lighter version appeared, the &quot;rail chariot&quot;, which featured an open cab and was most probably used as a battlefield transport rather than a fighting vehicle.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=44}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ships==
Mycenaean [[ship]]s were shallow-draught vessels and could be beached on sandy bays.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Castleden|2005|p=186}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There were vessels of various sizes containing different numbers of [[Rowing|oarsmen]]. The largest ship probably had a crew of 42–46 oarsmen, with one steering [[oar]], a [[captain]], two attendants and a complement of warriors.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=48}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most common type of Mycenaean vessel based on depictions of contemporary art was the oared [[galley]] with long and narrow [[Hull (watercraft)|hulls]]. The shape of the hull was constructed in a way to maximize the number of rowers. Thus, a higher speed could have been achieved regardless of wind conditions. Although it carried [[Mast (sailing)|mast]] and [[sail]], it was less efficient as a sailing ship.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Tartaron|2013|p=58}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mycenaean galley offered certain advantages. Although lighter compared to the oared-sailing ship of the [[Minoan civilization|Minoans]] of [[Crete]], it seated more rowers. Its steering mechanism was a triangular [[steering oar]], a forerunner of the latter steering oar of [[Archaic Greece|Archaic era]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Tartaron|2013|p=63}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campaigns==
Around 1450 BC, Greece was divided into a series of warrior [[Mycenaean_Greece#Palatial_states|kingdoms]], the most important being centered in Mycenae, Tiryns, Pylos and Thebes. Before the end of the same century, this militaristic civilization replaced the former priestess-dominated civilization of [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] [[Crete|Cretans]] in the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]]. Thus, the Mycenaeans began to build up their maritime power in the Aegean Sea, expanding towards the Aegean Islands and Anatolian coast.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|pp=71–72}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The warlike nature of the Mycenaeans was probably a decisive factor in their diplomatic relations towards the other Late Bronze Age powers. Mycenaean warriors were also hired as mercenaries in foreign armies, such as in [[New Kingdom of Egypt|Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schofield|2006|p=126}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Contemporary [[Hittites|Hittite]] texts indicate the presence of ''Ahhiyawa'', which strengthened its position in western Anatolia from c. 1400 to c. 1220 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bryce 2005 361&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bryce|2005|p=361}}.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ahhiyawa'' is generally accepted as a Hittite translation of Mycenaean Greece ([[Achaeans (Homer)|Achaeans]] in Homeric Greek).&lt;ref name=BeckmanBryceCline6&gt;{{harvnb|Beckman|Bryce|Cline|2012|p=6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kelder|2010|pp=8–9}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, the kings of ''Ahhiyawa'' were clearly able to deal with the Hittite kings both in a military and diplomatic way.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kelder|2010|pp=119–120}}.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ahhiyawa'' activity was to interfere in Anatolian affairs, with the support of anti-Hittite uprisings or through local vassal rulers, which the king of the ''Ahhiyawa'' used as agents for the extension of his influence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bryce|2005|p=59}}; {{harvnb|Kelder|2010|p=23}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In one occasion, in c. 1400 BC, [[Attarsiya]] (a possible Hittite translation of [[Atreus]]) launched a campaign deploying an army headed by war chariots and attacked regions which were under Hittite influence. Later, Attarsiya, invaded the island of [[Alashiya]] ([[Cyprus]]) together with a number of his Anatolian allies.&lt;ref name=Jorrit&gt;{{harvnb|Kelder|2005|pp=139–140}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The invading force finally succeeded in controlling the island and overthrowing the local Hittite authorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bryce|2005|pp=146–147}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The campaigns of Attarsiya represent the earliest recorded Mycenaean Greek military activity against the Hittites.&lt;ref name=Osprey&gt;{{harvnb|D'Amato|Salimbeti|2011|p=57}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Hittite-Ahhiyawan confrontation in Wilusa, the Hittite name for [[Troy]], in the 13th century BC may have provided the [[Historicity of the Iliad|historical foundation]] for the [[Trojan War]] tradition.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bryce|2005|pp=361, 364}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In circa 1250 BC, the first wave of destruction has been witnessed in various centers of mainland Greece for reasons that cannot be identified by [[Archaeology|archaeologists]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kelder|2010|p=34}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These incidents appear to have triggered the massive strengthening and expansion of the fortifications in various sites. In some cases, arrangements were also made for the creation of subterranean passages which led to underground [[cistern]]s.&lt;ref name=Castleden219&gt;{{harvnb|Castleden|2005|p=219}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, none of these measures appear to have prevented the final destruction of the Mycenaean palace centers in the 12th century BC. The reasons that lead to the collapse of the Mycenaean culture have been hotly debated among scholars. The two most common theories are population movement and internal conflict.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mylonas|1966|pp=227–228}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Due to the information offered by the Greek epics and especially by [[Homer]]'s epics, the ''[[Iliad]]'' and ''[[Odyssey]]'', this time period of Greek history was regarded as a period of warrior-heroes who led various military campaigns in Greece and adjacent areas.&lt;ref name=Cline303/&gt; The picture of the Mycenaean Greeks in the Homeric Epics is one of a quarrelsome people and of a warrior élite to whom personal [[honor]] was the highest value.&lt;ref name=Castleden235&gt;{{harvnb|Castleden|2005|p=235}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Ancient Greek warfare]]
*[[Bronze Age sword]]

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Sources===
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book|last1=D'Amato|first1=Raphaelo|first2=Andrea|last2=Salimbeti|title=Bronze Age Greek Warrior 1600–1100 BC|year=2011|publisher=Osprey Publishing Company|location=Oxford|isbn=978-1-84908-195-5|url=https://books.google.gr/books?id=ydE6bwAACAAJ|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Beckman|first1=Gary M.|last2=Bryce|first2=Trevor R.|last3=Cline|first3=Eric H.|title=Writings from the Ancient World: The Ahhiyawa Texts|year=2012|location=Atlanta|publisher=Society of Biblical Literature|url=http://www.sbl-site.org/assets/pdfs/pubs/061528P.front.pdf|issn=1570-7008|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Bryce|first1=Trevor|title=The Kingdom of the Hittites|date=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=978-0-19-927908-1|edition=New|url=https://books.google.gr/books?id=fYtnGF6zuRIC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Castleden|first=Rodney|title=The Mycenaeans|year=2005|location=London and New York|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-36336-5|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Kfi0dAlfJaoC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor-last1=Cline|editor-first1=Eric H.|title=The Oxford Handbook of the Bronze Age Aegean|year=2012|location=Oxford|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-987360-9|url=https://books.google.gr/books?id=9vueDKFX8rQC&amp;dq=|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Fields|first1=Nic; illustrated by Brian Delf|title=Bronze Age War Chariots|date=2006|location=Oxford|publisher=Osprey Publishing Company|isbn=978-1-84176-944-8|url=https://issuu.com/marosi_65/docs/_osprey__new_vanguard_-_119_-_bronz|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Fields|first1=Nic; illustrated by Donato Spedaliere|title=Mycenaean Citadels c. 1350–1200 BC|year=2004|location=Oxford|publisher=Osprey Publishing Company|isbn=978-1-84176-762-8|edition=3rd|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Howard|first=Dan|title=Bronze Age Military Equipment|year=2011|location=Barnsley|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Military|isbn=978-1-84884-293-9|url=https://books.google.gr/books?id=diOx0cfHegEC&amp;dq=|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Kagan|first1=Donald|last2=Viggiano|first2=Gregory F.|title=Men of Bronze: Hoplite Warfare in Ancient Greece|year=2013|location=Princeton, NJ|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-1-4008-4630-6|url=https://books.google.gr/books?id=xx6orLkVV4YC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Kelder|first=Jorrit|title=Greece During the Late Bronze Age|journal=Journal of the Ancient Near East Society: Ex Oriente Lux|year=2005|volume=39|pages=131–179|url=http://www.academia.edu/219025/Greece_during_the_Late_Bronze_Age|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Kelder|first=Jorrit M.|title=The Kingdom of Mycenae: A Great Kingdom in the Late Bronze Age Aegean|website=www.academia.edu|url=http://www.academia.edu/218696/The_Kingdom_of_Mycenae|year=2010|location=Bethesda, MD|publisher=CDL Press|accessdate=18 March 2015|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Mylonas|first=George Emmanuel|title=Mycenae and the Mycenaean Age|year=1966|location=Princeton, NJ|publisher=Princeton University Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wozpAAAAMAAJ|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Palaima|first1=Tom|title=Mycenaean Militarism from a Textual Perspective|journal=Polemos: Warfare in the Aegean Bronze Age (Aegaeum)|date=1999|volume=19|pages=367–378|url=http://www.utexas.edu/research/pasp/publications/pdf/militarism.pdf|accessdate=25 June 2016|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Schofield|first=Louise|title=The Mycenaeans|year=2006|location=Los Angeles, CA|publisher=J. Paul Getty Museum|isbn=978-0-89236-867-9|url=https://books.google.gr/books?id=QXwzT1048Z4C&amp;dq=|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Tartaron|first1=Thomas F.|title=Maritime Networks in the Mycenaean World|year=2013|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9781107067134|url=https://books.google.gr/books?id=sZbqAAAAQBAJ&amp;dq=|ref=harv}}
{{refend|2}}

[[Category:Military history of Ancient Greece]]
[[Category:Mycenaean Greece]]</text>
      <sha1>p5sxikojfu9zpttb7kp8miq9kpmwv10</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
