<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mochitsura Hashimoto</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10096572</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742369811</id>
      <parentid>742369784</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-03T08:40:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>104.234.241.194</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sinking of the Indianapolis */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26385">{{Good article}}
{{Infobox military person
 | name         = Hashimoto Mochitsura&lt;br&gt;橋本以行
 | birth_date        = 14 October 1909
 | death_date= 25 October 2000 (aged 91)
 | birth_place =[[Kyoto]], [[Japan]]
 | death_place =[[Kyoto]], [[Japan]]
 |image=Mochitsura Hashimoto.jpg
 | caption      = Hashimoto Mochitsura, as a lieutenant-commander (c. 1943)
 | nickname     =
 | allegiance   =[[Empire of Japan]]
 | serviceyears =1931–1945
 | rank         =[[Naval ranks of the Japanese Empire during World War II#Commissioned officer ranks|Commander]]
 | branch       = {{navy|Empire of Japan}}
 | commands     = [[Japanese submarine Ro-31|''Ro-31'']]&lt;br&gt;[[Japanese submarine I-158|''I-158'']]&lt;br&gt;[[Japanese submarine Ro-44|''Ro-44'']]&lt;br&gt;[[Japanese submarine I-58|''I-58'']]
 | unit         =
 | battles      = [[Second Sino-Japanese War]]&lt;br&gt;[[World War II]]
* [[Attack on Pearl Harbor]]
* [[Battle of Okinawa]]
* [[USS Indianapolis (CA-35)|Sinking of the USS Indianapolis]]
 | awards       = [[Order of the Golden Kite]], 5th Class&lt;br&gt;[[Order of the Rising Sun]], 5th Class&lt;br&gt;[[Order of the Sacred Treasure]]
 | laterwork    =[[Shinto]] priest
}}

{{Japanese name|Hashimoto}}
{{nihongo|'''Mochitsura Hashimoto'''|橋本 以行|Hashimoto Mochitsura|1909 – 25 October 2000}} was an academy-trained officer and a submarine commander in the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] during [[World War II]]. He is best known as the captain of [[Japanese submarine I-58 (1943)|Japanese submarine ''I-58'']], which sank {{USS|Indianapolis|CA-35|6}} in 1945 after its delivery of bomb parts for the first atomic weapon used in wartime, ''[[Little Boy]]'', but prior to the attack on [[Hiroshima]].

Born in [[Kyoto]] and educated at the [[Imperial Japanese Naval Academy]], Hashimoto volunteered for service in submarines and was later aboard [[Japanese submarine I-24|submarine ''I-24'']] during the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]] in 1941. Hashimoto commanded coastal patrol and training submarines off Japan for much of the war, and in 1944 took command of ''I-58'', a ship which was equipped to carry ''[[kaiten]]'', or manned torpedoes. After a number of unsuccessful operations, under the command of Hashimoto ''I-58'' sank ''Indianapolis'' on 30 July with two unmanned [[Type 95 torpedo]]es while on a midnight patrol. Ironically, he lost his entire family in the ''Little Boy'' [[Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki|atomic bombing of Hiroshima]] days after the sinking of ''Indianapolis''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.al.com/news/mobile/index.ssf/2016/07/uss_indianapolis_survivor_youv.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Hashimoto's submarine then returned to Japan, one of the few such ships to survive the war. Hashimoto was called to testify on behalf of the prosecution at the [[court-martial]] of [[Charles B. McVay III]], the commanding officer of ''Indianapolis'', a move which was controversial at the time. He was later part of an effort to exonerate McVay, which was eventually successful. Hashimoto later became a [[Shinto]] priest. He died in 2000.

==Biography==
Mochitsura Hashimoto was born in 1909 in [[Kyoto, Japan]],{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=213}} the eighth of nine children and fifth son of a ''[[kannushi]]'' ([[Shinto]] priest). He attended [[Kyoto Third High School]], a prestigious school, where he performed well.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=1}} In his youth he was described as self-possessed and respectful. At the behest of his father, he applied for the [[Imperial Japanese Naval Academy]]. The family did not have a naval background, but Hashimoto's father struggled financially on a priest's government subsidy and he felt entering his son into the military would help to provide for them. One of Hashimoto's older brothers subsequently attended the [[Imperial Japanese Army Academy]] and was commissioned into the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]. Hashimoto graduated from high school in 1927 and was accepted into the Naval Academy. Leaving home for the first time, Hashimoto then attended the naval academy at [[Eta Jima]] for four years, studying [[Japanese history]], engineering, and naval tactics, as well as [[judo]] and other military athletics.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=2}} He graduated and [[commissioned officer|commissioned]] in 1931.{{sfn|Tucker|2011|p=343}}

In 1937, Hashimoto married Nobuko Miki, the daughter of a successful [[Osaka]] businessman.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=2}} The couple had three sons; Mochihiro, born in 1940,{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=3}} Nobutake, born in 1942, and Tomoyuki, born in 1944.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=4}}and Sonoe, a daughter born in 1947.

=== Military career ===
In 1934, Hashimoto volunteered for the [[submarine]] service,{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=213}} and in 1937, he served aboard [[destroyer]]s and [[submarine chaser]]s off the shores of the [[Republic of China (1912–1949)|Republic of China]]. On 15 November, as a [[sub-lieutenant]], Hashimoto was assigned to the crew of the gunboat ''[[Japanese gunboat Hozu|Hozu]]'', and was promoted to [[lieutenant]] on 1 December.&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 15 November 1937, supplement to publication No. 91. Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072072500 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 1 December 1937, Publication supplement,Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072072500 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; During that time, his brother was killed in action fighting on the Chinese mainland.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=2}}

In 1938, he was assigned to the destroyer ''[[Japanese destroyer Okikaze|Okikaze]]'' on 15 December.&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 15 December 1938, supplement to publication (limited access) No. 273, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072074800 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; Selected for submarine school the following year, Hashimoto was assigned to the [[Yokosuka Naval District]] on 20 May 1939 and enrolled in a six-month torpedo course on 1 June, subsequently entering the naval submarine school as a Class B student on 1 December.&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 20 May 1939, Publication (limited access) No. 338, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072075700 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 1 June 1939, Publication (limited access) No. 342, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072075900 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 1 December 1939, Publication (limited access) No. 408, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072077100 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; Upon completion of this training, he was assigned to the submarine [[I-121-class submarine|''I-123]] on 20 March 1940 as torpedo officer, transferring to the [[I-153-class submarine|''I-155'']] on 15 October in the same role.&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 20 March 1940, Publication (limited access) No. 453, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072077800 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 15 October 1940, Publication (limited access) No. 543, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072079100 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 July 1941, he was assigned to the [[Japanese submarine I-24 (1939)|submarine ''I-24'']], becoming its torpedo officer on 31 October, under [[Lieutenant Commander]] Hiroshi Hanabusa; the ship was based out of [[Kure]].&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 15 July 1941, Publication (limited access) No. 673, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072081600 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 31 October 1941, Publication (limited access) No. 736, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072082900 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the year, the submarine conducted training maneuvers with a group of [[midget submarine]]s.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=3}} On 18 November, ''I-24'' and her group sailed from Kure with a midget submarine attached to her afterdeck. Steaming eastward, she surfaced {{convert|10|mi}} off [[Waikiki]] on 6 December.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=3}} The sub was a part of a large group of submarines which would support the [[Attack on Pearl Harbor]].{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=214}} Hashimoto witnessed the final ritual of [[Kazuo Sakamaki]] and Kyoji Inagaki, who would man the midget submarine, which cast off at 05:30. ''I-24'' remained at a rendezvous point to wait for the midget sub, which never came. On 9 December, ''I-24'' steamed for Kure.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=4}}

Upon the submarine's return to Kure, Hashimoto was detached and assigned to the advanced course at Submarine School on 1 February 1942, to prepare him for command of a submarine.&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 2 February 1942, Publication (limited access) No. 805, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072084200 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; Graduating from this course on 30 June, Hashimoto was given command of [[Japanese submarine Ro-31|submarine ''Ro-31'']], a coastal defense vessel.{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=214}} For the remainder of 1942, Hashimoto operated his ship in home waters off [[Yokosuka]] training crews and trying new equipment and doing research for the development of Japanese submarine doctrine. He was promoted to [[lieutenant commander]] on 1 November.&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 1 November 1942, Publication (limited access) No. 974, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072087700 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; In 1943, he was given command of [[Japanese submarine I-158|submarine ''I-158'']] for coastal defense, and later in the year was given command of [[Japanese submarine Ro-44|submarine ''Ro-44'']] for the same duties.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=4}}

=== Commanding ''I-58'' ===
In May 1944, Lieutenant Commander Hashimoto was given command of [[Japanese submarine I-58|submarine ''I-58'']]{{sfn|Harrell|2005|p=65}} which was still under construction in [[Sasebo, Nagasaki|Sasebo]]. Hashimoto oversaw much of the construction of ''I-58''. The submarine was later overhauled mid-construction to carry ''[[Kaiten]]'' manned [[torpedo]]es, which was considered a great honor by Hashimoto's crew.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=5}} ''I-58'' was commissioned on 13 September 1944 and Hashimoto commanded her during her [[shakedown cruise]]s, commanding his men on repeated drills without [[shore leave]].{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=6}}{{sfn|Harrell|2005|p=66}} He completed training on the submarine in December 1944. The ship traversed [[Shimonoseki Strait]] into the [[Seto Inland Sea|Inland Sea]] and to Kure for supplies. She then moved to [[Hirao]] where she loaded six ''kaitens''.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=7}}

[[File:IJN SS I-58(II) on trial run in 1944.jpg|thumb|left|{{ship|Japanese submarine|I-58}} in 1944]]
On 29 December, she left on her first war patrol, steaming for the [[Mariana Islands]]. She arrived off the coast of [[Guam]] at 03:00 on 11 January 1945 and Hashimoto ordered four ''kaitens'' launched. The kaitens tentatively claimed a [[Tanker (ship)|tanker]] sunk, though it was unable to verify if the ship had actually been struck.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=8–9}} The strike had been unsuccessful.{{sfn|Tucker|2011|p=344}} She then sped back to Kure and arrived there on 20 January. She remained in port there until March, likely due to supply shortages. On 1 March, she was ordered to [[Iwo Jima]] to support the [[Battle of Iwo Jima|battle taking place there]]. Once there, ''I-58'' was ordered to launch all of its ''kaitens'' without their pilots and immediately return home.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=8–9}} She was ordered out again on 2 April sailing to support Japanese forces at the [[Battle of Okinawa]]. While there, she was attacked by aircraft 50 times. She never surfaced for more than a few hours. She limped to Kure on 29 April 1945, the only Japanese submarine to withdraw from the operation. She remained in port because of continued [[naval mine|mining]] conducted by [[U.S. Army Air Forces]], and departed on 16 July on another war patrol. At the time, she was one of only four large submarines left in the Japanese Navy, and her mission was to harass [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] lines of communications.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=10}}{{sfn|Stanton|2002|p=79}}{{sfn|Boyd|Yoshida|2002|p=179}}

Passing through the Inland Sea around minefields, ''I-58'' headed for the east coast of [[The Philippines]] intending to attack ships there. Passing east of Okinawa and spotting no ships, she cruised south arriving at the Guam-[[Leyte]] shipping lane on 27 July.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=57}}{{sfn|Stanton|2002|p=80}} She spotted a tanker escorted by a [[destroyer]] and Hashimoto ordered her to launch two ''kaitens'' at 14:31 and 14:43. She heard explosions at 15:21 and 15:31 but her crew was unable to determine if the ''kaitens'' had struck their targets. Hashimoto reported a tanker assumed sunk.

=== Sinking of the Indianapolis===
On 29 July, he ordered the submarine to make for an area where he believed shipping lanes between Guam, Leyte, [[Peleliu]] and Okinawa intersected.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=58–59}} At 23:35 that evening, Hashimoto spotted the [[heavy cruiser]] {{USS|Indianapolis|CA-35|2}} at {{convert|10,000|m}} cruising for his position at medium speed.{{sfn|Stanton|2002|pp=93–95}} Believing the ship to be an [[USS Idaho (BB-42)|''Idaho''-class battleship]], he ordered ''I-58'' to dive and once ''Indianapolis'' closed to {{convert|1,500|m}} he ordered six regular torpedoes fired at 00:02 on 30 July.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=58–59}}{{sfn|Stanton|2002|p=100–101}} Spotting three explosions strike the ''Indianapolis'', Hashimoto ordered the submarine on a deep dive fearing detection. After an hour at a deep dive to reload, she surfaced and did not spot ''Indianapolis''. After searching unsuccessfully for [[flotsam]] or any sign of the ship,{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=60–61}}{{sfn|Tucker|2011|p=375}} he ordered the ''I-58'' to retire at 02:30. He transmitted a [[short wave radio]] message to the [[6th Fleet (Imperial Japanese Navy)|6th Fleet]] headquarters in [[Kure]] at about 03:00 noting the destruction of the ship.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=62}} He later wrote of the incident:

{{Quote|We had the moon behind us and the enemy ship was now clearly visible. She had two turrets aft and a large tower mast. I took her to be an ''Idaho''-class battleship. The crew were all agog, awaiting the order to fire the torpedoes. All was dead quiet&amp;nbsp;... the favorable moment for firing was approaching.&amp;nbsp;... At last in a loud voice, I gave the order 'Stand by—fire!' The torpedo-release switch pressed at intervals of two seconds and then the report came from the torpedo room, &quot;All tubes fired and correct.&quot; Six torpedoes were speeding, fanwise, toward the enemy ship.&amp;nbsp;... Bringing the boat on to a course parallel with the enemy, we waited anxiously. Every minute seemed an age. Then on the starboard side of the enemy by the forward turret, and then the after turret there rose columns of water to be followed immediately by flashes of bright red flame. Then another column of water arose from alongside the Number 2 turret and seemed to envelop the whole ship—&quot;A hit, a hit!&quot; I shouted as each torpedo struck home, and the crew danced for joy.{{sfn|Harrell|2005|p=68–71}} }}

Hashimoto ordered ''I-58'' northward looking for additional ships to attack.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=119}} She picked up reports of the [[Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki|atomic bombing of Hiroshima]] in intercepted radio transmissions on 7 August but Hashimoto continued to hunt for Allied ships south of [[Bungo Strait]]. On 9 August she launched two ''kaitens'' against a convoy, and Hashimoto claimed a destroyer probably sunk. On 12 August he launched his remaining ''kaitens'' and claimed a merchant ship probably sunk. ''I-58'' surfaced in Bungo Strait on 15 August, where Hashimoto learned of the ''[[Gyokuon-hōsō]]'' signaling the [[Surrender of Japan|Japanese surrender]] and end of the war. She traveled up the Inland Sea and arrived at Hirao where Hashimoto emotionally informed his crew of the end of the war.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=168}} After the war, it was confirmed ''Indianapolis'' was the only ship ''I-58'' had sunk.{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=213}} It was the last Japanese naval success of World War II.{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=215}}

=== McVay court-martial ===
[[File:USS Indianapolis at Mare Island.jpg|thumb|{{USS|Indianapolis|CA-35|6}} in 1945]]
Three days after Japan's formal surrender in Tokyo Bay, Hashimoto was promoted to his final rank of [[commander]].&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 11 September 1945, Publication No. 1908, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072108400 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 November, he was given command of the destroyer [[Japanese destroyer Yukikaze|''Yukikaze'']], among the few Imperial Navy ships to survive the war, and assigned to repatriation duties, returning troops to Japan from overseas.&lt;ref&gt;Naval appointment dated 29 November 1945, Publication No. 1994, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072147800 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; Before Hashimoto could begin his new duties, however, he was summoned by the [[United States military]] to be a witness for the prosecution in the [[court-martial]] against ''Indianapolis'' commander [[Captain (naval rank)|Captain]] [[Charles B. McVay III]], who was on trial on charges of negligence leading to the ship's sinking.{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=215}} On 9 December 1945 he was transported from [[Tokyo]] to [[Oakland, California]] aboard an aircraft of the [[Naval Air Transport Service]]. Hashimoto was assured he would be treated as a naval officer instead of a [[prisoner of war]] or [[war criminal]], but he remained under guard during his time in the United States and was not allowed to leave his hotel, as his appearance had been front page news that day in the ''[[New York Times]]'' and in other newspapers. The next day he arrived in [[Washington, D.C.]] where hearings were taking place.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=213–214}} For the duration of his time in the United States, he spoke through translator Francis Earl Eastlake from the [[Office of Naval Intelligence]].{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=224}}

Hashimoto spoke first with [[judge advocate]] Captain [[Thomas J. Ryan (admiral)|Thomas J. Ryan]] for four hours on 11 December. He spoke the next day with Captain John P. Cady, McVay's chief defense counsel, for several hours, as both officers sought to determine his credibility and competence to take the stand in the trial. He told them the visibility was good on the night of the attack and he had been able to easily spot the ''Indianapolis''. Hashimoto testified in the court on 13 December in a crowded courtroom.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=221–222}} It was the first time that an officer of a nation at war with the United States had testified against an officer of the U.S. Navy in a court martial.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=223}}{{#tag:ref|Historian [[Richard Newcomb]] noted that commanding officers of two [[Continental Navy]] ships were tried and acquitted for the loss of their ships during the [[American Revolutionary War]]: [[John Manley (naval officer)|John Manley]] of [[USS Hancock (1776)|USS ''Hancock'']] and Elisha Hinman of [[USS Alfred (1774)|USS ''Alfred'']]. However, no U.S. Navy officer had ever been tried in connection with the loss of his vessel in wartime.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=223}}|group=Note}} At the behest of Cady, Hashimoto took both a Japanese civil oath and an U.S. Navy oath so he could be charged for [[perjury]] in both nations if he lied.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=224}} Hashimoto's 50 minutes of testimony focused on whether or not ''Indianapolis'' was &quot;zigzaging&quot; and he noted the ship did not deviate from its course. However, he also noted that, due to his position, such [[evasive maneuvers]] would not have diminished his ability to attack the ship.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=226–227}}{{sfn|Stanton|2002|p=265–266}} Still, his testimony is considered integral in McVay's eventual conviction that he had been negligent.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=248}} Charles Butler McVay III was [[Charles B. McVay III#Exoneration|exonerated in 2001]]. Following his appearance at the trial, Hashimoto remained in U.S. custody under guard until early 1946, when he was returned to Japan aboard {{USS|Effingham|APA-165|6}}.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=228}}

With the [[Nuremberg Trials]] underway and [[Japanese war crimes]] during the war coming to light, the announcement of Hashimoto's appearance in testimony against an American officer caused considerable controversy in the American news media. Though Hashimoto was himself known to be innocent of any war crimes and was generally treated well by his guards, he spoke little English and was subject to derision in the press.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|pp=213–214}} Among the public responses, socialite [[Evalyn Walsh McLean]] sent an angry telegram to [[Secretary of the Navy]] [[James Forrestal]] to complain, and [[U.S. Representative]] [[Robert L. Doughton]] publicly stated, &quot;It is the most contemptible thing I ever heard of to summon a Jap officer to testify against one of our own officers. I made my living practicing law before Navy courts and boards for 25 years, and this reaches an all-time low in courts, board or congressional investigation.&quot;{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=215}} Columnist [[Robert Ruark]] accused the Navy of using Hashimoto to &quot;hype up&quot; the court martial.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=215}} Even after his departure his testimony remained controversial, and the ''[[Chicago Sun]]'' criticized his trip, which it estimated to have cost $1,820.{{sfn|Newcomb|2000|p=228}}

===Post-war===
After his return to Japan, Hashimoto worked as a demobilization officer with the naval section of the Ministry of Demobilization, responsible for demobilizing veterans and dismantling what remained of the Japanese Navy. He completed his final assignment in June 1946, after which he became a civilian, opting to retire from the military.{{sfn|Tucker|2011|p=344}}&lt;ref&gt;Ministry of Demobilization appointment dated 11 June 1946, Publication No. 155, Japan Center for Asian Historical Records, reference code C13072159300 (jp)&lt;/ref&gt; Towards the end of his life, he became a Shinto priest at a shrine in Kyoto.{{sfn|Fredriksen|2001|p=216}} He was later interviewed by author [[Dan Kurzman]] for his 1990 book ''Fatal Voyage'', in which Kurzman stated, &quot;Commander Hashimoto was amazed by the Americans. While penned up in his dormitory during the trial, he was treated more like an honored guest than an enemy officer who had caused the deaths of so many American boys.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;USS.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ussindianapolis.org/hashimoto.htm|title=Mochitsura Hashimoto|publisher=USSIndianapolis.org|accessdate=January 26, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hashimoto later authored a book ''Sunk: The Story of the Japanese Submarine Fleet, 1941–1945'' in which he detailed Japanese submarine operations in the war, including an account of the sinking of ''Indianapolis.''{{sfn|Hashimoto|2010|p=i}}{{sfn|Harrell|2005|p=67}}{{sfn|Boyd|Yoshida|2002|p=242}}

In December 1990, Hashimoto met with some of the survivors of the ''Indianapolis'' at [[Pearl Harbor]] where he stated (through a translator): &quot;I came here to pray with you for your shipmates whose deaths I caused,&quot; to which survivor Giles McCoy simply responded: &quot;I forgive you.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;USS.org&quot;/&gt;

In 1999, he assisted the surviving crew of the ''Indianapolis'' in attempting to exonerate McVay of blame for the ship's sinking, writing a letter to the [[Senate Armed Services Committee]] in which he stated, just as he had more than five decades earlier, that even if the ''Indianapolis'' had been zigzaging, it would have made no difference: &quot;I would have been able to launch a successful torpedo attack against his ship whether it had been zigzagging or not.&quot; Regarding McVay's conviction, Hashimoto wrote:

{{quote|Our peoples have forgiven each other for that terrible war and its consequences. Perhaps it is time your peoples forgave Captain McVay for the humiliation of his unjust conviction.&lt;ref name=&quot;USS.org&quot;/&gt;}}

Hashimoto died at age 91 on 25 October 2000.{{sfn|Stanton|2002|p=280}} Five days after his death, the reputation of Captain McVay was restored.

== References ==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{citation|last1=Boyd |first1=Carl |last2=Yoshida |first2=Ahiko |title=The Japanese Submarine Force and World War II |year=2002 |publisher=[[Naval Institute Press]] |location=[[Annapolis, Maryland]] |isbn=978-1-55750-015-1}}
* {{citation|last=Fredriksen |first=John C. |title=America's Military Adversaries: From Colonial Times to the Present |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |year=2001 |location=[[Santa Barbara, California]] |isbn=1-57607-603-2}}
* {{citation|last=Harrell |first=David |title=Out of the Depths |publisher=[[Xulon Press]] |year=2005 |location=[[Maitland, Florida]] |isbn=978-1-59781-167-5}}
* {{citation|first=Mochitsura |last=Hashimoto |title=Sunk: The Story of the Japanese Submarine Fleet, 1941–1945 |year=2010 |isbn=978-1-61577-581-1 |publisher=Progressive Press |location=[[New York City, New York]]}}
* {{citation|first=Richard F. |last=Newcomb |authorlink=Richard Newcomb |title=Abandon Ship! : The Saga of the U.S.S. Indianapolis, the Navy's Greatest Sea Disaster |publisher=[[HarperCollins Publishers]] |year=2000 |location=[[New York City, New York]] |isbn=0-06-018471-X}}
* {{citation|last=Stanton |first=Doug |title=In Harm's Way: The Sinking of the U.S.S. Indianapolis and the Extraordinary Story of Its Survivors |publisher=[[St. Martin's Press]] |year=2002 |location=[[New York City, New York]] |isbn=0-312-98337-9}}
* {{citation|last=Tucker |first=Spencer |title=World War II at Sea: An Encyclopedia |publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]] |year=2011 |location=[[New York City, New York]] |isbn=978-1-59884-457-3}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ussindianapolis.org/hashimoto.htm Mochitsura Hashimoto] at USSIndianapolis.org.
* [http://www.history.navy.mil/faqs/faq30-8.htm Interrogation of Commander Mochitsura Hashimoto] at Department of the Navy - Naval Historical Center.

{{Authority control}}


{{DEFAULTSORT:Hashimoto, Mochitsura}}
[[Category:1909 births]]
[[Category:2000 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Kyoto]]
[[Category:Imperial Japanese Navy officers]]
[[Category:Japanese military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Rising Sun]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Sacred Treasure]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Golden Kite]]</text>
      <sha1>j1pjn6fq07eoe3ly0yvk81vdwl08ksd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
