<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>O-class battlecruiser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6506136</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745940172</id>
      <parentid>745932102</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T08:32:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Britmax</username>
        <id>638137</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted unexplained random changes.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21606">{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:OclassCruiser2Dmap4-eBigFlagalt.jpg|300px]]
| Ship caption = Line-drawing of the O-class battlecruiser concept.
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
| Name = 
| Builders = 
| Operators = {{navy|Nazi Germany}}
| Class before = 
| Class after = 
| Subclasses = 
| Cost = 
| Built range = 
| In service range = 
| In commission range = 
| Total ships building = 
| Total ships planned = 3
| Total ships completed = 
| Total ships cancelled = 3
| Total ships active = 
| Total ships laid up = 
| Total ships lost = 
| Total ships retired = 
| Total ships preserved = 
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = 
| Ship type = [[Battlecruiser]]
| Ship displacement = {{convert|35400|LT|t|0}}
| Ship length = {{convert|256|m|ft|abbr=on}}
| Ship beam = {{convert|30|m|ft|abbr=on}}
| Ship height = 
| Ship draft = {{convert|8.02|m|ft|abbr=on}}
| Ship depth = 
| Ship propulsion =* 8 × 24 cylinder [[diesel engine]]s, 60,000 shp
* 4 × Wagner boilers
* 1 × [[Brown, Boveri &amp; Cie]] turbine set, 116,000 shp
  
| Ship speed = {{convert|35|kn|lk=in}}
| Ship range = {{convert|14000|nmi|abbr=on|lk=in}} at {{convert|19|kn}}
| Ship boats = 
| Ship complement =* 65 officers
* 1,900 men
  
| Ship sensors = 
| Ship EW = 
| Ship armament =* 6 × [[38 cm SK C/34 naval gun|{{convert|38.1|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK C/34]] guns
* 6 × [[15 cm SK C/28|{{convert|15|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK C/28]] guns
* 8 × [[10.5 cm FlaK 38|10.5&amp;nbsp;cm SK C/33]] AA
* 8 × [[3.7 cm SK C/30]] AA
* 20 × [[2 cm FlaK 30|2 cm SK C/30]] AA
* 6 × {{convert|53.3|cm|in|abbr=on}} torpedo tubes
  
| Ship armor =* Belt: {{convert|190|mm|in|abbr=on}}
* Deck: {{convert|80|mm|in|abbr=on}}
* Turrets: {{convert|210|mm|in|abbr=on}}
* Torpedo bulkhead: {{convert|45|mm|in|abbr=on}}
  
| Ship aircraft = 4 × [[Arado Ar 196]] seaplanes
| Ship aircraft facilities = 1 × double catapult, 3 hangars
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}
The '''O class''' was a planned [[Ship class|class]] of three [[battlecruiser]]s for the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' (German navy) before  [[World War II]]. Prompted by a perceived lack in ship numbers when compared with the British [[Royal Navy]], the O class' design was born with the suggestion of modifying the {{sclass2-|P|cruiser|1}} design with {{convert|380|mm|abbr=on}} guns instead of {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}}. The ships were incorporated into the 1939 [[Plan Z]]; while an [[Graf Zeppelin-class aircraft carrier|aircraft carrier]], [[H-class battleship proposals|H-class battleships]] and smaller ships engaged convoy escorts, one or more O-class ships would attack the merchant ships.

The O class' design reflected their intended role; a heavy [[main battery|main armament]] (six 380&amp;nbsp;mm guns in three dual [[gun turret|turrets]]) for possible encounters with escorting {{convert|203|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}-armed [[heavy cruiser]]s, enough armor to defend against the same and nothing more, and a high top speed so that they could get away from slower but much better armored [[capital ship]]s.

== Development ==

=== Genesis: P-class cruisers ===
{{main|P-class cruiser}}

Even with the completion of the two {{sclass-|Scharnhorst|battleship}}s and the construction of two {{sclass-|Bismarck|battleship}}s, the German Navy had fewer ships than other European navies. This led to a decision in 1937 to build ships to an improved {{sclass-|Deutschland|cruiser|0}} design. After more than twenty designs were considered to meet the navy's specifications,{{efn|name=specifications}} one was chosen; it was designated as cruiser &quot;P&quot; (the &quot;P&quot; for [[panzer]]&amp;nbsp;— German: &quot;armor&quot;). Under the original plan, twelve P-class ships were to be built. The ships were designed as [[cruiser killer]]s that would have heavy enough armament and armor to take on [[light cruiser|light]] and [[heavy cruiser]]s but enough speed to outrun [[battleship]]s and battlecruisers.{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=351}}

Many problems were encountered with designing the ships, the most prevalent being armor. The required maximum speed of {{convert|34|kn|lk=in}} meant that the minimum [[Length overall|length]] had to grow from the original {{convert|217|m|ft|abbr=on}} to {{convert|229.5|m|ft|abbr=on}}. It also meant that the [[Beam (nautical)|beam]] could be a minimum of {{convert|25|m|ft|abbr=on}}—unless [[diesel engine]]s, like those used in the ''Deutschland''{{'}}s, were desired; they would increase the beam by {{convert|2|m|ft|abbr=on}}. Unfortunately for the designers, the widened beam meant that an even longer hull was needed to maintain hydrodynamic efficiency. All of this complicated the armor arrangements, as more armor was needed to cover the longer length and widened beam. Eventually it was deemed that it was impossible to include diesel power on a {{convert|20000|t|LT|adj=on}} [[displacement (ship)|displacement]].{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|pp=351–352}}

The switch to battlecruisers was the result of a proposal to up the main armament from {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}}/55 [[Caliber (artillery)|caliber]] guns to {{convert|380|mm|in|abbr=on}}/47 caliber guns. Various reasons were behind this. Among other reasons, experiments showed that the smaller gun was &quot;far less effective&quot;{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=353}} than the larger gun, a class of twelve ships would have overtaxed the shipyards already heavily burdened with other ships, and the smallest guns on any foreign ship in service or under construction were more than {{convert|30|mm|in|abbr=on}} larger than the 283&amp;nbsp;mm guns.{{efn|name=foreign guns}} The most persuasive argument for increasing the armament came in 1939, when [[Adolf Hitler]] denounced the 1935 [[Anglo-German Naval Agreement]].{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=353}}

=== Battlecruisers ===
[[File:OclassCruiser1-24ShipRearAngleA1hullMid.blend.jpg|thumb|The stern and amidships portion of the O class]]

Although interest in the P-class ships and the battlecruiser proposal waned for a time in late 1937 and early 1938, it was quickly revived on 28 April 1938 with Hitler's public airing of his views on the 1935 Anglo-German Treaty and the consequent increased possibility of war with the [[United Kingdom]]. Calling the Naval Staff and [[Admiral Erich Raeder]] to him, Hitler laid out his thoughts of a strong navy that could pose enough danger to the British such that they would enter into an alliance with Germany rather than go to war. As decided here, [[Plan Z]] entailed two [[task force]]s each centered on three [[H-class battleship proposals|H-class battleships]] and one aircraft carrier, with [[cruiser]]s and [[destroyer]]s as escorts. In war, these forces would collaborate with the three battlecruisers by occupying convoy screens while [[U-boat]]s and one or more of the O class took out the cargo-carrying merchant ships.{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=353}} The presence of the battlecruisers operating at large would have the secondary effect of forcing the [[Royal Navy]] to deploy battleships as convoy escorts, thus weakening any fleet that could engage the Plan Z task forces.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau|p=226}}

As part of the plan, design work on the P class was halted in mid-1939 in favor of the O class. Displacement was limited to {{convert|30000|t|LT|link=y}} in the new designs so that the length of construction would be shortened from the normal four or more years that a battleship required, to an estimated three{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=354}} to three and a half years.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}} Required characteristics for the battlecruisers was a displacement of {{convert|30000|t|LT|link=n}}, a [[main battery]] of six {{convert|380|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns, a secondary battery of [[dual purpose gun]]s, a top speed of {{convert|34|kn}}, a range of {{convert|15000|nmi|km|abbr=on}} at {{convert|19|kn}}, and enough armor to counter the {{convert|203|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns of heavy cruisers.{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|pp=19 and 354}}

Like the P class, there were problems with fitting an all-diesel drive into the hull of the ships. It was enough that the design team decided that it would not be prudent to use an all-diesel arrangement; instead, a hybrid diesel-[[steam turbine]] propulsion plant was to be used. The change allowed the central armored citadel to be reduced by {{convert|9|m|ft|abbr=on}} and the [[stern|aft]] beam to be lowered by {{convert|3.5|m|ft|abbr=on}}.{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=354}}

Although plans were not finalized, the third battlecruiser, &quot;Q&quot;, was ordered from [[Friedrich Krupp Germaniawerft|Germaniawerft]] in [[Kiel]] on 8 August 1939. One month after, the contract design was refined. The displacement was increased to {{convert|31652|t|LT}} ([[Displacement (ship)|design]]) and {{convert|35945|t|LT|abbr=on}} ([[Full-load displacement|full-load]]), while the [[Draft (hull)|draft]] at those two figures was {{convert|8|m|ft|abbr=on}} and {{convert|8.8|m|ft|abbr=on}}, respectively. At the [[waterline]], the [[Waterline length|length]] was set at {{convert|246|m|ft|abbr=on}} and beam at {{convert|30|m|ft|abbr=on}}. The [[main battery]] was the same as previously (six {{convert|380|mm|in|abbr=on}}/47 caliber guns in dual turrets), while the secondary battery was split between six paired {{convert|150|mm|in|abbr=on}}/48 caliber anti-surface guns and paired {{convert|105|mm|in|abbr=on}}/65 caliber [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft guns]] because German designers had not been able to develop a satisfactory [[dual-purpose gun]]. Light anti-aircraft guns were eight 37&amp;nbsp;mm in four dual mounts and twenty 20&amp;nbsp;mm autocannon in single mounts. Twelve {{convert|533|mm|in|abbr=on}} torpedo tubes finished out the armament aboard the ships. Four floatplanes for scouting were planned. At the design displacement, the maximum speed was reduced by half a knot, to {{convert|33.5|kn}}; this required a top [[shaft horsepower]] of 173,600.{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|pp=354–355}}

By 1940, project drawings for the three battlecruisers were complete. They were reviewed by both Hitler and Admiral Raeder, both of whom approved. However, outside &quot;initial procurement of materials and the issuance of some procurement orders&quot;,{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=354}} the ships' [[keel]]s were never laid.{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=354}} In large part, this was due to severe material shortages, especially of high-grade steel, since there were more pressing needs for these materials for the war effort. In addition, the dockyard personnel necessary for the ships' construction were by now occupied with more pressing work, primarily on new U-boats.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau|p=220}}

== Specifications ==

=== General characteristics ===
The final design, which was completed by 1940, called for a ship that was {{convert|248.2|m|ft|abbr=on}} long at the waterline and {{convert|256|m|ft|abbr=on}} long overall. The planned ships had a beam of {{convert|30|m|ft|abbr=on}} and a designed draft of {{convert|8.02|m|ft|abbr=on}}. The ships' designed displacement was {{convert|31650|t|LT|abbr=on}}, but displaced {{convert|28900|LT|t|abbr=on}} standard and {{convert|35400|LT|t|abbr=on}} at full displacement. The ships were to be of welded steel construction, with 20 [[watertight compartment]]s and a [[double bottom]] that extended for 78% of the length of the hull. The ships were to have had a crew of 65 officers and 1,900 men.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}}

They were intended to carry a number of boats aboard, including two [[picket boat]]s, two barges, two [[Launch (boat)|launches]], two [[pinnace (ship's boat)|pinnaces]], two [[yawl]]s, and two [[Dinghy|dinghies]]. The ships were also to be equipped with a double catapult mounted between the two funnels, and four [[Arado Ar 196]] seaplanes for maritime reconnaissance. The aircraft were stored in a main hangar just aft of the forward funnel, along with two smaller hangars, one on each side of the rear funnel.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}}

=== Propulsion ===
The O-class ships were to be driven by three screws, two diesel powered and one steam.  Eight [[MAN SE|MAN]] 24-cylinder V-configuration two-stroke [[diesel engine]]s powered two Vulcan gearboxes, both of which drove the outer pair of {{convert|4.85|m|ft|abbr=on}} diameter three-bladed screws. Aft of the diesel engines was a single boiler room with four Wagner high-pressure [[boiler]]s that provided up to 55&amp;nbsp;atmospheres of pressure.  These supplied steam for one set of [[Brown, Boveri &amp; Cie]] [[turbine]]s, which provided power for the center {{convert|4.9|m|ft|abbr=on}} three-bladed screw. The O-class ships were designed to store 1,000&amp;nbsp;tons fuel oil for the high pressure boilers, and up to 4,610&amp;nbsp;tons of diesel oil for the diesel engines. This enabled a maximum range of 14,000&amp;nbsp;nautical miles at a cruising speed of 19&amp;nbsp;knots. They were designed to steam at a maximum of 33.5&amp;nbsp;knots, but were capable of up to 35&amp;nbsp;knots. The ships had two rudders each. Eight 920&amp;nbsp;kW diesel generators supplied electrical power for the ships, for a total of 7360&amp;nbsp;kW, at 220&amp;nbsp;V.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}}

=== Armament ===
[[File:OclassCruiser1-23BigGuns1A1hullMid.blend.jpg|thumb|The rear main battery turret, with the superfiring secondary turret. Also visible is a twin [[10.5 cm FlaK 38]] anti-aircraft gun]]
The ships' main armament batteries were to have consisted of six [[38 cm SK C/34 naval gun|{{convert|38.1|cm|in|abbr=on}} L/47 SK C/34]] quick-firing guns mounted in three twin [[Gun turret|turrets]], the same Drh LC/38 gun turrets as were used on the {{sclass-|Bismarck|battleship|2}}s.{{sfn|Campbell|p=229&amp;ndash;230}} Two of the turrets were mounted in a superfiring pair forward, with the third turret placed aft of the main [[superstructure]]. The guns could depress to −8 degrees and elevate to 35 degrees. At maximum elevation, the guns could hit targets {{convert|36200|m|yd|abbr=on}} away. The guns had a designed supply of 630 shells, for a total of 105 rounds per gun.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}} There were three types of shells: capped armor-penetrating, and two different high-explosive shells; all three shells weighed {{convert|800|kg|lb|abbr=on}}. The guns used a {{convert|99.5|kg|lb|abbr=on}} fore charge and a {{convert|112.5|kg|lb|abbr=on}} main charge in a brass case. This provided a [[muzzle velocity]] of 820&amp;nbsp;meters per second (2,690&amp;nbsp;feet per second).{{sfn|Campbell|p=229&amp;ndash;230}}

The secondary battery consisted of six [[15 cm SK C/28|{{convert|15|cm|in|abbr=on}} L/48 SK C/28]] quick-firing guns, also mounted in three twin turrets; two were placed on either side of the forward superstructure, the third was placed aft of the main superstructure, superfiring over the rear main battery turret. These guns were supplied with 900 rounds, for 150 shells per gun, and had a maximum range of {{convert|23500|m|yd|abbr=on}}. The ships were also armed with six {{convert|53.3|cm|in|abbr=on}} above-water torpedo tubes, with a total of 18 torpedoes.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}}

The ships had an anti-aircraft battery consisting of eight [[10.5 cm FlaK 38|{{convert|10.5|cm|in|abbr=on}} L/65 SK C/33]] heavy anti-aircraft guns, eight [[3.7 cm SK C/30|{{convert|3.7|cm|in|abbr=on}} L/83 SK C/30]] anti-aircraft guns, and twenty {{convert|2|cm|in|abbr=on}}. The 10.5&amp;nbsp;cm guns were emplaced in twin mounts, two on either side of the superstructure, as were the 3.7&amp;nbsp;cm guns. The [[2 cm FlaK 30|2&amp;nbsp;cm SK C/30]] guns were placed in single mounts, dispersed on the superstructure amidships.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}}

=== Armor ===
The O-class ships were to be protected by [[Krupp]] ''Wotan'' steel armor. The main [[armored belt]] was {{convert|190|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick in the most critical areas of the ship, including the machinery spaces and ammunition magazines, and {{convert|100|mm|in|abbr=on}} in other less important areas; the armor tapered to zero at the stern and bow of the ship. A [[torpedo bulkhead]] ran the length of the hull; the bulkhead was {{convert|45|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick for the majority of its length. A second bulkhead was placed in the central portion of the ship. The bulkhead was {{convert|80|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick but increased to {{convert|110|mm|in|abbr=on}} in the more important portions of the ship. Critical areas were further protected by 80&amp;nbsp;mm-thick shields set back from the torpedo bulkhead. All of the lateral armor protection was ''Wotan Hart'' steel, with the exception of the torpedo bulkhead, which was ''Wotan Weich''.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}}{{efn|name=armor types}}

The ships had several layers of horizontal deck armor. The upper deck was {{convert|50|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick, and the armored deck ranged in thickness from 20–80&amp;nbsp;mm (.79–3.1&amp;nbsp;in); important areas were also protected by {{convert|60|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick overhead shields. The armored belt connected to 110&amp;nbsp;mm-thick sloping armor. The forward [[conning tower]] had a roof 60&amp;nbsp;mm thick and {{convert|200|mm|in|abbr=on}} armored sides; the aft conning tower was significantly less well protected. The roof was decreased to {{convert|30|mm|in|abbr=on}} and the sides were 50&amp;nbsp;mm thick. The rangefinders were protected against shell splinters by {{convert|20|mm|in|abbr=on}} roofs and 30&amp;nbsp;mm sides. All of this armor was ''Wotan Hart''.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}}

The main battery turrets had 50&amp;nbsp;mm thick roofs and sides that were {{convert|210|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick. The inner shields were {{convert|180|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick. The 15&amp;nbsp;cm gun turrets had {{convert|14|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick protection against shell fragments. All of the anti-aircraft weaponry were also protected with 14&amp;nbsp;mm-thick gun shields. The aircraft hangars also had 14&amp;nbsp;mm-thick splinter protection.{{sfn|Gröner|p=68}} The relatively thin armor protection given to the ships of the O class led to their derisive nickname &quot;''Ohne Panzer Quatsch''&quot; (Without armor nonsense), a play on their provisional names.{{sfn|Breyer|p=190}}

== Ships of the class ==
'''Schlachtkreuzer O'''
* Laid down: [[Deutsche Werke]] in [[Kiel]], construction number 265 (projected)
'''Schlachtkreuzer P'''
* Laid down: [[Kriegsmarinewerft Wilhelmshaven]] in [[Wilhelmshaven]], construction number 133 (projected)
'''Schlachtkreuzer Q'''
* Laid down: [[Friedrich Krupp Germaniawerft|Germaniawerft]] in [[Kiel]]; ordered 8 August 1939{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=354}}

== Notes ==
{{portal|Battleships}}

{{notes
| notes =
{{efn
| name = specifications
| The exact specifications, taken from Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=352: {{convert|20000|t|LT|link=yes}} [[displacement (ship)|displacement]], six {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}}, four {{convert|150|mm|in|abbr=on}}, eight {{convert|105|mm|in|abbr=on}}, a maximum speed of 34–35 [[knot (unit)|knot]], a {{convert|15000|mi|km|abbr=on}} range at 19&amp;nbsp;knots, {{convert|120|mm|in|abbr=on}} side [[belt armor|belt]] with a {{convert|60|mm|in|abbr=on}} belt to the bow and a {{convert|110|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[sloped armor|sloping]] towards the stern.
}}

{{efn
| name = foreign guns
| These were {{convert|305|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns on the American [[World War I|First World War]]-era {{sclass-|Wyoming|battleship|2}}s. In addition, five Italian battleships had or were in the process of replacing 305&amp;nbsp;mm guns with a smaller number of {{convert|320|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns.
}}

{{efn
| name = armor types
| ''Wotan Hart'' is hardened ''Wotan'' armor, while ''Weich'' is more flexible soft steel. The hardened ''Wotan'' had a breaking strength of 85–96&amp;nbsp;kg/mm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and 20% expansion, while the soft steel ''Wotan'' had a breaking strength of 65–75&amp;nbsp;kg/mm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and 25% expansion. See: {{harvnb|Gröner|p=X}}.
}}

}}

== References ==
{{reflist|20em}}

== Bibliography ==
{{Wikipedia books|Battlecruisers of Germany}}

* {{cite book
  | last = Breyer
  | first = Siegfried
  | title = Schlachtschiffe und Schlachtkreuzer 1921&amp;ndash;1997: Internationaler Schlachtschiffbau
  | year = 2002
  | location = Bonn
  | publisher = Bernard &amp; Graef
  | isbn = 3-76376-225-6
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Breyer}}
  | language = German
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Campbell
  | first = John
  | year = 1985
  | title = Naval Weapons of World War II
  | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-459-2
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Campbell}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | editor1-last = Gardiner
  | editor1-first = Robert
  | editor2-last = Chesneau
  | editor2-first = Roger
  | year = 1980
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1922–1946
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, Maryland
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-913-9
  | oclc = 18121784
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=bJBMBvyQ83EC
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Garzke
  | first1 = William H.
  | last2 = Dulin
  | first2 = Robert O.
  | title = Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II
  | location = Annapolis, Maryland
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | year = 1985
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-101-0
  | oclc = 12613723
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Garzke &amp; Dulin}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Gröner
  | first = Erich
  | title = German Warships: 1815–1945
  | year = 1990
  | location = Annapolis
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-790-6
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gröner}}
  }}

{{Large cruisers}}
{{WWIIGermanShips}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:O-class battlecruiser}}
[[Category:Plan Z]]
[[Category:Battlecruisers of the Kriegsmarine]]
[[Category:World War II battlecruisers of Germany]]
[[Category:Proposed ships of Germany]]
[[Category:Abandoned military projects of Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>04kj61geeul0khc8dhu4ikzy4dcjldz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
