<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Oxford Castle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1137951</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749472182</id>
      <parentid>748487780</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T15:01:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>1 archive template merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21942">{{good article}}
{{Infobox Military Structure
|name = Oxford Castle
|location = [[Oxfordshire]], England
|coordinates = {{gbmapping|SP509063}}
|image = [[Image:Oxford Castle.JPG|225px]]
|caption = St George's Tower, Oxford Castle
|map_type = Oxfordshire
|latitude = 51.75180
|longitude = -1.26248
|coord_region=GB-OXF
|coord_display = title
|map_size = 200
|map_alt = 
|map_caption = Shown within [[Oxfordshire]]
|type = [[Shell keep]] and [[Ward (fortification)|bailey]]
|materials = [[Coral rag]] and [[gravel]]
|height = 
|condition = Ruined, elements used as a [[hotel]]
|ownership = [[Oxfordshire County Council]]
|open_to_public = 
|battles = 
|events = 
}}

'''Oxford Castle''' is a large, partly ruined [[Norman architecture|Norman]] [[medieval]] [[castle]] on the western side of central [[Oxford]] in [[Oxfordshire]], England. Most of the original [[moat]]ed, wooden [[motte and bailey]] castle was replaced in stone in the 11th century and played an important role in the conflict of [[the Anarchy]]. In the 14th century the military value of the castle diminished and the site became used primarily for [[county]] administration and as a prison.

Most of the castle was destroyed in the [[English Civil War]] and by the 18th century the remaining buildings had become Oxford's local [[prison]]. A new prison complex was built on the site from 1785 onwards and expanded in 1876; this became [[Her Majesty's Prison Service|HM Prison]] Oxford.

The prison closed in 1996 and was redeveloped as a [[Malmaison (hotel chain)|hotel]]. The medieval remains of the castle, including the motte and St George's Tower and crypt, are [[Listed building#Categories of listed building|Grade I listed buildings]] and a [[Scheduled Monument]].

==History==

===Construction===
According to the ''[[Historia Ecclesie Abbendonensis|Abingdon Chronicle]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Referenced in Harfield, p.388.&lt;/ref&gt; Oxford Castle was built by the [[Normans|Norman]] [[baron]] [[Robert D'Oyly (Oxford)|Robert D'Oyly]] the elder from 1071–73.&lt;ref name=JoyP28&gt;Joy, p.28.&lt;/ref&gt; D'Oyly had arrived in England with William I in the [[Norman Conquest of England]] in 1066 and [[William the Conqueror]] granted him extensive lands in Oxfordshire.&lt;ref name=JoyP28/&gt; Oxford had been stormed in the invasion with considerable damage, and William directed D'Oyly to build a castle to dominate the town.&lt;ref&gt;MacKenzie, 147; Tyack, p.5.&lt;/ref&gt; In due course D'Oyly became the foremost landowner in Oxfordshire and was confirmed with a hereditary royal constableship for Oxford Castle.&lt;ref&gt;Amt, pp.47–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Oxford Castle is not among the 48 recorded in the [[Domesday Book]] of 1086, but not every castle in existence at the time was recorded in the survey.&lt;ref&gt;Harfield, pp.384, 388–9.&lt;/ref&gt;

D'Oyly positioned his castle to the west side of the town, using the natural protection of a stream off the [[River Thames]] on the far side of the castle, now called [[Castle Mill Stream]], and diverting the stream to produce a [[moat]].&lt;ref name=MacKenzieP147&gt;MacKenzie, p.147.&lt;/ref&gt; There has been debate as to whether there was an earlier English fortification on the site, but whilst there is archaeological evidence of earlier Anglo-Saxon habitation there is no conclusive evidence of fortification.&lt;ref name=MacKenzieP147/&gt; Oxford Castle was clearly an &quot;urban castle&quot; but it remains uncertain whether local buildings had to be demolished to make room for it. The [[Domesday Book]] does not record any demolition, so the land may have already been empty due to the damage caused by the Norman seizure of the town.&lt;ref&gt;Jope, p.79; Creighton, p.146.&lt;/ref&gt; Alternatively the castle may have been imposed over an existing street front which would have required the demolition of at least several houses.&lt;ref&gt;Tyack, p.5; Creighton, p.148.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Map of Oxford Castle.png|thumb|left|Oxford Castle, around 1250. A: The keep and motte; B: St George's Tower and Chapel; C: The Round Tower; D: River Isis; E: Moat; F: City wall; G: West Gate; H: Barbican&lt;ref&gt;Map drawn after Hassall 1971, p.2; Tyack, p.6, p.80.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The initial castle was probably a large [[motte and bailey]], copying the plan of the castle that D'Oyly had already built {{convert|12|mi}} away at [[Wallingford Castle|Wallingford]].&lt;ref name=MacKenzieP147/&gt; The motte was originally about {{convert|60|ft}} high and {{convert|40|ft}} wide, constructed like the [[bailey (fortification)|bailey]] from layers of gravel and strengthened with clay facing.&lt;ref&gt;MacKenzie, p.148; [http://thehumanjourney.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=507&amp;Itemid=40 Oxford Archaeology], accessed 12 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; There has been debate over the sequencing of the motte and the bailey: it has been suggested that the bailey may have built first, which would make the initial castle design a [[ringwork]] rather than a motte and bailey.&lt;ref name=HassallP233&gt;Hassall 1976, p.233.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the mid-12th century Oxford Castle had been significantly extended in stone. The first such work was St George's Tower, built of [[coral rag]] stone in 1074, {{convert|30|x|30|ft|0}} at the base and tapering significantly toward the top for stability.&lt;ref&gt;Tyack, p.7; MacKenzie, p.148.&lt;/ref&gt; This was the tallest of the castle's towers, possibly because it covered the approach to the old west gate of the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tyack, p.6; Hassall 1976, p.233&quot;&gt;Tyack, p.6; Hassall 1976, p.233.&lt;/ref&gt;

Inside the walls the tower included a crypt chapel,&lt;ref name=&quot;Tyack, p.6; Hassall 1976, p.233&quot;/&gt; which may be the site of a previous church.&lt;ref name=HassallP233/&gt; The crypt chapel originally had a nave, chancel and an [[apse|apsidal]] sanctuary. It is a typical early Norman design with solid pillars and arches.&lt;ref&gt;Tyack, p.8.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1074 D'Oyly and his close friend, [[Roger d'Ivry]] endowed a chapel with a college of priests. At an early stage it acquired a dedication to [[Saint George]].

Early in the 13th century the wooden keep on top of the motte was replaced with a ten-sided stone [[shell keep]], {{convert|58|ft}}, closely resembling those of [[Tonbridge Castle|Tonbridge]] and [[Arundel Castle]]s.&lt;ref name=MacKenzieGravettHookP149&gt;MacKenzie, p.149; Gravett and Hook, p.43.&lt;/ref&gt; The keep enclosed a number of buildings, leaving an inner courtyard only {{convert|22|ft|0}} across.&lt;ref name=MacKenzieP149&gt;MacKenzie, p.149.&lt;/ref&gt; Within the keep, stairs led {{convert|20|ft|0}} down to an underground {{convert|12|ft}} wide stone chamber, with an [[English Gothic architecture#Early English Gothic|Early English]] hexagonal vault and a {{convert|54|ft}} deep well providing water in the event of siege.&lt;ref&gt;Tyack, p.8; MacKenzie, p.149.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Role in the Anarchy and Barons War===
[[File:Empress matilda.jpg|thumb|[[Empress Matilda]] escaped from Oxford Castle in 1141 in [[the Anarchy]].]]
[[Robert D'Oyly (Osney)|Robert D'Oyly the younger]], Robert D'Oyly the elder's nephew, had inherited the castle by the time of the civil war of [[the Anarchy]] in the 1140s.&lt;ref name=JoyP28/&gt; After initially supporting [[King Stephen of England|King Stephen]], Robert declared his support for [[Empress Matilda]], Stephen's cousin and rival for the throne, and in 1141 the Empress marched to Oxford to base her campaign at the castle.&lt;ref&gt;MacKenzie, p.149; Amt, p.48.&lt;/ref&gt; Stephen responded by marching unexpectedly from [[Bristol]] in December, attacking and seizing the town of Oxford and besieging Matilda in the castle.&lt;ref name=MacKenzieP149/&gt; Stephen set up two [[Siege#Offensive|siege mounds]] beside the castle, called Jew's Mount and Mount Pelham, on which he placed siege engines, largely for show, and proceeded to wait for Matilda's supplies to run low over the next three months.&lt;ref name=MacKenzieGravettHookP149/&gt; Stephen would have had difficulty in supplying his men through the winter period, and this decision shows the apparent strength of Oxford Castle at the time.&lt;ref name=GravettHookP44&gt;Gravett and Hook, p.44.&lt;/ref&gt;

Matilda responded by escaping from the castle; the popular version of this has the Empress waiting until the [[Castle Mill Stream]] was frozen over and then dressed in white as [[camouflage]] in the snow, being lowered down the walls with three or four knights, before escaping through Stephen's lines in the night as the king's sentries tried to raise the alarm.&lt;ref&gt;MacKenzie, p.149; Gravett and Hook, p.44.&lt;/ref&gt; The chronicler [[William of Malmesbury]], however, suggests Matilda did not descend the walls, but instead escaped from one of the gates.&lt;ref name=GravettHookP44/&gt; Matilda safely reached [[Abingdon-on-Thames]] and Oxford Castle surrendered to Stephen the next day.&lt;ref name=MacKenzieGravettHookP149/&gt; Robert had died in the final weeks of the siege and the castle was granted to [[William de Chesney]] for the remainder of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Amt, p.48.&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the war the constableship of Oxford Castle was granted to [[Roger de Bussy]] before being reclaimed by Henry D'Oyly, Robert D'Oyly the younger's son, in 1154.&lt;ref&gt;Amt, pp.56–7.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[First Barons' War|Barons' War]] of 1215–17 the castle was attacked again, prompting further improvements in its defences.&lt;ref name=HassallP235/&gt; In 1220 [[Falkes de Breauté]], who controlled many royal castles in the middle of England, demolished the Church of St Budoc to the south-east of the castle and built a moated [[barbican]] to further defend the main gate.&lt;ref&gt;Hassall 1971, p.9.&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining wooden buildings were replaced in stone, including the new Round Tower which was built in 1235.&lt;ref&gt;Hassall 1976, p.235; Tyack, p.8.&lt;/ref&gt; King [[King Henry III of England|Henry III]] turned part of the castle into a prison, specifically for holding troublesome University [[Scholarly method|clerks]], and also improved the castle chapel, replacing the older barred windows with [[stained glass]] in 1243 and 1246.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p.3; Marks, p.93.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the presence of [[Beaumont Palace]] to the north of Oxford, however, the castle never became a royal residence.&lt;ref&gt;Munby, p.96.&lt;/ref&gt;

===14th–17th centuries===
[[File:Oxford Castle 15th century.jpg|thumb|How an artist in 1845 imagined Oxford Castle looked in the 15th century]]
By 1327 the fortification, particularly the castle gates and the barbican, was in poor condition and £800 was estimated to be required for repairs.&lt;ref&gt;Crossley and Elrington, p.297.&lt;/ref&gt; From the 1350s onwards the castle had little military use and was increasingly allowed to fall into disrepair.&lt;ref name=HassallP235/&gt; The castle became the centre for the administration of the county of Oxford, a jail, and a criminal court. [[Assizes (England and Wales)|Assizes]] were held there until 1577, when plague broke out in what became known as the &quot;[[Black Assize]]&quot;: the [[Lord Lieutenant]] of Oxfordshire, two knights, eighty gentlemen and the entire [[grand jury]] for the session all died, including Sir Robert D'Oyley, a relative of the founder of the castle.&lt;ref name=TyackHassallMacKenzieDavies&gt;Tyack, p.8; Hassall 1976, p.235; MacKenzie, p.149; Davies, pp.91–2.&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter assizes ceased to be held at the castle.&lt;ref name=TyackHassallMacKenzieDavies/&gt;

By the 16th century the barbican had been demolished to make way for houses and the moat had begun to be occupied with housing. By 1600 the moat was almost entirely silted up and houses had been built all around the edge of the bailey wall.&lt;ref&gt;Hassall 1976, p.235, 254.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1611 [[King James I of England|King James I]] sold Oxford Castle to Francis James and Robert Younglove, who in turn sold it to [[Christ Church, Oxford|Christ Church College]] in 1613. The college then leased it to a number of local families over the coming years.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p.3.&lt;/ref&gt; By this time Oxford Castle was in a weakened state, with a large crack running down the side of the keep.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford Archaeology&quot;&gt;[http://thehumanjourney.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=507&amp;Itemid=40 Oxford Archaeology], accessed 12 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1642 the [[English Civil War]] broke out and the [[Cavaliers|Royalist]]s made Oxford their capital. Parliamentary forces successfully [[Siege of Oxford|besieged Oxford]] in 1646 and the city was occupied by Colonel Ingoldsby.&lt;ref name=JoyP29&gt;Joy, p.29.&lt;/ref&gt; Ingoldsby improved the fortification of the castle rather than the surrounding town, and in 1649 demolished most of the medieval stonework, replacing it with more modern earth [[bulwark]]s and reinforcing the keep with earth works to form a probable gun-platform.&lt;ref&gt;Joy, p.29; [http://thehumanjourney.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=507&amp;Itemid=40 Oxford Archaeology], accessed 12 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1652, in the [[third English Civil War]], the Parliamentary garrison responded to the proximity of [[King Charles II of England|Charles II]]'s forces by pulling down these defences as well and retreating to [[New College, Oxford|New College]] instead, causing great damage to the college in the process.&lt;ref name=JoyP29/&gt; In the event, Oxford saw no fresh fighting; early in the 18th century, however, the keep was demolished and the top of the motte landscaped to its current form.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford Archaeology&quot;/&gt;

===Role as prison===
[[File:Oxford Castle in 1832.jpg|thumb|St George's Tower in 1832]]
After the Civil War, Oxford Castle served primarily as the local prison.&lt;ref name=DaviesP6&gt;Davies, p.6.&lt;/ref&gt; As with other prisons at the time, the owners, in this case Christ Church College, leased the castle to wardens who would profit by charging prisoners for their board and lodging.&lt;ref name=DaviesP6/&gt; The prison also had a [[gallows]] to execute prisoners, such as [[Mary Blandy]] in 1752.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p.106.&lt;/ref&gt; For most of the 18th century, the castle prison was run by the local Etty and Wisdom families and was in increasing disrepair.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, pp.9–10.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1770s the prison reformer [[John Howard (prison reformer)|John Howard]] visited the castle several times, and criticised its size and quality, including the extent to which [[vermin]] infested the prison.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p.14.&lt;/ref&gt; Partly as a result of this criticism, it was decided by the County authorities to rebuild the Oxford Prison.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p.15.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1785 the castle was bought by the Oxford County Justices and rebuilding began under the London architect [[William Blackburn]].&lt;ref&gt;Hassall 1976, p.235; Whiting, p.54.&lt;/ref&gt; The wider castle site had already begun to change by the late 18th century, with [[New Road, Oxford|New Road]] being built through the bailey and the last parts of the castle moat being filled in to allow the building of the new [[Oxford Canal]] terminus.&lt;ref name=HassallP235&gt;Hassall, p.235.&lt;/ref&gt; Building the new prison included demolishing the old college attached to St George's chapel and repositioning part of the crypt in 1794.&lt;ref name=EH-Towers&amp;Crypt/&gt; The work was completed under [[Daniel Harris (Oxford)|Daniel Harris]] in 1805.&lt;ref&gt;Hyack, p.7; Whiting, p.54.&lt;/ref&gt; Harris gained a reasonable salary as the new governor and used convict labour from the prison to conduct early archaeological excavations at the castle with the help of the antiquarian Edward King.&lt;ref&gt;Munby, p.53; Davies, p.24.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th century the site continued to be developed, with various new buildings built including the new County Hall in 1840–41 and the [[Oxfordshire Militia]] Armoury in 1854. The prison itself was extended in 1876, growing to occupy most of the remaining space.&lt;ref name=HassallP235/&gt; In 1888 national prison reforms led to the renaming of the county prison as [[Her Majesty's Prison Service|HM Prison]] Oxford.

===Today===
[[File:OxfordCastle StGeorgesCrypt.jpg|thumb|St George's crypt chapel, rebuilt in 1794 re-using its late 11th-century [[Norman architecture|Norman]] columns and capitals]]
Since 1954 the two oldest parts of the castle have been Grade I listed buildings: the 11th-century motte with its 13th-century well-chamber,&lt;ref name=EH-WellHouse&gt;''[http://list.english-heritage.org.uk/resultsingle.aspx?uid=1369493 Well House Oxford Castle]'', National Heritage List for England, [[English Heritage]], accessed 26 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and the 11th-century St George's tower with its crypt chapel and the 18th-century D-wing and Debtors' Tower.&lt;ref name=EH-Towers&amp;Crypt&gt;''[http://list.english-heritage.org.uk/resultsingle.aspx?uid=1369490 St Georges Tower, St Georges Chapel Crypt and D Wing Including the Debtors Tower]'', National Heritage List for England, [[English Heritage]], accessed 26 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The site is protected as a [[Scheduled Monument]].&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.gatehouse-gazetteer.info/English%20sites/2961.html Oxford Castle]'', Gatehouse, accessed 27 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

The prison was closed in 1996 and the site reverted to [[Oxfordshire County Council]]. The Oxford Prison buildings have since been redeveloped as a restaurant and heritage complex, with guided tours of the historic buildings and open courtyards for markets and theatrical performances. The complex includes a hotel in the [[Malmaison (hotel chain)|Malmaison]] chain, Malmaison Oxford, occupying a large part of the former prison blocks, with cells converted as guest rooms. However, those parts of the prison associated with corporal or capital punishment have been converted to offices rather than being used for guests.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, p.93.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[mixed-use]] heritage project, officially opened on 5 May 2006, won the [[Royal Institution of Chartered Surveyors|RICS]] Project of the Year Award 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071023000124/http://www.rics.org/AboutRICS/Awards/RICSAwards/RICS+Awards+2007+Winners.htm |date=October 23, 2007 |title=RICS Awards 2007 Winners list }}, RICS&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Castles in Great Britain and Ireland]]
*[[List of castles in England]]

==References==

{{reflist|28em}}

==Bibliography==
[[File:OxfordCastle MotteWellVault.jpg|thumb|13th-century [[English Gothic architecture#Early English Gothic|Early English]] hexagonal vault of the well-chamber inside the motte]]
[[File:Oxford Malmaison Hotel.jpg|thumb|HMP Oxford has been converted into a [[Malmaison (hotel chain)|Malmaison Hotel]].]]
* Amt, Emilie. (1993) ''The Accession of Henry II in England: Royal Government Restored, 1149-1159.'' Woodbridge, [[Boydell &amp; Brewer|Boydell Press]]. ISBN 978-0-85115-348-3.
* Creighton, O. H. (2002) ''Castles and Landscapes: Power, Community and Fortification in Medieval England.'' London: Equinox. ISBN 978-1-904768-67-8.
* Crossley, Alan and C. Elrington. (eds) (1979) Victoria County History: ''[http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=22809 A History of the County of Oxford, Volume 4: The City of Oxford.]'' {{OCLC|7534514}}.
* Davies, Mark. (2001) ''Stories of Oxford Castle: From Dungeon to Dunghill.'' Oxford: Oxford Towpath Press. ISBN 0-9535593-3-5.
* Gravett, Christopher and Adam Hook. (2003) ''Norman Stone Castles: The British Isles, 1066-1216.'' Botley, Osprey. ISBN 978-1-84176-602-7.
*{{cite journal |last=Harfield |first=C. G. |title=A Hand-list of Castles Recorded in the Domesday Book |journal=English Historical Review |volume=106 |year=1991 |pages=371–392 |jstor=573107 |doi=10.1093/ehr/CVI.CCCCXIX.371}}
* Harrison, Colin. (ed) (1998) ''John Malchair of Oxford: Artist and Musician.'' Oxford: [[Ashmolean Museum]]. ISBN 978-1-85444-112-6.
* Hassall, T. G. (1971) &quot;Excavations at Oxford,&quot; in ''[[Oxfordshire Architectural and Historical Society|Oxoniensia]]'', XXXVI (1971).
* Hassall, T. G. (1976) &quot;Excavations at Oxford Castle: 1965-1973,&quot; in ''[[Oxfordshire Architectural and Historical Society|Oxoniensia]]'', XLI (1976).
* Jope, E. M. &quot;Late Saxon Pits Under Oxford Castle Mound: Excavations in 1952,&quot; in ''[[Oxfordshire Architectural and Historical Society|Oxoniensia]]'', XVII-XVIII (1952–1953).
* Joy, T. (1831) ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=-eoHAAAAQAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Oxford Delineated: A sketch of the history and antiquities.]'' Oxford: Whessell &amp; Bartlett. {{OCLC|23436981}}.
* MacKenzie, James Dixon. (1896/2009) ''The Castles of England: Their Story and Structure.'' [[Books LLC|General Books]]. ISBN 978-1-150-51044-1.
* Marks, Richard. (1993) ''Stained glass in England during the Middle Ages.'' London: [[Routledge]]. ISBN 978-0-415-03345-9.
* Munby, Julian. (1998) &quot;Malchair and the Oxford Topographical Tradition,&quot; in Harrison (ed) 1998.
* Smith, Philip. (2008) ''Punishment and Culture.'' Chicago: [[University of Chicago Press]]. ISBN 978-0-226-76610-2.
* Tyack, Geoffrey. (1998) ''Oxford: an Architectural Guide.'' Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN 978-0-19-817423-3.
* Whiting, R. C. (1993) ''Oxford: Studies in the History of a University Town Since 1800.'' Manchester: [[Manchester University Press]]. ISBN 978-0-7190-3057-4.

==External links==
{{commons category|Oxford Castle}}
* [http://www.oxfordcastle.com/ Oxford Castle website]
* [http://www.gatehouse-gazetteer.info/English%20sites/2961.html Gatehouse Website record for Oxford Castle]
* [http://www.oxfordcastleunlocked.co.uk/ Oxford Castle Visitor Attraction]
* [http://www.malmaison.com/locations/oxford/ Malmaison Oxford]

{{Museums and galleries in Oxfordshire}}
{{Prisons in South East England}}

{{coord|51.7517|N|1.2632|W|type:landmark_region:GB|display=title}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1073]]
[[Category:1071 establishments in England]]
[[Category:Castles in Oxfordshire]]
[[Category:Defunct prisons in Oxfordshire]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in Oxford|Castle]]
[[Category:Grade I listed castles]]
[[Category:Grade I listed prison buildings]]
[[Category:Hotels in Oxford]]
[[Category:Museums in Oxfordshire]]
[[Category:Norman architecture in England]]
[[Category:Prison museums in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Oxford|Castle]]
[[Category:Motte-and-bailey castles]]</text>
      <sha1>k9sx4hvcbj2kvwringtdigmiw8k32x2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
