<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Panavia Tornado</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>168682</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747349740</id>
      <parentid>747349594</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-01T21:34:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>85.211.216.28</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* {{anchor|Tornado ECR|ECR}} Tornado ECR (Electric Combat / Reconnaissance) */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="111034">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, and guidelines. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
 |name=Tornado IDS/ECR
 |image= File:Image of a 15 Squadron GR4 taken over Royal Air Force Lossiemouth, and surrounding countryside. MOD 45155748.jpg
 |caption=Tornado GR4 of [[No. 31 Squadron RAF]] in 2009 with typical counter-insurgency weapons of [[Brimstone (missile)|Brimstone]], [[Paveway IV]] and [[LITENING targeting pod]]
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
 |type=[[Multirole combat aircraft|Multirole aircraft]], [[Attack aircraft|strike aircraft]]
 |manufacturer= [[Panavia Aircraft GmbH]]
 |designer=
 |first flight=14 August 1974
 |introduced=1979
 |retired=
 |status= In service
 |primary user=[[Royal Air Force]]
 |more users=[[Italian Air Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[German Air Force]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Royal Saudi Air Force]]
 |produced=1979–1998
 |number built=992
 |program cost= 
 |unit cost=
 |developed from=
 |variants with their own articles= [[Panavia Tornado ADV]]
}}
|}

The '''Panavia Tornado''' is a family of [[Twinjet|twin-engine]], [[variable-sweep wing]] [[multirole combat aircraft]], which was jointly developed and manufactured by Italy, the United Kingdom, and [[West Germany]]. There are three primary [[Panavia Tornado variants|Tornado variants]]: the Tornado IDS ([[interdictor]]/[[attack aircraft|strike]]) fighter-bomber, the [[suppression of enemy air defences]] Tornado ECR ([[electronic warfare aircraft|electronic combat]]/[[reconnaissance aircraft|reconnaissance]]) and the [[Panavia Tornado ADV|Tornado ADV]] (air defence variant) [[interceptor aircraft]].

The Tornado was developed and built by [[Panavia Aircraft GmbH]], a tri-national consortium consisting of  [[British Aerospace]] (previously [[British Aircraft Corporation]]), [[Messerschmitt-Bölkow-Blohm|MBB]] of West Germany, and [[Aeritalia]] of Italy. It first flew on 14 August 1974 and was introduced into service in 1979–1980. Due to its [[multirole combat aircraft|multirole]] nature, it was able to replace several different fleets of aircraft in the adopting air forces. The [[Royal Saudi Air Force]] (RSAF) became the only export operator of the Tornado in addition to the three original partner nations. A tri-nation training and evaluation unit operating from [[RAF Cottesmore]], the [[Tri-National Tornado Training Establishment]], maintained a level of international co-operation beyond the production stage.

The Tornado was used by the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF), [[Italian Air Force]] and RSAF during the 1991 [[Gulf War]], in which the Tornado conducted many low-altitude penetrating strike missions. The Tornados of various operators were also used in conflicts in the former Yugoslavia during the [[Bosnian War]] and [[Kosovo War]], the [[Iraq War]], Libya during the [[Libyan Civil War (2011)|Libyan civil war]], as well as smaller roles in [[Afghanistan]], [[Yemen]], and [[Syria]]. Including all variants, 992 aircraft were built.

==Development==

===Origins===
[[File:AFVG (1965).jpg|thumb|Artist's concept of the [[AFVG]], an ancestor to the MRCA programme]]

During the 1960s, aeronautical designers looked to [[Variable-sweep wing|variable-geometry wing]] designs to gain the manoeuvrability and efficient cruise of straight wings with the speed of [[swept wing]] designs. The United Kingdom had cancelled the procurement of the [[TSR-2]] and subsequent [[General Dynamics F-111K|F-111K]] aircraft, and was still looking for a replacement for its [[Avro Vulcan]] and [[Blackburn Buccaneer]] strike aircraft.&lt;ref name = 'segell124'&gt;Segell 1997, p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt; Britain and France had initiated the [[AFVG]] (Anglo French Variable Geometry) project in 1965, but this had ended with French withdrawal in 1967.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/djreprints/access/72865521.html?dids=72865521:72865521&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:AI&amp;type=historic&amp;date=Jun+22%2C+1967&amp;author=&amp;pub=Wall+Street+Journal&amp;desc=British-French+Work+On+New+Military+Plane+Periled+by+Cost+Fight&amp;pqatl=google &quot;British-French Work On New Military Plane Periled by Cost Fight.&quot;] ''Wall Street Journal,'' 22 June 1967.&lt;/ref&gt; Britain continued to develop a variable-geometry aircraft similar to the proposed AFVG, and sought new partners to achieve this.&lt;ref name = 'torn birt 11'&gt;Willox 2002, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1968, West Germany, the Netherlands, Belgium, Italy and Canada formed a working group to examine replacements for the [[Lockheed F-104 Starfighter]],&lt;ref name = '104replac'/&gt; initially called the ''Multi Role Aircraft (MRA)'', later renamed as the ''Multi Role Combat Aircraft (MRCA)''.&lt;ref name = 'jerr53'&gt;Scutts 2000, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; The participating nations all had ageing fleets that required replacing; but, as the requirements were so diverse, it was decided to develop a single aircraft that could perform a variety of missions that were previously undertaken by a fleet of different aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Haglund 1989, pp. 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt; Britain joined the MRCA group in 1968, represented by [[Air Vice-Marshal]] [[Michael Giddings]], and a memorandum of agreement was drafted between Britain, West Germany, and Italy in May 1969.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id=VvYeAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=LowEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7327,1861291&amp;dq=multi+role+aircraft&amp;hl=en &quot;European Nations Plan Mammoth Military Aircraft.&quot;] ''Sarasota Journal,'' 14 January 1969.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of 1968, the prospective purchases from the six countries amounted to 1,500 aircraft.&lt;ref name = 'jef 28'&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Canada and Belgium had departed before any long-term commitments had been made to the programme;&lt;ref name = 'haglund 48'&gt;Haglund 1989, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; Canada had found the project politically unpalatable; there was a perception in political circles that much of the manufacturing and specifications were focused on Western Europe. France had made a favourable offer to Belgium on the [[Dassault Mirage 5]], which created doubt as to whether the MRCA would be worthwhile from Belgium's operational perspective.&lt;ref name = 'haglund 48'/&gt;

===Panavia Aircraft GmbH===
{{main article|Panavia Aircraft GmbH}}

On 26 March 1969, four partner nations&amp;nbsp;– United Kingdom, Germany, Italy and the Netherlands, agreed to form a multinational company, Panavia Aircraft GmbH, to develop and manufacture the MRCA.&lt;ref name ='segell124'/&gt;&lt;ref name = '104replac'&gt;Morris, Joe Alex Jr. &quot;Messerschmitt Back in Business.&quot; ''St. Petersburg Times,'' 30 April 1969.&lt;/ref&gt; The project's aim was to produce an aircraft capable of undertaking missions in the tactical strike, reconnaissance, air defence, and maritime roles; thus allowing the MRCA to replace several different aircraft then in use by the partner nations.&lt;ref name ='segell124'/&gt;&lt;ref name = '104replac'/&gt; Various concepts, including alternative fixed-wing and single-engine designs, were studied while defining the aircraft.&lt;ref name = 'jef 26'&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; The Netherlands pulled out of the project in 1970, citing that the aircraft was too complicated and technical for the [[Royal Netherlands Air Force|RNLAF]]'s preferences,&lt;ref name ='segell124'/&gt; which had sought a simpler aircraft with outstanding manoeuvrability.&lt;ref name = 'haglund 49'&gt;Haglund 1989, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; An additional blow was struck by the German requirement reduced from an initial 600 aircraft to 324 in 1972.&lt;ref name = 'jef 28-9'&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, pp. 28–29.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RAF Tornado F2.JPEG|thumb|Formation take-off of an RAF Tornado GR.1 and a Tornado F.2 prototype in September 1982]]

When the agreement was finalised, the United Kingdom and West Germany each had a 42.5% stake of the workload, with the remaining 15% going to Italy; this division of the production work was heavily influenced by international political bargaining.&lt;ref name = 'haglund 52+56'&gt;Haglund 1989, pp. 52, 56.&lt;/ref&gt; The front fuselage and tail assembly was assigned to [[British Aircraft Corporation|BAC]] (now [[BAE Systems]]) in the United Kingdom; the centre fuselage to [[Messerschmitt-Bölkow-Blohm|MBB]] (now [[EADS]]) in West Germany; and the wings to [[Aeritalia]] (now [[Alenia Aeronautica]]) in Italy.&lt;ref name ='segell125'&gt;Segell 1997, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, tri-national worksharing was used for engines, general and avionic equipment. A separate multinational company, [[Turbo-Union]], was formed in June 1970 to develop and build the [[Turbo-Union RB199|RB199]] engines for the aircraft, with ownership similarly split 40% [[Rolls-Royce plc|Rolls-Royce]], 40% [[MTU Aero Engines|MTU]], and 20% [[FIAT]].&lt;ref name ='segell124'/&gt;&lt;ref name = 'Wellington'&gt;Long, Wellington. [https://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id=BmAvAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=2dwFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5323,4133149&amp;dq=tornado+bomber&amp;hl=en &quot;Swing-Wing Wonder Weapon Is Going Into Production.&quot;] ''Ludington Daily News,''24 August 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the conclusion of the project definition phase in May 1970, the concepts were reduced to two designs; a single seat Panavia 100 which West Germany initially preferred, and the twin-seat Panavia 200 which the RAF preferred (this would become the Tornado).&lt;ref name = 'Wellington'/&gt; The aircraft was briefly called the ''Panavia Panther'', and the project soon coalesced towards the two-seat option.&lt;ref&gt;Dorrell, David, ed. &quot;Britain's Aircraft Industry enters the 1970s.&quot; ''Air Pictorial,'' Volume 32, No. 9, September 1970, p. 306.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1971, the three governments signed an Intention to Proceed (ITP) document, at which point the aircraft was intended solely for the low-level strike mission, where it was viewed as a viable threat to Soviet defences in that role.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Paul. [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FA0E12FC385D11728DDDAA0994D9415B898BF1D3 &quot;Europe's Fighter Jet Program: Tornado Offers Competition for U.S. Concerns Project Valued at $17&amp;nbsp;billion.&quot;] ''The New York Times,'' 13 November 1979. Retrieved 13 November 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; It was at this point that Britain's Chief of the Defence Staff announced ''&quot;two-thirds of the fighting front line will be composed of this single, basic aircraft type&quot;''.&lt;ref name ='segell125'/&gt;

===Prototypes and testing===
The first of more than a dozen Tornado prototypes took flight on 14 August 1974 at [[Manching]], Germany; the pilot, Paul Millett stated of the occasion: ''&quot;Aircraft handling was delightful... the actual flight went so smoothly that I did begin to wonder whether this was not yet another simulation&quot;''.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, pp. 89–90.&lt;/ref&gt; Flight testing led to the need for minor modifications. Airflow disturbances were responded to by re-profiling the engine intakes and the fuselage to minimise [[Compressor stall|surging]] and [[buffeting]] experienced at supersonic speeds.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, pp. 91–92, 95–96.&lt;/ref&gt; Testing revealed that a nose-wheel steering augmentation system, connecting with the [[yaw damper]], was necessary to counteract the destabilising effect produced by deploying the thrust reverser during landing rollouts.&lt;ref&gt;Burger, Κ.Η. &quot;In-Flight Short Field Landing Investigations on a Combat Aircraft with Thrust Reverser.&quot; ''International Journal of Turbo and Jet Engines''. 3, (2–3), pp. 99–104, ISSN 2191-0332.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1976, Soviet espionage activities were exposed trying to obtain information on the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Mutch, David. [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/csmonitor_historic/access/261193762.html?dids=261193762:261193762&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:AI&amp;date=Aug+18%2C+1976&amp;author=By+David+Mutch+Staff+correspondent+of+The+Christian+Science+Monitor&amp;pub=Christian+Science+Monitor&amp;desc=NATO+plane+found+to+be+spy+target&amp;pqatl=google &quot;NATO plane found to be spy target.&quot;] ''Christian Science Monitor,'' 18 August 1976. Retrieved 18 August 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;

Two prototypes were lost in accidents, both of which had been primarily caused by poor piloting decisions and errors leading to two ground collision incidents;&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, pp. 98, 127.&lt;/ref&gt; a third Tornado prototype was seriously damaged by an incident involving [[Pilot-induced oscillation|pilot-induced pitch oscillation]].&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, pp. 94–95, 98.&lt;/ref&gt; During the type's development, aircraft designers of the era were beginning to incorporate features such as more sophisticated stability augmentation systems and autopilots. Aircraft such as the Tornado and the [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon]] made use of these new technologies.&lt;ref&gt;Pratt 2000, pp. 10-11.&lt;/ref&gt; Failure testing of the Tornado's triplex [[analogue electronics|analogue]] command and stability augmentation system (CSAS) was conducted on a series of realistic flight control rigs; the variable-sweep wings in combination with varying, and frequently very heavy, payloads complicated the clearance process.&lt;ref&gt;Pratt 2000, pp. 199, 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Production===
[[File:F-15C Tornado IDS DFST8901717.JPEG|thumb|A USAF F-15C flanked by Luftwaffe and RAF Tornados in 1987]]

The contract for the Batch 1 aircraft was signed on 29 July 1976.&lt;ref name = 'Wellington'/&gt; The first aircraft were delivered to the RAF and [[German Air Force]] on 5 and 6 June 1979 respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Middleton, Drew. [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F40A14F93A5D11728DDDAA0A94D1405B898BF1D3 &quot;Military Analysis: West Germany Is Modernizing Military Forces.&quot;] ''The New York Times,'' 23 September 1979. Retrieved 23 September 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; The first Italian Tornado was delivered on 25 September 1981. On 29 January 1981, the Tri-national Tornado Training Establishment (TTTE) officially opened at [[RAF Cottesmore]], remaining active in training pilots from all operating nations until 31 March 1999.&lt;ref&gt;Parsons, Gary. [http://www.airsceneuk.org.uk/hangar/1999/ttte/ttte.htm &quot;TTTEnd of an era.&quot;] ''airsceneuk.org.uk''. Retrieved 19 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The 500th Tornado to be produced was delivered to West Germany on 19 December 1987.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor 1987, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;

Export customers were sought after West Germany withdrew its objections to exporting the aircraft; Saudi Arabia was the only export customer of the Tornado.&lt;ref&gt;Michael. &quot;Saudi Arabia considers Tornado fighter deal.&quot; ''Financial Times,'' 11 July 1984, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; The agreement to purchase the Tornado was part of the controversial [[Al-Yamamah arms deal]] between [[BAE Systems]] and the Saudi government.&lt;ref&gt;Hoon, Geoff. [http://www.theyworkforyou.com/wrans/?id=2004-05-25.171750.h &quot;Al Yamamah Contracts.&quot;] ''Hansard'', 25 May 2004. Retrieved 19 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hirst, C. [http://www.caat.org.uk/publications/countries/saudi-arabia.php &quot;The Arabian Connection: The UK Arms Trade to Saudi Arabia.&quot;] ''Financial Times'', 9 July 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; Oman had committed to purchasing Tornados and the equipment to operate them for a total value of £250&amp;nbsp;million in the late 1980s, but cancelled the order in 1990 due to financial difficulties.&lt;ref&gt;Allen and Rigsbee 2000, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1970s, Australia considered joining the MRCA programme to find a replacement for their ageing [[Dassault Mirage III]]s; ultimately the [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet]] was selected to meet the requirement.&lt;ref&gt;Ball 1979, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; Canada similarly opted for the F/A-18 after considering the Tornado.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1978/1978%20-%202197.html?search=panavia &quot;Tornado on Canadian fighter shortlist.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 1978. p. 1153.&lt;/ref&gt; Japan considered the Tornado in the 1980s, along with the [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon]] and F/A-18; before selecting the [[Mitsubishi F-2]], a domestically produced design based on the F-16.&lt;ref&gt;Lorell 1996, pp. 108, 121.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1990s, both [[Taiwan]] and [[South Korea]] expressed interest in acquiring a small number of Tornado ECR aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Martin 1996, p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harrison, Michael and Raymond Whitaker. [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/s-korea-lines-up-pounds-360m-tornado-order-bae-and-partners-would-benefit-from-new-arms-policy-less-dependent-on-us-1494402.html &quot;S Korea lines up pounds 360m Tornado order: BAe and partners would benefit from new arms policy less dependent on US.&quot;] ''The Independent,'' 28 June 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, [[EADS]] proposed a Tornado ECR variant with a greater [[electronic warfare]] capability for Australia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/australian-international-airshow-wild-weasel-air-defence-upgrade-offered-to-126343 &quot;Australian International Airshow&amp;nbsp;– Wild Weasel air defence upgrade offered to RAAF.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 20 February 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

Production came to an end in 1998; the last batch of aircraft being produced going to the Royal Saudi Air Force, who had ordered a total of 96 IDS Tornados.&lt;ref name=Janes_241/&gt; In June 2011, it was announced that the RAF's Tornado fleet had flown collectively over one million flying hours.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defenceiq.com/air-forces-and-military-aircraft/articles/royal-air-force-continues-libya-operations-in-face/ &quot;Royal Air Force Continues Libya Operations in Face of Force Structure Challenges.&quot;] ''defenceiq.com,'' 25 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bristol, Chris. [http://www.wattonandswaffhamtimes.co.uk/news/tornado_jets_that_fly_from_raf_marham_in_norfolk_clock_up_a_million_flying_hours_1_944231 &quot;Tornado jets that fly from RAF Marham in Norfolk clock up a million flying hours.&quot;] ''Watton and Swaffham Times,'' 27 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Aviation author John Lake noted that: &quot;The Trinational Panavia Consortium produced just short of 1,000 Tornados, making it one of the most successful postwar bomber programs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lake 2002, pp. 446, 455.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, ''AirForces Monthly'' said of the Tornado: &quot;For more than a quarter of a century... the most important military aircraft in Western Europe.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;afmimportance&quot;&gt;Martin, Guy. &quot;All The World's Tornados.&quot; ''AirForces Monthly,'' October 2008, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==

===Overview===
The Panavia Tornado is a multirole, twin-engined aircraft designed to excel at low-level penetration of enemy defences. The mission envisaged during the Cold War was the delivery of conventional and nuclear ordnance on the invading forces of the [[Warsaw Pact]] countries of Eastern Europe; this dictated several significant features of the design. Variable wing geometry, allowing for minimal drag during the critical low-level dash towards a well-prepared enemy, had been desired from the project's start. Advanced navigation and flight computers, including the then-innovative [[fly-by-wire]] system, greatly reduced the workload of the pilot during low-level flight and eased control of the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Scutts 2000, pp. 53–55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = 'Frédriksen 255'/&gt; For long range bombing missions, the Tornado has a retractable [[Aerial refueling#Probe-and-drogue|refuelling probe]].&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:US Navy 030617-N-4374S-016 A German fighter jet Panavia Tornado GR.Mk 1, flies over the Aegis class, guided missile cruiser USS Vella Gulf (CG 72) during the annual maritime exercise Baltic Operations 2003 (BALTOPS).jpg|thumb|left|Flyover of a German Navy Tornado during a training exercise in 2003]]

As a multirole aircraft, the Tornado is capable of undertaking more mission profiles than the anticipated strike mission; various operators replaced multiple aircraft types with the Tornado as a common type&amp;nbsp;– the use of dedicated single role aircraft for specialist purposes such as battlefield reconnaissance, maritime patrol duties, or dedicated electronic countermeasures (ECM) were phased out&amp;nbsp;– either by standard Tornados or modified variants, such as the Tornado ECR. The most extensive modification from the base Tornado design was the Tornado ADV, which was stretched and armed with long range anti-aircraft missiles to serve in the interceptor role.&lt;ref name ='eagles 88-91'/&gt;

The Tornado operators have chosen to undertake various life extension and upgrade programmes to keep their Tornado fleets as viable frontline aircraft for the foreseeable future. The RAF and RSAF have upgraded their Tornados to the GR4 standard to increase combat effectiveness, while German Tornados have been undergoing periodic upgrades under the multi-stage ASSTA (Avionics System Software Tornado in Ada) programme.&lt;ref name =BAE_GR4_up/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AIdec11 p74&quot;/&gt; With these upgrades, as of 2011, it is projected that the Tornado shall be in service until 2025, more than 50 years after the first prototype took flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIjun07 p29&quot;/&gt;

===Variable-sweep wing===
{{further information|variable-sweep wing}}
[[File:TornadoGR1 27Sqn RAF Mildenhall 1988.jpeg|thumb|A 27 Sqn RAF Tornado GR1 in flight; the wings are fully swept back]]

In order for the Tornado to perform well as a low-level supersonic strike aircraft, it was considered necessary for it to possess good high-speed and low-speed flight characteristics. To achieve high-speed performance, a [[swept wing|swept]] or [[delta wing|delta]] wing is typically adopted, but these wing designs are inefficient at low speeds. To operate at both high and low speeds with great effectiveness, the Tornado uses a variable-sweep wing.&lt;ref name = 'jerr53'/&gt; This approach had been adopted by earlier aircraft, such as the American [[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark]] strike fighter, and the Soviet [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-23]] fighter. The F-111 has many similarities with the smaller Tornado; however, the Tornado differs in being a multi-role aircraft with more advanced onboard systems and avionics.&lt;ref&gt;Spick, Green and Swanborough 2001, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

The level of [[wing sweep]], the angle of the wings in relation to the fuselage, can be altered in flight at the pilot's control. The variable wing can adopt any sweep angle between 25 degrees and 67 degrees, with a corresponding speed range for each angle; some Tornado ADVs were outfitted with an automatic wing-sweep system to reduce pilot workload.&lt;ref&gt;Aeroguide 21 1988, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; When the wings are swept back, the exposed [[wing loading|wing area]] is lowered and [[wave drag|drag]] is significantly decreased, which is conducive to performing high-speed low-level flight.&lt;ref name = 'jerr53'/&gt; The weapons pylons pivot with the angle of the variable-sweep wings so that the stores point in the direction of flight and do not hinder any wing positions.&lt;ref name = 'jerr54'&gt;Scutts 2000, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richardson 1986, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

In development, significant attention was given to the Tornado's short-field take-off and landing ([[STOL]]) performance. Germany, in particular, encouraged this design aspect.&lt;ref&gt;Lake 2002, p. 446.&lt;/ref&gt; For shorter take-off and landing distances, the Tornado can sweep its wings forwards to the 25-degree position, and deploy its full-span [[Flap (aircraft)|flaps]] and [[leading edge slats]] to allow the aircraft to fly at slower speeds.&lt;ref&gt;Aeroguide 21 1988, pp. 2, 8.&lt;/ref&gt; These features, in combination with the [[thrust reverser]]-equipped engines, give the Tornado excellent low-speed handling and landing characteristics.&lt;ref&gt;Aeroguide 21 1988, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Avionics===
[[File:Tornado GR.4 Forward Cockpit.jpg|thumb|upright|Forward cockpit of an RAF Tornado GR.4]]
[[File:Tornado GR.4 Aft Cockpit.jpg|thumb|Aft cockpit of an RAF Tornado GR.4]]

The Tornado features a [[tandem-seat]] cockpit, crewed by a pilot and a [[navigator|navigator/weapons officer]]; both [[electromechanical]] and [[electro-optical]] controls are used to fly the aircraft and manage its systems.&lt;ref&gt;Jukes 2004, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; An array of dials and switches are mounted on either side of a centrally placed [[Cathode Ray Tube|CRT monitor]], controlling the navigational, communications, and weapons-control computers.&lt;ref&gt;Jarrett 2005, pp. 3–4.&lt;/ref&gt; BAE Systems developed the Tornado Advanced Radar Display Information System (TARDIS), a {{convert|12.8|in|cm|sigfig=3|adj=on|disp=flip}} [[multi-function display]], to replace the rear cockpit's Combined Radar and Projected Map Display; the RAF began installing TARDIS on the GR4 fleet in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://baesystems.com/Newsroom/NewsReleases/2004/press_09022004.html &quot;BAE SYSTEMS Receives $70 Million Contract For Radar Map Display Subsystem On U.K. Tornado Aircraft.&quot;] ''BAE Systems,'' 9 February 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

The primary flight controls of the Tornado are a [[fly-by-wire]] hybrid, consisting of an analogue [[wikt:quadruplex|quadruplex]] Command and Stability Augmentation System (CSAS) connected to a digital Autopilot &amp; Flight Director System (AFDS);&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, pp. 2, 23.&lt;/ref&gt; in addition a level of mechanical reversion capacity was retained to safeguard against potential failure.&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, pp. 2, 22.&lt;/ref&gt; To enhance pilot awareness, [[Aircraft flight control system#Artificial feel devices|artificial feel]] was built into the flight controls, such as the centrally located [[Joystick#Aviation|stick]]; because of the Tornado's variable wings enabling the aircraft to drastically alter its flight envelope, the artificial responses adjust automatically to wing profile changes and other changes to flight attitude.&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; As a large variety of munitions and stores can be outfitted, the resulting changes to the aircraft's flight dynamics are routinely compensated for by the flight stability system.&lt;ref&gt;Pratt 2000, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Luftwaffe GR-4 Tornado undergoing maintenance during Cooperative Cope Thunder 2004.JPEG|thumb|left|A German Air Force Tornado undergoing maintenance in July 2004]]

The Tornado incorporates a combined navigation/attack [[Doppler radar|Doppler]] radar that simultaneously scans for targets and conducts fully automated [[terrain following radar|terrain-following]] for low-level flight operations; being readily able to conduct all-weather hands-off low-level flight was considered one of the core advantages of the Tornado.&lt;ref&gt;Ministry of Defence 2006, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; The Tornado ADV has a different radar system to other variants, designated [[AI.24 Foxhunter]], as it is designed for [[air defence]] operations; it is capable of continuously keeping track of up to 20 targets at ranges of up to {{convert|100|mi|km|sigfig=2|disp=flip}}.&lt;ref name = 'Frédriksen 255'/&gt; The Tornado was one of the earliest aircraft to fitted with a [[Bus (computing)|digital data bus]] for data transmission. A link 16 JTIDS integration on the F3 variant enabled the exchange of radar and other sensory information with nearby friendly aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, pp. 447–448.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Tornado variants carry different avionics and equipment, depending on their mission. The Tornado ECR is devoted to [[Suppression of Enemy Air Defences]] (SEAD) missions, operated by Germany and Italy. The Tornado ECR is equipped with an emitter-locator system (ELS) to spot radar use.&lt;ref name =janes_237&gt;Jackson et al. 1998, p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt; German ECRs have a [[Honeywell]] infrared imaging system for reconnaissance flights.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson et al. 1998, pp. 240–241.&lt;/ref&gt; RAF and RSAF Tornados have the [[Laser]] Range Finder and Marked Target Seekers (LRMTS) for targeting [[laser-guided]] munitions.&lt;ref&gt;Whitaker, Richard. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1981/1981%20-%202686.html &quot;Ferranti Mission Managers.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 15 August 1981, p. 506.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1991, the RAF introduced TIALD, allowing Tornado GR1s to [[target designation|laser-designate]] their own targets.&lt;ref&gt;Richardson 1991, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;

The GR1A and GR4A were equipped with TIRRS (Tornado Infrared Reconnaissance System), consisting of one SLIR (Sideways Looking Infra Red) sensor on each side of the fuselage forward of the engine intakes to capture oblique images, and a single IRLS ([[infrared linescan|InfrarRed LineScan]]) sensor mounted on the fuselage's underside to provide vertical images.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.janes.com/articles/Janes-Avionics/Tornado-Infra-Red-Reconnaissance-System-TIRRS-United-Kingdom.html &quot;Tornado Infra-Red Reconnaissance System (TIRRS) (United Kingdom), Airborne electro-optic (EO) systems.&quot;] ''Jane's Avionics,'' 23 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; TIRRS recorded images on six [[S-VHS]] [[video tape]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans p97-9&quot;&gt;Evans 1999, pp. 97–99.&lt;/ref&gt; The newer [[RAPTOR]] reconnaissance pod has replaced the built-in TIRRS system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/raptor.cfm RAPTOR]. ''Royal Air Force,'' Retrieved: 29 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.janes.com/articles/International-Defence-Review-97/UK-UPGRADES-AIRBORNE-RECONNAISSANCE.html &quot;UK Upgrades Airborne Reconnaissance.&quot;] ''Jane's International Defence Review,'' 1 June 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armament and equipment===
The Tornado is cleared to carry the majority of air-launched weapons in the [[NATO]] inventory, including various [[Gravity bomb|unguided]] and [[laser-guided bomb]]s, [[anti-ship missile|anti-ship]] and [[anti-radiation missile]]s, as well as specialised weapons such as [[anti-personnel mine]]s and [[anti-runway]] munitions.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans pp66-8&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Corde_298&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=granby_raf/&gt; To improve survivability in combat, the Tornado is equipped with onboard countermeasures, ranging from [[flare (countermeasure)|flare]] and [[chaff]] dispensers to electronic countermeasure pods that can be mounted under the wings.&lt;ref name =RAFGR4/&gt; Underwing fuel tanks and a [[Aerial refueling#Buddy store|buddy store]] [[aerial refuelling]] system that allows one Tornado to refuel another are available to extend the aircraft's range.&lt;ref name=lame&gt;Laming 1996, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Tornado ECR JaBoG 32 1997.JPEG|thumb|German Air Force Tornado ECR, queuing to be refuelled by a [[USAF]] [[Boeing KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135 Stratotanker]], in September 1997]]

In the decades since the Tornado's introduction, all of the Tornado operators have undertaken various upgrade and modification programmes to allow recently introduced weapons to be used by their squadrons. Amongst the new armaments that the Tornado has been adapted to deploy are the enhanced [[Paveway]] and [[Joint Direct Attack Munition]] bombs, and modern [[cruise missiles]] such as the [[KEPD 350|Taurus]] and [[Storm Shadow (missile)|Storm Shadow]] missiles; these upgrades have increased the Tornado's capabilities and combat accuracy.&lt;ref name=Corde_298&gt;Cordesman 2003, p. 298.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fi_assta2/&gt;&lt;ref name =defpro_jdam/&gt; Precision weapons such as cruise missiles have replaced older munitions such as [[cluster bomb]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Norton-Taylor, Richard. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2009/sep/26/brimstone-missile-video-afghanistan-raf &quot;RAF unveils Brimstone precision strike missile.&quot;] ''The Guardian,'' 26 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Strike variants have a limited air-to-air capability with [[AIM-9 Sidewinder]] or [[AIM-132 ASRAAM]] [[air-to-air missile]]s (AAMs); additionally the Tornado ADV is outfitted with [[beyond visual range]] AAMs such as the [[Skyflash]] and [[AIM-120 AMRAAM]] missiles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_6712/is_26_217/ai_n28996410/ &quot;Britain Deploying ASRAAM-Equipped Tornado Fighters To Middle East.&quot;] ''Defense Daily,'' 10 February 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1986/1986%20-%200336.html &quot;World Missile Forces.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 8 February 1986, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; The Tornado is armed with two {{convert|27|mm|abbr=on|3}} [[Mauser BK-27]] [[revolver cannon]] internally mounted underneath the fuselage; the Tornado ADV was only armed with one cannon.&lt;ref name ='eagles 88-91'/&gt; When the RAF GR1 aircraft were converted to GR4, the FLIR sensor replaced the left hand cannon, leaving only one;&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAp08 p25&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' April 2008, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; the GR1A reconnaissance variant gave up both its guns to make space for the sideways looking infra-red sensors.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans p98-9&quot;/&gt; The Mauser BK-27 was developed specifically for the Tornado, but has since been used on several other European fighters, such as the [[Dassault/Dornier Alpha Jet]], [[Saab JAS 39 Gripen]], and Eurofighter Typhoon.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAH&quot;&gt;[http://articles.janes.com/articles/Janes-Ammunition-Handbook/27-x-145-B-ammunition-Switzerland.html &quot;27 x 145 B ammunition (Switzerland), Cannon&amp;nbsp;– 20 to 30 mm cannon.&quot;] [[Jane's Information Group]], 27 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Tornado is capable of delivering air-launched [[nuclear weapon]]s. In 1979, Britain considered replacing its [[UGM-27 Polaris|Polaris]] submarines with either the [[Trident missile|Trident]] submarines or alternatively the Tornado as the main bearer of its [[nuclear deterrent]].&lt;ref&gt;Middleton, Drew. [https://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id=RMoTAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=E-IDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3301,6796683&amp;dq=tornado+bomber&amp;hl=en &quot;Europe worried about nuclear defence arsena.&quot;] ''Eugene Register-Guard,'' 11 October 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the UK proceeded with Trident, several Tornado squadrons based in Germany were assigned to [[SACEUR]] to deter a major Soviet offensive with both conventional and nuclear weapons, namely the [[WE.177]] nuclear bomb, which was retired in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;Burnell, Brian. [http://nuclear-weapons.info/images/1984.PNG &quot;Weapon detail and No.15 Squadron data for 1984.&quot;] ''nuclear-weapons.info''. Retrieved 19 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;strategicdefencereview&quot;&gt;[http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/65F3D7AC-4340-4119-93A2-20825848E50E/0/sdr1998_complete.pdf &quot;Strategic Defence Review 1998: Full Report.&quot;] ''Ministry of Defence,'' 1998, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; German and Italian Tornados are capable of delivering US [[B61 nuclear bomb]]s, which are made available through NATO.&lt;ref&gt;Chalmers, Malcolm [http://www.rusi.org/analysis/commentary/ref:C4B9A677D2E3B6/ &quot;Not with a bang but a whimper: Europe’s pending denuclearisation.&quot;] ''rusi.org.'' 8 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Engine===
{{main article|Turbo-Union RB199}}

Britain considered the selection of [[Rolls-Royce plc|Rolls-Royce]] to develop the advanced engine for the MRCA to be essential, and was strongly opposed to adopting an engine from an American manufacturer, to the point where the UK might have withdrawn over the issue.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, pp. 26, 50.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1969, Rolls-Royce's [[Turbo-Union RB199|RB 199]] engine was selected to power the MRCA. One advantage over the US competition was that a [[technology transfer]] between the partner nations had been agreed; the engine was to be developed and manufactured by a joint company, [[Turbo-Union]].&lt;ref name = 'jef 50'&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; The programme was delayed by Rolls-Royce's entry into receivership in 1971; the nature of the multinational collaboration process helped avoid major disruption of the Tornado programme.&lt;ref name = 'jef 51'&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; Research from the [[supersonic airliner]] [[Concorde]] contributed to the development and final design of the RB.199 and of the engine control units.&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, pp. 65–66.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RB199 Cosford.JPG|thumb|left|RB199 on static display at the [[Royal Air Force Museum Cosford]]]]

To provide the desired performance, several features were used in the RB.199. To operate efficiently across a wide range of conditions and speeds up to Mach 2, the RB.199 and several other engines make use of [[intake ramp|variable intake ramp]]s to control the air flow.&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; The hydraulic system is pressurised by syphoning power from both or either operational engine; the hydraulics are completely contained within the airframe rather than integrating with the engine to improve safety and maintainability.&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt; In case of double-engine, or double-generator, failure, the Tornado has a single-use battery capable of operating the fuel pump and hydraulics for up to 13 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;Moir and Seabridge 2011, p. 306.&lt;/ref&gt;

Relatively rare amongst fighter aircraft, the RB.199 is fitted with [[thrust reverser]]s to decrease the distance required to safely land.&lt;ref name = 'Frédriksen 255'/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.turbounion.co.uk/index.php?page=technology.html &quot;Turbo-Union: Engine Description.&quot;] ''turbounion.co.uk.'' Retrieved: 29 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; To fully deploy the thrust reverser during landings, the [[yaw damper]] is connected to the steering of the nosewheel to provide greater stability.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1974, the first RB.199 powered flight of a prototype Tornado occurred; the engine completed its qualification tests in late 1978.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.turbounion.co.uk/index.php?page=programme.html &quot;Turbo-Union: Programme Milestones Achieved.&quot;] ''turbounion.co.uk,'' Retrieved: 29 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The final production standard engine met both reliability and performance standards, though the development cost had been higher than predicted, in part due to the ambitious performance requirements.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, pp. 54–55.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the Tornado's introduction to service, the [[turbine blades]] of the engine suffered from a shorter life span than desired, which was rectified by the implementation of design revisions upon early-production engines.&lt;ref name = 'jef 54'&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; Several uprated engines were developed and used on both the majority of Tornado ADVs and Germany's Tornado ECRs.&lt;ref name = 'jef 55'&gt;Jefford et al. 2002, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = 'turbounion'/&gt; The DECU (''Digital Engine Control Unit'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diehl.com/de/diehl-aerosystems/aircraft-systems/flight-engine-control.html |title=Diehl Aerosystems - Flight Engine Control |publisher=Diehl |accessdate=2015-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the current engine control unit for RB 199 engines superseding the analogue MECU (''Main Engine Control Unit'') also known as CUE.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://maa.tools.mod.uk/linkedfiles/regulation/Formats/750%28HR7%29%28Tornado%29_enabled.pdf |title= RB 199 Performance Data: Mk 103 |publisher=Ministry of Defence |accessdate=2015-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
[[File:RAF Tornado GR4 MOD 45155235.jpg|thumb|GR4 of [[No. 9 Squadron RAF]] shows off a payload including Paveway, Brimstone and Litening pod]]

===Upgrades===
Being designed for low-level operations, the Tornado required modification to perform in medium level operations that the RAF adopted in the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;Tornado GR4: An Overview ''AirForces Monthly'' March 2002 pp. 26–27&lt;/ref&gt; The RAF's GR1 fleet was extensively re-manufactured as {{Anchor|Tornado GR4|GR4}}Tornado GR4s. Upgrades on Tornado GR4s included a [[Forward looking infrared]], a wide-angle HUD ([[Head-up display]]), improved [[cockpit]] displays, NVG ([[Night vision device]]s) capabilities, new [[avionics]], and a [[Global Positioning System]] receiver. The upgrade eased the integration of new weapons and sensors which were purchased in parallel, including the [[Storm Shadow]] [[cruise missile]], the [[Brimstone missile|Brimstone]] anti-tank missile, [[GBU-24 Paveway III|Paveway III]] laser-guided bombs and the [[RAPTOR]] reconnaissance pod was integrated.&lt;ref name =BAE_GR4_up&gt;[http://www.baesystems.com/Newsroom/NewsReleases/2001/press_17102001.html &quot;BAE SYSTEMS delivers 100th mid-life upgrade Tornado GR4.&quot;] ''BAE Systems,'' 17 October 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =RAFGR4&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/tornado.cfm &quot;Tornado GR4/GR4A.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force.'' Retrieved: 29 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ30 p119-0&quot;&gt;Lake ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 30, pp. 119–120.&lt;/ref&gt; The first flight of a Tornado GR4 was on 4 April 1997, on 31 October 1997 the RAF accepted the first delivery and deliveries were completed in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/tornado-forecast-30563/ &quot;Tornado forecast.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 10 December 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, the RSAF opted to have their Tornado IDSs undergo a series of upgrades to become equivalent to the RAF's GR4 configuration.&lt;ref name ='saudi upgrade'/&gt; On 21 December 2007 BAE signed a £210m contract for CUSP, the Capability Upgrade Strategy (Pilot).&lt;ref name=Hoyle20080109&gt;{{cite web | url=http://flightglobal.com/news/articles/bae-systems-gets-163210-million-contract-to-upgrade-uk-tornado-220726/ | title=BAE Systems gets £210 million contract to upgrade UK Tornado GR4s | first= Craig | last= Hoyle | publisher=Flight Global | date=9 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This project would see RAF GR4/4A improved in two phases, starting with the integration of the Paveway IV bomb and a communications upgrade, followed by a new tactical datalink in Phase B.&lt;ref name=Hoyle20080109 /&gt;

Beginning in 2000, German IDS and ECR Tornados received the ASSTA 1 (Avionics System Software Tornado in Ada) upgrade. ASSTA 1 involved a replacement weapons computer, new [[Global Positioning System|GPS]] and [[Inertial navigation system|Laser Inertial]] navigation systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sabatini|first=Roberto|author2=Richardson, Mark|title=New techniques for laser beam atmospheric extinction measurements from manned and unmanned aerospace vehicles|journal=Central European Journal of Engineering|date=12 September 2012|volume=3|issue=1|pages=11–35|doi=10.2478/s13531-012-0033-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new computer allowed the integration of the [[AGM-88 HARM|HARM III, HARM 0 Block IV/V]] and [[KEPD 350|TAURUS KEPD 350]] missiles, the [[LITENING|Rafael Litening II Laser Designator Pod]] and [[GBU-24 Paveway III]] laser-guided bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIdec11 p72-74&quot;&gt;Rachow ''Air International'' December 2011, pp. 72–74.&lt;/ref&gt; The ASSTA 2 upgrade began in 2005, primarily consisting of several new digital avionics systems, a new ECM suite and provision for the [[KEPD 350|Taurus cruise missile]]; these upgrades are to be only applied to 85 Tornados (20 ECRs and 65 IDSs), as the Tornado is in the process of being replaced by the [[Eurofighter Typhoon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AIdec11 p74&quot;&gt;Rachow ''Air International'' December 2011, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fi_assta2&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/german-air-force-starts-tests-with-upgraded-tornado-340632/ &quot;German air force starts tests with upgraded Tornado.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 14 April 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The ASSTA 3 upgrade programme, started in 2008, will introduce support for the laser-targeted [[Joint Direct Attack Munition]] along with further software changes.&lt;ref name =defpro_jdam&gt;[http://www.defpro.com/news/details/11683/ &quot;German Air Force Tornado aircraft get more punch for air-to-surface missions.&quot;] ''defpro.com,'' 3 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2016 the Bild newspaper revealed that the newsest upgrade of the ASSTA suite to version 3.1, which includes color multifunctional LCD screens in place of monochrome CRT displays, is interferring with helmet-mounted nigh-vision optical displays worn by pilots, rendering German Tornado bombers deployed to Syria useless for night missions.&lt;ref&gt;[https://tacairnet.com/2016/01/19/software-issues-ground-luftwaffe-tornadoes-at-night-in-the-fight-against-daesh/ Software Issues Ground Luftwaffe Tornadoes at Night in the Fight Against Daesh]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bild.de/politik/inland/bundeswehr/tornados-duerfen-nachts-nicht-gegen-isis-fliegen-44202376.bild.html&lt;/ref&gt; The defense ministry admitted that bright cockpit lights could be a distraction for pilots, and disclosed that the solution will be implemented in a few weeks, but denied the need to fly night missions in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dw.com/en/report-german-jets-useless-at-night/a-18988883 Deutsche Welle - Report: German jets useless at night]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Test platform for 3-D printed parts====
[[BAE Systems]] announced that, in December 2013, the company had test flown a Tornado equipped with parts that were made with [[3D printing]] equipment. The parts included a protective cover for the radio, a landing-gear guard and air-intake door support struts. The test demonstrated the feasibility of making replacement parts quickly and cheaply at the air base hosting the Tornado.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=3D-printed components flown in British fighter jet|url=http://news.yahoo.com/3d-printed-components-flown-british-fighter-jet-034848681.html|date=5 January 2014|publisher=Yahoo! News}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company claims that, with some of the parts costing less than £100 per piece to manufacture, 3D printing has already resulted in savings of more than £300,000 and will offer further potential cost savings of more than £1.2&amp;nbsp;million between now and 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pocket-lint.com/news/126185-printing-planes-bae-systems-now-using-3d-printed-parts-in-fighter-jets |title=Printing planes: BAE Systems now using 3D printed parts in fighter jets |author=Stuart Miles |publisher=pocket-lint.com |date=5 January 2014 |accessdate=5 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==

===German Air Force (Luftwaffe)===
[[File:German Panavia Tornado.JPG|thumb|A German Air Force Tornado IDS flying above [[Nevada]], US, in August 2007]]

The first Tornado prototype made its first flight on 14 August 1974 from [[Manching]] airbase, in what was then [[West Germany]].&lt;ref name=j75&gt;Taylor 1975–1976, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; Deliveries of production Tornados began on 27 July 1979. The total number of Tornados delivered to the [[German Air Force]] numbered 247, including 35 ECR variants.&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ32 p128&quot;&gt;Lake ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 32, p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt; Originally Tornados equipped five fighter-bomber wings (''[[Geschwader]]''), with one tactical conversion unit and four front line wings, replacing the Lockheed F-104 Starfighter.&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ32 p128,1&quot;&gt;Lake ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 32, pp. 128, 130.&lt;/ref&gt; When one of the two Tornado wings of the German Navy was disbanded in 1994, its aircraft were used to re-equip a Luftwaffe's reconnaissance wing formerly equipped with [[McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II|RF-4E Phantom]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ32 p129&quot;&gt;Lake ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 32, p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt;

As many as 15 German Tornados undertook combat operations as a part of [[NATO]]'s campaign during the [[Bosnian War]]; this was the first combat operation for the Luftwaffe since World War II.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen, Roger. [http://www.nytimes.com/1999/03/26/world/conflict-balkans-germany-half-century-after-hitler-german-jets-join-attack.html &quot;Conflict in the Balkans: Half a Century After Hitler, German Jets Join the Attack.&quot;] ''New York Times,'' 26 March 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; The Tornados, operating from in [[Piacenza]], Italy, flew reconnaissance missions to survey damage inflicted by previous strikes and to scout targets for other aircraft to strike.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;German Warplanes Risk Combat for the First Times since WWII.&quot; ''St. Louis Post,'' 2 September 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; These reconnaissance missions were reportedly responsible for a significant improvement in target selection throughout the campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Geiss and Berndt 2010, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, German and Italian Tornados participated in [[1999 NATO bombing of Yugoslavia|Operation Allied Force]], NATO's military operation against the [[Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] during the [[Kosovo War]]. The ECR aircraft would escort various allies' aircraft while carrying several [[AGM-88 HARM]] missiles to counter attempted use of radar against the allied aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Lambeth 2001, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; During the Kosovo hostilities, Germany's IDS Tornados would routinely conduct reconnaissance flights to identify both enemy ground forces and civilian refugees within Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Peters 2001, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Geiss and Berndt 2010, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Panavia Tornado Luftwaffe.jpg|thumb|left|A Luftwaffe Tornado of Jagdbombergeschwader 31 taking off from [[Eielson Air Force Base]], [[Alaska]], in 2004]]

In June 2007, a pair of Luftwaffe Tornado were controversially used to fly reconnaissance flights over an [[anti-globalisation]] demonstration during the [[33rd G8 summit]] in [[Heiligendamm]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upi.com/Business_News/Security-Industry/2007/06/12/German-war-jets-against-anti-G8-protesters/UPI-13951181675274/ &quot;German war jets against anti-G8 protesters.&quot;] ''United Press International,'' 12 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bode, Emma. [http://www.wsws.org/articles/2007/jul2007/germ-j31.shtml &quot;German army and air force deployed against G8 summit demonstrators.&quot;] ''World Socialist Web Site,'' 31 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the mission, the German Defence Ministry admitted one aircraft had broken the minimum flying altitude and that mistakes were made in the handling of security of the summit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upi.com/Business_News/Security-Industry/2007/06/21/Berlin-admits-security-mistakes-at-G8/UPI-37391182449280/ &quot;Berlin admits security mistakes at G8.&quot;] ''United Press International,'' 21 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, a detachment of six Tornados of the [[Aufklärungsgeschwader 51|Aufklärungsgeschwader 51 &quot;Immelmann&quot;]] (51st reconnaissance wing) were deployed to [[Mazar-i-Sharif]], Northern Afghanistan, to support NATO forces.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nato.int/isaf/docu/pressreleases/2007/04-april/pr070406-270.html &quot;German ‘Tornado’ aircraft deploy to Mazar-e Sharif.&quot;] ''NATO ISAF Press Release'', #2007-270. Retrieved 1 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The decision to send Tornados to Afghanistan was a controversial decision, including one political party launching an unsuccessful legal bid to block the deployment as unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,472696,00.html &quot;Letter from Berlin: Afghanistan Divides Germany's Social Democrats.&quot;] ''Spiegel Online,'' 20 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matussek, Karin. [http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&amp;sid=aVqR2oCLfNgk&amp;refer=germany &quot;German Court Rejects Bid to Halt Tornado Mission.&quot;] ''Bloomberg,'' 3 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In support of the Afghanistan mission, improvements in the Tornado's reconnaissance equipment were accelerated; improving the Tornado's ability to detect hidden [[improvised explosive device]]s (IEDs).&lt;ref&gt;Geiss and Berndt 2010, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; The German Tornados were withdrawn from Afghanistan in November 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defencetalk.com/germany-to-withdraw-tornado-jets-from-afghanistan-28987/ &quot;Germany to Withdraw Tornado Jets from Afghanistan.&quot;] ''defencetalk.com'', 28 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Defence cuts announced in March 2003 resulted in the decision to retire 90 Tornados from Luftwaffe service. This led to a reduction in its Tornado strength to four wings by September 2005.&lt;ref&gt;Ripley ''Flight International'' 25 November&amp;nbsp;– 1 December 2003, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AImay06 p51&quot;&gt;List ''Air International'' May 2006, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 January 2004, the then German [[Federal Minister of Defence (Germany)|Defence Minister]] [[Peter Struck]] announced further major changes to the German armed forces. A major part of this announcement is the plan to cut the German fighter fleet from 426 in early 2004 to 265 by 2015.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Germany Announces Major Armed Forces Cuts.&quot; ''AirForces Monthly,'' March 2004, p. 8. Retrieved 19 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The German Tornado force is to be reduced to 85, with the type expected to remain in service with the Luftwaffe until 2020.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIdec11 p74&quot;/&gt; The aircraft being retained have been undergoing a service life extension programme.&lt;ref&gt;Geiss and Berndt 2010, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, the Luftwaffe operates Tornados with Tactical Wings [[Taktisches Luftwaffengeschwader 33]] in Cochem / Büchel, [[Rhineland-Palatinate]] and with [[Taktisches Luftwaffengeschwader 51]] &quot;Immelmann&quot; in Jagel, [[Schleswig-Holstein]]. Aircrew training takes place at Fliegerisches Ausbildungszentrum der Luftwaffe, based on [[Holloman Air Force Base]] in New Mexico, US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.luftwaffe.de/portal/a/luftwaffe/!ut/p/c4/04_SB8K8xLLM9MSSzPy8xBz9CP3I5EyrpHK9nHK9_KJ0_YJsR0UAGi_vxQ!!/ |title=Team Luftwaffe |publisher= Bundesministerium der Verteidigung |date=2014-03-04 |accessdate=2015-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===German Navy (Marineflieger)===
[[File:Tornado MFG1 landing RAF Mildenhall 1984.JPEG|thumb|A German Navy Tornado landing at [[RAF Mildenhall]] in 1984]]

In addition to the order made by the ''Luftwaffe'', the [[German Navy]]'s ''[[Marineflieger]]'' also received 112 of the IDS variant in the anti-shipping and marine reconnaissance roles, again replacing the Starfighter. These equipped two wings, each with a nominal strength of 48 aircraft. The principal anti-ship weapon was the [[AS.34 Kormoran]] [[anti-ship missile]], which were initially supplemented by unguided bombs and [[BL755]] [[cluster munition]]s, and later by [[AGM-88 HARM]] [[anti-radar missile]]s. Pods fitted with panoramic optical cameras and an infrared line scan were carried for the reconnaissance mission.&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ32 p132&quot;&gt;Lake ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 32, p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;

The end of the [[Cold War]] and the signing of the [[Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe|CFE Treaty]] gave rise to a requirement for Germany to reduce the size of its armed forces, including the number of combat aircraft. To meet this need, one of the ''Marineflieger'''s Tornado wings was disbanded on 1 January 1994; its aircraft replaced the Phantoms of a Luftwaffe reconnaissance wing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans p94&quot;&gt;Evans 1994, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ32 p129,2&quot;&gt;Lake ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 32, pp. 129, 132.&lt;/ref&gt; The second wing was enlarged and continued in the anti-shipping, reconnaissance and anti-radar roles until it was disbanded in 2005 with its aircraft and duties passed on to the Luftwaffe.&lt;ref&gt;Wertheim 2007, p. 242.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italian Air Force (Aeronautica Militare)===
The first Italian prototype made its maiden flight on 5 December 1975 from [[Turin]], Italy. The Aeronautica Militare received a total of 100 Tornado IDS. 16 IDSs were subsequently converted to the ECR configuration; the first Italian Tornado ECR was delivered on 27 February 1998.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;First Tornado IT-ECR for 50° Stormo.&quot; ''AirForces Monthly,'' June 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; As a stop-gap measure for 10 years, the Aeronautica Militare additionally operated 24 [[Panavia Tornado ADV|Tornado ADVs]] in the air defence role, which were leased from the RAF to cover the service gap between the retirement of the Lockheed F-104 Starfighter and the introduction of the Eurofighter Typhoon.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFM&quot;&gt;Sacchetti, Renzo. &quot;Italy's British Tornados.&quot; ''[[AirForces Monthly]]'', Key Publishing, October 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{multiple image
 |direction = vertical
 |align = left
 |width     = 220
 |image1    = Italian Tornado Flight.JPEG
 |caption1  = Two Italian Tornados participating in [[NATO]] exercise Dragon Hammer, in 1987
 |image2    = Italian air force Tornado 1991.jpg
 |caption2  = An Italian Air Force Tornado IDS at the 1991 [[Paris Air Show]]
&lt;!-- Please do not add more images here as it disrupts the spacing --&gt;
}}
In 2000, with major delays hampering the Eurofighter, the Aeronautica Militare began a search for another interim fighter. While the Tornado itself was considered, any long term extension to the lease would have involved upgrade to RAF CSP standard and thus was not considered cost effective. In February 2001, Italy announced its arrangement to lease 35 [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16s]] from the United States.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Italy to lease 35 F-16 jets from USA until Eurofighter operational&quot;. ''ANSA News Agency,'' 1 February 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; The Aeronautica Militare returned its Tornado ADVs to the RAF, with the final aircraft arriving at RAF Saint Athan on 7 December 2004. One aircraft was retained for static display purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Final AMI Tornados F3s Returned |work=AirForces Monthly |page=9 |publisher=Key Publishing |date = February 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Italian Tornados, along with RAF Tornados, took part in the first [[Gulf War]] in 1991. Operation Locusta saw eight Tornado IDS interdictors deployed from [[Gioia del Colle]], Italy, to [[Al Dhafra]], [[Abu Dhabi]], as a part of Italy's contribution to the coalition.&lt;ref&gt;Donald and Chant 2001, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; During the conflict, one aircraft was lost to Iraqi anti-aircraft fire, the pilots ejected safely and were captured by Iraqi forces.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/61015085.html?dids=61015085:61015085&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Jan+20%2C+1991&amp;author=&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=Italy+Sends+Plane+to+Replace+Lost+Jet&amp;pqatl=google &quot;Italy Sends Plane to Replace Lost Jet.&quot;] ''Los Angeles Times'', 20 January 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

A total of 22 Italian Tornados were deployed in the NATO-organised [[Operation Allied Force]] over Kosovo in 1999, the IDS variant was used in the bombing role while the ECR variants patrolled the combat region, acting to suppress enemy anti-aircraft radars,&lt;ref&gt;Peters 2001, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; firing 115 AGM-88 HARM missiles.&lt;ref name=&quot;corriere&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archiviostorico.corriere.it/1999/giugno/12/Arpino_usati_115_missili_Ognuno_co_0_9906123448.shtml|title=Arpino: usati 115 missili Ognuno costa 900 milioni|publisher=archiviostorico.corriere.it|accessdate=26 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to anticipated violence during the [[Afghan parliamentary election, 2010|2010 Afghanistan election]]s, Italy, along with several other nations, increased its military commitment in Afghanistan, dispatching four IDS Tornados to the region.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.rian.ru/world/20090220/120241184.html &quot;Italy plans to send more troops to Afghanistan during elections.&quot;] ''RIA Novosti,'' 20 February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Italian Tornado IDS and ECR aircraft participated in the enforcement of a UN no-fly zone during the [[2011 military intervention in Libya]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/story/2011/04/27/libya-apr27.html &quot;NATO Rejects Gadhafi's Call for Cease-Fire.&quot;] ''CBC News,'' 30 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Various coalition aircraft operated from bases in Italy, including RAF Tornados.&lt;ref&gt;Coughlin, Con. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/columnists/concoughlin/8545476/Libya-On-a-wing-and-a-prayer.html &quot;Libya: On a wing and a prayer.&quot;] ''The Telegraph,'' 29 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Italian military aircraft delivered a combined 710 guided bombs and missiles during the strikes against Libyan targets. Of these Aeronautica Militare Tornados and AMX fighter-bombers released 550 guided bombs and missiles, and Italian Navy AV-8Bs delivered 160 guided bombs. Italian Tornados launched 20 to 30 [[Storm Shadow (missile)|Storm Shadow]] cruise missiles with the rest consisting of Paveway and JDAM guided bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;defensenews&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=8567271|title=Unknown|publisher=defensenews.com|accessdate=26 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2002, Italy signed a contract with the Tornado Management Agency (NETMA) and Panavia for the upgrading of 18 IDSs, the first of which was received in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;First Italian MLU Tornado.&quot; ''AirForces Monthly,'' February 2004, p. 7. Retrieved 19 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The upgrade introduced improved navigation systems (integrated GPS and laser INS) and the ability to carry new weapons, including the Storm Shadow cruise missile, Joint Direct Attack Munition and Paveway III laser-guided bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIjun07 p27&quot;&gt;Niccoli ''Air International'' June 2007, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;

Italy has opted to extend the Tornado's service life at the expense of alternative ground-attack aircraft such as the [[AMX International AMX]]; in 2010 a major upgrade and life extension program was initiated, which will provide new digital displays, [[Link 16]] communications capability, night-vision goggles compatibility, and several other upgrades.&lt;ref&gt;Nativi, Andy. [http://www.aviationweek.com/aw/generic/story.jsp?topicName=Check6&amp;id=news/awst/2010/09/20/AW_09_20_2010_p74-253057.xml&amp;headline=Italian%20Upgrades%20To%20Extend%20Tornado's%20Life&amp;channel=&amp;from=topicalreports &quot;Italian Upgrades To Extend Tornado's Life.&quot;] ''Aviation Week,'' 20 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In the long term, it is planned to replace the Tornado IDS/ECR fleet in Italian service with the [[Lockheed Martin F-35 Lightning II]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;First Upgraded Italian Tornado on show.&quot; ''AirForces Monthly,'' September 2004, p. 18. Retrieved 19 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; with the final Italian Tornado scheduled to be phased out in 2025.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIjun07 p29&quot;&gt;Niccoli ''Air International'' June 2007, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 November 2014, Italy announced it was sending four Tornado aircraft with 135 support staff to [[Ahmed Al Jaber Air Base]] in Kuwait in participation of [[2014 military intervention against the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|coalition operations against the Islamic State]].  The four aircraft will be used for reconnaissance missions only.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defensenews.com/article/20141114/DEFREG04/311140035/Italy-Send-4-Tornados-Recon-Iraq Italy To Send 4 Tornados for Recon in Iraq] - Defensenews.com, 14 November 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Air Force===
[[File:TornadoGR1 XVSqn RAF 1987.jpeg|thumb|A Tornado GR1 of XV Sqn RAF at [[Wright-Patterson Air Force Base]] in 1987]]

Nicknamed the &quot;Tonka&quot; by the British,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.flightglobal.com/blogs/the-dewline/2012/08/bonkers-tonkas-uk-sets-tornado/ | title=Bonkers Tonkas: UK sets Tornado retirement date | first=Craig | last=Hoyle | date=2 August 2012 | publisher=Flight Global}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Tornado made its combat debut as part of the British contribution to the [[Gulf War]] in 1991. [[Operation Granby]] saw nearly 60 RAF GR1s deploy to air bases at [[Al Muharraq|Muharraq]] in Bahrain and [[Tabuk, Saudi Arabia|Tabuk]] and [[Dhahran]] in Saudi Arabia.&lt;ref name=granby_raf&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/gulf/raf_ac.html#torngr1 &quot;RAF Tornado Aircraft Deployments in Operation Granby.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force.'' Retrieved: 27 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Several Tornado ADVs were deployed to provide air cover, the threat of their long range missiles being a significant deterrent to Iraqi pilots, who would deliberately avoid combat when approached.&lt;ref&gt;Clark 1993, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early on in the conflict, the GR1s targeted military airfields across Iraq, deploying a mixture of {{convert|1000|lb|disp=flip|abbr=on}} [[Gravity bomb|unguided bombs]] in [[Toss bombing|loft-bombing]] attacks and specialised [[JP233]] runway denial weapons. Six RAF Tornados were lost in the conflict, four were lost while delivering unguided bombs, one was lost after delivering [[JP233]], and one trying to deliver [[laser-guided bomb]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/gulf/loss.html &quot;Statement on the Loss of RAF Tornado Aircraft in Combat During the Conduct of Air Operations against Iraq.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force.'' Retrieved: 27 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 January 1991, the first Tornado to be lost was shot down by an Iraqi [[SA-16]] missile following a failed low-level bombing run.&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence 2002 {{page needed|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 January, another RAF Tornado was shot down during an intensive raid on [[Tallil Air Base]].&lt;ref&gt;Lowry 2008, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; The impact of the Tornado strikes upon Iraqi air fields is difficult to determine.&lt;ref&gt;Cox and Gray 2002, p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clark 1993, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

In an emergency deployment, the UK sent out a detachment of [[Blackburn Buccaneer]] aircraft equipped with the [[Pave Spike]] [[laser designator]], allowing Tornado GR1s to drop precision guided weapons. A further crash programme in support of the sudden military action saw multiple GR1s outfitted with the [[TIALD]] laser designation system; author Claus-Christian Szejnmann declared that the TIALD pod enabled the GR1 to &quot;achieve probably the most accurate bombing in the RAF's history&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans pp66-8&quot;&gt;Evans 1999, pp. 66–68.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Szejnmann 2009, p. 217.&lt;/ref&gt; Although laser designation proved effective in the Gulf War, only 23 TIALD pods were purchased by 2000; shortages hindered combat operations over Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt;Szejnmann 2009, p. 223.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the initial phase of the war, the GR1s switched to medium level strike missions, typical targets for these strikes included munition depots and oil refining facilities.&lt;ref&gt;Lowry 2008, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; Only the reconnaissance Tornado GR1As continued to operate at the low-altitude high-speed profile throughout the war, the GR1A emerged unscathed despite the inherent danger posed by missions such as conducting pre-attack reconnaissance.&lt;ref&gt;Olsen 2011, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; In the war's aftermath, Britain maintained a military presence in the Gulf, around half a dozen GR1s were based at [[Ali Al Salem]] airbase in Kuwait for operations over the southern no fly zone as part of [[Operation Southern Watch]]; another half a dozen GR1s participated in missions over Northern Iraq in [[Operation Provide Comfort]].&lt;ref&gt;Koch and Long 2003, p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RAF Panavia Tornado GR1A.jpg|thumb|left|RAF Tornados lined up at [[CFB Goose Bay]], June 1992]]

In March 1993, a Mid-Life Upgrade (MLU) project of the Tornado was launched to upgrade the GR1/GR1A to GR4/GR4A standard. The Tornado GR4 made its operational debut in [[Operation Southern Watch]]; patrolling Iraq's southern airspace from bases in [[Kuwait]]. Both Tornado GR1s and GR4s based at Ali Al Salem, Kuwait, took part in coalition strikes at Iraq's military infrastructure during [[Operation Desert Fox]] in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/238118.stm &quot; Unrest as Tornados hit Iraq again.&quot;] ''BBC News,'' 18 December 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1998, an Iraqi anti-aircraft battery fired six to eight missiles at a patrolling Tornado, the battery was later attacked in retaliation, no aircraft were lost during the incident.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall, Andrew. [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/iraq-fires-missiles-at-raf-tornado-1194972.html?CMP=ILC-refresh &quot;Iraq fires missiles at RAF Tornado.&quot;] ''The Independent'', 31 December 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported that during Desert Fox RAF Tornados had successfully destroyed 75% of allotted targets, and out of the 36 missions planned, 28 had been successfully completed.&lt;ref&gt;Davidson, John. [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/iraq-crisis-mod-declares-tornado-bomb-raids-a-success-1194019.html?CMP=ILC-refresh &quot;Iraq crisis: MoD declares Tornado bomb raids a success.&quot;] ''The Independent'', 23 December 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

The GR1 participated in the [[Kosovo War]] in 1999. The Tornados initially operated from [[RAF Bruggen]], Germany; they later moved to [[Solenzara Air Base]], Corsica.&lt;ref&gt;Olsen 2011, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; Experience from fighting in Kosovo led to the RAF procuring [[AGM-65 Maverick]] missiles and [[Paveway|Enhanced Paveway]] [[smart bomb]]s for the Tornado fleet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corde_298&quot;/&gt; Following the Kosovo War, the GR1 was phased out as more aircraft were upgraded to GR4 standard. The final GR1 was upgraded and returned to the RAF on 10 June 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ir.baesystems.com/bae/shareholder_info/communications/2003/2003-06-30/ &quot;BAE Systems Investor Brief&amp;nbsp;– June 2003.&quot;] ''BAE Systems plc,'' 30 June 2003. Retrieved 2 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The GR4 was heavily used in [[Operation Telic]], the British contribution to the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]]. RAF Tornados flew in the opening phase of the war, flying alongside American strike aircraft to rapidly attack key installations.&lt;ref&gt;Payne, Stewart. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/1425246/Missile-alerts-at-Tornado-base-after-bombing-raids.html &quot;Missile alerts at Tornado base after bombing raids.&quot;] ''The Telegraph'', 21 March 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Following an emphasis on minimising casualties, Tornados of [[No. 617 Squadron RAF|No. 617 Squadron]] deployed the new Storm Shadow precision [[cruise missile]] for the first time in the Iraq conflict; while 25% of the UK's air-launched weapons in Kosovo were precision-guided, four years later in Iraq this ratio increased to 85%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corde_298&quot; /&gt;

On 23 March 2003, a Tornado GR4 was shot down over Iraq by [[friendly fire]] from a US [[MIM-104 Patriot|Patriot missile]] battery, killing both crew members.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Michael. [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/iraq/article424174.ece &quot;Tornado Crew Shot Down After Friend-or-Foe System Failed.&quot;] ''The Times'', 15 May 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/2877349.stm &quot;RAF Tornado Downed by US Missile.&quot;] ''BBC News'', 23 March 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2003, a US board of inquiry exonerated the battery's operators, observing the Tornado's &quot;lack of functioning IFF ([[Identification Friend or Foe]])&quot; as a factor in the incident.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Michael. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/1436240/US-clears-crew-who-shot-down-Tornado.html &quot;US 'clears' crew who shot down Tornado.&quot;] ''The Telegraph,'' 16 July 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Problems with Patriot were also suggested as a factor, multiple incidents of mis-identification of friendly aircraft have occurred, including the fatal shootdown of a [[US Navy]] [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet]] a few weeks after the loss of the Tornado.&lt;ref&gt;Tweedie, Neil. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/middleeast/iraq/1426631/US-fighter-shot-down-by-Patriot-missile.html &quot;US fighter shot down by Patriot missile.&quot;] ''The Telegraph,'' 3 April 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leung, Rebecca. [http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/02/19/60minutes/main601241.shtml &quot;The Patriot Flawed.&quot;] ''CBS News,'' 5 December 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cordesman 2003, pp. 339–340.&lt;/ref&gt; Britain withdrew the last of its Tornados from Iraq in June 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defpro.com/news/details/7881/ &quot;RAF Ends 18 Years of Combat Operations in Iraqi Skies.&quot;] ''defpro.com'', 5 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RAF Tornado GR4 Iraq.JPEG|thumb|left|A [[Royal Air Force]] Tornado in flight during [[Operation Iraqi Freedom]]]]
In early 2009, several GR4s arrived at [[Kandahar]] airfield, Afghanistan to replace the [[British Aerospace Harrier II|Harrier GR7/9]] aircraft deployed there since November 2004.&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2008/06/17/224733/raf-tornados-to-replace-harriers-in-afghanistan.html &quot;RAF Tornados to replace Harriers in Afghanistan.&quot;] ''flightglobal.com,'' 17 June 2008. Retrieved 23 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, [[Paveway IV]] guided bombs were brought into service on the RAF's Tornados, having been previously used in Afghanistan by the Harrier II fleet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aerospacetestinginternational.com/news.php?NewsID=14434 &quot;Paving the way in Afghanistan.&quot;] ''aerospacetestinginternational.com'', 22 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In Summer 2010, extra Tornados were dispatched to Kandahar for the duration of the 2010 Afghan election.&lt;ref&gt;McVeigh, Karen. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/aug/11/britain-tornados-afghanistan-raf-kandahar &quot;Britain to send two more Tornadoes to Afghanistan.&quot;] ''The Guardian'', 11 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; British Tornados ended their operations in Afghanistan in November 2014.  They flew over 5,000 pairs sorties over 33,500 hours, including 600 &quot;shows of force&quot; to deter Taliban attacks.  During more than 70 engagements, some 140 Brimstone missiles and Paveway IV bombs were deployed in total (roughly half each) and over 3,000 27&amp;nbsp;mm cannon shells were fired.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/tornado-departure-ends-uk39s-fast-jet-role-in-afghanistan-405932/ Tornado departure ends UK's fast jet role in Afghanistan] - Flightglobal.com, 11 November 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the [[Strategic Defence and Security Review 2010|2010 Strategic Defence and Security Review]] (SDSR)'s publication, the retirement of the entire Tornado fleet was under consideration, savings of £7.5&amp;nbsp;billion were anticipated.&lt;ref&gt;Norton-Taylor, Richard and Nicholas Watt. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2010/oct/15/typhoons-cost-raf-dear &quot;MoD pays extra £2.7bn for unwanted Typhoons.&quot;] ''The Guardian'', 15 October 2010. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The SDSR announced the Tornado would be retained at the expense of the Harrier II, although Tornado numbers are to decline in transition to the Eurofighter Typhoon, and later on, the [[Lockheed Martin F-35 Lightning II|F-35 Lightning II]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.direct.gov.uk/prod_consum_dg/groups/dg_digitalassets/@dg/@en/documents/digitalasset/dg_191634.pdf &quot;Securing Britain in an Age of Uncertainty: The Strategic Defence and Security Review.&quot;] ''HM Government,'' 19 October 2010. Retrieved 30 October 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/uk-confirms-two-tornado-gr4-squadrons-will-go-by-june-353783/ &quot;UK confirms two Tornado GR4 squadrons will go by June.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 1 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 March 2011, British Prime Minister [[David Cameron]] announced the deployment of Tornados and [[Eurofighter Typhoon|Typhoon]]s to enforce a [[Libyan no-fly zone|no-fly zone in Libya]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-12784729 &quot;Libya: UK planes to be deployed.&quot;] ''BBC News'' Retrieved: 18 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2011, several Tornados flew {{convert|3000|mi|km|sigfig=2|adj=on}} strike missions against targets inside Libya in what were, according to Defence Secretary [[Liam Fox]], &quot;the longest range bombing mission conducted by the RAF since the Falklands conflict&quot;.&lt;ref name = BBC-Liam-Fox&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-12797500 &quot;Libya: British missiles fired at military sites.&quot;] ''BBC News'', 20 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Drury, Ian. [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1368259/Libya-Tornado-Top-Guns-3-000-mile-mission-hammer-Gaddafis-military-machine.html &quot;Tornado Top Guns' 3,000-mile mission to hammer tyrant's military machine.&quot;] ''The Daily Mail'', 21 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; A variety of weapons were used in operations over Libya, including [[Laser-guided bomb]]s and [[Brimstone (missile)|Brimstone missiles]].&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/us-french-militaries-interested-in-brimstone-missile-says-raf-355792/ &quot;US, French militaries interested in Brimstone missile, says RAF official.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 20 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; 59 RAF aircraft are receiving the CUSP avionics upgrade which achieved Initial Service Date (ISD) in March 2013&lt;ref name=Fish20140716&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.shephardmedia.com/news/defence-notes/farnborough-tornado-will-go-out-style/ | title=Farnborough: Tornado will go out in style | date=16 July 2014 | first=Tim | last= Fish | publisher=Shephard Media }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the type will be withdrawn from RAF service on 31 March 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld201213/ldhansrd/text/130422w0001.htm#13042232001049 | title=House of Lords Written Answers | date=22 April 2013 | journal=Hansard | publisher=UK Parliament}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:RAF CONDUCTS FIRST AIR STRIKES OF IRAQ MISSION MOD 45158635.jpg|thumbnail|right|Tornado over Iraq in 2014]]
On 11 August 2014, a Cabinet Office Briefing Room (COBR) emergency meeting concluded that the RAF would deploy Tornado GR4s to [[RAF Akrotiri]], Cyprus in support of refugees sheltering from [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|Islamic State militants]] in the [[Mount Sinjar]] region of Iraq. The decision came three days after the [[2014 military intervention against ISIS|United States began conducting air attacks against the Islamic State]]. Tornados were pre-positioned to use their surveillance capabilities to gather situational awareness to help with humanitarian efforts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/uk-to-deploy-tornados-in-support-of-iraq-operations-402592/ UK to deploy Tornados in support of Iraq operations] - Flightglobal.com, 12 August 2014&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last= |first= |date= |title=RAF Tornado jets in Cyprus for Iraq aid mission |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-28758370 |newspaper= |location= |publisher=BBC News |accessdate=12 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 September 2014, three days after Parliament approved of airstrikes against Islamic State forces inside Iraq, two Tornados conducted their first armed reconnaissance mission over the country, in conjunction with other coalition aircraft, and were cleared to conduct airstrikes if needed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armyrecognition.com/september_2014_global_defense_security_news_uk/british_raf_tornado_aircrafts_conducted_first_reconnaissance_flights_in_iraq.html British Tornado {{sic|nolink=y|aircrafts}} conducted first reconnaissance flights in Iraq] - Armyrecognition.com, 29 September 2014&lt;/ref&gt; Britain's first airstrike was conducted the next day, when two Tornados hit a heavy weapons post and an armored vehicle in the process of supporting [[Peshmerga|Kurdish forces]] in northwest Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.militarytimes.com/article/20140930/NEWS08/309300068/Kurds-claim-advances-Iraq-Britain-joins-fray Kurds claim advances in Iraq as Britain joins fray] - Militarytimes.com, 30 September 2014&lt;/ref&gt; By 1 March 2015, eight RAF Tornados had been deployed to Akrotiri and conducted 159 airstrikes against IS targets in Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/uk-details-extent-of-combat-activity-over-iraq-409617/ UK details extent of combat activity over Iraq] - Flightglobal.com, 2 March 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

On the 2 December 2015, the British Parliament voted to begin air strikes in Syria as well as Iraq, to combat the growing threat of ISIS. Tornados began their bombing that evening.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-34992032 Syria air strikes: RAF Tornado jets carry out bombing]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Saudi Air Force===
[[File:Tornado F3 RSAF Feb1991.jpeg|thumb|RSAF Tornado ADV, prior to embarking on a combat mission during Operation Desert Storm, February 1991]]

On 25 September 1985, the UK and Saudi Arabia signed the [[Al-Yamamah arms deal|Al Yamamah I]] contract including, amongst other things, the sale of 48 IDS and 24 ADV model Tornados.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor 2001, pp. 189–190.&lt;/ref&gt; The first flight of a RSAF Tornado IDS was on 26 March 1986, and the first Saudi ADV was delivered on 9 February 1989. Saudi Tornados undertook operations during the Gulf War. In June 1993 the [[Al-Yamamah arms deal|Al Yamamah II]] contract was signed, the main element of which was 48 additional IDSs.&lt;ref&gt;Fairhill, David. &quot;Britain signs 6&amp;nbsp;billion pounds Saudi arms contract.&quot; ''The Guardian,'' 9 July 1988.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Koch and Long 2003, pp. 81–82.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following experience with both the Tornado and the [[McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagle]], the RSAF discontinued low-level mission training in the F-15E in light of the Tornado's superior low-altitude flight performance.&lt;ref name =cord_210/&gt; In addition, 10 of the Saudi Tornados were outfitted with equipment for performing reconnaissance missions. The 22 Tornado ADVs were replaced by the Eurofighter Typhoon; the retired aircraft were being purchased back by the UK as of 2007.&lt;ref&gt;Cordesman 2007, p. 214.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 2007, both the [[Sea Eagle (missile)|Sea Eagle]] anti-ship missile and the [[ALARM (missile)|ALARM]] [[anti-radiation missile]] that previously equipped the RSAF's Tornados had been withdrawn from service.&lt;ref name =cord_210&gt;Cordesman 2007, p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2010, Saudi Arabia has signed several contracts for new weapon systems to be fitted to their Tornado and Typhoon fleets, such as the short range air-to-air [[IRIS-T]] missile, and the Brimstone and Storm Shadow cruise missiles.&lt;ref&gt;Chuter, Andrew. [http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=4506705 &quot;Saudi Arabia Buys MBDA Missiles.&quot;] ''DefenseNews,'' 19 February 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2006, the Saudi government signed a contract worth £2.5&amp;nbsp;billion (US$4.7&amp;nbsp;billion) with [[BAE Systems]] to upgrade up to 80 RSAF Tornado IDS aircraft to keep them in service until 2020. RSAF Tornado 6612 was returned to BAE Systems Warton in December 2006 for upgrade under the &quot;Tornado Sustainment Programme&quot; (TSP), which will &quot;equip the IDS fleet with a range of new precision-guided weapons and enhanced targeting equipment, in many cases common with those systems already fielded by the UK's Tornado GR4s.&quot;&lt;ref name ='saudi upgrade'&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2007/09/18/216775/saudi-arabia-reveals-progress-of-tornado-upgrade.html &quot;Saudi Arabia reveals progress of Tornado upgrade.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 18 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2007, the first RSAF aircraft to complete modernisation was returned to Saudi Arabia.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;First Upgraded Tornado Re-delivered to Royal Saudi Air Force.&quot; ''AirForces Monthly,'' February 2008, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting from the first week of November 2009, Saudi Air Force Tornados, along with Saudi F-15s performed air raids during the [[Shia insurgency in Yemen|Shia insurgency]] in north Yemen. It was the first time since [[Operation Desert Storm]] in 1991 that the Royal Saudi Air Force participated in a military operation over hostile territory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/33670149/ns/world_news-mideastn_africa/ &quot;Saudis bomb Yemen rebels across border.&quot;] ''Associated Press,'' 5 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Saudi Air Force Tornados are playing a central role in [[Saudi Arabian-led intervention in Yemen|Saudi-led bombing campaign in Yemen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url= http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/defence/11584269/Saudis-UK-made-war-jets-outnumber-RAFs.html |title=Saudis’ UK-made war jets outnumber RAF’s |date= 5 May 2015 |work= The Daily Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==

==={{anchor|IDS}}Tornado IDS===
{{multiple image
 |direction = vertical
 |width     = 220
 |image1    = Tornado 6Stormo Afghanistan Dec2008.jpg
 |caption1  = [[Italian Air Force]] Tornado in flight over [[Afghanistan]] in 2008
 |image2    = tornado gr4 za597 kemble arp.jpg
 |caption2  = RAF Tornado GR4 (ZA597) displaying at [[Kemble Air Show]] in 2008, the wings are partially swept
 |image3    = AGM-88 and AIM-9 on Tornado.jpg
 |caption3  = Luftwaffe Tornado ECR participating in [[Operation Allied Force]] in April 1999
&lt;!-- Please do not add more images here as it disrupts the spacing --&gt;
}}
;Tornado GR1
RAF IDS variants were initially designated the [[British military aircraft designation systems|Tornado GR1]] with later modified aircraft designated Tornado GR1A, Tornado GR1B, Tornado GR4 and Tornado GR4A. The first of 228 GR1s was delivered on 5 June 1979, and the type entered service in the early 1980s. A total of 142 aircraft were upgraded to GR4 standard from 1997 to 2003.&lt;ref name =BAE_GR4_up/&gt;

;Tornado GR1B
The Tornado GR1B was a specialised anti-shipping variant of the GR1. A total of 26 were converted,&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ30 p117&quot;&gt;Lake ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 30, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; which were based at [[RAF Lossiemouth]], Scotland, replacing the [[Blackburn Buccaneer]]. Each aircraft was equipped to carry up to four [[Sea Eagle (missile)|Sea Eagle]] anti-ship missiles.&lt;ref name=&quot;lame&quot; /&gt; At first the GR1B lacked the radar capability to track shipping, instead relying on the missile's seeker for target acquisition, later updates allowed target data to be fed from aircraft to missile.&lt;ref name=&quot;WAPJ33 p105&quot;&gt;Donald ''World Air Power Journal'' Volume 33, p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;

;Tornado GR4
In 1984, the UK [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] began studies for a GR1 Mid-Life Update (MLU). The update to GR4 standard, approved in 1994, would improve capability in the medium-altitude role based on lessons learned from the GR1's performance in the 1991 Gulf War. British Aerospace (later [[BAE Systems]]) upgraded 142 Tornado GR1s to GR4 standard, beginning in 1996 and finished in 2003.&lt;ref name =BAE_GR4_up/&gt; 59 RAF aircraft are receiving the CUSP avionics package which integrates the Paveway IV bomb and installs a new secure communications module from Cassidian&lt;ref name=Fish20140716 /&gt; in Phase A,&lt;ref name=Hoyle20080109 /&gt; followed by the Tactical Information Exchange (TIE) datalink from General Dynamics&lt;ref name=Fish20140716/&gt; in Phase B.&lt;ref name=Hoyle20080109 /&gt;

;Tornado GR1A/GR4A
The GR1A is the reconnaissance variant used by the RAF and RSAF, fitted with the TIRRS (Tornado Infra-Red Reconnaissance System), replacing the cannon.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans p98-9&quot;&gt;Evans 1999, pp. 98–99.&lt;/ref&gt; The RAF ordered 30 GR1As, 14 as GR1 rebuilds and 16 as new-builds.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans p97&quot;&gt;Evans 1999, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; When the Tornado GR1s were upgraded to become GR4s, GR1A aircraft were upgraded to GR4A standard.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAp08 p24&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' April 2008, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; The switch from low-level operations to medium/high-level operations means that the internal TIRRS is no longer in use.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIAp08 p28&quot;&gt;Lake ''Air International'' April 2008, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; As the GR4A's internal sensors are no longer essential, the RAF's Tactical Reconnaissance Wing operate both GR4A and GR4 aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafmarham/aboutus/iiacsqnhistorycurrent.cfm &quot;II (AC) Squadron History&amp;nbsp;– Current.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force,'' Retrieved: 4 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Tornado ECR|ECR}} Tornado ECR===
Operated by Germany and Italy, the ECR (Electric Combat / Reconnaissance) is a Tornado variant devoted to [[Suppression of Enemy Air Defenses]] (SEAD) missions. It was first delivered on 21 May 1990. The ECR has sensors to detect radar usage and is equipped with anti-radiation [[AGM-88 HARM]] missiles.&lt;ref name =janes_237/&gt; The Luftwaffe's 35 ECRs were delivered new, while Italy received 16 converted IDSs. Italian Tornado ECRs differ from the Luftwaffe aircraft as they lack built-in reconnaissance capability and use RecceLite reconnaissance pods, also only Luftwaffe ECRs are equipped with RB199 Mk.105 engine, which has a slightly higher thrust rating.&lt;ref name=Janes_241&gt;Jackson et al. 1998, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; The German ECRs do not carry a cannon.&lt;ref&gt;Davies, Steve. &quot;German SEAD: The Tornado ECRs of JaBoG 32.&quot; ''[[AirForces Monthly]]'', March 2003, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; The RAF uses the IDS version in the SEAD role instead of the ECR. It also modified several of its Tornado F.3s to undertake the mission.&lt;ref name=EF3&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.raf.mod.uk/equipment/tornadof3.cfm|title= Tornado F3|publisher=Royal Air Force|accessdate=26 March 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tornado ADV===
{{Main article|Panavia Tornado ADV}}

The Tornado ADV (air defence variant)  was an [[interceptor aircraft|interceptor]] variant of the Tornado, developed for the RAF (designated Tornado F2 or F3) and also operated by Saudi Arabia and Italy. The ADV had inferior agility to fighters like the [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle]],&lt;ref&gt;Haglund 1989, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt; but it was not intended as a dog-fighter, instead it was a long-endurance interceptor to counter the threat from Cold War bombers.&lt;ref name = 'eagles'&gt;Eagles 1991, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the ADV had 80% parts commonality with the Tornado IDS, the ADV had greater acceleration, improved RB199 Mk.104 engines, a stretched body, greater fuel capacity, the [[AI.24 Foxhunter]] radar, and software changes. It had only one cannon to accommodate a retractable [[inflight refuelling|inflight refuelling probe]].&lt;ref name ='eagles 88-91'&gt;Eagles 1991, pp. 88–91.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = 'turbounion'&gt;[http://www.turbounion.co.uk/ &quot;Turbo-Union: The Power for Peace and Freedom.&quot;] ''turbounion.co.uk.'' Retrieved: 29 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operators==
[[File:Tornado operators.png|thumb|upright=1.4|Operators of the Panavia Tornado]]
{{main article|List of Panavia Tornado operators}}

;{{GER}}
*[[German Air Force]] had 64 IDS and 29 ECR aircraft in service in December 2015.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zeit.de/politik/2015-12/bundeswehr-tornados-maengel Weniger als jeder zweite Tornado ist einsatzbereit.] Retrieved 27 January 2016&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{ITA}}
*[[Italian Air Force]] had 62 IDS and 16 ECR aircraft in operation in December 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flightworld air11 p41&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 13–19 December 2011, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{SAU}}
*[[Royal Saudi Air Force]] had 82 IDS in operation in December 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flightworld air11 p47&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 13–19 December 2011, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{UK}}
*[[Royal Air Force]] had 102 GR4/GR4A aircraft in service in March 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201314/cmhansrd/cm140317/text/140317w0006.htm#1403181000859 House of Commons Hansard Written Answers] (publications.parliament.uk) 17 March 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aircraft on display==
[[File:Tornado Schleswig Jagel.jpg|thumb|[[Gate guardian]] Tornado on display in Jagel, Germany]]
[[File:Panavia Tornado USAF.jpg|thumb|An RAF Tornado GR1 at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]]]]

;Bulgaria
*''44+13'' Tornado IDS on display at the [[National Museum of Military History (Bulgaria)|National Museum of Military History]], Sofia &lt;ref&gt;http://www.militarymuseum.bg/Pages/Exposures/Outside/Outside-en.html&lt;/ref&gt;

;Germany
*''D-9591'' Tornado Prototype P.01 on display at [[Militärhistorisches Museum Flugplatz Berlin-Gatow]] &lt;ref&gt;Militärhistorisches Museum Flugplatz Berlin-Gatow. [https://m2.facebook.com/MHMGatow/albums/322485887849005/?refid=17] Tornado - Der erste Protoyp jetzt in Gatow, October 2012 (German). Retrieved 5 October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''XX948'' Tornado Prototype P.06 on display at [[Hermeskeil]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*''43+01'' Tornado IDS (first series aircraft) at [[Taktisches Luftwaffengeschwader 33]] in Cochem / Büchel &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rhein-zeitung.de/region/lokales/mittelmosel_artikel,-Bestandsgaranten-fuer-Buechel-Tornados-sollen-laenger-fliegen-_arid,1211649.html#.VMpiuy7P6PU |title=Bestandsgaranten für Büchel? Tornados sollen länger fliegen |publisher=Rhein-Zeitung |date=2014-09-25 |accessdate=2015-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''43+96'' Tornado gate guard at the German air base in Jagel, near [[Schleswig, Schleswig-Holstein]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*''44+97'' Tornado IDS of the ''Einsatzgeschwader (Expeditionary Air Wing) [[Mazar-i-Sharif]]'' at the [[Deutsches Museum Flugwerft Schleissheim]], [[Oberschleißheim]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*''44+31'' Tornado IDS (Blue Lightning paint scheme) of the 31st Fighter Bomber Wing &quot;[[Boelcke]]&quot; at [[Nörvenich AB]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*Tornado IDS on display at the [[Luftwaffenmuseum]], in Berlin{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*Tornado IDS on display at the [[Technikmuseum Speyer]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*''43+86'' Tornado (MTU corporate design paint scheme) at [[MTU Aero Engines]], in Munich

;Italy
*''MM7210'' Tornado F3 on display at the [[Italian Air Force Museum]], Vigna di Valle{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}

;Saudi Arabia
*Tornado ADV on display at [[King Abdul-Aziz Air Base]], Dhahran
*Tornado ADV on display at the [[Royal Saudi Air Force Museum]] in Riyadh{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*Tornado IDS on display the [[Royal Saudi Air Force Museum]] in Riyadh{{Citation needed|date=March 2014}}
*Tornado IDS on display at [[King Abdul-Aziz Air Base]], Dhahran

;United Kingdom
*''XX946'' Tornado Prototype P.02 on display at the [[RAF Museum Cosford]], England&lt;ref&gt;Simpson, Andrew. [http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/cosford/collections/aircraft/aircraft_histories/1994-1458-A%20Tornado%20PO2%20XX946.pdf &quot;Individual History: Panavia Tornado PO.2 XX946/8883M (Museum Accession Number 1994/1458/A).&quot;] ''Royal Air Force Museum'', 2007. Retrieved 5 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''XX947'' Tornado Prototype P.03, was [[gate guardian]] at [[Shoreham Airport]] in West Sussex, England&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shorehamherald.co.uk/news/local/tornado-blows-into-airport-1-1139727]&lt;/ref&gt;  but was for sale in September 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.everettaero.com/tornado.html|title=Everett Aero - Aircraft/Panavia Tornado for Sale|work=everettaero.com|accessdate=17 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''XZ631'' Tornado GR4 Prototype P.15 on display at [[Yorkshire Air Museum]], Elvington, England&lt;ref name=&quot;York&quot;&gt;[http://www.yorkshireairmuseum.org/exhibits/aircraft-exhibits/post-world-war-ii-aircraft &quot;Post World War II Aircraft.&quot;] ''Yorkshire Air Museum''. Retrieved 5 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA319'' Tornado GR1T Gate Guard, MoD DSDA [[Arncott]], [[Bicester]], Oxfordshire, England&lt;ref&gt;Ellis 2014, p. 186&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA326'' Tornado GR1 on display at [[Bruntingthorpe Aerodrome]], Leicestershire, England.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis 2014, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA354'' Tornado GR1 on display at [[Yorkshire Air Museum]], Elvington, England&lt;ref name=&quot;York&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- *''ZA328'' Tornado GR1 Used for Apprentice Training, BAE Systems Training School, [[Preston, Lancashire]] not on public display --&gt;
''ZA361'' Tornado GR1 on display at RNAS Can Florit, Calvia, Palma Mallorca, Spain - not on public display
*''ZA362'' Tornado GR1 on display at [[Inverness Airport#Highland Aviation Museum|Highland Aviation Museum]], Inverness, Scotland&lt;ref name=&quot;aviationmuseum&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aviationmuseum.eu/World/Europe/UK/Inverness/Highland_Aviation_Museum.htm|title=Highland Aviation Museum - Inverness - Scotland - United Kingdom|publisher=aviationmuseum.eu|accessdate=26 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA452'' Tornado GR4 on display at [[Midland Air Museum]], [[Coventry]], England.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis 2014, p.274&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA457'' Tornado GR1B on display at RAF Museum, Hendon, England&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/london/collections/aircraft/panavia-tornado-gr1.cfm &quot;Panavia Tornado GR1B Aircraft History.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force Museum'', 2010. Retrieved 5 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA465'' Tornado GR1 on display at [[Imperial War Museum]], Duxford, England&lt;ref name=&quot;ellis23&quot;&gt;Ellis 2014, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA475'' Tornado GR1 on the gate at [[RAF Lossiemouth]], Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis 2014, p. 314&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZA407'' Tornado GR4 on display at [[RAF Marham]], Norfolk, England.
*''ZE760'' Tornado F3 on the gate at [[RAF Coningsby]], Lincolnshire, England&lt;ref&gt;Ellis 2014, p. 138&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZE887'' Tornado F3 on display at [[RAF Museum]], Hendon, England.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis 2014, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZE934'' Tornado F3 on display at [[National Museum of Flight]], East Fortune, Scotland&lt;ref&gt;Ellis 2014, p. 309&lt;/ref&gt;
*''ZH552'' Tornado F3 on display at [[RAF Leeming]], North Yorkshire, England&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thenorthernecho.co.uk/news/13327364.Fighter_jet_on_permanent_sentry_duty/|title=Fighter jet on permanent sentry duty|work=The Northern Echo|accessdate=17 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;United States
[[File:43+74 Panavia Tornado IDS German Marine (8738052307).jpg|thumb|''43+74'' Tornado IDS of the German Navy on display at the Pima Air &amp; Space Museum, Arizona]]
*''ZA374'' Tornado GR1 on display at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]], Wright Patterson AFB, Ohio&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/Visit/MuseumExhibits/FactSheets/Display/tabid/509/Article/198063/panavia-tornado-gr1.aspx Panavia Tornado GR1]. [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]]. Retrieved: 22 October 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
*''43+74'' Tornado IDS of the German Navy, Marinefliegergeschwader 1 at the [[Pima Air &amp; Space Museum]], Tucson, AZ

==Specifications (Tornado GR4)==
[[File:Panavia Tornado IDS.svg|right|450px]]
{{Aircraft specifications
&lt;!-- If you do not understand how to use this template, please ask at [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Aircraft]].
     Please answer the following questions: --&gt;
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=jet
&lt;!-- Now, fill in the specs. Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses).
If an item doesn't apply, like capacity, leave it blank. For additional lines, end your alt units with )&lt;/li&gt; and start a new, fully formatted line with &lt;li&gt;
--&gt;
|ref=''International Warbirds: An Illustrated Guide to World Military Aircraft, 1914–2000'',&lt;ref name = 'Frédriksen 255'&gt;Frédriksen 2001, p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Tornado, Modern Fighting Aircraft''&lt;ref&gt;Richardson 1986, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
        General characteristics --&gt;
|crew=2
|span main= 13.91&amp;nbsp;m at 25° wing sweep, 8.60&amp;nbsp;m at 67° wing sweep
|span alt= 45.6&amp;nbsp;ft / 28.2&amp;nbsp;ft
|area main= 26.6&amp;nbsp;m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|area alt= 286&amp;nbsp;ft&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|length main= 16.72&amp;nbsp;m
|length alt= 54&amp;nbsp;ft 10 in
|height main= 5.95&amp;nbsp;m
|height alt= 19.5&amp;nbsp;ft
|empty weight main= 13,890&amp;nbsp;kg
|empty weight alt= 30,620&amp;nbsp;lb&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home2.btconnect.com/AirFairRadio/TornadaGR4.htm|title=New Page 0|work=btconnect.com|accessdate=17 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|loaded weight main= 20,240&amp;nbsp;kg
|loaded weight alt= 44,620&amp;nbsp;lb&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aerospaceweb.org/aircraft/bomber/tornado_ids/|title=Aerospaceweb.org - Aircraft Museum - Tornado IDS|work=aerospaceweb.org|accessdate=17 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|max takeoff weight main= 28,000&amp;nbsp;kg
|max takeoff weight alt= 61,700&amp;nbsp;lb
|more general=
&lt;!--
        Powerplant --&gt;
|engine (jet)= [[Turbo-Union RB199]]-34R Mk 103
|type of jet= [[afterburner|afterburning]] [[turbofan]]s
|number of jets= 2
|thrust main= 43.8&amp;nbsp;kN
|thrust alt= 9,850&amp;nbsp;lbf
|afterburning thrust main= 76.8&amp;nbsp;kN
|afterburning thrust alt= 17,270&amp;nbsp;lbf
|thrust more=
&lt;!--
        Performance --&gt;
|max speed main= Mach 2.2
|max speed alt= 2,400&amp;nbsp;km/h, 1,490&amp;nbsp;mph
|max speed more= at 9,000&amp;nbsp;m (30,000&amp;nbsp;ft) altitude; 800 knots, 1,482&amp;nbsp;km/h, 921&amp;nbsp;mph [[indicated airspeed]] near sea level
|ceiling main= 15,240&amp;nbsp;m
|ceiling alt= 50,000&amp;nbsp;ft
|range main= 1,390&amp;nbsp;km
|range alt= 870&amp;nbsp;mi
|range more= for typical combat mission
|ferry range main= 3,890&amp;nbsp;km
|ferry range alt= 2,417&amp;nbsp;mi
|ferry range more= with four external drop tanks
|climb rate main= 76.7&amp;nbsp;m/s
|climb rate alt= 15,100&amp;nbsp;ft/min
|loading main=
|loading alt=
|thrust/weight= 0.77
|more performance=
&lt;!--
        Armament &amp; Avionics --&gt;
|guns= 1× {{convert|27|mm|in|abbr=on|sigfig=3}} [[Mauser BK-27]] [[revolver cannon]] internally mounted under starboard side of fuselage with 180 rounds 
|hardpoints= 4× light duty + 3× heavy duty under-fuselage and 4× swivelling under-wing pylon stations 
|hardpoint capacity=9,000&amp;nbsp;kg (19,800&amp;nbsp;lb) of payload, the two inner wing pylons have shoulder launch rails for 2× Short-Range AAM (SRAAM) each
|rockets=
|hardpoint missiles=&lt;br/&gt;
***[[AIM-9 Sidewinder]] ''or'' [[AIM-132 ASRAAM]] air-to-air missiles for self-defence
***6× [[AGM-65 Maverick]]; ''or''
***12× [[Brimstone missile]]; ''or''
***2× [[Storm Shadow]]
***9× [[ALARM missile|ALARM]] anti-radiation missile
|hardpoint bombs=&lt;br/&gt;
***5× 500&amp;nbsp;lb [[Paveway IV]]; ''or''
***3× 1000&amp;nbsp;lb [[Paveway|(UK Mk 20) Paveway II/Enhanced Paveway II]]; ''or''
***2× 2000&amp;nbsp;lb [[GBU-24 Paveway III|Paveway III (GBU-24)/Enhanced Paveway III (EGBU-24)]]; ''or''
***[[BL755]] [[cluster bomb]]s; ''or''
***Up to 2× [[JP233]] ''or'' [[MW-1|MW-1 munitions dispenser]]s (for runway cratering operations)
***Up to 4× [[B61 nuclear bomb|B61]] ''or'' [[WE.177]] tactical nuclear weapons
|hardpoint other=Up to 4× [[drop tank]]s for ferry flight/extended range/flight time
|avionics=
*[[RAPTOR]] aerial reconnaissance pod
*[[Rafael Advanced Defense Systems|Rafael]] [[LITENING]] targeting pod; ''or''
*[[TIALD]] [[laser designator]] pod
*[[BAE Systems Sky Shadow]] electronic countermeasure pod
}}

==Popular culture==
{{Main article|Aircraft in fiction#Panavia Tornado|l1=Panavia Tornado in fiction}}
&lt;!-- ===============({{NoMoreCruft}})===============--&gt;
&lt;!-- Please READ [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content#Popular_culture]] and [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Style guide#Popular_culture]] before adding any &quot;Popular culture&quot; items.

Please do not add the many minor appearances of the aircraft. This section is only for major cultural appearances where the aircraft plays a MAJOR part in the story line, or has an &quot;especially notable&quot; role in what is listed. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. Random cruft, including ALL Ace Combat, Battlefield, and Metal Gear Solid appearances, and ALL anime/fiction lookalike speculation, WILL BE removed.

If your item has been removed, please discuss it on the talk page FIRST. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. If a consensus is reached to include your item, a regular editor of this page will add it back. Thank you for your co-operation.--&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Royal Air Force|Aviation}}
{{Aircontent
|see also=
*[[Future Offensive Air System]]
*[[Wild Weasel]]
|related=
*[[Panavia Tornado ADV]]
|similar aircraft=
*[[Dassault Mirage 2000]]
*[[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark]]
*[[Grumman F-14 Tomcat]]
*[[McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagle]]
*[[Mikoyan MiG-27]]
*[[Sukhoi Su-24]]
*[[Xian JH-7]]
|lists=
*[[List of active United Kingdom military aircraft]]
*[[List of military aircraft of Germany]]
*[[List of active Italian military aircraft]]
*[[List of aircraft of the Royal Air Force]]
*[[Royal Saudi Air Force]]
}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* ''Aeroguide 21: Panavia Tornado F Mk 2/Mk 3.'' Ongar, UK: Linewrights Ltd. 1988. ISBN 0-946958-26-2.
* Allen, Calvin H. and W. Lynn Rigsbee. ''Oman Under Qaboos: From Coup to Constitution, 1970–1996.'' London: Routledge, 2000. ISBN 0-7146-5001-3.
* Ball, Desmond J. ''The Australian Tactical Fighter Force: Prologue and Prospects.'' Canberra: Australian National University, 1979. ISBN 0-85823-439-4.
* Clark, Richard B. ''Air Power and Desert Storm.'' Darby, Pennsylvania: DIANE Publishing, 1993. ISBN 1-56806-446-2.
* Cordesman, Anthony H. ''Gulf Military Forces in an Era of Asymmetric Wars, Volume 1.'' Westport, Connecticut: Greenwood Publishing, 2007. ISBN 0-275-99250-0.
* Cordesman, Anthony H. ''The Iraq War: Strategy, Tactics, and Military Lessons'' (CSIS Significant Issues Series). Westport, Connecticut: Praeger, 2003. ISBN 0-89206-432-3.
* Cox, Sebastian and Peter Gray. ''Air Power History: Turning Points from Kitty Hawk to Kosovo.'' London: Routledge, 2002. ISBN 0-7146-8257-8.
* Donald, David. &quot;Lossimouth Strike Wing&quot;. ''World Air Power Journal'', Volume 33, Summer 1998, pp.&amp;nbsp;104–113. London: Aerospace Publishing. ISBN 1-86184-015-2. ISSN 0959-7050.
* Donald, David and Christopher Chant. [https://books.google.com/books?id=7L-PvBlfFW0C&amp;pg=PA94&amp;dq=Panavia+Tornado+Gulf&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0Uw4TdLfEouYhQe7lvjOCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Tornado&amp;f=false ''Air War in The Gulf 1991.''] Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 2001. ISBN 1-84176-295-4.
* Eagles, J.D. [https://books.google.com/books?id=IOGCd7QreKgC&amp;pg=PA88&amp;dq=panavia+tornado&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=rdn3S-vqLMOlONXH1ZUM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCYQ6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=panavia%20tornado&amp;f=false &quot;Preparing a Bomber Destroyer: The Panavia Tornado ADV.&quot;] ''Putnam Aeronautical Review'' (Naval Institute Press), Volume 2, 1991, pp.&amp;nbsp;88–93.
*{{cite book |last=Ellis |first=Ken |authorlink= |coauthors= |title= Wreck &amp; Relics, 24th Edition |year=2014 |publisher= Crecy Publishing Ltd |location= Manchester |isbn=9 780859 791779}}
* {{Cite book|last=Evans|first=Andy|title=Panavia Tornado|location=Ramsbury, Marlborough, Wiltshire, UK|publisher=The Crowood Press, 1999|isbn=1-86126-201-9|ref={{harvid|Evans|1999}}}}
* Frédriksen, John C. [https://books.google.com/books?id=8tlOHHCRxuYC&amp;pg=PA255&amp;dq=Panavia+Tornado&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=zuM2TfrqN8qGhQe6naThAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=Panavia%20Tornado&amp;f=false ''International Warbirds: An Illustrated Guide to World Military Aircraft, 1914–2000.''] Santa Barbara, California: ABC-CLIO, 2001. ISBN 1-57607-364-5.
* Geiss, Juergen and Peter Berndt. [http://www.europeansecurityanddefence.info/Ausgaben/2010/03_2010/06_Geiss_Berndt/Geiss_Berndt.pdf ''Tornados and Further Planning.''] European Security and Defence, March 2010.
* {{Cite book|last=Haglund|first=David G|url=https://books.google.com/?id=6WEOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA46&amp;dq=Panavia+Tornado#v=onepage&amp;q=Panavia%20Tornado&amp;f=false|title=The Defence Industrial Base and The West|location=London|publisher=Routledge, 1989|isbn=0-415-00923-5|ref={{harvid|Haglund|1989}}|year=1989}}
* Hoyle, Craig. &quot;World Air Forces Directory&quot;. ''Flight International'', 13–19 December 2011. pp.&amp;nbsp;26–52.
* Jackson, Paul, Kenneth Munson, Lindsay Peacock and John W. R. Taylor, eds. ''Jane's All The World's Aircraft 1997–98.'' London: Jane's Information Group, 1998. ISBN 0-7106-1788-7.
* Jarret, D. N. ''Cockpit Engineering.'' Farnham, Surrey, UK: Ashgate Publishing, 2005. ISBN 0-7546-1751-3.
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Jefford|editor-first= C.G|url=http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/research/documents/Journal%2027A%20-%20Seminar%20-%20Birth%20of%20Tornado.pdf|title=The Birth of Tornado|location=London|publisher=Royal Air Force Historical Society, 2002|isbn=0-9530345-0-X|ref={{harvid|Jefford et al.|2002}}}}
* Jukes, Malcolm. ''Aircraft Display Systems.'' Reston, Virginia: American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics, 2004. ISBN 1-56347-657-6.
* Koch, Christian and David E. Long. ''Gulf Security in the Twenty-First Century.'' London: I.B. Tauris, 2003. ISBN 1-85043-386-0.
* Lake, Jon. &quot;Aircraft of the RAF: Part 1&amp;nbsp;– Panavia Tornado&quot;. ''[[Air International]]'', Vol. 74, No. 4, April 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;24–29. ISSN 0306-5634.
* Lake, Jon. ''Great Book of Bombers.'' Minneapolis, Minnesota: Zenith Imprint, 2002. ISBN 0-7603-1347-4.
* Lake, Jon. &quot;Tornado Variant Briefing: Part I: IDS and Recce&quot;. ''World Air Power Journal'', Volume 30, Autumn/Fall 1997, pp.&amp;nbsp;98–121. London: Aerospace Publishing. ISBN 1-86184-004-7. ISSN 0959-7050.
* Lake, Jon. &quot;Tornado Variant Briefing: Part III: Tornado Operators&quot;. ''World Air Power Journal'', Volume 32, Spring 1998, pp.&amp;nbsp;118–137. London: Aerospace Publishing. ISBN 1-86184-006-3. ISSN 0959-7050.
* Lambeth, Benjamin S. ''NATO's Air War for Kosovo: A Strategic and Operational Assessment.'' Santa Monica, California: Rand Corporation, 2001. ISBN 0-8330-3050-7.
* [[Tm McLelland|Laming, Tim]]. ''Fight's On: Airborne with the Aggressors.'' Minneapolis, Minnesota: Zenith Imprint, 1996. ISBN 0-7603-0260-X.
* Lawrence, Richard R. ''Mammoth Eyewitness Book Of How It Happened Battles: Eyewitness Accounts of History's Greatest Battles, from Thermopyle to the Gulf War''. London: Constable &amp; Robinson Ltd, 2002. ISBN 978-0-7867-1119-2.
* List, Friedrich. &quot;German Air Arms Review&quot;. ''Air International'', Vol. 70, No. 5, May 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;50–57. ISSN 0306-5634.
* Lorell, Mark A. ''Troubled Partnership: A History of US-Japan Collaboration on the FS-X Fighter.'' Piscataway, New Jersey: Transaction Publishers (Rutgers University), 1996. ISBN 1-56000-891-1.
* Lowry, Richard S. ''The Gulf War Chronicles: A Military History of the First War with Iraq.'' Bloomington, Indiana: iUniverse, 2008. ISBN 1-60528-006-2.
* Martin, Stephen. ''The Economics of Offsets: Defence Procurement and Countertrade.'' London: Routledge, 1996. ISBN 3-7186-5782-1.
* Moir, Ian and Allan Seabridge. ''Aircraft Systems: Mechanical, Electrical and Avionics Subsystems Integration.'' New York: John Wiley and Sons, 2011. ISBN 1-119-96520-9.
* Niccoli, Riccardo. &quot;New Capabilities for Italy's Tornados&quot;. ''Air International'', Vol. 72, No. 6, pp.&amp;nbsp;26–29. ISSN 0306-5634.
* Niccoli, Riccardo. &quot;SAM Busters&quot;. ''Air International'', Vol. 76, No. 4, pp.&amp;nbsp;46–51. ISSN 0306-5634.
* Olsen, John Andreas. ''Global Air Power.'' Sterling, Virginia: Potomac Books, 2011. ISBN 1-59797-680-6.
* Pratt, Roger. ''Flight Control Systems: Practical Issues in Design and Implementation.'' London:Institution of Electrical Engineers, 2000. ISBN 0-85296-766-7.
* Peters, John E. [https://books.google.com/books?id=Z8ebyLhPeZ4C&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''European Contributions to Operation Allied Air Force: Implications for Transatlantic Cooperation''.] Washington/Arlington Virginia: Rand Corporation, 2001. ISBN 0-8330-3038-8.
* Rachow, Volker. &quot;Luftwaffe Tornado MLU&quot;. ''Air International'', Vol. 81, No. 6, December 2011, pp.&amp;nbsp;70–75. ISSN 0306-5634.
* Richardson, Doug. ''Tornado (Modern Fighting Aircraft, Vol. 10)''. New York: Prentice Hall Press, 1986. ISBN 0-13-925504-4.
* Richardson, Doug. ''High Tech Warfare.'' New York: Crescent Books, 1991. ISBN 0-517-06673-4.
* Ripley, Tim. [https://books.google.com/books?id=WPQFXHzP-YUC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Conflict in The Balkans, 1991–2000.''] Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 2001. ISBN 1-84176-290-3.
* Ripley, Tim. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/2003/2003%20-%202743.html &quot;World Air Forces 2003&quot;]. ''Flight International'', 25 November&amp;nbsp;– 1 December 2003, pp.&amp;nbsp;27–71.
* ''The Royal Air Force Handbook: The Definitive MoD Guide.'' London: Ministry of Defence, via reprint, Conway, 2006. ISBN 1-85753-384-4.
* {{Cite book|last=Scutts|first=Jerry|title=Postwar Aircraft (Osprey Modelling Manuals)|location= Oxford, UK|publisher=Osprey Publishing, 2000|isbn=978-1-84176-159-6|ref={{harvid|Scutts|2000}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Segell|first=Glen|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UU39P_O2Ey8C&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Wither or Dither: British Aerospace Collaborative Procurement with Europe|location=Staffordshire, UK|publisher=Glen Segell Publishers, 1997|isbn=1-901414-03-5|ref={{harvid|Segell|1997}}|date=1 January 1997}}
* Spick, Mike and William Green, Gordon Swanborough. ''Illustrated Anatomy of the World's Fighters.'' Zenith Imprint, 2001. ISBN 0-7603-1124-2.
* Szejnmann, Claus-Christian W. ''Rethinking History, Dictatorship and War: New Approaches and Interpretations.'' New York: Continuum International Publishing, 2009. ISBN 0-8264-4323-0.
* Taylor, John W. R. ''Jane's All The World's Aircraft.'' London: Jane's, 1975–1976. ISBN 0-354-00521-9.
* Taylor, Michael J.H. ''Flight International World Aircraft &amp; Systems Directory.'' London: Reed Business Information, 3rd Edition, 2001. ISBN 0-617-01289-X.
* Taylor, Michael J.H. ''Jane's Aviation Review.'' London: Jane's Information Group, 1987. ISBN 0-7106-0446-7.
* Wertheim, Eric. ''Naval Institute Guide to Combat Fleets of the World: Their Ships, Aircraft, and Systems.'' Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press, 2007. ISBN 1-59114-955-X.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Panavia Tornado}}
*[http://www.panavia.de Panavia Managing Tornado]
*[https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/ac/row/tornado.htm Tornado (BAe) on Fas.org]
*[http://www.aerospaceweb.org/aircraft/bomber/tornado_ids/ Panavia Tornado IDS Attack Bomber on Aerospaceweb.org]
*[http://www.tornado-data.com/ Panavia Tornado on Tornado-data.com]
*[http://callsigns.de/search.php?do=search&amp;searchstring=tornado&amp;pages=0 List of all active German Tornados]
*[http://www.deutsches-museum.de/flugwerft/sammlungen/strahlflugzeuge/tornado-ids/ German IDS Tornado 44+97 at the [[Deutsches Museum]] subsidiary Flugwerft [[Oberschleißheim]], Germany (DE)]
*[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1971/1971%20-%200523.html &quot;MRCA: Six Years After TSR.2&quot;] a 1971 ''Flight'' article
*[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1975/1975%20-%202039.html &quot;Supremacy&amp;nbsp;– Panavia MRCA&quot;] a 1975 advertisement in ''Flight''

{{British Aircraft Corporation aircraft}}
{{Alenia aircraft}}
{{Italian military aircraft}}
{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}
{{EngvarB|date=August 2014}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Alenia aircraft]]
[[Category:British Aerospace aircraft]]
[[Category:International attack aircraft 1970–1979]]
[[Category:Messerschmitt-Bölkow-Blohm aircraft]]
[[Category:Variable-sweep-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:1979 introductions]]
[[Category:Twinjets]]</text>
      <sha1>qczo0qejfw18ak0ekak17iru438baz5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
