<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>RAF West Ruislip</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28835801</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730978971</id>
      <parentid>724308074</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-22T03:16:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kayser Ahmad</username>
        <id>23541669</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>([[c:GR|GR]]) [[c:COM:FR|File renamed]]: [[File:Group logo.gif]] → [[File:Naval Forces Europe and Naval Forces Africa group logo.gif]] [[c:COM:FR#reasons|File renaming criterion #2]]: To change from a meaningless or ambiguous name to a name that desc...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20517">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2013}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox Military Structure
|name= Royal Air Force West Ruislip
|ensign=[[File:Ensign of the Royal Air Force.svg|90px]] 
|location= [[Ickenham]], [[Middlesex]]
|latd=51|latm=34|lats=7.58|latNS=N
|longd=000|longm=26|longs=15.80|longEW=W
|coordinates_region = GB-HIL
|coordinates_display = inline,title
|image =[[File:Naval Forces Europe and Naval Forces Africa group logo.gif|90px]]
|image2=[[File:RAF West Ruislip.png|200px]]
|caption2= Aerial view of RAF West Ruislip in 1945 - RAF Blenheim Crescent is to the north-east of the railway line
|type=  Maintenance and administrative
|code=
|built= 1917
|builder= American Construction Company
|materials=
|height=
|used=
|demolished= 2007
|condition= Demolished
|past_commanders= Lieutenant Commander H. Lee (first)
|occupants= No. 4 Maintenance Unit (RAF)&lt;br&gt;RAF Records Office&lt;br&gt;Navy Exchange of U.S. Naval Activities, United Kingdom&lt;br&gt;US Navy Morale, Welfare and Recreation Department
|battles=
|events=
}}
'''RAF West Ruislip''' was a [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] site, located in [[Ickenham]] within the [[London Borough of Hillingdon]]. The base was originally built as a depot for the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF), split by what is now the [[Chiltern Main Line]]. North of the railway was [[RAF Blenheim Crescent]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Planning&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hillingdon.gov.uk/media/pdf/2/k/site_alloc7_2.pdf |title=RAF West Ruislip |publisher=London Borough of Hillingdon |accessdate=27 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; which housed the RAF Records Office and the depot's original personnel accommodation.

The site was leased to the US Air Force in 1955, followed by the US Navy in 1975, eventually housing the Navy Exchange of the [[U.S. Naval Activities, United Kingdom]] command,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/facility/london.htm |title=London, UK |publisher=Global Security |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Navy's Morale, Welfare and Recreation Department.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 31&quot;/&gt;

Following a review of properties, the US Navy vacated the site in 2006 and it became surplus to the Ministry of Defence's requirements under [[Project MoDEL]]. The following year, initial plans for around 415 homes and a retirement home were approved by the London Borough of Hillingdon in July 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vsmestates.co.uk/downloads/130707_west_ruislip.pdf |title=London Borough of Hillingdon approves plans for the redevelopment of RAF West Ruislip |date=13 July 2007 |publisher=VSM Estates |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost all buildings were subsequently demolished to make way for the new development.&lt;ref name=&quot;VSM&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vsmestates.co.uk/schemes_west_ruislip.htm |title=RAF West Ruislip |publisher=VSM Estates |accessdate=14 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cala Homes bought the {{convert|21|acre|m2|adj=on}} site for £180m in November.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cala&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cala.co.uk/homes/news/newsitem.aspx?id=748 |title=Cala Acquires West Ruislip RAF Site For Record £180M Housing Development |date=14 December 2007 |publisher=Cala Homes |accessdate=14 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Establishment===
[[File:Fairlight House US Navy Base Commander MWR at RAF West Ruislip 2.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Fairlight House building|Fairlight House, built in 1914]]
The land upon which the site was developed was originally owned by Edward Hilliard. It was chosen in March 1915 by Wing Commander T. O. Lyons of the [[Air Ministry]] to house the Ordnance Aircraft Stores Depot from Farnborough, although a decision was made instead to establish the depot in Didcot, beside the existing buildings there. In 1917, the Ruislip site was revisited, and on 3 July was selected to house a depot for the [[Royal Flying Corps]], under a military acquisition order. The close proximity to the Great Western and Metropolitan Railways made it ideal for the purpose.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, pp.5—6&lt;/ref&gt;

Additional construction costs meant the final total was £736,000, up from an original estimate of £235,000. The need for heating brought with it the requirement for boiler houses, plus additional foundations which were needed for the buildings to the north of the railway. Lieutenant J.G.N. Clifts of the [[Royal Engineers]] created the design for the site and buildings, and the contractor involved was a U.S. Army civil engineering company, appearing on records as American Construction Company. A temporary railway siding was created to aid in the delivery of building supplies. By 13 December 1918, several sheds had been completed, as were the Officers' Mess, sleeping quarters and the [[NAAFI#History|Navy and Army Canteen Board]].&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, pp.7—8&lt;/ref&gt;

Between May and July 1918, military stores from [[White City, London|White City]], [[Wormwood Scrubs]] and [[Baker Street]] were moved to the site, with items kept in the completed sheds. A shortage of bricks in October meant the widening of the bridge over the railway was delayed, as was the construction of the railway line into the site.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.8&lt;/ref&gt;

===Inter-war years===
[[File:NEX at US Navy MWR RAF West Ruislip.jpg|thumb|Shed No.1 was the only original storage shed on the site]]
The Air Ministry wrote to the land surveyors employed by Edward Hilliard on 3 September 1919 to announce they wished to buy the land to allow for its permanent use by the RAF. Hilliard did not accept the initial offer of £5,900, but agreed to sell by the eventual deadline of 17 January 1920, receiving the sum of £6,350. A resident of the land, Mrs Saitch of Home Farm, had her tenancy cancelled on 29 September and was paid compensation by the military until 25 March 1921, although the authorities did not believe her worthy.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.10&lt;/ref&gt;

Fairlight House, built in 1914, was included within the site and later became the residence of the Commander of US Naval Activities, United Kingdom. RAF Records were also based at the site along with the Maintenance Unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowlt&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Ickenham And Harefield Past |last=Bowlt |first=Eileen M. |year=1996 |publisher=Historical Publications |location=London |isbn=0-948667-36-2 |pages=137–138}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Great Western Railway, now the Chiltern Main Line, ran through the site, separating the regimental buildings to the north from the depot buildings to the south.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.6&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RAF Records Office Ruislip 1926.jpg|thumb|left|The RAF Records Office in 1926]]
A &quot;Homice Scheme&quot; was established at all RAF stations in 1921, to prepare for cases of civil disturbance. To prepare, the fences around the depot belonging to the nearby railway company were replaced by a non-climable variety. An RAF guard made up of a sergeant, corporal, acting corporal and twenty three airmen was formed to protect the site. During the rest of the decade, the [[Metropolitan Police]] provided a guard of eleven constables, eight of whom were housed in the sick bay. The remaining three were married, and were given their own houses in Park Road in [[Uxbridge]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 2007, p.13&quot;&gt;Francis 2007, p.13&lt;/ref&gt;

The Air Ministry placed an order in 1922 for the closure of the public footpath that ran through the site, providing £750 for the maintenance of nearby Green Lane where the path originated. The eventual order, dated 15 October 1924, replaced two previous orders from 1922 and 1923 which had required a replacement route, though no such route was established.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.12&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1924, the Air Ministry officially separated the two sites administratively, so that the depot site and accommodation site (RAF Blenheim Crescent) were considered two separate RAF stations. Between 1920 and 1939, the original accommodation buildings in the north of the site were replaced by new married quarters.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.29&lt;/ref&gt;

The RAF established the Apprentice Clerks Scheme at the Records Office in October 1925, after an earlier trial in 1921 had concluded successfully. Under the scheme, apprentices were trained in general administrative and accounting duties, practising shorthand typing in the depot while also acting as messengers in the Records Office. A total of 2,080 apprentices passed through the scheme between 1925 and 1942.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rafadappassn.org/ruislip.html |title=Royal Air Force Ruislip |date= |publisher=Royal Air Force Administrative Apprentice Association |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The station commander, [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]] Lyons died in his quarters on 1 February 1926 and was buried in the churchyard of [[St Giles' Church, Ickenham|St Giles' Church]] on 4 February. His funeral was attended by all personnel from the depot, the Records Office and the [[Central Band of the RAF]]. He was succeeded by Wing Commander F. H. Kirby.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 2007, p.13&quot;/&gt;

===Second World War===
[[File:NEX warehouse. US Navy MWR at RAF West Ruislip.jpg|thumb|Interior of Shed No. 1]]
Under the newly formed [[RAF Maintenance Command]], the depot became part of No. 40 Group RAF (Equipment) in 1939 as [[No. 4 Maintenance Unit RAF]], under the overall command of Air Commodore R. W. Thomas.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.14&lt;/ref&gt;

The depot became responsible for the provision and maintenance of engines for the [[RAF Advanced Air Striking Force|Advanced Air Striking Force]]. These were then sent to [[Hartlebury]] and [[Quedgeley]] to be despatched to units. Ammunition was also prepared and sent to squadrons in action.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.17&lt;/ref&gt;

[[No. 71 Maintenance Unit RAF]] in [[Slough]] came under control of the Ruislip depot in January 1941. The increase in personnel lead to an extension of the station canteen in May. Additionally, a [[Navy, Army and Air Force Institutes]] (NAAFI) canteen was built on the RAF Blenheim Crescent site on 6 May.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.19&lt;/ref&gt; In order to protect it from potential enemy bombing, the majority of the Records Office was moved to a temporary base in Gloucester on 10 May.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 30&quot;&gt;Francis 2007, p.30&lt;/ref&gt;

Later in the war, No. 4 Maintenance Unit became involved with radio and [[Radio Direction Finding|RDF]] preparations for the [[D-Day landings]]. It also produced waterproof radar equipment for use by the US Air Force's 2nd Tactical Air Force in 1944 which could be used even when submerged under {{convert|6|ft}} of water.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.23&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

===Post-war years===
[[File:American Forces Church RAF West Ruislip.jpg|thumb|left|The American Forces chapel]]
Following the end of the war, the depot was responsible for the repair of vehicles and the conversion of aircrew coaches. Aircraft engines, propellers and radar equipment also continued to be repaired on the site,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowlt&quot;/&gt; as were vehicles from the US Air Force's [[Third Air Force]] base at nearby [[RAF South Ruislip]] which began to be serviced from April 1949. The American vehicles were maintained in a dedicated shed, No. 5.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.25&lt;/ref&gt;

The remaining Records Office operation closed at Ruislip on 1 May 1951, having been run as a subsidiary of the Gloucester office since the previous year. A lack of available housing in the Gloucester area meant the closure was not completed until 16 May 1952. It was proposed in April of that year to convert the base to an Air Ministry Unit and transfer the operations of [[RAF West Drayton]] to it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 30&quot;/&gt;

On 1 August 1951, the Medical Survey Office was formed on the station as a unit of [[RAF Home Command]]. The office was responsible for all medical records, which were transferred from the RAF Records Office. It was moved to another building in November but was relocated to [[RAF Innsworth]] on 16 May 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 31&quot;/&gt;

[[File:The Movie Theater US Navy MWR at RAF West Ruislip.jpg|thumb|The station cinema screen room]]
The station was passed to the US Air Force Third Air Force on 1 December 1955, to enable the consolidation of facilities at several sites in the country into a single location. On 1 October 1962, the American 7500th Air Base Group was relocated to RAF West Ruislip from RAF South Ruislip. After the US Air Force decided to close RAF South Ruislip and move their headquarters to [[RAF Mildenhall]] in 1972, 77 civilian members of staff at West Ruislip were made redundant.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, pp.27—28&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1958 and 1960, the station's chapel was built by Brandt O'Dell. The building incorporated a [[nave]] with seating space for 350 people, and connecting wings to the hall and [[narthex]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 2007, p.67&quot;&gt;Francis 2007, p.67&lt;/ref&gt; In 1962, the gymnasium was built on the site.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.71&lt;/ref&gt;

The US Navy leased the site in December 1975 and constructed additional facilities for personnel and their families, including a bar,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.andythornton.com/en-UK/portfolio_items/interior-fit-out/bars/34-crown-anchor |title=Crown &amp; Anchor |date= |publisher=Andy Thornton |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; filling station, post office, cinema, chapel, school, baseball diamond and a medical and dental centre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowlt&quot;/&gt; These came under the Morale, Welfare and Recreation Department.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 31&quot;&gt;Francis 2007, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;

A large area of the site was demolished in the late 1980s for a large residential development named &quot;Brackenbury Village&quot;. Housing was shared between personnel and British families.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowlt&quot;/&gt; The Children's Welfare and Family Services Centre was built in 1988 by Kier Construction. The building incorporated separate sections for children and families.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.63&lt;/ref&gt; Among other recreational facilities, two squash courts were built in 1989,&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.73&lt;/ref&gt; and a baseball diamond and field house were built in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.77&lt;/ref&gt; Dugouts were also built nearby the following year.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.75&lt;/ref&gt;

==Closure and redevelopment==
[[File:The American Flag is lowered for the final time at RAF West Ruislip, United Kingdom.jpg|thumb|left|The American flag and RAF Ensign are lowered during the closure ceremony]]
Following a review of facilities, the US Navy elected to vacate the West Ruislip site, beginning on 30 June 2006. The final chapel service had been held on 5 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 2007, p.67&quot;/&gt; Many operations returned to the United States, as part of a plan to save $1 million each year. Staff redundancies involved 7 US service personnel, 55 civilian staff from the US Department of Defence and 95 British civilian staff.&lt;ref&gt;Francis 2007, p.28&lt;/ref&gt; The base closed during a ceremony on 28 September, in which the American flag and [[Royal Air Force Ensign]] were lowered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.mil/view_single.asp?id=39539 |title=Eye on the fleet |date=28 September 2006 |publisher=Navy News Service |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All personnel from the Navy Exchange had already transferred to [[Naval Support Activity Naples|new facilities in Naples]], [[Italy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USNavy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=31833 |title=Commander, Naval Activities, United Kingdom Disestablished |date=14 September 2007 |publisher=Commander, Navy Region Europe Public Affairs |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. Naval Activities, United Kingdom was officially stood down on 14 September 2007 at a ceremony at [[RAF Daws Hill]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USNavy&quot;/&gt;

In late 2007, all buildings on the site excluding the elementary school were demolished. RAF Blenheim Crescent was not included in the demolition works.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francis 31&quot;/&gt; The Brackenbury Village housing was retained as it was separate from the military buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;VSM&quot;/&gt; Cala Homes purchased the {{convert|21|acre|m2|adj=on}} site for a £180m development in November 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cala&quot;/&gt; Explore Living Thames Valley later bought a {{convert|5.5|acre|m2|adj=on}} plot from Cala Homes in February 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.exploreliving.co.uk/news/thames-valley-region-acquire-raf-west-ruislip-site-in-ickenham |title=Thames Valley Region Acquire RAF West Ruislip Site In Ickenham |date=26 March 2008 |publisher=Explore Living |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Scale Model of Ickenham Park.jpg|thumb|Scale model of the Ickenham Park development]]
Outline planning permission was granted by the London Borough of Hillingdon in January 2009 despite local opposition to some buildings having flat roofs. Up to 50% of the new homes will be social housing. The plan included 415 homes, with an 80-bed care home; the largest buildings will be six storeys high.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Row over roof shapes at 500-home RAF scheme |last=Coombs |first=Dan |url=http://www.uxbridgegazette.co.uk/west-london-news/local-uxbridge-news/2009/01/07/row-over-roof-shapes-at-500-home-raf-scheme-113046-22621244/ |newspaper=Uxbridge Gazette |date=7 January 2009 |accessdate=28 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2010, Cala Homes sought permission from the London Borough of Hillingdon to sell the first 30 completed homes before completing all highway work on the site in order to keep the development financially viable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Cash flow problems for RAF West Ruislip developers |last=Coombs |first=Dan |url=http://hillingdon.uxbridgegazette.co.uk/2010/09/cash-flow-problems-for-raf-wes.html |newspaper=Uxbridge Gazette |date=1 September 2010 |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By September 2011, around 50 of the first 100 homes had been sold, with an additional 30 houses under construction. The largest building under construction, Cottesmore House, was completed in October 2011. The final homes on the Ickenham Park development were completed during 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ickenhamchurchnews.co.uk/thismonth/page2.htm |title=Welcome to Ickenham! |date=September 2011 |publisher=Ickenham Church News |accessdate=28 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[McCarthy &amp; Stone]] tailored care living development received planning permission in May 2014, and is due to open in early 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mccarthyandstone.co.uk/retirement-properties-for-sale/ickenham-court-uxbridge/ |title=Ickenham Court |date=11 June 2014 |publisher=McCarthy &amp; Stone |accessdate=11 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2014, the Eden Academy Trust began a public consultation on reopening the former elementary school as a [[Free school (England)|free]] [[special school]] in January 2015. Under the plans, it would be refurbished and open to 32 pupils, and would be gradually expanded to eventually have a full intake of 140 pupils by September 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=New special free school proposed for youngsters in Ickenham |last=Drewett |first=Zoe |url=http://www.getwestlondon.co.uk/news/local-news/new-special-free-school-proposed-7746709 |newspaper=Uxbridge Gazette |date=10 September 2014 |accessdate=14 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school, named Pentland Field School, opened to its first intake of pupils on 12 January 2015, and was officially reopened by the [[Permanent Secretary]] for the [[Department for Education]], Chris Wormald.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Cooper|first1=Goolistan|title=Education chief opens new Ickenham special needs school|url=http://www.getwestlondon.co.uk/news/west-london-news/education-chief-opens-new-ickenham-8702093|accessdate=7 September 2015|work=Uxbridge Gazette|date=23 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[West Ruislip station]] for adjacent tube and railway station
* [[List of former Royal Air Force stations]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
* Francis, Paul. (2007) ''MoDEL RAF West Ruislip. Historical Building Survey''. London: VSM Estates

==External links==
{{Commons category|RAF West Ruislip}}
* [http://www.flickr.com/photos/routemaster/sets/72157604735012332/ Photographs of the facilities at RAF West Ruislip]
* [http://www.sheppardrobson.com/projects/page.cfm?projectID=100123 Sheppard Robson redevelopment proposal]
* [http://westruislipusnavychapel.com/ West Ruislip Navy Chapel]
* [http://londoncentral.org/classreps/77co/wrelemhukka1.htm West Ruislip Elementary School]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Raf West Ruislip}}
[[Category:Closed facilities of the United States Navy]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force stations in London|West Ruislip]]
[[Category:History of Hillingdon]]
[[Category:Former buildings and structures in Hillingdon]]
[[Category:Military history of Middlesex|West Ruislip]]</text>
      <sha1>0x99zp8b6w8vtdfog6e2n6sfeg1epw9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
