<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Raid on Manila (1798)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46799462</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735413248</id>
      <parentid>729703027</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-20T15:07:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Internet Archive]] (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24427">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Raid on Manila
|partof=the [[French Revolutionary Wars]]
|image=&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative&quot;&gt;[[File:BlankMap-MetroManila.png|250px]]{{Image label|x=0.255|y=1.100|scale=250|text=[[File:Red pog.svg|8px|Action]]}}&lt;/div&gt;
|caption=Map of modern Manila. Approximate site of battle marked in red.
|date=January 1798
|place=[[Manila]], [[Spanish Philippines]]
|result=British victory at Manila; Spanish victory at Zamboanga
|combatant1={{flagcountry|Kingdom of Great Britain}}
|combatant2={{flagicon|Spain}} [[Enlightenment in Spain|Spain]]
|commander1=Captain [[Edward Cooke (Royal Navy officer)|Edward Cooke]]
|commander2=Rear-Admiral [[Ignacio Maria de Álava y Sáenz de Navarrete|Ignacio Maria de Álava]]
|strength1=Frigates [[HMS Sybille (1794)|HMS ''Sybille'']] and [[HMS Fox (1780)|HMS ''Fox'']]
|strength2=Defences of Manila
|casualties1=None at Manila; 6 killed, 16 wounded and a boat sunk at Zamboanga
|casualties2=3 [[gunboats]] captured at Manila; 1 killed and 4 wounded at Zamboanga
}}
{{Campaignbox French Revolutionary Wars: Anglo-Spanish War (1796)}}
{{coord|14|31|N|120|56|E|display=title|type:event}}{{East Indies theatre of the French Revolutionary Wars}}

The '''Raid on Manila''' of January 1798 was a [[Royal Navy]] [[false flag]] military operation during the [[French Revolutionary Wars]] intended to scout the strength of the defences of [[Manila]], capital of the [[Spanish Philippines]], capture a [[Manila galleon]] and assess the condition of the [[Spanish Navy]] squadron maintained in the port. [[Enlightenment in Spain|Spain]] had transformed from an ally of [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]] in the [[War of the First Coalition]] into an enemy in 1796.  Thus the presence of a powerful Spanish squadron at Manila posed a threat to the China Fleet, an annual convoy of [[East Indiaman]] merchant ships from [[Macau]] in [[Qing Dynasty]] [[China]] to Britain, which was of vital economic importance to Britain. So severe was this threat that a major invasion of the Spanish Philippines had been planned from [[British India]] during 1797, but had been called off following the [[Treaty of Campo Formio]] in Europe and the possibility of a major war in India between the British [[East India Company]] and the [[Kingdom of Mysore]].

To ensure the safety of the merchant ships gathering at Macau in the winter of 1797–98, the British commander in the East Indies, Rear-Admiral [[Peter Rainier, junior|Peter Rainier]], sent a convoy to China escorted by the [[frigates]] [[HMS Sybille (1794)|HMS ''Sybille'']] and [[HMS Fox (1780)|HMS ''Fox'']] and commanded by Captain [[Edward Cooke (Royal Navy officer)|Edward Cooke]]. After completing his mission Cooke decided to investigate the state of readiness of Spanish forces in Manila himself. He was also intrigued by reports that a ship carrying treasure was due to sail from Manila, which would make a valuable prize. Sailing in ''Sybille'' and accompanied by Captain [[Pulteney Malcolm]] in ''Fox'', Cooke reached the Spanish capital on 13 January 1798.

Anchored in [[Manila Bay]], Cooke pretended that his ships were French vessels and successfully lured successive boatloads of Spanish officials aboard, taking them [[prisoner of war|prisoner]] in turn. Once he had determined from his captives the state of defences in Manila, that the treasure ship had been unloaded at [[Cavite]] and that the Spanish squadron was undergoing extensive repairs and thus unavailable for operations, he sent a raiding party against a squadron of gunboats in the mouth of the [[Pasig River]]. Capturing the gunboats in a bloodless attack, Cooke then released his prisoners and sailed southwards, unsuccessfully assaulting [[Zamboanga (province)|Zamboanga]] before returning to Macau.

==Background==
In 1796, after three years of the [[French Revolutionary Wars]], [[Enlightenment in Spain|Spain]] and the [[First French Republic|French Republic]] signed the [[Second Treaty of San Ildefonso|Treaty of San Ildefonso]]. The secret terms of this treaty required Spain to renounce its alliance with [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]] and subsequently to declare war on its former ally.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=104}} In the East Indies this shift of political allegiance meant that the dominant British forces in the region were faced with the threat of attack from the [[Spanish Philippines]] to the east. Britain dominated the East Indies in 1796, controlling the trade routes through the [[Indian Ocean]] from the ports of [[Bombay]], [[Madras]] and [[Calcutta]].{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=13}} [[Dutch Ceylon]], the [[Dutch Cape Colony]] and parts of the [[Dutch East Indies]] had been captured in 1795, and the French presence in the region had been confined to [[Isle de France (Mauritius)|Île de France]] and a few subsidiary islands in the Western Indian Ocean.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=98}}

Some of the most important trade routes began at [[Guangzhou|Canton]] and [[Macau]] in [[Qing Dynasty]] [[China]]. Early in each year a large convoy known as the &quot;China Fleet&quot;, composed of large [[East Indiaman]] merchant ships in the employ of the British [[East India Company]], sailed westwards to Europe from Macau laden with [[tea]] and other commercial cargo. This convoy was economically significant to Britain: one convoy in 1804 was valued at over £8 million (the equivalent of £{{Formatnum:{{Inflation|UK|8000000|1804|r=-8}}|0}} as of {{CURRENTYEAR}}).{{Inflation-fn|UK}}&lt;ref name= &quot;RG32&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1= Gardiner |first1=Robert, ed | last2= Woodman|first2=Richard  |authorlink = | year = 2001 | origyear = 1998 | chapter = | title = The Victory of Seapower | publisher = Caxton Editions |location=London, England | isbn = 1-84067-359-1 |page=32}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1797 the convoy had been attacked by the French squadron in the East Indies, comprising six [[frigates]] commanded by [[Contre-amiral]] [[Pierre César Charles de Sercey]]. In the ensuing [[Bali Strait Incident]] the commander deceived Sercey into believing that the unescorted convoy contained disguised [[ships of the line]] and the French admiral retreated, only learning of his error on his return to Île de France.{{sfn|James|2002|page=79}} There was considerable concern in India that Sercey might try again in 1798, or that the Spanish, who maintained a powerful squadron at [[Cavite]], might make an attempt of their own.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=137}}

Rainier's initial impulse on learning in November 1796 of the impending declaration of war between Britain and Spain was to draw up plans for a major invasion of the Philippines, centred on Manila in repetition of the successful British [[Battle of Manila (1762)|capture of Manila]] in 1762. Co-operating with the [[Governor-General of India]] [[John Shore, 1st Baron Teignmouth|Sir John Shore]] and Colonel [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Arthur Welleley]] among others, a substantial naval and military forces were earmarked for the operation which was in the advance planning stages,{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=117}} when unexpected news arrived in India in August 1797 announcing the [[Treaty of Campo Formio]] which brought the [[War of the First Coalition]] to an end.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=119}}  Britain now faced France and Spain alone, while emissaries from the [[Tipu Sultan]] of the [[Kingdom of Mysore]], an old opponent of Britain in Southern India, were seeking French assistance with a renewed outbreak of hostilities. The resources planned for the operation against Manila were therefore retained in India and the operation cancelled,{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=119}} but the protection of the China Fleet was still essential and Rainier diverted some of his squadron eastwards to China.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=137}}

A number of merchant ships had gathered at Bombay in the spring of 1797 in preparation for the trip to Macau to load trade goods and join the China Fleet. To escort this force, Rainier provided the 40-gun [[frigate]] [[HMS Sybille (1794)|HMS ''Sybille'']], captured from the French at the [[Battle of Mykonos]] in 1794,{{sfn|Clowes|1997|page=486}} and the 50-gun [[HMS Centurion (1774)|HMS ''Centurion'']], which sailed with the convoy in July, taking passage through the [[Straits of Malacca]], joined there by the ships of the line [[HMS Victorious (1785)|HMS ''Victorious'']] and [[HMS Trident (1768)|HMS ''Trident'']] and the 32-gun frigate [[HMS Fox (1780)|HMS ''Fox'']] under  Captain [[Pulteney Malcolm]] for the final voyage to Macau. The convoy arrived without incident on 13 December 1797, although the crews had been substantially weakened by tropical illnesses.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=137}}

==Cooke's raids==

===Reconnaissance of Manilla===
With his convoy safely at anchor in Macau and the China Fleet several weeks from sailing, Cooke decided to reconnoitre Manila and make observations on the port and the Spanish squadron based there.{{sfn|James|2002|page=211}} As an added motivation, rumours in Macau suggested that the annual [[Manila galleon]] was due to arrive. This ship brought up to two million Spanish silver [[Spanish dollars|dollars]] from [[Acapulco]] across the [[Pacific Ocean]] stopping at [[Guam]] on its way to Manila. Depositing its dollars in the Philippines, the ship then loaded trade goods from the East Indies for the return journey to [[New Spain]].{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=49}}  This round trip was essential to the maintenance of the Spanish Empire in the East Indies, which operated at an enormous financial loss only mitigated by the substantial subsidy from New Spain.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=42}} Spanish dollars were the accepted currency across most of the East Indies, and disruption of this financial system could have profound effects on regional trade; but British sailors had nevertheless been attacking the Manila galleons since [[Thomas Cavendish]] in 1587.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=43}}

Leaving the heavier warships at Macau, Cooke sailed on 5 January 1798 only with ''Sybille'' and ''Fox'', the latter carrying a Mr. Bernard, an experienced linguist.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=48}}  Passing [[Luzon]], Cooke's ships encountered a small Spanish merchant vessel, which was lured towards the frigates, which were flying [[French tricolors]].{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=49}} Seizing the Spanish vessel, Cooke closely questioned the captain and learned that most of the Spanish squadron in Manila were undergoing extensive repairs at Cavite and were unfit to sail. Cooke rewarded the captain by releasing his vessel with its cargo intact, although he did remove 3,900 silver dollars.{{sfn|James|2002|page=211}} The Spanish squadron had suffered badly in a [[typhoon]] in April 1797 and much of the damage had still not been repaired by the time Cooke's small squadron arrived off Manila.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=119}} Cooke had taken precautions to disguise his ships as French vessels, modelling ''Sybille'' on the powerful 40-gun [[French frigate Forte (1794)|''Forte'']] and ''Fox'' on the smaller [[French frigate Prudente (1790)|''Prudente'']].{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=49}}

===Dinner on ''Sybille''===
Late in the afternoon of 13 January 1798, ''Sybille'' and ''Fox'' arrived in [[Manila Bay]], slipping unchallenged past the fortress of [[Corregidor]] and then sailing across the bay on the morning of 14 January, anchoring between Manila and Cavite.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=50}} From his vantage point Cooke could see the Spanish squadron dismasted and under repair in Cavite, the ships of the line [[Spanish ship San Pedro|''San Pedro'']], [[Spanish ship Europa|''Europa'']] and [[Spanish ship Montañés (1794)|''Montañés'']] and the frigates [[Spanish ship Maria de la Cabeya|''Maria de la Cabeya'']] and [[Spanish ship Luisa|''Luisa'']] in dock and unfit for action.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=139}} To Cooke's disappointment he could also see the Manila galleon, ''Marquesetta'' being unloaded at the Cavite docks and another valuable merchant ship ''Rey Carlos'' aground in the harbour.{{sfn|James|2002|page=213}} The Spanish had learned only shortly before Cooke's arrival that the British frigate [[HMS Resistance (1782)|HMS ''Resistance'']] under Captain Edward Pakenham was in Philippine waters and had decided to remove the valuable cargo from the treasure ship rather than risk an attack.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=138}}

''Fox'' was the first British ship into the anchorage, and was consequently approached by the [[Guard ship|guardboat]], whose crew came aboard. Malcolm, like Cooke, spoke [[French language|French]] fluently and with Bernard translating was able to persuade the officer in charge that the new arrivals were ''Forte'' and ''Prudente'' seeking supplies and Spanish reinforcements for [[commerce raiding]] operations.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=51}} The officer offered supplies but cautioned that none of the Spanish ships would be in a position to sail until March at the earliest.{{sfn|James|2002|page=212}} Cooke then joined the party on the deck of ''Fox'', claiming to be Commodore Latour, a French officer who, unknown to the Spanish, had been killed in the [[Action of 9 September 1796]] off Sumatra.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=52}} The Spanish officer was now completely convinced by the ruse, which had been augmented by fake French uniforms. Inviting the visitor below decks, Cooke then passed [[wine]] around and together they drank a series of [[Toast (honor)|toasts]], including &quot;the downfall of England&quot;.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=138}}

For an hour the officers drank, Malcolm and Cooke learning detailed information about the state of the defences and squadron in the Philippines, until a second boat pulled alongside ''Fox'' containing more officers keen to greet the French arrivals. This vessel was the personal [[barge]] of the Spanish commander at Cavite, Rear-Admiral Don [[Ignacio Maria de Álava y Sáenz de Navarrete|Ignacio María de Álava]], who was not aboard, but who sent a message via an aide in a third boat.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=52}} Each time, the officers were escorted below to join the festivities whereupon their crews were seized at gunpoint and taken below decks as [[prisoners of war]].{{sfn|James|2002|page=212}} In Malcolm's cabin, the captured officers were informed of their situation, promised release before the British frigates sailed, and offered more wine.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=52}} The crew of ''Fox'' meanwhile forced the captured Spanish sailors to strip and donned their clothing. Climbing into the Spanish boats this party rowed for the mouth of the nearby [[Pasig River]], where they had learned that three heavy gunboats were moored. Taking the crews by surprise, the British [[naval boarding|boarding parties]] drove off the Spanish without a fight and brought all three boats alongside ''Fox''. These vessels normally carried crews of thirty and were well-armed, one with a [[32-pounder long gun]] and two with [[24-pounder long gun]]s, each supplemented by four [[swivel guns]].{{sfn|James|2002|page=213}}

The harbour captain reached ''Fox'' shortly afterwards, furious at the seizure of the gunboats and demanding they be returned. Malcolm received him with a tirade of near incomprehensible French and brought him to join the other captured officers in his cabin, while the boat's crew were imprisoned below decks.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=52}} Shortly afterwards, at 16:00, Cooke and Malcolm hosted a large dinner for their officer captives and sent food and [[grog]] to the crew, the total number of Spanish sailors on ''Fox'' now numbering approximately 200. Once the meal was finished, Cooke allowed all of the captives to return to their boats and row for shore without the conditions of [[parole]], although he retained the captured gunboats.{{sfn|James|2002|page=214}}

===Zamboanga===
Cooke led his small squadron past Corregidor on 15 January and turned south. Four days later in a storm one of the gunboats broke its tow line and was never seen again, lost with its twelve crew.{{sfn|James|2002|page=214}}  The frigates subsequently scouted [[Mindanao]] before reaching [[Zamboanga City|Zamboanga]] on 22 January. There Cooke raised Spanish colours in an attempt to deceive the authorities into supplying food and water to his squadron but ''Sybille'' grounded on a sandbank at the entrance to the port which raised the suspicions of a guardboat sent by the governor of Zamboanga, Raymundo Español.{{sfn|James|2002|page=215}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamboanga&quot;&gt;''[http://hemerotecadigital.bne.es/issue.vm?id=0003153721&amp;page=154&amp;search=zamboanga&amp;lang=es Recuerdos de un hecho glorioso]'', ''Por esos mundos'', No 161, June 1908, p. VIII–X.&lt;/ref&gt; The captain of the Spanish boat asked the British ships the names of their captains, and on receiving no answer but a volley of rifle fire, he put the town on alert.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamboanga&quot;/&gt; With the defenders forewarned, Cooke abandoned his ruse and after refloating ''Sybille'' the following morning, ordered a bombardment of the fort protecting the harbour. This had little effect, though later the Spanish recovered at least 450 [[round shot|cannonballs]] from different calibers,&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamboanga&quot;/&gt; and Malcolm then attempted an [[amphibious landing]] in order to storm the landward side of the fort. The boats came under heavy fire, one smashed by a cannonball, killing two and wounding four. Another boat grounded on a sandbar and became stuck; so with his force in disarray, as 250 villagers armed with lances ambushed and drove the British from the beach,&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamboanga&quot;/&gt; Malcolm called off the operation. After exchanging shot for an hour both frigates cut their anchor cables and retreated out of range, with two dead and one wounded on ''Sybille'' and eight wounded on ''Fox'', in addition to those lost in the boats.{{sfn|James|2002|page=216}} The defenders lost a single man killed and 4 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamboanga&quot;/&gt;

With his frigates now requiring repairs, Cooke withdraw half a league from Zamboanga and spent three days refitting the masts and rigging of the ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamboanga&quot;/&gt; Then he sailed north, scuttling the two remaining gunboats as he did not believe they would survive the return journey to [[Guangzhou|Canton]].{{sfn|James|2002|page=216}} Four days later, on 27 January the squadron halted at a village named &quot;Pullock&quot; in the north of the [[Sultanate of Maguindanao]] to collect fresh water. On the beach a boat party from ''Sybille'' was set upon by [[Lumad peoples|Lumad tribesmen]]. Two were killed and nine others taken captive and dragged into the forest before rescuers could arrive. Cooke complained to [[Sultan Kibab Sahriyal]] at [[Cotabato City|Kuta Wato]] and the captured sailors were eventually recovered, although not before ''Sybille'' and ''Fox'' had sailed for China to escort the merchant convoy back to India.{{sfn|James|2002|page=216}}

==Aftermath==
Cooke's opportunistic diversion had determined that the Spanish forces in the Philippines posed no immediate threat, although the mission had cost 18 lives: Admiral Rainier later expressed his satisfaction with the outcome in a letter to the [[Admiralty]].{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=139}}  More might have been achieved with reinforcements: Historian [[C. Northcote Parkinson]] suggests that had Cooke's squadron united with ''Resistance'' together they may have been able to destroy the disarmed Spanish warships at Cavite. He also notes however that in this scenario Pakenham would have been commanding officer, a man with considerably less imagination and guile than Cooke.{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=138}} Historian [[Richard Woodman]] was critical of the mission, considering the operation to have &quot;no glorious outcome&quot; and citing the failure to capture the treasure ships as its greatest short-coming.{{sfn|Woodman|2001|page=114}}

The 1798 China Fleet sailed without further incident. During the ensuing year ''Resistance'' was destroyed by an accidental explosion in July in the [[Bangka Strait]],{{sfn|Grocott|2002|page=58}} and the majority of Rainier's forces were focused on disrupting the French occupation of [[Suez]] in the [[Red Sea]].{{sfn|Parkinson|1954|page=.147}} This diversion of British resources created gaps in the coverage in merchant shipping and Sercey was able to send the frigate [[French frigate Preneuse (1795)|''Preneuse'']] and corvette [[French corvette Brûle-Gueule (1794)|''Brûle-Gueule'']] to Manila late in the year to join the repaired Spanish squadron. At the beginning of February 1799, this combined force sailed to Macau, taking the British defences by surprise. The British commander Captain [[William Hargood]] counterattacked, advancing on the Franco-Spanish force which retreated during the day and disappeared under cover of darkness that evening in the [[Wanshan Archipelago]].{{sfn|Gardiner|Woodman|2001|page=161}} The combined squadron then dispersed and the China Fleet was not attacked again until the [[Battle of Pulo Aura]] in 1804, at which a French squadron was again driven off in confusion.&lt;ref name= &quot;RG32&quot;/&gt; The frigates Cooke had mimicked, ''Forte'' and ''Prudente'' were sent to operate independently against British trade in the Indian Ocean in early 1799. ''Prudente'' was captured by [[HMS Daedalus (1780)|HMS ''Daedalus'']] at the [[Action of 9 February 1799 (South Africa)|Action of 9 February 1799]] near Southern Africa,{{sfn|James|2002|page=319}} and ''Forte'' was intercepted by HMS ''Sybille'' under Cooke on 28 February near [[Balasore]] in [[Bengal]]. In the [[Action of 28 February 1799|ensuing battle]] ''Forte'' was captured but Cooke mortally wounded, dying on 25 May.{{sfn|Henderson|1994|page=60}}

==Citations==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book | last = Clowes | first = William Laird | authorlink = William Laird Clowes | year = 1997 | origyear= 1900 | chapter =  | title = The Royal Navy, A History from the Earliest Times to 1900, Volume IV | publisher = Chatham Publishing | location = London |url=https://archive.org/stream/royalnavy07clow/royalnavy07clow_djvu.txt | isbn = 1-86176-013-2 |ref=harv}} at [[Internet Archive]]
* {{cite book | last1= Gardiner |first1=Robert, ed | last2= Woodman|first2=Richard | authorlink = | year = 2001 | origyear= 1996 | chapter = | title =Nelson Against Napoleon: from the Nile to Copenhagen, 1798–1801 |location=London, England |publisher=Chatham Pub. in association with the [[National Maritime Museum]], Caxton Editions| isbn = 1-86176-026-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last1= Gardiner |first1=Robert, ed | last2= Woodman|first2=Richard | authorlink = | year = 2001 | origyear = 1998 | chapter = | title = The Victory of Seapower |publisher = Caxton Editions | location=London, England | isbn = 1-84067-359-1 }}
* {{cite book | last = Grocott | first = Terence | authorlink =  | year=2002 |origyear=1997 | chapter =  | title =Shipwrecks of the Revolutionary &amp; Napoleonic Era |publisher=Caxton Editions | location=London, England  | isbn = 1-84067-164-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Henderson | first = James, CBE | authorlink = |year=1994 |origyear=1970 | chapter = | title = The Frigates | publisher = Leo Cooper | location = London | isbn = 0-85052-432-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = James | first = William | authorlink = William James (naval historian) | year = 2002 | origyear= 1827 | chapter =  | title = The Naval History of Great Britain, Volume 2, 1797–1799 | publisher = Conway Maritime Press |location=London, England | isbn = 0-85177-906-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Parkinson | first = C. Northcote | authorlink = C. Northcote Parkinson | year = 1954 | origyear =  | chapter =  | title = War in the Eastern Seas, 1793 – 1815 | publisher = George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd. |location=London, England | isbn =  |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Woodman | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Woodman | year = 2001 | chapter = | title =The Sea Warriors: Fighting Captains and Frigate Warfare in the Age of Nelson |publisher=Constable |location=London, England | isbn = 1-84119-183-3 |ref=harv}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Manila, Raid on}}
[[Category:Naval battles of the French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1798]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving Great Britain]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving Spain]]
[[Category:History of Manila]]
[[Category:History of the Philippines (1521–1898)]]</text>
      <sha1>mb3mfxzmh501v5cfr814jkieccm9x3d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
