<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rogožarski IK-3</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2273142</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751015558</id>
      <parentid>751014817</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T21:14:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dank</username>
        <id>5950998</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Operational history */  ce. done.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20283">{{good article}}
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
  |name = Rogožarski IK-3
  |image =Rogozarski IK-3.jpg
  |caption = Rogožarski IK-3
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
  |type = [[Fighter (aircraft)|Fighter]]
  |manufacturer = [[Rogožarski A.D]]
  |designer = Kosta Sivčev, Ljubomir Ilić, Slobodan Zrnić
  |first flight = late May 1938
  |introduced = late March 1940
  |retired =
  |status =
  |primary user = [[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]]
  |more users =
  |produced = &lt;!--years in production, e.g. 1970-1999, if still in active use but no longer built--&gt;
  |number built = 12
  |unit cost =
  |variants with their own articles =
}}
|}
The '''Rogožarski IK-3''' was a 1930s [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]] low-wing, [[monoplane]], single-seat [[Fighter aircraft|fighter]] with [[Landing gear|retractable landing gear]], designed by Ljubomir Ilić, Kosta Sivčev and Slobodan Zrnić as a successor to the [[Ikarus IK-2]] fighter. Its armament consisted of a [[propeller hub|hub]]-firing {{convert|20|mm|in|adj=on|abbr=on}} [[autocannon]] and two [[fuselage]]-mounted [[Synchronization gear|synchronised]] machine guns. It was considered comparable to foreign aircraft such as the [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]E and came into service in 1940. The prototype crashed during testing, but a total of twelve production aircraft had been delivered by July 1940.

Six IK-3s were serviceable when the [[Axis powers|Axis]] [[invasion of Yugoslavia]] began on 6 April 1941. All six were in service with the 51st Independent Fighter Group at [[Zemun]] near the capital, [[Belgrade]]. Pilots flying the IK-3 claimed to have shot down 11 aircraft during the 11-day conflict. According to one account, to prevent them from falling into German hands, the surviving aircraft and incomplete airframes were destroyed by their crews and factory staff. Another account indicates that one aircraft survived the invasion but it was later destroyed through sabotage. The IK-3 design was used as the basis for the post-war Yugoslav-built [[Ikarus S-49]] fighter.

==Background==
{{see also|Ikarus IK-2}} 
In the late 1920s, the [[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]] ({{lang-sh|Vazduhoplovstvo vojske Kraljevine Jugoslavije}}, VVKJ) and the Royal Aero Club of Yugoslavia helped send aspiring aeronautical engineers to France to develop their knowledge. It was intended that after this advanced training, they would return to Yugoslavia and be offered specialist roles in the VVKJ or in the aeronautical industry. Ljubomir Ilić and Kosta Sivčev went through this program but, when they returned to Yugoslavia, both were employed in administrative work. Frustrated by this, they decided in 1931 to design a replacement for the [[Czechoslovakia]]n-built [[Avia BH-33]]E biplane [[Fighter aircraft|fighter]], then in service with the VVKJ. Working in a basement in [[Belgrade]], and later in Ilić's apartment in [[Novi Sad]], they secretly devoted their spare time to work on their design. They originally planned a low-wing [[monoplane]] with [[Landing gear|retractable landing gear]]. However, contemporary thinking within the VVKJ led them to evolve their initial ideas into a strut-braced [[gull-wing]] monoplane armed with a [[propeller hub|hub]]-firing [[autocannon]] and [[fuselage]]-mounted [[Synchronization gear|synchronised]] machine guns. The design concept for what became the [[Ikarus IK-2]] was submitted to the VVKJ on 22 September 1933.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=170–171}} With this work completed, Ilić and Sivčev had time to start preliminary development of a new low-wing monoplane that could better meet and defeat the high performance bomber prototypes then in development by potential adversaries.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=182}}

==Design and development==
The new streamlined low-wing monoplane design was to have a retractable undercarriage. Like the IK-2 it was initially developed privately by Ilić and Sivčev. A scale model was tested in the Eiffel-built wind tunnel in Paris, but the pair soon realised that they needed a third engineer to help with evaluating the design and determining the structural details. Slobodan Zrnić, the head of construction at the Yugoslav State Aircraft Factory in [[Kraljevo]], was recruited, as he had worked as a specialist aircraft engineer in France. The project name for the IK-2 was changed from IK, standing for (Ljubomir) Ilić and Kosta (Sivčev), to IKZ, to include Zrnić. This name was changed, possibly due to the similarities between the Cyrillic &quot;[[Ze (Cyrillic)|З]]&quot; (Z) and the Arabic numeral &quot;3&quot;, and the aircraft became known as the IK-3. The aircraft was to be powered by a [[Hispano-Suiza 12Y]]29 engine, generating {{convert|980|hp|abbr=on}} at {{convert|5000|m|abbr=on}}. The designers chose to favour manoeuvrability over speed, trying to find a compromise between the German and British concepts of a modern monoplane fighter. The design had a smaller wing area than the [[Hawker Hurricane]] and the [[Supermarine Spitfire]], to achieve a relatively higher speed for the engine power. In comparison to the [[Messerschmitt Bf109]], the Yugoslav design had a shorter fuselage and smaller turning radius. It differed from British and German design concepts in that its proposed armament was concentrated in the fuselage.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=182}}

The designs were delivered to the VVKJ in time for approval by mid-1936, but a general reluctance to adopt new concepts delayed the IK-3, and a contract for the production of the prototype was not signed until March 1937. The company selected for construction was [[Rogožarski]] A.D. in Belgrade. The first flight of the prototype was carried out by the VVKJ Test Group towards the end of May 1938 and the aircraft was then flown by a group of VVKJ officers who were to determine the best employment for it within the VVKJ, along with tactics to be used in Yugoslav conditions.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=182}} These pilots observed that the controls were highly sensitive but the only real criticisms related to the distortion caused by the convex and concave panels of the canopy. Some pilots believed that the fuselage-mounted armament should be supplemented by two wing-mounted machine guns. The pilot group had to compare the performance of the IK-3 with the [[Hawker Fury]], [[Heinkel He 112]], [[Morane-Saulnier M.S.406|Morane-Saulnier M.S. 405]] and Hawker Hurricane. The pilot group concluded that the IK-3 most closely matched the Morane-Saulnier, although the Yugoslav aircraft was {{convert|40|km/h|abbr=on}} faster. In November 1938, the VVKJ placed an order with Rogožarski for 12 aircraft.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=183}}

On 19 January 1939, test pilot ''Kapetan'' Milan Pokorni put the prototype into a steep dive. When he reached {{convert|400|m|abbr=on}}, the windscreen detached from the aircraft; Pokorni pulled up hard and the strain broke off half of the starboard wing. The aircraft crashed, and Pokorni was killed.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=183}} An inquiry determined that modifications to the windscreen had contributed to the accident but the main factor had been the pilot's handling of the highly sensitive controls. Engineers recalculated the stress factors on the airframe and they were found to be safe; the crash was attributed to pilot error and the sensitivity of the controls.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=183}}

The loss of the prototype and some changes in the construction of the production model delayed the fulfilment of the contract. Further tests were conducted on the wing and it was found to withstand a [[g-force]] of 14. Modifications were made for the production model, including the use of flat [[Poly(methyl methacrylate)|plexiglass]] panels in the windscreen and the canopy to provide better visibility for the pilot. The instrument layout was improved and the upper rear fuselage behind the pilot's seat was re-shaped. The folding undercarriage leg covers were replaced by single plates. The main changes were the replacement of the engine with a modified version of the Hispano-Suiza 12Y engine made under licence by the Czechoslovak company [[Avia]] and the replacement of the cannon by a Swiss-made [[Oerlikon 20 mm cannon|Oerlikon FF 20 mm cannon]].{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=183}} The replacement engine was less powerful, generating {{convert|860|hp|abbr=on}} at {{convert|4000|m|abbr=on}}.{{sfn|Green|Swanborough|1994|p=502}} German-made [[Telefunken]] radios were to be installed but delays meant that only the first aircraft was delivered with a radio fitted. The production aircraft were numbered 2–13, as the prototype was number 1. The aircraft were built at the Rogožarski factory in Belgrade and the parts were assembled at the company hangar at Zemun. The first six aircraft were delivered by late March 1940 but delivery of the rest of the order was not completed until July due to delays by foreign suppliers. The first production aircraft was delivered to the VVKJ Test Group, where it was determined that the production aircraft were free of the faults in the prototype. The Test Group determined that the maximum speed, previously estimated at {{convert|540|km/h|abbr=on}}, was {{convert|527|km/h|abbr=on}},{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=183}} at {{convert|5400|m|ft|abbr=on}}. By July 1940, a further series of 25 IK-3s had commenced construction at the Rogožarski factory.{{sfn|Green|Swanborough|1994|p=502}}

===Planned developments===
A shortage of engines was a major obstacle to mass production and development of the IK-3, so tests were conducted with more powerful engines, including the [[Daimler-Benz DB 601]], [[Rolls-Royce Merlin]] II and Hispano-Suiza 12Y51. The tests were incomplete at the time of the [[Axis powers|Axis]] invasion, and the only prototype to be fitted with a non-production engine was destroyed by factory personnel along with the incomplete production aircraft.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=185–186}} Development of a dual-control two-seat trainer variant of the IK-3 had commenced but pressure on the design team had delayed the completion of the project when the invasion intervened.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=186–187}}

The development of the IK-3 encouraged the three designers to pursue the idea of a twin-engined fighter, capable of long-range reconnaissance, photographic reconnaissance and operation as a &quot;destroyer&quot; or [[heavy fighter]] similar to the [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]]. The concept included both one-seater and two-seater versions. Development of this new aircraft, designated IK-5, was commenced on the back of the success of the IK-3. The VVKJ ordered a one-seater prototype in early July 1939, with its first flight scheduled for autumn 1941. At the time of the invasion, the production of the IK-5 prototype was well advanced, but it was not pursued either during or after the war.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=189–190}} The advanced Yugoslav [[Ikarus S-49]] fighter, produced after World War II, was based on the IK-3.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=187}}

==Operational history==
When they entered service, the IK-3s suffered from minor equipment and instrument faults, largely caused by deficiencies in the Yugoslav aeronautical industry which had resulted in a mixture of foreign and Yugoslav-made instruments being fitted to the aircraft. The Yugoslav Minister of War approved the acquisition of a further 48 IK-3s to be delivered in 1941–42.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=183}} The in-service aircraft were allocated to the 51st Independent Fighter Group at Zemun, six each to the 161st and 162nd Fighter Squadrons. The IK-3 was then tested against Yugoslav Messerschmitt Bf 109Es in mock dogfights. The evaluation concluded that the IK-3 had several advantages over the Bf 109E; the Yugoslav aircraft was more manoeuvrable in level flight, enabling it to quickly get behind a pursuing Bf 109E by making tight horizontal turns.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=187–188}}

In its first year of service, an IK-3 was lost when one of the squadron commanders, ''Kapetan'' Anton Ercigoj, was making a mock attack on a [[Potez 25]] over the confluence of the [[Sava]] and [[Danube]] rivers. After passing below the Potez, he went into a climb with the intention of performing a loop. His rate of climb was too steep and the aircraft fell into a spin at low altitude and hit the water.

Before the Axis [[invasion of Yugoslavia]] in early April 1941, the 51st Fighter Group was placed under the 6th Fighter Regiment, which was responsible for the defence of Belgrade. The 51st Fighter Group was further reinforced the day before the invasion began, with the 102nd Fighter Squadron equipped with Bf 109Es. When the invasion began on 6 April, the two IK-3 squadrons had only three serviceable aircraft each.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=187–188}} The 161st Fighter Squadron was commanded by ''Kapetan'' Savo Poljanec, and the 162nd Fighter Squadron by ''Kapetan'' Todor Gogić.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|p=188}}

The invasion commenced with a wave of 234 German [[dive bomber]]s and [[medium bomber]]s attacking Belgrade, escorted by 120 fighters. This force reached Belgrade at 07:00, where it was met by the 51st Fighter Group, without an IK-3 from the 161st Fighter Squadron that developed engine trouble after takeoff and was unable to engage.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=188}} The other five IK-3s were the first to meet the initial bomber wave but they were almost immediately attacked by Bf 109Es of [[Jagdgeschwader 77|''Jagdgeschwader'' 77]]. The pilots of the IK-3s claimed five German aircraft; one aircraft from each Yugoslav squadron was lost. Poljanec had claimed a twin-engined bomber and a Bf 109E but when he returned to Zemun in his badly damaged aircraft, he was strafed by a Messerschmitt 110, which further damaged his aircraft and wounded him.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|pp=196–198}} After this encounter, only three IK-3s were serviceable, including the IK-3 that had developed engine difficulties prior to the first German wave.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=189}}

A second wave of German aircraft arrived over Belgrade at 10:00 and the remaining IK-3s were scrambled with the rest of the 51st Fighter Group but the IK-3 pilots claimed no victories. A joint claim was made during the third German attack at 14:00, a twin-engined bomber by Gogić and another pilot from the 162nd Fighter Squadron.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|p=199}} The following day, the IK-3 pilots made five or six [[sortie]]s against German bomber formations and their fighter escorts, and claimed three bombers between them. At 17:00, Milislav Semiz attacked a tight formation of three bombers; his aircraft received 56 hits from return fire, 20 of which were in the engine and propeller. Despite this, he managed to land the aircraft. The return of another IK-3 from the workshops meant that the number of serviceable IK-3s remained at three.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=189}}

It became difficult to continue activity from the 51st Fighter Group airfield at Zemun due to air attacks, so on 8 April the remaining IK-3s and Bf 109Es flew to an auxiliary airfield at [[Veliki Radinci]], some {{convert|50|km|abbr=on}} north-west of Belgrade, where the surviving aircraft of the 6th Fighter Regiment were concentrated. Poor weather made operations impossible until 11 April, when Semiz shot down a Bf 110 that had strafed the airfield. Later that day, Gogić and another IK-3 pilot claimed one [[Ju 87]] each during a patrol. That night, German troops approached within {{convert|15|km|abbr=on}} of the airfield at Veliki Radinci and the following day all remaining aircraft of the 6th Fighter Regiment, including the remaining IK-3s, were burned by their crews.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=189}}  According to aviation writers Dragan Savić and Boris Ciglić, one serviceable IK-3 was captured by the Germans in April 1941 and by the end of June a second IK-3 had been obtained. Both aircraft were located at Zemun, along with 23 other former VVKJ aircraft in serviceable condition. The Germans had used a fence to separate the serviceable aircraft from other aircraft that had been earmarked for scrapping. In late June, while the German guards were distracted listening to news of [[Operation Barbarossa|the invasion of the Soviet Union]], local communists, including former VVKJ mechanics, moved the fence. As a result, all the serviceable aircraft were scrapped, including the two IK-3s.{{sfn|Savić|Ciglić|2002|pp=59–60}}

&quot;The IK-3s put up a valiant resistance against the Luftwaffe,&quot; wrote William Green, &quot;scoring a number of 'kills' before they were finally destroyed in combat.&quot;{{sfn|Green|1969|p=207}} Aviation writers Šime Oštrić and Čedomir Janić credit the IK-3 pilots with 11 victories, Semiz being the most successful, with four victories.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=192}}

==Operators==
;{{flag|Kingdom of Yugoslavia}}
* [[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]]

==Specifications==
[[File:IK3.JPG|right|thumb|A model of an IK-3]]
'''Source''': {{harvtxt|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=192}}

{{aircraft specs
|ref=
|prime units?=met
|crew=1
|length m= 8
|span m=10.3
|height m=3.25
|wing area sqm=16.5
|empty weight kg= 2,048
|gross weight kg=2,630
|fuel capacity={{convert|330|l|abbr=on}}
|eng1 number=1
|eng1 name=[[Avia]]-built [[Hispano-Suiza 12Y]]crs
|eng1 type=liquid-cooled V-12 piston engine
|prop blade number=3
|prop name=adjustable pitch
|power main= 980 hp
|max speed kmh= 527
|cruise speed kmh=400
|range km=785
|ceiling m= 9,400
|time to altitude=7 minutes to {{convert|5000|m|abbr=on}}
|wing loading kg/m2=159.4
|armament=
* 1 × [[Oerlikon 20 mm cannon|Oerlikon FF 20 mm cannon]]
* 2 × [[7.92 mm caliber|7.92 mm]] [[M1919 Browning machine gun|Browning/FN]] machine guns with 500 rounds per gun
}}

==See also==
{{aircontent|
|related=
* IK-5
* [[Ikarus S-49]]
|similar aircraft=
* [[Curtiss P-40 Warhawk|Curtiss P-40]]
* [[Dewoitine D.520]]
* [[Hawker Hurricane|Hawker Hurricane I]]
* [[Heinkel He 112]]
* [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]
* [[Morane-Saulnier M.S.405]]
* [[Supermarine Spitfire]]
|lists=
* [[List of aircraft of World War II]]
|see also=
}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  | last=Green
  | first=William
  | title = War Planes of the Second World War: Fighters
  | volume = IV
  | year = 1969
  | publisher =MacDonald
  | location =  London
  | isbn = 0-356-01448-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Green
  | first1 = William
  | last2 = Swanborough
  | first2 = Gordon
  | title = The Complete Book of Fighters: An Illustrated Encyclopedia of Every Fighter Aircraft Built and Flown
  | year = 1994
  | publisher = Salamander Books
  | location = London, England
  | isbn = 978-0-86101-643-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Oštrić
  | first1 = Šime I.
  | last2 = Janić
  | first2 = Čedomir J.
  | year = 1973
  | chapter = IK Fighters (Yugoslavia: 1930–40s)
  | editor1-last = Cain
  | editor1-first = Charles W.
  | editor2-last = Windrow
  | editor2-first = Martin
  | pages = 169–193
  | title = Aircraft in Profile
  | volume = 13
  | series = 241–246
  | publisher = Profile Publications
  | location = Windsor, Berkshire
  | isbn = 0-85383-022-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Savić
  | first1 = Dragan
  | last2 = Ciglić
  | first2 = Boris
  | title = Croatian Aces of World War 2
  | year = 2002
  | publisher = Osprey
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1-84176-435-1
  | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=RaBh3kd2HoMC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Shores
  | first1 = Christopher F.
  | last2 = Cull
  | first2 = Brian
  | last3 = Malizia
  | first3 = Nicola
  | title = Air War for Yugoslavia, Greece, and Crete, 1940–41
  | year = 1987
  | publisher = Grub Street
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-948817-07-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Rogozarski IK-3}}
* [http://www.ipmssrbija.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/maketar-plus-04.pdf „Rogožarski IK-3“] by Nenad M. Miklusev (p 32 In English)

{{Rogozarski}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rogozarski IK-3}}
[[Category:Low-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Monoplanes]]
[[Category:Propeller aircraft]]
[[Category:Single-engine aircraft]]
[[Category:Yugoslav fighter aircraft 1930–1939]]</text>
      <sha1>nr1zdk7345jdqetrgpnybgcyeyzdhra</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
