<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Saborsko massacre</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12399804</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745163771</id>
      <parentid>745123021</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-19T16:41:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>23 editor</username>
        <id>16532586</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>tweak</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27020">{{good article}}
{{Infobox civilian attack
| title=Saborsko massacre
|partof = the [[Croatian War of Independence]]
| map={{Location_map+| Croatia | width=300| float=center 
| caption = 
| overlay_image =Cro-occup-lines-Jan92.svg
| places =
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Saborsko]] | lat=44.983486| long=15.478811 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=left| region=HR}}
}}
|map_caption=Saborsko on the map of Croatia, JNA/SAO Krajina-held areas in late 1991 are highlighted in red
|location= [[Saborsko]], [[Croatia]]
|target=[[Croat]] civilians
|date=12 November 1991
|time=
|timezone=
|type=[[Mass murder]]
|fatalities=29
|injuries=
|perps= [[SAO Krajina]] [[Territorial Defense Forces (Yugoslavia)|Territorial Defence Forces]] and the [[Yugoslav People's Army]]
}}
{{Campaignbox Croatian War of Independence}}
The '''Saborsko massacre''' ({{lang-hr|Pokolj u Saborskom}},{{sfn|Jutarnji list|27 March 2006}} {{lang-sr|''Operacija Saborsko''}}){{sfn|Rupić|2007|p=499}} was the killing of 29 [[Croat]] residents of the village of [[Saborsko]] on 12 November 1991, following the seizure of the village in a [[Yugoslav People's Army]] (''Jugoslovenska Narodna Armija'' – JNA) and [[Croatian Serb]] offensive during the [[Croatian War of Independence]]. The fall of the town occurred as part of a JNA and Croatian Serb operation to capture a Croatian-held [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|pocket]] centered on the town of [[Slunj]], southeast of [[Karlovac]]. While the bulk of the civilian population fled with the surviving [[Croatian police|Croatian forces]], those who remained in Saborsko were rounded up and either killed or expelled. The bodies of the victims were retrieved from two mass graves and several individual graves in 1995.

The capture of Saborsko and the killing and expulsion of its civilian population was included in the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY) indictments of [[Milan Babić]] and [[Milan Martić]], high-ranking officials of the Croatian Serb-declared wartime breakaway region of [[SAO Krajina]]. Following the war, the ICTY convicted Babić and Martić for their role in the events. Saborsko was subsequently rebuilt.

==Background==
[[File:Map 5 - Croatia - Banija-Kordun-Lika Operations October 1991 - January 1992.jpg|thumb|300px|Map showing the fighting in the Banovina, Kordun and Lika regions, October 1991&amp;ndash;January 1992; Slunj pocket is shown in the centre of the map]]
{{main|Croatian War of Independence}}
In 1990, following the [[Croatian parliamentary election, 1990|electoral defeat]] of the government of the [[Socialist Republic of Croatia]], ethnic tensions between Croats and Serbs worsened. The [[Yugoslav People's Army]] (''Jugoslovenska Narodna Armija'' – JNA) confiscated [[Croatia]]'s [[Territorial Defense Forces (Yugoslavia)|Territorial Defence]] (''Teritorijalna obrana'' - TO) weapons to minimize resistance.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=117}} On 17 August, the tensions escalated into an [[Log Revolution|open revolt]] by [[Serbs of Croatia|Croatian Serbs]],{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=118}} centred on the predominantly Serb-populated areas of the [[Dalmatia]]n hinterland around Knin,{{sfn|The New York Times|19 August 1990}} parts of the [[Lika]], [[Kordun]], [[Banovina (region)|Banovina]] and [[eastern Croatia]].{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007}} This was followed by two unsuccessful attempts by [[Republic of Serbia (1990–2006)|Serbia]], supported by [[Socialist Republic of Montenegro|Montenegro]] and Serbia's provinces of [[Vojvodina]] and [[Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija|Kosovo]] to obtain the [[Yugoslav Presidency]]'s approval for a JNA operation to disarm Croatian security forces in January 1991.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|pp=118–119}}

After a bloodless skirmish between Serb insurgents and [[Croatian special police order of battle in 1991–95|Croatian special police]] in March,{{sfn|Ramet|2006|pp=384–385}} the JNA itself, supported by Serbia and its allies, asked the Federal Presidency to give it wartime authority and declare a state of emergency. The request was denied on 15 March, and the JNA came under the control of Serbian President [[Slobodan Milošević]]. Milošević publicly threatened to replace the JNA with a Serbian army and declared that he no longer recognized the authority of the Federal Presidency.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=119}} By the end of the month, the conflict had escalated into the [[Croatian War of Independence]].{{sfn|The New York Times|3 March 1991}} The JNA stepped in, increasingly supporting the Croatian Serb insurgents, and preventing [[Croatian police]] from intervening.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=119}} In early April, the leaders of the Croatian Serb revolt declared their intention to integrate the area under their control, known as [[SAO Krajina]], with Serbia. The [[Government of Croatia]] viewed this declaration as an attempt to [[secession|secede]].{{sfn|The New York Times|2 April 1991}}

In May, the Croatian government responded by forming the [[Croatian National Guard]] (''Zbor narodne garde'' - ZNG),{{sfn|EECIS|1999|pp=272–278}} but its development was hampered by a [[United Nations]] (UN) [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 713|arms embargo]] introduced in September.{{sfn|The Independent|10 October 1992}} On 8 October, [[Independence of Croatia|Croatia declared independence from Yugoslavia]],{{sfn|Narodne novine|8 October 1991}} and a month later the ZNG was renamed the [[Croatian Army]] (''Hrvatska vojska'' - HV).{{sfn|EECIS|1999|pp=272–278}} Late 1991 saw the fiercest fighting of the war, as the [[1991 Yugoslav campaign in Croatia|Yugoslav campaign in Croatia]] culminated in the [[Siege of Dubrovnik]],{{sfn|Bjelajac|Žunec|2009|pp=249–250}} and the [[Battle of Vukovar]].{{sfn|The New York Times|18 November 1991}}

==Prelude==
The Saborsko Independent Company, consisting of approximately 30 personnel, was stationed in the village by the Croatian police the day after the [[Plitvice Lakes incident]] on 1 April 1991.{{sfn|Index.hr|23 July 2006}} The tensions worsened in July. That month the JNA distributed 1,000 [[small arms]] to ethnic Serbs living in [[Gorski kotar]] region, including Plaški. Skirmishes took place near [[Josipdol]] and Plaški.{{sfn|Nazor|December 2010 (a)}} In June–August, Saborsko was targeted by artillery and mortars positioned at JNA barracks in Lička Jasenica, and the bulk of its civilian population fled by early August. However, approximately 400 returned to their homes the same month after 20–30 special police troops were deployed from [[Duga Resa]] to Saborsko along with 15–20 regular police drawn from Slunj as reinforcements.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|pp=79–80}} On 25 September, 100–200 police reservists arrived to Saborsko from [[Zagreb]]. The final Croatian reinforcements arrived in October, consisting of 20–50 police.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=80}} By October, a [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|pocket]] of Croatian-controlled territory formed around the town of [[Slunj]] south of [[Karlovac]], on the boundary of the regions of Kordun and Lika, hampering direct communications between SAO Krajina-held areas in the two regions.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=225}} The pocket was separated from the bulk of the [[Croatian Government]]-controlled territory by the SAO Krajina-controlled town of [[Plaški]] to the west. In turn, Plaški was inaccessible to the central SAO Krajina authorities as the road to Plaški ran through the village of [[Saborsko]], situated within the Slunj pocket.{{sfn|Nazor|December 2010 (a)}}

In early October, the JNA and the SAO Krajina TO launched a joint offensive  which was aimed at capturing the peripheral areas of the Slunj pocket.{{sfn|Rupić|2007|pp=591–592}}{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=226}} The JNA also planned to airlift 44 truckloads of weapons from [[Željava Air Base]] to Gorski kotar and raise a combat brigade there in support of the operation and to extend their control into Gorski kotar. The airlift was cancelled after the [[Yugoslav Air Force]] refused to follow the orders.{{sfn|Nazor|September 2010}} That month, the JNA captured the village of [[Lipovača, Karlovac County|Lipovača]], {{convert|25|km|abbr=off}} east of Saborsko, and turned it over to Serb paramilitaries. Most of the Croat civilians fled, although at least seven civilians were killed and the village looted and torched.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|pp=73–76}} Three more Croat civilians were killed in the nearby village of Vukovići.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=76}} The Croatian police and the ZNG, including the forces based in Saborsko, launched a failed attempt to capture the JNA base in Lička Jasenica on 4–8 November resulting in the deaths of a number of Serb civilians.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|pp=80–81}} During the attack, a force commanded by JNA officers and including the [[63rd Parachute Battalion]] troops killed nine more Croat civilians in the village of Poljanak near Saborsko on 7 November.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|pp=77–78}}

==Timeline==
[[Image:Mass Grave, Saborsko, Croatia.JPG|thumb|right|A mass grave site in Saborsko]]
In early November, the JNA and the SAO Krajina TO intensified their offensive aimed at capturing Saborsko and the Slunj pocket. The main axes of the advance radiated north and northwest from the [[Plitvice Lakes]]—towards Slunj and Saborsko respectively.{{sfn|CIA|2002|pp=226–227}} The JNA force assigned to the offensive was organised as the Tactical Group 2 (TG-2), under the command of [[Colonel]] Čedomir Bulat.{{sfn|Nazor|December 2010 (b)}} The TG-2, whose bulk consisted of a reinforced motorised battalion detached from the 236th Motorised Brigade and a [[122 mm howitzer 2A18 (D-30)|D-30 howitzer]] battalion,{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=227}} was supported by the 5th Partisan Brigade, both subordinated to the 13th JNA Corps as well as a police unit and a SAO Krajina TO brigade drawn from Plaški. The attacking force, supported by the Yugoslav Air Force, artillery and tanks, approached the village from three directions on the morning of 12 November,{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=81}} while the main force advancing towards Slunj reached [[Rakovica, Croatia|Rakovica]].{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=227}} According to SAO Krajina sources, the air strikes commenced at 9&amp;nbsp;a.m. and lasted for fifteen minutes. They were followed by a 30-minute artillery bombardment before ground forces were ordered to attack.{{sfn|Nazor|December 2010 (b)}}

The defences of Saborsko were first breached at noon, and the attacking force reached the centre of the village at 3:30&amp;nbsp;p.m. According to SAO Krajina sources, resistance was light, with the defending force estimated to consist of only 150 armed troops.{{sfn|Rupić|2007|pp=498–499}} The village was secured by 5&amp;nbsp;p.m. with tanks attached to the attacking force withdrawn by 6&amp;nbsp;p.m. The assault resulted in the death of 50 Croatian troops,{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=81}} while the attacking forces suffered only four wounded.{{sfn|Rupić|2007|p=499}} In the immediate aftermath of the fighting to control Saborsko, the village was looted and many houses were torched.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=81}}

After the attack, the bulk of the civilian population and the remaining Croatian police and troops{{sfn|Slobodna Dalmacija|24 May 2012}} fled over snow-covered terrain in poor weather{{sfn|Nazor|December 2010 (b)}} to Karlovac, [[Ogulin]],{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=83}} and to the nearby territory of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]. Approximately 30–60 civilians, largely elderly people, remained in Saborsko.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=83}} The JNA and SAO Krajina troops forced those who remained behind to leave the village, killing or abusing the civilians.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|pp=83–84}} At least 25 civilians were murdered by the troops in the immediate aftermath of the capture of Saborsko. Some of the victims were shot, while others were beaten or burned to death.{{sfn|Cencich|2013|pp=89–90}}

==Aftermath==
[[Image:Denkmal, Massaker von Saborsko.JPG|thumb|right|A monument to the civilian victims in Saborsko]]
The destruction of Saborsko continued and both churches in the village were demolished by mid-December. By 1995, the entire village had been completely destroyed except for two Serb-owned houses, which were badly damaged.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|pp=82–83}} After its capture, the village was renamed Ravna Gora by the SAO Krajina authorities.{{sfn|Nazor|December 2010 (b)}} Croatian forces subsequently lost control of Slunj on 16 November and the rest of the pocket fell to the TG-2{{sfn|Nazor|December 2010 (c)}} when it captured [[Cetingrad]] on 29 November.{{sfn|Rupić|2007|pp=502–504}} The Saborsko Independent Company, which unsuccessfully defended Saborsko, was subsequently attached to Ogulin Home Guard Battalion, which was in turn amalgamated with other HV units to form the 143rd Home Guard Regiment.{{sfn|Ogulin}}

In the two months following the recapture of the area by Croatia in 1995 during [[Operation Storm]], the bodies of 27 victims were recovered in two mass graves containing three and fourteen bodies respectively, and in ten individual graves.{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|p=85}} In its indictment of [[Milan Babić]], leader of the SAO Krajina at the time when the killings in Saborsko took place, the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY) specified that 29 Croat civilians were killed in Saborsko on 12 November 1991.{{sfn|ICTY|6 November 2003|p=3}}

The killings in the Slunj pocket, including those in Saborsko, were prosecuted by the ICTY. The ICTY charged Babić and [[Milan Martić]], respectively the defence and interior ministers of the SAO Krajina, with persecution, extermination and murder of non-Serb civilians in the area as well as deportations and forcible transfer of the civilian population, intentional plunder and destruction of property.{{sfn|ICTY|6 November 2003|p=3}}{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007|pp=7–8}} Babić was tried at the ICTY in 2003–05, convicted and sentenced to 13 years in prison.{{sfn|ICTY|2006|p=1}} Martić was [[Trial of Milan Martić|tried in 2002–08]], convicted and sentenced to 35 years in prison.{{sfn|ICTY|2009|pp=1–2}} His involvement in the killings, among other charges brought forward by the ICTY, was interpreted by the tribunal as part of a campaign of [[ethnic cleansing]] of non-Serbs from SAO Krajina controlled areas.{{sfn|Warrell|31 March 2006}}{{sfn|BBC News|12 June 2007}}

Saborsko was rebuilt after the war with a total of 400 houses constructed, but the refugees returning to the village were mostly elderly due to a lack of employment options elsewhere.{{sfn|Večernji list|11 January 2012}} The site of one of the mass graves in Saborsko is marked with a monument to the victims.{{sfn|24 sata|12 November 2011}} Three different [[commemorative plaque]]s dedicated to Croatian policemen and troops killed in Saborsko in 1991 were placed at various sites in the village in 2009, but two were stolen on 11 November 2010.{{sfn|Nova TV|11 November 2010}} The missing commemorative plaques were replaced by November 2011.{{sfn|Saborsko|11 November 2011}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
;Books
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Confronting the Yugoslav Controversies: A Scholars' Initiative|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t0nYdgFrdG8C|editor=Charles W. Ingrao|editor2=Thomas Allan Emmert|chapter=The War in Croatia, 1991–1995|first=Mile|last= Bjelajac|first2=Ozren |last2=Žunec|publisher=[[Purdue University Press]]|year=2009|isbn= 978-1-55753-533-7|pages=230–271|location=West Lafayette, Indiana}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=The Devil's Garden: A War Crimes Investigator's Story|url=https://books.google.hr/books?id=tKiYPwudOZoC|first=John R.|last=Cencich|publisher=[[Potomac Books]]|location=Lincoln, Nebraska|isbn=9781612341729|year=2013}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|CIA|2002}}|url=https://books.google.hr/books?id=it1IAQAAIAAJ|title=Balkan Battlegrounds: A Military History of the Yugoslav Conflict, 1990–1995, Volume 2|publisher=Central Intelligence Agency|author=[[Central Intelligence Agency]], Office of Russian and European Analysis|year=2002|oclc=50396958|location=Washington, D.C.}}
*{{cite book|title=Eastern Europe and the Commonwealth of Independent States|year=1999|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qmN95fFocsMC| ref={{harvid|EECIS|1999}}|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-85743-058-5|location=London, England}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.hr/books?hl=hr&amp;id=oFXdiS25N78C|editor-first=Sabrina P.|editor-last=Ramet|title=Central and Southeast European Politics Since 1989|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2010|isbn=978-1-139-48750-4|chapter=The War of Yugoslav Succession|first=Marko Attila|last=Hoare|authorlink=Marko Attila Hoare|pages=111–136|location=Cambridge, England}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC|title=The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building And Legitimation, 1918–2006|first=Sabrina P.|last=Ramet|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]]|year=2006|isbn= 978-0-253-34656-8|location=Bloomington, Indiana}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|Rupić|2007}}|url=http://www.centardomovinskograta.hr/pdf/izdanja/Dokumenti_01.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=Hrvatski memorijalno-dokumentacijski centar Domovinskog rata|location=Zagreb, Croatia|year=2007|editor-first=Marko|editor-last=Rupić|title=Republika Hrvatska i Domovinski rat 1990. – 1995. – Dokumenti, Knjiga 1.|trans_title=The Republic of Croatia and the Croatian War of Independence 1990–1995 – Documents, volume 1|isbn=978-953-7439-03-3}}
{{refend}}

;News reports
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The Independent|10 October 1992}}|newspaper=[[The Independent]]|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/croatia-built-web-of-contacts-to-evade-weapons-embargo-1556500.html|title=Croatia built 'web of contacts' to evade weapons embargo|first=Christopher|last=Bellamy|date=10 October 1992|archivedate=10 November 2012|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20121110025827/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/croatia-built-web-of-contacts-to-evade-weapons-embargo-1556500.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Nova TV|11 November 2010}}|publisher=[[Nova TV (Croatia)]]|date=11 November 2010|url=http://dnevnik.hr/vijesti/crna-kronika/dan-prije-obljetnice-nestale-spomen-ploce-braniteljima-saborskog.html|language=Croatian|title=Dan prije obljetnice nestale spomen ploče braniteljima Saborskog|trans_title=Commemorative Plaques to Defenders of Saborsko Vanish a Day Ahead of the Anniversary}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The New York Times|3 March 1991}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/03/03/world/belgrade-sends-troops-to-croatia-town.html|first=Stephen|last=Engelberg|title=Belgrade Sends Troops to Croatia Town|date=3 March 1991|archivedate=2 October 2013|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20131002222925/http://www.nytimes.com/1991/03/03/world/belgrade-sends-troops-to-croatia-town.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Jutarnji list|27 March 2006}}|newspaper=[[Jutarnji list]]|date=27 March 2006|language=Croatian|title=Haag: Protiv Martića policajac svjedočio o pokolju u Saborskom|trans_title=The Hague: Policeman Testifies Against Martić on Saborsko Massacre|url=http://www.jutarnji.hr/haag--protiv-martica-policajac-svjedocio-o-pokolju-u-saborskom/24744/}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid||Index.hr|23 July 2006}}|publisher=[[Index.hr]]|date=23 July 2006|url=http://www.index.hr/vijesti/clanak/icty-protiv-martica-svjedocio-policajac-iz-saborskog/312169.aspx|language=Croatian|title=ICTY: Protiv Martića svjedočio policajac iz Saborskog|trans_title=ICTY: Saborsko Policeman Testifies Against Martić}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Slobodna Dalmacija|24 May 2012}}|newspaper=[[Slobodna Dalmacija]]|date=24 May 2012|url=http://www.slobodnadalmacija.hr/Hrvatska/tabid/66/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/175575/Default.aspx|language=Croatian|title=Denisio Kapović Klokan: Ubijali smo ljude i zato je Ivan proživljavao pakao|trans_title=Denisio Kapović Klokan: Ivan Went Through Hell Because We Killed Men|first=Mario|last=Pušić}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The New York Times|19 August 1990}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/08/19/world/roads-sealed-as-yugoslav-unrest-mounts.html|agency=[[Reuters]]|title=Roads Sealed as Yugoslav Unrest Mounts|date=19 August 1990|archivedate=21 September 2013|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20130921063029/http://www.nytimes.com/1990/08/19/world/roads-sealed-as-yugoslav-unrest-mounts.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|BBC News|12 June 2007}}|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=12 June 2007|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6743607.stm|title=Serb leader jailed for war crimes}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Večernji list|11 January 2012}}|newspaper=[[Večernji list]]|date=11 January 2012|first=Ivona|last=Škalamera|language=Croatian|title=Saborsko - općina pokraj koje sve samo prolazi, a stanovnici odlaze|trans_title=Saborsko - Municipality Bypassed by Everything, Deserted by its Population|url=http://www.vecernji.hr/sredisnja-hrvatska/saborsko-opcina-pokraj-koje-sve-samo-prolazi-a-stanovnici-odlaze-364914}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The New York Times|18 November 1991}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/18/world/croats-concede-danube-town-s-loss.html| title=Croats Concede Danube Town's Loss|first=Chuck|last=Sudetic|authorlink=Chuck Sudetic|date=18 November 1991|archivedate=14 November 2013|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20131114143713/http://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/18/world/croats-concede-danube-town-s-loss.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The New York Times|2 April 1991}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/04/02/world/rebel-serbs-complicate-rift-on-yugoslav-unity.html|title=Rebel Serbs Complicate Rift on Yugoslav Unity|first=Chuck|last=Sudetic|date=2 April 1991|archivedate=2 October 2013|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20131002222938/http://www.nytimes.com/1991/04/02/world/rebel-serbs-complicate-rift-on-yugoslav-unity.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|24 sata|12 November 2011}}|newspaper=[[24sata (Croatia)]]|date=12 November 2011|url=http://www.24sata.hr/news/u-saborskom-polozili-vijence-i-svijece-civilnim-zrtvama-rata-242187|first=Andreja|last=Thomas|language=Croatian|title=U Saborskom položili vijence i svijeće civilnim žrtvama rata|trans_title=Wreaths and Candles for Civilian Victims in Saborsko}}
{{refend}}

;Other sources
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Ogulin}}|url=http://www.ogulin.hr/povijest/domovinski-rat/143-pukovnija|title=143. Domobranska pukovnija|language=Croatian|trans_title=143rd Home Guard Regiment|publisher=The City of Ogulin}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Saborsko|11 November 2011}}|url=http://www.saborsko.net/index.php/arhiva/693-branitelji-saborskog-ponovno-postavili-spomen-ploce-poginulim-suborcima|title=Branitelji Saborskog ponovno postavili spomen ploče poginulim suborcima|language=Croatian|trans_title=Saborsko Veterans Replace Plaques Commemorating Fallen Comrades|date=11 November 2011|publisher=The Municipality of [[Saborsko]]}}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Nazor|September 2010}}|url=http://www.hrvatski-vojnik.hr/hrvatski-vojnik/3082010/domovinskirat.asp|journal=[[Hrvatski vojnik]]|issue=308|date=September 2010|language=Croatian|title=Naoružavanje Srba u Hrvatskoj (Gorski Kotar)|trans_title=Arming of Serbs in Croatia (Gorski Kotar)|publisher=[[Ministry of Defence (Croatia)]]|first=Ante|last=Nazor|location=Zagreb, Croatia|issn=1333-9036}}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Nazor|December 2010 (a)}}|url=http://www.hrvatski-vojnik.hr/hrvatski-vojnik/3212010/domovinskirat.asp|journal=Hrvatski vojnik|issue=321|date=December 2010|language=Croatian|title=Saborsko i Plaški u izvorima &quot;Republike Srpske Krajine&quot; (I. dio)|trans_title=Saborsko and Plaški in sources of the Republic of Serbian Krajina (Part 1)|publisher=Ministry of Defence (Croatia)|first=Ante|last=Nazor|location=Zagreb, Croatia|issn=1333-9036}}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Nazor|December 2010 (b)}}|url=http://www.hrvatski-vojnik.hr/hrvatski-vojnik/3222010/domovinskirat.asp|journal=Hrvatski vojnik|issue=322|date=December 2010|language=Croatian|title=Saborsko i Plaški u izvorima &quot;Republike Srpske Krajine&quot; (II. dio)|trans_title=Saborsko and Plaški in sources of the Republic of Serbian Krajina (Part 2)|publisher=Ministry of Defence (Croatia)|first=Ante|last=Nazor|location=Zagreb, Croatia|issn=1333-9036}}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Nazor|December 2010 (c)}}|url=http://www.hrvatski-vojnik.hr/hrvatski-vojnik/3232010/domovinskirat.asp|journal=Hrvatski vojnik|issue=323|date=December 2010|language=Croatian|title=Saborsko i Plaški u izvorima &quot;Republike Srpske Krajine&quot; (III. dio)|trans_title=Saborsko and Plaški in sources of the Republic of Serbian Krajina (Part 3)|publisher=Ministry of Defence (Croatia)|first=Ante|last=Nazor|location=Zagreb, Croatia|issn=1333-9036}}
*{{cite journal|ref={{harvid|Narodne novine|8 October 1991}}|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/1991_10_53_1265.html|journal=[[Narodne novine]]|issue=53|issn=1333-9273|language=Croatian|title=Odluka|trans_title=Decision|publisher=Narodne novine d.d.|date=8 October 1991}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|2006}}|title=RSK (IT-03-72) Milan Babić|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/babic/cis/en/cis_babic_en.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=[[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]]|year=2006}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|2009}}|title=RSK (IT-95-11) Milan Martić|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/martic/cis/en/cis_martic_en.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|year=2009}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|6 November 2003}}|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/babic/ind/en/bab-ii031117e.pdf|format=PDF|title=The Prosecutor of the Tribunal Against Milan Babić - Indictment|date=6 November 2003|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|12 June 2007}}|title=The Prosecutor vs. Milan Martic – Judgement|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/martic/tjug/en/070612.pdf|publisher=International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|date=12 June 2007|format=PDF}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Warrell|31 March 2006}}|url=http://iwpr.net/report-news/martic-implicated-ethnic-cleansing|first=Helen|last=Warrell|publisher=[[Institute for War and Peace Reporting]]|date=31 March 2006|issue=446|title=Martic Implicated in Ethnic Cleansing}}
{{refend}}
{{commonscat|Saborsko massacre}}

{{coord|44.983486|N|15.478811|E|region:HR_type:landmark_source:kolossus-dewiki|display=title}}

{{Croatian War of Independence}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Saborsko Massacre}}
[[Category:Mass murder in 1991]]
[[Category:1991 in Croatia]]
[[Category:Serbian war crimes in the Croatian War of Independence]]
[[Category:Massacres in Croatia]]
[[Category:Republic of Serbian Krajina]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1991]]</text>
      <sha1>iu0qyqhnbt1zul6as7cj7wjx3o23xuh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
