<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>School of Advanced Military Studies</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47720</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747568496</id>
      <parentid>742502086</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T02:49:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jdaloner</username>
        <id>4460044</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Disambiguated &quot;Chief of Staff of the Army&quot;.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36875">{{Good Article}}
{{Use American English|date=November 2012}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=School of Advanced Military Studies (SAMS)
|image=[[File:School of Advanced Military Studies (crest).png|200px]]
|caption=The School of Advanced Military Studies Crest
|dates=1981–Present
|country=[[United States of America|USA]]
|allegiance=[[Federal government of the United States|Federal]]
|branch=
|type=
|role=
|size=
|command_structure=
|current_commander=Colonel James Markert
|garrison=[[Fort Leavenworth]], [[Kansas]]
|ceremonial_chief=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=The mind is the key to victory&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. Foreword.&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors=
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=
|notable_commanders=Colonel Wass de Czege
|anniversaries=
}}

The '''School of Advanced Military Studies''' (SAMS) is one of four [[United States Army]] schools that make up the [[United States Army Command and General Staff College]] (CGSC) at [[Fort Leavenworth]], Kansas. This &quot;enormously rigorous&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sca09|Scales 2009]]. p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; graduate school comprises two programs: the larger Advanced Military Studies Program (AMSP), and the Advanced Operational Art Studies Fellowship (AOASF), which more senior officers attend. The student body is small but diverse and comprises members of each of the U.S. armed forces, various U.S. Government agencies, and allied military forces. Graduates are colloquially known as &quot;Jedi Knights&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hun09|Huntoon 2009]]. p. 4; [[#25th10|United States Army Command and General Staff College Public Affairs 2010]].&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref_label|A|a|none}}

The school educates the future leaders of the U.S. Armed Forces, its Allies, and the Interagency at the graduate level to be agile and adaptive leaders who think critically at the strategic and operational levels to solve complex ambiguous problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;About10_Reference&quot;&gt;[[#About10|United States Army Command and General Staff College: School of Advanced Military Studies]]&lt;/ref&gt;

SAMS graduates are innovative leaders, willing to accept risk and to experiment. They are adaptive leaders who excel at the art of command and anticipate the future operational environment by applying critical &amp; creative thinking skills in order to solve complex problems. All graduates demonstrate mastery of Operational Art and Doctrine and are able to synthesize the elements of US national power in Joint, Interagency, Intergovernmental and Multinational (JIIM) operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;About10_Reference&quot;/&gt;

The school issues a [[masters degree]] in Military Art and Science,&lt;ref&gt;[[#CARL11|Combined Arms Research Library Digital Library 2011]].&lt;/ref&gt; and provides its graduates with the skills to deal with the disparate challenges encountered in contemporary military and government operations. The modern course produces &quot;leaders with the flexibility of mind to solve complex operational and strategic problems in peace, conflict, and war&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#350-1|CGSC Circular 350-1]]. p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; Various senior military leaders have recognized the contributions of SAMS graduates in supporting global contingency operations.

The first class began at the school in mid-1983 and 13 students graduated the following year.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 2; [[#Tri12|United States Army Command and General Staff College (SAMS Tri-Fold) 2012]]. p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to increasing requirements for SAMS graduates in the U.S. military, the army expanded the school in the 1990s, and in 2010 over 120 students graduated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liewer 2010&quot;&gt;[[#Lie10|Liewer 2010]].&lt;/ref&gt; Since the school's inception, SAMS planners have supported every major U.S. military campaign, providing the army &quot;with many of its top campaign planners for the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hun09|Huntoon 2009]]. p. 2; [[#Ste10|Stewart 2010]]. p. 394.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{main|History of the School of Advanced Military Studies}}

The SAMS course was designed to fill a gap in U.S. military education between the CGSC's focus on tactics and the [[United States Army War College|War College]]'s focus on [[grand strategy]] and national security policy.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Nay91|Naylor 1991]]. pp. 10, 16.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1981, Colonel [[Huba Wass de Czege]] convinced Fort Leavenworth's Lieutenant General [[William R. Richardson]], who served as Commander of the Combined Arms Center and Commandant of the Command and General Staff College at Fort Leavenworth from 1979 to 1981, that a second year of military education was needed for select officers.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Was09|Wass de Czege 2009]]. p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; After receiving final approval, Wass de Czege helped plan and develop the school, which would open in mid-1983.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 2; [[#Swa96|Swain 1996]]. p. 160. According to Swain, this information was &quot;described in&quot; U.S. Army Combined Arms Center 1982–83–84, (1989) ''Annual Historical Review'', Fort Leavenworth, Kansas. Combined Arms Center History Office.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref_label|B|b|none}} Although there was some disagreement about the purpose of the course, army leaders and the course designers settled on a plan to provide officers with a &quot;broad, deep military education in the science and art of war.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1983, the first class of 13 U.S. Army students began in the basement of Bell Hall at Fort Leavenworth.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 2, 15; [[#Tri12|United States Army Command and General Staff College (SAMS Tri-Fold) 2012]]. p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, there were some internal problems with facilities and scheduling,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 14–15; US Army Military History Institute, Senior Officer Oral History Program, LTC Harold R. Winton, USA, Retired. Conducted by LTC Richard Mustion,  5 April 2001 at Carlisle Barracks, PA, 17, quoted in [[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; and in the school's early years there was uncertainty whether its graduates would be accepted and how they would perform in the force. When the first class graduated in 1984, SAMS had already become &quot;the symbol for intellectual renaissance in the officer corps&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ste10|Stewart 2010]]. p. 291.&lt;/ref&gt; When the first director, Wass de Czege, was succeeded by Colonel Richard Sennreich in 1985, the school was already beginning to produce results and the U.S. Army and the College regarded SAMS as a &quot;useful experiment&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1987, enrollment of high-quality officers had risen and sister services were becoming interested in sending students to SAMS.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 25, 27.&lt;/ref&gt; The program's growing popularity and reputation also began attracting students from allied countries.

[[Image:Wass de Czege U.S. Army photo.jpg|upright|left|thumb|Colonel Wass de Czege, the school's first director.]]

SAMS graduates first saw active service in December 1989 during [[Operation Just Cause]] in Panama.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; A core planning cell of seven SAMS graduates &quot;crafted a well rehearsed and well executed plan that simultaneously struck some roughly 50 objectives in a single coordinated blow&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Colonel Kevin Benson, the tenth director of the school, &quot;The Army and SAMS faced a test of battle and the new group of highly-educated planners appeared to have passed the test with flying colors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; After its mission in Panama, the army's leaders began to draw on SAMS to assist in additional ways. In the early 1990s, U.S. Army leaders called upon the school to help develop army doctrine. Lieutenant Colonel Thomas E. Mitchell, Colonel James McDonough (the fifth SAMS director), and other members of the SAMS team helped revise the U.S. Army Doctrinal Manual 100-5 ''Operations'' in 1990–1993.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Rom96|Romjue 1996]]. pp. 27–28, 31–33, 39–40, 44, 46, 51, 109.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fort Leavenworth Bell Hall No Date Building 111.jpg|thumb|right|Bell Hall. The first home of SAMS.]]

Lieutenant General Guy C. Swan noted that SAMS graduates were indispensable in Europe after the fall of the [[Berlin wall]] and the dissolution of the Warsaw Pact.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bower 2010&quot;&gt;[[#Bow10|Bower 2010]].&lt;/ref&gt; They were expected to &quot;re-engineer the decades of planning that had gone into the GDP [General Defense Plan] almost overnight&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bower 2010&quot;/&gt; Swan stated that this was &quot;the first true test of SAMS on a large scale&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bower 2010&quot;/&gt; SAMS graduates served in [[Operation Desert Storm|Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm]], and were &quot;remembered most famously in the early days for producing the 'Jedi Knights' employed by [[Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr.|Gen. Norman Schwarzkopf]] in developing the famous 'left hook'&amp;#160;&amp;thinsp;&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[#25th10|United States Army Command and General Staff College Public Affairs 2010]].&lt;/ref&gt; SAMS graduates also served in roles beyond the initial planning, with 82 graduates participating in diverse theater tasks by February 1991.&lt;ref&gt;[[#USN92|U.S. News and World Report 1992]]. p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, U.S. Army leadership regarded SAMS as a source of &quot;superb planners&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box
| quote  = &quot;The number one reason for the success of Desert Storm was General (H. Norman) Schwarzkopf. ... The number two reason was the air war, and the number three reason was the SAMS graduates who put together General Schwarzkopf's plan.&quot;
| source = [[Williamson Murray]], Professor of Military History at [[Ohio State University]], 1991.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Nay91|Naylor 1991]]. p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;
| width  = 30%
| align  = right
| style = padding:8px;
}}

After Desert Storm, the army struggled with [[military operations other than war]], such as peacekeeping and peace enforcement operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benson 2009. p. 44&quot;&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; The school and its graduates examined the situations in Bosnia, Haiti, and Somalia.  Graduates also participated in [[Defense Support of Civil authorities]] missions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benson 2009. p. 44&quot;/&gt; The course continued to change in the 1990s. Under Colonel Gregory Fontenot, the school moved from Fort Leavenworth's Flint Hall to Eisenhower Hall in October 1994. In later years, the school's leadership expanded the number of seminars and the civilian faculty.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 46–47, 50–51, 53.&lt;/ref&gt; The military continues to draw heavily on SAMS in the twenty-first century. SAMS planners have played a significant role in the [[Global War on Terror]]. Beginning in 2002, the [[United States Central Command]] requested planners from SAMS and its sister schools,&lt;ref name=&quot;Benson 2009. pp. 48–49&quot;&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 48–49.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United States Air Force]]'s [[School of Advanced Air and Space Studies]] (SAASS), which was designed to be similar to SAMS,&lt;ref name=&quot;West 1991. p. 10&quot;&gt;[[#Wes91|West 1991]]. p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref_label|C|c|none}} and the [[United States Marine Corps]]'s [[School of Advanced Warfighting]] (SAW).&lt;ref name=&quot;Benson 2009. pp. 48–49&quot;/&gt; SAMS students from the 2002 and 2003 classes participated as planners in the preparations for the [[invasion of Iraq]] and the plan for the post-combat occupation.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Eisenhower Hall - October 2012.jpg|thumb|left|Eisenhower Hall, the home of SAMS from 1994 to 2011.]]

The school continued to change and develop, and an additional faculty expansion occurred in 2005–2006. Also, the Fellows' curriculum shifted further away from that of the AMSP program.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 50–51.&lt;/ref&gt; To keep pace with increasing demand for SAMS planners, the commander of the army's [[Training and Doctrine Command]] directed an expansion that was approved by the [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Chief of Staff of the Army]], and the school's 11th director, Colonel Steve Banach, began a winter-start course in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, SAMS provided planners to help forward-deployed headquarters plan operations and contingencies.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; The school moved to new premises in the newly renovated Muir Hall at Fort Leavenworth on 30 August 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Erickson 2011&quot;&gt;[[#Eri11|Erickson 2011]].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Contributions ==
{{Quote box
| quote  = &quot;I realized that the SAMS guy in the Division HQ was the go-to person for everyone.&quot;
| source = [[Mark Hertling|Lieutenant General Mark Hertling]], 1988 SAMS graduate.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;
| width  = 27%
| align  = right
| style = padding:8px;
}}

SAMS graduates have supported every major U.S. military campaign between 1984 and 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hun09|Huntoon 2009]]. p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; SAMS graduates are known for their &quot;critical thinking skill sets&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bow10|Bower 2010]]. p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; and are consistently called for by combatant commanders around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hun09|Huntoon 2009]]. p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, [[Brigadier General]] [[Sean MacFarland]] said, &quot;In a crisis, the president always asks, 'where are the aircraft carriers?' In the Army, leaders ask, 'Where are the SAMS graduates?' Just as the aircraft carrier was a game changer in naval warfare, SAMS graduates and practitioners of operational art have been game changers in land warfare.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Liewer 2010&quot;/&gt;

The school has been praised by senior U.S. military leaders. According to Major General David Hogg, &quot;SAMS has a reputation for producing skilled planners that can take complex ideas and develop cohesive plans.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bow11|Bower 2011]].&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, army Vice Chief of Staff [[Peter W. Chiarelli]] said that SAMS was &quot;at the forefront of the effort to remake strategic military planning for the 21st century&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liewer 2010&quot;/&gt;

== Facilities and Student Body ==
[[File:Muir Hall - March 2012.jpg|right|thumb|Muir Hall.]]
{{As of|2014}}, the SAMS teaching facilities are mainly housed in Muir Hall (image right), which was once a stable, and Flint Hall. The AMSP courses are taught mostly in Muir Hall—the current SAMS headquarters—while Flint Hall houses additional AMSP seminars and the AOASF seminars. Both buildings were renovated in 2011 and their classrooms accommodate seminars of about 16–18 students and an instructor. The renovations for Muir Hall cost $12.2 million, including $3 million in information systems that allow students to collaborate digitally, replicating a common practice seen in militaries today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Erickson 2011&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Classroom Activities, School of Advanced Military Studies, Fort Leavenworth, 2 November 2010.jpg|thumb|SAMS classroom activities, November 2010.]]

The application process includes an examination, an interview, and a supervisor assessment. Applicants must also complete the U.S. Army's [[Command and General Staff School]] or an equivalent intermediate-level education course offered by another uniformed service. The student body of SAMS comprises mostly U.S. Army [[Field officer|field grade officers]] from combat, combat support, and [[combat service support]] branches.&lt;ref name=&quot;General Staff College p. 2&quot;&gt;[[#Tri12|United States Army Command and General Staff College (SAMS Tri-Fold) 2012]]. p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 1987 the [[U.S. Air Force]] graduated three officers and officers from the [[U.S. Navy]] and [[U.S. Marine Corps]] graduated the following years.  U.S. government agencies began sending students to SAMS in 2007.  The [[Department of State]], [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] and [[United States Agency for International Development]] (USAID) have provided students to the school.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tri12|School of Advanced Military Studies (SAMS Tri-Fold)]]. p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, [[Warrant Officer (United States)|Warrant officers]] first attended SAMS in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bow11|Bower 2011]]. p. A1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Allied foreign militaries also provide students. In 1999, the school graduated its first international officers—Norwegian and Canadian.&lt;ref name=&quot;General Staff College p. 2&quot;/&gt; Argentina, Australia, Colombia, France, Germany, Hungary, India, Jordan, Republic of Macedonia, the Netherlands, Pakistan, Romania, South Korea, Brazil, Spain, and the United Kingdom have also sent students through the course.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liewer 2010&quot;/&gt;

== Curricula ==

=== Advanced Military Studies Program ===

Most students participate in the Advanced Military Studies Program (AMSP). In 2009, the school held eight AMSP seminars.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tri12|United States Army Command and General Staff College (SAMS Tri-Fold) 2012]]. p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; AMSP is intended to educate students in &quot;military arts and science&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Liewer 2010&quot;/&gt; and focuses on operational art and covers a variety of subjects, including military problem solving; military theory and history, military doctrine, operational planning; battle dynamics, operational theory and practice, contemporary military operations, and the application of national elements of power.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;[[#350-1|United States Army Combined Arms Center and School]]. p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Besides classroom studies and operational exercises, students must complete a research monograph{{Ref_label|D|d|none}} and an oral examination.&lt;ref&gt;[[#US05|United States Army Command and General Staff College 2005]]. p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; After graduating, officers serve on a division, corps, or Army Service Component Command staff, or in a functional area assignment.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;[[#350-1|United States Army Combined Arms Center and School]]. p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box
| quote  = &quot;AMSP graduates are eagerly sought out by senior commanders for addition to their staffs as high-level planners and in other capacities demanding a more sophisticated appreciation of the operational level of war, joint operations, and the evolving contemporary operating environment.&quot;
| source = United States Army Command and General Staff College.&lt;ref&gt;[[#US05|United States Army Command and General Staff College 2005]]. p. 30.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/ref&gt;
| width  = 27%
| align  = right
| style = padding:8px;
}}

=== Advanced Operational Art Studies Fellowship ===
[[File:Fort Leavenworth Bldg 315 Flint Hall.jpg|thumb|left|Flint Hall, circa 1980s. Flint Hall was the home of SAMS from 1985 to 1994. In January 2012, portions of SAMS instruction began again at the newly renovated Flint Hall.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;]]

The AOASF is the school's senior program,&lt;ref name=&quot;General Staff College p. 2&quot;/&gt; and focuses on planning and executing full-spectrum operations with government and nongovernmental agencies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Liewer 2010&quot;/&gt; Its students comprise senior lieutenant colonels, colonels, and their civilian equivalents. Military AOASF fellows have typically commanded a battalion-sized unit in the armed services.&lt;ref&gt;[[#US05|United States Army Command and General Staff College 2005]]. p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; The course is equivalent to the [[United States Army War College|U.S. Army War College]],&lt;ref&gt;[[#US05|United States Army Command and General Staff College 2005]]. p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; and instructs 16 students annually.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;/&gt;

The program began in 1984 as the Advanced Operational Studies Fellowship (AOSF) by diverting [[lieutenant colonel]] War College selectees to Fort Leavenworth for an equivalent education program; these officers remained for a second year to help instruct AMSP students.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Nay91|Naylor 1991]]. p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; Because highly qualified officers could not remain at the faculty permanently, this program was designed to mitigate the effects of periodic faculty reassignments due to operational requirements. The AOSF program allowed students to complete the AMSP and then serve as the principal instructor of the AMSP during their second year. In 1995, the name of the program was changed to its current version, and in the early 21st century its curriculum was closer aligned with the strategic level of war.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 17–18, 50–51.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the first year, the AOASF curriculum includes classroom investigation of the multinational, joint and interagency environment, and extensive travel to the U.S. Defense Department's regional commands and headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;[[#US05|United States Army Command and General Staff College 2005]]. p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; In the second year, students become instructors of an AMSP seminar or take up other positions in the school.&lt;ref name=&quot;General Staff College p. 2&quot;/&gt; This course focuses on the operational and strategic realms of war and prepares students for assignments as leaders and to serve in critical staff positions within combatant and service component commands.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tri12|School of Advanced Military Studies (SAMS Tri-Fold)]]. p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; The course involves extensive travel, and the study of applied strategy, military theory, military history, strategic studies, campaign planning, regional studies, and practical work in joint planning.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; Fellows completing AOASF receive credit as a United States Army War College graduate,&lt;ref name=&quot;General Staff College p. 2&quot;/&gt;
and typically serve in a follow-on command assignment or work for a three- or four-star general officer as a member of his or her staff.&lt;ref&gt;[[#US05|United States Army Command and General Staff College 2005]]. p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notable graduates ==
*[[Charles C. Campbell (general)|General Charles C. Campbell]] (Class of 1986)
*[[David M. Rodriguez|General David M. Rodriguez]] (Class of 1989)
*[[Charles H. Jacoby, Jr.|General Charles H. Jacoby, Jr.]] (Class of 1991)
*[[William G. Webster|Lieutenant General William G. Webster]] (Class of 1984)&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
*[[William B. Caldwell, IV|Lieutenant General William B. Caldwell, IV]] (Class of 1988)
*[[Lieutenant General Mark P. Hertling]] (Class of 1988)
*[[David Huntoon|Lieutenant General David H. Huntoon]] (Class of 1988)&lt;ref&gt;[[#US09|United States Army Command and General Staff College 2009]]. This reference identifies Campbell, Dubik, Holder, and Huntoon as SAMS graduates.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Vincent K. Brooks|General Vincent K. Brooks]] (Class of 1992)
*[[John E. Sterling, Jr.|Lieutenant General John E. Sterling, Jr.]] (Class of 1992)

== Notes ==
{{refbegin}}
:'''a.'''{{Note_label|A|a|none}} According to Kevin Benson, the 10th director of the school, &quot;The first 'official' reference to the School of Advanced Military Studies (SAMS) graduates as Jedi Knights was on 12 May 1992 during a meeting of the Committee on Armed Services Military Education Panel in Washington D.C.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Congressman [[Ike Skelton]] stated, &quot;we all know that the real stamp of approval came when General Schwarzkopf requested SAMS graduates, sometimes referred to as 'Jedi Knights,&quot; be sent to his headquarters in Riyadh to assist in developing the campaign plan.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;House Committee on Armed Services, ''Advanced Military Studies Programs at the Command and Staff Colleges'', Hearings on H.A.S.C. No. 102-80, 102d Congress, 2d session, 1993, p. 5, quoted in [[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''b.'''{{Note_label|B|b|none}} The other two officers assigned to assist Wass de Czege in preparing the curricula for the school were Lieutenant Colonels Hal Winton and Douglas Johnson.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 6, 8–10.&lt;/ref&gt; Another key member of the SAMS staff was Mrs. Candace Hamm whose service to the school since 1988 earned her the title of &quot;''godmother'' of SAMS&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sch10|Schifferle 2010]]. p. ix.&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''c.'''{{Note_label|C|c|none}} SAASS's first director, Colonel William Fortner, stated in 1991 that the new school (originally called the School of Advanced Airpower Studies) &quot;will be similar to the Army's School of Advanced Military Studies at Fort Leavenworth&quot;, with additional focuses on air power topics.&lt;ref name=&quot;West 1991. p. 10&quot;/&gt;
:'''d.'''{{Note_label|D|d|none}} Initially, the requirement was to complete a master's thesis. School director Don Holder (1987–1989) changed this requirement to two monographs, the first with a tactical focus, and the second on an [[Operational level of war|operational]] level topic. This continued until the school's eighth director, Robin P. Swan (1998–2001) changed the monograph requirement back to one &quot;in the face of multiple and competing requirements&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ben09|Benson 2009]]. pp. 29–30, 46, 55.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{refend}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{Cite thesis |type= SAMS Monograph|title= The School of Advanced Military Studies in the 21st Century|url= |author= |last= Baggott|first= Christopher L.|year= 1998|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College}}
* {{cite journal |last1= Baker|first1= Jon E.|last2= Sepanic|first2= Jason R.|title= The School for Advanced Military Studies: An Untapped Resource for the Army Medical Department |journal= U.S. Army Medical Department Journal|publisher= U.S. Army Medical Department |volume= |issue= |ISSN = 1524-0436 |date= October–December 2010|pages= 78–80| ref = Bak10}}
* {{cite journal |last= Banach|first= Stefan J.|title= Educating by Design: Preparing Leaders for a Complex World|journal= Military Review|publisher= |volume= |issue= |ISSN= 0026-4148 |date= March–April 2009|pages= 96–104| ref = Ban09}}
* {{Cite thesis |type= SAMS Monograph|title= The Challenges of Leadership Development In the United States Army: Part II: The School of Advanced Military Studies (SAMS) |url= |author= |last= Barth|first= Frank L.|year= 2002|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College}}
*{{cite news |url= http://www.ftleavenworthlamp.com/newsnow/x2012969038/SAMS-graduates-renowned-for-skill-sets|title= SAMS graduates renowned for skill sets|last= Bower|first=Melissa|date= 9 December 2010| newspaper= The Lamp|accessdate= 18 April 2012 |ref=Bow10 }}
*{{cite news |url=  http://www.ftleavenworthlamp.com/community/community_features/x1984309365/SAMS-graduation-adds-to-pool-of-planners  | last = Bower | first = Melissa| title = SAMS graduation adds to pool of planners| newspaper = The Lamp| date = 8 December 2011 |ref=Bow11}}
* Brown, John S. &quot;The Maturation of Operational Art: Operation Desert Shield and Desert Storm.&quot; In {{cite book |title= Historical Perspectives of the Operational Art|edition= |editor-last= Krause|editor-first= Michael D.|editor2-last=Phillips|editor2-first=R. Cody|year= 2005|pages = 439–475|publisher= Center of Military History|location= Washington D.C.|ref = Bro05}}
*{{cite book |title= School of Advanced Military Studies Commemorative History: 1984–2009|edition= |last= Benson|first= Kevin|year= 2009|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College|location= Kansas|ref = Ben09}}
* {{Cite thesis |type= Ph. D. Diss.|title= Educating the Army's Jedi: The School of Advanced Military Studies and the Introduction of Operational Art into U.S. Army Doctrine, 1983–1994|author= |last= Benson|first= Kevin C. M.|year= 2010|publisher= University of Kansas|url=http://hdl.handle.net/1808/7716}}
*{{cite web |url= http://www.tonganoxiemirror.com/news/2011/aug/30/former-horse-stables-become-site-fort-leavenworth-/|title= Former Horse Stables Become Site of Fort Leavenworth Officer School after $12.2 Million Renovation |last= Erickson|first = Matt|date= 30 August 2011|publisher= The Tonganoxie Mirror|accessdate= 31 August 2011 |ref = Eri11}}
* {{Cite thesis |type= SAMS Monograph|title= Teaching and Learning the Operational Art of War: An Appraisal of the School of Advanced Military Studies|url= |author= |last= Gifford|first= John L.|year= 2000|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College}}
* {{Cite thesis |type= SAMS Monograph|title= Wants and Needs: SAMS’ Relationship with the Army|url= |author= |last= Goble|first= Jeffrey J.|year= 2008|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College}}
* {{cite journal |last= High|first= Gill|title= More than &quot;Officer U&quot;|journal= Soldiers|publisher= |volume= 54|issue= 4 |ISSN= 0093-8440 |date= April 1999|pages= 32–35| ref = Hig99}}
*{{cite web |url= http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/cgsc/events/SAMS25TH/HUNTOON%2025th%20SPEECH.pdf |title= Huntoon Speech|last= Huntoon|first = Samuel|date= 21 May 2009|work= |publisher= United States Army Combined Arms Center|accessdate= 16 December 2010|ref = Hun09}}
*{{Citation  | last = Kretchik| first = Walter E.  | title = Whither SAMS?| journal = Army Magazine| volume = 48 | issue = 12 | ISSN= 0093-8440 | pages = 31–34  | date = December 1998| ref = Kre98}}.
*{{cite web |url= http://usacac.army.mil/cac2/cgsc/events/sams/samsGrad1001.asp|title= SAMS Graduates Largest Class|last= Liewer|first=Steve|date= 21 May 2010|publisher= United States Army Combined Arms Center|accessdate= 16 December 2010 |ref = Lie10}}
*{{Citation  | last = Naylor| first = Sean D.| title = 'Jedi Knights' Put Together a Winning Plan| journal = Air Force Times| volume = 38 | ISSN= 0002-2403 | pages = 10, 16  | date = 29 April 1991| ref = Nay91}}.
*{{cite web |url= http://usacac.army.mil/cac2/cgsc/repository/SAMS_KCStar_Plank.pdf|title= Inside Modern Military Training|first= Lori|last= Plank |date= 16 April 2010|work= Kansas City Star|publisher= U.S. Army Combined Arms Center|location= Kansas |accessdate= 16 December 2010 |ref = Pla10}}
*{{cite book |last= Romjue|first= John L. |title= American Army Doctrine for the Post-Cold War |series= TRADOC Historical Monograph Series|date= |year= 1996 |publisher= Headquarters, United States Army Training and Doctrine Command, Military History Office|location= Fort Monroe, Virginia |ref=Rom96}}
*{{cite book |last1= Romjue|first1= John L. |last2= Canedy|first2= Susan |last3= Chapman|first3= Anne W. |title= Prepare the Army for War: A Historical Overview of the Army Training and Doctrine Command, 1973–1993 |series= TRADOC Historical Monograph Series|date= |year= 1993 |publisher= Headquarters, United States Army Training and Doctrine Command, Office of the Command Historian|location= Fort Monroe, Virginia}}
*{{Citation  | last = Scales| first = Robert H.| title = Return of the Jedi| journal = Armed Forces Journal
| ISSN = 0196-3597 | pages = 22–25, 45  | date = October 2009| ref = Sca09}}.
*{{cite book |last= Schifferle|first= Peter J.|title= America's School for War: Fort Leavenworth, Officer Education, and Victory in World War II |series= Modern War Studies|date= |year= 2010|publisher= University Press of Kansas|location= |isbn=978-0700617142 |ref = Sch10}}
* {{cite book |editor1-first= Richard W. |editor1-last= Stewart |title= The United States Army in a Global Era, 1917–2008 |edition= Second|volume= II|year= 2010 |series = American Military History |publisher= United States Army Center of Military History|location= Washington D.C.|ref = Ste10}}
* {{Cite thesis |type= Ph. D. Diss.|title= Raising a Pragmatic Army: Officer Education at the U.S. Army Command and General Staff College|url= |author= |last= Stewart|first= Michael David|year= 2010|publisher= University of Kansas}}
* {{cite book |last=Swain |first=Richard M. |chapter=Filling the Void: The Operational Art and the U.S. Army |editor=B.J.C. McKercher and Michael Hennesey |title=Operational Art: Developments in the Theories of War |year=1996 |publisher=Praeger Publishers |isbn=978-0275953058 |ref=Swa96 }}
*{{cite book|last=United States|title=DA Pamphlet 600-3: Commissioned Officer Professional Development and Career Management|date=1 February 2010|publisher=Headquarters, Department of the Army|location=Washington D.C.|page=44|ref=US2010}}
*{{cite book |last= United States Army Command and General Staff College|first= |title= Self-Study Report|date= December 2005|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College|location= Fort Leavenworth, Kansas|ref = US05}}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wMOFbyPjq3I|title= SAMS 25th Anniversary Documentary|author= United States Army Command and General Staff College|date= 2 June 2009|work= YouTube|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College|accessdate= 21 May 2011 |ref = US09}}
*{{cite book |last= United States Army Command and General Staff College|first= |title= Intermediate Level Education: Self-Study Report|date= 8 January 2008|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College|location= Fort Leavenworth, Kansas|ref = US08}}
*{{cite web |url= http://usacac.army.mil/cac2/cgsc/Events/SAMS25th/SAMSTri-fold.pdf |title= School of Advanced Military Studies (SAMS Tri-Fold)|author= United States Army Command and General Staff College|work= School of Advanced Military Studies|publisher= United States Command and General Staff College |accessdate= 3 March 2012 |ref = Tri12}}
*{{cite web |url= http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/cgsc/repository/350-1.pdf|title= Command and General Staff College Circular 350-1|author= United States Army Combined Arms Center and School|date= |work= |publisher= United States Army Combined Arms Center and School|accessdate= 6 March 2012|ref = 350-1}}
*{{cite web |author=United States Army Command and General Staff College |authorlink=United States Army Command and General Staff College |title=CGSC - Command and General Staff College: '''''School of Advanced Military Studies''' - Converting intellectual power into combat power.'' |work=www.cgsc.edu |url=http://www.cgsc.edu/SAMS/about.asp |accessdate=11 August 2013 |ref=About10}}
*{{cite web |url= http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/contentdm/sams.htm|title= Combined Arms Research Library Digital|author= United States Army Command and General Staff College|date= 13 July 2011|publisher= U.S. Army Command and General Staff College|location= Kansas |accessdate= 13 July 2011 |ref= CARL11 }}
*{{cite book |last= United States Army Training and Doctrine Command|first= |title= Transforming the Army: TRADOC's First Thirty Years, 1973–2003|series= TRADOC Historical Monograph Series|date= |year= 2003|publisher= Headquarters, United States Army Training and Doctrine Command, Military History Office|location= Fort Monroe, Virginia}}
* United States, Congress, ''Another Crossroads? Professional Military Education Twenty Years after the Goldwater-Nichols Act and the Skelton Panel''. 111th Congress. 1st Sess. 20 May 2009. United States Government Printing Office. Washington D.C. 2010.
*{{cite web |url= http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/cgsc/events/SAMS25TH/index.asp|title= SAMS 25th Anniversary Celebration: A Quarter Century of Excellence in Education|author= United States Army Command and General Staff College Public Affairs|date= 10 August 2010|publisher= United States Army Combined Arms Center|accessdate= 16 December 2010 |ref = 25th10}}
* {{cite book |title= Triumph Without Victory: The Unreported History of the Persian Gulf War |last= U.S. News and World Report|first= |year= 1992|publisher= Random House|location= New York and Toronto|isbn= 0-8129-1948-3|ref=USN92}}
* {{cite journal |last1= Wass de Czege|first1= Huba |title= How to Change an Army|journal= Military Review|publisher= |volume= |ISSN = 0026-4148 |issue= |date= November 1984|pages= 33–49| ref = Was84}}
* {{cite journal |last1= Wass de Czege|first1= Huba |title= The School of Advanced Military Studies: An Accident of History|journal= Military Review|publisher= |volume= 89|issue= 4 |ISSN = 0026-4148 |date= July–August 2009|pages= 102–106| ref = Was09}}
*{{cite book |last= Wass de Czege|first= Huba|title= Army Staff College Level Training Study (Final Report)|date= 13 June 1983|publisher= United States Army Command and General Staff College|location= Fort Leavenworth, Kansas| ref = Was83}}
*{{Citation  | last = West| first = Joe| title = AF to Develop Soldier-scholar| journal = Air Force Times| volume = 38 | ISSN = 0002-2403| pages = 10, 16  | date = 29 April 1991| ref = Wes91}}.
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* {{cite web |url= https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nV7iawEvjvk|title= SAMS Graduation Documentary, MAY 2014 |author= United States Army Command and General Staff College|date= |work= |publisher= YouTube.com|accessdate= 23 May 2014 }}
* {{cite web |url= http://usacac.army.mil/cac2/cgsc/sams/index.asp|title= School of Advanced Military Studies|author= United States Army Command and General Staff College|date= 3 December 2010|publisher= United States Army Combined Arms Center |accessdate= 16 December 2010 }}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/war_stories/2003/04/force_majeure.html|title= Force Majeure: What lies behind the military's victory in Iraq |author= Fred Kaplan | authorlink = Fred Kaplan (journalist) |date= 10 April 2003|work= Slate.com|publisher= The Slate Group|accessdate= 3 April 2012 }}

{{United States military academies and colleges}}
{{TRADOC}}

{{Coord|39.01190|-98.48425|display=title}}

[[Category:Military facilities in Kansas|Army School of Advanced Military Studies]]
[[Category:Fort Leavenworth]]
[[Category:United States Army schools]]</text>
      <sha1>kviplks8e9nly7kir2eslz8lshnsimw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
