<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Siege of Berat (1280–81)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27476748</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745894023</id>
      <parentid>745236689</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T00:46:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>23 editor</username>
        <id>16532586</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Aftermath */ pp→p</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13076">{{For|other sieges of the city|Siege of Berat (disambiguation){{!}}Siege of Berat}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Siege of Berat
|image=[[File:ShepherdByzempire1265.jpg|260px]]
|caption=Map of the Byzantine Empire and the surrounding states in 1265.
|partof=the [[Byzantine–Latin Wars]]
|date=1280–1281
|place=[[Berat]], [[Albania]]
|result=[[Byzantine]] victory
|combatant1={{flag|Byzantine Empire}}
|combatant2=[[File:Image-Blason Sicile Péninsulaire.svg|21px]] [[Kingdom of Sicily]]
|commander1={{flagicon|Byzantine Empire}} [[Michael Tarchaneiotes]]
|commander2=[[File:Image-Blason Sicile Péninsulaire.svg|21px]] [[Hugo de Sully]]{{POW}}
|strength1=Unknown
|strength2=8,000 men
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
}}
{{Campaignbox Byzantine-Latin Wars}}
{{Campaignbox Wars of Michael VIII}}
The '''Siege of Berat''' in [[Albania]] by the forces of the [[Capetian House of Anjou|Angevin]] [[Kingdom of Sicily]] against the [[Byzantine]] garrison of the city took place in 1280–1281. [[Berat]] was a strategically important fortress, whose possession would allow the Angevins access to the heartlands of the Byzantine Empire. A Byzantine relief force arrived in spring 1281, and managed to ambush and capture the Angevin commander, [[Hugo de Sully]]. Thereupon, the Angevin army panicked and fled, suffering heavy losses in killed and wounded as it was attacked by the Byzantines. This defeat ended the threat of a land invasion of the Byzantine Empire, and along with the [[Sicilian Vespers]] marked the end of the Western threat to reconquer Byzantium.

==Background==
Ever since the Emperor [[Michael VIII Palaiologos]] (r. 1259–1282) recovered [[Constantinople]] from the [[Latin Empire]] in 1261, the restored [[Byzantine Empire]] faced the threat of a [[Latins#Middle Ages|Latin]] [[crusade]] to reclaim the city. The antagonistic Greek [[Despotate of Epirus]] and the [[Latinokratia|Latin states]] of southern Greece, fearful of the Byzantine resurgence, sought aid from the [[Kingdom of Sicily]], first under [[Manfred of Sicily]] (r. 1258–1266), and after 1266 under the ambitious [[Charles of Anjou]] (r. 1266–1285), who quickly established himself as Byzantium's chief antagonist. Countering the Angevin ruler's alliances and efforts to conquer Byzantium would occupy the remainder of Michael VIII's reign.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fine|1994|pp=156–170, 184–194}}; {{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=47ff., 139ff., 189–190}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1258, the Sicilians took possession of the island of [[Corfu]] and the [[Albania]]n coast, from [[Dyrrhachium]] to [[Vlorë|Valona]] and [[Buthrotum]] and as far inland as [[Berat]]. This gave Manfred a strategically vital beachhead in the Balkans, controlling the western terminus of the great [[Via Egnatia]], the main overland route to Constantinople. Already in the 11th and 12th centuries, the same area had been the target of the [[Normans]] of southern Italy in their [[Byzantine–Norman wars|attacks on the Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=49–50, 235}}; {{harvnb|Setton|1976|pp=81, 109–110}}.&lt;/ref&gt; After overthrowing Manfred, in the [[Treaty of Viterbo]] (1267) Charles secured his recognition as Manfred's heir. In 1272, the Latin notables who had held the fortresses of Valona, [[Kaninë Castle|Kanina]], and Berat for Manfred surrendered them to Charles, and soon afterwards Charles's troops took Dyrrhachium too. Having secured the support of many Albanian chieftains, Charles proclaimed the establishment of the [[Kingdom of Albania (medieval)|Kingdom of Albania]] in the same year.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fine|1994|pp=184–185}}; {{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=233–234}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Michael VIII countered the emerging threat by a diplomatic mission to the Papacy, which in the [[Second Council of Lyon]] (1274) agreed to the union of the Orthodox and Catholic churches, estranged after the [[East–West Schism|Great Schism]] of 1054, and thereby placed Michael and his empire under papal protection. Taking advantage of Charles's entanglement in the conflict between [[Guelphs and Ghibellines]] in Italy, in spring 1274 Michael launched an attack against Angevin holdings in Albania. Berat and Buthrotum were taken and Charles's troops were pushed back from the hinterland to the two ports of Valona and Dyrrhachium. Although these were assaulted several times in 1274–1275, they remained in Angevin hands.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=279–280}}; {{harvnb|Nicol|1993|p=58}}; {{harvnb|Fine|1994|p=187}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1279 however, Charles had established his control not only over the Latin states of Greece (after 1278 he was the [[Principality of Achaea|Prince of Achaea]]), but also received the submission and vassalage of [[Nikephoros I Komnenos Doukas|Nikephoros I]], Despot of Epirus.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nicol|1993|p=63}}; {{harvnb|Fine|1994|pp=185–186}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1279, in preparation for resuming his offensive against Michael along the Via Egnatia, Charles appointed as his vicar-general in Albania the Burgundian [[Hugo de Sully]]. Over the next year, Sully received a steady flow of supplies, siege equipment and reinforcements.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=329–330}}; {{harvnb|Setton|1976|pp=135–136}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The siege==
[[File:Berat Albania 15.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The entrance of the citadel of Berat, with the 13th-century Byzantine church of the Holy Trinity.]]
[[File:Berat Albania 17.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The river Osum, flowing through Berat, with the hill of the citadel on the left.]]

In August/September 1280, with an army of 2,000 knights and 6,000 infantry, Sully began his attack by storming the fortress of Kanina and then advancing to central Albania and laying siege to Berat. The situation was grave for Byzantium: Berat was, in the words of the historian Deno J. Geanakoplos &quot;the key to the Via Egnatia and all of [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]]&quot;. If it were taken, the Empire would lie open to an invasion, which, if joined by the Latin states of Greece and the Greek rulers of Epirus and [[Medieval Thessaly|Thessaly]], might result in the fall of Constantinople to Charles.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Setton|1976|pp=135–136}}; {{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=330–331}}; {{harvnb|Nicol|1993|p=65}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Responding to the pleas for reinforcements of the governor of Berat, Michael VIII ordered special prayers for the salvation of the Empire, and assembled an army headed by some of his best generals. The army's commander-in-chief was the ''[[megas domestikos]]'' [[Michael Tarchaneiotes]], with the ''[[megas stratopedarches]]'' [[John Synadenos (megas stratopedarches)|John Synadenos]], the ''[[despotes]]'' [[Michael Komnenos Doukas]] (the emperor's son-in-law), and the [[eunuch]] court official [[Andronikos Enopolites]] as subordinate commanders.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nicol|1993|p=65}}; {{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|p=331}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, the siege of Berat continued through the winter of 1280/1281. By early December, the Angevin forces had seized a number of outlying forts around the city and penetrated its suburbs. Charles, however, remained anxious to take the city before the Byzantine relief force arrived. He ordered his governors in Albania to direct all their resources towards the siege, and displayed his close interest by a series of letters to Sully, instructing him to take the city by assault if necessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Setton|1976|pp=136–137}}; {{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=331–332}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Byzantine force advanced cautiously, and arrived in the area in early spring 1281. The ''megas domestikos'' Tarchaneiotes avoided a direct confrontation and relied on ambushes and raids instead. He also managed to resupply the besieged fortress with provisions, which were loaded onto rafts and then left to float down the river [[Osum]] which flows by the citadel.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|p=332}}; {{harvnb|Nicol|1993|pp=65–66}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The besiegers became aware of this, and, unlike the Byzantines, the Angevin commanders were eager for a decisive confrontation. At this point, Sully resolved to reconnoitre the area personally, accompanied only by a bodyguard of 25 men. As he approached the Byzantine camp, he fell into an ambush by Turkish mercenaries serving in the Byzantine army. The Turks attacked the small troop, killed Sully's horse, scattered his guard, and captured him.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=332–333}}; {{harvnb|Nicol|1993|p=66}}; {{harvnb|Setton|1976|p=137}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A few of Sully's guards escaped and reached their camp, where they reported his capture. Panic spread among the Angevin troops at this news, and they began to flee towards Valona. The Byzantines took advantage of their disordered flight and attacked, joined by the troops in the besieged citadel. Many Latins fell, many others were captured as the Byzantines aimed their arrows at the less well-protected horses of the Latin knights, unhorsing them. The Byzantines also took an enormous booty, including all the numerous siege machines. Only a small remnant managed to cross the river [[Vjosë]] and reach the safety of Kanina.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Setton|1976|p=137}}; {{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|p=333}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The victory at Berat represented Michael VIII's greatest success in battle over the Latins since the [[Battle of Pelagonia]] 20 years earlier. The many prisoners, including Sully, were taken to Constantinople, where they were publicly paraded in a [[Roman triumph|triumph]] celebrated by the exultant emperor, who further ordered [[fresco]]es depicting scenes from the campaign painted in his palace.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nicol|1993|p=66}}; {{harvnb|Setton|1976|p=137}}; {{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|pp=333–334}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of their victory at Berat, the imperial troops restored their control over Albania, except the two Angevin strongholds of Dyrrhachium and Valona. The defeat ended Charles's designs of an overland assault on Byzantium, but the Angevin ruler now redoubled his efforts, aiming to launch a seaborne invasion of the Empire with [[Republic of Venice|Venetian]] aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|p=334}}; {{harvnb|Nicol|1993|pp=66–67}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This he secured with the [[Treaty of Orvieto]] in 1281. The Papacy also, after the election of the pro-Angevin [[Pope Martin IV|Martin IV]], finally sanctioned his plans, excommunicating Michael Palaiologos and ending the Union of the Churches. Michael VIII countered this with an alliance with [[Peter III of Aragon]] (r. 1276–1285), and with his support to various anti-Angevin forces in Italy. Just as Charles was ready to launch his attack, an uprising known as the [[Sicilian Vespers]] broke out on March 30, 1282. The subsequent [[War of the Sicilian Vespers|wars]], in large part the result of Michael's diplomatic efforts, ended the threat of Charles on Byzantium.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Geanakoplos|1959|p=335ff}}; {{harvnb|Setton|1976|p=138ff}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book|last=Bartusis|first=Mark C.|title=The Late Byzantine Army: Arms and Society, 1204–1453|location=Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|year=1997|isbn=0-8122-1620-2|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rUs-hHd89xAC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Fine|first=John Van Antwerp|title=The Late Medieval Balkans: A Critical Survey from the Late Twelfth Century to the Ottoman Conquest|location=Ann Arbor, Michigan|publisher=University of Michigan Press|year =1994|isbn=0-472-08260-4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Hh0Bu8C66TsC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Geanakoplos|first=Deno John|title=Emperor Michael Palaeologus and the West, 1258–1282 - A Study in Byzantine-Latin Relations|location=Cambridge, Massachusetts|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=1959|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MPscAAAAYAAJ|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Nicol|first=Donald MacGillivray|authorlink=Donald Nicol|title=The Last Centuries of Byzantium, 1261–1453|location=Cambridge, United Kingdom|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1993|isbn=0-521-43991-4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y2d6OHLqwEsC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Setton|first=Kenneth Meyer|title=The Papacy and the Levant, 1204–1571: Volume I. The Thirteenth and Fourteenth Centuries|location=Independence Hall, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|publisher=The American Philosophical Society|year=1976|isbn=0-87169-114-0|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=i4OPORrVeXQC|ref=harv}}
{{refend|2}}

{{coord missing|Albania}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Siege Of Berat (1280-1281)}}
[[Category:Military history of Albania|Berat]]
[[Category:Sieges involving the Byzantine Empire|Berat]]
[[Category:13th century in Albania]]
[[Category:History of Berat]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1280]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1281]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Kingdom of Sicily|Berat]]
[[Category:13th century in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:1280 in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:1281 in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:1280 in Europe]] 
[[Category:1281 in Europe]]
[[Category:Charles I of Naples]]
[[Category:Michael VIII Palaiologos]]</text>
      <sha1>p967me29em83pd0q7pdducw27mqijmc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
