<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Siege of Bjelovar Barracks</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44327410</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748794205</id>
      <parentid>748793820</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-10T12:28:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PidgeCopetti</username>
        <id>17587958</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37721">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|image={{Location map+| Croatia | width=300| float=right
| caption=
| overlay_image =
| places =
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Varaždin]] | lat=46.308996 | long=16.328032 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=left}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Čakovec]] | lat=46.38957 | long=16.431715 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=right}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Koprivnica]] | lat=46.166041 | long=16.8207 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=right| mark= Blue pog.svg}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Križevci, Croatia|Križevci]] | lat=46.022237 | long=16.541922 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=left}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Bjelovar]] | lat=45.896699 | long=16.843016 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=bottom| mark= Blue pog.svg}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Virovitica]] | lat=45.829517 | long=17.389243 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| position=right}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=Captured by Croatia | lat=43.2 | long=13.392334 | label_size=75 | marksize=6 | position=right}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=Controlled by the JNA | lat=42.8 | long=13.392334 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| mark= Blue pog.svg| position=right}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=[[Okučani]] | lat=45.260389 | long=17.197723 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| mark= Yellow pog.svg | position=bottom}}
{{Location map~|Croatia| label=Detached units | lat=42.4 | long=13.392334 | label_size=75 | marksize=6| mark= Yellow pog.svg | position=right}}
}}
|caption=Major barracks of the JNA 32nd Corps, 29&amp;nbsp;September&amp;nbsp;1991
|date=14 – 29 September 1991
|conflict=Siege of Bjelovar Barracks
|partof=the [[Battle of the Barracks]]
|place=[[Croatia]]
|result=Croatian victory
|combatant1= {{flagicon|Croatia}} [[Croatian National Guard]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Croatia}} [[Croatian Police]]
|combatant2= [[File:Flag of SFR Yugoslavia.svg|22px|border|link=|alt=|Yugoslav People's Army]] [[Yugoslav People's Army]]
|commander1= {{flagicon|Croatia}} Želimir Škarec
|commander2= [[File:Flag of SFR Yugoslavia.svg|22px|border|link=|alt=]] [[Milan Tepić]]{{KIA}} &lt;br&gt; [[File:Flag of SFR Yugoslavia.svg|22px|border|link=|alt=]] Rajko Kovačević{{POW}}{{executed}}
|strength1= unknown
|strength2= approx. 550
|casualties1= 17 killed
|casualties2= 14 killed, 30 wounded&lt;br&gt;425 captured
|casualties3= 5 civilians killed, 70 Croatian troops and civilians wounded
}}
{{Campaignbox Croatian War of Independence}}
The '''Siege of Bjelovar Barracks''', also known by the [[codename]] '''Operation Bilogora''' ({{lang-hr|Operacija Bilogora}}), was the blockade and capture of the [[Yugoslav People's Army]] (JNA) barracks and other facilities in and around the city of [[Bjelovar]], a part of the JNA 32nd ([[Varaždin]]) Corps, during the [[Croatian War of Independence]]. A general blockade of the JNA facilities in Croatia was ordered on 14 September 1991, and it continued until 29 September when the JNA garrison was captured by Croatian forces. Its capture occurred one week after the [[Siege of Varaždin Barracks|bulk of the 32nd Corps surrendered]]. It was part of the [[Battle of the Barracks]]—an effort by Croatian armed forces to isolate JNA units based at barracks in Croatia, or capture the barracks to provide arms for Croatia's nascent army.

The fighting resulted in the capture of a substantial stock of weapons, including 78 tanks, 77 [[infantry fighting vehicle]]s and 13 artillery pieces greater than {{convert|100|mm|adj=on}} [[caliber]]. The clash also caused considerable damage to the city of Bjelovar and its surroundings due to artillery fire and the explosion of an ammunition storage depot on the outskirts of the city. The fighting erupted despite a ceasefire that had been arranged days before, and caused JNA [[General]] [[Veljko Kadijević]] to withdraw from negotiations regarding the ceasefire's implementation. He subsequently issued an ultimatum to Croatian authorities, warning against the capture of further JNA facilities.

==Background==
In 1990, ethnic tensions between [[Serbs]] and [[Croats]] worsened after the [[Croatian parliamentary election, 1990|electoral defeat]] of the government of the [[Socialist Republic of Croatia]] by the [[Croatian Democratic Union]] ({{lang-hr|Hrvatska demokratska zajednica}} – HDZ). The [[Yugoslav People's Army]] ({{lang-sr|''Jugoslovenska Narodna Armija''}} – JNA) confiscated Croatia's [[Territorial Defense Forces (Yugoslavia)|Territorial Defence]] ({{lang-hr|Teritorijalna obrana|links=no}} – TO) weapons to minimize resistance.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=117}} On 17 August, the tensions escalated into an [[Log Revolution|open revolt]] of the [[Serbs of Croatia|Croatian Serbs]],{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=118}} centred on the predominantly Serb-populated areas of the [[Dalmatia]]n hinterland around [[Knin]] (approximately {{convert|60|km|abbr=off}} north-east of [[Split, Croatia|Split]]),{{sfn|The New York Times|19 August 1990}} parts of the [[Lika]], [[Kordun]], [[Banovina (region)|Banovina]] and [[eastern Croatia]].{{sfn|ICTY|12 June 2007}} In January 1991, [[Republic of Serbia (1990–2006)|Serbia]], supported by [[Socialist Republic of Montenegro|Montenegro]] and Serbia's provinces of [[Vojvodina]] and [[Autonomous Province of Kosovo and Metohija|Kosovo]], unsuccessfully tried to obtain the [[Yugoslav Presidency]]'s approval for a JNA operation to disarm Croatian security forces.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|pp=118–119}} The request was denied and [[Pakrac clash|a bloodless skirmish]] between Serb insurgents and [[Lučko Anti-Terrorist Unit|Croatian special police]] in March{{sfn|Ramet|2006|pp=384–385}} prompted the JNA itself to ask the Federal Presidency to give it wartime authority and declare a state of emergency. Even though the request was backed by Serbia and its allies, the JNA request was refused on 15 March. Serbian President [[Slobodan Milošević]], preferring a campaign to expand Serbia rather than to preserve [[Socialist Federative Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] with Croatia as a federal unit, publicly threatened to replace the JNA with a Serbian army and declared that he no longer recognized the authority of the federal Presidency. The threat caused the JNA to abandon plans to preserve Yugoslavia in favour of expansion of Serbia as the JNA came under Milošević's control.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=119}} By the end of  March, the conflict had escalated with [[Plitvice Lakes incident|the first fatalities]].{{sfn|Engelberg|3 March 1991}} In early April, leaders of the Serb revolt in Croatia declared their intention to amalgamate the areas under their control with Serbia. These were viewed by the [[Government of Croatia]] as breakaway regions.{{sfn|Sudetic|2 April 1991}}

At the beginning of 1991, Croatia had no regular army. To bolster its defence, Croatia doubled its police numbers to about 20,000. The most effective part of the Croatian police force was [[Croatian special police order of battle in 1991–95|3,000-strong special police]] comprising twelve [[battalion]]s organised along military lines. There were also 9,000–10,000 regionally organised reserve police in 16 battalions and 10 companies, but they lacked weapons.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=86}} In response to the deteriorating situation, the Croatian government established the [[Croatian National Guard]] ({{lang-hr|Zbor narodne garde|links=no}} – ZNG) in May by expanding the special police battalions into four all-professional guards brigades. Under [[Ministry of Defence (Croatia)|Ministry of Defence]] control and commanded by retired JNA [[General]] [[Martin Špegelj]], the four guards brigades comprised approximately 8,000 troops.{{sfn|EECIS|1999|pp=272–278}} The reserve police, also expanded to 40,000, was attached to the ZNG and reorganised into 19 brigades and 14 independent battalions. The guards brigades were the only units of the ZNG that were fully equipped with [[small arms]]; throughout the ZNG there was a lack of heavier weapons and there was poor command and control structure above the brigade level.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=86}} The shortage of heavy weapons was so severe that the ZNG resorted to using [[World War II]] weapons taken from museums and film studios.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=400}} At the time, the Croatian weapon stockpile consisted of 30,000 small arms purchased abroad and 15,000 previously owned by the police. To replace the personnel lost to the guards brigades, a new 10,000-strong special police was established.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=86}}

==Prelude==
The views of the Croatian leadership on how to deal with the JNA's role in the Croatian Serb revolt gradually evolved between January and September 1991. Croatian President [[Franjo Tuđman]]'s initial plan was to win [[European Community]] (EC) and [[United States]] support, so he dismissed Špegelj's advice to seize JNA barracks and storage facilities in Croatia in late 1990. During the [[Ten-Day War]] in June and July 1991, Špegelj once again urged Tuđman to act while the JNA fought [[Slovenia]]'s TO. Špegelj's calls were echoed by [[Šime Đodan]], who succeeded him as Defence Minister in July. Špegelj remained in command of the ZNG.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=91}}

Tuđman's initial stance was based on his belief that Croatia could not win a war against the JNA. The ZNG was therefore limited to conducting defensive operations, even though the actions of the JNA appeared to be coordinated with Croatian Serb forces.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=91}} This impression was reinforced by buffer zones established by the JNA after fighting between Croatian Serb militia and the ZNG. The JNA often intervened after the ZNG had lost territory, leaving the Croatian Serbs in control of areas they had captured before the JNA stepped in. The JNA provided some weapons to the Croatian Serbs, although most of their weaponry was sourced from Serbia's TO and the Serbian [[Ministry of Internal Affairs (Serbia)|Ministry of Internal Affairs]].{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=92}}

In July 1991, Špegelj and Đodan's advice was supported by a number of [[Croatian Parliament]] members. In response, Tuđman dismissed Đodan the same month he was appointed Defence Minister, and Špegelj resigned his command of the ZNG on 3 August. The deteriorating situation in eastern Croatia,{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=91}} including the JNA expulsion of ZNG troops from [[Baranja]], intermittent fighting around [[Osijek]], [[Vukovar]] and [[Vinkovci]],{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=93}} increasing losses and the growing conviction that the JNA were actively supporting the Croatian Serb revolt, forced Tuđman to act. On 22 August, he issued an ultimatum to the federal Yugoslav authorities demanding the withdrawal of the JNA to its barracks by the end of the month. The ultimatum stated that if the JNA failed to comply, Croatia would consider it an army of occupation and take corresponding action.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=91}} On 1 September, the EC proposed a ceasefire and a peace conference was accepted by the Yugoslav Presidency and by Tuđman, despite his earlier ultimatum. The conference started on 7 September, but only four days later, the Croatian member and chair of the presidency, [[Stjepan Mesić]], ordered the JNA to return to its barracks within 48 hours.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=94}} This order was motivated by Tuđman's concern that the conference would drag on while the ZNG lost territory. Even though the order was opposed by other members of the presidency, it gave Croatia justification to openly confront the JNA.{{sfn|CIA|2002|pp=94–95}}

[[Prime Minister of Croatia|Prime Minister]] [[Franjo Gregurić]] advised Tuđman to implement Špegelj's plan.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=400}} According to General [[Anton Tus]], Tuđman ordered the ZNG to capture JNA barracks on 12 September, but rescinded the order the next day. The order was reinstated on 14 September after Tus pleaded with Tuđman to re-authorize action, arguing that the ZNG was running out of time.{{sfn|Žabec|28 May 2011}} The same day, the ZNG and the Croatian police blockaded and cut utilities to all JNA facilities it had access to, beginning the [[Battle of the Barracks]].{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=95}} This action comprised blockades of 33 large JNA garrisons in Croatia,{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=401}} and numerous smaller facilities, including border posts, and weapons and ammunition storage depots.{{sfn|CIA|2002|p=95}}

==Order of battle==
Since 1988, the JNA's [[Bjelovar]] garrison had been included in the 32nd Corps, which was headquartered in [[Varaždin]],{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=11}} and was the second largest JNA corps in Croatia.{{sfn|Hoare|2010|p=121}} It commanded the 32nd Mechanised Brigade and the 32nd Mixed Artillery Regiment both based in Varaždin, the 32nd Engineer Regiment in [[Čakovec]], the 411th Mixed Antitank Artillery Regiment based in [[Križevci, Croatia|Križevci]], the 73rd Motorised Brigade headquartered in [[Koprivnica]], the 265th Mechanised Brigade based in Bjelovar,{{sfn|Hrastović|2006|p=122}} and the 288th Mixed Antitank Artillery Brigade in [[Virovitica]].{{sfn|Škvorc|2010|loc=note 36}} The JNA did not have sufficient troops in the area to secure all its facilities,{{sfn|Bjelajac|Žunec|2009|p=247}} but it was possible that the 5th ([[Banja Luka]]) Corps units deployed to Okučani might attempt to relieve some of the garrisons.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=18}} A part of the 265th Mechanised Brigade was deployed to Koprivnica to reinforce the 73rd Motorised Brigade.{{sfn|Raguž|2009|p=205}} It consisted of a [[Battalion#Tank Battalion|battalion of tanks]] and one engineer battalion, and they were relocated to Koprivnica in August 1990 to boost the JNA's presence in the town.{{sfn|Raguž|2009|pp=176–177}} A battlegroup comprising 23 armoured and 14 other vehicles,{{sfn|Škvorc|2010|loc=note 32}} drawn from the 265th Mechanised Brigade and commanded by [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Milan Čeleketić]],{{sfn|Raguž|2009|p=173}} was deployed to Okučani. It was attached to the 5th Corps{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=19}} on 15 August to prevent Croatian special police from ousting Croatian Serb forces from the town.{{sfn|Raguž|2009|p=173}}

Bjelovar also hosted the headquarters of the 28th Partisan Division (TO) and one of the division's brigades.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=11}} The most significant JNA facility in Bjelovar and its immediate surroundings was the Božidar Adžija Barracks, situated on the western outskirts of the city. The barracks housed Bjelovar garrison headquarters and the bulk of the weaponry of the 265th Mechanised Brigade, and approximately 500 officers and soldiers. There was a JNA non-combat facility in the centre of Bjelovar, protected by a small security detail, a [[radar]] base and an [[anti-aircraft defence]] communications hub in the village of [[Zvijerci]], adjacent to the settlement of [[Trojstveni Markovac]] on the northern outskirts of Bjelovar, and two storage depots. The Logor Depot was used to store tanks and other equipment of the 265th Mechanised Brigade and weapons that had been confiscated from the TO in Bjelovar, and was guarded by approximately 50 troops. The Barutana Depot was used to store ammunition. Unlike the Logor Depot,  which was situated in the city itself, the Barutana Depot was located in the Bedenik Forest near Bjelovar.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=12}}

Croatia established a company-sized special police unit in Bjelovar on 23 February 1991.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=12}} Following the deterioration of the situation in western [[Slavonia]], the 105th Brigade of the ZNG was raised in the city, largely equipped with small arms only, and plans for a blockade of the routes in and out of the city were developed.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|pp=12–13}} A crisis headquarters was set up to coordinate the defence of the city and the manufacture of weapons in industrial plants which had been modified for their production.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|pp=16–17}}

==Timeline==

===Growing tensions and the blockade===
[[File:HVO Army T-55 Glamoc setup.jpg|right|thumb|The ZNG captured 75 JNA [[T-55]] tanks in Bjelovar.]]
The first significant conflict involving the JNA in the Bjelovar area occurred on 1 September, when 14 JNA officers and soldiers were disarmed at a Croatian checkpoint. The commanding officer of the Bjelovar JNA garrison, [[Colonel]] Rajko Kovačević, demanded that the weapons to be returned, however the Croatian forces declined the request, claiming that the weapons had already been sent to Zagreb. Tensions greatly increased after 18 ZNG troops from the 105th Brigade, deployed from Bjelovar, went missing during the [[Battle of Kusonje]] on 9 September. The civilian authorities in the city demanded that the JNA provide information on their fate, but the JNA declared it had no knowledge of the matter.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=17}}

By 22 September, Croatian forces had besieged and captured all major garrisons of the 32nd Corps, except those in Bjelovar and Koprivnica.{{sfn|Škvorc|2010|loc=note 36}} The JNA garrisons in those two cities were ordered to extract themselves to territory near Okučani that was under the control of the 5th Corps. The Koprivnica-based garrison was ordered to break out to Bjelovar, link up with the 265th Mechanised Brigade, then proceed towards [[Daruvar]] via [[Grubišno Polje]].{{sfn|Raguž|2009|p=205}} At the same time, the Bjelovar garrison had been blockaded, and its utilities and supplies were cut. Negotiations ensued for the surrender of the garrison, led by the civilian crisis headquarters{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=19}} presided over by Jure Šimić.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=21}} The negotiations stalled when the JNA demanded that the 265th Mechanised Brigade be allowed to evacuate to Okučani or Bosnia and Herzegovina.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=20}} At the time, a number of Croatian Serb civilians took refuge in the barracks either fearing for their safety or in order to isolate themselves from the Croatian authorities.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|pp=19–20}}

===Preparations for attack===
[[File:PT-76 01.JPG|right|thumb|Three [[PT-76]] amphibious tanks were captured by the ZNG in Bjelovar.]]
Preparations to seize the JNA facilities in Bjelovar took place on 21–29 September. These involved the placing of obstacles around the JNA facilities, setting up of artillery and air defence units, and drafting of plans to capture the JNA garrison, [[codename]]d Operation Bilogora.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=18}} The 1st Battalion of the 105th Brigade was deployed to around the villages of Bedenik and [[Velika Pisanica]], the 2nd Battalion in the village of [[Narta, Croatia|Narta]], and the 3rd Battalion north of Bjelovar, thereby encircling the city. In the city itself, nine battlegroups were deployed to attack armoured units which might attempt a breakout. Air defence systems consisting of two {{convert|12.7|mm|adj=on}} machine guns and two {{convert|20|mm|adj=on}} anti-aircraft guns were set up in nearby villages.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=20}} A [[Artillery battery|battery]] of towed {{convert |100|mm|adj=on}} [[T-12 antitank gun]]s was deployed to the Hrgovljani area.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=22}} In an attempt to mitigate an overall shortage of anti-tank weapons, 200 [[Molotov cocktail]]s were sent from Zagreb and three [[armoured personnel carrier]]s armed with [[9M14 Malyutka]] [[anti-tank guided missile]] systems arrived from Virovitica on 23 September.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=20}} The crisis headquarters was to coordinate all activities of the Croatian armed forces based in Bjelovar, as well as reinforcements received from Varaždin after the [[Siege of Varaždin Barracks|JNA garrison based there surrendered]], but Colonel Želimir Škarec, a member of the [[General Staff of the Armed Forces of the Republic of Croatia]], was appointed as the commanding officer of the military operation.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=18}}

Despite the ceasefire agreement signed on 22 September between the JNA and Croatia, which provided for the resumption of supplies to the JNA barracks, the authorities in Bjelovar refused to restore utilities, claiming that the agreement allowed for the supply of JNA officers and soldiers only, but there were also civilians sheltering in the barracks.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=19}} On 27 September, the Croatian General Staff directed that the garrison be captured on 28–30 September.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=18}} Tus, acting as the [[Chief of the General Staff of the Armed Forces of the Republic of Croatia|Chief of the General Staff]], ordered the clandestine killing of extremists before they caused mass killing of civilians or great material damage.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|pp=18–19}} According to Tus, this order was based on an assessment that there were extremist JNA officers present in Bjelovar, intent on carrying out such acts.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|loc=note 47}}

===Capture of the garrison===
[[File:M94 Plamen S 128mm 3.jpg|right|thumb|The ZNG captured four JNA [[M-63 Plamen]] [[multiple rocket launcher]]s in Bjelovar.]]
On the morning of 29 September, the ZNG and Croatian police attacked the JNA facilities in Bjelovar. In response, Kovačević contacted the JNA 5th Military District in Zagreb and requested [[airstrike]]s against the city and the ZNG. The sources do not indicate if the requested airstrikes were carried out.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=21}} The 5th Military District instead pressured the central Croatian authorities to order the ZNG in Bjelovar to observe a comprehensive ceasefire previously agreed between Croatia and the JNA on 22 September.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=19}} In order to verify the ceasefire, the [[European Community Monitor Mission]] (ECMM) deployed a monitoring team to the city. However, the authorities in Bjelovar ignored the order they received from the General Staff and stopped the ECMM team before it reached the city. According to Šimić, the move was made after [[Lieutenant General]] [[Petar Stipetić]] telephoned him and urged him to continue the attack.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=21}} The authenticity of Šimić's account of has been disputed by [[Admiral]] [[Davor Domazet-Lošo]], who claims it was an attempt to discredit Croatia before the ECMM.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|loc=note 57}} At 19:00, the ZNG captured Božidar Adžija Barracks.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=21}} By that time, all other JNA facilities in and near Bjelovar had been captured.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=22}}

Before Barutana Depot was captured by the ZNG, one of the four storage structures, containing {{convert|1700|t|abbr=off}} of ammunition, was blown up by JNA [[Major]] [[Milan Tepić]].{{sfn|Ivanković|14 September 2005}} The explosion occurred at 10:43,{{sfn|Večernji list|29 September 2013}} killing Tepić,{{sfn|Vesti|29 September 2011}} and eleven ZNG troops who were blockading the depot in Bedenik Forest. The blast knocked down trees in a circle {{convert|200|m|abbr=off}} wide, caused damage to nearby structures, and could be heard {{convert|20|km|abbr=off}} away.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|p=21}} The JNA lost [[Stojadin Mirković|another soldier]] in the area of the depot, killed by an antitank missile while he was engaging the ZNG using an [[infantry fighting vehicle]] gun.{{sfn|Vesti|29 September 2011}}

==Aftermath==
[[File:Oklopnjak vukovarska vojarna 3.JPG|right|thumb|Croatian forces acquired 77 JNA [[BVP M-80]] [[Infantry fighting vehicle|IFVs]] from barracks in Bjelovar.]]
The JNA suffered 14 killed,{{sfn|Karaula|2007|loc=note 59}} and 30 wounded during the siege and capture of the Bjelovar barracks. The ZNG lost 17 dead, and five civilians were killed. There were 70 wounded ZNG troops and civilians combined. The ZNG troops captured 60 JNA officers and 365 soldiers. The captured troops were released  on 14 November, in a [[prisoner exchange]] between [[Slavonski Šamac]] and [[Bosanski Šamac]]. Equipment captured by the ZNG included 75 [[T-55]] and three [[PT-76]] tanks, nine {{convert|122|mm|adj=on}} howitzers, four [[M-63 Plamen]] [[multiple rocket launcher]]s, 77 [[BVP M-80]] infantry fighting vehicles, small arms previously confiscated from the Bjelovar TO, and weapons of the 1st Brigade of the 28th Partisan Division (TO) including 1,300 assault rifles and machine guns and approximately 100 trucks. During the fighting, 437 residential structures, 513 apartments, 169 utility structures and 25 public and commercial buildings were damaged or destroyed in Bjelovar and Hrgovljani.{{sfn|Karaula|2007|pp=21–22}} The following day, the only remaining major unit of the 32nd Corps—the 73rd Motorised Brigade based in Koprivnica—surrendered to the ZNG.{{sfn|Škvorc|2010|loc=note 36}}

The capture of the JNA barracks in Bjelovar also affected the ceasefire agreement reached between the JNA and Croatia in [[Igalo]], specifically a provision regarding the lifting of the blockade of the JNA barracks there. Initially there was a dispute between Tuđman and JNA General [[Veljko Kadijević]] as to whether it meant achieving normal living conditions in the barracks or complete freedom of movement for the JNA in Croatia. A compromise interpretation was negotiated, only to be dropped by Kadijević specifically because of the events in Bjelovar.{{sfn|Libal|1997|p=57}} On 1 October, Kadijević issued an ultimatum to Croatia threatening destruction of one civilian facility vital to the Croatian population for each military post captured by the ZNG.{{sfn|Libal|1997|p=58}} The ultimatum demonstrated that the JNA considered Croatia enemy territory, rather than part of the country it had a responsibility to protect.{{sfn|Libal|1997|p=59}}

Tepić was considered a hero in Serbia because he preferred to die rather than surrender. He was posthumously awarded the [[Order of the People's Hero]] by the [[Presidency of Yugoslavia]] on 19 November 1991, becoming the last recipient of the order.{{sfn|Vesti|29 September 2011}} The authorities in Serbia subsequently painted his actions as heroic, and used him as a model for their soldiers.{{sfn|Pančić|15 July 2004}}

In 2005, authorities in Bjelovar announced they would file war crime charges against two unnamed JNA officers.{{sfn|Ivanković|14 September 2005}} In 2010, Šimić was charged with [[war crime]]s, specifically the killing of [[prisoners of war]]. According to the charges filed by the County Court of Bjelovar, Šimić or several persons directly commanded by him killed Kovačević and two other JNA officers after they surrendered on 29 September.{{sfn|Kokoruš|10 November 2010}} {{as of|2014}}, the trial is in progress.{{sfn|Kerbler|16 March 2014}} Four other persons were tried on charges of killing of six prisoners of war captured at the Božidar Adžija Barracks. These prisoners, along with one civilian who had been held in custody since 2 September, were taken to the Česma Forest near the village of Malo Korenovo to be shot. The soldiers were killed, but the civilian survived, although he sustained severe injuries.{{sfn|Index|24 February 2005}} The four accused were acquitted in 2012.{{sfn|Raić Knežević|6 July 2012}} Škarec and Chief of Staff of Bjelovar TO Stjepan Budimski were charged with disobeying the orders issued by the General Staff,{{sfn|Karaula|2007|loc=note 57}} and were imprisoned.{{sfn|Magaš|Žanić|2013|p=37}} After spending several months in custody, Škarec and Budimski were released without formal charges. Škarec was discharged from the Croatian armed forces.{{sfn|Špegelj|2001|p=281}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
;Books
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|title=Confronting the Yugoslav Controversies: A Scholars' Initiative|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t0nYdgFrdG8C|editor-first1=Charles W.|editor-last1=Ingrao|editor-first2=Thomas Allan|editor-last2=Emmert|chapter=The War in Croatia, 1991–1995|first=Mile|last= Bjelajac|first2=Ozren |last2=Žunec|publisher=[[Purdue University Press]]|year=2009|isbn= 978-1-55753-533-7|pages=230–271|location=West Lafayette, Indiana}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|CIA|2002}}|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=it1IAQAAIAAJ|title=Balkan Battlegrounds: A Military History of the Yugoslav Conflict, 1990–1995|publisher=Central Intelligence Agency|author=[[Central Intelligence Agency]], Office of Russian and European Analysis|year=2002|oclc=50396958|location=Washington, D.C.}}
*{{cite book|title=Eastern Europe and the Commonwealth of Independent States|year=1999|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qmN95fFocsMC|ref={{harvid|EECIS|1999}}|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-85743-058-5|location=London, England}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=hr&amp;id=oFXdiS25N78C|editor-first=Sabrina P.|editor-last=Ramet|title=Central and Southeast European Politics Since 1989|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2010|isbn=978-1-139-48750-4|chapter=The War of Yugoslav Succession|first=Marko Attila|last=Hoare|authorlink=Marko Attila Hoare|pages=111–136|location=Cambridge, England}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=N9qA2sLb5gkC|title=Limits of Persuasion: Germany and the Yugoslav Crisis, 1991–1992|first=Michael|last=Libal|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|location=Santa Barbara, California|year=1997|isbn=9780275957988}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vZO0AAAAQBAJ|title=The War in Croatia and Bosnia-Herzegovina 1991–1995|first1=Branka|last1=Magaš|first2=Ivo|last2=Žanić|publisher=[[Routledge]]|location=London, England|year=2013|isbn=9781136340925}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC|title=The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building And Legitimation, 1918–2006|first=Sabrina P.|last=Ramet|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]]|year=2006|isbn= 978-0-253-34656-8|location=Bloomington, Indiana}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?hl=hr&amp;id=cwM1AAAAMAAJ|title=Sjećanja vojnika|language=Croatian|trans_title=Memories of a Soldier|first=Martin|last=Špegelj|authorlink=Martin Špegelj|publisher=Znanje|location=Zagreb, Croatia|year=2001|isbn=9789531951906}}
{{refend}}

;Scientific journal articles
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite journal|ref=harv|journal=Polemos: Journal of Interdisciplinary Research on War and Peace|publisher=Croatian Sociological Association and Jesenski &amp; Turk Publishing House|issn=1331-5595|title=Zauzimanje vojarni JNA u Varaždinu i predaja 32. varaždinskog korpusa JNA|language=Croatian|trans_title=Capture of the JNA barracks in Varaždin and surrender of the 32nd Varaždin Corps of the JNA|first=Ivica|last=Hrastović|volume=9|issue=18|date=December 2006|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=26497&amp;lang=en|pages=119–135}}
*{{cite journal|ref=harv|journal=Journal of Contemporary History|publisher=Croatian Institute of History|issn=0590-9597|title=Osvajanje vojarne JNA &quot;Božidar Adžija&quot; u Bjelovaru 1991. godine|language=Croatian|trans_title=Capture of &quot;Božidar Adžija&quot; JNA barracks in Bjelovar in 1991|first=Željko|last=Karaula|volume=39|issue=1|date=June 2007|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=24487|pages=7–24}}
*{{cite journal|ref=harv|journal=Podravina: časopis za multidisciplinarna istraživanja|publisher=Historical Society of Koprivnica|issn=1333-5286|location=Koprivnica, Croatia|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=115640|title=Koprivnica u zapovijedima i izvješćima JNA 1990. i 1991. godine|trans_title=Koprivnica in JNA Orders and Reports in 1990 and 1991|volume=8|issue=15|date=June 2009|first=Jakša|last=Raguž|language=Croatian|pages=170–208}}
*{{cite journal|ref=harv|journal=Cris: Journal of the Historical Society of Križevci|publisher=The Historical Society of Križevci|issn=1332-2567|title=Zapadna Slavonija uoči i u Domovinskom ratu do studenoga 1991. godine|language=Croatian|trans_title=Western Slavonia on the eve of and in the Croatian War of Independence, till November 1991|first=Đuro|last=Škvorc|volume=11|issue=1|date=February 2010|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=79740&amp;lang=en|pages=116–126}}
{{refend}}

;News reports
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Vesti|29 September 2011}}|publisher=Vesti|language=Serbian|date=29 September 2011|url=http://www.vesti-online.com/Vesti/Ex-YU/167912/Dve-decenije-od-smrti-majora-Milana-Tepica|title=Dve decenije od smrti majora Milana Tepića|trans_title=Two Decades Since the Death of Milan Tepić}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Engelberg|3 March 1991}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/03/03/world/belgrade-sends-troops-to-croatia-town.html|first=Stephen|last=Engelberg|title=Belgrade Sends Troops to Croatia Town|date=3 March 1991|archivedate=2 October 2013|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20131002222925/http://www.nytimes.com/1991/03/03/world/belgrade-sends-troops-to-croatia-town.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Ivanković|14 September 2005}}|date=14 September 2005|newspaper=[[Večernji list]]|url=http://www.vecernji.hr/hrvatska/ratni-zlocin-bjelovar-tuzi-oficire-jna-810009|language=Croatian|first=Davor|last=Ivanković|title=Ratni zločin: Bjelovar tuži oficire JNA|trans_title=War Crime: Bjelovar Sues JNA Officers}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Kerbler|16 March 2014}}|date=16 March 2014|publisher=[[Večernje novosti]]|language=Serbian|first=Jurica|last=Kerbler|url=http://www.novosti.rs/vesti/naslovna/dosije/aktuelno.292.html:482923-Za-surovu-likvidaciju-srpskih-oficira-Simic-kaznjen-izbacivanjem-iz-HDZ|title=Za surovu likvidaciju srpskih oficira Šimić &quot;kažnjen&quot; izbacivanjem iz HDZ|trans_title=Šimić &quot;Punished&quot; for Brutal Killing of Serb Officers by Removal from the HDZ}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Kokoruš|10 November 2010}}|date=10 November 2010|newspaper=[[Slobodna Dalmacija]]|language=Croatian|url=http://www.slobodnadalmacija.hr/Hrvatska/tabid/66/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/120939/Default.aspx|title=Prosvjed zbog pritvaranja bivšeg predsjednika Kriznog štaba|trans_title=Protest Over Detention of Former Crisis Headquarters President|first=Igor|last=Kokoruš}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Večernji list|29 September 2013}}|date=29 September 2013|language=Croatian|newspaper=Večernji list|url=http://www.vecernji.hr/sredisnja-hrvatska/na-dan-grada-i-bjelovarskih-branitelja-prisjetili-se-11-poginulih-620694|title=Na Dan grada i bjelovarskih branitelja prisjetili se 11 poginulih|trans_title=Commemoration of 11 Killed on Occasion of the Day of the City and of the Defenders of Bjelovar}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Pančić|15 July 2004}}|date=15 July 2004|newspaper=[[Vreme]]|language=Serbian|title=Tehnološki višak istorije|trans_title=Technological Surplus of History|first=Teofil|last=Pančić|issue=706|url=http://www.vreme.com/cms/view.php?id=385436}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Raić Knežević|6 July 2012}}|date=6 July 2012|newspaper=[[Novi list]]|url=http://www.novilist.hr/Vijesti/Hrvatska/Skupa-pravda-Sud-mora-platiti-milijun-kuna-za-12-godina-dug-proces|language=Croatian|first=Ana|last=Raić Knežević|title=Skupa pravda: Sud mora platiti milijun kuna za 12 godina dug proces|trans_title=Expensive Justice: Court to Pay Million Kuna for 12 Years Long Process}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|The New York Times|19 August 1990}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/08/19/world/roads-sealed-as-yugoslav-unrest-mounts.html|agency=[[Reuters]]|title=Roads Sealed as Yugoslav Unrest Mounts|date=19 August 1990|archivedate=21 September 2013|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20130921063029/http://www.nytimes.com/1990/08/19/world/roads-sealed-as-yugoslav-unrest-mounts.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|Index|24 February 2005}}|publisher=[[Index.hr]]|url=http://www.index.hr/vijesti/clanak/sudjenje-za-zlocin-u-bjelovarskoj-vojarni-svjedocio-prezivjeli-kovac/251471.aspx|language=Croatian|title=Suđenje za zločin u bjelovarskoj vojarni; svjedočio preživjeli Kovač|trans_title=Bjelovar Barracks Crime Trial: Surviving Kovač Testified}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Sudetic|2 April 1991}}|newspaper=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/04/02/world/rebel-serbs-complicate-rift-on-yugoslav-unity.html|title=Rebel Serbs Complicate Rift on Yugoslav Unity|first=Chuck|last=Sudetic|authorlink=Chuck Sudetic|date=2 April 1991|archivedate=2 October 2013|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20131002222938/http://www.nytimes.com/1991/04/02/world/rebel-serbs-complicate-rift-on-yugoslav-unity.html|deadurl=no}}
*{{cite news|ref={{harvid|Žabec|28 May 2011}}|date=28 May 2011|newspaper=[[Jutarnji list]]|url=http://www.jutarnji.hr/antun-tus--petar-stipetic--martin-spegelj-i-imra-agotic--ljudi-koji-su-stvorili-hrvatsku-vojsku/949293/|language=Croatian|title=Tus, Stipetić, Špegelj i Agotić: Dan prije opsade Vukovara Tuđman je Imri Agotiću rekao: Rata neće biti!|trans_title=Tus, Stipetić, Špegelj and Agotić: A day ahead of the siege of Vukovar, Tuđman said to Imra Agotić: There will be no war!|first=Krešimir|last=Žabec|archivedate=21 April 2012|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20120421001532/http://www.jutarnji.hr/antun-tus--petar-stipetic--martin-spegelj-i-imra-agotic--ljudi-koji-su-stvorili-hrvatsku-vojsku/949293|deadurl=no}}
{{refend}}

;Other sources
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite web|ref={{harvid|ICTY|12 June 2007}}|title=The Prosecutor vs. Milan Martic – Judgement|url=http://www.icty.org/x/cases/martic/tjug/en/070612.pdf|publisher=[[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]]|date=12 June 2007|format=PDF}}
{{refend}}

{{Croatian War of Independence}}
{{Wars and battles involving Croatia}}

{{Coord|45.903407|16.833721|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bjelovar Barracks, Siege of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1991]]
[[Category:Battles of the Croatian War of Independence]]
[[Category:Barracks in Croatia]]
[[Category:1991 in Croatia]]</text>
      <sha1>qlrbj5ssint8ikvvo2kwxrdmjtboakr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
