<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Siege of Krujë (1466–67)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4016236</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750085008</id>
      <parentid>743895965</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-17T18:52:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>174.78.145.241</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Background */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39934">{{For|other sieges of Krujë|First Siege of Krujë|Third Siege of Krujë|Fourth Siege of Krujë}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict= Second siege of Krujë
|image=[[File:Second Siege of Krujë 1466.png|300px|Second Siege of Krujë 1466]]
|caption=Second Siege of Krujë 1466 - Engraving by Jost Amman 1587
|partof=the [[Ottoman Wars in Europe]]
|date=June 1466&amp;nbsp;– 23 April 1467
|place= [[Krujë]], Albania
|result=Albanian-Venetian victory; main Ottoman army withdraws from Albania. Ottoman presence remains after construction of [[Elbasan|Elbasan Fortress]]
|combatant1=[[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|18px]] [[League of Lezhë]] &lt;br/&gt; {{flag|Republic of Venice}}
|combatant2=[[File:Flag of the Ottoman Empire (1453-1844).svg|18px]] [[Ottoman Empire]]
|commander1=[[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|18px]] [[Skanderbeg]] &lt;br/&gt;[[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|18px]] [[Tanush Thopia]] &lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|Republic of Venice}} Baldassare Perducci &lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|Republic of Venice}} Nicolo Moneta
|commander2=[[File:Flag of the Ottoman Empire (1453-1844).svg|18px]] [[Mehmed II]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Flag of the Ottoman Empire (1453-1844).svg|18px]] [[Ballaban Badera]]{{KIA}}
|strength1=4,400 garrisoned; 13,400 set to relieve Krujë
|strength2=30,000–100,000; 23,000 remained with Ballaban upon Mehmed's withdrawal
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
|campaignbox={{Ottoman-Albanian Wars}}
}}

The '''second siege of Krujë''' took place from 1466 to 1467. Sultan [[Mehmed II]] of the [[Ottoman Empire]] led an army into Albania to defeat [[Skanderbeg]], the leader of the [[League of Lezhë]], which was created in 1444 after he began his war against the Ottomans. During the almost year-long siege, Skanderbeg's main fortress, [[Krujë]], withstood the siege while Skanderbeg roamed Albania to gather forces and facilitate the flight of refugees from the civilian areas that were attacked by the Ottomans. Krujë managed to withstand the siege put on it by [[Ballaban Badera]], sanjakbey of the [[Sanjak of Ohrid]], an Albanian brought up in the Ottoman army through the [[devşirme]]. By 23 April 1467, the Ottoman army had been defeated and Skanderbeg entered Krujë.

Mehmed had decided to construct a fortress in what is now [[Elbasan]] which would provide a perennial base for future Ottoman assaults on Skanderbeg's domains. The fortress especially worried Venice since Elbasan was constructed on the banks of the [[Shkumbin River]] which would allow the Ottomans to send ships into the Adriatic and threaten Venetian colonies. Seeing that his situation had become unfavorable, Skanderbeg made a trip to Italy where he would try to convince [[Pope Paul II]] and [[Ferdinand I of Naples]] to give him aid for his war. Despite many promises from the pope, Skanderbeg received little due to the fear of a Neapolitan war with Rome and infighting in the [[Roman Curia]]. Ferdinand and the [[Republic of Venice]] likewise deferred Skanderbeg's requests to the pope. By the time he left Italy, the League of Lezhë had been weakened and needed his intervention.

After his return the Venetians decided to send troops against the Ottoman advances. Skanderbeg gathered 13,400 men, among whom were many Venetians, to launch an assault on the Ottoman besieging camp, who had taken command once Mehmed left Albania after the construction of Elbasan. Skanderbeg had split his army into three parts and surrounded the besiegers. Ballaban was killed during the fighting and the Ottoman forces were left without a commander and a depleted force which was surrounded. Afterwards the Albanian-Venetian forces completed the rout by killing the remaining Ottoman forces before they could escape by way of Dibër. The victory was well received by both Albanians and Italians. This did not signal the end of the war, however, as soon after, Skanderbeg took up some assaults on Elbasan after being urged to by Venice, but was not able to take the fortress due to lack of artillery. Venice itself was in conflict with its Italian neighbors, which led Mehmed to begin another campaign against the Albanians. This would result in another [[Siege of Krujë (1467)|siege on Krujë]].

==Background==
[[File:Gentile Bellini 003.jpg|thumb|left|250x250px|[[Mehmed II]]]]
[[File:Gjergj Kastrioti.jpg|thumb|right|250x250px|[[Skanderbeg]]]]
[[Skanderbeg]] had been an Ottoman [[sanjakbey]], who defected from the empire and united several Albanian princes under the [[League of Lezhë]]. From [[Krujë]], his main fort, he led the league in the Ottoman-Albanian wars. Having defeated the Ottomans in many battles he allied with Western Christian states and leaders, especially with [[Alfonso V of Aragon]] and the [[Papal States]]. On 14 August 1464, [[Pope Pius II]], one of Skanderbeg's major benefactors, died and his plans for a crusade against the Ottoman Empire disintegrated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt363&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=363}}&lt;/ref&gt; The alliances and promises for help from the major Christian powers were canceled with the exception of the [[Kingdom of Hungary]] under [[Matthias Corvinus]] and the [[Republic of Venice]].&lt;ref name=Frasheri417&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=417}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sultan [[Mehmed II]] realized the power vacuum created after Pius died and he tried to take advantage of the situation. He thus attempted to sign a peace agreement with Hungary and Venice so that his forces could focus on Albania to gain a base for future campaigns in the Italian peninsula. His efforts were unsuccessful, however, since neither Venice nor Hungary accepted his proposed treaty. Mehmed thus kept his armies stationed in the Balkans, one force near [[Jajce Fortress|Jajce]] in [[Bosnia (region)|Bosnia]], one in [[Ohrid]], and another one in the [[Morea]].&lt;ref name=Frasheri417/&gt;

Skanderbeg led an incursion into Ottoman territory near Ohrid with the aid of Venetian forces under a ''[[condottiero]]'' named Antonio da Cosenza, also known as Cimarosto, on 6 September 1464. Together, they [[Battle of Ohrid|defeated]] the Ottoman forces under Şeremet bey stationed there on 14 or 15 September.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=418}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt359&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=359}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Venetian Senate informed the Hungarians the joint Albanian-Venetian success on 29 September. Mehmed, sensing the weakness in his frontier, assigned [[Ballaban Badera]] as commander, replacing Şeremet. Ballaban was an Albanian by birth who had been incorporated into the Ottoman army through the [[devşirme]] system and was sanjakbey of the [[Sanjak of Ohrid]] in 1464 and 1465. In the meantime, [[Pope Paul II]] began planning his own crusade, but with means different from his predecessor. He planned to get the major European states to help fund the crusade while Venice, Hungary, and Albania would do the fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri419&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=419}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also wanted to aid the Albanians as much as possible and urged the [[Kingdom of Naples]] to supply Skanderbeg with able forces. Venice began to consider peace with the Ottomans since its resources had significantly decreased, while Hungary adopted a defensive strategy, however, pressure from the Pope and Skanderbeg forced them to abort their efforts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri420&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=420}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ottoman-Albanian war continued through 1465 with Ballaban Badera meeting Skanderbeg at [[Battle of Vaikal|Vaikal]], [[Battle of Meçad (1465)|Meçad]], [[Ballaban's campaign of 1465#Battle of Vaikal|Vaikal again]], and [[Ballaban's campaign of 1465#Battle of Kashari|Kashari]]. In the meantime, Mehmed continued to negotiate peace with Hungary and Venice. Skanderbeg found himself isolated during these negotiations, even if they did not succeed, as the conflicting powers temporarily ceased conflict. Furthermore, [[Ferdinand I of Naples]] did not send his promised forces and the Venetian forces under Cimarosto left Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri421&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=421}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt361&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=361}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the autumn of 1465, Ottoman forces moved from the Morea and Bosnia in order to speed up the peace negotiations. Venice, however, refused peace and Skanderbeg believed that a new Albanian-Venetian campaign would begin. He kept [[Pal Engjëlli]], his ambassador, in constant correspondence with the [[Signoria]] (Venetian Senate), which sent him to Albania to inform Skanderbeg that troops were being raised, although only 300 had been recruited at the time, with Cimarosto as the commander.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri421&quot;/&gt; Venice was also in the process of sending its [[provveditore]]s in [[Albania Veneta]] 3,000 [[ducats]] to recruit men. They would also send four cannons, ten [[springald]]s, and ten barrels of gunpowder. Throughout April, rumors spread that the Ottomans were preparing to march into Albania. By 18 April 1466, Venice received knowledge that the Ottomans were heading towards Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri422&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=422}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campaign==
[[File:Albania mid XVth century AD.png|thumb|right|Main Albanian towns during the 15th century, including settlements in neighboring regions|350px]]
Once news of the Ottoman approach arrived, Venice sent reinforcements to its cities along Albania; [[Durrës|Durazzo]] (Durrës) had already garrisoned 3,000 men. The [[Rozafa Castle|Scutari Fortress]] was also reinforced after Skanderbeg's counsel and the walls were rebuilt. On 19 April 1466, news spread that the sultan was going to march into [[Vlorë|Avlonya]] (Vlorë) with an army of 100,000 men&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri423&quot;/&gt; although the [[Republic of Ragusa|Ragusans]] reported that the number was 30,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger252&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Babinger|1978|p=252}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ottoman forces were ready to enter the Kingdom of Naples and pressured Ferdinand to form an alliance with Mehmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmit365&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=365}}&lt;/ref&gt; The situation was not clear in the Balkans, however, as it was thought that the Ottomans could march against [[Bosnia]], [[Serbia]], [[Dalmatia]], [[Euboea|Negroponte]], or Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri423&quot;/&gt; By the beginning of May, however, it was clear that the Ottomans would attack Albania because of the approach of Mehmed's troops towards Albania after the end of his campaigns in [[Wallachia]], [[Karamanids|Karaman]], and the Morea. None of the promised reinforcements from Naples and Venice arrived and Skanderbeg was thus left to fight Ottoman forces only with the league's troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri423&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=423}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ottoman activities in Albania===
News arrived from eastern Albania that the Ottomans had initiated massacres in the area. The pope was distressed by this and called on the Christian princes of Europe to aid Skanderbeg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri423&quot;/&gt; Soon after, Mehmed's men marched into Albania. Unlike his father [[Murad II]], Mehmed considered that the only way Albania could be conquered would be through isolating [[Krujë]], the main Albanian fortress, by reducing Skanderbeg's manpower, supplies, and political and moral backing. Afterwards, Krujë would be put under siege. The Ottoman campaign was thus sent in two directions: one through the [[Shkumbin River]] valley and another through the [[Black Drin]] River valley. Both fielded men in the frontier regions, right and left of both valleys, and would engage in massacring the local populations, raiding inhabited areas, and burning every village which offered resistance. The populations thus decided to flee into safe areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri424&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=424}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Skanderbeg did not expect such a campaign and his army was not ready to halt the advances. According to an act released [[Monopoli]] in [[Apulia]], an army of 300,000 soldiers (a figure considered to be exaggerated) had marched into Albania, massacred 14,000 people, and sacked many populated areas, while Skanderbeg was preparing to flee to Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri424&quot;/&gt; However, Skanderbeg had remained in Albania but he had sent twelve ships with many inhabitants of Krujë to Italy as refugees. With them, he sent his wife, [[Donika Kastrioti|Donika]], and his son, [[Gjon Kastrioti II|John]]. They were headed to [[Monte Sant'Angelo]], a castle awarded to Skanderbeg after his [[Skanderbeg's Italian expedition|campaigns to restore]] Ferdinand's rule. The arrival of Albanian refugees further distressed the pope and many Italians who had come to believe that Albania had been conquered and that Mehmed was now preparing to march into Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri425&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=425}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely110&quot;/&gt; News to the contrary also reached Rome saying that the League of Lezhë had not been broken and that Krujë still stood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri426&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=426}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The League of Lezhë saw a massive struggle against Ottoman forces and its front was expanded throughout Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri426&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg retreated to the mountains surrounding [[Shkodër|Scutari]] (Shkodër) where he collected men to relieve Krujë.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt374&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=374}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mehmed's [[akıncı]] were allowed to raid the country, a decision which, according t scholar Mehmed Neshriu, was an act of reprisal regarding Skanderbeg's raids in Macedonia in 1464, which interrupted his siege on Jajce. [[Idris Bitlisi]], however, says that Mehmed's campaign was a response to the breaking of the ceasefire in 1463 when Skanderbeg learned that the crusade against the Ottomans organized by Pius II was ready to set off from [[Ancona]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri427&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=427}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resistance itself was described by [[Tursun Beg|Tursun Bey]]: the Albanians had gained control of the mountaintops  and valleys where they had their ''kulle'' (fortified towers) which were dismantled when captured; those inside, especially the young men and women, were sold to slavery for 3,000–4,000 [[akçe]] each. [[Michael Critobulus]], a Greek historian for the sultan, also describes the resistance and its aftermath. The Albanians in his chronicle had likewise gained the mountaintops;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri428&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=428}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely109&quot;/&gt; the light Ottoman infantry climbed up the heights where they cornered the Albanians behind a cliff and fell on them. Many Albanians jumped from the cliffs to escape massacre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri428&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely109&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Freely|2009|p=109}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|pp=209–210}}&lt;/ref&gt; The soldiers then spread throughout the mountains and captured many as slaves while also taking anything of value.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri429&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=429}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson210&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|p=210}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, in order to secure future marches into Albania, Mehmed ordered forests through which the main roads ran through to be cut down. In this way, he created wide military roads which were secure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt380&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=380}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Siege===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Skandeberginkruja.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The citadel of Krujë]] --&gt;
The first phase of the Ottoman campaign to isolate Krujë lasted for two months.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri429&quot;/&gt; According to [[Marin Barleti]], Skanderbeg's main biographer, Skanderbeg had placed 4,400 men under [[Tanush Thopia]] as defenders of the castle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli330&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=330}}&lt;/ref&gt; This force included 1,000 Venetian infantry under Baldassare Perducci&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger252&quot;/&gt; and 200 Neapolitan marksmen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt372&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=372}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg removed his men from the fortress of Krujë in a manner similar to the [[Siege of Krujë (1450)|first siege]]. Mehmed had marched into Albania with [[Ballaban Badera]] under his command.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri430&quot;/&gt; He offered rewards to the garrison if they surrendered, but the garrison responded by bombarding the Ottoman positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco343&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=343}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ottomans then began to heavily bombard the fortress but this came to no effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely110&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Freely|2009|p=110}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri430&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=430}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Karaiskaj&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Karaiskaj|1981|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to documentary sources, the siege began in mid-June, one month after Mehmed began his campaign to force the eastern regions of Albania into submission. Mehmed's campaigns there had put Skanderbeg under massive strain while the latter had yet to receive financial aid from abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri431&quot;/&gt;

In the beginning of July, Skanderbeg sent Pal Engjëlli to Venice. On 7 July, Engjëlli informed the Venetians that the League of Lezhë continued and Krujë still stood, contrary to rumors that said otherwise. He thus requested the arrival of promised Venetian forces when they signed a treaty of alliance on 20 August 1463 and the promised contribution of 3,000 ducats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri431&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=431}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Venetians responded that they were already in a difficult situation due to the Ottoman threat in [[Dalmatia]] and the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]] where they possessed territories. They also responded that they had had difficulty recruiting new soldiers due to financial trouble and could only send 1,000 ducats to its provveditores in Albania. Despite these difficulties, Skanderbeg and his men continued fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri431&quot;/&gt; After becoming convinced that Krujë would not be taken, Mehmed left 18,000 cavalry and 5,000 infantry under Ballaban and in June 1466 withdrew with his main army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton279&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|pp=343–344}}&lt;/ref&gt; He withdrew from the siege to Durazzo where he pillaged the area in rage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger252&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton279&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Setton|1978|p=279}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Mehmed withdrew from Albania, he deposed Dorotheos, the [[Archbishop of Ohrid]], and expatriated him together with his clerks and boyars and a considerable number of citizens of [[Ohrid]] to [[Istanbul]], probably because of their anti-Ottoman activities during [[Skanderbeg]]'s campaigns since many of them supported Skanderbeg and his fight.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shukarova|2008|p=133}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Srpsko arheološko društvo|1951|p=181}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Institut za balkanistika|1984|p=71}}&lt;/ref&gt; He took with him 3,000 Albanian prisoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger253&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Babinger|1978|p=253}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Construction of Elbasan Fortress===
[[File:Elbasan Castle 1.JPG|thumb|right|250px|The fortress in [[Elbasan]], Albania]]
Despite his inability to subdue Krujë, Mehmed decided that the Ottoman presence would not depart from Albania. He organized a [[timar]] in eastern Albania to weaken Skanderbeg's domains. The new Ottoman possessions were collected and placed under the administration of the [[Sanjak of Dibra]]. He also decided to build a powerful fortress in central Albania to counterbalance Krujë's position and to form a base for further Ottoman campaigns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri431&quot;/&gt; The fortress would be called ''Ilbasan'' ([[Elbasan Castle|Elbasan]]). According to Ottoman chronicler Kemal Pashazade, the sultan would place several hundred men to patrol the area and defend the fortress. The foundations were built upon a field called ''Jundi'', located in a Shkumbin valley, where the geographic conditions were regarded as favorable. Since the resources had been gathered and stored beforehand, Elbasan was built within a short time (one month&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli331&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=331}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and [[Franz Babinger]] believes the work to have begun in July.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri433&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=433}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critobulus, who accompanied Mehmed in this campaign, describes that the men stationed in Elbasan would constantly harass the Albanians, to leave them no place for refuge, and to repel any Albanian force which descended from the mountains. Due to his personal guidance, Mehmed was able to see the construction finish before the summer ended. There would also be inhabitants inside to serve the 400 soldiers stationed there along with cannons and catapults; the fortress would be under the command of Ballaban Badera.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|pp=433–434}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson212&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|p=212}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The personal care and attention Mehmed paid to Elbasan's construction testifies its importance in the sultan's plans. This is further testified by the message Mehmed gave to his son, the future [[Bayezid II]], describing how he had devastated the country and at its center built a powerful fortress. Upon his exit from Albania, Marin Barleti says that Mehmed passed through Dibra and massacred 8,000 people, a figure close to the number given by the Ottoman chronicler Oruc ben Adil of 7,500.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri437&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=437}}&lt;/ref&gt; The importance of the fortress was further underscored by its position on the ancient [[Via Egnatia]] and its central position in the Shkumbin valley from where the Ottomans could travel to the coast. Elbasan concerned not only the Albanians, but also the Venetians, who considered its proximity to Durazzo ({{convert|30|mi|km}}) alarmant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri437&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson211&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|p=211}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 August, around the time that the building of Elbasan was completed, Venice urged its proveditors in Albania to cooperate with the Italian and native forces in their proposed siege on Elbasan. Venetian faith in Skanderbeg began to subside, however, since the sultan took a much more aggressive approach in his relations with Venice. Since the Signoria still had not delivered its promised aid, Skanderbeg sent his son John to Venice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri438&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=438}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt391&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=391}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though the war was at its apogee, John returned from Venice empty-handed. This forced Skanderbeg to look towards Rome and Naples for aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|pp=438–439}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Skanderbeg in Rome==
[[File:Scanderbeg.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Skanderbeg's portrait above the entrance to the palace where he stayed in Rome]]
During October 1466, Skanderbeg travelled to Italy to reach an agreement with Ferdinand of Naples and Pope Paul II over the provisions, which they would be willing to provide. As a result of the inter-Italian rivalris, the possibility of a crusade was abandoned. Since Paul was Venetian, Ferdinand was also worried that his interests could be inhibited by the pope and eventually he didn't send any resources to Skanderbeg until disagreements with his neighbors were resolved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri440&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=440}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, Skanderbeg departed from Naples without any definitive agreement on the aid that would be provided by Napes. Venice offered the same and Skanderbeg went to Paul after the latter had declared that the Christian League had raised 100,000 ducats for the planned crusade. Skanderbeg reached Rome on 12 December 1466 where he was greeted by the cardinals and their families. Here they received the impression of Skanderbeg as a poor old man,&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri441&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=441}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt393&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=393}}&lt;/ref&gt; dressed as an ordinary soldier.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli331&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson215&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinsom|1999|p=215}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was offered residence in [[Palazzo Venezia|Palazzo di San Marco]], in what is now called ''[[Piazza Venezia]]'' but refused it and instead wanted to stay with another Albanian whose house later took the name ''[[Palazzo Scanderbeg]]''. He was greeted by Italian ambassadors from the various states who offered &quot;aid and favors&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri442&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=442}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by several bishops and prelates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli332&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=332}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paul, however, was still wary of giving Skanderbeg aid because he reasoned that the Neapolitan threat was more powerful than the Ottoman one. Unlike his predecessors, Paul never attempted to form a crusade against the Ottomans and instead preferred the use of pacification methods. Nevertheless, Skanderbeg continued to stay in Rome, hoping that Paul would allocate part of his funds (of about 500,000 ducats) to Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri445&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=445}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paul asserted to Skanderbeg that Venice's refusal to cooperate with him prevented him from directly helping Skanderbeg. Thus, Skanderbeg was sent to the Signoria to negotiate their stance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri446&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=446}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely111&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Freely|2009|p=111}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the last weeks of the year in Albania, there was no fighting since the Ottomans did not normally engage in battle during the winter. But Krujë was still under siege and Ottoman garrisons in other areas remained. Life became harder for the population after the destruction of crops and villages and the masses of refugees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri446&quot;/&gt; By November 22, news came to Venice about the campaigns of Sinan bey against Albania Veneta&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt382&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=382}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to pressure the Republic to accept a peace or a ceasefire. The Signoria was slow to come to terms with Mehmed due to the pressure put on it by Pope Paul, Hungary, and Naples to remain at war. The attempt to sway the Venetians failed and the campaign was cancelled. This had an adverse effect for the Ottomans since [[Lekë Dukagjini]], Skanderbeg's ally in northern Albania, decided to work without reservation with Skanderbeg against the Ottomans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri446&quot;/&gt; In Rome, the pope continued to hold Skanderbeg and would only give him 300 ducats to support his stay.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely111&quot;/&gt; On Christmas Eve, Paul invited Skanderbeg to a ceremony where he was awarded with a sword and helmet&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt395&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=395}}&lt;/ref&gt; and referred to him as ''Alexander, king of the Epirotes''. By 7 January 1467, a [[papal consistory|consistory]] convened where Skanderbeg and the pope were present. According to Cardinal [[Francesco Gonzaga (1444-1483)|Francesco Gonzaga]], the pope's appeal to fund Skanderbeg with only 5,000 ducats was heard and when the Cardinals responded that the fund was minimal, Paul explained that he would send more once Italy was pacified.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely111&quot;/&gt; Paul's decision led to a fierce debate on Italy's future which left Albania's fate undiscussed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt395&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri447&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=447}}&lt;/ref&gt; A second consistory was called on 12 January but did not result in anything favorable for Skanderbeg. Contemporaries were critical of the pope's delays but he explained that he was waiting to see what Ferdinand of Naples was willing to offer before offering anything himself, in order not to waste funds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri448&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=448}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Skanderbeg's view of the situation worsened with news coming from Albania, which strengthened his opinion that his time in Italy was becoming more and more irrational. His pessimism grew once he found out that Venice was now pressuring Paul into refusing Skanderbeg aid since they wished to put an end to the war and capitulate Krujë. During the first days of February, news arrived from the [[Republic of Ragusa]] that the campaign was nearing its end and that if the necessary actions were not brought up to speed, Albania would fall along with Venice's possessions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri448&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg's requests for proper aid were continually rejected on the basis that Italy's peace must first be secured and instead Paul ordered Ferdinand to award to Skanderbeg what tribute would have been given to Rome. Skanderbeg lost all hope and decided to return to Albania before pleas from several cardinals convinced to stay, offering aid from their own pockets and hope in persuading Paul. A third consistory was convened on 13 February 1467 which, like the other two, came to nothing regarding aid to Skanderbeg. Skanderbeg thus began his departure from Rome. Paul met with Skanderbeg and gave him the authority to pull 7,500 ducats from Ferdinand's aforementioned tribute to Rome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri449&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=449}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt396&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=396}}&lt;/ref&gt; This amount had not been gathered, however, and Paul thus offered Skanderbeg 2,300 ducats. Skanderbeg departed from Rome on 14 February and soon received news from Albania: the war was nearing its end and needed Skanderbeg to return; an Ottoman force sent to defeat the League of Lezhë definitively, however, had been defeated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri450&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=450}}&lt;/ref&gt; He met with [[Giosafat Barbaro]] in Scutari, the Venetian provveditore in Albania Veneta, where he gathered help from Venetian nobles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco344&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=344}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson216&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|p=216}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt399&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=399}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Final battles==
The defeat of the Ottoman forces showed that the League of Lezhë had yet to be fully defeated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri450&quot;/&gt; This allowed Skanderbeg to visit Ferdinand before his departure from Italy, but he received only 1,000 ducats, 300 carts of grain, and 500  ducats to support Krujë's munitions. While Skanderbeg was in his court, Ferdinand received an ambassador from Mehmed offering peace, signaling that the Ottomans did not have any aggressive intentions towards Naples. Ferdinand accepted the proposal and Skanderbeg thus began his return to Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri451&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=451}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ballaban continued to strengthen the siege against Krujë. Upon returning to Albania, the political situation began to change. The once distant Albanian nobles, among them Dukagjini, were now convinced of their impending defeat and allied themselves with Skanderbeg. Meanwhile, the Venetians ended their attempts to negotiate peace with Mehmed and accepted cooperation with Skanderbeg. Skanderbeg met with Dukagjini and other northern Albanian nobles in Alessio ([[Lezhë]]) where they gathered an army to assault Ballaban's forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri453&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=453}}&lt;/ref&gt; Together with 400 of Dukagjini's cavalry and a large number of infantry, 600 heavily armed Italian soldiers, and 4,000 locals from Durazzo, Scutari, Alessio, [[Drivast]] (Drisht), and Antivari ([[Bar, Montenegro|Bar]]), Skanderbeg commanded 13,400 men to relieve Krujë as reported by [[Dhimitër Frëngu|Demetrio Franco]], one of Skanderbeg's primary biographers and personal associates,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|pp=344–345}}&lt;/ref&gt; who also served in Skanderbeg's ranks. Among those who joined Skanderbeg was Nicolo Moneta, a lord of Scutari and wealthy Venetian [[patrician (post-Roman Europe)|patrician]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt399&quot;/&gt;

Ballaban's camp was located on the hills southwest of Krujë and at the bottom of the mountain nowadays known as Mt. Sarisalltëk, he placed a guarding force. The rest of his army surrounded Krujë.&lt;ref name=&quot;Karaiskaj&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg and his allies marched through the mouth of the [[Mat River]] and cut through the woods of Jonima to the boundaries of Krujë.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt400&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=400}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg's commanders were assigned different groups for an assault on the main Ottoman camp: northern Albanian forces would be put under Dukagjini's command, Venetian battalions were under the command of Moneta, and Skanderbeg's most trusted forces would be assigned to another group under his command; Krujë's garrison would continue to defend the fortress. Moneta's and Dukagjini's men would attack the besieging forces from the north and Skanderbeg's men would attack from south of Krujë while also blocking any possible Ottoman reinforcements from the east.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri454&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg first assaulted the guarding force which Ballaban had left and he gained control of this strategic point.&lt;ref name=&quot;Karaiskaj&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg then managed to defeat the Ottoman relief forces under Ballaban's brother, Jonuz, and captured him and his son.&lt;ref name=&quot;Karaiskaj&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli333&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=333}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four days later, an organized attack from Skanderbeg and the forces from Krujë was carried during which Ballaban forces were retreated and he himself was killed in the resulting clashes by Gjergj Lleshi (''Georgius Alexius'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri454&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=454}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco345&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=345}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:South-eastern Europe 1464.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Map of south-eastern Europe in 1464 AD]]
With the death of Ballaban, Ottoman forces were left surrounded and according to Bernandino de Geraldinis, a Neapolitan functionary, 10,000 men remained in the besieging camp. Those inside the encirclement asked to leave freely to Ottoman territory, offering to surrender all that was within the camp to the Albanians. Skanderbeg was prepared to accept, but many nobles refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri455&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=455}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among them was Dukagjini, who wanted to attack and destroy the Turkish camp. Demetrio Franco described Dukagjini's proposal with the Albanian word ''Embetha'' which in modern Albanian means ''Mbë ta'' or in English ''Upon them''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri456&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=456}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco346&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=346}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson217&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|p=217}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Albanians thus began to annihilate the surrounded army before the Ottomans cut a narrow path through their opponents and fled through Dibra.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli334&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=334}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 April 1467, Skanderbeg entered Krujë.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri455&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, the Venetians had taken advantage of Mehmed's absence in Albania and sent a fleet under Vettore Capello into the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]]. Capello attacked and occupied the islands of [[Imbros]] and [[Lemnos]] after which he sailed back and laid siege to [[Patras]]. [[Turahanoğlu Ömer Bey|Ömer Bey]], the Ottoman commander in Greece, led a relief force to Patras where he was initially repelled before turning on his pursuers, forcing them to flee, terminating their campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freely112&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Freely|2009|p=112}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The victory was well received among the Albanians, and Skanderbeg's recruits increased as documented by Geraldini: ''Skanderbeg was in his camp with 16,000 men and every day his camp grows with young warriors.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri456&quot;/&gt; The victory was also well received in Italy with contemporaries hoping for more such news. But, despite the Ottoman loss, the victory did not signal an end to the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri456&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg's damaged forces, however, had been renewed with northern warriors and Venetian battalions. The situation remained critical, however, due to the economic hardships suffered during the siege. Skanderbeg's only expectancy was for help to come from Italy, but the Italian states, despite sending contragulatory messages, send no financial aid. Hungary continued its defensive war and thus Skanderbeg's only remaining ally was Venice. Even Venice became skeptical of continuing the war and was alone in allying with Skanderbeg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri456&quot;/&gt; Venice reported to Hungary that Mehmed had offered peace and was willing to accept it. Hungary also opted for peace, but Mehmed only sought peace with Venice in order to isolate Skanderbeg and thus peace was not signed. Skanderbeg and Venice continually began to worry about the Ottoman garrison in Elbasan. Skanderbeg led some assaults on the fortress after being urged to by Venice but failed to capture it due to lack of artillery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri457&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=457}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Critobulos, Mehmed was troubled after learning of the Ottoman defeat and began preparations for a new campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli335&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=335}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt402&quot;/&gt; Venice itself was in conflict with its Italian neighbors who had grown wary of its increasing influence in the Balkans. With the western powers fighting among themselves, the road to Albania was open.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt401&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=401}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mehmed thus decided to send a force to subdue Albania conclusively which resulted in a new [[Siege of Krujë (1467)|siege on Krujë]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt402&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=402}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==References==
* {{citation|last=Babinger|first=Franz|year=1978|title=Mehmed the Conqueror and His Time|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, N.J.|isbn=0-691-01078-1}}
* {{citation|last=Franco|first=Demetrio|year=1539|title=Comentario de le cose de' Turchi, et del S. Georgio Scanderbeg, principe d' Epyr|location=Venice|publisher=Altobello Salkato|isbn=99943-1-042-9}}
* {{citation|last=Frashëri|first=Kristo |title=Gjergj Kastrioti Skënderbeu: jeta dhe vepra, 1405–1468|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vwR3PQAACAAJ&amp;dq=kristo+frasheri+skenderbeu&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=vD6aTMPAFoPGlQeau_HZDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA|year=2002 |publisher=Botimet Toena|location=Tiranë|language=Albanian|isbn=99927-1-627-4}}
* {{citation|last=Freely|first=John|year=2009|title=The grand Turk: Sultan Mehmet II, conqueror of Constantinople and master of an empire|location=New York|publisher=The Overlook Press|isbn=1-59020-248-1}}
* {{citation|last=Hodgkinson|first=Harry |authorlink= Harry Hodgkinson (writer)|title=Scanderbeg: From Ottoman Captive to Albanian Hero|year=1999|publisher=Centre for Albanian Studies|location=London|isbn=978-1-873928-13-4}}
* {{citation|author=Institut za balkanistika|title=Balkan studies|year=1984|publisher=Bulgarian Academy of Sciences|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Uj9pAAAAMAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}
* {{citation|last=Karaiskaj|first=Gjerak|title=Pesë mijë vjet fortifikime në Shqipëri|year=1981|chapter=Rrethimi i dytë dhe i tretë i Krujës (1466–1467)|publisher=Shtëpia Botuese &quot;8 Nëntori&quot;|location=Tirana|url=http://letersi.com/karaiskaj_gjerak/kapitulli_xi_vii.htm}}
* {{citation|last=Noli|first=Fan Stilian|authorlink= Fan Stilian Noli |year=1947|title=George Castroiti Scanderbeg (1405–1468)|publisher=International Universities Press| oclc=732882}}
* {{citation|last=Schmitt|first=Oliver Jens|authorlink= Oliver Jens Schmitt |year=2009|title=Skënderbeu|publisher=K&amp;B|location=Tiranë|isbn=978-3-7917-2229-0}}
* {{citation|last=Setton|first=Kenneth Meyer|authorlink=Kenneth Setton|year=1978|title=The Papacy and the Levant, 1204-1571|location=Philadelphia|publisher=DIANE Publishing|isbn=978-0-87169-127-9}}
* {{citation |last=Shukarova |first=Aneta |editor=Todor Chepreganov|title=History of the Macedonian People|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/66035878/History-of-The-Macedonian-People-ed-Todor-Chepreganov-Institute-of-National-History-Skopje-2008 |year= 2008 |publisher=Institute of National History|location=Skopje|isbn=9989-159-24-6 |oclc=276645834}}
* {{citation|author=Srpsko arheološko društvo |title=Starinar|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nIDjAAAAMAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|year=1951|publisher= Arheološki institut|location= Belgrade|language=Serbian|oclc=1586392}}

{{coord|41|31|N|19|48|E|type:event|display=title}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Siege of Kruje (1466-1467)}}
[[Category:Warfare by Skanderbeg]]
[[Category:Sieges involving the Ottoman Empire|Kruje]]
[[Category:1466 in Europe]]
[[Category:Battles involving Albania|Kruje]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1466]]
[[Category:Battles of Mehmed the Conqueror]]
[[Category:1466 in the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:1467 in the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:1467 in Europe]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Republic of Venice|Kruje]]</text>
      <sha1>kxn7mmbkyiorcv1tdn2a60yedt04mdf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
