<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Schwalbe</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42033006</id>
    <revision>
      <id>711748534</id>
      <parentid>688865780</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-24T16:45:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Parsecboy</username>
        <id>1879095</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* First deployment to East Africa */ no source for photo, cannot use it</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15248">{{good article}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin |infobox caption=}} 
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 134-B0211, Kleiner Kreuzer &quot;Schwalbe&quot;.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=''Schwalbe'' in the [[Kaiser Wilhelm Canal]]
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=[[German Empire]]
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|German Empire|naval}}
|Ship name=''Schwalbe''
|Ship laid down=April 1886
|Ship launched=16 August 1887
|Ship commissioned=8 May 1888
|Ship in service=12 November 1888
|Ship struck=6 December 1919
|Ship fate=Scrapped, 1922
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class={{sclass-|Schwalbe|cruiser|4}}
|Ship type=[[Unprotected cruiser]]
|Ship displacement={{convert|1359|t|LT|abbr=on}}
|Ship length={{convert|66.90|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|9.36|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|4.40|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion= 2-cylinder double expansion engines, 2 screws
|Ship speed={{convert|13.5|kn}}
|Ship range={{convert|3290|nmi|abbr=on}} at {{convert|10|kn}}
|Ship complement=*9 officers
*108 enlisted men
|Ship armament=*8 × {{convert|10.5|cm|in|abbr=on}} K L/35 guns
*5 × {{convert|37|mm|abbr=on}} revolver cannons

|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''SMS ''Schwalbe''''' (&quot;His Majesty's Ship ''Schwalbe''—''Swallow''&quot;){{efn|name=SMS|}} was an [[unprotected cruiser]] built for the German ''[[Kaiserliche Marine]]'' (Imperial Navy), the [[lead ship]] of the {{sclass-|Schwalbe|cruiser|4}}. She had one [[sister ship]], {{SMS|Sperber||2}}. ''Schwalbe'' was built at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Wilhelmshaven|''Kaiserliche Werft'']] (Imperial Dockyard) in [[Wilhelmshaven]]; her keel was laid down in April 1886 and her completed hull was launched in August 1887. She was commissioned for service in May 1888. Designed for colonial service, ''Schwalbe'' was armed with a main battery of eight {{convert|10.5|cm|sp=us|adj=on}} guns and had a cruising radius of over {{convert|3000|nmi}}; she also had an auxiliary sailing rig to supplement her [[steam engine]]s.

''Schwalbe'' spent the majority of her career overseas. She served in [[German East Africa]] from 1889 to 1893, and during this period she assisted in the suppression of the [[Abushiri Revolt]]. In 1893, she returned to Germany for a major overhaul. She was decommissioned until 1898, when she returned to service for another tour abroad. She initially returned to German East Africa, where she patrolled [[South Africa]]n waters to protect German shipping during the [[Second Boer War]]. The outbreak of the [[Boxer Rebellion]] in China in 1900 prompted the ''Kaiserliche Marine'' to send ''Schwalbe'' to join the European forces battling the Boxers. ''Schwalbe'' spent 1901 and 1902 in Chinese waters, blockading the mouth of the [[Yangtze]] and suppressing local unrest. The ship returned to Germany in 1903 for another major overhaul and another stint in reserve. She ended her career as a [[barracks ship]] during [[World War I]], and as a [[target ship]] in 1918. She was ultimately broken up for scrap in 1922.

==Design==
{{main|Schwalbe-class cruiser}}

''Schwalbe'' was {{convert|66.9|m|sp=us}} [[length overall|long overall]] and had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|9.36|m|abbr=on}} and a [[draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|4.40|m|abbr=on}} forward. She displaced {{convert|1359|t|LT|abbr=on}} at full combat load. Her propulsion system consisted of two horizontal 2-cylinder [[Double expansion engine|double-expansion]] [[steam engine]]s powered by four coal-fired cylindrical [[water-tube boiler]]s. These provided a top speed of {{convert|13.5|kn}} and a range of approximately {{convert|3290|nmi|lk=in}} at {{convert|10|kn}}.&lt;ref name=G934&gt;Gröner, pp. 93&amp;ndash;94&lt;/ref&gt; To supplement the steam engines, she was fitted with a [[barquentine]] rig.&lt;ref name=G252/&gt; ''Schwalbe'' had a crew of 9&amp;nbsp;officers and 108&amp;nbsp;enlisted men.&lt;ref name=G934/&gt;

The ship was armed with eight [[10.5 cm K L/35|10.5&amp;nbsp;cm K L/35]] guns in single pedestal mounts, supplied with 765&amp;nbsp;rounds of ammunition in total. They had a range of {{convert|8200|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=G934/&gt; Four guns were mounted on each [[broadside]]. The gun armament was rounded out by five {{convert|3.7|cm|abbr=on}} revolver cannon.&lt;ref name=G252&gt;Gardiner, p. 252&lt;/ref&gt;

==Service history==
The keel for ''Schwalbe'' was laid down at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Wilhelmshaven|''Kaiserliche Werft'']] (Imperial Dockyard) in [[Wilhelmshaven]] in April 1886. Her completed hull was launched on 16 August 1887; then-''[[Konteradmiral]]'' (Rear Admiral) [[Alexander von Monts]] gave the launching speech. She was commissioned for [[sea trials]] on 8 May 1888, and they lasted until 8 August. ''Schwalbe'' was formally placed into service on 12 November and assigned to the East Africa Station in [[German East Africa]]. The assignment came following requests for reinforcement from ''Konteradmiral'' [[Karl August Deinhard]], the local commander of naval forces in the region, to help suppress the [[Abushiri Revolt]]. She departed Germany eight days later and arrived in [[Zanzibar]] on 31 December, and was joined by the [[aviso]] {{SMS|Pfeil||2}}. The two ships reinforced the old sail [[corvette]]s {{SMS|Leipzig|1875|2}} and {{SMS|Sophie||2}}.&lt;ref name=G252/&gt;&lt;ref name=HRS145&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 145&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, pp. 202&amp;ndash;203&lt;/ref&gt;

===First deployment to East Africa===

On 3 January 1889, ''Schwalbe'' bombarded rebel positions at [[Bagamoyo]] before taking Deinhard aboard to [[Dar es Salaam]]. The next day, she ran aground on the reef surrounding [[Fungu Yasini Island]]. The ship remained stranded for two days before ''Leipzig'' and the British steamer {{SS|Woodcock}} arrived to pull her free. She thereafter took her place in a blockade line to prevent contraband from reaching the rebels; ''Schwalbe'' patrolled the line from [[Kiswere]] to [[Ras Kimbiji]]. On 1 March, she was moved to the area between [[Kilwa Kisiwani]] and [[Mafia Island]]. ''Schwalbe'', ''Leipzig'', and the corvette {{SMS|Carola||2}} sent a contingent of naval infantry ashore at [[Kunduchi]] to attack rebel forces there; the three warships also provided artillery support to the landing force. ''[[Korvettenkapitän]]'' (''KK''&amp;ndash;Corvette Captain) Hirschberg, ''Schwalbe''{{'}}s captain, commanded the operation. ''Schwalbe'' returned to Bagamoyo on 8 May to launch another attack; further engagements took place at [[Saadani]] on 6 June and at [[Pangani]] on 8 July. ''Schwalbe'' and her crew were given a respite from the conflict from 20 July to 17 August for a period of rest and refit at [[Port Louis]] in [[Mauritius]].&lt;ref name=HRS145/&gt;

[[File:Deutsch Ost-Afrika,1892.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Contemporary map of [[German East Africa]]]]

On 29 August, ''Schwalbe'' returned to the blockade line off German East Africa. During this period, she frequently carried Deinhard on special trips. Between 7 and 10 October, she carried the station commander to survey the colony's northern border with [[British Kenya]] in company with the British [[gunboat]] {{HMS|Mariner|1884|6}}. ''Schwalbe'' continued to operate against insurgent forces, particularly to support ''[[Reichskommissar]]'' (Imperial Commissioner) [[Hermann Wissmann]]'s forces. At the end of October, ''Schwalbe'' was joined by her [[sister ship]] {{SMS|Sperber||2}}. In early December, ''Schwalbe'' and ''Sperber'' were present at ceremonial reception of the [[Emin Pasha Relief Expedition]] at Bagamoyo. Both ships were also involved with settling the border of [[Wituland]] on 27&amp;ndash;29 December. In mid-January 1890, ''Pfeil'', ''Leipzig'', and ''Sophie'' left East Africa, leaving ''Schwalbe'', ''Sperber'', and ''Carola'' on the station. ''Schwalbe'' went to [[Cape Town]] in [[South Africa]] for an overhaul that lasted from 3 March until mid-April.&lt;ref name=HRS145/&gt;

Following her return from Cape Town, ''Schwalbe'' returned to supporting operations to pacify the coastal area in southern German East Africa carried out by Wissmann. During this period, several artillery pieces were captured, one of which was taken aboard ''Schwalbe'' before eventually being given to the Training Inspection for the colonial troops. By mid-May, the uprising had finally been suppressed. ''Schwalbe'' thereafter conducted the normal peacetime routine of cruising the coast to show the German flag. Hirschberg contracted [[malaria]] and became severely ill, prompting his return to Germany on 24 June to recover; ''KK'' Rüdiger arrived on 13 July to take over command of the ship. On 9 October, Rüdiger presided over a ceremony to dedicate a memorial in [[Tanga, Tanzania|Tanga]] to the naval personnel who had been killed in the Abushiri revolt.&lt;ref name=HRS145/&gt; Meanwhile, on 1 July, Wituland had been ceded to Britain as part of the [[Heligoland–Zanzibar Treaty]]; this development upset the Sultan of Wituland, who ordered the killing of several Europeans in the colony, mostly Germans. The British launched a punitive expedition, and ''Schwalbe'' remained in the area as an observer until the end of October.&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, pp. 145&amp;ndash;146&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1891, ''Schwalbe'' went to [[Mahé, Seychelles|Mahé]] in the [[Seychelles]] to rest her crew. Rüdiger was promoted to the position of Deputy Governor of the colony in October, and ''KK'' Oelrichs replaced him aboard the ship. ''Schwalbe'' then departed to visit [[Bombay]], returning to German East Africa on 27 January 1892. Unrest in [[Moshi, Tanzania|Moshi]] required ''Schwalbe''{{'}}s presence to provide support for the ''[[Schutztruppen]]''. She was anchored off Tanga by June, and in October, the death of [[Ali bin Said of Zanzibar|Ali bin Said]], the [[Sultan of Zanzibar]], caused a succession crisis that forced ''Schwalbe'' and other vessels to steam to the island to help mediate the disputes. By January 1893, ''Schwalbe'' was free to return to Bombay for repairs. In May, ''Schwalbe'' received the order to return to Germany. She arrived in Kiel on 6 August, and was decommissioned on 25 August. The [[Kaiserliche Werft Kiel|''Kaiserliche Werft'']] in Kiel took the ship into drydock for an extensive overhaul and modernization. She remained out of service after the repair work was completed, until 1 April 1898, when she was recommissioned for another tour in German East Africa, to replace the cruiser {{SMS|Seeadler||2}}.&lt;ref name=HRS146&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 146&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second deployment overseas===
On 20 April, ''Schwalbe'' left Germany and arrived off Zanzibar a month and a half later, on 7 June. She went to Cape Town for periodic maintenance from 10 October to mid-November. In January 1899, she towed the disabled German East-Africa Line steamer {{SS|Setos}} to Dar es Salaam. For this, the Line donated a sum to the Navy, which the ''[[Reichsmarineamt]]'' (Imperial Navy Office) used to improve the sailors' barracks. In October, the [[Second Boer War]] broke out between British South Africa and the Boer [[Orange Free State]] and the [[South African Republic|Transvaal]]. ''Schwalbe'' and the cruiser {{SMS|Condor||2}} were sent to South Africa to protect German shipping, since the British had begun aggressively searching foreign freighters to prevent contraband from reaching the Boers. Despite the presence of the two cruisers, several German ships, including the Imperial post steamers {{SS|Bundesrat}} and {{SS|General}}, the freighter {{SS|Hans Wagner}}, and the [[barque]] ''Marie'' were seized by the [[Royal Navy]]. This caused a major diplomatic incident and led to the passage of the [[German Naval Laws|Second Naval Law]] in Germany. During her patrol of South African waters, she stopped in Durban from 19 to 21 January 1900, [[Port Elizabeth]], [[East London, Eastern Cape|East London]], Cape Town, and [[Delagoa Bay]]. Tensions eased as the Boers began to suffer several defeats in early 1900, and on 7 May, ''Schwalbe'' was back in Dar es Salaam. From here, she was ordered to leave for East Asian waters to reinforce the German [[German East Asia Squadron|East Asia Squadron]] and assist with suppressing the [[Boxer Rebellion]] in China.&lt;ref name=HRS146/&gt;

She arrived in Chinese waters in late September, and was assigned to the blockade of the mouth of the [[Yangtze]]. She spent the period from 14 February to 3 March 1901 in the German concession at [[Tsingtao]], after which she returned to the Yangtze. The blockade of the river ended in June, and on 10 June she returned to Tsingtao. From 4 September to 11 November, she underwent an overhaul in [[Shanghai]]. She then returned to Tsingtao and the Yangtze area, before riots in [[Zhejiang]] province forced her to steam to [[Ningpo]] to assist in suppressing the unrest on 9 April 1902. On 16 April, she left for repairs at Shanghai.&lt;ref name=HRS146/&gt; On 23 July, while ''Schwalbe'' was moored in Tsingtao, she received the order to return to Germany. On 16 August, she departed Tsingtao and arrived in [[Danzig]] on 10 December. There, she was decommissioned a second time three days later. Another lengthy overhaul followed,&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, pp. 146–147&lt;/ref&gt; which lasted from 1903 to 1905 at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Danzig|''Kaiserliche Werft'']] in Danzig.&lt;ref name=G94&gt;Gröner, p. 94&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later career===
''Schwalbe'' remained in reserve following the completion of her overhaul in 1905, until 26 October 1911, when she was recommissioned for use as a special-purpose ship. The Navy planned to convert her into a [[survey ship]] for use abroad, but in 1912 the Navy instead decided to use her to replace the old aviso {{SMS|Grille||2}} as a training ship. After the outbreak of [[World War I]] in August 1914, she was converted into a [[barracks ship]] based in Kiel. She served in this capacity until 1918, when she was used as a [[target ship]] outside Kiel. She was stricken from the [[naval register]] on 6 December 1919 and sold for scrapping on 7 August 1920. ''Schwalbe'' was ultimately broken up for scrap in 1922 in [[Hamburg]].&lt;ref name=G94/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 147&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==

=== Footnotes ===
{{notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = SMS
| &quot;SMS&quot; stands for &quot;''[[Seiner Majestät Schiff]]''&quot; ({{lang-de|link=no|His Majesty's Ship}}).
}}

}}

=== Citations ===
{{reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==References==
*{{cite book|editor-last=Gardiner|editor-first=Robert|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1860–1905|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=Greenwich|year=1979|isbn=0-8317-0302-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Gröner|first=Erich|title=German Warships 1815–1945|year=1990|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, MD|isbn=0-87021-790-9}}
* {{cite book| last1 = Hildebrand| first1 = Hans H.| last2 = Röhr| first2 = Albert| last3 = Steinmetz| first3 = Hans-Otto| year = 1993| title = Die Deutschen Kriegsschiffe (Volume 7)| publisher = Mundus Verlag| location = Ratingen, DE|asin=B003VHSRKE |asin-tld=de}}
*{{Cite book |last=Sondhaus|first=Lawrence|title=Preparing for Weltpolitik: German Sea Power Before the Tirpitz Era|year=1997|publisher=Annapolis|location=Naval Institute Press|isbn=1-55750-745-7}}

{{Schwalbe class cruisers}}

[[Category:Schwalbe-class cruisers]]</text>
      <sha1>2s78hm3es07objf1467ojs9rdgk9swt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
