<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Pillau</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3524276</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736503165</id>
      <parentid>735686217</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-27T23:35:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DPdH</username>
        <id>1539540</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Design */ Added wikilink.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21442">{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:SMS Pillau.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=''Pillau'', c. 1914&amp;ndash;16
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=[[German Empire]]
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|German Empire|naval}}
|Ship name=''Pillau''
|Ship namesake=City of [[Baltiysk|Pillau]]
|Ship ordered=
|Ship builder=[[Schichau]], [[Danzig]]
|Ship laid down=1913
|Ship launched=11 April 1914
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=14 December 1914
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship struck=5 November 1919
|Ship fate=Ceded to Italy 20 July 1920
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=title
|Ship country=[[Italy]]
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|Kingdom of Italy}}
|Ship name=''Bari''
|Ship namesake=city of [[Bari]]
|Ship acquired=20 July 1920
|Ship commissioned=21 January 1924
|Ship fate=sunk 28 June 1943, scrapped 1948
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class={{sclass-|Pillau|cruiser|0}} [[light cruiser]]
|Ship displacement=*Design: {{convert|4390|MT|abbr=on}}
*Full load: {{convert|5252|MT|abbr=on}}
|Ship length={{convert|135.3|m|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|13.6|m|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|5.98|m|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=*2 × [[steam turbine]]s
*2 × shafts
*{{convert|30000|shp|abbr=on}}
|Ship speed={{convert|27.5|knot|km/h|1}}
|Ship range={{convert|4300|nmi|abbr=on}} at {{convert|12|kn|abbr=on}}
|Ship complement=*21 officers
*421 enlisted men
|Ship armament=*8 × [[15 cm SK L/45]] guns
*2 × [[8.8 cm SK L/45 naval gun|8.8 cm SK L/45]] guns
*2 × {{convert|50|cm|in|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s
*120 mines
|Ship armor=*Deck {{convert|80|mm|abbr=on}}
*[[Conning tower]]: {{convert|75|mm|abbr=on}}
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''SMS ''Pillau''''' was a [[light cruiser]] ordered by the Imperial Russian navy under the name ''Maraviev Amurskyy'' from the [[Schichau-Werke]] shipyard in [[Danzig]] in 1913 and launched in April 1914. Following the outbreak of [[World War I]], the ship was confiscated in August 1914 and renamed SMS ''Pillau'' in honor of the [[East Prussian]] port of [[Pillau]] (now [[Baltiysk]], Russia). The ship was commissioned into the [[High Seas Fleet]] in December 1914. The [[lead ship]] of [[Pillau-class cruiser|her class]], she had one sister ship, {{SMS|Elbing||2}}. She was armed with a main battery of eight [[15 cm SK L/45]] guns and had a top speed of {{convert|27.5|kn|abbr=on}}.

''Pillau'' spent the majority of her career in the [[II Scouting Group]], and saw service in both the [[Baltic Sea|Baltic]] and [[North Sea]]s. In August 1915, she participated in the [[Battle of the Gulf of Riga]] against the [[Russian Navy]], and on 31 May &amp;ndash; 1 June 1916, she saw significant action at the [[Battle of Jutland]]. She was hit by a large-caliber shell once in the engagement, but suffered only moderate damage. She assisted the badly damaged [[battlecruiser]] {{SMS|Seydlitz}} reach port on 2 June after the conclusion of the battle. She also took part in the [[Battle of Heligoland Bight (1917)|Second Battle of Heligoland Bight]], though was not damaged in the engagement. ''Pillau'' was assigned to the planned, final operation of the High Seas Fleet in the closing weeks of the war, but a large scale mutiny forced it to be canceled. 

After the end of the war, ''Pillau'' was ceded to Italy as a [[war prize]] in 1920. Renamed ''Bari'', she was commissioned in the ''[[Regia Marina]]'' (Royal Navy) in January 1924. She was modified and rebuilt several times over the next two decades. In the early years of [[World War II]], she provided gunfire support to Italian troops in several engagements in the Mediterranean. In 1943, she was slated to become an anti-aircraft defense ship, but while awaiting conversion, she was sunk by [[USAAF]] bombers in [[Livorno]] in June 1943. The wreck was partially scrapped by the Germans in 1944, and ultimately raised for scrapping in January 1948.

==Design==
{{main|Pillau class cruiser}}

''Pillau'' was ordered by the [[Imperial Russian Navy]] as ''Maraviev Amurskyy'' from the [[Schichau-Werke]] shipyard in [[Danzig]]. She was laid down in 1913, and was launched on 11 April 1914, after which [[fitting-out]] work commenced. She was requisitioned by the German Navy on 5 August 1914, and renamed ''Pillau''. She was commissioned into the [[High Seas Fleet]] on 14 December 1914.&lt;ref name=G1101&gt;Gröner, pp. 110–111&lt;/ref&gt; The ship was {{convert|135.3|m|sp=us}} [[length overall|long overall]] and had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|13.6|m|abbr=on}} and a [[draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|5.98|m|abbr=on}} forward. She displaced {{convert|5252|t|abbr=on}} at full combat load.&lt;ref name=G111&gt;Gröner, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; Her propulsion system consisted of two sets of Marine [[steam turbine]]s driving two {{convert|3.5|m|adj=on|sp=us}} propellers. They were designed to give {{convert|30000|shp|lk=in}}. These were powered by six coal-fired [[Yarrow boiler|Yarrow]] [[water-tube boiler]]s, and four oil-fired Yarrow boilers. These gave the ship a top speed of {{convert|27.5|kn}}. ''Pillau'' carried {{convert|620|t|LT}} of coal, and an additional {{convert|580|t|LT}} of oil that gave her a range of approximately {{convert|4300|nmi|lk=in}} at {{convert|12|kn}}. ''Pillau'' had a crew of twenty-one officers and 421 enlisted men.&lt;ref name=G1101/&gt;

The ship was armed with eight [[15 cm SK L/45]] guns in single pedestal mounts. Two were placed side by side forward on the [[forecastle]], four were located amidships, two on either side, and two were side by side aft.&lt;ref name=C161&gt;Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 161&lt;/ref&gt; She also carried four [[5.2 cm SK L/55 naval gun|5.2&amp;nbsp;cm SK L/55]] anti-aircraft guns, though these were replaced with a pair of two 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm SK L/45 anti-aircraft guns. She was also equipped with a pair of {{convert|50|cm|abbr=on|1}} [[torpedo tube]]s mounted on the deck. She could also carry 120 [[naval mine|mines]]. The [[conning tower]] had {{convert|75|mm|abbr=on}} thick sides, and the deck was covered with up to {{convert|80|mm|abbr=on}} thick armor plate.&lt;ref name=G110&gt;Gröner, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt;

==Service history==

Following her commissioning, ''Pillau'' was assigned to the [[II Scouting Group]]. Her first major operation was the [[Battle of the Gulf of Riga]] in August 1915. A significant detachment from the [[High Seas Fleet]], including eight [[dreadnought]]s and three battlecruisers, went into the Baltic to clear the [[Gulf of Riga]] of Russian naval forces.&lt;ref name=H197&gt;Halpern, p. 197&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 August, Russian submarines fired three torpedoes at the ship, all of which missed.&lt;ref&gt;Polmar &amp; Noot, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; ''Pillau'' participated in the second attack on 16 August, led by the dreadnoughts {{SMS|Nassau||2}} and {{SMS|Posen||2}}.&lt;ref name=H197/&gt; The minesweepers cleared the Russian minefields by the 20th, allowing the German squadron to enter the Gulf. The Russians had by this time withdrawn to [[Moon Sound]], and the threat of Russian [[submarine]]s and mines in the Gulf prompted the Germans to retreat. The major units of the High Seas Fleet were back in the North Sea before the end of August.&lt;ref&gt;Halpern, p. 198&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of Jutland===
[[File:Map of the Battle of Jutland, 1916.svg|thumb|Maps showing the maneuvers of the British (blue) and German (red) fleets on 30–31 May 1916]]
{{main|Battle of Jutland}}

In May 1916, Admiral [[Reinhard Scheer]], the fleet commander, planned to lure a portion of the British fleet away from its bases and destroy it with the entire High Seas Fleet. ''Pillau'' remained in the II Scouting Group, attached to the I Scouting Group, for the operation. The squadron left the [[Jade (river)|Jade]] [[roadstead]] at 02:00 on 31 May, bound for the waters of the [[Skagerrak]]. The main body of the fleet followed an hour and a half later.&lt;ref&gt;Tarrant, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly before 15:30, the opposing cruiser screens engaged; {{SMS|Elbing||2}} was the first German cruiser to encounter the British. ''Pillau'' and {{SMS|Frankfurt||2}} steamed to assist, and at 16:12 they began firing on {{HMS|Galatea|1914|6}} and {{HMS|Phaeton|1914|2}} at a range of {{convert|16300|yd}}. As the British ships turned away, the German shells fell short, and at 16:17, ''Pillau'' and ''Frankfurt'' checked their fire.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, pp. 32&amp;ndash;33&lt;/ref&gt; About fifteen minutes later, the three cruisers engaged a [[seaplane]] launched by the [[seaplane tender]] {{HMS|Engadine|1911|6}}. They failed to score any hits, but the aircraft was forced off after which its engine broke down and it was forced to land. The three cruisers then returned to their stations ahead of the German battlecruisers.&lt;ref&gt;Tarrant, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly before 17:00, the British [[5th Battle Squadron (United Kingdom)|5th Battle Squadron]] had arrived on the scene, and at 16:50 they spotted ''Pillau'', ''Elbing'', and ''Frankfurt''. Eight minutes later, the powerful battleships {{HMS|Warspite|03|6}} and {{HMS|Valiant|1914|2}} opened fire at ''Pillau'' at a range of {{convert|17000|yd}}. Several salvos fell close to the German cruisers, prompting them to lay a cloud of smoke and turn away at high speed.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, pp. 43&amp;ndash;45&lt;/ref&gt; About an hour later, the German battlecruisers were attacked by the destroyers {{HMS|Onslow|1916|2}} and {{HMS|Moresby|1915|2}}, but ''Pillau'', ''Frankfurt'', and the battlecruisers' secondary guns drove them off.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 100&lt;/ref&gt; At around 18:30, ''Pillau'' and the rest of the II Scouting Group encountered the cruiser {{HMS|Chester|1915|6}}; they opened fire and scored several hits on the ship. As both sides' cruisers disengaged, [[Rear Admiral]] [[Horace Hood]]'s three battlecruisers intervened. His flagship {{HMS|Invincible|1907|6}} scored a hit on ''Wiesbaden'' that exploded in her engine room and disabled the ship.&lt;ref&gt;Tarrant, pp. 127–128&lt;/ref&gt; ''Pillau'' was also hit by a {{convert|12|in|abbr=on}} shell from {{HMS|Inflexible|1907|6}}. The shell exploded below the ship's chart house; most of the blast went overboard, but the starboard air supply shaft vented part of the explosion into the second boiler room. All six of the ship's coal-fired boilers were temporarily disabled, though she could still make {{convert|24|kn|abbr=on}} on her four oil-fired boilers, allowing her to escape under cover of heavy fog.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, pp. 112&amp;ndash;113&lt;/ref&gt; By 20:30, three of the six boilers were back in operation, allowing her to steam at {{convert|26|kn|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;

At around 21:20, the II Scouting Group again encountered the British battlecruisers. As they turned away, ''Pillau'' briefly came under fire from the battlecruisers, though to no effect.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 251&lt;/ref&gt; {{HMS|Lion|1910|6}} and {{HMS|Tiger|1913|2}} both fired salvos at the ship before turning their attention to the battlecruiser {{SMS|Derfflinger}}; ''Pillau''{{'}}s official record states that the British shooting was very inaccurate.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; ''Pillau'' and ''Frankfurt'' spotted the cruiser {{HMS|Castor|1915|2}} and several destroyers shortly before 23:00. They each fired a torpedo at the British cruiser before turning back toward the German line without using their searchlights or guns to avoid drawing the British toward the German battleships.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 279&lt;/ref&gt; By 04:00 on 1&amp;nbsp;June, the German fleet had evaded the British fleet and reached [[Horns Reef]].&lt;ref&gt;Tarrant, pp. 246–247&lt;/ref&gt; At 09:30, ''Pillau'' was detached from the fleet to assist the crippled battlecruiser {{SMS|Seydlitz||2}}, which was having trouble navigating back to port. ''Pillau'' steamed ahead of ''Seydlitz'' to guide her back to Wilhelmshaven, but shortly after 10:00, the battlecruiser ran aground off [[Sylt]]. After freeing ''Seydlitz'' at 10:30, the voyage back resumed, with a division of minesweepers steaming ahead testing the depth to prevent another grounding.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, pp. 330&amp;ndash;331&lt;/ref&gt; ''Seydlitz'' continued to take on water and sink lower in the water; she turned around and steamed in reverse in an attempt to improve the situation. ''Pillau'' also attempted to tow the battlecruiser, but was unable because the line repeatedly snapped.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 332&lt;/ref&gt; A pair of pumping steamers arrived in the evening, and slow progress was made through the night, with ''Pillau'' still guiding the voyage. The ships reached the outer Jade [[Lightvessel|lightship]] at 08:30 and anchored twenty minutes later.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 333&lt;/ref&gt; In the course of the engagement, ''Pillau'' had fired 113 rounds of 15&amp;nbsp;cm ammunition and four 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm shells.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 360&lt;/ref&gt; She also launched one torpedo.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 403&lt;/ref&gt; Her crew suffered four men killed and twenty-three wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 341&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later service===
In July 1917, a series of mutinies occurred on several ships of the fleet, including ''Pillau''. While the ship was in harbor in Wilhelmshaven on the 20th, a group of 137 men left the ship to protest a cancellation of their leave. After a couple of hours in the town, the men returned to the ship and began to complete the tasks they had been ordered to do that morning as a show of good will. ''Pillau''{{'}}s commander did not take the event seriously, and ordered a limited punishment for the crewmen who had staged the protest.&lt;ref&gt;Woodward, pp. 71&amp;ndash;72&lt;/ref&gt; By late 1917, ''Pillau'' had been assigned to the [[IV Scouting Group]], along with {{SMS|Stralsund||2}} and {{SMS|Regensburg||2}}. In late October 1917, the IV Scouting Group steamed to [[Baltiysk|Pillau]], arriving on the 30th. They were tasked with replacing the heavy units of the fleet that had just completed [[Operation Albion]], the conquest of the islands in the [[Gulf of Riga]], along with the battleships of the [[I Battle Squadron]]. The risk of mines that had come loose in a recent storm, however, prompted the naval command to cancel the mission, and ''Pillau'' and the rest of the IV Scouting Group was ordered to return to the North Sea on 31 October.&lt;ref&gt;Staff, pp. 146–147&lt;/ref&gt; 

Upon returning the North Sea, ''Pillau'' returned to the II Scouting Group. On 17 November, the four cruisers of the II Scouting Group, supported by the battleships {{SMS|Kaiser||2}} and {{SMS|Kaiserin||2}}, covered a minesweeping operation in the North Sea. They were attacked by British cruisers, supported by battlecruisers and battleships, in the [[Battle of Heligoland Bight (1917)|Second Battle of Heligoland Bight]]. {{SMS|Königsberg|1915|2}}, the II Scouting Group flagship, was damaged in the engagement, but the four cruisers managed to pull away from the British, drawing them toward the German dreadnoughts. They in turn forced the British to break off the attack; neither side had significant success in the operation. ''Pillau'' emerged from the battle unscathed.&lt;ref&gt;Woodward, pp. 90&amp;ndash;91&lt;/ref&gt; On 23&amp;ndash;24 April 1918, the ship participated in an abortive fleet operation to attack British convoys to Norway. The [[I Scouting Group]] and II Scouting Group, along with the Second Torpedo-Boat Flotilla were to attack a heavily guarded British convoy to Norway, with the rest of the High Seas Fleet steaming in support.&lt;ref&gt;Halpern, p. 418&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans failed to locate the convoy, which had in fact sailed the day before the fleet left port. As a result, Admiral [[Reinhard Scheer]] broke off the operation and returned to port.&lt;ref&gt;Halpern, p. 419&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 1918, ''Pillau'' and the rest of the II Scouting Group were to lead a [[Naval order of 24 October 1918|final attack]] on the British navy. ''Pillau'', {{SMS|Cöln|1916|2}}, {{SMS|Dresden|1917|2}}, and ''Königsberg'' were to attack merchant shipping in the [[Thames estuary]] while ''Karlsruhe'', ''Nürnberg'', and {{SMS|Graudenz||2}} were to bombard targets in [[Flanders]], to draw out the British [[Grand Fleet]].&lt;ref name=W116&gt;Woodward, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; Admirals [[Reinhard Scheer]] and [[Franz von Hipper]] intended to inflict as much damage as possible on the British navy, in order to secure a better bargaining position for Germany, whatever the cost to the fleet.&lt;ref&gt;Tarrant, pp. 280–281&lt;/ref&gt; On the morning of 29 October 1918, the order was given to sail from Wilhelmshaven the following day. Starting on the night of 29 October, sailors on {{SMS|Thüringen||2}} and then on several other battleships [[Wilhelmshaven mutiny|mutinied]].&lt;ref&gt;Tarrant, pp. 281–282&lt;/ref&gt; The unrest ultimately forced Hipper and Scheer to cancel the operation.&lt;ref name=T282&gt;Tarrant, p. 282&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italian service===
''Pillau'' briefly served in the newly reorganized ''[[Reichsmarine]]'' following the end of the war. She was stricken on 5 November 1919 and surrendered to the Allies in the French port of [[Cherbourg]] on 20 July 1920. She was ceded to Italy as a [[war prize]] under the name &quot;U&quot;.&lt;ref name=G111/&gt; She was renamed ''Bari'' and commissioned into the [[Regia Marina]] on 21 January 1924. The 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm anti-aircraft guns were replaced with {{convert|76|mm|abbr=on}} /40 guns.&lt;ref name=C265/&gt; In August 1925, ''Bari'' ran aground off [[Palermo]], [[Sicily]]; she was refloated on 20 September.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper The Times |articlename=Telegrams in Brief |day_of_week=Tuesday |date=22 September 1925 |page_number=13 |issue=44074 |column=G }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 July 1929, ''Bari'' was reclassified as a cruiser.&lt;ref name=C265&gt;Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 265&lt;/ref&gt; In 1933&amp;ndash;1934, she was refitted for colonial service and converted to oil-firing.&lt;ref name=Whitley&gt;Whitley, pp. 156&amp;ndash;157&lt;/ref&gt; The six coal-fired boilers were removed to allow for additional oil bunker space, and the forward funnel was removed and the remaining two were cut down. This reduced her power to {{convert|21000|shp}} and a top speed of {{convert|24.5|kn|abbr=on}}. Her cruising range was increased considerably, from {{convert|2600|nmi|abbr=on}} at {{convert|14|kn|abbr=on}} to {{convert|4000|nmi|abbr=on}} at that speed.&lt;ref name=C265/&gt;

By the outbreak of [[World War II]] in [[europe]] in September 1939, her armament had been increased by six {{convert|20|mm|abbr=on}} guns and six {{convert|13.2|mm|abbr=on}} machine guns.&lt;ref name=C265/&gt; Italy entered the war on the side of the [[Axis powers|Axis]] in June 1940. ''Bari''′s wartime career was in support of landings at [[Corfu]] in 1940 and [[Bastia]] in 1942 and anti-partisan bombardments off the [[Montenegro|Montenegrin]] coast in 1942.&lt;ref name=Whitley/&gt; In early 1943, she was slated for conversion to an anti-aircraft ship. She was to be rearmed with six {{convert|90|mm|abbr=on}} /50 guns, eight {{convert|37|mm|abbr=on}} guns, and eight new model 20&amp;nbsp;mm /65 or /70 machine guns. On 28 June, however, American bombers badly damaged ''Bari'' at [[Livorno]] and she sank in shallow water two days later.&lt;ref name=C265/&gt; At the [[Italian armistice]] in September 1943, she was further damaged to render her useless to the German occupiers.&lt;ref name=Whitley/&gt; The wreck was partially scrapped by the Germans in 1944. She was officially removed from the navy list on 27 February 1947, and raised on 13 January 1948 for scrapping.&lt;ref name=C265/&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==References==
* {{cite book |last=Campbell|first=John|title=Jutland: An Analysis of the Fighting|year=1998|location=London, UK|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|isbn=1-55821-759-2}}
*{{cite book|editor1-last=Gardiner|editor1-first=Robert|editor2-last=Gray|editor2-first=Randal|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1922|year=1984|location=Annapolis, MD|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-87021-907-3}}
*{{Cite book |last=Gröner|first=Erich|title=German Warships: 1815–1945|year=1990|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-87021-790-9|location=Annapolis, MD}}
*{{Cite book |last=Halpern|first=Paul G.|title=A Naval History of World War I|year=1995|location=Annapolis, MD|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=1-55750-352-4}}
*{{Cite book |last1=Polmar|first1=Norman|last2=Noot|first2=Jurrien|title=Submarines of the Russian and Soviet Navies, 1718&amp;ndash;1990|year=1991|location=Annapolis|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-87021-570-1}}
*{{cite book |last=Staff|first=Gary|title=Battle for the Baltic Islands|year=2008|location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Maritime|isbn=978-1-84415-787-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Tarrant|first=V. E.|title=Jutland: The German Perspective|year=1995|location=London|publisher=Cassell Military Paperbacks|isbn=0-304-35848-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Whitley|first=M J|title=Cruisers of World War Two: An International Encyclopedia|publisher=Arms and Armour Press|year=1995|location=London, UK|isbn=1-85409-225-1}}
* {{cite book |last=Woodward|first=David|title=The Collapse of Power: Mutiny in the High Seas Fleet|year=1973|publisher=Arthur Barker Ltd|isbn=0-213-16431-0|location=London}}

{{Pillau class light cruiser}}
{{1925 shipwrecks}}
{{June 1943 shipwrecks}}
{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pillau}}
[[Category:Pillau-class cruisers]]
[[Category:Ships built in Danzig]]
[[Category:1914 ships]]
[[Category:World War I cruisers of Germany]]
[[Category:Cruisers of the Regia Marina]]
[[Category:World War II cruisers of Italy]]
[[Category:Ships sunk by US aircraft]]
[[Category:Ships built by Schichau]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1925]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in June 1943]]</text>
      <sha1>92xifee8v65bmin9zk2ejj9lnb083or</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
