<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Kaiser (1858)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38792504</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745958271</id>
      <parentid>745337296</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T11:59:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Parsecboy</username>
        <id>1879095</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22097">{{good article}}
{{other ships|SMS Kaiser}}
{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:Kaiser (ship, 1859) - NH 87010.jpg|300px]]
| Ship caption = SMS ''Kaiser'' in her original configuration
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header = 
| Ship country = [[Austria-Hungary]]
| Ship flag = {{shipboxflag|Austria-Hungary|naval}}
| Ship name = SMS ''Kaiser''
| Ship namesake = [[Kaiser]]
| Ship builder = 
| Ship laid down = 25 March 1855
| Ship launched = 4 October 1858
| Ship commissioned = 1859
| Ship renamed = ''Bellona'', 1902
| Ship fate = Unknown after 1918
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = (as built)
| Ship displacement = {{convert|5194|MT|sp=us|abbr=on}}
| Ship length = {{convert|242|ft|10|in|flip=yes}}
| Ship beam   = {{convert|53|ft|2|in|flip=yes}}
| Ship propulsion =
* 1 × two-cylinder horizontal [[steam engine]]
|ship power=
*6 × [[boiler]]s
*800&amp;nbsp;[[nominal horsepower]]
| Ship speed =
| Ship range =
| Ship complement =900
| Ship armament =
*16 × 60-pounder guns
*74 × 30-pounder guns
*2 × 24-pounder guns
| Ship notes = 
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = (1873)
| Ship displacement = {{convert|5720|MT|sp=us|abbr=on}}
| Ship length = {{convert|255|ft|flip=yes}}
| Ship beam   = {{convert|58|ft|3|in|in|flip=yes}}
| Ship draft  = {{convert|24|ft|2|in|in|flip=yes}}
|ship power=
*{{convert|2786|ihp|abbr=on}}
| Ship speed = {{convert|11.55|kn|abbr=on}}
| Ship range =
| Ship complement =471
| Ship armament =
*10 × {{convert|9|in|abbr=on|0}} guns
*6 × 8-pounder guns
| Ship armor = 
*[[Belt armor|Belt]]: {{convert|152|mm|abbr=on}}
*[[Casemate]]: {{convert|127|mm|abbr=on}}
}}
|}
'''SMS ''Kaiser''''' was a 92-gun wooden [[ship of the line]] of the [[Austrian Navy]], the last vessel of the type, and the only screw-driven example, to be built by the Austrians. She was built by the naval shipyard in [[Pula|Pola]]; she was laid down in March 1855, was launched in October 1858, and was completed the following year. The ship took part in the [[Second Schleswig War]] of 1864, but saw no action during her deployment to the [[North Sea]]. ''Kaiser'' did see action during the [[Seven Weeks' War]] two years later, during which she took part in the [[Battle of Lissa (1866)|Battle of Lissa]] as the [[flagship]] of [[Anton von Petz]], commander of the Austrian 2nd Division. ''Kaiser'' engaged several Italian ironclads simultaneously, rammed one&amp;mdash;{{ship|Italian ironclad|Re di Portogallo||2}}&amp;mdash;and damaged another&amp;mdash;{{ship|Italian ironclad|Affondatore||2}}&amp;mdash;with gunfire. In doing so, she became the only wooden ship of the line to engage an [[ironclad warship]] in battle.

In 1869, the Austro-Hungarians decided to rebuild ''Kaiser'' into an ironclad [[casemate ship]]; the work lasted until 1873, and was delayed significantly by budget shortfalls, which slowed the acquisition of armor plate from British firms. By this time, however, casemate ships were being superseded by [[turret ship]]s, and as a result, ''Kaiser'' spent the years 1875&amp;ndash;1902 in reserve. She was nevertheless modernized periodically throughout the 1870s and 1880s in attempts to improve her performance. In 1901&amp;ndash;02, she was renamed '''''Bellona''''' and had her armament and engines removed so she could be used as a [[barracks ship]] in Pola, a role she filled through [[World War I]]. Italy seized the ship as a [[war prize]] after the end of the conflict, but her ultimate fate is unknown

==Design==
Starting in the early 1850s, the [[Austrian Empire]], faced with a strengthening [[Kingdom of Sardinia]]&amp;mdash;which unified most of the Italian peninsula in a decade&amp;mdash;began to modernize its navy with new steam-driven warships. [[Archduke]] [[Maximilian I of Mexico|Ferdinand Maximilian]] oversaw the program, which began with the screw [[frigate]] {{SMS|Radetzky|1854|2}} laid down in Britain in 1852. Two years later, Ferdinand decided a steam [[ship of the line]] should be built next; he originally intended the new ship would be built as a copy of the British 91-gun ship of the line {{HMS|Agamemnon|1852|6}}, the plans for which the [[Royal Navy]] provided to Austria in exchange for the country remaining neutral during the [[Crimean War]] of 1853&amp;ndash;1856. The excellent performance of the French ship {{ship|French ship|Algésiras|1855|2}} during the war prompted the Austrians to modify the ''Agamemnon'' design to incorporate features of the French vessel, including a greater size and more powerful machinery. A second vessel of a slightly larger design, to have been named ''Österreich'' and armed with 101 guns, was cancelled in 1859 before she was [[keel laying|laid down]].&lt;ref&gt;Lambert, pp. 114&amp;ndash;115&lt;/ref&gt;

Figures for ''Kaiser''{{'}}s original characteristics are unclear. According to the contemporary historian Wilhelm von Rüstow, ''Kaiser'' was {{convert|242|ft|flip=yes|sp=us}} long, with a displacement of {{convert|5337|MT|sp=us}}.&lt;ref name=R670/&gt; But the modern naval historian Andrew Lambert states her length was {{convert|242|ft|10|in|flip=yes}} on {{convert|5194|MT|sp=us|abbr=on}}. He also provides a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|53|ft|2|in|flip=yes}}.&lt;ref name=L147&gt;Lambert, p. 147&lt;/ref&gt; Her crew numbered some 900&amp;nbsp;officers and men, which included a contingent of naval [[infantry]]. She was armed with a battery of ninety-two guns, consisting of sixteen 60-pounder guns, seventy-four 30-pounder [[smoothbore]]s, and two 24-pounder [[breech loader]]s.&lt;ref name=R670&gt;Rüstow, p. 670&lt;/ref&gt; The ship was powered by a two-cylinder horizontal [[steam engine]], which drove a single [[screw propeller]] that was {{convert|5.75|m|abbr=on}} in diameter. Steam was provided by six coal-fired [[boiler]]s with twenty-six [[firebox (steam engine)|fireboxes]]. The engine, which was manufactured by [[Maudslay, Sons and Field]], was rated at 800&amp;nbsp;[[nominal horsepower]]. A three-[[mast (sailing)|masted]] [[ship rig]] supplemented the steam engine.&lt;ref name=G270/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lambert, pp. 114, 147&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=P49/&gt;

==Service history==
The [[keel]] of ''Kaiser'' was laid down on 25 March 1855 at the naval shipyard in [[Pula|Pola]];&lt;ref name=G270&gt;Gardiner, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt; the ship was launched on 4 October 1858, and commissioned into the Austrian Navy in 1859. She began [[sea trials]] on 6 December that year, with the first trip under her own power taking place from [[Muggia]] to Pola.&lt;ref&gt;Aichelburg, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1864, the Austrian Empire joined [[Prussia]] in the [[Second Schleswig War]] against Denmark. ''Kaiser'' was sent with the new [[armored frigate]] {{SMS|Juan de Austria||2}} and two smaller vessels under Vice Admiral [[Bernhard von Wüllerstorf-Urbair]] to reinforce a smaller force consisting of the screw frigates {{SMS|Schwarzenberg||2}} and ''Radetzky'' under then-Captain [[Wilhelm von Tegetthoff]]. After the two groups combined in [[Den Helder]], the Netherlands, they proceeded to [[Cuxhaven]] on 27 June, arriving three days later. The now outnumbered Danish fleet remained in port for the rest of the war and did not seek battle with the Austro-Prussian squadron. Instead, the Austrian and Prussian naval forces supported operations to capture the islands off the western Danish coast.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 210&amp;ndash;211&lt;/ref&gt; During the campaign, ''Kaiser'' was commanded by [[Friedrich von Pöck]].&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of Lissa===
{{main article|Battle of Lissa (1866)}}
[[File:Ludwig Rubelli von Sturmfest Die Schlacht bei Lissa.jpg|left|thumb|''Kaiser'' surrounded by Italian ironclads at Lissa]]

In June 1866, Italy declared war on Austria, as part of the [[Third Italian War of Independence]], which was fought concurrently with the [[Austro-Prussian War]].&lt;ref name=S1&gt;Sondhaus, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; Tegetthoff, by now promoted to Rear Admiral and given command of the entire fleet, brought the Austrian fleet to [[Ancona]] on 27 June, in an attempt to draw out the Italians, but the Italian commander, Admiral [[Carlo Pellion di Persano]], refused to engage Tegetthoff.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 216&amp;ndash;218&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, ''Kaiser'' served as the [[flagship]] of the 2nd Division of the Austrian fleet, under the command of Baron [[Anton von Petz]].&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 July, Persano took the Italian fleet, with twelve ironclads, out of Ancona, bound for the island of [[Vis (island)|Lissa]], where they arrived on the 18th. With them, they brought [[troop transport]]s carrying 3,000 soldiers.&lt;ref name=S1/&gt; Persano then spent the next two days bombarding the Austrian defenses of the island and unsuccessfully attempting to force a landing.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 221&amp;ndash;224&lt;/ref&gt; Tegetthoff received a series of telegrams between 17 and 19 July notifying him of the Italian attack, which he initially believed to be a feint to draw the Austrian fleet away from its main bases at Pola and [[Venice]]. By the morning of the 19th, however, he was convinced that Lissa was in fact the Italian objective, and so he requested permission to attack.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 229&amp;ndash;230&lt;/ref&gt;

As Tegetthoff's fleet arrived off Lissa on the morning of 20 July, Persano's fleet was arrayed for another landing attempt. The latter's ships were divided into three groups, with only the first two able to concentrate in time to meet the Austrians.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 223&amp;ndash;225&lt;/ref&gt; Tegetthoff had arranged his ironclad ships into a wedge-shaped formation, with the wooden warships of the 2nd and 3rd Divisions following behind in the same formation. ''Kaiser'' led the 2nd Division at the center of the line.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 230&amp;ndash;231&lt;/ref&gt; While he was forming up his ships, Persano transferred from his flagship, {{ship|Italian ironclad|Re d'Italia||2}}, to the [[turret ship]] {{ship|Italian ironclad|Affondatore||2}}. This created a gap in the Italian [[line of battle|line]], and Tegetthoff seized the opportunity to divide the Italian fleet and create a [[melee]]. He made a pass through the gap, but failed to ram any of the Italian ships, forcing him to turn around and make another attempt.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 232&amp;ndash;235&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime, Petz took ''Kaiser'' and his division further south, hoping to attack the Italian wooden ships that had not joined the action. Instead, the rear of the Italian ironclad line turned to block Petz from Tegetthoff and attacked ''Kaiser''.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 234&amp;ndash;236&lt;/ref&gt; Petz in turn reoriented his division to attack the Italian ironclads, leading the charge with ''Kaiser''.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p. 238&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Kaiser (ship, 1859) - NH 87011.jpg|thumb|''Kaiser'' after the battle, partially [[Dismasting|dismasted]]]]

The ironclads {{ship|Italian ironclad|Castelfidardo||2}}, {{ship|Italian coastal defense ship|Varese||2}}, and {{ship|Italian ironclad|Principe di Carignano||2}} circled around ''Kaiser'', trading broadsides with her. In the ensuing melee, the Austrian and Italian vessels repeatedly attempted to ram each other. Persano arrived in ''Affondatore'' and unsuccessfully tried to ram ''Kaiser'', but missed and struck only a glancing blow. Shortly thereafter, ''Kaiser'' rammed the ironclad {{ship|Italian ironclad|Re di Portogallo||2}} in an attempt to protect the Austrian unarmored ships {{SMS|Erzherzog Friedrich|1857|2}} and {{SMS|Kaiserin Elizabeth||2}}. ''Kaiser'' also struck a glancing blow, however, and inflicted little damage. ''Re di Portogallo'' fired her light guns into the ship in response, starting a fire, and killing or wounding a number of Austrian gunners before ''Kaiser'' could break free. ''Affondatore'' then made a second, unsuccessful attempt to ram ''Kaiser''. Though she missed with her [[naval ram|ram]], ''Affondatore'' did score a hit with one of her guns, badly damaging ''Kaiser'', killing or wounding twenty of her crew.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 238&amp;ndash;240&lt;/ref&gt; In return, ''Kaiser''{{'}}s gunners fired their guns into ''Affondatore''{{'}}s deck, badly holing it and starting a fire, while riflemen in her [[fighting top]]s shot at Italian sailors.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p. 244&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, a shot from ''Kaiser'' struck one of ''Affondatore''{{'}}s turrets, jamming it for the remainder of the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; ''Kaiser'' had lost her foremast and funnel in the collision with ''Re di Portogallo'', and Petz ordered his damaged ship to put into port at Lissa.&lt;ref&gt;Paine, p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

By this time, the Austrian ironclads disengaged from the melee to protect their wooden ships; ''Re d'Italia'' had been rammed and sunk and the [[coastal defense ship]] {{ship|Italian coastal defense ship|Palestro||2}} was burning badly, soon to be destroyed by a [[Magazine (artillery)|magazine]] explosion. Persano made an attempt to follow them with ''Affondatore'', but he broke off the attempt when only one of his other ironclads followed him. His crews were badly demoralized by the lost of ''Re d'Italia'' and ''Palestro'', and his ships were low on ammunition and coal. The Italian fleet began to withdraw, followed by the Austrians; as night began to fall, the opposing fleets disengaged completely, heading for Ancona and Pola, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp. 238&amp;ndash;241, 250&lt;/ref&gt; In the course of the battle, ''Kaiser''{{'}}s crew had suffered twenty-four killed and thirty-seven wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p. 246&lt;/ref&gt; ''Kaiser'' was and is the only ship of the line to have engaged ironclad warships in battle.&lt;ref&gt;Sandler, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conversion and later career===
[[File:Kaiser (1859) - NH 75928.jpg|thumb|left|''Kaiser'' after her reconstruction into a casemate ship]]

After returning to Pola, Tegetthoff kept his fleet in the northern Adriatic, where it patrolled against a possible Italian attack. The Italian ships never came, and on 12 August, the two countries signed the [[Armistice of Cormons]]; this ended the fighting and led to the [[Treaty of Vienna (1866)|Treaty of Vienna]]. Though Austria had defeated Italy at Lissa and on land at the [[Battle of Custoza (1866)|Battle of Custoza]], the Austrian army was decisively defeated by Prussia at the [[Battle of Königgrätz]]. As a result, Austria, which became [[Austria-Hungary]] in the [[Austro-Hungarian Compromise of 1867|''Ausgleich'']] of 1867, was forced to cede the city of Venice to Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, pp. 1&amp;ndash;3&lt;/ref&gt; In the immediate aftermath of the war, the bulk of the Austrian fleet was decommissioned and disarmed.&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

Chronic budgetary problems confronted the navy of the new Austro-Hungarian Empire; Tegetthoff had great difficulty securing funding for new ships to modernize the fleet. In 1868, he attempted to start a new building program, but the government refused to budget for new warships. Parliament did include funds to modernize ''Kaiser'', however.&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 February 1869, ''Kaiser'' was taken into [[drydock]] and her [[hull (watercraft)|hull]] was examined. Found to be in good condition, the ship was rebuilt into an ironclad [[casemate ship]]. Old wood planking below the waterline was replaced, but the hull was completely rebuilt with iron above the waterline. Her bow was replaced with a more pronounced ram and she received a new stern as well. This increased her length to {{convert|77.75|m|abbr=on}} at the waterline and increased her beam to {{convert|17.76|m|abbr=on}}. Her draft remained similar, at {{convert|7.37|m|abbr=on}}, though her displacement increased to {{convert|5720|MT|sp=us|abbr=on}}. Superheaters were added to her original boilers to provide more power, though her top speed fell to {{convert|11.55|kn}} from {{convert|2786|ihp|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=G270/&gt;&lt;ref name=P49/&gt;

The ship was rearmed with a battery of ten {{convert|9|in|abbr=on}} 23-pounder [[muzzle-loading gun]]s manufactured by [[Armstrong Whitworth|Armstrong]] in a central, two-story casemate. These were supported by a [[secondary battery]] of six 8-pounder [[Rifled Muzzle Loader]]s. An [[armored belt]] was installed on the waterline; in the central citadel that protected the machinery spaces, the belt was {{convert|152|mm|abbr=on}} thick. On either end of the ship, the belt was reduced to {{convert|102|mm|abbr=on}}. Iron plating {{convert|127|mm|abbr=on}} thick protected the [[casemate]]. ''Kaiser'' was re-launched in 1871,&lt;ref name=G270/&gt; but further budgetary problems, particularly payments for the armor plate and iron fittings that were purchased from Britain, delayed completion of the conversion.&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; Work was finally completed in December 1873.&lt;ref name=G270/&gt; She began [[sea trial]]s on 21 December.&lt;ref name=P49&gt;Pawlik, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; By this time, the ship had become obsolescent; the same year, Italy laid down the two {{sclass-|Caio Duilio|ironclad|1}}s, very powerful turret ships twice the size of ''Kaiser'' and that carried [[100-ton gun|{{convert|450|mm|abbr=on}} guns]].&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner, p. 340&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Kaiser (1859) - with armour shown.png|thumb|Line drawing of ''Kaiser'' after her reconstruction]]

The ship did not see further active service, however. She remained [[:wikt:laid up|laid up]] from 1875,&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 100&lt;/ref&gt; spending the first four months of 1876 in the II Reserve, followed by repairs and modifications for the rest of the year.&lt;ref name=P50&gt;Pawlik, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, naval engineers attempted to improve the ship's performance. In 1876, her original screw was replaced with a larger propeller that was {{convert|7.62|m|abbr=on}} in diameter. During speed tests conducted on 7 December, the ship reached {{convert|12.72|kn}}, more than a knot increase in speed.&lt;ref name=P49/&gt; She was immediately returned to the II Reserve. In 1880, the ship had her rigging reduced and received new boilers.&lt;ref name=P50/&gt; A new secondary battery that consisted of six {{convert|9|cm|abbr=on}} 24-[[caliber (artillery)|caliber]] (cal.) [[breech-loading gun]]s, two {{convert|7|cm|abbr=on}} 15-cal. guns, four {{convert|47|mm|abbr=on}} 33-cal. [[quick-firing gun]]s, three 47&amp;nbsp;mm [[Hotchkiss gun|Hotchkiss revolver cannon]], and four {{convert|25|mm|abbr=on}} [[machine gun]]s was installed in 1882. In 1885, three {{convert|35|cm|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s were added, one in the bow and one on each broadside.&lt;ref name=G270/&gt;

A commission examined the ship in 1893 and recommended that the ship was &quot;not suitable for commissioning&quot;. The government began negotiations with [[Venezuela]] in 1895 to sell ''Kaiser'', but the discussion came to nothing.&lt;ref name=P50/&gt; In 1897, she was stricken from the list of active battleships.&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; The ship was disarmed in 1901, and the following year had her engines removed so she could be used as a [[barracks ship]] in Pola. She was formally stricken from the [[naval register]] on 4 January 1902, was renamed ''Bellona'', and added to the list of [[hulk (ship)|hulks]]. She served as a barracks ship through [[World War I]]. From 1910 to 1917 the staff of the II Reserve was housed aboard the ship, and in 1918 the naval training school staff was brought aboard as well. After the war the ship was seized by Italy as a [[war prize]]; her ultimate fate is unknown.&lt;ref name=G270/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pawlik, pp. 50, 59&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Greger, p. 135&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
* {{cite book|last=Aichelburg|first=Wladimir|title=Maximilian, Erzherzog von Österreich, Kaiser von Mexiko in zeitgenössischen Photographien|trans-title=Maximilian, Archduke of Austria, Emperor of Mexico in Contemporary Photographs|year=1987|location=Vienna|publisher=Orac|isbn=3-7015-0100-9}}
* {{cite book |editor-last=Gardiner|editor-first=Robert|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1860–1905|year=1979|location=London|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|isbn=0-85177-133-5}}
*{{Cite book |last1=Greene|first1=Jack|last2=Massignani|first2=Alessandro|title=Ironclads at War: The Origin and Development of the Armored Warship, 1854–1891|year=1998|location=Pennsylvania|publisher=Da Capo Press|lastauthoramp=y|isbn=0-938289-58-6}}
* {{cite book| last = Greger| first = René| year = 1976| title = Austro-Hungarian Warships of World War I| publisher = Ian Allan| location = London| isbn = 978-0-7110-0623-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Lambert|first=Andrew|title=Battleships in Transition. The Creation of the Steam Battlefleet 1815–1860|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|year=1984|isbn=0-85177-315-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Paine|first=Lincoln|title=Warships of the World to 1900|year=2000|location=Boston|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|isbn=0-395-98414-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Pawlik|first=Georg|title=Des Kaisers Schwimmende Festungen: die Kasemattschiffe Österreich-Ungarns|trans-title=The Kaiser's Floating Fortresses: The Casemate Ships of Austria-Hungary|year=2003|publisher=Neuer Wissenschaftlicher Verlag|location=Vienna|isbn=978-3-7083-0045-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Rüstow|first=Wilhelm von|authorlink=Wilhelm Rüstow|title=Der deutsch-dänische krieg 1864|trans-title=The German-Danish War 1864|year=1864|location=Zurich|publisher=Schulthess|oclc=20029853}}
*{{Cite book| last=Sondhaus| first=Lawrence| title=The Naval Policy of Austria-Hungary, 1867&amp;ndash;1918| year=1994| location=West Lafayette| publisher=Purdue University Press| isbn=978-1-55753-034-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Sandler|first=Stanley|title=Battleships: An Illustrated History of Their Impact|year=2004|location=Santa Barbara|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=1-85109-410-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilson|first=Herbert Wrigley|title=Ironclads in Action: A Sketch of Naval Warfare from 1855 to 1895|year=1896|publisher=S. Low, Marston and Company|location=London|oclc=1111061}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite journal|first=Christian|last=Ortner|title=Der Seekrieg in der Adria 1866|journal=Viribus Unitis: Jahresbericht 2010 des Heeresgeschichtlichen Museums|pages=100–124|oclc=499702006|publisher=Heeresgeschichtliches Museum|location=Vienna}}

{{SMS Kaiser}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kaiser}}
[[Category:Ironclad warships of the Austro-Hungarian Navy]]
[[Category:Ships built in Pola]]
[[Category:1858 ships]]</text>
      <sha1>ln649ca4zpjb84lcsqyicw9mhbvt5yg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
