<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Stephen III of Hungary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4947882</id>
    <revision>
      <id>708187563</id>
      <parentid>707549934</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-04T04:15:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Borsoka</username>
        <id>6098631</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Family */ -OR</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27280">{{good article}}
{{Infobox royalty|monarch
|name = Stephen III
|full name =
|image =File:Stepan3.jpg
|caption =Stephen III's seal
|succession = [[King of Hungary]] and [[King of Croatia|Croatia]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;contested by [[Ladislaus II of Hungary|Ladislaus II]] (1162–63), and by [[Stephen IV of Hungary|Stephen IV]] (1163–65)&lt;/small&gt;
|reign = 1162–1172
|coronation = June 1162
|cor-type = hungary
|predecessor = [[Géza II of Hungary|Géza II]]
|successor = [[Béla III of Hungary|Béla III]]
|issue-link=#Family
|issue={{plainlist|
* Béla (died young)
* Unnamed Son
}}
|spouse =[[Agnes of Austria (1154–1182)|Agnes of Austria]]
| house = [[Árpád dynasty]]
| house-type=Dynasty
|father = [[Géza II of Hungary]]
|mother = [[Euphrosyne of Kiev]]
|birth_date = Summer of 1147
|birth_place =
|death_date = 4 March {{Death year and age|1172|1147}}
|death_place =
|place of burial= [[Esztergom]]
| religion =[[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]]
|}}
'''Stephen III''' ({{lang-hu|István}}, {{lang-hr|Stjepan}}, {{lang-sk|Štefan}}; summer of 1147{{spaced ndash}}4 March 1172) was [[King of Hungary]] and [[King of Croatia|Croatia]] between 1162 and 1172. He was crowned king in early June 1162, shortly after the death of his father, [[Géza II of Hungary|Géza II]]. However, his two uncles, [[Ladislaus II of Hungary|Ladislaus]] and [[Stephen IV of Hungary|Stephen]], who had joined the court of the [[Byzantine Empire]], challenged his right to the crown. Only six weeks after his coronation, the [[Byzantine Emperor]] [[Manuel I Komnenos]] launched an expedition against Hungary, forcing the Hungarian lords to accept Ladislaus' rule. Stephen sought refuge in [[Duchy of Austria|Austria]], but returned and seized [[Pressburg]] (now Bratislava in [[Slovakia]]). Ladislaus, who died on 14 January 1163, was succeeded by Stephen's younger uncle and namesake, Stephen IV, without resistance, but his rule was unpopular. The young Stephen defeated his uncle on 19 June 1163 and expelled him from Hungary.

Stephen IV attempted to regain his throne with Emperor Manuel I's support, but the latter made peace with Stephen III. He agreed to send his younger brother, [[Béla III of Hungary|Béla]], to [[Constantinople]] and to allow the Byzantines to seize Béla's duchy, which included [[Croatia]], [[Dalmatia]] and [[Sirmium]]. In an attempt to recapture these territories, Stephen III waged wars against the Byzantine Empire between 1164 and 1167, but could not defeat the Byzantines.

Historians attribute the creation of the &quot;[[Székesfehérvár laws]]&quot;, the first example of extensive privileges granted to a town in the [[Kingdom of Hungary]], to him. He concluded a [[concordat]] with the [[Holy See]] in 1169, renouncing the control of the appointment of the prelates. He died childless.

==Childhood (1147–1162) ==
Stephen was the eldest child of [[Géza II of Hungary]] and his wife [[Euphrosyne of Kiev]].{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=190}}{{sfn|Makk|1994|p=293}} He was born in the summer of 1147 when the French [[Second Crusade|crusaders]] were marching through Hungary towards the [[Holy Land]].{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=190}} King [[Louis VII of France]] sponsored his baptism.{{sfn|Makk|1994|p=293}} One Lady Margaret, who wrote her last will in 1152, mentioned that &quot;King Géza reigned together with his son, Duke Stephen&quot; in that year, indicating that the King had officially nominated the child Stephen as his heir.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=190}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=56}} However, his position as his father's successor remained insecure, especially after his two uncles, [[Stephen IV of Hungary|Stephen]] and [[Ladislaus II of Hungary|Ladislaus]], left Hungary in the late 1150s.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=190}}{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=51}} They would settle in the court of the [[Byzantine Emperor]] [[Manuel I Komnenos]] in [[Constantinople]].{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=51}}{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=247}} Géza II granted [[Dalmatia]], [[Croatia]], and [[Sirmium]] to his younger son [[Béla III of Hungary|Béla]] as an [[appanage]] shortly before his death.{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=52}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=77}}

==Reign==

===Struggle for the throne (1162–1164)===
[[File:III Istvan koronazasa KK.jpg|thumb |right |190px |alt=A bishop puts a crown on the head of a man sitting on the throne | Stephen III is crowned king (from the ''[[Illuminated Chronicle]]'')]]
[[File:Chronicon Pictum P121 A korona elrablása.JPG|thumb |right |190px |alt=A man wearing a ducal hat sits on the throne speaks with an other man while a horseman is taking the crown | Stephen III's uncle, [[Ladislaus II of Hungary|Ladislaus II]] usurps the throne (from the ''[[Illuminated Chronicle]]'')]]

Géza II died on 31 May 1162.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=247}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=79}} [[Lucas, Archbishop of Esztergom]], crowned the 15-year-old Stephen king without delay.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=79}}{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=191}} On hearing of Géza II's death, Emperor Manuel hastened towards Hungary,  because he &quot;put a high value on the overlordship&quot; of the country, according to the Byzantine historian [[John Kinnamos]].&lt;ref name=John_Kinnamos_5.1&gt;''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (5.1), p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Makk|1989|pp=79–80}} Another Byzantine historian, [[Niketas Choniates]], wrote that the Emperor decided to support the young King's uncle and namesake, Stephen, to acquire the throne in the hope that &quot;he might receive the undisputed and guaranteed possession&quot; of Sirmium and [[Zimony]] (now Zemun in [[Serbia]]) from his protégé.&lt;ref&gt;''O City of Byzantium, Annals of Niketas Choniates'' (4.127) , p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=81}} When supporting the claim of the late King's brother to the crown, the Emperor referred to &quot;the law of the Hungarians&quot; which prescribed that the crown should pass &quot;always to the survivors of brothers&quot;, according to Kinnamos.&lt;ref name=John_Kinnamos_5.1/&gt;{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=191}} 

Emperor Manuel dispatched an army to Hungary which advanced as far as Haram (now [[Ram, Serbia]]) where his envoys opened negotiations with the Hungarian barons.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=82}} Bribed by the Byzantines and fearful of an invasion by the Emperor, the magnates agreed to accept Ladislaus, who was the older of the young King's two uncles, as a &quot;compromise candidate&quot;.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=247}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=82}} The young Stephen's army was routed at [[Kapuvár]].{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=82}} He fled from Hungary and sought refuge in [[Duchy of Austria|Austria]] six months after his coronation.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=82}} Archbishop Lucas was one of the few who remained loyal to the young monarch, refusing to crown his uncle.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=191}}{{sfn|Bartl|Čičaj|Kohútova|Letz|2002|p=29}} After [[Mikó, Archbishop of Kalocsa]] performed Ladislaus's coronation, Archbishop Lucas even [[excommunication|excommunicated]] the usurper, stating that he had unlawfully seized the crown from his nephew.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=192}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=83}}

Stephen III returned from Austria and captured [[Pressburg]].{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=83}}{{when|date=October 2014}} He could not take advantage of his uncle's death on 14 January 1163, because Ladislaus II was succeeded by his younger brother, Stephen IV.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=83}}{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=52}} However, Stephen IV's unveiled support for the interests of the Byzantine Empire caused discontent among the Hungarian barons.{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=52}} The young Stephen mustered an army of the barons who had deserted his uncle and supplemented it with German mercenaries.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=85}} Stephen III defeated his uncle at [[Székesfehérvár]] on 19 June 1163.{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=52}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=85}} The elder Stephen was captured, but Stephen III released him upon the advice of Archbishop Lucas.{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=52}}{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=193}} The archbishop, along with the Dowager Queen Euphrosyne, remained the young monarch's principal advisors throughout his reign.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=193}} The dethroned Stephen IV first fled to the [[Holy Roman Empire]], but left shortly afterwards for the Byzantine Empire, where Emperor Manuel again promised him support.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=250}}

===Wars with the Byzantine Empire (1164–1167)===
Emperor Manuel sent an army to Hungary to help Stephen IV to regain the throne from his nephew.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=250}} The young Stephen sought assistance from [[Vladislaus II, Duke of Bohemia|Vladislaus]], [[King of Bohemia]], against his uncle and the Byzantines, but the [[Bohemian nobility|Bohemian barons]] refused to fight.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=250}} Thereafter Stephen III sent envoys to Emperor Manuel, but &quot;they promised nothing genuine&quot;, according to Kinnamos.&lt;ref&gt;''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (5.5), p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Makk|1989|pp=86, 159}} The Emperor continued his campaign, but in short &quot;realized that it was then impossible for&quot; his protégé &quot;to rule the Hungarians' land&quot;, and opened negotiations with Stephen III.&lt;ref&gt;''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (5.5), p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=251}} According to their peace treaty, Emperor Manuel recognized the rule of the young Stephen, and the latter agreed to send his brother, Béla, to Constantinople.{{sfn|Treadgold|1997|p=646}}{{sfn|Fine|1991|p=240}} Stephen III also promised that he would allow the Byzantines to take control of Béla's duchy.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=86}} 

Abandoned by Emperor Manuel, Stephen IV approached [[Frederick I, Holy Roman Emperor]].{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=89}} Around the same time, a group of Hungarian barons and prelates sent a letter to Emperor Frederick, stating that they were willing to accept his suzerainty.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=89}} Stephen III also dispatched his envoys to Frederick, who decided not to intervene, but ordered his vassals{{mdash}}the King of Bohemia, the [[Duke of Austria]], and the [[Margrave of Styria]]{{mdash}}to keep an eye on the political situation in Hungary.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=89}} King Vladislaus' son, Sviatopluk, even married Stephen III's sister, [[Odola of Hungary|Odola]].{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=250}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=89}}{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=194}} The betrothal of Stephen III to an unnamed daughter of [[Yaroslav Osmomysl]], [[Prince of Halych]], was also arranged around this time.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=89}}

Next year Stephen broke his treaty with Emperor Manuel I and &quot;usurped Béla's heritage&quot;, according to Kinnamos.&lt;ref&gt;''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (5.5), p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Makk|1989|pp=90, 161}} A charter of 1164 of [[Peter, Archbishop of Spalato]] (now [[Split, Croatia]]) was dated in reference to the rule of Stephen III and his [[Ban of Dalmatia|ban]], [[Ampud]], suggesting that at least a part of Béla's duchy{{mdash}}Central Dalmatia{{mdash}}was under Stephen III's rule in that year.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=161}} On the other hand, Stephen III's dethroned uncle invaded [[Sirmium]] where masses of the residents celebrated his return.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|pp=251–252}}{{sfn|Curta|2006|pp=332–333}} Accompanied by the forces of King Vladislaus of Bohemia, and auxiliary troops from Austria and [[Halych]], Stephen III launched a campaign against him.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=90}} Emperor Manuel I, who was about to march against [[Armenian Cilicia]], returned to the Danube and stormed into Hungary, advancing as far as Bács (now [[Bač, Serbia]]).{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=90}}{{sfn|Curta|2006|p=333}} He contacted King Vladislaus and persuaded him to negotiate a peace treaty with Stephen III.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=252}} Abandoned by his most important ally, Stephen III was obliged to renounce Sirmium in favor of the Byzantine Empire, but only after the Emperor promised that he would never support his uncle.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=252}} Even so, Emperor Manuel allowed the dethroned king to stay in Sirmium.{{sfn|Curta|2006|p=333}}   
[[File:Manuel I Comnenus.jpg|thumb |right |190px |alt=A bearded man wearing a crown | [[Byzantine Emperor]] [[Manuel I Komnenos]] who seized large parts of Stephen III's kingdom]]
{{Quote|We have come, my boy, not to wage war on the Hungarians but to recover his land for Béla, your brother, not something which we have torn away by our might, but which you and your father long before granted. Also to rescue from peril your uncle Stephen, who is [[Maria Komnene, Queen of Hungary|related by marriage to our majesty]]. If it is according to your will that Béla [[Maria Komnene (Porphyrogenita)|should be our son-in-law]], something which was previously agreed by you, why do you quickly abandon our friendship by failing to render him the land? If you oppose the marriage, and something else seems right to you in regard to it, know that we abstain from constraining you further.|''Emperor Manuel I's letter of 1164 to Stephen III''&lt;ref&gt;''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (5.6), p. 165.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In short, Stephen III invaded Dalmatia, although he had pledged to [[Vitale II Michiel]], [[Doge of Venice]], that he would withdraw from the Dalmatian towns.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=255}} Upon Stephen's arrival the citizens of [[Zadar]] expelled the Venetian governor and accepted his suzerainty.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=255}}{{sfn|Curta|2006|p=342}} He again stormed into Sirmium and laid siege to his uncle in Zimony in spring 1165.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=255}} Emperor Manuel decided to make a counterattack, but a rebellion by his cousin [[Andronikos I Komnenos|Andronikos Komnenos]] prevented him from marching to the Danube.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=255}} Nevertheless, Manuel I sent envoys to the monarchs who had earlier supported Stephen III, persuading them to remain neutral in the conflict.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=91}} Stephen III's uncle died of poisoning during the siege of Zimony, on 11 April.{{sfn|Bartl|Čičaj|Kohútova|Letz|2002|p=29}} The fortress soon fell to Stephen III.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=92}} The Byzantine counter-offensive started at the end of June.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=92}} An army under the command of Emperor Manuel I laid siege to Zimony and recaptured it; an other Byzantine force invaded and occupied Bosnia and Dalmatia.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=92}}{{sfn|Curta|2006|pp=333, 342}} The Venetian fleet intervened on the Byzantines' side in Dalmatia, forcing Zadar to again accept the rule of the Doge.{{sfn|Curta|2006|p=342}}{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=256}} Stephen III could only conclude a new peace treaty with Emperor Manuel after he renounced Sirmium and Dalmatia.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=92}}{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=256}} 

{{Quote|[Stephen] sent envoys to the emperor, men of the aristocracy and one who enjoyed the office of bishop, and agreed to render [Sirmium] again to the [[Rhomaios|Romans]], and in addition the whole of Dalmatia. When they came in sight of the emperor, they uttered what had been commanded to them and petitioned the emperor to abandon his wrath. At first he refused, saying, &quot;It would indeed be estimable, envoys, if someone thought it proper to restore those things which he had previously stolen. We hold [Sirmium], we have regained [Zimony], we are already masters of the Dalmatians, we are lords of all those together, of which you the givers have been deprived. So then is there among you another [Sirmium]? Is there another [Zimony] and Dalmatia which you now come giving us? ...&quot; So he first answered them, then changing his mind, he said, &quot;But then, so that you may know that we wish to make peace as a gift to you, who are Christians, come, take the oaths.&quot; |[[John Kinnamos]]: ''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus''&lt;ref&gt;''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (5.16), p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A Hungarian army under the command of ''[[Ispán]]'' [[Denis, Palatine of Hungary|Denis]] stormed into Sirmium once more in spring 1166.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}}{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=259}} The Hungarians routed a Byzantine army, and occupied the whole province with the exception of Zimony.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}}{{sfn|Fine|1991|p=242}} Emperor Manuel sent three armies against Hungary.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}} The first army, which was under the command of ''[[protostrator]]'' [[Alexios Axuch]] and Stephen III's brother, Béla, was stationed by the Danube to distract attention from the movements of the two other units, which plundered Transylvania under the command of Leon Batatzes and [[John Doukas (general under Manuel I)|John Doukas]].{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}}{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=260}} The Byzantine campaign caused great devastation in the eastern territories of the Kingdom of Hungary, forcing Stephen III to seek reconciliation.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}} Upon his request, [[Henry Jasomirgott]], [[Duke of Austria]], [[Theodora Komnene, Duchess of Austria|whose wife]] was Emperor Manuel's niece, mediated an armistice.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}}{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=260}} At the end of the year, Stephen married the Duke's daughter [[Agnes of Austria (1154–1182)|Agnes]].{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}} Around the same time, a Hungarian army invaded Dalmatia and captured Nikephoros Chalouphes, the Byzantine governor of the province.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=100}}{{sfn|Curta|2006|p=343}} Stephen confirmed estates in [[Biograd na Moru]] and the privileges of Sebenico in 1166 and 1167, respectively, proving that the two towns accepted his suzerainty after the campaign.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=167}}

Emperor Manuel dispatched an army to Sirmium and sent his fleet to Zimony after Easter 1167.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=100}} The Hungarians assembled their troops, and recruited no small number of allied forces as mercenaries, especially Germans, according to Choniates.&lt;ref&gt;''O City of Byzantium, Annals of Niketas Choniates'' (4.153) , p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=100}} The contemporaneous [[Rahewin]] writes that Stephen III &quot;made war on the emperor of the Greeks&quot; because he had received and assisted his brother, Béla.&lt;ref&gt;''The Deeds of Frederick Barbarossa'' (Appendix), p. 337.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=101}} According to Rahewin and [[Henry of Mügeln]], Stephen received support from his father-in-law, Duke Henry Jasomirgott.{{sfn|Makk|1989|pp=100–101}} However, the Byzantine army led by [[Andronikos Kontostephanos]] annihilated the Hungarians, who were under the command of ''Ispán'' Denis, in [[Battle of Sirmium|a decisive battle]] which was fought near Zimony on 8 July.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=100}}{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|pp=260–261}} Kinnamos wrote that &quot;the war on the Hungarians&quot; concluded on the battlefield.&lt;ref&gt;''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (5.8), p. 205.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=261}} According to Henry of Mügeln, Stephen signed a peace treaty renouncing the duchy that their father had bequeathed upon his brother, Béla.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=101}} He also came to terms with Doge Vitale Michiel, giving his niece, Mary, to the Doge's son, [[Nicholas Michiel|Nicholas]], on 17 December 1167, according to the early 13th-century ''History of the Doges of Venice''.{{sfn|Stephenson|2000|p=261}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=104}}

===Later years (1167–1172)===
There is evidence that suggests that Stephen seized Church revenues to finance his war with the Byzantine Empire.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=195}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=105}} The correspondence of [[Thomas Becket]] and [[John of Salisbury]] reveals that the principles of the [[Gregorian Reform]] were not fully introduced in Hungary &quot;on account of the unbridled acts of tyranny by the seculars against the apostolic institutions&quot; in the late 1160s.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=105}} Stephen transferred [[Prodanus]], [[Bishop of Zagreb]] from his diocese without consulting the Holy See.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=105}} [[Pope Alexander III]] sent [[papal legate|his legate]] Cardinal Manfred to Hungary in 1169, who discussed the debated issues with the king, the queen mother, and the prelates.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=105}} The negotiations ended with an agreement that prohibited the monarch from arbitrarily deposing or relocating the prelates or confiscating their property.{{sfn|Makk|1989|pp=105–106}} The Pope supported Stephen against Archbishop Lucas of Esztergom when the Archbishop attempted to hinder the consecration of the King's protégé, Andrew, [[Bishop of Győr|Bishop-elect of Győr]], because of his allegedly non-canonical election.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=195}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=106}}

The [[Knights Templar]] settled in Hungary during Stephen's reign.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=195}} According to historians Ferenc Makk and Pál Engel, Stephen III granted special privileges to the [[Walloons|Walloon]] settlers of [[Székesfehérvár]], including their exemption of [[Duty (economics)|customs duties]] throughout the kingdom.{{sfn|Makk|1994|p=293}}{{sfn|Kubinyi|1994|p=629}}{{sfn|Engel|2001|p=293}} In the 13th century, the same privileges, the so-called &quot;[[Székesfehérvár laws]]&quot;, were granted to additional towns, contributing to their development.{{sfn|Kubinyi|1994|p=628}}  

Stephen died on 4 March 1172.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=106}}{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=196}} [[Arnold of Lübeck]], who was in Hungary at that time, wrote that a rumor spreading in the country attributed the 25-year-old monarch's unexpected death to poisoning.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=106}} Stephen was buried in [[Esztergom]].{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=196}}

==Family==
{{ahnentafel top|width=100%|Ancestors of Stephen III of Hungary{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=190, Appendices 2–3}}}}
&lt;center&gt;{{ahnentafel-compact5
|style=font-size: 90%; line-height: 110%;
|border=1
|boxstyle=padding-top: 0; padding-bottom: 0;
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Stephen III of Hungary'''

|2= 2. [[Géza II of Hungary]]
|3= 3. [[Euphrosyne of Kiev]]
|4= 4. [[Béla II of Hungary]]
|5= 5. [[Helena of Serbia, Queen of Hungary|Helena of Rascia]]
|6= 6. [[Mstislav I of Kiev]]
|7=  
|8= 8. [[Álmos, Duke of Croatia]] 
|9= 9. [[Predslava of Kiev]]
|10= 10. [[Uroš I, Grand Prince of Serbia|Uroš I of Serbia]]
|11= 
|12= 
|13= 
|14=
|16= 16. [[Géza I of Hungary]]
|17= 17. Sophia
|18= 18. [[Sviatopolk II of Kiev]]
|19=
|20=
|22=
|23=
|24=
|25=
|26=
|27=
}}&lt;/center&gt;
{{ahnentafel bottom}}
Stephen's betrothal to the daughter of Yaroslav Osmomysl of Halych was broken in 1166.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=194}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=99}} He married Agnes of Austria at the end of the year.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=194}} From this marriage a son, Béla, was born in 1167, but the child died in the same year.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=196}}{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=167}} Agnes survived her husband and was pregnant at the time of his death.{{sfn|Kristó|Makk|1996|p=196}} Her father, who was staying in Hungary when Stephen III died, took Agnes back to Austria.{{sfn|Makk|1989|p=107}} Agnes gave birth to a second son, but his fate is unknown.{{sfn|Bodri|2003|p=114}} She later married [[Herman, Duke of Carinthia]].{{sfn|Bodri|2003|p=114}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|25em}}

==Sources==
===Primary sources===
{{Refbegin}}
*''Deeds of John and Manuel Comnenus by John Kinnamos'' (Translated by Charles M. Brand) (1976). Columbia University Press. ISBN 0-231-04080-6.
*''O City of Byzantium, Annals of Niketas Choniatēs'' (Translated by Harry J. Magoulias) (1984). Wayne State University Press. ISBN 978-0-8143-1764-8.
*''The Deeds of Frederick Barbarossa by Otto of Freising and his Continuator, Rahewin'' (Translated and annotated with an introduction by Charles Christopher Mierow with the collaboration of Richard Emery) (2004). Columbia University Press. ISBN 0-231-13419-3.
{{Refend}}

===Secondary sources===
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last1=Bartl |first1=Július |last2=Čičaj |first2=Viliam |last3=Kohútova |first3=Mária |last4=Letz |first4=Róbert |last5=Segeš |first5=Vladimír |last6=Škvarna |first6=Dušan |year=2002|title=Slovak History: Chronology &amp; Lexicon |publisher= Bolchazy-Carducci Publishers, Slovenské Pedegogické Nakladatel'stvo |isbn=0-86516-444-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Bodri |first=Ferenc |year=2003 |title=Lukács érsek és kora [Archbishop Lucas and his Times] |publisher=Kossuth Kiadó |isbn=963-09-4474-X |ref=harv|language=hu}}
*{{cite book |last=Curta |first=Florin |year=2006 |title=Southeastern Europe in the Middle Ages, 500–1250 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-89452-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Engel |first=Pál |year=2001 |title=The Realm of St Stephen: A History of Medieval Hungary, 895–1526 |publisher= I.B. Tauris Publishers |isbn=1-86064-061-3|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Fine |first=John V. A |year=1991  |title=The Early Medieval Balkans: A Critical Survey from the Sixth to the Late Twelfth century |publisher= The University of Michigan Press |isbn=0-472-08149-7|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book |last1=Kristó |first1=Gyula |last2=Makk |first2=Ferenc |year=1996 |title=Az Árpád-ház uralkodói ''[Rulers of the House of Árpád]''|publisher=I.P.C. Könyvek | isbn=963-7930-97-3|ref=harv|language=hu}}
*{{cite book |last=Kubinyi |first=András |editor1-last=Kristó |editor1-first=Gyula |editor2-last=Engel |editor2-first=Pál |editor3-last=Makk |editor3-first=Ferenc | title=Korai magyar történeti lexikon (9–14. század) ''[Encyclopedia of the Early Hungarian History (9th–14th centuries)]'' |publisher=Akadémiai Kiadó |year=1994 |page=628-629 |chapter=székesfehérvári jog [Székesfehérvár laws] |isbn=963-05-6722-9|ref=harv|language=hu}}
*{{cite book |last=Makk |first=Ferenc |year=1989 |title=The Árpáds and the Comneni: Political Relations between Hungary and Byzantium in the 12th century (Translated by György Novák)|publisher=Akadémiai Kiadó |isbn=963-05-5268-X|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Makk |first=Ferenc |editor1-last=Kristó |editor1-first=Gyula |editor2-last=Engel |editor2-first=Pál |editor3-last=Makk |editor3-first=Ferenc | title=Korai magyar történeti lexikon (9–14. század) ''[Encyclopedia of the Early Hungarian History (9th–14th centuries)]'' |publisher=Akadémiai Kiadó |year=1994 |page=293 |chapter=III. István |isbn=963-05-6722-9|ref=harv|language=hu}}
*{{Cite book |last=Stephenson |first=Paul |year=2000 |title=Byzantium's Balkan Frontier: A Political Study of the Northern Balkans, 900–1204 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn= 978-0-521-02756-4|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book |last=Treadgold |first=Warren |year=1997 |title=A History of the Byzantine State and Society |publisher=Stanford University Press |isbn= 0-8047-2630-2|ref=harv}}
{{Refend}}

{{commons category|Stephen III of Hungary}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[House of Árpád]]||1147|4 March|1172}}
{{s-reg}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Géza II of Hungary|Géza II]] }}
{{s-ttl |title=[[King of Hungary]] and [[King of Croatia|Croatia]] |years=1162–1172 }}
{{s-aft|after=[[Béla III of Hungary|Béla III]] }}
{{s-end}}
{{Hungarian kings}}
{{Croatian kings}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stephen 03 Of Hungary}}
[[Category:12th-century Hungarian people]]
[[Category:Kings of Hungary]]
[[Category:Kings of Croatia]]
[[Category:House of Árpád]]
[[Category:Hungarian people of Ukrainian descent]]
[[Category:Hungarian people of Russian descent]]
[[Category:Hungarian exiles]]
[[Category:1147 births]]
[[Category:1172 deaths]]</text>
      <sha1>092r8hlm37yo78e0gb72jazt99wc49y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
