<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Strez</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29531173</id>
    <revision>
      <id>725531791</id>
      <parentid>719061601</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-16T07:15:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gligan1</username>
        <id>14345259</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>m</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17362">{{Good article}}
{{Infobox nobility|type
| name                 = Strez
| title                = ''[[sebastokrator]]''
| more                 = no 
| noble family         = [[Asen dynasty]]
| birth_date           = 12th century
| death_date           = 1214
| death_place          = [[Polog|Polog Valley]]
}}

'''Strez''' ({{lang-bg|Стрез}}; original spelling: &lt;small&gt;СТРѢЗЪ&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rendered as Στρέαζος, ''Streazos'' in [[Medieval Greek|Byzantine Greek]] and as ''Straces'' or ''Stratius'' in [[Latins#Middle Ages|Latin]] sources. Златарски, p. 270&lt;/ref&gt;) ([[floruit|fl.]] 1207–1214) was a [[Bulgarians|Bulgarian]] ''[[sebastokrator]]'' and a member of the [[Asen dynasty]]. A major contender for the [[Second Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarian]] throne, Strez initially opposed the ascension of his close relative [[List of Bulgarian monarchs|Tsar]] [[Boril of Bulgaria|Boril]]. He fled to [[Serbian Grand Principality|Serbia]], where he accepted the [[vassal]]age of [[List of Serbian monarchs|Grand Prince]] [[Stefan Nemanjić]], and Serbian support helped him establish himself as a largely independent ruler in a large part of the region of [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]]. However, Strez turned against his [[Suzerainty|suzerains]] to become a Bulgarian vassal and joined forces with his former enemy Boril against the [[Latin Empire|Latins]] and then the Serbs. Strez was murdered amidst a major anti-Serbian campaign under unclear circumstances in a plot that likely involved [[Saint Sava]].

==Throne contender and Serbian vassal==
[[File:Asen dynasty.png|thumb|right|250px|Genealogical chart of the Asen dynasty, including Strez and Boril.]]
Nothing is mentioned of Strez until the events in the wake of the sudden death of Tsar [[Kaloyan of Bulgaria|Kaloyan]] (1197–1207) during his siege of the [[Kingdom of Thessalonica|Crusader-held]] [[Thessaloniki]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bozhilov98&quot;&gt;Божилов, p. 98&lt;/ref&gt; Just like [[Alexius Slav]], another noble who would later emerge as a separatist, Strez was a nephew of the Asen brothers [[Peter IV of Bulgaria|Peter]], [[Ivan Asen I of Bulgaria|Ivan Asen]] and Kaloyan, who were the first three emperors of the Second Bulgarian Empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov(2003)&quot;&gt;Бакалов (2003)&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is unclear whether through his relation to the early Asens he was a first cousin or a brother of Boril (1207–1218).&lt;ref&gt;Fine, p. 94&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pavlov&quot;&gt;Павлов&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-353&quot;&gt;Андреев (1999), p. 353&lt;/ref&gt;

At the time of Kaloyan's death, Strez was in the capital [[Veliko Tarnovo|Tarnovo]], perhaps seeking to capitalize on his ancestral rights to the Bulgarian crown. However, Boril proved to be the more ambitious candidate. Boril persecuted the other candidates for the throne, and Alexius Slav, along with Ivan Asen's sons [[Ivan Asen II of Bulgaria|Ivan Asen II]] had to leave Bulgaria.&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-354&quot;&gt;Андреев (1999), p. 354&lt;/ref&gt;

As happened to other members of the royal family, Boril's ascension forced Strez and his closest supporters to flee, in that case to neighbouring Serbia, where he was welcomed by the reigning Stefan Nemanjić (1196–1228) in 1207 or early 1208.&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov(2003)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;curta385&quot;&gt;Curta, p. 385&lt;/ref&gt; Even though Boril requested the extradition of Strez to Bulgaria,&lt;ref&gt;Андреев (2004), p. 179&lt;/ref&gt; the Serbian ruler hoped to use Strez as a puppet in gaining Bulgarian-held territory. Stefan believed that Strez's royal ancestry and imperial aspirations would make it much easier to impose Serbian rule over Macedonia, [[Kosovo]] and [[Braničevo (region)|Braničevo]], as well as [[Belgrade]], all captured by Bulgaria under Kaloyan.&lt;ref&gt;Fine, pp. 94–95&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Boril was unable to take military action against Strez and his Serbian patron, as he had suffered a major defeat at the hands of the Latins [[Battle of Philippopolis (1208)|at Plovdiv]].&lt;ref name=&quot;curta385&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;velimirovic61&quot;&gt;Velimirović, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev2-180&quot;&gt;Андреев (2004), p. 180&lt;/ref&gt; Stefan went as far as to become a [[blood brother]] of Strez in a ceremony which Stefan was hoping would secure Strez's loyalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;bozhilov98&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-354&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Demirkapiska klisura vo 1863 03.jpg|thumb|left|255px|alt=A 19th-century monochrome photograph of a rocky river canyon, with sharp high cliffs in the background.|The gorge of the [[Vardar]] at modern [[Demir Kapija]] was the site of Strez's capital, [[Prosek]], from 1208 to 1214]]

In 1208, Strez headed a Serbian force which seized much of the [[Vardar]] valley from Bulgaria. He established himself as a Serbian vassal at the [[Prosek]] fortress (near modern [[Demir Kapija]]), formerly the capital of another Bulgarian separatist, [[Dobromir Chrysos]]. By 1209, Strez's realm spread over much of Macedonia,&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov(2003)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pavlov&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;curta385&quot;/&gt; from the [[Struma River|Struma]] valley in the east, where he bordered the lands controlled by Boril, to [[Bitola]] and perhaps [[Ohrid]] in the west, and from [[Skopje]] in the north to [[Veria]] in the south. While Strez quickly gained the support of the local Bulgarian population and possibly inherited the remaining administration from Boril's rule, Serbian units nevertheless remained in his domains, either to guarantee his loyalty or with the intent to oust him and annex his lands.&lt;ref&gt;Fine, pp. 95–96&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bulgarian vassal==
Alexius Slav's marriage to the daughter of [[List of Latin Emperors|Latin Emperor]] [[Henry of Flanders]] in 1209 was potentially a great danger to Boril, who could be facing their joint forces. Fearing such a coalition, Boril approached Strez, who was at the time gaining more power and was close to complete independence from Serbia.&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev2-180&quot;/&gt; Strez agreed to a union with his former enemy, though only after Boril reconfirmed his complete autonomy.&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev2-181&quot;&gt;Андреев (2004), p. 181&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bozhilov99&quot;&gt;Божилов, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; Strez eliminated the remaining Serbian troops in his lands in an act that the Serbs saw as devil-inspired treason. It is not impossible that Boril persuaded Strez through military action, though it is more likely that the union was achieved through negotiations.&lt;ref&gt;Fine, pp. 97–98&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same year, Strez and Boril had come to peace with [[Michael I Komnenos Doukas]], the ruler of [[Despotate of Epirus|Epirus]]. In late 1209, Strez and Michael may have attempted a joint campaign against Thessaloniki,&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-355&quot;&gt;Андреев (1999), p. 355&lt;/ref&gt; as they both lost lands to the Latins in what was likely a retaliation raid in late 1209 or early 1210. The failure of this attack prompted Michael to break away from his Bulgarian allies and support the Latins. In early 1211, Strez clashed with the Latins and Epirotes at Thessaloniki and required Boril's assistance after Michael and Henry invaded the western reaches of Strez's realm. In the early summer, the allied Bulgarian army suffered a heavy defeat at Bitola&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov(2003)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bozhilov99&quot;/&gt; at the hands of Michael, Henry's brother Eustace and Bernard of Katzenellenbogen.&lt;ref&gt;Housley, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; Even though it resulted in no territorial losses,&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-355&quot;/&gt; it prevented Strez from an expansion to the south. In relation to an anti-[[Bogomilism|Bogomil]] council in 1211, Strez is referred to as a ''sebastokrator''. The title was either conferred to him by Boril as part of their agreement in 1209, or was awarded to Strez by Kaloyan during his rule. In any case, Boril certainly recognized Strez's right to that appellation. There are signs that Strez divided his possessions into administrative units, each headed by a ''[[sebastos]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Fine, p. 98&lt;/ref&gt; In 1212, Strez was powerful enough to be considered one of the Latin Empire's chief adversaries, along with Boril, Michael and [[Empire of Nicaea|Nicaean]] emperor [[Theodore I Laskaris]], by Henry himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;bozhilov99&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-355&quot;/&gt;

==Anti-Serbian campaign and death==
After a series of military failures against the Latins, Boril made peace with Henry in 1213, cemented through two royal marriages.&lt;ref&gt;Fine, pp. 100–101&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Андреев (2004), p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; As Boril's vassal, Strez joined the Bulgarian–Latin union, the short-term goal of which was a double invasion of Serbia.&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov154&quot;&gt;Бакалов (2007), p. 154&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fine, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; In 1214, the forces of Boril and Henry attacked Serbia from the east, while Strez's army, deemed in contemporary sources to be &quot;countless&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-355&quot;/&gt; penetrated Serbian territory from the south and reached the [[Polog]]. Facing a major invasion on two fronts, the Serbs were quick to ask for peace. After Stefan's envoys to Strez failed, he sent his brother, [[archbishop]] Sava ([[canonization|canonized]] as [[Saint Sava]]) to Strez's camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev2-183&quot;&gt;Андреев (2004), p. 183&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fine, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;

Even though Sava's diplomacy was of no effect either,&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov(2003)&quot;/&gt; Strez died the night after Sava's departure. Serbian sources present the death of Strez as a miracle, Strez being stabbed by an [[angel]],&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-356&quot;&gt;Андреев (1999), p. 356&lt;/ref&gt; though in reality he was very likely murdered in a plot orchestrated by Sava.&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev2-183&quot;/&gt; Historian John V. A. Fine theorizes that Sava may have found supporters among Strez's nobles, some of whom had turned against him and organized his murder, only to defect to Serbia immediately afterwards. According to the [[hagiography]] of Saint Sava, in his dying words Strez claimed he was stabbed by a young soldier on the order of Sava.&lt;ref&gt;Fine, pp. 103–104&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;velimirovic62&quot;&gt;Velimirović, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;

While Strez's murder meant an end to the Latin–Bulgarian campaign, Stefan did not undertake a campaign into Macedonia due to the proximity of the coalition troops, which had halted at [[Niš]]. In 1217, all of Strez's territory was under the Epirote rule of [[Theodore Komnenos Doukas]],&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov(2003)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bakalov154&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev2-183&quot;/&gt; though Boril may have controlled some or all of it in the meantime.&lt;ref&gt;Fine, p. 104&lt;/ref&gt; The Serbs failed to take advantage of Strez's death as far as they did not manage to acquire any of his former domains.&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-356&quot;/&gt;

==Assessment and legacy==
Contemporary Serbian sources, such as the hagiography of Saint Sava, are highly critical of Strez's actions. The Serbs accused Strez of recklessness, drunkenness, ungodliness, treason and cruelty. The hagiography of Saint Sava tells of Strez's alleged tendency to have captives thrown from a high cliff into the Vardar River for his and his guests' entertainment. As the prisoners were falling to their death, Strez would sarcastically shout at them not to get their coats wet.&lt;ref name=&quot;velimirovic60-62&quot;&gt;Velimirović, pp. 60–62&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-355-356&quot;&gt;Андреев (1999), pp. 355–356&lt;/ref&gt; Bulgarian historian Ivan Lazarov dismisses these allegations as slanderous. In his biography of Strez, he hails the medieval ruler as a &quot;true member of the Asen dynasty&quot; and defends his actions due to him being a &quot;child of his time&quot;. Lazarov assesses Strez as a characteristic, vivid personality who put his independence above all.&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-356&quot;/&gt;

The name of Strez has become a part of Bulgarian folklore,&lt;ref name=&quot;andreev1-356&quot;/&gt; including a legendary account of his life written down as the ''Biography of Prince Stregan'' in the 18th century or later.&lt;ref name=&quot;bozhilov99&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mutafchiev110&quot;&gt;Мутафчиев, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; At least one location throughout Macedonia was tied by the locals with Strez, whom the folk interpreted as a [[voivode]] or [[hajduk]] who defended the people against the [[Ottoman Turks|Ottomans]]. Some ruins by the Vardar River near [[Jegunovce]] west of Skopje were known to the locals as &quot;Strez's Fortress&quot; (Стрезово кале, ''Strezovo kale'').&lt;ref name=&quot;mutafchiev276&quot;&gt;Мутафчиев, p. 276&lt;/ref&gt; Even though in reality his capital, Prosek, lay far to the south, the castle at Jegunovce may have formed part of Strez's border fortifications, or it may have been the site of his negotiations with Sava and his murder.&lt;ref name=&quot;mutafchiev280&quot;&gt;Мутафчиев, p. 280&lt;/ref&gt;

==References and notes==
{{reflist|3}}

==Sources==
* {{cite book|last=Curta|first=Florin|authorlink=Florin Curta|title=Southeastern Europe in the Middle Ages, 500–1250|year=2006|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-81539-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Fine|first=John Van Antwerp|title=The Late Medieval Balkans: A Critical Survey from the Late Twelfth Century to the Ottoman Conquest|publisher=University of Michigan Press|year=1994|pages=175–184|isbn=978-0-472-08260-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Housley|first=Norman|title=Knighthoods of Christ: essays on the history of the Crusades and the Knights Templar, presented to Malcolm Barber|year=2007|publisher=Ashgate Publishing|isbn=978-0-7546-5527-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Velimirović|first=Nikolaj|title=The life of St. Sava|year=1989|publisher=St Vladimir's Seminary Press|isbn=978-0-88141-065-5}}
* {{cite book|last1=Андреев|first1=Йордан|last2=Лазаров|first2=Иван|last3=Павлов|first3=Пламен|title=Кой кой е в средновековна България|trans_title=Who is Who in Medieval Bulgaria|year=1999|publisher=Петър Берон|language=Bulgarian|isbn=978-954-402-047-7}}
* {{cite book|last1=Андреев|first1=Йордан|last2=Пантев|first2=Андрей|title=Българските ханове и царе|trans_title=Bulgarian Khans and Tsars|year=2004|publisher=Абагар|location=Велико Търново|language=Bulgarian|isbn=978-954-427-216-6}}
* {{cite book |title=Електронно издание &quot;История на България&quot; |trans_title=Electronic edition &quot;History of Bulgaria&quot; |language=Bulgarian |last1=Бакалов |first1=Георги |last2=Куманов|first2=Милен|publisher=Труд, Сирма |location=София |year=2003 |isbn=954528613X |chapter=СТРЕЗ (неизв.-ок. 1214) |trans_chapter=STREZ (unknown&amp;nbsp;— c. 1214)|type=CD}}
* {{cite book|last=Бакалов|first=Георги|title=История на българите: Военна история на българите от древността до наши дни|trans_title=History of the Bulgarians: Military History of the Bulgarians from Antiquity to Modern Times|year=2007|publisher=Труд|location=София|language=Bulgarian|isbn=978-954-621-235-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Божилов|first=Иван|year=1994|title=Фамилията на Асеневци (1186–1460). Генеалогия и просопография|location=София|publisher=Издателство на Българската академия на науките|trans_title=The Family of the Asens (1186–1460). Genealogy and prosopography|language=Bulgarian|isbn=954-430-264-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Златарски|first=Васил|authorlink=Vasil Zlatarski|editor=Димитър Ангелов|title=История на българската държава през средните векове. Второ българско царство. България при Асеневци (1187–1280)|trans_title=History of the Bulgarian State in the Middle Ages. Second Bulgarian Empire. Bulgaria Under the Asens (1187–1280)|edition=2nd|volume=Том III|year=1972|origyear=1940|publisher=Наука и изкуство|location=София|language=Bulgarian|oclc=611774943}}
* {{cite book|last1=Мутафчиев|first1=Петър|title=Изток и Запад в европейското Средновековие. Избрано|trans_title=East and West in the European Middle Ages. Selected Works|year=1993|publisher=Христо Ботев|location=София|language=Bulgarian|chapter=Владетелите на Просек. Страници из историята на българите в края на XII и началото на XIII век|trans_chapter=The rulers of Prosek. Pages from the history of the Bulgarians in the late 12th and early 13th century|origyear=1911|isbn=978-954-445-079-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Павлов|first=Пламен|title=Бунтари и авантюристи в средновековна България|trans_title=Rebels and Venturers in Medieval Bulgaria|publisher=LiterNet|location=Варна|year=2005|chapter=Съперничества и кървави борби за престола на Асеневци|trans_chapter=Rivalries and bloody struggles for the throne of the Asens|chapterurl=http://liternet.bg/publish13/p_pavlov/buntari/sypernichestva.htm|language=Bulgarian|isbn=954-304-152-0|accessdate=11 November 2010}}

[[Category:12th-century births]]
[[Category:1214 deaths]]
[[Category:13th-century Bulgarian people]]
[[Category:Asen dynasty]]
[[Category:Medieval Bulgarian nobility]]
[[Category:Rulers in medieval Macedonia]]
[[Category:Bulgarian murder victims]]
[[Category:Medieval Bulgarian military personnel]]
[[Category:Sebastokrators]]</text>
      <sha1>pm7h7dmjhygyfv6wos0jb020ct6vkv9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
