<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tantallon Castle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3416349</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723923133</id>
      <parentid>710769147</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-06T02:34:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dcirovic</username>
        <id>11795905</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */refs using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30595">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2014}}
{{Infobox military structure
|name=Tantallon Castle
|location=Near [[North Berwick]], [[East Lothian]], [[Scotland]]&lt;br&gt;[[OSGB]] {{gbmapping|NT596851}}
|coordinates=
|image= Tantallon Castle, 2015.JPG
|caption=Approach to Tantallon from the south
|map_type = Scotland East Lothian
|latitude = 56.0564  
|longitude = -2.6506
|map_caption = Location of Tantallon within East Lothian
|type=Castle of ''[[enceinte]]''
|built=c.1350
|builder=[[William Douglas, 1st Earl of Douglas]]
|controlledby=[[Earl of Angus]]
|materials=Stone
|height=
|used=Until 1650
|condition=Ruined
|ownership=[[Historic Scotland]]
|open_to_public= Yes
}}

'''Tantallon Castle''' is a semi-ruined mid-14th-century fortress, located {{convert|5|km}} east of [[North Berwick]], in [[East Lothian]], [[Scotland]]. It sits atop a promontory opposite the [[Bass Rock]], looking out onto the [[Firth of Forth]]. The last medieval curtain wall castle to be constructed in Scotland,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindsay&quot;&gt;Lindsay, ''The Castles of Scotland'', p.440–442&lt;/ref&gt; Tantallon comprises a single wall blocking off the headland, with the other three sides naturally protected by sea cliffs.

Tantallon was built in the mid 14th century by [[William Douglas, 1st Earl of Douglas]]. It was passed to his illegitimate son,  [[George Douglas, 1st Earl of Angus|George Douglas]], later created [[Earl of Angus]], and despite several sieges, it remained the property of his descendants for much of its history. It was besieged by King [[James IV of Scotland|James IV]] in 1491, and again by his successor [[James V of Scotland|James V]] in 1528, when extensive damage was done. Tantallon saw action in the [[First Bishops' War]] in 1639, and again during [[Oliver Cromwell]]'s [[Scotland in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms#Third Civil War|invasion of Scotland]] in 1651, when it was once more severely damaged. It was sold by the Marquis of Douglas in 1699 to [[Hew Dalrymple, Lord North Berwick]] and the ruin is today in the care of [[Historic Scotland]].

==Construction== 
[[File:Tantallon Plan.png|thumb|left|Plan of the inner court of Tantallon Castle]]
Tantallon is of a singular construction within Scotland, the defences comprising only a single large wall securing a coastal promontory. The south-east, north-east, and north-west approaches are naturally defended by steep sea cliffs, and were only ever protected by relatively small defensive walls. To the south-west, a massive [[curtain wall (fortification)|curtain wall]] blocks off the end of the promontory, which forms the inner courtyard. The curtain wall is built of the local [[Old Red Sandstone|red sandstone]], and has a tower at either end and a heavily fortified gatehouse in the centre, all of which provided residential accommodation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tabraham&quot;&gt;Tabraham, ''Scotland's Castles'', pp.65–69&lt;/ref&gt; A north range of buildings, containing a hall, completed the main part of the castle, enclosing a courtyard around {{convert|70|by|44|m}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;&gt;Salter, ''The Castles of Lothian and the Borders'', pp.86–88&lt;/ref&gt; In total, the buildings of the castle provided around {{convert|1100|m2}} of accommodation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tabraham&quot;/&gt;

In its form, Tantallon follows on from the 12th-century castles of [[Bothwell Castle|Bothwell]] and [[Kildrummy Castle|Kildrummy]], as a castle of ''[[enceinte]]'', or curtain wall castle. It was the last of this type to be built in Scotland, as the smaller [[tower house]] was becoming increasingly popular.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tabraham&quot;/&gt; For example, [[Threave Castle]], built at around the same time by Earl William's cousin [[Archibald the Grim]], is a much more modest tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindsay&quot;/&gt; There are also similarities between Tantallon and &quot;courtyard&quot; castles, such as [[Doune Castle|Doune]], which also dates from the late 14th century, and is entered via a passage beneath a strong [[keep]] tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;MR&quot;&gt;MacGibbon and Ross, ''The Castellated and Domestic Architecture of Scotland'', vol.I, pp.429–435&lt;/ref&gt;

===Curtain wall===
[[File:The curtain wall of Tantallon Castle, East Lothian, Scotland, 1972.jpg|thumb|Curtain wall, with the gatehouse in the centre]]
The curtain wall is over {{convert|15|m}} high, {{convert|3.6|m}} thick, and around {{convert|90|m}} long.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindsay&quot;/&gt; There are several small chambers within the walls, and stairs with arched ceilings accessing the parapet walk.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;&gt;McWilliam, ''Lothian, except Edinburgh'', pp.444–6&lt;/ref&gt; This parapet walk, beneath the 16th-century [[crenel]]s of the curtain wall, connects the three towers.

The northwest tower, known as the Douglas Tower, was circular in plan and {{convert|12|m}} across, although the west side has collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; Seven storeys high, this tower would have formed the lord's &quot;donjon&quot;, or [[keep]], containing his private accommodation, and connecting to the hall in the north range.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tabraham&quot;/&gt; The lowest storey was a [[Dungeon|pit prison]] and the timber-floored chambers above were square, with [[vault (architecture)|vault]]ed [[garderobe]]s or privies.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;/&gt;

The East Tower is of D-plan, with the curved face outwards, and is {{convert|9|m}} across. Originally consisting of five storeys, the bottom three were reduced to two after the 1528 siege, by the insertion of stone vaults. Large gun ports were also added in the basement at this time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; The third floor of the tower was designed to have access to a parapet on the south-east wall, although this wall was never built.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Inside of Tantallon ruins.jpg|thumb|left|Inner court, void above entrance]]

The central gatehouse tower is square, {{convert|13|m}} across, and up to {{convert|24|m}} high. It contained four storeys of chambers, some with canopied fireplaces, although the internal walls and floors are now missing.&lt;ref name=LBR&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hsewsf.sedsh.gov.uk/hslive/hsstart?P_HBNUM=14722 |title=Tantallon Castle, Listed Building Report |publisher=[[Historic Scotland]] |accessdate=2008-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main entrance ran through a passage below, protected by a drawbridge, three pairs of doors, a [[portcullis]], and [[machicolation]]s; holes in the ceiling enabling the defenders to drop missiles on to intruders below. There are two [[bartizan]]s, or corner turrets, facing in toward the courtyard, where a 16th-century spiral stair gives access to the head of the curtain wall.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;/&gt; The entrance was originally via a pointed arched gateway, flanked by round towers. A defensive [[barbican]], or outer gate, was added in the early 14th century, and was destroyed in the 1528 siege, although fragments can still be seen.&lt;ref name=LBR/&gt; After the siege, the facade of the gatehouse was rebuilt, with more gun ports at ground level, and the gateway corridor was narrowed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; The rebuilding covered up the remains of the earlier round towers, narrowed the main gate, and gave the tower rounded corners for additional strength.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;/&gt;

===Inner court===
[[File:Tantallon Castle wall and Bass Rock.jpg|thumb|upright|Ruins of the Douglas Tower, with the Bass Rock behind]]
The north range of buildings, around {{convert|10|by|40|m}}, is connected to the Douglas Tower. The western section dates from the 14th century, and comprises the remains of the great hall, used by the lord, over the former laigh, or low, hall, used by the labourers, and later divided to form cellars. The marks of the hall's pitched roof can be seen on the inside wall of the Douglas Tower. The 16th-century eastern section contained a bakehouse and further private chambers, and has partially collapsed into the sea. Only a small section of the other walls remains to the east, and contains a [[postern]] gate, giving access to the sea through a cleft in the cliffs below.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; The well is {{convert|32|m}} deep, and was re-excavated in the 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Tantallon Castle 3.jpg|thumb|left|North range, seen from the gatehouse]]

===Outer court===
Alongside the curtain wall is a deep, rock-cut ditch, with a larger second ditch around {{convert|100|m}} away, defining the  [[outer ward|outer court]] of the castle. Within the outer ditch are two mounds, which [[Charles McKean]] suggests may conceal 16th-century [[caponier]]s, defensive positions allowing covering fire along the trench. McKean notes that Sir [[James Hamilton of Finnart]], the [[Master of Work to the Crown of Scotland|King's Master of Works]], and a noted [[military engineer]] who built Scotland's only known caponiers at [[Craignethan Castle|Craignethan]] and [[Blackness Castle|Blackness]], was present with the King during the 1528 siege, and worked at Tantallon afterwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKean&quot;&gt;McKean, ''The Scottish Chateau'', pp.49–50&lt;/ref&gt; A stone-fronted mound formerly ran along the outside of the ditch, although only a {{convert|30|m|adj=on}} section of the outer wall survives, at the south end, terminating in a two-storey round tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;MR&quot;/&gt; This tower, with several gun ports, was built prior to the siege of 1528, and may have been inspired by the new artillery defences at nearby [[Dunbar Castle]].&lt;ref&gt;Tabraham, ''Scotland's Castles'', p.102&lt;/ref&gt; A 17th-century &quot;lectern&quot; type [[doocot]], or pigeon house, is the only building within the outer court. Beyond the outer ditch is a 17th-century [[ravelin]], a triangular earthen artillery defence, and the remains of a third, smaller, ditch.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;/&gt;

==History==
[[File:Tantallon Castle, courtyard with well and southern wing.jpg|thumb|upright|Inner face of the curtain wall from the north range]]

A map of the area, dated to before 1300, shows a castellated site with the name of &quot;Dentaloune&quot;,&lt;ref name=Rich12&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.12&lt;/ref&gt; possibly a corruption of the [[British language (Celtic)|Brythonic]] ''din talgwn'' or &quot;high-fronted fortress&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston, ''Place Names of Scotland'', p.307&lt;/ref&gt; The barony of North Berwick, including Tantallon, was in the possession of the [[Earl of Fife|Earls of Fife]] at this time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt;

===Early history===
In 1346, [[William Douglas, 1st Earl of Douglas|William Douglas]] (c. 1327–1384), nephew of Robert the Bruce's companion Sir [[James Douglas, Lord of Douglas|James Douglas]], had returned to Scotland, from France, to claim his inheritance as chief of the name of [[Clan Douglas|Douglas]]. By murdering his godfather, Sir [[William Douglas, The Knight of Liddesdale|William Douglas of Liddesdale]], William became the undisputed head of the House of Douglas. He was created [[Earl of Douglas]] in 1358.

It is not clear how Douglas came to possess Tantallon,&lt;ref name=Rich12/&gt; but in correspondence of 1374, he refers to &quot;our castle of Temptaloun&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fawcett, ''Scottish Architecture'', p.16&lt;/ref&gt; Douglas may have been made [[castellan]] of Tantallon, as a tenant of [[Isabella, Countess of Fife]],&lt;ref name=Rich12/&gt; and it appears that he built the present castle either shortly before, or shortly after, his elevation to the peerage, to reflect his new-found status.&lt;ref&gt;Tabraham, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.16&lt;/ref&gt; It was intended as a status symbol, although it followed the medieval curtain wall type, which at the time was becoming outmoded and superseded by the [[tower house]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; The Douglases continued to hold the lands of Tantallon as tenants of [[Robert Stewart, Duke of Albany|Robert Stewart, Earl of Fife]] (c.1340-1420), from 1371 until 1372, when he resigned the title in favour of his son [[Murdoch Stewart, Duke of Albany|Murdoch]]. Tantallon was the home of William Douglas' sister-in-law and mistress, [[Margaret Stewart, 4th Countess of Angus|Margaret Stewart, Countess of Angus]], the mother of his illegitimate son [[George Douglas, 1st Earl of Angus|George Douglas]] (1380–1403).&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; In 1377, the Earl made his close friend, Alan de Lawedre of The Bass, [[Constable]] of Tantallon Castle, an office he held until at least 1389.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, ''The Douglas Book'', vol.III, p.398&lt;/ref&gt; In 1388, when the [[James Douglas, 2nd Earl of Douglas|2nd Earl of Douglas]] died, the Earl of Fife claimed the lands of Tantallon, and confirmed the Countess' right to live there.&lt;ref&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', pp.12–13&lt;/ref&gt; Several attempts were made to dislodge the Countess, but the agreement was formalised by parliament in April 1389, and George Douglas was recognised as Earl of Angus, as his mother's heir.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, ''The Black Douglases'', pp.83,86&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Seacliffview.jpg|thumb|left|View from [[Seacliff]] Harbour, showing the fortifications blocking the promontory]]

===The Red Douglases===
The Barony of North Berwick, surrounding Tantallon, stayed with the Earldom of Fife, but despite the Earl's claim, the castle passed outright into the Douglas family, and was inherited by George Douglas, illegitimate son of the Earl of Douglas, who also inherited his mother's [[Earl of Angus|Earldom of Angus]] in 1389. This was the start of the division in the House of Douglas. [[Archibald the Grim]] became head of the main line, known as the &quot;Black Douglases&quot;. George Douglas was the progenitor of the &quot;Red Douglases&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Maxwell, ''A History of the House of Douglas'', vol.II, pp.3–5&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1397, George Douglas married Mary, daughter of King [[Robert III of Scotland|Robert III]], allying the Red Douglases with the Royal [[House of Stewart]]. From 1425 to 1433, [[Isabella, Countess of Lennox]], the widow of the executed [[Murdoch Stewart, Duke of Albany|Duke of Albany]], was warded at Tantallon. In 1429 another royal enemy, [[Alexander of Islay, Earl of Ross|Alexander, Lord of the Isles]], was held at Tantallon until his reconciliation with King [[james I of Scotland|James I]] two years later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; The [[James Douglas, 3rd Earl of Angus|3rd Earl of Angus]] (1426–1446) made Tantallon his main residence, and was in rebellion from 1443 until his death. He raided the Black Douglas lands of [[Abercorn]], leading to retaliation, and his [[Asset forfeiture|forfeit]]ure in 1446, a few months before his death.&lt;ref name=Rich13&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.13&lt;/ref&gt; In 1452, King [[James II of Scotland|James II]] granted Tantallon to the [[George Douglas, 4th Earl of Angus|4th Earl]], brother of the 3rd Earl, who led the Royal force which defeated the Black Douglases at the [[Battle of Arkinholm]], in May 1455.&lt;ref name=Rich14&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.14&lt;/ref&gt;

The Red Douglases, in the person of [[Archibald Douglas, 5th Earl of Angus|Archibald &quot;Bell-the-Cat&quot;]] (1453–1514), the 5th Earl, turned against the Royal house in 1482. Around 1490, Angus struck a treasonable deal with [[Henry VII of England]], against [[James IV of Scotland]]. On 11 October 1491, Tantallon Castle was besieged by James IV, with guns sent from Edinburgh and [[Linlithgow]], and crossbows and [[culverin]]s (a primitive type of hand gun) from [[Leith]].&lt;ref name=Rich14/&gt; However, Angus submitted and the castle did not suffer extensive damage. By 1493 Angus was back in favour as [[Chancellor of Scotland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Portrait of James V of Scotland (1512 - 1542).jpg|thumb|upright|James V of Scotland, who successfully besieged Tantallon in 1528]]

===The Siege of 1528===
In 1514, [[Archibald Douglas, 6th Earl of Angus]] (1490–1557) married James IV's widow [[Margaret Tudor]], daughter of Henry VII, and Regent of Scotland for her infant son [[James V of Scotland|James V]]. The couple unsuccessfully conspired to take the young King to England, sparking off civil war. The Regency was handed to [[John Stewart, Duke of Albany]], who seized Tantallon in 1515, although it was returned the following year when Angus made his peace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt;

In 1525, Angus, with support from [[Henry VIII of England]], staged a virtual ''[[coup d'état]]'', taking custody of the young King, and becoming Chancellor. But, in 1528, the sixteen-year-old James V escaped, and, joining his mother at [[Stirling Castle|Stirling]], pronounced Angus [[attainted]], banishing him to &quot;north of the [[River Spey|Spey]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=Rich16&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.16&lt;/ref&gt; Angus instead retreated to Tantallon, and then to England. The castle was seized by the King, but Angus managed to return and refortify his stronghold.&lt;ref name=Rich16/&gt; On 23 October 1528, King James laid siege to Tantallon which was defended by Angus's servant Simon Penango.&lt;ref name=Rich17&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.17&lt;/ref&gt; Angus himself remained at Billie in the [[Merse (Scotland)|Merse]].&lt;ref&gt;Reid, David ed., ''Hume of Godscroft's History of the House of Angus'', vol. 1, STS (2005), 97-8.&lt;/ref&gt; James V borrowed the guns from [[Dunbar Castle]] which was held by the French garrison of the [[John Stewart, Duke of Albany|Duke Albany]]. According to [[Robert Lindsay of Pitscottie|Pitscottie]], the guns supplied by Captain Maurice of Dunbar were Thrawinmouth, Mow and her marrow (partner), two great botcards, two moyanes, two [[Falconet (cannon)|double falcons]], four quarter falcons, with powder, gunners and bullets. James left three hostages with Maurice in pledge for the guns.&lt;ref&gt;Lindsay of Pitscottie, Robert, ''The History of Scotland'', Edinburgh (1778),222-223, Thrawinmouth was used at [[St Andrews Castle]] in 1547.&lt;/ref&gt; The castle was bombarded with this cannon for 20 days, although the King's guns could not be brought close enough to the walls to do substantive damage, due to the deep outer ditch.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKean&quot;/&gt; The King lifted the siege and returned to Edinburgh, at which point Angus counterattacked and captured the King's artillery and his principal gunner David Falconer was killed.&lt;ref name=Rich17/&gt; In May 1529, Angus fled to England, leaving the castle to James. Simon Penango, having received no further supplies or reinforcements from Angus made terms and surrendered the castle. Tantallon was retained as a Royal fortress until James V's death in 1542, when Angus returned and recovered it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt;

To repair damage sustained during the siege, the King set about rebuilding and strengthening the castle. First, [[Thomas Erskine of Haltoun|Sir Thomas Erskine of Brechin]], the king's secretary, was made the keeper and organised strengthening and repair works. Then the castle was given to the king's eldest illegitimate son James.&lt;ref&gt;''The Spalding Club Miscellany'', vol. 2, Aberdeen (1842), 188-9, James V to Erskine, 23 February 1535.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, [[Oliver Sinclair]] was installed as captain,&lt;ref name=&quot;MR&quot;/&gt; and the surviving accounts for the period 1537–1539 record that George Sempill was the master mason, carrying out the repairs under the direction of [[John Scrimgeour of Myres|John Scrimgeour]], the [[Master of Work to the Crown of Scotland|King's Master of Works]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McWilliam&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.19&lt;/ref&gt; The front of the gatehouse was rebuilt, and the East Tower strengthened. Wide-mouthed gun holes were punched through the landward walls of the tower, and a [[Battlement|crenellated]] parapet was added to the curtain wall.&lt;ref&gt;The Listed Building Report for Tantallon dates the repair works to 1556.&lt;/ref&gt; To strengthen the great landward curtain wall several chambers and passages within were filled with masonry, and can be seen today. Pitscottie described this operation: &quot;the king caused masons come and ranforce the wallis, quhilkis war left waste before as transis (passages), and through-passages; and maid all massie work, to mak it the more strang.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lindsay Pitscottie, Robert, ''Chronicles of Scotland'', vol. 2 Edinburgh (1814), 340.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later 16th century===
[[File:View of Tantallon Castle and the Bass Rock by Alexander Nasmyth, NGS.JPG|thumb|View of Tantallon Castle and the Bass Rock by [[Alexander Nasmyth]]]]
On Angus' return in 1542, he was still in contact with Henry VIII, and allowed [[Ralph Sadler|Sir Ralph Sadler]], English ambassador to Scotland, to reside at Tantallon during the attempts to negotiate a marriage between the infant [[Mary, Queen of Scots]], and [[Edward VI of England|Edward, Prince of Wales]] in 1542–43.&lt;ref&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', pp.20–21&lt;/ref&gt; It has been claimed that when the [[Edward Seymour, 1st Duke of Somerset|Earl of Hertford]] invaded Scotland in 1544, during the ensuing [[The Rough Wooing|War of the Rough Wooing]],  Tantallon was bypassed by the English army, due to the Earl's English sympathies,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackay&quot;&gt;Mackay, ''Investigating Tantallon Castle'', p.2&lt;/ref&gt; though the castle of Oliver Sinclair is listed amongst places burnt by the returning English army in contemporary sources,&lt;ref&gt;Grafton, Richard, ''A Chronicle at Large, 1569,'' vol. 2, London (1809), 491.&lt;/ref&gt; but it was left unmolested in 1547.&lt;ref&gt;Patten, William, ''The Expedition into Scotland, 1547''.&lt;/ref&gt; Angus was finally imprisoned at [[Blackness Castle]] in 1544, after which he changed sides to support the Scottish cause. The gunners of Tantallon were rewarded in August 1548, after firing on English ships during an engagement in the Firth of Forth.&lt;ref&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', pp.22–23&lt;/ref&gt;

Angus died at Tantallon in January 1557, and the castle was seized by the Queen Regent, [[Mary of Guise]]. It was given over to the Laird of [[Craigmillar Castle|Craigmillar]], and repairs were carried out the following year. In 1558, George Drummond of Blair was keeper of Tantallon, with a garrison of seven horsemen and 22 soldiers.&lt;ref name=Rich23&gt;Richardson, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.23&lt;/ref&gt; [[James Douglas, 4th Earl of Morton]] took control in 1565, on behalf of his nephew, the young [[Archibald Douglas, 8th Earl of Angus|8th Earl of Angus]], but the following year, [[Mary, Queen of Scots]], gave the Captaincy to [[Robert Lauder (d. 1576)|Robert Lauder of the Bass]], and his son, [[Robert Lauder of Popill|Robert Lauder, younger of the Bass]]&lt;ref name=Rich23/&gt; The appointment of the Lauders followed the surrender of Sir [[William Douglas of Lochleven]], who was one of those charged with the murder of Queen Mary's favourite, [[David Rizzio]], in March 1566.&lt;ref&gt;Young, ''The Parliaments of Scotland'', vol.I, p.407&lt;/ref&gt; Mary visited Tantallon herself in November 1566.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackay&quot;/&gt; The ''Yester Writs'' record an Andrew Hume as Captain of Tantallon Castle in 1577.&lt;ref&gt;Harvey &amp; MacLeod, ''Calendar of Writs preserved at Yester House 1166-1625'', No.798&lt;/ref&gt; Following the death of the 8th Earl in 1588, the Earls of Angus lived elsewhere, and had little to do with Tantallon Castle.&lt;ref&gt;Tabraham, ''Tantallon Castle'', p.25&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:George Monck 1st Duke of Albemarle Studio of Lely.jpg|thumb|upright|General Monck, who successfully besieged Tantallon in 1651]]

===17th century===
After a period of peace, Tantallon again saw military action during the [[Bishops' Wars]] in 1639. The Douglas family had remained Catholic after the [[Scottish Reformation]], incurring the wrath of the [[Presbyterian]] [[Covenanter]]s, who opposed [[Charles I of England|Charles I]]'s attempts to interfere with the Scottish Church. In 1639, the Covenanters captured Tantallon while [[William Douglas, 1st Marquess of Douglas|William]], newly created Marquess of Douglas, was in Edinburgh.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Monk's siege of Tantallon.jpg|thumb|left|1651 siege]]
In 1650, during the [[Third English Civil War]], [[Oliver Cromwell]]'s Parliamentarian forces invaded Scotland, taking control of the south of the country after their victory at [[Battle of Dunbar (1650)|Dunbar]] in September. In February 1651, Cromwell found his lines of communication under attack from a small group of Royalists based at Tantallon. This group, led by [[Alexander Seton, 1st Viscount of Kingston|Alexander Seton]], comprised just 91 men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackay&quot;/&gt; Despite this, Cromwell's retaliation was to send 2,000 to 3,000 troops under [[George Monck, 1st Duke of Albemarle|General Monck]], together with much of the artillery he had in Scotland, and lay siege to Tantallon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackay&quot;/&gt; Seton was ennobled by [[Charles II of England|Charles II]], as Viscount of Kingston, on 14 February, during the siege. After twelve days of bombardment with cannon a breach was made in the Douglas Tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salter&quot;/&gt; The defenders were compelled to surrender, but only after [[No quarter|quarter]] had been granted to them in recognition of their bravery.&lt;ref name=Tabraham94p27&gt;Tabraham, ''Tantallon Castle'', pp.26–27&lt;/ref&gt; After the siege Tantallon was left in ruins: it was never repaired or inhabited afterwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackay&quot;/&gt; The siege of Tantallon was also interesting in that the Commonwealth land forces were supported by the [[Royal Navy#1500.E2.80.931707|Commonwealth Navy]].

===Later history===
[[James Douglas, 2nd Marquess of Douglas]], the 12th Earl of Angus, was forced, due to gambling debts accrued by himself and his father, to consolidate his estates. The ruins of Tantallon were sold, in 1699, to [[Hew Dalrymple, Lord North Berwick|Sir Hew Dalrymple]], the [[Lord President of the Court of Session|President of the Court of Session]], who also owned the Barony of North Berwick, the Bass, [[Fidra]] and other properties in the area. Dalrymple allowed the castle to decay further, and to be quarried to a certain extent for stone. Sir [[Walter Scott]] described the castle at length in his 1808 epic poem ''[[Marmion (poem)|Marmion]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindsay&quot;/&gt; Some restoration was carried out by the Dalrymples in the late 19th century, and in 1924, the castle was handed over to the UK Government's [[Office of Works]] by Dalrymple's descendant, Sir Hew Hamilton-Dalrymple, Bt.&lt;ref name=Tabraham94p27/&gt; It is now in the care of Historic Scotland, and is a category A [[listed building]] and a [[Scheduled Ancient Monument]].&lt;ref name=LBR/&gt;

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
*{{cite web |url=http://www.rcahms.gov.uk/pls/portal/newcanmore.newcandig_details_gis?inumlink=56630 |title=Tantallon Castle, NMRS site reference NT58NE 5.00 |publisher=[[Royal Commission on the Ancient and Historical Monuments of Scotland]] (RCAHMS) |accessdate=2008-04-08}}
*{{cite book |author=Brown, Michael |title=The Black Douglases |publisher=John Donald |location=Edinburgh |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-904607-59-5}}
*{{cite book |author=Fawcett, Richard |title=Scottish Architecture from the accession of the Stuarts to the Reformation, 1371&amp;ndash;1560 |series=Architectural History of Scotland |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |location=Edinburgh |year=1994 |isbn=0-7486-0465-0}}
*{{cite book |author=Fraser, William |year=1885 |title=The Douglas Book |publisher=T. and A. Constable |location=Edinburgh |oclc=4963543}}
*{{cite book |editor1-last=Harvey |editor1-first=Charles C. H. |editor2-last=MacLeod |editor2-first=John |year=1930 |title=Calendar of Writs preserved at Yester House 1166-1625 |publisher=[[Scottish Record Society]] |location=Edinburgh |oclc=3384900}}
* {{cite book|author=Johnston, James B. |title=Place Names of Scotland |year=1934 |edition=3rd |publisher=John Murray |location=London |oclc=7443418}}
* {{cite book|author=Lindsay, Maurice |year=1986 |title=The Castles of Scotland |publisher=Constable |location=London |isbn=978-0-09-464600-1}}
* {{cite book|author=Maxwell, Herbert |year=1902 |title=A History of the House of Douglas |publisher=Freemantle |location=London |oclc=4121292 |authorlink=Herbert Maxwell}}
* {{cite book |author1=MacGibbon, David |author2=Ross, Thomas  |lastauthoramp=yes |year=1887 |title=The Castellated and Domestic Architecture of Scotland |volume=I |publisher=D. Douglas |location=Edinburgh |oclc=154087595 |authorlink=MacGibbon and Ross}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/investigating-tantallon-nov08.pdf |format=PDF|title=Investigating Tantallon Castle |author=Mackay, Elspeth |date=n.d. |accessdate=2008-04-08 |publisher=Historic Scotland}}
* {{cite book|author=McKean, Charles |year=2004 |title=The Scottish Chateau |edition=2nd  |publisher=Sutton Publishing |isbn=978-0-7509-2323-1 |location=Stroud}}
* {{cite book|author=McWilliam, Colin |year=1978 |title=Lothian, except Edinburgh |series=The Buildings of Scotland |publisher=Penguin |location=Harmondsworth |isbn=978-0-14-071066-3}}
* {{cite book |author=Paul, James Balfour |title=Accounts of the Lord High Treasurer of Scotland |year=1916 |volume=XI: 1559–1566 |location=Edinburgh |publisher=[[Her Majesty's Stationery Office]] (HMSO) |oclc=271083331 |authorlink=James Balfour Paul}}
* {{cite book|author=Richardson, J. S. |year=1950 |title=Tantallon Castle |publisher=HMSO |location=Edinburgh |edition=2nd |oclc=49244930}}
* {{cite book |author=[[Royal Commission on Historical Manuscripts]] |year=1902 |title=Report on the manuscripts of Colonel David Milne-Home of Wedderburn Castle |location=London |publisher=HMSO |oclc=2551716}}
* {{cite book|author=Salter, Mike |year=1994 |title=The Castles of Lothian and the Borders |publisher=Folly Publications |location=Malvern |isbn=978-1-871731-20-0}}
* {{cite book|author=Tabraham, Chris |year=1997 |title=Scotland's Castles |publisher=BT Batsford/Historic Scotland |location=London |isbn=978-0-7134-8147-1}}
*{{cite book |author=Tabraham, Chris |author2=Grove, Doreen |year=1994 |title=Tantallon Castle |publisher=Historic Scotland |location=Edinburgh |isbn=978-0-7480-0855-1}}
*{{cite book|editor=Young, Margaret D. |year=1993 |title=The Parliaments of Scotland - Burgh &amp; Shire Commissioners |volume=II: A–K |location=Edinburgh |publisher=Scottish Academic Press |isbn=978-0-7073-0703-9}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Tantallon Castle}}
* {{historic-scotland-link|284}}
* [http://www.rcahms.gov.uk/pls/portal/newcanmore.newcandig_details_imgsummary?inumlink=56630 Images of the castle, including plans and aerial photographs, from RCAHMS]
* [http://www.maybole.org/history/castles/Tantallon%20and%20Bass%20Rock.htm Reconstruction image of Tantallon Castle by Andrew Spratt]

{{good article}}

[[Category:Castles in East Lothian]]
[[Category:House of Douglas and Angus|*Castle Tantallon]]
[[Category:Wars of Scottish Independence]]
[[Category:Wars of the Three Kingdoms]]
[[Category:Listed castles in Scotland]]
[[Category:Category A listed buildings in East Lothian]]
[[Category:Scheduled Ancient Monuments in Scotland]]
[[Category:Historic house museums in East Lothian]]
[[Category:Reportedly haunted locations in Scotland]]</text>
      <sha1>qn7hk8y61qo3kz315lrcjapymin9f8a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
