<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Hurt Locker</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16733548</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748034411</id>
      <parentid>747551967</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-05T23:24:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Super997</username>
        <id>28598625</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Critical response */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="70513">{{Infobox film
|name = The Hurt Locker
|image = HLposterUSA2.jpg
|alt = From above a flat. and dry desert floor, a person in a green military uniform with heavy padding holds red wires attached to seven pill-shaped bomb canisters scattered around him. At the top of the poster are three critics' favorable opinions: &quot;A near-perfect movie&quot;, &quot;A full-tilt action picture&quot;, and &quot;Ferociously suspenseful&quot;. Below the quotes is the title &quot;THE HURT LOCKER&quot; and the tagline, &quot;You don't have to be a hero to do this job. But it helps.&quot;
|caption = Theatrical release poster
|director = [[Kathryn Bigelow]]
|producer = {{plainlist|
* Kathryn Bigelow
* [[Mark Boal]]
* [[Nicolas Chartier]]
* Greg Shapiro
}}
|writer = Mark Boal
|starring = {{plainlist|
* [[Jeremy Renner]]
* [[Anthony Mackie]]
* [[Brian Geraghty]]
* [[Christian Camargo]]
* [[Ralph Fiennes]]
* [[David Morse (actor)|David Morse]]
* [[Guy Pearce]]
}}
|music = {{plainlist|
* [[Marco Beltrami]]
}}
|cinematography = [[Barry Ackroyd]]
|editing = {{plainlist|
* [[Chris Innis]]
* [[Bob Murawski]]
}}
|studio = {{plainlist|
* [[Voltage Pictures]]
* [[Grosvenor Park Productions|Grosvenor Park Media]]
* Film Capital Europe Funds&lt;br&gt;First Light Production
* Kingsgate Films
}}
|distributor = [[Summit Entertainment]]
|released = {{Film date|2008|9|4|[[65th Venice International Film Festival|Venice]]|2009|6|26|United States}}
|runtime = 131 minutes&lt;!-- U.S. theatrical release: 130:31 --&gt;
|country = United States
|language = English
|budget = $15 million&lt;ref name=bom/&gt;
|gross = $49.2 million&lt;ref name=bom&gt;[http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=hurtlocker.htm &quot;''The Hurt Locker'' (2009)&quot;]. [[Box Office Mojo]]. Retrieved 2014-09-22.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''''The Hurt Locker''''' is a 2009 American [[war film]] about an [[Iraq War]] [[Bomb disposal|Explosive Ordinance Disposal]] team who are being targeted by insurgents with booby traps, remote control detonations and ambushes. Directed by [[Kathryn Bigelow]], it received critical acclaim and won six [[Academy Award]]s, including [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]]. Bigelow won the award for [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]]; as of 2016, ''The Hurt Locker'' is the sole film by a female director to win in either category. It is also the lowest-grossing Best Picture winner in history.

''The Hurt Locker'' shows soldiers' varying psychological reactions to the stress of combat, which though intolerable to some, is addictive to others. The story unfolds after a staff sergeant is killed by an insurgent trap and an apparently calm veteran is brought in to head the squad. His comrades suspect that their new team leader is being driven to take terrifying risks. Writer [[Mark Boal]] drew on his experience during embedded access to provide an authentic background for the production, although certain army procedures were portrayed with artistic licence.

==Plot==
''The Hurt Locker'' opens with a quotation from ''[[War Is a Force That Gives Us Meaning]]'', a best-selling 2002 book by [[Chris Hedges]], a ''New York Times'' war correspondent and journalist: &quot;The rush of battle is a potent and often lethal addiction, for war is a drug.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotsman&quot;&gt;Harkness, Alistair (August 28, 2009). [http://thescotsman.scotsman.com/features/Film-review-The-Hurt-Locker.5596366.jp &quot;Film Review: ''The Hurt Locker''&quot;]. ''[[The Scotsman]]''. Retrieved 2010-10-09.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Chris Hedges|Hedges, Chris]] (2003). ''War is a Force that Gives us Meaning'' (Reprint ed.). New York, NY: [[Random House|Random House Inc]]. p. 3 of introduction. ISBN 978-1-4000-3463-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Chris Hedges]]' book ''[[War Is a Force That Gives Us Meaning]]'' has the full quote on page 3: &quot;The rush of battle is often a potent and lethal addiction, for war is a drug, one I ingested for many years.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sergeant First Class]] William James ([[Jeremy Renner]]), a battle-tested veteran, arrives as a new team leader of a [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] [[Bomb disposal|Explosive Ordnance Disposal]] (EOD) unit in the Iraq War,&lt;ref name=npr&gt;Edelstein, David (June 26, 2009). [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=105964997 &quot;'Hurt Locker': American Bomb Squad In Baghdad&quot;]. [[NPR]]. Retrieved 2009-11-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=popmech&gt;McCarthy, Erin (July 9, 2009). [http://www.popularmechanics.com/technology/military_law/4324279.html &quot;Hurt Locker: Iraqi Explosive Ordnance Disposal Hits the Big Screen&quot;]. ''Popular Mechanics''. Hearst Communications. Retrieved 2009-11-02.&lt;/ref&gt; replacing [[Staff sergeant#United States|Staff Sergeant]] Matthew Thompson ([[Guy Pearce]]), who was killed by a radio-controlled [[M107 projectile|155mm]] [[improvised explosive device]] (IED) in [[Baghdad]]. His team includes Sergeant J.T. Sanborn ([[Anthony Mackie]]) and [[Specialist (rank)|Specialist]] Owen Eldridge ([[Brian Geraghty]]).

James' maverick methods and attitude lead Sanborn and Eldridge to consider him reckless, and tensions mount. When they are assigned to destroy some explosives in a remote desert area, James returns to the detonation site to pick up his gloves. Sanborn openly contemplates killing James by &quot;accidentally&quot; triggering the explosion, making Eldridge very uncomfortable, but Sanborn does nothing.

Returning to [[Camp Victory]] in their [[Humvee]], the team encounters five armed men in traditional Arab garb standing near the men's [[Ford Excursion]], which has a flat tire. After a tense encounter, the men reveal themselves to be [[Private military company|private military contractors]] and British [[Mercenary|mercenaries]]. They have captured two prisoners featured on the [[most-wanted Iraqi playing cards]]. The entire group suddenly comes under fire, and when the prisoners attempt to escape in the confusion, the leader of the mercenaries ([[Ralph Fiennes]]) remembers the bounty for them is &quot;dead or alive&quot; and shoots them. Enemy snipers kill three of the mercenaries, including the leader. Sanborn and James borrow a [[Barrett M82|Barrett .50 cal]] to dispatch three attackers, while Eldridge kills a fourth.

During a raid on a warehouse, James discovers the body of a young boy, in which a live bomb has been surgically implanted. James believes it to be &quot;Beckham&quot; (Christopher Sayegh), an Iraqi youth he had previously befriended. During evacuation, [[Lieutenant colonel|Lieutenant Colonel]] John Cambridge ([[Christian Camargo]]), the camp's [[psychiatrist]] and a friend of Eldridge's, is killed in an explosion; Eldridge blames himself for the Colonel's death. Later, James leaves the military compound seeking revenge for Beckham and breaks into the house of an Iraqi professor, but his search reveals nothing and he leaves.

Called to a petrol tanker detonation, James decides on his own to hunt for the insurgents responsible, guessing they are still in the immediate area. Sanborn protests, but when James heads out, he and Eldridge reluctantly follow. After they split up, insurgents capture Eldridge. James and Sanborn rescue him, but accidentally shoot him in the leg. The following morning, James is approached by Beckham, who James believed was dead.&lt;!-- Please do not change. Script says it is indeed Beckham. See discussion page. --&gt; The young boy tries to play soccer with James and sell him more DVDs, but the soldier walks by without saying a word. Before being airlifted for surgery elsewhere, Eldridge angrily blames James for his injury.

James and Sanborn's unit is called to another mission in their last two days of their rotation. An innocent Iraqi civilian man has had a bomb vest strapped to his chest. James tries to cut off the locks to remove the vest, but there are too many to undo in the time available before the bomb will detonate. He has to abandon the man, who is killed when the bomb explodes. Sanborn is left distraught by the man's death. He confesses to James that he can no longer cope with the pressure, and he wants to return home and have a son.

After Bravo Company's rotation ends, James returns home to his ex-wife, Connie ([[Evangeline Lilly]]) and their infant son who both still live with him in his house. However, he is bored and disconnected from routine civilian life, with its ordinary tasks of shopping at the supermarket and family dinners. One night, James confesses to his son that there is only one thing that he knows he loves. Shortly thereafter, he starts another tour of duty serving with Delta Company, U.S. Army EOD unit as they are starting their 365-day rotation.

==Cast==
* [[Jeremy Renner]] as Sergeant First Class William James
* [[Anthony Mackie]] as Sergeant J. T. Sanborn
* [[Brian Geraghty]] as Specialist Owen Eldridge
* [[Guy Pearce]] as Staff Sergeant Matthew Thompson
* [[Christian Camargo]] as Lieutenant Colonel John Cambridge
* [[David Morse (actor)|David Morse]] as Colonel Reed
* [[Ralph Fiennes]] as the leader of a [[Private Military Company]] unit
* [[Evangeline Lilly]] as Connie James
* Christopher Sayegh as Beckham
* [[Malcolm Barrett (actor)|Malcolm Barrett]] as Sergeant Foster
* [[Sam Spruell]] as Contractor Charlie
==Production==

The small budget film was independently produced and directed by [[Kathryn Bigelow]] and the screenplay was written by [[Mark Boal]], a freelance writer who was [[Embedded journalism|embedded]] as a journalist in 2004 with a [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] EOD team in [[Iraq]]. It stars [[Jeremy Renner]], [[Anthony Mackie]], and [[Brian Geraghty]].

The film premiered at the [[Venice Film Festival]] in Italy during 2008. After being shown at the [[Toronto International Film Festival]], it was picked up for distribution in the United States by [[Summit Entertainment]]. In May 2009, it was the Closing Night selection for [[Maryland Film Festival]]. The film was released in the United States on June 26, 2009 but received a more widespread theatrical release on July 24, 2009.

Since the film was not released in the United States until 2009, it was eligible for the [[Academy Awards]] [[82nd Academy Awards|only the following year]], where it was nominated for nine [[Academy Award]]s. Although the film had not recovered its budget by the time of the ceremony,&lt;ref name=&quot;desertnewsoscars&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.deseretnews.com/article/700006507/Box-office-numbers-for-Oscar-best-picture-nominees.html |title=Box-office numbers for Oscar best-picture nominees |publisher=[[Deseret Management Corporation]] |work=[[Deseret News]] |accessdate=April 26, 2011 |date=February 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; it won six Oscars, including [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]], [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]] for Bigelow (the first woman to win this award), and [[Academy Award for Best Writing (Original Screenplay)|Best Original Screenplay]] for Boal.

===Writing===
''The Hurt Locker'' is based on accounts of [[Mark Boal]], a freelance journalist who was embedded with an American bomb squad in the [[Iraq War|war in Iraq]] for two weeks in 2004.&lt;ref name=Goodwin&gt;Goodwin, Christopher (August 16, 2009). &quot;Kathryn Bigelow is back with ''The Hurt Locker'',&quot; ''The Sunday Times''.&lt;/ref&gt; The director Kathryn Bigelow was familiar with Boal's work before his experiences, having adapted one of his ''[[Playboy]]'' articles as the short-lived television series ''[[The Inside (TV series)|The Inside]]'' in 2002. When Boal was embedded with the squad, he accompanied its members 10 to 15 times a day to watch their tasks, and kept in touch with Bigelow via email about his experiences.&lt;ref name=story&gt;Keogh, Tom (July 8, 2009). &quot;Hurt Locker goes for 'you-are-there' effect in war story,&quot; ''[[The Seattle Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Boal used his experiences as the basis of a fictional drama based on real events. He said of the film's goal, &quot;The idea is that it's the first movie about the Iraq War that purports to show the experience of the soldiers. We wanted to show the kinds of things that soldiers go through that you can't see on CNN, and I don't mean that in a censorship-conspiracy way. I just mean the news doesn't actually put photographers in with units that are this elite.&quot;&lt;ref name=lands&gt;Kit, Borys (July 17, 2007). &quot;Locker lands 3 in Iraq story&quot;. ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Bigelow was fascinated with exploring &quot;the psychology behind the type of soldier who volunteers for this particular conflict and then, because of his or her aptitude, is chosen and given the opportunity to go into bomb disarmament and goes ''toward'' what everybody else is running from.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dawson&gt;Dawson, Nick (2009). &quot;Time's Up: Kathryn Bigelow's The Hurt Locker,&quot; ''The Times''&lt;/ref&gt;

While working with Boal in 2005 on the script, originally titled ''The Something Jacket,'' Bigelow began to do some preliminary, rough storyboards to get an idea of the specific location needed. Bomb disarmament protocol requires a containment area. She wanted to make the film as authentic as possible and &quot;put the audience into the Humvee, into a boots-on-the-ground experience.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt;

===Casting===
{{triple image|right|82nd Academy Awards, Jeremy Renner - army mil-66454-2010-03-09-180356.jpg|112|Anthony Mackie by Gage Skidmore.jpg|126|Brian Geraghty by David Shankbone.jpg|120|[[Jeremy Renner]]|[[Anthony Mackie]]|[[Brian Geraghty]]}}
For the main characters, Bigelow made a point of casting relatively unknown actors: &quot;it underscored the tension because with the lack of familiarity also comes a sense of unpredictability.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt; Renner's character, Sergeant First Class William James, is a [[composite character]], with qualities based on individuals whom screenwriter Boal knew when embedded with the bomb squad.&lt;ref name=story/&gt; Bigelow cast Renner based on his work in ''[[Dahmer (film)|Dahmer]]'', a film about [[Jeffrey Dahmer]], the notorious serial killer whose victims were boys.&lt;ref name=Ayres&gt;Ayres, Chris (March 6, 2010). &quot;''The Hurt Locker''s Jeremy Renner on his long road to the Oscars,&quot; ''The Times''&lt;/ref&gt; To prepare for the film, Renner spent a week living and training at [[Fort Irwin]], a U.S. military reservation in the [[Mojave Desert]] in [[California]]. He was taught to use [[C4 explosives]], learned how to render safe improvised explosive devices, and how to wear a bomb suit.&lt;ref name=Ayres/&gt;

Mackie plays Sergeant J.T. Sanborn. Describing the experience of filming in Jordan in the summer, he said, &quot;It was so desperately hot, and we were so easily agitated. But that movie was like doing a play. We really looked out for each other, and it was a great experience. It made me believe in film.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stewart, Sara (August 24, 2009). &quot;Mackie's back in town,&quot; ''[[New York Post]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Several hundred thousand [[refugees of Iraq]] live in Jordan. Bigelow cast refugees who had theatrical backgrounds, such as Suhail Aldabbach. He plays the innocent man used as a [[suicide bomber]] at the film's end.&lt;ref name=story/&gt;

===Filming===
The film was shot in [[Jordan]], within miles of the Iraqi border, to achieve Bigelow's goal of authenticity. Iraqi refugees were used for extras and the cast worked in the intense heat of the Middle East. The filmmakers had scouted for locations in [[Morocco]], but director Kathryn Bigelow felt its cities did not resemble Baghdad. In addition, she wanted to get as close to the war zone as possible. Some of the locations were less than three miles from the Iraq border.&lt;ref name=eye/&gt; She had wanted to film in Iraq, but the production security team could not guarantee their safety from snipers.&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt;

Principal photography began in July 2007 in Jordan and [[Kuwait]]. Temperatures averaged {{convert|120|F}} over the 44 days of shooting.&lt;ref name=lands/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt;&lt;ref name=Ayres/&gt; Often four or more camera crews filmed simultaneously, which resulted in nearly 200 hours of footage.&lt;ref name=eye&gt;Olsen, Mark (September 8, 2008). [http://articles.latimes.com/2008/sep/08/entertainment/et-hurt8 &quot;'Hurt Locker' a soldier's-eye view of the Iraq war&quot;]. ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''. Retrieved 2009-08-16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DGA&gt;Ressner, Jeffrey (Winter 2008). [http://www.dgaquarterly.org/AllArticles/DirectorProfiles/KathyrnBigelow.aspx &quot;Kinetic Camera&quot;]. ''DGA Quarterly''.&lt;/ref&gt; The producer Greg Shapiro spoke about security concerns of filming in Jordan, &quot;It was interesting telling people we were going to make the movie in Jordan because the first question everybody asked was about the security situation here.&quot;

Her choice to film in the Kingdom met some resistance. In discussion, Bigelow found that her cast and crew shared stereotypes of the region from American culture. “Sadly people in America and Los Angeles have these perceptions,” she said. “But once you get off the plane you realise it's like Manhattan without the trees,” she continued. As Iraq dominated discourse in America and across the world, Bigelow believed that filmmakers would continue to explore the conflict, making Jordan the natural place to film.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jordan Times&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.jordantimes.com/?news=2564 |author=Luck, Taylor |title=Jordan poses as Iraq Cinecittà for Hollywood |work=Jordan Times |date=October 1, 2007 |accessdate=2011-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to producer Tony Mark, the blood, sweat and heat captured on-camera in the production was mirrored behind the scenes. &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It's a tough, tough movie about a tough, tough subject&quot;, Mark said in an interview, &quot;There was a palpable tension throughout on the set. It was just like the onscreen story of three guys who fight with each other, but when the time comes to do the work, they come together to get the job done.&quot;&lt;ref name=Producer&gt;Nott, Robert (July 28, 2009). [http://www.santafenewmexican.com/Local%20News/-Hurt-Locker--producer-lauds-film-crew---and-N-M--industry &quot;Hurt Locker Producer Lauds Film Crew and New Mexico Industry&quot;]. ''The New Mexican''. Retrieved 2010-10-20.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Renner remembered, &quot;I got food bugs. Then I got food poisoning: lost 15&amp;nbsp;lbs in three days&quot;.&lt;ref name=Ayres/&gt; In addition to the burden of the heat, the bomb suit he had to wear all day weighed {{convert|80|-|100|lb|kg|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=Tobias&gt;Tobias, Scott (June 24, 2009). [http://www.avclub.com/articles/kathryn-bigelow,29544/ &quot;Kathryn Bigelow&quot;]. ''The Onion'' A.V. Club. Retrieved 2010-10-16.&lt;/ref&gt; In a scene in which his character carries a dead Iraqi boy, Renner fell down some stairs and twisted his ankle, which delayed filming because he could not walk. At that point, &quot;people wanted to quit. All the departments were struggling to get their job done, none of them were communicating&quot;.&lt;ref name=Ayres/&gt; A week later, filming resumed.&lt;ref name=Ayres/&gt;

The producer Tony Mark recalled the armorer David Fencl's finishing a 12-hour day. He found he had to stay up all night to make proper ammunition for a sniper rifle, as the supplies did not clear Jordanian customs in time for the scheduled shoot.&lt;ref name=Producer/&gt; Due to import restrictions on military props, the film's special effects artist Richard Stutsman used Chinese fireworks for gunpowder. One day, he was assembling a prop, and the heat and friction caused the fireworks to blow up in his face. Two days later, he returned to work.&lt;ref name=Ayres/&gt; The film shoot had few of the normal [[Cinema of the United States|Hollywood]] perks; nobody on the set got an air-conditioned trailer or a private bathroom.&lt;ref name=Producer/&gt; Renner said that great care was taken to ensure the film's authenticity.&lt;ref name=MPM&gt;[[Elliot V. Kotek]] &quot;Jeremy Renner&amp;nbsp;– ''The Hurt Locker''&quot;, ''Movie Pictures Magazine''.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Renner, shooting the film in the Middle East contributed to this. &quot;There were two-by-fours with nails being dropped from two-story buildings that hit me in the helmet, and they were throwing rocks.... We got shot at a few times while we were filming&quot;, Renner said. &quot;When you see it, you're gonna feel like you've been in war.&quot;&lt;ref name=WNNN&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/news/ni0264141/ &quot;Renner Caught Up In Film 'War'&quot;], WENN news, July 20, 2008. Retrieved 2010-10-16.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;You can't fake that amount of heat&quot;, Mackie says, adding, &quot;When you are on set and all of the extras are Iraqi refugees, it really informs the movie that you're making. When you start hearing the stories from a true perspective&amp;nbsp;... of people who were actually there, it gives you a clear viewpoint of where you are as an artist and the story you would like to tell. It was a great experience to be there.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;VOA&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.newjerseynewsroom.com/movies/the-hurt-locker-provides-life-and-death-drama-of-a-us-army-bomb-squad-in-iraq |author=Silverman, Alan |title='The Hurt Locker' provides life and death drama of a U.S. Army bomb squad in Iraq |work=VOA News |date=July 18, 2009 |accessdate=2010-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Cinematography===
For the film, Bigelow sought to immerse audiences &quot;into something that was raw, immediate and visceral&quot;. Impressed with cinematographer [[Barry Ackroyd]]'s work on ''[[United 93 (film)|United 93]]'' and ''[[The Wind That Shakes the Barley (film)|The Wind That Shakes the Barley]],'' Bigelow invited him to work on her film. While the film was independently produced and filmed on a low budget, Bigelow used four [[16&amp;nbsp;mm film|Super 16&amp;nbsp;mm cameras]] to capture multiple perspectives, saying, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;That's how we experience reality, by looking at the microcosm and the macrocosm simultaneously. The eye sees differently than the lens, but with multiple focal lengths and a muscular editorial style, the lens can give you that microcosm/macrocosm perspective, and that contributes to the feeling of total immersion.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;thomson45&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Thomson|2009|p=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; In staging the film's action sequences, Bigelow did not want to lose a sense of the geography and used multiple cameras to allow her to &quot;look at any particular set piece from every possible perspective.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt;

===Editing===
''The Hurt Locker'' was edited by [[Chris Innis]] and [[Bob Murawski]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Avid&quot;&gt;[http://www.avid.com/US/about-avid/customer-stories/Hurt-Locker?cmpid=AV-EM-SV710 &quot;Artful Editing and All-Avid Workflow Propel The Hurt Locker,&quot; Avid.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;&gt;[https://www.editorsguild.com/FromtheGuild.cfm?FromTheGuildid=85 &quot;Between Iraq and a Hard Place, Part 2&quot; by Chris Innis, MPEG, &quot;From the Guild&quot; web site, March 23, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;  The two editors worked with almost 200 hours of footage from the multiple hand-held cameras in use during the shoot.&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;/&gt; Adding to the challenge, Boal's screenplay had a non-traditional, asymmetrical, episodic structure. There was no traditional &quot;villain&quot;, and tension was derived from the characters' internal conflicts and the suspense from the explosives and snipers.&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;/&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;This movie is kind of like a horror film where you're unable to see the killer,&quot; says Innis. &quot;You know a bomb could go off at any minute, but you never know just when it's going to happen, so the ideas of [Alfred] Hitchcock—about making your audience anxious—were influential for us when we did the editing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;VarietyEditors&quot;&gt;[http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118013652?refCatId=3843 Karen Idelson, &quot;Editors Get in Rhythm&quot;], ''Variety'', 12  January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;The raw footage was described as a &quot;hodge-podge of disconnected, nausea-inducing motion that was constantly crossing [[180-degree rule|the 180-degree line]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;/&gt;
 
Innis spent the first eight weeks editing the film on location in Jordan, before returning to Los Angeles, where she was joined by Murawski. The process took over eight months to complete.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avid&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Craft&quot;&gt;[http://incontention.com/2010/01/07/tech-support-the-crafts-of-the-hurt-locker/ Guy Lodge, &quot;The Crafts of 'The Hurt Locker'&quot;], ''In Contention'', 7 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The goal was to edit a brutally realistic portrayal of the realities of war, using minimal special effects or technical enhancement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avid&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;/&gt; Innis stated that they &quot;really wanted the film to retain that 'newsreel' documentary quality... Too many stage-y effects would have been distracting. The editing in this film was all about restraint&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avid&quot;/&gt;  
 
Editing on location led to additional complications in post-production. The production was unwilling to risk sending undeveloped film through high-security airports where the cans could be opened, X-rayed, or damaged. Accordingly, film was hand-carried on a flight by a production assistant from Amman to London. After the Super 16mm film was transferred to DVcam at a lab in London, the video dailies were transported by plane back to the Middle East to be imported into the editing system. The whole journey would take anywhere from three days to a week and was described by Innis as the &quot;modern-day equivalent of shipping via donkey cart&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;/&gt; The low production budget and the lack of a developed film infrastructure in the area hampered the process, according to Innis. &quot;We were working with grainy Super 16mm film, editing in standard definition. We tried doing FTP downloads, but at the time the facilities in Jordan simply couldn't handle it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Avid&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;/&gt; The producer Tony Mark later negotiated the use of a local radio station late at night to receive low-grade [[QuickTime]] clips over the Internet so the crew would not be shooting blindly.&lt;ref name=&quot;MPEG&quot;/&gt;

==Reception==
{{Anchor|Response}}

===Critical response===
{{Anchor|Critics}} 
''The Hurt Locker'' received universal acclaim, with Renner's performance receiving praise from critics. [[Rotten Tomatoes]] gives the film a rating of 98%, based on 254 reviews, with a [[weighted mean]] rating of 8.5/10. It was the second highest-rated film of 2009, behind [[Pixar]]'s ''[[Up (2009 film)|Up]]''. The critics' consensus reads, &quot;A well-acted, intensely shot, action filled war epic, Kathryn Bigelow's ''The Hurt Locker'' is thus far the best of the recent dramatizations of the Iraq War.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;rt&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/hurt_locker/ |title=The Hurt Locker (2009) |work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]] |publisher=[[Flixster]] |accessdate=2010-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Metacritic]], which assigns a [[Standard score|normalized score]], gave the film an average score of 94 out of 100, based on 35 critics, indicating &quot;universal acclaim&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.metacritic.com/film/titles/hurtlocker |title=Hurt Locker, The reviews at Metacritic.com |work=[[Metacritic]] |publisher=[[CBS]] |accessdate=2010-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roger Ebert]] of ''[[The Chicago Sun Times]]'' rated the film as the best film of 2009, writing, &quot;''The Hurt Locker'' is a great film, an intelligent film, a film shot clearly so that we know exactly who everybody is and where they are and what they're doing and why.&quot; He applauded how the suspense was built, calling the film &quot;spellbinding.&quot; Ebert considered Renner &quot;a leading contender for Academy Awards,&quot; writing, &quot;His performance is not built on complex speeches but on a visceral projection of who this man is and what he feels. He is not a hero in a conventional sense.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Ebert |first=Roger |authorlink=Roger Ebert |title=The best films of the decade |url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090708/REVIEWS/907089997 | work=[[The Chicago Sun-Times]] |date=July 8, 2009 |accessdate=2009-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; He eventually ranked it the second-best film of the decade, behind only ''[[Synecdoche, New York]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Ebert |first=Roger |authorlink=Roger Ebert |title=The Hurt Locker |url=http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/2009/12/the_best_films_of_the_decade.html | work=Roger Ebert's Journal |date=December 9, 2009 |accessdate=2009-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Richard Corliss]] of ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine also spoke highly of Renner's performance, calling it a highlight of the film. Corliss wrote, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;He's ordinary, pudgy-faced, quiet, and at first seems to lack the screen charisma to carry a film. That supposition vanishes in a few minutes, as Renner slowly reveals the strength, confidence and unpredictability of a young Russell Crowe. The merging of actor and character is one of the big things to love about this movie... It's a creepy marvel to watch James in action. He has the cool aplomb, analytical acumen and attention to detail of a great athlete, or a master psychopath, maybe both.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Corliss praised the film's &quot;steely calm&quot; tone, reflective of its main character. Corliss summarized, &quot;''The Hurt Locker'' is a near-perfect movie about men in war, men at work. Through sturdy imagery and violent action, it says that even Hell needs heroes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Corliss |first=Richard |url=http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1838615,00.html |title=''The Hurt Locker'': A Near-Perfect War Film |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=September 4, 2008 |accessdate=2009-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[A. O. Scott]] of ''The New York Times'' called ''The Hurt Locker'' the best American feature film yet made about the war in Iraq: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;You may emerge from ''The Hurt Locker'' shaken, exhilarated and drained, but you will also be thinking ... The movie is a viscerally exciting, adrenaline-soaked tour de force of suspense and surprise, full of explosions and hectic scenes of combat, but it blows a hole in the condescending assumption that such effects are just empty spectacle or mindless noise.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Scott noticed that the film reserved [[Criticism of the Iraq War|criticism of the war]] but wrote of how the director handled the film's limits, &quot;Ms. Bigelow, practicing a kind of hyperbolic realism, distills the psychological essence and moral complications of modern warfare into a series of brilliant, agonizing set pieces.&quot; He also applauded the convergence of the characters in the film, saying that it &quot;focuses on three men whose contrasting temperaments knit this episodic exploration of peril and bravery into a coherent and satisfying story.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Scott | first=A. O. | authorlink=A. O. Scott | url= http://movies.nytimes.com/2009/06/26/movies/26hurt.html | title=Soldiers on a Live Wire Between Peril and Protocol | work=The New York Times | date=June 26, 2009 | accessdate=2009-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenneth Turan]] of the ''Los Angeles Times'' wrote that the performances of Renner, Mackie, and Geraghty would raise their profiles considerably, and said their characters reveal their &quot;unlooked-for aspects&quot;, such as Renner's character being playful with an Iraqi boy. Turan applauded Boal's &quot;lean and compelling&quot; script and said of Bigelow's direction, &quot;Bigelow and her team bring an awesome ferocity to re-creating the unhinged mania of bomb removal in an alien, culturally unfathomable atmosphere.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Turan | first=Kenneth | authorlink= Kenneth Turan | url= http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-hurtlocker26-2009jun26,0,4546320.story | title= The Hurt Locker | work= [[Los Angeles Times]] | date=June 26, 2009 | accessdate= 2010-09-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Guy Westwell of ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]'' wrote that the cinematographer Barry Ackroyd provided &quot;sharp handheld coverage&quot; and that Paul N.J. Ottosson's sound design &quot;uses the barely perceptible ringing of [[tinnitus]] to amp up the tension.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Westwell&quot;/&gt; Westwell praised the director's skill: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The careful mapping of the subtle differences between each bomb, the play with point of view ... and the attenuation of key action sequences ... lends the film a distinctive quality that can only be attributed to Bigelow's clever, confident direction.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Westwell&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;The critic noted the film's different take on the Iraq War, writing that &quot;it confronts the fact that men often take great pleasure in war.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Westwell&quot; /&gt; He concluded, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;This unapologetic celebration of a testosterone-fuelled lust for war may gall. Yet there is something original and distinctive about the film's willingness to admit that for some men (and many moviegoers) war carries an intrinsic dramatic charge.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Westwell&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last=Westwell | first=Guy | url= http://www.bfi.org.uk/sightandsound/review/5082 | title=The Hurt Locker | journal=[[Sight &amp; Sound]] |date=September 2009 | volume=19 | issue=9 | pages=67–68 | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Amy Taubin of ''[[Film Comment]]'' described ''The Hurt Locker'' as &quot;a structuralist war movie&quot; and &quot;a totally immersive, off-the-charts high-anxiety experience from beginning to end.&quot; Taubin praised Ackroyd's &quot;brilliant&quot; cinematography with multiple viewpoints. She said of the film's editing, &quot;Bob Murawski and Chris Innis's editing is similarly quick and nervous; the rapid changes in POV as they cut from one camera's coverage to another's makes you feel as if you, like the characters, are under threat from all sides.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=Taubin | first=Amy | title=Hard Wired | journal=[[Film Comment]] | date=May–June 2009 | volume=45 | issue=3 | pages=30–35 | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Joe Morgenstern of ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' called it &quot;A first-rate action thriller, a vivid evocation of urban warfare in Iraq, a penetrating study of heroism and a showcase for austere technique, terse writing and a trio of brilliant performances.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WSJ&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204621904574249972655817950.html |title=Locker: Shock, Awe, Brilliance |work=The Wall Street Journal |last =Morgenstern | first = Joe |date=June 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Toronto Star]]'' critic Peter Howell said, &quot;Just when you think the battle of Iraq war dramas has been fought and lost, along comes one that demands to be seen... If you can sit through ''The Hurt Locker'' without your heart nearly pounding through your chest, you must be made of granite.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;TStar&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.thestar.com/entertainment/FilmFest/article/487954 |work= The Star.com |title= Fest Bet: The Iraq war, brought down to the pavement |last= Howell | first = Peter |date=August 31, 2008 | location=Toronto}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'''s film critic Lisa Schwarzbaum gave the film the rare &quot;A&quot; rating, calling it, &quot;an intense, action-driven war pic, a muscular, efficient standout that simultaneously conveys the feeling of combat from within as well as what it looks like on the ground. This ain't no war videogame.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EW2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20285519,00.html |work=Entertainment Weekly |publisher=[[Time Inc.]] |title=The Hurt Locker (2009) |last=Schwarzbaum |first=Lisa |date=June 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Derek Elley of ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' found ''The Hurt Locker'' to be &quot;gripping&quot; as a thriller but felt that the film was weakened by, &quot;its fuzzy (and hardly original) psychology.&quot; Elley wrote that it was unclear to know where the drama lay: &quot;These guys get by on old-fashioned guts and instinct rather than sissy hardware—but it's not a pure men-under-stress drama either.&quot; The critic also felt that the script showed &quot;signs of artificially straining for character depth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Elley |first= Derek |url= http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117938188.html |title=The Hurt Locker |journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |date=September 4, 2008 |accessdate=2009-08-28 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anne Thompson, also writing for ''Variety'', believed ''The Hurt Locker'' to be a contender for Best Picture, particularly based on the unique subject matter pursued by a female director and on being an exception to other films about the Iraq War, which had performed poorly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Thompson |first=Anne |url=http://weblogs.variety.com/thompsononhollywood/2009/06/hurt-locker-other-award-pics-directed-by-women.html |title=Hurt Locker, Other Award Pics Directed by Women |journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |date=June 28, 2009 |accessdate=2009-08-29 |ref=harv |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091004153626/http://weblogs.variety.com/thompsononhollywood/2009/06/hurt-locker-other-award-pics-directed-by-women.html |archivedate=October 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Tara McKelvey]] from ''[[The American Prospect]]'' wrote that the film is pro-U.S. Army propaganda, although it suggests it is anti-war with the opening statement: &quot;War is a drug.&quot; She continues, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;You feel empathy for the soldiers when they shoot. And in this way, the full impact of the Iraq war—at least as it was fought in 2004—becomes clear: American soldiers shot at Iraqi civilians even when, for example, they just happened to be holding a cell phone and standing near an IED.&quot; She concludes, &quot;For all the graphic violence, bloody explosions and, literally, human butchery that is shown in the film, ''The Hurt Locker'' is one of the most effective recruiting vehicles for the U.S. Army that I have seen.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_hurt_locker_as_propaganda |title=The Hurt Locker as Propaganda |first=Tara |last= McKelvey |date=July 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[John Pilger]], journalist and documentarian, criticized the film in the ''[[New Statesman]]'', writing that it &quot;offers a vicarious thrill via yet another standard-issue psychopath high on violence in somebody else's country where the deaths of a million people are consigned to cinematic oblivion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/film/2010/02/pilger-iraq-oscar-american-war |title=Why the Oscars are a con |first=John |last=Pilger |date=February 11, 2010 |accessdate=2011-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Response among veterans===
The film was criticized by some Iraq veterans and embedded reporters for inaccurately portraying wartime conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.newsweek.com/id/234064 |title=When Cinéma Vérité Isn't |author=Paul Rieckhoff |date=February 24, 2010 |work=Newsweek |accessdate=2010-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writing for ''[[The Huffington Post]]'', Iraq veteran Kate Hoit said that ''The Hurt Locker'' is &quot;Hollywood's version of the Iraq war and of the soldiers who fight it, and their version is inaccurate.&quot; She described the film as being more accurate than other recently released war films, but expressed concerns that a number of errors—among them wrong uniforms, lack of radio communication or misbehavior of the soldiers—would prevent service members from enjoying the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kate-hoit/the-hurt-locker-doesnt-ge_b_449043.html |work=The Huffington Post |date=February 4, 2010 |title=The Hurt Locker Doesn't Get this Vet's Vote |last=Hoit |first=Kate |accessdate=2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Author [[Brandon Friedman]], also a combat veteran of Iraq and [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Afghanistan]], shared a similar view at ''[[VetVoice]]'': &quot;''The Hurt Locker'' is a high-tension, well-made, action movie that will certainly keep most viewers on the edges of their seats. But if you know anything about the Army, or about operations or life in Iraq, you'll be so distracted by the nonsensical sequences and plot twists that it will ruin the movie for you. It certainly did for me.&quot; Friedman criticized the inaccuracy of the film's representation of combat, saying &quot;in real life, EOD techs don't conduct dangerous missions as autonomous three-man teams without communications gear ... Another thing you'll rarely hear in combat is an EOD E-7 suggesting to two or three of his guys that they leave the scene of an explosion in an Iraqi city by saying: 'C'mon, let's split up. We can cover more ground that way.{{' &quot;}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Friedman |first=Brandon |url=http://www.vetvoice.com/showDiary.do?diaryId=2975 |work=VetVoice |title=Movie Review: The Hurt Locker |date=July 21, 2009 |accessdate=2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the blog ''Army of Dude'', infantryman and Iraq veteran Alex Horton noted that &quot;the way the team goes about their missions is completely absurd.&quot; He still generally enjoyed it and called it &quot;the best Iraq movie to date.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Horton |first=Alex |url=http://armyofdude.blogspot.com/2009/07/review-hurt-locker.html |work=Army of Dude |title=Review: The Hurt Locker |date=July 22, 2009 |accessdate=2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Troy Steward, another combat veteran, wrote on the blog ''Bouhammer'' that while the film accurately depicted the scale of bomb violence and the relations between Iraqis and troops, &quot;just about everything else wasn't realistic.&quot; Steward went on to say: &quot;I was amazed that a movie so bad could get any kind of accolades from anyone.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Steward |first=Troy |url=http://www.bouhammer.com/2010/01/bouhammer-review-of-the-hurt-locker/ |title=Bouhammer Review of The Hurt Locker |work=bouhammer.com |date=January 16, 2010 |accessdate=2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A review published March 8, 2010 in the ''[[Air Force Times]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Ford |first=Matt |title=Real Hurt Lockers in Iraq: Life is no movie |date=March 8, 2010 |work=Air Force Times |url=http://www.airforcetimes.com/news/2010/03/ap_hurtlocker_reallife_030810/ |accessdate=2010-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; cited overall negative reviews from bomb experts in Iraq attached to the 4th Brigade, 1st Armored Division, quoting a bomb disposal team leader who called the film's portrayal of a bomb expert &quot;grossly exaggerated and not appropriate,&quot; and describing the lead character as &quot;more of a run and gun cowboy type … exactly the kind of person that we're not looking for.&quot; Another bomb disposal team member said that the lead character's &quot;swagger would put a whole team at risk. Our team leaders don't have that kind of invincibility complex, and if they do, they aren't allowed to operate. A team leader's first priority is getting his team home in one piece.&quot;

On the embedded side, former correspondent for ''[[The Politico]]'' and ''[[Military Times]]'' Christian Lowe (who embedded with U.S. military units each year from 2002 to 2005) explained at ''DefenseTech'': &quot;Some of the scenes are so disconnected with reality to be almost parody.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://defensetech.org/2009/07/10/hurt-locker-is-a-blast-without-the-spark/ |work=DefenseTech |author=Christian |title=Hurt Locker is a Blast Without a Spark |date=July 10, 2010 |accessdate=2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, Henry Engelhardt, an adjutant with the National Explosive Ordnance Disposal Association having twenty years' experience in bomb defusal, complimented the film's atmosphere and depiction of the difficulties of the job, saying, &quot;Of course, no film is realistic in all its details, but the important things were done very well.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118013551.html |title=Experts on Oscar contenders' accuracy |work=Variety |date=January 8, 2010 |last1= Engelhardt | first1 = Henry |accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Screenwriter Mark Boal noted that ''The Hurt Locker'' was produced independently, without US Army extras.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebertblog&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/2009/07/not_how_the_army_would_fight_aliens.html |title= Open the hurt locker and learn how rough men come hunting for souls |work=Sun-Times | last1 = Ebert | first1 = Roger | authorlink = Roger Ebert |date=July 10, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Former British bomb disposal officer Guy Marot said, “James makes us look like hot-headed, irrational adrenaline junkies with no self-discipline. It’s immensely disrespectful to the many officers who have lost their lives.” &lt;ref&gt;http://www.careeraftermilitary.com/10-most-inaccurate-military-movies-ever-made/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lawsuits==

===Sarver lawsuit===
In early March 2010, U.S. Army bomb disposal expert Master Sergeant Jeffrey Sarver filed a multimillion-dollar lawsuit against ''The Hurt Locker''.  Sarver's lawsuit claimed he used the term &quot;hurt locker&quot; and the phrase &quot;war is a drug&quot; around Boal, that his likeness was used to create the character William James, and that the portrayal of William James defames Sarver.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thewrap.com/ind-column/hurt-locker-sued-over-stolen-identity-do-not-publish-14850 |title='Hurt Locker' Sued Over Stolen Identity |author1=Lang, Brent  |author2=Waxman, Sharon  |lastauthoramp=yes |date=March 3, 2010 |work=The Wrap |accessdate=2010-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sarver said he felt &quot;just a little bit hurt, a little bit felt left out&quot; and cheated out of &quot;financial participation&quot; in the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaclaim&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2010-03-03-hurt-locker-lawsuit_N.htm |title=Army bomb expert claims 'Hurt Locker' based on him |work= [[USA Today]] |last=Hinds |first=Julie |accessdate=2010-04-09 |date=March 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sarver claimed he originated the title of the film; however, the title is a decades-old colloquialism for being injured, as in &quot;they sent him to the hurt locker.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.themajlis.org/2009/08/10/movie-review-the-hurt-locker |title=Movie Review: The Hurt Locker |accessdate=2010-02-14 |quote=The name of the movie, according to the official Web site, is G.I. slang for being injured in an explosion, i.e., &quot;put in the hurt locker&quot; |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100311191947/http://www.themajlis.org/2009/08/10/movie-review-the-hurt-locker |archivedate=March 11, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It dates back to the [[Vietnam War]] where it was one of several phrases meaning &quot;in trouble or at a disadvantage; in bad shape.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.visualthesaurus.com/cm/wordroutes/2195/ |last=Zimmer |first=Ben |title=At the Movies: Plumbing the Depths of 'The Hurt Locker' |date=March 5, 2010 |work=Visual Thesaurus |accessdate=2010-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boal defended himself to the press, saying &quot;the film is a work of fiction inspired by many people's stories.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;usaclaim&quot; /&gt; He said he talked to more than 100 soldiers during his research.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE6220HO20100304 |title=U.S. Bomb Expert Says ''Hurt Locker'' Stole His Story |last=Woodall |first=Bernie |date=March 4, 2010 |work=Reuters |accessdate=2010-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jody Simon, a Los Angeles-based entertainment lawyer, noted that &quot;soldiers don't have privacy&quot;, and that when the military embedded Boal they gave him full permission to use his observations as he saw fit. Summit Entertainment, the producers of the film, said in early March that they hoped for a quick resolution to the suit.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaclaim&quot; /&gt; In the December 8, 2011, issue of ''The Hollywood Reporter'', it was announced that Master Sergeant Sarver's lawsuit was thrown out by the court, and a federal judge ordered him to pay more than $180,000 in attorney fees.&lt;ref&gt;Belloni, Matthew (December 8, 2011) [http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr-esq/hurt-locker-lawsuit-jeremy-renner-jeffrey-sarver-271605 &quot;Iraq War Vet Ordered to Pay $187,000 in Failed Lawsuit Against 'Hurt Locker' Producers&quot;], ''The Hollywood Reporter''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Copyright infringement lawsuit===
On May 12, 2010, [[Voltage Pictures]], the production company behind ''The Hurt Locker'', announced that it would attempt to sue &quot;potentially tens of thousands&quot; of online computer users who downloaded unlicensed copies of the film using the [[BitTorrent]] and [[Peer-to-peer|P2P]] networks. It would be the largest lawsuit of its kind.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tomshardware.com/news/BitTorrent-Pirate-Bay-Comcast-Time-Warner-Verizon,10415.html |first=Jane |last=McEntegart |date=May 13, 2010 |title=Hurt Locker Producers Suing Torrent Downloaders |publisher=Tom's Hardware US |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-31001_3-20004860-261.html |first=Greg |last=Sandoval |date=May 12, 2010 |title='Hurt Locker' producers follow RIAA footsteps |publisher=Cnet News |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 28, 2010, it filed a complaint against 5,000 unidentified BitTorrent users in the United States District Court for the District of Columbia; Voltage announced its intention to demand $1,500 from each defendant to release him or her from the suit.&lt;ref name=&quot;hreporter-suit-filed&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://thresq.hollywoodreporter.com/2010/05/hurt-locker-pirates-lawsuit.html |title='Hurt Locker' producer files massive antipiracy lawsuit |last=Gardner |first=Eriq |date=May 28, 2010 |work=The Hollywood Reporter |publisher=e5 Global Media |accessdate=2010-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several people, however, have refused to settle with the studio.&lt;ref&gt;Sandoval, Greg. [http://news.cnet.com/8301-31001_3-20020260-261.html &quot;Accused pirates to indie filmmakers: Sue us&quot;] Cnet News.&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Copyright Group (USCG) has since dropped all cases against the alleged ''Hurt Locker'' downloaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://torrentfreak.com/us-copyright-group-drops-cases-against-alleged-hurt-locker-pirates-110118/|author=Ernesto|date=March 18, 2011 |title=US Copyright Group Drops Cases Against Alleged Hurt Locker Pirates |publisher=TorrentFreak |accessdate=2011-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 29, 2011, the Federal Court of Canada ordered the three Canadian [[Internet service provider|ISP]]s—[[Bell Canada]], [[Cogeco]], and [[Vidéotron]]—to disclose the names and addresses of the subscribers whose [[IP address]]es were suspected to have downloaded a copy of the film. The ISPs were given two weeks to comply with the order.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.michaelgeist.ca/content/view/5999/|first=Michael|last=Geist|date=September 9, 2011 |title=Hurt Locker File Sharing Suits Come North: Federal Court Orders ISPs to Disclose Subscriber Info |publisher=Michael Geist |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release==

===Festival screenings===
''The Hurt Locker'' had its world premiere at the [[Venice International Film Festival]] on September 4, 2008, and the film received a 10-minute standing ovation at the end of its screening.&lt;ref name=&quot;jolt&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last=Vivarelli | first=Nick | url=http://variety.com/2008/film/news/hurt-locker-gives-venice-a-jolt-1117991591/ | title='Hurt Locker' gives Venice a jolt | journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date=September 4, 2008 |accessdate=2009-08-12 | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; At the festival, the film won the [[SIGNIS]] award,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.signis.net/article.php3?id_article=3389 | title=The Hurt Locker | work=signis.net | publisher=[[SIGNIS]] | accessdate=August 16, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the Arca Cinemagiovani Award (Arca Young Cinema Award) for &quot;Best Film Venezia 65&quot; (chosen by an international youth jury); the Human Rights Film Network Award; and the Venezia Cinema Award known as the &quot;Navicella&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mostradelcinemadivenezia.tv/2008/en/articolo.php?a=23 |title=Collateral Awards&amp;nbsp;– 65th Venezia Film Festival 2008 |work=VeniceWord International Media Services |date=September 6, 2008 |accessdate=2010-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film also screened at the [[2008 Toronto International Film Festival|33rd Annual]] [[Toronto International Film Festival]] on September 8,&lt;ref name=&quot;jolt&quot; /&gt; where it generated &quot;keen interest&quot;, though distributors were reluctant to buy it since previous films about the Iraq War performed poorly at the box office.&lt;ref name=&quot;interest&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 =McClintock | first1 =Pamela | first2 =Anne | last2 = Thompson | url= http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117991965.html | title=Bigelow's 'Locker' sparks interest | journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date=September 9, 2008 | accessdate=2009-08-12 | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Summit Entertainment]] purchased the film for distribution in the United States in what was perceived as &quot;a skittish climate for pic sales&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;summit&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last=Swart | first=Sharon | url= http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117991968.html | title=Summit takes 'Hurt Locker' in U.S. | journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date=September 10, 2008 | accessdate=2009-08-12 | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the rest of 2008, ''The Hurt Locker'' screened at the [[2008 Zurich Film Festival|3rd Zurich Film Festival]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Meza |first=Ed |url=http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=story&amp;id=1061&amp;articleid=VR1117992031&amp;cs=1 |title=Peter Fonda rides to Zurich |journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |date=September 11, 2008 |accessdate=2009-08-16 |ref=harv |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080915031058/http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=story&amp;id=1061&amp;articleid=VR1117992031&amp;cs=1 |archivedate=September 15, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the 37th [[Festival du nouveau cinéma|Festival du Nouveau Cinéma]], the 21st [[Mar del Plata Film Festival]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=Newbery | first=Charles | url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117994960.html?categoryid=1061&amp;cs=1 | title='Hurt Locker' to open Mar Festival | journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date=October 30, 2008 | accessdate=2009-08-16 | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; the 5th [[Dubai International Film Festival]], and the 12th [[Tallinn Black Nights Film Festival]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://2008.poff.ee/?lang=2&amp;id=1915&amp;module=1&amp;todo=film | title=The Hurt Locker | work=poff.ee | publisher=[[Tallinn Black Nights Film Festival]] | accessdate=2009-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, ''The Hurt Locker'' screened at the [[Gothenburg Film Festival|Göteborg International Film Festival]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.goteborgfilmfestival.se/filmfestival/info/en/festivalprogram/chart/?date=2009-01-30 | title=Göteborg International Film Festival 2009 | work=goteborgfilmfestival.se | publisher=[[Gothenburg Film Festival|Göteborg International Film Festival]] |accessdate=2009-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; the 10th ''[[Film Comment]]'' Selects festival,&lt;ref&gt;[[A. O. Scott|Scott, A. O.]] (February 19, 2009). [http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/20/movies/20comm.html &quot;Recovering Treasures From Below the Radar&quot;]. ''[[The New York Times]]''. Retrieved 2009-08-29.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[South by Southwest]] film festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Siegel |first=Tatiana |url=http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=story&amp;id=1061&amp;articleid=VR1117999404&amp;cs=1 |title=SXSW unveils lineup |journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |date=February 1, 2009 |accessdate=2009-08-29 |ref=harv |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090414151948/http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=story&amp;id=1061&amp;articleid=VR1117999404&amp;cs=1 |archivedate=April 14, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the closing night film at [[Maryland Film Festival]] 2009, with Bigelow presenting. It had a centerpiece screening at the 3rd AFI Dallas International Film Festival, where director Kathryn Bigelow received the Dallas Star Award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.afidallas.com/daily/index.php/2009/03/afi-dallas-galas-and-star-awards/ | title=AFI DALLAS Galas and Star Awards | work=afidallas.com | publisher=[[American Film Institute]] | date=March 5, 2009 |accessdate=2009-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other 2009 festivals included the Human Rights Nights International Film Festival,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.humanrightsnights.org/html/schedule_item.php?lang=ENG&amp;id=455&amp;url=%2Fhtml%2Fschedule.php%3Flang%3DENG%26cat_id%3D0 | title=The Hurt Locker | work=humanrightsnights.org | publisher=Cineteca di Bologna |accessdate=2009-08-16}} {{Dead link|date=April 2012|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Seattle International Film Festival]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.siff.net/festival/film/detail.aspx?id=28805&amp;FID=123 |title=The Hurt Locker |work=siff.net | publisher=[[Seattle International Film Festival]] |accessdate=2009-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Philadelphia Film Festival]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.phillycinefest.com/film-details.cfm?id=8566 | title=The Hurt Locker | work=phillycinefest.com | publisher=[[Philadelphia Film Festival]] |accessdate=2009-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theatrical run===
''The Hurt Locker'' was first publicly released in Italy by [[Warner Bros.]] on October 10, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;jolt&quot; /&gt;  [[Summit Entertainment]] picked the film up for distribution in the United States after it was shown at the [[Toronto International Film Festival]] for $1.5&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Defies&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-word6-2009aug06,0,2706666.story |work=The Los Angeles Times |title=The Hurt Locker defies the odds |last1=Horn |first1=John |date=August 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
''The Hurt Locker'' was released in the United States on June 26, 2009, with a limited release at four theaters in Los Angeles and New York City.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=McClintock | first=Pamela | url= http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118005300.html | title='Transformers' expected to crash B.O. | journal=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date=June 23, 2009 | accessdate=2009-08-17 | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; Over its first weekend the film grossed $145,352, averaging $36,338 per theater. The following weekend, beginning July 3, the film grossed $131,202 at nine theaters, averaging $14,578 per theater.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=weekend&amp;id=hurtlocker.htm | title=The Hurt Locker (2009)&amp;nbsp;– Weekend Box Office Results |work=[[Box Office Mojo]] |publisher=Amazon.com |accessdate=2009-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
It held the highest per-screen average of any film playing theatrically in the United States for the first two weeks of its release,&lt;ref name=bom/&gt; gradually moving into the top 20 chart with much wider-released, bigger budget studio films.&lt;ref name=&quot;APTop20&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.accesshollywood.com/500-days-of-summer/harry-potter-franchise-shows-no-sign-of-slowing_article_20799 |title='Harry Potter' franchise shows no sign of slowing |date=July 20, 2009 |agency=Associated Press |accessdate=2010-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; It held around number 13 or number 14 on box office charts for an additional four weeks. Summit Entertainment took ''The Hurt Locker'' wider to more than 200 screens on July 24, 2009 and more than 500 screens on July 31, 2009.

The film's final gross was $17,017,811 in the United States and Canada, and $32,212,961 in other countries, bringing its worldwide total to $49,230,772 (less than any other Best Picture winner). It was a success against its budget of $15 million.&lt;ref name=bom/&gt;

According to the ''Los Angeles Times'', ''The Hurt Locker'' performed better than most recent dramas about Middle East conflict.  The film outperformed all other Iraq-war-themed films such as ''[[In the Valley of Elah]]'' (2007), ''[[Stop-Loss (film)|Stop-Loss]]'' (2008) and [[War in Afghanistan (2001–2014)|Afghanistan]]-themed ''[[Lions for Lambs]]'' (2007).&lt;ref name=&quot;Defies&quot; /&gt;

In the United States, ''The Hurt Locker'' is one of only four Best Picture winners (''[[The English Patient (film)|The English Patient]]'', ''[[Amadeus (film)|Amadeus]]'', and ''[[The Artist (film)|The Artist]]'' being the other three) to never enter the weekend box office top 5 since top 10 rankings were first recorded in 1982. It is also one of the only two Best Picture winners on record never to have entered the weekend box office top 10 (''[[The Artist (film)|The Artist]]'' being the other).

''The Hurt Locker'' opened in the top ten in the United Kingdom in 103 theaters, scoring the fourth-highest per-screen average of $3,607, ranking between ''[[G-Force (film)|G-Force]]'' and ''[[G.I. Joe: The Rise of Cobra|G.I. Joe]]'' in overall grosses. The film garnered half a million dollars in its opening weekend in the United Kingdom of August 28 through August 30, 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/intl/uk/?yr=2009&amp;wk=35&amp;p=.htm |title=United Kingdom Box Office, August 28–30, 2009 |work=Box Office Mojo |accessdate=2010-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and grossed over a million dollars in the UK, Japan, Spain, and France through March.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=intl&amp;id=hurtlocker.htm |title=The Hurt Locker (2009)&amp;nbsp;– International Box Office Results |work=[[Box Office Mojo]] |accessdate=2009-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Distribution: Independent film print shortage===
According to an article in the [[Springfield, Illinois]] ''State Journal-Register'', as of August 2009 there was a shortage of film prints of ''The Hurt Locker'', as well as other hit independent films such as ''[[Food, Inc.]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Prints&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sj-r.com/entertainment/x772322502/Brian-Mackey-Declare-your-love-for-indie-films |title= Brian Mackey: Declare your love for indie films. |work=The State Journal-Register |last1=Mackey |first1=Brian |date=August 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Distributors told theater owners that they would have to wait weeks or months past the initial U.S. release date to get the few available prints that were already in distribution. &quot;Sometimes the distributors goof up,&quot; said a film buyer for one theater. &quot;They misjudge how wide they should go.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Prints&quot; /&gt; One theory is that the independent films have a hard time competing for screen space during the summer against blockbuster [[Tent-pole (entertainment)|tent-pole]] films that take up as much as half the screens in any given city, flooding the United States market with thousands of prints. Theater owners have also complained about distributors &quot;bunching too many movies too close together&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prints&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bunching&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1 = McClintock | first1 = Pamela |url= http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118001812.html |title=Theaters deal with glut of new films: Sequels, Tentpoles Crowd Release Schedule |work=Variety |date=March 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also thought that independent film distributors are trying to cut their losses on prints by recycling them.  Given the popularity of some of the films that are &quot;hard to come by&quot;, this strategy may be leaving box office money on the table.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prints&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bunching&quot; /&gt;

===Home media===
{{Anchor|DVD|Video}}
''The Hurt Locker'' was released on DVD and [[Blu-ray Disc|Blu-ray]] in North America on January 12, 2010. This disc includes an added [[audio commentary]] featuring director Kathryn Bigelow, writer Mark Boal, and other members of the production crew; an image gallery of photos from shooting; and a 15-minute [[Press kit|EPK]] featurette highlighting the filming experience in Jordan and the film's production. The UK DVD and Blu-ray has no commentary.

U.S. sales of the DVD topped $30 million by mid-August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2009/HURTL-DVD.php |title=The Hurt Locker&amp;nbsp;– DVD Sales |date=May 30, 2010 |work=The Numbers |publisher=Nash Information Services |accessdate=2010-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and accolades==
{{Anchor|Awards}} 
{{Main|List of accolades received by The Hurt Locker}}
Starting with its initial screening at the 2008 [[Venice International Film Festival]], ''The Hurt Locker'' has earned many awards and honors. It also ranked on more film critics' top 10 lists than any other film of 2009. It was nominated in nine categories at the [[82nd Academy Awards]] and won in six: [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]], [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]], [[Academy Award for Best Writing (Original Screenplay)|Best Original Screenplay]], [[Academy Award for Best Sound Editing|Best Sound Editing]], [[Academy Award for Best Sound|Best Sound Mixing]], and [[Academy Award for Best Film Editing|Best Film Editing]]. It lost the award for [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]] to ''[[Crazy Heart]]'', [[Academy Award for Best Original Score|Best Original Score]] to ''[[Up (2009 film)|Up]]'', and [[Academy Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography]] to ''[[Avatar (2009 film)|Avatar]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oscars2010&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oscars.org/awards/academyawards/legacy/ceremony/82nd-winners.html |title=The 82nd Academy Awards (2010) Nominees and Winners |accessdate=2011-11-22|work=oscars.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bigelow became the first woman to win an Oscar for Best Director,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nj.com/oscar-awards/index.ssf/2010/03/academy_awards_kathryn_bigelow_is_the_first_woman_to_win_an_oscar_for_best_director.html |title=Academy Awards: Kathryn Bigelow is the first woman to win an Oscar for best director |date=March 7, 2010 |author=Venutolo, Anthony |work=nj.com |accessdate=2010-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''The Hurt Locker'' is to date, the lowest-grossing film to win Best Picture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/movies/2010/03/08/2010-03-08_the_hurt_locker_is_lowestgrossing_movie_to_ever_win_best_picture_may_get_postosc.html |title='The Hurt Locker' is lowest-grossing movie to ever win Best Picture, but it may get post-Oscar bump |work=NY Daily News |author=Carter, Nicole |date=March 8, 2010 |accessdate=2010-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kathryn Bigelow was awarded the [[Directors Guild of America Award]] for Outstanding Achievement in Feature Film for the film, the first time a female director has ever won.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAtops&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/movieawards/2010-01-31-bigelow-hurt-locker-directors-guild_N.htm?csp=34 |work=USA Today |title=Kathryn Bigelow tops directors with 'Hurt Locker' |author=Bowles, Scott |date=February 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film won six awards at the BAFTAs held on February 21, 2010, including Best Film and Best Director for Bigelow. ''The Hurt Locker'' was nominated for three [[Golden Globe Award]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;GlobeList&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ca.eonline.com/uberblog/b158059_complete_list_of_2010_golden_globe.html |title=Complete List of 2010 Golden Globe Nominations |date=December 15, 2009 |work=Eonline}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Washington D.C. Area Film Critics Association Award for Best Director]] was given to Kathryn Bigelow, the first time the honor has gone to a woman. The film swept most critics groups awards for Best Director and Best Picture, including Chicago, Boston, and Las Vegas, Los Angeles, New York' film critics group associations. ''The Hurt Locker'' is one of only five films that have won all three major U.S. critics group prizes (LA, NY, NSFC), together with ''[[Goodfellas]]'', ''[[Schindler's List]]'', ''[[L.A. Confidential (film)|L.A. Confidential]]'', and ''[[The Social Network]]''.

The five awards from the [[Boston Society of Film Critics]] were the most by that organization to a single film in the group's 30-year history.&lt;ref name=&quot;BostonSFC&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118012678.html |work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |title='Hurt Locker' tops with Boston critics: Pic takes four other kudos as journos hand out honors |author=Kimmel, Daniel |date=December 13, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2010, the film's producer [[Nicolas Chartier]] emailed a group of Academy Award voters in an attempt to sway them to vote for ''The Hurt Locker'' instead of &quot;a $500M film&quot; (referring to [[Avatar (2009 film)|''Avatar'']]) for the Best Picture award. He later issued a public apology, saying that it was &quot;out of line and not in the spirit of the celebration of cinema that this acknowledgment is&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |first=Pete |last=Hammond |url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/season/2010/02/hurt-letter-plot-thickens-as-producer-offers-mea-culpa-by-pete-hammond.html |title='Hurt Letter' plot thickens after producer offers mea culpa |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |location=Notes on a Season |date=2010-02-25 |accessdate=2010-02-25 |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20100228231328/http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/season/2010/02/hurt-letter-plot-thickens-as-producer-offers-mea-culpa-by-pete-hammond.html |archivedate=February 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences|Academy]] banned him from attending the [[82nd Academy Awards|award ceremony]], the first time the Academy has ever banned an individual nominee.&lt;ref&gt;Zeitchik, Steven (March 3, 2010). [http://articles.latimes.com/2010/mar/03/entertainment/la-et-chartier3-2010mar03 &quot;'Hurt Locker' producer banned from Oscars&quot;]. ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''. Retrieved 2010-04-06.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Iraq}}
* ''[[Nine From Aberdeen]]'', a 2012 book by [[Jeffrey M. Leatherwood]] on the WWII forerunners of EOD, with an afterword by CSM James H. Clifford, military consultant for ''The Hurt Locker''.

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Thomson |first=Patricia |title=Risk and Valor: The Hurt Locker |journal=[[American Cinematographer]] |date=July 2009 |volume=90 |issue=7 |pages=44–50 |url=http://www.patriciathomson.net/PatriciaThomson/AC-Hurt_Locker.html |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite book|last = Barker| first = Martin| year = 2011| title = A 'Toxic Genre': The Iraq War Films| publisher=Pluto Press |location=London | isbn = 978-0745331294 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|hurt locker}}
* {{Official website|http://www.thehurtlocker-movie.com}}
* {{IMDb title|0887912|The Hurt Locker}}
* {{Rotten Tomatoes|hurt_locker}}
* {{Metacritic film|the-hurt-locker}}

{{Kathryn Bigelow}}
{{AcademyAwardBestPicture 2001-2020}}
{{BAFTA Best Film 2001-2020}}
{{Broadcast Film Critics Association Award for Best Film}}
{{Producers Guild of America Award for Best Theatrical Motion Picture}}
{{Satellite Award Best Motion Picture}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hurt Locker}}
[[Category:2008 films]]
[[Category:2000s war films]]
[[Category:American independent films]]
[[Category:American war films]]
[[Category:American action thriller films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:Best Picture Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Films that won the Best Sound Editing Academy Award]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films set in 2004]]
[[Category:Films set in Iraq]]
[[Category:Films shot in British Columbia]]
[[Category:Films shot in Jordan]]
[[Category:Films directed by Kathryn Bigelow]]
[[Category:Films whose director won the Best Directing Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films whose writer won the Best Original Screenplay Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films whose editor won the Best Film Editing Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films that won the Best Sound Mixing Academy Award]]
[[Category:Iraq War films]]
[[Category:Summit Entertainment films]]
[[Category:Warner Bros. films]]
[[Category:Voltage Pictures films]]
[[Category:Lions Gate Entertainment films]]
[[Category:Universal Pictures films]]
[[Category:Film scores by Marco Beltrami]]
[[Category:Best Film BAFTA Award winners]]
[[Category:Films whose director won the Best Direction BAFTA Award]]
[[Category:Films whose writer won the Best Original Screenplay BAFTA Award]]
[[Category:Screenplays by Mark Boal]]</text>
      <sha1>7udquqpyocmoyqiyqj6okywx0bj1fdf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
