<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Holocaust in Albania</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39141908</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741237110</id>
      <parentid>725424784</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-26T06:56:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29102">[[File:Map of Albania during WWII.png|thumb|right|220px|A map of Albania during the Second World War, with territory annexed to the country shown in light yellow.]]
'''The Holocaust in Albania''' consisted of murders, deportations and [[crimes against humanity]] committed against [[Jews]], [[Slavs]], [[Romani people|Roma]] and other minorities in [[Greater Albania]] by German, Italian and Albanian collaborationist forces while the country was under [[Albanian Kingdom (1939–1943)|Italian]] and [[Albanian Kingdom (1943–1944)|German]] occupation during the [[Second World War]]. Throughout the war, nearly 2,000 Jews sought refuge in Albania-proper. Most of these Jewish refugees were treated well by the local [[Albanians|Albanian]] population, despite the fact that the country was occupied first by [[Kingdom of Italy|Fascist Italy]], and then by [[Nazi Germany]]. Albanians, following a traditional custom of hospitality known as {{lang|sq|''[[Besa (Albanian culture)|besa]]''}}, often sheltered Jewish refugees in mountain villages, and transported them to [[Adriatic Sea|Adriatic]] ports from where they fled to Italy. Other Jews joined resistance movements throughout the country.

For the 500 Jews who lived in Albanian-dominated [[Kosovo]], the experience was starkly different and many did not survive the war. With the [[Armistice of Cassibile|surrender of Italy]] in September 1943, German forces occupied Albania, Kosovo and other territories that had been annexed to the country. In 1944, an Albanian ''[[Waffen-SS]]'' division was formed, which arrested and handed over to the Germans a further 281 Jews from Kosovo who were subsequently deported to the [[Bergen-Belsen concentration camp]], where many were killed. In late 1944, German forces were driven out of Albania-proper and [[Communists]] led by [[Enver Hoxha]] came to power in the country. At the same time, Axis forces in the Albanian-annexed regions of Kosovo and western Macedonia were defeated by the [[Yugoslav Partisans]], who subsequently re-incorporated these areas into the newly Communist [[Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]].

Approximately 600 Jews were killed in Albania-proper, and Albanian-annexed Kosovo and western Macedonia during the war. As up to 1,800 Jews were living in Albania-proper at the end of the war, it is estimated that the country emerged from the Second World War with a population of Jews eleven times greater than at the beginning. Most of these subsequently emigrated to Israel, but several hundred remained until the [[fall of Communism]] in the early 1990s before they did the same. In 1995, the [[Albania|Republic of Albania]] was declared [[Righteous Among the Nations]] for the role that dozens of Albanian families played in saving Jewish refugees in the country during the Second World War. As of 2011, 69 Albanians have been recognized as Righteous Among the Nations.

==Background==
According to the census of 1930, 24 [[Jews]] lived in [[Kingdom of Albania (1928–39)|Albania]]. In 1937, the Jewish community, which then numbered nearly 300, was granted official recognition in the country. With the rise of Nazism, a number of German and Austrian Jews took refuge in Albania, and the Albanian embassy in [[Berlin]] continued to issue visas to Jews until the end of 1938, at a time when no other European country was willing to do so.{{sfn|Elsie|2010|p=218}} Prior to the outbreak of the [[Second World War]], most [[Albanians]] had never had contact with Jews because of the small number of them in the country. As a result, [[antisemitism]] was less widespread in Albania than in other countries.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|pp=93–94}} Before the war, most [[History of the Jews in Albania|Albanian Jews]] lived in the town of [[Korçë]], in the southeastern part of the country.{{sfn|Gilbert|2009|p=222}} The Jewish community in Kosovo, part of the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]], numbered approximately 500.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=93}}
[[File:Ahmet-Zogu-1895---1961.jpg|thumb|right|180px|King [[Zog I]] was deposed as ruler of Albania when the country was invaded by Italy in April 1939.]]
The least developed country in Europe, Albania was subjected to [[Kingdom of Italy|Italian]] economic and political influence throughout the 1930s. On 25 March 1939, Italian dictator [[Benito Mussolini]] gave Albanian King [[Zog of Albania|Zog I]] an ultimatum demanding the acceptance of an Italian military [[protectorate]] over Albania.{{sfn|Bideleux|Jeffries|2007|pp=30–31}} When Zog refused to accept, the Italians [[Invasion of Albania|invaded]] on 7 April 1939, and deposed him. Afterwards, they [[Albanian Kingdom (1939–1943)|re-established]] the Albanian state as a protectorate of the Kingdom of Italy,{{sfn|Fischer|1999|pp=21–57}} then installed a [[quisling]] regime headed by the biggest landowner in the country, [[Shefqet Vërlaci]]. An Albanian &quot;national assembly&quot; was established, which quickly voted for the full economic and political union of Albania with the Kingdom of Italy, led by Italian King [[Victor Emmanuel III of Italy|Victor Emmanuel III]].{{sfn|Bideleux|Jeffries|2007|p=31}} Under the direction of viceroy general [[Francesco Jacomoni]], the Italian administration implemented laws that prohibited Jewish immigration to Albania and mandated the deportation of all foreign Jews in the country.{{sfn|Perez|2013|p=26}}

Within a month of the Italian occupation, the [[Albanian Fascist Party]] ({{lang-sq|Partia Fashiste e Shqipërisë}}, or PFSh) was formed.{{sfn|Lemkin|2008|p=102}} It enacted laws that prevented Jews from joining it and excluded them from professions such as education.{{sfn|Frank|2010|p=97}} Composed of ethnic Albanians and [[Italians]] residing in Albania,{{sfn|Fischer|1999|pp=45–46}} the party existed as a branch of the [[Italian Fascist Party]] ({{lang-it|Partito Nazionale Fascista}}, or PNF) and its members were required to swear an oath of loyalty to Mussolini.{{sfn|Lemkin|2008|p=102}} All Albanians serving the Italian occupiers were required to join, and it became the only legal political party in the country.{{sfn|Bideleux|Jeffries|2007|p=31}}

As the war progressed, Italy transformed the Albanian Kingdom into [[Greater Albania]], a protectorate of Italy that included most of Kosovo and a portion of western Macedonia which was detached from Yugoslavia after the [[Invasion of Yugoslavia|Axis powers invaded]] in 1941.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=93}} Kosovo Albanians enthusiastically welcomed the Italian occupation. Although officially under Italian rule, the Albanians in Kosovo controlled the region and were encouraged to open Albanian schools, which had been prohibited under Yugoslav rule.{{sfn|Judah|2002|pp=27–28}} They were also given Albanian citizenship by Italian authorities and allowed to fly the [[Flag of Albania|Albanian flag]].{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=141}} Nevertheless, the Italians kept hundreds of thousands of troops in Albania and surrounding areas. Yugoslav sources indicated that there were approximately 20,000 Italian soldiers and 5,000 Italian police and frontier guards in Kosovo, and 12,000 soldiers and 5,000 police and border guards in the Albanian-annexed portion of Macedonia.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=152}} At the same time, Italian military authorities warned that at least ten hostages would be shot for every Italian soldier killed or wounded in these regions.{{sfn|Rodogno|2006|p=345}}

==Holocaust==
[[File:WannseeList.jpg|thumb|right|200px|A list of European Jews compiled at the [[Wannsee Conference]] in January 1942. Albania is listed  by the Germans as being inhabited by 200 Jews.]]

===1939–43===
After the invasion of Yugoslavia, the Jewish community in Albania grew as Jews from Macedonia and northern Serbia, as well as Jewish refugees from Germany, Austria and Poland, came to Italian-controlled, Albanian-annexed Kosovo and settled in the towns of [[Pristina]], [[Prizren]] and [[Uroševac]].{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=93}} As many as 1,000 refugees arrived, attributed by German sources to a Jewish organization which was responsible for smuggling Jews into the country. The refugees did not experience persecution to the level that Jews were experiencing in German-controlled territories, because the Italians considered them to be of economic importance and &quot;representative of Italian interests abroad&quot;.{{sfn|Rodogno|2006|p=387}} However, the Italians did arrest approximately 150 Jewish refugees and transferred them to the town of [[Berat]] in Albania, where they were given a chance to work to earn money.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=93}} Also arrested were 192 Jews from the Italian-annexed [[Bay of Kotor]] who were transferred to [[Nazi concentration camps]] in Albania on 27 or 28 July 1941, before being transferred to camps located within Italy.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=597}} As many as 2,000 Jews sought refuge in Albania during the war.{{sfn|''Deutsche Welle''|27 December 2012}}{{sfn|''Voice of America''|7 December 2010}}

The local population of Albania was very protective of the Jewish refugees. Many were transported to Albanian ports on the [[Adriatic]] from where they could travel to Italy. Other Jews hid in remote mountain villages, while some joined resistance movements across the country.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=94}} The Albanian treatment of Jews was in accordance with traditional Albanian customs of hospitality and {{lang|sq|''[[Besa (Albanian culture)|besa]]''}} (&quot;word of honour&quot;).{{sfn|''Voice of America''|7 December 2010}} Despite this, instances of cruelty towards Jews did occur in Albania during the war, and on several occasions Jews being smuggled into the country were killed by Albanians who seized their jewellery and money.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=94}}

In January 1942, the Germans estimated at the [[Wannsee Conference]] that Albania was inhabited by 200 Jews.{{sfn|Arad|Gutman|Margaliot|1999|p=254}} That same month, Jews were interned by the Italians at a camp in the town of Pristina.{{sfn|Israeli|2013|p=38}} Although they feared that they would be handed over to the Germans, the Italian commander of the camp promised them that this would never happen. However, on 14 March the Italians blockaded the camp and arrested the Jews who had been detained there. Some were then handed over to German forces and transported to the [[Sajmište concentration camp]] near [[Belgrade]], where they were killed.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=94}} Others, together with [[Serbs]], were taken to the camp in Berat, where they remained until Italy's capitulation.{{sfn|Israeli|2013|p=38}} It is estimated that as many as 500 Jews were interned in the camps in Berat, [[Krujë]] and [[Kavajë]] during the Italian occupation.{{sfn|Perez|2013|p=27}}

===1943–45===
When Italy [[Armistice of Cassibile|surrendered]] to the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] in September 1943, all concentration camps in Albania were dissolved.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=94}} Shortly after, the Germans invaded and [[Albanian Kingdom (1943–1944)|occupied]] Albania, and most Italian soldiers in the country surrendered to the Germans.{{sfn|Vickers|1999|p=152}} German forces then began to target for extermination all Jews living in Albania and the Albanian-dominated regions of occupied Yugoslavia.{{sfn|Mojzes|2009|p=94}} The Jewish community in western [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]], which had remained untouched under Italian occupation, was targeted and several groups of Jews were dispatched to extermination camps. Their property and belongings were later taken by many organizations, institutions and private individuals.{{sfn|Laqueur|Baumel|2001|p=712}}

The Germans arranged for Albania's administration to be reorganized shortly after occupying the country. On 15 September, the Albanian National Committee was established under German sponsorship. It governed until a Regency Council was established and recognized by Germany as the official government of the country on 3 November 1943. [[Xhafer Deva]], a Kosovo Albanian ally of the Germans in the region, was then appointed the [[Ministry of Interior Affairs (Albania)|Minister of Interior]] of Albania.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=152}} Deva later founded the Nazi-aligned [[Second League of Prizren]] in Kosovo, which declared ''[[jihad]]'' (holy war) against [[Slavs]], Gypsies and Jews and sought to create an ethnically cleansed Greater Albania. The League had the backing of [[Haj Amin al-Husseini]], the [[Mufti of Jerusalem]]. A leading supporter of the Nazis, he pressed for the implementation of the [[Final Solution]].{{sfn|Frank|2010|p=97}} With a new administration in place, the Germans demanded that Albanian authorities provide them with lists of Jews to be deported.{{sfn|Green|2 April 2013}} However, local authorities did not comply and even provided Jewish families with forged documents.{{sfn|''Deutsche Welle''|27 December 2012}} The situation in Albanian-dominated Kosovo was quite different.{{sfn|Elsie|2010|p=219}} There, Deva began recruiting Kosovo Albanians to join the ''[[Waffen-SS]]''.{{sfn|Fischer|1999|p=215}} The [[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)|21st ''Waffen'' Mountain Division of the SS ''Skanderbeg'' (1st Albanian)]] was formed on 1 May 1944.{{sfn|Nafziger|1992|p=21}} Composed of ethnic Albanians, it was named after Albanian national hero [[George Kastrioti Skanderbeg]], who fought the Ottoman Turks in the 15th century.{{sfn|Judah|2002|p=28}} Members took a religious oath using the [[Quran]], pledging &quot;''jihad'' against unbelievers&quot;.{{sfn|Simeunović|Dolnik|2013|p=94}} The division had a strength of 6,500 men at the time of its creation{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=100}} and was better known for murdering, raping, and looting in predominantly Serbian areas than for participating in combat operations on behalf of the German war effort.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|pp=94–95}} On 14 May,{{sfn|Perez|2013|p=27}} members of the division raided Jewish homes in Pristina, arrested 281 native and foreign Jews, then handed them over to the Germans.{{sfn|Judah|2002|p=29}}{{sfn|Fischer|1999|p=187}}{{sfn|Elsie|2010|p=219}} On 23 June, 249 of these were taken to the [[Bergen-Belsen concentration camp|Bergen-Belsen]] concentration camp, where many were killed.{{sfn|Perez|2013|pp=27–28}} With the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] victory in the Balkans imminent, Deva and his men attempted to purchase weapons from withdrawing German soldiers in order to organize a &quot;final solution&quot; of the Slavic population of Kosovo. Nothing came of this as the powerful [[Yugoslav Partisans]] prevented any large-scale [[ethnic cleansing]] of Slavs from occurring.{{sfn|Yeomans|2006|p=31}}

Kosovo Albanians were generally less hospitable to Jews than their counterparts in Albania. Due to their historical experiences with Serbs and the [[Ottoman Empire]], they tended to be more unfriendly towards non-Albanians. Many enthusiastically supported the Germans as a result.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=94}} Claims have been made that Kosovo Albanians protected Jews after German forces took over territories that Italian authorities had controlled during the war, but the protection that Jews received in Kosovo in the early years of the war was due more to the Italian authorities than to the local Albanian population.{{sfn|Mojzes|2011|p=94}} It is estimated that 210 Jews from Kosovo perished during the war.{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=83}} An official Yugoslav state report published in 1964 recorded 74 Jewish wartime fatalities in the region.{{sfn|Frank|2010|pp=97–98}} Approximately 600 Jews were killed in Albania, Kosovo and other Albanian-controlled territories during the war.{{sfn|Green|2 April 2013}} A somewhat greater number, as well as several hundred refugees, hid and survived with the assistance of the local Albanian population.{{sfn|Laqueur|Baumel|2001|p=1}}

==Aftermath==
[[File:HODŽA druhá míza.jpg|thumb|right|Albanian Partisan leader [[Enver Hoxha]] turned Albania into a Communist country after the defeat of German forces in 1944. His rule saw widespread religious repression. As a result, several hundred Jews who remained in Albania after the Second World War emigrated to Israel when the country's Communist regime collapsed in the early 1990s.]]
From October to November 1944, the [[Yugoslav Partisans]], supported by both the Western Allies and the [[Soviet Union]], and assisted by the forces of the newly anti-fascist Bulgarian regime and two brigades of Albanian partisans, retook the region of Kosovo as the Germans withdrew.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=156}} The area was then reincorporated into the [[Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia]].{{sfn|Frank|2010|p=97}} With defeat guaranteed, the withdrawing Germans helped Albanian collaborators escape the country as [[Communist]] forces drew closer. However, many failed to escape and were executed by the Communists upon capture.{{sfn|Fischer|1999|p=237}} On 28 November 1944, Communist forces under [[Enver Hoxha]] emerged victorious in Albania.{{sfn|Elsie|2010|p=194}} Hoxha subsequently implemented a [[totalitarian]] [[Stalinism|Stalinist]] government which banned all religions in the country.{{sfn|Plaut|1996|p=180}}

It is estimated that there were 1,800 Jews in Albania at the end of the Second World War,{{sfn|Fischer|1999|p=187}} eleven times more than the number of Jews living in the country at the beginning of the war.{{sfn|Elsie|2010|p=219}} The Jewish community in Kosovo never fully recovered from the war.{{sfn|Frank|2010|pp=99}} Few Jews remained in the region and many emigrated to [[Israel]] during the Communist period.{{sfn|Frank|2010|p=97}} Similarly, most Jews in Albania decided to emigrate following the Communist takeover, but approximately 300 remained in the country until the early 1990s.{{sfn|Ehrlich|2009|p=945}} The official Albanian census of April 1989 recorded 73 Jews living in the country.{{sfn|Elsie|2010|p=219}} With the [[fall of Communism]], Albania eased restrictions on religion and foreign travel, which resulted in virtually the entire Jewish community of the country emigrating to Israel. From December 1990 to June 1991, 350 Albanian Jews were airlifted from Albania to Israel in what was codenamed &quot;Operation Flying Carpet&quot;.{{sfn|Plaut|1996|p=181}} Most of the 60 remaining Jews in the country left in 1997, after an outbreak of political violence.{{sfn|Elsie|2010|p=194}}

The [[Republic of Albania]] was recognized as [[Righteous Among the Nations]] at the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]] in [[Washington, D.C.]] on 2 February 1995.{{sfn|Ehrlich|2009|p=945}} As of 2011, 69 Albanians have been recognized by [[Yad Vashem]] as Righteous Among the Nations for their role in helping Jews in Albania survive the [[Holocaust]].{{sfn|Green|2 April 2013}} The only public space in Albania dedicated to the Holocaust is a small display at the [[National Historical Museum (Albania)|National Historical Museum]] in Tirana. Consisting of photographs, texts, maps, and wartime documents, it was opened on 29 November 2004.{{sfn|Perez|2013|pp=40–41}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
;Books
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Arad
  | first1 = Yitsḥaḳ
  | last2 = Gutman
  | first2 = Yisrael
  | last3 = Margaliot
  | first3 = Abraham
  | year = 1999
  | title = Documents on the Holocaust: Selected Sources on the Destruction of the Jews of Germany and Austria, Poland, and the Soviet Union
  | publisher = University of Nebraska Press
  | location = [[Lincoln, Nebraska]]
  | isbn = 978-0-8032-5937-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=4_4PlAy7kdwC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Bideleux
  | last2 = Jeffries
  | first1 = Robert
  | first2 = Ian
  | year = 2007
  | title = The Balkans: A Post-Communist History
  | publisher = Routledge
  | location = [[London]]
  | isbn = 978-0-203-96911-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=5jrHOKsU9pEC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Cohen
  | first = Philip J.
  | authorlink = Philip J. Cohen
  | year = 1996
  | title = Serbia's Secret War: Propaganda and the Deceit of History
  | publisher = Texas A&amp;M University Press
  | location = [[College Station, Texas]]
  | isbn = 978-0-89096-760-7
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Fz1PW_wnHYMC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Ehrlich
  | first = Mark Avrum
  | year = 2009
  | title = Encyclopedia of the Jewish Diaspora: Origins, Experiences and Culture
  | volume = 1
  | publisher = ABC-CLIO
  | location = [[Santa Barbara, California]]
  | isbn = 978-1-85109-874-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=NoPZu79hqaEC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last =  Elsie
  | first = Robert
  | authorlink = Robert Elsie
  | year = 2010
  | title = Historical Dictionary of Albania
  | publisher = Scarecrow Press
  | location = [[Lanham, Maryland]]
  | isbn = 978-0-8108-7380-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=haFlGXIg8uoC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fischer
  | first = Bernd Jürgen
  | authorlink = Bernd Jürgen Fischer
  | year = 1999
  | title = Albania at War, 1939–1945
  | publisher = Purdue Research Foundation
  | location = [[West Lafayette, Indiana]]
  | isbn = 1-55753-141-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=vTZnAAAAMAAJ
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Frank
  | first = Chaim
  | editor1-last = Petersen
  | editor1-first = Hans-Christian
  | editor2-last = Salzborn
  | editor2-first = Samuel
  | year = 2010
  | title = Antisemitism in Eastern Europe: History and Present in Comparison
  | publisher = Peter Lang
  | location = [[Bern]]
  | isbn = 978-3-631-59828-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=k6sqlTGHpsAC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Gilbert
  | first = Martin
  | authorlink = Martin Gilbert
  | year = 2009
  | title = The Routledge Atlas of the Holocaust
  | publisher= Routledge
  | location = [[London]]
  | isbn = 0-415-48481-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=GaAtH_yKTHAC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Israeli
  | first = Raphael
  | authorlink = Raphael Israeli
  | year = 2013
  | title = The Death Camps of Croatia: Visions and Revisions, 1941–1945
  | publisher = Transaction Publishers
  | location = [[New Brunswick, New Jersey]]
  | isbn = 978-1-4128-4975-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=M66fG2bhi1AC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Judah
  | first = Tim
  | authorlink = Tim Judah
  | year = 2002
  | title = Kosovo: War and Revenge
  | publisher = Yale University Press
  | location = [[New Haven, Connecticut]]
  | isbn = 978-0-300-09725-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=sVf1na3FN_UC
  | ref=harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Laqueur
  | last2 = Baumel
  | first1 = Walter Ze'ev
  | first2 = Judith Tydor
  | year = 2001
  | title= The Holocaust Encyclopedia
  | publisher = [[Yale University Press]]
  | location = New Haven, Connecticut
  | isbn = 978-0-300-08432-0
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=nPbr0XzlTzcC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | first = Raphael
  | last = Lemkin
  | authorlink = Raphael Lemkin
  | year = 2008
  | title = Axis Rule in Occupied Europe
  | publisher = The Lawbook Exchange
  | location = [[Clark, New Jersey]]
  | isbn = 978-1-58477-901-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=y0in2wOY-W0C
  | ref= harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Mojzes
  | first = Paul
  | editor1-last = Jacobs
  | editor1-first = Steven L.
  | year = 2009
  | title = Confronting Genocide: Judaism, Christianity, Islam
  | publisher = Lexington Books
  | location = [[Lanham, Maryland]]
  | isbn = 978-0-7391-3590-7
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=H2UdOMWoQ2MC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last= Mojzes
  | first = Paul
  | year = 2011
  | title = Balkan Genocides: Holocaust and Ethnic Cleansing in the 20th Century
  | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield
  | location = [[Lanham, Maryland]]
  | isbn = 978-1-4422-0665-6
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=KwW2O7v7CUcC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Perez
  | first = Daniel
  | editor1-last = Himka
  | editor1-first = John-Paul
  | editor2-last = Michlic
  | editor2-first = Joanna Beata
  | year = 2013
  | title = Bringing the Dark Past to Light: The Reception of the Holocaust in Postcommunist Europe
  | publisher = Nebraska University Press
  | location = [[Lincoln, Nebraska]]
  | isbn = 978-0-8032-4647-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Ya7RMPN9-ZsC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Plaut
  | first = Joshua Eli
  | year = 1996
  | title = Greek Jewry in the Twentieth Century, 1913–1983: Patterns of Jewish Survival in the Greek Provinces Before and After the Holocaust
  | publisher = Associated University Presses
  | location = [[Cranbury, New Jersey]]
  | isbn = 978-0-8386-3911-5
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=VpWK_N3qnNQC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Simeunović
  | first1 = Dragan
  | last2 = Dolnik
  | first2 = Adam
  | editor1-last = Cross
  | editor1-first = Sharyl
  | editor2-last = Kentera
  | editor2-first = Savo
  | editor3-last = Nation
  | editor3-first = R. Craig
  | editor4-last = Vukadinović
  | editor4-first = Radovan
  
  | year = 2013
  | title = Shaping South East Europe's Security Community for the Twenty-First Century: Trust, Partnership, Integration
  | chapter = Security Threats of Violent Islamist Extremism
  | publisher = Palgrave Macmillan
  | location = [[Basingstoke]], England
  | isbn = 978-1-137-01020-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=X6MOMYYeULUC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Ramet
  | first = Sabrina P.
  | year = 2006
  | title = The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building and Legitimation, 1918–2005
  | publisher = Indiana University Press
  | location = [[Bloomington, Indiana]]
  | isbn = 978-0-253-34656-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Rodogno
  | first = Davide
  | year = 2006
  | title = Fascism's European Empire: Italian Occupation During the Second World War
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | location = [[Cambridge]]
  | isbn = 978-0-521-84515-1
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ZcUNELPsQQsC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tomasevich
  | first = Jozo
  | authorlink = Jozo Tomasevich
  | year = 2001
  | title = War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: Occupation and Collaboration
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = [[San Francisco, California]]
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-3615-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=fqUSGevFe5MC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Vickers
  | first = Miranda
  | year = 1999
  | title = The Albanians: A Modern History
  | publisher = I.B. Tauris
  | location = [[London]]
  | isbn = 978-1-86064-541-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=IzI0uOZ2j6gC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Yeomans
  | first = Rory
  | editor1-last = Blamires
  | editor1-first = Cyprian
  | editor2-last = Jackson
  | editor2-first = Paul
  | year = 2006
  | title = World Fascism: A Historical Encyclopedia
  | chapter = Albania
  | volume = 1
  | publisher = ABC-CLIO
  | location = [[Santa Barbara, California]]
  | isbn =  978-1-57607-940-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=nvD2rZSVau4C
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{refend|2}}

;Journals
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal
| last = Nafziger
| first = George
| year   = 1992
| title = Organizational History of the German SS Formations 1939–1945
| publisher  = Combined Arms Research Library Digital Library
| url = http://usacac.army.mil/cac2/CGSC/CARL/nafziger/939GXWA.pdf
| accessdate = 7 March 2014
| ref = harv
| postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}
}}
{{refend}}

;Websites
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{cite news
  | newspaper = [[Deutsche Welle]]
  | date = 27 December 2012
  | title = Albanians saved Jews from deportation in WWII
  | url = http://www.dw.de/albanians-saved-jews-from-deportation-in-wwii/a-16481404
  | ref = {{sfnRef|''Deutsche Welle''|27 December 2012}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Green
  | first= David B.
  | date= 2 April 2013
  | title= Jewish Albanians Gain a Foothold
  | newspaper = [[Haaretz]]
  | url = http://www.haaretz.com/news/features/this-day-in-jewish-history/this-day-in-jewish-history-jewish-albanians-gain-a-foothold.premium-1.512974
  | ref = {{SfnRef|Green|2 April 2013}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | newspaper = [[Voice of America]]
  | date = 7 December 2010
  | title = Muslims Save Jews in Untold WWll Story
  | url = http://www.voanews.com/content/muslims-save-jews-in-untold-wwll-story-111517964/132021.html
  | ref = {{sfnRef|''Voice of America''|7 December 2010}}
  }}
{{refend|2}}

==External links==
* [https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/vjw/albania.html Albania] the [[Jewish Virtual Library]]

{{good article}}
{{The Holocaust|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Holocaust in Albania, The}}
[[Category:Jewish Albanian history|Holocaust]]
[[Category:The Holocaust by country|Albania]]</text>
      <sha1>sh5iqazt7dxje0wd7kjn7u3io86kyx8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
