<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tube Alloys</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>698908</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750465156</id>
      <parentid>750465005</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T22:28:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hawkeye7</username>
        <id>302229</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Oliphant's visit to the United States */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="68570">{{good article}}
{{use British English|date=May 2016}}
[[File:Winston Churchill with his scientific advisor Lord Cherwell (extreme left), Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles Portal and Admiral of the Fleet Sir Dudley Pound, watching a display of anti-aircraft gunnery, June 1941 H10306.jpg|thumb|right|[[Frederick Lindemann, 1st Viscount Cherwell|Lord Cherwell]], scientific advisor to the Prime Minister, Air Chief Marshal Sir [[Charles Portal]], Admiral of the Fleet Sir [[Dudley Pound]] and [[Winston Churchill]] in June 1941]]
'''Tube Alloys''' was a codename of the clandestine [[research and development]] programme, authorised by the United Kingdom, with participation from Canada, to develop [[nuclear weapons]] during the [[Second World War]]. Starting before the [[Manhattan Project]] in the United States, the British efforts were kept [[Classified information in the United Kingdom|classified]] and as such had to be referred to by code even within the highest circles of government.

The possibility of nuclear weapons was acknowledged early in the war. At the [[University of Birmingham]], [[Rudolf Peierls]] and [[Otto Frisch]] co-wrote [[Frisch–Peierls memorandum|a memorandum]] explaining that a small mass of pure [[uranium-235]] could be used to produce a chain reaction in a bomb with the power of thousands of tons of [[TNT]]. This led to the formation of the [[MAUD Committee]], which called for an all-out effort to develop nuclear weapons. [[Wallace Akers]], who oversaw the project, chose the deliberately misleading name &quot;Tube Alloys&quot;. His Tube Alloys Directorate was part of the [[Department of Scientific and Industrial Research (United Kingdom)|Department of Scientific and Industrial Research]].

The Tube Alloys programme in Britain and Canada was the first nuclear weapons project. Due to the high costs, and the fact that Britain was fighting a war within bombing range of its enemies, Tube Alloys was ultimately subsumed into the  Manhattan Project. Despite [[Quebec Agreement|reaching an agreement]] with the United States to share nuclear weapons technology, and to refrain from using it against each other, or against other countries without mutual consent, the details were not completely provided to the United Kingdom. The [[Soviet Union]] gained valuable information through its [[atomic spies]], who had infiltrated both the British and American projects.

The United States terminated cooperation after the war ended. This prompted the United Kingdom to (re)launch its own project. Production facilities were established and British scientists continued their work under the auspices of an independent British programme. Finally in 1952, Britain performed a [[nuclear test]] under codename [[Operation Hurricane|Operation ''Hurricane'']]. In 1958, after British demonstration of a two-stage [[thermonuclear bomb]], the United Kingdom and the United States signed [[US-UK Mutual Defence Agreement|an agreement]] that resulted in a resumption of Britain's nuclear [[special relationship]] with the United States.

==Origins==
[[File:William Penney, Otto Frisch, Rudolf Peierls and John Cockroft.jpg|thumb|right|[[William Penney]], [[Otto Frisch]], [[Rudolf Peierls]] and [[John Cockcroft]] receive the [[Medal of Freedom]] in May 1947]]

=== Discovery of fission ===
In December 1938, [[Otto Hahn]] and [[Fritz Strassmann]] conducted experiments in Hahn's laboratory in [[Berlin-Dahlem]] that involved bombarding [[uranium]] with slowed [[neutron]]s.{{sfn|Clark|1961|p=5}} They discovered that [[barium]] had been produced, and therefore that the uranium [[atomic nucleus|nucleus]] had been split.{{sfn|Clark|1961|p=11}} Atoms had been split before, by [[John Cockcroft]] and [[Ernest Walton]] at the [[Cavendish Laboratory]] at the [[University of Cambridge]] in  1932; but they had split [[lithium]] atoms with accelerated [[proton]]s.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=17–18}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Experiments with High Velocity Positive Ions. (I) Further Developments in the Method of Obtaining High Velocity Positive Ions |first=J. D. |last=Cockcroft |authorlink=John Cockcroft | first2=E. T. S. |last2=Walton |authorlink2=Ernest Walton |journal=[[Proceedings of the Royal Society]] of London A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences |issn=1364-5021  |date=1 June 1932 |volume=136 |issue=830 |pp=619–630 |doi=10.1098/rspa.1932.0107 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Experiments with High Velocity Positive Ions. (II) The Disintegration of Elements by High Velocity Protons |first=J. D. |last=Cockcroft |authorlink=John Cockcroft | first2=E. T. S. |last2=Walton |authorlink2=Ernest Walton |journal=[[Proceedings of the Royal Society]] of London A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences |issn=1364-5021  |date=1 July 1932 |volume=137 |issue=831 |pp=229–242 |doi=10.1098/rspa.1932.0133  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The neutron had been discovered by [[James Chadwick]] at Cavendish only in 1932.{{sfn|Clark|1961|p=9}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Chadwick |first1=James |authorlink=James Chadwick |year=1932 |title=Possible Existence of a Neutron |url=http://web.mit.edu/22.54/resources/Chadwick.pdf |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |volume=129 |issue=3252 |page=312 |bibcode=1932Natur.129Q.312C |doi=10.1038/129312a0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Experiments with bombardment of elements by slow neutrons had always produced heavier [[Chemical element|elements]] and [[isotope]]s.{{sfn|Clark|1961|p=11}} Hahn wrote to colleague [[Lise Meitner]], who with her nephew [[Otto Frisch]] developed a theoretical justification for the process based on [[Niels Bohr]]'s [[liquid drop model]] of the atom, which they published in ''[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]'' in 1939.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Meitner | first1 = L. | authorlink1 = Lise Meitner| last2 = Frisch | first2 = O. R. | authorlink2 = Otto Robert Frisch| doi = 10.1038/143239a0 | title = Disintegration of Uranium by Neutrons: A New Type of Nuclear Reaction | journal = Nature | volume = 143 | issue = 3615 | pages = 239–240 | year = 1939 |bibcode = 1939Natur.143..239M }}&lt;/ref&gt; This phenomenon was a new type of nuclear disintegration and was radioactively more powerful than ever seen before. Frisch and Meitner calculated this energy released by each disintegration to be approximately 200,000,000 [[electron volt]]s. By analogy with the [[Fission (biology)|division of biological cells]], they named this process ''[[nuclear fission|fission]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Zimmerman |first1=David |title=The Tizard Mission and the Development of the Atomic Bomb |journal=War in History |date=1995 |volume=2 |issue=3 |pages=259–273 |doi=10.1177/096834459500200302}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Paris Group===
This was followed up by a group of scientists at the [[Collège de France]] in Paris: [[Frédéric Joliot-Curie]], [[Hans von Halban]], [[Lew Kowarski]], and [[Francis Perrin]]. In February 1939, the Paris Group showed that when fission occurs in uranium, two or three extra neutrons are given off. This important observation suggested that a self-sustaining [[nuclear chain reaction]] might be possible.{{sfn|Clark|1961|pp=18–21}} It was immediately apparent to many scientists that, in theory, an extremely powerful explosive could be created, although most thought a practical bomb was an impossibility.{{sfn|Clark|1961|pp=25–29}} The term &quot;[[atomic bomb]]&quot; was already familiar to the British public through the writings of [[H. G. Wells]], in his 1913 novel ''[[The World Set Free]]''.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=15–24}}

Perrin defined a [[critical mass]] of uranium to be the smallest amount that could sustain a chain reaction.{{sfn|Clark|1961|p=42}} The neutrons used to cause fission in uranium are considered slow neutrons, but when neutrons are released during a fission reaction they are released as fast neutrons which have much more speed and energy. Thus, in order to create a sustained chain reaction, there existed a need for a [[neutron moderator]] to contain and slow the fast neutrons until they reached a usable energy level.{{sfn|Gowing|1974|pp=264–263}} The [[College de France]] found that both water and [[graphite]] could be used as acceptable moderators.{{sfn|Clark|1961|pp=21–22}}

Early in 1940, the Paris Group decided on theoretical grounds that [[heavy water]] would be an ideal moderator for how they intended to use it. They asked the French Minister of Armaments to obtain as much heavy water as possible from the only source, the large [[Norsk Hydro]] [[hydroelectric station]] at [[Vemork]] in Norway. The French then discovered that Germany had already offered to purchase the entire stock of Norwegian heavy water, indicating that Germany might also be researching an atomic bomb. The French told the Norwegian government of the possible military significance of heavy water.{{sfn|Clark|1961|pp=68–73}}

Norway gave the entire stock, {{convert|187|l|impgal usgal}}, to a French Secret Service agent, who secretly brought it to France, just before [[Operation Weserübung|Germany invaded Norway]] in April 1940. On 19 June 1940, following the [[Battle of France|German invasion of France]], it was shipped to England by the [[Charles Howard, 20th Earl of Suffolk|Earl of Suffolk]] and Major Ardale Golding, aboard the steamer {{SS|Broompark|1939|2}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cachalots.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/The-Suffolk-Golding-Mission-A-Considerable-Service..pdf |first=Roy |last=Martin |title=The Suffolk Golding Mission, A Considerable Service |accessdate=3 May 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The heavy water, valued at £22,000,{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=52}} was initially kept at [[HM Prison Wormwood Scrubs]], but was subsequently secretly stored in the library at [[Windsor Castle]].{{sfn|Owen|2010|p=69}}{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=50}} The Paris Group moved to Cambridge, with the exception of Joliot-Curie, who remained in France and became active in the [[French Resistance]].{{sfn|Clark|1961|pp=95–103}}

===Frisch–Peierls memorandum ===
{{main|Frisch–Peierls memorandum}}
In Britain, a number of scientists considered whether an atomic bomb was practical. At the [[University of Liverpool]], Chadwick and the Polish refugee scientist [[Joseph Rotblat]] tackled the problem, but their calculations were inconclusive.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013||pp=123–125}} At the [[University of Cambridge]], [[Nobel Prize in Physics]] laureates [[George Paget Thomson]] and [[William Lawrence Bragg]] wanted the government to take urgent action to acquire [[uranium ore]]. The main source of this was the [[Belgian Congo]], and they were worried that it could fall into German hands. Unsure as to how to go about this, they spoke to Sir [[William Spens]], the  [[Master (college)|master]] of [[Corpus Christi College, Cambridge]]. In April 1939 he approached Sir [[Kenneth Pickthorn]], the local [[Member of Parliament]], who took their concerns to the Secretary of the [[Committee for Imperial Defence]], [[Major-General (United Kingdom)|Major General]] [[Hastings Ismay, 1st Baron Ismay|Hastings Ismay]]. Ismay in turn asked Sir [[Henry Tizard]] for an opinion. Like many scientists, Tizard was sceptical of the likelihood of an atomic bomb being developed, reckoning the odds against success at 100,000 to 1.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=34–36}}

[[File:Poynting Physics building 3.jpg|thumb|left|Poynting (physics) Building at the [[University of Birmingham]]]]
Even at such long odds, the danger was sufficiently great to be taken seriously. [[Ernle Chatfield, 1st Baron Chatfield|Lord Chartfield]], 
[[Minister for Coordination of Defence]] checked with the [[HM Treasury|Treasury]] and [[Foreign Office]], and found that the Belgian Congo uranium was owned by the ''[[Union Minière du Haut Katanga]]'' company, whose British vice president, [[Lord Stonehaven]], who arranged a meeting with the president of the company, [[Edgar Sengier]]. Since ''Union Minière '' management were friendly towards Britain, it was not considered worthwhile to immediately acquire the uranium, but Tizard's [[Committee on the Scientific Survey of Air Defence]] was directed to continue the research into the feasibility of atomic bombs.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=34–36}} Thomson, at Imperial College London, and [[Mark Oliphant]], an Australian physicist at the [[University of Birmingham]], were each tasked with carrying out a series of experiments on uranium. By February 1940, Thomson's team had failed to create a chain reaction in natural uranium, and he had decided that it was not worth pursuing.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=37–39}}

But at Birmingham, Oliphant's team had reached a strikingly different conclusion. Oliphant had delegated the task to two German refugee scientists, [[Rudolf Peierls]] and Otto Frisch, who could not work on Oliphant's [[radar]] project because they were [[enemy alien]]s and therefore lacked the necessary security clearance.{{sfn|Szasz|1992|pp=3–5}} Francis Perrin had calculated the critical mass of uranium to be about {{convert|40|t}}. He reckoned that if a [[Neutron reflector]] were placed around it, this might be reduced to {{convert|12|t}}. Peierls attempted to simplify the problem by using the fast neutrons produced by fission, thus omitting consideration of moderator. He too calculated the critical mass of a sphere of uranium in a theoretical paper written in 1939 to be &quot;of the order of tons&quot;.{{sfn|Rhodes|1986|p=321}}

Peierls knew the importance of the size of the [[critical mass]] that would allow a chain reaction to take place and its practical significance. In the interior of a critical mass sphere, neutrons are being spontaneously produced by the fissionable material.  A very small portion of these neutrons are colliding with other nuclei, while a larger portion of the neutrons are escaping through the surface of the sphere. Peierls worked at calculating the equilibrium of the system, where the number of neutrons being produced equalled the number of neutrons escaping the mass.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bernstein |first=Jeremy |authorlink=Jeremy Bernstein |date=1 May 2011 |title=A Memorandum that Changed the World |url=http://scitation.aip.org/content/aapt/journal/ajp/79/5/10.1119/1.3533426 |journal=American Journal of Physics |volume=79 |issue=5 |pages=441–446 |doi=10.1119/1.3533426 |issn=0002-9505}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However Niels Bohr had theorised that the rare [[uranium-235]] isotope, which makes up only about 0.7% of natural uranium,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernstein&quot; /&gt; was primarily responsible for fission with fast neutrons, although this was not yet universally accepted.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=102–103}} Frisch and Peierls were thus able to revise their initial estimate of critical mass needed for nuclear fission in uranium to be substantially less than previously assumed. They estimated a metallic sphere of uranium-235 with a radius of {{convert|2.1|cm}} could suffice. This amount resembled approximately {{convert|1|kg}} of uranium-235.{{sfn|Peierls||2007|p=690}} These results led to the [[Frisch–Peierls memorandum]], which was the initial step in the development of the nuclear arms program in Britain. This marked the beginning of an aggressive approach towards uranium enrichment and the development of an atomic bomb. They now began to investigate processes by which they could successfully separate the uranium isotope.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernstein&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bernstein |first=Jeremy |date=2011-05-01 |title=A memorandum that changed the world |url=http://scitation.aip.org/content/aapt/journal/ajp/79/5/10.1119/1.3533426 |journal=American Journal of Physics |volume=79 |issue=5 |pages=441 |doi=10.1119/1.3533426 |issn=0002-9505}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Their results  were discussed with Oliphant, Tizard and Thomson. These men set up a government committee, the MAUD Committee, which in time became Britain's Tube Alloy program.  The committee’s purpose was to examine the potential of Frisch and Peierls' quantitative and qualitative analysis regarding critical mass and uranium separation.{{sfn|Peierls||2007|p=690}} After investigation the committee endorsed the Frisch and Peierls memorandum. The conclusion of their report was that a super weapon was both possible and feasible.{{sfn|Peierls|2007|p=692}}

== MAUD Committee ==
{{main|MAUD Committee}}
The [[MAUD Committee]] was founded in June 1940. The Committee was originally a part of the [[Committee for the Scientific Survey of Air Defence]], but later gained independence with the [[Ministry of Aircraft Production]].{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=41}} The committee was initially named after its chairman, Thomson, but quickly exchanged this for a more unassuming name, the MAUD Committee.{{sfn|Laucht|2012|p=41}} MAUD is assumed by many to be an acronym, but it was not. The name MAUD came to be in an unusual way. Shortly after Germany invaded Denmark, Bohr had sent a telegram to Frisch. The telegram ended with a strange line: &quot;Tell Cockcroft and Maud Ray Kent&quot;.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=45}} At first it was thought to be code regarding radium or other vital atomic-weapons-related information, hidden in an [[anagram]]. One suggestion was to replace the y with an i, producing 'radium taken'. Regardless of how crazy it seemed it was enough to cause concern in Britain.{{sfn|Szasz|1992|p=5}} When Bohr returned to England in 1943, it was discovered that the message was addressed to Bohr's housekeeper Maud Ray and Cockcroft. Maud Ray was from Kent. Thus the committee was named The M.A.U.D. Committee.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=45}} Meetings were normally held in the offices of the [[Royal Society]] in London. In addition to Thomson, its original members were Chadwick, Cockcroft, Oliphant and [[Philip Burton Moon|Philip Moon]]. [[Patrick Blackett]], [[Charles Drummond Ellis|Charles Ellis]] and William Haworth.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=45}}

[[File:George Paget Thomson.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[George Paget Thomson]], chairman of the [[MAUD Committee]], which initiated Tube Alloys]]
Four universities provided the locations where the experiments were taking place. The laboratory at the University of Birmingham was responsible for all the theoretical work, such as what size of critical mass was needed for an explosion. It was run by Peierls, with the help of fellow German refugee scientist [[Klaus Fuchs]]. The laboratories at the University of Liverpool and the [[University of Oxford]] experimented with different types of isotope separation. Chadwick's group at Liverpool dealt with [[Enriched uranium#thermal diffusion|thermal diffusion]], which worked based on the assumption that different isotopes of uranium are attracted to different temperatures. [[Franz Simon]]'s group at Oxford investigated the [[gaseous diffusion]] of isotopes. This method works on the principle that at differing pressures uranium 235 would diffuse through a barrier faster than uranium 238. Eventually the most promising method of separation was gaseous diffusion. [[Egon Bretscher]] and [[Norman Feather]]'s group at Cambridge investigated whether another element, now called [[plutonium]], could be used as an explosive compound. Because of the French scientists, Oxford also obtained the world's only supply of heavy water, which helped them theorise how uranium could be used for power.{{sfn|Laucht|2012|pp=42–45}}

The research from the MAUD committee was complied in two reports, commonly known as the MAUD reports in July 1941. The first report, &quot;Use of Uranium for a Bomb&quot;, discussed the feasibility of creating a super-bomb from uranium, which they now thought to be true. The second, &quot;Use of Uranium as a Source of Power&quot; discussed the idea of using uranium as a source of power, not just a bomb. The MAUD Committee and report helped bring about the British nuclear program, the Tube Alloys Project. Not only did it help start a nuclear project in Britain but it helped jump-start the American project. Without the help of the MAUD Committee the American program, the [[Manhattan Project]], would have started months behind. Instead they were able to begin thinking about how to create a bomb, not whether it was possible.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=77–80}} Historian [[Margaret Gowing]] noted that &quot;events that change a time scale by only a few months can nevertheless change history.&quot;{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=85}}

The MAUD reports were reviewed by the Defence Services Panel of the Scientific Advisory Committee. This was chaired by [[Lord Hankey]], with its other members being Sir [[Edward Victor Appleton|Edward Appleton]], Sir [[Henry Hallett Dale|Henry Dale]], [[Alfred Charles Glyn Egerton|Alfred Egerton]], [[Archibald Hill]] and [[Edward Mellanby]]. The panel held seven meetings in September 1941, and submitted its report to the [[Lord President of the Council]], Sir [[John Anderson, 1st Viscount Waverley|John Anderson]]. At this point it was feared that German scientists were attempting to provide their country with an atomic bomb, and thus Britain needed to finish its first. The report ultimately stated that if there were even a sliver of a chance that the bomb effort could produce a weapon with such power, then every effort should be made to make sure Britain did not fall behind. While it recommended that while a pilot separation plant be built in Britain, the production facility should be built in Canada.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=97–104}} The Defence Services Panel submitted its report on 24 September 1941, but by this time the final decision had already been taken. [[Frederick Lindemann, 1st Viscount Cherwell|Lord Cherwell]] had taken the matter to the [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]], [[Winston Churchill]], who became the first national leader to approve a nuclear weapons program on 30 August 1941. The [[Chiefs of Staff Committee]] supported the decision.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=188–191, 504}}

==Tube Alloys organisation==
[[File:John Anderson, 1st Viscount Waverley 1947.jpg|thumb|right|Sir [[John Anderson, 1st Viscount Waverley|John Anderson]], as [[Lord President of the Council]], was the [[Minister (government)|minister]] responsible for Tube Alloys.]]
A directorate of Tube Alloys was established as part of Appleton's [[Department of Scientific and Industrial Research (United Kingdom)|Department of Scientific and Industrial Research]], and [[Wallace Akers]], the research director of [[Imperial Chemical Industries]] (ICI), was chosen as its head. Anderson and Akers came up with the name Tube Alloys. It was deliberately chosen to be meaningless, &quot;with a specious air of probability about it&quot;.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=109}} An advisory committee known as the Tube Alloys Consultative Council was created to oversee its work, chaired by Anderson, with its other members being Lord Hankey, Lord Cherwell, Sir Edward Appleton and Sir Henry Dale. This handled policy matters. To deal with technical issues, a Technical Committee was created with Akers as chairman, and Chadwick, Simon, Halban, Peierls, and Roland Slade from ICI as its original members,{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=109}} with [[Michael Perrin]] as its secretary. It was later joined by [[Charles Galton Darwin]], Cockcroft, Oliphant and Feather.{{sfn|Smyth|1945|p=278}}

==Isotopic separation==
The biggest problem faced by the MAUD Committee was to find a way to separate the 0.7% of uranium-235 from the 99.3% of uranium-238. This is difficult because the two types of uranium are chemically identical. Separation ([[uranium enrichment]]) would have to be achieved at a large scale. At Cambridge, [[Eric Rideal]] and his team investigated using a [[gas centrifuge]].{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=52}} Frisch chose to perform gaseous thermal diffusion using [[Klaus Clusius|Clusius]] tubes because it seemed the simplest method.  Frisch’s calculations showed there would need to be 100,000 Clusius tubes to extract the desired separation amount. Simon proceeded in a different direction, Peierls turned to Franz Simon, a chemist shielded in Britain, to consult methods of isotope separation. Simon preferred to find a method more suitable for mass production.{{sfn|Rhodes|1986|pp=339–340}}

[[File:Appleton.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Sir [[Edward Victor Appleton|Edward Appleton]] was [[permanent secretary]] of the [[Department of Scientific and Industrial Research (United Kingdom)|Department of Scientific and Industrial Research]], of which Tube Alloys was a part.]]
When Moon examined the suggestion that gaseous thermal diffusion be the method of choice to the MAUD committee, there was no majority agreement upon to move forward with it. The committee consulted with Peierls and Simon over the separation method and came to the agreement that “ordinary” gaseous diffusion was the best method to pursue. This relies on [[Graham's Law]], the fact that the gases diffuse through porous materials at rates that are determined by their molecular weight. [[Francis Ashton]] applied this method in 1913 when he separated two isotopes of [[neon]] by diffusing a sample thousands of times through a pipe clay. Thick materials like pipe clay proved too slow to be efficient on an industry scale. Simon proposed using a metal foil punctured with millions of microscopic holes would allow the separation process to move faster.{{sfn|Rhodes|1986|pp=339–340}} He estimated that a plant that separated {{convert|1|kg}} per diem of uranium-235 from natural uranium would cost about £5,000,000.{{sfn|Rhodes|1986|p=343}} The MAUD Committee realised that an atomic bomb was not just feasible, but inevitable.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=87–89}}

In 1941, Frisch moved to London to work with Chadwick and his cyclotron. Frisch built a Clusius tube there to study the properties of uranium hexafluoride. Frisch and Chadwick discovered that it is of one the gases for which  the Clusius method will not work.{{sfn|Rhodes|1986|p=345}} This was only a minor setback due to the fact that Simon was already in progress of establishing the alternative method of separation through ordinary gaseous diffusion.{{sfn|Rhodes|1986|p=343}}

The chemical problems of producing gaseous compounds of uranium and pure uranium metal were studied at the University of Birmingham and by ICI. Very early experiments were carried out by [[Michael Clapham (industrialist)|Michael Clapham]], who at the time was working on print technology at the [[Kynoch|Kynoch Works]] in Aston in Birmingham&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=[[BBC]] |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/643913.stm |title=Brum and the Bomb |first=David |last=Gregory |date=17 February 2000 |accessdate=6 February 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Philip Baxter]] at ICI made the first small batch of gaseous uranium hexafluoride for Chadwick in 1940. ICI received a formal £5,000 contract in December 1940 to make {{Convert|3|kg}} of this vital material for the future work.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=52}}  The prototype gaseous diffusion equipment itself was manufactured by [[Metropolitan-Vickers]] (MetroVick) at Trafford Park, Manchester, at a cost of £150,000 for four units.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=217–221}}  ICI pilot plants for producing {{convert|1|long cwt|kg|lk=in}} of pure uranium metal and {{convert|50|to|100|kg}} of uranium hexafluoride per diem commenced operation in Widnes in mid-1943.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=228–229}}

==Plutonium==
The breakthrough with plutonium was by Bretscher and Norman Feather at the Cavendish Laboratory. They realised that a slow neutron reactor fuelled with uranium would theoretically produce substantial amounts of [[plutonium-239]] as a by-product. This is because uranium-238 absorbs [[slow neutron]]s and forms a short-lived new isotope, [[uranium-239]]. The new isotope's nucleus rapidly emits an electron through [[beta decay]] producing a new element with an [[atomic mass]] of 239 and an [[atomic number]] of 93. This element's nucleus then also emits an electron and becomes a new element with an atomic number 94 and a much greater half-life. Bretscher and Feather showed theoretically feasible grounds that element 94 would be [[fissile]] — readily fissioned by both slow and fast neutrons, with the added advantage of being different from uranium, and therefore could be chemically separated from it. Bretscher even devised a chemical method to separate.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=59–60}}

This new development was also confirmed in independent work by [[Edwin M. McMillan]] and [[Philip Abelson]] at [[Berkeley Radiation Laboratory]] also in 1940. [[Nicholas Kemmer]] of the Cambridge team proposed the names [[neptunium]] for the new element 93 and plutonium for 94 by analogy with the outer planets Neptune and Pluto beyond Uranus (uranium being element 92). The Americans fortuitously suggested the same names.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=59–60}} The production and identification of the first sample of plutonium in 1941 is generally credited to [[Glenn Seaborg]], using a [[cyclotron]] rather than a reactor at the [[University of California, Berkeley|University of California]]. In 1941, neither team knew of the existence of the other.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=70–71}}

Chadwick voiced concerns about the need for such pure plutonium to make a feasible bomb. He also suspected that the gun method of detonation for a plutonium bomb would lead to proposed premature detonations. After Chadwick met [[Robert Oppenheimer]] at the [[Los Alamos Laboratory]] in 1943, he learned of a proposed bomb design which they were calling an implosion. The sub-critical mass of plutonium was supposed to be surrounded by explosives that were arranged to detonate simultaneously. This would cause the Plutonium core to be compressed and become supercritical. The core would be surrounded by a [[depleted uranium]] tamper which would reflect the neutrons back into the reaction, and contribute to the explosion by fissioning itself. This design solved Chadwick's worries about purity because it did not require the level that would be needed for the [[gun-type fission weapon]]. The biggest problem with this method was creating the [[explosive lens]]es. Chadwick took this information with him and described the method to Oliphant who then took it with him to England.{{sfn|Brown|1997|pp=253–254}}

==Montreal Laboratory==
{{Main|Montreal Laboratory}}
[[File:Montreal Group.jpg|thumb|right|Montreal Laboratory, 1944. Standing, left to right: A. M. Munn, B. Goldschmidt, J. W. Ozcroft, B. W. Sargent, G. A. Graham, [[Jules Guéron|J. Guéron]], H. F. Freundlich, [[Hans von Halban|H. H. von Halban]], R. Newell, J. Jackson, [[John Douglas Cockroft|J. D. Cockcroft]], [[Pierre Auger|P. Auger]], S. G. Bauer, N. Q. Lawrence, [[Allan Nunn May|A. N. May]]. Sitting, left to right: W. Knowles, P. Demers, J. R. Leicester, H. Seligman, E. D. Courant, E. P. Hincks, F. W. Fenning, [[George Laurence|G. C. Laurence]], [[Bruno Pontecorvo|B. Pontecorvo]], [[George Volkoff|G. Volkoff]], [[Alvin Weinberg|A. Weinberg]], [[George Placzek|G. Placzek]] ]]
Halban's heavy water team from France continued its slow neutron research at Cambridge University; but the project was given a low priority since it was not considered relevant to bomb making. It suddenly acquired military significance when it was realised that it provided the route to plutonium.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=72–75}} The British Government wanted the Cambridge team to be relocated to North America, in proximity to the raw materials it required, and where the American research was being done. But Sir John Anderson wanted the British team to retain its own identity, and was concerned that since the Americans were working on [[nuclear reactor]] designs using [[nuclear graphite]] as a neutron moderator instead of heavy water, that team might not receive a fair share of resources.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=187–188}} The Americans had their own concerns, particularly about security, since only one of the six senior scientists in the group was British.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cns-snc.ca/media/history/early_years/earlyyears.html |title=Early Years of Nuclear Energy Research in Canada |publisher=Canadian Nuclear Society |accessdate=6 May 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They also had concerns about [[patent]] rights; that the French team would attempt to patent nuclear technology based on the pre-war work. As a compromise, Thomson suggested relocating the team to Canada.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=187–188}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Early years&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2012/03/05/70-years-ago-vannevar-bush-worries-about-french-patents/ |title=70 years ago: Vannevar Bush worries about French Patents |publisher=Restricted Data |first=Alex |last=Wellerstein |date=5 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Canadian government was approached, and [[Jack Mackenzie|Dean Mackenzie]], the president of the [[National Research Council of Canada]], immediately welcomed and supported the proposal. The costs and salaries would be divided between the British and Canadian governments, but the British share would come from a billion dollar war gift from Canada.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=188–189}} The first eight staff arrived in Montreal at the end of 1942, and occupied a house belonging to [[McGill University]]. Three months later they moved into a {{convert|200|m2}} area in a new building at the [[University of Montreal]]. The laboratory grew quickly to over 300 staff; about half were Canadians recruited by [[George Laurence]]. A subgroup of theoreticians was recruited and headed by a Czechoslovak physicist, [[George Placzek]]. Placzek proved to be a very capable group leader, and was generally regarded as the only member of the staff with the stature of the highest scientific rank and with close personal contacts with many key physicists involved in the Manhattan project. [[Friedrich Paneth]] became head of the chemistry division, and [[Pierre Auger]] of the experimental physics division. Von Halban was the director of the laboratory, but he proved to be an unfortunate choice as he was a poor administrator, and did not work well with the National Research Council of Canada. The Americans saw him as a security risk, and objected to the French atomic patents claimed by the Paris Group (in association with ICI).{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=191–199}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Early years&quot; /&gt;

The Montreal team in Canada depended on the Americans for supplies of heavy water from the US heavy water plant in [[Trail, British Columbia]], (which was under American contract), as well as technical information about plutonium. The Americans said that they would give heavy water to the Montreal group only if it agreed to direct its research along the limited lines suggested by [[du Pont]]. Despite doing much good work, by June 1943 work at the Montreal Lab had come to a complete standstill. Morale was low and the Canadian Government proposed cancelling the project. In April 1944 a Combined Policy Committee meeting in Washington agreed that Canada would build a heavy water reactor. John Cockcroft became the director. The Americans supported the project with information and visits. They also supplied material, for example, uranium and heavy water. The [[Chalk River Laboratories]] opened in 1944, and in 1946 the Montreal Laboratory was closed. The project developed the [[ZEEP]] reactor, which went critical in September 1945.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=271–280}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Early years&quot; /&gt;

==Niels Bohr's contribution to Tube Alloys==
Sir John Anderson was eager to invite Niels Bohr to the Tube Alloys project because he was a world-famous scientist who would not only contribute his expertise to the project, but also help the British government gain leverage in dealings with the Manhattan Project.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=245}} 
In September 1943, word reached Bohr in Denmark that the Nazis considered his family to be Jewish, and that they were in danger of being arrested. The Danish resistance helped Bohr and his wife escape by sea to Sweden on 29 September 1943.{{sfn|Rhodes|1986|pp=483–485}} When the news of Bohr's escape reached Britain, Lord Cherwell sent a telegram asking Bohr to come to Britain. Bohr arrived in Scotland on 6 October in a [[de Havilland Mosquito]] operated by the [[British Overseas Airways Corporation]] (BOAC).{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=245–247}}

[[File:Niels Bohr 1935.jpg|thumb|right|[[Niels Bohr]] joined Tube Alloys after escaping from Denmark in 1943.]]
At the invitation of the director of the Manhattan Project, [[Brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]] [[Leslie R. Groves, Jr]], Bohr visited the Manhattan Project sites in November 1943. Groves offered Bohr substantial pay, but Bohr initially refused the offer because he wanted to make sure that the relationship between the [[United States]] and [[Great Britain]] remained a real cooperative partnership. In December 1943, after a meeting with [[Albert Einstein]], Bohr and his son [[Aage Bohr|Aage]] committed to working on the Manhattan Project.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=251–253}}

Bohr made a substantial contribution to the atomic bomb development effort.{{sfn|Pais|1991|pp=496–497}} He also attempted to prevent an atomic arms race with the Soviet Union after the war, which he believed to be a serious threat. In 1944, Bohr made several key points he believed to be essential towards international nuclear weapon control. He urged that Britain and the United States should inform the Soviet Union about the Manhattan Project in order to decrease the likelihood of it feeling threatened on the premise that the other nations were building a bomb behind their back.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|p=258}} His beliefs stemmed from the fact that he was convinced the Russians already knew about the Manhattan Project, which therefore led him to believe that there was no point in hiding it from them.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|p=261}}

Bohr's evidence came from an interpretation of a letter he received from a Soviet friend and scientist in Russia, which he showed to the British security services.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|p=261}}&lt;ref&gt;Kapitza to Bohr, 28 October 1943, CAB 126/39, NA. 'Correspondence between Kapitza and B.' 2 May 1945, CAB 126/39&lt;/ref&gt; He reasoned that the longer the United States and Britain hid their nuclear advancements, Russia would feel increasingly threatened and more inclined to speed up their effort to produce an atomic bomb of their own. With the help of [[U.S. Supreme Court]] justice [[Felix Frankfurter]], Bohr met with the [[President of the United States]], [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], who was initially sympathetic to his ideas about controlling nuclear weapons on 26 August 1944; but Churchill was adamantly opposed to informing the Soviet Union of such work.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=273}}{{sfn|Aaserud|2006|pp=706–709}} At the [[Second Quebec Conference]] in September 1944, Roosevelt sided with Churchill, deciding that it would be upon the nation's best interest to keep the atomic bomb project a secret. Moreover, they decided Bohr was potentially dangerous and specific security measures must be made in order to prevent him from leaking information to the rest of the world, Russia in particular.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=268–272}}

==Tube Alloys and the United States==

===Tizard mission===
{{main|Tizard Mission}}
In 1940, a [[Tizard Mission|British mission, led by Tizard]] and with members that included Cockcroft, was sent to America to create relations and help advance the research towards war technology with the Americans. The most important device transferred through the Tizard Mission was the [[cavity magnetron]]. This inquiry from the Tizard Mission made it possible for the Americans to create a [[Radiation Laboratory (MIT)|radiation laboratory]]. This lab would later be used as a model for the Los Alamos laboratory. Tizard Mission members were involved in advising scientists on construction of the lab and its relations with the armed forces. A barrier had been broken and a pathway to exchange technical information between the two countries had been developed. The mission did not discuss the development of nuclear fission because at the time the process of fission was deemed impractical and was not a main priority for Tizard Mission members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Zimmerman |first=David |date=November 1995 |title=The Tizard Mission and the Development of the Atomic Bomb |journal=[[War in History]] |issn=0968-3445 |doi=10.1177/096834459500200302 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Oliphant's visit to the United States===
[[File:Sir Mark Oliphant.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Australian physicist [[Mark Oliphant]] played a key role in starting both the British and American atomic bomb projects.]]
The MAUD Committee reports urged the cooperation with the United States should be continued in the research of nuclear fission. [[Charles Christian Lauritsen|Charles C. Lauritsen]], a Caltech physicist working at the [[National Defense Research Committee]] (NDRC), was in London during this time and was invited to sit in on a MAUD meeting.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=85, 116}} The committee pushed for rapid development of nuclear weapons using gaseous-diffusion as their isotope separation device.{{sfn|Hewlett|Anderson|1962|p=42}} Once he returned to the United States, he was able to brief [[Vannevar Bush]], the director of the [[Office of Scientific Research and Development]] (OSRD), concerning the details discussed during the meeting.{{sfn|Hewlett|Anderson|1962|p=42}}

In August 1941, Mark Oliphant, Director of the physics department at the University of Birmingham and original member of the MAUD Committee, was sent to the United States to assist the NDRC on radar.{{sfn|Paul|2000|p=22}} Upon his visit to the U.S., Oliphant met with William D. Coolidge. Coolidge was shocked when Oliphant informed him that the British had predicted that only ten kilograms of uranium-235 would be efficient to supply a chain reaction effected by fast moving neutrons.{{sfn|Hewlett|Anderson|1962|p=43}} While in America, Oliphant discovered that the chairman of the OSRD [[S-1 Section]], [[Lyman Briggs]], had locked away the MAUD reports transferred from Britain entailing the initial discoveries and had not informed the S-1 Committee members of all its findings.{{sfn|Paul|2000|p=22}}

Oliphant took the initiative himself to enlighten the scientific community in the U.S. of  the recent ground breaking discoveries the MAUD Committee had just exposed. Oliphant also travelled to Berkley to with meet with [[Ernest Lawrence]], inventor of the cyclotron. After Oliphant informed Lawrence of his report on uranium, Lawrence met with NDRC chairman [[James Bryant Conant]], [[George B. Pegram]], and [[Arthur Compton]] to relay the details which Oliphant had directed to Lawrence.{{sfn|Hewlett|Anderson|1962|p=42}} Oliphant was not only able to get in touch with Lawrence, but he met with Conant and Bush to inform them of the significant data the MAUD had discovered. Oliphant’s ability to inform the Americans led to Oliphant convincing Lawrence, Lawrence convincing Compton, and then Kistiakowsky convincing Conant to move forward with nuclear weapons. These actions from Oliphant resulted in Bush taking this report directly to the president.{{sfn|Hewlett|Anderson|1962|pp=45–46}}

===Information sharing ceases===
The American effort increased rapidly and soon outstripped the British as the American authorities were reluctant to share details with their British counterparts. However, separate research continued in each country with some exchange of information. Several of the key British scientists visited the United States early in 1942 and were given full access to all of the information available. They were astounded at the momentum that the American atomic bomb project had then assumed. The British and American exchange of information and efforts continued but the nations did not combine their efforts, leading their programmes separately. Furthermore, in 1941 the British Government rebuffed and vetoed attempts and proposals by Bush and Conant to strengthen cooperation between Great Britain and America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton J. Bernstein and the Western Political Quarterly (University of Utah)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | last =Bernstein
 | first =Barton J.
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | title =The Uneasy Alliance: Roosevelt, Churchill, and the Atomic Bomb, 1940–1945
 | journal =The Western Political Quarterly
 | volume =29
 | issue =2
 | pages =202–230
 | year =1976
 | jstor =448105
 | doi =10.2307/448105 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1942, the [[United States Army Corps of Engineers]] took over the Manhattan Project from OSRD, and Groves became the project's director. He tightened security, which dried up the flow of information to Britain. American officials were particularly concerned that Akers and other people from ICI involved in the Tube Alloys project were trying to exploit American nuclear scientific knowledge to create a profitable post-war industry.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=218}} In October 1942, Bush and Conant  convinced Roosevelt that the United States should independently develop the atomic bomb project, despite an agreement of unrestricted scientific interchange between United States and Britain.{{sfn|Farmelo|2013|pp=224}}

This disastrously affected British efforts as they lacked manpower, facilities, equipment and materials. Tube Alloys therefore fell behind in the race with the Manhattan Project. On 30 July 1942, Anderson advised Churchill that: &quot;We must face the fact that ... [our] pioneering work ... is a dwindling asset and that, unless we capitalise it quickly, we shall be outstripped. We now have a real contribution to make to a 'merger.' Soon we shall have little or none&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton J. Bernstein and the Western Political Quarterly (University of Utah)&quot; /&gt; By the time Great Britain realised it, the position had worsened; Bush decided that outside help for the Manhattan Project was no longer needed. The [[Military Policy Committee]] (MPC) supported Bush's arguments and restricted access to the classified information which Britain could utilise to develop its atomic weapons programme, even if it slowed down the American efforts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton J. Bernstein and the Western Political Quarterly (University of Utah)&quot; /&gt;

The Americans stopped sharing any information on heavy water production, the manufacture of [[uranium hexafluoride]], the method of [[electromagnetic separation]], the physical or chemical properties of plutonium, the details of bomb design, or the facts about fast neutron reactions. This was a major disappointment which hindered the British and the Canadians, who were collaborating on heavy water production and several other aspects of the research programme.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton J. Bernstein and the Western Political Quarterly (University of Utah)&quot; /&gt; By 1943 Britain had stopped sending its scientists to the United States, which slowed down the pace of work being done there. The British boycott affected the American project, which had relied on efforts led by British scientists. In March 1943 Conant approached the Military Policy Committee, which decided that Britain's help would benefit some areas of the project. Chadwick, Penney, Peierls, Oliphant and other British scientists were important enough that the bomb design team at the Los Alamos Laboratory needed them, despite the risk of revealing weapon design secrets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton J. Bernstein and the Western Political Quarterly (University of Utah)&quot; /&gt;

===Quebec Agreement===
{{main|Quebec Agreement}}
[[File:RooseveltChurchillMackenzie.jpg|thumb|[[William Mackenzie King]], [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], [[Winston Churchill]] and the [[Alexander Cambridge, 1st Earl of Athlone|Earl of Athlone]] at [[Quebec Conference, 1943|Quebec Conference]] in July 1943]]
Churchill then sought information about building Britain's own gaseous diffusion plant, a heavy water plant and an atomic reactor in Britain, despite its immense cost. However, in July 1943, in London, American officials cleared up some major misunderstandings about British motives, and after many months of negotiations the [[Quebec Agreement]] was signed by Churchill and Roosevelt on 19 August 1943 during the [[Quebec Conference, 1943|Quebec Conference]]. The British handed over their material to the Americans and in return received the copies of the American progress reports to the President. Tube Alloys was subsumed into the Manhattan Project.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=174–177}}

In a section of the Quebec Agreement formally entitled &quot;Articles of Agreement governing collaboration between the authorities of the USA and UK in the matter of Tube Alloys&quot;, Britain and the USA agreed to share resources &quot;to bring the Tube Alloys [i.e. the Atomic Bomb] project to fruition at the earliest moment.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quebec Agreement&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.atomicarchive.com/Docs/ManhattanProject/Quebec.shtml |title=Quebec Agreement |publisher=Atomic Archive |accessdate=4 May 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The leaders further agreed that:
* &quot;First, we will never use this agency against each other,
* &quot;Secondly, we will not use it against third parties without each other's consent, and
* &quot;Thirdly, we will not either of us communicate any information about Tube Alloys to third parties except by mutual consent.&quot;
It was also agreed that ''any post-war advantages of an industrial or commercial nature'' would be decided at the discretion of the President.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quebec Agreement&quot;/&gt; The Quebec Agreement established the [[Combined Policy Committee]] to control the Manhattan Project, consisting of [[Henry Stimson]], Bush and Conant from the United States; [[Field Marshal (United Kingdom)|Field Marshal]] Sir [[John Dill]] and [[Colonel]] [[John Jestyn Llewellin, 1st Baron Llewellin|J. J. Llewellin]] were the British members, and [[C. D. Howe]] was the Canadian member.{{sfn|Jones|1985|p=296}} Llewellin returned to the United Kingdom at the end of 1943 and was replaced on the committee by Sir [[Ronald Ian Campbell]], who in turn was replaced by the British Ambassador to the United States, [[Edward Wood, 1st Earl of Halifax|Lord Halifax]], in early 1945. Dill died in Washington, D.C., in November 1944 and was replaced both as Chief of the [[British Defence Staff – US|British Joint Staff Mission]] and as a member of the Combined Policy Committee by Field Marshal Sir [[Henry Maitland Wilson]].{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=234}}

==British contribution to the Manhattan Project==
{{main|British contribution to the Manhattan Project}}
Akers summoned Chadwick, Oliphant, Simon and Peierls to the United States. They arrived the day the Quebec Agreement was signed, ready to assist the Manhattan Project in any way possible. Akers was generally disliked and the Americans refused to move forward with collaboration unless a top British scientist who was &quot;accepted and sound of judgement&quot; was appointed instead. British officials dug in over Britain's right to make its own appointments to its own government agencies. A compromise was reached, with  Chadwick put in charge as Britain's technical advisor for the Combined Policy Committee, and as the head of the British Mission to the Manhattan Project.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|pp=169–173}}

[[File:Groves and Chadwick 830308.jpg|thumb|left|[[James Chadwick]], head of the British Mission to the Manhattan Project, with Major General [[Leslie R. Groves, Jr.]], the project's director]]
With this dispute settled collaboration could once again take place. Chadwick wanted to involve as many British scientists as possible so long as Groves accepted them. Chadwick's first choice, Joseph Rotblat refused to give up his Polish citizenship. Chadwick then turned to Otto Frisch, who to Chadwick's surprise accepted becoming a British citizen right away and began the screening process so that he could travel to America. Chadwick spent the first few weeks of November 1943 acquiring a clear picture of the extensive Manhattan Project. He realized the scale of such sites as [[Oak Ridge, Tennessee]], which was the new headquarters of the project, and could safely conclude that without similar industrial site being found in Germany the chances of the Nazi atomic bomb project being successful was very low.{{sfn|Brown|1997|pp=250–253}}

With Chadwick involved the main goal was to show that the Quebec Agreement was a success. It was Britain's duty to cooperate to the fullest and speed along the process. Chadwick used this opportunity to give as many young British scientists experience as possible so that they might carry that experience to post-war Britain.{{sfn|Brown|1997|p=254}} He eventually convinced  Groves of Rotblat's integrity to the cause, and this led to Rotblat being accepted to the Manhattan Project without renouncing his nationality. Rotblat had been left in charge of the Tube Alloys research, and brought with him the results obtained since Chadwick had left.{{sfn|Brown|1997|pp=254–255}}

[[William Penney, Baron Penney|William Penney]], one of the Tube Alloys scientists, was an expert in shock waves. In June 1944 he went to America to work at the [[Los Alamos Laboratory]] as part of the British delegation.{{sfn|Gowing|1964|p=263}}  He worked on means to assess the effects of a nuclear explosion, and wrote a paper on what height the bombs should be detonated at for maximum effect in attacks on Germany and Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Height of the Bomb |first=Alex |last=Wellerstein |date=8 August 2012 |publisher=Restricted Data|url=http://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2012/08/08/the-height-of-the-bomb/|accessdate=2 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He served as a member of the target committee established by Groves to select Japanese cities for atomic bombing,{{sfn|Jones|1985|p=528}} and on [[Tinian]] with [[Project Alberta]] as a special consultant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roster&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mphpa.org/classic/CG/CG_09D.htm |title=Project Alberta/Destination Team roster of personnel |publisher=The Manhattan Project Heritage Preservation Association |accessdate=8 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with [[Group Captain]] [[Leonard Cheshire]], sent as a British representative, he watched the [[bombing of Nagasaki]] from the observation plane ''[[Big Stink (B-29)|Big Stink]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;eyewitness&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.atomicarchive.com/Docs/Hiroshima/Nagasaki.shtml |title=Eyewitness Account of Atomic Bomb Over Nagasaki |first=William L |last=Laurence |authorlink=William L. Laurence |publisher=National Science Digital Library |accessdate=18 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also formed part of the Manhattan Project's post-war scientific mission to Hiroshima and Nagasaki that assessed the extent of the damage caused by the bombs.{{sfn|Szasz|1992|p=64}}

The ''[[Smyth Report]]'' was issued by the US War Department on 12 August 1945, giving the story of the atomic bomb and including the technical details that could now be made public. It made few references to the British contribution to the bomb, and a White Paper, ''Statements Relating to the Atomic Bomb'' was hurriedly drafted by Michael Perrin. This account was issued just after Attlee had replaced Churchill as Prime Minister, and was the only official statement on the British contribution for fifteen years.{{sfn|Coleman|1976|p=208}}

==Soviet spies in the Tube Alloys project==
{{main|Atomic spies}}
The Soviet Union received details of British research from its [[atomic spies]] [[Klaus Fuchs]], [[Engelbert Broda]], [[Melita Norwood]] and [[John Cairncross]], a member of the notorious [[Cambridge Five]]. [[Alan Nunn May]] was recruited later in Canada. [[Lavrenty Beria]]'s report to Stalin of March 1942 included the MAUD reports and other British documents passed by Cairncross.{{sfn|Gordin|2009|pp=111–115}}{{sfn|Rhodes|1995|p=58}} Fuchs began disclosing information to the [[Soviet Union]] about the possible production of a British atomic bomb when he joined the Tube Alloys project,{{sfn|Rhodes|1995|pp=57–58}} although his contribution towards Soviet espionage was more severe during the Manhattan Project.{{sfn|Rhodes|1995|pp=117–119}} Fuchs was able to contact a London-based [[Communist Party of Germany|KPD]] leader, [[Jürgen Kuczynski]] and his [[courier]] [[Ursula Beurton]].{{sfn|Laucht|2012|p=86}}

==Post-war==
{{main|Nuclear weapons and the United Kingdom}}
The [[Atomic Energy Research Establishment]] (AERE or the Harwell Laboratory) near [[Harwell, Oxfordshire]], was established by Cockcroft in 1946 as the main centre for military and civilian [[atomic energy]] research and development in Britain. Former [[Royal Air Force station]]s were selected for AERE and AWRE as they were isolated, with large hangars. Penney returned from the United States and was appointed to a  professorship (for Mathematics) at Imperial College. He accepted the directorship position at the Armament Research Department (ARD) in 1946.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wikileak.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Contributions from Carey Sublette, Jay Lim, C. Nicholas Hill and [[Julian Assange]] |title=How Britain got the Bomb |url=https://wikileaks.org/wiki/How_Britain_got_the_bomb#Penney_and_the_Start_of_the_Post-War_British_Atomic_Bomb_Program |work=Nuclear Weapon Archives, several other media correspondents, and anti-nuclear weapons organisations |publisher=Wikileaks.org |accessdate=5 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the end of the war the The [[Special Relationship]] between Britain and the United States &quot;became very much less special&quot;.{{sfn|Gowing|Arnold|1974|p=93}} The British government had trusted that America would share nuclear technology, which the British saw as a joint discovery. On 9 November 1945, Mackenzie King and the British Prime Minister, [[Clement Attlee]] went to Washington, D.C., to confer with President [[Harry Truman]] about future cooperation in nuclear weapons and nuclear power.{{sfn|Gowing|Arnold|1974|pp=73–77}} The three leaders agreed that there would be full and effective cooperation on atomic energy, but British hopes for a full resumption of cooperation on nuclear weapons were disappointed.{{sfn|Gowing|Arnold|1974|p=92}} The Americans soon made it clear that this was restricted to basic scientific research.{{sfn|Paul|2000|pp=80–83}}

The passing of the [[Atomic Energy Act of 1946]] (McMahon Act) in August 1946, made it clear that the UK would no longer be allowed access to the United States' atomic research. This partly resulted from the arrest for espionage of Alan Nunn May in February 1946.{{sfn|Gowing|Arnold|1974|pp=105–108}} On 8 January 1947, Prime Minister [[Clement Attlee]] formed a secret &quot;GEN.163 Cabinet committee&quot;, consisting of six cabinet ministers of his government,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wikileak.org&quot; /&gt; which decided that Britain required the atomic bomb to maintain its position in world politics. In the words of Foreign Secretary [[Ernest Bevin]], &quot;That won't do at all&amp;nbsp;... we've got to have this&amp;nbsp;... I don't mind for myself, but I don't want any other Foreign Secretary of this country to be talked to or at by a Secretary of State in the United States as I have just had in my discussions with [[James F. Byrnes|Mr Byrnes]]. We've got to have this thing over here whatever it costs&amp;nbsp;... We've got to have the bloody Union Jack on top of it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/theissues/article/0,,1730784,00.html | location=London | newspaper=[[The Guardian]] | first=Mark | last=Oliver | title=Q&amp;A: replacing Trident | date=15 March 2006}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Penney did not have any knowledge of such committee until he was approached by [[Marshal of the Royal Air Force|Marshal of the Air Force]] [[Charles Portal, 1st Viscount Portal of Hungerford|Lord Portal]], to lead the clandestine efforts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wikileak.org&quot; /&gt; The project was code-named ''High Explosive Research'' (or HER). In May 1947, Penney was appointed as the director to lead the programme, based at the [[Defence Research Agency|Royal Armament Research Development Establishment]] (RARDE) at [[Fort Halstead]] and the [[Royal Arsenal]] at Woolwich (AWE).  In short span of time, Penney assembled a team to initiate the work on [[atomic weapons]], firstly preparing a report on describing the feature, science and idea of the American ''Fat Man'' implosion bomb.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wikileak.org&quot; /&gt; Penney broke down the development tasks required to replicate it, and identifying outstanding questions that required further research on nuclear weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wikileak.org&quot; /&gt; The report entitled, &quot;Plutonium Weapon – General Description&quot; was roughly equivalent in terms of scientific data and reports that were provided to the [[Soviet nuclear program]] by Klaus Fuchs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wikileak.org&quot; /&gt;

In April 1950 an abandoned Second World War airfield, [[RAF Aldermaston]] in Berkshire was selected as the permanent home for Britain's nuclear weapons programme. This was to become the [[Atomic Weapons Research Establishment]] (AWRE). On 3 October 1952, under the code-name &quot;[[Operation Hurricane]]&quot;, the first British nuclear device was successfully detonated off the west coast of Australia in the [[Monte Bello Islands]]. The development of the independent British nuclear deterrent led to the Atomic Energy Act being amended in 1958, and to a resumption of the nuclear Special Relationship between America and Britain under the [[1958 US–UK Mutual Defence Agreement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Gott |first1=Richard |title=The Evolution of the Independent British Deterrent |journal=International Affairs |date=April 1963 |volume=39 |issue=2 |pages=238–252|jstor=2611300 |issn=1468-2346 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/STATUTE-72/pdf/STATUTE-72-Pg276-2.pdf |publisher=US Government Printing Office |date=2 July 1958 |title=Public Law 85-479 |accessdate=12 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite conference |last=Aaserud |first=Finn |year=2006 |pages=706–709 |url=http://www.2iceshs.cyfronet.pl/2ICESHS_Proceedings/Chapter_25/R-17_Aaserud.pdf |title= Niels Bohr's Mission for an 'Open World' |editor-last=Kokowski |editor-first=M. |conference=Proceedings of the 2nd ICESHS|location=Cracow |accessdate=26 June 2011 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Brown |first=Andrew |title=The Neutron and the Bomb |location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1997 |isbn=0-19-853992-4 |ref=harv }}
*{{cite book  |last=Clark |first= Ronald W. |authorlink=Ronald W. Clark|title=The Birth of the Bomb: Britain’s part in the weapon that changed the World |publisher=Phoenix House |year=1961 |location=London |oclc=824335 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite journal|last = Coleman |first=Earle E. |url=http://libweb5.princeton.edu/visual_materials/pulc/pulc_v_37_n_3.pdf |title=The &quot;Smyth Report&quot;: A Descriptive Checklist | journal =The Princeton University Library Chronicle | publisher= Princeton University Press |date = Spring 1976 |volume=37 | pages = 204–18 |issn = 0032-8456 |ref = harv | issue = 3}}
*{{cite book |last=Farmelo |first=Graham |title=Churchill's Bomb: How the United States Overtook Britain in the First Nuclear Arms Race |publisher=Basic Books |year=2013 |isbn=978-0-465-02195-6 |location=New York |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Gordin |first=Michael D. |title=Red Cloud at Dawn : Truman, Stalin, and the End of the Atomic Monopoly |location=New York |publisher=Farrar, Straus and Giroux |year=2009 |isbn=9780374256821 |oclc=300718864 |ref=harv }} 
*{{cite book |last=Gowing |first=Margaret |authorlink=Margaret Gowing |title=Britain and Atomic Energy 1939–1945  |publisher=Macmillan |year=1964 |location=London |oclc=3195209 |ref=harv }}
*{{cite book |last=Gowing |first=Margaret |authorlink=Margaret Gowing |title=Independence and Deterrence: Volume 2 Policy and Execution  |location= London |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=1974 |isbn=0-333-16695-7 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last1 = Gowing | first1 = Margaret | first2 = Lorna | last2 = Arnold | authorlink2=Lorna Arnold | year = 1974 | title=Independence and Deterrence: Britain and Atomic Energy, 1945–1952, Volume 1, Policy Making | publisher= Macmillan| location = London | isbn = 0-333-15781-8 | oclc = 611555258 | ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Hewlett |first=Richard G. |authorlink=Richard G. Hewlett |last2=Anderson |first2=Oscar E. |url=http://www.governmentattic.org/5docs/TheNewWorld1939-1946.pdf |title=The New World, 1939–1946 |publisher=Pennsylvania State University Press |year=1962 |isbn=0-520-07186-7 |location=University Park |oclc=637004643 |ref=harv|accessdate=26 March 2013 }}
* {{cite book |last=Jones | first =Vincent |title = Manhattan: The Army and the Atomic Bomb |publisher = United States Army Center of Military History | location = Washington, DC |year = 1985 | format = [[Portable document format|PDF]] | url = http://www.history.army.mil/html/books/011/11-10/CMH_Pub_11-10.pdf | accessdate =June 8, 2013 | oclc = 10913875 |ref = harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Laucht|first1=Christoph|title=Elemental Germans: Klaus Fuchs, Rudolf Peierls and the making of British nuclear culture 1939–59|date=2012|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|edition=1|location=Basingstoke|isbn=978-1-137-02833-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Owen |first=James |title=Danger UXB – The Heroic Story of the WW II Bomb Disposal Teams |location=London |publisher=Little, Brown |year=2010 |isbn=0-349-12237-7 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Pais |first=Abraham |authorlink=Abraham Pais |year=1991 |title=Niels Bohr's Times, In Physics, Philosophy and Polity |location=Oxford |publisher=Clarendon Press |isbn=978-0-19-852049-8 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Paul |first=Septimus H. |year=2000 |title=Nuclear Rivals: Anglo-American Atomic Relations, 1941–1952 |location=Columbus, Ohio |publisher=Ohio State University Press |isbn= 978-0-8142-0852-6 |oclc=43615254 |ref = harv }}
*{{cite book |last1=Peierls |first1=Rudolf |title=Sir Rudolf Peierls : Aelected Private and Scientific Correspondence |date=2007 |publisher=World Scientific |location=Singapore  |isbn=981-256-503-5  |ref=harv }}
*{{cite book |last1=Rhodes |first1=Richard |authorlink=Richard Rhodes |title=[[The Making of the Atomic Bomb]] |date=1986 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-671-65719-4 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book  |last=Rhodes |first=Richard |authorlink=Richard Rhodes |title=Dark Sun: the Making of the Hydrogen Bomb|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |year=1995 |isbn=0-684-80400-X |location=New York |oclc= 32509950 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last = Smyth | first=Henry DeWolf | authorlink =Henry DeWolf Smyth |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gp2aAAAAIAAJ | title =Atomic Energy for Military Purposes; the Official Report on the Development of the Atomic Bomb under the Auspices of the United States Government, 1940–1945 | location =Princeton | publisher =Princeton University Press |year = 1945 |ref=harv |isbn = 978-0-8047-1722-9}}
* {{cite book | last = Szasz |first=Ferenc Morton |year=1992 |title=British Scientists and the Manhattan Project: the Los Alamos Years |location=New York |publisher=St. Martin's Press |isbn=978-0-312-06167-8 |oclc=23901666 |ref= harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last=Cathcart |first=Brian |title=Test of Greatness: Britain's Struggle for the Atom Bomb |publisher=John Murray |year=1995 |isbn=0-7195-5225-7 |location=London |oclc=31241690}}
*{{cite book |last=Ehrman |first=John |title=The Atomic Bomb: An Account of British Policy in the Second World War |publisher=Cabinet Office |year=1953 |location=London |oclc=488868259|authorlink=John Ehrman }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
*[http://avalon.law.yale.edu/subject_menus/quebec.asp The Quebec Conference: ''Agreement Relating to Atomic Energy'']
*[http://www.atomicarchive.com/History/british/index.shtml The British Mission]
*[http://media.cns-snc.ca/history/early_years/earlyyears.html Early Years of Nuclear Energy Research in Canada]
*[http://manhattanprojectvoices.org/oral-histories/eileen-doxfords-interview 2009 Interview with Eileen Doxford, Tube Alloys program lab assistant] Voices of the Manhattan Project
*[http://manhattanprojectvoices.org/oral-histories/myfanwy-pritchard-robertss-interview Interview with Myfanwy Pritchard-Roberts, Tube Alloys program lab assistant] Voices of the Manhattan Project
{{portal bar|Canada|History of Science|Nuclear technology|United Kingdom|World War II}}

[[Category:Nuclear weapons programme of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Nuclear history of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Code names]]
[[Category:Secret military programs]]
[[Category:Nuclear proliferation]]
[[Category:1942 establishments in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1942 in science]]
[[Category:1942 in military history]]
[[Category:1952 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Military history of the United Kingdom during World War II]]</text>
      <sha1>mv943h1rgu5tnzan9zu72lop0lcc8tw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
