<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Type 94 Nambu pistol</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1898395</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740342544</id>
      <parentid>733608455</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-20T13:21:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mitch F Davis</username>
        <id>28080568</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Design */Typo: duplicate words</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13615">{{good article}}
{{Infobox Weapon
|name=Nambu Type 94 Pistol
|image=[[Image:Type 94 1835.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Type 94 Pistol
|origin={{flag|Empire of Japan|23px}}
|type=[[Semi-automatic pistol]]
&lt;!-- Type selection --&gt;
|is_ranged=yes
|is_UK=
&lt;!-- Service history --&gt;
|service=1935–1945
|used_by= {{flag|Empire of Japan|23px}}
|wars=[[Second Sino-Japanese War]]&lt;br&gt;[[World War II]]&lt;br&gt;[[Chinese Civil War]]
&lt;!-- Production history --&gt;
|designer=[[Kijiro Nambu]]
|design_date=1929
|manufacturer= Nambu Rifle Manufacturing Company
|production_date=1935–1945&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 191&lt;/ref&gt;
|number=71,000&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;
|variants=
&lt;!-- General specifications --&gt;
|weight=765 [[Gram|g]] (1 lb 11oz)&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;/&gt;
|length=187 mm (7.36 in)&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;/&gt;
|part_length=96 mm (3.78 in)&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;/&gt;
|width=
|height=199 mm (4.69in)&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;/&gt;
|crew=
&lt;!-- Ranged weapon specifications --&gt;
|cartridge=[[8x22mm Nambu]]
|caliber=
|action= recoil operated, locked breech
|rate=
|velocity=305 m/s (1000 ft/s)&lt;ref name=&quot;msa67&quot;&gt;Hogg, Ian, ''Military Small Arms of the 20th Century'', 7th Edition, (2000) p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;
|range=
|max_range=
|feed=6 round detachable box magazine&lt;ref name=&quot;msa67&quot;/&gt;
|sights= Front Blade, Rear fixed V&lt;ref name=&quot;UEW277&quot;&gt;Miller, David. ''Fighting Men of World War II Axis Forces  Uniforms, Equipment, and Weapons'' (2010), p. 277&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The '''Type 94 Nambu  8&amp;nbsp;mm Pistol''' ('''Type 94 Handgun''', Japanese: 九四式拳銃 Kyūyon-Shiki Kenjū) is a semiautomatic pistol developed by [[Kijirō Nambu]] and his associates for the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]. Development of the Type 94 pistol began in 1929, and after several redesigns the final prototype was tested and officially adopted by the Japanese Army in late 1934 ([[Japanese calendar]], 2594).&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; The Type 94 pistol entered production in 1935. Approximately 71,000 pistols were manufactured before production ended in 1945.

The Type 94 pistol was designed for, and popular among, Japanese tank and aircraft crews who preferred a smaller, lightweight design. Japanese weapons experts have subsequently criticized some design elements of the Type 94; in particular the pistol could be fired unintentionally before the breech was fully locked if the sear bar on the side of the [[Receiver (firearms)|receiver]] was jarred loose and the pistol was improperly handled. Additionally, the process to disassemble the pistol is overly complex and awkward.  The build quality of the Type 94 pistol declined over its production run; &quot;last ditch&quot; pistols made in 1945 were crudely manufactured.

==History==
The Type 94 Nambu pistol was designed by Kojiro Nambu after he retired from the Japanese Army and founded the Nambu Rifle Manufacturing Company.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 189&lt;/ref&gt; Design for the Type 94 Nambu pistol commenced in 1929 with the goal of reducing the bulk and price of previous Nambu designs.&lt;ref name=&quot;msa67&quot;/&gt; The Imperial Japanese Army felt a smaller pistol of domestic design that could accommodate the standard [[8×22mm Nambu]] cartridge was needed to substitute the larger, heavier, and only official military pistol, the Type 14 Nambu.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;/&gt; The demand for officer's handguns had increased as a result of Japan's invasion of [[Manchuria]] during the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;/&gt; A new design was also wanted by the Japanese Army to include a [[Safety (firearms)|magazine safety]], to prevent unintentional discharges during cleaning that were common among Japanese personnel.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;/&gt; Naming of the Type 94 pistol reflects the change in Japanese nomenclature with the 94 reckoning back to the mythical foundation of Japan in 660 BC therefore year 2594 instead of the  traditional emperor reign period used to name the [[Type 26 revolver]] or [[Nambu pistol|Type 14 Nambu pistol]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pow190&quot;&gt;Hogg, Ian, ''Pistols of the World'', 4th Edition, (2004) p. 234&lt;/ref&gt; The final prototype for the Type 94 was officially adopted by the Japanese Army in late 1934 after several redesigns.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; Production began under the supervision of the [[Nagoya Arsenal|Nagoya Army Arsenal]] at the Nambu Rifle Manufacturing Company and later its successor, Chuo Kogyo Company, Ltd.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; An estimated 71,000 pistols were produced for the military but the exact quantity is unknown because of the production of unserialized pistols and undated pistols.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; During World War II the pistol became a preferred weapon for tank crews and paratroopers who required a smaller, more convenient pistol.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;/&gt; The Type 94 was never officially adopted by the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] but was available to officers through the Japanese officer's union.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt;

==Design==
The Type 94 pistol is operated by a different mechanism than previous Japanese sidearms.&lt;ref name=&quot;jsp22&quot;&gt;Skennerton, Ian, ''Japanese Service Pistols Handbook'' (2008) p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike previously designed Nambu pistols, the Type 94 operates with a concealed hammer and with a firing pin rather than a hammer.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; According to authors, Harry L. Derby and James  D. Brown, the [[firing pin]] is inherently weak and is prone to breakage because of a recess cut provided for the crossbolt and is prone to breaking at this point. &lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; The sturdier hammer firing mechanism was developed and included in the Type 94 to replace the poor striker on the Type 14 Nambu.&lt;ref name=&quot;pow190&quot;/&gt; The locking system is a rising-block type which floats independently between the lugs underneath the chamber end of the barrel.&lt;ref name=&quot;jsp22&quot;/&gt; The single coil mainspring is positioned around the barrel instead of to the rear of the barrel as found on other Nambu pistols.&lt;ref name=&quot;jsp22&quot;/&gt;  The grip is smaller than other Japanese pistols and is finished with smooth wood&lt;ref name=&quot;jsp16&quot;&gt;Skennerton, Ian, ''Japanese Service Pistols Handbook'' (2008) p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; but according to author Jeff Kinard, are more comfortable for use by men with smaller hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;phi247&quot;&gt;Kinard, Jeff. ''Pistols: An Illustrated History of Their Impact'' (2003), p. 247&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Magazine (firearms)|magazine]] holds a maximum of six rounds because of the smaller grip&lt;ref name=&quot;pow190&quot;/&gt; and it is considered difficult to reload the weapon, with pressure from the bolt holding it inside the pistol.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; The magazine catch protrudes far enough to occasionally disengage when the  pistol is placed on its left side on a hard surface.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; The magazine could also disengage if squeezed into or jarred in a holster.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; The manual safety lever is located on the left rear of the frame and has the [[kanji]] for fire and safe stamped onto the frame.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt; The front blade sight on the muzzle of the Type 94 pistol and the rear fixed V were occasionally inaccurately positioned making them useless when the weapon is being aimed.&lt;ref name=&quot;UEW277&quot;/&gt; The rear sight was reduced from a U-shape to a simple notch in 1944 with the front blade being left unchanged but less attention to detail being applied as World War II progressed.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH207&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 207&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final production===
The quality of Type 94 Nambu pistols decreased towards the end of World War II as the Japanese faced bombing raids from allied forces and material shortages increased.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH219&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; This drastic change in quality from late March 1945, onwards with all quality standards appearing to disappear towards the end of June 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH220&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 220&lt;/ref&gt; The smooth wooden finished grip was replaced by a [[bakelite]] checkered pattern.&lt;ref name=&quot;jsp16&quot;/&gt; Many pistols were not serialized and no pistols have been reported that bear July 1945 manufacture date.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH220&quot;/&gt; Only four unserialized and undated pistols are known to exist and include mismatch parts with no inspection marks, lanyard loops, and extractors.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH221&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 221&lt;/ref&gt; A small number of pistols made during the final production stages include earlier production dates and appear to have been salvaged from previously discarded pistols that had minor or cosmetic defects.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH221&quot;/&gt;

==Disassembly==
Disassembly of the Type 94 Nambu pistol is considered difficult and can lead to damage to the pistol if done carelessly.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;/&gt;  After clearing the Type 94, the operator must draw the slide against the magazine follower to hold the bolt to the rear of the pistol.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;/&gt; This will allow the crossbolt to be released after the firing pin is depressed.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH193&quot;/&gt; Removal of the crossbolt without depressing the firing pin will damage both the firing pin and the crossbolt.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH194&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 194&lt;/ref&gt; Removing the crossbolt is further complicated as the disassemblers hands are both holding the pistol and depressing the firing pin.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH194&quot;/&gt;

[[File:TYPE94ERROR.JPG|left|thumb|Diagram showing the location of the sear bar that can be jarred loose and cause a misfire]]

==Holster==
Holsters for the Type 94 pistol were generally made from either pigskin or cowhide leather and ranged in color from tan to dark reddish brown.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH225&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; Holsters faced the same degradation in quality as the Type 94 pistol.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH225&quot;/&gt; As supplies of leather were exhausted in Japan, holsters manufactured in 1944 became fabricated from olive drab fabric.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH225&quot;/&gt; The Type 94 pistol holster is distinguishable from other Japanese holsters having a pointed closure flap and a vertically positioned magazine pouch.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH224&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 224&lt;/ref&gt; The pouch tow has a narrow extension to accommodate a cleaning rod.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH225&quot;/&gt; The majority of holsters were made in civilian owned [[tanneries]] with some ink stamped with arsenal and inspection marks.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH226&quot;&gt;Derby, Harry L. ''Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945'' (2003), p. 226&lt;/ref&gt; A belt loop and two shoulder strap &quot;D&quot; rings are provided on the rear of the holster and are made from brass, galvanized steel, or nickel plating.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH225&quot;/&gt;

==Unintentional firing==
The poor design of the breech allowed the Type 94 Nambu to be fired unintentionally.&lt;ref name=&quot;msa67&quot;/&gt; The sear bar on the Type 94 Nambu converts the forward pull of the trigger into a lateral movement that frees the hammer.&lt;ref name=&quot;jsp23&quot;&gt;Skennerton, Ian, ''Japanese Service Pistols Handbook'' (2008) p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; Because the sear bar is on the outside of the pistol,&lt;ref name=&quot;jsp23&quot;/&gt; it could be jarred loose during engagement if the pistol was cocked and handled carelessly.&lt;ref name=&quot;pow190&quot;/&gt; The forward end of the  sear bar would need to be depressed approximately  2mm to cause the weapon to fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;/&gt; The ability to fire the Type 94 without pulling the trigger gave rise to war stories of Japanese soldiers surrendering, only to fire the pistol, earning the pistol monikers such as the &quot;suicide special&quot; and the &quot;surrender pistol&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;/&gt; These stories are widely discredited because of the difficulty to fire the weapon by squeezing the sear bar.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH189&quot;/&gt; If the safety is engaged on the Type 94 it is impossible for the weapon to discharge unintentionally.&lt;ref name=&quot;JMCH191&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite book|last=Derby|first=Harry L.|author2=Brown, James D. |title=Japanese Military Cartridge Handguns 1893–1945|publisher=Schiffer Publishing|location=Atglen, Philadelphia |year=2003|isbn=0-7643-1780-6}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hogg|first=Ian|author2=Weeks, John |title=Military Small Arms of the 20th Century|edition=7th|publisher=Krause Publications|location=Iola, Wisconsin |year=2000|isbn=0-87341-824-7}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hogg|first=Ian|author2=Walter, John |title=Pistols of the World|edition=4th|publisher=Krause Publications|location=Iola, Wisconsin|year=2004|isbn=0-87349-460-1}}
* {{Cite book|last=Kinard|first=Jeff|title=Pistols: An Illustrated History of Their Impact|publisher=ABC-CLIO|location=Santa Barbara, California| year=2003|isbn=1-85109-470-9}}
* {{Cite book|last=Miller|first=David|title=Fighting Men of World War II Axis Forces  Uniforms, Equipment, and Weapons|publisher=Chartwell Book INC|location=New York, New York |year=2010|isbn=978-0-7858-2815-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=Skennerton|first=Ian|title=Japanese Service Pistols|publisher=Arms and Militaria Press|location=Labrador, Queensland |year=2008|isbn=978-0-949749-88-8}}
{{refend}}

{{Commons category|Type 94 8 mm Pistol|Type 94}}

{{Japanese WWII infantry weapons}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Type 94 8 Mm Pistol}}
[[Category:Semi-automatic pistols of Japan]]
[[Category:8 mm firearms]]
[[Category:World War II infantry weapons of Japan]]</text>
      <sha1>cwngbahd6727zvil7qmhlosc9mygarq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
