<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>USS Monitor</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32197</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746457334</id>
      <parentid>746455923</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-27T14:39:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Andy Dingley</username>
        <id>3606755</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/64.83.131.35|64.83.131.35]] ([[User talk:64.83.131.35|talk]]) to last revision by Llammakey. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="121478">{{About|the first USS Monitor, a Civil War ironclad|the World War II vehicle landing ship|USS Monitor (LSV-5)}}
{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:USS Monitor at sea.jpg|300px|border]]
|Ship caption=USS ''Monitor'' at sea
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country= United States
|Ship flag={{USN flag|1862}}
|Ship name=USS ''Monitor''
|Ship namesake=
|Ship ordered=4 October 1861
|Ship builder=[[Continental Iron Works]], [[Greenpoint, Brooklyn]], U.S.
|Ship original cost=$275,000
|Ship laid down=25 October 1861
|Ship launched=30 January 1862
|Ship sponsor=
|Ship christened=
|Ship completed=
|Ship commissioned=25 February 1862
|Ship struck=
|Ship motto=
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honors=
|Ship fate=Lost at sea, 31 December 1862
|Ship status=Wreck located 27 August 1973, partially [[Marine salvage|salvaged]]
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship type=[[Monitor (warship)|Monitor]]
|Ship tons burthen=776 tons ([[Builder's Old Measurement|bm]])
|Ship displacement={{convert|987|LT|t}}
|Ship length={{convert|179|ft|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|41|ft|6|in|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|10|ft|6|in|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship power=*{{convert|320|ihp|lk=in|abbr=on}}
*2 × Horizontal [[fire-tube boiler]]s
|Ship propulsion=*1 × [[Propeller]]
*1 × [[Marine steam engine#Vibrating lever|Vibrating-lever steam engine]]
|Ship speed={{convert|6|kn|lk=in}}
|Ship range=
|Ship complement=49 officers and enlisted men
|Ship armament=2 × {{convert|11|in|mm|adj=on}} [[smoothbore]] [[Dahlgren gun]]s
|Ship armor=*[[Gun turret]]: {{convert|8|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
*[[Belt armor|Waterline belt]]: {{convert|3|-|5|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
*[[Deck (ship)|Deck]]: {{convert|1|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
*[[Pilot house]]: {{convert|9|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}

|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox NRHP
  | name = USS ''Monitor''
  | embed = yes
  | nrhp_type = nhl
  | image = 
  | caption =
  | nearest_city= [[Cape Hatteras, North Carolina]]
  | locmapin = North Carolina#USA
  | built = 1862
  | architect = Ericsson, John
  | architecture = Other, Ironclad warship
  | added = 11 October 1974
  | designated_nrhp_type = 23 June 1986
  | area = {{convert|9.9|acre}}
  | governing_body = Federal
  | refnum = 74002299&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|version=2010a}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
|}

'''USS ''Monitor''''' was an iron-hulled [[steamship]]. Built during the American Civil War, she was the first [[ironclad warship]] commissioned by the [[Union Navy]].{{efn|The first ironclad warship commissioned by the United States was the {{Sclass2-|City|ironclad|1}} {{USS|Carondelet|1861|6}} commissioned on 15 January 1862. While manned by Union Navy officers and enlisted personnel, the construction of the [[Western Gunboat Flotilla]] was funded by the [[War Department (US)|War Department]], and at her commissioning the ''Carondelet'' was [[Union Army]] (rather than Navy) property.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Silverstone|Silverstone, 2006]], pp. 109, 112.&lt;/ref&gt;}} ''Monitor'' is most famous for her central role in the [[Battle of Hampton Roads]] on 9 March 1862, where, under the command of Lieutenant [[John Lorimer Worden|John Worden]], she fought the [[casemate ironclad]] {{ship|CSS|Virginia}} (built on the hull of the former [[steam frigate]] {{USS|Merrimack|1855|6}}) to a standstill. The unique design of the ship, distinguished by its [[gun turret|revolving turret]] which was designed by American inventor [[Theodore Timby]], was quickly duplicated and established the [[Monitor (warship)|monitor type]] of warship.

The remainder of the ship was designed by the Swedish-born engineer and inventor [[John Ericsson]] and hurriedly built in [[Brooklyn]] in only 101 days. ''Monitor'' presented a new concept in ship design and employed a variety of new inventions and innovations in ship building that caught the attention of the world. The impetus to build ''Monitor'' was prompted by the news that the Confederates were building an ironclad warship, named ''Virginia'', that could effectively engage the Union ships blockading [[Hampton Roads]] and the [[James River]] leading to [[Richmond, Virginia|Richmond]] and ultimately advance on [[Washington, D.C.]] and other cities, virtually unchallenged. Before ''Monitor'' could reach Hampton Roads, the Confederate ironclad had destroyed the sail frigates {{USS|Cumberland|1842|6}} and {{USS|Congress|1841|6}} and had run the steam frigate {{USS|Minnesota|1855|6}} [[Ship grounding|aground]]. That night ''Monitor'' arrived and the following morning, just before ''Virginia'' was about to finish off ''Minnesota'', the new Union ironclad confronted the Confederate ship, preventing her from wreaking further destruction on the wooden Union ships. A four-hour battle ensued, both ships pounding the other with close-range cannon fire, although neither ship could destroy or seriously damage the other. This was the first-ever battle fought between two armored warships and marked a turning point in naval warfare.

After the Confederates were forced to destroy ''Virginia'' as they withdrew in early May, ''Monitor'' sailed up the James River to support the Union Army during the [[Peninsula Campaign]]. The ship participated in the [[Battle of Drewry's Bluff]] later that month and remained in the area giving support to General McClellan's forces on land until she was ordered to join the [[Union blockade|blockaders]] off North Carolina in December. On her way there she [[Shipwrecking#Instability and foundering|foundered]] while under tow, during a storm off [[Cape Hatteras]] on the last day of the year. ''Monitor''{{'}}s wreck was discovered in 1973 and has been partially [[Marine salvage|salvaged]]. Her guns, [[gun turret]], engine and other relics are on display at the [[Mariners' Museum]] in [[Newport News, Virginia]].

==Conception==
While the concept of ships protected by armor existed before the advent of the ironclad ''Monitor'',&lt;ref name=Bennett212&gt;[[#Bennett|Bennett, 1900]], pp. 212–13.&lt;/ref&gt; the need for iron plating on ships only arose after the [[shell (projectile)|shell]]-firing cannon was introduced to naval warfare in the 1820s. The use of heavy iron plating on the sides of warships was not practical until steam propulsion matured enough to carry its great weight. Developments in gun technology had progressed by the 1840s so that no practical thickness of wood could withstand the power of a shell.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1933]], pp. 3–9.&lt;/ref&gt;  In response, the United States began construction in 1854 of a steam-powered ironclad warship, ''[[Stevens Battery]]'',&lt;ref name=Gardiner50&gt;[[#Gardiner|Gardiner, 1992]], pp. 50–55.&lt;/ref&gt; but work was delayed and the designer, [[Robert L. Stevens|Robert Stevens]], died in 1856, stalling further work. Since there was no pressing need for such a ship at the time, there was little demand to continue work on the unfinished vessel.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Konstam2|Konstam, 2002]], p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; It was France that introduced the first operational armored ships as well as the first shell guns and rifled cannons.&lt;ref name=Bennett64&gt;[[#Bennett|Bennett, 1900]], p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt;  Experience during the [[Crimean War]] of 1854–55 showed that armored ships could withstand repeated hits without significant damage when French ironclad [[floating batteries]] defeated Russian coastal fortifications during the [[Battle of Kinburn (1855)|Battle of Kinburn]]. Ericsson claimed to have sent the French [[Emperor]] [[Napoléon III]] a proposal for a monitor-type design, with a gun turret, in September 1854, but no record of any such submission could be found in the archives of the French Ministry of the Navy (''[[Ministre de la Marine]]'') when they were searched by naval historian [[James Phinney Baxter III]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1933]], pp. 184–85.&lt;/ref&gt; The French followed those ships with the first ocean-going ironclad, the [[armored frigate]] {{ship|French ironclad|Gloire||2}} in 1859, and the British responded with {{HMS|Warrior|1860|6}}.&lt;ref name=Gardiner50/&gt;

The [[Union Navy]]'s attitude towards ironclads changed quickly when it was learned that the Confederates were converting the captured {{USS|Merrimack|1855|6}} to an ironclad at the naval shipyard in Norfolk, Virginia. Subsequently the urgency of ''Monitor''{{'}}s completion and deployment to Hampton Roads was driven by fears of what the Confederate ironclad, now renamed ''Virginia'',  would be capable of doing, not only to Union ships but to cities along the coast and riverfronts. Northern newspapers published daily accounts of the Confederates' progress in converting the ''Merrimack'' to an ironclad; this prompted the Union Navy to complete and deploy ''Monitor'' as soon as possible.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

Word of ''Merrimack''{{'}}s reconstruction and conversion was confirmed in the North in late February 1862 when Mary Louveste of Norfolk, a freed slave who worked as a housekeeper for one of the Confederate engineers working on ''Merrimack'',&lt;ref&gt;[[#cia|CIA: Historical Document: Black Dispatches'']].&lt;/ref&gt; made her way through Confederate lines with news that the Confederates were building an ironclad warship. Concealed in her dress was a message from a Union sympathizer who worked in the Navy Yard warning that the former ''Merrimack'', renamed ''Virginia'' by the Confederates, was nearing completion.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Davis96|Davis, 1996]], pp. 214–15.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Accounts vary. Some sources claim she stole and was carrying the ship's plans, rather than a letter from a third party.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sutherland|Sutherland, 2004]], p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Allen115/&gt;&lt;ref name=Tomblin161/&gt;}} Upon her arrival in Washington Mary managed to meet with [[United States Secretary of the Navy|Secretary of the Navy]] [[Gideon Welles]] and informed him that the Confederates were nearing the completion of their ironclad, which surprised Welles. Convinced by the papers Mary was carrying he had production of ''Monitor'' sped up. Welles later recorded in his memoirs that ''Mrs. Louveste encountered no small risk in bringing this information&amp;nbsp;...''&lt;ref name=Allen115&gt;[[#Allen|Allen, 2008]], pp. 115–16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Tomblin161&gt;[[#Tomblin|Tomblin, 2009]], p. 161&lt;/ref&gt;

==Approval==
[[File:Johnericsson.battary.jpg|thumb|184px|left|alt=Photo of Statue of John Ericsson in [[Battery Park]], New York City, holding a model of ''Monitor'' in his hand|Statue of John Ericsson in [[Battery Park]], New York City, with model of ''Monitor'' in hand]]
After the United States received word of the construction of ''Virginia'', [[United States Congress|Congress]] appropriated $1.5 million on 3 August 1861 to build one or more armored steamships. It also ordered the creation of a board to inquire into the various designs proposed for armored ships. The Union Navy advertised for proposals for &quot;iron-clad steam vessels of war&quot; on 7 August and Welles appointed three senior officers as the [[Ironclad Board]] the following day. Their task was to &quot;examine plans for the completion of iron-clad vessels&quot; and consider its costs.&lt;ref name=r5&gt;[[#Roberts99|Roberts, 1999]], p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Members of the Ironclad board included Commodores [[Joseph Smith (1790–1877)|Joseph Smith]], [[Hiram Paulding]] and [[Charles Henry Davis|Charles H. Davis]]. The board lacked experienced ship builders but was compensated by the fact that two of the members had years of shipyard experience.&lt;ref name=r5/&gt;}}

Ericsson originally made no submission to the board, but became involved when [[Cornelius Bushnell]], the sponsor of the proposal that became the armored [[sloop]] {{USS|Galena|1862|6}}, needed to have his design reviewed by a [[naval architect|naval constructor]]. The board required a guarantee from Bushnell that his ship would float despite the weight of its armor&lt;ref&gt;[[#Roberts99|Roberts, 1999]], p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Cornelius H. DeLamater]] of New York City recommended that Bushnell consult with his friend Ericsson.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1933]], p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; The two first met on 9 September and again on the following day, after Ericsson had time to evaluate ''Galena''{{'}}s design. During this second meeting Ericsson showed Bushnell a model of his own design, the future ''Monitor'', derived from his 1854 design. Bushnell got Ericsson's permission to show the model to Welles, who told Bushnell to show it to the board.&lt;ref name=t4/&gt; Upon review of Ericsson's unusual design, the board was skeptical, concerned that such a vessel would not float, especially in rough seas, and rejected the proposal of a completely iron laden ship. [[Abraham Lincoln|President Lincoln]], who had also examined the design, overruled them. Ericsson assured the board his ship would float exclaiming, &quot;The sea shall ride over her and she shall live in it like a duck&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ward-p99&quot;&gt;[[#Ward|Ward, Burns and Burns, 1990]], p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 September, after further deliberations, the board accepted Ericsson's proposal.&lt;ref name=t4&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], p. 224&lt;/ref&gt; The Ironclad Board evaluated 17 different designs, but recommended only three for procurement on 16 September, including Ericsson's ''Monitor'' design.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Roberts99|Roberts, 1999]], pp. 7, 16–17&lt;/ref&gt;

The three ironclad ships selected differed substantially in design and degree of risk. ''Monitor'' was the most innovative design by virtue of its low [[freeboard (nautical)|freeboard]], shallow[[draft (hull)|-draft]] iron hull, and total dependence on steam power. The riskiest element of its design was its rotating [[gun turret]], something that had not previously been tested by any navy.{{efn|British trials of a turret designed by [[Cowper Phipps Coles|Cowper Coles]] on board the [[floating battery]] [[Aetna-class ironclad floating battery|HMS ''Trusty'']] began the same month.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 41–43&lt;/ref&gt;}} Ericsson's guarantee of delivery in 100 days proved to be decisive in choosing his design despite the risk involved.&lt;ref name=r711&gt;[[#Roberts99|Roberts, 1999]], pp. 7–11&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design and description==
[[File:Monitor model2.jpg|thumb|324px|Model of USS ''Monitor'']]
[[File:USS Monitor plans.jpg|thumb|324px|alt=Inboard plans of USS ''Monitor''|&lt;center&gt;Inboard plans of USS ''Monitor''&lt;br/&gt;[[:File:USS Monitor plans2.jpg|See also: Outboard plans]]&lt;/center&gt;]]

''Monitor'' was an unusual vessel in almost every respect and was sometimes sarcastically described by the press and other critics as &quot;Ericsson's folly&quot;, &quot;cheesebox on a raft&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thulesius|Thulesius, 2007]], pp. 108, 113&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bushnell|Bushnell, Ericsson, Welles, 1899]], pp. 17, 41&lt;/ref&gt; and the &quot;Yankee cheesebox&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#McCordock|McCordock, 1938]], p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; The most prominent feature on the vessel was a large cylindrical gun turret mounted [[amidships]] above the low-freeboard upper [[Hull (watercraft)|hull]], also called the &quot;raft&quot;. This extended well past the sides of the lower, more traditionally shaped hull. A small armored [[pilot house]] was fitted on the upper deck towards the bow, however, its position prevented ''Monitor'' from firing her guns straight forward.&lt;ref name=Tucker171/&gt;{{efn|Ericsson later admitted that this was a serious flaw in the ship's design and that the pilot house should have been placed atop the turret.}} One of Ericsson's prime goals in designing the ship was to present the smallest possible target to enemy gunfire.&lt;ref name=t8/&gt; The ship was {{convert|179|ft|m|1}} [[length overall|long overall]], had a [[Beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|41|ft|6|in|m|1}} and had a maximum draft of {{convert|10|ft|6|in|m|1}}. ''Monitor'' had a tonnage of 776 [[Builder's Old Measurement|tons burthen]] and [[displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|987|LT|t}}. Her crew consisted of 49 officers and enlisted men.&lt;ref name=s9&gt;[[#Silverstone|Silverstone]], p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;

The ship was powered by a single-cylinder horizontal [[Marine steam engine#Vibrating lever|vibrating-lever steam engine]],&lt;ref name=ck2/&gt; also designed by Ericsson, which drove a {{convert|9|ft|m|1|adj=on}} propeller,&lt;ref name=t8&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], p. 228.&lt;/ref&gt; whose shaft was nine inches in diameter.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; The engine used steam generated by two horizontal [[fire-tube boiler]]s&lt;ref name=c4&gt;[[#Canney|Canney, 1993]], p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; at a maximum pressure of {{convert|40|psi|kPa kg/cm2|0|abbr=on|lk=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], p. 227&lt;/ref&gt; The {{convert|320|ihp|lk=in|adj=on}} engine was designed to give the ship a top speed of {{convert|8|kn|lk=in}}, but ''Monitor'' was {{convert|1|-|2|kn}} slower in service.&lt;ref name=ck2&gt;[[#Chesneau|Chesneau &amp; Kolesnik, 1979]], p. 119&lt;/ref&gt; The engine had a [[bore (engine)|bore]] of {{convert|36|in|mm|0}} and a [[stroke (engine)|stroke]] of {{convert|22|in|mm|0}}.&lt;ref name=s9/&gt; The ship carried {{convert|100|LT|t}} of coal.&lt;ref name=ck2/&gt; Ventilation for the vessel was supplied by two [[Centrifugal force|centrifugal]] blowers near the stern, each of which was powered by {{convert|6|hp|adj=on}} steam engine. One fan circulated air throughout the ship, but the other one forced air through the boilers, which depended on this forced draught. Leather belts connected the blowers to their engines and they would stretch when wet, often disabling the fans and boilers. The ship's pumps were steam operated and water would accumulate in the ship if the pumps could not get enough steam to work.&lt;ref name=t8/&gt;

[[File:USS Monitor - Transverse hull section through the turret.jpg|thumb|264px|alt=Plans showing view of the transverse hull section through the turret|left|Transverse hull section through the turret]]

''Monitor''{{'}}s turret measured {{convert|20|ft|m|abbr=on}} in diameter and {{convert|9|ft|m|abbr=on}} high, constructed with {{convert|8|in|cm|0}} of armor (11 inches in front at the gun ports) rendering the overall vessel somewhat top heavy. Its rounded shape helped to deflect cannon shot.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mindell|Mindell, 2000]], p. 41&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#McCordock|McCordock, 1938]], p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; A pair of [[donkey engine]]s rotated the turret through a set of gears; a full rotation was made in 22.5 seconds during testing on 9 February 1862.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], p. 226&lt;/ref&gt; Fine control of the turret proved to be difficult as the engine would have to be placed in reverse if the turret overshot its mark or another full rotation could be made. The only way to see out of the turret was through the [[Glossary of nautical terms#G|gun ports]]; when the guns were not in use, or withdrawn for reloading during battle, heavy iron port stoppers would swing down into place to close the gunports.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Canney|Canney, 1993]], pp. 30, 80&lt;/ref&gt; Including the guns, the turret weighed approximately {{convert|160|LT|t|0}}; the entire weight rested on an iron spindle that had to be jacked up using a wedge before the turret could rotate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson p. 225&quot;&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt; The spindle was {{convert|9|in|cm|0}} in diameter which gave it ten times the strength needed in preventing the turret from sliding sideways.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1933]], p. 256&lt;/ref&gt; When not in use, the turret rested on a brass ring on the deck that was intended to form a watertight seal. In service, however, this proved to leak heavily, despite [[caulking]] by the crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson p. 225&quot;/&gt;  The gap between the turret and the deck proved to be a problem as debris and shell fragments entered the gap and jammed the turrets of several {{sclass-|Passaic|monitor|3|warship}}s, which used the same turret design, during the [[First Battle of Charleston Harbor]] in April 1863.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Canney|Canney, 1993]], pp. 79–80&lt;/ref&gt; Direct hits at the turret with heavy shot also had the potential to bend the spindle, which could also jam the turret.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Reed|Reed, 1869]], pp. 253–54.&lt;/ref&gt; To gain access to the turret from below, or to hoist up powder and shot during battle, the turret had to rotate facing directly to [[starboard]], which would line up the entry hatch in the floor of the turret with an opening in the deck below.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Wilson|Wilson, 1896]], p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; The roof of the turret was lightly built to facilitate any needed exchange of the ship's guns and to improve ventilation, with only gravity holding the roof plates in place.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 211–12&lt;/ref&gt;

The turret was intended to mount a pair of {{convert|15|in|adj=on}} [[smoothbore]] [[Dahlgren gun]]s, but they were not ready in time and {{convert|11|in|adj=on}} guns were substituted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson p. 225&quot;/&gt; Each gun weighed approximately {{convert|16000|lb}}. ''Monitor''{{'}}s guns used the standard propellant charge of {{convert|15|lb|kg}} specified by the 1860 ordnance for targets &quot;distant&quot;, &quot;near&quot;, and &quot;ordinary&quot;, established by the gun's designer Dahlgren himself.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Field|Field, 2011]], p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; They could fire a {{convert|136|lb|1|adj=on}} round shot or shell up to a range of {{convert|3650|yd}} at an elevation of +15°.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Olmstead|Olmstead, Stark &amp; Spencer, 1997]], p. 90&lt;/ref&gt;

The top of the armored deck was only about {{convert|18|in|mm}} above the [[waterline]]. It was protected by two layers of {{convert|1/2|in|adj=on}} wrought iron armor. The sides of the &quot;raft&quot; consisted of three to five layers of {{convert|1|in|adj=on}} iron plates, backed by about {{convert|30|in|0}} of pine and oak. Three of the plates extended the full {{convert|60|in|0|adj=on}} height of the side, but the two innermost plates did not extend all the way down. Ericsson originally intended to use either six 1-inch plates or a single outer {{convert|4|in|adj=on}} plate backed by three {{convert|3/4|in|adj=on}} plates, but the thicker plate required too much time to roll.&lt;ref name=c5&gt;[[#Canney|Canney, 1993]], p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; The two innermost plates were riveted together while the outer plates were bolted to the inner ones. A ninth plate, only {{convert|3/4|in|mm}} thick and {{convert|15|in|0}} wide, was bolted over the [[butt joint]]s of the innermost layer of armor. Glass [[porthole]]s in the deck provided natural light for the interior of the ship; in action these were covered by iron plates.&lt;ref name=t8/&gt;

After the duel between the two ironclads at Hampton Roads there was concern by some Navy officials who witnessed the battle that ''Monitor''{{'}}s design might allow for easy boarding by the Confederates. In a letter dated 27 April 1862 Lieutenant Commander O.C. Badger wrote to Lieutenant H. A. Wise, Assistant Inspector of Ordnance, advising the use of &quot;liquid fire&quot;, scalding water from the boiler through hoses and pipes, sprayed out via the vents and pilothouse window, to repel enemy boarders.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Rawson|Rawson, 1898]], pp. 285–86.&lt;/ref&gt; Wise who was aboard and inspected ''Monitor'' after the battle responded in a letter of 30 April 1862: &quot;''With reference to the Monitor, the moment I jumped on board of her after the fight I saw that a steam tug with twenty men could have taken the upper part of her in as many seconds&amp;nbsp;... I hear that hot water pipes are arranged so as to scald the assailants when they may dare to set foot on her.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Rawson|Rawson, 1898]], pp. 293–94&lt;/ref&gt; The chance to employ such a tactic never arose. There are conflicting accounts as to whether such an anti-personnel provision was installed.&lt;ref name=Garrison140&gt;[[#Garrison|Garrison, 1994]], p. 140&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Gentile|Gentile, 1993]], p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;

==Construction==
[[File:Launch USS Monitor.jpg|thumb|264px|alt=drawing showing the Launch of USS ''Monitor'' into the East River at Brooklyn|Launch of USS ''Monitor'', 1862]]
[[Commodore (rank)|Commodore]] [[Joseph Smith (1790–1877)|Joseph Smith]], Chief of the [[Bureau of Yards and Docks]], sent Ericsson formal notice of the acceptance of his proposal on 21 September 1861. Six days later, Ericsson signed a contract with Bushnell, [[John F. Winslow]] and [[John Augustus Griswold|John A. Griswold]] which stated that the four partners would equally share in the profits or the losses incurred by the construction of the ironclad. There was one major delay, however, over the signing of the actual contract with the government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1968]], pp. 258–59&lt;/ref&gt; Welles insisted that if ''Monitor'' didn't prove to be a &quot;complete success&quot;, the builders would have to refund every cent to the government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#McPherson|McPherson, 1988]], pp. 374–375&lt;/ref&gt; Winslow balked at this draconian provision and had to be persuaded by his partners to sign after the Navy rejected his attempt to amend the contract. The contract was finally signed on 4 October for a price of $275,000&lt;ref name=McPherson375/&gt; to be paid in installments as work progressed.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1968]], pp. 257–59&lt;/ref&gt;

Preliminary work had begun well before that date, however, and Ericsson's consortium contracted with Thomas R. Rowland of the Continental Iron Works at [[Greenpoint, Brooklyn]] on 25 October for construction of ''Monitor''{{'}}s hull, with her [[keel]] being laid on that same day. The turret was built and assembled at the [[Novelty Iron Works]] in [[Manhattan]], disassembled and shipped to Greenpoint where it was reassembled.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], pp. 229, 234–37&lt;/ref&gt; The ship's steam engines and machinery were constructed at the [[DeLamater Iron Works]], also in Manhattan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nelson, James L 2005 400 pages&quot;&gt;[[#Nelson2009|Nelson, 2009]] p. 467&lt;/ref&gt; Chief Engineer [[Alban C. Stimers]], who once served aboard ''Merrimack'',&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Thulesius109&gt;[[#Thulesius|Thulesius, 2007]], p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; was appointed Superintendent of the ship while she was undergoing construction.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bennett|Bennett, 1900]], p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; Although never formally assigned to the crew, he remained aboard her as an inspector during her maiden voyage and battle.&lt;ref name=Thulesius109/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;

Construction progressed in fits and starts, plagued by a number of short delays in the delivery of iron and occasional shortages of cash, but they did not significantly delay the ship's progress by more than a few weeks. The hundred days allotted for her construction passed on 12 January, but the Navy chose not to penalize the consortium.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], pp. 236–37&lt;/ref&gt; The name &quot;Monitor&quot;, meaning &quot;one who admonishes and corrects wrongdoers&quot;,&lt;ref name=McPherson375&gt;[[#McPherson|McPherson, 1988]], p. 375&lt;/ref&gt; was proposed by Ericsson on 20 January 1862 and approved by Assistant Secretary of the Navy [[Gustavus Fox]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mariner|Mariners' Museum article, 2013]]&lt;/ref&gt;  While Ericsson stood on its deck in defiance of all his critics who thought she would never float,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein99|Quarstein, 1999]], p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; ''Monitor'' was [[Ship naming and launching|launched]] on 30 January 1862 to the cheers of the watching crowd, even those who had bet that the ship would sink straight to the bottom,&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson p. 237&quot;&gt;[[#Thompson90|Thompson, 1990]], p. 237&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Ship commissioning|commissioned]] on 25 February.&lt;ref name=mon&gt;[[#DANFS|DANFS: ''Monitor'']]&lt;/ref&gt;

Even before ''Monitor'' was commissioned, she ran an unsuccessful set of [[sea trial]]s on 19 February. Valve problems with the main engine and one of the fan engines prevented her from reaching the [[Brooklyn Navy Yard]] from Greenpoint and she had to be towed there the next day. These issues were easily fixed and ''Monitor'' was ordered to sail for Hampton Roads on 26 February, but her departure had to be delayed one day to load ammunition. On the morning of 27 February the ship entered the [[East River]] preparatory to leaving New York, but proved to be all but unsteerable and had to be towed back to the navy yard. Upon examination, the steering gear controlling the [[rudder]] had been improperly installed and Rowland offered to realign the rudder, which he estimated to take only a day. Ericsson, however, preferred to revise the steering gear by adding an extra set of [[pulley]]s as he believed it would take less time. His modification proved to be successful during trials on 4 March.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson p. 237&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bennett|Bennett, 1900]], p.  119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 27–28&lt;/ref&gt; Gunnery trials were successfully performed the previous day, although Stimers twice nearly caused disasters as he did not understand how the [[recoil]] mechanism worked on Ericsson's [[gun carriage|carriage]] for the 11-inch guns. Instead of tightening them to reduce the recoil upon firing, he loosened them so that both guns struck the back of the turret, fortunately without hurting anybody or damaging the guns.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 30–31&lt;/ref&gt;

Ericsson's revolutionary turret, although not without flaws, was a unique concept in gun mounting that was soon adapted and used on naval ships around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Park|Park, 2007]], p. 193&lt;/ref&gt; His ''Monitor'' design employed over forty patented inventions and was completely different from any other naval warship at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ward-p99&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 46&lt;/ref&gt; Because ''Monitor'' was an experimental craft, urgently needed, hurriedly constructed and almost immediately put to sea, a number of problems were discovered during her maiden voyage to Hampton Roads and during the battle there.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein06|Quarstein, 2006]], p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; Yet ''Monitor'' was still able to challenge ''Virginia'' and prevent her from further destroying the remaining ships in the Union [[flotilla]] blockading Hampton Roads.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein06|Quarstein, 2006]], p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;

During the &quot;boom time&quot; of the Civil War, Ericsson could have made a fortune with his inventions used in ''Monitor'', but instead gave the U.S. government all his ''Monitor'' patent rights saying it was his &quot;contribution to the glorious Union cause&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thulesius|Thulesius, 2007]], p. 140&lt;/ref&gt;

==Crew==
[[File:John Lorimer Worden.jpg|thumb|alt=Engraving showing Commander Worden likeness in 1862|Commander Worden in 1862]]

''Monitor''{{'}}s crew were all volunteers and totaled 49 officers and enlisted men as the warship required ten officers: A commander, an executive officer, four engineers, one medical officer, two masters and a paymaster.&lt;ref name=Quarstein40&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; Before Worden was allowed to select, assemble, and commit a crew to ''Monitor'', the vessel had to be completed.&lt;ref name=Quarstein40-41/&gt;
The original officers at the time of ''Monitor''{{'}}s commissioning were:
{|style=&quot;margin: 1em auto 1em auto;&quot;
|+'''Officers of USS ''Monitor'' at commissioning'''&lt;br&gt;(25 February 1862)
|-
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|Lieutenant [[John Lorimer Worden]], Commanding Officer
|-
|Lieutenant [[Samuel Greene|Samuel Dana Greene]], [[Executive officer#Military|Executive Officer]]
|{{nbsp|3}}Third Assistant Engineer, Robinson W. Hands
|-
|[[Master (naval)|Acting Master]], [[Louis N. Stodder]]
|{{nbsp|3}}Fourth Assistant Engineer, Mark T. Sunstrom
|-
|Acting Master, J.N. Webber
|{{nbsp|3}}Acting Assistant Paymaster, William F. Keeler
|-
|First Assistant Engineer, Isaac Newton Jr.
|{{nbsp|3}}Acting Assistant Surgeon, Daniel C. Logue&lt;ref name=Quarstein40/&gt;
|-
|Second Assistant Engineer, Albert B. Campbell
|
|-
|}

Four of the officers were of the line and responsible for the handling of the vessel and operation of guns during battle, while the engineering officers were considered a class unto themselves.&lt;ref name=Quarstein40-41&gt;[[#Quarstein|Quarstein, 2010]], pp. 40–41&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Monitor''{{'}}s turret, Greene and Stodder supervised loading and firing of the two 11-inch Dahlgrens. Each gun was crewed by eight men. Thus, during battle, at least 18 men were present in the turret.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Konstam|Konstam, 2002]], p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; In Worden's report of 27 January 1862 to Welles, he stated he believed 17 men and 2 officers would be the maximum number in the turret that allowed the crew to work without getting in each other's way.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Rawson|Rawson and Woods, 1897]], p. 534&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:MonitorCrew.jpg|thumb|300px|left|alt=photo showing original Officers of Monitor in 1862|&lt;center&gt;Officers on deck of USS ''Monitor''&lt;br&gt;James River, 9 July 1862{{efn|&lt;big&gt;Standing, top row, left to right:&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;
 Master's Mate George Frederickson;&lt;br&gt;
 Third Assistant Engineer Mark Trueman Sunstrom;&lt;br&gt;
 Lieutenant Samuel Dana Greene;&lt;br&gt;
 Lieutenant L. Howard Newman (Executive Officer of USS Galena)&lt;br&gt;
 First Assistant Engineer Isaac Newton.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;big&gt;Seated in chairs, middle row, left to right:&lt;/big&gt; &lt;br&gt;
 Acting Master Louis N. Stodder;&lt;br&gt;
 Acting Assistant Paymaster William F. Keeler;&lt;br&gt;
 Acting Volunteer Lieutenant William Flye;&lt;br&gt;
 Acting Assistant Surgeon Daniel C. Logue.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;big&gt;Seated on deck in front, left to right:&lt;/big&gt; &lt;br&gt;
 Third Assistant Engineer Robinson W. Hands;&lt;br&gt;
 Second Assistant Engineer Albert B. Campbell;&lt;br&gt;
 Acting Master E.V. Gager.&lt;br&gt;
([[Naval History &amp; Heritage Command]] photograph.)}}
----
Other photos:&lt;br&gt;[[:File:USSMonitor1862.1.ws.jpg|''Monitor'' crew members]]&lt;br&gt;[[:File:USSMonitor1862.4.ws.jpg|Crewmembers cooking on deck]]&lt;/center&gt;]]
''Monitor'' also required petty officers: among them was Daniel Toffey, Worden's nephew. Worden had selected Toffey to serve as his Captain's Clerk. Two black Americans were also among the enlisted men in the crew.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 44&lt;/ref&gt; During ''Monitor''{{'}}s service, commanders and several officers were replaced because of injuries or for other reasons.&lt;ref name=Quarstein149/&gt;

Living quarters for the senior officers consisted of eight separate well-furnished cabins, each provided with a small oak table and chair, an oil lamp, shelves and drawers and a canvas floor covering covered with a rug. The entire crew were given goat-skin mats to sleep on. Lighting for each living area was provided by small skylights in the deck above, which were covered by an iron hatch during battle. The officer's wardroom was located forward of the berth deck where officers would eat their meals, hold meetings or socialize during what little spare time they had. It was well furnished with an oriental rug, a large oak table and other such items. Ericsson had personally paid for the costs of all the officer's furnishings.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 50&lt;/ref&gt;

Many details of ''Monitor''{{'}}s history and insights of everyday crew life have been discovered from correspondence sent from the various crew members to family and friends while serving aboard the ironclad. In particular the correspondence of [[George Spencer Geer|George S. Geer]], who sent more than 80 letters, often referred to as ''The Monitor Chronicles'',{{efn|See [[USS Monitor#Bibliography|Bibliography:]] Marvel, William, ed. (2000). ''The Monitor Chronicles: One Sailor's Account&amp;nbsp;...''}} to his wife Martha during the entire time of ''Monitor''{{'}}s service provide many details and insights into every chapter of the ironclad's short lived history, offering a rare perspective of a sailor's experience on the naval front during the Civil War. The letters of Acting Paymaster [[William Frederick Keeler|William F. Keeler]] to his wife Anna also corroborate many of the accounts of affairs that took place aboard the ''Monitor''. The letters of Geer and Keeler are available for viewing and are housed at the [[Mariners' Museum]] in Virginia.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Geer|George S. Geer, 1862, letters to wife Martha]]&lt;/ref&gt; Other crew members were interviewed later in life, like Louis Stodder, who was one of the last crew members to abandon ''Monitor'' minutes before she sank in a storm at sea,&lt;ref name=&quot;Still, 1988, p. 20&quot;&gt;[[#Still88|Still, 1988]], p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; was the last surviving crew member of ''Monitor'' and lived well into the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thulesius|Thulesius, 2007]], p. 138&lt;/ref&gt;

==Service==

On 6 March, the ship departed New York bound for [[Fort Monroe]], Virginia, towed by the ocean-going [[tugboat|tug]] ''Seth Low'' and accompanied by the gunboats {{USS|Currituck|1861|2}} and {{USS|Sachem|1861|2}}.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1968]], pp. 266, 286&lt;/ref&gt; Worden, not trusting the seal between the turret and the hull, and ignoring Ericsson's advice,&lt;ref name=Konstam40&gt;[[#Konstam|Konstam, 2002]], p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; wedged the former in the up position and stuffed [[oakum]] and sail cloth in the gap.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1968]], p. 167&lt;/ref&gt; Rising seas that night washed the oakum away and water poured underneath the turret, as well as through the [[hawsepipe]], various hatches, ventilation pipes, and the two [[funnel (ship)|funnel]]s, so that the belts for the ventilation and boiler fans loosened and fell off and the fires in the boilers were nearly extinguished over the course of the next day; this created a toxic atmosphere in the engine room that knocked out most of the engine-room crew. First Assistant Engineer Isaac Newton ordered the engine room abandoned and had the able-bodied crew drag the afflicted engine room hands to the top of the turret where the fresh air could revive them.&lt;ref name=Konstam40/&gt; Both Newton and Stimers worked desperately to get the blowers to work, but they too succumbed to the noxious fumes and were taken above.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1968]], p. 289&lt;/ref&gt; One [[fireman (steam engine)|fireman]] was able to punch a hole in the fan box, drain the water, and restart the fan. Later that night, the wheel ropes controlling the ship's rudder jammed, making it near impossible to control the ship's heading in the rough seas. ''Monitor'' was now in danger of [[Shipwrecking|foundering]], so Worden signaled ''Seth Low'' for help and had ''Monitor'' towed to calmer waters closer to shore so she was able to restart her engines later that evening. She rounded [[Cape Charles (headland)|Cape Charles]] around 3:00&amp;nbsp;pm on 8 March and entered [[Chesapeake Bay]], reaching [[Hampton Roads]] at 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm, well after the first day's fighting in the Battle of Hampton Roads had concluded.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 54–57, 74&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of Hampton Roads===
{{Main article|Battle of Hampton Roads}}

[[File:The Monitor and Merrimac.jpg|thumb|right|310px|alt=Painting showing ''Monitor'' engaging ''Virginia'', 9 March 1862|USS ''Monitor'' engaging CSS ''Virginia'', 9 March 1862&lt;center&gt;[[:File:Battle of Hampton Roads Map.png|See map of the battle]]&lt;/center&gt;]]

On 8 March 1862, {{ship|CSS|Virginia}}, commanded by [[Commander]] [[Franklin Buchanan]],&lt;ref name=Davis216&gt;[[#Davis96|Davis, 1996]], p. 216&lt;/ref&gt; was ready to engage the Union flotilla blockading the James River.{{efn|Buchanan was commander of the Washington Navy Yard when the war broke out.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Holzer06|Holzer, Mulligan, 2006]], p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;}} ''Virginia'' was powered by ''Merrimack's'' original engines, which had been condemned by the Union Navy before her capture. The ship's chief engineer, H. Ashton Ramsay, served in ''Merrimack'' before the Civil War broke out and knew of the engine's unreliability, but Buchanan pushed forward undaunted.&lt;ref name=Nelson6&gt;[[#Nelson2009|Nelson, 2009]], p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; {{efn|Before setting out to engage the Union blockade Buchanan had quizzed Ramsay and learned of the history of their questionable reliability.&lt;ref name=Nelson6/&gt;}}

The slow moving ''Virginia'' attacked the Union blockading squadron in Hampton Roads, Virginia, destroying the sail frigates ''Cumberland'' and ''Congress''.{{efn|Serving aboard ''Congress'' was Buchanan's brother, McKean Buchanan.&lt;ref name=Davis216/&gt;}} Early in the battle, the steam frigate {{USS|Minnesota|1855|6}} ran aground while attempting to engage ''Virginia'', and remained stranded throughout the battle. ''Virginia'', however, was unable to attack ''Minnesota'' before daylight faded. That day Buchanan was severely wounded in the leg and was relieved of command by [[Catesby ap Roger Jones]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Konstam|Konstam, 2002]], p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

Days before the battle a telegraph cable was laid between Fortress Monroe, which overlooked Hampton Roads, and Washington.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;  where Washington was immediately informed of the dire situation after the initial battle.  Many were now concerned ''Virginia'' would put to sea and begin bombarding cities such as New York while others feared she would ascend the [[Potomac River]] and attack Washington.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein99|Quarstein, 1999]], p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; In an emergency meeting among President Lincoln, Secretary of War [[Edwin M. Stanton]], Secretary Welles and other senior naval officers, inquiries were made about ''Monitor''{{'}}s ability to stop ''Virginia''{{'}}s prospect of further destruction. When the temperamental Stanton learned that ''Monitor'' had only two guns he expressed contempt and rage as he paced back and forth, further increasing the anxiety and despair among members of the meeting. Assurances from Admiral Dahlgren and other officers that ''Virginia'' was too massive to effectively approach Washington and that ''Monitor'' was capable of the challenge offered him no consolation. After further deliberations Lincoln was finally assured but Stanton remained almost in a state of terror and sent telegrams to various governors and mayors of the coastal states warning them of the danger.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1933]], p. 297&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Welles|Welles Diary]], Vol. I, p. 65&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently Stanton approved a plan to load some sixty canal boats with stone and gravel and sink them in the Potomac, but Welles was able to convince Lincoln at the last moment that such a plan would only prevent ''Monitor'' and other Union ships from reaching Washington and that the barges should only be sunk if and when ''Virginia'' was able to make her way up the Potomac.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Welles|Welles Diary]], Vol. I, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt;

About 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm, ''Monitor'' finally arrived on the scene only to discover the destruction that ''Virginia'' had already wrought on the Union fleet. Worden was ordered upon reaching Hampton Roads to weigh anchor alongside {{USS|Roanoke|1855|6}} and report to Captain [[John Marston (sailor)|John Marston]] where Worden was briefed of the situation and received further orders to protect the grounded ''Minnesota''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein99|Quarstein, 1999]], p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Field|Field, 2011]], p. 44&lt;/ref&gt; By midnight, under the cover of darkness, ''Monitor'' quietly pulled up alongside and behind the ''Minnesota'' and waited.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Wagner|Wagner, 2002]], p. 553&lt;/ref&gt;

====Duel of the ironclads====
The next morning at about 6:00&amp;nbsp;am ''Virginia'', accompanied by {{ship|CSS|Jamestown||2}}, {{ship|CSS|Patrick Henry||2}} and {{ship|CSS|Teaser||2}}, got underway from [[Sewell's Point]] to finish off ''Minnesota'' and the rest of the blockaders, but were delayed sailing out into Hampton Roads because of heavy fog until about 8:00&amp;nbsp;am.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein99|Quarstein, 1999]], p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Monitor'' Worden was already at his station in the pilot house while Greene took command of the turret.&lt;ref name=Still18&gt;[[#Still|Still, 1988]], p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; Samuel Howard, Acting Master of ''Minnesota'' who was familiar with Hampton Roads with its varying depths and shallow areas, had volunteered to be the pilot the night before and thus was accepted, while Quarter Master [[Peter Williams (Medal of Honor)|Peter Williams]] steered the vessel throughout the battle (Williams was later awarded the [[Medal of Honor]] for this act).&lt;ref&gt;[[#Field|Field, 2011]], pp. 38, 46&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], pp. 181, 191&lt;/ref&gt; The speaking tube used to communicate between the pilothouse and the turret had broken early in the action so Keeler and captain's clerk Daniel Toffey{{efn|Toffey was Worden's nephew.&lt;ref name=Quarstein78/&gt;}} had to relay commands from Worden to Greene.&lt;ref name=Quarstein78&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Greene/&gt; As ''Virginia'' was approaching she began firing at ''Minnesota'' from more than a mile away, a few of her shells hitting the vessel. When the firing was heard in the distance, Greene sent paymaster Keeler to the pilot house for permission to open fire as soon as possible where Worden ordered,&lt;ref name=Still18/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hoehling155&gt;[[#Hoehling|Hoehling, 1993]], p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Tell Mr. Green not to fire till I give the word, to be cool and deliberate, to take sure aim and not waste a shot.&quot;&lt;ref name=Hoehling155/&gt;

''Monitor'', to the surprise of ''Virginia''{{'}}s crew, had emerged from behind ''Minnesota'' and went straight for the approaching ''Virginia'' and positioned herself between her and the grounded ''Minnesota'', preventing the Confederate ironclad from further engaging the vulnerable wooden ship at close range. At 8:45&amp;nbsp;am Worden gave the order to fire where Greene fired the first shots of the battle between the two ironclads which harmlessly deflected off the Confederate ironclad. During the battle ''Monitor'' fired solid shot, about once every eight minutes, while ''Virginia'' fired shell exclusively.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Maclay|Maclay, 1894]], p. 314&lt;/ref&gt; The ironclads generally fought at close range for about four hours, ending at 12:15pm,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ward|Ward, Burns and Burns, 1990]], pp. 95, 101&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Accounts vary, some claim the battle lasted no more than three and a half hours,&lt;ref name=Tucker171/&gt; while some claim as many as five hours.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Varhola|Varhola, 1999]], p. 221&lt;/ref&gt;}} ranging from a few yards to more than a hundred. Both ships were constantly in motion, maintaining a circular pattern. Because of ''Virginia''{{'}}s weak engines, massive size and weight and with a draft of {{convert|22|ft|m|abbr=on}}, she was slow and difficult to maneuver, taking her half an hour to complete a 180-degree turn.&lt;ref&gt;[[#McPherson|McPherson, 1988]], pp. 373–74&lt;/ref&gt;

During the engagement, ''Monitor''{{'}}s turret began to malfunction, making it extremely difficult to turn and stop at a given position, so the crew simply let the turret continuously turn and fired their guns &quot;on the fly&quot; as they bore on ''Virginia''. Several times, ''Monitor'' received direct hits on the turret, causing some bolts to violently shear off and ricochet around inside. The deafening sound of the impact stunned some of the crew, causing nose and ear bleeding.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 109–11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=leckie211&gt;[[#Leckie|Leckie, 1990]], p. 211&lt;/ref&gt; However, neither vessel was able to sink or seriously damage the other. At one point, ''Virginia'' attempted to ram, but only struck ''Monitor'' a glancing blow and did no damage. The collision did, however, aggravate the damage to ''Virginia''{{'}}s bow from when she had previously rammed ''Cumberland''. ''Monitor'' was also unable to do significant damage to ''Virginia'', possibly due to the fact that her guns were firing with reduced charges, on advice from Commander [[John Dahlgren]], the gun's designer, who lacked the &quot;preliminary information&quot; needed to determine what amount of charge was needed to &quot;pierce, dislocate or dislodge iron plates&quot; of various thicknesses and configurations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nelson, James L 2005 400 pages&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dahlgren279&gt;[[#Dahlgren|Dahlgren, 1882]], p. 279&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|In a letter of 19 March 1862, to Captain A. A. Harwood, Chief of Bureau of Ordnance and hydrography, Dahlgren emphasized &quot;''A subject so important cannot be perfected without much reflection and extensive experiment. But we lack almost the preliminary information indispensable to commence with.''&quot;&lt;ref name=Dahlgren279/&gt;}} During the battle Stodder was stationed at the wheel that controlled the turning of the turret but at one point when he was leaning against its side the turret received a direct hit directly opposite to him which knocked him clear across the inside, rendering him unconscious, at where he was taken below to recover and relieved by Stimers.&lt;ref name=Greene&gt;[[#Green|Greene letter, 1862]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Maclay|Maclay, 1894]], p. 313&lt;/ref&gt;

The two vessels were pounding each other at such close range, they also managed to collide with one another at five different times.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ward|Ward, Burns and Burns, 1990]], p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; By 11:00&amp;nbsp;am ''Monitor''{{'}}s supply of shot in the turret had been used up. With one of the hatches to the gun ports damaged and jammed shut she hauled off to shallow waters to resupply the turret and effect repairs to the damaged hatch, which could not be repaired. During the lull in the battle Worden climbed through the gun port out onto the deck to get a better view of the overall situation. ''Virginia'', seeing ''Monitor'' turn away turned her attention to the ''Minnesota'' and fired shots that set the wooden vessel ablaze, also destroying the nearby tugboat ''Dragon''. When the turret was resupplied with ammunition Worden returned to battle with only one gun in operation.&lt;ref name=Field56&gt;[[#Field|Field, 2011]], p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;

Towards the end of the engagement, Worden directed Williams to steer ''Monitor'' around the stern of Confederate ironclad, where [[John Taylor Wood|Lieutenant Wood]] fired his 7-inch Brooke gun at the vessel's [[pilothouse]], striking the forward side directly beneath the sight hold, cracking the structural &quot;iron log&quot; along the base of the narrow opening just as Worden was peering out.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Field|Field, 2011]], pp. 36–37, 56–57&lt;/ref&gt; Worden was heard to have cried out, ''My eyes—I am blind!'' Others in the pilothouse had also been hit with fragments and were also bleeding.&lt;ref name=Holzer14&gt;[[#Holzer06|Holzer, Mulligan, 2006]], p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; Temporarily blinded by shell fragments and gunpowder residue from the explosion and believing the pilothouse to be severely damaged, Worden ordered Williams to sheer off into shallow water, where ''Virginia'' with her deep draft could not follow. There ''Monitor'' drifted idly for about twenty minutes.&lt;ref name=Wilson32&gt;[[#Wilson|Wilson, 1896]], p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; At the time the pilothouse was struck Worden's injury was only known to those in the pilothouse and immediately nearby. With Worden severely wounded, command passed to the Executive Officer, [[Samuel Greene]]. Taken by surprise and confused he hesitated briefly and was undecided as to what action to take next,&lt;ref name=Holzer14/&gt; but after assessing the damage soon ordered ''Monitor'' to return to the battle area.&lt;ref name=Greene/&gt;&lt;ref name=Field56/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baxter|Baxter, 1933]], p. 294&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after ''Monitor'' withdrew , ''Virginia'' had run aground at which time Commander Jones came down from the spar deck only to find the gun crews not returning fire. Jones demanded to know why and was briefed by Lieutenant [[John R. Eggleston|Eggleston]] that powder was low and precious and given ''Monitor''{{'}}s resistance to shot after two hours of battle, maintained that continued firing at that point would only be a waste of ammunition.&lt;ref name=Tucker171&gt;[[#Tucker|Tucker, 2006]], p. 171&lt;/ref&gt; ''Virginia'' soon managed to break away and headed back towards Norfolk, believing that ''Monitor'' had withdrawn from battle. Greene, now in command, did not pursue ''Virginia''&lt;ref&gt;[[#Still88|Still, 1988]], p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; and, like Worden, was under orders to stay with and protect ''Minnesota'',&lt;ref&gt;[[#Holzer06|Holzer, Mulligan, 2006]], p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; an action for which he was later criticized.

As a result of the duel between the two ironclads, ''Monitor'' had been struck twenty-two times, including nine hits to the turret and two hits to the pilothouse. She had managed to fire forty-one shots from her pair of Dahlgren guns. ''Virginia'' had sustained ninety-seven indentations to her armor from the fire of ''Monitor'' and other ships. Neither ship had sustained any significant damage, and there were no casualties incurred on either side. In the opinion of ''Virginia''{{'}}s commander Jones and her other officers, ''Monitor'' could have sunk their ship had she hit the vessel at the waterline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson32&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;

After an informal war council with his officers, ''Virginia''{{'}}s captain decided to return to [[Norfolk, Virginia|Norfolk]] for repairs. ''Monitor'' arrived back on the scene as ''Virginia'' was leaving. Greene, under orders to protect ''Minnesota'', did not pursue.&lt;ref name=Wagner553&gt;[[#Wagner|Wagner, Galleghar, Finkelman, 2002]], p. 553&lt;/ref&gt;

Strategically, the battle between these two ships was considered the most definitive naval battle of the Civil War. The battle itself was largely considered a draw, though it could be argued ''Virginia'' did slightly more damage.&lt;ref name=Wilson32/&gt; ''Monitor'' did successfully defend ''Minnesota'' and the rest of the U.S. blockading force, while ''Virginia'' was unable to complete the destruction she started the previous day. The battle between the two ironclads marked a turning point in the way naval warfare would be fought in the immediate future and beyond.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Konstam|Konstam, 2002]], p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; Strategically, nothing had changed: the Union still controlled Hampton Roads and the Confederates still held several rivers and Norfolk,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Davis75|Davis, 1975]], p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; making it a strategic victory for the North. The battle of the ironclads led to what was referred to as &quot;Monitor fever&quot; in the North. During the course of the war other and improved Monitor designs emerged with a total of 60 ironclads built.&lt;ref name=Wagner553/&gt;

====Events after the battle====
[[File:USS Monitor James River 1862.jpg|thumb|264px|left|alt=Photo showing Officers standing on deck, one seated|&lt;center&gt;''Monitor'' on the [[James River]], Virginia, 1862
----
Officers on deck (left to right): Robinson W. Hands, Louis N. Stodder, Albert B. Campbell (seated), William Flye (with binoculars).&lt;br&gt;Note dents in turret from cannon fire.&lt;br&gt;(Photo courtesy U.S. Navy)&lt;/center&gt;]]

Immediately following the battle Stimers telegraphed Ericsson, congratulating and thanking him for making it possible to confront the Confederate ironclad and for &quot;saving the day&quot;. No sooner than ''Monitor'' had weighed anchor, numerous small boats and spectators on shore flocked around the ship to congratulate the crew for what they regarded as their victory over ''Virginia''. Assistant Secretary Fox, who observed the entire battle from aboard ''Minnesota'' came aboard ''Monitor'' and jokingly told her officers, &quot;''Well gentlemen, you don't look as though you just went through one of the greatest naval conflicts on record''&quot;. A small tug soon came alongside and the blinded Worden was brought up from his cabin while crew members and spectators cheered. He was taken directly to Fort Monroe for preliminary treatment, then to a hospital in Washington shortly thereafter.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;

Engineers Stimers and Newton soon began repairing the damage to the pilot house and reconfigured the sides from an upright position to a slope of thirty degrees to deflect shot. During this time, Mrs. Worden personally brought news of her husband's progress and recovery and was optimistic, informing the crew his eyesight would soon return but he would be laid up for some time. She also informed them President Lincoln had personally paid Worden a visit extending his gratitude.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 97&lt;/ref&gt; However Worden was later taken to his summer home in New York and remained unconscious for three months but never fully recovered.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Still88|Still, 1988]], p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

The Confederates were also celebrating what they considered a victory, as crowds of spectators gathered along the banks of the [[Elizabeth River (Virginia)|Elizabeth River]], cheering and waving flags, handkerchiefs and hats as ''Virginia'', displaying the captured [[ensign]] of ''Congress'', passed along up the river. The Confederate government was ecstatic and immediately promoted Commander Buchanan to Admiral.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein12|Quarstein, 2012]], p. 169&lt;/ref&gt;

Both the Union and Confederacy soon came up with plans for defeating the other's ironclad. Oddly, these did not depend on their own ironclads. The Union Navy chartered a large ship (the [[Paddle steamer|sidewheeler]] {{USS|Vanderbilt|1862|6}}) and reinforced her bow with steel specifically to be used as a [[naval ram]],&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; provided ''Virginia'' steamed far enough out into Hampton Roads.

On 11 April, ''Virginia'',  accompanied by a number of gunboats, steamed into Hampton Roads to Sewell's Point at the southeast edge, almost over to [[Newport News]], in a challenge to ''Monitor'' in an attempt to lure the Union ironclad into battle.

''Virginia'' fired a few shots ineffectively at very long range, however, while ''Monitor'' returned fire, she stayed near Fort Monroe, ready to fight if ''Virginia'' came to attack the Federal force congregated there.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Bennett|Bennett, 1900]], pp. 136–37&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, ''Vanderbilt'' was in position to ram ''Virginia'' if she approached the fort. ''Virginia'' did not take the bait.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 88&lt;/ref&gt; In a further attempt to entice ''Monitor'' closer to the Confederate side, so she could be boarded, the James River Squadron moved in and captured three merchant ships, the brigs ''Marcus'' and ''Sabout'', and the schooner ''Catherine T. Dix''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; These had been grounded and abandoned when they sighted ''Virginia'' entering the Roads. Their flags were then hoisted &quot;[[Distress signal#Flags|Union-side down]]&quot; to taunt ''Monitor'' into a fight as they were towed back to Norfolk. In the end both sides had failed to provoke a fight on their terms.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Anderson|Anderson, 1989]], pp. 77–78&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Confederate Navy]] originally had devised a plan where the [[James River Squadron]] would swarm ''Monitor'' with a party of men with the intention of capturing the vessel by boarding and disabling her by using heavy hammers to drive iron wedges under and disabling the turret and by covering the pilot house with a wet sail effectively blinding the pilot. Others would throw combustibles down the ventilation openings and smoke holes. At one point Jones made such an attempt to board the vessel but she managed to slip away around the stern of ''Virginia'' in time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Field56&quot;/&gt;

A second meeting occurred on 8 May, when ''Virginia'' came out while ''Monitor'' and four other Federal ships bombarded Confederate batteries at Sewell's Point. The Federal ships retired slowly to Fort Monroe, hoping to lure ''Virginia'' into the Roads. She did not follow, however, and after firing a gun to windward as a sign of contempt, anchored off Sewell's Point. Later when Confederate forces abandoned Norfolk on 11 May 1862, they were forced to destroy ''Virginia''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein12|Quarstein, 2012]], p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of Drewry's Bluff===
[[File:Battle of Drewry's Bluff.jpg|thumb|244px|alt=Engraving showing ships on the James River during the Battle of Drewy's Bluff|Battle of Drewry's Bluff]]
{{main article|Battle of Drewry's Bluff}}
After the destruction of ''Virginia'', ''Monitor'' was free to assist the [[Union Army]] and [[George B. McClellan|General McClellan's]] campaign against Richmond.  As the Navy always gave command to officers based on seniority Greene was passed over the day after the battle and was replaced with Lieutenant [[Thomas O. Selfridge]]. Two days later, Selfridge was in turn relieved by Lieutenant [[William Nicholson Jeffers]] on 15 May 1862.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Davis75|Davis, 1975]], p. 147&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fuller178&gt;[[#Fuller|Fuller, 2008]], p. 178&lt;/ref&gt; ''Monitor'' was now part of a flotilla under the command of Admiral [[John Rodgers (American Civil War naval officer)|John Rodgers]] aboard ''Galena'', along with three other gunboats which steamed up the James River and engaged the Confederate batteries at [[Drewry's Bluff]]. The force had instructions to coordinate their efforts with McClellan's forces on land and push on towards Richmond to bombard the city into surrender if possible. Without any assistance, the task force got within {{convert|8|mi|km|abbr=on}} of the Confederate capital but could not proceed further because of sunken vessels and debris placed in the river blocking further passage. There were also artillery batteries at [[Fort Darling]] overlooking and guarding the approach, along with other heavy guns and sharpshooters positioned along the river banks. The fort was strategically situated on the west bank of the James River atop of a [[Hill|bluff]] some {{convert|200|ft|m|abbr=on}} above and overlooking the bend in the river.&lt;ref name=Fuller178/&gt;&lt;ref name=Stern90&gt;[[#Stern|Stern, 1962]], p. 90&lt;/ref&gt; ''Monitor'' was of little help in the assault because the confinement and small gun ports of her turret would not allow her to elevate her guns sufficiently to engage the Confederate batteries at close range, so she had to fall back and fire at a greater distance,&lt;ref name=Stern90/&gt; while the other gunboats were unable to overcome the fortifications on their own.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nelson, James L 2005 400 pages&quot;/&gt; After ''Monitor'' received only a few hits, without incurring any damage, the Confederates, many former crew members of ''Virginia'' well aware of her ability to withstand cannon shot even at close range,&lt;ref&gt;[[#McCordock|McCordock, 1938]], p. 349&lt;/ref&gt; concentrated their guns on the other ships, especially ''Galena'', which sustained considerable damage and loss of crew members.&lt;ref name=Stern90/&gt; After a near four-hour artillery duel and sustaining numerous hits overall, the flotilla was unable to neutralize the fortification and had to turn back.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Wagner|Wagner, Galleghar, Finkelman, 2002]], p. 530&lt;/ref&gt; Not a single Union ship reached Richmond until near the end of the war, when the city was finally evacuated by the Confederates.&lt;ref name=Stern90/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Wagner|Wagner, Galleghar, Finkelman, 2002]], p. 574&lt;/ref&gt;

After the battle at Drewry's Bluff ''Monitor'' remained on the James River providing support, along with the ''Galena'' and other gunboats, to McClellan's troops at various points along the river including [[Harrison's Landing]]&lt;ref name=Quarstein149&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], pp. 149–50&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tucker06|Tucker, 2006]], p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; which ended in August. However most of the time spent on the river was marked with inactivity and hot weather which had a negative effect on the morale of ''Monitor''{{'}}s crew. During the long hot summer several crew members took sick and were transferred to Hampton Roads while various officers were replaced including ''Monitor''{{'}}s first Engineer Isaac Newton, while Commander Jeffers was replaced by Commander [[Thomas H. Stevens, Jr.]]{{efn|Stevens previously served as commander of {{USS|Maratanza|1861|6}}.&lt;ref name=Quarstein149/&gt;}} on 15 August. By the end of August ''Monitor'' was ordered back to Hampton Roads and dropped anchor nearby the sunken ''Cumberland'' at Newport News Point on 30 August, much to the approval of the crew. ''Monitor''{{'}}s sole purpose now was to blockade the James River from any advances made by the newly constructed {{ship|CSS|Virginia II||2}}, an ironclad ram.&lt;ref name=Quarstein149/&gt;

===Repairs and refit===
In September Captain [[John P. Bankhead]] received orders to take command of ''Monitor'', relieving commander Thomas Stevens, and was sent to Hampton Roads to take charge of the vessel.&lt;ref name=Bankhead&gt;[[#Mariner2013|Mariener's Museum, 2013: ''John P. Bankhead'']]&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after command was passed on to Bankhead  ''Monitor''{{'}}s engines and boilers were condemned by a board of survey which recommended that they be overhauled completely.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Still|Still, 1988]], p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 September the ironclad was sent to the [[Washington Navy Yard]] for repairs&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein06|Quarstein, 2006]], p. 140&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thulesius|Thulesius, 2007]], p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; arriving there on 3 October 1862.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2006]], p. 241&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon arrival at Washington ''Monitor'' and her crew were greeted by a crowd of thousands of cheering admirers who came to see the ship that &quot;saved the nation&quot;. ''Monitor'' was now a premier tourist attraction and the crowd was soon allowed on board to tour the vessel.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarsstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], pp. 155–56&lt;/ref&gt; During this time the vessel was picked clean of artifacts for souvenirs by the touring civilians that came aboard. When Stodder and others came to close up the dock and ship one evening Stodder noted, ''When we came up to clean that night there was not a key, doorknob, [[Escutcheon (furniture)|escutcheon]] – there wasn't a thing that hadn't been carried away.''&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein06|Quarstein, 2006]], p. 241&lt;/ref&gt;

Before ''Monitor'' was put into dry dock for repairs President Lincoln, Navy Secretary Fox, various officials and a few of Worden's close friends arrived to ceremoniously review the vessel and pay respect to the crew and former commander Worden, who after a long and partial recovery arrived for the occasion. Entire regiments were also directed to come by the naval yard and review the ship and honor the crew. ''Monitor''{{'}}s crew assembled on deck in formation with their officers in front, while Lincoln, Fox and other guests stood near the turret. When Worden, with part of his face blacked from the wounds he received at Hampton Roads, came aboard, the heavy guns in the navy yard were fired in [[Salute#Heavy arms: gun salutes|salute]]. President Lincoln came forward and greeted Worden and then introduced him to some of the others. After Lincoln's formal greeting the crew swarmed around Worden and embraced and shook hands with their former commander and thanked God for his recovery and return. Worden called each of them by name and spoke friendly to and complimented each of them personally. When order was restored the President gave a short speech about Worden's career. At Fox's request, Worden gave a speech to the gathering about his voyage from New York to Hampton Roads, the trials they were faced with along the way and of the epic battle between ''Monitor'' and ''Virginia'', while paying [[tribute]] to many of the officers and men involved. In closing he gave special thanks to Ericsson, Lincoln, Welles and all who made construction of ''Monitor'' possible.&lt;ref name=Nelson323&gt;[[#Nelson2009|Nelson, 2009]], p. 323&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Worden|Worden, Greene, 1912]], pp. 1–6, 21–22&lt;/ref&gt;

While ''Monitor'' was undergoing repairs her crew was put aboard {{USS|King Philip|1845|6}} and were eventually granted a furlough by Bankhead who himself went on leave.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 156&lt;/ref&gt; For approximately six weeks the vessel remained in [[drydock]] while her bottom was scraped clean of [[barnacles]] and other sea growth while the engines and boilers were overhauled and the entire vessel cleaned, painted, and a number of improvements made, including an iron shield around the top of the turret.&lt;ref name=Bankhead/&gt; To make the vessel more seaworthy a {{convert|30|ft|m|0}} funnel shaped smokestack was placed over the smoke outlet while taller fresh air vents were installed. The [[berth deck]] below was also enlarged and raised by removing some of the side storerooms and placing them below, thus reducing the height of the interior which now barely allowed the crew to stand upright. Several cranes were also added while interior improvements were made making the confining environment more livable. A large blower that operated with its own engine was installed which drew fresh air down through the pilothouse. During this time the two Dahlgren guns were each engraved with large letters, ''MONITOR &amp; MERRIMAC – WORDEN'' and ''MONITOR &amp; MERRIMAC – ERICSSON'', respectively.{{efn|In the actual engravings the men's names are inscribed below those of the ships' names. e.g.&lt;center&gt;MONITOR &amp; MERRIMAC&lt;br&gt;WORDEN''&lt;/center&gt;}} Additional iron plates were installed covering where dents were made during the previous battles. Each plate was inscribed with the name of the source from where the shell causing the dent was made. i.e. ''Merrimack, Fort Darling'', etc.&lt;ref name=Nelson323/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], pp. 156–57&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stanchions]] were also installed around the perimeter of the freeboard with a rope strung through each making it safer to walk about the deck amid stormy weather and rough seas.&lt;ref name=Nelson323/&gt; ''Monitor'' was finally taken out of drydock on 26 October. By November the ship was fully repaired and refitted, resupplied and ready to return to service.&lt;ref name=Bankhead/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Still88|Still, 1988]], p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final voyage===
[[File:USS Monitor - H58758.jpg|thumb|260px|alt=Engraving of Monitor sinking with rescue vessel in back ground|Engraving of ''Monitor'' sinking]]

On 24 December 1862, orders were issued directing ''Monitor'' to [[Beaufort, North Carolina|Beautfort]], [[North Carolina]] to join {{USS|Passaic|1862|6}} and {{USS|Montauk|1862|6}} for a joint Army-Navy expedition against Wilmington, North Carolina, where she would join the blockade off [[Charleston, South Carolina|Charleston]]. The orders were received by the crew on Christmas Day, some of whom were aboard ''Monitor'' on her harrowing journey from New York to Hampton Roads in March, and were not pleased with the prospect of taking to the high seas once again. Dana Green remarked ''I do not consider this steamer a sea going vessel''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein99|Quarstein, 1999]], p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;

The crew celebrated Christmas aboard ''Monitor'' while berthed at Hampton Roads in what was described as a most merry fashion, while many other celebrations were occurring along the shore. The ship's cook was paid one dollar to prepare a meal for the crew befitting the day; it was received with mixed opinion. That day, ''Monitor'' was made ready for sea, her crew under strict orders not to discuss the impending voyage with anyone, but bad weather delayed her departure until 29 December.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quarstein-p106&quot;&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 106&lt;/ref&gt;

While the design of ''Monitor'' was well-suited for river combat, her low freeboard and heavy turret made her highly unseaworthy in rough waters. Under the command of John P. Bankhead, ''Monitor'' put to sea on 31 December, under tow from {{USS|Rhode Island|1860|6}}, when a heavy storm developed off [[Cape Hatteras|Cape Hatteras, North Carolina]]. Using chalk and a blackboard, Bankhead wrote messages alerting ''Rhode Island'' that if ''Monitor'' needed help she would signal with a red lantern.&lt;ref name=Quarstein171&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 171&lt;/ref&gt;

''Monitor'' was soon in trouble as the storm increased in ferocity. Large waves were splashing over and completely covering the deck and pilot house so the crew temporarily rigged the wheel atop the turret which was manned by Helmsman Francis Butts.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Thulesius|Thulesius, 2007]], p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; Water continued flooding into the vents and ports and the ship began rolling uncontrollably in the high seas. Sometimes she would drop into a wave with such force the entire hull would tremble. Leaks were beginning to appear everywhere. Bankhead ordered the engineers to start the [[Worthington pump]]s, which temporarily stemmed the rising waters, but soon ''Monitor'' was hit by a squall and a series of violent waves and water continued to work its way into the vessel. Right when the Worthington pump could no longer keep pace with the flooding a call came from the engine room that water was gaining there. Realizing the ship was in serious trouble, Bankhead signaled ''Rhode Island'' for help and hoisted the red lantern next to ''Monitor''{{'}}s white running light atop the turret. He then ordered the anchor dropped to stop the ship's rolling and pitching with little effect making it no easier for the rescue boats to get close enough to receive her crew. He then ordered the towline cut and called for volunteers,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], p. 172&lt;/ref&gt; Acting Master Stodder, along with crewmates John Stocking, and James Fenwick volunteered and climbed down from the turret, but eyewitnesses said that as soon as they were on the deck Fenwick and Stocking were quickly swept overboard and drowned. Stodder managed to hang on to the safety lines around the deck and finally cut through the {{convert|13|in|cm|0|abbr=on}} towline with a hatchet.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mariner30|Mariner's Museum, Article: The Last Voyage of the USS Monitor]]&lt;/ref&gt; At 11:30&amp;nbsp;p.m. Bankhead ordered the engineers to stop engines and divert all available steam to the large Adams centrifugal steam pump;&lt;ref name=Voyage&gt;[[#Mariner24|Mariner's Museum, Article: Last Voyage]]&lt;/ref&gt; but with reduced steam output from a boiler being fed wet coal it too was unable to stem the rapidly rising water.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Quarstein10|Quarstein, 2010]], pp. 171–72;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; After all steam pumps had failed, Bankhead ordered some of the crew to man the hand pumps and organized a [[bucket brigade]], but to no avail.&lt;ref name=Quarstein149/&gt;

Officers Greene and Stodder were among the last men to abandon ship and remained with Bankhead who was the last surviving man to abandon the sinking ''Monitor''. In his official report of ''Monitor'' to the Navy Department Bankhead praised Green and Stodder for their heroic efforts and wrote, &quot;I would beg leave to call the attention of the Admiral and of the Department of the particularly good conduct of Lieutenant Greene and Acting Master Louis N. Stodder, who remained with me until the last, and by their example did much toward inspiring confidence and obedience on the part of the others.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Still, 1988, p. 20&quot;/&gt;

After a frantic rescue effort, ''Monitor'' finally foundered and sank approximately {{convert|16|mi|km}} southeast off Cape Hatteras with the loss of sixteen men, including four officers, some of whom remained in the turret and went down with the ironclad, while forty-seven men were rescued by the life boats from ''Rhode Island''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Holloway|Holloway, 2013]], pp. 7–8&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|William Keeler in Annual Report of the Secretary of the Navy, (Washington: D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1863)}} Bankhead, Green and Stodder barely managed to get clear of the sinking vessel and survived the ordeal&lt;ref name=Voyage/&gt; but suffered from exposure from the icy winter sea.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mariner2013|Mariner's Museum, Article: John P. Bankhead, 2013]]&lt;/ref&gt; After his initial recovery, Bankhead filed his official report, as did the commanding officers of the ''Rhode Island'', stating officers and men of both ''Monitor'' and ''Rhode Island'' did everything within their ability to keep ''Monitor'' from sinking. The Navy did not find it necessary to commission a board of inquiry to investigate the affair and took no action against Bankhead or any of his officers.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

Some time later a controversy emerged over why ''Monitor'' sank. In the ''Army and Navy Journal'' Ericsson accused the crew of drunkardness during the storm, being consequently unable to prevent the vessel from sinking. Stodder vigorously defended the crew and rebuked Ericsson's characterization of the crew and events and wrote to Pierce that Ericsson ''cover's up defects by blaming those that are now dead'', pointing out that there were a number of unavoidable events and circumstances that led to the ship's sinking, foremost being the overhang between the upper and lower hulls which came loose and partially separated during the storm from slamming into the violent waves. Stodder's account was corroborated by other shipmates.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mindell|Mindell, 2000]], p. 140&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rediscovery==
[[File:MonitorTurretInt.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Photo showing side view of the cutaway replica of the turret in the Mariner's Museum|Side view of the cutaway replica of the turret in the Mariners' Museum; only one {{convert|11|in|adj=on}} Dahlgren gun is mounted.]]

After months of investigation, research and one false positive, ''Monitor'' was rediscovered off Cape Hatteras at a depth of {{convert|220|ft|m|1}}, 111 years after her sinking. The Navy tested an &quot;underwater locator&quot; in August 1949 by searching an area south of the [[Cape Hatteras Light]]house for the wreck of ''Monitor''. It found a {{convert|140|ft|m|1|adj=on}} long object bulky enough to be a shipwreck, in {{convert|310|ft|m|1}} feet of water that was thought to be ''Monitor'', but powerful currents negated attempts by divers to investigate.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; Retired [[Rear Admiral]] [[Edward Ellsberg]] proposed using external [[pontoon (boat)|pontoon]]s to raise the wreck in 1951, the same method of [[marine salvage]] he had used on the sunken [[submarine]] {{USS|S-51|SS-162|2}}, for the cost of $250,000.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Harvard51|Harvard Journal, April 1951]]&lt;/ref&gt; Four years later, [[Robert F. Marx]] claimed to have discovered the wreck based on the idea she had drifted into shallow water north of the [[lighthouse]] before sinking. Marx said he had dived on the wreck and placed a Coke bottle with his name on it in one of the gun barrels, although he never provided any proof of his story.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 32–33&lt;/ref&gt;

Interest in locating the ship revived in the early 1970s and [[Duke University]], the [[National Geographic Society]] and the [[National Science Foundation]] sponsored an expedition in August 1973 to search for the wreck using a towed [[sonar]] system. On 27 August, they discovered the wreck at coordinates {{Coord|35|0|6|N|75|24|23|W|display=inline,title}}. They sent a camera down to photograph the wreck, but the pictures were so fuzzy as to be useless; on a second attempt the camera snagged something on the wreck and was lost. The sonar images did not match what they expected the wreck to look like until they realized that the sinking vessel had turned over while descending and was resting at the bottom upside down. The team announced their discovery on 8 March 1974. Another expedition was mounted that same month to confirm the discovery and the research [[submersible]] ''[[Alcoa Sea Probe]]'' was able to take still photos and video of the wreck that confirmed it was ''Monitor''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 34–37&lt;/ref&gt;

These photos revealed that the wreck was disintegrating and the discovery raised another issue. Since the Navy had formally abandoned the wreck in 1953, it could be exploited by divers and private salvage companies as it lay outside North Carolina's territorial limits.{{efn|&quot;Research and case law in the 1970s and 1980s determined that the U.S. Navy abandonment of the USS ''Monitor'' consisted only of striking the vessel from the [[Navy List]], an action more accurately described as a decision to &quot;surplus&quot; ships, not a legal abandonment of the warship as an item of federal property. In fact, aside from express authority from Congress, the act of abandonment is outside the authority of any agency, including the Navy. The Navy can decommission a ship, but must follow &quot;surplus property&quot; procedures administered by the [[General Services Administration]] to actually dispose of the ship.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;}} To preserve the ship, the wreck, and everything around it, a {{convert|.5|nmi|lk=in|adj=on}} radius was designated as the [[Monitor National Marine Sanctuary]], the first U.S. [[marine sanctuary]], on 30 January 1975.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 37–38&lt;/ref&gt; ''Monitor'' was also designated a [[National Historic Landmark]] on 23 June 1986.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 91&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:USS Monitor Anchor.JPG|thumb|left|alt=Photo showing anchor of the Monitor at the Mariner's Museum|USS ''Monitor'' anchor at the Mariners' Museum]] In 1977, scientists were finally able to view the wreckage in person as the submersible ''[[Johnson Sea Link]]'' was used to inspect it. The ''Sea Link'' was able to ferry divers down to the sunken vessel and retrieve small artifacts.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 38–40&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. Navy interest in raising the entire ship ended in 1978 when Captain [[Willard Franklyn Searle|Willard F. Searle Jr.]] calculated the cost and possible damage expected from the operation: $20&amp;nbsp;million to stabilize the vessel in place, or as much as $50&amp;nbsp;million to bring all of it to the surface.&lt;ref name=orlando1998&gt;[[#Erickson98|Erickson, 1998]], part 5 of 5, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; Research continued and artifacts continued to be recovered, including the ship's {{convert|1500|lb|adj=on}} anchor in 1983. The growing number of relics required conservation and a proper home so the U.S. [[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration]] (NOAA), in charge of all U.S. marine sanctuaries, selected the Mariners' Museum on 9 March 1987 after considering proposals from several other institutions.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 42–43&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Broadwater|first1=John|title=The USS Monitor: In Situ Preservation and Recovery|url=http://www.academia.edu/3257947/The_USS_Monitor_In_Situ_Preservation_and_Recovery|website=academia.edu|accessdate=8 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

===Recovery===
[[File:UpsideDownTurret1.jpg|thumb|alt=Photo showing recovery of turret as it hoisted up and breaks the surface|Replica of ''Monitor''{{'}}s turret in the Mariners' Museum as it was recovered]]
Initial efforts in 1995 by Navy and NOAA divers to raise the warship's propeller were foiled by an abnormally stormy season off Cape Hatteras. Realizing that raising the whole wreck was impractical for financial reasons as well as the inability to bring up the wreck intact, NOAA developed a comprehensive plan to recover the most significant parts of the ship, namely her engine, propeller, guns, and turret. It estimated that the plan would cost over 20 million dollars to implement over four years. The Department of Defense Legacy Resource Management Program contributed $14.5 million. The Navy divers, mainly from its two [[Mobile Diving and Salvage Unit]]s, would perform the bulk of the work necessary in order to train in deep sea conditions and evaluate new equipment.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 44–48&lt;/ref&gt;

Another effort to raise ''Monitor''{{'}}s propeller was successful on 8 June 1998, although the amount of effort required to work in the difficult conditions off Cape Hatteras was underestimated and the fewer than 30 divers used were nearly overwhelmed. The 1999 dive season was mostly research oriented as divers investigated the wreck in detail, planning how to recover the engine and determining if they could stabilize the hull so that it would not collapse onto the turret. In 2000 the divers [[Shoring|shored]] up the port side of the hull with bags of [[grout]], installed the engine recovery system, an external framework to which the engine would be attached, in preparation for the next season, and made over five times as many dives as they had the previous season.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 48–50&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2001 dive season concentrated on raising the ship's steam engine and [[condenser (heat transfer)|condenser]]. Hull plates had to be removed to access the engine compartment and both the engine and the condenser had to be separated from the ship, the surrounding wreckage and each other. A [[Mini Rover ROV]] was used to provide visibility of the wreck and divers to the support staff above water. The engine was raised on 16 July and the condenser three days later by the [[crane barge]] ''Wotan''. [[Saturation diving]] was evaluated by the Navy that dive season on ''Monitor'' and proved to be very successful, allowing divers to maximize their time on the bottom.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], pp. 156–62&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Surface supplied diving|surface-supplied divers]] evaluated the use of [[heliox]] due to the depth of the wreck. It also proved to be successful once the [[dive table]]s were adjusted.&lt;ref name=IEEE2001&gt;[[#Southerland|Southerland; Davidson; Journal, 2001]]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:US Navy 020717-N-0331L-004 Monitor salvage and recovery.jpg|thumbnail|A Navy diver prepares &quot;the spider&quot;.]]
[[File:US Navy 020805-N-0872M-503 USS Monitor gun turret pulled from the water during salvage operation.jpg|thumb|right|The turret, moments after it reached the surface, secure in the &quot;spider&quot; lifting frame]]
Much like the previous year, the 2002 dive season was dedicated to lifting the {{convert|120|LT|t|adj=on}} turret to the surface. Around 160 divers were assigned to remove the parts of the hull, including the armor belt, that lay on top of the turret using chisels, [[exothermic]] [[cutting torch]]es and {{convert|20000|psi|kPa kg/cm2|0|abbr=on}} [[Hydrodemolition|hydroblasters]]. They removed as much of the debris from inside the turret as possible to reduce the weight to be lifted. This was usually [[Concretion|concreted]] coal as one of the ship's coal bunkers had ruptured and dumped most of its contents into the turret. The divers prepared the turret roof for the first stage of the lift by excavating underneath the turret and placed steel beams and angle irons to reinforce it for its move onto a lifting platform for the second stage. A large, eight-legged lifting frame, nicknamed the &quot;spider&quot;, was carefully positioned over the turret to move it onto the platform and the entire affair would be lifted by the crane mounted on the ''Wotan''. The divers discovered one skeleton in the turret on 26 July before the lift and spent a week carefully chipping about half of it free of the concreted debris; the other half was inaccessible underneath the rear of one of the guns.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 63, 102, 120, 186, 210&lt;/ref&gt;

With [[Tropical Storm Cristobal (2002)|Tropical Storm Cristobal]] bearing down on the recovery team, and time and money running out,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 212–13, 230&lt;/ref&gt; the team made the decision to raise the turret on 5 August 2002, after 41 days of work, and the gun turret broke the surface at 5:30&amp;nbsp;pm to the cheers of everyone aboard ''Wotan'' and other recovery ships nearby.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 183&lt;/ref&gt; As archaeologists examined the contents of the turret after it has been landed aboard ''Wotan'', they discovered a second skeleton, but removing it did not begin until the turret arrived at the Mariners' Museum for conservation. The remains of these sailors were transferred to the [[Joint POW/MIA Accounting Command]] (JPAC) at [[Hickam Air Force Base]], Hawaii, in the hope that they could be identified.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 265–67, 277–79&lt;/ref&gt;

Only 16 of the crew were not rescued by ''Rhode Island'' before ''Monitor'' sank and the [[forensic anthropologist]]s at JPAC were able to rule out the three missing black crewmen based on the shape of the [[femur]]s and skulls.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], pp. 279–84&lt;/ref&gt; Among the most promising of the 16 candidates were crew members Jacob Nicklis, Robert Williams and William Bryan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=28 December 2012|title=150th Anniversary of the USS Monitor: Meet Civil War Naval Heroes Robert Williams and William Bryan|author=Megan Smolenyak |publisher=The Huffington Post |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/megan-smolenyak-smolenyak/uss-monitor-anniversary_b_2372051.html|accessdate=16 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=26 December 2012|title=Crew of the USS Monitor: Could Sailor Jacob Nicklis Be One of the Mystery Skeletons?|author=Megan Smolenyak |publisher=The Huffington Post |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/megan-smolenyak-smolenyak/uss-monitor-skeletons_b_2359637.html|accessdate=16 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=13 May 2012|title=Crew Members of the USS Monitor: Solving the Mystery of the Skeletons in the Turret 150 Years Later|author=Megan Smolenyak |publisher=The Huffington Post |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/megan-smolenyak-smolenyak/crew-members-of-the-uss-m_b_1513018.html|accessdate=16 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=9 November 2011|title=USS Monitor: Could William Bryan Be One of the Skeletons in the Turret?|author=Megan Smolenyak |publisher=The Huffington Post |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/megan-smolenyak-smolenyak/uss-monitor-could-william_b_1083790.html|accessdate=16 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; but a decade passed without their identities being discovered. On 8 March 2013 their remains were buried at [[Arlington National Cemetery]] with full military honors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Civil War sailors laid to rest 150 years later|url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/08/us/monitor-sailors-buried/index.html|publisher=CNN|accessdate=8 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003 NOAA divers and volunteers returned to the ''Monitor'' with the goal of obtaining overall video of the site to create a permanent record of the current conditions on the wreck after the turret recovery. Jeff Johnston of the [[Monitor National Marine Sanctuary]] (MNMS) also wanted a definitive image of the vessel's pilothouse. During the dives, ''Monitor''{{'}}s iron pilothouse was located near the bow of the vessel and documented for the first time by videographer Rick Allen, of [[Nautilus Productions]], in its inverted position.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://monitor.noaa.gov/expeditions/log072603.html |title=''Monitor'' Expedition 2003 |website=[[NOAA]] |date=26 July 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conservation of the propeller was completed nearly three years after its recovery and it is on display in the Monitor Center at the Mariners' Museum.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Broadwater|Broadwater, 2012]], p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2013, conservation of the engine, its components, the turret and the guns continues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marinersmuseum.org/uss-monitor-center/uss-monitor-center|title=USS Monitor Center|publisher=The Mariners' Museum|accessdate=4 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Dahlgren guns were removed from the turret in September 2004 and placed in their own conservation tanks.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Clancy|Clancy, 2013]], p. 271&lt;/ref&gt; Among some of the artifacts recovered from the sunken vessel was a red signal lantern, possibly the one used to send a distress signal to ''Rhode Island'' and the last thing to be seen before ''Monitor'' sank in 1862 – it was the first object recovered from the site in 1977. A gold wedding band was also recovered from the hand of the skeletal remains of one of ''Monitor''{{'}}s crew members found in the turret.&lt;ref&gt;[[#artifacts|NOAA: ''Monitor's Artifacts'']]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Northrop Grumman]] Shipyard in Newport News constructed a full-scale non-seaworthy static replica of ''Monitor''. The replica was laid down in February 2005 and completed just two months later on the grounds of the Mariners' Museum.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |author=Northrop Grumman Newport News |title=Northrop Grumman Employees Reconstruct History with USS Monitor Replica |url=http://www.nn.northropgrumman.com/news/2005/050226_news.html |accessdate=21 May 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070219052656/http://www.nn.northropgrumman.com/news/2005/050226_news.html |archivedate = 19 February 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Monitor National Marine Sanctuary conducts occasional dives on the wreck to monitor and record any changes in its condition and its environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://monitor.noaa.gov/about/expeditions.html|title=About Your Sanctuary: Expeditions|publisher=Monitor National Marine Sanctuary|accessdate=4 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Memorials==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:US Postage Stamp Monitor &amp; Virginia.jpg|thumb|200px|In 1995 the US Postage stamp commemorating the USS ''Monitor'' and CSS ''Virginia'' at the Battle of Hampton Roads {{ffdc|1=US Postage Stamp Monitor &amp; Virginia.jpg|log=2013 July 22|date=August 2013}}]] --&gt;
The [[:File:Monitor Monument jeh.JPG|Greenpoint Monitor Monument]] in [[McGolrick Park]], [[Brooklyn]], depicts a sailor from ''Monitor'' pulling on a [[capstan (nautical)|capstan]]. The sculptor [[Antonio de Filippo]] was commissioned by the [[State of New York]] in the 1930s for a bronze statue to commemorate the Battle of Hampton Roads, John Ericsson, and the crew of the ship. It was dedicated on 6 November 1938.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nycgovparks.org/parks/mcgrmcgolrickpark/monuments/1049|title=Monitor Memorial: History|publisher=City of New York: Parks &amp; Recreation|accessdate=4 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; A vandal doused it with white paint on 7 January 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/brooklyn/vandal_covers_klyn_civil_war_statue_SemeCY6SzZQtc3soGEd80M|title=Vandal covers B'klyn Civil War statue in white paint|last=Calder|first=Rich|date=7 January 2013|work=New York Post|publisher=NYP Holdings|accessdate=4 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1995 the U.S. Postal Service issued a stamp commemorating USS ''Monitor'' and CSS ''Virginia'' depicting the two ships while engaged in their famous battle at Hampton Roads. For an image of the stamp, see footnote link.&lt;ref&gt;[[#SNPM|Smithsonian National Postal Museum]]. An image of the stamp is available at Arago: people, postage &amp; the post online, [http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=2&amp;cmd=1&amp;id=192338&amp;pg=1&amp;mode=1&amp;tid=2043413 Monitor*Virginia stamp].&lt;/ref&gt;

The 150th anniversary of the ship's loss prompted several events in commemoration. A memorial to ''Monitor'' and her lost crew members was erected in the Civil War section of [[Hampton National Cemetery]] by NOAA's [[Office of National Marine Sanctuaries]], together with the U.S. Navy and the [[U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs]], and dedicated on 29 December 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://monitor.noaa.gov/150th/news_monument.html|title=USS Monitor Monument Dedication|last=Ricles|first=Shannon|work=USS Monitor: Preserving a Legacy|publisher=Monitor National Marine Sanctuary|accessdate=4 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Greenpoint Monitor Museum]] commemorated the ship and her crew with an event on 12 January 2013 at the grave sites of those ''Monitor'' crew members buried in [[Green-Wood Cemetery]] in Brooklyn, followed by a service in the cemetery's chapel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://greenpointmonitormuseum.org/events/eventanouncementindex.htm |title=The Greenpoint Monitor Museum|publisher=The Greenpoint Monitor Museum|accessdate=4 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

New Jersey-based indie rock band [[Titus Andronicus (band)|Titus Andronicus]] named their critically acclaimed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.robertchristgau.com/get_artist.php?id=6195&amp;name=Titus+Andronicus|title=Robert Christgau: CG: Titus Andronicus|work=robertchristgau.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/album/the-monitor-mw0001960073|title=The Monitor - Titus Andronicus|author=Jason Lymangrover|work=AllMusic}}&lt;/ref&gt; sophomore album, 2010's ''[[The Monitor (album)|The Monitor]]'', for the ship. Featured on the album's sleeve are the crewmen of ''Monitor'', taken from a tintype portrait. The album's interwoven references to the Civil War include speeches and writings from the period, as well as the side-long closing track &quot;The Battle of Hampton Roads&quot;. The latter refers to the ''Monitor''{{'}}s encounter with CSS ''Virginia'' in prominent detail. Singer/guitarist Patrick Stickles commented while making the album that he was inspired by [[Ken Burns]]'s ''[[The Civil War (TV series)|The Civil War]]'' and the ship itself so much that he decided to name Titus Andronicus's second album in its honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4jMWgputRLo|title=Titus Andronicus- The Making of the Monitor Pt 1|date=July 12, 2010|work=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
{{See also|Monitor (warship)}}
''Monitor'' gave her name to a new type of [[mast (sailing)|mastless]], low-freeboard warship that mounted its armament in turrets. Many more were built, including [[river monitor]]s, and they played key roles in Civil War battles on the Mississippi and James Rivers. The [[breastwork monitor]] was developed during the 1860s by Sir [[Edward James Reed|Edward Reed]], [[Director of Naval Construction|Chief Constructor]] of the [[Royal Navy]], as an improvement of the basic Monitor design. Reed gave these ships a superstructure to increase seaworthiness and raise the freeboard of the gun turrets so they could be worked in all weathers. The superstructure was armored to protect the bases of the turrets, the funnels and the ventilator ducts in what he termed a [[breastwork (fortification)|breastwork]]. The ships were conceived as harbor defense ships with little need to leave port. Reed took advantage of the lack of masts and designed the ships with one twin-gun turret at each end of the superstructure, each able to turn and fire in a 270° arc.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Parkes|Parkes, 1990]], p. 166&lt;/ref&gt; These ships were described by Admiral [[George Alexander Ballard]] as being like &quot;full-armoured knights riding on donkeys, easy to avoid but bad to close with&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Ballard|Ballard, 1980]], p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; Reed later developed the design into the {{sclass-|Devastation|ironclad|4}}, the first ocean-going [[turret ship]]s without masts, the direct ancestors of the [[pre-dreadnought battleship]]s and the [[dreadnought]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Chesneau|Chesneau &amp; Kolesnik, 1979]], p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|American Civil War|United States Navy|right=yes}}
*[[Bibliography of early American naval history#American Civil War|Bibliography of American Civil War naval history]]
*[[List of monitors of the United States Navy]]
*[[List of National Historic Landmarks in North Carolina]]
*[[National Register of Historic Places listings in Dare County, North Carolina]]
{{clear}}

==Notes==
{{notes|30em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book |title=Harriet Tubman, Secret Agent: How Daring Slaves and Free Blacks Spied for the Union During the Civil War |last=Allen |first=Thomas B. |ref=Allen |publisher=National Geographic Books|year=2008 |isbn=978-1-4263-0401-9}} 191 pages.
*{{cite book |title=By Sea and by River: The Naval History of the Civil War |last=Anderson |first=Bern |ref=Anderson |publisher=Da Capo Press |year=1989 |isbn=978-0-306-80367-3}} 303 pages.
* {{cite book|last=Ballard |first=G. A., Admiral |title=The Black Battlefleet |ref=Ballard |year=1980 |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, Maryland |isbn=0-87021-924-3}} 261 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Baxter |first=James Phinney, 3rd |authorlink=James Phinney Baxter III |title=The Introduction of the Ironclad Warship  |edition=reprint of the 1933 publication |year=1968 |publisher=Archon Books |location=Hamden, Connecticut,  |oclc=695838727 &lt;!-- |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4CQzAAAAMAAJ no preview--&gt; |ref=Baxter}} 398 pages.
*{{cite book |title=The Monitor and the Navy under steam |last=Bennett, Lieutenant, U.S. Navy |first=Frank M.  |ref=Bennett |location=Boston and New York |publisher=Houghton, Mifflin and Company |year=1900 |isbn= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9xiZsRXWVRYC}} 369 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Broadwater |first=John D. |title=USS Monitor: A Historic Ship Completes Its Final Voyage  |publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press |year=2012 |isbn=978-1-60344-473-6 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ht7Im50Mec8C&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s |ref=Broadwater}} 239 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Brown |first=David K. |title=Warrior to Dreadnought: Warship Development 1860–1905 |ref=Brown |edition=reprint of the 1997 |year=2003 |publisher=Caxton Editions &lt;!-- |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QqPfAAAAMAAJ no preview--&gt; |location=London |isbn=1-84067-529-2}} 224 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Canney| first=Donald L. |title=The Old Steam Navy |ref=Canney |publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland &lt;!-- |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GzAhAQAAIAAJ no preview--&gt; |year=1993 |volume=2: The Ironclads, 1842–1885 |isbn=0-87021-586-8}} 162 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Clancy |first=Paul |title=Ironclad; The Epic Battle, Calamitous Loss, and Historic Recovery of the USS Monitor |ref=Clancy |publisher=Koehler Books |year=2013 |isbn=978-1-938467-11-0 |location=New York}} 340 pages.
*{{cite book |editor1-last=Chesneau |editor1-first=Roger |editor2-last=Kolesnik |editor2-first=Eugene M. |ref=Chesneau |title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1860–1905 |publisher=Conway Maritime Press |location=Greenwich, UK |year=1979 |isbn=0-8317-0302-4}} 440 pages.
*{{cite web |chapter=Black Dispatches |title=Intelligence in the Civil War |year=2007 |ref=cia |website=[[Central Intelligence Agency]] |department=Library |accessdate=20 June 2013 |url=//www.cia.gov/library/publications/additional-publications/civil-war |chapterurl=//www.cia.gov/library/publications/additional-publications/civil-war/p20.htm}}
*{{cite book |last=Davis |first=Kenneth C. |title=Don't Know Much About the Civil War |ref=Davis96 |authorlink=Kenneth C. Davis  |publisher=William Morrow and Co. |location=New York |year=1996 |isbn=0-688-11814-3 }} 518 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Davis |first=William C. |authorlink=William C. Davis (historian) |title=Duel Between the First Ironclads |ref=Davis75 |publisher=Doubleday |location=Garden City, New York |edition=Book club |year=1975 |oclc=1551282}} 201 pages.
*{{cite journal |date=16 April 1951 |title='USS Monitor Can Be Raised,' Says Top Underwater Salvaging Expert |journal=The Harvard Crimson |ref=Crimson |url=http://www.thecrimson.com/article/1951/4/16/uss-monitor-can-be-raised-says/ |accessdate=19 June 2013}}
*{{cite journal |last=Dinsmore |first=David A |last2=Broadwater |first2=John D. |title=1998 NOAA Research Expedition to the Monitor National Marine Sanctuary |ref=Dinsmore |editor-last=Hamilton |editor-first=RW |editor-last2=Pence |editor-first2=DF |editor-last3=Kesling |editor-first3=DE |journal=Assessment and Feasibility of Technical Diving Operations for Scientific Exploration |publisher=[[American Academy of Underwater Sciences]] |year=1999 |url=http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org/9000 |accessdate=8 January 2011}}
*{{cite news |last=Erickson |first=Mark St. John |title=Sands of time: Part 5 of 5 |newspaper=[[Orlando Sentinel]] |agency=Daily Press |date=4 January 1998 |ref=Erickson98 |url=http://www.orlandosentinel.com/news/dp-news-ussmonitor98_5,0,3504569.story?page=2}}
* {{cite book |last=Field |first=Ron |year=2011 |title=Confederate Ironclad vs Union Ironclad: Hampton Roads |ref=Field |publisher=Osprey Publishing |isbn=978-1-78096-141-5}} 80 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Fuller |first=Howard J |title=Clad in Iron: The American Civil War and the Challenge of British Naval Power |ref=Fuller |location=Annapolis, Maryland |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year=2008 |isbn=978-1-59114-297-3}} 409 pages.
*{{cite book |editor=Gardiner, Robert|title=Steam, Steel and Shellfire: the Steam Warship 1815–1905|series=Conway's History of the Ship|year=1992|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|isbn=1-55750-774-0| &lt;!-- |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qHoSAQAAMAAJ no preview--&gt; |ref=Gardiner}} 192 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Garrison |first=Webb |title=Civil War Curiosities: Strange Stories, Oddities, Events and Coincidents |ref=Garrison |publisher=Rutledge Hill Press |location=Nashville, Tennessee |year=1994 |isbn=1-56865-527-4 }} 281 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Gentile |first=Gary |ref=Gentile |title=Ironclad Legacy: Battles of the Uss Monitor |publisher=Gary Gentile Productions |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-9621453-8-4}} 280 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Holloway |first=Anna |title=The Last Voyage of the USS Monitor |ref=Holloway |year=2013 |publisher=The Mariner's Museum |location=Newport News, VA |url=http://www.marinersmuseum.org/sites/default/files/holloway-last_voyage_monitor.pdf|format=pdf}}
* {{cite book |last=Holzer |first=Harold |last2=Mulligan |first2=Tim |year=2006 |title=The Battle of Hampton Roads: New Perspectives on the USS Monitor and CSS Virginia |publisher=Fordham University Press |location=New York |isbn= 0-8232-2481-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cPZfXUj5l4sC |ref=Holzer06}} 222 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Konstam |first=Angus Konstam |title=Hampton Roads 1862: First Clash of the Ironclads |ref=Konstam |publisher=Osprey Publishing |year=2002 |isbn=978-1-84176-410-8}} 96 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Konstam |first=Angus Konstam |authormask=2 |title=Union Monitor 1861–65 |ref=Konstam2 |publisher=Osprey Publishing |isbn=978-1-84176-306-4}} 48 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Leckie |first=Robert |title=None Died in Vain: The Saga of the American Civil War |ref=Leckie |publisher=Harper-Collins |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=0-06-016280-5}} 682 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Maclay |first=Edgar Stanton |title=A history of the United States Navy, from 1775 to 1893 |ref=Maclay |year=1894 |authorlink=Edgar Stanton Maclay |publisher=D. Appleton &amp; Company |location=New York |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UHWpn7IEuMoC}} 647 pages.
*{{cite web |last=Mariners' Museum |url=http://themarinersmuseum.org/uss-monitor-center/naming-monitor |title=The Naming of the Monitor |ref=Mariner |publisher=The Mariner's Museum |location=Newport News, Virginia |accessdate=16 June 2013}}
*{{cite web |last=Mariners' Museum  |authormask=2 |url=http://www.marinersmuseum.org/uss-monitor-center/john-payne-bankhead |title=John Payne Bankhead |ref=Mariner2013 |publisher=The Mariner's Museum |location=Newport News, Virginia  |accessdate=30 June 2013}}
*{{cite web |last=Mariners' Museum  |authormask=2 |url=http://www.marinersmuseum.org/uss-monitor-center/last-voyage-monitor-december-24th-forward |title=Last Voyage of the Monitor: December 24th – Forward |ref=Mariner24 |publisher=The Mariner's Museum |location=Newport News, Virginia  |accessdate=30 June 2013}}
*{{cite web |title=George S. Geer Papers, 1862–1866 |first=George S. |last=Geer |ref=Geer |publisher=The Mariner's Museum, Newport News, Virginia |authormask=2 |accessdate=August 15, 2013 |url=http://www.marinersmuseum.org/sites/default/files/MS010_George_Geer.pdf|format=pdf}}
*{{cite book |editor=Marvel, William |title=The Monitor Chronicles: One Sailor's Account: Today's Campaign to Recover the Civil War Wreck|year=2000|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-684-86997-7}}
*{{cite book |last=McCordock |first=Robert Stanley |title=The Yankee Cheese Box |ref=McCordock |publisher=Dorrance |year=1938 |oclc= }} 470 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Mindell |first=David A. |year=2000 |ref=Mindell |title=War, Technology, and Experience Aboard the USS Monitor |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |isbn=978-0-8018-6250-2}} 187 pages.
*{{cite book |last=McPherson |first=James M. | authorlink = James M. McPherson |title=[[Battle Cry of Freedom (book)|Battle Cry of Freedom]] |ref= McPherson |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |year=1988 |isbn=0-19-503863-0}} 904 pages.
* {{cite web|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/m13/monitor-i.htm|title=''Monitor''|work=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships (DANFS) |ref=DANFS |publisher=[[Naval History &amp; Heritage Command]] (NH&amp;HC)|accessdate=7 July 2013}}
*{{cite web |title=Monitor's Artifacts |ref=artifacts |url=http://monitor.noaa.gov/150th/artifacts.html |publisher=National Oceanic &amp; Atmospheric Administration, National Marine Sanctuary |location=Newport News, Virginia |accessdate=24 July 2013}}
*{{cite book |last=Nelson |first=James L. |title=Reign of Iron: The Story of the First Battling Ironclads, the Monitor and the Merrimack |ref=Nelson2009 |publisher=HarperCollins |year=2009 |location=New York |isbn=978-0-06-052404-3}}
* {{cite book |last1=Olmstead |first1=Edwin|last2=Stark|first2=Wayne E. |last3=Tucker |first3=Spencer C. |year=1997 |title=The Big Guns: Civil War Siege, Seacoast, and Naval Cannon |ref=Olmstead |publisher=Museum Restoration Service |location=Alexandria Bay, New York |isbn=0-88855-012-X}} 360 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Park |first=Carl D. |title=Ironclad Down: The USS Merrimack-CSS Virginia from Construction to Destruction |ref=Park |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, Maryland |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-59114-659-9}} 238 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Parkes |first=Oscar |title=British Battleships |ref=Parkes |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, Maryland |year=1990 |edition=reprint of the 1957 |isbn=1-55750-075-4}}
*{{cite book |last=Quarstein |first=John V. |title=The Battle of the Ironclads |ref=Quarstein99 |publisher=Arcadia Publishing |year=1999 |isbn= 978-0-7385-0113-0}} 128 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Quarstein |first=John V. |title=A History of Ironclads: The Power of Iron Over Wood |ref=Quarstein06 |publisher=The History Press |authormask=2 |year=2006 |isbn=978-1-59629-118-8}} 286 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Quarstein |first=John V. Quarstein |authormask=2 |title=The Monitor Boys: The Crew of the Union's First Ironclad  |ref=Quarstein10 |publisher=The History Press |year=2010 |isbn=978-1-59629-455-4}} 249 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Quarstein |first=John V. |title=The CSS Virginia: Sink Before Surrender |ref=Quarstein12 |authormask=2 |publisher=The History Press |year=2012 |isbn=978-1-60949-580-0}} 591 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Rawson |first=Edward K. |last2=Woods |first2=Robert H. |title=Official Records of the Union and Confederate Navies in the War of the Rebellion |ref=Rawson |publisher=Government Printing Office, Secretary of the Navy, John D. Long |location=Washington |year=1897}}
*{{cite book |title=Our Iron-clad Ships: Their Qualities, Performances, and Cost. With Chapters on Turret Ships, Iron-clad Rams |last=Reed |first=Sir Edward James |ref=Reed |location=London |publisher=J. Murray |year=1869 |isbn= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CggLAAAAYAAJ}} 332 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Rhodes |first=James Ford |title=History of the Civil War |ref=Rhodes1917 |publisher=MacMillian &amp; Co.|location=New York, Boston, London |year=1917 |oclc= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T2eM6_ON2HkC}} 467 pages.
* {{cite book |last=Roberts |first=William H. |title=USS New Ironsides in the Civil War |ref=Roberts99 |year=1999|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=1-55750-695-7}}
*{{cite book |last=Roberts |first=William H. |location=Baltimore, Maryland |title=Civil War Ironclads: The U.S. Navy and Industrial Mobilization |ref=Roberts02 |authormask=2 |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-8018-8751-2}} 284 pages.
* {{cite book|last=Silverstone|first=Paul H.|title=Civil War Navies 1855–1883|publisher=Routledge|location=New York|year=2006|series=The U.S. Navy Warship Series|isbn=0-415-97870-X|ref=Silverstone}}
*{{cite web |title=American Civil War Issue |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=2&amp;cmd=1&amp;id=192338&amp;img=1&amp;mode=1&amp;pg=1&amp;tid=2043413 |accessdate=August 11, 2013 |publisher=Smithsonian National Postal Museum |ref=SNPM}}
*{{cite book |vauthors=Southerland DG, Davidson DL |title=Electronic diving data collection during Monitor expedition 2001 |ref=Southerland |publisher=MTS/IEEE, |year=2002 |volume=2 |journal=Oceans '02 |doi=10.1109/OCEANS.2002.1192089 |isbn=0-7803-7534-3}}
*{{cite book |last=Stern |first=Philip Van Doren |title=The Confederate Navy |ref=Stern |publisher=Doubleday &amp; Company |location=New York |year=1962  |lccn=62-15914}} 256 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Still |first=William N. |editor-last=Hill |editor-first=Dina B.|title=Ironclad Captains: The Commanding Officers of the U. S. S. Monitor |ref=Still88 |publisher=National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, U.S. Government Printing Office |location=Washington, D.C. |year=1988 |isbn=978-0-16-003560-9 |url=http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CZIC-e595-m7-s74-1988/html/CZIC-e595-m7-s74-1988.htm}} 83 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Sutherland |first=Jonathan |title=African Americans at War: An Encyclopedia, Volume 1 |year=2004 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=978-1-57607-746-7}} 692 pages.
*{{cite journal |last=Thompson |first=Stephen C. |year=1990 |title=The Design and Construction of the USS Monitor |ref=Thompson90 |journal=Warship International |publisher=International Naval Research Organization |location=Toledo, Ohio| volume=XXVII|issue=3 |issn=0043-0374}}
*{{cite book |last=Thulesius |first=Olav |title=The Man who Made the Monitor: A Biography of John Ericsson, Naval Engineer |ref=Thulesius |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company |location=Jefferson, North Carolina |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-7864-2766-6}} 255 pages.
* {{cite book |first=Barbara |last=Tomblin |title=Bluejackets and Contrabands: African Americans and the Union Navy |year=2009 |publisher=University Press of Kentucky |isbn=978-0-8131-7348-1 |ref=Tomblin}} 400 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Tucker |first=Spencer |year=2006 |title=Blue &amp; gray navies: the Civil War afloat |ref=Tucker06 |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Maryland |isbn=1-59114-882-0}} 426 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Varhola |first=Michael J |ref=Varhola |title=Everyday Life During the Civil War |publisher=Writer's Digest Books |year=1999 |isbn=978-1-58297-337-1 &lt;!-- |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DUMBAAAACAAJ no preview--&gt;}} 292 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Wagner |first= Margaret E. |last2=Gallagher |first2=Gary W. |last3=Finkelman |first3=Paul |ref=Wagner |title=The Library of Congress Civil War Desk Reference |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York |year=2002 |isbn=0-684-86350-2}} 949 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Ward |first=Geoffrey |last2=Burns |first2=Ric |last3=Burns |first3=Ken |ref=Ward |title=The Civil War: An Illustrated History |publisher=Alfred A. Knopf |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=0-394-56285-2}} 426 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Wilson |first=H. W. |title=Ironclads in Action: A Sketch of Naval Warfare From 1855 to 1895 |volume=1 |ref=Wilson |year=1896 |publisher=Little, Brown |location=Boston |oclc= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=M3DgGKmaHDEC}}

===Primary sources===
*{{cite book |last=Brooke |ref=Brooke |first=John Mercer |authorlink=John Mercer Brooke |title=Ironclads and Big Guns of the Confederacy: The Journal and Letters of John M. Brooke |publisher=Univ of South Carolina Press |year=2002 |isbn=978-1-57003-418-3}} 257 pages.
*{{cite book |first=Cornelius Scranton |last=Bushnell |first2=John |last2=Ericsson |first3=Gideon |last3=Welles |ref=Bushnell |title=The original United States warship &quot;Monitor&quot; |publisher=National Memorial Association |location=New Haven, Connecticut |year=1899 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FLlAAAAAYAAJ}} 50 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Dahlgren |first=Madeleine Vinton |title=Memoir of John A. Dahlgren, Rear-admiral United States Navy |ref=Dahlgren |publisher=J. R. Osgood |year=1882 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vfpBAAAAYAAJ}} 660 pages.
* {{cite web |title=An Eye-Witness Account of the Battle Between the U.S.S. Monitor and the C.S.S. Virginia |year=1862 |author=Lieutenant Samuel Dana Green, U.S.N. |ref=Green |publisher=U.S. Navy, Naval Historical Foundation, Washington, DC |accessdate=18 July 2013 |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/library/online/monitormerri.htm}}
*{{cite book |title=OFFICIAL RECORDS of the UNION AND CONFEDERATE NAVIES in the WAR OF THE REBELLION |last=Rawson |first=Edward K., Superintendent Naval War Records |last2=Woods |first2=Robert H. |ref=Rawson |year=1898 |publisher=Published by [[John Davis Long|John D. Long]], Secretary of the Navy, Government Printing Office |location=Washington D. C. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=96cSAAAAYAAJ}} 895 pages.
*{{cite book |title=Diary of Gideon Welles, Secretary of the Navy Under Lincoln and Johnson |volume=1 |last=Welles |first=Gideon |authorlink=Gideon Welles |ref=Welles |year=1911 |publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company |location=Boston and New York |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jsdFt7XOr9QC}}
*{{cite book |title=The Monitor and the Merrimac: Both Sides of the Story |last=Worden |first=John Lorimer |last2=Greene |first2=Samuel Dana  |last3=Ramsay |first3=H. Ashton  |last4=Watson |first4=Eugene Winslow  |ref=Worden |authorlink=John Lorimer Worden |publisher=Harper and Brothers |location=New York, London |year=1912 |isbn= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rC5XAAAAYAAJ}} 72 pages.

===Further reading===
*{{cite book |title=The Steam Navy of the United States: A History of the Growth of the Steam Vessel of War in the U. S. Navy, and of the Naval Engineer Corps |last=Bennett |first=Frank Marion  |last2=Weir |first2=Robert  |ref=Bennett |location=Pittsburgh |publisher=Warren &amp; Company; Press of W. T. Nicholson |year=1896  |isbn= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=G9eFAAAAIAAJ}} 953 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Gott |first=Kendall D. |title=Where the South Lost the War: An Analysis of the Fort Henry—Fort Donelson Campaign, February 1862 |publisher=Stackpole books |year=2003 |isbn=0-8117-0049-6}}
*{{cite book |last=Holzer |first=Harold |title=The Civil War in Fifty Objects |ref=Holzer13 |publisher=Penguin Books: New York Historical Society |location=New York |year=2013 }} 416 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Johnson |first=Robert Underwood |first2=C.C. |last2=Buel (editors) |authorlink=Robert Underwood Johnson |title=Battles and Leaders of the Civil War|volume=I |publisher=Century Company|location=New York |year=1887 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OOISAAAAYAAJ}}
* {{cite book |last=Mokin |first=Authur |title=Ironclad: the Monitor and the Merrimack |authorlink= |publisher=Presidio Press |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-8914-1405-6 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4GcfAQAAMAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s |ref=mokin}}
*{{cite book |last=Quarstein |first=John V. |year=2000 |title=C.S.S. Virginia, Mistress of Hampton Roads |ref=Quarstein2k |publisher=self-published for the Virginia Civil War Battles and Leaders Series |isbn=1-56190-118-0}}
* {{cite book |last='''Quarstein''' |first=John V. |ref=Quarstein97 |title= The Civil War on the Virginia Peninsula |publisher=Arcadia Publishing |authormask=2 |year=1997 |isbn=978-0-7385-4438-0 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wSBRAdLN7X4C}} 128 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Sheridan |first=Robert E. |title=Iron from the Deep: The Discovery and Recovery of the USS Monitor |ref=Sheridan |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, Maryland |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-55750-413-5 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZaKzNC09va0C}} 261 pages.
*{{cite book |last=Still |first=William N., Jr. |title=Iron Afloat: The Story of the Confederate Armorclads |isbn=978-0-87249-616-3  |edition=Reprint of the 1971 |year=1988 |publisher=University of South Carolina Press|location=Columbia, South Carolina}}
*{{cite book |title=Diary of Gideon Welles, Secretary of the Navy Under Lincoln and Johnson |volume=2 |last=Welles |first=Gideon |authorlink=Gideon Welles |ref=Welles |year=1911 |publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company |location=Boston and New York |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uiVAAAAAYAAJ}}
*{{cite book |title=Diary of Gideon Welles, Secretary of the Navy Under Lincoln and Johnson |volume=3 |last=Welles |first=Gideon |authorlink=Gideon Welles |authormask=2 |ref=Welles |year=1911 |publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company |location=Boston and New York |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=negWAQAAIAAJ}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|USS Monitor|USS Monitor (ship, 1862)}}
*[http://www.monitorcenter.org/ The ''Monitor'' Center] at the [http://www.mariner.org/ Mariners' Museum], [[Newport News, Virginia]]
*[http://www.civilwar.org/battlefields/hampton-roads/maps/hamptonroadsmaps.html Battle of Hampton Roads schematic map]
*[http://www.seattlepi.com/national/78394_monitor13.shtml Seattle Pilot mentioning the depth charging of the Monitor]
*[http://www.moc.org/ Museum of the Confederacy in Richmond, VA official website]
*[http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/sh-usn/usnsh-m/monitr-u.htm U.S. Naval History Center]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VWn8gQ9Ykpk Video of model vibrating-lever engine of USS ''Monitor'']
* {{cite web |url=http://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/explorations/monitor01/monitor01.html |title=Preserving the USS ''Monitor'' 2001 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line--&gt; |website=NOAA Ocean Explorer |date=March–August 2001 |accessdate=24 February 2015 }}
* {{cite web |url=http://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/explorations/02monitor/welcome.html
 |title=''Monitor'' Expedition 2002 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line--&gt; |website=NOAA Ocean Explorer |date=June–December 2002 |accessdate=24 February 2015 }}

{{Union ironclads}}
{{Battle of Hampton Roads|state=autocollapse}}
{{National Register of Historic Places in North Carolina}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Monitor}}
[[Category:American Civil War monitors of the United States]]
[[Category:Ships built in New York]]
[[Category:Dare County, North Carolina]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks of the Carolina coast]]
[[Category:National Historic Landmarks in North Carolina]]
[[Category:Monitors of the United States Navy]]
[[Category:Ships of the Union Navy]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks of the American Civil War]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1862]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks on the National Register of Historic Places in North Carolina]]
[[Category:1862 ships]]
[[Category:Archaeology of shipwrecks]]
[[Category:National Register of Historic Places in Dare County, North Carolina]]
[[Category:Underwater archaeological sites]]
[[Category:Underwater archaeology]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks in the Atlantic Ocean]]
[[Category:American Civil War on the National Register of Historic Places]]</text>
      <sha1>rdscxl3gyzurba58hvgo4m0k9m60hi4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
