<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>USS Vermont (BB-20)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>205895</id>
    <revision>
      <id>719715696</id>
      <parentid>719715218</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-11T10:21:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pennsy22</username>
        <id>5958044</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22068">{{other ships|USS Vermont}}
{{good article}}
{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:Uss vermont bb 20.jpg|300px|''Vermont'']]
| Ship caption=  ''Vermont''
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header = 
| Ship country = United States
| Ship flag = {{USN flag|1920}}
| Ship name = ''Vermont''
| Ship namesake = [[State of Vermont]]
| Ship builder = [[Fore River Shipyard]]
| Ship laid down = 21 May 1904
| Ship launched = 31 August 1905
| Ship commissioned = 4 March 1907
| Ship decommissioned = 30 June 1920
| Ship struck = 10 November 1923
| Ship fate = Sold 30 November 1923 and broken up for scrap
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header =
| Header caption = {{sfn|Gardiner|p=144}}
| Ship class = {{sclass-|Connecticut|battleship}}
| Ship displacement = {{convert|16000|LT}}
| Ship length = {{convert|456|ft|4|in|m|abbr=on}}
| Ship beam = {{convert|76|ft|10|in|m|abbr=on}}
| Ship draft = {{convert|24|ft|6|in|m|abbr=on}}
| Ship propulsion =*12 [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox boiler]]s
*{{convert|16500|ihp|abbr=on|lk=in}}
| Ship speed = {{convert|18|kn|mph km/h|abbr=on}}
| Ship range = 
| Ship complement = 827&amp;nbsp;officers and men
| Ship armament =*  4 × [[12&quot;/45 caliber Mark 5 gun|{{convert|12|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}/45 caliber Mark 5 gun]]s
*  8 × [[8&quot;/45 caliber gun|{{convert|8|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}/45 caliber guns]]
* 12 × [[7&quot;/44 caliber gun|{{convert|7|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}/45 caliber guns]]
* 20 × [[3&quot;/50 caliber gun|{{convert|3|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}/50 caliber guns]]
* 12 × 3 pounder guns
*  4 × 1 pounder guns
*  4 × {{convert|21|in|mm|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s
  
| Ship armor =* [[Belt armor|Belt]]: {{convert|6|-|11|in|abbr=on|0}}
* [[Barbette]]s: {{convert|6|-|10|in|abbr=on|0}}
* [[Gun turret#Warships|Turret]] Main: {{convert|8|-|12|in|abbr=on|0}}
* Turret secondary: {{convert|7|in|abbr=on|0}}
* [[Conning tower]]: {{convert|9|in|abbr=on|0}}
  
}}
|}

'''USS ''Vermont'' (BB-20)''', a {{sclass-|Connecticut|battleship}}, was the second ship of the [[United States Navy]] named after [[Vermont|the 14th state]]. She was the third member of the class, which included five other ships. The ''Connecticut''-class ships were armed with a main battery of four {{convert|12|in|adj=on}} guns and had a top speed of {{convert|19|kn|lk=in}}. ''Vermont'' was laid down in May 1904 at the [[Fore River Shipbuilding|Fore River]] shipyard and launched in August 1905. The ship entered service with the [[United States Fleet Forces Command|Atlantic Fleet]] in March 1907.

Shortly after she entered service, ''Vermont'' joined the [[Great White Fleet]] for its circumnavigation of the globe in 1908&amp;ndash;09. She took part in the international [[Hudson-Fulton Celebration]] in New York in 1909 and made trips to Europe in 1910 and 1913. Thereafter, the ship became involved in interventions in several Central American countries, including the [[United States occupation of Veracruz]] during the [[Mexican Revolution]], where two of her crew earned the [[Medal of Honor]]. During the United States' participation in [[World War I]] from April 1917 to November 1918, ''Vermont'' served as a [[training ship]] for engine room personnel. From November 1918 to June 1919, she made a series of trips to return American soldiers from Europe before being decommissioned in June 1920. She was sold for scrap in November 1923 according to the terms of the [[Washington Naval Treaty]]. Her bell currently resides at the Vermont State Capitol in Montpelier, VT.

==Design==
[[File:Connecticut-class battleship line-drawing.png|thumb|left|Line-drawing of the ''Connecticut'' class]]
{{main|Connecticut-class battleship}}

''Vermont'' was {{convert|456.3|ft|m|abbr=on}} [[length overall|long overall]] and had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|76.9|ft|m|abbr=on}} and a [[draft (nautical)|draft]] of {{convert|24.5|ft|m|abbr=on}}. She [[Displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|16000|LT}} as designed and up to {{convert|17666|LT}} at full load. The ship was powered by two-shaft [[triple-expansion engine|triple-expansion]] [[steam engine]]s rated at {{convert|16500|ihp|lk=in}} and twelve coal-fired [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] [[boiler]]s, generating a top speed of {{convert|18|kn|lk=in}}. As built, she was fitted with heavy [[military mast]]s, but these were quickly replaced by [[lattice mast]]s in 1909. She had a crew of 827&amp;nbsp;officers and men, though this increased to 881 and later to 896.{{sfn|Gardiner|p=144}}

The ship was armed with a [[main battery]] of four [[12&quot;/45 caliber Mark 5 gun|12&amp;nbsp;inch /45 Mark 5]]{{efn|/45 refers to the length of the gun in terms of [[Caliber (artillery)|calibers]]. A /45 gun is 45 times long as it is in bore diameter.}} guns in two twin [[gun turret]]s on the centerline, one forward and aft. The secondary battery consisted of eight [[8&quot;/45 caliber gun|{{convert|8|inch|adj=on|0}} /45 guns]] and twelve [[7&quot;/44 caliber gun|{{convert|7|in|adj=on|0}} /45 guns]]. The 8-inch guns were mounted in four twin turrets [[amidships]] and the 7-inch guns were placed in [[casemates]] in the hull. For close-range defense against [[torpedo boat]]s, she carried twenty [[3″/50 caliber gun|{{convert|3|in|adj=on|0}} /50]] guns mounted in casemates along the side of the hull and twelve 3-pounder guns. She also carried four {{convert|37|mm|abbr=on}} 1-pounder guns. As was standard for [[capital ship]]s of the period, ''Vermont'' carried four {{convert|21|in|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s, submerged in her hull on the broadside.{{sfn|Gardiner|p=144}}

''Vermont''{{'}}s main [[armored belt]] was {{convert|11|in|abbr=on|0}} thick over the magazines and the machinery spaces and {{convert|6|in|abbr=on|0}} elsewhere. The main battery gun turrets had {{convert|12|in|adj=on}} thick faces, and the supporting [[barbette]]s had the {{convert|10|in|abbr=on}} of armor plating. The secondary turrets had {{convert|7|in|abbr=on}} of frontal armor. The [[conning tower]] had {{convert|9|in|abbr=on}} thick sides.{{sfn|Gardiner|p=144}}

==Service history==

===Construction and the Great White Fleet===
The [[keel]] for ''Vermont'' was laid down on 21 May 1904 at the [[Fore River Shipyard]] in [[Quincy, Massachusetts]]. The completed hull was launched on 31 August 1905, with the christening performed by Jennie Bell, the daughter of [[Charles J. Bell]], the governor of the ship's namesake state. On 4 March 1907, ''Vermont'' was commissioned into the US Navy at the [[Boston Navy Yard]], with Captain [[William P. Potter]] as her first commanding officer. The ship then embarked on a [[shakedown cruise]] from Boston to [[Hampton Roads]], Virginia. She then joined the 1st Division of the [[United States Fleet Forces Command|Atlantic Fleet]] for training exercises. ''Vermont'' left Hampton Roads on 30 August, bound for [[Provincetown, Massachusetts|Provincetown]]. She stayed there until 5 September before returning to the Boston Navy Yard two days later for repairs that lasted until November.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

[[File:USS Vermont in heavy seas.tiff|thumb|left|''Vermont'' in heavy seas, probably during the cruise of the Great White Fleet]]
On 30 November, the ship left Boston to begin preparations to join the world cruise of the [[Great White Fleet]]. Her first two stops were in [[Rhode Island]]; she took on coal in [[Bradford, Rhode Island|Bradford]] before moving to [[Newport, Rhode Island|Newport]], where she loaded stores. She then steamed to [[Tompkinsville, New York]] to receive her full stock of ammunition. The ship arrived in Hampton Roads on 8 December, where she joined the rest of the Great White Fleet, which was commanded by [[Rear Admiral]] [[Robley Dunglison Evans|Robley D. Evans]]. ''Vermont'' and fifteen other battleships began their voyage on 16 December.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}} The fleet cruised south to the [[Caribbean]] and then to South America, making stops in [[Port of Spain]], [[Rio de Janeiro]], [[Punta Arenas]], and [[Valparaíso]], among other cities. After arriving in Mexico in March 1908, the fleet spent three weeks conducting gunnery practice.{{sfn|Albertson|pp=41&amp;ndash;46}} The fleet then resumed its voyage up the Pacific coast of the Americas, stopping in [[San Francisco]] and [[Seattle]] before crossing the Pacific to Australia, stopping in Hawaii on the way. Stops in the South Pacific included [[Melbourne]], [[Sydney]], and [[Auckland]]. {{sfn|Albertson|pp=47&amp;ndash;56}}

After leaving Australia, the fleet turned north for the Philippines, stopping in [[Manila]], before continuing on to Japan where a welcoming ceremony was held in [[Yokohama]]. Three weeks of exercises followed in [[Subic Bay]] in the Philippines in November. The ships passed [[Singapore]] on 6 December and entered the Indian Ocean; they coaled in [[Colombo]] before proceeding to the [[Suez Canal]] and coaling again at [[Port Said]], Egypt. The fleet called in several Mediterranean ports before stopping in [[Gibraltar]], where an international fleet of British, Russian, French, and Dutch warships greeted the Americans. The ships then crossed the Atlantic to return to Hampton Roads on 22 February 1909, having traveled {{convert|46729|nmi}}. There, they conducted a [[naval review]] for President [[Theodore Roosevelt]].{{sfn|Albertson|pp=57&amp;ndash;66}} During the cruise, Captain Potter was promoted to Rear Admiral and advanced to the 1st Division commander; his place as ''Vermont''{{'}}s commander was taken by Captain [[Frank Friday Fletcher]].{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

===Peacetime service, 1909&amp;ndash;1913===
[[File:USS Vermont BB-20.jpg|thumb|''Vermont'' following her modernization in 1909]]

''Vermont'' returned to the Boston Navy Yard for repairs after the ceremonies at Hampton Roads concluded; the work lasted from 9 March to 23 June. She then rejoined the fleet off Provincetown; the 1st Division made a trip to Boston for the 4th of July celebration there. Starting on 7 July, the Atlantic Fleet conducted extensive maneuvers until 4 August. ''Vermont'' then took part in gunnery training off the Virginia Capes. Additional training exercises followed through the end of the year, interrupted only by visits to New York City and to [[Stamford, Connecticut]], for the [[Hudson-Fulton Celebration]] and Columbus Day, respectively. In late December, she was back in New York City. ''Vermont'' then steamed south to [[Guantanamo Bay]], Cuba, which she reached on 12 January 1910. Two months of exercises there followed before gunnery training off the Virginia Capes. The ship was back in Boston on 29 April for repairs that lasted until mid-July. After returning to service, she took on a contingent of [[Naval Militia]] at Boston for a cruise to Provincetown from 22 to 31 July.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

''Vermont'' then steamed to Newport before proceeding to Hampton Roads no 22 August where more target practice followed from 25 to 27 September. She and several other ships from the Atlantic Fleet then visited New York before some minor repairs were effected at the [[Philadelphia Navy Yard]]. By this time, the ship had been transferred to the 3rd Division. On 1 November, ''Vermont'' and several other ships of the Atlantic Fleet crossed the Atlantic for a visit of several western European ports, including [[Gravesend, England|Gravesend]] from 16 November to 7 December and [[Brest, France|Brest]]. The ships left Brest on 30 December to recross the Atlantic, bound for Cuban waters. From 13 January 1911 to 13 March, ''Vermont'' and the rest of the ships conducted maneuvers off Cuba. Further exercises followed off the Virginia Capes and in the [[Chesapeake Bay]]. A brief stop at Hampton Roads, where she carried target materials, followed on 8 April, though she left later that day for another period in the Philadelphia Navy Yard for repairs.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

In mid-1911, ''Vermont'' cruised south the Gulf of Mexico, stopping first in [[Pensacola, Florida]]. She then continued to [[Galveston, Texas]], stopping there from 7 to 12 June, before returning to Pensacola the following day. The ship returned to the Atlantic and steamed north to [[Bar Harbor, Maine]]; she was present there for the 4th of July celebrations, after which the typical routine of training with the Atlantic Fleet off Provincetown and in [[Cape Cod Bay]] followed. She remained off [[New England]] through mid-August. During this period, she visited [[Salem, Massachusetts]] and underwent repairs at the Boston Navy Yard. Later in the year, she moved south to [[Tangier Sound]] and the Virginia Capes for gunnery experiments and target practice. From 12 September to 9 October, ''Vermont'' was in the [[Norfolk Navy Yard]] for repairs, after which she steamed to Hampton Roads before proceeding with the fleet to New York City for a [[Naval Review]] that lasted from 24 October to 2 November. After the conclusion of the review, she joined the 1st Squadron for maneuvers and then returned to Hampton Roads.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

''Vermont'' stopped in [[Tompkinsville, Staten Island|Tompkinsville]] on 7&amp;ndash;8 December before continuing to the [[New York Navy Yard]] later on the 8th for periodic maintenance. On 2 January 1912, she steamed south to the Caribbean for the annual maneuvers off Cuba. She remained in Cuban waters until 9 March, when she returned to the Norfolk Navy Yard. She underwent a major overhaul there that lasted until October. On the 8th, she steamed to New York City, arriving two days later. A Naval Review followed there from 10 to 15 October, followed by maneuvers and gunnery training off the Virginia Capes through December. On 2 November, she joined the search effort for the stranded steamer {{SS|Noruega||2}}, and on 13&amp;ndash;15 December she assisted the [[submarine]] {{USS|B-2|SS-11|2}}. ''Vermont'' was back in the Norfolk Navy Yard on 25 December, after which she departed for the normal winter training period in Cuban waters. While on the way, she stopped in [[Colón, Panama]], at the entrance to the [[Panama Canal]], which was nearing completion. She arrived in Guantanamo Bay on 19 January 1913 and remained in the area for nearly a month.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

===Interventions in Central America and World War I===
[[File:USS Vermont in storm, December 1913.png|thumb|right|''Vermont'' returning home from Mediterranean cruise hit a gale which resulted in damage to her propeller]]

On 12 February, the ship departed for Mexico, as the country was in the midst of the [[Mexican Revolution]]; ''Vermont'' was tasked with protecting American interests in [[Veracruz (city)|Veracruz]]. She arrived in the port on 17 February and remained there until 29 April, when she returned to the United States. She rejoined the fleet in Hampton Roads before beginning a training cruise for midshipmen at the [[US Naval Academy]] at Annapolis on 6 June. Following the conclusion of the cruise, she operated in [[Block Island Sound]] and stopped in Newport. Starting in July, the ship's normal overhaul at Norfolk began, with the work lasting until October. She then took part in gunnery training off the Virginia Capes. ''Vermont'' made a second trip to Europe on 25 October, this time to French Mediterranean waters. She stopped in [[Marseille]] from 8 November to 1 December and then recrossed the Atlantic. While on the voyage back, a severe storm damaged one of her propellers, which necessitated a tow back to Norfolk, where she arrived on 20 December. Repairs were effected there, which were followed by a short period of sea trials to test the propulsion system.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

After their ship returned to service, ''Vermont''{{'}}s crew began preparations to perform the normal spring target practice off the Virginia Capes, but the exercises were cancelled when the situation in Mexico worsened. ''Vermont'' steamed out of Hampton Roads on 15 April, bound for Veracruz. There, she joined her sister {{USS|New Hampshire|BB-25|2}}, the pre-dreadnought {{USS|New Jersey|BB-16|2}}, and the [[dreadnought battleship|dreadnoughts]] {{USS|South Carolina|BB-26|2}} and {{USS|Arkansas|BB-33|2}}. ''Vermont'' contributed twelve officers and 308&amp;nbsp;men to a landing force that [[United States occupation of Veracruz|occupied the city]] to prevent an arms shipment&amp;mdash;aboard the [[steamship]] {{SS|Ypiranga||2}}&amp;mdash;from reaching the dictator [[Victoriano Huerta]]. One man from ''Vermont'' was killed and two earned the [[Medal of Honor]]: [[Lieutenant]] [[Julius C. Townsend]], the commander of ''Vermont''{{'}}s contingent, and Surgeon [[Cary DeVall Langhorne]], the regimental surgeon of the Second Seaman Regiment. The ship remained in Veracruz through October, apart from a visit to [[Tampico]] from 21 September to 10 October.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

[[File:USS Vermont c. 1919-20.tif|thumb|left|''Vermont'' c. 1919&amp;ndash;20]]
After returning to the east coast of the United States in late 1914, ''Vermont'' resumed her normal routine of training cruises and exercises. The ship was temporarily placed in reserve from 1 October to 21 November 1916, though after returning to service she supported a Marine expeditionary force sent to Haiti. This duty lasted from 29 November to 5 February 1917, after which she took part in battle training in Cuban waters. ''Vermont'' arrived back in Norfolk on 29 March before proceeding to Philadelphia for maintenance on 4 April. While she was in dry dock, the United States entered [[World War I]] be declaring war on Germany. ''Vermont''{{'}}s overhaul was completed on 26 August, and she was assigned as a training ship for engine room personnel, based at Hampton Roads. On 28 May 1918, the remains of the Chilean ambassador to the United States were brought aboard the ship. The US ambassador to Chile, J. H. Shea, came aboard the ship on 3 June, and ''Vermont'' departed Norfolk that day. She transited the Panama Canal on 10 June, stopped briefly in [[Tongoy]], Chile on the 24th, and arrived in [[Valparaiso]] three days later. Admiral [[William B. Caperton]] and Ambassador Shea escorted the Chilean ambassadors remains ashore.{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}}

''Vermont'' left Valparaiso on 2 July, stopping in [[Callao]], Peru on the way back to the Panama Canal. After returning to the United States, she resumed her training ship duties, which lasted almost to the end of the war. On 5 November, less than a week before the [[Armistice with Germany]] ended the fighting in Europe, ''Vermont'' was sent to the Philadelphia Navy Yard for conversion into a troop transport. She began her first transport mission on 9 January 1919; she made another three trips to return American soldiers from France, with the last concluding on 20 June 1919. In the course of these voyages, she carried some 5,000 men back to the United States. On 18 July, she steamed out of Norfolk for the last time, bound for the west coast of the United States. She visited [[San Diego, California|San Diego]], [[San Pedro, California|San Pedro]], [[Monterey, California|Monterey]], [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]], and [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]] in California, and [[Astoria, Oregon]]. Her final destination was the [[Mare Island Navy Yard]] at [[Vallejo, California]], where she arrived on 18 September. She was decommissioned there on 30 June 1920 and reclassified as BB-20 on 17 July. She remained there until 10 November 1923, when she was struck from the [[Naval Vessel Registry]]. On 30 November, she was sold for scrap and [[ship breaking|broken up]] under the terms of the [[Washington Naval Treaty]].{{sfn|DANFS Vermont}} Her bell currently resides at the Vermont State Capitol in Montpelier, VT.

[[File:Bell of the USS Vermont.jpg|Bell of the USS Vermont]]

==Footnotes==
'''Notes'''

{{notes}}

'''Citations'''

{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
* {{cite book
  | last = Albertson
  | first = Mark
  | title = U.S.S. Connecticut: Constitution State Battleship
  | location = Mustang
  | publisher = [[Tate Publishing &amp; Enterprises|Tate Publishing]]
  | year = 2007
  | isbn = 1-59886-739-3
  | ref={{sfnRef|Albertson}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | editor-last = Gardiner
  | editor-first = Robert
  | year = 1979
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1860–1905
  | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-85177-133-5
  | oclc = 
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gardiner}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/v/vermont-ii.html
  |title=Vermont
  |work=[[Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships]]
  |publisher=[[Naval History &amp; Heritage Command]]
  |date=31 March 2014
  |accessdate=15 May 2015
  |ref={{sfnRef|DANFS Vermont}}
  }}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book
  | last = Alden
  | first = John D.
  | year = 1989
  | title = American Steel Navy: A Photographic History of the U.S. Navy from the Introduction of the Steel Hull in 1883 to the Cruise of the Great White Fleet
  | location = Annapolis
  | publisher = [[Naval Institute Press]]
  | isbn = 0-87021-248-6
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Friedman
  | first = Norman
  | year = 1985
  | title = U.S. Battleships, An Illustrated Design History
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 0-87021-715-1
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Reilly
  | first1 = John C.
  | last2 = Scheina
  | first2 = Robert L.
  | year = 1980
  | title = American Battleships 1886–1923: Predreadnought Design and Construction
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 0-87021-524-8
  }}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|USS Vermont (BB-20)}}
* [http://www.maritimequest.com/warship_directory/us_navy_pages/uss_vermont_bb20.htm Maritimequest USS Vermont BB-20 Photo Gallery]
*[http://www.navsource.org/archives/01/20a.htm NavSource Online: Battleship Photo Archive BB-20 USS VERMONT]

{{Connecticut class battleship}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vermont (BB-20)}}
[[Category:Connecticut-class battleships]]
[[Category:Ships built in Quincy, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:1905 ships]]
[[Category:World War I battleships of the United States]]
[[Category:United States Navy Vermont-related ships]]</text>
      <sha1>4uaz9ak91f4jsoyi61a9zkcw8hr19pf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
