<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Wyoming-class battleship</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>294509</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744010308</id>
      <parentid>744006726</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-12T15:31:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Parsecboy</username>
        <id>1879095</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>not helpful</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26029">{{good article}}

{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:USS Wyoming BB-32 circa 1912-13.jpg|300px]]
| Ship caption = ''Wyoming'' as completed
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
| Name = ''Wyoming''-class battleship
| Builders =
*[[William Cramp and Sons]]
*[[New York Shipbuilding Corporation]]
| Operators = [[File:US flag 46 stars.svg|20px]] United States Navy
| Class before = {{sclass-|Florida|battleship|4}}
| Class after = {{sclass-|New York|battleship|4}}
| Subclasses = 
| Cost = 
| Built range = 1910–1912
| In service range =
| In commission range = 1912–1947
| Total ships building = 
| Total ships planned = 2
| Total ships completed = 2
| Total ships cancelled = 
| Total ships active = 
| Total ships laid up = 
| Total ships lost = 
| Total ships retired = 2
| Total ships preserved = 0
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
| Header caption = (As built){{efn|Many of these figures changed dramatically during the careers of the ships.}}
| Ship class = 
| Ship type = [[Battleship]]
| Ship displacement =
* {{cvt|26000|LT|t|lk=on|0}} (standard)
* {{cvt|27243|LT|t|0}} (full load)
| Ship length = 
* {{cvt|562|ft|lk=on}} ([[overall length|overall]])
* {{cvt|554|ft|0}} ([[Waterline length|waterline]])
| Ship beam = {{cvt|93|ft|3|in}}
| Ship draft = 
* {{cvt|28|ft|6|in}} (mean)
* {{cvt|29|ft|7|in}} (max)
| Ship power =
* 12 × coal-fired [[superheater|superheating]] [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] [[water-tube boiler]]s
*{{cvt|28000|shp|lk=in|0}}
| Ship propulsion =
* 4 × [[Parsons Marine Steam Turbine Company|Parsons]] [[steam turbine]]s
* 4 × [[Propeller|screws]]
| Ship speed = {{cvt|21|kn|lk=on}}
| Ship range = {{cvt|8000|nmi|mi km|-1}} at {{cvt|10|kn}}
| Ship complement = 1,063 officers and enlisted
| Ship armament =
* 12 × [[12&quot;/50 caliber Mark 7 gun|{{cvt|12|in|0}}/50 caliber Mark 7 guns]]
* 21 × [[5&quot;/51 caliber gun|{{cvt|5|in|0}}/51 cal guns]]
* 4 × [[QF 3-pounder Hotchkiss#US service|3-pounder {{cvt|47|mm|2}}/40 cal]] [[Saluting gun#Heavy arms: gun salutes|saluting guns]] 
* 2 × [[Mark 15 torpedo|{{cvt|21|in|0}}]] [[torpedo tubes]] (submerged)
| Ship armor =
* [[Belt armor|Belt]]: {{cvt|5|-|11|in|0|lk=on}}
* [[Gun turret#Warships|Turret]] face: {{cvt|12|in|0}}
* [[Barbette]]s: 11 in
* [[Conning tower]]: {{cvt|11.5|in|0}}
* [[Deck (ship)|Deck]]s: {{cvt|1.5|-|2.5|in|0}}
| Ship aircraft = 
| Ship aircraft facilities = 
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}

The '''''Wyoming'' class''' was a pair of [[dreadnought battleship]]s built for the [[United States Navy]]. The two ships, {{USS|Wyoming|BB-32|2}} and {{USS|Arkansas|BB-33|2}}, were authorized in early 1909, and they were built between 1910 and 1912. They were the fourth dreadnought design of the US Navy, and they marked an incremental improvement over the preceding {{sclass-|Florida|battleship|4}}. The primary changes being the addition of a sixth twin-[[gun turret]], bringing the number of {{convert|12|in|adj=on|0}} guns to twelve, and improved armor protection, including the first use of a [[torpedo bulkhead]] in an American battleship design. The Navy had seriously considered a significantly more powerful {{convert|14|in|adj=on|0}} gun, but it would have entailed major delays and required extensive harbor improvements to accommodate what would have been much larger ships.

The two ships frequently served together, first in the [[United States Fleet Forces Command|Atlantic Fleet]] in the 1910s. Both vessels were deployed to British waters after the United States entered [[World War I]] in April 1917 to reinforce the [[Royal Navy]]'s [[Grand Fleet]]. They served in the [[US Pacific Fleet|Pacific Fleet]] in 1919–21, before both returned to the Atlantic Fleet. Much of their time in the Atlantic Fleet was spent conducting peacetime training exercises, along with taking midshipmen from the [[US Naval Academy]] on training cruises. ''Wyoming'' and ''Arkansas'' were heavily modernized in the mid-1920s, receiving more efficient oil-fired boilers to replace their old coal-fired models, thicker deck armor to protect against plunging fire, [[anti-torpedo bulge]]s to increase their resistance to underwater damage, and [[anti-aircraft gun]]s to defend against aerial attacks.

The [[London Naval Treaty]] of 1930 mandated that ''Wyoming'' be demilitarized; she accordingly was converted into a [[training ship]], with half of her main battery turrets, belt armor, and anti-torpedo bulges removed. ''Arkansas'' was permitted to continue in service with the fleet, however. After the United States entered [[World War II]], ''Arkansas'' was used to escort [[convoy]]s to North Africa. By 1944, she served as a coastal bombardment vessel; in this role, she supported Allied landings at Normandy ([[Operation Overlord]]) and southern France ([[Operation Dragoon]]) before being transferred to the Pacific, where she provided [[Naval gunfire support|fire support]] to Marines [[Battle of Iwo Jima|fighting on Iwo Jima]] and [[Battle of Okinawa|at Okinawa]] in 1945. ''Wyoming'' meanwhile continued as a training ship, being modified further in 1944 to include the various types of anti-aircraft guns that trainees would operate in the fleet. Both ships were decommissioned shortly after the war, with ''Arkansas'' being expended as a [[target ship]] during the 1946 nuclear tests at [[Operation Crossroads]], and ''Wyoming'' being sold for scrap in 1947.

== Design ==
On 22 July 1908, the Newport Conference was held; this included the [[General Board]], the staff of the [[Naval War College]], President [[Theodore Roosevelt]]—who had a keen interest in naval matters—and other officers. This conference examined a series of issues relating to existing battleships and new designs; the first of these new ships would become the ''Wyoming'' class. The [[Board on Construction]] received general instructions from the Newport Conference; those at the conference favored adopting the 14-inch gun, as the British [[Royal Navy]] had already traded their 12-inch guns for {{convert|13.5|in|adj=on|0}} pieces.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|pp=81, 85}} The [[Bureau of Ordnance]] (BuOrd) estimated that design work on the new gun, production, and testing would take two years. On 26 August, the [[Secretary of the Navy]], [[Victor Metcalf]], issued a request for eight- and ten-gun battleships armed with the 14-inch weapons to the [[Bureau of Construction and Repair]] (C&amp;R). Speed was to be at least {{cvt|20|kn|lk=on}}, with as much armor as could be accommodated.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=86}}

BuOrd argued that at likely battle ranges, {{cvt|8000|to|8500|yd|lk=on}}, the 12-inch gun was powerful enough to penetrate existing armor, and so the 14-inch gun was unnecessary. C&amp;R produced three designs to meet Metcalf's request, all based on the preceding {{sclass-|Florida|battleship|5}} design; the first, referred to as design 404, was a battleship armed with eight 14-inch guns. The second, design 502, had an additional twin turret for a total of ten 14-inch guns. The third, design 601, would be fitted with twelve 12-inch guns. The General Board chose 601, since the design work for the 14-inch gun had not begun, and adopting it would have caused the class to be delayed. In addition, the ships' displacement would have increased more dramatically with the larger gun, requiring extensive improvements to harbor facilities; design 502 would have only been able to dock in [[Pearl Harbor]] and [[Puget Sound]] with the existing facilities. The placement of the secondary battery also proved to be problematic. The cruise of the [[Great White Fleet]] in 1907–09 had demonstrated the problems with [[casemate]]s on the main deck. They were too easily washed out in even moderate seas, making them unusable. Some officers at the Newport Conference had advocated placing them in the [[superstructure]], but the heavy {{convert|5|in|adj=on|0}} guns used by the Navy would have added excessive top weight. Another alternative was to place them in the [[forecastle]], but the additional weight forward would have strained the ship where the forecastle stepped down to the main deck. The designers ultimately settled on a full-length forecastle, which allowed the casemates to be moved about {{cvt|4|ft}} higher in the hull.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|pp=87–89}}

The ships' armor protection was improved over earlier designs. The [[armor belt|belt]] and [[barbette]] armor was increased by an inch compared to an earlier version of the twelve-gun battleship. A new protection scheme for the [[funnel (ship)|funnels]] was devised, after the Russian experience at the [[Battle of Tsushima]] three years before had highlighted the risk of a destroyed exhaust system. The designers also emphasized the need for improved underwater protection. As a result, the ''Wyoming''s design incorporated a [[torpedo bulkhead]], the first time the feature was included on an American battleship design.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|pp=89–93}} [[United States Congress|Congress]] approved two new battleships, BB-32 and BB-33, on 3 March 1909.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=88}} Design 502 later proved to be the basis for the subsequent class of battleships, the {{sclass-|New York|battleship|5}}s.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=93}}

===General characteristics and machinery===
The ships of the ''Wyoming'' class were {{cvt|554|ft}} [[length at the waterline|long at the waterline]] and {{cvt|562|ft}} [[length overall|long overall]]. They had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{cvt|93|ft|3|in}} and a [[draft (nautical)|draft]] of {{cvt|28|ft|7|in|0}}. The ships displaced {{cvt|26000|LT|t|lk=on|0}} as designed and up to {{cvt|27243|LT|t}} at full combat load. They had a full length [[flush deck]], which improved sea-keeping and the ability to work the secondary guns in heavier seas. Both ships were fitted with [[lattice mast]]s. Their transverse [[metacentric height]] was {{cvt|5.4|ft|0}} They had a crew of 58&amp;nbsp;officers and 1,005&amp;nbsp;enlisted men.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}{{sfn|Friedman 1985|pp=434–435}}

The ships were powered by four-shaft [[Parsons Marine Steam Turbine Company|Parsons]] [[steam turbines]] rated at {{cvt|28000|shp|lk=on}}. Steam was provided by twelve mixed oil and coal-fired [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] [[boiler]]s, which were trunked into two closely spaced funnels amidships. The engines generated a top speed of {{cvt|20.5|kn}}, though on speed trials ''Arkansas'' made {{convert|21.22|kn}} from {{cvt|25546|shp}}. Fuel capacity was {{cvt|1667|LT|t}} of coal and {{cvt|266|LT|t}} of oil. This allowed the ships to cruise for {{cvt|6700|nmi|lk=on}} at a speed of {{cvt|10|kn}}. At {{cvt|20|kn}}, the range fell considerably, to {{cvt|2655|nmi}}. Steering was controlled by a single [[rudder]].{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=434}}

=== Armament ===
[[File:USS Arkansas Main Guns Firing.jpg|thumb|''Arkansas''{{'}}s four after turrets firing during gunnery practice]]
The ships were armed with a [[main battery]] of twelve [[12&quot;/50 caliber Mark 7 gun|12-inch/50 caliber Mark 7 Mod 0]]{{efn|/50 refers to the length of the gun in terms of [[Caliber (artillery)|calibers]]. A /50 gun is 50 times long as it is in bore diameter.}} guns in six Mark 9 twin-[[gun turret]]s all on the centerline, two of which were placed in a [[superfire|superfiring pair]] forward. The other four turrets were placed aft of the superstructure in two superfiring pairs.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=434}} These guns fired a {{cvt|870|lb|lk=on|0}} shell with a {{cvt|353|lb}} [[propellant]] charge, which produced a [[muzzle velocity]] of {{cvt|2900|ft/s|lk=on}}. ''Wyoming'' and ''Arkansas'' were the only ships of the US Navy to receive the gun; earlier [[dreadnought]]s were equipped with the lower-velocity [[12&quot;/45 caliber Mark 5 gun|12-inch/45-caliber Mark 5]] gun. The Mark 7 had significantly better armor penetrating capabilities, owing to its higher muzzle velocity (and thus higher striking velocity). At a range of {{cvt|12000|yd}}, the gun could penetrate {{cvt|12.3|in}} of contemporary face-hardened armor, compared to {{cvt|10.8|in}} for the Mark 5. The guns were mounted in the Mark IX gun turret, which allowed for elevation to 15&amp;nbsp;degrees and depression to -5&amp;nbsp;degrees. Unlike the turrets used on earlier dreadnoughts, the Mark IX turret required the guns to return to 0&amp;nbsp;degrees to reload.{{sfn|Friedman 2011|pp=172–173}}

The secondary battery consisted of twenty-one [[5&quot;/51 caliber gun|5-inch/51 caliber guns]] mounted in casemates along the side of the hull.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=434}} These guns fired a {{cvt|50|lb}} shell with a charge of {{cvt|24.5|lb}}, at a muzzle velocity of {{cvt|3150|ft/s}}.{{sfn|Friedman 2011|p=185}} As was standard for [[capital ship]]s of the period, they carried a pair of submerged {{convert|21|in|adj=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s in the hull on the broadside.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=434}} They were equipped with the Mark III Bliss-Leavitt design, which carried a {{cvt|218|lb}} [[warhead]] and had a range of {{cvt|4000|yd}} at a speed of {{cvt|26.5|kn}}.{{sfn|Friedman 2011|p=342}}

===Armor===
The main [[armored belt]], which was {{cvt|8|ft}} high, was {{cvt|11|in}} thick over the central portion of the ship, where it protected the ammunition magazines and machinery spaces. The belt reduced to {{cvt|5|in}} toward the stern. On the bottom edge it was reduced to {{cvt|9|in}}. The forward end of the belt was connected with an 11&amp;nbsp;in thick transverse [[bulkhead (partition)|bulkhead]] with the forward-most main battery barbette, while the aft end of the belt was connected with a 9&amp;nbsp;in bulkhead. The main armored deck was {{cvt|2.5|in}} of [[special treatment steel]], reduced to {{cvt|1.5|in}} in less critical areas. The [[conning tower]] had {{cvt|11.5|in|0}} thick sides and a {{cvt|3|in}} thick roof.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}{{sfn|Friedman 1985|pp=90, 434}}

The gun turrets had {{cvt|12|in|0}} thick faces and 3&amp;nbsp;in thick roofs. Their supporting barbettes had 11&amp;nbsp;in thick sides where they were exposed; the portions that were masked by the armored belt were reduced to {{cvt|4.5|in}}. The lower half of the casemate armor was 11&amp;nbsp;in thick, and the upper half was reduced to {{cvt|6.5|in}}. Inboard of the casemate battery were longitudinal armored bulkheads; these were designed to protect the uptakes to the funnels. These were deemed important because during the [[Russo-Japanese War]], three years before, Russian battleships had had their uptakes damaged, which ducted the boiler smoke into the ship rather than out through the funnels.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}{{sfn|Friedman 1985|pp=90–91, 434}}

=== Modifications ===
Both ships were significantly modified throughout their careers. During and shortly after [[World War I]], the horizontal armor of the ships was improved, including the roofs of the conning tower and the gun turrets. Their deck armor was increased to {{cvt|3.5|in}}, and eight [[3&quot;/50 caliber gun|{{convert|3|in|adj=on|0}}/50]] caliber [[anti-aircraft gun]]s were installed.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau|p=91}} Following the signing of the [[Washington Naval Treaty]] in February 1922, modernization work was strictly controlled. The treaty governed what modifications could be made to existing ships, and included restrictions on what could be changed or added. Displacement could rise by no more than {{cvt|3000|LT|t}} and no alterations of any kind could be made to the main battery guns or mounts. The primary areas that could be improved were those that concerned defense against aerial and underwater attack, along with propulsion systems.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=189}}

[[File:USS Arkansas (BB-33) - 80-G-229753.jpg|thumb|''Arkansas'' in her 1944 configuration, with tripod foremast]]
The two ''Wyoming''s, along with the ''Florida''s and ''New York''s were heavily modernized in the 1920s. All six ships were converted to completely oil-fired boilers with equipment taken from the cancelled [[South Dakota-class battleship (1920)|''South Dakota''-class battleships]]. The boilers were trunked into a single funnel. These boilers were much more efficient than the coal-fired models the ships had been completed with, and they allowed a significantly greater cruising radius of {{cvt|11000|nmi}}. The ships were also fitted with [[anti-torpedo bulge]]s, which improved their underwater defense and also provided additional oil storage capacity.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|p=193}} ''Wyoming'' and ''Arkansas'' lost their cage [[main mast]], which was replaced by a short tripod mast that carried searchlights and radio antennas. Some of their secondary battery guns were relocated higher in the ship to improve their workability in heavy seas. A [[sponson]] for six guns was built into the hull abreast of the conning tower and the eight 3-inch anti-aircraft guns were moved to the top of the sponson. Both ships had their torpedo tubes removed.{{sfn|Friedman 1985|pp=195–196}}

Under the terms of the 1930 [[London Naval Treaty]], ''Wyoming'' was to be demilitarized and converted into a [[training ship]]. During the demilitarization process, her anti-torpedo bulges, side armor, and half of her main battery guns were removed. ''Wyoming'' was modernized at Norfolk Navy Yard from 12 January to 3 April 1944;{{sfn|DANFS Wyoming}} the reconstruction removed the last of her three 12-inch gun turrets, and replaced them with four twin and two single enclosed mounts for [[5&quot;/38 caliber gun|5-inch/38 caliber guns]].{{sfn|Breyer|p=202}} New fire control radars were also installed; these modifications allowed ''Wyoming'' to train anti-aircraft gunners with the most modern equipment they would use while in combat with the fleet.{{sfn|DANFS Wyoming}} Modifications to ''Arkansas'' during [[World War II]] were kept to a minimum. In 1942, ''Arkansas'' received a new tripod foremast and bridgework, along with more anti-aircraft guns throughout the war. By 1945, she carried nine quadruple [[40 mm Bofors]] mounts and twenty-eight [[20 mm Oerlikon]]s,{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau|p=91}} and the number of 3-inch guns had been increased to ten.{{sfn|Breyer|p=202}}

==Ships in class==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!Ship Name!!Hull No.!!Builder{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}!!Laid down{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}!!Launched{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}!!Commissioned{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=114}}!!Decommissioned!!Fate
|-
|{{USS|Wyoming|BB-32}}
| BB-32
| [[William Cramp &amp; Sons]]
| 9 February 1910
| 25 May 1911
| 25 September 1912
| 1 August 1947
| Struck 16 December 1947; Sold for scrap, October 30, 1947 
|-
|{{USS|Arkansas|BB-33}}
| BB-33
| [[New York Shipbuilding Corporation]]
| 25 January 1910
| 14 January 1911
| 17 September 1912
| 29 July 1946
| Struck 15 August 1946; Sunk on 25 July 1946, as part of Operation Crossroads
|}

== Service history ==
[[File:USS Arkansas (BB-33) 1920.jpg|thumb|left|''Arkansas'' underway in 1920]]

After entering service, both ships were assigned to the [[United States Fleet Forces Command|Atlantic Fleet]]. The ships took part in the normal routine of training and fleet maneuvers off the east coast of the United States and in the Caribbean, interspersed with periodic maintenance. Both ships toured the Mediterranean in late 1913, making stops in Italy and France, among others. In April 1914, ''Arkansas'' was involved in the [[occupation of Veracruz]] during the [[Mexican Revolution]], and ''Wyoming'' arrived later to support the operation. Two men from ''Arkansas'' earned the [[Medal of Honor]] for their actions during the initial occupation of the city. After the United States declared war on Germany on 6 April 1917, ''Wyoming'', along with the rest of [[United States Battleship Division Nine (World War I)|Battleship Division 9]] (BatDiv 9), steamed to Britain to reinforce the Royal Navy's [[Grand Fleet]], stationed in [[Scapa Flow]]. ''Arkansas'' initially remained in the United States, training gun crews for the expanding wartime fleet. In July 1918, she too was sent to Britain. Neither ship saw action during the war, though they were present when the German [[High Seas Fleet]] surrendered in November 1918.{{sfn|DANFS Wyoming}}{{sfn|DANFS Arkansas}}

From mid-1919 to mid-1921, ''Arkansas'' and ''Wyoming'' served in the [[US Pacific Fleet|Pacific Fleet]], with the latter serving as the [[flagship]] of BatDiv 6. During this time, the ships made a tour of Central and South American countries, culminating in a visit to [[Valparaiso]], where they took part in a [[naval review]] for the Chilean president. Both battleships returned in service with the Atlantic Fleet in mid-1921. They returned to their peacetime routine of training and maneuvers and periodic maintenance. In the summers, the ships would generally take [[midshipmen]] from the [[US Naval Academy]] on training cruises. In June 1925, ''Arkansas'' assisted relief efforts after the [[1925 Santa Barbara earthquake]]. From late 1925 to late 1926, ''Arkansas'' received her reconstruction, followed by ''Wyoming'' in 1927. In 1929 and 1930, ''Arkansas'' visited European waters on midshipmen cruises; she made stops in several countries. ''Wyoming'' was reduced to a training ship in 1931 in accordance with the London Naval Treaty, and she spent the next decade conducting training cruises for midshipmen and [[NROTC]] cadets.{{sfn|DANFS Wyoming}}{{sfn|DANFS Arkansas}}

[[File:USS Wyoming, gunnery training ship, 1944.jpg|thumb|''Wyoming'' after conversion to a gunnery training ship]]

From early 1932 to early 1934, ''Arkansas'' returned for another stint in the Pacific Fleet, followed by another tour of Europe later in the year. After the outbreak of World War II in September 1939, she was assigned to the reserve force for the [[Neutrality Patrol]]s. She supported the [[Invasion of Iceland|occupation of Iceland]] in July 1941 as an escort for the troopship [[convoy]]s. In November, as it became increasingly apparent that the United States would become involved in World War II, ''Wyoming'' was reassigned as a gunnery training ship, a role she served in for the duration of the war. ''Arkansas'', meanwhile, continued in front-line service during the war, first as an escort to convoys to North Africa, and then as a shore bombardment vessel. She supported the landings at [[Normandy landings|Normandy]] in June 1944, shelling German positions at [[Omaha Beach]], before [[Bombardment of Cherbourg|bombarding Cherbourg]] later in the month. Her next bombardment mission came with [[Operation Dragoon]], the invasion of southern France, in August that year. She was then transferred to the [[Pacific Ocean theater of World War II|Pacific Theater of Operations]] for action against the Japanese. She bombarded Japanese positions on [[Iwo Jima]] in February 1945 and on [[Okinawa]] in April.{{sfn|DANFS Wyoming}}{{sfn|DANFS Arkansas}}

With the end of the war in September 1945, ''Arkansas'' was employed with [[Operation Magic Carpet]], repatriating American soldiers in the Pacific. ''Wyoming'' remained in service briefly after the war, though she was decommissioned in August 1947. She was sold for scrap in October and subsequently [[ship breaking|broken up]]. ''Arkansas'' was instead retained for use as a [[target ship]] during the [[Operation Crossroads]] nuclear tests in mid-1946. She survived the first test, an air-burst code-named ABLE, though the second experiment, an underwater detonation code-named BAKER, sank the ship.{{sfn|DANFS Wyoming}}{{sfn|DANFS Arkansas}}

==See also==
{{Portal bar|Battleships|Military of the United States|World War I|World War II}}
{{Commons category|Wyoming class battleships}}

==Notes==

'''Footnotes'''

{{notes}}

'''Citations'''

{{reflist|24em}}

== References ==
* {{cite DANFS
  | title = Wyoming III (Battleship No. 32)
  | url = http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/w/wyoming-iii.html
  | accessdate = 7 May 2013
  | ref = {{sfnRef|DANFS Wyoming}}
  }}
* {{cite DANFS
  | title = Arkansas III (Battleship No. 33)
  | url = http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/a/arkansas-battleship-no-33-iii.html
  | accessdate = 17 February 2012
  | ref = {{sfnRef|DANFS Arkansas}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | editor1-last = Breyer
  | editor1-first = Siegfried
  | title = Battleships and Battle Cruisers 1905-1970
  | year = 1978
  | location = [[Garden City, New York]]
  | publisher = [[Doubleday and Company]]
  | oclc = 7284895
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Breyer}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Friedman
  | first = Norman
  | authorlink = Norman Friedman
  | year = 2011
  | title = Naval Weapons of World War I
  | publisher = [[Naval Institute Press]]
  | location = [[Annapolis]], Maryland
  | isbn = 978-1-84832-100-7
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Friedman 2011}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Friedman
  | first = Norman
  | year = 1985
  | title = U.S. Battleships: An Illustrated Design History
  | location = Annapolis, Maryland
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | isbn = 0-87021-715-1
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Friedman 1985}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Gardiner
  | first = Robert
  | last2 = Chesneau
  | first2 = Roger
  | year = 1980
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1922–1946
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, Maryland
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-913-9
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | editor1-last = Gardiner
  | editor1-first = Robert
  | editor2-last = Gray
  | editor2-first = Randal
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1906–1921
  | year = 1985
  | location = Annapolis, Mayland
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-907-8
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gardiner &amp; Gray}}
  }}

{{Wyoming class battleship}}
{{WWI US ships}}
{{WWIIUSShips}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wyoming Class Battleship}}
[[Category:Battleship classes]]
[[Category:Wyoming-class battleships| ]]
[[Category:World War I battleships of the United States]]
[[Category:World War II battleships of the United States]]
[[Category:Battleships of the United States Navy]]</text>
      <sha1>o1xhttu73z4jon85630yn9idbx69332</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
