<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Galician)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3609974</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750948595</id>
      <parentid>750911476</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T12:35:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KylieTastic</username>
        <id>2790592</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed broken (red-linked) image - editor 'correcting' text in file names</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52748">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS
|image=[[File:Dyvizia Galychyna.svg|76px]]&lt;br&gt;Divisional insignia of the 14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Galician)
|dates= 28 April 1943 – 15 April 1945
|country={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|allegiance=[[Adolf Hitler]]
|branch= [[File:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|23px]] [[Waffen-SS]]
|type=[[Infantry]]
|role= 
|size=[[Division (military)|Division]]
|nickname=Galician Division&lt;br&gt; ''Dyviziya [[Halychyna]]''
|battles=[[World War II]]
* [[Lvov-Sandomierz Offensive]]
* [[Slovak National Uprising]]
* [[Vienna Offensive]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
|colors= Blue &amp; Yellow {{color box|#0000CD}}{{color box|#F9DD16}}&lt;ref name=&quot;ua1455&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Abbott|first=Peter|title=Ukrainian Armies 1914–55|year=2004|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=1-84176-668-2|pages=41|url=https://books.google.com/?id=S0Us4SD3_3QC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Abbot,+Peter.+Ukrainian+Armies#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false| accessdate= 1 April 2011 &lt;!--Added by DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors_label= Colors
|march=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|commander2=
|commander2_label=
|commander3=
|commander3_label=
|notable_commanders=[[Walter Schimana]]&lt;br&gt;[[Fritz Freitag]]
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
|identification_symbol_3=
|identification_symbol_3_label=
|identification_symbol_4=
|identification_symbol_4_label=
}}

The '''14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Galician)''' ({{lang-de|14. Waffen Grenadier Division der SS (galizische Nr.1)}}, {{lang-uk|''14а Гренадерська Дивізія СС (1а галицька)''}}), prior to 1944 titled the '''14th SS-Volunteer Division &quot;Galicia&quot;''' ({{lang-de|14. SS-Freiwilligen Division &quot;Galizien&quot;}}, {{lang-uk|''14а Добровільна Дивізія СС &quot;Галичина&quot;''}})&lt;ref name=&quot;ua1455&quot;/&gt; was a World War II German military formation made up predominantly of volunteers with a [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] ethnic background from the area of [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Galicia]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson Gordon 1994, pp.123-4&quot;&gt;Williamson Gordon, SS Hitler's Instrument of Terror, Amber books 1994, pp.123–4&lt;/ref&gt; later also with some [[Slovaks]], [[Czechs]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson Gordon 1994, pp.123-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;IRikmenspoel Marc, Waffen SS Encyclopedia, Aberjona Press, 2004. p.90&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Dutch people|Dutch]] volunteers and officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kleitmann K. G p. 183&quot;&gt;Kleitmann K. G. Die Waffen SS; eine Dokumentation. Osnabreuck, Der Freiwillige, 1965 p. 183&lt;/ref&gt; Formed in 1943, it was largely destroyed in the [[Lvov-Sandomierz Offensive|battle of Brody]], reformed, and saw action in [[Slovakia]], [[Yugoslavia]] and Austria before being renamed the first division of the [[Ukrainian National Army]] and surrendering to the Western Allies by 10 May 1945.

==Background==
After World War I and the dissolution of [[Austria–Hungary]], the territory of [[Galicia (Central Europe)|Eastern Galicia]] ([[Halychyna]]), populated by a Ukrainian majority but with a large Polish minority, was incorporated into Poland following the [[Polish–Ukrainian War]]. Between the wars, the political allegiances of Ukrainians in eastern Galicia were divided between moderate national democrats and the more radical [[Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists]]. The latter group itself splintered into two factions, the more moderate OUN-M led by [[Andriy Atanasovych Melnyk|Andriy Melnyk]] with close ties to German intelligence ([[Abwehr]]), and the more radical OUN-B led by [[Stepan Bandera]]. When Poland was divided between Germany and the Soviet Union under the terms of the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]] in 1939, the territory of eastern Galicia was [[Soviet annexation of Western Ukraine, 1939–1940|annexed to Soviet Ukraine]]. In 1941 it was [[Operation Barbarossa|occupied by Germany]].

Ukrainian leaders of various political persuasions recognised the need for a trained armed force. The Germans had earlier considered the formation of an armed force made up of Slavic people, but they decided this to be unacceptable as they regarded Slavs as sub-humans (''[[untermenschen]]'') compared to the Germanic ubermenschen master race.&lt;ref&gt;[[Domenico Losurdo]], &quot;Toward a Critique of the Category of Totalitarianism&quot;, ''Historical Materialism'' 12.2 (April 2004), p.25-55, p.50.&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of 1943, growing losses&lt;ref&gt;Idzio, V. Ukrains'ka Povstans'ka Armiya – zhidno zi svidchenniamy nimetskykh ta radians'kykh arkhiviv, Lviv, 2005, p.82&lt;/ref&gt; inclined Nazi leaders to alter their initial opinions.

==Organizing the division==
The idea to organize a division of volunteers from Galicia was proposed by the German Governor of [[District Galicia]], Dr. [[Otto Wächter|Otto von Wächter]]. He suggested creation of a [[Waffen-SS]] division composed of Galician volunteers and designed for regular combat on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. The creation of 14th Voluntary Division SS ''Galizien'' was announced in April 1943 at ceremonies throughout Galicia. At least 50 documents including contemporary newspaper clippings, radio broadcasts and speeches etc. record the date of 28 April. By June 1943 the first phase of recruitment had taken place. Initially Wächter's proposal (which he was certain would be supported by Ukrainian circles) was rejected. In Berlin Wächter was able to get support from [[Heinrich Himmler]] who made the stipulation that the division would only made up of Galicians, who Himmler considered &quot;more Aryan-like&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toronto p. 17&quot;&gt;Hajke Wolf-Dietrich The Ukrainian Division &quot;Galicia&quot; Toronto, 1970 p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; The terms &quot;Ukrainian&quot;, &quot;Ukraine&quot;, could not be used when addressing the division, stressing the Imperial Austro-Hungarian heritage of the term &quot;Galizien&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Idzio, V. Ukrains'ka Povstans'ka Armiya – zhidno zi svidchenniamy nimetskykh ta radians'kykh arkhiviv, Lviv, 2005, p.83&lt;/ref&gt; David Marples suggests that the division was titled &quot;Galicia&quot; to ensure stricter German control to avoid direct use of inflammatory term &quot;Ukrainian&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;David R. Marples,  ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=bGPjqNGPc40C&amp;pg=PA184 Heroes and villains: creating national history in contemporary Ukraine]'', CEU Press, 2007, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lemberg280443-2.jpg|thumb|[[District Galicia|Distrikts Galizien]] Spring 1943. Celebrations dedicated to the creation of the [[14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Galicia (1st Ukrainian)|SS-Freiwilligen-Schützen-Division «Galizien»]]. Regional recruitment center ]]

Wächter approached the Ukrainian Central Committee, a nonpolitical social welfare organization headed by [[Volodymyr Kubiyovych]] which supported the idea of the formation of the division.&lt;ref&gt;[[Orest Subtelny]]. (1988). ''Ukraine: a History.'' Toronto: University of Toronto Press. pg. 457&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church|Ukrainian Catholic Church]] demanded the presence of its chaplains in the division, which was usually not permitted by Germans. Thus the Ukrainian division along with the [[13th Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Handschar (1st Croatian)|Bosnian]] one became notable exceptions.

Germans made two [[concession (politics)|political concessions]]: It was stipulated that the division shall not be used to fight Western Allies, and would be used exclusively to &quot;fight Bolsheviks&quot;. The other concession was in that its oath of allegiance to Hitler was conditional &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.litmir.net/br/?b=123432&amp;p=190 taken from [[Richard Landwehr]], Fighting for Freedom: The Ukrainian Volunteer Division of the Waffen-SS, Bibliophile Legion Books, Silver Spring, Maryland, 1985, p. 45 ] Standard German Waffen SS oath: &quot;I swear to you Adolf Hitler, as Leader and Chancellor of the Reich, loyalty and valor. I vow to you and all those you place over me obedience until death, so help me God.&quot; Galician Oath: &quot;I swear by God this holy oath, that in the struggle against Bolshevism I will give the Commander-in-Chief of the German Armed Forces, Adolf Hitler, absolute obedience, and if it be his will, as a fearless soldier, I will always be prepared to lay down my life for this oath.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; on the fight against Bolshevism and in the fact that Christian (mostly [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]] and [[Ukrainian Orthodox]]) chaplains were integrated into the units and allowed to function (in the Waffen-SS, only the Bosnian division and [[Sturmbrigade Wallonien]] had a clerical presence). The latter condition was instituted at the insistence of the division's organizers in order to minimize the risk of Nazi demoralization amongst the soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Logusz&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| author=Michael O. Logusz | title=Galicia Division: The Waffen-SS 14th Grenadier Division, 1943–1945| location=Altglen, Pennsylvania | publisher=[[Schiffer Publishing|Schiffer Military History]] | year =1997| isbn=0-7643-0081-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=August 2010}} Indeed, Nazi indoctrination was absent within the division.&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrong&quot; /&gt;

The creation of foreign SS units had been carried out previously in the name of fighting against communism; with [[33rd Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Charlemagne (1st French)|French]], [[Nederlandsche SS|Dutch]], [[15th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Latvian)|Latvian]], [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)|Estonian]], Croatian, and [[30th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS|Belarusian]] units, among others, had been created.&lt;ref&gt;Mazower, Mark (2008) Hitler's Empire, pp 454–460&lt;/ref&gt; The creation of a Ukrainian SS division was perceived by many in Ukraine as a step towards the attainment of Ukrainian independence and attracted many volunteers.

==The Division's Support==
The Division enjoyed support from multiple political and religious groups within the western Ukrainian community. The Division's prime organizer and highest ranking Ukrainian officer, [[Dmytro Paliiv]], had been the leader of a small legal political party in the [[Second Polish Republic]]. Many of his colleagues had been members of the pre-war moderate, left-leaning democratic [[Ukrainian National Democratic Alliance|UNDO movement]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Timothy Snyder]]. (2004) ''The Reconstruction of Nations.'' New Haven: Yale University Press: pg. 218.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|John A. Armstrong. (1963). ''Ukrainian Nationalism''. New York: Columbia University Press, pp. 18–19 Armstrong stated that the UNDO was &quot;definitely democratic in character, with varying amounts of Catholic, liberal, and socialist ideology embedded in its program&quot;|group = nb}} that before the war had also been opposed to the authoritarian OUN. The Division also obtained moral support from officers of the exiled Polish-allied [[Ukrainian National Republic]] such as General [[Mykhailo Omelianovych-Pavlenko]].&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrong&quot;&gt;John A. Armstrong. (1963). ''Ukrainian Nationalism''. New York: Columbia University Press, pp. 170–175&lt;/ref&gt; The Division was also strongly supported by [[Andriy Atanasovych Melnyk|Andriy Melnyk]]'s moderate faction of the OUN, who saw it as a counterweight to the extremist Banderist-dominated UPA.&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrong&quot; /&gt;

The Bandera faction of the OUN-B strongly opposed the idea of creating the division, in part because it was an organization outside its control, and claimed in its propaganda that the division was to be used by the Germans as cannon fodder. {{#tag:ref|Michael O. Logusz. (1997). ''Galicia Division: The Waffen-SS 14th Grenadier Division, 1943–1945''. Altglen, Pennsylvania: [[Schiffer Publishing|Schiffer Military History]]. Pg. 62. In an article entitled ''Around the SS Division Galiica'' published in the OUN-B's underground newspaper, the division was claimed to be formed by the Germans in order to &quot;deprive (the Ukrainian movement) of its active element&quot; by &quot;throwing it away as cannon fodder&quot;, emphasizing that the division was to be &quot;a typical colonial element, somewhat comparable to the British Army's Indian or New Zealand Divisions&quot; and concluding that &quot;today, we have no doubts that not a Ukrainian, but a German colonial element is forming. The attitude of the Ukrainian nation to it, as it was to all previous German experiments – negative.&quot;|group = nb}}  Nevertheless, it did not interfere in its formation and once the division was formed it sent some of its members, a number of whom would obtain prominent positions, into the division in order for them to gain military training and to prevent it from completely getting out of their hands. Despite this infiltration, Bandera's OUN failed to gain control over the division.&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrong&quot; /&gt;

It also had the support of both the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church and the [[Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church]]. Among its members was a son of [[Patriarch Mstyslav (Stepan Skrypnyk)|Mstyslav Skrypnyk]], the Orthodox Bishop of Kiev.&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrong&quot; /&gt;

==The division==

===Command===

The Division SS &quot;Galizien&quot; was commanded by German, Austrian and Ukrainian officers&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchum162&quot;&gt;Mitcham, p162&lt;/ref&gt; who were delegated to the division.

Training for the recruits began within the SS-Special Purpose Training Battalion (SS-Ausbildungs-Battalion z.b.V, commanded by SS Sturmbannfuher Bernard Bartlet while the man appointed to oversee the raising of the Division was [[SS-Obergruppenfuhrer|General]] [[Walter Schimana]] (until October 1943). Schimana never commanded the division as up until the point of his departure it was still a training battalion, staffed mostly by temporary training personnel. From 20 November 1943 SS-[[Brigadeführer|Brigadier General]] [[Fritz Freitag]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchum162&quot; /&gt; [[Hauptmann|Captain]] [[Wolf Dietrich Heike]] (temporarily seconded from the [[Wehrmacht]]) was the chief of staff from January 1944. All regimental commanders were Germans.

===The soldiers===
[[File:GalSSestact.gif|thumb|right|200px|SS Galizien Appeal leaflet in Ukrainian. Comprise a description of the division inauguration ceremony. [[General Government]], May 1943.]]

In total 81,999 men enlisted for service in the division. Of these, 42,000 were called up during the first &quot;recruitment phase&quot; which took place in May and June 1943 from which only 27,000 were deemed fit for military service and 13,000 were enlisted.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Logusz. (1997). ''Galicia Division.'' Altglen, PA: Schiffer Military History. pg. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; To boost the recruitment figures the height minimum requirement was lowered from 1.65m to 1.61m.

[[File:1943 hofscheller.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Hans Frank]] and Dr. Hofstetter of SS Galizien enter a [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church|Ukrainian Greek Catholic]] church prior to the installation of volunteers in [[Sanok]], 1943.]]
[[File:1943sanok kosciuszki ukr ss.jpg|thumb|right|200px|SS Galizien volunteers march on Kosciuszko Street in [[Sanok]], 1943 May]]

==Deployment==

===Anti-partisans actions with ''Kampfgruppe Beyersdorff''===
In mid February 1944 the division received an order to form a battle group known as SS [[Kampfgruppe]] Beyersdorff for action against Soviet and Polish [[Partisan (military)|partisans]]. It operated in the [[Zamość]] area together with elements of the 5th Regiment, while elements of the 4th Regiment were sent to [[Brody]]. The SS Kampfgruppe performed its duty well enough that it earned the rare praise of German Field Marshal [[Walter Model]].&lt;ref&gt;* {{Cite book  |last=Mitcham  |first=Samuel W  |year=2007  |title=The German Defeat in the East, 1944–45  |location=Mechanicsburg, PA  |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]]  |isbn=978-0-8117-3371-7  |page=74}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Brody===
In July the division was sent to the area of Brody, where [[Lvov-Sandomierz Offensive|heavy combat]] was under way, and was attached to the 13th Army Corps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Logusz&quot; /&gt; Together with six under-strength German infantry divisions, the Galicia Division was responsible for holding a frontage of approximately {{convert|80|km|mi|abbr=off}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Logusz&quot; /&gt; On 8 July, the 13th Corps was transferred to the 1st Panzer Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Logusz&quot; /&gt; The Galician Division was placed in reserve. Deployed at Brody were the division's 29th, 30th, 31st regiments, a fusilier and engineering battalion, and its artillery regiment. The 14th SS Field Replacement Battalion was deployed {{convert|15|mi|km|spell=in|abbr=off}} behind the other units.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot;&gt;* {{Cite book  |last=Mitcham  |first=Samuel W  |year=2007  |title=The German Defeat in the East, 1944–45  |location=Mechanicsburg, PA  |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]]  |isbn=978-0-8117-3371-7  |pages=74–86}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 13 July, Soviet forces under the command of Marshal [[Ivan Konev]] launched their attack. By the next day, they routed a German division to the north of the 13th Corps and swept back an attempted German counterattack.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}  On 15 July, the [[1st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|1st]] and [[8th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|8th]] Panzer Divisions along with the Galicia Division bore the brunt of a fierce assault by the Soviet [[2nd Air Army|Second Air Army]], who in only a five-hour period flew 3,288 aircraft sorties and dropped 102 tons of bombs on them as they attempted a counterattack.&lt;ref&gt;cited in Michael Logusz's ''Galicia Division: the Waffen-SS 14th Grenadier Division, 1943–1945.''&lt;/ref&gt; On 18 July, the division's Field Replacement Battalion was destroyed with its remnants fleeing west, whilst the remainder of 13th Corps, consisting of over 30,000 German and Ukrainian soldiers, was surrounded by the Soviets within the Brody pocket.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt;

Within the pocket, the Galician troops were tasked with defending the eastern perimeter near the [[Pidhirtsi Castle|castle and town of Pidhirtsy]] and [[Olesko]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt; The Soviets sought to collapse the Brody pocket by focusing their attack of what they perceived to be its weakest point, the relatively inexperienced Galician Division, and on 19 July attacked.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt; The 29th and 30th regiments of the division, supported by the division's artillery regiment, put up unexpectedly fierce resistance. Pidhirtsy changed hands several times before the Galicians were finally overwhelmed by the late afternoon, and at [[Olesko]] a major Soviet attack using [[T-34]] tanks was repulsed by the division's Fusilier and Engineer battalions.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt;

On 20 July, the German divisions within the pocket attempted a breakout which failed despite early successes.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt; The Division's 31st regiment was destroyed in fighting. A second German breakout attempt that began at 1:00&amp;nbsp;am on 21 July ended in failure. {{convert|10|mi|km|spell=in\abbr=off}} to the west of the pocket, however, a German [[Panzergrenadier]] Regiment broke through Soviet lines and briefly established contact with the Brody pocket, resulting in the rescue of approximately 3,400 soldiers, including approximately 400 Galicians, before being repulsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt; By the end of that day, in the face of overwhelming Soviet attacks, the 14th Division as a whole disintegrated.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt; Its German commander, Fritz Freitag, resigned his command and decreed that everyone would be on his own during the breakout. He and his staff formed their own battle group and headed south, abandoning the division.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt; Some Ukrainian assault groups remained intact, others joined German units, and others fled or melted away. The Ukrainian 14th SS Fusilier battalion, still intact, came to form the rearguard of what was left of the entire 13th Corps. Holding the town of [[Bilyi Kamin]], it enabled units or stragglers to escape to the south and was able to withstand several Soviet attempts to overwhelm it. By the evening of 21 July, it remained the only intact unit north of the [[Bug River]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt;

In the early morning of 22 July, the 14th Fusilier battalion abandoned Bilye Kamin. The Brody pocket was now only {{convert|4|to(-)|5|mi|km|abbr=off}} long and wide. The German and Galician soldiers were instructed to attack with everything they had by moving forward until they broke through or were destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt; Fighting was fierce and desperate. The German and Ukrainian soldiers surging south were able to overwhelm the Soviet 91st Independent Tank Brigade &quot;Proskurov&quot; and its infantry support, and to escape by the hundreds. The remaining pocket collapsed by the evening of 22 July.&lt;ref name=&quot;mitchum&quot; /&gt;

Despite the severity of the fighting, the division maintained its discipline and most of its members were ultimately able to break out of the encirclement. Of the approximately 11,000 Galician soldiers deployed at Brody, about 3,000 were able to almost immediately re-enter the division. Approx 7,400 were posted as &quot;Missing in combat&quot;.

Soviet statistics give the German losses at Brody as 2 Generals, 30,000 men killed and 17,000 captured (which was more than the number in the entire Corps).&lt;ref&gt;Landwehr Richard – Fighting for freedom – The Ukrainian Volunteer Division of the Waffen SS. Bebliophile Legion Books, (2nd edition), 1985. p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been mistakenly suggested {{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} that the losses for the 14th SS Division in Brody ran at 73%, higher than the rest of the Corps. The other battle-hardened German units which had formed XIII.A.K. produced similar casualty reports. About 5,000 men of Korpsabteilung 'C' which formed the spearhead of the breakout forces escaped the encirclement with sidearms but without vehicles, horses, and other weapons, supplies, and equipment. A total of 73 officers and 4,059 NCOs and men were listed as killed or missing. By comparison, the [[361st Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|361st Infantry Division]] which deployed fewer troops at the beginning of the battle than the Galician Division and together with it formed the rearguard, suffered equal losses. Between 16–22 July, it sustained almost as many casualties with total losses amounting to 6,310 officers and men (dead, missing or wounded). The necessary manpower required to rebuild this and the other German formations was not available and they were subsequently disbanded and the survivors incorporated into other divisions.

As for XIII.A.K., the final report of the Corps's liquidation commission (applicable to its regular army units only) recorded 21,766 killed or missing in action, which together with the 7,000 killed or missing men from the Galician Division brings to the total lost to about 29,000. This figure corresponds with General Lange's own estimate of a total of 25–30,000 killed in the encirclement. On the other hand, the recently declassified secret Soviet General Staff report states that during the course of the battle their forces destroyed more than 30,000 soldiers and officers, 85 tanks and self-propelled guns, over 500 guns of various calibres, 476 mortars, 705 machine guns, 12,000 rifles and submachine guns, 5,843 vehicles, 183 tractors and trailers and 2,430 motorcycles and bicycles. It also claims that over 17,000 soldiers and officers were taken prisoner, 28 tanks and self-propelled guns were captured, as were over 500 guns of various calibres, more than 600 mortars, 483 machine guns, 11,000 rifles and sub-machine guns, over 1,500 vehicles, 98 tractors and trailers, 376 motorcycles and bicycles, in excess of 3,000 horses and 28 warehouses full of military goods. An estimated total number of survivors of all XIII.A.K. units has been given by the adjutant of the [[349th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|349th Infantry Division]] as 15,000 officers and men, while a slightly lower figure of 12,000 was subsequently given by Oberst Wilck.

The 3000 survivors of the Galician Division were used as a nucleus for the rebuilt 14th SS Division. Those that were captured were either executed or sent to slave-labour camps. Approximately 2,000 + are thought to have joined up with the [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army|UIA]].&lt;ref&gt;Landwehr Richard – Fighting for freedom – The Ukrainian Volunteer Division of the Waffen SS. Bebliophile Legion Books, (2nd edition), 1985. p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; {{Dubious|date=October 2010}}

===The division in Slovakia===
The Germans rebuilt the division over several months using reserve units. From the end of September 1944, the division was used against the [[Slovak National Uprising]].&lt;ref&gt;Боляновський А.В. Дивізія «Галичина»: історія  — Львів: , 2000. ISBN 966-02-1635-1 pages 270–281&lt;/ref&gt;

The first unit, the 29th regiment with auxiliary units, arrived 28 September 1944. Eventually all divisional units were transferred to Slovakia. From 15 October 1944 they formed two Kampfgruppe, Wittenmayer (which included 3 battalions) and Wildner.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Боляновський А.В. Дивізія «Галичина»: історія  — Львів: , 2000. ISBN 966-02-1635-1-page 271&lt;/ref&gt; The division acted against rebels together with the [[18th SS Volunteer Panzer Grenadier Division Horst Wessel]], the [[36th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS|SS-Sturmbrigade Dirlewanger SS]], the [[Andrey Vlasov|Vlasov detachment]] and other SS and SD formations until 5 February 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Michaelis, Rolf &quot;Esten, Russen und Ukrainer in der Waffen-SS&quot; ISBN 3-938392-25-8 Winkelried-Verlag 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Jan Stanislav, the director of the National Uprising Museum in Slovakia, denied that the division or that Ukrainians took part in any brutalities committed against the Slovak people at this time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Interview with Dr. Jan Stanislav May 2000 |url=http://www.telusplanet.net/public/mozuz/articles/torontostar20001227.html#bot8 |work= |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5jWEpw3rj?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.telusplanet.net%2Fpublic%2Fmozuz%2Farticles%2Ftorontostar20001227.html |archivedate=3 September 2009 |deadurl=no |accessdate=3 September 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-partisans actions on the Slovenian-Austrian border===
In the end of January 1945, it was moved to [[Slovenia]], where from the end of February until the end of March 1945, it together with other SS and SD formations fought [[Yugoslav Partisans]] in the [[Styria]] and [[Carinthia (province)]] areas near the Austrian-Slovenian border.&lt;ref&gt;Karel Prusnik-Gasper, Gemsen auf der Lawine. Der Kдrntner Partisanenkampf (Ljubjana/Klagenfurt 1981)&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, the division absorbed the 31 [[Sicherheitspolizei|SD]] Schutzmannschafts Battalion, also known as the Ukrainian Self Defense legion.&lt;ref name=&quot;WOLF-DIETRICH HEIKE 1945&quot;&gt;WOLF-DIETRICH HEIKE.UKRAINISCHE DIVISION &quot;GALIZIEN&quot;. Geschichte der Aufstellung und des Einsatzes (1943–1945) 1970&lt;/ref&gt; When on 31 March Soviet forces commenced an [[Vienna Offensive|attack from Hungary into Austria]] that ruptured the German front, the division was ordered to advance northward to Gleichenberg in a desperate attempt to halt the Soviet advance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Logusz&quot; /&gt;

===Graz===
From 1 April until the end of the war, with a strength of 14,000 combat troops and 8,000 soldiers in a Training and Replacement Regiment, the division fought against the Red Army in the region of [[Graz]] in Austria&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=ss galizien|url=http://ipn.gov.pl/portal/pl/24/1304/?poz=3| accessdate=9 October 2009 &lt;!--Added by DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
where in early April it seized the castle and village of [[Bad Gleichenberg|Gleichenberg]] from Soviet forces (including elite Soviet airborne troops from the [[3rd Guards Airborne Division]]) during a counterattack and on 15 April repulsed a Soviet counterattack. The division at this time maintained a 13-km front.&lt;ref name=&quot;Logusz&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lib.galiciadivision.com/heike/r12.html On-line Ukrainian-language translation Of Wolf-Dietrich Heike's book ''THE UKRAINIAN DIVISION &quot;GALICIA&quot; THE HISTORY OF ITS FORMATION AND MILITARY OPERATIONS''] The English-language [http://lib.galiciadivision.com/heike-eng/synopsis.html synapse] mentions that the division &quot;distinguished itself&quot; and maintained a sector of the front until German capitulation&lt;/ref&gt; During one critical situation, Freitag became so alarmed by the developments at the front, that in the presence of the commander of the 1st Cavalry Corps General der Kavallerie Harteneck, he reacted instinctively and announced his abdication as Divisional commander and responsibility for its performance in action – as he had done at Brody. General Harteneck refused Freitag's resignation and ordered him to remain at his post. Due to his performance during the battles surrounding Gleichenberg, Waffen-[[Obersturmführer]] Ostap Czuczkewycz was awarded the [[Iron Cross]], 1st class.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Melnyk. (2007). ''To Battle: The Formation and History of the 14. Gallician SS Volunteer Division''. Helion and Company. ISBN 1-874622-19-1 pg. 262. Cited from Personal-Akte A3343-SSO-133 (ff. 25–26) NA.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Division suffered heavy casualties while in Austria, with an estimated 1,600 killed or wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Melnyk. (2007). ''To Battle: The Formation and History of the 14. Gallician SS Volunteer Division''. Helion and Company. ISBN 1-874622-19-1 pg. 268&lt;/ref&gt;

==1st Ukrainian Division UNA==
On 17 March 1945, Ukrainian émigrés established the Ukrainian National Committee to represent the interests of Ukrainians to the Third Reich. Simultaneously, the [[Ukrainian National Army]], commanded by general [[Pavlo Shandruk]], was created. The Galician Division nominally became the 1st Division of the Ukrainian National Army, although the German Army's High command continued to list it as the Ukrainian 14th SS Grenadier Division in its order of battle.&lt;ref&gt;Gosztony, Peter, Endkampf an der Donau 1944/45, Wien: Molden Taschenbuch Verlag, 1978. ISBN 3-217-05126-2&lt;/ref&gt; The Division surrendered to British and US forces by 10 May 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;WOLF-DIETRICH HEIKE 1945&quot; /&gt;

===Rimini===
The Ukrainian soldiers were interned in [[Rimini]], Italy, in the area controlled by [[Polish II Corps]] forces. The UNA commander [[Pavlo Shandruk]] requested for a meeting with Polish general [[Władysław Anders]] in London, and asked him to protect the army against the deportation to Soviet Union. Despite the Soviet pressure, Anders managed to protect Ukrainian soldiers, as the former citizens of the [[Second Republic of Poland]]. This, together with the intervention of the [[Holy See|Vatican]] saved its members from deportation to the USSR. Bishop Buchko of the [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]] had appealed to [[Pope Pius XII]] to intervene on behalf of the division, whom he described as &quot;good Catholics and fervent anti-Communists&quot;. Due to Vatican intervention, the British authorities changed the status of Division members from POW to surrendered enemy personnel&lt;ref&gt;Howard Margolian. (2000). ''Unauthorized Entry: The Truth about Nazi War Criminals in Canada, 1946–1956.''
Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2000. ISBN 0-8020-4277-5. pg. 135&lt;/ref&gt; and the Polish II Corps declined their deportation to Soviet Union.
176 soldiers of the division joined [[Władysław Anders]]'s [[Polish Armed Forces in the West|Polish army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ipngov1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://ipn.gov.pl/portal/pl/24/1304/?poz=3 | title=DYWIZJA SS &quot;GALIZIEN&quot; | year=2001 | publisher=[[Instytut Pamięci Narodowej]]| accessdate=9 October 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GD1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.galiciadivision.com/personalities/ | title=Personnel | year=2009 | publisher=&lt;nowiki&gt;[Galicia Division .com]&lt;/nowiki&gt;| accessdate=9 October 2009 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091109210238/http://www.galiciadivision.com/personalities/| archivedate=9 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Former soldiers of SS &quot;Galizien&quot; were allowed to immigrate to Canada&lt;ref name=&quot;ucccanada&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.parl.gc.ca/information/library/PRBpubs/873-e.htm | title = War criminals: The Deschenes Commission | date=16 October 1998 | publisher=&lt;nowiki&gt;[Library of Parliament (Canada)]&lt;/nowiki&gt;| accessdate=9 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the United Kingdom in 1947.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Ukrainian SS 'Galicia' Division allowed to settle in Britain|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/releases/2005/highlights_aug/aug3/default.htm|date=August 2005 | publisher=UK National archives| accessdate=9 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The names of about 7,100 former soldiers of the regiment who were admitted to the UK have been stored in the so-called &quot;Rimini List&quot;. Despite several requests of various lobby groups, the details of the list have never been publicly released. In 2003 the anti-terrorist branch of [[Scotland Yard]] launched an investigation into people from the list by cross-referencing [[National Health Service (England)|NHS]] patient, [[social security]] and pensions records; however, the order to release confidential medical records was met with outcry from [[civil liberties]] groups.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt; Daniel Foggo, &lt;/nowiki&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/1433729/Police-to-use-NHS-records-to-find-Nazi-war-criminals.html Police to use NHS records to find Nazi war criminals], ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]'', 22 June 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accusations of war atrocities==
Although the Galizien Division has not specifically been found guilty of any war crimes by any war tribunal or commission, numerous unproven accusations of impropriety have been levelled at the division and at particular members of the division from a variety of sources. It is difficult to determine the extent of war criminality among members of the division.&lt;ref name=&quot;Margolian&quot;&gt;Howard Margolian. (2000). ''Unauthorized Entry: The Truth about Nazi War Criminals in Canada, 1946–1956.'' Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2000. ISBN 0-8020-4277-5. pp. 132–145&lt;/ref&gt;  If prior service in Nazi police units is a measure of criminality, only a small number were recruited from established police detachments. Among those who had transferred from police detachments, some had been members of a coastal defence unit that had been stationed in France, while others came from two police battalions that had been formed in the spring of 1943, too late to have participated in the murder of Ukraine's Jews. According to Howard Margolian there is no evidence that these units participated in anti-partisan operations or reprisals prior to their inclusion into the division. However, a number of recruits, prior to their service within the police battalions are alleged to have been in Ukrainian irregular formations that are alleged to have committed atrocities against Jews and Communists. However, both the Canadian government and the Canadian Jewish Congress in their investigations of the division failed to find hard evidence to support the notion that it was rife with criminal elements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Margolian&quot; /&gt;

It has been claimed that the division destroyed several Polish communities in western Ukraine during the winter and spring of 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;snyderdivision&quot;&gt;[[Timothy Snyder]]. (2004) ''The Reconstruction of Nations.'' New Haven: Yale University Press: pp. 165–166&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, the 4th and 5th SS Police Regiments have been accused of murdering Polish civilians in the course of anti-guerilla activity. At the time of their actions, these units were not yet under Divisional command, but were under German police command.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;Institute of Ukrainian History, Academy of Sciences of Ukraine, [http://history.org.ua/oun_upa/Upa/16.pdf ''Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists and the Ukrainian Insurgent Army'', Chapter 5, p. 284]. Accessed 9 September 2009. [http://www.webcitation.org/5ji172zi1 Archived] 11 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Yale historian [[Timothy Snyder]] concluded that the division's role in the [[Massacres of Poles in Volhynia and Eastern Galicia|ethnic cleansing of Poles]] from western Ukraine was marginal.&lt;ref name=&quot;snyderdivision&quot; /&gt;

Heinrich Himmler in a speech to the soldiers of the division stated &quot;&quot;…Your homeland has become so much more beautiful since you have lost – on our initiative, I must say – those residents who were so often a dirty blemish on Galicia's good name, namely the Jews...I know that if I ordered you to liquidate the Poles...I would be giving you permission to do what you are eager to do anyway.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Poland's Holocaust: Ethnic Strife, Collaboration with Occupying Forces and Genocide in the Second Republic, 1918-1947, page 231
 By Tadeusz Piotrowsk&lt;/ref&gt;

===Huta Pieniacka===
''For more information about the subject, see: [[Huta Pieniacka massacre]]''
[[File:HutaPieniacka-3.jpg|thumb|upright|One of the stone tablets of the monument which lists the names of Poles killed at Huta Pienacka]]
[[File:Поховання (Меморіал воїнів Української дивізії “Галичина” ).jpg|thumbnail|Memorial to SS-Galizien division in Chervone, [[Lviv Oblast]], western Ukraine]]
The Polish historian [[Grzegorz Motyka (historian)|Motyka]] has stated that the Germans formed several SS police regiments (numbered from 4 to 8) which included &quot;Galizien&quot; in their name. These police regiments would later join the division in Spring 1944. Before being incorporated into the division in June 1944,&lt;ref name=Logusz/&gt; the 4th and 5th police regiments had participated in anti-guerrilla action at [[Huta Pieniacka]] on 23 February 1944,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Instytut Pamięci Narodowej !-- BOT GENERATED TITLE --&gt; |author=IPN-KŚZpNP – Sebastian Górkiewicz !-- BOT GENERATED AUTHOR --&gt; |url=http://www.ipn.gov.pl/portal.php?serwis=pl&amp;dzial=24&amp;id=1304&amp;poz=3 |work=|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5jY7czGBZ |archivedate=4 September 2009 |deadurl=no |accessdate=3 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; against Soviet and Polish [[Armia Krajowa]] partisans in the village of [[Huta Pieniacka]] which had also served as a shelter for Jews and as a fortified centre for Polish and Soviet guerrillas.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt; Huta Pieniacka was a Polish self-defence outpost&lt;!--''Was it really ? was it not against the Germans, the Russians AND the UPA ?'': against [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army|UPA]] --&gt;,&lt;ref&gt;G. Motyka, ''Ukraińska partyzantka, 1942–1960'', PAN, 2006, p.383&lt;/ref&gt; organized by inhabitants of the village and sheltering civilian refugees from [[Volhynia]].&lt;ref&gt;Bogusława Marcinkowska, ''Ustalenia wynikające ze śledztwa w sprawie zbrodni ludobójstwa funkcjonariuszy SS &quot;GALIZIEN&quot; i nacjonalistów ukraińskich na Polakach w Hucie Pieniackiej 28 lutego 1944 roku'', Biuletyn Instytutu Pamięci Narodowej, 1/2001 [http://www.ipn.gov.pl/portal.phpserwis=pl&amp;dzial=24&amp;id=1304&amp;poz=4&amp;update=1]&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 February 1944 two members of a detachment of the division were shot by the self-defense forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;melnyk&quot;&gt;Michael James Melnyk. (2007). ''To Battle: The Formation and History of the 14th Waffen-SS Grenadier Division''. Helion and Company. Chapter 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Five days later a mixed force of Ukrainian police and German soldiers shelled the village with artillery before entering it and ordering all the civilians to gather together. In the ensuing massacre, the village of Huta Pienacka was destroyed and between 500&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archives.gov.ua/Archives/Dzerelna_baza.php Ukrainian state archives]&lt;/ref&gt; and 1,000&lt;!-- no source states more than this --&gt; of the inhabitants were killed. According to Polish accounts, civilians were locked in barns that were set on fire while those attempting to flee were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;IPN&quot;&gt;[http://www.ipn.gov.pl/portal/en/19/188/Investigation_of_the_Crime_Committed_at_the_Village_of_Huta_Pieniacka.html]. Accessed 3 September 2009. [http://www.webcitation.org/5jWExyI3v Archived] 3 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Polish witness accounts state that the soldiers &lt;!--Already stated their uniforms were covered so cannot possibly have known: SS Galizien --&gt;were accompanied by Ukrainian nationalists (paramilitary unit under [[Włodzimierz Czerniawski]]'s command), which included members of the [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army|UPA]], as well as inhabitants of local villages who took property from the village's households.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiadomosci.wp.pl/kat,1342,title,IPN-prowadzi-sledztwo-ws-mordu-w-Hucie-Pieniackiej,wid,10895470,wiadomosc.html Polish Instytute of Membrance]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Institute of History of the Ukrainian Academy of Sciences concluded that the 4th and 5th SS Galizien Police regiments&lt;!-- See previous note &quot;''These regiments later joined the division in Spring 1944. Before being incorporated into the division''&quot;: of the division, --&gt; did indeed kill the civilians within the village, but added that the grisly reports by eyewitnesses in the Polish accounts were &quot;hard to come up with&quot; and that the likelihood was &quot;difficult to believe.&quot;  The Institute also noted that at the time of the massacre the police regiments&lt;!-- See previous note - Unfortunately the opening paragraph says they joined later:, while members of the Division,--&gt; were not under 14th division command, but rather under German police command (specifically, under German [[Sicherheitsdienst]] and [[SS]] command of the [[General Government]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Institute of Ukrainian History, Academy of Sciences of Ukraine, [http://history.org.ua/oun_upa/Upa/16.pdf ''Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists and the Ukrainian Insurgent Army''], Chapter 5, pp. 284 . Accessed 3 September 2009. [http://www.webcitation.org/5jY7j5Ua1 Archived] 4 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The Polish Institute of National Remembrance stated &quot;According to the witness' testimonies, and in the light of the collected documentation , there is no doubt that the 4th battalion 'Galizien' of the 14th division of SS committed the crime&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://ipn.gov.pl/en/commission/selected-investigations/investigation-into-the-crime-committed-at-the-village-of-hut&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pidkamin and Palikrowy===
''For more information about the subject, see: [[Pidkamin massacre]]''

The village of [[Pidkamin]] had a monastery where Poles sought shelter from the encroaching front. Around 2,000 people, the majority of whom were women and children, were seeking refuge there when the monastery was attacked on 11 March 1944, by the [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army]] (unit under [[Maksym Skorupsky]] command), allegedly cooperating with an SS-Galizien unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;motyka&quot; /&gt; The next day, 12 March the monastery was captured and civilians were murdered (at night part of the population managed to escape). Other civilians were also killed in the town of Pidkamin from 12 to 16 March.&lt;ref name=&quot;motyka&quot; /&gt;

Estimates of victims include 150 by Polish historian [[Grzegorz Motyka]],&lt;ref name=&quot;motyka&quot;&gt;[[Grzegorz Motyka]], Ukraińska Partyzantka 1942–1960, Warszawa 2006, p. str. 181, 385&lt;/ref&gt; and 250 according to the researchers of the Institute of History of the Ukrainian Academy of Sciences.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt;

''For more information about the subject, see: [[Palikrowy massacre]]''

Allegedly another sub-unit also participated in the execution of Polish civilians in [[Palykorovy]] located in [[Lviv oblast]] near [[Pidkamin]] (former [[Tarnopol Voivodeship]]). It is estimated that 365 ethnic Poles were murdered including women and children.&lt;ref name=&quot;motyka&quot; /&gt;

===The Deschênes Commission===
The Canadian &quot;[[Deschênes Commission|Commission of Inquiry on War Crimes]]&quot; of October 1986, by the Honourable Justice [[Jules Deschênes]] concluded that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Galicia Division (14. Waffen grenadier division der SS [gal. #1]) should not be indicted as a group. The members of Galicia Division were individually screened for security purposes before admission to Canada. Charges of war crimes of Galicia Division have never been substantiated, either in 1950 when they were first preferred, or in 1984 when they were renewed, or before this Commission. Further, in the absence of evidence of participation or knowledge of specific war crimes, mere membership in the Galicia Division is insufficient to justify prosecution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=galiciadivision |url=http://www.infoukes.com/galiciadivision/deschenes |author=Gerald William Kokodyniak &lt;!-- BOT GENERATED AUTHOR --&gt; |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5jXYjE15l?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.infoukes.com%2Fgaliciadivision%2Fdeschenes |archivedate=4 September 2009 |deadurl=no |accessdate=3 September 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Michael Karkoc==

In June 2013, the Associated Press (AP)  published an article claiming that an American, [[Michael Karkoc]], who was allegedly a former &quot;deputy company commander&quot; in the Division, was implicated in war crimes committed before he joined the Division in 1945.   According to AP,  Karkoc had previously served as a &quot;lieutenant&quot; of the 2nd Company of the [[SS and Police Leader|German SS Police-led]] Ukrainian Self Defense Legion (USDL).&lt;ref&gt;Rising, David, R. Herschaft and M. Scislowska.  News article: AP IMPACT: Commander in SS-led unit living in US.  http://apnews.myway.com/article/20130614/DA6TETCO2.html&lt;/ref&gt;  The USDL was a paramilitary police organization in the [[Schutzmannschaft]].  Karkoc was found living in [[Lauderdale, Minnesota]]. [[Michael Karkoc]], arrived in the United States in 1949 and became a naturalized citizen in 1959.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Photos: Former Nazi SS commander Michael Karkoc &amp;#124; Minnesota in Photos &amp;#124; Minnesota Public Radio News &lt;!-- BOT GENERATED TITLE --&gt; |author=Minnesota Public Radio &lt;!-- BOT GENERATED AUTHOR --&gt; |url=http://minnesota.publicradio.org/display/web/2013/06/14/news/photos/karkoc-nazi-minneapolis |work= |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6HU0fPIQW?url=http%3A%2F%2Fminnesota.publicradio.org%2Fdisplay%2Fweb%2F2013%2F06%2F14%2Fnews%2Fphotos%2Fkarkoc-nazi-minneapolis |archivedate=18 June 2013 |deadurl=no |accessdate=2013-06-16 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://apnews.myway.com/article/20130614/DA6TETCO2.html SS Commander in Minnesota- AP News&lt;/ref&gt;

==Division's names==
The division during its short history changed its name a number of times, being known as:
* '''SS Schuetzen Division &quot;Galizien&quot;''' or '''Galizien Division''' – from 30 July 1943 to August 1943 (during recruitment)
* '''SS Freiwilligen Division &quot;Galizien&quot;''' – from August 1943 to 27 July 1944 (during training)
* '''14. Waffen-Grenadier-Division der SS (Galizische Nr.1)''' – from August 1944 to the Winter of 1944
* '''14. Waffen-Grenadier-Division der SS (ukrainische Nr.1)'''- from the Winter of 1944 to Spring 1945
* '''1st Ukrainian Division of the [[Ukrainian National Army]]''' – from Spring 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toronto p. 17&quot; /&gt;

===Formation===
*Waffen [[Grenadier]] Regiment der SS 29
*Waffen-Grenadier Regiment der SS 30
*Waffen-Grenadier Regiment der SS 31
*Waffen-Artillery Regiment der SS 14
*SS-Waffen-Füsilier-Battalion 14
*SS-Waffen-[[Panzerjäger]] Company 14
*SS-Volunteer[[Flak]] Battalion 14
*Waffen Signals Battalion der SS 14
*SS-Radfahr-Battalion 14
*Waffen-Pionier-Battalion der SS 14
*SS-Versorgungs-Company 14
*SS-Division-Signals Troop 14
*SS Medical Battalion 14
*SS-Veterinary Company 14
*SS-Field post department 14
*SS-War Reporter platoon 14|
*SS [[Feldgendarmerie]] troop 14&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Wendal, Marcus |accessdate=22 March 2009 |publisher=Axis History |title=14. Waffen-Grenadier-Division der SS (ukrainische Nr. 1) |url=http://www.axishistory.com/index.php?id=1959 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5gQrFH4OY?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.axishistory.com%2Findex.php%3Fid%3D1959 |archivedate=30 April 2009 |deadurl=yes |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
[[File:SS-Galizien-Banner.jpg|thumb|250px|Fans of the [[FC Karpaty Lviv]] football club honoring the Waffen-SS Galizien division, [[Lviv]], [[Ukraine]], 2013]]
The 14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Galician) is today honored by many Ukrainian nationalists.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.timesofisrael.com/ukraine-divided-over-legacy-of-nazi-fighters/&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2010 every year on April 28 a march is held to celebrate the foundation of the division.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kyivpost.com/multimedia/photo/ss-volunteer-division-galician-323866.html&lt;/ref&gt; In addition streets were named after the division in [[Ivano-Frankivsk]] (Ukrains`koi Dyvizii Street) and [[Ternopil]] (Soldiers Division &quot;Galicia&quot; Street).&lt;ref&gt;https://www.google.de/maps/place/Soldiers+Division+%22Galicia%22+St,+Ternopil,+Ternopil's'ka+oblast,+Ukraine/@49.55566,25.5989384,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x4730314c51342683:0xc14cb32293088585&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[:Category:Members of the Galizien division]]
* [[List of German divisions in World War II]]
* [[Waffen-SS foreign volunteers and conscripts]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em|group=nb}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
*{{pl icon}} Jurij Kyryczuk, &quot;{{Lang|pl|Problem ukraińskiej kolaboracji w czasie II wojny światowej}}&quot; in &quot;Polska-Ukraina&quot; vol 6., Karta, Warszawa 2002, ISBN 83-915111-5-4, pp.&amp;nbsp;244–266
*Caballero Jurado, Carlos. Breaking the Chains: 14 Waffen-Grenadier-Division der SS and Other Ukrainian Volunteer Formations, Eastern Front, 1941–45. Halifax, West Yorkshire: Shelf Books, 1998 ISBN 1-899765-02-6
*{{Cite book| author=Davies, W.J.K. | title=German Army Handbook 1939–1945 | edition=Second U.S. | location=New York | publisher=Arco Publishing | year=1981 | isbn=0-668-04291-5}}
*{{Cite book| author=Heike, Wolf-Dietrich| title=The Ukrainian Division 'Galicia', 1943–45, A Memoir | publisher=Shevchenko Scientific Society | year= 1988| isbn=0-9690239-4-4}}
*{{cite journal |first=Olesya |last=Khromeychuk |title=The Shaping of ‘Historical Truth’: Construction and Reconstruction of the Memory and Narrative of the Waffen SS ‘Galicia’ Division |journal=Canadian Slavonic Papers |volume=54 |issue=3–4 |year=2012 |pages=443–467|doi=|issn=0008-5006 }}
*{{Cite book| author=Logusz, Michael O.| title=Galicia Division: The Waffen-SS 14th Grenadier Division 1943–1945| publisher=Schiffer Publishing | year=1997| isbn=0-7643-0081-4}}
*{{Cite book|last=Mitchum|first=Samuel W|year=2007|publisher=Stackpole books|title=German Order of Battle: Panzer, Panzer Grenadier, and Waffen SS divisions in World War II|isbn=0-8117-3438-2}}
*{{Cite book| author=Melnyk, Michael James| title= To Battle, The History and Formation of the 14th Waffen SS Grenadier Division | publisher= Helion and Co | year=2002 | edition= second updated edition 2007 | isbn=978-1-874622-19-2}}
*Melnyk, Michael James, The History of the Galician Division of the Waffen SS: On the Eastern Front: April 1943 to July 1944, Fonthill Media, 2016, ISBN 978-1781555286
*Melnyk, Michael James, The History of the Galician Division of the Waffen SS: Stalin's Nemesis, Fonthill Media, 2016.  ISBN 978-1781555385
*{{Cite book| author=Munoz, Antonio J. | title= Forgotten Legions: Obscure Combat Formations of the Waffen-SS| publisher=Axis Europa | year= 1991| isbn=0-7394-0817-8}}
*{{Cite book|title=Poland's holocaust: ethnic strife, collaboration with occupying forces and genocide in the Second Republic, 1918–1947|first=Tadeusz|last=Piotrowski|publisher=McFarland|year=1998|isbn=0-7864-0371-3}}
* [[Per Anders Rudling]], ''They Defended Ukraine’: The 14. Waffen-Grenadier-Division der SS (Galizische Nr. 1) Revisited'', The Journal of Slavic Military Studies, 25:3, 329–368 [http://lu.academia.edu/PerAndersRudling/Papers/1912325/_They_Defended_Ukraine_The_14._Waffen-Grenadier-Division_der_SS_Galizische_Nr._1_Revisited_The_Journal_of_Slavic_Military_Studies_25_3_2012_329-368 online version]
*{{Cite book| author= Quarrie, Bruce | title=Hitler's Samurai: The Waffen-SS in Action | publisher=Arco Pub. 161 pp. | year=1983 | isbn=0-668-05805-6}}
*{{Cite book| author=Williamson, Gordon | title=Loyalty is my Honor | publisher=Motorbooks International. 192 pp. | year= 1995| isbn=0-7603-0012-7}}

==External links==
* [http://www.lonesentry.com/manuals/tme30/ch3sec1sub6.html Waffen-SS from TM-E 30-451 Handbook on German Military Forces] (U.S. World War II manual, March 1945)

{{SS Divisions}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}

{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Military of Germany
| portal2=World War II
| commons=y
| commons-search=Category:14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Ukrainian)
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Ukrainian)}}
[[Category:Military history of Ukraine during World War II]]
[[Category:Ukrainian collaborators with Nazi Germany| ]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1943]]
[[Category:Foreign volunteer units of the Waffen-SS]]
[[Category:Infantry divisions of the Waffen-SS]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1945]]</text>
      <sha1>bfm8tlcdjh159vjljkibv5zkvvsq18w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
