<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Abu al-Misk Kafur</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2197831</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751077356</id>
      <parentid>751076950</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T06:38:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Al Ameer son</username>
        <id>3932527</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Patronage of the arts */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8424">'''Abu al-Misk Kafur''' (905&amp;ndash;968), also called '''al-Laithi''', '''al-Suri''', '''al-Labi''' was a dominant personality of [[Ikhshidid]] [[History of Muslim Egypt|Egypt]] and [[Bilad al-Sham|Syria]].&lt;ref name = EJBrill&gt;&quot;Kāfūr , Abu'l Misk al-Ikhsidi.&quot; ''E.J. Brill's first encyclopaedia of Islam 1913-1936''. Edited by: M. Th. Houtsma, E. van Donzel. Brill, 1993. p. 623&lt;/ref&gt; Originally a black slave from [[Ethiopia]], he was promoted as [[vizier]] of Egypt, becoming its de facto ruler from 946. After the death of his master, [[Muhammad bin Tughj]], Kafur succeeded the latter to become the ''de jure'' ruler of the Ikshidid domains, Egypt and southern Syria (including [[Damascus]]),  until his death in 968.&lt;ref name = Britannica&gt;Abū al-Misk Kāfūr.&quot; Encyclopædia Britannica. 2008. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. Jul. 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
[[Muhammad ibn Tughj]], the founder of the [[Ikhshidid dynasty]] of Egypt, bought Abu al-Misk Kafur as a slave from Ethiopia in 923. He is recorded as having a dark complexion and being a [[Eunuch (court official)|eunuch]]. Recognizing the slave's intelligence and talent, Ibn Tughj freed him.&lt;ref name = Britannica/&gt; The story goes that Kafur was freed because he kept his eyes fastened upon his master, while others kept their eyes on the master's gifts. Thus, historian [[Philip Hitti]] notes, Kafur would be generously rewarded for such loyalty.&lt;ref name = Hitti/&gt;

Ibn Tughj appointed Kafur to be the supervisor of princely education for his two sons. The Egyptian ruler then promoted Kafur as a military officer. As a field commander Kafur conducted a military mission to Syria in 945. He was put in charge of some campaigns in the [[Hejaz]]. Kafur was involved in some diplomatic exchanges between the Ikhshidids and the caliph of Baghdad.&lt;ref name = EOI&gt;Ehrenkreutz, A.S. &quot;Kāfūr , Abu'l-Misk .&quot; Encyclopaedia of Islam. Edited by: P. Bearman , Th. Bianquis , C.E. Bosworth , E. van Donzel and W.P. Heinrichs. Brill, 2008. Brill Online.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kafur became the ''[[de facto]]'' ruler of Egypt in 946 (since Kafur was the guardian of bin Tughj's sons, he ruled in their stead upon the death of their father). He died in [[Cairo]] and was probably buried in [[Jerusalem]]. Though subsequent historians have portrayed him as a just and moderate ruler, he owes a great deal of his fame to the scathing satirical poems directed against him by [[al-Mutanabbi]], a famous medieval Arab poet.

==Status as former slave==
Kafur's status as former slave did not hinder him from rising to power under the Ikhshidids. In fact, his status helped him, as it had become customary for former slaves to enter the military organization and even reach high positions in it.&lt;ref&gt;Kashif, S.I. ''Misr fi Asr al-Ikhshidiyin'' 2 ed. (Cairo, 1970), p. 255&lt;/ref&gt; Kafur's rise to power, from being an African slave to the ruler of Egypt and parts of Syria, is one of the first examples in [[Islamic history]] of a sovereign with the lowliest of origins.&lt;ref name = Hitti/&gt; In Muslim states in general, Africans such as Kafur did not continue to be slaves. They were employed in various occupations and maintained a cohesive culture interacting with that of their hosts.&lt;ref&gt;Jacob F. Ade Ajayi. ''General History of Africa: Africa in the Nineteenth Century Until the 1880s''. University of California Press. p. 749&lt;/ref&gt;

==Policies==

===Domestic politics===
While Kafur held ''de facto'' control over Egypt, he operated behind the facade of Ikhshdid rulers. On his deathbed, Ibn Tughj had appointed Kafur as guardian over his two sons. In 946, Kafur helped Anūdjūr secure the succession to Ibn Tughj. And in 961, he helped ʿAlī ibn al-Ikhshīd, Anūdjūr's younger brother (and his late master Ibn Tughj's second), secure the Egyptian throne. Only in 966, following the death of ʿAlī, did Kāfūr publicly declare himself as the sole master of Egypt.&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt;

Kafur, despite tremendous pressure on him, maintained stability inside Egypt. From 947 to 948, he fought and put down the rebellion by Ghalbūn. In 954 he successfully averted an abortive coup d'état by Anūdjūr. He also survived the spread of subversive Ismāʿīlī propaganda against him. His ability to resolve internal political complications is considered as having significantly prolonged the lifespan of the Ikhshidids.&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt;

===Foreign politics===
One of Abu al-Misk Kafur's greatest achievements is his successful protection of the Ikhshidid establishment from the [[Hamdanids]] (in Syria), [[Fatimids]] (in northern Africa, to the west of Egypt), [[Qarmatians]] (in the Arabian peninsula), and the [[Nubians]] (from south of Egypt).&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt;

Very early on Kafur's master, Muhammad ibn Tughj, trusted him to handle the military campaigns of Syria and Hejaz (in the Arabian peninsula). His military and diplomatic measures secured Damascus for the Ikhshidids (from the Hamdanids) in 947.&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt; [[Sayf ad-Dawla]], governor of Aleppo, had tried to overrun Syria, but his efforts were frustrated by Kafur, and the former recognized the latter's lordship over parts of Syria.&lt;ref name = Hitti&gt;[[Philip Hitti|Hitti, Philip K]]. ''History of Syria Including Lebanon and Palestine''.
Gorgias Press LLC. p.562-3&lt;/ref&gt;

He was also able to delay the Fatimid expansion into Egypt, frustrating the efforts of the latter's agents. So long as Kafur was alive, the Ikhsidid establishment kept the Fatimids at bay; upon his death, the Fatimids took over.&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt;

===Economy===
Kafur generally maintained economic stability in Egypt, despite serious setbacks:&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt;
*a fire devastated the business section of [[Fustat]] in 954;
*a major earthquake rocked Egypt in 955;
*recurrence of food-price inflation (sometimes resulting in famine), and consequent civil disturbances, in 949, 952, 955, and 963-968.

Excepting the heavy government expenditure, Kafur's administration refrained from extortionate fiscal practices. His gold coinage displayed remarkable stability, though it did fluctuate. Kafur also enrolled the services of competent administrators, and merchants, (such as the famous [[Yaqub ibn Killis]]), contributing to his economic accomplishments.&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt;

==Patronage of the arts==

Abu al-Misk Kafur gained popularity by being the patron of scholars and writers. Perhaps the most celebrated patronage, according to A.S. Ehrenkreutz, is that of the great poet [[al-Mutanabbi]].&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt; In return al-Mutanabbi praised the former slave. However, after Kafur's failure to reward him with high office that he aspired, al-Mutanabbi ridiculed Kafur. Thus Kafur was immortalized in the poetry of al-Mutanabbi - the greatest poet of Kafur's time, according to [[Philip Hitti|historian Hitti]].&lt;ref name = Hitti/&gt;

As he was a pious man, Kafur was more comfortable with the [[ulema]] (Muslim scholarly establishment) than the poets. He surrounded himself with religious men, some of whom he showered with gifts. He constructed two mosques in Giza and on al-Muqattam and a hospital.&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt; Nevertheless, he still clung to superstitions, abandoning a home once, believing it to be under a ''[[jinn]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Daly, Carl F. ''The Cambridge History of Egypt''. 115-116&lt;/ref&gt;

Kafur also maintained a magnificent and luxurious court. This, however, at times of famine, accorded poorly with the general population.&lt;ref name = Britannica/&gt; In addition to the mosques and the hospital, Kafur had constructed a number of sumptuous palaces, and the ''Kāfūriyya'' gardens in his capital. No archaeological remains of his contributions have been found thus far.&lt;ref name = EOI/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Slavery in Islam]]
*[[List of rulers of Egypt]]
*[[History of Egypt]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Abu'l-Hasan Ali ibn Muhammad]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Ikhshidid]] governor of [[List of governors of Islamic Egypt|Egypt]], [[Bilad al-Sham|southern Syria]] and the [[Hejaz]]&lt;br&gt;(''de jure'' for the [[Abbasid Caliphate]])|years=January 966 – April 968}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Abu'l-Fawaris Ahmad ibn Ali]]}}
{{s-end}}
[[Category:Ikhshidid emirs]]
[[Category:Ethiopian slaves]]
[[Category:905 births]]
[[Category:968 deaths]]
[[Category:Eunuchs]]
[[Category:Viziers]]
[[Category:10th-century rulers in Asia]]
[[Category:10th-century rulers in Africa]]
[[Category:Ikhshidid officials]]
[[Category:Ikhshidid military leaders]]</text>
      <sha1>enwc2j1g2tmtb3bxuq6rswweermszh7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
