<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>American imperialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>215140</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751156753</id>
      <parentid>751156624</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T19:07:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Upstatelee18</username>
        <id>11769904</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="59042">{{POV check|date=August 2016}}
'''American [[imperialism]]''' is the economic, military and cultural philosophy that the [[United States]] effects and controls other countries. Such influence is often closely associated with [[expansionism|expansion]] into foreign territories. The concept of an American Empire was first popularized during the presidency of [[James K. Polk]] who led the United States into the [[Mexican–American War]] of 1846, and the eventual [[Conquest of California|annexation of California]] and other western territories via the [[Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo]] and the [[Gadsden purchase]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lens&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Lens|first1=Sidney|authorlink1=Sidney Lens|last2=Zinn|first2=Howard |title=The Forging of the American Empire|publisher=Pluto Press|location=London|year=2003|origyear=1971 |isbn=0-7453-2100-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qvLfIHqkOOAC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=American Imperialism: The Worst Chapter in Almost Any Book |last=Field |first=James A., Jr. |journal=The American Historical Review |volume=83 |issue=3 |date=June 1978 |pages=644–668 |doi=10.2307/1861842 |jstor=1861842}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Imperialism ==
{{Further information|Empire of Liberty|Modern empires|Overthrow of the Kingdom of Hawaii|History of the Philippines (1898–1946)|Philippine–American War}}
[[File:Puck cover2.jpg|upright|thumb|On the cover of ''[[Puck (magazine)|Puck]]'' published on April 6, 1901, in the wake of gainful victory in the [[Spanish–American War]], [[Columbia (name)|Columbia]]—the [[National personification]] of the U.S.—preens herself with an [[Easter bonnet]] in the form of a warship bearing the words &quot;World Power&quot; and the word &quot;Expansion&quot; on the smoke coming out of its stack.]]
[[File:Victor Gillam A Thing Well Begun Is Half Done 1899 Cornell CUL PJM 1136 01.jpg|upright=1|thumb|This cartoon reflects the America's imperial ambitions following a quick victory in the Spanish–American War of 1898. The American flag flies from the Philippines and Hawaii in the Pacific to Cuba and Puerto Rico in the Caribbean.]]
[[Thomas Jefferson]], in the 1790s, awaited the fall of the [[Spanish Empire]] &quot;until our population can be sufficiently advanced to gain it from them piece by piece.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Susan Welch|author2=John Gruhl|author3=Susan M. Rigdon|author4=Sue Thomas|title=Understanding American Government|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GT-8oHlIp1UC|year=2011|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=978-0-495-91050-3|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=GT–8oHlIp1UC&amp;pg=PA583 583], [https://books.google.com/books?id=GT–8oHlIp1UC&amp;pg=PA671 671] (note 3)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Walter LaFeber|title=Inevitable Revolutions: The United States in Central America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RqMp5TsWCqkC|year=1993|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=978-0-393-30964-5|page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In turn, historian [[Sidney Lens]] notes that &quot;the urge for expansion{{spaced ndash}}at the expense of other peoples{{spaced ndash}}goes back to the beginnings of the United States itself.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lens&quot; /&gt; Yale historian Paul Kennedy put it, &quot;From the time the first settlers arrived in [[Virginia]] from [[England]] and started moving westward, this was an imperial nation, a conquering nation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Trends 2002&quot;&gt;Emily Eakin &quot;Ideas and Trends: All Roads Lead To DC&quot; New York Times , March 31, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2008 address to [[Boston University]], [[Noam Chomsky]] stated that &quot;talking about American imperialism is rather like talking about triangular triangles.&quot; Detailing George Washington's description of the early United States as an &quot;infant empire&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/i9118.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Benjamin Franklin's writing that &quot;the Prince that acquires new Territory ... removes the Natives to give his own People Room... may be properly called [Father] of [his] Nation,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.columbia.edu/~lmg21/ash3002y/earlyac99/documents/observations.html&lt;/ref&gt; and Thomas Jefferson's statement that the United States &quot;must be viewed as the nest from which all America, North &amp; South is to be peopled,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://jeffersonswest.unl.edu/archive/view_doc.php?id=jef.00071&lt;/ref&gt; Chomsky stated, &quot;the United States is the one country that exists, as far as I know, and ever has, that was founded as an empire explicitly.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;https://chomsky.info/20080424/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7PdJ9TAdTdA&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Benevolent Assimilation (book)|Stuart Creighton Miller]] says that the public's sense of innocence about [[Realpolitik]] impairs popular recognition of U.S. imperial conduct. The resistance to actively occupying foreign territory has led to policies of exerting influence via other means, including governing other countries via surrogates or [[puppet regime]]s, where domestically unpopular governments survive only through U.S. support.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Chalmers, ''Blowback: The Costs and Consequences of American Empire'' (2000), pp.72–9&lt;/ref&gt;

The maximum geographical extension of American direct political and military control happened in the [[aftermath of World War II]], in the period after the surrender and occupations of [[Allied-occupied Germany|Germany]] and [[Allied-occupied Austria|Austria]] in May and later [[Occupation of Japan|Japan]] and [[United States Army Military Government in Korea|Korea]] in [[Japanese Instrument of Surrender|September 1945]] and before the independence of the [[Philippines]] in [[Treaty of Manila (1946)|July 1946]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gov.ph/republic-day/|title=Philippine Republic Day|work=www.gov.ph}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== American exceptionalism ==
{{Main article|American exceptionalism}}
[[American exceptionalism]] is the theory that the United States occupies a special niche among the nations of the world&lt;ref name=&quot;sagehistory.net&quot;&gt;Frederick Jackson Turner, {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080521064528/http://www.sagehistory.net/gildedage/documents/TurnerFT.html |date=May 21, 2008 |title=Significance of the Frontier }}, sagehistory.net (archived from [http://www.sagehistory.net/gildedage/documents/TurnerFT.html the original] on May 21, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt; in terms of its national [[credo]], historical evolution, and political and religious institutions and origins.

Philosopher [[Douglas Kellner]] traces the identification of American exceptionalism as a distinct phenomenon back to 19th century French observer [[Alexis de Tocqueville]], who concluded by agreeing that the U.S., uniquely, was &quot;proceeding along a path to which no limit can be perceived.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Kellner, Douglas | url=http://www.gseis.ucla.edu/courses/ed253a/american-exceptionalism.htm | title=American Exceptionalism | date=April 25, 2003 | accessdate=February 20, 2006 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060217113947/http://www.gseis.ucla.edu/courses/ed253a/american-exceptionalism.htm |archivedate = February 17, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American exceptionalism is popular among people within the U.S.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | first = Frederick | last = Edwords |date=November–December 1987 | title = The religious character of American patriotism. It's time to recognize our traditions and answer some hard questions. | journal=The Humanist | issue = p. 20-24, 36}}&lt;/ref&gt; but its validity and its consequences are disputed. Some American citizens will participate in [[exceptionalism]] without even being aware of it. Such instances occur when American interests and advancements are justified solely on the basis of its economic standing or the protection of human rights. The American public's attitude towards intervention in [[Cuba]] and the [[Philippines]] was one of enthusiasm.{{citation needed|reason=looks like editorializing/opinion|date=February 2016}}

As a ''[[Monthly Review]]'' editorial opines on the phenomenon, &quot;in Britain, empire was justified as a benevolent [[The White Man's Burden|'white man's burden']]. And in the United States, empire does not even exist; 'we' are merely protecting the causes of freedom, democracy and justice worldwide.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| first =Harry| last =Magdoff|author2=John Bellamy Foster|date=November 2001 | title =After the Attack...The War on Terrorism| journal=[[Monthly Review]]| volume =53| issue =6| page =7| id =| url =http://www.monthlyreview.org/1101edit.htm| accessdate =October 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== World War I ==
[[File:American troops in Vladivostok 1918 HD-SN-99-02013.JPEG|thumb|American troops in Vladivostok during the [[Allied intervention in the Russian Civil War]], August 1918]]
When [[World War I]] broke out in Europe, President [[Woodrow Wilson]] promised American neutrality throughout the war. This promise was broken when the United States entered the war after the [[Zimmermann Telegram]]. The war for the United States was &quot;a war for empire&quot; according to the historian [[W. E. B. Du Bois]], as historian [[Howard Zinn]] explains in his book, ''A Peoples Republic'' .&lt;ref&gt;Zinn, Howard. ''A People's History of the United States''. New York: HarperCollins, 2003. p. 363&lt;/ref&gt; Zinn argues that the United States entered the war in order to create an international market that could be beneficial to the United States through conquest.&lt;ref&gt;Zinn, pp. 359–376&lt;/ref&gt;

During the First World War, some of the American Imperialism at the time can be viewed as imperialism to stop the spread of [[democracy]] to certain countries, such as [[Haiti]]. According to the noted writer and progressive [[Randolph Bourne]], the United States did not enter the war with intentions to make the world a better place or else they would have required a principle of international order. Bourne criticizes intellectuals who gave support for the war without knowing the true intentions of the United States government. Even though Bourne believes that the United States entered the war imperialistically, he states that many intellectuals believed at the time that the United States intervened in the war to promote democracy. Bourne believes that by leading the public into the war, with many intellectuals unsure of the actual reasons for the war, the country led an apathetic nation into what he considers an irresponsible war.&lt;ref&gt;Bourne, &quot;The War and the Intellectuals,&quot; ''The Seven Arts'', pp. 133–146&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States invaded [[Haiti]] in July 1915 after having made landfall eight times previously. American rule in Haiti continued through 1942, but was initiated during World War I. The historian Mary Renda in her book, ''Taking Haiti'', talks about the American invasion of Haiti to bring about political stability through U.S. control. The American government did not believe Haiti was ready for self-governing or democracy, according to Renda. In order to bring about political stability in Haiti, without allowing for self-governance, the United States secured control and integrated the country into the international capitalist economy, while preventing Haiti from securing their own democracy. In order to convince the American public of the uncivilized nature of Haiti, the United States government used [[paternalism]] to make it seem to the American government that the Haitian political process was uncivilized. While Haiti had been running their own government for many years before American intervention, the United States felt as though Haiti was unfit for self-rule, even though it may not have been true at all. Americans saw the Haitians as children in need of guidance due to the corrupt thoughts of the U.S. officials who rationalized American imperialism in Haiti. Through their imperialistic control, the United States made the Haitian government agree to terms laid out by the U.S. government as well as directly supervising the Haitian economy. This direct supervision of the Haitian economy stressed the uncivilized nature of the Haitian political process by the American government to the U.S. citizens and prevented the spread of democracy to Haiti where they were unable to form their own government under U.S. imperialistic control.&lt;ref&gt;Renda, &quot;Introduction,&quot; in ''Taking Haiti: Military Occupation &amp; the Culture of U.S. Imperialism'', 1915–1940, pp. 10–22, 29–34&lt;/ref&gt;

In February, [[Russia]] went through the first revolution of 1917, which removed [[Nicholas II of Russia|Czar Nicholas II]] from power. The United States, including President Wilson, praised this revolution and felt that it was a step towards post-war world order. Not long after in October 1917, the [[Bolshevik]]s overthrew the new Russian 'unity' government in the second revolution. The United States government was stunned with the second revolution and was against the Bolshevik proposed armistice with the Central Powers. In order to keep the Bolsheviks from gaining allied supplies in Russia, Wilson agreed to an intervention in Russia. The United States and the allies entered into a war with the [[Soviet Union|Soviets]], with the first U.S. troops landing in Russia in September 1918. After the defeat of the Germans, the [[Russian Civil War|war in Russia]] continued, with the United States and the allies opposing the Bolsheviks. This intervention in Russia was imperialistic by its nature opposing the Soviet government in favor of a government that would align with the allied and American views. In their attempt to overthrow the Bolshevik government, the United States showed an imperialistic attitude towards a nation that was still aligned with the allies officially.&lt;ref&gt;Powaski, &quot;The United States and the Bolshevik Revolution, 1917–1933,&quot; in ''The Cold War:. The United States and the Soviet Union, 1917–1991'', pp. 5–34&lt;/ref&gt;

== Views of American imperialism ==
[[File:School Begins (Puck Magazine 1-25-1899).jpg|290px|thumb|Caricature showing [[Uncle Sam]] lecturing four children labelled Philippines, Hawaii, [[Puerto Rico]] and Cuba, in front of children holding books labelled with various U.S. states. The caption reads: &quot;School Begins. Uncle Sam (to his new class in Civilization): Now, children, you've got to learn these lessons whether you want to or not! But just take a look at the class ahead of you, and remember that, in a little while, you will feel as glad to be here as they are!&quot;]] Journalist Ashley Smith divides theories of the U.S. imperialism into 5 broad categories: (1) &quot;liberal&quot; theories, (2) &quot;social-democratic&quot; theories, (3) &quot;Leninist&quot; theories, (4) theories of &quot;[[super-imperialism]]&quot;, and (5) &quot;Hardt-and-Negri-ite&quot; theories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite conference | first = Ashley | last = Smith | title = The Classical Marxist Theory of Imperialism | conference = Socialism 2006 | date = June 24, 2006 | location = [[Columbia University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=February 2011|reason=Where does this author make these claims? Page what? And why is ''this'' used as the orgainsation of the article?}} There is also a conservative, anti-interventionist view as expressed by American journalist [[John T. Flynn]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The enemy aggressor is always pursuing a course of larceny, murder, rapine and barbarism. We are always moving forward with high mission, a destiny imposed by the [[Deity]] to regenerate our victims, while incidentally capturing their markets; to civilise savage and senile and paranoid peoples, while blundering accidentally into their oil wells.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.mises.org/books/aswegomarching.pdf|title=Books|work=Mises Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A &quot;[[social-democratic]]&quot; theory says that imperialistic U.S. policies are the products of the excessive influence of certain sectors of U.S. business and government—the [[arms industry]] in alliance with military and political bureaucracies and sometimes other industries such as oil and finance, a combination often referred to as the &quot;[[military–industrial complex]]&quot;. The complex is said to benefit from [[war profiteering]] and the looting of [[natural resource]]s, often at the expense of the public interest.&lt;ref&gt;[[C. Wright Mills]], ''The Causes of World War Three'', Simon and Schuster, 1958, pp. 52, 111&lt;/ref&gt; The proposed solution is typically unceasing popular vigilance in order to apply counter-pressure.&lt;ref&gt;Flynn, John T. (1944) ''As We Go Marching.''&lt;/ref&gt; Johnson holds a version of this view.

Alfred T. Mahan, who served as an officer in the [[U.S. Navy]] during the late 19th century, supported the notion of American imperialism in his 1890 book titled ''[[The Influence of Sea Power upon History]]''. In chapter one Mahan argued that modern industrial nations must secure foreign markets for the purpose of exchanging goods and, consequently, they must maintain a maritime force that is capable of protecting these trade routes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Alfred Thayer Mahan|title=The Influence of Sea Power upon History, 1660–1783|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nc7H1eQiArQC|year=1987|publisher=Courier Dover Publications|isbn=978-0-486-25509-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=February 2011|reason=inline citation policy requires exact pages this information comes from; article has extensive [[WP:OR]]; unsourced claims to be removed}}

A theory of &quot;super-imperialism&quot; argues that imperialistic U.S. policies are not driven solely by the interests of American businesses, but also by the interests of a larger apparatus of a global alliance among the economic elite in developed countries. The argument asserts that [[capitalism]] in the [[North–South divide|Global North]] (Europe, the U.S., Japan, among others) has become too entangled to permit military or geopolitical conflict between these countries, and the central conflict in modern imperialism is between the Global North (also referred to as the [[core countries|global core]]) and the Global South (also referred to as the [[Third World|global periphery]]) rather than between the imperialist powers.

=== Empire ===
[[File:Mexico nebel.jpg|thumb|290px|[[Mexican–American War|American occupation of Mexico City]] in 1847]]
[[File:Raising of American flag at Iolani Palace with US Marines in the foreground (detailed).jpg|thumb|Ceremonies during the [[Overthrow of the Kingdom of Hawaii#Annexation|annexation of the Republic of Hawaii]], 1898]]
Following the [[Invasions of Afghanistan#Invasion by the United States and allies|invasion of Afghanistan in 2001]], the idea of American imperialism was reexamined. In November 2001, jubilant marines hoisted an American flag over Kandahar and in a stage display referred to the moment as the third after those on [[Battle of San Juan Hill|San Juan Hill]] and [[Battle of Iwo Jima|Iwo Jima]]. All moments, writes [[Neil Smith (geographer)|Neil Smith]], express US global ambition. “Labelled a war on terrorism, the new war represents an unprecedented quickening of the American Empire, a third chance at global power.”&lt;ref&gt;Neil Smith, ''American Empire: Roosevelt's Geographer and the Prelude to Globalization'', (Berkeley &amp; Los Angeles &amp; London: University of California Press, 2003), p XI-XII.&lt;/ref&gt; 

On October 15, the cover of [[William Kristol]]'s [[Weekly Standard]] carried the headline, &quot;The Case for American Empire.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Max Boot]], &quot;The Case for American Empire,&quot; ''Weekly Standard'' 7/5, (October 15, 2001), http://ontology.buffalo.edu/smith/courses01/rrtw/boot.htm&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rich Lowry]], editor in chief of the [[National Review]], called for &quot;a kind of low-grade [[colonialism]]&quot; to topple dangerous regimes beyond Afghanistan.&lt;ref&gt;Nina J. Easton, &quot;Thunder on the Right,&quot; American Journalism Review 23 (December 2001), 320.&lt;/ref&gt; The columnist [[Charles Krauthammer]] declared that, given complete U.S. domination &quot;culturally, economically, technologically and militarily,&quot; people were &quot;now coming out of the closet on the word 'empire.'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Trends 2002&quot; /&gt; The [[New York Times]] Sunday magazine cover for January 5, 2003, read &quot;American Empire: Get Used To It.&quot; The phrase &quot;American empire&quot; appeared more than 1000 times in news stories during November 2002 – April 2003.&lt;ref&gt;David A. Lake, &quot;Escape from the State-of-Nature: Authority and Hierarchy in World Politics,&quot; ''International Security'', 32/1: (2007), p 48.&lt;/ref&gt; Two Harvard Historians observed:
{{quote|
Since September 11, 2001 … if not earlier, the idea of American empire is back... Now … for the first time since the early Twentieth century, it has become acceptable to ask whether the United States has become or is becoming an empire in some classic sense.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Charles S. Maier]], ''Among Empires: American Ascendancy and Its Predecessors'', (Massachusetts &amp; London: Harvard University Press, 2006), p 2-24.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{quote|
It used to be that only the critics of American foreign policy referred to the American empire… In the past three or four years [2001-2004], however, a growing number of commentators have begun to use the term American empire less pejoratively, if still ambivalently, and in some cases with genuine enthusiasm.&lt;ref&gt;[[Niall Ferguson]], ''Colossus: The Rise and Fall of the American Empire'', (New York: Penguin Books, 2005), p 3-4.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
In the book &quot;[[Empire (Negri and Hardt book)|Empire]]&quot;, [[Michael Hardt]] and [[Antonio Negri]] argue that &quot;the decline of Empire has begun&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/Archive/Article/0,4273,4221990,00.html Empire hits back]. [[The Observer]], July 15, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Hardt says the [[Iraq War]] is a classically imperialist war, and is the last gasp of a doomed strategy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | first=Michael | last=Hardt | date=July 13, 2006 | title=From Imperialism to Empire | journal=[[The Nation]] | url=http://www.thenation.com/article/imperialism-empire }}&lt;/ref&gt; They expand on this, claiming that in the new era of imperialism, the classical imperialists retain a colonizing power of sorts, but the strategy shifts from military occupation of economies based on physical goods to a networked [[biopower]] based on an informational and [[affect (philosophy)|affective]] economies. They go on to say that the U.S. is central to the development of this new regime of [[Power in international relations|international power]] and [[sovereignty]], termed &quot;Empire&quot;, but that it is decentralized and global, and not ruled by one sovereign state: &quot;the United States does indeed occupy a privileged position in Empire, but this privilege derives not from its similarities to the old European imperialist powers, but from its differences.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Negri, Antonio |author2=Hardt, Michael | year=2000 | title=Empire | publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] | url=http://www.angelfire.com/cantina/negri/ |isbn=0-674-00671-2 |accessdate=October 8, 2009}} p. xiii–xiv.&lt;/ref&gt;  Hardt and Negri draw on the theories of [[Spinoza]], [[Michel Foucault|Foucault]], [[Deleuze]] and Italian [[autonomist marxism|autonomist Marxists]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Hardt, ''[[Gilles Deleuze]]: an Apprenticeship in Philosophy'', ISBN 0-8166-2161-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Autonomism#Italian autonomism]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Geographer [[David Harvey (geographer)|David Harvey]] says there has emerged a new type of imperialism due to geographical distinctions as well as unequal rates of development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harvey|first=David|title=The new imperialism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=N3VZWhA-OhoC|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-927808-4|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=N3VZWhA–OhoC&amp;pg=PA101 101]|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; He says there has emerged three new global economic and political blocs: the United States, the [[European Union]] and Asia centered on [[China]] and [[Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Harvey|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=N3VZWhA-OhoC&amp;pg=PA31 31]}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{VN|date=February 2013|reason=The edit at http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=American_imperialism&amp;curid=215140&amp;diff=539849336&amp;oldid=539669263 changed &quot;East Asia centered around China and Japan&quot; to &quot;Asia centered around China and Russia&quot; with no explanatory edit summary. The cited supporting source is not previewable online.}} He says there are tensions between the three major blocs over resources and economic power, citing the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]], the motive of which, he argues, was to prevent rival blocs from controlling oil.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Harvey|2005|pp=[https://books.google.com/books?id=N3VZWhA-OhoC&amp;pg=PA77 77–78]}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Harvey argues that there can arise conflict within the major blocs between business interests and the politicians due to their sometimes incongruent economic interests.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Harvey|2005|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=N3VZWhA-OhoC&amp;pg=PA187 187]}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Politicians live in geographically fixed locations and are, in the U.S. and Europe{{VN|date=September 2016|reason=can't see the book so I'm not sure he said this. This is a very 'imperialist' view (only U.S. and Europe democratic) which would appear to be a departure from the rest of his analysis}}, accountable to an electorate. The 'new' imperialism, then, has led to an alignment of the interests of capitalists and politicians in order to prevent the rise and expansion of possible economic and political rivals from challenging America's dominance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Harvey|2005|pp=[https://books.google.com/books?id=N3VZWhA-OhoC&amp;pg=PA76 76–78]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Classics professor and war historian [[Victor Davis Hanson]] dismisses the notion of an American Empire altogether, with a mocking comparison to historical empires: &quot;We do not send out proconsuls to reside over client states, which in turn impose taxes on coerced subjects to pay for the legions. Instead, American bases are predicated on contractual obligations — costly to us and profitable to their hosts. We do not see any profits in Korea, but instead accept the risk of losing almost 40,000 of our youth to ensure that Kias can flood our shores and that shaggy students can protest outside our embassy in Seoul.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.victorhanson.com/articles/hanson112702.html|title=http://www.victorhanson.com/articles/hanson112702.html|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Factors unique to the &quot;Age of imperialism&quot; ==
A variety of factors may have coincided during the &quot;[[Age of Imperialism]]&quot; in the late 19th century, when the United States and the other major powers rapidly expanded their territorial possessions. Some of these are explained, or used as examples for the various perceived forms of American imperialism.

*The prevalence of racism, notably [[John Fiske (philosopher)|John Fiske]]'s conception of [[British people|Anglo-Saxon]] racial superiority, and [[Josiah Strong]]'s call to &quot;civilize and Christianize&quot;—all manifestations of a growing [[Social Darwinism]] and racism in some schools of American political thought.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Friedman, &quot;The Lexus and the Olive Tree&quot;, p. 381, and Manfred Steger, &quot;Globalism: The New Market Ideology,&quot; and Jeff Faux, &quot;Flat Note from the Pied Piper of Globalization,&quot; Dissent, Fall 2005, pp. 64–67.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Early in his career, as Assistant Secretary of the Navy, [[Theodore Roosevelt]] was instrumental in preparing the Navy for the [[Spanish–American War]]&lt;ref&gt;[[H. W. Brands|Brands, Henry William]]. (1997). ''T.R.: The Last Romantic.'' New York: Basic Books. Reprinted 2001, full biography [http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/36954615?referer=di&amp;ht=edition OCLC 36954615], ch 12&lt;/ref&gt; and was an enthusiastic proponent of testing the U.S. military in battle, at one point stating &quot;I should welcome almost any war, for I think this country needs one&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first= |url=http://www.pbs.org/crucible/tl7.html |title=April 16, 1897: T. Roosevelt Appointed Assistant Secretary of the Navy |work=Crucible of Empire—Timeline|publisher=PBS Online|accessdate=July 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first= |url=http://www.pbs.org/crucible/Transcript.txt |title=Transcript For &quot;Crucible Of Empire&quot; |work=Crucible of Empire—Timeline|publisher=PBS Online|accessdate=July 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tilchin, William N. Theodore Roosevelt and the [[British Empire]]: A Study in Presidential Statecraft (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

Industry and trade are two of the most prevalent factors unique to imperialism. American intervention in both Latin America and Hawaii resulted in multiple industrial investments, including the popular industry of [[Dole Food Company|Dole]] bananas. If the United States was able to annex a territory, in turn they were granted access to the trade and capital of those territories. In 1898, Senator Albert Beveridge proclaimed that an expansion of markets was absolutely necessary, &quot;American factories are making more than the American people can use; American soil is producing more than they can consume. Fate has written our policy for us; the trade of the world must and shall be ours.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Zinn, Howard. A People's History of the United States: 1492–2001. New York: HarperCollins, 2003. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

== U.S. foreign policy debate ==
{{further2|[[Military history of the United States]], [[Overseas interventions of the United States]]}}
{{Cleanup rewrite|2=section|date=January 2014}}
[[File:10kMiles.JPG|thumb|left|1898 [[political cartoon]]: &quot;Ten Thousand Miles From Tip to Tip&quot; meaning the extension of U.S. domination (symbolized by a [[bald eagle]]) from [[Puerto Rico]] to the [[Philippines]]. The cartoon contrasts this with a map of the smaller United States 100 years earlier in 1798.]]

[[Annexation]] is a crucial instrument in the expansion of a nation, due to the fact that once a territory is annexed it must act within the confines of its superior counterpart. The United States Congress' ability to annex a foreign territory is explained in a report from the Congressional Committee on Foreign Relations, &quot;If, in the judgment of Congress, such a measure is supported by a safe and wise policy, or is based upon a natural duty that we owe to the people of Hawaii, or is necessary for our national development and security, that is enough to justify annexation, with the consent of the recognized government of the country to be annexed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;United States. Cong. Senate. Committee on Foreign Relations. Annexation of Hawaii.  Comp. Davis. 55th Cong., 2nd sess. S. Rept. 681. Washington, D.C.: G.P.O., 1898. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to annexing a territory, the American government still held immense power through the various legislations passed in the late 1800s. The Platt Amendment was utilized to prevent Cuba from entering into any agreements with foreign nations, and also granted the Americans the right to build naval stations on their soil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pérez, Louis A 1998&quot;&gt;Pérez, Louis A. The War of 1898: The United States and Cuba in History and Historiography. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina, 1998. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Executive officials in the American government began to determine themselves the supreme authority in matters regarding the recognition or restriction of [[independence]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pérez, Louis A 1998&quot; /&gt;

When asked on April 28, 2003, on [[al-Jazeera]] whether the United States was &quot;empire building,&quot; Secretary of Defense [[Donald Rumsfeld]] replied &quot;We don't seek empires, we're not imperialistic. We never have been.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/opinion/editorials/2003-05-05-boot_x.htm|title=USATODAY.com – American imperialism? No need to run away from label|work=usatoday.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, historian [[Donald W. Meinig]] says the imperial behavior by the United States dates at least to the [[Louisiana Purchase]], which he describes as an &quot;imperial acquisition—imperial in the sense of the aggressive encroachment of one people upon the territory of another, resulting in the subjugation of that people to alien rule.&quot; The U.S. policies towards the [[Native Americans]] he said were &quot;designed to remold them into a people more appropriately conformed to imperial desires.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Meinig |first= Donald W. |authorlink= Donald W. Meinig|title= The Shaping of America: A Geographical Perspective on 500 Years of History, Volume 2: Continental America, 1800–1867 |year= 1993 |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn= 0-300-05658-3 |pages= 22–23, 170–196, 516–517}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Writers and academics of the early 20th century, like [[Charles A. Beard]], in support of [[non-interventionism]] (sometimes referred to as &quot;[[American isolationism|isolationism]]&quot;), discussed American policy as being driven by self-interested expansionism going back as far as the writing of the Constitution. Some politicians today do not agree. [[Pat Buchanan]] claims that the modern United States' drive to empire is &quot;far removed from what the Founding Fathers had intended the young Republic to become.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Buchanan, Pat |authorlink=Pat Buchanan| title=[[A Republic, Not an Empire: Reclaiming America's Destiny]]| publisher=Regnery Publishing|location=Washington, DC | year=1999 | isbn=0-89526-272-X}} p. [https://books.google.com/books?id=eJSJw6GT5VYC&amp;pg=PA165 165].&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Andrew Bacevich]] argues that the U.S. did not fundamentally change its [[Foreign policy of the United States|foreign policy]] after the [[Cold War]], and remains focused on an effort to expand its control across the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Bacevich, Andrew | title=American Empire: The Realities and Consequences of U.S. Diplomacy | publisher=Harvard University Press | year=2004 | isbn=0-674-01375-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the surviving superpower at the end of the Cold War, the U.S. could focus its assets in new directions, the future being &quot;up for grabs&quot; according to former Under Secretary of Defense for Policy [[Paul Wolfowitz]] in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;ERIC SCHMITT, &quot;Washington at Work; Ex-Cold Warrior Sees the Future as 'Up for Grabs'&quot; The New York Times December 23, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media]], the political activist [[Noam Chomsky]] argues that exceptionalism and the denials of imperialism are the result of a systematic strategy of propaganda, to &quot;manufacture opinion&quot; as the process has long been described in other countries.&lt;ref&gt;Edward Hallett Carr, The Twenty Years' Crisis 1919–1939: An Introduction to the Study of International Relations, 1939.&lt;/ref&gt;

Thorton wrote that &quot;[...]imperialism is more often the name of the emotion that reacts to a series of events than a definition of the events themselves. Where colonization finds analysts and analogies, imperialism must contend with crusaders for and against.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;thor&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Thornton, Archibald Paton| title= Imperialism in the Twentieth Century | publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |date=September 1978| isbn=0-333-24848-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Political theorist [[Michael Walzer]] argues that the term [[hegemony]] is better than empire to describe the US's role in the world;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| author=Walzer, Michael | title =Is There an American Empire?| work=www.freeindiamedia.com| url =http://www.freeindiamedia.com/america/5_jan_04_america2.htm| archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20061021013321/http://www.freeindiamedia.com/america/5_jan_04_america2.htm| archivedate =October 21, 2006| accessdate=June 10, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; political scientist [[Robert Keohane]] agrees saying, a &quot;balanced and nuanced analysis is not aided...by the use of the phrase 'empire' to describe United States hegemony, since 'empire' obscures rather than illuminates the differences in form of rule between the United States and other Great Powers, such as Great Britain in the 19th century or the [[Soviet Empire|Soviet Union]] in the twentieth.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Keohane|Keohane, Robert O.]] &quot;The United States and the Postwar Order: Empire or Hegemony?&quot; (Review of Geir Lundestad, ''The American Empire'') ''Journal of Peace Research'', Vol. 28, No. 4 (November , 1991), p. 435&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2001,&lt;ref&gt;Emmanuel Todd, ''After the Empire. The Breakdown of the American Order'', 2001, (tr. Delogu, C. Jon, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Emmanuel Todd]] assumes that USA cannot hold for long the status of mondial hegemonic power due to limited resources. Instead, USA is going to become just one of the major regional powers along with European Union, China, Russia, etc.
Other political scientists, such as Daniel Nexon and Thomas Wright, argue that neither term exclusively describes [[foreign relations of the United States]]. The U.S. can be, and has been, simultaneously an empire and a hegemonic power. They claim that the general trend in U.S. foreign relations has been away from imperial modes of control.&lt;ref&gt;Nexon, Daniel and Wright, Thomas [http://homepage.mac.com/mgemmill/Nexon_Wright_Empire.pdf &quot;What's at Stake in the American Empire Debate&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110917073455/http://homepage.mac.com/mgemmill/Nexon_Wright_Empire.pdf |date=September 17, 2011 }} ''American Political Science Review'', Vol. 101, No. 2 (May 2007), p. 266-267&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cultural imperialism ===
[[File:McDonalds in St Petersburg 2004.JPG|right|thumb|McDonald's in [[Saint Petersburg]], Russia]]
[[File:McDonald's restaurant in Ortaköy.jpg|left|thumb|McDonald's in [[Istanbul]], Turkey]]
Some critics of imperialism argue that military and [[cultural imperialism]] are interdependent. American [[Edward Said]], one of the founders of [[post-colonialism|post-colonial theory]], said that,

{{quote|[...], so influential has been the discourse insisting on American specialness, altruism and opportunity, that imperialism in the United States as a word or ideology has turned up only rarely and recently in accounts of the United States culture, politics and history. But the connection between imperial politics and culture in [[North America]], and in particular in the United States, is astonishingly direct.&lt;ref name=&quot;Said&quot;&gt;Said, Edward.{{cite web|url=http://www.zmag.org/zmag/articles/barsaid.htm |title=Culture and Imperialism, speech at York University, Toronto, February&amp;nbsp;10,&amp;nbsp;1993. |accessdate=2006-02-23 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071013004955/http://www.zmag.org/zmag/articles/barsaid.htm |archivedate=2007-10-13 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

International relations scholar David Rothkopf disagrees and argues that cultural imperialism is the innocent result of [[globalization]], which allows access to numerous U.S. and Western ideas and products that many non-U.S. and non-Western consumers across the world voluntarily choose to consume.&lt;ref&gt;Rothkopf, David [http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/protected/rothkopf.html In Praise of Cultural Imperialism?] Foreign Policy, Number 107, Summer 1997, pp. 38–53&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Matthew Fraser (journalist)|Matthew Fraser]] has a similar analysis, but argues further that the global cultural influence of the U.S. is a good thing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Fraser, Matthew | title=Weapons of Mass Distraction: [[Soft Power]] and American Empire | year=2005 | publisher=St. Martin's Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Nationalism]] is the main process through which the government is able to shape public opinion. [[Propaganda]] in the media is strategically placed in order to promote a common attitude among the people. Louis A. Perez Jr. provides an example of propaganda used during the war of 1898, &quot;We are coming, Cuba, coming; we are bound to set you free! We are coming from the mountains, from the plains and inland sea! We are coming with the wrath of God to make the Spaniards flee! We are coming, Cuba, coming; coming now!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pérez, Louis A 1998&quot; /&gt;

[[Progressivism in the United States|American progressives]] have been accused of engaging in cultural imperialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalreview.com/article/417556/new-cultural-imperialism-josh-craddock|title=The New Cultural Imperialism|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianpost.com/news/the-missionary-zeal-of-the-new-progressive-imperialism-140064/|title=The Missionary Zeal of the New Progressive Imperialism|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, many other countries with American brands have incorporated themselves into their own local culture. An example of this would be the self-styled 'Maccas' an Australian derivation of 'McDonalds' with a tinge of Australian culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://mcdonalds.com.au/about-maccas/maccas-story|title=Our Story {{!}} About Macca's {{!}} McDonald's AU|website=mcdonalds.com.au|access-date=2016-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== U.S. military bases ==
{{further information|List of United States military bases}}

[[Chalmers Johnson]] argued in 2004 that America's version of the colony is the military base.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.commondreams.org/views04/0115-08.htm|title=http://www.commondreams.org/views04/0115-08.htm|publisher=|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040117024125/http://www.commondreams.org/views04/0115-08.htm|archivedate=2004-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Chip Pitts]] argued similarly in 2006 that enduring U.S. bases in Iraq suggested a vision of &quot;[[Iraq War#Iraqi opinion|Iraq as a colony]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Pitts, Chip | title=The Election on Empire | url=http://www.nationalinterest.org/Article.aspx?id=12930 |publisher=The National Interest | date =November 8, 2006 | accessdate =October 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{outdated inline|date=June 2016}}

While territories such as [[Guam]], the [[United States Virgin Islands]], the [[Northern Mariana Islands]], [[American Samoa]] and [[Puerto Rico]] remain under U.S. control, the U.S. allowed many of its overseas territories or occupations to gain independence after [[World War II]]. Examples include the [[Philippines]] (1946), the [[Panama canal zone]] (1979), [[Palau]] (1981), the [[Federated States of Micronesia]] (1986) and the [[Marshall Islands]] (1986). Most of them still have U.S. bases within their territories. In the case of [[Okinawa]], which came under U.S. administration after the [[Battle of Okinawa]] during the Second World War, this happened despite local popular opinion.&lt;ref&gt;Patrick Smith, [http://www.iht.com/articles/1998/03/06/edsmith.t_0.php&lt;!-- also at http://www.nytimes.com/1998/03/06/opinion/06iht-edsmith.t_0.html --&gt; Pay Attention to Okinawans and Close the U.S. Bases], International Herald Tribune (Opinion section), March 6, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2003}}, the United States had bases in over 36 countries worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Jun2003/basestructure2003.pdf
|title = Base Structure Report
|accessdate =January 23, 2007
|year=2003
|publisher=USA Department of Defense|format=PDF| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070110080620/http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Jun2003/basestructure2003.pdf| archivedate= January 10, 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Benevolent imperialism ==
{{Main article|Neoconservatism|Monroe Doctrine}}
[[File:Roosevelt monroe Doctrine cartoon.jpg|thumb|right|Political cartoon depicting [[Theodore Roosevelt]] using the Monroe Doctrine to keep European powers out of the [[Dominican Republic]].]]
One of the earliest historians of American Empire, [[William Appleman Williams]], wrote, &quot;The routine lust for land, markets or security became justifications for noble rhetoric about prosperity, liberty and security.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;William Appleman Williams, &quot;Empire as a Way of Life: An Essay on the Causes and Character of America's Present Predicament Along with a Few Thoughts About an Alternative&quot; (New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1996), S1.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Max Boot]] defends U.S. imperialism by claiming: &quot;U.S. imperialism has been the greatest force for good in the world during the past century. It has defeated communism and Nazism and has intervened against the Taliban and Serbian ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Max Boot|url=http://www.cfr.org/iraq/american-imperialism-no-need-run-away-label/p5934|title=American Imperialism? No Need to Run Away from Label|work=Op-Ed|publisher=[http://www.cfr.org/ Council on Foreign Relations]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&quot; Boot used &quot;imperialism&quot; to describe United States policy, not only in the early 20th century but &quot;since at least 1803&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfr.org/publication.html?id=5934 American Imperialism? No Need to Run Away From the Label ''USA Today'' May 6, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/bush/boot.htm|title=Max Boot, &quot;Neither New nor Nefarious: The Liberal Empire Strikes Back,&quot; November 2003|work=mtholyoke.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; This embrace of empire is made by others [[neoconservatism|neoconservatives]], including British historian [[Paul Johnson (writer)|Paul Johnson]], and writers [[Dinesh D'Souza]] and [[Mark Steyn]]. It is also made by some liberal [[War Hawk|hawks]], such as political scientist [[Zbigniew Brzezinski]] and [[Michael Ignatieff]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Heer, Jeet | title=Operation Anglosphere |work=Boston Globe | url=http://www.jeetheer.com/politics/anglosphere.htm | date=March 23, 2003 | accessdate=October 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

British historian [[Niall Ferguson]] argues that the United States is an empire and believes that this is a good thing: “What is not allowed is to say that the United States is an empire and that this might not be wholly bad.”&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Unconscious Colossus: Limits of (Alternatives to) American Empire,&quot; ''Daedalus'', 134/2, (2005): p 21.&lt;/ref&gt; Ferguson has drawn parallels between the [[British Empire]] and the imperial role of the United States in the late 20th and early 21st centuries, though he describes the United States' political and social structures as more like those of the [[Roman Empire]] than of the British. Ferguson argues that all of these empires have had both positive and negative aspects, but that the positive aspects of the U.S. empire will, if it learns from history and its mistakes, greatly outweigh its negative aspects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Ferguson, Niall | title=Colossus: The Rise and Fall of the American Empire | publisher=Penguin | isbn=0-14-101700-7 | date=June 2, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=February 2011|reason=page numbers need to be listed; article suffers from excessive [[WP:OR]]—what page says this?}}

Another point of view implies that United States expansion overseas has indeed been imperialistic, but that this [[imperialism]] is only a temporary phenomenon; a corruption of American ideals or the relic of a past historical era. Historian Samuel Flagg Bemis argues that [[Spanish–American War]] expansionism was a short-lived imperialistic impulse and &quot;a great aberration in American history&quot;, a very different form of territorial growth than that of earlier American history.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Miller |first=Stuart Creighton  | title=&quot;Benevolent Assimilation&quot; The American Conquest of the Philippines, 1899–1903 | publisher=Yale University Press | year=1982 | isbn=0-300-02697-8 | url=http://www.livejournal.com/users/bailey83221/4300.html#miller |ref=harv}} p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;  Historian [[Walter LaFeber]] sees the Spanish–American War expansionism not as an aberration, but as a culmination of United States expansion westward.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author=Lafeber, Walter| title =The New Empire: An Interpretation of American Expansion, 1860–1898 | publisher=Cornell University Press| isbn =0-8014-9048-0| year = 1975 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian [[Victor Davis Hanson]] argues that the U.S. does not pursue [[Hegemony|world domination]], but maintains worldwide influence by a system of mutually beneficial exchanges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Hanson, Victor Davis |date=November 2002 | title = A Funny Sort of Empire | journal=National Review | url = http://www.nationalreview.com/hanson/hanson112702.asp | accessdate =October 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, a Filipino revolutionary General [[Emilio Aguinaldo]] felt as though the American involvement in the Philippines was destructive, &quot;...the Filipinos fighting for Liberty, the American people fighting them to give them liberty. The two peoples are fighting on parallel lines for the same object.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Aguinaldo, Emilio |date=September 1899 | title=Aguinaldo's Case Against the United States | journal=North American Review | url= http://nationalhumanitiescenter.org/pds/gilded/empire/text9/filipino.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; American influence worldwide and the effects it has on other nations have multiple interpretations according to whose perspective is being taken into account.

[[Neoliberalism in international relations|Liberal internationalists]] argue that even though the present world order is dominated by the United States, the form taken by that dominance is not imperial. International relations scholar [[John Ikenberry]] argues that international institutions have taken the place of empire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Ikenberry, G. John | date= March–April 2004 | title = Illusions of Empire: Defining the New American Order | journal=Foreign Affairs | url = http://fullaccess.foreignaffairs.org/20040301fareviewessay83212a/g-john-ikenberry/illusions-of-empire-defining-the-new-american-order.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[International relations]] scholar [[Joseph Nye]] argues that U.S. power is more and more based on &quot;[[soft power]]&quot;, which comes from [[cultural hegemony]] rather than raw military or economic force.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. [[Joseph Nye|Nye, Joseph Jr.]] (2005). ''Soft Power: The Means to Success in World Politics''. Public Affairs. 208 pp.&lt;/ref&gt; This includes such factors as the widespread desire to emigrate to the United States, the prestige and corresponding high proportion of foreign students at U.S. universities, and the spread of U.S. styles of popular music and cinema. Mass immigration into America may justify this theory, but it is hard to know for sure whether the United States would still maintain its prestige without its military and economic superiority.

Although it could be argued that the United States is dependent on other military powers to ensure cooperation and limit the controversy of its actions.

== See also ==
{{Portal|United States}}
&lt;!--please keep the list in alphabetical order--&gt;
{{colbegin}}
* [[Americanization]]
* [[American Century]]
* [[Criticism of the United States government]]
* [[List of Indian massacres|Indian massacre]]
* [[Inverted totalitarianism]]
* [[Manifest destiny]]
* ''[[A People's History of American Empire]]'' – 2008 book by [[Howard Zinn]], et al.
* [[Territories of the United States]]
* [[Superiority complex]]
* [[Neocolonialism]]
* [[New Imperialism]]
* [[Anti-Americanism]]
* [[Anti-imperialism]]
* [[Soviet Empire]]
* [[Empire]]

&lt;!-- These articles are only tangentially related to this article
* [[British Empire]]
* [[Stereotypes of Americans|American stereotypes]]
* [[Anarchism in the United States]]
--&gt;
{{colend}}

== Notes and references ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite book|last=Bacevich|first=Andrew|authorlink=Andrew Bacevich|year=2008|title=The Limits of Power: The End of American Exceptionalism|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=0-8050-8815-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Boot|first=Max|authorlink=Max Boot|year=2002|title=The Savage Wars of Peace: Small Wars and the Rise of American Power|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=0-465-00721-X}}
*{{cite book |last=Brown |first=Seyom |title=Faces of Power: Constancy and Change in United States Foreign Policy from Truman to Clinton |year=1994 |publisher=[[Columbia University Press]] |location=New York |isbn=0-231-09669-0 }}
*{{cite book |last=Burton |first=David H. |title=Theodore Roosevelt: Confident Imperialist |year=1968 |publisher=[[University of Pennsylvania Press]] |location=Philadelphia |isbn= |asin=B0007GMSSY }}
*{{cite book |last=Callahan |first=Patrick |title=Logics of American Foreign Policy: Theories of America's World Role |year=2003 |publisher=Longman |location=New York |isbn=0-321-08848-4 }}
*{{cite book| last =Card| first =Orson Scott | authorlink =Orson Scott Card| year =2006| title =Empire | publisher=TOR | isbn =0-7653-1611-0}}
*{{cite book |last=Daalder |first=Ivo H. |title=America Unbound: The Bush Revolution in Foreign Policy |authorlink=Ivo Daalder |author2=James M. Lindsay |year=2003 |publisher=Brookings Institution |location=Washington, DC |isbn=0-8157-1688-5 }}
*{{cite book| last =Fulbright | first =J. William | authorlink =J. William Fulbright|author2=Seth P. Tillman|year =1989| title =The Price of Empire | publisher=Pantheon Books| isbn=0-394-57224-6}}
*{{cite book |last=Gaddis |first=John Lewis |title=Strategies of Containment: A Critical Appraisal of Postwar American National Security Policy |authorlink=John Lewis Gaddis |year=2005 |edition=2nd  |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn=0-19-517447-X }}
*{{cite book |last=Hardt |first=Michael |title=[[Empire (Negri and Hardt book)|Empire]] |authorlink=Michael Hardt |author2=[[Antonio Negri]]  |year=2001 |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge, MA |isbn=0-674-00671-2  }} [http://www.infoshop.org/texts/empire.pdf online]
*{{cite book |last=Huntington |first=Samuel P. |title=[[The Clash of Civilizations]]|authorlink=Samuel P. Huntington |year=1996 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-684-81164-2 }}
*{{cite book|last=Johnson|first=Chalmers|authorlink=Chalmers Johnson|title= Blowback: The Costs and Consequences of American Empire|year= 2000|isbn= 0-8050-6239-4|publisher=Holt|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Johnson|first=Chalmers|authorlink=Chalmers Johnson|year=2004|title=The Sorrows of Empire: Militarism, Secrecy, and the End of the Republic|isbn= 0-8050-7004-4|publisher=Metropolitan Books|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Johnson|first=Chalmers|authorlink=Chalmers Johnson|year=2007|title=Nemesis: The Last Days of the American Republic|isbn= 0-8050-7911-4|publisher=Metropolitan Books|location=New York, NY}}
*{{cite book |last=Kagan |first=Robert |title=Of Paradise and Power: America and Europe in the New World Order |authorlink=Robert Kagan |year=2003 |publisher=Knopf |location=New York |isbn=1-4000-4093-0 }}
*{{cite book |last=Kerry |first=Richard J. |title=The Star-Spangled Mirror: America's Image of Itself and the World |authorlink= Richard J. Kerry |year=1990 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |location=Savage, MD |isbn=0-8476-7649-8 }}
*{{cite book |last=Lundestad |first=Geir |title=Empire by Integration: The United States and European Integration, 1945–1997 |authorlink=Geir Lundestad |year=1998 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn=0-19-878212-8 }}
*{{cite book |last=Meyer |first=William H. |title=Security, Economics, and Morality in American Foreign Policy: Contemporary Issues in Historical Context |year=2003 |publisher=Prentice Hall |location=Upper Saddle River, NJ |isbn=0-13-086390-4 }}
*{{cite book |last=Nye |first=Joseph S., Jr |title=[[The Paradox of American Power]]: Why the World's Only Superpower Can't Go It Alone |authorlink=Joseph Nye |year=2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn=0-19-515088-0 }}
*{{cite book| last=Odom| first=William | authorlink=William Eldridge Odom |author2=Robert Dujarric|year =2004|title=America's Inadvertent Empire|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn =0-300-10069-8}}
*{{cite book |last=Patrick |first=Stewart |title=Multilateralism and U.S. Foreign Policy: Ambivalent Engagement |author2=Shepard Forman, eds. |year=2001 |publisher=Lynne Rienner |location=Boulder, CO |isbn=1-58826-042-9 }}
*{{cite book| last =Perkins| first =John| authorlink =John Perkins (author)| year =2004| title =[[Confessions of an Economic Hit Man]]| publisher=Nashr-i Akhtarān| location =Tihrān| isbn =1-57675-301-8}}
*{{cite book |last=Rapkin |first=David P., ed. |title=World Leadership and Hegemony |year=1990 |publisher=Lynne Rienner |location=Boulder, CO |isbn=1-55587-189-5 }}
*{{cite book |last=Ruggie |first=John G., ed. |authorlink=John Ruggie|title=Multilateralism Matters: The Theory and Praxis of an Institutional Form |year=1993 |publisher=Columbia University Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-231-07980-8}}
*{{cite book |last=Smith |first=Tony |title=America's Mission: The United States and the Worldwide Struggle for Democracy in the Twentieth Century |year=1994 |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton, NJ |isbn=0-691-03784-1 }}
*{{cite book |last=Tomlinson |first=John |title=Cultural Imperialism: A Critical Introduction |year=1991 |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |location=Baltimore, MD |isbn=0-8018-4250-6 }}
*{{cite book |last=Todd |first=Emmanuel |authorlink=Emmanuel Todd |title=After the Empire: The Breakdown of the American Order |publisher=Columbia University Press |location=New York |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-231-13103-2 |url=http://cup.columbia.edu/book/978-0-231-13102-5/after-the-empire}}
*{{cite book| last =Tremblay| first =Rodrigue | authorlink =Rodrigue Tremblay| year =2004| title =[[The New American Empire]] | publisher=Infinity Pub| location =Haverford, PA| isbn =0-7414-1887-8}}
*{{cite book| last =Zepezauer| first =Mark| year =2002| title =Boomerang!: How Our Covert Wars Have Created Enemies Across the Middle East and Brought Terror to America| publisher=Common Courage Press| location =Monroe, Maine| isbn =1-56751-222-4}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote|American imperialism}}
{{Wikiquote|American benevolence}}
*[http://monthlyreview.org/wp-content/uploads/2003/05/Imperial_America_Richard_N_Haass.pdf &quot;Imperial America&quot;] by Richard Hass, 2000
*[https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/2001/08/21/empire-or-not-a-quiet-debate-over-us-role/d57204a6-d3b9-4330-b1ce-44e8bdd5b410/ &quot;Empire or Not? A Quiet Debate Over U.S. Role&quot;] by Thomas E. Ricks, 2001
*[http://tanakanews.com/b1112wsj.htm &quot;The Answer to Terrorism? Colonialism&quot;] by Paul Johnson, 2001
*[http://lists.csbs.utah.edu/pipermail/marxism/2001-October/055018.html &quot;The Need for a New Imperialism&quot;] by Martin Wolf, 2001
*[http://ontology.buffalo.edu/smith/courses01/rrtw/boot.htm &quot;The Case for American Empire&quot;] by Max Boot, 2001
*[http://www.nytimes.com/learning/teachers/featured_articles/20020401monday.html &quot;All Roads Lead to D.C.&quot;] by Emily Eakin, 2002
*[http://www.ic.ucsc.edu/~rlipsch/Pol177/Mallaby.html &quot;The Reluctant Imperialist: Terrorism, Failed States, and the Case for American Empire&quot;] by Sebastian Mallaby, 2002
*[http://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/apr/07/1 &quot;The New Liberal Imperialism&quot;] by Robert Cooper, 2002
*[http://www.dineshdsouza.com/news/in-praise-of-american-empire/ &quot;In Praise of American Empire&quot;] by Dinesh D'Souza, 2002
*[http://www.prospectmagazine.co.uk/features/empirelite &quot;Empire lite&quot;] by Michael Ignatieff, 2003
*[http://www.iasc-culture.org/THR/archives/America/5.1GKaplan.pdf &quot;America and The Tragic Limits of Imperialism&quot;] by Robert D. Kaplan, 2003
*[http://hir.harvard.edu/an-empire-in-denial/ &quot;An Empire in Denial: The Limits of US Imperialism&quot;] by Niall Ferguson, 2003
*[http://www.econ.ucla.edu/Lal/papers/In%20defense%20of%20empires.pdf &quot;In Defence of Empires&quot;] by Deepak Lal, 2003

{{United States topics}}
{{North America topics}}
{{Globalization}}

[[Category:History of United States expansionism| 01]]
[[Category:Imperialism]]
[[Category:Empires]]
[[Category:History of the foreign relations of the United States]]
[[Category:Criticism of the United States|Imperialism]]

[[de:Imperialismus#Vereinigte Staaten]]</text>
      <sha1>2d8wg6e15ld4ecieumzmcfxuu9hvhrf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
