<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bato (Dardanian chieftain)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15863617</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746414563</id>
      <parentid>726294107</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-27T07:44:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Annotations */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6988">{{Other uses|Bato (disambiguation){{!}}Bato}}
{{Infobox monarch
|name            = Bato
|title           = King Bato
|image           = Adriatic Coast 201 BC 3rd century (English).svg
|caption         =
|reign           = c. 206 BC – c. 176 BC
|coronation      =
|full name       =
|predecessor     = [[Longarus]]
|successor       = [[Monunius II]]
|spouse          =
|issue           =
|royal house     = 
|dynasty         = 
|father          = [[Longarus]]
|mother          = 
|birth_date   = 
|birth_place  =
|death_date   = 
|death_place  = 
|date of burial  =
|place of burial =
|}}

'''Bato''' (ruled ''c.'' 206&amp;nbsp;– 176 &lt;small&gt;BC&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Illyrians by J. J. Wilkes, 1992, ISBN 0-631-19807-5, page 86, &quot;... including the names of Dardanian rulers, Longarus, Bato, Monunius and Etuta, and those on later epitaphs, Epicadus, Scerviaedus, Tuta, Times and Cinna.  Other Dardanian names are linked with ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;) was an Illyrian king of the [[Dardanian Kingdom|Dardanian State]]. Bato was the son of [[Longarus]] whom he succeeded and the brother of [[Monunius II]] who ruled after him.&lt;ref&gt;BATON or BATO. 1. The son of Longarus, a Dardanian chief, who joined the Romans in their war with Philip of Macedon, B.C. 200. (Liv. xxxi. 28.).&lt;/ref&gt; Bato fought alongside the [[Roman Republic|Romans]] against [[Macedon]] during the [[Second Macedonian War]]. Bato is known for using advanced war tactics against [[Athenagoras of Macedon|Athenagoras]]. Bato became a major threat to the Macedonians but after the war was over Dardanian and Roman relations soon diminished.

When the Romans returned to [[Illyria]] in 200 BC under the experienced commander [[Publius Sulpicius Galba Maximus|P. Sulpicius Galba]], they expected support from their former allies. After the Roman victories many kings, enemies of Macedonia came to the Roman camp: [[Pleuratus]] of the Ardiaean Kingdom, Amynander, king of the Athamanians and Bato of the Dardanian State. The Roman commander told them he would call on their help when his army had entered Macedonia.&lt;ref&gt;Livy 31028 (Bato, son of Longarus)&lt;/ref&gt; Bato was hoping that with the territorial gains [[Rome]] had achieved, he would have [[Paeonia (kingdom)|Paeonia]] under his control.

[[Philip V of Macedon|Philip V]] anticipated that the Romans line of advance would be in the Erigon valley and he was determined to protect his flanks from raids by Roman allies, the Aetoliansin the south and Bato's forces in the north. He ordered his son [[Perseus]] to blockade the pass leading into [[Pelagonia]]. When the Romans made their move Philip recalled the troops under Perseus, and his cavalry defeat at Ottobolus on the river Erigon, though not a major reverse, was the outcome of a gamble after learning that Pleuratus' and Bato's armies had crossed the passes in strength and were already in Macedonia.&lt;ref&gt;The Illyrians by, John Wilkes pg. 150&lt;/ref&gt; In 199 BC took advantage of Philip's engagement in a war with the Romans on the western borders of kingdom. Though the invasions were concerted, it was the Dardanians who did the most damage. As soon as the Romans left to winter in [[Apollonia, Illyria|Apollonia]], Philip sent his general Athenagoras against the Dardania army, which was returning home laden with booty.

At the beginning, Athenagoras made skirmishes against their rear lines but when Bato's army turned their flags and assumed regular positions in front of the enemy, the battle turned into a full-fledged war. As soon as the Dardanians set out on the road, the king's men attacked them with their cavalry and light infantry. Bato did not have an army of this type and were carrying heavy weapons,&lt;ref&gt;The Illyrians to the Albanians -Neritan Ceka p. 179&lt;/ref&gt; but the nature of the terrain helped them.. Few were killed and few more were injured, but none were taken prisoner, because in those few cases the Dardanians come out of their lines and in close formation they fight together or withdraw. The Dradanian army under Bato was a well-organized military force in line with the most advanced tactics of that time, but also distinguished by bravery, discipline and solidarity.&lt;ref&gt;Livy (XXI, 43, 1-3)&lt;/ref&gt;

News of the Roman victory in 197 BC, drew Bato once again down the [[Vardar]] valley, but Philip caught and defeated him near the Paeonian capital [[Stobi]] with an army he had hastily conscripted from the cities of his kingdom. The Macedonians continued to hold Bylazora and through that Paeonia, whose return the Dardanians were still demanding thirty years after another major Roman victory.&lt;ref&gt;Livy 31.38 - 41; 33.19 (after Cynoscephalae)&lt;/ref&gt; Bato did not receive any land as he had hoped in contrast to the Ardiaean Kingdom which was given lands so that Pleuratus could attack Macedonia from them. This angered the Dardanian State which hoped to annex Macedonian land and to free Paeonia, their allies. Such is the fact that in 190 BC, the Aetolians asked Bato for paid soldiers in their war against Rome.

Since it was difficult to defeat Bato militarily, Philip V drew up a plan to set the large Germanic/[[Celts|Celtic]] of the [[Bastarnae]] against him. He proposed to them that he would open a way to the Dardanian State so that the Bastarnae could settle there for a while and later continue on their way through Illyria, finally reaching [[Italy]]. Philip's purpose was to wipe out the Dardanians and settle the Bastarnae in their lands, and send the Bastarnae to Italy to lay it waste, leaving their women and children in Dardania. It was up to Monunius, the brother of Bato to confront the Bastarnae, as he succeeded Bato in 176 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Livy (XL, 574-9)&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Dardani]]a
* [[Illyrian warfare]]
* [[List of rulers of Illyria]]

==Annotations==
Bato was the first known person with this name. He is scarcely known in modern historiography as &quot;Bato of Dardania&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hammond1967&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Nicholas Geoffrey Lemprière Hammond|title=Epirus: the Geography, the Ancient Remains, the History and Topography of Epirus and Adjacent Areas|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kEFoAAAAMAAJ|year=1967|publisher=Clarendon P.|quote=At the other end of the protectorate Rome obtained promises of aid from Pleuratus the Illyrian and from Bato of Dardania.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Bato the Dardanian&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dewar1968&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=James Arthur Dewar|title=The Second Macedonian War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WdpOAAAAMAAJ|year=1968|publisher=University of Wisconsin--Madison|quote=This policy was facilitated by the accession to the Roman cause of the minor chieftains, Pleuratus of Scodra and Bato the Dardanian and Amynander, king of Athamania.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In modern history books, he is mostly indexed as &quot;Bato, son of Longarus&quot; (from {{lang-la|Bato, Longari' filius}} and &quot;Bato, prince of the Dardani&quot;.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{commons|Illyria &amp; Illyrians}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bato Of Dardania}}
[[Category:Illyrian royalty]]
[[Category:Dardanians (Balkan)]]</text>
      <sha1>4rcqv143rmxlc4di4gqgntiyf4mmsku</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
