<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Moon Sound</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5182712</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747717350</id>
      <parentid>745458292</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T23:51:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DagosNavy</username>
        <id>1723027</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Involved a number of troop landings</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12372">{{About|the naval operation|the film|Moonzund (film)}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|CONFLICT = Battle of Moon Sound
|partof=[[Eastern Front (World War I)]]
|image = [[File:Slawa.jpg|300px]]
|caption= The Russian pre-dreadnought ''Slava'' sinking off Saaremaa, October 1917.
|date = 16 October–3 November 1917
|LOCATION = [[West Estonian Archipelago]] and [[Gulf of Riga]], [[Baltic Sea]]
|place=[[Baltic Sea]]
|result= German victory
|combatant1= {{flag|German Empire}}
|combatant2= {{flagicon|Russia}} [[Russian Republic]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]
|commander1= {{flagicon|German Empire|naval}} Vizeadmiral [[Ehrhard Schmidt]]
|commander2= {{flagicon|Russian Empire|naval}} Admiral [[Mikhail Bakhirev]]
|strength1= 1 battlecruiser, &lt;br/&gt; 10 battleships, &lt;br/&gt; 9 light cruisers, &lt;br/&gt; 1 Mine cruiser &lt;br/&gt; 50 destroyers, &lt;br/&gt; 6 submarines, &lt;br/&gt; transports
|strength2= {{flagicon|Russia}} 2 pre-dreadnoughts, &lt;br/&gt; 3 cruisers, &lt;br/&gt; 3 gunboats, &lt;br/&gt; 21 destroyers &lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Great Britain}} 3 submarines
|casualties1= 2 torpedo boats, &lt;br/&gt; many ships damaged by mines
|casualties2= 1 pre-dreadnought, &lt;br/&gt; 1 destroyer, &lt;br/&gt; 1 submarine
}}
{{Campaignbox Baltic Sea 1914-1918}}
[[File:Estonian archipelago (Saaremaa and Hiiumaa).jpg|thumb|left|300px|The area of the battle]]
The '''Battle of Moon Sound''' was a [[naval battle]] fought between the forces of the [[German Empire]], and the then [[Russian Republic]] (and [[British submarine flotilla in the Baltic|three British submarines]]) in the [[Baltic Sea]] from 16 October 1917 until 3 November 1917&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Navies in modern world history |last=Sondhaus |first=Lawrence |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2004 |publisher=Reaktion Books |location= |isbn=1-86189-202-0 |page=193 |pages= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ka-1eQRnXMUC&amp;pg=PA193&amp;dq |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; during [[World War I]]. The German intention was to destroy the Russian forces and occupy the [[West Estonian Archipelago]]. The [[Imperial German Navy]] had 1 battlecruiser, 10 battleships, 9 light cruisers, 1 mine cruiser, 50 destroyers and 6 submarines while the Russians had only 2 pre-dreadnoughts, 3 cruisers, 3 gunboats, 21 destroyers, plus the 3 [[United Kingdom|British]] submarines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Soviet Naval Battles&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Soviet Naval Battles-Revolution and Civil War|url=http://www.soviet-empire.com/ussr/viewtopic.php?f=112&amp;t=47758|accessdate=October 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
It was the Germans' intention to destroy the Russian Army and occupy the West Estonian Archipelago (Moonsund Archipelago). The Germans captured the archipelago, with its main islands of [[Saaremaa]] (Ösel), [[Hiiumaa]] (Dagö), and [[Muhu]] (Moon) during [[Operation Albion]] in September 1917. This left a Russian squadron consisting of the old [[Russo-Japanese War]]-era [[pre-dreadnought battleship]]s Grazhdanin ({{Ship|Russian battleship|Tsesarevich||2}}), and {{Ship|Russian battleship|Slava||2}}, together with cruisers and destroyers, stranded in the [[Gulf of Riga]]. The Russian fleet escaped on 17 October 1917 by way of the Suur Strait separating the island of Muhu from the Estonian mainland.

==Battle==
At the start of the Battle of Moon Sound, there were two submarines in the Gulf of Riga. They were [[HMS C27|''C 27'']] (Lt. Sealy) and [[HMS C32|''C 32'']] (Lt. Satow). When the Germans got there, [[Francis Cromie|Captain Francis Cromie]] sent out another submarine called [[HMS C26|''C 26'']] (Lt. Downie). On the night of the 16th of October, Lt. Sealy fired two torpedoes at two German ships but missed. Two further torpedoes struck their targets. ''C 27'' returned to [[Hanko]] when it was no longer needed. ''C 32'' attempted to attack a German ship but was spotted and bombed. In the afternoon of 16 October, Gruppe Behncke travelled to the south exit of the Suur Strait and dropped anchor around 8:30 pm. All German ships were anchored in a close line with a torpedo boat at each end. The Germans made significant progress on shore on 16 October, taking 120 officers and 400 men prisoner and capturing 49 guns. By the end of the day, German forces were prepared to capture the West Estonian Archipelago and the navy was ready to attack in the [[Matsalu National Park|Matsalu Bay]] and the Suur Strait.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;

The Russian battle strategy was changed at 4:30 am on October 17 due to a mistake made in the transfer of an order. That morning, ships were on the move by 7:00. The 3rd M.S.H.F was heading east while the 8th H.f.F.l. was heading north under command of [[Erich Koellner]].&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

At 7:20, Russian battleships opened fire on the 8th H.f.F.l, the 3rd M.S. Dive and the Sperrbrecher. The 8th advanced but were under constant Russian fire. It was the 3rd M.S.H.F's duty to clear mines.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

At 8:00 am Admiral Behncke ordered that the cruisers stay put and not advance any farther. At this point, [[SMS König|''König'']] and [[SMS Kronprinz|''Kronprinz'']] proceeded east by the 3rd M.S.H.F, both under the command of [[Georg von der Marwitz]]. ''Slava'' was advancing so that she came between Paternoster and Werder and started firing upon any east-bound German ship. While this was going on, the 3rd M.S.H.F. had reached Laura Bank and turned north, ''König'' and ''Kronprinz'' continued east and ''Slava'' was now heading north. Admiral Hopman was at the same time heading west towards the Väike Strait.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

At 9:10, two Russian ships that had returned south opened fire on the 3rd M.S.H.F. The Russians now understood that if they could stop the minesweepers, they could stop the entire German attack. At 9:40, 3rd Ms. Dive was brought over to the east side of Russian minefields to assist the 3rd H.f.F.l.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

By 10:00, the minesweepers were on the northern edge of the rectangular minefield. ''König'' and ''Kronprinz'' now went forward. Around 10:13, ''König'' opened fire on ''Slava''. By 10:17, ''Kronprinz'' followed ''König''`s lead and opened fire on the battleship ''Grazhdanin''. ''Bayan'' was also attacked by ''König''. ''Slava'' took many underwater hits, causing extensive damage. ''Grazhdanin'' only got hit twice in all of the chaos. at 10:40 the Germans ceased fire. The Russians continued to fire on the 3rd M.S.H.F. Around 10:30, Admiral Bachirev ordered all sea forces to withdraw to the northern Suur Strait. ''Slava,'' now fatally wounded, was scuttled by Turkmerec Strauropolski.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt; The Russians were determined to make the channel impossible to pass through so they laid out more mines and used damaged ships to their advantage. At 10:46, the Werder Battery opened fire on the German battleships.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

At approximately 11:09, two German battleships anchored while under fire at [[Võilaid]]. At 11.28 there was a false submarine alarm followed by a legitimate one at 12:08.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

Around 1:35, Kolberg attacked Võilaid for approximately ten minutes but met no reply. At 3:45, Admiral Hopman`s flagleutnant Obltz Keln led a landing party to take over Woi. At 5:30, white star shell could be seen which meant that the battery had successfully been taken but the guns were unserviceable. By 3:00, [[Kommodore]] Heinrich took V100 toward the channel that would lead them to the Suur Strait but were immediately under fire by gunboats under the control of Admiral Makarov.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

At 10:00pm, Kptlt Zander began to go forward to the Suur Strait. The destroyer ''S 50'' took up position to mark the passage. At the end of the day, Germans were in control over the southern Suur Strait, the Väike Strait and the Matsalu Bay. On the night of October 17, Russians gave up trying to capture the Suur Strait. Just after midnight on October 18, ''S 64'' was shaken by a mine detonation and was rendered unmanoeuvrable.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

By 1:00 am, ''S 64'' was sunk by mine. At dawn, German torpedo boats assumed patrol stations in the Matsalu Bay. The landing operations on Hiiumaa gained momentum between 7:15 and 8:00 am, and the area around [[Emmaste]] was secured. By 8:30, German minesweepers had worked forward to a mile south of the [[Viirelaid]] lighthouse.  At 8:00, Behncke's group started east and went behind the 3rd M.S.H.F.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

Just after 10:00, Behncke ordered Admiral Hopman to dispatch ''Strassburg'' and the 8th M.S.H.F. to the 3rd squadron while ''Kolberg'', the torpedo-boats and Sperrbrecher would remain to the west. At 12:40 the 3rd M.S.H.F. and two boats of the half flotilla confirmed that ''Slava'' was sunk along with two freight steamers. The Germans could see Russian destroyers laying mines, the Russians had not yet detected the Germans, so the Germans opened fire, which was met with a reply. Two German torpedo boats opened fire as the Germans continued northward, two Russian gunboats and several destroyers took them under fire. They then turned south at high speed under the cover of a smoke screen. By the evening of the 18th, [[Kuressaare]] had been made a supply base, the southern part of Hiiumaa under control of the second Cyclist Battalion and the S-Flotilla landing section, [[Saaremaa]] and [[Muhu]] were now firmly in German hands.&lt;ref name=Albion /&gt;  

On October 19 the forces of the Gulf of Riga and numerous transport steamers and auxiliaries left the northern Suur Strait under the protection of minesweepers and destroyers. By mid-afternoon, the German forces had penetrated the strait. The German losses were seven minesweepers, nine trawlers and small boats as well as one torpedo-boat. The Imperial Navy had a total of 156 dead and 60 wounded. The army had 54 dead and 141 wounded. The German Army captured 20,130 prisoners, 141 Russian guns including 47 heavy pieces and 130 machine guns.&lt;ref name=Albion&gt;{{cite web|last=Staff|first=Gary|title=Operation Albion|url=http://www.gwpda.org/naval/albion3.htm|accessdate=October 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
{{refimprove|section|date=October 2015}}
{{unreliable sources|section|date=October 2015}}
Casualties of the Battle were far more extensive for the Germans than the Russians. 300 German soldiers were killed, and 200 were wounded while the Russians suffered fewer than 100 deaths and around the same number of wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Soviet Naval Battles&quot; /&gt;{{Unreliable source?|certain=y|reason=WP:USERG|date=October 2015}} German destroyers ''S 46'', ''S 64'' and the Russian destroyer ''Grom'' were sunk. All the four ships, ''Slava'', ''Citizen'', ''König'' and ''Kronprinz'' were damaged, with ''Slava'' in particularly bad condition. The German battleships ''Bayern'' and ''Grosser Kurfürst'' were badly damaged, destroyer ''B 98'' was damaged, ''A 32'' ran aground, the auxiliary ship ''Corsika'' was damaged, 7 minesweepers and the destroyers ''S 65'' and ''S 66'' were sunk.&lt;ref name=&quot;Soviet Naval Battles&quot; /&gt;{{Unreliable source?|certain=y|reason=WP:USERG|date=October 2015}}

==See also==
*[[Moonsund Landing Operation]] (1944)

==References==
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book |title=Operation Albion: the German conquest of the Baltic Islands |last=Barrett |first=Michael B |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2007 |publisher=Indiana University Press |location= |isbn=0-253-34969-9 |page= |pages= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KudmAAAAMAAJ&amp;q |accessdate=}}
*{{cite book |title=A Naval History of World War I|last=Halpern| first=Paul |authorlink=|coauthors= |year=1994 |publisher=UCL Press| location= |isbn=1-85728-295-7| pages= | url=}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of Moon Sound}}
*[http://www.neva.ru/EXPO96/book/chap11-4.html Account of Russian naval activities in World War I; includes a short section on the Battle of Moon Sound]
*[http://ship.bsu.by/main.asp?id=4042#4042 Article in Russian Language on the Battle]
*[http://www.gwpda.org/naval/albion3.htm Article in English]

{{coord missing|Baltic Sea}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Moon Sound}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1917]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War I involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War I involving Russia]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War I involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Baltic Sea operations of World War I]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations of World War I]]</text>
      <sha1>onlmwqyz2l2xda60ah3owx4f8a169k9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
