<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Breath (2009 film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24923144</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748338738</id>
      <parentid>713093735</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T18:40:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 2 sources and tagging 1 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18448">{{Infobox film
| name           = Breath
| image          = Nefes film poster.jpg
| caption        = Theatrical poster
| director       = [[Levent Semerci]]
| producer       = [[Levent Semerci]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Murat Akdilek]]
| writer         = [[Hakan Evrensel]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mehmet İlker Altınay]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Levent Semerci]]
| starring       = [[Mete Horozoğlu]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Birce Akalay]]&lt;br/&gt;[[İlker Kızmaz]]
| music          = [[Fırat Yükselir]]
| studio         = [[Fida Film]]&lt;br /&gt;Creavidi
| distributor    = [[Medyavizyon]]&lt;br /&gt;Maxximum Film und Kunst
| released       = {{Film date|2009|10|16}}
| runtime        = 120 minutes
| country        = Turkey
| language       = Turkish
| budget         = $2 million
| gross          = $14,727,335
}}
'''''Breath''''' ({{lang-tr|Nefes: Vatan Sağolsun}}, literally ''Breath: Long Live the Homeland'') is a 2009 [[Turkey|Turkish]] [[drama film]] directed by [[Levent Semerci]]. The film, which tells the story of 40 soldiers in charge of protecting a relay station near the Iraqi border in southeastern Turkey, was adapted from the short stories ''Tales from the Southeast'' and ''Ground Minus Zero'' by [[Hakan Evrensel]] and is, according to ''[[Hürriyet Daily News]]'' reviewer Emine Yıldırım, ''the first Turkish film that tackles, through an authentic perspective and convincing realness, the contemporary situation of the Turkish army and its long battle with the terrorist [[Kurdistan Workers' Party]] (PKK) ''.&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ01&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=A rainbow of Turkish films awaits moviegoers |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-148129-a-rainbow-of-turkish-films-awaits-moviegoers.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2008-07-22 |accessdate=2010-08-11 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121007182255/http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-148129-a-rainbow-of-turkish-films-awaits-moviegoers.html |archivedate=2012-10-07 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ02&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=70 domestic productions to debut this season |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-184991-70-domestic-productions-to-debut-this-season.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2009-08-25 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ03&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=This week in theaters  |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-190144-this-week-in-theaters.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2009-10-17 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ04&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Levent Semerci’s ‘Nefes’ marks milestone in Turkish cinema |first=Emine |last=Yıldırım |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-190497-levent-aqua-aquasemercis-nefes-marks-milestone-in-turkish-cinema.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2009-10-21 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tcm01&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Misc Notes for Nefes: Vatan sagolsun |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.tcm.com/tcmdb/title.jsp?stid=778509&amp;category=Misc%20Notes |work=Turner Classic Movies |date= |accessdate=2010-02-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film, according to ''[[Today's Zaman]]'', ''sparked a growing discussion on whether it includes militaristic and nationalist elements or whether it is merely aiming to show the deadly and difficult conditions soldiers face in the vast mountainous terrain of southeastern Anatolia, fighting against outlawed Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) militants.'' Critics such as columnists Emre Aköz and Nedim Hazar pointed out that writer Hakan Evrensel, upon whose works the film was based, had worked at the public relations department of the National Security Council (MGK) when the terrorist activities were at their peak and claimed the film fails to be impartial and objective in indicating the genuine motives of the terrorists fighting in the mountains.&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ05&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=‘Nefes’ causes debate on militarism and nationalism |first=Mınhac |last=Çelık |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-191607-nefes-causes-debate-on-militarism-and-nationalism.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2009-11-01 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ06&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Could film ‘Nefes’ be made by Turkish military? |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-193153-could-film-nefes-be-made-by-turkish-military.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2009-11-17 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film went on general release across Turkey on {{start date|2009|10|16}} and won two awards at the [[3rd Yeşilçam Awards]] as well as being one of the highest grossing films of 2009, prompting its re-release on {{start date|2010|07|23}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ07&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Ugly thugs, tearjerkers top Turkish box office in 2009 |first=Emine |last=Yıldırım |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-196623-ugly-thugs-tearjerkers-top-turkish-box-office-in-2009.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2009-12-26 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HDN02&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=3rd Yeşilçam Awards presented |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=0324013922118-2010-03-24 |work=[[Turkish Daily News]] |date= |accessdate=2010-03-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ08&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=‘Nefes’ named best film at Yeşilçam, ‘Vavien’ wins 3 prizes |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-205309-112-nefes-named-best-film-at-yesilcam-vavien-wins-3-prizes.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2010-03-25 |accessdate=2010-08-11 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029195626/http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-205309-112-nefes-named-best-film-at-yesilcam-vavien-wins-3-prizes.html |archivedate=2013-10-29 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ09&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Second time around one time too many for moviegoers |first=Ali |last=Koca |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-216849-second-time-around-one-time-too-many-for-moviegoers.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2010-07-23 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==
The film was shot on location in [[Istanbul]] and [[Antalya]], [[Turkey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb01&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Filming locations for Nefes: Vatan sagolsun |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1171701/locations |work=IMDB |date= |accessdate=2010-02-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Plot ==
This film is about a small unit of 40 Turkish soldiers in a remote patrol station in eastern Turkey, in a state of near certain death, during the most violent times, in the [[Timeline of the Kurdish–Turkish conflict|conflict]] between the [[Turkish Army]] and the [[Kurdistan Workers' Party]] (PKK).

==Release==

===General Release===
''Thanks to cleverly edited teasers that barely gave any clue to the movie, a constant delay of the release date over the last six months and a nation overly sensitive to war, civil-military relations and nationalism,'' Emrah Güller, writing in the ''[[Hürriyet Daily News]]'', states, ''Heated debates preceded the release of director Levent Semerci’s war drama “Nefes” (Breath) in chat rooms, Web forums, Facebook groups and mass media.'' ''Ironically,'' he concedes, ''the release of advertisement director Semerci’s debut film put a halt to many of the discussions because the audience had a hard time pinning down the message of the movie and labeling it as positive or negative propaganda for the military.'' ''The unprecedented success of “Nefes” lies in its ability to put a stop to all desperate attempts to maneuver the film into a nationalistic or anti-military stance,'' Güller concludes.&lt;ref name=&quot;HDN01&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Breathing life into a history of war |first=Emrah |last=Güler |coauthors= |url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=breathing-life-into-a-history-of-war-2009-10-23 |work=[[Hürriyet Daily News]] |date=2009-10-23 |accessdate=2010-02-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film opened in 608 screens across Turkey on {{start date|2009|10|16}} at number one in the Turkish box office chart with an opening weekend gross of [[US$]]2,018,862. ''Some,'' according to ''[[Today's Zaman]]'' journalist Mınhac Çelık, ''argue the timing of the highly publicized film’s release is critical because it comes almost simultaneously with the return of a small group of PKK members from neighboring Iraq who surrendered to Turkish authorities.''&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ05&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM01&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Nefes |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/intl/?page=&amp;wk=2010W30&amp;id=_fNEFES01 |work=[[Box Office Mojo]] |date= |accessdate=2010-02-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film opened across Germany on {{start date|2009|10|22}} and across Austria on {{start date|2009|10|23}}. It later re-opened in 106 screens across Turkey on {{start date|2010|07|23}} at number ten in the Turkish box office chart with an opening weekend gross of [[US$]]7,569.&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM01&quot; /&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;
|+ Opening weekend gross
|-
!Date!!Territory!!Screens!!Rank!!Gross
|-
| {{start date|2009|10|16}}
| [[Turkey]]
| 608
| 1
| [[US$]]2,018,862
|-
| {{start date|2009|10|22}}
| [[Germany]]
| 65
| 16
| [[US$]]259,166
|-
| {{start date|2009|10|23}}
| [[Austria]]
| 8
| 13
| [[US$]]38,786
|-
| {{start date|2010|07|23}}
| [[Turkey]] (re-release)
| 106
| 10
| [[US$]]7,569

|}

===Festival screenings===
* New York Turkish Film Days (opening film)&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ10&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Semerci’s ‘Nefes’ opens NY Turkish Film Days |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-211118-aqua-aquasemercis-nefes-opens-ny-turkish-film-days.html |work=[[Today's Zaman]] |date=2010-05-26 |accessdate=2010-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[17th Adana &quot;Golden Boll&quot; International Film Festival]] (September 20–26, 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;AKFF01&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=BREATH / NEFES: VATAN SAĞOLSUN |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.altinkoza.org/eng/national-long-film-competition/nominees/nefes/ |work=AKFF |date= |accessdate=2010-09-27 }}{{dead link|date=November 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==

===Box office===
The movie was number one at the Turkish box office for four weeks running and is the second highest grossing Turkish film of the year with a total worldwide gross of $14,727,335.&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM01&quot; /&gt;

===Reviews===
''[[Radikal]]'' executive editor İsmet Berkan, who considered the film a masterpiece with its realist characteristics, wrote, ''I can claim that it is the most beautiful and meaningful Turkish movie I have ever watched. It is a real masterpiece with its perfect technical and aesthetic aspects as well as its theme. The film displays the naked realities of the war. … Thank you, Levent Semerci.''&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ05&quot; /&gt;

''[[Today's Zaman]]'' reviewer Emine Yıldırım describes the, ''&quot;[[Full Metal Jacket]]&quot;-inspired army epic,'' as, ''&quot;one of the most disturbing films I have seen in a very long time&quot;'', despite the fact she admits that she, ''&quot;still remain undecided whether the film is a masterpiece or an emotionally explosive disaster.&quot;'' Following a slow start in which, according to Yıldırım, the film, ''&quot;seems to launch into too much of an advertisement&quot;'', ''&quot;Semerci manages to create a stunning atmosphere of abandonment, fear and camaraderie&quot;'', as, ''&quot;we get a better inside look at these young men.&quot;'' ''&quot;The film is currently playing to a full house in almost all of Istanbul's movie theatres&quot;'', she says of its popularity, ''&quot;all hypnotized throughout its 128-minute running time and especially transfixed by its final sequence.&quot;'' Though the film, which according to Yıldırım, ''&quot;remains patriotic from start to finish&quot;'', ''&quot;does not aim to be political in the general sense,&quot;'' ''&quot;what Semerci does is to directly put the viewer in the shoes of the commandos and make the audience confront a violent truth that it has already been aware of for the past 30 years but had never seen on screen in such a continuously graphic way&quot;''. ''&quot;The problem,&quot;'' she continues, ''&quot;is that this particular film gets lost in its own heroism while over-emotionalizing the predicament of the soldiers, and it also lacks a comprehensive and tight story structure while its political stance remains too murky&quot;''. ''&quot;Despite its flaws&quot;'', Yıldırım concludes, the film, ''&quot;marks a milestone in Turkish cinema by being the first film to take the risk of duly tackling an issue that has long been evaded&quot;'', and, ''&quot;provides a succinct depiction of what being a soldier in southeastern Turkey entails&quot;''. ''&quot;Hopefully,&quot;'' she adds, ''&quot;it will be the harbinger of a long line of films undertaking the condition of people whose lives are directly influenced by the Turkish military.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ04&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ07&quot; /&gt;

''[[Hürriyet Daily News]]'' reviewer Emrah Güler states that, ''the teasers and the constant delay of the release date might have fueled debates before it met audiences, but the beautifully shot film featuring unknown actors successfully refrains from making any statements, instead remaining a haunting slice-of-life film about soldiers.'' ''Semerci moves his camera skillfully, slowly and with confidence across the skies, naked mountains, and a few soldiers lost along the depressing landscape. Most of the time, the scenes of stillness are enough to give the sense of loneliness, despair and meaninglessness of war,'' he continues, ''and when the movie moves into crafty and realistic scenes of military engagement, it refuses to stay a mix of detached action scenes but turn into tales of horror for everyone touched by war.'' Güller commends the cast by saying, ''Semerci’s selection of unknown names from acting schools around the country proves to be the right choice as no one character stands out, and it helps to amplify the sense of voyeurism into the lives of a real group of soldiers.'' He concedes that, ''For the Turkish audience, the experience of watching the everyday lives of these soldiers becomes more haunting as these border stations are the epitome of the lives of thousands claimed in the last two decades, and most people don’t have a clue what they look like or what it feels like to be on the edges of a country.'' ''The film strategically moves away from putting forward any message, and simply tells the stories of young men at war. It’s easy to interpret the movie in any way, depending on your take on the war. Semerci’s simply captures a group of scared young men ready to accept death because it’s the easiest option or, if they’re lucky, about to become damaged goods, scarred for life.'' This Güller concludes, is where, ''The unprecedented success of “Nefes” lies.''&lt;ref name=&quot;HDN01&quot; /&gt;

''[[Sabah (newspaper)|Sabah]]'' columnist Emre Aköz, refuting claims that the film was anti-militaristic, said, ''The producers of the film, Levent Semerci, Hakan Evrensel and Mehmet İlker Altınay, have used all the symbols of Turkey’s dominant nationalist ideology: Atatürk’s sculpture on the mountain at a height of 2,365 meters, the slogan of ‘Vatan Sağolsun’ (may the country survive), a compassionate big-hearted Turkish soldier who treats a PKK militant rather than killing her, the city dwellers who do not care about the young men defending the country. After using all these symbols, how can this film not be a nationalist militarist one?''&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ05&quot; /&gt;

''[[Zaman (newspaper)|Zaman]]'' columnist Nedim Hazar, who felt it wrong to shoot a film about an ongoing war, stated, ''Blood is still being shed. Ambushes, raids and attacks are going on; therefore it is impossible to raise criticism, make a comprehensive analysis or sum up the fight with a film about a bloody process in which there are thousands of victims and slain soldiers with their families.'' ''Furthermore, it serves to cover up the genuine factors that are still instrumental to the war,'' and, he concluded, ''If you criticize the film, you will be an enemy of the nation and the army; in contrast, when you praise the film and its context, you will be labeled as fascist.''&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ05&quot; /&gt;

[[Galatasaray University]] scholar Hülya Uğur Tanrıöver, in an interview with [[NTV Turkey|NTV]], criticises the film for gender discrimination, observing, ''The film underestimates the difficulties women face in big cities. In a phone conversation between a soldier and his lover living in İstanbul, the soldier ignores the problems she has in the city, saying, ‘What difficulties can you experience in İstanbul?’ Moreover, in the next scene, the commander tells a soldier whose girlfriend has left him, ‘This girl would cuckold you if you had not separated.’ These are clear insults to girls living in big cities, and the film, from this point of view, has definite elements of gender discrimination.''&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ05&quot; /&gt;

===Accolades===
* [[3rd Yeşilçam Awards]] (March 23, 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;HDN02&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TZ08&quot; /&gt;
** Best Film Award (won)
** Turkcell First Film Award (won)
* [[17th Adana &quot;Golden Boll&quot; International Film Festival]] (September 20–26, 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;TDN01&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Turkey's Golden Boll film festival draws to a close |first= |last= |coauthors= |url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=golden-boll-film-festival-draws-to-a-close-2010-09-26 |work=[[Hürriyet Daily News]] |date=2010-09-26 |accessdate=2010-09-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Best Director: [[Levent Semerci]] (shared with [[Selim Demirdelen]] for ''[[The Crossing (2010 film)|The Crossing]]'')
** Audience Jury Best Picture (won)

== See also ==
* [[2009 in film]]
* [[Turkish films of 2009]]
* [[Kurdish–Turkish conflict]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://www.nefesfilm.com/}} 
* {{Allmovie title|504211|Nefes: Vatan sagolsun}}
* {{IMDb title|1171701|The Breath}}
* {{tcmdb title|778509|Nefes: Vatan sagolsun}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach|aw}}
{{succession box
| title=[[Yeşilçam Award#Best Film Award|Yeşilçam Best Film Award]]
| years=2010
| before=''[[Three Monkeys]]''
| after=[[Majority (film)|Majority]]}}
{{succession box
| title=[[Yeşilçam Award#Turkcell First Film Award|Turkcell First Film Award]]
| years=2010
| before=''[[Autumn (2008 film)|Autumn]]''
| after=[[Majority (film)|Majority]]}}
{{end}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Breath}}
[[Category:2009 films]]
[[Category:Turkish films]]
[[Category:Turkish-language films]]
[[Category:2000s adventure films]]
[[Category:2000s drama films]]
[[Category:Films set in Turkey]]
[[Category:Turkish war films]]</text>
      <sha1>70nlevb3jpfkrtetws85ar1w2rvjtaw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
