<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chen Sheng</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1287084</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748421012</id>
      <parentid>742009189</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-08T03:08:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cirolchou</username>
        <id>17721758</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7534">{{for|the Chinese rhytmic gymnast|Chen Sheng (gymnast)}}
{{more footnotes|date=February 2013}}
{{chinese-name|[[Chen (surname)|Chen]]}}
{{Chinese|t=陳勝|s=陈胜|p=Chén Shèng|w=Ch'en Sheng|j=Can4 Sing3|altname=Chen She|t2=陳涉|s2=陈涉|p2=Chén Shè|w2=Ch'en She|j2=Can4 Sip3}}

'''Chen Sheng''' (died 208 BC), also known as '''Chen She''', was the leader of the first rebellion, known as [[Dazexiang Uprising]], against the [[Qin Dynasty]] during the reign of the second Qin emperor [[Qin Er Shi]].

==Start of the rebellion==
Chen Sheng was born in Yangcheng (陽城; in present-day [[Fangcheng County]], [[Henan]]). In 209 BC, he was a military captain along with [[Wu Guang]] when the two of them were ordered to lead 900 soldiers to Yuyang (漁陽; southwest of present-day [[Miyun County]], [[Beijing]]) to help defend the northern border against [[Xiongnu]]. Due to storms, it became clear that they could not get to Yuyang by the deadline, and according to law, if soldiers could not get to their posts on time, they would be executed. Chen Sheng and Wu Guang, believing that they were doomed, led their soldiers to start a rebellion. They announced that [[Fusu]], the crown prince of Qin, who had wrongly been forced to commit suicide, and [[Xiang Yan]], a general of [[Chu (state)|Chu]], had not died and were joining their cause. They also declared the reestablishment of Chu.

Using 900 men to resist an empire seemed to be a suicidal move, but the people, who had felt deeply oppressed by the Qin regime, joined Chen Sheng and Wu Guang's cause quickly. More than 20,000 men joined. Soon, there were people asking Chen Sheng to declare himself &quot;King of [[Chu (state)|Chu]]&quot;. Acting against the advice of [[Zhang Er]] and [[Chen Yu of Dai|Chen Yu]], Chen Sheng declared himself &quot;King of Rising Chu&quot; (張楚王).

==Downfall and death==
Chen Sheng, setting his capital at Chen County (陳縣; in present-day [[Huaiyang County|Huaiyang]], [[Henan]]), then commissioned various generals to advance in all directions to conquer Qin territory. Among these were: Wu Guang, whom he created acting-'King of Chu'; [[Zhou Wen (Qin Dynasty)|Zhou Wen]] (周文), whom he ordered to head west toward Qin proper; his friend [[Wu Chen (Qin Dynasty)|Wu Chen]] (武臣), whom he ordered to head north toward the old territory of [[Zhao (state)|Zhao]]; [[Zhou Fu (Qin Dynasty)|Zhou Fu]] (周敷), whom he ordered to head northeast toward the old territory of [[Wei (state)|Wei]]. However, none of these generals returned. After initial defeats Qin forces regrouped under general [[Zhang Han (Qin dynasty)|Zhang Han]]. Wu Guang was assassinated by generals under him; Zhou Wen was defeated by Qin forces; Wu Chen was initially successful but then declared himself the King of [[Zhao (state)|Zhao]] and became independent of Chu; and Zhou Fu supported a descendant of the royal house of Wei to be the King of Wei, also independent of Chu. A major reason why Wu Chen and the generals who assassinated Wu Guang broke away was that Chen Sheng was paranoid as a king: generals were executed at any sign of infidelity, even by rumours. Chen Sheng's ruthlessness and constant defeats in battle made it harder and harder for him to gather followers. Chen Sheng was greatly weakened, and as he suffered losses at the hands of the Qin army, he personally led a force to try to gather reinforcements, but he was assassinated by his guard [[Zhuang Jia (rebel)|Zhuang Jia]] in winter 209 BC-208 BC. His rebellion ended just six months after it started.

==Legacy==
Chen Sheng was often idealised by versions of history promulgated by Chinese historians as a great leader of the peasants against intolerable oppression of the Qin nobility and [[bourgeois]]. However, that perception is not reality. Chen Sheng's decisions, while motivated by his desire to overthrow Qin, was also often motivated by self-interest and self-aggrandisation. He also failed to take in good advice and overly estimated himself. As the [[Song Dynasty]] historian [[Sima Guang]] wrote in the ''[[Zizhi Tongjian]]'':

{{blockquote|
When Chen Sheng first became the King of Chu, his relatives and friends all arrived to join him, as did his father-in-law. But when his father-in-law arrived, Chen treated him as an ordinary guest and only made a slight bow and did not kneel to him. His father-in-law became angry and stated, &quot;You are leading a rebellion and falsely claiming the title of a king, but you are arrogant toward your elders: You surely cannot last.&quot; He turned to leave without further discussion, and even though Chen knelt to ask for his forgiveness, he ignored Chen. Later, when there were more and more relatives and friends arriving, they were discussing the stories when Chen was young. Someone suggested, &quot;The old friends and guests of Your Royal Highness are foolish and often liked to talk in vain; they will damage your image and hurt your reputation.&quot; Chen executed a good number of his old friends, and therefore his friends began to leave him and not follow him. Chen made Zhu Fang to be his examination minister and Hu Wu to be the head of his guard, to be in charge of intelligence and security. When the generals conquered cities and returned, the two of them often criticised and nit-picked on the commands issued by those generals or their acts; often, if they felt the commands or the acts were not lawful, they would arrest the generals. Chen considered those who are strict to be the most faithful ones. The ones that Chen did not like were either given over to courts martial or personally punished by him. The generals had no affection for Chen, and this led to his downfall. 
}}

While Chinese historians may quibble with Sima Guang's characterisation of Chen,{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} it appears to be quite correct. He claimed the title of king only months after the start of his rebellion, without a sufficient foundation, and once he did he effectively became stuck in Chen County and could not firmly hold territories that were conquered, because the people in the territories did not view him with great affection. While he had his role in the downfall of Qin, he should not be viewed as a hero.

==Miscellaneous==
Chen Sheng appears&lt;ref&gt;Sima Qian. ''Records of the Grand Historian'', Volume 48.&lt;/ref&gt; to be the person who coined the Chinese proverb, &quot;How can a little songbird understand the ambitions of a grand swan!&quot; ([[wikt:燕雀安知鴻鵠志|燕雀安知鴻鵠志]]), a saying that figures prominently in [[s:Romance of the Three Kingdoms/Chapter 4#24|Chapter 4]] of the historical novel ''[[Romance of the Three Kingdoms]]''.

The pattern of an impostor and his general, founded by Chen Sheng, was closely followed by [[Han Shantong]] and Liu Futong in the end of [[Yuan Dynasty]].

==See also==
* [[Dazexiang Uprising]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
* [[Sima Qian]]. ''[[Records of the Grand Historian]]''.

{{S-start}}
{{S-pre}}
{{s-break}}
{{S-vac|recreated|last=[[Lord Changping of Chu|Lord Changping]]|reason=[[Dazexiang Uprising]]}}
{{S-tul|title=[[Chu (state)|King of Chu]]|years=210 BC &amp;ndash; 209 BC}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Jing Ju]]&lt;!--景駒--&gt;}}
{{end}}

{{Qin Dynasty insurgent states|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chen, Sheng}}
[[Category:Generals from Henan]]
[[Category:Chinese nobility]]
[[Category:Qin Dynasty people]]
[[Category:208 BC deaths]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:Murdered monarchs]]
[[Category:Assassinated Chinese politicians]]
[[Category:People from Nanyang, Henan]]</text>
      <sha1>nnmqm2h67tohgngfnv8tic2dda0vxki</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
