<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dagobert Sigmund von Wurmser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2659526</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747975726</id>
      <parentid>744954058</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-05T15:44:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ÄDA - DÄP</username>
        <id>16734816</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* External links */clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27969">{{more footnotes|date=February 2015}}
{{Infobox military person
| name          = Dagobert Sigmund von Wurmser
| image         = Dagobert Wurmser.jpg
| caption       =
| birth_date          = {{birth-date|7 May 1724}}
| death_date          = {{death-date and age|22 August 1797|7 May 1724}}
| birth_place  = [[Strasbourg]], [[Alsace]], [[Kingdom of France]]
| death_place  = [[Vienna]]
| allegiance    = {{flag|Habsburg Monarchy}} 
| branch        = Cavalry
| serviceyears  = 1756–1763 (France)&lt;br&gt;1763–1796 
| rank          = General of Cavalry
| battles       = [[War of the Bavarian Succession]]
* [[Skirmish at Habelschwerdt]]
[[Austro–Turkish War (1787–1791)]], as Commanding General.
&lt;br&gt;[[French Revolutionary Wars]]
* 1793, [[First Battle of Wissembourg (1793)|Battle of Weissenburg]]
* 1795, [[Battle of Mannheim]]
* 1796, [[Battle of Castiglione]]
* 1796, [[Battle of Bassano]]
* 1796, [[Battle of La Favorita]]
| awards        = 1778, Knight's Cross of the [[Military Order of Maria Theresa]]&lt;ref name=&quot;MTO&quot; &gt;Jaromir Hirtenfeld. ''Der militär-Maria-Theresien-Orden und seine Mitglieder: nach authentischen Quellen bearbeitet.'' Wien: Hofdruckerei, 1857, pp. 1736, 1731.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;1789, Commander's Cross of the Military Order of Maria Theresa&lt;ref name=&quot;MTO&quot;/&gt;
1793, Grand Cross of the Military order of Maria Theresa&lt;ref name=&quot;MTO&quot; /&gt;
| laterwork     = Imperial and Royal Privy Councilor; Imperial and Royal Chamberlain.
}}
'''Dagobert Sigismund, Count von Wurmser''' (7 May 1724 – 22 August 1797) was an [[Habsburg Monarchy|Austrian]] [[field marshal]] during the [[French Revolutionary Wars]]. Although he fought in the [[Seven Years' War]], the [[War of the Bavarian Succession]], and mounted several successful campaigns in the Rhineland in the initial years of the French Revolutionary Wars, he is probably most remembered for his unsuccessful operations against [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] during the 1796 campaign in Italy.

Although initially in the Army of France during the Seven Years' War, Wurmser left France after Louis reached a peace agreement with Britain, and joined the military of the [[House of Habsburg]]. He later took part in the short-lived [[War of the Bavarian Succession]], also called the so-called ''Kartoffelkrieg'' (Potato War). During the French Revolutionary Wars, Wurmser commanded several imperial Habsburg armies on in the Rhine River valley between 1793 and 1795, and perhaps his most conspicuous achievement was the taking of the [[lines of Lauterburg and Weissenburg]] in October 1793.

In 1796, [[Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor]] sent him to northern Italy, where the Habsburg military defended Austria's southern territories. In a series of well-fought battles with the French army, under the command of the up-and-coming general [[Napoleon Bonaparte]], Wurmser was trapped with his army in [[Siege of Mantua (1796-1797)|Mantua]]; after a negotiated capitulation, Wurmser left the city with his honors and 700 men, and marched back to Vienna. His defeat at Mantua did not diminish the luster of his service in imperial eyes—he was granted another appointment immediately—but he was an old man of 72 years who had spent most of his adult life in arduous campaigning. His health failed him shortly after his appointment and he died in 1797.

== Family and early career ==
Born in [[Strasbourg]], in the [[Kingdom of France|French]] province of [[Alsace]], he was the son of Frantz Jacob Wurmser von Vendenheim. He was christened in the Protestant church of Saint Nicolas and first served in the French Army during the early campaigns of the [[Silesian Wars]] as a cavalry officer under the command of Marshal [[Charles, Prince of Soubise]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wurzbach Wurmser&quot;&gt;{{de icon}} Constant Wurzbach. ''Biographisches Lexikon des Kaiserthums Österreich.'' Vienna, 1856–91, vol 59, p. 1-5.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1747, he was promoted to Captain of Cavalry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pennysworth&quot; &gt;Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge. ''The Penny cyclopædia''. London : C. Knight, 1833–1843. p. 594.&lt;/ref&gt;

He married on 25{{nbsp}}January 1761 in Vendenheim (Département du Bas-Rhin) Sophia Henrietta Rosina Juliana von und zu der Thann. She died aged 39 in Trautenau (Bohemia) on 27{{nbsp}}June 1772 as a consequence of childbirth, and was buried in Michelsdorf (Schlesien).&lt;ref&gt;Protestant Church Book of Sundhouse, and that of Vendenheim&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1750, when his father left Alsace and became a Habsburg subject, Wurmser too left French service and joined the [[House of Habsburg]] military. He brought with him the legions he commanded from France.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pennysworth&quot;/&gt; As part of the imperial Austrian army, he participated in the last years of the continental war, sometimes called the &quot;Little War&quot; because it did not involve three of the five great powers of Europe.{{clarify|date=February 2015}} In these engagements against the Prussians, he showed exceptional command capabilities and a wily and courageous attitude.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wurzbach Wurmser&quot; /&gt; On 30{{nbsp}}January 1761, [[Francis I, Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor Francis I]] raised him to [[comital]] status of the [[Holy Roman Empire|Holy Roman Empire of the German Nation]]. Two years later, Archduke Charles of Lothringen, the Statthalter of Netherlands, known as an audacious partisan collected his volunteers—a regiment each of Infantry and Hussars, with an artillery company—and joined Austrian service.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB Wurmser&quot;&gt;Oscar Criste. [http://de.wikisource.org/w/index.php?title=ADB:Wurmser,_Dagobert_Sigmund_Graf_von&amp;oldid=1036844 Dagobert Sigmund von Wurmser]. ''Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie.''  Herausgegeben von der Historischen Kommission bei der Bayerischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, Band 44 (1898), S. 338–340, Digitale Volltext-Ausgabe in Wikisource. (Version vom 24. März 2010, 13:18 Uhr UTC).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB Wurmser&quot;/&gt;

== War of the Bavarian Succession ==
In Spring 1778, Wurmser's 30th Hussars were posted in northern Bohemia, to cover the Border with Saxony and Silesia. [[Friedrich Joseph, Count of Nauendorf|Friedrich von Nauendorf]], the son of the previous Colonel-Proprietor of the Regiment, was a captain in a village outpost, with about 50 Hussars under his command.  In early July, the Prussian General [[Johann Jakob von Wunsch]] (1717–1788), crossed into Bohemia near the fortified town of [[Náchod]], in the opening action of the [[War of the Bavarian Succession]]. Nauendorf led his 50 Hussars to engage Wunsch's considerably larger force. When they encountered Wunch's force, he greeted them as friends; by the time the Prussians realized the allegiance of the Hussars, Nauendorf and his small force had the upper hand, and Wunsch withdrew. The next day Nauendorf was promoted to major.&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}} Jens-Florian Ebert. &quot;Nauendorf, Friedrich August Graf.&quot; ''Die Österreichischen Generäle 1792–1815''. Accessed 15 October 2009; {{de icon}} Constant von Wurzbach. &quot;Nauendorf, Friedrich August Graf.&quot; ''Biographisches lexikon des kaiserthums Oesterreich, enthaltend die lebensskizzen der denkwürdigen personen, welche seit 1750&amp;nbsp;in den österreichischen kronländern geboren wurden oder darin gelebt und gewirkt haben.'' Wien: K.K. Hof- und staatsdruckerie [etc.] 1856-91, Volume 20, pp. 103–105, p. 103 cited.&lt;/ref&gt; As the war evolved over the summer, Wurmser's Hussars covered the left flank of the main army, which was positioned in the entrenched heights above [[Jaroměř]], in a triple line of [[redoubt]]s extending {{convert|15|km|0|sp=us}} along the river to [[Königgrätz]].&lt;ref&gt;Benians, pp. 703–705. See also [[Fortress Josefov]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In October, [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor]] withdrew most of the [[Imperial Army (Holy Roman Empire)|Imperial army]] to the Bohemian border, under threat of intervention by [[Catherine II of Russia]]; [[Frederick II of Prussia]] did the same. A small force of hussars and dragoons remained in Bohemia to provide a winter cordon, designed to prevent Prussian incursions into Bohemia. Appointed to be commander of the winter cordon, Wurmser ordered a small assault column under command of Colonel Wilhelm Klebeck to attack the village of Dittersbach.&lt;ref&gt;Shortly afterward, Klebeck was elevated to the rank of Baron (Freiherr), and awarded the Knights Cross of the [[Military Order of Maria Theresa]] (15 February 1779). Digby Smith. [http://www.napoleon-series.org/research/biographies/Austria/AustrianGenerals/c_AustrianGeneralsK.html#K37 Klebeck]. Leonard Kudrna and Digby Smith, compilers. ''A biographical dictionary of all Austrian Generals in the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars, 1792–1815''. [http://www.napoleon-series.org Napoleon Series]. Robert Burnham, Editor in Chief. April 2008. Accessed 22 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Klebeck led a column of Croats into the village. During the action, 400 Prussians were killed, another 400 made prisoner, and eight colors were captured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wurzbach Wurmser&quot; /&gt; Following his successes against the Prussians in 1778, Joseph awarded him the Knights Cross of the Military Order of Maria Theresa on 21 October 1778.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith Wurmser&quot; &gt;Digby Smith. ''[http://www.napoleon-series.org/research/biographies/Austria/AustrianGenerals/c_AustrianGeneralsW.html#W59 Dagobert Sigmund von Wurmser].'' Leonard Kurdna and Digby Smith, compilers. ''A biographical dictionary of all Austrian Generals in the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars, 1792–1815''. [http://www.napoleon-series.org Napoleon Series]. Robert Burnham, Editor in Chief. April 2008. Accessed 22 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In another raid, in January 1779, Wurmser advanced into the County of [[Grafschaft Glatz|Glatz]] in five columns, two of which, commanded by Major General [[Franz Joseph, Count Kinsky]], surrounded [[Habelschwerdt]] on 17–18 January. While one column secured the approach, the other, under the leadership of Colonel Pallavicini,&lt;ref&gt;This officer was probably Colonel, later Count, Carlo Pallavicini, of the [[Pallavicini|House of Pallavicini]], who had been in Habsburg service since the latter days of the Seven Years' War. Erik Lund. ''War for the every day: generals, knowledge and warfare in early modern Europe.'' Westport, Ct: Greenwood Press, 1999, ISBN 978-0-313-31041-6, p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; stormed the village, captured the Prince of Hessen-Philippsthal and 700 men, three cannons and seven colors. Wurmser himself led the third column in an assault on the so-called Swedish blockhouse at [[Oberschwedeldorf]];&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB Wurmser&quot;/&gt; it and the village of Habelschwerdt were set on fire by [[howitzer]]s. Major General [[Ludwig, Baron of Terzi]] (1730–1800), who was covering with the remaining two columns, threw back the enemy relief and took 300 Prussian prisoners. Meanwhile, Wurmser maintained his position at the nearby villages of Rückerts and Reinerz. His forward patrols reached the outskirts of Glatz, and were able to cover the Silesian borders, almost reaching [[Schweidnitz]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wurzbach Wurmser&quot;/&gt; Halberschwerdt and Oberschedeldorf were both destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Carlyle]]. ''History of Friedrich II of Prussia called Frederick the great: in eight volumes.'' Vol. VIII in ''The works of Thomas Carlyle in thirty volumes.'' London: Chapman and Hall, 1896–1899, p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

== French Revolutionary Wars ==
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 2em; font-size: 85%; background:#c6dbf7; color:black; width:30em; max-width: 40%;&quot; cellspacing=&quot;5&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | 
'''Promotions'''
*''Transferred from French service to Austrian military in 1763''
*Major General: 1763
*Lt. Field Marshal: 10 October 1778 (effective 10 January 1768)
*General of Cavalry: 8 September 1787 (effective 2 September 1787)
*Field Marshal 11 December 1795
|}
In 1787, Wurmser received a promotion to [[General of the Cavalry (Austria)|General der Kavallerie]]; he held a series of posts in Vienna, Bohemia and [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Galicia]], becoming Commanding General at the latter in 1787 during the [[Austro–Turkish War (1787–1791)|Austrian War with the Ottoman Empire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wurzbach Wurmser&quot; /&gt; While Wurmser fought Austria's battles in the Balkans, in France, a coalition of the clergy and the professional and bourgeoisie class—the [[Estates General (France)|First]] and [[Estates General (France)|Third]] estates—led a call for reform of the French government and the creation of a written constitution. Initially, the rulers of Europe viewed the [[French Revolution]] as an event between the French king and his subjects, and not something in which they should interfere. In 1790, [[Leopold II, Holy Roman Emperor|Leopold]] succeeded his brother Joseph as emperor and by 1791, he considered the situation surrounding his sister, [[Marie Antoinette]], and her children, with greater alarm. In August 1791, in consultation with French ''émigré'' nobles and [[Frederick William II of Prussia]], he issued the [[Declaration of Pillnitz]], in which they declared the interest of the monarchs of Europe as one with the interests of Louis and his family. They threatened ambiguous, but quite serious, consequences if anything should happen to the royal family. The French émigrés continued to agitate for support of a counter-revolution. On 20 April 1792, the [[French National Convention]] declared war on Austria. In the [[War of the First Coalition]] (1792–1797), France opposed most of the European states sharing land or water borders with her, plus Portugal and the Ottoman Empire.&lt;ref&gt;Timothy Blanning. ''The French Revolutionary Wars''. New York: Oxford University Press, 1996, ISBN 0-340-56911-5, pp. 41–59.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Rhine campaign 1793–1794 ===
From February 1793 to January 1794, Wurmser commanded the [[Imperial Army (Holy Roman Empire)|Imperial Army]] of the Rhine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith Wurmser&quot;/&gt; He commanded the successful storming of the Lauterburg and Weissenburg lines on 13 October 1793. The Lines, a series of earth works on the south side of the Lauter river, a tributary of the Rhine river in Alsace-Lorraine, offered a major strategic defensive position for the French.

Part of France's Army of the Vosges, under general command of [[Jean Victor Moreau]], manned the French position. The three battalions and six squadrons, commanded by General of Brigade Illier, held the position with ten artillery pieces. The French defensive line ran west from [[Lauterbourg]] on the  Rhine to [[Saarbrücken]]. The western part of this line, from Lauterbourg to Wissembourg, was protected by the Lines of Wissembourg, a series of fortifications  built nearly a century earlier to protect Alsace from invasion along the flat plain between the Vosges and the Rhine. The Army of the Rhine defended these Lines. The Army of the Rhine also was at Saarbrücken and the Corps of the Vosges linked the two, with camps at Hornbach and Kettrick.

On 20 August, Wurmser directed the 4th Allied Column, and Field Marshal Kavanagh's Hessen and Austrian troops, augmented by a battalion of Emigre troops, to assault part of the works; Kavanagh's attack successfully ousted the French from the position; General Illier was killed by a Hessen Jäger. An unknown number of the 3,000 French defenders were killed or wounded; three officers and 100 men were captured. The testing for the Weissembourg Lines continued for the next 45 days, Each skirmish, each probe, tested the French strength and resolve. In mid-September the Prussians successfully defeated a French assault on [[Pirmasens]], a small fortification to the north and east; this success encouraged the Austrian and Prussian alliance to venture a major assault on the French defenses.&lt;ref&gt;Smith states there were skirmishes and clashes on 21 and 27 August, 7, 11, 12, 14, 19, 20, 23, and 30 September, culminating in the major assault on 13 October. Digby Smith. ''Napoleonic Wars Data Book.'' Mechanicsburg, PA: Stackpole, 1998, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float: right; margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 2em; font-size: 85%; background:#c6dbf7; color:black; width:30em; max-width: 40%;&quot; cellspacing=&quot;5&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | 
'''Field Armies Commanded by Wurmser'''&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith Wurmser&quot;/&gt;
*Army of the Rhine February 1793–January 1793
*Army of the Upper Rhine, August 1795–June 1796
*Army of Italy, June 1796–September 1796
*Commanding General, Galicia, September 1796 – 1797
|}
Wurmser's force of 33,599 infantry and 9,635 cavalry had whittled away at the Lines, skirmishing throughout August and September with French infantry and cavalry, which always withdrew to the superior defensive position behind the earthen works. While the Prussians marched around the lines, from Pirmasens, Wurmser organized his force into seven columns, and they assaulted the Lines in waves. In the [[First Battle of Wissembourg (1793)|First Battle of Wissembourg]] on 13 September the French defenses were successfully breached.&lt;ref&gt;J. Rickard, J (9 February 2009) [http://www.historyofwar.org/articles/storm_lines_wissembourg.html Storming of the lines of Wissembourg, 13 October 1793]''. [http://www.historyofwar.org/about.html History of War]. Peter D Antill, Tristan Dugdale-Pointon, and John Rickard, editors. 9 February 2009. Accessed 23 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Two months later, the French committed major forces to recover the Lines. Wurmser commanded the Austrian contingent at the defeat at the [[Second Battle of Wissembourg (1793)|Second Battle of Wissembourg]] on 26 December 1793.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith Wurmser&quot;/&gt;

===Upper Rhine campaign===
From August 1795 to June 1796, Wurmser commanded the Army of the Upper Rhine.

===Battle of Mannheim===

==Campaign in northern Italy==
[[File:Tramonto su Brescia (Foto Luca Giarelli).jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|alt=The sun, low on the horizon, bathes a small city in light; the light casts deep shadows on tiled roofs, church towers, gardens and walls.|Klenau approached the town of Brescia at night, surprising the garrison, and taking as his prisoners three officials of the [[French Directory]]. Photo courtesy of Luca Giarelli. &lt;!-- (CC-BY-SA 3.0) --&gt;]]
In 1796, Wurmser descended into northern Italy, with 25,000 men from his old Army of the Rhine, to unite with Beaulieu's battered army of northern Italy. The two armies met at Trent, and marched to Mantua in three columns.&lt;ref name=&quot;McLynn&quot; &gt;Frank McLynn. ''Napoleon: A Biography.'' New York: Arcade, 2002, ISBN 978-1-55970-631-5, pp 121–123.&lt;/ref&gt;

Wurmser's columns scored some initial successes. The forward column, under command of under [[Peter Quasdanovich]] moved toward Lake Garda,&lt;ref name=&quot;McLynn&quot; /&gt; and a small reconnaissance force under [[Johann von Klenau]] advanced from the alps on the city of [[Brescia]]; there, they found the local French garrison unprepared. At midnight, Klenau led two squadrons of the ''Wurmser'' 8th Hussar Regiment and several other battalions and squadrons in an attack on the French garrison. They captured 600–700 French soldiers stationed there and three officials of the French Directory: [[Jean Lannes]], [[Joachim Murat]], and [[François Étienne de Kellermann]].&lt;ref&gt;Martin Boycott-Brown. ''The Road to Rivoli''. London: Cassell &amp; Co., 2001. ISBN 0-304-35305-1, p. 382; Smith, Battles of &quot;Lonato&quot; and &quot;Castiglione delle Stiviere,&quot;  p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; Quasdanovich managed to occupy Lonato.&lt;ref name=&quot;McLynn&quot; /&gt;

Wurmser did not count on swift movement by the French.  Within two days, Klenau's force retreated in the face of [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon Bonaparte]] and 12,000 Frenchmen; his small advance guard was quickly pushed out of Brescia on 1 August. At the subsequent [[Battle of Lonato]] of 2–3 August 1796, the French also forced Quasdanovich's column to withdraw into the mountains, with heavy losses.&lt;ref&gt;Kudrna and Smith. [http://www.napoleon-series.org/research/biographies/Austria/AustrianGenerals/c_AustrianGeneralsK.html#K45 &quot;Klenau&quot;.]&lt;/ref&gt; The mopping up operations lasted until mid-August, isolated Quasdanovich's force by [[Lake Garda]], and freed the French to concentrate on Wurmser's main force at [[Castiglione delle Stiviere]], further south; Bonaparte's subsequent victory against Wurmser at the [[Battle of Castiglione]] forced the old commander across the [[Mincio]] river and allowed the French to return to the [[Siege of Mantua (1796–1797)|siege of Mantua]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Battles of &quot;Lonato&quot; and &quot;Castiglione delle Stiviere,&quot; ''Data Book.'' p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt;

The resumed siege was not without its problems. To move swiftly against Wurmser, Napoleon had abandoned his all his siege equipment, leaving it at Mantua. When he resumed the siege, it was much less effective without his guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;McLynn&quot; /&gt; Furthermore, by early September, many of the scattered Austrian units had rejoined Wurmser's column. Even so, at the [[Battle of Bassano]] on 8 September, the Austrians were outnumbered almost two to one by the French.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith Wurmser&quot;/&gt; As the Austrian army retreated, Bonaparte ordered a pursuit that caused the Austrians to abandon their artillery and baggage. Most of the third battalion of the 59th ''Jordis'', and the first battalion of the Border Infantry Banat were captured and these units ceased to exist after this battle. The Austrians lost 600 killed and wounded, and 2,000 captured, plus lost 30 guns, eight colors, and 200 [[limbers]] and ammunition wagons.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, &quot;Bassano,&quot; ''Data Book.'' p. 123.&lt;/ref&gt; Wurmser's column fought its way to besieged [[Mantua]], but emerged suddenly, in an effort to escape, at the Battle of [[La Favorita]] near there on 15 September. This was the second attempt to relieve the fortress; as the Austrians withdrew from the battle, they retreated into Mantua itself, and from 15 September until 2 February 1797, Wurmser was trapped inside the fortress while the city was besieged.&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}} [http://de.wikisource.org/w/index.php?Attitle=ADB:Klenau,_Johann_Graf&amp;oldid=876203 Klenau] (''ADB'').&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the Austrian loss at the [[Battle of Rivoli]], {{convert|48|km|0|sp=us}} north of Mantua, on 14–15 January 1797,&lt;ref&gt;At the [[Battle of Rivoli]], 22,000 French overwhelmed 28,000 Austrians; the Austrians lost 4,000 killed or wounded, and 8,000 prisoners, including 11 colors and standards. Three Austrian units (i.e., two battalions of the Nr. 14 ''Klebek'' and a battalion of the Jägerkorps ''Kurz'') were captured in their entirety. Smith, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; when clearly there would be no Austrian relief for Mantua, Wurmser sent one of his juniors, Johann von Klenau, to negotiate conditions of surrender with French General [[Jean-Mathieu-Philibert Sérurier|Jean Sérurier]],&lt;ref&gt;Boycott-Brown, p. 521.&lt;/ref&gt; Additional evidence suggests that Bonaparte was present and dictated far more generous terms than the Austrians had expected. Wurmser, who Napoleon held in high esteem, left Mantua with his men and officers, and his battle honors, and marched back to Austrian lands.&lt;ref&gt;John Ashton. ''English caricature and satire on Napoleon I''. London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1888, p. 39. Kudrna and Smith. [http://www.napoleon-series.org/research/biographies/Austria/AustrianGenerals/c_AustrianGeneralsK.html#K45 &quot;Klenau&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Of all the field marshals in Habsburg service during the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars, Wurmser was recognized among the best. Some historians attribute Austrian problems to its aging general staff, compared to the relatively young general staff of the French Empire. For instance, Wurmser was 72, approaching 73 in the 1796 campaign, and [[Peter Vitus von Quasdanovich]] (b. 1738) was nearing 70. Besides the graying general staff, there were also youngsters, and these demonstrated acute military acumen: [[Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen|Archduke Charles]] was 26 years old in the 1796 campaign and had been tutored by Hohenlohe-Kirchberg and Wurmser; Schwarzenberg was also young, under 30; [[Johann von Klenau]], at 31, was the youngest field Marshal in the Habsburg military; and there were many others. But Wurmser may have been hampered more by the [[Aulic Council]] than by his age; Digby Smith points out that he descended into Italy fettered with a new and inexperienced chief of staff sent to him by the Council with battle plans and instructions in writing. These restricted his movements in Italy and prevented him from responding to targets of opportunity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith Wurmser&quot;/&gt;

Broken in health, a ''knight without fear and above reproach'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Wurzbach Wurmser&quot; /&gt; Wurmser died in Vienna the following summer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith Wurmser&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Joseph Alvinczy]]
*[[Peter Quasdanovich]]
*[[Paul Davidovich]]

==Sources==

===Citations and notes===
{{reflist|30em}}

===References===
* Ashton, John. ''English caricature and satire on Napoleon I. ''London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1888.
* Boycott-Brown, Martin. ''The Road to Rivoli.'' London: Cassell &amp;  Co., 2001. ISBN 0-304-35305-1
*[[Thomas Carlyle|Carlyle, Thomas]]. ''History of Friedrich II of Prussia called Frederick the great : in eight volumes.'' Vol. VIII in ''The works of Thomas Carlyle in thirty volumes.'' London: Chapman and Hall, 1896–1899.
* {{de icon}} Criste, Oscar. '''[http://de.wikisource.org/w/index.php?title=ADB:Wurmser,_Dagobert_Sigmund_Graf_von&amp;oldid=1036844 Dagobert Sigmund von Wurmser].''' ''Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie.''  Herausgegeben von der Historischen Kommission bei der Bayerischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, Band 44 (1898), S. 338–340, Digitale Volltext-Ausgabe in Wikisource. (Version vom 24. März 2010, 13:18 Uhr UTC).
* {{de icon}} Ebert, Jens-Florian. &quot;Nauendorf, Friedrich August Graf.&quot; ''Die Österreichischen Generäle 1792–1815''. Accessed 15 October 2009.
* {{de icon}} Hirtenfeld, Jaromir. ''Der militär-Maria-Theresien-Orden und seine Mitglieder: nach authentischen Quellen bearbeitet.'' Wien: Hofdruckerei, 1857.
* McLynn, Frank. ''Napoleon: A Biography.'' New York: Arcade, 2002, ISBN 978-1-55970-631-5.
* Rickard, J. ''[http://www.historyofwar.org/articles/storm_lines_wissembourg.html Storming of the lines of Wissembourg, 13 October 1793]''. In '''[http://www.historyofwar.org/about.html History of War]'''. Peter D Antill, Tristan Dugdale-Pointon, and John Rickard, editors. 9 February 2009. Accessed 23 March 2010.
* [[Digby Smith|Smith, Digby]]. [http://www.napoleon-series.org/research/biographies/Austria/AustrianGenerals/c_AustrianGeneralsK.html#K37 Klebeck]. Leonard Kudrna and Dibgy Smith, compilers. ''A biographical dictionary of all Austrian Generals in the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars, 1792–1815''. [http://www.napoleon-series.org Napoleon Series]. Robert Burnham, Editor in Chief. April 2008. Accessed 22 March 2010.
* {{de icon}} Wurzbach, C., von. ''Biographisches Lexikon des Kaiserthums Österreich.'' Vienna, 1856–91, vol 20, 59.

== External links ==
* [[:de:Husaren-Regiment „von Tersztyánszky“ Nr. 8|German Wikipedia Husaren-Regiment von Tersztyánszky Nr. 8]]
{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{s-bef|before= Karl von Nauendorf}}
{{s-ttl|title= [[Inhaber|Proprietor (Inhaber)]]&lt;br&gt;Hussar Regiment No. 30 (formerly No.8)| years=1775–1797}} 
{{s-aft|after= [[Friedrich Joseph, Count of Nauendorf]]}}
{{end}}
{{French Revolution navbox}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wurmser, Dagobert Sigmund Von}}
[[Category:1724 births]]
[[Category:1797 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Strasbourg]]
[[Category:Alsatian nobility]]
[[Category:Counts of Austria]]
[[Category:Austrian people of French descent]]
[[Category:Field marshals of Austria]]
[[Category:18th-century Austrian people]]
[[Category:18th-century French people]]
[[Category:Austrian Empire military leaders of the French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:Austrian military personnel by war]]
[[Category:Military leaders of the French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:Austrian generals]]
[[Category:Austrian soldiers]]
[[Category:Imperial generals of the Holy Roman Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>b7eeal9krijp8k4vt2nbplj4ot5wgda</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
