<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dana Olden Baldwin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>51875762</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751241105</id>
      <parentid>747847929</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-24T08:06:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WereSpielChequers</username>
        <id>4071608</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], replaced: a a  →  a using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11087">{{Orphan|date=October 2016}}

{{Infobox person | name =Dana Olden Baldwin|  birth_name = | birth_date = March 20th, 1881| birth_place = [[Belvoir, North Carolina]] | death_date = {{Death date and age|1972|11|09|1881|03|20}} | death_place = [[Martinsville, Virginia]]| death_cause = stroke| resting_place = Baldwin Family Cemetery, Apex Wake County, [[North Carolina]], [[United States|USA]] | resting_place_coordinates = | residence = | nationality = | other_names = | known_for = | education = [[Leonard Medical School]] (1910) | employer = | occupation = physician | title = [[File:US-O2 insignia.svg|15px]] [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]]  | salary = | networth = | height = | weight = | term = | predecessor = | successor = | party = | boards = | religion =  | spouse = Vina A. Flood| partner = | children = Mae and Rosa (adopted)&lt;br&gt; three boys and one girl (foster) | parents = Reverend Jay Halsey Baldwin&lt;br&gt;Mary Crutchfield Baldwin | relatives = Jerry Baldwin (paternal grandfather)&lt;br&gt;Margaret Crutchfield (maternal grandmother) | signature = | website = | footnotes = }}

'''Dana Olden Baldwin''', [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]] (March 20, 1881&amp;ndash; November 9, 1972) was a prominent African- American physician situated in Martinsville, Virginia.  He participated in [[World War I]] as a medical officer until he was honorably discharged in 1918.  He is well known for prospering an independent African-American economy by his formation of the Baldwin Business Center, St. Mary's Hospital, and Sandy Beach Resort.  The institutions were meant to go over the restrictions placed upon African-Americans by [[Jim Crow laws]], preventing entry to white establishments. [[The Baldwin Memorial Park]] was formed in his honor.

==Early life==
Baldwin was born on March 20, 1881, in [[Belvoir, North Carolina]], and was the oldest child of Reverend Jay Halsey and Mary Crutchfield Baldwin.  His father was a Methodist priest.  Baldwin's paternal grandfather, Jerry Baldwin, and maternal grandmother, Margaret Crutchfield, were both slaves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Caldwell |first1=Arthur Bunyan |last2= |first2= |date=1917 |title=History of the American Negro and his institutions; (Volume 5) |location=Atlanta, Georgia |publisher=A. B. Caldwell Publishing Co. |pages=289–290|isbn=978-1149335567}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Baldwin worked as a farm worker from a very young age and displayed his intelligence by graduating from the Apex Normal and Industrial Institute at the age of 16 in 1897.  Soon after, Baldwin moved to attend [[Shaw University]] in [[Raleigh]], North Carolina.

After college, Baldwin performed a number of jobs, including working as a waiter and teacher in public schools.  Already at a young age, Baldwin was exhibiting his desire to provide for the community.  At the advice of his mother, who'd believed in Baldwin's potential, the young man attended [[Leonard Medical School]] (part of Shaw University) and graduated in 1910 at the age of 29.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Buckley |first1=Joann H. |last2=Fisher |first2=W. Douglas |date=2016 |title=African American Doctors of World War I: The Lives of 104 Volunteers |location=Jefferson |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. |pages=22–23|isbn=9781476663159}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Baldwin soon moved to [[Martinsville, Virginia]], a city situated along the southern border of the state.  He was responsible for opening the very first African-American practice in the city, which was situated in [[Henry County, Virginia|Henry County]].&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Rz4KAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA1726&amp;lpg=PA1726&amp;dq=Dana+Olden+Baldwin&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ExpvyAQwNo&amp;sig=WT0jhF6romXOaB0diRtfa2caNhw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi755j1oMTPAhVF0YMKHd8yAwU4ChDoAQgpMAM#v=onepage&amp;q=Dana%20Olden%20Baldwin&amp;f=false|title=Journal of the American Medical Association, Volume 70|date=1 June 1918|publisher=American Medical Association.|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He had a relative, possibly one of his brothers, who lived nearby in the Roanoke County of Virginia.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;  The years before the war, Baldwin found it difficult to maintain his practice, but found that it grew more each year by the growing African-American population.  Baldwin married a woman named Vina in 1911. They were situated on Fayette Street, the heart of Martinsville's African American American business district.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aahistoricsitesva.org/items/show/32?tour=16&amp;index=1|title=Baldwin Block (including the Dr. Dana O. Baldwin Memorial Park)|date=|publisher=Virginia Foundation for the Humanities|via=Afircan American Historical Sites Database}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At the start of World War I, Baldwin was 36 years old and immediately he volunteered.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Buckley |first1=Joann H. |last2=Fisher |first2=W. Douglas |date=2016 |title=African American Doctors of World War I: The Lives of 104 Volunteers |location=Jefferson |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. |pages=22–23 |isbn=9781476663159}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military Service==
Upon entry into the military, Baldwin was commissioned to the [[Medical Reserve Corps]], and, like many of his peers, he was sent for basic training at [[Fort Des Moines Provisional Army Officer Training School]].  He was given the rank of [[First Lieutenant]].  Fort Des Moines had been opened for training African-American men as there had been a huge influx of African-American volunteers and a petition was erected by the students of Howard University.  However, there was still some discontent at the facility as many soldiers found that he had been unfairly assessed for merely being black.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Barbeau |first1=Arthur E. |last2=Henri |first2=Florettte |date=1996 |title=The Unknown Soldiers: African American Troops in World War I |location=New York |publisher=Da Capo Press |pages=60–61 |isbn=0-306-80694-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This or discontent with his superior might have been a factor in Baldwin submitting his resignation from the 368th Ambulance Company of the 92nd Division, 317 Sanitary Train post he had been assigned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Reports, Documents, and Journals of the U.S. Senate and House of Representatives.|first1= |last2= |first2=|date=1918 |title=Congressional Serial Set : Noncombatant Commissioned Officers of the Army |location=Washington D.C. |publisher=U.S. Government Printing Office |pages=114|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Once he arrived in [[France]], Baldwin had the main responsibility of handling sanitation concerns, surgery duties and hospital illnesses.  Much of the [[92nd Infantry Division (United States)|92nd Infantry Division]] was involved with trench warfare and were aiding the French in pushing back the German forces, who sent a large number of gas attacks into the field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Buckley |first1=Joann H. |last2=Fisher |first2=W. Douglas |date=2016 |title=African American Doctors of World War I: The Lives of 104 Volunteers |location=Jefferson |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. |pages=20–21|isbn=9781476663159}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, Baldwin found himself mostly concerned with the breakout of [[influenza]] which came in September 1918.  A large portion of the Baldwin's patients mostly consisted of illness.  The war came to a close in 1919 and Baldwin was honorably discharged on April 2.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto1&quot;/&gt;

==Career==
Bailey returned to [[Martinsville, Virginia|Martinsville]], and resumed working in his practice.  It was after his military service that Baldwin really began to put an active effort in improving the conditions of the African-American Community.  In the Virginia edition of The History of the American Negro&quot;, Dr. Baldwin stated that in order for the African American community to prosper, people should start &quot;by advocating and working for better schools, better churches... by seeing to it that children are instructed in civic duty in the schools and taught the importance and power of the ballot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Caldwell |first1=Arthur Bunyan |last2= |first2= |date=1917 |title=History of the American Negro and his institutions; (Volume 5) |location=Atlanta, Georgia |publisher=A. B. Caldwell Publishing Co. |pages=289 |isbn=978-1149335567}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the white hospitals in the area had barred entrance or denied rights for African-Americans.  In 1929, Dr, Baldwin opened a 27-bed facility meant to house the poor African-American population unable to afford or enter other hospitals.  It was named St. Mary's, for his mother who had encouraged him down the road to medicine.  He coordinated with a younger brother who'd owned his pwn pharmacy.  The area was designated &quot;Baldwin Block&quot;.  Baldwin opened a number of other business in the majority of the 1920s and 1930s, including the Sandy Beach Resort, Baldwin Miniature Golf Course, Baldwin's Gymntorium and Baldwin Business Center.  All these facilities were opened to the African American community as the many white institutions were barred because of the Jim Crow laws.

Dr.Baldwin was also a heavy contributor for a number of churches and societies, including AMR Church, the Masons, Old Fellows, [[Magic City Medical Society]] and [[The National Medical Association]].
Dr. Baldwin was given media attention after treating a African American man for a broken leg and forced the police department to pay his bill regarding the injury.  Baldwin continued his practice for 60 years and never retired.

==Death and legacy==
Dr. Baldwin died of a [[stroke]] on November 9, 1972.  He was buried in [[Wake County]], North Carolina in the Baldwin Burial site, where a number of his family are also buried.

Dr. Baldwin was well remembered in the Martinsville community as being selfless and working with all his might to provide a brighter future for his brethren.  [[The Virginia Foundation for the Humanities]] erected [[the Dr. Dana O. Baldwin Memorial Park]] situated in Baldwin Block.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aahistoricsitesva.org/items/show/32?tour=16&amp;index=1|title=Baldwin Block (including the Dr. Dana O. Baldwin Memorial Park) - African American Historic Sites Database|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  There are also a number of streets in the area named after him.  St. Mary's stayed open until 1952 and was memorialized in an exhibit made by the Virginia Foundation for the Humanities.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto2&quot;/&gt;

==Personal life==
On December 24, 1911, Baldwin married Vina S. Flood, daughter of L. F. and Elizabeth Flood.  Vina had been educated in Hatshorn College and was a teacher in a number of local public schools.  The couple did not have children of their own.  However, they adopted two girls: Mae and Rosa Baldwin.  The couple also raised another three boys and one girl as foster children.

==References==
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bailey, Everett Russell}}
[[Category:1972 deaths]]
[[Category:1881 births]]
[[Category:African-American military personnel]]
[[Category:African-American physicians]]
[[Category:American homeopaths]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:American military physicians]]
[[Category:Shaw University alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>955kngelr6iond4kp0wntkas7gjfaex</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
