<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dover Strait coastal guns, 1940–1944</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14530176</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745352990</id>
      <parentid>745352884</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T16:53:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith-264</username>
        <id>925588</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* German guns */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23258">{{EngvarB|date=October 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military installation
| name = Dover Strait coastal guns
| ensign =
| native_name =
| partof = British coast defences/[[Atlantic Wall|''Atlantikwall'']]
| location = [[English Channel]]
| nearest_town = Dover/Calais
| country = Britain/occupied France
| image = [[File:Strait of Dover map.png|300px]]
| caption = Strait of Dover 
|coordinates = {{coord|51|00|00|N|01|27|00|E|display=title}}
| ownership = &lt;!-- government department such as the MoD or the United States DoD --&gt;
| operator = Dover Command/''[[Kriegsmarine]]''
| controlledby = British Army/German Navy
| open_to_public = &lt;!-- for out of use sites/sites with museums etc --&gt;
| built = {{Start date|1940}}
| used = {{End date|1944}}
| builder = British civilian contractors/[[Organisation Todt]]
| materials = Steel-reinforced concrete
| fate = Defunct
| condition = Museum pieces or demolished
| battles = Channel convoys&lt;br /&gt;[[Channel Dash]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Operation Undergo]]
| events = [[Battle of Britain]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Normandy landings]]
| current_commander = &lt;!-- current commander --&gt;
| past_commanders = &lt;!-- past notable commander(s) --&gt;
| garrison = &lt;!-- such as the 25th Bombardment Group --&gt;
| occupants = &lt;!-- squadrons only --&gt;
| website =
| footnotes = &lt;!-- catchall in case it's needed to preserve something in infobox that doesn't work in new code --&gt;
}}
The '''Dover Strait coastal guns''' were British and German long-range [[coastal artillery]] pieces, on the [[English Channel]] coasts of [[Kent]], England and the [[Pas-de-Calais]], occupied France. The [[Strait of Dover]] is the narrowest channel between England and [[continental Europe]]. During the [[World War II|Second World War]], both sides used their guns to bombard shipping in the Channel as well as coastal towns and military installations.

==History==

The [[Battle of France]] in May and June 1940 placed [[Calais]] and vicinity under the control of an enemy of Britain for the first time since the end of the [[Napoleonic Wars]], 125 years earlier. On 21 May 1940, [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] discussed the possibility of invasion with ''Großadmiral'' (Grand Admiral) [[Erich Raeder]], the Commander-in-Chief of the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' (German Navy) and on 25 June surprised ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'' (''OKW'', supreme command of the armed forces), by ordering the preparation studies and appreciations for an invasion of Britain, which were ready on 2 July. 

In an OKW directive on 10 July, the purpose of the guns was to

{{quote|All preparations are to be made to provide strong frontal and flank artillery protection for the transportation and landing of troops in case of a possible crossing from the coastal strip Calais–Cape Gris Nez–Boulogne.|Keitel{{sfn|CARL|2008|pp=106–107}}}}

under the control of the ''Kriegsmarine''.

Hitler issued [[List of Adolf Hitler's directives|Fuhrer Directive 16]] on 16 July for an invasion as [[Operation Sealion|''Unternehmen Seelöwe'']] (Operation Sea Lion), in which, 

{{quote|Strong forces of coastal artillery must command and protect the forward coastal area.|Hitler 16 July 1940{{sfn|CARL|2008|p=108}}}} 

''[[Organisation Todt]]'' began work on positions capable of withstanding the heaviest bombing for every heavy artillery piece available, primarily at [[Pas-de-Calais]], commenced on 22 July 1940.{{sfn|CARL|2008|p=109}}

===German guns===
The first such guns began to be installed around the end of July 1940. First came [[Todt Battery|''Siegfried'' Battery]] at [[Audinghen]], south of [[Cap Gris Nez]], with one [[38 cm SK C/34 naval gun]] (15-inch) gun (later increased to 4 and renamed [[Fritz Todt|''Todt'']] Battery), shortly followed by:
* Three {{convert|30.5|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns at ''Friedrich August'' Battery, to the north of [[Boulogne-sur-Mer]]
* Four {{convert|28|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns at ''[[Grosser Kurfürst]]'' Battery at [[Cap Gris Nez]]
* Two {{convert|21|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns at [[Prince Henry of Prussia (1862–1929)|''Prinz Heinrich'']] Battery just outside [[Calais]]
* Two {{convert|21|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns at ''[[Battery Oldenburg|''Oldenburg'' Battery]] in Calais
* Three [[40.6 cm SK C/34 gun|40.6 cm SK C/34]] (16-inch) guns (from among the so-called [[Adolf Gun#Gun sites in France|''Adolf'' Guns]]) at ''Lindemann'' Battery between Calais and [[Cap Blanc Nez]]. The battery was named after the fallen commander of the battleship [[German battleship Bismarck|''Bismarck'']].

By early August, ''Siegfried'' Battery and ''Grosser Kurfürst'' Battery were fully operational as were all of the Army’s [[railway gun]]s. Seven of the railway guns, six {{convert|28|cm|in|abbr=on}} [[Krupp K5|K5]] guns and a single {{convert|21|cm|in|abbr=on}} [[21 cm K 12 (E)|K12]] gun with a range of {{convert|115|km|mi|abbr=on}}, could only be used against land targets. The remainder, thirteen {{convert|28|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns and five {{convert|24|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns, plus additional motorised batteries comprising twelve {{convert|24|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns and ten {{convert|21|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns, could be fired at shipping but were of limited effectiveness due to their slow traverse speed, long loading time and ammunition types. Land-based guns have always been feared by navies because they are on a stationary platform and are thus more accurate (and can be larger, with more ammunition stowage) than those on board ship. Super-heavy railway guns can only be traversed by moving the entire gun and its carriage along a curved track, or by building a special cross track or turntable. This, combined with their slow rate of fire (measured in rounds per hour or even rounds per day), makes it difficult for them to hit moving targets. Another problem with super-heavy guns is that their barrels (which are difficult to make and expensive to replace) wear out relatively quickly, so they could not be fired often.

Better suited for use against naval targets were the four heavy naval batteries installed by mid-September: ''Friedrich August'', ''Prinz Heinrich'',  ''[[Battery Oldenburg|Oldenburg]]'' and ''Siegfried'' (later renamed ''Todt'') – a total of eleven guns, with the firepower of a [[battlecruiser]]. Fire control for these guns was provided by both spotter aircraft and by DeTeGerät [[radar]] sets installed at Blanc Nez and Cap d’Alprech. These units were capable of detecting targets out to a range of {{convert|40|km|mi|abbr=on}}, including small British patrol craft near the English coast. Two additional radar sites were added by mid-September: a DeTeGerät at Cap de la Hague and a FernDeTeGerät long-range radar at Cap d’Antifer near [[Le Havre]].{{sfn|Schenk|1990|pp=324–325}}

Perhaps the most remarkable gun was the {{convert|21|cm|in|abbr=on}} ''Kanone'' 12 ''in Eisenbahnlafette'', which had an effective range of {{convert|45|km|mi|abbr=on}}. Designed as a successor to the World War I [[Paris gun]], it is claimed to have had a maximum range of {{convert|115|km|mi|abbr=on}}. Shell fragments from the gun were found near [[Chatham, Kent]], {{convert|88|km|mi|abbr=on}} from the nearest point on the French coast. There were two of these guns, operated by ''Artillerie-Batterie'' 701 (E) and they remained on the Channel Coast for the rest of the war.

The guns started shelling the [[Dover]] area during the second week of August 1940 and continued firing until 1944. Over a thousand rounds were fired but the German coast batteries only sank:
* [http://www.wrecksite.eu/wreck.aspx?4747 ''Sambut''], 7,219 BRT, 6 June 1944
* ''Empire Lough'', 2,824 BRT, 24 June 1944{{sfn|Sakkers|Machielse|2013|p=}}
''Empire Lough'' was one of 21 coastal vessels in the convoy ETC-17, escorted by the frigate {{HMS|Dakins|K550|6}} and corvette {{HMS|Sunflower|K41|6}}. On 24 June 1944, the convoy left Southend en route to the Seine Bay when the ships were engaged by German long-range coastal artillery guns off Dover. ''Empire Lough'' was set on fire and declared a total loss after she was beached near Folkestone. The master Robert Robinson and one crew member were lost. The freighter ''Gurden Gates'' (1,791 grt, built 1943) was damaged in the same action.

===Dover===
[[File:Winnie 14 inch gun St Margaret March 1941 IWM H 7918.jpg|thumb|{{center|&quot;Winnie&quot;, a [[BL 14 inch Mk VII naval gun|14-inch gun]] at [[St Margaret's at Cliffe]] near Dover, March 1941}}]]
Having withdrawn in the [[Dunkirk evacuation]] and winning the [[Battle of Britain]], the British did not have an immediate answer to this threat but  the high ground to either side of the [[Port of Dover]] was fortified on the personal order of [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] (who had visited to see the situation in person) and  large calibre guns dug in there. The only British cross-Channel guns already in place were ''Winnie'' (named after Churchill) and – later in 1940 – ''Pooh'' (named after the story book character [[Winnie the Pooh]] who in turn was named after &quot;Winnipeg&quot; the bear at the London Zoo.).{{sfn|Evans|2004|p=59}} These were two [[BL 14 inch Mk VII naval gun|BL 14 inch Mk VII (35.6&amp;nbsp;cm) guns]] positioned behind [[St. Margarets Bay, Kent|St Margaret's]]. They were spares taken from the stock of guns of the battleship {{HMS|King George V|41|6}}. One used a mounting from {{HMS|Furious|47|6}} and the other a mounting from a test range; neither was turret-mounted. They were operated from a separate firing-control room and were manned by 25 men of the [[Royal Marine]] Siege Regiment. These boosted morale – ''Winnie'' fired Britain's first shell onto continental Europe in August 1940 – but were slow and ineffectual compared to the German guns. They conducted extreme range counter-battery operations against the German guns (though they were too inaccurate and slow to fire on ships) and  were protected from German aerial attack by anti-aircraft emplacements. Their separate and well-camouflaged cordite and shell magazines were buried under deep layers of earth and connected to the guns by railway lines.

Due to these guns' lack of success in targeting shipping, Churchill ordered three new heavy gun batteries to be built in Dover and manned by the [[Royal Artillery]] for that purpose:
* Three [[BL 6-inch Mk VII naval gun|BL 6 inch (152mm) Mk VII guns]] with a range of {{convert|25000|yd|m|abbr=on}}, at ''Fan Bay Battery''
* Four [[BL 9.2 inch gun Mk IX - X|BL 9.2 inch (234mm) Mks IX–X guns]] with a range of {{convert|31000|yd|m|abbr=on}} at ''[[South Foreland]] Battery''
* Two [[BL 15 inch /42 naval gun|BL 15 inch (381mm) Mk I guns]] with a range of {{convert|42000|yd|m|abbr=on}} at ''Wanstone Battery'', known as ''Clem'' (after [[Clementine Churchill]]) and ''Jane'' (after [[Jane (comic strip)|the pin-up]]).

[[File:Pooh 14 inch gun St Margaret 1941 IWM H 7922.jpg|thumb|left|{{center|&quot;Pooh&quot; in March 1941}}]]
The guns were later joined by [[Lydden Spout Battery]]. Also, three [[BL 13.5 inch Mk V naval gun|BL Mk V]] (34-cm) naval guns  from the [[First World War]] (named ''Gladiator'', ''Scene Shifter'' and ''Piece Maker''[sic]) were brought out of retirement in 1939 and mounted on railway chassis.{{sfn|Clarke|2005|pp=41–42}}{{sfn|BGD|2015|nopp=y}}

The British coast batteries sank:
* ''Pentiver'', 2,382 BRT, 2 March 1943
* ''Livadia'' 3,094 BRT, 4 October1943
* ''Munsterland'' 6,315 BRT, 20 January 1944
* ''Recum'' 5,500 BRT, 20 March1944
* ''S.184'' (sunk 5 September 1944, by its own troops){{sfn|Sakkers|Machielse|2013|p=}}
{{clear left}}

===Hellfire Corner===

[[File:Wanstone Battery 15 inch gun 18-05-1942 IWM H 19833.jpg|thumb|{{center|15-inch gun at Wanstone Battery under construction, May 1942}}]]
This gunnery duel, along with heavy German shelling and bombing of [[Dover strait]] and the Dover area, led to this stretch of the Channel being nicknamed ''Hellfire Corner'' and led to 3,059 alerts, 216 civilian deaths and  damage to 10,056 premises in the Dover area. British coastal [[convoy]]s had to pass through the bottleneck of the Dover strait to transport supplies, particularly coal; Britain's road and rail network was not then able to cope with the volume of traffic that had to be handled. Although the German guns regularly fired on these slow moving convoys from 1940 to 1944, with an interlude in 1943, they only sank two ships and damaged several others. Two seamen were killed and others were injured by shell splinters from near misses. However, the civilian crews of the merchant ships found the shelling more unnerving than the attacks by aircraft or [[E-boat]]s that they were also subjected to and  there were instances of crews refusing to sail from their forming-up point at [[Southend-on-Sea]] because of the German guns.{{sfn|Hewitt|2008|p=109}}

===The Channel Dash===

{{main|Channel Dash}}

On 11 February 1942, the German [[battleship]]s {{Ship |German battleship|Scharnhorst||2}} and {{ship|German battleship|Gneisenau||2}}, the [[heavy cruiser]] {{ship |German cruiser|Prinz Eugen||2}} and more than twenty smaller escort vessels, sailed from [[Brest, France|Brest]] in [[Brittany]] to their home port of [[Wilhelmshaven]] by an audacious dash through the English Channel, codenamed ''Unternehmen Zerberus'' (Operation Cerberus). Due to poor visibility and a number of communication failures by British forces, the first response to the German squadron was by the 9.2-inch guns of the South Foreland Battery, which were the only guns which could be directed by radar but the 10-cm [[K band (NATO)|K band]] set had only recently been installed and had never been used in conjunction with the guns. As the visibility was only {{convert|5|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}}, it was hoped that the radar would be able to register the splashes as the shells landed so that the guns would be able to correct their aim but nothing was detected. After firing three two-gun [[salvo]]es without being able to detect the &quot;fall of shot&quot; – the shells were actually landing almost a mile astern of the main German ships – it was decided to fire full salvoes using only the ranging information from the radar. After six minutes of rapid fire, the last shots were fired at a range of {{convert|30,000|yd|m|abbr=on}}. None of the 33 shells fired came close to the German ships. A minute before the last shots were fired, South Foreland came under counter-battery fire from across the Channel but little damage was sustained.{{sfn|Ford|2012|pp=33–36}}

===Final duels===

{{Main|Operation Undergo}}

During the Anglo-Canadian operation to capture Calais, on 26 September 1944 (the last day of shelling) fifty shells were fired, killing five people, the last of whom was 63-year-old Patience Ransley, who was killed by a shell from the ''Lindemann'' Battery while sheltering in the {{convert|900|ft|m|abbr=on}} long &quot;Barwick's Cave&quot; reinforced cliff tunnel.{{sfn|Vaughan|2009|nopp=y}} Accurate bombardment from the British heavy guns at Dover disabled the ''Grosser Kurfürst'' Battery at Floringzelle near Cap Gris Nez, ending the duels.{{sfn|Copp|2006|p=82}} Dover was finally freed from bombardment and to mark the event the town's mayor was sent a German flag from the batteries.{{sfn|Stacey|1960|pp=344–354}}

==Aftermath==

Between Calais and [[Boulogne-sur-Mer]] considerable parts of the concrete gun emplacements and associated bunkers remain, in accessible, although often somewhat dangerous, condition. One of the [[casemate]]s of the Todt Battery can be visited at the ''Musée du Mur de l'Atlantique'', the Atlantic Wall Museum, at Audinghen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.batterietodt.com/ Batterie Todt Museum homepage]&lt;/ref&gt; One of the Krupp K5 guns is also there. Since 1954, a section of painted armour plating taken as a [[war trophy]] from a turret of the Lindemann Battery has been on display on the Dover seafront. Many of the British batteries remained until the decision was taken to retire all the coastal artillery in 1956. The big 15-inch guns at Wanstone Farm were not removed until 1959.{{sfn|Gander|2011|nopp=y}} The sites have either been demolished, buried or left to decay. At Wanstone Farm Battery, ancillary buildings such as the plotting room and the guard house are visible, although overgrown and the sergeants' mess has reverted to its original use as a farm house.{{sfn|Catford|2011|nopp=y}}

==Gallery==

&lt;gallery mode=packed&gt;
File:428 Battery, Coastal Defence Artillery Headquarters, Dover, Kent, December 1942 TR566.jpg| 428 Battery, Coastal Defence Artillery Headquarters, Dover, Kent, December 1942
File:Sangatte Battery near Calais used for Cross-channel Bombardment Art.IWMARTLD4604.jpg| Sangatte Battery near Calais, used for cross-channel bombardment
File:04-06-10 a deutsches Fort bei Cap Gris-Nez 04.JPG| Rear of a ''Batterie Todt'' gunhouse, open to visitors
File:Observation post.jpg| The derelict Battery Observation Post at [[Hougham Battery]] which was constructed in 1941 for three [[BL 8 inch Mk VIII naval gun|8 inch Mk VIII]] naval guns
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[V-3 cannon]] German supergun of 1943–44 at Mimoyecques, Pas-de-Calais
* [[Dover Castle]]
* [[Hougham Battery]]
* [[List of naval guns]]
* [[Operation Sea Lion]]
* [[Fan Bay Deep Shelter]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|Catford|2011}}
|last=Catford |first=N. |title=Hougham Battery - Fortress &amp; Battery Plotting Room |year=2011 |website=Subterranea Britannica |url=http://www.subbrit.org.uk/sb-sites/sites/h/hougham_battery_plotting_room/index.shtml |accessdate=20 October 2016}}
* {{cite book |last=Copp |first=Terry |authorlink=Terry Copp |title=Cinderella army: the Canadians in north-west Europe, 1944–1945 |publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]] |year=2006 |isbn=0-8020-3925-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book  |ref={{harvid|Clarke|2005}}
|last=Clarke |first=Dale |title=British Artillery 1914–19: Heavy Artillery |year=2005 |publisher=Osprey |location=London |isbn=}}
* {{cite book |last=Evans |first=Martin Marix |year=2004 |title=Invasion! Operation Sealion 1940 |publisher=Longmans |location=London |isbn=978-0-582-77294-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Ford |first=Ken |year=2012 |title=Run The Gauntlet: The Channel Dash 1942 |publisher=Osprey |location=London |isbn=978-1-84908-570-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|CARL|2008}}
|author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |series=World War II Operational Documents |title=Fuhrer Directives and other Top-Level Directives of the German Armed Forces, 1939–1941 |others=Part 2 |year=2008 |orig-year=1948 |publisher=U.S. Office of Naval Intelligence |location=Washington, DC |edition=Combined Arms Research Library Digital Library |id=N16267-A |url=http://cgsc.cdmhost.com/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p4013coll8/id/2356/rec/1 |accessdate=20 October 2016 |oclc=464601776}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.fsgfort.com/uploads/pdfs/Public/British%20Coastal%20Artillery%20P.pdf |title=Twentieth Century British Coast Defence Guns |last1=Gander |first1=Terry |date=2011 |website=www.fsgfort.com |publisher=Fortress Study Group |accessdate=13 April 2014 |ref=harv}}{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}
* {{cite book |last=Hewitt |first=Nick |title=Coastal Convoys 1939–1945: The Indestructible Highway |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Maritime |year=2008 |isbn=978-1-84415-861-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Sakkers|Machielse|2013}}
|last1=Sakkers |first1=Hans |last2=Machielse |first2=M. |title=Artillerieduell der Fernkampfgeschütze am Pas de Calais 1940–1944: aus Sicht der schweren deutschen Marinebatterien &quot;Großer Kurfürst&quot;, &quot;Todt&quot;, &quot;Prinz Heinrich&quot;, &quot;Friedrich August&quot;, &quot;Lindemann&quot; und der Heeres-Eisenbahnartillerie |language=German |trans_title=Artillery Duel of the Long-Range Guns in the Pas de Calais 1940–1944: from the Perspective of the Heavy German Naval Batteries &quot;Großer Kurfürst&quot;, &quot;Todt&quot;, &quot;Prinz Heinrich&quot;, &quot;Friedrich August&quot;, &quot;Lindemann&quot; and the Army Railway Guns |year=2013 |publisher=Helios |location=Aachen |isbn=978-3-86933-092-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Schenk|1990}}
|last=Schenk |first=Peter |title=Invasion of England 1940: The Planning of Operation Sealion |publisher=Conway Maritime Press |location=London |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-85177-548-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Stacey|1960}}
|first1=Colonel Charles Perry |last1=Stacey |authorlink= |last2=Bond |first2=Major C. C. J. |series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War |volume=III |title=The Victory Campaign: The Operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945 |chapter=XIV; Clearing the Coastal Belt and the Ports, September 1944 |chapterurl=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/Canada/CA/Victory/Victory-14.html#cn31 |pages=336–344 |publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery Ottawa |year=1960 |edition=online |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/docs/Victory_e.pdf |accessdate=11 October 2016 |oclc=256471407}}
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|BGD|2015}}
|author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=The Big Guns At Dover WW2 World War Two |url=https://weaponsandwarfare.com/2015/09/17/the-big-guns-at-dover-ww2-world-war-two/ |accessdate=21 October 2016}}
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|Vaughan|2009}}
|last=Vaughan |first=J. |title=The Unlikely Death of Patience Ransley |year=2009 |url=http://www.doverwarmemorialproject.org.uk/Information/Articles/Incidents/ShellingRansley.htm |website=The Dover War Memorial Project |accessdate=20 October 2016}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite report |last=Monaghan |first=J. W. |title=Operation &quot;Wellhit&quot;, – The Capture of Boulogne |id=Report 184 |work=Canadian Participation in the Operations in North-West Europe 1944 |date=24 September 1947 |chapter=Part V: Clearing the Channel Ports, 3 Sep 44 – 6 Feb 45 |pages=11–37 |publisher=Historical Section, Canadian Military Headquarters |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/rep-rap/doc/cmhq/CMHQ184.pdf |format=pdf |accessdate=20 October 2016}}

==External links==
* [http://www.losapos.com/francebunkers Batterie Todt in Northern France]
* [http://www.doverpages.co.uk/big_guns.htm DoverPages]
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/stories/97/a4117097.shtml BBC ''People's War'']
* [http://www.battlefieldsww2.com/cross_channel_bombardments.html Cross channel bombardments during Second World War]
* [http://www.britishpathe.com/video/winnie-in-action British Pathé wartime newsreel of the 14-inch gun &quot;Winnie&quot; being loaded and fired]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t-n23Ee7rAk British Pathé wartime newsreel of ships being shelled - the shells miss and  a spotter plane turns up but is forced to retreat by the RAF]
* Terry Gander, [http://www.fsgfort.com/uploads/pdfs/Public/British%20Coastal%20Artillery%20P.pdf Twentieth century British coast defence guns]{{dead link|date=September 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dover Strait coastal guns, 1940–1944}}
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:World War II in the Pas-de-Calais]]
[[Category:English Channel]]
[[Category:Military history of Kent]]
[[Category:Dover (district)]]
[[Category:Superguns]]</text>
      <sha1>od8xld8rays7ak22dvufsbqtg77krnd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
