<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Foreign fighters in the Syrian and Iraqi Civil Wars</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39829229</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749458520</id>
      <parentid>748926829</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T13:23:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Narky Blert</username>
        <id>22041646</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Link to DAB page repaired</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="135733">{{Update|date=October 2015}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2015}}
[[File:YPG Volunteer Michael Enright on Frontline VOA 2.jpg|250px|thumb|A foreign fighter of the [[People's Protection Units]] in Syria]]
During the course of the [[Syrian Civil War]] as well as the [[Iraqi Civil War (2014–present)]], many foreign nationals have been documented to have fought for Syria's rebel forces, either for the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] (which has elicited the biggest international response), [[al-Nusra Front]], the [[Free Syrian Army]] or other factions. Many foreign fighters have also died in the conflict. Fighters include those from the Gulf Arab states, Tunisia (following its own [[Tunisian revolution]]), Libya (following the similar [[Libyan Civil War (2011)|Libyan Civil War]]), Bosnia, China, other Arab states, Russia's Chechnya and North Caucasus region and Western countries (despite warnings of radicalism from those governments). The conflict has taken on a largely sectarian bent with foreign [[Sunni]]s fighting for the opposition, while foreign [[Shia]]s fight for the government. Estimates of the total number of foreign Sunnis who have fought for the rebels over the course of the conflict range from 5,000 to over 10,000, while foreign Shia fighters are thought to number around 10,000 at the most.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://carnegie-mec.org/syriaincrisis/?fa=53811|title=Who Are the Foreign Fighters in Syria? An Interview With Aaron Y. Zelin |last=Lund|first=Aron|work=Guide to Syria in Crisis|publisher=Carnegie Middle East Center|accessdate=7 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 600 foreign fighters were killed in the first half of 2013 alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;/&gt; The Soufan Group reported on 15 October 2016 that there has been &quot;a significant increase in the number of foreign fighters travelling to Syria&quot; since 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;MEO-Soufan-15-10-2016&quot;&gt;{{cite url|url=http://www.middle-east-online.com/english/?id=79269|title=How Many Foreign Fighters in Syria|work=Middle East Online|date=15 October 2016|accessdate=18 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. State Department reported on 2 June 2016 that their &quot;intelligence community&quot; estimates that possibly &quot;in excess of 40,000 total foreign fighters have gone to the conflict [in Syria] and from over 100 countries&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RTSyriaFightersJune-2-2016&quot;&gt;{{cite url|url=https://www.rt.com/usa/345269-40000-foreign-terrorists-syria/|title=Over 40,000 foreign militants from 100 countries fighting in Syria – US State Department|work=Russia Today|date=3 June 2016|access-date=18 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USStateJune-2-2016&quot;&gt;{{cite url|url=https://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2016/06/258013.htm|title=Country Reports on Terrorism 2015|work=US State Department|date=2 June 2016|access-date=18 October 2016|quote=QUESTION: I might have missed this somewhere else in the report, but in the 2014 report you state specifically that the rate of foreign fighter terrorist travel to Syria was more than 16,000 from 90 countries. In this year’s report you write that thousands of foreign terrorist fighters came from more than 100 countries. Is there a specific number for foreign terrorist fighter travel to Syria or – MR SIBERELL: Yeah. Well, the numbers that we have available to us come from analysis out of our intelligence community. And I think the most recent figures they’ve provided – and these are not calendar year 2015; this will be the most recent – but I’ve seen in excess of 40,000 total foreign fighters have gone to the conflict and from over 100 countries. But it’s been difficult, of course, to associate the numbers with a particular date and time, and that’s because of the way that the numbers come in and the reporting. So it’s been difficult to correlate.}}&lt;/ref&gt; while six months prior, the Russian Defense Ministry estimated that there were about &quot;25-30,000 foreign terrorist mercenaries are fighting for ISIL&quot; alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;RTSyriaFightersJune-2-2016&quot;/&gt;

The phenomenon causes concerns in the home countries of the foreign fighters, for example because of foiled or successful attacks, but also because of countries being used as transit countries or departing bases. The phenomenon is not new, but the size and widespread origins in this case are.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://icct.nl/publication/report-the-foreign-fighters-phenomenon-in-the-eu-profiles-threats-policies/ | title=The Foreign Fighters Phenomenon in the European Union |date=April 2016 | publisher=The International Centre for Counter-Terrorism - The Hague (ICCT) | accessdate=31 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Campaignbox Syrian civil war}}

==Reasons==
According to figures collected by the Soufan Group, between 27 000 to 31 000 people including women and children who would not normally engage in conflict have traveled to Syria and Iraq to join the Islamic state and other extremist groups fighting in the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Lydia Khalil|author2= Rodger Shanahan|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/03/29/iraq-and-syria-how-many-foreign-fighters-are-fighting-for-isil/ |title=&quot;Iraq and Syria: How Many Foreign Fighters are Fighting for ISIL?&quot;|date=24 March 2016 |accessdate=28 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Reasons that these people join Islamic state or any other extremist group seem to depend on where they come from. Those fighters that come from places like United States or European Union seem to join because they are experiencing some type of identity crisis.This is especially true in regards to first generation and second generation immigrants who join because of the continued marginalization and alienation that they experience from their native peers. Their hope is that joining the Islamic state will give them a sense of purpose and belonging. People who join that are from Islamic countries are likely to join because they want to assist their Muslim brothers that are fighting the Assad regime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Martin Reardon|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2015/12/why-people-join-isis/419685/ |title=The real threat of foreign fighters in Syria |date=13 December 2015 |accessdate=28 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One reason suggested for the influx of foreigners in the fight is that the Syrian government took no steps to curtail the inflow of foreigners who then moved to Iraq during the [[Iraqi insurgency (Iraq War)|Iraqi insurgency]]. In the first half of 2012, 700-1,400 fighters were said to have entered Syria. In 2011 total foreign fighters were roughly in line with foreign fighters in other Muslim jihads such as Bosnia, Chechnya, Afghanistan (In the 1980s and 2000s) and Iraq at up to 10% of the fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;/&gt; Their numbers continue to increase, however, and may now number more than 11,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/middleeast/syria/10523203/Number-of-foreign-fighters-in-Syria-nearly-doubles.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Alex | last=Spillius | title=Number of foreign fighters in Syria nearly doubles | date=17 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Syria's easy accessibility through Turkey is probably an important factor in making it the current number one destination for jihad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://icct.nl/publication/destination-jihad-why-syria-and-not-mali/|title=Destination Jihad: Why Syria and not Mali|publisher=The International Centre for Counter-Terrorism - The Hague (ICCT)|accessdate=1 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Places such as Tunisia had a high number of fighters abroad due to the accessible mobility and expatriates and larger middle class than most other countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kyiv&quot;/&gt; Syria was said to be a breeding ground for fighters as most foreign recruits had little or no combat experience. An analysis of martyrdom videos indicated that of the 600 reported dead in the first half of 2013, less than 20 of the dead fighters were experienced fighters from Afghanistan, Libya, or elsewhere.&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;/&gt;

On 31 May 2013, [[Yusuf al-Qaradawi]] called for a jihad against Syria. It was speculated in the Western media that this could lead to an influx of foreign fighters to the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Thomas Hegghammer |author2=Aaron Y. Zelin |url=http://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/139557/thomas-hegghammer-aaron-y-zelin/how-syrias-civil-war-became-a-holy-crusade |title=How Syria's Civil War Became a Holy Crusade |publisher=Foreign Affairs |date=7 July 2013 |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An October 2016 World Bank study found that &quot;ISIL’s foreign fighters are surprisingly well-educated.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quartz6Oct2016Educated&quot;&gt;{{cite url|url=http://qz.com/802276/the-foreign-fighters-of-isisislamic-state-are-surprisingly-well-educated-according-to-the-world-bank/|title=ISIL’s foreign fighters are surprisingly well-educated, according to the World Bank|work=Quartz|author=Aamna Mohdin|date=6 October 2016|accessdate=18 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Using the fighters' self-reported educational levels, the study concluded that &quot;69% of recruits reported at least a secondary-level education&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quartz6Oct2016Educated&quot;/&gt; of which &quot;a large fraction have gone on to study at university&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WorldBankOct2016Educated&quot;&gt;{{cite url|url=http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/409591474983005625/pdf/108525-REVISED-PUBLIC.pdf|title=Economic  and Social Inclusion to Prevent Violent Extremism|work=World Bank|date=October 2016|accessdate=18 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also that &quot;only 15% of recruits left school before high school; less than 2% are illiterate.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quartz6Oct2016Educated&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WorldBankOct2016Educated&quot;/&gt; The study also found that foreign fighters are often more educated than their countrymen where those &quot;from Europe and in Central Asia have similar levels of education to their countrymen&quot; while those &quot;from the Middle East, North Africa, and South and East Asia are significantly more educated than what is typical in their home nations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quartz6Oct2016Educated&quot;/&gt; The report notes that its conclusions that terrorism is not driven by poverty and low levels of education does not conform with previous research.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quartz6Oct2016Educated&quot;/&gt; However, the report did find a strong correlation &quot;between a country’s male unemployment rate and the propensity of the country to supply foreign fighters&quot; leading the report to recommend that governments pursue a policy of lowering the unemployment rate among the educated as a counter-terrorism strategy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quartz6Oct2016Educated&quot;/&gt;

==Passage==
Most fighters travel to Turkey first before slipping across the border with somewhat lesser contingents coming from Lebanon and even fewer from Jordan and Iraq;&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;/&gt; many of the fighters also use forged passports as they try and escape secret services. Upon entering the country, many of the [[Islamist]] fighters were dispersed to the various groups such as [[Ahrar ash-Sham]] and the [[Nusra Front]]. Languages reportedly spoken in rebel camps include: Chechen, Tajik, Turkish, French, the Saudi Arabic dialect and Urdu (Pakistan or India). In regards to the [[Free Syrian Army]], ''[[The Guardian]]'' reported the recruits to be more secretive.&lt;ref name=&quot;guard&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Ghaith Abdul-Ahad in Aleppo |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/sep/23/syria-foreign-fighters-joining-war |title=Syria: the foreign fighters joining the war against Bashar al-Assad |publisher=The Guardian |date= 23 September 2012|accessdate=1 July 2013 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jihadist internet fora have also been fertile recruiting grounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;/&gt; The easy access to the country was a reason for the growing number of foreign fighters. ''[[Al-Sharq al-Awsat]]'' reported that Libyan fighting leader Abu-Yahya indicated an easy travel route for Tunisian and Libyan fighters, who are first trained in Libya to fight in Syria and then smuggled into Syria with the help of militant groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Bill Gertz |url=http://freebeacon.com/syria-new-terrorist-training-ground/ |title=Up to 6,000 jihadists fighting with al Qaeda groups in Syria |publisher=Freebeacon.com |date= |accessdate=2 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even in July 2013, it was reported that foreign fighters continued to come to Syria and commit atrocities against both supporters and opponents of the government, as well as clashing with moderate rebel groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/07/08/world/middleeast/tension-between-rebel-groups-intensifies-in-syria.html?_r=0 | work=The New York Times | first1=Anne | last1=Barnard | first2=Hania | last2=Mourtada | title=Opposition in Syria Continues to Fracture | date=7 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; This followed President [[Bashar al-Assad]] signing into law a bill that would punish anyone entering the country illegally with jail time and a fine. The fine would be between five million and 10&amp;nbsp;million Syrian pounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almanar.com.lb/english/adetails.php?eid=99029&amp;cid=23&amp;fromval=1&amp;utm_source=twitterfeed&amp;utm_medium=twitter |title=Syria: Anyone Who Enters Country Illegally Will Be Jailed, Fined |publisher=Almanar.com.lb |date= |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==

===2015 Soufan Group Report===
A 7 December 2015 report by [[the Soufan Group]] gave estimates for the number of foreign fighters in Syria and Iraq by their country and region of origin based on information dated between 2014 and 2015.&lt;ref name=TSG7Dec2015FFs&gt;{{cite url|url=http://soufangroup.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/TSG_ForeignFightersUpdate_FINAL3.pdf|title=Foreign Fighters An Updated Assessment of the Flow of Foreign Fighters into Syria and Iraq|work=[[the Soufan Group]]|date=7 December 2015|accessdate=24 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study listed the countries with the largest number of foreign fighters were Tunisia (6000), Saudi Arabia (2500), Russia (2400), Turkey (2100), Jordan (2000+)&lt;ref name=Quartz8Dec2015TSGReport&gt;{{cite web|url=http://qz.com/568503/foreign-fighters-in-iraq-and-syria-come-from-86-countries-and-their-numbers-have-doubled/|title=Foreign fighters in Iraq and Syria come from 86 countries—and their numbers have doubled|work=Quartz|author=Aamna Mohdin|date=8 December 2015|accessdate=18 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TSG7Dec2015FFs/&gt; while the number of fighters by region was reported to be: the Middle East (8240), the Maghreb (8000), Western Europe (5000), former Soviet Republics (4700), Southeast Asia (900), the Balkans (875), and North America (289).&lt;ref name=Quartz8Dec2015TSGReport/&gt; Of Western Europe's estimated 5000 total fighters, almost 3700 fighters were produced by just four Western European counties: France (1700), Germany (760), the United Kingdom (760), and Belgium (470).&lt;ref name=Quartz8Dec2015TSGReport/&gt;&lt;ref name=TSG7Dec2015FFs/&gt; Between 2014 and 2015, the report estimated a nearly 300% increase in the number of fighters originating from Russia and Central Asia whereas the total number of fighters traveling to Syria and Iraq had become &quot;relatively flat.&quot;&lt;ref name=Quartz8Dec2015TSGReport/&gt; The report mentioned that the flow of foreign fighters &quot;is neither uniform by region nor by country,&quot; with some countries having distinguishable &quot;Hotbeds of recruitment&quot; with some hotbeds, such as the Lisleby district of [[Norway]]'s [[Fredrikstad]] which is populated by only 6000 people, being small and relatively new while other cities and regions, such as [[Tunisia]]'s [[Bizerte]] and [[Ben Gardane]], [[Libya]]'s [[Derna District|Derna]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]'s [[Pankisi Gorge]], and [[Brussel]]'s [[Molenbeek]], &quot;are well-established incubators and radiators of extremist behavior.&quot;&lt;ref name=TSG7Dec2015FFs/&gt;

==Arab world==
The total number of foreign fighters was estimated to be the largest for Libyans with several hundred fighters; Saudis numbered at least 330; several hundred Egyptian Islamists; about 300 Iraqis and over 500 Jordanians.&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;/&gt;

===Persian Gulf states===
Bahraini Sunni sheikh Adel al-Hamad said that his son, Abdulrahman, was killed while fighting in Syria and that he had &quot;hoped to fall as a martyr.&quot; He added: &quot;He visited Syria once, then he returned to Bahrain where he prepared his fighting gear and returned to Syria.&quot; In response, Interior Minister Rashid bin Abdullah al-Khalifa said that support should be given from the international community and that individuals should not be indoctrinated and radicalised. It follows calls from mosques to join the &quot;jihad&quot; in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailystar.com.lb/News/Middle-East/2013/May-30/218898-bahraini-killed-in-syria-fight-government-warns-citizens.ashx#axzz2XpZNyLi6 |title=Bahraini killed in Syria fight, government warns citizens |publisher=The Daily Star |date= |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are also Saudi fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;guard&quot;/&gt; ''[[USA Today]]'' reported that over 1,200 death row inmates were sent from Saudi Arabia to fight against the Syrian government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Michael Winter |url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/world/2013/01/21/saudi-inmates-fight-syria-commute-death-sentences/1852629/ |title=Saudis sent death-row inmates to fight Syria |publisher=Usatoday.com |date=21 January 2013 |accessdate=20 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lebanon===
{{further information|Syrian Civil War spillover in Lebanon}}
Mostly Lebanese fighters tend to have their own groups and militias. Members of [[Fatah al-Islam]] and the [[Abdullah Azzam Brigades]] were also present though they were fighting under independent banners.&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;/&gt; Many Lebanese fighters for the opposition come from the Sunni stronghold of [[Tripoli, Lebanon|Tripoli]]. The city's Sunni cleric Sheik Masen al-Mohammed said: &quot;The struggle for freedom in Syria is our own struggle for freedom. We Lebanese are part of the Syrian revolution, part of the rebellion. If Syria gains its freedom, then we will also win in Lebanon.&quot; He also said of Syrian President [[Bashar al-Assad]] that he was an &quot;infidel...It is the duty of every Muslim, every Arab to fight the infidels. There is a holy war in Syria and the young men there are conducting jihad. For blood, for honor, for freedom, for dignity. We know of Palestinian, Libyan and Yemen fighters who are active there.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;de&quot;/&gt;

===Libya===
Libya's [[Transitional National Government]] was the first and only UN recognised entity to see the [[Syrian National Council]] as the sole legitimate representative of the Syrian people. In December 2011, it was reported in the French media that the former [[Libyan Islamic Fighting Group]]'s [[Abdulhakim Belhadj]]'s associate [[Mahdi Al-Harati|Abd al-Mehdi al-Harati]] was leading a Libyan group of fighters with rumours suggesting some of the Nusra Front's fighters came from this group.&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;/&gt; Arms from the recently concluded [[2011 Libyan Civil War|Libyan Civil War]] were also present in Syria.&lt;ref name=&quot;rebels get libyan weapons&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=In Turnabout, Syria Rebels Get Libyan Weapons |first=C.J. |last=Chivers |first2=Eric |last2=Schmitt |first3=Mark |last3=Mazzetti |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/22/world/africa/in-a-turnabout-syria-rebels-get-libyan-weapons.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=1&amp; |newspaper=New York Times |date=21 June 2013 |accessdate=2 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; While many fighters from the civil war were reported to have gone to fight in Syria, several were said to have returned home amidst escalating violence and threats of a new civil war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-30011640|title=BBC News - Libya violence: Activists beheaded in Derna|work=BBC News|accessdate=4 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Towards the end of 2014, the city of [[Derna, Libya|Derna]] reportedly swore allegiance to ISIS, the first outside Syria or Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://firstlook.org/theintercept/2014/11/11/happened-humanitarians-wanted-save-libyans-bombs-drones/|title=What Happened to the Humanitarians Who Wanted to Save Libyans With Bombs and Drones?|work=The Intercept|accessdate=4 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tunisia===
Following the first [[Arab Spring]] uprising that led to the [[Tunisian revolution]], when the Islamist [[Ennahda Movement|Ennahda]] party came to power, many Tunisian fighters fought alongside the Syrian opposition fighters. In early 2012, Tunisia also withdrew recognition of Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Amara |first=Tarek |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/02/04/us-syria-tunisia-flag-idUSTRE8130IF20120204 |title=Tunisia to withdraw recognition of Syria government |publisher=Reuters |date= 4 February 2012|accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tunisians have been killed or captured in Syria, with at least five deaths from the town of [[Ben Guerdane]], from where many fighters departed Tunisia for Syria. The Syrian government informed the United Nations of the arrest of 26 alleged al-Qaeda militants, 19 of whom were Tunisian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Noueihed |first=Lin |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/05/14/us-syria-tunisia-fighters-idUSBRE84D0UN20120514 |title=Tunisian Islamists join jihad against Syria's Assad |publisher=Reuters |date= 14 May 2012|accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tunisians are reportedly a large percentage of the foreign Arab fighters in the country. President [[Moncef Marzouki]]'s spokesman Adnan Mancer said that the government was trying to follow up on the fate of Tunisians in Syria with the help of international organisations like the Red Cross as official ties between governments had been cut. He said: &quot;Our youth have good intentions, but it is possible they fell into the hands of manipulators.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kyiv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kyivpost.com/content/world/tunisian-radicals-travel-to-syria-308459.html |title=Tunisian radicals travel to Syria |publisher=Kyivpost.com |date=21 June 2012 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2013, an inquiry was initiated into recruitment of Tunisian Islamists. In May, Foreign Minister [[Othmane Jarandi]] said that there were about 800 Tunisians fighting for the opposition in Syria. He added that &quot;the repatriation of Tunisians can be facilitated by the embassy in Lebanon after the government makes contact with the Syrian authorities about imprisoned Tunisian citizens.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.naharnet.com/stories/en/82683 |title=Tunisia FM: 800 Tunisian Islamists Fighting in Syria |publisher=Naharnet.com |date=11 May 2013 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Iraq===
{{further information|Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant}}
Rifts within the [[al-Qaeda]] subgroups were also exposed by the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;/&gt; Amongst the various Iraqis fighting in Syria's opposition are [[Al-Qaeda in Iraq]]. Its leader [[Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi]] also issued a video tape that said his group had merged with the Nusra Front in order to form the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant. However, Nusra Front disavowed the claim, while al-Qaeda leader [[Ayman al-Zawahiri]] ordered them to be separate groups. al-Baghdadi then issued another video tape in which he rejected al-Zawahiri's ruling.

===Israel===
[[Israeli-Arabs]] were also found to have traveled to Syria and fought for the rebels. At least one returnee, who was reportedly asked to carry out a suicide bombing in Israel, was convicted of &quot;endangering national security.&quot; Judge Avraham Yaakov said at a session of the trial at [[Lod]] district court that &quot;there's no legal guidance regarding the rebel groups fighting in Syria.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailystar.com.lb/News/Middle-East/2013/Jul-08/222945-israel-jails-arab-citizen-who-briefly-joined-syrias-rebels.ashx#ixzz2YUi1Cyul |title=Israel jails Arab citizen who briefly joined Syria's rebels |publisher=The Daily Star |date= |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Others===
In June 2013, a recently promoted Jordanian Air Force captain was reported to have taken leave from his job and traveled to Turkey in order to fight for the Nusra Front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailystar.com.lb/News/Middle-East/2013/Jul-01/222153-jordan-air-force-captain-joins-syria-jihadists-sources.ashx#axzz2XpZNyLi6 |title=Jordan air force captain joins Syria jihadists: sources |publisher=The Daily Star |date=19 June 2013 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yemenis have also fought for both sides in the Syrian battle; Palestinians have also fought for both sides of the conflict&lt;ref name=&quot;guard&quot;/&gt; with [[Hamas]] being more supportive of the opposition and the [[PFLP-GC]] supporting the government. A leading Mauritanian jihadist ideologue, Sheikh Abu al-Mundhir al-Shinqiti, has called for support for the Nusra Front.&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtoninstitute.org/policy-analysis/view/foreign-fighters-trickle-into-the-syrian-rebellion |title=Foreign Fighters Trickle into the Syrian Rebellion |publisher=The Washington Institute for Near East Policy |date=11 June 2012 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most recruits are Arabs (Lebanese, Iraqis, Jordanians, Palestinians, Kuwaitis, Tunisians, Libyans, Algerians, Egyptians, Saudis, Sudanese and Yemenis). The largest contingents of about 500-900 fighters come from Syria's neighbors: Lebanese, Iraqis, Palestinians and Jordanians, many of whom fought U.S. forces in Iraq. The second-largest contingent is from other Arab countries in North Africa: around 75-300 fighters from Libya, Tunisia, and Algeria.&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;/&gt; Al Qaeda leader Ayman al-Zawahiri also called for a jihad in Syria with the main target of message said to be Lebanon, Jordan, Turkey and Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;de&quot;/&gt;

In November 2014, five people were jailed in Jordan for three to five years for &quot;promoting... terrorist organisations&quot; in reference to ISIS. Two others were also on trial as part of a crackdown on militants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presstv.in/detail/2014/11/18/386441/jordan-jails-5-over-promoting-isil/#sthash.27Eh1r0c.dpuf|title=PressTV-Jordan jails 5 over promoting ISIL|publisher=|accessdate=4 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Azerbaijan==
[[Azerbaijan]] is a largely unobservant Shia majority country with a Sunni minority. Many Sunni citizens of Azerbaijan have joined terrorist organizations in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jihadology.net/2015/02/02/the-clear-banner-azerbaijani-foreign-fighters-in-2014/|title=The Clear Banner: The Forgotten Fighters: Azerbaijani Foreign Fighters in Syria and Iraq|work=JIHADOLOGY|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jihadology.net/2014/01/28/guest-post-azerbaijani-foreign-fighters-in-syria/|title=GUEST POST: Azerbaijani Foreign Fighters in Syria|work=JIHADOLOGY|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iGkL9uwZdN4|title=Suriyada azərbaycanlı vəhhabilər kütləvi şəkildə öldürüldü|date=25 March 2014|work=YouTube|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.meydan.tv/az/site/opinion/791/rim-suriyaya-5-manatla-gedib-v-deo.htm|title=&quot;Ərim Suriyaya 5 manatla gedib&quot; [ VİDEO ]|author=Meydan TV|work=Meydan TV - Alternativ və Azad Media Kanalı|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It's estimated that the number of Azerbaijanis in Syria ranges from 200 to 300.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-azerbaijan-killed-syria/26642573.html|title=Why Did An Azerbaijani Wrestling Champion Join (And Die For) IS?|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=4 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Georgia==
A veteran of the 2008 Russo-Georgian War and a former sergeant in the [[Georgia (country)|Georgian]] Army, the
[[Georgia (country)|Georgian]] [[Abu Omar al-Shishani]], currently serves as a commander for the Islamic State in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-why-kadyrov-claims-shishani-killed/26692100.html|publisher=Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty|title= The Chechen Leader With A Grudge And The IS Commander With Nine Lives |date=14 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=25084|title=Umar Shishani’s Man Who Fought At Menagh, Then Was Killed In Dagestan|date=28 April 2016|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/725704607255552000|title=Joanna Paraszczuk on Twitter|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another one is [[Muslim Abu Walid al Shishani|Muslim Shishani]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=25074|title=More About Muslim Shishani’s Early Years As a Militant In Ingushetia (With Pics!)|date=19 April 2016|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/722366109593133056|title=Joanna Paraszczuk on Twitter|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=21316|title=Syria: Who is Muslim Abu Walid Shishani? Part One|date=26 March 2014|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==China==

[[File:Flag of the Turkistan Islamic Party in Syria.svg|thumb|Flag of Turkistan Islamic Party in Syria]]
The [[Uyghurs|Uyghur]] militant group [[Turkistan Islamic Party in Syria]] (TIP) sent a large number of its fighters, operating in a unit called the &quot;Turkistan Brigade&quot; (Katibat Turkistani), to take part in the [[Syrian Civil War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;turkestan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.siteintelgroup.com/Jihadist-News/tip-division-in-syria-releases-video-promoting-cause-inciting-for-jihad.html|title=TIP Division in Syria Releases Video Promoting Cause, Inciting for Jihad|publisher=SITE Institute|date=6 June 2014|accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/details/Tuba4Ilan1|title=Tuba 4 Ilan 1|work=Internet Archive|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/details/Raziman|title=Raziman|work=Internet Archive|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/details/mensure|title=mensure|work=Internet Archive|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have taken part in numerous battles in Syria, including the [[2015 Jisr al-Shughur offensive]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JEnv694zinM|title=A short video showing the opening of yesterdays ongoing battle in Jisr ash-Shugur|date=22 April 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=23 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Weiss|first=Caleb|title=Turkistan Islamic Party in Syria involved in new Idlib offensive|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2015/04/turkistan-islamic-party-in-syria-involved-in-new-idlib-offensive.php|work=Long War Journal|date=23 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Turkistan Islamic Party had significant role in recent Idlib offensive|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2015/04/turkistan-islamic-party-had-significant-role-recent-idlib-offensive.php|website=Long War Journal|date=30 April 2015|first=Caleb|last=Weiss}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/rConflictNews/status/594579201266585602|title=Conflict News on Twitter|work=Twitter|accessdate=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=cb1_1430611230|title=LiveLeak.com - Turkistan/Chechnya group releases combat footage of capture of Jsir Shurour|publisher=|accessdate=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ia802702.us.archive.org/27/items/JennetAxikliri14/jennet%20axikliri14.mp4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=c10_1438594302|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] NEW Hizb al-Islami at-Turkistan release - Routing SAA brigade from a city in Idlib (August, 2015)|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thelineofsteel.weebly.com/analysis/turkistan-islamic-party-in-syria-fighting-alongside-junud-al-sham-in-idlib|title=Turkistan Islamic Party in Syria fighting alongside Junud al Sham in Idlib|work=The Line of Steel|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The leader of TIP (ETIM) in Syria was Abu Rida al-Turkestani.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.washingtoninstitute.org/policy-analysis/view/26142 |title= Syria: The Epicenter of Future Jihad  |last1=Zelin  |first1=Aaron Y. |last2= |first2= |date=30 June 2014 |website=The Washington Institute |publisher= |access-date= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.washingtoninstitute.org/ar/policy-analysis/view/syria-the-epicenter-of-future-jihad |title= سوريا، مركز الجهاد المستقبلي  |last1=زيلين|first1=هارون ي.  |last2= |first2= |date=30 حزيران/يونيو 2014 |website=معهد واشنطن |publisher= |access-date= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://foreignfighters.weebly.com/archive/category/turkestan-islamic-party |title=Turkestan Islamic Party |date=14 April 2015 |website= Foreign Fighters in Iraq and Syria  |publisher= |access-date= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thelineofsteel.weebly.com/news/turkestan-islamic-party-in-syria|title=Turkestan Islamic Party in Syria|work=The Line of Steel|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant released a video featuring an 80-year-old Uyghur man who came to join ISIL in Syria along with his grandchildren, wife, and daughter after he was inspired by his son who died in combat in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=80-year-old Chinese man joins Islamic State|url=http://www.therakyatpost.com/world/2015/06/04/80-year-old-chinese-man-joins-islamic-state/|accessdate=4 June 2015|agency=The Rakyat Post|date=June 4, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Setiawan|first1=Teguh|title=Muhammad Amin, Serdadu ISIS Tertua asal Tiongkok|url=http://m.inilah.com/news/detail/2210582/muhammad-amin-serdadu-isis-tertua-asal-tiongkok|accessdate=4 June 2015|agency=INILAHCOM|date=3 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first1=Muhaimin|title=Usia 80 Tahun, Inilah Militan ISIS Tertua asal China|url=http://international.sindonews.com/read/1008724/43/usia-80-tahun-inilah-militan-isis-tertua-asal-china-1433393428|accessdate=4 June 2015|agency=SINDONEWS.com|date=4 June 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=[VIDEO] - Usia Sudah 80 Tahun, Kakek Asal Cina Ini Bergabung dengan ISIS|url=http://jabar.tribunnews.com/2015/06/04/video-usia-sudah-80-tahun-kakek-asal-cina-ini-bergabung-dengan-isis|accessdate=4 June 2015|publisher=TRIBUNJABAR.CO.ID|date=4 January 2015&lt;!-- 13:01--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Crowcroft|first1=Orlando|title=The oldest Isis jihadi: 80-year-old Chinese grandfather fights for Islamic State in Syria|url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/oldest-isis-jihadi-80-year-old-chinese-grandfather-fights-islamic-state-syria-1504293|accessdate=4 June 2015|agency=International Business Times|date=June 3, 2015 &lt;!-- 17:23 BST --&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt; Footage also emerged online of a Chinese rebel fighter in Syria, ne Bo Wang, a Muslim convert who calls himself Youssef. He appeared in a video in the northern Syrian countryside, in which he condemned the Syrian government for &quot;butchering every Muslim here in cold blood, including children and women&quot; and stating that &quot;people have no freedom, no democracy, no security and no respect here, not at all.&quot; He also spoke of [[China–Syria relations|historical Chinese ties to Syria]], claiming that the Chinese government had destroyed the &quot;traditional friendship between the Chinese and Arab people&quot; because they &quot;sell weapons and provide financial assistance to the Assad government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/30/world/asia/an-unlikely-chinese-warrior-in-the-battle-for-syria.html?_r=0 | work=The New York Times | first=Edward | last=Wong | title=An Unlikely Warrior in the Battle for Syria | date=29 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Central Asia==
In September 2013, a Kazakh and two Kyrgyz returned from Syria and were arrested in [[Osh]] on terrorism charges on claims that they were sent to Kyrgyzstan by the [[Islamic Jihad Union]] (IJU) to perpetrate attacks. In early February 2014, six suspects were arrested in Osh, some of whom were said to have trained in camps in Syria before returning to Kyrgyzstan. They were reportedly planning attacks in Osh and [[Bishkek]]. Some Kyrgyz fighters that were known to be in Syria joined the Al Nusrah Front.&lt;ref name=&quot;more&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Linda Lundquist |url=http://lubpak.com/archives/314433#sthash.vnvxPLti.dpuf |title=Analysis: Blowback from the Syrian jihad has begun |publisher=Lubpak.com |date=4 June 2014 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kazakhs have joined ISIL in Syria&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=22344|title=&quot;Jump On A Plane &amp; Come&quot; – IS Kazakhstan Jamaat Urges Kazakhs To Fight In Syria|work=From Chechnya To Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=22440|title=New Video From ShamToday Shows Children In Umar Shishani's Swimming Pool|work=From Chechnya To Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=21795|title=Iraq: Claimed Images Of Kazakhstan ISIS Fighter In Ramadi|date=24 April 2014|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; ISIL released a video called &quot;Race Toward Good&quot; showing Kazakh children being trained as fighters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/kazakhstan-isis-syria-recruiting/26724862.html|title=Kazakhstan Muftiate: 'Kazakh Jihadis' With IS In Syria 'Acting Against Islam'|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The families of Kazakh fighters have accompanied them to Syria including children and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/under-black-flag-kazakhstan-kazakh-women-islamic-state/26698040.html|title=Kazakhstan Intelligence: 150 Kazakh Women Are Members Of IS|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/blogs-news-from-elsewhere-24642632|title=Kazakhstan: Video claims of 'family jihad' - BBC News|work=BBC News|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Families of Azeri and Kazakh members of ISIL have been reportedly massacred by the Syrian Islamist rebel group [[Harakat Nour al-Din al-Zenki]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=22184|title=ISIS: Syrian Brigade Massacred Families From Kazakhstan, Azerbaijan|work=From Chechnya To Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Kazakh fighter has appeared in [[Jaish al-Muhajireen wal-Ansar]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=21351|title=Syria: A Portrait Of 3 Jaish al-Muhajireen Wal Ansar Fighters|work=From Chechnya To Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the testimony of a Kazakh student who returned to Kazakhstan from Syria, the Arab Jihadist rebels in Syria were racist against the Kazakhs, assigned them the most difficult duties, and called them &quot;Chinese&quot; and there were little feelings of solidarity among the militants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=22550|title=A Cautionary Tale: &quot;I Was Brainwashed Syria War Victim,&quot; Claims Kazakh Jihadi|work=From Chechnya To Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new video of ISIL Kazakh child soldiers being given military training was reported in the media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-children-terror-training-video/27312748.html|title='Next Generation' Stars In IS Terror-Training Video Of 'Caliphate Cub'|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kazakh passports were seized by SDF.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/arisroussinos/status/714394208371666944|title=aris roussinos on Twitter|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anfenglish.com/kurdistan/relations-between-turkey-and-isis-documented-once-again#|title=ANF - Ajansa Nûçeyan a Firatê|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Shadadi emir was Abu Khatab al-Kazakhi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/vvanwilgenburg/status/701301827258736640|title=Wladimir|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Aisha al-Kazakhi died in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=25055|title=Who Was Abu Aisha Kazakhi, The Kazakh IS Militant Killed In Palmyra?|work=From Chechnya To Syria|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/716995854423293952|title=Joanna P.|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/715803908132700160|title=Joanna P.|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kazakh and Uzbek ISIS members invited entire families form their home countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-central-asia-recruitment-family-affair/27653606.html|title=IS Central Asian Recruitment Drive A Family Affair|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/716974196211978240|title=Joanna P.|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Uzbek foreign fighters in Syria include [[Imam Bukhari Jamaat]] (كتيبة الامام البخاري) (Uzbek: Imom al buxoriy katibasi) (Turkish: İmam Buhari Cemaati),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://janlok.in/tag/katibat-al-imam-bukhari/|title=Katibat Al-Imam BukhariJanlok - Janlok|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gW_zCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT84&amp;lpg=PT84&amp;dq=katibat+bukhari+iraq&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=pDCcRoTmW_&amp;sig=NQiLeoWfpObdbOuh7QZI0tAxq5M&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CFkQ6AEwCWoVChMI-PWPmPyDyAIVCms-Ch3kYQ6W#v=onepage&amp;q=katibat%20bukhari%20iraq&amp;f=false|title=The Islamic State|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=23101|title=Uzbek Imam Bukhari Jamaat In Syria Release New Training Camp Video|date=9 December 2014|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Katibat al Tawhid wal Jihad]] (كتيبة التوحيد والجهاد) (Uzbek: Tavhid va Jihod katibasi) (Turkish: Tevhid ve Cihad Cemaati),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thelineofsteel.weebly.com/news/an-update-on-katibat-al-tawhid-wal-jihad|title=An Update on Katibat al Tawhid wal Jihad|work=The Line of Steel|accessdate=25 October 2015}} https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/759296386097672192 https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/759312091396341760 https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/760212899990212608 https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/760219422313156608 https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/760219783228891136 https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/760220004893589504 https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/760214596254707712 https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/760421737221726208 https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/760422193754959872&lt;/ref&gt; and Katibat Sayfulla (كتيبة سيف الله), which is part of Jabhat al-Nusra.

Uzbek Jihadist groups operate four training camps in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2015/06/over-100-jihadist-training-camps-identified-in-iraq-and-syria.php|title=Over 100 jihadist training camps identified in Iraq and Syria|work=The Long War Journal|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Katibat Tawhid wal Jihad (Тавҳид ва Жиҳод&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ozodlik.mobi/a/27450425.html|title=Ўшда &quot;Тавҳид ва Жиҳод&quot; гуруҳининг 8 нафар аъзоси ушланди|work=Озодлик радиоси|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/681173203113394177|title=Caleb Weiss on Twitter|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;) (also called Jannat Oshiklari&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/contentlive/live-blog-syria-islamic-state-isis/27363628.html?liveshare=82008#featured|title=Live Blog: Tracking Islamic State|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/691559895934615552|title=Joanna P.|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=25096|title=From South Korea to an Uzbek Al Qaeda group in Syria…to a Russian prison|date=2 June 2016|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;) participated in the [[2015 Northwestern Syria offensive]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A-8TznIrq-g|title=Idlibga oid so'ngi qishloqlardagi janglar - Идлибга оид сўнги қишлоқлардаги жанглар|date=31 July 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=6 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A-8TznIrq-g|title=Idlibga oid so'ngi qishloqlardagi janglar - Идлибга оид сўнги қишлоқлардаги жанглар|date=31 July 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=7c7_1450110740|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] Katibat al-Tawhid wal-Jihad (Uzbeks) - Assault on SAA-held Jisr al-Shughour in Idlib prov. (April, 2015)|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Al-Ghab offensive (July–August 2015)]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A-8TznIrq-g|title=Idlibga oid so'ngi qishloqlardagi janglar - Идлибга оид сўнги қишлоқлардаги жанглар|date=31 July 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=5 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Rlx9gHXP4Z0|title=Tel Vosit qishlog'idagi amaliyot - Тел Восит қишлоғидаги амалиёт|date=5 August 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=12 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7n74ZuNUPIo|title=Sahl al G'ob mintaqasidagi fathlari - Саҳл ал Ғоб минтақасидаги фатҳлар|date=12 Aug 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=12 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Battle of Aleppo (2012–present)]]&lt;ref name=TLWJ&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2015/07/al-nusrah-front-new-coalition-aleppo.php |title= Al Nusrah Front, allies form new coalition for battle in Aleppo |publisher= The Long War Journal |last=Joscelyn |first= Thomas|agency= |date= 3 July 2015 |accessdate= 4 July 2015 |quote= Jaysh al Fateh (&quot;Army of Conquest&quot;) Qalamoun was formed in early May to fight Hezbollah, the Iranian-backed terrorist group that supports Bashar al Assad's regime, and the Islamic State.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thelineofsteel.weebly.com/news/katibat-al-tawhid-wal-jihad|title=Katibat al Tawhid wal Jihad|work=The Line of Steel|accessdate=19 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://twitter.com/ibnnabih1/status/564366855130071040 https://twitter.com/ibnnabih1/status/568739912402530304 https://twitter.com/Terror_Monitor/status/760297780510273537 https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B2PRkLQnfaE&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sendvid.com/reb3nge9|title=Sendvid - Instant video upload|work=Sendvid|accessdate=19 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/IbnNabih1/status/635383358651019264|title=Ibn Nabih|work=Twitter|accessdate=19 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=246_1450111572|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] Katibat al-Tawhid wal-Jihad (Uzbeks) - GoPro footage of the assault on Tell Mimu, Southern Aleppo countryside (November, 2015)|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=617_1450110373|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] Katibat al-Tawhid wal-Jihad (Uzbeks) - GoPro footage of the assault on Tell Bajar, Southern Aleppo countryside (November 27, 2015)|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/681523666040033280|title=Caleb Weiss|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=fb5_1451416974|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] Katibat al-Tawhid wal-Jihad Infantry GoPro footage from the assault on Banes village, South Aleppo (December 8, 2015)|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=32b_1451416430|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] Katibat al-Tawhid wal-Jihad (Uzbeks) GoPro footage from the failed assault on SAA positions in Bashkoy, Northern Aleppo (December, 2015)|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2016/06/uzbek-groups-part-of-new-offensive-in-southern-aleppo.php|title=Uzbek groups part of new offensive in southern Aleppo - The Long War Journal|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/740541178303684612|title=Caleb Weiss on Twitter|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=66f_1465396219|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] Uzbek foreign fighters (KTJ &amp; KIB) joint spearhead offensive on Marata, S. Aleppo (June 3, 2016)|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=787_1465480037|title=LiveLeak.com - Katibat al-Tawhid wal Jihad (Uzbek): A Bullet Hits An RPG During A Firefight With SAA|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/744529911780679680|title=Caleb Weiss on Twitter|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mashreghnews.ir/fa/news/592680/%D9%85%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%B1%DA%A9%D8%AA-%D8%AA%DB%8C%D9%BE-%D8%A7%D8%B2%D8%A8%DA%A9%D8%B3%D8%AA%D8%A7%D9%86%DB%8C-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%AF%D9%87-%D8%AF%D8%B1-%D9%86%D8%A8%D8%B1%D8%AF%D9%87%D8%A7%DB%8C-%D8%AC%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A8-%D8%AD%D9%84%D8%A8%D8%B9%DA%A9%D8%B3 http://elat.ir/1395/04/%D9%85%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%B1%DA%A9%D8%AA-%D8%AA%DB%8C%D9%BE-%D8%A7%D8%B2%D8%A8%DA%A9%D8%B3%D8%AA%D8%A7%D9%86%DB%8C-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%AF%D9%87-%D8%AF%D8%B1-%D9%86%D8%A8%D8%B1%D8%AF%D9%87/ http://tnews.ir/news/8e2865183806.html http://www.parset.com/FaNews/271872_msharkat_tip_azbaksatany_alghaadeh_dar_nabradhay_janob_halb_aks.html http://mashreghnews-jahan.sotiba.ir/page-79793.html http://macho.ir/news/381343/%D9%87%D9%84%D8%A7%DA%A9%D8%AA+25+%D8%AF%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%B4%DB%8C+%D8%AF%D8%B1+%D8%AC%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A8+%D9%85%D9%88%D8%B5%D9%84 http://newslist.ir/news/general/693481/%D9%85%D8%B4%D8%B1%D9%82-%D9%86%DB%8C%D9%88%D8%B2/t/%D9%85%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%B1%DA%A9%D8%AA-%D8%AA%DB%8C%D9%BE-%D8%A7%D8%B2%D8%A8%DA%A9%D8%B3%D8%AA%D8%A7%D9%86%DB%8C-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%AF%D9%87-%D8%AF%D8%B1-%D9%86%D8%A8%D8%B1%D8%AF%D9%87%D8%A7%DB%8C-%D8%AC%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A8-%D8%AD%D9%84%D8%A8-%D8%B9 http://www.shomaokhabar.com/news/details/912dcdad-2ff9-4ce1-bd6f-be8466f69366/%D9%85%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%B1%DA%A9%D8%AA-%D8%AA%DB%8C%D9%BE-%D8%A7%D8%B2%D8%A8%DA%A9%D8%B3%D8%AA%D8%A7%D9%86%DB%8C-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%AF%D9%87-%D8%AF%D8%B1-%D9%86%D8%A8%D8%B1%D8%AF%D9%87%D8%A7%DB%8C-%D8%AC%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A8-%D8%AD%D9%84%D8%A8-%D8%B9%DA%A9%D8%B3 http://sahebkhabar.ir/news/13550469/%D9%85%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%B1%DA%A9%D8%AA-%D8%AA%DB%8C%D9%BE-%D8%A7%D8%B2%D8%A8%DA%A9%D8%B3%D8%AA%D8%A7%D9%86%DB%8C-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%AF%D9%87-%D8%AF%D8%B1-%D9%86%D8%A8%D8%B1%D8%AF%D9%87%D8%A7%DB%8C-%D8%AC%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A8-%D8%AD%D9%84%D8%A8-%D8%B9%DA%A9%D8%B3 http://www.emrooznews.com/news/50219/%D9%85%D8%B4%D8%A7%D8%B1%DA%A9%D8%AA-%D8%AA%DB%8C%D9%BE-%D8%A7%D8%B2%D8%A8%DA%A9%D8%B3%D8%AA%D8%A7%D9%86%DB%8C-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%AF%D9%87-%D8%AF%D8%B1-%D9%86%D8%A8%D8%B1%D8%AF%D9%87%D8%A7%DB%8C-%D8%AC%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A8.html https://twitter.com/LongWarJournal/status/746421833516253184 http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2016/06/al-qaeda-and-allies-gain-more-ground-in-aleppo-province.php https://twitter.com/bm21_grad/status/738165652695830529 https://twitter.com/bm21_grad/status/748928984843448320 https://twitter.com/Malikejder47/status/748860653667049477 https://twitter.com/Malikejder47/status/748855880645537792 https://twitter.com/Malikejder47/status/748857036608266240 https://2ch.hk/wm/res/2225967.html http://www.peypi.com/detay/rejim-cetelerinin-kacarken-arakalarinda-biraktigi-ganimetlerin-bir-kismi-lazkiye-kinessibba/868278&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Siege of Al-Fu'ah-Kafarya (2015)]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/645283284524662785|title=Caleb Weiss|work=Twitter|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/645283498073456640|title=Caleb Weiss|work=Twitter|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0rUHZ8yXno|title=Фуа минтақаси жанглари - Fua mintaqasi janglari|date=19 September 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reddit.com/r/syriancivilwar/comments/3lknsk/katiba_turkistani_fighting_in_the_fuah_offensive/|title=Katiba Turkistani[?] fighting in the Fu'ah offensive : syriancivilwar|work=reddit|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the seizure of the Qarmid military camp.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://videoonline.su/video/6URQiQOQWXI|title=Қармид муаскари учун жанглар|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nw0mGam0n5w&amp;t=3m8s|title=Қормид &quot;Куфр&quot; муаскарига ҳужум - Qormid &quot;Kufr&quot; muaskariga hujum|date=30 April 2015|work=YouTube|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://videoonline.su/video/Nw0mGam0n5w|title=Қормид 'Куфр' муаскарига ҳужум - Qormid 'Kufr' muaskariga hujum смотреть видео онлайн бесплатно в хорошем качестве|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a former part of Jabhat al-Nusra,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foreignfighters.weebly.com/archive/category/katibat-al-tawhid-wal-jihad|title=Category: Katibat Al Tawhid Wal Jihad|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thelineofsteel.weebly.com/news/katibat-al-tawhid-wal-jihad|title=Katibat al Tawhid wal Jihad|work=The Line of Steel|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is still an ally of the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2015/02/over-150-killed-in-aleppo-fighting.php|title=Over 150 killed in Aleppo fighting|work=The Long War Journal|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The leader of Katibat al Tawhid wal Jihad is Abu Saloh.&lt;ref&gt;https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/677902783211773952 https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/750947539529203712&lt;/ref&gt;

Katibat al Imam al Bukhari is also called Imam Bukhari Jamaat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trackingterrorism.org/group/imam-bukhari-jamaat|title=Imam Bukhari Jamaat|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Uzbek group Imam Bukhari Jamaat pledged allegiance to the Taliban&lt;ref&gt;http://jihadology.net/2016/07/19/new-video-message-from-katibat-imam-al-bukhari-pledge-of-allegiance-to-mawlawi-hibat-allah-akhund-zadah https://videopress.com/embed/9jzV5hz3?hd=0&amp;amp;autoPlay=0&amp;amp;permalink=0&amp;amp;loop=0 https://twitter.com/Jihadology_Net/status/756130583105769472&lt;/ref&gt; and is an Al-Qaeda ally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foreignfighters.weebly.com/archive/imam-bukhari-jamaat|title=Imam Bukhari Jamaat|work=Foreign Fighters in Iraq and Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Uzbek foreign fighters have flocked to Katibat Imam al-Bukhari.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtoninstitute.org/policy-analysis/view/26142|title=Syria: The Epicenter of Future Jihad|publisher=|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Salahuddin al-Uzbeki is the leader of Imam Bukhari Jamaat and his son Umar, a 16 year old teenager, died while fighting in Aleppo against the Syrian military.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-commander-got-son-killed-in-syria/27225025.html|title=Why An Uzbek Militant Commander Got His Son Killed Fighting In Syria|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-uzbek-militant-jihad-age-limit/27251073.html|title=Uzbek Militant: Jihad Has No Age Limit|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A member of Imam Bukhari Jamaat defended the utilization of child soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/RFERL/status/644244128935510016|title=RFE/RL on Twitter|work=Twitter|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/644087556607475712|title=Joanna Paraszczuk|work=Twitter|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Allegiance was pledged to the Taliban and their leader Mullah Omar by Imam Bukhari Jamaat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-uzbek-militant-faction-syria-taliban/26686992.html|title=Main Uzbek Militant Faction In Syria Swears Loyalty To Taliban|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2014/12/jihadists_continue_t.php|title=Jihadists continue to advertise training camps in Iraq and Syria|work=The Long War Journal|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foreignfighters.weebly.com/archive/category/all/2|title=All Categories|work=Foreign Fighters in Iraq and Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-weeping-suicide-bomber-migrant-worker-kyrgyzstan-russia/27305925.html|title=How Babur The Migrant Worker Became Jafar The Weeping Suicide Bomber|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-tajik-brothers-syria-shirbekov/27273447.html|title=How Three Brothers Went To Syria, Taking Their Families With Them|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the VK social networking website, an illustration of a militant aiming an RPG at Santa Claus' flying sleigh was posted by Imam Bukhari Jamaat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/679668190595657729|title=Joanna P.|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The leader of Imam Bukhari Jamaat is Salohiddin. Child soldiers are being drilled by Imam Bukhari Jamaat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2015/12/uzbek-group-in-syria-trains-children-for-jihad.php|title=Uzbek group in Syria trains children for jihad|work=The Long War Journal|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; They battled in Aleppo and Latakia's Jabal al Akrad region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/703642163494658048|title=Caleb Weiss|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/Weissenberg7/status/703642754098839552|title=Caleb Weiss|work=Twitter|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://buhoriy.com/News_d85168.html|title=Бухорий Катибаси Ҳалабга ёрдамчи куч юборди|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://buhoriy.com/m/News_d85168.html|title=Бухорий Катибаси Ҳалабга ёрдамчи куч юборди|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=82e_1457733088|title=LiveLeak.com - [Combat edit] Katibat Imam al-Buxoriy (Uzbeks) GoPro footage of clashes with SAA at Mount Akrad, Latakia (Feb, 2016)|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VJVznSs34Ts|title=Lazaqiyaning Jabal Akrod tog'ida kofirlar bilan to'qnashuv|date=13 February 2016|publisher=|accessdate=18 April 2016|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Katibat Sayfulla is part of Jabhat al-Nusra.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/639007939735519232|title=Joanna Paraszczuk|work=Twitter|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/islamic-state-al-nusra-front-crowdfunding/27272117.html|title=Al-Qaeda's Affiliate In Syria Tries Crowdfunding|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It participated in the [[Siege of Abu al-Duhur Airbase]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=24130|title=Uzbek-Led Katiba Sayfullah (Nusra) Involved In Abu Duhour Air Base Assault|work=From Chechnya To Syria|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/645235946883932160|title=Joanna Paraszczuk|work=Twitter|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Uzbek fighters in ISIL have participated in suicide bombings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailystar.com.lb/News/Middle-East/2015/Mar-12/290493-isis-says-australian-teen-behind-iraq-suicide-bombing.ashx|title=ISIS says Australian teen behind Iraq suicide bombing|work=The Daily Star Newspaper - Lebanon|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ISIL has recruited hundreds of Tajiks from [[Tajikistan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/russia-tajik-in-limbo-after-tricked-syria-islamic-state/27445161.html|title=After Fleeing IS Recruiters, A Precarious Limbo In Moscow|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/tajikistan-double-estimate-of-islamic-state-members/27509293.html|title=Authorities Say Up To 1,000 Tajiks Joined IS In Syria, Iraq|work=RadioFreeEurope/RadioLiberty|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.tj/en/news/how-many-tajik-jihadists-fighting-isil-syria-and-iraq|title=How many Tajik jihadists fighting for ISIL in Syria and Iraq? - ASIA-Plus|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.farsnews.com/newstext.aspx?nn=13940923001505|title=Farsnews|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iraqinews.com/arab-world-news/tajik-prosecutor-reveals-death-100-tajik-fighters-ranks-isis/|title=Tajik Prosecutor reveals the death of 100 Tajik fighters in the ranks of ISIS - Iraqi News|first=Abdelhak|last=Mamoun|date=3 August 2015|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.crisisgroup.org/|title=International Crisis Group|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamicinvitationturkey.com/2015/11/24/over-300-tajik-isil-members-killed-in-syria-iraq/|title=Over 300 Tajik ISIL Members Killed in Syria, Iraq - Islamic Invitation Turkey|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.barackobama.ir/en/news/39427/over-300-tajik-isil-members-killed-in-syria,-iraq&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.irib.ir/news/world/asia/item/213594-over-100-tajik-citizens-killed-in-syria,-iraq-chief-prosecutor|title=Over 100 Tajik citizens killed in Syria, Iraq: Chief prosecutor|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.avesta.tj/eng/5854-over-100-tajik-citizens-killed-in-syria-iraq.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jihadology.net/2015/01/20/the-clear-banner-tajik-fighters-in-iraq-and-syria/|title=The Clear Banner: Tajik Fighters in Iraq and Syria|first=Aaron Y.|last=Zelin|date=20 January 2015|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://eurasianews.info/en/node/8189&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.syriahr.com/en/2015/01/18/about-200-tajik-citizens-fighting-in-syria-iraq/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presstv.com/Detail/2015/06/08/414891/Tajik-ISIL-Iraq-Syria-Tajikistan-Gulmurod-Khalimov|title=PressTV-‘Over 400 Tajiks join ISIL ranks'|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;tajik44.rssing.com/chan-48521376/all_p3.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://el-akhbar.com/en/Over-Tajik-ISIL-Members-Killed-31906/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tajikistannews.net/index.php/sid/238855515|title=Over 300 Tajik ISIL Members Killed in Syria, Iraq|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://pk.shafaqna.com/EN/PK/524026&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islam14.com/english/?p=14587|title=Over 100 Tajik citizens killed in Syria, Iraq: Chief prosecutor - islam 14 english|date=1 August 2015|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eurasia-online.com/300-tajik-isis-members-killed-in-syria-and-iraq/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.voanews.com/content/rferl-why-did-a-tajik-student-and-mixed-martial-arts-champ-die-for-is-in-iraq/2656421.html|title=Why Did Tajik Student, MMA Champ Die for IS in Iraq?|first=|last=RFE/RL|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Former Yugoslavia==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; table align=&quot;right&quot;
|+ Fatalities among ethnic Albanian fighters
|-
!Citizenship!! Killed!! As of
|-
|Albania || 18 || March 2016&lt;ref name=&quot;Bogdani&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Aleksandra Bogdani|title=Albania Faces ‘Jihadi Fighters in the Shadows’ Threat|publisher=Balkan Insight|url=http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/albania-faces-jihadi-fighters-in-the-shadows-threat-03-21-2016|date=18 March 2016|accessdate=3 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Kosovo || {{circa|60}} || March 2016&lt;ref name=&quot;Qafmolla&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Ervin Qafmolla|title=‘Offer Kosovar Fighters &quot;Jihadi Rehab&quot; to Combat Extremism’|publisher=Balkan Insight|url=http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/offer-kosovar-fighters-jihadi-rehab-to-combat-extremism--03-23-2016|date=24 March 2016|accessdate=3 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Macedonia || 15 ||January 2015&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Amre Sahan|publisher=Iraqi News|title=130 Macedonian and Serbian nationals fight alongside ISIS in Iraq and Syria|url=http://www.iraqinews.com/iraq-war/130-macedonian-serbian-nationals-fight-alongside-isis-iraq-syria/|date=30 April 2015|accessdate=3 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Montenegro || 1 || January 2016&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=RTS|title=Mladić iz Plava poginuo u borbama u Siriji|url=http://www.rts.rs/page/stories/sr/story/11/Region/2201983/Mladi%C4%87+iz+Plava+poginuo+u+borbama+u+Siriji.html|date=7 February 2016|accessdate=3 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Total || {{circa|94}} || 2015–16
|}
Muslims from the Balkans have joined the opposition in fighting against the Syrian government, and some have been killed. Many recruits came from Serbia's Muslim-inhabited [[Sandžak]] region, particularly the city of [[Novi Pazar]]. Several hundred come from Albania, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Kosovo, Montenegro and Macedonia. Many of the recruits were [[Salafi]]sts and, though denied by some Salafist leaders, Rešad Plojović, the deputy leader of the Sandžak muftiate, said that &quot;some organisations and individuals [are recruiting Balkan Muslims]. There are centers or individuals who probably have connections with certain organisations, and they are motivating people. They also may know ways to transport them to the war zone. Let's be frank. Many here do not even know where Syria is. They cannot know how to go there and get involved in all that is happening there.&quot; Anel Grbović, a journalist from Novi Pazar, writes that most fighters from the Sandžak had been removed from the country's two official Islamic communities before traveling to Syria. &quot;The fact is, there are illegal organisations recruiting people here. The fact is, there are houses where they come together. The fact is, there are facilities where they conduct their religious rituals – which means they exclude themselves from the mosque. That means they exclude themselves from the system of the Islamic community and are more easily influenced by some individuals or organisations.&quot; As for Albanian Muslims in Kosovo and Macedonia, they fought for the rebels in order to help &quot;Sunni brothers&quot; in their fight. At least one Macedonian fighter said he was recruited via an intermediary in Vienna. From Bosnia and Herzegovina, many [[Bosniaks]] joined the Nusra Front as Salafists ([[Islam in Bosnia|Salafism came to Bosnia]] during the [[Bosnian War]] with Saudi financing, though foreign fighters in that war stayed on in the country despite controversy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6642353.stm |title=Bosnia fighters face uncertain fate |publisher=BBC News |date=10 May 2007 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;). Some of relatives of the fighters have said that the leader of the predominantly Salafist Bosnian village of [[Gornja Maoča]], Nusret Imamović, recruited the fighters; however he refused to be interviewed about the allegations. The director of the Bosnian [[State Investigation and Protection Agency]], Goran Zubac, said that his office had questioned at least eight men linked to recruiting and sending the fighters to Syria, while he said his office was monitoring the Salafists. &quot;If our priority is to fight against terrorism and these activities are a part of this sector, then you can rest assured that nobody in the State Investigation and Protection Agency is sleeping.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Teodorovic Milos |author2=Ron Synovitz |url=http://www.rferl.org/articleprintview/25011213.html |title=Balkan Militants Join Syria's Rebel Cause |publisher=Radio Free Europe / Radio Liberty |date=8 June 2013 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Federalna televizija|FTV]] reported that a group of 52 Bosniak fighters went to Syria since the fighting commenced, though 32 fighters returned, while two were killed. An additional nine Bosniaks released a video tape saying they were going to fight in [[Homs]], though they also mentioned the ''jihad''s in Iraq and Afghanistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dalje.com/en-world/bosnian-radical-islamists-preparing-to-join-syrian-rebels/473536 |title=Bosnian radical Islamists preparing to join Syrian rebels |publisher=Dalje.com |date=26 June 2013 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By April 2015, a total of 232 [[Kosovo Albanians]] had gone to Syria to fight with Islamist groups, most commonly the IS.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Economist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=The Economist|title=Fight the Good Fight: With the Western Balkans at Peace, Some Go Abroad to Look for War|date=18 April 2015|url=http://www.economist.com/news/europe/21648697-western-balkans-peace-some-go-abroad-look-war-fight-good-fight}}&lt;/ref&gt; Forty of these are from the town of [[Ferizaj]] (Srbica), according to Kosovo police reports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.b92.net/info/vesti/index.php?yyyy=2014&amp;mm=05&amp;dd=02&amp;nav_category=640&amp;nav_id=843121 |title=100 Albanaca sa KiM ratuje u Siriji |work=Vesti|publisher=B92 |date= |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; By September 2014, a total of 48 ethnic Albanians from several countries were killed fighting in Syria and Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Info.ks|title=Još jedan kosovski Albanac poginuo u Siriji|trans_title=Another Kosovo Albanian Killed in Syria|language=Serbian|date=15 September 2014|url=http://www.info-ks.net/vijesti/crna-hronika/48188/jos-jedan-kosovski-albanac-poginuo-u-siriji}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Kosovar Centre for Security Studies, around 60 Kosovar fighters have been killed in combat as of March 2016.&lt;ref name=&quot;Qafmolla&quot;/&gt; As of March 2016, the Albanian Government estimates that over 100 Albanian citizens have joined militant groups in Syria and Iraq, 18 of whom have been killed and 12 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bogdani&quot;/&gt;

[[Albanians in Macedonia|Macedonian citizens of Albanian descent]] are also fighting in Syria, and a number are reported to have been kiled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.republika.mk/?p=123640|title=Another Macedonian Albanian reported killed in Syria|work=Republika Online|accessdate=12 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/sixth-macedonian-albanian-reported-killed-in-syria|title=Another Macedonian Albanian Reported Killed in Syria|publisher=Balkaninsight.com|accessdate=12 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chechnya and Russia==
The Russian security agency [[Federal Security Service]] in July 2013 estimated that about 200 Russian citizens were fighting for the Syrian opposition, while it expressed fears the fighters could carry out militant attacks upon returning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.themoscowtimes.com/news/article/fsb-worried-about-russian-fighters-in-syria/480036.html#ixzz2XprNQs99 |title=FSB Worried About Russian Fighters in Syria |publisher=The Moscow Times |date= |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2013, the Russian media estimate for Russian citizens fighting for the rebels was increased to 400.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mignews.com/news/society/world/051213_152234_59587.html |script-title=ru:Общество &amp;#124; Россия готовит спецназ к противостоянию боевикам из Сирии |language=ru |publisher=MIGnews |date= |accessdate=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Chechen-led [[Jaish al-Muhajireen wal-Ansar]] (JMA), which was said to be cooperating with the [[al-Nusra Front]], was mid 2013, according to ''[[The Washington Free Beacon]]'', one of the leading recruiters of foreign fighters into the jihad in Syria to fight Assad. Its online forum was said to show an easy access route, via Turkey, to the battlefield, which brought in more fighters. The ''Free Beacon'' also reported that Chechen fighters were bringing with them Russian-made [[Strela 2|SA-7 anti-aircraft missiles]] which are shoulder-fired and could be used to target civilian commercial airliners.&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;/&gt; 
In December 2013, [[Jaish al-Muhajireen wal-Ansar]] (JMA) split away from the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant (ISIL),&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.rferl.org/content/georgia-isis-islamic-state-pankisi-gorge-russia/26637101.html Should Georgia Fear IS Threat To Its Pankisi Gorge?]&quot;. Radio Free Europe / Radio Liberty. October 14, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; and continued respecting the [[Bay'at|Oath of Allegiance]] they had made to the [[Caucasus Emirate]]'s [[Dokka Umarov]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Syria crisis: Omar Shishani, Chechen jihadist leader|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-25151104|work=BBC|date=3 December 2013|accessdate=20 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2015, JMA pledged allegiance to the [[al-Qaeda]] affiliated [[al-Nusra Front]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.reuters.com/article/2015/09/23/us-mideast-crisis-syria-nusra-idUSKCN0RN1Z920150923 Insurgent group pledges allegiance to al Qaeda's Syria wing]&quot;. Reuters. 23 September 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;  
As of September 2015, according to [[Civic Chamber of the Russian Federation|Russian Civic Chamber]]'s commission on public diplomacy and compatriots abroad, approximately 2,500 Russian nationals and 7,000 citizens of other post-Soviet republics were fighting alongside [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|ISIL]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.ibtimes.com/security-service-moscow-airport-detains-siberian-man-suspected-join-isis-syria-2111685 Security Service At Moscow Airport Detains Siberian Man Suspected To Join ISIS In Syria]&quot;. ''IBTimes''. 24 September 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

Khamza Shishani is a leader in Ajnad al-Kavkaz.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=24632|title=A More Detailed Biography Of Khamza Shishani of Ajnad al-Kavkaz|date=7 January 2016|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/672847093225136128|title=Joanna Paraszczuk on Twitter|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ajnad al-Kavkaz is Chechen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://twitter.com/joaska_/status/720252873079070720|title=Joanna Paraszczuk on Twitter|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mesop.de/mesop-special-new-chechen-faction-ajnad-kavkaz-fights-alongside-jan-in-idlib-by-joanna-paraszczuk/|title=Mesopotamische Gesellschaft  « MESOP SPECIAL : New Chechen Faction Ajnad Kavkaz Fights Alongside JAN In Idlib / By Joanna Paraszczuk|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chechensinsyria.com/?p=23585|title=UPDATE: Chechen Faction Ajnad Kavkaz Fights Alongside JAN In Idlib|date=30 March 2015|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chechens lead [[Junud al-Sham]].

==Southeast Asia==
[[Indonesia]] and [[Malaysia]] are the main source of foreign fighters from Southeast Asia with an estimated of 500 Indonesians and 200 Malaysians have travelling to Syria to fight for the [[Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant|Islamic State]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.themalaymailonline.com/what-you-think/article/why-malaysia-has-a-problem-with-islamic-state-julien-gradot |title=Why Malaysia has a problem with Islamic State |first=Julien |last=Gradot |publisher=The Malay Mail |date=21 October 2015 |accessdate=21 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also suspected that more than 200 Filipinos,{{by whom|date=February 2016}} mostly the members of [[Abu Sayyaf]] (ASG) and [[Bangsamoro Islamic Freedom Fighters]] (BIFF) are training and fighting in Iraq and Syria under Islamic State.&lt;ref name=&quot;aus2&quot;/&gt; Southeast Asian countries are the origin of approximately 500 child fighters in ISIL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almayadeen.net/news/syria-QFMkgbau,ES37aVvANTbkw/%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A7%D8%B3%D8%AA%D8%AE%D8%A8%D8%A7%D8%B1%D8%A7%D8%AA-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%85%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%8A%D8%B2%D9%8A%D8%A9---%D8%AF%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%B4--%D9%8A%D8%AF%D8%B1%D8%A8-500-%D8%B7%D9%81%D9%84-%D9%85%D9%86-%D8%AF%D9%88%D9%84-%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%B9%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%85-%D9%81%D9%8A|title=الميادين - الأخبار - &quot;داعش&quot; يدرّب 500 طفل من دول العالم في سوريا|author=قناة الميادين|work=قناة الميادين|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Western countries==
Both European converts and immigrant or immigrant's children have gone to fight for the Syrian opposition. This includes citizens from France (with the leading number of fighters), followed by the United Kingdom, Germany, Belgium, the Netherlands &lt;ref name=&quot;ita&quot;/&gt; and Italy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ispionline.it/it/pubblicazione/home-grown-jihadism-italy-10309|title=Home-Grown Jihadism in Italy|publisher=Ispionline.it|accessdate=12 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://mobile.nytimes.com/2014/06/28/opinion/sylvie-kauffmann-frances-homegrown-jihadists.html?referrer=&amp;_r=0|title=Foreign rebel fighters in the Syrian Civil War|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=12 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A report by the International Centre for Counter-Terrorism - The Hague (ICCT) from April 2016 shows that there is a total of 3,922-4,294 foreign fighters from EU Member States of whom 30 percent have returned to their home countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt; EU anti-terrorism coordinator [[Gilles de Kerchove]] said that this was a worrying trend as those who return could be more radicalized. [[EUROPOL]] Director [[Rob Wainright]] issued his 2013 report and said that the returning fighters &quot;could incite other volunteers to join the armed struggle,&quot; as well as use their training, combat experience, knowledge and contacts to conduct such activities within the EU.&lt;ref name=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ansamed.ansa.it/ansamed/en/news/sections/generalnews/2013/06/19/Syria-EU-eyes-potential-threat-volunteer-fighters_8893641.html |title=Syria: EU eyes potential threat from volunteer fighters |publisher=Ansamed.ansa.it |date= |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were also Australians&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/middle-east/syria/130301/the-australian-terrorist-abu-walid-yusuf-toprakkaya-syria-rebels-assad |title=An Australian in Syria: The journey of a foreign fighter |publisher=GlobalPost |date=4 March 2013 |accessdate=2 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and citizens of the United States fighting for the Syrian opposition camp,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.voanews.com/a/us-man-suspected-of-fighting-alongside-militants-killed-in-syria/2429355.html|title=Details Emerge About Douglas McCain, American Jihadist Killed in Syria|work=VOA|accessdate=12 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite possible prosecution by their government for terrorism amid fears they could return home and carry out attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://icct.nl/publication/pathways-of-foreign-fighters-policy-options-and-their-unintended-consequences/ | title=Pathways of Foreign Fighters: Policy Options and Their (Un)Intended Consequences | date=26 May 2015 | publisher= The International Centre for Counter-Terrorism - The Hague (ICCT) | accessdate=1 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Australian security agencies estimated about 200 Australians to be fighting in the country with dozens said to be part of the Nusra Front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://muslimvillage.com/2013/07/01/41109/australia-lists-anti-bashar-fighters-as-a-terrorist-group/ |title=Australian rebel fighters in Syria could face terrorism charges |publisher=MuslimVillage.com |date= |accessdate=2 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first European to fight for the Syrian opposition was reported by ''[[Der Spiegel]]'' to be a fighter for the Free Syrian Army who was &quot;a Frenchman who had just turned 24 and comes from a wealthy family. He just turned up here with his credit card in hand.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;de&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Putz |first=Ulrike |url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/foreign-jihadists-declare-war-on-syria-s-assad-a-824875.html |title=Foreign Jihadists Declare War on Syria's Assad |publisher=Spiegel.de |date=30 March 2012 |accessdate=1 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Michigan]]-born U.S.-convert to Islam was also the first U.S. citizen to be killed in Syria, reportedly by the government, as she was taking part in a reconnaissance mission with two Britons near Aleppo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/06/30/syria-michigan-woman-killed/2477393/ |title=From Michigan to a violent death in Syria |publisher=Usatoday.com |date=10 June 2013 |accessdate=1 July 2013 |first=Niraj |last=Warikoo}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2013, a U.S.-Egyptian man named Amiir Farouk Ibrahim (from Pennsylvania) went missing in Syria, presumed by the media to be fighting with rebel forces. His passport was discovered, amongst others, in an [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] base which had been captured by Kurdish rebels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/170185 |title=U.S. Passport Found among Syria Jihadists |publisher=Israel National News |date=23 July 2013 |accessdate=28 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; His family was aware he was in Syria, but his father did not believe that his son had gone there for humanitarian purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wpxi.com/news/news/local/pittsburgh-man-reportedly-dead-syria/nY4rk/ |title=Pittsburgh man reportedly dead in Syria |publisher=www.wpxi.com |date= |accessdate=28 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://triblive.com/news/editorspicks/4415705-74/ibrahim-syria-syrian#ixzz2a9XASaYD&amp;w |title=Pittsburgh man reported killed in Syria |publisher=TribLIVE |date= |accessdate=20 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 August, two Lebanese-Swedish brothers, Hassan and Moatasem Deeb, were killed in a rebel assault on the Abu Zeid army checkpoint near Qalaat al-Hosn, according to their cousin and a Tripoli cleric. Moatasem died as he exploded his suicide vest in a car at the checkpoint and his brother died in the ensuing fighting. This followed their other brother, Rabih's, death in Tripoli the previous year. The cleric claimed that the deaths were not in vain as that the checkpoint had been taken by rebels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2013/08/03/lebanese-swedish-brothers-killed-in-syria/#ixzz2b0P2Bc5u |title=Lebanese-Swedish brothers killed in Syria |publisher=Fox News |date= 3 August 2013|accessdate=20 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; A suicide attack on a school where Syrian troops were stationed in Deir al-Zor was said to have been perpetrated by an Australian named Abu Asma al-Australi for the al-Nusra Front. Reports indicated he was from Queensland and travelled to Syria with his wife before sending her back to Australia. A spokesman for the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade said that the Australian government was aware of the reports that an Australian had killed himself, but could not confirm any of the speculation. He added that the government had concern about its citizens fighting in the country, including with the al-Nusra Front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author1=Natalie O'Brien |author2=Nick Ralston |url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/australian-man-in-syria-abu-asma-alaustrali-suspected-to-be-suicide-bomber-20130914-2trfh.html#ixzz2erdFr4qL |title=Australian man in Syria, 'Abu Asma al-Australi', suspected to be suicide bomber |publisher=Theage.com.au |date=14 September 2013 |accessdate=20 September 2013 |location=Melbourne}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Syrian-born head of a Stockholm mosque, Haytham Rahmeh, reportedly smuggled weapons to the rebels for 18 months. Rahmeh, a member of the Syrian National Council and a former member of the Muslim Brotherhood, was said to have bought the weapons mainly in Libya and with support from the Commission for Civilian Protection and then transported them through Turkey to Syria. In June 2013, the chief analyst{{who|date=June 2014}} at the Swedish intelligence agency{{which|date=June 2014}} expressed concern about the dangers of those returning from the fighting and noted that at least 30 Swedes were known to have fought in Syria and &quot;many&quot; had returned. On 27 May 2014, a Somali and two Kosovars, all Norwegian citizens from [[Oslo]], were arrested after being suspected of supporting the ISIS. The death of Kosovar, Egzon Avdyli, who grew up in Norway was highlighted in the media as he fought for ISIS. He was also a spokesman for the Norway-based [[Profetens Ummah|Prophet's Ummah]] and was said to have left for Syria earlier in the year. He &quot;supported the establishment of an Islamic state in Norway or other Western countries.&quot; At least 50 Norwegians were thought to have traveled to Syria to fight for the Islamists, with Norwegian intelligence groups said to be concerned of the danger of them returning. In a joint operation in mid-March, Spanish and Moroccan security services targeted an al Qaeda recruiting network and arrested four suspected members in Spain and three others in Morocco. The network, whose activities extend to Morocco, Belgium, France, Tunisia, Turkey, Libya, Mali, Indonesia, and Syria, is headed by Melilla resident Mustafa Maya Amaya, who funneled recruits to the ISIS, the Al Nusrah Front and AQIM. Some of those arrested had returned home from conflict zones such as Syria; and in January, a suspected jihadist returning from Syria was arrested in Malaga as a potential &quot;threat to national security.&quot; On 30 April, Spanish security forces, working with French police, arrested Abdelmalek Tanem, a dual Algerian-French citizen, in [[Almeria]], who had recently returned from Syria where he worked towards facilitating integration of Europeans into the Al Nusrah Front and ISIS. On 30 May 2014, Spanish security forces arrested six people in [[Melilla]] who were involved in a network that sends fighters to al Qaeda camps in Syria, Mali, and Libya. The cell leader, Benaissa Laghmouchi Baghdadi, had spent eight months in Syria and also had ties to [[al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb]] (AQIM) and the [[Movement for Oneness and Jihad in West Africa]] (MUJAO) in Mali. Some of those arrested also had linked to [[Sharia4Spain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;more&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsinenglish.no/2014/04/30/norwegian-killed-in-syrian-conflict/|title=Norwegian killed in Syrian conflict|publisher=Newsinenglish.no|accessdate=12 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Western countries, including the U.K., have provided aid to the rebels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Kim Sengupta |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/revealed-what-the-west-has-given-syrias-rebels-8756447.html |title=Revealed: What the West has given Syria's rebels |publisher=The Independent |date=11 August 2013 |accessdate=20 September 2013 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of November 2013, there are believed to be approximately 600 fighters from Western countries in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=American and International Militants Drawn to Syria|url=http://www.adl.org/combating-hate/international-extremism-terrorism/c/syria-foreign-fighters.html#.Ul1ybBDQvZ0|publisher=Anti-Defamation League|accessdate=25 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Norway's Thomas Hegghammer issued a report that suggested one in nine Westerners who fight in foreign ''[[jihad]]''ist insurgencies end up becoming involved in attack plots back home. The Associate Director of the [[Melbourne School of Government]] David Malet, however, suggested that while research on foreign fighters was a new field, different studies showed another view to the likelihood of [[blowback (intelligence)|blowback]] from returning fighters. &quot;Other studies show that most foreign fighters simply resume their previous lives so long as they are provided [[amnesty]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aus&quot;/&gt;

The U.K. arrested former [[Guantanamo Bay detention camp]] detainee Moazzam Begg for &quot;attending [a] terrorist training camp&quot; in Syria and &quot;facilitating terrorism overseas.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/europe/2014/02/uk-holds-ex-guantanamo-inmate-over-syria-trip-2014225143222328690.html |title=UK holds ex-Guantanamo inmate over Syria trip |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, France was estimated to have up to 700 of its citizens fighting in Syria.&lt;ref name=&quot;aus2&quot;/&gt; At least one pregnant Austrian indicated she wanted to return home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rt.com/news/195100-syria-isis-austria-teenagers|title=Pregnant Austrian teen who ran off to join ISIS says she 'made a mistake'|work=RT English|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
There were an estimated 50&lt;ref name=&quot;aus2&quot; /&gt;–100 Australians fighting in the country as of January 2014, with total calculations for the war reaching about 200 fighters. About six were reported to have died and the others were suggested as having returned home. In Sydney and Melbourne, in particular, opponents and supporters of the government have resorted to beatings, assaults, shootings and property, largely along sectarian lines. There were more than 15 incidents of violence involving members of the Lebanese, Turkish and Syrian communities, although in 2013 it had decreased from the previous year. The [[Australian Security Intelligence Organisation]] (ASIO) reported at the end of the year: &quot;The situation in Syria, with the potential for violence spilling into other parts of the Middle East, increases the possibility of associated communal violence in Australia and remains a concern for ASIO.&quot; Zaky Mallah, the first person to be charged and acquitted under Australia's anti-terrorism laws, suggested: &quot;The majority of Australians heading to Syria are from Lebanese backgrounds. The Lebanese youth here feel disadvantaged, isolated and discriminated against. Many [are] unemployed and have turned to religion as a result.&quot; After the death of a couple from western Sydney in the country, Immigration Minister [[Scott Morrison (politician)|Scott Morrison]] suggested those fighting in Syria could risk losing their citizenship, while the [[Australian Federal Police]] added that those returning from the fighting would be considered a national security threat. ASIO confiscated the passports of those it suspected of travelling to engage in &quot;politically motivated violence;&quot; from mid-2012 to mid-2013 18 passports were confiscated. Former Victoria Multicultural Affairs Commissioner and founder of the [[Australian Arabic Council]] [[Joseph Wakim]] said:&lt;ref name=&quot;aus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Sophie Cousins |url=http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2014/02/australian-fighters-syria-alarm-officials-201422132139299187.html |title=Australian fighters in Syria alarm officials |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=4 February 2014 |accessdate=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The new coalition government has been critical of both sides and sympathetic to the Christian minorities who have been targeted by the anti-Assad {{sic}} forces. With Australia's suite of anti-terror laws, and concerted efforts by our intelligence agencies to share resources and establish strategic community contacts, Australia's buffer against terrorist acts has been bolstered. Local community elders and clerics have also been more vigilant and public in encouraging good citizenship and close cooperation with authorities, including denouncing potential terrorists. [Those Australian fighting in Syria had a perceived moral duty to aid their Muslim brothers to] rid Syria of an infidel secular authoritarian regime and replace it with one that upholds their brand version of pure Islam. While there is no evidence of such individuals planning attacks in Australia, their recruitment activities tap into a population of Australian-born and disengaged youth searching for a worthy cause – and at times martyrdom.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Ireland===
As of January 2015, the [[Department of Justice and Equality]] estimates that approximately 50 Irish residents have travelled to Syria to fight for rebel forces in the civil war since 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=O'Halloran|first1=Marie|last2=O'Regan|first2=Michael|title=Shatter says up to 30 Irish residents gone to fight in Syria|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/news/politics/oireachtas/shatter-says-up-to-30-irish-residents-gone-to-fight-in-syria-1.1680575|accessdate=3 June 2014|publisher=The Irish Times|date=5 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; At least three [[Irish nationality law|Irish citizens]] are known to have been killed in combat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=McQuinn|first1=Cormac|title=26 fighters have left Ireland to join Syrian rebels|url=http://www.independent.ie/irish-news/26-fighters-have-left-ireland-to-join-syrian-rebels-29173266.html|accessdate=3 June 2014|work=Irish Independent|date=4 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Department of Justice, many have &quot;participated in the conflict under the flag of fundamentalist and extreme organisations&quot; and &quot;may pose certain threats&quot; upon their return to Ireland and the [[European Union]]. The [[Garda Síochána]] (Irish national police) &quot;will continue to monitor developments in this area and take action as required,&quot; including officers from the Garda Middle Eastern Bureau of the [[Special Detective Unit]] (SDU) and Garda Racial, Intercultural and Diversity Office (GRIDO).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Ryan|first1=Nicky|title=Gardaí monitoring potential radicalisation of Irish residents in Syrian conflict|url=http://www.thejournal.ie/syria-irish-conflict-travel-arms-rebel-civil-war-1300726-Feb2014/|publisher=thejournal.ie|accessdate=3 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[The International Centre for the Study of Radicalisation and Political Violence]] (ICSR), &quot;per capita, Ireland is probably the biggest (contributor of fighters) of all the countries we looked at because Ireland has a small population.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Malik|first1=Shiv|title=Syria conflict drawing hundreds of jihadists from Europe, says report|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/apr/03/syria-hundreds-jihadists-europe|accessdate=3 June 2014|work=The Guardian|date=3 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to media reports, [[Garda Crime &amp; Security Branch|Garda]] and [[Directorate of Military Intelligence (Ireland)|Military Intelligence]] are monitoring between 30 and 60 potential [[Jihadism|Islamist fighters]] both in the Irish state and Irish citizens fighting abroad in Syria and Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Brady|first1=Tom|last2=Phelan|first2=Shane|title=30 irish jihad fighters travelling to middle east from Dublin base|url=http://www.herald.ie/news/30-irish-jihad-fighters-travelling-to-middle-east-from-dublin-base-30525759.html|accessdate=25 August 2014|agency=The Herald|date=21 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Secret army squad keeps watch on 60 Al Qaeda in Ireland|url=http://www.thestar.ie/star/secret-army-squad-keeps-watch-on-60-al-qaeda-in-ireland-26336/|accessdate=7 February 2014|newspaper=Irish Daily Star|date=26 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Security sources estimated that some 20 fighters may have returned to Ireland as of November 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=O'Keefe|first1=Cormac|title=Islamic terrorists: Radicalisation and fighters returning to Ireland are our biggest threat|url=http://www.irishexaminer.com/viewpoints/analysis/islamic-terrorists-radicalisation-and-fighters-returning-to-ireland-are-our-biggest-threat-366201.html|accessdate=21 November 2015|publisher=Irish Examiner|date=21 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
Robin Simcox of the [[Henry Jackson Society]] claimed that the number of British citizens who went to fight in Syria is higher than during the [[Iraq War]] and [[War in Afghanistan (2001-present)|Afghanistan War]] combined. The International Centre for the Study of Radicalisation assessed that up to 366 British citizens had been involved in the war in Syria as of December 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2014/05/why-british-boys-are-fighting-s-201458103336479836.html|title=Why British boys are fighting in Syria's war|date=12 May 2014|accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a report from the International Centre for Counter-Terrorism – The Hague from April 2016, showed that there are between 700-760 foreign fighters from the United Kingdom. Over 350 people have returned to the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt; The Rayat al-Tawheed group is composed of British combatants linked to the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant. Similarly, the suffix &quot;al-Britani&quot; was adopted by British Islamist fighters. In May 2014, a British citizen was killed in fighting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-27681189 |title=Syria crisis: British man 'killed during battle' |publisher=Bbc.com |date=3 June 2014 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Free Syrian Army]]'s Abdullah al-Bashir asserted that British fighters were the largest foreign contingent of Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.alalam.ir/news/1597606 |title=British militants, the most bloodthirsty in Syria |publisher=En.alalam.ir |date=26 May 2014 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were also a few [[British-Somali]] fighters for ISIS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hull |first=Liz |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2682120/Teenage-twin-sisters-Manchester-crept-bedrooms-middle-night-flew-join-Isis-Syria.html?ITO=1490&amp;ns_mchannel=rss&amp;ns_campaign=1490 |title=Manchester teen twin sisters crept out of bedrooms and flew to Syria to join Isis |publisher=Dailymail.co.uk |date=6 July 2014 |accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[Ramadan]] 2014, over 140 Imams signed an [[open letter]] asking British Muslims not to travel to Syria (as well as ISIS conflict that had spread to Iraq at the time). Additionally, they were urged to make donations to people in the country from the U.K. itself with one such imam, Shahid Raza of Leicester Central Mosque, making the call.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-28182206 |title=Syria and Iraq: Ramadan plea to British Muslims |publisher=Bbc.com |date=6 July 2014 |accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2014, Metropolitan Police Commissioner [[Bernard Hogan-Howe]] said: &quot;We still have an average of five people joining them (ISIS) a week. Five a week doesn't sound much but when you realise there are 50 weeks in a year, {{Sic}} 250 more would be 50% more than we think have gone already. Those are the ones that we believe have gone. There may be many more who set out to travel to another country and meandered over to Syria and Iraq in a way that is not always possible to spot when you have failed states and leaky borders.&quot; He added that this estimate was a &quot;minimum&quot; and &quot;the drumbeat of terrorism in Britain&quot; is now &quot;faster and more intense.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;presstv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presstv.in/detail/2014/10/22/383164/5-britons-join-isil-every-week/#sthash.fU2p5AHm.dpuf|title=Five Britons join ISIL every week: UK police chief|publisher=presstv.in|accessdate=30 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At least one aspirant convert attacker, had his passport confiscated on suspicion he was to go overseas to fight. On 21 October, he was killed after trying to run over two Canadian security service personnel.&lt;ref name=&quot;cbc&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/martin-couture-rouleau-case-underscores-passport-seizure-dilemma-1.2807239|title=Martin Couture-Rouleau case underscores passport seizure dilemma |publisher=cbc.ca|accessdate=3 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An ISIS video released by British-based Abu Muthanna al Yemeni claimed &quot;We have brothers from Bangladesh, from Iraq, from Cambodia, Australia, U.K.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEA&quot;/&gt; ISIS also threatened fighters with execution for returning to Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;rt2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rt.com/uk/199468-british-jihadists-home-death/|title=ISIS threatens to kill British jihadists who want to go home |publisher=rt.com|accessdate=3 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November, ''[[Regnum news agency|Regnum]]'' reported that &quot;White Widow&quot; [[Samantha Lewthwaite]], who had fought in Syria the previous month, was shot dead by a Russian voluntary sniper while she was fighting for the Ukrainian volunteer battalion [[Aidar Battalion|Aidar]] during the [[War in Donbass]]. Though it was not formally verified, and her father has not confirmed the reports, it was reported in the Western press.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/uk-news/wanted-british-white-widow-terrorist-4616471|title=Wanted British 'White Widow' terrorist Samantha Lewthwaite 'shot dead by Russian sniper in Ukraine'|author=Will Stewart|date=12 November 2014|work=mirror|accessdate=4 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===France===
An ICCT report shows that more than 900 people have travelled from France to Syria and/or Iraq by October 2015. There is no profile that defines a French foreign fighter, as is the case with other countries. This means that foreign fighters come from all regions and socio-economic environments.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt;

Following the accusation of French government by a mother in court , it was clear that a teen and some young joined in ISIS in Syria. One of the three young died during this journey. The women accused the government in court of failing to protect her son from travelling to notorious war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2015/06/09/french-mother-in-court-to-accuse-government-negligence-in-teen-son-one-way/|title=French mother in court to accuse government of negligence in teen son's one-way Syria journey|work=Fox News|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scandinavia===
In May 2015, two [[Norway|Norwegian]] men, 30-year-old Djibril Abdi Bashir and 28-year-old Valon Avdyli, were sentenced to four years in prison for joining Islamic State militants in [[Syria]]. Valon's 25-year-old brother, Visar Avdyli, was convicted of providing logistical support, and sentenced to a seven month prison term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4655304,00.html|title=Norwegian court convicts 3 men of links to ISIS|work=ynet|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A month later, another Norwegian man was arrested for suspected ties to the Islamic State, suspected of heading to Syria to join jihadi militants. The 18-year-old was apprehended by the [[Sweden|Swedish]] government at [[Göteborg Landvetter Airport]] at Norway's request. If convicted, the unidentified man faces up to six years in prison.

About 70 people have left Norway to become foreign fighters in Syria or Iraq, while some 20 have returned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2015/06/09/swedes-nab-norwegian-man-suspected-heading-to-join-jihadi-fighters-in-syria-and/|title=Swedes nab Norwegian man suspected of heading to join jihadi fighters in Syria and Iraq|work=Fox News|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that at least 124 people have travelled from Denmark to Syria and/or Iraq since January 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt;

===Belgium===
As an ICCT report from April 2016 shows, Belgium has the highest per-capita foreign fighter contingent. The estimated number is between 420-516 individuals. This group consists of a wide age rage, with people between 14–69 years old – with an average of 25,7.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt;

The Chief of the '[[:nl:Coordination Unit for Threat Analysis|Coordination Unit for Threat Analysis]]', Paul Van Tigchelt, said on the 28th of September 2016 that there are 632 known persons designated as 'foreign terrorist fighters'. Out of these 632 people, 273 are believed to be abroad, fighting or dead.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hln.be/hln/nl/32616/Terreurdreiging-in-Belgie/article/detail/2890164/2016/09/28/Tiental-Syriegangers-zou-zonder-slechte-bedoelingen-willen-terugkeren-naar-Belgie.dhtml|title=Tiental Syriëgangers zou &quot;zonder slechte bedoelingen&quot; willen terugkeren naar België|date=28 September 2016|publisher=|accessdate=27 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
For Germany, the estimation is that between 720 and 760 people have travelled to Syria and/or Iraq. 40 percent of this group holds only German citizenship, while another 20 percent holds dual citizenship of which one is German.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt;

===The Netherlands===
From the Netherlands 220 people have left to go to Syria/Iraq. The majority of them is male and under 25.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt;

==Pakistan==
The [[Pakistani Taliban]] said that its fighters, from a variety of countries, were fighting against the Syrian government. They were reportedly working with the Nusra Front and al-Qaeda in Iraq, which have grouped themselves under the banner of the [[Syrian Islamic Front]]. The group's commanders said that they sought to fight in Syria in order to foster closer links with al-Qaeda's central leadership. An unnamed Taliban commander was quoted by [[Reuters]] as saying that the group was fighting alongside their &quot;Mujahedeen friends. When our brothers needed our help, we sent hundreds of fighters along with our Arab friends.&quot; He added that videos would be released showing the group's &quot;victories&quot; in Syria. Another commander said: &quot;Since our Arab brothers have come here for our support, we are bound to help them in their respective countries and that is what we did in Syria. We have established our own camps in Syria. Some of our people go and then return after spending some time fighting there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Atul Aneja |url=http://www.thehindu.com/news/international/south-asia/pak-taliban-presence-turns-syria-into-a-theatre-of-global-jihad/article4918221.ece?homepage=true |title=Pak. Taliban presence turns Syria into a theatre of global jihad |work=The Hindu |date=15 July 2013 |accessdate=20 July 2013 |location=Chennai, India}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group's spokesman, Abdul Rashid Abbasi, said on 16 July 2013 that its first batch of fighters had arrived in Syria and set up a command and control centre and that another batch of at least 120 fighters were expected to join the others within a week.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2013/07/20137167916826540.html |title=Pakistan Taliban says its fighters in Syria |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=16 July 2013 |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; While a militant said that 100 fighters had reached Syria and another 20 were on the way with an untold number of volunteers waiting, the Foreign Office spokesman Aizaz Chaudhry said: &quot;We have seen these reports in the media and the concerned authorities are verifying these claims by the militants.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dnaindia.com/world/1861891/report-pakistan-verifying-reports-of-taliban-fighting-in-syria |title=Pakistan verifying reports of Taliban fighting in Syria |publisher=Dnaindia.com |date=16 July 2013 |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Syrian National Council]] released a statement that read: &quot;We ask for clarification regarding coverage that reflects poorly on the Syrian revolution, particularly news about Taliban's office in Syria and other news items about Islamist fighters.&quot; It also cited the Taliban's [[Shura Council]] as denying the news and calling it a &quot;rumor.&quot; Specifically, [[Ahmed Kamel]] said the reports of the Taliban's presence were a &quot;systematic&quot; and &quot;rapid&quot; campaign by pro-government outlets to &quot;smear&quot; the rebels. He said that these were &quot;sick attempts to make the Syrian people look like a bunch of radical Islamists. Syria is bigger than all of these lies and we know, based on our contacts inside Syria, that no Pakistani Taliban are fighting alongside the Syrian rebels. The Taliban want to kill Americans and Israelis, so why they should go to Syria when we are fighting for freedom, democracy and justice against a tyrant?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2013/07/18/world/meast/syria-pakistan-taliban-claim/?hpt=hp_t3 |title=Syrian opposition questions Taliban rebel role |publisher=CNN |date=19 July 2013|accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States==
The numbers of fighters for [[ISIS]] from [[United States]] of America is not clear.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}} They are apparently not of single ethnicity, and include naturalized citizens, as well as some young women.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}} [[Mohammad Hamzeh Khan]] arrested by the [[United States]] while leaving to join ISIS, declared that ISIS had established the perfect Islamic state and that he felt obligated to &quot;migrate&quot; there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2015/05/06/opinions/bergen-isis-american-recruits/index.html|title=Who are ISIS' American recruits?|author1=Peter Bergen |author2=David Sterman |date=6 May 2015|work=CNN|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ahmad Khan, an American teenager, was to meet a member of Isis in Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2014/10/07/us/who-is-mohammed-hamzah-khan/|title=Who is Mohammed Hamzah Khan?|author=Jethro Mullen and Ted Rowlands, CNN|date=7 October 2014|work=CNN|accessdate=25 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another young American, a 17 years old, acknowledged distributing nearly 7 thousand tweets in support of Isis, aiding the immigration of another youth to [[Syria]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://alhayat.com/Articles/9495270/|title=الحياة - شاب اميركي يعترف بنشر 7 آلاف تغريدة دعماً لـ &quot;داعش&quot;|work=Alhayat|accessdate=18 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Others==
Other Non-Arab fighters came from Turkey, Tajikistan and Pakistan. Though they were reported to be callous, under-trained and poor, particularly in comparison to the Chechens.&lt;ref name=&quot;guard&quot;/&gt; Other Muslim contingents included: South and Central Asians (Afghans, Bangladeshis and Pakistanis), Westerners (Belgian, British, French, U.S.,&lt;ref name=&quot;wi&quot;/&gt; Australia, Denmark, Germany, Netherlands, Sweden, Canada and Austria), as well as Azerbaijan (members of the country's Sunni minority), Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Uzbekistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;/&gt; The core foreign support lies with the Al Qaeda-linked [[Islamic State of Iraq and Syria|ISIS]], which is in opposition to the [[Islamic Front (Syria)|Islamic Front]] and other non-Islamist groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/01/20/us-syria-crisis-bomb-idUSBREA0J10L20140120 |title=Sixteen killed by twin bombs at Syria-Turkey border post |publisher=Reuters |date= 20 January 2014|accessdate=4 February 2014 |first=Oliver |last=Holmes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports indicated the inclusion of Buddhist-majority [[Khmer people|Khmer]]s fighting with ISIS, including those who studied in madrassas in the Middle East.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEA&quot;/&gt;

==Reactions==

===Government===
;Syria
On 3 July 2013, it was reported that Syrian aircraft had dropped leaflets over areas in Idlib province calling on both rebels to turn themselves over to the authorities and for foreign fighters to return to their countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=DIAA HADID |url=http://news.yahoo.com/syrian-troops-battle-retake-rebel-held-areas-072227497.html |title=Syrian troops battle to retake rebel-held areas |publisher=News.yahoo.com |date=3 July 2013 |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;International
;;Official
In June 2014, the European Union's Director of Justice and Home Affairs [[Gilles de Kerchove]] estimated that there were about 500 fighters from the E.U. with the U.K., Ireland and France estimated to have the most citizens fighting there. He added that while &quot;not all of them are radical when they leave, but most likely many of them will be radicalised there, will be trained. And as we've seen this might lead to a serious threat when they get back.&quot; European intelligence agencies were said to have stepped up investigations with Britain and Belgium increasing efforts to track how people are recruited. The Netherlands' officials raised the terror threat level to &quot;substantial&quot; partly over concerns about radicalised citizens returning from Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-22275456 |title=Hundreds of Europeans fighting in Syria, says EU expert |publisher=Bbc.com |date=24 April 2013 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The director of the U.S. government's [[National Counterterrorism Center]] Matthew Olsen told the [[Aspen Security Forum]] that an increasing number of foreign fighters from the West were fighting for the Nusra Front and that they were &quot;the most capable fighting force within the opposition. Syria has become really the predominant jihadist battlefield in the world. We see foreign fighters going from Western Europe and, in a small number of cases, from the United States to Syria to fight for the opposition.&quot; He, along with other speakers, speculated that there was an increased threat of attacks should the fighters return home. The European Union's counter-terrorism coordinator, Gilles de Kerchove, said that about 600 fighters had traveled from Europe to Syria and that should the Balkans and North Africa be counted there would be thousands of fighters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Atlas |first=Terry |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-07-19/u-s-stakes-in-syria-grow-as-radicals-rally-to-the-fight.html |title=Foreign Fighters Flocking to Syria Stirs Terror Concerns |publisher=Bloomberg |date=29 June 2013 |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Olsen added that &quot;the concern going forward from a threat perspective is there are individuals traveling to Syria, becoming further radicalised, becoming trained and then returning as part of really a global jihadist movement to Western Europe and, potentially, to the United States.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/07/28/world/middleeast/worries-mount-as-syria-lures-wests-muslims.html?pagewanted=all | work=The New York Times | first=Eric | last=Schmitt | title=Worries Mount as Syria Lures West's Muslims | date=27 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite former Egyptian President [[Mohamed Morsi]]'s call for a ''jihad'' in Syria, the interim leadership in the country said that it had no intention of calling for such a ''jihad''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://in.reuters.com/article/2013/07/20/egypt-syria-jihad-idINDEE96J02P20130720 |title=Egypt has no intention of waging Syria jihad - minister |publisher=In.reuters.com |date= 20 July 2013|accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that it would re-evaluate Morsi's cutting of diplomatic relations with Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Maamoun Youssef |url=http://news.yahoo.com/egypt-reevaluate-syria-ties-121843357.html |title=Egypt to reevaluate Syria ties - Yahoo! News |publisher=News.yahoo.com |date=20 April 2011 |accessdate=20 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 July, following the [[2013 Egyptian coup d'état]], amid fears that many fighters were going to Egypt in support of the Muslim Brotherhood, Egypt put travel restrictions on Syrian entering that country and required a visa before they entered Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Zeina Karam |author2=Bassem Mroue |url=http://news.yahoo.com/egypt-puts-travel-restrictions-syrians-163023226.html |title=Egypt puts travel restrictions on Syrians |publisher=News.yahoo.com |date=8 July 2013 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Kremlin]] was said to be concerned about links between northern Caucasus militants and the Islamist oppositions fighters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wsws.org/en/articles/2013/08/15/dage-a15.html |title=Violence escalates in Dagestan amid incipient Islamist insurgency |publisher=Wsws.org |date=15 August 2013 |accessdate=20 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Australian government was also concerned about returning fighters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gL2fWLOUpXgduw8CtSlnFLxF2Uwg?docId=ec340058-7ba0-46ef-a869-4f1a76153472 |title=Australia fears domestic extremism from Syria conflict |work=AFP |publisher=Google.com |date= |accessdate=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Saudi Grand Mufti [[Abdulaziz Al al-Sheikh]] called for Syrians to be &quot;enable[d]&quot; to protect themselves. He also said of fighters going to the country that &quot;this is all wrong, it's not obligatory. I do not advise one to go there...you will be a burden to them, what they want from you is your prayer. These are feuding factions and one should not go there. I do not advise one to go there...Going to a land that you do not know and without experience, you will be a burden to them, what they want from you is your prayer. Muslim should be fearful of God and not deceive young Muslims and exploit their weakness and lack of insight and push them to an abyss. I advise them to advise as they would advise their sons.&quot; This was seen as a Saudi fear of its citizens returning home with skills they learnt against the Saudi state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2013/10/top-cleric-tells-saudis-avoid-syria-war-201310282238800365.html |title=Young Saudis urged to avoid Syria war |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Turkish intelligence supported Islamist radicals like the al-Nusra Front and aided their passage into Syria and supported arming the rebels. Then President [[Abdullah Gul]] said Syria risks becoming &quot;Afghanistan on the shores of the Mediterranean&quot; and that Turkey could become a Mediterranean Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Nathalie Tocci |url=http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2013/11/turkey-europe-syrian-crisis-edging-towards-new-consensus-201311510320978326.html |title=Turkey, Europe and the Syrian Crisis: Edging towards a new consensus? |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

French Interior Minister [[Manuel Valls]] said that French national fighting for extremist groups could become enemies of France when they return to home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=M. Klostermayr |url=http://www.syrianews.cc/enemies-syria-france-extremists/?utm_source=twitterfeed&amp;utm_medium=twitter |title=French Minister: Enemies of Syria perhaps also Enemies of France |publisher=Syrianews.cc |date= |accessdate=20 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Norwegian Police Security Service]] estimated that up to 40 Norwegians had gone to Syria to fight, but that the number might be higher. As of November 2013 at least five are presumed&lt;ref name=vg/&gt; dead and some have returned to Norway. Many are recruited through Islamist groups in Norway and fight for organisations such as [[Jaish al-Muhajireen wal-Ansar]],&lt;ref name=vg&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vg.no/nyheter/innenriks/artikkel.php?artid=10133405 |title=Norske ekstremister kriger i skandinavisk islamist-brigade - VG Nett om Syria |language=Norwegian |publisher=Vg.no |date=1 January 1970 |accessdate=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|ISIS]] and [[al-Nusra]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrk.no/1.11374131 |title=– &quot;Norske jihadister&quot; i kontakt med Al Qaida-grupperinger - NRK |publisher=Nrk.no |date=25 November 2013 |accessdate=4 February 2014 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both the Security Service and academics have expressed worry that returning fighters might pose a future threat to Norway.&lt;ref name=nrk/&gt; The U.K. also confirmed over 200 Syrian trained fighters had returned home with the intent to carry out attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rt.com/op-edge/uk-jihadists-syria-preventative-initiative-523/?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter |title='Brits fighting in Syria were no surprise for UK govt' |publisher=Rt.com |date=18 February 2014 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2014, it was announced that nine unnamed European countries were to take measures to prevent its citizens from fighting in Syria. They would be joined by the United States, Turkey, Morocco, Jordan and Tunisia. Belgian Interior Minister [[Joelle Milquet]] said that his country had taken steps in 2014 to address the problem and sought to increase international cooperation in the matter because &quot;coping with the return [of fighters], that is our main concern.&quot; It followed European Union warnings that its citizens were going to fight in Syria and countries like Somalia and Sudan and that they could return more radicalised and trained in guerrilla tactics that could prove a security risk. Milquet added that an informal ministerial group with France in 2013 year, brought together officials from the U.K., Netherlands and Spain, which, in turn, then met officials from the U.S., Canada and Australia. France and England had also announced plans to prevent their citizens from fighting in Syria. France announced a set of 20 measures to deal with the issue with President Francois Hollande saying &quot;France will take all measures to dissuade, prevent and punish those who are tempted to fight where they have no reason to be,&quot; while Foreign Minister Laurent Fabius estimated that about 500 French citizens were involved in the conflict. The U.K. police announced that they would appeal to Muslim women to help persuade youths not to fight in the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2014/04/move-curb-foreign-fighters-syria-2014424172354903949.html |title=Move to curb foreign fighters in Syria |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2014, the U.K. enacted Operation Mum that seeks Muslim women informing against family members who consider going to Syria to fight. It comes as up to 700 citizens were said to have traveled there, with 20 known deaths and more in detention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/apr/25/operation-mum-british-muslims-syria-mothers |title=Operation Mum won't stop British Muslims going to Syria. But peace will |publisher=theguardian.com |date=13 September 2013 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia expressed concern that veterans of the conflict posed a graver threat that those during the [[September 11 attacks]], while another unnamed official compared the threat to the [[2008 Mumbai attacks]]. Prime Minister [[Tony Abbott]] said:&lt;blockquote&gt;This is a big issue; it's concerning people right around the world. We have an ongoing Islamist terror threat and the situation in Syria has the potential to escalate that threat as militarised radicals come back. I don’t say that there is any simple solution to this problem, but the vigilance that's been maintained since 2001 needs to be increased in these circumstances and its certainly no time to be reducing the emphasis on good intelligence which has been a very important part of Australia's response to the terror threat ever since then.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Abbott signed an agreement with French President François Hollande to share intelligence on each other's citizens who had fought in Syria. He made a similar deal with Indonesian President [[Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono]] when the met on [[Batam Island]] in early June 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;aus2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afr.com/p/national/syria_war_graduates_bigger_threat_2hwUer2QZMX4xjPtjdusjM |title=Syria war graduates bigger threat than 2001 attacks, says Abbott |publisher=Afr.com |date= |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ISIS flag was seen being waved thrice in [[Jammu and Kashmir]]. However, Chief Minister [[Omar Abdullah]] alleged that: &quot;You have to understand that no ISIS group has been identified so far in the valley. The flag of the ISIS was waved by some idiots, which does not mean that ISIS has any presence in Kashmir.&quot; He further noted that legal action was taken against the tailor who made it and those who flew it.&lt;ref name=&quot;indiatimes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Some-idiots-waved-ISIS-flag-group-has-no-presence-in-Kashmir-valley-Omar-Abdullah-says/articleshow/44819518.cms|title=Some idiots waved ISIS flag, group has no presence in Kashmir valley, Omar Abdullah says |publisher=timesofindia.indiatimes.com|accessdate=30 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In another instance it was waved after [[Friday prayers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dnaindia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report-isis-flags-again-displayed-in-kashmir-valley-2027042|title=ISIS flags again displayed in Kashmir Valley |publisher=dnaindia.com|accessdate=30 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The governments of Malaysia and Indonesia as well the Philippines and Thailand were also concerned about returning fighters. On at least one occasion Malaysian reports indicated that Islamic State supporter terrorist groups have emerged to stake a claim over parts of mainland Southeast Asia. While some arrests were made, some of them had fled to the Philippines to forged an alliance with [[Abu Sayyaf]], which is one of the Filipino terrorist group notourious for kidnapping, beheading and extortion. Many of the terrorists fled from Malaysia are believed to be not a Malaysian citizens, but instead were either Filipino and Indonesian nationalities who have disguised as a Malaysians by using fake identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailyexpress.com.my/news.cfm?NewsID=106313|title=
'Sabah' terror suspect likely illegal|publisher=[[Daily Express (Malaysia)|Daily Express]]|date=26 January 2016|accessdate=2 February 2016|quote=Many Indonesian and Filipinos have illegally obtained [[MyKad|Malaysian identity cards]] from [[Illegal immigrants in Malaysia|syndicates and made their way]] to the [[Peninsular Malaysia|peninsula]] for employment.|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160202054509/http://www.dailyexpress.com.my/news.cfm?NewsID=106313|archivedate=2 February 2016|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Malaysia's first suicide bomber attack occurred under the auspices of ISIS (though in Iraq).&lt;ref name=&quot;SEA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thediplomat.com/2014/07/isis-a-threat-well-beyond-the-middle-east/|title=ISIS: A Threat Well Beyond the Middle East |author1=Luke Hunt |author2=The Diplomat |publisher=thediplomat.com|accessdate=3 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, U.S. Senator [[Ted Cruz]] introduced the [[Expatriate Terrorist Act]] which would allow the federal government go to court to revoke the citizenship of those who joins or aids a [[List of designated terrorist organisations|foreign terrorist group]]. He cited his view that it was &quot;necessary&quot; to prevent citizens to fight for ISIS from returning to carry out &quot;unspeakable acts of terror here at home.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;reason&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://reason.com/blog/2014/10/23/steve-chapman-should-we-strip-terrorists|title=Steve Chapman: Should We Strip Terrorists of Citizenship? |publisher=reason.com|accessdate=30 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2014, the United Nations Security Council adopted Resolution 2178 which focused on how states should deal with the foreign fighter phenomenon. The Resolution presents a holistic approach to the problem and therefore stresses to not only focus on military and intelligence solutions, but incorporate preventative and rehabilitative measures as well. Furthermore, governments are encouraged to developed counter narratives together with communities and NGO's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://icct.nl/publication/the-new-security-council-resolution-2178-on-foreign-terrorist-fighters-a-missed-opportunity-for-a-holistic-approach/ | title=The New Security Council 2178 on Foreign Terrorist Fighters: A Missed Opportunity for a Holistic Approach | date=4 November 2014| publisher=The International Centre for Counter-Terrorism - The Hague (ICCT) | accessdate=1 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Governments have adopted a wide range of policies and measures in order to deal with the issue of foreign fighters. Measures change per country, and focus for example on prevention, law enforcement or rehabilitation and reintegration. For example, informative hotlines have been set up as well as implementation of the deprivation of citizenship. With a focus on more preventative measures, countries have developed programs that focus on inter-cultural and inter-religious dialogue as well the use of counter-narratives.&lt;ref name=&quot;icct.nl&quot;/&gt;

===Other===
;;Personal
In at least [[Suluk]] in Raqqa, ISIS was teaching their version of [[Sharia]] to Europeans and other foreigners at a house. Further, at least three fathers, two Belgians and a Russian, traveled to northern Syria to try and bring home their sons fighting for the opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-28353575 |title=The Belgian fathers who lost their sons in Syria |publisher=Bbc.com |date= |accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another former Belgian soldier successfully brought back his son from Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-24649704 |title=Belgium teenager Jejoen Bontinck: Humanitarian or jihadist? |publisher=Bbc.com |date= |accessdate=18 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;;Analysis

Western reactions have generally been of concern about returning Islamist foreign fighters. Former U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations [[John R. Bolton|John Bolton]] said: &quot;The balance of power within the Syrian opposition between responsible forces and terrorists is already murky at best. If even more al Qaeda supporters are moving in, it raises the risks of supplying weapons even to 'friendly' opposition forces even higher.&quot; Former CIA official and former staff member of the White House National Security Council [[Bruce Riedel]] added: &quot;Syria is the new epicenter for the global jihad with would be 'martyrs' arriving from across the Islamic world to fight Assad. {{sic}} They are getting experience in the terror arts they will bring home.&quot; Aaron Zelin of the [[Washington Institute for Near East Policy]] wrote that &quot;not everyone who has joined the Syrian rebels is al Qaeda, and only a small number may ever become involved in terrorism after returning to Europe. That said, it would be wrong to conclude that individuals who have trained and fought in Syria pose no potential threat. Numerous studies show that individuals with foreign training and/or fighting experience have featured prominently in European based terrorist plots. [Other studies have shown that foreign-trained fighters] are far more lethal, dangerous and sophisticated than purely domestic cells.&quot; because the returning fighters are more experienced and battle hardened than those in domestic cells. Having fought and survived the war, domestic cells would most likely look up to and follow the instructions of returning fighters when carrying out violent attacks. It might be more difficult to prevent a terrorist attack from a cell headed by a Foreign fighter that have knowledge in weapons handling, constructing explosives out of improvised goods and operational planning than a cell headed by a leader without this practical training.  He suggested a recurrence of roving attackers that followed the Iraq war in the 2000s, the Bosnia war in the 1990s and the [[War in Afghanistan (1978–present)|Afghanistan war]] in the 1980s.

The ''Free Beacon'' suggested the growing number of foreign fighters was indicated by the release of videos such as one showing the execution of three Christians, including a Roman Catholic priest. Other such videos are the increasing number of &quot;martyrdom announcements.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fb&quot;/&gt; The ''[[New York Times]]'' suggested the influx of foreign Islamist fighters could make Syria a new haven for such fighters akin to Afghanistan, Pakistan and Yemen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/09/world/middleeast/as-foreign-fighters-flood-syria-fears-of-a-new-extremist-haven.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0 | work=The New York Times | first1=Anne | last1=Barnard | first2=Eric | last2=Schmitt | title=As Foreign Fighters Flood Syria, Fears of a New Extremist Haven | date=8 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Norwegian Defence Research Establishment]]'s Thomas Hegghammer estimated in November 2013 that between 1,132 and 1,707 Europeans from 12 such countries had gone to Syria to fight, with a majority from France (200–400), the United Kingdom (200–300) and Belgium (100–300).&lt;ref name=nrk&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrk.no/norge/andel-norske-syria-krigere-i-toppen-1.11384553 |title=Andel norske Syria-krigere i toppen - NRK – Norge |language=Norwegian |publisher=Nrk.no |date=29 November 2013 |accessdate=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, an ISIL deserter alleged that foreign recruits were treated with less respect than Arabic-speaking Muslims by ISIL commanders and were placed in suicide units if they lacked otherwise useful skills.  In order to gain respect, foreign fighters may engage in far more violent actions than local fighters.  Most local fighters are unwilling to terrorize their own relatives or neighbors and thus foreign fighters are deployed to violently control the locals.

Turkey was said to be concerned about the presence of radical jihadists on their border with Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2013/10/15/jihadists-flooding-into-northern-syria-put-turkey-on-edge/ |title=Jihadists flooding into northern Syria put Turkey on edge |publisher=Fox News |date=15 October 2013 |accessdate=4 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Carnegie Middle East Center]] noted the &quot;unprecedented&quot; speed at which the numbers of fighters have mobilised in comparison to earlier modern conflicts in the Islamic world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt;

Shahriman Lockman of the Malaysia-based [[Institute of Strategic &amp; International Studies]] said of the return of fighters: &quot;It is worrisome, yes. If they wanted a safe haven for their training and operations, they could easily go to the numerous failed states in Africa. But they chose to operate from Malaysia, where the risk of being under surveillance is much higher.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEA&quot;/&gt;

==Blowback==
Amidst concern of blowback, the first reported case of a former fighter in the conflict to attack those outside Syria occurred in May 2014 at the [[Jewish Museum of Belgium shooting]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Newman |first=Marissa |url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/suspected-brussels-gunman-admitted-to-attack-on-film/ |title='Brussels museum suspect admitted responsibility in video clip' |publisher=The Times of Israel |date=1 June 2014 |accessdate=10 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though unconfirmed, ISIS reportedly claimed responsibility for the [[2014 shootings at Parliament Hill, Ottawa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://heavy.com/news/2014/10/michael-zehaf-bibeau-ottawa-parliament-shooting-terro-attack/|title=Michael Zehaf-Bibeau: 5 Fast Facts You Need to Know - Heavy.com|author=Paul Farrell|work=Heavy.com|accessdate=22 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Threats by ISIS also led to the [[2014 shootings at Parliament Hill, Ottawa]].--&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of armed groups in the Syrian Civil War]]
*[[Military activity of ISIL]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Edwin Bakker, Christophe Paulussen, Eva Entenmann, [http://www.icct.nl/publications/icct-papers/dealing-with-european-foreign-fighters-in-syria-governance-challenges-and-legal-implications &quot;Dealing with European Foreign Fighters in Syria: Governance Challenges and Legal Implications&quot; (International Centre for Counter-Terrorism - The Hague)]
* Sergei Boeke, Daan Weggemans [http://www.icct.nl/publications/icct-commentaries/destination-jihad-why-syria-and-not-mali &quot;Destination Jihad: Why Syria and not Mali?&quot; (International Centre for Counter-Terrorism - The Hague)]

{{Syrian civil war}}

[[Lists of the Syrian Civil War]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Foreign rebel fighters in the Syrian civil war}}
[[Category:Foreign involvement in the Syrian Civil War|*]]
[[Category:21st century in international relations]]
[[Category:Military units and factions of the Syrian Civil War|*]]
[[Category:Islamic terrorism and Norway]]
[[Category:Islamic terrorism in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Islamic terrorism in the United States]]
[[Category:Islamic terrorism in France]]
[[Category:Islamic terrorism in Russia]]
[[Category:Islamic terrorism in China]]
[[Category:Islamic terrorism in Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>fhhtkir7kny7dum2pkjm6c79uqmqkv7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
