<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Green-water navy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5666376</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748491432</id>
      <parentid>748491356</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-08T13:06:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Antiochus the Great</username>
        <id>18657785</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Singapore */ and again</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21960">[[File:USS Independence LCS-2 at pierce (cropped).jpg|thumb|upright 1.6|The [[littoral combat ship]] {{USS|Independence|LCS-2|6}} was designed for green-water operations]]

'''Green-water navy''' is [[terminology]] created to describe a [[naval force]] that is designed to operate in its nation's [[littoral zone]]s and has the competency to operate in the open oceans of its surrounding region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bratton&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Bratton|first=Patrick C|title=Sea Power and the Asia-Pacific|publisher=Routledge|year=2012|location=London, United Kingdom|pages=|isbn=1-136-62724-3|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RxOpAgAAQBAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a relatively new term, and has been created to better distinguish, and add nuance, between two long-standing descriptors: [[blue-water navy]] and [[brown-water navy]].

It is a non-doctrinal naval term used in different ways. It originates with the [[United States Navy]], who use it to refer to the portion of their fleet that specializes in offensive operations in coastal waters. Nowadays such ships rely on stealth or speed to avoid destruction by shore batteries or land-based aircraft.

The US Navy has also used the term to refer to the first phase of the expansion of China's navy into a full [[blue-water navy]]. Subsequently other authors have applied it to other national navies that can project power locally, but cannot sustain operations at range without the help of other countries. Such navies typically have amphibious ships and sometimes small aircraft carriers, which can be escorted by destroyers and frigates with some logistical support from tankers and other auxiliaries.

== Definitions ==
The elements of [[maritime geography]] are loosely defined and their meanings have changed throughout history. The US's 2010 Naval Operations Concept defines blue water as &quot;the open ocean&quot;, green water as &quot;coastal waters, ports and harbors&quot;, and brown water as &quot;navigable rivers and their estuaries&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.marines.mil/news/publications/Documents/Naval%20Operations%20Concept%202010.pdf | format=pdf | page=16 | title=Naval Operations Concept 2010 – Implementing the Maritime Strategy | publisher=US Naval Service | accessdate=7 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Rubel of the US Naval War College includes bays in his definition of brown water,&lt;ref name=Rubel&gt;{{citation | title=Talking About Sea Control | first=Robert C. | last=Rubel | url=http://www.dtic.mil/dtic/tr/fulltext/u2/a536641.pdf | pages=44–46 | journal = Naval War College Review | date=Autumn 2010 | volume=63 | number=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the past US military commentators have extended brown water out to {{convert|100|nmi|km}} from shore.&lt;ref name=PLAN75&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.strategicstudiesinstitute.army.mil/pdffiles/pub52.pdf | title=The Lessons of History : The Chinese People's Liberation Army at 75 | first1=Laurie | last1=Burkitt| first2=Andrew | last2=Scobell | first3=Larry M. | last3= Wortzel | authorlink3=Larry Wortzel | date=July 2003 | publisher=Strategic Studies Institute, U.S. Army War College | format=pdf | page=185 | accessdate=7 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Cold War]], green water denoted those areas of ocean in which naval forces might encounter land-based aircraft.&lt;ref name=Rubel /&gt; The development of long-range bombers with anti-ship missiles turned most of the oceans to &quot;green&quot; and the term all but disappeared.&lt;ref name=Rubel /&gt; After the Cold War, US amphibious task forces were sometimes referred to as the green-water navy, in contrast to the blue-water carrier battle groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url=http://www.dtic.mil/dtic/tr/fulltext/u2/a272337.pdf |format=pdf | title= Composite Warfare and The Amphibians | pages=9–24 | first1=T.C. | last1=Gillespie | first2=S.M. | last2=Lesher | first3=P.D.|last3=Miner | first4=B.P. | last4=Cyr | date=23 March 1992 | publisher=Marine Corps University | accessdate=7 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; This distinction disappeared as increasing threats in coastal waters forced the amphibious ships further offshore, delivering assaults by helicopter and tiltrotor from over the horizon. This prompted the development of ships designed to operate in such waters – the {{sclass-|Zumwalt|destroyer}} and the [[littoral combat ship]]s; modelling has suggested that current NATO frigates are vulnerable to swarms of 4-8 small boats in green water.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA508855 | title=Frigate Defense Effectiveness in Asymmetrical Green Water Engagements | first=Heiko | last=Abel | publisher=Naval Postgraduate School | date=September 2009 | accessdate=7 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rubel has proposed redefining green water as those areas of ocean which are too dangerous for high-value units, requiring offensive power to be dispersed into smaller vessels such as submarines that can use stealth and other characteristics to survive.&lt;ref name=Rubel /&gt; Under his scheme, brown water would be zones in which ocean-going units could not operate at all, including rivers, minefields, straits and other choke points.&lt;ref name=Rubel /&gt;

As the preeminent blue-water navy of the early 21st century, the US Navy is able to define maritime geography in terms of offensive action in the home waters of its enemies, without being constrained by logistics. This is not true for most other navies, whose supply chains and air cover typically limit them to power projection within a few hundred kilometres of home territory. A number of countries are working on overcoming these constraints. Other authors have started to apply the term &quot;green-water navy&quot; to any national navy that has ocean-going ships but lacks the logistical support needed for a blue-water navy. It's often not clear what they mean, as the term is used without consistency or precision.

It should be noted that a green-water navy does not mean that the individual ships of the fleet are unable to function away from the coast or in open ocean, instead it suggests that due to logistical reasons they are unable to be deployed for lengthy periods, and must have aid from other countries to sustain long term deployments. Also the term &quot;green-water navy&quot; is subjective as numerous countries that do not have a true green-water navy maintain naval forces that are on par with countries that are recognized as having green-water navies. For example, the [[German Navy]] has near the same capability as the [[Royal Canadian Navy|Canadian Navy]] but is not recognized as a true green-water navy. Another example is the [[Portuguese Navy]] that, despite being usually classified as a minor navy, has several times conducted sustained operations in faraway regions typical of the green-water navies. However, the differences between blue-water navies and brown or green-water navies is usually quite noticeable, for example the US Navy was able to quickly respond to the disappearance of [[Malaysia Airlines Flight 370]] and continue operations in the region with relative ease even though the search area covered the Indian Ocean. On the contrary, in 2005 the then green-water navy such the [[Russian Navy]] was unable to properly respond when its AS-28 rescue vehicle became tangled in undersea cables unable to surface, relying on the blue-water [[Royal Navy]] to respond and carry out the rescue in time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/world/2005-08-06-russian-sub_x.htm |title=Russian submarine surfaces with entire crew alive |work=USAToday.com |agency=Associated Press |date=6 August 2005 |accessdate=17 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Just as nations build up naval capability some lose it, for example the [[Austro-Hungarian Navy]] was a modern green water navy of the time, however as the countries lost their coasts during [[World War I]] their navies were confiscated and their ports became parts of [[Italy]] and [[Yugoslavia]]. The [[Axis powers|Axis]] powers lost naval capabilities after their defeat in [[World War II]] with most of Japan's [[Imperial Japanese Navy|Imperial Navy]] and Germany's [[Kriegsmarine|Navy]] being disarmed and their troop and ship numbers capped and monitored by the allies. The collapse of the [[USSR]] also brought with it the collapse of the second largest naval force in the world, and the largest submarine force in the world.  Although the [[Russian Federation]] made sure to inherit the most capable ships, passing most older models to successor states, as it had lost the logistical capabilities of the [[Soviet Navy]], it was no longer able to operate away from Russian shores for extended periods of time. Moreover, budget cuts forced large cuts in the submarine force, such as the retirements of the {{sclass2-|Typhoon|submarine}}. As the Soviet Navy was built largely around submarine warfare the losses in the submarine capability have adversely affected the capability of the newly formed Russian Navy as well.

== Examples of green-water navies ==

=== Australia ===
[[File:HMAS Canberra (LHD 02) at berth prior to commissioning.jpg|thumb|{{HMAS|Canberra|LHD 02|6}}]]
The [[Royal Australian Navy]] is well established as a green-water navy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Routledge&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Till|first1=Geoffrey|title=Naval Modernisation in South-East Asia: Nature, Causes and Consequences|date=15 August 2013|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=1-135-95394-5|page=267}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Canada /&gt; The navy sustains a broad range of maritime operations, from the [[Middle East]] to the [[Pacific Ocean]], often as part of international or allied coalitions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/navy-today/operations|title=Operations |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |accessdate=31 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The RAN operates a modern fleet, consisting of destroyers, frigates, conventional submarines as well as an emerging amphibious and [[power projection]] capability based on the commissioning of {{HMAS|Choules|L100|6}} and two {{sclass-|Canberra|landing helicopter dock|1}}s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Canberra commissioning marks new era in ADF amphibious warfare|url=http://australianaviation.com.au/2014/11/canberra-commission-marks-new-era-in-adf-amphibious-warfare/|accessdate=16 March 2015|agency=Australian Aviation|date=28 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Carrier / Amphibious capability - 27,000 tonne {{HMAS|Canberra|LHD 02|6}} and {{HMAS|Adelaide|L01|6}}
* Amphibious capability – 16,190 tonne {{HMAS|Choules|L100|6}}.
* Replenishment capability – 18,221 tonne {{HMAS|Success|OR 304|6}} and the 46,755 tonne {{HMAS|Sirius|O 266|6}}.
{{Clear}}

=== Brazil ===
[[File:Brazilian aircraft carrier São Paulo (A12).jpg|thumb|The {{ship|Brazilian aircraft carrier|São Paulo|A12|6}}]]
The [[Brazilian Navy]] has frequently been dubbed a ‘green-water’ force by experts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Pryce|first1=Paul|title=The Brazilian Navy: Green Water or Blue?|journal=Offiziere.ch|date=19 January 2015|url=http://www.isn.ethz.ch/Digital-Library/Articles/Detail/?lng=en&amp;id=187085|accessdate=17 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The navy is primarily focused on securing the nation's littorals and exclusive economic zone (EEZ), but also maintains the capacity to operate in the wider [[South Atlantic Ocean]]. Since the early 2000s, the Brazilian Navy has contributed to a number of [[Brazilian Navy#Peacekeeping Operations (2004–present)|peacekeeping and humanitarian missions]].
* Carrier capability – 32,800 tonne {{ship|Brazilian aircraft carrier|São Paulo|A12|2}}.
* Amphibious capability – 12,000 tonne [[French ship Siroco (L9012)|''Bahia'']], 8,757 tonne {{sclass-|Newport|tank landing ship|2}}, two 8,571 tonne {{sclass2-|Round Table|landing ship logistics|2}}
* Replenishment capability – 10,000 tone {{ship|Brazilian tanker|Almirante Gastão Motta|G23|2}} and the 12,889 tonne ''Marajó''.
{{Clear}}

=== Canada ===
[[File:HMCS Halifax (FFH 330) en route to Haiti 2010-01-18.jpg|thumb|{{HMCS|Halifax|FFH 330|6}}]]
According to the criteria as outlined in the 2001 publication, &quot;''Leadmark: The Navy’s Strategy for 2020''&quot;, the [[Royal Canadian Navy]] had met its description of a 3rd tier &quot;Medium Global Force Projection Navy&quot; - a green-water navy with the capacity to project force worldwide with the aid of more powerful maritime allies (e.g. United Kingdom, France and the United States).&lt;ref name=Canada&gt;[http://publications.gc.ca/collections/collection_2012/dn-nd/DB3-22-2001-eng.pdf Leadmark: The Navy’s Strategy for 2020], Directorate of Maritime Strategy,
Department of National Defence&lt;/ref&gt; In this context, the Royal Canadian Navy ranked itself alongside the navies of Australia and the Netherlands.&lt;ref name=Canada /&gt; However, as of 2016, the recent decommissioning of obsolete ships has left Canada without replenishment or amphibious capable ships, as well as the lack of a credible air-defence capability. The RCN's submarine capability consists  of four second hand vessels of unreliable availability, with only one available for operations as of June 2016. This has led critics to view the Royal Canadian Navy as being more akin to a brown-water navy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalpost.com/full-comment/national-post-view-harpers-shipbuilding-strategy-is-coming-apart-at-the-seams National Post View: Harper’s shipbuilding strategy is coming apart at the seams], http://news.nationalpost.com/, 29 June 2015&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

=== Italy ===
[[File:Cavour (550).jpg|thumb|The aircraft carrier {{ship|Italian aircraft carrier|Cavour|C 550|2}}]]
The [[Italian Navy]] has been categorised as a &quot;regional blue-water navy&quot; in [[Liu Huaqing]]'s Memoirs (1994),&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=SDDDP_a3yIQC&amp;pg=PA100&amp;dq=offshore+navy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y#v=snippet&amp;q=regional-blue%20water%20type&amp;f=false The Chinese Navy: Expanding Capabilities, Evolving Roles?], 2012 (Footnote no. 16, page 139)&lt;/ref&gt; and as a &quot;multi/extra regional power projection navy&quot; by Professors Daniel Todd and Michael Lindberg.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=he5KL_tWQvMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;hl=it#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Navies and Shipbuilding Industries: The Strained Symbiosis|last=Todd|first=Daniel|last2=Lindberg|first2=Michael|date=1996|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|year=|isbn=9780275953102|location=|pages=56–57|ref=Todd-1996|via=|first1=|accessdate=30 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1989 publication &quot;''The Atlantic Alliance and the Middle East''&quot;, Joseph I. Coffey asserts that Italy's blue-water capabilities do not extend beyond the Mediterranean sea.&lt;ref name=Coffey&gt;{{cite book|last1=Coffey|first1=Joseph I.|title=The Atlantic Alliance and the Middle East|date=1989|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press|location=United States|isbn=9780822911548|page=89|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RmttAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=The+Atlantic+Alliance+and+the+Middle+East&amp;dq=The+Atlantic+Alliance+and+the+Middle+East&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiR4ZKn0LjJAhXB7w4KHc_SAa0Q6AEIITAB|accessdate=30 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, the navy possesses two [[light aircraft carrier]]s ({{ship|Italian aircraft carrier|Cavour|C 550|2}} and {{ship|Italian aircraft carrier|Giuseppe Garibaldi|C 551|2}}) as well as a modern fleet of surface combatants and submarines. The Marina Militare routinely deploys to the [[Indian Ocean]] and [[Persian Gulf]] as part of multinational anti-piracy missions such as [[Operation Ocean Shield]] and [[Operation Atalanta]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marina.difesa.it/EN/operations/Pagine/default.aspx Marina Militaire – Operations], marina.difesa.it, (In Italian)&lt;/ref&gt; and is capable of deploying a carrier battle group in support of NATO or EU operations; such as during [[Participants in Operation Enduring Freedom#.Italy|Operation Enduring Freedom]] (2001) and [[EU Navfor Med]] ([[European migrant crisis]]).
* Carrier capability -  27,910 tonne {{ship|Italian aircraft carrier|Cavour|C 550|2}} and the 13,850 tonne {{ship|Italian aircraft carrier|Giuseppe Garibaldi|C 551|2}}.
* Amphibious capability -  three 8,000 tonne {{sclass-|San Giorgio|amphibious transport dock|0}} LPDs.
* Replenishment capability - 13,400 tonne {{ship|Italian ship|Etna|A5326|2}} and two 8,000 tonne {{sclass-|Stromboli|oiler|4}} replenishment ships.
{{Clear}}

=== Japan ===
[[File:JS Hyūga, Ise Bay 01.jpg|thumb|{{JS|Hyūga|DDH-181|6}}]]
The [[Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force]] is considered to be a green-water navy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Routledge&quot; /&gt; Overseas JMSDF deployments include participation in the [[Combined Task Force 150]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Japan Ministry of Defense|url=http://www.mod.go.jp/e/data/refueling/refueling.html|title=Activities based on Anti-Terrorism Special Measures Law (December 2001 – October 2007) – Replenishment Operations|accessdate=2013-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Asahi Shimbun]]|url=http://www.japanfocus.org/-The_Asahi_Shimbun_Culture_Research_Center-/1812|title=Japan’s New Blue Water Navy: A Four-year Indian Ocean mission recasts the Constitution and the US-Japan alliance|accessdate=2013-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an additional task force in the Indian Ocean from 2009 to combat [[piracy in Somalia]]. The first postwar overseas naval air facility of Japan was established next to [[Djibouti-Ambouli International Airport]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Japan Ministry of Defense|url=http://www.mod.go.jp/e/about/answers/anti/index.html|title=MOD/JSDF ANSWERS – Anti-Piracy Efforts|accessdate=2012-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Helicopter carrier capability – two 19,000 tonne {{sclass-|Hyūga|helicopter destroyer|1}}s and two 27,430 tonnes [[Izumo-class helicopter destroyer]]s. - Can be modified to carry fixed wing aircraft.
* Amphibious capability – three 14,000 tonne {{sclass-|Ōsumi|tank landing ship|1}}s.
* Replenishment capability – two 25,000 tonne ''Mashu'' class and three 15,000 tonne ''Towada'' class.
{{Clear}}

=== The Netherlands ===
[[File:Johan de Wit L801.JPG|thumb|{{HNLMS|Johan de Witt|L801|6}}]]
The [[Royal Netherlands Navy]] has been officially described as a 3rd tier &quot;Medium Global Force Projection Navy&quot; - or a green-water navy with the capacity to project force worldwide with the aid of more powerful maritime allies (e.g. Britain, France and the United States).&lt;ref name=&quot;Canada&quot; /&gt; In this context, the Royal Netherlands Navy ranks alongside the navies of Australia and Canada, while the USN is a 1st tier global blue-water navy and Britain and France are 2nd tier blue-water navies.&lt;ref name=Canada /&gt; For many years since the end of the Cold War, the Royal Netherlands Navy has been changing its role from national defence to overseas intervention.&lt;ref&gt;Warship 2006, Conway's Maritime Press – World Navies in Review 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Amphibious capability – 12,750 tonne {{HNLMS|Rotterdam|L800|6}} and the 16,800 tonne {{HNLMS|Johan de Witt|L801|6}}.
* Replenishment capability – 27,800 tonne [[Karel Doorman-class support ship|''Karel Doorman'']] (Also has amphibious capabilities).
{{Clear}}

=== South Korea ===
[[File:해군 독도함 (7438321572).jpg|thumb|{{ship|ROKS|Dokdo|LPH-6111|6}}]]
The [[Republic of Korea Navy]] is considered to be a green-water navy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Routledge&quot; /&gt; In 2011, the government authorized the building of a naval base on [[Jeju Island]] to support the new {{sclass-|Dokdo| amphibious assault ship|1}}s, the base will also be capable of supporting joint forces with the [[US Navy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/19/world/asia/19base.html?pagewanted=all | work=The New York Times | first=Choe | last=Sang-Hun | title=South Korean Navy Base Divides Jeju Island Residents | date=18 August 2011 |accessdate=17 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Flight deck#Ski-jump ramp|ski-jump]] for the operation of [[V/STOL]] jet fighters is being considered for the second ship of the ''Dokdo'' class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defensenews.com/article/20131026/DEFREG03/310260005/S-Korea-Envisions-Light-Aircraft-Carrier |title=S. Korea Envisions Light Aircraft Carrier |work=defensenews.com |first=Jung |last=Sung Ki |date=26 October 2013 |accessdate=17 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Korean government is considering to buy surplus Harriers as a possible interim for the [[F-35 Lightning II]] if they choose to operate VTOL aircraft at all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.naval-technology.com/projects/dodko-class/ |title=Dokdo Class Landing Platform Helicopter (LPH) |work=naval-technology.com |accessdate=17 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Amphibious capability – 18,800 tonne {{ship|ROKS|Dokdo|LPH-6111|6}}, four 4,300 tonne {{sclass-|Go Jun Bong|LST|2}}'s, and one 7,000 tonne {{sclass-|Cheon Wang Bong|LST|2}}, with more under construction.
* Replenishment capability – three 9,180 tonne ''Cheonji''-class replenishment ships.
{{Clear}}

=== Spain ===
[[File:08.05.11 Las Palmas 001.JPG|thumb|{{ship|Spanish ship|Juan Carlos I|L61|2}}]]
The [[Spanish Navy]] is a green-water navy and participates in joint operations with NATO and European allies around the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eunavfor.eu/esps-rayo-joins-eu-naval-force-operation-atalanta/ |title=ESPS Rayo Joins EU Naval Force Operation Atalanta |publisher=eunavfor.eu |date=10 December 2014 |accessdate=17 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fleet has 54 commissioned ships, including; one [[amphibious assault ship]] (also used as an [[aircraft carrier]]), two [[amphibious transport dock]]s, 11 [[frigate]]s (of which 5 are fitted with the modern [[Aegis Combat System]]) and three conventional [[submarine]]s.
* Amphibious/carrier capability – 26,000 tonne {{ship|Spanish ship|Juan Carlos I|L61|2}}.
* Amphibious capability – two 13,815 tonne {{sclass-|Galicia|landing platform dock|1}}s.
* Replenishment capability – 17,045 tonne {{ship|SPS|Patiño|A14|6}} and the 19,500 tonne {{ship|SPS|Cantabria|A15|6}} replenishment ships.
{{Clear}}

== See also ==
* [[Blue-water navy]]
* [[Brown-water navy]]
* [[Maritime geography]]

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Warship types of the 19th &amp; 20th centuries}}

[[Category:Navies by type|Green-water]]
[[Category:Types of military forces]]</text>
      <sha1>mosu9vw89bylvesw8u05k22rv6xvbhk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
