<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Kodandera Subayya Thimayya</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5607528</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751109838</id>
      <parentid>751076576</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T12:18:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Krishna Chaitanya Velaga</username>
        <id>23619103</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17389">{{about|the Indian Army general|the 16th century Hindu privateer|Timoji}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|honorific-prefix= [[General]]
|name= Kodendera Subayya Thimayya
|honorific-suffix= [[Distinguished Service Order|DSO]]
| native_name=ಕೊದಂಡೇರ ಸುಬ್ಬಯ್ಯ ತಿಮ್ಮಯ್ಯ
| office             = [[Chief of the Army Staff (India)]]
| term_start         = 8 May 1957
| term_end           = 7 May 1961
| predecessor        = [[Satyawant Mallannah Shrinagesh|General SM Shrinagesh]]
| successor          = [[Pran Nath Thapar|General PN Thapar]]
|image= [[File:Gen_K_S_Thimayya.jpg|200px]]
|caption= General KS Thimayya
|birth_date={{Birth date|df=yes|1906|3|30}}
|birth_place=[[Madikeri]], [[Coorg]], [[Kingdom of Mysore|Mysore]], [[British Raj|India]]
|death_date= {{death-date and age|df=yes|17 December 1965|March 30, 1906}}
|death_place= [[Cyprus]]
|allegiance=[[File:British Raj Red Ensign.svg|23px]] [[British Indian Empire]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|India}}
|branch=[[File:British Raj Red Ensign.svg|23px]] [[British Indian Army]]&lt;br/&gt;{{army|India}}
|serviceyears=1926&amp;nbsp;– 1961
|rank= [[File:General of the Indian Army.svg|20px]][[General]]
|unit= [[19th Hyderabad Regiment]] (Now [[Kumaon Regiment]])
|commands=[[File:Flag COAS India.jpg|20px]] Chief of Army Staff&lt;br/&gt;[[File:IA Southern Command.jpg|20px]][[Southern Command (India)|Southern Army]]&lt;br/&gt;[[19th Infantry Division (India)|19th Infantry Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[268th Indian Infantry Brigade]]&lt;br/&gt;8th battalion The [[19th Hyderabad Regiment]]
|Wars=[[World War II]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Indo-Pakistani War of 1947]]
|awards=[[File:IND_Padma_Bhushan_BAR.png|20px]] [[Padma Bhushan]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Dso-ribbon.png|20px]] [[Distinguished Service Order]]
|relations=
|laterwork=
}}

[[General]] '''Kodendera Subayya Thimayya''', [[Distinguished Service Order|DSO]] was a distinguished soldier of the [[Indian Army]] who served as [[Chief of Army Staff of the Indian Army|Chief of Army Staff]] from 1957 to 1961 in the crucial years leading up to the [[Sino-Indian War|conflict]] with China in 1962. Gen. Thimayya was the only Indian to command an Infantry brigade in battle during the [[World War II|Second World War]] and is regarded as the most distinguished combat officer the Indian Army has produced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jacob|first1=J.F.R|title=An Odyssey in War and Peace|publisher=Roli Books Pvt. Ltd.|isbn=978-81-7436-840-9|pages=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Korean War]], Thimayya headed a [[United Nations]] unit dealing with the repatriation of prisoners of war. After his retirement from the Army, he was appointed Commander of the [[United Nations peacekeeping|United Nations Peace Keeping Force]] in [[Cyprus]] from July 1964 to December 1965 and died in Cyprus while on active duty on 18th Dec 1965.

==Early life and education==
Kodandera Subayya Thimayya was born in [[Madikeri]], the district town of [[Kodagu]] (formerly known as [[Coorg]]), [[Karnataka]], on 30 March 1906, to Thimayya and Sitamma. His family was one the leading coffee planters in the area. His mother, Sitamma, was highly educated and a social worker. She was the recipient of [[Kaisar-i-Hind Medal|Kaisar-e-Hind Medal]]. Thimayya was the second child of six children in his family. The eldest was Ponappa, then Thimayya, followed by Somayya, and three younger sisters. All the three boys of the family rose to become officers in the Indian Army.{{Sfn|Singh|2007|p=87}}

On his father's side, he belonged to the Kodendera clan to which India's first commander-in-chief [[Cariappa]] also belonged. His mother Cheppudi Chittauwa was from the Cheppudira family. His wife Mrs Nina Thimayya was a recipient of the Kesar-e-hind for her philanthropic contribution during the Quetta Earthquake of 1935. His maternal uncle [[C B Ponnappa]] was in first batch of [[King's commissioned Indian officer|commissioned Indian officers]] from the [[Daly College|Indore defence school]] and a batchmate of Cariappa. Desiring that he receive a good education, he was sent at the age of eight years to St Joseph's College in [[Coonoor]] a convent run by Irish brothers. Later, Thimayya was sent to [[Bishop Cotton Boys School|Bishop Cotton Boys' School]] in [[Bangalore]]. After completing school, Thimayya was sent to the [[Prince of Wales Royal Indian Military College]], a necessary stepping stone for a commission in the [[Indian Army]].His elder brother Ponappa (later joined INA )as well as younger brother Somayya (died in a mine accident in 1947-48 Kashmir operations) joined Indian army. Following his graduation from RIMC, &quot;Timmy&quot;, as he was affectionately known, was one of only six Indian cadets selected for further training at the [[Royal Military College, Sandhurst]]. He was commissioned into the [[British Indian Army|Indian Army]] in 1926.

==Early career==

After completing his training, he was commissioned into the Army in 1926 as a [[Second Lieutenant]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/33130/pages/888]&lt;/ref&gt; and was attached to the [[Highland Light Infantry]] as was the norm then, prior to a permanent posting with a regiment of the British Indian Army. He was soon posted to the 4th Battalion of the [[19th Hyderabad Regiment]] (now [[Kumaon Regiment]]) and was promoted to [[Lieutenant]] in 1928&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/33396/supplements/4268]&lt;/ref&gt; Appointed the regimental [[adjutant]] in September 1930, Thimayya honed his soldiering skills on that famous training ground in the Northwest Frontier (present-day Pakistan), battling recalcitrant Pathan tribals.

In January 1935, Thimayya married Nina Cariappa (no relation to K M Cariappa), and was promoted to [[Captain (land)|Captain]] the following month.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/34142/pages/1810]&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 March 1936, they had a daughter, Mireille. The same April, Thimayya was posted as an Adjutant at the University Training Corps in [[Madras]], as a fitting example for young Indian undergraduates interested in joining the Indian Army, of what a good soldier should be.

===Second World War===
After this tenure, Thimayya was posted to his battalion in [[Singapore]]. In October 1941, he was transferred at his request to India. Thimayya was posted as the Second-in-Command of a new raising at the Hyderabad Regimental Centre in [[Agra]]. He was then detailed to attend the Staff College at [[Quetta]] where he and his wife had earlier made a name for themselves by selfless service during the [[1935 Quetta earthquake]]. Thimayya was promoted to Major in February 1943,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/36042/supplements/2579]&lt;/ref&gt; and served as [[Staff (military)#British .2F Commonwealth staff|GSO2 (Ops)]] (a Grade II Staff Officer) of [[25th Infantry Division (India)|25th Indian Division]], the first Indian officer to get this coveted staff appointment.

His infantry division was conducting jungle warfare training and was preparing to go into [[Burma]] to face the [[Imperial Army of Japan|Japanese Army]] during the Second World War, serving in the [[Arakan Campaign 1942–43|Second Arakan campaign]]. Thimayya was promoted to temporary [[Lieutenant-Colonel]] in May 1944. In Burma, he was posted to his old regiment as Commanding Officer of 8/19th Hyderabad, which he led with outstanding success in battle. For a short while the battalion was under the command of the [[3rd Commando Brigade]], with Brigadier C. R. Hardy at the helm, who during the height of a battle presented a trophy to the battalion. It was a green beret&amp;nbsp;— the command's head dress&amp;nbsp;— with a little typed message on a card, &quot;We cannot buy anything here but we would like you to accept this as a token of our great admiration for the bravery and achievement of your battalion.&quot; He was also promoted to the rank of [[Brigadier]] in the field on 25 March 1945. For his outstanding service in battle, he was awarded the much coveted [[Distinguished Service Order]] (D.S.O) and also a [[Mentioned in Dispatches|Mention-in-Dispatches]].

His innate talents of professional soldiering and leadership were soon recognized by [[Claude Auchinleck|Field Marshal Sir Claude Auchinleck]], the Commander-in-Chief of the Indian Army. He was specially selected to lead the [[268th Indian Infantry Brigade]] as part of the [[British Commonwealth]] Occupation Force in [[Japan]] after World War II. He got this assignment due to his outstanding battle experience as a Brigadier and being the only Indian to command a battle formation in the field.
British, as a matter of policy avoided giving operational command to Indians. Thimmayya was the only exception. As an independent brigade, the 268th had done excellent work in the Burma Campaign and was detailed as part of [[BRINDIV]] led by [[David Tennant Cowan|Maj Gen D. T. &quot;Punch&quot; Cowan]].

Gen. Thimayya proved to be an outstanding commander and his diplomatic skills emerged as he had to deal with [[Douglas MacArthur|General Douglas MacArthur]], the [[Supreme Allied Commander]] of the [[South West Pacific Area (command)|Southwest Pacific Theatre]], the other Allies and the vanquished Japanese. Thimayya's personality, charm of manners and unassailable reputation, impressed the Japanese of the calibre of Indian commanders. Thimayya was called on to defuse the sit-down strike by the 2nd Battalion, [[5th Royal Gurkha Rifles]] at the palace of the [[Emperor of Japan|Mikado]] in [[Tokyo]] when the battalion refused to obey its British officers.

Thimayya represented the country during the surrender of the Japanese in Singapore, followed by the surrender of the Japanese in the Philippines. At the ceremony of Japanese surrender in Singapore, he signed on behalf of India. He was awarded the 'Keys to Manila' when he was sent to the Philippines. As [[Independence Day (India)|Indian Independence]] approached, he was recalled to India by then Commander-in-chief of British India, [[Claude Auchinleck|Field Marshal Sir Claude Auchinleck]].

==Role in independent India==
He returned to India in 1947, during the [[Partition of India|Partition]], as member of the committee to agree to the allotment of weapons, equipment and regiments that were to remain in India, or to be allotted to Pakistan. Soon after the commission was completed, he was promoted to the rank of [[Major-General]] in September 1947 and was then assigned the command of the [[Indian 4th Infantry Division|4th Infantry Division]] and also to take over the Punjab Boundary Force, dealing with the exodus and intake of refugees fleeing to their respective countries. In 1948 he was one of the active officers in the actions against the forces of [[Pakistan]] in the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1947|conflict]] over [[Kashmir]]. His next appointment was command of the [[Indian 19th Infantry Division|19th Infantry Division]] in [[Jammu &amp; Kashmir]] where he succeeded in driving the raiders and the Pakistan Army out of the Kashmir Valley. Personally leading the attack in the forward-most tank, the [[Military operations in Ladakh (1948)#Capture of Zoji La|surprise attack on Zoji La]] on 1 November 1948 by a brigade with [[M3 Stuart|Stuart Light Tanks]] of the [[7th Light Cavalry]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Amazing&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Thimmayya:An Amazing Life |last=Khanduri|first=Chandra B. |year=1969 |publisher=Centre for Armed Historical Research, United Service Institution of India, New Delhi through Knowledge World |location=New Delhi |isbn=81-87966-36-X |page=137 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZWXfAAAAMAAJ |accessdate=6 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; succeeded in driving out the entrenched raiders and [[Pakistan Army]] regulars and the eventual capture of [[Dras]], [[Kargil town|Kargil]] and [[Leh]]. He established the best of relations with [[Sheikh Abdullah]] and [[Bakshi Ghulam Mohammad]] and even Prime Minister [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], but his pleas to give him three more months to drive the raiders back to [[Muzaffarabad]] fell on deaf ears and instead, Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru went to the United Nations.

Thereafter, Thimayya served as the [[Commandant]] of the prestigious [[Indian Military Academy]], Dehra Dun. The experience gained by him in Japan stood him in good stead when he was specially selected by the United Nations to head the [[Neutral Nations Repatriation Commission]] in Korea. It was a very sensitive and delicate task dealing with unruly Chinese and Korean prisoners. Here again, through sheer charisma, impartiality, firmness and diplomacy, he completed this task to the satisfaction of the world body. He returned to India and was promoted to [[General Officer Commanding]], [[Southern Command (India)|Southern Command]], with the rank of [[Lieutenant-General]], in January 1953. In 1954, he was awarded the [[List of Padma Bhushan Award recipients (1954–1959)|Padma Bhushan]] for Civil Service. He took over the reins of the Indian Army on 7 May 1957.

==Chief of Army Staff==

General Kodandera Subayya Thimayya assumed charge of the Indian Army, as the 6th Chief of the Army Staff, on 7 May 1957. He briefly resigned his post in 1959 over a dispute with [[V. K. Krishna Menon]], the then [[Minister of Defence (India)]]. Prime Minister Jawahar Lal Nehru refused to accept his resignation and persuaded him into withdrawing it. However, little action was taken on Thimayya's recommendations and he continued as the Army Chief till his retirement on 7 May 1961, completing 35 years of distinguished military service. Hence retired from the army in 1961, almost 15 months before the Chinese invasion of India in November 1962.

==After retirement==
After retirement from the Indian Army, the United Nations sought his services yet once again when he was appointed as the Commander of UN Forces in [[Cyprus]] ([[UNFICYP]]) in July 1964. He died during his tenure at UNFICYP in December 1965 and his mortal remains were flown to Bangalore for the last rites. The street perpendicular to East Street (a road parallel to MG road in [[Pune]]), Richmond Road in [[Bangalore]], and the main road through [[Larnaca]]/Cyprus (East to West) were renamed as Gen Thimmayya Road in his memory. The Republic of Cyprus, also honored him by issuing a commemorative stamp in his memory in 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;ph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.philatelism.com/details.php?issueid=24|title=Cyprus Stamp Issue: General Thimmayya |accessdate=29 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Old Boys of Cottons, the alumni association of [[Bishop Cotton Boys' School]], annually hold the General K S Thimayya Memorial Lecture Series in his memory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=General K S Thimayya Memorial Lecture Series|url=http://genthimayya.org/|publisher=Old Boys of Cottons|accessdate=9 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and Decorations==

&lt;center&gt;
{|
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award‐star|ribbon=IND Padma Bhushan BAR.png|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=India_General_Service_Medal_1947.svg|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Indian_Independence_medal_1947.svg|width=106}}
|}&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
{|
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award‐star|ribbon=Dso-ribbon.png|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Ribbon_-_1939-45_Star.png|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Ribbon_-_Burma_Star.png|width=106}}
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=award-star|ribbon=Ribbon_-_War_Medal.png|width=106}}
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|&lt;center&gt;[[Padma Bhushan]]&lt;/center&gt;
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; |&lt;center&gt;[[General Service Medal 1947]]&lt;/center&gt;
|&lt;center&gt;[[Indian Independence Medal]]&lt;/center&gt;

|-
|&lt;center&gt;[[Distinguished Service Order]]&lt;/center&gt;
|&lt;center&gt;[[1939–1945 Star]]&lt;/center&gt;
|&lt;center&gt;[[Burma Star]]&lt;/center&gt;
|&lt;center&gt;[[War Medal 1939–1945]]&lt;/center&gt;
|}&lt;/center&gt;

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=lower-alpha}}
;Citations
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{citation|first1=Vijay Kumar|last1=Singh|title=Leadership in the Indian Army: Biographies of Twelve Soldiers|author-link = Vijay Kumar Singh|year=2005|isbn=978-0-7619-3322-9|publisher=SAGE|accessdate=July 30, 2016}}
*{{citation|first1=Satinder|last1=Sharma|title=Services Chiefs of India|year=2007|isbn=978-81-7211-162-5|publisher=Northern Book Centre|access-date=18 August 2016}}

==External links==
* {{cite web | url=http://mha.nic.in/sites/upload_files/mha/files/LST-PDAWD-2013.pdf | title=Padma Awards | publisher=Ministry of Home Affairs, Government of India | date=2015 | accessdate=July 21, 2015}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
|before = [[S. M. Shrinagesh]]
|title = [[Chief of Army Staff of the Indian Army|Chief of Army Staff]]
| years = 1962 – 1966
|after = [[Pran Nath Thapar]]
}}
{{s-end}}

{{Chief of the Army Staff India}}
{{PadmaBhushanAwardRecipients 1954–59}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Thimayya, K. S.}}
[[Category:1906 births]]
[[Category:1965 deaths]]
[[Category:Chiefs of Army Staff (India)]]
[[Category:Companions of the Distinguished Service Order]]
[[Category:British Indian Army officers]]
[[Category:People of the Korean War]]
[[Category:Kodava people]]
[[Category:People from Kodagu district]]
[[Category:Bishop Cotton Boys' School alumni]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Padma Bhushan in civil service]]
[[Category:Indo-Pakistani War of 1947]]
[[Category:Indian Army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Graduates of the Royal Military College, Sandhurst]]</text>
      <sha1>m7cgng7xjisyohfnk7urar764kqsz5x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
