<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ljudevit</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2892020</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742503008</id>
      <parentid>740930475</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-04T02:56:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14465">{{about|the medieval duke|the given name|Ljudevit (name)}}
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Infobox monarch
| name = Ljudevit/Liudewit
| title = Duke of Lower Pannonia{{Cref2|b|2}}
| image= Ljudevit Posavski.jpg
| caption=
| reign=c. 810 &amp;ndash; c. 823
| coronation=
| predecessor=
| successor=[[Ratimir, Duke of Lower Pannonia|Ratimir]]
| royal house=
| birth_date=|
| birth_place=|
| death_date=823
| death_place=Dalmatia
| place of burial=|
| father=|
| mother=|
}}
'''Ljudevit''' ({{IPA-sh|ʎûdeʋit|pron}}) or '''Liudewit''' ({{lang-la|Liudewitus}}, often also '''{{lang|hr|Ljudevit Posavski}}'''), was the [[Duke]] of [[Lower Pannonia (9th century)|Lower Pannonia]]{{Cref2|b|1}} from 810 to 823. The capital of his realm was in [[Sisak]]. As the ruler of the Pannonian Slavs,&lt;ref name=SS3-21&gt;{{cite book|title=Studia Slovenica|volume=3|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sIM6AQAAIAAJ|year=1960|publisher=Studia Slovenica|page=21|quote=... in the unsuccessful rebellion of Ljudevit of Posavia (Ljudevit Posavski), leader of the Pannonic Slavs, against the Franks, the semi-independence of the land was definitely at an end. From 828 onward it was administered by Bavarian counts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; he led a resistance to [[Franks|Frankish]] domination. He held close ties with the [[Karantanians|Carantanian]] and [[Carniola]]n tribes and with the [[Timočani]] tribe.

==Rebellions against the Franks==
In 818 Ljudevit sent his emissaries to [[Emperor]] [[Louis the Pious|Louis]] in [[Heristal]]. They described the horrors conducted by Cadolah and his men in [[Pannonia]], but the King of [[Franks]] refused to make peace. Ljudevit raised a rebellion against his Frankish rulers in 819 after he was seriously accused by the Frankish court. The [[List of Frankish Kings|Emperor]] [[Louis the Pious]] (814-840) sent [[Margrave]] [[Cadolah of Friuli]] (800-819) to quell the rebellion. The Frankish Frontier forces led by Cadolah have raided the land and tortured the population, most notably the children. As the Pannonian Slavs were amassing forces, so did the [[Franks]] led by Cadolah return in 819. But the Frankish forces were soon defeated; and Cadolah himself had to retreat back to his home [[Friuli]], where soon he died of disease.

In July 819 on the Council in [[Ingelheim]] Ljudevit's emissaries offered truce conditions, but Emperor Louis refused; demanding more concessions to him. Ljudevit started to gather allies for his plight. His original ally was [[Borna of Croatia|Duke Borna]] (Dux Dalmatiae et Liburniae) - the leader of the [[Guduscani]] (Gačani), but the Frankish ruler had promised Borna that he would make him ''Prince of Pannonia'' if he helped the Franks to crush Ljudevit's rebellion; so Borna accepted. Ljudevit found assistance among the [[Carantanians|Carantanian]] and [[March of Carniola|Carniolan]] Slavs who, as neighbours of the margravate of [[Friuli]], were jeopardized the same as the Pannonians. The [[Timočani]] (living around the valley of [[Timok (river)|Timok]]) also joined him, because they were jeopardized by the neighbouring [[Bulgars]].{{fact|date=April 2015}}

The Franks sent a large army led by the new [[Margrave of Friuli]], duke [[Baldric of Friuli]] to meet Ljudevit in autumn, the same year while he was conscripting more Carantanian troops along the [[Drava]] river. The Frankish forces had numerical advantage, so they pushed Ljudevit and his men from Carniola across the Drava. Ljudevit had to fall back to central parts of his realm. Baldric didn't chase Ljudevit, since he had to pacify the Carantanians. Borna moved with Ljudevit's father-in-law Dragomuž and their forces from the south-west. At the heat of the [[Battle of Kupa]], his own Guduscani abandoned Borna and crossed to Ljudevit's side; while Dragomuž was killed. Borna escaped from the battlefield with the help of his bodyguards.

Ljudevit seized the opportunity and breached into and raided [[Dalmatia (theme)|Dalmatia]] in December. Borna was too weak, so the Dalmatians defended themselves through sneaky tactics and used [[Attrition warfare|attrition]] as their best ally to exhaust the Pannonian forces. Harsh winter came to the hill areas, forcing Ljudevit to retreat. According to Borna's reports to the Frankish Emperor, Ljudevit suffered heavy casualties: 3,000 soldiers, over 300 horses and lots of food.

==War continues==
In January of 820, Borna made an alliance with the Frankish Emperor in [[Aachen]]. The plan was to crush Ljudevit's realm with a joint-attack from three sides. As soon as the winter retreated, massive Frankish armies were being amassed in [[Italy|Italia]], [[Francia|East Francia]], [[Bavaria]], [[Saxony]] and [[Alamanni|Alemannia]] that were going to simultaneously invade Ljudevit's lands in the spring. The northern Frankish group moved from Bavaria across Pannonia to make an invasion across the river of Drava. Ljudevit's forces successfully stopped this [[Army]] at the river. The southern group moved across the [[Noric Alps]], using the road from [[Aquileia]] to [[Emona]].{{citation needed|date=November 2010}} Ljudevit was successful again, as he stopped them before crossing the Alps. The central group moved from [[county of Tyrol|Tyrol]] to [[Carniola]]. Ljudevit attempted to halt its advance three times, but every single time would the Franks win, using numerical advantage. When this Army reached the [[Drava]], Ljudevit had to fall back to the heart of his realm.

The Franks have opened ways for the southern and northern Armies, so they launched a total invasion. Ljudevit concluded that all resistance would be futile, so he retreated to a stronghold that he built on top of hill that was heavily fortified; while his people took shelter in local [[forest]] and [[swamps]]. Ljudevit did not negotiate with the Franks. The Franks eventually retreated from his lands, with their ranks thinned by disease which the northern forces caught in the [[marshes]] of [[Drava]]. The [[Slavs]] from [[Carantania]] lost their internal independence and were forced to recognize the Friulian margrave Balderic as their ruler, while some remained loyal to Ljudevit. Prince Borna died in 821, and was succeeded by Ljudevit's nephew, [[Vladislav of Croatia|Vladislav]]. Emperor Louis recognized as ''Prince of Dalmatia and Liburnia'' in February 821 at the [[Council of Aachen]].

The Emperor discussed again about war plans against Ljudevit on that Council. The Franks decided to repeat the progress, and push towards Ljudevit from three sides again. Ljudevit saw that it was obvious that he couldn't fight the Franks on open field, so he began to construct massive [[fortifications]]. He was helped by the [[Venetia (region)|Venetia]]n [[Patriarch]] Fortunat who sent him [[architects]] and [[Stonemason|masons]] from [[Italy]].

During the last and final Frankish invasion of 822, the Patriarch from Grad, Fortunat, who was a supporter of Ljudevit, fled to [[Zadar]] into exile with the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantines]].

==Flight to the Serbs==
According to [[Einhard]], the writer of the [[Royal Frankish Annals]], following the final Frankish attack, Ljudevit escaped from his seat in [[Sisak]] to the Serbs who controlled a great part of [[Dalmatia (theme)|Dalmatia]] (''Siscia civitate relicta, ad Sorabos, quae natio magnam Dalmatiae partem obtinere dicitur, fugiendo se contulit.'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldstein-p235&quot;&gt;[[#Goldstein-1985|Goldstein, 1985]], p. 235.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Curta|2006|pp=136-137}} The notion of Serbs in the relative vicinity of Ljudevit has puzzled numerous historians because the relevant area wasn't otherwise known to have been inhabited by Serbs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldstein-p235&quot;/&gt; At the same time, the Royal Frankish Annals did not mention the Croats at all, causing historians to have to cross-reference other sources to compensate.{{sfn|Curta|2006|pp=136-137}}

[[Tadija Smičiklas]] did not attempt to define the area where Ljudevit fled, while [[Vjekoslav Klaić]] wrote it was beyond [[Sava]] and [[Bosna (river)|Bosna]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldstein-p235&quot;/&gt; [[Konstantin Jireček]] only indirectly mentioned that the Serbs had a fort around 820, but didn't specify its location. [[Ferdo Šišić]] put the ''ad Sorabos'' to the southeast of Sava and [[Vrbas (river)|Vrbas]], near the Dalmatian Croats. [[Vladimir Ćorović]] mentioned the flight to the Serbs, but didn't expound on it. The 1953 &quot;History of the peoples of Yugoslavia&quot; published by ''[[Školska knjiga]]'' added apparently fictitious details to the original story. [[Anto Babić]] discussed the original text and whether it was a reference to a single fort or a territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldstein-p236&quot;&gt;[[#Goldstein-1985|Goldstein, 1985]], p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Svetislav M. Prvanović]] tried to connect Ljudevit and the Guduscani with the Roman city of Guduscum in eastern Serbia, but using only the interpretation of a single comma in [[Franjo Rački]]'s text and conjecture. [[Sima Ćirković]] thought there was a consensus that the place was somewhere in Bosnia, but called the claims of exact locations speculation. [[Nada Klaić]] thought that the place Ljudevit fled to was actually the medieval county of [[Srb]] by the river [[Una (Sava)|Una]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldstein-p237&quot;&gt;[[#Goldstein-1985|Goldstein, 1985]], p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Relja Novaković]] analyzed Einhard and concluded that the area could be somewhere near [[Kozara]], [[Grmeč]], Una and [[Kupa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldstein-p238&quot;&gt;[[#Goldstein-1985|Goldstein, 1985]], p. 238.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ivo Goldstein]] acknowledged and accepted the theory that it was located in Srb, but advocated against misinterpreting the scarce historical records.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldstein-p243-244&quot;&gt;[[#Goldstein-1985|Goldstein, 1985]], p. 243&amp;ndash;244.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Radoslav Katičić]] argued against the theory, and [[Tibor Živković]] concurred with him.&lt;ref&gt;Tibor Živković: ''On the Beginnings of Bosnia in the Middle Ages'', 2010; in the Yearbook of the Center for Balkan Studies of the [[Academy of Sciences and Arts of Bosnia and Herzegovina]], p. 153, in Serbian, [http://www.anubih.ba/godisnjak/izdanja/Godisnjak%2039.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; Živković's 2011 interpretation of the Latin text says the second-hand accounts given to the Franks by their agents in Siscia and Croatia establish the existence of some sort of a Serbian claim over parts of (Roman) Dalmatia, similar to the analogous Frankish claim, but not necessarily settlement outside of places already known from other sources.{{sfn|Živković|2011|pp=392&amp;ndash;396}}

Ljudevit was welcomed at the unnamed Serbian ruler's court, but Ljudevit tricked him, killing the ruler and then taking the power for himself. Some believe the Serbian ruler was an ally of the [[Franks]] and Ljudevit thought that he was about to betray him.{{cn|date=July 2016}} Ljudevit soon sent an envoy to the Frankish court, claiming that he is ready to recognize the Frankish Emperor Louis the Pious as his supreme ruler.  After Ljudevit had left the Serbs, he was a guest of [[Ljudemisl]], Borna's uncle who treacherously killed him.{{sfn|Scholz|1970|p=113}}

==Annotations==
{{Cnote2 Begin|liststyle=upper-alpha}}
{{Cnote2|b|He was mentioned as &quot;Liudewitus, dux Pannoniae inferioris&quot; in the [[Frankish Annals]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Balcanoslavica|volume=5-7|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-lU8AAAAIAAJ|year=1977|page=114|quote=The report refers to the uprising of Liudewitus, dux Pannoniae inferioris (Ljudevit Posavski), which was joined by the inhabitants of Carniola (Annales regni Francorum, ad a. 818 — 823).}}&lt;/ref&gt; This title is translated as &quot;Duke of Lower Pannonia&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luthar2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Oto Luthar|title=The Land Between: A History of Slovenia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=G9tDboBJ70EC&amp;pg=PA109|year=2008|publisher=Peter Lang|isbn=978-3-631-57011-1|pages=109–}}&lt;/ref&gt; In older Croatian historiography, his title was claimed to have been &quot;Duke of Pannonian Croatia&quot;, which is erraneous, as it is anachronistic. The Croat ethnonym was first mentioned in the late 9th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | ref = Gračanin-2008 | url = http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=57788&amp;lang=en | language = Croatian | title = Od Hrvata pak koji su stigli u Dalmaciju odvojio se jedan dio i zavladao Ilirikom i Panonijom: Razmatranja uz DAI c. 30, 75-78 | first = Hrvoje | last = Gračanin | journal = History Teaching | issn = 1334-1375 | publisher = Croatian Historical Society | volume =  VI | number = 11 (1) |date=June 2008 | accessdate = 2012-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}
{{Cnote2 End}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
* Royal Frankish Annales [[Annales Regni Francorum]] ed. G. H. Pertz. Monumenta Germanicae Historica, Scriptores rerum Germanicarum 6, (Hannover 1895) for the years 819-822.
* Life of the Emperor Louis ([[Vita Hludowici]]), ed. E. Tremp. Monumenta Germaniae Historica: Scriptores rerum Germanicarum 64 (Hannover 1995) chapters 31-35.
* Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus, [[De Administrando Imperio]]
* {{cite journal | ref = Goldstein-1985 | url = http://www.historiografija.hr/hz/1984/HZ_37_11_GOLDSTEIN.pdf | accessdate = 2012-07-27 | language = Croatian | first = Ivo | last = Goldstein | authorlink = Ivo Goldstein | title = Ponovno o Srbima u Hrvatskoj u 9. stoljeću | journal = Historijski zbornik | volume = XXXVII (1) | publisher = Savez povijesnih društava Hrvatske, [[Faculty of Philosophy, Zagreb]] |date=May 1985}}
* {{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=YIAYMNOOe0YC&amp;pg=PA136 | title = Southeastern Europe in the Middle Ages, 500-1250 | authorlink = Florin Curta | first = Florin | last = Curta | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 2006 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Živković|first=Tibor|title=The Origin of the Royal Frankish Annalist's Information about the Serbs in Dalmatia|journal=Collection of works - Homage to Academician Sima Ćirković|editor-last=Rudić|editor-first=Srđan|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t_ZCCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA392|year=2011|publisher=Institute of History|location=Belgrade|volume=25|isbn=978-86-7743-091-7|pages=381–396|ref=harv}}

{{Dukes of Pannonia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Posavski, Ljudevit}}
[[Category:823 deaths]]
[[Category:Dukes of Croatia]]
[[Category:9th century in Croatia]]
[[Category:9th-century Slavs]]
[[Category:9th-century rulers in Europe]]
[[Category:History of Slavonia]]
[[Category:Medieval Slovenia]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:People of the Carolingian Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>ozkwgica7tx0w88dymb7edevq5jvwru</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
