<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mark I trench knife</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19815555</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748783716</id>
      <parentid>748779011</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-10T10:28:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KylieTastic</username>
        <id>2790592</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/89.207.213.13|89.207.213.13]] ([[User talk:89.207.213.13|talk]]): Rvt. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11543">[[File:S-mine.jpg|thumb|On the left a Mark I knife used to dig up an anti-personnel mine. The mine is an [[S-mine]]]]

The '''Mark I trench knife'''  was an American [[trench knife]] designed by officers of the [[American Expeditionary Force]] (AEF) for use in [[World War I]]. It had a {{convert|6.75|in|cm|abbr=on}} double edged [[dagger]] blade useful for both thrusting and slashing strokes, unlike previous U.S. trench knives such as the M1917 and M1918. The handle is made of [[Casting (metalworking)|cast]] [[bronze]] and uses a conical [[steel]] [[Nut (hardware)|nut]] to hold the blade in place.&lt;ref&gt;Cassidy, William L., ''The Complete Book Of Knife Fighting'', ISBN 0-87364-029-2, ISBN 978-0-87364-029-9 (1997), p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;  The Mark I's blade was [[bluing (steel)|blued]] with a [[black oxide]] finish, the bronze handle was chemically blackened, with cast spikes on the bow of each [[Brass knuckles|knuckle]].  The spikes were intended to prevent an opponent from grabbing the knife hand, as well as to provide a more concentrated striking surface when employed in [[hand-to-hand combat]].

==History==
[[File:M1918 Trench Knife.jpg|left|thumb|Mark I Trench Knife]]
The Mark I was a development of the earlier U.S. M1917 and the slightly improved M1918 trench knives designed by ''Henry Disston &amp; Sons'' of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;&gt;Crowell, Benedict (1919),''America's Munitions 1917-1918, Report of Benedict Crowell, Assistant Secretary of War (Director of Munitions)'', U.S. War Department, Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office, pp. 88, 228&lt;/ref&gt;  Both the M1917 and M1918 used a triangular blade and a handle equipped with a guard designed to protect the user's knuckles.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;  By 1918 it was apparent that the M1917 and M1918 designs were too limiting to succeed in their intended role,&lt;ref&gt;Cassidy, p. 45: Both the M1917 and M1918 had a narrow triangular stilletto-type blade which was not only prone to breakage, but restricted them to use as stabbing weapons.&lt;/ref&gt; and a new trench knife design was requested.&lt;ref&gt;Cassidy, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;   

On 1 June 1918 a panel of AEF officers conducted an exhaustive field test of various trench knives, including the U.S. M1917, the ''Hughes'' trench knife&lt;ref&gt;''Military affairs: journal of the American Military Institute'', American Military History Foundation, American Military Institute, Kansas State University, Dept. of History (1937) Vol. I, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hughes, Rupert, ''Letters Patent No. 1,315,503 issued September 9, 1919'', Washington, D.C.: United States Patent Office: An experimental design submitted by its inventor, U.S. Army Captain Rupert Hughes, the ''Hughes'' trench knife was a curious device consisting of a folding spring-loaded knife blade attached to a hasp which was fastened to the back of the hand by a strap, leaving the palm and fingers free for grasping other objects.  Pressing a button on the hasp automatically extended the knife blade into an open position and locked position, much like a [[switchblade]].  Unfortunately, after testing the board found the ''Hughes'' design to be of no value.&lt;/ref&gt; and the standard-issue trench knives of the British and French armies, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;  The field test was performed to examine the qualities of each knife based on the following criteria: 1. Serviceability - ability to carry one-handed while performing other tasks; 2. Quickness or rapidity of employment in action;  3. Security of grip, in case user was stunned or knocked unconscious; 4. Ease of carrying when crawling in low prone position;  5. Probability of knife being knocked out of hand during a struggle;  6. Suitability of blade weight, length, and shape; and 7. Shape of handle.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;

Testing confirmed that the existing M1917 and M1918 designs were in need of improvement.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;  Therefore, a replacement trench knife designated the U.S. Trench Knife, Mark I was jointly developed by officers of the AEF and the Engineering Division of U.S. Ordnance.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;  This knife was entirely different from the M1917, bearing a flat double-edged blade, a unique metal [[scabbard]], and a cast-bronze handle with built-in guard for individual fingers.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;  The AEF stated that the Mark I was a combination of all of the best features of the trench knives evaluated, and the Mark I's double-edged blade was taken directly from the ''Couteau Poignard Mle 1916 ''(known as'' Le Vengeur''), a trench knife design then currently in service with the French Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassidy, p. 47&quot;&gt;Cassidy, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

With the end of hostilites in World War I, large scale wartime contracts for Mark I knife production were cancelled.  Most Mark I knives that were produced by U.S. manufacturers were never issued, and remained in Army storage stateside.  During World War II, stocks of Mark I knives were released for issue to Army units with a need for a close-combat fighting knife, though in terms of actual numbers the Mark I did not see widespread use during the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassidy, p. 47&quot;/&gt;  Of those Mark I knives released for service, most were issued in 1942 and 1943 to soldiers serving in elite Army Ranger and airborne formations,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://ww2.rediscov.com/spring/VFPCGI.exe?IDCFile=/spring/DETAILS.IDC,SPECIFIC=16050,DATABASE=objects KNIFE - U.S. KNIFE MODEL 1918 MKI TRENCH]'' Springfield Armory Museum - Collection Record&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Canfield, Bruce N., ''U.S. INFANTRY WEAPONS OF WORLD WAR II'', Lincoln, RI: Andrew Mowbray Publishers, ISBN 0-917218-67-1, ISBN 978-0-917218-67-5 (1994)&lt;/ref&gt; though some Mark I knives were used by Marine units in 1942 and 1943, in particular Marines serving with the four [[Marine Raider]] battalions.&lt;ref&gt;Shackleford, Steve, ed. (2009), ''Blade's Guide To Knives And Their Values'', Krause Publications, ISBN 978-1-4402-0387-9, p. 387&lt;/ref&gt;  Army and Marine field reports concerning the effectiveness of the Mark I knife were mixed; some men liked the design, while others complained that Mark I was poorly balanced, with a relatively thin blade that was prone to snapping at the blade/handle junction, particularly when employed for utility tasks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassidy, p. 47&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walker, Greg, ''Battle Blades: A Professional's Guide to Combat/Fighting Knives'', Boulder, CO: Paladin Press, ISBN 0-87364-732-7 (1993), p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cassidy, William L., The Complete Book Of Knife Fighting, ISBN 0-87364-029-2, ISBN 978-0-87364-029-9 (1997), p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;  Other reports noted that the Mark I's large 'brass-knuckle' fingerguard handle was expensive to produce and limited the number of useful fighting grip positions, while preventing the knife from being carried in a conventional leather sheath or scabbard.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;Cassidy, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;  The Mark I also came in for criticism from Marine Raiders for its poor balance, relatively slow deployment speed and limited quick-kill penetration capability when used in an offensive role (the Raiders would eventually adopt a combat knife with a [[stiletto]]-style blade patterned after the [[Fairbairn-Sykes Fighting Knife]]).  Additionally, U.S. war planners had announced a need for a general-purpose trench knife that could fulfill both the fighting and utility roles, while at the same time conserving [[strategic metal]] resources.&lt;ref&gt;''Blending Metals to Arm Our Fighting Men'', Popular Science, Vol. 142 No. 6 (June 1943), p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;  

The Mark I trench knife was replaced in Army service by the '''[[M3 Fighting Knife|M3 trench knife]]''' in 1943,&lt;ref&gt;Cassidy, p. 47: While the M3 largely replaced the Mark I in service in 1943, the latter was not formally declared obsolete until January 1945.&lt;/ref&gt; while the U.S. Marine Corps issued its own combat and utility knife the same year designated the '''1219C2''', later known as the '''[[KA-BAR|USMC Mark 2 Combat Knife]]''' aka the '''USMC Knife, Fighting Utility'''.&lt;ref&gt;Shackleford, Steve (ed.), ''Blade's Guide To Knives And Their Values'' (7th ed.), Iola, WI: Krause Publications, ISBN 978-1-4402-0387-9, p. 387&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==
In order to save time in getting the new knife to troops in the field, the first Mark I trench knives were procured from a French manufacturer, ''Au Lion'' (Au Lion/Société Générale, France).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassidy, p. 47&quot;/&gt;  Subsequently the U.S. government placed orders for 1,232,780 Mark I knives with several U.S. contractors, including ''[[Landers, Frary &amp; Clark]]'' (L.F.&amp;C.) of [[New Britain, Connecticut]]; ''Henry Disston &amp; Sons'' (HD&amp;S) of [[Philadelphia]]; and ''Oneida Community Limited'' (O.C.L.), with deliveries to commence in December 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;  Ordnance records note that the end of the war in November 1918 caused Ordnance to cancel all orders for the Mark I with the exception of a single reduced order for 119,424 knives from ''Landers, Frary &amp; Clark Co.'' (L F &amp; C).&lt;ref name=&quot;BC&quot;/&gt;  Despite this apparent cancellation, otherwise original U.S. Mark I trench knives have been found with ''HD&amp;S'' and ''O.C.L.'' stamps, with grip handles cast in either bronze or aluminum.

The French version of the Mark I is stamped on the blade [[ricasso]] with a recumbent lion, and the words ''Au Lion'', while the grip is typically stamped &quot;U.S. 1918&quot;, and fitted with a four-sided [[Hilt#Pommel|pommel]] cap.  Made under wartime conditions, the French Mark I knife is generally more roughly finished than U.S. contracted examples, and incorporates several deviations from production specifications.  Several versions of the French model exist - some with grooves on top of the grip, some without, and some bearing letters and numbers cast into the bronze fingerguard.  As steel was a strategic material in wartime France, the French-manufactured Mark I was issued with a proprietary unmarked scabbard made of iron.       

U.S.-contracted Mark I knives are stamped on the right side of the brass grip &quot;U.S. 1918&quot;, with the contractor's initials located just below.  The U.S. knives utilized a six-sided pommel cap.  Like the French-made version, U.S. Mark I knives came with proprietary scabbards designed to accommodate the Mark I knife with its oversized grip, but fabricated of steel instead of iron.  Both blades and scabbards were issued with a [[Bluing (steel)|blackened finish]] to prevent reflection.  However, many soldiers (and later, civilian owners) attempted to polish the blades and/or scabbards, believing the blackened finish to be tarnish.  As a result, many original Mark I knives and scabbards have lost their original finish.   American-made steel scabbards for the Mark I trench knife were marked &quot;L.F.&amp;C. 1918&quot;.

==See also==
*[[List of daggers]]
*[[Push dagger]]
*[[BC-41]]
*[[Yarara Parachute Knife]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*Crowell, Benedict, ''America's Munitions 1917-1918, Report of Benedict Crowell, Assistant Secretary of War (Director of Munitions)'', U.S. War Department, Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office (1919)
*Walker, Greg, ''Battle Blades: A Professional's Guide to Combat/Fighting Knives'', Boulder, CO: Paladin Press, ISBN 0-87364-732-7 (1993)

==External links==
*http://arms2armor.com/Knives/m1trench.htm
*[http://worldwide.espacenet.com/publicationDetails/originalDocument?CC=GB&amp;NR=127777A&amp;KC=A&amp;FT=D&amp;ND=3&amp;date=19190612&amp;DB=EPODOC&amp;locale=en_EP Original Patent]

{{Knives}}
[[Category:Daggers]]
[[Category:Military knives]]
[[Category:World War I infantry weapons of the United States]]
[[Category:World War II infantry weapons of the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>lbfp6fjde2a7sdmtap1tzh5tqp6jh8q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
