<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Melvin Laird</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>80225</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750955102</id>
      <parentid>750411903</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T13:38:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rihioser</username>
        <id>29717016</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding Congress Delegations that Laird was in</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29536">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2016}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name         = Melvin Laird
|image        = Melvin Laird official photo.JPEG
|office       = [[United States Domestic Policy Council|White House Domestic Affairs Advisor]]
|president    = [[Richard Nixon]]
|term_start   = May 1, 1973
|term_end     = January 8, 1974&lt;br&gt;{{small|Acting: May 1, 1973 – June 6, 1973}}
|predecessor  = [[John Ehrlichman]]
|successor    = [[Kenneth Reese Cole, Jr.|Ken Cole]]
|office1      = [[United States Secretary of Defense]]
|president1   = [[Richard Nixon]]
|term_start1  = January 21, 1969
|term_end1    = January 29, 1973
|predecessor1 = [[Clark Clifford]]
|successor1   = [[Elliot Richardson]]
|office2      = [[Republican Conference Chairman of the United States House of Representatives|Chair of the House Republican Conference]]
|leader2      = [[Gerald Ford]]
|term_start2  = January 3, 1965
|term_end2    = January 3, 1969
|predecessor2 = [[Gerald Ford]]
|successor2   = [[John B. Anderson|John Anderson]]
|state3       = [[Wisconsin]]
|district3    = {{ushr|WI|7|7th}}
|term_start3  = January 3, 1953
|term_end3    = January 21, 1969
|predecessor3 = [[Reid F. Murray|Reid Murray]]
|successor3   = [[Dave Obey]]
|birth_name   = Melvin Robert Laird
|birth_date   = {{birth date|1922|09|01}}
|birth_place  = [[Omaha, Nebraska|Omaha]], [[Nebraska]], U.S.
|death_date   = {{nowrap|{{death date and age|2016|11|16|1922|9|1}}}}
|death_place  = [[Fort Myers, Florida|Fort Myers]], [[Florida]], U.S.
|party        = [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
|spouse       = Barbara Masters {{small|(1942–1992)}}&lt;br&gt;Carole Fleishman {{small|(1993–2016)}}
|children     = John&lt;br&gt;Allison&lt;br&gt;David&lt;br&gt;Kimberly
|alma_mater   = [[Carleton College]] {{small|([[Bachelor of Arts|BA]])}}
|allegiance   = {{flag|United States}}
|branch       = {{flag|United States Navy}}
|serviceyears = 1942–1946
|battles      = [[World War II]]
|mawards      = [[Purple Heart]]
}}
'''Melvin Robert''' &quot;'''Bom'''&quot; '''Laird''' (September 1, 1922 – November 16, 2016) was an American politician and writer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/dictionary/index.asp?action=view&amp;term_id=2566&amp;search_term=laird|title=404 Error: File Not Found - Wisconsin Historical Society|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was a [[U.S. House of Representatives|U.S. congressman]] from [[Wisconsin]] from 1953 to 1969 before serving as [[United States Secretary of Defense|Secretary of Defense]] from 1969 to 1973 under President [[Richard Nixon]]. Laird was instrumental in forming the administration's policy of withdrawing U.S. soldiers from the [[Vietnam War]]; he invented the expression &quot;[[Vietnamization]],&quot; referring to the process of transferring more responsibility for combat to the South Vietnamese forces. First elected in 1952, Laird was the last surviving Representative elected to the [[83rd United States Congress|83rd Congress]] at the time of his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jsonline.com/story/news/politics/elections/2016/11/16/former-defense-secretary-melvin-laird-dies/93974304/|title=Former defense secretary Melvin Laird dies|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Laird was born in [[Omaha, Nebraska]], the son of [[Melvin R. Laird, Sr.]], a politician, businessman, and clergyman.&lt;ref name=&quot;nydailynews.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/news/politics/melvin-laird-defense-secretary-nixon-dead-age-94-article-1.2876466|title=Melvin Laird, Defense Secretary under Nixon, dead at age 94|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He grew up and attended high school in [[Marshfield, Wisconsin]],&lt;ref name=&quot;nydailynews.com&quot;/&gt; although in his junior year he attended [[Lake Forest Academy]] in [[Lake Forest, Illinois]].  He was nicknamed &quot;Bambino&quot; (shortened to &quot;Bom&quot; and pronounced like the word 'bomb') by his mother.

Laird was the grandson of [[William D. Connor]], the [[Lieutenant Governor of Wisconsin]] from 1907 to 1909, and the great-grandson of [[Robert Connor (politician)|Robert Connor]], a member of the [[Wisconsin State Assembly]]. His niece is Jessica Laird Doyle, wife of former [[Wisconsin]] Governor [[Jim Doyle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nydailynews.com&quot;/&gt;

He graduated from [[Carleton College]] in [[Minnesota]] in May 1944, having enlisted in the [[United States Navy]] a year earlier. Following his commissioning as an [[ensign (rank)|ensign]], he served on a destroyer, the [[USS Maddox (DD-731)|USS ''Maddox'' (DD-731)]], in the [[Pacific War|Pacific]] during the end of [[World War II]]. A recipient of the [[Purple Heart]] and several other decorations, Laird left the Navy in April 1946.

==Legislative career==
Laird entered the [[Wisconsin State Senate]] at age 23, succeeding his deceased father.&lt;ref&gt;'Wisconsin Blue Book 1948,' Biographical Sketch of Melvin R. Laird, Jr., pg. 36&lt;/ref&gt; He represented a legislative district encompassing [[Stevens Point, Wisconsin]]. He remained in the Senate until his [[election]] in November 1952 to the [[United States House of Representatives]] representing Wisconsin's 7th District in central Wisconsin, including the areas of [[Marshfield, Wisconsin|Marshfield]], [[Wausau, Wisconsin|Wausau]], [[Wisconsin Rapids, Wisconsin|Wisconsin Rapids]] and [[Stevens Point, Wisconsin|Stevens Point]]. In the [[Republican Party (United States) presidential primaries, 1964|1964 Republican presidential primaries]], Laird was an &quot;unannounced&quot; supporter of [[Arizona]] Senator [[Barry Goldwater]], and chaired the Platform Committee at that year's Republican convention, at which Goldwater was nominated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,939007-1,00.html Nation: What the Platform Says], ''[[Time Magazine]]'' (July 24, 1964)&lt;/ref&gt;

Laird was re-elected eight consecutive times and he was chairman of the House Republican Conference when Nixon selected him for the cabinet. He was known for his work on both domestic and defense issues, including his service on the Defense subcommittee of the [[House Appropriations Committee]]. He left Congress reluctantly, making it clear when he became secretary on January 22, 1969 that he intended to serve no more than four years.

As a congressman Laird had supported a strong defense posture and had sometimes been critical of Secretary [[Robert McNamara|McNamara]]. In September 1966, characterizing himself as a member of the loyal opposition, he publicly charged the [[Lyndon Johnson|Johnson administration]] with deception about [[Vietnam]] war costs and for delaying decisions to escalate the ground war until after the 1966 congressional elections. Laird also criticized McNamara's management and decision-making practices.

Laird was reportedly the elder statesman chosen by the Republicans to convince [[Vice President]] [[Spiro Agnew]] to resign his position after Agnew's personal corruption became a public scandal. He also had a prominent role in the selection of [[Gerald Ford]] as Agnew's replacement as Vice President.

==Secretary of Defense==
[[File:Nixon with Melvin Laird.gif|thumb|right|238px|Laird with President [[Richard Nixon]], under whom he served as [[Secretary of Defense]].]]
After he became [[Secretary of Defense]], Laird and President Nixon appointed a Blue Ribbon Defense Panel that made more than 100 recommendations on [[United States Department of Defense|DoD]]'s organization and functions in a report on July 1, 1970. The department implemented a number of the panel's proposals while Laird served in the Pentagon.

===Managerial style===
Laird did not depart abruptly from the McNamara-[[Clark M. Clifford|Clifford]] management system, but rather instituted gradual changes. He pursued what he called &quot;participatory management,&quot; an approach calculated to gain the cooperation of the military leadership in reducing the Defense budget and the size of the military establishment. While retaining decisionmaking functions for himself and the deputy secretary of defense, Laird somewhat decentralized policymaking and operations. He accorded the service secretaries and the [[Joint Chiefs of Staff|JCS]] a more influential role in the development of budgets and force levels. He revised the PPBS, including a return to the use of service budget ceilings and service programming of forces within these ceilings. The previously powerful systems analysis office could no longer initiate planning, only evaluate and review service proposals.

Laird noted this in his FY 1971 report, &quot;Except for the major policy decisions, I am striving to decentralize decisionmaking as much as possible ... So, we are placing primary responsibility for detailed force planning on the Joint Chiefs and the Services, and we are delegating to the Military Departments more responsibility to manage development and procurement programs.&quot; The military leadership was enthusiastic about Laird's methods. As the [[Washington Post]] reported after his selection as secretary of defense, &quot;Around the military-industrial complex these days they're singing 'Praise the Laird and pass the transformation.'&quot;

Laird did not shrink from centralized management where he found it useful or warranted. His tenure saw the establishment of the [[Defense Investigative Service]], the [[Defense Mapping Agency]], the [[Office of Net Assessment]], and the [[Defense Security Assistance Agency]] (to administer all DoD military assistance programs). In October 1972 Congress passed legislation creating a second deputy secretary of defense position, a proposal Laird strongly supported, even though he never filled the position. Laird paid special attention to two important interdepartmental bodies: the [[Washington Special Action Group]] (WSAG), composed of senior Defense, [[United States Department of State|State]], and [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] officials, which gathered information necessary for presidential decisions on the crisis use of U.S. military forces; and the [[Defense Program Review Committee]] (DPRC), which brought together representatives from many agencies, including DoD, State, the [[Council of Economic Advisers]], and the [[Office of Management and Budget]], to analyze defense budget issues as a basis for advising the president, placing, as Laird commented, &quot;national security needs in proper relationship to non-defense requirements.&quot;

===Pentagon budget===
Laird succeeded in improving DoD's standing with Congress. As a highly respected congressional veteran, Laird had a head start in his efforts to gain more legislative support for Defense programs. He maintained close contact with old congressional friends, and he spent many hours testifying before Senate and House committees. Recognizing the congressional determination, with wide public support, to cut defense costs (including winding down the Vietnam War), Laird worked hard to prune budgetary requests before they went to Congress, and acceded to additional cuts when they could be absorbed without serious harm to national security. One approach, which made it possible to proceed with such new strategic weapon systems as the [[B-1 bomber]], the [[Trident missile|Trident nuclear submarine]], and [[cruise missile]]s, was agreement to a substantial cut in conventional forces. As a result, total military personnel declined from some 3.5 million in FY 1969 to 2.3 million by the time Laird left office in January 1973. Those weapon platforms, as well as the [[F-15]], [[F-16]], [[A-10]], and [[Los Angeles-class submarine|Los Angeles-class nuclear submarine]] were all programs started by the Laird Pentagon.

Other initiatives, including troop withdrawals from Vietnam, phasing out old weapon systems, base closures, and improved procurement practices, enabled the Pentagon to hold the line on spending, even at a time when high inflation affected both weapon and personnel costs. In Laird's years, total obligational authority by fiscal year was as follows: 1969, $77.7 billion; 1970, $75.5 billion; 1971, $72.8 billion; 1972, $76.4 billion; and 1973, $78.9 billion.

===Vietnam War===
Vietnam preoccupied Laird as it had McNamara and Clifford. In 1968 Nixon campaigned on a platform critical of the Johnson administration's handling of the war and promised to achieve &quot;[[peace with honor]]&quot;. Although not receptive to demands for immediate withdrawal, Laird acknowledged the necessity to disengage U.S. combat forces gradually. Thus he developed and strongly supported &quot;[[Vietnamization]]&quot;, a program intended to expand, equip, and train [[South Vietnam]]'s forces and assign to them an ever-increasing combat role, at the same time steadily reducing the number of U.S. combat troops. During 1969 the new administration cut authorized U.S. troop strength in Vietnam from 549,500 to 484,000, and by May 1, 1972 the number stood at 69,000. During this same period, from January 1969 to May 1972, U.S. combat deaths declined 95 percent from the 1968 peak, and war expenditures fell by about two-thirds. Laird publicized Vietnamization widely; in his final report as secretary of defense in early 1973, he stated: &quot;Vietnamization ... today is virtually completed. As a consequence of the success of the military aspects of Vietnamization, the South Vietnamese people today, in my view, are fully capable of providing for their own in-country security against the [[North Vietnam]]ese.&quot;

In this same report Laird noted that the war had commanded more of his attention than any other concern during his four-year term. Upon becoming secretary he set up a special advisory group of DoD officials, known as the Vietnam Task Force, and he met with them almost every morning he was in the Pentagon. He also visited Vietnam several times for on-the-scene evaluations. Although his program of Vietnamization could be termed a success, if one considers the progress of troop withdrawals, U.S. involvement in the conflict became perhaps even more disruptive at home during Nixon's presidency than during Johnson's. The U.S. incursion into [[Cambodia]] in May 1970 to eliminate North Vietnamese sanctuaries, the renewed bombing of North Vietnam and the mining of its harbors in the spring of 1972 in response to a North Vietnamese offensive, and another bombing campaign against the North in December 1972 brought widespread protest. Nixon's Vietnam policy, as well as that of previous administrations, suffered further criticism when, in June 1971, the [[Pentagon Papers]], a highly classified narrative and documentary history of U.S. involvement in Vietnam from 1945 to 1967, prepared at Secretary McNamara's order, was leaked and published in part in several major newspapers.

Laird publicly supported Nixon's Vietnam course, although Laird privately opposed the deception used to mask the Cambodian invasion from the American populace. He counted on the success of Vietnamization, peace talks that had begun in 1968 in Paris, and the secret negotiations in Paris between [[Henry Kissinger]], the president's assistant for national security affairs, and North Vietnamese representatives to end the conflict. On January 27, 1973, two days before Laird left office, the negotiators signed a Vietnam settlement in Paris. They agreed to an in-place cease-fire to begin on January 28, 1973, complete withdrawal of U.S. forces within 60 days, the concurrent phased release of U.S. [[prisoners of war]] in North Vietnam, and establishment of an international control commission to handle disagreements among the signatories. Although, as time was to demonstrate, South Vietnam was not really capable of defending its independence, Laird retired from office satisfied that he had accomplished his major objective, the disengagement of United States combat forces from Vietnam.

===Cold War and nuclear war planning===
Vietnam preoccupied Laird, but not to the exclusion of other pressing matters. Although not intimately involved in the development of strategic nuclear policy as McNamara had been, Laird subscribed to the Nixon administration's program of &quot;[[Strategic Sufficiency]]&quot; - that the United States should have the capability to deter [[nuclear weapons|nuclear]] attacks against its home territory and that of its allies by convincing a potential aggressor that he would suffer an unacceptable level of retaliatory damage; it should also have enough nuclear forces to eliminate possible coercion of its allies. The policy, not much different from McNamara's except in name and phrasing, embraced the need both to avoid mass destruction of civilians and to seek mechanisms to prevent escalation of a nuclear conflict. The administration further refined its strategic ideas in July 1969 when the president issued a statement that came to be known as the &quot;[[Nixon Doctrine]]&quot;, stressing &quot;pursuit of peace through partnership with our allies.&quot; Instead of the previous administration's &quot;2½ war&quot; concept - readiness to fight simultaneous wars on two major fronts and one minor front - the Nixon Doctrine cut back to the &quot;1½ war&quot; level. Through military aid and credit-assisted sales of military equipment abroad, the United States would prepare its allies to take up a greater share of the defense burden, especially manpower needs, in case of war. U.S. military forces would be &quot;smaller, more mobile, and more efficient general purpose forces that ... [would] neither cast the United States in the role of world policeman nor force the nation into a new isolationism.&quot; Laird supported the strategic arms talks leading to the [[SALT I]] agreements with the [[Soviet Union]] in 1972: a five-year moratorium against expansion of strategic nuclear delivery systems, and an [[Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty|antiballistic missile treaty]] limiting each side to two sites (later cut to one) for deployed ABM systems. As Laird put it, &quot;In terms of United States strategic objectives, SALT I improved our deterrent posture, braked the rapid buildup of Soviet strategic forces, and permitted us to continue those programs which are essential to maintaining the sufficiency of our long-term strategic nuclear deterrent.&quot;

===Conscription suspended===
Other important Laird goals were ending [[conscription]] by June 30, 1973 and the creation of an [[Volunteer military|All Volunteer Force]] (AVF). Strong opposition to selective service mounted during the Vietnam War and draft calls declined progressively during Laird's years at the Pentagon; from 300,000 in his first year, to 200,000 in the second, 100,000 in the third, and 50,000 in the fourth. On January 27, 1973, after the signing of the Vietnam agreement in Paris, Laird suspended the draft, five months ahead of schedule.

==Later career==
Laird completed his term of office as secretary of defense on January 29, 1973. Because he had stated repeatedly that he would serve only four years (only [[Charles Erwin Wilson|Charles E. Wilson]] and [[Robert McNamara]] among his predecessors served longer), it came as no surprise when President Nixon on November 28, 1972 nominated [[Elliot Richardson]] to succeed him. In his final report in January 1973 Laird listed what he considered to be the major accomplishments of his tenure: Vietnamization; achieving the goal of strategic sufficiency; effective burden-sharing between the United States and its friends and allies; adequate security assistance; maintenance of U.S. technological superiority through development of systems such as the B-1, Trident, and cruise missiles; improved procurement; &quot;People Programs&quot; such as ending the draft and creating the AVF; improved [[United States National Guard|National Guard]] and Reserve forces; enhanced operational readiness; and participatory management. One of Laird's most active initiatives was his persistent effort to secure the release of the American captives held by the enemy in Vietnam.

During his tenure as Defense Secretary, Laird did not share President Nixon's lingering timetable for withdrawal from Vietnam. He publicly contradicted the administrations policy, which upset the [[White House]]. Laird wished to return to the political arena, and was said to be planning a run for president in 1976. After Watergate,  this proved implausible. There was also talk of a Senate run and perhaps a return to his old House seat in hopes of becoming Speaker.

[[File:Melvin Laird, Donald Rumsfeld, Dale VanAtta · DD-SC-07-14896.JPEG|left|200px|thumb|Laird (left) with one of his successors, [[Donald Rumsfeld]], and biographer [[Dale Van Atta]], 2001]]
In spite of Vietnam and the unfolding [[Watergate scandal|Watergate]] affair, which threatened to discredit the entire Nixon administration, Laird retired with his reputation intact. Although not a close confidant of the president and not the dominant presence that McNamara was, Laird had been an influential secretary. He achieved a smooth association with the military leadership by restoring some of the responsibilities they had lost during the 1960s. His excellent relations with Congress enabled him to gain approval for many of his programs and budget requests.

After a brief absence, Laird returned to the Nixon administration in June 1973 as [[counselor to the president]] for domestic affairs, concerning himself mainly with legislative issues. In February 1974, as the Watergate crisis in the White House deepened, Laird resigned to become senior counselor for national and international affairs for ''[[Reader's Digest]]''. Following [[Richard Nixon]]'s resignation as [[President of the United States|President]], Laird was reported to be the first choice of successor [[Gerald Ford]] to be nominated [[Vice President of the United States|Vice President]], a position ultimately filled by [[Nelson Rockefeller]].

In 1974, he received the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]]. Since 1974, he has written widely for ''Reader's Digest'' and other publications on national and international topics.

On January 5, 2006, he participated in a meeting at the [[White House]] of former Secretaries of Defense and State to discuss United States foreign policy with Bush administration officials.

Journalist [[Dale Van Atta]] has written a biography of Laird entitled, &quot;With Honor: Melvin Laird in War, Peace, and Politics,&quot; published by the [[University of Wisconsin Press]], 2008.&lt;ref&gt;Van Atta, Dale. ''With Honor: Melvin Laird in War, Peace, and Politics''. Madison, Wis: University of Wisconsin Press, 2008. ISBN 0299226808 {{OCLC|182056519}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Role in health care research==
Laird played a key role in advancing medical research, although this part of his biography is often overshadowed by his political achievements.
“Laird’s position on the House Appropriations subcommittee handling health matters allowed him to play a key congressional role on many medical and health issues. He often teamed up with liberal Democrat [[John E. Fogarty|John Fogarty]] of Rhode Island to pass key legislation on education or health matters. Their impact on the [[National Institutes of Health]] was pivotal in a vast expansion of health research programs and facilities. They also sponsored the buildup of the [[National Library of Medicine]], the [[Center for Disease Control]] in [[Atlanta]], the National Environmental Center in North Carolina, and the nation’s eight National Cancer Centers, later part of the [[National Institutes of Health]]. Laird received many awards for his work on health matters, including the [[Albert Lasker Medical Research Award]] (1964) and the [[American Public Health Association]] award for leadership.” This account of his role is noted in the [[Gerald R. Ford]] Presidential Library biography.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fordlibrarymuseum.gov/library/guides/findingaid/Laird,_Melvin_-_Papers.asp|title=Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library and Museum|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Between 1956 and 1967, Laird was appointed a member of the U.S. Delegation to the [[World Health Organization]] in [[Geneva]], [[Switzerland]], by three U.S. Presidents – [[Dwight Eisenhower]], [[John Kennedy]] and [[Lyndon Johnson]].

In fact, President Eisenhower so admired Laird's work in Congress for world health and national security that he described Congressman Laird as &quot;one of the 10 men best qualified to become President of the United States.&quot;

Laird's interest in medical research is documented by his co-authoring legislation to finance the construction of the [[National Library of Medicine]], and important centers for medical research on many university campuses (among them the [[McArdle Laboratory for Cancer Research]] and the [[University of Wisconsin]] Cancer Center in Madison) and the major institutes of the [[National Institutes of Health]] in [[Bethesda, MD]]. Laird, Congressman Fogarty and Senator [[Lister Hill]] (D-Alabama) also authorized legislation which funded the building of the [[Centers for Disease Control]] and Prevention (CDCP) in Atlanta, GA.&lt;ref&gt; BenchMarks Magazine, Fall, 1994 {{cite web|url=https://www.marshfieldclinic.org/giving/benchmarks|title=BenchMarks|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and legacy ==
Following the death of [[Clarence Clifton Young]] on April 3, 2016, Laird became the last surviving member of the [[83rd United States Congress|83rd Congress]], as well as the last surviving member elected in either the [[United States House of Representatives elections, 1952|1952]] or [[United States House of Representatives elections, 1954|1954 elections]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bioguide.congress.gov/biosearch/biosearch.asp|title=Congressional Biographical Directory (CLERKWEB)|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Laird died of [[congestive heart failure]] in [[Fort Myers]], [[Florida]] on November 16, 2016 at the age of 94.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/melvin-laird-nixon-defense-secretary-at-the-height-of-the-vietnam-war-dies-at-94/2016/11/16/7956cdca-ac44-11e6-8b45-f8e493f06fcd_story.html|title=Melvin Laird, Nixon defense secretary at the height of the Vietnam War, dies at 94|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/cheats/2016/11/16/nixon-s-secretary-of-defense-dead-at-94.html|title=Nixon’s Secretary of Defense Dead at 94|date=November 16, 2016|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Laird Center, a medical clinic in Marshfield, Wisconsin is named after him.&lt;ref name=&quot;nydailynews.com&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Navy}}
* [[Laird v. Tatum]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}
{{CongBio|L000024}}
*[http://www.defense.gov/specials/secdef_histories/bios/laird.htm] US Department of Defense Biography
*[http://www.marshfieldnewsherald.com/] Marshfield Herald News archives
*[https://www.marshfieldclinic.org/giving/benchmarks] BenchMark Magazine archives

;Bibliography
*Laird, Helen L., ''A Mind of Her Own: Helen Connor Laird and Family, 1888–1982'', [[The University of Wisconsin Press]], 2006.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Melvin Laird}}
* Laird Center [http://www.lairdcenter.org/melvinlaird/default.aspx?page=lairdbio Biography]
*[http://www.fordlibrarymuseum.gov/library/guides/Finding%20Aids/Laird.htm Melvin Laird Papers at the Gerald Ford Library]
*[http://www.foreignaffairs.org/20051101faessay84604/melvin-r-laird/iraq-learning-the-lessons-of-vietnam.html Iraq: Learning the Lessons of Vietnam&quot; by Melvin R. Laird.] – ''[[Foreign Affairs]]'' Magazine article, November/December 2005 Issue.
*[http://purl.fdlp.gov/GPO/gpo58541 Melvin Laird and the Foundation of the Post-Vietnam Military, 1969-1973] [[Office of the Secretary of Defense]]

{{s-start}}
{{s-par|us-hs}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Reid F. Murray|Reid Murray]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Member of the [[List of United States Representatives from Wisconsin|U.S. House of Representatives]]&lt;br&gt;from [[Wisconsin's 7th congressional district]]|years=1953–1969}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Dave Obey]]}}
|-
{{s-ppo}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Gerald Ford]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Republican Conference Chairman of the United States House of Representatives|Chair of the House Republican Conference]]|years=1965–1969}}
{{s-aft|after=[[John B. Anderson|John Anderson]]}}
|-
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Clark Clifford]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[United States Secretary of Defense]]|years=1969–1973}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Elliot Richardson]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[John Ehrlichman]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[United States Domestic Policy Council|White House Domestic Affairs Advisor]]|years=1973–1974}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Kenneth Reese Cole, Jr.|Ken Cole]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{USSecDef}}
{{Nixon cabinet}}
{{Authority control}}
{{USCongRep-start|congresses=83rd–90th [[United States Congress]]es|state=[[Wisconsin]]}}
{{USCongRep/WI/83}}
{{USCongRep/WI/84}}
{{USCongRep/WI/85}}
{{USCongRep/WI/86}}
{{USCongRep/WI/87}}
{{USCongRep/WI/88}}
{{USCongRep/WI/89}}
{{USCongRep/WI/90}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Laird, Melvin R.}}
[[Category:1922 births]]
[[Category:2016 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American naval officers]]
[[Category:American naval personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:American people of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:American Presbyterians]]
[[Category:Carleton College alumni]]
[[Category:George Washington University trustee]]
[[Category:Lake Forest Academy alumni]]
[[Category:Members of the United States House of Representatives from Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Nixon administration cabinet members]]
[[Category:People from Marshfield, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Politicians from Omaha, Nebraska]]
[[Category:Presidential Medal of Freedom recipients]]
[[Category:Republican Party members of the United States House of Representatives]]
[[Category:United States Secretaries of Defense]]
[[Category:Wisconsin Republicans]]
[[Category:Wisconsin State Senators]]</text>
      <sha1>b593k2y852biffwgsxmogdqj8vfb74q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
