<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Montford Point Marine Association</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5689955</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746194262</id>
      <parentid>746194180</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-25T21:01:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FieldMarine</username>
        <id>5113002</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* History of Camp Montford Point */ Spelling.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8521">{{About|the nonprofit organization|the article about the military base|Montford Point}}

{{Infobox organization
| name   = Montford Point Marine Association, Inc
| logo   = [[File:MPMA Logo.JPG|200px]]
| type   = 
| founded_date      = 
| founder           = 
| location          = &lt;!-- this parameter modifies &quot;Headquarters&quot; --&gt;
| origins           = 
| key_people        = 
| area_served       = 
| product           =
| focus             = 
| method            = 
| revenue           = 
| endowment         = 
| num_volunteers    = 
| num_employees     = 
| num_members       = 
| subsib            = 
| owner             = 
| Non-profit_slogan = 
| homepage          = [http://montfordpointmarines.com/ montfordpointmarines.com]
| dissolved         = 
| footnotes         = 
}}

'''The Montford Point Marine Association''' ('''MPMA''') is a nonprofit military veteran's organization, founded to memorialize the legacy of the first African Americans to serve in the [[United States Marine Corps]]. The first African American U.S. Marines were trained  at [[Montford Point|Camp Montford Point]], in [[Jacksonville, North Carolina]], from 1942 to 1949.

The Association's stated creed is:

&lt;blockquote&gt;  
To promote and preserve the strong bonds of friendship born from shared adversities and to devote ourselves to the furtherance of these accomplishments to ensure more peaceful times.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The organization supports educational assistance programs, veterans programs, and community services, with an emphasis on improving the social conditions of the growing population of military veterans who are disabled or senior citizens.

Membership in the nonprofit organization is open to veterans and active members of all branches of the [[U.S. Armed Forces]] regardless of race, creed, or national origin. The MPMA also hosts the MPMA Ladies Auxiliary.  Membership in the Ladies Auxiliary is open to wives, daughters, sisters, and mothers of members or former members of the United States Armed Forces.

==History of Camp Montford Point==
[[File:MPMA Generations.JPG|thumb|right|Reuben J. McNair, Sr., and a fellow veteran of the Montford Point Marine Association, converses with a present-day African American Marine officer.]]

In 1940 while the United States prepared for war, millions of jobs in the defense industry were being created.  Blacks seeking jobs in the growing defense industries suffered violence and discrimination. Many black leaders, including [[A. Philip Randolph]], president of the [[Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters]] and the most widely known spokesperson for black working-class interests in the United States, met with [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] and his administration to demand that he sign an executive order banning discrimination against black workers in the defense industry. Randolph threatened to bring tens of thousands of marchers to [[Washington, D.C.]]  On June 25, 1941, days before the march was to occur, Roosevelt issued [[Executive Order 8802]], which barred government agencies and federal contractors from refusing employment in industries engaged in defense production on the basis of race, creed, color, or national origin. It was the first Presidential decree issued on race since [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]]. The order required the armed services, including the  Marine Corps, to recruit and enlist [[African Americans]].

Recruiting for the &quot;Montford Marines&quot; began on June 1, 1942. Thousands of African American men, eager to serve, flocked to recruiting offices. The first black recruits received basic training at the segregated [[Camp Gilbert H. Johnson|Camp Montford Point]] in [[Jacksonville, North Carolina]]. The 1,200 men in the quota were housed in prefabricated huts.  Racism continued in the Marine Corps after the issuance of [[Executive Order 9981]], reflecting that in the society. Railroad tracks divided white residents from the camp for African American troops, and the black recruits were not allowed to enter the main base of nearby [[Camp Lejeune]] unless accompanied by a white Marine. By 1945, all drill instructors and many NCOs at Montford Point were African Americans.

Between 1942 and 1949, more than 20,000 men were trained at Montford Point. In July 1948, despite strong opposition from [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] of the segregated South, President [[Harry S. Truman]] signed Executive Order 9981, which required the desegregation of the military.  In 1949 Montford Point was deactivated, and new black recruits were sent to [[Marine Corps Recruit Depot Parris Island|Parris Island]] and [[Marine Corps Base Camp Pendleton|Camp Pendleton]]. During the [[Korean War]], the United States Marine Corps fully integrated.

In 1965, a reunion of Marines was held in Philadelphia which included former Montford Point Marines along with Marines on active duty. With more than 400 Marines from throughout the United States gathered, they decided to establish the Montford Point Marine Association as a nonprofit veterans organization, to preserve military history and help people in need. The Association has many chapters, and is a member of the Marine Corps Council, a council of Marine-related service groups.

The Montford Point Marine Association maintains archives, and the [[Camp Gilbert H. Johnson#Montford Point Marines Museum|Montford Point Marines Museum]] at Camp Gilbert H. Johnson, Jacksonville, North Carolina. It holds an annual convention to celebrate the Montford Point Marines, make organizational decisions, and distribute scholarships.

On 27 June 2012, the [[Congressional Gold Medal]] was awarded to the Montford Point Marines.

==Notable Montford Point Marines ==
* [[Sergeant major#United States Marine Corps|Sgt. Maj.]] [[Gilbert Johnson|Gilbert &quot;Hashmark&quot; Johnson]], one of the first African Americans to enlist and serve as a drill instructor in the Marine Corps
* [[David Dinkins]], former Mayor of New York City

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot;&gt;
File:MPMA Groves1.JPG|Training picture of Eugene Groves, one of the first African Americans to enlist in the United States Marine Corps and train at Montford Point
File:Gilbert Johnson.jpg|[[Sergeant major#United States Marine Corps|Sgt Maj]] Gilbert &quot;Hashmark&quot; Johnson, one of the first African American drill instructors in the Marine Corps
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Appearances in Popular Culture ==
The main character of the long-running crime drama [[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]], [[Leroy Jethro Gibbs]] is played by [[Mark Harmon]] and his character is named for his father's best friend, Leroy Jethro Moore, a Montford Point Marine (played by [[Billy Dee Williams]]). The character L.J. Moore was depicted receiving the [[Congressional Medal of Honor]] for his actions in the [[Pacific Theater of World War II]], notably only receiving the medal after corrective actions were taken by U.S. Congress in 1996. A photo showing Williams shaking hands with [[President Bill Clinton]] was also displayed, lending some extra realism to the story. The episode titled [[The Namesake (NCIS)|The Namesake]] was the fifth episode of the tenth season and originally aired on [[CBS]] on October 30, 2012. The episode ends with a dedication to the Montford Point Marines &quot;Honored with the Congressional Gold Medal, June 27, 2012.&quot; 

== See also ==
{{Portal|United States Marine Corps}}

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
* McLaurin, Melton A. (2007). ''The Marines of Montford Point: America's First Black Marines''. UNC Press. ISBN 0-8078-3097-6.
* {{cite web |url=http://marinesmagazine.dodlive.mil/2009/07/16/paving-the-way-2/ |title=Paving the Way |last=Werling |first=LCpl Nichole R. |date=July 16, 2009 |work=Corps Lore: ''Marines'' Magazine |publisher=United States Marine Corps |accessdate=1 April 2010}}

==External links==
* [http://www.montfordpointmarines.com/index.html Montford Point Marine Association, Inc. Website] 
* [http://library.uncw.edu/web/montford/ &quot;Camp Montford Point&quot;], University of North Carolina Wilmington, Randall Library
* [http://www.pbs.org/thewar/detail_5178.htm The War Witnesses: John Gray], Ken Burns and Lynn Novick, ''The War'', Public Broadcasting System
* [http://www.aflcio.org/aboutus/history/history/randolph.cfm &quot;John Philip Randolph&quot;], AFL-CIO America's Union Movement

{{US Marine Corps navbox}}

[[Category:American veterans' organizations]]
[[Category:Organizations associated with the United States Marine Corps]]
[[Category:African-American history of the United States military]]</text>
      <sha1>aq5f7edbuqkw850jof1pqctne1mqcer</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
