<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pakistan Rangers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4611195</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750732936</id>
      <parentid>750732903</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T14:42:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>175.103.25.136</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Gallery */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25644">{{EngvarB|date=July 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2016}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= Pakistan Rangers
|image= 
|caption= Pakistan Rangers Punjab Insignia
|start_date=14 August 1947
|country= Pakistan
|type=Paramilitary
|size= 100,000 active troops&lt;ref name=b1&gt;Pakistan Intelligence, security Activities and Operations Handbook, Int'l Business Publications, 2011 Edition, pp. 131, ISBN 0-7397-1194-6&lt;/ref&gt;
|command_structure= [[Paramilitary forces of Pakistan]]
|garrison= [[Islamabad]], [[Karachi]] and [[Lahore]]
|garrison_label=Headquarters
|motto= Daim's Sahir'n &quot;Ever Ready&quot;
|colors=red and blue  &lt;br /&gt;{{colour box|red}}{{colour box|blue}}|colors_label=Colour
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=[[Major-General]] Umar Farooq Burki, 
|commander1_label=[[Director General]], Punjab
|commander2=Major-General Bilal Akbar
|commander2_label=Director General, [[Sindh]]
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=}}
{{externalvideo|video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hgcby5bwwWw Security tight in wake of blast ahead of Muharram (English).]}}
The '''Pakistan Rangers''' ({{lang-ur|{{nq|'''پاکستان رینجرز'''}}}}) is an [[umbrella term]] for the paramilitary Rangers of the [[Sindh]] and [[Punjab, Pakistan|Punjab]] provinces of Pakistan, despite the fact that although these two organisations are federal agencies they operate at the provincial level under two distinct and separate chains of command. Rangers are formally supervised by Special Security Unit, [[National Crises Management Cell]], [[Ministry of Interior (Pakistan)|Ministry of Interior]], [[Government of Pakistan]] but very often they carry activities under the command and leadership of [[Pakistan Army]], though not a part of it.  The Rangers are a border security force with the prime objectives to guard, defend and secure borders in peace time as well as war time, provide and maintain security in war zones and areas of conflict, and maintain law and order which includes providing assistance to the police.

The Pakistan Rangers are two separate forces with the '''Punjab Rangers''' being headquartered in [[Lahore]], [[Punjab, Pakistan|Punjab]], and the '''Sindh Rangers''' headquartered in [[Karachi]], [[Sindh]]. The two forces maintain their different uniforms and chains of command but work under same ordinances, such as the Pakistan Rangers Ordinance 1959.

Each evening, Pakistan Rangers stationed near Lahore, together with their counterparts in the [[Border Security Force|Indian Border Security Force]], participate in a flag lowering ceremony at [[Wagah]].

==History==
{{externalvideo|video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF02Ro7j22I Sindh Rangers in previous uniforms alongside the police (mid 90s).]}}
The origins and roots of Rangers dates back to 1942, when the British government established a special unit as the Sindh Police Rangers. After the independence of Pakistan in 1947, the protection of its eastern boundaries was allotted to particular forces, such as the [[Punjab Border Police Force]], [[Bahawalpur State Police]], [[Khairpur State Police]] and [[Sindh Rifles]]. Because the Rangers were neither correctly structured nor outfitted for a specific duty, in 1958, they were restructured and renamed as the West Pakistan Rangers. In 1972 following the [[Legal Framework Order No. 1970]], the force was renamed from the West Pakistan Rangers to Pakistan Rangers and given under the control of Federal Government (Ministry of Defence). In 1974, it became part of the Civil Armed Force under the Ministry of Interior.

In late 1989, due to growing riots and worsening Law and Order situation in Sindh, a new force was raised for a strategic [[anti-dacoit]] operation in the interior of Sindh. The force operated under the name of [[Mehran Force]] and included the then existing Sindh Rangers, 3 Battalions of Pakistan Army (inc. SSG), Northern Scouts. It was this force constitution that eventually became the modern day Sindh Rangers. Mehran force was under the direct command of Director General Pakistan Rangers with its nucleus Headquarters in Karachi. Laterly Federal Government decided to substantially increase the strength of Rangers and the raising of separate Headquarters for Pakistan Rangers in Sindh. Consequently, 1 July 1995 Pakistan Rangers was bifurcated into two separate branches [[Pakistan Rangers (Punjab)]] and [[Pakistan Rangers (Sindh)]] Mehran Force and other Corps of Pakistan Rangers operated in the province of Sindh formed part of Pakistan Rangers (Sindh). Both branches area of responsibility is divided by provinces, [[Pakistan Rangers (Punjab)]] is primarily responsible for guarding 1300&amp;nbsp;km Eastern Border of Province of Punjab., [[Pakistan Rangers (Sindh)]] Defend Eastern Border with India in Sindh province, approximately 912 kilometres. The Force is governed by Rangers Ordinance 1959

==War performances==
The Rangers had fought together with the Pakistan Army in several conflicts, namely the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1965|1965 Indo-Pak war]] and [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1971|1971 Indo-Pakistan War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =Pakistan Army
  | first = 
  | authorlink = 
  | author2 = 
  | title =Pakistan Army Rangers (Punjab)
  | work =Pakistan Army Press Publications
  | publisher =ISPR
  | date = 
  | url =http://www.pakistanarmy.gov.pk/AWPReview/TextContent.aspx?pId=139
  | doi = 
  | accessdate = }}
&lt;/ref&gt; After the 1971 war, the force was federalised underneath the [[Ministry of Defense (Pakistan)|Ministry of Defence]] as the Pakistan Rangers, and, shortly in 1974, it was made a component of the [[Federal Security Force|Civil Armed Forces]] (CAF) under the [[Ministry of Interior]]. Pakistan Rangers guard the borders during peace and war. In 1995, the [[Mehran Force]] was merged into the Pakistan Rangers (Sindh). The Pakistan Rangers (Sindh) are credited for providing the Pakistan Army troops for Special Police Units in [[Kosovo]] and Haiti Peace mission every year.

These troops are entrusted with the task to provide protection and security to UN officials, provide operational and backup support, respond to threats to public order in co-ordination with the Kosovo administration, and assist humanitarian agencies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =Pakistan Rangers (Sindh)
  | first = 
  | authorlink = 
  | author2 = 
  | title =United Nations Peace Mission
  | work =[[Pakistan Army]]
  | publisher =[[Inter Services Public Relations]] (ISPR)
  | date = 
  | url =http://www.pakistanarmy.gov.pk/AWPReview/TextContent.aspx?pId=141
  | doi = 
  | accessdate = }}
&lt;/ref&gt; The Rangers also had participated in numerous special military operations along with [[Pakistan Army Special Forces]] branch in the past. Since their revitalisation and re-building after the 1971 war, the Rangers have been involved in the numerous special military operations in Pakistan. The Rangers have also assisted the [[Pakistan Army|Army]]'s [[Special Service Group]] in performing special operations. They first participated in 1973, when they, based on the intelligence reports, had successfully accompanied the SSGs to [[Arms discovery in Iraqi Embassy (Pakistan)|raid the Iraqi Embassy]]. In 1992, the Rangers were deployed to [[Karachi]], and the [[Government of Sindh]] had used Rangers to keep peace in the city. The Rangers had also participated in [[Operation Clean-up|Operation Blue Fox]] in 1992 along with the Army. Due to their close association with the Army, the Rangers also fought in [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1999]] (Best known as [[Kargil War]]) deployed in [[Jammu and Kashmir]]. Despite the fact of it being a paramilitary force, the [[Government of Pakistan]] had recognised the Rangers as its one its special forces in 2004. The Rangers were among one of the special forces that participated in [[Operation Silence]] and accompanied Army Commandos in the operation. During the operation, the Rangers suffered a single casualty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last =Lal Masjid
  | first = 
  | author2 = 
  | title =102 killed in Lal Masjid operation, Sherpao
  | newspaper =Geo Tv
  | location =
  | pages = 
  | publisher = 
  | date = 
  | url =http://www.geo.tv/important_events/lalmasjid/pages/english_news.asp
  | accessdate = }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2009, Rangers completed a special military operation in Lahore alongside the [[Special Service Group]], when terrorists attacked the [[Manawan Police Training School|Manawan Police Academy]]. While it was led by the Pakistan Rangers, the operation, codenamed [[2009 Lahore police academy attacks|Lahore Police Academy Operation]], ended with eight militant deaths with one captured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7971345.stm | work=BBC News | title=How Pakistan academy attack started | date=30 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, the [[Government of Pakistan]] deployed the Rangers to secure the outskirts of [[Islamabad]] when [[Taliban]] forces had taken over the [[Buner]], [[Lower Dir]], [[Swat, Pakistan|Swat]] and [[Shangla]] districts. Its members also participated in [[Operation Black Thunderstorm]] while securing the capital.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Bill Roggio|url=http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2009/04/rangers_deployed_to.php |title=Rangers deployed to secure Islamabad outskirts |publisher=The Long War Journal |date=24 April 2009 |accessdate=9 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Leadership==
Pakistan Rangers is a paramilitary Border Security Force which comes under control of Federal Interior Ministry for Internal Security duties and work under umbrella of Corps V in Sindh and IV Corps in Punjab for duties in war zones and borders. Pakistan Rangers are divided into two separate branches: Pakistan Rangers (Sindh) and Pakistan Rangers (Punjab). Each branch is headed by a [[Director General]] appointed by the Pakistan Army after the clearance from the Chief of Army Staff. The Director General of the Pakistan Rangers currently holds the 2-star rank of [[Major-General]]. The current Director General of Pakistan Rangers (Sindh) is [[Major General]] [[Bilal Akbar]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pakistanrangerssindh.org|title=Pakistan Rangers (Sindh) : Official Web Portal|publisher=|accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas Director General of Pakistan Rangers (Punjab) is [[Major General]] [[Farooq Berki]], (&lt;ref&gt;Dawn news 19 March 2015&lt;/ref&gt;).

The equivalent paramilitary force in [[Balochistan (Pakistan)|Balochistan]] and [[Khyber Pakhtunkhwa]] is called the [[Frontier Corps]] (FC), each province with its own FC unit.

==Role==
[[File:Armed_guard_at_allama_iqbals_tomb.jpeg|thumb|Punjab Ranger guarding the [[Tomb of Muhammad Iqbal]] in [[Iqbal Park]], [[Lahore]], [[Punjab, Pakistan|Punjab]], Pakistan.]]

One prime objective of the Rangers is to safeguard the eastern borders of Pakistan with India which with the Sindh province, shares approximately 912 kilometres and in the Punjab Province approximately shares 1200 kilometres. The Rangers are also responsible for maintaining internal security in Pakistan and a major [[law enforcement in Pakistan|law enforcement organisation in the country]]. Despite this, they are not privileged with the power to arrest like the police except in desperate but rare time eras, when the state temporarily sanctions them with such a power. Their primary objective as an internal security force is to prevent crime by taking preventive security measures, disable organised criminals and thwart organised crime. All suspects apprehended by Rangers are later handed over to police for further investigation and possible prosecution except for the rare instances when Rangers are legally empowered by the state to arrest and detain suspects. The same privileges are also temporarily granted by the government to other security organisations such as the Frontier Corps for the same reasons.

The Rangers are also tasked with securing important monuments and guarding national assets in all major cities of Pakistan, including [[Islamabad]].

In the past, they have also served as prison guards for high profile terrorists until they were withdrawn from such duties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Punjab withdraws Rangers from guard duties|url=http://www.dawn.com/news/1226883|work=Mohammed Asghar|publisher=[[Dawn News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Rangers have notably contributed towards maintaining law and order in Islamabad, Karachi, and Lahore in major crises. The Sindh Rangers consist of approximately 25,000 persons whereas almost half of the total force is deployed to Karachi. Due to the unstable situation in Pakistan, the Rangers have become extremely necessary to maintain law and order in all major cities.

==Organization==
{{expand section|date=July 2015}}{{see also|Law enforcement in Pakistan}}
Like the police of Pakistan, the Rangers collectively function as provincial organisations independent of one another: The '''Sindh Rangers''' of the province of [[Sindh]] and the '''Punjab Rangers''' belonging to the province of [[Punjab, Pakistan|Punjab]].

Sindh Rangers requested [[Supreme Court of Pakistan]] to allow paramilitary force to establish its own Police stations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sindh Rangers want to set up its own ‘police stations’ in Karachi|url=http://tribune.com.pk/story/1061330/sindh-rangers-want-own-police-stations-in-karachi/|accessdate=13 July 2016|agency=[[The Express Tribune]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rangers Anti-Terrorist (RAT) Wing==
The Rangers Anti-Terrorist wing has been active since early 2004. It is same like army SSG .They are trained by Zarrar Company of [[Special Services Group]] (SSG) of the Pakistani Army. This company also participated in a recent exercise with [[Special Air Service|UK Special Air Service]] operators and [[United States Army Rangers|US Army Rangers]].

==Training and selection==
The selection for rangers lasts 2–3 weeks. Both male and females can join the Rangers and an applicant must be between 18–25 years old for '''Punjab Rangers''' and 18 to 30 years old for '''Sindh Rangers'''. To apply for the Rangers, the applicant must passed F.A or F.Sc. (an equivalent to US matriculation system) from a government-registered college. An applicant must hold Pakistani citizenship to join the Force. The Rangers can be deployed at any place either in Pakistan or abroad, according to the Rangers Act of 1959.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pak.jobs-career-employment.com/articles/378/1/Headquarter-Pakistan-Rangers-Sindh-Jobs-Karachi/Page1.html|title=Pakistan Jobs – Pakistan New Job Vacancies.|publisher=|accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In spite of its role as paramilitary, the Rangers have been recognised by [[Government of Pakistan]] as one of its special forces.

==Appointments==
{{externalvideo|video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_OJr2DbmQY0 A Sindh Rangers shooting range.]}}
Although the Pakistan Rangers are under the administration of the Interior ministry, key positions in the force, including [[Director-General]] of the Rangers, are headed by the members [[Pakistan Army]]. The Director General of the Pakistan Rangers is appointed by Pakistan Army's Generals Headquarters (GHQ). The majority of the officers are departmental officers who get promotion from the rank of Sub Inspector.

The rank structure of OR's, NCO's, JCO'S of the force is:-

Sepoy equal to Sepoy

Lance Naik equal to Lance Naik

Naik equal to Naik

Havaldar equal to Havaldar

Inspectors who get promoted from OR's Ranks are equal to Army JCO's:-

Ranker Sub Inspector, Inspector and Senior Ranger Inspector(SRI) Ranks are Equal to Naib Subedar, Subedar, Subedar Major.Direct entry Sub inspectors/ranker sub inspectors can maximum reach to the rank of SSR(Senior superintendent of Rangers EQUAL To lieutenant colonel).

===Flag lowering ceremony===
[[File:Soldiers at Wagah border.jpg|thumb|290px|Punjab Rangers at the Wagah border]]

[[Wagah]], the only road border crossing between Pakistan and India, is the site of a flag lowering ceremony each evening. During the ceremony, Pakistani Rangers and their counterparts in the [[Border Security Force|Indian Border Security Force]] carry out a drill in which they mirror each other's drill with high kicking steps, foot stamping and aggressive stares. Despite the outward display of aggression, the drill of both sides actually requires a high degree of co-operation.

The ceremony is attended by numerous spectators from both nations, as well as foreign tourists.

==Standard equipment==
* Automatic Rifles – 7.62&amp;nbsp;mm [[Heckler &amp; Koch G3|G3A3]], 7.62&amp;nbsp;mm [[Heckler &amp; Koch G3|G3P4]] Steyr AUGs and [[AK-47s]]
* Machine Guns – 7.62&amp;nbsp;mm [[Rheinmetall MG3|MG3]]
* Sub-Machine Guns – 9&amp;nbsp;mm [[Heckler &amp; Koch MP5|MP5A2]] &amp; [[Heckler &amp; Koch MP5|MP5P4]], 9&amp;nbsp;mm [[Pakistani Arms Industry#Small Arms|SMG-PK]].
* Pistols – Glock series, Sigma series [[TT pistol]]
*Dragunov sniper rifle,PSG 1 (POF made)
*RPG-7,Carl Gustav recoilless rifle,RPG-29
*heavy machine gun – 12.7mm DShk
* Bullet Proof Jackets – Various local and foreign types
*Helmets – Modular Integrated Communications Helmet and indigenous helmets produced by AWC, Pakistan.
*Bell 407 Jet ranger
*APC – Talha, Saad, mohafiz
*NVG goggles
*Unknown Mortars

The formal headwear of the Rangers are somewhat similar to the ones worn by the Frontier Corps.

==Notable officers==

* [[Sub-Inspector]] Amarjeet Singh- The first [[Sikh]] Pakistani Officer of the Pakistan Rangers (Punjab).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/First+Sikh+youth+completes+training+as+Pakistan+Rangers+officer.-a0210194084 |title=First Sikh youth completes training as Pakistan Rangers officer. – Free Online Library |publisher=Thefreelibrary.com |date=21 October 2009 |accessdate=9 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Senior Superintendent of Rangers|SSR]] Malik Mukhtar- is the first officer of Pakistan Rangers who reach to rank of Senior Superintendent of Rangers which is equal to Army Lieutenant Colonel rank and he is doing duty as Wing Commander apart from this he is also known by his bravery specially in Karachi operation 1992

BG Shaukat Ali Raja was in command in a post where a LG usually is in charge. As a result, MG would have to salute his motorcade. The only BG to ever be in command to date of the Punjab Rangers located in Lahore.

==Role of peace maintenance in Karachi==
[[Image:Pakistan ranger soldier.jpg|thumb|right|225px|A Sindh Rangers commando on duty at the seashore in Karachi.]]
{{See also|Target killings in Pakistan}} 
While kidnapping for ransom, extortion, threats to the business community were common in Karachi and industrialists were shifting their
investment in Bangladesh and other countries, Chief of Army Staff, Gen Ashfaq Pervaiz Kiyani took the notice of dire situation and on request of government and business community, the Rangers were deployed with special powers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dunyanews.tv/index.php/en/Pakistan/200219--Rangers-get-special-powers-in-Karachi|title=Dunya News: Pakistan:- Rangers get special powers in Karachi ...|publisher=|accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Rangers played a crucial role in maintaining peace and curbed law offenders without any discrimination and consideration of political affiliation. Business community in particular and masses in general took sight of relief and lauded the role of rangers in Sindh. Director General Rangers Sindh Lt.General Ejaz Chaudry visited Karachi Chamber of Commerce and Industry on 17 November 2011, on this occasion business community unanimously acclaimed the rangers role in maintaining peace in the city and demanded extension in its stay with special orders for another one year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nation.com.pk/national/11-Nov-2014/nisar-lauds-sindh-rangers-role-in-karachi-operation|title=Nisar lauds Sindh Rangers' role in Karachi operation|work=The Nation|accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

US General [[Vincent R. Stewart]] praised the [[War in Northwestern Pakistan|anti-insurgency operations in the western areas of Pakistan]] by the Pakistan military. He also praised the Karachi operations by the Rangers, arguing they all helped reduce violence in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tribune.com.pk/story/1044791/military-operations-helped-reduce-violence-in-pakistan-us-defence-intel-chief/|title=Pakistan Military operations helped reduce violence in Pakistan: US defence intel chief|publisher=The Express Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Foreign peacekeeping missions for the United Nations==
{{main article|United Nations peacekeeping missions involving Pakistan}}
The Pakistan Rangers have also been involved in international peacekeeping operations for the United Nations (UN) in a number of countries such as [[Kosovo]], [[Haiti]] and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pakistanrangerspunjab.com/un.html|title=Welcome to Pakistan Rangers (Punjab)|publisher=|accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thenews.com.pk/TodaysPrintDetail.aspx?ID=98870&amp;Cat=4&amp;dt=3/19/2008|title=Pakistan Rangers on UN peacekeeping mission|date=29 February 2008|work=The News International, Pakistan|accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable operations, incidents and controversies==
{{externalvideo|video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y7sr3d-MUmQ Sindh Rangers engaged in an anti-criminal operation that turned deadly.]}}
*In 1973 the Punjab Rangers and [[Islamabad Police]] [[Arms discovery in Iraqi Embassy (Pakistan)|raided the Iraqi embassy in Islamabad]] after a discovery of illegal arms stored there.
*More recently in 2011 the Punjab Rangers participated in the ''Lal Masjid Operation'' or [[Operation Silence]].
*Also in 2011 the Sindh Rangers were involved in a [[2011 Sindh Rangers shooting incident|controversial shooting of an unarmed civilian]] which was caught on camera, broadcast by news networks throughout the country and sparked public outcry. All Rangers involved were prosecuted and the one who directly fired the shots was sentenced to death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/pakistan/8568657/Pakistani-soldiers-arrested-after-TV-footage-shows-them-shooting-unarmed-man.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Dean | last=Nelson | title=Pakistani soldiers arrested after TV footage shows them shooting unarmed man | date=10 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dawn.com/news/651246/one-rangers-personnel-sentenced-to-death-for-sarfraz-killing|title=One Rangers personnel sentenced to death for Sarfaraz killing|author=AFP|publisher=|accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2015 the Sindh Rangers in a controversial move raided the office of the [[Muttahida Qaumi Movement]] (previously ''Muhajir Qaumi Movement'') in Karachi and detained members of the MQM party. Also caught in the raids were illegal guns and ammunition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dawn.com/news/1168840|title=Rangers raid MQM HQ in Karachi, detain member of Rabita Committee|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tribune.com.pk/story/851291/rangers-conduct-siege-and-search-operation-at-mqm-headquarters-in-karachi/|title=One dead, several injured as Rangers raid MQM headquarters|date=11 March 2015|work=The Express Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In January 2016, two employees of [[Pakistan International Airlines]] were feared dead during a public protest which blocked a road near [[Karachi airport]] and which Rangers were assigned to clear from protesters which is suspected in resulting these two deaths.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/feb/02/pakistan-international-airlines-workers-killed-protest-karachi-flights-suspended&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mass communication==
Pakistan Rangers Sindh is starting its own radio show in Karachi known as &quot;Rangers Hour&quot; on [[FM 101 (Pakistan)|FM 101]] intended to communicate with the people of the metropolis; earlier to this such radio service was also established by [[Sindh Police]] on [[FM88.6]] . Before this Sindh Rangers also established a 24hours helpline 1101 for the people to report any crime information in the metropolis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The new voice on Radio: Rangers|url=http://staging.tribune.com.pk/story/965698/the-new-voice-on-radio-rangers/|accessdate=13 July 2016|agency=[[The Express Tribune]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Allama_Iqbals_Tomb_East_wall_close-up_July_1_2005.jpg|Pakistan Rangers guarding the [[Tomb of Muhammad Iqbal]] in [[Iqbal Park]], [[Lahore]], [[Punjab, Pakistan|Punjab]], Pakistan. 
File:Baba Chamliyal Mela at Indo-Pak international Border, near Jammu.jpg|Baba Chamliyal Mela at Indo-Pak international Border, near Jammu
File:Punjab Rangers.jpg|Punjab Rangers marching.
File:Wagah Border Crossing Guards.JPG|Border personnel from both countries, during the Wagah Border ceremony.

&lt;/gallery&gt;
{{clear}}

==See also==
*[[Frontier Corps]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://pakistanrangerssindh.org/ Official Web Portal of Pakistan Rangers (Sindh)]
*[http://www.pakistanrangerspunjab.com/ Pakistan Rangers (Punjab)]
*[http://www.defence.pk/ Pakistan Defence]

{{Pakistan Special Forces}}
{{Law enforcement in Pakistan}}
{{Military of Pakistan}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rangers, Pakistan}}
[[Category:Paramilitary forces of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Military provosts]]
[[Category:Special forces of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Pakistan Army]]
[[Category:Federal law enforcement agencies of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Government of Zulfikar Ali Bhutto]]
[[Category:Pakistan federal departments and agencies]]
[[Category:Paramilitary organizations]]
[[Category:Military in Sindh]]
[[Category:1947 establishments in Pakistan]]
[[Category:Government agencies established in 1947]]</text>
      <sha1>eu2da8wjtqii3vv6fhg21ybpl1ix7kw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
