<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Patriot's Park</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30269839</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749235285</id>
      <parentid>746688896</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T06:00:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot</username>
        <id>27446209</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Migrate {{Infobox park}} coordinates parameters to coords={{Coord}}, see [[Help:Coordinates in infoboxes]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17980">{{Infobox park
| name = Patriot's Park
| photo = Patriot's Park, Tarrytown-Sleepy Hollow, NY.jpg
| photo_width = 300
| photo_caption = Decorative features of park, including Captors' Monument at right, 2012
| photo_alt = A grassy landscape with trees in the background. In front of them is a small creek with two stone bridges. A tall monument is at right
| map = New York
| map_width = 300
| map_caption = Location within New York
| map_alt = A map of New York showing county boundaries and water bodies. There is a red dot on the right side of the Hudson River a short distance above New York City
| type = Public
| location = [[Sleepy Hollow, New York|Sleepy Hollow]] and [[Tarrytown, New York|Tarrytown]], [[New York (state)|NY]], USA
| nearest_city = [[White Plains, New York|White Plains]]
| coords = {{coord|41|4|54|N|73|51|31|W|region:US-NY|format=dms|display=inline,title}}
| coords_ref = 
| area = {{convert|4|acre}}
| created = 1853&lt;ref name=&quot;nrhpinv_ny&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oprhp.state.ny.us/hpimaging/hp_view.asp?GroupView=10741|title=National Register of Historic Places Registration:Patriot's Park|date=April 1982|accessdate=2010-12-30 |author=Austin N. O'Brien|publisher=[[New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation]]}} ''See also:'' {{cite web|url=http://www.oprhp.state.ny.us/hpimaging/hp_view.asp?GroupView=10731|title=Accompanying seven photos}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| operator = Villages of Sleepy Hollow and Tarrytown
| visitation_num = 
| status = 
| open = 
| embedded = {{Infobox NRHP
  | name = Patriot's Park
  | architect = Carrere &amp; Hastings
  | added = June 14, 1982
  | refnum = 82003415&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|version=2009a}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
}}

'''Patriot's Park''' (originally referred to as '''Brookside Park''') is located on [[U.S. Route 9 in New York|U.S. Route 9]] along the boundary between [[Tarrytown, New York|Tarrytown]] and [[Sleepy Hollow, New York|Sleepy Hollow]] in [[Westchester County]], [[New York (state)|New York]], United States. It is a four-acre (1.6-ha) parcel with a walkway and several monuments. In 1982 it was added to the [[National Register of Historic Places]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;/&gt;

==Overview==
During the [[American Revolutionary war|Revolutionary War]] Major [[John André]] of the British Army was captured, disguised in civilian clothing, at the site by three [[Patriot (American Revolution)|Patriot]] militiamen. They found papers on him that implicated him in espionage with [[Benedict Arnold]], a high-ranking officer of the [[Continental Army]]. After a military trial André was executed; Arnold [[defection|defected]] to the British and lived his remaining years after the war in England.

A memorial was erected on the site in 1853, on land donated by some members of the local [[African American]] community.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt; It was one of the earliest monuments to honor any event of the Revolutionary War. Later it was expanded and incorporated into Brookside Park, a late 19th-century [[Beaux-Arts architecture|Beaux-Arts]] residential development by the firm of [[Carrère and Hastings]] . Later it became the campus of two different girls' boarding schools, one of which was attended by [[Lauren Bacall]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lauren Bacall&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Bacall|first=Lauren|title=By Myself and Then Some|year=2005|publisher=[[HarperCollins]]|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-06-075535-5|pages=8–9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TGlAkk-oMeIC&amp;pg=PA8|authorlink=Lauren Bacall|accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It became a park and took its current name in the middle of the 20th century, and all buildings but the [[gatehouse]] were demolished.

==Grounds==
The park is a four-acre (1.6 ha) parcel located between North Broadway (Route 9) on its east, North Washington Street to the west and College Avenue on the north. The southwest corner has some houses continuing down to Wildey Street; Tarrytown's public library is to the southeast. Across North Washington are more houses, which continue to the College intersection at the northwest. Church of the Immaculate Conception is across from the park at College and North Broadway. To the east is the large open lawn of John Paulding School, the public [[elementary education|elementary]] school of the Union Free School District of the Tarrytowns, which has its headquarters north of the school in the former [[Edward Harden Mansion]], also listed on the National Register. Behind them runs the [[Old Croton Aqueduct]], a [[National Historic Landmark]]. The commercial areas of downtown Sleepy Hollow are two blocks to the north along North Broadway.

Topographically the park consists of two slight rises, more pronounced toward the west, reflecting the land's general descent toward the nearby [[Hudson River]]. They are divided by the narrow channel followed by Andre Brook, which also forms the boundary between the two villages, Tarrytown to the south and Sleepy Hollow to the north. The land is mostly open, with tall mature trees providing shade opportunities, more in the north of the park than the south.

The park's organizing feature is an oval walkway with entrances at the north, east and west, and short paths to a basketball court at the south and North Broadway to the southeast. The main entrance is at the west. It is flanked by two gateposts of [[Rustication (architecture)|rusticated]] granite blocks. Stone walls in random [[ashlar]] with granite [[coping (architecture)|copings]] begin at the posts and follow the sidewalks to create [[terrace (building)|terraces]], broken by granite steps to the walkway, on either side of the entrance. They end in granite consoles.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

In the north terraces is a stone [[gatehouse]], one [[bay (architecture)|bay]] on each side with walls laid in a random [[ashlar]] pattern and topped by a [[cornice]] line. Atop is a [[hip roof|hipped roof]] shingled in asphalt, with exposed [[rafter]] ends. Its entrance is on the west [[facade]]; the only window is on the north.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

South of the west entrance is the Captors' Monument, enclosed by a square iron fence. It consists of two [[pedestal]]s topped by a bronze statue of [[John Paulding]], one of the local men who apprehended André. The older lower pedestal is a square block of white [[Sing Sing]] [[marble]] with a recessed panel on the west side. Inside the panel is a bronze [[commemorative plaque]] with a [[bas-relief]] depicting André's capture. It supports the upper pedestal, a narrowing concrete block, and the statue of Paulding atop that. South of the Captors' Monument is a more modern statue of [[Christopher Columbus]].&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;
[[File:Patriots Park Tarrytown NY water basin and stone bridge.jpg|thumb|left|Uppermost of the three stone bridges in the park|alt=A decorative stone bridge, with curving stairs down to the water below on either side, in a park]]
Opposite the entrance curving stone steps, along with a sloped walkway from the south, lead down from battered stone piers at either end of a [[retaining wall]] to a basin where Andre Brook flows out from a [[culvert]] that has carried it under North Broadway and the schools to the east. It emerges from an arch with alternating scaled [[voussoir]]s and a scaled [[keystone (architecture)|keystone]] in the monochrome ashlar retaining wall on the west side of the walkway. Above it is a balcony supported by two consoles.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

The brook flows over a dam and west down a concrete-lined channel, paralleled by a stone path on the south bank. Midway along it is a small stone foot bridge, with battered stone piers and an arch, with the same voussoirs as the retaining wall arch but a shouldered keystone. From there it flows over another waterfall and under the drive bridge, similar to the foot bridge but heavier, then into another culvert under North Washington Avenue.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

There are two playgrounds within the park. A smaller, older one is in the northwest corner, and a newer and larger one in the southwest, near the library. Decorative lamps line the drive, and benches are located around the park.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

==History==
The park derives its primary importance from the capture of Major André during the war. The monument was erected in the mid-19th century. After being developed for residential use in the late 19th century, it became home to two girls' schools and finally, today's park, undergoing several renovations in the process.

===1780: Capture of Major André===
In 1780, five years from the start of the [[American Revolutionary War|Revolutionary War]], the settlements that would later become the Tarrytowns were in the middle of [[Neutral Ground (New York)|Neutral Ground]], the {{convert|30|mi|adj=on}}–wide no man's land between British forces occupying New York City (at the time, what is today [[Lower Manhattan]]) and the [[Continental Army]] north of the [[Croton River]]. Gangs of armed bandits roamed the lightly populated area, raiding farms in a search for livestock and other goods they could sell to the warring armies. Those with [[Loyalist (American Revolution)|Loyalist]] sympathies were called Cow-boys; their counterparts who sold to the [[Patriot (American Revolution)|Patriots]] were known as Skinners.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

On the morning of September 24 that year, three young men—[[John Paulding]], [[Isaac Van Wart]] and [[David Williams (soldier)|David Williams]]—set themselves up along the road through Tarrytown, approximately {{convert|200|yd}} east of where the Captors' Monument is now. They were part of a group of eight Skinners, hoping to ambush a party of Cow-boys. A rider approached them, and they raised their guns to stop him. It was Major [[John André]] of the British Army, returning from a clandestine visit to [[West Point, New York|West Point]], where he had been negotiating the terms of a surrender with General [[Benedict Arnold]] of the Continental Army.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;
[[File:Capture of John andre.jpg|thumb|right|1845 lithograph of André's capture|alt=A black-and-white illustration of a man in white, with one boot off, on a stone bridge, surrounded by three darker men with hats, coats and long guns]]
Paulding, who had recently escaped from British custody, wore a [[Hessian (soldiers)|Hessian]] coat he had taken in the process, which led André to assume, in the ensuing conversation, that the three were Cow-boys who could thus aid him in continuing on to New York. When informed of his mistake, he produced a pass signed by Arnold. The three searched him and found papers in his boots, not only his correspondence with Arnold but diagrams of the defenses at West Point. Paulding, the only literate member of the trio, read them and realized quickly that André was a spy. Williams asked André what money he could pay them, but Paulding quickly ended any talk of a payoff, swearing that not even 10,000 [[Guinea (British coin)|guineas]] would be enough.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

After André was turned over to the Continental command at [[North Castle, New York|North Castle]], he was taken across the Hudson to [[Tappan, New York|Tappan]] where he was held prisoner. After being convicted of espionage at a military trial in the [[DeWint House]] (today a [[National Historic Landmark]]), he was hanged by order of [[George Washington]], who had attended the trial. Had André successfully conveyed the information Arnold had given him to New York, the British could have managed to secure the Hudson and cut [[New England]] off from the other rebellious colonies, resolving the stalemate of the time in their favor and drastically changing the outcome of the war.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

Arnold, tipped off about André's arrest by a member of his staff unaware of his commander's involvement, was able to escape to the British with his family. After holding some commands in the British Army, he emigrated to England at war's end, where he was buried two decades later. Paulding, Van Wart and Williams were recognized and compensated for their roles in the capture. The [[Continental Congress]] awarded them lifetime pensions and the [[Fidelity Medallion]], generally considered the first U.S. military decoration; the state gave them farms confiscated from Loyalists.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt; Two decades later, three [[List of counties in Ohio|counties in the new state of Ohio]] were named after them. Later the elementary school near the memorial would take Paulding's name as well.

===1853–1942: homes and schools===
David Williams, the sole survivor of the trio that captured Major John Andre, died in 1831. After his death, a movement began to build a monument at the capture site. It never gained enough support, but never completely disappeared either. In 1852 the Monument Association to the Captors of Major André was formally established at last, and it was able to bring those plans to fruition. A local freed [[African American]] couple, William and Mary Taylor, donated the property they owned at the intersection of the brook and the highway. The [[cornerstone]] was laid on [[Independence Day (United States)|Independence Day]], July 4, 1853. Among those at the ceremony were [[Alexander Hamilton]]'s son [[James A. Hamilton|James]], and [[Horatio Seymour]] and [[Henry J. Raymond]], governor and lieutenant governor of New York, respectively. The lower pedestal was raised shortly thereafter, of marble quarried in nearby Sing Sing, today [[Ossining (village), New York|Ossining]]. It was topped with an [[obelisk]].&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;
[[File:PatriotsParkMemorial-TarrytownNY-01.jpg|thumb|left|Captors' Monument, 2010|alt=A tall stone pedestal with a metallic figure atop it, with two large trees above it. The base is surrounded by an iron fence. In the front right is a blue marker with yellow type headed &quot;André Captured&quot;, over smaller type describing that event.]]
On the centennial of the capture in 1880, the monument was expanded and rededicated. A crowd of 70,000 attended the ceremony, presided over by [[Samuel J. Tilden]] (one of his last public appearances) and [[Chauncey Depew]]. The obelisk was replaced with the current concrete block and topped with a statue of Paulding by [[William Rudolf O'Donovan|William R. O'Donovan]], donated by a Tarrytown resident.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

At that time there were three houses across North Broadway, dating to at least 1865. They were demolished to clear the way for an 1892 plan to incorporate the monument into Brookside Park, a new residential development. [[Carrère and Hastings]] designed eight wood and stone [[Beaux-Arts architecture|Beaux-Arts]] cottages and a stone gatehouse, meant to blend in with the site, and laid out the park's extant landscaping, its symmetry and grandiose treatment of the basin characteristic of their chosen style. By the end of the year all were completed, at a cost of $10,000 (${{formatnum:{{inflation|US|10000|1892|r=-3}}}} in modern dollars{{Inflation-fn|US}}) apiece. Developer Eugene Jones intended to lease the units individually rather than sell them.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

In 1896 he sold them to Amos Clark, who continued to lease out the cottages until renting the property to the recently established Knox School for Girls in 1911. It named the buildings, which housed its 42 students, after roses. By the end of the decade Knox had outgrown Brookside, and moved to a new campus in [[Cooperstown, New York|Cooperstown]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Knox history page&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=-Knox School: History and Traditions|url=http://www.knoxschool.org/page.cfm?p=10|publisher=Knox School|year=2009|accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another girls' school, Highland Manor, moved in in 1920.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

Among the students to attend Highland Manor was [[Lauren Bacall]], later a successful actress.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lauren Bacall&quot; /&gt; In 1942, as its predecessor had, the school moved to a larger campus elsewhere. Two local women bought the park, had all but one of the neglected cottages demolished, and then donated the property to the two villages. At that time it was renamed to Patriot's Park.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

===1943–present: park===
After [[World War II]] ended, three local garden clubs formed a committee to guide the restoration of the park. Following a plan by a still-unidentified architect, the [[foundation (architecture)|foundations]] of the demolished houses were filled in and planted in 1949. Over the next six years further improvements were made. New paved paths were created, dead trees replaced with younger [[dogwood]]s and the brook channel lined with concrete. All the masonry was reset and repointed.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

The remaining house from Brookside Park was used as a gymnasium and storage area until it was demolished around 1970. The gatehouse is the only building left from that development. As of 1982 the villages of Tarrytown and North Tarrytown (as Sleepy Hollow was known until changing its name in the early 1990s) both allocated a thousand dollars a year to the park's maintenance.&lt;ref name=nrhpinv_ny /&gt;

==See also==
*[[National Register of Historic Places listings in northern Westchester County, New York]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{commons category-inline}}

{{National Register of Historic Places in New York}}
{{New York in the American Revolutionary War}}

[[Category:Parks in Westchester County, New York]]
[[Category:American Revolutionary War sites]]
[[Category:Parks on the National Register of Historic Places in New York]]
[[Category:Beaux-Arts architecture in New York]]
[[Category:New York in the American Revolution]]
[[Category:U.S. Route 9]]
[[Category:1853 establishments in New York]]
[[Category:Sleepy Hollow, New York]]
[[Category:Tarrytown, New York]]
[[Category:National Register of Historic Places in Westchester County, New York]]
[[Category:American Revolution on the National Register of Historic Places]]</text>
      <sha1>thhz1yhdulom5on9jnpv6zktyeb0zft</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
