<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Powder River Expedition (1865)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1552075</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740789133</id>
      <parentid>738243098</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-23T08:55:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>158.169.150.8</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30964">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Powder River Expedition
| partof      =the [[Sioux Wars]], [[American Indian Wars]]
|image        = The Powder River in Johnson County, Wyoming.jpg
|caption      = Powder River in present-day Johnson County, Wyoming north of Fort Connor
| date        = July 1 to October 4, 1865
| place       = [[Powder River Country]], [[Montana]], [[Wyoming]], [[South Dakota]], and [[Nebraska]], [[United States]]
| territory   = 
| result      = inconclusive 
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|United States|1863}} [[United States]]
| combatant2  = [[Sioux]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cheyenne people|Cheyenne]]&lt;br&gt;[[Arapaho people|Arapaho]]
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United States|1863}} [[Patrick Edward Connor|Patrick E. Connor]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1863}} [[Nelson D. Cole]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1863}} [[Samuel Walker (soldier)|Samuel Walker]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1863}} [[Frank North]]
| commander2  = [[Red Cloud]]&lt;br&gt;[[Sitting Bull]]&lt;br&gt;[[Roman Nose]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dull Knife]]&lt;br&gt;[[George Bent]]
| strength1 = 2,300 soldiers, 179 [[United States Army Indian Scouts|Indian scouts]], 195 civilians
| strength2 = ~2,000 warriors 
| casualties1 = 31 killed, 15 wounded
| casualties2 = ~100 killed, 10 wounded, 21 captured including women and children}}
{{Campaignbox Powder River Expedition}}
{{Campaignbox Sioux Wars}}
:''This event should not be confused with the [[Big Horn Expedition]] during the [[Black Hills War]].''
The '''Powder River Expedition''' of 1865 also known as the '''[[Powder River (Montana)|Powder River]] War''' or '''Powder River Invasion''', was a large and far-flung military operation of the [[United States Army]] against the [[Sioux]], [[Cheyenne]], and [[Arapaho]] [[American Indians in the United States|Indians]] in [[Montana Territory]] and [[Dakota Territory]].  Although soldiers destroyed one Arapaho village and established [[Fort Reno (Wyoming)|Fort Connor]] to protect travelers on the [[Bozeman Trail]], the expedition is considered a failure because it failed to defeat the Indians and secure peace in the region.

==Background==

The [[Sand Creek massacre]] of Cheyenne in November 1864 intensified Indian reprisals and raids in the [[Platte River]] valley. (See [[Battle of Julesburg]])  After the raids, the Sioux, [[Lakota people|Lakota]], Cheyenne and Arapaho congregated in Powder River country, remote from white settlements and confirmed as Indian territory in the 1851 [[Treaty of Fort Laramie (1851)|Treaty of Fort Laramie]].

The Indians also perceived that the Bozeman Trail, blazed in 1863 and traversing the heart of Powder River country, was a threat.  Although roads through Indian territory were permitted by the Fort Laramie Treaty, the Sioux, mostly [[Lakota people|Lakota]], Cheyenne, and Arapaho harassed miners and other travelers along the trail in 1864 and 1865. In July 1865, 1,000 Indian warriors in the [[Battle of Platte Bridge]] attacked a bridge across the North Platte River near [[Fort Caspar]] and succeeded in temporarily shutting down travel on both the Bozeman and the [[Oregon Trail]]. After the battle the Indians broke up into small groups and dispersed for their summer [[Bison|buffalo]] hunt. A weakness of Indian warfare was that they lacked the resources to keep an army in the field for an extended period of time.&lt;ref&gt;McGinnis, Anthony &quot;Strike &amp; Retreat: Intertribal Warfare and the Powder River War, 1865-1868&quot; ''Montana: The Magazine of Western History'', Vol 30, No. 4 (Autumn 1980), pp. 32-34&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Major General]] [[Grenville M. Dodge]] ordered the [[Powder River (Montana)|Powder River]] expedition as a punitive campaign against the [[Sioux]], [[Cheyenne]] and [[Arapaho]].  It was led by [[Brigadier General]] [[Patrick Edward Connor|Patrick E. Connor]].  [[File:GenPEConnor.jpg|thumb|right|300px||Brigadier General Patrick E. Connor]] Dodge ordered Connor to &quot;make vigorous war upon the Indians and punish them so that they will be forced to keep the peace.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, H.D. &quot;The Powder River Expedition 1865&quot; ''Montana: The Magazine of Western History'',Vol.14, No. 4 (Autumn 1964), p. r&lt;/ref&gt;  The Connor expedition was one of the last Indian war campaigns carried out by [[United States Volunteers|U.S Volunteer soldiers]]. One of Connor's guides was [[Mountain man]] [[Jim Bridger]].

Connor's strategy was for three columns of soldiers to march into the Powder River Country.  The &quot;Right Column&quot; was composed of 1,400 Missouri soldiers, mostly mounted, led by Colonel Nelson Cole. It marched from [[Omaha, Nebraska]] and was to follow the [[Loup River]] in Nebraska westward to the [[Black Hills]] and meet up with Connor near the Powder River.  The &quot;Center Column&quot; of 600 men was commanded by Samuel Walker of the 16th Kansas Cavalry and was to head north from [[Fort Laramie]] and traverse the country west of the Black Hills.&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; [[File:Alfred Jacob Miller - Fort Laramie - Walters 37194049.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Fort Laramie was General Connor's starting point for the expedition.  [[Plains Indians]] often visited and camped near the Fort.]] The &quot;Left Column&quot; of 675 men was composed of the [[6th Michigan Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]] under Colonel James H. Kidd, recently transferred from the Civil War battlefields of Virginia. This command included 95 [[Pawnee Scouts]] and 84 [[Omaha people|Omaha]] [[United States Army Indian Scouts|scouts]] and a wagon train full of supplies with 195 civilian teamsters.&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, p. 8; Countant, Charles Griffin, &quot;History of Wyoming'', Chapter xxxvi, http://www.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~wytttp/history/countant/chapter36.htm, accessed 6 Aug 2012&lt;/ref&gt;  General Connor would personally accompany Kidd's column and would move along the Powder River with the goal of establishing a fort near the Bozeman Trail. All three columns were to unite at the new fort.

Connor's orders to his commanders were, &quot;You will not receive overtures of peace or submission from Indians, but will attack and kill every male Indian over twelve years of age.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://rootswebancestry.com/~wyttp/history/countant/chapter34.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Connor's superiors, Generals [[John Pope (military officer)|John Pope]] and Dodge attempted to countermand this order, but too late as Connor's expedition had already departed and was out of contact.&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, pp. 8-9&lt;/ref&gt;

The expedition was troubled from the start. The number of men to be involved in the campaign was reduced from 12,000 to 2,300 because many soldiers were mustered out of the army at the end of the [[American Civil War]].  The remaining soldiers were &quot;mutinous, dissatisfied, and inefficient.&quot;  Few of the men and officers had any experience fighting Indians or travel on the [[Great Plains]].  Procuring supplies was also a problem.&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, p.6&lt;/ref&gt;

== Connor's expedition ==

Brigadier General [[Patrick E. Connor]], Colonel Kidd and their 675 soldiers, Indian scouts, and teamsters left [[Fort Laramie]], [[Dakota Territory]], on August 2, 1865, to unite with the column's of Colonel's [[Nelson D. Cole]], and [[Samuel Walker (soldier)|Samuel Walker]].  Connor's column proceeded northward, and established [[Fort Reno (Wyoming)|Fort Connor]], on the upper Powder River.

=== The Battle of Crazy Woman's Fork===

On August 13, 1865, Captain [[Frank North|Frank J. North]], of the Pawnee Scouts, was riding with some of his [[Pawnee Scouts]] near the Crazy Woman's Fork of the Powder River. Captain North and his scouts then spotted a small group of Cheyenne warriors, and commenced to chase them. In the pursuit, North became separated from the U.S. Scouts by about a mile. The retreating Warriors then turned to engage North. One of the Natives wounded North's horse, so the Captain got behind his downed animal and used it as a barricade from which position he then fought off his attackers. Bob White, a Pawnee Scout, came upon North, and joined him. Several more Pawnee Scouts arrived, and the small party then shot at, and Wounded a few of the warriors, who then quickly fled. The Battle of Crazy Woman's Fork was the first engagement of the [[Powder River Expedition]].&lt;ref name=&quot;grinnell177&quot;&gt;[[George Bird Grinnell|Grinnell, George Bird]] ''The Fighting Cheyennes'' Norman: U of OK Press, 1915, pp. 177&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Pawnee Scouts William Henry Jackson.jpg|thumb|right|300px||Four of the Pawnee Scouts.]]

=== Powder River Massacre ===

{{Main|Powder River Massacre}}

For two days, Captain Frank North and his Pawnee Scouts had trailed a band of Cheyenne, who were heading north. The trail showed that the Cheyenne had about 40 horses and mules, along with one travoi. At 2:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. on August 16, 1865, the Captain and his Scouts caught up with the group, on Powder River, about 50 miles north of Fort Connor. The Cheyenne had made their camp for the night, and were asleep. North decided to wait until dawn to attack. In the morning, Captain Frank North's group closed on the camp. Spotting the scouts, the Cheyenne thought the approaching Indians were not the Pawnee Scouts, but friendly Cheyenne, and made no hostile moves. However, the Pawnee suddenly charged in on the Cheyenne, surprising them and killing all 24 Cheyenne men and women, including Yellow Woman, who was the stepmother of George Bent. North's scouts lost 4 horses, but captured 18 horses and 17 mules, many with government brands showing they had been captured in the recent Battle's of Red Buttes and Platte Bridge Station that had both occurred on July 26, 1865, near present-day [[Casper, Wyoming]].&lt;ref name=&quot;grinnell177&quot;/&gt;

=== The Battle of the Tongue River===

{{Main|Battle of the Tongue River}}

Connor marched north from Fort Connor, and on August 28, his Pawnee scouts found an Arapaho village of about 600 people on the [[Tongue River (Montana)|Tongue River]] near present-day [[Ranchester, Wyoming]]. [[Image:Jim Bridger.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The mountain man Jim Bridger was a guide for Connor during the Powder River Expedition.]] The next day, August 29, Connor attacked the village, whose leader was Black Bear, with 250 cavalrymen, and 80 Pawnee Scouts.  The people in the village were primarily women, children, and old men.  Most of the warriors were absent, engaged in a war with the [[Crow people|Crow]] on the [[Bighorn River]]. The surprised Indians fled the village, but regrouped and counterattacked and Connor was dissuaded from pursuing them.  The soldiers destroyed the village, captured about 500 horses, and 8 women and 13 children who were subsequently released.  Conner claimed to have killed 35 Arapaho warriors, a probably exaggerated estimate, at a cost to himself of 2 killed and five wounded. Connor then turned around and returned to Fort Connor, harassed by the Arapaho en route.  The Arapaho, who had not been overly hostile before, now joined the Sioux and Cheyenne.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Powder River (Montana) http://www.enotes.com/topic/Tongue_River_(Montana)?print=1, accessed 9 Aug 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McDermott, John Dishon (2003). ''Circle of Fire: The Indian War of 1865.'' Stackpole Books. pp. 112. ISBN 978-0-8117-0061-0&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sawyers' expedition ==

Meanwhile, an expedition commanded by Lieut. Col. James A. Sawyers consisting of train of 80 wagons, engineers, supplies, and escorting soldiers of Companies C and D of the [[Galvanized Yankees#Federal regiments composed of &quot;galvanized Yankees&quot;|5th U.S. Volunteer Infantry]] was en route to meet Connor on the Powder River with the plan to continue on to Montana.  Sawyers' group was to construct a new road for the use of emigrants to the Montana gold fields.

=== The Battle of Bone Pile Creek===
{{Main|Battle of Bone Pile Creek}}

On August 13, 1865, the soldiers, civilians, and wagon train of the Sawyers Expedition were moving west. The soldiers accompanying the train included a battalion of the [[Galvanized Yankees|5th U.S. Volunteer Infantry]], Companies C, and D, under the command of [[Captain (armed forces)|Captain]] George Williford. In the evening near Pumpkin Butte, Cheyenne and Sioux Native American Warriors attacked the train, killing Nathaniel Hedges, a 19-year-old civilian employee. Later in the evening of the thirteenth, the wagons were corralled near Bone Pile Creek, and Hedges was buried at the center of the corral. The next morning, the warriors returned and attacked again. The warriors again attacked the corralled wagons on the fifteenth, but they could not overtake the wagon train. Chief [[Red Cloud]] of the Sioux, and [[Dull Knife]] of the Cheyenne, accompanied by [[George Bent]] and [[Charles Bent]] of the Cheyenne negotiated with [[Lieutenant Colonel]] Sawyers for a safe passage of the wagon train in exchange for one wagon's load of supplies. Soldiers of the [[Galvanized Yankees|5th U.S. Volunteer Infantry]] reported that at this time that the Cheyenne warrior [[George Bent]] was dressed in a United States military uniform. Sawyers agreed to give the supplies, which included a wagon full of sugar, bacon, coffee, flour, and tobacco. When the wagons began moving again, the Natives attacked again, killing Privates Anthony Nelson, and John Rawze. The soldiers fired back, killing two warriors, and the Native Americans quickly withdrew from the corralled wagons.  After burying Private Nelson beside Nathaniel Hedges, and being unable to locate the body of Private Rawze, the Sawyers Expedition continued on.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Doyle|first1=Susan|title=Journeys to the Land of Gold: Emigrant Diaries from the Bozeman Trail, 1863-1866}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sawyers' fight ===

{{Main|Sawyers Fight}}

On September 1, 1865, Arapaho warriors, infuriated by the destruction of their village on the Tongue River, attacked Sawyers' wagon train, killing three men. Two of the Arapaho Warriors were killed. The wagon train was held under virtual siege for two weeks when it was finally rescued by Connor's forces.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell, pp. 208-209;McDermott, p. 124-127&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cole's and Walker's expedition's==

=== The two columns set out ===

Colonel [[Nelson D Cole]], left [[Omaha, Nebraska]], on July 1, 1865, with over 1,400 Missourians and 140 wagon-loads of supplies.  His column followed the [[Loup River]] upstream and then marched across country to [[Bear Butte]] in the [[Black Hills]], arriving there on August 13, 1865.  Cole's command, during the {{convert|560|mi|km}} of traveling, suffered from thirst, diminishing supplies, and near mutinies.  Lieutenant Colonel [[Samuel Walker (American Soldier)|Samuel Walker]] and his 600 Kansas Cavalrymen left [[Fort Laramie]], [[Dakota Territory]] on August 6, 1865, and met up with Cole's Expedition on August 19, 1865, near the [[Black Hills]].  He had likewise suffered from shortages of water, and had lost several of his soldiers of the [[16th Regiment Kansas Volunteer Cavalry]] from bad water.  The two columns marched separately, but remained in contact as they moved west to [[Powder River (Montana)|Powder River]] in [[Montana Territory]].  By this time, some of the men were barefooted and many of the horses and mules were growing weak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hampton, p. 10&quot;&gt;Hampton, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

=== March on Powder River ===
{{Main|Powder River Battles (1865)}}
On the morning of September 1, 1865, the over 1,400 United States soldiers and civilians, of Colonel Nelson D. Cole's column of the [[Powder River Expedition]], were encamped on Alkali Creek, a tributary of the [[Powder River (Montana)|Powder River]]. This was in [[Montana Territory]], in present-day, [[Custer County, Montana]]. In the early morning, over 300 Hunkpapa, Sans Arc, and Miniconjou Lakota [[Sioux]] Warriors attacked the camps' horse herd. The first of the soldiers to respond were seven men of Battery K, in the 2nd Missouri Light Artillery Regiment. Shortly after leaving the camp, Warriors ambushed this party, and in the following battle, five of these seven soldiers became casualties, with two killed, one mortally wounded, and two wounded. Later that night, two unknown U.S. soldiers in a hunting party were killed. The known Sioux Casualties during the battle of Alkali Creek, are four unknown Warriors killed, and four unknown Warriors wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hampton, p. 10&quot;/&gt;

On the next day, Saturday, September 2, 1865, there were at least three small skirmishes with warriors. In the first, at least one warrior was killed in the fight. In the second, no casualties were reported. In the third, later in the day, two soldiers were killed, while returning to camp after a hunting trip. In desperate need of supplies, Colonel Cole and Walker decided to follow Powder River north, to search for Brigadier General [[Patrick E. Connor]]'s column, and his wagon train. The expeditions continued north to the mouth of Mizpah Creek in [[Custer County, Montana]].  There, the two Colonels decided to turn back around and retrace their steps south up the [[Powder River (Montana)|Powder River]], to search for Connor's left column. The Indians attacked again on September 4 and 5, 1865, in present-day [[Custer County, Montana]]. They continued to harass Cole and Walker as the soldiers moved south up Powder River.&lt;ref name=Odyssey&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wagner|first1=David E. |last2=Bennett |first2=Lyman G.  |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Powder_River_odyssey.html?id=zUTzAAAAMAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y |title=Powder River Odyssey: Nelson Cole's Western Campaign of 1865, The Journals of Lyman G. Bennett and Other Eyewitness Accounts |date=2009 |publisher=Arthur H. Clark Co. |ISBN=978-0-87062-370-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Sioux Chief 'Roman Nose', from Robert N. Dennis collection of stereoscopic views.jpg|thumb|300px|right|The Cheyenne warrior Roman Nose fought at the Battle of Dry Creek on September 8, 1865. Avstereoscopic image of Roman Nose.]]
On September 8, 1865, the over 2,000 United States soldiers and civilians of Colonel Cole's and Walker's column's were marching South, up Powder River in Montana Territory. Unbeknownst to them, a village of Over 2,500 Cheyenne, Sioux, and Arapaho including the Cheyenne chief [[Roman Nose]], were camped less than ten miles away. When discovering this, the Cheyenne, Sioux, and Arapaho Warriors, not wanting the soldiers to attack their village, attacked the soldiers first. The soldiers' lead guard, was marching about one quarter of a mile ahead of the column. This command was hit first. Out of the 25 men of the lead guard, two men became casualties. After seeing this first confrontation, Lieutenant Colonel Walker sent a courier back to inform Colonel Cole of the attack. At the time, Cole was overseeing the crossing of his wagon train to the east bank of the Powder River. Cole ordered the train, out of the timber and corralled, and the 12th Missouri Cavalry to skirmish through the woods along the river bank, and to drive out a body of Indians in the woods. The soldiers pushed the Warriors off the battlefield. Near the end of the engagement, another Private was wounded. At least one Native American was killed in the engagement. A snowstorm during the night of September 8–9, 1865, caused further problems for the soldiers, most of whom were now on foot, in rags, and reduced to eating raw horse meat.&lt;ref name=Odyssey&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wagner|first1=David E. |last2=Bennett |first2=Lyman G.  |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Powder_River_odyssey.html?id=zUTzAAAAMAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y |title=Powder River Odyssey: Nelson Cole's Western Campaign of 1865, The Journals of Lyman G. Bennett and Other Eyewitness Accounts |date=2009 |publisher=Arthur H. Clark Co. |ISBN=978-0-87062-370-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the morning of September 10, 1865, Cole's, and Walker's column's were encamped near the confluence of the Little Powder River and the Powder River when Native American Warriors appeared. There were volleys and some sporadic firing. On September 11, there was more light skirmishing. On September 13, two scouts from Brigadier General Connor's column found Walker's and Cole's column's on Powder River and informed them of the newly established [[Fort Reno (Wyoming)|Fort Connor]] on Powder River east of [[Kaycee, Wyoming]]. Cole, Walker and their soldiers arrived there on September 20, 1865. Connor deemed the soldiers unfit for further service and sent them back to Fort Laramie where most of them were mustered out of the army.

[[File:YellowstoneRiverMap.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The soldiers in the Powder River Expedition followed Powder River from near its mouth to its headwaters.]]

== Casualties ==
Colonel Cole reported that the Eastern column sustained twelve men killed and two men missing.  Lieutenant Colonel Walker reported that the Center column suffered one man killed and four men wounded.  Cole claimed that his soldiers had killed two hundred Indians.  By contrast, Walker said, &quot;I cannot say as we killed one.&quot;  Indian casualties were likely light.&lt;ref&gt;[[George E. Hyde|Hyde, George E.]] ''Life of George Bent: Written from his Letters'' Norman: U of OK press, pp. 240-241&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Connor finally united all the components of his expedition on September 24, 1865, at Fort Connor.  However, orders transferring him to Utah were awaiting him when he arrived there. The [[16th Regiment Kansas Volunteer Cavalry|16th Kansas Volunteer Cavalry]] remained to staff Fort Connor and all other troops withdrew to Fort Laramie, most to be mustered out of the army.

Although achieving some successes, the expedition failed to defeat decisively or intimidate the Indians.  The Cheyenne warrior, [[George Bent]], a participant in the [[Battle of Dry Creek (1865)|Battle of Dry Creek]], on September 8, 1865, stated that the Lakota would have annihilated Cole's and Walker's column's had they possessed more good firearms. Indian resistance to travelers on the Bozeman Trail became more determined than ever. &quot;There will be no more travel on that road until the government takes care of the Indians,&quot; a correspondent wrote.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Dee. &quot;The Fetterman Massacre'' Lincoln: U of NE Press, 1962, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; The most important consequence of the expedition was to persuade the United States government that another effort to build and protect a wagon road from Fort Laramie to the gold fields in Montana was desirable.  That conviction would lead to a renewed invasion of the Powder River country a year later and [[Red Cloud's War]] in which the Sioux, Cheyenne, and Arapaho would emerge victorious.&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

==Officers accompanying the Powder River Expedition==

===Headquarters===
* [[Brigadier General]] [[Patrick E. Connor]], Commanding.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] C. J. Laurant, Assistant Adjutant General, Headquarters.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Samuel Robbins, Chief Engineer, 1st Colorado Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Henry E. Palmer, Quartermaster, 11th Kansas Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] William H. Tubbs, Acting Commissary of Subsistence, Headquarters.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Oscar Jewett, [[Aide-de-camp]] to Connor, Headquarters ([[Wounded in action]]).

===Right Column===

* [[Colonel]] [[Nelson D. Cole]], Headquarters, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Colonel]] Oliver Wells, Headquarters, 12th Missouri Cavalry.
* [[Major]] (retired) [[Lyman G. Bennett (soldier)|Lyman G. Bennett]], Chief Engineer, 4th Arkansas Cavalry.
* [[Major]] Clemenz Landgraeber, Headquarters, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Surgeon]] George Washington Corey, Headquarters, 12th Missouri Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] McMurray, Headquarters, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Samuel Flagg, Battery B, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Jefferson Miller, Battery E, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] William C. F. Montgomery, Battery H, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Edward S. Rowland, Battery K, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Charles H. Thurber, Battery L, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Napoleon Boardman, Battery M, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[First Lieutenant]] John H. Kendall, Battery L, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[First Lieutenant]] Charles H. Springer, Company B, 12th Missouri Cavalry.
* [[First Lieutenant]] William Rinne, Battery C, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Frederick J. Amsden, U.S. Signal Corps, Department of the Missouri.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] George R. Thorne, Acting Assistant Quartermaster
* [[Second Lieutenant]] William T. Shaver, Headquarters, 12th Missouri Cavalry.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Hiram L. Kelly, Battery A, 2nd Missouri Artillery ([[Wounded in action]]).
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Philip Smiley, Battery H, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Abram S. Hoagland, Battery K, 2nd Missouri Artillery.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] James A. Ferren, Battery K, 2nd Missouri Artillery.

===Central Column===

* [[Brevet (military)|Brevet]] [[Brigadier General]], [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Samuel Walker (soldier)|Samuel Walker]], Headquarters, 16th Kansas Cavalry.
* [[Major]] Clarkson Reynolds, Headquarters, 16th Kansas Cavalry.
* [[Surgeon]] James P. Erickson, Headquarters, 16th Kansas Cavalry (Died at Fort Connor).
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Oscar F. Dunlap, Company H, 15th Kansas Cavalry.
* [[First Lieutenant]] R. M. Fisk, Company H, 15th Kansas Cavalry.
* [[First Lieutenant]] James L. Walker, Company D, 16th Kansas Cavalry ([[Mortal wound|Mortally Wounded]]).
* [[First Lieutenant]] Wesley T. Smith, Company H, 16th Kansas Cavalry 
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Charles Balance, Company F, 16th Kansas Cavalry.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Edward Gill, Company H, 15th Kansas Cavalry.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Francis E. Smith, Company H, 15th Kansas Cavalry.

===Left Column===

* [[Colonel]] James H. Kidd, Headquarters, 6th Michigan Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] [[Frank North]], Company A, Pawnee Indian Scouts.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Albert Brown, Company M, 2nd California Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Osmer F. Cole, Company L, 6th Michigan Cavalry ([[Killed in action]]).
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] George Conrad, Company L, 2nd California Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Jacob L. Humphreyville, Company K, 11th Ohio Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Levi G. Marshall, Company E, 11th Ohio Cavalry.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Edwin R. Nash, Company A, Omaha/Winnebago Indian Scouts.
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] N. J. O'Brian, Company F, 7th Iowa Cavalry.
* [[First Lieutenant]] John S. Brewer, Company F, 7th Iowa Cavalry.
* [[First Lieutenant]] Michael Evans, Company A, Omaha/Winnebago Indian Scouts.
* [[First Lieutenant]] Charles A. Small, Company A, Pawnee Indian Scouts.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Joseph Willard Brown, U.S. Signal Corps, Department of the Missouri.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Gavin Mitchell, Company A, Omaha/Winnebago Indian Scouts.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] James Murie, Company A, Omaha/Winnebago Indian Scouts.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Alonzo V. Richards, U.S. Signal Corps, Department of the Missouri.
* [[Second Lieutenant]] Eugene F. Ware, Company F, 7th Iowa Cavalry.

== Order of battle ==

'''United States Army''', Powder River Expedition, July 1,-October 4, 1865.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Division
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Column
! Regiments and Others
|-
| rowspan=4 |
Powder River Expedition, [[Brigadier General]] [[Patrick E. Connor|Patrick Edward Connor]], commanding.&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;

| Left, Western Column
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
[[Colonel]] James H. Kidd
|
* [[Battery F, 2nd Missouri Light Artillery|2nd Missouri Volunteer Light Artillery Regiment]], (Detachment, 14 men):
* [[2nd California Cavalry Regiment|2nd California Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]], (Companies L, and M, 105 men): Captain George Conrad, Captain Albert Brown
* [[6th Michigan Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]], (6 Companies, ~200 men): Colonel James H. Kidd
* [[7th Regiment Iowa Volunteer Cavalry|7th Iowa Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]], (Company F, 88 men): Captain N. J. O'Brian
* [[11th Ohio Cavalry|11th Ohio Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]], (Companies E, and K, 127-130 men): Captain Levi G. Marshall, Captain Jacob L. Humphreyville
* [[Pawnee Scouts]] (95 men): Captain [[Frank North|Frank J. North]]
* [[Omaha people|Omaha]] and [[Winnebago people|Winnebago]] Scouts (84 men): Captain Edwin W. Nash
* 195 Civilian Wagon Train Employees: Chief Wagon Train Master Robert Wheeling 
* Civilian Guides: [[Jim Bridger]]
* Mountain Howitzer Section, (2 Cannon), (manned by 14 men from [[Battery F, 2nd Missouri Light Artillery|2nd Missouri Volunteer Light Artillery Regiment]]):
* [[Signal Corps (United States Army)|United States Signal Corps]], (Detachment, 15 men): Lieutenant Joseph W. Brown, Lieutenant Alonzo V. Richards
|-
| Central, Middle Column
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
[[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Samuel Walker (soldier)|Samuel Walker]]
|
* [[15th Regiment Kansas Volunteer Cavalry|15th Kansas Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]] (Company H, ~50 men): Second Lieutenant Edward Gill
* [[16th Regiment Kansas Volunteer Cavalry|16th Kansas Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]] (8 Companies, ~550 men): Lieutenant Colonel [[Samuel Walker (soldier)|Samuel Walker]]
* Mountain Howitzer Section, (2 Cannon)
|-
| Right, Eastern Column
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
[[Colonel]] [[Nelson D. Cole]]
|
* [[Battery F, 2nd Missouri Light Artillery|2nd Missouri Volunteer Light Artillery Regiment]], (7 Batteries, 797 men): Colonel [[Nelson D. Cole]]
* [[12th Missouri Volunteer Cavalry|12th Missouri Volunteer Cavalry Regiment]], (12 Companies, 311 men): Colonel Oliver Wells
* Ordinance Rifle Section (2 Cannon), (manned by men from [[Battery F, 2nd Missouri Light Artillery|2nd Missouri Volunteer Light Artillery Regiment]]):
* [[Signal Corps (United States Army)|United States Signal Corps]], (Detachment, 7 men): Second Lieutenant Frederick J. Amsden
|}

'''Native Americans'''
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Native Americans
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Tribe
! Leaders
|-
| rowspan=3 |
[[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
| Sioux
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
|
* [[Sitting Bull]]
* [[Crazy Horse]]
|-
| Cheyenne
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
|
* [[Roman Nose]]
* [[George Bent]]
* Charles Bent
* Black Whetstone[[Killed in action|†]]
* Yellow Woman[[Killed in action|†]]
|-
| Arapaho
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
|
* Black Bear
* Medicine Man
|}

==See also==
* [[Red Cloud's War]]
* [[Black Hills War]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Montana Indian Battles}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1865]]
[[Category:Montana Territory]]
[[Category:Pre-statehood history of Wyoming]]
[[Category:Sioux Wars]]
[[Category:Wyoming in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:Idaho Territory]]
[[Category:1865 in the United States]]
[[Category:1865 in Idaho Territory]]
[[Category:1865 in Montana Territory]]
[[Category:1865 in Wyoming Territory]]</text>
      <sha1>6ox549fk8xyy24ol3d0j7nefv17f97s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
