<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Saxon Rebellion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29330982</id>
    <revision>
      <id>698617478</id>
      <parentid>698617405</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-07T06:01:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jim1138</username>
        <id>7695475</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/69.235.0.170|69.235.0.170]] ([[User talk:69.235.0.170|talk]]): Editing tests ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.1.18)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10491">{{About|the rebellion in 1073-75|the revolt of 1077–88|Great Saxon Revolt|the wars under Charlemagne from 772 to 804|Saxon Wars}}
[[File:Herzogtum Sachsen.png|thumb|320px|Duchy of Saxony 919-1125, ''Historical Atlas'' by [[William Robert Shepherd|William R. Shepherd]], 1923]]
The '''Saxon Rebellion''' or '''Rebellion of the Saxons'''&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, James Westfall (1928). ''Feudal Germany'', University of Chicago Press, Chicago, Cambridge University Press, London.&lt;/ref&gt; ({{lang-de|Sachsenkrieg}}) refers to the struggle between the [[Salian dynasty]] ruling the [[Holy Roman Empire]] and the rebel [[Duchy of Saxony|Saxons]] during the reign of [[Henry IV, Holy Roman Emperor|Henry IV]]. The conflict reached its climax in the period from summer 1073 until the end of 1075, in a rebellion that involved several clashes of arms.

== Origins ==
Undercurrents of discord between the Salian royal family and the Saxons already existed under Henry's father, Emperor [[Henry III, Holy Roman Emperor|Henry III]]. This may have been primarily due to his [[Rhenish Franconia]]n origin as well as his numerous stays in the [[Imperial Palace of Goslar]], which were associated with a disproportionately high economic burden on the surrounding population. With the accession of Henry IV in 1065 this conflict intensified, as Henry made demands on numerous Imperial domains (''Reichsgüter'') in the centre of the Saxon heartland around the [[Harz]] mountains—especially the [[silver mining|silver mines]] of [[Rammelsberg]]. To secure these estates he initiated a castle building programme, erecting numerous fortresses along the range, the most prominent being the [[Harzburg]]. This was perceived as a threat by the Saxons. In addition, these castles were staffed with [[ministerialis|ministeriales]] of [[Duchy of Swabia|Swabian]] origin, who frequently plundered the Saxon population to make up for their lack of income.

In 1070 the Saxon count [[Otto of Nordheim]], Duke of [[Duchy of Bavaria|Bavaria]] since 1061, had been accused by the ministerialis [[Egeno I of Konradsburg]] of planning an assault on the king's life. Otto was deposed and [[Imperial ban|banned]], nevertheless he gained support by the son of the [[House of Billung|Billung]] duke [[Ordulf, Duke of Saxony|Ordulf of Saxony]], the young [[Magnus, Duke of Saxony|Magnus]]. King Henry IV had both captured and arrested. While Otto was pardoned, Magnus remained in custody at the Harzburg and was not released even after his father's death in 1072, as he showed no intention to renounce the Saxon ducal dignity.

== Beginning of the rebellion ==
According to the chronicler [[Lambert of Hersfeld]], the Saxon princes came to the Imperial Palace of Goslar on 29 June 1073 in order to point to these abuses and demand improvements. Henry IV refused to enter discussions and then fled from the large, advancing Saxon army to the nearby castle of Harzburg, where he was besieged by the Saxon rebels, again led by Count Otto of Nordheim together with Bishop [[Burchard II (Bishop of Halberstadt)|Burchard II of Halberstadt]]. The king, however, was able to escape on the night of 10 August 1073, allegedly through the castle's well shaft. Henry fled across the Harz mountains reaching the Landgraviate of Thuringia at [[Eschwege]] first and then moved on to Franconian [[Bad Hersfeld|Hersfeld]] further into southern Germany. But he found hardly any support among the princes of the Empire, who were not willing to go to battle with him against the Saxons.

As a result, on 27 January 1074, Henry stood at the head of what was only a small army compared to the much larger Saxon one at Hersfeld. Both sides were afraid to join in battle, but for different reasons. Henry probably because of his obvious inferiority. The Saxon leaders, by contrast, were aware that a victory by their army, consisting mainly of peasants, would have strengthened the position of the latter, something they were not in favour of. So it happened that on 2 February 1074 [[Treaty of Gerstungen|peace negotiations in Gerstungen]] took place, which resulted in a settlement between the warring parties. The main outcome was that Henry IV agreed to the [[slighting]] of his castles on the edge of the Harz.

Henry's accession to the demolition of his Harz castles included the Harzburg, which included a [[collegiate church]] and a family grave containing Henry's dead son and brother. To protect the royal burial ground, Henry directed that only the towers and walls of the Harzburg would be removed. This enraged the surrounding rural population who, in March 1074, razed the castle and its church to their foundation walls and desecrated the royal tombs. This deed may have had a considerable personal effect on Henry, but politically it put all the trumps in his hand: the plunder of the church and the desecration of the royal tomb caused great outrage in his kingdom, and many [[Princes of the Holy Roman Empire|Imperial princes]] returned to Henry's side. The Saxon nobility refused any blame for the actions of the rural population and immediately offered to restore the castle and church at their own expense.

== First Battle of Langensalza ==
{{main|Battle of Langensalza (1075)}} 
Henry was once again bent on confrontation and this time gathered a much larger army, although he was not able to march against  Saxony until 1075. In the First Battle of Langensalza (known in Germany as the &quot;Battle of Homburg on the Unstrut&quot;, Homburg being a former monastery near [[Bad Langensalza]]) on 9 June 1075 he dealt the Saxon army, which consisted mainly of simple peasants, a crushing defeat and then rampaged through Saxony and Thuringia laying waste.

Amongst the followers of King Henry who fought with him were the Swabian duke [[Rudolf of Rheinfelden]], Duke [[Vratislaus II of Bohemia]], Duke [[Theodoric II, Duke of Lorraine|Theoderic II of Upper Lorraine]] and the [[House of Babenberg|Babenberg]] margrave [[Ernest, Margrave of Austria|Ernest of Austria]], who was killed in battle, as well as Bishop Hermann of [[Archdiocese of Bamberg|Bamberg]] and Count Hermann II of Gleiberg. On the Saxon side, in addition to Count Otto of Northeim and Bishop Burchard II von Halberstadt, were Magnus Billung, meanwhile Duke of Saxony, Margrave [[Lothair Udo II, Margrave of the Nordmark|Lothair Udo II of the Nordmark]] and Count [[Gebhard of Supplinburg]], who was killed in battle, as well as the Saxon [[count palatine]] Frederick II of [[Goseck]] and Count Dietrich II of [[Katlenburg-Lindau|Katlenburg]].

One of the two leaders, Bishop Burchard II of Halberstadt, was detained in Homburg by royal troops and finally handed over on 13 June to the Bishop of Bamberg as a prisoner.

The chronicler [[Lambert of Hersfeld]] described the battle in his ''Annals'':
{{quotation|''The battle raged from midday until the ninth hour, and the armies of the two states, Swabia and Bavaria, were on the brink of fleeing as messengers repeatedly reported to the King that their people were in danger, when suddenly Count Hermann of Gleiberg and the Bamberg troops launched an attack. Now the Duke of Bohemia, followed by Duke [[Godfrey IV, Duke of Lower Lorraine|Godfrey of Lorraine]] galloped with their cavalry to join the battle. The Saxons could not withstand this massive onslaught and slowly fell back.''}}

On 27 October at the village of Spier near [[Sondershausen]], the Saxon leader finally capitulated to the king in public, i.e. in front of the whole army. Henry had no mercy, but savoured his triumph. The Saxon leader's submission was barefoot, according to Lambert, and the surrender, without exception, unconditional. Henry then held numerous Saxon princes in prison in various places and transferred their fiefs to others.

== Aftermath ==
Beginning almost simultaneously with the surrender, the [[Investiture Controversy]] took Henry's full attention in the years that followed. Unrest in Saxony also flared up during this period again and again, but did not reach the same level of political and military as in the time from 1073 to 1075.

At the diet of princes in [[Trebur]] in October 1076, [[Otto of Northeim]] again aligned himself with the opposition. Although he was always a potential candidate, the princes did not choose him; instead, in 1077 in [[Forchheim]], they selected [[Rudolf of Rheinfelden]] and, later, [[Hermann of Salm]] as [[antiking]]s. Nevertheless, Otto's had a significant influence on the opposition's politics. Militarily, he distinguished himself again in the battles of [[Battle of Mellrichstadt|Mellrichstadt]], [[Battle of Flarchheim|Flarchheim]] and the [[Battle on the Elster|Elster]], leading from the front.

Even Henry's son, King [[Henry V, Holy Roman Emperor|Henry V of Germany]], still had to fight the Saxons. He lost, for example, the 1115 [[Battle of Welfesholz]] to the Saxons led by his later successor, King [[Lothair III, Holy Roman Emperor|Lothair III]].

== Sources ==

=== Primary sources ===
* [[Bruno the Saxon]], &quot;Brunos Sachsenkrieg&quot; [''Brunonis Saxonicum bellum''; German], translated by Franz-Josef Schmale. In: ''Quellen zur Geschichte Kaiser Heinrichs IV'', Darmstadt: 1968. (= selected sources about the German history of the Middle Ages. Freiherr vom Stein - memorial edition; 12), pp.&amp;nbsp;191–405.
* [[Carmen de bello saxonico]]. ''Das Lied vom Sachsenkrieg'', translated by Franz-Josef Schmale. In: ''Quellen zur Geschichte Kaiser Heinrichs IV'', Darmstadt, 1968. (= selected sources about the German history of the Middle Ages. Freiherr vom Stein - memorial edition; 12), p.&amp;nbsp;142–189.
* [[Lambert of Hersfeld]]: ''Annalen'', Darmstadt 1957. (= selected sources about the German history of the Middle Ages. Freiherr vom Stein - memorial edition; 13)

The two well-known authors, Bruno and Lambert of Hersfeld, describe the conflict from the perspective of the Saxons, while the unknown author of ''Carmen'' was a partisan of Henry.

=== Secondary sources ===
* Schulze, Hans K. (1991). ''Hegemoniales Kaisertum: Ottonen und Salier''. Berlin, ISBN 3-88680-307-4.
* Talkenberg, Fabian (2010). ''Rebellion am Vorabend von Canossa: Der Sachsenaufstand gegen Heinrich IV.''. Marburg, ISBN 978-3-8288-2355-6.

==External links==
* [http://www.genealogie-mittelalter.de www.genealogie-mittelalter.de] {{de icon}}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Battles involving the Holy Roman Empire]]
[[Category:Battles involving Saxony]]
[[Category:1070s in the Holy Roman Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>0xfgtaur6lrhdlmlyhe29ylkr0479ox</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
