<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Scipio Aemilianus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>317286</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742843574</id>
      <parentid>742835754</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-06T04:19:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Secondary sources */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25296">'''Publius Cornelius Scipio Aemilianus Africanus Numantinus''' (185–129 BC), also known as ''Scipio Aemilianus'' or ''Scipio Africanus Minor'' (Scipio Africanus the Younger), was a politician of the [[Roman Republic]]. He was elected [[consul]] twice. In 147 BC, he was under the age required to be consul, with an exception made by popular demand, and took over the command of the [[Third Punic War]] (149-146 BC) and besieged and destroyed [[Carthage]]. In 134 BC he took over the [[Numantine War]] (143-133 BC), restored the discipline of the Roman army, besieged [[Numantia]] and destroyed it. He was a prominent patron of writers and philosophers.

== Family ==
Scipio Aemilianus was the second of two sons of [[Lucius Aemilius Paulus Macedonicus]], (the commander who led the victorious campaign of the Romans in the Third Macedonian War) and his first wife, Papiria Masonis. He was adopted by the eldest son [[Publius Cornelius Scipio P.f. P.n. Africanus|Publius Cornelius Scipio]] of his aunt [[Aemilia Tertia]] and [[Publius Cornelius Scipio Africanus]] (the commander who won the decisive battle of the [[Second Punic War]]), and became Publius Cornelius Scipio Aemilianus (assuming the name of his adoptive father with a fourth name Aemilianus added to indicate his original [[Roman naming conventions#Nomen|nomen]]). His elder brother was adopted by a son or grandson of [[Quintus Fabius Maximus Verrucosus]] (a prominent commander in the Second Punic War), whose name became [[Quintus Fabius Maximus Aemilianus]].

==First involvement in a war (Third Macedonian War, 171–168 BC)==
Lucius Aemilius Paullus took his two older sons with him in his campaign in Greece. [[Plutarch]] wrote that Scipio was his favourite son because he &quot;saw that he was by nature more prone to excellence than any of his brothers.&quot; He related that during mopping-up operations after the  [[Battle of Pydna]],  Aemilius was worried because his younger son was missing.  Plutarch also wrote that &quot;The whole army learned of the distress and anguish of their general, and springing up from their suppers, ran about with torches, many to the tent of Aemilius, and many in front of the ramparts, searching among the numerous dead bodies. Dejection reigned in the camp, and the plain was filled with the cries of men calling out the name of Scipio. For from the very outset he had been admired by everybody, since, beyond any other one of his family, he had a nature adapted for leadership in war and public service. Well, then, when it was already late and he was almost despaired of, he came in from the pursuit with two or three comrades, covered with the blood of the enemies he had slain ...&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, Parallel Lives, The Live of Aemilius, 22.2-7&lt;/ref&gt; Scipio Aemilanus was seventeen at the time.

== First involvement in the Numantine War (143-133 BC)==
In 152 BC, the consul Marcus  Claudius Marcellus urged the senate to conclude a peace with the [[Celtiberians]]. The senate rejected this and one of the consuls for 151 BC, [[Lucius Licinius Lucullus (consul 151 BC)|Lucius Licinius Lucullus]], was sent to [[Hispania]] to continue the war. However, there was a crisis of recruitment. Due to rumours about of the incessant battles and heavy Roman losses, and with Marcellus  appearing to be afraid of continuing the war, there was panic. Young men avoided enrollment as soldiers through unverifiable excuses. Men eligible to be legates (legion commanders) or Military tribunes (senior officers) did not volunteer.&lt;ref&gt;Polybius, The Histories, 35.4.1-7&lt;/ref&gt; Scipio Aemilianus, who was thought to have advised the prosecution of the war, asked the senate to be sent to Hispania either as a [[military tribune]] or a legatus, even though it was safer for him to go to [[Macedon]] where he had been invited to go to settle domestic disputes, because the crisis in Hispania was more urgent. The senate was at first surprised, but Scipio became popular and those who had been avoiding their duty, ashamed by Scipio’s example begun to volunteer as legates or to enroll as soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Polybius, The Histories, 35, 4.8-14&lt;/ref&gt; He served under Lucullus. [[Velleius Paterculus]] wrote and was awarded a [[mural crown]] (a military decoration awarded to a soldier who first climbed the wall of a besieged city or fortress to successfully place the military standard on it).&lt;ref&gt;Velleius Paterculus, Roman History, I.12.3&lt;/ref&gt; [[Florus]] wrote that &quot;having been challenged by their king to a single combat, carried off the spolia opima (the armour and arms stripped from the body of an opposing commander slain in single combat. They were regarded as the most honourable of all war trophies).&lt;ref&gt;Florus, Epitome  of Roman History 1.17&lt;/ref&gt;

==Third Punic War (149-146 BC)==
Although the power of Carthage been broken with her defeat in the Second Punic War, there was still lingering resentment in Rome. [[Cato the Elder]] ended every speech with, &quot;[[Carthago delenda est|Carthage must be destroyed.]]&quot; In 150 BC an appeal was made to Scipio Aemilianus by the Carthaginians to act as mediator between them and the Numidian prince [[Massinissa]] who, supported by the anti-Carthaginian faction in Rome, was incessantly encroaching on Carthaginian territory. In 149 BC Rome declared war, and a force sent to Africa (Tunisia), Carthage's homeland.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|title=Scipio |volume=24|pages=406-407 |url=https://archive.org/stream/encyclopaediabri24chisrich#page/406/mode/2up}} This Scipio is listed as the third of four with the name.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early stages of the war, the Romans suffered repeated defeats. Scipio Aemilianus, was a military tribune (senior officer), and distinguished himself repeatedly. In 147 BC he was elected [[Roman consul|consul]], while still under the minimal age required by law to hold this office.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; Without the customary procedure of drawing lots, he was assigned to the African theatre of war. After a year of desperate fighting and stubborn heroism on the part of the defenders, he took the city of Carthage, taking prisoner about 50,000 survivors (about one tenth of the city's population.) Complying with the mandate of the [[Roman Senate|Senate]], he ordered the city evacuated, burnt it, razed it to the ground and ploughed it over, ending the Third Punic War. On his return to Rome he received a [[Roman Triumph|Triumph]], having also established a personal claim to his adoptive ''[[agnomen]]'' of Africanus.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

==Numantine War (143-133 BC)==
In 134 BC Scipio was elected consul again because the citizens thought that he was the only man capable of defeating the Numantines in the [[Numantine War]]. The [[Celtiberians]] of the City of [[Numantia]], which had strong defensive geographical features, held off the Romans for nine years. The army in Hispania was demoralised and ill-disciplined. Scipio concentrated on restoring discipline by forbidding luxuries the troops had become accustomed to, through regular tough exercises (all-day marches, building camps and fortifications and then demolishing them, digging ditches and then filling them up, and the like) and by enforcing regulations strictly. When he thought that the army was ready he encamped near Numantia. He did not proceed along the shorter route to avoid the guerrilla tactics the Numantines were good at. Instead, he made a detour though the land of the Vaccaei, who were selling food to the Numantines. He was ambushed several times but defeated the enemy. In one of these ambushes by a river which was difficult to cross, he was forced to make a detour along a longer route where there was no water. He marched at night when it was cooler and dug wells which had bitter water. He saved his men, but some horses and pack animals died of thirst. Then he passed through the territory of the Caucaei who had broken the treaty with Rome and declared that they could return safely to their homes. He returned to the Numanitine territory and was joined by [[Jugurtha]], the son of the king of [[Numidia]], with twelve elephants, archers and slingers.&lt;ref&gt;Appian, Roman History, Book 6, The Wars in Spain, 84-89&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually, Scipio prepared to besiege Numantia. He asked the allied tribes in Hispania for specified numbers of troops. He built a circuit of fortifications which was nine kilometres long. The wall was three metres high and two and a half metres wide. He built an embankment of the same dimensions as the wall around the adjoining marsh. He built two towers by the River [[Durius]] ([[Douro]]) to which he moored large timbers with ropes which were full of knives and spear heads and were constantly kept in motion by the current. This prevented the enemy from slipping through covertly. He managed to force Numantia into starvation. The Numantines surrendered. Some killed themselves. Scipio sold the rest into slavery, destroyed the city and kept fifty men for his triumph.&lt;ref&gt;Appian, Roman History, Book 6, The Wars in Spain, 90-98&lt;/ref&gt; For his success Scipio Aemilianus received the additional ''agnomen'' of &quot;Numantinus.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

== Political career ==

In 142 BC Scipio Africanus was a censor. During his [[Roman censor|censorship]], he endeavoured to check the growing luxury and immorality of the period. In 139 BC, he was unsuccessfully accused of high treason by [[Tiberius Claudius Asellus]], whom he had degraded when [[Roman censor|censor]]. The speeches he gave on that occasion (now lost) were considered brilliant.

Scipio helped his relative [[Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus (I)|Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus]] who in 134 BC  had served in the Numantine War as a [[quaestor]] (treasurer) under the consul [[Gaius Hostilius Mancinus]]. The consul was pinned down by the enemy and, unable to escape, made a peace treaty. Tiberius negotiated the peace terms. The treaty was rejected by the senate as a disgrace. [[Plutarch]] wrote that &quot;the relatives and friends of the soldiers, who formed a large part of the people&quot; blamed this on Mancinus and insisted &quot;that it was due to Tiberius that the lives of so many citizens had been saved.&quot; Those who disagreed with the violation of the treaty &quot;cast forth those who had taken hand and share in the treaty, as for instance the quaestors and military tribunes, turning upon their heads the guilt of perjury and violation of the pact. In the present affair, indeed, more than at any other time, the people showed their good will and affection towards Tiberius. For they voted to deliver up the consul unarmed and in bonds to the Numantines, but spared all the other officers for the sake of Tiberius.&quot; Scipio used his influence to help to save the men &quot;but none the less he was blamed for not saving Mancinus, and for not insisting that the treaty with the Numantines, which had been made through the agency of his kinsman and friend Tiberius, should be kept inviolate.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, Parallel lives, The live of Tiberius Gracchus, 7.1-3&lt;/ref&gt;

The Encyclopædia Britannica suggests that Scipio Aemilianus was not in sympathy with the [[optimates]], the political faction which supported the aristocracy.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Scipio Africanus the Younger|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/529059/Scipio-Africanus-the-Younger|work=Encyclopaedia Britannica Online|accessdate=4 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whatever the case, he was in disagreement with the militant actions of the movement led by Gracchus when he was a  [[Plebeian Tribune|plebeian tribune]], which pressed for a law to redistribute land to the poor. Plutarch wrote that &quot;this disagreement certainly resulted in no mischief past remedy&quot; and thought that if Scipio had been in Rome during the political activity of Gracchus, the latter would not have been murdered &lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, Parallel lives, The live of Tiberius Gracchus, 7.4&lt;/ref&gt; - he was fighting the war in Hispania. Still, he disliked the actions of Gracchus. Plutarch wrote &quot;[while] at Numantia, when he learned of the death of Tiberius, he recited in a loud voice the verse of Homer: [from the [[Odyssey]] I.47] ''&quot;So may all who engage in such lawless conspiracies perish.&quot;'' Plutarch also wrote that (after his return to Rome) &quot;when Caius and Fulvius asked him in an assembly of the people what he thought about the death of Tiberius, he made a reply which showed his dislike of the measures advocated by him,&quot; this made him unpopular, &quot;the people began to interrupt him as he was speaking, a thing which they had never done before, and Scipio himself was thereby led on to abuse the people.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, Parallel Lives, The life of Tiberius Gracchus, 21-4-5&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gaius Papirius Carbo (consul 120 BC)|Gaius Papirius Carbo]] was a plebeian tribune and [[Marcus Fulvius Flaccus (consul 125 BC)|Marcus Fulvius Flaccus]] was a senator sympathetic to the Gracchian cause.

Scipio made himself unpopular again. [[Appian]] related that Fulvius Flaccus, Papirius Carbo and Tiberius’ younger brother, [[Gaius Sempronius Gracchus|Caius Sempronius Gracchus]], chaired a commission to implement the Gracchian law. There never had been a land survey and land owners often did not have land deeds. The land was resurveyed. Some owners had to give up their orchards and farm buildings and go to empty land or move from cultivated to uncultivated land or swamps. As anyone was allowed to work undistributed land, many tilled land next to their own, blurring the demarcation between public and private land. Rome’s Italian allies complained about lawsuits brought against them and chose Scipio Aemilianus to defend them. As the allies had fought in his wars, he accepted. In the senate Scipio did not criticise the Law, but argued that the cases should be heard by a court rather than the commission which did not have the confidence of the litigants. This was accepted and the consul [[Gaius Sempronius Tuditanus]] was appointed to give judgement. However, seeing that the job was difficult he found a pretext to fight a war in Illyria. The people were angry &quot;because they saw a man, in whose favour they had often opposed the aristocracy and incurred their enmity, electing him consul twice contrary to law, now taking the side of the Italian allies against themselves&quot; His enemies claimed that he was determined to abolish the Gracchian law and was about to start &quot;armed strife and bloodshed.&quot;  When the people heard these allegations  they were in a state of alarm until Scipio died at home in his bed.&lt;ref&gt;Appian, Roman History, Book 13 The Civil Wars, 1.18-20&lt;/ref&gt; Then  According to Appian, he died without a wound.

Appian wrote that it could not be known whether Scipio was murdered by Cornelia (the mother of the Gracchi brothers) and her daughter Sempronia (who was married to Scipio) who were worried that the Gracchian law might be repealed or whether he committed suicide because he saw that he could not deliver on his promises. He added that &quot;[s]ome say that slaves under torture testified that unknown persons were introduced through the rear of the house by night who suffocated him, and that those who knew about it hesitated to tell because the people were angry with him still and rejoiced at his death.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Appian, Roman History, Book 13, The Civil Wars, 1.20&lt;/ref&gt; [[Plutarch]] wrote  that &quot;although Scipio Africanus died at home after dinner, there is no convincing proof of the manner of his end, but some say that he passed away naturally, being of a sickly habit, some that he died of poison administered by his own hand, and some that his enemies broke into his house at night and smothered him. And yet Scipio's dead body lay exposed for all to see, and all who beheld it formed therefrom some suspicion and conjecture of what had happened to it.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, Parallel Lives, The live of Romulus, 27.4-5&lt;/ref&gt; In another book Plutarch wrote &quot;no cause of such an unexpected death could be assigned, only some marks of blows upon his body seemed to intimate that he had suffered violence&quot; The heaviest suspicions fell on Fulvius Flaccus who &quot;that very day had reflected upon Scipio in a public address to the people.&quot; Caius Gracchus also came under suspicion. However, &quot;this great outrage, committed too upon the person of the greatest and most considerable man in Rome, was never either punished or inquired into thoroughly, for the populace opposed and hindered any judicial investigation, for fear that Caius should be implicated in the charge if proceedings were carried on.&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, Parallel lives, The live of Caius Gracchus, 10.4-5.&lt;/ref&gt; Gaius Papirius Carbo also came under accusation. During a trial [[Lucius Licinius Crassus]] accused Carbo of being a party in the murder of Scipio.&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, De Oratore, II.40&lt;/ref&gt; Ian Worthington rejects all these speculations and argues that Scipio Aemilianus died of natural causes.&lt;ref name =&quot;worthingtonref&quot;&gt;Worthington, I, ''The Death of Scipio Africanus'', Hermes, Vol. 117, No. 2 (1989), pp. 253–256 ( [http://www.jstor.org/pss/4476690 JSTOR reference])&lt;/ref&gt;

== The man==
Velleius Paterculus wrote that Scipio was &quot;a cultivated patron and admirer of liberal studies and of every form of learning, and kept constantly with him, at home and in the field, two men of eminent genius, Polybius and Panaetius. No one ever relieved the duties of an active life by a more refined use of his intervals of leisure than Scipio, or was more constant in his devotion to the arts either of war or peace. Ever engaged in the pursuit of arms or his studies, he was either training his body by exposing it to dangers or his mind by learning.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Velleius Paterculus, Roman History, 1.13.3&lt;/ref&gt; Polybius mentioned going to Africa with Scipio to explore the continent &lt;ref&gt;Polybius,The Histories,  34, 15.7, 16.2&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Gellius]] wrote that Scipio &quot;used the purest diction of any man of his time.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Gellius, Attic Nights, 2.20.4&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero cited him among the orators who were &quot;a little more emphatic than the ordinary, [but] never strained their lungsof shouted …&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Cicero De Oratore, 2.60&lt;/ref&gt; It seems that he had a good sense of humour and Cicero cited a number of anecdotes about his puns.&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, De Oratore, 2.61, 64, 65, 66, 69&lt;/ref&gt; He is also a central character in Book VI of Cicero's [[De re publica]], a passage known as the [[Somnium Scipionis]] or &quot;Dream of Scipio.&quot;

Culturally, Scipio Aemilianus was both progressive and conservative. He was the patron of the so-called [[Scipionic circle]], a group of 15 to 27 philosophers, poets, and politicians, Besides Roman satirists and comedy writers such as [[Lucilius]] and [[Terence]], there were Greek intellectuals, such as the scholar and historian Polybius and the Stoic philosopher [[Panaetius]]. Hence, Scipio had a [[Philhellenism|philhellenic]] disposition (love and admiration for Greek culture). Such disposition was criticised by Roman traditionalists who disliked the growing [[Hellenization|Hellenisation]] of Rome which, they thought was corrupting Roman culture and life though alien influences and advocated adherence to old Roman traditions and ancestral virtues and mores. Yet, Scipio was also a supporter of such traditions and mores. Gellius wrote that when he was censor, Scipio made a speech &quot;urging the people to follow the customs of their forefathers.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Gellius, Attic Nights, 4.20.10&lt;/ref&gt; He criticised several things which &quot;were done contrary to the usage of our forefathers,&quot; and found fault with adoptive sons being of profit to their adoptive father in gaining the rewards of paternity, and said: &quot;A father votes in one tribe, the son in another, an adopted son is of as much advantage as if one had a son of his own; orders are given to take the census of absentees, and hence it is not necessary for anyone to appear in person at the census.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Gellius, Attic Nights, 19.15&lt;/ref&gt;

Gellius wrote that after he was censor, Scipio was accused before the people by Claudius Asellius, a plebeian tribune, whom he had stripped of his knighthood during his censorship. He does not mention what the accusation was. Although under accusation, Scipio did not stop to shave and to wear white clothing and did not appear in the garb of those under accusation. He added that in those days noblemen started shaving in middle age.&lt;ref&gt;Gellius, Attic Nights, 3.4&lt;/ref&gt; The satirist Lucilius wrote a verse about the episode: &quot;Thus base Asellus did great Scipio taunt: Unlucky was his censorship and bad.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Gellius Attic Nights, 4.17.1&lt;/ref&gt;

Scipio Aemilianus will be forever be associated with the destruction of Carthage.

{{cquote|
''Scipio, when he looked upon the city as it was utterly perishing and in the last throes of its complete destruction, is said to have shed tears and wept openly for his enemies. After being wrapped in thought for long, and realizing that all cities, nations, and authorities must, like men, meet their doom; that this happened to [[Troy|Ilium]], once a prosperous city, to the empires of [[Assyrian Empire|Assyria]], [[Medes|Media]], and [[Greater Iran|Persia]], the greatest of their time, and to [[Kingdom of Macedonia|Macedonia]] itself, the brilliance of which was so recent, either deliberately or the verses escaping him, he said:'' 
:::''A day will come when sacred Troy shall perish,''
:::''And [[Priam]] and his people shall be slain.''
''And when Polybius speaking with freedom to him, for he was his teacher, asked him what he meant by the words, they say that without any attempt at concealment he named his own country, for which he feared when he reflected on the fate of all things human. Polybius actually heard him and recalls it in his history.''&lt;ref&gt;Polybius 38.22 ''[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Polybius/38*.html The Fall of Carthage]''&lt;/ref&gt; }}

==See also==
*[[Scipio–Paullus–Gracchus family tree]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

==References==

===Ancient sources===
* Appian, ''Roman History'', Book 6, ''The Wars in Spain'', Loeb Classical Library, Vol I, Books 1-8.1., Loeb, 1989; ISBN 978-0674990029
* Appian, ''Roman History'', Book 8 Part 1, ''The Punic Wars'', Loeb Classical Library, Vol III, Books 1-3.26., Loeb, 1989;  ISBN 978-0674990029
* Appian, ''Roman History'', Book 13, ''The Civil Wars'' (Book I) in Spain, Loeb Classical Library, Vol I, Books 1-81., Loeb, 1989; ISBN 978-0674990050
* Cicero, ''De oratore I-III'', Bloomsbury 3PL; new edition, 2013; ISBN 978-1853996313
* Florus ''Epitome of Roman History'', CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform, 2015; ISBN  978-1519684851
* Plutarch, ''Parallel Lives, The live of Caius Gracchus'', Plutarch's Lives (two volumes), Modern Library, 2001; Vol. 1 ISBN 978-0375756764; Vol 2 ISBN 978-0375756771
* Plutarch, ''Parallel Lives, The live of Romulus'', Plutarch's Lives (two volumes), Modern Library, 2001; Vol. 1 ISBN 978-0375756764; Vol 2 ISBN 978-0375756771
* Plutarch, ''Parallel Lives, The live of Tiberius Gracchus'', Plutarch's Lives (two volumes), Modern Library, 2001; Vol. 1 ISBN 978-0375756764; Vol 2 ISBN 978-0375756771
* Polybius, ''The Histories'', Oxford World's Classics, OUP Oxford, 2010; ISBN 978-0199534708
* Velleius Paterculus, Roman History, Hackett Publishing, 2011; ISBN 978-1603845915

===Secondary sources===
*Astin, A. E., ''Scipio Aemilianus'', Oxford University Press, 1967; ISBN 978-0198142577
*{{cite book |last=Person |first=Émile |date=1877 |title=De P. Cornelio Scipione Æmiliano Africano Et Numantino Thesim |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-E8JMwEACAAJ }}
* Chisholm, Hugh, ed. (1911). &quot;Scipio&quot;. Encyclopædia Britannica 24 (11th ed.). Cambridge University Press. pp.&amp;nbsp;406–407
*Warmington, B.H. ''Carthage, A History'', Barnes &amp; Noble,  New edition edition, 1994;ISBN 978-1566192101
*Ward, A. M., Heichelheim, F. M., and Yeo, C. A., ''A History of the Roman People'', Pearson; 3 edition, 1998. 158.ISBN 978-0138965983
* Worthington, I, ''The Death of Scipio Africanus'', Hermes, Vol. 117, No. 2 (1989), pp.&amp;nbsp;253–256 ( [http://www.jstor.org/pss/4476690 JSTOR reference])

{{s-start}}
{{succession box|title=[[List of Roman Republican consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Republic]]|before=[[Spurius Postumius Albinus Magnus]] and [[Lucius Calpurnius Piso Caesoninus (consul 148 BC)|Lucius Calpurnius Piso Caesoninus]]||after=[[Gnaeus Cornelius Lentulus]] and [[Lucius Mummius Achaicus]]|years=''with [[Gaius Livius Drusus]]''&lt;br /&gt; 147 BC}}
{{succession box|title=[[List of Roman Republican consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Republic]]|before=[[Quintus Calpurnius Piso]] and [[Servius Fulvius Flaccus]]||after=[[Lucius Calpurnius Piso Frugi (consul 133 BC)|Lucius Calpurnius Piso Frugi]] and [[Publius Mucius Scaevola]]|years=''with [[Gaius Fulvius Flaccus]]''&lt;br /&gt; 134 BC}}
{{s-end}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aemilianus, Scipio}}
[[Category:185 BC births]]
[[Category:129 BC deaths]]
[[Category:2nd-century BC Romans]]
[[Category:Roman Republican consuls]]
[[Category:Roman censors]]
[[Category:Cornelii|Scipio Aemilianus Africanus Numantinus, Publius]]
[[Category:Cornelii Scipiones|Publius Cornelius Scipio Aemilianus Africanus Numantinus]]
[[Category:Aemilii|Scipio Aemilianus Africanus Numantinus, Publius]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman generals]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman adoptees]]
[[Category:Third Punic War]]</text>
      <sha1>9zasgq5foh3z7perdvjfyh3vmmo74ve</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
