<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Shaista Khan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7186953</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745520297</id>
      <parentid>741712534</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-21T16:21:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jonathansammy</username>
        <id>12366037</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early life */ unreferenced tag added</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11103">{{refimprove|date=March 2012}}
{{infobox nobility 
|name=Mirza Abu Talib
|image=Nawab Sháyista Khán.jpg
|caption=Shaista Khan
|succession=[[Subahdar]] of [[Bengal]]
|predecessor=[[Mir Jumla II|Mir Jumla]]
|successor=[[Ibrahim Khan II|Ibrahim Khan]]
| reign = 1664 – 1688 as Bengal
1658-1669 as Khandesh(Deccan)
|father=[[Asaf Khan IV]]
|title = Amir-ul-Umara, Shaista Khan
|issue=Bujurg Umid Khan&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hossain |first1=AKM Yakub |last2=Haque |first2=AKM Khademul |year=2012 |chapter=Buzurg Umed Khan |chapter-url=http://en.banglapedia.org/index.php?title=Buzurg_Umed_Khan |editor1-last=Islam |editor1-first=Sirajul |editor1-link=Sirajul Islam |editor2-last=Jamal |editor2-first=Ahmed A. |title=Banglapedia: National Encyclopedia of Bangladesh |edition=Second |publisher=[[Asiatic Society of Bangladesh]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
Iran Dukht Rahmat Banu (Bibi Pari)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hossain |first1=AKM Yakub |last2=Chowdhury  |first2=AM |year=2012 |chapter=Bibi Pari |chapter-url=http://en.banglapedia.org/index.php?title=Bibi_Pari |editor1-last=Islam |editor1-first=Sirajul |editor1-link=Sirajul Islam |editor2-last=Jamal |editor2-first=Ahmed A. |title=Banglapedia: National Encyclopedia of Bangladesh |edition=Second |publisher=[[Asiatic Society of Bangladesh]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{History of Bangladesh}}
'''Mirza Abu Talib''' شاه خان, better known as '''Shaista Khan''' ({{lang-bn|শায়েস্তা খান}}) was a [[subahdar]] and a general in the [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] army. A maternal uncle to [[Aurangzeb|Emperor Aurangzeb]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Samaren Roy|title=Calcutta: Society and Change 1690–1990|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y-W6TjM2n1AC&amp;pg=PA52|accessdate=25 February 2012|date=May 2005|publisher=iUniverse|isbn=978-0-595-34230-3|pages=52–}}&lt;/ref&gt; he served as the Mughal governor of [[Bengal]] from 1664 to 1688, and was a key figure during the rule of his nephew. Under Shaista Khan's authority, the city of [[Dhaka]] and Mughal power in the province attained its greatest heights. One of this notable achievements was the [[Mughal conquest of Chittagong]]. In the year 1660, he was sent to participate in the struggle against the [[Maratha]] king [[Shivaji]]. However, he was defeated in a surprise attack and lost one of his sons. He then  left Pune and shifted his camp to Aurangabad.

==Early life==
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2016}}
Shaista Khan was of [[Persian people|Persian]] origin. His grandfather Mirza Ghias Beg Itimaduddaula and father Asaf Khan were the [[Vizier|wazirs]] of the Mughal Emperors [[Jahangir]] and [[Shahjahan]], respectively. Emperor Jahangir awarded the title of Shaista Khan to Mirza in recognition of his family's service and position in the Mughal court.He is said as being the brother of Shahjahan's wife though it is not clear if he was cousin or real.

Shaista Khan trained and served with the Mughal army and court, winning multiple promotions and being appointed governor of various provinces. He also developed a reputation as a successful military commander and grew close to the prince [[Aurangzeb]] when the duo fought against the kingdom of [[Golconda]]. Shaista Khan is also known as being very cruel, It is said that shaista khan also wanted to take control of the mughal empire{{Citation needed|date=November 2015}}. He couldn't succeed and then became a loyal follower and prominent personality in the court of aurangzeb and the [[Mughal Empire]] at that time.

==Confrontation with Shivaji==
{{main article|Battle of Chakan}}
After his accession to the throne and the dramatic death of [[Afzal Khan (general)|Afzal Khan]], Aurangzeb sent Shaista Khan as viceroy of the [[Deccan]] with a large army to defeat Shivaji. In January 1660 Shaista Khan arrived at [[Aurangabad, Maharashtra|Aurangabad]] and quickly advanced, seizing [[Pune]], the center of Shivaji's realm. He also captured the fort of [[Chakan, Maharashtra|Chakan]] and [[Kalyan, India|Kalyan]] and north [[Konkan]] after heavy fighting with the Maratha.&lt;ref name=&quot;Majumdar2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book |date=2007 |orig-year=First published 1974 |editor1-last=Majumdar |editor1-first=Ramesh Chandra |editor1-link=R. C. Majumdar |editor2-last=Pusalker |editor2-first=A. D. |editor3-last=Majumdar |editor3-first=A. K. |title=[[The History and Culture of the Indian People]] |volume=Volume VII: The Mughal Empire |edition= |location=Mumbai |publisher=Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|243, 259–60}} The Maratha were banned from entering the city of Pune and Mughal distance from the locals turned out to be an error. On the evening of April 5, 1663, a wedding party had obtained special permission for holding a procession. Shivaji and many of his nearly 400 men disguised as the bridegroom's procession members entered Pune. Others entered in small parties dressed as laborers and soldiers of Maratha generals serving under Shaista Khan. After midnight, they raided the Nawab's compound and then entered the palace in an attempt to assassinate Shaista Khan.

Shaista Khan was clearly unaware and unprepared. The Marathas broke into the courtyard of the palace and slaughtered the palace guards. Shaista Khan lost three fingers in a skirmish with Shivaji, while his son was killed in an encounter with the Marathas in the palace courtyard. Forty attendants were also killed. Taking advantage of the confusion and darkness, the Marathas escaped the palace and Pune, despite the widespread camping of Mughal forces. Shocked by the sudden and bold attack in Pune, Aurangzeb angrily transferred Shaista Khan to Bengal, even refusing to give him an interview at the time of transfer as was the custom.

==Subahdar of Bengal==
[[File:Charles D'Oyly06.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Construction of [[Saat Masjid]] is credited to Shaista Khan]]
[[File:The Small Kuttra with its enclosed Mosque, Dhaka (1817).jpg|thumb|right|250px|The [[Choto Katra]] with its enclosed Mosque, Dhaka (1817) by Charles D'Oyly's and constructed by Shaista Khan.]]
Shaista Khan was appointed the Subahdar of Bengal upon the death of [[Mir Jumla II]] in 1663. As governor, he encouraged trade with Europe, Southeast Asia and other parts of India. He consolidated his power by signing trade agreements with European powers. Despite his powerful position he remained loyal to Aurangzeb, often mediating trade disputes and rivalries. He banned the [[British East India Company]] from Bengal, sparking [[Child's War]] in 1686.

===Construction projects===
Shaista Khan encouraged the construction of modern townships and public works in Dhaka, leading to a massive urban and economic expansion. He was a patron of the arts and encouraged the construction of majestic monuments across the province, including [[mosque]]s, [[mausoleum]]s and palaces that represented the finest in Indo-Sarcenic and [[Mughal architecture]]. Khan greatly expanded [[Lalbagh Fort]], [[Chawk Mosque|Chowk Bazaar Mosque]], [[Saat Masjid]] and [[Choto Katra]]. He also supervised the construction of the mausoleum for his daughter Bibi Pari.

==Conquest of Chittagong==
[[File:ShaistaKhan.png|thumb|left|180px|Shaista Khan in later days]]
Upon his arrival in Bengal, Shaista Khan was immediately engrossed in putting down the rebellions of hill tribes. He foresaw a potent threat from the [[Rakhine State|Arakan]] Kingdom (in modern [[Myanmar]]), which had developed its military and naval strength. He immediately began developing the Mughal [[navy]], increasing its fleet to as many as 300 ships within a year. He also made strenuous diplomatic efforts to win the support of the [[Dutch East India Company]] as well as [[Portugal]], which was supporting Arakan with resources and troops. With active Dutch military support, Shaista Khan led Mughal forces on an assault on the island of Sandwip, which lay in Arakanese control. Shaista Khan gained a considerable advantage when a conflict erupted between the Arakanese and the Portuguese. By promptly offering protection and support, Khan sequestered the aid of the Portuguese against the Arakanese and Mughal forces succeeded in capturing the island in November 1665.

In December 1665 Shaista Khan launched a major military campaign against [[Chittagong]], which was the mainstay of the Arakenese kingdom. The imperial fleet consisted of 288 vessels of their own and about 40 vessels of the Ferinigis (Portuguese) as auxiliaries. Ibn Hussain, Shaista Khan's admiral, was asked to lead the navy, while the subahdar himself took up the responsibility of supplying provisions for the campaign. The overall command was given to Buzurg Ummed Khan, a son of Shaista Khan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Majumdar2007&quot; /&gt;{{rp|230}} The Mughals and the Portuguese held sway in the following naval battle. The conquered territory was placed under direct imperial administration. The name of Chittagong was changed to Islamabad and it became the headquarters of a Mughal [[faujdar]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Majumdar2007&quot; /&gt;{{rp|230}} Khan also re-asserted Mughal control over [[Cooch Behar]] and [[Kamarupa]].

Upon his victory against the Arakanese, he ordered the release of thousands of [[Bengali people|Bengali]] peasants being held captive by the Arakanese forces.

==Legacy==
 [[File:Dhaka Lalbagh Fort 5.JPG|thumb|200px|Pari Bibi's tomb inside [[Lalbagh Fort]] complex]]
In his late years, Shaista Khan left Dhaka and returned to [[Delhi]]. His legacy was the expansion of Dhaka into a regional centre of trade, politics and culture; a thriving and prosperous city from a small township. The [[Shaista Khan Mosque]] is a massive standing monument to Shaista Khan, built on his palace grounds. Incorporating unique elements of Bengali and Mughal architecture, it is a major tourist attraction and a valued historical monument protected by the [[Government of Bangladesh]] today.

==Legend==
The rule of Shaista Khan is, sometimes, considered as [[golden age]] of [[Bengal]]. It is said that eight 'mon' (around 295 [[kilogram]]) processed [[rice]] or 'chaal' could be bought with one [[taka]]. Still in [[Bangladesh]], cheap price conditions are known as Reign of Shaista Khan ('Shayesta Khan-r aamol').

==See also==
* [[List of rulers of Bengal]]
* [[History of Dhaka]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* {{cite book |last=Sarkar |first1=Jadunath |author-link1=Jadunath Sarkar |date=1948 |title=History of Bengal |volume=Vol. 2, Muslim period, 1200-1757 |location=Dacca |publisher=University of Dacca |page= }}
* {{cite book |last=Karim |first1=Abdul |date=1992 |title=History of Bengal: Mughal Period |volume= |publisher=University of Rajshahi |page= }}
* {{cite book |last=Duff |first1=James Grant |author-link1=James Grant Duff |date=1921 |orig-year=First published 1826 |url=http://ebook.lib.hku.hk/CADAL/B31419239V1/ |title=History of the Marhattas |volume=Vol. 1 |edition=Revised Annotated |location=London |publisher=Oxford University Press |page= }}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Khan, Shaista}}
[[Category:Medieval India]]
[[Category:History of Bangladesh]]
[[Category:Dhaka]]
[[Category:Indian Muslims]]
[[Category:Mughal Empire]]
[[Category:Subahdars of Bengal]]
[[Category:Mughal nobility]]</text>
      <sha1>2j3x3hdc2uen2wzwvezsegkrfvuap24</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
