<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sokol Baci</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42108957</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750575671</id>
      <parentid>743809597</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-20T16:36:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Early life */[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: a Catholic Church → a Catholic church using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17268">{{Use American English|date=May 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|name           = Sokol Baci Ivezaj /&lt;br&gt; Sokol Baci
|birth_date     = 1837
|death_date     = 1920
|birth_place    = [[Gruda (tribe)|Gruda]], [[Sanjak of Scutari]], [[Ottoman Empire]] (now [[Montenegro]])
|death_place    = [[Shkodër]], [[Albania]]
|place of burial  = Gruda
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|image          = Sokol_Baci.jpg
|nickname       = 
|allegiance     = {{flag|Ottoman Empire}} (before 1870s–1877)&lt;br&gt;Albanian League (1878-1884)&lt;ref&gt;AMAE ,CPC ,Konsullata e Frances  në Shkoder vëll. 21 ,fl.350r-351v.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Principality of Montenegro}}(1884–1913)&lt;br&gt;Northern Albanian (Malissor) tribes (1837-1920)
|serviceyears   = 1870s–1913
|rank           = [[Commander]] (bajraktar)&lt;br&gt;Brigadier-general (Montenegro)&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt;
|commands       = Gruda clan&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} Abdul Hamid's Albanian guard (before 1876)&lt;br&gt;Scutari (1913–)
|battles        = [[Albanian Revolt of 1911]]
|awards         = 
|religion       = Roman Catholic
}}
'''Sokol Baci'''{{Cref2|a}} (1837–1920) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Burzan|first=Danilo|title=Podgoricki Toponimi i Znamenja|location=Podgorica}}&lt;/ref&gt;was the chief of the [[Gruda (tribe)|Gruda]], a northern Albanian tribe in the vicinity of [[Podgorica]] (now [[Montenegro]]). Originally, he had served the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman sultan]] in his personal guard, but switched sides after he was maltreated, and fought the Ottoman forces in the [[Sanjak of Scutari]]. After his clan was defeated and subjugated, he was exiled and sought refuge in Montenegro, even though he had earlier fought against them in the 1870s, and lived in [[Podgorica]] beginning in approximately 1884. Prince [[Nicholas I of Montenegro]] recognized his status and employed him. He was one of the leaders of the [[Albanian Revolt of 1911]], alongside chiefs such as [[Ded Gjo Luli]], [[Mehmet Shpëndi]], [[Mirash Luca]] and [[Luigj Gurakuqi]]. In 1912, the entire tribes of Gruda and [[Hoti (tribe)|Hoti]], along with major portions of the [[Kastrati]], [[Shkreli (tribe)|Shkreli]], and [[Klimenti]] tribes, backed Montenegro during the [[Balkan Wars]]. In 1913, he was appointed commander of [[Shkodër|Scutari]] by King [[Nicholas I of Montenegro]], where he lived until his death in 1920.

==Life==

===Early life===
Sokol Baci Ivezaj was the son of Bac, hence his most commonly used name is (''Sokol Baci''), and he belonged to the Precaj family of the Ivezaj brotherhood in Gruda.&lt;ref name=Anali-448&gt;{{cite book|title=Anali Pravnog fakulteta u Beogradu|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=v6seAQAAIAAJ|year=1955|publisher=Pravni fakultet|page=448|quote=Пуно име грудског главара који је давао одговоре капетану Лазо- вићу гласи: Сокол Бац Прецај Ивезић Вуксановић (Вуксангељовић) Груда. Шта ова имена уствари означују? Сокол је лично име и у кући оца му Баца он ће бити означаван само по личном имену — Сокол, изван куће он је у роду Сркол Бац, ван рода зову га Сокол Бац Прецај (Прецај је један од родсва у братству), изван свога братства [...]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ivezaj brotherhood claimed they were descendants of Iveza, a son of a certain Vuksan Gela (also spelled Vuksan Gelja), who allegedly came from Suma, below [[Shkodër]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Petrović1941&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Mihailo Petrović|title=Đerdapski ribolovi u prošlosti i u sadašnjosti|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-PYMAQAAMAAJ|year=1941|publisher=Izd. Zadužbine Mikh. R. Radivojeviča|pages=47–48|quote=Ивезићи}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a youth, Sokol was taken by the Ottoman authorities to be trained and raised in Istanbul.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}} Due to his intelligence and athletic abilities, Sokol was selected to attend the military academy at the [[University of Sorbonne]] in Paris, France.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}} As a result of the many battles he fought for the Ottomans, he was eventually selected, along with five other young men of high standing, for the personal bodyguard of the Sultan.{{citation needed|date=March 2014}} In 1877, during the [[Serbo-Turkish War (1876–78)|Serbo-Turkish]] and [[Russo-Turkish War (1877–78)|Russo-Turkish]] Wars, while on leave at home, the order came for the disarming of the northern Albanian tribes.&lt;ref name=Wyon-314&gt;Wyon 1903, p. 314&lt;/ref&gt; The Gruda refused to obey, and refusing to be a traitor to his people, he led his clan in battle against Ottoman forces.&lt;ref name=Wyon-314/&gt; He managed to behead two high Ottoman officers, however, the clan was defeated, and he was forced to flee.&lt;ref name=Wyon-315&gt;Wyon 1903, p. 315&lt;/ref&gt;
 [[File:Sokol Baci Ivezić.jpg|thumb|Sokol Baci in his middle years.]]
He became a fugitive and outlaw, in exile in Montenegro, against whom he had earlier fought against in the 1870s.&lt;ref name=Wyon-315/&gt; He took refuge with his wife's tribe in [[Zatrijebač]], which had been annexed by the [[Principality of Montenegro]] after the [[Montenegrin–Ottoman War (1876–78)|Montenegrin–Ottoman War]]. On September 21, 1879, Sokol Baci, along with the other chiefs of the Hoti and Gruda, submitted a memorandum to the Great Powers requesting that their land not be ceded to Montenegro.&lt;ref&gt;AMAE ,CPC ,Konsullata e Frances  në Shkoder vëll. 21 ,fl.350r-351v.&lt;/ref&gt;{{verification needed|date=March 2014}} [[Nicholas of Montenegro|Prince Nicholas of Montenegro]] recognized him, gave him a house and land, and employed him in the Montenegrin government for northern Albanian affairs. After 1883, Prince Nicholas' diplomacy with the Malissori mainly went through Sokol Baci.&lt;ref name=Stojancevic&gt;{{cite book|author=Vladimir Stojančević|title=Srbija i Albanci u XIX i početkom XX veka: ciklus predavanja 10-25. novembar 1987|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RrVBAAAAYAAJ|year=1990|publisher=Srpska akademija nauka i umetnosti|pages=165–6, 183|quote=Sokol Baco}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Montenegrin document, dated November 1891, with a list of Herzegovinian and Albanian leaders, showed that Sokol Baci received the largest payment from the Montenegrin government: 540 florins and 967 measures of flour annually for his service.&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; In mid-July 1902, Sokol Baci gave a list to Prince Nicholas of Malissori chieftains and their escorts, who were given 1,190 florins on the Prince's order.&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; Sokol Baci financed the building of a Catholic church in Podgorica in 1904. That Church was destroyed during the WWII bombing of Podgorica in may of 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Burzan|first=Danilo|title=Podgoricki Toponimi i Znamenja|location=Podgorica}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sokol Baci returned briefly to Gruda upon the [[Young Turk]] regime's accession to the Ottoman government in 1908, but problems arose and he returned to [[Podgorica]].{{citation needed|date=May 2014}}

[[File:Sokol_Baci2.jpg|thumbnail|Sokol Baci (1902)]]

==1911–13==
{{main|Albanian Revolt of 1911}}

Among the leaders of the [[Albanian Revolt of 1911]], who had turned their weapons and clans on the Ottomans, was &quot;... the intelligent Sokol Baci&quot;&lt;ref name=Fishta&gt;Gjergj Fishta, 2006, ''The Highland Lute'', I.B. Tauris, Canto 28&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=March 2014}} (from Gruda).&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; Other leaders included: [[Mirash Luca]] (from Kastrati);&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; [[Ded Gjo Luli]] (from Hoti);&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; [[Ton Nika]] (from Shkreli);&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; [[Mehmet Shpendi]] (from Shala);&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; [[Ljub Mark Gjeloshi]], [[Mirash Pali]] and [[Franjo Pali]] (from Selce)&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; and also intellectual [[Luigj Gurakuqi]], among others.&lt;ref name=Fishta/&gt;{{page needed|date=March 2014}} A previously classified intelligence document from the British Foreign Affairs indicates that Sokol Baci along with [[Ded Gjo Luli]] and [[Mirash Luca]] were the principal instigators of the [[Albanian Revolt of 1911]].  It describes Sokol Baci as &quot;a man of some culture and very considerable intelligence&quot;.  During the [[Albanian Revolt of 1911]] &quot;he organized with considerable skill the service of supplies to the insurgents&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite book|last=Bourne|first=Kenneth|title=British Documents on Foreign Affairs|year=1989|publisher=University Publications of America|volume=15|pages=511-}}&lt;/ref&gt; To Sokol, much respected by the tribesmen, Nikola entrusted the task
of inducing the Albanian Catholics to migrate in numbers into Montenegro, promising them that if they would revolt against the Turks their wives and children should have shelter and protection till their land was freed from the Turks, and that they should receive sufficient arms and ammunition. Nikola himself promised independence to the tribesmen. Sokol was a simple-minded old fellow. Bitterly did he and his family repent later of the way they had let themselves be made cat's paws of.&lt;ref name=&quot;Durham 1920&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Durham|first=Edith|title=Twenty years of Balkan Tangle|year=1920|publisher=George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd., London|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Grece Memorandum Copy.jpg|thumbnail|Copy of the Grece Memorandum (1911) with Sokol Baci as the lead signatory]]
[[File:Grece Plaque.jpg|thumbnail|Memorial plaque of the [[Gërçe Memorandum]], in Gërçe, Albania]]
On June 24, 1911, the Ottoman minister to Montenegro, [[Saddridin Bey]], came to negotiate with the Malissori, and promised an extension of the armistice and an increase of compensation money; Sokol Baci, however, urged the Malissori to not surrender, saying, &quot;Where is the European guarantee?&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pearson2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Owen Pearson|title=Albania in the Twentieth Century, A History: Volume I: Albania and King Zog, 1908-39|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3_Sh3y9IMZAC&amp;pg=PA19|date=22 July 2005|publisher=I.B. Tauris|isbn=978-1-84511-013-0|pages=19–}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1912, the tribes of Gruda and [[Hoti (tribe)|Hoti]] were allied with Montenegro, while support also came from the greater parts of the [[Kastrati (tribe)|Kastrati]] and [[Shkreli (tribe)|Shkreli]] tribes, as well as a part of the [[Klimenti]] tribe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Srpski etnografski zbornik|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aw0mAQAAIAAJ|year=1923|publisher=Akademija|page=111|quote=Груде и Хоти су били уз Црну Гору, па онда већи дио Кострата и Шкреља, и један дио Кли- мената. Тиме је, да је било такта у команди црногорске војске, био олакшан напад и заузеће Скадра, и да се радило }}&lt;/ref&gt;

1912 dawned ominously. Montenegro worked ceaselessly to rouse the Maltsors, promising them that they should receive sufficient arms and, this time, gain freedom. It is pathetic to note that the luckless Albanians at first believed that the Serbs and Montenegrins spoke truth when they said the war was in order to liberate their brethren. That whole districts of solid Albanian population would be seized, did not occur to them. Later, they found their mistake.&lt;ref name=&quot;Durham 1920&quot;/&gt;
During her war correspondence in the Winter of 1913, Edith Durham details her conversation with Sokol Baci and his son, Kole Sokoli, who stated that they were fighting to free Albania from the Ottomans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Durham|first=Edith|title=The Struggle for Scutari|year=1914|publisher=E. Arnold|location=London|page=215}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the Montenegrin conquest of [[Shkodër|Scutari]] (1913), Nicholas I appointed Sokol Baci the commander (vojvoda) and brigadier of Scutari. When congratulated on his appointment, Sokol replied, &quot;He who does not see through the screen, may his eyes fall out!&quot; On May 26, 1913, 130 leaders of the Gruda, Hoti, Kelmendi, Kastrati and Shkreli sent a petition to [[Cecil Burney]] in Shkodër against the incorporation of their territories into Montenegro.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pearson2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Pearson|first=Owen|title=Albania in the twentieth century: a history|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3_Sh3y9IMZAC&amp;dq=Kelmendi+%2B+nikola&amp;q=Kelmendi#v=snippet&amp;q=Kelmendi&amp;f=false|accessdate=18 November 2011|year=2004|publisher=I.B. Tauris|isbn=978-1-84511-013-0|page=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sokol broke ties with Nicholas I and lived in Shkodër for the remainder of his life. On November 14, 1918, [[Luigj Gurakuqi]], [[Anton Harapi]] and [[Gjergj Fishta]] led the leaders of the Hoti and Gruda on a march from Montenegro to Shkodër, where they submitted a memorandum to the French Colonel, Bardy de Fourton.  The memorandum was addressed to the Ministers of Foreign Affairs in Washington, London, Paris and Rome requesting that Hoti and Gruda be united with Albania.  The Memorandum was signed by the Chiefs of Gruda, including Sokol's closest cousins, Dede Nika Ivezaj, Zef Martini Ivezaj, Mirash Hasi Ivezaj and Marash Pllumi Ivezaj.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harapi|first=Anton|title=Andrra e Pretashit|year=2008|publisher=Botime Françeskane|location=Shkodër}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
English traveller and [[albanophile]], [[Edith Durham]], was on very close terms with Sokol Baci.  In her book ''The Struggle for Scutari'', she explained:

{{quote|Sokol Baci, for whom, though he is now blamed alike by Montenegrin and Albanian, I have both esteem and respect. He acted as best he knew, according to his dim lights, and believed that he was acting for the good of his country. A burly figure, in full Albanian dress, and with great white mustachios like walrus tusks. Chief of the Gruda tribe, in his young days he was one of Abdul Hamid's famous Albanian guard, but he left it owing to the way the Turks maltreated his country, and fell, therefore, upon evil times. After the war of 1876-77 he sided with the party which wished for free Albania, and in consequence was forced to flee for his life. Hunted like wild beasts, he and his wife took refuge with his wife's tribe, Triepshi, which was then annexed by Montenegro as part of the spoils of war, searched for by both Montenegrins and Turks. Finally, King Nikola, recognizing his value as an influential chieftain, gave him a house and land and employed him largely for Albanian affairs. Sokol served him with doglike fidelity and touching faith, but never forgot his ancestral home across the border. When the Young Turk regime started, he hoped to return to it, but a short visit showed him that was impossible, and he returned to Podgoritza, to play an important part in the drama of the next few years. Poor Sokol! he was used as a cat's-paw. But I believe that he acted in perfect good faith.&quot;&lt;ref name=Durham-34&gt;{{cite book|last=Durham|first=Edith|title=The Struggle for Scutari|year=1914|publisher=London : E. Arnold|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Annotations==
{{Cnote2 Begin|liststyle=upper-alpha}}
{{Cnote2|a|His full name which he gave to captain Lazović was: '''Sokol Bac Precaj Ivezić Vuksanović (Vuksangeljović) Gruda'''.&lt;ref name=Anali-448/&gt; Another source wrote his name as '''Sokol Rac Grcaj Vezirić Vuksangeljović'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Prilozi proučavanju jezika|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=juIKAQAAMAAJ|year=1988|publisher=Katedra za južnoslovenske jezike Filozofskog fakulteta|page=106|quote=Сокол Рац Грцај Везирић Вуксангељовић}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other spellings of his short name include '''Sokol Baca''' (Сокол Баца), '''Sokol Baco''',&lt;ref name=Stojancevic/&gt; '''Sokol Batzi''', etc. In Austrian documents, he is known as '''Nikola Bacci'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skendi1967&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Stavro Skendi|title=The Albanian national awakening, 1878-1912|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qmm4AAAAIAAJ|year=1967|publisher=Princeton University Press|page=449|quote=The man used as intermediary in this offer was Sokol Baci (in Austrian documents, Nikola Bacci), Albanian chieftain of the clan of Grade, who at the time was in the service of Montenegro.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''sokol'' means &quot;falcon&quot; in Slavic languages.&lt;ref name=&quot;ComrieCorbett2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Bernard Comrie|author2=Greville G. Corbett|title=The Slavonic Languages|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uRF9Yiso1OIC&amp;pg=PA539|year=2002|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-415-28078-5|pages=539–}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Cnote2 End}}

==See also==
{{commons category}}
*[[Tringe Smajl Martini]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Sources===
*{{cite book|last=Wyon|first=Reginald|title=The Land of the Black Mountain|year=1903|publisher=London, Methuen and co.|chapter=8|pages=312–16}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Baci, Sokol}}
[[Category:20th-century Albanian military personnel]]
[[Category:Ottoman rebels]]
[[Category:Activists of the Albanian National Awakening]]
[[Category:Ottoman Albanians]]
[[Category:People of the Principality of Montenegro]]
[[Category:People from Podgorica]]
[[Category:Montenegrin people of Albanian descent]]
[[Category:Montenegrin Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Albanian Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Malsorë]]
[[Category:1837 births]]
[[Category:1920 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Scutari Vilayet]]</text>
      <sha1>0oevnjt918idu6458vsezr1k0cwbydk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
