<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Speaking tube</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2949311</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742709744</id>
      <parentid>734081900</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-05T08:55:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Slippyd</username>
        <id>1041871</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Domestic use */Fully translate French caption in English, instead of the existing half-translation.  “Porte-voix” is a simple compund noun, easy to derive a literal translation for.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9466">{{Refimprove|date=July 2016}}
[[File:Voice tube.jpg|thumb|A speaking tube in use on a United States Navy [[Landing Craft Utility]] (2005)]]
A '''speaking tube''' or '''voicepipe''' is a device based on two [[cone (geometry)|cone]]s connected by an [[air]] pipe through which [[Speech communication|speech]] can be transmitted over an extended distance. While its most common use was in intra-[[ship]] communications, the principle was also used in affluent{{vague|date=November 2013}} homes and offices of the 19th century, as well as expensive {{vague|date=November 2013}} [[automobiles]], military [[aircraft]], and even [[locomotive]]s. For most purposes, the device was outmoded by the [[telephone]] and its widespread adoption. This device was also known as a &quot;[[megaphone]]&quot;, but that use has since become superseded.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

==Design==
[[File:1910 aircraft intercom - Two tubes for duplex send and receive.jpg|thumb|''[[Le Petit Journal (newspaper)|Le Petit Journal]]'', 21 August 1910.  French air-force ready to deter hostile advances along the eastern frontier, and equipped with intercom - two speaking tubes for full duplex send and receive.]]
Early voicepipes consisted of two cones, of [[wood]] or [[metal]], one end shaped to fit the speaker's mouth, connected to the other which was flared to amplify the sound (specifically to match the [[Impedance matching#Acoustics|impedance of the tube]] to that of the open room). Later designs of the voicepipe inserted a removable cork-mounted whistle, which could be sounded by blowing into the tube from the other end. On naval vessels, this created a distinctive sound associated with urgent intra-ship communication on old warships. The sound of the whistle would summon the listener, who would remove the whistle and answer the call.

Voice pipes could be used over distances as long as {{convert|300|ft|m|-1}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;museumretro&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.aqpl43.dsl.pipex.com/MUSEUM/COMMS/voicepipe/voicepipe.htm | title=Voicepipes and Speaking-Tubes | publisher=The Museum of Retro-Technology | date=March 15, 2010 | accessdate=October 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, very long speaking tubes might use an electrical signalling device to indicate a call, as the large volume of air in the pipe would make it difficult to blow with enough pressure to sound a whistle at the far end.&lt;ref name=&quot;museumretro&quot; /&gt; Despite this, a pipe with a larger internal diameter was desirable for longer runs as the signal loss is inversely proportional to the pipe's cross-sectional area.&lt;ref name=&quot;museumretro&quot; /&gt;

Voicepipes have no [[switch]]ing mechanism and so, to provide multiple destinations, separate voicepipes with dedicated transit pipes have to be provided between all pairs of desired endpoints.

The technology continues to be used into the electronic age due to its reliability and low cost. Voice pipes are unaffected by a complete electrical power loss or by an [[electromagnetic pulse]]. Warships built as late as the 1950s continued to incorporate voicepipes alongside more advanced technology.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

==Maritime use==

Voice pipes, the maritime term, served to transmit reports from lookout positions aloft to the deck and from the bridge to the steering position and [[engine room]]. These were somewhat larger in diameter than the domestic version and were often covered in sound absorbent material to increase their efficiency. About 1780, one captain removed a canvas voice pipe installed by an [[Richard Hall Gower|imaginative midshipman]] saying he was sure the topmen would &quot;use it for an improper purpose&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gower&quot;&gt;Pseudo. 'Suffolk Coast' (1933). ''Memories of an Old Ipswich Mariner'' Capt. R. H. Gower. Suffolk Chronicle 2 December.&lt;/ref&gt;

Copper voice pipes were being fitted to British two and three-deck warships as early as 1803. A notable use was on board [[HMS Victory|HMS ''Victory'']] at the [[Battle of Trafalgar]] in 1805. ''Victory's'' [[ship's wheel]] was shot away early in the battle. A voice tube was then used to carry steering orders from the [[quarterdeck]] down three decks, to where a gang of sailors operated the ship's [[tiller]] directly using ropes and pulleys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=HMS Victory | publisher=Haynes | author=Goodwin, Peter | year=2012 | pages=69 | isbn=9780857330857}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One disadvantage of voice pipes is that they may breach the integrity of watertight spaces. This led to the introduction of shut-off valves on both ends of voicepipes to prevent water from a flooded compartment from entering other compartments via its voicepipes.

Permanently fitted, rigid voice pipes are still in use and are generally covered with heavy lids to avoid ingress of water. The speaker has to place his mouth in the &quot;horn&quot; or bell-shaped end of the pipe and the receiver has to 'bend an ear' to hear what is being said.

Voice pipes have generally been replaced by [[sound powered telephone]]s. Even on modern ships, however, they may still be found linking wheelhouse and binnacle for communication of magnetic compass heading to the helmsman in the event of a blackout.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

==Domestic use==
[[File:Office speaking tubes 1903.jpg|thumb|right|An office in 1903, showing speaking tubes hanging on the end of a desk]]
[[File:Parlophone pneumatique.jpg|thumb|190px|&lt;center&gt;Domestic speaking tube on the sidewalk end. Brussels,(2014) Caption is ''Please listen to the voice-gateway''.]]

In domestic applications, voicepipes were smaller and referred to as &quot;speaking tubes&quot;. The ends of the tube were often flexible for convenience of use. The speaking tube supplemented the array of remotely controlled [[hand bell]]s that were operated in the upstairs rooms and rang in the servant's quarters in even modest houses in the 19th century.  The phrase &quot;get on the horn&quot; and &quot;give him a blow&quot; as well as the use of &quot;blower&quot; as a synonym for &quot;telephone&quot; are generally accepted as having their origin in this feature of speaking tubes.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

Speaking tubes were employed in some offices, with whistles at either end and were therefore also known as '''whistling tubes'''.&lt;ref&gt;http://familytreemaker.genealogy.com/users/w/a/r/Silas-j-Ward/BOOK-0001/0003-0010.html&lt;/ref&gt; Several speaking tubes could be hung from the edge of a desk to communicate with different locations.

Speaking tubes were also used in fine automobiles such as the 1927 Rolls Royce Phantom, allowing communication between the separate passenger and driver's compartments when desired.

==Gosport tube==
A 'Gosport Tube' was a voice tube used by flight instructors in the early days of military aviation to give instructions and directions to their students. It was invented by flying instructor [[Robert Raymond Smith-Barry]] at the School of Special Flying he opened at [[Gosport]] in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;Vincent Orange, &quot;Barry, Robert Raymond Smith- (1886–1949)&quot;, ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'', Oxford University Press, 2004 [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/72242 accessed 12 September 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern usage==
Acoustic tube [[earphones|headphones]] (also called pneumatic earphones or air earphones) are used especially in [[two-way radio]]. These are useful because a clear tube can be used to hide the earphones. They are also sometimes used for the microphone on telephonists headsets and to provide music to patients undergoing an MRI scan, as it would be dangerous to use metal wiring in the scanner's magnetic field.

They were installed on the wards of UK hospitals for a time where the patient's 'radio' was built into the nurse call and lighting control unit. This unit contains an electromagnetic conventional speaker but from there to the patients ears was by tube - presumably so that the part contacting the patient could be easily cleaned. These systems are still in use.

Pneumatic [[intercom]]s can be applied to motorcycle helmets for pilot-passenger communication. Similar systems are common on [[ultralight aviation]] too. They are sometimes preferred over [[bluetooth]] or other radio technologies due to their simplicity and absence of batteries.

Up to the 2000s acoustic tubes were in use in some civil aircraft for movies, audio and other audio broadcasting in-flight entertainments.

The principle of the speaking tube can be found on certain [[playground]] equipment, which employs tubing connecting sound horns or other speaking boxes to allow voices to travel to separate points, for the amusement of the children.

==See also==
* [[Acoustic transmission line]]
* [[Headphones]]
* [[History of the telephone]]
* [[Intercom]]
* [[Pipe (fluid conveyance)]]
* [[Pneumatic tube]]
* [[Stethoscope]]
* [[Tin can telephone]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*{{Commonscat-inline|Speaking tubes}}
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o467FsFL2fM Michele Gervais, &quot;Empress of Ireland - Voice Tubes&quot;, ''Canadian Museum of Immigration at Pier 21'']
*[http://www.aqpl43.dsl.pipex.com/MUSEUM/COMMS/voicepipe/voicepipe.htm#voice Maritime voice pipes and terrestrial speaking tubes], The Amplifier Institute
*[http://www.aqpl43.dsl.pipex.com/MUSEUM/LOCOLOCO/quadruplex/quadrapl.htm Voicepipe usage proposed for a locomotive (never built)], The Amplifier Institute

{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

{{telecommunications}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Speaking Tube}}
[[Category:History of telecommunications]]
[[Category:Telephony]]</text>
      <sha1>jwjqdlae3ofh14h56qtugucync52ows</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
