<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>UAVs in the U.S. military</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>45755485</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744979957</id>
      <parentid>741720869</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-18T16:21:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>89.79.128.207</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Armed attacks by U.S. UAVs */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23614">As of January 2014, the [[U.S. military]] operates a large number of [[unmanned aerial system]]s: 7,362 [[RQ-11 Raven]]s; 990 [[AeroVironment Wasp III]]s; 1,137 [[AeroVironment RQ-20 Puma]]s; and 306 [[RQ-16 T-Hawk]] small UAS systems and 246 Predators and [[MQ-1C Grey Eagle]]s; 126 [[MQ-9 Reaper]]s; 491 [[RQ-7 Shadow]]s; and 33 [[RQ-4 Global Hawk]] large systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoD Buzz&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dodbuzz.com/2014/01/02/pentagon-plans-for-cuts-to-drone-budgets/|title=Pentagon Plans for Cuts to Drone Budgets|work=DoD Buzz|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The military role of unmanned aircraft systems is growing at unprecedented rates. In 2005, tactical- and theater-level unmanned aircraft alone had flown over 100,000 flight hours in support of [[Operation Enduring Freedom]] and [[Operation Iraqi Freedom]], in which they are organized under [[Task Force Liberty]] in Afghanistan and [[Task Force ODIN]] in Iraq. Rapid advances in technology are enabling more and more capability to be placed on smaller airframes, which is spurring a large increase in the number of Small Unmanned Aircraft Systems (SUAS) being deployed on the battlefield. The use of SUAS in combat is so new that no formal DoD wide reporting procedures have been established to track SUAS flight hours. As the capabilities grow for all types of UAS, nations continue to subsidize their research and development, leading to further advances and enabling them to perform a multitude of missions. UAS no longer only perform intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance missions, although this still remains their predominant type. Their roles have expanded to areas including [[electronic attack]], strike missions, [[suppression of enemy air defenses|suppression]] or destruction of enemy air defense, network node or communications relay, [[search and rescue|combat search and rescue]], and derivations of these themes. These UAS range in cost from a few thousand dollars to tens of millions of dollars, with aircraft ranging from less than one pound to over 40,000 pounds.{{Citation needed|date=February 2013}}

==Classifications by the United States military==

{{main|U.S. Military UAV tier system}}
[[File:Group photo of aerial demonstrators at the 2005 Naval Unmanned Aerial Vehicle Air Demo.jpg|thumb|U.S. UAV demonstrators in 2005]]
The modern concept of U.S. military UAVs is to have the various aircraft systems work together in support of personnel on the ground. The integration scheme is described in terms of a &quot;Tier&quot; system and is used by military planners to designate the various individual aircraft elements in an overall usage plan for integrated operations. The Tiers do not refer to specific models of aircraft but rather roles for which various models and their manufacturers competed. The [[U.S. Air Force]] and the [[U.S. Marine Corps]] each has its own tier system, and the two systems are themselves not integrated.

==Use in the &quot;War on Terror&quot;==
{{see also|Drone strikes in Pakistan|Drone strikes in Yemen}}
When the Obama administration announced in December 2009, the deployment of 30,000 new troops in Afghanistan, there was already an increase of attacks by unmanned [[Predator UAV]]s against Taliban and al-Qaeda militants in Afghanistan and [[Federally Administered Tribal Areas|Pakistan's tribal areas]], of which one probably killed a key member of al-Qaeda. However, neither [[Osama bin Laden]] nor [[Ayman al-Zawahiri]] was the likely target, according to reports. According to a report of the [[New America Foundation]], armed UAV strikes had dramatically increased under President Obama&amp;nbsp;– even before his deployment decision. There were 43 such attacks between January and October 2009. The report draws on what it deems to be ''&quot;credible&quot;'' local and national media stories about the attacks. This can be compared to a total of 34 in all of 2008, which was President Bush's last full year in office. Between 2006 and 2009, UAV-launched missiles allegedly had killed between 750 and 1,000 people in Pakistan, according to the report. Of these, about 20 people were said to be leaders of al-Qaeda, Taliban, and associated groups. Overall, 66% to 68% of the people killed were militants, and 31% to 33% were civilians. U.S. officials disputed the percentage for civilians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Military/2009/1211/Drone-aircraft-in-a-stepped-up-war-in-Afghanistan-and-Pakistan|title=Drone aircraft in a stepped-up war in Afghanistan and Pakistan|author=The Christian Science Monitor|work=The Christian Science Monitor|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Air Force has recently begun referring at least to larger UAS like Predator, Reaper, and Global Hawk as Remotely Piloted Aircraft (RPA) to highlight the fact that these systems are always controlled by a human operator at some location.

===Armed attacks by U.S. UAVs===
[[MQ-1 Predator]] UAVs armed with [[AGM-114 Hellfire|Hellfire missiles]] have been used by the U.S. as platforms for hitting ground targets. Armed Predators were first used in late 2001 from bases in [[Pakistan]] and [[Uzbekistan]], mostly aimed at assassinating high profile individuals (terrorist leaders, etc.) inside Afghanistan. Since then, there have been many reported cases of such attacks taking place in Afghanistan, Pakistan, Yemen, and Somalia.&lt;ref name=&quot;SauerSchoernigKillerDrones&quot;&gt;Sauer, Frank/Schörnig Niklas, 2012: [http://sdi.sagepub.com/content/43/4/363.abstract Killer drones: The ‘silver bullet’ of democratic warfare?], in: ''Security Dialogue'' 43 (4): 363–380. Retrieved 1 September 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  The advantage of using an unmanned vehicle rather than a manned aircraft in such cases is to avoid a diplomatic embarrassment should the aircraft be shot down and the pilots captured, since the bombings take place in countries deemed friendly and without the official permission of those countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,177709,00.html|title=Shrapnel Points to Drone in Pakistan Attack|work=Fox News|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/predator-kills-important-alqaeda-leader-in-pakistan-0547/|title=Predator Kills Important al-Qaeda Leader in Pakistan|date=19 May 2005|work=Defense Industry Daily|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/7847008/|title=CIA drone said to kill al-Qaida operative - US news - Security - NBC News|work=msnbc.com|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080131.walq0131/BNStory/International/home|title=globeandmail.com: Al-Qaeda chieftain killed|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=|access-date=|accessdate=March 19, 2015|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080205092943/http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080131.walq0131/BNStory/International/home|archivedate=February 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Predator based in a neighboring Arab country was used to kill suspected [[al-Qaeda]] terrorists in [[Yemen]] on 3 November 2002. This marked the first use of an armed Predator as an attack aircraft outside of a theater of war such as Afghanistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fas.org/irp/program/collect/predator.htm|title=RQ-1 Predator Medium Altitude Endurance (MAE) UAV|publisher=Fas.org|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. has claimed that the Predator strikes killed at least nine senior al-Qaeda leaders and dozens of lower-ranking operatives, depleting its operational tier in what U.S. officials described as the most serious disruption of al-Qaeda since 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes1&quot;/&gt;  It was claimed that the Predator strikes took such a toll on al-Qaeda that militants began turning violently on one another out of confusion and distrust.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes1&quot;/&gt;  A senior U.S. counter-terrorism official said: &quot;They have started hunting down people who they think are responsible [for security breaches]. People are showing up dead, or disappearing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes1&quot;/&gt;

By October 2009, the CIA claimed to have killed more than half of the 20 most wanted al-Qaeda terrorist suspects in targeted killings using UAVs.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|series=Heard on Fresh Air from WHYY |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/transcript/transcript.php?storyId=113978637|author=Terry Gross, host |title=Jane Mayer: The Risks Of A Remote-Controlled War |publisher=NPR |date=21 October 2009 |accessdate=20 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By May 2010, counter-terrorism officials said that UAV strikes in the Pakistani tribal areas had killed more than 500 militants since 2008 and no more than 30 (5%) nearby civilians – mainly family members who lived and traveled with the targets.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes6&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/14/world/14awlaki.htm|title=U.S. Approval of Killing of Cleric Causes Unease - NYTimes.com|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=|access-date=|accessdate=March 19, 2015|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120430124804/http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/14/world/14awlaki.htm|archivedate=April 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Entous |first=Adam |url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/idUKTRE64H5U720100519?pageNumber=3 |title= How the White House learned to love the drone  |publisher=Reuters |date= 19 May 2010|accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  UAVs linger overhead after a strike, in some cases for hours, to enable the CIA to count the bodies and attempt to determine which, if any, are civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters1&quot;/&gt;  A Pakistani intelligence officer gave a higher estimate of civilian casualties, saying 20% of total deaths were civilians or non-combatants.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters1&quot;/&gt;

In February 2013, U.S. Senator Lindsey Graham stated that 4,756 people have been killed by U.S. UAVs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Terkel|first=Amanda|title=Lindsey Graham: Drone Strikes Have Killed 4,700 People|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/02/21/lindsey-graham-drone-strikes_n_2734133.html|publisher=Huffington Post|date=21 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[CIA]] officials became concerned in 2008, that targets in Pakistan were being tipped off to pending U.S. UAV strikes by Pakistani intelligence, when the U.S. requested Pakistani permission prior to launching UAV-based attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2009/mar/22/world/fg-pakistan-predator22|author=Greg Miller |title=U.S. missile strikes said to take heavy toll on Al Qaeda |work=Los Angeles Times  |date=22 March 2009 |accessdate=19 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Bush administration therefore decided in August 2008 to abandon the practice of obtaining Pakistani government permission before launching missiles from UAVs, and in the next six months the CIA carried out at least 38 [[Predator drone|Predator]] strikes in northwest Pakistan, compared with 10 in 2006 and 2007 combined.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes1&quot;/&gt;

One issue with using armed drones to attack human targets is the size of the bombs being used and the relative lack of discrimination of the {{convert|100|lb|abbr=on}} [[AGM-114 Hellfire|Hellfire]], which was designed to eliminate tanks and attack bunkers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=4649372&amp;c=FEA&amp;s=TEC|title=Smaller, Lighter, Cheaper : New Missiles Are 'Absolutely Ideal' for Irregular Warfare|publisher=Defensenews.com|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smaller weapons such as the [[Raytheon]] [[Griffin (missile)|Griffin]] and [[Small Tactical Munition]] are being developed as a less indiscriminate alternative,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/08/26/346610/auvsi-raytheon-designing-uav-specific-weapons.html|accessdate=19 December 2010|title=AUVSI: Raytheon designing UAV-specific weapons}}&lt;/ref&gt; and development is underway on the still smaller  [[US Navy]]-developed [[Spike (missile)|Spike missile]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aviationweek.com/aw/generic/story_generic.jsp?channel=dti&amp;id=news/DTI-UAVs.xml&amp;headline=Efforts%20Are%20Underway%20to%20Arm%20Small%20UAVs] {{dead link|date=September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The payload-limited [[MQ-1 Predator|Predator A]] can also be armed with six Griffin missiles, as opposed to only two of the much-heavier Hellfires.

===Public opinion in the US (military use)===
{{main|Public opinion about US drone attacks}}
In 2013, a [[Fairleigh Dickinson University]] poll found that 48% of American voters believe it is &quot;illegal for the U.S. government to target its own citizens living abroad with drone attacks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fairleigh Dickinson University's PublicMind. (7 February 2013) [http://publicmind.fdu.edu/2013/drone Public Say It's Illegal to Target Americans Abroad as Some Question CIA Drone Attacks] Press release.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the same poll, however, a majority of voters approved of the U.S. military and the CIA using UAVs to carry out attacks abroad “on people and other targets deemed a threat to the U.S.”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://publicmind.fdu.edu/2013/drone/ |title=Respondents Question CIA Drone Attacks |publisher=Publicmind.fdu.edu |accessdate=27 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a number of critics of the use of UAVs to track and kill terrorists and militants. A major criticism of drone strikes is that they result in excessive collateral damage. However, others maintain that drones &quot;allow for a much closer review and much more selective targeting process than do other instruments of warfare&quot; and are subject to Congressional oversight.&lt;ref name=&quot;etzioni2013&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Etzioni|first=Amitai|title=The Great Drone Debate|journal=Military Review|date=March–April 2013|url=http://icps.gwu.edu/files/2013/03/Etzioni_DroneDebate.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Like any military technology, armed UAVs will kill people, combatants and innocents alike, thus &quot;the main turning point concerns the question of whether we should go to war at all.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;etzioni2013&quot;/&gt;

==Infrastructure==
In 2012, the [[USAF]] trained more UAV pilots than ordinary [[jet fighter]] pilots for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.migflug.com/jetflights/uav-replace-fighter-jets.html|title=F-35 and F-22 over budget – drones to take over aerial warfare? » MiGFlug Blog|publisher=[[MiGFlug]]|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike other UAVs, the Predator was armed with [[Hellfire missiles]] so that it can terminate the target that it locates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carafano, J. 2007&quot;&gt;Carafano, J., &amp; Gudgel, A. (2007). The Pentagon’s robots: Arming the future [Electronic version]. Backgrounder 2093, 1-6.&lt;/ref&gt; This was done after Predators sighted [[Osama Bin Laden]] multiple times but could not do anything about it other than send back images. In addition, the Predator is capable of orchestrating attacks by pointing lasers at the targets.&lt;ref&gt;Singer, P. (2009b). Wired for war: The robotics revolution and conflict in the 21st century. New York: Penguin Group.&lt;/ref&gt; This is important, as it puts a robot in a position to set off an attack. Their overall success is apparent because from June 2005 to June 2006 alone, Predators carried out 2,073 missions and participated in 242 separate raids.&lt;ref&gt;Singer, P. (2009a). Military robots and the laws of war [Electronic version]. The New Atlantis: A Journal of Technology and Society, 23, 25-45&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to the Predator, which is remotely piloted via satellites, the [[Global Hawk]] operates virtually autonomously.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer&quot;&gt;Singer, Peter W. [http://www.brookings.edu/articles/2009/11_robotic_revolution_singer.aspx &quot;A Revolution Once More: Unmanned Systems and the Middle East&quot;], [http://www.brookings.edu/ The Brookings Institution], November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The user merely hits the button for ‘take off’ and for ‘land’, while the UAV gets directions via GPS and reports back with a live feed. Global Hawks have the capability to fly from San Francisco and map out the entire state of Maine before having to return.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer&quot; /&gt; In addition, some UAVs have become so small that they can be launched from one’s hand and maneuvered through the street.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer&quot; /&gt; These UAVs, known as [[RQ-11 Raven|Raven]]s, are especially useful in urban areas, such as Iraq, in order to discover insurgents and potential ambushes the next block up.&lt;ref&gt;Carafano, J., &amp; Gudgel, A. (2007). The Pentagon’s robots: Arming the future [Electronic version]. Backgrounder 2093.&lt;/ref&gt; UAVs are especially useful because they can fly for days at a time. Insurgents in the open for more than a few minutes at a time fear UAVs locating them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carafano, J. 2007&quot;/&gt;

In the U.S., thousands of civilian UAV operators work for contractors, piloting and maintaining UAVs.&lt;ref name=Economist20130606/&gt;  Up to four UAVs and about 400 to 500 pilot and ground support personnel are required for a single 24-hour-coverage combat air patrol (CAP).&lt;ref name=WashPost201311&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/drone-combat-missions-may-be-scaled-back-eventually-air-force-chief-says/2013/11/13/470deda4-4c97-11e3-b692-e722f1795169_story.html |title=Drone combat missions may be scaled back eventually, Air Force chief says |last=Whitlock |first=Craig |date=13 November 2013 |website=The Washington Post |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6LIn6oKFC |archivedate=21 November 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2011 study by the [[Brooks Air Force Base#Aerospace Medicine|Air Force School of Aerospace Medicine]] indicated that nearly 50% of spy UAV operators suffer from high stress.&lt;ref name=Economist20130606/&gt;  The president of a civilian UAV operators' union, the Association of Unmanned Operation (AUO), cited long working hours and decreasing wages as U.S. involvement in wars in Iraq and Afghanistan was reduced and as a result of the U.S. government's [[budget sequestration]].&lt;ref name=Economist20130606&gt;
{{cite news |url=http://www.economist.com/news/united-states/21580461-stressful-lives-drone-pilots-alone-joystick |title=Drone warfare: Alone with a joystick |last= |first= |date=6 June 2013 |website=The Economist |archiveurl= |archivedate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Given the increasing military use of cyber attacks against [[Microsoft]] software, the [[United States Armed Forces]] have moved towards [[Linux]] ground control software.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson, Iain. [http://www.theregister.co.uk/2012/06/08/us_navy_linux_drones/ &quot;US Navy buys Linux to guide drone fleet.&quot;] ''The Register'', 8 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leyden, John. [http://www.theregister.co.uk/2012/01/12/drone_consoles_linux_switch/ &quot;US killer spy drone controls switch to Linux.&quot;] ''The Register'', 12 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scale of use of UAVs by the U.S. military==
An August 2013, Brookings Institution study reported that in the U.S. Air Force there were approximately 1,300 remotely piloted aircraft (RPA) pilots, 8.5 percent of total Air Force pilots, up from 3.3 percent in 2008.&lt;ref name=Brookings201308/&gt;  The study indicated that the U.S. military's combat air patrol (CAP) daily missions requirement is growing at a faster pace than RPA pilots can be trained, with an attrition rate during RPA flight screening being three times that of traditional pilots and a 13% lower promotion rate to Major than other officers.&lt;ref name=Brookings201308&gt;
{{cite web |url=http://www.brookings.edu/~/media/research/files/papers/2013/08/06%20air%20force%20drone%20pilot%20development%20hoagland/manning%20unmanned%20force_final_08052013.pdf |title=Manning the Next Unmanned Air Force / Developing RPA Pilots of the Future |last=Hoagland |first=Bradley T. |date=August 2013 |publisher=Brookings Institution |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6J4Q3egdp |archivedate=22 August 2013 }} • Referenced by {{cite web |url=http://www.nbcnews.com/technology/air-force-wants-drone-pilots-incentives-lacking-says-report-6C10974055 |title=Air Force wants drone pilots, but incentives lacking, says report |last= Subbaraman |first=Nidhi |date=22 August 2013 |publisher=NBC News |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6J4TEckLL |archivedate=22 August 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of January 2014, the U.S. military operates a large number of unmanned aerial systems: 7,362 [[RQ-11 Raven]]s; 990 [[AeroVironment Wasp III]]s; 1,137 [[AeroVironment RQ-20 Puma]]s; and 306 [[RQ-16 T-Hawk]] small UAS systems and 246 Predators and [[MQ-1C Gray Eagle]]s; 126 [[MQ-9 Reaper]]s; 491 [[RQ-7 Shadow]]s; and 33 [[RQ-4 Global Hawk]] large systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoD Buzz&quot;/&gt;

As of mid-2014, the U.S. air force is training more drone pilots than fighter and bomber pilots combined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.economist.com/news/united-states/21604608-stressful-lives-chair-force-dilbert-war|title=Drone pilots: Dilbert at war - The Economist|work=The Economist|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==Research and development==
At the center of the American military's continued UAV research is the MQ-X, which builds upon the capabilities of the Reaper and Predator UAVs. As currently conceived, the MQ-X would be a stealthier and faster fighter-plane sized UAV capable of any number of missions: high-performance surveillance; attack options, including retractable cannons and bomb or missile payloads; and cargo capacity.&lt;ref&gt;Singer, Peter W. [http://www.brookings.edu/articles/2010/0517_robots_singer.aspx &quot;How the US Military Can Win the Robotic Revolution&quot;], [http://www.brookings.edu/ The Brookings Institution], 17 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Development costs for American military UAVs, as with most military programs, have tended to overrun their initial estimates.  This is mostly due to changes in requirements during development and a failure to leverage UAV development programs over multiple armed services. This has caused [[United States Navy]] UAV programs to increase in cost from 0% to 5%, while [[United States Air Force]] UAV programs have increased from 60% to 284%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gao.gov/products/GAO-09-520|title=U.S. GAO - Defense Acquisitions: Opportunities Exist to Achieve Greater Commonality and Efficiencies among Unmanned Aircraft Systems|publisher=Gao.gov|accessdate=8 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The USAF said in 2012, that it will focus development of UAVs to be collaboratively networked with manned aircraft in &quot;buddy attacks,&quot; while continuing to be able to fly as standalone systems.&lt;ref&gt;Majumdar, Dave. [http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/anti-accessarea-denial-challenges-give-manned-aircraft-edge-over-uavs-374745/ &quot;Anti-access/area denial challenges give manned aircraft edge over UAVs.&quot;] ''Flight Global'', 25 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. Defense Department's Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency ([[DARPA]]) planned in 2014 to award grants and contracts up to $5.5 million each, for its Fast Lightweight Autonomy Program (FLAP) program, which specifies UAVs capable of traveling 60 feet per second to include autonomy algorithms for quickly and autonomously navigating indoor obstacles and learning from past travels.&lt;ref name=WashPost20141230&gt;{{cite web |last1=Scola |first1=Nancy |title=DOD wants to build drones that can buzz into bad guys’ doorways |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-switch/wp/2014/12/30/dod-wants-to-build-drones-that-can-buzz-into-bad-guys-doorways/ |website=The Washington Post |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6VEmUMsR1 |archivedate=December 31, 2014 |date=December 30, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Civilian casualties from US drone strikes]]
* [[Use of UAVs by the CIA]]
* [[82d Aerial Targets Squadron]]
* [[Unmanned Aerial Vehicle Battlelab]], U.S. Air Force facility

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:American military aviation]]
[[Category:Unmanned aerial vehicles|United States]]</text>
      <sha1>tj4g9yiqt47jk1hnc4iux3hlyrk7a75</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
