<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Venezuela during World War II</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39726285</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748594803</id>
      <parentid>625765052</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-09T02:02:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jdaloner</username>
        <id>4460044</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Added manual sort key to one category tag.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12400">{{infobox
| above       = Venezuela during World War II
| abovestyle  = 
| image1      = [[File:Medina Angarita, NYC.jpg|230px]]
| caption1    = A floral offering in front of a [[Simón Bolívar]] statue in [[New York City]], during the official visit of Venezuela's President [[Isaías Medina Angarita]] (right) to the United States in 1944.
| label2      = Location
| data2       = [[Venezuela]]
| label3      = Date
| data3       = 1939–1945
| label4      = Events
| data4       = ''Koenigstein'' and ''Caribia''&lt;br&gt;–March 1939&lt;br&gt;Severing of relations&lt;br&gt;–December 31, 1941&lt;br&gt;The [[Attack on Aruba]]&lt;br&gt;–February 16, 1942&lt;br&gt;Declaration of war&lt;br&gt;–February 15, 1945
| label5      = 
| data5       = 
}}

The history of '''Venezuela during World War II''' is marked by dramatic change to the country's economy, military, and society. At the beginning of [[World War II]] in 1939, [[Venezuela]] was the world's leading oil exporter, and subsequently one of the main beneficiaries of the [[United States|American]] [[Lend-Lease]] programs. Economic assistance from the United States, as well a booming oil industry, led Venezuela to become one of the few [[Latin American]] countries that was able to finance its own modernization in the post-war era. Furthermore, through skillful diplomacy, Venezuela was able to gain territory, increase its share in oil profits, and also reduce its reliance on foreign oil companies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Leonard| first=Thomas M.| authorlink=|author2=John F. Bratzel | title=Latin America during World War II| publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield| series=| year=2007| doi=| isbn=0742537412}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;counterpunch.org&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | title=U.S. Fourth Fleet in Venezuelan Waters &gt;&gt; CounterPunch: Tells the Facts, Names the Names| work=| url=http://www.counterpunch.org/2008/05/24/u-s-fourth-fleet-in-venezuelan-waters/| accessdate=June 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Venezuela was officially neutral for most of the war, it secretly supported the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]], and eventually declared war on the [[Axis powers]] in February 1945, a few months before the end of the conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;counterpunch.org&quot;/&gt;

==History==

===The oil industry===
According to author Thomas M. Leonard, Venezuela's oil garnered &quot;intense interest&quot; from the Allies and the Axis, both before and during World War II. Thus, Venezuela's main strategic goal from 1939 to 1945 was to protect its oil from being seized by a belligerent nation. Closely related to this goal was the need to market oil, which had become the mainstay of the Venezuelan economy. Leonard says that the war could, ideally, have resulted in an &quot;economic boom&quot; if Venezuela could maintain a policy of strict neutrality and sell oil to both sides. However, neither the Axis or the Allies were likely to tolerate such a situation, and in the end, Venezuela sided with the Allies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;

Even though Venezuela was decidedly pro-Allied, the government attempted to increase its hold on the oil market, which was dominated by American-owned petroleum firms. One option was to nationalize the oil industry, like [[Mexico]] did in 1938. This option, however, was never seriously considered, because nationalizing the oil industry meant seizing American-owned oil, which would have likely resulted in a military intervention. Although Mexico's nationalization of its oil industry did not result in an American military intervention, just the possibility of one was enough to keep the Venezuelan government content with seeking a mere increase in its share of profits, rather than taking all of it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;

Subsequently, the United States, eager to maintain its access to the oil, agreed to increase oil revenues for Venezuela. Profits were split fifty-fifty between the Venezuelan government and the oil companies, such as [[Standard Oil]] and the British-owned [[Royal Dutch Shell|Shell Oil]]. As result, in 1944 Venezuela's oil income was 66% higher than it was in 1941, and by 1947 total income had increased 358%. This &quot;largesse,&quot; as Leonard calls it, allowed Venezuela to become one of the few Latin American countries that was able to finance its own modernization in the postwar era, unlike many of the other states in the region, which relied on American economic assistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;

===Axis influence===
Nazi efforts to increase their influence in Venezuela, and thus access Venezuelan oil, date back to 1933, when Arnold Margerie formed the Venezuelan Regional Group of the Nazi Party, or ''Grupo Regional de Venezuela del Partido Nazi''. After that, the Germans began &quot;courting&quot; the Venezuelan military through its military mission. On the &quot;cultural front,&quot; according to Leonard, General Wilhelm von Faupel, head of the [[Ibero-American Institute]], attempted to gain influence by sending his wife, Edith, to Venezuela to &quot;extol the virtues of [[fascism]].&quot; Germany was also active in countering American economic influence, by expanding its holdings in mining, agriculture, and railroading.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;

During the war, there were nearly 4,000 [[German Venezuelan#20th century|German immigrants]] residing in Venezuela. As result of which, there was fear among certain Allied leaders of a &quot;[[fifth column]]&quot; forming to commit [[sabotage]] and the like against the Venezuelan government or oil-related infrastructure. The nearby British, [[France|French]], and [[Netherlands|Dutch]] colonies also presented security concerns: If any were to fall under Axis control, they would certainly become bases for the interdiction of the [[Caribbean]] sea lanes, which carried Venezuela's crude oil to be refined in [[Aruba]], and thence to market. They could also be used as staging areas for the invasion of neighboring countries, or for [[commando]] operations to interrupt oil production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;

In 1938, the [[Venezuelan Navy]] purchased two [[Azio class]] [[minesweeper (ship)|minesweeper]]s from [[Kingdom of Italy|Fascist Italy]]. Moreover, trade with [[Empire of Japan|Imperial Japan]] reached an all-time high in 1939. After the war in [[Europe]] began in September 1939, and after [[President of Venezuela|President]] [[Eleazar López Contreras]] declared the country's neutrality, Venezuela continued to trade with Japan and Italy, but trade with Germany ceased due to the British [[blockade]]. It was because of these circumstances some observers concluded that Venezuela would join the Axis if it were forced to take sides. However, the fear of Venezuela aligning itself with Germany, or any of the other Axis powers, was mostly unwarranted, because the sentiment of your average Venezuelan was &quot;bitterly anti-German.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;counterpunch.org&quot;/&gt;

===The Venezuelan military===
When World War II began, the Venezuelan military was badly in need of modernization, and the United States was eager to help in return for Venezuela's support in the war. However, the United States was concerned about a possible enemy attack on Venezuela, in order to disrupt oil production, if it did openly join the Allied cause and declare war. As result, the Venezuelan government broke relations with the Axis powers on December 31, 1941, but it did not declare war until February 15, 1945, when the threat of an attack against the oil was gone. Therefore, the Venezuelan military never met the enemy on the battlefield, although a few Venezuelan merchant ships were sunk; the first of which occurred during the German [[attack on Aruba]] in February 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;counterpunch.org&quot;/&gt;

Because Venezuela was officially neutral for most of the war, the task of guarding the Venezuelan coast for enemy activity and escorting Venezuelan ships was left to the Americans. Accordingly, after the attack on Aruba, the [[United States Navy]] established the [[United States Fourth Fleet|Fourth Fleet]], which was responsible for countering enemy naval operations in the Caribbean and in the [[South Atlantic]]. The [[United States Army]] also sent aircraft and personnel to help protect the oil refineries and bolster the [[Venezuelan Air Force]]. To support the mission, Venezuela granted American ships and planes access to the country's ports and airstrips.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, pg. 118-124&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;counterpunch.org&quot;/&gt;

===''Koenigstein'' and ''Caribia''===
The SS ''Koenigstein'' and the SS ''Caribia'' were a pair of German [[steamboat]]s that were used to carry about 300 [[Jewish]] refugees from Europe to Venezuela between February and March 1939. The ''Koenigstein'', with eighty-six Jews on board, left Germany in January 1939 for the British colony of [[Trinidad]], but when it arrived, the British refused to accept the passengers because of a recent prohibition on the admission of refugees. As result, the ''Koenigstein'' sailed to [[Honduras]], but again the passengers were denied entry. With nowhere else to go, the ''Koenigstein'' then sailed for Venezuela, and arrived on February 17, 1939. The SS ''Caribia'', carrying 165 Jews, went through a very similar ordeal. After sailing to [[British Guiana]], [[Georgetown, Guyana|Georgetown]] authorities refused to allow the passengers to land, and so the ''Caribia'' sailed to Venezuela, arriving on March 16, 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caestecker, pg. 278&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=| first=| authorlink=| title=Refugees from Nazi Germany and the Liberal European States| publisher=Berghahn Books| series=| year=2010| doi=| isbn=1845455878}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;morasha.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | title=Morasha Magazine – Articles| work=| url=http://www.morasha.com.br/conteudo/artigos/artigos_view.asp?a=679&amp;p=4| accessdate=June 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jta.org1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | title=86 Allowed Temporary Stay in Venezuela| work=The Global Jewish News Source| url=http://www.jta.org/1939/02/17/archive/86-allowed-temporary-stay-in-venezuela| accessdate=June 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jta.org2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | title=165 Reich Refugees Find Haven in Venezuela| work=The Global Jewish News Source| url=http://www.jta.org/1939/03/16/archive/165-reich-refugees-find-haven-in-venezuela| accessdate=June 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At first, the Venezuelan government gave the refugees special permission to stay in the country temporarily, until new homes could be found for them in other Latin American countries, but they were banned from finding employment in any industry other than agriculture. Furthermore, the Venezuelan government made it clear that it would not accept any more refugees, unless they came through the proper channels. Later, President Contreras gave the refugees permission to remain in the country permanently. As result of which, the passengers of the ''Koenigstein'' and the ''Caribia'' became some of the founding members of Venezuela's [[History of the Jews in Venezuela|Jewish community]], as most Jewish emigration to Venezuela would occur after the war, in the 1950s and 1960s.&lt;ref name=&quot;morasha.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jta.org2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;luxner.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | title=A precarious democracy threatens Venezuelans — Jews and non-Jews – Luxner News Inc.| work=| url=http://www.luxner.com/cgi-bin/view_article.cgi?articleID=1127| accessdate=June 17, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Rio Chico, Miranda Venezuela 1940.jpg|[[Río Chico, Venezuela|Río Chico]] in [[Miranda, Venezuela]] in 1940.
File:Medina Angarita at U.S. Congress.jpg|President Isaías Medina Angarita speaking to the [[United States Congress]] in 1944.
File:Manifestación en Caracas Año 1945.png|Protesters in [[Caracas]] in 1945.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II|Venezuela}}

* [[Operation Bolivar|Operation ''Bolivar'']]
* [[American Theater (1939–1945)]]
* [[1945 Venezuelan coup d'état]]
* [[1948 Venezuelan coup d'état]]
* [[History of Venezuela]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Latin America during World War II}}
{{WWII history by nation}}
{{Venezuela topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:World War II, Venezuela during}}
[[Category:Military history of Venezuela]]
[[Category:Military history of the United States during World War II|Venezuela]]
[[Category:1939 in Venezuela]]
[[Category:1940s in Venezuela]]
[[Category:World War II by country|Venezuela]]
[[Category:Wars involving Venezuela]]</text>
      <sha1>l98ntrtre39hqq40tqua2sjw2x6dqwx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
