<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Walls of Amsterdam</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35880907</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749669338</id>
      <parentid>727950156</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-15T16:19:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster|Substing templates]]: {{ill}}. See [[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster]] for info.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18284">[[File:Cornelis anthonisz vogelvluchtkaart amsterdam.JPG|thumb|260px|The medieval city with its walls, gates and towers can be seen on this map by [[Cornelis Anthonisz.|Cornelis Anthoniszoon]] dating to 1538]]
[[File:Amsterdam1688.jpg|thumb|260px|The 17th-century walls with 26 bastions can be seen on this city map by  [[Frederik de Wit]]]]

The '''[[Defensive wall|walls]] of [[Amsterdam]]''' were built in the [[Middle Ages]] to protect the city against attack. The Medieval walls were replaced with a series of [[bastion]]s in the 17th century. In the 19th century, the walls were torn down and replaced with the [[Stelling van Amsterdam|Defence Line of Amsterdam]] (''Stelling van Amsterdam''), a fortification line which encircled Amsterdam at a distance from the city.

Remains of the Medieval and 17th-century defenses include the former city gates [[Waag (Amsterdam)|Waag]] and [[Munttoren]], as well as the defensive tower [[Schreierstoren]] and the watchtower [[Montelbaanstoren]]. 

== History ==
=== Earthen walls ===
Around the year 1300, an earthen wall had been erected behind the [[Nieuwendijk (Amsterdam)|Nieuwendijk]] dike. Traces of this wall were discovered during archeological excavations around [[Nieuwezijds Kolk]] in 1994. Following the {{Interlanguage link multi|Siege of Amsterdam (1303)|nl|3=Beleg van Amsterdam (1303)|lt=Siege of Amsterdam}} in 1303, Count [[William II of Holland]] withdrew the privilege of Amsterdam to have defenses, forcing the town to remove the wall.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot;&gt;[http://onsamsterdam.nl/tijdschrift/jaargang-2004/759-nummer-9-september-2004?start=1 Ernest Kurpershoek, &quot;De laatste stadswal van Amsterdam: Oude muur niet bestand tegen modern geschut&quot;, ''Ons Amsterdam'', nr. 9, September 2004] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

About 40 years later, around 1340, new walls were constructed, both along the western ''oudezijde'' (&quot;old side&quot;) and along the eastern ''nieuwezijde'' (&quot;new side&quot;) of the [[Amstel]] river. On either side of the town, a moat was dug, and a wall topped by a wooden [[palisade]] was then built on the inner side of the moat. When in 1385 new walls and moats were built beyond these original walls and canals, the existing walls became known as ''Achterburgwal'' (&quot;back wall&quot;) and the new walls were called ''Voorburgwal'' (&quot;front wall&quot;). This is how the canals {{Interlanguage link multi|Oudezijds Voorburgwal|nl}}, {{Interlanguage link multi|Oudezijds Achterburgwal|nl}}, [[Nieuwezijds Voorburgwal]] and {{Interlanguage link multi|Nieuwezijds Achterburgwal|nl}} got their name.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

The city walls had three [[city gate|gates]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;bma&quot;&gt;
[http://www.bma.amsterdam.nl/publish/pages/336948/aar_45_waag1.pdf &quot;De Sint Anthoniespoort en de stadsmuur: Archeologische Begeleiding De Waag, Nieuwmarkt (2007)&quot;. AAR (Amsterdamse Archeologische Rapporten) 45, 2010. Gemeente Amsterdam, Bureau Monumenten en Archeologie] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Sint Olofspoort|nl}} at the northern end of the [[Warmoesstraat]] street
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Haarlemmerpoort|nl|3=Haarlemmerpoort (Amsterdam)}} at the western end of the Nieuwendijk
* [[Bindwijkerpoort]] on the southern edge of the city, by [[Spui (Amsterdam)|Spui]]. 

[[File:Amsterdam Waag februari 2003.jpg|thumb|260px|The [[Waag (Amsterdam)|Waag]], originally the city gate Sint Antoniespoort]]
In 1425 the city expanded and a new moat was dug, which still exists as the [[Singel (Amsterdam)|Singel]], [[Kloveniersburgwal]] and {{Interlanguage link multi|Geldersekade|nl|3=Geldersekade (Amsterdam)}} canals. Along the inner side of the canal, an earthen wall was built with three gates: a new Haarlemmerpoort gate, the Sint-Antoniespoort (now the [[Waag (Amsterdam)|Waag]]), and the Regulierspoort (now the bottom half of [[Munttoren]] tower). &lt;ref name=&quot;bma&quot;/&gt;

=== Stone walls ===
After visiting Amsterdam in 1481, Emperor [[Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor|Maximilian I]] decreed that the town was to build stone walls to safeguard against attacks by the [[Guelders|Duchy of Guelders]] and the [[Bishopric of Utrecht]]. The city had to pay for the walls itself, and instituted a tax to fund the costly project. Construction started in 1482 and took about 20 years to complete, all in all.&lt;ref name=&quot;bma&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Schreiers2.jpg|thumb|260px|The [[Schreierstoren]] tower (left)]]
The end result was a brick wall, 5 to 6 metres high, supported by stone arches. The walls encircled the entire town, with the exception of the harbour front on the [[IJ (Amsterdam)|IJ]] bay along the northern side of the city. At regular intervals along the walls, a number of semicircular defensive towers were built. One of these towers is still standing, the [[Schreierstoren]], built around 1487.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bma&quot; /&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;schreierstoren&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080212060404/http://www.bmz.amsterdam.nl/adam/nl/groot/schreiers.html &quot;Schreierstoren (±1487)&quot;, Amsterdam Monumenten] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1494, a ceremony was held to mark the completion of the city walls. Ironically, by that time the walls were already antiquated. The walls were built to withstand medieval [[siege]]s, but [[gunpowder]] and iron instead of stone cannonballs had come into general use for attacks on walled cities.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

The city walls had five gates:
* Haarlemmerpoort
* Regulierspoort (now the bottom half of [[Munttoren]] tower)
* Sint Antoniespoort (now the [[Waag (Amsterdam)|Waag]])
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Heiligewegpoort|nl}}
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Korsjespoort|nl}}

[[File:Oudeschans.jpg|thumb|260px|The [[Oudeschans (Amsterdam)|Oudeschans]] canal, with [[Montelbaanstoren]] tower (right)]]
In 1512, troops from the Dutchy of Guelders attacked the city and looted the [[Lastage]], an area of shipyards beyond the city walls on the eastern side of the town. To protect the Lastage, a new moat was dug in the period 1515-1518. By expanding a branch of the Amstel river, the Nieuwe Gracht (&quot;New Canal&quot;, now the {{Interlanguage link multi|Oudeschans (Amsterdam)|nl|3=Oudeschans (Amsterdam)|lt=Oudeschans}}) canal was created. The soil produced by widening the river branch into a canal was used to build a wall along the inner side of the canal, topped by a wooden palissade. As part of these new defensive works, the [[Montelbaanstoren]] was built around 1516 as a watchtower. &lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071112101540/http://www.bmz.amsterdam.nl/adam/nl/groot/montelbaans.html &quot;Montelbaanstoren (1516, 1606)&quot;, Amsterdam Monumenten] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Bastions ===
[[File:Haarlprt.jpg|thumb|260px|The 17th-century [[Haarlemmerpoort]] gate, designed by [[Hendrick de Keyser]]]]
[[File:Johannes Jelgerhuis - De Amsterdamse buitensingel bij de Leidse poort.jpg|thumb|260px|The [[Singelgracht]] canal at [[Leidsepoort]] gate, depicted in an 1816 painting by [[Johannes Jelgerhuis]]]]
[[File:Willem Hekking - De Utrechtsche Poort in Julij 1858.jpg|thumb|260px|A colored [[lithograph]] of the Utrechtsepoort by [[Willem Hekking]], July 1858. This gate was located on the south side of what is now the Frederiksplein.]]
During the 17th century, the city expanded rapidly. To protect the grand new ''[[Canals of Amsterdam|grachtengordel]]'' (the concentric belt of canals), a system of 26 [[bastion]]s was constructed along the [[Singelgracht]] canal.

Immediately following the ''[[Alteratie]]'' in 1578, the city began to strengthen the weak spots in its defenses. For instance, a bastion was constructed by the Haarlemmerpoort gate, which at that time lay near Herenmarkt square. [[William the Silent|William of Orange]] ordered the fortifications engineer [[Adriaen Anthonisz]] to Amsterdam in 1581 in order to oversee the construction of the new defensive works.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

In 1585, the city government decided to construct new earthen walls with 11 bastions beyond the existing walls. The city was expanding so rapidly that the area between the old and new walls was filled with new houses within a matter of a few years. In 1613 it was decided to construct new defensive walls with bastions on the western side of town, along the current Marnixstraat and Weteringschans streets, with a new outer moat (the Buitensingel, now [[Singelgracht]]) and inner moat (the {{Interlanguage link multi|Lijnbaansgracht|nl}}). Within these new walls, the ''[[Canals of Amsterdam|grachtengordel]]'' (the concentric belt of canals) could now be constructed.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

Amsterdam in 1657 began to construct fortifications to protect its fourth and largest 17th-century city expansion. This was one of the most ambitious construction projects undertaken in the 17th-century Dutch republic. Supporting the heavy walls on the porous Amsterdam soil required large numbers of [[deep foundation]] piles and [[retaining wall]]s. Thousands of labourers transported soil and sand from the dunes and the [[Gooi]] using carts and wheelbarrows. Kilometers of retaining walls were built, canals were dug, and bridges and sluice gates were constructed. Around 1663, the massive project was complete.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

The walls rested on a nine metres deep wooden floor, supported by over 100,000 piles with crossbeams. On the top of the wooden floor, brick arches were built. Each bastion had 44 arches and each [[Curtain wall (fortification)|curtain wall]] had 47 arches. The arches were then covered with soil, and the walls were covered with stone. The walls were supported by 14 kilometres of retaining walls to prevent the soil from sinking away.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

The fortifications consisted of 26 bastions in total. In the flanks of these bastions were [[casemate]]s with cannon and munition. [[Windmill]]s were placed on top of most of the bastions.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

There were five main gates in the 17th-century fortifications:&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Haarlemmerpoort|nl|3=Haarlemmerpoort (Amsterdam)}}
* [[Leidsepoort]]
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Utrechtsepoort|nl|3=Utrechtsepoort (Amsterdam)}}
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Weesperpoort|nl}}
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Muiderpoort|nl|3=Muiderpoort (Amsterdam)}}

In addition, there were several smaller gates:
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Weteringpoort|nl|3=Weteringpoort (Amsterdam)}}
* {{Interlanguage link multi|Raampoort|nl}}
* [[Zaagmolenpoort]]

The city walls were never seriously put to the test. During the ''[[Rampjaar]]'' of 1672, the [[Dutch Water Line]] proved sufficient to stop the invading French troops from taking Amsterdam. The fortifications were neglected and began to decay. In 1769, for instance, the Muiderpoort gate collapsed, and in 1794, part of the Reguliersbolwerk bastion sank into the canal. Following the [[History of the Netherlands#The French-Batavian period (1785–1815)|Napoleonic era]], the bastions were turned into a park area. A path was constructed along the top of the bastions so that the citizens of Amsterdam could go for a leisurely stroll. In the period 1839-1848, the city defenses were gradually demolished. The final remaining curtain wall, between the bastions Rijkeroord and Slotermeer, was demolished in 1862 and replaced with a path for strolling. The gates were left standing but were repurposed as offices for tax collection.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reneros&quot;&gt;[http://doccentrum.stelling-amsterdam.nl/publicaties/documenten/erfgoedamsterdam/erfgoedamsterdam.pdf René Ros, &quot;Verdedigingswerken van Amsterdam door de eeuwen heen&quot;, ''Erfgoed van Industrie en Techniek'' 2010, nr. 1] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Industrial Revolution]] in the second half of the 19th century, the city started expanding beyond its 17th-century walls. The former bastions, now an area of recreation, were largely replaced with new buildings, and the Singelgracht canal was straightened; the bastions which had once jutted out were now no longer visible.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurpershoek&quot; /&gt;

=== Fortification lines ===
[[File:2007 1020Naarden0117.JPG|thumb|260px|[[Fort bij Uitermeer]], one of the forts of the [[Stelling van Amsterdam|Defence Line of Amsterdam]] (''Stelling van Amsterdam'') ]]

In 1787, the ''[[Patriots (faction)|Patriotten]]'' city government sought to protect the city against the [[Prussia]]ns by erecting 27 defensive posts along the seven entrances into the city. The [[polder]]s between each of these posts were flooded. The Prussians were unable to overcome these defensives, but managed to get by the posts using the poorly defended entrance by the [[Haarlemmermeer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;reneros&quot; /&gt;

During the [[Anglo-Russian invasion of Holland]] in 1799, [[Cornelis Rudolphus Theodorus Krayenhoff|Cornelis Krayenhoff]] protected the capital by erecting the ''[[Linie van Noord-Holland]]'' (&quot;North Holland Line&quot;). He flooded the lower-lying areas between [[Monnickendam]] and [[Krommeniedijk]], and protected the higher situated areas using earthen walls and field artillery. A year later, Krayenhoff oversaw the construction of a second defensive line, west of Amsterdam, the ''[[Linie van Beverwijk]]'' (&quot;Beverwijk Line&quot;), consisting of three lines of [[Lunette (fortification)|lunette]]s. The lunettes were spaced at a distance of 400 metres from each other. Ten of these lunettes still remain.&lt;ref name=&quot;reneros&quot; /&gt;

Krayenhoff reused a number of the 1787 defensive posts for the ''[[Posten van Krayenhoff]]'' (&quot;Krayenhoff Posts&quot;), a defensive line constructed around Amsterdam in the period 1805-1810.&lt;ref name=&quot;reneros&quot; /&gt;

The range and accuracy of artillery significantly improved as a result of the [[Industrial Revolution]]. To keep the city out of range of enemy artillery fire, it was decided to build a new line of fortifications around Amsterdam, at 15 to 20 kilometres' distance from the city centre. This [[Stelling van Amsterdam|Defence Line of Amsterdam]] (''Stelling van Amsterdam''), constructed in the years 1880-1914, was the most modern and largest-area circular fortification system in Europe in its day. The line stretched 135 kilometres and included 42 forts as well as four [[Artillery battery|artillery batteries]]. The line was never tested, but did have a deterrent effect. In 1914, at the outbreak of [[World War I]], the Defence Line, as well as the [[Dutch Water Line#New Dutch Water Line|Dutch Water Line]], were a factor in the German decision not to invade the Netherlands. The Defence Line has survived largely intact and was named a [[World Heritage Site]] in 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;reneros&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stellingvanamsterdam.nl/ Stelling van Amsterdam] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Remains==
[[File:De gooyer amsterdam.jpg|thumb|260px|Windmill [[De Gooyer, Amsterdam|De Gooyer]] originally stood on top of the Oosterbeer bastion ]]
[[File:Eerste marnixplantsoen.jpg|thumb|260px|The park Eerste Marnixplantsoen, formerly Haarlem bastion. This is the only remaining site along [[Singelgracht]] canal that still has the pointed shape of a bastion]]
The well-known [[red-light district]] around the canals Oudezijds Voorburgwal and Oudezijds Achterburgwal is still known as ''[[De Wallen]]'' (&quot;The Walls&quot;), after the original Medieval earthen walls.

Remains of the Medieval defensive works include the [[Waag (Amsterdam)|Waag]] (originally Sint Antoniespoort gate) and the bottom half of [[Munttoren]] tower (originally Regulierspoort gate), as well as the defensive tower [[Schreierstoren]] and the watchtower [[Montelbaanstoren]]. 

In the Geldersekade canal walls, there are still some sandstone fragments of the original Medieval city walls. On 19 June 2007, part of the Medieval walls were briefly exposed when a four metres deep hole was dug to inspect the foundations of the Waag.&lt;ref name=&quot;schreierstoren&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amsterdam.nl/@71316/pagina/ &quot;15de eeuwse stadsmuur even zichtbaar&quot;, Amsterdam.nl] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

A few patches remain of the park that was constructed on top of the bastions in the 19th century. These include the Eerste Weteringplantsoen, Tweede Weteringplantsoen, Eerste Marnixplantsoen, and Tweede Marnixplantsoen. The Eerste Marnixplantsoen, formerly bastion Haarlem, is the only remaining site along [[Singelgracht]] canal that still has the pointed shape of a bastion. Two windmills remain of the mills that stood on top of the bastions: [[De Gooyer, Amsterdam|De Gooyer]] and [[De Bloem]]. However, neither windmill still stands on its original location.

Although [[Singelgracht]] canal was straightened, the canal and the Nassaukade, Stadhouderskade and Mauritskade streets along the canal still follow a zigzag pattern, revealing the location of former bastions.

== Bolwerkenroute ==

In 2010, the Bolwerkenroute Amsterdam was presented. This route is to consist of 26 stone plaques at each of the 17th-century bastions. The first plaque, measuring 60 by 60 centimetres, was presented on 24 February 2010 at [[Max Euweplein]] square. The route was an initiative of local mime artist Rob van Reijn.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centrum.amsterdam.nl/publish/pages/265013/stadsdeelnieuws102010.pdf ''Stadsdeelnieuws'', Gemeente Amsterdam, Stadsdeel Centrum, nr. 10, jaargang 6, 11 March 2010] (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Canon of Amsterdam==
* The Amsterdam City Walls is window number 5 in the [[Canon of Amsterdam]].

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==

* Ernest Kurpershoek, ''Amsterdam verdedigd: Bescherming van de stad'', Uitgeverij Bas Lubberhuizen, Amsterdam 2004 (Dutch)
* [http://doccentrum.stelling-amsterdam.nl/publicaties/documenten/erfgoedamsterdam/erfgoedamsterdam.pdf René Ros, &quot;Verdedigingswerken van Amsterdam door de eeuwen heen&quot;, ''Erfgoed van Industrie en Techniek'' 2010, nr. 1] (Dutch)
* Raoul Serree, ''Amsterdam ommuurd: Het raadsel van de middeleeuwse stadsmuur (1481-1601)'', Uniepers, 1999 (Dutch)

== External links ==
* [http://www.stellingvanamsterdam.nl/ Website of the Defence Line of Amsterdam]
* [http://www.stelling-amsterdam.nl/english/ Website about the Defence Line of Amsterdam ]
* [http://www.bolwerken.amsterdam.nl Bolwerkenroute] {{nl}}

{{Amsterdam}}

[[Category:City walls|Amsterdam]]
[[Category:History of Amsterdam]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Amsterdam]]
[[Category:Fortifications in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Gates in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Canon of Amsterdam]]</text>
      <sha1>7au0ugeowq9aoea8jnaukosrdklovoc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
