<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>William Stephen Raikes Hodson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1651193</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750129396</id>
      <parentid>749714442</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T00:01:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mtthwknnd4</username>
        <id>23416735</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>unnecessary</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25036">{{Refimprove|date=June 2016}}
{{copy edit|date=June 2016}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= William Stephen Raikes Hodson
|birth_date=10 March 1821
|death_date= 11 March 1858
|birth_place= Maisemore Court, near [[Gloucester]]
|death_place=[[Lucknow]], [[British India]]
|image= WilliamHodson.jpg
|caption=William Hodson, engraving printed as frontispiece to his biography ''Rider on a Grey Horse'', by B.J. Cork, 1958
|nickname=
|allegiance= {{UK}}
|serviceyears=
|rank= [[Brevet (military)|Brevet]] Major 
|branch=[[Bengal Army]]
|commands=[[Corps of Guides (India)|Corps of Guides]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hodson's Horse]]
|unit=
|battles=[[First Anglo-Sikh War]]&lt;br&gt;[[Indian Mutiny]]
|awards= 
|laterwork=
}}
Brevet Major '''William Stephen Raikes Hodson''' (10 March 1821 – 11 March 1858) aka &quot;Hodson of [[Hodson's Horse]]&quot;, was a British leader of irregular light cavalry during the [[Indian Rebellion of 1857]], commonly referred to as the Indian or Sepoy mutiny.

His most celebrated action was to apprehend the King of Delhi (also referred to as [[Emperor of India]] and [[Bahadur Shah II]]). The following day he rode to the enemy camp, heavily outnumbered by the rebels, and demanded the surrender of the [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] princes who were leading the rebellion around [[Delhi]] and killed them.&lt;ref&gt;LJ Trotter, ''A Leader of Light Horse'', pages 200-202&lt;/ref&gt; In the course of the Mutiny a number of male members of Bahadur Shar II's family were killed by [[East India Company]] forces, who imprisoned or exiled the surviving members of the Mughal dynasty; furthermore, Bahadur Shah II was tried on four counts, two of aiding rebels, one of treason, and being party to the murder of 49 people. However, as Hodson had previously guaranteed his life, the Emperor eventually died peacefully of old age.&lt;ref&gt;Charges against Mahomed Bahadoor Shah, ex-King of Delhi reprinted in Perth Inquirer &amp; Commercial News, 7 April 1858&lt;/ref&gt; 

Hodson's career received praise from a number of senior military commanders such as General [[Hugh Gough, 1st Viscount Gough|Hugh Gough]]&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;''Old Memories'' 1897 memoirs published by H. Gough&lt;/ref&gt; (see references below) but there were certain dissenting voices from other members of the military. There were also a few politicians who felt the killing of Mughal princes by Hodson had been 'dishonourable'.&lt;ref&gt;From a speech delivered by [[Thomas Perronet Thompson|Gen. Thompson]], MP for Bradford, in the House of Commons, February 1858. Cited in Michael Edwardes, ''Red Year: The Indian Rebellion of 1857'', London: Cardinal Books, 1975, p.165&lt;/ref&gt; However, Hodson's career received praise from more senior politicians including the Prime Minister and Minister for India.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hansard&quot;&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1859/apr/14/thanks-to-the-government-and-army-in#S3V0153P0-02194 Hansard; 14 April 1859]&lt;/ref&gt;

Hodson is credited with being jointly responsible for the introduction of the [[khaki]] uniform.

== Early career ==

William Hodson was born on 9 March 1821 at [[Maisemore|Maisemore Court]], near [[Gloucester]], third son of the Rev Dr George Hodson, Archdeacon of Stafford. His older brother was Rev Dr [[James Stephen Hodson]] [[FRSE]] who served for many years as Rector of [[Edinburgh Academy]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.anatpro.com/index_files/James_Stephen_Hodson.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

He was educated at [[Rugby School]] under [[Thomas Arnold|Dr Arnold]] and at [[Trinity College, Cambridge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{acad|id=HT840WS|name=Hodson, William Stephen Raikes}}&lt;/ref&gt; He accepted a cadetship in the Indian Army at the age of twenty-three; joining the [[2nd Regiment of Bengal Native Infantry|2nd Bengal Grenadiers]], he went through the [[First Anglo-Sikh War]].

A contemporary described him as &quot;a tall man with yellow hair, a pale, smooth face, heavy moustache, and large, restless, rather unforgiving eyes… a perfect swordsman, nerves like iron, and a quick, intelligent eye&quot;{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}. Hodson delighted in fighting and his favourite weapon was the hog spear{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}. He was a brilliant horseman with the capacity to sleep in the saddle{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}. He was described as 'the finest swordsman in the army'.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 1911 edition&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The initial assistance he gave in organising the newly formed [[Corps of Guides (British India)|Corps of Guides]] in December 1846 had been one of [[Sir Henry Lawrence]]'s projects in which Hodson excelled. The Guides Corps had Lt [[Harry Burnett Lumsden]] as its commandant and Lt Hodson as adjutant. Significantly among the duties assigned to Hodson, his responsibility was for equipping the new regiment which necessitated his choosing the regiment's uniform.  With Lumsden's approval, Hodson decided upon a lightweight uniform of [[Khaki (color)|Khaki colour]] - or 'drab' as it was then referred to. This would be comfortable to wear and 'make them invisible in a land of dust'. Accordingly, in May 1848 he liaised with his brother Rev. George H. Hodson, in England, to send 'drab' cloth for 900 men as well as 300 carbines.&lt;ref&gt;pages 50-51 from ''Twelve Years of a Soldier's Life in India'', published 1859 - first edition of the biography on Hodson by his brother George&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Hodson and Lumsden had the joint distinction of being the first officers to clothe a regiment in Khaki, which many view as the precursor of modern camouflage uniform.

Later on, he was transferred to the Civil Department as Assistant Commissioner in 1849 and stationed at [[Amritsar]]; and from there he travelled in [[Kashmir]] and [[Tibet]]. In 1852 he was appointed Commandant of the [[Corps of Guides (British India)|Corps of Guides]].

While it was unusual at that time for a British soldier in India to be a Cambridge graduate, William further differed from the norm by enjoying classical literature for relaxation, and was a keen linguist - this included having an interest in learning the main language(s) of his host country at that time. On his arrival in India he started first learning ‘Hindustani' and later Persian, with the help and encouragement from his mentor Sir Henry Lawrence.&lt;ref&gt;Trotter, Hodson of |Hodson’s Horse&lt;/ref&gt;  This apparently was of intellectual and cultural interest to him, particularly as his army quarters offered him little in the way of culture or reading-matter, save for the &quot;usual copy of the Bible and works of Shakespeare&quot;. He even asked for “a formidable collection of classics&quot; from his brother, although he probably didn't see anything unusual in spending three hours a day studying Persian. He even &quot;found it relaxing to read untranslated Xenophon…”.&lt;ref&gt;pp.40 B. Joynson Cork, ‘Rider on a Grey Horse’&lt;/ref&gt;

==Indian Rebellion==
At the outset of the Indian Mutiny Hodson made his name by riding with despatches from [[George Anson (1797–1857)|General Anson]] from [[Karnal]] to [[Meerut]] and back again, a distance of 152 miles in seventy-two hours, through country full of hostile cavalry.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} Following this feat, the commander-in-chief empowered him to raise and command a  new regiment of 2000 irregular horse, which became famed as &quot;[[Hodson's Horse]]&quot;, and placed him at the head of the Intelligence Department.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}

In his double role of cavalry leader and intelligence officer, Hodson played a large part in the [[Siege of Delhi|reduction of Delhi]]. As already indicated, his major achievement{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} at this time was the capture&lt;ref&gt;Or, more probably, the astute negotiation of the surrender of Bahadur Shah, his favourite wife Zeenat Mahal, her young son Jawan Bakht, and a few other members of the Royal Family. See Edwardes, ''Red Year'', p.58&lt;/ref&gt; of the Mughal Emperor, [[Bahadur Shah II]]; and his major discredit{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} the execution of the three Mughal princes, Bahadur's sons [[Mirza Mughal]] and [[Mirza Khizr Sultan]] and his grandson Mirza Abu Bakr.&lt;ref&gt;For a detailed study of this issue, which became very controversial in 19th century England and India, see Appendix N of TR Holmes's ''History of the Indian Mutiny'', London, 1898, pp. 591-617&lt;/ref&gt;

The British knew{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} that the old Emperor of India (or &quot;King of Delhi&quot;) was proving to be a focus for the uprising and the mutineers, and that he, his sons and their army were camped just outside Delhi at [[Humayun's Tomb]]. The General in command{{who?|date=June 2016}} said he could not spare a single European.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} Hodson volunteered to go with 50 of his irregular horsemen. This request was turned down but after some persuasion Hodson obtained from Colonel (later General) [[Archdale Wilson]] permission to ride out to where the enemy was encamped.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} Hodson rode six miles through enemy territory into their camp, containing some 6000 or more armed mutineers, who are said to have laid down their arms when he ordered them to.&lt;ref&gt;Edwardes, p.58-59&lt;/ref&gt; Some{{whom?|date=June 2016}} have seen this surrender as symbolic of the decline of the Turks and Mughals in India,&lt;ref&gt;Including Holmes (1898), Kaye (1880) and others&lt;/ref&gt; which had started after Aurangzeb; but the fact was that the mutineers, or rebels, at Delhi were simply demoralised after their hard-fought defeat and severe privations.&lt;ref&gt;Edwardes, pp.60-61&lt;/ref&gt;
	
[[File:The capture of the king of delhi by Captain Hodson.jpg|thumb|300px|&quot;Capture of the king of Delhi by Captain Hodson&quot; from ''The Indian Empire''  (1857) by [[Robert Montgomery Martin]]]]
Here he accepted the surrender of Bahadur Shah II, the last of the Moghul Emperors of India, promising him that his life would be spared.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1857/dec/11/the-ex-king-of-delhi-question#S3V0148P0-01950 Hansard; 11 December 1857]&lt;/ref&gt; The capture of the Emperor in the face of a threatening crowd dealt the mutineers a heavy blow. As a sign of surrender the Emperor handed over his arms, which included two magnificent swords, one with the name ‘Nadir Shah’ and the other with the seal of [[Jahangir]] engraved upon it, which Hodson intended to present to [[Queen Victoria]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.harappa.com/engr/mughal.html ''Illustrated London News''; 20 March 1858]&lt;/ref&gt; The swords he took from the Emperor were given to the Queen as a symbol of the Emperor's surrender and are still held in the Queen's Collection.

The sons of the king, the princes had refused to surrender, demanding guarantees of safety&lt;ref&gt;Which Hodson refused, see Edwardes, p.59&lt;/ref&gt; and on the following day with a few horsemen Hodson went back and demanded the princes' unconditional surrender. Again a crowd of thousands of mutineers gathered, and Hodson ordered them to disarm, which they did. He sent the princes on with an escort of ten men, while with the remaining ninety he collected the arms of the crowd.&lt;ref&gt;Edwardes, p.59&lt;/ref&gt; The princes were mounted on a bullock-cart and driven towards the city of Delhi. As they approached the city gate, a crowd of people again started to gather around them, and Hodson ordered the three princes to get off the cart and to strip off their top garments. He then took a carbine from one of his troopers and shot them dead before stripping them of their [[Seal (device)|signet rings]], turquoise arm-bands and bejewelled swords. Their bodies were ordered to be displayed in front of a ''kotwali'', or police-station, and left there to be seen by all.&lt;ref&gt;It was later confirmed that Hodson wrongly believed that some Englishmen had been killed at this place. Edwardes, p.59&lt;/ref&gt; The gate near where they were killed is still called the [[Khooni Darwaza]], or 'Bloody Gate'.

The actions were controversial even&lt;ref&gt;And remained so for quite some time later too. Much can be said on both sides, for the situation during the Mutiny/Rebellion remained very volatile and considerable violence was done on both sides. In the matter of the princes' execution, it is quite certain that Hodson was earlier negotiating with an agent of the Queen of Delhi, Zeenat Mahal, for the surrender of the Mughal King/Emperor, as well as herself and her young son Jawan Bakht, and a few other members of the Royal Family. However, the executed princes were not mentioned or included in this 'deal' and a lot of speculation is also attached to Zeenat Mahal's own possible ulterior motives, although this in no way exonerates Hodson. See Edwardes, p.58, and TG Metcalfe, ''Two Narratives of the Mutiny in Delhi'', London, 1898, which mentions some of the court intrigues in Delhi, briefly, too&lt;/ref&gt;  at the time. The future [[Frederick Roberts, 1st Earl Roberts]], then a junior officer serving in the Delhi campaign, would later call it a &quot;blot&quot; and criticised &quot;an otherwise brilliant officer&quot; for exposing himself to criticism.&lt;ref&gt;See also his ''Letters Written During the Indian Mutiny'', London, 1924&lt;/ref&gt; Other first hand accounts, such as William W. Ireland also called into question the exigency of his actions {{citation needed|date=April 2012}}. Hodson's service record showed that he had often behaved in arbitrary fashion before, and he had previously been removed from civil duties by the then Governor General of India, [[James Broun-Ramsay, 1st Marquess of Dalhousie|Lord Dalhousie]].

[[File:Hodson grave in la martiniere Lucknow.jpg|300px|thumb|''Hodson's grave in [[La Martiniere Lucknow|La Martiniere College]] in Lucknow'']]

==Accusations of corruption==

In 1855, two separate main charges were brought against Hodson. The first was that he had arbitrarily imprisoned a [[Yusufzai]] [[Pashtun people|Pathan]] chief named Kader Khan,&lt;ref&gt;As well as his young son&lt;/ref&gt; on suspicion of being concerned in the murder of Colonel Mackeson.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Charles Allen (writer)|Charles Allen]] (2000), ''Soldier-Sahibs'', p.237, for these and various other, minor charges brought against Hodson&lt;/ref&gt; The man was acquitted, and [[James Broun-Ramsay, 1st Marquess of Dalhousie|Lord Dalhousie]] removed Hodson from his civil functions and remanded him to his regiment on account of his lack of judgment and gross negligence.&lt;ref&gt;Allen, pp.236-237&lt;/ref&gt;

The second charge was more serious, amounting to an accusation of misappropriation of the funds of his regiment. He was tried by a court of inquiry, who found that his conduct to natives had been unjustifiable and oppressive, that he had used abusive language to his native officers and personal violence to his men, and that his system of accounts was calculated to screen [[peculation]] and fraud. However, a subsequent inquiry was carried out by Major [[Reynell Taylor]]: 'Taylor's investigation took two months, during which time he went through every item received or paid out by Hodson over the two years of his command'.&lt;ref&gt;page 85, Barry Joynson Cork, 'Rider on a Grey Horse: Life of Hodson of Hodson's Horse'.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of his investigation into the record of Hodson's accounts Taylor found 'it to be an honest and correct record from beginning to end - It has been irregularly kept, but every transaction, from the least to the greatest, has been noted in it, and is traceable to the individual concerned'&lt;ref&gt;. page 126, LJ Trotter, 'Hodson of Hodson's Horse'&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/lifeofhodsonofho00trotiala The life of Hodson of Hodson's horse]&lt;/ref&gt;

During a tour through [[Kashmir]] with Sir Henry Lawrence he kept the purse and Sir Henry could never obtain an account from him;{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} subsequently, Sir Henry's younger brother Sir [[George St Patrick Lawrence|George Lawrence]] accused him of embezzling the funds of the Lawrence Asylum at [[Kasauli]];{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} while Sir [[Neville Bowles Chamberlain|Neville Chamberlain]] in a published letter says of the third brother, Lord Lawrence, &quot;I am bound to say that Lord Lawrence had no opinion of Hodson's integrity in money matters. He has often discussed Hodson's character in talking to me, and it was to him a regret that a man possessing so many fine gifts should have been wanting in a moral quality which made him untrustworthy.&quot;{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} Finally, on one occasion Hodson spent £500 of the pay due to Lieutenant Godby, and under threat of exposure was obliged to borrow the money from a local banker named Bisharat Ali through one of his officers.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}

==Financial matters==
Throughout his career Hodson was dogged by accusations of financial impropriety.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} He was investigated on more than one occasion but nothing was ever proved. His detractors{{whom?|date=June 2016}} claim he was a looter.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} His supporters{{whom?|date=June 2016}} say that these accusations came from those who disliked his manner and his military success.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} The Rev. G. H. Hodson states in his book that he obtained the inventory of his brother's possessions made by the Committee of Adjustment and it contained no articles of loot{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}, and Sir [[Charles John Stanley Gough|Charles Gough]], president of the committee, confirmed this evidence.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} This statement is totally incompatible with Sir [[Henry Daly]]'s.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} Sir [[Henry Wylie Norman|Henry Norman]] stated that to his personal knowledge Hodson remitted several thousand pounds to [[Calcutta]] which could only have been obtained by looting.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} On the other hand, again, Hodson died a poor man, his effects, which included a ring, watch, Bible and Prayer book, and a miniature, were sold for only £170{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}. General remarked &quot;there was nothing in his boxes but what an officer might legitimately and honourably have in his possession.&quot;{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} His widow did not have money enough to pay for her passage home and she had to apply to the Compassionate Fund for assistance, which was granted.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} She was given apartments by the Queen at [[Hampton Court Palace|Hampton Court]], and left only £400 at her death.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}}

== Death ==
On 11 March 1858 Hodson's regiment was in [[Capture of Lucknow|Lucknow]] and while storming the Begum's palace (''Begum Kothi'') he was shot. His last words were &quot;I hope I have done my duty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''The Spectator'' (Literary Supplement), Nov. 2, 1911 - article: 'Hodson of Hodson's Horse, pp.631-632.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the evening of 12 March 1858, his body was buried in the garden of [[La Martiniere Lucknow]]. His grave is still located within the grounds of La Martiniere College.  The memorial bears the inscription &quot;Here lies all that could die of William Stephen Raikes Hodson&quot;.

==Legacy==
In parliamentary speeches made on 14 April 1859 the Prime Minister [[Edward Smith-Stanley, 14th Earl of Derby|Earl of Derby]], and the Minister for India [[Edward Stanley, 15th Earl of Derby|Lord Stanley]] paid tribute to Hodson. Lord Stanley is quoted as saying: {{quote|&quot;Major Hodson, of the Guides, who, in his short but brilliant military career, displayed every quality which a cavalry officer should possess. Nothing is more remarkable in glancing over the biography of Major Hodson that has just appeared than the variety of services in which he was engaged, unless it be the energy and versatility with which he turned from one to the other. At one time displaying his personal courage and skill as a swordsman in conflict with the Sikh fanatics; then transferred to the Civil Service, the duties of which he performed as though he had passed his whole life at the desk; afterwards recruiting and commanding the corps of Guides, and, lastly, taking part in the operations before Delhi, volunteering for every enterprise in which life could be hazarded or glory could be won; he crowded into the brief space of twelve eventful years the services and adventures of a long life. He died before the reward which he had earned could be received, but he attained that reward which doubtless he most coveted — the consciousness of duty nobly done, and the assurance of enduring military renown.&quot;}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Hansard&quot;/&gt;

The Prime Minister said of him {{quote|&quot;Doubtless many have fallen who, if they had been spared, might have risen to greatest eminence and have held the highest stations in public service. I allude to Hodson a model of chiefs of irregular forces. By his valour, his rigid discipline, and careful attention to his men's real wants, comforts, desires, and even prejudices, he had obtained an influence which was all but marvellous. This enabled him to lead his troops so formed and disciplined into any danger and into any conflict as if they had been British soldiers. He has met a soldier's death. It will be long before the people lose the memory of Hodson&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hansard&quot;/&gt;}}

General [[Hugh Gough, 1st Viscount Gough|Hugh Gough]] said of him, {{quote|&quot;A finer or more gallant soldier never breathed. He had the true instincts of a leader of men; as a cavalry soldier he was perfection; a strong seat, a perfect swordsman, quick and intelligent&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;}}

This recognition of Hodson by the Prime Minister was reflected in the special pension granted his widow by the Secretary of State for India in Council, who declared it was 'testimony of the high sense entertained of the gallant and distinguished services of the late Brevet-Major W.S.R. Hodson'. Her Majesty Queen Victoria honoured Major Hodson posthumously by granting his widow a [[Grace and favour]] apartment at [[Hampton Court Palace]] &quot;in consideration of the distinguished service of your late husband in India&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Grace &amp; Favour; A handbook of who lived where in Hampton Court Palace, 1750 to 1950'' Sarah E Parker, p39&lt;/ref&gt;

He features as one of the main characters in [[James Leasor]]'s novel about the Mutiny, ''Follow the Drum'' (1972), which describes his part in these events and his death in some detail.

== Family ==

On 5 January 1852,&lt;ref&gt;Lionel James Trotter ''A Leader of Light Horse'' (W. Blackwood and sons 1901) p. 129&lt;/ref&gt; he married Susan (d. 1884), daughter of Capt C. Henry, RN and widow of John Mitford of Exbury, at [[St. Paul's Cathedral, Kolkata|Calcutta Cathedral]], whom he had known and liked for some time prior to her first marriage. A daughter, Olivia, was born in 1853 but died in July 1854.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibiblio.org/britishraj/Hodson/pt01ch07.html ''Twelve years of a soldier's life in India: being extracts from the letters of the late Major W. S. R. Hodson'']  ed. by his brother, the Rev. George H. Hodson; p119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;At [[Murree]], and is buried there in the [[Christian]] cemetery. See [[Charles Allen (writer)|Charles Allen]], (2000) ''Soldier Sahibs'', pp. 230 and 235&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Chhibramau]] for Hodson's Adventure

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* ''Twelve years of a soldier's life in India: being extracts from the letters of the late Major W. S. R. Hodson'' ed. by his brother, the Rev. George H. Hodson
* Lionel James Trotter ''A Leader of Light Horse: Life of Hodson of Hodson's Horse'' (W. Blackwood and sons 1901)
* James Leasor ''The Red Fort'', (Werner Laurie 1956, James Leasor Ltd 2011)
* Barry Joynson Cork, ''Rider on a Grey Horse, A life of Hodson of Hodson's Horse'', (Cassells 1958)
* James Leasor ''Follow the Drum'' (Heinemann 1972, James Leasor Ltd 2011)
* [[Charles Allen (writer)|Charles Allen]] ''Soldier Sahibs, the Men who made the North-West Frontier'', (John Murray 2000)
* Saul David, ''The Indian Mutiny'', (Vicking 2002)
* Julian Spilsbury, ''Indian Mutiny'', (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicholson 2007).
* Perth Inquirer &amp; Commercial News, 7 April 1858

==External links==
* [http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/William_Stephen_Raikes_Hodson ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 1911 edition]
* [http://www.oocities.org/hodson_of_hodsons_horse/hodsonofhodsonshorse.htm Hodson of Hodson's Horse]
* {{Gutenberg author | id=Hodson,+W.+S.+R. | name=W. S. R. Hodson}}
* {{Internet Archive author |search=(&quot;William Stephen Raikes Hodson&quot; OR &quot;Hodson, William Stephen Raikes&quot; OR &quot;W. S. R. Hodson&quot; OR &quot;Hodson, W. S. R.&quot;)}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hodson, William}}
[[Category:1821 births]]
[[Category:1858 deaths]]
[[Category:People educated at Rugby School]]
[[Category:Alumni of Trinity College, Cambridge]]
[[Category:People from Gloucester]]
[[Category:British military personnel killed in the Indian Rebellion of 1857]]
[[Category:British East India Company Army officers]]
[[Category:British military personnel of the First Anglo-Sikh War]]
[[Category:British military personnel of the Indian Rebellion of 1857]]
[[Category:Corps of Guides (India) officers]]</text>
      <sha1>gjg9zx473xbgoqssx53l06xvq21ws5x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
