<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Wz. 35 anti-tank rifle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1401124</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746009238</id>
      <parentid>746008802</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T18:49:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Arjayay</username>
        <id>5718152</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Flag Rm as [[MOS:ICON#Avoid_flag_icons_in_infoboxes]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14081">{{more footnotes|date=May 2012}}
&lt;!--SCROLL DOWN IN ORDER TO EDIT THE ARTICLE--&gt;

{{Infobox Weapon|is_ranged=yes
|     image=[[Image:Wz35 antitank rifle SA-kuva 113078.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Karabin przeciwpancerny wzór 35
|   name='''Karabin przeciwpancerny wz.35'''
|   type=[[Anti-tank rifle]]
| origin=Poland
|    era=World War II
|   design_date=
| manufacturer=[[Państwowa Fabryka Karabinów]]
|prod_design_date=1936 to 1939
|serv_design_date=1939
|used_by=[[Poland]], [[Nazi Germany]], [[Italy]]
|   wars=[[World War II]]
|spec_type=
| part_length={{convert|1200|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|   cartridge=[[DS 7.92|7.92×107mm DS]]
| caliber=7.9mm
|    feed=4-round [[box magazine]]
| action=[[Bolt action]]
|    rate=8–10 round/min
|velocity={{convert|1275|m/s|ft/s|abbr=on}}
| weight={{convert|10|kg|lb|abbr=on}} (loaded)
| length={{convert|1760|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|variants=
|number=3500
}}
[[File:Polski ułan z karabinem przeciwpancernym UR.jpg|thumb|200px|Polish [[uhlan]] with wz. 35 anti-tank rifle. Military instruction published in [[Warsaw]] in 1938.]]
'''''Karabin przeciwpancerny wzór 35''''' (abbreviated &quot;'''''kb ppanc wz. 35'''''&quot;; &quot;anti-tank rifle, model 35&quot;), also ''UR'', was a [[Poland|Polish]] 7.9&amp;nbsp;mm [[anti-tank rifle]] used by the [[Polish Army]] during the [[Invasion of Poland]] of 1939. It was also known by its [[codename]] ''Uruguay'' ('''''kb Urugwaj''''') ('''''kb Ur'''''), or by the name of its designer, [[Józef Maroszek]].

==Secrecy and confusion==
The weapon was initially a top secret of the Polish Army, and was also known by various codenames. Until mobilization in 1939, the combat-ready rifles were held in closed crates enigmatically marked: &quot;Do not open! Surveillance equipment!&quot;.  Another of the rifle's cover names was ''[[Uruguay]]'' (Polish: ''Urugwaj'', hence ''Ur''), the country to which the ''&quot;surveillance equipment&quot;'' was supposedly being exported.

After the fall of Poland, the German army captured large numbers of the ''kb ppanc wz.35'' and renamed it &quot;''Panzerbüchse 35 (polnisch)''&quot; (abbreviated &quot;''PzB 35(p)''&quot;). The Italian army received 800 of the captured weapons and used it under its own designation as &quot;''fucile controcarro 35(P)''.&quot;  Both names translate roughly as &quot;Anti-tank Rifle 35 (Polish).&quot;

In early 1940, one of the rifles, its stock and barrel sawed off, was smuggled out of Poland across the [[Tatra Mountains]] into [[Hungary]] for the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] by [[Krystyna Skarbek#Hungary|Krystyna Skarbek]] and Polish fellow [[courier]]s. The rifle never saw service with the Allies, however, because the drawings and specifications had been destroyed by the Poles during the invasion of Poland; [[reverse engineering]] would have required too much time.

==Description==
In appearance it resembled a rifle with a longer-than-normal barrel supported by a bipod at the front of the wooden stock. It was a [[Mauser]] style, [[bolt action|bolt-action]] [[rifle]], fed from a 4-round box magazine. The barrel was equipped with a [[muzzle brake]] to limit the recoil. The brake absorbed approximately 65% of the shot energy and the recoil was comparable to the standard Mauser rifle, even though the cartridge carried more than twice the amount of propellant. It had iron sights fixed for a 300-meter range. An unusual feature of this rifle was that it lacked a pistol grip, which was commonly seen on contemporary anti-tank rifles, and instead resembled an infantry rifle.

Unlike other [[anti-materiel rifle]]s of the time, the wz. 35 did not use an armour-piercing bullet with a hard core, but rather a lead core, full metal jacket bullet weighing 14.579&amp;nbsp;g; due to the high muzzle velocity this was effective even under shallow angles, as instead of ricocheting, the bullet would &quot;stick&quot; to the armour and punch a roughly 20&amp;nbsp;mm diameter hole. Calculated kinetic energy, by shot, before brake was about 11,850&amp;nbsp;J. The high energy was due to the relatively long barrel, and nitro powder giving a muzzle velocity of 1,275&amp;nbsp;m/s.&lt;ref&gt;http://heksan.umcs.lublin.pl/obliczarka/index.php&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Ammunition===
{{main|7.92mm DS}}

[[Image:MWP DS7 92.JPG|thumb|right|200px|[[7.92mm DS]] antitank [[cartridge (firearms)|cartridge]] (''left''). Box (''right'') held 12 cartridges.]]

In the late 1920s the Polish [[General Staff]] started the development of a light anti-tank weapon for the Polish infantry. In 1931 Lt. Colonel Tadeusz Felsztyn from the Institute of Armament Technology in [[Warsaw]] started the first tests of various low-calibre [[Cartridge (weaponry)|cartridges]]. After the tests of German-made [[Hagler]] bullets proved the possibilities of that type ammunition in perforating steel plate, the National Ammunition Factory in [[Skarżysko-Kamienna]] was ordered to develop its own 7.92&amp;nbsp;mm cartridge with a [[muzzle velocity]] of over 1,000 meters per second. After a series of tests, the new ''DS'' [http://www.antitank.co.uk/polish1.htm cartridge] was proposed.

The ''DS'' ammunition was originated from the [[7.92×57mm Mauser|standard 7.92×57mm]] [[Cartridge (firearms)|cartridge]] as used by both the Mauser rifle [[Gewehr 98|1898]] (wz.98) and its Polish variant the [[kbk wz. 29|Karabinek wz.29]]. The length of the cartridge was extended to {{convert|131.2|mm|in}} and the overall weight was {{convert|64.25|g|oz}}. After an additional series of tests the [[copper]] cartridge case was replaced with a case made of [[brass]] (67% copper/ 23% [[zinc]]).

The rounds armor-defeating properties were not through penetration, i.e. by punching the core through the armor like a typical [[Kinetic energy penetrator|penetrator]], but through the impact of the bullet flattening against the plate, transferring kinetic energy to the metal. The result was that the bullet would cause [[spall]]ing on the interior of the armor plate, ideally ejecting an approximately 20mm diameter fragment from the interior surface of the armour at high speed, which would then ricochet around the interior, hopefully killing crew and/or damaging equipment or engines (this is similar in concept to modern [[High-explosive squash head|HESH]] [[Anti-tank warfare|anti-tank]] rounds, albeit less potent). Due to the physics of spalling, the size of this spall was larger than the actual rifle caliber, and could theoretically do more damage ricocheting around inside the vehicle than the bullet itself would if it penetrated. The downside was that since the bullet itself was not designed to penetrate, it could not be filled with an [[Incendiary ammunition|incendiary]] component and used to ignite fuel tanks, or filled with [[tear gas]] (as used by the similar German [[7.92×94mm Patronen]] anti-tank rifle cartridge), which was intended to force the crew to evacuate, or at least greatly reduce their combat effectiveness, even if no-one was hit by the bullet itself.

===Rifle===

[[File:Kbur.jpg|500px|left|Wz. 35 anti-tank rifle]]
Simultaneous to the development of the ammunition, a young graduate of the [[Warsaw University of Technology]], Józef Maroszek was ordered to design an anti-tank rifle. On August 1, 1935, the Committee of Equipment and Armament officially ordered the rifle and in October the first tests of the new weapon commenced.

The rifle was based on the Mauser [[Gewehr 98]], with the action modified to sustain the higher pressure and length of the new cartridge and the barrel lengthened significantly. The first tests carried out in [[Brzesc Litewski|Brześć]] and [[Pionki]] showed that the new weapon was capable of penetrating a 15&amp;nbsp;mm steel plate at a distance of 300 metres with similar results against angled steel plate. Initially the barrel could only sustain up to 30 shots, after which it had to be replaced with a new one. However, this drawback was soon corrected and the final prototype could fire approximately 300 shots. The committee accepted the new design on November 25, 1935, and in December the Ministry of Military Affairs ordered the delivery of 5 rifles, 5000 cartridges and a set of spare barrels for further tests.

After the tests carried out by the Centre of Infantry Training in [[Rembertów]] proved the effectiveness and reliability of ''kbk ppanc wz.35'', the Ministry ordered 7610 rifles to be delivered to the Polish Army by the end of 1939. It is uncertain how many rifles were actually produced, but it is estimated that there were more than 6,500 delivered by September 1939.
[[File:2007.07.21 Gdynia, Polish &quot;soldier&quot; carrying Anti-tank rifle model 35 or 39.jpg|thumb|200px|right|2007 Military [[Re-enactment]] in [[Gdynia]]. Polish soldier with anti tank rifle.]] [[File:Finnish AT-rifle team.jpg|thumb|Finnish soldiers with Wz. 35 in 1942.]]

===Use===
The rifle was the main anti-tank weapon of an infantry [[platoon]]. Each infantry company and cavalry squadron was to be equipped with three rifles, each operated by a team of two soldiers. Additional anti-tank teams were to be created at a later stage. Although the weapon was successively introduced to the units, it remained a top secret. The rifles were kept in closed wooden crates, each marked with a number and a notice ''do not open; surveillance equipment''. The teams were trained in secret military facilities just before the war, beginning in July 1939, and  had to swear to preserve the secret.

The rifle was carried by the leader of the two-man rifle team on a carrying strap. The other member of the squad was his aide and provided him with cover while he was reloading. The weapon was usually fired from prone supported position with the bipod attached to the barrel. However, it could be also used in other positions, like prone unsupported and crouch. The effective range was 300 metres and the weapon was effective against all German tanks of the period (the [[Panzer I]], [[Panzer II|II]] and [[Panzer III|III]], as well as the Czech-made [[LT-35]] and [[LT-38]]) at 100 meters. At up to 400 meters it could penetrate all lightly armored vehicles. It could penetrate 15&amp;nbsp;mm of armor, sloped at 30° at 300 m distance, or 33&amp;nbsp;mm of armor at 100 m.
==== Panzerbüchse 35(p) ====
The ''Karabin przeciwpancerny wz.35'' was extensively used during the [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|Invasion of Poland]] of 1939 by most Polish units. After Poland was overrun by [[Germany]] and the [[Soviet Union]], large quantities of this weapon were captured. The Germans pressed it into service as ''Panzerbüchse 35 (polnisch)'' (PzB 35(p)), and sped up work on their own simplified, one-shot anti-tank rifle ''[[Panzerbüchse 39]]'' (PzB 39), which was merely a version of their already-in-service Panzerbüchse 38, several dozen of which were used during the invasion of Poland, with minor tweaks such as built in cartridge carriers. According to some sources, the Germans replaced the captured Polish DS ammunition, with their own 7.92&amp;nbsp;mm hardened-[[steel]]-core bullets.

The Soviet [[PTRD]] [[14.5×114mm]] anti-tank rifle also used a bolt based on the [[Mauser]] [[Gewehr 98]] rifle, as this design is legendary for its strength and simplicity and has become the most widely adopted and copied designs of all time. The Wz. 35 is itself inspired by the [[13.2mm TuF]] anti-tank rifle, also a scaled-up G98 rifle. The main difference is that while the TuF and PTRD were chambered in a large-caliber round, the Wz. 35 used an oversized cartridge case mated to a rifle-caliber 8mm bullet, giving very high velocity at the expense of hitting power. The Panzerbüchse 39 also used an 8mm bullet, but with an out-sized [[8mm Mauser]] cartridge case known as the [[7.92×94mm Patronen|7.92x94mm Patronen]], and a special [[Hardened steel|tool-steel]] cored bullet.

In 1940, Germany sold some 800 Polish antitank rifles to the [[Italy|Italian]] armed forces, which used them in combat under the designation ''Fucile Controcarro 35(P)'' until the end of [[World War II]].

==Survivors==
There are at least three in the [[United Kingdom]]. One is on exhibit in Poland, at Warsaw's [[Polish Army Museum]]; another is located in Armament Museum in [[Fort Winiary|Poznań Citadel]], and the last one is in Australian War Memorial in Canberra.  The Norwegian Armed Forces Museum holds several specimens of the wz 35.

The .wz 35 has recently been valued in England at $130,000.

==See also==
{{commons|Category:Wz.35}}
* [[Anti-tank rifle]]
* [[Boys Anti-tank Rifle]]
* [[Krystyna Skarbek#Hungary|Krystyna Skarbek]]

===Possible Descendant===
* [[Saboted light armor penetrator]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book |author=Departament Broni Piechoty |title=Dodatek do instrukcji o broni piechoty. Część I. Karabin wzór 35 |publisher=Polish Ministry of War |year=1938 |id=}}
* {{cite book |author=Zbigniew Gwóźdź, Piotr Zarzycki |title=Polskie konstrukcje broni strzeleckiej |publisher=SIGMA NOT |year=1993 |isbn=83-85001-69-7}}
* {{cite journal |author=Aleksander Smoliński |title=Wybrane problemy z historii karabinu przeciwpancernego wz. 35 |journal=MWP bulletin |year=1992 |volume= |pages=}}
* {{cite journal |author=Jerzy Sadowski |title=Karabin przeciwpancerny wz.35 w fortyfikacjach II RP |journal=Nowa Technika Wojskowa |year=1995 |volume=11 |pages=}}
* {{cite journal |author=Tadeusz Nowakowski |title=Karabin przeciwpancerny wz. 35 |journal=Nowa Technika Wojskowa |year=1995 |volume=6 |pages=}}

==External links==
* [http://www.antitank.co.uk Anti-Tank Rifle History and Collecting]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20091027135457/http://geocities.com/Augusta/8172/panzerfaust6.htm  WW II German Infantry Anti-Tank Weapons]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071026014038/http://hem.passagen.se/dadkri/Wz35.htm kb ppanc wz. 1935]
* [http://i18.photobucket.com/albums/b136/bonzo123/UR/PC160044.jpg Replica of kb ppanc wz. 1935]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{WWIIPolishInfWeapons}}
{{WWIIGermanInfWeapons}}
{{Anti-Tank Rifles}}
}}

[[Category:8 mm firearms]]
[[Category:Anti-tank rifles]]
[[Category:World War II infantry weapons of Poland]]
[[Category:Rifles of Poland]]
[[Category:Polish inventions]]</text>
      <sha1>2hky20ucft6nf48frp5okqjtj00xa8v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
