<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Yeop Mahidin Bin Mohamed Shariff</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6078582</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744025936</id>
      <parentid>735166945</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-12T17:36:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>203.106.154.186</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Summarize</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5879">{{BLP sources|date=July 2008}}
'''Yeop Mahidin bin Mohamed Shariff''' (20 February 1918 – 1999) was the first Director of [[Rejimen Askar Wataniah]], the reserves component of the [[Malaysian Army]]. He was widely regarded as the “''Father of Wataniah''” for his efforts in establishing the [[Rejimen Askar Wataniah]] as a credible force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=PENGARAH ASKAR WATANIAH PERTAMA|url=http://army.mod.gov.my/raw/index.php/bahagian-pasukan-simpanan/15-sejarah-ringkas-bps|publisher=army.mod.gov|accessdate=4 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Biography ==
{{unsourced section|date=July 2008}}

Yeop Mahidin was born on 20 February 1918 in [[Parit]], [[Perak]] to a Customs officer. He was educated at the Anderson School and a keen boxer who was a [[bantam weight]] champion. He was a keen [[Football (soccer)|footballer]], and was active in field hockey and cricket, in which he was once given the “Batsman Of The Year” award.

According to his family, Yeop Mahidin came from a long line of [[silat]] exponents who served as protectors to the Perak Sultanate. His children,both the men and the women in the family are known as  efficient fighters with a style of fighting handed down over generations. One of his sons, named Mokhtar, nicknamed Apin, went on to establish the largest silat schools in the United Kingdom.He is known as the Mahaguru Silat Gayong or Grand Master of Silat Gayong.

He aspired to join the [[Royal Malay Regiment|Malay Regiment]] but was discouraged to do so by his headmaster L.D Whitfield who wanted him to join the [[British Malaya|Malayan]] [[Civil Service]].  In 1937, Yeop Mahidin went to the [[Malay College]] to prepare him for life in the [[Civil Service]].

In 1938, Yeop Mahidin was appointed a [[magistrate]] in Telok Anson (now [[Teluk Intan]]) before transferring to [[Kajang]] in 1939. In 1940 he again transferred, this time to [[Kuala Lipis]] as Assistant [[District Officer]]. He joined the local Malay State Volunteer Rifles Reserve and commissioned a 2nd Lieutenant.

'''World War II'''

When World War II broke out, Yeop Mahidin  formed a resistance group called the Pahang Wataniah. The unit had a strength of 254 men and was assisted by Force 136, which assigned Major Richardson to help train the unit. His bravery and exploits earned him the nickname “Singa Melayu” (Malay Lion).
The main success of the team is still in the memories of Dato 'Yoep is the success they ambushed the Japanese Army, where a group of 20 locals under the leadership of Lt Confident to kill 30 to 40 people and destroyed 41 Japanese military vehicles. This success is the result of planning and selection of an ambush spot by Dato 'Yoep as the head of the team. 
During 1950, the team `Home Guard was formed and Dato 'Yoep was appointed as Deputy Director. The primary goal of the Home Guard is to assist the security forces in the face of the communist threat. In 1958, the team disbanded and Dato 'Yoep has been appointed as Chief Food Denial' Officer 'in Perak. When the Territorial Army was established to replace the Home Guard, Dato 'Yoep was appointed as the first Director of the Territorial Army with the rank of Colonel. In addition, he was also Chairman of the Armed Forces Boxing and Football. 
Then in November, 1963, Dato 'Yoep have left the military and became a District Officer of Kuala Lipis. In 1965, he was appointed as Secretary, Ministry of Social Welfare and in 1967 joined Felda settlers Affairs Director.

In 1945, Yeop Mahidin was made Commander of local resistance forces and made a Major. He was offered by the British to undergo military training in Britain but he refused.  Captain [[Abdul Razak bin Hussein]] (later Malaysia’s Second Prime Minister) and Lieutenant [[Ghazali bin Shafie]] (a renowned Malaysian Foreign Minister) was sent instead.

== Founding Rejimen Askar Wataniah ==
{{unsourced section|date=July 2008}}
In 1950, the British Malaya government formed the “Home Guard” and yeop Mahidin was made the Deputy Director of the Malayan Home Guard. The Home Guard was tasked with static local Defence and manned checkpoints that curbed the flow of supplies to Communist Terrorists.

In 1958, as the threat of the communist terrorists receded, the Malayan Home Guard was disbanded. The Malayan Territorial Army was formed in 1958 with the passing of the Territorial Army Ordinance 1958. The Territorial Army soon changed its name to Askar Wataniah. Yeop Mahidin was made the First Director of Askar Wataniah with the rank of Colonel.

== Retirement ==

Yeop Mahidin left the [[Rejimen Askar Wataniah|Askar Wataniah]] in 1963 when he was made the District Officer of Kuala Lipis.
Yeop Mahidin was also a renowned [[Silat]] exponent and instructor. [http://www.asianoutlook.com/sensilat.htm] [http://www.silat.f9.co.uk/senisilathaqq.htm]

He was also active in the [[Malaysian Olympic Movement]] was the Chef-de-Mission of the Malaysian contingent during the 1971 [[South East Asian Peninsular Games]] in Kuala Lumpur. [http://www.olympic.org.my/web/gamesrecords/sea/sea_pchefdemission.htm]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* [http://rmecc.mmu.edu.my/502AW/wataniah/pengasas.html  KOLONEL DATO' YEOP MAHIDIN BIN MOHAMED SHAFIFF]
* [http://www.rmaf.org.ph/Awardees/Biography/BiographyAbdulRazak.htm The 1967 Ramon Magsaysay Award for Community Leadership BIOGRAPHY of Tun Abdul Razak]
* The Japanese Occupation of Malaya, 1941-45 By Paul H. (Lecturer in History, National University of Singapore, Singapore) Kratoska pg 294
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mohamed Shariff, Yeop Mahidin bin}}
[[Category:Malaysian military personnel]]
[[Category:1918 births]]
[[Category:1999 deaths]]
[[Category:British Malaya military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:People from Perak]]
[[Category:Malaysian people of Malay descent]]
[[Category:Malaysian Muslims]]


{{Malaysia-bio-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>a0zbxotvurswd1srtadcck8kta3wzsc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
