<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>York Factory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>771425</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737592107</id>
      <parentid>735991266</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-03T20:53:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11634">{{Infobox historic site
| name                 = York Factory
| native_name          = 
| native_language      = 
| other_name           = 
| etymology            = 
| image                = HS34 1.jpg
| caption              = York Factory in 1853
| alt                  = 
| locmapin             =
| lat_degrees  =  | lat_minutes  =  | lat_seconds  =  | lat_direction  = N
| long_degrees =  | long_minutes =  | long_seconds =  | long_direction = W
| coord_parameters     = 
| coord_display        = inline,title
| coord_region         = 
| location             = [[Manitoba]], Canada
| area                 = 102 hectares
| elevation            = 
| founded              = 
| founder              = [[Hudson's Bay Company]]
| built                = 1788 to 1850
| original_use         = [[Fort]]; military structure; [[fur trade|fur trading]] [[trading post|post]]
| current_use          = 
| architect            = 
| architecture         = 
| governing_body       = Parks Canada
| owner                =
| visitation_num       = 
| visitation_year      = 
| website              = [https://web.archive.org/web/20140806220309/http://www.pc.gc.ca/eng/lhn-nhs/mb/yorkfactory/index.aspx Parks Canada official website]
| designation1         = National Historic Site of Canada
| designation1_offname =
| designation1_date    = 1936
| designation1_number  =
| designation2         = 
| designation2_offname =
| designation2_date    =
| designation2_number  =
}}

'''York Factory''' was a settlement and [[Hudson's Bay Company]] [[factory (trading post)]] located on the southwestern shore of [[Hudson Bay]] in northeastern [[Manitoba]], [[Canada]] at the mouth of the [[Hayes River]], approximately {{convert|200|km|miles}} south-southeast of [[Churchill, Manitoba|Churchill]]. York Factory was one of the first fur-trading posts established by the HBC, built in 1684 and used in that business for more than 270 years. The settlement was headquarters of the HBC's Northern Department from 1821 to 1873.&lt;ref name=&quot;canenc&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |first=Frits |last=Pannekoek |title=York Factory |work=[[The Canadian Encyclopedia]] |publisher=[[Historica Canada]] |edition=online |date=7 February 2006 |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/york-factory/ |access-date=5 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1957, the HBC closed it down. The remains of the complex were designated a [[National Historic Sites of Canada|National Historic Site of Canada]] in 1936.&lt;ref&gt;{{CRHP|12789|York Factory|17 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It has been owned by the Canadian government since 1968 and the site is now operated by [[Parks Canada]]. There is currently no one living permanently at York Factory, aside from a summer residence for Parks Canada staff and nearby seasonal hunting camps. The wooden structure at the park site dates from 1831 and is the oldest and largest wooden structure built on [[permafrost]] in Canada.

York Factory is located on the north bank of the Hayes River about {{convert|7|mi|km|0|abbr=off|order=flip}} inland. The mouth of the [[Nelson River]] is to the north, across &quot;Point of Marsh&quot;. The Hayes is a more practical canoe route, although the Nelson is much larger (it drains Lake Winnipeg). Seagoing ships anchored at Five Fathom Hole {{convert|7|mi|km|0|abbr=on|order=flip}} from the fort due to the shallow bottom, and goods were transferred by smaller boats. The [[Shamattawa Airport]] and [[Gillam Airport]] are close.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://shamattawafirstnation.com/ |title=About Us |accessdate=8 Jun 2014 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160116105025/http://shamattawafirstnation.com/ |archivedate=January 16, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Ruperts land.svg|left|thumb|Rupert's Land, showing location of York Factory]]  
[[File:York-Factory-Express.png|thumb|left|Map of the route of the York Factory Express, 1820s to 1840s. Modern political boundaries shown.]]
During the 17th through late 19th century, the depot at York Factory and its predecessors were the central base of operations for the Hudson's Bay Company's (HBC)'s control of the [[fur trade]] and other business dealings with the [[First Nations]] throughout [[Rupert's Land]], the vast territory comprising the entire watershed of Hudson Bay, and which now forms much of Canada.

The first three HBC posts were established on [[James Bay]] about 1670. In 1684, Fort Nelson (a fur trading post at the mouth of the Nelson River, Manitoba, Canada and the first headquarters of the Hudson's Bay Company) was established at the mouth of the nearby [[Nelson River]].  The company built a second fort, York Factory, on the Hayes river, naming it after the [[James II of England|Duke of York]].  The establishment of these forts provoked a response from [[New France]]. In the [[Hudson Bay expedition (1686)]], the French marched overland from Quebec and captured all the posts on James Bay.  During [[King William's War]], France several times sent a naval force to [[Hudson Bay]] to capture or destroy the fort.  In 1690, [[Pierre Le Moyne d'Iberville]] tried but was driven away by a larger English ship.  In 1694, d'Iberville returned and [[Capture of York Factory|captured York Factory]] with a show of force. He renamed it Fort Bourbon.  English forces returned the next year and retook the fort from its small French garrison.  In 1697, d'Iberville won the [[Battle of Hudson's Bay]], the largest [[Arctic]] naval battle in North American history.  The French force won in the naval battle with three [[Kingdom of England|English]] [[warship]]s and again captured York Factory - D'Iberville had laid siege to the fort in such a way as to give the appearance of having a much stronger force.  York Factory was held by the French until 1713, when it was returned to the [[Kingdom of Great Britain|British]] in the [[Treaty of Utrecht]].  At that time, the HBC again placed its northern headquarters at York Factory, at the mouth of the Hayes River.

Between 1788 and 1795, the company constructed an [[octagon]]al [[star fort]] of stone and brick at York Factory. The choice of material was poor, however, as the stone and brick could not stand up to heaving permafrost, and in 1831, the stone fort was razed. The three-story center section of the current compound was completed that same year, with the two-story wings finished within the two years that followed.

[[Image:YorkFactoryaerial.jpg|right|thumb|Aerial view of York Factory, ca. 1925]]
During its first century, the depot operated by drawing First Nations traders to the post, rather than sending its own traders out into the field.  Its position at the mouth of the Nelson allowed access by [[canoe]] from the watersheds of the [[Saskatchewan River|Saskatchewan]] and [[Red River of the North|Red]] rivers.

In the late 18th century, the centralized nature of the [[Hudson's Bay Company]]'s operation from the depot began to become a disadvantage against the more nimble ''[[voyageurs]]'' of the [[North West Company]]. They operated by traveling among the First Nations on the vast water network of lakes and rivers. In response, the company began sending out its own traders from the depot and eventually established inland posts, first along the Saskatchewan River, and then stretching as far as the [[Oregon Country]]. Twice annually from 1821 to 1846, brigades known as the [[York Factory Express]] traveled overland to [[Fort Vancouver]], headquarters for the HBC's [[Columbia Department]].  They brought supplies and trade goods and returned with furs destined for London.

By the mid nineteenth century, York Factory had developed an extensive trading post and settlement with fifty on-site buildings, most currently destroyed, and a permanent workforce. However, the reign of York Factory as one of the most important Hudson Bay Company posts declined within two decades. This is due to the transfer of Northwest Territory to Canada, and changes in the HBC Northwest transportation network’s increased use of the United States railways, steamboats, and Red River carts for Upper Fort Garry’s southern supply line. The depot remained in company hands after the acquisition of Rupert's Land by the [[Dominion of Canada]] In 1870. In 1872, York Factory’s role diminished to only outfitting to particular posts located in Manitoba. The post’s fur trade headquarters title was removed a year later and certain responsibilities were transferred to Upper Fort Gary, which is now known as Winnipeg.&lt;ref name=Voices&gt;{{cite book |editor-last1=Beardy |editor-first1=Flora |editor-last2=Coutts |editor-first2=Robert |title=Voices from Hudson Bay: Cree Stories from York Factory |location=Montréal |publisher=McGill-Queen’s University Press |date=1996 |p=xxi |isbn=0-7735-1440-6 |url={{google books|_CsLnP-tJGgC|plainurl=yes}} |access-date=5 October 2015 |ref=Voices}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The importance of York Factory declined further. In the years 1874-75, the post virtually stopped receiving supplies and goods to be transported elsewhere. The following years, specifically 1878, the post’s British products began being relocated to [[Norway House]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Innis |first=Harold A. |author-link=Harold Innis |title=The Fur Trade in Canada: An Introduction to Canadian Economic History |location=Toronto, Ontario |publisher=University of Toronto Press |date=2001 |orig-year=1930 |edition=reprint |p=341 |isbn=0-8020-8196-7 |url={{google books|eCgps70cHV4C|plainurl=yes|page=341}} |access-date=5 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; York Factory had a brief upswing when it was designated the headquarters for the new Nelson River District in 1911. However, the Factory lost the title in 1929 to Churchill due to the establishment of the railway line that connected Churchill to Winnipeg. Until closing, York Factory would be known as a regional trading post.&lt;ref name=Voices/&gt;

The historic site is currently staffed by Parks Canada from June 1 to mid-September. Archaeological excavations of the 18th-century &quot;octagon&quot; have been conducted since 1991.

In 1957, Hudson's Bay York Factory closed.  The residents were relocated to [[York Factory First Nation|York Landing Cree Nation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=About Us |url=http://www.yorkfactoryfirstnation.ca/?page_id=2 |work=York Factory First Nation |accessdate=16 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; about {{convert|116|km|m}} ENE of [[Thompson, Manitoba]], as well as Split Lake and Shamattawa. In oral stories, Cree elders who once resided at York Factory in the first half of the twentieth century recalled their desires to remain at Kihci-waskahikan or Great House when operations ceased. Kihci-waskahikan and Great House are words for the post used by the Swampy Cree, West Main Cree, Lowland Cree, and/or Home Guard Cree.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Voices|Beardy &amp; Coutts (1996)]], pp. xi &amp; xvi&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[York Factory Express]]
*[[North American fur trade]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refbegin}}

;Secondary sources
*{{cite book | first=Peter C. | last=Newman | title=The Empire of the Bay | date= 1998 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|York Factory, Manitoba}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070911203247/http://www.pc.gc.ca/lhn-nhs/mb/yorkfactory/index_e.asp Parks Canada: The York Factory National Historic Site of Canada]

{{Canadian colonies}}
{{Manitoba}}
{{NHSC}}

{{Coord|57|00|9.8|N|92|18|17.3|W|region:CA-MB_type:landmark|display=title}}

[[Category:French forts in Canada]]
[[Category:Fur trade]]
[[Category:Ghost towns in Manitoba]]
[[Category:Hudson's Bay Company forts]]
[[Category:Localities in Manitoba]]
[[Category:National Historic Sites in Manitoba]]
[[Category:Populated places on Hudson Bay]]</text>
      <sha1>t9lytts1lf9z67zztt3wfgesf4u9kar</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
