<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Special Air Service Regiment</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1097535</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739939699</id>
      <parentid>737001380</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-18T01:51:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Melbguy05</username>
        <id>26535467</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Removal of info on three year training and operational cycle */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16790">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=11:58, 12 June 2014 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Special Air Service Regiment/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=612623906
|topic=Warfare
|dykdate=23 June 2014
|dykentry= ... that the '''[[Special Air Service Regiment|SAS]]''' is based in Australia?
|currentstatus=GA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{MILHIST|class=GA|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|ANZSP=y|Middle-Eastern=y|Southeast-Asian=y|Cold-War=y}}
{{WP Australia|class=GA|importance=mid|military=yes|military-importance=High}}
}}
{{backwardscopy|url=http://www.sasspecialairservice.com/SASR-SAS-Australia.html|title=SASR Australian SAS|date=publication date ca. 2009|author=saspsecialairservice.com|comments=The oldest archive I can find for this website is 2009. This content has been in our article for years and shows substantial sign of natural evolution. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;oldid=29845191 This is what the article looked like on 1 December 2005. A few weeks later, to content that already bore some resemblance to that site, Nick [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;diff=31669118&amp;oldid=31167568 added history]. But it was not by any means word for word as it appears on the external site. See the addition of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=32566979 this sentence], which is published on that external site, and [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=33113652 this fragment] and [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=33227634 this one] and [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=33720989 these]. It goes on that way, in a manner very natural for Wikipedia articles. --[[User:Moonriddengirl|Moonriddengirl]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Moonriddengirl|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:28, 16 March 2013 (UTC)}}

== Weapons used by SASR ==

Hi there, I stumbled across a series of pictures of a well-known SASR soldier who used a M-14 in Afghanistan. 

http://m14forum.com/modern-m14/95802-australian-sas-soldier-receives-vc-action-while-using-his-m-14-a.html

Might be worth updating the page to reflect this. Cheers. 

[[Special:Contributions/27.252.5.69|27.252.5.69]] ([[User talk:27.252.5.69|talk]]) 05:54, 25 May 2015 (UTC) Jake
: Gday. Thanks for this suggestion - I've added something on this now. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 13:33, 25 May 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Special Air Service Regiment]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=713230468 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://i-mockery.com/forum/showthread.php?t=13525

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:43, 2 April 2016 (UTC)

== Four sabre squadrons ==

Has it been confirmed that there are four sabre squadrons? or is the only source a newspaper article. --[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 08:39, 14 August 2016 (UTC)
Brigadier Beutel has stated regimental headquarters, four squadrons, an operational support squadron, a specialist support squadron and a signals squadron. But &quot;Base Squadron&quot;?--[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 08:44, 14 August 2016 (UTC)

:Sorry, I hit enter half way through the edit summary. The Hansard transcript and Defence submission to the inquiry you found which explain the redevelopment of Campbell Barracks repeatedly states that the SAS has four squadrons, as well as supporting elements which I take to mean from the context that these squadrons are all &quot;operational&quot;. The existence of 4 Squadron has also been repeatedly reported over the last few years and never denied by the government so I don't think that there's any need to put provisos around it any more. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 08:49, 14 August 2016 (UTC)
:: I've no issue with this being updated in light of newer sources becoming available; however, it seems to me that the &quot;organization&quot; section now doesn't explicitly address 4 Squadron and presents it in the structure without any explaination. Specifically it now reads simply: &quot; Two sabre squadrons maintain the regiment's warfighting capability and train for operational contingencies, while a third squadron is maintained on rotation for counter terrorist or recovery operations designated as the Tactical Assault Group.&quot; What of the 4 Squadron? Of cse the previous version included: &quot;It is believed that there may be a fourth sabre squadron&quot; with a ref which at least acknowledged the reason for its inclusion in the list but that has now been removed. Given that it now seems to be publicly acknowledged is there some other way we can mention 4 Squadron to explain it now being on the list? I.e should we simply say &quot;three sabre squadrons maintain...&quot; or would this be inaccurate given the 4 Squadron seems to have a fairly different mission to the others? Are there any suggestions on how to address this? Thanks. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:09, 16 August 2016 (UTC)
::: Or maybe we just include something like: &quot;A fourth sabre squadron has recently been publicly acknowledged&quot; or something like that and use the Hansard entry as a source? Thoughts? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:26, 16 August 2016 (UTC)
::::David Horner's book explained the roles of the three squadrons pre-2001 and the rotations. Brigadier Beutel states that the regiment's roles and responsibilities have expanded exponentially over the last 10 years. There is no information on squadrons or rotations with this new structure. Roles for the squadrons could be black role x 1 (TAG), green role x 2 (contingency squadrons) and x 1 (with an unknown squadron designation) possibly similar to UK [[Special Reconnaissance Regiment]]. --[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 17:35, 16 August 2016 (UTC)
::::: Reading the Epstein &amp; Welch article again, it is describing a special recovery operation.  ASIS in the early 1980s started to establish a SR capability, including females, whilst the SASR had the CT/TAG and then SR was given to the SASR in the mid 80s so they had both CT/SR. This 2010 [[https://defence-honours-tribunal.gov.au/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/SASR-Final-Report-Public-Release.pdf report]] states &quot;As Special Operations Command has developed the SR capability it has found that it needs to send elements overseas to prepare for possible SR tasks, and the Command is now seeking to have the maintenance of the SR capability declared to be a standing, ongoing operation.&quot; I think the new squadron is tasked as a special recovery squadron. --[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 22:41, 16 August 2016 (UTC) 
:::::: Given that the Horner ref about the roles of the squadrons is dated (2002) and only covers three of them I've added the date for context into the text. I've also now mentioned that 4 Squadron exists but have left out anything about its role until / unless we can find something explicit which clearly states what it does. These are my edits [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=734823910&amp;oldid=734680575] does anyone have anything to add / change? I agree SR is likely but wouldn't want to guess. Thanks. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 23:10, 16 August 2016 (UTC)  
:::::::Various news reports have noted that 4 Squadron's duties include protecting ASIS personnel in combat zones, which is also a task conducted by the British SAS. Given that only point in time information exists on the SASR's structure and operational model, Anotherclown's changes look good. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 10:19, 17 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::::: Ack fairpoint Nick there certainly is some information about roles so it wouldn't be right to say it was &quot;unknown&quot; either, although it looks to me like we agree on this currently (Melbguy05 or Nick-D pls correct me if I wrong of cse!) I guess I'd just prefer to try to be cautious and not state something unless the sources were definitive (as there seem to be a lot of incorrect information around regarding special forces without us adding to it - anymore than we already have at least). Just to be clear though I'm happy with the way this is currently covered. All the best. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 20:49, 17 August 2016 (UTC)

Specialist support squadron maybe the old Base Squadron?--[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 08:58, 14 August 2016 (UTC) 
: Agree - I've changed this now to reflect the Hansard source which looks good to me. This is my edit [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=734676792&amp;oldid=734676411], happy to revert if others disagree though. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:09, 16 August 2016 (UTC)
4th is not at Swan Island, all at Campbell Barracks.--[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 09:00, 14 August 2016 (UTC)
: Gday do you have a reference for this? All we can go off at the moment is what we have in the refs available. The Epstein &amp; Welch article from 2012 states it is based at Swan Island etc. If you have an updated ref by all means pls go ahead, although I don't see any harm in retaining the older information too in some form, even if its proved inaccurate as we can specifically acknowledge that etc. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:09, 16 August 2016 (UTC)
::In the [[http://www.aph.gov.au/DocumentStore.ashx?id=2fca4f86-f011-44da-82ce-b169fa168ae4&amp;subId=353034 statement of evidence]] for Campbell Barracks Redevelopment by Department of Defence, on page 4 &quot;There are four Squadrons within the SASR, which are currently housed in separate buildings spread across the Barracks.&quot; and &quot;The SASR requires a new facility that houses the Regimental Headquarters and the four squadrons within one building complex&quot;. The Swan Island Army Detachment (SIAD) facilities were redeveloped recently for nearly $27 million as part of the Enhanced Land Force Project around the time of the Epstein &amp; Welch article. --[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 17:35, 16 August 2016 (UTC)
::: Yes that does seem to make it clear they are all at Campbell Barracks, so perhaps the info in Epstein &amp; Welch is out of date / wrong or maybe its use of the phrase &quot;based at Swan Island&quot; is a bit loose and really just means that it has used that facility for training etc. That said I think the way our article is currently worded does imply that all squadrons are co-located at Campbell. For instance follow recent rewrites it now says: &quot;Based at Campbell Barracks, it is a battalion-sized element and is known to be made up...&quot; Is that sufficient? It seems ok to me but certainly if there are suggestions on further rewording pls fire away. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 23:10, 16 August 2016 (UTC)

== Removal of info on three year training and operational cycle ==

Gday - I note that the information from Miller and from Micheletti re the three year training and operational cycle has recently been removed - per these edits [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special_Air_Service_Regiment&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=734891126&amp;oldid=734824972]. As both of these sources are from 2003 (i.e. 13 years ago) and there has obviously been significant changes in the unit since then so I agree that this is very probably dated / now wrong and can see the logic for its removal. That said I am wondering if there would be any value in retaining something from it given we now have nothing on the topic at all (for instance if we reword a bit and acknowledge the date of the information in the text as we have in some other places etc.). Or does anyone know of more up to date sources which cover these aspects? Thanks in advance. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 20:57, 17 August 2016 (UTC)
:Yes, I agree that it should continue to be noted - though the date of this information should be clear. It seems probably that SASR squadrons continue to rotate through different roles and levels of readiness, given that this is the norm for most other elements of the ADF as far as I'm aware (eg, the RAAF's three F/A-18 Hornet rotate through different roles, as do the Army's three combat brigades). [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 10:35, 18 August 2016 (UTC)
:: I guess that is the main part I see as missing, i.e. discussion of rotation of roles b/n sqns, otherwise the recent update and re-write looks good to me. {{ping|Melbguy05}} I would be keen in knowing your opinion about this before proceeding. Thanks. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 22:33, 20 August 2016 (UTC)
:::The information is too dated. The three year cycle information was first published either in the 1st edition of Phantoms of the Jungle in 1989 or later Army magazine articles in the early 90s. Nothing published recent that I know of with roles of the four squadrons and their rotation periods. There has to be a rotation above all for the TAG given the high level of commitment being on call. --[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 16:03, 30 August 2016 (UTC)
:::: Thanks for that. Ack the sources being dated, I'll leave it as it is for now but keep a look out for any more recent sources that cover rotation of roles (as it seems fairly obvious that this would still have to occur etc). [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 05:04, 31 August 2016 (UTC)
::::: This is from 2003 from a counter terrorist perspective [[http://webarchive.nla.gov.au/gov/20030222191627/http://www.veteransreview.gov.au:80/report/chapters/ch17.htm Report of the Review of Veterans' Entitlements]]...&quot;On completion of initial selection and testing....SASR members are posted to a squadron and undergo further training to develop their skills and teamwork. Basically, the SASR is divided into four squadrons — one on line, one off line, one war squadron and one in training. The training squadron is made up of those who have passed the initial selection and testing, and are training to become operational members of the SASR. The war squadron is specially trained for more traditional wartime activities, and the two other squadrons are specialist CT squadrons.&quot; &quot;A squadron will normally be kept on line for six months before rotating with the off-line squadron.&quot;      Later from 2009 [[https://defence-honours-tribunal.gov.au/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/SASR-Final-Report-Public-Release.pdf report]] in regards to off line TAG and on line TAG, &quot;posted to an online TAG&quot;, &quot;Before going online, CT/SR personnel undertake individual or team training over a period of three to four months before they are allocated to an online TAG.&quot; and &quot;intense period of final training (colloquially referred to in units as the ‘CT Olympics’)&quot;. The six months is redacted in this report &quot;The period for online CT/SR service has normally been [ ].&quot; --[[User:Melbguy05|Melbguy05]] ([[User talk:Melbguy05|talk]]) 01:50, 18 September 2016 (UTC)

== Is any information available on use of mortars? ==

Does anyone know of any references which clarify use of mortars (i.e. specifically size / type). I'm assuming they have recently used / are using both 60 mm commando mortars and 81 mm but I can't find anything that specific. The only refs I can dig up just mention mortars and don't specify type. I'd been keen on adding a bit more on this if something were available. Thanks. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 22:49, 20 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>0m1yr7jr48inz13lh5sna4fopsd8eo2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
