<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Torvioll</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20076860</id>
    <revision>
      <id>669258758</id>
      <parentid>559081283</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-06-30T00:01:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2015-06-29.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10331">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=16:22, 30 March 2011
|action1link=Talk:Battle of Torvioll/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=421392038
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war
}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Medieval=y|Ottoman=y|Balkan=y}}
{{WikiProject Albania|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2011-06-29|oldid1=436875566|date2=2015-06-29|oldid2=668890322}}

== Do not remove the categories before talking in the talk page ==

This goes for [[User:Jaraalbe|Jaraalbe]] and other trollers. Otherwise, I have an ANI ready.[[user:sulmues|sulmues]] ([[user talk:sulmues|talk]])--Sulmues 15:10, 22 January 2010 (UTC)

== Soon? Go back? Reins? Rebellion? ==

''&quot;who, soon after his father (John Kastrioti) died, decided to go back to his native land and take the reins of a new Albanian rebellion.&quot;''

John Kastrioti died on May 2, 1437. Skanderbeg deserted Ottoman Empire army on November 28, 1443 when Ottoman Empire lost [[Battle of Nish]] against Hunyadi.

I think that it is wrong to hide from readers fact that '''it took Skanderbeg 6 years, 6 months and 26 days''' after his father died to decide to go back to his native land (btw he was there in 1437, because sultan appointed him to be lord of Krujë zeamet in period 1437–1438, therefore there was no need for him to go back to his native land after his father died, because he was there, being sipahi within Ottoman Empire and participating in battles of Ottoman Empire during next more than 6 and half years (period that is hard to be reffered as soon after his father's death).

It was impossible for Skanderbeg to go back to his native land and take the reins of new Albanian rebellion because there was no rebellion that he could take reins of when he decided to go back to his native land after deserting Ottoman army on November 28, 1443.

Since Skanderbeg's decision was not connected with his father's death and since there was no rebellion when he decided on November 28, 1443 to go back, I propose to change that sentence to correspond with informations from reliable sources and basic logic and delete above mentioned part.
--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:39, 10 December 2010 (UTC)
:This was the 15th century. Six months was not much back then. And [[Oliver Schmitt|Oliver Jens Schmitt]] says that the only reason Skanderbeg returned to Albania was to avenge his father's death. George Arianiti was still defiant in the South.--[[User:Gaius Claudius Nero|Gaius Claudius Nero]] ([[User talk:Gaius Claudius Nero|talk]]) 21:26, 10 December 2010 (UTC)
:: I did read carefully. It was not six months. It was 6 years, 6 months and 26 days.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 22:11, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

== Who was Skanderbeg? ==

''&quot;Skanderbeg was a renegade Ottoman captain of Albanian origin.&quot;''

I find this sentence '''absurd''':
# Skanderbeg deserted Ottoman Empire army more than 8 month before this battle, gained control over Kroja and many other castles, elected as leader of League of Lezhe and fought this battle on June 29, 1444. When Battle of Torvioll was fought he was not anymore renegade Ottoman captain, but leader of League of Lezhe.
# Even if there was rank of captain in Ottoman Army, Skanderbeg was not captain but much higher rank.
# And finally, ethnic origin of Skanderbeg is disputed and that dispute is probably described in every single work about him (except main body of the article on wikipedia) and writing only information that he is of Albanian origin without description of this dispute is violation of WP:NPOV.

I propose to change above mentioned sentence to:

“Skanderbeg was leader of [[League of Lezhe]].”

--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:53, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

: Maybe it is better to merge beggining of this two sentences:
: “Skanderbeg was a renegade Ottoman captain of Albanian origin. He, along with 300 other Albanians fighting at the battle of Nish, deserted the Ottoman army to head towards Krujë which fell quickly through a subversion.” 

: to be:

: “Skanderbeg along with 300 other Albanians fighting at the battle of Nish, deserted the Ottoman army to head towards Krujë which fell quickly through a subversion.” --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:57, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

== Peacock terms and POV ==

[[Wikipedia:Peacock#Puffery|Peacock terms]] is requesting:
# Strive to eliminate expressions that are flattering, disparaging, vague, clichéd, or endorse a particular point of view.
# Instead of making unprovable proclamations about a subject's importance, use facts and attribution to demonstrate that importance.

There are lot of peacock terms that are supporting disputed perspective of Skanderbeg and his Albanianess and therefore those terms should be replaced with more appropriate that would not violate wikipedia policies.

From there, Skanderbeg continued to reconsolidate his father's lands by laying siege to the '''most important''' fortresses in central Albania which had been occupied by Turkish forces. He then participated in establishing the League of Lezhë, a confederation of Albanian princedoms united in war against the Ottoman Empire. Murad II, realizing the threat, sent his''' most experienced''' captain, Ali Pasha, to crush the rebellion with a force of 25,000 men.

Skanderbeg, '''well-versed''' in Ottoman tactics and strategy, expected a reaction so he moved with 15,000 of his own men to defeat Ali Pasha's army.

The victory served as a '''huge''' morale boost to the Albanian men and princes who gave Skanderbeg much support.

'''All of these were unsuccessful''', with the League only yielding once Skanderbeg died.(this is not true)

..... 

I could copy paste whole article. But it needs serious reconstructuring because it is serious violation of WP:NPOV and written in absurd glorifying perspective.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 16:11, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

== Venetian occupation of Lezhe? ==
{{resolved}}
''&quot;Venetian occupied town of Lezhë&quot;''

Occupation occurs when the control and authority over a territory passes to a hostile army. Control over town of Lezhe was given by Dukagjini family without fight. [http://www.rastko.rs/rastko-bl/istorija/corovic/istorija/4_1.html]. It is wrong to state that Lezhe was occupied.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 16:17, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

{{Talk:Battle of Torvioll/GA1}}

== Inaccurate map ==
{{Not resolved}}
''&quot;Ali Pasha, one of Murad's most favoured commanders, left Üsküp (Skopje) in June 1444 with an army of 25,000 – primary sources say 40,000 – in Albania's direction.&quot;''

The map is inaccurate and misleading and contradicts above sentence. It presents Ottoman forces coming from Prizren (although OE captured Prizren in 1455) and Bitola, although the text of the article explains that they came from Skopje.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 08:58, 28 December 2011 (UTC)
: [http://books.google.rs/books?ei=Ud_6Tqa1LKj14QTJ38WNCA&amp;id=e3xpAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=Ali-pasha+torvioll&amp;q=%22En+juin+1444%2C+une+arm%C3%A9e+turque+de+25+000+hommes%2C+command%C3%A9e+par+Ali+pacha%2C+p%C3%A9n%C3%A9trait+en+Albanie+par+Ochrid.%22#search_anchor Above mentioned assertion connected with Skopje should be double-checked. &quot;En juin 1444, une armée turque de 25 000 hommes, commandée par Ali pacha, pénétrait en Albanie par Ochrid].&quot; - Stefanaq Pollo, Arben Puto, Kristo Frashëri, Skënder Anamali.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 09:26, 28 December 2011 (UTC)
:: [http://books.google.rs/books?id=kMxBAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=Ali-pasha+skanderbeg+1444&amp;dq=Ali-pasha+skanderbeg+1444&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=T-P6Tv2kCpSP4gTJnMSNCA&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAw Kristo Frashëri] is probably most precise. He stated that Ottoman army entered Albania &quot;[http://books.google.rs/books?ei=T-P6Tv2kCpSP4gTJnMSNCA&amp;id=kMxBAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=Ali-pasha+skanderbeg+1444&amp;q=%22from+the+Dibra+district%22#search_anchor from the Dibra district]&quot; (at that time there was no other Dibra district besides [[Sanjak of Debar]]). There are many other sources which emphasize Dibra district.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 09:43, 28 December 2011 (UTC)

== Branilo? ==

There are sources (like [http://books.google.rs/books?id=JmGMLUR-0EwC&amp;q=%22+Ali+Pasha,+with+40000+men,+was+already+on+the+march.+Scander-+beg's+little+army+consisted+of+7000+foot+and+8000+horse,+besides+which+Branilo+commanded+a+corps+3000+strong%22&amp;dq=%22+Ali+Pasha,+with+40000+men,+was+already+on+the+march.+Scander-+beg's+little+army+consisted+of+7000+foot+and+8000+horse,+besides+which+Branilo+commanded+a+corps+3000+strong%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Veb6TtOuJuPe4QTj3JXVBg&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA this]) which mention certain Branilo as one of the commanders in this battle. I propose to further research this valuable information about this commander of Skanderbeg's forces who commanded with 3,000 men.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 09:54, 28 December 2011 (UTC)

== Ajdin Muzaka ==
{{Unresolved}}
If [[Ajdin Muzaka]] was one of the important Skanderbeg's commanders, that information should be presented in the infobox. Together with information that he was killed in this battle, if the article about him is true.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 10:11, 28 December 2011 (UTC)

== What about Crnojević? ==

''&quot;Among the nobles that attended were George Arianiti, Paul Dukagjini, Andrea Thopia, Lekë Dushmani, Teodor Korona, Peter Spani, Lekë Zaharia, and Paul Stres Balsha.&quot;''

Is there any particular reason for excluding Stefan Crnojević and his three sons from the list of nobleman who forged League of Lezhe?--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:51, 9 June 2013 (UTC)

== Paul Stres Balsha ==

Who is Paul Stres Balsha?--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 15:52, 9 June 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>m3d68im27yd1b5grz64evv3evjojk3n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
