<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:North American XF-108 Rapier</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>8474718</id>
    <revision>
      <id>655294954</id>
      <parentid>490449124</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-04-07T04:06:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SporkBot</username>
        <id>12406635</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove template per [[Wikipedia:Templates for discussion/Log/2015 March 16|TFD outcome]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7105">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=07:33, 29 July 2011
|action1link=Talk:North American XF-108 Rapier/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=441999019
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War
}}
{{WPMILHIST|Aviation-task-force=yes|class=GA
|US-task-force=y|Cold-War=yes
}}
{{WPAVIATION|class=GA|Aircraft-project=y
}}

== Armament Questions ==
Firstly, I'm puzzled by the armament data listed in this article.  I do remember hearing that, when they were developing the XF-108, they had flirted with the idea of fitting the aircraft with 2 x 20mm cannon, and/or the provision to carry some 2.75&quot; rockets.  I don't remember reading anything about the aircraft carrying 4x20mm cannon.  I also do not remember reading about the aircraft being fitted with the provision to be able to carry and release bombs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Secondly, I have read that there was a variant of the GAR-9/AIM-47 that had folding fins, and I do remember hearing it was being designed during the XF-108's timeframe &lt;i&gt;(Though I could be wrong, and it could have been developed during the YF-12 period, but I did read it was conceived during the XF-108 program)&lt;/i&gt;.  I've seen drawings which showed the aircraft carrying three missiles in the bay, however no folding fins were shown.  Would the folding fins have allowed 4 to be carried? [[User:AVKent882|AVKent882]] ([[User talk:AVKent882|talk]]) 18:44, 11 June 2010 (UTC)

== Any survivors? ==
What happened to the mock-up? Is it on display somewhere? Should be mentioned in the article.
:Hmmm, you're right. IIRC I read that the mock-up did survive and ended up at the Smithsonian, but I'll have to track it down. [[User:Maury Markowitz|Maury]] 12:14, 29 August 2007 (UTC)

== Discrepancy? ==
This article states that the A-5 Vigilante incorporated a number of the design features and systems of the XF-108, but the A-5's article [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A-5_Vigilante] makes no such connection. [[User:24.115.82.38|24.115.82.38]] 20:20, 19 October 2007 (UTC)
:Definitely a connection, it will be established in the upcoming rewrite and I will make that connection clear in the A-5 Vigilante article. FWiW [[User:Bzuk|Bzuk]] ([[User talk:Bzuk|talk]]) 12:46, 30 March 2009 (UTC).
::Did the F-108 have any FBW systems?  I know the A3J/A-5 Vigilante did (they called it &quot;electric flight&quot; I believe but it's the same thing), it also had the all-moving tail, so I'm wondering if the F-108 had FBW as well?  [[User:AVKent882|AVKent882]] ([[User talk:AVKent882|talk]]) 16:36, 11 June 2010 (UTC)

== Revision started ==
Before starting a more extensive rewrite, I am canvassing for any other editor's comments. I am now in the process of gathering research material. FWiW [[User:Bzuk|Bzuk]] ([[User talk:Bzuk|talk]]) 18:42, 29 March 2009 (UTC).
:Apparently there were two different design studies. The photo and three-view show the original design mock-up. Bill Gunston's ''Fighters of the Fifties'' has a brief overview of the differences. (pp. 178-179 in my copy) Cheers.--[[User:Phyllis1753|Phyllis1753]] ([[User talk:Phyllis1753|talk]]) 16:52, 11 April 2009 (UTC)
:...and Lloyd Jones ''U.S. Fighters...'' has a three-view of the second version.--[[User:Phyllis1753|Phyllis1753]] ([[User talk:Phyllis1753|talk]]) 17:34, 11 April 2009 (UTC)
==Unusual number of design and designation names==
This particular aircraft has been afflicted by a tremendous number of names and designations. It appears as the F-108, F-108A, YF-108A pre-production as well as company designation NA-236, NA-257 (the designations used prior to the USAF providing both a number and name to the project). FWiW [[User:Bzuk|Bzuk]] ([[User talk:Bzuk|talk]]) 04:06, 1 August 2009 (UTC).

== Maneuverability/Agility ==
Does anybody have any idea how agile the XF-108 would have been?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Despite the fact that the aircraft was designed as a high-speed, long-range interceptor, and was very large and quite massive, it was stressed to be able to pull the same g-loads as other ADC interceptors.   Despite the fact that the aircraft weighed 104,320 lbs fully-loaded &lt;i&gt;(IIRC:  This figure is from a book titled &quot;VALKYRIE:  North American's Mach 3 Superbomber&quot; written by Dennis R. Jenkins and Tony R. Landis.  The figure is mentioned in the section about the XF-108 Rapier)&lt;/i&gt;, it had a massive wing-area &lt;i&gt;(1,865 square feet)&lt;/i&gt; which indicates a rather light wing-loading, which is often indicative of good sustained-turning performance, though not always the case &lt;i&gt;(It's possible, for example, to have a somewhat small, yet highly efficient wing, or to have a somewhat larger, less-efficient wing)&lt;i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I'm wondering how the plane's agility &lt;i&gt;(sustained)&lt;/i&gt; would have compared to the F-102A and F-106A, which despite being interceptors, were quite nimble and possessed a great degree of sustained agility &lt;i&gt;(Interestingly, the F-102's and F-106's were used to simulate MiG-21's as aggressor aircraft.  The MiG-21 at Mach 0.8 at 16,000 feet, could sustain over 6g without loss of speed and was known for being a remarkably agile aircraft)&lt;/i&gt; due to their large wings.  While the XF-108A's wing is very large, it is also very thin, with T/C ratio of around 3.5% on average if I recall &lt;i&gt;(The F-102 and F-106's wings while relatively thin, were thicker, possessing a T/C ratio of 4.65%)&lt;/i&gt; which is pretty close to the F-104's T/C-ratio &lt;i&gt;(3.4%)&lt;/i&gt; and is not always favorable towards sustained agility at intermediate airspeeds &lt;i&gt;(300-400 kts at low altitude)&lt;/i&gt;, and/or Mach numbers of 0.75 to 0.95 &lt;i&gt;(at altitude)&lt;/i&gt;.  There do appear to be exceptions, such as the CF-105 Arrow who's wings were 3.5% thick at the root, and 3.8% at the tips and seemed to possess a pretty good degree of sustained agility in that airspeed/mach-range.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Anybody have any guesses?  [[User:AVKent882|AVKent882]] ([[User talk:AVKent882|talk]]) 18:32, 11 June 2010 (UTC)

== Refs! ==

The &quot;Design&quot; section is currently lacking in references; rather than tag it, I thought I'd just bung a quickie note here, as I  know this article is being worked-up at the moment. :o) [[User:ThatPeskyCommoner| &lt;span style=&quot;color:#003300; font-family: cursive;&quot;&gt;'''Pesky'''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:ThatPeskyCommoner|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#336600;&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]] …[[Special:Contributions/ThatPeskyCommoner|''stalk!'']]) 07:47, 1 July 2011 (UTC)

==File:F-108 mockup.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[Image:Icon Now Commons orange.svg|50px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:F-108 mockup.jpg|File:F-108 mockup.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests July 2011'' 
;What should I do?
|-
|
| A discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. If you feel the deletion can be contested then please do so ([[commons:COM:SPEEDY]] has further information). Otherwise consider finding a replacement image before deletion occurs.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 03:57, 26 July 2011 (UTC)
|}</text>
      <sha1>0k8c3l6ntwxj70401dn9120ruqfbd2i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
