<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:School of Advanced Military Studies</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2485657</id>
    <revision>
      <id>583708853</id>
      <parentid>583708800</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-11-28T21:19:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Airborne84</username>
        <id>9474535</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Reading List */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10088">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject United States|class=GA|importance=low|USMIL=Yes}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA|A-Class=fail|b1=yes|b2=yes|b3=yes|b4=yes|b5=yes|US=yes}}
{{WikiProject Universities|class=GA|attention=yes}}
{{WikiProject Kansas|class=GA|importance=Low}}
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=09:21, 21 April 2012
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/School of Advanced Military Studies/archive1
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=488413101

|action2=GAN
|action2date=13:44, 22 October 2012 
|action2link=Talk:School of Advanced Military Studies/GA1
|action2result=not listed
|action2oldid=518147558

|action3=WAR
|action3date=19:34, 21 November 2012 (UTC)
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/School of Advanced Military Studies/archive1
|action3result=Not approved
|action3oldid=523035717

|action4=GAN
|action4date=04:36, 2 January 2013
|action4link=Talk:School of Advanced Military Studies/GA2
|action4result=listed
|action4oldid=530865167

|action5=WAR
|action5date=05:07, 25 January 2013 (UTC)
|action5link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/School of Advanced Military Studies
|action5result=Not approved
|action5oldid=533804256

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=education
}}

==Untitled==
Please if you wish to re-insert the 'attention' tag, explain ''why'' it need IMMEDIATE attention. (Or better still, expand the article!)
[[User:Buckshot06|Buckshot06]] 05:52, 22 November 2006 (UTC)

==Interested in possible rewrite / cleanup ==

I've been thinking about possibly rewriting this page. However, I am pretty unexperienced at writing here. I've been reading the rules and guidelines and such, and it has occurred to me that a lot of the content of such rewrite might be original research unless I could find it published somewhere. If these publications exist, I'll find them, an immediate family member has been an employee for over 20 years (which might conflict with me being eligible to do such a rewrite). Anyways, its something I'm interested in possibly doing if I can, maybe if anyone else was interested, in a collab.

:Feel free to have a go at it.  Most of the content came from me, and admittedly I mostly cribbed from the School's website.  Just don't overly plagiarize, or if you do include quoted text, cite at least in coarse terms that you are doing so (&quot;according to so-and-so, the school's cirriculum includes...&quot;) and you'll do fine. [[User:Whiskey Pete|Whiskey Pete]] 02:54, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

::I did some expansion. There is no conflict with you adding material. There would only be a conflict if you were writing an article about yourself or another such narrow topic. 
::The web sources I used should meet the [[WP:RS]] requirements, for the most part. There's nothing overly contentious, so I don't think that people will ping editors here for more reliable sources. 
::I did a rough rewrite. Much more polishing is possible. The current version is about B-class quality now. --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 03:41, 17 December 2010 (UTC)
:::I've done a bit more cleaup. IMO, the only major issues remaining are the lack of inline citations and references for the section on the Advanced Military Studies Program, as well as information on the other program within SAMS. 
:::There is room for expansion, such as the proportion of officers in the two respective programs within the school. Ideally, this would come from a reliable source as opposed to inserted from firsthand knowledge. --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 05:46, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

== FAC issues ==

Hi there.  Firstly can I send my apologies for the last minute oppose.  I was leaning to that persuasion anyway but there was just too many issues.  I agree with every thing {{u|Nikkimaria}} and {{u|Nick-D}} found all of which were among my issues so rather than write them out again I will list them here.  The eighteen issues were mainly the over use of quotes, so rather than list them all individually,  I have covered them under one point listed below. So this bring the eighteen down a bit. Here goes:

*Some unsourced material - for example, &quot;SAMS' leaders view...&quot; should include a citation to where these leaders said this

*[[WP:MOS|Manual of Style]] editing needed - [[WP:OVERLINK]], don't begin section headings with &quot;The&quot;, etc

*Tone problems, ex. &quot;continued to morph to meet the demands of a changing world&quot;

*Over use of quotes, see [[WP:QUOTEFARM]]. Some not referenced.

*Coverage. Lots of pictures but not much text in relation to the physical campus. 

*Images: File:Combined Arms Research Library in Eisenhower Hall, at US Army Command General Staff College is tagged as lacking author and date information. Missing Army-specific template for Army images too. 

*Sourcing: formatting issues. Publications should always be italicized, missing information (ex. Bower 2011 is missing publication/publisher), generally inconsistent formatting

*Most of the article's references are to public relations products produced by the US military, many of which are directly related to the institution. These obviously aren't neutral.

*Related to this, the article reads like something written by the military and contains no criticisms of the institution or its products. The graduates are only associated with successes for the military.

*As an example, the article states that &quot;SAMS students from the 2002 and 2003 classes participated as &quot;reach&quot; planners in the preparations for the invasion of Iraq, as well as the &quot;post-hostility plan for the occupation of Iraq&quot;.&quot; - given that this planning is widely regarded as being deeply flawed, this suggests that there might be problems with what SAMS is producing. This should be discussed. Likewise, the invasion of Panama is not normally regarded as a military masterpiece. 

*The article doesn't really explain what it is that SAMS teaches and how this is delivered - when this is discussed its centred on quotes written in military jargon.

If you can fix these, then list at PR, it may be easier and quicker for you. I would also consider listing on [[WP:FAR]] when your ready.  All the best! &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#539 0.2em 0.2em 0.5em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Cassianto|&lt;b style=&quot;color:#008;&quot;&gt;Cassianto&lt;/b&gt;]] ([[User talk:Cassianto|&lt;b style=&quot;color:#000&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/b&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt; 01:26, 20 April 2012 (UTC)
:Many thanks!! --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 01:52, 20 April 2012 (UTC)

{{Talk:School of Advanced Military Studies/GA1}}
{{Talk:School of Advanced Military Studies/GA2}}

== Reading list ==

I moved the &quot;reading list&quot; here because (1) it has no source, and (2) there is no date. The reading list likely changes over time, so there is no telling when this list was current. Please readd only with a reliable source and date. [[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 21:17, 28 November 2013 (UTC)

===Reading List===
:''Roots of Strategy: Book 1 (''Bk. 1) by Brig.Gen. Thomas R. Phillips
:''The Art of War'' (Smithsonian History of Warfare): War and Military Thought by Martin L. Van Creveld
:''The Grand Strategy of the Roman Empire: From the First Century A.D. to the Third'' (Johns Hopkins Paperbacks) by Edward N. Luttwak
:''The Wizards of Armageddon'' (Stanford Nuclear Age Series) by Fred M. Kaplan
:''Roots of Strategy: Book 2'' by Curtis Brown
:''Roots of Strategy Book: 4 Military Classics : The Influence of Sea Power upon History, 1660–1783'', Some Principles of Maritime 
:''Strategy, Command of the Air, Winged Defense'' by Col. David Jablonsky
:''Strategy: Second Revised Edition'' (Meridian) by Sir Basil Henry Liddell Hart
:''The Prince'' (Bantam Classics) by Niccolò Machiavelli
:''On War'', Indexed Edition by Carl von Clausewitz
:''The Landmark Thucydides: A Comprehensive Guide to the Peloponnesian War'' by Thucydides
:''The Art of War'' by Sun Tzu
:''Clausewitz: A Very Short Introduction'' by Michael Howard
:''History of the Peloponnesian War'' by Thucydides
:''Moneyball: The Art of Winning an Unfair Game'' by Michael Lewis
:''The Cambridge Illustrated History of Warfare'' (Cambridge Illustrated Histories) by Geoffrey Parker
:''Understanding Terror Networks'' by Marc Sageman
:''On Bullshit'' by Harry G. Frankfurt
:''The Cambridge Dictionary of Philosophy'' by Robert Audi
:''Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Vol 7&amp;8 in One Book'' by Paul Edwards
:''How We Think'' by John Dewey
:''The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order'' by Samuel P. Huntington
:''The Tragedy of Great Power Politics'' by John J. Mearsheimer
:''Understanding International Conflicts: An Introduction to Theory and History'' (Longman Classics in Political Science) by Joseph S. Nye
:''The Lexus and the Olive Tree: Understanding Globalization'' by Thomas L. Friedman
:''The Coming Anarchy: Shattering the Dreams of the Post Cold War'' by Robert D. Kaplan
:''Surprise, Security, and the American Experience'' (Joanna Jackson Goldman Memorial Lecture on American Civilization) by John Lewis Gaddis
:''American National Security'' by Amos A. Jordan
:''The Making of Strategy: Rulers, States, and War'' by Williamson Murray
:''Bounding the Global War on Terrorism'' by Jeffrey Record
:''Organization Theory: Modern, Symbolic, and Postmodern Perspectives'' by Mary Jo Hatch
:''Rise and Fall of Strategic Planning'' by Henry Mintzberg
:''Causality and Explanation'' by Wesley C. Salmon
:''Causality and Modern Science: Third Revised Edition'' by Mario Bunge
:''Causality: Models, Reasoning, and Inference'' by Judea Pearl
:''The Visual Display of Quantitative Information'' by Edward R. Tufte
:''Visual and Statistical Thinking: Displays of Evidence for Making Decisions'' by Edward R. Tufte
:''Kaigun: Strategy, Tactics, and Technology in the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1887–1941'' by David C. Evans
:''Harnessing Complexity'' by Robert Axelrod
:''Issues and Methods in Comparative Politics'' by Todd Landman
:''Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance'' by Robert M. Pirsig</text>
      <sha1>g3a4eo42gw2t3erf2kg1bitg94dopsn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
