<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Dunnottar Castle</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3861305</id>
    <revision>
      <id>718143867</id>
      <parentid>573647696</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-01T19:56:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot</username>
        <id>27446209</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>subst /Comments to [[WP:DCS|discontinue comments subpage]]) ([[Project:AWB|AWB]] [12009]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7037">{{Article history
|action1=PR
|action1date=14:39, 24 March 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Dunnottar Castle/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=45263253

|action2=GAN
|action2date=15:19, 13 December 2012
|action2link=Talk:Dunnottar Castle/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=527867006

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War and military
}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|1=
{{WikiProject Scottish Castles|class=GA}}
{{WikiProject Medieval Scotland|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA
|British-task-force=yes
|Fortifications-task-force=yes
|Medieval-task-force=yes
}}
}}
==Merger==
this is the way to do it...dunnottar is the best spelling, but the superior content is in the present dunnotar article....i will clean up and edit after the merge...[[User:Anlace|Anlace]] 06:15, 27 January 2006 (UTC)
:also the existing pic on dunnottar should survive as it is the best image [[User:Anlace|Anlace]] 06:18, 27 January 2006 (UTC)
::I agree the merge is a good idea, put the best article into the correctly spelled article. [[User:Thatcher131|Thatcher131]] 04:37, 14 February 2006 (UTC)

== Peacock terms (and the opposite) ==
please explain in detail by line reference the tag or remove it at once...please post your reply here where it belongs not on my talk page... thank you [[User:Anlace|Anlace]] 14:44, 11 March 2006 (UTC)e
:Hi. Just to expand on the reasons for the NPOV tag - this article uses terms which appear to me to be out of place in a encyclopaedia article e.g. magnificent, stunning, brutality, inhumane. Should be fairly easy to fix [[User:SP-KP|SP-KP]] 18:14, 11 March 2006 (UTC)
::do you have another word other than &quot;brutality&quot; for incinerating hundreds of people who are imprisoned
::i cant think of a more accurate word (i am neither english or scottish and have no real point of view here)[[User:Anlace|Anlace]] 22:23, 11 March 2006 (UTC)
:::whats a better word for treatment of men, women and children prisoners of all ages including many sick and elderly, when the captors deprive them of food, crowd them into a space of no more than one square meter per person, and force them to live in fecal matter up to their ankles for many months? the word &quot;inhumane&quot; comes to mind to me
:::what word would you suggest kpsp? be sure to be poitically correct now.  [[User:Anlace|Anlace]] 22:33, 11 March 2006 (UTC)

== Improvement suggestions ==

Hi Anlace, can I make some suggestions: (i) take a look at [[WP:PEACOCK]] - where you'll learn about the justification for avoiding &quot;peacock terms&quot;, which I think applies in this case, and how you can re-word them to better fit with Wikipedia recommended style; (ii) on a re-reading, I also noticed squalid, tragic, a couple of importants and a breathtaking, all of which I think require attention - I won't re-insert the POV check tag just yet, I'll give you a chance to sort these issues out first [[User:SP-KP|SP-KP]] 22:51, 11 March 2006 (UTC)

Also, you could try putting this article up for peer review, which should help you to get a broader range of opinions on how the article could be improved. Let me know if you need help with doing that. [[User:SP-KP|SP-KP]] 22:58, 11 March 2006 (UTC)

== Link error ==
I believe the link to Andrew Murray goes to wrong family member, it should go to his grandson Sir Andrew Murray, 4. lord of Bothwell, 3. regent of Scotland (1297 - 1338). --[[User:85.165.99.39|85.165.99.39]] 16:25, 18 March 2006 (UTC) Finn Bjo
:made change as you suggested. now its of course a red link [[User:Anlace|Anlace]] 00:27, 19 March 2006 (UTC)

==The name &quot;dun&quot; being Pictish for fort==

Not so. It is Gaeilge (Irish) for fort. Very, very little of the Pictish language is extant. [[User:Fergananim|Fergananim]] 14:53, 21 March 2006 (UTC)

:broadened reference to gaelic. there is actually considerable debate regarding how to term word origins this far back...blends of irish gaelic, scottish gaelic and pictic [[User:Anlace|Anlace]] 15:02, 21 March 2006 (UTC)

::I was under the impression that Gaelic was never a particularly important language in this area - I mean, it wasn't even widely spoken in the 15th century, let alone at the time of the Romans. Also, where did you get the information that the Roman camp was called Radex? The place is currently called Raedykes, which understandably could be a corruption of Radex, but I've never seen it spelled that way - and can't find any information to confirm it online. Have removed until it is more than conjecture. -[[User:Taras|taras]] 20:04, 31 July 2006 (UTC)

==No Adverts!==
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''Janet Elaine Smith is married to Ivan Smith, the great-grandson of Carolyn (Keith) Smith, who was a direct descendent of Rev. James Keith, the first Congregational minister in Barnstable. Rev. James Keith was recruited by Rev. Increase Mather, when Keith was just a teenager and a graduate of Aberdeen University, which was founded by his ancestor, George Keith. Rev. Keith was a direct descendent of the Keiths of Inverugie Castle in Peterhead, Scotland, as well as (prior to that) the Keiths of Dunnottar Castle, where the Scottish regalia was hidden to protect it from being melted down by Oliver Cromwell in the British Civil War. Dunnottar Castle was the last stronghold to stand against the attacks of Cromwell.

''Read more about Dunnotar in the historically accurate trilogy, Dunnotar, Marlybone, and Par for the Course, written by Janet Elaine Smith.''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This is blatantly an advert for this persons books! Unless reasonable justification for keeping this paragraph in can be presented, it should be deleted. Wikipedia is a place for learning, not somewhere to drum up sales!I cannot begin to convey how disappointed and angry I am that wikipedia, a non-profit, public SERVICE is being exploited in such a manner.If no response/reasonable objection is made within three days(to give a fair chance)deletion will occur. Very, Very disappointed.[[User:Songsofsolace|*killerpsychobunny*]] 17:08, 21 May 2007 (UTC)

In accordance with conversation with pages parent, this is gone. Ta much.[[User:Songsofsolace|*killerpsychobunny*]] 21:33, 24 May 2007 (UTC)

{{Talk:Dunnottar Castle/GA1}}

== Coordinate error ==

{{tlc|geodata-check}}
The following coordinate fixes are needed for
—[[Special:Contributions/121.14.162.3|121.14.162.3]] ([[User talk:121.14.162.3|talk]]) 16:52, 29 August 2013 (UTC)
:{{not done}}. You haven't specified what you think is in error, and the coordinates currently in the article appear to be correct. If you still think that there is an error in the article, please post here again, using the {{tl|geodata-check}} template and explaining what error you perceive. [[User:Deor|Deor]] ([[User talk:Deor|talk]]) 20:17, 29 August 2013 (UTC)

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=150|lastedit=20070411083721|comment=This article is not at all far off GA status. [[User:Ben MacDui|Ben MacDui]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Ben MacDui|(Talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 08:37, 11 April 2007 (UTC)}}
Substituted at 19:56, 1 May 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hg6l818ep3s8fvifv08tv3fbap083so</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
