<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Bockscar</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>294182</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733766833</id>
      <parentid>676896842</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-10T00:02:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2016-08-09.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15957">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=03:19, 1 April 2013
|action1link=/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=548087121

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=warfare
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA |B-Class-1=yes |B-Class-2=yes |B-Class-3=yes |B-Class-4=yes |B-Class-5=yes
|importance=top
|Aviation-task-force=yes
|US-task-force=yes
|WWII-task-force=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=GA |B-Class-1=yes |B-Class-2=yes |B-Class-3=yes |B-Class-4=yes |B-Class-5=yes
|Aircraft-project=yes}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=GA|importance=low}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2016-08-09|oldid1=733658955}}

==Comments==
If the actual name is &quot;Bockscar&quot;, shouldn't that be the name of the article? - [[User:Molinari|Molinari]] 19:05, 11 Aug 2003 (UTC)

Google thinks so:
*Bock's Car (795)
*Bocks Car (259)
*Bockscar (819)
That, combined with the fact that the US Air Force Museum Archives calls it &quot;Bockscar&quot; is good enough for me: http://www.wpafb.af.mil/museum/research/bombers/b3-35.htm
-- [[User:Wfeidt|Bill]] 19:12, 11 Aug 2003 (UTC)
* New link: http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=2546 USAF Museum - BOCKSCAR Story. [[User:LanceBarber|LanceBarber]] 18:52, 2 August 2007 (UTC)

== &quot;BOCK'S CAR&quot;? ==

As painted on the plane, the name is [http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/shared/media/photodb/photos/050809-F-1234P-003.jpg &quot;BOCKS CAR&quot;]; there's a small but clear space between the S and C. In my opinion, since &quot;Bockscar&quot; and &quot;Bocks Car&quot; don't parse, and &quot;[Frederick] Bock's Car&quot; does--and probably was a pun on [[Boxcar]]--we should call it  that. My guess is that the apostrophe went the way of [[Neil Armstrong]]'s &quot;a&quot; in &quot;That's one small step for [a] man,...&quot;
&lt;br/&gt;[[User:Wwoods|&amp;mdash;wwoods]] 03:02, 12 Dec 2004 (UTC)

In his book ''Mission : Hiroshima'' (originally published as ''The Tibbets Story'') (Stein &amp; Day, 1979, ISBN 0-8128-8169-9) Colonel Paul W. Tibbets refers to the aircraft as &quot;Bock's Car&quot; throughout. Is this not definitive? [[User:Dawkeye|Dawkeye]] 23:27, 29 May 2006 (UTC)

:I would say that the spelling used by the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]], where they have professional curators and try to be as accurate as possible, would be the best source.  They use &quot;Bockscar&quot; [http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=2546].  --[[User:Rogerd|rogerd]] 17:54, 24 June 2006 (UTC)

:::That it was a pun on &quot;boxcar&quot; (one word) is indisputable--the painted cartoon is of a boxcar. The &quot;perceived&quot; gap between the S and the C is in the eye of the beholder and therefore, in the absence of any documentation showing that the namer or the artist intended it to be such is ORIGINAL RESEARCH and therefore forbidden. The point about Tibbets is irrelevant--he wasn't the namer nor the artist, nor do we know under what circumstances the ghost writer/editor of his book chose that spelling (&quot;Bockscar&quot; looks odd--very possibly an editor chose the spelling). The point about the NMUSAF exhibit is well-taken. An impeccably-credible source has defined the name: ''Bockscar''. We don't, in the words of the first editor above, need to &quot;guess&quot;.--Buckboard 05:25, 9 May 2007 (UTC)

:::It is completely silly and foolish to say that Col/Gen. Tibbets's opinion is &quot;irrelevant&quot;. (Are you in the business of handing out insults?) Col. Tibbets was the commanding officer of the USAAF 509th Composite Group, and as such, he was responsible for everything in that B-29 Group, including the names of all the airplanes and all the nose art. It is insulting to say that he did not KNOW the name of such an important airplane as &quot;Bock's Car&quot;. 

:::To say so is like saying that a commanding Admiral did not know the names of every ship in his Task Force, or in his squadron of ships (in the example of the commander of a destroyer or submarine squadron, or a cruiser division). It is just completely unbelievable.

== Bocks Car ==

Well, I'll give a reason for the third possible choice: I think the spelling on the aircraft should be definitive, grammatical or not, most commonly used or not.  So I think the article should be titled '''Bocks Car''', although the space between S and C is pretty thin, more the absence of an overlap than an actual space.

In any case, I've put a link to the above image on the article page and edited it to leave it to the reader to decide whether there's a space in there.
[[User:207.176.159.90|207.176.159.90]] 00:03, 26 Feb 2005 (UTC)

:I agree, Bocks Car makes most sense.  The Enola Gay was also all caps, but it is written in this format. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ragesoss|Ragesoss]] ([[User talk:Ragesoss|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ragesoss|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; 
::Wow, look at the change from the older photo to the newer. Clearly, someone has done a poor job restoring here. There is a clear absence of an overlap in the older photo, and not in the newer one. Still, even the oldest version must have been made after the mission. Does anyone know who the artist was?  [[User:Greswik|Greswik]] 13:29, 25 July 2007 (UTC)

==The Great Artiste==
According to ''The Bomb: A Life'', Bocks Car (or whatever the format) was the original name, after it's normal pilot, and it was renamed The Great Artiste by Sweeney but the name didn't stick.  The line about manning the Great Artiste is confusing and seems to suggest that the plane flown by Bock on the Nagasaki mission was the The Great Artiste.--[[User:Ragesoss|ragesoss]] 00:14, 22 January 2006 (UTC)
:I can't see any confusion. The intro quite  clearly says &quot;On the day of the attack Bockscar was manned by the crew of The Great Artiste and was commanded by Major Charles W. Sweeney of Massachusetts.&quot; Also, it is probably more accurate to say Sweeney '''attempted''' to rename the aircraft, not that he actually did so. Does the book say exactly when the BOCKSCAR name was painted on the aircraft? [[User:Moriori|Moriori]] 02:00, 22 January 2006 (UTC)

:The plane that flew the instrumentation missions for both Hiroshima and Nagasaki was already named the ''Great Artiste''. The ''Great Artiste'' was originally scheduled to drop the second bomb, but when it was realised that there was not enough time to move the instrumentation from the ''Great Artiste'' to ''Bocks Car'', the crews were swapped. The document at [http://www.uwosh.edu/faculty_staff/earns/olivi.html], which is an External link from the article, explains most of this. The initial press releases said that the second bomb had been dropped from the ''Great Artiste'' because that had been the plan.[http://www.atomicarchive.com/Docs/Hiroshima/Nagasaki.shtml] Note that the press release states the mission was flown in no. 77, which was the ''BocksCar''.[http://home.att.net/~sallyann4/509.html] As for when the nose art was painted on ''Bocks Car'', a photo taken right after the mission shows a clean nose; the nose art was added later. Unfortunately, I can't find the photo right now. -- '''&lt;font color=&quot;navy&quot;&gt;[[User:Dalbury|Dalbury]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Dalbury|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Talk]])&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;''' 05:09, 22 January 2006 (UTC)

:::None of the aircraft except ''Enola Gay'' were &quot;named&quot; (i.e. painted on the nose) before the missions. One (''Luke the Spook'') was not named until the next year, and one (''Jabit III'') very possibly never carried a name. All nose art was unofficial and there are no documents showing when any were applied, except that Tibbets has confirmed that the plane was lettered the day before the mission. The reason the Nagasaki press release gives a victor number is that it was the only ID painted on the a/c at the time. The debate over &quot;all caps&quot; etc is a little overblown--nose art lettering came out in the style of the artist, without regard to caps etc. ''Enola Gay'' was lettered in BLOCK lettering. Many nicknames were painted by their artists using quotation marks, so some here would have them shown in an article as &quot;&quot;Name&quot;&quot;. Also, the reason victor 77 was chosen to drop the Kokura-Nagasaki bomb was that it had been used by Sweeney and Albury's crew to conduct all three Fat Man test drops on August 1, 5, and 8. It was ready to go and they were comfortable flying it. The switchover of instrumentation could have been done, but why bother? Of the 393rd B-29s, only one (''Some Punkins'') was flown exclusively by its assigned crew, and one (''Big Stink'') was flown on missions by nine of the fifteen 393rd crews.--Buckboard 05:14, 9 May 2007 (UTC)

:The main article may engender some confusion regarding when the &quot;Bocks Car&quot; nose art was restored and contains a reference to the  nose art having been &quot;restored&quot; AFTER the aircraft arrived at the Air Force Museum. While that is no doubt literally true, one may infer from the article that the &quot;Great Artiste&quot; art may have lasted until after the plane had been flown to the Museum. At least as early as Spring 1960 the &quot;Bocks Car&quot; nose art was back on the plane. It was photographed in April or May of that year on display at Davis-Monthan AFB bearing the &quot;Bocks Car&quot; nose art. It is evident from the photograph that sometime during the plane's &quot;stay&quot; at DMAFB the &quot;Bocks Car&quot; nose art was restored or reapplied. That photograph is available for downloading, if appropriate. [[User:Herandher|Herandher]] ([[User talk:Herandher|talk]]) 05:54, 2 July 2011 (UTC)

== Restoration ==

Should it be mentioned that that there are plans to bring the box car to flight status? The idea came about when inspection of the Enola Gay reviled her to be in remarkable shape, except for severed wire bundles dooming a restoration project. These wires where cut when the Enola Gay was disassembled for storage purposes. Bockscar never underwent such disassembly, and was store better than any other of the B-29's on display (almost all survivors but Bockscar and the Enola Gay sat at China Lake missile range as unused missile targets for years, Including FiFi). Inspection of Bockscar relieved a little more damage than was hoped but is still hands down the best candidate for a second flying Super-fortress.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.155.113.22|69.155.113.22]] ([[User talk:69.155.113.22|talk]]) 06:18, 10 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Requested move ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:requested moves|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. Editors desiring to contest the closing decision should consider a [[Wikipedia:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''not moved'''. With three editors each supporting a different version, this defaults to no move without consensus. Of the arguments put forward, the most convincing is In ictu oculi's: gbooks does have far more &quot;Bock's car&quot; (with apostrophe) than &quot;Bockscar&quot;, which might indicate that as the common form, but both forms are found. [[User:DrKiernan|DrKiernan]] ([[User talk:DrKiernan|talk]]) 11:05, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

----

[[Bockscar]] → {{no redirect|Bocks Car}} – The name of the aircraft is clearly shown in the photo of the nose-art as being written in two words, so I feel that the ghost should be laid to rest, particularly as the evidence is already published in Wikipedia. &lt;small&gt;''Relisted''. [[User:Jenks24|Jenks24]] ([[User talk:Jenks24|talk]]) 09:22, 7 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; [[User:Petebutt|Petebutt]] ([[User talk:Petebutt|talk]]) 02:32, 11 September 2012 (UTC)
:A more proper Alternative would be all caps as BOCKS CAR, the same goes for ENOLA GAY[[User:Petebutt|Petebutt]] ([[User talk:Petebutt|talk]]) 02:34, 11 September 2012 (UTC)
::Arguments that museum spellings are paramount are obviously bogus due to the evidence available[[User:Petebutt|Petebutt]] ([[User talk:Petebutt|talk]]) 02:37, 11 September 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' Bock's Car gets twice the hits, 2,800, in GB of Bockscar - in addition to the likelihood of someoneone misreading &quot;Bock Scar&quot;., plus the nose art photo which shows S not overlapping with C like the other letters. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 12:52, 13 September 2012 (UTC)
::Is Bock's a typo since the request you are supporting was for Bocks Car not Bock's Car?--[[Special:Contributions/174.93.171.108|174.93.171.108]] ([[User talk:174.93.171.108|talk]]) 00:12, 16 September 2012 (UTC)

* '''Oppose'''  &quot;Bockscar&quot; is correct. It's supported by the nose art, the museum, and the pun on &quot;[[Boxcar]]&quot;.  &quot;Bocks Car&quot; is against both WP capitalisation conventions and grammar. &quot;Bock's Car&quot; would at least have grammar in its favour, but it's very clear that no halfway decent sources claim there's an apostrophe in there. [[User:Andy Dingley|Andy Dingley]] ([[User talk:Andy Dingley|talk]]) 01:22, 12 October 2012 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page or in a [[WP:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

{{Talk:Bockscar/GA1}}

== Contradiction - How much damage to Nagasaki? ==

This article (Bockscar) indicates that 44% of Nagasaki was destroyed.
But, the Wikipedia article on Charles Sweeney states that 60% of Nagasaki was destroyed.
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Sweeney

Which is correct?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.73.52.186|70.73.52.186]] ([[User talk:70.73.52.186|talk]]) 17:30, 18 May 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


== Which Type of Boeing ? ==

In the right upper square, we read : &quot;Type 	Boeing B-29A-40BN Superfortress&quot;.&lt;br&gt;
But the Airplane History section starts by : &quot;Bockscar, B-29-36-MO 44-27297, (...)&quot;.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/195.6.224.137|195.6.224.137]] ([[User talk:195.6.224.137|talk]]) 10:47, 1 December 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Well spotted. The latter is correct. I have corrected the article accordingly. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 11:41, 1 December 2013 (UTC)

== Salt Lake ==

The drawing on the fuselage depicts a route from &quot;Salt Lake&quot; to &quot;Nagasaki&quot;. What is the relevance of Salt Lake [City?] to the Bockscar? —[[User:JamesLucas|jameslucas]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;([[User talk:JamesLucas|&quot;&amp;nbsp;&quot;]]&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/JamesLucas|+]])&lt;/small&gt; 20:43, 17 August 2015 (UTC)
: [[Wendover Field]]  [[User:Andy Dingley|Andy Dingley]] ([[User talk:Andy Dingley|talk]]) 21:34, 17 August 2015 (UTC)
:: I was thinking that too. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 23:09, 17 August 2015 (UTC)
:::I guess it's more romantic than the hexagonal outline of Utah, even if the the base is not exactly near the lake. I wonder if it should be more explicit in the article. —[[User:JamesLucas|jameslucas]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;([[User talk:JamesLucas|&quot;&amp;nbsp;&quot;]]&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/JamesLucas|+]])&lt;/small&gt; 17:07, 19 August 2015 (UTC)
::::Only if you can find a [[WP:RS|reliable source]]. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 20:58, 19 August 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>4bzcecvgjatrweqp4crqebxfprr5dbi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
