<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Borodino</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2115853</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746977117</id>
      <parentid>746707618</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-30T18:48:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pinkbeast</username>
        <id>11291690</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links modified */ checked</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12105">{{talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=04:38, 2 November 2010
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Battle of Borodino/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=394100864

|action2=GAN
|action2date=22:50, 2 March 2011
|action2link=Talk:Battle of Borodino/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=416806299

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject France|class=GA|importance=Mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA
|Peer-review=yes
|French-task-force=yes
|Napoleonic-task-force=yes
|Russian-task-force=yes

&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=GA|importance=Top|hist=yes|mil=yes}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=GA|category=History|importance=Mid}}
}}
{{On this day |date1=2005-09-07|oldid1=22805037|date2=2009-09-07|oldid2=311957522|date3=2010-09-07|oldid3=383400244|date4=2012-09-07|oldid4=511269797|date5=2014-09-07|oldid5=624578014|date6=2016-09-07|oldid6=738159397}}
{{Archive box |auto=long |search=yes |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months |index=/Archive index }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 4
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Battle of Borodino/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}



== Canvassing on RFC by {{u|ZidaneZidane98}} ==
{{archive top|result=I'm taking this opportunity to editorialize. {{U|Pinkbeast}}, in the previous sections it was {{U|ZinedineZidane98}} who behaved less than admirably; this time it's you. Please refrain: there is no evidence that an editor was picked because they were likely to influence the outcome in a manner favorable to the alleged canvasser. In other words, there was no canvassing. Note that I'm simply going down the list on this talk page, from one unholy conflict to the next. [[User:Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]) 18:16, 9 September 2015 (UTC)}}
I notice that {{u|ZidaneZidane98}}, not content with the RFC itself, is inviting specific editors to participate:
https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Auntieruth55&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=669337970
https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Ian_Rose&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=668878112

The potential to cherry-pick ones who they feel are likely to agree is obvious. This is sharp practice. [[User:Pinkbeast|Pinkbeast]] ([[User talk:Pinkbeast|talk]]) 15:11, 30 June 2015 (UTC)

:Nice try. But &quot;Auntieruth55&quot; was suggested to me by &quot;Ian_Rose&quot;, as you would have seen, if you bothered to read the above diff you posted. [[User:ZinedineZidane98|ZinedineZidane98]] ([[User talk:ZinedineZidane98|talk]]) 15:22, 30 June 2015 (UTC)

::So, so far, you have only cherry-picked one editor. Good. Please don't do it again. [[User:Pinkbeast|Pinkbeast]] ([[User talk:Pinkbeast|talk]]) 15:23, 30 June 2015 (UTC)

:::Who have I &quot;cherry-picked&quot;? Ian Rose is the head of the Military History Project - https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Military_history/Coordinators , and he excused himself due to an admitted lack of expertise (an honorable move, you should take note), suggesting two editors who he knew to be specialists in this area, both of whom have commented. Who else do you suggest I should have asked for input? The more eyes on this the better, as far as I'm concerned. The sources are definitive. [[User:ZinedineZidane98|ZinedineZidane98]] ([[User talk:ZinedineZidane98|talk]]) 15:33, 30 June 2015 (UTC)

:Pinkbeast, I was not cherrypicked, I was identified as an authority in the Napoleonic wars by Ianrose, the lead coordinator.  I suggest you two stop this mindless bickering.  Add Pyrrhic French victory to the info box, and get on to other things.  Make sure the article clearly states why it was a Pyrrhic victory, please, and cite such sources as Rothenberg and Alex's book, and we're good.  Please move on guys.  There is a lot of work to be done, and we don't need to expend energy in discussing the number of angels on the head of a pin.  [[User:Auntieruth55|auntieruth]] [[User talk:Auntieruth55|(talk)]] 19:48, 30 June 2015 (UTC)

::We wouldn't be expending this energy if [[User:ZinedineZidane98|ZinedineZidane98]] - someone whose entire use of Wikipedia is edit-warring, judging by their talk page history - hadn't been willing to go on about it for years. It takes two to tango (or rather, at least two, since I'm hardly the only editor fed to the back teeth with their approach) - difference being, I've actually been editing the article itself to try and improve the situation rather than coming back every few months for another revert.

::I agree with the instructions on the template, and I don't agree it was a pyrrhic victory, full stop, because it was not the costs of Borodino that caused the eventual disaster. I'm not the only one, either in the previous talk page history or attracted by this RFC. I do appreciate the point that leaving it blank is undesirable, which is why I've made a third proposal.

::Essentially, you're saying &quot;shut up and do it my way&quot;. I can get that from Zinedine (and indeed I have had a surfeit thereof). [[User:Pinkbeast|Pinkbeast]] ([[User talk:Pinkbeast|talk]]) 21:36, 30 June 2015 (UTC)

:::We're not saying &quot;my way&quot;, we're saying, &quot;the historians/scholars way&quot;. This isn't a matter of opinion between random anonymous internet identities. The sources are all that count. [[User:ZinedineZidane98|ZinedineZidane98]] ([[User talk:ZinedineZidane98|talk]]) 03:11, 1 July 2015 (UTC)
{{archive bottom}}

==This thing from an admin's point of view==
This admin subscribes to the opinion given above by {{U|Auntieruth55}}, which was echoed by {{U|Tirronan}}. We have something in the infobox right now. (To link to the section with a footnote is awkward, but OK.) No one's fighting at this very moment. But if this flares up again, y'all should run a new RfC, but you'll have to do it without Pinkbeast and ZinedineZidane, since I'll go to AN and get an article ban for those two editors--I doubt that this would be difficult to obtain. Both are guilty of wikilawyering (one more than the other, perhaps, but still) and their presence on this talk page is simply not helpful. Thank you, [[User:Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]) 18:30, 9 September 2015 (UTC)
{{archive bottom}}

== Nikolai Rostov - Fictional character detailed as a commander at the Battle of Borodino ==

Looking at the box containing 'Commanders and leaders' I am surprised to see there is no mention of Mikhail Kutuzov whereas Nikolai Rostov, a fictional character (?) from 'War and Peace' by Leo Tolstoy, is included.

I am not (yet) a contributor to the otherwise very helpful content and would not wish to edit anything which I might not have fully understood - but is it right that Rostov is there and Kutuzov is not? I do note Kutuzov is mentioned elsewhere in the main text.

[[User:Nimrifs|Nimrifs]] ([[User talk:Nimrifs|talk]]) 17:56, 3 March 2016 (UTC)
:You can revert cases of obvious vandalism - checking the page history would show it was a random drive-by edit by an IP. Mind you, what do I know, my presence on this talk page is simply not helpful, says {{u|Drmies}}. [[User:Pinkbeast|Pinkbeast]] ([[User talk:Pinkbeast|talk]]) 18:48, 3 March 2016 (UTC)

::It is uncertain if Kutuzov was on the battlefield or not. Chandler says that he was, later historians say not. As listed in the article there were many outright lies when it came to recording the battle. A lot of accounts intended to settle old scores on top of the normal &quot;I remember this the way I want it to be&quot; sort of normal distortion. I've simply put down both accounts and let it be. Pinkbeast I am sorry if I came across harshly but you had to know you and Zine had pushed things way too far. I let someone push me way too far once at Wikipedia and I wish that I had behaved the way I do now but I didn't. Getting in ownership battles over articles is just never going to turn out well. I had to ask myself how I behaved regardless of what the other guy did and I did not like the answer. My suggestion is 1st and foremost learn from it as I had to. I ended up taking a two year wiki vacation to get my perspective in order. These are just observations from what I saw without judgment. From where I stood you were &quot;defending the article&quot; well when I got in that place it tends to be appointing me appointing myself as the article's protector. The problem is that we can't do that it is ownership. I had one fellow while I was writing this article constantly changing the results box while I was doing it. Not helping not doing anything but being a POV warrior for the Russians. I exploded over it in frustration over being dragged into info box results instead of being allowed to expand the article in desperate need of expansion. We lose ourselves in our passion sometimes. I think you did. I learned that I had to get a bit dispassionate about my work here. So learn from my mistakes and yours and ask yourself a few questions as I had to.[[User:Tirronan|Tirronan]] ([[User talk:Tirronan|talk]]) 21:44, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

:::Hang on, there seem to be three issues here:
:::Kutuzov not at battlefield: I think we mostly have this one right in that we don't place too much stock in Soviet-era accounts of him curing cancer and leaping tall buildings at a single bound, but rightly reflect both contemporary accounts and modern analysis that has him well to the rear and not very involved at times.
:::Insertion of a fictional character - that was just vandalism and {{u|Nimrifs}} could have reverted it without discussion.
:::Me griping at Drmies. Well, you're not Drmies. I admit I was vexed when you had a go at me midway for changing the page _away_ from my preferred option, but let's not rehash all that. I was considerably more vexed with what I felt (and feel) was misuse of being an admin to issue vague threats of topic bans later. [[User:Pinkbeast|Pinkbeast]] ([[User talk:Pinkbeast|talk]]) 00:56, 14 March 2016 (UTC)
::::I'll give you a laugh, my preferred outcome was &quot;Just one more loss in an unending series of causalities&quot;.[[User:Tirronan|Tirronan]] ([[User talk:Tirronan|talk]]) 23:18, 15 March 2016 (UTC)

== Map-Symvbols ==

There is a mistake on the map:

Boney and Kutuzov are  &quot;Spureme Commanders&quot; so they are marked by  5 X (XXXX) 4 X is a &quot;Field Army&quot; --[[Special:Contributions/95.223.135.1|95.223.135.1]] ([[User talk:95.223.135.1|talk]]) 10:36, 7 September 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Battle of Borodino]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=746617281 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20021029162023/http://www.fortunecity.com:80/victorian/riley/787/Napoleon/1812/boro1.html to http://www.fortunecity.com/victorian/riley/787/Napoleon/1812/boro1.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 13:47, 28 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1lryn0zhoczwesfrm30v77e2zdd0rkl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
