<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Wannsee Conference</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>710706</id>
    <revision>
      <id>725130081</id>
      <parentid>725128454</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-13T19:22:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Diannaa</username>
        <id>10728040</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Is the phrase precise? */ ok</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21900">{{Article history
|action1=GAN
|action1date=18:50, 10 February 2009 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Wannsee Conference/Archive 1#GA Quick fail
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=268816004

|action6=GAN
|action6date=2013-08-13
|action6link=Talk:Wannsee Conference/GA1
|action6result=listed
|action6oldid=568355006
|topic=World history
|currentstatus=GA
}}

{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WP Military History|class=GA|importance=mid|WWII=yes}}
{{WikiProject Human rights|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Jewish history|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WP History|class=GA|importance=High}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-01-20|oldid1=9517664|date2=2006-01-20|oldid2=33549693|date3=2007-01-20|oldid3=102103995|date4=2008-01-20|oldid4=185535204|date5=2009-01-20|oldid5=265216288|date6=2010-01-20|oldid6=338659089|date7=2012-01-20|oldid7=472280237}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 125K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(100d)
|archive = Talk:Wannsee Conference/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archive box|bot=MiszaBot I|age=100|auto=long|search=yes}}
[[Category:GA-Class Nazi Germany articles]]

== Background ==

If I compare [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wannsee_Conference&amp;diff=556157552&amp;oldid=550732949 these versions] it seems that there was a lot of editing on the background-chapter. I cannot make up if it is better this way. Anyone got an idea if it is?[[User:Jeff5102|Jeff5102]] ([[User talk:Jeff5102|talk]]) 20:34, 21 May 2013 (UTC)
: Hi Jeff5102. I am the person who did these edits. I edit a lot on Nazi Germany topics and am pretty knowledgeable on this topic. One difference is that the old version was largely unsourced, and the new version has sources. Do you have any specific parts of the new version that you think are sketchy or questionable? Thanks. -- [[User:Diannaa|Dianna]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 23:53, 21 May 2013 (UTC)
::As far as I can see, the things you wrote are not the problem. The problem I had was the gap between 1939 and 31 Juli 1941 that is in the background-paragraph at the moment. Before your edits, it read:
 
::''In 1939, [[Adolf Hitler]] signed a &quot;euthanasia decree&quot; (later known as [[Action T4]]), which instituted a forced eugenics program extending the existing laws enabling sterilisation for those deemed genetically or socially unfit. Under this new policy doctors were allowed, and in some cases required, to take the lives of those deemed unfit rather than to sterilize them, as had been the law before. The term ''[[euthanasia]]'' in this context is a [[euphemism]], since its aim was not to relieve pain and suffering but rather, for the sake of societal purity, to prevent further 'pollution' of the race by [[eugenics|'inferior' genetics]].''

::''The notion of mass deportation of Jews, as part of the plan to &quot;purify&quot; all of Europe, reached its peak in the forced deportation of Jews to labor camps in Poland and in the [[Madagascar Plan]] of 1940, but was shelved due to logistical challenges during the war.''

::''The rapid German advances in the opening weeks of the invasion of the [[Soviet Union]], ''[[Operation Barbarossa]]'', created a mood of euphoria among the Nazi leadership, which began to take a view of the &quot;solution&quot; of the &quot;Jewish question&quot; increasingly freed from moral or ethical restraints. The so-called &quot;Jewish question&quot; seemed even more urgent with the growing likelihood that the four million Jews of the western Soviet Union would fall under German control. REFERENCE-The minutes of the Wannsee Conference estimated the Jewish population of the Soviet Union to be five million, including nearly three million in the Ukraine and 900,000 in Byelorussia.&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 July 1941 Hitler addressed a meeting of ministers, including [[Reichsmarschall]] [[Hermann Göring]], at which administration of the occupied Soviet territories was discussed. He said that Soviet territories west of the [[Ural Mountains|Urals]] were to become a &quot;German [[Garden of Eden]]&quot;, and that &quot;naturally this vast area must be pacified as quickly as possible; this will happen best by shooting anyone who even looks sideways at us.&quot; REFERENCE-[[Christopher R. Browning]], ''The Origins of the Final Solution'' (University of Nebraska Press 2004), 309. The quotations are from [[Martin Bormann]]'s minutes of the meeting, which were presented in evidence at the [[Nuremberg Trials]].&lt;/ref&gt;''

::''Hitler's chief lieutenants, Göring and the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] chief [[Heinrich Himmler]], took this and other comments by Hitler at this time (most of which were not recorded, but were attested to at postwar trials) as authority to proceed with a definitive &quot;final solution of the Jewish question&quot; (''Die Endlösung der Judenfrage'') involving the complete removal of the Jews from the German-occupied territories...''

::Now it is deleted. It might be done with all the right reasons, but I am curious what these reasons are. Regards,[[User:Jeff5102|Jeff5102]] ([[User talk:Jeff5102|talk]]) 09:13, 8 June 2013 (UTC)
:::The paragraph about Aktion T4 was off-topic and unsourced. The second paragraph was also unsourced, and was replaced with two paragraphs of more detailed well-sourced information about [[Generalplan Ost]] and the [[Hunger Plan]]. The next three paragraphs were largely unsourced as well. The only thing that had a citation was the Garden of Eden quotation, which was sourced to Browning page 309. This material was replaced with one paragraph of more detailed well-sourced information covering what happened after the start of Barbarossa. I think you are right in that we should add some material about the activities of the Einsatzgruppen in Poland from the start of the war to Barbarossa to cover the time frame September 1939 to July 1941, but I think the material on Aktion T4 should stay out, as it's off-topic. -- [[User:Diannaa|Dianna]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 15:33, 8 June 2013 (UTC)
::: I think if I give you a little background information on myself, perhaps you might find it reassuring. I have been editing on this wiki since 2009 and became an administrator a year later. I currently have over 71,000 edits to this wiki. Since late 2011 I have been focussing on improving our most important articles on Nazi Germany. Specifically I have been doing re-writes of articles for which I am able to obtain sources, with an eye toward nominating articles for Good Article status. In most cases it's sourcing that separates an ordinary article from a Good Article. Unsourced or poorly sourced material has to be removed and replaced with sourced material. Vague and generalised unsourced information can and should be replaced with detailed information sourced to high-quality books and journal articles. Off-topic material needs to be removed in order to pass a GA nomination.&lt;p&gt;A list of articles that I've already brought to GA status can be found at [[User:Diannaa/Barnstars]] and my most recent nomination, [[Nazi Germany]], will be promoted in the next few days. [[Talk:Nazi Germany/GA1]]. I chose to work on Wannsee Conference because there's two good books on the topic available at my local library, and there's information on this topic in Longerich and Evans as well, so I have almost enough source material to bring the article up to GA. I am now awaiting a copy of ''Eichmann: His Life and Crimes'' which I have ordered from Amazon and then I will be able to finish up here and nominate for GA. -- [[User:Diannaa|Dianna]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 16:49, 8 June 2013 (UTC)

::::: I wrote the first and second paragraphs which you say are off-topic and unsourced.   I disagree.   First, in the context of a increasingly murderous regime, culminating in genocide, the inclusion of the [[Aktion T4]], a program of forced euthanasia, is not only germane, but serves to underscore the point that the Wansee Conference did not represent a distinctly different or new direction for Nazi Germany circa 1941:  it is called a 'final solution' not for the end result but because of the increasingly drastic solutions tried beforehand.   The' euthanasia' decree also underlines how far the Nazis were willing to go for racial and societal purity.  It is context.   Secondly, I was careful to link them to other wikipedia articles, which are themselves sourced.   Why does this not provide adequate sourcing?  Not every sentence has to be sourced rigorously if the focus of that sentence has it's own page and that page well sourced. --[[User:Petrsw|Petrsw]] ([[User talk:Petrsw|talk]]) 16:24, 26 November 2013 (UTC)
:::::: At [[WP:Good article]] level and above, all material requires a source. That's what separates GA-class articles from B-class and C-class. Pointing to other articles is not considered adequate sourcing to pass an article to GA-class. I chose not to include any information on Action T4 or the Madagascar Plan in the background section when I did the re-write, as I think it's too much detail for this article. The article was promoted to GA in pretty much its present state, so I think these were good choices. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 20:10, 26 November 2013 (UTC)

::::Thank you very much for your explanation. I've been editing om Wikipedia for some time now, and one of the things I do is chasing vandals who abuse WWII-articles (like [[User:Sempi]] or the person behind [[User talk:188.223.142.186]].) When I saw you deleting certain paragraphs here I was too swift with my conclusions.  It looks like I was suffering from [[tunnel vision]], I fear. My apologies and keep up the good work! Regards, [[User:Jeff5102|Jeff5102]] ([[User talk:Jeff5102|talk]]) 20:16, 8 June 2013 (UTC)

== Pop culture trivia ==

I removed pop culture trivia from this article on June 20, and it has now been re-added. The reason I removed it is because of the rationale provided in my edit summary: [[WP:MILPOP]] calls for the exclusion of &quot;In popular culture&quot; sections unless the subject has had a well-cited and notable impact on popular culture. This conference has not had a wide impact on popular culture, so the section needs to be removed, and I am doing so right now. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 02:33, 24 June 2013 (UTC)
:Diannaa, I will look in detail into the wikipedia guidelines you mention. If indeed the section does not belong here, it then it would be appropriate to list both films under the &quot;See also section&quot;, as they are wikipedia articles related to the topic. I will add them there. ([[User talk:Al83tito|talk]]) [[user:Al83tito|user:Al83tito]]  3:58, 24 June 2013 UTC
::That would be a good compromise. Thanks, -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 14:24, 24 June 2013 (UTC)

{{Talk:Wannsee Conference/GA1}}

== Aftermath ==

Isn't there a place to mention in the table, what happened to the Conference participants after the war was over?
Many of them were sent to jail for a few years, and later worked as clerks in West Germany.
Hardly any of them, like most of the German war criminals, was seriously punished by post-war Germany's juridical system.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.173.56.94|76.173.56.94]] ([[User talk:76.173.56.94|talk]]) 06:27, 20 January 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: I think it an excellent idea to add a section on post conference activities of the participants.  I don't think, however, it is entirely accurate to say &quot;hardly any of them was seriously punished&quot;   Some did escape formal punishment: Heydrich, for example was killed by Czech partisans only a few months after the Conference; Friesler died in a bombing raid in '45; Lange is believed to have died fighting the Soviets in '45.   As for punishment: Buhler was indicted at Nuremburg and later transferred to Poland for further trial, after which he was executed;  Shongarth was executed by the Brits;   Eichmann escaped, lived in Argentina until capture, trial and execution by the Israelis in '62.  A few of the others died, either from natural causes, or apparent suicide, before being caught.  Some served some time but the courts were unable to accurately determine guilt.  Only Heinrich Muller was completely unaccounted for: he disappeared, and it is believed that he died in the bunker shortly after Hitler killed himself but no body was ever found. [[User:TreebeardTheEnt|TreebeardTheEnt]] ([[User talk:TreebeardTheEnt|talk]]) 13:59, 20 January 2014 (UTC)

: I don't think it's a good idea to add material on the fate of the attendees, as it's off-topic for this article and is readily available in their individual articles. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 15:17, 20 January 2014 (UTC)

:: Completely disagree.  If the postwar Nuremberg trials occurred and are referenced here (which they are prominentlly) it is accurate and wholly on-topic to note the relationship of the conference attendees to the aftermath.   Indeed,  If the house itself is now a holocaust museum... that is to say if there is a section on the aftermath with respect to the setting of the conference (...and there is...) why are relationships of the attendees to the trials not mentioned.  Indeed, I think this a rather glaring omission and not at all 'off-topic'.   [[User:TreebeardTheEnt|TreebeardTheEnt]] ([[User talk:TreebeardTheEnt|talk]]) 15:31, 20 January 2014 (UTC)

:: Also missing, in light of the section entitled &quot;Interpretation&quot; in which the analyses points to power consolidation by Heydrich rather than new policy as to the meetings purpose, is any discussion whatsoever about Heydrichs death , less than six months later and the effect, if any, this had upon the plans.    Given that it is clearly stated that Heydrich called the meeting to &quot;impose his own authority on the various ministries and agencies involved in Jewish policy matters, and to avoid any repetition of the disputes that had arisen earlier in the annihilation campaign.&quot;  One is left to wonder if, in fact, these disputes arose again...   I think failure to note the aftermath is not good history, the conference didn't occur in a vacuum and it did have consequences... well, what were they?  [[User:TreebeardTheEnt|TreebeardTheEnt]] ([[User talk:TreebeardTheEnt|talk]]) 15:42, 20 January 2014 (UTC)
::: The only trial that is mentioned in the article is Eichmann's trial, and only to discuss his testimony about the Wannsee Conference. Heydrich's death is off-topic, and does not belong in this article unless there's reliable sources that make a link between the two events. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 19:49, 20 January 2014 (UTC)

:::: What are you talking about? Did you even read the article?  The third graf of the intro specifically mentions the Tribunal at Nuremberg.  It's mentioned again later.  Also,  Heydrichs death is absolutely on topic, unless you want to treat the Wansee Conference as an isolated event, in a vacuum, untouched by, and untouching, other events.   Why have a page on the conference at all if not to put it in the context of what the Nazis were and what they did?  It absolutely makes NO SENSE to insert all that information about Heydrich consolidating power and the resulting plan put into place without noting that &lt;em&gt;VERY SHORTLY&lt;/em&gt; afterward Heydrich was killed...  If Heydrichs death is off-topic then the entire &quot;interpretation&quot; section is likewise off topic, else you have to argue that the Wannsee Conference had no implications on further actions of the Nazis.  Why, then, have the page at all?   If nothing about the aftermath is, as you allege, on-topic than the section about the building now being a holocaust museum is likewise off topic. [[User:TreebeardTheEnt|TreebeardTheEnt]] ([[User talk:TreebeardTheEnt|talk]]) 22:28, 20 January 2014 (UTC)

== Purpose mistated ==

The purpose of the conference was not &quot;whereby most of the Jews of German-occupied Europe would be deported to Poland and murdered&quot;. It was to &quot;cleanse&quot; Germany - or rather a Greater Germany - of Jews by emigration to the East.[[User:Royalcourtier|Royalcourtier]] ([[User talk:Royalcourtier|talk]]) 03:34, 6 April 2015 (UTC)
:The purpose of the conference - as cited by numerous sources - was to work out the practical issues of the Holocaust for ANYPLACE that the German army held or was to hold - i.e., if the Nazi's had control of the territory, the Jews in that territory would be eliminated.[[User:HammerFilmFan|HammerFilmFan]] ([[User talk:HammerFilmFan|talk]]) 16:21, 26 April 2015 (UTC)
: The Germans often used euphemisms, especially when discussing illegal activities. &quot;Evacuation to the east&quot; was a euphemism for death. Heydrich called the conference for a couple of reasons. First, he wanted to assert that his dept (the RSHA) would be heading up the project, and that the SS would be in charge of the actual exterminations. Second, he wanted to arrive at a decision as to who exactly would be killed. Longerich points out that the conference also has the side benefit of making everyone present an accomplice to the crime, and thus ensuring their silence. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 16:34, 26 April 2015 (UTC)

::Yehuda Bauer, professor of Holocaust Studies at the Avraham Harman Institute of Contemporary Jewry at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, says that to claim that the Wannsee Conference was all about “killing Jews,” or as Netanyahu told the United Nations, that the minutes contain “precise instructions on how to carry out the extermination of the Jews . . .” is an outright lie, a &quot;silly story.&quot;

::Bauer is also the founding editor of the journal Holocaust and Genocide Studies, and a member of the editorial board of the Encyclopaedia of the Holocaust, published by Yad Vashem in 1990. 

::As long ago as 1992, Bauer, speaking at a conference held in London to mark the fiftieth anniversary of the Wannsee meeting, told the audience that the claim that Wannsee was a “master plan” to kill Jews was nothing a but a “silly story.”

::Bauer’s remarks were reported in the Jewish Telegraphic Agency of January 23, 1992, and the Canadian Jewish Times of January 30, 1992.

::Titled “Nazi Scheme Not Born at Wannsee, Israeli Holocaust Scholar Claims,” (http://www.jta.org/1992/01/23/archive/nazi-scheme-not-born-at-wannsee-israeli-holocaust-scholar-claims) the JTA report continued:

::&quot;London (JTA)—An Israeli Holocaust scholar has de-bunked the Wannsee Conference, at which top Nazi officials are said to have gathered at a villa in a Berlin suburb in 1942 to draw the blueprints of the ‘Final Solution.’

::According to Prof. Yehuda Bauer of the Hebrew University in Jerusalem, Wannsee was a meeting, ‘but hardly a conference’, and ‘little of what was said there was executed in detail.’

::Bauer addressed the opening session of an international conference held here to mark the 50th anniversary of the decision to carry out the &quot;Final Solution&quot;. &quot;But it was not made at Wannsee&quot;, the Czech born scholar said.

::&quot;The public still repeats, time after time, the silly story that at Wannsee the extermination of the Jews was arrived at, Wannsee was but a stage in the unfolding of the process of mass murder,&quot; he said.&quot;

::His comments were repeated in the Canadian Jewish News, which read as follows:

::&quot;Wannsee’s importance rejected 

::London (JTA) — An Israeli Holocaust scholar has debunked the Wannsee Conference, at which top Nazi officials are said to have gathered at a villa in a Berlin suburb in 1942 to draw the blueprints of the “Final Solution.”

::According to Prof. Yehuda Bauer (photo) of the Hebrew University in Jerusalem, Wannsee was a meeting, “but hardly a conference”, and “little of what was said there was executed in detail.”

::“The public still repeats, time after time, the silly story that at Wannsee the extermination of the Jews was arrived at.”

== Is the phrase precise? ==

:''Jews of German-occupied Europe would be deported to Poland and murdered''
:Poland belonged to German-occupied Europe but the phrase excludes it.
:Some German Jews were transported to places outside Poland, see [[Riga Ghetto]].[[User:Xx236|Xx236]] ([[User talk:Xx236|talk]]) 06:53, 13 June 2016 (UTC)
::Do you have a suggested wording? how about &quot;Jews of German-occupied Europe would be deported and murdered&quot; ? — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 15:44, 13 June 2016 (UTC)
::*Deported, but where? The word deportation implies expulsion from one territory to another. Meanwhile, the point of destination still needs to be defined in an unambiguous way. '''&lt;font color=&quot;darkblue&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;[[User:Poeticbent|Poeticbent]]&lt;/font&gt;''' &lt;font style=&quot;color:#FFFFFF;font-size:7.0pt;font-weight:bold;background:#FF88AF;border:1px solid #DF2929;padding:0.0em 0.2em;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Poeticbent|talk]]&lt;/font&gt; 17:07, 13 June 2016 (UTC)
:::They were deported to multiple locations or killed on the spot. How much of this needs to be included in the lead? because that's where the sentence under discussion is located. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 17:38, 13 June 2016 (UTC)
::::The first and the last paragraphs in the lede seems stubby and should be merged. Not everybody needs to be mentioned upfront, like [[Robert Kempner]] for example. '''&lt;font color=&quot;darkblue&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;[[User:Poeticbent|Poeticbent]]&lt;/font&gt;''' &lt;font style=&quot;color:#FFFFFF;font-size:7.0pt;font-weight:bold;background:#FF88AF;border:1px solid #DF2929;padding:0.0em 0.2em;&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Poeticbent|talk]]&lt;/font&gt; 19:06, 13 June 2016 (UTC)
:::::Sounds okay to me. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 19:22, 13 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>f22oud2r1onwpx313kre1qopdvpet4n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
