<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Byzantine Empire under the Komnenos dynasty</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12406141</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743152865</id>
      <parentid>743095852</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-08T04:58:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>3family6</username>
        <id>8294396</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Iazyges|Iazyges]] ([[User talk:Iazyges|talk]]): I think that this was a mistake. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12517">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=22:27, 24 December 2007
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=180026652
|dykdate=July 25 2007
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=History
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=GA}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=GA|Medieval=yes|Roman=y|Balkan=y|Middle-Eastern-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Eastern Orthodoxy|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=GA|importance=High|Crusades-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Greece|class=GA|importance=High
&lt;!-- B-Class parameters --&gt;
|B-Class-1       = yes
|B-Class-2       = yes
|B-Class-3       = yes
|B-Class-4       = yes
|B-Class-5       = yes
|topic=history|byzantine-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Turkey|class=GA|importance=high}}
}}

== What this article should have ==
Hi Bigdaddy1204, nice work, though I think this article needs a little rough bits removed and some others added.

*First of, I know this may sound like I am getting left out but the [[Byzantine-Seljuk Wars]] article should be either linked and/or mentioned with its own section. Since you have already spread the article amongst the three prominent Komnenoi leaders, its probably just best to mention it a little, link to [[Byzantine-Seljuk Wars]] and leave it be.

*Secondly the Angeloi and decline section should be reduced - I know that the Angeloi were related to the Komnenoi but they have their own dynasty I thought, so we should make it its own article. 

*From the second point the decline section should only mention Andronikus Comnenus and the other Comnenoi leader, I forget his name. In any case it wasn't so much of a decline as a stagnation period since the empire was still strong and Andronikus had attempted to maintain the wise reforms of Manuel Comnenus.

Apart from that it looks great. I believe we can add more detail. Its summer and believe it or not I usually have more time to edit when I am at Uni then at free time. So I can't make any promises, I might stick my head in now and again to assist.

Regards,

[[User:Tourskin|Tourskin]] 19:40, 23 July 2007 (UTC)

Thanks! I have added the link to Byzantine-Seljuk Wars. Nice article, by the way. 

*I agree about the Angeloi and decline. I will try to tidy that section up at some point. 

*I also agree that there should be more on Andronikos. Unfortunately I don't know so much about him as the other Komnenoi, but it would certainly be a good idea to add more. 

I must go, but I shall return soon! [[User:Bigdaddy1204|Bigdaddy1204]] 15:11, 25 July 2007 (UTC)

: I'll see what the Oxford encyclopedia of Byzantium has about Andronikus. [[User:Tourskin|Tourskin]] 18:27, 25 July 2007 (UTC)

I have now added a large section dedicated to Andronikos, using information taken mainly from Ostrogorsky's 'History of the Byzantine state'. I will try to clear up the sections on the Angeloi and Fourth Crusade next, together with the conclusion. [[User:Bigdaddy1204|Bigdaddy1204]] 16:43, 26 July 2007 (UTC)

== GA review ==

I have taken on [[Byzantium under the Komnenoi]] for review under the [[WP:WIAGA|Good Article criteria]], as nominated on the [[WP:GAC|Good article candidates]] page by [[User:Deucalionite]]. You'll be pleased to hear that the article meets none of the [[WP:QFC|quick-fail criteria]], so I'll shortly be conducting an in-depth review and will post the results below.

Where an article is not an outright ''pass'', but requires relatively minor additional work to be brought up to GA standard, I will normally place it ''on hold'' - meaning that editors have around a week to address any issues raised. As a precaution to prevent failure by default should this occur, if editors are likely to be unavailable over the next ten days or so, feel free to leave a message on my [[User talk:EyeSerene|talk]] page so we can arrange a more convenient time for review. Regards, [[User:EyeSerene|EyeSerene]]''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;'' 09:28, 26 July 2007 (UTC)

:I would be very pleased if this article could become a 'Good article'. I will try, time permitting, to improve it as best I can. Perhaps it may even become a Featured Article eventually; I am reminded of an article I worked on, [[Manuel I Komnenos]], which first became a 'Good Article', and then became a 'Featured Article', and ended up appearing on the Wiki Main Page. Thanks for taking on the review; hopefully this article has a good future ahead of it :) [[User:Bigdaddy1204|Bigdaddy1204]] 16:49, 26 July 2007 (UTC)

::Thanks for the comment. I'm a bit reluctant to start the GA review process whilst the article is being worked on (although minor edits are not a problem), so I'll check back at the weekend. If you are undertaking a lengthy copyedit, it might be best to delist the article and re-nom later when you are ready. Regards, [[User:EyeSerene|EyeSerene]]''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;'' 10:31, 27 July 2007 (UTC)

Perhaps that would be best, for now. I am going away this weekend, so I won't be able to do much more until I return on Monday evening. I think there is still some more work to be done on this article, including improving the Conclusion section, improving the references, expanding the bibliography, and tidying up minor issues such as spelling mistakes, etc. I don't think this work will take very long, but I probably won't have time to complete it until early next week. [[User:Bigdaddy1204|Bigdaddy1204]] 11:31, 27 July 2007 (UTC)

:::If your copyedit is likely to be finished next week I don't really see a problem with keeping the review on hold for now. If you don't mind, just drop a note on my talk page when it's done. Cheers! [[User:EyeSerene|EyeSerene]]''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;'' 12:00, 27 July 2007 (UTC)

===GA Status on hold===

I have now reviewed this article under the six [[WP:WIAGA|Good article criteria]], and have placed it '''on hold''' pending the issues below being addressed:
*Prose - in places this is unencyclopedic in its tone. The main offender is the '''Andronikos I Komnenos''' section, with sentences like &quot;Endowed by nature with the most remarkable gifts both of mind and body, he was handsome and eloquent, but licentious; and, at the same time, active, hardy, courageous, a great general and an able politician. However, he was also capable of terrifying brutality, violence and cruelty.&quot; If this is a direct quote from a book, which is how it reads, it should be marked as such... otherwise it needs a rewrite.
*Sourcing - there are a number of statements that should be either sourced or removed. To give a couple of examples:
:*&quot;This helps to explain how the Komnenian emperors, Manuel Komnenos in particular, were able to project their power and influence so widely at this time.&quot; (also maybe a slight rewrite here for tone)
:*Parts of '''Andronikos I Komnenos''' are unsourced (generally at least one cite for each paragraph is preferred)
*Sections
:*The '''Conclusion''' section should be merged into the rest of the article. This is not an essay and should not have a conclusion; much of this probably belongs in the article introduction.
:*Some headings do not comply with the [[WP:MOS|Manual of Style]]. I would recommend changing '''John's restoration of the empire''' to either '''John's restoration''' or simply '''Restoration'''; and possibly '''Slow recovery''' to '''Recovery'''
:*'''Military reform''' lacks detail - it states that there was one, but does not explain what it was or how it was accomplished... although this is mentioned elsewhere. It might be worth either removing this section entirely or padding it out a bit (although the latter might mean removing parts of other sections to avoid repetition).
*Footnotes - although not a requirement for GA status, it's useful to use the templates on [[WP:CITET]] to format references and footnotes. This helps out later when bots are used for tasks like converting 10-digit ISBNs to 13-digits, or for tracking down archived versions of web pages that  have gone dead. In any case, ISBNs should be provided for all book references used.
'''Hold''' status gives editors up to 7 days to implement the changes requested - I'll check back here in a week, or feel free to leave me a note on my talk page if ready before that. I have fixed a few minor things myself as I was reviewing (mostly grammar to avoid word repetition and remove commentary). All the best, [[User:EyeSerene|EyeSerene]]''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;'' 10:20, 2 August 2007 (UTC)

:I have done my best to address the issues raised above, and I feel the article is now ready to be reconsidered. I have also left a message at your talk page. Best wishes, [[User:Bigdaddy1204|Bigdaddy1204]] 16:00, 2 August 2007 (UTC)

===GA Pass===
Congratulations on an excellent copyedit on the suggestions provided. I have no hesitation in passing [[Byzantium under the Komnenoi]] as fully meeting the standards required of a Good Article, and have listed it as such on the [[WP:GA|Good articles]] page (under History &gt; World History). For the record, [[User:Bigdaddy1204|Bigdaddy1204]] was the major contributor, with 41 edits at the date of final review. Well done! [[User:EyeSerene|EyeSerene]]''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;'' 17:48, 2 August 2007 (UTC)

== Alexios and his origins ==

At the moment Alexios seems to appear as emperor out of nowhere, perhaps a little background to his family might be useful.

They were members of the Anatolian &quot;military aristocracy&quot; with their powerbase in the region of Kastamonou (Castra Comnenion) in the northern Anatolian plateau. A relative of Alexios, Isaac (his uncle?) had been emperor (aknowledged as legitimate), relatively briefly, before him and his wife was a member of the imperial Dukas dynasty.  He was involved in the suppression of the the revolt of the Norman mercenary Roussel in Anatolia before he became emperor.  Therfore, Alexios had a solid reputation as a general and all the important family connections to make a bid for the throne successful.

[[User:Urselius|Urselius]] 15:06, 14 August 2007 (UTC)

== A problem of style versus meaning ==

&quot;Some headings do not comply with the Manual of Style. I would recommend changing John's restoration of the empire to either John's restoration or simply Restoration; and possibly Slow recovery to Recovery&quot; 


I disagree with this change on the grounds that the original phrase was explicit - &quot;John oversaw a restoration in the empire's fortunes&quot; whereas the replacement phrase suggests the alternative meaning &quot;John was restored to his throne.&quot;   The latter meaning is historically untrue, John never lost his throne and was never restored.

[[User:Urselius|Urselius]] 15:13, 14 August 2007 (UTC)

:I changed this to '''Restoration under John II Komnenos''' - is this better? [[User:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;RoyalBlue&quot;&gt;EyeSerene&lt;/font&gt;]]''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;OliveDrab&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;'' 09:42, 19 September 2007 (UTC)

Aye! - Eye [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] 12:41, 26 September 2007 (UTC)

:I just grin and bear it. [[User:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;RoyalBlue&quot;&gt;EyeSerene&lt;/font&gt;]]''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:EyeSerene|&lt;font color=&quot;OliveDrab&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;'' 13:11, 26 September 2007 (UTC)

==GA Sweeps (Pass)==
This article has been reviewed as part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Good articles/Project quality task force]]. I believe the article currently meets the criteria and should remain listed as a [[WP:GA|Good article]]. The article history has been updated to reflect this review. Cheers, [[User:Canadian Paul|CP]] 22:42, 24 December 2007 (UTC)

==Merging this article==

Each dynasty under the Byzantine Empire has its own article, and therefore material from the article [[Byzantine civilisation in the twelfth century]] would fit in nicely here as merged material. I would hope this is agreeable... [[User:Monsieurdl|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000C8;font-family: vivaldi&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=3&gt;'''Monsieur&lt;font color= &quot;#DC143C&quot;&gt;dl'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Monsieurdl|mon talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:36, 8 November 2009 (UTC)

==Move discussion in progress==
There is a move discussion in progress on [[Talk:Komnenoi#Propose move |Talk:Komnenoi]] which affects this page. Please participate on that page and not in this talk page section. Thank you. &lt;!-- Talk:Komnenoi crosspost --&gt; —[[User:RM bot|RM bot]] 08:30, 8 November 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ocldbihyxcd0lq4tz8oeiuz620gkbq0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
