<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Sajmište concentration camp</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12381928</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742109427</id>
      <parentid>720888312</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-01T19:34:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DatBot</username>
        <id>29088686</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */Converting WikiProject Belgrade to WikiProject Serbia/Belgrade task force per consensus (BOT)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15986">{{GA|00:10, 8 July 2013 (UTC)|topic=World history|page=1|oldid=563304133}}
{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST
|class=GA
|B-Class-1=yes
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|German=yes
|Balkan=yes
|WWII=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Correction and Detention Facilities|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Serbia|class=GA|importance=high|Belgrade=y|Belgrade-importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Yugoslavia|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Jewish history|class=GA| importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Discrimination|class=GA|importance=mid}}
}}


==Direct quotes are too long==
I just noticed that there are huge sections of direct quotes from a book in this article. Those quotes should be condensed, because Wikipedia isn't just supposed to copy and paste big chunks of text from other sources. The two very long quotes may even be a copyright violation, but I'm not certain.[[User:Spylab|Spylab]] 11:49, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
:This is hilarious - it remembers me to a Viennese Royal Opera director who once claimed that Mozart's Figaro had too many notes! Quotes to be condensed???  &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/{{{IP|{{{User|4.249.9.127}}}}}}|{{{IP|{{{User|4.249.9.127}}}}}}]] ([[User talk:{{{IP|{{{User|4.249.9.127}}}}}}|talk]]) {{{Time|23:18, August 23, 2007 (UTC)}}}&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

See [[WP:QUOTE]] for Wikipedia's guidelines on using quotes. (Also note that {{User|4.249.9.127}} is a suspected sock puppet of a permanently and repeatedly-banned individual).[[User:Spylab|Spylab]] 23:48, 23 August 2007 (UTC)

Quotes fixed.[[User:Mtsmallwood|Mtsmallwood]] ([[User talk:Mtsmallwood|talk]]) 16:18, 19 January 2009 (UTC)

===Note related to my August 30 2007 fix===

This user [[User:Spylab|Spylab]] does not read this article nor references given in this article even though he was warned about it several times. He requested reference for numbers of victims given in this article, even though the reference is given along with the quote (Dr Hinko Salz's testimony, Adolf Eichmann Trial, Tel Aviv 1961)

The second problem with his 'correction' is insertion of ''even though'' between these two sentences

As of 2006 Sajmište is still not a memorial center. On [[February 11]], [[1993]], the European parliament adopted the Resolution on European and International Protection of Concentration Camps as Historical Monuments.

which turns both statements into a false claim. The document (Resolution on European and International Protection of Concentration Camps as Historical Monuments) is just a set of recommendations - not obligatory to anyone, nor it mentione Sajmiste at all. But Spylab's 'correction' suggest that there are some obligations not fullfilled by someone. --[[User:4.249.6.37|4.249.6.37]] 02:45, 31 August 2007 (UTC)

*Note that the above comment was posted by a sock puppet of an individual who has been permanently-banned from posting on Wikipedia due to personal attacks, disruptive edits and sock puppetry. [[User:Spylab|Spylab]] 12:37, 3 September 2007 (UTC)

==Revisions January 19 2009==
I paraphrased the quotes, broke up the text into smaller sections, added some links in the text, added some categories, added The Holocaust navbox, added categories, and did some other clean up, such as bringing material from the notes into the body of the article.[[User:Mtsmallwood|Mtsmallwood]] ([[User talk:Mtsmallwood|talk]]) 16:18, 19 January 2009 (UTC)

== Sept 6th 2007 ==

I did not find it rational mentioning that Sajmiste was on the Belgrade outsikirts - not a singe reference found it rational. Moreover - it introduces ambiguity (occupied territory of Serbia vs. Independent State of Croatia)

[[Security Police]] is definitely not German Sichersheit Polizei - no need for this false linkage.

The Resolution on European and International Protection of Concentration Camps as Historical Monuments document has jurisdiction only over EU i.e. over her member states and it is not written to cover all concentration camps in Europe. So, this document is mentioned here out of the article context.

Linkages like [[As of 2006]] are meaningless due to the fact that the text under such a link does not have any information related to this article  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/4.249.75.44|4.249.75.44]] ([[User talk:4.249.75.44|talk]]) 01:45, 7 September 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Un-referenced ==

I completely removed 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
On [[February 11]], [[1993]], the European parliament adopted the ''Resolution on European and International Protection of Concentration Camps as Historical Monuments.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://eur-lex.europa.eu/smartapi/cgi/sga_doc?smartapi!celexapi!prod!CELEXnumdoc&amp;lg=en&amp;model=guicheti&amp;numdoc=51993IP0208M EUR-Lex - Simple search&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; However, it seems this does not pertain to 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

for seeing that reference as given leads nowhere. If someone can find online information about this resolution - it's ok with me to put the removed text back.

--[[User:Standshown|Standshown]] ([[User talk:Standshown|talk]]) 04:01, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
{{reflist-talk}}

== error: gas van ==

This Van is clearly a [[Magirus]]. Nothing is known about gas vans from &quot;Magirus&quot;. It should be removed because gas vans are known from the companies [[Saurer]], [[Diamond T], [[Opel]] and [[Renault]].  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Thomas Maierhofer|Thomas Maierhofer]] ([[User talk:Thomas Maierhofer|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Thomas Maierhofer|contribs]]) 07:34, 5 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

see Link: deathcamps.org/gas_chambers/gas_chambers_vans --[[User:Holgerjan|Holgerjan]] ([[User talk:Holgerjan|talk]]) 14:53, 5 September 2009 (UTC)

== NDH Territory ==

I wouldn't normally make an issue of it, but the mentioning of [[Independent State of Croatia]] in the lead section has a history in this article: there is an attempt at &quot;whitewashing&quot; or sidetracking the role of Serbian authorities concerning the camp. Yes, technically, it was located in NDH territory, but, terrible as they were, NDH puppet government had no role with this camp whatsoever. The camp was operated by Nazi, with assistance of Nedić's people, and it was meant exclusively for citizens of Serbia. [[Independent State of Croatia]] has nothing to do with it, and its mentioning in the lead, in my opinion, violates [[WP:UNDUE]] as an &quot;attention diversion&quot;. [[User:No such user|No such user]] ([[User talk:No such user|talk]]) 11:14, 21 October 2010 (UTC)

== again: gas van error ==


This Van is clearly a Magirus. Nothing is known about gas vans from &quot;Magirus&quot;. It should be removed because gas vans are known from the companies Saurer, [[Diamond T], Opel and Renault.

Das Foto zeigt keinen Gaswagen. Es handelt sich bei diesem Fahrzeug offensichtlich um einen Magirus-Deutz. Nach allen Veröffentlichungen wurden nur Wagen der vier Firmen Diamond, Renault, Sauer und Opel umgebaut.

 --- Vergleiche dazu folgenden Link: 
http:       //www.deathcamps.org/gas_chambers/gas_chambers_vans_de.html deathcamps

Der Fall des Vernichtungslagers Chelmno wurde durch die &quot;Hauptkommission für die Untersuchung von Verbrechen der Deutschen in Polen&quot; ab Mai 1945 untersucht (dies war der Name der Kommission zu Beginn ihrer Existenz). 
Die Kommission erhielt die Information, dass in der ehemaligen Ostrowski-Fabrik in der Stadt Kolo (ca. 12 km von Chelmno entfernt) ein Gaswagen steht, der laut Zeugenaussagen im Vernichtungslager Chelmno eingesetzt worden war. Der Wagen wurde gefunden, fotografiert und untersucht. 
Die damals aufgenommenen Fotos sind verwahrt im Archiv der Hauptkommission in Warschau (Signaturen: 47398, 47396, 47397, 47399, am besten ist Nr. 47398). Die Titel dieser Fotografien lauten auch heute noch: &quot;ein Wagen zum Töten von Menschen durch Auspuffgase, in Chelmno&quot;. Eines dieser Fotos wurde abgebildet in Flemings Buch &quot;Hitler and the Final Solution&quot;, mit der Information, dass es das Foto eines &quot;Gaswagens&quot; sei, der in Chelmno benutzt worden war. 
--[[Special:Contributions/87.142.146.158|87.142.146.158]] ([[User talk:87.142.146.158|talk]]) 17:29, 19 November 2010 (UTC) (de.Wikipedia Benutzer:Holgerjan)
==File:Chelmno Gas Van.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Chelmno Gas Van.jpg|File:Chelmno Gas Van.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests August 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 10:51, 14 August 2011 (UTC)
|}

{{Talk:Sajmište concentration camp/GA1}}

== Copyedit Nov 2013 ==

Hi

;Initial operation
*&quot;By October,&quot; - the previous section states that the camp was opened on 28 October, while this sentence claims that the killings were done before that. It also then talks about &quot;more frequent killings occurring in mid-September, between 9 and 11 October, and on 11 November.&quot; Something seems off with the dates as described. After re-reading the previous paragraphs and sections, I still am not sure which is correct.

Checks:
*Check for basic copyvio using Duplication Detector against 3 main refs - cannot complete as I do not have the books used.
*Citation bot - broken?
*dmy check script - not run
*Dashes script - run
*Enabled feedback tool - left for regular editors to choose implementation

I have given it one pass through, and will give it another later tonight, as well as running the other checks (my dashes script needs fixing for some reason). [[User:Chaosdruid|Chaosdruid]] ([[User talk:Chaosdruid|talk]]) 22:48, 22 November 2013 (UTC)

I also have a problem with the refs and notes sections. They are ''all'' refs, including the notes section. A notes section is for [NB-1] etc, and I would rename them:
*Notes -&gt; sub of References, renamed to Citations
*Books renamed as Bibliography
*Websites separated from the current &quot;Notes&quot; section and put into references on their own, as it currently seems impossible to see ''where they were used as inline citations'' from the Websites section of References. [[User:Chaosdruid|Chaosdruid]] ([[User talk:Chaosdruid|talk]]) 23:41, 23 November 2013 (UTC)

==Drljević==
I haven't been able to find a single source other than Kurapovna which states that Drljević &quot;administered&quot; the camp. Nor does Kurapovna provide a source to back up this assertion. Probably best to remove it. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 18:43, 22 February 2016 (UTC)

== Errors ==

''in late 1943, the new German ambassador to Serbia proposed that the camp be moved deeper into NDH territory''

Serbia was under military occupation as Gebiet des Militärbefehlshabers in Serbien. It was not recognized by Germany as an independent nation - so the Germany didn't have any diplomatic relationships with the puppet government in Serbia. I would like to check that at Christopher Browning's book before correcting it.

''Serbs send there jews, and this concentration camp was conducted by Serbs (Nedić). Beograd is a capital city of Serbia, but then it was just formally NDH.''

This poorly written statement is simply not true. Belgrade was not part of the Independent State of Croatia during the WW2. The German military authorities in Serbia sent Jews to this extermination camp. Please check other articles, such as [[The Holocaust in Serbia]], [[Territory of the Military Commander in Serbia]], [[Government of National Salvation]], and [[Staro Sajmište]]. I will correct this.
--[[User:N Jordan|N Jordan]] ([[User talk:N Jordan|talk]]) 16:50, 15 May 2016 (UTC)

:::Half the city was incorporated into the NDH (pretty much everything west of the Sava), so your statement is partially incorrect as well. It's true that a number of Jews were sent to the camp by collaborationist forces in Serbia but most had been arrested and deported by the Germans and Ustashe. The camp was run by the Germans and briefly by the NDH (though the vast majority of those who perished were killed by the Germans, not the Ustashe). In case, thanks for reverting the IP. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 22:28, 15 May 2016 (UTC)

::::I'm not sure if we can even talk about the city of Belgrade west of Sava, before the WW2. Other than the site of new city fair (built in 1938), there were only two settlements there. Both of them were not urbanized. The village of Bežanija was not part of the city at that time. 

::::Before the WW2, there was an administrative district called Uprava grada Beograda (eng. Belgrade City Administration) but that was a district - not the city of Belgrade itself. It included cities of Zemun and Pančevo. 

::::Maybe we could talk about the outskirts of Belgrade incorporated into the Independent State of Croatia (NDH), but definitely not about the half of the city.

::::Regarding the role of Serbian puppet government and local collaborationist forces, it is true that they helped round up Jews in Serbia. But they didn't send anybody to the camp, as they were even not permitted to enter the territory of the NDH. 

::::I'm ok with your edit but sooner or later somebody will want to emphasize that the NDH had nothing to do with the Judenlager Semlin (which is true). At that time, they will say that was operated by the Serbian puppet government (which is not true).--[[User:N Jordan|N Jordan]] ([[User talk:N Jordan|talk]]) 07:15, 16 May 2016 (UTC)

::I think we're more or less in full agreement. However, it is factually inaccurate to suggest it was ''not'' in the NDH as a number of sources point out and as can be seen on any wartime map. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 16:02, 16 May 2016 (UTC)

:::It was in the NDH, but it was organized or operated by the German military administration in Serbia. The civil and military authorities of the NDH had nothing to do with this camp.--[[User:N Jordan|N Jordan]] ([[User talk:N Jordan|talk]]) 04:11, 17 May 2016 (UTC)

::::I reshuffled the lead sentences to stress its geographical location – after all, this was a camp chiefly for Serbian inmates – and moved the NDH to second sentence as objectively less important. As N Jordan points out, from reading of the lead (and seeing just the intro in e.g. Google search or navigation popups) the reader gets a misleading impression that it was operated by the NDH. [[User:No such user|No such user]] ([[User talk:No such user|talk]]) 11:00, 17 May 2016 (UTC)

:::::Please check my latest revision. I tried to connect location to Zemun and Belgrade. At the same time to emphasize it was operated by Nazi forces in occupied Serbia. IMO we need this at the very beginning of article in order to avoid confusion. --[[User:N Jordan|N Jordan]] ([[User talk:N Jordan|talk]]) 06:25, 18 May 2016 (UTC)

::::::I'm OK with it, and 23 editor tweaked it further, so I think it closes the issue. For the time being, at least. [[User:No such user|No such user]] ([[User talk:No such user|talk]]) 15:29, 18 May 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gju3q62i1gznoa90lx3jhzgc8fgr67z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
