<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Shays' Rebellion</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>274476</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744007080</id>
      <parentid>744007036</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-12T15:04:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/71.125.29.245|71.125.29.245]] - &quot;/* Pseudonym */ Listing correct sources to end debate&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19762">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=19:35, 4 April 2012
|action1link=Talk:Shays' Rebellion/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=485581082
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=World history
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject United States|class=GA|importance=Low|MA=yes|MA-importance=}}
{{WPMILHIST
|class=GA
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes
|US=yes}}
{{WikiProject History|class=GA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject United States History|class=GA|importance=}}
}}
{{archive banner}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-08-29|oldid1=5533528|date2=2005-08-29|oldid2=22071515|date3=2006-02-03|oldid3=37995592|date4=2007-02-03|oldid4=105268709|date5=2010-02-03|oldid5=341416435|date6=2012-08-29|oldid6=509688624}}


==It is definitely NOT &quot;Shay's&quot; ==
I'm surprised that there can even be any question about it.  His name was Shays, not Shay.  The standard way to form a possessive in English is to add apostrophe-s.  Unless the possessor is a ''plural'' noun ending in s, in which case only the apostrophe is added.  So it's  cow -&gt; cow's and cows -&gt; cows' but ox -&gt; ox's and oxen -&gt; oxen's.  And Shays -&gt; Shays's. [[User:Katzenjammer|Katzenjammer]] 18:02, 18 October 2006 (UTC)

:I thought we'd finally gotten over the apostrophe problem.  Let's just leave it as &quot;Shays'&quot; since that's the predominant spelling.  Even Strunk &amp; White acknowledge the use of following apostrophes in historical context. --[[User:Dunkelza|Dunkelza]] 03:14, 29 October 2006 (UTC)

As for how it is spelled, the National Park website spells the event three different ways on the same page. I think that means in Wikipedia, we need to not highlight one way as the official way or the correct way to spell this event. Thus I am deleting any references to a correct spelling.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Agenbite|Agenbite]] ([[User talk:Agenbite|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Agenbite|contribs]]) 04:51, 12 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

No correct spelling -- great!  Below is the monument, modest as it may be, to the last battle: spelling is clearly &quot;Shays Rebellion.&quot;  As it is the only monument I know of, I suggest this be the &quot;authoritative source.&quot;--[[User:John Bessa|John Bessa]] ([[User talk:John Bessa|talk]]) 16:06, 22 October 2011 (UTC)

[[File:Monument to shays rebellion.jpg|200px]]

As it appears in the image above, it appears the name Shays is being used in a descriptive, as opposed to possessive, fashion. That is, we'd call it Kentucky Moonshine, and not Kentucky's Moonshine. Wonder if that point helps... --[[User:Foofighter20x|Foofighter20x]] ([[User talk:Foofighter20x|talk]]) 04:31, 21 January 2013 (UTC)

:Most [[WP:RS|sources]] use &quot;Shays'&quot; or &quot;Shays's&quot;; see various titles in the listed references.  We can forgive a stone carver for not adding an apostrophe. ''[[User:Magicpiano|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:khaki;color:firebrick;&quot;&gt;Magic&lt;/span&gt;]]''[[User_talk:Magicpiano|♪piano]] 15:02, 21 January 2013 (UTC)

::Just to be clear, I'm not making a case to change it from what it is, as it's been hashed out already. I just say the image and the thought occurred to me... Though, if I had been here and had a vote, I would have stood behind the &quot;Shays's&quot; version. -- [[User:Foofighter20x|Foofighter20x]] ([[User talk:Foofighter20x|talk]]) 17:20, 21 January 2013 (UTC)

:::It should definitely be '''Shays's Rebellion'''.&amp;nbsp; The only way &quot;Shays' Rebellion&quot; would be correct is if there were multiple Shayses leading the rebellion, and since there was only one Shays leading the rebellion, that makes it &quot;Shays's.&quot;&amp;nbsp; [[User:Allixpeeke|allixpeeke]] ([[User talk:Allixpeeke|talk]]) 02:35, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

::::Sources I've seen on the specific subject of possessive nouns and proper names ending in S are quite varied in their assessment of proper usage.  For example, [http://data.grammarbook.com/blog/apostrophes/apostrophes-with-words-ending-in-s/ this source] says that it is appropriate for proper name possessives to omit the trailing S.  [http://grammar.ccc.commnet.edu/grammar/possessives.htm This source] notes that Strunk and White recommend the trailing S as a general rule, but that other style guides (e.g. that of the New York Public Library) disagree in the case of words ending in S.  The fact that published sources discussing this event disagree in their treatment of the possessive form is to me an indicator that there is no single correct answer, and that either is correct, unless there is a specific Wikipedia MOS guideline on the matter. ''[[User:Magicpiano|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:khaki;color:firebrick;&quot;&gt;Magic&lt;/span&gt;]]''[[User_talk:Magicpiano|♪piano]] 13:18, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

:::::Even Strunk is not radical enough on this issue.&amp;nbsp; He makes exceptions for &quot;ancient proper names&quot; like Jesus.&amp;nbsp; I do not.&amp;nbsp; There are no exceptions.&amp;nbsp; [[User:Allixpeeke|allixpeeke]] ([[User talk:Allixpeeke|talk]]) 18:55, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

::::::Good luck getting your point of view enshrined in [[MOS:POSS]] then.  It allows both forms, as long as one is consistent within an article. ''[[User:Magicpiano|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:khaki;color:firebrick;&quot;&gt;Magic&lt;/span&gt;]]''[[User_talk:Magicpiano|♪piano]] 20:10, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

:::::::Just getting it enshrined in [[MOS:POSS]] is not enough.&amp;nbsp; It should be enshrined in every English grammar textbook in the universe.&amp;nbsp; There's no reason why ''any'' source needs to deceive people into thinking it is ''ever'' proper to make a singular noun possessive by merely adding an apostrophe.&amp;nbsp; Similarly, there's no reason why ''any'' source needs to deceive people into thinking that it is ever proper to use &quot;their&quot; as a possessive singular determiner or &quot;they&quot; as a singular pronoun (or, for that matter, to deceive people into thinking that it is ''im''proper to split infinitives.)&amp;nbsp; [[User:Allixpeeke|allixpeeke]] ([[User talk:Allixpeeke|talk]]) 05:04, 7 September 2015 (UTC)
...says a man referring to himself as allix and not Alex or even Alexander. [[User:Hackwrench|Hackwrench]] ([[User talk:Hackwrench|talk]]) 00:34, 4 September 2016 (UTC)
{{od}} 
Just chiming in to say there is also a monument in Petersham, Massachusetts that mentions the rebellion. It can be seen [http://shaysrebellion.stcc.edu/shaysapp/artifact_zoom.do?shortName=petersham_monument&amp;page= here]. Note that i do not agree with its editorial content in the least. [[User:SageRad|SageRad]] ([[User talk:SageRad|talk]]) 18:18, 15 November 2015 (UTC)

I was taught by my 8th grade English teacher Mr. Burgess (his name ends with an s, so he might have known) that all words ending in s can be made possessive by simply adding an apostrophe to the end of it, Thus, the man's name was Shays so it can become Shays' [[User:Hackwrench|Hackwrench]] ([[User talk:Hackwrench|talk]]) 00:22, 4 September 2016 (UTC)
And as for using their as a singular pronoun, I was informed that there was a long history of doing so until a relatively recent push to standardize English. At any rate, maybe all people trying to enforce a 'proper'English should be dragged behind horses and then shot! Jusy saying maybe, though. [[User:Hackwrench|Hackwrench]] ([[User talk:Hackwrench|talk]]) 00:30, 4 September 2016 (UTC)

== Leonard Richards' book as reference ==

The URL/links to Richards' book are to a sale listing at UPenn Publishing.  A preview version exists at GoogleBooks, but there are statements within this article that directly reference the UPenn Publishing statements as if they are quotes from the book and they are not.  I know that Richards is a respected historian and have no issue with using this book as a source/reference but the information/statements need to be quotes or need to be clearer, not synthesis by an unknown person on a publishing house website.  This is just an FYI that I'll be tidying up some of the information.  Thanks, [[User:Shearonink|Shearonink]] ([[User talk:Shearonink|talk]]) 18:55, 10 March 2015 (UTC)

: I changed the reference [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Shays%27_Rebellion&amp;diff=690927463&amp;oldid=690925549 here] to long format instead of just the URL. [[User:SageRad|SageRad]] ([[User talk:SageRad|talk]]) 15:59, 16 November 2015 (UTC)

== Pseudonym ==

(Name probably is assumed however multiple reliable sources attribute quoted material to this person. That being said, however, &quot;plough-jogger&quot; was another name for plowman/farmer. I have therefore delineated the name with quote-marks.)

I'd suggest two things.  One, we do '''not'' have ''multiple reliable sources.''  We have a mistake by Zinn, multiplied, quoted and plagiarized.  Secondly, I'd suggest that although Zinn is reliable in certain ways, he was a man with a strong, persistent habit of injecting his worldview in his work; something sourced strictly to Zinn, or to someone who used his work uncritically, has POV problems almost by definition.  [[User:Anmccaff|Anmccaff]] ([[User talk:Anmccaff|talk]]) 20:08, 25 April 2016 (UTC) 

The &quot;'''Plough Jogger'''&quot; as used to delineate this particular personage whose words are quoted is referenced in the following sources:
*'''The background of Shays's rebellion: a study of Massachusetts history 1780-1787''' by John Willard Hahn (1946, University of Wisconsin Press)
*'''Heritage from Hamilton''' by Broadus Mitchell (1957, Columbia University Press) - Page 26
*'''A little rebellion''' by Marion Lena Starkey (1955, Knopf) - Page 15
*'''AmericanHeritage, American Voices: Colonies and Revolution''' by David C. King (2003, John Wiley &amp; Sons) This book delineates the quoted words as being from an interview with one of the farmers, and as '''From an Interview in the Massachusetts Centinal, October 25, 1786'''
*'''Harvey Wasserman's history of the United States''' by Harvey Wasserman (1975, Harper &amp; Row)
*'''Yale Journal of the Law &amp; Humanities''' (Volume 25, Issue 2, Article 3) by Aaron T. Knapp (2013 Yale University PhD dissertation) found at http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1412&amp;context=yjlh which quotes from the statements and says these words are found in The Massachusetts Centinel/October 25, 1786 in a article or section called ''The Spirit of the Times''.

:To me this &quot;Plough Jogger&quot; seems to be along the same lines as &quot;Publius&quot;, the pseudonym by Hamilton, Madison &amp; Jay in the writing of the Federalist Papers.  It would seem that a &quot;report&quot; was published on October 25, 1786 that credited the speaker or interviewee as being &quot;Plough Jogger&quot;, which in that day &amp; age would have been understood not to be someone's real name, somewhat the same as if I interviewed a political adherent in the present US election season and said the interviewee was Hillary Clinton Supporter or Bernie Bro.  This speech was published in a paper of record and the person being interviewed was credited as &quot;Plough Jogger&quot;.  Unless we can find a reliable source that states this was not a real person but rather a straw man, standing in for the interviewer, I think setting the name/title off by quote-marks might be the best solution. [[User:Shearonink|Shearonink]] ([[User talk:Shearonink|talk]]) 21:36, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
::Well, &quot;Publius&quot; is a liitle more prep-school than grammar, but yeah.  &quot;Duhh,&quot; even.  An obvious pen-name or other pseudonym, that quite likely was also a Cincinnatus reference.  Of the cites you have above, how many have you seen in the print, vs the screen?  Hahn uses it quotes, and obviously realizes it isn't a real name.  [[User:Anmccaff|Anmccaff]] ([[User talk:Anmccaff|talk]]) 22:15, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
:::This is what I have been able to find in my short bit of research online today, here are the refs:
:::Hahn's writing seems to be a dissertation, due to its poor quality on the page, he sets the names off in quotes on his Page 33:
:::*&quot;Ploughjogger&quot; writing in the Massachusetts Centinel states that &quot;every person knows that we have waded through a long, bloody, and expensive war...&quot;
:::Broadus Mitchell writes (page 26):
:::*A farmer--&quot;plough-jogger he called himself--from the heart of Shays country, expressed in the Massachusetts convention&quot;
:::On Page 15 Marion Lena Starkey refers to the speaker:
:::*Old Plough Jogger still had the floor. &quot;I have been obliged to pay and nobody will pay me.&quot;
:::King has the speech or interview's words set off on Page 118 as being 
:::*&quot;From an Interview in the Massachusetts Centinal, October 25, 1786&quot; [https://books.google.com/books?id=sZzWgivOjbcC&amp;pg=PA118#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]
:::*So far as I can tell, Wasserman does not delineate the speaker as being &quot;Plough-jogger/Plough Jogger&quot; but he does quote the same words and says on Page 117 of the 2003 edition that it's &quot;a newspaper interview with one of the farmers&quot; [https://books.google.com/books?id=sZzWgivOjbcC&amp;pg=PA118#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Page 118]
:::The Yale Journal reference is from Aaron T. Knapp's PhD dissertation, the complete essay can be found at [http://digitalcommons.law.yale.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1412&amp;context=yjlh].  Knapp refers to &quot;a contemporaneous newspaper report purporting to have penetrated the minds of the insurgents and appropriately entitled ''The Spirit of the Times'' quoted one leading Shaysite's mission statement&quot;:
:::*&quot;The great men are going to get all we have, and I think it is time for us to rise and put a stop to it, and have no more courts, nor sheriffs, nor collectors, nor lawyers!&quot;  This information is sourced from ''The Spirit of the Times'', MASS. CENTINEL, Oct 25, 1786
:::The only way I can see to actually '''see''' what was said would be to get a hold of a digitized copy or microfiche copy that last out the complete article.  The various authors &amp; experts don't seem to lay out the actual source-material as it appeared at the time, but Zinn doesn't seem to be completely wrong in this matter.  It is absolutely clear to me that &quot;Plough Jogger&quot; is a pseudonym of some sort, that there might have been someone who actually said those things &amp; was quoted as saying them but there was never a living individual named Mr. Plough Jogger.[[User:Shearonink|Shearonink]] ([[User talk:Shearonink|talk]]) 23:17, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
::::Not completely wrong, but it suggests a truly superficial reading; grab a soundbite to quote and move on.  Wrong enough, I'd say. But I think your edit fixed it enough, just so long as some bozeau doesn't take one of the many cloned sources and revert it based on them. [[User:Anmccaff|Anmccaff]] ([[User talk:Anmccaff|talk]]) 05:46, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
:::::Sounds good.  Maybe there's some way to get a hold of an actual image of the Mass. Centinel/Centinal article/interview, to see what it actually says.  It would be even better if I could find some contemporaneous sources that react to the interview and see how they delineate the so-called &quot;name&quot;, if they put it in quotes or use adjectives like &quot;so-called&quot; or a pseudonym-type word to characterize Plough Jogger.  In any case, I'm going to put a permanent link to this discussion up at the top of the talk page and a hidden comment about the quote marks within the text, so people can refer to it before reverting or changing. [[User:Shearonink|Shearonink]] ([[User talk:Shearonink|talk]]) 16:53, 26 April 2016 (UTC)
::::::I added some more refs - that this interview exists, that the person is named as a &quot;plough jogger&quot;. Left comment re: Zinn but hid it from general readership's view pending any further developments. [[User:Shearonink|Shearonink]] ([[User talk:Shearonink|talk]]) 19:33, 26 April 2016 (UTC)

* '''Original source of &quot;old plough jogger&quot; quotation:''' The quote is from '''an unauthored piece called &quot;The Spirit of the Times&quot; in the ''Massachusetts Centinel'' (Boston, MA) vol VI, issue 11, 25 October 1786, p. 42.''' Marion Starkey re-imagines the tavern meeting in his book ''A Little Rebellion'' and pulls a long quotation, giving voice to &quot;old plough jogger&quot; which is likely where Zinn found the reference (Starkey includes no direct citations, hence the confusion). Accusing Zinn of &quot;hiding&quot; his citations is highly ungenerous, as he lists Starkey as a source. As others have noted, &quot;plough jogger&quot; was an often-used term for a type of person, with connotations anywhere from lower-class to a politicized populist persona -- letters of grievance through the 1800s are signed &quot;Plough Jogger.&quot; Thus the newspaper journalist referred to &quot;an old plough jogger&quot; at the meeting who said this. 

:Numerous historians other than Zinn have used the quote, including Elizabeth Beaumont, T''he Civic Constitution: Civic Visions and Struggles in the Path Toward Constitutional Democracy'' ch. 3, and as mentioned above, Aaron Knapp in his article &quot;Laws Revolution.&quot; The full quote, pulled directly from a digitized version of the ''Massachusetts Centinel'', is below. Its slight typographic divergence from the quote as given in People's History is, I think, a change that occurred in the transcription from ''Centinel'' to Starkey to Zinn:

::“.... I inquired of an old plough jogger the cause and aim of the people of that assembly? He said to get redress of grievances. I asked what grievances? He said we have all grievances enough, I can tell you mine; I have laboured hard all my days, and fared hard; I have been greatly abused; been obliged to do more than my part in the war; been loaded with class-rates, town-rates, province-rates, continental-rates, and all rates, lawsuits, and have been pulled and haulled by sheriffs, constables and collectors, and had my cattle sold for less than they were worth: I have been obliged to pay and nobody will pay me: I have lost a great deal by this man and that man and t’other man; and the great men are going to get all we have; and I think it is time for us to rise and put a stop to it, and have no more courts, nor sheriffs, nor collectors, nor lawyers; I design to pay no more; and I know we have the biggest party, let them say what they will.”  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.125.29.245|71.125.29.245]] ([[User talk:71.125.29.245#top|talk]]) 15:03, 12 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Very militant==
The article makes no attempts at addressing that there are alternatives to military action. There is no mention that there was or wasn't negotiations. [[User:Hackwrench|Hackwrench]] ([[User talk:Hackwrench|talk]]) 00:39, 4 September 2016 (UTC)
:Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, it does not publish [[WP:OR]], it is a compendium of information published in [[WP:IRS|reliable sources]].  If reliable sources have statements about the various alternatives to the putting down of Shays' Rebellion that were proposed at the time or these sources mention that negotiations took place or reputable historians have written articles/books about the circumstances surrounding the Rebellion (that then include if there were negotiations or not) in the intervening years, then the article could include that information.  Otherwise?...no. [[User:Shearonink|Shearonink]] ([[User talk:Shearonink|talk]]) 01:53, 4 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8mhmip9vt7algrespe3fetl7n4ksmkr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
