<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Edward Nicolls</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>26689329</id>
    <revision>
      <id>631133530</id>
      <parentid>630988453</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-26T02:21:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AustralianRupert</username>
        <id>8731061</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>update assessment; implement article history; detransclude review</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10334">{{ArticleHistory
| action1       =  GAN
| action1date   = 02:21, 26 October 2014 (UTC)
| action1link   = Talk:Edward Nicolls/GA1
| action1result = listed
| action1oldid  = 631132747
| currentstatus = GA
| itndate       = 
| dykdate       = 4 April 2010
| dykentry      = ... that '''[[Edward Nicolls]]''' proposed that [[oak]] trees be grown in [[Sierra Leone]] for the [[Royal Navy]]?
| dykviews = 1186
| topic         =  Warfare
| small         = 
}}
{{WPBiography|living=no|class=GA|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=mid|listas=Nicolls, Edward}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|Biography=yes|British=yes|Napoleonic=yes}}

==Untitled==
Some more mentions in James: http://freepages.genealogy.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~pbtyc/Naval_History/Index/Index_N.htm. &amp;mdash;[[User talk:Innotata|''innotata'']] 17:50, 10 April 2010 (UTC)

== Long quotations ==

The long quotations don't belong in the article or refs, so I'm moving them here:

Hart's Annual Army List, 1865 edition: &quot;2. Sir Edward Nicolls, with thirteen volunteers in a boat of the (HMS) Blanche frigate, boarded and captured, on the 3rd Nov. 1803, the French armed cutter Albion from under the guns of Monte Christie, St.Domingo,--in this action he was severely wounded by a musket-ball, which entering the abdomen, and coming out at his right side, lodged in the arm. On board the (HMS) Standard at the passage of the Dardanelles on 19thfeb.1807. On 26th June 1808, with a boat's crew, he boarded and captured the Italian gunboat Volpe near Corfu. Present at the reduction of the Island of Anholt in May 1809. Severely wounded at the attack on Fort Bowyer 15th September 1814 (NB: He lost the sight of his right eye). Was frequently employed in boat and battery actions. In 1804 was in a boat at the capture of a French brig; in 1804 he commanded the Royal Marines during the siege of Curaçao, and for 28 consecutive days was exposed to severe attacks of the enemy. At the passage of the Dardanelles he captured the Turkish flag, and was honourably mentioned. In 1807 he was at the blockade of Corfu, and the expedition to Egypt. In North America he raised and commanded a regiment of Indians, and was senior Major of all troops engaged in the attack on New Orleans in 1815. Was also governor of the islands of Anholt and Ascension. During the above service(s) he had his left leg broken,and right leg severely wounded, was shot through the body and right arm, received a severe saber cut in the head, was bayonetted in the chest, and lost the sight of an eye in his 107th action (at Fort Bowyer!) with enemies of his country. He was frequently mentioned in Dispatches, and received a sword of honor from the Patriotic Fund.&quot;

Nicolls's pamphlet in Louisiana: &quot;Pensacola, West Florida, Sloops of War HMS Hermes and Caron [via Bermuda and Havana] 29 August 1814....Natives of Louisiana! On you is made the first call to assist in liberating from a faithless, and imbecile government, your native soil.
Spaniards, Frenchmen, Italians, and Britons, whether settled or residing for a time in Louisiana, on you I also call to aid me in this just cause. The American usurpation in this country must be abolished, and the lawful owners of the soil put in possession. I am at the head of a large body of Indians, well armed, disciplined, and commanded by British officers-----a good train of artillery, with every requisite, seconded by the powerful aid of a numerous British and Spanish squadron of ships and vessels of war.

Be not alarmed, inhabitants of the country, at our approach; the same good faith and disinterestedness which has distinguished the conduct of Britons in Europe, accompanies them here. You will have no fear of litigious taxes imposed upon you for the purpose of carrying on an unnatural and unjust war; your property, your laws, and the peace and tranquility of your country will be guaranteed to you by men who will suffer no infringement on theirs;rest assured that these brave Red Men only burn with an ardent desire of satisfaction  for the wrongs they have suffered from the Americans, to join you in liberating these Southern Provinces from their yoke and drive them into the limits formerly prescribed by my sovereign.

The Indians have pledged themselves, in the most solemn manner, not to injure, in the slightest degree, the persons or properties of any but enemies to their Spanish or English fathers; a flag over any door, whether Spanish, French, or British, will be a certain protection, nor dare any Indian put his foot on the threshold thereof, under penalty of death, except resisting in arms; and, as for injuring helpless women and children, the Red Men, by their good conduct and treatment to them, will (if it be possible) make the Americans blush for their more inhumain conduct lately on the Escambia, and within a neutral territory.

Inhabitants of Kentucky, you have too long borne with grievious impositions; the whole brunt of the war has fallen on your brave sons; be imposed on no longer, but either range yourselves under the standard of your forefathers, or observe strict neutrality. If you comply with either of these offers, whatever provisions you send down will be paid for in dollars, and the safety of the persons bringing it, as well as the free navigation of the Mississippi, guaranteed to you.

Men of Kentucky, let me call to your view (and I trust to your abhorrence)the conduct of those factions which hurried you into this civil, unjust and unnatural war. At a time when Great Britain was straining every nerve in defense of her own and the liberties of the world-----when the bravest of her sons were fighting and bleeding in so sacred a cause----when she was spending millions of her treasure in endeavoring to pull down one of the most formidable and dangerous tyrants that ever disgraced the form of man----when groaning Europe was almost in her last gasp-----when Britons alone showed an undaunted front---basely did those assassins endeavor to stab her from the rear. She has turned on them, renovated from the bloody but successful struggle; Europe is happy and free, and she now hastens justly to avenge the unprovoked insult.

Show them that you are not collectively unjust; leave that contemtible few to shift for themselves; let these slaves of the tyrant send an embassy to Elba, and implore his aid; but let every honest, upright American spurn them with merited contempt. After the experience of twenty-one years, can you any longer support those brawlers for liberty, who call it freedom, when themselves are free? Be no longer their dupes; accept my offers;everything I have promised in this paper I guarantee to you on the sacred honor of a British officer.

&amp;mdash;[[User talk:Innotata|''innotata'']] 15:31, 12 March 2011 (UTC)

==Seniority of Major Nicolls in January 1815==
There were two Royal Marine officers holding the rank of Major who are documented as being present at New Orleans. Nicolls was appointed Major (by brevet) on 8 August 1810, whereas Adair was appointed Major (by brevet) on 4 June 1814.

As the more senior of the two, Nicolls should have commanded the 100 Marines. For the reasons stated in the article, Cochrane forbade Nicolls to participate.

Whether or not Nicolls was senior, in terms of tenure, to that of army officers present who held the field rank of Major is irrelevant.

It has been clearly stated in the article for the past 12+ months that Colonel William Thornton was in the 85th Foot. By verifying copies of the Army list, it is possible to double-check the regiment to which an officer belonged to. [[User:Keith H99|Keith H99]] ([[User talk:Keith H99|talk]]) 20:37, 14 September 2012 (UTC)
:He was the most senior Royal Marines officer present, though, correct? We should keep this simple (so only note this) and specifically cite stuff. &amp;mdash;[[User talk:Innotata|''innotata'']] 20:00, 17 September 2012 (UTC)

::Yes, this is correct. The aforementioned now explains the &quot;seniority&quot; context, as stated in the 19th century biography, where, presumably, the reader would have been aware of this practice, which is now outdated 150+ years on. [[User:Keith H99|Keith H99]] ([[User talk:Keith H99|talk]]) 21:52, 17 September 2012 (UTC)

==Portrait==
A 19th Century portrait of General Sir Edward Nicolls, KCB, Late of the Royal Marines has been circulating on the Web for a number of years. Variously described as (the copy of) a family portrait, or the possession of an institution or individual, this portrait may fall within the scope of policies permitting &quot;creative commons.&quot;. If the possibility exists to join this or other illustrations to the text, I would be grateful. Hopefully there are some editors or or contributors who are more savvy about this than I am. USMarine51 22:29, 20 December 2012 (UTC)   &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:USMarine51|USMarine51]] ([[User talk:USMarine51|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/USMarine51|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:We need to know it's 19th century, how do you know this? It presumably is out of copyright ('public domain'; Creative Commons works are those released by the author under a certain set of licenses), but we need information about it. &amp;mdash;[[User talk:Innotata|''innotata'']] 21:00, 22 December 2012 (UTC)


According to Nigel Moss (via Ancestry.com message boards...)

From: Nigel Moss
To: (USMarine51)
Subject: General Sir Edward &quot;Fighting Nicolls&quot; KCB

&quot;Dear Brian,
The original portrait of &quot;Fighting Nicolls&quot; is in the wardroom of the Royal Marine's Stonehouse Barracks, Plymouth, Devon, England. I believe the portrait was painted in 1855 when he (Nicolls) was knighted on 5 July 1855. The artist is unknown. I hope that is helpful, 
Regards, Nigel.&quot;

Note: The Royal Marines Museum at Portsmouth [info@royalmarinesmuseum.co.uk] might be a helpful place to start for enquiries concerning the portrait of Fighting Nicolls. Regards to all USMarine51 00:35, 1 January 2013 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:USMarine51|USMarine51]] ([[User talk:USMarine51|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/USMarine51|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>jzxm6ss52n73d4wz169j03tkbx05wxs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
