<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Gone with the Wind (film)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3082195</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744729632</id>
      <parentid>740140386</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-17T02:38:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Andrzejbanas</username>
        <id>1719098</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18803">{{Talk header}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talk archive navigation}}
|maxarchivesize = 70K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 4
|algo = old(31d)
|archive = Talk:Gone with the Wind (film)/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=12:48, 20 March 2013
|action1link=/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid= 545502684

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=film
}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=Art|class=GA}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Film|class=GA|B-Class-1=no|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=no|B-Class-4=no|B-Class-5=yes|core=yes|American-task-force=yes|War-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=GA|importance=low|USFilm=yes|USFilm-importance=low|USMIL=Yes|ACW=Yes}}
{{WikiProject Library of Congress|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Romance|class=GA}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA
&lt;!-- B-Class 5-criteria checklist --&gt;
 |B1 &lt;!-- Referencing and citations --&gt; = yes
 |B2 &lt;!-- Coverage and accuracy --&gt; = yes
 |B3 &lt;!-- Structure --&gt; = yes
 |B4 &lt;!-- Grammar and style --&gt; = yes
 |B5 &lt;!-- Supporting materials --&gt; = yes|Films=yes|US=yes|ACW=yes}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2013-12-15|oldid1=586012531|date2=2014-12-15|oldid2=638078161}}
{{Talk:Gone with the Wind (film)/GA1}}

== including Butler's &quot;Frankly, my dear&quot; quote in the Plot synopsis? ==

If anyone could find a way of working Butler's quote into the plot synopsis, I think that that would be useful.  I'd done so, but was told that referring to the line as the film's &quot;most famous&quot; was editorialising.  (I note that the box listing the AFI's &quot;100 years&quot; series lists it as the #1 movie quote over the past century.)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Colin Rowat|Colin Rowat]] ([[User talk:Colin Rowat|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Colin Rowat|contribs]]) 09:55, 26 June 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:It's a plot summary, and therefore the point of the section is to convey the story to readers. If you look at other articles about films they rarely included prominent quotes. In this case I think the AFI box is more than sufficient; however, there is [[Frankly, my dear, I don't give a damn|an article covering the quote and its context]] so I've come up with a compromise: [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gone_with_the_Wind_(film)&amp;diff=668757140&amp;oldid=668739035] [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 13:08, 26 June 2015 (UTC)

== Uncredited credits.  ==

Hi I have reverted the recent good faith edits of a contributor who understandably thinks it would be valuable to add some of the many officially uncredited performers and directors to the credits section. I believe this has come up before, and at the time the concensus was to limit the credits to exactly those presented in the film. Multiple conflicting sources and potentially hundreds of uncredited personnel on this film would seem point the advisability of this decision. But perhaps this has changed? Would other editors like to weigh in? Thanks, [[User:Markhh|Markhh]] ([[User talk:Markhh|talk]]) 17:46, 13 September 2015 (UTC)
:I only wanted to include a few of them, for example notable actors like [[Richard Farnsworth]] or memorable small roles (like [[Tommy Kelly (actor)|Tommy Kelly]]). There are numerous sources for those actors who agree that they were in the film. In fact, articles like ''[[Casablanca (film)|Casablanca]]'' (also featured article) or ''[[Citizen Kane]]'' in it's casting section include lots of uncredited actors. --[[User:Clibenfoart|Clibenfoart]] ([[User talk:Clibenfoart|talk]]) 18:40, 13 September 2015 (UTC)
::Firstly, you have a history of disruptive behavior at this article and it needs to stop. I don't want to have to seek a topic ban against a fellow editor but I will if I feel it is justified. Secondly, user edited websites such as IMDB are not reliables sources per [[WP:RS/IMDB]] (and Fandango isn't much better). And finally, per [[WP:FILMCAST]] ''Wikipedia is not an indiscriminate collection of information'' i.e. we don't include entire cast lists in articles. Each film is considered on a case-by-case basis, but given the size of the cast (hundreds of extras) the list is limited to the credited roles only. Does that mean further additions won't be considered? No. If there is something interesting or noteworthy to say about somebody's role or casting then we can consider mentioning them but it does mean we are not going to list uncredited cast members just for the sake of listing them. [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 19:47, 13 September 2015 (UTC)
:::Well, Betty Logan, you sure have another opinion at ''[[To Kill a Mockingbird (film)|To Kill a Mockingbird]]'' where you belong to the main editors of the article. There the uncredited roles are listed in a lavish way without any citations. I also wouldn't include the whole cast, just a few well-known uncredited cast members like [[Richard Farnsworth]]&amp;[[Frank Faylen]] or actors with memorable roles like [[Tommy Kelly (actor)|Tommy Kelly]] as the crying member of the boy band. --[[User:Clibenfoart|Clibenfoart]] ([[User talk:Clibenfoart|talk]]) 15:32, 15 November 2015 (UTC)
::::I am certainly not a &quot;main editor&quot; (I have edited it at most half a dozen times) and that article is not graded a &quot;Good article&quot;, unlike this one. My stance is the same there as it is here, as you can see at [[Talk:To_Kill_a_Mockingbird_(film)#Cast_listings]]: &quot;When we provide a full cast list in the article it should adhere to the cast list in the film as much as possible  ...  But when we explicitly present billing credits or cast lists these should factually reflect the credits and casts lists as found in the film itself.&quot; What we list depends on the nature of the film itself. If a film only has a handful of unbilled cast members there is no harm in adopting a completist approach and listing them but if you have hundreds of unbilled extras it would be [[WP:INDISCRIMINATE]] to list all of them, and an arbitrary selection based on an editor's opinion of what is memorable is just an arbitrary selection. As I pointed out in my previous comment, if there is something substantive to say about an unbilled cast member's casting or role then we can consider their inclusion, but the criteria is what sources consider worth documenting, not a single editor's opinion of what is memorable. [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 17:04, 15 November 2015 (UTC)

== misleading references to MGM ==

I have deleted recent additions that have crept in referring to MGM as a co-producer of GWTW. Nothing I have read about the film supports this. MGM did indeed play a pivotal role in loaning Clark Gable in exchange for the rights to distribute the film. They also loaned Victor Fleming and invested $1.25 million. However creatively it was entirely the work of Selznick and Selznick International Pictures. MGM was not part of its production. Perhaps I'm misunderstanding this, but crediting MGM I think is misleading as they had no part of the film's development and production except as noted above. I think this is important because as the company later assumed ownership of the film, it is often mistakenly thought of as an &quot;MGM production&quot;, but it absolutely was not. I would like to hear from other editors on this. Thanks, [[User:Markhh|Markhh]] ([[User talk:Markhh|talk]]) 20:06, 2 April 2016 (UTC)
:It may be worth looking at the opening credits here: [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pL2yPFxBQQ4]. The film opens with &quot;A Selznick International Picture&quot; followed by &quot;Selznick International in association with Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer&quot;. It was clearly &quot;made&quot; by SIP, and MGM was an associate producer (basically Hollywood lingo for an investor). Clearly SIP had a far more prominent role than MGM, but that's not to say MGM's role was negligible, so I'm receptive to both interpretations. Personally I thought [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gone_with_the_Wind_(film)&amp;oldid=710662542 the original version of the article] struck the correct balance i.e. just mentioning SIP in the lead as the company that actually made the film and including MGM in the list of companies in the infobox. [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 20:26, 2 April 2016 (UTC)
::Thanks Betty, I stand corrected. There it is in the second title card! I agree then regarding leaving MGM in the infobox but not in the lead para, which gives a bit too much prominence. Thanks. [[User:Markhh|Markhh]] ([[User talk:Markhh|talk]]) 20:57, 2 April 2016 (UTC)

== Last surviving cast members ==

A recent edit [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gone_with_the_Wind_(film)&amp;diff=722920138&amp;oldid=722874510 removed] the list of surviving cast members from the &quot;cast&quot; section on the basis of being &quot;irrelevant trivia&quot;. I don't know on what basis something is determined to be trivia or not but the claim is explicitly sourced and the subject is commonly reported in the media (you can see the number of publications that report on it from just a basic [http://www.google.com/search?q=surviving+gone+with+the+wind+cast Google search]). The upshot though is that when the media write about the GWTW cast they often list the surviving cast members, so secondary sources obviously do not consider information to be trivia. I also think it will be very relevant next month when [[Olivia de Havilland]] celebrates her centenary and I think there will be plenty of discussion in the media regarding her and other surviving cast members (in this case Mickey Kuhn and the odd extra). [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 23:57, 30 May 2016 (UTC)
:It's irrelevent because it doesn't help any reader understand anything significant about the movie.  Old people die.  This is an old movie, people who worked on it have gotten old.  A tally of who has died and who hasn't yet may be able to be referenced, and may be discussed somewhere (let's face it, in the modern world, someone discusses everything somewhere).  The issue is not if it's true, nor is it if someone else has noticed.  The issue is whether or not including it ''makes this a better written article''.  It doesn't, it makes it objectively worse by being a non-sequitur that doesn't directly impact the reader's understanding of the film or its context or impact in the world.  Including it adds nothing to the understanding of the topic, and removing it reduces nothing.  That's the very definition of trivia.  --[[User:Jayron32|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#009&quot;&gt;Jayron&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Jayron32|&lt;b style=&quot;color:#090&quot;&gt;''32''&lt;/b&gt;]] 14:01, 31 May 2016 (UTC)
::{{ping|Jayron32}} There are lots of things in the article that don't directly inform about the movie, but are included because they are often discussed by the media in relation to it. I don't think the article would be damaged by removal of the information, I just felt your basis for removing it was slightly flawed and we are only talking about a single sentence at the end of the day. Honestly, it's not a huge deal for me, but can we just leave this discussion open for a week? If no-one else objects to its removal (an dthe article has plenty of watchers) then I will withdraw my objection. [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 18:24, 31 May 2016 (UTC)
:::I see nothing inappropriate about this item. It answers one of the most often asked questions about the film, is simply stated, and cites a source. Cheers [[User:Markhh|Markhh]] ([[User talk:Markhh|talk]]) 22:20, 31 May 2016 (UTC)
::::I concur with Markhh. It's not irrelevant given the film's importance and the fact so many are interested in that information. [[User:Coinmanj|Coinmanj]] ([[User talk:Coinmanj|talk]]) 05:33, 9 July 2016 (UTC)

== Ray Rennahan ==

An editor is [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gone_with_the_Wind_(film)&amp;oldid=prev&amp;diff=724353159 repeatedly adding Ray Rennahan] to the infobox on the basis he jointly won an Academy Award with Ernest Haller. It is in fact [[WP:Original research]] to draw conclusions on the basis of awards he won. Yes, Rennahan jointly won the cinematography oscar but for his role as the ''Technicolor consultant''. It was not uncommon at the time for the Technicolor consultant to be jointly awarded the color cinematography oscar, but advising on the color process does not make you the photographer of the film. According to [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0031381/fullcredits IMDB] Haller was the cinematographer (it also lists Lee Garmes who was fired a month into shooting) and it lists Rennahan as the &quot;technicolor associate&quot;. This is also backed up by the [http://www.afi.com/members/catalog/DetailView.aspx?s=&amp;Movie=1181 American Film Institute] who also credit Rennahan has the &quot;technicolor associate&quot;. Unsurprisingly, &quot;technicolor associate&quot; is also the credit formally assigned to him in the actual credits as can be seen at [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pL2yPFxBQQ4#t=1m40s Youtube] (1 min 40 seconds in).

Rennahan's formal role was as a consultant on the colorization process. He did not photograph the film and both the film credits and secondary sources are specific about his role: he shared the cinematography oscar for his role in the colorization process as was common at the time because it was a new technology, but he did not photograph the film which is what the &quot;cinematography&quot; field is for. [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 18:27, 8 June 2016 (UTC)

== Question about the ranks of the top 10  ==

I think the ranks of the top 10  grossing film are incorrect and many are too small. Currently Gone with the Wind is at no 1, with 3.4 billion and Jaws is no 9 with 2.04 billion roughly.

Ticket prices in 1981, for adults were £1:95 and children £1.  In 1960, adult ticket prices were between 25 to 50p and in 1940, they were about 18p for adults tickets.

The 1981 prices, mean that  ticket prioes for adults tickets have rises over 5 times, to the current price of £10:75.
Given this, when ET is adjusted for inflation, its 700 million initial run gross, becomes 3.5 billion.  Jaws becomes about 2.7 billion, if tickets in 1975 to 1978 period were about £1:50. Gone with the Wind, made £32 million in it's first year I believe,  and adjusting that for inflation, gives 1.9 billion. Gone with the Wind did get released several times over the following 4 decades as well.  Star Wars 1977, when adjusted for inflation, if ticket prices in 1977 to 1980, were about £1:80, it comes to about 3.3 billion. I think it is possible, that ET when one adjusted for inflation, may have made more than Gone with the Wind.

Perhaps someone could look at this, and make corrections appropriately.

Sincerely

Mr FW Hooton, Film director &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/89.241.235.104|89.241.235.104]] ([[User talk:89.241.235.104|talk]]) 19:35, 1 August 2016‎ (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Xsign --&gt;

: &lt;small&gt;This doesn't appear to relate directly to this article, but, out of an abundance of caution and to spare a new editor needless frustration, I have refactored this comment from the article, where it was inappropriately added. &lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:bold&quot;&gt;[[User:Rebbing|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#f660ab;color:#60f6f6&quot;&gt;Rebb&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_talk:Rebbing|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#60f6f6;color:#f660ab&quot;&gt;ing&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 20:15, 1 August 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:There is quite a lot wrong with the above calculations:
#Gone with the Wind didn't gross £32 million in its first year, it grossed $32 million of ''rentals'' (which is the fee paid to MGM and was the metric in use at the time) across its entire initial release, which lasted until 1942. The gross will have been around $70 million, going by the rental ratios of the time.
#As the article points out GWTW had a roadshow and the tickets initially cost about $1. Adjusting for ticket price inflation makes no sense because that is like saying tickets would cost $20 today, which they don't because they no longer have roadshows. If you are talking worldwide grosses then using British(?) ticket prices is highly questionable anyway because tickets don't cost the same around the world. Something like US dollar inflation would be more appropriate, since that is the monetary unit used by the article.
#If you adjust for inflation you have to account for re-releases: GWTW had many reissues down the years (the dates are in the article) so to adjust for inflation you have to adjust the gross from each year using an appropriate index. The same for Star Wars and ET.
:The flawed calculations above illustrate why Wikipedia does not permit [[WP:Original research]]. I have seen several attempts at ranking films adjusted for inflation, and while they often come up with different numbers (illustrating the inherent difficulty of the task) they all have one thing in common: Gone with the Wind comes out on top. It is so far ahead of other films that there isn't really much of a debate about it. [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 21:00, 1 August 2016 (UTC)

== Servants/Slaves ==

{{u|EditTruth}} [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gone_with_the_Wind_%28film%29&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=740061846&amp;oldid=738892008 changed &quot;servants&quot; to &quot;slaves&quot;] in the plot summary. I appreciate the logic behind the change, but question whether this is a correct description. They were clearly slaves at the beginning of the film, but by this point I was under the impression that the remaining &quot;slaves&quot; chose to stay of their own free will. If they have been freed by this point is it still correct to refer to them as slaves? [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 23:18, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
*That's a fine point that the movie doesn't really clarify. The Emancipation Proclamation had already been made, but the war wasn't quite over so technically they were still living in the Confederacy that considered them slaves. But the Confederacy was never recognized as a legitimate government. By this point in the story it is clear that their continued presence at Tara was voluntary, not that they had many other options. How about calling them &quot;former slaves&quot;? [[User:Markhh|Markhh]] ([[User talk:Markhh|talk]]) 03:45, 19 September 2016 (UTC)
::I think that would probably read better in the context of the story at that point. If EditTruth doesn't chip in today I will initiate the change tomorrow. [[User:Betty Logan|Betty Logan]] ([[User talk:Betty Logan|talk]]) 08:40, 19 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7xilgxvio3jrvaz4ucbt3xtgzbzdoee</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
