<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Operation Barbarossa</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>22711</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751190589</id>
      <parentid>751190466</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T23:14:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Obenritter</username>
        <id>18162346</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Failure to aim directly for Moscow a strategic mistake? */ must be tired ...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16883">{{Talk header}}
{{article history
|action1=WAR
|action1date=7 September 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Operation Barbarossa/archive1
|action1result=not approved
|action1oldid=74261765

|action2=GAN
|action2date=18:15, 16 May 2015 (UTC)
|action2link=Talk:Operation Barbarossa/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=662629652

|action3=WAR
|action3date=02:06, 26 July 2015 (UTC)
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Operation Barbarossa
|action3result=not approved
|action3oldid=673051331

|currentstatus=GA
|otddate=2004-06-22
|otdoldid=4235214
|otd2date=2005-06-22
|otd2oldid=15658215
|otd3date=2006-06-22
|otd3oldid=59943225
|otd4date=2008-06-22
|otd4oldid=220943587
|otd5date=2009-06-22
|otd5oldid=298016058
|topic=Warfare
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=High|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA|A-Class=fail|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|German=y|Italian=y|Russian=y|WWII=y|Romanian=y}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=GA|importance=Top|hist=yes}}
{{WikiProject Ukraine|class=GA|importance=high}}
}}

{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav|noredlinks=y}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 6
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Operation Barbarossa/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archives |bot=Lowercase sigmabot III‎ |age=90 |small=yes|search=yes }}

[[Category:GA-Class Nazi Germany articles]]
== Three Soviet Directives from 22 June 1941: ==

I tried to put this into the article, however my edition was deleted:

== Wrong name ==

Barbarossa was the name for the attack on Soviet positions in eastern Poland, not the invasion of the Soviet Union. ([[User:JacobDewer|JacobDewer]] ([[User talk:JacobDewer|talk]]) 13:22, 4 September 2016 (UTC))

== Army Group Center course in the initial stages ==

From Guderian's memoir (Guderian, Heinz (tr. Constantine Fitzgibbon). ''Panzer Leader''. Da Capo Press (2nd ed.; 2002), ISBN: 978-0-306-81101-2 p.146), after Smolensk, it seems he was almost sent North!:

&quot;Preliminary orders as issued by the ''OKH'' indicated that the plan was then probably to switch Hoth's 3rd and my 2nd Panzer Groups due north to capture Leningrad.&quot; [[User:Renassault|Cornelius]] ([[User talk:Renassault|talk]]) 22:33, 22 September 2016 (UTC)

== Recent edit: Black Sea Operations  ==

I reverted this additions as I believe there's a strong likelyhood that they were done by an IP address belonging to Romanian-and-proud, who has been topic banned from this area. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 16:05, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:I apologize, I did not know that. Although, if he would be true to his/her name, I doubt he/she would have included the Germans. I simply wanted to add the naval front of the Operation. [[Special:Contributions/86.123.123.192|86.123.123.192]] ([[User talk:86.123.123.192|talk]]) 16:20, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
::Then I would recommend registering for an account so that the edits can be done under a user name. Please see this extensive ANI thread re: the disruptions caused by IP editors in the same topic area: [[Wikipedia:Administrators%27_noticeboard/IncidentArchive929#Disruptive_IP_editor|Disruptive IP editor]]. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 16:32, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:::I honestly was reluctant to, because I already have plenty of accounts that I have to memorize passwords for, and in some cases the username. I will think about it.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.123.123.192|86.123.123.192]] ([[User talk:86.123.123.192#top|talk]]) 16:34, 14 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::::Yes, that would be best as some of the earlier tagged addresses are close to your range: 86.123.121.21 &amp; 86.123.123.74, for example. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 16:37, 14 October 2016 (UTC)

== Phase two ==

The section &quot;Phase two&quot; relies far too much on TV documentaries and needs to be carefully edited with scholarly texts. There are some discrepancies with some of the dates and units mentioned when contrasted against sources. Since I do not have many of the detailed works from Glantz (probably the foremost expert on Barbarossa), somebody who does should clear out these TV references with better citations. The same applies to parts of &quot;Phase four&quot;.--[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 02:45, 6 November 2016 (UTC)

:I cleaned up Phase 1 a while back, but I haven't had the chance to proceed to the others, as I've been prepping Battle of Prokhorovka for FA. But I'll get around to them eventually. In the meantime, it would be lovely if others can start chipping away at it. I have a number of Glantz' works, and I'll be glad to provide numbers or specific details if requested. [[User:EyeTruth|EyeTruth]] ([[User talk:EyeTruth|talk]]) 02:59, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
::No worries mate -- just thought it worth mentioning since this article gets so many hits given the topic. I've tried to clean up a bit myself as well and will continue to do so when the time permits.--[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 03:48, 6 November 2016 (UTC)

== Failure to aim directly for Moscow a strategic mistake? ==

This is what German generals believed both during and after the war, but do historians generally agree? Alan Clark seems not to (but his book is quite old), nor does Bevin Alexander IIRC. Also the comment that Hitler was more interested in destroying the Red Army than in specific territorial gains seems off. I believe that was standard German army doctrine, whereas Hitler was more interested in economic objectives. [[User:Mmeijeri|Martijn Meijering]] ([[User talk:Mmeijeri|talk]]) 10:26, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
: Many military historians agree that it was a strategic error to delay the attack on Moscow.--[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 23:28, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
::Really? I was not getting this impression from various sources. If the Wehrmacht pushed onto Moscow, they would have an undefeated South Western Front on their flank / rear. Moscow was being fortified since July and it's not a certainty that the German forces could have taken it, or effectively encircled it. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 23:38, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
:::This fact does not suggest they would have won the war as a result, it was simply a strategic mistake because it gave Stalin time to refortify. Hitler made a fatal error by delaying the drive towards Moscow by diverting needed Panzers to the southern front towards Kiev, which was stalled. What many people fail to realize is that Moscow was THE railway transportation hub of the entire Russian rail system. If the German generals had been allowed to press for Moscow sooner, they could have cut off the city and its rail connections which would have severely hampered the Russians ability to move materials and caused serious logistical problems. Glantz argues of course (like you contend), that had the Russians troops not been occupied at Kiev, this may have changed the situation as well on the German south-western flank. Still, the Russian forces and equipment were qualitatively inferior at this stage, so the Germans very well could have taken Moscow otherwise (siding with German historians here since the facts speak for themselves -- the German forces captured over 665,000 troops near the Kiev cauldron). What makes you think these forces (who were categorically defeated) would have repulsed a more concentrated assault? Anyway, it is all opinion at this point but many agree that while it was likely a strategic mistake to delay the attack on Moscow by redirecting forces, the overall outcome remains the same. Logistical obstacles kept the German under-supplied, they would have still been dealing with severe weather for which they were not equipped and had Moscow been taken, the Russians would have just retreated deeper inland and attacked from the South and East. The Germans could not match the Soviet industrial capacity nor could they overcome the supply stretch deep into the Soviet interior. What we end up with in the end is a prolonged war and not some counterfactual reality where the Nazis outright defeat the Soviets. --[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 01:45, 17 November 2016 (UTC)
::::Do you have a citation that shows most military historians believe it was a strategic mistake? If not, then we should present the various opinions instead. As an aside, I believe Heinrici wrote after the war that an immediate drive on Moscow was the only chance Germany had, but it would have been much more of a gamble than the generals had realised at the time. [[User:Mmeijeri|Martijn Meijering]] ([[User talk:Mmeijeri|talk]]) 16:23, 17 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::Of course we should present the various opinions. Having read hundreds of books on the Third Reich, a considerable number in German - my understanding and recollection is that many historians view the delay on Moscow as a strategic error. Heinrici's comment even supports that notion to a degree; when he asserts &quot;an immediate drive on Moscow was the only chance Germany had&quot; but they failed to do it -- doesn't that constitute a strategic error? By the way, Stalin even later claimed that he sacrificed three-quarters of a million men on the southwest front with the intention to delay the German assault on Moscow. That supports the historians who see the delay as a pretty significant error. Anyway - perhaps &quot;most&quot; historians is too strong; ''many'' would be more appropriate. Many disagree as well. As you'll note from my commentary above, that did not change the fact that the Russians would have regrouped anyway and Germany was doomed. This is especially the case when Germany declared war on America just a few months later. Nonetheless, the mistake at Moscow notwithstanding, the greatest error made by the Germans was their failure to co-opt the assistance of the Ukrainians and other peoples who were otherwise disillusioned with the Soviet system under Stalin.--[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 18:18, 17 November 2016 (UTC)
:: Much of what the German generals wrote post-1945 was of the &quot;blame Hitler&quot; school of thought. Very convenient for them to blame the hated dead guy, who could not of course respond. That doesn't mean that everything they wrote was nonsense, it's simply a word of caution. 
:: The Soviet economy was quite a bit smaller than the German, so it is not correct to say the &quot;Germans could not match the Soviet industrial capacity&quot;; actually it was the other way round. But the Soviets' military/industrial system management was much better at converting raw materials and labor into combat power than the Germans were. 
:: Regards, [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 17:27, 17 November 2016 (UTC)
:::I'm in the process of checking the books I have on this subject. Mercatante argues that the correct course of action would have been to focus on Leningrad, Ukraine and the Caucasus, just as Hitler had wanted from the beginning. I don't know how serious a scholar Mercatante is however. [[User:Mmeijeri|Martijn Meijering]] ([[User talk:Mmeijeri|talk]]) 20:55, 17 November 2016 (UTC)
::::No need to beat this horse much longer Martijm. A very strong case on how the Germans &quot;could have won&quot; is made by Russell H. S. Stolfi (1992) ''Hitler's Panzers East: World War II Reinterpreted''. Nonetheless, I read plenty of earlier studies which were likely tainted by the German general's view (Liddel-Hart comes to mind) of the situation, pro-German authors writing about their own countrymen in the sixties and seventies, and of course, the whole era of the Invincible Wehrmacht which tainted what would have been otherwise objective studies. More and more modern scholars are shedding doubt on the soundness and feasibility of the attack on Moscow. Robert Citino makes a great case that the efforts around Kiev were remarkable and a stunning success, which in his opinion validated the approach Hitler took. Still - I am not entirely sold that they could not have captured Moscow - the question for me is &quot;at what cost and to what end?&quot; given their supply and weather problems. I'd rather see scholarly editors like yourself improving the article (like replacing all the TV documentary citations) in lieu of debating &quot;what ifs.&quot;[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 00:34, 18 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::Just to keep notice: the IHR is a negationist institution and any paper that gives even 0.1% credibility to the pre-emptive strike hypothesis should be take as serious as one claiming the Moon is made of cheese. [[User:Bertdrunk|Bertdrunk]] ([[User talk:Bertdrunk|talk]]) 01:51, 19 November 2016 (UTC)

:::::: Indeed. [[User:DMorpheus2|DMorpheus2]] ([[User talk:DMorpheus2|talk]]) 01:19, 20 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::::{{ping|Bertdrunk}} -- great point, I should have made that disclaimer immediately so thanks for that. I just stumbled across this and found its content worth mentioning since we were debating &quot;what ifs&quot;. Nonetheless -- given the often controversial nature and offensive content the journal publishes -- I have removed that link accordingly.--[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 04:40, 20 November 2016 (UTC)
:::: Twenty years ago (and earlier) this issue would be a completely worthy point. But thanks to the opening of Soviet archives in the 1990s, and the info they held subsequently making their way into English military history literature over the past 10–15 years, the assessment above becomes problematic. There are several piece of information that undermines the entire notion that an attack on Moscow in July/August would have produced a different outcome. The Germans may have captured Moscow, but they would be just as exhausted as they were in the real battle, and they will have to winter in a ruined city and still be forced to face fresh reserves from Siberia. Historians who have wider access to Soviet archives (and conversant with the language), like Glantz, over the past decade have hammered the untenability of the argument (that the diversion to Kiev was the cause of failure) from almost every angle imaginable. [[User:EyeTruth|EyeTruth]] ([[User talk:EyeTruth|talk]]) 01:57, 22 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::And {{ping|EyeTruth}} drops the mic !--[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 01:37, 23 November 2016 (UTC)
::::::I share EyeTruth's understanding here. Glantz and the other major recent authors on this topic tend to argue that the Axis forces simply weren't capable of achieving the goals of Barbarossa in light of the capabilities of the Soviet Union, and there wasn't an alternate set of German decisions which could have delivered victory. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 02:18, 23 November 2016 (UTC)

After rereading some of the books I have on the subject, I get the impression that there is less debate on the merits of an attack on Moscow than I thought. The discussion appears to be more about whether Hitler's diversion was the cause of Germany's defeat, which is not the same thing. It's possible to believe the diversion was a mistake, but that Germany would still have lost the war even if they had aimed straight for Moscow. This appears to be what Glantz believes. I'll keep reading and see if I can find a summary of the debate somewhere. [[User:Mmeijeri|Martijn Meijering]] ([[User talk:Mmeijeri|talk]]) 09:11, 23 November 2016 (UTC)
:: Thanks for that input {{ping|Mmeijeri}}. That's been my stance for a long time even though I must confess as a student of history, older than many of you perhaps, my traditional education about this battle was tainted by the German (''and British'' I might add) authors of many years ago. It's always interesting to see progress and deeper comprehension of historical events thanks to enduring research. Ideology and its philosophical influence on history was my focus area so I was not surprised when the Wehrmacht exhibit first appeared in Germany (which wiped away its &quot;clean&quot; myth), with its now permanent, ''Verbrechen der Wehrmacht. Dimensionen des Vernichtungskrieges 1941–1944'' (Crimes of the German Wehrmacht: Dimensions of a War of Annihilation 1941-1944) manifestation in Berlin. Much of their worst was perpetrated during the course of Barbarossa as we all know now. Nonetheless, I appreciate the respectful debate and research that many of you have put into this article.--[[User:Obenritter|Obenritter]] ([[User talk:Obenritter|talk]]) 23:10, 23 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>29uabg77lp78il7joclmqadcpncyme5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
