<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Kowloon Walled City</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>269207</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750898511</id>
      <parentid>731374316</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T03:21:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>120.199.57.178</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision by [[Special:Contributions/68.45.174.58|68.45.174.58]] - block evasion by HeinrichMueller</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24533">{{GA|01:36, 7 April 2014 (UTC)|topic=Places|page=1|oldid=603087041}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject China|class=GA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Hong Kong|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Urban studies and planning|class=GA|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA|Chinese=yes|Fortifications=yes}}
}}
{{Press
 | subject     = Kowloon Walled City
 | author      = Amy O'Leary
 | title       = Everybody Inhale: How Many People Can Manhattan Hold?
 | org         = New York Times
 | url         = http://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/04/realestate/how-many-people-can-manhattan-hold.html?pagewanted=1&amp;hp
 | date        = 2012-03-01
 | quote       = &quot;An iPhone was produced. A Wikipedia entry was summoned. A photo was passed around the table. Gasps. Profanity.&quot;
 | archiveurl  = 
 | archivedate = 
 | accessdate  = 2012-03-04
}}

== Validating Information ==

&quot;Also, as the Walled City was beginning to be torn down, a group of Japanese explorers took about a week to tour the empty walled city, making a sort of map and a cross section of the city&quot;

Interesting bit of information with no online source to validate or confirm. Would someone mind posting a link to this reference? This statement just hangs there... Not saying to remove it, just support it.

:Accidently found it http://web.archive.org/web/20020208225753/www.flex.co.jp/kowloon/story/index_e.html Now would someone mind adding the citation?
----

I agree with the first comment.  Referring to this as &quot;Kowloon&quot; for the article is a bad idea... why not Walled City?

:The first comment is here in the hope that a knowlegeable person will make the relevant changes in the article. [[User:Olivier|olivier]] 13:47 16 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:OK, tried my first attempt to consolidate everything.  Did it traditional inverted pyramid style -- try to give big picture first and go more specific. Feel free to clean up and clarify.  ([[User:Fuzheado|Fuzheado]])

This is a new comment and I'm not totally sure that this is the correct way to do this but oh well.  The walled city was documented before it was torn down.  A book was published entitled &quot;City of Darkness, Life in Kowloon Walled City.&quot;  It's available on Amazon.com and it runs around $85.  It's expensive, but if you're interested in urban culture and architecture it's fascinating.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.21.97.102|24.21.97.102]] ([[User talk:24.21.97.102|talk]]) 03:53, 7 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Depictions in Popular Culture==

I'm gonna get a screenshot of this as soon as I find the episode of where it's at, but if anyone can help me out on this - In Ghost In the Shell : SAC 2nd GiG, when Hideo Kuze talks about his revolution and a new society, there is a scene which is basically identical to this one &gt;&gt;&gt; http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image:KowloonWalledCityAlley2.jpg

In fact, I think that the whole refuge district concept is very similar to this. [[User:Rokasomee|Rokasomee]] 08:19, 10 March 2007 (UTC)

:got it. http://www.fileden.com/files/10493/combo1.png &gt;&gt;&gt; a screenshot of the refugee district [[User:Rokasomee|Rokasomee]] 10:09, 22 March 2007 (UTC)

Yes...the Japanese Wikipedia article on this topic does mention that Ghost in the Shell drew inspirations from this place, maybe that's why. [[User:Deadkid dk|_dk]] 10:26, 22 March 2007 (UTC)

I think a mention of Long Arm of the Law and its sequel deserves mention.  It used the locale memorably in both films climactic action sequences.

== Questionable copyvio? ==
I swear i've read the text somewhere... and it's not on wikipedia. What caught my attention is the style. 

:''... With the Triads' power diminished, '''a strange sort of synergy blossomed''', and the Walled City began to grow almost organically, the square buildings folding up into one another as thousands of modifications were made, virtually none by architects, until hundreds of square metres were simply a kind of '''patchwork monolith'''. Labyrinthine corridors ran through the '''monolith''', some of those being former streets (at the ground level, and often clogged up with trash), and some of those running through upper floors, practically between buildings. The only rules of construction were twofold: electricity had to be provided to avoid fire, and the buildings could be no more than about fourteen stories high (because of the nearby airport). A mere eight municipal pipes '''somehow''' provided water to the entire structure (although more could have come from wells). By the early 1980s, Kowloon Walled City had an estimated population of 35,000 - with a crime rate far below the Hong Kong average, despite the notable lack of any real law enforcement.''

:''Over time, both the British and Chinese governments found this massive, anarchic city to be '''a bit too much''' - despite the low crime, for if the 'Black Market' ever had a physical location, this would have been it, and '''needless to say''', the sanitary conditions '''were, well, a bit wanting'''.''

Here I've highlighted some perculiar use of description and structures that are not very scientific and encyclopedic. POV? I will fix up some of the punctuation in the meantime. --[[User:Kvasir|Kvasir]] 23:04, 25 Apr 2005 (UTC)
::I have placed a copyright violation tag. Some sections appeared to be lifted word for word from this paper.[http://www.vinokurov.info/downloads/theoryofenclavescomplete.pdf] See page 131. --[[User:Kvasir|Kvasir]] ([[User talk:Kvasir|talk]]) 22:16, 3 April 2008 (UTC)

:::I'm pretty sure that this site copied from Wikipedia, not the other way around. This paper is dated 2005, while large parts of the article already existed in 2004. See [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kowloon_Walled_City&amp;diff=203151324&amp;oldid=9656159]. I don't think that this is a copyvio. [[User:Andrew_pmk|Andrew_pmk]] | [[User talk:Andrew pmk|Talk]] 04:20, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

::::Is this settled?  I'm going to remove the tag for now, it's really distracting and it doesn't seem like there's any evidence that this article is a copyvio.  Putting that tag on an article without specifying what source it's copied from is really bad form.[[User:P4k|P4k]] ([[User talk:P4k|talk]]) 04:29, 5 April 2008 (UTC)

== Shenmue 2 ==

Is this the same city as Ryo visits in [[Shenmue II|Shenmue 2]], called Kowloon? If it is, maybe information on differences btw Kowloon in the game vs Kowloon in real life could be added? --[[User:Konstantin|Konstantin]] 12:23, 19 Jun 2005 (UTC)
: I just read this article and the similarity occured to me. This might go under a &quot;trivia&quot; section. [[User:Shawnc|Shawnc]] 03:40, 5 June 2006 (UTC)

:The city in Shenmue 2 is most definitely the Kowloon Walled City. --[[User:Golbez|Golbez]] 03:45, 5 June 2006 (UTC)

== neutral POV? ==

I think this paragraph is a bit biased:
_____________________________
Evacuation and demolition
 
Kowloon Walled City before its demolition.

Over time, both the British and the Chinese governments found this massive, anarchic city to be a bit too much - despite the low reported crime. If the 'Black Market' ever had a physical location, this would have been it. Needless to say, the sanitary conditions were a bit wanting.
_________________
Can someone change it without losing the general message?

== Picture ==

I changed the picture to the normal non-edited version. It's clearer to see the city like that; not sure why there is a blurred one that doesn't look like as it does in the caption. If you get what I mean. [[User:Seriphyn|Seriphyn]] 12:13, 9 April 2007 (UTC)
==Fair use rationale for Image:KowloonWalledCityplane.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:KowloonWalledCityplane.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:KowloonWalledCityplane.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is other other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 05:24, 5 June 2007 (UTC)
==Fair use rationale for Image:KowloonWalledCityAlley2.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:KowloonWalledCityAlley2.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:KowloonWalledCityAlley2.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is other other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 05:24, 5 June 2007 (UTC)

==Exclave vs. enclave==
The intro previously called Kowloon an exclave, but it also said it is located &quot;in the middle&quot; of Hong Kong. I'm pretty sure it can't be both. An exclave, by definition, must not be entirely contained within the larger state. If it's completely surrounded by one state (such as Hong Kong) then it is an enclave. [[List of enclaves and exclaves]] has it as an enclave, and assuming the &quot;in the middle of Hong Kong&quot; part is true, I believe that's the correct classification. [[User:Kafziel|Kafziel]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Kafziel|Complaint Department]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:19, 18 July 2008 (UTC)

==Needs better description==
This article needs a better quantitative description of the city, i.e. location, size, dimensions, etc.  It's written in a sort of anecdotal fashion. -[[Special:Contributions/67.67.15.123|67.67.15.123]] ([[User talk:67.67.15.123|talk]]) 01:36, 19 October 2008 (UTC)

==Another &quot;walled&quot; city==
We might consider adding [[Shibam]] city to the See also section. It looks like &quot;walled&quot; too and has the &quot;stuffed&quot; appearance as well.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mountleek|Mountleek]] ([[User talk:Mountleek|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mountleek|contribs]]) 23:22, 9 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Under construction... ==

Just posting here as a heads up that I'm currently doing a fair amount of work on this article. At the moment ''City of Darkness'' is listed just as a general reference, so I'm not sure what statements use it as their source. I will be reading through that book and adding inline citations where applicable. I am also compiling some possible quotes that could be used in the article. If anyone can provide additional good images, or reliable sources for unsourced statements in the article, that would be very helpful. —'''&lt;font color=&quot;#0010A0&quot;&gt;[[User:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#003FFF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#308EFF&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 03:21, 21 October 2009 (UTC)

:Having looked over various population estimates, I've seen a few sources claim that 50,000 people lived in KWC at one point. However, given that (according to ''City of Darkness'') the population was about 10,000 in 1971 and about 33,000 in 1987 based on government surveys, this seems doubtful. It may well be that people took the highest estimate that anyone had come up with and ran with it. If anyone can provide a solid, reliable source for the claim, though, I'd be quite happy to be proven wrong. —'''&lt;font color=&quot;#0010A0&quot;&gt;[[User:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#003FFF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#308EFF&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 21:57, 23 October 2009 (UTC)

:I am also removing (after searching for sources) examples in the &quot;Cultural depictions&quot; section that do not explicitly reference KWC. A &quot;Walled City&quot; is a generic term that could mean any city with walls, and &quot;Kowloon&quot; is the general area in which KWC is located. Neither term on its own can be definitively said to be referencing KWC. Of course, if a reliable source can be found for anything I've removed, please do add it back. —'''&lt;font color=&quot;#0010A0&quot;&gt;[[User:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#003FFF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#308EFF&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 22:37, 24 October 2009 (UTC)

:I've removed two of the images that are copies of the photos in ''City of Darkness'', and put them up for deletion on Commons. It's really unfortunate (aereakowloon.jpg in particular was amazing), but copyright violations do need to be dealt with. I replaced them with another image and a quote from ''City of Darkness'' that gives a wonderfully vivid description of life in KWC circa the 1970s. —'''&lt;font color=&quot;#0010A0&quot;&gt;[[User:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#003FFF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#308EFF&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 03:04, 6 November 2009 (UTC)


==Interestingly enough==
Doing [[WP:original research|informal calculations]], I found population densities of cruise ships such as the Carnival Triumph, etc., to be something like 1200/acre (although such densities could well be more)(note: the unusual footprint of a ship makes it hard to calculate density per square foot of &quot;land&quot;, given the bulletlike floorplan of a ship's hull and varying floorplan of its superstructure.) Kowloon Walled City clocked in at over 5000 people/acre, which is a lot. The population density of a Boeing 737-300 approaches that of KWC (4 964.93649 people/acre), but that population is all on the same floor on an airplane, whereas multistory buildings made up KWC. [[Special:Contributions/192.12.88.7|192.12.88.7]] ([[User talk:192.12.88.7|talk]]) 07:46, 3 April 2010 (UTC)

:Going with the population of 33,000 and the area of .01 sq mi, the desity would be 3,300,000 per sq mi. [[User:Daniel Christensen|Daniel Christensen]] ([[User talk:Daniel Christensen|talk]]) 12:34, 23 November 2011 (UTC)

== &quot;Hak Nam&quot; ==

Kowloon Walled City was also widely known as &quot;Hak Nam&quot;, Cantonese for &quot;City of Darkness&quot;, I am told.  Could someone add this to the article?  ''I'' would, but I don't know where would be best, nor what hanzi should accompany the term.

(And ideally a Hongkong-ese person could please add whether Hak Nam was a matter-of-fact name, or something deeply disparaging?  I think you'd have to be from around there to know.) [[User:Sburke|Sean M. Burke]] ([[User talk:Sburke|talk]]) 13:35, 23 August 2010 (UTC)

== In the Hitman series ==

Though the article mentions it is used as the setting for certain missions from the Hitman video-game series, it is not actually the case. No mission from the game takes place within the Walled City itself. The larger city of Kowloon is used however. I may be wrong on this but I remember the series well and cannot recall any overt reference or depiction of the Walled City. 
[[Special:Contributions/70.180.248.94|70.180.248.94]] ([[User talk:70.180.248.94|talk]]) 03:45, 18 December 2010 (UTC)

== Location, location, location! ==

Overlaying the 1915 map on Google Earth imagery puts the &quot;Chinese Town&quot; shown in that map about half mile SE (22.3283 N, 114.19454 E) of the location given in the article (22.33228 N, 114.18866 E) and in what later became part of the airport.  The possibilities are: (1) The map is distorted and wrong, (2) The &quot;Chinese Town&quot; shown in the map is not the walled city which would be outside the area of this map, (3) The location given by the article is wrong, (4) I have made a mistake somewhere. All seem unlikely but what is the explanation?  Other maps of the late 19th or early 20th century could shed some light. [[User:GS3|GS3]] ([[User talk:GS3|talk]]) 11:59, 30 August 2011 (UTC)
:The location you got from overlaying the map (22.3283 N, 114.19454 E) is roughly in the middle of the [[Lung Tsun Stone Bridge]], which was the pier used for accessing Kowloon City aka. the &quot;Chinese Town&quot;. You can see it very clearly with the satellite view of Google Maps, including the excavated remnants of the bridge. You can find additional old maps and a lot of information by browsing the references and external links of the [[Lung Tsun Stone Bridge]] article. It is very possible that the two different location data simply point to two opposite ends of the Kowloon City, which was fairly large.  [[User:Underwaterbuffalo|Underwaterbuffalo]] ([[User talk:Underwaterbuffalo|talk]]) 13:02, 30 August 2011 (UTC)
::After more investigation it seems clear that the four corners were roughly located at (22.33112, 114.18959), (22.33225, 114.18893), (22.33319, 114.19087), (22.33201, 114.19152) and so the center was at about (22.33214, 114.19023), where the remains of the yamen are still today. I have corrected the coordinates in the article accordingly even though the change is very small. Still, overlaying the 1915 map in Google Earth puts the city itself out where the airport end was. Not the bridge but the city itself. Not a big deal because the map might be slightly distorted and it might show as built city areas which were deemed to belong to the city but were open.[[User:GS3|GS3]] ([[User talk:GS3|talk]]) 16:17, 30 August 2011 (UTC)

how about a basic street map in the infobox or at least a note in the opening paragraph about WHERE it is relative to something in the modern world?!  rather than some dusty old 1915 map.  &quot;NT&quot; is pretty vague and most people don't really want to go off-page tracking this down.

was it indeed near Kai Tak?  their existences overlap so obviously comments above that Kai Tak took over the space cannot be correct.

what MRT station(s)?  all this talk of overlay maps -- please someone put it IN THE ARTICLE!  [[Special:Contributions/66.105.218.25|66.105.218.25]] ([[User talk:66.105.218.25|talk]]) 03:44, 24 December 2011 (UTC)
:Coordinates are given at the top of the page. You can click on them and view the location on Google Maps. Seems quite modern world to me. In case this is not enough, the article mentions &quot;The area where the Walled City once stood is now Kowloon Walled City Park&quot;, which in fact means that there is nothing really notable in the vicinity. So interested readers will better go off-page to figure out the location, I believe. [[User:Underwaterbuffalo|Underwaterbuffalo]] ([[User talk:Underwaterbuffalo|talk]]) 20:34, 27 December 2011 (UTC)

== Flat unit size ==

Thanks to {{u|MusikAnimal}} for nominating this as a GA, and {{u|LT910001}} for reviewing. There was some uncertainty about the meaning of the statistic &quot;Because apartments were so small — about 60% were {{convert|23|m2|ft2|abbr=on}}&quot; so it was taken out. Here's the original quote, which is talking about compensation for moving residents out pre-demolition:

:''&quot;The final formula tied compensation to bringing the cheapest HOS [Home Ownership Scheme] flat within reach of the owner-occupier. Based on a unit size of 23 square metres, the size of some 60 per cent of all flats in the City, owners in the first phases were to be given $320,000[.]&quot;''

It seems pretty clear to me from &quot;unit size&quot; that the author is saying those flats are exactly 23 m², rather than &quot;up to&quot; 23 m². I've re-added the statistic (and clarified the wording to say &quot;about 60% had a unit size of {{convert|23|m2|ft2|abbr=on}}&quot;), as I think it helps readers to better visualize just how small many of the flats were. If anyone takes issue with that interpretation, let me know. —'''&lt;font color=&quot;#0010A0&quot;&gt;[[User:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#003FFF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#308EFF&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 05:04, 7 April 2014 (UTC)
:{{ping|Tktktk}} Hi there. I found [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=o5wl61GSwu8C&amp;pg=PT30&amp;dq=City+of+Darkness:+Life+in+Kowloon+Walled+City&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=4TVCU5mpM8PN7Abo34EY&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=City%20of%20Darkness%3A%20Life%20in%20Kowloon%20Walled%20City&amp;f=false this], which suggests that the flats were &quot;approximately 23 m²&quot;, not exactly. Might be a useful ref to add as it's quite detailed. Best, [[User:Philg88|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#646464; font-weight:bold; font-size:11px; border:2px solid #FFCC33;background-color:#cde0fc; padding: 2px 10px;&quot;&gt;►&amp;nbsp;Philg88&amp;nbsp;◄&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;♦[[User_talk:Philg88|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:27, 7 April 2014 (UTC)
::Yep, no worries. &quot;Based off&quot; indicates that they took an average size. I would be extremely surprised based on the hodge-podge housing and notorious lack of law-and-order if the units all turned out to be exactly the same size. --[[User:LT910001|LT910001]] ([[User talk:LT910001|talk]]) 10:31, 7 April 2014 (UTC)
:::{{u|Philg88}}, unfortunately the paragraph you're referring to actually looks like it's describing the New Territories in general. {{u|LT910001}}, you may be right about them taking an average size. I've changed the article to say &quot;a typical unit was {{convert|23|m2|ft2|abbr=on}}&quot;, since that would be accurate in either case. —'''&lt;font color=&quot;#0010A0&quot;&gt;[[User:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#003FFF&quot;&gt;[[User talk:tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#308EFF&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Tktktk|tk]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 17:35, 7 April 2014 (UTC)
::::{{ping|Tktktk}} Indeed. Looks good. [[User:Philg88|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#646464; font-weight:bold; font-size:11px; border:2px solid #FFCC33;background-color:#cde0fc; padding: 2px 10px;&quot;&gt;►&amp;nbsp;Philg88&amp;nbsp;◄&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;♦[[User_talk:Philg88|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:45, 7 April 2014 (UTC)
:Nice! Should have pinged you before removing that, but glad we got it back in. Thanks :) &amp;mdash; [[User:MusikAnimal|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;MusikAnimal&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:MusikAnimal|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot; &gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;b&gt;talk&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 14:55, 7 April 2014 (UTC)

== Wall Street Journal project ==

There's some good information in this interactive webpage from WSJ http://projects.wsj.com/kwc/ including interviews with the residents, a virtual tour, newspaper clippings of the years before its destruction, and a discussion on its cultural legacy. I think some of the stuff from there can be added into this page; and if not, they're interesting nonetheless! [[User:Underbar dk|_dk]] ([[User talk:Underbar dk|talk]]) 10:03, 27 April 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rezin5dbixv8lemxs4wgea8erxxrtup</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
