<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Glenn T. Seaborg</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2886354</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717769559</id>
      <parentid>711610785</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-29T16:23:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot</username>
        <id>27446209</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>subst /Comments to [[WP:DCS|discontinue comments subpage]]) ([[Project:AWB|AWB]] [12009]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14695">{{GA|12:25, 25 July 2013 (UTC)|topic=Chemistry and materials science|page=1|oldid=565744180}}
{{Old peer review|archive=1}}
{{WikiProject banner shell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=GA
|military-work-group=yes
|military-priority=low
|s&amp;a-priority=High
|listas=Seaborg, Glenn
|s&amp;a-work-group=yes
}}
{{WikiProject University of California|UCB=yes|UCB-importance=|class=GA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Chemistry|class=GA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Physics|class=GA|importance=high|bio=yes}}
{{WikiProject History of Science|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Michigan|class=GA|importance=mid}}&lt;!--downstaters might not know, but he is BIG in the U.P.--&gt;
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y|Biography=y|SciTech=y|US=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject California|class=GA|sfba=yes|sfba-importance=high|importance=mid}}
}}
{{On this day|date1=2012-04-19|oldid1=487960123}}

==Untitled==
*'''This article has a [[Talk:Glenn T. Seaborg/Comments|Comments]] page which may be more properly placed on the talk page.'''

== Alpha Chi Sigma ==
I can confirm he was one of the founding members of the UCLA chapter of Alpha Chi Sigma, the professional chemistry fraternity. [[User:Restevens1|Restevens1]] 04:02, 20 May 2007 (UTC) restevens1

Seaborg also was chair of the fraternity's scholarship committee and served on its Educational Foundation Board of Directors.  He frequently attended the national meetings, preferring to bunk in the dormatory with the other members, rather than a hotel room of his own.  This lead to surprising introductions with collegiate members from universities from across the country, in the dorm restroom, standing there shaving early in the morning.  [[User:Restevens1|Restevens1]] 04:22, 20 May 2007 (UTC)restevens1

== Seaborg Medal ==

UCLA's Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry awards the [http://www.chem.ucla.edu/dept/alumni/Seaborg/medal.html Seaborg Medal] for achievement in chemistry and biochemistry.   --[[User:205.175.225.5|205.175.225.5]] 17:58, 13 October 2005 (UTC)

== Plutonium preceded the Manhattan Project ==

While it is commonly assumed that plutonium was discovered during the Manhattan project, it was actually created by Seaborg and his associates on February 23, 1941 at 307 Gilman Hall, University of California, Berkley. The Manhattan Project did not begin until 1942.

Seaborg and his colleagues were quite disappointed and upset that pre-war secrecy prevented them from publishing their discoveries in scientific journals. They did send notices to both the Uranium Committee and the editors of Physical Review with a reluctant request that publication be withheld.

== Books Section (help needed) ==

Seaborg wrote 50+ books. Please help complete this section if you can. [[User:Glenn4pr|Glenn4pr]] 08:53, 11 July 2006 (UTC)

== Cleanup: Legacy section ==

I put a cleanup tag there because that section, a list of &quot;principal accomplishments&quot; seems like promotional material that is not ordinarily present in encyclopedic biographies. I really don't see the need for this list, as everything in it has already been mentioned in the article. The scope of the list should be better defined, or the list itself should be deleted.--[[User:Jiang|Jiang]] 07:38, 10 September 2006 (UTC)

:As you know, a biography of this sort is complicated by the sheer mass and range of the individual's accomplishments. In these cases, a summarizing section is in order to help crystallize the subject's principal accomplishments. For WP parallels, see the &quot;Honors&quot; section in the Einstein article. The &quot;Legacy&quot; section in the article on Isaac Newton, FDR and Mao. I suppose it becomes subjective to determine which biographies require these kind of summarizing sections regarding legacy. In Seaborg's case, however, he was listed in the Guiness Book of World's Records as having the longest entry in Marquis' Who's Who, which sort of justifies the need for a summary. Someone nominated this as one of the more important biographies, so that may be taken as another objective justification for a legacy section. Anyway, I'll try removing the bullet points and focusing on the legacy implications, when I get a chance. [[User:Glenn4pr|Glenn4pr]] 15:20, 11 September 2006 (UTC)

The summary of the article resides in its lead section; it is not necessary to summarize again. The &quot;honors&quot; section of the Einstein article lists awards (i.e. honors) given to Einstein over the years, ''after his death''. The &quot;legacy&quot; section of the Newton article lists discoveries that were later expanded and molded. This is precisely what the word &quot;legacy&quot; means: things handed down from the past. &quot;Legacy&quot; does not mean &quot;principal accomplishments&quot; or &quot;summary of one's biography&quot;. Element 106 is part of Seaborg's legacy; that he won the Nobel Prize or was given the title of University Professor is not. We don't need to repeat that he won the Nobel Prize since this fact is already visible in the lead section. --[[User:Jiang|Jiang]] 23:47, 17 September 2006 (UTC)
::Jiang, since you have already given this some thought, I suggest that you go through this section and remove those items you object to. If they are already in the article, they should not be reinstated, and I would support you on that. Sincerely, [[User:GeorgeLouis|GeorgeLouis]] 19:23, 15 October 2006 (UTC)

== His alma mater ==

The infobox now gives him two alma maters. This is not possible. UCLA is his only alma mater (the school he graduated from). UC Berkeley is not his alma mater. I would change this but I don't know how to work infoboxes and can't find any help article about them. Sincerely, [[User:GeorgeLouis|GeorgeLouis]] 05:32, 1 October 2006 (UTC)
:Seaborg received his bachelor's at UCLA and his doctorate at UC Berkeley. Since the definition of &quot;Alma Mater&quot; is the college or school that one attended or graduated from, I think it is reasonable to list both. Seaborg certainly considered himself an alumnus of both schools, regularly attending college bowl games for both schools (whenever they made it) until late in his life. [[User:Glenn4pr|Glenn4pr]] 02:12, 2 October 2006 (UTC)
::After checking my  Webster's 11th, I grant your point. Sincerely, [[User:GeorgeLouis|GeorgeLouis]] 03:14, 2 October 2006 (UTC)
::I'll bet, though, that during the period when he was chancellor at Berkeley, he muted his love for UCLA &lt;grin&gt;. [[User:MWS|MWS]] 16:21, 15 November 2006 (UTC)

== Writing address w/ elements ==

Removed the following: &lt;blockquote&gt;For the remainder of his life, Seaborg was the only person in the world who could write his address in chemical element symbols: [[seaborgium]], [[lawrencium]], [[berkelium]], [[californium]], [[americium]] (Glenn Seaborg, [[Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory]], [[Berkeley, California|Berkeley]], [[California]], [[United States|United States of America]]), or, in chemical symbols: Sg, Lr, Bk, Cf, Am.&lt;/blockquote&gt;  as it's trivial, and I doubt it's veracity.  Seems out of place on a formal biography.[[User:Dirtyharry2|Dirtyharry2]] 00:27, 17 October 2006 (UTC)

:::It might or might not be true, but it should be sourced if true. Did Seaborg actually do this? Seems like a stretch. [[User:GeorgeLouis|GeorgeLouis]] 01:36, 17 October 2006 (UTC)

::One of the first sources for this oft quoted point was an article in Discover magazine. See Jeffrey Winters, &quot;What’s in a Name?&quot; DISCOVER, Vol. 19 No. 01, January 1998. Also available on the web at http://www.discover.com/issues/jan-98/features/theyearinscience1309/ , website, accessed October 17, 2006. See also http://crookedtimber.org/2005/07/17/acronymity/ and http://www.tbtf.com/archive/0145.html#s09 [[User:Glenn4pr|Glenn4pr]] 05:56, 18 October 2006 (UTC)

::Rewrote passage regarding his address. It is more than trivia. It is instructive of both his prolific contributions to science and his strong ambition to create an enduring legacy. [[User:Glenn4pr|Glenn4pr]] 06:30, 18 October 2006 (UTC)

::I'm still not following.  Other than Seaborgium (which is a proper name), anyone else who happened to live in the same place could claim the same 'achievement' regarding the address.  I simply don't see the relevance.  The fact that he discovered so many elements is documented at length elsewhere in the article, and tangential relevance to his address simply doesn't add much, IMHO.  However, since I'm the poster who originally removed the text, I'll step back for someone else to act/not act.[[User:Dirtyharry2|Dirtyharry2]] 18:21, 18 October 2006 (UTC)

Although Seaborg never actually wrote his address on an envelope like this (to the best of my knowledge), I heard him say this. It is a &quot;trivial&quot; but unique fact.  No one else living (before, at that time, nor currently) had an element named them.  All were deceased at the time of naming, save Seaborg.  [[User:Restevens1|Restevens1]] 04:08, 20 May 2007 (UTC)restevens1

== Transmuting lead into gold? ==

I haven't been able to find any solid reference for the claim that he ever transmuted lead into gold. I did find a paper where he transmuted ''bismuth'' into gold. I suspect that the whole lead claim is just a kind of urban legend (bismuth didn't sound as glamorous, and most people haven't even heard of it!). The paper is K. Aleklett, D. J. Morrissey, W. Loveland, P. L. McGaughey, and G. T. Seaborg. Energy dependence of 209Bi fragmentation in relativistic nuclear collisions. ''Phys. Rev. C'' '''1981''', ''23'', 1044-1046. {{doi|10.1103/PhysRevC.23.1044}}. (This work was originally presented at an ACS meeting in 1980, so the 1980 date in the article is correct.) --[[User:Itub|Itub]] 12:08, 16 February 2007 (UTC)

== Seaborgium - unconfirmed anecdote ==

I had the pleasure of briefly meeting Professor Seaborg while attending [[University of California, Berkeley|UCB]] and was struck by how tall and charming he was.  Supposedly shortly after academics began using the seaborgium name for element 106, the [[American Chemical Society|ACS]] issued a statement reaffirming the policy of not naming elements after living people.  As the story goes, when Seaborg was asked to comment on this, he said something to the effect of, &quot;Well, it seems I've done enough to be nominated as the namesake for element 106, but as far as the ACS is concerned, I have yet to do one last thing--that is, to die.&quot;  As morbid as it sounds, I'm certain it was meant to be humorous. It was definitely taken that way by people.  (It's entirely possible that while the paraphrased comment is attributed to Seaborg, it was really made by someone else.)   Of course, ultimately, the ACS relented.  If anyone was worthy of making that exception, Seaborg was.  --[[User:67.188.0.96|67.188.0.96]] 04:00, 13 March 2007 (UTC)
:FWIW, I've heard the story too. I have no idea if it is real or just a legend, though. --[[User:Itub|Itub]] 09:19, 14 March 2007 (UTC)
:: The anecdote actually appears in his autobiography... &quot;Adventures in the Atomic Age&quot;  or at least something similar to the anecdote does.  The only reason I remember this anecdote was that it also applied to another, but by the time they named that element the other scientist had died. [[User:Das Nerd|Das Nerd]] 02:00, 15 March 2007 (UTC)

Per my personal conversation with Dr. Darleane Hoffman, she and Dr. Al Ghiorso had put together the idea to honor Glenn Seaborg.  They ran it by Helen, his wife.  She thought he would be pleased (and a little embarassed).  So, they proposed it to IUPAC, which adopted it.  Then they told Glenn.  He was taken aback, but finally relented and agreed to this honor (since it was already a &quot;done deal&quot;, he couldn't do much about it!) [[User:Restevens1|Restevens1]] 04:15, 20 May 2007 (UTC)restevens1


== Number of children ==

This article says Glen and his wife had six children; her article says they had seven children, one of whom died young. Can someone confirm which is correct and edit the page which is wrong?


[[User:Molybdomancer|Molybdomancer]] ([[User talk:Molybdomancer|talk]]) 15:04, 14 September 2009 (UTC)

They had a female child die as an infant, she is not listed in this article. She was a fraternal twin to one of the boys. I know this for a fact, but don't have a source handy so won't add it to the article. [[User:Glenn4pr|Glenn4pr]] ([[User talk:Glenn4pr|talk]]) 23:23, 10 February 2012 (UTC)

== Discovery of fission ==

I have removed a sentence that claimed Seaborg discovered the fission of 235U. Fission of uranium was discovered by Hahn and Strassmann in 1938 and explained theoretically by Meitner and Frisch in 1939. It was Neils Bohr who showed that fission observed in natural uranium came from 235U.[[User:Struvite|Struvite]] ([[User talk:Struvite|talk]]) 15:46, 12 December 2010 (UTC)

== Patents ==

Did he receive patents on the elements Americium and Curium themselves (seems unlikely) or just on the methods for &quot;manufacturing&quot; them? --[[User:Dante Alighieri|Dante Alighieri]] | [[User talk:Dante Alighieri|Talk]] 19:56, 22 September 2011 (UTC)

He received the patents on the elements themselves. They are on record as the shortest patent &quot;claim&quot; ever: &quot;1. Element 95&quot; in the one case and &quot;1. Element 96&quot; in the other. US 3,164,462 (Dec. 15, 1964; filed Feb. 7. 1949)
Element 96 and compositions thereof
“1. Element 96”
US 3,156,523 (Nov. 10, 1964; filed Aug. 23, 1946)
Element 95 and method of producing said element
“1. Element 95”
Dr. Glenn T. Seaborg
U.S. Atomic Energy Commission (Washington, DC)
[[User:Glenn4pr|Glenn4pr]] ([[User talk:Glenn4pr|talk]]) 23:35, 10 February 2012 (UTC)

{{Talk:Glenn T. Seaborg/GA1}}

== External link? ==

Would an interview with transcript with Glenn Seaborg from 1986 be useful here as an external link? Focus of conversation is nuclear weapons policy. http://openvault.wgbh.org/catalog/V_26A09FA3EFD24CA59DFCA3A22B27E450 (I have a conflict of interest; otherwise I would add it myself.) [[User:Mccallucc|Mccallucc]] ([[User talk:Mccallucc|talk]]) 17:11, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
:{{tick}} Added. I like external links where the reader can actually see and hear the subject. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 21:49, 23 March 2016 (UTC)

==Assessment comment==
{{Substituted comment|length=394|lastedit=20070217024606|comment=I recently submitted an edit to this article. It had said that Seaborg sneaked a tiny camera past Soviet guards to photograph Kennedy and Khrushchev signing the Limited Test Ban Treaty in 1963. In fact, the Treaty was signed in Moscow, but Kennedy was not present. The U.S. delegation was headed by Averill Harriman, who signed for the U.S. I edited the article to remove the Kennedy reference.}}
Substituted at 16:23, 29 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rmbk00kfu069s7cfxmo6obv4s4ludvv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
