<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:No Gun Ri massacre</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>16770177</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749983954</id>
      <parentid>736841117</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-17T05:26:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Legobot</username>
        <id>7304691</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>BOT: Adding |oldid=706356217 to {{[[Template:GA|GA]]}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17229">{{GA|21:23, 22 February 2016 (UTC)|topic=Warfare|page=1|oldid=706356217}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 16
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(10d)
|archive = Talk:No Gun Ri Massacre/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Talk header|index=/Archive index}}
{{controversial}}
{{Calm|#FFCCCC}}
{{not a forum|the No Gun Ri Massacre|&lt;br&gt;If you are attacked, '''please do not retaliate.''' It's not worth it.&lt;/br&gt;}}
{{WPBS|
{{WikiProject Korea|class=GA|importance=High|milhist=yes}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|US=y|Korean=y|Cold-War=yes}}
{{WPUSA|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Cold War|class=GA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Crime|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=GA|importance=mid}}
}}
{{oldafdfull| date =  | result = '''keep''' | page = No Gun Ri Massacre }}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2012-07-29|oldid1=504683282|date2=2015-07-29|oldid2=673588976}}
{{Archive box |auto=yes |search=yes |title=[[Help:Archiving a talk page|Archives]] ([[{{#titleparts:{{TALKPAGENAME}}|1}}/Archive index|index]]) |bot=lowercase sigmabot III |age=10|
*[[/Archive 1|Archive 1 (2005 - 17 July 2007)]] 
*[[/Archive 2|Archive 2]]
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:No Gun Ri Massacre/Archive index
|mask=Talk:No Gun Ri Massacre/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes
}}

== Let's now move toward consensus ==
Except for dealing with our overly long &quot;Further Reading&quot; and &quot;External Links&quot; lists, I have finished a basic cleanup, update and reorganization of this article. {{U|Timothyjosephwood}}, {{U|GeneralizationsAreBad}}, {{U|Wikimedes}}, {{U|Iryna Harpy}}, {{U|Irondome}}, {{U|Binksternet}}, please review, question, suggest, reorder sensibly, rewrite literately, critique unsparingly ... all, one hopes, toward the end of reaching the consensus that TJWood spoke of some weeks back: an agreement that as it now stands this is an accurate, solidly sourced, coherent presentation of a historic event, and it shouldn't be tampered with except by competent hands doing honest work. Thanks. [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 20:26, 10 October 2015 (UTC)
:Apologies for taking so long to respond to the multiple pings you've left here, {{u|Cjhanley}}. Every time I try to return to the discussion I end up being sidetracked by innumerable other articles and issues demanding immediate attention on Wikipedia. I suspect that I'm also speaking on behalf of the other editors you've pinged.

:Given that you've thought out the structure and details carefully, I'd be amenable to your going [[WP:BOLD]] in working on the article rather than continue to hamper progress. Naturally, this would be on the proviso that these changes be subject to [[WP:BRD]]. I'd just like to check with the other editors that they are comfortable with such an arrangement. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 00:07, 11 October 2015 (UTC)
::While this is one of the most fascinating subjects (and disputes) that I've ever come across, I just find myself without any constructive edit proposals to make. I'm also not sure what exactly what there is left to do. [[User:GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:GeneralizationsAreBad|Hello!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:23, 11 October 2015 (UTC)

Thank you both. As for further work (besides the reading and links lists), I do recall there was some sentiment weeks back for looking again at the '''Lead section''', now that the entire piece is revised. Two matters strike me there:

:*Citations are not usual in WP leads. My understanding is that the lead is simply a summation of already well-sourced material in the body. To me, the current lead suggests that central elements hinge on a single source, e.g., the very first sentence, saying refugees were killed by the U.S. military, is sourced singly to Baik’s law journal article when, of course, it’s the undisputed conclusion of official and journalistic investigations.

:*Writing that the (AP’s) massacre account was found to be “essentially correct” is superfluous. It’s enough to say the AP reported the massacre, and the official investigations reaffirmed it. The “essentially correct” sentence that comes between those two facts is strange in another way: It sounds as though the AP report was confirmed, and ''then'' the governments investigated. The sentence can be dropped entirely, in my view.

On another matter, subject to discussion some time ago, I find that in the line in “Background” saying, “orders were issued to fire on Korean civilians in front-line areas”, the idea of “orders” is dropped in there much too matter-of-factly, as though this is routine business in war. There was objection (with which I disagree) some time ago to identifying these at this point as illegal orders. Fine. But it needs ''some'' wording alerting readers to the fact that such orders are surprising/unusual/jawdropping to military lawyers. And so I propose the following:

{{talkquote|
With gaps in their lines, U.S. forces were attacked from the rear, and reports spread that disguised North Korean soldiers were infiltrating refugee columns. &lt;ref name=&quot;Appleman&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Appleman | first1 = Roy E. | title = South to the Naktong, North to the Yalu (June–November 1950) | publisher = Office of the Chief of Military History, Department of the Army | year = 1961 | location = Washington, D.C. | url = http://www.history.army.mil/BOOKS/KOREA/20-2-1/toc.htm | accessdate = February 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|131,158,202}} &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Williams |first=Jeremy |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/coldwar/korea_usa_01.shtml |title=Kill 'em All: The American Military in Korea |work=British Broadcasting Corp. |date=2011-02-17 |accessdate=2015-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of these concerns, orders were issued to fire on Korean civilians in front-line areas''', orders discovered decades later in declassified military archives'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Occurrence at Nogun-ri Bridge |journal=Critical Asian Studies |date=December 2001 |last=Cumings |first=Bruce |volume=33 |issue=4 |page=512 |issn=1467-2715 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Williams |first=Jeremy |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/coldwar/korea_usa_01.shtml |title=Kill 'em All: The American Military in Korea |work=British Broadcasting Corp. |date=2011-02-17 |accessdate=2015-08-13 |quote=Declassified military documents recently found in the U.S. National Archives show clearly how US commanders repeatedly, and without ambiguity, ordered forces under their control to target and kill Korean refugees caught on the battlefield.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among those issuing the orders was [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Cavalry Division]] commander [[Major general (United States)|Maj. Gen.]] [[Hobart R. Gay#Korean War|Hobart R. Gay]], who deemed Koreans left in the war zone to be “enemy agents,” according to U.S. war correspondent O.H.P. King and U.S. diplomat Harold Joyce Noble.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Noble |first1=Harold Joyce |title=Embassy at War |location=Seattle |publisher=University of Washington Press |year=1975 |page=152 |isbn=0-295-95341-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=King |first1=O.H.P. |title=Tail of the Paper Tiger | location=Caldwell, Idaho |publisher=The Caxton Printers, Ltd. |year=1962 |pages=358-359}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{reflist-talk}}
}}

Thanks. [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 16:43, 11 October 2015 (UTC)

== Re 'Further reading,' 'External links' ==
The &quot;Further reading&quot; and &quot;External links&quot; sections are clearly well beyond the recommended WP length and criteria. It seems the WP guideline is to include sources not already cited and-or linked to in the References section, except for a very few that are so useful and central that they bear repeating.
	
I'll trim the two sections bearing in mind those considerations, along with the need to delete dead links (unless so important they're worth retrieving via &quot;Wayback&quot;), and to delete outdated and barely relevant or irrelevant sources.
	
Among the irrelevancies is the Bateman book. How can Wikipedia recommend that one's understanding of the well-established historical event called No Gun Ri can be deepened by reading a &quot;book&quot; -- in reality a jaw-dropping pastiche of fantasies -- that insists that No Gun Ri &quot;never happened&quot;?
	
Here is Bateman on his pages 126-127: ''&quot;The unanimity of the Koreans' testimony suggests that it is the product of years of group and individual discussions. ... In hindsight, the Korean accounts appear to be a montage, a collection of the memories of several different events that took place at other times and other places, if they took place as described at all. ... Rather, the killings occurred in dozens and possibly hundreds of the small misfortunes that make war so horrible.&quot;''
	
Bateman is just that unbelievable.

This rank absurdity, stupid and absurd on so many levels and based on ''absolutely nothing'' beyond this denialist's wishful &quot;thinking,&quot; was published in 2002, after teams of professional journalists from major news organizations '''''confirmed''''' the outlines of the massacre, after the 15-month-long investigations by two sovereign governments '''''reaffirmed''''' it, and after the president of the United States '''''issued a statement of regret'''''.
	
Wikipedia might just as well recommend David Irving books in the &quot;Further reading&quot; section of the Holocaust article. As we delete serious works by serious people such as Suhi Choi and Kim Dong-choon from the list for other reasons, how can we possibly still recommend such a collection of inanities?
	
Thanks. [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 21:48, 21 October 2015 (UTC)

: It seems Bateman has now been entirely purged from the article, which has apparently been your goal for several months. Bateman is not what I would call a high-quality source, and I would not use it as a template for structuring the article in any significant way. It is, however, a reliably published source, and the controversies surrounding him (and you) received ample secondary coverage and commentary. In short, the article is not in compliance with NPOV if Bateman is completely absent. Regardless of Bateman's deficiencies, you have exceeded the bounds of prudent editing given your conflict of interest. I have restored a mention to his book in the most parsimonious fashion. I'm content to leave it at that, and I suggest you do the same. [[User:Rhoark|Rhoark]] ([[User talk:Rhoark|talk]]) 15:04, 24 October 2015 (UTC)

: I fear that a de-facto POVFORK will develop, with the article on Bateman's book becoming the &quot;alternative version&quot; of this page. [[User:GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:GeneralizationsAreBad|Hello!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:55, 24 October 2015 (UTC)

::Whoops, {{U|GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB}}, I'm afraid you've slipped into Bateman's rabbit hole with your edit. &quot;35&quot; was only one of his wildly erratic &quot;casualty estimates,&quot; which he described as &quot;ballpark estimates&quot; based on a &quot;lack of evidence&quot; (!) to the contrary. In other words, &quot;Time for me to make up my own numbers! But I'll keep them below triple figures!&quot; (Of course, there's overwhelming evidence to the contrary; citing Bateman at all, as though worthy of attention, is frankly an outrage.) His numbers of dead, scattered throughout the book, range from &quot;some half-dozen&quot; and eight, up to 70. No basis cited, because there's no basis for any of it. At the same time, in at least four places, he certainly ''did'' deny No Gun Ri happened. On one and the same page (126) he describes survivors’ accounts as &quot;unanimous,&quot; that is, a composite memory that should be discounted; and then, ''five sentences later,'' that they are &quot;different&quot; and so must stem from “hundreds of small misfortunes,” meaning No Gun Ri did not occur. This guy's outrages -- and his obtuseness in contradicting himself repeatedly and stunningly -- seem to know no bounds.

::Bottom line: We've worked too hard to stay out of rabbit holes in this article, and we cannot descend into this warped mind-world again. Rhoark seems to think the lies-laden attack on the AP by 7th Cav men, ages ago made moot by immediate refutations and then by an avalanche of accumulated journalistic and official findings, is worthy of attention (as though adding to anyone's knowledge of No Gun Ri). I'll edit to roll back to that basic point, and avoid a silly diversion into Batemania. Thanks. [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 16:02, 25 October 2015 (UTC)

:::I am actually with Rhoark on this one. A passing mention is harmless, though I understand your frustration. [[User:GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:GeneralizationsAreBad|Hello!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:00, 25 October 2015 (UTC)

{{Talk:No Gun Ri Massacre/GA1}}

== Whoops ==
Because I apparently deleted an extraneous space in the text, that edit of mine today appeared to affect a big chunk of text involving Bateman etc. It didn't. All that blue is not &quot;new.&quot; The only change there was to say the AP defended its work with &quot;a lengthy, detailed refutation.&quot; (Up above, the other change was simply to note that Daily &quot;incorrectly identified himself as an eyewitness.&quot; The previous wording left open the possibility that the AP had misrepresented Daily.) Thanks. [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 22:47, 24 February 2016 (UTC)

== Thanks Everybody ==
Just wanted to say, I apologize that my editing perpetually comes in waves, but I'm glad to see the article has continued to see productive work. Good job everybody. [[User:Timothyjosephwood|Timothyjosephwood]] ([[User talk:Timothyjosephwood|talk]]) 12:30, 18 March 2016 (UTC)

== Deleted final graf of lead section ==

{{U|GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB}}, today's deletion of the lead section's final sentence points up a couple of problems. First, the sentence (“The attention gained by No Gun Ri prompted South Korean government investigations into other alleged U.S. killings of civilians during the Korean War”) seems to be a telescoping of the way things read before our dear departed troll descended destructively upon the article in 2013. It originally read: “Prompted by the exposure of No Gun Ri, survivors of similar alleged incidents in 1950-1951 filed reports with the Seoul government. In 2008 an investigative commission said more than 200 cases of alleged large-scale killings by the U.S. military had been registered, mostly air attacks.” And that was drawn from the first graf of the section “Truth and Reconciliation Commission,” which still stands and which is properly sourced (sourcing that can easily be improved by me, by the way).

I don’t know where the USIP sourcing came from for the sentence you deleted. And that points up the second problem: I maintain that the lead section ''should not have citiations'', since it is merely a summary of matters duly sourced in the body. Citations lead to silly situations such as the very first sentence of the article, summarizing the most important facts of No Gun Ri, being attributed to an unknown legal scholar writing in an obscure journal – when the central facts are powerfully established by dozens of sources, big and small, in the body. My personal bible, ''Wikipedia: The Missing Manual'', says, “Citations aren’t generally appropriate in the lead section; they belong in the body of the article.”

I propose restoring the original wording to the end of the lead section. But I’ll do it with citations for the moment, for consistency’s sake. And meantime I’d like to discuss eliminating the lead section’s citations completely. Thanks! [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 19:51, 7 July 2016 (UTC)
:{{replyto|Cjhanley}} Sure, no concerns here. Feel free to remove the citations as needed and restore the sentence - I believe the citations were inserted some time ago, when things were much more tense. Thanks for bringing this up. [[User:GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:GeneralizationsAreBad|gab]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:59, 7 July 2016 (UTC)

::Thanks, {{U|GeneralizationsAreBad|GAB}}. As said, I'll retain cites in the lead for now, including with my new addition, while I study the ramifications of removing each one. [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 22:14, 7 July 2016 (UTC)

=== Removing citations from lead section ===
As proposed, I will edit the lead section to remove the citations, per usual WP practice. Each of the statements of the lead is repeated with at least one source, often more, in the body of the article. In order to maintain coherence, this will be an edit of the entire article in one fell swoop, since several of the cites of the lead have to be reconstructed in the body -- substituting a full first citation for a previous cite in the body that was simply in &quot;refname&quot; shorthand. Several of the lead's cites were one-off cites, and so this edit will now incorporate them in &quot;Further Reading&quot; and &quot;External Links,&quot; so as not to lose them entirely. Thanks! [[User:Cjhanley|Charles J. Hanley]] ([[User talk:Cjhanley|talk]]) 21:35, 8 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hqf33a870udivyw5s5dn8tuzh71v162</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
