<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Reflector sight</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>29305185</id>
    <revision>
      <id>647997408</id>
      <parentid>602100897</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-02-20T05:50:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster|Substing templates]]: {{unsigned2}}. See [[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster]] for info.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9259">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=02:39, 20 July 2011
|action1link=Talk:Reflector sight/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=440336299
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=Engtech
}}
{{Merged-from|Reflex sight}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|Weaponry=y|Aviation=y}}
{{WPGUNS|class=GA|importance=mid}}

==Reflex sight merged==
Merged per [[WP:MERGE]] - Overlap to overcome many of the problems noted at [[Talk:Reflex sight#Merger and scope]]. There were several articles describing some narrow aspect of the Reflector sight, [[Red dot sight]]--&gt;moved to and expanded at [[Reflex sight]][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Reflex_sight&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=273130347&amp;oldid=273129651], and this original Reflector sight article[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Reflector_sight&amp;oldid=401131608]. Merged to this article for broader overall description since these are all the same device per reference ([http://books.google.com/books?id=g_YXAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=Elementary%20optics%20and%20application%20to%20fire%20control%20reflector%20%20sight&amp;pg=SA8-PA27#v=onepage&amp;q=reflector%20sight&amp;f=false example]) and per [[WP:TITLEFORMAT]] per avoid abbreviations. Article heavily rewritten and expanded with many added references. There could probably be articles on sub-types, I think [[Red dot sight]], [[Collimator sight]], and [[Holographic weapon sight]] have unique description that could probably be seperate articles. [[User:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|Fountains of Bryn Mawr]] ([[User talk:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|talk]]) 01:11, 4 May 2011 (UTC)

{{Talk:Reflector sight/GA1}}

==Telrad==
removed citation needed December 2011 because the information basic and common knowledge. The following was left for the edit/removal
/* Other uses */  citation needed removed links for information will be on talk page, CN writer lacks any basic professional knowledge on the subject to request such.[[Special:Contributions/68.210.95.127|68.210.95.127]] ([[User talk:68.210.95.127|talk]]) 07:12, 31 December 2011 (UTC)
links to back up telrad sights on follow spots in the the entertainment industry which by its ad hock nature lacks a multiple history sources for references.
*  http://roadietools.com/spotsight.html [[Roadie]] redirects to [[Road_crew]] and [[tool]]
from here down I will list basic links with out breaking the terms down, as in you ether know the words or you should start at [[Stagecraft]]  and read towards stage lighting and follow spots and follow spot operators
*  http://www.controlbooth.com/wiki/Telrad theater forum and wiki website
*http://www.productionadvantageonline.com/Followspot-Parts/TELRAD.aspx sales deescription
*http://www.amazon.com/Telrad-Finder-Sight/dp/B0000ALKAN  see reviews for information
*http://www.stagespot.com/product/TELRAD/TelRad%20Spotting%20Scope sales page
*http://www.controlbooth.com/forums/lighting-electrics/4018-followspot-aiming-tips.html discuss methods for spotlights to aim and telrad is mentioned and linked to
*http://www.enlightenment.co.uk/lighting/techSpecs/followspots/fs4.html
*http://www.theatrecrafts.com/lx_followspotting.shtml
*http://www.barbizon.com/product_info.php?products_id=15028

Two links for images in use
*http://www.hbernstaedt.de/knowhow/scheinwerfer/verfolger/verfolger.htm you'll find them on numerous follow spotlights
*http://behindthebeam.blogspot.com/search?updated-max=2006-12-15T17:05:00-05:00&amp;max-results=14 second image shows the view through a telrad combined with dancers on stage and farther down you will see telrads on followspots.

I don't have the time hunt up more images of it in use. However that short sampling will show the &quot;citation needed December 2011&quot; was  not necessary nor valid. Their use is not a matter of debate, the preference for types of sights used by follow spot operator are.  Which comes down to each users preference including using light leaks and making marks on a dry erase board for them when the light is aimed at a spot. Since most links are commercial in nature none were added to the main article. Feel free to choose which ever one you like and/or want.

:Please note: Wikipedia is not an encyclopedia of &quot;common knowledge&quot; and the knowledge of the editor on the subject has nothing to do with whether he/she can edit it (you may want to read [[WP:V]]). Any &quot;facts&quot; claimed have to be verifiable (with citation), and ''any'' editor can (and will) look up those citations or note the total lack of them. I have put back the need for citation because the addition of this information is very sketchy re: only the Telrad?[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Reflector_sight&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=467760870&amp;oldid=467754542]... no[http://www.controlbooth.com/forums/lighting-electrics/4857-red-dot-scope-followspots.html], use on other types of spots?, use in other types of event besides ''theater''? .... general lack of third party reference. [[User:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|Fountains of Bryn Mawr]] ([[User talk:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|talk]]) 14:07, 1 January 2012 (UTC)

== Retiflector sights ==

I am an unskilled Wikipedia user.  I would love to discuss this with you, since I have a fourth figure that shows the retiflector configuration.

If you wouldn't mind talking about it directly, please e-mail me at rwhistler25@hotmail.com.

The only references I know of that describe the retiflector sight are the pertinent Air Force Tech Orders and a Baille-Lemaire manual, as well as an article describing the NIFE sight.  I can pull these together for you, though many will be hard for you to find.

Ross

[[User:Rosswhis|Rosswhis]] ([[User talk:Rosswhis|talk]]) 20:57, 25 August 2012 (UTC)
==[[Chuck Yeager]]'s thoughts==
''&quot;To my estimation, the M14 sight is the biggest improvement to combatequipment to Fighter up to this date.&quot;'' - from his combat report of 12 October 1944,when he downed 5 Me109s.[http://www.chuckyeager.com/five-victory-me-109-report] &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Snori|Snori]] ([[User talk:Snori|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Snori|contribs]]) 10:11, 6 October 2012‎&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Changes and GA de-listing ==

Actually not sure if this was supposed to have been GA de-listed since there is no comment on that and simple MOS changes fall outside [[WP:GAR]]. The removed section heading structure was a logical one, a reflector sight has uses and sub-uses and it is on more devices than just &quot;military&quot;, such as probably 100000+ astronomical telescopes at this point. Also I am not sure a history section should go first in an encyclopedia listing for a device, it should probably be description first. The rest of the MOS changes seem correct and should probably be put right back in. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|Fountains of Bryn Mawr]] ([[User talk:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Fountains of Bryn Mawr|contribs]]) 19:50, 27 March 2014&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

: Right well, as you appeared to notice at the end there was no de-listing: the icon was merely moved to the foot of the code out of the way of the content, which as far as I'm aware is the prevailing style. As this seems to have been the primary point of disagreement, I've rolled back to this afternoon's revision. Regarding the history section, my reading of it is that it actually does a better job than the previous &quot;overview&quot; of providing the required context for the rest of the article; in my experience it is also the case that a brief history, where present, is usually the first section after the lead. The next two sections flow logically into one another and the previous split was incongruous. [[User:Thumperward|Chris Cunningham (user:thumperward)]] ([[User talk:Thumperward|talk]]) 00:10, 28 March 2014 (UTC)

::[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Reflector_sight&amp;diff=601581188&amp;oldid=601568386] Actually it was a Wikipedia brain problem mixed in  --- pages would not refresh (I could see my edits in page history, but they would not show) so gave up to give the overworked Wikipedia servers a rest. Back at it, simply moved &quot;History&quot; section and preserved sub-sections. I used to put History sections first but other editors would move them down below description and now I can see the value in that. I looked to see if there were guidelines or MOS to follow but saw none. [[User:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|Fountains of Bryn Mawr]] ([[User talk:Fountains of Bryn Mawr|talk]]) 15:14, 28 March 2014 (UTC)

::: Well, again, the diff clearly shows that a bunch of smaller edits were undone there. It's far easier simply to manually reorder the paragraphs than to try to piece the preferred version together from diffs which may not have discrete changes. I've fixed things up now. I'm still not happy that we're going as deep as level 4 section headers here; this suggests an imbalance to the article's coverage, as (much as I said before) the majority of the material covers weapon sights and yet they're being hived off into one section. [[User:Thumperward|Chris Cunningham (user:thumperward)]] ([[User talk:Thumperward|talk]]) 12:15, 31 March 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>k20ujpnbwimju0p6iayevvs2igeaewj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
