<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Zyklon B</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>354467</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748312685</id>
      <parentid>748255489</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T15:24:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rivertorch's Evil Twin</username>
        <id>17607405</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* &quot;disinfect&quot; vs &quot;disinfest&quot; */ r</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22830">{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{Not a forum}}
{{GA|12:28, 4 October 2014 (UTC)|topic=World history|page=1|oldid=628201575}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=GA|importance=mid|German-task-force=yes|WWII-task-force=yes}}
{{WPMED|class=GA|importance=low|toxicology=yes|toxicology-imp=low}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2013-09-03|oldid1=571182405|date2=2015-09-03|oldid2=679282685|date3=2016-09-03|oldid3=737502710}}
[[Category:GA-Class Nazi Germany articles]]
{{Archives |search=yes }}

==Too much bitterness and ax-grinding on this article==
{{Archive top|Article has been comprehensively rewritten. Thankyou. [[User:AnotherNewAccount|AnotherNewAccount]] ([[User talk:AnotherNewAccount|talk]]) 19:35, 24 February 2016 (UTC)}}
Stumbled on this page, and found it in fairly sorry shape. A lot of loaded language, some of it shoe-horned in such a way as to disrupt the flow of the article. A lot of minute detail that would otherwise fall outside of the scope of an article on a pesticide. Only a cursory explanation on how it works. The entire tone of the article implies the product was designed and used exclusively in what became the Holocaust. It's important to keep things in perspective. Remember that prior to this, Zyklon-B was a generic and otherwise unremarkable pesticide. [[User:AnotherNewAccount|AnotherNewAccount]] ([[User talk:AnotherNewAccount|talk]]) 14:13, 24 June 2014 (UTC)

:Wikipedia normally covers topics mostly proportionate to the coverage those topics receive in reliable sources. Zyklon-B's use as a pesticide has not received a great deal of coverage in reliable sources. Perhaps the current &quot;Production and marketing&quot; section could be relocated higher in the article and be a little clearer. (The lead is perfectly clear and neutral about the original purpose of the concoction.) --[[User:Demiurge1000|Demiurge1000]] ([[User_talk:Demiurge1000|talk]]) 21:46, 24 June 2014 (UTC)
{{Archive bottom}}

{{Talk:Zyklon B/GA1}}

== Czech production ==

Uragan D2 is (still) produced in [http://www.draslovka.cz/products/uragan-d2 Lučební závody Draslovka a.s. Kolín] in [[Kolín]], see also the [http://www.sdruzeni.dddinfo.cz/index.php?option=com_phocadownload&amp;view=category&amp;download=147:uragan-d2&amp;id=5:insekticidy&amp;Itemid=33&amp;start=50 label]. Adezin is a company that just uses it. --[[User:Matěj Orlický|Matěj Orlický]] ([[User talk:Matěj Orlický|talk]]) 19:47, 16 July 2015 (UTC)
:Corrected, thank you -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 20:01, 16 July 2015 (UTC)
::Thank you. Nice to find a picture taken few steps from my place on your user page. --[[User:Matěj Orlický|Matěj Orlický]] ([[User talk:Matěj Orlický|talk]]) 21:28, 16 July 2015 (UTC)

== Legacy ==

Some points in the &quot;Legacy&quot; section:
* ''Subsequent use of the word &quot;Zyklon&quot; in trade names has prompted angry reactions.'' There is of course a difference between German, where &quot;Zyklon&quot; is a mundane word available for branding, and English, where the Holocaust is its sole connotation. (Search amazon.de for &quot;zyklon&quot;.) They may well fall under unfortunate-misunderstanding rather than wilful-ignorance, still less deliberate-allusion; of course that's what the companies will say and their critics will doubt. In [[:Category:Brands]] I couldn't find any &quot;international branding mistakes&quot; article (like [http://books.google.com/books?id=5T30CQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA94 this book]) to link to. It would be good to know how salient the Holocaust in for ''Zyklon'' in Germany, or in other language-zones.  Page 34 of [http://books.google.com/books?id=xOUcAQAAIAAJ this 1997 German book about English poetry] explains the significance of &quot;Zyklon&quot; in English, which suggests it needs explaining to Germans.
* ''Use of hydrogen cyanide as a pesticide has been widely banned or restricted.'' Putting this at the end invites the inference that the ban is due to the Holocaust, rather than to the fact that the chemical is too dangerous for the purpose. Perhaps the post-war production history belongs separate from (and before) the &quot;Legacy&quot; section; noting the restriction would be in that context.
* The Degussa [[Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe|Berlin Holocaust Memorial]] controversy merits mention.
[[User:Jnestorius|jnestorius]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Jnestorius|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 18:42, 5 August 2015 (UTC)

:We have to rely on what reliable sources have to say about the topic. If you have a source that specifies why the chemical was banned, then we can add specifics. We can't assume. I have done some re-ordering of the content to try to address your concerns. I have added the Degussa controversy as a see-also; it's out of scope to include it here in my opinion. Your concern {{xt|&quot;It would be good to know how salient the Holocaust in for ''Zyklon'' in Germany, or in other language-zones&quot;}} sorry, but I don't understand this sentence. There possibly are some words missing or incorrect words. Likewise I don't understand your poetry reference, or the need to explain thing to Germans, as this is the English-language Wikipedia,  not the German one. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 19:38, 5 August 2015 (UTC)

::*&quot;Holocaust in for&quot; should have read &quot;Holocaust is for&quot;, but let me try a complete paraphrase: When English-speakers see the word &quot;Zyklon&quot;, they immediately think of the Holocaust. Not so for German-speakers, for whom &quot;Zyklon&quot; is an ordinary everyday word meaning &quot;cyclone&quot;. I don't think Germans think of the Holocaust at all when they see/hear  &quot;Zyklon&quot; (whereas they would when they see/hear  &quot;Zyklon B&quot;). Moreover, I think the fact that English speakers immediately think of the Holocaust is not an obvious fact for German-speakers. (As evidence for my belief, there is a German book that specifically explains for German readers that the occurrence of the word &quot;Zyklon&quot; in an English-language poem is not a reference to a cyclone, but rather a reference to the Holocaust.) Thus, Germans continue to use &quot;Zyklon&quot; in the brandnames of products, just as English product names might include &quot;Thunder&quot;, &quot;Tornado&quot;, &quot;Whirlwind&quot;, &quot;Hurricane&quot;. When such German products are seen in an English-speaking country, it may cause offence. My concern is that the current statement {{xt|Subsequent use of the word &quot;Zyklon&quot; in trade names has prompted angry reactions}} might suggest that naming a rollercoaster, sneaker, or vacuum cleaner &quot;Zyklon&quot; was a deliberate allusion to the Holocaust gas rather than a coincidence. So I would ideally change it to something like {{xt|Subsequent use of ''Zyklon'' (&quot;cyclone&quot;) in German product names has caused [[foreign brandname misconstrual]] and offence among English speakers and Jewish groups.}} Which of course would need to be referenced; and there seems to be no Wikipedia article &quot;foreign brandname misconstrual&quot;, though there is [[User:Benjamin Mako Hill/List of unintentionally offensive product names]].
::*I disagree that the Degussa controversy is out-of-scope: the Zyklon-B connection was central to the controversy; it seems to me to be quite clearly part of the &quot;Legacy&quot; of Zyklon B. I also dislike using &quot;See also&quot; where the connection between the current topic and the linked article is not obvious until you click through; this violates [[WP:EASTEREGG]].
::*I couldn't find the 2002 edition of the UN guide that's the cite for {{xt|Use of hydrogen cyanide as a pesticide has been widely banned or restricted}} but [https://books.google.ie/books?id=OtVZqdPHsm8C the 1997 edition] lists only four countries with restrictions (none on p.545; South Africa on p.438 bans in cleaning products; on p.171 Belgium Germany and the Philippines restrict to authorised fumigators.)
::[[User:Jnestorius|jnestorius]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Jnestorius|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 22:58, 5 August 2015 (UTC)
:::The source book &quot;Consolidated list of products whose consumptionand/or sale have been banned, withdrawn, severely restricted or not approved by governments&quot; 2002 edition was available online at the time I used it as a source, but its contents are no longer visible to me in Google Books. I have amended the sentence to read &quot;Use of hydrogen cyanide as a pesticide or cleaner has been banned or restricted in some countries&quot;. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 01:02, 6 August 2015 (UTC)

==Unusual container opening ??==
Since the article puports to be about the product it should discuss issues such as packaging. Such as : what is the purpose of the unusual offset opening, which appears to be flush with the top of the can with a tube running into the can. How was the can opened as there does not appear a method of securing a cap ? [[User:Rcbutcher|Rcbutcher]] ([[User talk:Rcbutcher|talk]]) 01:29, 26 August 2015 (UTC)
:This topic wasn't covered in the sources I used when I re-wrote the article in October 2014. It looks like they had a punch opener of some kind the cans are all cut with a uniform size round hole. Our article [[can opener]] does not show any devices that could punch that kind of hole. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 13:28, 26 August 2015 (UTC)

== Zyklon A ==

&quot;Research at Degesch of Germany led to the development of Zyklon A,....&quot; &quot;The new product was also named Zyklon, but it became known as Zyklon B to distinguish it from the earlier version.&quot; Was the first product actually developed as &quot;Zyklon A&quot; or simply as &quot;Zyklon&quot; with the A and B being retronyms invented to distinguish the two products? As a parallel, the acoustic guitar was not developed under that name, but was called that later to distinguish it from the electric guitar. --[[User:Khajidha|Khajidha]] ([[User talk:Khajidha|talk]]) 11:21, 3 September 2015 (UTC)
:Both products were named &quot;Zyklon&quot;, and the suffixes were added later to distinguish the two. I have added a bit to the prose to clarify this point. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 13:51, 3 September 2015 (UTC)

== Gas or solid? ==

The article refers a lot to the hydrogen cyanide gas, but shows Zyklon B as solid pellets. This confused me when reading the article. Presumably the gas is released when heated  water is added or something? [[Special:Contributions/76.104.181.96|76.104.181.96]] ([[User talk:76.104.181.96|talk]]) 15:17, 3 September 2015 (UTC)
:The product was solid pellets that turned to a gas when exposed to moisture and heat. This is mentioned both in the lead and in the first paragraph of the &quot;history&quot; section. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 18:43, 3 September 2015 (UTC)

== Errol Morris documentary reference backed out ==

I cited [[Mr._Death:_The_Rise_and_Fall_of_Fred_A._Leuchter,_Jr. | this documentary]] by Oscar-winner [[Errol Morris]] showing why even the chemist who performed the analysis for Holocaust denier [[Fred Leuchter]] thinks the Leuchter results are meaningless. The chemist hadn't been told to test only for the very thin surface deposits, and instead he crushed the samples and did a test over the entire volume of the brick shards, guaranteeing a result far too low.

I added this information but it was backed out. Morris is an Oscar-winning documentarian, not some fringe flake; see The New Yorker, February 1, 1999 http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/1999/02/01/the-friendly-executioner for a review, including a mention that Roth had repudiated the Leuchter result. I linked to the film's transcript on Morris's own site showing what the chemist -- James Roth -- had to say, which was that it was a bogus result.

I do not understand why this material was removed, and I think it should be returned. [[User:AnnaLiver|AnnaLiver]] ([[User talk:AnnaLiver|talk]]) 21:58, 3 September 2015 (UTC)
:I've had a second look at this and now that I understand better what the website is I agree. I've expanded your addition a bit so that it's clearer why the test was flawed. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 14:56, 4 September 2015 (UTC)
::Thank you. [[User:AnnaLiver|AnnaLiver]] ([[User talk:AnnaLiver|talk]]) 17:17, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

== Questionable source ==

The citation (no. 18, &quot;Hitler's Willing Executioners&quot;) is poor. It is not a neutral source and the credibility of the writing is contested by other, prominent historians. It does not meet the standards on Verifiability.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:TrueHistory39|TrueHistory39]] ([[User talk:TrueHistory39|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/TrueHistory39|contribs]]) 15:48, 26 October 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Yes, it does meet the standards.&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Volunteer Marek|&lt;font style=&quot;color:orange;background:blue;font-family:sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;nbsp;Volunteer Marek&amp;nbsp;'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 15:50, 26 October 2015 (UTC)

The work cited, is not neutral and has not been peer-reviewed. It has been said to be &quot;ahistorical&quot; and &quot;totally wrong about everything&quot; by other Holocaust historians such as Raul Hilberg.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:TrueHistory39|TrueHistory39]] ([[User talk:TrueHistory39|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/TrueHistory39|contribs]]) 15:57, 26 October 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:His conclusions yes, but not about Zyklon B.  [[User:Dbrodbeck|Dbrodbeck]] ([[User talk:Dbrodbeck|talk]]) 16:27, 26 October 2015 (UTC)
:I think Goldhagen is an okay source for certain types of content. Regardless, the content is also supported by Longerich 2010, pp.281-282, so I have removed Goldhagen. --[[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 20:20, 26 October 2015 (UTC)

== Poorly written ==

The first three paragraphs of this article is full of grammatical errors such as this following line:

&quot;It consisted of hydrogen cyanide (prussic acid), a warning eye irritant, and one of several adsorbents such as diatomaceous earth.&quot;

This would be better written as:

&quot;It consisted of hydrogen cyanide (prussic acid), an eye irritant warning, and one of several adsorbents such as diatomaceous earth.&quot;

as the first way doesn't make syntactical sense.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Technomagesty|Technomagesty]] ([[User talk:Technomagesty|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Technomagesty|contribs]]) 15:56, 25 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Sorry I don't agree with you; &quot;warning&quot; is being used as an adjective. Perhaps &quot;cautionary&quot; would be better, as it actually ''is'' an adjective. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 16:40, 25 March 2016 (UTC)
::It's a warning like the smell they add to natural gas, not sure of the details but if you smell natural gas, it's a significant warning, [http://www.nizkor.org/ftp.cgi/camps/auschwitz/cyanide/cyanide.001 here's a ref]. [[User:Raquel Baranow|Raquel Baranow]] ([[User talk:Raquel Baranow|talk]]) 22:22, 25 March 2016 (UTC)

I don't think you understand &quot;a warning eye irritant&quot; makes no sense juxtapose to the preceding part of the sentence as what the sentence is now referring to would be a label on the canister to warn that it's an eye irritant. The sentence is poorly written.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Technomagesty|Technomagesty]] ([[User talk:Technomagesty|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Technomagesty|contribs]]) 15:17, 26 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I as a native English speaker and reader had to go over that sentence a few times to make any sense of it. Please reedit it. There are a few other articles that I've seen similar issues with, imagine if you didn't speak English as a first language and had this to try and translate, something that doesn't even make sense to someone that speaks the language, it's a disgrace.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Technomagesty|Technomagesty]] ([[User talk:Technomagesty|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Technomagesty|contribs]]) 18:11, 26 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Here's exactly what it is: &quot;ethyl bromacetate, a [[lachrymatory]] irritant with a pungent fruity smell that warned people of the presence of the toxic cyanide&quot; [https://books.google.com/books?id=2TRoBAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PA178&amp;ots=X4poEJoR1b&amp;dq=zyklon%20b%20irritant%20warning&amp;pg=PA178#v=onepage&amp;q=zyklon%20b%20irritant%20warning&amp;f=false reference] [[User:Raquel Baranow|Raquel Baranow]] ([[User talk:Raquel Baranow|talk]]) 20:44, 26 March 2016 (UTC)
:The article already specifies that the cautionary irritants used were [[chloropicrin]] and [[cyanogen chloride]]. Source: Christianson 2010, page 95. I already yesterday changed the prose from &quot; warning eye irritant&quot; to &quot;cautionary eye irritant&quot;. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 23:27, 26 March 2016 (UTC)

I still don't think you understand. There have been several things mentioned here first it has been mentioned that it is an eye irritant, the next thing that has been suggested that it's an olfactory warning both have been suggested because the original article is so badly written that you are trying to cover for yourselves in regards to the poor quality.

If it had been written correctly either one of those two things (preferably the actual one if any) would have been mentioned in the sentence instead of the vague language used in the original article.

As of date the article now says this &quot;developed a method of packaging hydrogen cyanide in sealed canisters along with a cautionary irritant and adsorbent stabilizers.&quot;

Which is better but also vague in wording as it doesn't mention the nature of the &quot;cautionary irritant&quot; which I've discovered here in talk might be an eye irritant or an olfactory one but apparently no one knows. Sad.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Technomagesty|Technomagesty]] ([[User talk:Technomagesty|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Technomagesty|contribs]]) 15:39, 27 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The sources I used say it was an eye irritant, so I am going to amend again to include that. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 17:54, 27 March 2016 (UTC)

Oh you're going to use sources now? Wow I do applaud you.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Technomagesty|Technomagesty]] ([[User talk:Technomagesty|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Technomagesty|contribs]]) 18:41, 27 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Also prussic acid isn't an irritant it's hydrogen cyanide.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Technomagesty|Technomagesty]] ([[User talk:Technomagesty|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Technomagesty|contribs]]) 18:46, 27 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Technomagesty, you might consider cutting back on the sarcasm.  The current edit does not say that the prussic acid was the irritant.  [[User:Dbrodbeck|Dbrodbeck]] ([[User talk:Dbrodbeck|talk]]) 20:08, 27 March 2016 (UTC)

== &quot;disinfect&quot; vs &quot;disinfest&quot; ==

Zyklon B is not a disinfectant and has no disinfecting properties.

The German wartime guidelines and procedure for using Zyklon B was a 2-page double sided document given the document title &quot;NI-9912&quot; in the postwar Nuremberg Trials.  During the war these guidelines and procedures were mass printed and sent throughout German and German occupied territories for them to use for Zyklon fumigations.

There are plenty of copies to google around for;  but this one webpage on Robert Faurisson's blog has both the German copy of the 4 pages and a very good English translation in 6 pages:

http://robertfaurisson.blogspot.com/2015/07/a-document-among-others-stating.html

At the very end of the first section it clearly states:

&quot;Bakterian werden durch Blausäure nicht vernichtet&quot;

or in English:

&quot;Prussic acid does not kill bacteria&quot;

Hydrogen cyanide is not a disinfectant and has never been used as a disinfectant because it is useless as a disinfectant.

I am therefore replacing all instances of &quot;disinfect&quot; with &quot;disinfest&quot; in this wikipedia page.

While it is true that there are many persons incorrectly claiming that Zyklon is a disinfectant;  they are all wrong and are quite confused on this matter.  The &quot;disinfecting department&quot; handled delousing in wartime Germany - delousing is NOT &quot;disinfecting&quot; though - and this is probably why so many people incorrectly use the term &quot;disinfect&quot;.  It is categorically undeniably incorrect though because neither hydrocyanic acid (liquid) nor hydrogen cyanide gas has any effect on germs (nor cyanide salts for that matter - that handles liquid, gas, and solid ;) ).  I have little doubt that the instances of the word &quot;disinfect&quot; in this article are mistranslations of the German word for disinfest.

I am unable to edit the head portion which states:

&quot;Uses included delousing clothing and disinfecting ships, warehouses, and trains&quot;

&quot;Disinfecting&quot; things would mean scrubbing them with bleach or Lysol or something.  Zyklon is a substrate with HCN adsorbed on to it that evaporates off in use - fumigating the area around it with HCN.  The HCN has no effect on microorganisms but is very toxic to larger organisms like lice, rats, people, etc.  Someone needs to change this instance of &quot;disinfecting&quot; above with &quot;disinfesting&quot;.  Zyklon is of course a pesticide - not a disinfectant.

EDIT:  I figured out how to edit that section.

&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.64.79.161|173.64.79.161]] ([[User talk:173.64.79.161#top|talk]]) 06:41, 7 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Thank you for fixing this. Sometimes one is so focused on certain aspects of an article that mistakes like that one become effectively invisible. Incidentally, if you [[WP:REGISTER|create an account]], you can set your preferences so that a first-paragraph Edit link is displayed. [[User:Rivertorch&amp;#39;s Evil Twin|Rivertorch&amp;#39;s Evil Twin]] ([[User talk:Rivertorch&amp;#39;s Evil Twin|talk]]) 15:24, 7 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rv29rqnlji52u2yr6bc8hngrwtkabtp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
