<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Spanish coup of July 1936</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>31807545</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730278855</id>
      <parentid>684134264</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-18T00:03:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2016-07-17.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4206">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=22:05, 17 September 2011
|action1link=Talk:Spanish coup of July 1936/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=450421343

|action2=PR
|action2date=17:50, 7 November 2011
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Spanish coup of July 1936/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=459287445

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War
}}
{{WikiProject Spain|class=GA|importance=low}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|b1=yes|b2=yes|b3=yes|b4=yes|b5=yes|Spanish=yes}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2011-07-17|oldid1=439969403|date2=2013-07-17|oldid2=564671323|date3=2016-07-17|oldid3=730194649}}

== Pre-GAN comments ==

Taking a look at this now, since I've been meaning to have an excuse to take &quot;The Battle for Spain&quot; off my bookshelf and actually read it.  Nice job, FWIW, especially on the referencing.  One thing that jumps out at me immediately, though: the lede needs some serious work.  Maybe not a huge concern for GAN vs. FAC, but it reads kind of incoherently at the moment - things are happening!  This person did something!  This other thing happened!  The lede is the only section that many viewers will read, and it should strive to &quot;tell a story,&quot; even if it leaves out side facts.  It's not really well connected at the moment.  The third &amp; fourth paragraphs mention a lot of specific names being arrested, or surrendering, or plotting, who then aren't mentioned again in the lede.  I'd be in favor of cutting out as much of these details as practicable, and focusing on just a few key movers &amp; shakers.

A few other notes before doing a proper review:
* It'd probably be fair to mention abortive leftist murmuring about a coup of their own during the 34-36 period.

* &quot;The Falange expanded massively&quot; - I see this is referenced to Preston.  Does he go into more detail about what exactly this means?  I see from your other election articles that the Falange was pretty much a non-player electorally, getting 1 deputy or so...  was this a recruitment drive?  Sudden outpouring of pro-Falange feeling and &quot;conversions?&quot;  Just mobilizing supporters they already had?

* Would you mind if I referenced the bit about tenuous Republic control of areas with armed anarchist militas to someone other than Chomsky?  An uncontroversial fact that could be ref'd from several sources, and I think it'd be better to avoid a politicized and somewhat unreliable Chomsky.

* The ending is very abrupt at the moment - talking about lack of officers for the Republican fleet and airplanes.  Not sure if there really is a good ending point, but I think there should be something better than that? [[User:SnowFire|SnowFire]] ([[User talk:SnowFire|talk]]) 01:21, 12 September 2011 (UTC)
:Thanks you for your comments. I looked over your changes to the lead and made one slight revert. With regards to the other things, the naming of important people in the lead would depend on what summary you're providing. This page doesn't get many readers, so my assumption is that they're interested in the civil war as a whole. As such, the character narratives are important enough to warrant inclusion, since they're mentioned in the background, again here and then later on in the war.
:The Asturias rising of 1934 is probably the leftist attempt most worth mentioning - I've found a link for it, since it was briefly mentioned. However the actual relavance to the coup of 1936 is really only tangential. The [[background of the Spanish Civil War]] probably does a better overview of opposition from both sides, I figured a focus on the right's opposition more relevant here.
:I'll clarify the Falange bit and I've written out Chomsky. The ending, well, I don't know, not sure what else to do. &lt;span style=&quot;color:#3A3A3A&quot;&gt;'''Grandiose''' &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray&quot;&gt;([[User:Grandiose|me]], [[User_talk:Grandiose|talk]], [[Special:Contributions/Grandiose|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt; 10:12, 12 September 2011 (UTC)

== How and why did the war end? ==
A summary or conclusion as to how and why the war ended seems to be missing? Can someone explain either the omission or the end of the war? - preferably both. [[Special:Contributions/99.4.120.135|99.4.120.135]] ([[User talk:99.4.120.135|talk]]) 20:14, 4 October 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>784x807e2lrxtmp7qjfs1cvw3rgh6q6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
