<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Non-intervention in the Spanish Civil War</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>31826420</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521701763</id>
      <parentid>521701576</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T18:09:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sayerslle</username>
        <id>8624548</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6521">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=03:10, 20 June 2011
|action1link=Talk:Non-intervention in the Spanish Civil War/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=434914855
|dykdate=5 June 2011
|dykentry=... that [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]] suggested the '''[[Non-intervention in the Spanish Civil War|Non-Intervention Committee]]''' might as well have been called the &quot;Intervention Committee&quot;?
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War and military
}}
{{WikiProject Spain|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|importance=|Spanish=yes}}

==Boldface==
The relevant section in [[Wikipedia:BOLDFACE]] is &quot;If, however, a term is strictly synonymous with the subject of the article, then bold face should be used in place of italics.&quot; Combined with the reasons given in my edit summary, I think that is sufficient to justify boldface in this instance. '''Grandiose''' &lt;span style=&quot;color:gray&quot;&gt;([[User:Grandiose|me]], [[User_talk:Grandiose|talk]], [[Special:Contributions/Grandiose|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt; 08:55, 4 June 2011 (UTC)

== Thoughts for improvement ==

I'll try to review it for GA properly within a few days. Few early thoughts: 1) more images can be added 2) note 1 should have an English red-link, which would achieve the purpose behind [[WP:RED]] and be meaningful to the reader 3) the structure is a bit unclear, mixing structure and history. I'd suggest restructuring around a history section 4) I think that the Agreement and Committee are notable in itself, and should be redlinked instead of bolded. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; talk &lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 00:12, 12 June 2011 (UTC)
:*I couldn't think of any images. There are people mentioned in the article, but I did wonder whether this is that relevant to the international diplomacy they are discussing. (I specifically had a look for pictures of any of them meeting each other, more or less without success  - there are one or two German ones, but Hitler features in the, which I thought was rather unnecessary).
::I've added the portraits of Chamberlain and Blum; both heavily associated with non-intervention and both one-time leaders of their countries, makes the most sense to pick them out. &lt;span style=&quot;color:#3A3A3A&quot;&gt;'''Grandiose''' &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray&quot;&gt;([[User:Grandiose|me]], [[User_talk:Grandiose|talk]], [[Special:Contributions/Grandiose|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt; 16:43, 12 June 2011 (UTC)
:*&quot;Armindo Monteiro&quot; is red-linked in the main text, I'm not quite sure what you mean.
:*Structure/history: the article in its entirety follows a more or less chronology. (Whilst I can see the subtitle &quot;Control plan&quot; might hint at a non-chronological section, it doesn't. It needed breaking up &amp;ndash; it's sort of &quot;This bit of time when they were mostly discussing the control plan&quot;.) I'd welcome your further thoughts.
:*This a bit of a special situation. &quot;[[Non-Intervention Agreement]]&quot; and &quot;[[Non-Intervention Committee]]&quot; redirect to sections on this page, as a stand in for the more extensive articles which haven't been written yet. I think it's too early to spin them off (with &quot;main&quot; links, for example) as they'd end up being mostly duplicates of each other - the two things don't really exist outside the framework. It's convenient, at the moment, to have them both here (whilst they are not reams long). But it is, in essence, the redirects that would be annoying, particularly since most actually relate to non-intervention in general, despite one of the two terms being linked (this page was at &quot;Non-Intervention Committee&quot; before I expanded it). &lt;span style=&quot;color:#3A3A3A&quot;&gt;'''Grandiose''' &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray&quot;&gt;([[User:Grandiose|me]], [[User_talk:Grandiose|talk]], [[Special:Contributions/Grandiose|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt; 09:39, 12 June 2011 (UTC)

{{Talk:Non-intervention in the Spanish Civil War/GA1}}

==Lead==
I have removed two sentences from the lead, for different reasons.

*{{xt|A resolution approved  at the XXXII [[Universal Peace Congress]] noted: &quot;Congress considers that a policy of non-intervention, or of abstention, is shown to be insufficient in principle and in practice dangerous, for it paralyses those states which obey it and becomes advantageous to those which violate it.&quot;[ref]}}
**Uncontextualised. Often quoted on a single side of the debate but here presented without any additional information. Sticks out to the reader and is overweighted, in so far as we don't discuss it in the article (I wouldn't be opposed to doing that).
*{{xt|In effect the policy denied Western arms only to the Republicans because Franco was able to obtain whatever arms he needed from Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy and the British and French Governments appeared determined ''not'' to support any Left-wing Spanish Government against European fascism.}}
**Some innaccuracies here, mostly as a result of not being able to discuss each side of the argument in such a small space. Franco most certainly did not get &quot;whatever arms he needed&quot; from the Germans or Italians. He got a fraction of it, some late, some different. &quot;British and French Governments appeared determined&quot;: the positions of both governments were complicated. In the case of the French, there was considerable assistance to the Republicans. Also, why &quot;Western&quot;? The Soviet Union signed the declaration as well and its position ought to be considered, as it is in the main article. Overall it fails to accurately summarise the article.
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#3A3A3A;background-color:#FFFFFF&quot;&gt;'''Grandiose''' &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray;background-color:#FFFFFF&quot;&gt;([[User:Grandiose|me]], [[User_talk:Grandiose|talk]], [[Special:Contributions/Grandiose|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt; 16:25, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
::if the french provided 'considerable assistance  to the Republicans' - i don't see that set out in the lead. it says 'occasionally so'.  Spain is in western Europe - why were  Western arms denied basically only  to the Republicans? - this question is fundamental - the Soviet Union, faraway, 'helped' the Republicans to a lesser extent than Hitler and Mussolini who openly supported their fellow fascist -&lt;span style=&quot;color:#CC3300;background-color:#FFFFFF&quot;&gt; ''it was partly the' '''hypocritical unfairness of 'Non-Intervention' ''' that led to some growing intellectual anti-Fascist protests in the West'''(Tosco Fyvel) . [[User:Sayerslle|Sayerslle]] ([[User talk:Sayerslle|talk]]) 17:19, 6 November 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>5ydh66uo9nutfufa63h8zcuwywjkyix</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
