<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Schutzstaffel</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>73130</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750112855</id>
      <parentid>750109288</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-17T22:04:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kierzek</username>
        <id>9088688</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* South Park season 20 episode 8 */ rv - talk page not for general discussion and inappurtenant to article</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19678">{{article history
|action1=FAC
|action1result=not promoted
|action1date=2005-04-02, 17:00:07
|action1oldid=11907039
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Schutzstaffel/archive1
| action2       = GAN
| action2date   = 19:01, April 14, 2016(UTC)
| action2link   = Talk:Schutzstaffel/GA1
| action2result = listed
| action2oldid  = 715270095
| currentstatus = GA
| topic         = World history
}}

{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1=
{{WikiProject Military history
|class=GA
|German-task-force=yes
|European-task-force=yes
|WWII-task-force=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Politics |class=GA|importance=High|fascism=yes}}
{{WikiProject Organizations|class=GA|importance=}}
}}

{{Old moves
| list =
* RM, SS → Schutzstaffel, '''Moved''', 5 Nov 2004, [[Talk:Schutzstaffel/Archive 1#Page move Nov 2004]]
* RM, Schutzstaffel → SS, '''Not moved''', 7 September 2005, [[Talk:Schutzstaffel/Archive 2#Requested move]]
* RM, Schutzstaffel → SS (Nazi Germany), '''Not moved''', 5 June 2015, [[Talk:Schutzstaffel/Archive 5#Requested move 5 June 2015]]
}}
{{archive box|auto=yes|bot=MiszaBot I|age=90}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav|noredlinks=y}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 7
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Schutzstaffel/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== Parking spot: Latvian Legion ==

I believe this is pertinent, as Waffen-SS was the only SS branch that strove for recognition and rehabilitation in the post-war decades. The [[Latvian Legion Day]] is part of that movement. It may be combined with some of the [[HIAG]] content along these lines. I will propose a version on this Talk page.

*On 21 February 2012, The [[Council of Europe]]’s Commission against Racism and Intolerance published its report on [[Latvia]] (fourth monitoring cycle), in which it condemned [[Latvian Legion Day]] which commemorates persons who had fought in a [[Latvian Legion|Latvian unit of the Waffen-SS]] and takes place every year on 16 March. It is held in the centre of Riga. Within that report is the following statement which applies universally concerning the Waffen-SS, &quot;All attempts to commemorate persons who fought in the Waffen-SS and collaborated with the Nazis, should be condemned. Any gathering or march legitimising Nazism in any way should be banned.&quot;{{sfn|Council of Europe (ECRI)|2012|p=9}}

{{reflist-talk}}

[[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 21:00, 19 March 2016 (UTC)
:It can be added to the Waffen-SS article page. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 21:02, 19 March 2016 (UTC)
:I think placing it on the Waffen-SS page is a good suggestion. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 21:42, 19 March 2016 (UTC) Adding rationale for removal: It's slightly off-topic for this article (see GA criterion 3b). Current word count (without this material) is 11419 words, which I think we can justify given the importance of the topic. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 21:54, 19 March 2016 (UTC)
*I think it belongs in this article, but as a couple of sentences. I note that the section &quot;links to contemporary movements&quot; was removed because it did not relate specifically to the SS. However, here we have an SS legion honored, so it is directly relevant. Also I note the absence of a Legacy section that belongs in the article. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 15:39, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
* I looked through the 10 books I have here that I used in conjunction with my recent copy edits, and did not find any material that was suitable for constructing a Legacy section. Thinking some more about the Latvian Legion material, I think another good reason to omit it is because it would be kinda just tacked on there at the end on its own, which would give this one event undue weight. Why is it important enough to be included? is the question our GA reviewer will ask. Why so important, especially when we are still over the suggested 10,000 word limit for page size. I think it could be placed in the Waffen-SS article. There's already extensive coverage in the Latvian Legion article. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 19:21, 20 March 2016 (UTC)

:*&quot;Legacy&quot; sections are common in far less consequential articles. I see them often in Wikipedia articles about movies and minor historical figures, and I doubt very much that you find many source materials with separate &quot;legacy&quot; chapters. I don't think it's a leap to include one here. Just because ten books don't have legacy sections doesn't mean that we should not have such an obvious section. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 19:30, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
::*You are of course welcome to search for sources and create the section yourself. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 20:17, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
:::*I agree with you that the Latvian legion aspect, alone, is not enough to sustain a legacy or similar section. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 20:31, 20 March 2016 (UTC)

== Image ==

I commented out the image of &quot;demonstates the ovens...&quot; -- it's a staged photo and I also find it problematic as it could be interpreted as &quot;blaming the victims&quot; (members of the Sonderkommandos). If an image of the ovens / crematoria is needed, a free/properly licensed image is available on Commons: [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Fotothek_df_pk_0000125_003.jpg Majdanek]. 

Feedback/suggestions? [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 19:02, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
:I suggest the featured picture, [[:File:Crematorium at Auschwitz I 2012.jpg]]. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 19:10, 20 March 2016 (UTC)

::Yes, that's a good one.  [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 19:18, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
:::I have changed the image. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 20:13, 20 March 2016 (UTC)

*Just noticed this. Sorry but I strongly disagree with substituting [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Bundesarchiv_Bild_183-H26996,_KZ_Dachau,_Verbrennungsofen.jpg the preexisting photo] with [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Crematorium_at_Auschwitz_I_2012.jpg a museum photo]. First I have to say that I couldn't disagree more that the presence of a Sonderkommando in any way &quot;blames the victim.&quot; I've seen that photo for years and the thought never crossed my mind. I don't think most people would feel that way unless they are utter fools. It is well-known that prisoners were forced to engage in the concentration camp/extermination machinery. The old photo shows how the actual cremation was done. The new photo is excessively sanitized and is not as informative as the previous one.
:Re &quot;staged.&quot; Come on. Is a museum photo from seventy years later any less artificial? I think it's fine as long as we state that yes, this a prisoner demonstrating the process. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 13:29, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
::I also do not believe this photo &quot;blames the victim&quot;; it instead shows the horror of the situation as &quot;demonstrated&quot;. I agree with Coretheapple as to this photo; with that said, as to the replacement, I don't have a problem with that one being used where appropriate, in addition. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 13:37, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
:::In addition - yes, of course. But not as a replacement. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 13:42, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
::::I would suggest: &quot;Demonstration photo by former prisoners at the Crematorium in Dachau concentration camp.&quot; The word, Sonderkommandos, does not need to be used. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 13:47, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
:::::Of course the photo was staged; most photos were, as film and processing were both very expensive. I don't agree that the image blames the victims though. I have no objection to its use on that basis and am putting it back, since two people object to its removal and I have no strong preference either way. For a caption, i have used &quot;Former prisoner at Dachau concentration camp poses at the camp crematorium, May 1945&quot; to start with. — [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 14:12, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
::::::Thanks for that. I actually wonder whether that really was a sonderkommando. Virtually all were liquidated, and this was Dachau, not a death camp. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 14:50, 21 March 2016 (UTC)

{{od}} Let me preface that the image is okay with the image after the caption has been adjusted. 

Re: &quot;blame the victim&quot; narrative, it most definitely exists. The Nazi origins of it are evidenced in Rudolf Hoess's memoirs, where he wrote that he &quot;could not understand how the Sonderkommandos could kill their own kind&quot; (or something to this effect). 

Most recently, I came across this notion while watching the Cannes press conference on ''[[Son of Saul]]'' movie. One of the journalists started asking a question of the director on (IIRC) whether it was difficult to find funding for a movie that treated a &quot;controversial subject dealing with half-killers and half-victims&quot;. At that point, the actor who played Saul interrupted the journalist and delivered a passionate statement that you can see in this 1-min clip. It got quite heated for a while: [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eMddYZSlxGk Cannes presents: Hungarian director Nemes' ''Son of Saul'']. 

Hope this clarifies! [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 04:21, 22 March 2016 (UTC)

:Well it is sad that people feel that way. There's certainly no accounting for idiots. Incidentally to change the subject somewhat, re the Legacy section, I recall a book that came out in the late 1950s called ''Schizophrenic Germany'', by a Newsweek correspondent, that might be useful. I used to have a copy but can't find it. I recall there's much on the aftermath of the SS. The author was John Dornberg. I imagine &quot;aftermath&quot; genre books like that would be helpful. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 05:05, 22 March 2016 (UTC)
::No one doubts that it exists; it happens in court cases. The point was we were focused only on this photo. Which is discussed above. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 10:54, 22 March 2016 (UTC)

:::The photo appears to be in the wrong section, as Dachau was technically not a &quot;death camp&quot;. In the context of this section, the Majdanek photo I linked to earlier may be more appropriate, as it was both a labor camp and an extermination camp. I believe Majdanek was the only extermination camp that fell into the Allied hands somewhat intact, with the evidence of the mass exterminations present; the rest were raised to the ground (i.e. Treblinka) or largely destroyed (Auschwitz). 

:::As a side note, the accounts from Majdanek appeared so outlandish, that the BBC initially refused to run an article filed by the British war correspondent [[Alexander Werth]]. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 15:28, 22 March 2016 (UTC)

::::That's a good point about the photo's location. I moved it to the section where Dachau is discussed. We can have one of the other crematorium photos in its place in the death camp section. I have no preference among the two offered. I think both would work. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 16:12, 22 March 2016 (UTC)

== SS offices: naming / moves ==

I have moved ''SS-Wirtschafts-Verwaltungshauptamt'' to [[SS Main Economic and Administrative Office]]. 

I also proposed moves for [[SS Führungshauptamt]] and [[Hauptamt SS-Gericht]]. Additional suitable move suggestions for the offices that appear in [[Schutzstaffel#SS_offices]] would be welcome. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 20:59, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
: I DON'T agree with them all being changed to &quot;English translations&quot;: such as Einsatzgruppen, Ordnungspolizei, Sicherheitsdienst, Allgemeine SS, SS-Verfügungstruppe, SS-Totenkopfverbände, Kriminalpolizei, Sicherheitspolizei; but with that said, others such as: SS-Wirtschafts-Verwaltungshauptamt, and Persönlicher Stab Reichsführer-SS, are two I do agree with changing out. &lt;s&gt;SS Führungshauptamt and Hauptamt SS-Gericht, I would like more feedback on as I consider them.&lt;s&gt; I have thought about them and I can agree to them. SS Leadership Main Office for the first and the second one: Main SS Legal Office or SS Court Main Office (this second one being used more widely). [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 22:35, 20 March 2016 (UTC)

::I did not mean to suggest that all should be changed. Einsatzgruppen is widely used in English-language literature, for example. The rest I'm not that well versed on, so I was asking for feedback. The SS terminology was so complex and arcane, that the more we can simplify for the reader (in agreement with mainstream historiography) the better. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 22:52, 20 March 2016 (UTC)
:::I added a note on the [[Talk:Persönlicher_Stab_Reichsführer-SS|Persönlicher Stab Reichsführer-SS Talk page]] about the proposed move. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 01:39, 21 March 2016 (UTC)
::::Good. I moved today, the article and talk page since there was no objection noted. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 13:31, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
:::::I don't personally object to the move but I think any such move should have gone through the proper channels through [[Wikipedia:Requested moves/Controversial]] to allow for a larger input of other contributors in the discussion. [[User:Calistemon|Calistemon]] ([[User talk:Calistemon|talk]]) 21:30, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
::::::That only if it is controversial/contested, which Persönlicher Stab Reichsführer-SS, above was not. The regular editors herein and the people who watchlist this page and that particular page were all made aware. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 22:17, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
:::::::A discussion about the move was started, therefore the move was seen as at least potentially controversial, therefore the proper procedure as per [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] should have been followed. If the move was uncontroversial no discussion was needed in the first place and the page could have been moved straight away. [[User:Calistemon|Calistemon]] ([[User talk:Calistemon|talk]]) 23:37, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
::::::::That was probably due to my unfamiliarity with the process. sorry! I think I was trying to gauge whether or not the moves would be considered controversial. It appeared that they were not. 
::::::::What about the other two? Should they go through the move noticeboard?  [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 01:44, 24 March 2016 (UTC)
{{od}}
I think you can't go wrong doing things by the book and using the proper process. It will add an extra week to the process but it may get greater amount of input because it will get listed at [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] and, hopefully, get a clear consensus. [[User:Calistemon|Calistemon]] ([[User talk:Calistemon|talk]]) 02:14, 24 March 2016 (UTC)
:Sounds good, I will do it for the other two. There's no rush. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 02:45, 24 March 2016 (UTC)
::What was the outcome, if any, for the two: SS Führungshauptamt and Hauptamt SS-Gericht? I checked the &quot;Requested moves&quot; page but did not see it (unless I missed it). Cheers, [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 21:47, 14 April 2016 (UTC)
:::I'm sorry, I got distracted. If you are willing to request these moves, that would be great. If not, I will get to them eventually :-) . [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 01:24, 15 April 2016 (UTC)
::::No problem, it can wait. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 03:46, 15 April 2016 (UTC)
{{od}}
Finally got around to this; it was not as complicated as I had thought. I've proposed the moves for the following articles:

*''[[SS-Hauptamt]]'' 
*''[[SS Führungshauptamt|SS-Führungshauptamt]]''
*''[[Hauptamt SS-Gericht]]''
*''[[SS Personalhauptamt|SS-Personalhauptamt]]''

Please feel free to comment on the respective Talk pages. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 04:56, 12 June 2016 (UTC)

== Origin of the name ==

The term ''Schutzstaffel'', short ''Schusta'', was already in use during the First World War. It was than used for squadrons of escort fighter planes. German Jewish fighter ace [[Fritz Beckhardt]] for example served in ''Schutzstaffel 11'' before transferring to Göring's unit. In a non-reliable source I recently read that Göring misappropriated the name for the future SS. Trying to find anything on this naming connection to the original First World War ''Schutzstaffel'' is difficult as everything is of course overshadowed by the latter use. Has anybody come across some information in any reliable source confirming this or is it just a myth? [[User:Calistemon|Calistemon]] ([[User talk:Calistemon|talk]]) 10:20, 21 March 2016 (UTC)

:I actually don't think this should even be the name of the article, given that SS is far and away the most common usage. [[User:Coretheapple|Coretheapple]] ([[User talk:Coretheapple|talk]]) 14:06, 15 April 2016 (UTC)

== Further reading ==

I removed the following books which appear to be from non-scholarly authors and publishers:

*{{cite book | last = Blandford | first = Edmund L. | title = SS Intelligence: The Nazi Secret Service | publisher = Castle | location = Edison, NJ | year = 2001 | isbn = 978-0-78581-398-9 }}
*{{cite book | last = Cawthorne | first = Nigel | authorlink = Nigel Cawthorne | title = The Story of the SS: Hitler's Infamous Legions of Death | publisher = Arcturus | location = London | year = 2012 | isbn = 978-0-7858-2714-6 }}
* {{cite book | last = Williamson | first = Gordon | authorlink = Gordon Williamson (writer) | title = The SS: Hitler's Instrument of Terror: The Full Story from Street Fighters to the Waffen-SS | year = 1994 | publisher = Motorbooks International | location = Osceola, WI | isbn = 978-0-87938-905-5}}
* {{cite book | last = Miller | first = Michael | year = 2015 | title = Leaders of the SS and German Police, Vol. 2 | publisher = Bender | location = San Jose, CA | isbn = 978-19-329-7025-8}}
* {{cite book | last = Hatheway | first = Jay | title = In Perfect Formation: SS Ideology and the SS-Junkerschule-Tölz | year = 1999 | publisher = Schiffer Military History | location = Atglen, PA | isbn = 978-0-76430-753-9}}

Williamson is discussed in HIAG. Schiffer is one the small time presses that publishes various Waffen-SS guru authors and translations of HIAG's authors. The article on Cawthorne presents him as sketchy. The other two entries did not inspire confidence either. Please let me know if we need to discuss. [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 19:11, 26 March 2016 (UTC)
:I cannot agree as to Miller and am re-adding. His first volume is an accepted RS source used in the article, already. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 20:53, 26 March 2016 (UTC)

::Sounds good; thank you for re-adding.  [[User:K.e.coffman|K.e.coffman]] ([[User talk:K.e.coffman|talk]]) 01:51, 27 March 2016 (UTC)

{{Talk:Schutzstaffel/GA1}}</text>
      <sha1>t98l8260h3tv3hb7116f5neobuodluq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
