<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Invasion of Isle de France</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20962079</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745667935</id>
      <parentid>635786477</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-22T15:29:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wizardman</username>
        <id>713860</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */Project cleanup, replaced: {{WikiProject Mauritius → {{WikiProject Africa|Mauritius=yes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5564">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=01:10, 10 January 2009
|action1link=Talk:Invasion of Île de France/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=263087954

|action2=GTC
|action2date=19:30, 28 February 2009
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Mauritius campaign of 1809–1811
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=265803909

|ftname=Mauritius campaign of 1809–1811
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=war
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|British=y|Napoleonic=y|French=y|Maritime=y}}
{{WikiProject UK|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject France|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Africa|Mauritius=yes|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject British Empire}}
}}
{{todo}}

== Cornwallis conflicts  ==

The orders of battle on this article have Cornwallis as 44 gun 5th rate with Captain James Caufield, while [[HMS Cornwallis (1805)]] has 54 gun 4th rate with Captain William Fisher. Can someone please check this out from sources, to which I have no ready access. Perhaps only a dyslexic typo. Thanks, [[User:Benyoch|Benyoch]] ([[User talk:Benyoch|talk]]) 17:08, 30 March 2012 (UTC)

:It's not a typo, the sources used do say 44 guns and under Caulfield. Fisher was not actually a post-captain, and so able to take command of a post-ship like Cornwallis except in acting capacity. Caulfield however was. He appears to have taken over from Montague and commanded the ship during the campaign. Fisher superseded him on 10 December, after the end of the campaign, and with orders to take the ship to Madras carrying troops that had been involved in the successful expedition (Fisher had previously commanded the Racehorse between 1809-10, employed in surveying in the Mozambique). So it is accurate here to say Caulfield was in command. As to the guns and rating, Akbar (as she was then) was not surveyed and registered until her arrival in Britain in July 1812. She appears on an order of battle for the East Indies station in June 1809 as an 38-gun 18-pdr ship. This doubtless a hold over from her days as a East India Company cruiser. She was officially rated as a 50-gun fourth rate only in 1813, when her full armament of 30 24-pdrs on the maindeck, and 26 42-pdr carronades on her spar deck were fitted. (You will note that despite this amounting to 56 guns she was rated as a 50-gun ship, a quirk of the RN's system at the time). 44 guns is therefore not improbable for the Cornwallis at the time of the invasion, and is made even more likely that if she was carrying troops, her armament may have been reduced to fit them and their stores. Both articles are therefore correct, the Cornwallis article is merely slightly incomplete. [[User:Benea|Benea]] ([[User talk:Benea|talk]]) 01:49, 31 March 2012 (UTC)

::Thanks Benea, I understand how the senario works (I take it you meant Fisher was not actually a post-captain, and so NOT able ... ). It will be good to see what the views of others are, too; certainly your assessment seems plausible and quite probable on the face of it.
 
::On giving some thought ''Akbar'' here, and the talk on [[Talk:HMS Cornwallis (1805)|''Cornwallis'']] naming, I am suspicious that there was another ''Akbar'' prior to and apart from ''Cornwallis'' being re-named ''HMS Akbar''. Can this be entertained for the sake of research, and looked into? I have no source resources to do so. 

::BTW, is there any capacity on WP for hidden, non-public peer-to-peer messaging? [[User:Benyoch|Benyoch]] ([[User talk:Benyoch|talk]]) 10:10, 31 March 2012 (UTC)

:::It's not so much my view as what is in the sources. The removal of guns for her trooping role is my supposition, all the rest you can find in books on the topic. A previous Akbar, possibly to have been built along the lines of the Vengeur class design, was laid down on 4 April 1807 at Prince of Wales Island, Penang. The shipyard collapsed two years later from a lack of resources and manpower, resulting in the cancellation of the putative Akbar on 12 October 1809. No other ship, projected or otherwise, had been named Akbar prior to Cornwallis/Akbar (you can find this in the comprehensive listings of both volumes of Colledge's ''Ships of the Royal Navy'' and the relevant volumes of Winfield's ''British Warships in the Age of Sail''). As to your final query, [[WP:EMAIL]] has information of relevance. [[User:Benea|Benea]] ([[User talk:Benea|talk]]) 16:15, 31 March 2012 (UTC)

== Aftermath - Governor Robert Townsend Farquhar of Île Bourbon ==

A notice appears in the London Gazette, dated March 2, 1811, &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/16459/pages/381], ''[[London Gazette]]'', Number 16459, p391&lt;/ref&gt; for the official appointment of Robert Townsend Farquhar as Governor of the Islands of Mauritius and Bourbon and their dependencies. [[User:Leboite|Leboite]] ([[User talk:Leboite|talk]]) 01:08, 9 September 2012 (UTC)

:If Farquhar was appointed in March 1810 then it was not part of the 'aftermath' of the [[Mauritius campaign of 1809–1811]], including the invasion of Ile de France in late Nov 1810. A ceasefire was agreed early Dec 1810. So whay was Farquhar appointes so early -- in anticipation? Leboite, is the 1810 date correct? [[User:Benyoch|Benyoch&lt;sup&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp;...Don't&amp;nbsp;panic!&amp;nbsp;Don't&amp;nbsp;panic!...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]] ([[User talk:Benyoch|talk]])  06:22, 9 September 2012 (UTC)

:My bad. The notice was dated March 2, 1811.  I have corrected my original talk entry, above. [[User:Leboite|Leboite]] ([[User talk:Leboite|talk]]) 15:11, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}</text>
      <sha1>6hd8m9i28wc9avvwrv57vn7nd26vjqc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
