<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:HMS Barham (04)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6094150</id>
    <revision>
      <id>698822245</id>
      <parentid>698689176</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-08T13:08:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jaguar</username>
        <id>9913007</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>GA</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7861">{{GA|13:08, 8 January 2016 (UTC)|page=1|topic=Warfare|oldid=698811882}}
{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Ships|class=GA|B1=yes|B2=yes|B3=yes|B4=yes|B5=yes}}
{{WikiProject Military history
|class=GA
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes
|British-task-force=yes|Maritime-task-force=yes|WWI-task-force=yes|WWII-task-force=yes|OMT=1}}
{{WikiProject Shipwrecks|importance=|class=GA}}
}}

==Untitled==
&quot;U-331 returned to Salamis on 3 December, where her commander von Tiesenhausen was subsequently promoted to Kapitänleutnant and awarded the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross.&quot; for the sinking of HMS Barham. So, the German high command must have known a lot earlier than &quot;late january&quot; that Barham was sunk. Or was the award for merely damaging this ship? The first quote is from Wikipedia's page on U 331.[[Special:Contributions/80.101.7.35|80.101.7.35]] ([[User talk:80.101.7.35|talk]]) 19:37, 19 February 2010 (UTC)

:U-331 had radio equipment – torpedoing and observing a battleship blowing up a mile away was probably instantly reported to their base at Salamis.  Will modify the text and remove this nonsense of &quot;an opportunity to mislead ...&quot;–[[User:Gamahler|Gamahler]] ([[User talk:Gamahler|talk]]) 17:54, 7 April 2010 (UTC)

::Probably, but wasn't. Leaving supposition out of it and looking at the sources, Tiesenhausen underwent a heavy depth charge attack, and was forced to dive to save his submarine. He only heard the torpedo detonate, and was unaware of what the result had been. He waited until the area was clear before resurfacing. He couldn't be sure whether ''Barham'' had been sunk, or had been damaged and left the area. He radioed in the torpedoing of a battleship, but ''Barham''{{'}}s fate was unknown. Tiesenhausen was granted the award of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross, but on 27 January 1942. The U-331 article doesn't make this clear, hence the ip's reading that the award came well before this is understandable, but incorrect. When the Admiralty announced the sinking on 27 January, the circumstances of the loss became clear and Tiesenhausen received his award. [[User:Benea|Benea]] ([[User talk:Benea|talk]]) 19:36, 7 April 2010 (UTC)

:::Thanks for your explanation and source! -[[User:Gamahler|Gamahler]] ([[User talk:Gamahler|talk]]) 20:08, 7 April 2010 (UTC)

I misread the article.

== 1939 OF LEWIS ==

WHEN THE BARHAM WAS HIT IN 1939 FOUR MEN DIED, THEY WERE BURIED IN UNMARKED GRAVES IN BOTTLE LIVERPOOL. the navy denied this and told the relatives they lost at sea. in later years the graves were discovered by prisoners clearing the grave yard. this was kept for the families and denied by the navy... my great uncle was one of the four men. ASM Lockerly  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/31.221.17.28|31.221.17.28]] ([[User talk:31.221.17.28|talk]]) 14:42, 15 April 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Jutland section ==

I think the level of detail is just about right in comparison to articles I've written on ships that took part in the battle, and certainly so for those that were as heavily involved in the fighting as ''Barham'' was. It is a bit of a &quot;wall of text&quot;, but there's not a whole lot that can be done, apart from adding more pictures. You might want to put [[:File:Headstone for the dead of H.M.S. Barham - geograph.org.uk - 1533677.jpg]] toward the end, and maybe a photo of one of the German BCs (probably ''Seydlitz'' would be the best choice, IMO) - [[:File:Seydlitz badly damaged.jpg]]. [[:File:HMS Warspite and HMS Malaya during the battle of Jutland.jpg]] might even be an option if you need another image. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 20:43, 5 August 2015 (UTC)
:Hmm, since you mention it I think it's far too long. Most of the Jutland section does not concern Barham - she is not even mentioned until the fourth paragraph - and she didn't play a particularly noteworthy role (at least not independently of the rest of the 5th Battle Squadron). Compare this with the equivalent section on Warspite (which did play a notable role): That is is 550 words and this is 1860 words. [[User:Wiki-Ed|Wiki-Ed]] ([[User talk:Wiki-Ed|talk]]) 19:24, 7 August 2015 (UTC)
::As squadron flagship, you have to detail the movements of the squadron considerably more than private ships, IMO. Barham's not mentioned until the 4th para because she did nothing of note as an individual ship until then. Warspite's section will probably get expanded somewhat whenever I get around to it, although most of the squadron movement stuff won't be covered.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 00:45, 8 August 2015 (UTC)
:::I don't buy that. The level of detail ''might'' be appropriate for the article on the squadron, but not for an article on an individual ship. Take a look at the coverage of Trafalgar in the Victory article, or Tsushima in Mikasa. And I was offering Warspite as an example of how to cover the topic, not as a candidate for 'treatment'. It is fine as it is. [[User:Wiki-Ed|Wiki-Ed]] ([[User talk:Wiki-Ed|talk]]) 11:28, 8 August 2015 (UTC)
::::I don't think that I agree. I wrote Mikasa and the reason why the account is sparse is because it's hard to get reliable details about her actions during the battle. And as for Victory, Trafalgar was not a complicated battle tactically. I mean, you need some set up for Nelson's tactical principals, but after the ships break the Allied line of battle, it's merely engaged this ship, take damage, it surrenders, take more damage, move to fight different ship, etc. And much the same is true for the bulk of the Grand Fleet. Not so for the battlecruisers on both sides, nor of the 5th BS.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 13:13, 8 August 2015 (UTC)

== SINKING ==
Regarding the number of casualties, the loss of life is given as 863 at the following site:
http://www.britishpathe.com/gallery/ten-tragedies-caught-on-film/4
while the narrator for the newsreel (Archive: British Pathé, Issue Date: 09/07/1945) at:
http://www.britishpathe.com/video/hms-barham-1914-1941-aka-hms-barham-1914-41
states the loss of life as being 859
The figure in the article is unreferenced and indicates 841 people died. I am new to contributing to Wikipedia so maybe someone with greater skill might edit the article to reflect these facts? [[User:Lord Ferguson|Lord Ferguson]] ([[User talk:Lord Ferguson|talk]]) 13:41, 11 November 2015 (UTC)Lord Ferguson

==B Class Review==
The meaning of the following sentence is unclear. &quot;Evan-Thomas turned northeast at around 18:06 and then made arced around to the southeast once he spotted the Grand Fleet.&quot; Please fix. Thanks. [[User:Djmaschek|Djmaschek]] ([[User talk:Djmaschek|talk]]) 05:57, 4 December 2015 (UTC)
*Forgot to mention location: Battle of Jutland, paragraph 8. [[User:Djmaschek|Djmaschek]] ([[User talk:Djmaschek|talk]]) 06:02, 4 December 2015 (UTC)
::Thanks for spotting this.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 00:23, 14 December 2015 (UTC)
:Tidied references.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 18:25, 13 December 2015 (UTC)

{{Talk:HMS Barham (04)/GA1}}</text>
      <sha1>7tonqr4nn5qxuu6eyuvq5e869n6cw4g</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
