<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Prince Rupert of the Rhine</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4361105</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724619176</id>
      <parentid>690473160</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-10T11:52:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robocon1</username>
        <id>15030566</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Teenage years */ new section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16972">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=15:15, 21 August 2012
|action1link=Talk:Prince Rupert of the Rhine/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=508465529
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=Royalty, nobility and heraldry
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=GA|peerage-work-group=yes|listas=Rupert Of The Rhine, Prince
|peerage-priority=high
|military-work-group=low
|military-priority=mid
}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject England|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA
|B1=y|B2=y|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y
|Biography=y|British=y|German=y
|Early-Modern=y}}
{{WikiProject London|class=GA|importance=mid}}
}}
__TOC__

==Untitled==
Surely calling a non-reigning Palatine Wittelsbach &quot;Duke '''of''' Bavaria&quot; is taking recognition of titular claims to excess.[[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] 02:33, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
:Duke of Bavaria was used by all agnates of the palatine house of Wittelsbach, much like Duke of Brunswick and Lunenburg for all members of the house of Hanover and Duke of Wuerttemberg for remaining dynasts of the house of Wuerttemberg. Prince of the Rhine is, at best, an invention or courtesy title. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 02:36, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
::On the contrary, it is English usage, which &quot;Duke of Bavaria&quot; is not.[[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] 03:27, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
:::Why would he really be a prince of the Rhine when the family were counts-palatine of the Rhine? I am not saying it isn't English usage. I am saying that it factually was not a true title. However, the title duke of Bavaria is a real title and that is why it is included. Wikipedia practice is to show legal names and titles. That is what was done with Rupert. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 03:33, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
::::Whatever the case, some kind of explanatory note in the article might be in order.  I looked at the articles for &quot;Duke of Bavaria&quot; and the list of counts palatine of the Rhine and Rupert is not listed in either, so it might be nice to explain what's going on.  [[User:Ahkond|Ahkond]] ([[User talk:Ahkond|talk]]) 05:45, 24 January 2010 (UTC)
:::::You won't find him because he was a junior member of the family and not its head. It is in the same category as the title of duke for all members of the house of Wettin (''Herzog zu Sachsen'') or title landgrave for all members of the House of Hesse. This is from an era when most dynasties used the same title for all members below the rank of Grand Duke or Elector. [[User:7 Letters|Seven Letters]] 18:08, 21 September 2010 (UTC)

&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #eeffee; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #AAAAAA;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived debate of the {{{type|proposal}}}. &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/font&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

{{{result|The result of the debate was}}} '''don't move'''. &amp;mdash;[[User:Nightstallion|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;Nightst&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Nightstallion/esperanza|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User:Nightstallion|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;llion&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Nightstallion|''(?)'']] 08:07, 16 March 2006 (UTC)

==Requested move== 

* [[Talk:Prince Rupert of the Rhine]] — [[Prince Rupert of the Rhine]] → [[Rupert of the Rhine]] – Simplicity. Why shouldn't both Prince [[Rupert of the Rhine]] and [[Rupert of the Rhine]] be direct links? [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] 02:31, 12 March 2006 (UTC)

----
:''Add *'''Support''' or *'''Oppose''' followed by an optional one-sentence explanation, then sign your opinion with &lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;''
*'''Support''' Nominator vote. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] 02:31, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' Rupert's titles are an absolute mess anyway. Current title seems to be most common usage, prince appended to front is fine. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 17:22, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' Don't see why this should be moved. [[User:Gryffindor|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Gryffindor&lt;/font&gt;]] 17:22, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
::[[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]], it is my understanding that the format &quot;xxxx of xxxx&quot; for males applies only to monarchs, see point 1 on [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (names and titles)]]. In this case, the prince falls under the category &quot;Other royals&quot;, see points 1-4. [[User:Gryffindor|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Gryffindor&lt;/font&gt;]] 18:49, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
* '''Oppose''', given [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis's]] posting to this page &quot;''Please not; present title better than that''&quot; this seems a reasonable compromise page name. --[[User:Philip Baird Shearer|Philip Baird Shearer]] 13:36, 14 March 2006 (UTC)

===Discussion===
:''Add any additional comments''
This is odd. The article states that he was commonly known also as &quot;Prince Rupert of the Palatinate&quot; so shouldn't this article fall under this name? I think it better in this case to contact the creators of this article directly instead of deciding this over their heads.. [[User:Gryffindor|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Gryffindor&lt;/font&gt;]] 17:51, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
:Google gives over 20 times the results for &quot;of the Rhine&quot; than for &quot;of the Palatinate&quot;. The various houses-palatine have always left me with headaches :-P. I will change it to &quot;of the Rhine&quot;. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 18:04, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
::Yes but does this only apply to Prince Rupert with the google hits, or all &quot;of the Palatinate&quot;s. For example [[Elizabeth Charlotte, Princess Palatine]] was always Princess Palatine, not of Rhine. [[User:Gryffindor|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Gryffindor&lt;/font&gt;]] 18:18, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
:::Yes, that is with Rupert only. It is so incredibly inconsistent though! Look at the Elector Palatine's page for his children, for instance. Sadly, common usage reigns supreme in this instance. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 18:20, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
::::It is really inconsistent, but I think &quot;Prince Rupert of the Rhine&quot; is the best title.  &quot;Prince Rupert&quot; is highly ambiguous, and thus unacceptable, and any other name is not in common use. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 15:40, 14 March 2006 (UTC)
----
He is commonly known in English as &quot;Prince Rupert&quot; (See for example the GREAT REBELLION article in [[1911 Encyclopaedia Britannica]]). If further explanation is needed it is: a German relation of King Charles I who had more experiance than most English men at the start of the Civil War in matters military. He falls under that quote an inhabitant of &quot;a distant country that we know little about&quot;. His entry in 1911 is: RUPERT, PRINCE, COUNT PALATINE OF THE RHINE AND DUKE OF BAVARIA.
Google:
* about 651 English pages for &quot;Prince Rupert of the Rhine&quot; -wikipedia
* about 545 English pages for &quot;Rupert of the Rhine&quot; -&quot;Prince Rupert of the Rhine&quot; -wikipedia.
* about 56,300 English pages for &quot;Prince Rupert&quot; -&quot;Rupert of the Rhine&quot; &quot;civil war&quot; -wikipedia
So there are several other options. We could do what the modern http://www.britannica.com which uses &quot;Prince Rupert&quot; or we could move the article to &quot;Prince Rupert, Count Palatine of the Rhine, Duke of Bavaria&quot; which is as he is named in this [http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/rupert_prince.shtml BBC link] or the 1911 Encyclopaedia Britannica &quot;Prince Rupert, Count Palatine of the Rhine and Duke of Bavaria&quot;. --[[User:Philip Baird Shearer|Philip Baird Shearer]] 19:00, 12 March 2006 (UTC)

:I can cite the case of the duc des Deux-Ponts, who took his comital palatine title as equal to duke, rendering it of importance. If any move is made, Prince Rupert of the Rhine could be moved to Prince Rupert, Count Palatine of the Rhine, in order to avoid such a long title. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 19:27, 12 March 2006 (UTC)
::Please not; present title better than that. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] 00:32, 14 March 2006 (UTC)
::*I still feel that permitting [[Rupert of the Rhine]] to be a direct link would be even better; but I will not sulk if the present consensus endures. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] 16:42, 14 March 2006 (UTC)

The titles are a mess, for sure: Check the name he's got on de:, he's got even more titles there. ;) &amp;mdash;[[User:Nightstallion|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;Nightst&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Nightstallion/esperanza|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User:Nightstallion|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;llion&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Nightstallion|''(?)'']] 08:07, 16 March 2006 (UTC)

:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the debate.  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/font&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;

==But What's In A Name ?==

As per: [http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.asp?compid=16652]
: ''Between 1673 and 1679 the Admiralty Board was composed of between twelve and sixteen Privy Counsellors who served without salaries''.

The next Lord High Admiral after the Duke of York (1661-1673) was Prince George (1702-1708).

Prince Rupert could be styled First Lord of succesive Admiralty Boards ( 1673, 1674, 1677 ).

Let's not comment on the &quot;''humiliating failure''&quot; until we have the facts straight.

Hoped to have gone fishing,
: a salty
: ([[User:Lunarian|Lunarian]] 12:40, 1 November 2006 (UTC))

== Children ==

According to Stephen Turnbull in his book, ''The Ottoman Empire, 1326 - 1699'', a son of Prince Rupert fought at the [[Great Turkish War]] in the name of the Archduke of Austria. But this article doesn't even mention a wife or mistress - something that is hard to believe given the fact that his cousin [[Charles II]] was quite the [[hedonist]], with all due respect (I support the Monarchy).[[User:Tourskin|Tourskin]] ([[User talk:Tourskin|talk]]) 03:29, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

== The Sack of Birmingham ==

Strange that there's no mention of it or his role in its instigation and yet the illustration from the pamphlet features it. [[User:Jatrius|Jatrius]] ([[User talk:Jatrius|talk]]) 21:19, 15 November 2009 (UTC)

: Have added in a bit in the extension. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 19:06, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

== Expansion ==

I've gone through and fleshed the article out a bit, and added in-line citations. It'll probably need some copy editing, however.
[[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 19:28, 15 February 2010 (UTC)
It looks like it's shaping up well.[[User:Jatrius|Jatrius]] ([[User talk:Jatrius|talk]]) 20:08, 15 April 2010 (UTC)

==Career in the Restoration Navy==

I have an issue with the following text:

:''The Four Days Battle was at best a draw, but the St. James's Day Battle the following month allowed Rupert and Monk to use the same tactics to inflict heavy damage on the Dutch, resulting in a significant English victory.[127]''

:''Rupert also played a prominent role in the Third Anglo-Dutch War (1672–4).'' 

Not mentioned is the [[Raid on the Medway]], the article of which lists Prince Rupert of the Rhine as commander. For sake of completeness this should be included as the text now might leave the reader to think that the Second Anglo-Dutch War ended with &quot;a significant English victory&quot; which isn't exactly what happened.

BTW: Are only print references acceptable for the article? [[Special:Contributions/82.170.244.87|82.170.244.87]] ([[User talk:82.170.244.87|talk]]) 21:01, 6 March 2011 (UTC)

:On-line references are acceptable on wikipedia, but should be a [[Wikipedia:Identifying reliable sources|reliable source]] - i.e. &quot;reliable, third-party, published sources with a reputation for fact-checking and accuracy&quot;. If a site is self-published (i.e. the author has placed the material on the web themselves, as opposed to it being peer reviewed etc.), you'd probably want to argue on the talk page about why the author had particular credentials to be trusted on that particular topic. A site which lists its sources (e.g. where each bit of information has come from) is usually given more credence than one that just claims particular facts.[[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 21:10, 6 March 2011 (UTC)

== &quot;Prince Rupert&quot; redirect to here? ==

Just curious about how Prince Rupert redirects to here.  Is he a well-known in British history?  Just curious how it stacks up against [[Prince Rupert, British Columbia]].  A Google search has the city and local information coming as the first few results for me.  It's a city of 10,000 people and a reasonably well-known port in Canada, but I'm not sure how well it's known in the English speaking world. - [[User:Wmcduff|Wmcduff]] ([[User talk:Wmcduff|talk]]) 21:31, 15 December 2011 (UTC)
: Well I'm English-speaking and I'd never heard of Prince Rupert the place until now. Whereas I first heard of Prince Rupert the person when learning about the Civil War in primary school (age ten or eleven). [[User:Opera hat|Opera hat]] ([[User talk:Opera hat|talk]]) 23:20, 15 December 2011 (UTC)
:: Seems to be location based.  Europe (and England specifically, I suspect) are more likely to know Prince Rupert the historic figure, while Canadians are going to think of the place.  And someone from the United States is unlikely to have heard of either, I'd bet (well, not counting history/geography buffs).  As there are more English than Canadians, the redirect seems reasonable. - [[Special:Contributions/69.176.176.99|69.176.176.99]] ([[User talk:69.176.176.99|talk]]) 17:39, 16 December 2011 (UTC)
:::I'm American, I've heard of the man but never heard of the town in BC.  There is also (Prince) [[Rupert's Land]] too. [[User:Hot Stop|Hot Stop]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Hot Stop|talk]]-[[Special:Contributions/Hot Stop|contribs]]&lt;/small&gt; 17:49, 16 December 2011 (UTC)
::::Rupert's Land was always known by that name.  Prince Rupert the city might be looked for by simply the city name, however, thus the adjustment to the disambiguation. - [[Special:Contributions/69.176.176.99|69.176.176.99]] ([[User talk:69.176.176.99|talk]]) 22:09, 16 December 2011 (UTC)

{{Talk:Prince Rupert of the Rhine/GA1}}

== African slave trade....... ==

Lofa, I haven't seen any sources linking the Prince to the Maafa, only to the early slave trade. Can you give a source that does? If so, very happy that we incorporate it. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 19:03, 26 February 2014 (UTC)

== Spencer ==

I've changed the first ref to 'Spencer' to a full reference to Charles Spencer, 2008, ''Prince Rupert: The Last Cavalier'' as this seems indicated by the Bibliography; can someone confirm that this is correct?  Also, if someone could confirm that this is the same source used in [[Margaret Hughes]] I'd be grateful.  [[User:GoldenRing|GoldenRing]] ([[User talk:GoldenRing|talk]]) 04:41, 8 December 2014 (UTC)
:There's no need to change the citation style here, since as you say, as it is already listed in the bibliography at the bottom of the article. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 06:30, 8 December 2014 (UTC)
::Yes, fair enough.  I'm used to the non-bibliography style of citations and it confused me for a bit.  [[User:GoldenRing|GoldenRing]] ([[User talk:GoldenRing|talk]]) 07:14, 8 December 2014 (UTC)
:::No prob's. On the morganic issue, it sounds a plausible enough statement, but, like you, I can't think of any sources which have actually said it. I'll have a hunt around, but if not, it should probably come out of Peg Hughes' article. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 14:53, 8 December 2014 (UTC)

== Mother tongue? ==

 &quot;By the age of three he could speak some English, Czech and French, and mastered German while still young . . . .&quot;

Born in Prague to German(sort of) and English(sort of) parents, and raised in The Netherlands, but in an atypical milieu, what was his first language? Is the answer known; is the question even meaningful? {The poster formerly known as 87.81.230.195} [[Special:Contributions/185.74.232.130|185.74.232.130]] ([[User talk:185.74.232.130|talk]]) 16:20, 13 November 2015 (UTC)

== Teenage years ==

First sentence of this section of the article: &quot;Rupert spent the beginning of his teenage years in England between the courts of The Hague and his uncle King Charles I, before being captured and imprisoned in Linz during the middle stages of the Thirty Years' War.&quot; The Hague is not in England. If this means that he divided his time between The Hague and London, it should say so, not that he spent his time in England.[[User:Robocon1|Robocon1]] ([[User talk:Robocon1|talk]]) 11:52, 10 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>2ra4u86e4iy43hwylc8zjq4zm00f12y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
