<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Al-Khalid tank</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3459869</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740257664</id>
      <parentid>740256029</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-20T00:40:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fahrenheit666</username>
        <id>27979956</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Development */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39172">{{GA|18:54, 24 July 2013 (UTC)|topic=Warfare|page=1|oldid=565649874}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA
|Weaponry=yes
|Pakistani=yes
|Land-vehicles=yes
|B1=yes
|B2=yes
|B3=yes
|B4=yes
|B5=yes
}}
{{WP Pakistan|class=GA|importance=mid
|B1=yes
|B2=yes
|B3=yes
|B4=yes
|B5=yes
}}

==Automatic target track==
The Al-Kahlid isn't the second tank in the world after the LeClerc to automatically track targets. Several major MBTs have had that ability for years. I took that out.

== T-90 link is to a Japanese tank ==
I think the T-90 link reference in this article is incorrect.  It should link to a Chinese tank and not a Japanese one.

i agree. there seems to be some confusion as to what the tank is called, but this is the article:
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_96

The T-90-II is not T-96.  Added background info on development of T-90-II/MBT-2000.
[[User:Adeptitus|Adeptitus]] 23:55, 26 June 2006 (UTC)

==Unique Abilities==
This section said that the Al-Khalid is the only tank in the world that can auto-track targets.  Then it said only French tanks could do this.  So how does this make the Al-Khalid the only tank in the world to auto-track targets?  And why is it important to point out how it is vastly superior to the Russian T-90? [[User:DarthJesus|DarthJesus]] 23:21, 6 August 2006 (UTC)

:: The user is most likely pro-Pakistani.  It's POV, AFAIK.  The T-90 is India's new most up to date MBT, given that the Arjun is going nowhere.  Therefore, the Al Khalid is the direct opponent of Indian T-90s. [[User:Catalan|JonCatalan]] 22:43, 28 October 2006 (UTC)

::: Sounds like something from a promotional press release. What exactly does that mean anyway?  That it has a battlefield communications net that keeps track of targets?  That the gunsight  is smart and changes the point of aim to track a target with the stabilizer?  The Al-Khalid is assembled from all foreign components, so it is doubtful that it has anything that is completely unique.

::: Comparing the Al-Khalid and T-90 makes sense, but one can only say so much about two designs not tested in battle.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2006-10-28&amp;nbsp;22:54&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

The implication that the Al-Khalid  can snorkel using GPS to navigate seems a little unlikely to me. Can GPS be received underwater? [[User:145.253.108.22|145.253.108.22]] 16:57, 5 December 2006 (UTC)

: Maybe the GPS antenna is mounted on top of the snorkel.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2006-12-05&amp;nbsp;17:52&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''
It does have GPS active on both land and water as i had the privilege to see one in action at Heavy Industry Taxila myself. (Nabil 05)

==Place of origin==
I have removed Ukraine from &quot;place of origin&quot; in the infobox, again.

Ukraine did not help design or develop this tank.  They did not build any prototypes.  The tank was not tested in Ukraine.  China and Pakistan developed the prototype (Type 90-IIM) which would accept foreign power trains.  Variants of the Type 90-IIM were demonstrated with Chinese, German, British, French, and Ukrainian power-train components.  This doesn't make all of these countries the tank's &quot;place of origin&quot;

The variant chosen for production in Pakistan, the Al-Khalid, happens to have a major component supplied by Ukraine.

The variant marketed by China, the MBT 2000, does not have a Ukrainian engine.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-14&amp;nbsp;15:01&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

: Can you point out the Pakistani contribution. Ukraine provided the engine. This was selected for the MBT-2000/Al-khalid. The prototype version must have tested many engines. The production variant had the Ukranian engine. Hence it is very necessary to have Ukraine also as a co-developer. What made you say that the MBT-2000 did not have the Ukranian engine. The MBT-2000 is the Al-Khalid. Want to know more. The variants with Chinese engines are the other variant of the Type 90.
[[User:Chanakyathegreat|Chanakyathegreat]] 17:29, 22 August 2007 (UTC)

:: Nope.  The Type 90-IIM was built as part of the Chinese-Pakistani co-development project to accept different engines.  They spent ten years developing the final version.  The prototype with the Ukrainian engine was chosen to be produced as the Al-Khalid.  Read through the linked articles to see where this information comes from.

::  Ukraine did not participate in designing the tank, it simply supplied a component.  &lt;del&gt;We don't list France as a co-developer, even though they supplied fire-control systems.&lt;/del&gt; &lt;ins&gt;Incorrect: at least one source implied that the final prototype's fire-control system was &quot;Western&quot;, but according to RAZA0007's source cited below, it is Chinese-Pakistani&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-24&amp;nbsp;01:45&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''&lt;/ins&gt;

:: &quot;What made you say that the MBT-2000 did not have the Ukranian engine. The MBT-2000 is the Al-Khalid.&quot;—please provide a reference describing the engine of the MBT-2000 offered by China at Abu Dhabi.

:: &quot;Want to know more.&quot;  I can't tell if that is a request or a question.

:: &quot;The variants with Chinese engines are the other variant of the Type 90.&quot;—I don't think so, so please provide some references.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-22&amp;nbsp;17:41&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

You still don't get it. The Type 90-II/MBT-2000 tank is a Chinese tank and China owns the right to export it or allow the transfer of technology to license build the tank in any other nation. It may have any names in other services. But it still is the Type 90-II. Changing the name of the tank to Al-Khalid is creating trouble since in other links (especially in Chinese tanks), the tank is listed as Type-90/MBT-2000 but is taking to the Al-Khalid tank article. This need to be corrected.
[[User:Chanakyathegreat|Chanakyathegreat]] 12:34, 30 August 2007 (UTC)
[[User:Chanakyathegreat|Chanakyathegreat]] 12:34, 30 August 2007 (UTC)

: When another version is exported or built elsewhere, we can examine renaming or splitting this article.  Has China even demonstrated the MBT 2000 since 2001?

: What needs to be corrected?  If the article was named Type 90-II or MBT 2000, then still more links to Al-Khalid would be &quot;creating trouble&quot;, as you put it.  There is nothing wrong with redirects.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-30&amp;nbsp;15:46&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

The PRC should be included in the Place of origin section as there would be no Al-Khalid without China. The tank was originally designed by china &amp; later customized for Pakistani use. [[User:Hj108]]'s argument that &quot;Al-Khalid is produced ONLY in Pakistan by Heavy Industries Taxila&quot; is irrelevant as that information has already been correctly added to the Manufacturer section.
Even the article's development section has the following points:
*The tank was co-developed
*The prototypes were all chinese etc
The removal of the PRC gives the impression that the tank was entirely conceived by Pakistan which is of course incorrect.
The Al-Kalid is a customized version of the Chinese tank. Yes Pakistan has contributed but its efforts are dwarfed by that of the Chinese![[User:20enlightened1|20enlightened1]] ([[User talk:20enlightened1|talk]]) 21:03, 30 August 2009 (UTC)

There is already a section for place of origin you chose to open a new one.  I will be inactive for for some time now will respond to your arguments when i get back.--[[User:20enlightened1|20enlightened1]] ([[User talk:20enlightened1|talk]]) 11:59, 31 August 2009 (UTC)

==Al Khalid or MBT 2000?==

Why is Al khalid under the heading of MBT 2000. Al khalid is not a 1 to 1 copy of MBT 2000. Yes, it is based on the original MBT 2000 but Pakistan has modified MBT 2000 for its own needs. For example MBT 2000 never had a Ukranian engine. Under Wkipedia policy only the lincence production (1 to 1 copy) is listed under a common name. Thus, Al khalid should be a seperate artice. Does anyone agree?
[[User:Raza0007|Raza0007]] 22:06, 14 August 2007 (UTC)

: The article should be moved to [[Al-Khalid tank]] instead, since this is the one and only real product of this project.  I'm not sure which policy you're referring to—we should just give the article a sensible name.  There's no point in splitting this into two articles, since they are the closely related result of a single project.

: MBT 2000 doesn't have any particular engine, it is merely the marketing name of the Type 90-IIM prototype, which could theoretically be produced with Chinese, German, British or Ukrainian engine, and possibly others.  It is a speculative tank.  Collectively, the fruits of this development project are often called &quot;MBT 2000/Al-Khalid&quot;.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-14&amp;nbsp;22:21&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

:: Right. So then this article should be named '''Al-Khalid'''. That is what I was trying to say. The wiki policy I mentioned says that if something is produced under a licence then it should be put under the original name. For example if a country produces F-16s under licence, even if they call it differently, the resultant plane should be under F-16 heading. But it has to be a 1 to 1 copy (exact copy). Since Al-Khalid does not fall under this crieteria it should not be under MBT 2000 name. I hope it is clear now. [[User:Raza0007|Raza0007]] 22:36, 14 August 2007 (UTC)

:: Also there is no tank called MBT 2000 produced anywhere in the world right now. The Chinese company has sold the right to produce these tanks to Pakistan. Pakistan has modifed this tank considerablly from the original MBT 2000. Thus, it should be called by its rightful name '''Al-Khalid'''. This article seems to be alright but it should be moved under '''Al-Khalid'''. Right now Al-Khalid redirects to MBT 2000. It should be the other way around. [[User:Raza0007|Raza0007]] 22:47, 14 August 2007 (UTC)

==Requested move - 2007==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of the {{{type|proposal}}}. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/font&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

{{{result|The result of the {{{type|proposal}}} was}}}
[[MBT 2000]] → [[Al-Khalid tank]] — Move from prototype name to name in service —&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-16&amp;nbsp;19:10&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

===Survey===
:''Feel free to state your position on the renaming proposal by beginning a new line in this section with'' &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;*'''Support'''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; ''or'' &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;*'''Oppose'''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;'', then sign your comment with'' &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;''. Since [[Wikipedia:Polling is not a substitute for discussion|polling is not a substitute for discussion]], please explain your reasons, taking into account [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions|Wikipedia's naming conventions]].''

*'''Support''' as nominator.  ''MBT 2000'' is the name being used to market this tank family internationally by China—it refers to a prototype of unknown specifications and undetermined engine type.  ''Al-Khalid'' is the name of the specific version being produced and serving in Pakistan, equipped with a Ukrainian-made diesel engine.  This article is about a tank in service, and should be titled by its common name.  For example, we don't title the article about the [[T-90]] tank after one of its prototypes, ''Object 188'' (original prototype) or ''Object 187'' (another prototype whose turret was used for the latest T-90S).&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-16&amp;nbsp;19:18&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

*'''Support'''. I support the name change from MBT 2000 to Al-Khalid. The Chinese company Nornico, in partnership with Pakistan, developed MBT 2000, but then sold the rights to Pakistan, who manufactures the modified version of this tank called Al-Khalid. Nornico is not interested in producing this tank any more as they also produce Type 96 and Type 99 for China. This tank is now produced solely by Pakistan as Al-Khalid. See discussion entry below for the title of the article. [[User:Raza0007|Raza0007]] 22:59, 16 August 2007 (UTC)
 
===Discussion===
:''Any additional comments:''

I proposed the specific article title &quot;Al-Khalid tank&quot; to head off potential naming conflicts with any other [[Khalid]]s. &quot;Tank&quot; is much more accessible than the jargonesque &quot;[[MBT]]&quot;.

Although I don't want to put too much weight on Google tests, the results seem strongly in favour of the proposal (3.8:1 ratio):
* [http://www.google.com/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en-us&amp;q=%22Al-Khalid%22+tank+-wikipedia&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8 &quot;Al-Khalid&quot; tank -wikipedia] 10,400 results
* [http://www.google.com/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en-us&amp;q=%22MBT+2000%22+tank+-wikipedia&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8 &quot;MBT 2000&quot; tank -wikipedia] 2,710 results

''Jane's Tanks and Combat Vehicles Recognition Guide'', 2nd ed., uses &quot;Al Khalid&quot;, not &quot;MBT 2000&quot; (although most other sources hyphenate &quot;Al-Khalid&quot;).&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-16&amp;nbsp;19:33&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''


:'''&gt;''' I propose to call the article '''Al-Khalid''' and not '''Al-Khalid tank'''. The reason is that all other tank articles on wikipedia are called just by their name e.g [[T-90]], [[Type 96]], [[M1 Abrams]], [[Merkava]], [[Leopard 2]] etc. The only exception is [[Challenger 2 tank]] where the word &quot;tank&quot; is part of the heading. This is why Al-Khalid article should be called just '''Al-Khalid'''. Anybody who ends up on the page will see the picture of a tank and know in a second that the article is related to a tank. Also I do not think there is anyother tank or military hardware called Al-Khalid so chances of confusion are slim. Now about the hyphen, the official name given to the tank by Pakistan is '''Al-Khalid''' with a hyphen in between. Although there is nothing wrong in calling it Al Khalid without the hyphen but the official name should be used for an encyclopedia entry. [[User:Raza0007|Raza0007]] 22:59, 16 August 2007 (UTC)

:: But the point is that anybody who ''doesn't'' end up on the page doesn't have to click a link to find out that it is a tank.  Titles of articles show up in all kinds of places in isolation: in lists, in category pages, in search results, etc.  We shouldn't force someone to click, wait for a page to load and start reading, if they are not interested in a tank in the first place.

:: Chances of confusion aren't slim, because so far there 40 articles listed on the [[Khalid]] disambiguation page.  Again, the title is the one and only facet of the article which is seen by the reader ''before'' they have loaded the page.

:: And it's untrue that all other tank articles lack &quot;tank&quot; in their title.  Before I got bored, I found [[Black Eagle tank]], [[Bob Semple tank]], [[BT tank]], [[Cavalier tank]], [[Centurion tank]], [[Challenger 1 tank]], [[Challenger tank]], [[Charioteer tank]], [[Chieftain tank]], [[Churchill tank]], [[Comet tank]], [[Conqueror tank]], [[Covenanter tank]], [[Cromwell tank]], [[Crusader tank]], [[Excelsior A33 Tank]], [[Iosif Stalin tank]], [[Leopard tank]], [[Light Tank Mk VI]], [[Lion of Babylon tank]], [[M103 heavy tank]], [[M15/42 tank]], [[M2 Light Tank]], [[M2 Medium Tank]], [[M6 Heavy Tank]], [[Mark I tank]], [[Matilda II|Matilda tank]], [[P40 tank]], [[Panther tank]], [[Patton tank]], [[Ram tank]], [[Sentinel tank]], [[Stingray Light Tank]], [[Stuart tank]], [[T-100 tank]], [[T-18 tank]], [[T-28 Super Heavy Tank]], [[T-37 tank]], [[T-38 tank]], [[T-43 tank]], [[T-50 tank]], [[T-60 tank]], [[T20 Medium Tank]], [[T29 Heavy Tank]], [[T30 Heavy Tank]], [[Tetrarch tank]], [[Tiger tank]], [[Tsar Tank]], [[Valentine tank]], [[Valiant tank]].&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-17&amp;nbsp;03:49&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

::: Well, it is fine with me then. What I was talking about were the articles in the list of modern tanks. If you go to [[M1 Abrams]] page and scroll to the bottom, there is a templete for modern tanks, on that templete all tanks except Chellenger 2 have just the name of the tank listed in the article heading. There is no word &quot;tank&quot; after them. Since Al-Khalid is placed in the category of modern tanks so that is why I thought it should be named just Al-Khalid.

:::: In the context of that template it is obviously a tank.  So we just make use of the redirect or pipe the link, so it appears as [[Al-Khalid]].  But that one is the exception.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-17&amp;nbsp;15:43&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

:::: You'll note that four of the article links in that template already do this: [[Arjun MBT]], [[Challenger 2 tank]], [[K1 88-Tank]], and [[Zulfiqar MBT]].&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-17&amp;nbsp;19:24&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the {{{type|proposal}}}.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;
''This article has been renamed {{{{{subst|}}}#if:MBT 2000|from [[MBT 2000]] to [[Al-Khalid tank]]}} as the result of a [[wikipedia:requested moves|move request]].'' --[[User:Stemonitis|Stemonitis]] 05:26, 22 August 2007 (UTC)

== Development ==

The development is done by the Chinese. Engine development done by the Ukranians. Provide details on any Pakistani contribution if it exists.
[[User:Chanakyathegreat|Chanakyathegreat]] 16:53, 22 August 2007 (UTC)

: Sources linked from the article say that China and Pakistan spent about ten years co-developing the tank design and its production facilities.  I haven't seen any which contradict this.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-22&amp;nbsp;17:43&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

Apart from the 10 year R&amp;D, since 2001 all major parts used in Al-Khalid are locally made. The only exception is the engine. Currently Pakistan does not posses the abiltity to make a reliable tank engine, very few countries actually do. This is the reason they are importing the engines from Ukraine. Currently the fire controle system in use is Chinese too.  
Here are the links for some of the parts used in Al-Khalid that are made in Pakistan
* [http://www.depo.org.pk/index.php?a=profile&amp;id=5 Laser Range Finder, Laser Actuated Target System, Laser Threat Sensor etc]
* [http://www.depo.org.pk/index.php?a=org_prod_listings&amp;pid=157&amp;id=7&amp;product=Armoured%20Fighting%20Vehicles%20and%20Upgrades 125 mm Tank Gun Barrel]
* [http://www.depo.org.pk/index.php?id=6&amp;a=org_prod_listings&amp;pid=72&amp;product=Artillery%20and%20Mortars TANK AMMUNITION for Al-Khalid]
* [http://www.depo.org.pk/index.php?a=org_prod_listings&amp;pid=78&amp;id=6&amp;product=Artillery%20and%20Mortars 12.7 MM ANTI AIRCRAFT MACHINE GUN]
* [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heavy_Industries_Taxila Heavy Industries Taxila responsible for the Armour, Hull etc]  [http://www.depo.org.pk/index.php?a=showallproducts&amp;id=7 &quot;Another link for HIT&quot;]

In comming years Pakistan will most likely be producing this tank A-Z in Pakistan.
---&gt;&gt;[[User:Raza0007|Raza0007]] 03:11, 23 August 2007 (UTC)

: I believe this is a valid consideration too, which has not been mentioned much.  China is offering a version of this tank for sale, but all actual production, and the concurrent further practical development which must occur along with it (i.e. debugging and in-service mods), has been taking place in Pakistan (probably with Chinese co-operation?) for the last six years.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2007-08-24&amp;nbsp;01:49&amp;nbsp;Z&lt;/small&gt;''

:: Michael Z, I am sure the Chinese company is still providing valuable cooperation to Pakistan but below is the reason why I do not think they are still offering this tank for sale. Chinese Army did not order a single Type 90-IIM/MBT 2000 tank. The reason was they already had about Approx 2000 [[Type 96]] tanks in service, made by the same company. If you compare the specs, [[Type 96]] and [[Al-Khalid]] are very similar to each other. No wonder Chinese Army did not want another slightly different Type 96 tank. So, Nornico sold the rights to manufacture Type 90-IIM to Pakistan. Before it was 50-50 partnership. I am sure they are getting royalities on every copy of Al-Khalid produced. Also, Janes reported that Saudi Arabia was planning to evaluate Al-Khalid in March 2006. But they went to Pakistan not China. Had Nornico still manufatured this tank, I am sure Saudis would have gone to them instead. After all Pakistan is still new to Tank manufaturing and China has a lot of experience. Thus, this tank is now only produced in Pakistan.

:: As a side note to Chanakyathegreat, why Pakistan is put as the &quot;place of origin&quot; for Al-Khalid? Well, this is because they in partnership with China developed this tank. Granted it has the engine from Ukraine but that does not mean Pakistan does not have the right to call it their tank. Look at [[M1 Abrams]], the place of origin is United States, but if you look at the specs, the protective Armor, the [[Chobham armour]], is British! The gun on the original M1, the M68A1 105 mm rifled tank gun, was a license-built version of the British Royal Ordnance L7 gun. The current gun of M1A2, the M256 120 mm smoothbore gun, is German! produced under licence in USA. So, tell me, without Armor and main gun what is left in a tank? Does that mean USA is not the sole developer of M1A2? Of course it does not! Thus, Al-Khalid is developed by Pakistan and China, it does not matter if the engine is imported from Ukraine. I hope I made my point clear. ---&gt; [[User:Raza0007|Raza0007]] 05:29, 24 August 2007 (UTC)
:::The Saudis were only looking at the MBT2000 to support Pakistani industry; they didn't actually ''want'' it, because they already have several hundred much better tanks and can get more whenever they want. There would be no point in them buying from China, because that wouldn't support Pakistan.--[[User:Fahrenheit666|Fahrenheit666]] ([[User talk:Fahrenheit666|talk]]) 00:29, 20 September 2016 (UTC)
:::Saying that Pakistan developed it in partnership with China is over-egging things somewhat. The Chinese developed the tank as an evolution of the Type 85, which was an evolution of the Type 80, which itself has a clear ancestry leading back to the T-54. The Type 90-II is just the latest, and almost certainly last, incarnation of a tank series the Chinese have been making since the early 1960s and which, frankly, has long outlived its usefulness. Pakistan's contribution was about $22 million, which is peanuts and probably not even enough to localise the design for Pakistani service. It's a Chinese tank that Pakistan has the right to build under license. It is not a Pakistani design. --[[User:Fahrenheit666|Fahrenheit666]] ([[User talk:Fahrenheit666|talk]]) 00:40, 20 September 2016 (UTC)

==Needs an Update==

This article needs an update. Have the goals mentioned within the article been reached?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.112.49.160|71.112.49.160]] ([[User talk:71.112.49.160|talk]]) 14:55, 9 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Move? 2009 ==
{{discussion-top}}

&lt;pre&gt;{{move|Al-Khalid}}&lt;/pre&gt;

* '''[[:Al-Khalid tank]] → {{noredirect|Al-Khalid}}''' — ''Over redirect with history'' &quot;tank&quot; is an unnecessary qualifier as there is nothing else called &quot;Al-Khalid&quot; — {{#ifeq:{{{sig}}}|no||[[User:Patton123|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Patton&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Patton123|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;t&lt;/font&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Patton123|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;c&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 12:50, 16 February 2009 (UTC)}}
* The name component &quot;Khalid&quot; is common in Islamic names. The disambiguator is needed. [[Al-Khalid (tank)]]? [[User:Anthony Appleyard|Anthony Appleyard]] ([[User talk:Anthony Appleyard|talk]]) 16:32, 16 February 2009 (UTC)

Isn't ''al'' just an article?  I don't think it provides any meaningful disambiguation to differentiate this tank from the 40-odd other things called [[Khalid]].  There is also usage like [[Mohamad Al-Khaled Samha]].&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2009-02-16&amp;nbsp;17:12&amp;nbsp;z&lt;/small&gt;''
:{{tl|lowercase}} may display the lower case, which is probably correct here. (And I agree; disambiguation by ''al-'' is unwise as disambiguation by ''the''.) [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 18:46, 16 February 2009 (UTC)

:: I think the capitalization “Al-Khalid tank” is fine in the title, just as it would appear at the beginning of a sentence.  The l.c. template is rarely necessary, perhaps when something like IPod looks wrong.

:: ''Al'' isn't an article in English anyway, and I don't see any of the article's sources using the capitalization ''al-Khalid'', so we probably shouldn't use it at all in Wikipedia.&amp;nbsp;''—[[User:Mzajac |Michael]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Mzajac |Z.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;2009-02-16&amp;nbsp;20:32&amp;nbsp;z&lt;/small&gt;''

{{discussion-bottom}}

==Proposal - Move article to &quot;Al-Khalid MBT&quot;==
{{discussion-top}}

I have a source here calling the tank &quot;Al-Khalid MBT&quot;:
http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/pakistan/hit.htm
Apart from that, the original project name was &quot;MBT-2000&quot;.
I believe Al-Khalid MBT is the most appropriate title for the article. Thoughts? [[User:Hj108|Hj108]] ([[User talk:Hj108|talk]]) 21:40, 9 March 2009 (UTC)
:Would help clarify the tank issue that was above.--[[User:UnknownForEver|→ Ãlways Ãhëad]] ([[User talk:UnknownForEver|talk]]) 01:47, 10 March 2009 (UTC)

{{discussion-bottom}}

==Al-Khalid origin== 
http://www.forecastinternational.com/press/release.cfm?article=58
:&quot;Dean Lockwood, a weapons systems analyst at Forecast International, notes that in terms of sheer numbers, Pakistan’s Al-Khalid, the Type 98 of the People’s Republic of China, and the Russian Federation’s T-90 represent the most significant new-production main battle tanks on the international market.&quot;

http://www.pakdef.info/pakmilitary/army/tanks/alkhalid_new.html
:&quot;The initial Al-Khalid prototype was revealed in June 1991, based on the NORINCO Type 90-II MBT, which compared to earlier Chinese MBTs, has significant improvements in the three key areas of MBT design: armour, mobility and firepower. Under the initial contract signed in 1990, the Type 90-II was to be licensed produced at Heavy Industries Texila (HIT) but '''further developments resulted in Al-Khalid, which is tailored to meet the specific operational requirements of Pakistan Armoured Corps.'''&quot;  

http://usmanansari.com/id13.html
:&quot;...Pakistan continues to maintain a large fleet of MBTs (over 2,000), whilst elsewhere in the world their number is falling. The best tank currently in service is the indigenous Al-Khalid produced by Heavy Industries Taxila, (HIT). In terms of induction of new MBTs it is set to be one of the most significant MBTs in the coming decade. '''It is a development of the ... Type 90-II''', which first made an appearance in 1990, and was itself a further manifestation of the Chinese requirement to field an MBT superior to the Russian T-72...&quot;

http://usmanansari.com/id15.html
:&quot;However, in terms of technological capabilities and general performance the Al-Khalid is the most important tank in PA service. As it appears now it is a result of a continuous evolution process that has been taking place since the early 1990s. '''The basic design was of the Chinese Type-90II... but it was modified to suit the needs of the PA.''' The main PA considerations for the Al-Khalid were that it should be supportable by indigenous industry to the fullest extent possible, and also that it would have a high degree of commonality with the existing MBT fleet. Finances did not exist for a replacement on a one to one basis for the whole fleet with a completely new type, and ways had to be found with which to keep operational expenditure at manageable levels. The Al-Khalid therefore shares much commonality with the Type-59/69, Type-85 and commonality of ammunition with the Ukrainian supplied T-80UD.&quot;
--[[User:Hj108|Hj108]] ([[User talk:Hj108|talk]]) 19:08, 30 August 2009 (UTC)

:According to [[User:20enlightened1]]'s arguments above:
::&quot;The PRC should be included in the Place of origin section as there would be no Al-Khalid without China.&quot; 
:There would be no Al-Khalid without the T-54 and T-72, but the Soviet Union isn't being added.
::&quot;The tank was originally designed by china &amp; later customized for Pakistani use.&quot; 
:No, the Type 90-II was developed by China. The Al-Khalid is a Pakistani development of Type 90-II.
::&quot;User:Hj108's argument that &quot;Al-Khalid is produced ONLY in Pakistan by Heavy Industries Taxila&quot; is irrelevant as that information has already been correctly added to the Manufacturer section.&quot; 
:How can it not be relevant? Nobody can manufacture the Al-Khalid except Pakistan. China could build a Type 90-II but it would not have the features of the Al-Khalid, such as the Ukrainian engine, French transmission and thermal imaging systems, Western fire-control system, the Pakistani battlefield management system and data-link, etc. You can't get an Al-Khalid from anywhere but Pakistan, therefore it is of Pakistani origin.
::&quot;Even the article's development section has the following points:
::* The tank was co-developed
::* The prototypes were all chinese etc&quot;
:This is what the current version of the article's development section actually says:
:::&quot;A development deal was signed with Pakistan in January 1990. Initial Chinese-built prototypes were tested in Pakistan in August 1991. '''Pakistan spent more than US$20 million over the next ten years on the co-development of a model suitable for their needs and on creating a capability to manufacture it locally...''' '''The design team modified the tank to accept a foreign-built power pack (engine). A number of different prototypes were evaluated'''.&quot;
:So Pakistan's HIT didn't simply customise a Chinese shell, they modified it before adding their own selection of components, including power-train and electronics. 
::&quot;The removal of the PRC gives the impression that the tank was entirely conceived by Pakistan which is of course incorrect. The Al-Kalid is a customized version of the Chinese tank.&quot;
:The article clearly states Al-Khalid is an evolution of Chinese designs, which in turn are evolutions of Soviet designs. Doesn't change my above arguments.
::&quot;Yes Pakistan has contributed but its efforts are dwarfed by that of the Chinese!&quot;
:Where is the source comparing amount of &quot;effort&quot; the Chinese and Pakistanis put into the tank?
:--[[User:Hj108|Hj108]] ([[User talk:Hj108|talk]]) 22:17, 30 August 2009 (UTC)

== Rehbar IBMS Pic - Please add attached picture to page. ==

Hi, please add the picture of the Rehbar IBMS to the article from the below link. Thank you.
Also the system is by HIT &amp; CARE, not IDS.

http://www.carepvtltd.com/products/products.htm

http://img.photobucket.com/albums/v125/maakn786/p0590103.jpg

== Requested move 2010 ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:RM|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''move to [[Al-Khalid (tank)]]''' [[User:Graeme Bartlett|Graeme Bartlett]] ([[User talk:Graeme Bartlett|talk]]) 06:48, 16 January 2010 (UTC)

----

{{tlx|movereq|Al-Khalid}}
* [[:Al-Khalid tank]] → [[Al-Khalid]] — same reason as all the other requests. Should have {{For|the surname|Khalid (name)}}.— [[User:User name one|username 1]] ([[User talk:User name one|talk]]) 22:10, 8 January 2010 (UTC)
* Al-Khalid or similar is a very common Islamic name for various people and things. Keep the disambiguator. Move to [[Al-Khalid (tank)]]? [[User:Anthony Appleyard|Anthony Appleyard]] ([[User talk:Anthony Appleyard|talk]]) 14:00, 9 January 2010 (UTC)
* Agree with requested move to &quot;Al-Khalid (tank)&quot;.--[[User:Hj108|'''Hj108''']] ([[User talk:Hj108|'''talk''']]) 16:29, 10 January 2010 (UTC)
* Agree, sounds reasonable. [[User:User name one|username 1]] ([[User talk:User name one|talk]]) 04:05, 11 January 2010 (UTC)

:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

== Morocco and the MBT2000/VT1A ==

Before someone adds Morocco as an operator again... can we please, please, please have a ''reputable'' source?  Not personal blogs which don't cite where they got the info from, not Chinese propaganda sites, not dead links to non-existent articles.  A few pictures of tanks in Morocco do not a sale make.  Don't you think that something like this would have been put out by a reputable source like Jane's, or one of the many, many other widely read and respected defence news sites or columns?  Or maybe even, say, a reputable Moroccan newspaper?  Or hey, even the Moroccan government?  Crazy thoughts, I know...  - [[User:Jonathon A H|Jonathon A H]] ([[User talk:Jonathon A H|talk]]) 23:51, 30 August 2010 (UTC)

== Requested move 2011 ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of the proposal. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

'''Page moved''' to [[Al-Khalid tank]]. [[User:Vegaswikian|Vegaswikian]] ([[User talk:Vegaswikian|talk]]) 06:27, 1 February 2011 (UTC)

[[Al-Khalid (tank)]] → {{no redirect|1=Al-Khalid}} — &lt;small&gt;'''Relisted'''. I'm not seeing a consensus to keep this at the current name.  Taking into consideration all of the previous discussions, it looks like consensus is for [[Al-Khalid tank]].  So I plan to move to that unless a consensus not to develops. I would really like to have more input. [[User:Vegaswikian|Vegaswikian]] ([[User talk:Vegaswikian|talk]]) 03:38, 25 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; Per [[WP:PRIMARY|PRIMARY]]. The Al-Khalid tank article is getting way more page views than [[Khalid]]. [[Al-Khalid]] just redirects here anyway so disambiguating is pointless. Most of the other foreign language articles don't disambiguate the tank article anyway. --[[User:Marcus Qwertyus|&lt;font color=&quot;#21421E&quot; face=&quot;font-family: 'Maiandra GD', sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''Marcus'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Marcus Qwertyus|&lt;font color=&quot;#CC7722&quot; face=&quot;font-family: 'Maiandra GD', sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''Qwertyus'''&lt;/font&gt;]]  07:49, 17 January 2011 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per discussion exactly one year ago, and approximately two years ago. [[Special:Contributions/65.93.13.210|65.93.13.210]] ([[User talk:65.93.13.210|talk]]) 08:27, 17 January 2011 (UTC)
::[[WP:Consensus can change|Consensus can change]]. [[User:Marcus Qwertyus|&lt;font color=&quot;#21421E&quot; face=&quot;font-family: 'Maiandra GD', sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''Marcus'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Marcus Qwertyus|&lt;font color=&quot;#CC7722&quot; face=&quot;font-family: 'Maiandra GD', sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''Qwertyus'''&lt;/font&gt;]]  08:36, 17 January 2011 (UTC)
:::It hasn't yet. [[Special:Contributions/65.93.13.210|65.93.13.210]] ([[User talk:65.93.13.210|talk]]) 16:18, 17 January 2011 (UTC)
*'''Move to [[Al-Khalid tank]]''', per wp:precise, &quot;use natural disambiguators&quot;. &quot;Al-Khalid&quot; is as common a name as &quot;Abraham&quot; or &quot;Spencer&quot; in the west. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Victor_falk|''walk'']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[user:victor falk|''victor falk'']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[user_talk:victor falk|''talk'']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 01:10, 24 January 2011 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the proposal.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;
==File:Mbt2000iii.jpg Nominated for speedy Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Mbt2000iii.jpg|File:Mbt2000iii.jpg]], has been nominated for speedy deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] for the following reason: ''Copyright violations'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; deletions can take a little longer at Commons than they do on Wikipedia. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion (although please review Commons guidelines before doing so). The best way to contest this form of deletion is by posting on the image talk page.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.
* If the image has already been deleted you may want to try [[commons:COM:UR|Commons Undeletion Request]]
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[commons:File:Mbt2000iii.jpg|image page (File:Mbt2000iii.jpg)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 14:28, 14 May 2012 (UTC)
|}

== Good Article status ==

There would be much struggle to elevate the article to a &quot;Good article&quot;. The article would be under construction and improvement for a few weeks. I am putting a &quot;under construction&quot; tag to the article. I request the editors to aid me in this target. We will see [[Al-Khalid]] as a good article soon. &lt;span style=&quot;border:2px solid #000;background:#000&quot;&gt;[[User:Faizan|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#fff;&quot;&gt;Fai&lt;/span&gt;]][[User Talk:Faizan|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0f0&quot;&gt;zan&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 12:56, 14 June 2013 (UTC)
:The article has been nominated for GA assessment, after much improvements. &lt;span style=&quot;border:2px solid #000;background:#000&quot;&gt;[[User:Faizan|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#fff;&quot;&gt;Fai&lt;/span&gt;]][[User Talk:Faizan|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0f0&quot;&gt;zan&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 12:40, 23 June 2013 (UTC)

{{Talk:Al-Khalid tank/GA1}}</text>
      <sha1>jw41emngojvflu6eokze59jw091zit9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
